<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/189/0 images: 142-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] . n -- ---   tj hPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1927.SECRET. - Copy No.    25CP. 265 (27).CABINET.THE PROPOSALS OF THE JOCKEY CLUB FOR THE AMENDMENT OFTHE GAMING LAWS.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.1. I CIRCULATE for the information of the Cabinet a copy of the Report of a Committee appointed by the Jockey Club to enquire into the means by which Betting may best be made to contribute to the maintenance of Sport.2. The Report has been adopted by the Jockey Club, and the Stewards have been instructed to take any necessary steps to secure the adoption of the recom-mendations of the Report.3. The Stewards accordingly came to see me on the 1st November to ask whether tiie Government would introduce legislation to permit (1) the installation of the Totalisator or Pari Mutuel on racecourses, and (2) the charging of fees by the Racecourse Executives to bookmakers on the courses.4. I replied that their request raised an important issue of general policy, on which I would consult the Cabinet without delay.5. The question at issue is whether we are prepared to support&apos;an amendment of the Gaming Laws in the directions desired by the Jockey Club, either by introducing a Bill ourselves or by giving facilities to a Private Member&apos;s Bill. From the revenue point of view there would be no objection and some advantage in the installation of the Totalisator. But the amendment of the Gaming Laws in any particular raises wider considerations of policy than the purely revenue aspect. The Report of the Committee has been well received in the Press, and, although the bookmakers will object, I should not anticipate any serious opposition in Parliament to the amendments of the law which are suggested. On the contrary, I believe that they would be welcomed by the best elements in the sporting world as well as by the general public.6. I recommend, therefore, that I should be authorised to inform the Stewards that the Government will be prepared to facilitate legislation in the directions they desire.7. The Report raises other matters in regard to the structure and administra-tion of the Betting Tax, which I propose to examine and discuss with the Stewards when the general question of principle has been decided.w. s. c.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1, November 7, 1927.[16782]
Torms of Reference.(1) At a Meeting of the Jockey Club held in the First Spring week at Newmarket, it was decided that the Committee formed originally to enquire into the effect of the Betting Tax on Racing should further &quot; Institute without delay an enquiry into tho means by which betting may best be made to contribute to the maintenance of sport, and report to the Club&quot;.Composition of the Committee.(2) The Committee had been formed jointly of Members of the Jockey Club, of the National Hunt Committee, and National Coursing Club, with power to co-opt additional Members.The following are the names of those who served on the Committee: Lord Hamilton of Dalzell &quot;j Lord Ellesmere J- Stewards.Sir George Bui lough, Bart. J Lord Lonsdale Lord Ronaldshay Lord Dalmeny Sir Berkeley Sheffield, Bart. Sir Leonard Brassey, Bart. Sir Henry GreerSeveral other Members of the Club attended Meetings from time to time. Col. Hon. A. Hore-Ruthven &quot;jJockey Club.Sir William Bass, Bart. j- National Hunt Committee.Hon. Gilbert Jobnstone lord Sefton \Brig.-Gen. R. McCalmont j- National Coursing Club.Major C. Blundell JAs Senior Steward of the Jockey Club Lord Hamilton of Dalzell has acted as Chairman.(3) The Report which the Committee has prepared deals with Flat Racing. The gentlemen appointed by the National Hunt Committee and by the National Coursing Club concur in the main points of the Report, and will make a separate report to the bodies which appointed them on any points on which modifications may be necessary in applying the general principles of this Report to Sport under their Rules.Witnesses examined.(4) The following witnesses have given evidence before us, and the Committee wouldlike to take this opportunity of recording their thanks to them for the valuable assistance given them : Capt. Algernon Howard (Secretary, Calcutta Turf Club). Mr. A. N. Skipwith (late Totalisator Manager at Calcutta). Major Hildebrand (Secretary, Madras Race Club).Mr. J. H. Hardie (Chartered Accountant, Partner in Fergusson &amp; Co., Auditorsto the Western India Turf Club, Bombay). Mr. R. M. McDonald (Honorary Totalisator Steward of the Canterbury RacingClub, New Zealand). Major F. J. Henley (Secretary, Jockey Club of South Africa). Mr. I. Isaacs\Mr. H. SlowburnMr. A. Heathorn    \ Bookmakers. Mr. J. McLean Mr. A. Bendir Mr. B. GottschalkMr. 0. A. Mills       \ Professional Backers. Mr. F. C. Parker    J Mr. G. A. Julius (Automatic Totalisators, Limited, Sydney, Australia). Mr. F. A. Wilkinson (Manager to the above). Sir Loftus Batos \Hon. Reginald Parker   J- Race-course Association, Limited. Mr. T. F. Dawkins        JEEPOETOF THECOMMITTEE APPOINTED BY THE JOCKEY CLUB TO ENQUIRE INTO THE MEANS BY WHICH BETTING MAY BEST BE MADE TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE MAINTENANCE OF SPORT.
We found that a very full examination of the question wo had to consider had been made by tho Select Committee of the House of Commons which considered in 1923 the question of imposing a Retting Duty. The evidence taken by that Committee was before us, and we have not thought it necessary to cover tho ground which had already been traversed.Legal Position.(5) Before submitting our report we think it well to state what we understand to be the present legal position in regard to betting as it affects the matter we have to report upon.Betting is not in itself illegal, but becomes so if it is carried on under certain conditions. Betting is not illegal on a race-course, either for ready money or on credit, unless it is carried on in such a way as to involve tho creation of a house,office, room,or other &quot; place&quot; within the meaning of the Gaming Act of 1853. If that is done the owners of the race-courses arc liable to prosecution for &quot;opening, keeping,or using a place for the purpose of betting,&quot; and bookmakers and backers arc liable to prosecution as being persons using the same for the purpose of betting.There are two ways in which betting may be made to contribute to the maintenance of Sport: (a) By charging bookmakers a fee for the privilege of making a book on tho race-course,and(b) By means of the Pari-Mutuei or Totalisator.We are advised that under the Judgment given in the House of Lords in the case of Powell v. the Kempton Race Course Company, Limited, in 1899 (A.C.) (which is accepted as the ruling Judgment on such cases), neither of these methods is advisable in the present, state of the law, for the following reasons: If a fee were to be charged to bookmakers for the privilege of being allowed to make a book in any of the enclosures on a race-course, those enclosures would thereby be constituted &quot;places&quot; kept by the owners of the race-course for purposes of Letting. This is not so at present, because everyone whether a bookmaker, a backer, or a spectator who has no intention of betting pays the same fee for admission to the enclosure and stand. The man who takes the admission fee neither knows nor cares whether the man who pays for his admission intends to bet or not. The &quot;owner or occupier&quot; has no interest in any bet and is in no way concerned with any bet. iTurthermore, if a bookmaker paid for the right of being allowed to bet on a particular spot that would be even more likely to constitute a violation of the law.The setting up of the booths or buildings which are necessary for canning on betting by means of the Pari-Mutuel or Totalisator would almost certainly be held to be the setting up of a &quot; place &quot; where betting was to be carried on.In these circumstances it is obvious that it would be difficult to draw revenue for Sport from betting without an alteration of the law. In our recommendations we have assumed that the legislation which is necessary to remove the present restrictions will be passed.Systems adopted in other Countries.(6) Turning to foreign countries, and to the Dominions and Colonies, for guidance in our enquiries we found that there appear, as has been said above, to be two, and only two, ways of raising revenue through betting. These are by the setting up of the Totalisator (or Pari-Mutuel) on race-courses, or by imposing a licence fee on bookmakers attending race meetings either at a flat rate, or in accordance with the Ring they frequent, or the position which they occupy in that Ring. In Calcutta, only a limited number of bookmakers (IS to 20) are allowed, and these pay heavy licence fees, up to  SO per day on important race days. A similar system is in vogue in South Africa. These two systems are adopted either singly or side hy side in practically every country except Great Britain and Ireland.The Pari-Mutuel, or Totalisator.(7) These are often spoken of as distinct systems, but really involve tho same principle, i.e., the establishment of a number of booths whore people wishing to back a horse pay in their money and receive in exchange a ticket; all the money received is divided among the backers of the winner or placed horses in proportion to tho amount invested less a specified percentage which is deducted to pay the tax, tho expenses of the Pari-Mutuel or &quot; Tote,&quot; and the contribution to tho maintenance of tho sport.The establishment of this system of betting would involve considerable exponso, and probably some alteration of tho &quot; lay out&quot; of tho ground in tho neighbourhood of the stands on our courses, and some time must elapse beforo it could bo brought into operation. It would also involve a complete change in the method in which race-goers have been accustomod to bet.
It can bo brought into operation alone as has been dono (theoretically) in Franco, New Zealand, &amp;c, or in conjunction with book male ing-as has been clone in Belgium, Western Australia, parts of India, South Africa, and elsewhere.The Paiu-Mutuel lias been in operation in France for many years, and Members of the Club are no doubt familiar with it.The totalisator has been in use in parts of Australia, New Zealand,India,North and South America, &amp;c, for some time. It is a development or the Pari-Mutuel system under which, by means of a machine worked electrically, all bets are immediately recorded on a conveniently placed board, or boards. The advantage of tho Totalisator system is that, instead of the return payable on any horse being unknown until the totals from all the booths are collected after the betting closes, as happens with the Pari-Mutuel, there is a running total of the amount in tho pool and of the amount invested on each horse, which enables backers to judge approximately of the rate of odds current when they make their bet. The payment of winnings is much quicker under this system than under the Pari-Mutuel. The machine which docs this is expensive, the expense being regulated by the scale on which the system is installed.The experience of these Systems in other Countries.(8) In ascertaining what measure of success had resulted from the use of these systems in other countries, we received from all sides glowing accounts oE the enormous benefits which accrue to Pacing from the percentages deducted from tho turnover of the Totalisator and, in India particularly, from the licence fees of bookmakers; but in Australia, New Zealand, India (Calcutta and Bombay), and in France, we found the laws governing betting entirely opposed to the laws in force here. In Calcutta, under the Bengal Hotting Act, betting outside a race-course is illegal, and race-courses under the control of the Calcutta Turf Club are actually specified in the Act as the only places on which the Totalisator is allowed, and on which bookmakers licensed by the Club may carry on their business.In New Zealand also betting by bookmakers is illegal, but licences are j^iven to race-courses to run a Totalisator on condition that 2A per cent, is deducted for the Government and 7i per cent, (making 10 per cent, in all) is deducted for the improvement of racing and the stakes.In France the only form of betting allowed is that done through the machine, although it is well known that there are bookmakers who carry on a secret and illicit business.(9) In all the countries mentioned where betting is illegal and the Totalisator is permitted, the bulk of the money has to find its way through the Totalisator, where it is taxed without difficulty, and very largo revenues are collected. One could not arrive at even an approximate estimate of what the turnover of the Totalisator would be in Great Britain, because the machine would be competing not only with a mass of bookmakers on the course, but also with all the Starting Price betting away from the race-course, which, according to evidence given before the Select Committee of the House of Commons, constituted at least nine-tenths of all betting.(10) A further advantage claimed for these systems of betting, to which we attach considerable importance, was this: Witnesses from India who gave evidence before us said that the dual system of the Totalisator and licensed bookmakers had had a marked effect in reducing dishonest practices on their courses. The Totalisator does not lend itself to the practice of making money out of horses which for one reason or another are what is known in betting circles as &quot; dead meat&quot;, because horses cannot bo &quot; laid&quot; under that system, they can only be &quot; backed &quot;. Further and this was the point to which these witnesses attached most weight the licensing of bookmakers by tho racing authority in Calcutta carries with it the right to inspect all books, and so gives facilities for tracing thoso who have profited by a &quot; ramp&quot; in a way which is unknown to us, and which would greatly strengthen tho hands of the Stewards of tho Jockey Club. Wo consider this a strong argument in favour of the proposed change.Conditions necessary for giving the Totalisator a fair chance here.(11) If tho Totalisator is to bo given a fair chance on English race-courses, it would seem that course bookmakers would have to pay taxes and fees approximately equivalent in amount to tho deductions mado from the money passing through tho Totalisator, but subject to allowance for their expenses and for a fair working profit, in order to put tho two systems on a lovol footing; and tho Starting Price Bookmakers, who would bo outside the jurisdiction of tho Club, would havo to bo taxod by tho Govornmont to an extent that would place them on terms of equality with tho two systems of Courso-Betting.3
General Report on the suitability of our Race-courses for the Totalisator.(12) During our enquiry we have been fortunate enough to have tho assistance ot Mr. Julius, from Sydney, who is the inventor of the Automatic Totalisator machine called after him and generally made use of, also of Mr. Wilkinson, Manager of the Company which owns the Julius Totalisator machine and now in charge of the erection of a large installation at Longchamps. Mr. Wilkinson was asked, in company with Colonel Wilkinson, our Inspector of Courses, to visit some of our English race-courses and to advise us whether they considered there would be any great difficulty from a structural or other point of view in installing machines, with their full equipment of Power Houses, Indicator Boards, Selling and Pay Out Boxes, &amp;c, on our courses. Their report was to the effect that out of forty-seven courses, thirty offered no difficulties, eleven offered difficulties which could be got over without much trouble, and that the remaining six present considerable difficulties, which do not, however, appear to be insuperable. In the last category were meetings which, owing to their cramped condition, and to the fact that their Stands backed directly on to a public road, had no room for additional buildings, and also some small nieetings&quot;&quot;&quot;with only one fixture in the year and which for that reason might find it difficult to get sufficient return on their outlay. Mr. Wilkinson included Epsom in this category, because when attending the Summer Meeting he saw an immense crowd apparently uncontrolled and spread over a large area of common land. The Committee consider that if power was obtained to enclose more land on the Downs, there would be no reason why Epsom should not be adapted to the system.Detailed Report on Newmarket Courses.(13) With a view to getting some idea of the cost of installing an up-to-date machine, Mr. Wilkinson was asked to give an estimate for our two courses at Newmarket. As an approximate estimate he gave the costs as  13,000 for the Rowley Mile, and  7,000 for the July Course, not to include buildings. It has been estimated that plain but solid buildings suitable for housing the machinery, &amp;c, would briug the total cost of the two Courses up to roughly, from  30,000 to  35,000. The cost to other meetings would of course vary in accordance with their size, the number of enclosures, and the attendance to be catered for. It was suggested to the Committee that in the case of small meetings, or National Hunt Meetings, the Pari-Mutuel system might be substituted^for the Totalisator machine as is done at small meetings in France and in Australia. In addition to this there is a portable Totalisator machine likely to be brought out which might easily fulfil the requirements of the minor meetings. If such a machine were available, the capital expenditure necessary to instal the Totalisator system at the smaller meetings would probably not exceed  3,000 to  4,000.Schemes submitted to the Committee.(14) Schemes were submitted by the Race-course Association, and by Mr. McLean, Bookmaker, of Glasgow. Both schemes were regarded by the Committee as being valuable constructive proposals, and well worth careful consideration, and for that reason they are given in detail in the Appendix. It will be noted that the latter provides additional revenue for racing, without the introduction of the Totalisator.Provision of Capital, &amp;c.(15) The questions of the working of the Totalisators, of control of the revenue derived, and of finding capital for the initial outlay, appear to us to have so important a bearing on the whole subject that they will probabty entail a separate and detailed enquiry. We consider, however, that it is essential that this should all be done by one central, non-dividend paying, authority acting under the direction of the Stewards of the various authorities concerned. We do not anticipate that there should be any difficulty in raising the necessary capital.Bookmakers.(16) Several bookmakers appeared before us as witnesses, both starting price and race-course bookmakers. It was evident from figures produced that possibly owing to a general shortage of money, and certainly to the new Betting Tax, the betting profession was going through difficult times, and it was not unnatural that with the effects of a betting tax weighing on them for the first time they wore somewhat reticent in giving tho Committee information on points which appeared to have as their object the extraction of still more money from bettingiTo tho Totalisator system they were opposed; wo did not expect anything else. With tho system of licensing bookmakers they wore generally in sympathy, chiefly for the reason that it gave tho authorities an opportunity of discriminating between tho honest and dishonest men in tho profession, and perhaps because it gave thorn, in some respects, a sounder footing.
Bearing in mind tho fact that bookmakers were at present crying out against a 2 per cent, tax on turnover, the Committee have been attempting to ascertain what amount of licence fee. would be equivalent to this tax. It did not appear likely that the Government would accept/ any scheme which did not bring them at least as much as the 2 per cent, tax, yet if Racing also was to benefit further revenue must be obtained. This is provided for in Scheme &quot; B &quot; in the Appendix, submitted by Mr. McLean. The professional backers we interviewed seemed generally in favour of the Totalisator.Various Proposals.(17) In the first part of this Report we stated that the introduction of the Totalisator could only be considered if Parliament was prepared to revise the Betting Laws. On the extent to which this was done would depend the success of the Totalisator scheme. If all other forms of betting were made illegal, as in most other countries, and the Totalisator alone was allowed, the Totalisator in itself would produce a vast income. If betting outside race-courses was made illegal, and licence was given to the Totalisator aud the bookmakers to function on race-courses, they would between them produce quite as large an income. If starting price betting were not made illegal, but was taxed to an extent that would impose a charge on it at least equivalent to what was imposed on race-course betting, and the Betting Act was altered so as to permit of the use of the Totalisator under certain conditions, and of licensing bookmakers on a graduated scale, the Committee believe that revenue would be obtained sufficient to give the Chancellor of the Exchequer as much as he is likely to obtain under the present tax aud to provide in addition a considerable and valuable new source of revenue for the sport itself. The Committee consider that such a fresh source of revenue would be very valuable at the present moment, as it would enable race-courses to lower the charges now made for admission to their enclosures, thus adjusting the burden of providing the funds necessary for carrying on racing and for improving the comfort and amenity of our race-courses more equitably than can be done at present. The person who only wanted to see the sport would pay much less than he now does, but the person who could afford to bet would contribute in proportion to the money he betted.Finding.(18) The Committee therefore beg to submit the following as the result of the enquiry they have made into the means by which Betting may best be made to contribute to the maintenance of the Sport: &quot; By obtaining such alteration in the Gaming Act of 1853 as would permit (a) of the Totalisator or Pari-Mutuel being installed on race-courses under the Rules of the Jockey Club or National Hunt Committee, and(b) of Bookmakers on such race-courses and at Coursing Meetings under the Rules of the National Coursing Club being charged fees on a graduated scale by the above-mentioned Racing and Coursing Authorities.&quot;The Committee are of opinion that the two methods mentioned would produce a valuable contribution to the maintenance of sport if they were adopted either separately or in combination, provided such a tax were imposed on the business of Starting Price Offices as, after making due allowance for working expenses, would put them on a level footing with the Totalisator and Race-course Bookmakers.(Signed) HAMILTON of DALZELL, Chairman.ELLESMERE. GEORGE BULLOUGH. LONSDALE. RONALDSHAY. DALMENY. LEONARD BRASSEY. WILLIAM BASS. SEFTON.BERKELEY SHEFFIELD. HENRY QREER.
APPENDIX.Section (14) of the Report refers to two schemes put forward,(a) by Sir Loftus Bates on behalf of tho Racecourse Association, (6) by Mr. McLean, Bookmaker of Glasgow.SCHEME   A.As the Betting Tax in its present form seems far from yielding the amount expected by Government, and is certainly most unpopular with all classes of racegoers, tho Racecourse Association wishes to make the following suggestions which will, it considers, increase very largely the amount that will bo received by the Government and at the same time be as little unpopular as any tax can be to the general public. That a Dual System of Betting be Legalised to consist of(1) Bookmakers divided into two classes, viz., Course and Office. (2) Totalisators (or Pari-Mutuel). Dealing  first with  Course  Bookmakers, it is recommended that there should be no direct tax on course betting, but that bookmakers should pay their quota of the tax By Annual Licences(1) To be issued only to persons of good character. (2) To be forfeited for misconduct. (3) To be granted only to established bookmakers and not to newcomers, as it is generally acknowledged there are too many at the present time, and a gradual reduction would ensure only satisfactory men surviving.By Course Fee to be paid by all bookmakers on each dajr they bet. This fee to be graduated according to the Ring and the position therein, and to be collected by the Racecourse Executives and 50 per cent, handed over to Government.N.B. There was some difference of opinion among the Members of the Association as to the rates to be chargedrbut it is thought that at a moderate estimate, with the present number of bookmakers, the Government would receive  350,000.Any loss of revenue from these sources hy reduction of the number of bookmakers would be made up by increased takings from the Tote, and the charge for licences might be raised to the survivors.Second^. Totalisators (or Pari-Mutuels). These should be erected and managed by the Racecourse Executives and they should be permitted to deduct S per cent, from the gross takings, to be divided as follows: Government      -      -      2A per cent. Expenses   -      -      -      1&amp;   ,,     ,, Executive -      -      -      4    ,,     ,, The Government already takes 12 J per cent, of our gross takings as entertainment tax.N.B. The Government would get 2i per cent, without any deductions for cost of-collection, &amp;c.It is very difficult to estimate what the yield for the Tote would be, but taking figures from other countries, it is estimated that there would be an immediate yield of  300,000 per annum, which soon would gradually expand as the public got used to the machine. Besides which, it is confidently expected that with the greator amenities and lower charges of admission which will be possiblo with the extra revenue obtained by tho Racecourse Executives, the number of people attending races will very largely increase   But it is expected the chief source of revenue for tho Government would be Office Bookmakers. They would pay on Tote prices, and as theso are returned after 8 per cent, had been deducted, it appears that tho Bookmakers could afford to pay 4 per cent, and still have 4 per cent, for themselves. It is an acknowledged fact that the great volumo of betting is dono in offices; somo put it as high as 95 per cent., but taking the figure at 90 per cent, and tho course yield as above, tho total for the offices would amount to        - ... . .         4,320,000Add Bookmakers fees, say - - 350,000Yearly Liconcos - - - 350,000Course Toto      .... 300,000Making a grand total for the Govornmont of     -       5,320,000
FLAT  RACE  MEETINGS.1925.		1927.	% Decrease. 		 	179.034	March and April           IGiVJTI		9.00121,401)	May	104,242	14.13170.S88	June	104,317	9.0992,210	July	74,830	1S.S7138,085	August                       103,885		24.70140,502	September                  112,072		23.09848,704		712,220	16.08		NORTHERN.	Ayr		Hamilton Park	PontefractBeverley		Haydock Park	KedcarBogsido		Lanark	KiponCarlisle		Liverpool	StocktonCatterick Bridge		Manchester	ThirskDoncaster		Newcastle	YorkEdinburgh					MIDLAND.	Birmingham		Leicester	AVarwickChops tow		Lincoln	AArolverhamptonChester		Newmarket	AVorcestcrDerby		Nottingham	Yarmouth		SOUTHERN.	Alexandra Park		Folkestone	Linglield ParkBath		Gatwick	NewburyBibury	*	Hurst Park	SalisburyBrighton		Kempton Park	Sandown ParkEpsom		Lewes	A\rindsor		1925.              1927.	% Decrease.Northern ...		                         394,123            322,581	18.15Midland   ...		172,431             140,955	1S.25Southern ...		2S2.210            248.0S4	11.87		848,764            712,220	16.08
In addition, Racecourse Executives would receive sums which would enable them not only to maintain the amount of added money (which will be impossible without new sources of revenue), but to increase the amount, lower the prices of admission and increase tho amenities of racecourses an increased prosperity which the Government would share.Course Fee.Flat Racing 300 days per annumTattersalls-200 at  3 -Silver Ring-400 at  2 -Outside-500 at 10$.SayGovernment Racecourse Co. 250,000 250,000 500,000National Hunt 250 days&apos; racing per annumTattersalls-200 at  2 -400 at  1 -400 at 5s.   -SayGovernment Racecourse Co. 100,000 100,000 200,000Totalisator. 180,000 240,000 75,000 495,000 100,000 100,000 25,000 225,000Takings per person per day.Egypt (before Bookmakers were allowed double) -Bombay (no Bookmakers) Club and 1st enclosure   15   02nd enclosure   -      -      3 1510:  s. 3 15d. 0 18 15   0(A to allow for Bookmakers) Average  9 7s. 6d. Australia (rather vague)   -Average say4	13	01	10	0 9	18	0 3	6	0 3	0	0300 days&apos; racing Jockey Club at 10,000 persons per day - -  3,000,000 at  3 each.......... 9,000,0002i per cent........... 225,000250 days&apos; racing National Hunt say one-third        ...  73,000 29S.000say         300,0001925 France     .... Fr. 1,200,000,000at say      -      -      -      - -      48,000,0002J per cent.      ... -        1,200,000(A to allow for Bookmakers) -  600,000[P.T.O.
SCHEME   B.Every Starting Price Bookmaker, or representative of a Firm of Bookmakers, to pay an Annual Licence of  200 (instead of  10 as at present).The business of all Starting Price Bookmakers to be taxed at the rate of 1 per cent, in turnover.Racecourse Bookmakers to pay an Annual Licence fee (payable quarterly) at the following rate: Tattersalls Ring      -      -       200 per annum 10s. Ring ---      -       100 ,, Cheap Ring    ...        50 ,,      ,,and a Racecourse fee for each Meeting they attend at the following rate: Tattersalls Ring (on the Rails)  2 per day,,        ,,    (not on the Rails)     -  1  ,,  ,,10s. Ring...... 10s. ,,   ,,Cheap Ring      -      -      -      -      - 5s. ,,   ,,The estimated yield from the above is reckoned as follows: 10,000 Starting Price Bookmakers at  200 -     -      -     2,000,0001 per cent, on Turnover on Betting transactions of10,000 Starting Price Bookmakers      -      -      -      1,200,0002000 Racecourse Bookmakers at an average licence fee of  100........        200,000 3,400,000This sum, in addition to any sums accruing from Taxation on Betting on other forms of Sport, to go to the Exchequer.The daily fees of  2,  1,10s., or 5s. to go to the maintenance of the Sport of Racing.

</content>
</cab>
