<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/189/0 images: 325-330</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY * S GOVERNMENT.Iff.     . copy NO. 3 jj39) (27)0 A 3 I II E T Memorandum by the President of the Boardof Trade. Purchases of^Rusgian. Oil.A company which distributes petrol produced in this country from Russian oil is pressing the Board of Trade to inform them of the view of His Majesty^ Government in regard to purchasing Russian oil in order that, if no objection 1b raised, they can make use of the statement in obtaining contracts.     The Department receives a number of enquiries as to the propriety of trading with Russia to which the usual reply is a referenoe to the statements in the House of Commons by the Prime Minister and Foreign Secretaryj   but the case of oil is peculiar in view of the large proportion of the general publio who are interested in motor spirit and the propaganda against Russian petrol whioh has been going on in the Press.    It seems inevitable that His Majesty1s Government will have to make some definite pronouncement in regard to their own attitude as purchasers of oil.As regards the extent to which the Government are committed in the direction of discouraging the purchase of Russian oil, referenoe may be made to the following Resolution approved at the Final Plenary meeting of the Non-Russian Commission of the Hague Conference on 20th July, 1922:-&quot;The Conference recommends for the consideration of the Governments represented thereon the dor.irability of all Governments
not assisting their nationals in attempting to acquire property in Russia which belonged to other foreign nationals and which was confiscated since November 1st, 1917, without the consent of such foreign owners or concessionaires, provided that the same recommendation is subsequently made by Governments represented at the Hague Conference to all Governments not so represented, and that no decision shall be come to except jointly with those Governments&quot;.It may be taken for granted that practically all the oil exported by Russia is obtained from concessions which have been taken by the Soviet Government from foreign owners, although no doubt a certain quantity of oil is being obtained from new wells drilled in reoent years.   The Resolution, it will be seen, was of a tentative character and action was dependent on its acceptance by other Governments but in so far as the above Resolution imposes any sort of obligation on Eis Majesty&apos;s Government it relates only to refusing to help to British nationals acquiring oil concessions In Rusaia.     At the same time it perhaps implies discouragement of the purchase in this country of the oil produced in the confiscated concessions.Although no formal official steps have been taken the three great oil groups (Anglo-Persian, Shell and American) havo been encouraged by the Homo Secretary to
agree among themselves not to buy Russian oil. How far persons other than those directly concernod are aware of the action of the Home Secretary is not known.      The position has been complicated by contracts with Russia made in the present year by the Standard Oil Co. of New York and tho Vacuum Oil Company (a subsidiary of the Standard .oil of New Jersey) which have led to public announcements of the Standard Oil of Now Jersey that they are opposed to purchasing Russian oil.The contracting Departments themsolves are understood to pursue a policy of not knowingly purchasing Russian oil.      It is, however, very probable that some of their contracts for lubricating oil are with firms who obtain supplies from Russia.     Moreover, the Admiralty are believed to purohase from British firms timber which is known to b6 of Russian origin.     It is difficult, therefore, to say that the Government have a consistent policy in this matter.As against theso indications of a policy of boycotting Russian oil we have public statements to the effect that the Government do not wish to place any obstaoles in the way of Russian trade. The Prime Minister on May 24th stated in the House of Commons that H.M.G. while torminating the privileges conferred by Articles 4. 5 and 6 of the Trade Agreement, were prepared to mako all arrangements necessary for ordinary trade
facilitiea between the two countries.   The Foreign Secretary on 28th July said &quot;but trade may go on. We will do nothing to interfere with it.&quot;   The Home Secretary in a letter to Sir Philip Nash: &quot;It cannot be stated too emphatically that far from desiring to place any obstaole in the way of trade between the two countries, H.M. Government desire to foster that trade and there is not, and never has been, any intention, to interfere with the freedom of any British trader who desires to do business with Russia.&quot;It is clear that trade cannot be carried on in one direction only and that the authorisation of trade with   Russia applies to imports of Russian goods as well as to exports of British goods, though It is true that the Soviet sells here a great deal more than it buys.It may, however, be urged that special considerations apply to trade in goods which are identifiable as having been confiscated by the Russians.   In view of the legal position no obstacle is plaoed in the way of trading in such goods and it must be left to every private trader to decide for himself whether he should buy or refrain from buying a particular article.   But I suggest the time has oome for the Government as a Government to oonsider the possibility of having a consistent policy in this matter of purchasing goods of Russian origin.   It is known in the oil world that the Government do appear to have a policy of not buying Russian oil and there is little doubt that
they will soon be forced to answer the question whether or no they purchase it.Viewed as a general question it would seem very desirable that the policy of the Government should be consistent, that is, that not only should all contracting Departments pursue ti:e sane policy In regard to all petroleum products but that the same policy should apply to other goods, e.g. timber.   This general policy presumably would be not knowingly to purchase any goods known to have been stolen. There is also the furtner question whether inquiry should be made as to ultimate origin in cases where there is a possibility of Russian origin.How far it is possible to pursue a consistent policy in this matter is a question on wnich obviously the views of the Contracting Departments must be obtained. There may be articles which these Departments consider it necessary or desirable to obtain from Rib sia (e.g. platinum) and there may be others (including oil) in the case of which for defence and similar reasons such a course is undesirable.    Petrol was a vital article during the General Strike, when Russian Oil Products held back their petrol and Russia stopped the export of oil to this country.   Had Government Departments been dependent on Russian Oil Products for their petrol, difficulties might have arisen.    In the case of petrol the Contracting Departments have a favourable contract with the Combine Companies based on exclusive dealing with them and this in itself makes it unlikely that the Government Departments will be able to buy Russian pe^rol^I suggest therefore, that &quot;when asked their attitude to the sale of Russian oil or other stolen commodities, the answer of the Government should be that while no obstacle is placed by the Government in the way of any form of trade, and while every British subject is free to buy or not a3 he pleases\ -5-
it ia the practice of His Majesty^ Government to avoid buying goods which have been confiscated without payment.F.C-L.3oard of Trade,22nd November, 1927.

</content>
</cab>
