<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/189/0 images: 334-340</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
his document is the property of His Britannic Majesty1s Government SECRET.CABINET. CP. 291(27) _PROPOSED PURCHASE OF PERSIAN OPIUM BY THE GOVERNMENT OF HONG KONG.3.Joint Memorandum by the Secretaries of State for Foreign Affairs and the Home Department.We circulate for tho information of our colleagues the attached memorandum by Sir Malcolm Delevingne, the Chairman of the Standing Inter Departmental Committee on the Opium and Dangerous Drugs Policy of His Majesty1s Government, which has had under consideration the change recently introduced by the Governor of Hong Kong into the opium policy of the Colony and his resulting request for permission to purchase for the Colony a considerable quantity of Persian opium.We agree entirely with the views expressed in the memorandum and, unless His Majesty&apos;s Government is prepared to abandon all its previous pretensions and in effect to repudiate its obligations under the Hague Convention, we fear that we do not see how the change in policy introduced by the Governor of Hong Kong can be approved or his request for permission to purchase large quantities of Persian opium can be sanctioned.      It seems to us to be very regrettable that the Governor should have introduced without previous consultation with His Majesty&apos;s Government so serious a departure from its established policy.A .C . W.J .H.22 .11.27 .
Memorandum by Sir Malcolm Delevingne, Chairman of the Standing Inter-Departmental Committee on the Opium Policy of H.M. Government.The proposal of the Governor of Hong Kong which has been brought before the Cabinet by the Acting Secretary of State for the Colonies in C.P.2B4(27),  to import a considerable quantity of Persian opium, has been considered by the Inter-Departmental Committee(representing the Home Office, Foreign Office and Colonial Office) which v/as appointed this year by the instructions of the Cabinet to consider questions of policy relating to opium, and dangerous drugs.     After an adjournment   during which further information was sought from the Governor of Hong Kong, and consideration of the explanations given by him, the representatives of the Foreign Office and the Home Office were unable to agree with the Colonial Office in recommending the Governor&apos;s proposal for the approval of the Cabinet.While not underrating the difficulties in which the extensive smuggling of opium from China, following upon the deplorable opium situation in that country, has involved the Government of Hong Kong in common with other Far Eastern territories (Hong Kong no doubt to a greater extent than most), there appear to the Foreign Office and Home Office to be important considerations arising out of the position and policy of H.M. Government in Great Britain in regard to the opium question to which sufficientTHE CHANGE WHICH THE GOVERNOR OP HOHG KONG HAS INTRODUCED IN THE OPIUM POLICY OP THE COLONY AND HIS RESULTING REQUEST FOR PERMISSION TO IMPORT A CONSIDERABLE QUANTITY 0?  PERSIAN OPIUM, A REQUEST FOR WHICH SANCTION IS BEING ASKED IN THE COLONIAL OFFICE MEMORANDUM  (CP. 204(27)).
weight, in their, view, is not given in the Colonial Office memorandum and which should be taken into account before a decision is reached.     They can be summarised quite briefly.1. H.M. Government is committed by the Hague Convention of 1912 to the eventual suppression of opium smoking in its territories.      In face of the charges made by the United States Delegation at the Geneva Conference of 1924-5 that Great Britain, with other Powers, was not fulfilling its obligations in this respect, the policy of H.M. Government was reaffirmed at that Conference and its intention to proceed with the restrictive measures already introduced or in contemplation emphatically asserted.It is not claimed by the Colonial Office, nor apparently by the Governor of Hong Kong, that the new policy will eventually pave the way for further restrictions or will - so far as the actual rate of opium consumption is concerned - lead to any improvement in the situation.The position in the Colony is that the plentiful supply of opium from China has greatly increased the consumption of opium in the Colony.      The proposal of the Governor is apparently to capture the field at present occupied by the smugglers by placing a large quantity of cheap Government opium on the market, and to drive the smugglers out of business.     At any rate, in his telegram of 23rd October, replying to the request for explanations, he says that he has every reason to expect as a result of the new policy that Government will emerge masters from the field.     It may be conceded at once that if there was a good prospect of driving the smugglers permanently out of business, the resulting advantages would be so great in the long run as possibly to outweigh the disadvantages which will be referred to presently.     Ho such prospect, however, exists.     The Colonial Office admit (Par. 20 of CO.
id tf himemorandum) that it is not expected to recax^ture the whole of the field occupied by the smugglers - and even if the whole field were captured, it is evident that it could only be held by continuing indefinitely a supply of cheap opium the amount of whioh would be limited only by the demands of the consumers.     As soon as any attempt were made to reduce supplies with a view to resuming the Government *s policy of restriction and eventual suppression, the field would be at onoe invaded again by cheap opium from China.These points were put to the Governor of Kong Kong in Colonial Office telegram of 15th October but not answered by him in his reply of the 23rd.The new policy cannot then be justified on the ground that it is a measure which is only transitional in character and will pave the way for a continuance of the policy of restriction and eventual suppression to which HGovernment is deeply pledged.2. The effect of the new policy will be to raise the sales of Government opium in Hong Kong and the imports of opium into Hong Kong to a figure much exceeding that of any year since the Government monopoly was established. The Governor asks for 40 chests a month of Persian opium at once, in addition to the 196 chests which will be received from India in 1928 - a total for next year of at least 676 chests.     The imports for the last 11 years have been -1916 360 chests 1917 420 &quot; 1910 450 &quot; 1919 540 &quot; 1920 180 &quot; 1921 120 &quot; 1922 150 &quot; 1923 260 &quot; 1924 220 &quot; 1925 250 &quot; 1926        165      &quot;The new policy was introduced on the 3rd October.The Governor telegraphing four days later reported that the
sales   had already risen from 500 to 2,ono taels a day and might go higher.     What the figure stands at now has not yet been reported.     There can be no guarantee that the increase will stop at the point reached by October 7th.     If the proportion of illicit to licit opium consumed in the Colony has risen to 10 to l (Art. 12 of CO. Memorandum) there is a wide field still left for expansion - 2,000 taels still represents less than one half of the daily consumption in the Colony.The Government is therefore faced with the consequence, if the Governor&apos;s proposal is approved, that if the new policy is completely successful in capturing the -whole or greater part of the field occupied by the illicit traffic, the sales of Government opium will rise to an enormous figure, while if only one half the field is captured, the figures will still exceed greatly the figures for any year since the Government monopoly was established.The revenue derived from the Government sales will presumably also increase,  though not in the same proportion.It is hardly necessary to point out the handle this situation will give to the anti-British propagandists and the critics of our policy in the United States, in China, and no doubt also in Japan which is watching us closely. It is inevitable also that our hands will be weakened at Geneva in the efforts we are making to bring the much bigger problem of the drug traffic under better control and that our position there in regard to the whole question, and perhaps in other respects too, will be prejudiced.3. The probable effect on the Persian&apos; situation is not negligible.     At the request of the Persian Government and with the unanimous approval of the Council and Assembly, a commission was sent by the League to Persia last year to report on the measures which could be taken to reduce the
production of Persian opium, almost the whole of which for years past has been sent out to the Par East for smoking purposes, in large part clandestinely to the detriment of Hong Kong as well as other countries,     The work of the Commission received the approval of the recent Assembly, and the Persian Government have decided to give effect in large measure to its recommendations.     Since the Commission reported, the situation has already been affected by the large orders from Malaya for Persian opium (a matter which engaged the attention of the Cabinet earlier in the present year and about which the Colonial Office is still in correspondence with the Government, of the Straits Settlements) and other Far Eastern territories, resulting in part from the decreased exports from India and in part from the increased demands of consumers.     Speaking in the Fifth Committee of the recent Assembly, Colonel MacCormack, one of the Persian Delegation, warned the Assembly that this increased demand for Persian Opium would intensify the opposition of the producers and merchants in Persia to the Persian Government&apos;s new policy.Hong Kong is now asking to add to this demand by contracting for an annual supply of 4P0 chests, and there is at least a strong probability that the supply eventually required to carry through the new policy of the Hong Kong Government will be much larger.It will be observed that it is not a question merely of making good the reduction in the supply of Indian opium to the Colony whioh will follow from the Government of India&apos;s policy of progressively reducing exports - the proposal goes much further.4. In the Acting Governor&apos;s reply of the 23rd Ootober, the advantages from the new policy on whioh he mainly insists are the prevention of wholesale violation of the
21st November, 1927.law, relief to the local prison, and a check to the decline in the opium revenue.     As to the first and second of these, it can only be said that unless the new policy is far more successful than is anticipated, smuggling will still continue on an extensive scale (see paragraph 2 above) and that the reestablishment of Government control and of respect for the law can be very partial only.In the Appendix to his despatch of October the 6th the Acting Governor gives the number of convictions during the last four years and the first eight months of this. These figures do not show that the  situation this year has grown appreciably worse.     Its figures are on the same level as those for 1924, 1925 and 1926.In conclusion, it seems most unfortunate that so serious a departure from the established policy of the Government should have been made by the Governor of Hong Kong without any previous consultation with the Home Government.M.D.

</content>
</cab>
