<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 46-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(5 9) 8COPY NO.20th January, 1959CABINETREPRESENTATION OF THE VATICAN IN THEUNITED kingdom memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Duke of Norfolk has written to the Prime Minister, at therequest of the Catholic Union of Great Britain, to urge again theacceptance of an Internuncio (equivalent to a Minister in the diplomatic corps) as representative of the Vatican in this country.2.      This question was last considered by the Cabinet on 14th May,1957 (C.C.(57) 40th Conclusions, Minute 6).   As I then informed mycolleagues, the anomaly whereby Her Majesty&apos;s Government are represented by a Minister at the Vatican, but the Vatican is not represented diplomatically here, has lasted since 1914.   Although the vatican has maintained an Apostolic Delegate in London since 1938,he is a strictly ecclesiastical functionary with no diplomatic status.The Vatican has made no direct request for diplomatic status for itsrepresentative, but the case for an Internuncio (who would rank as a minister) has frequently been put by representatives of the roman catholic community in the United Kingdom.   The Law Officers of theCrown stated in 1957 that they foresaw no legal or constitutional objectionto such an appointment.   But the Archbishop of Canterbury made it plain informally that he would object to the reception of an Internuncio,and I had received a number of letters from Members of Parliament andFrotestant bodies stating their objection to a change.   The objections toa change thus related to domestic rather than foreign policy.3.      In submitting this question to my colleagues in May, 1957, Isummarised these arguments as follows:-In favour of an Internuncio -(a)It is a logical measure of reciprocity to the Vatican.(b)It would please Roman Catholics at home.(c)It would please certain Western European and Latin-american countries.Against an Internuncio -(a)There is no pressing demand for it.
(b) It might relight the flames of a religious controversy which(for example, in Liverpool) has died down even within my own lifetime.(c) It would offend some Protestants in the United Kingdom.   in ulster, it might have a serious political effect for a time.4.      On balance I thought it would be inexpedient to make any change,particularly since there appeared to be no considerable public support for it.   Discussion showed that my colleagues were in agreement withthis view.   They agreed that it would be inexpedient to respond favourably,at that time, to representations that the representative of the Vaticanin the United Kingdom should be accorded diplomatic status.5.      In raising this question again now, the Duke of Norfolk&apos;s letterto the Prime Minister (Annex A) states that he is encouraged by the universal sympathy and understanding which British Catholics have met with over the death of the late Pope, to feel that the proposal (to accept an Internuncio) would now meet with a wide measure of approval both at  home and in the Commonwealth.   He advances the argument that the coronation of the new Pope would seem to offer a very favourable opportunity for Her Majesty1 s Government to make this gesture.   Thememorandum by the Catholic Union of Great Britain, enclosed with the duke of Norfolk*s letter (Annex B), makes the additional points that thepresent Apostolic Delegate experiences difficulties in his officialcontacts owing to the private character of his office;  that it is unsatisfactory that the Vatican should be represented in so many other non-Catholic countries but not in the United Kingdom;  that the presentanomaly is disadvantageous to Her Majesty&apos;s Government;  and that full co-operation and understanding between all anti-Communist forces is most desirable.   The memorandum finally expresses the opinion that thefears that the appointment of an Internuncio would lead to an outburstin Protestant circles are groundless.6.      I have consulted the Home Secretary about this letter.   while he will no doubt wish to express his own views, I am informed that, while recognising that the granting of diplomatic status would undoubtedly givepleasure to Roman Catholics in this country (who are believed to number4-f millions) he is doubtful about the Duke of NorfolkTs belief that itwould meet with wide support from the rest of the country, in particular the Church of England and the free churches.   He considers that a periodof delay is desirable to assess the position since the appointment of another British Cardinal, and that we must be satisfied that the appoint-ment of an Internuncio would not be taken as the prelude to the appoint-ment of a Nuncio which might, he suggests, raise problems about the&quot;doyenship&quot; of the Diplomatic Corps.   He adds that the British roman catholics are intransigent about attending religious functions, and feels that as they are apparently not closely in tune with the other religiousbodies in this country, it is necessary to delay till later considerationof any new experiment in representation.7.      From the Foreign Office point of view, we should naturallywelcome all allies against Soviet subversion, and to this end we valuestrong relations with the Vatican.   But the prestige of the Vatican does-2-
not depend upon the relations which it maintains with other purely-temporal powers.   Despite the arguments advanced in the CatholicUnion of Great Britain&apos;s memorandum, the fact remains that neitherthe United States, nor any Protestant country in Europe except Holland(which has a very large Roman Catholic minority) has diplomatic relations with the Vatican.   Nor do Canada or Australia, except insofar as they are represented at the Vatican by Her Majesty&apos;s Minister.I do not think that in these circumstances our present extremelycordial relations would suffer if it became known that we had once againjudged it premature to make a change.   I am certainly aware of no specific disadvantage to Her Majesty&apos;s Government in the continuation of the present long-standing situation, anomalous though it may appearto be.   While, therefore, I should have liked to mark the new reign bythe gesture of making the Apostolic Delegate an Internuncio, and am not particularly afraid that that would lead to his later seekingAmbassadorial status or putting forward a claim to be regarded asDoyen of the Diplomatic Corps, I think the balance of arguments remainsmuch as it was in 1957, and that nothing has happened, at any rate in theinternational field, which would call for a change in the decision reachedthen.8.     At the present time this matter is perhaps more one of domesticpolitics than one principally affecting the Foreign Office.   I should therefore be grateful for the views of my colleagues.S.L.Foreign Office, S.W.1.20th January, 1959-3-
ANNEX ACOPY &apos;T A LETTER FROM THE DUKE OF NORFOLKTO THE PRIME MINISTERArundel Castle1st November, 1958My dear Prime Minister,As you know the Queen has commanded me to attend the coronation of the new Pope as her personal representative.2.     I am writing at the request of the Catholic Union of GreatBritain, of which I am the President,to ask whether at the beginningof a new Pontificate you would reconsider the position of the Pope!personal representative in this country.   Specifically we would ask thathe be given the same diplomatic status as that of Her Majesty&apos;representative to the Holy See, that is, not as a Nuncio or Ambassador,but as an Internuncio or Minister.3.      I enclose a memorandum stating the case for making this change and I think the arguments advanced in it very cogent.4.      This question was first raised with Winston Churchill in 1953,but at that time the Apostolic Delegate was a British subject, and I was told that there would be difficulties in giving diplomatic status to anEnglishman in this country.   When a United States citizen was appointedI took the matter up through Salisbury, who, I believe, personallysupported the proposal.5.      I am aware that, after Salisbury&apos;s resignation, Selwyn Lloydmade a statement, which appeared in the Times of 29th May, 1957, to theeffect that he was &quot;not contemplating any new initiative&quot; about the appoint-ment &quot;of an Ambassador from the Vatican to the United Kingdom&quot;.   Iam, of course, not asking for the appointment of an Ambassador, but only of an Internuncio.   The circumstances, moreover, seem to me to have changed considerably since Selwyn Lloyd&apos;s statement.6.      I am encouraged by the universal sympathy and understanding which British Catholics have met with over the death of the late Pope, to feel that the proposal would now meet with a wide measure of approvalboth at home and in the Commonwealth.   The country as a whole hasrecently shown its appreciation of the role which the Vatican plays in furthering the cause of international peace, and in co-operating inchecking the spread of atheistic communism.7. The Coronation of the new Pope would seem to offer a very favourable opportunity for Her Majesty&apos;s Government to make thisgesture.-4-
8.     The request for this change of status would of course have tocome from the Vatican.   But I know that they will certainly make itas soon as they are privately assured that Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentwill favourably respond.Yours sincerely,(Signed)  NORFOLK.ANNEX BSTATUS OF THE VATICAN REPRESENTATIVE INTHE UNITED KINGDOMThe United Kingdom like most other countries outside the iron curtain has long been represented at the Vatican by a fully accrediteddiplomatic Minister;  but the arrangement is not reciprocal, as the vatican is only unofficially represented in the United Kingdom by anApostolic Delegate who has no diplomatic status.   The situation thuscreated is anomalous and has been proving increasingly embarrassingand inconvenient.   Very large numbers of Catholic British subjects are anxious to see this anomaly remedied.   Many Catholic foreign diplomatsin London have expressed surprise at its continuance, and at least oneof the senior Commonwealth High Commissioners has spoken privatelyin the same sense.2.      The difficulties of the present situation are real.   Although thepresent Apostolic Delegate, Archbishop 0&apos;Hara, held full diplomaticstatus when he was Papal Nuncio in Dublin before coming here, hisposition in London is entirely unofficial.   He deals with various Govern-ment Departments, more particularly the Colonial Office on matters which concern the Vatican, but can only do so privately and informally.He maintains similar unofficial contacts with the Foreign &quot;&quot;office, but here again can only act informally.   He is in fact tolerated rather thanrecognised.   Although the Catholic diplomats in London regard him as acolleague, he has in fact no such status, and is conspicuous by his absence on such official diplomatic occasion as the Lord Mayor&apos;sBanquet, etc.3.     Apart from countries such as France, the German federal republic, Belgium (and Luxembourg), Italy, Spain, Portugal, the irish republic, Switzerland, the Latin-American countries, etc. which acceptPapal Nuncios with the status of Ambassador, the Vatican is represented,on a reciprocal basis, by Internuncios, with the status of Minister, ina number of non-Catholic countries such as the Netherlands, Japan,Egypt, India, Pakistan, Fersia, Indonesia and Syria.   It may be questioned whether it is entirely satisfactory that official Vatican representations should be so strong in other countries, including two member-statesof the Commonwealth, and particularly in so many Asian countries, while there is no official Vatican representative in London.
4e4.     It may be asked what British advantage would be served by accepting a Vatican Representative in this country when there is already a British Minister to the Holy See.    It is, of course, the normal inter-national practice that diplomatic representation should be on a reciprocal basis.    But it is not merely to conform with practice, or asan act of courtesy, that the British Government receives in London a diplomatic Representative from every other State to which a BritishDiplomatic Representative is accredited.    It is because it has found thatthe system pays.    There are many occasions when the British point ofview, or a British request, can be far more forcibly impressed on aforeign Government through its representative in London than through theBritish Representative in the State concerned.5.     Two other points may be worth noting particularly from the pointof view of those opposed to the proposal.     Firstly, full diplomatic relations, i. e. full &quot;recognition&quot;, do not constitute &quot;approval&quot; as therelations of the U.S.A. with Russia have shown.    Secondly in the presentconflict between the Free World and Communism, full co-operation and understanding between all anti-Communist forces is most desirable, andit is generally recognised that one of the strongest forces opposed toCommunism is the Holy See.6.     When the proposal has been put forward on previous occasionsvarious arguments have been urged against it.   I would only deal with two.   (l)   Under the customary right recognised by the Congress of vienna a Nuncio is normally Doyen of the Diplomatic Corps.   Thiswould clearly be impossible in a non-Catholic country.    (2)   Theacceptance of Her Majesty&apos;s Government of a fully accrediteddiplomatic representative from the Vatican might create an outcry incertain circles, which might embarrass Her Majesty&apos;s Government andlead to an unfortunate revival of anti-Catholic feeling.7.     These arguments can all be effectively answered.   As for (l) theproposal is for the appointment of an Internuncio with the status of minister, not of a Nuncio with the status of Ambassador.   Pie would therefore rank after all the foreign Ambassadors, and the question ofDoyenship would not arise.    (2)  Although similar fears were expressed at the time in certain quarters, there was in fact no serious outbreak of anti-Catholic feeling when the United Kingdom diplomatic mission tothe Vatic3.n was established some forty years ago.   Is there really anyground for believing that there would now be an outburst of such feelingif the normal corollary of the existence of a United Kingdom Legationat the Vatican were carried through by the acceptance of a VaticanInternuntiature in London?   There was no outcry when the ApostolicDelegation was established here with the consent of Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment some years ago.-6-

</content>
</cab>
