<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 109-110</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.(59) 19 C6PY NO6th February, 1959CABINETVOLUNTARY SCHOOLS;   INCREASED AIDMemorandum by the Minister of Education&quot;Tantaene animis caelestibus irae ? &quot; (Virgil, Aeneid I, ll)introduction in the White Paper on Secondary Education, Cmnd. 604, weundertook to consider the possibility of giving more help to the churches.I have now had talks with representatives of the churches and other interests concerned as well as with leaders of the Opposition and Ishould like to tell my colleagues what I think we should do next.2.        It will be remembered that the Church of England have asked that the existing grants should be increased from their presentmaximum of 50 per cent to 75 per cent and that in addition the roman Catholics (and the Jews) have asked that grant should be paid on new schools needed to extend their school systems.   The roman catholics are oppressed by the size of their financial burden which islikely to be increased by the growth of their school population.   they expect the number of Roman Catholic children of school age to increase from 865,000 to over 1,200,000 by 1970.Increase in the rate of grant3.        It is generally accepted that some increase in the rateof grant is inevitable, though some sections of educational opinionconsider that an increase to 75 per cent would be excessive.4.        There is no doubt, however, that the churches would not beable to meet even their existing commitments without a substantial increase in the existing grants and our proposals for the developmentof secondary education will be seriously impeded if we do not give it to them.   The Free Churches have told me that, though for reasons of principle they cannot support, they would not violently oppose theChurch of England&apos;s request and it would, I think, be a difficult operationpolitically for front bench spokesmen on either side of the House, once the principle of an increase has been accepted, to justify to back benchsupporters of the church schools a decision to increase the grant to say65 per cent but not to 75 per cent.5.        In all the circumstances, I propose that the maximum rate of grant on work at present eligible for grant should be increased from50 per cent to 75 per cent.   I estimate that this would cost the exchequer on the average about  1. 25 millions a year for the next twenty years.-1-(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
CONRDENTSALThe extension of grant6.        When my colleagues last considered the matter they were agreed that it was out of the question to pay grant on all new schoolsbut that I might explore the possibility of extending grant to theprovision of new secondary schools needed to match aided primary schools of the same denomination which exist at present.   On thebasis of a 75 per cent grant, the extra cost of this would averageabout  650,000 a year for twenty years.7.         The Church of England, who have openly rejected any ideaof asking for grant for new schools, because it would be a substantial change in the settlement of 1944, are uneasy about this proposal.   TheFree Churches also are opposed to it, partly for reasons of principlebut, more fundamentally, because they are fearful of the growing number and influence of the adherents of the Church of Rome andof the long-term consequences for our way of life which they apprehendfrom that growth.8.        At the same time this proposal, which is conceived in thespirit of the Education Act, 1936, would not involve any serious changein the settlement of 1944 and it has definite educational advantages,not the least of which is that it would enable me to pay grant on theprovision of new Roman Catholic grammar and technical schools.This is particularly important in the context of our proposals for developing secondary education.   The educational organisations are notunanimous but some of them recognise the advantages of this proposal.The Church of England might, I believe, be persuaded to see theunwisdom of appearing to stand in the way of educational progress and it is possible that the opposition of the Free Churches could atleast be contained.9. The Roman Catholics, too,   acknowledge that this proposal would be a real help to them.   It is, of course, very far from meetingtheir full demands which they will, therefore, renew sooner or later,especially for help with the provision of new primary schools in new towns and other developing areas.   But in my judgment a futureMinister of Education will be better able to deal - with their demandsif we have put the Roman Catholics in a position where they will beable to play their part in the educational advance which we are now making.   If we do not, I think that there is a serious risk that theirsecondary schools will lag badly behind.Conclusion10.      Accordingly, I ask my colleagues to agree that we should give more help to the churches and that this help should take the form of anincrease in the rate of grant to 75 per cent and of a limited extensionof grant to certain new secondary schools.   I should propose then tohave afurther round of talks with representatives of the churches andto report again to my colleagues when I have done so.G.L.Ministry of Education, W. 1.6th February, 1959-2-

</content>
</cab>
