<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 129-130</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC. MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1959 .......C. (59) 2720th February, 1959CABINET. EUROPEAN ECONOMIC community memorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerThere are four fundamental difficulties in the way of the United Kingdomjoining the European Economic Community (E.E.C.):  (a) A Customs Union forces the adoption of a common commercial policy.But, if the United Kingdom had not its own commercial policy, relationswith the Commonwealth would be fundamentally changed. Moreover,in a situation where three-quarters of our trade is with the world outside europe, whereas three-quarters of the trade of the Six is with Europe,things that are fundamental to us appear marginal to them. Thecommon commercial policy that was hammered out over, the years would, in practice, tend to be damaging to the Commonwealth.For example, import of Asiatic textiles would be very restricted.Lancashire might approve, but our relations with India, Pakistan and ceylon would be fundamentally changed.(b) The Treaty of.Rome provides for the elaboration of a common agricultural policy. So far as British agriculture is concerned such an obligationwould be in conflict with the Agriculture Act, 1957. The farmers mightnot object; they, and the horticulturalists would, however, expect toget in such a system a satisfactory level of protection.But the Commonwealth interest could hardly be safeguarded.A common agricultural production policy necessarily implies a common agricultural import policy, and the open market in the United kingdom for Commonwealth food producers would be bound to disappear.(c) Implicitly the Six are working towards some sort of political unity.   Forexample, the Treaty provides that in due course the Assembly shall be directly elected by universal suffrage. Whether the France ofGeneral de Gaulle is in fact, may be doubted. But, unless the six were to renounce any political objectives, the act of the United kingdom in joining the E.E.C. would implicitly accept them.(d) It cannot be assumed that the Six would be prepared to have us in on terms which would begin to safeguard the Commonwealth position.Safeguarding the Commonwealth position means reducing theattractiveness of the United Kingdom market to the other members ofthe Customs Union. Buying wheat, meat, dairy products, from theCommonwealth means that we cannot buy them from the Europeanproducers. Moreover, we must not lose sight of the fact that we could have had a Free Trade Area with the Five. It was France whichresisted, because she was determined to limit the competition to whichFrench industry was exposed and not to reduce her chances of makingthe common commercial policy of the Six a reflection or magnificationof existing French commercial policy. These French objections to a free Trade Area would also be valid objections to our membership of the E.E.C., and they would be effective in practice because the admission of a new member involves renegotiation of the most delicatelybalanced part of the whole structure.Copy No.    5954781
Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,U9fh February, 1959.2. There are two points which were regarded as insuperable in 1955 but which might not be so to-day if all the Six were really anxious to include the UnitedKingdom and if on other grounds the United Kingdom wished to join (a) It was assumed in 1955 that if the United Kingdom were a member of a customs Union we should have to put a tariff on Commonwealth goods,and this was clearly an insuperable obstacle. But in principle this is nolonger the case. The Treaty of Rome implicitly includes the possibilityof free entry Eastern German goods into Western Germany, Tunisian,Moroccan and French overseas territories&apos; goods into France. Whetherthe Six would agree to Commonwealth free entry is another matter; thescale of the Commonwealth problem is altogether different from theexisting exceptions. And formidable origin problems would arise, evenif the common tariff was tailor-made to suit us.(b) We assumed in 1955 that the institutions of the Customs Union would beso supra-national that we could not accept them. We may not like verymuch the existing arrangements in the E.E.C., but they are far short ofbeing supra-national.3. There are two other points of serious but perhaps not insuperable difficulty (a) The Treaty of Rome has obligations about the free movement of workers.What they mean is not entirely clear. In an extreme form they wouldbe unacceptable to the trade unions.(b) Harmonisation of social  and  fiscal policies.    Generally,  these  areobligations in principle and the detailed application of them over theyears is subject to unanimous voting. There are three specificobligations: the two relating to overtime and paid holidays we were. ready to accept in the Free Trade Area; the third, dealing with equal pay &quot;for men and women, would involve a change in our policy, probablyacceptable to the trade unions but unwelcome to the employers.D. H. A.

</content>
</cab>
