<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 137-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1959C. (59) 31 Copy No.   5 416th February, 1959CABINETMALAYAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations have just returned from a 10-day visit to the Federation of Malaya. I thinkmy colleagues may wish to have a brief report on the progress made by this newestmember of the Commonwealth during the 18 months since it became independent.Progress2.   In general, the situation in Malaya is very encouraging.Decline of the Emergency(a) Thanks to the determined efforts of the Malayan Government with substantial British and Commonwealth assistance, the Emergency is for most ofthe country practically over. There are now under a thousand terrorists left andmost of them are hiding in the dense jungle along or beyond the Thai border.Though active operations in the border area still continue and Emergencyexpenditure will not fall off very quickly, elsewhere in Malaya most of therestrictions, on for example movement and food, have been removed and thereis little remaining evidence of the Emergency. There has, therefore, been a quitespectacular change in the atmosphere and the general outlook is one of confidence and optimism.Stability and Good Government(b) There is a general impression of stability and good government. this impression which mainly derives from the efficiency of the day-to-day conduct bythe Malayan authorities of their ordinary affairs is fortified by (i) ample evidenceof very good police and security forces; (ii) the stabilising effects of the religiousauthority and popular respect which the ruling Princes continue to enjoy; and (iii)the continued presence of large numbers of British expatriate officers in all kinds of posts. The atmosphere of order and stability is further strengthened by the immense majority which the present Government enjoy in the Federal Legislatureand which most observers expect them to maintain after this year&apos;s elections.High Standard of Living(c) The standard of living of the average Malayan is still the highest in Asia.Rubber and tin, on which the economy is so dependent, have had their ups anddowns, but are on the whole doing better than was expected and the future of rubber is generally agreed to be good. One feature of this high standard of livingis the exceptionally advanced facilities for education.Friendship Towards the United Kingdomid) The attitude towards the United Kingdom of most Malayans at presentin positions of authority and influence is extremely friendly. They respect theway they were helped towards independence. They greatly appreciate theassistance they have received and are receiving from the United Kingdom (andfrom Australia and New Zealand) particularly in dealing with the Emergency.54755
They recognise and seem reasonably happy about their reliance on us in the field of defence. They value United Kingdom economic investment in Malaya and givegood treatment! to; our planters: and, business;people. And to a remarkable extent they seem uncontaminated; by and even uninterested in the Afro-Asian neutralismprevalent in so manyneighbouring countries.Potential Dangers3. On the other hand, despite the favourable factors which I have just listed,there is clearly an inherent fragility in the economic and political situation in malaya which we should be unwise to ignore.Subversion(a) Though the Emergency is virtually over there is an immense field forsubversion which the Communists are actively exploiting. They have a firm base in Singapore, latent racial conflict to play on, and millions of young Chinese tocatch in the schools. The Federal Government is well aware of this danger butthey will need much wisdom if they are at once to be firm with the Communists andto retain the loyalty of the Chinese.; (b) The apparent stability of the political situation could be endangered atfour points:Over-rapid Malayanisation(i) Malayanisation of the Government Services is now proceeding much more rapidly than is really healthy. Theoretically 1962 is the deadline butthe vast majority of expatriate officers will have gone long before then.Ministers see the dangers but for political reasons feel unable to do anything about them. There is some good material among the Malayrecruits, and hitherto corruption has made little headway. Nevertheless,there are already the first signs of a slowing down in the administration and of a slight lowering of standards.Chinese Dissatisfaction(ii) The Chinese, living mainly in the towns, are cleverer and more efficientthan the Malays and outdistance them in most occupations. An attempt is being made to create a new generation which will be Malayan first and always. In the primary schools the children are taught the samecurriculum in Malay and Chinese. In the secondary schools Chinesedrops out and English becomes the second language. The newexperiment may succeed in blurring the racial division. As long asbusiness is good and the Chinese can make money, they are willing togo along and seem to be quite good if rather superior neighbours tothe Malays. But if the economic situation were to deteriorate or the malays were to abuse their present controlling position, then aninflammable situation could easily arise and the present progress towardsracial harmony would be badly disrupted.Singapore(iii) Malayan Ministers are very afraid of the domination of the Federation bythe Singapore Chinese and the spread to the Federation of the politicalatmosphere of that City. Singapore is anxious for union but the malayan Prime Minister told me that any kind of union or federation was out of the question as Singapore would use any such arrangement to swamp the Malays in conjunction with the local Chinese. To remainapart when so many obvious advantages can be claimed for union willbe a very difficult political exercise, but there is certainly substance inthe Prime Ministers fears.Elections(iv) While most shrewd observers feel entirely confident about the outcome of this year&apos;s elections, the enormous increase in the number of young people, possibly upsetting the present racial balance, makes them much less confident of their ability to foresee what will happen in 5 or10 years&apos; time.
&apos; Population Increase -ntd \u\ n- ynqivH v ihiu: -r:v, - -&apos; (c) While:&apos; Malaya&apos;s economy is at present fairly strong, its future isovershadowed by the very rapid increase in population. 50 per cent, of thepopulation are under 20 years of age. Food supply and employment will becomemajor problems. The answers lie broadly in increasing the acreage and yield of paddy, in replanting with higher yielding rubber trees and developing secondary industries, along of course with a campaign for birth control which will be difficultto establish. Naturally, in this context, Malayan Ministers are much interestedin the success of the Tin Pool Scheme and in launching a scheme to help to stabilise the price of rubber. They would particularly value any help we can giveover the latter scheme.Conclusion4. Drawing a balance, my own conclusion is that the outlook in Malaya is good at any rate for the next 5 or 10 years. Tunku Abdul Rahman who is the outstanding political leader and a very good friend will, I hope, come back againas Prime Minister after his party has won the election, as it should do. But evenif he does not, Dato Razak, who is only 37, should keep the country on a soundcourse for some time to come. There is, of course, the danger that in the longterm Malaya might go the way of Ceylon. I do not myself rate this too highlyin the years immediately ahead. She is much more aware of China and has learnedmuch by experience, and the Emergency in particular has helped her to judge forherself where her true friends and interests lie. Her present co-operation with usin many fields is moreover exceptionally close and our influence very extensive.We can on many subjects talk to Malayan Ministers much more as we would tothose from the so-called old Commonwealth. If things develop in Malaya with justa little luck and if we approach our relationship with her in a sympathetic way,giving her within the limit of our resources at least some of the kind of help shemost needs in the way of experts, investment and defence, keeping our defence arrangements as unobtrusive as possible and not trying to push her too far or toofast in her foreign policies (pressure for her to join the South-East Asia treaty organisation would be disastrous), we should continue to have in Malaya a muchmore than usually reliable friend in this crucial part of Asia.H.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W.1,13th February, 1959.

</content>
</cab>
