<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 149-180</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COPY NO.cabinet anglo-EGYPTIAN FINANCIAL AGREEMENTNote by the Chancellor of the exchequer circulate for the consideration of the Cabinet a draft of thestatement I would propose to make in Parliament on the signing of theAnglo-Egyptian financial agreement.   The alternative at Case 3 inparagraph 8 assumes that a clarifying exchange of letters has been agreed;that at Case A assumes that it has not.G.(59):.3625th February,1959Annexed to the draft statement is a draft of Notes for Supplementaries.which has been prepared by officials; there may be some additions and amendments to these Notes.D.H.A.Treasury Chambers, S.W.I.25th February, 1959FINANCIAL AGREEMENT WITH EGYPT:. DRAFT STATEMENT TO parliament the Financial Agreement with Egypt which was initialled   on17th January was signed  todav7 in Cairo by representatives of the twoGovernments, and comes ^came7 into effect immediately.2.     The main provisions of the agreement are as followsi-First,the United Arab Republic (U.A.R.) Government will releaseto the owners, under an agreed procedure, the British properties which theyat present hold in sequestration.  J\\ is impossible to give the exact valueof this property since the only figures available are based on the assess-ments of the owners themselves.   Nevertheless7 the claimed value of theseproperties is well over  100 millions.Second, the U.A.R. Government are paying to Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment a lump sum of  27^ millions in compensation for British private property that has been Egyptianised, that is to say nationalised or compulsorilacquired.   This sum is also on account of that part of the property to bereturned which may have suffered injury or damage.    3^ millions of this sum is being paid at once, the balance is due in a year&apos;s time, and meanwhileHer Majesty&apos;s Government will hold in London British Government stocksdeposited by the Government of the UA.R. as collateral security to thevalue of  25 millions.-I-
Third, provision is made for the resumption of full payment and transfer by the U.A.R. of Egyptian Government pensions to United kingdom nationals, together with all arrears.   In addition the Government of theU.A.R. is paying to Her Majesty*s Government the sum of  100,000 sterlingas an interim payment in respect of compensation due to British officialsdismissed in 1951 - as Hon. Msmbers will be aware, a sum of this order has already been advanced by Her Majesty&apos;s Government to the officials concerned - and is reactivating the Commission dealing with the case ofthese officials to make a final assessment of the compensation due andpermit the payment of the balance thereof in sterling.Fourth, provision is made for owners not wishing to take upresidence in Egypt to have remitted to them in the United Kingdom, subjectto the normal requirements of the Egyptian Exchange Control Regulations,at least  E5.000 from any cash or bank balances which are released tothem following desequestration, or the proceeds of the sale of any of their property in Egypt.Fifth, the balances at present held by Egypt in this country inblocked accounts are being /TTave been/ released from Exchange Controlrestriction.Sixth, provision is made for the resumption of normal commercialrelationships, including aviation.3,      In addition the agreement reached provisionally on 22nd Decemberbetween the Egyptian authorities and the Anglo-Egyptian Oil Company andthe Shell Company of Egypt now comes into force.   This will enable theCompanies to resume business in Egypt on a basis acceptable to them.4.     The agreement that has been signed today ^was signed on.....J. is hot concerned with inter-Government claims the validity of which isnot admitted on either side.   The two Governments have, however, agreed in a simultaneous exchange of notes to a mutual waiver of such claims.5.     It is necessary for the proper implementation of the agreement thatwe should have a United Kingdom representative in Cairo with adequatestaff.   The Government of the U.A.B.. have agreed to receive sudi arepresentative who will be accorded diplomatic immunities and facilities.6.     The office of the United Kingdom representative in Cairo, working in conjunction with the British Properites in Egypt section of the ForeignOffice already established in London to register the property of UnitedKingdom nationals in Egypt, will be ready to help and advise the ownersover the resumption of possession of their property and in claiming duecompensation.     My Rt. Hon. and learned friend the Foreign Secretary issending today to each owner who has registered his property with thesection a letter explaining the procedure to be followed.   This letter willbe published in the Pxess.   Before making arrangements to return to egypt to resume possession of their property, owners are advised to consult this section of the Foreign Office in advance.7.     Distribution of the  27j millions will be entrusted to the ForeignC compensation Commission in accordance with the provisions of orders in Council the first of which is now being prepared.   My Rt. Kon. and-2-
learned friend the Foreign Secretary will&apos; be laying.this Order before theHouse as soon as possible.   The Commission was set up by the foreign compensation Act of 1950 to determine claims for compensation anddistribute payments received by Her Majesty&apos;s Government from foreign government.  The Chairman of the Commission is Mr. MontgomeryWhite, CT.C.8.     Case A (if no written assurances are obtained from the U.A.R.).After the initialling of the agreement scrutiny of the detailed lists provided in Cairo by the U.A.R. Government revealed the possibility of misunderstandings over the interpretation of the agreement.   In view of the furtherinformation which was provided by the Government of the U^A. JR.. to theUnited Kingdom delegation and to Mr. Black it was agreed that signature of the agreement could now take place.Case B (if the Egyptians agree to have an Exchange of Letters).After the initialling of the agreement scrutiny of the detailed lists provided in Cairo by the U,A,R, Government revealed the possibility of misunderstandings over the interpretation of the agreement.   In the light of the writtenassurance which was subsequently received from the Government of theU.A.R, it was agreed that signature of the agreement could now take place.9.     The full text of the agreement and the Exchange of Notes is being published as a White Paper /which is now available at the Vote Office7It is a comprehensive agreement on a wide range of financial matters that have been in dispute between the two countries, some of them for a longtime.   Taken as a whole the agreement provides a reasonable and practicalsettlem ent.10.    Finally, I should like to record my own thanks and the thanks ofHer MajestyTs Government to Mr. Eugene Black, President of the Inter-national Bank.   He agreed at the request of the two Governments to use his good offices on a personal and informal basis, and his efforts werethe key to the settlement /satisfactory outcome^ that has now been reached.
ANNEX&apos; te  FINANCIAL AGREEMENT WITH EGYPTstatement Tsr7i^um^^r&apos;im^(5T-3m^mmj^iE81.     General relations with Egypt.   This is a settlement offinancial questions in dispute between the two countries.    Itdoes not in itself alter Her Majesty&apos;s Government1s policiestowards Egypt in other respects though it will remove an obstacle to the possibility of better relationships.    IX isunderstood that Ministers wish to reserve the Bubstance ofthis paragraph for the proposed meeting with the LobbyCorrespondents./2.     Agreement roust be viewed as a whole.   The agreement isa comprehensive settlement to be judged as a whole.    both countries, have been losing from the past deadlock and &quot;bothwill stand to gain from the settlement.3.     Number of Properties.   Over h,000 owners of private propertyare due to benefit from the Agreement.    In most cases their property has been sequestrated and will be returned, but someland belonging to private individuals has been Egyptianised andthe owners will be able to claim compensation out of the lump sum.   About 400/500 businesses will be covered.   Most of this number represents small businesses, which have been sequestratedand are due to be returned.   Broadly speaking it is the largerbusinesses that have been Egyptianised.    The detailed figures,based on claimB registered with the Foreign Office, are asfollows -Sequestrated:Individuals (excluding claims by the suez contractors&apos; employees) U,101Business 297Egyptianised:Land (mainly belonging to individuals) 127Businesses (including 60 insurance companies and 10 scholastic institutions)    122k.     Valuation of Property to be Returned.   This willsubstantially exceed the value of the balances that we havereleased to Egypt (see paragraph 13).   It is impossible togive the exact value because the only figures available are based on the estimates of the owners themselves.   nevertheless the claimed value of these properties is well over  100 millions.7?he precise figures from the Foreign Office records is 13U millions but there are oblections to endorsing such anobviously unreliahle estimate./-1-
The properties fall into various categories, for example -(a) The Shell assets in Egypt, which are to he desequestra--ted in accordance with the Inter-governmentalAgreement and operated on the terms and conditions set out in the separate agreement between theCompany and the Egyptian Government.   This is thelargest single British industrial enterprise inEgypte(b) Other properties, including shares, bank balances andcertain forms of land, none of which would by their nature be susceptible to damage.(c) Other kinds of property which may have suffered damage to an extent which cannot at present be ascertained.Some, properties have been sold.5.     Value of Property Egvptianised.   The total value of claimsregistered with the Foreign Office in respect of property whichhas been &quot;Egyptianised&quot; amount to over  1+0 millions hutHer Majesty&apos;s Government cannot say at this stage whether allthese claims can be substantiated in detail.    Tn fact thetotal figure as registered is about  1+7 millions and this doesnot include certain land belonging to the Smouha family about which the position is still not entirely clear.   To quotetais inflated figure, however, as if it were authentic would place the Agreement in an unnecessarily bad light.J6.     Why was a lnnip sum of only  27g millions accepted?   Thiswas the best settlement that we could get with the united arab Republic after a long period of negotiation.    In deciding to accept it the Government had in mind -(a) This is only part of what the United Kingdomreceived under the agreement;   we gain in addition the return of the sequestrated properties, the resumption of trade, etc.(b) There is no reason to think that a better settlement could have been obtained by further negotiation.(c) On the contrary further delay v/ould mean lossof trade and deterioration of the properties.
The properties fall Into various categories, for example -(a) The Shell assets in Egypt, which are to he desequestra-ted in accordance with the Inter-governmentalAgreement and operated on the terms and conditions set out in the separate agreement &quot;between theCompany and the Egyptian Government.    This Is thelargest single British industrial enterprise inEgypt.(b) Other properties,  including shares, bank balances andcertain forms of land, none of which would by their nature be susceptible to damage,,(c) Other kinds of property which may have suffered damage to an extent which cannot at present be ascertained.Some properties have been sold.5*      Value of Property Egyptianised.    The  total value of claimsregistered with the Foreign OfTice in respect of property whichhas been &quot;Egyptianised&quot; amount to over  1+0 millions butHer Majesty&apos;s Government cannot say at this stage whether allthese claims can be substantiated in detail,    /in fact thetotal figure as registered is about  1+7 millions and this doesnot include certain land &quot;belonging to the Smouha family about which the position is still not entirely clear.    To quotethis inflated figure, however, as if it were authentic would place the Agreement in an unnecessarily bad lightPJ6o     Why was a lump sum of only  27s- millions accepted?   Thiswas the best settlement that we could get with the united arab Republic after a long period of negotiation.    Ir. deciding to accept it the Government had in mind -(a) This is only part of what the United Kingdomreceived under the agreement;    we gain in addition the return of the sequestrated properties, the resumption of trade, etc.(b) There is no reason to think that a better settlement could have been obtained by further negotiation.(e)    On the contrary further delay would mean lossof trade and deterioration of the properties,,
7.        How much in the   will the claimants get?    The extentof the claims to he met from the  27zmillions cannot he stated.The Foreign Compensation Commission will he unable to make an assessment until the sequestrated property has &quot;been returned tothe owners.    It will then he possible to assess -(a)    the value of the property that is not to he returned. (i.e.  which has &quot;been Egyptianised);(h)    the damage to the returned property.In considering the adequacy of the compensation in relation tothe size of the claims it should he home in mind that theowners will receive payment in sterling from Her Majesty&apos;sGovernmenc.    The alternative would have been to leave them to pursue their claims against the Egyptian Government who would. -no doubt after some expensive wrangling - have settled them inEgyptian pounds.8.        Is the Smouha estate to rank against the lump sum? Case A,(if the Egyptians do not agree to an Exchange of Letters aboutland).    The Smouha estate is, and has throughout been regardedas coming in the same category as any other land property:    tothe extent that it was sold between 30th October,  1956 and2nd August, 1958, under the provisions of Egyptian ProclamationNo.  5 of 1st November,  1956,  it will not be returned to theowners but will form the subject of a claim against the lump sum in accordance with Article IV(l)(a) of the Agreement.    2^0^for use in the House.    According to the owners&apos; valuation theSmouhas&apos;    land is worth about  12 millions.    Such informationas is available suggests that this may be a greatly exaggeratedvalue^J7Case B.     (if the Egyptians agree to an Exchange of Letters).As in Case A with the insertion of the following after&quot;Proclamation 5 of 1st November,  1956&quot; &quot;and dees not come within those categories of land which under the Exchange of letters are excluded from paragraph (c)  of Article III of theAgreement&quot;.9.        Will -pronerty owners be compelled to return to Egypt ifthey do not want to&quot;?    No.     (According to newspaper reportsabout 80 per cent of the claimants will not wish to return.)But in so far as this argument is meant to imply that we shouldhave done better to insist on the Egyptians retaining thesequestrated property and paying a bigger lump sum,  the answer is that we cannot insist on the Egyptians nationalisingadditional property simply because the owners do not want it back.10.      Will owners who do not wish to return be free to sell?Yes.    The agreement contains a provision under which they willbe entitled to transfer part at least of the proceeds of thesale into sterling.    It is expected that in a good proportionof cases the amount involved will not exceed  5,000,  and inthose circumstances the cwner will be able to apply for trans-fer of the whole of the purchase price.11.      Have the &quot;little men&quot; been sacrificed under a &quot;compre-hensive settlement&quot;,,  in the interests of the big companies?    Onthe contrary the United Kingdom negotiators have been particu-larly concerned to see that the interests of private claimantsand the proprietors of small businesses should be safeguardedas far as possible.
12.      What do the -property owners do next?    They will no doubtwish to study first the terms of the Agreement, and theyshould keep in touch with the Foreign Office.    It is undesira-ble, however,  that they should dash off to Egypt prematurelyto pursue their claims before the necessary administrative arrangements have been made.    The Foreign CompensationCommission will not have to wait until the balance of the lump sum has been paid over &quot;by Egypt in a year&apos;s time.    Ifasked whether the Commission will be authorised to make an interim distribution of compensation, Ministers could reply that the possibility of making such payments is not excluded,but it must be left to the Chairman of the Commission todetermine at what stage in the assessment of claims he can safely do this.13.      Publicity.    Lord Alexander has suggested in the Houseof Lords that there should be an explanatory White Paper (inaddition presumably to publication of the text of theAgreement).    The Lord President promised that this suggestion would be considered.    The plan that has now been worked out,however,  seems likely to be more effective.    There are two main objectives(a) to inform Parliament,  the Press and the general public of the essential features of theAgreement;(b) to help the British property owners with theirspecific problems.The first should be achieved by the proposed statement and publication of the text.    There would be very little ofgeneral interest to add in an explanatory White Paper.    Forthe purpose of (ft),  the Foreign Office are communicatingindividually with each claimant registered with them.    Therewould in any case be practical difficulties in. publishingsomething in the nature of a legal interpretation of theprovisions of the Agreement - partly because of the great variety of circumstances that would have to be covered, andpartly because Her Majesty&apos;s Government is not in a position(acting alone) to issue an authoritative interpretation;points of difficulty will have to be pursued with theEgyptian authorities.1q..      What about the ex-gratia loans made to former Britishresidents in Egypt?    It is proposed to leave the question ofthe repayment of these loans in abeyance for the time being./it will be easier to reach a decision when more is known about how the Agreement will really work out//   Under theex-gratia loans scheme about  q. millions has been paid out under the scheme introduced in July, 1957 for ex-gratialoans related to the amount of individuals&apos; property inEgypt.    A further  3 millions approximately is being paid-k-
out under the extension of the scheme to cover businessassets, which was announced in October,  1958-    In additionto the   &quot;ex gratia loans about  2 millions has been spent &quot;bythe Anglo-Egyptian Resettlement Board on relief and rehabilitation.15.      Collateral.    As collateral for the payment of 21). millions^ due in a year&apos;s time the Egyptians havedeposited /are depositing/7 securities to a current market value of  25 millions.1 6.   . Release of Egypt&apos;s sterling balances.    Under the termsof the Agreement we have released /are releasing7 to the egyptians cash and securities to a market value of about lid millions.    This is the total standing to the credit ofthe Nc.  1 and No.  2 Accounts after payment of the 3.5 millions cash and the  25 millions deposit.17.      Why Rive Egypt an interest-free loan of  21+ millions?(The Egyptian Press have suggested that this is what theprovision for postponement of payment amounts to,  and it maybe argued that other countries are more deserving).    This isa misleading approach.    The Egyptians hold most of theirfunds in the form of securities and have asked for time to market them.    We have conceded the point to the extentdefined in the Agreement as part of a comprehensivesettlements18.      War damage.    It is not correct to say that we have recognised Egypt&apos;s claim for war damage and allowed her tokeep the Canal base in settlement.    Neither side has felt able to recognise the inter-Governmental claims of theother;    but as a practical decision to avoid keeping these issues under fruitless dispute indefinitely a mutual waiverhas been agreed.
3-9.    Sequestration charges.      (The Egyptian Press has mentionedthis point)&quot;.      We have accepted the position that certaincharges are payable under Egyptian law hut we have gainedassurances limiting the total amount.      It may he asked whetherthe sequestration charges will he reclaimable out of the lump sum.     A final decision on the nature and extent of the claims which will rank for compensation can only he taken when all claims concerning injury or damage to property have beensubmitted to the Foreign Compensation Commission and assessed by theme      It will he open, therefore, to claimants to submitinformation to the Commission concerning any charges which havebeen levied on their property before it is returned to them.No hope should, however, he held out that such charges will be reimbursed- by the Commission, since it is clear that indistributing the sums available priority will have to he givento those whose property had been expropriated altogether or has been returned to them in a damaged condition.20.    &quot;Shell&quot; Agreement.      This is not an inter-Governmentagreement, hut a commercial agreement between the &quot;Governmentof the Republic of Egypt&quot; on the one hand and Anglo-EgyptianOilfields and the Shell Company of Egypt on the other, which now comes into force on the signature of the inter-Governmentagreement.      The details have not &quot;been published (they are primarily a matter for the companies concerned) hut it isgenerally known that the agreement provides for a settlementof past disputes and for a resumption of business by theCompanies in Egypt on acceptable terms.21*    Sjyinburn and Zarb.      The Secretary of State has approved the following formula.      &quot;This is a different question fromthe financial agreement.      (if pressed add:    It is hoped thatthe Agreement will produce an atmosphere in which that; mattercan he disposed of)&quot;.     Any further questions could hedeclined by Treasury Ministers.22.    Suez Flnanoe Company.      Her Majesty&apos;s Government is not(directly) a party to the agreement between the Company(formerly the Suez Canal Company) and Egypt, though theGovernment is, of course, substantially concerned as the major shareholder in the Company.      Any question about theinterpretation of that Agreement will therefore he a matterbetween the Company and the Egyptian authorities.      If thepoint is pressed it might he said that as a consequenceof the agreement between the United Kingdom and the united arab Republic the Company will be entitled to ask Egypt forthe payment of two instalments of compensation - otherwisedue January, I960 and January, 196l - immediately.     /It is undesirable to enlarge on this;    there are signs that the egyptians may he thinking of disputing such a claim and thelegal position is not clear, but we ought to say nothing tosuggest lack of confidence in Egyptian good faitho/7--6-
23.   Diplomatip, status.      The question of diplomatic relationshas in Itself nothing to do with the financial Agreement and questions should he addressed, to the Foreign Secretary.Foreign Office Ministers propose to take the line which hasbeen agreed with Dr. Fawzi, as follows:Our immediate requirements are met by the establishmentof a representative in Cairo with diplomatic immunities and facilities for the implementation of the Agreement.     Withregard to the opening of formal diplomatic relations, it isunderstood that these will be resumed as soon as possible.If asked what &quot;as soon as possible&quot; means they will say thatit means &quot;as soon as both sides have agreed that the time isripe&quot;.2^4-*    Will the  100,000 he made immediately available to the19.5.1.. off ioials?     As I &quot;have&quot; already&quot;said&quot;, &quot;these officialshave already received an advanoe from Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment against a payrnont of compensation by the united arab Republic Government such as is provided for in theAgreement.      The next step is with the Egyptian authorities who have agreed to reactivate the Commission dealing withthese officials with a view to a final settlement.      (The 100,000 when received, will be paid into the ExchequerExtra Receipts Account of the Home Office which made theoriginal advanoe).25.    Why did we not take business people&apos;s advice?     Thegeneral issues arising in these negotiations were discussed at a series of meetings between representatives of theDepartments concerned and the representatives of persons and organisations with interests in Egypt.      It would not havebeen practicable however to consult such persons and organisations at every stage in the negotiations.26.    Why could not an agreement have been reached sooner?It is alleged that British property has meanwhile beendeteriorating through delay and mismanagement.     The difficulty was not, however, over reaching an agreement but over reachingone on acceptable terms.27.    The experience of the French.     The reports of what theFrench were able to achieve in their agreement with theUnited Arab Republic were taken into account in our ownnegotiations.      There is no reason to think that we havemissed anything that they managed to get.      There are varyingaccounts of how the French agreement is being implemented.It would not be appropriate to discuss in detail (even if wehad full information) how the relationships between theFrench and the United Arab Republic authorities are now working out.    There  is nothing, however,  in the information available to justify Her Majesty&apos;s Government refusing on thatground to enter into an agreement with the Egyptians.
28.    Have the United Kingdom negotiators been hoodwinked?There is no reason to think that any subsiTantiaTly better termscould have been reached by any different method of negotiation.On the contrary the Egyptians were persuaded to increase theirpx^previous inadequate offers.     What critics have in mind hereapparently is the dispute which arose subsequent to theinitialling of the Agreement which was taken by the Press to mean that the United Kingdom was having second thoughts.      as explained above, however, we were not asking for an amendmentof the Agreement but for the co-operation of the Egyptiansin spelling out its practical application.      In the light of experience it might have been better to insist on the detaileddrafting of the exchanges of letters in advance of theinitialling of the Agreement.      On the other hand under thecircumstances of the time the negotiators might well havebeen regarded as blameworthy if they had lost the opportunityof getting the terms of the Agreement settled and initialledby the Egyptians.      In the absence of any reason to suspectthat the Egyptians were not ready to follow the recognisedprocedure of using the interval between initialling andsignature for the purposes of clarification, it would havebeen undesirable to lose the opportunity of Mr. Black&apos;spresence in Caj.ro for what would have looked, like formalpunctilio.     Z^31 any case, &quot;hoodwinked&quot; implies intentionto deceive;   we think these may have been genuine mi sunder stand-ings/.29.    Why not seize and distribute the Egyptian balancesinstead of having an Agreement?     Apart from the generalobjections, to seizing funds which we hold as bankers,  sucha step would inevitably have led to the seizure of all british property still sequestrated in Egypt.     The whole ofthe Egyptian balances would have been quite insufficient tomeet the resulting claims for compensation.      Moreover, theprospect of a resumption of trade with Egypt would have been set back indefinitely.30.    Technical and administrative matters.      The Treasury have -ordinated, the negotiations towards a comprehensive financial agreement, but the application of its provisions will restprimarily with the Foreign Office and questions on suchmatters should (after first studying the text of the Agreement)be addressed to the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs.-2-5-th-F-ebmary-r-1-9-59sscret
3$.    Why have we given the Base - worth  65 millions - away?The stores and equipment left in the Suez Base were valued at  60o6 millions (excluding  11+.5 millions for departmentalexpenses and movement costs),,     The in situ value of the fixed assets was assessed as  2.7 millions (salvage value 1.5 millions).      The United Kingdom claims in respect ofthe Base were placed on record by the United Kingdom delegation at the talks in Rome in May, 1957*      The Egyptian Delegationsaid, however, that Egypt had the right to seize british military equipment after being attacked, and it was agreedthat governmental claims should be left for discussion at alater stage.Governmental claims were excluded from the discussions in rome in October, 1957*      In deciding that we should seek a lump sum settlement with the United Arab Republic, the cabinet agreed in July, 1958 that the settlement should include ade facto waiver of governmental claims, including theUnited Kingdom claims in respect of the Suez Base.31*    Did we make a claim on Egypt when we evacuated the suez Canal Base?No claim was made was made against Egypt in connectionwith the Suez Canal Base Agreement of 19th October, 1954(Command 9586).When we evacuated the Suez Canal Zone following the signature of this agreement a Base was established with themaintenance responsibility shared between Egypt and theUnited Kingdom.      The question of disposal of facilitiesmaintained by the United Kingdom under the agreement was subject to discussion with the Egyptians.      Certain assetsoutside the Base were handed over to the Egyptians free of charge (Appendix B to Annex II of the Agreement).      the stores which the United Kingdom was allowed to retain inthe Base were set out in an appendix to the Agreement.      under an exchange of letters dated 19th October, 1954 allfinancial claims between the two Governments outstanding atthe date of the Agreement were waived.-9-
H.M. TREASURYAgreementbetween the Government of theUnited Arab Republic and the Government, of theUnited Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Irelandconcerning Financial and commercial relations and British Property in EgyptPresented to Parliament by the Chancellor of the exchequer by Command of Her majesty january 1959LONDONHER MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY office net cmnd.
jAGRllLxtiENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE united arab REPUBLIC AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITEDKINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELANDCONCERNING FINANCIAL AND COMMERCIAL relations and BRITISH PROPERTY IN EGYPTThe Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and NorthernIreland (hereinafter referred to as the United Kingdom Government) and theGovernment of the United Arab Republic (as successors of the Governmentof the Republic of Egypt, and acting so far only as concerns the territory of the Republic of Egypt),Desiring to re-establish normal relations,Have agreed as follows:  Article I(1) For the purposes of the present Agreement the terms &quot; property,&quot;&quot; British property,&quot; &quot; United Kingdom nationals &quot; and &quot; owners &quot; shall havethe meaning ascribed to them in Annex A to the present Agreement.(2) All Annexes to the present Agreement shall be an integral part thereof.Article IIThe United Kingdom Government shall on the date of the signature of the present Agreement:  (a) remove all Exchange Control restrictions imposed since July 26, 1956.on the No. 1 Account of the National Bank of Egypt and on the accounts in the United Kingdom of Egyptian banks and companiesincorporated under the laws in force in Egypt and on the accounts of Egyptian residents; and(b) remove the restrictions imposed on March 15, 1957, on transactionsaffecting securities owned by residents of the Egyptian MonetaryArea.Article iii the Government of the United Arab Republic shall:  (a) on the date of the signature of the present Agreement terminate theapplication of all measures of sequestration taken by the Governmentof the United Arab Republic against British property betweenOctober 30, 1956, and the date of the signature of the present agreement, and all restrictive measures taken against United kingdom nationals during the same period in accordance with the provisions ofProclamation No. 5 of November 1, 1956;(b) return all British property (or the proceeds of any such property soldbetween October 30, 1956, and the date of the signature of the present agreement) to the owners thereof in accordance with the provisions of annex B to the present Agreement and after payment only of thecharges referred to in the said Annex B;(c) be entitled to exclude from the provisions of paragraph (b) of thisArticle property sold between October 30, 1956, and August 2, 1958,54614
Article IV(1) The Government of the United Arab Republic shall pay to the UnitedKingdom Government the sum of  27,500,000 sterling in full and final settlement of the following:  (a) all claims in respect of the property referred to in paragraph (c) ofArticle III of the present Agreement;(b) all claims in respect of injury or damage to property suffered prior tothe date of the signature of the present Agreement as a result of themeasures referred to in paragraph (a) of Article III of the present agreement.C1) &quot;Treaty Series No. 3 (1938),&quot; Cmd. 5639.(z) &quot; Treaty Series No. 67 (1955),&quot; Cmd. 9586, page 68.under the provisions of Proclamation No. 5 of November 1,         and.......referred to in Annex E to the present Agreement; \ )) .Xd) take the measures in respect of industrial property referred to in annex C to the present Agreement;(e) resume full payment and transfer of Egyptian Government pensions to united Kingdom nationals together with all arrears, in accordancewith the Egyptian Laws Nos. 28 of 1923 and 58 of 1940, and theExchange of Notes between the United Kingdom Government andthe Egyptian Government of August 12, August 31 and September 9,1936(0;(/) pay to the United Kingdom Government the sum of  100,000 sterlingas an interim payment in respect of compensation due to british officials dismissed in 1951, in respect of which an Exchange of Notesbetween the Government of the Republic of Egypt and the UnitedKingdom Government dated October 19, 1954,(2) provided for theestablishment of a Commission, and cause the aforementioned Corn-mission to make a final assessment of the compensation due, andpermit the payment of the balance thereof, in sterling;(g) authorise the release to the beneficial owners who are United kingdom nationals or institutions of securities and funds (other than those .formerly owned by United Kingdom nationals in the corporations and associations listed in Annex E to the present Agreement) held by united Kingdom and other banks outside Egypt to the order of banksin Egypt;(h) ensure that the running of periods within which rights may be exer-cised in the Courts or tribunals of the United Arab Republic, whichhave not expired on the date, of the termination of the application ofthe measures referred to in paragraph (a) of this Article shall be suspended for a period of three months after the date of the signature of the present Agreement in favour of the owners of British property;(f) permit United Kingdom nationals to request a re-examination of anytax matter which has become final because legal rights have not been exercised by the Sequestrator. In each case a request for suchre-examination shall be made in writing to the Director-General ofthe Taxation Department within a period of two months following the date of reconsignment referred to in paragraph (4) (i) of Annex Bto the present Agreement. Re-examination shall be carried out bya Committee presided over by a member of the Egyptian conseil &apos;Etat, which will consider each application and submit its opinion to the competent Minister. The decision of the Minister shall be final and without right of appeal.
(3^:   he Government of the United Arab Republic shall:-(a) pay the sum of  27,500,000 sterling referred to in paragraph (1) ofthis Article as follows:  (i) the sum of  3,500,000 sterling on the date of the signature ofthe present Agreement;(ii) the sum of  24,000,000 sterling on , 1960,(b) on the date of the signature of the present Agreement deposit, in thename of the United Kingdom Government, United KingdomGovernment securities of a market value of not less than  25,000,000sterling (computed at the middle closing prices ruling on the LondonStock Exchange on the previous day).(3) The securities referred to in paragraph (2) (b) of this Article and the proceeds referred to in sub-paragraph (c) of this paragraph shall remain theproperty of the National Bank of Egypt who shall be entitled to:  (a) receive the income therefrom;(b) exchange any of these securities for securities of equal market value(computed at the middle closing prices ruling on the London stock exchange on the previous day); and(c) give instructions for the sale of any of these securities provided thatthe proceeds, less all costs and expenses of sale, are either:  (i) used in order to extinguish in whole or in part any outstandingliability on the part of the Government of the United Arab Republicarising out of the provisions of this Article, or(ii) deposited in the name of the United Kingdom Government.(4) In order to extinguish in whole or in part any outstanding liability onthe part of the Government of the United Arab Republic arising out of theprovisions of this Article, the United Kingdom Government may, on or after, 1960, sell any or all of the securities referred to inparagraphs (2) (b) and (3) (b) of this Article, which remain deposited in thename of the United Kingdom Government, and may appropriate the proceeds,less all costs and expenses of sale, and any sums deposited in accordance withthe provisions of paragraph (3) (c) of this Article. The United KingdomGovernment shall pay the balance of the said proceeds, after extinction of thesaid liability, to the Government of the United Arab Republic. Upon theextinction of the said liability the United Kingdom Government shall returnto the Government of the United Arab Republic any of the securities andproceeds referred to in paragraphs (2) (b), (3) (b) and (3) (c) of this article which remain deposited in the name of the United Kingdom Government.(5) The United Kingdom Government hereby declare on their own behalf,and on behalf of United Kingdom nationals, that payment by theGovernment of the United Arab Republic of the sum of  27,500,000 sterlingreferred to in paragraph (1) of this Article fully and finally discharges theGovernment of the United Arab Republic and nationals of the United arab republic from all liability to the United Kingdom Government and UnitedKingdom nationals in respect of the claims referred to in paragraph (1) ofthis Article.Article V(1) If the owners of British property at any time subject to the measures referred to in paragraph (a) of Article III of the present Agreement have at no time been residents in the United Arab Republic, or decide not to resume residence in the United Arab Republic, or to terminate their54614c* 2
residence in the United Arab Republic, the Government of th^ j ;iitedArab Republic shall, subject to the normal requirements of the EAchangeControl regulations of the United Arab Republic set out in Annex F to thepresent Agreement:(a) give immediate approval to applications for the transfer into sterlingby each such owner of cash and bank balances held by him in theUnited Arab Republic which have at any time been subject to themeasures referred to in paragraph (a) of Article III of the present agreement, and sums realised by the sale of property subsequent tothe signature of the present Agreement which has at any time been subject to the aforesaid measures, up to the equivalent of  E.5,000;(b) give favourable consideration to applications for further transfers intosterling in excess of the transfers provided for in sub-paragraph (a)of this paragraph of the cash, bank balances and sums referred to in sub-paragraph (a) of this paragraph;(c) permit such owners to export to the United Kingdom their jewelleryand other personal and household effects which have at any time been subject to the measures referred to in paragraph (a) of Article III ofthe present Agreement.(2) For the purposes of this Article:(a) the Exchange Control regulations at any time in force in the united arab Republic concerning rates of exchange shall be applied in sucha way that United Kingdom nationals shall be accorded treatment notless favourable than that accorded to nationals of any other countryhaving a convertible or transferable currency; and(b) in the case of applications which were made on behalf of UnitedKingdom nationals and approved prior to July 27, 1956, for the transferof sums into sterling, the rate of exchange for the Egyptian pound interms of the pound sterling shall in each case be calculated by using the respective parity values for the Egyptian pound and the poundsterling declared to the International Monetary Fund on July 27, 1956.Article vi the two Governments shall take steps, including those referred to in annex D to the present Agreement, to permit the resumption of normal commercial relations.Article VII(1) The two Governments shall permit such freedom of entry and exit, andaccord such other facilities, as may be necessary for the implementation ofthe present Agreement; and the Government of the United Arab Republicshall give favourable consideration to the issue of residence permits to UnitedKingdom nationals who left Egypt between October 30, 1956, and the dateof the signature of the present Agreement, even if they have signedundertakings not to return to the United Arab Republic.(2) The Government of the United Arab Republic shall afford to theUnited Kingdom Government facilities for obtaining information about theclaims referred to in Article IV of the present Agreement, and in particularshall supply to the United Kingdom Government and United Kingdom
natic^LnS all the available particulars which are held by the appropriateEgyptian authorities concerning the said claims, including documents relatingto sale or transfer to Egyptian ownership.Article viii the Sterling Releases Agreement between the United KingdomGovernment and the Egyptian Government of July 1, 1951,(?) as modified by the Exchanges of Notes between the said two Governments ofOctober 30, 1952,(4) and August 30, 1955,(5) shall terminate on the finalrelease from the No. 2 Account of the National Bank of Egypt.Article IX The present Agreement shall enter into force on the date of the signaturethereof.In witness whereof the undersigned, being duly authorised thereto by theirrespective Governments, have signed the present Agreement and have affixedthereto their seals.Done in duplicate at............................this......... day of........., 1959.For the Government of the United    For the Government of the UnitedKingdom  of Great Britain and      Arab Republic:Northern Ireland:ANNEX A(1) &quot; Property &quot; shall mean all movable or immovable property whethertangible or intangible, and includes rights to receive payment (whethercontractual or not), other contractual rights, copyright, patents, trade marksand other forms of industrial property, as well as rights or interests of any kind in property.(2) &quot; British property&quot; shall mean the property in Egypt of UnitedKingdom nationals. British property shall be deemed to include shares, ofwhich United Kingdom nationals are the owners, in corporations orassociations incorporated or constituted under the laws in force in the united arab Republic even though the documentary evidence of title to those sharesis held outside the United Arab Republic.(3) &quot; United Kingdom nationals &quot; are:(i) physical persons who at the date of the signature of the present agreement are citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonies, citizens of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Southern Rhodesian citizens, Britishsubjects without citizenship, or British protected persons belonging toany of the territories for whose international relations the UnitedKingdom Government are responsible; and(3) &quot;Treaty Series No. 67 (1951),&quot; Cmd. 8336.(4) &quot;Treaty Series No. 23 (1953),&quot; Cmd. 8811.(5) &quot;Treaty Series No. 74 (1955),&quot; Cmd. 9611.
-    16..... I FiW(ii) corporations and associations incorporated or constituted uiui^cr the laws in force in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and NorthernIreland or in any territory for whose international relations the UnitedKingdom Government are, at the date of the signature of the present agreement, responsible;provided that the persons, corporations and associations concerned were equally United Kingdom nationals on October 31, 1956.(4) &quot; Owners &quot; shall mean United Kingdom nationals who, on any datebetween October 30, 1956, and the date of the signature of the present agreement, were entitled to the property, rights or interests in question, to theextent to which they were so entitled, and shall include any successors of theowners provided such successors are United Kingdom nationals as defined in paragraph (3) of this Annex.ANNEX B(1) The two Governments shall, upon the date of the signature of thepresent Agreement, issue public statements advising owners of british property remaining under the control of the Government of the United arab republic to take over, or duly to authorise agents to take over, their property.(2) Subject to the provisions of paragraph (6) of this Annex, theGovernment of the United Arab Republic shall administer and protect such property until it is returned to the owners at the owners&apos; request.(3) Each owner or his duly authorised agent shall submit to theSequestrator-General an application for taking over the property, togetherwith evidence of identity or authority.(4) (i) The Sequestrator-General shall ensure that within three monthsafter the date of the receipt of each application under paragraph (3) of this annex the property concerned be released and handed over by theSequestrator-General, or other agent of the Government of the United arab republic having possession of such property, to the owner or his duly authorised agent, according to an inventory of the property to be restoredand an instrument of reconsignment drawn up and signed by both parties.(ii) The Sequestrator-General or aforementioned other agent of theGovernment of the United Arab Republic shall, on handing over the property to the owner or his duly authorised agent, provide copies of all records keptby the Sequestrator-General or other agent of the Government of the united arab Republic in respect of the property during the period of sequestrationand copies of the inventory and instrument of reconsignment referred to inparagraph (4) (i) of this Annex. The Sequestrator-General&apos;s jurisdiction inrespect of each item of property shall terminate with the handing over of itto the owner or his agent.(5) If any complaint or claim which may arise concerning the way inwhich effect is given to the provisions of paragraphs (2) or (4) of this Annexshall be made to the Sequestrator-General, he shall give his opinion on thematter in writing.(6) The Government of the United Arab Republic may sell any propertythat has not been applied for after one year from the date of the signature of the present Agreement and shall pay the proceeds into an account in thename of the United Kingdom Government.
(7) Before the property is returned to the owner the Sequestrator-general shall be entitled to levy sequestration charges, provided that the total of allcharges levied or to be levied upon all British property as a result of themeasures referred to in paragraph (a) of Article III of the present Agreementor as a result of the administration or protection referred to in paragraph (2)of this Annex shall not exceed  2,250,000. In addition the Sequestrator-General shall, in accordance with the laws of the United Arab Republic, beentitled to recover from any owners appearing on the list set out in Annex to the present Agreement the payments made on their behalf and specifiedin the said Annex.ANNEX C(1) The Government of the United Arab Republic shall take all necessary steps to ensure that owners to whom the industrial property rights are restoredby reason of the provisions of paragraph (b) of Article III of the present agreement shall enjoy these rights in full, including rights of recourse tothe Courts in the same way as if the measures referred to in paragraph (djof Article III of the present Agreement had not been taken.(2) Periods of priority provided for by Article IV of the international convention for the Protection of Industrial Property of 1883 (as revised inLondon in 1934)(6) which had not expired on October 30, 1956, and thosewhich commenced to run after that date but before the date of the signature of the present Agreement, shall be extended in favour of the owners ofindustrial property rights for a period of six months following the date ofthe signature of the present Agreement.(3) A period of six months, to run from the date of the signature of thepresent Agreement, shall be allowed by the Government of the United arab republic with no penalty of any kind to the owners of industrial propertyrights including those provided for or recognised by the Convention referredto in paragraph 2 of this Annex, to perform all acts, comply with allformalities, pay all taxes or charges and generally discharge all requirementsof the laws and regulations of the United Arab Republic in order to maintain and defend industrial property rights already acquired on October 30, 1956,or to obtain those which could have been acquired as a result of an applicationfiled before that date if the measures referred to in paragraph (a) of Article iii of the present Agreement had not been taken.(4) The renewal of registration of trade marks in respect of which theperiod of protection lapsed between October 30, 1956, and the date of the signature of the present Agreement, shall have effect retrospectively fromthe date of expiry of the period, provided that the renewal is effected beforethe expiry of a period of not more than six months after the date of the signature of the present Agreement.ANNEX D(1) The Provisional Commercial Agreement between the United arab republic and the United Kingdom Government contained in the Exchange of notes of June 5-7, 1930,(7) as modified and renewed by the Exchange of(6) &quot;Treaty Series No. 55 (1938),&quot; Cmd. 5833.(7) &quot;Treaty Series No. 31 (1930),&quot; Cmd. 3662.
Notes of October 19, 1952(8) shall be deemed to be in force as from dateof the signature of the present Agreement.(2) In accordance with the provisions of Article VI, and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of Article III, of the present Agreement: - -(i) the Government of the United Arab Republic shall not institute ormaintain any measure which results in persons who effect transactionspayment in respect of which is made in sterling receiving less favourable terms than they would receive if payment were made inany other convertible or transferable currency;(ii) shipping agencies which are owned or controlled by United kingdom nationals shall receive treatment no less favourable than that accorded to the shipping agencies of any other foreign country;(iii) in all that relates to civil aviation, including the exercise of trafficrights, the Government of the United Arab Republic shall accord to united Kingdom nationals, and to aircraft registered in the UnitedKingdom or in any territory for whose international relations theUnited Kingdom Government are at the date of the signature of thepresent Agreement responsible, the same treatment which was beinggranted to them, in accordance with the Air Agreement initialled bythe representatives of the two Governments on April 1, 1950, and alsoaccord treatment in accordance with any temporary Permit issued bythe aeronautical authority of the Egyptian Government before october 29, 1956.(3) The United Kingdom Government shall, in all that relates to civilaviation, including the exercise of traffic rights, accord to nationals of theUnited Arab Republic and to aircraft registered in any territory for whoseinternational relations the Government of the United Arab Republic are atthe date of the signature of the present Agreement responsible, the same treatment which was being granted to them, in accordance with the AirAgreement initialled by the representatives of the two Governments on April 1,1950, and also accord treatment in accordance with any temporary Permitissued by the aeronautical authority of the United Kingdom before october 29, 1956.ANNEX E(1) The properties in the United Arab Republic of any United kingdom nationals, and the shares of any United Kingdom nationals in any corporationsor associations incorporated or constituted in the United Arab Republic,appearing on the folowing list:  Barclays Bank D.C.O., 6, Sh. Sherif, Alexandria.Ottoman Bank, Sh. Mohamed Bey Farid, Cairo.Ionian Bank Ltd., 106, Sh. Mohamed Farid, Cairo.The Prudential Assurance Co. Ltd., 14, Sh. Soliman Pacha, Cairo.Pearl Assurance Company Ltd., 17, Sh. El Horreya, Alexandria.Schools and Colleges in the United Arab Republic.Minia Ginning Co., Ltd., Minia.Peel &amp; Co. Ltd., 32, Sh. Sherif, Alexandria.(8) &quot; Treaty Series No. 67 (1952),&quot; Cmd. 8712.10
Ufiion Club (furniture, building  and land), Midan  Saad Zaghloul,Alexandria.Lloyds Insurance Brokers and other Insurance Branches, Offices andAgencies.Marconi Radio Telegraph Co. of Egypt, 9, Sh. El Sherifin, Cairo.The Eastern Telegraph Co. Ltd., 9, Sh. El Sherifin, Cairo.British Institute, Alexandria (furniture and Library), 2, Sh. Tosson,Alexandria.British Council, Cairo (furniture and Library), 22, Sh. Adly Pacha, Cairo.Societe Pharmacoutique Egyptienne, Setton Brothers &amp; Co., 164, MidanEl Tahrir, Cairo.W. A. Lancaster &amp; Son, Pharmaceutical Branch, 11, Sh. Mohamed Farid,Cairo.C. Sender &amp; Co. Ltd., 15a, Sh. Sherif Pacha, Cairo.Ecadil (Egyptian Chemical &amp; Drug Industries Ltd.), 38, Sh. Shaaban,Choubrah, Cairo.The Egyptian Phosphate Co. Ltd., Safaga.Egyptian Oxygen &amp; Acetylene Co. Ltd., Teret El Ismailia, Mostored.Lipton Ltd., 1, Sh. El Boustan, Cairo.Brooke Bond Co. Ltd., 93 Sh. Kasr El Eini, Cairo.British Broadcasting Corporation (B.B.C.) Sh. Ahmed Pacha, Garden City.Near East Broadcasting, 37, Sh. Maspero, Cairo.Imperial Chemical Industries (Egypt), 26, Sh. Sherif Pacha, Cairo.Sinai Mining (subject to a special arrangement).National Insurance Co. of Egypt, 41, Sh. Kasr El Nil, Cairo.Eastern Company (S.A.E.) Guizah, Sh. El Ahram, Guizah.Helwan Portland Cement Co. (S.A.E.) Sh. Elhami, Kasr El Doubarah.The Smelting Company (Egypt) S.A.E., 155, Sh. Mohamed Farid.Associated Mines (S.A.E.), 155, Sh. Mohamed Farid, Cairo.Societe Egyptienne des Industries Textiles S.A.E. Karmous, Alexandria.The Tractor &amp; Engineering Co. S.A.E. (subject to a special arrangement)18, Sh. Mohamed Farid, Cairo.The Egyptian Engineering Stores, 33, Sh. Emad El Din, Cairo.Elakyas Ltd., Sh. Elhamid, Kasr El Doubarah.The Albert Moussa Agency and Stevedoring Co. S.A.E., 6, Sh. El Baharya,Alexandria.Grieve &amp; Irwin Ltd., 16, Sh. Abdel Khalek Pacha Sarwat, Cairo.Etam B. Landa &amp; Co.. 4, Sh. 26 July. Cairo.Beida Dyers, 17, Sh. Kasr El Nil, Cairo.The Alexandria Manufacturing Co. Ltd., Sh. Mohandes Mahmoud Fahmy,Alexandria.The Welcome Foundation Co., 26, Sh. Sherif, Cairo.Albert Vassallo, 5 Midan Orabi, Alexandria.Eastern Radio Co., 2, Sh. El Kadi El Fadel, Cairo.Egyptian Aviation &amp; Travel Services, 20, Sh. Soliman Pacha, Cairo.G. Beyts &amp; Company, Sh. Sultan Hussein, Port Said.The Commercial &amp; Agency Co. of Egypt Ltd., 7, Sh. Mohandes MahmoudFahmy, Alexandria.The National Bank of Egypt.The Egyptian Copper Works (S.A.E.).Misr Insurance Company (S.A.E.).The Nile Insurance Company.Alexandria Commercial Co. (S.A.E.).Al Shark (S.A.E.) (Insurance Company).Credit Foncier Egyptien.Garbouchian &amp; Sasson.
Yh 1(2) The lands in the United Arab Republic of any United kingdom nationals appearing on the following list:  Kafr El Dawar Region1. Arman Victor Nahman.2. Raymond Elie Nessim Ades.3. Temouni Raymond Elie Nessim Ades.4. Max Rolo Jack Rublin.5. Paul Jack Victor Rolo Jack.6. Jacqueline Rolo Max.7. Sasson Isabel and Coy.Abu El Mat amir Region9.1011121314.151617181920,Adolph Yacoub.Oland and Zammit.Salomon Sawares.Irama Zammit daughter of Oland.Jean Sanid.Rene Sammit Oland.Richard and Finan Garcian.Fotine Hector.Michel George Ben Gand.Leopold James Ben Charles.Antoun Bayboun Ben Jean.Mary Joseph Emanuel.Ellet Elma Avar wife of Armando.Ellet Anaketripilides.Edward Ben George Keram.Eliofen Bosco.Slin Gabriel Tewfik Karam.Gabriel Tewfik Karam.George Gabriel Karam.Resior Peracos.Etia El Baroud Region1.   Robel String John.Dessouk Region1. Yanni Christopaki.2.   Emil Ades.Kafr El Cheikh Region1. Jack Chalom Tobi.2. Georgette Tobi.3. Nelli Fares Nemr.4. Emil Fares Nemr.5. Jacqueline Astrok.6. Geora Fiorah Harouf.Seberbai Region1. Mahmoud Mohamed El Meshad.2.   Aram and Max Rollo.Dekernes Region1.   Paulette Khalil Saab.2.   Fortune Aribol.
VShei\,in Region1.   Paulette Khalil Aziz.2.   Carver Brothers.Mansurah Region1.   Robert Macledin.2.   Carver Brothers and Company.Fakous Region1.	Nelli Fares Nemr.2.	Caroline Smith.3.&apos;	Lewis Simon Sednaoui.4.	Commandant of British Forces.5.	Harold Bouhagiar son of Joseph.6.	British Marine and Air Force Association.7.	William Narengo.8.	Leno Levi.9.	Mathon Oil Co.10.	English Oil Co.11.	English Oilfields Co.12.	Evan Throp.13.	Josephine daughter of Kwar.14.	Francis Bergeba.15.	Caramelle Gouti Kerdana.16.	Lewis Kamelleri Bargoun.17.	Cook &amp; Son.Zagazig Region1.   Felix Antoun Youssef Micallef.Damanhour Region1.   Ellet Kharikelia widow of Redokaneki daughter of BandeletSalvago.El Manshiet Region1.   Antoun Carlena.1.  William Narengy.3.   Hena Road.4.   Johny Quilina.Oualiubia Region1.   Emanuel Eil.2.   Osman Khalil.3.   Estate of Nessim AdesGizeh Region1.   Captain Demitri Claidon and Mrs. Doren Claidon and GeraldCharles.2.   Captain Melawla.3.   Moussa Green.4.   Jack and Elie Green.5.   Samuel Sornaga.6.   Yanni Makokano.Fayoum West Region1.   Alfred Karmy.
Fayoum East Region1.   Alfred Karmy.2.   Rene Levy.Beni Souef Region1. Alfred Karmy and Mohamed Khamis.2. Analor Melek widow of High Serg.3. F. B. Menzaki &amp; Co.4. Ernest Ebrabel State.5. Reginald Sidney Ernest Baramel.6. State of Ernest Ebrabel Ermel.Malawi Region1.   Edwin Nessim Youssef Gohar.Assiut Region1. Antoun Roglatsh.2. Imperial Chemical Industries Co.3. Peel &amp; Co.Alexandria Region1. Ades State (Elie, Emilie, Gaston. Clement, Eliah, Jean RaymondElie, Rosemary Nessim Ades and Nessim Habib).2. Smouha &amp; Sons.3. R. Rollo Melio &amp; Co.4. Mart Edward Richlar.5. Panayoti George Benas.6. Antoinette Terderis.7. Mart Edward.8. Nicola Terdwesi.9. Welford Edgar.10. Josin Terdesi.11. George Bebas.12. John Michel William.13. August Frein.14. Hold Gold.15. Gustaf Nehman.16, Elst Weliver Tef Micalleh.17. John Cassar Selvator.18. Geffrey Bell.19. Olive Cecil Khorne.20. Adolph Cherine.21. Hercrat Lemotodi.22. Joseph Bagada.23. Philip James.24. G. James.25. Paul M. Breen.26. Fati Cafalos.27. William Mestali Alexander.28. Ewa widow of Ongor.29. Frederic Assor.30. Abramino Sasson.31. Ernest Bless Paul.32. Ganitel Israel.
Elfa never Nenando.Oswald Finney.35.   State of Oswald Feny.36.   Mariut Lands Co.37.   Godini Balenberda Sermoise.38.   Mariopolis Land Co.ANNEX FApplications for non-resident status or transfer of capital submitted bybanks on behalf of their clients to the Central Exchange Control should,normally, be supported by the following documents:  (1) A Certificate from the Ministry of the Interior, stating that theapplicant will be permanently non-resident in the United arab republic;(2) A Clearance Certificate from the Taxation Department, to the effectthat no taxes are due by the applicant;(3) A Statement of Account from the applicant^ bank or banks, denotingthe nature and origin of any credit items exceeding  E.100 which havebeen entered into his account during the year preceding the date ofhis departure from the United Arab Republic.Where the amount applied for represents the sale proceeds of assetsbelonging to the applicant, documents should be submitted to the CentralExchange Control proving his ownership thereof before the sale was effected.Where the amounts applied for represent indemnities to an employee, acertificate from the employer or from a Certified Accountant should besubmitted to the Central Exchange Control in support thereof.ANNEX G	LE.	Mms.British Overseas Airways Corporation    ..:	186,494	439Alexandria Tramways      ............	15,000	000Arab News Agency............	6,000	000Anglo-American Hospital ...      .........	9,466	230Bohagiar State        ...............	2,000	000The People&apos;s Dispensary for Sick Animals	1,806	000Santex Factory       ...............	758	650Maurice Carasso    ...............	500	000Khofo General Ceramic Factory ...      ......	314	280The Pipe Drainage Company of Egypt......	300	000Alexandria Rubber Factory         .........	41	550Shebin El Kanatar Hospital        ...      ...      ...	2,660	000
UNITED KINGDOM NOTE 0 )Cairo, , 1959.Mr. Minister,I have the honour to refer to the Agreement signed this day betweenthe Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and NorthernIreland and the Government of the United Arab Republic concerningfinancial and commercial relations and British property in Egypt, and to thenegotiations leading thereto. In the course of these negotiations there arosecertain claims put forward on the one hand by the Government of the UnitedKingdom and on the other by the Government of the United Arab Republic,for which no provision is made in the Agreement.(2) For their part the United Kingdom Government put forward claims,arising out of the events of October-November 1956, including claims inrespect of United Kingdom Government property situated in the Suez CanalBase (as defined in paragraph (1) of Part A of Annex II to the Suez CanalBase Agreement of October 19, 1954,(9) and in respect of the costs incurred by the Government of the United Kingdom for clearance of the Suez Canal,being costs for which the United Nations Organisation did not assume responsibility. The Government of the United Arab Republic do not admitliability in respect of any of these claims.(3) For their part the Government of the United Arab Republic putforward claims arising out of the events of October-November 1956, includingdamage to Government and private property, and damage to public utilitiesincluding loss of revenue, damage to the Suez Canal including loss of revenue to the Suez Canal Authority and other damage to the Egyptian economy.The United Kingdom Government do not admit liability in respect of any ofthese claims.(4) In consideration of the foregoing and without prejudice to any ofthe provisions of the Agreement referred to in paragraph (1) of this Note,I have the honour to propose that the two Governments shall waive all theclaims and categories of claims described in paragraphs (2) and (3) of this note.(5) If the foregoing proposal is acceptable to the Government of theUnited Arab Republic, I have to suggest that the present Note, together with your reply in that sense should be regarded as constituting an Agreementbetween the two Governments in this matter.I avail myself of this opportunity to express to you, Mr. Minister, the assurance of my highest consideration.(9) &quot;Treaty Series No. 67 (1955),&quot; Cmd. 9586.
Cairo, , 1959.Sir.I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your Note of today&apos;s date which reads as follows:  [Text of United Kingdom Note](2) In reply I have the honour to inform you that the foregoing proposals is acceptable to the Government of the United Arab Republic and that yourNote and the present reply shall be regarded as constituting an Agreementbetween the two Governments.I avail myself of this opportunity to express to you. Sir, the assurance of my highest consideration.UNITED KINGDOM NOTECairo, , 1959.Mr. Minister,I have the honour to refer to the Agreement signed this day between theGovernment of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Irelandand the Government of the United Arab Republic concerning financial and commercial relations and British property in Egypt. I have the honour to propose that no action shall be taken against any United Kingdom national inrespect of any infringement of the provisions of Proclamation No. 5 ofNovember 1, 1956.If the foregoing is acceptable to you, I have the honour to propose thatthe present Note and your reply to that effect shall constitute an Agreementbetween the two Governments which shall enter into force immediately.I avail myself of this opportunity to express to you, Mr. Minister, the assurance of my highest consideration.UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC NOTECairo, , 1959.Sir.I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your Note of today&apos;s date which reads as follows:  [Text of United Kingdom- Note]In reply I have the honour to inform you that the proposal containedin your Note is acceptable to the Government of the United Arab republic and that they will regard that Note and the present reply as constituting anAgreement between the two Governments in this matter.I avail myself of this opportunity to express to you, Sir, the assurance of my highest consideration.
Cairo, , 7959.Sir,I have the honour to inform you that it is the expectation of theGovernment of the United Arab Republic that all the documents of titlerelating to the property set out in Annex (E) to the Agreement signed to-dayon behalf of our two Governments will be handed over to the Government ofthe United Arab Republic; and that in any case the Government of the UnitedKingdom undertakes to hand over the securities and/or any other evidenceof title or of payment received upon the payment of compensation to the claimants.I have the honour to be,Sir,Your obedient Servant,UNITED KINGDOM NOTECairo, , 1959.Mr. Minister,I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of to-day&apos;s date: -&quot; I have the honour to inform you that it is the expectation of theGovernment of the United Arab Republic that all the documents of titlerelating to the property set out in Annex (E) to the Agreement signedto-day on behalf of our two Governments will be handed over to theGovernment of the United Arab Republic and that in any case theGovernment of the United Kingdom undertakes to hand over the securitiesand/or any other evidence of title or of payment received upon thepayment of compensation to the claimants.&quot;I have taken note of its contents and I confirm the undertaking of theGovernment of the United Kingdom proposed therein.I have the honour to be,Sir,Your obedient Servant,UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC NOTECairo, , 1959.Sir,With reference to Article VI of the Agreement signed this day betweenthe Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and NorthernIreland and the Government of the United Arab Republic and to the actionwhich the two Governments have agreed to take with a view to resumingnormal commercial relations I have the honour to confirm that the competent authorities of the United Arab Republic will give favourable considerationto applications from United Kingdom nationals for permission to establishor maintain import, export and other commercial establishments in theterritory of the United Arab Republic. It is understood that the United arab republic authorities concerned may withold permission in particular casesor may grant it subject to compliance with specified conditions.   I can,
howevflU&apos; onfirm that any United Kingdom commercial establishments set up on maintained in this way will enjoy treatment no less favourable in any respect than the comparable establishments of any other foreign country.I have the honour to be,Sir,Your obedient Servant,UNITED KINGDOM NOTECairo, , 1959.Mr. Minister,I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of to-day aboutthe establishment or maintenance of commercial establishments in the territory of the United Arab Republic.I have the honour to be,Sir,Your obedient Servant,UNITED KINGDOM NOTECairo, , 1959.Mr. Minister,I have the honour to refer to the Agreement signed this day between theGovernment of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Irelandand the Government of the United Arab Republic concerning financial and commercial relations and British property in Egypt.In the course of the negotiations you have expressed concern lest sharesheld by United Kingdom nationals in the Eastern Company, the HelwanPortland Cement Company, Beida Dyers and Societe Egyptienne desIndustries Textiles, some details of which are given in the attached list,*should have been disposed of to non-United Kingdom nationals since theoriginal sequestration. You also requested an assurance that the originalUnited Kingdom nationals who owned the shares at the time of sequestrationwere still United Kingdom nationals.I am authorised to inform you that:(a) the shares in question should not have been sold by United Kingdomresidents to non-United Kingdom residents without the permission ofHer Majesty&apos;s Treasury granted in accordance with the exchange control Act, 1947;(b) no such permission had been granted by Her Majesty&apos;s Treasury since october 30, 1956, or will be granted;(c) the persons owning the shares referred to in the first paragraph of this letter remain United Kingdom nationals. (All the beneficial owners of shares held by Barclays Nominees (City Office) Limited andLombard Street Nominees Limited are United Kingdom nationals.)I avail myself of this opportunity to express to you, Mr. Minister, the assurance of my highest consideration.* Not published
54614   Wt.       IPrinted and published by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery office i /59   F.O P.Cairo, , 1959.Sir,I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of today&apos;s date.[Text of United Kingdom Note.]I have taken note of its contents.I have the honour to be, Sir, your obedient Servant,

</content>
</cab>
