<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 193-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1959C. (59) 41 Copy No.   5827th February, 1959- - - .    - . -CABINETSALARIES OF MEMBERS OF THE BOARDS OF THE B.B.C., I.T.A.AND C.T.B.Memorandum by the Postmaster-general on 4th July, 1957, the Prime Minister announced in the House that theGovernment had decided that the long-deferred adjustment of the salaries of the boards of nationalised industries should be made with effective date from 1st July,1957. New salaries for the British Broadcasting Corporation (B.B.C.), independent television Authority (I.T.A.) and Commonwealth Telecommunications Board(C.T.B.), as shown in the Appendix were proposed as being consequential. with treasury concurrence the proposed new rates were conveyed in confidence to the chairmen of the B.B.C. and I.T.A., and the Commonwealth Relations Officestarted the process of obtaining the views of the other Governments in regardto the C.T.B.2. The B.B.C. increases required an Order in Council, and for the I.T.A.it would have been necessary for me to lay a statement of the new salaries before each House of Parliament. Before this could be done the question was raised at the end of October 1957 whether the decision as regards the B.B.C. and I.T.A.should be suspended for the following reasons :i (i) In the then economic climate it was difficult to defend raising the salaries,particularly for the post in the politically sensitive sphere of commercialtelevision.(ii) It was a question whether the Chairmen of the B.B.C. and I.T.A.performed such exacting tasks as the people responsible for thecommercial operations of big nationalised undertakings.(iii) At that time the B.B.C. were considering a pay claim, and it would havebeen embarrassing to have announced a large increase for the chairmen.The Prime Minister agreed that the decision should be rescinded.3. The Chairmen of the B.B.C. and I.T.A., and the commonwealth governments, were informed that the Government was not able to proceed withits proposals.4. I think we might now reconsider the position in regard to these three bodiesfor the following reasons:  (i) The salaries of the B.B.C. and I.T.A. should naturally move with those ofmembers of Nationalised Boards, and were deferred in specialcircumstances. None of the B.B.C. and I.T.A. appointments arefull-time but the Chairmen of both bodies are expected to make the job their first interest.(ii) The salary of the Chairman of the B.B.C. has remained unchanged( 3,000) since the inception of the Corporation in 1927. The salaries of the ordinary Governors have been  700 in 1927,  1,000 in 1937 and 600 from 1947. National Governors were introduced, with the salaries shown in the Appendix, in 1952.54823
General Post Office, E.C. 1,27th February, 1959.APPENDIXB.B.C., I.T.A. AND C.T.B. SALARIESPresentBJ&amp;C.ChairmanVice-Chairman        ..:      ......National Governors for Scotland andWalesNational Governor for IrelandOther Governors 3,000 1,000 1,000 600(or  1,000 when a NationalBroadcasting Council for northern Ireland is es-tablished) 600Proposed 4,000 1,500 1,500 1,000(or  1,500 when a NationalBroadcasting Council for northern Ireland is es-tablished) 1,000I.T.A.ChairmanVice-ChairmanMember of Authority 3,000 1,000 500 4,000 1,500 1,000C.T.B.Chairman      ...Vice-ChairmanOther Members 2,500 1,750 1,250 3,500 2,500 1,750(Note. Alterations to the C.T.B. salaries require a regulation amending the CommonwealthTelegraphs Act 1949, Amendment Regulations 1953, after the alterations have been approved by thepartner Governments.)   &apos;(iii) The IT.A. salaries date from the setting up of the Authority in 1954, andwere lined up with those of the B.B.C., except that the ordinary members were given  500 which at that time was the standard rate applicableto part-time members of Public Boards:(iv) In the 1946 White Paper on Broadcasting it was stated that: &quot;TheGovernment .... are convinced that the importance of broadcastingmakes it essential that the Corporation should be controlled by thebest possible talent.&quot; This need still remains. An equal need exists for effective and strong direction in the I.T.A.(v) Many of the people concerned, and the Commonwealth Governments, were told of the revised salaries provisionally agreed.(vi) With the recent shift in wages policy the Treasury think that it might beopportune to get out of the way quickly any settlements which can properly be regarded as left overs.5. There is the question whether the move might draw attention to the B.B.C.and I.T.A. as political targets, but they seem to be permanently in the limelight,and the timing of the announcement could perhaps be left to me. I should be glad to have the views of the Cabinet.E. M.

</content>
</cab>
