<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/96/0 images: 198-200</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1959C. (59) 44 Copy No.    5 77th March, 1959CABINETFARM PRICE review memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the Ministerial Committee on the Farm Price Review have considered reports on the progress of the Annual Review discussions with the representatives of theNational Farmers&apos; Unions. These have been carried out in accordance with the cabinet&apos;s conclusion that the total of agricultural guarantees in 1959-60 should remain at the same level as in 1958-59, after account had been taken of the benefitderived by the industry from the schemes for assistance to small farmers (C.C. (59)8th Conclusions, Minute 1).   We now seek further guidance from the Cabinet.Progress of Discussions2. So far proposals have been tabled on the Governments behalf whichwould reduce the total value of the guarantees by about  2J millions, including a reduction of \d. a gallon in the guaranteed price for milk. This leaves open the final move authorised by the Cabinet to no net change in the total value ofthe guarantees and no change in the guaranteed price for milk.3. The Farmers&apos; Unions have asked for an increase of  14 millions in thetotal value of the guarantees, including an increase of ^d. a gallon on milk. Theybase this total largely on a claim that the net income of the industry ought to be restored to the level of real income in 1948 a claim which we cannot accept.4. The Agricultural Ministers say that they see no prospect of agreementwith the Unions this year unless the total value of the guarantees is increased. Itis difficult to say at what total they might agree. They appear to be aiming at notless than plus  6 millions, and at small increases in the guarantees on milk and pigswith only a small reduction on eggs, all of which may be difficult for them togive up.5. The Unions have not mentioned the hill cow subsidy, though there ispressure for continuation of the Marginal Agricultural Production Scheme inScotland. No offer, therefore, of an increase in the hill cow subsidy has so far been made.Views of the Farm Price Review CommitteeThe Agricultural Ministers6. The Agricultural Ministers feel, in the light of the Annual Reviewdiscussions, that the final determination should be an increase in the total valueof the guarantees of  2 millions or  3 millions and that an attempt should be madeto get the Unions&apos; agreement to this. Their reasons are (i) This would have great psychological advantages in presentation, not least to the Governmenfs supporters, particularly in view of the industry&apos;difficulties in the last year.(ii) There is a chance that the Unions could be forced to agree on this basis.But whether they do or not, the Governmenfs position with the industry would be stronger.54862
(iii) This would still mean that at least half the cost of the new Small FarmerSchemes was offset by a reduction in other guarantees, but the criticism of the financing of the Small Farmer Schemes would be blunted.However unjustified it may be, this is still a sore point with many in theindustry.(iv) This could be done as shown in the Appendix without damage to theGovernments commodity objectives. There could still be reductions in the guaranteed price for eggs, wheat and wool and no change in the guaranteed price for milk.7. The Agricultural Ministers have seen the Unions formally and propose tosee them again early next week to offer them no net change. They think that theUnions are certain to reject this. If the Cabinet accept the views of the agricultural ministers, the Minister of Agriculture would then say to Sir James Turner, thePresident of the National Farmers&apos; Union, that he would be prepared to consult his colleagues on the possibility of an increase of  2 millions or  3 millions in thetotal value of the guarantees, subject to the assurance that the Unions would agreeto a determination on that basis. Finally, and subject to any further consultationwith the Cabinet that might be necessary, the Agricultural Ministers would proposeto make a determination at plus  2 millions or  3 millions whether or not the unions had agreed to it, though they warn their colleagues that Government supporters willintensely dislike a &quot; disagreed &quot; settlement.The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations8. The Commonwealth Secretary points out that at our annual consultationson agricultural and food policies with Australia and New Zealand we are under constant pressure to reduce as much as possible the level of subsidy to the UnitedKingdom farmer under the Agriculture Acts. Australia and New Zealand fear that the constantly rising level of United Kingdom agricultural production underthe stimulus of the subsidy will more and more limit their share of the UnitedKingdom market, as has already happened with Cggs. It will be difficult to explain to them that no reduction is being made in the total of the guarantees this year:it would be embarrassing to have to explain an increase.The Chancellor of the Exchequer9. For my part I do not find the arguments of the Agricultural Ministers(in paragraph 6) convincing. By comparison With the maximum reductionpermitted this year and the actual reduction in the level of support last year (both 19 millions) there is little to choose presehtationally between a no-changesettlement and brie of plus  2 millions. The former is generous perhapsexcessively so and already makes a considerable allowance for&quot; the effect of lastyear&apos;s weather, though it has always been accepted that this is not the Governmentsresponsibility. The latter would in my view, be inconsistent with our assessment of the state and prospects of the industry. Any suggestion that we should give any higher award because of the credit taken for the Small Farmer Schemes is alsounjustified and dangerous: this was the clear understanding on which the schemes were approved by the Cabinet and put to the industry, in fact tlie Small FarmersSchemes are already going to cost the Exchequer about  3-4 millions for which wecannot take credit in the Annual Review. Finally I cannot agree that to reduce theproposed cuts on eggs, wheat and wool would do no damage to our commodityobjectives. The cuts on a no-change basis are already inadequate to achieve the objectives and to whittle them away further must inevitably reduce their force stillmore.10. My own view* therefore, is that ah increase in the value of the guaranteeswould Be quite unjustified. On the contrary, all objective Considerations point toa significant reduction. Net income on a normal weather basis has reached a newpeak and the rising trend Of the last few years has been confirmed. Efficiency hascontinued to increase and the rise in factor costs has been moderate certainly lessthan the improvement in efficiency. The subsidy bill has fallen this year, and thishas been most welcome, but it is still very high, both in absolute terms and in comparison with market prices^ and may easily go up again. Some commodities arein overproduction and this situation is likely to get worse in the coming year given
^ SECRET 3j\mdre normal weather. The present level of agricultural support is an embarrassment to our trade with other countries, particularly in the Commonwealth.For these reasons it seems to me that &quot; no change &quot; is the limit to which we should go and that anything more, however small, would be an unjustified concession, whichwould be an embarrassing precedent for the future.D. H. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,6th March, 1959.appendix the following changes would result in a determination of plus  2 millions:    MillionsWheat and rye 6d. per cwt.............      -1-3Wool-2d. per lb.        ...      ............      -0-7Eggs Id. per doz.      ...............      -3-0-5-0Small Farmer Schemes................      4-6-2Hill cows, milk standard quantities, &amp;c.       ......      +0-8-1-2-02. If it were decided to make a determination at plus  3 millions, rather thanplus  2 millions, there would be various possible ways of giving the extra 1 million.

</content>
</cab>
