<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/59/42 images: 426-431</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRiAnNIC MAJSSTY&apos;5 GOVERNMENT ^ q 1Printed for the War Cabin\tg December 1944.SECRET. Copy N0.0 yW.P. (44) 742.\Uh December, 1944.WAR CABINET.ADDRESS BY Mr. STOKES, M.P., IN EGYPT.Note by the Prime Minister.MY colleagues should see the attached letter from General Sir Bernard Pagetto the Secretary of State for War enclosing a report of an address made byMr. Stokes, M.P., to an R.A.F. audience in Egypt.(Intld.) W. S. C.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,IQth December, 1944.

THIS DOCUMENT. IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY-S GOVERNMENTANNEX.Copy of a Letter from General Sir Bernard Paget to the Secretary of State forWar.THE enclosed is an article by the correspondent of the Sunday Expressdescribing an address delivered by Mr. Stokes, M.P., to a R.A.F. audience atHeliopolis airfield.   I have put a stop on its publication.I do not yet know the circumstances under which Mr. Stokes was allowed togive this address, but I think it was arranged unofficially by a warrant officer orn.c.o. of the R.A.F. I therefore send it to you privately. But, if the audience hadbeen of the Army, I tremble to think of the rocket I should have got!It is, however, scandalous that a M.P. can come out here on private business and talk as Mr. Stokes did to service men. I am told that he proposes to go on toItaly, and I am warning Jumbo Wilson about him.Enclosure.From Rostron to Sunday Express, London.HAVING escaped &quot; from the lunatic asylum which is called Parliament, inwhich I have been incarcerated for four years,&quot; Mr. Richard Stokes, M.P. forIpswich, who is touring the Middle East on a private business visit, presentedseveral hundred service men at Heliopolis on yesterday night with a number ofprovocative thoughts. I noted the following from his speech, which lasted overan hour : 1. &quot; The world was betrayed at Teheran Conference by Winston, Uncle Joeand Roosevelt, and in settling Poland&apos;s fate sowed the seeds of the next war.Nobody yet knows the terms.&quot;2. Stressing the point that there should be no question of a hard or softpeace, but that economic injustice should not be done to Germany or Japan,Mr. Stokes said : &quot; It is of no importance whatever to you whether the resourcesof Malaya are controlled by the Japanese or by Mr. Oliver Lyttelton.&quot;3. &apos;&apos; The Beveridge scheme, which is being swallowed by a gullible public, isthe same old dope under a different disguise which was peddled to the public afterthe last war, when the same man invented the dole to arrest a social revolution,which would probably be obstructed again by a new plan.&quot;Answering one questioner in a lively question time, about criticisingChurchill, Mr. Stokes said &apos;&apos; He is an old man of 70, and it cannot be denied he isa great war Premier who was badly needed in 1941, but he loves war and is totallyunfitted for peace.&quot;[28837]




</content>
</cab>
