<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/36/0 images: 49-52</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(QS E 0 R E T -5      5 .SS^-f1.0? A MEETING HELD AT 10, DOWNINGblR^T,  S.v. .l,on MONDAY,   FEBRUARY 23    1922at 12-30 p,m.PRESENT:-&quot;&quot;he Prime Minister.Mr Chamberlain.Lord Curzon.Sir Maurice Hankey.Sir Edward Grigg.(This Meeting took place immediately afterthe withdrawal of Lord Allenby, the meeting with whom is recorded separately (3.-44).)OF. (1) LORD CURZON said that there? was some confusion asto the situation vis-a-vi3 M. Poincare. He had seen theMemorandum of the Prime Minister&apos;s conversation with Dr.Benes.THE PRIME MINISTER said he was very anxious to meetthe suspicions of M. Poincare, and he thought this could-best be done by a meeting.-LORD OURZON agreed that the idea was excellent, buthe was not certain that the best way of conveying the invitation to m.. Poincar4 was through the medi\im of Dr Benes.THE PRIME MINISTER thought it was important to do itinformally.    If a formal invitation were ma^e to M. Poincareand he were to refuse, the same- awkward situation would arise as ir **act arisen when a similar invitation had been
sent to Mr Hughes, the American Secretary of State.

LORD CURZON recalled that M. Poincaré was very punctilious. When Dr Benes made his proposal he would probably say that if Mr Lloyd George wished to see him he should ask himself.

THE PRIME MINISTER remarked that in that event we might make a formal request. 

LORD CURZON thought that M. Poincaré could not and would not refuse such a request. He then gave the most recent developments. When M. St. Aulaire had called on Thursday he had complained that no formal reply had been sent to M. Poincare&apos;s Notes. He (LORD CURZON) had pointed out that the French Government had already published their Notes and would probably publish any reply that was sent. This would provoke a serious controversy in the Press of both countries. He had added that the British Government would deplore such a controversy. A discussion of the economic aspects of the Genoa Conference had already been provided for. He had asked why, if M. Poincaré wished for a discussion of the political aspects, he should not either instruct the Ambassador or send a special emissary? Thus, LORD OURZON remarked, he had unconsciously taken exactly the same line as the Prime Minister had taken with Dr Benes on the following day. M. St. Aulaire said that this was a very good idea, which he would put to his Chief. Nevertheless on Saturday afternoon M. St. Aulaire had called on Sir Eyre Crowe, in Lord Ourzon&apos;s absence, and had insisted on a reply to certain points in the French memorandum. Sir Eyre Crowe had pointed out the British desire to avoidary controversy, that they expressed their willingness to see some emissary of the French Government, and that they had only not sent a reply because they did not wish to provoke a controversy. M. St. Aulaire said that nevertheless there were certain points on which the French Governement
&quot;Alt they must have a written reply.    This morning these points had been received from M. St. Aulaire.   LORD OURZONthen gave a list o^ the points proposed by the French Sov-ernrnent,THE PRIMF MINISTER pointed out that even if a Note were sent in reply on those various points, it. Poincare&apos; would almost certainly say that in some respects they were not satisfactory to him.    He would then send a fresh Note, andthe correspondence would continue endlessly.    He himselffelt it was essential to have a meeting to discuss them,and the meeting should be between Ministers.    Ambassadorswho were not in immediate, touch with their Cabinets couldnot conduct such negotiations ,THE LORD PRIVY SEAL agreed that a detailed reply would lead straight into controversy.    He suggested that a reply should be sent to the effect that we wished to avoid beingled into a controversy, that we believed the two G-ovem-rents fundamentally were aiming at the same thing, and that everything could be arranged at a meeting between either thePrime Ministers-or the Foreign Ministers.TIP&quot; PRIMF- MINISTER agreed to this reply,  and suggestedthat Lord Curzon should add that- after a Conversation wewould be quite prepared to send an official reply.LORD OURZON agreed with the gist of the r-^ply proposedby vr Chamberlain,  and said he would conclude with thesuggestion for an informal Conversation between the PrimeMinisters or Ministers designated by them.(2) Arising out of a Question in Parliament, a short discussion took place in regard to the Russian Famine.tht?i ppimf MINISTER said he was rather ashamed of what this country vas doing, or, rather, not doing, in regard tothe Russian Famine.    5,000,000 people, he was informed, were bound to perish from star-ration this year, and another5,000,000 would probably perish next year if nothing were done. --3-
THE LORD PRIVY SEAL agreed as to the deplorable natureof the situation in Russia, but pointed cut that while theUnited. States Government was waiting for the passage of aBill through their Legislature which would enable them toassist Austria, this country was putting its hand in itspocket to the tune of over  3*000,000.    It was impossibleto finance all these countries.   The Chancellor of the Exoshe-quer was under great pressure not to spend more than could teavoided^ and it was very difficult for him to find any meansovf financing these great demands upon hini.IG^T) otjrzou suggested that as  2,000,000 were being givento Austria it might be possible to find  1,000,000 for Russia.His suggestion for a reply to any Parliamentary Question onthe subject would be that the Government would only give assistance if there were an overwhelming opinion in parliament in favour of it;    or it&apos;might be put differently, - that unless there were an overwhelming opinion in Parliament infavoTir of action^ nothing could be done.....Whitehall Gardens, S.w&quot;.l,February 20,  1922.

</content>
</cab>
