<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/36/0 images: 188-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
iphjLB Document is.the Property/, of Eis Britannic Majesty&apos;^ Government)secret, 56 MIEUTES of a Conference of Ministers heldat 10, Downing Street,- 3-,-.?%- on lion day,7th August, 1922 atlvO pirn.-PRESET:Hie Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Rt.Hon. The Rt.H6n4A.Chamberlain, L1.-P., Sir Robert Home, G. B.E.,Lord Privy Seal. , X.C., ll.2,r Chancellor ofthe Exchequer.The lit. Eon.3ir Earning Vorthingt on-Eyans, Sir IS oh n Bradbury, G.C.B.,Bt., II.P., Secretary of Principal British Repre---State for War. sentaiive, ReparationCommission.Sir Basil Blackett, E.C.B.,Controller of Einance. P. Leith Ross,, Esq.,Reparation Commission.P,J,grigg, Esci.Treasury. R. G, Tans it tart,. Esq., CM. G.,M.V.0,, foreign Office.S4D;V/aley, Esq;, Sir Edward Grigg, E.C.Y.0.,T r e as u. ry. C. M. G*Sir maurice Hankey,   G.C.B.,Secretary,I\T.B, This meeting followed Immediately after thp Allied npctlngiI2iA,N * THE PR BE MINISTER commented on what appearedto be an extraordinary change of front in M,PoincareTsattitude.     He recalled that M,poincare   had first been interpreted as indicating that he Could not com-promide on any of the proposals he had made, as every member&apos; of the Erench Government had expressed his agree-ment   in them and he was not entitled to give way.Then he had interrupted the interpreter to ernp lainthat the x^oint on which he could not compromise was theprinciple that there could bo no moratorium without some counterpart;
MR. VANSITTART said his impression had been that M. Camerlynck&apos;s original translation had been correct. All depended, however, upon whether M. Poincare had used the words "ces conditions" or "cette condition".

THE PRIME MINISTER said the proposals appeared to he quite hopeless. M. Briand had suggested something similar before he had seen clearly that they were impracticable. Supposing, for example, the Allies were to seize the forests. He had put the position to M. Theunis and M. Jaspar and asked, if they, as Theunis-Jaspar and Co. had to handle the German forests as a commercial proposition, what would they do with it? M. Theunis had made a very sensible proposal, namely, that the question should be put to experts to work out how many gold marks would be obtained from the proposals - how much cash would the Allies obtain.

SIR BASIL BLACKETT said that there was a certain amount of money in the proposal for a customs barrier.

THE PRIME MINISTER remarked that this would only be paper money.

SIR BASIL BLACKETT said that before, the French and Belgians had made the mistake of keeping the marks, which only depreciated, instead of disposing of them at once. 

SIR JOHN BRADBURY entered at this point.

MR.LEITH ROSS said that at the values then obtaining, half-a-million sterling might have been obtained.

SIR JOHN BRADBURY, in reply to the Prime Minister, said that out of all the proposals made by M. Poincare, the Allied Governments might obtain a little cash, but it would make the bankruptcy of Germany complete.
THE PRIME MINISTER remarked that Marshal Foch had always said that seven divisions would be required for the occupation of the Ruhr. If the French occupied the Ruhr, it would take a good deal of the proceeds to pay the cost. He then reverted to M. Theunis&apos;s proposal to remit the proposals to experts, which he thought should he adopted.

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR agreed that this was a good proposal.

THE PRIME MINISTER said he objected to the constant allusion to the sufferings of Belgium and France, without a word being said about the British Empire&apos;s losses and casualties and without a word about the Italian lesses and casualties.

SIR BASIL BLACKETT said that a very considerable figure could be built up as to what Great Britain had advanced to Germany if calculated on the same lines as M. Poincare&apos;s statement.

THE PRIME MINISTER said he thought he ought to say something on the subject of what M.Poincare had said about disarmament, for he felt convinced that whatever was said would be published and it was necessary to state the facts.

THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER asked whether the Prime Minister would like to say something about M. Poincare&apos;s remarks that French taxation was not comperable with British.

THE PRIME MINISTER said he would be glad if Sir Robert Horne, who had gone into the question, would say something about this.

THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUE pointed out that the Committee on Guarantees had just returned from Germany and the German Government had undertaken to


whatdo all that they wished.     He folt that/they neededwas to get the co-operation of Ocrinany, and that theuse of the iron hand was Of no use.After some further discussion, the Conferenceadjourned after agrCeinp(a) To neet again at 4.0 p. in.(h) hat Sir Basil Blachctt should by thoufurnish an estimate calculated on thesame lines as 11. PoincarcI3 estimateas to mfoat advances had he on mde to Seraany(o) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should be prepared,to naho a replyto what M. Poincare had said on the subjectof British and French taxation.2g Yvhitehall Gardens, 3.v/,/17th l&amp;gust, 1922

</content>
</cab>
