<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/36/0 images: 207-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETNotes of a Conference of Ministers heldS. 60 at 10,Downing Street on Saturday,August 12th, 1922, at 10.0 a.m. resell&quot;!2he Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Rt.Hon. The Rt.Hon.A.Chamberlain, M.P., Sir Robert horne,  G.B.E.,Lord Privy Seal. E.C., M.P.,  Chancellorof the Exchequer.The RtJIon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans, Sir Basil B3a ckett, k.C.B.,Bt., M.P., Secretary of Controller of finance.State for War,p. Leith Ross,  Esq.,Sir John Bradbury,  G.C.B., Reparation Commission.Principal British Repre-sentative, Reparation Sir Edward Grigg, E.C.V.O.,G ommi s s i on. C. M, G.Sir Mai rice Hankey,  G.C.B.,Secretary.ESI REPARATIONS. This meeting was summoned before the meetingof experts at 10.30 to discuss the joresent positionas regards Reparations.      There were no d?fe^^^^tconclusions;    the general trend was similar to the trend of the Cabinet discussion recorded in Cabinet.45(22).      The following points in the discussionare deserving of record:-SIR JOHN BRADBURY described a conversation he had had with Herr Bergmann,  the Geriaan PinancialRepi&quot;esentative, who v/as on a visit to London.He. had told Herr Bergmann the present position andthe extent to which the British representatives had succeeded in toning down the Prench proposals.Herr Bergmann , who had said he could not speakfor the German Government but could only give his
personal views, had had the strongest objections to theproposals as regards the interference with mines andforests, which would have a shattering effect in Germany.Any German Government would have to refuse these proposals.SIR EDWARD GRIGG said that Herr Bergmann had told him that he would rather have the French acting againstGermany alone on such an issue than/the Allies as a whole.SIR JOHN BRADBURY also expressed the view that itwould be very difficult for the German    Government tomake further concessions.     Herr Hermes, the GermanFinance Minister, had had the greatest difficulty in agreeing to the proposals earlier in the year aboutGerman taxation and had only been induced to do so asthe result of long personal negotiations with Sir john bradbury himself.     His position had been weakened by this concession and he would probably fall if he was asked for more, though Sir John Bradbury would be quite prepared to impress upon him the vital importance of accepting theBritish proposals.THE PRIME MINISTER emphasised the fact that thereis a Preach election in eighteen months,      This wouldprobably bring different forces into power in Prance asaccording to all information he received,  the Paris Pressdid not represent Prance as a whole, and neither did thepresent French Chamber.      The intervening period was verydifficult for Germany and for Great Britain.    Their policy should be to try and tide over until the French election and this ought to be impressed on the Germans.In the course of the Conference it was mentioned thatM. Schanzer had ca!3e d on the Prime Minister the previous evening and had said that Italy could not sign the british proposals without a remission of their debt.
2UflSIR JOHN BRADBURY said that according to his informationall intelligent Germans,  including those who were infavour of a policy of fulfilment of the Treaty, had cometo the conclusion that this policy involved death and destruction.      His own view was that for the next twoyears there ought to he a moratorium as regards &quot;allreparations by Germany, except as regards coal deliveries.THE PRIIIS MINISTER raised the question as to whetherit would be useful for him to see Herr Bergmann.ME. CHAMBER LI IN thought that this might be inexpedient.Herr Bergmann1s presence in London would soon be known andthe Prench would draw their own conclusions from the inter-view.      It would probably be better for the Prime Ministerto be in a position to say he had not seen Herr Bergmann.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that at any rate it wouldbe useful for Sir Robert Horne to see Herr Bergmann.SIR JCEN BRADBURY thought that one of the dangers of the present situation was that the Reparation commission would be drawn into declaring Germany in default.     He didnot think that the Belgian representative could be relied on to support the British view in this matter, neithercould the Italian representative be relied on.      Consequent-ly,  there was very considerable risk that the decision to declare Germany in default might be taken by a majority vote.      Only Belgium, Prance,  Great Britain and italy had votes, and the Prench Chairman had a casting vote.Consequently, unless he could get two representatives onhis side, he would be out-voted.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W./112th August.1922

</content>
</cab>
