<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/16 images: 318-345</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
t158- MOST SECRET -WJf. (40) 16th. CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 8.Confidential Annex.!*   *   *iTHE VATICAN. THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS read to his colleagues a Secret letter from Mr Osborne, our minister to the Vatican, dated 12th January. On theprevious day Mr Osborne had had an audience of HisHoliness the Pope, who had said that he had receiveda visit from a German representative, or representatives,!who claimed to be speaking for certain German ArmyChiefs,   Their names were said to be known, but the pope did. not give them.The gist of this message was that a great german offensive had. been prepared for the middle of February,jor even earlier.   This offensive would be very bitterand quite unscrupulous, but it need never be delivered,   jIf the German Generals could be assured of a peace withGreat Britain (France was not mentioned) they wereprepared to replace the present German Government by a&quot;Verhandlungsfahige Regierung&quot; - a Government withwhich it was possible to negotiate - and then to reach a settlement in Eastern Europe with the British Govern-ment.   This settlement would include a restoration in poland and Czechoslovakia, and would, also deal withRussia.   No details, however, were given.   There could,however, be no concession, over the Anschluss withAustria.   The Pope had said that he had not been askedj:to put forward the communication, but felt his conscience;would not be easy unless he had sent for Mr Osborne.The latter&apos;s comment had been that the whole thing was    ij;hopelessly vague and dangerously reminiscent of the-i- Is

Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,17th January, 1940.answer for the good faith of the intermediary (who wasQQt. Prince Ruppreeht of Bavaria), he could not guarantee the good faith of the principals.   Still less could he guarantee that, if they effected the change ofGovernment they spoke of, they would he any morereliable than Hitler.   As to the guarantees they wanted, they had only to read the Prime Minister&apos;sor Lord Halifax&apos;s speeches.   Their first step shouldbe to effect the &quot;Change of Government and then to talk of peace.   With the best will in the world, HisMajesty&apos;s Government eould not take up such a nebulousIproposition. jThe Pope had not in any way demurred, or made any  jattempt to justify or support the communication madeto Mr Osborne.   On the contrary, he had been at pains to disavow any responsibility for it except for hisconscience sake.   He begged that the matter, on whichhe had. not spoken to anyone else, should be regardedas absolutely secret.Mr Osborne had promised that he would not speak of the matter to anyone in Rome, but he would report it, as a matter of great secrecy, to the foreign secretary.   It was clear, however, that the FrenchGovernment would have to be informed of the matter.The Pope said that he understood this.The War Cabinet agreed  That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should take suitable steps toinform the French Government&quot; of the communication which had been made byHis Holiness the Pope to Mr Osborne.Venice affair.   While His Holiness said that he could

*   THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT-to BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.MOST   SECRET.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO..M.(40) 16TH CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 9.Confidential Annex.SCANDINAVIA.(previous reference:W.M.(40) 15thConclusions,Minute 12).Discussion took place on a proposal that a mission, headed by a Member of the War Cabinet, should proceed to Scandinavia.     In this connexion the WarCabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, covering the draft of atelegram from His Majesty The King to the King of norway (W.P.(40) 25).THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY thoughtthat the proposal to send a Mission to Norway and sweden at this stage required careful examination.No decision to send a Mission should be taken until agreement had been reached on the instructions to begiven to it.     How far was the Mission to go in bring-ing pressure to bear on the Scandinavian Governments?What weapons did we intend to place in its hands?     Wasits armoury to include the threat of British Navalinterference with the iron ore vessels passing down the Norwegian cpast?His Majesty&apos;s Minister in Oslo had reportedin telegram No.&apos; 27 off 15th January that a Hamburgtanker named the WEST WALL had been allowed to operateinside Norwegian territorial waters.     She was, in fact,an auxiliary cruiser of a type suitable for providingsubmarines with oil, ammunition and fresh crews.     Ifthese were substantiated, we had a serious grievanceand we ought to bring it home to the Norwegian Govern-ment. .

A Mission, if sent, should be instructed tohold very plain language with the scandinavian government.   Did those Governments realise that ifthe Allies were beaten, Germany and Russia would be ina position to divide the world between them.   Were theywilling to be parties to bringing about such a stateof affairs?   They were, in fact, contributing to suchan end if they permitted their ore products to be usedto keep Germany going.    These supplies would become the means of sending hundreds of thousands of Britishand French soldiers to their death.If it was to be an instruction to the lord privy Seal to inform the Scandinavian Governments thatwe would not for an indefinite period tolerate theirsupplying Germany with the means of continuing the war,The First Lord said he would gladly assent to thedespatch of the Mission.It might be pointed out to the swedish government that the destruction of Finland, with which their country had a close relationship, was beingconsummated before their eyes.   Finland, however, wouldnot be the last small neutral country to go down beforethe war was terminated.    It was practically certain thatthe Scandinavian countries would, sooner or later,become involved in the struggle. .To sum up, the Mission ought to be instructedto bring the maximum amount of pressure to bear upon thetwo Scandinavian Governments.THE PRIME MINISTER said he was in agreementwith much, though not with all, that had been said bythe First Lord of the Admiralty.    In particular, he

could not bring himself to contemplate j as he thought theFirst Lord contemplated, the capture of the Galivare orefields in the face of Norwegian and Swedish opposition.His reasons were as follows.-(i) the Chiefs of Staff had reportedvery strongly against undertakingthis military operation (.W.P. (40)24) j(ii) action of this kind on our part would have disastrous results in theDominionsj(iii) those results would extend to theUnited States.It was essential to us, for financial and other reasons, to retain the support of public opinion in theUnited States.He greatly wished to obtain possession of theGalivare ore fields.    Should we attain this objectthrough the despatch of the proposed Mission?   It wouldbe difficult to think of a better head for such a mission that the Lord Privy Seal, but he (the PrimeMinister) must admit that he saw small prospect of immediate success attending the Mission&apos;s efforts.The country we were really out to convince wasSweden.    If Sweden moved in the direction which we desired, Norway would probably follow in her wake.   Whatpolicy should the Lord Privy Seal pursue with theSwedish Government?     In his (the Prime Minister&apos;s) view the policy should be that enunciated by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty, minus the threat of Naval action on our part.    The Swedes must be brought to see that theyhad a vital interest - their future security -r to preserve by adhering to our side, and that they hadeverything to lose by a German vistory.

The Lord Privy Seal might point out to the swedes that victory was in the balance.   The centraldecision of the war might well be that which the scandinavian Governments were called upon to take.    Ifthey denied their iron ore to Germany, the balance wouldin all probability turn in our favour.    If they refusedto fall in with our wishes, the balance might quitepossibly turn against us.The next point to be considered was the veryvulnerable position of Sweden,, and especially ofStockholm.   Very careful consideration would have tobe given to what the Lord Privy Seal was, in fact, tosay in this connection.    The best solution mightprobably be to give the Swedes an assurance that, if thingscame to the worst, we should, by such and such a date, bein a position to give them military help to such andsuch an extent.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said that we might offer the Swedes Staff Conversations.    There wasno reason why these should not take place immediately.The French military authorities would probably be willing to participate.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he entirelyagreed.He thought that it was fair to say that behind the policy which Norway and Sweden, like Belgium,were now pursuing lay the question &quot;Can this war runits course without our country being overrun?&quot;Our answer to that question must be &quot;Even if youare overrun, we are in a position to make itcertain that you will not be finally overwhelmed&quot;.

The Mission might point out to the swedish government that Germany was unlikely to attack theircountry until she was desperate, since by doing soshe would make certain that her essential suppliesof iron ore would be cut off for a considerable period.The draft telegram to the King of Norway*attached to W.P.(40) 25, proposed that the Lord privy seal should visit Oslo first and Stockholm afterwards.If this itinerary was to be adhered to, it wouldprobably be necessary for the Lord Privy Seal to avoidgoing very deeply into the central problem during his visit to Oslo.     He would no doubt say to the norwegians that the German use of Norway1s territorial waters had created a situation which was intolerablefor us.     A good part of the conversations, however,might be devoted to matters connected with the Anglo-Norwegian War Trade Agreement and the chartering of tankers.He would have to spend a longer time in stockholm in order to establish confidential relationsfor his task with the Swedish Government and theSwedish military authorities.     The Swedes could seevery little beyond the fact of a powerful Germanystanding at close quarters to them.     It would take time to alter this point of view.       We must notdeceive ourselves into thinking that the Swedes wouldwillingly stop their iron ore trade with Germany inthe next few months.       They might, however, be

induced gradually to work up to that conclusion,For a start,they might cease all overtime working and might connive at certain forms of sabotage.    Itwould be some time, however, before they tookcourage and came into the open.It remained to be considered what line was to be taken with the press regarding the mission to Scandinavia.     This was a difficult question.To sum up, the prospects of success were somewhat uncertain, but the objects at stake were sovaluable that he was disposed to think we should bejustified in taking the risk of despatching theMission.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he agreed as to the aims of the proposed mission.     They would be:-(a) to lead the two scandinavian government to view the problemsof the war in their true perspective.(b) to persuade them to slow down theirdeliveries of iron ore to Germany -this without prejudice to our long-term object of getting those deliveriescompletely closed down.In proposing the Mission, we should exposeourselves to a rebuff at the hands of the scandinavian government.     We need not trouble about that,however, provided that we were able to set in action the educational processes of which the Prime Minister

The arguments for and against the despatchof the Mission were, in the Foreign Secretary^ view,very nicely balanced, and he had not found it easy toarrive at a judgment.     Perhaps the two considerationstrhich had weighed with him most were the foilowing:-(a) The Swedes would probably take their main decision in the light of facts,not of arguments.     The main facts which would be present to their mindswould be -(i) the fear of Russia;   and(ii) the amount of military assistanceto be expected from the UnitedKingdom.(b) the probable German reactions to a slowing down of Swedish deliveries of iron ore.However much the Swedes attempted to cover up whatthey were doing, the Germans would at once perceivethat they were coquetting with us.   The German Govern-ment might be expected to present strong demands to sweden, with the threat of strong action in the back-ground.The Foreign Secretary confessed that, in thelight of these considerations, he doubted whether weshould be wise to send the Mission to Scandinavia atthis juncture.     He would not, however, resist the project if his colleagues were in favour of it.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL agreed with the foreign secretary that the arguments for and against thedespatch of the Mission were very finely balanced.   Hewould very gladly undertake the task if his colleagues were unanimous in wishing him to do so.     Unless,however, his colleagues expressed a clear view in favourof the Mission, he would feel considerable hesitation ingoing to Scandinavia.     Balancing all the considerations,his personal view was on the whole against the Missionat this stage.

IS?THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER agreed thatthe arguments for and against the project were evenly balanced.   The War Cabinet had rejected one solution.    Ifthey made no move, they must face the fact that from now until the end of the war the Germans would be free to import ore from the Galivare ore fields.   he therefore favoured action to break up the present unsatisfactory situation, and a Mission to Scandinaviaappeared to offer the best means of doing so.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said that hewas apprehensive of the publicity which must attend a mission of this kind.   Would it not be possible toexercise our pressure in some less public way?THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO had grave doubts whether any Mission could achieve the desiredresult without being able to give a more encouraginganswer to the question &quot;What help we should be able togive Sweden in the event of an attack by Germanyand/orRussia in May?&quot;   Southern Sweden and Stockholm werewithin easy reach of Northern Germany, and the russian air bases in Estonia were even nearer to the Swedishcapital.   He concluded that, if we were unable to offermore substantial forces than were indicatedin W.P. (40) 2.3, a discussion would only revealour weakness.   He recalled that during the last war we had succeeded by economic pressure, in particularby restricting Sweden&apos;s supplies of coal and wheat,1in reducing her exports of iron ore to Germany to3^ million tons, while securing 2 million tons for ourselves.
CO.
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR pointed outthat the economic weapons at our disposal now were likely to he far less effective.     What would reallycount, would be the help that we could give     IfFinland Were overrun, public opinion in Sweden would demand some active measures for her assistance, and her decision would depend on the assistance we could give them.     This might seem small, but it might be morethan the Swedes expected, and he thought it would bevery advantageous to open up channels for informing them what was in our minds;   but the discussions should at the early stages be carried on as far as possible ina private atmosphere.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that itwas impossible to guarantee Sweden against the effects of air attacks, but he thought it very important to let them know what help we could give them and thatwe should be prepared to offer as substantial help aspossible by May, when they would have to make their decision.     He agreed that it would be objectionablethat any publicity should be attached to our discussions on this matter,THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was clearthat the general feeling was against the proposed mission under the Lord Privy Seal, but that it was not enough to take this negative decision.     He feared thatin May,if it seemed likely that the Russian   invasibnof Finland would not stop at the Swedish border, theGermans would offer the Swedes their help against russia, and would force help on them.     It might thenbe too late for us to intervene.       If difficulties of publicity made it undesirable to send the Lord privy seal, someone else should explain the situation tqutheScandinavians and in particular bring home to them where

their real interests lay.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL pointed out that recent telegrams suggested that our influence with the scandinavian Government was growing weaker rather thanstronger, and he could not resist the conclusion thatour case was not perhaps being presented as well aspossible.    He referred to the great influence exercised by our Ministers in Scandinavia in the last war.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he had thought at one time of suggesting that,if the Lord Privy Seal did not go, a junior minister might be sent, but he had reached the conclusion thatthis alternative would represent the worst of bothworlds.   . He agreed that we could not leave matters asthey were, and he proposed that as a first step he shouldhave a full and strong talk with the Swedish Minister inLondon, and then with the Norwegian Minister.   The latter was of less importance, but as the two Governments were indaily consultation it was inevitable that an approach should be made to him too.     He would try to get them torecognise the situation as it was, and to open up channelsfor consultation with their Governments as to what could he done to remedy it.     He would hope incidentally to heable to put to them the suggestion mentioned by SirCecil    Dormer that the Norwegian Government mightestablish military zones at selected points in theirterritorial waters, so as to force traffic into the open sea..    But the main purpose of his conversationswould be to try to lead the Swedish Government on to face the big issue, that they must choose between one side or the other.

THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY suggested thatit might he preferable to send a short but strongly-worded despatch based on the suggestions for the lord privy Seal outlined by the Prime Minister in the courseof the discussion.   He only regretted that it was notpossible for us to use the threat of talcing the orefields hy force, but the despatch should be worded as strongly as possible and should be reinforced byconversations with the two Ministers.The War Cabinet agreed:-(1) Not to invite the Lord Privy seal to go on a Mission to the Governmentsof Norway and Sweden; in reachingthis conclusion, they had in mindparticularly that the publicityinevitably attending such a Missionwould be most undesirable atthis juncture, and would tend to defeat the objects in view.(S) Not to recommend to His Majesty TheKing to reply to the King of Norwayin the terms of the draft telegramannexed to W.P. ( 0).86fbut to invite the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to considerwhether any further message wasnecessary or whether the interimreply already sent would suffice,(3) To invite the Foreign Secretaryto see the Swedish and NorwegianMinisters in London, and to put ,the position to them as outlined in the above discussion, and then to report again to the War Cabinet.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.,17th January, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
