<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 30-32</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fffiifiMfftf^tt 18 tiis Propertyfc3r ^Government if ALL  AIR-RAID WARNINGS  IN LONDON  BY NIGHI.f     1 submit a memorandum by  the&apos; Commitsion^r of Police on the aboVe subject and ask Ihe War Cabinet to decide,  -        (a)  Whether  the  present  system of night warnings should be maintained, or        (b)  Whether  it should  be maintained but should be supplemented by allowing     local authorities to  sound  siren0, or        (c)  ?/hether  the  system in  use by day of firing high explosive sound-bombs     should  be extended  to the night.     1 agree with the Commissioner as to the inadvisability of Using the sound-bombs [t night j   These form an excellent warning by day, when the streets are congested and  ie roar of the London traffic  drowns all other sounds? including the most powerful fciren.   But  to use them  at night, &apos;&quot;hen there is comparative quiet and the use of these  oinbs would, give the  imnression that a bombardment of London is proceeding, would  nuse unnecessary alarm and  might lead to serious consequences.&apos;   When these bombs were  irst used  by day,  two persons  of weak physique are said to have died of heart failure     The use of sirens would not be open to the above objections *    They would,  as the bands si oner  says,  reach  the inmates of all houses and would not improbably cause some persons to  leave their houses and incur danger in the streets   iJut there is a widely  if fused feeling among the  public that when a raid is impending they are entitled, to be tc&apos;.&apos;.d the truth,  and that  those  foolish persons who upon being warned rush into danger me only themselves to blame.   The prudent householder says &quot;i  have made careful pangements  for  getting my family into the basement  of my house  (or some other safe lacej  when a raid  is threatened,  and when  the  authorities know the raiders  are coming  ought  to have  the information so that I may take  the measuree required  for the  protec-lion of  my household&quot;.   And he is not sati-fied  by the  answer  that,  if the  informationI? given, other  oeople will act foolishly.    I  believe that a siren i* actually sounded  at Woolwich Arsenal which is  heard  everI&apos;considerable area of London;   and  the local  authorities  at Leytonstone and some  other   eo have set up a system of warnings by  siren  and  refuse to  discontinue it.   To forbidI -se local warnings without set+ing up some  other  form  of public warning would lead  tol-?e-at dissatisfaction.    If it is decided to  allow and  encourage the local  authorities to give warning by  ren, -       (a) they should  be prevented  from  using the  siren before the &quot;take cover1&apos; notice    issues.       (b) a regulation  should be  made forbidding the use of  sirens for other purposes    during the hours when  thejr are intended to be used as air-raid warnings;   (these    hours should be fixed,  e.g, in  winter from 3 p..rn. until  6 a9m. the sound bomb?    being used at all other times).       (c) the public should be  strongly cautioned against leaving their houses  on    hearing the warning.rP October, 1917G0 CAVE.
rrbAIR  RAID WARNINGS  IN  LONDONMEMOROTUM BY THE COMMISSIONER OF POLICE.    After escon raid the controversy a&quot;B to the form in whioh-warning should  begiven is invariably revised and it would be satisfactory if  a decision upon  thenoint were given by the War Cabinet, as this would be deemed authoritative andaccepted by everybody.    At present from half an hour before sunrise until half  an hour after sunset,warning is given by the discharge from selected centres of two sound signals.  Atother times, the warning is disseminated by the Constabulary, regular and special,on foot and on cycles or in motor cars, carrying &quot;Take Cover&quot; placards, whocirqulate through the streets sounding their whistles, bells or horns and callingout &quot;Take Cover&quot;*  The placards carried by the cars and oycles are illuminated soas to be visible from a distance.  Experience justifies the  statement that so faras clearing the streets is concerned this method has proved  quite satisfactory.It may be added that it is very effectively supplemented by  other indications topeople actually in the streets0  Tram cars turn dovm their lights;  pedestrians inthe vicinity ofifthe river bank see the Tower Bridge carriage way lifted up;  clse-where they see Fire Engines proceeding to allotted stations, the Constabulary andmembers of Air Raid Relief parties g and ambulances and other motor transportassembling.  In brief the indications are si3numerous that some of them cannot failto reach even the most unobservant.    Though this warning may be deemed to be quito sufficient for the purpose ofinforming persons in the streets it is urged that it does not reach the occupantsof all houses, and some of them may be anxious to leave their homes for shelterin the neighbourhood or to proceed from upper to lower rooms for greater security*    They demand therefore that the warning shall be given by sound signals, thesound of which will necessarily reach everybody, indoors as  well as out of doors;and it may be admitted that if the method of giving the warning by day were  adopteefor the dark hours, this object would be achieved.    The objections to this course are very weighty,.  Firing sound signals atnight when most people are in their homes would, more especially in districtsoccupied by the working classes., create -great alaria, in places amounting to  panic.A liumber, far in excess of the accoimaDda-fcion available, would rush for shelter.;children half clad would be dragged out -of their beds and taken out into  thestreets.and possibly be still there when.&quot;the guns begin to fire., not having  foundroom in the shelters.  The weather is becoming colder and if many raids takeplace under such conditions there will be a heavy toll taken of child life.,  as &apos;the result of the exposure to.which children will be subjected.    Besides the ohildren there are the inmates of hospitals to be considered,also women in delicate health, old persons, persons with weak hearts or in badhealth,: or recovering from sickness and so forth, all of .whom might be veryseriously affected, by the alarming sound - for it is an alarming sound -- of  thesignals that are fired by day.  The justification for firing them by day is  that
the streets then are greatly congested with people and that an instantaneousand emphatic warning is required to enable them to be quickly emptied.  Atnight time conditions are different and the streets, being less congested,can be cleared in time&apos;, by the means now adopted, which cause no special alarmto the category of persons above referred to.     An alternative proposal that finds favour with many is that the warningat night should be given by syrons to be set up by the various local author-ities, of whom there are 121 in the Metropolitan Police District.  There canbe no doubt that if this system is set up there will be many instances ofpremature signals, some of which will be taken  up by adjoining districts,with the result&apos; that the public will be unnecessarily disturbed.     The syren would certainly be less alarming, but, as its sound wouldreach the inmates of all houses,&apos;the effect would be to impel great numbersof personsmore especially in the poorer districts, to rush for shelterswhich do not exist.  It&apos; is, I venture to urge, most desirable that the peopleshould remain, in their houses.  What has to be combated is the conviotion ofso many of them that any&apos;&apos;publie building, such as a Town Hall, Library orPolice Station, ,1s soinfinitely more secure than their own homes that, atany risk, they must get there.&apos;    / - -     Tube Stations, Goods Depots, Warehouses and the basements of well builtfaototios are certainly quite secure)  but where working class residentialdistricts are not centres of industry, these securo sheltere do not exist,and saoh shelters as are available are insufficient in accommodation and atbest only makeshifts, which in many instances are splinter preof only, andin  this respect very little better than private houses.  At the present timethere is a marked insufficiency of even this imperfect air raid shelter ina&apos; great number of densely &quot;populated areas and in such circumstances no measureshould,  I venture to submit, be taken, which will have the effeot of bringinginto the streets people for whom there is no shelter accommodation.     Y,re arc  gradually increasing this accommodation and we have it now forabout I3 millions;  but it is very badly distributed, some areas having muchmoro than they really need, others much less.     Y^eighing all these considerations and having regard to what I know of thestate of mind of the people in the East End, who in the past have sufferedmuch from raids, and whose nerves in consequence have been greatly strained,I am not desirous to see any change made which might have the effoot ofaggravating  their existing restlessness without adding to their security.      It will be necessary when this decision is taken to havo power to corn-pel local authorities to come into line and to refrain from taking independ- ent action  not formally authorised.  At present two or three local authorities contemplate  action which, if carried out, may create great oonfusion and possibly result in alarm.  An Order under Regulation IB (8) Defence of the ;Realm Regulation would meet this..                                                              E.R.H,.-                                                                   25.10.17.

</content>
</cab>
