<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 311-313</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                  JJhls Document is the Property of C ^   &amp;aiM^S                   His  Britannic  MalestWs Government&quot;)      /                               SEQRET :.-                     il*&apos;Sb2^^%^\  LOSSES OP SHIPPING BY SUBMARINE ACTION,        21                      17th - 20th October, 1917,Adiairalty Memorandum for the War Cabinet,         Referring to Minuie 11 Of War Cabinet 254^ the following report is forwarded in regard to the heavy- shipping losses sustained through the operations of enemy submarines from 17th - 20th instants         The names and nationalities of the vessels sunk are  shewn on the attached list, an analysis of which reveals that  the heaviest losses occurred off the Yorkshire Ooast and  in the Mediterranean,         In regard to&quot;these localities, the following points are notable         YORKSHIRE OOABH?.  4 British and 2 Neutral ships were  sunk in this area, which relies in a special degree on an Air Patrol, since it has been necessary to?weakon considerably the surface  patrol in order to provlcte escort vessels for the Scandinavian Convoy System,         The Patrol appropriated for the duty consisted of Handley-Page machines based on Redcar,         The enemy activity in this area referred to followed immediately on the withdrawal of the Handley-Pagemachines for Prance,       -  MEDITERRANEAN.   5 British ships  were sunk in this period, and of these 4 were  sunk East of Malta,  2 of them being in a Convoy.         The Convoy in question was the  first of  a system of through Convoys from the United Kingdom to Port  Said&quot; and was composed entirely of cargo8liners.   This  Convoyhas boon instituted with the intention of  graduallydiverting the Eastern Trade from the  Gape  to  theMediterranean route,  and at the same  time  with a view  to                                               releasing
releasing Colliers now carrying coal to Port Said toreinforce the Italian Coal Trade.         Special arrangements were made as regards Escortthrough the Mediterranean, and the 0o voy had completed thegreater portion of its voyage in safety when it was attacked.         The first attack took place aboutjSS 50 miles fromPort Said and the second about 100 miles from the same port.One ship was sunk on each occasion.         This incident demonstrates the danger attached tothe Mediterranean Route, a danger which was realised andwhich had led to the adoption of the longer route rlound thoCape,Naval Staff,   27:10:17.
LIST OF BRITISH, ALLIED AND NEUTRAL VESSELS SUNK BY ENEMY SUBMARINES, 17th - 20th OCTOBER 1917.



?  Nationality.             Name                    Remarks.



?   British              S.S. California           150&apos; N.W. Finisterre.

    

    British              S.S. Polvena   )

                         S.S. Manchuria )          Approaches to English Channel



    British              S.S. Adams                West of English Channel



    American             S.S. Antilles             250&apos; West of Ushant



    Norwegian            S.S. Altair               Approaches to Bristol Channel



?   British              S.S. Madura               Approaches to English Channel



    British              S.S. Amsteldam            Yorkshire Coast



    British              S.S. Calmus               Yorkshire Coast



    British              S.S. Togston              Yorkshire Coast



    British              S.S. Sten                 Approaches to Bristol Channel



    British              S.S. Hazlewood            English Channel



    Italian              S.S. Lorenzo              West of Gibraltar



    Italian              S.S. Anna Scotto          Mediterranean



?   British              S.S. Waikawa              West of English Channel



    British              S.S. Australdene          180&apos; N.W. Finisterre



    British              S.S. Pera                 Mediterranean



    British              S.S. War Clover           Mediterranean



    British              S.S. Good Hope            Mediterranean



    British              S.S. Elsiston             Mediterranean



    British              S.S. Gemma                Yorkshire Coast



?   Russian              S.S. Slavonic             Off Shetlands



    British              S.S. Collegian            Mediterranean



    British              S.S. Algarve              English Channel



    British              S.S. Colorado             West of English Channel



    Norwegian            S.S. Leander              Yorkshire coast



    Norwegian            S.S. Nitedal              Yorkshire coast.             

</content>
</cab>
