<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 340-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fW* Document \t the Property ef            taaj*-*ty&apos;e Government.)rCRET.2                              Operations              General Delme Radcliffe, Italy.              C.I.G.S., War Office.                                               Handed  in October 29th                                                   12.30 a.m.       506  October 28th.                As well as can be ascertained, situation to-day       is as  follows:- 3rd Army is withdrawing on to the line       Codroipo  Latisana.  Bridge-heads Have been established and       occupied  at Latisana Madrisio, and near Codroipo by the 25th       Army Corps under General Ravazzo,  Headquarters  of 3rd Army       have been transferred to Motta-DI-Livenza.  Command of 3rd       Army,  with which also 8th Corps  is returning, report it has       saved  some of  Its heavy artillery, and almost all its       medium and light artillery.   Intention is that  3rd Array       shall  occupy line Tagliamento River  long enough to allow       2nd  Army  to pass through and  reform  behind that  line.                2nd  Army H.Q. moved to Pordenone, 6th and 24th       Corps  reported to be retiring under  fairly satisfactory       conditions.  Line of the Torre have  been occupied by six       Brigades  under General Petiti-Di-Roreto, who thinks that       he can hold  it long  enough  to permit 6th and 24th Corps       to disengage themselves.  27th and especially 28th Corps       under General  Badoglio and  General Albriccl are reported       to be fighting their way back, successfully.  Two Cavalry       Divisions have been  sent to cover left flank as much as       possible.  To  facilitate retirement  of 2nd Army north  of       Codroipo, bridge-heads have been established at Santodoricc       and Pinzano where  ore the  three  fresh divisions referredulated  to in my telegram 505  charged with duty of protecting  thisnet     flank and the  passage  of the river.  Retirement along  all .17.       roads of the columns of transport,  is prooeeding, without       panic, in a quiet  and orderly fashion.  Although mass  of
transport etc, is very considerable, there has not beenattack by the enemy !s aircraft.   Enemy has also apparentlyno cavalry.   Understand that guns and cartridges of theBritish batteries have been saved, but not the shells.On the whole, situation seems to me to be rather lesshopeless than it might have been.   If during next 48 hours,retirement can proceed without serious interference fromthe enemy, a considerable portion of the army will be saved,but it is too early yet to judge as to this.   I saw Ministerof War to-day, who came to see Cadorna, also General Dallolioand General De Robilant, commanding 4*tJh Army.   Minister ofWar is hopeful of rousing the country to a sense of itspatriotic duty, and of making sufficient resistance on theline of the Piave or some other line during winter, toenable army to be reformed, re-supplied with much of thelost materiel, and to resume offensive in the spring.  lossof materiel very heavy and may amount to 1,000 or 1,200guns, but no accurate estimate can yet be made.   Two-thirdsof the ammunition supply in the country is still in thecentral depot, so that even if whole supply in the fieldwere lost, this would be only one-third of total amountavailable.   In the plains Italians hope to compensate tosome extent their inferiority in guns, by their great super-iority in aircraft.   Dallolio is hopeful of making good verysoon a large proportion of the lest artillery materiel.De Robilant has not yet begun retirement of 4th Army as itwill be a slow and difficult process to disentangle hisforce from the mountains. He hopes it may not be necessary.          Greater part of the Commando Supremo isestablished at Padua.  Intendenza Generale will probably
                     3.go to Monselioo, while Cadorna will remain at Trvisoa little longer to superintend occupation of the MonteGrappa-Fiave line.     General Staff thinks there are twelve German Divisionson Italian eastern front and that most  of these  are activelyengaged in the operations *   As to German concentration inthe Trentino, I have no further information yet.     Announcement of intention to send  British and Frenchtroops has given satisfaction and is  as  soon as  possibleto be communicated to the troops.
                                           SEC RE T.                   OPERATIONS .From: General Delme Radcliffe, Italy.       29.10.17.To:   C.I.G.S. War Office.                   12.45.a.m.507, 28.10.17.          Reference my telegram 505x. Cadorna has directedthat the four French Divisions shall go into the quadrilateralBASSANO-THIENE-VTCENZA-CITADELLA with the heads cf the fourDivisions on the line BASSANO-THIENE.  The Commanders of the1st Army and of 3rd Army Corps have teen directed that the&quot;best accommodation for H.Q. and staffs arriving in theirrespective commands shall he at once provided.        z Circulated to War Cabinet 29.10.17.

</content>
</cab>
