<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 531-535</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty^ Government.)bBALI&quot; GJ^Si/Mediterranean/ 2157.it9 -7 2           WAR CABINET,       L^jGen. Milne&apos;s DespatchMemorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State for War             I propose, if the War Cabinet see no objection,   to publish the attached Despatch from Lt.Gen Milne with   regard to the British operations in Salonica, subject to   the excision of the words enclosed in red brackets.                                          DERBY   31st October,1917.
  The Secretary of State for War has receivedthe  following   despatch   from  Lieutenant-General G. F. Milne, C.B., D.S.O., Command-ing-in-Chief, British Salonika Force;             General Headquarters,                 British Salonika Force.                        1st October, 1917.My Lord,  I have the honour to submit the  followingreport on the operations of the British Forces inMacedonia from 9th October., 1916, to the pre-sent date.  Since the  29th November,  1916,  when, inaccordance with General SarraiFs request, Itook over the sector then  held by the Italiantroops, the army under my  command has occu-pied the front covering Salonika from the eastand north, and extending from the mouth ofthe River Struma along the Tahinos-Butkova-Doiran lakes to the River Vardar, a distance ofapproximately ninety miles.  In addition, fromthe commencement of December until the endof February one infantry brigade was detachedto the neighbourhood of Katerini on the westernshores of the Gulf of Salonika.  The necessity of holding this long line placeda considerable  strain on the endurance of thetroops, especially during the  winter  months,when, owing to the unprecedented rainfall, themountain roads became almost impassable andrendered the question of supply one of consider-able difficulty, a difficulty overcome only by theenergy and determination of all concerned.  Inspite of the fact that the whole  of this force hasbeen in the line without relief  for over a year,with only occasional  limited opportunities fortraining and without the encouraging effects ofoffensive action, a very high standard of moraleand efficiency has been  maintained.  At the commencement of the period underreview, the role allotted to the British troopshad for its object the engaging of the enemyalong  the  front during the operations whichculminated in the capture of Monastir on the19th November. From that date onwards theadvent of  the  winter season,  accompanied asit was by heavy falls of snow  and rain, madeoperations, except on a  small scale, a matter ofconsiderable  difficulty owing to the paucity ofmetalled roads and the heavy nature of the soilin the valleys.  In the Struma River valley, since  the con-clusion of  the  operations reported in my lastdespatch, the  front  line had  been graduallypushed forward across the river so as to includethe localities of Ago Mah,  Homondos, Kalen-dra Woods,  Cuculuk, and  Elisan on the leftbank.    The mounted  troops, supported  byarmoured ears and contact aeroplanes, pushedtheir reconnaissances between  Seres and  LakeTahinos, and in places even succeeded in cross-ing the Demirhissar-Seres-Drama railway.  Meanwhile the enemy had been actively em-ployed behind their advanced positions in pre-paring a defensive line  along  the foothills onthe opposite side of the valley and had  occu-pied the large village of Barakli Dzuma anda line of trenches across the low ground fromSavjak to Butkova Lake.  In order to carry out my instructions andat the same time to strengthen  the left flank ofthe troops in the valley, I decided towards theend of October to capture Barakli Dzuma andto advance the whole line.   As a preliminarymeasure  the villages  of  Elisan-Kavdarmah-Ormanli-Haznatar  were occupied in  order toform a strong bridgehead within which bridgeswere thrown over the river, then considerablyswollen  by heavy rain.  In carrying out thisduty  under difficult circumstances the RoyalEngineers gained great credit for their  skilland rapidity in construction.  The attack itself,  admirably conceived  andskilfully executed by the troops^of the 28thDivision^ was carried out  after a  short bom-bardment on the morning of the 31st October,and was a complete success.   In  conjunctionwith other operations in the valley, some 350prisoners were taken.  Under cover of patrol encounters a defensiveline was constructed from Jenimah via OsmanKamila-Homondos-Jenikoj-Nevoljen-Cuculuk-Elisan-Barakli  Dzuma-Haznatar to Alipsa onthe Struma and remained  as such  during thewinter months.  At the commencement of  December the Greekregiment which  had co-operated in the valleyduring October and November  was withdrawnand transferred to another section of the Alliedline.  I much regret the severance of the cor-dial relations which had been established withthese gallant troops.  On the Doiran-Vardar front the commandwas faced with an entirely different situation,and minor operations undertaken with a viewto continually  harassing an enemy, stronglyentrenched in mountainous and rocky country,and to inflicting as  much loss as possible, both.in material  and in personnel, had of necessityto be  restricted to continual patrol  encounters,raids  and artillery bombardments.   The mostsuccessful of these  raids were  carried out bybattalions of the Welsh and  Cheshire Regi-ments on separate  occasions towards the endof October, when, after a heavy bombardment,the enemy&apos;s trenches were  attacked with greatdetermination and  gallantry and severe casu-alties inflicted.  During the month of November and the earlypart of  December these harassing  tactics werecontinued along both fronts, resulting, in theStruma valley, in the occupation of  the villagesof Kumli, Barakli and Prosenik,  where theRoyal Dublin Fusiliers captured practically thewhole garrison, and an advance  against theenemy&apos;s  positions in the vicinity of TumbitzaFarm.  Owing to the  decision  to withdraw  toanother  area the  Greek troops co-operatingwith us, I decided to discontinue the last-men-tioned operation.  The winter season had now fully set in, andthe frequent rains  had  rendered  the Strumavalley wet and heavy.   Problems of transportand communications became more difficult, andthe main Seres road,^he only  line of supplyto that  froirtywas  kept open  only with thegreatest  difficulty.   In the valley &quot;itself horsetransport had to be abandoned north of Orljak,and recourse had to light  railways, while thesudden rises of the river rendered communica-tion precarious, and necessitated considerablework in the construction of heavy bridges.  On the left bank  of the Vardar considerabledamage was inflicted on the enemy by a success-ful attack  on the night 26th/27th Novemberagainst  a portion of the ridge called &quot; Cretedes Tentes,&quot; lying to the north-east of Macu-kovo.  In spite of climatic difficulties, similaroperations with varying success  were conductedduring the ensuing months, resulting in con-tfnual loss to the enemy in-killed and prisoners.  During the early months of this year raidingtactics were.iurther. developed, and were carried
out with an increasing degree of success.  Bat-talions of the Suffolk Regiment, the Northum-berland Fusiliers, the Welsh Fusiliers,  and theDevonshire Regiment showed conspicuous skilland gallantry,  the  last-mentioned  during avery successful raid on the Petit Couronne hill,south of Doiran, inflicting severe loss on  theenemy, who counter-attacked in force.  By thismeans the co-operation  of  the artillery andengineers with &quot;the  infantry  was  constantlypractised and a high standard of offensive spiritmaintained in the Army.  Towards the end of February I received in-structions from the allied Commander-in-Chiefto be prepared to commence offensive operationsduring  the first week  of April.   The roleallotted  to the force under my command wasto engage the enemy on the Struma front andto the east of Lake. Doiran while making anattack in force west of that lake.  The time atmy disposal was short, more especially  as  theunusual  inclemency of the weather had reducedthe  Seres road to such  a state of mud  as  torender motor&apos; transport practically impossiblebeyond Likovan, and thus tended to delay theearly  commencement  of  operations  in  theStruma valley; but the sudden and unexpectedchange from intense wet  and cold to  unusualheat, which  took place  towards the  end ofMarch,  considerably facilitated  preparations.By the 10th of March the Corps on the left hadpushed forward for  a distance of 1,000 yardson a front of  3,500 yards, extending in a south-westerly direction from Horseshoe Hill, on theridge which forms the watershed between theDoiran Lake and the  Vardar Valley.    Thisridge, commonly called the &quot; P &quot; ridge, run-ning north into the  left centre of the  enemy&apos;sposition, rises to  a height of about 500 feetabove Horseshoe Hill, and dominates the wholecountry  between Doiran Lake and the  Vardar.On both flanks in front of Doiran, and oppositeMacukovo,- the Bulgariantrenches are pushedforward, forming strong bastions, with  flanksresting on Doiran Lake and the Vardar Riverrespectively.   These fortifications, which werelaid out when the Bulgarian army first arrivedon  the Greek frontier, are skilfully planned andwell executed, the trenches themselves beingcut out  of solid rock.   Situated some  800 yards in front   of&apos; theHorseshoe Hill, which formed the apex of thesalient between these two bastions, and about 11,000 yards north-east of Krastali village, ahostile advanced work called &quot;P.  4  &quot; formed avaluable observation station to the enemy, andits  capture was essential to  any further ad-Vance.   The front, therefore,  selected for theinitial attack, with  a view to threatening the approaches to Doiran town, extended from thewestern  shore  of  Doiran  Lake,  along the enemy&apos;s salient in front of the town,  to the crest of the &quot;P&quot; ridge.   Preparations for the offensive  were  com- pleted by 8th April,  but for various reasons the  Commander-in-Chief found it necessary to  postpone operations until 24th April, whenthe attack was launched after a bombardment of., the hostile positions extending over several days, which  elicited the fact that the  strength of  the opposing heavy artillery had been con- siderably increased during the interval.   The assaulting infantry succeeded in  enter- ing the  hostile trenches along the whole front attacked,.meeting everywhere with very severeopposition.  On.the right,  owing to the very %eayy.artmery.and.-trench mortar fire encoun- tered, more especially in the Jumeaux ravine, a deep and  difficult obstacle with steep 6ides which separated the opposing lines, only the leading troops were able to gam a footing, and reinforcements found the greatest difficulty  in advancing to their support.  During the night several determined hostile counter-attacks were repulsed with heavy loss, but eventually, after- several hours&apos; hard fighting, the attackers were forced back to their own trenches.  This opera- tion was carried out with the greatest gallantry and determination by representative battalions of English county regiments,  among whom the Devonshire Regiment and the Berkshire Regi- ment deserve special credit for &quot;their dash and tenacity.  &quot;   On the left all objectives were gained, and the enemy &apos;s front trenches occupied on a front of nearly a mile from Hill &quot; 380/&apos; five hun- dred  yards north  of the  ruins  of  Doldzelli village, to the enemy&apos;s work of Hill &quot; P. i^.&quot; During  the following days the captured posi- tion   was  consolidated  in spite of repeated counter-attacks, during which battalions of the Manchester Regiment and the Shropshire Light Infantry inflicted severe loss on the  enemy, who  fought with great determination.   Preparations had been commenced  with   a view  to taking advantage of the commanding position gained on the ridge by advancing our line  on its western slopes, when information was received  that, owing to climatic and other reasons, it had been found necessary again  to postpone the  Allied operations  on the right bank of the Vardar River and in the  vicinity of Monastir.    Finally,  I received  instruc- tions that the 8th May had  been selected  as the date for the re-commencement of the Allied advanee, on  which  date  the  army under my command should again concentrate&apos;&apos;its main effort in the vicinity of Doiran.   On this occasion it was decided to restrict the attack on the salient to the section lying be- tween the  lake  and the  &quot; Petit  Couronne &quot; Hill.  After a preliminary bombardment, the leading  troops  advanced, and  succeeded  in reaching  the enemy*s  trenches  under  very heavy artillery fire.  A battalion of the Argyll and  Sutherland Highlanders in the centre, ad- vancing in a most spirited manner, had not only commenced   consolidation  of  the   position gained, but had pushed forward to Red Scar Hill on their immediate  front, when, owing to counter-attacks both in front and in flank, they were compelled after severe hand-to-hand fight- ing, in which all  ranks greatly  distinguished themselves, to relinquish their position. Mean- while, the Oxfordshire  and  Buckinghamshire Light Infantry, supported by the  Berkshire Regiment, assaulted &quot;the eastern  end  of the ce Petit Couronne &quot; Hill, and, though  met  by heavy artillery  and  trench   mortar fire, re- peatedly returned to the attack with great de- termination.  After defeating several counter- attacks,  they succeeded  in establishing them- selves on the slopes of the hill, which they held tiH about mid-day of the 9th,  when   it was found  impossible  to  maintain the positions . gained.  The dash and gallantry exhibited by all ranks of  these two battalions is worthy  of high  praise.   On the western slopes of the Horseshoe Hill Ridge the attack succeeded in advancing to a depth of 500 yards on a front of two miles, and in seizing and occupying an important under- &apos; feature,  termed  Goldie&apos;s Hill, 2,000  yards-!&apos; south of DevedzihY&quot; The positions gained, after
being further increased on the 15th, and againon the  20th, were consolidated in spite of theenemy&apos;s  repeated  endeavours  to  recapturethem, and now form the main line of defence,which runs along the  ridge of hills from justsouth of Krastali village to Sejdelli village.  Meanwhile, operations  on  the Struma fronthad been held in abeyance pending the develop-ment of events in the west,  but,  on the 15thMay, the village of Kjupri was seized and held,and a series of - intermediate trenches betweenErnekoj and the River Struma were captured,about 100 prisoners being taken.    A furtheradvance was in progress when, on the 24th inst.,definite instructions were received from GeneralSarrail that offensive -operations were to ceaseall along the front.  As summer was commencing, I now had toconsider  the best means  of maintaining thehealth  and efficiency  of  the Army  during aperiod when malaria and dysentery are more orless prevalent in the low-lying areas.  In viewof the experience gained last year, and in spiteof the fact that a considerable amount of anti-malarial work  had been carried out  in thevalleys  during  the  winter,  I   decided  toabandon the forward positions on the right andcentre of the line, and to retire to the foothillson the right bank of the Struma River, and tothe south of the Butkova Valley.   All bridge-heads were garrisoned and arrangements madefor the vacated  area  to be daily  patrolled, anarduous duty, for the successful  carrying outof which during the whole summer the Derby-shire  and  Surrey   Yeomanry   deserve  thehighest commendation.  By  the 14th June thewithdrawal had  been  carried out  without inci-dent or interference by the enemy.   In accordance with my instruction, two  de-tachments were  despatched  during the monthof June  to  co-operate with  the French inthe occupation of old Greece.  One detachmentwas placed under the orders of General Reg-nault at  the Piraeus  and in  Corinth.    Thesecond, under those of General Venel, in Thes-saly.   These detachments  returned  in thecourse  of the next six weeks.   In spite of the intense heat experienced dur-ing  July  and  August,  during   which lattermonth the mean temperature was 5 deg. in ex-cess of that of last year, minor encounters withthe enemy have been of almost daily occurrence,among the most successful being a raid on thevillage of Homondos by battalions of the RoyalScots and the  Scottish  Horse, when 35 pri-soners were taken  and  two guns destroyed.Another small raid by the Lancashire Fusiliers,when the number of  enemy killed was nearlydouble the strength of the raiding party, formsa good example of the spirit which permeatesall ranks.  In all operations which have takenplace  the co-operation of the Royal Artillery and Field Companies, Royal Engineers,  hasbeen of a high standard.   During the  past  year the  Royal  FlyingCorps  has rendered very efficient service.  To-wards the end of February the hostile  aircraftwere reinforced  by a  powerful bombing squad- ron, and  it is due to  the unaided efforts of the Royal Flying Corps that but little damage was caused in the British area.   Towards the end of  April,  the  Vice-Admiral   Commanding Eastern Mediterranean Squadron kindly placed at my disposal bombing and fighting machines of the Royal Naval Air Service, by whose wel- come assistance complete mastery  of the air was obtained during the May operations.   During the  summer months  almost daily  bombing attacks have been made on the various hostile railheads and encampments,  and in the nume- rous air combats which have taken place our pilots have  shown marked gallantry  and skillnh spite of the superiority in pace and climJaing^&quot;power  of the hostile machines on this  front/   I  am greatly  indebted to  the  Army Signal Service for the efficient manner in which their worK &quot;has been carried out  over such a large extent of  country.   The  maintenance of communications has been one  of my most difficult tasks.  To-appreciate- fully the  work done under  this.heading it is necessary to realise what f abilities existed in the winter of 1915-1916, and compare them with those that now  obtain.  In  1915, apart from two  partially-metalled roads, one to  Monastir and  one to Seres both of which were in a de- plorable  condition no roadway possible  for mechanical  transport existed.  Now these two roads have, by constant work, been improved out  of all knowledge,  widened  and  drained; cross-roads  have been cut through the hills; new roads  in  base  and  forward  areas con- structed and old roads re-made; while the con- struction of a further main route from Salonika to Kukus, and thence to the fronts  on either.- side of Lake Doiran, has rendered  dependence on the Doiran  railway  no  longer  essential. Moreover, the winter of 1916-1917 was excep- tionally wet, and the difficulty of  road main- tenance correspondingly increased,  the absorb- ent  nature of  the soil in many parts  of the Seres  road  especially  causing- portions  of the roadway to disappear  after  prolonged spells of snow and rain.  Determined efforts on the part of the Royal Engineers and of the  infantry working with them, however, successfully  pre- vented interruptions of any length in the supply machinery.    The expansion of hospitals, erection of hut- ments, improvements in landing facilities,  pro- vision of water supply, &amp;c,  have thrown heavy work on the Engineer services at the base, but satisfactory results have been achieved.    The railway directorate has been fully occu- pied with  the  construction of new standard gauge as well as Decauville lines, with the im- provement  and maintenance of existing tracks and in the  formation of railheads.    The dock system,   too,  has  been supplemented,  and rapidity of transit largely increased.    Recently, further transit facilities at  this port have  been  acquired,  consequently the speed  of  off-loading ships  has been  quick- ened  up,  and  the  military   landing  staff. under  the  Base Commandant  have turned to the best advantage alb the resources now at their  disposal.    The system adopted for the clearance of docks and quays works well and smoothly.    To the Principal  Naval Transport  Officer  Commodore F.  Travers,  R.N. and  to his  assistants, my thanks  are due for their unfail- ing  co-operation in all matters relating to em- barkation and disembarkation.    During the past year the supply of the troops has  proceeded satisfactorily, in  spite of the  attendant difficulties.  During the worst of the  winter the work devolving on the drivers of the  mechanical transport was arduous  and trying,  but all ranks displayed the greatest  zeal and  cheerfulness in the performance of their duties.    It is satisfactory to be able to record that the  wastage amongst the  animals of this  force, in  spite of the heavy strain during the winter, has  been  exceptionally  low.    The supply  of  all
material to the troops necessitates the use ofboth wheeled  and pack  transport, while thetracks  branching outwards  from  the   mainroutes,  although  in  dry  weather providing agood running surface,  are, in the majority ofcases, deep in mud  after  prolonged  snow orrain.   The calls on horse flesh have hence beensevere, and it speaks well for the Army  Vete-rinary  Services that the mortality  and losethrough wastage  has been kept to  such  a lowfigure.  Valuable work has,  too, been performed bythe  Remount  Department,  and the institu-tion of  convalescent  depots  for   debilitatedanimals has proved a  success.  The  Ordnance Services, under Brigadier-General Sir C. M. Mathew, K.C.M.G.,  C.B.,D.S.O., whose departure I much regret, havebeen most ably conducted, and skill and fore-thought have been shown in the establishmentof workshops  for the  manufacture of articlesordinarily sent from overseas.  The Army Postal Department has continuedits  unostentatious methods of collection anddelivery of postal matter,  and is deserving ofhigh praise for the successful manner in  whichit has overcome  all  obstacles.  The  work of the Army Pay Department hasbeen most satisfactorily  performed.  Financial transactions in  this  area  are attimes somewhat  complicated,  and my thanksare due to the  Financial Adviser ColonelA.  B. Beavis for his able assistance  in alldetails connected with finance.  The Allied  organisations referred to  in mydespatch of the  8th October 1916, viz.,  theCustoms Control  and the Claims CompensationCommissions have  performed  most  usefulwork.    The  machinery  adopted  has  beenthoroughly tested, and has proved  reliable andefficient.  A word of praise is  due to the Officer Com-manding and Staff of the Expeditionary ForceCanteen.  Every effort  to meet the require-ments  of the troops has been made, and energyhas been displayed in the management andconduct of this institution. .  The health of the  troops  has been on  thewhole  satisfactory.  With the advent  of  thecold weather malaria  abated rapidly, and thesick rate remained low during the winter.  Pre-parations for the next summer in  the form ofanti-malarial work were  however steadily pur-sued, drainage of swamps and canalisation ofstreams were extended,  and  the personnel fortechnical work strengthened; but what provedof almost greater importance was  the instruc-tion of all ranks in the value  of field sanitationand the prevention of disease  in the field.  Theresults  have been most satisfactory, and, whilegiving full credit to the various ranks of  themedical services and to the devoted band  ofnursing-sisters,  I  consider  that  the  greatdiminution in disease in this Army as comparedwith last summer is due chiefly to the fact thatthe  value of  preventive measures  is fuliyrealised by all ranks, and that the whole Armyhas profited by the experience of last year.  The arrangements for retaining all 6ick  andwounded  in  this theatre have  worked mostsatisfactorily,  and the  decision has,  in  myopinion, much to recommend it.  The arrivalof sufficient  transport and the  opening up ofnew roads has permitted  the  establishmentin the hills of hospitals and convalescent camps,where, under trained instructors, convalescentsare put through a graduated course of physicaldrill  before  returning to the depots.  As regards the general work of the RoyalArmy  Medical  Corps   and  the  assistanceafforded by the British Red Cross Society  andthe Order of St. John,  I can  only reiteratethe remarks  contained in my last despatch.  I desire to take this opportunity of placingon record  my appreciation of  the  very highstate  of discipline and efficiency  maintained byall  ranks of this Army  under what are, attimes, trying and arduous conditions, alwaysborne with loyalty and cheerfulness.  My thanks are due to Vice-Admiral Sir CecilThursby,  K.C.M.G., and to the officers  andmen of the Royal Navy and  R.N.A.S. underhis orders, for  their close co-operation  andready assistance at all times, more especially onthe occasion of the landing of troops at Kateriniunder difficulties, and during operations in thevicinity of the mouth of the Struma River.  Finally, I  desire to bring to your LordshipVnotice the good  services  rendered during thepast eighteen months by my  two former staffofficers,  Major-General   W.  Gillman,  C.B.,C.M.G., D.S.O.,  and Major-General  T raversClarke, C.B., the latter of whom had been withthis force since it first landed, and both of whomhave  lately been transferred to  other  theatresof war, and  by Surgeon-General Sir  H.   R.Whitehead, K.C.B., whose tactful administra-tion has been fully appreciated  by our Allies,and with whom I part with much regret.  I propose  to submit,  in due course,  a list ofthe names of those officers, non-commissionedofficers and men  whose distinguished and  gal-lant services I consider specially deserving ofmention and&apos;reward.     I have the honour to be,             My Lord,      Your Lordship&apos;s obedient servant,                            G.  F. Milne,       Lieu tenant-General, Commanding-in-          Chief, British Salonika Force.

</content>
</cab>
