<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 610-610</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
senof puojoQ(This Document It the Property  ofHis Britannic MajestyGovernment,)  ORT relating to  the War Work of the Board of Agriculture for    Scotland  for the week  ending 31st October, 1917.food Production.    During the,week the weather has been fairly suitable for potatolifting and ploughing but there have been few opportunities ofsecuring the grain  that  is  still standing in the fields.  A consider-able quantity  of oats  is reported to be standing out in the South eetern part of Scotland and in some of the higher districts.1. Compulsory  Orders under  Defence of the Realm Regulation 2. If.    The Board have issued  an Order under Section (l) (e) of this egulation requiring the occupier of the farm of West Cambus, Alloato put at least 50  acres of the farm under grain crop.2. Agricultural Tractor  and Plough Demonstration.    The third and  last  of  the series of demonstrations of tractorsand ploughs organised  by the Highland &amp; Agricultural Society was arried out at Perth on  26th and 27th October and proved to be assuooessful as  the previous  exhibitions at Edinburgh and Glasgow. Theimmense development in Tractor ploughing was fully demonstrated andthe exhibition has  been  of value to the cause of Food Produotion.  Corn Produotion  Act 1917 .    In view of representations received as to the difficulty ofrepresent at issa from the counties of Orkney and Shetland attending eetings of the District Stages Committee to be formed for theDistrict No. (l) including the oountiea of Shetland, Orkney, Caith-iieas and Sutherland as specified in the Board&apos;s Memorandum of 22ndSeptember  (3ee Report dated 26th September 1917), the Board haveagreed to make special arrangements for this District under whichthe business of the Wages Committee may be delegated largely tofour Sub-Committees, one operating within each county.I- Agricultural Employment  (Scotland) Order 1917.    Under Section 41 AAA of the Defence of the Realm Regulationsthe Board  have issued an Order detailing the procedure  to beadopted  in giving effect to the terms  of the above Regulation  inthe case of persons ceasing to be employed  in Agriculture.Heoruitinq in Agriculture.Military Service Acts 1916.    The number of certificates  issued to date by the Board  inconnection with the scheme  for vouching agricultural workers is asfollows              Areac.           Certificates  Issued.           Aberdeen...............     191           Ayr......&apos;,.............      34           Berwiok-on-Tweed.......     582           Fort George............     371           Glenoorse,.............     763           Hamilton...............     169           Inverness..............      98           Perth..................     219           Stirling...............     102Total.   2,529

</content>
</cab>
