<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 611-617</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Thit Document is th* Property ofHis Britannic !Mtajesty&apos;&amp; Government.)GOVERNMENT  BUILDING  CONTRACTS *Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and&apos;W! the Minister of National Service.     &quot;We desire to obtain at the earliest possible moment thodirection of tho War Cabinet on the subject of the supply oflabour for the building works already started and about to bostarted by the Government Dopartments.     At tho present time a largo number of building works ofvarious kinds have been undertaken by different GovernmentDepartments.   Some of these are being carried out directlyby the Government Departments, but the majority have beenplaced with the big contractors.   Tho decision of the WarCabinet to expand the Air Services has already added to thonumber of undertakings in hand, and will greatly increase thenumber in the near future.   At tho samo time large demandsarc being made in connection with the extension of existingand the construction of new shipyards.     Even if the fullest use is made of all labour availablein the building, trade, it is impossible,  in our opinion, tocomplete in a reasonable time the wholo of the building pro-grammes of the various Government Departments, and&apos; we under-stand that other Government Departments concur in this view.It is, therefore, essential that the War Cabinet should decidethe general lines of priority to be accorded to these under-takingsj 1 and that the Ministry of Labour and the Ministry ofNational Service should be in a position to supply the WarCabinet with sufficient information to enable thorn to arriveat a decision.
    Further,  the  system of  placing  contracts  almostexclusively with  big contractors  makes  it  impossible  toobtain full use of  the  labour  in  the  building trade.   Thesmall bmilder retains his workmen and employs them on smallcivil jobs, the greater number of which are unnecessary.The bulk of this  labour should be employed on Governmentcontract a;  but as  the  small builder  has no interest  inthe contract, he  does all he can  to retain his labour forhis own business.  This is  facilitated  by  the fact that anybuilding operation  under  500  $an be  carried  out without alicense.     The result is  that the Government  Contractors bidagainst each  other  for  the  labour already  on  Government work,and wages are thereby forced up without any correspondingbenefit to the Government,  a procedure  &quot;better suited to a^itfechapel auction than to the conduct of the State&quot;.  Infact the State actually loses  both  in money and in output,because many  working kours  are lost in  the migration  oflabour from one Government  undertaking  in  course of con-struction to  another.     In addition  to determining the general lines of  priorityto be accorded to competing undertakings,  it  is necessary  todevise a scheme which will  ensure that  all labour that canbe made available should be secured for Government work.     The Minister of National  Service has  already securedthe assent of the Employers of the  Central English BuildingTrades Committee  and the Scottish Central  Building TradesCommittee to  the  following  proposal,  which was submittedto them, subject  to the agreement of  the Government Depart-ments concerned  and the final  approval  of  the ?rar Cabinet:-
    (a)  That the National Federation of Building Trade       Employers in England and the National Service Joint       Building Trade Committee in Scotland should act as       agents of the Government for  he distribution of       building contracts.    (b)   That  a full statement of these contracts should       be  communicated In confidence1 to a small HJommilrtee       composed of  representatives dt the Federation in       England  and  of the Joint Committee in Scotland, who       would refer  them to  the local Federation,, or Local       Joint Committee of the district in which the con-       tract is to  be carried out.    (c)    That the Local Federation or Local Joint       Committee should arrange for a suitable contractor  -       or  group of  contractors to undertake the work, and       become responsible- to the Government, thereby  *       securing that the resources bf the district In men       and plant should, be  pooled in the Government interest.    (d)    That the Local Federation or Committee should       treat on exactly the same footing every firm whether       federated or not.   We therefore ask .the War Cabinet to approve the followingproposals:-     (1)    All Government  Departments shall forthwith make          a return  to the Minister of National Service          showing all building contracts already undertaken,          giving short particulars of the  work, the stage          of completion reached, the estimated cost&apos;, and,          if possible, the  approximate number of men          employed  or required.
(2)   The Minister of  National  Service  in consultation     with the Minister of  Labour  will  report  to  the War     Priorities Committee  the  extent to  which the pro-     grammes  of the various Departments  can be carried     out, assuming that the proposals  outlined below for     mobilising In the Government interest all available     labour in the building trade are  followed.(3)   The War  Priorities Committee shall  determine whether     any and  if so what classes  cf Government building     undertakings are to be postponed  altogether for tho     time being and the relative  priority to  be  accorded     to such  of the various classes of building  undert&amp;k-     ings as  are to be continued.(4)   For the  purpose  of carrying  out building contracts,     the country shall be  divided into districts, corres-     ponding  with the existing areas for which Local&quot;Feder-     atlons exist, subject to  any further subdivision that     may be necessary.(5)   All future Building Contracts of  Government Depart-     ments shall be referred to  the local Federation of     the District in  which tho work is to be  carried out     and the  local Federation  will arrange for a contract-     or or group of contractors to undertake  the work.(6)   Any outstanding  contracts which are entitled to     priority under the decisions of the War  Priorities     Committee,  but which  cannot  be  completed owing to     the inability of the  contractor  to procure labour     shall be reconsidered with a view to the  introduc-     tion by  the local Federation of other contractors     who would combine their resources with those of the     original contractor.
A Committee of employers and workmen in eachDistrict s hali-nave&quot; ^oTOjrr&quot;i;o-JFix the standardrates of pAy to be paid on all ^Gc^vornmorcrtvc^^contracts in that district.   The rates so fixedshall be-sanctioned by the Government Departmentwith whom the contract has been made,: and failingagreement or sanction, shall be roferred as a&quot;difference&quot; under the Munitions of War Acts, tothe Ministry of Labour^The authority to g^ant building licenses for privatework shall be transferred from the Ministry of Muni-tions tc the Ministry of National Service,   Thelimit shall be reducedf rom  500 to  100; and theMinister of National Service shall have power toreview all existing licenses.   The necessary legalsteps to effect transfer of this authority and makeamendments of existing regulations to be taken im-mediately.Undertakings of a strictly military or navalcharacter in out of the way districts for whichcivilian labour is not available should be carriedout by 1    Military Works Companies;   but it isimportant that in.such cases military and civilianlabour should not be  mixed.G. H, ROBERTS.A. C GEDDES,
                                                           4f 4G. T. 2479.In view of the decision of the War Priorities Committeeto appoint a Building Priority Sub-Committee to go intotho question of the building programme and to report tothe Committee with a view to securing proper priorityin regard to labour and material for the construction ofnew buildings, it does not appear expedient that theproposals contained in the above memorandum should bebrought before the ^ar Cabinet until the matter has beenconsidered by the War Priorities Committee. As, however,the paper raises questions with regard to standardizingrates of pay and pooling of Government contracts whichare not raised on the Hinute of the War Priorities Oom-mittee, it is circulated for information.
                    *.  5  -   (?)  A Committee of employers and workmen in each        District shall have power&quot;to fix the standard        rates of pay to be paid on all Qoyo3T^itc^V^i3^tn^. .        contracts in that district.   The rates so fixed        shall be sanctioned by the Government Dopartment        with whom the contract has been made, and failing        agreomcnt or sanction, shall be referred as a        &quot;difference&quot; under the Munitions of War Acts, to        the Ministry of Labour,   (8)  The authority to grant building licenses for private        work shall be transferred from the Ministry of  Muni-        tions to the Ministry of National Service,    The        limit shall be reducedf rom  500 to  100; and the        Minister of National Service shall have power to        review all existing licenses.   The necessary legal        steps to effect transfer of this authority and  make        amendments of existing regulations to be taken  im-        mcdiately.   (9)  Undertakings of a strictly military or naval        character in out of the way districts for which        civilian labour is not available should be  carried        out by &apos;    Military Works Companies;  but it is        important that in such cases military and civilian        labour should not be mixed.                                            G.  H. ROBERTS.                                            A.  C. GEDDES.2,11.17.

</content>
</cab>
