<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 652-656</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/. *t o w(Thig Docum^^t \% *hs Prophsrty ofHj* Britannic XafcrtW. Qovemm*j479 3   intelligence Bureau,Department of Information,        FIYf/016.          W-3KLY  KEPOHT  01?   ITALY?  XVI/                (Nov. lat  1917)  Trustworthy data for a judgement  on  the  causes,  extent and effects  the recent lamentable disaster on the  Italian  front are at present [eking.   There are probably well-founded  grounds  for believing that  was some Piedmontese troops  (among whom  the  Giolittian element is jrong and who had not behaved  well  during  the  Turin riots) that gave iy on the left of the Italian  front;   but  without  further informa- ion it is unsafe to dogmatise.   We therefore  defer comment.  Meanwhile it could only be termed unfortunate  if any section of cur ress should, as it seems already inclined  to do, without definite aformation, make comments on the situation such  as might alienateItalian sympathies at the moment when solidarity  between the Allies[s most essential and spoil the good impression created by thepounced decision of the British and French Governments at once to end considerable forces to the support of  Italy.    This would be&quot;specially regrettable in view  of the somewhat  ambiguous internal ...lituation created by the recent Cabinet crisis  ana  its solution.^Parliamentary Situation.  The fr.ll  of  the Boselli  Ministry has for some time been regarded asinevitable.    It  was  attacked both from front and rear - by theinterventionists  who  accused  it  of lack of cohesion and energy and*o doubted  its capacity and  will to deal effectively with the paci-fist agitation;   by the  Giolittians and Socialists who nrofessed todetect in  it$ reactionary tendencies^ desire to evade Parliamentarycontrol and  to  delegate  to  the Military authorities functions whichProperly belong to the Civil,    The objective of the former attack
mQ Boselli and the older Ministers and  Orlando  in his capacity ofMinister of the Interior; the latter attack was  directed ageinst theMinistry as a whole and, on the part of  the official  Socialists,against Bissolati in particular.  Canepa&apos;s speech on the 20th Oct. in which  he  explained at lengththe reasons for the failure of the Food  Control  Department and defen-ded his ov/n actions, was very damaging to  the Government.    In fact helaid upon the Government the chief ehareof the responsibility for thebreak-down which had occureed.    Just at the  most  critical moment -when ov/ing to defective crops and inadequate  importations the need -  &apos;arose for apportioning supplies and requisition  of grain - theCommittee of 5 Ministers, under which the  Commissariat had been placed by the Decree of Jan. 16th, 1917, struck  work and left him to dealsingle-handed not only with the task of  requisition and provincialrationing (contingentamento) but  with the  reorganisation of the wholeadministrative machinery.   The Committee, disgusted  by the consistentrejection or neglect of all its proposals  by  the Cabinet,  had refused                                             i.to co-operate longer and had met  for the last time on July 7th.  Canepa was followed by Signor  lUtti,  who obtained  a notable successby an extremely clever 3peech, in which, while professing to take anentirely impartial view of the situation,  he  virtually placed himselfat the head of the hitherto leaderless  &quot;Parliamentary Group&apos;.    Hepointed out that it was mad and foolish  to talk, as the Socialists cAid, of Revolution, when it was obvious  that  Revolution would involvethe cutting off of the foreign supplies  on which Italy depended for hervery existence.   But the Socialists did not  really aim at Revolution,and others were equally to blame  for the internal  discontent whichexisted and for sowing the seeds  of revolution.    It  was high time toPut an end to the feud between Minority  (Interventionist)  andMajority (Giolittian)   A strong  Government was  needed whose watchword
must be &quot;Maintenance of public order  combined  with tolerance&quot;.   The general applause which the  speech  secured seemed to show thatthe theme wr.s acceptable to the majority  of  Deputies.   This was mrde clearer still by  the equrlly  f: vour-ble receptiongiven on Oct. 22nd to Signor Orlando&apos;s defence of his  administration.His speech was practioally an endorsement of Signor Hitti&apos;s thesis, areaffirms tl on of his faith in tolerance rnd  respect for civil libertiesif not a renunciation of the stronger policy of repression which theBoselli Government had apparently  accepted under pressure of theInterventionists and of events.   Baron SonninoTs declaration on  foreign policy delivered on the 25th,in the course of which he dealt very  fully and very severely ^ith thePapal Note, had little bearing on  the Parliamentary situation and neednot be noticed in  this connection.   (The  speech is well and fullysummarised in the Daily Review of  the Foreign  Press for Oct. S9th)   On the 26th the resignation of  the Cab^inet was announced in theChamber and the sittings were adjourned pending the solution of thecrisis.   A Ministry is reported to have  been formed  under the Presidency ofSignor Orlando.   According to the list published in the 1 Times1 Nov,l,eleven members of the retiring Cabinet are included in the new,  of whomnine retain their former offices viz    Signor Orlando   President of Council and Minister of Interior,      &quot;   Sonnino    Foreign Affairs.      &quot;   Colosimq^  Colonies1    Admiral Del Baono   Marine.    General Dall Olio   Arms and  !;!unitions.    Signor Fera      Posts and Telegraphs       &quot;   Bianehi   Transport.       ,?   Sacchi    Justice       &quot;   I-Ieda      Finance.    Signor Bissolati receives a portfolio - that of Public Assistancel*d Pensions while General Alfieri,  the recently appointed FoodController, takes the place of General Gi^rdino at the WEr Office.
    The new members of the Ministry are      Signori Nitti     Treasury-in place of S. Carcano.         &quot;    Berenini  Public Instruction - in place of  Signor                                                   Huffini.         &quot;    Dari      Public Works 9 in place of Signor fconomi.         &quot;    Miliani   Agriculture - in place of Signor  Raineri.         &quot;    ciuffelli Industry, Commerce and Labour - in place                                          Of Signor De Nava.  ;KV?recaeting in our last week&apos;s report the possible alternatives  in  ^of the Boselli Cabinet being overthrown we said that  the  ohoice ay  between (1) A Giolittian Government relying en pacifist groups  and nspired by an anti-British animus and a desire to save the German fimectlon (2) a Ministry pledged to .a policy of  thorough&apos; both on he  external and internal fronts, which would of course have to rely ainly on the Interventionist groups, including the Liberal Right,  the tronghold of Salandrars supporters.  This statement requires some qualification.   A Government  such s has now been formed,  rn&amp;y containing five new Ministers in  postsof purely internal importance, and in which Baron Sonnino  retains thecontrol of Foreign Affairs, obviously cannot introduce any new de-parture or new attitude in Italy&apos;s relations with her Allies.Moreover Signor Orlando, it must be remembered, in his speech  deliveredat Palermo in November 1915, definitely accepted and emphasised thenecessity for Italy&apos;s complete solidarity with the Allies.   &quot;Italy&apos;swar&quot;, he said, &quot;though emminently national is necessarily  bound upwith and welded to the international war&quot;.   There could be&quot;noisolated victory, no separate peace, but only complete observanceof the principle *All for one and one for all1&quot;  At the same time the presence of Signer Nitti in the new Governmentand the position taken up by Signor Orlando in his speech  on the 23rdmake it fairly clear that the new Cabinet will have to rely forsupport on a majority composed of Deputies who are still loyal toGiolitti and still hope for a restored Giolittian regime,  Clerioals
  [friendly to Giolittism, and official Socialists.    &quot;That this may  [eventually lead to is fairly clearly indicated by the Radical Secolo  (in its leading article of Oct. 22nd, where it is  said that Signor  lUitti &apos;s friends are triumphant over the complete  accord established  between Signor Uitti and Signor Orlando, believing that the former,  as author and representative of the policy of conciliation and un-  ibampered by any connection with juseu&apos;au boutistee,  will prove to be  the predominant partner in the dual alliance and  will eventually  supplant in the Premiership Orlando, who is identified with Inter-  [ventionism and with the recent measures of repression.  The Austro-German Advance.    Meanwhile the great reverse now suffered on the Isonzo front and  the cordial co-operation of the Allies in the effort to repair it will,  as far as one can tell, have the double effect of uniting Italian  parties  and of drawing Italy closer to her Allies.  If this should prove to be the case4 it will merely be  one mere  instance of German miscalculation of foreign mentality.    Bor there  is little doubt that the mainjobject of the Austro-German advance was  to cause a revolution in Italy and to profit by the  ensuing chaos[I in order to enforce peace-terms on that country before  proceeding to  deal with Prance-fe exposed flank.    It is too early to judge of the effect,  but,  so^far,  all reports  point to the closing up of the political ranks and to  the oonosal  of an united front to the enemy.

</content>
</cab>
