<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/30/0 images: 711-723</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
        (This f&amp;apumaai it the Property^of         i i II in HIIIB in MI m. i jiljujwwiiiniiiiiiii i n ttm ^ITTJ--Mfii WWLFTRN imi n i i miwn .. i        His Sritannic  Majesty&apos;* Government,)MINISTEY   OF   FOOD.Eeport for Week ending  Wednesday, October 31,  1917.                        PART  I.-ACTION  TAKEN.                       CONTROL  OF SUPPLIES AND PRICES.    Allied Purchases. Requirements of. the British, French, and Italian Governmentshave been sent out to the Allied Provisions Export Commission for hog products upto December and during next year.    Mr.  Owen Smith has reported that  he  anticipates being able to fill all theserequirements, with a possible shortage of lard.    The terms on which the Allied Provisions Export Commission should be allowedto make purchases in America on behalf of the Inter-Allied Meat and Fats Executivehave been discussed with the Treasury, who are anxious that, before definite purchasingarrangements are concluded, dollar credits should be made available in New York bythe respective purchasing Allies.    Bacon, Hams, and Lard. Returns of  stocks of lard have now been received, andthe question of requisitioning unsold stocks or allowing  a further increase in the priceis under consideration.    The scheme of distribution of bacon, hams, and lard was discussed at a conference&apos;with wholesale and retail traders.  The main  lines of the scheme have been settled.An Order fixing maximum prices has been prepared.    About 27,000 boxes of bacon  have been purchased during the week on Govern-ment account.   The total arrivals are 11,278 boxes of which approximately 3,700 havebeen allotted to&apos;the Army, the same quantity to the civilian population, the remainderremaining unallotted.    Butter. The purchase of Argentine butter has been increased by 750 tons to atotal of 7,620  tons at 70s. per cwt. f.o.b.   Negotiations  are still in progress  for  thepurchase of 15,000 tons of New Zealand butter.    The Butter (Maximum Prices)  Order  (No. 4), 1917, has been issued prescribingmaximum first-hand prices of butter to be enforced on and after October 26th, 1917.The adjustment made in the prices of Colonial and  other imported  butter is  in viewof the arrival  of several shipments from New Zealand, and will have  the effect ofplacing the different varieties of butter,, except French and Danish, on a parity.    A scheme which should effect a substantial reduction  in the price of Danishbutter will shortly be put into operation.    The Butter (Maximum Prices) Amendment Order, 1917, was issued on October 31stto come into force on November 4th, 1917.  Its provisions allow a second wholesalera small profit, and govern wholesale and retail transactions in butter not specified inthe Schedule.  It allows alternative charges for blended butter, and wholesalers andretailers who carry butter in their  own vans are permitted to charge fid. per cwt. for10 miles, and Is. per cwt. for more  than  10 miles.  Retailers  who blend their ownbutter may charge 4s. per cwt. for blending.  It is made  clear, that all prices in theButter  Order  include  charges  for wrapping and packages,  and that retailers mustexhibit a list of the varieties and prices of butter offered for sale.  Catering businessesare exempted from the provisions of this Order.     Cheese. An offer has been accepted for the purchase of 15,000  tons of Australiancheese at 9d  per lb. f.o.b., but the details of the arrangement have not yet beensettled.     Dried  Fruits.-Instructions  have  been given to the  Buying  Commission  inGreece to purchase 10,000 tons of currants for November shipment.   Arrangementshave been made for the shipping of 400 tons out of the 850 tons already purchasedby this Ministry.     Negotiations are  still proceeding between the Foreign Office  and the SpanishGovernment on the subject of the importation of raisins into the United Kingdom.     The Portuguese Government having removed the prohibition on the export offigs in favour of the quantity required hj this Ministry, instructions have been cabledto our Portuguese representative to purchase 2,000 tons  of dried figs.     A (33)4299-1 Pk 1 60 11/17  E &amp; S                                           ASECRET.
     Fresh Fruit and&apos; Jcwn.-Purchases have  been made of 200,000. half. chests oforanges  for shipment  during the next three months from Spain.  These  will  beconverted into  marmalade for consumption, by the Navy and Army as well as by thecivilian  population.  When the cost of the fruit freight and insurance is  ascertaineda  Marmalade  Order will  be prepared fixing  maximum prices  for the makers andretailers; . .  ..  -  .      : \ &apos;&apos;.   -To.-&apos;&quot;  *-  &apos;-   &quot; &apos;-\   &apos;-&apos; &apos;:.;&apos;V&apos;-&apos;&quot;?J       *&apos;      - ;     Requests have been received from various  Fruit Associations asking for somemodifications of the restrictions on imports of apples.  In view, however, of  tonnagescarcity, these requests have had to be refused.     Feeding Stuffs. Meetings have been held this week of the Flour Mills  ControlCommittee, which is anxious that the price  of  millers&apos;  offals should  be fixed.  AnOrder  is being drafted fixing maximum prices  for  cattle cakes and meals  and formillers&apos; offals, and it is proposed to issue this as soon as possible.     Fish.-The Treasury have declined to sanction  the contemplated  purchase ofNorwegian sardines.     The embargo  on canned salmon  has been removed, and it is hoped that largequantities of  this commodity, especially  oi  Siberian canned  salmon,  will  now beimported into this country.   .  Flour and Bread.-In view of the Cabinet, assent to Lord Rhondda&apos;s proposal toreduce the price of potatoes to bakers so as to make their use in bread attractive froma  financial point of view,  a scheme is under consideration by which  bakers willindent on their local food committees for weekly supplies ;  these indents  will  bepooled by the  local food committees who will in turn indent every month  on  thePotato Section of the Ministry of Food ; the potatoes  will be delivered to the railwaystations specified  by the committees  through registered wholesale dealers in orderto ,save unnecessary carriage;  they  will  then  be  invoiced to the  bakers  by  thelocal committees.   The greater use of potato flour  should offset in some  degree theamount paid in subsidising the 9d. loaf.     Inland Transport and  Cold  Storage. In  dealing with  the question  of  railwaytransport in regard to  foodstuffs  the representatives at  the various ports have beenspecially useful in arranging to  deal  quickly with cargoes as they  arrive, with a viewto expediting the turn round of the ships.     The transport of potatoes has become  a  vital question ; the  Railway ExecutiveCommittee are being urged  to. stop less urgent traffic until the potatoes which havebeen held back are&apos; dealt with. -     Negotiations are in progress with regard  to the  provision of works, for  freezinghome-grown cattle at Cardiff, Manchester, Birkenhead, and Glasgow.  In regard toCardiff&apos;,  this,  accommodation will be ready  within  two weeks, and when TreasurySanction is received in regard to Manchester, Birkenhead, and Glasgow these placescan be fixed Avithin two months&apos; time..  The  only Government expenditure involved isin regard to  works for freezing  home-grown  cattle  and cold storage accommodationin the Devonport Dockyard.     Meat. Model scales of  retail meat  prices  have  been issued, based  on  themaximum wholesale dead meat price for November, and have been forwarded to LocalFood Control Committees both in London and  throughout the country.     A  meeting of the Central Advisory Committee on Live Stock  and Meat Supplieswas held at Palace Chambers on October 30th,  at which was discussed the draft Meat(Control) Order providing for the registration of wholesale  and retail meat  dealers,keepers of slaughter-houses, and other persons engaged in the cattle and meat trades.The  draft, order also provides for the licensing of stock auctioneers  and cattle dealers,,and will  supersede. Part I. of the Meat (Sales) Order.     A mass meeting of Smithfield Market Tenants and other  members of  the LondonMeat Trade, was held at the Butchers&apos; Hall, Bartholomew Close, E.C., on Wednesday,October 31st, at the suggestion of  Mr.  Boys, Director,  of Meat Supplies.  A resolutionwas  passed authorising the Committee to take&apos; steps  towards forming  a LondonWholesale Meat Supply Association, and approving of the appointment &quot;by. the Ministryof Food of a Wholesale. Meat Traders&apos;  Advisory Committee with a Secretary and Staff,continuously attached to it at the Ministry of Food, to, carry out such duties as  may beallotted, to them by the Ministry of Food &quot;in connection with the: Wholesale Meat Trade.A further resolution was carried to the effect that  the names of the suggested membersof the proposed Advisory Committee should be  submitted to the Ministry of Food.
\  ,.. Milk:-TJte Milk Factories (Restriction) Order, 1017,  dated October 21, 1917,limits trie - amount of milk taken  by - any factory for  making milk; p roducts. to theamount taken either  on  August 31st, 1917, or on December 31st, 1916, whicheveramount be greater.   This measure has been taken in order to ensure as full a supplyas possible of liquid milk for the civil population, and also to safeguard the needs ofthe Army  and Navy as well as of the civil populatioa with regard to condensed milk.    Oil Seeds-Tlio restricted supply of oils and seeds now coming forward indicatethat it will become necessary to obtain more freight room for these commodities ifthe necessary quantities required for the manufacture of glycerine and margarine arcto be  supplied.    Oils and Fats. The output of home-produced margarine has been increased froma weekly average of 2,219 tons in 1915 to 3,582 tons in Sept.  1917.  Arrangementshave been made whereby the margarine output will be further increased, by the endof June 1918 to a capacity of  over  7,000 tons per week.  By November 1st, 1917,the capacity for the output of margarine will be 4,410 tons per week, and the refiningplant at the  same date will be capable of a weekly output of 4,302 tons.    Potatoes-The Potatoes (Growers&apos; Returns) Order,  1917, dated  October 30, 1917,requires farmers to furnish particulars of the stocks of potatoes  on their farms once  amonth. With the object of watching the  situation and  ensuring that the best keepingkinds  should be preserved  as much as  possible  until- the next crop  is  in sight,particulars are  required  concerning stocks of  certain kinds  of potatoes;  and thequantity sold and delivered, or  consumed on the farm during  the preceding month,must also be stated.  The order  does not  apply to growers  of less than  2 acresin Wales  and  Monmouth, or to  growers of less  than 5 acres in the rest of GreatBritain.    A separate Order has been made for  Ireland, requiring farmers growing not lessthan  one  acre  of potatoes to furnish particulars of the  stocks on their,farms oncea month.     The Food Controller, has issued a general licence authorising sales and dealingsin Ireland of potatoes grown in Ireland  of  the varieties  King Edward, Arran Chief,Langworthy, What&apos;s Wanted, and  Golden Wonder.     Sugar. The  Sugar  (Registration of  Retailers)  (Ireland)  Order, 1917, datedOctober 27,  1917,. brings into operation as regards Ireland the provisions of theSugar (Registration of Retailers) Order, 1917, which applied to  Great Britain only.     Tea.-Mr. Richard  Pigott, of the firm of David  Lloyd, Pigott &amp; Co.,  has  beenappointed Director of Tea Supplies.     A  meeting of  the  Committee of  the Indian  Tea  Association was  held  onOctober 30,  when  the arrangements  for buying  Indian tea was  discussed.  TheIndian Government has sent a preliminary reply to the recent  cable, saying  that thePurchase  Scheme is under consideration.     Lord Rhondda has made very urgent. representations to the Shipping Controlleron the subject of the supply of tonnage.     Arrangements have  been  made which will, it is anticipated, cause stocks bothof controlled and free tea to be liquidated by the end of the present year.     Arrivals of tea during October at Liverpool and Machester show a very largeincrease,  and the sales during November will  be much larger.than they have  beenfor some months.  Efforts are being made in Liverpool and Manchester to expeditethe handling of tea on arrival.                               LOCAL AUTHORITIES.     Food Control Committees have now  been asked  to undertake the organisation ofthe transport by retailers in their areas of food, and, if necessary, of other goods soldby retailers.  It. has  been suggested that in  many cases a special Sub-Committee ofthe Food  Control Committee shall  be formed for this purpose.  It is anticipated thata large saving in transport can be gained in many areas by proper organisation.  Forthe present the Committees within the  London  and Home Counties  Division have notbeen included in this scheme.             -      .    J         &apos;     Statistics  have now been received as  to  the number  of  retailers  of  sugarregistered in connection with the  Sugar Distribution Scheme.   These statistics so farshow an average of  3:83 retailers per 1,000 population.  A preliminary count of thenumber: of  persons- included in the household  applications for  Sugar RegistrationCards received has. been  made-  in  the  majority of districts,- and it&quot;  appears &quot;from the
returns so  far received&apos; that in England the  mimber of. persons thus registered is8*15 per cent, below the estimated civil  populationdn 1915.   In Wales, the:numberregistered is  5&apos;&quot;75; per cent,  below the estimated civil-population-in. 1915, while inScotland, the number registered is 13 &quot;0 per cent, below the estimated civil populationin 1911.  It  must,  however, be: remembered ^hat:persohs-residing-in institutions orestablishments, such as hotels, which are registered as caterers, are  not included inthe applications for Sugar  Registration, Qards.,.rand  that  the population has beenreduced by enlistment sincerl915.     ^    t     ,,       .     ,;1.        ,l&quot;     j/   --           PROSECUTIONS.    A  potato salesman of Spitalfields was fined 320Z,  on 16 summonses and wasfurther sentenced to six weeks&apos;  imprisonment for charging prices above the maximumallowed ;by the. Seed Potatoes (Prices) Order,  1917.  lie had made an illegal profitof 2241.   Two  wholesale greengrocers  were  fined  82Z.  and  721.  respectively  atHuddersfield on the .24th October for selling potatoes above the legal price.    There.have been  numerous  convictions under the Price of Milk .Orders, 1917.Before  the Taunton Bench, on the  22nd October, 10 farmers  were  summoned forselling  milk  at  excess prices,  and were fined in the  sum  of 5Z.  each.   On  the23rd October at Blyth a milk seller was fined 5Z.,  and at  Bilston Police Court, on thesame day, a farmer was  fined  10Z., with costs.  At Widnes  on the 18th  October aCo-operative  Society was  fined 10Z. for selling milk  above the fixed prices,  and atWolverhainpton cn. the 19th October four milkmen were fined 1Z. each for a  similaroffence.-  The last-named cases were under the Milk Order, 11)17.    -The Carlisle Bench on  the 22nd October fined the Carlisle Bread and Flour  Co.25Z. for selling bread above the legal  price.  At Birkenhead, on the 17th October,five persons were fined 5Z. each for a similar offence.  At Walsall, on the 22nd October,a grocer was  lined 5Z. for selling flour above the maximum price.- ,  At the Thames Police Court to-day, Phillip Grodzinsky, baker, of  Bedford Street,Mile End,.was. fined  1007., or 51 days, for selling bread which had not been made  atleast 12 hours.  For aiding and abetting  him, Louis Harovifch, a  tailor, John&apos;s Road,Clapbam, was;,fined 50Z., or 51 days.    It is reported from Nottingham that on the 27th October, a draper was fined 50Z.for hoarding  four -sacks of flour, and the miller who supplied the flour was fined 25Z.The costs were, assessed  at  40Z. to be paid  proportionately to the fines.   In  theMetropolitan  .area an Order issued by the Commissioner of Police requires all casesof hoarding to be reported to the Ministry before action is taken.   Investigation hasbeen restricted elsewhere to instances in which there is a strong prima facie case, andgreat care is&apos;  taken hot to&apos;authorise house searches on insufficient evidence.    At Hamilton Sheriff  Court on the 21st October, a butcher was fined  25Z. underthe Meat (Sales) Order  for  buying eight bullocks and re-selling them  at  a profitoflSZ. TOs.At&quot; &quot;Leamington on the 22nd October, a grocer was fined  10Z.  in each oftwo  cases for imposing  conditions of  sale.   At Greenock Sheriff  Court  on  the18th October, a  man called Sangster was fined 10Z. for  acquiring  192 lbs. of sugarfor purposes  other than that for which  it  had been issued under the Sugar (DomesticPreserving) Order, and at St. Helens a  farmer was fined 5Z. for a similar offence.              PART II.  SUMMARY  OF THE FOOD  POSITION.V   &quot;V---                            IMPORTS.    -The aggregate weight of imports of principal foods (including rice and tea) lastweek was 1.40,400 tons (Table A).  This  is an improvement of 25,100 tons over  theprevious week, but is still below the level of the first half of:  October and  far belowtheleyelsofr August and September.        ...     ...srJj ;Wheat arid flour have increased 28,000 tons,, while barley, oats, and ,-maize havefallen 13,Q0()Ttons, anclrice; 10,300 tons after several weeks of large imports.. &apos;.. .  .. Large.impiprtatjons of meat of all kinds arrived, especially of beef; the aggregate,36,00(1 tons,, is nearly three times the  average for the first .1.0 months of T916 and of1917       XS vfTs\1 rm ?&apos;L*:               A     -V. Bacon ,and: Kams show Httle change from  the prcviousrWeek.  An increase inmargarihe is eiacilly  balanced&apos;.by ti- decrease in: butter,  ;ahd: together this week:s
Date.	100 Sacks.			Used in Bread, &amp;e.	gold as Flour.	Total.Four weeks ended October 12th, 1916 -,, ,, September 15th, 1917 ,, ,, October 13th, 1917 -	6,109 5,950 6,175	1,991 1,658 2,016	8,100 7,608 8,191    The great rise  in  purchases  of flour is mainly attributable to the  NorthernCounties of England where  the  prevalence of home-baking is shown by  the largeproportion of  flour  generally bought.  No doubt home-stocks were  cut down to aminimum  before September 17th and replenished afterwards.  When allowance is &apos;made for  this it appears  that the actual consumption of bread and flour was verynearly the same in October 1917 as in October 1916.    During the period May 26th to September 15th less was  consumed in 1917 thanin 1916.   Until another return is tabulated it  is difficult to determine how far theincrease is due to a seasonal variation and how far to the alteration in price.    Increased sales in the last four weeks are  shown in the great majority of townsfrom which we have returns  and  in every food control  district.  A study of Table L,however, will show that the movement,.lias not been -uniform, throughout the UnitedKingdom.   In the  Eastern Counties/(Cambridge district), the  South  Midlands    a  4299-1                           &apos;&apos; &quot;&quot;    *  ^&apos;                  SJ      B      imports amount to only 61  per  cent, of. the average for  1917, so far.  5,900 tons of      cheese makes good the deficit of the previous week. -  K      - ;        :  , - .      &apos;    Only 4,400 tons of sugar arrived, but the total for the month is fairly adequate.          Of tea 2,707 tons  were recorded, an. amount 2 per cent, greater than  the averageif     imports of 19 L3 and equal to one week&apos;s requirements, y            .;:     &apos;                        1  &apos;            CONSUMPTION.          -&apos;:y---  -   t       \,          Meat. The supplies  of home-fed meat entering the Central Market London, and      the markets of Manchester. Glasgow, and Liverpool in the week  October 14th-20th      again showed an increase  and were 2 per cent above the previous week and 4 per cent.      above the corresponding week last year (Table B).          On the other hand the  supplies of fat stock at 59 markets in Great Britain show      a falling off in the week  October 18th-24th of 5 per cent, and 1   per cent, for cattle      and sheep respectively (Table C), as compared with the previous week.   They are      still 8 per cent, and 16 per cent., respectively, above the corresponding week  last year.          Only 1,830 tons of foreign  meat were m  the  meat markets in the week October      14-20th (Table B), and the  aggregate of home-fed  and foreign was 10 per  cent, below      the previous week, and 15 per cent, below last year.          It  is evident that the  position cannot be judged  adequately,  except  by con-      sideration of the movements for several weeks.          In Table D are shown the preliminary results of an enquiry as to the number of      animals  slaughtered  in  (59  public and nearly  5,000 private slaughter-houses  in      England and  Wales.   The  numbers of  cattle  and  sheep slaughtered were 4&apos;7 per      cent, and 12*7 per cent, more and of pigs 27 per  cent, less in  September 1917 than      in September .1916.  The actual  weight of meat from all the  animals  together is very      nearly the sanie in the two months, unless. the weight per carcase is less  this  year      than last.  The  index number of home-fed meat based  on 59 markets (Table E),      which includes some Scotch markets,  shows a fall of 2 per  cent, from September      1916 to September 1917.   In  Table B,  where there is a rise of 10 per cent., pigs      are  under-represented.   On the  whole  the  evidence points to the  conclusion that the,      consumption  of  home-fed meat  was very nearly  the  same  in September 1916 and      September 1917, while the consumption of imported meat  was considerably lower.          A  serious fact brought to  light in the slaughter-house  returns  is the great      increase (45 per cent, over last year) in the number of calves  slaughtered.          Bread and Flour. The preliminary results  given last  week of the change in      consumption  of  bread and  flour between the four  weeks before  and the four weeks      after the reduction in retail-price are  confirmed, with  slight  modification,  by the      completed returns (Table E).          The sales of flour show a different rate of change to those of bread.
(Reading district), and West Scotland (Edinburgh district) there has been little or noreduction  through the  summer, and a perceptible increase  in the autumn.   Londonand the Home Counties and the West  Midlands (Birmingham district)  are  the onlydistricts which show a decrease as compared with last year.    Very  little advantage was taken of the; permission to use potatoes in  the firstweek after the Order, which is the only one included in the returns.   / Contrary  to  expectation.  the stocks held by  the retailers  fell  again  betweenSeptember 15th and October 13th, possibly owing  to difficulties  in  transit anddelivery.  -	Four Weeks Consumption to October 13th.	Stocks, October 13th.	Number of Weeks&apos; Consumption held in Stock.	Corresponding Figures Four Weeks earlier.Yorks., Lanes., and North England Rest of England and Wales Scotland - - -Ireland - -Total - - -	Sacks. 223,092 361,431 109,771 76,595	- Sacks. 66,522 121,790 71,117 78,726	1-2 1-3 2-6 - 4-1	1-4 1-6 3-2 3-4	770,889	338,155	oo	* 2-0    Provisions. Returns have been obtained from a number of firms with multipleshops throughout the United Kingdom as to the sale of butter, margarine, lard, bacon,ham and cheese in a series of weeks (Table E).  It is estimated that they include fromone-sixth to one-third of the whole consumption in the country in the cases of butter,margarine and cheese, and smaller proportions of  the other commodities.  A generalfall is seen when this year is compared with last.  During July to September of  thisyear the sales  of bacon and ham have decreased; an increase of  margarine hascompensated a fall in butter, and cheese remains at an unchanged level.                              WHOLESALE PRICES.    There have been no important changes (Table F).
tKf tit  l^SSr^                                                EEEDiNTr/STUFFS,-.;   V;;5,..ir.... Article,..; P.r. 1.	.en5mg&apos;:- &apos; 2.	:,rW.^ fl ending il0cftjbef3i.i .20th, 1917. 3.	ending ^ i&apos; Oc.tGibeP&quot;v ,28t.h,,.l:916.7 :V--:&apos;- ---- % 4.	beisqxr. * Average 3 I Weekly H Nef. .. . &apos;impofts*&apos; 5.	OO Avera^ Weekly *r -T&apos;53iSj ISygOEt&amp;^-r^-i -----		n Tptal JtRpprts/&apos;						from: Dec. r ;$ls09lC 27th, 1917. 6-	*;0orres-&apos; ponding i. Period, &quot;1916. 7.	^43 Weeks-cfrom Dec-r 31st, 1916,&apos; 27th, 1917. 8.	Corres-&apos; Spending . Period. . &quot; ^ 1916, 9.1.- Wheat 2. Wh eaten flour 3. Beef (fresh, refrigerated and frozen). 4. Mutton (fresh, refrigerated and frozen). 5. Meat, unenu-merated (re-frigerated and &apos; pre-served). 6. Bacon -7. Hams -8. Lard -9. Margarine -10. Cheese 11. Butter -12. Sugar (refined and un-refined). 13. Sugar, glucose Total 14. Barley -15. Oats 16. Maize -Total All principal foods and feeding stuffs. 17. Rice -18. Tea -19. Oil seeds and nuts and kernels. 20. Oilseed cake	Tons. 40,120 21,340  24,539 17,285 * 4,072 3,501 924 158 1,743 5,923 671 4,415 48	Tons. 22,705 10,870  6,907 497 2,249 3,922 &quot; 718 1-71 1,041 998 1,373 15,703 146	-Tons. &apos; 82,115 5,730 8,919 3,078 2,903 6,238 1,048 405 3,754 3,254 2,035 33,873 1,269	Tons. 101,378 9,712 8,849 5,125 2,126 j 5,267 1,629 1,460 2,137 3,867 37,333 1,408	Tons. 99,900 13,092 6,016 2,510 2,609 ( 6,760 1 1,136 1,795 1,893 2,926 2,037 27,445 1,091	Tons. 99,561 9,921 6,531 3,641 2,849 7,177 1,464 2,167. 2,532. - 2,538. 2,053 30,202 1,294	Tons. 4,295,700 562,955&quot; 258,684 &quot;&quot;1157,945&apos; 112,170 : 290,695 -48,828 81*383 125,806 V 87,601 : 1,180,13:1 46,910	Tons. 4,281,125 426,610 280,854 156,552 122,508 !%4o8f589 - -!; 62,975 ,::.;93,178 ,,,108,87:7-. &apos;; 109,132 88,263 1,298,670 55,656	114,739	67,300	154,621	180,291	169,210	171,930	7,276,012	7,392,989	5,210 10,280 1,550	12,525 12,030 5,675	13,740 17,530 45,015	21,565 17,464 46,450	7,723 13,612 27,104	16,690 13,632 30,872	332,0^0 585,330 1,165,450	717,665 586,160 1,327,495	17,040	30,230	76,285	85,479	48,439	61,194	2,082,860	2,631,320	131,779	97,530	230,906	265,770	217,649	233,124	9,358,872	10,024,309	5,910 2,707	16,267 1,496	2,620	&apos; 2,554 2,640	15,024 2,045	f5,7l3 3,1.80	fl95,932 87,956	t222,788 136,755	Net Imports.*			Average Monthly Net Imports* in 1913.	Average Monthly Net Imports. *		Total Net Imports.*		Month ending Sept. 30th, 1917.	Month ending Aug. 31st, 1917.	Month ending Sept. 30th&apos;, 1916.		9 Months Jan.-Sept., 1917.	Corres-ponding Period, 1916.	9 Months Jan.-Sept., 1917.	Corres-ponding Period, 1916.	Tons. 50,252 - 22,340	Tons. 60,633 16,570	Tons. 82,129 40,704	Tons. 120,314 29,436	Tons. 86,002 19,304	Tons; 116,747 21,859	Tons. 774,019 * 173,734	%Tons. 1,050,721 196,731* Imports less re-exports of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind.f These figures relate to net imports during the nine months January to September.J Including certain importations made in previous weeks, particulars of which could not be given at the time.A  4299-1C
         TABLE B.-STATISTICS  ILLUSTRATING CONSUMPTION OF  MEAT.                                       &quot;   .&apos;                      &apos;      Tons.Average weekly supplies during June and July  1913 :           -   :  ^     Central Market, London    -        -        -       -             8,245     Manchester Market   *     -       &apos; -  ;      -   : *   -       -      8^5     Glasgow Market   -        -        -      .  -       -       -      798-   &apos;  Liverpool Market  -  .      -&apos;      -        -       -       -      221Total10,119Period.January -FebruaryMarchAprilMayJuneJulyAugust  -SeptemberWeek ended : &quot; 6th October - 13th October - 20th October -Supplies of Meat entering the Central Market, London, and Manchester, Glasgow, and                        Liverpool Markets.Home-fed.Weekly Average.1916. Tons. 5,629 4,863 4,756,4,215 3,720 3,452 3,371 3,584 4,4064,7905,2505,3571917.Tons.4,4014,4224,5464,2113,9193,3693,3454,3964,8445,1395,4505,579Foreign.Weekly Average.1916.Tons.3,8514,1433,4603,5193,2683,9393,7753.3343,5764,0353,2303,3491917.Tons.4,2792,9772,9712,9572,5372,9862,8442,3502,3002,1602,7431,830Home and Foreign.Weekly Average.1916.Tons.9,4809,0068,2167,7346,9887,3917,1466,9187,9828,8258,4808,7061917.Tons.8,6807,3997,5177,1686,4566,3556,1896,7467,1447,2998,1937,409Percentage Changefrom 19io.Per Cent.- - 8-4 -17-8 - 8-5 - 7-3 - 7-6 -14-0 -13-4 - 2-5 -10-5-17-3-  3-4-14-9TABLE  C. SUPPLIES  OF FAT STOCK  AT 59 MARKETS IN  GREAT  BRITAIN.Period.	Fat Cattle.		Fat Sheep.		Fat Pigs.		Weekly Average, 191fi.	Weekly Average, 1917.	Weekly Average, 1916.	Weekly Average, 1917.	Weekly Average, 1916.	Weekly Average, 1917.January - - -February - - - -March - -April - - - -May - - * - -Juue - - - -July - - -August - - -September - -Week ended : 10th October 17th October -24th October	18,509	16,234	68,923 .	64,462	17,329	14,283	18,292	17,259	65,729	58,630	14,140	11,722	19,232	18,184	66,126	66,454	13,607	11,562	18,347	17,479	73,590	63,260	14,915	11,777	18,123	18,201	70,026	60,014	12,658	11,637	16,944	14,642	77,721	61,777	11,666	10,789	14,487	15,672	68,848	71,896	10,283	8,689	15,864	16,424	81,857	78,228	9,995	8,953	16,222	16.728	75,425	74,452	12,474 &apos;	7,781	16,603 16,730 17,116	17,382 19,420 18,412	68,297 66,422 69,755	77,180 82,019 80,773	13,489 13,310 14,438	8,419 8,716 9,006
TABLE I).-ANIMALS  SLAUGHTERED IN THE PUBLIC SLAUGHTERHOUSES OF 69  TOWNS          AND IN  4,905 OTHER SLAUGHTERHOUSES IN ENGLAND  AND  WALES.	Cattle.	Calves.	Sheep.	Lambs.	Pigs.	Total Equivalent Cattle. :September 1916 ... -September 1917 - - -Increase (-f-) or decrease (-) -Percentage - - -	77,023 80,648 + 3,625 + 4-7.1	13,401 19,407 ^ 6,006 + 44-81	222,495 250,647 -f-28,152 + 12-71	162,262 165,283 -h 3,021	106,056 77,538 -28,518 -26-91	135,800 136,100 + 300 + 0-2XTABLE E. INDEX NUMBERS OF  CONSUMPTION OF BREAD,  MEAT, AND PROVISIONS.Retail Consumption of Bread and Flour* (measured as percentages of the level of May 1917).		i	1916.	1917.(4 weeks ended) : March 31st- - - - - -April 28th - : - - - -. May 26th - - ..... - -June 23rd -&apos; - -July 21st - - -August 18th -September 15th - - - &apos; -October 13th - -	99 100 97* 99&quot; 95 94i 96*	109 104 100 941 &apos; 92 89* 90* (92) 97K96)    Tbe numbers in brackets are adjusted for the probable change in the stock of flour held at home beforeand after the re luction in price 011 September 17th.                 Consumption of Meat(measured as percentages of the levels of May 1917). Revised Figures.	Home Fed. Fat Stock at 59- Markets in Great Britain.		Foreign. Central and Three Provincial Meat Markets.		Home and Foreign. Index Numbers combined.		1916.	1917.	1916.	1917.	1916.&apos;	1917.March April - -May . - - -June - - -Jnly - - - - -August - - - - - - . -September - -	108 109 104 102 - 88 98 99	! 102 99 100 87 92 98 , 97	. 136 139 129 155 149 131 141	117 117 100 118 112 93 91	116 118 112 118 106 108 112	107 104 100 96 98 97 95						Consumption of Provisions, based on returns from multiple shops and stores (measured as percentages of the levels of July 1917). -							Butter.	Margarine.	&apos; Lard.	Bacon.	Hams.	Cheese. &apos;(4 weeks ended)  September 2nd, 1916 -September 30th, 1916 -	101 98		941 94$	105 98	80 74	135 130August 4th, 1917 September 1st, 1917 -. September 29th, 1917-	100 101 90	100 106 : 111	100 104 106	100 97 81	100 80 74	100 100 . 99* For details in separate districts, see Table L bdlow.
       TABLE F. WHOLESALE  PRICES OF CERTAIN FOOD AND FEEDING STUFFS.    The prices given in  the  first column of figures  are the latest available in eachcase, and necessarily relate to somewhat different dates in regard to different articles.Those for imported cereals (other than rice)  and for flour  and for oilseeds and, cakerelate actually  to Monday, October 29th.  The prices, for, rice, sugar,  and tea relateto week ended  Saturday,  October  27th ; those for beef, mutton,  bacon,  butter, andcheese to the week ended &quot;Wednesday, October 24th, and those for  home-grown cerealsto the week ended Saturday, October 20th.    The prices given for imported wheat and maize  are Wheat Commission prices ;the prices for  meat,  butter, and cheese are taken from the Board of Agriculture^Returns  of Market Prices; for tea,  sugar, and  rice  from the &quot; Grocer &quot; ;  and  foroilseeds  and  oilseed cake  from Broomhall  and the &quot;London  Grain, Seed, and  OilReporter.&quot;---	Latest Price.	Week before.	Month before	Y ear before.	July 1914.Wheat - British (Gazette average), per - qr. (480 lbs.). No. 3 Northern Manitoba (Liverpool), per qr. (480 lbs.) Flour - Home Milled, per sack (280 lbs.) Bailev - British (Gazette average), per qr. (400 lbs.). Canadian (London), per qr. (400 lbs.). Oats - British (Gazette average), per qr. (312 lbs.). Maize - Plate (London), per qr. (480 lbs.). Rice - Rangoon and Bassein, per cwt. -Beef . - English, per cwt. - -Argentine, chilled, per cwt. Mutton - English, per cwt. &apos; -Argentine, per cwt. Bacon - Irish, green and dried, per cwt. -Danish, per cwt. -Canadian, per cwt. -Butter - Irish creamery and factory, per cwt. Danish, per cwt. -New Zealand, at London, per cwt. Cheese - Cheddar (English), per cwt. Canadian, per cwt. -Sugar - English refined, Tate&apos;s Cubes, No. 1, per cwt. Granulated, fine, per cwt. Tea (in bond, duty 1.*. per lb.)  Indian, Pekoe Souchong, per lb. Pekoe, per lb. Ceylon, Pekoe Souchong, per lb. Pekoe, per lb. Oilseeds - Linseed, Calcutta, at London, per ton. Cottonseed, Egyptian, at London, per ton. Palm kernels, at Liverpool, per ton. Oilseed cake, London made linseed, at London, per ton. Egyptian cottonseed, at London, per ton. ! Palm kernel, at Liverpool, per ton.	s. d. 70 10 &apos;72 0 44 3 60 r 43 0 68 0 28 3 112 6 101 6 118 6 107 6 173- 6 164 0 162 0 144 0 130 6 53 9 46 9 114.-1*. 84. 114.-1*. 44. 114.-1*. 34. 114.-1*. 64. 595 0 380 0 520 0 405 * 0 330 0 302 6	*. 4. 70 8. 72 0 44. 3 59 3 44 1 68 0 28 3 114 0 101 0 118 6 107 6 173 6 164 0 162 0 144 0 . 130 6 53 9 46 9 114.-1*. 84. 114.-1*. 44. 114.-1*. 34. 114.-1*. 64. 595 0 330 0 520 0 405 0 -330 0 302 6	*. d. 70 6 72 0 44 3 58 5 . 44 7 68 0 28 3 110 0 92 6 119 0 106 6 172 6 162 0 160 0 140 0 130 6 53 9 46 9 114.-1*. 64. 114.-1*. id. 114.-1*. 34. 114.-1*. 64. 595 0 330 0 520 0 400 0 300 0 277 6	*. 4. 62 10 *59 6 f55 0 54 6 55 3 32 10 56 6 18 4 82 6 76 6 107 0 80 6 119 0 115 0 106 6 189 6 208 6 200 0 -118 6 113 0 47 1 41 7 94.-1*. 34. 914.-1*. 2d. 944.-114. 9\d.-\s.\\d. 479 3 317 0 487 6 302 6 220 0 222 6	*. 4. 3i 1 $36 7 *27 0 t24 3 24 10 23 8 19 10 26 10 11 6 59 0 44 6 73 0 40 6 74 6 68 0 62 0 107 6 125 0 115 0 70 6 62 6 18 0 16 4* 84.-1*. 24. 7*4.-914. 7f4.-l*. 24. 152 0 165 0 155 0 94 0* Town Households.                   f Country Whites.                  * No. 2.
TABLE  G *-STOCKS of the PRINCIPAL  FOODS&quot; and  FEEDING  STUFFS  in  the                                    UNITED KINGDOM.Article.	October 1st, 1917.	September 1st, 1917.	October &quot;1st, 1916.	Stocks in the United Kingdom including estimated Farm Stocks.		Wheat (including flour) - - - -Barley -Oats - - -&quot; Beans - - - - -Peas - - - - -Maize - - - -Rice (including ground rice and rice flour) Grain Meals - - - , Sugar Butter - .... Margarine -Lard . -Cheese - - - -Meat: Beef (chilled and frozen) Mutton (chilled and frozen) Bacon - - -. Hams - -Poultry, Game, and Rabbits Other Meat Fish - -Tea &apos; -Coffee -Cocoa ------	Tons. 3,060,000 11,270,000 3,223,000 182,000 75,000	Tons. 3,252,000  1,317,000 3,319,000 184,000 73,000	Tons. 2,399,000  1,132,000 2,749,000 .176,000 49,000	Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, &amp;c.			88,000 120,000 44,000 192,000	102,000 107,000 24,000 136,000	150,000 $88,000 -23,000 62,000	Stocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and in Importers&apos;Warehouses.			8,100 5,000 20,300 17,400 36,800 14,100 . 14,000 4,600 6.100 19,000 21,900	13,700 6,800 ; 27,100 15,700 26,100 18,300 21,900 7,500 4,800 21,000 24,800	8,100 4,000 13,200 13.400 , 18,800 23,700 18,700 7,600 7,200 13,700	Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.			16,200 66,000 57,500	23,500 67,700 60,400	53,000 65.200 47,200    * The figures for wheat and flour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, inland warehouses, mills,-and bakers&apos;shops, as well as estimated stocks on the farms ; those for barley, oats, beans, and peas include stocks in port granaries andwarehouses and in  mills,  and estimated fann stocks.  In regard to all other articles,. home produce is, with yerv smallexceptions, excluded.    t Excluding, stocks held by maltsters.   Stocks in  maltsters&apos; hands on 1st October 1917 were 128.000 tons, and on1st September 1917,  140,000.tons.    J Estimate based on Trade Circular.    ^&apos; Figures not available.       -
      TABLE H. PERCENTAGE INCREASE IN RETAIL FOOD PRICES  IN THEUNITED KINGDOM, AT EACH OF THE UNDERMENTIONED DATES,  AS COMPARED WITH                      &quot; NORMAL-PRICES IN  JULY  1911.&quot; [Compiled  from information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics^Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.Article.	1st Jan. iSlo.	1st Julv 1915.&quot;	1st Jan. 1916.	1st July 1916.	1st Jan. 1917.	1st July 1917.	1st Sept. 1917.	1st Oct. 1917.Beef :-liritish Ribs Thin flank Chilled or frozen  Ribs -Thin flank -Mutton :  British Legs i Breast Frozen Legs Breast Bacon, streaky* Fish-Flour. -Bread Tea Sugar, granulated Milk&quot; - --Potatoes - -Margarine Butter, fresh -Butter, salt - - . Cheese, Canadian or u.s.* Eggs, fresh - . All above articles	7-0 11-2 16-3 26-7 5-8 11-7 16-3 24-8 7-1 40-9 20-3 15-8 13-6 67-0 -6-7 \16-1 4-4 13-8 12-1 10-0 63-4	37-2 45-9 46-2 63-8 29-0 42-3 41-0 61-3 17-5 64-3 48-7 40-6 27-8 67-7 9-7 \2-l 4-3 15-2 16-1 33-3 23-6	35-3 45-2 46-7 63-1 27-9 41 -3 41-8 62-7 30-7 96-7 49-0 41-7 48-2 93-3 28-8 \4-8 6-9 33-9 31-5 31-7 104-9	60-4 80-6 82-7 102-2 55-4 79-8 85-7 120-4 37-5 80-7 47-6 44-3 50-2 158-0 33-1 108-6 17-5 31-7 32-3 51-4 45-3	64-2 83-5 85-4 101/2 58-7 84-2 86-4 122-0 56-3 131-1 88-5 73-3 50-9 170-0 56-6 121-7 25-0 72-9 70-6 74-8 175-0	96-1 132-2 119-6 156-5 100-0 142-2 134-4 190-8 76-4 127-1 109-3 100-3 73-7 1877 59-7 144-3, 73-5 64-7 65-3 108-0 95-3	97-4 130-9 122-1 157-9 &apos; 97-7 138-2 136-0 190-9 96-0 136-1 109-2 99 6 78-9 190-0 61-0 38-9 66-0 90-8 90-1 94-7 142-4	84-4 110-9 118-2 147 p 80-1 103-6 133-1 173-3 1101 156-0 51-7 54-S 83-8 190-1 78-2 39-8 66-0 -98-7 97-9 - 91-4 &apos; 160-0	18-3	32-5	44-9	60-8	86-8	104-3	105-6	97-3* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally r; preseutative.f Decrease.TABLE K. RETAIL  PRICES OF  SUBSIDIARY FOODS IN APRIL,  1917, AND SUBSEQUENT      MONTHS COMPARED WITH THE  PRICES IN JULY,  1914, IN  LONDON AND                               OTHER LARGE TOWNS.   [Compiled from information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.&apos;]Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.- Article.	April 1st, 1917.	May 1st, 1917.	June 1st, 1917.	July 1st, 1917.	August 1st, 1917.	Sept. 1st, 1917.	Oct. 1st, 1917.Butter beans -Haricot beans (white) -Peas, split (yellow) Lentils, split (red) ... Oatmeal, Scotch - - - -Rice, Rangoon - - - -Sago - -Tapioca - - ... Condensed milk - -Lard, British -., American -	160 230 140 210 140 90 140 - 120 65 125 130	230 300 170 255 170 100 160 140 90 130 130	170 220 190 230 . 160 100 170 150 100 125 120	140 180 210 230 150$ 100 180 160 110 120 110	110 140 210 220 150$ 100 180 160 110 120 110	110 140 210 220 150$ 100 180 150 110 120 120	110 140 210 220 150$ 100 180 150&apos; 110 125 125I 125 in Scotland.
TABLE L-CONSUMPTION AND SALE  OF FLOUR BY  BAKERS AND  RETAILERS.        - Comparison of Four-weekly Periods in 1916 and 1917.      All expressed as Percentages of Amounts used in May 1917.Four weeks endedFood Control District.	October 13.	September 15.	August 18.	July 21.	June 23.	May 26.Newcastle - - - 1917 1916 Leeds ... - - 1917 1916 Manchester - - - 1917 1916 Nottingham - - - 1917 1916 Birmingham - - - 1917 1916 Cambridge - - - 1917 1916 London - - - 1917 1916 Home Counties, North - 1917 1916 Home Counties, South - 1917 1916 Reading - . - - - 1917 1916 Bristol - - - - 1917&apos; 1916 Carnarvon - - - 1917 1916 Cardiff - - - - 1917 1916 ENGLAND AND WALES - 1917 1916 Glasgow .... 1917 1916 Edinburgh - - - 1917 1916 SCOTLAND^ - - - 1917 1916 IRELAND- - - - 1917 1916 UNITED KINGDOM - 1917 1916 ENGLAND AND WALES :  Boroughs, other than London, with popula,-tion over 50,000 - 1917 1916 Smaller towns and rural districts - - - 1917 1916	96 95 96 89 96 93\ 98 94 931 951 108 101 93^ 001 95 96k, 981 100 1021 101 99 97 100 96 97 94 98 97	81 92 82 88\ . 89 . 92 89 92\ 891 94 \W\ 98$ 87 031 91-. 99k 97 100 981 100 92 98 96 100 90k 94 90 94\	83 98\ 80&quot; 92k 89 94k 88 88 88 051 100&quot; 101 84 93 94 00 96 001 99&quot; 101 92 96 . 99 108 911 06&quot; 88 05	821 101 821 93 91 104 91 95k 931 94&quot; 102 1021 90J 102 94 104 95 103 99 102k 94&quot; 99k 95 107 931 05 91 100	92 92k 91 94 9ik 97 941 0c9 941 97 101 102k 911 200 961 103 96 102k 98 103 961 96$ 98 106 , 95 0c9 94 071	100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100 100	95 95 103 98$ 98 96	91 90 99 97 &apos; 94 .92k	88 89 - 96 94 91 91	86 98 99 97k 91 97	96 96 98 071 97 07	100 100 100	96^ 93	92k 90k	92 91	94k	95 07	100	. 91k 96\	901 94k	891 05	92 00	941 97k	100	951 93^ 981? 97&quot;	861 91 92 96k	85 &apos; 92 921 98	88 &apos; 0C? 931 100	93 95 96 98k	100 100* Including Inverness district for which the returns are too few to allow a separate statement.

</content>
</cab>
