<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/112/0 images: 69-70</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL60OBTAINING Oif SUPPLIES BY MAilLIlS 01*&apos; NAVALGMVm ML mi.Admiralty togormflisiffi lot \lIn June 1919 I laid before the Viar Cabinet asuggestion ((jftT0!7528) that facilities should he given to the wives and families of Naval Officers and Ratings for obtain-ing supplies from the Canteen Depots outside Naval Barracks at the Rome Ports.    Ohjectibn was raised to the proposals as likely to meet with hostility from private traders and co-operative societies, in view of which;I promised to reconsider the question,    (war Cabinet 586 of 30.6,19)*removing the grievance under which Naval Officers and men are undoubtedly sufferings,  but it is evident that no proposal will be really effective or place the Navy upon the same footing as the Army in this respect unless permission is given to the families of Officers and men of the PuN. to purchase provisions from the Savy and Army Canteen Board0memorandum to the Cabinet, and hope that the decision of the 30tho June 1919 will be reconsidered, and my proposals sanctioned.I have examined various alternative suggestions forI am therefore re-circulating my previous(Initialed),    W. H. L.30. 9. 20.
461fc-(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 00 VBRN.MKNT) * CONFtD^TTXAL, WAR   CABINET.G.T* 7528. OBTAINING 0^ SUPPLES BY WOTS AND FAMILIES OF&quot; - ML OFFICERS and admiral tyjtooraridum for the &quot;Jar Cabinet.The Board of. Admiralty have had under consideration the question of affording facilities to the wives and families of Naval Officers and men similar to those enjoyed by the &apos;&quot;ives and families of Officers and men of the Army and the Royal Marines, for the purchase of provisions from the Navy and Army Canteen Board.Such facilities have not hitherto been extended to the wives and families of Naval Officers and mem     It v;ould obvious-ly be impossible to give any such facilities for dealing with the Canteens on board ship, and It has aiways been considered that, in view of the fact that the organisation and arrangements at Naval Barracks on shore differ essentially from those fit Military Barracks, it would be undesirable to permit the -rives and families of Weva1 Officers and Hen resident in&quot; the Port to deal at the Canteens in the Naval Barracks.During the War the privilege was withdrawn from soldiers1 wives in receipt of Separation or Dependants1 Allowances, but by s recent Army Order this limitation has been removed, thus restoring the differentiation in. treatment of the two Services.Some grievance ^as been felt in the Navy that the wives of Naval Officers and men should be debarred fro?1! the advantages of buying their groceries, etc. from the-Navy and Army Canteen Board while the wives of Army Officers and men are permitted to do so, and from time to time complaint of this differential treat-ment has been made.It is desirable that this grievance should be removed but in view of the objection to permitting the wives to deal at the Canteens within the Naval Barracks, it has been proposed that the Canteen Board should establish a shop outside the Barracks at each of the Home Ports at which the wives and families of Naval Officers and Men should be permitted to deal.It is anticipated that complaints may be raised in regard to the establishment of such shoos in, the interests of trades-people with whom the shops would compete.      This competition would of course be no greater than if the   toymen concerned were permitted to enter the Barracks and deal at the Barrack Canteens in accordance with the existing Army system, and the objection will in reality be to the establishment - of such competition *rViere it has not previously existed.In view of this possibility of complaint by private traders, tho approval of the &apos;:-ar Cabinet is sought to the principle involved before arrangements are made with the Navy and Army Canteen Board for opening the shops.(-Signed) ^.H. LONG,20th June, 1919*

</content>
</cab>
