<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/112/0 images: 73-78</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovernmentSECRET.iY;  ;&apos; p1.2    y\THE CABINET.RECENT EVENTS IN MESOPOTAMIA.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR. I circulate a Memorandum on recent events in Mesopotamia.w. s. c.The War Office,30th September, 1920.1. To understand and appreciate the course of the present operations in Mesopotamia, it is necessary to give a short account of the cause of the present trouble. There is reason to believe that its main source is not in Mesopotamia at all, and that the local trouble is only part of a general agitation against the British Empire and all&quot;it stands for.2. The Middle East has been a fertile field for such propaganda and use has been made of the- Turkish Nationalist and pan-Arab movements, and of religious fanaticism, among the Moslem population. The publication of the peace terms imposed on Turkey and the feeling aroused by them among Mohammedans, had already created a spirit of anger among many peaceably disposed Arabs, which it only required the work of an agitator to bring to active life. In addition to these underlying factors, there are also various local causes which have contributed to the general unrest. Delay in defining the status of Mesopotamia which necessitated the maintenance of absolute British administration long after the armistice, had an unfortunate influence on the country. In the opinion of the Civil Commissioner at Baghdad we have been going too fast in various, administrative matters affecting certain tribes causing gradual loss of that popularity which the Civil Administration enjoyed at first in such a marked degree. Collection of the land revenue and other taxes, and the fear of the country being exploited by western commercialism have been sources of trouble coupled with the disappointment felt by the Arab landed interests, who reject the idea that landlords have duties as well as rights. We have, as a matter of policy, backed the sheikhs and supported their authority. They, in their turn, have tried to impose too great a burden on their tribesmen, with the laudable intention of improving, the cultivation and ensuring good crops, by extensive work on clearing canals and making bunds, and incidentally have lined their own pockets very substantially. The sheikhs have discovered too late that they did not possess the influence that they imagined they had over their tribesmen, and are suffering accordingly. Complexity of Turkish law on the subject often makes the position of political officers exceedingly difficult.3. Another factor which has tended to cause discontent is the gradual appearance in the country of what may be called post-war conditions, such as have been felt for some time in Europe. High prices, shortage of necessaries, &amp;c, and the sudden acquisition by certain classes of the population of wealth brought into the country by the Army of Occupation have caused discontent among the more numerous class who feel the pinch of present conditions ; for these we as the victors in the war are in Mesopotamia as elsewhere naturally held responsible.4. An important contributory factor to the actual outbreak was the perception by the tribes of our military weakness. To kick a man when he is down is the most popular pastime in the East sanctioned by centuries of precept and practice. As it was, our withdrawals on the Upper Euphrates, and our evacuation of Enzeli and Resht, were seized upon by the agitators and depicted as showing Great Britains military weakness. Our inability to deal rapidly and effectually with the Rumaitha rising, owing to the non-existence of a mobile reserve, and other minor withdrawals, gave colour to these ideas and by diminishing our military prestige encouraged other hotheads to join in the strife on the side of, as they thought, the top dog.5. There is also reason to believe that the spread of the trouble has been fostered by articles in the British Press,- inspired by the very natural desire for economy. Unfortunately the demand for our withdrawal from Mesopotamia and for handing over(B20/396)   100  10/20  h&amp;S, Ltd.  8567wo
that country immediately to an Arab Government merely succeeded in convincing the Arab mind, swayed already by his agitators, that Great Britain was in severe financial straits, that her general military power was on the wane, and that British public opinion was in favour of deserting the country for which we had paid so heavily.6. The following is a summary of the location and potential fighting strength of the hostile Arab tribes in Mesopotamia according to the latest information : TribeApproximate fighting strength.Spheres of activity.Muntafik*KhazailVariousZobeidJanabyinMasud(1.) From Basra to Baghdad (a.) On the Euphrates line.43,00011,500 16,0001,500Kurna via Hamar Lake to Nasiriyah and up the Shatt-el-Hai.Samawah-Rumaitha Hillah Kufa area. Left bank between Musayib and Mahmudiyah.Bani Malich and neighbours Albu Muliammed Albu Darraj .. Beni Lam-Beni Rabiah .. Various(6.) On the Tigris Line,18,500 8,000 4,300 5,000 5,500 3,000Kurna to Amara. j Ainara..Kut-e!-Amara to Baghdad.(2.) Baghdad Hit Area.Zobaa .. Dulaimf2,500 27,000Zuqlawiyah to Abugharaib. falujah to Asshur.(3.) Baghdad Mosul Area.Shammar Jarba Various2,700 3,4001 Mosul lines of communication. Spasmodic raiding.(4.) Baghdad Kirkuk Quairitu (Persian Railway).Diyala District (except Mendali) VariousDauda ......Various       ......4,000 2,900 1,300 800Baquba to Khanikin. j Kifri Kirkuk Sulaimanyeh.The total of the above is about 160,000, but it is probable that some of the figures refer to rifle strength and not fighting strength, since a previous estimate put the fighting strength of these tribes at 270,000. This statement does not, of course, include the Kurdish tribes, who are believed to total 481,000 fighting men, of whom about one-third are believed to be armed with rifles. They do not, however, as a rule, fight far from their homes, and any concentration of a centrally controlled force of any ,size is considered improbable. Action on their part would probably be confined to looting villages or attacking isolated weak posts and convoys. It should be borne in mind that the Arab and Kurd are traditional enemies, and any combination between the two is very unlikely.7. As regards the actual sequence of events, reports at the end of June indicated &quot;that a spirit of unrest was prevalent amongst certain tribes in the Middle Euphrates. Matters came to a head on 1st July when a party of the Dhawalim, a section of the Beni  Huchaim tribe, attacked the prison at Rumaitha, killing the local Arab* Of this tribe about 10,000 are at present active around Nasiriyah and Samawah ; the remainder are not openly hostile, and there have recently been signs of internal dissension amongst them on the Shatt-el-Hai.f This tribe have stood firm to the present time and have assisted in keeping open communications on the Upper Euphrates.
guard and forcibly releasing their sheikh (Sheikh Shalam) who had been imprisoned for sedition. The following day the tribes rose in rebellion and cut the railway and telegraph line in several places. Reinforcements from Hillah and Basra respectively managed to reach both Rumaitha and Samawah. On 5th July a small column was despatched from Diwaniyah to relieve Rumaitha, but was unable to proceed further than Imam-Hamza (15 miles south-east of Hillah). Trouble now began to spread to the north of Rumaitha and on 14th July the Beni Hasan tribe, one of the most powerful in the Shamiya area, revolted and attacked a village 3 miles from Kufa (35 miles south-west of Hillah&quot;), which seems to have been the signal for a general rising among the. tribes in this area. Owing to the enlargement of the affected area the General Officer Commanding asked that the Brigade which had been held in readiness in India should be despatched at once. The despatch of the Brigade was concurred in on 16th July and India was asked to hold the remainder of a Division in readiness.8. By 19th July the disaffection in the Shamiya area had, however, not spread as had been anticipated; on this date the 34th Brigade Relief Column from Hillah, having concentrated at a point 15 miles north-west of Rumaitha, moved forward and found the enemy in a strong position with three lines of trenches supported with machine guns and bombs. The Arabs were completely defeated with heavy casualties after severe fighting. The garrison of Rumaitha was thus relieved and returned with the Relief Column to Hillah on 21st July. The Samawah area had been quieter after two attacks on stations, but sniping and raids on the railway still continued. In the Shamiya area the situation deteriorated and an aeroplane reconnaissance on 22nd July found the garrison at Kufa (108th Mahrattas, less 1^- companies) besieged in&apos; the Serai with the &quot; Green Fly&quot; moored alongside. On 24th July the tribes occupied Kifl and cut the rail-way and telegraph lines. A small column was sent from Hillah along the Kifl Road in the hope of preventing the spread of the disaffection northwards. The column came in contact with a superior force of the enemy and was severely handled, part of the force apparently being cut off, as 200 British and 81 Indians, were reported missing. The Royal Air Force during July carried out daily reconnaissances,, sometimes being our only means of obtaining information of gatherings and isolated posts. At the end of July, at the request of the General Officer Commanding, orders-were given for the despatch from India of the full Division as reinforcements. Thus, the rebellion had spread from Samawah nearly up to Baghdad. The General Officer Commanding had to strip the Mosul Lines of Communication of the 55th Brigade from Tekrit and 53rd Brigade from Baiji to form reserves at Hillah and Baghdad, respectively.9. During the first week of August the situation slowly got worse south of Baghdad. The Samawah area, however, was quieter, only periodic raids on the: railway occurring. In the Hillah area the rebels were incessantly concentrating round the town of that name, the insurgents being dispersed by the garrison, which periodically sent out columns, to the south and towards Baghdad, for the purpose of repairing communications and undertaking punitive measures. During the second week in August the trouble spread northward to the Baquba area, north-east of Baghdad, on the Persian Railway; and on the 10th communication with Persia and Kirkuk was cut, by damage to the railway north of Baquba, the Samawah area remaining quiet, except for some sniping and raiding of the railway.10. The following measures were adopted at this stage to cope with the situation. On 7th August orders were sent to recall to Mesopotamia the aeroplane flight from Bushire. The 1st Battalion of the Division coming from India, which landed at Basra, on the 7th, was sent on to Baghdad at once, where the bulk of the 53rd Brigade had meanwhile been concentrated to act as a reserve. On the 10th a mobile column moved from Baghdad along the Persian Railway and carried out punitive measures, burning the recalcitrant villages, but was recalled to Baghdad on the 12th where trouble was thought to be brewing. Subsequently, an Indian Battalion and one section of mountain artillery was desptched to Baqubah on the 16th. On the 11th an order was issued proclaiming that a state of war existed in Mesopotamia similar that before the armistice,11. During the third week in August trouble spread still further. Tribal unrest in the areas to the east of Sulaimaniyah, in Kurdestan, and around Kirmanshah was reported. In the Baquba area the situation got worse. Qizil Robat Station was attacked and burnt by Arabs on 15th and Quara Tappa Station on 16th August, various other places and posts were attacked unsuccessfully, including the bridge at Baquba. On the 18th the Levy post at Shahraban was captured after a 3 days&apos; battle, all the British personnel being killed and Mrs. Buchanan being taken prisoner.   In(8567)
fact, the whole of the area Quara Tappa, Khanikin, Baquba, was in open rebellion and the military situation was very serious. Quaraghan was relieved from Khanikin on the 26th and Baquba reoccupied from Baghdad on the 29th. The Kirkuk area was also becoming disturbed and different places on the road Kifri to Kirkuk were sniped, but reconnaissance parties met with no opposition. The communications between Baghdad, Falujah and Ramadi were interrupted and some river transport was burnt after running aground on the 19th.12. During the last week of August the general situation became still more serious. On the Middle Euphrates the- situation around Samawah deteriorated, but except for sniping and one attempted attack on the Railway Station nothing further of military importance occurred. Around Hillah there was considerable activity and movement by the Arabs. Mosul area itself was quiet, but Samarra on the Mosul Lines of Communication was reported restless on the 27th, and aerial reconnaissance reported the town invested on the 29th, and Istabulat Railway Station attacked and burnt on the 31st.13. In order to protect British personnel and interests, and as far as possible to safeguard the general situation and to stop the spread of unrest, Baghdad was put in a state of defence and improved works were erected. The principle was adopted of protecting the railways by a system of blockhouses similar to that employed in South Africa towards the close of the war. Isolated posts were to a great extent abandoned, enabling troops to be sufficiently concentrated to allow of punitive columns being despatched to restore order and communications in various areas. Blockhouse construction along the Baghdad-Hillah line was completed by 23rd August, on which day work was begun from Baghdad along the Kut line. On the 27th a start was made on the Persian line from Baghdad towards Baquba. Aeroplanes were used for dispersing insurgent gatherings, reconnoitring, and in some cases for carrying supplies to beleagured posts.14. At the end of August, the rebellion had thus spread along the Upper Euphrates and the Mosul Lines of Communication as far as Samarra. The Kirkuk Lines of Communication was restless and the Baghdad line to Quaritu was in open revolt. On the other hand, eight battalions and one battery of the 6th Division coming from India had arrived by 29th August.15. At the beginning of September the signs of agitation shown by the Muntafik Arabs in the Shatt-el-Hai area, who can muster 43,000 rifles, seriously affected the Lower Euphrates and Hamar Lake districts. The leading sheikh of the Shatt-el-Hai area, though himself staunch in his friendship for us, has been unable to control his tribesmen. On the 4th an armoured train, which was covering the withdrawal of the garrison at Samawah Station into the main camp, was cut off and rushed by 4,000 insurgents the crew of 40 with 2 British officers being overpowered after inflicting 500 casualties. The Arabs captured with this train a 13-pr. gun (which has since been used against the camp, manned, it is reported, by escaped Turkish prisoners of war), 4 machine guns and ammunition. The situation at Samawab, though not satisfactory is, so far, secure. Further up the Middle Euphrates, considerable activity has been shown by &quot;the insurgents, though nothing but more or less minor attacks have been made on our posts. Kufa (35 miles south-west of Hillah) is still invested but panel signalling to aeroplanes indicates that all is well with the garrison.16. By the middle of September a certain amount of inter-tribal fighting was evidently taking place. In the Baghdad Hit area much assistance towards preserving -order has been afforded by the co-operation with us of local sheikhs of the Dulaim and Anaizeh tribes. , Along the Persian Railway the situation has sensibly improved, thanks to the methodical &quot; clearing up &quot; operations which have been carried out in this area, little serious opposition being met with. The Baghdad Samarra area is still in a disturbed condition, particularly around the latter place. Communication is, however, now open by railway and telegraph between the two. Mosul itself has been quiet and the district which has up till recently been considered disturbed, has now quietened down. Arbil, Kirkuk and Kifri which have all been the scenes of local disorder have been pacified by the action of small mobile columns. The Diwaniyah Kurds, numbering 6,800 rifles, are reported to be mobilizing near Arbil for the purpose of preventing the hill tribes from invading the plains. At Rowanduz, now garrisoned by Arab levies under British officers, the situation is satisfactory. Blockhouse construction is steadily progressing and has been completed from Baghdad half-way to falujah, on the Hit Railway, and to a point just beyond Sharaban, on the Persian Railway. A mixed brigade with guns, followed by a smaller column to protect their lines of communication, left Baghdad earlier in the month to operate along the Persian Railway, and was last reported 10 miles
north of Sharaban. A smaller mixed column, which left Kizil Robat at the same time, has reached Kurdarra, the columns being in touch with each other. A column operating in the Hillah area secured the mouth of the Husainiyah. Canal on the 12th in order to give us control of an important water supply.17. Latest reports indicate that there has been no further spread of unrest, and that a general improvement is noticeable in the demeanour of the tribes, who appear to have withdrawn to their homes to a large extent. This does not, however, apply to the Samawah area and to a few isolated points.  The situation is now briefly as follows : (a.) We have lost control of the Euphrates between Nasiriyeh and Hillah, and rail communication with Baghdad is closed. Kufa and Samawah garrisons are isolated.(6.) The Baghdad Mosul railway is-working, but the tribes are restless, and there are frequent half-hearted attacks, especially at Samarra.(c.) The Persian Lines of Communication has been restored, and the situation is quieter.id.) The Upper Euphrates situation gives some cause for anxiety, but no serious threat from that direction at present.(e.) Kurdistan. No general rising at present, but the situation is delicate, and there is more or less serious unrest in the Erbil and Rowanduz districts.(/.) Tigris Lines of Communications so far undisturbed. Risings of Muntafik tribes have not spread east of Hammar Lake. There are indications of inter-tribal dissension, which is all in our favour,That disaffection has not so far spread to the tribes on the Lower Tigris is no doubt due, in a great measure, to the moral effect of the continual transport of reinforcements up the river. With the advent of the cold weather and harvest season and the arrival in the country of the greater part of two divisions of fresh reinforce-inents from India, it is confidently expected that order will be completely restored.18. The following reinforcements have been asked for, and supplied, from India : 1 Indian Division (less 1 Brigade, R.F.A., and 1 Brigade, Mountain Artillery).1 Indian Infantry Brigade.3 additional Indian Infantry Battalions.Total. 3 British Infantry Battalions. 17 Indian Infantry Battalions. 1 Brigade, R.F.A.1 Battery, R.H.A., ,  ,and various ancillary units,of the above, the following have already arrived in Mesopotamia : 13 Indian Infantry Battalions. 1 Brigude, R.F.A. 3 British Infantry Battalions. 1 Battery, R.H.A. Most of the ancillary units.The remainder have now all left India.An additional Air Squadron has also been despatched from Constantinople and has arrived at Basra.19. The above outline of the events which have recently been taking place in Mesopotamia gives some idea of the strain thrown on all ranks of the Army, Air Force and Civil Administration. Since early in July the troops of the Mesopotamian garrison have been called upon to face continuous hard work and fighting without relief or rest. The withdrawal of the Rumaitha garrison to Diwaniya and thence to Hillah, a total distance of 100 miles, was carried out under the greatest difficulties, involving
3 days&apos; stiff fighting before Rumaitha. Two hundred miles of vital railway have been protected by the construction of a system of blockhouses, necessitating the provision of strong covering parties during the process of the work. Operations have been constantly undertaken for repairing communications and restoring order in disturbed areas. Owing to their great mobility, elusiveness and knowledge of the country, it has been most difficult to bring the insurgents to a decisive action and to prevent them from assembling rapidly, harassing communications and dispersing as quickly again. The spirit of all ranks has been magnificent under most trying conditions of climate in a shade temperature exceeding 110 degrees, and with a scanty water supply.

</content>
</cab>
