<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/112/0 images: 418-419</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Air\ * (Ji HIS DOCUMENT IS TH^ PROPERTY OF HID BRITAIN IC MAJ^ITY&apos; S GOV^NflW.)0 ^S E C R E T* X&quot;    &quot; &quot; CABIM3T * \C. P. 1963.PROPOSED HTSETING QT? T.rr? PCTRIAL CAEIKfST IK 1921.Paraphrase Telegram from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Governors-General of Canada., fev Zealand and the Union of South Africa. (Sent 3.15 p.m.13th October., 1920].( Circulated with reference to Cabinet 54/20 Conclusion.10).13th Oct.oher.   Secret,,Following from Mr, Lloyd George for your Prime Minister: Bogins*I hare been anxious for some time that vvo should renew that personal consultation between Prime Ministers which v.;as productive ox such good results in the last t,: o years of the war and at Paris,     I fully realise that the British government in tho absence of such consultation and of some machinery for giving it more continuity, must inevit-ably tend to taice upon itself the responsibility for settling tho many urgent questions of foreign policy which arise from day to day and which require immediate docision, but which yet often involve consequences by which the whole Bmpira is vitally affected.     This I feel to be fair neitherto the Dominions nor to the British Government. I Joaow also that there are many other matters of common interest whichcall for consultation and decision.I have received from the Prime Minister of Australia a telegram in which similar views are expressed and he urges that a meeting ox the Imperial Cabinet should be held next year.I would therefore suggest that we should hold a meeting of the Imperial Cabinet not later than June next year on the lines of the Imperial War Cabinet Meetings in 1917-18,     At suoh a mooting wo could as faras
as possible cloar tho decks of the more urgentproblems which will havo accumulated, and we couldtry to devise some praotical working method forarriving at a common Imperial policy in foroign affairs. The composition,   agenda and meeting place of thoConstitutional Oonforonco which it was contemplated in 1917 should be hold immediately after the war but which I incline tc think could hardly be hold with advantage till public opinion in tho Empire has had time to give somewhat more attention to the whole problem could also bo discussed,-Will you please let me know whether you canattend such a meeting of tho Imperial Cabinet and whetherthe approximate date whioii I have suggested would beoorvonient to you ?    Bnds*MIMKH.Whitehall Gardens, S.f,vl. October 14th, 1920,

</content>
</cab>
