<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/112/0 images: 435-435</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Military Secret. 1430From Viceroy, Army Department, to Secretary of State for India,1th October 1920.Priority A.12931.   7th October.Part 1. (1) Afghanistan. All quiet Kabul up to.-21st September. Afghanistan Press publishes Government notice asking Indian companies to apply through Afghan envoy, Simla, for the following : (a) Contract for repair of road, Dacca to Kabul; (6) monopoly of the passenger transport by motor and horse carriage, Dacca to Kabul; (c) monopoly of fruit trade ; (d) terms for establishing sugar factories in Afghanistan.(2) Two infantry battalions and one regiment of cavalry reported to have left Mazar-i-sharif for the Oxus.(3) Jemal Pasha and Mission of 46 persons, including Kasim Bey and 20 Turkish officers, arrived at Herat 17th September. Advent of Mission apparently unpopular with Herat authorities, but members accorded courteous treatment under orders from Kabul.(4) Eight hundred Muhajarins returned via Khyber last week, including Jan Mahomet, leader of Sind Muhajarins. He stated that 5,000 Muhajarins still remain in Afghanistan till they can get money and transport to return to India, and that of Muhajarins enlisted in Afghanistan Army, all except 25 have deserted.Part, 2. (5) Chitral relief column reached - Drosh Fort on 1st without incident. return march to India will commence as soon as the relieved detachment from Chitral Fort arrives Drosh.(6) Hazara Border. Negotiations for submission of tribes continue satisfactorily. Bombarding of recalcitrant Akazia section has had good effect, and they now intimate desire to submit.(7) Waziristan. Reference para. (1) of my serial No. 213. Troops reached Drazinda on 30th without opposition. Garrison post had one casualty. Raiders&apos; tribe, most of whom were Zelli Khel VVaziris from Wana withdrew evening of 29th, apparently as result of bombarding by aeroplanes. Small bands still reported in neighbouring district.(8) Baluchistan. Convoy moving from Kila Saifullah to Loralai on 30th September attacked by 30 raiders and had seven casualties.(9) East Persia. Withdrawal normal except that one company infantry has been temporarily detained at Hurmuk owing to slight local disturbance on Chakansur border due to malicious report of intended British aggression.Paras. (4) to (8) given to Press.

</content>
</cab>
