<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/112/0 images: 468-475</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

SECRET.

C.P. 1968.

CABINET.

THE ECONOMIC ORGANISATION OF THE LEAGUE OF NATIONS.

Note for Mr. Balfour.

"The attached note on the Economic Organisation of the League of Nations, which has been supplied by the Board of Trade to Mr. Balfour for his use at the forthcoming meeting of the Council of the League of Nations is circulated for the information of the Cabinet."

(Sgd.) M.P.A. HANKEY.

2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.

15th October, 1920.


tQ a m(l)    At its-meeting at Rome the council of the League of JTatidAtffc directed the secretary General to discuss with &quot;competent exports&quot; &quot;the best mode of establishing a pei^ajien^-ecoriomic organisation under the League.   It is understo-od-that a scheme for this purpose is accordingly &quot;being prepared, by the secretariat, and it is to be exptcted that it will be submitted to the Council for consideration at an early date - possibly at the forthcoming meeting at Brussels, so as to admit of it receiving the approval of the Assembly in November.(2)     it therefore seems desirable without delay to inform the British Delegate on the Council of the views arrived at by the Board of Trade after very careful consideration, as to the type of organisation which is required, so that he may be in a position te consider any proposals formulated by the secretariat in the light of this information.*(3)     in a memorandum already communicated to Iir. Balfour in view *f the resolution of which signor Tittoni has given, notice an indication has been given of the general character of the organ!sa-tion which the Board of Trade consider suitable for this purpose. It is the object of the present memorandum to deal with the subject in somewhat greater detail.(4)     As indicated in the Memorandum referred to, the Board con-sider th-vt the character of the economic questions which have to be dealt with by the League of Nations&apos; unaer the peace settlement is such that no conference or committee can profitably handle them even in a preliminary and advisory oapacity except one corn-posed of the Ministers of the various states who are responsible for dealing with industry and Trade.   It is for each of them to obtain what assistance he requires from his own expert advisers; either official or other, but there can be no room on the committee now contemplated for any independent expert member eiiho are not directly instructed by and responsible to any Government.   The presence of any such irresponsible element would be extremely embarrassing and would probably make free negotiation and dis-cussion practically impossible.
(5)     The type of organisation here recommended is quite consist-tent with some degree of selection among the states members of the League so as to reduce the Committee to a workable size and 3uch selection is high?Jr advisable if it *an be arranged without causing unoue jealousy among the excluded states.   Probably it would be weii -either(a) to constitute a comparatively small committee for current and preparatory work with the obligation to advise the Council to summon a fuller conference of the- Ministers of all the states to consider the results of its labours,in any matters of sufficient importance cir(b) to constitute the full conference at once-and leave it to establish a sort of &quot;G-eneral purposes Sub-Committee&quot; for current purposes.(6)     The important point is that both the larger and the smaller body should be similarly constituted, viz., that both should consist of responsible Ministers and not of individuals selected ad hoc however competent or eminent.   This would not prevent a Minister who is unable to attend any particular meeting from sending a representative to take his place, but such a representa-trvc would be purely a &quot;surrogate&quot; and have no independent status. (7)     The main reason why the Board of Trade attach great im-pertancc to the above points is that the principal matters likely to engage the attention of the Committee involve questions of high policy and are not wholly or mainly technical questions. They can therefore only be dealt with by the authorised repre-sentatives of the various Governments who are responsible for advising those CrOvernments on their commercial and economic policy.(8)     An additional reason is that one of the principal advant-ages to be hoped for from the&quot;establishment of the League i3 the bringing /
of the responsible authorities in various Countries into close personal contact, so that they may conduct the business of their own Countries&apos;with full understanding of whflt is being done and aimed at by their colleagues throughout the world.   In this way it is to be hoped that the danger of friction among the various , States through action taken by one of them with insufficient&quot; re-gar d to the views and susceptibilities of the others will be sensibly diminished,     The personal contact of Hinistore and mutual discussion between then of problems of common interest before they have reached the stage of a &quot;fait accompli&quot; is bound to have a beneficial effect, and to reduoi the chance ofeventual disputes and dissensions.   But no such effect would follow from discussions among individuals who are not responslhl^ for the economic policy of their respective Countries.(9)    Moreover the constitution of an international Committee consisting wholly or partly of more or less detached individuals to deal even in a provisional and preliminary way with great questions of economic policy presents a grave danger.    Everyone knows how powerful an influence is exercised by a body entrusted with preparing th9 drafts for discussion, even if nominally it possesses no powers of decision.     Wo oould no; view without ^reat anxiety the establishment of such a body which ^ould inevitably tend towards the development of a sort of Economic&quot;Super State&quot;.     The retention of our power of vetoing itsanproposals at a later stage would be/insufficient safeguard, since the pressure to acquiesce in propositions which (it would bo represented) had already been the subject of exhaustive expert examination might be very strong and (especially under certain political conditions) irrestible.(10)   That the above apprehensions are not baseless appears from the fact that it is understood that one of the schemes ^hich has been suggested for consideration involved the ,admission as members of the proposed Committee of representatives of Labour and of the International Chamber of Commerce.     The Board of Trade could not agree tz cither of these proposals as they hold strongly that any assistanoe and3.advice
advice required by the Govenn-ent delegates either with regard to Labour, Commerce or any other matter should be obtained by each of them in euih manner as he considers most useful.(11)        If the above priouples are accepted it remains to consider the range of.subjects which should fall within the scope of the Commit bee or Conference.   It is believed that the Secretariat have bad in rdr-d the constitution of a single body to deal both witb economic and financial questions.   On consideration the  qai  ef Vrade are disposed to deprecate any such ocrubj nation.    It is true that some financial and economic^-, questiQ&apos;ov ere closely connected and overlap each other. Nevertheless it is the universal practice of civilised Govern--.... ments to deal with them &quot;by entirely separate organs, and it is unlikely that the Chancellor of the Exchequer would consent to be represented on questions entirely within his province by the President of the Board of !*rade or vice versa.   Hence we must either duplicate representation and make a very unwieldy body, or adopt the far preferable course (which was in fact adopted at the Peace Conference) of having a Committee exclusively concerned with Commercial and Economic Questions, and (if necessary) a separate Committee, similarly constituted, concerned with financial questions, leaving any adjustments of overlap to mutual discussion and joint committees,   There Is however no objection to the same branch of the secretariat dealing with both Committees if desired, and this would go far to avoid any overlapping.It is therefore recommended that the proposed ilconomic Conference or Committee should deal with ouestiona of trade, industry and shipping, excluding finance, Labour and Transit and Communications (other than Merchant Shipping).   It is further recommended that the subjects to be Immediately referred to the Conference or Committee for confide ration should be $he steps, to be taken to give effect to the various economic obligations imposed on the League ifider the Treaties ofpeace/
Peaea, so far as they fall within the scope of the Committee.-;v y jas above defined.(12)        Objection is lively to be taken to the above proposals from more than one point of view.(a) It will be urged that the League of Nations cannot dictate to the various States the character of their representation on the Committee, and consequently it oannot ensure that the Committee shall consist of Ministers, still less of Ministers holding any particular portfolio.   This criticism is probably technically correct.   The actual invitation made to each of the various powers must probably be to send one representative without specifying his quality, but in sending out this invitation the Council would not seem to be exceeding its functions if it directed the atten-lion of the states to the importance, in view of the character of the questions for discussion, of being represented, if possible, by the Ministers responsible fsr Commerce and Industry.   *.t all events it seems desirable that ll.ll,. Government should themselves decide to adopt this course and let their intention be known in advance to the principal other Powers:(b) It may be objected that the scheme of purely Government representation will exclude other important elements and interests, and the example of the labour Covenant which provides for representation of employers and labour as well as governments, may be appealed to.   is a matter of fact the scheme of representation of interests at,Labour Conferences has yet to justify itself and while some . arrangement of the kind may well have been inevitable in this particular; case, the extension of the same principle to such a different subject matter as the regulation of the Commercial relations among states is greatly to be deprecated:(c) It may also possibly be objected that thescheroe does not provide for any Economic &quot;Office&quot; or &quot;permanentbureau&quot;
bureau&quot; corresponding to the &quot;International Labour Offioe&quot;.   The omission is intentional, since in view of the character of the subject matter the Board of Trade would view with great anxiety any proposal tending to create any such International Bureau for dealing v.ith commercial, industrial and shipping matters.   In their judgment it is of great importance to insist that the secretarial arrangements for the Economic (and ^indncial) Committees must form part of the work of the general secretariat of the League, and must in no circumstances be entrusted to any separate or quasi separate organisation capable of developing into a &quot;permanent bureau&quot; with a &quot;director&quot; staff and-(eventually) a polioy of its own.
SBCRET. 1CP. 1969.CABINET.REVOLUTIONARY ORGANISATIONS IN TE3 UNITED KINGDOM. (Report Ilo. 76.)It is rsquastod thatmthis do oilman t may he treated as highly confidential.3, Whitehall Gardens. 16th. October 192Q.

</content>
</cab>
