<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/112/0 images: 721-722</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL.C. P. 1991. Uh   1 0&apos;DISTRIBUTION 0? &quot;FOOD IN THIS TITOIT OP ANSXT3?TSIQ?T OF TIH COAL STRIKE.Proposed co- o T-erat i on r bctw?;-^ Min i st ry of Food andad,es concerned.Copy of letter fror; the ICiniot crof Fooc! tpinthe, P r foe^ in ijter *Palace Charters,Weetminster, S.W.1, 19th October, 1920.Dear Prime- Minister,At a meeting of the Consumerst Council this morning at whichTrade Unionists were strongly represented I was asked whether Ishould &quot;be willing to invite representatives of the railway men andthe transport workers to discuss with me the possibility of thedistribution of food, in the event of any extension of the presentstrike, being carried, on ty the Ministry of Food in co-operationwith those trades which normally distribute in ti^es of industrialpeace, and so obviating the necessity for extensive appeals for voluntary assistance, wftich is resented by the Trade Unionists, andwhich is regarded as an invitation to &quot;blackle^ing&quot;, and thereforetends to embitter and extend the strike.I should add for your information that.the Standing Committeeof the London Labour Conference, which represents practically everyTrade Union and Trade Council in London, four weeks ar^o passed thefollowing resolutions&quot;In view of the serious unrest throughout the country and the possible contingency of either a sectional or national strike or strikes, this Committee of the Conference which represents the Labour and Co-operativd Movement in London urges the Ministry of Food and the Labour Movement to co* operate in assisting the former to carry out its functions as to distribution etc. of food, so that the feeding of the people shall not be jeopardised *   Also that the Ministry of Food shall maintain a strictly neutral attitude in any such dispute, restricting its efforts wholly to the distribution of the people&apos;s food.&quot;I understand that Ileil McLean, who was present at the meeting, proposes t.o addresc a question to you next Monday to ask whether the suggestion made to me has been conveyed to the Government, and what response has been r.ade.
523I have discussed tho natter with Sir vric Credd^e and I imagine that there ni:;ht &quot;be :;r-:at difficulties in arriving at any practical^/ forr: of co-operation, at any rate so far as the railway men are concerned, though rjo;rothin;;: rni-rht be possible in the base of the transport workers, hut even if there is no possibility of practical results I would su^eet that it would be well to agree to neet representatives of Labour if they desire a discussion as an earnest of the willingness of the Government to explore any avenue in the direction of peaceful co-operation or limitation of the present dispute.Yours sincerely,(Signed ) CHOIRS A. :*cCURDY.The Hi. honble..David Lloyd George, 0 .Lh ,H.F. , 10 Dooming Street,

</content>
</cab>
