<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/169/17 images: 317-328</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THE POSSIBILITY OF DISPERSING MORE government work FROM london memorandum by the Lord Privy seal. Ministers parts of whose Departments are proposed for dispersaland the Secretaries of State for Scotland and for Wales have given me theirviews on the proposals made in Sir Henry Hardman!s report &quot;A Review ofthe Possibility of Dispersing More Government Work from London&quot; (TheReport).    The purpose of this memorandum is to agree the basis for thenext stage of the exercise, namely discussions with the Staff Sides and publication of the Report.REACTIONS TO THE report.        With the exception of the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary andthe Home Secretary, Ministers are, subject to some minor changes,content with the numbers proposed for dispersal.    Almost invariably,however, where The Report has proposed a distant location in an assistedarea, the Minister would prefer a location nearer to London.    With a few exceptions Ministers will take The Reports first alternative, the&quot;efficient&quot; solution.    If we could settle on that, we could agree on a newdispersal programme now, but that would be paying too little attention to regional policy.    Regional Ministers object and would prefer an allocationmore favourable to the assisted areas.3.        There are two areas of particular concern in the reactions I havereceived.    First, the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and the HomeSecretary object to the proposals for their Departments, as follows:a.        Apart from the Passport Office, dispersal would seriouslyimpair the efficiency of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO)The policy divisions concerned in the Migration, Nationality and consular areas are often required to give urgent advice to ministers and to be readily accessible to both other GovernmentDepartments and foreign embassies.    Even the move of the PassporOffice would arouse public and Parliamentary criticism.16 6CP(73) 57 COPY NO27 April ?973CABINET
b. The dispersal of &apos;chn Immigration and Nationality Departmentof the Home Office would be damaging,, owing to the urgency andsensitivity of immigration issues and the need for services to thepublic    Even the recent move to Croydon was adversely criticised in Parliament.    Moreover a second move alter such a short time would be much resented by an already heavily burdened staff.4. These points well illustrate the tension between the two criterialaid down for The Report, a proper concern for operational efficiency andour desire to create new employment outside London, and it is forconsideration whether a decision should be taken from the outset not toaccept the recommendations for these two Departments in so far as they relate to policy divisions, but to concentrate on the other possibilitiesmentioned in The Report.5.        Second, it is also for consideration how we should respond to the criticism which so large an allocation of work to the South East Regionwill attract, most particularly from West Central Scotland.    The followingseem to be the only possible courses:a. To ride out any criticism on the basis that the assisted areas have done well out of dispersal so far, especially the glasgow area, that the work now to be dispersed cannot be separated from its natural communicaticn and locational patternswithout serious loss of efficiency and that Government is not theonly source of mobile employment to which the assisted areas should be encouraged to look.b. To re-examine the allotment of Ministry of Defence workto Milton Keynes on the basis that this presents the only realisticopportunity for finding work for Scotland and to invite the Secretaryof State for Defence to try and find work for Scotland among the divisions which his Department is to identify for dispersal in preference to those suggested in The Report.c. To send to Cardiff some of the Ministry of Defence workproposed for Milton Keynes and to transfer from Cardiff to Glasgowthe work of the Property Services Agency (PSA).d. To present the movement of work within the South East not as dispersal but as undertaken to reduce costs, notably onaccommodation, and to reduce congestion in the London area.6.        I believe the choice is between the first and second options.    Asthe evidence adduced in The Report implies, it would be difficult to administer the PSA services for England and Wales from Scotland; indeedsuch are the communications difficulties that Cardiff itself is onlymarginally acceptable.    The fourth option is more a matter of semantics2
than of substance.    It may help us with presentation, but it is not analternative course of action to the other three.    Indeed, if we opt forcourse a. we shall need to consider whether we should at the same timeadopt course d.THE NEXT STAGE7. The next stage must be the promised consultations with the staffinvolved.    This memorandum accordingly invites the Cabinet not to takea complete set of decisions on The Report but to approve a basis for consultation.    So far, staff have been quiet on dispersal but the national staff Side are now pressing for copfes of the Report as a preliminary todiscussions and it would be unwise to bank on their remaining indifferent to the knowledge that it has now been with Ministers for some time.    Innarrowing down the area for discussion, we must have regard to regional policy as well as the efficient operation of Departments.    The points i suggest we should confirm before opening discussions are:a. No alteration to the list of places approved by Ministerslast year and reflected in The Report. Dispersal is long-term and changes to meet short-term problems would be wrong.b. Only a few locations should be chosen.c. With the possible exception of the Ministry of Defence, wekeep any options within the three solutions in The Report (or a mixof them), but, without in any way implying that all of them are necessarily acceptable to the Government, we should not refuse todiscuss with the Staff Side any of the courses which appear in TheReport.8.        If this is agreed, consultations can begin with Staff Sides on thebasis of some virtually firm decisions and some where the Governmentwould be saying that, before making up its mind within the alternativerecommendations put forward, it wanted to take account of Staff Sidereaction.    However, it would be important not to present staff with a fal.seprospectus.    Where Departments are invited to consider more than onelocation, we should make it clear that we are disposed to select a particulainamed place.    Our minds are not closed; the process of consultation is a real one and in reaching final decisions we shaLl take full account of anyarguments the Staff Side may wish to advance.    On the other hand we arenot giving them a straight choice; there are many considerations to be balanced and their views will not necessarily be decisive.9. Subject to the issues discussed in paragraphs 3-6 above, if we areto give any weight to the regional criterion, our preferred location shouldbe the one which appears in The Reports &quot;recommended&quot; course.    On this basis, Departments would fall into two groups,,3
10.        This comprises Departments whose Ministers accept The Reporfsrecommended solution as regards both numbers and places (usuallybecause the location proposed is the existing dispersal centre for theDepartment),    There would be little room here for the Staff Side to arguefor a different decision, but this is not likely to be difficult because theyare for the most part the recommendations most acceptable to the staff.The Departments in this group are the Civil Service Department, theBoard of Customs and Excise, the Ministry of Defence (subject to what issaid above), the Department of the Environment (excluding PSA),HM Stationery Office, the Department of Trade and Industry, and the science and Natural Environment Research Councils.    (The two research councils, who have been kept waiting for a long time, would like early agreement to their dispersal to Swindon and 1 suggest that we should give it- subject to the completion of consultations with their Staff Sides).GROUP 211.        This covers all ether Departments where there are sometimesobjections to the numbers (FCO, Department of Health and Social Security(DHSS), Home Offj.ce and Office of Population, Censuses and Surveys) and always objections to the recommended location.    In these cases, I suggestthat consultation with the Staff Side should be on the basis covered byparagraphs 7-9 above.    While the locations to be discussed should be those recommended in The Report in the case of DHSS, I suggest that,given the good arguments for adding Blackpool to the list, it would be reasonable to regard this as sufficiently near the Central Lancashire NewTown to qualify,    On numbers, while I am not unsympathetic to the views expressed by my colleagues, I think there would be advantage in puttingall the proposals to the staff concerned, so that they can be fully discussed,while making it clear that final decisions, both on numbers and on locationsmust be taken in the light of the national interest.12.       For ease of reference, Annex A sets out the basis on which weshould undertake discussions with the Staff Side if the proposals above aieaccepted by my colleagues.PROCEDURE13.        The Prime Ministers statement of 22 February undertook to publish the Report in due course.    The view of Departments is that while TheReport, if issued widely to the staff, would be bound to leak, nevertheless there would be advantages in letting both the National and DepartmentalStaff Sides have The Report a few days before publication.    Leaks are more likely from Departmental Staff Sides, if only because of the numbers involved, than from the National Staff Side.    I suggest that we give TheReport to the latter a few days, and the former one day, ahead of publication, which should be accompanied by a statement, a possible draftof which is at Annex B.4
14.       As to timing, I have been advised privately by the Secretary Generalof the National Staff Side that it would invite the worst possible reaction from the staff associations if the Government were to publish during their annual conferences (4-24 May).    The Government would also be open to criticism if it published on Friday, 25 May, when Parliament is expectedto rise fcr the Whitsuntide Recess.    It seems best therefore to deferpublication until immediately after the Recess.    This timing means thatthe Government can hardly announce final decisions before the summer recess, as tiie Staff Sides are likely to argue that when the Governmenthas taken three months to consider The Report it is unreasonable to ask them to formulate their own views in less than two,    The right course may therefore be to accept that decisions cannot be announced until the autumn,,15.        This need not however prevent Departments and Staff Sides coming to earlier agreement if they can.CONCLUSIONS16.       I ask my colleagues to agree that:i. The Report should be given to the National and DepartmentalStaff Sides after the Whitsuntide Recess.ii. Consultation with the Staff Sides should follow the lines indicated in paragraphs 7-U above and in Annex A and that theGovernment must ultimately in addition retain a final say as towhether to make further changes in the national interest.iii. The issue of The Report to the Staff Sides should immediately precede its publication under cover of a statement as at Annex B.iv. The Science and Natural Environment Research councils should have our agreement now to disperse to Swindon.J civil  Service Department27 April 19735
DEPARTMENT   RECOMMENDEDSOLUTIONNo  LocationMINISTERS1PRELIMINARY RESPONSENo LocationANNEX ABASIS PROPOSED FOR DISCUSSIONWITH STAFFNo      Location (Government&apos;spreference__underline)CUSTOMS357 Norwich300 Baaingstoke50 Sunningdale500 SouthendvmnCE   10,890  M KeynesffiVHENT 1,348NERC 191SRC 3883801,442358TRADE &amp;INDUSTRYBristolSwindonSwindonNorwichCardiffTeddington3573005050010,8901,2481913883801,442358NorwichBasingstokeSunningdaleSouthendM KeynesBristolSwindonSwindonNorwichCardiffTeddington357 Norwich300 Basingstoke50 Sunningdale500 Southend10,890 M Keynes /But see coveringpaper/1,248 Bristol191 Swindon388 Swindon38O Norwich1,442 Cardiff358 TeddingtonGROUP 2HAFF 1,250ARC 140EMPLOYMENT 1,400140D0E(PSA)   4,100ManchesterManchesterLiverpoolPlymouthCardiffFCC986   CLNTFCO(ODA)   1,177   GlasgowDKSSHOMEpiCBREVENUEJDPCSECGD5009801,43783NewcastleCLNTPlymouthPlymouth1,2501401,4004,100Nil or400(PassportOffice)1,177950NilCoventryCoventryWithin 2 hoursof london,610  Teesside920   CLNT600  LiverpoolBasingstoke/M KeynesNewcastle &amp;Blackpool1,610500/600600LeedsTitchfieldCardiff1,250    Manchester, Coventry andLiverpool140    Manchester, Coventry andLiverpool1,400    Liverpool140    /^Depends on decision ofHome Office/4,100    Cardiff and Teesside986     CLNT, Bristol and Liverpool/But see covering paper/1,177    Glasgow and Manchester500 Newcastle98O    Blackpool1,437    Plymouth and Liverpool /Butsee covering papery83    Plymouth and Liverpool/Depends on decision ofHome Office/1,610     Teesside, Leeds and Plymouth)920     CLNT and Titchfield600    Liverpool, Cardiff,_Glasgow and Manchester *fOTALS    31,427 28,331I- ECGD itself has offered to consider Manchester and as it /  approved locations for dispersal it seems reasonable to31,427is one of the Ministeriallyadd it to the list.
1DRAFT STATEMENT1. As already announced (House of Commons, official report,  22 February, Written Answers, cols 173 and 174), theGovernment has received a report by Sir Henry Hardman onthe possibility of dispersing more Government work from london.    The Government is indebted to Sir Henry Hardmanfor his review and for his comprehensive presentation ofthe issues involved;    it is also grateful for the work of departments and associated bodies which took part in the review, and for the contributions made to the exercise bythe Institute for Operational Research, the Tavistock centre for Human Resources and the Joint Unit for Planning Researchat University College,  London.2. The Government now publishes Sir Henry Hardman&apos;sReport,  as office location policies, whether in the privateor the public sector, are a matter of general interest andit believes that the material it contains will be the bestbackground to any public discussion there may be in thecomming months.3. In the past, the dispersal of Government work from london has been substantially of work which is relativelyself-contained and can be done anywhere.    In the past
10 years decisions have been taken to transfer from orcreate outside London nearly 50,000 posts in such government work.    The regional distribution of this work is given inthe attached annex.    It will be seen that well over halfthis work has gone t.o, or is planned for, the assisted areas,  particularly Scotland and Wales which will each havereceived some 11,000 posts.4. Sir Henry Hardman has been looking at the possibilityof taking this process a stage further.    However, his review was concerned largely with work of a different characterfrom that of previous dispersals, namely policy work.    Hehas examined some 86,000 posts in Government departments and in offices which, while not part of the central machineryof government are closely associated with it, eg the research councils.    Such work cannot be done outside London without some loss of effectiveness in the services provided for ministers,  Parliament and the public, whether individuals or organisations.      Sir Henry Hardman has therefore been considering how much could be moved at what price in lostefficiency.    In deciding what work should be dispersed, theGovernment will take serious account of the evidence hepresents in relation to operational efficiency.2
5. This is one of the principal criteria by whichthe Government will be influenced and which Sir Henry Hardmanhas had in mind in arriving at his main recommendation.This is that some 30,000 of the 86,000 posts reviewed couldbe dispersed over a period of years.6. The second main criterion is the need of placesoutside London for office work opportunities.    Where thebalance of advantage so lies, the Government will wish tosend work to new and expanding towns and to cities withinthe assisted areas.    Accordingly, as well as consideringthe possibility of sending more work from a Department toits existing dispersal centre or centres,  for which thereare good reasons as described in the Report,  or to regionaladministration centres, the Government invited Sir Henry Hardmanto consider the scope for sending work to specified places in assisted areas.    Sir Henry Hardman has consequentlysuggested,  as part of his principal recommendations,  adistribution of the 30,000 posts between a number of differentplaces.    This distribution is also set out in the attachedannex.    The Government will take serious account of theneed for new office work in studying the recommendations,but is not necessarily committed to the pattern proposedby Sir Henry Hardman.7. While in principle endorsing Sir Henry Hardman&apos;view that few rather than many locations should be selected^
the Government now wishes to consider his recommendationsfurther before making final decisions.    In doing so,  itwill want to consider the implications of the proposals,not only for the organisation and management of theDepartments affected, but also for the staff concerned.It has accordingly invited staff to give their opinionsthrough the National and Departmental Whitley Council machinery.It expects to reach and announce decisions during the autumn,but it has already given its approval in principle to the dispersal of the Science Research Council and the NaturalEnvironment Research Council to Swindon.Civil Service DepartmentWhitehallLondon SwT27 June 1973
DISTRIBUTION OF THE NON-INDUSTRIAL SERVICE AND OF WORK SITED OUTSIDE london under DISPERSAL. AND NEW OFFICE POLICIES SINCE MAY 1963,  TOGETHER WITH WORKHOW PROPOSED FOR DISPERSAL BY SIR HENRY HARDMAN:      NUMBER OF POSTSRegion       Location	Non-industrial Civil Service Work at loca-tion (at 1 Oct 1972)	Work already dispersed: New offices created (included in previous col)	Work to be dispersed: New offices to be created (pre-Hardman)	Additional Work Pro-posed for dispersal by Sir H HardmanScotland		6,481	4,476	ljl77Glasgow	10,910	3,681	3,419	1,177Northern		3,692	790	2,110Newcastle Teesside	15,770 1,950	699 195	91 150	500 1,610f-------- 1 --...................   .i   i i North West		4,797	3,118	6^276Liverpool Manchester Central Lanes New Town	9,540 13,170 3,270	898 2,180	2,685 335	2,000 1,390 2,886Yorkshire &amp; [Humberside		783	55	Wales		3,283	6,284&quot;*&quot;	5,542Cardiff) Newport)	8,490	1,007	550&quot;1&quot;	5,542,West iHidlands		279		1lEast Midlands		746	140	East		1,192	-&quot;-----    -	737Norwich	3,170	1,103		737South West		1,332	1,185	3,487Plymouth Bristol Swindon	5,840 4,540 616	252	623	1,660 1,248 579South East                        /		9,004	1^861	12,098Basingstoke v Milton Keynes Southend Sunningdale Teddington	1,100 133 2,634 225	601 1,711	650 495	300 10,890 500 50 358Excludes 1,500 posts to have been dispersed under pre-Hardman plans, as these posts are now to be identified as a result of the Hardman review.Excludes 150 posts in the HQ of the Forestry Commission, which is tomove to Edinburgh.ANNEX TO ANNEX B


</content>
</cab>
