<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/3/9 images: 127-28 November 1939</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>
'C. Llb
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT)
p J ^ U 3 9 ) 1 2 1 . COPY NO. /3
WAR CABINET.
WORKMEN* S COMPENSATION.
pajldum "by the Lord Privy Seal,
I circulate to my colleagues for consideration a
draft record of a discussion on Worlanen's Compensation
at the Meeting of the Home Policy Committee held on
37th November, 1959, (H.P.0.(39)18th Meeting, Minute 1 ).
(Initialled). S.H.
asury Chambers,S.W. 1.
28th November, 193 9.

WBKMW S
(Previous
Reference:
1Jth Meeting,
Conclusion 1 2 ) .
Home Secretary could confer with the Departments
responsible for other pensions and allowance
schemes in order to consider how far they were
comparable and inter-reiatedo
THE HOME SECRETARY explained that the
memorandum which he had circulated (paper No,
H.P.C. (39)111 ) and was now before the Committee was
intended to present a comparative statement, in so
far as that was possible, between the
Departments concerned in allowance and
pension schemes. . It was very difficult to make
a direct comparison because of differences in the
basis of schemes, but in so far as comparison was
possible the Personal Injuries (Civilians) Scheme
prepared by the Ministry of Pensions was more
similar to the Workmen's Compensation Scheme than
tliie others. The structure of the Civilian Injuries
Scheme had two main features in which it was
dissimilar to the Workmen's Compensation, namely
that it took into account married obligations, and
secondly, it might be said to fall into two parts,
Short-term compensation and long-term compensation.
The short-term compensation was not substantially
more favourable than the Workmen's Compensation
Scheme; for example, a single man got less, but
a married man with two children more. As far as
long-term compensation was concerned, the Civilian
Injuries scheme gave more favourable terms. This
scheme was framed to deal with the Civil Defence
Voluntary Forces, assuming a basic rate of £3 a
week. It also took into account the ordinary
private soldier's pension arrangementSr The
Workmen's Compensation Scheme benefits were markedly
less generous in the case of long-term compensation
where there might be a reduction to 13% in the
compensation payable, whereas the Civilian Injuries
scheme had no provision for any such reductionQ
The total cost of the scheme excluding
cost of administration, including medical and legal
costs was eight million pounds, and taking into
consideration the other factors, set out in
paragraph 5 of his memorandum (Paper No. H.P. C. (39)111),
his proposals might be estimated to add two million
pounds a year to the present figure, of which rather
1 . At their 17th Meeting THE COMMITTEE had
before them memoranda by the Home Secretary
(Paper No, H.P.0. ( 3 9 ) 95), the Minister of pensions
(Paper No. H.P.0. ( 3 9)108), and the Financial
Secretary to the Treasury (Paper No. H.PrC*(39)109)?
which dealt with a proposal that an announcement
should be made in the House of Commons by the Home
Secretary to the effect that he would endeavour
to formulate, in consultation with the Trade Union
Congre s s and representatives of employers and
other interests, some provisional legislation on
the subject of rates of benefit under the Workmen's
Compensation Acts, on the understanding that this
would be without prejudice to the recommendations
of the Royal Commission as to the principles to be
adopted in permanent legislation.,"
The Committee was adjourned so that the

less than one half would fall on the coal mining
industry, costing about an additional ^d. per ton
of coal raised. Accidents in that industry
represented about 50',': of the total,
THE SECRETARY FOR MINES said there was a
strong demand from miners for an increase in the
present rates. He could not, however, argue
that the industry could not bear this extra cost;
it would, for example, not interfere with ex-port
trade.
THE CHAIRMAN said that it appeared to him
that there were two sides to the problem. First,
would this proposal be yet another factor in the
rising spiral of prices; and secondly, what
reactions would it have on the position of other
Departments who had to meet demands for increased
pensions and allowances?
THE FINANCIAL SECRETARY TO THE TREASURY said
that his views had been set out in Memorandum
Paper N0.H.P.C.(39)109 which he had circulated.
The essential point to him seemed to be that the
conditions which led to the setting up of the Royal
Commission were entirely different from those which
were now prevailing. He fully sympathised with
the Home Secretary in the position which he found
himself, but he thought that the Government would
have to recognise that marry social services which
t h e y might wish to see developed (and in many cases
he was in sympathy with such developments) must now
be postponed in view of the strain placed upon our
financial resources by the war, and also in view
of the fact that every such increase adds to the
rise in wages and costs. In his view the Government
should take a firm line. It would not be fair to
place the odium of refusing to agree on the employers.
THE MINISTER OP LABOUR said that if the
Government were successful in holding a policy of
minimum increase in wages, a sympathetic view must
be taken of the position of the lower paid workers.
He was convinced that workers all over the country
would watch what happened in the case of the
Workmen1 s Compensation Act.
THE MINISTER OP HEALTH said that at a recent
meeting which the Chancellor of the Exchequer had
held in regard to Old Age Pensions, employers had
pointed out the increase to the burden on industry,
and the Chancellor had given them to understand
that it would be necessary to improve the position
of old age pensioners. The question in the
employers' mind was whether the increase in old
age pensions would lead to an increase in health
benefits. Now there was to be a question of further
burden in connection with the Workmen's Compensation
Act. The Chancellor was going to meet the National
Joint Advisory Council on the 6th December to explain
the position frankly to them. In his view all these
matters should be considered together including the
stabilisation of the price of food.
THE PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OP TRADE said that
in his view the important point was what a decision

t o i n c r e a s e Workmen's C o m p e n s a t i o n " b e n e f i t m i g h t l e a d to
r a t h e r t h a n t h e a c t u a l e f f e c t or i n d u s t r y a s t h e t o t a l b u r d en
o n l y a m o u n t e d t o £2 m i l l i o n . . At t h e moment r i s i n g c o s ts
a n d p r i c e s were due t o a l a r g e e x t e n t to m a t t e r s o u t s i d e our
c o n t r o l . Secondly, a l l c l a s s e s would h a v e t o t a k e t h e ir
s h a r e i n p a y i n g f o r t h e war b u t i t was o b v i o u s t h a t c e r t a in
p e o p l e c o u l d n V t , f o r example "those i n r e c e i p t of payment from
t h e Unemployment A s s i s t a n c e Boardo Gould i t be s a i d t h at
men r e c e i v i n g . Workmen's C o m p e n s a t i o n a s s i s t a n c e came i n to
t h i s l a s t c a t e g o r y?
THE MINISTER OF PENSIONS s a i d that he h a d b e e n a t t a c k ed
i n t h e House of Commons on t h e g r o u n d s t h a t t h e C i v i l i an
I n j u r y Scheme was nob s o f a v o u r a b l e as t h e Workmen1s
C o m p e n s a t i o n Scheme, It was h o w e v e r framed l a r g e l y on t h at
s c h e m e . He h a d h a d a d e p u t a t i o n from t h e Seamen a n d Firemen's
U n i o n w a n t i n g t o go b a c k tc Workmen's C o m p e n s a t i o n R a t e so
He d i d n o t t h i n k he c o u l d d e f e n d k e e p i n g c i v i l i a n I n j u ry
r a t e s a t t h e i r p r e s e n t f i g u r e if the o t h e r s were i n c r e a s e d.
He t h o u g h t i t would b e u n w i s e to make any m e n t i o n of r a t es
o f b e n e f i t i n the s t a t e m e n t.
THE LORD PRIVY SEAL a s k e d w h e t h e r it would be
p o s s i b l e t o g e t t h e Royal Commission to c o n t i n u e i ts
e n q u i r i e s . He a l s o a s k e d whether i t would b e p o s s i b l e f or
n y s t a g m u s o r r e h a b i l i t a t i o n t o b e t a k e n i n t o c o n s i d e r a t i o n.
MR. PEAKS s a i d t h a t t n e e m p l o y e r s were i n the
p o s i t i o n of d e f e n d a n t s and t h e y had not s t a r t e d t o make t h e ir
c a s e . There were 400 o r 500 p a g e s of e v i d e n c e p u t f o r w a rd
b y t h e l a b o u r s i d e t o be d e a l t w i t h , and t h e e m p l o y e rs
t h o u g h t t h a t t h e y would be u n a b l e to d e a l w i t h t h i s , b e c a u s e,
a p a r t f r o m ' p r e s s u r e of more u r g e n t work,, it was d i f f i c u l t to
g e t p e o p l e t o c o n c e n t r a t e on s u c h p r o b l e m s d u r i n g t h e w a r.
He h a d e x p l o r e d t h e p o s s i b i l i t y of o b t a i n i n g a s m a l l e r body
f r om t h e r a n k s of t h e Commission t o d e a l w i t h c e r t a i n p a r ts
o f t h e p r o b l e m , b u t i t was c l e a r t h a t n e i t h e r s i d e l i k e d t he
i d e a of r e m i t t i n g a p a r t of the p r o b l e m t o a s m a l l e r body.
The a l t e r n a t i v e was f o r the Government t o t a k e t h e c h a i r as
b e t w e e n t h e two s i d e s .
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND s a i d t h a t he
f o r e s a w a r e c r u d e s c e n c e of L a b o u r P a r t y a c t i v i t y i n so f a r as
H e a l t h s e r v i c e s in S c o t l a n d were c o n c e r n e d and t h e r e would be
s t r o n g p r e s s u r e f o r i n c r e a s i n g Old Age P e n s i o n s and H e a l th
b e n e f i t s . He s h a r e d t h e a p p r e h e n s i o n of t h e M i n i s t e r of
H e a l t h a n d h e would l i k e to h a v e s e e n p r e s s u r e b r o u g h t , if
p o s s i b l e , on t h e e m p l o y e r s to c o n t i n u e t o t a k e t h e i r p a r t in
t h e e n q u i r y.
THE LORD PRIVY SEAL s a i d t h a t if the b a t t l e a g a i n st
i n f l a t i o n was t o be f o u g h t it was n e c e s s a r y f o r t h e Government
t o g e t r i d of weak p o s i t i o n s . It was c l e a r t h a t t h e re
w o u l d h a v e t o b e i n c r e a s e d Unemployment A s s i s t a n c e Board
r e l i e f b u t Workmen % C o m p e n s a t i o n d i d n o t seem t o h im t o be
i n q u i t e t h e same c a t e g o r y , , . On t h e o t h e r h a n d t h e r e was
s u p p o r t on t h e i r own s i d e of che House f o r d e a l i n g w i th
t h e Workmen's C o m p e n s a t i o n q u e s t i o n.
-3r

THE HOME SECRETARY said that he would be most
anxious to keep the door open for the Royal Commission
c-jntinuing its enquiries. The two points which
required decision were in his view, first, whether it
was reasonable to retain 30/- as a maximum and secondly
whether the tapering scale should be retained or modified.
It tapered at present from 75% to 50% and the Minister
of Labour had pointed out the arguments in favour of
adopting 66 2/3% following the International Labour
Recommendation of 19S5 which had been widely adopted.
Some disucssion ensued and the LORD PRIVY SEAL
suggested that the Committee might be prepared to
adopt the suggestion in the Home Secretary's supplementary
memorandum H.P,C.(39) 111, paragraph 2, that the
announcement to be made in the House should at any
rate not refer specifically to rates of benefits but
refer more vaguely to "such provisional legislation as
may be practicable under war conditions". It was
suggested that the statement should include proposals
for dealing with nystagmus problems and rehabilitation
measures.
It was pointed out that a decision about Old Age
Pensions would probably be taken before it was possible
to take a decision with regard to Workmen's Compensation.
THE MINISTER OP HEALTH said that a statement in
the House of Commons to the effect that the Government
would endeavour to formulate some provisional legislation
on the subject of rates of benefits in consultation with
the T.U.C. and representatives of employers and other
interests, would involve some increase in such benefits.
He, therefore, thought that it was not possible to deal
with one side of the question, (Workmen's Compensation),
without considering other sides, such as Old Age Pensions,
Health benefits and so forth. He did not think the
Committee ought to put any recommendation to the War
Cabinet without referring to this point and he suggested
that the words "and would be considered in connection
with other legislation of the same nature" should be
added to the proposed announcement.
THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR SCOTLAND agreed with
this view.
It was pointed out that a statement of this nature
would imply that the Government were contemplating alterations
in other schemes as well which^might lead
to an embarrassing position. THE MINISTER OP
LABOUR said that it was most important that the
Government should not be put in a position in which they
had to deal with these various subjects together as it
was the strategy of the Labour Party to attempt to get
them regarded as a whole, whereas in his view they should
be dealt with separately and on their merits.
It was also pointed out that the question of
increasing benefits under the Unemployment Assistance
Board had been under consideration by the Committee on
Economic Policy. Further, the Chancellor of the
Exchequer had been considering the question of increases
to Old Age Pensions.

A f t e r d i s c u s s i o n , t h e Committee a g r e e d : (
a ) To recommend t h a t t h e War C a b i n e t s h o u ld
a u t h o r i z e t h e Home S e c r e t a r y t o make an
a n n o u n c e m e n t i n t h e House of Commons t h at
he would c o n s i d e r i n c o n s u l t a t i o n w i t h t he
T r a d e Union C o n g r e s s and r e p r e s e n t a t i v es
of e m p l o y e r s and o t h e r i n t e r e s t s , w h e t h er
a n y p r o v i s i o n a l l e g i s l a t i o n f o r amending
t h e Workmen's C o m p e n s a t i o n A c t s s u c h as
may h e p r a c t i c a b l e u n d e r war c o n d i t i o ns
c a n b e f o r m u l a t e d , on t h e u n d e r s t a n d i ng
t h a t t h i s w o u l d be w i t h o u t p r e j u d i c e to
t h e r e c o m m e n d a t i o n of t h e R o y a l Commission
a s t o t h e p r i n c i p l e s t o be a d o p t e d in
p e r m a n e n t l e g i s l a t i o n and t h a t t h e p r o s p e ct
of e a r l y l e g i s l a t i o n d e p e n d s on a hope t h at
s u b s t a n t i a l a g r e e m e n t on t h e p r o v i s i o n al
p r o p o s a l s may b e r e a c h e d . Any s u ch
s t a t e m e n t s h o u l d b e i n s u f f i c i e n t l y g e n e r al
t e r m s to c o v e r o t h e r p o i n t s b e s i d e s b e n e f i t s,
f o r e x a m p l e , n y s t a g m u s.
( b ) T h a t t h e L o r d P r i v y S e a l s h o u l d draw the
a t t e n t i o n of t h e War C a b i n e t t o t h e v i e ws
o f t h e M i n i s t e r of H e a l t h , t h e S e c r e t a ry
o f S t a t e f o r S c o t l a n d , and t h e F i n a n c i al
S e c r e t a r y t o t h e T r e a s u r y , as s e t out
i n t h e d i s c u s s i o n a b o v e , t h a t any amendment
o f t h e Workmen's C o m p e n s a t i o n A c ts
i n v o l v i n g an i n c r e a s e i n r a t e s s h o u ld
b e c o n s i d e r e d i n r e l a t i o n t o p o s s i b le
r e a c t i o n s on b e n e f i t s u n d e r o t h e r s c h e m e s.

</content>
</cab>