<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/17/20 images: 154-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1941.SECRET.W.M. (41)20th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 20 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing StreetrS.W. 1, on Monday, February 24, 1941, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Aircraft Production.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. R. G. Menzies,K.C., M.P., Prime Minister of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. H. D. Margesson,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper,M.P., Minister of Information.The Hon. - Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState, Foreign Office.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Lieut.-General Sir Robert Haining,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[22254]
WAR CABINET 20 (41). QContents.M minute no. Subject. page 1      Mr. Menzies, Prime Minister of Australia ....      ....      ....     1012      Naval, Military and Air Operations, ....      ....      ....      ....     101Naval Operations Shipping losses.The Hipper Class Cruiser.Enemy raiders.Libya.Eritrea.Military Operations Italian Somaliland.3      Blockade................................     101Application to Japan : the Asaka Maru.Relations with Japan.4      The Balkans and the Middle East   ................     102Future military policy.5      Government Departments     ....      ....      ....      ....       ....     102Protected accommodation.6      Man-power        ............................     103Requirements of Fighting and Civil Defence Services.7      Parliament       ........................      ....     103M.P.&apos;s and offices under the Crown.t!
101W.M. 20 (41),Mir. Menzies, 1.   On behalf of the  War Cabinet,  the Prime  MinisterPrime Minister  welcomed Mr. Menzies, the Prime Minister of the Commonwealthof Australia.     of Australia, who would he hoped attend the Meetings of the WarCabinet while he was in this country.   The War Cabinet werefortunate to have Mr. Menzies with them at this juncture.The Prime Minister paid a tribute to the way in which theDominions had made common cause with this country. The relation-ship between the States in the British Commonwealth was uniquein history.Mr. Menzies thanked the Prime Minister for his words ofwelcome, which were warmly endorsed by the War Cabinet.Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 19thConclusions,Minute 2.)naval operations.Shipping Losses.The HipperClass Cruiser.Enemy raiders.Libya.Eritrea.MilitaryOperations.italian somaliland.2. The Chiefs of Staff made the following reports in amplification-tion of the information contained in Cabinet War Room RecordsNos. 537 do 540.There had been serious shipping losses since the last meetingof the War Cabinet. Two outward bound convoys had been attacked by a U-boat; in one case four vessels had been lost. There had beenother losses from mines and aircraft.Air reconnaissance showed the Hipper Class cruiser still indry dock at Brest on the morning of the 23rd February.On the evening of the 22nd February a pocket battleship hadbeen sighted between Madagascar and the Seychelles Islands. Itwas to be feared that the raider had made her escape.A vessel had reported being shelled by a warship raider theprevious day when 500 miles East of St. John&apos;s, Newfoundland,but there was some doubt about this report.H.M. Monitor Terror had been attacked twice from the air,and had been sunk off Derna the previous evening.Seven aircraft of the Fleet Air Aim had carried out a dive-bombing attack on Massawa at dawn on the 21st February. Resultshad been difficult to observe, but it was thought that 3 destroyers and 1 submarine had been hit. More than 35 merchant vessels hadbeen reported in the anchorage.We had captured Jumbo and were advancing in the directionof Brava. A message reported the capture of over 3,000 prisoners and much material on this front. Modun (near Brava) had beenbombarded by H.M.S. Shropshire.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Blockade.Application toJ apan.The AsakaMaru.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 19thConclusions,Minute 3.)[22254]3. The War Cabinet were informed that Lord Halifax had now consulted President Roosevelt about the Asaka Maru. Thelatter had advised against interception of this vessel.The A saka Maru had sailed from Lisbon that morning for an unknown destination. We had as yet no reliable information about her cargo.b 2
Relations with The Prime Minister reported that he had had an interviewJapan. with the Japanese Ambassador in London.   The Ambassador hadprevious said that his  country  had  no aggressive  intentions  againstReference: Australia, Singapore or the Netherlands East Indies.   He had.M. (41) 19th handed the Ambassador a Memorandum in reply to the messageConclusions, from the Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs to Mr. EdenMinute 4.) (Telegrams 216 and 217 to Tokyo).Sir Robert Craigie had also had an interview with the JapaneseForeign Minister. Relations between this country and Japanseemed easier.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The balkans and the middle east.Future military policy.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 19thConclusions,Minute 1.)GovernmentDepartments.protected accommodation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 304th-Conclusions,Minute 3.)them certain telegramsby the Chiefs of Staffs4. The War Cabinet had before(W.P. (41) 38 and 40), and a Report(W.P. (41) 39 (Revise)).A record of the discussion and the conclusions reached is con-tained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet conclusions. The War Cabinet had before them a Report by the Chiefsof Staff on the vulnerability of Whitehall to air attack (W.P. (41)37).In discussion, the following points were made : (i) It was agreed that we should fight the battle fromWhitehall unless and until we were bombed out of it orour communications broke down. Reserve accommoda-tion should, however, be maintained in a state of readiness to meet these eventualities.(ii) Although about 146 H.E. bombs had already fallen within1,000 yards of the Cenotaph the Chief of the Air Staffthought that we must be prepared for a considerablyheavier attack on the Whitehall area.The War Cabinet: (1) Gave general approval to the recommendations in the Chiefsof Staff Report (W.P. (41) 37).(2) Invited the Minister of Aircraft Production, in consulta-tion with the Ministers and Departments concerned, to concert the measures necessary to ensure (a) That a sufficient degree of protection was affordedas rapidly as possible to the accommodationoccupied by essential operational staffs, including in particular the Headquarters of Home Forces.(6) That adequate alternative accommodation was avail-able for Government Departments, particular regard being paid to communications.(3) Agreed that, with a view to ensuring that the Citadels werein proper order, a meeting of the War Cabinet should beheld at &quot;Paddock&quot; at an early date, and the service departments should have a similar try-out of theiralternative quarters.
103W.M. 20 (41):Man-Power. 6.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theRequirements of Minister of Labour and National Service (W.P. (G) (41) 22).Fighting and After a short preliminary discussion, the War Cabinet agreedCivil Defence     as follows : Services. ^ -j;ne decision as to the intake into the Army should not, for(Previous the moment, extend beyond the six months the 1st AprilReference: to the 30th September, 1941. /W.M. (41) 10th (2) The Minister of Labour and National Service and theConclusions, Secretary of State for War should forthwith consultMinute 5.) together with a view to determining the Army&apos;s man-power requirements for the six months April to september 1941, and the measures necessary to meet them, reporting to the War Cabinet as necessary.(3) The decision in (1) should not, however, preclude theSecretary of State for War from continuing to makeadvance arrangements, so far as might be necessary, forstores, buildings, &amp;c, on the basis of his estimate of theArmy&apos;s requirement in man-power over the period to march 1942.(4) The Army&apos;s man-power requirements after the30th September, 1941, should be brought before theCabinet not later than the 1st August, 1941.(5) There was an anticipated requirement of 300,000 men forthe Royal Air Force in the period to March 1942. this it was thought could not be met without recruitment inthe United States of America. The Secretary of Statefor Air was authorised to have preliminary discussions with the Departments concerned as to the measures necessary to give effect to this scheme, without, however,making any approach to the United States authorities at this stage.Parliament.M.P.&apos;s and offices underthe Crown.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 19thConclusions,Minute 14.)7. The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet that it was proposed to publish a White Paper on the following Wednesday,giving particulars of the Members of both Houses who since thewar had accepted offices or employment under the Crown. The listwould show-which Members were employed in an honorary capacity(that is to say, without salary, but with or without expenses&apos;/ andwhich were paid; but it was not proposed to give details of the salaries paid.   To do so would be invidious and embarrassing.The Prime Minister added that while the Bill introduced dealtwith the position during the war, he saw no reason why a SelectCommittee of the House should not be set up to make recommenda-tions in regard to the position in this matter after the war.The War Cabinet approved these suggestions.Great George Street, S.W. 1,February 24, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
