<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/215/10 images: 330-332</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALMENT Is THe PROpERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT C(82) 35COPY NO23 September 1982CABINETPUBLIC SERVICE PAY AND PUBLIC EXPENDITUREIN 1983-84Memorandum by the Chief Secretary, Treasury&quot;        We need now to decide how to deal with public seTrice pay in nahsing the public expenditure plans for 1983-84.    In the Ministerial ^ mmittee on Economic Strategy on 1 July (E(82) 17th Meeting, Item 1) we ^8yeed tha* the aim must be to seek a lower level of settlements throughout economy in the next pay round.    The question of a pay assumption for public services was left for further consideration at the end of September.2.a^      Our plans already contain provision for inflation, covering both pay an ^rices*  * 0 per cent.    That is public knowledge.    We now have to make f0j&gt;exP^ci*: assumption about pay, as we did last year, to provide a firm basis 0  j, Uf Public expenditure discussions and subsequently for the preparation p , fkmates.    The assumption will have to be disclosed when the plans are Pre 8      *n *ate November or early December.    There has already been ai*d th 8pecu*atl n&apos;    Doing nothing would be taken to imply 6 per cent for pay, at would of course be extremely damaging.IVING A LEAD:  THE QUESTION OF ANNOUNCEMENT 3%aniift    ^bat we do, and the manner in which it becomes known or is reacti  e(*&apos; ^^1 have an impact on the private sector and produce a political on from the unions concerned.4.an ^     or 1982-83, we used a general pay factor of 4 per cent, applied to 0f ^ e Public services, and announced it in September.    In the circumstance! 8ettle *aS* **a^ roun&lt;!  this had a moderating effect on public service pay ment8, and gave a useful signal to the rest of the economy.In^j      ^e next pay round will begin against a different background. But    on 18 coming down rapidly.    Some unions are in a less militant mood. mounfrrU&quot;88 iU ^e pUDlic services have been falling behind, and there are Ul*ion 1v,8 Pre8SUres for some &quot;catching up&quot;.    The two biggest Civil Service chancS      6 conferences in December, at which militants would welcome the discus i  lnterpret any announcement as provocation and prejudicial to the inte       n of Megaw,    A specific early announcement would undoubtedly be ^Preted in that sense.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALMoreover, for our expenditure planning we need a figure which is  th credible and tenable.    This may make it less useful this year as a ^gnal to the private sector.    It is for this reason that the Confederation ofrihsh Industry (CBI) only favour an early quantified signal if it is lower than last year&apos;s.7^        For these reasons the Chancellor and I have concluded against a ha.rma* announcement until late November or early December when we shallye a batch of post-survey announcements to make.    This will still be ^ore the union conferences.    But it would be the natural time to disclose 8 among other assumptions embodied in the plans then announced.    If it  ed before then, as must be expected, this may be no bad thing.    It would le us to give a lead without appearing to throw down a gauntlet to the ^ons.P*OPoSED DECISION 8. T^        i propose, therefore, that we decide a single general assumption for (fr Prov*8i-,:&gt;n *n our expenditure plans, and Estimates, for pay increases |V     and^ ^ settlement dates) in 1983-84 for the Civil Service, Armed Forces ^H^ds^^^er public service groups, but that we should not announce this until QaQ 3^|^u^^**n^^ate^rtefl^r&apos; We have to leave the National Health Service on one Reedf r t*ie ^me De*ng&gt; until the present dispute is settled.    There is no ab    t0 make any assumption for the local authorities.    The July statements ^e Ut local authority current expenditure and the Rate Support Grant (RSG) as     maae without reference to pay.    But we can say if necessary that our 8Urnption is consistent with the provision, for local authorities.THE NUMBER 9.^ith h        figure higher than this year&apos;s 4 per cent would be inconsistent e aim of pay settlements lower than last year.reai     With inflation coming down, 4 per cent would be more generous in Cert          403,11 tne same figure last year and might be seen as &apos;easing up&apos;, the tne uni ns will regard it as a floor for negotiations.    This yearit       ^dge settlement was about 6 per cent.    If we choose 4 per cent again, level    e crucial to stress that we are nevertheless seeking a much lower  * settlements next year.n. A1reducti       Wer flgure - perhaps 3 per cent - would point more strongly to a that    on in the level of settlements and be welcome to the CBI and others on *8 that   Unt*    This is of course a very considerable advantage.    The danger value   lt Would he too low to carry conviction, would therefore be of less c nce  8 a 8*8na*&apos; and would provoke unhelpful confrontation with the unions *ts value**&apos; because    would n t De credible, and in the end not tenable,nivick      aS a constraining influence in our expenditure planning would be Weakened.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALThis is a choice which colleagues will wish to *scu.8.    ^ ^nce my own conclusion is in favour of 4 per cent, as the 1  * X^^^ be presented as realistic.    But the need for settlements lower than in the current year must be stressed.13.      when we come to announce or explain this^assumptionwe should Present it as before, not as a forecast, nor as a decxsxon on the &lt;^ to *e -de in any individual case, but as the provision we are makxng; xn^our cash Plans and Estimates for the various programmes. ^^^^^ settlements higher, or lower, than 4 per cent; but xt does xmply^ Won that the additional costs of any higher settlement would be ou^to ^thin existing provisions, by reducing numbers or by  other econorrxies. ^course to the  Contingency Reserve is not necessarily excluded, but equally mere i8 no presumption that it will be allowed.Effect on public expenditurel*.      i shall take account of the effects of this new assumption ab 8**vice pav, and of the latest forecast of prices, xn the proposals aboutpublic e*PenditurI which i shall be putting to Cabinet shortly.    The figures for local authority current expenditure will not be affected.later yearsl5-      We do not need at present to make any specific assumptions about Public service pay in 1984-85 and later years.CONCLUSION16 T1 propose that:-i.       for the cash plans and Supply Estimates we use a single general assumption for increases in pay in 1983-84 of 4 per cent for pubUc service groups apart from the National Health Service (about whom a decision should be deferred).    If necessary, we can say tha t thxs is consistent with the proposals already announced for local authority current expenditure and the RSG settlements;ii.       this decision should not be formally announced until late November or early December;iii. without delay we should take every opportunity to stress the need for settlements in the coming year to be much lower than those in the past year;iv. I should take account of the assumption as appropriate, Programme by programme, in making my proposals to Cabxnet next month about public expenditure.L BTrea8ury Chambers23 September 1982 3CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
