<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 17-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
7 x i(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET COPY NO,C.P. (47 )  104S1ST MARCH.   1947CABINETINTRODUCTION OP FIVE DAY WEEK IN MINING industry memorandum by the Minister of Fuel and power with reference to the discussions which took place at the Cabinet on the 18th March on the above subject(CM. (4-7) 29th Conclusions, Minute 9) I now circulate aletter which I have received from the National Coal Boardabout the introduction of the Five Day Week at the beginningof May.In view of the administrative arrangements whichwill have to be made to prepare for a Five Day Week in the pits the National Goal Board have asked for a reply totheir letter at the earliest possible date.I now therefore ask for a decision whether theNational Coal Board are to be authorised to introduce nextMay a Five Day Week of the present underground hours withthe conditions which they have agreed.E. S.Ministry of Fuel and Power,S. W. 121st March,  194-7.
loNATIONAL COAL BOARDLans&amp;owne House,Berkeley Square,LONDON, W. 1,CONFIDENTIAL &apos;13 th&apos;  -Si;A &apos;        &quot;&apos;      &apos; March j1947My dear Minister, ,,,As you are aware we were approached by the National Union of mineworkers towards the end of last year with a request for the early introduction of the five-day week,     &quot;The Union took up the position -rightly,  in our view- that the principle of the five-day week hadalready been conceded by the Government,&apos;&apos;     They pointed out that theyhad already more than once deferred the date on which they asked thatthe five-day week- should come into operation and that they were unwilling further to- defer it beyond May next.      They asked us tonegotiate with them the conditions which were to be attached to it.After consultation with you, we arranged a programme of discussions with the Union,     We announced that any conditions not agreed by the end of February -would be submitted to arbitrationunder the agreed conciliation machinery and that we would thenannounce the date on which the five-day week should be introduced,subject to the authorisation of the Government,     We made it knownat the same time that, subject to that authorisation, the date would be the beginning of May,I am glad to tell you that after prolonged and often difficult negotiations we have now reached agreement on all points,      I enclosea memorandum embodying the agreed conditions.      This provides fora five-day week with the present underground hours,      The Unionmainta: ned that surface shifts also could not be lengthened withoutinfringing the principle of the five-day week and declined toaccept this as an arbitrable  issue;    but in the end they agreed thatsurface hours should be A-2-g- per week except where existing districtagreements provide for a shorter working week and should be spreadover five shifts.We have included various conditions designed to encourageregular attendance and effort, chief among which is the conditionalbonus payable to men who work their full five shifts in a week.      Inthe case of pieceworkers this is directly related to individual output,During our negotiations the present crisis has arisen,     I neednot set out in this letter its effect on the country&apos;s economic position,  or the importance which attaches to coal production overthe coming year.     You are fully informed of our views about thevolume of production which is to be expected under the five-day weekand about the results which we expect from the measures contemplatedfor increasing production.We have now reached the stage when, according to the programme which we agreed with the Union last December, we ask the government whether we are authorised to introduce the five-day week in May nextwith the conditions which we have agreed.     We should in any casethink it necessary to seek the authorisation of the Government,before/actually
actually giving effect to so far-reaching a change in the structure of the coal industry.     We regard it as even more important today,having regard to the fact that, whilst we all favour the introductionof a five-day week at the earliest practicable date, we do not allbelieve that in present circumstances it will be possible, howevergreat the efforts of management and men, to secure the&apos; country&apos;sminimum needs over the next six   months at least, unless either the sixth shift is still to be worked for a period beyond May or thehours worked underground under a five-day week are to be longer thanthey are now.     We have not negotiated on either of these points,which are regarded by the Union as being outside the scope of our discussions.     They regard an extension of hours as involving,apart from an alteration in the law, a modification of the principle which has been conceded, i0eo, as they claim, a five-day.week&apos; of thepresent underground hours,I should add that, whilst v/e cannot estimate with any assurancethe effect&quot; on cost of a five-day week as now negotiated,&apos; its directeffect at the/start may be of the order of 4/&quot; Ver ton-with o.a.s,at its present level,,     An increase- in o?m.s. would- operate&apos;to reducethe increase in cost,,We would ask you to let us have as soon as possible the government&apos;s decision whether,we are authorised to introduce nextMay a five-day week of the present underground hours with the&apos;conditions which we have agreed,,Yours sincerely,(Sgd) - -The Rt. Hon. Bnanuel Shinwell, M.E.,Ministry of Fuel and Power,7, Milifoank,
SCHEDULE TO BE APPENDED TO AN AGREEMENT BETWEENTHE NATIONAL COAL BOARD AND THE NATIONAL UNIONOF KENEWORKERS FOR THE INTRODUCTION OFTHE FIVE DAY WEEKNormal Working Weak1.     The normal working week for underground workers shall be one of 5consecutive shifts of 7? hours plus one winding time.2.     The normal working week for surface workers employed in or aboutcollieries shall be one of 42-g- hours (exclusive of meal times) to be worked in  consecutive shifts of Si. hours provided that(a) if, under an existing district agreement, any categories of surfaseworkers are working a normal week of less than hours they shall continue to work such lesser number of hours spread.over  consecutive shifts.(b) where the effect of this clause is to lengthen the daily hours of a workman engaged in handling coal he shall not be required to remainbeyond, his present daily hours if he has finished his work.Jo     The Union through its Area or local representatives will enter into arrange-ments with the Board to provide for the regular working of additional shifts by certain categories of workman where the working of such additional shifts isnecessary to ensure the safety of the pit.4.     The Board and the Union through their divisional, area or local represent-atives shall determine by agreement the 5 normal shifts to be worked by eachshift or grade of workman as may be necessary for the most effective working ofthe pit.     Such shifts shall fall within the period extending from the beginningof the Sunday night .shift to the beginning of the Saturday morning shift, exceptthat in the case of faceworkers (other than coal fillers) engaged on preparatory work which forms part of the cycle of operations in double shift seams or pitsthis period may be extended to include the Saturday morning shift.Eligibility for Bonus5.     A workman who works five full qualifying shifts in any week shall bepaid a bonus calculated as provided in clause 18.     A workman&apos;s qualifying shiftsare his five normal shifts or alternatively one or more- full overtime shiftsworked at the request of the management between his first and fifth normal shifttogether with such number of his normal shifts as makes a total of five.     Saveas provided in Clauses 6 and 7 a workman who fails in any week to satisfy theconditions mentioned in this Clause shall not be paid a bonus.
6.     Shifts not worked in any week, due to(a) the occurrence of one or more of the six days comprising the recognised statutory holidays for which payment is made, or(b) reasons which entitle the workman to payment of guaranteed wage,or(c) attendance, by invitation of the Secretary, at a meeting-of the colliery, Area or Divisional Consultative Committee, convenedduring working hours or the carrying out of duties authorised by such committees in respect of Y\toich compensation for loss of -earnings is paidshall, for the purpose of Clause.5, be deemed to have been worked.7.      Shifts not worked or not fully worked in any week due to(a) accident sustained by a workman in tho course of his work in a previous shift of that week (and reported to the appropriateofficial) or to industrial disease (in respect of which he isduly certified) or(b) absence on Trade Union business certified by the Lodge secretary and notified to the appropriate colliery official if practicablebefore the commencement of the shiftshall not be deemed to have been worked, but provided a workman is otherwisequalified in the week in question he shall be entitled to receive a proportionatebonus calculated in accordance with Clause 18.Co-operation in the Interests of Production8.     It is the joint determination of the Board and the Union to establishthroughout the industry a relation of mutual confidence and respect, betweenworkers and managerial personnel at all levels and a spirit of mutual co-operationbased on the recognition of their joint responsibility for a national service.To this end the Board will do everything possible to ensure that all managerialpersonnel act with reason and understanding in carrying out their duties and theUnion will do everything possible to promote and maintain a spirit of selfdiscipline throughout the ranks of its members involving a readiness, to carr-  outall reasonable orders given by the management.     In the event of it beingcontended that either the management or the workmen have acted unreasonably theissue must be resolved in accordance with the agreed procedure.-
&apos; &apos; if   - 3 -9o     The Board and the Union giving due consideration to the socialimplications of all changes involved will co-operate fully in promoting -(i)   recruitment to the industry;(ii)   upgrading and transfer-of workmen in the interests of the most effective utilisation of the coalmining labour force within eachpit, district and na ti onally;(iii)    the modernisation and reorganisation of the industry;(iv)    the proper care, use and maintenance of plant and machinery,,10.    The Union through its Area and local representatives will co-operate withthe management in persuading workmen to work any shifts or parts of shifts out-side their normal working week, where this is necessary in order to ensureproper maintenance and the development of productive capacity.11.    The number of men required to perform given work within each shift or thework to be performed by a given number of men as the case may be shall be assessed by agreement between the management and the men concerned or theirappropriate&quot;representatives as the case may be on the basis of a fair day?s work by the men concerned working thoughout the full time below ground less agreedtravelling and meal times.      In case of difference between the men concerned andthe management it shall be settled by reference to the pit conciliation machinery.The Union will not countenance any restriction of effort by workmen resulting infailure to perform the work so assessed.12. &apos; Underground workmen shall make every effort to complete the cycle of operations within the shift time and the Union will co-operate in securing &quot;theagreement of the workmen if the Management so desire,&quot;to work reasonable overtimewhere, due to unforeseen circumstances, it is necessary in order to complete thecycle.13,    In the event of a workman&apos;s normal work not being available, he shall performany alternative work which he is competent to undertake and is required bjr themanagement to perform.      If a workman being of the opinion that he ought not reasonably to have been expected to perform any such alternative work objects tothe instructions given to him by the Management, he shall, nevertheless, carrythem out to the best of his ability and thereafter submit his objection inaccordance with the i.rovisions of the Pit Conciliation Scheme.14-    So far as is compatible with safe working workmen shall do their utmost toincrease output by cleaning up spillage on both sides of the conveyor and byrecovering loose coal and coal from the waste.
15*   The Management may, in co-operation with the appropriate representativesof the workmen and with the approval of H.M. Inspectors determine (on a rota&quot;basis or otherwise) separate winding times for different sections or districts of a pit so that the workmen will descend by sections in a specified order andascend in the same order and their obligation to present themselves within the separate winding times so determined for them respectively, shall be the same asit now is as regards existing winding times.l6o   Having descended the pit workmen shall proceed without delay to theirinspection station and to their place of work or where man riding facilities areavailable to their man riding station,17&quot;    The Union shall, unless they are of the opinion that such alteration is unreasonable, co-operate in securing the acceptance by the workmen of any alteration in existing shift times desired by the Management in the interests ofthe most effective working of the pit and determined in the exercise of theManagement&apos;s statutory right under the Coal Mines Act 1911,Terms as to Payment18.    The amount of the bonus payment referred to in clauses 5 and 7 shall be -(a) for a daywageman qualifying under clause 5 his average day wagerate for the week in question including the war addition and the skilled shilling (if payable) but excluding other allowances(b) for a daywageman qualifying under clause 7 &quot;the same proportion ofthe bonus which he would have received under (a) as the number ofqualifying shifts worked or deemed to have been worked by him in that week bears to five(c) for a pieceworker (whether qualifying under clause 5 or clause 7)16 per cent of his aggregate earnings (excluding overtime) inrespect of his qualifying shifts in that week with a minimum of  1(or the appropriate proportion of  1 where he qualifies for bonusin respect of less than five shifts).19;.    (l)   -The national weekly minimum wage shall be payable to all workers who in any week work five qualifying shifts or any larger number of shifts w   ohthey are under agreement to work.     For the purpose of this clause shiftsnot worked in any week due to the causes mentioned in Clause 6(a), (b) and&apos;        (c) shall be deemed to have been worked and the holiday payments guaranteed
wage or compensation for loss of earnings shall be taken into account when determining the amount of the payment by way of make-up to the minimumdue in respect of that week. .-(2)    In any week in which(a) a workman qualifies for a proportionate bonus under clause 7j    or(b) a workman who is under agreement to work more than fiveshifts qualifies for the full bonus under clause p butfails to work the full number of shifts which he isunder agreement to work  the daily minimum applicable to the shifts which he actually works shallbe his weekly minimum wage divided by five or, if he be under agreement towork more than five shifts, by the number of shifts which he is underagreement to work.(3)    In any week in which a workman fails to qualify for any bonus the&apos;dailyminimum applicable to the shifts which he actually works shall be bis weeklyminimum wage divided by six or, if he be under agreement to work sevenshifts, by seven-,    provided that a workman who when this agreement comes into force is entitled to a daily minimum higher than would be produced bythis formula shall continue to be entitled to such higher minimum so longas he remains at that pit or works at any other pit at which similarlycalculated minima are in force.,20.    Subject to the authorisation of the National Reference Tribunal sub-paras.(l) and (2) of the Fifth Award shall be amended as follows:(l)    Payment for weekend work and over-time shall be at the rate of double and one and one half times the normal rates respectively.(2)   Weekend work shall comprise all work done during a period beginning with the commencement of the Saturday afternoon shift and ending withthe commencement of the Sunday night shift.21.   Where any period worked is less than a full shift, payment at plain time or at the appropriate overtime rate, as the case may be, shall be made for thatperiod and not for a full shift.22.   The shilling per shift worked payable to certain categories of workmen inaccordance with the provisions of the National Wage Agreement of April 1944, shall continue to be paid in addition to the minimum.13th March, 1947

note the attached paper,CP. (1+7)  105?  is circulated inconnection with. Item k on theAgenda for tomorrow&apos;s Cabinet,Tuesdays  25th March,  19U-7.Cabinet Office,  Sfff. 1,21+th March.  102+7;*

</content>
</cab>
