<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 41-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT 18 THE PROPERTY OP HIE BRITAUNIC -liAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)S E G R E TCP. (47)   10326TH MARCH.  1947CABINETDOMESTIC FUEL RATIONINGMemorandum by the Minister of Fuel and powers draft statement shout fuel rationing on the lines suggested by the Prime Minister at the Meeting of the Cabineton 25th March,  (CM. (47)  32nd Conclusion, Minute 6),  is annexed.It embodies the Cabinet decision to continue throughout the summer the existing restrictions on the consumption of electricitybetween certains hours of the day and. to extend thoserestrictions to the consumption of gas.2*      On reconsideration, however,  I feel that these restrictionsrequire modification in certain respects  if they are to becontinued in the Summer.      In their present form some of the mare vexatious to the public and of little use as a means of saving fuel,  in particular, those applied during specifiedhours to lifts, lighting and the miscellaneous uses (the radioset, the electric iron, the vacuum cleaner and the refrigerator).I would not propose to continue these uses in the newrestrictions.3.      I do not think it would he unreasonable to have a prohibition throughout the whole 24 hours on the use of gas and electricity for space heating of residential premises duringthe Summer months, say from 1st May to 30th September,  subjectto exceptions on medical certificate for illness and possibly to lifting the ban (as is done with the present prohibition on central heating) during a cold spell.4.      Further, we might, I think, prohibit the use of gas and electricity for cooking and. water heating during certain hourseach day and,  in the light of experience of the present restrictions, I would suggest the hours of 9 a.in. to 11.30 am.and 2 to 4 p.m.5.      These proposals would provide some fuel saving, but it isnot possible to estimate what it would, be.     Enforcement wouldbe difficult and., as we cannot contemplate taking powers forinspectors to enter and search premises, it would rarely bepossible to obtain evidence for a prosecution,,     Accordingly,these measures would need to be supported by a strong fuel economy campaign and if these proposals are approved, I will arrange for one to be set in motion,6.     Discussions are taking place  between. my Department and thevarious trade organisations representing &quot;establishments&quot;,shops, offices,  hotels, places of entertainment, etc.  on the steps to be taken to secure fuel economy during the Summer.In general, the aim will be to limit them to a proportion of previous consumption, but in view of the wide variation inthe needs of these establishments we shall have to rely on voluntary co-operation and not  impose statutory obligations.
7,     On the assumption that the Cabinet accept my recommendationsthere is for consideration, an alternative form of words in thedraft statement.      At this  stage, and until there has &quot;beenproper  consultation with the Supply  industries, and inparticular, with the gas industry, the announcement should bekept in a general form and should not go into details.
annex draft PARLIAMENTARY statement the Government have had under consideration the possibilityof rationing the domestic consumption of gas and electricity.Several alternatives have been examined but all suffer fromgrave disadvantages from the point of view of enforcementand equity.      Not only would the complications of the schemesbe considerable in relation to the possible saving of gas and electricity during the Sunnier months &quot;but also the schemes would require a large staff which in present circumstances itwould be hard to recruit.     For the time being the Governmenthave accordingly decided not to introduce a rationing scheme,but because of the need to check domestic consumption they/propose to continue throughout the Summer months the existing restrictions on the consumption of electricity between certainhours of the day and to extend those restrictions to.theconsumption of gas/   /will shortly &quot;be announcing newrestrictions applying to the use of gas as    well as electricityfor the purpose of heating rooms during the Summer months:there will also be some variation of the present prohibitionin its application to cooking, water heating and other purposes/7.Meanwhile, the existing restrictions on the use ofelectricity during certains hours must be maintained and theGovernment must call upon the public for their co-operationduring the corning months in securing the utmost economy inthe domestic use of fuel,  in order to make available to industry the additional supplies of coal,  gas and electricitythat will be needed to keep industry running and to build upstocks for the Winter.      Domestic consumption will be kept under close review and the question whether there should be a rationing scheme will be considered again for the end of the summer in the light of the response made by the public tothis appeal for fuel economy.NOTE:      It is hoped to he ready with a furtherannouncement by the end of next week whenthe necessary consultation with the gasand electricity industries has taken place.

note the attached paper,CP. (47) 109,  is circulated inconnection with Item 3 on theAgenda for tomorrow&apos;s Cabinet,Thursday,  27th March,  1947.Cabinet Office, S.W.1.26th March,   1947.

</content>
</cab>
