<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 235-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT).BE; OR E T COPY NO.   - :   &apos;CP- (J-i-7) 11729th MafchP 19U7*CABINETJAPANESE REPARATIONSMemorandum &quot;by the Minister of state attach a note &quot;by the Chairman of the ParEastern (Official) Committee covering a memorandum on aproposal put forward by the United States representative on the Par Eastern Commission that limited allocations onaccount of Japanese reparations should be made at once tocertain countries which were occupied and devastated bythe Japanese.      Details of the plan are given in paragraph 3of the memorandum.The members of the Par Eastern Commission willbe called upon at a special meeting to be held on,  or very soon after,  the 1st April,  to give the final views of their governments upon the American proposal.      It is most desirable that H.M. Representative should be in a positionto state the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government at thismeeting.:    The matter is therefore one of urgency.I invite my colleagues to agree to therecommendations contained in paragraph 15 of the memorandum.H. McN*Foreign Office,  S.W.1.29th March,  19U7.
ANNEXJAPANESE REPARATIONSNote by the Chairman of the Par Eastern (Official)committee at their meeting on 13th January,  1947,  the cabinet considered an American plan for resolving the deadlockreached on the Par Eastern Commission over japanese reparations as a result of the refusal of the SovietGovernment to agree to the inclusion of Japanese overseasassets in the Reparations Pool.    Under this plan the UnitedStates Government proposed that they&apos;should issue &quot;interimdirectives&quot; to the Supreme Commander, Allied Powers in Japan,to enable reparations&apos;  deliveries to begin.    The cabinet decided that the reply to be returned to the United StatesGovermrient should explain the political objections to thiscourse,  but should promise the support of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment if,  after considering these objections,  theUnited States Government decided to proceed with their proposal.Information.Unas recently been received from washington to the effect that the United States Governmenthave decided to abandon their -plan of issuing &quot;interimdirectives&quot;, that the problem   had been returned to the far Eastern Commission,  find that the United states representative on the Commission had made a proposal tothe Commission that limited allocations on account of .reparations should be made to certain countries which hadbeen occupied and devastated by the Japanese.    The proposedextent of these limited deliveries was to be 30vb ofthe material covered by the Commission&apos;s interim removalsprogramme;       the   number of countries was to be kept verysmall.    In discussion on the Commission, however,  it hasbeen urged by some representatives that the extent ofthe assistance which should be made available should beas high as 70% of the interim programme and that the numberof countries benefitting should be considerably extended.The United States Government have asked for the viewsof His Majesty&apos;s Government on the question.
The implications of the new American proposal have been examined by the E.I.p.3. Committee and the Par Eastern(Official) Committee and arc set out in the attached memorandum which has been agreed by both Committees.    Their recommendations are contained in paragraph 15 of the memorandum.    Briefly,it is recommended that the new plan should be accepted subjectto certain conditions if there is a reasonable chance of itsleading to an early agreement in the Par Eastern Commission.(Signed)    M.E. DENING21ST MARCH, 191+7
-AAPPsroixADVANCE TRANSFERS OP JAPANESE REP RATIGMSle     The Cabinet at its meeting on 13th January agreed thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom should support   &quot;the United States proposal for the distribution of japanese reparations by the issue of interim directives, if theUnited States Government reached the conclusion that nofurther progress towards a solution could be made withinthe Par Eastern Commission.    These interim directives wouldbe made   in full    consultation with such other members ofthe Par Eastern Commission as wished to participate and HisMajesty&apos;s Government would accept the United States Government&apos;invitation to participate.2.      In reaching these conclusions His Majesty&apos;s government felt some mis-givings,  as did some of the Dominions, as tothe political consequences of the interim directives procedurebut were persuaded to agree to the American proposal byconsideration of the urgency of enabling at least somedeliveries of reparations plant to begin,.    It was foreseenthat the Russians would almost certainly object to theproposed procedures    It has now been learnt (Washingtontelegrams Nos:  952 of 15th February and 995 of 15th February)that the United States Government have in fact abandonedtheir plans for the issue of interim directives and decidedto return the problem to the Par Eastern Commission.    Theyhave accordingly put forward for consideration by the Commissionproposals for a programme of immediate deliveries of a proportion of the reparations items declared as available under the interim removals agreement.3.      The Par Eastern (Official) Committee at its meetingon the 18th February invited the E.I.P.S.  Committee to study the implications of this latest United States plan and to report to.the Official   Committee as a matter- of urgency..   The planproposes:(i)    30% of the items covered by the Par eastern commission interim removals agreements and designated by Supreme Commander, Allied powers,  shallimmediately be made available for transfer.(ii)    The beneficiaries of these advance transfers areto be China 15%;  the Philippines 5%;  theNetherlands 5% and the United Kingdom (forMalaya and Burma) 5%; the allocations within these percentages to be made by S.G.A..P.(iii)   The beneficiaries must supply evidence toS.C.A.P.  that they can employ the assetsimmediately and usefully in relief andr ahabilita t i on me asures.(iv)   None    of    the beneficiaries shall receive morethan its allotted percentage of any singlecategory of assets available and within these categories 3.C.A.P. will designate for deliverysuch a balanced selection of items as will not represent a disproportionate deduction of thevalue or quality of the items remaining for later alloc at ion.
(v)   Deliveries under this scheme will be treatedas advances against the final reparationsshare of the beneficiaries.4. This plan offers no solution to the deadlock in negotiationsfor an overall reparations settlement. It &quot;may in fact prejudice the possibility of a solution on the lines advocated by His Majesty&apos;s Government.    His Majesty&apos;s Government havetaken the view that the division of shares of reparationsbetween the Allies should be agreed before any allocationsor plans for removals   is   made.        His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave also taken the view that the division of shares must take into account both external and internal assets.    Henceno agreement can be reached on percentage shares until thevexed question of the inclusion of Japanese external assetshas been settled.    Agreement to the present plan regarded asapreliminary step towards a reparations settlement would prejudice this whole doctrine.    The clanger that this will lead to an extension of the principle of allocating Internalassets separately, without regard to external assets,  is brought out by the fact that immediately the plan was mentioned,proposals were made for its extension to cover 50% or even70% of available internal assets (Washington telegram No: 995).5.      The plan proposes to allocate certain percentages of japanese internal assets to a select few of the claimantsto Japanese reparations.    The percentages proposed in theplan are percentages of the total of items covered by the far Eastern Commission interim removals agreements anddesignated under these agreements by 8.C.A. P.  as availablefor removal.    But it is now becoming clear that the assetsalready declared as available for reparations are very likelyto be a substantial proportion of all reparations from Japan.    Itis unlikely that further agreements of the Par Eastern commission will make available for reparations any further, large amount,of plant and equipment in the categories covered by thescheme.    Therefore the 3Cy.j proposed for advance transfermust be regarded as about SOjo of all Japanese internalassets in the final reparations pool.    To agree to distribute30% of Japanese internal assets   on the basis proposedby the present scheme is to go a good way towards subscribingto the Russian theory of reparations i.e. to distributeJapanese internal assets without regard to the amounts of external assets held by the recipients,6.      The present plan, making no reference to Japaneseexternal assets held by recipients, proposes that China should receive 15&apos;si of certain Japanese internal assets.But in view of the very large amount of Japanese assets in China it is not considered that China should receiveas much as 15% of all Japanese internal assets andexception should be taken to so large an allocation in an initial or advance distribution, more especially as theproposed allocation to China is as much as 50% of thetotal the scheme is designed to allocate and three times the amount it is proposed to allocate to the United Kingdom(for Burma and Malaya),    It cannot be thought that China
1 V PI J 0will be satisfied to receive nothing in later allocationsor that she will refrain from using the proportions ofthe present proposed allocations as precedents for demandinga substantial share of future allocations.    Even if HisMajesty&apos;s Government were induced to agree to the figureof 15/o as a final share for China from Japanese internalassets, we should wish to assure ourselves a larger shareactually and relatively to China in auccesaive transfers,7.      A further disadvantage of the plan is that the proposed allocation to the United Kingdom is for Burma and Malaya only.His Majesty&apos;s Government could not agree to the singlingout of these two countries tc be the only beneficiariesof an early distribution of reparations assets and it isnoted with approval that His Majesty&apos;s representative in washington suggested that the United Kingdom allocationshould be for Burma and &quot;certain Colonial territories in SouthEast Asia&quot; in order to take care of the interests of borneo and Hongkong.    This suggestion, His Majesty&apos;s representativereports, Was favourably received.    There is, however, noreason why all the four territories concerned should not be mentioned by name and His Majesty&apos;s representative mightpress for this,,    The Colonial Office have pointed out that theallocation of a total of only 5% to these four geographicallyseparate territories seems small.    They were all occupiedby the enemy and in none of them is there any substantial amount of Japanese external assets to set off against thevery small initial allocation of internal assets they may expect to receive to assist them in their task of rehabilitat ion.8.      There are, however, certain immediate and importantadvantages to the proposed plan.    In the first place,if itis adopted some of the urgent needs of war ravaged countries could be met from what is,  in the case of some requirements,the only possible source of supply.    The criteria ofdevastation and urgent need of materials for rehabilitation,while they are not points which His Mfiiosty&apos;s Governmenthave advocated as a basis for reparations allocations,must nevertheless command much sympathyon humanitarian grounds.    Moreover,  there is the aaaitionaladvantage that they would seem to be the only criteria whichwould make it possible to limit the number of claimants toan initial share-out and thus afford some prospect of reachingearly agreement on an interim deliveries programme whilethe thorny issues which hive resisted solution for over ayear are still under discussion.9,      In the second place, it is likely that the United StatesGovernment are under pressure from S.CA.P.  to do anything to make possible the early removal of a -proportion of the reparations items declared as&apos;available under the interimremovals agreements.    The non-removal of items designatedand taken under S.C.A.P.&apos;s custody for reparations may becausing S.CA.P.  embarrassment quite apart from the factthat the items themselves may be deteriorating.    As anemergency measure to solve this particular problem in a
practical manner the present proposal has something to commend, it.    Indeed the arguments of urgency which led theCabinet to agree the previous proposal apply with equal force to this plan which has the additional advantage ofupholding the competence of the Far Eastern Commission todeal with reparations.,10.    It may be noted that Sir George Sansom has reportedthat the United States Government have introduced this plan in this particular form because they think it is the onlyone.which offers possibility of speedy agreement.    He addsthat the Americans are opposed to any extensions to cover a wider field of claimants because they consider that the consequent discussion of percentages would lead to long delay.Sir George Sansom was urged privately by the United states representative at the Commission tc persuade His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to agree to the new plan because otherwise itwould be necessary to return to the interim directiveprocedure, opposition to which was considerable both inthe United States administration and among members of theCommission.    The United States representative added that ifthe new plan did not get through within a fortnight hethought that &quot;we should get into most undesirable difficulties&quot;.In reply to a request for elucidation of the phrase&quot;undesirable difficulties&quot; Sir George Sansom has explainedthat a certain section of American official opinion hasadvocated that the United States Government should proceedto the Issue of interim directives without consultation and that resort to this alternative was meant by the phrasein question.11. There are, therefore, strong arguments for and against the acceptance of the proposed plan. Whileacceptance involves considerable risks,, itis probable that, on grounds of policy, it would be better to agree to the plan as an emergency measure if -there isa reasonable chance of its being agreed by the Far eastern commission at an early date;    and if it can be ensured thatthe plan is carried into effect only for the purposes and.on the scale of the original United States proposal,  andis not so extended as to introduce the different principleof allocating separately Japanese internal assets without regard to the external assets retained by any recipientcountry.12.   Pending formulation of the views of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom it has been thought&apos;inappropriate to seek the views of Canada, Australia,..New Zealand and India, but the following information regarding the attitudes of these countries is available:-canada the Canadian Government have - accepted the american proposal.
australia the Government of Australia have opposed theproposal.It has been learnt that the Australian government sopposition to the plan is based on:(a) their view that overall percentage sharesshould first be determined;(b) their view that relief is a bad principle on which to settle reparations divisions;(c) their contention that the degree of discretionextended to S.C.A.P.  is unwise.They further state that if there is&apos;to be a selection of initial beneficiaries,then New Guinea. Papua and Nauruqualify for inclusion.It would appear that the case for the inclusion ofNew Guinea, Papua and Nauru under the American criteria isprobably quite&apos; as strong as the case for the inclusionof e. g. Borneo, but, as has already been pointed out,proposals for extensions to the plan would alter its wholepurpose and character.    It is therefore suggested that ifit appears that some provision for the needs of the three territories would enable the Australian Government toagree to the plan, the United Kingdom representative should propose that the territories concerned should receive a partof the United Kingdom allocation and be listed as recipientswith the other British territories occupied by the Japanese.New zealand the New Zealand Government have concurred semi-officially in the proposal *IndiaIndia&apos;s initial reactions, as voiced by the Indianrepresentative in Committee No. 1 of the Far Eastern Commissi*(Washington Telegram No. 995) were that India and Indo-Ohina,or better still, all countries, should be included in theproposed distribution.    It has since been learnt (washington telegram No. 1492) that India is opposed to the American planbecause she is not named as a beneficiary.    Sir George Saris omhas reported that the United States have evidently&apos;committeda tactical error in omitting India from their list, and itis possible,(though unlikely in view of the developmentsreferred to in paragraph 13 below) that a disposition to add India to the list might emerge in the course of further discussions in the Comniissiono
JL ij ejj13*    The French Embassy in London have informed theForeign Office that the French delegate on the Far eastern commission has been instructed to put forward a strong claim that the French Union,  on behalf of Indo-China,  should beincluded among the beneficiaries under the American planeHe is to suggest that the proportion of Japanese reparationsmaterial to be distributed at once should be raised to 40%,which would enable Indo-China and India to receive 5% each.The French Government believe that their proposal will havethe support of Australia and India, and they express the hopethat His Majesty&apos;s Government  in the United Kingdom will alsobe willing to support it.    There is,  of.course, no questionof contesting the right of France to receive her fair shareof Japanese reparations, when the final settlement is made.The American plan   is, however, an emergency scheme with a strictly limited purpose.    To admit any other country(however deserving) in addition to those proposed would open the door to the inclusion of all countries on theFar Eastern Commission.    This would at once involve theissue of Soviet participation before a decision had beenreached on the overseas assets problem.    It would implyacceptance of the Soviet thesis which has been consistentlyopposed by His Majesty&apos;s Government and all other governments or&apos; the Far Eastern Commission.    The United States member on the Commission has informed the United Kingdom delegateprivately that his Government could not agree to any variation of the plan,  for the reasons indicated above.    The plan is,  in fact,  one which must either be accepted as It standsor rejected.    The French proposal is open to too manyobjections to be supported but it may be assumed that theUnited States will be ready to bear the brunt of opposingit in&quot;the Commission.lk*   The virtues of the plan as it stands and the danger of agreeing to any extensions have now been very clearly brought out by the attitude which the Soviet Government have adopted.The Soviet member stated in the Far Eastern Commission on12th March that his Government would approve the American planprovided the U.S.S.E.  were included as an initial beneficiary.The Soviet Government would welcome the inclusion of alleleven countries.    They proposed that the total quantityof reparations to be distributed under the plan should beraised to 40 or 50%.    They&apos;would themselves require a minimum of 5% of advance transfers, but made it clear that they wouldnot be content with as little as 5% as their allocation in thefinal division of shares.    There is nothing unexpected in theSoviet attitude.    The Russian amendment would destroy thebasis and raison. d&apos; tre of the new American plan.    Anextension of the plan along the lines proposed by the russians would cut right across the policy on Japanese reparationswhich His Majesty&apos;s Government have always maintained.Since the Soviet Government have the power of veto, there now appears to be little or no&apos;possibility of the plan being accepted by the Comoiission, but this does not affect thedesirability of defining His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s attitudetowards it/   The United States Government have particularly asked for an early indication of our views.
15 .    R ec recommend t i onsIt is recommended that:-His Majesty&apos;s representative on the Par eastern commission be authorised to state thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government in the United kingdom are willing to agree to a plan along the lines proposed,amended to cover all British territoriesoccupied by the Japanese, i.e. Burma, Malaya,&apos;Hongkong, Borneo, and if agreed with Australia,New Guinea, Papua and Nauru,   if there is areasonable chance of this leading to an early agreement in the Far Eastern Coinmission   andon the clear understanding that His Majesty!sGovernment:-(a) t\?eagreeing to the plan as an emergencymeasure for the purposes declared in theplan, i. e., relief and rehabilitation,and would oppose any extension ofallocations on this basis;(b) consider it important that percentagesallocated under the scheme should not betaken as in any way creating a precedent for the percentages to be allocated inthe final division of shares;(c) maintain their view that the Japanese externalassets must be included in the pool of assets available in the final reparationssettlement;(d) pending investigation of the amount of japanese external assets taken over byChina and a comparison of this amount withthat to be agreed as China&apos;s share oftotal Japanese assets, reserve their view on what is an appropriate initial percentagefor China and suggest that in themeantime she should not be allocatedmore than 10% of items in any categorycovered by the scheme.


</content>
</cab>
