<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 264-278</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF  his OSCULATED ISorifrtfc).,., ft ^^QxtvVBRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;&quot;S&quot; G01TERWMENT&apos;Printed for the Cabinet.   April 194&apos;SECRETCP. (37) 121IWh April, 1947CAB IN 1stCIVIL SERVICE MAN-POWERReport from the Civil Service Man-Power CommittefI. introductory. The Civil Service Man-Power Committee was set up in accordance witha Minute by the Prime Minister (CP. (46) 431) to deal with the increasing demands made by the Civil Service on national man-power.2. With the assistance of an Official Committee we have completed a survey of 22 of the larger Departments covering 90 per cent, of the Civil Service. Oursurvey related in particular to the more immediate future, but also included a forecast of the position as it may be expected to develop over the next 5 years.This memorandum sets out our broad findings and conclusions. The detailedresults of the survey are set out in the annex.II. Future Trends3. Assuming no major changes of policy, the main factors which will affectthe size of the Civil Service over the next few years are : In the direction of decrease: (a) The gradual abolition of rationing and other controls.(&amp;) The completion of terminal wrork resulting from the war or resettle-ment, e.g., in the Service and Supply Departments, the Ministryof Labour and the War Damage Commission.(c) Administrative economies to ensure greater efficiency and saveman-power.In the direction of increase.- (a) Social Service developments, e.g., national insurance, the health services.(&amp;) Socialisation and the increasing part played by Government in economic matters, e.g., in civil aviation, town and country planning, agriculture, &amp;c.III. The Outlook in Numbers4. The starting point of our survey is that the non-industrial Civil service at 1st October, 1946, numbered 713,500. In the immediate future (i.e., the18 months ending April 1948) the figures given to us by Departments, so farfrom showing a prospective net decrease, showed that the Service must beexpected to increase.   The main reason for increases are : (a) The development of social services notably the introduction of the fullNational Insurance scheme from 1st April, 1948, the implementation of the Education Act, 1944, at a reasonably high rate of progress,and new work arising under the National Health Act, 1945. Theseaccount for anticipated increases over October 1946 of 20,000 bvApril 1948.[33439] b
a(b) The more active part which the Government is playing in trade andindustry, e.g., the Ministry of Agriculture&apos;s work in developing fullhome food production, and the development of airport services underthe Ministry of Civil Aviation. The increase here by April 1948 is put at 16,000.(o) The necessary parallel expansion in agency services, notably by theMinistry of Works.5. Against these immediate increases will be reductions in the staff of theService and Supply Departments which had already by October 1946 reduced their civilian staffs 80,000 below their war-time peak. In the 18 months endingApril 1948 they will be able to make further savings of 18,000. (The reasons why this decrease will not be larger are explained in paragraphs 8-11 of the annex.)6. Looking ahead over a longer, period, there will be substantial reductions in the Civil Service as a whole. Thus by 1952 the Service and Supply Depart-ments expect to reduce their staffs by 32,000 (i.e., in addition to the figures givenin the preceding paragraph). In addition, as shortages of food and other commodities disappear there will be savings over a number of Departments ofsome 45,000 on the withdrawal of rationing and controls. The total ultimatesaving below the October 1946 figure to be foreseen from the conclusion of war-time terminal activities and from the withdrawal of controls is of the order of105,000.7. These factors taken together may be expected to produce a total non-industrial Service at April 1948 of 740,000. This is the peak figure, after which there will be a gradual decline to a total of the order of 640,000-650,000unless future new duties are imposed.IY.-The Peak at April 19488. The increase as at April 1948 to the figure of 740,000 mentioned above is due in the main to two changes which will be the result of Government legisla-tion, but which are &quot; paper adjustments &quot; rather than real increases, namely : (a) the increase of the staff at the Ministry of National Insurance by 16,000between October 1947 and April 1948 to a total of 32,000 will takeplace largely by the transfer of staffs now engaged on similar workin the employment of Approved Societies (staffs of these societies now engaged on this work number 10,000 whole time and 80,000 part time);(&amp;) an increase of 10,000 in the staff of the Ministry of Agriculture owingto the transfer to direct national emolovment of staffs now engaged on similar work in the employment of County agricultural committees.9. If it were not for these two increases it could be said that the non-industrial Civil Service has now about reached its peak, and we have consideredthe case for avoiding the further paper increase to April 1948 by postponing the transfer of staffs until countervailing decreases can be shown. In our view,however, such a step would not be worth while. In neither case does the transferrepresent a drain on man-power which would otherwise be available for more productive employment.V. Administrative Economies10. \\ e have examined a number of suggestions for carrying out theGovernments policy with fewer staffs, and would like here to mention two ofthese in particular : (a) The possibility of doubling up the local and regional offices projectedon a large scale by the Ministry of National Insurance with theexisting offices of the..Ministry of Labour and/or the assistance board.We do not recommend the setting up of a combined organisation under a single Minister of Labour and National Insurance in chargeof a staff using a single set of offices and records. While this might result in some immediate staff economies, the prospect of substantialstaff economies would be remote in the absence of better and largeroffices, since the existing Employment Exchanges are not of a type which could support an amalgamated service.
315 yWe do, however, favour the complete merger of the Ministryof National Insurance and Assistance Board departmental machines.Under this arrangement, the Assistance Board would continue to beresponsible for Assistance policy, but would work wholly through a unified departmental machine run by the Ministry of national insurance. The resulting economies of staff might not be very large in the first instance, but would increase with the development ofinterchangeability within the new combined service.(&amp;) The quality of the Civil Service has been diluted by war-time engage-ment of temporary staffs, and despite the longer hours being worked,output and efficiency may be below the pre-war standard. Improve-ment depends, first and foremost, on the programme, which is well advanced, of rapid recruitment and training of young and well-qualified staff to the established ranks in place of the less efficient.The effect will be improved output per Civil Servant but largeeconomies under this head cannot be expected in the short run.Indeed, training (which is an investment in the long run) calls forthe time being for some temporary additions to numbers.11. Other suggestions for administrative economies are described in the annex to this paper. They are being energetically pursued. But it should notbe thought that they will result in very substantial savings.YI.-Staffs of Public Boards, &amp;c.12. It is perhaps not within our terms of reference to express a judgment on the suggestion made to us that these bodies are tending to add appreciablyto the administrative and! clerical &quot; overheads &quot; of the industry with whichthey are concerned. But we think it right to bring this suggestion to the noticeof our colleagues and to mention that every new public Board which is &quot; serviced &quot;by a Government Department, e.g., the Ministry of Works, Stationery Office.Ordnance Survey, adds to the pressure of work and increases the difficulty ofstaff reductions in those Government Departments. We accordingly recommend-further examination of this matter.YII. The Limited Scope for Cuts13. On 3rd March, 1947, we imposed a temporary standstill at the levelof the numbers of staff in post at 1st January, 1947, which was not, without special permission, to be exceeded by 1st April, 1947 (Treasury Circular 7/47).The halt thus called should enable us for the time being to hold the figure at1st April, 1947, at no more than 3,000-4.000 above 1st January, 1947, figure,although Departments had themselves forecast an increase of 16,000 at thatdate. But most at any rate of this saving must be regarded as a temporarypostponement only, so long as the factors making for increase to the figure of740,000 at April 1948 persist. We have explained why we do not recommendspecial measures to avoid that part of the increase which is due to transfers;in addition to these &quot; paper adjustments,&quot; the forecast for April 1948 takes account of increases flowing directly from the Governments legislative pro-gramme, e.g., development of the health services, education, civil aviation, and town and country planning, which together account for increases of 6,500. savings to be had from administrative economies do not offer the prospect of anygeneral cuts of substantial size if Departments are to discharge the duties laid upon them.YIII. Conclusions14. Our main finding is that we are satisfied that the present numbers ofnon-mdustrial Civil Servants are barely adequate to discharge efficiently the tasks placed upon them by the policy of the Government. At every point inour enquiry we have been impressed by the close relation between duties andstaffs. We cannot escape the weight of the evidence that anything&apos; of the natureof an arbitrary cut in the overall size of the Civil Service would need to be associated with a policy decision to abandon a corresponding proportion of duties and services. We have not found is possible save in certain relatively minorinstances, e.g., by the curtailment of more improvements of postal services [33439] B 2
to suggest duties and services which should be so abandoned. But we would emphasise that if the Cabinet attaches cardinal importance to effecting sub- jstantial reductions, it will be necessary for them to decide what parts of theGovernments programme should be selected to be curtailed or postponed. If Ithe cut merely took the form of a reduction of the present numbers withoutreduction of duties there would be a risk of a series of administrative break-downs; particularly when it is remembered that in many sections there mustof necessity be increases, and that the incidence of the cut would fall acutelyon other branches. If, on the other hand, the decision were to maintain indefinitelyand indiscriminately the temporary standstill of staffs at their 1st January, 1947,strength, the Governments forward programme would undoubtedly suffer. Inour view action in either of these directions would not be justified on man-powergrounds, and would be very dearly bought.15. The corollary of this is that the position in regard to Civil Service staff numbers should be defended in the face of outside criticism, in the knowledge thatat April 1948 the non-industrial Civil Service will have reached its peak; that theincrease over the present level is due to transfers which do not make any furthercall on labour which might be engaged on more productive work; and that in thenext four years , unless further duties are imposed on the Civil Service, there willbe fairly substantial savings. The curtailment of postal services (see Annex,paragraph 2), the complete merger of the local offices of the Assistance Board inthe Ministry of National Insurance organisation, and the maintenance of the&quot;standstill&quot; where justifiable, together with such savings as may result from [administrative economies (see Annex, paragraph 41), will all help to limit the additions to staff arising from extra duties.16 In conclusion, we wish to emphasise one point to which we attach greatimportance the morale and standing in public esteem of the Civil Service. Thissurveys shows that no decrease, and in fact an increase, in numbers is expectedbefore April 1948. Therefore, especially during these next 12 months, we may expect that the Civil Service will be even more heavily under fire than it hasbeen in recent months. This is a matter on which the Government must takea definite line. No organisation can long sustain morale or attract the right typeof recruit if it is publicly or privately stigmatised as consisting of parasiteson the community or unjustly criticised in other equally opprobious terms; andif, being debarred from replying for itself, is left undefended. Equally, noorganisation has any right to expect to be defended unless it can show that itsown house is in order. No doubt there are improvements still to be made in theorganisation and work of the Civil Service, but we are convinced that those inauthority are determined to pursue these vigorously and open-mindedly. this being so, we hope that the Prime Minister, in his capacity as the First Lordof the Treasury and responsible for its direction, will take an early opportunityto underline the part which the Civil Service plays and its contribution to thepublic good. Then other Ministers, on suitable occasions, should do the same,with the result that the Civil Service will be encouraged by those responsiblefor its direction to take a proper pride in its work and the heart will not betaken out of the new entrants on whom the building up of a more efficient Servicelargely depends.IX. Summary of Recommendations17. (a) Broadly speaking, the strength of the non-industrial Civil service is related closely to the volume of work resulting from Government policy, and could not be cut without detriment to that policy.(&amp;) A Government statement should be prepared stating that the numbers ofthe Civil Service are not inflated in relation to the tasks falling upon them, andpresenting a picture of the essential activities in which the Service is engaged.(c) As part of this statement the total of non-industrial Civil Servants shouldbe analysed, e.g., the Post Office operatives and the civilian staffs of the service departments should be shown separately from the general body. (See Annex,paragraphs 4 and 9.)\d) It would be bad policy to force the pace of reduction of staff engaged onterminal activities to an extent which would mean that the work would be undulyprolonged and less efficiently executed.  (See Annex, paragraphs 11 and 14.)(e) The Post Office should render to the Treasury periodic reports of progress made in recovering pre-war standards of output by the adjustment of staff to the traffic load.  (See Annex, paragraph 2.)
(/) The local and regional organisations of the Assistance Board should be merged under the Ministry of National Insurance network. (See paragraph 10 (a)above.)(g) Other administrative economies should be energetically pursued. (see annex, paragraphs 41 and 42.)(A) The growth of the clerical and administrative staff of public boards,e.g., in the socialised industries, should be investigated.  (See paragraph 12 above.)(Intld.) J. C. E.,On behalf of the Committee.Home Office, S.W. 1,10th April, 1947.ANNEXCIVIL SERVICE MAN-POWERSummary of Position : March 1947 and Estimate of Numbers in Post forthe Five Years 1947-52I. introductory. This report is based on a review of the staffing of twenty-two of thelarger Departments, employing together about 90 per cent, of the total strengthof the non-industrial Civil Service. For purposes of convenience, the Depart-ments have been divided into groups and are dealt with below accordingly. Theestimates shown for 1st April,- 1947, and 1st October, 1947, are the estimatesmade by the Departments, revised and adjusted where necessary in the lightof the Committee&apos;s enquiry. The forward estimates up to 1952 are more con-jectural. In some cases they have been furnished by Departments at the requestof the Committee; in the remaining cases broad assumptions have been madeby the Treasury, as indicated in this memorandum. Graphs are attached showingthe forward estimates under various hypotheses.II.-Post office staff in post at 1st October, 1946..Estimate 1st April, 1947   .....Estimate 1st October, 1947OperatingStaff224,092229,248233,456Others34,05936,10237,494Total258,251265,300270,6002. The estimated increase of 12,350 was related to improvements in thequality of service and to growth in the volume of work.The Postmaster-General, in discussion with the Ministerial Committee, has,however, agreed to abandon certain improvements of services, some of whichhad already been introduced. The result will be to save about 6,000 staff: therewill also be a further saving of 1,750 which will be realised as an offset against further growth. The saving clue to curtailment of services will not be effected,by 1st April, 1947, but should have been completed in the ensuing six months.3. The Ministerial Committee do not recommend any further reductionof staff by means of curtailment of services. With the return from the armed forces of more experienced staffs and the replacement of temporary womenemployees, some improvement in output is to be expected over a period, andthe Postmaster-General has undertaken that the work of adjustment of staff to the traffic, with a view to further staff economies, should be speeded) up and completed within a year. Periodic reports should be obtained as to the progress made under this heaa.4. The Post Office &quot; operative &quot; staffs numbering in all 224,000 (or over30 per cent, of the whole of the Civil Service), though graded as non-industrial civil Servants, are employed as postmen, telephone operators and the like. their position is not unlike that of the operative staffs of the railways as they willbe after nationalisation. It is suggested that they should be shown separately from the general run of non-industrial Civil Servants in future staff returns.
III. Reirenue DepartmentsStaff in post Estimates1st Oct.,      1st April,     1st Oct.,     1st April, 1st April,1946            1947            1947           1948 1952Customs     .........      12,030         12,750         18,089         14,500 16,000Inland Revenue   ......      46,767         47,766         49,250         49,250 42,000Total   .........      58,797 60,516 62,839 68,750 58,0005. Both departments claim that they have insufficient staff to carry out their existing duties; that they are already heavily in arrears; that the staffsare working excessive houTs and that revenue is being lost through insufficientstaff.6. In response to Treasury Circular 7/47 the Customs have reduced their estimate of the staff required on 1st April, 1947, and 1st October, 1947, from13,569 and 14,502 respectively, the revised figure at the later date being 1,413less than that previously proposed. The Inland Revenue, whose staff numbered47,766 on 1st January, 1947, have accepted this as their ceiling and have notsubmitted any application for an increase above this total.7. It is clear that there can be no immediate reduction in the staff ofthese departments. Curtailment of recruitment carried with it extra risk tothe Exchequer and inconvenience to the public through increasing arrears. Thequestion is the minimum increase of staff for which it is safe to budget forthe next two to three years. Towards the end of the five-year period somereductions might be expected in Inland Revenue on the basis that (a) all arrears of work on P.A.Y.E. will by then have been made up and (6) the number ofpersons within the field of direct taxation will have been reduced.enrice and	Supply J	)epartm	ents	Staff in post		Estimates		1st Oct.,	1st April.	1st Oct.	1st April,	1st April,1946	1947	1947	194S	195238,317	35,650	34,200	33,550	25,00026,731	24,300	23,200	22,700	19,00048,365	46,834	49,580	47,785	37,14042,851	41,356	37,350	34,000	25,000156,264	147,130	144,330	138,035	106,140IY.AdmiraltyAir MinistryWar Office&apos;......Supply, Ministry ofTotal   ......8. These figures do not show the whole picture since there is no cleardividing line in many Service establishments between uniformed and civilpersonnel. The rapid rundown of Service personnel owing to demobilisationhas meant that, particularly in the War Office, the reduction of civilian staffshas not been proportionate. Indeed, in some establishments it has been necessaryto recruit additional civilian staffs in order to fill the places of some of thedemobilised! soldiers. The position in the War Office is shown in the following figures : 2s* April, 1947      1st Oct., 19471st Oct., 1945      1st Oct., 1946       (Estimate) (Estimate)Civil Staff.........      61,310 4S.365 46,834 49,580Military Staff      ......      77,820 36,965 32,771 27,727Total   ......      ...     139,130 85,165 79,605 77,3059. The present position whereby the non-industrial civil personnel of theService Departments are shown in the Civil Staff return, in which no account is taken of the numbers of uniformed personnel in these establishments, is clearlyunsatisfactory. It has been suggested that the only satisfactory course wealdbe that, as from some future date, an overall ceiling should be fixed for the total demand of the three Services on the man-power of the country. This would coverall uniformed personnel (not only those serving in mixed civilian and Serviceestablishments), non-industrial Civil Servants, and industrial workers, includingstaff at home and home-based staff on service overseas; and that the civil staffs of the Service Departments should be taken altogether out of the Civil ServiceReturn.10. On the narrower issue of the size of the civilian staffs of the service departments, these have been reduced from 152,000 at the peak to 113,000 bvOctober 1946 and to just under 110,000 at 1st January, 1947. The service departments say that the best guess they can give of the ultimate figure of the
civil staffs which they will require (on the basis of employing civilian ratherthan uniformed personnel wherever possible) is 81,000. They do not, however,expect that this further reduction will be completed in less than three years.(In the long-term estimate of the size of the Civil Service it has been assumed that the figure will be reached by 1952.)11. The Service Departments&apos; representatives point out that they are allfaced with a very heavy volume of liquidation and terminal work, and that theirproblem has been made more difficult by the heavy staff reductions made in theyear after the war, which exceeded the rate of decline in the volume of workto be handled. The War Office are intending to take the first possible opportunity to accelerate the overhaul of the organisation and accounting systems of pay and records offices. Taking the three Service Departments as a whole,however, no prospect can be seen of a more rapid reduction in staff over thenext few months than that forecast in the heading to this section, save by post-postponing terminal activities (in itself an uneconomic process in the long run) orby abandoning certain major functions.12. The figure of 81,000 (106,000 minus 25,000) given as the ultimate civilianstaffs for Service Departments compares with a figure of 52,420 in 1939; butthe anticipated size of the Armed Forces under compulsory military service willbe very much greater than before the War.Ministry of Supply13. This Department has reduced its civilian strength from over 82,000 to42,800 by 1st October, 1946, and propose to get down to 37,350 by 1st October,1947. By 1st April, 1948, they would hope to reduce this to 34,000 and by 1st April, 1949, they might get down to 27&apos;,000. They estimate provisionallythat their ultimate strength will be about 25,000.14. The Ministry of Supply have undertaken to examine certain suggestionsput to them for staff economies. The broad position is that a more rapid reductioncan only be brought about by spreading the work on disposals and other terminalactivities over a longer period or by curtailment of the duties which they are askedto undertake. In the last few weeks they have been asked to undertake additionalduties in connexion with supplies for the Ministry of Fuel and Power.Y. Social Sendees GroupStaff in post		Estinia	tea	1st Oct.,	1st April,	1st Oct.,	1st April,	1st April,1946	1947	1947	1948	195240,734	42,300	39,780	27,380	29,00012,493	14,223	16,350	32,500	32,0009,151	8,230	8,000	8,000	12,0002.556	2,920	3,500	3,625	4.1504,486	4,7S5	5,400	5,600	6,800900	1,030	1,100	1,200	1,2002,600	2,700	2,700	2,700	50012,635	12,450	12,200	12,000	9,000				1,80085,555	88,638	89,030	103,005	96,450Ministry of labour ministry of NationalInsuranceAssistance Board   ...Ministry of education ministry of health ministry    of    Town    and country PlanningWar  Damage CommissionMinistry of PensionsCentral  Land  Board   (in-cluding Inland RevenueValuers   as  required   byTown and Country Plan-ning Bill)Total    .........15. As originally estimated, this group showed an increase between October1946 and October 1947 of nearly 20,000, which was almost exactly the increaseoriginally proposed by the Ministry of National Insurance. It now appears,however, that the requirement of this Ministry on 1st October, 1947, will be16.300 not 32,000, but the reduction of 16,000 is only a postponement.16.   In making the estimates for 1948 to 1952 it is assumed that (i) The Assistance Board will take over from Local Authorities in 1949 some3,500 staff to implement the National Assistance Bill.(ii) The Ministry of Town and Country Planning will by 1949 have reached its peak and thereafter any additional work will be carried by thenew Towns Corporation and the Central Land Board.
(iii) The War Damage Commission will begin to decline in the spring of1948 and to all intents and purposes will have wound up by 1952.National Insurance17.   Two big issues arise in regard to the duties imposed by the national insurance Acts (a) whether economy would result from the complete amalgamation of theMinistry of National Insurance with the Ministry of Labour and national Service. While in the long run (when adequate premisescould be built to house the local staffs of an amalgamated organisa-tion) such a change might produce some economy the size of whichit is impossible to estimate we think that the disadvantages of theproposal outweigh the advantages;(6) whether the date for introduction of the new services should be post-ponecl. The staff to be saved for the time being by postponement would be largely those to be drawn from the approved societies andnot from productive employment. We do not think therefore thatpostponement for these reasons only would bring any advantagecommensurate with the political difficulty which would be involved.Ministry of Labour and National Service18. A reduction of 500 in the estimated requirements at 1st April, 1947,and 1st October, 1947, has been agreed on vocational training because of a cut inthe requirements of the building trade. Three suggestions have been made inregard to this Department: (i) Notwithstanding the reduction mentioned, savings in other directionsare being offset by the increased work on vocational training. Anybig reduction would be at the expense of the numbers trained for pro-ductive work, mainly on building. This must depend on the require-ments of the building trade for trainees.(ii) It has been suggested that the Appointments. Service might be integratedin the Employment Exchanges with some economy in premises and eventually in staff.(iii) It has also been suggested that the Resettlement Advice centres mightbe closed down more speedily.The savings to be effected in these ways might number some hundreds. Butsubstantial reductions can only be expected when &quot; training for industry&quot; has completed its main purpose, and the estimates for 1948 onwards assume thatthis work will have been reduced by stages to its ultimate level and that terminalwork following the war will have been wound up. The rundown in these matters should be carefully watched and economies effected as soon as opportunity occurs.Ministry of Education19. This Department shows a progressive increase and forecasts an ultimateestablishment of perhaps 4,500. Broadly this increase results from the education act, 1944, and the Department claim that this is unavoidable unless Ministersdecide that it is no longer their policy to implement the Education Act, at a reasonably high rate of progress. The raising of the school-leaving age to 16has been left out of this calculation.Ministry of Health20. The Ministry state that the increase of staff for which they budget isalmost wholly attributable to the new work falling on them under the national health Act, 1945, for which a regional organisation is being created.21. The advantage of the regional organisation is manifest, but there arereasons for thinking that, unless care is taken, there may be duplication betweenthe work done in London and in the regions and that the system may beextravagant of staff. Steps have been taken to set up an enquiry into thepossibility of an overlap of functions in the regions leading to excessive staffing.22. The work of the Ministry of Health lends itself, perhaps, more thanthat of any other Department to the suggestion, which is also of more general application, that substantial staff savings would result if the Government wereto delegate as much responsibility as possible from. Headquarters to the regions,and from the regions to the local authorities. It would follow that ministers would have to be ready to take the line that a particular question has been
dealt with, in a certain way by a local authority and that they would not interfere with the decision taken. It is unlikely that Parliament would allowthis position to be established.Summary of Social Services Group23. The problem here is, not to reduce staffs, but to limit the increasesresulting from the extension of the social services which forms an essential part of the Government policy.Some countervailing savings may be effected by suggestions to which attention has been drawn. But it is clear that they will not amount to much, as comparedwith the very heavy increases in duties assumed by central Government in this field.By 1952, however, the Ministry of Labour may be expected to effect con-siderable reductions (provided the number of unemployed does not appreciablyincrease) and the War Damage Commission will have been reduced to a skeletonstaff.VI. Trade and Industry Group	Staff in post		Est	i mates		1st Oct.,	1st April,	1st Oct.,	1st April,	1st April	1946	1947	1947	194S	1958Ministry of Food   ...	44,361	43.500	43,500	43,000	9.000Board of Trade	15,337	15,150	14,250	14,000	7,750Ministry of Transport	10,645	10.870	9,800	9,500	7.000Ministry of Fuel and Power	6,822	6,650	7,300	5,200	1,750Ministry of Agriculture and					Fisheries	5,958	6,420	7,000	17,300	9,300Forestry Commission	1,031	1,330	1,500	1.800	2,000Ministry of Civil Aviation	2,868	4,950	6,900	7,300	11,000Department   of   Scientific					and Industrial Research	2,185	2,350	2,500	2,800	4,000Total   .........	89,207	90,720	91,350	100,800	51.800Introductory24. The numbers employed in this group show a very large increase indeedas compared with the pre-war figure of 13,738. This is due to two main causes.First, the much greater part played by the Government to-day in trade andindustrial matters. Secondly, the very large blocks of staff engaged in the routinework of the rationing schemes and the controls. As and when the period of shortage passes and the rationing schemes can be abandoned, there will be verylarge savings under this head.An attempt is made, dealing with the major Departments in this group, togive some indication as to the relevant importance of these two factors.Ministry of Food25. 80 per cent, of the total staff are directly engaged in rationing andwill disappear when rationing ceases. There is thus a prospective saving hereof about 35,000.   There is no prospect of substantial ng as rationing-continues as at present.Trade26. The numbers engaged on control of various kinds-raw materials, con-sumer rationing, the utilitv scheme, price controls, &amp;c. total rather less than half [approximately 6,500-7,000] of the existing total of 15,000. Some of the raw material controls will be relaxed this year, but the continuance of shortagesmeans that further reductions must remain prospective. Apart from the con-trols, there is little scope for staff saving in the Board of Trade so long as it isGovernment policy that the Department should actively concern itself with the promotion of export trade, and with fostering and guiding and improving theefficiency of the main industries in this country.Transport27. It is estimated that the staff will ultimately be reduced to about 6.000.The main question here is how long it will take to deal with various terminalactivities, especially on the shipping side. There are also substantial staffsengaged on fuel rationing (650) and in conveyance of Government goods by road(800) and. it is reasonable to hope for some reductions under these two heads.[33439] c
1:028. Some of the anticipated decreases in this Department will, however, be offset by increases on the Highways side, where staff is needed to overtake wararrears and to deal with the increased volume of work, due to the fact that theMinister is now responsible for a mileage of trunk road twice the pre-war figure.Fuel and Power29. The number of staff engaged on petrol rationing is 1,500. It is alsoanticipated that in due course there will be a substantial reduction, amountingperhaps to as much as 2,000, on transfer of duties to the National Coal Board.Agriculture and Fisheries30. The increase of 1,700 shown over the year October 1948 to October 1947is due to a decision of policy whereby the Ministry has become directly responsiblefor certain advisory duties.31. Under the Agriculture Bill there will be a further increase of 10,000staff which will result from staffs of the County Agricultural Committees being transferred to the Ministry as from 1st April, 1948. This involves no change induties and does not, of course, affect the number of persons withdrawn from other employment. As and when livestock feeding-stuffs and farm equipment become more easily obtainable then staffs will be reduced by over a half.32 Broadly, the Government&apos;s policy of developing home food productioninvolves putting more direct responsibilities on the Ministry than during the war.Forestry33. The increase of 500 in the next six months is required to give effect tothe Governments forestry programme, which is substantially larger than thepre-war scale of activities. (The Government have approved a  20 millionprogramme of planting for the next five years.) Subsequent expansion will be checked by the shortage of labour for planting and maintenance.Civil Aviation34. The expansion of 4,000 during the year October 1946 to October 1947is due to the development of post-war civil aviation and to the responsibilitiesresulting from the Civil Aviation Act, 1946. This Act embodies the policy ofsocialising the air transport industry and involves, e.g., the transfer to nationaladministration and ownership of the transport aerodromes in the UnitedKingdom, and the extension of air communication, navigation and air traffic control services. In fulfilment of the policy of building up to a network of90 to 100 airports in the United Kingdom, still further expansion is to come;the ultimate strength is still conjectural, but is at present estimated at 10,750.Department of Scientific and. Industrial Research35. The Governments post-war programme of research now costs  4 million a year, as compared with  1 million before the war.Summary as to Trade and Industry36. The increases in this group are due to the more active part which departments are now called upon to play in trade and industrial matters, andalso to the need to retain large staffs to deal with rationing schemes and controls which amount to between 40,000 and 45,000. No decreases under the latter headcan be confidently forecast this year.YII. Agency ServicesNumber of StaffStaff in post Estimates1st Oct.,      1st April,      1st Oct.,      1st April 1st April,1946           1947           1947           1948 1952Ministry of Works         ...      20,288         20,700         21,013         21,400 13,50037. The Ministry of Works is the Government building Department and provides accommodation and supplies for Government purposes. But by virtueof its responsibility for the Building Industry, including building materials, ithas close links with the Trade and Industry Group.
38. The pressure of work on both these sides is very heavy. While labourand materials remain scarce, controls must be maintained, with permits for building materials and licences for private building work. On the other side,there is a heavy building programme, as well as considerable arrears of work on government buildings which must be greatly improved if the most economicaluse is to be made of staffs.39. In sum there can be little prospect of staff savings until the shortageof labour and materials is lessened, and until arrears of agency work have beencaught up. The long-term estimate assumes that the shortages have been sub-stantially eliminated and in consequence that building controls will have beenrelaxed.YIII.-Public Boards40. The Government&apos;s legislative programme has also led, or will lead,to the recruitment of staffs for Public Board and the like, e.g.. the National coal board, the Transport Commission and the Electricity Supply Councils. the staffs of these Public Boards are not, of course, included in the Civil service staff Returns; but they in turn will make additional demands on the Civil Service,,eg., for accommodation and equipment, stationery and office supplies and maps.IX. Administrative Economies41. Meetings of the Ministerial and Official Committees have brought to light a number of particular suggestions for improving management and organisa-tion to produce greater efficiency and more economical administration over and!above the day-to-day attention given to such matters.   They include :  (a) Common Services.   Work is being done to improve the organisation ofregistries, typing services, messenger and cleaning services, and pay-roll work. Registries are being decentralised and the volume oftyping work will be reduced where possible, e.g.. by the wider useof photographic reproduction and by economies on demands on typingtime. The Civil Service already compare veryr favourably with out-side industry in the use made of mechanical aids, but it is recognisedthat expanded use of such aids should be made wherever possible and where no undue expenditure of dollars is involved.(b) The provisions of offices for large units of staff in London and the regions would contribute greatly to man-power savings. At presentstaff are widely dispersed in many buildings, some of which are not designed as offices, with consequent loss of efficiency and economy instaffing. The solution lies in large new office buildings. This work should be given high priority in the Building Programme, but even so it will be some time before it becomes effective.(c) The devolution of responsibility from the centre to the regions (withinsistence on savings of staff at headquarters) and to Local Authorities(see paragraph 22).(d) A major contribution towards efficient and economic staffing is the recruit-ment, at all levels, of young officers to fill vacancies in the permanentcadre to make good the lack of intake through the wrar years, andto meet permanent expansion. The recruitment programme is in fullswing and by the end of 1948 Reconstruction Competitions will havebeen completed.(e) Some saving could also be made by avoiding over-elaboration in the workof interdepartmental Committees. Despite the efforts made to thecontrary, too many questions are remitted for interdepartmentaldiscussion; and too much time is taken in discussing matters in whicha particular Department should take the initiative and make itselfresponsible for taking action. But while this may lead to waste oftime by senior officials, the aggregate staff saving to be effected isprobably not very great. (The size of the administrative class as awhole is less than 3,500.)42. All these suggestions and others are being and will be energeticallyfollowed up. The work done on these lines is well worth while, and the standardof administration is certainly capable of improvement. But it would be wrong-to hold out hopes that the savings to be effected by these means are likely toproduce any very large result in 1947, or for some time thereafter.[33439] d
Total   ...... 722,700 737,000 704,200 644,000Bationing/Controls to continueunchanged beyond 1952 (a) Post Office operativestaffs excluded     ... 498,700 513,000 502,400 465,800(b) Post Office operativestaffs         ...... 224,000 224,000 224,000 224,000Total    ......      722,700 737,000 726,400 689,800X.: Overall Forecast43. Two long-term forecasts have been made for the years 1947-52 on the assumptions -.r-(1) That rationing and controls would continue as at present until April1948 but from then on would be lifted progressively, and would be finally removed by 1952;(2) That rationing will be needed substantially in its present form until after 1952.The position under these alternatives is shown in the Table below. In thiscalculation, it is assumed that the operative staff of the Post Office will be keptsubstantially at the present level. This is no more than a statistical assumption,as their numbers will vary in proportion to the traffic load over the period.Estimated Number of Civil Servants 1947-521st,Jan..1947    1st April, 1948    1st April, 1950    1st April, 1952Bationing/Controls relaxed asfrom 1948 (a) Post Office operativestaffs excluded     ...      498,700 513,000 480,200 420,000(b) Post Office operativestaffs ......      224,000 224,000 224,000 224,000
AH ESTIMATE OF THE NUMBERS IN THE CIVIL SERVICE IN THE FIVE YE(NON-INDUSTRIAL   STAFF ONLY)&quot;APPOINTED BAY  FOV. AGRICULTURE BILL POSTPONED TO   1^ APTUL  1150&quot;APPOINTED DAV FOTi  AGRICULTURE BILL,&quot;) POSTPONED TO   1^  APTdL   jWjANP FOR  NATIONAL  INSURANCE ACT    J&quot;APPOINTED 3AND  FOP,   hifujsi
&quot;APPOINTED DAY&quot; FOR  AgRICULTtfRE BILL.-)  pOST?ONED TO  I a  ATRIL  1350AND FOR   NATIONAL   INSURANCE   ACT     J3NEB TO  1^ APTUL  iqMIrPONEB  TO   l-g^ ATRIL  1^50 *APPOINTED SAY&quot; FOR  NATIONAL  INSURANCE ACT POSTPONED TO  1^ ATRIL  1150Z OF THE NUMBERS IN THE CIVIL SERVICE IN THE FIVE YEARS iqii--f-H5a(NON-IMPUSTRIAL  STAFF ONLY)


</content>
</cab>
