<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 315-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S 0OGUMIIS   THE   PROPERTY. OF   HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1947 &quot;        EiOSECRET CoPy       ^CP. (47) 12510*A 4-^7, 1947CABINETANGLO-IRANIAN  OIL  company memorandum by the Minister of state in view of the interest taken by my colleagues in the Anglo-Iranian oil company, I attach for their information, with reference to CP. (46) 365 of1st October, 1946, a summary of a report by the Labour Attache recently appointedto His Majesty&apos;s Embassy at Tehran on labour conditions provided by theCompany.The Ministry of Fuel and Power have taken up with the Company the various recommendations for action made in the report.Since the report was written, His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Tehran has visitedAbadan. He reports that during the past six months a great amount has beendone in the way of developing housing, essential services, clinics, stores, &amp;c.Among the new developments is a comprehensive sewage scheme, which will cost about one and a quarter million pounds and will be the only one of its kind in persia. He concludes that all these activities should impress any impartialobserver with the seriousness with which the Company are tackling their greattask. The general impression which he derived from his visit was distinctlyencouraging and reassuring.H. McN.Foreign Office, lQth April, 1947.Summary of a Report on Labour Conditions in the Anglo-Iranian oil company dated 31st December, 1946, by Mr. K. J. Hird, Labour Attacheat His Majesty&apos;s Embassy, Tehran1. Terms of ServiceMinimum wages, maximum hours, overtime rates, leave and holidays havebeen laid down in. recent Persian Government legislation. The Company&apos;sworkers enjoy conditions that are in most respects superior to the minima of theLabour Law. The Company&apos;s hours of employment 44-^ in winter, 45 in summer are more favourable than those prescribed by the Labour Law, viz., 48.Employees are able to purchase food and clothing at cheap prices in theCompany&apos;s shops.2. general at Abadan, where the Refinery is situated, little attempt is made by Persianofficialdom to discharge the functions of a public authority. The making of roads,street cleansing, the building of schools, medical services, the inspection andcleaning of the municipal abattoir are left to the Company. There is a markedaifference between facilities (hospitals, clubs, housing) afforded by the company to its own employees and those available to non-employees. Social conditions and amenities of Company labour are, in general, superior to those to which thenormal Persian manual worker is accustomed, and the contrast with living condi-tions of non-employees is therefore all the more marked. The provision ofsatisfactory social amenities and community services for that part of the popula-tion not employed by the Company depends on the provision of better municipalofficials by the Persian Government whom the Company might be able toencourage by contributing to the cost of public works or by assisting withmaterials and equipment.3- housing the present shortage of houses provided for Company labour is fully realisedby all concerned and the future programme of construction is comprehensive. But[33442
it will be some time before minimum housing requirements are met; estimatesvary from two years for the Abaclan area to five years- for the Oil Fields. Inparticular at Agha Jari Oil Field the problem is complicated by the imminenttransfer of the Oil Field Centre to a point some 10 miles from its present site.Extensive building is going on at the new Centre, but it may be years beforethe move is completed, and meanwhile many workers will be in a state ofdiscomfort. The quality of the new housing is excellent, the four-room type, bothin Abadan and the Oil Field, comparing very favourably with the accommodation available to large numbers of workers in Great Britain. At Abadan existingtwo-room houses are being turned into three-room houses. It is open to doubt whether, with such a large number of workmen without Company accommodation,it might not be better to concentrate present efforts on mass producing emergencyaccommodation and then rebuilding to raise standards. With regard to thedevelopment of Oil Fields which may be brought into production in the future, itis the intention of the Company to see that the development of production shallnot outstrip the provision of facilities for workers and their families.4. Up-grading of Persian workers the quality of Persian workers is, on the whole, good. There appears tobe scope for more up-grading of Persian workers. This would largely be atthe expense of Indians. The Company have arrangements for reviewing the contracts of Indian employees with special reference to the possibility of replacingthem by Persians.5. Contractors&apos; Employees- A problem is presented by the employees of Persian contractors engaged on work for the Company. As these men are not directly employed by the Companythey do not receive all the amenities of Company employees and are vulnerable to such malpractices or irregularities as their employers may pursue. Out of63,000 men working for the Company some 11,000 are the employees of contrac-tors. This problem needs review, and if it is impracticable to transfer largenumbers of these men to the company^s direct employment it should be ensuredthat the terms and conditions of contract labour are not less favourable thanthose of men directly employed by the Company.6. training the various training schemes at Abadan are well conducted. There is,however, large wastage as many youths after completing their training go off tojobs elsewhere. In present conditions this is probably partly due to a fear of notfinding in Abadan accommodation comparable to that enjoyed in the hostelsattached to the Training Centres. A remedy lies in the speeding up of actionon the housing problem as a whole. A special survey might be conducted intothis problem.7. Industrial RelationsWorkers&apos; organisations or any form of authoritative representation do not exist. The development of joint negotiating machinery and the growth of freelyelected Trade Union organisation is vital. Factory Councils are a first essential and through these workers&apos; representatives should be encouraged to organiseTrade Unions. (Note. Since this report was written the Persian Governmentand the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company have decided to introduce Factory Councilsinto the Company&apos;s establishments forthwith. The Persian Government approvedon 3rd March the regulations which under the Persian Labour Law are to govern the formation of Trade Unions and define their status).8. MedicalFree medical services are recognized conditions of service. The Company&apos;scheme for medical treatment and compensation for sickness and injury comparesvery favourably with the requirements of Persian Law. Benefits granted bythe Company range from full pay during sickness to the provision of artificiallimbs and free burial, all of which exceed the requirements of the Law.9. EducationAbadan is probably far better served than anywhere else in Persia witheducational facilities. &apos; The donation of 17 schools to the municipality andfinancial aid to the teaching staff demonstrate the Company&apos;s real desire toensure adequate facilities shall be available. There are sufficient adulteducational facilities for any worker wishing to become literate.


</content>
</cab>
