<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 318-320</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
, . ..ent is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovernmentPrinted for the Cabinet, April, 1947 2 1ECopy No.CABINETCYRENAICAMEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY  OF  STATE  FOR  WAR1. At their meeting on 26th September, 1946, the Cabinet approved certain proposals about the administration of Cyrenaica put forward by the Foreign Secretary(CM. (46) 83 (4)). Among these was the sending of a Working Party to that country under the a;aegis of the War Office to draw up a comprehensive plan covering three points:  (a) the increase of opportunities for local Arabs to hold responsible posts in theAdministration;(b) the setting up of an Advisory Council; and(c) the restoration of war damage and the remedying of the economic disabilitiesof the country.My colleagues will wish to know what progress has been made giving effect to thisdecision.SECRETCP. (47) 126nth April, 19472. A Working Party under the chairmanship of Sir Bernard Reilly, K.C.M.G.,OLE., O.B.E., have been investigating these problems on the spot during the winter and have submitted a report. Their recommendations, together with some observationsby the Chief Civil Affairs Officer, M.E.L.F., have been considered by an inter-departmental meeting at official level, and general agreement reached over the actionto be taken on the various items. These conclusions I have approved.3. Further action can proceed at the official level and I do not think that I needtrouble the Cabinet with the detail. As regards the three main points mentionedabove, it is proposed on (a) to take immediate steps to appoint a few Cyrenaicansto higher posts in the Administration and to start the training of others. As to (6) Iam advised that the time is not quite ripe for the appointment of an Advisory Council,but the Commander-in-Chief, M.E.L.F., will be given instructions which will enable him to proceed with this measure as soon appeal practicable. As to (c) various proposalsfor the rehabilitation of the country and its commerce have been approved in principle.The Treasury are in general agreement with the conclusions and do not regard their cost as prohibitive, but they naturally require each particular project entailingexpenditure to be submitted to the Treasury in the normal manner, and this is in train.4. There is one point to which I wish to draw particular attention. In their Reportthe Working Party emphasise the importance of retaining staff of high quality with theBritish Military Administration in Cyrenaica during the remaining period of its responsi-pility, and subsequently under any trusteeship in which His Majesty&apos;s Government is involved. They suggest certain principles which should be followed by GovernmentDepartments in respect of appointments in Cyrenaica, namely:  (a) That, save in exceptional circumstances, the period of secondment of existingpersonnel now serving in the territory be extended in all cases when requested by the Chief Civil Affairs Officer, and that their interests be safeguarded intheir parent service.(b) lhat suitable officers now filling key posts in the territory who do not belong to an existing service be given opportunities of entering contractual orpermanent service with the Colonial or Foreign Office or other GovernmentDepartment. The number of such officers willing to consider such anarrangement is not more than six.(c) That the balance of key posts, both administrative and technical, be filled bysecondment from existing services, or by recruitment under contractsufficiently attractive to command a satisfactory standard of applicant.I endorse these principles which are being brought to the notice of all Departmentsconcerned, and I hope that my colleagues will assist me to the best of their power inthese ways in retaining and recruiting suitable officers.
5. Finally, the Working Party have recommended that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentshould now make a public statement of policy as regards their future intentions towardsCyrenaica, and also suggest for consideration the possibility of a further early statement in Parliament. The interdepartmental meeting took the view that any such statements by His Majesty&apos;s Government at this juncture might have unfortunate repercussions inother territories and on the international plane, and might also lead to misconception in cyrenaica itself. At the same time it is obviously desirable that the civil population of cyrenaica should be made aware of the more liberal treatment which it is the intentionshortly to accord to the territory, and that this information should be released sufficientlyearly after the departure of the Working Party to avoid anything in the nature of an anti-climax. The meeting accordingly recommended that the release of such information or the issue of any statement should be undertaken by the Administration locally, whichis in a better position to avoid political issues and to stress the material advantages whichit is hoped will be conferred. (The representative of the Colonial Office reserved hisposition on these points.) I am in agreement with the general view and I ask mycolleagues to agree that further consideration be given, in conjunction with the ForeignOffice and Colonial Office, to the methods by which due publicity arrangements can bemade by the Administration locally.F. J. B.The War Office,nth April, 1947.(B47/45)   120   4/47   W.O.P.   27535


</content>
</cab>
