<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 321-338</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
((pHIg DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC: MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET\ (47,127] 3th April 1947 COPY NO, A*f &apos;&quot;- CABINET h&quot;COiiPENSATION TERMS FOR MEMBERS OF THE INDIAN AND BURMASERVICES APPOINTED BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE AND for officers OF THE INDIAN AND BURMA ARMED FORCES.Memorandum by the Prime MinisterAt their meetiiig on 19th November 1946^ the cabinet approved scales of compensation^ Dor loss or career and prospects to be paid to members of the Indian civilianService-s when their appointments under the Secretary ofState were terminated as a result of constitutional changes and authorised the Secretary of State to invitethe Viceroy to lay them before the Interim Governmentin India.2.    The compensation scales in question have, m the meanwhile, been the subject of correspondence and discussions with the Government of India and of furtherprolonged consideration by the India and Burma Committeein the light of the Government of India&apos;s views, astatement of which is contained in the telegram fromthe Vioerov reproduced as Annex I to this Memorandum.It will be&apos;seen that, broadly, the Government of Indiaraise no objection to the payment by H.M.G. ofcompensation on the scales&apos; proposed to European membersof the Services;   the only cases in which the Governmentof India are prepared themselves to boar the cost ofsucpi compensation are those (which they consider unlikely to arise) in which a European officer who wishes tocontinue to serve under government in India is notinvited to do so.     So far as Indian officers areconcerned, the Government of India are strongly opposedto the payment of compensation, whether by themselvesor by HoMo Go , except in certain limited categories oioases o..O.M. (46) 98th. Conclusions, Minute 6.Set out In full in CMP. (46) 424.     (The I.C.S. scalesare also set out in the left hand column of Annex %Mto this Memorandum.)
oases, namely, to officers who:-(1)   are not invited to continue to serve under government in India after the transfer of power;     or(2)   can satisfy the Federal Public Service Commis-sion that their actions in the course of dutyduring service prior to the transfer of powerhave created a prejudice against them and damaged their prospects.3o    The Viceroy recommends that compensation should begranted to European officers on the scales originallyapproved but that, so far as Indian officers areconcerned, the proposals of the Government of india should be accepted.     As regards those members of theIndian Armed Forces who will, on the transfer of power,be placed in a position similar to that of the membersof the Secretary of State&apos;s Services, the Government ofIndia recognise that the same general considerationsfor compensation should be made in regard oC wjiom.   the scales of compensation for commissioned ofiicers willbo broadly equivalent to those prescribed for membersof the Secretary of State&apos;s Services other than the.has,   with appropriately lower scales for the various categories of other ranks affected.     British officersand other ranks who transfer to the British Service will receive one quarter of the standard rate.4.     After the fullest possible consideration of all the factors involved, including the undertakings given inthe past to members of the Services, the India and BurmaCommittee have endorsed the Viceroy&apos;s recommendation and agreed that it should be submitted to the Cabinet torapproval.     as stated in the two draft announcementscontained in Annexes II and III respectively to thisMemorandum, the source from which the necessary monieswill ultimately come must be a matter to be dealt withhereafter.     It is the intention that the draft announce-mentsshould be telegraphed to the Viceroy for hiscomments, and that the draft of the Viceroy&apos;s announcement should be submitted by him to his Cabinet, since itembodies certain propositions, in particular the Govern-liierit or India&apos;s undertaking to maintain their presentterms for officers who are invited and agree to continueto serve under government in India, the formal acceptanceof which bv the Government of India is still required.5. The
5,    TlTu Secretary of State for India has felt unable to associate himself with the proposals made in thisMemorandum.     It is his view that, having regard to theterms of the undertaking given to serving members oftrie Secretary of State&apos;s Services in June 1945 at thetime of the announcement of the decision to resumerecruitment to the Indian Civil Service and Indian Police(see Annex TV to this memorandum), it is out of the -question that compensation should be withheld altogether from any Indian members of the Services,,     At the sametime he recognises that the circumstances that will ariseafter the transfer of power will place Indian and british members of the Services respectively in fundamentallydifferent positions and he, therefore, favours the adoptionof a scheme whereby, while European officers would receive compensation on the scale originally proposed, Indianmembers generally (apart from those falling in the specialcategories mentioned above, who would receive compensationor. the same scale as Europeans) would receive compensationou a lower scale (the figures for which, In the case ofthe I.G.S. , are set out in the right hand column of annex V to this hemorandum) which is consistent with theterms of the June 1945 pledge and, in his view, is likelyto be less unacceptable to the Government of India.6.     The India and Burma Committee have given full consideration to the point of view of the Secretary ofState but are unable to accept the wide interpretationwhich he gives to Mr. amery&apos;s pledgee  . This pledge wasmade to the members of the Services in a Communiquepublished on June 1st, 1945 and referred to a pamphletwhich set out the terms upon which temporary entrants tothe Services would be compensated.     The basis of these terms was the need to compensate officers for loss ofcareer and prospects, as a result of constitutional changes.   The statement in the communique was that presentmembers would receive terms not less favourable considered as a whole than those applicable to new entrants.     Aspresent members were pensionable while new entrants werenot it was clear that the amount of compensation would beless in the case of the former, but this is not the onlyfactor to which   the phrase considered as a whole hasreference,     it must also refer to the extent to whichthe career and prospects of the officers will be affectedby constitutional changes.     Clearly British and indian officers are affected very differently.     The former haveto take the chance of being employed by a Government,Whether Dominion or foreign, outside the control of theBritish Parliament.   The latter have the opportunity of serving in.their own country under a Government of Indians.to from being worsened there Is every probability thattheir prospects will be improved, except for the limitedcategories mentioned in paragraph 2 above.     There iscertainly no reason why an Indian Government should com-compensate officers whom they are prepared to employ.     It: 1  &apos; &apos; ;ls .j&apos;. &apos;M, &apos;nf
II2 JL iis not clear to the Committee why the British Governmentshould pay compensation to Indians who are unwilling toserve in their own country.     Further, to give largecompensation to serving Indian officers would actually bean inducement to them not to serve and would be doing a grave disservice to the Indian Government of the future.7,    For these reasons the Committee .are unable to acceptthe position that there should be no distinction made between British and Indian officers.     They also considerthat the compromise proposal of the Secretary of Statemakes the worst of both worlds.     Either it accepts the absolute nature of the pledge and fulfils it only partially or it rejects the pledge, but gratuitouslyexpresses lack of confidence in any future indian government.8c    I therefore invite the Cabinet to approve the Indiaand Burma Committee&apos;s endorsement of the Viceroy&apos;recommendation.9o     It will be seen that the draft of the Statement tobe made in Parliament also refers to the Burma services which are in a similar position to the Indian.     TheGovernor of Burma has not yet consulted his Council but he proposes to do so as soon as a decision has been reached in regard to India.   It is impossible yet to say what theattitude of his Council will be but the Governor hopes that they may follow the line taken by the interim government in India.     The reference to Burma in thedraft Statement is, therefore, at this stage purelyprovisional.     If an announcement in regard to Burma hasto be postponed until after the announcement in regardto India, no reference will be made to Burma in theStatement in Parliament dealing with India.C. R. A.10, Downing Street, S.W.1.13th April. 1947.
TELEGRAM NO. 700-S DATED 2ND APRIL, 1947, FROM viceroy to SECRETARY OF STATE REPORTING VIEWS OF GOVERNMENTOF INDIA __.A. Civil Services.1.    British officers.British officers who wish to leave will be givenproportionate pension by Government of India but theGovernment of India will not be prepared to pay compensation.If compensation is to be paid it Is the feeling of thebmet that it should bo paid by H. M. Government.Gai-British officers who wish go stay and are acceptable to Government of India will be retained on their presentconditions of service.   Should, any such officer wish toleave the service afterwards the Government of India willbe prepared to pay him proportionate pension but hiscompensation when he leaves must be paid by H. M. Government.The ordinary disciplinary rules will of course continue toapply and proportionate pension will only be payable ifit has not been forfeited owing to some act which entailsforfeiture of pension.   Any such case would be decided onadvice of Federal Public Service Commission or a similarauthority set up-for the purpose..   British officers who wish to stay on but are not acceptable to Government of India will be paid bothproportionate pension and compensation by Government ofIndia though it is unlikely that there will be any suchcases.2.     Indian officers.   It is suggested that the BritishGovernment should announce that though they wished tooffer compensation to Indian officers as well as british officers, in view of the increased prospects for Indianmembers of Service and f ct that feelings of patriotismwould naturally impel them to serve on, the Government ofIndia have desired that compensation should be payableonly in special cases, such as where an officer&apos;can prove-to satisfaction of Federal Public Service Commission or,.a similar authority that his actions in course of duty, curing his service up to transfer of power have -createdp.^prejudice against him and damaged his prospects.   SuchIpf36^,are likely to be rare and may be further reduced byiexpedient of transferring officers from one administrationanother,   in such cases compensation would be payable by government of India.Bf     GsneralL   The Home Member urged that point put -BTriHiaPniS^ &apos;nilfl in       previous note which is already withjGuuia office should be considered   These related to/payment
Payment of compensation to officers with, over 25 years service, and to method of calculation of compensationoayabis to services other thanB.Defence Services.   The same generaltansiderations apply as in case of Civil Services.
DriArT STATEMENT 3Y HIS a-XCElXaNCY THE viceroy, . H.ii.G. have announced their intention that theBritish Government&apos;s authority in India will be finallytransferred to Indian hands by June 1948.    It. is the aim off BP Mo Go that the transfer of power should bo effected in an orderly and regulated manner so that the nowauthorities may assume their responsibilities in conditions conducive to the best interests of India andthe maintenance of good relations with Great Britain.H.M.G. are confident that during this period of  .transition the Services and all those who&apos; man them,whether British or Indian, will respond to this call inthe manner to be expected from their great traditionand record.20   To those serving under covenant or other form ofagreement with the Secretary of State for India or whohold Commissions from H.M. The King, the transfer of power will mean the premature termination on that dateof a career under the ultimate authority of H.M.G., and&apos;the British Parliament; and for many there is added to for their own future and that&quot;of those who depend ohthem.3,   The Government of India are naturally and rightlymost anxious - and H.M.G. share their anxiety - thatthe administration shall not be weakened by the loss of experienced officers.,   To this end the Government oxIndia undertake on their own behalf and that cfProvincial Governments that those, members of theSecretary of State&apos;s Services who continue to serve under Government in India after the transferof powershall do so on their present terms as to scales of pay,leave, pensionary rights and safeguards in matters of discipline, (and that provision to this effect, should)e made in the Treaty to deal with matters arising outof the transfer of power).4.   The Government of India agree that compensation should be payable to such Indian officers of theServices as:-(1) are not invited to continue to serve under government in India after thetransfer of power;(2) can satisfy the Federal Public service commission that their actions in thecourse of duty during their serviceprior to the transfer of power have created .....
(U Icreated a prejudice against themana damaged their prospects or thatthe appointments offered to them are such as cannot be regarded as satisfactory in the altered circumstances.But the Government of India feel that sentiments ofpatriotism will naturally impel Indian officers tocontinue to serve their country and that, in the lightof the undertaking that they have given and theconsideration that in fact Indian members of theServices will have improved prospects, there is no ground, save in thes-  special cases, for the paymentof compensation to Indian officers on account&quot;of thetransfer of power.It Mo Go have reviewed the whole position.   They haveid the undertaking which the Government of India havegiven in regard to officers whom they desire shouldcontinue to serve under government in India.   they recognise the force of the Government of India&apos;sarguments and1; they agree that, to Indian officers,compensation should not be admissible except in thecases which I have just mentioned.6.   V/ith these reservations I am now authorised byHoMo;Go to inform members of the Secretary of State&apos; services that they accept the obligation&quot; to see thatthey are duly compensated for the consequences of thetransfer of power    They also undertake that membersof the Secretary of State&apos;s Services who retire will besecured in their right to the leave then due to thorn.Tables are&apos; being published forthwith setting out the scales of compensation.7,   To European officers and other ranks of the R. IMN.,Indian Army and Medical Service whose services underthe Crown in these forces are brought to an end. byreason of the transfer of power, I am authorised to announce the acceptance by H.M.G. of a similarobligation.   For some it will be possible to pursue their profession in the corresponding British&quot;Service:and for them a lower scale of compensation for loss ofSjh Indian career is provided    Tables are being published at once setting out in detail in respect ofthe difference categories in the different services the scales of compensation prescribed.p
8.   Compensation will not ordinarily be admissible tothose who retire before the date of the final transferof power; but, in the interests of a smooth transfer itmay be desirable to spread releases over a period andif I am satisfied that in the public interest anycivilian officers should be released with entitlement to compensation in advance of the final date, i willorder accordingly after such consultation with theauthorities concerned as may be necessary&apos;.   If in theFighting Services any European officer or other rank iscertified by the Commander-in-Chief as having, afterJuly 1st, 1947, been compulsorily retired as a result ofaccelerated reduction of the British element in anticipation of the transfer of power, he will acquire a title to compensation at the date of his retirement.9,   The sources from which these monies will ultimately come  ist  be a matter to be dealt withhereafter but, so far as the individuals affected areconcerned, they have the assurance of H.M.G. that theywill receive the monies to which they will become entitled.
FT OF STATE! LENT To BE : lADv TN BOTH H&apos; USES OF tAliIAMENTlo   The question of compensating members of the IndianServices&quot;whose careers will be affected by the transferas now constituted has been receiving Ion? and consideration, and a decision has now been reached    Asthe decision needs to be viewed against its historic-]background I will   with the permission of the Houseideate briefly the circumstances which have led up to^crPt^ officers appointed by theoecretc,r.v 01 otate in subordination for the first timeto Indian ainistgrs.....under the system of dvarchyestablished m the Provinces.    This was considered tohad been appointed to serve and Section 96B or the actwas enacted to provide compensation in the case ofpersons appointed before the commencement of the Act.But the altered conditions of service created doubts inthe minds of possible candidates as to the futuresecurity of tenure and, in order to dispel these doubtsand to ensure the necessary flow of recruits,authoritative explanations which carried assurance 01 apermanent career&apos;i,. India were given at the universities and elsewhere. The principle of assured service or, indefault, compensation was enunciated in 1934 by theJoint jclect Com Itteo of Parliament without limitation to those appointed before any particular date.    In this form it was given statutory effect by the detailed   _   .provisions contained in Fart X of the Government of india act, 1935.3... It was thus the intention of a-parliament that     - Fjofficers whose careers and prospects were prejudiced byconstitutional changes should receive such compensation as the Secretary of State might consider just anaequitable.4.:  When in 1945 recruitment for the 1,0.3, and theIndian Police was resumed with provision for compensationif service was terminated prematurely for constitutionalreasons the then Secretary of State undertook, at therequest of the Government of India, that, officersconditions under which they already
already serving would if their services were similarlyterminated, be granted terms not less favourableconsidered as a whoIf than those applicable to the newrecruits,   H.H.G. have considered what arrangements should be made, having regard to the undertaking givenin 1945, to compensate these ant other officers appointedby the Secretary of State for loss of career and prospects.5,   The Government of India inform us that they are most anxious to avoid the loss of experienced officers,.They have stated, that they are prepared to give tothose members of the Secretary of state&apos;s Services whocontinue to serve under government in India the same terms as to scales of pay, leave, pensionary rightsand safeguards in matters of discipline as hitherto.In the case of Indian officers they feel that sentimentsof patriotism will impel them to continue to serve theircountry ana that they can look for a positive improve-incnt in their prospects.    They agree, however, that compensation should be payable, to Indian officers who:-(1) arc not invited to continue to serve under government in India, after thetransfer of power, or(2)   can satisfy the Federal ,ublic service commission that their actions in thecourse of duty during service priorto the transfer of power have created a prejudice against them and damagedtheir prospects or that the appointmentsoffered to them are such as cannot beregarded as satisfactory in the alteredcircumstances.They do not feel that compensation should be admissibleto Indian officers in other cases.6.   H,H.G, have now reviewed the whole position.   Theynave &quot;taken account of the undertaking given, of theview expressed, by the Government of India, and of allother relevant circumstances,   H.M,G. feel that chore isa radical difference in the effect which the transfer of power will have upon the position of Indian and european officers respectively.   European officers will no longer be serving under the ultimate control of the-Liamcnt of their own country and. it cannot bomaintained that their prospects will be the same as inHJf Pjst.   It cannot on the other hand be contendedLnat the same case for compensation arises where Indiansontinur. to serve their own country on the same terms asI J-ore and with improved prospects!   They have accordinglyauthorised...&apos;..
authorised the Viceroy to announce that H.M. G. acceptthe obligation to see that European officers and thoseIndian officers whom I have mentioned -should receive compensation for the loss of their careers and prospects consequent on the transfer of power.   Theyundertake also that the members of the Secretary ofState&apos;s Services in India who re tire will: be secured intheir rights to the leav  then due to the u Tables arebeing published forthwith setting out the scales ofcompensation.7.   The development of the policy of H. H. G. for constitutional advance in India has now created inrelation to the Indian armed forces a situation similarto that which 1 have already described in relation tothe Civil Services and those affected have an equallyvalid claim to compensation.   The scales proposed forthem are also being published forthwith,8.   For many of those who will 00come entitled to&apos;compensation opportunities will exist for further government service.   It is&quot; the earnest hope of II. LuG.that officers will freely avail themselves of theseopportunities.   The terms of such further cmployrm atare a matter for consideration by the government concerned.   Candidates for employment under H.M.G. inthe Home, Foreign and Colonial Services are beinginformed of the conditions on which the posts will be offered to those who are selected,,   The question of anyadjustment of the compensation terms that may be needed in the case of those who continue ?n service under government in India will be considered as soon as the detailed terms offered to them are known.9-   The Services&apos; in Burma are in a similar position,iiany of the officers in the Burma Civil Service Class I,the Burma Police, Class I, and other Civilian Services,were in fact recruited to the Indian Civil Service, the&quot;Indian Police or other Indian Service before Burma wasseparated from India; and an assurance was given to these9Ificore that their Indian service rights would not beinfringed by the act of separation,   moreover,theGovernment of Burma Act, 1935, contains provisionsidentical in effect with those already mentioned ascontained in fart X of the Government&quot; of India Act andthus; establishes equally for officers recruited, sinceseparation in 1937 the- principle of assured service or,in default, equitable compensation.   The undertaking!vv, .ne 1945 was, moreover, addressed to the Burmaservices equally with the Indian Services.
10.   The sources from which the monies involved will ultimately come must be a matter to be dealt withhereafter, but, so far as the individuals affected areconcerned, they have the assurance of H.M.G. that theywill receive the monies to which they will become entitled.11.   H.M.G. have accordingly authorised the viceroy and the  Governor 01 Burma to make announcements whichare puolished in a white Paper laid to-day.   The white paper also contains Tables setting out the scales ofcompensation for the various Services affected
y*2&amp; iA:jnex V 2/EXTRACT FROM PRESS COiEiUNIQJE PUBLISHED ON 1st June, 1945ANNOUNCING THE DECISION TO RECRUIT &quot;WAR SERVICE&quot;CANDIDATES__._________The pamphlet shows that provision is made for the contingency that service under the Secretary of State, forwhich candidates are invited to apply, may be terminatedprematurely as a result of constitutional changes.     this contingency would affect not only new recruits but also such the present members of the Indian Civil Service and theIndian Police as are serving at the time.      The preciselearns to be granted in such event to present members ofthese Services have not yet been settled but they will benot less favourable, considered as a whole, than those appli-cable to new entrants.M I.B.S. (1)EXTRACTS FROM RECRUITMENT PAMPHLET I.B.S.1 published__on 1st June. 1945    __X X X X X X X:    THE INDIAN CIVIL SERVICEX      X X        X X XXConditions of serviceX      X X X        X X X revision for retirement - Appointments will not bepensionable. &quot; During ois service under the Secretary ofState an officer will have the right to retire voluntarilyat any time after completing 5 years&apos; service and will beentitled to the retirement grant appropriate to the lengthof hisiservice as shown in the second column of the table inAppendix II.* .... 0........ If as a result of constitutional-tjanges an officer9 s appointment under the Secretary of-e Ls ter ;in-.ted and he does not receive and accept an?r to continue to serve under government in India, hewill be entitled to the grant appropriate to his lengthoi service as shown in the third column of the table inappendix II.       it is, however, hoped that many of theoincers whose appointments under the Secretary of State areterminated will be invited and will be willing to continueto serve under government in India.       In such cases the grants appropriate to their length of -service under theoocretary of State will be placed to their credit with aninoependent authority and will bo paid to them on theirjj-caving the service of government in India, or to their-hn1&apos;^ lf. they die while still serving.      The conditions forcpntinuance of their service under government in Indiabe for settlement by the Indian Government concerned,reproduced below &quot; ,x X X X X X X
-2-APPENDIX IIGrants admissible, to &quot;war service&apos; recruits to the IndianGivil Service or tine Burma Civil Service (Class I)_fftdrigtri       Retirement grant admis-if Service sible to officers whoretire voluntarilyGrant admissible to officerswhose appointments under theSecretary of State are termination-nated on account ofconst ituional changes _Years o6789101112131415161718192n21222324or1,5002,0002,5005,0003,5004,0004,5005,0005,5006,0006,500over7,0007,5008,0009,00010,00011,00012,00013,00014,00015,0004,00.05,0006,0007,0008,0009,00010,00011,00012,00013,00014,00015,00015,00U15,00015,00015,00015,00015,00015,00015,00015,00uNote^lo   In the event of an officer&apos;s appointment under theSecretary of State being terminated on account of constitutional changes before he has completed 5 years service, he will be entitled to such proportionate grantas the Secretary of State may decide.Note 2. In the case of an Indian or Burrnan officer the grantadmissible will at his option be paid in rupees, the sterling sum being converted into&quot;rupees at such rate ofexchange as the Secretary of State may prescribe.^XTKACT PROM RECORD OF MEETING BETWEEN SECRETARY OF STATE FOxiJSPIA AND MEMBERS OF I.C.S. AND INDIAN POLICE ASSOCIATIONS,^f-J-Ch50 a.m. on SATURDAY APRIL 15th. 1946    ____Is,the principle accepted that in the event of termina--^fl-Qf the Sfiryinas^ due...to....constitutional changes, members
9 9 3nfiJiha^Secretary of State&apos;s Services will be grantedcompensation for loss of career and prospects&quot; in addition tonensien?The Secretary of State said that the Services hadalready been given can assurance to this effect and hecould neither add to it nor subtract therefrom.This was the assurance given in connection with thegrant admissible on retirement to war service recruits, andwas that the terms to be granted to existing members ofthe Services, while they had yet to be settled, would be!inot less favourable, considered as a whole, than thoseapplicable to new entrants1&apos;.
ANNEX Vsars oftwiceProposecl compensationgrants for Europeano f f: i c e r a o 1  t h e I v G. S;and for Indian Officersof the I.0.3.   in specialcategories.Secretary of State&apos;proposed grants for indian officers of the 1.0.S.other than those fallingin special categoriescovered by lefthand column(to b e  suitab1y roun ded)5	2,500	7 90	3,000 :	3417		61 9	h,ooo	! .  .       &apos; . .   , : 915&quot;9	ks 500	1 ,229	5,000	1 ,56211	5,500	i ,91412	6,000	2,28613	; 6:, 500	2,680in	7,000	2- 3,09515	2 7,500 .	&apos;          ,,,:3,&apos;5331b	8,000	4, 00017	7,500	3,48018	7,000	2,99219	2;!   &apos; 2   :2 6,500	2,530	6,000	2,09521	5,500	1 ,688^2 1 &apos;        3l2	5,000	1 ,31223	4,500	964	4,000	6 Us25	3,500 3,000	I 2 &apos; &apos;        ; 2&apos;:. .   360It	2,500	u	2, 000	29	1 , 500		1 , 000 500 2          [l!	I1    :   !		32 and over	Nil	


</content>
</cab>
