<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 339-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)9%9iJCOPY NO.HOME PRODUCTION OF EOOD IN 19U7Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and FisheriesAt the meeting of the Cabinet on 1st April,  191+7(C.M.(b7) 3Uth Conclusions, Minute 9)  the Agricultural ministers were invited to circulate a further memorandum outlining themeasures they were taking to secure the maximum output of home produced food in 191-1-7.      The following memorandum has beenprepared on a Great Britain basis but owing to the absence of theSecretary of State for Scotland today on official duties he hasnot had an opportunity of seeing it in its final form.      I am therefore,   in view of the urgency,  circulating it as a memorandumby myself and I trust that the Secretary of State for scotland will be able to inform the Cabinet on Tuesday of his concurrence.2. In complying with the Cabinet&apos;s request I have deemed it advisable to deal with the subject from the following aspects:-(a) A fresh appreciation of the losses of crops and stockand of their effect  upon  production in  the current year.(b) An outline of the measures already taken to securemaximum production.(c) The probable effect of such measures.(d) Possible methods of securing additional production.Losses of Crops and Stock3&quot; An approximate interim estimate of farming losses asascertained during the period 21 st/2b,.th March was included in cp. (a,7)  1-16,  circulated to the Cabinet on 28th March,  19b7-A further appreciation of the position has since been prepared.It is still incomplete but it is clear that the losses of livestock in the hill areas are heavier than in the earlierestimate, while the loss or damoge to crops will probably be less;  than was at first  feared.h*      (a)    Extent of Floods.      The estimate of the area flooded isnow increased from 6&quot;00,00Q acres to 690,000 acres,  of which325,000 acres are tillage.      183,000 acres out of this 325,000acres should recover in time for ordinary cropping this year and half of the remainder should be fit for catch crops or specialcrops of one kind or another, leaving 71,000 acres not croppablethis year.      The previous estimate was 100,000 acres.Aja 0 R 3 Tn.V.(U7) 12818th April; 19b7oCABINET
(b) Crop Losses.      The estimate of winter corn  lost byfrost or flood is now reduced to 116,000 acres;    and some ofthat winter corn will be replaced by spring corn or other crops.It seems likely that taking into account not only the above116,000 acres but also reduced sowings last autumn,  the wheatacreage this year will come out at about 1,940,000 acrescompared with the target of 2,500,000 acres.      The sugar beetacreage is likely to be reduced by 25,000 acres compared withthe target  (L20,000 acres),  and potatoes are also likely to bereduced,  though by an unknown amount.      For the remaining crops,mainly barley and oats,  it is difficult to say whether therewill be a net gain or loss.      Generally, we have to take intoaccount not only flood damage but the lateness of the seasonand the waterlogged condition of much of the heavy land not affected by major floods.      These factors also make it probable that crop yields per acre will be lower than average.(c) 19L6 Potatoes.      The latest estimate of 1946 potatoeslost through frost or flood (Great Britain)  is 75,000 tons.(d) Reduction in Crop Values.      A loss of 71,000 floodedacres not croppable this year represents about  2-j millions of food production.      A general reduction in yields of the mainfarm crops of 10 per cent,   (if this is how the season turnsout) would, add a further  20 millions.      75,000 tons of 1 9i4.6potatoes lost represents  600,000 and there has also been asubstantial loss of vegetables.(e) Losses of Livestock.      Present estimates of sheep and lamb losses-&quot;(&quot;including Scotland)  are 1,137,000 hill sheen(25/c of the flock),  351,000 lowland sheep (8/0),  and 2,700,000lambs (30/i of a normal crop).      Total sheep and lamb losses are put at 4, 188,000 (21/0 of the 1946 flocks).Losses of cattle are now estimated at 50,000 head,an increase of 20,000 on the previous figure.The effect of livestock losses on food production will be spread over several years.      In 1947/48 they will amountto about  14 millions.(f) Total Lossi in Production.      Combined losses of cropand livestock production in  1947/48,  assuming normal cropyields,  would represent  16-g- millions,  or assuming a 10;*, declinein yields if the remainder of the season  is not favourable, 36f millions..5* These losses represent a  serious disaster,  both fromthe standpoint of our national  economy,   but particularly to large numbers of the smaller farmers whose financial position,even alter six years of Improved war-time prices,  is relatively weak and quite incapable of standing the strainunaided.      It is by no means certain that the measures already adopted will prove sufficient to produce a recovery in production which will avoid a serious loss of our home food supplies.Measures already taken to stimulate production.6.      (i)    Relief measures for those farmers who have sufferedserious loss by flood, snow or frost are already making good progress and will provide a valuable encouragement to them tore build their farming enterprises.      The Agricultural DisasterFund has made a most&quot;promising start.      Up to 18th April thetotal sum received -was approximately  135,000 and this will be
doubled by the Exchequer contribution.      There is still,  however,an immense gap between the relief sums at present in  sight andthe estimate of direct losses of stock,  crops and means ofproduction which is about  8f millions.      This figure representscapital losses and takes no account of loss of income.(ii) Pour meetings of the Emergency Advisory Committee havebeen held, and action has been taken on a considerable number oforactical suggestions put forward.(iii)    In particular,   the details of the scheme for specialacreage payments in respect of late-sown crops grown on floodedland (approved in  principle by the Cabinet on 1st April)  havebeen announced.(iv)    An emergency meeting of all Chairmen of county agricultural Executive Committees in England and Wales was heldon 15th ppril at which the situation was reviewed and plans to stimulate maximum production through the medium of the county committees and their District Committees were discussed.(v)    Detailed advice on emergency cropping has been  issued to County Agricultural Executive Committees in England and wd.esana to officers of the National Agricultural Advisory Service for communication to farmers.      This indicates the crops and cultivationmethods likely to give the best results under the conditions of late sowing and inadequate preparation of the land that must prevailthis season.(vi)    Additional supplies of fodder and rationed feedingstuffshave been despatched to the hill areas.(vii)    Energetic action has been taken to repair breaches ofriver embankments and to pump off water from the flooded areas,including the procurement on  loan of special equipment and experts from the Netherlands.      At the height of the floods some690,000 acres were under water.      This has now been reduced to85s000 seres consisting of the land flooded Owing to breachesin embankments.      The lighter lands that have been cleared arealready being cultivated.(viii) To help farmers to re-stock depleted flocks and herdsthe Agricultural Goods and Services Scheme is being extended toprovide credit for the purchase of livestock.(ix)    All available resources of labour and machinery are beingmobilised and utilised in those parts of the country where suchhelp can be most effective.Probable effect of measures already taken7* No quantitative estimate can yet be prepared of theeffect of the measures specified above,  but they have undoubtedly helped to put new heart into the farming community and in conjunction with the propaganda already undertaken,  haveimpressed upon them the urgent need to go all out with springcultivations and sowings in order to make up for lost time.8* The Chairmen of -County Agricultural Executive Committees,at the Conference on  15th April,  expressed the view that while there is n0 lack of willingness,  there is serious anxiety asregards the considerable additional expense which is being incurred by farmers owing to long hours of overtime for whichthey cannot be certain of recoupment in view of the probability that yields generally will be reduced through late sowing and
*w O CJ, P**hs 4) ijinadequate preparation of the land.      The heavy clay lands inparticular (which represent about 25% of the total tillage area in the country) are still waterlogged and even with the improvedweather in the past week, will take some time to dry out, andcropping this season if undertaken must entail a serious riskof low yields.      Such land does not,  of course,  come within thescheme for acreage payments on flooded land (paragraph 6  (iii)above).      There are also some serious problems especially in hilldistricts where on some farms the losses of sheep and lambs havebeen as high as 75)&apos;o or even 90y0s  so that there is a real risk of farmers giving up.possible methods of securing additional production9. Since I submitted my previous paper (C.P.(d7)  116)  tothe Cabinet    on 28th March I have given further considerationto possible methods of applying a further stimulus to productionboth in the present season and in the next two or three years.10. The short-term problem is to secure the maximumrecovery in the production of crops this year,  and the maintenanceof milk production next winter, notwithstanding the setbacksof these recent disastrous months.      This will only be possible if farmers and their workers put in long hours of overtime,involving a substantial increase in costs of production which,it is estimated,  might amount to some  5-10 millions.      looked at as a practical food production proposition it is undoubtedly the case that a.quite considerable increase in our food suppliesthis year would be secured by the injection of  a special ad hocallowance to all farmers (since all are affected by the latenessof the season and the prospect of reduced yields)  to offset the extra costs which extra effort will involve.      An appropriateamount would be  7 millions.      Any such sum would have to beregarded as a wholly exceptional addition to farmers&apos;remuneration related to the unparalleled agricultural difficulties and food production needs of the present season;    and anundertaking would have to be secured from the farmers&apos;organisations that they recognised that there would be no questionof treating it as a new basis for price revisions at the nextFebruary review.11. There are two  alternative methods of injecting such asum,  via:-(0)    By price increasesThis method would give the maximum incentive to increased production since each additional unit of crops ox1 livestock product thereb3&apos;&apos; secured would increase the farmers&apos;  return;    there would be noextra costs of  administration nor new forms to beprepared and completed by formers.      On the otherhand price increases give the major benefit to those with the most productive soil.If prices were to be the chosen instrument I should propose to confine the increases to barley,  oats,potatoes,  sugar beet and probably milk,  seeing thatthe production of fodder crops for dairy herds will involve considerable over-time.-U-
fj 9fo   iii(d)    By acreage paymentsAn acreage payment of,  say,  1  per acre in respect ofthose spring crops the production of which is most needed in the national interest (barley, oats,dredge corn,  potatoes and sugar beet) would be muchmore of an ad hoc payment and most farmers,  even milkproducers, would benefit in some degree.      There is,however,  one serious objection, namely that theincreased reward could be earned with very littleincrease in&apos; output.      The return to the milk produceris also more indirect than with a price increase.Of the two methods the first would provide the betterincentive and more food.12. If my colleagues agree that some additional stimulusof this nature to food production during the next few months isdesirable, the detailed allocation of the proposed global sum of 7 millions would raise technical problems which would needdiscussion with the Farmers&apos; Unions.      I would accordingly suggestthat if the principle is approved its detailed application shouldbe left to the Agricultural Ministers to settle in-consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister of Pood.13. On the longer term problem all the evidence shows if-a tour food situation is likely to remain extremely difficult forsome years.      The productive processes in agriculture are necessarily slow moving and must be set in motion now to secureresults up to two years or even longer ahead.      Within the next two months farmers must be settling their cropping programme for the 19.1+8 harvest and any measures to encourage the developmentof livestock production may take still longer to fructify.11)-. On 9th April the Royal Agricultural Society of Englandsummoned a conference of representatives of all the leadingagricultural organisations in the country including farmers,  workersend landowners,  to consider the contribution which agriculturecould m..ive towards our food supply problems.      The Conference putforward a series of recowmendations which are reproduced in theAppendix to this memorandum.      Although the conference was entirelynon-political,  it was very representative in character and our political opponents will not fail to make use of these recommendations if the Governments actions can be represented asin any way insufficient to deal with the serious situation whichundoubtedly confronts the nation.15. In the light  of these circumstances I feel that I should indicate to my colleagues certain additional methods of encouraging the maximum development of production in this country that couldbe taken if the necessities of the situation are considered tojustify them.      These ore as follows:-(i).   Hill Sheep.      Payment of hill sheep subsidy in the threeyears I9I48,  191+9 and 1950 on the basis of the numbers inDecember 1 BUG which has already been approved by the Cabinet,  will only afford partial relief,  particularly in those cases where theloss of income will bo heavy.      The real need is to give sufficientencouragement to farmers who have had heavy losses to strive tohang on during the next two or three years while they are slowly-rebuilding their flocks.      There have been strong representationsin favour of the announcement of a minimum rate of subsidy for atleast two years, so that,  coupled with the payment on 1 9I+6 numbers,hill farmers would be assured of a minimum income.      The Kill
9 *i ?ySheep Subsidy is normally based on the economic position of hillfarmers in the preceding year.      In the present year the rate of subsidy is 8/9d.   per ewe and in the next two years it will certainly have to be substantially increased.      Next year it isprobable that the rate may well be as high as 15/-.      It would be quite sufficient for present purposes to guarantee a minimum of 10/- per ewe in 192+8 and 19b. 9.(ii)    Feedingstuffs.      The substitution of home production for part of our imports of livestock products is largely dependent uponincreased imports of feedingstuffs.      a limited increase in rotionscales for pigs,  poultry and certain other classes of stock will operate from 1 st. May.      Further substantial purchases offeedingstuffs from overseas countries would bring good dividends.This is a factor stressed by the Royal Agricultural Society&apos;conference and in other representations made to roe by farmers&apos;organisations.      The sooner.we can tell the farming community that further supplies of feeding stuff&apos;s are definitely in sight the sooner will they respond by expanding their breeding operations.It would slso help if an announcement could be made in the neiarfuture that a definite  proportion,  for example 20 per cent. ,  ofthe mi liable wheat and barley grown in 192+8 would be retainabluby the grower for livestock feeding.      &quot;//hen this question wasconsidered on 22+th January by the Lord President fs Committee it   .was decided that the announcement then to be made should be &quot;ingeneral terms and in  the statement made in the House on17th February farmers were merely told that they would be allowedto retain if they wish a significant proportion,  to be announcedlater,  of their rnillable wheat ond barley from the 192+8 harvest.(iii)    Rural Housing- and Labour.      Fear of a labour shortage has undoubtedly a retarding effect upon increased production.      labour supply is likely to be the main limiting factor,  at all eventsafter 192+7;    end more houses is the key to the labour problem.The R..4.S.E. Conference made a number of recommendations on thissubject (see paragraph (h)  of the Appendix).      These recommendationsdeserve immediate consideration,  ond I suggest that even if their adoption may not in every case be practicable in presentcircumstances, the general objective underlying thern should be approached with the utmost sympathy.16. Each 5 per cent,  increase in home production of cropsrepresents additional food to the value of  22 millions.      Each5 per cent,   increase  in total home production represents additionalfood to the value of  31 millions.      With the resources of men  and materials at our command we cannot expect an increase of the orderof  150 millions mentioned in the White Paper, Cmd.  7072,  on thePost War Contribution of British Agriculture to the Saving ofForeign Exchange.      But a material expansion could be secured if additional steps are taken on the lines indicated above.Losses of national production this year owing toblizzards,  floods and decreased yields from latesowing may amount to over  36 millions.      Farmerslosses will be of the same order of magnitude.(b)The emergency measures already taken or announced canonly cover a limited proportion of such losses.
(c)    Increased food supplies from home, production would besecuredThis year if an additional emergency allowance were providedfor 1,947 crops and milk at an approximate costof  7 millions.In future years(i)    If a minimum rate of hill sheep subsidy in 1946and 1949 of 10/- per head were declared.(ii)    If more feedingstuffs -were imported and an early announcement made that farmers could retain up to20 per cent,   of their raillable wheat and barley01  the 1948 crop.(iii)    If further efforts were made to provide houses for farm workers and thus to facilitate thelabour supply.T. w.-nistry of Agriculture and Fisheries,  S.W.1.18th April,&apos; 1947-
APPENDIXRenpraraendatipns.-of..theRoyal agricultural 3oe i e tyof England&apos;s Cdriference(a) An immediate statement must &quot;be made of minimum requirementsof production for all the main Crops to cover at least thenext five years,  accompanied by a continuing firm guarantee of prices and markets.(b) Special emphasis must be laid on the increased growing offeedings:!uffs and fodder crops, particularly protein-richcrops.(c) (i)    It is highly desirable that formers should be immediately informed that they may keep for their stock cdefinite proportion of all the grain that they can grow.Farmers would then be able to increase substantially theirdeliveries of meat and eggs for general consumption.(ii) Price    schedules should be designed to emphasise theimportance and encourage the rearing and production of livestock,  and especially the rehabilitation of the hillfarmer.(iii) Without prejudice to the system of periodic pricerevision, now generally accepted by the industry, weconsider that the exceptional nature of the present emergency necessitates  special measures to cover productionrisks during the next eighteen months.(d) The area of grassland lost by the larger tillage acreagecould be far more than  replaced if there were a vigorouscampaign for grassland improvement by direct re-seedingor other methods,  especially in those areas best suitedby soil and climate to grass production.      Such improvementmust constitute a major source of the requisite increasedfeedingstuff production and could be brought about at lecstas quickly as could the increased numbers of cattle and sheep needed to consume it.(e) Concurrent with this must be an extensive campaign toencourage the increased conversion of grass into concentratedfeedingstuffs,  e.g.,  silage and dried grass.      everything possible  should be done by His Majesty&apos;s Government to give priority to labour and material for the manufacture ofdried grass plants and to fuel for operating them.(f) We welcome the promised restoration of feedingstuffs rations.The full development of our livestock production can onlybe achieved if more feedingstuffs arc purchased from over-seas,  even if this means the sacrifice of existingalternative uses of our dollar resources.      As the EconomicWhite Paper points out,   1,0:00 expended on importedfeedingstuffs will produce twice that value of human food.
Any additional feeding stuff s must be used first to enablefarmers to rebuild their pig and poultry stocks, if necessarythrough some modification in the rationing system.      Such acourse will bring about a considerable increase in home foodproduction with very little  extra demand for labour orhouses,  os so many small farmers who depend on their pigs and poultry are to-day compelled to under-produce.A decision should be made that His Majesty&apos;s Government intendas a matter of policy to apply to those engaged in agriculturea measure of special deferment from National Service.      Allpossible steps must be taken to recruit more farm workers to meet the demands of increased production.(i) Special allocation of materials is urgently needed forthe rebuilding of traditional end prefabricated houses in rural areas,   on the basis of a transfer of 100,000 adultmale workers from the towns to the countryside.(ii) The h to 1 ratio against private buildings ofagricultural houses not for sale should be relaxed.(iii) Instructions must be given to local authorities(a) to give  priority for new houses in rural areas to farmworkers,  and (b)  that farmers  intending to employ additionalagricultural workers should apply for such houses.(iv) Increased allocation of materials for the repair ofexisting farm buildings and new buildings for agriculturalpur poses.(v) The Hobhouse report, which recommends the reconditioning of 100,000 rural houses,  must be put intoimmediate effect.(vi) Every facility should be given for accelerating theprovision of rural amenities (water,   electricity and sanitation)by local authorities,  by local supply companies,  and by private individuals.(vii) Increased food rations must be made available throughoutthe year to those who work overtime on the land.No machinery required for food production in this country must be exported until the requirements of our own farmers aresatisfied.      Special efforts must be continued to supply-spare parts and to import particular types of machines thatare not available in this country.No efforts should be spared to ensure adequate supplies of fertilisers - including potash - of which we are now short.


</content>
</cab>
