<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 364-366</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)1 9th Aj2Zii^i2kLCOAYY NO.  MiCABINETto bringImycolleagues when it bee;It is now necessary tomust ask my colleagues the sugar ration.RATION CHANGESMemorandum by the Minister of Foodwas&quot; instructed (CM. (kl) 33rd Conclusions, Minute 3)proposal to increase the sugar ration before myime necessary to reduce some other ration,reduce the ration of tea and meat so Ito  reconsider my proposal to increaseTEA . -2. It is now clear that the tea ration must be reduced from 2-f to 2 ozs.   per week:.      This is due to the refusal ofboth the Ceylon and Indian Governments to continue our bulk purchase ar.rangeme.nts.      The price of tea will also have to beraised by lid.  per lb.      The possibility of a restoration of the ration to the higher level depends upon the outcome of negotiations in India  and Ceylon, which ore being activelypursued at the present time.      In this connection one of myofficials is leaving for India this week.The cut must be made in the ration  period beginningThe Ministry of Agriculture has now furnished us Withestimate of the loss of livestock as a result of the recentizzards and floods.      These losses,  coming on top of theavy home killings last autumn due to the shortage of animaleding stuffs,  have proved the last straw, making inevitable aduction by 2d.  in the present meat ration.      I propose to  hakes reduction as from the end of June in the hope - but it more than a hope - of being able to restore the cut in theautumn,  so that consumers will not suffer the cut during thewinter months.h- My colleagues will see that two highly unpalatableannouncements must be made in regard to food in the immediatefuture.     There are probably no ration cuts more severe thantea and meat.nefethisI fear that these announcements,   unless offset in someaegree at least, will give very considerable assistsections of the Press end to themceConservative Party whoto thosearesecking^jio^ make the public believe that the fuel crisis is tcfr^i followed by a food crisis.
5. My main reason,  however, for again urging that weshould use our present ability to raise the sugar rationfrom&quot;8 to 10 oas.,  is that it would be profoundly wrong to refuse to distribute to the public such supplies of foodstuffs as can be made available to them.      I believethat it is essential to do what is possible to offset theabove severe cuts both on nutritional and psychologicalgrounds.      I should fear extremely the effect upon publicmorale generally,  and on production in particular,  of twonegative announcements unrelieved by any increase.I am fully alive to the extremely critical situationwhich faces the Chancellor in regard to dollars.      I neednot repeat here the  position as set out in my paper cp. (47)  99*  since it is common ground between myself andthe Chancellor that no further dollar expenditure is needed for the increased distribution of sugar.I submit to my colleagues that we should havereached an impossible position if we felt unable to distributeto the public even what foodstuffs we had been able topurchase,  for fear of contingent effects upon our dollarposition eighteen months to two years hence.      In general i could not agree with such a refusal to make available basicfoodstuffs,  such as sugar,  which have actually been purchased,until and unless far less Important imports had been dispensed with.J. S.Ministry of Pood,  S.W.1.&apos;19th April,  1947.


</content>
</cab>
