<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 376-380</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SEC RET COPY NO.CP. (47).. 155   &apos;82ND: APRIL; 1947CABINETTHE NATIONAL SERVICE bill memorandum by the Minister of defence i have discussed with the Service Ministers certainimplications of the recent decision to amend the NationalService Bill by reducing the period of full-time service withthe Forces from eighteen months to twelve.      As some of theseImplications may require additional amendment of the Bill,  i submit them for the decision of my colleagues.(1)    The total jievtod of liability to service under theBill is not affected by the decision to reduce the period of full-time service to twelve months:    i.e.   it remains as stated in Clause 2 of the Bill as expiring with the end ofthe seventh year after the beginning of a man&apos;s whole-time service.      But,  as a consequence of the reduction in theperiod of full-time service to twelve months,  the part-time service liability will now extend over the remaining six years.      The question arises whether the aggregate periodof training during those six years should remain at sixtydays, with a maximum of twenty-one days in any one year.The Service Ministers all stress the fact that national Service men after only twelve months&apos; full-time service with the Forces will be less efficient to take theirplaces in the reserve,  and in turn to fill the ranks of theForces in an emergency.      The six months&apos;  reduction in full-time service means,   in particular,  that National Service men,while they will in the majority of cases be able to carry through their basic training, will not have the same term ofservice on a sea-going ship or  in the ra-nks  of a unit which makes a great difference to the readiness of a reserviston mobilisation.On Service grounds,   therefore,  there are very strong arguments for increasing the aggregate period of sixtydays at present set out in Clause 2 of the Bill,  and i recommend that the Cabinet should approve an increase inthe period.      As regards the nature of the increase, myService colleagues are strongly in favour of amending theBill to fix the aggregate period of part-time service at90 days, which would enable the Army and the R.A.F.,  if they wished?  to call up a man for 15 days annual training in eachof the&apos;six years of reserve service (or to adopt any variantof those arrangements found to be more satisfactory inpractice).      This  increase would also cover the Navy&apos;s wishto be able to call up a man for not less than 84 days spreadover six years, preferably in fairly long spells at a time.
On the other hand,  a proposal to increase the period to90 days,  apart from its political reactions,  may beregarded as too onerous a burden upon our civilian economy.In that event the alternative would be to adopt a reasonablecompromise &quot;between the conflicting needs of the Servicesand of industry by fixing the period at say 75 days.The related question concerns the maximum periodof a man&apos;s reserve liability in any one year - at present21 days.      In the Army and the Royal Air Force, approximately15 days annual training will be the normal rule.      The FirstLord,  on the other hand,  has represented strongly that aminimum of 28 days sea-going training at a time will now he required for the naval reservist.      The Arimiraltyrealise that it may not be easy to spare men from their civil employment for as long as a month at a time.      Onthe other hand,  the man himself - and in certain casespossibly also his employer - may prefer reserve trainingin periods of four continuous weeks  in certain yearsrather than a fortnight each year.       In view of thepolitical and economic  issues involved,  I think theCabinet should decide whether Clause 3 of the Bill shouldalso be amended to provide for a maximum of 28 days(instead of 21 days) of part-time service in any year of reserve liability.(2)   With 18 months full-time service,  it had been hoped to have a fairly comprehensive syllabus of further education for national service men on a compulsory basis in Service time,  supplemented by wide facilities on a voluntary basis in a man&apos;s own time.      The amount ofService time available for such purposes  in the 12 monthsperiod of full-time service will necessarily now be smaller,  and I must warn ray colleagues that the obligationplaced upon the Service Departments,   in Clause 10(2) ofthe Bill,  to provide further education, will have to be interpreted in a narrower sense than had been contemplatedwith 18 months full-time service.       I suggest no amendmentof this Clause of the Bill:    the obligation is alreadyqualified by the words &quot;so far as may be ijracticable&quot;which give wide discretion to the Services.      It shouldbe made clear&quot; on the Committee stage in the House thatthere will be practical limitations  on the amount offurther education possible for the national service manin Service time.(5)    The next point concerns the treatment of nationalservice entrants before 1st January 1949, when the proposals in the new Bill take effect.The White Paper (Cmd.   6831) relating to  the callup in the transition years 1947/48 provided for the&quot;shading-off&quot; of the two year period of service of such men during the call-up months January to December 1948,in order that such men might be released gradually overthe period to July 1950.      Under the National Service bill as originally introduced men called up from 1st January 1949with an 18 months liability would begin to be released from july 1950.      Now that these latter men will serve only for12 months and that the first of them will be due for releaseby January 1950,  the shadirig-off of the period of serviceof pro-January 1949 entries calls for re-consideration.
The questions involved are complicated ones and require expert  examination by the Service Departments andthe Ministry of Labour.      Meanwhile,  however,  the more immediate question arises of whether a pledge should begiven in the very near future that national service men called up before  1st January 1949 will not be held toserve (apart possibly from individual cases of operationalurgency) after the first call up of men under the newBill are released,   i,e.  by January 1950.       I have already had one Parliamentary Question on this point, but I haveavoided giving any specific pledge.There might be some advantage in such a pledgebeing given at an early date.      The Service Ministerspoint out,  however,  that the effect of guaranteeing therelease of all pre-January 1949 men by 1st January 1950may lead to a dangerous denuding of the Forces in thelatter part of 1949 and during 1950.      They also pointout that those called up before 1st January .1949 willescape all reserve liability and that from the point.ofview of equity, they could be held to a longer periodof service.      I think this is a matter- which requiresdec is i on. by t he C ab ine t.The points on which I ask for Cabinet decisionare as follows:-(i)    Is the aggregate period of part-time service ofnational service men during their 6 yearsreserve liability to be increased above thepresent total of 60 days in Clause 2(3) ofthe Bill,  and if so to a period of 90 days:  or  to the intermediate period of 75 days?(ii)    Is the maximum duration of full-time trainingin any year of reserve liability to beincreased from the SI days, mentioned in clause 2(5),  to 28 days?Both the above would require amendments to thepresent Bill.(iii)    Is a pledge to be given at an early date in theHouse that no man called ud before 1st January1949 will be held to serve&quot; after January 1950,when men called up under the provisions of thenow Bill are released?A.V.A.&quot;Ministry of Defence,  S. W. 1.22nd April,   1947,

The attached paper,CP. (47) &quot;134,  is circulated for consideration at theMeeting of the Cabinet to deheld tomorrow, TUESDAY,22FD APRIL,  1947, at 11.0 a.rnCabinet Office, S.W.1.21 ST APRIL,  1947.

</content>
</cab>
