<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/18/0 images: 401-404</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS IOCTUIIEIMT iS TfiE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC HAj^TYjg GOVMTOT)&apos;SECRET COPY NO.      2 9CP. (47) 137.26th April, 1947CABINETINTERNATIONAL ALLOCATION OP TUCBERL emoiT.ndum by the President of the Board cf TradeI feel that,  in considering my paper (CP. (47) 136) on theinternational allocation of timber, my colleagues should also have before them the attached telegram since received from the Secretary for overseas Trade in Moscow, on which I should like to offer the followingpurely objective observations,(i) The suggestion that we;should only offer to discuss with other  .E.G.E. members the allocation of any global excess over 1,965,000standards, rather than any British excess over 1,122,000 standards, hasthe difficulty that we have already accepted allocation from the TimberSub-Committee of 1,122,000 standards; on the basis of total estimatedavailabilities of 1,965*000&apos; standards, and arc therefore only entitledto more if estimated availabilities are increased.    To assume and actupon such an increase in availabilities now without prior discussionwith Timber Sub-Goran ittee would, not only expose us to c charge of bad faith, but would almost certainly lead to a break up of the wholeallocation system.   Moreover, it would be difficult at present to showwhether total availabilities were in excess cf 1,965,000, which includes100,000 from U.S.S.R.(ii) The U.K. representative stated, at last meeting of E. E. C. E.  onthe 1st April last that we accept principle of equitable distribution,that we will abide by our total allocation from the present estimatedavailabilities, and that if these increase we will adhere to ourpercentage of the total.    This is more than our share on a pre-war basis.(iii) I had not thought that an offer to share excess over 1,122,000standards was very dangerous.    It would refer explicitly to probablearrivals in 1947, and. on present estimates a substantial excess is not likely.    In any event, our share of the excess would be not less thanelevcn-ninet eenths.(iv) The offer to share excess was not intended to apply specifically to Russian timber as such,  and there is nothing; in the proposals in cp. (47)136 which need at present affect cur demand for timber in theRussian negotiations.   We should, expect to offer adjustments mainly on german logs and sawn timber, and by offers of dollar or krona timber,though some flexibility may be necessary both on technical grounds andto meet currency position of particular countries,  e.g, Penmark and holland.It0 8j C,Board of Trade,Millbank,S.W.1.April, 1947,
Cypher/OTP ASKE17-EROir MOSCOW TO BOivRP OF TRADE(From United Kingdom Delegation to Council of foreign ministers)No, 12 ASKEW - D, 5.18 p.m.    23rd. April, .1947.23rd Aoril, 1947.P., 7.59 p.u.   23rd April, 1947.MOST BaiSDIATEFollowing from Secretary for Overseas Trade to President ofBoard of Trade.With reference to paper which Board of Trade were consideringputting in on European timber allocation machinery as affecting any supplies v;c may got from Russia I have mentioned to foreign secretary and have told him yours and my view that our general line should be to got the timber first and argue about it afterwards.2.   While agreeing with proposal that in case we appear to behogging all the timber supplies we should discuss with Denmark and holland methods whereby softwood logs felled in Germany might be diverted to then, my own view is that the suggestion that we should give a prior (repeat prior) general undertaking that if our Russianpurchases should bring us above our total of 1,122,000 standards weshould give other E.E. G.E. members an opportunity to share in the excess on a pro rata -presumably eleven-nineteenths basis, would betying our hands far too much.   Wc might consider saying wo should prefer to discuss the allocation of any global excess over1,965,000 standards rather than any British excess over 1,122,000standards since it is possible we may reach our quota, though the global figure of 1,965,000 remains unattained, but wc should keepour hands fairly free so as to be able to offer dollar timber forre-allocation but on such a basis that if dollar timber is to beincluded in pool all countries take fair share of dollar timberand not leave us in position that patient ox bears undue share of dollar burden thus making it easier for other European countries toacquire soft currency timber.3c    Foreign Secretary has seen the foregoing and agrees with it.   He agrees we should not bo too tender about international machinery for European timber allocation if this means sacrificingour own interests in respect of any extra timber wc get as a resultof our own enterprise, dollars and/or steel.    Taking a toughline about the E.E. C.E. timber arrangements should not (repeatnot) have any effect on other international bodies allocatingscarce materials which are on different basis being much moredependent on American supplies.   E.E.C.E. timber is partlydependent on our efforts and sacrifices and the dollar timber isnot fundamental to the allocation and is in fact unwelcome to anumber of countries.    He would strengthen my suggestion inparagraph 2 to say not only that dollar burden should be shared butthat if any increase in global supply duo to our exporting steeletc., were to be allocated wc should receive quid pro quo inadditional steel e,g. from Belgium as in dollar value of steel.Suggested compromise based on 1,965,000 rather than 1,122,000 isvery important because prospects of reaching latter much betterthan those of reaching former.    Foreign Secretary stresses that
arrangcncnts agreed here for removing German factories in category i will make great demand on Gorman packaging naterials particu.lo.rly timberand this :iay affect global figure of 1,9653 000 more than our own supplyof 1,122,000 would bo affected if we succeeded here.    Timber availabilitiesfrom Germany nay also be affected by any upward adjustment of the levelof industry which we nay agree bilaterally with the Americans,4.    There is no doubt that prior undertaking to submit Russiantimber to re-allocations would greatly cnbarrass us here in dealings&apos;with Prussians.   Foreign Secretary was very definite on this point,5,    Foreign Secretary enquired about Prague timber, conference andI told him. of our offorbs at Washington and elsewhere to prevent it-being held.    He very much endorsed the line in the instructions to ourPrague team that allocation of timber in period of short supply was not(repeat not) the function of F.A.0.  and that we should resist theestablishment of new machinery for this purpose.


</content>
</cab>
