<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/209/23 images: 491-494</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(80) 4fc29 July 1980COPY NO82CABINETEDUCATION AND LOCAL AUTHORITY CURRENTEXPENDITURE IN 1981-82Memorandum by the Chief Secretary, Treasury1.        At Cabinet last week (CC(80) 30th Conclusions, Minute 7) we agreedI should discuss further, with the Secretaries of State for Education andScience, the Environment, Scotland and Wales, my proposals for savingson the education programme in 1981-82, and to report.   I and the otherMinisters have been unable to reach agreement, and I now ask Cabinet toresolve the issue.2. We have two agreed aims: (a) to keep the public expenditure totalfor 1981-82 within the Cmnd 7841 figure as reduced by the EuropeanCommunity receipts, and (b) to announce a 2 per cent reduction in totallocal authority current expenditure between 1980-81 and 1981-82.   In orderto achieve (a), I still consider that we need a net cut of  50 million in thetotal education programme in England ( 87 million gross allowing for theloss on school transport).   In order to achieve (b), we need at least a 28 million net ( 67 million gross) reduction in total local authoritycurrent expenditure in England and Wales from the levels agreed so far,and I propose that that cut should be made on education ( 63 million grossin England,  4 million in Wales).3. The Secretary of State for Education and Science has offered areduction of only  45 million gross on his total programme, ie about 8 million net, made up as follows:1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL m 1980 survey pricesLocal authority current, relevantfor Rate Support Grant:Advanced further education 10Other (village halls etc) 5Central government, andl.a. other:15UniversitiesStudent awardsSchools, capitalHigher education capital3045101055In order to protect current spending on schools, he proposes that only 15 million should come off bis local authority current expenditure, resultingin a net increase in such expenditure of about  22 million.   This wouldmean an overall net reduction in local authority current expenditure inEngland and Wales between 1980-81 and 1981-82 of only 1. 6 per cent.4. The Secretary of State for Education and Science has suggested thatthe needed reduction in local authority current expenditure should not be oneducation alone.    I attach a table covering both England and Wales,demonstrating the consequences if, concentrating for the moment solelyon our second agreed aim, we either make the cut on education (columns 4and 5) or spread it pro rata over all services except law and order(columns 6 and 7).5. I do not recommend the second course.    The education programmewould still have to take a much bigger gross cut than the Secretary of Statehas yet offered, and some programmes would need to be cut even thoughwe have reason to think that the local authorities will overspend rather thanunderspend on them (personal social services and local environmentalservices).   Moreover, the Secretary of State for the Environment hasmade it clear to me that he would wish to reconsider his agreement tocontribute a cut of  65 million on housing to our first aim ((a) above) ifthe proposed cut of  87 million gross is not made in the Secretary of Statefor Education and Science&apos;s programme.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALCONCLUSION6.        I invite Cabinet to agree that:i. the total education programme in England in 1980-82should be reduced by  50 million net (about  87 million gross);andii. within that figure, local authority current expenditureon education in England in 1981-82 should be cut by at least 26j million net (about  63 million gross), with a correspondingreduction in Wales.J BTreasury Chambers29 July 19803CONFIDENTIAL
IN ENGLAND AND WALKEducation (includingschool meals + milk)Arts and LibrariesPersonal social servicesPoliceAdministration of justiceFireHighways and transportHousing (non HRA)Local environmental, ser-vicesAgricultureIndustry, Energy, Trade,EmploymentOther public servicesTOTALPercentage difference fromcolumn 11980-81RSGsettlement6703223124615121623911123551896j13311  million, 1980 survey prices1981-82surveybaselineplus schoolt&apos;port loss(2)(3)6544 6583211127315691633781076501586m 69012813074-113113Cut in education00651621112731569163378107650158569012813045-2.0%(5) =(4)-(3)-67*Cut in all servicesexcept law + order(6)-1/-6813045-2.0%(7) =(6)-(3)6544	-39210	-11265^	lf 1569	 163	 376	-21069-J	-6}50	 1575^	-10}6	 89*	127	-1-68% Gross of school transport.   The reduction of  67 million divides as  63 million to England and  4 million toWales.   The cuts xn column 7 would divide similarly./ Arterial drainage. # School transport loss about  39 million:  37m in England and about  2m in Wales

</content>
</cab>
