<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/124/0 images: 244-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC Iv AJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)66C(66) 30 copy NO._9th February, 1966CASKETIiSASEHQID REFORML-&quot;. e it ii or an dura by the -Lord ChancellorIntroductoryI regret that I disagree with the majority of the ministerial committee on Legislation on Rent, Land Commission and leasehold enfranchisement on several of the proposals outlined in thememorandum by the Lord president  of the Council (C(66) 29)*    hiDecember (C. C. (65) 73rd Conclusions, I/minute 2) the Cabinet were unable to accept proposals submitted by the Ministerial Committee(in C.(65) 184) because it considered them too expropriatery.    I am convinced that the present proposals would result in considerably more extensive expropriation than the earlier proposals.    It is true that inthe limited number of cases where the property has a substantialdevelopment potential, compensation under the present proposals will-be higher than under the earlier ones;  but in all other cases it will notbe significantly different (there is no material difference between theeffect of a 50 year extension and a 999 year extension on the freeholder^interest) and the number of properties to which the present proposals will apply will be very much greater.    In December it was proposed to exclude persons who had originally purchased a term of 21 years or less(C(65) 184, paragraph 2(3)):  now, subject only to a residentialqvtalification of five years, all late-comers are to be included.    Ashouses change hands on average once in seven years, a very largenumber of leasehold properties disqualified under the earlier proposals are now included.Leaseholders on short terms2.       Cur legislation is intended to be a social measure to consolidate the leaseholder^ stake in his house and to prevent him being deprived of the value of the property he has bought and paid for.    It is not designed simply to confer benefits on every leaseholder, still less toexpropriate all reversionary rights.    We therefore propose to excludeleases originally granted for 21 years or less;   only long leases qualify.But the interest acquired by the leaseholder is the same whether heoriginally bought a new lease for a short term or the remainder of an existing lease for the same term.    In neither case does he pay forthe building;  he is not in any sense &quot;buying the house&quot;.     The proposed scheme would fortuitously give the latter, but not the former, the rightto acquire the freehold with vacant possession on highly advantageous terms.    (As the figures in the Appendix show, in fee first example(Case IV) fee proposal v/ould enable a leaseholder who bought the tail-end of the lease, probably for a few hundred pounds, to buy out fori     j -1- &apos;:
/&apos; u /, 0 &apos; 195 a freeholder1 s interest worth  825 and so to gain an immediatelysaleable capital asset of  1, 500;  in the second example  800 would buyhim a freeholder1 s interest worth  2, 630 giving him a capital assetv/oth  4, 000.     The only comparable case in the table annexed to theLord President&apos;s memorandum is No. 3 (i, e. the only example wherethe lease will shortly expire) where a payment cf  150 will buy a 1, 300 asset.)    Many leaseholders who had bought short remainders for very little money could be given large windfalls which could not bejustified by any social merit.     Unless the leaseholder has a claim in social equity (o. g. because of the price he paid for the house or of the prolonged occupation by himself and his forbears) there can be no justification for giving him mis fortuitous gain or for depriving thefreeholder (who may have paid for the full present day value of thereversion).    In their application to late-comers the proposals areindefensible.     There must either be an exclusion of purchasers of short terms, or the calculation of the enfranchisement price must take account of the length cf the term originally acquired by the leaseholder.I/Iinimum term of 21 years.       One solution would be to revert tc the proposal made inDecember, in paragraph 2(3) of C. (65) 184, that holders of terms of 21years or less should not be entitled to any extension of their leases andshould be given the right to enfranchise only at the market value of thefreeholder&apos;s interest.Price related to leaseholder 1 s interest4.       Another solution, which has the attraction that it does not draw a somewhat arbitrary line between those who benefit from the legislation and those who do not, is the Minority proposal indicated in paragraph 5of C(66) 29.    It would take account of the leaseholder&apos;s merit in calculating the price for enfranchisement and enable those leaseholderswho originally bought a long term, or who still have a lengthy unexpiredterm, to enfranchise cheaply, while those who bought a short term andare now near the end of that term, would pay something approaching thefull market value.     This result can be achieved if the price forenfranchisement is made the value which the freeholder&apos;s interest wouldhave at the date of enfranchisement, if it were subject to a lease which still has as long a, period to run as that originally acquired by the leaseholder or his forbears.    Examples of the operation of such a formula are given in the Appendix.    Broadly speaking, the price whichthe leaseholder would have to pay for enfranchisement would be equivalent (expressed in up-to-date money terms) to the additionalamount which he would have had to pay when he bought his lease ifinstead cf buying only a lease he had then bought the freehold.    In my view, that is exactly what in equity v/e ought to achieve.Extension of fee lease5.       The 50 year extension proposed in paragraph 2(2) of 0(66) 29v/ill give the leaseholder in every case the full value of the building,whether he has paid for it or not.     The figures annexed to thememorandum show that the value of the freeholder&apos;s interest isdrastically reduced.    The objections raised earlier in this memorandum to the uncovenanted benefits which the proposed enfranchisement rights
would confer on late-comers apply equally to this extension.Leaseholders who bought late in the term have no mo-*al claim to the valuable proprietary interest which a 50 year extension gives them, andI can see no justification for giving them more than the right to remainin occupation on a &quot;fair rent&quot; which they already enjoy under the 1954Landlord and Tenant Act.    For holders of longer terms the terms ofenfranchisement v/ill be so generous, that I would doubt that manyleaseholders would fail to take advantage of them and rely on anextension of the lease.    However, to assist those who fail to enfranchise,I would not be averse to an extension for a moderate period, say 21year s.Rights reserved to the freeholder6.       I am also unable to agree with the majority of the ministerial committee on the proposed rights reserved to the freeholder (paragraph2(4) cf C(66) 29).     They would deny the freeholder the right to resistenfranchisement on the ground that he wished to redevelop the property.At present a freeholder who is intent on redeveloping a leasehold areacan keep his property intact by refusing enfranchisement andredeveloping when the leases fall in.    The proposals would enable anyleaseholder in the area to enfranchise and thereby to frustrate any possibility cf planned redevelopment by the freeholder.    In effect theproposals would put an end to ail future planned redevelopment ofleasehold property by private landlords.     That in my view is notconsistent with the public interest or with our vision of a modernisedBritain.    I suggest that a freeholder who can show a settled intentionto redevelop should be able to resist enfranchisement (or an extensionof the lease) but that he should have to pay the leaseholder compensationequal to the lec beholder!s interest as enhanced by this legislation.conclusion.       I therefore ask my colleagues not to agree to the proposals putforward by the majority of the Ministerial Committee unless they are qualified in the way I have suggested.G.House of Lor d s, S. &quot;V7. .1.8th February, 19&amp;6
APPENDIXFiaST 3XA2PLEA small house - original lease 99 years -rateable value  40 - ground rent  1 -current value ground rent  10 - &quot;fair rent&quot; 50.Vacant possession value 1,500Case case IICase IIICase IVPresent occupier bought with 60 years unexpired.At date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 30 years.Present occupier bought with 40 years unexpired.At date of enfranchisement unexpired tern is 10 years.Present occupier bought with 20 years unexpired.At date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 5 years.Present occupier bought with 10 years unexpired,,At date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 1 day.Case case IICase IIICase IVPresent market value ofFreeholder^Interest65*135**2A0*400**348*550**550*825**Price for Enfranchisementif leaseextendedby 50 years55125160195if leaseextendedby 21 years55125165220Price forEnfranchi s ementon basis proposedin this paper45     .110185305*   Vfnere third party buys freeholder1 s interest.** Market price where leaseholder purchases freeholder&apos;s interest,(DCOMFBDENTIAL
SECOND example suburban house Tfith garden - originallease 99 years - rateable value  150 -ground rent  7 - current value groundrent  AO - &quot;fair rent&quot;  185.Vacant possession value A,000Case case IIPresent occupier bought 60 years unexpiredoAt date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 30 years.Present occupier bought with AO years unexpired.At date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 10 years.Case IIICase IVPresent occupier bought with 20 years unexpired.At date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 5 years.Present occupier bought with 10 years unexpired.At date of enfranchisement unexpired term is 1 day.Case case IICase IIICase IVPresent market value ofFreeholder&apos;sInterest340*675**925*1380**1400*1900**2020*2630**Price for Enfranchisement   jif lease	if leaseextended	extended by 50 years	by 21 years250	250510	510650	650845800Price forEnfranchis ementon basis proposedin this paper2254827601165*   Where third party buys freeholder&apos;s interest** Market price where leaseholder purchases freeholder&apos;s interest(2)


</content>
</cab>
