<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/124/0 images: 292-305</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy No.C[66Ilth FebruaiCABINETDEFENCE BS^jpNh^BJTUEE EC^E^mUCTUljEMemorandum by the Secretary of State fcr defence the defence review aimed at reducing defence expenditure in1969/70 from about  2,400 million at 1964 prices, which would havebeen the cost of the programme we inherited from the previous administration, to  2,000 million.     It also aimed at reducing theforeign exchange cost of defence,,     On 5th August last year I told the House that we had managed to reduce the forecast total to about 2,180 million.     I now submit proposals for talcing the review asfar as it can be taken at present,2a     The Defence and Oversea Policy Committee have reviewed alloverseas defence commitments and have agreed that we should make some changes which would enable the cost of the forces to bereduced.     A detailed statement of the resulting force structure,the assumptions on which it is based and its cost is contained in annex A.     The main assumptions on commitments are -(i)   our commitments to NATO in Germany will continue asat present planned but with some reduction In theprovision of strike aircraft;(ii)   it will be possible to agx-ee with the United States a sufficiently firm basis for joint action in Libya to limit our commitment to the provision of a securepoint of entry;(iii)   in the Middle East we shall have no obligations toAden or the South Arabian Federation after Adenbecomes independent in. 19^8, and the commitment toassist Kuwait will be limited to the provision ofair support unless the Ruler gives us time to moveland forces from the United Kingdom or the Far east to Kuwait;-1-TQP  secret the circulation of this paper has been strictjIt is issued for the personal use of......-:TOP  SECRET
(iv) in the Indo/Pacific area we shall provide a visiblemilitary presence of sea, land and air forces basedon Australia.The defence review has throughout been based on the assumption thatthe confrontation of Malaysia by Indonesia will have ended before1969/70.3,     The force structure described in Annex A would contain fixedwing aircraft carriers until 1975? but no new carriers, would be built.The Army would be reduced to 176,000 and the Gurkhas disbanded.For the koyal Air Force 50 3? lllAJs would be bought and the P 1127provided.4.     Annex A shows that this force structure would require a defenoebudget of  2,060 million in 1969/70 at 1964 prices.     The foreign exchange cost in 1969/70 would amount to about  195 million forstationing forces overseas and about  80 million for the purchase of equipment, a total of  275 million compared with  355 million on   ,present plans, without taking account of any arrangements with theGerman Government to offset our foreign exchange costs in germany or with the American Government to offset the cost of the F 111Apurchase.     All these figures assume that the revised deploymentwill be in full effect by 1st April 19^9,     In fact, however, the uncertainty about when confrontation by Indonesia will end, the physical difficulties of redeployment and reorganisation, added toother possible delays before the revised pattern of commitments canbe put into effect, may well make this assumption unrealistic,     Itis not possible to estimate the amount of transitional expenditure involved.5,     Annex A also shows that in the years after I969/7O there wouldbe a small increase in the size of the defence budget,     Whateverwe decide about 1969/70 it is important that the Ministry of defence should be able to plan on the assumption that if it proves to benecessary some small increase in later years will be permitted,perhaps related to the rate of growth of the G-ross National Product.6,     I have considered what further economies might be made inorder to eliminate the gap of  60 million between the estimatedcost of the defence programme in I969/7O and the target of 2,000 million.     This difference is in fact accounted for by
the contingency allowance which we have added to the calculated costof the programme to cover unexpected requirements and increases in costs other than those due to rises in pay and the prioe level,when we have the results of the 1966 Long Term Costing in June itmay be possible to make some further reduction in this contingencyallowance,7,     The only way of achieving substantial further savings withoutgrave danger of failing to meet the commitments now envisaged wouldbe to cancel the P 1127,     This would save  35 million&apos; in 1969/70*though it would increase foreign exchange costs by  5 million.There is no other project which could be given up without a serious risk that commitments could not be met,8,     The assumptions about commitments on which the costing is basedmay well prove to be unrealistic.     This is particularly true ofthe assumptions about the ending of confrontation and the redeploy-ment of forces in Australia,     My discussions in Canberra showed that, if we have to leave Singapore and Malaysia by 1969/70, thereis no possibility of redeploying forces of the size proposed inAustralia by then; moreover, even if redeployment were only post-poned, it is unlikely that the Australian Government would agreethat land forces of the size proposed should be based in Australia,It follows, therefore, that once we leave Singapore and Malaysia, weshould be able to achieve some further savings in foreign exchange and, if the total size of the forces can be reduced, in budgetaryexpenditure also.     However we are committed to remaining in singapore and Malaysia as long as possible.     We cannot base decisions on expenditure there, and particularly works expenditure, on an assumption that the forces will have been withdrawn by a particulardate.     We can only assume that, until confrontation ends, the forces there cannot be substantially reduced, ,9.     There are also other possibilities of changes in commitments which might yield further savings in due course.     They include the ending of the residual commitment to the Ruler of Kuwait and some reduction in our forces in BAOR either as a result of a revisedNATO strategy or because the Federal German Government fails to offset the foreign exchange costs*-3-
10,   If we can agree that the P 1127 should he cancelled it shouldnot he difficult to close the remaining gap of  25 million.     Ifthe P 1127 continues some further major savings on commitments mayvrell he necessary.     In either case, however, it would he unwise to attempt to decide now which of the several ways in which the gapmight he closed should he adopted.Recommendations11,   I invite my colleagues -a,     to decide whether the P 1127 should he cancelled;h,     to agree that we should not attempt to decide for thethe present how the remaining gap between the costof the defence programme in 1969/70 and the targetshould he closed.D0H.Ministry- of Defence, SaW,l,11th February, 1966,-4-
THE.. adviced FORCE,3TOUGTUREAssumptions on CommitmentsThe revised, force structure has been costed onthe following assumptions about overseas commitmentsa.     Berlin   -   Our tripartite commitment inBerlin will continue0&quot;b-     Ojermajry   -   Our commitments to NATO inGermany will continue as at present planned.While we shall be able to rely on the use ofthe forces in Germany for reinforcement in real emergency, we should not rely on using,them for such purposes any more than at present.c. Cajcibb^jin   -   V/e shall withdraw our forces from the Caribbean, except for a company in&apos;British- Honduras and a frigate which will bein the Caribbean part of the time, to meetinternal security commitments in ourremaining dexoendenc ies.d. S^ojith^Ajblantic and S^oul^Afrijga -   We shall make arrangements with &quot;the&quot; South African authoritiesto retain the use of facilities under the simonstown Agreement without having to maintain a naval presence there, exce-pt an ice patrolvessel in the Falkland Islands and in the antarctic,e. Gibjialtjijg   -   We shall maintain a garrison,airfield and other facilities, but there may beminor savings on naval facilities.     the dockyard will continue to operate.f. MsdiJ^erran^ean   -   There will be no naval force(&quot;or maritime patrol aircraft) permanently inthe Mediterranean and our maritime commitment to NATO will be renegotiated.     We shall continue to retain a commitment to providenuclear support for CENTO.So     Mjilta   -   Malta will be reduced to a staging postwith an RAF reconnaissance squadron.h.     Li/bjya    -   V/e shall secure a point of entry only by stationing one infantry company, an armoured car squadron and a stockpile of one squadronTs-worth of tanks in the El Adem/Tobruk area.RAF El Adem will be retained as a staging postbut with minimum facilities only.ANNEX A
2j.     Qll! vjL   -   Akrotiri will &quot;be retained as a sovereign Base Area (SBA) from which we shall provide nuclear support for CENTO.      On theassumption that this commitment is tocontinue after the CANBEARAS phase out,  itwill he met &quot;by V-bombers stationed at Akrotiri.V/e shall have no obligations to Libya which require forces or facilities in the DhekeliaSBA.k*     Aden   -   After Independence in 1968, we shallhave no obligations to,  or defence facilitiesor forces in, Aden or the South ArabianFederation.1.     Persian Gulf   -   Our obligations to the otherPersian Gulf States will continue and our commitment to come    to the assistance of Kuwait will he renegotiated so that it is limited to the provision of air support,unless the Ruler gives us adequate time tomove in the land forces from the UnitedKingdom or Par East to Kuwait.     The force ,structure in this area should include asecond battalion, and additional capitalexpenditure should not exceed  1Om.m&quot;      Hong Kong   -   We shall continue to provide agarrison of 6f major units with a fewcoastal minesweepers, hut no aircraft.      Itis assumed that the Hong Kong Government will increase their present defence contribution from  1 .5m to  5.5nun.     Indo/Pacific Area -     We shall provide a visiblemilitary presence based on Australia, includingnaval and amphibious forces, with 7&quot;? Armymajor units (including RM Commandos) and appropriate RAP aircraft for strike, maritime and army support roles.,    Our forces will heunaccompanied.     The Gurkhas will he disbanded.Assumptions on Equipment2.     The following equipment assumptions have been takento form the basis of a revised force structure related to these commitmentsa. The new carrier CVAO 1 will not he built.The present carrier force will continue until1975.     55 PHANTOMS will he bought for theRoyal Navy, those remaining when the carrierforce is phased out (3h) being handed overto the RAF.     The carrier strike component willhe reduced so there will he only a total buy of96 BUCCANEER 2s, 52 of which will he availablefor the RAP in 1975.b. A total of 50 P 111A aircraft will he purchased..
3c. The P 1127 will continue with PGB.d. The Type 82 destroyer will he provided.e. The LANCE weapons system will &quot;be provided forBAQRcf. There will be naval reprovision, above thatin existing plans, for s-(i)      escort cruisers to succeed the TIGERclass;(ii)      the short-range anti-ship missile.Force StructureRoyal Navy3 c     The carrier force would remain in being -until 1975?reducing from four to three ships in 1971*     Theabandonment of carriers would make it necessary tocontinue with a programme of ships to follow theconverted TIGERS in the mid-1970s0     These ships would reprovide the ASW capability and the fleet commandfacilities which would otherwise be lost with thecarrierso     The strength of the destroyer and frigate fleetwould be reduced by nearly 20%.      In detail, the changesin fighting units are, for 1969/70Unit                            Current Plan		New Plan	ReductjCarriers	h	h	-Commando/Assault Ships	k	k	-Cruisers	3	3	-GM Destroyers (COUNTYS)	8	8	-Other Destroyer/Frigates	86	70	16Submarines	36	33	3.Mine-Count ermeasures	72	us	27Vessels				213	167	(a)    reducing to 3 in 1971	and nil in	1976,	Armyho      One of the assumptions upon which the force structureis based is that it will be possible to agree with theUnited States a sufficiently firm basis for joint actionin Libya for us to limit our commitment to theprovision of a secure point of entry.
k5.     The reduction in the total of the Army&apos;s fightingunits would he k%,  or i1$ including the Gurkhas.     At themoment there is the greatest difficulty in meeting the requirement for battalions to go on unaccompaniedemergency tours overseas.     This is having a hadeffect on re-engagement and is causing other difficulties.Under the new proposals, five battalions will have to be stationed permanently overseas on planned unaccompaniedtours apart from any additional battalions required foremergencies.      If the infantry is to maintain itself upto strength under these circumstances,  it is essentialthat a good sized pool of battalions is maintained in the uk to support unaccompanied battalions overseas, and theArmy in the UK has been tailored to meet this requirement.In detail the reductions in units would he of thefollowing order, subject to detailed study later:	Current Plan	New Plan	ReductionInfantry Battalions	61	60	1        (2%)Gurkha Units	9i(a)	Nil	9i (100$)RAC Regiments	23i	21 f	1f , (7fo)RA Regiments		31.f	f     (2%)RE Regiments	16	131	24r   (15%)Total	1h2	127	15     (11$)Reduction in other	Supporting Arms	and Services	would heapproximately 5%			Note     (a) Includes 8 Gurkha battalions, 1 GurkhaEngineer Regiment, 1 Parachute Company,Royal Air &apos; Force&quot;6.      The Royal Air Force front line would be reduced by1969/70 from the present planned force of 8U5 to 810.The main features of the new force structure would hea*     Trans port;:f o.rce,s.     There would be no reductionin -capability because the requirement to move the Strategic Reserve remains unaltered and indeed increased reliance is to he placed on theprinciple of overseas reinforcement.     In additionto the front line of U  C 130s to replace theHASTINGS and the BFVERLEY, nine C 130s havebeen included to offset shortcomings in the belfast;    the total C 130 buy would he 66.&quot;b-     Air.&quot;Defence.   The global fighter force would bereduced by &quot;2h aircraft to a front line of 96 by1975 and to a front line of 8h by 1976, as  vLIGHTNINGS are replaced gradually by PHANTOMSreleased by the build-up of the JAGUAR force.
5G*     Tactical Strike/Rec onna is sance .     The presentforce of 150&quot;&quot;CANBS?dlAS would start to be phasedout of service in 1968/69.     Their replacementwould be confined to 36 front &quot;lines1 mAs(from the buy of 50-)&apos;,  supplemented by 96 frontline V-bombers retained in a tactical roleuntil the introduction of the Anglo/French variablegeometry strike aircraft.d.     Ground Attack.     The planned buys of 148 RAFPHANTOMS and 110 P 1127 to give front lines of84 and 60 respectively would be unchanged, butthe JAGUAR would progressively replace thePHANTOM in this role from 1973 (see b. above);provision is made for a second stage developmentof the P 1127.e-      Maritime Tasks.      The SHACKLFTON Mk.2 force wouldbe replaced by 30 HS. 801 s (from a buy of 38);only 18 SHACKLETON Mk.3s would be retained in thefront line instead of the 24 envisaged until recently.     36 front line PHANTOMS (making useof those made available by the RN) will beprovided for maritime tasks after the withdrawal ;of the carriers.     36 front line ex-RN BUCCANEERSwill also be provided for maritime tasks in1975-77 until this role is taken over by theVG aircraft.To provide a tactical reserve of personnel for overseasreinforcement, 2,000 extra men have been added to UKestablishments.Manpower7. The Service strength (adult male) of the Forces would beas follows in 1969/70RNArmyTotalOtherTotal(UK)Current Plan95 , 400181,130121,670398,20024,5601+22,760Revised ForceStructure92,000176,000119,990387,9901 0,400Reduction3,4005,130 (a)1,680 (b)398,39010,2101U,1602^,370(a) All Gurkha&apos; units (now planned to run down by 1969/70from about 14,000 to 10,000) will have been disbanded..It has been assumed that the new Army volunteer reserve (establishment 50,800) will have taken theplace of the existing Army Emergency Reserve and territorial Army.(b) There will in fact be a reduction in RAF strengthoverseas of 6,535, but this is offset by an increasein the UK of 4,855.\ ./8 -      N
8.     Numbers of women and boys would be reduced as follows :-Royal Navy 380Army 1,567Royal Air Force -Total 1,9U7There would be reductions in civilian numbers at home and overseas as followsRoyal NavyArmyRoyal Air ForceTotal 395 30-:Works Fror^ramme9o     A comparison of the works programme on present plans and for the revised force structure offers savings of about 100m between 1969/70 and 1975/76,     A comparison for thefirst and last years is m (1965       Present Plans   Rgvisejl For;eg       Sayingsprices) Structure1969/70 208 19k Ik1975/76 153 138 151 0-   For the purposes of this study it has been assumed that capital facilities in Australia will not have to beprovided at UK expense.      It has also been assumed, forcosting purposes,  that service in Australia will beunaccompanied and that, in general, units will change overonce a year.     The cost of the accommodation, storage and operational facilities required in Australia cannot beaccurately estimated without detailed consultation with theAustralian authorities.     A rough estimate is that theprovision of permanent accommodation for 22,000 militaryand civilian personnel, together with repair and storage facilities, airfield improvements,  etc. would cost some 1.00m.     This would obviously be a long term programmespread over perhaps as much as ten years, depending on the capacity of the building industry in the chosen sites.     Forthe first few years after the establishment of a base inAustralia the majority of the facilities would have to bein temporary construction./ivhirristrv of Aviation
ministry of Aviation. R &amp; D Programme11.      It has heen assumed that there will he no developmentof an AM7 aircraft.      In addition there will he nofurther development of the BUCCANEER 2 although provision is made for fitting AJ 168 to the BUCCANEER 2 and P 111A.There is also provision for the development of a shortrange surface-to-surface ship-horne weapon.     It has been assumed that the reductions in the research fieldrecommended in the Plowden Re-port will amount to  6mper annum.     Allowing for variations and adjustments inthe rest of the MRCA programme since the 1965 Long TermCosting it is estimated that the effect of the revised programme would he to reduce most expenditure in 1969/70to  199m.other^Fxjoeiidatur^e12.      Other expenditure within the Defence Budget is nowforecast at  60m (1965 prices) in 1969/70 and from about ,S50ra to  3 0m a year in the subsequent period.Since the str-ategic nuclear force plans and plans for nuclear propulsion remain unchanged and. capital chargesincurred in the past by the Atomic Energy Authority have  Ito he repaid, there is little scope for manoeuvre in the forecasts for fissile material costs which range from 23m in 1969/70 to a credit of  hm in 1975/76.     AEAresearch expenditure (current forecast  6.5m in 1969/70)will depend on strategic nuclear policy for the 1970sand later;    a reduction to  5m a year has heen assumed.Finally,  there is the Ministry of Defence Central Vote,a large part cf which covers international defenceorganisations and NATO infrastructure.     At present noreductions in our NATO commitment can he foreseen and,since last summer no provision was made for satellite communications which now appear to he a definiterequirement,  the Ministry of Defence Central forecasthas been increased, by . 3m a 3^ear to allow for them.Defence Buclget13.     The cost		, at 1965	costings	prices	( m),	of the	revised	force	structure	is estimated to		he as	follows:	-1969/70		1970/1	1921/2	1972/3	1973/4	19X^/5	1975^Navy	538	546	589	577	558	558	528Army	551	552	555	555	561	567	572RAP	566	606	586	586	571	591	642MPBW	194	193	185	166	1h9	142	138MOA	199	183	190	190	190	190	190AExi.	5	5	5	5	5	5	5Special	23	16	1k	-4	-4	-4	-4Materials							MOD	32	31	30	30	30	30	30Central							Total	2i 08	2132	2154	2105	2060	2079	2101/It
8It is usual to add to these figures a contingency allowance for cost growth and to cover unforeseen objects ofexpenditure in the later years.     The assessment of asensible contingency allowance is by no. means an exactscience.     The most reasonable assumption to take at thisstage would appear to he en addition of  60m in 1969/70rising hy  25m a year to  210m in 1975/76.      On this basis the forecast, at 1965 costings prices ( m), would he bestexpressed as1969/70   1970/1   1971/2   1972/5   1973/4   19Jit/5j   1975/6+60 -f85       +110        +135       +160     +185       +210Total    2168 2217       2264 22h0       2220     2264       23111965 costings price levels were, hov/ever, almost exactly 5%( 104m on  2000m) higher than Defence Review price levels(1964 prices).     At Defence Review prices ( m), the overallDefence Budget estimate is therefore:-1962/20   1225a   197V2   1972/2   197JA   1924/5.   1975/62060 2106       2151        2128       2109       2151     2196Foreign Exchange14.     The latest forecast of foreign exchange costs in1969/70 which -would result from the stationing of forces overseas under present plans is as follows (, m 1965costings prices) :-B/lediterranean   Aden/     kinds/7 Hong     Other   total^ -. . ^       p.Gulf   Pacific        Konre94	36	35	71	10	14	260Deployment in accordance with the revised assumptions would reduce foreign exchange in 1969/70 hy about  65m, giving a total of ah out  195m- as follows  %-						Germany Mediterranean		Persian	Indo/	Hong	Other	Tota:		Gulf	pa cijCic	Kong		RN	5	1	Tex.H.K 17	3	1	27Army     62	3	3	&quot;   11	7	3	89RAF       11	8	3	11	-	2	35Other   21 (v/orks Central most)	3	8 s	3	2	7	44Total   94	19	15	42	12	13	195k   including Aldahra
15.      Other defence foreign exchange expenditure, includingthe purchase of foreign military equipment, would on currentplans he about  95m net in 1969/70, and about  80m netunder the revised plans.     Thus the total estimated foreign exchange costs in 1969/70 are  355m (current plans) and about  275m (revised plans).Conclusion16.     a.     Without the addition of a contingency allowance,the cost of the revised force structure in1969/70 is about  2000m but with the addition ofan . allowance of  6om, the cost is  60m abovethe ceilinrb, Local stationing costs (foreign currenay) wouldbe reduced by  o5m ih 1969/70,    The correspondingreductions for other foreign exchange costs(largely for the purchase of foreign equipment)would, be  1 5m.c. It would not be possible to contain expenditure at the 1969/70 level in subsequent years withoutfurther reductions in commitments or capabilitiesbut expenditure could be contained within separately of increase lower than the forecast rise in: GNP.


</content>
</cab>
