<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/124/0 images: 377-381</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(66) 4022nd February, 1966CABINETDECEViAIISATIQNMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the climate of opinion is moving on this subject and expecta-tions of a Government decision have been stimulated by theintroduction of decimalisation into Australia.    The Confederation ofBritish Industries (CBI) are about to write to me urging an early decision and the Association of British Chambers of Commerce havealready done so.2.      The Halsbury Committee which reported in July, 1963,showed that the case for decimalisation is strong and it has been strengthened even more by our decision to go metric.    The mainbenefits will accrue in the form of a saving of time in banksP shops,offices and schools.    The saving will show up either in a reductionin the labour force or in greater ability by the same labour force totake on other work.    It will simplify the teaching of arithmetic.The standardisation of text books and machines will also improve our export prospects.3,      The cost is likely to be large, probably of the order of 1; 120 million of which possibly rather more than half (allowing for tax relief) would fall on the Exchequer, even if we decide that compensa-tion as a general principle is unacceptable.    Because many of thebenefits are intangible it is not possible to put a precise figure on theactual savings, but there would be a good return in national cost/benefit terms.4.     The additional public sector expenditure involved, for whichwe should have to make provision at the next review in June, will beabout  40 million.    The cost would be spread over a number of years but would reach its peak in the year of the change-over,5,     There are three main issues to deal with?   choice of unit,compensation and date of introduction.Choice of Unit6.     After examining a very large number of possible systems theHalsbury Committee finally decided that the choice lay between a -cent-!- cent and a 10s. decimal system, and in the intervening period no one has made out a strong case for any other system.    Intheir Report, and especially in the minority Memorandum of Dissent,the arguments developed in South African, Australian and other6 6COPY NO    L *--1-SECRET
enquiries in favour of the 10s. system are given full weight.     Thechief advantages of the 10s.  system are listed as being its simplicity,its flexibility and convenience for money transactions of most values;its easy associability with our present system;  the somewhat lowercost of introducing it, the fact that it would be less likely to causeprice increases;   and the fact that without the ^ cent it would be a puredecimal system.7.     The majority by four votes to tv/o recommended the adoptionof the   -cent-!- cent system.    They agreed that people would find it easier to adapt themselves initially to a 10s. -cent than to a  -cent-\ cent system for small transactions but thought this was only amatter of degree.     On the longer term considerations the majoritythought that the \ cent, which spoils the symmetry of the system would fall into disuse, perhaps in one generation.     They concluded that in view of the gradual decline in the value of money over thecenturies it would be &quot;against the economic logic of history&quot; to move to a new major unit of only half the value of the present pound.Looking only at domestic considerations the majority conclusion was that the 10s. system presented lesser difficulties of adaptationin the change-over period and avoided the inconvenience of a \ cent,but that the other advantages claimed for each system were relativelyunimportant.8.     This seems a fair assessment, except that the Committee mayhave under-estimated the transitional convenience for largei&quot; trans-actions of retaining the  , not only because of the records and contracts that would have to be changed if it were dropped, but also because it is the familiar measure of value and forms the background to everyone1 s thinking about prices and incomes.    In the narrativememorandum which Mr. Plolt, the Australian Prime Minister, sentme last November, in his capacity as Treasurer, he says of the newdollar system (as against the  ):-&quot;It is going to be somewhat of a nightmare for the nextfew years getting used to new figures for items of budgetreceipts and expenditure, national income and balance ofpayments statistics, and banking and financial statisticsgenerally, 119.     A factor which did not affect Australian thinking but is boundto enter into our own, even if its weight is debatable, is what theHalsbury Committee called the &quot;international case for the   &quot;,    the salient propositions put forward are that the   is an international unitrecognised throughout the world, widely used as a reserve currency and for commercial transactions between third countries as well as for the United Kingdom^ own trade.    Any change in the name orvalue (e. g. by adopting the 10s. system) of the United Kingdom*s maincurrency unit involves the risk that some of those who at present holdor use sterling may cease to do so.    It is claimed that this could leadto a loss of reserves and even a crisis of confidence, if a differentunit was substituted for the   during a period when sterling was weak.It could also affect the City&apos;s livelihood and therefore the invisiblereceipts in our balance of payments.    Habit plays a large part in determining which currency is used and which financial centres get
certain business.    A change from the  1 unit however technical,could cause people to question those habits.     The majority of theHalsbury Committee were cautious about giving as much weight to theinternational case for the   as some of its advocates claimed for it.Nevertheless they concluded that:-&quot;a change-over in our main currency unit must have someeffect, however slight, both on the standing of sterling and on the business of the City, and that this effect could only be adverse&quot;.10.     Opinion in this country seems fairly evenly divided on theissue of choice of system.    Broadly speaking, the choice of the   isupheld by the Bank of England, Building Societies and other financial institutions and the Co-operative Union, while the 10s. is supportedby the retail tra.de, by transport interests and by the TUC.    A numberof organisations are neutral between the two.    The CBI have been carrying out an enquiry and I understand that they are unlikely to come out with a firm recommendation in favour of either unit.     press comment was in favour of the 10s. at the time of the Halobury lleporfspublication.11.     The balance of advantage between the two systems may besummarised;-^ ^ Ps* maJor unit would provide a decimal systemunblemished by a \ cent and easier associability insubsidiary coinage during the transition;A   -cent-\ cent system would mean that we retainedthe   both as a familiar measure of value at home andas a valuable national asset in our international dealings.It would be a more lasting system, with greater inbuiltresistance to the gradual decline in importance from whichsmaller currency units suffer as inflation reducespurchasing power and standards of living rise.This is a difficult choice because moot arguments tend to berationalisations of prejudices.    I started off as a neutral but havingread the Halsbury Report very carefully and heard the arguments Ihave come down in favour of the  1 as the unit.     There is anindefinable prestige about having a &quot;heavy&quot; currency, the system weare altering will need to last for several centuries, and I believethere is less in the argument about difficulties on change-over than some of the retail traders seemed to think.Compensation12.     I do not think there is a good case for wholesale compensation of machine owners for costs of conversion and replacement in spiteof the Australian precedent.    Exceptional treatment might benecessary in some cases, such as the small retailer who owns a cash register or weight/value scales.    It is fair to say that the organisations which would have to incur substantial costs ondecimalisation are those that stand to benefit most both from the case of working after the change-over and from the greater cheapness
and adaptability of decimal machines.    Moreover, under thepresent system of tax allowances it seems likely that as much ashalf of the machine conversion costs falling in the private sectormight be recouped in tax relief.    We might announce that ourpreliminary view was that compensation as a general principle wasnot acceptable but that we would consider giving some assistance incertain cases.Date of introduction13.     As regards the date of introduction, Halsbury recommendedand everyone agrees that February is the best time of year,Australian experience may suggest the possibility of making economiein costs of conversion by having a longer preparatory period than thethree years recommended by Halsbury,    We are getting from the machine manufacturers an up to date view of the optimumpreparatory period.     The Mint needs a substantial period to prepare the coinage.     I do not think that a date earlier than February, 1971,v/ill be feasible.     I recommend that we should announce this date.Or gani satisfaction on14.     When the decision to decimalise is announced we should saythat we shall set up a Decimal Currency Board who will beresponsible for working out the detailed arrangements for thechange-over.&apos; &apos;&quot;Conclusion15.     I accordingly invite my colleagues to agree.(a) that the currency should be decimalised;(b) that the date of introduction should be February, 19711(c) that the unit should be the  1;(d) that compensation as a general principle is unacceptablebut that we should consider giving some assistance inparticular cases;(e) that a Decimal Currency Board will be set up to makethe necessary arrangements for the change-over.L. J, C,Treasury Chambers, S. W, 1,21st February, 1966


</content>
</cab>
