<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/124/0 images: 403-408</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J3513 DOCUMENT IS TKE PROPERTY CF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(66) 44g6COPY NO.25th February, 1966CABINETMINISTRY OF SOCIAL SECURITY: DRAFT WHITE paper note by the Minister of Pensions and National insurance attach for the Cabinet1 s consideration a draft White Paper onthe Ministry cf Social Security.     The text incorporates amendmentsmade in the light of discussion at the Ministerial Committee on social services.Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance, W.C.2.25th February, 1966
PLAN FOR THE MINISTRY OF SOCIAL SECURITYDRAFT Y/HITE PAPERIntroduction.........1.     In recent years social workers and social science researchworkers have maintained that a large number of old people who could have national assistance do not apply for it.   Last year the Government carried out its own survey of the circumstancesof retirement pensioners.   About 9,000 people were interviewed.There is still some work to be done on the detailed analysis ofthe results; but the broad picture is now clear.   One of themain objects of the enquiry was to find out the numbers of pensioners who could receive national assistance, if they wished,but were not doing so.   As regards the total number of such people,the findings are broadly consistent with those of earlier studiesin this field.   The survey showed that there Mr. be about 700,000retirement pensioners who might receive some national assistance if they asked for it.   However, it seemed that for more than half of them the gap between their resources and their needs,measured by the national assistance standards is being met either by income which the Board would disregard, or by help fromrelatives or friends, particularly those&apos; living in the same house-hold.   For many of the others the gap appeared to be partly, butnot wholly, met in this way.   Nevertheless, there may be approaching250,000 who really need help but have not asked for it.2.     The survey also tried to find out why people did not applywhen they could do so.   Of those in the sample about a thirdsaid they were managing all right.   About one in five said thattheir pride would not let them apply, or that they dislikedcharity, or were unwilling to lose their independence, or gavesimilar reasons.   Three out of ten gave answers showing thatlack of knowledge or misconceptions had kept them from applying;the proportion of these was higher among the younger pensionersthan among the older.3-     It seems clear therefore that something more than increasedpublicity and improved information services are needed to solve the problem of getting help to all the elderly people who need it.The problem is an urgent one and the Government believes that itshould have the next priority in the development of social security.   The changes which the Government has accordingly decided to make, subject where necessary to the approval ofParliament, are described in the succeeding paragraphs.i -1.CONFIDiWTBALCj f
The Ministry of Social Security4.     A Ministry of Social Security will be established this year,bringing together the existing Departments of the Ministry ofPensions and National Insurance and the National Assistance Board.This reorganisation will have three main aims in view.   Firstly,the creation of the new Ministry will put an end to the distinctionbetween separate offices for the administration of insurance benefits on the one hand and means-tested benefit on the other.Secondly, the local administration of the two present Departments,with their skilled and experienced staff, will be developed toprovide a more comprehensive and convenient service for the public,and a more effective instrument to ensure that people who havenot so far claimed the help to which they are entitled are encouraged to do so.   Thirdly, the co-ordination of policy for all social security benefits will be made easier by the substitution of oneMinistry for two Departments.New non-contributory benefits5&apos;     With the establishment of the new Ministry will go a new structure of non-contributory benefits which will replace national assistance.This will include a form of guaranteed income to be known as a &quot;pension&quot;for the old.   The benefit for the others will be known as an &quot;allowance&quot;.Assessment   of the pension or allowance will be based on different levels of income, for householders and.non-householders and for single people, married couples and families.   Rent will be allowed for in addition.   Provision will be made for additional payments tomeet special individual needs1   but the aim will be to make this partof the scheme more readily understandable than the discretionaryadditions now made, mainly for the elderly, under present arrangements.6.     &quot;Disregards!! will be completely revised.   National insurance pensions and benefits, family allowances and maintenance payments will be taken fully into accountp   but there will be a small&quot;disregard&quot; of other forms of income.   The amount of savings ofany kind to be totally ignored will be substantially increased andmodest savings will all be ignored, no matter how they are invested.Further, the fixed upper limit, at present  600, on the amount of savings above which no benefit is payable will be abolished. Instead,capital which exceeds the amount which can be totally ignored willbe taken into account as income under a graduated tariff and this&quot;tariff&quot; income will be aggregated with any other income in applying the income disregard.   The special treatment at present accorded to&quot;war savings&quot; will no longer be justified.   Accordingly, the amountof capital, above the amount to be ignored, which will make a personineligible for an award will vary with the extent of his other resources, as well, of course, as his needs.
Procedure for claiming and review of awards7.     It will still be necessary for claimants to make a statementof circumstances so that benefit can be assessed.   But theprocedure will become much more flexible for people over retirementage.   They v/ill have a choice of sending to the Ministry&apos;s local office a written declaration of their circumstances or of beingvisited at home.   If they choose the first, the assessment basedon the written declaration will need to be confirmed by an inter-view, but if desired this could take place at the local office.8.     The pension for the old will normally be reviewed andrenewed only once a year.9*     The combined effect of these changes will be to reduce the frequency of home visiting of the long-term cases.   There will befewer visits; but visiting officers will have more time,when theydo make a visit, to ensure that any welfare needs are identifiedand brought to the notice of the appropriate service.Combined Order Books10.   The Government intends that when an elderly person receiving the new pension also has a national insurance pension the twoshall be paid together on a single order book.   Those who are notreceiving retirement pension will receive payment on an orderbook of similar appearance to the retirement pension order book.The process of replacing the separate books by the combined bookmust necessarily take some time but the Government hopes to start a pilot programme in a selected Region soon after the new scheme begins.Making sure that pensioners&apos; needs are met11.   To overcome lack of knowledge or diffidence the new ministry will send to everyone claiming a national insurance retirement pension details of the new pension with a claim form. arrangements will be introduced as soon as possible to make personal contactv/ith every national insurance pensioner who, on retirement, does notclaim the new pension unless he indicates that he does not want one.Similar arrangements will be made to get in touch with marriedwomen not already receiving a non-contributory benefit if they arewidov/ed.   As this scheme for personal contact develops furtherchecks will be introduced by arranging to contact pensioners after they have been retired for some years if they have not alreadyclaimed the new pension.12.   Cash grants are not the only kind of help that old peoplefail to seek.   A wide range of services to meet health and welfareneeds is provided by local authorities but recent investigations bysocial scientists and the experience of both local officers of theBoard and of local authorities have shown that these are too oftennot known by old people or the effort to make the necessary contactis beyond them.   The Government intend to ensure that all such people are ma.de fully aware both of the cash grants and of theother services available.   The contacts made under the arrangements described in this paper v/ill make a valuable contribution to thisobject.3.
Administration of non-contributory benefits13,   The Government believes that in order to preserve flexibilityand responsiveness to human needs the new non-contributory benefits should, like national assistance today, be administered by anindependent corporate body.     Within the Ministry of Social Securitytherefore there will be a Commission of persons chosen for their interest in, and knowledge of, social problems, in whom will be vested the responsibility for running the new scheme, includingdecisions on individual awards, under broad regulations made bythe Minister:   arrangements for appeals to local Tribunals willbe retained.     Other responsibilities at present laid upon theNational Assistance Board, for example assessments for legal aid, will be transferred to the new body.Time-table, 14.   The Government hopes to introduce early legislation on theseproposals. .   .Conclusion1p.   When the changes are complete the Government believes thatthey will be seen to preserve what is good in the present schemeof national assistance while getting rid of those features whichat present create dislike or misconception.     These featuresare in no way the fault ofthe national Assistance Board or its officers.     Everybody recognises the humanity, efficiency anddevotion with which the present scheme is administered and theGovernment is confident that these qualities will be carried over into the new organisation.     But the new Commission and thestaff doing its work will be enabled to do, an even better jobfor those of our people in need.     There will no longer be thepresent sharp distinction between national insurance benefitsrelated to contributions and help which our people as a wholewishes its less fortunate members to have.     The elderly in needwill be supported by a system of payments which gives dignitybecause it will incorporate more stability and involve less frequent enquiries.4-


</content>
</cab>
