<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/103/0 images: 120-120</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Military Secret.1346From Viceroy, Foreign Department, to Secretary of State for India,31st March 1920.(Received 1st April.)559 S. Please refer to Cox&apos;s two telegrams No. 150 to Foreign Office, and No. 15 to India, both of 26th March. Situation in Eastern Persia. On 1.6th March Malleson telegraphed that there was scare at Daraguz over expected invasion by Bolsheviks, but that the object of the Bolsheviks was probably to make population uneasy, and he thought, provided morale of local Persian authorities remained good, situation should he successfully dealt with. Consul-General agreed, and informed us that the Governor-General had sent reassuring telegram to the Persian frontier officials. On 21st March Malleson in telegram 03507 sent version of the Governor-GeneraPs so-called reassuring telegram which amounted to instructions to local officials not to resist the Bolsheviks&apos; incursions if they took place, but to make formal protests and declare neutrality of Persia. Malleson reported that this message was interpreted at Daraguz as almost an invitation to the Bolsheviks to enter Persia, and in any case an assurance of no resistance. On 22nd March consul-General in telegram No. 70 telegraphed that as our intention is to retire from Khorasan, he felt sure he was not expected to advise the Governor-General to resist official Bolshevik invasion with force, and that the instructions sent to Daraguz had been to abstain from provocative action, and meet armed invasion if that should occur with protest. On 23rd March, consul-General telegraphed translation of the foregoing instructions sent to Daraguz, which were to the effect that small invading detachments should he turned, but large ones met with protest only, and by announcement of Persian neutrality, Consul-General was of course mistaken in assumption that His Majesty&apos;s Government had definitely decided on withdrawal of our forces, and he is being informed accordingly. Moreover, instructions issued by the Governor-General that large Bolshevik forces should be met by protest only seem to go beyond the views of the Persian Government expressed in Cox&apos;s telegram No. 15 of 26th March, that shall the Bolsheviks intrude or attack, the Persians will defend themselves.Our military officers in Khorasan consider that the instructions make the position of our troops in advanced posts near the frontier very difficult, we agree in this vieAV as it gives the Bolsheviks opportunity to maintain that the Persians are in their favour, and the British the only hostile element, and furnishes them with excuse for attacking our troops. Considering, however, doubt as to the Bolsheviks&apos; intentions, we incline to think that until Bis Majesty&apos;s Government make definite announcement of military policy in respect of East Persia, our best course is to instruct Malleson to hold on and bluff so long as this is compatible with the safety of the troops. Military authorities agree.   Please confirm by clear line.

</content>
</cab>
