<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/103/0 images: 159-162</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^J Ji2JLj^ertX^ His Britannic Frned to the Foreinn Qffi^ if notGERMANY.Confidential, (189705..)(April 1st.) Section 1.Earl Curzon to the Earl of Derby (Paris)Foreign Office, April 1st,.192Q.(No. 1121),My lord the French Ambassador called upon me by appointment at noon today in order to discuss the Syrian question,I had just received a series of telegrams - reporting the action of the French Government, both in Paris and Berlin, in relation to the German request to be allowed to send troops into    *the &quot;Ruhr Valley - which revealed a state of affairs so surprising-and so disquieting that I seized the opportunity to speak to.M. Cambon at once upon the subject.   Only yesterday, at the meeting of the Allied Conference, when I had mentioned the persistent rumours in the newspapers that M, Millerand had been dealing separately with the German representative in Paris, and had made proposals or used threats about the French occupation of Frankfort and DarmstadtM. Cambon had himself declined to attach the I slightest importance to these rumours, which he had told me were I only newspaper gossip, and had said that it,was incredible that M, Millerand should have used such language or have contemplated such action without prior:consultation with the Allies.  He had further
further told me that, in the interview in Paris with Herr von Meyer, it was the latter who had made the suggestion that the French should occupy the above-mentioned German towns, and that M, Millerand had merely promised to give the proposal his favourable consideration.  Now, I said, it seemed that, so far from this being a correct description of what had happened, M. Millerand had handed to Herr von Meyer a note in which the French occupation of Frankfort and Darmstadt appeared, nob as a German, but as a French proposal, and in which certain conditions were attached by the French Government to the permission to German troops to occupy the disturbed area.   This official communication had actually been published in the &quot;Times J5   I had also heard from Berlin that either this communication or some other on the same subject - J was not certain which - had been sent by the French Foreign Office tc the German Govern-ment;  had been read to the German National Assembly;   and had been made the basis of debate there.At
At this stage, I said, there seemed to be some doubt or dispute as to the actual terms of the French communication, for whereas the German Government insisted that the only condition which the French Government had attached was a limit of time, the French Government, on the other hand, declared that they had imposed as a condition the approval of the Control Commissjb a These points it was impossible for me, on the information I possessed, to resolve0  But whatever the contents of the communica-tion might be, one thing appeared to be quite certain, end that was that what M*Cambon had told us yesterday was incredible  had actually occurredc M. Millerand had acted, and was acting, independently of the- Allies, and, indeed, without even informing them of his action.    He was conductirgra sepal&quot;ate bargain with the German Government as to the conditions on which German troops might be permitted to enter the neutral 2one0    He was making conditions as to the occupation of German towns, not by Allied troops, but by French troops0This, I went on to say,, was an impossible state of affairs^ Therefore only two ways of dealing with the situation;-   either the Allies should act as they had hitherto acted, in combination; or they might act separatelyo    The former was the only sound and practical policy *    We are anxious to adhere to it, end prepared to do so*    But if &apos;M-Millerand was unable to attend the meetings of the Conference, here, preferred to remain in Paris and regarded himself in his double capacity of French Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs, as if he were the soleSupreme
Supreme Council now in existence, and if he took advantage of that position to speak and act independently in the way he had apparently done, then we might have to abandon the policy of co-operation, and to consider very seriously whether we should not withdraw altogether from the occupied area, and decline to share the responsibility for. act ion concerning which we were not even consulted.The French Ambassador was ai a loss either to understand or to explain the reported action of his chief, about which he had only the most meagre information;  but he realised very clearly the seriousness of the situation which it had created, and he promised to communiaate at onco my observations to his Government, Y/hile I informed him that I would repeat them at once to your Excellency,I am, etc.,CURZON OF KEDLESTON,

</content>
</cab>
