<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/103/0 images: 289-290</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMT IS TH^ PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MA JEST Vg- GOVERBTOT;)Secret, Copy No._;   wCABINET.cy P, 1Q5S.TREATY OP PEACE WITH TURKIC.ADMINISTRATION OE THE WATERWAYS OP THE STRAITS,Copy of letter from British secretary^peaoe Conference, tothe chairman, praiTin^ CommiTEee.(Circulated for information).due ed -2 white hall Gardens, S.W.I. April 10th 1920*Sir,I am directed by Mr. Ll*yd George to enclose, for the information of the Drafting Committee, a oopy of a letter from tho Secretary to the British War Office to the British Secretary, supreme Council, dated April 1st 1920 (A.J. 146), in respect cf the proposed administration of the waterways of the Straits and the Sea of Marmora. The said letter was considered at a meeting of the C*nference of Foreign Ministers and Ambassadors held this morning at the Eereign Office, London, and it wa;s agreed that the point raised by the British War Office appeared to be unobjectionable.    It was decided that the said letter should be referred to the Drafting Committee.     I attach an extract from lot repro-     the Minutes of the Conference (I.CP. 9$, Minute 5)I am directed to request that the Drafting Committee will kindly take note of the above decision in drafting an appropriate Section of the Treaty of Peace with Turkey.I amSir,Your; obedient Servant, (Signed)   l. STORR. for British Secretary.The Chairman,The Drafting Crmmittee, PARIS.
TREAT? OF PEACE WITH TURKEY.   -ADHINISTRATION Cg THE WATERWAYS OF -THESTRAITS.(Copy of letter from the Secretary! British.War Office, to the British Secretaryfc Supremo Council..).War Office,London, S.,7.0152/5462. (M.I.2.) 1st April, 1920.Sir,V/ith reference to the Draft Articles of&quot; the Treaty of Peace with Turkey dealing with the Administration of the Waters of the Straits, (enclosure to CP.926 forwarded on 25th March, 1920), I am commanded by the Army Council .tt point out that in order to cover the establishment of the proposed local police under the High Commission of the Straits it will be necessary to insert wording in Article 20, Chapter V. of the1 Military Clauses to cover this increase, in personnel.The amendment suggested is the insertion at the commencement of that Article of the werds - &quot;Apart from the establishment of Police required fir service under the High Commission of the Straits.,,&quot;.Copies of this.letter have been forwarded to the Foreign Office and to Major-General. Saokville-Fest(in Paris*I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant, (Sgd) B.B.Cubitt.The British Secretary, Supreme Council,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.SECRET.A.Jel46a

</content>
</cab>
