<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/103/0 images: 291-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S: G0VBRBM3NT)SECRET.G.P.-1053.Copy NoCABINETTREATY OP PEACE WITH TURKEY.MILITARY GLAUSES 92Li^^i^I-lt^-..?!/^^sil.3o3Jeta^y, Peace Conference&quot; to the .-^s&apos;Ir&amp;j[]^^graftlia^JC/oaiml-jFUeaV(Circulated for information with, reference toC.P-,-945)..2 Whitehall Gardens, LONDON, S.W.I. 9th april&quot;h, 1920.Sir,For&apos; py of ause945.I am directed by Mr. Lloyd George to enclose for the information of the Drafting Committee, an extract from the British secretary Notes of a Conference of Foreign Ministers and Ambassadors held at the British Foreign Office on Wednesday, April 7th, 1920, approving some small altera-tions in Articles 17 and 27, of the Military Clauses/ of the Treaty of Peace with Turkey (l.C.P,92, Minute 13).I am to request that the Drafting Committee will take the necessary action to give effect to this decision.I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, . . (Signed).    lvhP.AvHii.NOY.British Secretary.The Chairman,DRAFTING COMMITTEE.1 em
EXTRACT FROM T.,r. ,P,r9g,  &apos;TREATY OF        (13)   The Conference had under canaidaraUon a letter PEACE mmTURKEY *      from-the Secretary to the War Office to the british military Secretary to the Supreme Council * tho contents -^rTi^ichr -ware-Clauses.as followsAr tides17 &amp; 27. &quot;tfar OfficeLondon, S.W.1.April 4, 1920.Sir,I am commanded by the Army Council to inform you, with reference to the draft military terms of the Turkish teaoe Treaty, that the foreign Office have pointed out the desirability of including soms expression in Article 17 to make it quite clear that the principle of enlistment laid down in Article 15 is also applicable to the appointment of Officers1.Also, with regard to Article 27, that it should be made quite clear that it is the Turks who will be responsible for the destruction of the fortifications in the zone Trebizond-Erzlnjan.I am to eay that the Army Council endorse both the above suggestions, which they venture to propose might he dealt with direct by the Drafting Committee.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Signed)     H*J. GREEDY.&quot; ^After a short discussion the Conference agreedTo accept both the above suggestions, and the Secretary was instructed to inform the  rafting Committee accordingly.Z Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. April 7, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
