<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/103/0 images: 471-474</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^ 358jj/i y /vf THLJ DQQIL.131IT IS        PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC HAJ;:1STY&apos;3 (X)VERIEE1NT,)S E 0 R 5 3f, Copy No.    %j .0 A B I H E T.OtP.-1095.THS   &apos;OTB   DUTIES.H2toby tho Chancellor of the Exchequer covering No to l^om the Board of Customs and Excise.The Cabinet will, I think, wish to see this note from the Board of Customs on the reasons for treating Sparkling,. Eines differently from other T&apos;:&apos;inee imported in bottle, and from Port.(Intd.) A..C.Treasury, S.&apos;E.17th Aprils 1920.
MOTE ITOi THE BOARD 302 CUSTOMS Ml gXCISS.1.   Tho question has been raised why sparkling wines should be subjected to an additional ad valorum duty and other wines of a more or less expensive kind.should be left alone. The answer. in a sentence is that, sparkling, wines represent an altogether different degree of luxury from any other class of wines. &apos;&apos;; ;&quot;&apos;:  &quot;XV- -    :&quot; -.. , ... ...2.   It is understood that, apart from the question of Revenue, the underlying principle of :the proposed ad valorum duties on sparkling wines and imported cigars in the taxation of imports which spring to the eye as preeminently suitable for a special tax.     It Is indeed net eworthy. that already surtaxes have been imposed on both these articles, although those duties have failed hitherto to discriminate in the manner that is now considered desirable according to the degree of luxury :   doubling the surtaxes; which is part of the present proposals concerning wine, will also fail to make this discrimination.3.   It will be remembered that in the previous note on the wine duties, dated 5th April last,, a. suggestion was made for extending the ad valorum duty not only to sparkling wines but also to still wines in bottle j*ich form the other class coming within the scope of the existing surtaxes online. Leaving sparkling wines out of account, still wines in bottle are amongst the most expensive;wines imported, and in making a comparison between sparkling and,, still wines for the purpose of investigating the propriety of the present proposals, a oase: is being taken favourable to those who hold the view that other wines should bo specially taxed as well as sparkling wines.      &apos;*
4.   The average price of sparkling&apos;TT1 no in 1919 was 52b. 5d. per gallon., in the three months January to ^ai^h-19-20.it had risen to 55s.   The average import price of still wine in bottle in 1919 was 83s. 8. per gallon, in the three months January to March 1920, it had fallen to 21s.   So far, therefore, as the luxury element in sn article is reflected in its import price, sparkling Wine stands in an entirely different category from still wine.5.   This aspect of the matter is brought out still more clearly when retail oriccs are considered.   Champagne, which represented 75 per cent,, of the sparkling wine imported into this country in 1919, is being retailed to-day at prices of about 180s. and upwards per dozen, whilst in hotels and restaurants 25s. a bottle and upwards is being charged.   On the other hand, claret imported in bottle is only fetching upwards of 70s. per dozen.   The difference between the retail price-sis, therefore, oven more marked than in the case of the import price.6.     It may bo well, in this connection, to compare sparkling wines not only with still wines imported in bottle^ but also with heavy winos such as ?ort and Sherry, most of which is imported in cask.   The total amount of these wines retailed for consumption in 1919 was 8,500,000 gallons of which 7,000,000 gallons osm from Portugal.   Here, again, it is easy to prove that Port and similar winos are not in tho same class as spa re ling wines as regards the prices charged.     The import value of Port at tho present time -is about 15/- a gallon   as compared with an import value of 55/- a gallon in the case of 8/ark: ling wines.     The retail price of Port of fair quality ranges from about 66/-to 90/- por dozen, old bottled Port being sold et a somewhat higher,flguvb.     Those prices cannot, of course, be compared
with the 180/- \no no arrh: for ohattp^no, - iv&quot;  u). \ higher prices that are charged in hotels, and rostaurants as sot out above.7.   To charge tho proposed ad valor urn duty on still wines in bottle would bo a small thing in itself, and would, merely be adding, in fact, one more burden to the wine trade of France.   The imposition of a similar fluty on heavy wines would SB the above figures show hit&apos; Portugal far more than any other country, and judging from the prices, the same case cannot be made out for a luxury surtax.8.   looking at the matter from rather a different point of view, there would seem to be no doubt on the facts given above that the amount of profit derived from the trade in sparkling wines is at a higher rate than in the case of trade in heavy or still wines.     This again would seem to be a good reason for differentiating between sparkling and other kinds of wines for purposes of taxation, as it appears probable that tho trade could well afford to pay part of the tax out of its own pocket.16th April, 1980.

</content>
</cab>
