<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/103/0 images: 475-487</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNiiEiiT.L.G.27.Census Bill.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.In presenting the annexed draft Bill for examination by the Home Affairs Committee, it may be convenient for me to indicate certain features which may appear to call for explanation or comment.General Form of the Bill.     A Census Bill must makeprevision for two different sets of requirements.     It must confer the powers under which a legal obligation is placed upon individual members of the population to give truthful replies to certain enquiries.     Secondly, it must enable the necessary administrative machinery to be set up for carrying out the executive process of enumeration.     In a perpetual Census Bill these provisions must be reduced to their most elementary and general form, uncomplicated by the specific requirements of a particular Census.the obligation upon the individual members of the population to reply to the authorised enquiries;   and Clauses 2 and 3 con-fer the necessary powers to establish and operate the machinery of enumeration.of objections raised by the Chancellor of the Exchequer. Quinquennial powers have however been included in the draft Bill for consideration by the Home Affairs Committee on the understanding, which I have accepted after consultation with the Chancellor, that provision charging the expense of a Census upon the Exchequer should only be applicable where theClause I makes provision, therefore,for imposingnnial Census Powers.This question was reserved by the Cabinet in viewTreasury/
Treasury assent to the Census being taken.&apos;    The terms of Proviso i to Clause 1 and ox Clause 2(3) have been agreed to by the Treasury as giving, effect to this understanding.Clause 5.     In a perpetual Census Bill (as distinct from, a Bill authorising a particular Census only) it would appear to be proper to include some provision indicating that the operations of the Legistrar-General in connection with the taking of Censuses and the publication of Census statistics are not merely isolated acts, but links in a continuous chain. Apart from the provision, included hitherto in each separate Census act, that there should, be. a report upon the Census, end apart from the unimportant provision (temporarily suspended by emergency legislation) in Section 6 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act of 1836 that the Registrar-General should furnish an annual &quot;abstract of the number&quot; of births, deaths and marriages, there is no recognition whatever on the Statute Book of the important statistical work necessarily performed by the Eegistrar-Gereral&apos;s Department.    Clause 5 has accordingly been inserted, first to indicate that a common policy should link together one Census with another in a chain of continuity and co-ordination, and, secondly, not only to give statutory recognition to the important statistical work performed by that Department duxung inter-censal periods, but also to indicate that this wbi^c also must be governed by the same continuous policy.    Further, the Clause indicates the course by which the Department may best amplify   and improve its statistics, viz:   by making arrangements to utilize any material which is already available and can conveniently be acquired for the purpose.Local Census.   Clause 6.      Occasions have arisen in the past when it has been extremely desirable for thepurposes/
purposes of a local authority to obtain particulars of the population of its area or of the component parts of its area.     For example, under the London Equalisation of Rates Act, 1894, important financial adjustments within, the County of London depend upon the population of the several metropolitan boroughs;   and strong pressure has been brought to bear by the London County Council in the past to secure a Census of the population of the County in the inter-Censal period, owing to the admitted unreliability of population estimates during that period.     That need in particular would be met by the exercise of the quinquennial powers conferred by Clause 1. But it may not prove possible when tlie occasion arises in 192C or 1SS6 to exercise these powers;   and if this is the case, the need of the London County Council and any similar needs of other local authorities could conveniently be met by the powers which Clause 6 of the Bill proposes to confer. Schedule.It will be appreciated that one items included in this Schedule are &quot;matters, in respect of which particulars may be required&quot;, and that the exact nature of the enquiries   to be asked.at any Census (i,e. the .particulars) will be precisely defined by the Order in Council to be submitted to Parliament, especially in the case of enquiries falling under Items 5 and 8.     The nature of the enquiries, to be asked necessarily varies from Census to Census, and the requisite degree of latitude in framing the enquiries upon each future occasion by Order in Council cannot be securedVunless the heads of subject matter in the iict itself are specified in sufficiently general terms. Ireland,The Bill has been prepared after consultation,with/
with representative a of the Secretary for Scotland and the Chief Secretary for Ireland;   and It embodies, I understand, substantially agreed provisions.     It has not, however, been found possible to form any definite conclusions as to the inclusion of Ireland in a single United Kingdom Bill; and the Bill in its present form is put forward wholly without prejudice to this question, and in order that it may now be decided.Ministry of Health.C ADDISON. 17. 4. 1920.
Census Bill.ARRANGEMENT OF CLAUSES.Clause.1.  Power to direct taking of census.2.  Duty of Registrar-General to carry out census, and provision for expenses.3.  Regulations with respect to proceedings for taking census.4  Preparation of reports and abstracts.5.  Preparation of statistics in respect of periods between one census and another.6.   Local census.7.  Penalties.8.  Application to Scotland. 9.   Application to Ireland. 10.   Short title. Schedule.92-4
[10 Geo. 5.] Census.DRAFTop a toMake provision for the taking of a Census from time a.d. 1920. to  time  and  for   otherwise   obtaining  Statistical Information with respect to the Population of the United Kingdom.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5       1. (1) Subject to the provisions of this Act it shall be Power to lawful for His Majesty by Order in Council from time to time direct takingJ    13    - of census.to direct that a census shall be taken for the United Kingdom, or for any part of the United Kingdom, and any Order under this section may prescribe 10       (a) the date on which the census is to be taken; and(6) the persons by whom and with respect to whom the returns for the purpose of the census are to be made; and(c) the particulars to be stated in the returns:   -15       Provided that (i) an Order shall not be made under this section soas to require a census to be taken in any part of the United Kingdom in any year unless at the commencement of that year at least five years 20 have elapsed since the commencement of the year in which a census was last taken in that part of the United Kingdom; and(ii) no particulars shall be required to be stated other 1than particulars with respect to such matters as are 25 specified in the Schedule to this Act.92 ^ A
A.D. 1920. (2) Before any Order in Council is made under this section a draft thereof shall he laid before each House of Parliament for a period of not less than twenty days on which that House has sat, and if either House before the expiration of that period presents an address to His Majesty against the draft or any 5 part thereof, no further proceedings shall be taken thereon, hut without prejudice to the making of a new draft Order. &quot;(3) Any Order in Council made under this section may be revoked, amended or varied by a subsequent Order.Duty of 2.-(1) It shall be the duty of the Registrar-General to 10Generafto ma^e sucn arrangements and do all such things as are necessarycarry out for the taking of a census in accordance with the provisions ofcensus, and ^g j^Gi an(j 0  any order jn Council or regulations made provision tor *expenses.    thereunder, and for that purpose to make arrangements for thepreparation and issue of the necessary forms and instructions 15 and for the collection of the forms when filled up.(2) The Registrar-General in the exercise of his powers and in the performance of his duties under this Act or under any Order in Council or regulations made thereunder, shall be subject to the control of, and comply with any directions given 20 by, the Minister of Health.(3) Any expenses incurred with the sanction of the Treasury by the Minister of Health or the Registrar-General in connec-tion with the taking of a census or otherwise in connection ,with the exercise of his powers or the performance of his duties 25 under this Act shall be defrayed out of moneys provided by Parliament.Regulations 3. (1) Por the purpose of enabling any Order in Council with respect Erecting a census to be taken to be carried into effect  theto pro-ceedingsfor Minister of Health may make regulations  30census M providing for the division of the country into districtsfor the purpose of the census and the appointment of persons to act in those districts in connection with the census; (5) prescribing the duties in connection with the census of 35 superintendent registrars, registrars, and other persons employed for the purpose of the census;(c) requiring persons employed for the purpose of the census to make a statutory declaration with respect to the performance of their duties; 40
[10 Geo, 5,]Census.3(d) requiring the chief officers of public or charitable A.D. 1920,institutions, or of any other institutions prescribed by the regulations, to make returns with respect to: the inmates thereof;5 (e) requiring information to be given to the persons liable to make returns by the persons, with respect to whom the returns are to be made;(/) with respect to the forms to be used in the taking of a census;10 (g) making provision with respect to any other matters with respect to which it is necessary to make provision for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of the Order in Council.(2) Every regulation made under this section shall be laid 15 before both Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after it is made, and if an address is presented to His Majesty by either House within the next subsequent twenty days on which that House has sat next after any such regulation is laid before it praying that the regulation may be annulled, His Majesty in 20 Council may annul the regulation, and it shall thenceforth be void, but without prejudice to the validity of anything done thereunder.4.-(1) The Registrar-General shall, as soon as maybe after Preparation the taking of the census, prepare reports on the census returns, !^reports 25 and every such report shall be printed and laid before both abstracts. Houses of Parliament.(2) The Registrar-General may, if he so thinks fit, at the request and post of any local authority or person, cause abstracts to be prepared containing any such statistical information, being 30 information which is not contained in the reports made by him under this section and which in his opinion it is reasonable for that authority or person to require, as can be derived from the census returns.5. It shall be the duty of the Registrar-General, from time Preparation 35 to time to collect and publish any available statistical informa- ?f statlstlCi*m respect utilisation with respect to the number and condition of the population periods be-in the interval between one census and another, and otherwise tween oned to further the supply and provide for the better co-ordination of another, such information, and the Registrar-General may make arrange-40 ments with any Government Department or local authority for 92 A 2
Provision with respect to local census.Penalties.6. (1) If an application is made by a local authority to the Minister of Health asking that a census may be taken for the whole or any part of the area of the authority, or for an 5 area consisting of the whole or any part of that area and of the whole or any part of an adjoining area, the Minister may if he thinks fit submit the application to His Majesty, and His Majesty may by Order in Council, if it appears to His Majesty necessary so to do for the purpose of facilitating the due 10 performance by the local authority of its statutory duties, direct that a census shall be taken for the area specified in the application, or for any part of that area.(2) The provisions of this Act with respect to the taking of a census for the United Kingdom (other than the provision 15 with respect to the interval between one census and another) shall, with such modifications and adaptations as may he specified in the Order, apply to the taking of a census under this section.(3) Any expenses incurred in connection with the taking 20 of a census under this section (including the publication of any reports or returns with reference thereto) shall be paid&apos; by the local authority by which the application for the census was made, and. shall  be deemed to be part of the general expenses of that authority. 25(4) The expression &quot;local authority&quot; in this section means the council of a county, of a borough, or of an urban district.7. (1) If any person (a) refuses or neglects to comply wdth or acts in con-contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or 30 any Order in Council or regulations made under this Act; or(b) being a person required under this Act to make a statutory declaration with respect to the performance of his duties, makes a false declaration; or 35(c) being a person required by any Order in council or regulations made under this Act to make, sign, or deliver any document, makes, signs, or delivers, or causes to be made, signed, or delivered a false document; or 40A,Dll.920&apos;       PurPose of acquiring any materials or information necessary for the purpose aforesaid.
&quot;10 Geo. 5.&apos;Census.5(d) being a person required in pursuance of any such Order A.D. 1920. in Council or regulations to answer any question, refuses to answer or gives a false answer to that question;5 he shall for each offence be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding ten pounds,(2) If any person (a) being a person employed in taking a census, withoutlawful authority publishes or communicates to any 10 person any information acquired by him in thecourse of his employment; or(b) having possession of any information which to his knowledge has been disclosed in contravention of this Act, publishes or communicates that informa-15 tion to any other person;he shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, and shall on conviction he liable to imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term   &apos; not exceeding two years or to a fine, or to both such imprison-ment and fine.20 8. Applicationto Scotland.9.Application to Ireland.10. This Act may he cited as the Census Act, 1920.Short title.
AI)- l92()- SCHEDULEMatters in respect oe which Particulars may be required.A.Throughout the United Kingdom. 1.  Names, sex, age, 52.   Occupation, profession, trade or employment. 3.  Nationality, birthplace, race, language. 4.  Place of abode and character of dwelling place. 5.   Education.6.  Infirmity or disability. -^q7. Condition as to marriage, relation to head of family, parentage, issue.8. Any other matters with respect to which it is desirable to obtain statistical information with a view to ascertaining the social or civil condition of the population. -   15B.In Ireund,Religious - denomination,

Census.D E, A FTOP AB   I   L  tTo make provision for the taking of a Census from time to time and for otherwise obtaining Statis-tical Information with respect to the Population of the United Kingdom.LXXXV.   (4.)31st March 1920.92-4

</content>
</cab>
