<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/62/36 images: 348-353</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJEBTT&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET.&quot;W.P. (45) 181.3rd March, 1945.WAR CABINET.WOMEN&apos;S LAND ARMY AND POST-WAR WELFARE SCHEMES.Memorandum by Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.1. I attach herewith a revised statement on the proposed special schemefor the Women&apos;s Land Army. I should be glad if this could be substitutedfor that appended to my memorandum (W.P. (45) 120).2. The Minister of Labour in his memorandum (W.P. (45) 123) states thatif the proposals for the Women&apos;s Land Army were adopted&apos; there would beirresistible claims from certain other groups of workers who have also receivedthe wage appropriate to the industry in which they are employed. I believethat a convincing case can be made out to satisfy those other industrial workersthat special treatment should be accorded to the Women&apos;s Land Army.3. The Land Army was recruited on a voluntary basis by the departments of Agriculture; it is provided by the Government with a specially designednational uniform, and its badge bears the Crown; it constitutes a separate body,working in agriculture and forestry, but drawn from outside those industries;it has to give fully mobile service until after the end of the war; its rates of payare those appropriate to immobile workers in the industry, which are less thanthose in other industries and those in the Auxiliary Services and Civil Defence.4. No other body of workers can claim that all these conditions apply tothem, except perhaps the Civil Nursing Reserve.5. Some women have been directed away from home to work in the transport services, although the majority of women in those services work in places near to their own homes. Uniforms have been provided by their employers, but not by the State. Their earnings are higher than those in Civil Defence, which arein turn higher than those of the Land Army.6. Youths directed to coal-mining probably have a strong case in any event,because gratuities are to be given to the Armed Forces, and because they were directed,        st their will, into mining instead of one or other of the forces.7, Women directed into munitions and other essential war work generallyearn wages appreciably higher than those in agriculture. Moreover, the WarCabinet recently took the view (WM. (45) 24th Conclusions, Minute 3) that civil defence workers, although they had shared in the progressive increases in militarypay, &quot;would have benefited still more had they been free to go into industry.&quot;The case for assistance to women directed to work away from home in war industries can therefore be resisted on the ground that they have been better offfinancially than those in the Auxiliary Services and Civil Defence. A special scheme for the Women&apos;s Land Army, whose members may not leave agricultureexcept for health or other very good reasons, can be defended on the ground thattheir earnings have been below those of the Auxiliary Services and Civil Defence.8. Women already working in agriculture are refused admission to theW.L.A. because they are immobile, and are mostly living at home. There is everyjustification for giving special consideration to members of the Land Army, whowhile mobile receive only the wages appropriate to other women in agriculturewho are immobile.iopy No.[29347]
9. The Merchant Navy would admittedly receive very strong popularsupport. This may well be forthcoming whatever decision is reached regardingthe Land Army. The pay&apos; of the Merchant Navy is, however, appreciably higherthan that of men in agriculture, who receive nearly 50 per cent, more than women.10. When at the outbreak of war it was realised that the country&apos;s existencemight well depend upon an adequate supply of home-produced food, it became clear-that substantial numbers of women would have to be recruited for work onthe land. There were insufficient numbers of immobile women available in mostlocalities to provide the necessary labour locally. An appeal to women to seekemployment in agriculture through Employment Exchanges would certainly have failed to produce satisfactory results, and it has not been considered practicableor expedient to direct women into agriculture. The only method by which asufficient number of recruits could be obtained was by the establishment of acorporate body and an appeal-to women to join a Service which has throughoutbeen understood by the public, and believed by its members, to be a NationalService comparable with that of the Women&apos;s Auxiliary Services. The preservation-tion of this corporate spirit, and of the feeling that they were members of a uniform and uniformed State Service, has done much to maintain the keenness,and even the membership, of those who joined, and it has undoubtedly helpedrecruitment throughout the war. The effect both on existing and on prospectivemembers of a flat refusal to do anything for them would be disastrous.11. If the suggestion made when the Resettlement Grant scheme was underconsideration, or still earlier when the Further Education and Training schemewas being discussed, that the Land Army should be given equality with the civil defence Services, had been adopted, there would probably have been no criticism from, or repercussions in, any quarter. In the event of a decision adverse tothe Women&apos;s Land Army, the Governments position will have been made muchmore difficult by the announcement that the Women&apos;s Land Army case was receiving sympathetic consideration, since the Land Army and Members ofParliament have been led to expect that something at any, rate will be secured forthem.12. If post-war benefits are given to the Civil Defence Services and not tothe Women&apos;s Land Army the Government is likely to find the decision hard todefend. It will, in my opinion, be difficult to explain why it has been decided to discriminate in favour of one civilian service and yet to exclude another whosewages are lower. To justify the inclusion of Civil Defence workers on thegrounds that their wages have been fixed by the State at a level approximating tothose of the Armed Forces would not be defensible unless it could be shown thatthe wages were below those of other civilian services and those of industrial workers generally. I must again emphasise, however, that the earnings of land army members (mobile) are appreciably below those of women in Civil Defence(mostly immobile), while the average earnings of the classes of worker referredto in the Minister of Labour&apos;s memorandum are, on the other hand, above them.(Initialled) R. S. H.Ministry of A griculture and Fisheries, S.W. 1,3rd March, 1945.
Draft Statement by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.THE Government has given careful consideration to the position of membersof the Women&apos;s Land Army in relation to schemes for financial assistance to women released from the Women&apos;s Auxiliary Services. As I explained to theHouse on the 20th February, there are differences between conditions of recruit-ment and service which precludes treatment on the same basis.The Government recognises, however, that the Women&apos;s Land Army wasrecruited under conditions which suggested that its members, while to aconsiderable extent in private employment, would yet belong to a State service;that they have had to undertake to give fully mobile service while receiving wagesappropriate to immobile workers in the industry; and that they will be wanted to give mobile service up to and possibly after the defeat of Japan.While, therefore, the Government is not able to agree that members of theW.L.A. should be treated on the same basis as women in either the Auxiliary orthe Civil Defence Services, it proposes to make an outfit allowance of  12 10s. toany member upon being given willing release from the Land Army, provided thatshe has given satisfactory service for not less than six months; and for those members who undertake to continue in the Land Army for not less than one year-after the defeat of Germany, to pay a cash bonus at the rate of 4s. per month for each month of service, payable on completion of service, but subject to a;minimum period of six months&apos; service.Members of the W.L.A. will be eligible to participate in the schemes forfurther education and training and for vocational training which have alreadybeen announced. Special consideration will be given to those members of theLand Army who satisfy the essential conditions and who wish to undergoeducation and training with a view to making a career in agriculture orhorticulture.




</content>
</cab>
