<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/44 images: 506-515</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  April 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)99th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UND1LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.Yi/AR CABINET 99 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Sunday, April 21, 1940, at 4-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir King-sley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Secretary of State for War. Bt., M P-, Secretary of State for Air.The    Right   Hon.    Lord    Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon.secretary affairs.ofViscount Halifax,State   for   foreign the following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security (Items 1-8).Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-8).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 1-8).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadqgan,Permanent Under-Secretary of State,Foreign Office (Items 1-8).Admiral  of  the   Fleet  Sir  dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chiefof Naval Staff (Items 1-4).General  Sir  W.  Edmund  Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-8).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.[211871
WAR CABINET 99 (40).Contents.Subject.The Air SituationEnemy activity.E.A.F. activity: Aalborg.Stavanger aerodrome.Mine-laying.Western Eront.The Naval Situation ...The Military SituationWestern Front.Operations in Norway ...The Western Front    .................Air action if Holland or Belgium is invaded.Supreme War Council : 8th MeetingPolish and Norwegian representation.Possible Allied action in the Caucasus.Italy.......................Probable intentions.Suggested approach to Signor Mussolini through the Vatican.GermanyProbable intentions: account received from a United States visitorto Denmark.The Admiral Scheer.The Budget     ....................
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 98thConclusions,Minute 1.)Enemy activity.R.A.F. activity:Aalborc.stavanger aerodrome.Mine-laying.Western Front.1. The Secretary of State for Air said that during theprevious night some 20 enemy raids had been reported betweenHarwich and the Downs. It was believed that the aircraft had been engaged in mine-laying.During the same period a convoy had been attacked offYarmouth, but without damage.There had been great activity by the Bomber Command in theprevious 24 hours, although operations had been considerablyhampered by unfavourable weather conditions. A night bombing attack had been made on the aerodrome at Aalborg in Denmark.From preliminary reports, it had been ascertained that a hangarhad been bombed from 800 feet and a German transport aircraftcoming in to land had been attacked.Twelve aircraft had been despatched to attack stavanger aerodrome. Three of these had reached the objective and obtainedhits on the aerodrome and the seaplane base. A balloon barrage hadbeen put up during this attack.Formations of bombers had also been sent out to attack the aerodromes at Oslo, the aerodrome at Vaernes, and shipping in oslo fjord. In each case Stavanger had been given as a secondaryobjective. Full reports of these latter operations had not yet beenreceived, but a number of attacks had been made on Stavanger,which had been seen to be blazing fiercely.Mines had been successfully laid by aircraft in the Weser andElbe estuaries.All our bombers had returned safely from all these operations.An enemy submarine had been attacked by a Coastal command aircraft 50 miles to the westward of Haugesund earlier in the day,but no results had been observed.Reconnaissances by the Air Component of the british expeditionary Force on the previous day had disclosed no unusualroad or rail activity.Fighter aircraft of the Advanced Air Striking Force had hada number of combats, in the course of which two Heinkels 111 andtwo Messerschmitts 109 had been shot down. Two furtherMesserschmitts 109 were claimed, but their destruction had not yetbeen confirmed. One of our Hurricanes had been forced down, butthe pilot was safe. There had been no other casualties to british personnel or aircraft.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 98thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Chief of the Naval Staff reported the following losses by mines on the 20th April: S.S. Mersey (1,000 tons) off Deal. Seven survivors, twokilled, eleven missing.S.S. Hawnby (5,380 tons) off Thames Estuary. Crew of thirty-nine saved.The Chief of Naval Staff gave the War Cabinet informationof certain projected warship movements.[21187]
The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 97thConclusions,Minute 4.)Western Pront.3. The Secretary of State for War said that there was nothing of importance to report from the Western Front.Operations in 4.   The War Cabinet were informed that the situation in norway. Norway had taken a somewhat less favourable turn.   Namsos had(Previous been bombed from the air from 10 a.m. the previous day, and veryReference.-        considerable damage had been done.   The town had been destroyedW.M. (40) 98th  by fire and the railhead put out of action.   The wharf, however,Conclusions,      had not been damaged, and it was believed that there had been fewMinute 3.)        casualties.   It was feared, however, that considerable quantities ofammunition and stores had been destroyed.     The anti-aircraftcruiser which had accompanied the second French convoy and hadcovered its disembarkation had been withdrawn by the french admiral, and the base had thus been left undefended against air attack.General Carton de Wiart had telegraphed that for the present no more men or supplies could be landed at Namsos, and he was proposing to maintain his force from a point further to the north.He was, however, short of motor transport, and until the main-tenance difficulties of his forces had been overcome, he could not hope to act decisively to the north of Trondhjem.Andalsnes had also been bombed on the 20th April, but therehad been no casualties. This base was protected by an anti-aircraftcruiser. Unfortunately an M/T ship in the convoy which had arrived there the previous day had been sunk by a submarine. this had carried the transport of Brigadier Morgan&apos;s Brigade and fourBofors guns.Brigadier Morgan had, however, made considerable progress inthe south. He had pushed ahead and joined the Norwegians atLillehammer with two battalions, after mopping up the parachutistsat Dombaas. The Germans were reported to have a small detach-ment at Storen, the junction of the two railways just south ofTrondhjem.The total number of troops ashore at the present time in theTrondhjem area was about 6,500 at Namsos and 2,400 at Andalsnes.The Chief of the Air Staff, in answer to a question by thePrime Minister, said that the aircraft which had bombed Namsoswere probably using a frozen lake near Trondhjem as an advancedbase, but their main bases would be at Stavanger and Oslo, and in, Denmark and Germany. It would be possible for Messerschmitt110&apos;s to reach Andalsnes from Stavanger to protect their bombingaircraft.Considerable discussion followed on plans to meet thesituation described above, a record of which, together with theconclusions reached, is contained in the Secretary&apos;s standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.It was pointed out that the Germans might try to forestall us,;by telegraphing exaggerated accounts of the bombing of Namsos andAndalsnes. In particular, they might try to use this event to influence the Italian Government.It was suggested that we ought, with the least possible delay,to issue our own account in which we would make it clear that no casualties had been inflicted on any of the troops we had landed at Namsos. Our communique might also bring out the fact thatthe previous day had, on the whole, been a good day for this countryin the air.
.. 249387 W.M. 99 (40).The War Cabinet-Invited the Lord Privy Seal to arrange, as soon as possible,for the issue of a suitable communique in consultationwith the Ministers concerned.The western front.Air action if holland or belgium is invaded.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 92ndConclusions,Minute 7.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChiefs of Staffs on the air action to be taken in the event of aGerman invasion of the Low Countries (W.P. (40) 132).A report of the discussion and of the conclusions reached is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Supreme WarCouncil: 8thMeeting.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 98thConclusions,Minute 5.)Polish andNorwegianrepresentation.Possible allied action in theCaucasus.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 93rdConclusions,Minute 11.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that hehad received a telephone message from His Majesty&apos;s ambassador in Paris to the effect that the French Government thought it wouldbe desirable that representatives of the Polish and Norwegian Governments should be given an opportunity of being present forthe last half-hour of the meeting of the Supreme War Council on tuesday, 23rd April.The French had also suggested that the subject of operations in the Caucasus should be added to the agenda for the meeting.The Foreign Secretary said that both requests had appearedto him to be unobjectionable, and he had therefore agreed to them on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Italy.probable intentions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 98thConclusions,Minute 6.)7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto Rome telegram No. 404 DIPP, dated 20th April, reporting afurther conversation which had taken place between Lady Loraineand the Duke d&apos;Aosta. The Duke had seemed depressed by thegeneral situation, and had confirmed that there had been differences of opinion between Signor Mussolini and Count Ciano. He had expressed himself as highly concerned about the internal politicalsituation. Marshal Balbo, Count Grandi and Count Ciano were, hesaid, most preoccupied.He had reiterated what he had said on his former visit, viz.,that Signor Mussolini was afraid of Germany and apprehensivelest northern Italy should be devastated by war. The Brennerdefences were not completed. He did not pretend to know whatthe outcome of events would be, and, as regards the Duce, hadremarked &quot; I do not know what he has got in his head.&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Minister thought that the fact that the Duked&apos;Aosta had come to see Lady Loraine at the present time was an indication that in the Duke&apos;s opinion no immediate crisis was likely.
Suggestedapproach to signor Mussolinithrough the vatican.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 95thConclusions,Minute 7.).The Foreign Secretary also drew attention to telegrams nos. 343 DIPP, dated 19th April, and 44 DIPP, dated 20th April,from His Majesty&apos;s Minister to the Holy See, reporting thatMr. Myron Taylor had needed little persuasion to induce him to payable visit to the Cardinal Secretary of State, with a view to the Pope&apos;sputting pressure on Signor Mussolini to remain neutral. Theproposal which Mr. Myron Taylor had put before the CardinalSecretary of State was that not only President Roosevelt but alsothe Pope and the King of Italy (after being approached for thispurpose by the Vatican) should address themselves privately to signor Mussolini, and urge him to keep the peace. The Pope had agreed in principle to this method of approach to Signor Mussolini,who should receive the three communications very shortly, unlessthe President should feel unable to act, which Mr. Myron Taylordid not anticipate.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Germany.probable intentions:account receivedfrom a UnitedStates visitor toDenmark.The admiral scheer.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 96thConclusions,Minute 2.)8. The Foreign Secretary said that he had received an account,from an American visitor just returned from Denmark, of hisimpressions of that country under the German occupation. ThisAmerican had apparently been in friendly communication with anumber of German Military and Air Commanders who had talkedfreely to him, and had made no secret of what they alleged to be theGerman plans. According to these Commanders, who had appearedto be full of confidence in themselves and in Germany, the plan wasthat the Germans would make themselves masters of Denmark and norway as quickly and as completely as possible, and would thenturn their attention to the Western Front and to the UnitedKingdom.On the Western Front the plan would be to incur up to 50,000casualties in a feint attack on the Maginot Line, to be followedimmediately by the real advance through Holland and Belgium.The main attack would be accompanied by intensive air bombardment.There was also to be mass bombing of this country, althoughbefore this took place the Germans would have to get possessionof air bases in Holland and to bring back their air forces from norway.The American visitor said that he had been taken to the aerodrome at Aalborg, which was being developed by the Germanswith feverish activitjr. He said that there were no less than400 aircraft there, wing-tip to wing-tip. The American could not understand why we had not bombed Aalborg.He had also visited Frederikshaven, where he had seen a vesselsunk in the harbour, which he had understood to be the admiral scheer.  Only the funnel and mast were above water.The Foreign Secretary said that one would naturally askoneself why this foreigner, assuming that his account was true, hadbeen taken so readily into the confidence of the German high command. The probable explanation was that it was in order thathe might spread abroad tales of Germany&apos;s invincibility. It didnot follow, however, that the strategical plans which he had mentioned were not in substance Germany&apos;s real plans.
The Budget. 9.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer communicated to the War(Previous Cabinet full- details of his financial proposals for the forthcomingBef erence: Budget.W.M. (39) 27th In view of the great importance of secrecy, the details, in conclusions.)     accordance with precedent, are not recorded in the War cabinet conclusions.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,April 21, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
