<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/137/0 images: 22-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1922.SECRET.C.P-4003.CABINET.IMPERIAL WIRELESS CHAIN.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I CIRCULATE a Memorandum by the Imperial Communications Committee,, of which I endorse the recommendations. The Governments of Australia, India (and probably the LTnion of South Africa) desire to establish direct communication, with the United Kingdom instead of by 2,000 miles steps as proposed in the scheme of the Imperial Wireless Chain now approved. The Governments of Australia and India propose to hand over to private companies the erection and operation of the stations in their territory. . In the annexed Memorandum proposals are put forward by the Imperial Communications Committee to meet the wishes of these Governments for direct services with the United Kingdom by the erection by the Imperial Govern-ment of a 240-k.w. station in the United Kingdom.2. In order to provide funds necessary for the erection of the increased power station, it is proposed to defer the erection of the second station in Egypt and of the stations at Hong Kong and Nairobi, thus reducing the capital liabilities of the Imperial Government from  853,000 to  593,000 (saving  260,000), and annual charges from  268,000 to  183,000 (saving  85,000). The annual receipts are estimated at  164,000.3. At the meetings of the Imperial Communications Committee apprehensions were expressed that pressure will be brought to bear upon His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment to secure the reversal of the decision that stations in the United Kingdom to-communicate with Dominions oversea shall be erected and operated by Government. It has been suggested that the Marconi Company will organise a strong protest if a licence to erect such a station is withheld from them; and that the services of Mir. Hughes will be enlisted to support that protest.4. On the merits of the question the Commonwealth Government have no locus standi to intervene, and there is nothing in Mr. Hughes&apos;s remarks at the Imperial meetings last year (of which relevant extracts are annexed) to show that he desires to do so, although his attitude may have changed since then.W. S. c.Colonial Office, June 9, 1922.ANNEXURE.Imperial Meetings, 1921.Extract from Proceedings of Vsth Meeting, July 5, 1921.Discussion on the Imperial Wireless Chain. * * * * * *Mr. Hughes: I am not going to deal now with the recommendations of that Committee.  I say, however, this, that nothing has followed upon either the decision[8487]
of any of the Conferences or the recommendations of the Norman Committee. We still do nothing. Now, if I am asked what scheme I prefer, I say I prefer any scheme which will get itself done. When you refer these matters to the Post Office, your Post Office or our Post Office, we always get the same answer. It may be taken as symptomatic of Post Offices, but it is well known that they are obsessed with the idea that they, and they alone, are to be entrusted with the latest achievements of science. No doubt the Admiralty quite properly have to consider the effect of all this when at war, and they must take control when war breaks out. That goes without saying. I have had very spirited Conferences with my Postmaster-General, and with his officials, and I am bound to say they have not been altogether satisfactory. I come very reluctantly to the conclusion that our only hope for doing this thing is to get it done by somebody other than the Post Office, otherwise it will never be done at all.I hope that nothing I have said will be taken as a reflection on the Post Office.-TV VY* -TV -TVMr. Hughes: If you say that &quot; the Government will do this,&quot; then I say, &quot; I shall be content that no one else than the Government shall do it.&quot; If you say, We will get it done, whether in this or that way,&quot; I am satisfied. All I ask is that it should be done. We cannot go on now as we are, imperilling our Imperial connec-tions, imposing an intolerable handicap on commerce, and leaving our citizens in the various parts of the Empire generally uninformed of what the other parts are doing -left helplessly and hopelessly in the race for supremacy in a scheme of communica-tion, of which we were eleven years ago the originators. And so I say I am not going to pin myself down to any scheme so long as something is done.M. M. .AA. Jf. M, JJ,TV&quot; &quot;TV &quot;TV -TV- WMr. Hughes: What I propose is very simple, and it has the merit of simplicity. It is this, that this Conference shall approve of a scheme of wireless linking the Empire together; that Great Britain shall say, &quot; We will put up our plant; you put up yoiir plant.&quot; In this event we will put up a plant in Australia which will com-municate&apos; direct with you, and every other Dominion can do the same. Then every Dominion is in this position, it need not wait on any other, either to begin construc-tion or to reap the advantages.*fc &apos;IV &quot;TV TV wVMr. Hughes: I do strongly urge that from every point of view, from the point of view of what may be termed Government of Empire, in order to ensure that the Dominions&apos; share in formulating foreign policy shall be real, in order that the defence of Empire shall be effective, in order that trade and commerce may be benefited, and in order that public opinion throughout the Empire may be well informed and that Empire and British propaganda throughout the world may be in a position at least to hold its own with anti-British propaganda, that this should be done. For all these reasons I urge very strongly that a wireless scheme should be adopted.$fv *X* ^t-Appendix III.Imperial Wireless Scheme.Resolution.It is agreed that His Majesty&apos;s Government should take steps for the erection of the remaining stations for which they are responsible, as soon as the stations are designed; that the Governments of Australia, the Union of South Africa, and India, should take similar action so far as necessary, and that the Governments of Canada and New Zealand should also co-operate.The above scheme was accepted by the Prime Minister of the Commonwealth, subject to giving full freedom of action to Australia to decide the method in which Australia will co-operate.* * * * * *
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s G-overnment.]Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1922.SECRET. C.P.-4003.CABINET.IMPERIAL WIRELESS CHAIN.Memorandum by the Imperial Communications Committee.RECENT despatches from the Governments of the Dominions, which agreed to participate in the Imperial Wireless Chain, have made it necessary to review the arrangements at present approved, and to make proposals to meet the new situation arising from the change of plans of these Governments.2. In a telegram dated the 12th November, 1921, the Government of India suggested that the Imperial Government should finance the construction of the Indian station, or, failing that, that the work should be carried out by private enterprise.  rIn a further telegram dated the 3rd March, 1922, the Government of India stated that they were definitely unable to provide funds at present for the construc-tion of the Indian station of the Imperial Wireless Chain, and they put forward a proposal that the construction, ownership and operation of the Indian station should be entrusted to a commercial company.3. The Commonwealth Government have recently entered into an arrangement with a commercial company in which they are interested to establish and operate all wireless stations in Australia, including a station for direct wireless communication between Australia and Great Britain.4. In a telegram dated the 24th April, the Government of the Union of South Africa report that they have been approached by the Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company, who offer to construct a station in South Africa at their own expense, which they guarantee would provide satisfactory continuous, direct wireless communication with Great Britain. The Union Government propose to ask the Company to furnish full particulars of the proposed scheme, but they desire to be informed of the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government before doing so.5. A telegram dated the 28th March, 1922, from the Governor-General of Canada states that the Canadian Government are making arrangements to send two representatives to England to discuss the possible participation of Canada in the scheme for the Imperial Wireless Chain.6. The Governments of India, Australia and the Union of South Africa, while desirous of co-operating in the scheme for an Imperial Wireless Chain, are anxious that communication with England should be direct without the intermediate stations proposed in the scheme as previously sanctioned.7. In submitting the following proposals, we have accepted the principle that each Government participating in the Imperial Wireless Chain shall do so in the manner it thinks fit. We therefore assume that the Governments of Australia and the Union of South Africa will construct stations to give direct communication with the United Kingdom, and we recommend that the station in the United Kingdom should be designed to enable these direct services to be effectively operated, i8. At a meeting on the 4th August, 1920, the Cabinet agreed to adopt the recommendations of the Imperial Wireless Telegraphy Committee, which were summed up in a Memorandum by Lord Milner (C.I.D. 248-B) in the following terms: &quot; In view of the undesirability of granting to any company a monopoly such as that which the adoption of the Marconi Company&apos;s proposals is estimated to involve, I submit: &quot;(a.) That the recommendations of the Imperial Wireless Telegraphy Committee should be adopted, and that the Governments of the self-governing Dominions and India should now be approached with a view to ascertaining the extent to which they are prepared to co-operate.[8430]
&quot; (&amp;.) That long-distance wireless communication with foreign countries should be left to private enterprise, and that licences, if desired, for the erection of stations for such communication should be issued under suitable conditions to commercial companies.&quot;The recommendations of the Imperial Wireless Telegraphy Committee referred to in [a) above included a recommendation that wireless stations erected in the United Kingdom to communicate with British territory oversea should be constructed and operated by Government. They were of opinion that if wireless communication with British territory oversea was left to commercial companies &quot;the stimulus arising from competitive activity would tend to disappear, technical research would be discouraged, and wireless technicians or operators could hardly look for employment outside the Fighting Services, except in the Company&apos;s service. Indeed, the conces-sion, from the moment it was granted, would tend to deprive the Services and the Post Office of their best engineering personnel. The heads of the Departments of State will doubtless have regard to this prospect. For ourselves, we should regard the inclusion of virtually all civilian wireless activity in the hands of one commercial company as likely to be deeply prejudicial to research and progress.&quot;9. The principal objections to placing the Imperial Wireless Chain in the hands of a commercial company are as follows :-(a) Commercial, rather than Imperial, interests will obviously receive first consideration.(b.) It is practically certain that only one company will be in a position to tender for the Chain, and this company would therefore establish a virtual monopoly, and there will be no competition.(c.) It would be to the Company&apos;s interest to standardise apparatus as much as possible, and to avoid the introduction of new apparatus unless this was likely to prove of definite commercial advantage.(d.) It is unlikely that any single commercial company has the same facilities for research as the Government, or spends so large a sum of money, on research, nor can any single company command the services or the result of experiences of the Navy, Army, Air Force and Post Office, which is at present so valuable. It follows, therefore, that the efficiency of the stations would not necessarily be as high as is desirable from the Imperial point of view.We therefore strongly recommend that the decision that no private company should be granted a licence to erect a wireless station in the United Kingdom with the object of communicating with British territory oversea should be adhered to, and that all such stations should be constructed and operated by the Government.10. In addition to the reasons stated above for adhesion to that decision, it would be undesirable, alike from a technical and financial point of view, to operate two or more high-power wireless stations under Government and private control in the United Kingdom for communication with one Dominion.11. The Planning Commission recommended that the English station of the Imperial Wireless Chain should be first erected of 120 K.W. magnitude, which they believed would give good direct.communication with Australia during several hours daily. The Commission proposed that the station should be ultimately extended to 240 KW. power, which would enable communication to be maintained with Australia during several more hours daily. But during the two years that have elapsed great progress has been made under Government auspices in the development of high powers by valve, and indeed the most powerful valve installation in the world is now being successfully tested at His Majesty&apos;s Signal School at Horsea.To enable direct communication to be established with India, Australia and South Africa on a commercial basis, we recommend that the station in England should be erected of the full 240 K.W. power at the outset.
12. In reply to their telegram of the 24th April, we recommend that a telegram be sent to the Government of the Union of South Africa recommending that the South African station should for the present be of 120 K.W. power, but capable of extension to 240 K.W. The 120 K.W. station could be provided either by the conversion of the present station at Windhuk or by the erection of a new station elsewhere.We are informed that: (a.) The present Windhuk station, if equipped with valves, could transmit to England about 4,500 words per day direct, and about 6,000 words per day through Cairo.(&amp;.) A new station erected in South Africa of 120 K.W. power could transmit to England! about 8,000 words per day direct, and about 10,000 words per day through Cairo.13. We recommend that the erection of the station at Nairobi be deferred. A saving of  185,000 in capital expenditure will thereby be effected.14. We now turn to the Indian station. In view of the desirability of avoiding dual management and operation of the central link of the Imperial Chain, we are of opinion that that station should be constructed and operated by Government. As the Government of India are unable at present to provide the necessary funds, we recommend that the construction and operation of the station in India should be undertaken by the Imperial Government at a capital cost of  185,000. We recommend that the station be of 120 K.W. power for the present. The new station in India will be able to communicate with England direct for several hours daily, and through the Egyptian station when atmospherics are bad.15. The extra capital expenditure entailed by the immediate construction of the English station of 240 K.W. instead of 120 K.W. power would be  110,000. The construction of such a station in England would render the construction of the second Imperial station in Egypt unnecessary, thus effecting a saving of  185,000 in capital expenditure.We are advised that the existing Egyptian station at Abu Zabal could be used as an intermediate station when necessary, and that it would be capable of handling all the traffic likely to be offered for some years to come.16. In view of the change in the situation in the Pacific due to the Quadruple Pacific Treaty, the value of the Hong Kong station is somewhat diminished. We propose that the erection of the station in Hong Kong, estimated to cost  185,000, should also be deferred.17. The representatives of the Fighting Services present at our meeting pointed out that the decision to abandon the station at Hong Kong was one with which they were unwilling to associate themselves for reasons.of Imperial Defence. We desire to draw the attention of the Cabinet to that aspect of the question.18. Owing to the strategic, political and commercial importance of the station at Singapore, we recommend that the construction of this station, as at present approved, should be proceeded with.19. The net financial effect of our proposals would be a saving of  260,000 in the capital expenditure chargeable to the Imperial Treasury, and a reduction of  85,000 in annual charges. A statement showing the financial effect of the proposals now submitted, as compared with those hitherto sanctioned, is annexed.The annual charges under the present proposals are estimated at  183,000. Against this annual charge, however, must be placed the average yearly revenue from the stations in England, India and Singapore, which is estimated at  164,000 for the next five years, after which an annual increase of 5 per cent, may be expected.20. It is desirable that the Commonwealth Government be reminded without delay that, as explained in paragraph 8 above, the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government is that stations erected in the United Kingdom for the purpose of communicating with British territory oversea should be erected and operated by Government; and that they be informed that His Majesty&apos;s Government propose to meet the wishes of the Commonwealth for a direct service by at once erecting in the United Kingdom a new station of the full power (240 K.W.) contemplated by their experts.
i     21. Summary of Recommendations : I     (1.) That the erection of the second Imperial station in Egypt be deferred.(2.) That the decision to erect the station in Hong Kong be reconsidered. &apos;-.     (3.) That the erection of the station at Nairobi be deferred.(4.) That a telegram be sent to the Government of the Union of South Africa:(a) informing them of the proposal to erect in the United Kingdom at the outset a station of 240 K.W. power to communicate direct with. Australia, and capable of direct communication with South Africa; and(b) recommending that the South African station should for the present be of 120 K.W. power, but capable of extension to 240 K.W. power.(5.) That in order to provide direct communication with Australia the station in England be erected of the full power (240 K.W.) contemplated by the Imperial Wireless Telegraphy Committee.(6.) That the Commonwealth Government be reminded that the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government is that stations erected in the United Kingdom for communicating with British territory oversea should be operated by Government.(7.) That the station in India should be constructed and operated by HisMajesty&apos;s Government. (8.) That the erection of the station at Singapore be proceeded with.(Signed) HENRY NORMAN [Vice-Chairman).M. F. HEADLAM (Treasury).. H. KITSON (Admiralty). H. CLEMENTI SMITH (War Office). L. F, BLANDY (Air Ministry). *R. C. BARKER (India Office). F. J. BROWN (General Post Office). R. SPERLING (Foreign Office). E. J. HARDING (Colonial Office). C. HIPWOOD (Board of Trade).* Mr. Barker signed the Memorandum, but wished to record that the Secretary of State for India must reserve his opinion on paragraph 14 until he had received the views of the Government of India, which had been requested by telegram.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., May 19, 1922.APPENDIX.Imperial Wibeless ChainsLiabilities of His Majesty&apos;s Government.	Under Scheme at Present Sanctioned.		Under Scheme now Submitted.		Station.					Remarks.	Capital Cost.	Annual Charges.	Capital Cost.	Annual Charges.	English    Station  .. Cairo           ,, . Singapore     ,, Hong Kong   ,, Nairobi        ,,	  113,000 185,000 185,000 185,000 185,000	  39,000 67,000 60,000 50,000 52,000	  223,000 l85,&apos;oOO	  64,000 60,000	India           ,,			185,000	59,000	Total	853,000	268,000	593,000	183,000	Showing a total reduction of .&apos;.			260,000	85,000	Estimated annual revenue from the stations in the United Kingdom, Singapore and India is 164,000/. for the next five years, after which an annual increase of a per cent, may be expected.

</content>
</cab>
