<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/137/0 images: 571-573</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J -    337DEHTIAL.C A 3 I ir s T.4044.(ffQ.!^,    J^&quot;..?60?0^0-1?^ Cabinet.),The appended extract from the *TimesM of June 19th, 1922, on the above subject is circulated to the Cabinet for information by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. -   -(Sgd.)   l!Up.A-, HA1IKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.J Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1. 20th June, 1922.
&quot;Sirl ay I, as the father of one of the officers kidnapped, and without, reasonable doubt., murdered, at Maeroom, be permitted to say a few words upon events which have touched me so nearly?Let me briefly recall the facts..   The three officers &quot;with their soldier driver stopped at the inn in Macroom, entered it voluntarily, either for refreshaent or Hex some purpose connected with the oar, and were never seen again.There was no civil authority in that district.    The British Government had ab&amp;ioated; the provisional Government did not-and does not &quot;function&quot; there.   The &quot;Reds&quot; urho hold Jlacroom Castle which stands just opposite the inn, are not interested in the administration, of Justice.   Both parties When appealed to contented themselves with making inquiries and giving assurance3 that none of their own men were con-cerned; neither lifted a finder to prevent or to punish the crime&apos;.The military authorities at Cork, hampered as they ?rere by ihe political conditions , did everything in their power to recover the kidnapped men alive.   In this they failed, and sucoeededl only in obtaining sufficient informa-7ion to convince them that they had bcten murdered.   Nothing more could be done, and the military force was shortly after-*ards withdrawn &quot;according to plan&quot;.There is now, apparently, no authority whatever in &apos;,hat neighbourhood; it is not possible, we are told, even &apos;.o search for the bodies.   If the drime remains undetected it is not for want of oluea, tout beoause the ordinary biachinery of justice does not exist.   The victims, it must &apos;i*e remembered were not private individuals, still less partisans of any Irish faction, but officers of the Imperial government, which is one of the parties to the Treaty.The incident is, of oourse, but one of many; and incidents of this kind appear to be regarded on both sides is am. inevitable accompaniment of the Treaty policy.   But hat is precisely the point I wish to raise in this letter. Criticism, of the Governments policy has been left too duch to those who are violently opposed to it.   There have *een but two views; one, which happens to be my own, that ft is sound and wise, the only policy which could be any-ihing but the initiation of a rfew cycle of horror; the other ;hat It is a cowardly surrender, an infamous betrayalsBut a good pollcyf may be ruined in the execution; The methods by whioh it is carried out are as crurially important as the policy itselfo   &quot;Of these there has prac-ttcally been no cr it idem; it has been assumed that the policy and the application are parts of a single and inevitable whole.   Hy suggestion is that the tragedy of Macroom and&apos; the&apos; many similar incidents show. clearly that, whatevei may, be thought of the policy, the methods &quot;by which it  jas been carried out have been wrong from the beginning.    The roere.. enurwoia-tion of the terms embodied in theTreaty/
Treaty, apart from all questions as to their execution, secured at once tactical advantages of the highest value. They would satisfy every reasonable Irishman and.rally every sane element in the country; they would divide the enemy, would present the British Government in the li^ht no longer of a tyrannical power ruling &quot;by force, hut as the merely interim custodian of law and order; Would make difficulty for the extremists, and make.infinitely easier the task of repressing crime.   It might have seemed the.most obvious course to maintain, or even tighten, the imperial grip till the new conditions could male - the;-:.selves felt; till it was clear that the terms were accepted by the country at large; and that a Government worthy of the name.could be formed.   It might have been months even years, before these results were fully consummated; but with time and patience they would have come, and&apos; the Government would have escaped the reproach of having abandoned their friends and of having handed over whole districts to anarchy.Those who, like myself, have welcomed and supported the Treaty, have never been able to understand why&quot; it was necessary that the British Government should begin handing ov$r almost before the ink was dry..   It was doubtful enough from the beginning whether&apos; a decent Government could be evolved at once out of the Iri3h chaos; and the lapse of a very few weeks showed clearly that it could not.   Yet the British withdrawal continued&apos; without interruption.There ma3r be an answer to these questions; I hope there is.    I can speak, I am sure, for the relatives of the other victims as well as for myself, when I say that the anguish we have suffered would have been infinitely less if we could have felt; thai it was necessary and inevitable.   &quot;When the fate of nations is at stake, no individual life - however infinitely promising, however ineffably sweet - can weigh in the balance; but we are entitled to claim that before such sacrifices are called for the necessity should be proved up to the hilt.I venture to suggest that the methods by which the policy of the Treaty have bee.-;       rif-d out, apart from the policy itself, should be definitely challenged in Parliament, and that the Government should be oallied on to prove its case.Is it too late to return to the safer and, as it will seem to many, the leas ignoble way ?    The present Lord Salisbury was once criticised for saying &quot;England grants alliances; she does not s ..- for them&quot;   The course of events since the Treaty suggests an almost grovelling attitude of supplication to Irishmen to accept one most generous terms ever offered by a great nation to a people &quot;struggling to be free*l!I am, &amp;o.s(Sgd,)   IToJhlU EESEY.Oxford,June 14th, 192Z.

</content>
</cab>
