<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/137/0 images: 621-624</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/Ifbls Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;a government).SE C R E T. C jF .4054CABINET.GAS   WARFARE.Copy No3Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I desire to take the decision of the Cabinet oh a question which arises between the Treasury and the War Office on the subject of Gas Warfare,Article 171 of the Treaty of Versailles prohibitsthe use of lethal gases.       It is as follows :-&quot;The use of asphyxiating, poisonous or other gases and all analogous liquids, materials or devices being prohibited, their manufacture and importation are strictly forbidden in Germany.&quot;The same applies to materials specially intended for the manufacture, storage and use of the said products or devices.&quot;In May 1920 the Cabinet decided, on the groundthat other nations were doing the same, that &quot;pending adefinite decision on the subject by the League of Nations,the fighting servioes should continue their researches airtdexperiments&quot; .As a result the Chemical Warfare Research Committee was appointed (or revived) and the Gas Experimental Station at Porton was created (or revived) as a post-war establishment.On a cost basis which includes the value of accommodation and of stores used for experiments the Chemical Warfare Committee is to-day costing us (1922-23 Estimates)  39,300 per annum (of which, however,  32,400 is for experiments, stores, accommodation and stationery) and the Porton Station is costing us  130,400 per annum (of which 77,350
 77,350 Is for stores, accomrodation, stationery, travelling and miscellaneous expenses).The I or ton staff Is regarded by the VJar office as fixed only on a provisional basis and the tendency Isstill to expand it.     Army Estimates contain a note thata reduction in stores Is partly counterbalanced by certain increases in staff found by experience necessary for the efficient working of the Station.Moreover, the Porton establishment is at presenthoused in huts and a large building programme is involved.Head V of Army Estimates (page 168, items 40 to 42) providesfor a total expenditure of  109,100 on married quarters and various technical buildings.     Of this expenditure only 23,400 has been incurred up to 31st March last.      67,400is taken for this year and  18,300 is left for future years.Probably these Estimates cannot be regarded as final.   Further,I understand that it Is certain that we shall have to buya large quantity of the adjoining land which is devastatedby the poison gas.     The commitments are therefore heavy and they are Increasing.So far as I am aware, no action on the general question has been taken by the League of Nations, but atWashington the signatory Powers pledged themselves to abstain from the use of gas warfare and to endeavour to persuadeother nations to do likewise.Article V. -&quot;The use in war of asphyxiating, poisonous or other gases, and all analogous liquids, materials or devices, having been justly condemned by the general opinion of the civilised world and a prohibition of such use having been declared inTreaties -
&quot;Treaties to which a minority of the civilised Powers are parties,The Signatory lowers, to the end that this prohibition shall be universally accepted as a part of international law binding alike the conscience and practice of nations, declare their assent to such prohibition, agree to be bound thereby as between themselves and invite all other civilised nations to adhere thereto&quot;.This binds the United States, Prance, Italy, Japan andthe British Empire.The lorton establishment is understood to be required for &quot;anti-gas&quot; or protective measures, and not for experiments for offensive use.     But, if there is no knowing what kind of gas at some future date might be employed, defensive experiment must involve a certain amount of offensive experiment, and it seems certain that so long as any Power maintains an experimental establishment for defensive purposes, no other lower could be persuaded that It was not at the same time making experiments for offensive purposes.     Consequently every Power, while professing a pious resolution to conform to the Washington agreement, will in fact be developing the invention of poison gases just as if no such agreement had ever been made.It is no doubt a serious thing to abstain, if there Is any real danger of the use of new poison gases in future, from taking all possible steps to protect the Forces of the Crown and the inhabitants of the country against gas attacks in times of war.   But in view of the conventions to which the British Empire has become a party, embracing as they do all the principal military lowers with the exception of the ex-enemy lowers and Russia, I feel most reluctant to sanction expenditure on a constantly developing service, without any limit of time, one effect of which to my mind must be to leadother
other Powers to continue experiments possibly not purely defensive.I think therefore that we ought at least to try to persuade all the Powers to shut down all their lethal gas researches and offer to do the same ourselves, even If we cannot yet venture to take independent action, and that In the meantime Forton ought not to be allowed to expand. Even if it Is now closed, there must have been accumulated from war experience and the costly experiments undertaken since the war, a large amount of knowledge, which would be available should we unhappily ever require It in future.R .S .H.TREASURY, S .W.22nd June, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
