<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/137/0 images: 779-783</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS^rXXTDMBNT IS THE PHOPEETI OP HTS^BRITANNIC MAJESTIES GOVERNMENT.CABINET.EMPLOYMENT OF SEVERELY DISABLED MEN.Note **y the Minister of Labour.On the 25th May, 1921, I circulated a Report and Summary of a Oommittee whioh, under the Chairmanship of the Parliamen-tary Secretary of the Ministry of Labour enquired into the above subject (CP. 2972).     A brief stamnary of the reoommenda-tions of the Report Is attached.Tho Report has not been published.     Sir John Davidson1s Select Committee on the Employment of Disabled Ex-Service men are now pressing that they may be supplied in confidence with copies of the report.     If copies are sent to them it will not bo possible to keep the recommendations socret and a decision is necessary as to whether oopies should be supplied and whether, if necessary, we should go further and publish the report.On 3rd June, 1921, the Chancellor of the Exchequer circulated a memorandum (CP. 3013) raising objection on financial grounds to the adoption of the recommendations in tho Report.The Cabinet never came to any general dooision as to the adoption of the recommendations;action has, however, been taken on lines recommended by the Report in the following cases :-(l).   For the year beginning June, 1921, a capitation grant at the rate of  25 por head for each severely disabled ex-Service man employed has been given to Lord/Roberts1
Roberts&apos; Memorial Work-shops.     The total amount of the grant so paid is about  6,000, for the first year. (2),     The Treasury have recently approved the giving of a Bimilar grant to Enham Village Centre whore about 20 men eligible for it are at present employed. (5).     The Treaeury have before them recommendations from the Ministry of Labour for granto to be given to the Guild of Sailor and Soldier Broderere,. London, employing about 60 men, and Ershine House, Glasgow, employing about  0 men.(4) .     The Ministry of Labour have one or two tentativ applications from other email institutions before them But it is important to notice that if the  25 grant is promised to the Broderers and to Erskine House, that will exhaust the list of existing institutions of any large size working on these lines;  consequently the financial liability of tho Government at any rate in the immediate future cannot be great even If the Report be accepted.(5).     A small amount of Government contract work has been given to the Lord Roberts&apos; Workshops. It will thus be seen that already considerable action has been taken on the lines recommended In the Report.     In my view, wo ought certainly to give copies to Sir John Davidson&apos;s Committee and If they press for publication I see no sufficient reason for refusing.     If the Committee&apos;3 recommendations were followed up, further expenditure by the State would only result from action being taken by other localities to provide institutions similar to Lord Roberts&apos; Workshops.     In the ordinary course private enterprise/would
would have to find tho Initial capital outlay and 5/6the of the running cost.   .&apos; There is very little prospect indeed at present of proposals on thoso lines developing,     Moreover, to refuse publication creates a foeling of mystery and aus-picion which is most undesirable.In view of the Select Committee&apos;a representations a deoision is very urgently required.(SIgnod)    T. J. MACNAMARA.3rd July, 1923.
SUMMARY.REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON THE EMPLOYMENT OF SEVERELY DISABLED EX-SERVICE MEN.(1).     Committee set up by the Minister of Labour on 22nd Septefflbor, 1920, under the Chairmanship of the Parliamentary Secretary, and consisting of representatives of the Ministry of Labour and Ministry of Pensions.(2).     Committee went Into matter with care and heard evidence. They estimated that the number of disabled ex-Service men who would never be aole to obtain employment in ordinary^ industry, even with considerate employers, was from 10,000 to 50,000, and that the maximum number for whom provision would ultimately have to be made would be from 20 ,000 to 25,000 , a total which could not, even under favour-able circumstances, be reached for a long time.(3).     Their chief recommendations were:-(1) the establishment in each county and borough of a General Committee of those Interested in Ex-Service men, including representatives of such bodies as the Local Employment and /far Pensions Committees and ex-t Service men&apos;s organisations.(2) The General Committee to set up a Classification Sub-Committee to survey the problem in the area and to discover definitely the number of men of the type contemplated in the area.(fc) The General Committee then to take steps to provide Institutions of the nature of Lord Roberts Workshops.(4) Initial expenses and any running losses to be borne by the locality, the assistance from the State being limited to/(a)
(a)   Government contracts;   and(b )   a capitation grant of not more than&apos; 25 per head.(5) Provision to be made for assessment of wages with some regard to the men&apos;s economic value.-     .      /

</content>
</cab>
