<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/137/0 images: 784-791</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT.PROPOSALS TO REDUCE INTERVALS BETWEEN PERIODS OP BENEFIT DURING 1922.MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF LABOUR.orot. 1.     A deputation representing Poor Law Authorities, and ii. including a number of Members of Parliament, urged unon theJ$4.        Prime Minister on 20th June, that the Government should give financial assistance tc the Poor Law Authorities.     The corn-plaint made by these Authorities was that the pressure on them has been accentuated by the provision In the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1922, that when persons have recoivod five weeks of uncovonanted benefit they are required to wait a period of five weeks before again becoming entitled to benefit.     The deputation stated that these &quot;gaps&quot; in benefit resulted in a very substantial increase in the burden on the Poor Law.     In reply to the deputation the Prime Minister undertook to con-sidor tho matter in conjunction with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.2,     The position has been discussed at a conference between the Chancellor, tho Minister of Health, tho Secretary for Scotland and mydelf, and the present Memorandum seto out generally tho conclusions at which wo have arrived,3.     The provision with regard to the &quot;gaps&quot; in benefit was deliberately inserted in an Unemployment Insurance Act passed as recently as last April .     That Act made a new grant of 15 weeks of uncovonanted benefit between April and November of this year, and 22 weeks between November next and July,
1923, and this follows on very large grants of uncovenanted benefit previously made -     The burden on the Poor L&amp;w has been correspondingly reduced.     The Poor Law Authorities now ask that benefit shall be paid continuously for everyiweek of unemployment.     In connection with this request, it may be observed that such evidence as Is availablo goes to show that, although there has boon an increase in the weekly amount of out-relief to able-bodied persons and their dependants, the increase between April and May was not more than about 6 per cent (or  16,000 a week).    The request now inad is quite contrary to the principles on which the Unemployment Insurance Scheme is based, and would be a most dangerous precedent for the future.     Moreover, the expedient of filling in the gaps Is unsatisfactory because it Involves paying additional benefit to all the unemployed in all areas, whereas the object is merely to assist the Guardians in necessitous areas to deal with the destitute unemployed. It appears that only one-fourth or ono-third of the persona drawing unemployment benefit are in receipt of out-relief, and the fraotion If limitod to out-relief in necessitous areas in comparison with benefit in the whole country is of course much smaller.4.     On account of the grave objections to any altera-tion in the Unemployment Insurance Scheme, the possibility of meeting the situation by some other means has been care-fully examined.     We have considered, for instance, whether it would be possible to reimburse the Poor Law Authorities in necessitous ar^as to the extent of the additional payments (not exceeding the weekly amount of benefit) which they might make to persons serving the gap.     Any such expedient,, however, necessarily involves a direct subsidy of Poor Law/expenditure
expenditure out of States-funds,,, and on this account ia regarded by the Minister of Health and the Secretary for Scotland as Inadmissible.     While the immediate cost would probably be much less than that entailed by a modification of the Inauranoe Scheme, the precedent thus set would, in their opinion, be enormously expensive to the Exchequer in the long run.5.     We were thus driven to the conclusion that theonly course is to modify the Unemployment Insurance Soheme,in spite of tho fact that it may prove a dangerous and costly precedent to grant benefit practically continuously.It is important not to abolish the gaps altogether, nor dowe think it necessary to dc so.     But we consider that thegaps should be reduced to one week instead of the presentfive weeks - that is, that the alternation should be five weeks&apos; benefit, one week gap, five weeks&apos; benefit, one weekgap and so on up to 2nd November,, when a new period ofbenefit begins .     As the majority of the unemployed persons concerned have now served their first gap of five weeks,and will not reach their second gap until 20th July, it isnot necessary * evon if, in. view of the need for legislation,it were possible - to bring the new arrangement into opera-tion before 20th July.     We do not think it necessary todeal with the position after 2nd November;   (though the stepsnow proposed will, if adopted, he no doubt urged as an.argument for further weeks of Benefit next year when theprovision already made is exhausted).     22 weeks of benefit is, however, already provided betweon November 2nd 1922,and July, 1923.The Government Actuary estimates that the additionalamount of benefit that will be paid under these proposals will be about  2,750,000.      If it were found necessary to. &apos; /deal
deal on similar lines with the position in the early part of next year, tho cost would be a further sum of  4,500,000-   6.     The rate of unemployment since last April, has been somewhat lower than was estimated and, in addition, the special conditions which I have imposed restricting the grants of uncovenanted benefit, e.g*, boys and girl3, and in the cases of single men and women, have resulted in a considerable saving.     The total saving as compared with tho estimate is sufficient, I am advised, to enable me to adopt the present proposals for the period up to November next without necessitating any increase in the weekly rate of contributions or in the borrowing powers. It should be borne in mind, however, that an increase in the amount of benefit paid involves a corresponding additloi to the dobt of the Unemployment Fund, and a consequent prolongation of the period during which tho present very high contributions must continue.The proposals mean that the debt borrowed through the Treasury would be increased by  2,750,000 above what it would otherwise be, that the Treasury would bear about one-fourth of this sum (with interest) as a final charge, and that the prospect of the Treasury being repaid the balance depends on the continuance of the present high contributions for as long as 1b necessary for this purpose.7.     Legislation will be necessary in order to give effect to these proposals, and the draft of a Bill for this purpose, is attached.     As tho new proposals are to take effect as from 20th July, tho matter is clearly one of great urgency and I. ask for authority to introduce the Bill and to carry it into law immediately.(3 i gn ed)    T.J. MACNAMARA.&apos;--iittistry of Labour. 5th July, 192!?.
[12 &amp; 13 Geo. 5.]   Unemployment Insurance. 1D R A F TOE AB I JL , LTOAmend section four of the Unemployment In- a.d. 1922. surance Act, 1922, so far as relates to the third special period mentioned in that Act.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows: 1. (1) The periods for which the Minister of Labour Amendments may, under section four of the Unemployment Insurance of s. 4 of Act, 1922, authorise a person to receive benefit during *2 &amp; ]s the third special period shall be periods not exceeding in   eo&apos; a&apos;e&apos; &apos; 10 the aggregate twenty-two weeks instead of periods not exceeding in the aggregate fifteen weeks.(2) The period during which a person who has at any time received benefit under the said section four in the third special period, for periods amounting in the 15 aggregate to five weeks is under subsection (2) of that section not to be qualified for the receipt of benefit, shall be reduced from five weeks to one week :Provided that where by virtue of the said subsection any person is at the commencement of this Act disqualified 20 for the receipt of benefit in the third special period, he shall continue to be so disqualified until the expiration of five weeks from the date on which he began to be so . disqualified, or the expiration of one week from the com-mencement of this Act, whichever first happens.166-2
Short title and repeal.A.D. 1922. (3) Notwithstanding anything in the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1921, or in this Act, no person shall, except as otherwise expressly provided by section four of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1922, as amended by this Act, be entitled to receive benefit in the 5 third or the fourth special period for periods amounting in the aggregate to more than fifteen weeks and eighteen weeks respectively.The provisions of this subsection shall have effect in substitution for the provisions of subsection (5) of section 10 four of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1922.2. (1) This Act maybe cited as the Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1922, and shall be construed as one with, and shall be included among the Acts which may be cited together as, the Unemployment Insurance 15 Acts, 1920 to 1922. .(2) This Act shall  come into  operation on  the twentieth day of July, nineteen hundred and twenty-two.

Uneniploy ment Insurance.DRAFTof ABILLTo amend section four of the Unem-ployment Insurance Act, 1922, so far as relates to the third special period mentioned in that Act.CXLVIL   (2.)6th July 1922.166-2

</content>
</cab>
