<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/137/0 images: 855-859</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ids document is the property of His Britannic Majesty*s Government).3.CABINET,HOME   AFFAIRS    COMMITTEE,DANGEROUS DRUGS ACT  (AMENDMENT) BILL,Memorandum by the Home Secretary,,I ask authority to introduce the attached Bill to strengthen the penalties under the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1920, and to make certain other amendments with a view to securing stricter enforcement of the Act.    There is a strong public demand for stringent measures to repress the nefarious traffic in cocaine and other dangerous drugs and the Bill will, I am sure, be entirely non-controversial,E.8th July,  1922,
[12 &amp; 13 Geo. 5.]   Dangerous Drugs (Amendment).     VD It A E Tof aB I L LTOAmend sections ten and thirteen of the Dangerous a.d. 1922.Drugs Act, 1920. &quot;BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 1. (1) The following subsection shall be inserted in Amendment, section ten of the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1920, after of s- 10 of subsection (1) thereof :- I0 &amp; rn ,r&quot; (Ia) If a justice of the peace is satisfied by infor-mation on oath that there is reasonable ground for suspecting that any drugs to which this Act applies are, in contravention of the provisions of this Act or any regulations made thereunder, in the possession or under the control of any person in any premises, he may grant a search warrant authorising any constable named in the warrant, at any time or times within one month from the date of the warrant, to enter, if need be by force, the premises named in the warrant, and to search the premises and any persons found therein, and, if there is reasonable ground for suspecting that an offence against this Act or any regula-tions has been committed in relation to any such drugs which may be found in the premises or in the possession of any such persons, to seize or detain those drugs.&quot;165-3
2      Dangerous Drugs (Amendment):.   [12 &amp; 13 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1922. (2) In subsection (2) of the said section ten, for the words &quot; any such hooks or stocks &quot; there shall be substi-tuted the words &quot;any such books, stocks or drugs.&quot;Amendment 2. (1) Section thirteen of the Dangerous Drugs Act. 10 &amp; 11 1920 (which relates to offences and penalties), shall have 5 Geo. 5. c. 46. effect as if for the words &quot; shall be liable on summary &quot; conviction to a fine not exceeding two hundred pounds, or &quot; to imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term &quot; not exceeding six months, or to both such fine and &quot; imprisonment,&quot; there were substituted the words &quot; shall 10 &quot; be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding &quot; two hundred and fifty pounds, or to imprisonment with or &quot; without hard labour for a term not exceeding twelve &quot; months, or to both such fine and imprisonment.&quot;(2) It is hereby declared that, notwithstanding any- 15 4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5. thing in section eighteen of the Criminal Justice Admini- -e. 58. stration Act, 1914, or in any other enactment, any termof imprisonment imposed under section thirteen of the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1920, whether as originally enacted or as amended by this Act, on any person by a court of 20 summary jurisdiction in respect of the non-payment of a fine for an offence against that Act may he ordered to commence at the expiration of any term of imprisonment imposed on that person for the same offence in addition to the fine. 25Short title. 3. This Act may be cited as the Dangerous Drugs(Amendment) Act, 1922.

Dangerous Drugs (Amendment).D 11 A W TOF A .BILLTo amend sections ten and thirteen of the Dangerous Drilgs Act, 1920.OXLVI.&apos;   (3.)8th July 1922.I 05-3

</content>
</cab>
