<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/53/0 images: 54-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
In kit Memorandum of 14th May, Mr. Protkero refers specially to twopoints as illustrating the unsatisfactory relationsof the Ministry of Food and the Agricultural Departments, namely tke appointment by the fermsr ef a 1 Permanent Agricultural Advisory Committee1 and the Control of Fish Distribution,as to the eeoond of these, it will. I nope, be sufficient for me to say thati as the result of a conference between the officials concerned on Mfyl6 and 16 (Us, just afjber the date of Mr. Prothere&apos;s Memorandum and before It was known to the Ministry of Food) complete agreement has been reached as to immediate action, and arrangements hate been made whloh should secure full oo-operetion In future,   I am sure that nothing but an unfortunate series of genuine     ml sunder^ standing! prevented m earlier sgr*S!Bentt   X may perhaps add. as Mr, Prothere specially  refers to the future of the fishing industry, that tfcw Ministry of Re eons truo tion, as well as the English and Soott-lsh Fishery Departments, was represented in the recent conferences.As to the first point, the eons tl tut Ion of a strong Agricultural Advisory Committee at the Ministry of Food should at least be taken as svidenoe of my desire to consider fully the just olaims of the agricultural community hvfore taking action whloh may effect them. The appointment of this Committee was. indeed, the result of Mr. Frothere&apos;a own suggestion to me that I should get into closer touch with producers,   It was not Intended in any way to affect the position of the Agricultural Departments as the regular official advisers of HoM,Government on all matters relating to agricultural production or to supersede full consultation between the Ministry of Food and those Departments,   If the procedure now available for securing this consul-tat Ion is not satisfactory. I shall be most ready to consider any practical alternative.v,,      MINISTRY OF POOD AHD BOARD OF AGRICULTURE.!tlH   .........................................MEMORANDUM Bi THE POOD CONTROLLER.
I cannot, indeed, regard as a practical alternative the establishment of three separate departments to deal with food supplies.   For reasons which have been sot out at length in memoranda sent to Mr, fesesfeta Chamberlain, it is impossible of foe-tire ly to separate supply from distribution, particularly in respect of home produce.   The bringing of home produce under control and the  distribution thereof are parts of one eontin-uoua process, requiring to be undertaken through the same decentralised trade machinery.   It is impossible to say in regard to home grown meat or milk or potatoes or butter or wheat, where 1 supply1 ends and distribution1 begins.   Any attempt to put these into two separate departments would simply lead to chaos, It is not, however, necessary for me to develop the case against a new Ministry of Supply, in view of the second paragraph of Mr, &amp;ts4 n Chamberlain^ report of the 15th May (G,T.4559) In which he states, that he is unable to recommend the setting up of such an organisation,I agree, however, with Mr, Prothero both in looking /oncard to a further control of home produce as inevitable and In desiring that this control should be exercised with due regard to the interests of the agricultural community, and after the fullest consultation with the Agricultural Departments *I may, indeed, point out that in the case of potatoes oontrol has been introduced mainly in the interests of the producers. The purchase of the 1918 crop was decided on after exhaustive discussions and with the full consent of the representatives of all the departments concerned, as the one effeotlve way of guaranteeing to the producer both his minimum price and his market. The success of that agreed policy in stimulating production ie sufficiently attested by the remarkable increase in the potatoacreage/
acreage that has been secured.   After the Immense development from 1916 to 1917, to have added In 1918 another 25$ to the high figures for 1917, is a striking testimony alike to the judgment of the departments which Jointly framed the scheme and to the &apos; energy of the agricultural community.In the case of meat and milk, control is required in the interests of consumers, that is to say, of the whole urban population.    There is actual shortage of meat, and there is reason to anticipate a future shortage of milk, as the inevitable result of the scarcity of feeding stuffs,wart of labour, and other considerations.In the case of fish, I hope it may prove possible to avoidany complete control, toAs/the method of consultation between the Ministry of Pood and the Agricultural Departments, the most appropriate machinery appears to lie In the establishment of a standing Joint committee of all these Departments, consisting of some of the principal permanent officials in each case,   Various committees of this type do, indeed, already exist,   Ons deals with potatoes and other vegetables, and another has just been established for fish,   Thers is a Joint Orders Committee which considers regulations affecting livestock, feeding stuffs, milk and milk products, as weli as other questions of agricultural policy.   Continual consultation takes place on questions affecting cereals^ fruit, and other agricultural products,Xt is possible that the time has come for uniting these various committees into a single joint committee for all agricultural questions, with standing sub-committees for dealing with particular elasses of produce.   If Mr, Frothsre desires such a course, X shall be most happy to agree to it.This Committee of officials should consider all important points of agricultural policy, including both the policy of the Agricultural Departments in respect of food production and the policy of the Ministry of Food in respect of the control of home produce.This/
****Tills suggestion is, I think, in accord with the spirit of Mr. Prothero^ own proposal in the last paragraph but one ef his memorandum; .   The deliberations of the Joint Committee should, however, as a rule precede and not follow (as suggested by Mrs Prothere) personal discussions between the heads tf the Departments,   Moreover, if the Committee is to be ef value a very large measure of responsibility mast be allowed to its members. The representatives of the various departments on the Committee met be authorised to commit their respective departments on points of minor importance, and must be eo far in the confidence of the heads ef their departments that any agreement reached by the Committee, even on points of major ijnportance, is likely to secure the assent of the respective heads.There remains the question of the Agricultural Advisory Committe I understand Mr* Prothero to be of opinion that any Committee of outside agricultural representatives should either be attached to his department (rather than to the Ministry of Food) or hi a single Committee for all Departments,   I have no objection to the latter course *   All that I desire is that I and the officials of the Ministry of Pood should be able to get into direct ttuoh with th* agricultural community and they with me, through a body of advisers which can be taken to represent all important agricultural interests. I am quite prepared If Mr, Prothero wishes it to combine my Committee with the Committee already established by him, if this can be done without producing an altogether unwieldy body, or I will agree to any other practical method ef constructing a Joint Advisory Committee whioh might be called together by either Department (according as the subjects &quot;for discussion affected mainly production or control and distribution) and all of those meetings would be equally open to representatives of all the departments.
I should add that I have refrained from dealing in this Memorandum with the detailed criticisms made by Mr. Prothero, particularly in respect of special articles such as meat, bacon, onions and feeding stuffs.   If necessary, I am of course prepared to deal with them and I am satisfied that there is no just ground of complaint against lay Department, or foundation for the charge that I have unduly favoured traders or harassed producers.   I prefer, however, if possible, to lay the basis of a permanent good understanding in future, rather than to discuss past misunderstandings,RHONDDA,MINISTRY OP POOD. 29th May, 1918,

</content>
</cab>
