<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/53/0 images: 71-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
isV/AR^ CABINET. PRISONERS OP WAfi. &apos; -Iffil^RANDUM BY THE ARMY COUNCILThe Army Council view with alarm the present tendency of public opinion, as voiced by certain sections of the Press,in regard to the attitude adopted towards British soldiers who have become prisoners of war.     In the opinion of^ho Army Council the attitude that should be adopted towards those offioers and men who are captured by the enemy varies in accordance with the class into which prisoners fall, viz:*.(a) Wounded, or(b) Unwounded.Officers and men who are wounded and.incapacitated, and thus fall into the hands of an enemy, can rightfully claim the sympathy of their comrades and the Hatioxu     But when an officer or man who is unwounded and in -full possession of his physical powers falls into the hands of the enemy, it is necessary that such prisoners of war should be able to justify their act of surrender, which, without justification is, if not a military crime, a lapse from the high standard of the past which has enabled the British Army to assist in building up the Empire.In the South African war an idea became prevalent that officers and men were justified in surrending in order to save unnecessary waste of life, and on more than one occasion a Victoria Cross was awarded to an officer who chose the clear path of duty and came off victorious rather than accept this false idea.During the present war a large number of surrenders have I taken place which, if evidence could be producewould be found to have been without any justification^ and records exist indicating that when those concerned are released, drastic steps should be taken to deal with them for their behaviour.The recent exchange of prisoners while the war is in progress and the oampaign lately undertaken by the press of this country, in orde? to influence the nation to look upon prisoners of war indiscriminately as objects of sympathy, and indeed almost as heroes, will in the opinion of the Army Council . go far towards undermining the fighting discipline of the Army*The Council, hold that while soldiers who are captured owing to their be ing incapacitated by wounds are deserving Of the most sympathetic treatment on their release, those officers and men who surrender while unwounded should be looked upon ae having failed to carry out their duty as soldiers to the fulXj and to have fallen short of the example set by their comrades in days gone by and during the present war, who did their duty to the last.MILKER *31stISay,, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
