<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/53/0 images: 137-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JoloM W. Bally UuiTelegrams-&quot;SHIPMJNDER, VIC, LONDON.&quot;Any further communication on this subjoot should bo addressed to-Tlio Secretary,Ministry oJ: Shipping,St, Jamcs&apos;8 Park,London, S.W. 1,and the following number quoted:-MINISTRY  OF  SHIPPING&quot;123rd June, 1918.&apos;   Sir,In continuation of my letter of the 25th May, I am directed by the Shipping Controller to report, for the information of the War Cabinet, as follows:-.   CONVOYS.(a) Homeward bound Convoys.    Since the last report 12 convoys consisting of 157 ships (1,247,800 tons deadweight) have arrived.There was one casualty by enemy action.   The H.M.S. &quot;MOLDAVIA&quot; was torpedoed and sunk in the English Channel off Brighton on the 23rd May.    There were no casualties by marine peril.    There are how on passage home 24 convoys consisting of 366 ships.(b) Outward bound Convoys.   Since the last report 5 convoys consisting of 100 ships (698,300 tons deadweight) have been escorted through the danger zone.There was one casualty.   The s/s &quot;RATHLIN HEAD&quot; was torpedoed after being detached from the Convoy, but was able to return to Berehaven.    There are now in the danger zone 7 convoys, consisting of 113 ships.Two statements are attached showing (a) the number of convoys and tonnage convoyed up to the 25th May, 1918, and (b) the percentage of steamers gross registered tonnage and deadweight capacity sunk on the different routes. .   FINANCE.During the week ended the 25th May, the sum of  1,046,000was paid in compensation for loss of requisitioned ships, makinga total of  9,396,608 paid on this account since the 1st April,1918.HE SECRETARY, 3./WAR CABINET.
3. LOSSES ASP SAINS OF BRITISH TOHHASEThe losses of British steamers of 500 gross tons and upwards during the week ended the 25th May were as follows Lost by enemy action 4 ships of 9811 gross tonsM      11  marine peril 3   &quot; 11,609   &quot;Re-transferred to Foreign Flag 1 ship of     67$   &quot;ii nmaking a total of8 ships of 22,098 gross tons...The gains during the-week were as follows:-New vessels (British built) brought into service2 ships of 5467 gross tonsNew;-ve-ssols :.purchasod--Overeeas1 ship of   2053it      itTotal      3 ships of 7520ii      timaking a net loss of 5 ships of 14,578 gross tons.In addition one ship of 2269 tons was transferred from Foreign Flag, This, while representing additional tonnage under the British flag, is not additional tonnage available for servica^&quot; as the vessel now transferred was already engaged in the service of the Allies,The tonnage Casualties reported during the month of May were as follows:-British Ships, British*Allledand Neutral ships273,158 gross tons,5^,911 gross tons,136,658 gross tons,936,932 gross -tons,Lost by enemy actionii     tiMarine perilDamaged by enemy actionti     iiMarine peril189,488 28,989 104,083 398,432Total casualties720,992 1,406,659 gross ._ tonsCOAL.POSITION,Special memoranda have been put before the War Cabinet regarding the present supply of ooal available for export. Theposition/
position for the last few weeks has been Bteadily getting worse, and we are now faced with the practical certainty of the Italian ooal programme&apos;realising only 450,000 tons instead of 600,000 tone and of the French Supplies being down by 15$, . STORES FOR THE BRITISH ARMY IN FRANCEIn the week ending 25th May, 182,810 tons of Military Stores were discharged in France., EXCHANGE OF BRITISH AND GERMAN PRISONERS OF WAR.The prisoners of war vessels arrived back at Boston on the 26th instant and sailed on the 28th.   No British prisoners were brought back.   The following German prisoners were embarked:-635 military 17 civilians REMOVAL OF ENEMY ALIENS FROM CHINA.With reference to paragraphs 10 and 8 of my letters of the 9th and 23rd February respectively on this subject, the Japanese are providing two vessels and the Admiralty one vessel to convey as many as possible-of these aliens from China to Australia. CONVEYANCE OF CZECHO SLEVAK TROOPS FROM VLADIVOSTOCK.In accordance with the conclusion of the Anglo-French Conference of May 28th, arrangements are now being made by this Department to provide shipping tonnage for the conveyance from Vladivostock to Vancouver of about 5,000 Czecho Slevak troops.I em, Sir,Your obedient Servant, (Signed)   JOHN ANDERSON.
A.CONVOY REPORT 25th HAY 1918.STATEMENT SHOWING NUMBER OP CONVOYS AND TONNAGE CONVOYED TO 25th MAY 1918.HOMEY/ARDDirectionShips :Halifax 275 Sydney 761New York 1,091 Halifax Chan. 5 Norfolk I 986 Sierra Leone 248 Dakar 372Gibraltar 1114 Medmthro&apos; 162 Rio de Jan.   62BayTOTAL16Falmouth Dovonport Milford Queers town Lorn i ash Liverpoolsp, Liverpool Mednrthro1TOTAL463 1,038 1,652 209 69418 83214?Homeward OutwardTOTAL5,090 4,299GrossRegistered Tons3,541,955 3,605,674 6,605,358 45,592 4,709,911 1,774,972 1,590,055 3,499,042 1,016,542 337,263 85,44126,611,805Deadweight^ Capacity   iSinkingsHo2,065, 5,466, 0,440,55, 7,141, 1,979, 2,372v 5,600, 1,418, 413, 127,500 400 700 500 600 500 500 700 700 ICO 50036,061,700Porcentage of lossesOUTWARD1,619,069 6,114,904 6,087,988 954,503 3,926,877227,686 708,115 908,51520,547&apos;6572,565,550 8,428,500 9^,634,400 1,455,150 5,457,100167,000 768,800 1,280,90029,736,400Percentage.of lossesHOMEWARD AND OUTWARD26,611,805 j 36,881,700 20,547,657    i 29,736,4009,389Jfmpi Km ****47,159, 46266,618,100Percentage of losses3 813 114 3 421 7 2761.473 4 527,6276 27Deadweight Copacity23,800 63,700115,300 800 95,700 21,100 23,900110,800 60,400 10,400525,9001.4120,800 29,000 34,-90074,1001 j 8,000 5   !  50,200217,000,73525,900 217,000103   i 742,9001.091.1
B.CONVOY REPORT 25th MAY 1918.PERCENTAGE. OF STEAMERa, CROSS REGISTERED TONNAGE, AND DEAD WEIGHT CAPACITY SUNK ON THE DIFFERENT ROUTESHOMEWARDI Ships!_________.....Direction joon-jvoyed jShipsSINKINGSHalifaxSydney273 761New York 1,091 Halifax Ch, 5 Norfolk , 986 Sierra Leone Dakar Gibraltar1 Meda.thro1248 372 1,114 162Rio Bayde Jan,62 16TOTALFalmouth Devonport463 1,038Milford 1,652 Queenstown 209 Lemlash 694 Liverpool sp,&apos;l8 Liverpool 85 Medruthro1   142TOTAL4,299Homeward Outward&apos;TOTAL3047627103&quot;12GrossRegistered Tons&quot;41,375 39,039 78,822 9,500 60,52919,739 15,430 67,295 41,611 6,737380,077. /     I      %Deadweight   Ships   GrossCapacity23,800 63,700 115,300 800 95.70021,100 23,900 110,800 60,400 10,400525,90012,919 17,666 20,91455,046tm6?515 36,766149,826OUTWARD20,800 29,000 34,90074,1008,000 50,200217,000Registered TonsHOMEWARD AND OUTWARD380,077 149, 86529.903525,900 217,000742,9001*47 .621.091.22 1.07 1.18 17,25 1*271*1 .911,89 3,93 2.. 011.48.79 .29 .34mm1,38.913,&apos;97.721.48 .721.11MEDITERRANEAN HOMEWARD AND OUTWARD78,377110,6003,85*95-%-Dead ^weightCapacity.82 1.151 3 211.42 1,321.05 .99 1.94 4.08 2.461.41.80 ,34 ,36Ml1,341,033,85.731.41 .731.13.98

</content>
</cab>
