<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/53/0 images: 179-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/V   /       /?  ff\l &apos; I1I THIS DOOUKTO IB THE PROPERTY Qii1 HIS BKIMMg IiAJEbTY&apos;S SOVgBMgJ&apos;)! SECRET.f WAR     CABIN a T.G,T,- 4747,    , R JjSP0gg ggl TONCE AND ITALY,Copy of ffl^te from Secretary. British Section, Supremo &quot;1^r^^&apos;,unoIll^T^or^gQorexary&apos;, War dafrinoT.(Soo also Joint Noto No, 22, and G.T. 4345),No,, 18/A/l,The Secretary, War Cabinet,3With reference to Minute No, 9, War Cabinet 399, dated 25th April, 1918, and in continuation of telegram No,EL.456, dated 29th May, 1918 (copy below), I forward herewith copies of two letters dated 11th April and 29th May, respectively, from the British Representative, Inter-Allied Transportation Council,Would you kindly inform me what action may have been taken to carry out the recommendations contained in Joint Note Ho,EE of the Military Representatives of the Supreme War Council,(Signed). A,M,CACCIA,Major, for Secretary British Section, Supreme War Council,Versailles........ ^une^Sndy 1918,iParaphrase of telegram from Secretary, British Section, Supreme       ^Council,to. Secretary, War Cabinet.Despatched 9,45 p.m, 29,.5.18, Received     8,a,m,        30,5,18,No,.....33. L. 456.A reply is requested by telegram as to whethor the re com-mendatlons contained in Joint Note No,22, which have been aocep. ted by the three other oountries represented at the last Meeting of the Supreme War Oouncil, have also received tho approval of the British Government.   General Nash is of opinion that immediate steps should be taken to give effect to its recommendations,, but he cannot act until they are accepted by British Government,
Tho Secretary,British Section,Supreme War Council.See Joint In connection with the report 1/4,dated loth inst, onote No.82,   transport facilities for troops between France and Italy, anox: 1.       submitted in reply to Joint Questionnaire No.l datod torch  71$, 1918, I wish to draw the attention of the British Military-, Representative to tho fallowing important matter.The scheme submitted by the Inter-Allied transportation Council is merely a study, and cannot he, put into effect with-out considerable preparation.    An examination of the measures which it will be necessary to adopt should be made by the Au-thorities responsible, executively, for the carrying out of the move.    Such preparations involve:-Organisation for the use of the march and rail routes, including the provisioning of entraining and detrains ing points, the clearing of the roads of snow, the provision of motor transport, etc.The selection of entraining areas in France and detraining areas in Italy.    The latter is likely to be the most difficult, due to tho restricted railway facilities of that nature, and on that account should receive early consideration.The collection of rolling stock both in France and Italy.The strengthening of the establishment of tho Assistant Director General of Transportation in Italy, if British troops are involved. -The allotment of tonnage if tftop movements by sea from France to Italy are utilised.In regard to (a), the French Array have good experience of what is required, and I believe I aa correct in saying that the British Army have no organisation complete for this purpose.In (b) the important matters would require to be considered by G.H.Q. Is&amp;fft and G.H.Q. Italy.In regard to (e), the ^uatriome Bureau, Paris and the Director of Transports of the Italian Army at BOLOGNA are concerned.As regards fd), the Director General of Movements and Railways at the War Office would require to make arrangements for additional staff.    When tho troop movement towards Italy was carried out last October I was able, as Director General of Transportation, Prance, to assist by providing staff for Italy, but I feel certain that this cannot be defended upon again*In rogard to (e), the Director of Movements at the War Office should make his preparations in advance with the Controller of Shipping.(Sd). F.A.M. NASE. M.G.British Representative,, mtar-Allied Transportation Councils(a) fb)fc] (dl(ej[r sal lies, 1th April, 19* t
british section,supremo far council. ...&quot; &apos;l. * 1  1      i inni in    ii i   111 . i l . ^i &quot;beg to refer to my minute t/4 dated 11th april, 1918,ain connection with the transport of troops between prance and it in which i drew the attention of the british military bepresentatl to the necessity of an examination being made of the measures whig it would be necessary to adopt to enable a troop movement of any! size between france and italy to be carried out.     I beg to enqui] whether preparations have been made for the strengthening of the establishment of the assistant director general of transportation at the headquarters of the british expeditionary force, italy, in the event of such a troop movement as that under reference taking place.     i would also enquire whether preliminary arrangements k been made, as between the war office and the ministry of shipping for the allotment of tonnage to enable the transport of troops sea from marseilles to italian ports to be carried out if requirthe permanent military representatives on the supreme far council, in their &quot;collective note no.22&quot;, recommended(i) that a stock of ooal of approximately 150,000 tons should be accumulated in italy,(ii)that stocks of supplier for the use of the franco-british army in italy and the allied armies of the east should be arranged in advance. -these two measures are essential if an intensive trio op movement by rail from france to italy, or vice versa, is to be carried ouiji beg that i. may be permitted to know if the necessary arrangements have been made.(Sgd) P.A.M. Mailversailles. major general29th may, 1918. british bepres^ntati* . inter^aliied transportation ooun

</content>
</cab>
