<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/53/0 images: 246-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
biis document Is the property of His Britannic MajestyTs Government)SECRETARMY DEMOBILISATION. Memorandum by the Minister of Rec onstruction. (1) On November 15th the Y&apos;ar Cabinet approved the general principles laid down in the Second Interin Report of the Amy Demobilisation C omit tee, but referred back for further consideration by the Ministry of Reconstruction,(a) the scale of unemployment &quot;benefit to be paid to soldiers after demobilisation,(b) the recognition of a statutory right to employment./-s to (b.) the ratter is still under consideration by iir. Roberts and. myself.(2) Cut - of  7 ork D onat 1 on. So far as uner.pl oyment benef it (or-&apos;out-of-uo*,k donation) is- concerned,, there wore, two questions to be considered:-(a) tho class of men to be included in the scheme(b) the scale of payment.-,(5) SgEpe of tho Scheme, I suggest that the following should be eligible for out-of-work donation.(a) all those in the army at the end of the war,(b) all those discharged before the end of the war who have served overseas,(c) all those belonging to the Colonial contingonts paid and maintained from Imperial Funds who arc resident in the&apos;United Kingdom duringthe period when out-of-work.donation scheme Is in operation,(4)   Tho scale of Payment, There can be little doubt   .that the public will desire generous treatment for discharged9soldiers who happen during the transition period, to fall out-of-work,   Further it is pretty certain that prices will/remain
fairly high during tho time the scheme Is operative,   It is to be remembered also that payment of out-of-work donation will be made only during the year following a man&apos;s discharge and moreover that there is every prospect of a strong demand for labour during this time.(5) The scheme which is proposed is based on the prin-ciple that tho payment made to a man should bear some relation to his obligations,-&apos; The flat rate has therefore been abandoned, and a scale agreed upon, between the War Office, the ministry of Labour, and the Ministry of Reconstruction varying with the number of children under 14 years of age. Thi scale is as follows:-Plat rate 15/- per week.Supplementary rate      7/6 per week for one child,1/6. per week Tor eachadditional child under tho age of fourteen,I soldier who was a single man. or a widower or marriedman without children under 14 would receive 15/- a weekr-Aman with one child would receive 22/6 a week, with twochildren 24-/- aer week, with three children 25/6 per week,   -and so on.(6) Out-of-work Donation w,ill be paid for not more than an aggregate of 20 weeks during the year following discharge.   If it were found necessary to raise tho flat rate, adjustments would have to bo made in the- supplementary allowances- for children, but not on tho same scale,(7) The conditions attaching to the receipt of the out-of-work Donation would be those which operate in respect of the payment of Unemployment Benefit under Part II of tho National Insurance Act,(8) I shall be glad to receive the approval of the &quot;rar Cabinet to these proposals,C, ADDISOxT. 3 Juno 1918.

</content>
</cab>
