<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/160/0 images: 87-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Referred to Committee of Home Affairs(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)ICRET-\F.2l 1 (23).CABINET. COMMITTEE    OE   HOME   AEEAIRS.EDUCATION BILL.Note by the Secretary for Scotland on the Clauses which affect Scotland,Clause 1(1)  (d) and (2),These subsections simply apply to Scotland the pro-visions raising the lower limit for compulsory attendance from five to six.Whatever opposition there may be to this clause fix.;., probably be on the ground that the youngest children in poor districts are better in school, and that the parents of these children are of a careless class for whom the existing com-pulsion is desirable.Clause 9.As the School Sites Act, 1841, applies to Scotland, it is thought better that Clause 9&apos; should also be brought into line.Clause 10.The Scottish Education Department attach great importance to this clause as in Scotland the Reformatory and Industrial Schools are now under their supervision.     The Committee on National Expenditure and the subsequent Cabinet Committee recommended the closing of a number of the schools. The Department&apos;s advice has been accepted in the majority ofcases/
cases, but the Managers of one or two well-conducted schools insist on their being continued, although they cannot be regarded as necessary any longer.     This provision would enable the Department to take further action in such cases. -Clause 11.The Committee on National Expenditure recommended Strongly that fees for secondary education should be exacted from.parents able to pay them.Subsection (1) will remove doubts which at present exist as to the extent to which free secondary education may be claimed.     The existing Statutes will still make it necessary for Education Authorities to provide properly for children whose parents could not otherwise afford to find higher education for them.     This amendment must be regarded as con-controversial, as it will be represented as a limitation.of educational provision now possible.Subsection (2).   Under the operation of the Education (Scotland) Act, 1918, practically all Voluntary Schools in Scotland have been transferred to the Education Authorities, As a safeguard to the former Managers, provision was made that the Schools should be carried on as before the passing of the Act for ten years.   &apos; Several cases have, however, occurred in which, the former Managers were agreed that a School should be closed, and the nev; provision simply allows of this being done where all parties are agreed.   It is not expected that there will be any opposition to this change.Subsection (5).   At present Education Authorities are required to meet once a month, except that not more than one meeting need be held between the end of June and beginning of October.     Several of the Authorities are of opinion that less frequent/
frequent meetings are now necessary,  and this subsection will give them greater liberty.     As all travelling expenses and &apos; subsistence allowances are made from the funds of the Authority it is expected that considerable economies will also be effected.Subsection (4).    It has been found that the repeal of certain words relating to the provision for physically or mentally defective children effected in the Education (Scot-land) Act, 1918, allowed greater power to Education Authorities than was intended.     This subsection will reimpose the necessary limitation, and it is not expected to be controversial.Subsection (5). The Education (Scotland) Act,  1908, gave School Boards - now superseded by Education Authorities -certain powers of feeding necessitous children.     No serious difficulty arose until the Emergency Provisions Act, 1921, was passed, which extended the powers of Scottish Parish Councils in respect of relief to able-bodied persons.     Acting on the advice of the Scottish Law Officers, and in consultation with the Scottish Board of Health, a Circular was issued to Education Authorities intimating that their responsibility did not&apos; extend to the children of persons in receipt of relief of any kind, from a Parish Council.     As the matter rests at present simply on the Opinion of the Law Officers, it is thought desirable to remove doubt by this Subsection,   It is possible that opposition may be found from quarters that are anxious to exclude the parish Councils, as far as possible, from dealing with school children.(Sgd.)   NOVAE.\Scottish Office, Whitehall.25th April, 192?..

</content>
</cab>
