<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/160/0 images: 313-320</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
g DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 01? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CABINET-AGRICULTURAL RATES BILL.Note by the Minister of Health.The attached Draft Bill is circulated for consideration at the Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 11,30 a.m. today.(Intd.)        N. 0.Ministry of Health, 15th May, 1923.
Agricultural Slates.ARRANGEMENT OP CLAUSES.Clause:1.   Further exemption of agricultural land from rates. 2.   Additional deficiency grant.3.   Computation of amount of additional annual grant and of shares of spending authorities.4.   Amendments as to rates to which the principal Act does not apply.5.   Application of certain provisions of principal Act.6.   Principal Act made permanent.7.   Adjustment of excess payment of rates.8.   Short title and duration.Schedule. &apos;   &apos;105-2
[13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]   Agricultural Bates.iDRAFTof aBILLtoAmend the law with respect to the rating of a.d. 1923.occupiers of agricultural land, and for purposes   connected therewith.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, arid Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows: 1. During the continuance of this Act, section one Further of the Agricultural Rates Act, 1896 (hereinafter in this, exemption Act referred to as &quot;the principal Act&quot;), which provides of agiicul-that an occupier of agricultural land shall be liable to jj&quot;^1 ^^j, 10 pay only one half of any rate to which that Act applies, 59 &amp; soviet, shah have effect as if for the references in that section to 0.16. &quot; one half&quot; there were substituted references to &quot; one quarter.&quot;2. (1) In respect of the deficiency which will arise Additional 15 by reason of the foregoing provisions of this Act in the deficiency produce of rates made by spending authorities, there Srant&apos; shall (a) be paid in respect of every year during whichthis Act continues in force to the Local Taxation 20 Account a sum (in this Act referred to as &quot; theadditional annual grant&quot;) of such an amount as is certified from time to time under the provisions of this Act; and(b) be issued from the Local Taxation. Account by 25 half-yearly payments to each spending authoritysuch sum as is certified in manner aforesaid to represent the share of that authority in the additional annual grant.105-2 A 2
2Agricultural Rates.   [13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1923.        (2) The additional annual grant shall be charged on        the Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof, and shall be issued thereout in such manner and at such times as the Treasury direct.Computa- 8. (1) For the purpose of the foregoing provisions tion of       of this Act the Minister of Health, shall from time to amount ot   ^me compute, as respects each spending authority, the annual^    deficiency which will arise by reason of the foregoing grant and of provisions of this Act in the produce of the rates made shares of     by that authority, and, subject as hereinafter provided, 10 spending     the amount of that deficiency shall be taken to be a sum authorities. equai to one half of the amount which would, if this Act had not passed, have been produced by those rates sp far as leviable in respect of agricultural land, and a sum equal to the total amounts of the deficiency so estimated 15 for all the spending authorities shall he the amount of the additional aannual grant:Provided that (a) in computing any such deficiency as aforesaid   , no account shall be taken of any highway rate 20 levied under paragraph (2) of section two hundred and sixteen of the Public Health 3&amp;&amp;39Vict, Act, 1875, in any part of an urban district -c- 55- unless a rate under that section was ^levied in&apos; &apos;   that part of the district before the commence- 25ment of this Act; and (&amp;) where since the commencement of the principal Act and before the commencement of this Act a rate to which section One of the principal Act applied has been consolidated 30 with a rate to which that section did not - apply, the amount of the deficiency in respect of the consolidated rate shaU be taken to be the difference between the sum which occupiers of agricultural land would have been liable 35 to pay in respect of that rate if this Act had not passed and the sum which those occupiers are liable to pay under the provisions of this ... Act.  .(2) The deficiency arising in the case of a spending 40 authority shall, as the Minister of Health may from time to time direct, be computed either in respect of the
[13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]   Agricultural Rales.3whole year or in respect of each half year, and. the A.!). 1923. Minister shall from time to time, as soon as may be after   the necessary computations have been made, certify the sums which represent the respective shares of the several 5 spending authorities in the additional annual grant and the aggregate amount to be paid to the Local Taxation Account in respect of the additional annual grant.4. (1) For&apos;the purpose of any enactment under Amend-which the occupier of land is liable, as compared with ments as to10 the occupier of buildings or other hereditaments, to be ra)*&apos;?s,to, assessed to or to pay any rate, being a rate to which pri^ci 3 j6 the principal Act as amended by this Act does not apply, Act does in the proportion only of one quarter or less than one not apply, quarter, the expression &quot;land&quot; shall during the con-15 tinuance of this Act, be deemed to include all land which is agricultural land within the meaning of the principal Act.(2) Notwithstanding the provisions of any other enactment, occupiers of agricultural land shall not during20 the continuance of this Aot, be liable, as compared with the occupiers of buildings or other hereditaments, to be assessed to or to j)ay any rate, being a rate to which the principal Act as amended by this Act does not apply, in the proportion of more than one quarter.25       5. The provisions of the principal Act set out in Application: the Schedule to this Act shall have effect for the purposes of certain of this Act as if they were herein re-enacted with the Provisions modifications specified in the second column of the said ^PUIlclPa -Schedule, and section three of the principal Act and the30 definition of &quot;rateable value &quot; in section nine of that Act shall during the continuance of this Act cease to have effect.[6. The principal Act is hereby made permanent, Principal and the words &quot; during the continuance of this Act &quot; Act made 35 wherever they occur in the principal Act are hereby permanent, repealed.]7. Where any person in the case of any rate first Adjustment made after the commencement of this Act has paid an of excess amount in excess of the amount which he was, having payment of 40 regard to the provisions of this Act, liable to pay, the rates&apos; amount of that excess shall be repaid either by means of an allowance from the amount of any subsequent rate payable in respect of the same hereditament or by such other means as may be prescribed.
4Agricultural Bales.   [13 &amp; 14 Geo- 5.]8. (1) This Act may be cited as the Agricultural Rates (Extension) Act, 1923.(2) This Act shall have effect as respects any rate made on or after the first day of April, nineteen hundred and twenty-three, and shall continue in&apos; force until the 5 [thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and twenty-five] and no longer.[(3) Nothing in this Act shall affect any rate levied on the owner of tithe rentcharge to which the Ecclesiastical Tithe Rentcharge (Rates) Act, 1920, applies.] , 1&apos;(4) This Act does not extend to Northern Ireland.schedule.Provisions of principal Act applied.Section 3 (contribu-tions from more than one parish).Subsections (4), (5) and (6) of section 4, (certifying of annual sums payable in re-spect of deficiency.)Suqsections (1) (3) and (4) of section 6 (pro-cedure for ascertain-ing deficiency and for separation of value of agricultural land from buildings and other heredita-ments).Modifications.The words *&apos; the sums issuable to them &quot;15 &quot; in respect of the said rate out of the &quot; Local Taxation Account under the &quot; principal Act and this Act&quot; shall be substituted for the words &quot; the sum &apos;&apos; issuable to them in respect of the said 20 &quot; rate on account of their share of the &quot; annual grant,&quot; and three-quarters of the rateable value of the agricultural land in the parish shall be substituted for one half of that rateable value.     25In subsection (5) the words &quot; or altera-tion in the valuation list&quot; shall be inserted after the word &quot; error,&quot; and in subsection (6) the word &quot; first&quot; shall be omitted.For paragraph (a) of subsection (1) there shall be substituted &quot; [a) by &quot; every spending authority in relation &quot; to the sums received or to be &quot; received by them, or their pre-&quot; predecessors or successors in respect of &quot; any rate to which the provisions &quot; of the principal Act apply,&quot; and in subsection (3) the words from &quot; enacted in this Act&quot; to the end of 40 the subsection shall be omitted.30
[13 &amp; 14&apos; Geo. 5.]  Agricultural Bates.&apos;5Provisions of principal Act applied.Modifications.A.D. 1923.Subsection    (2)    of section    7   (as  to 5    spending authorities).Section 8 (as to limit of rate or expendi-ture in case of any local, authority).10 Section 9 (Definitions)1520For the words &quot; this Act,&quot; in the second place where they occur, there shall be substituted the words &quot; the &quot; principal Act or this Act.&quot;The following shall be substituted for the definition of &quot;rateable value&quot;: &quot; The expression &apos; rateable value &apos; in &quot; the case of the county rate means &quot; the net annual value according to &quot; the basis or standard for the county &quot; rate, in the case of any other rate &quot; levied on a value based on any &quot; annual value, not being the rateable &quot; value as stated in the valuation &quot; list, means that annual value.&quot;Schedule     (Spending authorities).
Agricultural -Rates./DRAFTOF Ab   i   l   i,To amend the law with respect to the rating of occupiei-s of agricultural land, and for purposes connected therewith.CV.   (2.)Uth May .1923.105-2

</content>
</cab>
