<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/160/0 images: 364-374</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Majesty&apos;s 282Government.11 iB requested that this document he treated &quot;   &apos;       ae highly cpnf:ldanti a J,&quot;Sjijg g El &apos; Speoial Branch,Report No. SOS Hew Scotland Yard,B.W.1.Hay 17th, 1923.REPORT ON REVOLUTIONARY ORGANISATIONSIN THE UNITED KINGDOMTHE COMMUNISTS.............................,.?age 1RED INTERNATIONAL OP LABOUR UNIONS............ &quot; 5THE YOUNG COMMUNIST LEAGUE................... &quot; 7THE UNEMPLOYED.........-..V-................... &quot; 7THE COMINTERN AND THE COMMUNIST PARTY OFIRELAND................................. &quot; irish REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES IN GREATBRITAIN..................&apos;.............. &quot; 8SUMMARYOn May 7th the wholly unemployed on the live registers totalled approximately 1,203,000, a decrease of 14,467 on the preceding week:   on &quot;i,Le same date the number working short time and drawing benefit for intervals of unemployment was 55,200 as compared with 38,271 on April 30th.During the week extremists have displayed abnormal activity in their agitation against a breach of the Anglo-Russian Trade Agreement:   the &quot;v.ar&quot; bogey has been introduced on every possible occasion.   Protest meetings have, however, not been very successful from the point of view of attendance.A document reproduced in this report shows that the Communist International has given financial assistance to the Communist party of Ireland and that the Russian Trade Delegation in London is used for the transmission of correspondence which has no connection with trade matters.
Agitation against &quot;war -with Russia&quot; has been the dominating note in communist propaganda during the week and in several cases communists have shared platforms with speakers of the labour Party and the Independent Labour Party.     The Trafalgar Square Meeting was held under the auspices of the. Independent Labour Party,     $he speakers included John Scurr, The Rev, Campbell Stephen, M.P., the Rev. - langcion, J. Brotherton, LLP., Ben Smith, Skene McKay, J. I&amp;xton, 11.P., H* Wilson, M.P., W. Wright, M.P., Tom Griffiths, Mrs. Boyce, Duncan Carmichael,        ,  i - Friend, S. Saklatvala, M.P., C. Wilson, 11.2., E. Hunter, ?,. 0. Y/allhead, M.P., Mrs. Barton, RoSen Burton, M.P., and J. T. Walton Uowbold , M.P.Despite the fact that so many phases of the labour movement were represented by the above speakers the attendance was only about 5,500:   speeches were concerned for the most part with the danger of war with Russia and condemnation of the action and attitude of the British Government in regard to Russia.     Mr. Brothsrton, M.P., stated that in the event of war with Russia the dockers had decided not to handle munitions and Skene McKay said th in the event of a rupture of trade relations &quot;we expect at any rate that the organised workers in this country wil3 be prepared to come out on strike tin til such time as Lord Curzon and his permenent officials at the Foreign -Office are removed.&quot;She resolution passed is quoted below as It is typical of those adopted at meetings in various parts of the country:-&quot;Shis/
&quot;This meeting of London Citizens views with alarm the great danger to International peace caused by lord Curaon^s provocative note to the Russian Government.   We declare that any attempt to end the Trading Agreement or to embitter the relations between our country and Russia will meet with the strongest resistance of organised labour.   We affirm our belief that the difficulties existing between Great Britain and Prussia are inevitable so long as Great Britain refuses to adopt full and friendly diplomatic relations with, Russia.      We demand the withdrawal of the ultimatum in favour of a conference between the British ant Russian Governments to examine the charges made in the notes and oall; for the fall recognition of the Soviet Government and the adoption of a policy whioh aims at the peace and goodwill and the restoration of trade and work.&quot;The attendance at meetings held in Ion don trader the auspices of the Communist Party in the same connection onMay Igth was as follows:Provincial meetings have also been held hut according to thereports bo far received from Chief Constables the audiencesdid not average more than 200.The speeches made by communists were based upon the&quot;Outline&quot; issued hy the Communist Party of Great britain on May 9th which covered, inter alia, the following points:&quot;The Trading Agreements were concessions wrung . from the military defeat of intervention assisted by the mass agitations of the workers of this and other countries.   Always the Workers&apos; Government has had to fight its way in the teeth of tremendous opposition.   And this latest attack is a repetition and development of all these preceding struggles.&quot;The British Note.     The document itself is packed wifE&quot;Iies.   Its preamble about propaganda is&apos; a repetition easily disposed of as valueless from the standpoint of voracity as the statement about the Communist Party receiving  75,000.&quot;As a matter of fact the date mentioned by the Government as to when the decision was taken to allocate  I2t3p00 is very unfortunate for their state-merit.   November 25th is one of the Fourth Congress dates.   The Congress opens November 7th - December 3rd.   During this time&quot;there are no commissions of this character in existence,   with the opening of the Congress all .offices are vacant,   A special. Presidium is elected to conduct the proceedings of the Congress and only at the end of the Congress are new B..C. Officers elected.   No financialClapham Common Pirtsbury Park-Tic to ria Park200 S00 200commission/
&quot; 3 -285commission even met during this time. The whole statement is an absolute fabrication,,a palpable lie on the face of it.&quot;The note passing between the two Governments we quote in full and add. also a statement on the position.re trawlers.&quot;The significance of the Note.     The decisionto igoIaTe&apos;&quot;sus&apos;5&quot;3a&quot;Is&quot;anotner forward step on the part, of the universal capitalist offensive connected with the wholesale attack upon wages and hours of labour.   The wresting of &quot;privileges1 from the worksrs, and. the intensification of the working coufiituoas. .   eight from the coons a Cxnfa.rer.es through genoa and the hague, the vhu-e thame has been to re-establish private proper:1;;; in kunfiia and to make of her a colony for the capitalists of the went, to break off control of foreign trans by the russian workers&quot; government, to secure old debts contracted with the Czar-s Government.&quot;All these conferences and efforts coincide with the attacks on the workers of every other country and their efforts to place the whole burden of the war on the backs of the masses.&quot;The immediate effect of the breaking off relations will be to set loose every reactionary force in Europe.&quot;NOTE.   foch in Warsaw this week.&apos;&apos;I.T0TB.   General cesim.auder-in-chief of theBritish forces now in italy with the King and Mussolini is due in Warsaw on May 16 flu&quot;NOTE.   The pressure of Curzon at the Latisamie conference to gag Warships through the Dardanelles to the Black Sea.&quot;All these facts are indications of the meaning of the British Note.   It points to war.&quot;These things the workers cannot stand for,,&quot;the forces of class war are consolidating.   Cur z on congratulates mussolinii   . the sing bestows honours upon him.   fascism is triumphant.&quot;Only the united action of the masses can stop this reaction from making a graveyard of Europe.&quot;form Councils of Action.&quot;Got the All-in Conference of the Workers.&quot;Stand by the Trade Delegation.&quot;Demand/
&quot;Jtow&amp;ria iHcfc dilate aiafi unconditional recognition ofGl/fiet Il-liiiSiao&quot;Damand Peace Conference between Russia and Britain.&quot;Do\;;n with war on the workers republic.&quot; - Tory largo quantities of a leaflet issued by the Communist Party of Groat Britain and entitled &quot;Stand by the Workers1 Republic&quot; have been distributee! all over the country between 80,000 and 30,000 copies of this leaflet were at the premises of Arcos in Lincoln&apos;b Inn Fields at the beginning of this week.    The text of the leaflet follows the same lines as the manifesto quoted on Pages 5 and 6 of last week&apos;s report:   it declares that another world war is imminent, that &quot;the British Government to-day, in a fever of rage and terror, is sticking at no means to bring about thfe downfall of the Soviet Republic, whose very existence is a challenge to British sweating and murdering in Russia&quot;, demands Immediate and unconditional recognition of Russia, the formation of Councils of Action and an &quot;All-in Labour conference a correspondent, who is in close touch with King Street,comments as follows upon the opinions held there:&quot;In the inner circle of the Communist party it has been well-known for some time (through Russian sources of course) that though there is not the least-probability of the British Government going to war with Russia it is not impossible nor remote that trade relations with Russia might be broken off,   As a matter of fact it is said that ever since the coming into power of the Conservative Government this lias been feared,   &apos;2he last Government, they pay, wao always uncertain as to what it would do, vac-ja^ating as it always was between extreme loft and extreme right influences of the Liberals and Tories !,-y turns,&quot;Thos- Bell mentioned at a Party Training Group meet tog hold at Headquarters, at which I was present, that the Russian act against the British trawler at Murmansk was only coawitied to test tho attitude of the British Government and the temper of the British pe op la.&quot;Our/
&quot;Our policy i-3 to say that the British Government desires to declare war on Russia, ana through that fear of war, to save at least the Russian Trade arrangements, without which communication between us and Russia will became extremely difficult,&quot;In tho current issue of the &quot;Communist Review&quot;, WilliamPaul makes oertain comments in his &quot;Review of the Month&quot;,which are interesting in that they represent instructedcommunist opinion on the position of the party:&quot;The alarming results of the determination of MacDonaia and Thomas to split the labour movement in this country may be seen in the tremendous struggle that is going on within the labour Party at the present moment.   Because the Communists are active ana oourageous in the worktops, they are elected by their mates to represent them in the local Labour parties-in the mine, the railroad, the factory, and the workshop-in the industrial trenches of the class struggle-it is there that the masses respect and honour the Communists; it is there that the Communists are chosen as Labour Party delegates, end it is there that the real struggle regarding the Communist Party application to join the. Labour Party and to solidify the whole working-class movement, from Left to Right, is being fought out. It is highly possible that the dead-weight of dictatorial bureaucracy and red-tape, operated by the officials at the top, may prevent, for the time being, the official entrance of the Communist Party into the Labour Party. But the main thing is that the Communist influence in the Labour movement is spreading from below upwards. And because these active and respected workers, appointed by the rank and file, happen to be members of the Communist Party, the national leaders of the Labour Party insist upon the local groups refusing either to recognise or to accept them as bona-fide delegates.&quot;Under the sub-heading &quot;Fascism not Discussed&quot; Paulwrites:&quot;We have stated that the I.L.P. Conference refused to deal with the most vital problems at present confronting the working class.&apos;..&quot;It seems almost belated to Btate, in the year 1923, that the capitalists do not intend to conduct their struggle against the masses within the confines of their own political constitution.   At the slightest sign of trouble, the propertied interests speedily protect themselves by special methods and with the aid of the armed forces.   Strikes, lock-out, and political agitations which are conducted by any determination on the part of the masses, or by leaders who are bent on a viotory for the workers, are speedily dealt with by such things as L.O.R.A., Orders in Council,Emergency/
BED IHTBRHATIOEAI. CF LABOUR unions on May 12th a conference held under the auspices of tho Red International, of labour Unions in the Memorial Hall passed a resolution calling for a general strike in case of war with Russia end another instructing Trades Councils to take up immediately the question of forming Councils of Action.The following extract from a letter sent to the british bureau of the Red International of Labour Unions by the mid-Suropoan Bureau, dated May 5th, 1925, while not initself important is an example of the close touch maintained by Moscow with labour movements in this country:&quot;We duly received yours of April 18th, together with the report on the agricultural workers&apos; strike in Horfolk ana the list of Trade Union brandies that sent delegates to Glasgow.&quot;Tire seEmergency Acts... etc., any of which may lead to Martial Law&apos; ana the employment of police, army and navy.   But the extension of Socialist and Communist propaganda is slowly permeating and undermining the armed forces of the capitalist State, with the result that the ruling class is creating its own private armed forces, which it,secretly subsidises, and which it uses for the special purposo of destroying the labour movement and for murdering those leaders who are dangerous and daring.   Only a few days ago the Government introduced a Bill to enable it maintain a civilian police to be used during any emergency;   this is ono of the instruments that.the British capitalists intend to use against the Labour movement.&quot;Most of the oommunists who were summoned to Moscow have left this country but Walton Hewbold delayed his departure in order &quot;to note the state of the crisis existing betv^een England and Russia and make a report when in Moscow&quot;.J. T. Murphy is acting political secretary of the party during the absence of Thomas Bell.W. MoLaine has resigned the secretaryship of British Joint Lwbour Aid Committee of the Workers&apos; International Russian Relief, in order to work with Aicos.
During tho week most of the unemployed have joined forces with the Communist Party in protesting against the British Hots to Russia:   in the Ytest of Scotland, however, there is considerable activity in connection with evictions Rm5 fooling is running fairly high.icomhct AiSfD THE COMMUNIST PARTY OP IRELANDImportant documents regarding the relations between the Comintern and the Communist party of Ireland have come into my possession:   they slvow, firstly, that the Communist Party of Ireland have received money from the Comintern end secondly that the Russian Trade Delegation in London is used for the transmission of correspondence to Russia which has no Ration to trade matters.    In a letter dated Dublin, May 8th, ^23, sent to Inkpin under a cover address, J.J. 0&apos;Loary, 0jganising secretary of the Communist Party of Ireland,wrote/-    mThese mats rials have been immediately forwarded by us to Mosoou, to the R.I. i.u. as well as to the respective International Propaganda Committees.&quot;The International Propaganda Committees for Textile Workers and &quot;3ooa&quot; Workers are endeavouring to establish oonnection with tha. unions concerned in this country.It is reported that saklatvsla has been instructed by the Committee of Propaganda and Action concerned to &quot;make lull use as a communist propaganda organisation&quot; of the reoently fonned International Oriental Seafarers&apos; Union.i YQUH5 cqmctiay leaguliAccording to a statement recently made by Charles I KoSfem, the organisation of the Young Communist League of Groat Britain Is in &quot;a toriible state&apos;1 and &quot;absolutely bankrupt&quot;.$EMPLOYED
&quot;Dublin, 8th Hey, 19 KS.nijjo She Ex o c ut ive Go minit t.e e , Gciaints rn, Mo so ow.Dear Comrades,&apos;-iis we are net sure whether our communications- have been getting through or not we again raise the question of tho subsidy.   Wo desire definite information as regards the amount allocated for 1923 and also a reply to ours re  150 spent on mission as arranged with Comintern representative in July 1922, end which expenditure was guaranteed by him to bo refunded to us. Vie regret our inability to send representative to E.E.C. of the C.I. which is entirely due to lack of finance,, At present we are heavily in debt and working on an overdraft and loans to keep our Party Organ going.   We would be very glad if you would send the second quarters -allotment at once.&quot;A lull report of tho Party&apos;s development and of Irish developments generally will be sent shortly by the new political Secretary (Com, G. Melay).&quot;As Jim Larkin has arrived here and during an interview with members of the CE.C* made vague reference to his relations, etc., with the Comintern, we shall be glad if you would let us know viiat relations, if any, he has with the Comintern, as this is absolutely&apos; necessary to enable us to define our position towards him.&quot;With Comradely Greetings,J. J. 0&apos;Ieary,For Ihe Central Executive Committee Gcmraur.ist Party of Ireland,,M HBVOLOTIOfliRY AQglYIglES IN GRBAg BRITAINMany of the extremists are elated over Art OlBrienTs success before the Courts! but the majority here know that the Republican cause is lost, for the present at any rate, and dread publicity,&apos;-2he Irish Republican Army left in this country are reported to be engaged particularly on Intelligence work, the smallest detail being recorded:   women are active in this direction and are doing most of this rocord work.As/wrote &quot;I enclose a. corumunioatiorTto     /     OQj&amp;.,,;Oishkon. comsaunlo-ation-enolosea was addressed to the Secretary, Executive Conmittee, Comintern, and the text was as foliows:-
As far as Ireland Itself is concerned, the general opinion is that de Yalera has lost control, and he is. ndVlrj a position to order his followers to give up their arms:   hei only leads them as fur as they are prepared to follow, and so long&apos; as he ia his turn obeys thoir ciiotate.      Here he is. regarded as being only reasonable as long i&amp;e he gets his oxvh v/ay in everything,Jim Larkln&apos;8 position in regard to the Communist Party of Ireland is very doubtful,   A friend who has been in close touch with him since ho returned from Jimerioa says he is not tho man ho was, there Is something missing mentally, but is still a force to be considered.   His name alone means so much to the Dublin fioaker.At 2.45 p.m. on May 11th  Liverpool Polioe raided Ho.15, Ueston Street in that city, occupied by s man named John Finn, and found therein approximately 3,500 rounds of &apos;45 automatic revolver ammunition contains6 in three canvas carriers, with the exoeption of 150 rounds which were in cardboard boxes, 76 screws, nuts or oapa for Thompson Machine Guns;   and 76 Maxim gun silencers.-    While the police were searching William Joseph Horan of 102, Venmore Street, Liverpool, entered the house (this man is known to have succeeded Fleming as 0/C Liverpool) and both he and Finn were arrested.A search.was made at once at Koran&apos;s lodgings when the following articles were found:A &apos;45 six chambered revolver, loaded, and with spareammunition, and a suit case containing&apos; documents, the moreimportant of which are:- -1.   Envelope addressed to I.H. (Liam Horan) containing a sheet of paper written on as follows:- . i :::.;8.5.23.To 0.0.   L.1.     Send to Dublin the remaining Thompson looking pieces in your possession.
2.    Sand 2,000 rds, Th, to Cork.3,    Divide remaining [&amp;omp..&apos; round s between sligo end Dublin - 1500 rde each.4. For the present avoid sending north of the border anything that you can send south of it.(sc. )   Adj. B.g.    Slip of paper on which the following was written:&quot;A Cars.. The ship is the Melifout. &apos; She will be in to-morrow night&quot;   Signed O.H.     (Anmunition was found on this vessel recently by the Free State Authorities on our information).3.    A list of expenses, showing that the prisoner Finn had received payments.4,    A certificate of character issued by the O.C.. 1st Battalion, Cork Brigade I.E.Ai dsted 19.3.23. to Coleman Spillane, and fc number of receipts for anmunltion despatched and monies received.She Republican clubs have at last produced a printeddocument shewing the aims and constitution of theorganisation.   The &quot;aims&quot; are given as follows:-1.     &quot;Id unite all persons of Irish birth or descent living in Scotland in upholding the Republic of Ireland proclaimed by the patriot men and women of 1916, ratified by the free&apos;vote of the Irish people in the General Election of 1916, and formally established by their elected Representatives on January 21st, 1919.&quot;2.     &quot;To co-operate with the Official Republican Organisation in Ireland in all its efforts to maintain the Republic, and to secure for it International recognition.&quot;3.     &quot;To foster in Scotland a knowledge of the Irish language, literature, History and General Culture.&quot;4.    &quot;To promote the trade, commerce, and Industries of Ireland.&quot;5,     &quot;Generally to assist the people of Ireland in achieving the full realisation of their ideals, Political, Cultural and Economic&apos;1There are now 32 clubs, one in Edinburgh, two in Dundee, and the remainder in the South Western district of Sootland.

</content>
</cab>
