<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/160/0 images: 513-519</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/^T^TmCUMSUT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMEN I.)S HI C B B T. I-S-&quot;&apos; CABINET.^. 264(231.THE POLITICAL SITUATION IN SOUTH AFRICA.Copy of Despatch No. 2 from the Governor-General of the Union of South Africa bo the Secretary of State for the Solonies.odd)(Circulated by the Secretary of State for the Colonies *Governor-General1s Office, Cape Town, 27th April, 1923.My Lord Duke,I have the honour to report, in continuation of my despatch Confidential of the 13th April, that the Government has succeeded in making valuable political capital out of the mysterious alliance contracted between the Labour and Nationalist Parties.   Recent utterances by their leaders have betrayed, in a most significant manner, the difficulties in the way of transforming a fusion between two parties holding such conflicting views into a serviceable political weapon. Ear from being a source of strength, the combination has so far proved extremely embarrassing to both sides and the Government1s supporters have been quick to exploit the discords that have from time to time manifested themselves, 2.       The Labour Party&apos;s repudiation of its socialistic aspirations, which the Nationalists rewarded by professing their willingness to acknowledge the English Royal family, was followed by a number of clumsy attempts to reassure supporters whose indignation was aroused by these perfidious recantations. In a speech at Ermelo Mr. Tielman Roos, whose sudden conversionHis Grace the Duke of Devonshire, K.G..G.C.M.G..G.C.V.G., Colonial Office, London;
to the monarchial system led to his being nicknamed the &quot;King maker&quot;, protested that General Hertzog had gone further than anyone else when he announced his readiness to admit Labour members into the Cabinet if a Nationalist Government were formed.    The agreement with the Labour Party, he added with brutal candour, was &quot;only extended to co-operation at the polling booths&quot;.     General Hertzog also became alarmed at the possible bad effect the alliance might have upon his backveld followers and dashed off to a Nationalist stronghold where he reaffirmed his hatred of everything British in the following fulmination:   &quot;If your English Imperialists   and sometimes your IXztch-epeaking Africanders Btick the British flag under my nose I say Hake the stinking thing away&apos;&quot;.     When he returned to Cape Town he was promptly challenged to admit or deny this statement and offered in reply the rather feeble excuse that he did not apply the word &quot;stinking&quot; to the British flag but to the British colours because they were deliberately used to insult him.     The Prime Minister and other Government members retorted that the expressions used by General Hertzog were in deplorable taste and shewed that he had not the least consideration for the feelings of half his fellow-citizens who would never, for example, think of saying anything derogatory about the Free State flag or colours.3.   In a recent speech at the Automobile Club dinner General Smuts emphasized the anomalous position of South Africa which was still the country of the ox-wagon, although it was also pre-eminently the country of the motor.     Progress had been so rapid that the old and the obsolete were found jostling the new and most novel and presenting almost   ineoluble problems.
this    juxtaposition of the ancient and the modern was at one and the same time the romance and the tragedy of South Africa.4.   This theme was developed by Mr. Burton in a very able speech he made yesterday in reply to the Budget debate. Referring to the Labour-Haiionalist combine the Minister of Finance said that the Labour Party prided Itself on being the most progressive and enlightened body in Union politics and yet they had definitely linked themselves with the most retrograde party whioh is hostile to every tenet of their creed.     For this reason he found it easy to demolish their combined attack upon the financial policy of the Government. Contrasting the general criticisms of each party, the Minister drew attention to the fact that the Nationalists clamoured for the overthrow of the   Government because it was grossly extravagant, while Labour members complained that it was a miserly Government and must therefore be turned out.     Their individual grievances, he continued, revealed the same dis-crepancies.     The Nationalists complained of the excessive -number of public servants and the burden of administrative expenditure, while their Labour allies protested vehemently against retrenchment.    Again, the industrial Labour Party agitated for a land tax and increased estate duty while -the Nationalists alleged that agriculturalists were, being taxed out of existence.     &quot;There is no common bond between them&quot;, the Minister remarked, &quot;no political affection.      They are going to live together in this curious menage, not because they love each other but because they hate someone else.&quot;5. In reply to Opposition criticism that the income tax bore too heavily upon the poorer classes and too lightly upon the wealthy, Mr. Burton quoted some interesting figures.-3-
Taking the year ending Juno 1921, the last for which complete returns were available, the Minister was able to shew that taxpayers with incomes below  500 contributed  242,500 on a total income of  18,200,000 (1.3 per oont.) whereas incomes exceeding  20,000 per annum paid for the same year  281,250 tax on a total income of  992,256 (28,3 per cent.)    As a further evidence of the utter fallacy of tho accusations that tho Governments taxation policy tended to favour the rich to the detriment of the poor, Mr, Burton cited tho following figuresIncomes below  1000.&quot;      above  1000. (supertax point)6.     In the course of the debate the Ojjposition had reverted to tho time-worn accusation that the Government were &quot;in the pay of the mining magnates&quot; and that as a consequence the mining industry was not being required to contribute to the revenue of the country in proportion to its means or to tho same extent as other Industries, such as agricultu.ro.     Mr, Burton disposed of those wild statements by pointing out that in 1918-19 tho mines alono paid  1,254,000 out of a total income tax yield of  4,398,000, while the total direct taxation collected from them, including licenses, export duties, etc. amounted to  2,746,000,     Some members of the Opposition even went so far as to say that tho diBoovory of precioiis stones and metals had proved a curse on the country.     &quot;This sort of talk&quot;, replied Mr. 3urton, &quot;is foolish and dangerous talk employed for political &quot;propaganda&quot;.    He reminded theHouse..Peroentage of   Average contri-total tax-       bution per head. payers- t88%  10.Ill  184-2o3  675.
House of the disastrous consequences to tho country whioltS /followed upon the brief stoppage of mining operations duringthe strike and endeavoured to expose the mischievous natureof this kind of criticism by explaining that in 1918-22the gold mines of the Witwatersrand paid out in -White wages.     Native wages.   S.A,Stores.   Imported ^__     ^__,_. Stores. 45,000,000      28,000,000       36,000,000    28,000,000.or altogether  137,000,000, of which  109,000,000 was spent in the country.7.     The Government&apos;s retrenchment policy, the Minister proceeded, had been attacked cn the grounds that it had been rigorously applied to men in the lower grados of the Service, while highly paid officials had been confirmed in their appointments.   Retrench by all means bad been the cry of the Opposition but restrict its operation to your friends at the top.     Mr. Burton exposed tho futility of this proposal by informing the House that out of a total of 35,400 Civil Servants only 131 drew more than  1,000 per annum, while their total salaries only amounted to loss than  170,000.    Owing to the small numbers involved it was obvious that any schemer, of retrenchment confined to this class would not effect any appreciable reduction in expendituro.8.     Tho proposals put forward by the Opposition, concludod the Minister, arc typical of their whole attitude in tho House.   They know 3uch criticisms are utterly im-practicable but they advocate them because they go down well in the country.     They are quite prepared to reap political advantage by criticising the Government&apos;s efforts to perform this troublesome and unpleasant task but they have not got the moral courage to suggest an alternative remedy.      &quot;why should..
should we prescribe?&quot;, they reply, &quot;wait till we got into &quot;power then wc shall proscribe&quot;*9*     There can be no doubt that tho Government has lost influence all over the country.   Tho Nationalists have strengthened their position in the backveld and there are indications that on tho Witwatererand unemployment has sus-talned tho animosities aroused by the strike aocl driven the whole population of that important area into the ranks of labour.   Many people with South African Party inclinations hava come to think that a change of Government at the next election is not only inevitable but desirable - a contention which they excuse on tho grounds that the South African party would be stimulated by a term of opposition while theiritopponents would soon prove themselves unfit to discharge the responsibilities of office     But the more influential politicians and the captains of commerce and industry are convinced that, even if such a stimulant is desirable the prico (five years of Nationalist Government) is too high. Thoy believe too that a political smash will be accompanied by a financial one and that it behoves    wealthy nan, like Mr. Solly Joel, to consider the consequences if thoy continue to take no unselfish interest in the country and make no effort to associato themselves with the appropriate political party.    And, even if one admits that the South African Party has provided.in some respects a disappointing govern-ment, it has to bG remembered that thoy assumed po-ser when the prosperity of the country had reached its zenith and have continued to spend considerable sums on development in spite of the tlmos of stress and difficulty that have pre-prevailed throughout their terra of office.   Thoy stand too forracial,..-6-
racial co-operation which has been accepted as the only possible policy in the Union and are associated with the English, whose enterprise, when all is said and done, is almost entirely responsible for unity and progress that has already been achieved.   The alternative Is their Nationalist opponents whose ideals are of the obsolete ox-wagon type, founded on unworthy prejudices and who derive their energy, judging from the motiveB divulged by the recent alliance with labour, from a voracious thirst for the spoils of office.I have the honour to bet My Lord Duke, Your Grace&apos;s most obedient, humble Servant,(Sgd.) ARTHUR FREDERICK.G0T3RH0R-G3HERAL.2, Whitehall Gardens., .S..W.1. June 8th, 1923.

</content>
</cab>
