<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/160/0 images: 724-732</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS TEE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S. E 0 RvE Tri..?, 266 (22).OA 33 I JET,:&apos; HOME AFFAIRS &quot;COMMITTEE. EXPIRING LAWS CONTINUANCE Bill-Note by the Financial Secretary to the Treasury.- &apos;/ - : The annexed draft Bill is circulated.^ for consideration at the meeting  the^Eome Affairs Committoe on Jfcnday next, J-ane 25th,, 1923^ at 4,3^p.my&apos; No formal decision of the Cabinet has:yet been-taken as to the continuance for a further year from 8tfr: Sejtember^p next of the., power of the Board of Trade to give guarantees   w in respect of exports under the Overseas Trade (Credit and Insurance) Act 1920 which has been included provisionally in Part IV of the Schedule.There is also under consideration by the Treasury the question of the continuance for a further year, from 10th -November next of the power of the Treasury to guarantee  . loans under the Trade Facilities Act which would involve an addition to the Schedule of the Trade Facilities and  . Loans, Guarantee Act 1922, Section (X) Sub-Section (2).(Signed ) CT. JOYNSON-HICKS..Treasury Chambers, June 23rd, 1923.
[13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]   Expiring Laws Continuance.1DRAFT&apos; i OF AB ILLTo continue certain expiring laws.Til 7 HERE AS the Acts mentioned in the Schedule to Y.V this Act are, in so far as they are in force and are temporary in their duration, limited to expire as respects the Acts mentioned in Parts I., II., and III. of that 5 Schedule on the thirty-first day of December, nineteen hundred and twenty-three, the thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and twenty-four, and the thirty-first day of August, nineteen hundred and twenty-four, respectively, and as respects the Act mentioned in Part IV. of that 10 Schedule on the eighth day of  September, nineteen hundred and twenty-three, and as respects the Acts mentioned in Part V. of that Schedule on the thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and twenty-four :And whereas it is expedient to provide for the con-15 tinuance as in this A.ct mentioned of those Acts and of the enactments amending or affecting the same:Be it therefore enacted hy the K&quot;ing&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present&apos; 20 Parliament assembled, and hy the authority of the same, as follows: 1. (l) The Acts mentioned in Parts I., II. and Continuance. III. of the Schedule to this Act shall, to the extent of Acts in specified in column three of that Schedule, be continued    ie u e-25 until the thirty-first day of December, nineteen hundred and twenty-four, and shall then expire, unless further continued.. &quot;81-2 A.
2Expiring. Lg,ws Continuance,, [13 fell Geo;,5;]A.D. 1923. (2) The Act mentioned in Part IV. of the Schedule to this Act shall, to the extent specified in column three of that Schedule, be continued until the eighth day of September, nineteen hundred and twenty-four, and shall then expire, unless further continued. &amp;(3.) The Acts mentioned in Part V. of the Schedule to this Act shall, to the extent specified in column three of that Schedule, be continued until the thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and twenty-five, and shall then expire, unless further continued. 10(4s) Any unrepealed enactments amending or affecting the enactments continued by this Act shall, in so far as they are temporary in their duration, be continued in like manner, whether they are mentioned in the Schedule to this Act or not. 15Short title 2. (1) This Act may be cited as the Expiringand applica- j^ws Continuance Act, 1923.tion toIreland. (2) This Act. shall apply to Northern Ireland inso far as it deals with any enactment relating to a subject with respect to which the Parliament of Northern 20 Ireland has not power to make laws, but subject to this provision this Act shall not apply to Ireland.
13 &amp;.11 Gi:o. 5.1   Expiring Laioii&apos; Continuance.schedul e.Pakt I.Ses3icm and Chapter.Short Title.How far continued.Amending Acts.0)46 &amp; 47 Viet, o. 60..101520253035(2)58 &amp; 59 Viet, c. 21.-10(324Edw. 7.0.2481The Labourers (Ire-land) Act, 1883.The Seal Fisheries (North Pacific) Act, 1895.The Wireless Tele-graphy Act, 1904.The whole act the whole Act.The whole Act.48 &amp; 49 Viet.c. 77. 49 &amp; 50 Viet.c 59 54 &amp; 55 Viet.c. 48. 54 &amp; 55 Viet.c.7l. 55 &amp; 56 Viet.c. 7. 59 &amp; 60 Viet.c. 53. 61 &amp; 62 Viet.c. 37. 3  Edw.   7.c. 37. 6   Edw.c. 37. 7    Edw. - c. 44. 9   Edw.c. 42. 1 &amp; 2 Geo. 5.c. 19. 4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5.c. 32. 8 &amp; 9 Geo. 5.c. 20. 9&amp;10Geo.5.A 2
4 JJJccpiring Laws Continuance.   [13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]A.D.1923Session and Chapter.Short Title.,: t.Amending Acts.I7 Sdw. 7.0.55.(5)1 &amp; 2 Geo. 5. o. 55.The London Cab and Stage Carriage Act, 1907.The National   In-surance Act, 1911.(6)2 &amp; 3 Geo. 5. c. 2. -(7)i &amp; 5 Geo. 5. c. 3.[     (8) 4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5. c. 78.6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5. c. 12.The Coal Mines (Minimum Wage) Act, 1912.The Grey Seals Pro-teetion Act, 1914.The Courts (Emer-gency Powers) Act, J914.The Local Govem-ment (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1916.As to the abolition of the privileged cab system, sec-tion two.Section forty-two -The whole Act.The whole Act.So far as it relates	6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5.	to orders made	c. 13.	by   any xcourt	6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5.	30before the thirty-	c. 18.	first    day    of	7 &amp; 8 Geo. 5.	August, nineteen	c. 25.	hundred      and	9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.	twenty-two.	c. 64.	35	10 &amp; 11 Geo.		5. c. 5.     ]	Section five, except paragraph (a) ; Sections six, seven, nine, and twelve ; Section thirteen, except subsection (6) ; Sections four-teen, twenty-one-and twenty-two, and subsection (1) of section twenty-four.3 &amp; 4 Geo. 5.	10c. 37.	4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5.	c. 57.	4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5.	c.81.	157 &amp; 8 Geo. 5.	c. 62.	10 &amp; 11 Geo.	5. e. 10.	-	20	25il&amp;12Geo.5. c. 12. 40
[13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]   Expiring Laws Continuance. 5	i. Session and Chapter.	2. Short Title.	-          &apos; .3.         .    . How far continued.	4. Amending Acts.5	(10) 6&amp;7Geo.5. c. 55.	The Local Govern-ment (Emergency Provisions) (No. 2) Act,: 1916.	The whole Act	11&amp; 12 Geo. 5. c. 12.  .10	(11) 7 &amp;geo. 5. o. 19.	The Coroners (Emer-geney Provisions) .   Act, 1917.	The whole Act	12&amp;13Geo.5. c. 2.15	(12) 7 &amp; 8 Geo. 5. c, 42.	The Workmen&apos;s Comp e n s a t i o n (War Addition) Act, 1917.	The whole Act   -	9&amp; lOGei.ft. c. 83.20	(13) . 8 &amp; 9 Geo. 5. e. 23.	The Juries Act, 1918	Section seven	12 &amp;13 Geo. 5. c. 2.	(14) 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 35.	The Housing, Town Planning, &amp;o. Act, 1919.	Section twenty-five.	12&amp;13Geo.5. o. 16.25	(15) 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 60.	The Housing, Town &quot; Planning,      &amp;c. (Scotland)   Act, 1919.	Section twenty-two.	*30	(16) 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 92.	The Aliens Restric-tion (Amendment) Act, 1919.	Section one.	- .35	(17) 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 97.	The Laud Settle-ment (Scotland) Act, 1919.	Sections one and two.	12&amp;13Geo.5. c. 52.40	(18) 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.	The Housing (Addi-	Segtjons^one, -two,, eleven, and thir-*Kw&apos;&apos;tRenij6art. farv- as. they   apply T;6&apos; Scotland.	A.D. 1923.
6Expiring Laws Continuance.   [13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1923.1.Session and Chapter.(19) 1.0 &amp; IT Geo. 5. c. 47.(20) 10&amp;IlGeo.5 c. 57.(21) 10&amp;llGeo.5 c. 58.(22) 11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5. c. 66.(23) 12&amp; 13 Geo.5 a. 22.Short Title.The Ministry of Food (Continu-anoe) Act, 1920.The Unemployment (Relief Works) Act, 1920.The Shops (Early Closing) Act, 1920.The National Health Insurance (Pro-prolongation of In-surance) Act, 1921.The Summer Time Act, 1922.How far continued.So far as it autho-rises the making, or revoking in whole or in part, of Parts t. and III. of the Sale of Food Order, 1921, and&apos; pro-vides for the enforcement and imposes penalties for the breach thereof.The whole Act.The whele act the whole Act.The whole Act.i.Amending Acts.101520lU12&apos;Geo.5. c. 60.2530Part II.(24)			8 &amp; 9 Geo. 5.	The        Statutory	So far as it relates	10&amp;llGeo.5.c. 34.	Undertakings (Temporary  Tn-crease of Charges) Act, 1918.	to        tramway undertakings.	c. 14.3540
[13 &amp; 14 Geo. 5.]   Expiring Laws Continuance.2530Part III.			i. Session and Chapter.	2. ;::JV:v-^:&apos;V,v Short Title.	3. How far continued.	4. Amending Acts.- (25) 5 &amp; 6 Geo. 5. c. 21.	The British  Ships., (Transfer-;R;estfic-.:.^tioif)*&apos;&apos; &apos;ct, 1915.	..Tlie whole &quot;Act;&apos;&quot;	^%7:&apos;.Geo. 5. c. 12.Part IV.			(26) 10&amp;llGeo.5. e. 29.	The Overseas Trade (Credits and lu-suranoe) Act, 1920.	As to the powers of the Board of Trade with re-spect to the granting of credits and the giving of new guarantees.	ll&amp;12Geo.5. e. 26. 11 &amp;12Geo.5. c. 65. 13   Geo.   5. (Sess.   2) c. 4.Part V.			(27) 59 &amp; 60 Viet, c. 16.	The    Agricultural . Rates Act, 1896.	The whole Act&apos;  -	2   Edw.   7. c.42. 7   Edw. 7. c. 13.(28) 59 &amp; 60 Viet, e. 37.	The Agricultural Rates, Congested Districts, and Burgh Land Tax Relief (Scotland) Act, 1896.	The whole Act	60 &amp; 61 Viet. c. 53. 7  Edw.   7. e. 13. 1 &amp;2 Geo. 5. c. 49. .A.D. 1923.
Expiring-  jaws Continuance.D BAITOj? ABILLTo continue certain expiring laws.LXXXV.   (2.)IZih June 1923,SI-2

</content>
</cab>
