<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/160/0 images: 744-745</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government) 7&quot;CRET.&apos;P7&quot;3&quot;8S (2525615CABINET.THE SCOPE OF THE STANDING JOINT COMMITTEE FOR EXTOVICE QUESTIONS.MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OP PENSIONS.Thia controversy has now lasted about two years and is embarrassing the otherwise useful work of the Standing Joint Committee by whioh I think both the Government and the ex-service men have benefited.     At every meeting questions affecting the Service Departments are presented for discussion which have to be ruled out of order because this point has not been settled.     I hope it may now be settled definitely by a decision of the Cabinet, because the tension which exists is, in my opinion, due almost more to the delay whioh has arisen in settling the question than to the merits of the question itself.    Meanwhile, I have only two observations to make.In the first place, I would remind the Cabinet that since the Committee was founded it was decided for very good reasons (and embodied in the War Pensions Act 1920) that my Department should have no responsibility for any post-war Service questions, and that therefore I have no direct concern in the manner in which it may be thought best to settle the present, difficulty.    If, however, it is decided that post-war questions are to be discussed at Meetings of the Committee, it follows that the relations to the Committeeof the Service Departments who are responsible for suchtquestions must be reconsidered and Ministers of the Service Departments in a position to give authoritative replies must be placed in charge of these discussions when they arise,- - Secondly
Secondly, while I shall, of course, be happy to co-operate in any inquiry the Cabinet may desire, I have some doubt whether a further inquiry of the kind suggested by the Minister of Labour (CP.284 (25)) is likely to be profitable.    The ground of dispute is so narrowly defined that there is, in fact, little room for compromise.    What seems to me to be wanted is that the Government, advised by the Service Departments who are chiefly if not solely concerned, should clearly decide one way or the other whether or not there shall be a Standing Committee at which post-war questions not affecting serving soldiers can be authoritatively dealt with and that the decision should be announced as soon as possible.I do not believe that the British Legion, whatever happens, will be very ready to break up the Standing Joint Committee from which they have derived very definite advantages, but- I may perhaps point out that, in the event of a refusal of their present request, the Legion would probably proceed to ventilate their grievances on post-war questions by way of demands for deputations to Ministers, thus to some extent renewing the inconveniences which the Committee has, on the whole been successful in preventing,(SIGNED)   G.C. TRYDN,Minister of pensions.Ministry of Pensions. 26th June, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
