<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/27/10 images: 106-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret.P.(42)550 COPY NO.   ^51 ST JULY, 1942WAR   CABINETTHE USE OP PSYCHOLOGISTS AND PSYCHIATRISTSIN THE SERVICESJoint Memorrjidum by the Lord Privy Seal 0 the First Lord ofthe Admiralty3 the Secretary of^State for War and&apos; theSecretary of State for Air&apos;,&quot;&quot;1. The War Cabinet    invited us (&apos;.y.M. 75(42)Conclusion 5)    to consider   the question whether there   might   he    a   tendency   to use the psycho-analytical technique too extensively, andwhether, if unwisely handled, it might encourage the verytendencies it was hoped to combat.   l&quot;e have received and considered a number of memoranda from the service departments and have heard the views of a number ofofficers of the three Services.   V/e have also had thebenefit of the advice of Sir E. Mellanby, Secretary tothe Medical Research Council, and Sir W. Jameson, ChiefMedical Officer to the Ministry of Health, to both of whomexpress   our gratitude for their help.2. A distinction should be made between the two main types of work on which psychologists and psychiatristsare engaged, namely the selection of personnel for various kinds of employment and the maintenance of the mental health of the Services.     Particularly in theArmy, however, the two types of work are closely related.     There is in addition a minor but notunimportant part played by psychiatrists in cases ofdelinquency.     Where the.medical officer so advisessuch cases may be referred to the psychiatrist forreport and his report will be taken into account just as the report of a medical officer would be in similar cases.

SELECTION OF P&quot;R^on n^I.3. In all three Services a number of non-medicalpsychologists with industrial experience are employed in working out and applying tests of intelligence or aptitude.      The Rc A, F.use intelligence tests for air crews and ground staff.,  andaptitude tests are used in the department of technical training.In the Navy and the Army,  all recruits now undergo what is called the  &apos;Matrix&apos;  test.      Each recruit is given a bockcontaining a number of printed patterns,  each with a piecemissing.      below each pattern,  several smaller patterns areprinted,  each identified by a number.      The candidate isrequired to write on a sheet of paper the identification numberof the smaller pattern which,   in his opinion,  fits best into thelarger.      The original purpose of this test was to detectpersons who were mentally deficient, but it has been found togive very reliable results as a test of general teachabilitywhich enables recruits to be classified into a few broad  classcs;.as well as disclosing these who may be of sub-normal intelligence.;The lowest 10&quot;&apos;i category of those tested are referred forinterview by a psychiatrist to determine whether they should be rejected as mentally unfit, passed,  or recommended for specialemployment suited to their mental capacity.      In the R, A, F- ,where the &quot;Matrix&apos;  test is not used,  the question of referenceto a psychiatrist is decided by the lay interviewing officer..h. Recruits for the Navy are given further tests at their training establishment,  designed majnly to pick out men withmechanical aptitude.      For example, candidates are shovvr.pictures of men carrying weights,  a boat being towed along acanal,  etc.,  and are required to say which of the two men is carrying the heavier load or at which of &quot;two points the tow-ropeshould be attached to the boat.5. Under the recently introduced system of a &apos;general serviceintake&apos;   in the Army,  there is an opportunity of giving recruitsa relatively long series of tests during their first six weeks&apos;service after they have enlisted but before they are allocated to a corps.     Tests of mechanical    aptitude and normal dexterity areincluded, and are used, for example,  to help in deciding whethermen are suitable for training in technical  jobs.6&quot;. Soldiers recommended for Officer Cadet Training units are now given a three-day test at a residential testingestablishment.      General intelligence tests are included as well-as military and physical tests of various kinds, with a view to determining character and leadership, and those     whosesuitability or unsuitability is not obvious^ are interviewedby a military psychiatrist- who makes an assessment of theirpersonality.      He sees them,  not as a doctor, but as an officer who,  from his experience,  is particularly skilled in ^summine---&quot;-^the individual&apos;s character.      He encourages the candidate to talk about himself, his past experiences,  tastes and ambitions,The psychiatrist is one of the five members of the board whichdiscusses each candidate after the conclusion of the course,The board is presided ever by the Commandant of the testingestablishment and includes the military testing officer and

two visiting regimental officers of the rank of lieutenant-colonel;    the decision whether a candidate is posted to anO.C.T. U.  is in the hands of the President and his two visitingassistants.      Having visited one of these establishments the lord privy Seal has no doubt that they are a great improvement uponthe old selection boards, and it is interesting to observe thatthey are almost universally approved by those who go through them whether they pass or fail.      They have also had the effect ofincreasing the number of applications for commissions&apos;, as they give a sense of fairness and confidence to the applicants,7. In all Services the practice is that before apsychological test is adopted it is tried out on large numbersof individuals whose qualities are known by experience andrecord, and unless the test passes with a small margin of errorall those v/ho are known to be efficient and fails those who are known to be inefficient at the particular job in question, itis discarded.      An example of this is the test, tried for the selection of motor drivers in the Army.     When tested on knowndrivers it was found to give too uncertain a result- and so was dropped.      Nevertheless, it is recognised that the psychologicaltests in use are not infallible and they are used as *pointers1in conjunction v/ith more familiar methods of selection,      their value is that they help to save time, which in v/ar is all-important, by weeding out some at any rate of the unteachablecandidates before a training course begins.      They also preventmen of talent and useful experience from being relegated toduties which do not fully employ their capabilities.      There is some further evidence to show that the &quot;squadding&quot; of men bytheir capacity to learn speeds up training.8. The need for the application of such tests and for amore careful selection of personnel has arisen from the shortnessof the period, of training which is available in time of war.Given a period of years persons with even the lowest intelligencecan be trained and may become very good soldiers at the end ofh or 5 years of peace-time training.    In time of war, however,when the period is 6 months or less, it is necessary to pass thedifferent batches through a course which, unless there is aconsiderable degree of teo.chability in the personnel, results inmany failures, who cannot receive further training and whotherefore become rejects and waste much time and energy.      The whole system of selection is therefore aimed at sending the right manto the right job; in the sense that he will be able to learn the job allotted to him in the time available for teaching him.      the improved methods of selection detailed above have already resultedin a considerable improvement in this respect.      There is anothervaluable aspect of the same process.      The., fewer the misfits, thatis, men put into jobs which are either too simple or too complexfor their intelligence, the less liability is there to subsequentbreakdowns and mental illnesses.      The question of personnelselection is more difficult and more important in the Army than inthe other Services, since the Navy and Air Force get the firstpick of recruits, whereas the Army must take all that remain andconsequently the average level of intelligence in Army recruitstends to be lower than in the other two services.In these circumstances there is a tendency on the partof the interviewing officers to pass on to psychiatrists forfurther interview a large proportion of recruits.      Since such

expert&quot; are limited in no.- bcr, there is o. real, danger oftheir &quot;being driven too hard, with consequent impairment of theirstandard of work.MENTAL. HEALTH.9. The methods adopted by each Service to maintain the mental health of its members are described below, taking each service in turn.10.        In the R. A, P.   the main concern in this connection isthe mental health of flying personnel, and the instructions to medical officers lay stress on this.      Broadly speaking?however,  the same procedure is followed, for ground staffs as for air-crews.      Each squadron has a medical officer   and eachstation a senior medical officer.      Great importance is.attached to each squadron having its own medical officer who can be in daily and hourly contact with the personnel and soget to know their personalities and watch their health.      these officers, while they are instructed not tc go round the squadron suggesting to people that they are suffering from amental disorder,  are encouraged to maintain close informalcontact with the men in their charge,  to observe them,  and tokeep notes about each individual.      The Commanding Officer andthe Medical Officer are encouraged to consult together aboutmen whom either suspects to be suffering from strain-Incipient cases of mental strain or breakdown are dealt with bythe Medical Officer on the spot,  as, if such cases can bepromptly and effectively -created before they go too far,  theycan be put right in very many  instancesoSdch eases may be giverleave, without calling it sick leave,, and thus breakdown from&quot;neurasthenia&quot;,  &quot;anxiety states5&apos;&apos;,  &quot;hysteria&quot;,  etc, may be avoided.      Sometimes a confidential talk with the medical officer on informal lines may give the necessary reassuranceand encouragement.      Cases who show no improvement when treatedlocally in this way are sent to a neurological centre for examination by a neuropsychiatrist, and it is stated that of lying personnel so sent for examination a number ^ever returnto full flying duty,  though some do return after treatment,       NOthers are sent to convalescent  hospitals, at Torquay (officers;andHatlock (airmen).      At these homes not only nervous cases but all kinds of cases convalescing from wounds or illness are treated.        It has been represented that the presence ofnervous cases retards the recovery of the others,  but thebenefit to the nervous cases of contact with other patients whoare mentally normal is considered to outweigh this disadvantage.Occupational therapy is used,  together with the technique ofreassurance and suggestion that the patient&apos;&apos;s mental health isimproving.      If the disorder is not cured by this treatment thecatient is discharged from the Service or if psychotic2 may betransferred, to an Army Qr Civilian Mental Hospital.Xle were supplied with the following figures of casestreated at Torquay and hatlock since the outbreak ox war;

(a) Torquay Hospital.        185 cases were treated and were disposed of as follows:(Officer Returned to full flying duties 36^members of 11 &quot; limited   &quot; &quot; 32^air-crew) &quot; &quot; ground duties 19^invalided 13&apos;^(b) Matlock Hospital.(airmen (i) Aircrews:    398 cases treated and only) disposed of as follows:Returned to flying duties 37r1&quot; &quot;    ground     &quot; 38c1Invalided 25c*(ii) Ground Personnel:    1233 cases treatedand disposed of as follows:Returned to duty 55^Invalided. 1+5^11. The R.A.P.   attempt to distinguish between the man whois unwilling to carry on with his job because of &quot;lack of moralfibre&quot; and the man who is judged by a neuropsychiatrist to besuffering from a mental illness.      The latter are treated as above;    cases of the former type are referred to the Air Miniswith a view to their being asked to resign their commissions,,if officers,  or returned to duty as general aircraft hands,  ifairmen.      Where it is doubtful which of these two categories is appropriate,  the man is now sent to a reseiection establishmentwhich has just been started at Brighton where retraining of ageneral kind is given to men returned from abroad;, menreturning from sick-leave,  etc and eventually he is disposed of either by re-posting, transfer to another branch,,  invaliding,or being asked to resign, as seems appropriate after this further period.of training and examination.12.        As regards nervous cases generally in the R.A. P.  treat-ment has been given to a total of 2,267 air crews, of whom L\.0&apos;^have returned to duty and to a total of 10,k60 ground personnel,of whom 2f1f$ have returned to duty.    The number of flyingpersonnel who since the beginning of the war have eeased to flybecause of nervous  disorders is roughly equivalent to 10 of the flying personnel o This figure includes  u/ v,--0have become unfit through genuine flying stress. zya13.        In the Navy,  the ship&apos;s medical officer is given instructions broadly similar to those in force In the R, A, P.There is a medical officer on each destroyer;    larger ships have one or more - two for ships carrying between 500 and 1?000men, and three for ships with more than 1,000 men.     Ships&apos;medical officers,  ex-civilians many of them, have,  it is stated,proved quite equal to the heavy strain the Navy has carriedsince the outbreak of war.      The duty of the ship&apos;s medical officer is to keep as many men on duty as possible,, and thoughcommanding officers naturally tend to get rid of nervous men,who are a bad influence on their comrades, by sending themashore for &quot;observation-mental&quot; everything is done to discouragethis and to encourage the practice of dealing with incipient

mental troubles by a short rest in the sick bay, by grant ofleave,  or by encouragement.      Once a man is sent to hospital,  it becomes difficult to get him into a proper frame of mind forgoing to  sea again, and for this reason the Navy&apos;1 s neu.ro-psychiatrists work largely at Naval Barracks, not hospitals,  sothat while a man is under treatment he can continue to performa certain amount of naval duty.      It is to such Barracks thatcases are sent by Ships&apos; Medical Officers.      The exception tothe rule that men once sent to hospital for mental troubles donot easily recover is the case of the really first-classofficer or man &quot;hose breakdown is due to severe strain in battle.These recover quickly, and it may be said, generally,  thatprofessional sailors, both officers and men, rarely suffer fromnervous troubles,  except in cases of very direct and severephysical strain from explosions.      Most mental illness cases arehostilities only&quot; enlistments or reservists who, getting on inlife, find it difficult to readjust themselves to th^ Navy after a long period as civiliansih.        Cases that are too bad to be dealt with at a NavalBarracks as described above are usually sent to a Naval Hospitalwith a Psychiatric Department.    Importance is attached to thepractice of treating these cases at general hospitals instead ofat special establishments, which, it is held, would tend toaccentuate their eccentricities.      There are two special estab -lishmentss    at Cholmondely Castle (which has only recently beenestablished) cases of men with good records who have broken down,under battle -stress are dealt with by occupational therapy-,physical training,  etc. while at Kieldar Camp, which is run bythe executive branch, cases of &apos; ;or morale with an element of mental sub-normality or delinquency are given a rehabilitationcourse under strict naval discipline,,    It is stated that yj&amp; ofthe Kieldar Camp cases return successfully to duty.    Of the ohcases admitted to Cholmondely Castle before 30th June, 19L2, 2uwere discharged before that date.      Of the 2J+, i6 were returned to sea duty, 6 were recommended for home shore service and 2 pro--ceeded to other establishments on account of injury,&apos;     It isthought that some of those who may appear to be cured are likelyto break down again if returned to sea duty.15.       As a guide to the incidence of mental disorders i,n theNavy,  it was stated that in 19^4-0 there were about 5?000 cases ofmen sent ashore for this reason.16,        The Army&apos;s mental health problem is more serious than thoseof the other Services, partly because the Army has perforce toaccept men of low intelligence who must be placed in carefully selected jobs if they are not to break down.    In.the Army theregimental medical officer, though recognised like his oppositenumbers in the other,Services as a most important factor in themaintenance of the mental health of the Service, works at a disadvantage.    It is not at present possible to allot a medical officer to each battalion;    battalion medical officers have toact as area medical officers in addition;   moreover,  the exigencies of the Service are such that it is generally impossiblefor a medical officer to remain with a unit for more than sixmonths.    It is therefore difficult for him to get to know his menwell.    At ,pre-sent no printed instructions on dealing with mentaldisorders are issued, but there are some instructions in draft which follow broadly the same lines as those of the R.A,E,   though they will be rather fuller.      Before taking up their duties Unitmedical officers are given a three weeks&apos;  course which includestwo lectures on the application of psychiatry to Army problems;arrangements are also made for them to receive lectures fromCommand psychiatrists after posting and to sit in with apsychiatrist when he sees patients.

.17. For specialist work., which includes the interviewingof candidates&quot;referred as a result of selection proceduresthere are in this country about loO   psychiatristsin hospitals and attached to various Commands,  and some 50in the Middle East.    .Cases of mental disorder not amountingto insanity were formerly sent to civilian hospitals underthe Emergency Medical Service scheme, hat two militaryhospitals have now been set up where  the patients remain under military discipline and are given treatment by para-military occupational therapy as well as the methods we have mentioned in describing the R, A-F, establishments at Matlockand Torquayo      Many patients when they leave these hospitalsare fit for useful military work but  they are not posted tothe Field Army.      For cases that would have to be certifiedif they were discharged from the Army there are now tenmilitary mental hospitals where patients may be kept fornine months;    most of the patients when discharged fromthese hospitals., though not fit for military service, are able to return to civil life without having to be certified -..Of 5,000 to 6,000 soldiers invalided out of the Army each month 30 per cent are psychiatric cases-18c It was stressed that the Army&apos;3 most important methodof preventing mental illness or nervous breakdown is theprocedure for putting men in jobs which arc not beyond theirmental capacity.      The Army has to take a lot of dull men who-,if put in units where there is a lot to learn, become barrack-room butts, go absent without leave,  and become either habitualoffenders or mental cases -      These are now fitted into jobswithin their capacity and in some cases are sent to the newunarmed units of the Pioneer Corps where they are happv.efficient,  clean, and useful members of the Army.    $p. \ Qtthese latter are definitely sub-normal mentally bud sanywootet &quot;**civil life become unemployables ^      It is of interest to note that they are both happy and efficient, when working together in a unit in which there is not a continual struggle for themto keep up to a level of intelligence which they caiinot attain,19. The connection between psychology, psychiatry andmoraleo(i) It is clear that the activities of psychologistsand psychiatrists in the work of selecting personnel, have agood effect on morale.      These activities are carefullycontrolled and it is recognised that the judgment of thepsychologist and the psychiatrist is a &quot;pointer&quot;-, to be usedin conjunction with the judgments of trained regimentsIofficers and other methods of select!en,,(ii) The technique of psyeho-analysis in the strictsense1 of the term is not used at all-      It is a processlasting over a period, of years and time and other conditions would not permit of its being used in war-time even if those responsible in the Services admitted its value0      In point of fact they do not consider it applicable to wcrk in the Services.-(iii) The medical officer of the ship, batt^&quot;1Ion orsquadron is the man chiefly responsible for the mental health

of the sailor,  soldier or airman as he is for his physical   -health.     Excellent v/orl&apos; has been done by these medical Officerssand   we    should   like    to cee        the unit medical officer,in the Army particularly v&quot; given better prospects of promotion^(iv) The arrangements for selecting psychiatrists for service in the Forces seem to be satisfactory in view of the limited choice available.      A proper emphasis is laid on theimportance of appointing men with good medical and generalexperience rather than highly specialised persons -      Among thelarge number of psychiatrists in the Army only some half-dozen out of 150 have had to be relieved of their duties0Three of these themselves suffered nervous breakdowns*(v) The psychiatrists theirs elves give no encouragement to the idea that there is nothing disgraceful about cowardiceor slackness.      The bias is quite the other way and it isstated that in general the executive officer is more anxiousthan the psychiatrist to let a man down lightly on account ofsupposed nervous trouble c(vi) The line taken on the v^ry difficult question ofmalingering seems to be sound.      &quot;Pour decourager ies autresi!the treatment of a malingerer has to be firm, but it isrightly recognised that a man who is inclined to malinger isnot a good man to have in the fighting line.      Pure malingeringis stated to be rare, and a tendency to malinger disappearswhen the man is put in another (not necessarily a safer) joboTHE DESIRABILITY OP UTILISING- PSYCHOLOGISTS AMD PSYCHIATRISTSIN THE SERVICES.20. The main criticisms which seem to have been made against the use of psychologists and psychiatrists in theServices fall under four heads:-(i) that these specialists put ideas of fear andmental instability into the minds of otherwise healthy men with the result that they cause the very state of mental illness they are supposed to cure;(ii) that unintelligent types who would make goodfighting soldiers are relegated to non-fighting j^bsj(iii) that malingering is made easier and that persons are able to escape or are encouraged to escape military service or the consequences of military crimes by feigning mental illness which does not existj(iv) that cowardice is treated as an excusable mental illness and is therefore not punished, and so becomes more widespread.The answer to these points is contained in the foregoingdescription, but &quot;We should make it clear that we have had allfour points particularly in view in making the enquiry anci that weare - satisfied that they have n^ validity as criticisms in viewof the valuable contribution that is being made by these

specialists to the efficiency of the Forces,      It must ofcourse always be borne in mind that no Service is perfect andthat cases may arise from time to time v/here specialists ormedical officers take an unwise course or are careless.Such cases can never be wholly eliminated but we aresatisfied that those in control are fully alive to the dangers and that they have successfully prevented any ofthem from making their presence felt.21.       We summarise quite shortly the answer to the fourcriticisms detailed above:(i) No psychiatrist sees any man or officer - apartfrom men referred as a result of selection procedure - untiland unless his own medical officer has (a; come to theconclusion that he is a case of mental illness and (b) has failed by the means at his disposal to cure him.     Care istaken to prevent the &quot;automatic&quot; reference of such cases bythe Medical Officer to the specialist.      No psycho-analysisis used for Service patients and the whole tenor of thetreatment is encouragement and a normal healthy life of activity.(ii) This point has already been dealt with inparagraph 7 above,(iii) The number of true malingerers is small, and agreat many of the cases of absence without leave, etc, can betraced to backward or misplaced individuals.      It is interesting to note that there has been a decrease in suchcases since selection of personnel became more specialiseda task and psychiatry played its part in the process.      Onthe whole, it is probably more difficult for the dishonestevader of duty to get past the psychiatrist than to get pastan unskilled person and there is no evidence that men havebeen discharged on grounds of mental illness v/ho have infact been perfectly sound.      There is, however, a good reason why this should often appear to be so,      A soldier who has a breakdown, a genuine case of mental illness, may on returnto civil life and to his family rapidly become normal andmay be able to keep the illness completely under, so longas he remains in those conditions.      This does not mean that .he would have &quot;got well&quot; in the conditions in which hebecame ill.      As regards the use of psychiatrists inconnection with delinquency, there is no evidence thatpsychiatrists&apos; reports lead to evasion of punishment exceptin very clear cases of mental illness.(iv)  It is doubtful whether any officer or man chargedwith cowardice has got off because of a psychiatric report.,In very few cases has psychiatric evidence in a court swayedthe court&apos;s decision, though in many cases, other thancowardice, where reports of mental dullness have&apos;been sentto the convening officer, proceedings have been quashed ormodified.      If there is set against the possibility ofmistaken leniency the great amount of help in avoidingbreakdowns and of curative work done by Medical Officersthrough their contact with and instruction by psychiatrists,there can be no doubt that morale has gained as a result ofthe introduction of psychiatry.22, One further incidental point arises in the case of theArmy,    &apos; A good many complaints have come from the Middle Eastas to the poor quality of the replacements sent out, both asregards officers and men.     There is no doubt that in a number

of cases units at home have used these drafts as a method of getting rid of their worst personnel with most unfortunate andwasteful re suits*     An example of the poor material being sent out to the Middle Hast is the case of a draft of 80 men to asearchlight regiment.     Twenty-seven of these men were examined and, before testing, 7 were diagnosed as feeble-minded mental defectives and 11 as dull and backward.      On testing withthe Matrix tests, 24 out of the 27 were shown to beintellectually defective or below averager and only 3 wereintellectually average.     &apos;inis was in the last quarter of lastyear.     This should, of course, be stopped and we understandthat steps are being taken and that the position is improvingIt is probable that the selection technique can bo appliedto these drafts in some slightly altered form.      In addition,the selection procedures in the United Kingdom are graduallyovertaking more and more of the Army in this country andconsequently the indiscriminate posting overseas of backwardor u:b table men becomes less Iikeiy023.    It is important with this parallel development in the three services that there should be the fullest exchange of dataand experience so that each may take advantage of the work ofthe others.     There is an acute shortage of both psychologistsand psychiatrists for the development   -f this work and it isin our view advisable that some sort of co-ordinated control should be exercised in the three Services-,     Work of this kind which though upon established lines, has a large element of uncertainty in it requires to be carefully watched.      It is evident that only the best aptitude methods for selectionshould be adopted, and that care should be taken to controland validate all psychiatric experiments and new methods.There is evidence that these matters are at present well inhand, but in view of the great value and importance of the workwe think it would be well to have some small expert committeewhich could report from time to time and make recommendationsupon the general question of the use of psychiatry and psychology.Such a committee could examine and correlate the facts andthe results of the work in the three Services which cannot now be. done by the departments themselves owing to lack of personnel and time.      One value of such a committee would bethat it could watch the development, with a view to theapplication of these methods much more generally after the war to peace-time activities.     We suggest that the Ministers whohave carried out the present enquiry, namely the Lord Privy Sealand the three Service Ministers,  should constitute a standingCommittee for the purpose of carrying on this general supervision and that five experts should be added t^ the committee who would themselves act as a Sub-Committee under the chairmanship of oneof their number.      They would report from time to time tothe Lord Privy Seal as chairman of the Committee and he couldsummon the main Committee when he considered it necessary.(Intd.) R.S.C.A.V.A*P.J.C.A.H.M.S.3.1st July. 1942,

ADDENDUM BY THE LORD PRIVY SEALAfter discussion with Sir EvMollanby and Sir W.Jameson,I put forward the following suggestions for the five membersof the Sub-coromittee:-Professor E*DoAdrian, M. A. ,M.B.,F,R.S.,F.R.C.P..(Professor of Physiology, Cambridge University)(Chairman)Professor D*K.Henderson, M.,Ch.. B. , M.D. ,P.R.C.P.  and S.(Glasgow), F.R.C.P.E,.&quot;(Professor of Psychiatry,Edinburgh University)Professor F.C*Bartlett, C.B.E., M.A.,F.R. S.,PRofessor of Experimental Psychology, CambridgeUniversity).Dr. Aubrey J. Lewis, M.D. ,F.R. CP. , (Clinical Director.Maudsley Hospital,  and Consultant in PsychologicalMedicine, British Post-Graduate Medical ScJaool inH amme r smi th)*Mr. A.W.P.Walters, -IfcA. , Lecturer in Psychology, ReadingUniversity.In accordance with paragraph 25 above the followingmight be the terms of reference of the Sub-committee.(l) To examine and correlate the facts andthe results of the -psychiatric andpsychological work in the three Services.(2) To make  suggestions in the field of furtherco-ordination,  or development or controlof this work.(5) T study the application of these methods witha view to their post-war application.(intd.) 1.3.C1st August, 1942,




</content>
</cab>
