<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/118/0 images: 13-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CRETTHIS DOOUlffiffg? IS 5JHB iSBOKlMIT Oil&apos; HISJIRIMltlO MAJSSn^RtOHBBP C0WJ3  ) CEP ElKlUIRY ON UMIPLQM^T. Moto by tho Minister of labour.With reference to Cabinet 88 (20) Conclusion 5 and 0.P.2402, I now oirculato for information and rooord a complete copy of tho correspondence oto. with Mr. Henderson and Sir Allan Smith, on tho above subjoot,(Initialled)   T.J.M.Ministry of labour. 12.1.21.1,   SETTERS TO IB. ffiMMggM AgD SIR ALLAH SMITH,JANUARY 1st. 1981,My dear Henderson,I have consulted tho Prime Minister respecting&quot; your strong representations that it is necessary at present to enquire, not only into tho question of what further steps nay be necessary to alleviate distress consequent upon tho present unemployment but also into the oauoes of unemployment itself.Tho Prime Minister agrcos that ultimately an investigation into the root causes is necessary.   But the immediate t.vd urgent problem which brought us together on Christmas Day is thG present emergency and how it may boot bo facod.   This is the pressing duty,      Further, tho Board of Trade which is specially concerned with the questions relating to the trade and commerce of the country, out of which employment springs, is now considering what stopsSt. Eon, Arthur Henderson, M.P. 15, Rodenhurst Road, Claphem Park.
(A letter in similar terms was sent to sir ^3Ian Smith substituting four other representatives of Employers&quot;).E-FOLLOrJIIif&amp; ghgMS OF jCTiggjajg flEHS BSQLOBSI) II SHE ABOTTE LETTSfig: -&quot;2o consider and report within a month as to -(1) 2he extent, probable duration and development of the present unemployment;(h) Whether, in order to cope with the distress arising from unemployment, a fund should be established on the basis of compulsory contributions over and above those provided by the Unemployment Insurance Act,1920, such contributions being made by all classes of the co;.i:;iunity other than those unemployed.( ) If so, in what janner should the fund be raised and administered, and in what form should it be applied in the case of those for whose benefit it is provided&quot;.can be taken by the uovornment to assist in restoring Trade; and the j-overnment propose that a committee should be set up to deal v,&apos;ith the oauses ox&quot; the present depression.Meanwhile, the ,?x -e Linister is strongly of the opinion that it is most expedient that the reference to the Committee now the subject of our consideration should stand as approved by the Cabinet (I enclose a co^y of the same) and hopes, in view of the hardships of unemployment, you will see your way to assist by joining in the inquiry..Sir Robert Borne would act as Chairman of the Committee..  The repiescntatives from Employers,and Employed would be five each res-pectivoly; and in view of the situation created by the present indus-trial depression I tra desired to express most sincerely the hope that you will agree to help us by serving yourself and by suggesting to me the names of four other representatives of Labour who may be approached with a view to joining      in his inquiry,    here would be added to the Committee three other arsons, one of whom it is hoped may be Sir Hardman Lever,ana another two who would be members of parliament. The services of the Government actuary, Sir Alfred Watson, will, of course, be gt the disposal of the Committee.Yer;, faithfully yours, (Sgd) T,J. kacnamara. 2:*Sm I have written similarly to Sir Allan Smith,
m. HiiiroiiiRSOJj&apos;s HiiPLY go gaJSagK OF J&amp;JaU^RY 1ST.BBS LABOUR EaREY,53, Baaleston Square, London, S.W.1.3rd January. IS21,My dear Maonaaara,I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the let instant enclosing a oopy of the terms of roferenoe of the proposed Committee to deal with distrocs arising out of the present unemployment.I deeply rogrot that the suggestions whioh 1 mado et an interview on the evening of December 31st have not bgon aooopted oy the Government.   The  proposals whioh you now make aro open to grave oritioism.(1) Aii enquiry on the lines of Clause (1) of the suggested terms of reference is in ny opinion impracticable apart from an investigation into the causes whioh havo contributed and are still contributing to produce the present orisis.   It does not appear to me that the estaolishment of two Committees, one under the auspices of the Board of Trade to desl with the oauses of the oresent tradeMdepression and the other undei the auspices of the Ministry of Labour, with the terms of reference you suggest, is a satisfactory way of arriving at a national policy.    It is clear that no Committee oould report on the&quot;probable duration and development of the present unemployment&quot; without taking into account the factors whioh have created end aro continuing to create the present situation and the proposals of the Board of Trade for the restoration of &apos; commerce l,rtout of whioh employment springs&quot;.   By separating the two enquiries the Government must reduoe the suggested Committee on Unemployment to the level of a body ignoring causes and remedies and abandoning any hope of estimating the duration of those causes, and dealing only with the oreation and administration of a distress fund.    After full and careful consideration I am firmly of the/opinion
opinion that the limitation of the terms of reforenoe, at; suggested by the Government, will defeat the DDjeot whioh you have in view, of formulating the best methods of dealing with the present emergency, as it is impocsiblo to frame proposals without a know-ledge of the oauces whioh govern the &quot;extent and probable duration and development of the present unemployment&quot;.(2)   The aeoond ol^use of the proposed torms of reference clearly indicates that the suggested Committee is to deal with &quot;distress&quot;.    Che drafting of this seotioa of the terms of reference would seem to imply that the Committeo would be limited to advising as to whether a oontrioutory iuac should bo established for alleviating distress *&amp; distinct iron making payments to all persons out of employment (as under the National Insuranoo ..ots). ^t is not clear whether the Oomaiictee, if it rejected such a proposal, would be entitled to recommend an alternative scheme.But clause (2) is open to even more serious objection.   It suggests a method of meeting distress whioh will not commend itself to organised labour, oapeoially in vi*w of the fact that tho government has announced a policy of extending part time employment in order to absorb those at preeeni unemployed and to ration amongst all workers the available employment.   You may remember that the joint industrial conference, whioh reported in April, 1S19, recommended the institution of short time during periods of trade depression, but this was to je in oonjunotion with provision for organised under-employment, as well as main-tenance in the case of unemployment,   as. I understand it, the Governments suggestion is that persons employed only for part time would be oalled upon to make additional opmpulsory contribution-butions to an unemployment fund.*I am not dear what meaning the government attached to the term &quot;distress&quot; more particularly sinoe tho adoption of the short time policy,    I am sure you will agree that workpeople employed for say two days a week and QOxiSequontly obtaining no unemployment/pay.
pay, axe suffering distress.   Yet as all persons employed are presumably to be expected to contribute to the proposed ne- fund, it would not appear that at the same time they would be eligible for benefit,   moreover, it would be entirely inadmissible to levy compulsory contributions in connection witn the National Insurance Acts, not for payment to all unemployed contributors, but merely for the relief of such persons as are in distress.I raise these ,-points, not to traverse the ground which the Committee, if established, must cover, but in orcier to emphasise the inadequacy and restricted character of the suggested terms of reference,as defective because(a) they do not provide for an enquiry into the whole problem with a view to the formulation of a co-ordinated policy and(b) they confine the Committee to pronouncing for or against a fund, the character of which, it may be inferred from clause (2)of the terms of reference, would be inadequate in its scope.I am extremely anxOous to be of the utmost assistance in the present emergency in order that the lot of lar^e numbers of wording men and women and their families might be alleviated, but I do not c/Dnsider that the methods of approach suggested by the Government &apos;is the best means of dealing with the present situation.   I have consulted the -uondon members of the National i^-eoutive of the labour tarty, and it was considered inadvisable that I should ta^e part in the wor,i of a Committee whose activities are so narrowly circumscribed    kay I, therefore, urge you to reconsider widening the terms of reference so as to enable the proposed Committee to formulate a national policy for a national emergency?iours sincerely,(Signed) jdiWK HMDfi&amp;SOili&apos;he lit. Hon. jDr. T.J. kacnamara, Ministry of labour,Whitehall, S.W.I.   ,___MOgjfc. Sir i-lian Smith gave his concurrence verbally, and suggestednames of gentlemen who might be invited to represent employers-
EM TO MR, HEI!JffijfSOII.   JPIUAKY 5th.5th January, 1921.Ky dear Henderson,I havo received your letter of January 3rd, and have discussed it with the Prime Minister.We are most anxious not to delay the immediate purpose we have in view by charging the proposed Committee with an investigation into the causes of unemployment.   That mani-festly would involve a olose study of the whole eoonomic position of tho woria to-day - including the state of bankruptcy in which many of our customers abroad find themselves, the position of foreign kxohanges, the relation of production to consumption, the methods and principles of taxation, and many other very difficult and intricate problems which in all human probability would involve months cf continuous labour.   To embark upon such an investigation would of necessity push into the background the problem of dealing vdth the present emergency - a problem which in the view of the Government cannot wait;   and I greatly fear Ihtti any attempt to combine the immediate with the ultimate would only result-in both issues being  QtiEaaofi jand nothing effective done,I very earnestly hope, however, that we may have your/assistance and that of your, colleagues,,   And to this end I suggest and herewith append a Terms of Inference which, particularly as regards Part 1, cover a wide field.As regards Part  , there is raised the question of the feasibility of developing by Industries insurance against Unemployment on a scale more adequate than that of the Act of 1920,   I have always myself looked to the provision in that lot which would enable Industries to develop Special Schemes of their ova aB the most promising -feature in tho
machinery of the Act.   I know that the moment is not altogether auspicious, because of trade depression, but tho Act specially provides :;or an easy and automatic transition up to tho middle, of the present year from the Gonoral Scheme to any Special Scheme that may be devised.I do most sincerely hopo that you and your colleagues in the labour and Trc.de Union movement may be prepared to take part in such an enquiry as my now proposed Torms of Reference would provide for.As I told you in my letter of the 1st January, it is theintention of the Prime Minister to set up a Committee to dealwith the causes of Unemployment;   and if, as I trust, you maylond your aid in proceeding forthwith with tho immediate enquiry,I think it duo to both yourself and Sir Allan Smith that thisshould be made clear in the public announcement of the appoint-mont of the Committee we are hore considering.Very faithfully yours,(Signed)   T. J. laCUAIvIARA.The Kt. Hon. A. Henderson, M.P. 33, Uccleston Squaro, S * w * 1.Enclosure to above :-   TOEM- Off IBgg,.&quot;(l)   To consider and report upon the Schemes nov; in operation for meeting the hardships of tho present Unemployment, and make recommendations.(E)   To consider and report how far it may bo feasible for each Industry or group of Industries to develop schemes of Insurance against Unemployment beyond that provided by the UnemploymentInsurance Act, 1920.&quot;goto       A copy of the revised terms of reference vi&amp;s handed to Sir Allan Smith, who gave his concurrence verbally.
4,   1BU HINDERS OttTS KCPLY TO gJTOK Qg JAHUAKY 5th,THE LADOUft PAHTY.33, Eccloston Sqtiare, London, SJ6.1*6th January, 1921,My dear Maonamara,Thanks for your letter enclosing the revised terms of referonoe of the proposed Committee on Unemployment,   On roceipt of your coannnioatioh Mr, Bowerman and I called together the London menbors of the Labour Party lizeoutive and the Parliamentary Committee of the Trade &quot;Union Congress.This Joint Committee met to-day and your letter and the new suggested terms of reference were very fully discussed.   It was recognised that the scope of the proposed Committee^ work was somewhat widened by the modifications which have been made by the Government in the draft terms of reference, but they are still seriously defective from our point ef view.Tho obJ3otiono to the terms of reforence as they now stand are threefold(l)   The causes t/hich have resulted in the present crisis are oxoluded from them.   As I explained in my previous letter, tho causos of unemployment at the present time must largely determine the policy to be adopted for . dealing with the situation, and it in no way meets our objection that another Committee, of the personnel of vfcioh wo have no Jaiowlodge, will be investigating the ciroumstanoes which have given rise to the present unemployment *(2)   Moreover, the new draft of the terms of reforenceappears to restrict the Committee now proposed in such a way as to preclude any consideration of schemes for dealing with Unemployment other than those already sanotioned.   Clause 1 of tho terms of reference, striotly interpreted, would restrict the suggested Committee to rooommendations on tho 3chcmo now in operation, and would prohibit recommendations as to possible sohemes of other kinds and in othor directions^
^i 1 \ \:&apos;f(3!   Tho second clause of the terms of reference has, in our opinion, no value from the point of view of the present emergency.   Schemes or&quot; the kind con1/orapla G*L even if thare^ is goneral agreement amongst the employers1 a SC-oJLa4ii0&apos;nS and* trade unions concerned, must necessarily take some months to work out and bring into operation.   Thus tho second clause \vould do nothing to alleviate the existing situation, or to assist the revival of industry.In viow of the limited character of tho terms of reference, and tho persistent rofuoal of tho Covemmont to broaden the ooopo of the Comnittoo to include all aspects of tho present crisis, so as to enable it to formulate a comprehensive and practical policy for tho alleviation of tho sufferings of tho unorsployod population and the restoration of industry and trade, tho Joint mooting was of opinion that no good purpose would be -served by tho appointment upon the proposed Committee of labour representatives,I think I ou?ht to inform you that my colleagues felt unable to convince themselves that there was any evidence that the Government contemplated, on the report of the Conmittoc, any immediate assistance from the I^cheajier of a substantial character for dealing with the present emergency.    It wa&apos;s felt that tho  v failure of the Government to adopt the proposals relating to unemployment, and undor-cmployment, unaniDOusly agreed to as long as tho 4th April 1919 by the representative employers and workmen whom tho Government itself had invited to constitute the Industrial Confer once, afforded no encouragement to join a nev Committee,   I may point out that the recent Government declaration of policy as to Short Time disregards in important respects tho recommendations then unanimously agreed to on that subject by the Employers and the ) Employed.   % colleagues felt stronc.ly that tho terrible conditionsof hunger and want alroady manifest in ten thousand of homes;   the \ ularminr prospect of tho number of the sufferors increasing daily at a rate almost without parallel;   the absence of any prospect oi inaaedlato action being taken to set going our foreign trade whore it has now almost ceased, amount, together, to such a state of social
bankruptcy as to demand something very much more effective than any Committee with a reforenco of oo limited a nature as that now proposed.Under those Qircumstancos my colloa^uos saw no use in any of thorn talcing part in its deliberations.Yours sincerely,fsgd) Ad&apos;imi mvhi&amp;auThe Right Eon. Dr. 1\J, Hacnamara, M.P. Ministry of Labour, Montagu Houso, Whitehall, S i ii 11101-&apos; Jiil-UiftY 7th to M^^imiim^^.....SIR   ALLAH   SMITH.7th January, 1921.My dear Henderson,I am in receipt of your letter of yesterday.   The problem of Unemployment to-day is acute and already inflicting grave hardships upon tons oi thousands of people,   l-o met on Christmas Day to see if we could not dovise suoh further means of mitigation and alleviation as the situation may demand. I cannot believe that differences as to methods of procedure will prevent our co-operation in so grave a matter.
Lot mo therefore make those further proposals on procedure.   As regards your roquost - put forward both by you and Sir Allan Smith from the outcot - that the enquiry should cover tho causoc which havo led to, as well as the immediate remedios for tho present Unemployment, I havo in my cor:ospondonce with you &quot;stated our view on that course.   .*o really must not allow tho immediate and pressing duty of alloviating the present distress to he hung up by a nooossarily longthy and difficult investigation.And even if this wero not so, it must be quite cloar that a Committee competent to advise on causes would necessarily need to bo differently constituted from a Committoe competent to advise on the provision of immediate remedies.   It was for those reasons that the Prime Minister suggested the appointment of a separate Committee charged to go into the causes of present Unemployment, to serve upon which, of course, Labour Representatives would hare been invited.I havo consulted the lyimo Ministor in respect of your letter of yesterday.     Recognising the orbrcme gravity of tho Unemployment problem, he foels, as do wo all, that no stone must be loft unturnec. in order to moot the situation.   Ho therefore authorises mo to make the following suggestions to you - and of course to Sir Allan Smith at the same time - narroly, that tho reference to the proposod Committeo of Enquiry/should
3hould bo as followsj-(1)   To consider ant- report upon the causes, that have led to the present Unemployment, and to make recom nendat ions : there on.(2)   To consider and report within one month upon theschemes now in operation for meeting the hardships of tho present Unemployment, and to make reoommienda* tions as to their adequacy, and if found to be Inadequate, to ma;:e recommendations for their improvement.(5)   To consider and. report within threo months how for it may be feasible for each Industry or group of Industries to develop schemes of Insuranoe against Unemployment beyond that provided by the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.In order.to meet the necessities of this wider reference,it uould be accessary, and I venture to think you bill here not-Usar-roe, to add to the proposed personnel of the Committeemembers specially competent to advise as to certain aspectsof causes,   fce should therefore propose to constitute it asfollows J-5 Representatives of Lmployers,5 Representatives of Labour.4 Representatives chosen r:ith special regardto Para-raph 1 of the terms of Reference; and a Chairman.Let me again sincerely express the hope that you and your colleagues in the Labour anc. Trad? Union -movement may be prepared to take part in the   enquiry under the Terms of Reference now survested.Very faithfully yours, (Sgd.) T.0&apos;.   MACNAMARA.The KttHon.A. enderson, VI.p., 55,  ecleeton Square,S..Y.1,
Q 9ho7th January, 1921.My dear Allan Smith,I rooeivcd yeeterday a letter from Henderson in which he states that he and his colleagues see no use in talcing part in tho deliberations of the Committee called together with the reference which you were so good as to concur in v;hen I caw you earlier in the week.   I have consulted the Prime Minister again and have sent Henderson a further letter, oopy of which I herewith enclose to you.   That lettor, as you will see, and for the reasons stated therein, suggests a revised terms of reference.Would you bo so good as to say whether you would be prepared to assist in the enquiry as now proposed.Very faithfully yours.(Sgd)   Te J* Macnaaara.Sir Allan Smith, IC3,E.fM.P. 9, Oakhill Avenue, B.V.3.(6)   MR. HBKBShSOlPS HP PLY TO EHB I&amp;TTLR Off JAOTJAHT 7th.mi LABOUR PARTY,33, Lcoleston Square, London, S*u*l* January 12th, 1921.Hight Hon. T.J. Macnamara, M.P., Ministry of Labour, Montagu House, S *Vi .1*My dear macnamara,The Joint Meeting of tho two national oommittoes held yesterday instructed mo to forward you a oopy of the enclosed resolution, whioh contains the decision regarding the proposed Unemployment Enquiry.The correspondence and drafts of the suggested Terms of Reference, together with a statement by pysclf as to the negotia-tions were before the meeting and as reported to your secretary over the telephone, it was unanimously agreed not to accept appointment to the committee.Yours sincerely,(S gd)   ARTHUR HBfiSBBSOH.
Oopy;t) . ReiK^ with above letters-The Joint Meeting of the parliament^merrUary&apos; Committee of the Trades Union Congress and the National Executive of the Labour Party unardmously rejects the Government^ invitation to appoint representatives to a Committee of Inquiry upon Unemployment; and decider to appoint its own Committee to formulate practical schemes for- securing immediate relief for those now unemployed^ and definite proposals for dealing &quot; ith the whole problem as one of national urgency;   suoh schemes and proposals to be submitted for consideration and endorsement to a special Joint National Conference of the Trade Union Movement and the Labour Party on 27th January,1921 The Joint Meeting regrets that the Government has disregarded the warnings of, and failed to give timely effect to the preventive and remedial measures suggested by the successive National and Inter-Allied Labour Conferences during 1917* 1918, and 1919, and even the Joint Industrial Conference of 1919, which was summoned by the Government itself, with an undertaking that its finding would be embodied in immediate legislation.The only proposal that has emanated from the Government in the present crisis is one for the universal extension of short time, without any consideration, either of the diminution of home demand ihich this would create, or of the lowering of the standard of life and consequent suffering of the entire wage-earning class which would ensuet   This Joint Meeting emphatically declares this proposal to be inadmissiblej and to be, as a universal policy, impracticable; anc even as a partial measure, unsatisfactory, by reason of the absence of any provision of under-employment allowances in respect of the time lost.The/
The Joint Meetvjg further calls attention to the resolution of the Special Labour Conference on 29th December, 1920, which the Government appears to have ignored.j   and refers that resolution, together with the proposal already named, to thn Committee now to be appointed for elaboration into a definite programme and policy, to be commended to the Labour Movement for such action as it may deem necessary, and to be pressed upon the Government, and; unless action is immediately taken, at the beginning of the Session upon the House of Commons,

</content>
</cab>
