<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/118/0 images: 462-469</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
if to be destroyed v/hen replaced by a subsequent number.SE0R?P ADMIRALTY V/EBKLY   INTELLIGENCE   SUMMARy.No. 2.   15th January, 1921.Issued by the Naval Intelligence Division. Naval Staff, Admiralty, for the Information of Recipients only.DISTRIBUTION.Sent by All British Route to Copies.0 codestard of Admiralty.................. 10ci (Nav. Sec. ,S.A. S. ,A. S. P.) ........ 3ty Captain........................ 19 Cabinet (O.I.D.) ................ 40c., Navy Board, Melbourne......... 1ector Naval Service, Ottawa ...... 1A.N.A.C........................... 111Admiralty Naval StaffI.D............0..D................P.D................T.D................Intelligence Officers18 3 2 1of Naval Section, Paris val Representative,........League of Nationsmanders^in-chief the Nore .......Portsmouth .....Plymouth .......Scotland .......W.Approaches ... Atlantic .......N.A. k W.I.....mediterranean china.......East Indies .Africa ......S.America ..* t  * *  *************l&apos;C,lst Battle Squadron..........^0.,2nd Battle Squadron..........(f*0.,Re serve Fleet.................1*, Battle Cruiser Squadron .......*i 1st Battle Squadron............I&apos;, 2nd Battle Squadron ...........Im 1st Light Oruioer Sqn.........podore, 2nd Light Or. Sqn........*) 3rd Lisjit Cruiser Sqn.........* i 8th Light Or. Sqn..............* * Mediterranean.................* ? Yangtse .. *..........*.........?.W).............................dore, Australian Fleet.........frnodore, New Zealand ............i H.M.S. &quot;Malaya&quot; ...............TOTAL (Distributed by Copying Branch)1 1 1 1 1 2 1 1 1 1 1 11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1. 1 1 1 1S.I.0&apos;s -Mediterranean.......   1China...............   1East Indies .........   13* America..........   1N. America..........   1D.I.0&apos;s -Portsmouth..........   1Chatham.............   1Devonport...........   1Rosyth ..............   1Hull................   1Liverpool...........   11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1.........Queenstovm .Gibraltar ...........Malta ..............*Colombo.............Singapore ...........Shanghai............Wellington..........Cape Town...........Bermuda .............Ascension...........   liason 1.0., MeIbourne,N.L.O., Hong Kong .....N.L.O., Cairo..........N.V.C, Monte Video .... N.V.C., Oallao ........1 1 1 11TOTAL   (I. D. 50Distribution)
SHORET admiralty in&apos;fgLLIGgJigB   SIMMPY. &apos; (W.I.S.)No. 2.   For the week ending 15th January, 1921*PART I.   NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. (fRFAT ,, BRITAIN. , Principal Movements of H.I-/I. Ship3.&quot;Dauntless&quot; arrived Bevonport from Copenhagen.H...C.S. &quot;Betfbioe&quot; arrived Portsmouth from the Mediterranean.H.M.S. &quot;Greenwich&quot; left Portsmouth for Arosa Bay.PRO GRA U M 5 S.1st Li/^it Cruiser Squadron - leaves Portland 1st February (&quot;Dauntless&quot; Joins on completion of leave). Horta, Azores 5th - 10th February. Ponta Delgada, Azores, 11th - 15th February.   Funohal 17th - 28th February.   Las Palmas 1st - 10th March. &apos; (2 ships visit Tsneriffe 1st - 5th March, and possibly 2 ships Casa Blanoa 7th - 11th March)   Gibraltar 12th - 17th March.H.M.S. &quot;Centaur&quot; leaves Malta shortly, visiting Palermo, Cagliari, Port Mah on, Pa lira, i&amp;jprca, Valencia and Malaga arriving Gibraltar for refit 28th January (approx.)H.:.!1.S. &quot;Iron Duke&quot;.loaves Malta 21st February for Portsmouth to re commission.   Returns to Malta 21st March (approxH.M.3. &quot;Cardiff&quot;, leaves Malta 3rd February (approx.) for Smyrna, Lemnos and Constantinople.   Due Constantinople 11th February.   Leaves 15th February visiting; North Anatolian Coast and Batoum returning; 24th February.H.M.S.S. &quot;AJax&quot; and &quot;Centurion&quot;, leave Malta 31st January7- on cruise to Smyrna and Constantinople.&quot;AJax&quot; returns to Malta 18th February.SECRET.To &quot;be destroyed, when replaced by a subsequent number.
RUSSIA.The Soviet Government have issued the following Black Sea Port regulations as complement to the regulations as to the entry of foreign ships into Russian ports, oonmnicated to Foreign Governments in the radios of (? June) 12, 1920, and of July 24th, 1920, the Russian Government hereby notify that certain portions of the territorial waters of Russia in the Black Sea are mined and guarded by means of other methods of defence. For that reason Foreign ships entering Russian territorial waters in the Black Sea run tho risk of being destroyed on the minefield and are therefore invited not to proceed in the Black Sea beyond the line which is at a distance of12 miles.............. from the Russian coast, except intho caso of any place where such an advance is authorised by the above mentioned radios.   The disregard of the present orders will result in the artillery taking all the usual measures instituted under the law of nations for cases of ships violating the maritime police regulations published by the sovereign state concerned.(Sgd.)      TCHITCH3RIN.12th January, 1921.SWEDEN.Engineer Officers of the Swedish Mercantile Marine have declared a strike from the New Year, to get owners to agree to a considerable increase in wages.   All Swedish Steamers in coastal and foreign trade are affected.     The Owners expect the struggle to be protracted and are reported to be laying up their ships as a result of the strike.G E R M A N Y.Naval Bases.   On 1st April 1921, the fortresses of Pillau and Swinemnnde will be transferred from the Army to the Navy.Ex-German Stoamers.   In November 1920 five ex-German steamers and in December seven were sold at an average price of about  10 per ton.Peace Treaty Article 357 (Rhine tonnage),   The American arbitratofoecTfled&apos; that Germany is to code to Franco barges amounting to 250,150 tons and tugs of 23761 H.P., also certain harbour facilities at Rotterdam, the property of a German company on 1st August 1914, and certain&quot;Rhine shipping shares.    Unless the two countries can come to an agreement as to details by the 10th February 1921, the arbitrator will give his final decision which rail take effect on the 10th May 1921.D.feared U B S.It has been decided that all armour is to be removed from those monitors of the ex-Austro-Hungarian Flotilla which are to be used as pontoons.BLACK    SEA.The British destroyer patrol in the Black Sea has been withdrawn but, whenever practicable, H.M.Ships will continue to stop and search vessels suspected of arms traffic.
PORTUGAL.The sloops &quot;Republica&quot; (ex H.&apos;..:.S. &quot;Gladiolus11) and &quot;Oarvalho Aranrjo&quot; (ex H..::.S. &quot;Jonquil&quot;) sailed from Dovonport for Lisbon on 14th January.? R A N CHI.The Li^it Cruiser 11 Strasbourg&quot; (ex-German * Regans burg&quot;) now fitting out at Brest ani expected to be ready for service during the 2nd quarter o&quot; this year, will ,iake her first oruiso under the French ?lag to South American ports.     This cruise will extend over two or tlire3 months.     On completion of this the 11 Strasbourg&quot; vdll probably relieve the &quot;Jurien de la Graviere11 in the Syrian Squadron.BELGIUM.The &quot;Thetis11, the last ship   blocking   the entrance to the port of Seebruggo, was successfully shifted clear of the channel on 11th January, under the Supervision of Coraaodore Sir Rredericx ^7. Young, K.B.E., R.N.R.
PART   II.------------...... 0 ^MH!nOPO^AKIA.It is reported that tho leading instigators of tho insurrection in Mesopotamia.arrived at Doir ez Bor about the beginning of December, Yusif Assuwaidi being the ldader of the party.   It is further reported that they are en route to Turkey.Over 50,000 rifles have now been surrendered and over one and a half million rounds of ammunition.The Defence vessel &quot;Greenfly&quot; has been tewed toNasiriya.PERS J. A *The Shah has informed our Minister at Teheran that he cannot bear to remain at Teheran under constant threat of attack by the Bolsheviks and that he has resolved to abdicate and leave the country as a private individual.RUSSIA.North Russia.   It is reported that tho Soviet Government at 1T\q end of December 1920 sent a Commission of Specialists to work out Coast Defence plans for the Murmansk District.Interpal,Reports fram Russia state that Moscow is becoming alarmed at the general indications of anti-Bolshevik feeling. The revival of religious feeling had obliged the authorities to permit the reopening of churches, and the clergy, despite persecution, wore preaching against Bolsheviks.   Moscow on 31st December 1920, announced that gradual demobilisation is to commence and the army is to be reduced to half its present strength by the middle of 1921*   Tiflis reports that Trotsky, in a telegram dated 20th December 1920, deplores ;jtb.e madid&amp;sire of the mobilised to return home&quot;;, which is demoralising the Army, and directs that &quot;all deserters and their families are to be shot without mercy&quot;, also &quot;a red terror against capitalists and Bourgeois both Russian and foreign, and their representatives throughout - the world..Latvia.   The RuFso-Lottish frontier commission to detexroine the &quot;frontier IriMts between Latvia and Russia held its first meeting at Riga on January 8th.   A second Soviet commission has also&quot;arrived at Riga to make arrangements for Railway inter- comurd oat ion with Russia..Aj^erl^ijan.;The report thai a large number of Soviet troops have left, Georgian and Armenian frontiers is confirmed.   4fter plundering Baku, many left by train for Russia.Trans-Oaucasia and Trtan?;j0oSj)la.Since the evacuation of the Crimea by //rangel, Soviet forces have been increased west of the Caspian, on ike Armavir -Georgievsk - Baku, Akstafa Railway.   A large increase is also reported in Trans-Caspia.     These increased are chiefly drawn from      (l) Central Russian reserve, (2) Units in South Russia, (3) Units in Kuban.
Unrest is prevalent due to the present small ration, and lack of clothing, hut ruthless requisitioning is to he undertaken to make up the deficiency.   Special disciplinary units have heen organised to meet the above and they can be relied on to maintain authority as they receive preferential treatment.   It would therefore be unwise to overrate the importance of factors tending to the lower efficiency of the Army whioh must obviously keep multiplying in order to support itself.Georgia.The Bolshevik Mission at Tiflis has had no tf/T communication with1 Moscow since 3th January 1921.   It appears to attribute this to serious disorders in Central Russia. The same Mission was informed from Baku on 10th January 1921, that insurgents had destroyed the railway between Baku and Derbcnt.   Risings have occ/arrod in North Caucasus, chiefly of Chechens, and also in the South where the insurgents have ocdupied Lenkoran.   Other sources confirm the risings in North Caucasus.   In the South the insurgents appear to be Persian Shahsavas tribesmen who invaded&quot;Bolshevik territory and were Joined by the local population.   Persian Consul General at Tiflis confirms this.GERMANY.Reparations.   Representations have been made to the German Government to agree in principle to an rannuity of three milliard gold marks for five years.The principal German contention is that, unless the Upper Silesdan plebiscite goes in favour of Germany, her capacity to support this burden would be doubtful and that a Government agreeing to these terms would be swept out of office.DANZIG.lieutenant General Sir Richard Haking, K.0.B.,K.0.M.G., the new High Commissioner, is expected to arrive at Danzig on the 24th January.AUSTRIA.Tho restless state of Austria continues.   Railway and postal communications are practically at a standstill.ARABIA.   .The withdrawal of the British garrison from Hodeidah will take plaoo about 22nd January.ITALY.Although it is praotically certain that Signor Giolitti intends to dissolve Parliament, still it is known that he will not resort to this extreme moasure oxcept in case of necessity.   His intention is to prolong tho adjournment of Parliament for a couple of months, in order-to devote all his energies towards striving to settle the internal situation -::r both repressive and persuasive methods against the Extremists n -1 the Pascisti.
ITALY (contd.)The greatest and most serious menace to Italy is not due to either political, labour, or revolutionary agitations, but to the disastrous economic conditions of the country, which are being aggravated to such an extent that no remedy appears possible &quot;to avert national bankruptcy.ROMANIA.The Russian Soviot Government deny any hostile intentions towards Rumania. They account for the concentration of troops as being merely a preliminary step in the process of demobilisation.Reports have been received foreshadowing the probable early fall of the Averesou Government.TURKEY.The following summary of the situation in Turkey has been received .-The Government&apos;s attitude towards the Nationalists is undoubtedly one of sympathy, but being alive to the reality of the situation its point of&apos; view is less extreme.   The Government in brief is anxious to secure as many of tho Nationalist demands as possible, without risking a rupture with the Allies or adopting an attitude of defiance. The Government is refuting&quot;various reports regarding the ratification of the treaty in the hope that the change in tho situation!), produced by tho return of Constantino to Greece, may automatically result in a modification of the Treaty of Sevres sufficient to secure its acceptance by Angora.The Government Mission of reconciliation, under Izzet Pasha, reached Angora about 7th December, but no results havo been officially reported or appear to havo been achieved. Tho Mission is now believed to have been recalled, and to have left Angora on the 29th December.   The absence of any definite result is believed to be due to the Government Mission holding out about the Treaty regarding Smyrna and Thrace, whioh appears still to be the pervading ground for Nationalist defiance.   Hitherto Mustapha Kemal Pasha has been sitting on the fence between compromise with the Central Government and Allies on the one hand, and irrevocable conjunction with the Bolsheviks on the other.JUnver Pasha is now believed to be in Berlin.   It is reported that ho has had a serious disagreement with tho Soviet Government, and with Talaat, and&quot;fears to return to Russia.General Karington reports that signs of unrest aro manifesting themselvds&apos;among the Russian refugees in the concentration camps in the Straits zone, especially among the Cossacks9   It is also reported that the French Government propose shortly to withdraw their financial assistance to the refugees, in which case a situation of considerable gravity will arise, especially as it is understood that a considerable number of the refugees are still in possession of arms.   The above applies also to Lemnos, where a large number of regugees have been landed, and the 0. in 0. Mediterranean, &quot;has called attention to the difficulties which may confront the small R.M, garrison still maintained there should disturbances occur.
Asia Minor.A Greek advance on the northern position of the front has recently been launched. &apos; Greek troops have advanood on the line Bazar Keui - Aksu (about 13 miles east of Brusa) and the advance has already reached the Anatolian railway. It is understood that the objective is Eskishehr, the occupation of which place according to the original programme was to have been achieved on Jan, 9th.FRANCE.On January 12th the Prime Minister, M, Leygues, having asked the Chamber not to press interpellations pending the meeting of the Supreme Council at Paris on 19th January, the Chamber refused by 463 vote to 125, and Mons. Leygues irmnediatoly resigned,    M. Briand was called upon to form a Ministry,The Chamber is decidedly pro-British in tone, but it is determined that the new Ministry will insist on pressing the French viow in regard to disarmament and reparations.On 16th January, M. Briand was able to form a Cabinet, and himself takes the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.   M. Guist&apos; Hau is the new Minister of Marine.CHINA.It is officially reported that the friction between the Portuguese authorities at MACAO and the Chinese, which arose in December 1919 over the question of dredging in MACAO harbour, has boon satisfactorily settled.

</content>
</cab>
