<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 58-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNME$ )SECRET9 7C..P.(50) 158COPY NoiiZ&apos;5TH JULY, 1950CABINETTHE SMITHFIELD strike memorandum by the Home secretary in accordance with the arrangements approved by the Cabineton 29th June (CM. (50) 40th Conclusions, Minute 5), 640 Service vehicles and between 2,000 and 3,000 Servicemen are this week being usedto move meat from the cold stores to Smithfield and from Smithfieldto the retailers.    The Minister of Food expects to be able to supply a ration of l/4d. worth of carcase meat per head this week in the london area, and to make up the remainder with corned beef.2. On 5th July Service vehicles and men began handlinggeneral provisions (e. g. butter, cheese and bacon) which they are takingfrom warehouses in the Smithfield area to the retailers.    This wasnecessary because a strike of drivers and warehousemen employed bywholesale provision merchants in the Smithfield area, which started on 3rd July as a protest against the use of troops in Smithfield, made itnecessary for Service assistance to be given to the wholesale provisionmerchants if the rations of these commodities in the London area for thisweek were to be met.3. Orders have been given that neither the Servicemen working on meat nor those working on general provisions should enter tiiedock area this week.   By the end of the week, however, the cold storeswhich are not in the dock area will be practically exhausted of meat, andon Monday, 10th July, it will be necessary for Servicemen to begin workon the cold stores in the dock area.   Moreover, by 12th or 13th July theServicemen will have&apos;to begin to get meat from the ships in the docks if,as may be expected, the dockers refuse to deliver it to cold stores wheretroops are operating.    It will also be necessary next week for theServicemen to get general provisions from Hay&apos;s Wharf cold stores in orderto maintain the bacon ration.4. Imports of meat into London Docks total approximatelyo00,000 tons a year or an average of nearly 12,000 tons a week.   The rateof arrival varies between 5,000 and 30,000 tons per week.   The total amount of meat which passes through Smithfield every week is on average5,000 tons, the requirement to meet the ration for the London area, and ofthis, on average, 4,000 tons is imported meat.   If in a given week, say,12,000 tons of meat (the average figure) came into the London Docks, itmight be disposed of as follows:-(a) One-quarter of Smithfield&apos;s 4,000 tons per week of imported meat, i.e. 1,000 tons, would go to Smithfield direct fromthe docks.(b)7,000 tons would be moved from the docks into Londoncold stores.

9 o(:i 0(c) 3,000 tons would be moved into provincial cold stores.(d) 1,000 tons would go direct to meat depots outside London.This is how things would work out in a typical week, but the disposal ofthe supplies would vary from week to week according to the arrivalsin the docks (varying from 5,000 to 30,000 tons) and also to the stock position in London and the country   generally (stocks may be anythingfr om 50,000 to 200,000 tons according to the time of the year).    Thetotal capacity of all the London cold stores averages 125,000 tons of meat and general provisions, .but varies according to the balance of the commodities which are stored.    If they were all filled with meat thetotal capacity would be 100,000 tons.   At present stocks are low andthe cold stores outside the docks will be virtually emptied of meat thisweek, while the stocks in the cold stores in the docks are not sufficientto provide a full meat ration for London next week and will be exhaustedwithin two or three days.5. When the Servicemen enter the dock area, whether to work incold stores or to work in ships, there is a strong likelihood that the dockers, or a considerable section of them, will come out on strike.The Ministry of Food state that, while most of the doc.-, cold stores arein the area of the Royal Group, they would have difficulty in obtainingenough meat if they confined themselves to this Group.6. If the use of Service labour in the dock area on Monday gives rise to a serious strike of doc^ workers it is necessary to decide:(a) whether Service labour should, so far as possible, be used only for handling essential foodstuffs.    (Sometimes there isa mixed cargo of food and other goods. )(b) whether an attempt should be made to work the waole of the docks (or so much as may be affected) with Service labour.If course (a) is followed, the 1,000 vehicles and 6,000 men which theService Departments will have available in London on Monday, withthe addition of certain naval technicians for the dock work, would be enough to meet the situation for a few days and even after that it would notbe necessary to add greatly to the number of men and vehicles.   Ifcourse (b) is decided upon, additional Servicemen would be needed byearly next week, and it would be necessary thereafter to increase thenumber rapidly.    How many additional men would be needed in allwould depend on how far the strike spread in the docks, but up to a totalof 20,000 might be required. . The Emergencies Committee after con-sidering this matter were unanimously in favour of limiting the effort bythe Services to course (a) as far as possible, though it should be recognisedthat if a dock strike went on lor any length of time the pressure to handlegeneral cargoes as apart from food and to load ships as well as unloadingthem in order to keep the port working, would grow very strong.7. If the Service Departments are required to implement course(b) above it will cause most serious difficulties of accommodation for themen brought to London..   It is doubtful whether they could provide vehicles and drivers to transport 20,000 men daily from barracksto the docks as well as the vehicles being used for moving meat and provisions and it will have grave effects on their own commitments.These effects are described in the following paragraphs.-2-

8- By next Monday, 10th July, on present plans, the services will have provided approximately 6,000 men (2,000 drivers, 4,000 troops and administrative personnel) and 1,000 vehicles and these, perhapswith limited reinforcements, will probably be sufficient to handlep.erishable goods.   The effects of withdrawing a force of this size fromthe Services are serious and will become more so, the longer the period for which it is committed.    Thus a variety of training will be deferredand dislocated;   there is a risk that Territorial Army, Reserve forces and Cadet Camps may have to be cancelled;   the maintenance anddistribution of equipment will also suffer.9. All this, however, is on the basis of a limited commitment which can be met from selected units in order, so far as possible, to limit its effects on the operational and training programmes of theServices,   If, however, it were decided that the Services must work theLondon Docks completely (i. e. if they were no longer to be confined tothe handling of perishable goods), the number of men involved would riseto about 20,000 plus administrative backing.   In these circumstances theeffect on the Services would be much more serious, particularly at thepresent time when training programmes are at their height.    This effect is not simply to be measured in terms of numbers;   the troops posted tothe docks fall particularly into certain specialist categories, e. g. drivers,signallers and cooks, and their removal from their units affects thefunctioning of their units as a whole.    The ill-effects of the withdrawal ofmen on this scale are heightened, too, by the state of unbalance between thevarious trades, arising from post-war recruiting difficulties, from whichthe Services are already suffering.10. Accordingly, if 20,000 men were required training programmes would have to be very severely curtailed.    The summer camps of theTerritorial Army, the Cadet    Forces and the Reserve Forces generally would certainly be affected seriously through the withdrawal of Regularadministrative personnel and transport.    Overseas drafts would have tobe held up.    The training of the Army strategic reserve formations wouldbe suspended.    Operational units in the R.A.F. would have to be groundedon a large scale.    In addition, of course, it would raise major administrative problems in the spheres both of transport and quartering.11. To provide 20,000 troops with administrative backing andtheir accompanying vehicles would mean drawing in men from all overthe United Kingdom and would strain the resources of the Services tothe limit.   It must be realised, therefore, that if the strikes spread beyondLondon the Services could not help much further.12. At Appendix A is a list of recent industrial disputes in whichthe Services have been involved or in which preparations for using them have had to be made.   All these cases have involved a considerablediversion of effort to the detriment of the proper tasks of the Services.The Minister of Defence and the Service Ministers urge the Cabinet toweigh carefully the serious effects upon the Services of diversions of thiskind in considering whether they should be committed to further intervention in the present dispute.13. The Emergencies Committee recommend accordingly that theGovernment should approve the use of Service labour to obtain meat andgeneral provisions from the cold stores at the docks and wharves and, when necessary, from ships, from Monday, 10th July, but that the work of theServicemen should be limited as far as possible to dealing with essential foodstuffs.J C EHome Office, S. W. 1. ,5TH JULY, 1.950.

APPENDIX ALIST OP RECENT INDUSTRIAL DISPUTESINVOLVING THE&quot; SERVICESSerialDateIIIDisputeRemarksHI1.       April, 1949LONDON Dock StrikeAll preparationsincluding assembly oftroops for use of6100 troops and 1200vehicles from all three Services, butnot actually used.2.       May/ June,  1949AVONMOUTH Dock Strike800 Army, 100 R.N.and LOO R.A.P.employed in docksfor nearly threeweeks.3.       June, 1949LIVERPOOL Dock StrikeAll preparationsincluding assemblytroops for use of700 Army, 120 R.N.and 800 R.A.P.  butnot actually used.ofk.       June, 1949NEWPORT Dock StrikeAll preparationsmade for use of2100 Army,  1400 R.A.P.and 500 vehicles butnot actually used.No movement of troops.5.       June, 19496.       July, 1949Threatened railwaystrikeThreatened LONDONElectricity Power-StrikePreparations did not go further thanpreliminary planning.Preparatory actionbut no actualmovement of troops.July, 1949LONDON Dock StrikeServices worked docksfor just under threeweeks.      total numbers employed1-7,000 men and1200 vehicles.

Q&apos;1,u&quot;ialDateHEDisputezmzRemarksfay0.September,  1949       BELFAST ElectricityPower strikeServices operatedpower stations for. aweek.      About 250 men employed.9.        September,  1949       SMITHFIELD StrikePreparatory actiononly for use of600 vehicles.October, 1949Threatened BELFASTElectricity PowerStrikePreparatory actiononly.December, 1949LONDON ElectricityPower StrikeFour power stationsoperated for just under a week,    420 menfrom all three Servicesemployed.12.        April,  3r9*T9*LONDON Dock StrikeServices worked docksfor just under threeweeks.      Total numbers employed 20,000 menand 645 vehicles.13.        June,SMITHFIELD DriversStrike1500 men and 660vehicles of Army andR. A.F.   at work.Expected build-up to5,000 men and 1,000vehicles.Note Where figures are quoted they represent only the effective labour force and effective numbers ofload-carrying vehicles.      The administrativebacking normally comprises an approximate increaseof 15 per cent for the labour force and 10 per cent for vehicles.


</content>
</cab>
