<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 120-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  document  is the  property of  his   britannic   majesty&apos;s   governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 1950SECRETCP. (50) 163llth July, 1950Copy No.CABINETSHORT-TERM MEASURES TO INCREASE COAL PRODUCTIONMemorandum by the Minister of Fuel and power at the Cabinefs meeting on 15th June (CM. (50) 36th Conclusions, Minute 4),I was invited to submit a memorandum on the steps which might be taken in the short-term to increase the total output of coal by accelerating the technical develop-ments which were taking place in the industry. This invitation arose out of mysuggestion that in the long run increased mechanisation could offset the declinein the labour force, and out of the fears we all felt that exports might have to bereduced during the current year.2. Mechanisation is a somewhat loose term which we have been accustomed to use for general convenience. But it shoujd. be realised that it covers the useof new machines for old, as well as the replacement of hand methods by machinery;and that the new machines may be of types locomotives are an example which require radical changes in the whole lay-out of a mine before they can be installed.In the following paragraphs I have briefly described the main lines on whichmechanisation is proceeding, differentiating, so far as possible, between those formswhich can be installed with comparatively slight changes in lay-out and methodsof working, and going on to make some assessment of the results which might beobtained from concentrating upon short-term measures as against long-termdevelopments. I feel bound to add, however, that the appreciation that follows isthat of a layman and not of a technician, for, as my colleagues are aware, I haveno mining engineers on my staff apart from the Inspectorate. 1 felt, moreover,that it was hardly appropriate at this stage to seek the expert opinion of the coal board upon the matter which had been remitted to me, but in certain circumstances(to which I refer in paragraph 30 below) it might be worth doing so.3. There are three main fields in which mechanisation and measures of reorganisation are being applied, though, of course, there are innumerable activitiesof less fundamental importance to which new plant or machinery is being applied.The main fields are: (i) face mechanisation; (ii) transport reorganisation, covering the underground roadways, shaft bottoms, shafts, and shaft tops; and (iii) surfaceworks. I will briefly discuss each of these.(i) Face Mechanisation4. One of the most important conclusions of the Reid Report was that thepre-war efforts to improve output per man shift had substantially failed becausemechanisation had started at the wrong end: efforts had been concentrated on the face, where a large quantity of machinery was installed to facilitate the getting ofthe coal, without prior or simultaneous efforts to ensure that the coal could be moved smoothly and expeditiously away from the face to the surface. Under-ground transport, it was pointed out, had become a bottle-neck, and the greater the rate of output from the face the more prejudicial became the limit of transport.5. The first job which the Coal Board took in hand was to try to increasecoal output in a matter of months, and to start with there was considerable scope for the. installation of conventional types of coal face machinery, such as coal-cutters and face conveyors, and for the replacement of the older machines of this39005 b
type which had suffered the wear and tear of wartime use. A great influx of these machines occurred in the first two years of the Board&apos;s work, but the time has now come when there is little more scope for this kind of mechanisation.6. The next step forward in the way of face mechanisation is the installation,where conditions permit, of machines which load the coal mechanically, or, betterstill, combine in one operation both the cutting of the coal and its loading on tothe conveyor. The best known and most widely used machine of this type is theMeco-Moore cutter-loader, and by 1949, 3-6 million tons were mechanically butand loaded by these machines. It is by no means everywhere, however, that suchmachines as the Meco-Moore can be installed. It is essential to their efficient working that the underground transport should be capable of dealing with thegreater output of the faces on which these machines are being used. Moreover,natural underground conditions impose limitations on their use, and there havebeen many cases in which, for these reasons, and because of the failure of the human factors, the machines have had to be withdrawn or have achieved results which fell seriously short of those expected.7. Several other types of machines are being developed and tried out, someof which, such as the Samson Stripper, show great promise. Three SamsonStrippers are in use; each produces 100,000 tons of coal per annum, with only fiveworkers on the machine. They reduce dust and the risk of accidents, and they donot break up coal as other cutting machines tend to. They may be suitable for20 per cent, of British seams; a new model is being prepared which may be suitablefor thinner seams. The National Coal Board have ordered a much larger numberOf the present model.8. So far as mechanisation at the face is concerned it can be assumed that itis only by the use of such new machines as these that any striking increase in output per man shift at the face will be obtained; that none of the machines thusfar developed is as yet suitable for all conditions in the same way as is the well-established conventional coal cutter; and that a great deal of practical experimental work is necessary in connection with each machine installed.9. To conclude: there is no material scope remaining for the mechanisationof face working along conventional lines, while the use of the newer machinescan only be gradually expanded after extensive trials of their applicability to theconditions prevailing on individual faces. I am satisfied that the Board are doing everything possible to hasten the installation of these machines.(ii) Underground Haulage10. The conditions of the underground haulage was found by the ReidReport to be the greatest weakness of all in British mining technique, and damningcomparisons were made with the tonnage handled per man in other countries.Not only is this the most serious defect of technique, but it is also one which requires a long time and heavy expenditure to rectify. Moreover, its limitations exercisean important influence on the rate at which the face output can be increased.11. There are two main methods of improving underground haulage: thefirst is to install conveyors on a much bigger scale on the roads; the second isto install locomotive haulage.12. The National Coal Board have in fact already installed very large numbersof &quot; gate &quot; conveyors, that is comparatively small conveyors which take the coal from a single face and deliver it into tabs or mine cars at a loading point a fewhundred yards from the face.13. An alternative to loading into tubs is discharge on to larger &quot;trunk&quot;conveyors, serving two or more faces, which usually deliver the coal into tubsnearer the winding shaft. In a few cases, these conveyors may extend all the wayto the shaft, and occasionally, by a drift, to the surface. The main difficulty abouttrunk conveyors is their cost, and the manner in which the mine has been laid out.Normally, too, the coal has to be transferred at some point into tubs for winding up the shaft. It is generally cheaper, as well as more convenient, to effect this transfer at some distance from the the shaft. There is now no shortage of machinesof this type, but there are practical and economic reasons for limiting the numberinstalled.
14. The installation of conveyers usually means that manpower savings canbe effected, and this has been a substantial source of additional manpower for &quot; up-grading &quot; to the face. Several examples of manpower economies by the use ofconveyors installed as a short-term measure are quoted in the report of theNational Coal Board for 1949. At three Kent collieries 80 haulage workers were saved; at Markham colliery in the East Midlands 100 haulage workers were released for upgrading to the face, and output was increased by 15 per cent, in1949; at other collieries in other Divisions similar results were obtained.15. The other main method of reorganising underground transport is bythe installation of locomotive haulage. Many conversions have already been effected, but many more are planned. In 1947 and 1948, 185 locomotives wereinstalled; and in 1949, 146. The main obstacle is that locomotives require levelor almost level roadways, in contradistinction to the rope haulages which were almost universal when the Board took over; and such roadways are seldom avail-able. In order to provide level roadways a vast programme of tunnelling has hadto be undertaken, and since tunnelling is an inherently slow process an advanceof 500 to 1,000 yards a year is about normal-and the length of the road requiredmay be as great as 2\ miles, it is not expected that the important savings in man-power and costs which are obtainable from locomotive haulage can be quicklyachieved or substantially accelerated.16. Winding the coal up the shaft is the continuation of undergroundhaulage. The provision of &quot; skips,&quot; which obviates the winding of tubs as well astbiS coal, is a valuable economy, but it may cause excessive breakage of the coal;and, in any event, it requires extensive works at the pit bottom. It frequentlyforms part only of a general reorganisation of the underground haulage to dealwith increased output, and it cannot be regarded as a short-term measure ofimprovement.17. The foregoing will have served to show that a great deal of short-termwork has already been undertaken to reorganise underground haulage operations,and considerable economies have been effected, especially by the installation ofconveyors. In fact, over  40 million had&apos; already been spent by the national coal Board by the end of 1949 on short-term capital re-equipment. This means that much of the short-term work, and the comparatively straightforward installa-tion of gate and trunk conveyors, has already been done.18. The major work of reorganising the haulage still remains, and is in hand,but this requires a great amount of tunnelling, which is an inherently slow process.There is, however, no reason to believe that the Board are not making as good progress on this work as can be expected; and substantial further numbers of men should be released from the &quot; unproductive &quot; work on the haulages for more directlyproductive work on filling coal at the face when these major schemes mature.19. There appear to be no particular shortages of materials or machinery which are impeding developments; but it is undoubtedly true that the Board are stillaffected by a shortage of skilled and experienced planning engineers without whose work neither long-term reorganisations nor short-term reforms can be undertaken.The Board are fully conscious of this bottle-neck; but it is one which can only bewidened by encouraging promising young men, whether among the miners or thecommunity generally, to take up mining engineering as a career. Scholarships and opportunities for those entering the mines to qualify themselves for higher appoint-ments are being freely offered by the Board, but the past unattractiveness of theindustry takes time to live down, and the recruiting and training of sufficient newmining engineers is inevitably a slow process.(iii) The Surface20. Re-organisation of surface plant can, in itself, contribute comparatively little to the production of increased quantities of coal. It can, of course, providebetter prepared coal and enable the Various processes to be completed with a smallerstaff, and thus contribute to a higher output per man shift for all employed, and tothe reduction of costs per ton of saleable coal produced. The release of surface workers will certainly give some scope for increasing the number of underground workers; but it Will be less than might at first sight appear. Surface jobs are veryvarious and include work as different as that of the winding engineman, lamproom39005 b 2
attendants, screen pickers and general labourers. A big source for economy in man-power is the substitution of mechanical for hand cleaning. But the coal-pickers thusdisplaced will consist in large part of compensation men, or boys passing throughthe required period of surface training; and no large proportion of them are suitablefor underground work.21. Another source of savings is in the disposal of pit and washery refuse. Atone Lancashire colliery, for example, no less than 50 men were saved in 1949 byimprovements in this process.22. None the less, improved surface equipment is essential, and newpreparation and cleaning plant, in particular, is of the highest importance. Suchplant is becoming more elaborate, and its construction cycle is often a matter ofyears rather than months. Since nationalisation 38 new plants have beenbrought into operation at a cost of  2  million with a capacity of % million tonsa year. At the end of 1949 another 27 plants were under construction with a capacity of about 9\ million tons annually. Much still remains to be done, however,and further progress is threatened by the cut which has been imposed on theBoard&apos;s capital investment programmes for 1950 and 1951. In the eyes of thegeneral public, cleaner coal may well be one of the crucial tests of nationalisation;for this reason, it is eminently desirable that more washeries and other plant shouldbe installed with the least possible delay.(iv) Other Forms of Reorganisation23. The closure of uneconomic collieries and the transfer of the men emplyed to more productive mines is another method of increasing output and productivity.An essentially similar process is the &quot; concentration&quot; of workings within an individual colliery, involving the closing of some districts or faces, and the more intensive exploitation of others. An example of the benefits to be derived fromthe planned closure of collieries is provided by South Normanton Colliery, in theEast Midlands Division, Where, in September 1949, 168 were made available for transfer to Langton Colliery. The loss in output at South Normanton was 230 tonsa day: the gain in output at Langton was 470 tons a day, equivalent to 60,000 tons annually. The financial gain is estimated at over  130,000 annually. By concen-trating output at a North-Western Division colliery, involving the handling of80 per cent, of the output at a single loading point, output per man shift was raised from 21 ewts. in 1948 to 25 cwts, in 1949. At Clipstone Colliery, in the EastMidlands Division, where one of the Samson Strippers is at work, and output permanshift is already 51 cwts., a reconstruction scheme is in progress providing fordeeper shafts, skip winding with new electric winders, and underground locomotivehaulage. At Thoresby Colliery, a scheme of reorganisation which will raise theannual output from 720,000 tons to about 1,250,000, is nearing conclusion.Conclusion24. It is an undoubted fact that the Board have undertaken a vast programmeof both long- and short-term projects for increasing output and reducing its cost. Intheir report for 1949, just published, major capital schemes at 133 collieries arelisted involving expenditure (excluding that on schemes already completed at thebeginning of the year) of  61-4 million. In addition heavy expenditure has been incurred on a multitude of &quot; short-term measures,&quot; of which numerous examples are provided from each Division in Chapter II of the report.25. From the moment that the Board took over responsibility for theindustry they have had most prominently in their minds the importance of thosetechnical developments which are most likely to produce quick results, without an undue sacrifice of those longer term developments which are indispensable tothe maintenance and improvement of production in the years further ahead. I am confident that they have retained a due sense of proportion in balancing the needsof the present against the requirements of the future, and there is no particularsphere of technical development in which I have any reason to believe that more could have been done than has been done.
26. The fruits of their endeavours are apparent in the steady increase in total output, and in output per man shift at the face and overall. The followingTable shows the progress that has been made.Output of output per man shift (tons) SaleableAt the        Elsewhere     On the Mined CoalYear                 Face      Underground   Surface Overall (million tons)1938     .........      2-90           3 05           4;90            1 14 227 01945      ...      ......      2-70            2-64            3-90            1-00 174-71946     .........      2-76           2-76           4 00           1 03 181-21947     .........      2-86           2-89           4-30            1 07 187-21948      ...      ...      ...      2-92            2-94            4 50            111 196-71949     ......      ,..      3 02           3 13           4-70            1 16 202-71950 (1st Quarter)     ...      3 11 3-25 4-90 1-20The increases shown reflect better equipment and improved performance and discipline among the workers. The movement in the output per man shift elsewhereunderground is particularly interesting. Starting at the same level as output permanshift at the face it advanced at much the same pace in 1947 and 1948. In1949, however, it took a notable leap ahead and a further advance is noticeable inthe figure for the first quarter of 1950. This is indicative of the improvedproductivity of the underground workers elsewhere than at the face, and moreparticularly of the haulage workers. There is reason to suppose that the acceleration-tion in the improvement of this index is attributable to the longer-term plans for there organisation of underground transport beginning to bear fruit after rather slow progress while the preliminary planning and tunnelling works were proceeding,and this accelerated progress should continue. It is clear that the National coal board have made remarkable progress during the past three years bearing in mind that output has been increased by over 21 million tons, and that costs, after an inevitable rise owing to increased labour costs, have now taken a downward turn.27. In these circumstances we must largely depend upon the efforts of theminers themselves for further improvements in output. The Board and the NationalUnion of Mineworkers have recently combined to commend for wider adoption asystem of piece-work already followed in some collieries, which may have valuableresults, if applied more generally. It is common practice for each worker on alongwall face to undertake the same stint, and these stints will naturally not reflect the capacity of the best workers, but rather that of the average or even the slowestworker. Under the new system workers will be able to choose their own stints orcombine with others in a group to work a collective stint: those who feel able to fill off more will take, or join a group with, a longer stint, and those less able willtake shorter stints. Earnings will no longer be based on an average performancefor the face, but will be weighted according to the length of stint undertaken bythe individual worker.28. Reforms of this kind win slow acceptance, and cannot be forced on theindustry. This is true too of other measures to increase output, ihus a consider-ably greater production would certainly be obtained if every face was regularlycleared each shift. The Board have made, and still are making, persistent efforts to achieve this result, but the habits of years die hard, and no revolutionary resultscan be expected in the short run from these efforts.29. Notwithstanding the absenteeism figures (which incidentally show a wel-come improvement in 1950 compared with 1949) I am satisfied that the miners are working reasonably well (the specific subject of involuntary absenteeism, which showed a marked increase in 1949 over 1948, was inquired into by the LidburyCommittee and on this I have circulated a separate memorandum) and I feel sure that reliance for higher output and productivity must depend mainly upon expendi-ture on the kind of developments which the Board are in fact undertaking. Wageincentive schemes of the kind referred to in paragraph 27 may affect the situation to some extent, but the available evidence tends to suggest that the high level ofpiece-rate earnings in the arduous conditions of coal-mining, combined with security of employment, are unlikely to lead to any materially greater effort, nor to much more regular attendance than prevail at present.30. All in all I am afraid that we cannot expect a level of output this yearmuch above the lower limit of the range of 205-210 million tons set out in theEconomic Survey, though it may happen that output in the second half of the year
will again show a spurt as a result, for example, of some of the longer term schemesbeginning to bear fruit. The best hope of increasing output by technical measureslies in increasing the volume of investment in the industry to the greatest possible extent, and if my colleagues would be willing to consider raising the investmentlimits imposed upon the Board for 1950 and 1951 I should be very glad to take up with the Board the question of whether further investment, promising quick results,(i.e., within the next two years) could be undertaken.P. J. N-B.Ministry of Fuel and Power, S.W. 1,l\th July, 1950.



</content>
</cab>
