<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 140-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  DOCUMENT. IS   THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;8   GOVERNMENT&quot;Prined for the Cabinet.   July 1950CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.0 4CP. (50) 1681th July, 1950CABINETUNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND cultural organisation FIFTH GENERAL conference memorandum by the Minister of education. I submit, for the information of my colleagues, the following report on the fifth session of the General Conference of Unesco.2. The Conference was held in Florence from 22nd May to 17th Juneinclusive. 55 Member States attended, including delegations from the followingcountries represented for the first time as new Member States: Sweden, Guatemala,Switzerland, Yugoslavia, Panama, Costa Rica, Korea, Indonesia and HashemiteJordan.Czechoslovakia was represented by its Ambassador in Paris, who did not remain, however, longer than the first two or three days. The Hungarian repre-sentative likewise withdrew, both on the issue of the admission of the ChineseNationalist representatives as the delegation of China. For the first time poland was not represented.3.   The main work of the Conference was:  (a) To approve the programme of the Organisation.The programme has now been recast to show separately (i) a basic programme setting forth the main objectives  of theOrganisation;(ii) an annual programme stating what the Organisation expects to under-take in the ensuing calendar year 1951;(iii) a list of the principal methods whereby effective work is chiefly to beundertaken.(b) To approve the budget for 1951.The Director-General asked for a budget of $8,200,000. The UnitedKingdom Delegation hoped to reduce this sum to $8 million, but agreed finallyto the figure proposed. As usual, the discussions over the budget total wereprolonged and arduous. They were complicated by the fact that the organisa-tion had not received all the contributions due to it from Member States in previous years, outstanding deficits being those of China (about $1 million per annum), Poland (about $84,000 per annum), and Argentina (about $170,000per annum). The United Kingdom Delegation succeeded in getting assent to a special resolution to prevent the recurrence of difficulties arising over pastdeficits by securing authority for the Executive Board and the Director-general to regulate the rate of expenditure in 1951 so as to ensure that it does notexceed the total amount of income which may reasonably be expected to bereceived from Member States and from certain other financial resources. this resolution was nearly wrecked at the last moment by an ill-advised UnitedStates amendment, but the main principle was saved after prolonged eleventh-hour negotiations. Although, therefore, the budget total of $8 million was- not achieved, the more important principle of limiting expenditure to incomewas established and as a result the finances of the Organisation are now betterregulated than they have ever been before. :&quot; 1 -&quot; 38995      &quot;&apos;       &quot; &apos; &apos;   &quot;   &quot; -   rr- ..   ;  . , : :       ^   ^
4. A feature of the work of the Conference was the close and assiduous study of all financial questions by a special Budget Committee appointed as a result of previous and continuing United Kingdom pressure on the Executive Board. For thefirst time, the Budget Committee of the Conference had authority to review thet expenditure of the Organisation as a whole and not merely that arising out of its pro-gramme activities. The Budget Committee has, moreover, been perpetuated by aresolution appointing another Budget Committee to meet immediately before the sixth session of the General Conference. The United Kingdom was appointed tothis Committee.The United Kingdom contribution to the budget, which stood at 13-27 per cent,in 1950, becomes 13-26 per cent, for 1951. The United States delegationreduced their contribution from 37-82 per cent, in 1950 to 35 per cent, in 1951, thusabsorbing the bulk of the new money arising from the contributions of new member States.   It proved impossible to resist this reduction.A determined effort by the Secretariat to ensure that all Member States paysome of their contribution in dollars was successfully resisted, and the UnitedKingdom will continue therefore to be able to pay in sterling.5. The Conference proceeded calmly until its last week, when the Director-General, on a scanty pretext,placed his resignation before the Executive Board andthe Conference. The occasion of his resignation arose during an unspectaculardebate in a commission of the Conference on two feeble proposals (Belgian andYugoslav) that Unesco should sponsor a conference of intellectuals to discuss theeffects of war on economic and social welfare and to seek ways of promoting peace.Mr. Torres Bodet has been exceedingly worried about the world situation and, somemonths before the Conference, he urged the Executive-Board and all Member states to come forward at the Conference with concrete proposals showing how Unescocould promote peace. For obvious reasons this appeal met with no effectiveresponse. He had also shown himself most uneasy at the strict control which theExecutive Board were endeavouring to impose upon the expansion of the Organi-sation, particularly through its efforts to limit the size of the budget which he wishedto present to the General Conference. For some time past the Director-Generarshealth has not seemed all it might be, and his precipitate action in offering to resignhas in all probability a background of illness, overwork, Conference strain in theheat of an Italian summer, combined with his imperfect understanding of Westernpolitical and administrative methods. While it would have been somewhat tragicto lose a promising Director-General so shortly after his appointment, particularlybecause of his undoubted ability, personal charm of manner and devotion toUnesco&apos;s cause, the United Kingdom delegation would have been Content to see himreplaced. To jeopardise a United Nations Specialised Agency towards the end ofits General Conference by suddenly involving it in a major crisis without warningrevealed a lack of responsibility and political understanding scarcely credible in a former Minister for Foreign Affairs. The incident was patched up by a vote ofconfidence in the Director-General passed unanimously by the heads of all delega-tion at a special meeting, and his letter of resignation, which fortunately had notbeen published, was withdrawn and the incident closed. It has, howe\er, dealta very considerable blow to the prestige and standing of the Director-General inthe eyes of all responsible delegations which will inevitably have lasting effects. Hehas gained nothing bv the incident, for if it was intended as blackmail in a good cause, it has produced neither, more cash for his budget nor increased activities for peace. :- .6. The main business of the Conference was undertaken in four commission of the whole:   ;,./ . &apos;-(a) Programme&apos; and Budget Commission   vBy whom the revised programme of the Organisation and its correspondingbudget, reported in paragraph 3 above, were very fully considered and-      approved..: -./:&apos;.        . v :     - -.;       v ,^..JiC .., V ^ ,     ,1:..(b). Administrative commission which studied all aspects; of the finance and control of the secretariat of the Organisation, the contributions of Member States and staff and salaryquestions. A notable economy in the cost of the Secretariat staff on the sevenlowest grades will be achieved beginning on 1st January, 1951.
(c) External Relations commission which faced the heavy task of undertaking a complete revision of thedirectives governing Unesco&apos;s relationships with international non-govern-. mental organisations, including the rules under which grants-in-aid orsubventions are payable.(d) Procedure CommitteeWhich is the scene of the annual battle over the introduction of Spanishas a working language, a battle which this year was lost owing to the deter-mined effort of the Latin American States. Impervious to reasoned argumenteffectively launched against them, in a particular by two Scandinavian States,they succeeded in forcing Spanish as a working language at General Conferencesat an additional cost to the Organisation of some $90,000 per annum.7. The United Kingdom delegation was able to take the lead in securing the unanimous support of the Conference for the text of a draft agreement on theimportation of educational, scientific and cultural materials. This text, first draftedat meetings at Annecy and Geneva by a conference seeking a General agreement on Trade and Tariffs, was accepted at the Florence Conference with minor amend-ments after considerable difficulty with the United States delegation. The UnitedKingdom provided the chairman of the special committee appointed to deal withthe draft agreement, and his achievement in securing its acceptance is regarded as a useful contribution to freeing international channels through which British tradein educational, scientific and cultural materials may expect to secure an easierpassage as Member States ratify the new agreement.8. The Conference was attended for the first time by Germans and Japanese,who were present as advisers to the Allied High Commission for Germany and theSupreme Commander of the Allied Powers in the Pacific respectively, both ofwhom were accredited observers to the Conference. The Germans and Japanesedid not speak to the Conference, but Unesco&apos;s proposed activities in their countries were fully reviewed and approved to the satisfaction of both the Allied High Com-missioner&apos;s and Supreme Commander&apos;s representatives. There are firm hopes thatUnesco, which enjoys a considerable prestige both in Germany and Japan, will prove an effective force in guiding both countries towards a firm allegiance to theprinciples of the United Nations.9. The first five years of Unesco&apos;s life have already shown that annualconferences make too large demands on Member States and on the Secretariat ofthe Organisation. The compromise, effected on United Kingdom initiative, of holding a short business conference every other year did not last year provide the fullrelief for which we had hoped, and there was a general welcome for the proposal made in Florence that Unesco&apos;s General Conference should be held biennially infuture. A constitutional amendment will be needed to make biennial meetingspossible and arrangements have been made to consider such an amendment at thenext conference, which should be a short business session held in Paris in May-June1951. The delegate for Uruguay gave notice that the General Conference wouldprobably be invited to Montevideo in 1952.10. Unesco&apos;s progress in the preceding twelve months and as a result of theConference, although slow, is definite. In Mr. Lionel Elvin, formerly Principalof Ruskin College, Oxford, the Organisation has once again secured the servicesof an able Director of its Education Division. The publications of the Organisa-tion have been taken firmly in hand and are now under the able direction of a former Publications Officer of the United Nations. The Deputy Director-General,Mr. Walter Laves, has still to be replaced, but the general staff picture is somewhatbetter than it has been in recent months, and this fact, coupled with the improvedprogramme and budgetary arrangements effected by the Conference, give firmgrounds for believing that the Organisation is in reasonably good condition to embark upon the essential long-term task of assisting education, science and culturethroughout the world by international action. ,1.1. As on previous occasions I propose to issue as a White Paper a summaryreport by the United Kingdom delegation to the Florence Conference.. G. T.Ministry of Education, W.\i1th July, 1950. - - - .

SECRETNOTEC. P.. (50) 169The attached is an additional papefor consideration under item 4 of theAgenda for the Cabinefs meeting on.13th July.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1. ,12TH JULY, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
