<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 146-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. July 1950SECRET   - Copy No.CP. (50) 169\2th July, 1950CABINETGENERAL LABOUR RELATIONS IN THE COALMINING industry memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service at the Cabinefs meeting on 15th June (CM. (50) 36th Conclusions, Minute 4)I was invited to submit a memorandum on general labour relations in the coal mining industry in conjunction with a memorandum by the Minister of Fuel and Power(now circulated as CP. (50) 163) on the steps which might be taken in the short-termto increase the total output of coal by accelerating the technical developments whichwere taking place in the industry.1. Conciliation procedure present conciliation procedure between the National Coal Board and theNational Union of Mineworkers rests upon two agreements. The first of these isdated 5th December, 1946, and provides for machinery at national and districtlevels, continuing the National Conciliation Scheme established by the mining association of Great Britain and the Miners Federation of Great Britain in 1943.The second agreement, of 1st January, 1947, provides for the establishment of a uniform pit conciliation scheme.The outstanding feature of the conciliation procedure in the industry is theprovision at each level, namely pit, district and national, of machinery for negotia-tion and, where this fails, of arbitration as the final step. Thus a purely pit disputewhich cannot be settled by negotiation at pit level is referred to an Umpire whoarbitrates in accordance with the provisions of the appropriate Pit ConciliationScheme. District questions not cleared by the District Conciliation machinery are settled by a District Referee, whose appointment is provided for by the DistrictConciliation Agreement. Similarly national questions which cannot be settled byagreement are referred for decision to the National Reference Tribunal, appointed under the National Conciliation Scheme. There is provision in certain cases forthe transfer of questions from pit to district and from district to national level.2. Wages structure in December, 1946 the National Coal Board entered into an Agreement withthe National Union of Mineworkers to adopt existing collective agreements andsettlements made between the N.U.M. and the Mining Association of Great Britainand between constituent associations of both bodies. Consequently, the presentwages structure is based on that obtaining immediately before nationalisation.The structure underwent important changes as a result of the National Agree-ment of 20th April, 1944, but to appreciate the present position, it is necessary to note briefly the pre-1944 position. The wages rates at that time consisted of threesections:  Basic rates were the subject of a large number of separate pit agreements between the accredited representatives of the Colliery Owners and theworkmen for each separate pit or colliery concerned. The agreementsranged from the fixing of piece-work prices at defined parts Of the pitto the establishment of time-rates for the many classes of day wage workersin each pit. The rates so fixed form what is known as the price list for the colliery concerned.39012
Percentage additions were made to the basic rates by reference to the periodicalascertainment of the aggregate proceeds of the coal produced in thedistrict less costs other than wages. The percentage added varied fromdistrict to district.Flat Rate Additions. During the years 1936-42 certain fiat rate additions weremade and in 1940 a cost of living increase was introduced. This has stood at 2s. 8d. per shift from 1941 onwards.In April, 1944, a National Wages Agreement was concluded. Its main pointsas they affected structure were: -(1) Piece rates were consolidated by the freezing of the ascertainment per-centages at their existing level and the fusion in the piece rates of the specified fiat rate additions, other than cost of living.(2) The current day wage rates were similarly amended and a further increaseof Is. per shift was applied in the case of certain skilled craftsmen.Although there may have been changes in local agreements, the position as it stood in 1944 remained the same until Vesting Day and consequently still appliesin principle. Proposals were made by the N.U.M. to the Board early in 1950 for acomplete revision of the wages structure, but negotiations have not yet started.3. Minimum WageThe national minimum wage which now applies was introduced during 1942.It was increased by an Award of 1944, when the National Reference Tribunal, inrejecting the application for an increase in piece work rates, declared that a generaloverhaul of the wages structure was overdue and stressed their view that theAward they had given was a temporary expedient. The minimum wage was againincreased by agreement in November 1947 and negotiations are at present in pro-gress on a claim for an increase of 2s. 6d. per shift and 155. in the weekly minimum,for adult day workers, with proportionate increases for juveniles.4. Guaranteed WageThe Essential Work (Coal Mining Industry) Order was revoked as from 1st September, 1946, but the guaranteed wage provisions were continued under an ad hoc arrangement between the two sides of the industry &quot; until such time as anew agreement can be entered into with the National Coal Board &quot;; these arrange-ments still hold good.5. Hours of work  the hours of work in Coal Mines are regulated by the Coal Mines RegulationsAct, 1908, as amended by subsequent Acts, which provides that the hours of workbelow ground must not exceed seven a day plus winding time, with the right ofthe Owner, agent or manager, to require the men to work an extra half-hour daily,thus making the daily maximum 1\ hours, except in the case of certain specifiedclasses for whom the daily maximum is fixed at %\ hours. By an Order in Council(S.R.O. 2505 of 1947) made under the Coal Mines Regulations Act, 1908, these provisions have been temporarily relaxed to permit the hours of work below groundto be increased from 7-1- hours plus &quot; one winding time &quot; to 8 hours plus &quot; onewinding time.&quot;An Agreement effective from 5th May, 1947, provided for the introductionof a 5-day week and an agreement of 31st October, 1947, invited Divisional boards and Area Executives of the Union to arrange either an extra \ hour a day or as many extra Saturday shifts as possible each Division and Area Executive beingfree to choose between the two methods or to leave the choice to be made atCollieries; the agreement was to continue in force until 30th April, 1948, but ithas been extended year by year up to 30th April, 1951.6. Holidays with PayThe present holidays with pay arrangements arise from an Award of theNational Reference Tribunal in October, 1943 (known as the Second PorterAward). It was decided that six consecutive days holiday with pay should begranted and the award also laid down the manner of calculating payment for theannual holiday with the object of providing an average week&apos;s wage over the whole industry. As a result, the parties agreed in April, 1944, for one weeks holiday with
APPENDIX AStoppages of work arising from industrial disputes in the coal mining industry in 1935-1949Year193519361937193819391940194119421943194419451946194719481949No. of stoppagesbeginning in year2172704573634043814705268431,2531,306^)1,3291,0531,116874Y Average342V Average695^-Average1,136Number of workersinvolved in stoppages000&apos;s2001182392174206y Average231190154252294568 j^-Average292243&quot;]217308 y Average189248241Aggregate duration ofstoppages in progressin year in working days000&apos;s1,3688521,496697565.505&apos;3358408862,481 J641422912464. 754Average996y Average1,009y Average639pay at the rate of  5 5s. for adult males. Similar agreements have been reachedyearly since; the 1950 agreement provides for payment of  7 16s.An agreement of 23rd May, 1947, between the N.C.B. and the N.U.M. providesfor payment in respect of six statutory and customary holidays at the rate of 1 /6thof the amount of the annual week&apos;s holiday payment.7. StatisticsStatements are attached in Appendices A, B and C respectively of stoppages ofwork arising from industrial disputes, awards of the National Reference tribunal and absenteeism............ ...............-.....8. General.....The general picture of industrial relations in the coalmining industry sincevesting day is of an increase in the number of strikes but a decrease in their duration-.What in fact seems to have been happening is not so much the sudden appearance of a large and unwarranted number of disputes over wages as a general impatienceand restiveness with any delays, real or imagined, in the consideration of grievancesor claims at the pits. This would seem to be due either to a lack of responsibilityamong the workers or a general lack of understanding of the local machinery and organisation of the industry or a combination of both. The negotiation and con-ciliation machinery is comprehensive and it appears to operate with speed whenstrikes occur. It can certainly be claimed by the industry that agreements arehonoured and that the arbitration system of the National Reference Tribunal iswell understood and trusted by all concerned. It has established an authority whichis of very great benefit to the industry as a whole.&quot;31 If anything there would appear to be a need to develop amongst the mena greater understanding of the industrial structure of the industry and their responsibilities towards it.G. A. I.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,Uth July, 1950.
APPENDIX BAnalysis of AwardsThe National Reference Tribunal			Subject			Year			Overtime and	Concessionary	Interpretations	Total	Wages	Holidays	week-end	coal and	of				working	allowances	awards	1943	1	1	1			31944	3	* * *	2	- * *	&quot;3	81945	2			1		31946						Nil1947						Nil1948	&quot;i		&quot;i			31949	i	&quot;i		i		31950	i					1	10	2	4	2	3	21Note. In addition to the above main scheme the N.R.T. has issued 3 other awards as under: February 1950. Colliery Management Scheme regarding Concessionary Coal.May 1950. Coke and Bye-Products Scheme regarding Holidays.May 1950. Coke and Bye-Products Scheme regarding Wages.APPENDIX CPercentages of AbsenteeismAll absenteeism per cent.Voluntary absenteeism per cent.All workersFace workersAll workersFace workers1935	6-05&quot;^								1936	6-29	Average							1937	7-08	-   6-56							1938	6-44			, , , &apos;		. . .			1939	6-94 J			...		...			1940	8-26&quot;&quot;								1941	9-03	Average							1942	10-40	Y 10-75							1943	12-46		15-12^	Average	4-89&quot;	Average	6	nt	I Average1944	13-61^		16-29j	r 15-7	5*58.,	r    5-24	6	84 j	r 6-471945	16-3p		19-12^		7-12&quot;		8	61&quot;]	1946	15-95	Average	19-32	Average	8-37	Average	10	63	Average1947	12-43	- 13-72	.15-05	* 16-51	6-46	*   6-68	8	21	.   8-471948	11-55		14-13		6-03		7	81	1949	12-34		14-94		5-43		7	11	Note. Separate figures in respect of voluntary absenteeism and face workers available from 1943onwards only.



</content>
</cab>
