<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 254-269</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-1 MITHIS  DOCUMENT  IS   THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTl:iPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1950SECRET Copy No. 3 2CP. (50) 17925th July, 1950CABINETCOUNCIL OF EUROPE-CONVENTION ON HUMAN RIGHTS-Memorandum by the Minister of state the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe is to consider at itsSession beginning on 3rd August the draft Convention on Human Rights, whichhas been drawn up on their instructions and of which a copy is annexed to thismemorandum. It is recommended that the Foreign Secretary be given discretion,on the conditions set out in paragraph 12 (3) below, to accept this convention on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government.History2. On 8th September, 1949, the Consultative Assembly adopted a resolution in which it recommended the Committee of Ministers to cause a draft convention to be drawn up as early as possible providing a collective guarantee and designedto ensure the effective enjoyment of fundamental rights and freedoms. To thisend the Consultative Assembly framed a text laying down the general lines onwhich it desired the Convention to be drawn up. A number of the particularproposals of the Assembly were quite unacceptable to us. In CP. (49) 204 of24th October, 1949 (Annex V), the Foreign Secretary recommended that at theforthcoming Session of the Committee of Ministers he should accept in principlethat a Convention on Human Rights should be drawn up. This recommendation was approved by the Cabinet on 27th October, 1949 (CM. (49) 62nd Conclusions,Minute 5). The Committee of Ministers subsequently authorised the holding of anumber of meetings at Strasbourg, first of a group of legal experts, and secondlyof a group of senior officials representing Governments. The object of these meetings was to prepare a draft Convention for the Committee and the text annexed to this memorandum is the result.Description of the Convention3. The chief recommendation of the Consultative Assembly was that thereshould be established a European Court of Human Rights which should judge casesof alleged violations of human rights on the part of States parties to the Convention.Such complaints could be lodged either by States themselves or by individuals.The Assembly did not consider it necessary to define in any detail the rights whoseenjoyment it would be the function of this Court to ensure; it was of the opinionthat a definition of the obligations of parties to the Convention by reference tocertain articles in the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights would besufficient, leaving the Court to elaborate a jurisprudence which defined these obligations more precisely.4. At the various meetings in which the draft was elaborated the UnitedKingdom representatives expressed the view (1) that in an instrument such as this, which would impose binding legal obligations on States, it was important that these obligations shouldbe precisely defined, i.e., that the rights whose enjoyment States wereto guarantee and the permissible limitations thereto must be definedwith proper precision in the Convention itself;
(2) that the establishment of a European Court of Human Rights was unnecessary and undesirable;(3) that the right to complain to an international body that their enjoyment of their rights as defined in the Convention had been violated shouldnot be granted to individuals but only to States parties to the Conven-tion. The proposal to allow individual petitions was unacceptable tous because in the present state of international relations it appeared likely that the system would be abused for political purposes and because there appeared to be a danger that it would be misunderstoodamong the backward peoples of the Colonies as suggesting that theultimate source of authority in those territories resided elsewhere thanin the Crown.5. The present text of the Convention contains a definition of the rights andlimitations thereto which follows almost word for word the actual texts proposedby the United Kingdom representatives (Articles 2-17), and which is thought tobe consistent with our existing law in all but a small number of comparativelytrivial cases. (In respect of these cases it may be necessary for us on accession totake advantage of the right to make reservations provided in Article 60.) Similarly,although the Convention as drafted provides for the establishment of a EuropeanCourt of Human Rights, States can only be required to appear before it if theyhave made a voluntary declaration that they regard its jurisdiction as compulsory(Article 46) or by special agreement ad hoc (Article 48). Thus there can be no danger of His Majesty&apos;s Government^ being obliged to appear before it as a partyagainst their will.6. At the latest meeting of officials in Strasbourg only the Greek represen-tative joined the United Kingdom representative in declaring his Government &quot;unableto accept the inclusion in the Convention of provisions permitting the submission of petitions by individuals. The present text, therefore, contains such provisions(Article 23). They are, however, subject to certain safeguards in Articles 24 and 25,and especially to that in Article 30 that the decision regarding the action to betaken in cases where a party to the Convention is found to be in breach of its obligations (and where the case is not submitted to the Court of Human Rights) isin the hands of the Committee of Ministers itself.7. Since the conclusion of the meeting of officials in Strasbourg, a communi-cation has been received from the Belgian Government stating that they wouldbe disposed to oppose at the forthcoming Session of the Committee of ministers the provisions granting to individuals the right to submit petitions. It is not clear from the Belgian communication that they would be prepared to refuse to acceptthe Convention if they failed to secure the suppression of this provision.8. It is recognised that acceptance of a Convention containing these provisionsmay possibly cause difficulties. Thus it is, in theory at least, possible that a supremetribunal in this country may find itself bound, by an existing law which is incon-sistent with the terms of this Convention, to give a verdict which constitutes a breach of His Majesty&apos;s Governments obligations under it. It must be recognisedthat in such a case a petition might be successfully lodged and that in the endlegislation would be necessary in order to bring the law into agreement with HisMajesty&apos;s Governmenfs obligations under the Convention. It appears, however,that the consequences of our being one of a small minority of the members of theCouncil which refuses to accept the Convention would be serious. Thus it wouldbe hailed on the Continent as further evidence of the luke-warm attitude of HisMajesty&apos;s Government towards the affairs of the Council of Europe in general andmight be expected to be seized upon by the Cominform as showing that our pro-fessed interest in the enjoyment of human rights by the inhabitants of other countries was mere hypocrisy and that, when it came to the point, we were unwilling to accept in respect of our own territories obligations similar to those which had been imposed on the Eastern European States under their peace treaties. It is also pertinentthat, at the meeting which took place between the Prime Minister and the leader of the Opposition before the first Session of the Consultative Assembly, Mr.Churchill stressed the importance which he attached to the adoption by the Councilof Europe of satisfactory arrangements for guaranteeing the enjoyment of human rights and that the Chairman of the Legal Committee of the Consultative assembly which prepared the original proposals is Sir David Maxwell-Fyfe, who has, with theconsent of the Committee of Ministers, been shown the present draft of the Conven-tion and has expressed his satisfaction with it.
conclusions . There are a few comparatively minor amendments which are still necessaryto make the text satisfactory to us. Provided that these are agreed to by other member States the Convention could be accepted by His Majesty&apos;s Government inthe United Kingdom.10. The Convention as it stands is probably the best draft that is likely to emerge from the Council of Europe. Further discussion, whether between Govern-ments or in the Consultative Assembly or its Committees, is unlikely to result inimprovement. On the contrary, discussion in the Assembly is likely to result inpressure for the reintroduction of precisely those objectionable features ofthe Assembly&apos;s original draft (see paragraph 2 above) which have been eliminatedin the discussions between Governments. Any further delay or any display ofreluctance to conclude a convention would also be open to the political objectionsset out in paragraph 8 above.1.1. As against this, it must be recognised that the Convention is not perfectand that (apart from the political disadvantages mentioned above) no real harm to essential British interests is likely to result if it is not signed.Recommendations12.   It is therefore recommended that the Foreign Secretary should:(1) urge on his colleagues on the Committee of Ministers the desirability of completing the work of the Convention in the course of the forthcoming session of the Committee;(2) reiterate the difficulties which we foresee in granting to individuals the rightto petition and try to secure the omission of the relative provisions;(3) none the less have discretion to accept the Convention in its present form,subject to the minor amendments referred to in paragraph 9, if itappears that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom wouldbe one of an embarrassingly small minority in opposing it;(4) recommend that the Consultative Assembly be informed of the action taken by the Committee of Ministers.K. G. Y.Foreign Office, S.W.1,25th July, 1950

annex draft C0NVENT80N  ON HUMAN  RIGHTS
annex draft CONVENTION ON HUMAN RIGHTSSection article 1The High Contracting Parties undertake to secure to all individuals within their jurisdiction the rights and freedoms defined in Section II of this Convention.Section IIArticle 2(1) Everyone&apos;s right to life shall be protected by law.(2) No one shall be deprived of his life intentionally, save in the execution ofa sentence of a court following his conviction of a crime for which this penalty isprovided by law.(3) Deprivation of life shall not be regarded as a contravention of this articlewhen it results from the use of force which is no more than absolutely necessary (a) in defence of any person from unlawful violence;(b) in order to effect lawful arrest or to prevent an escape from lawful custody;(c) in action lawfully taken for the purpose of quelling a riot or insurrection.Article 3No one shall be subjected to torture or to.inhuman or degrading treatment orpunishment.Article 4(1) No one shall be held in slavery or servitude.(2) No one shall be required to perform forced or compulsory labour.(3) For the purpose of this article, the term &quot; forced or compulsory labour &quot;shall not include (a) any work required to be done in the ordinary course of detention imposedaccording to the provisions of article 5 hereafter;-   (b) any service of a military character or, in case of conscientious objectors in countries where they are recognised, service exacted instead of com-pulsory military service;(c) any service exacted in case of an emergency or calamity threatening the lifeor well-being of the community;(d) any work or service which forms part of normal civic obligations.Article 5(1) Everyone has the right to liberty and security of person.No one shall be deprived of his liberty save in the following cases and in accord-ance with a procedure prescribed by law:  (a) the lawful detention of a person after conviction by a competent court;(b) the lawful arrest and detention of a person for non-compliance with thelawful order of a court, or in order to secure the fulfilment of any obliga-tion prescribed by law;(c) the lawful arrest or detention of a person effected for the purpose of bringinghim before the competent legal authority on reasonable suspicion of having committed an offence or which is reasonably considered to benecessary to prevent his committing a crime or fleeing after havingdone so;(d) the lawful detention of minors by lawful order for the purpose of educa-tional supervision;
Q (e) the lawful detention of persons for the prevention of the spreading ofinfectious diseases, of persons of unsound mind, alcoholic or drugaddicts or vagrants;(/) the lawful arrest or detention of&apos; a person to prevent his effecting anunauthorised entry into the country or of a person against whom deportation-tion or extradition proceedings are pending.(2) Anyone who is arrested shall be informed promptly, in a language whichhe understands, of the reasons for his arrest and of any charge against him.(3) Anyone arrested or detained in accordance with the provisions of para-graph 1(c) shall be brought promptly before a judge or other officer authorised by law to exercise judicial power and shall be entitled to trial within a reasonable time or to release pending trial. Release may be conditioned by guarantees to appear for trial.(4) Everyone who is deprived of his liberty by arrest or detention shall beentitled to take proceedings by which the lawfulness of his detention shall be decidedspeedily by a court and his release ordered if the detention is not lawful.(5) Anyone who has been victim of unlawful arrest or deprivation of libertyshall have an enforceable right to compensation.Article 6(1) In the determination of any criminal charge against him of his rights and obligations in a suit at law, everyone is entitled to a fair and public hearing withina reasonable time by an independent and impartial tribunal established by law.Judgment shall be pronounced publicly but the press or public may be excludedfrom all or part of the trial to the extent strictly necessary in the opinion of thecourt in the interests of morals, public order or national security in a democraticsociety, or where, in the special circumstances of the case, publicity would prejudice the interests of justice.(2) Everyone charged with a criminal offence has the right to be presumedinnocent until proved guilty according to law.(3) In the determination of any criminal charge against him, everyone is entitled to the following minimum guarantees: - (a) to be informed promptly, in a language which he understands, of the nature and cause of the accusation against him;(b) to have adequate time and facilities for the preparation of his defence;(c) to defend himself in person or through legal assistance of his own choosingand, if he has not sufficient means to pay for legal assistance, to begiven it free when the interests of justice so require;(d) to obtain the attendance and examination of witnesses on his behalf underthe same conditions as witnesses against him;(e) to have free assistance of an interpreter if he cannot understand or speakthe language used in court.Article 7(1) No one shall be held guilty of any criminal offence on account of any actor omission which did not constitute a criminal offence under national or inter-national law at the time when it was committed. Nor shall a heavier penalty be imposed than the one that was applicable at the time the criminal offence was committed.(2) Nothing in this Article shall prejudice the trial and punishment of anyperson for any act or omission which, at the time it was committed, was criminalaccording to the general principles of law recognised by civilised nations..Article 8(1) Everyone&apos;s right to respect for his private and family life, his home and hiscorrespondence shall be recognised.(2) There shall be no interference by a public authority with the exercise ofthis right except such as is in accordance with law and is necessary in a democraticsociety in the interests of national security, public safety, for the prevention of disorder or crime or for the protection of health or morals.
Article 14(1) In time of war or other public emergency threatening the life of the nation,a State may take measures derogating from its obligations under this convention to the extent strictly limited by the exigencies of the situation, provided that such measures are not inconsistent with its other obligations under international law.(2) No derogation from Articles 2, except in respect of deaths resulting fromlawful acts of war, 3, 4 (paragraph 1) or 7 can be made under this provision.(3) Any State party hereto availing itself of this right of derogation shallinform the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe fully of the measures whichit has thus enacted and the reasons therefore. It shall also inform the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe when such measures have ceased to operate andthe provisions of the Convention are again being fully executed.(1) Everyone has the right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion;this right includes freedom to change his religion or belief and freedom, eitheralone or in community with others and in public or private, to manifest his religionor belief, in teaching, practice, worship and observance.(2) Freedom to manifest one&apos;s religion or beliefs shall be subject only to suchlimitations as are prescribed by law and are necessary in a democratic society, inthe interests of public safety, or for the protection of public order, health or morals,or for the protection of the rights and freedoms of others.Article 10(1) Everyone has the right to freedom of expression. This right shall includefreedom to hold opinions and to receive and impart information and ideas without interference by public authority regardless of frontiers, either orally, in writingor in print, in the form of art or by duly licensed visual or auditory devices.(2) The exercise of these freedoms, since it carries with it duties and responsi-bilities, may be subject to such penalties, liabilities and restrictions as are prescribed by law and are necessary in a democratic society, in the interests of national security, territorial integrity, or public safety, for the prevention of disorder orcrime, for the protection of health or morals, for the protection of the reputationsor rights of others, for preventing the disclosure of information received in confi-dence, or for maintaining the authority and impartiality of the judiciary.Article 11(1) Everyone has the right to freedom of peaceful assembly and to freedom of association with others, including the right to form and to join trade unions for theprotection of his interests.(2) No restrictions shall be placed on the exercise of these rights other thansuch as are prescribed by law and are necessary in a democratic society in theinterests of national security, public safety, or for the prevention of disorder orcrime, for the protection of health or morals in a democratic society, or for theprotection of the rights and freedoms of others; provided that this Article shallnot prevent the imposition of lawful restrictions on the exercise of this right bymembers of the armed forces, the police or the administration of the State.Article 12Men and women of full age have the right to marry and to found a family,according to the national laws governing the exercise of these rights.Article 13(1) The rights and freedoms defined in this Convention shall be secured without discrimination on any grounds such as sex, race, colour, languages, religion; political or other opinion, national or social origin, association with a national minority,property, birth or other status.(2) The restrictions to these rights and freedoms shall not be applied for any purpose other than those for which they have been prescribed.
The High Contracting Parties undertake to ensure that any person whose rightsand freedoms as herein defined are violated shall have an effective remedy before anational authority notwithstanding that the violation has been committed by persons acting in an official capacity.Article 16Nothing in Articles 10, 11 and 13 (paragraph 1) shall be regarded as preventing the High Contracting Parties from imposing restrictions on the political activity of aliens.Article 17Nothing in this Convention may be interpreted as implying for any State, groupor person, any right to engage in any activity or perform any act aimed at thedestruction of any of the rights and freedoms set forth herein or at their limitation to a greater extent than is provided for in the Convention.Section IIIArticle 18To ensure the observance of the engagements undertaken by the High Con-tracting Parties in the present Convention, there shall be set up:  (1)A European Commission of Human Rights hereafter referred to as the&quot; Commission &quot;;(2) A European Court of Human Rights, hereafter referred to as the &quot; Court.&quot;Section IVArticle 19The Commission shall consist of a number of members equal to that of theHigh Contracting Parties, and not more than one national of each State may bea member of the Commission.Article 20(1) The members of the Commission shall be elected by the Committee ofMinisters by an absolute majority of votes, from a list of names drawn up by the bureau of the Consultative Assembly; each group of the Representatives of theHigh Contracting Parties in the Assembly shall put forward three candidates, ofwhom two at least shall be its nationals.(2) The members of the Commission shall sit on the Commission in their individual capacity.(3) As far as applicable, the same procedure shall be followed in appointingas members nationals of States which become Parties to this Convention, and to fill the casual vacancies.Article 21(1) Members of the Commission shall be elected for a period of six years.They may be re-elected, provided however, that of the members elected at the firstelection, the terms of seven members shall expire at the end of three years.(2) The members whose terras are to expire at the end of the initial period ofthree years shall be chosen by lot to be drawn by the Secretary-General immediatelyafter the first election has been completed.(3) A member of the Commission elected to replace a member whose term of office has not expired shall hold office for the remainder of his predecessor^ term.(4) The members of the Commission shall hold office until replaced. after having been replaced, they shall continue to deal with such cases as they already had under consideration.
Any High Contracting Party may refer to the Commission through theSecretary-General of the Council of Europe any alleged breach of the provisionsof the Convention by another High Contracting Party.Article 23Any person, any non-governmental organisation or any group of individuals,which claims to be the victim of a violation by one of the High Contracting parties of the rights secured by this Convention may petition the Commission in an applica-tion addressed to the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe. The High Con-tracting Parties undertake not to hinder in any way the effective exercise of this right.Article 24The Commission may only deal with the matter after all domestic remedieshave been exhausted according to the generally recognised rules of internationallaw and within a period of six months from the date on which the final decision wastaken.Article 25(1) The Commission shall not deal with any application submitted underArticle 23 which (a) is anonymous,(b) is substantially the same as a previous application and contains no relevantnew information.(2) The Commission shall consider inadmissible any application submittedunder Article 23 which it considers (a) incompatible with the provisions of the present Convention,(b) manifestly ill-founded, or an abuse of the right of application.(3) The Commission shall reject any application which it considers inadmissibleunder Article 24.Article 26In the event of the Commission accepting the application, it shall thenundertake (a) an examination together with the representatives of the parties of theapplication;(b) if need be, an investigation, for the effective conduct of which, the states concerned shall furnish all facilities after an exchange of views withthe Commission.Article 27If it does not reject the application, the Commission shall ascertain the facts and place itself at the disposal of the parties concerned with a view to securing a friendly solution of the matter on the basis of respect for Human Rights as defined in this Convention.Article 28(1) The Commission shall exercise the activities set out in Articles 26 and 27by means of a Sub-Commission consisting of seven members of the Commission.(2) Each of the parties concerned may appoint as member of this Sub-Commission a person of its choice.(3) The remaining members of the Commission shall be chosen by lot inaccordance with arrangements prescribed in the Rules of Procedure of theCommission.
Section l&apos;article 36The European Court of Human Rights shall consist of a number of judgesegual to that of the Members of the Council of Europe and no two of the judgesmay be nationals of the same State.Article 37(1) The members of the Court shall be elected by the Consultative assembly and by the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe from a list of persons nominated by the High Contracting Parties; each Party shall nominate threecandidates, of whom two at least shall be its nationals.(1) If the Sub-Commission succeeds in effecting a settlement in accordancewith Article 27, it shall draw up a Report which shall be sent to the States con-cerned, to the Committee of Ministers and to the Secretary-General of the Councilof Europe for publication. This Report shall be confined to a brief statement ofthe facts and to the solution reached.(2) If such a solution is not reached, the Commission shall draw up a Reporton the facts and state its opinion as to whether the facts found disclose a breachby the State concerned of its obligations under the Convention. It may make such proposals as it thinks fit.(3) The opinions of all the members of the Commission may be stated in itsReport.(4) The Report shall be transmitted to the Committee of Ministers.; it shall also be transmitted to the States concerned, who shall not be at liberty to publish it.Article 30(1) The Committee of Ministers shall decide by a two-thirds majority vote ofthe representatives entitled to sit on the Committee what effect shall be given tothe Commission^ Report, and shall publish the Report.(2) The provisions of the preceding paragraph shall not apply if, within aperiod of three months from the submission to the Committee of Ministers of theCommission^ Report, the matter is referred to the Court in accordance with article 48.(3) The High Contracting Parties undertake to regard as binding on them everydecision which the Committee of Ministers may take in application of the provisionsof paragraph 1.Article 31The Commission shall draw up its own rules of procedure.Article 32The Commission shall meet in camera.Article 33The Commission shall take its decisions by a majority of the Members presentand voting; the Sub-Commission shall take its decisions by a majority of its members.Article 34The Commission shall hold its sessions as the circumstances require. Theseshall be convened by the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe.Article 35The Secretariat-General of the Council of Europe shall assist the Commission.
(2) These members shall be of high moral character and must possess the qualifications required for appointment to high judicial offices, or shall be juris-consults of recognised competence.(3) The Consultative Assembly and the Committee of Ministers shall proceedindependently of one another to elect the members of the Court.Article 38Members of the Court shall be elected by the majority of the representatives on the Assembly casting a vote and by the majority of the representatives on theCommittee of Ministers entitled to sit on the Committee.Article 39(1) Members of the Court shall be elected for a period of nine years. Theymay be re-elected; provided, however, that of the members elected at the firstelection the terms of four members shall expire at the end of three years, and theterms of four more members shall expire at the end of six years.(2) The members whose terms are to expire at the end of the initial periods of three and six years shall be chosen by lot to be drawn by the Secretary-Generalimmediately after the first election has been completed.(3) A member of the Court shall hold office until replaced. After having been replaced, he shall continue to deal with such cases as he already had underconsideration.Article 40The Court shall elect its President and Vice-President for a period of threeyears. They may be re-elected.Article 41The members of the Court shall receive a compensation for each day of duty to be determined by the Committee of Ministers.Article 42The Court shall draw up its own rules and shall determine its own procedure.Article 43The Court shall consist of one Chamber composed of 7 judges, to considercases brought before it. Any State party concerned shall be represented by the member of the Court who is its national, or, failing such by a person of its choicewho shall act as a judge; the names of the other judges shall be drawn by lot bythe President before the opening of the case.Article 44Only the High Contracting Parties and the Commission shall have the rightto bring a case before the Court.Article 45The jurisdiction of the Court comprises all cases concerning the interpretationand application of the present Convention which the High Contracting Parties orthe Commission shall refer to it in accordance with article 48.Article 46(1) Each of the High Contracting Parties may at any time declare that it recognises as compulsory ipso facto and without special agreement the jurisdiction of the Court in all matters concerning the interpretation and application of theprovisions of the present Convention.(2) The declarations referred to above may be made unconditionally or on condition of reciprocity on the part of several or certain other Contracting Partiesor for a specified period.(3) These declarations shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of theCouncil of Europe who shall transmit copies thereof to the High Contracting Parties.
Section VI. Miscellaneous and Final provisions article 56On receipt of a request to that effect from the Secretary-General of the Councilof Europe the Government of any State Party to this Convention shall supply an explanation of the manner in which the law of that State gives effect to any ofthe provisions in this Convention.The Court may only deal with a case after the Commission has acknowledgedthe failure of efforts at settlement.Article 48The following may bring a case before the Court, provided that the HighContracting Party concerned, if there is only one, or the High Contracting parties concerned, if there is more than one, are subject to the compulsory jurisdiction ofthe Court or, failing that, with the consent of the High Contracting Party concerned,if there is only one, or of the High Contracting Parties if there is more than one:  (a) the Commission;(b) the High Contracting Party whose national is alleged to be a victim;(c) the High Contracting Party who referred the case to the Commission;(d) the High Contracting Party against which the complaint was made.Article 49In the event of dispute as to whether the Court has jurisdiction, the matter shallbe settled, by the decision of the Court.Article 50If the Court finds that a decision or a measure taken by a legal authority orany authority of one of the High Contracting Parties is completely or partiallyopposed to the obligations arising from the present Convention, and if the internallaw of the said Party only allows partial reparation to be made for the consequences of this decision or measure, the decision of the Court shall, if necessary, accord justsatisfaction to the injured party.Article 51(1)   Reasons shall be given for the judgment of the Court.(2)   If the judgment does not represent in whole or in part the unanimousopinion of the judges, any judge shall be entitled to deliver a separate opinion.Article 52The judgment of the Court is final.Article 53Each High Contracting Party shall undertake to abide by the decision of theCourt in any case to Which it is a party.Article 54The judgment of the Court shall be transmitted to the Committee of ministers which shall supervise its execution.Article 55(1) The first election of the members of the Court will take place after the declarations by the High Contracting Parties mentioned in Article 45 have reached a total of nine.(2)   No cases can be brought before the Court before this election.
The expenses of the Commission and the Court shall be borne by the Councilof Europe.Article 58Nothing in this Convention shall be construed as limiting or derogating fromany of the rights and freedoms which may be ensured under the laws of any HighContracting Party or under any other agreement to which it is a Party.Article 59a(1) Any State may at the time of accession or at any time thereafter declareby notification addressed to the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe thatthe present Convention shall extend to all or any of the territories for whose inter-national relations it is responsible.(2) The Convention shall extend to the territory or territories named in the notification as from the thirtieth day after the receipt of this notification by theSecretary-General of the Council of Europe.Article 59b(1) The provisions of this Convention shall be applied in the overseas terri-tories with due regard, however, to local requirements., (2) This Convention shall only apply to territories of the High ContractingParties possessing jurisdiction within the fields covered by the present Conventionwhen the consent of the appropriate authorities of these territories has beenobtained.(3) The High Contracting Parties responsible for these territories shall, ifnecessary, take steps to obtain this consent.Article 60(1) Any State may when signing this Convention or when depositing itsinstrument of ratification or accession, make a reservation in respect of any particu-lar provision of the Convention to the extent that any law then in force in its territory is not in conformity with that provision. Reservations of a general character shall not be permitted under this Article.(2) Any reservation made under this Article shall contain a brief statement ofthe law concerned.Article 61. (1) This Convention shall be open to the signature of the Member States ofthe Council of Europe and submitted for ratification. The ratification shall be deposited with the Secretariat-General of the Council of Europe.(2) This Convention shall come into force after the deposit of ten instruments of ratification.(3) As regards any signatory State ratifying subsequently the Convention shall come into force at the date of the deposit of its instrument of ratification.(4) Any members of the Council of Europe may accede thereafter to this Con-vention by depositing their instrument of accession with the Secretariat-Generalof the Council of Europe.(5) The Secretary-General of the Council of Europe shall notify all the High&quot;Contracting Parties of the entry into force of the Convention, the names of theHigh Contracting Parties who have ratified it, and the deposit of all instruments of ratification or accession which may be effected subsequently.



</content>
</cab>
