<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 396-399</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^ lATHIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENT-\ Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1950SECRET Copy No.CP. (SO) 18424th July, 1950CABINETCAPITAL INVESTMENT PROGRAMME-SEWERAGE AND  sewage disposal WORKSMemorandum by the Minister of Health1. At the meeting of the Production Committee on 21st July (P.C. (50)14th Meeting, Minute 6) I was invited to submit to the Cabinet my proposals for a relaxation of the capital investment programme in respect of new schemes of ruralsewerage.2. The current capital investment programme has a severely restrictive effect upon new works of sewerage and sewage disposal in rural areas, and I seek mycolleagues&apos; approval to some easing of the position by the restoration of the cuts of  2 - 5 million and  4 - 5 million made in my Departments proposed programme for investment in water and sewerage in 1951 and 1952 respectively. I am veryconcerned at the growing volume of complaints from Members on our side of theHouse who sit for areas where highly desirable schemes of rural sewerage havebeen promoted by the local authority but have been turned down by me in orderto keep within the limits of the programme; there is a strong feeling that these decisions are having a seriously adverse effect politically.3. In my Departments estimates for the 1951-52 investment programmerequirements for works of water supply and sewerage were, on the footing of stricteconomy, stated to be  25 - 5 million in 1951 and  32 - 5 million in 1952. An estimatewas also furnished on request of the amounts required if only the essential minimum of new works were to be allowed, i.e., only those works needed in connexion with government programmes, e.g., housing and new industrial development, and worksneeded to remove a positive danger to health, and on this basis requirements weregiven as  23 million for 1951 and  28 million for 1952. These reduced figures were adopted.4. It was recognised at the time that compliance with this reduced programme would necessitate a very serious restriction on new works, particularly on sewerage and sewage disposal, and that the restrictions would fall heavily on the rural areas,where numerous schemes were being promoted to remedy backward conditions.5. With the restricted programme I am able to authorise only a small propor-tion of these rural schemes, in those cases where the need is immediately urgentowing to positive danger to health or to enable new houses to be occupied.Some 250 rural sewerage schemes, as well as a large number of urban schemes ofwater supply and sewerage, now stand postponed although otherwise ready to pro-ceed. Many of these rural projects are small parish schemes and about half ofthem cost less than  25,000 each. They were promoted in the main to remedyconditions which can only be regarded as shockingly disgraceful, although it maybe hard to show that they are a direct menace to health.6. It is true that the approved programmes allow for a largely increasedinvestment in 1951 and 1952 as compared with previous years. But this increase is mainly taken up by expenditure on large schemes of water supply and seweragestarted in previous years, and is not the reflection of comparatively large increases in approvals for new works. Indeed, so far as sewerage in rural areas is concerned,
there has been a falling off in the amount of new works authorised. Until recently,new work put in hand compared favourably with achievement immediately beforethe war, but now it is substantially less.* 7. I realise that in present circumstances it would not be practicable to allowall,-the water and sewerage projects now pending to proceed at once, and myDepartment^ original estimates contemplated that many of them must jCOriiinueto be deferred. The restricted programme, however, weighs, and if adhered&quot;to7mustcontinue to weigh, too heavily on rural sewerage schemes. The restoration Of the cuts would enable me to approve the start of a substantial number of small schemeswhere conditions are very bad, and to that extent to relieve the disquiet amongstour Members.A. B.Ministry of Health, S.W. 1,24th July, 1950.



</content>
</cab>
