<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/41/0 images: 474-479</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1950SECRET copy no.^^c.p. (so) 19a3lst August, 1950CABINETKOREAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsAnnexed for the consideration of my colleagues is a memorandum on Korea,which sets out certain considerations which govern the problem and outlines theprocedure by which it may be possible to make arrangements, under the a?aegis ofthe United Nations, for a long-term political settlement in Korea. The subjectof Korea is on the agenda for the forthcoming Tripartite Ministerial Talks in new York, and the memorandum was drafted primarily with a view to its usein that connection. I have already sent a copy to Washington for use bySir Oliver Franks in the preliminary official discussions.2. Subject to the agreement of my colleagues, I would propose to pursuediscussions of the political settlement in Korea on the lines discussed in the attached memorandum not only with the United States and France but also with theCommonwealth and other friendly countries.E. B.Foreign Office, SWA,31 st August, 1950.ANNEXKoreaOn any realistic view, it is difficult to be optimistic about the future of Korea.The domination, of the whole Korean peninsula has been an objective of Russianforeign policy since Czarist days and it may be taken as axiomatic that it willremain so. Korea&apos;s contiguous land frontiers with both the great CommunistStates of the world, the fact that the Soviet Union disposes of a substantial bodyof ruthless and disciplined Korean Communists who have undergone years oftraining in the Soviet Union, and the extreme political immaturity and irresponsi-bility of the Korean people as a whole, give the Soviet Union obvious and decidedadvantages in the achievement of their purposes. It can be assumed that the soviet union will only co-operate in any United Nations proposals for Korea in so faras she believes that she will be able to further her own designs by doing so. Indeed,the Soviet Union will be implacably opposed to the establishment of a genuinelydemocratic and independent Government of a unified Korea. Any new democraticState established at the end of the present hostilities in a part or the whole of korea will, therefore, need a protracted period of tutelage and protection and willbe a constant prey to attempts at internal subversion.2.   It is of the first importance that the impressive degree of unanimity overKorea in the United Nations should be maintained and that at every phase, action39279
should command the widest possible measure of support from the governments and peoples of all non-Communist States, especially those in Asia. It follows,therefore:  (a) That the United Nations should endeavour to make arrangements forKorea which are palpably just and reasonable even though they may prove in practice difficult of attainment.(b) That if these arrangements are in fact frustrated, it should be clear to theworld who is responsible.- i3.   IHsmost^desirable in the interest(rf-PJ^exmunanimity in the UnitedJ^tions that somejearly statement should be made, setting&quot;^vrTTne^rolH^^ec^^^! tfie&quot;TO^ It will, of cburseT^beuntil a later stage in the fighting. Much might, for example, depend on whether the North Koreanarmies suffer almost total destruction in the South, or whether substantial forcessucceed in retiring in reasonably good order beyond the 38th parallel. In theformer case, it is conceivable that in the absence of more direct Soviet intervention,the administration in North Korea might disintegrate of itself.4. A statement of objectives would be unlikely to achieve its purpose unless it envisaged something more than the mere restoration of the authority of thepresent Government (even though this was set up under United Nations auspices)and a return to the previous precarious status quo. A limited objective of this kind would satisfy neither world opinion nor the Korean people. In any case, theUnited Nations can hardly abandon their declared objective of working for theestablishment of a urrffiedjand democratic Government. The statement might perhaps, therefore, tike-tire form of a resolution in the General Assembly recom-mending that as soon as the military situation permits all possible steps should betaken to implement previous Assembly resolutions on the subject and to securethe holding under United Natioiis^auspiCies^oL-elections^. Korea .,on. a national.&quot;Basis&quot; with a view to the establishment of a unified, independent and democratic&quot;&quot;^KdTelffi &quot;Governrne^ such a resolution to be--passed^inlrle General Assembly than in the Security Council, since the Assemblyhas hitherto been responsible for political arrangements in Korea. Moreover, aresolution in the Assembly provides clearer evidence of wide support for a policythan does a resolution in the Security Council; and there is, of course, the impor-tant added advantage that a resolution in the Assembly could not be vetoed bythe Soviet Union. The general question of the nature of a possible resolution inthe Assembly is further discussed in paragraph 6 below.5. A resolution on the above lines would not necessarily commit the united nations to the view that United Nations forces should eventually pass beyondthe 38th parallel and occupy the whole of North Korea, which is a question whichwill have to be left for later decision in the light of the developing military andpolitical situation. But it would emphasise the continuing desire of the united nations to bring about the unification of Korea on a democratic.basis, and if,&quot;,in&quot;&quot;the&quot;evehtptriisi proves impossible of attainment, the responsibility will be made clear, &quot;&quot;&quot;.............-r -----6. Whatever decision may eventually be reached on the question whether theUnited Nations forces should proceed beyond the 38th parallel, there may be doubt whether such action (apart of course from such minor incursions as may benecessary in the course of military operations conducted from the south) could bejustified on the basis of the Security Council Resolution of 27th June. Action underthis Resolution is for the purpose of repelling the armed attack on the republic of Korea, and consequently action beyond the 38th parallel would be legitimatefor this purpose. But permanent occupation would be another matter. In theview of many members of the United Nations, the Republic of Korea derives itslegality from the elections held in 1948 under the supervision of a United nations commission, and has no title to sovereignty in those parts of Korea where it proved impossible to hold elections, and where, therefore, it has no claim to be representative. It is known that President Syngman Rhee considers that hisGovernment is the Government of all Korea and is fully entitled to exercise juris-diction throughout the peninsula. If these pretensions were to be accepted, therewould be no necessity for new elections; but they are, in fact, unlikely to findfavour with many members of the United Nations, and any proposal based on them
would be calculated to cause a split in the ranks of the democratic Powers. Indeed,if there is to be any question of United Nations forces operating on any extensiveor semi-permanent basis beyond the 38th parallel, it is considered essential that suchaction should only be taken after some statement of general objectives has beenmade on the lines discussed in paragraph 4 above. It might also be desirable forthe General Assembly resolution contemplated in paragraph 4 above to recall therecommendation contained in the Security Council Resolution of 27th June andto carry it a stage further by recommending that the necessary steps should betaken, under the aegis of the United Nations forces, to promote conditions of stability and security in which the required rehabilitation of the whole area canbe begun.7. The Soviet Union would view United Nations military operations in north korea as an attempt to extinguish by force the satellite &quot; People&apos;s Republic &quot; she has established there. Soviet reactions to such operations cannot be foreseen, but the risks of Soviet (or possibly Chinese) intervention would be increased, since Sovietprestige would suffer if she were to stand by and let her satellite be destroyed. Itis believed that the Soviet Union wishes to avoid provoking a major war, but she might none the less pour in an increased supply of arms and equipment and arrangefor the despatch of increased numbers of &quot; advisers.&quot; She might even arrange forthe despatch of a &quot; volunteer &quot; force, perhaps composed of Russians or Chinese or both, to aid the North Koreans. The resulting situation, which would be much like that which developed during the Spanish Civil War, would be full of explosivepossibilities.8. It is conceivable that irrespective of any intention on the part of the united nations forces to penetrate North Korea, the Soviet Union may decide, once it hasbecome clear that the North Korean offensive has failed either (a) to reoccupy Korea without warning down to the 38th Parallel (a movewhich could not fail to intensify the dangers of the situation, and might even lead to war); or(b) to propose in the United Nations that since United States forces are nowback in South Korea Soviet forces should reoccupy the North to assist in restoring peace.Such moves might be accompanied by specious and plausible unification proposalsdesigned to ensure the establishment of a Communist State throughout Korea.These possibilities make it all the more important that the United Nations shouldclarify their objectives in Korea, if only in general terms, at the earliest possible moment.9. If the Soviet Union were to reoccupy North Korea, there would be aperiod during which Korea would again be under joint military occupation, this time with Soviet forces in the North and United Nations forces in the South. Sovietoccupation authorities would, in so far as this might be practical in the light of the outcome of the present hostilities, endeavour to utilise this period to rearm andre-equip the North Koreans.. Once they had done this they might be able to with-draw and a situation would result in which the unification of Korea would only bepossible if the United Nations were themselves prepared to take the initiative inresuming hostilities. Such a step would, of course, be unthinkable and the situation would be very much what it was before the North Korean attack. In view of thesharp reaction of the United Nations to North Korean aggression, the Soviet Unionmight well decide to forego any further overt assault on South Korea. But SouthKorea would, as before, be subject to continuous attempts at internal subversion.10. Another possibility is that the Russians may resuscitate the proposaloriginally adopted at the Moscow Conference in December 1945, for a Four-PowerTrusteeship for Korea. The four Trustee Powers were the Soviet Union, China,United States and the United Kingdom, the United Kingdom having reserved itsright to invite Australia to take its place. If, as would appear to be the appropriateprocedure, the Soviet Union were to address such a proposal to the other great powers concerned, the grounds of rejection would be clear, viz.: that the problemof Korea had become a matter for discussion by the United Nations. If the soviet union were to introduce a proposal into the United Nations seeking United Nationsendorsement for the revival of the Four-Power Trusteeship proposal, the bestground for rejection might be that this was an inappropriate and retrograde step,since the Koreans had already had an opportunity to demonstrate their capacity
for self-Government. It would be easy, at the same time, to expose Soviet motivesfor introducing such a proposal.11. On the assumption that new national elections throughout Korea even-tually prove possible, it would be necessary for the United Nations forces to remainin Korea at any rate until the elections had been held. Once the North Koreanshave been defeated (and they appear in fact to be so deeply committed in the Souththat their forces may be largely destroyed far to the south of the 38th Parallel), andon the assumption that neither the Russians nor the Chinese enter North Korea,the next step would be to endeavour to establish contact. With the North Koreanauthorities. It is considered that the present United Nations Commission in Koreawould not be a suitable body for this purpose, and that it would be preferable forthe United Nations to set up in the first place an ad hoc group, preferably composedpredominantly of representatives of Asian States, to function as a Truce Com-mission and to be charged with the task of conducting preliminary discussions withrepresentatives of the Korean people regarding the political future of Korea, Theymight appropriately be attached to the United Nations military command for thispurpose, and associated with any discussions that may be held with a view to thetermination of hostilities and the restoration of order. Their main task would beto inform the North Koreans (a) of the intention of the United Nations to hold new elections throughoutKorea on a national basis with a view to the establishment of anindependent and unified Government;(b) that United Nations forces would enter North Korea for the purpose ofmaintaining law and order until the elections had been held and a new national Korean Government established.It would also be desirable for the North Koreans to be told that the United nations forces would prevent violent retaliation against innocent citizens of the North, andthat people should return to their jobs and the administrative machine continue to function as before for the time being. It is to be hoped that it would thus bepossible to arrange for United Nations forces to enter North Korea unopposed.12. It would be necessary thereafter to establish a new United Nations Corn-mission for the purpose of supervising elections throughout Korea. The presentCommission would not be suitable for this purpose, if only because of the low calibreof its members. It is essential that the new Commission should be composed ofmembers of real weight. It is premature to consider in detail the composition ofthe new Commission at this stage, but it would clearly be preferable that it should consist predominantly of Asian members, perhaps with a first-class British Secretary-General. It might also be advisable that the Commission should contain no repre-sentative of a country which has contributed to the United Nations forces in Korea.It might appear anomalous, that the Powers who have made substantial sacrifices forthe defeat of aggression in Korea should be excluded from the Commission. Theywould, of course, be able to play their full part in deciding the political future of korea in the deliberations in the General Assembly. But it is suggested that ifdetailed discussions with the Koreans on the spot were to be conducted by repre-sentatives of Powers other than those who have been engaged in the hostilities, itwould serve to emphasise the special nature of the fighting in Korea and the desire ofthe United Nations to reach an impartial solution.13. It would be desirable for the new Commission to remain in Korea for atleast twelve months and to report on its activities to the next General Assembly. Itwill not, however, be practicable to tie up substantial military forces in Korea forany long period and the contributing Powers will doubtless be anxious to withdraw their forces as soon as possible after the elections. It is hoped that for the reasonstated in paragraph 9, any new democratic State which it is possible to establish in korea will not be subject to external aggression, at any rate in the immediately fore-seeable future. It will, however, be a constant prey to internal subversion and will need continuous diplomatic and material support. It is, in any case, certain that conditions in Korea will remain unsettled and the possibility of serious civil disturb-ances from time to time cannot be excluded. An armed attack on the new Govern-ment from within would, of course, be a civil war, and it would therefore be ex-extremely difficult for United Nations to intervene.Foreign Office, S.W. 1.



</content>
</cab>
