<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/12/7 images: 124-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UMBER LOGIC AND KEY. * .. .It is requested that special care may be taken toomsiipe the secrecy of this document.MOST SECRET^COPY NOASSISTANCETO FINLAND.(previous reference:W.M.(40)61stConclusions,Minute 5.)W.m. (40) 6Snd CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 7.Confidential Annex.(7th March, 1940. )THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR V/AR recounted a longtalk which he had had on the previous day with MajorMagill, who had returned by air from Finland on Monday,the 4th March.Major Magill, who had many and close connections with the Swedes and Finns, had seen much of Field-marshal mannerheim, and reported that he had never seen himso depressed.   Major Magill&apos;s assessment of the presentsituation had been as follows.   The Finns, by character,had immense powers of endurance, but once they crackedthey would break altogether   There were signs of physical failing, due to the tremendous strain to whichthe rank and file had been put, but the fighting troops would not be likely to give in unless the Finnish high command began to weaken.    The fear, therefore, was thatthe rot would set in at the top, particularly as the resultofthe constant defeatist pressure which Sweden nev?r ceased to exert.   Furthermore, the ability of the Russians tofollow up their recent attack? had undoubtedly come asa catastrophic surprise to the Finnish High Command.   Therewas still time to save the situation, but the remedy - andaccording to Major Magill, the only remedy in the opinion  .of the Finns - was the immediate despatch of bombingaircrait.    The Finns had had to withdraw two Divisions

to deal with the attacks which the Russians werelaunching across the ice, but these attacks could easily be countered by bombing the very vulnerabletargets which wore presented by the Russian columnsadvancing without cover across the open ice.   Morebombers were also required for attacking the Russianlines of communication in the Karelian Isthmus, wherevery telling damage could be inflicted.   Above all,these bombers wore needed to put heart into the Finns,without which there was grave danger that they might make peace at any moment.   Major Magill had informed him that there were 3 Blenheim bombers in action withthe Finns and 5 in the workshops, 2 having been lost in action.    The remainder were apparently still ontheir way.   He had brought back with him a completestatement of the ground facilities which the Finnspossessed for the operation of additional aircraft.THE MINISTER FOR 00-ORDINATION OF DEFENCE saidthat he had not any very up-to-date information ofwhat aircraft had actually arrived in Finland, butthe position so far as he knew it was as follows:-gladiators.30 promised.   All had arrived in Finland.G-aunt lets .38 promised.   8 already shipped;   none yet arrived in Finland.   Manufacturers weresupplying 2 a day to the packers.Blenheims.12 long-nosed and 12 short-nosed promised.1 long-nosed Blenheim had been lost in transit and 1 delayed, for some unknownreason, in Sweden;   10 had arrived in finland.   12 short-nosed Blenheims had reached Finland on the 27th February.-2-

Lvsandors .....17 promised..     9 already shipped;    6 had left by air, of which 2 had crashed en route..   2 more were duo to leove by air on the 9th March,Hurricanes.12 promised.   11 had reached Sweden, one havingcrashed en route.Rocs .33 promised.   5 -would go every four days by air, starting about the 9th March.A considerable quantity of bombs, spare parts and ancillary equipment was being sent at the same time as the aircraft.The French were also sending 12 bombers, but itwas understood that these could not fly direct from north Scotland and they would have to be shipped-The only way to get immediate assistance to the Finnsseemed to be to send our own first-line aircraft overby air.   They would have to be flown by R.A.F.personnel, either officially or in the guise of&quot;volunteers&quot;.   It vras true that if we sent these aircraft, and some ground staff to accompany them,the ground staff might be lost for a long time if the finns collapsed, but the aircraft could presumably be flown back and the ma chines themselves put intores reserve.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidthat he did not think we should do any good by continuing to manoeuvre for position with Sweden and finland,   According to Brigadier Ling, Field marshal mannerheim felt that he had already made his appeal,though it was for bombers that he had asked as being

his most urgent need 4   He thought that the right course was , therefore^ to send some bombers immedi-at-cly, and to waste no more time haggling withSweden *Continuing, the Foreign Secretary gave the WarCabinet an account of an interview which Sir alexander cadogan had just had with the French Ambassador, whohad informed him that, according to information inthe possession of the French, the Finns had startednegotiations with the Russians, but would not acceptthe terms which the Russians had offered.   They werenot prepared to give up Viborg, but would be willingto cede Hango, which the Russians ranted as a naval base.   They would not continue their negotiationswith the Russians after the 12th March, and if theycould not get the terms for which they were standingout, would turn once more to the Allies for assist-anee.   The Swedes were pressing the Finnish Govern-ment very hard to make peace, but when asked if theywould guarantee Finland against Russia, if theRussian terms were accepted, they had refused.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR pointed out that so long as -e kept our expedition all ready to sailto Scandinavia, we were less able to spare any material for Finland.    If it was decided definatly to call the expedition off, we should probably beable to lot the Finns have more material&apos;.THE PRIME MINISTER said that there were two questions to be decided.   First, what was to be done about the proposed expedition, and, secondly, whatimmediate assistance *--e could send to the Finns-

He suggested that we should tell the Finns forthwiththat they must make up their minds within, say, 24hours, whether they were going to appeal to us forarmed assistance.     If no such appeal was received, weshould cancel the expedition altogether.     We might at the same time inform them what we could do in theway of immediate assistance.     As to that, he himself was in favour of taking considerable risks and sending a substantial number of bombers, provided always, ofcourse, that the Finns were not intending to give wayto the Russians.Considerable discussion then ensued as towhat communication should be made to the Finns.     Thefollowing were the principal points which emerged:(i)    The Finnish Minister had been informedtwo days before that we could not take any decision about the despatch ofadditional aircraft until we receivedour appeal from the Finns.     But itwas agreed that the situation had now changed.     The Swedes were clearly not going to allow our troops to pass through and any hope of bringing off the majorproject was therefore receding..(ii)    If we made any mention in the communication of our willingness to send additional aircraft immediately, the Finns wouldbe encouraged to press us for this formof assistance rather than for an Alliedexpedition which was, of course, essentialto the carrying through of the mainproject of getting control of Galivare.The Finns probably had no   intention ofappealing for armed assistance, but were only hesitating to say so for fear of losing their chance of getting moreaircraft.(iii)    It was suggested that it might be better to inform the Finns that we had now beenwaiting for some time to receive theiranswer;    that this delay was very em-barrassing to. us;    that we had therefore no option but to treat them as if theywere not intending to appeal for Allied

land forces, and that in these circum-stances we now proposed that our assistance should take the form of sending bomber aircraft.     It was felt,however, that it would be undesirable togive the Finns an opportunity for sayingthat we had withdrawn our offer of help.(iv)   The Finns were now being offered harsherterms by Russia than those which had ledto the war in the first place.     If wepromised them additional bombers, this offer might well encourage them to holdout for better terms.     We could not forbidthem to come to terms of any kind, and wecould not make our offer of bombers con-ditional on their not coming to terms withRussia.      If Finland did come to terms withRussia, it might be possible to hold up atleast some of the bombers before they hadall been sent.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he would not haveacceded to any request for the despatch of furtherfighters,since this would have meant a direct weakening of ourown defences.     Our bomber   force on the other hand wasonly a deterrent to attack on this country.       he therefore suggested that we might offer 50 bombers tothe Finns.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR pointed outthat to weaken our bomber force in this country mightinvite attack on us by the Germans.       He would liketo have an opportunity of consulting his technical advisers before coming to a final decision.     suppose that we sent these aircraft,and then after all the finns collapsed a short time afterwards, we shouldhave incurred grave risk to no purpose.     He doubted whether, if the Finns managed to last out till- April,they would then be able to hold on until July, duringthe period of the thaw.     His own opinion was that thedespatch of these aircraft would do nothing more thanpostpone the inevitable for about three weeks.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said thatMajor Magill&apos;s report tended to confirm this view.

THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER pointed outthat the offer of 50 &quot;bombers would make a very bigdifference in the presentation of our case to the world.The Swedes would no doubt try to make out that we were only serving our own selfish interests and had no real desire to assist the Finns at all.    But if we nowoffered 50 bombers, which we could ill afford, after the swedes had refused to allow us to send an expedition tohelp the Finns, it would be clear that we had doneeverything possible to aid Finland.    This was an important political consideration, which must be balanced against therisk we were running in denuding our bomber force in thiscountry.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO observed that ifwe sent bombers, we must expect further demands from the finns for other material, such as artillery, which theywould say was essential to enable them to continue thestruggle.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that one ofthe main reasons why the Finns wanted aircraft was forcounter-battery work.    We had no artillery to spare whichwere suitable for this purpose.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of Statefor Air and himself should draft a communication to theFinnish Government in the light of the discussion which had taken place.The War Cabineti-(i) Agreed that authority should be given forthe despatch of up to 50 bomber aircraft to Finland, subject to further consultation as to the technical problems involved,the arrangements necessary in regard topersonnel, the dates of despatch, etc.

THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER pointed outthat the offer of 50 bombers would make a very bigdifference in the presentation of our case to the world.The Swedes would no doubt try to make out that we were only serving our own selfish interests and had no real desire to assist the Finns at all.   But if we nowoffered 50 bombers, which we could ill afford, after the swedes had refused to allow us to send an expedition tohelp the Finns, it would be clear that we had doneeverything possible to aid Finland.    This was an important political consideration, which must be balanced against therisk we were running in denuding our bomber force in thiscountry.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO observed that ifwe sent bombers, we must expect further demands from the finns for other material, such as artillery, ?/hich theywould say was essential to enable them to continue thestruggle.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that one ofthe main reasons why the Finns wanted aircraft was forcounter-battery work.   We had no artillery to spare whichwere suitable for this purpose.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of Statefor Air and himself should draft a communication to theFinnish Government in the light of the discussion which had taken place.The War Cabinets -(i) Agreed that authority should be given forthe despatch of up to 50 bomber aircraft to Finland, subject to further consultation as to the technical problems involved,the arrangements necessary in regard topersonnel, the dates of despatch, etc.

(ii) Authorised the Prime Minister and the secretaries of State for Foreign Affairs and Air, inconsultation, to draft a telegram for despatch to Helsinki on the lines indicated in discussion;(a) Asking for a definite answer withina specified period as to whether the finns intended to issue an appeal for allied land forces.(b) Conveying to the Finns the promise offurther air assistance as at (i) above.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
