<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/67/0 images: 232-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Tx^Tlffis^ocuDient is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1918.CONFIDENTIAL.G.T.-6062.THE INDIANS AND GERMAN EAST AFRICA.Memoeandum by Lord Cuezon.MR. MONTAGU in his paper (G.T.-6028) has expressed surprise that none of us who have written or spoken on the future of the German colonies has said anything about Sir T. Morisons proposal in an earlier paper (G.T.-5132), that German East Africa should, if we are able to control its future, be reserved as a colony for Indians from India. I refrained from doing so, because I felt that my knowledge of India was not sufficiently recent to enable me to speak with authority on the subject. Since, however, those who question the wisdom or practicability of such an idea have been challenged, I may perhaps indicate some of the reasons why the proposition seems to me to require a good deal of examination before it can be accepted.1. Sir T. Morison spoke of the grant of this territory double the size of Germany itself to India as a compensation to her for her inability to force her emigrants upon the other dominions of the Crown. I regret this conclusion as much as anyone, and fought hard to mitigate it. But that a restriction, imposed by economic, political, and other considerations of unquestionable validity, entitles India to compensation or to a position of especial interest or privilege in some other portion of the British Empire or of the world, I fail to see. Indian soldiers have fought splendidly in the war. But the doctrine that they are therefore entitled as an act of justice to a slice of another continent when they already possess so large a portion of the earth&apos;s surface in their own, is in my view untenable, and, if accepted, could not be confined to Indians alone.2. But this at once raises the question whether their own land does suffice in the present state for the Indian population for of course a new colony could not be confined to fighting soldiers alone. Mr. Montagu rests his case in the main on the alleged congestion of India. I do not accept this view. In my time there was a surplus of unoccupied but cultivable land in India said to amount to 80,000,000 acres. The land under&apos; cultivation could undoubtedly, with improved methods, have supported a much larger population. The conservative habits of Indians and the difficulties attending internal migration, prevented these gaps from being filled up. But with every year that passes the improvement in means of communication and the advancing intelligence of the people are remedying these defects. Further, the growth of manufacturing industries on a large scale and herein lies a great future for India will provide opportunities for the employment of a vastly increased industrial population. The total emigrant population of India in my day was, I think, between one and one and a half millions attracted abroad by the lure of higher pay or lucrative business. But their departure was a regrettable rather than an admirable symptom, and I would far sooner have seen them remaining and working in or on their native land. As a matter of fact, the demand for coolie labour in India is greatly in excess of the supply, and this is shown by the rapid and unarrested increase in the rate of coolies&apos; wages. When India is clamouring for labour, and can find employment for far more than she produces, it seems absurd to plan schemes for the expatriation of what she has got.3. I submit therefore that the first call upon Indian manhood and Indian patriotism is not Africa, but India itself. The Secretary of State has embarked upon a policy of arousing the national sentiment of Indians. He is anxious to see them I enjoy responsible government. Let the class whom he hopes to produce devote some portion of their labour and energies to filling up and developing their native land before they scatter themselves on a foreign soil.4. Further, if we take the case of the retired Indian soldier, it is a mistake to suppose either that he ought to be encouraged to go abroad, or that he cannot be pro-vided for at home. If he emigrates, he, and very likely his family, are lost to India, and the advantages of his service, patriotism, and influence are sacrificed.   He ought to-in
in.   ^Itbe encouraged to settle down in India and to give his sons to the army after him. Nor are the opportunities of satisfying his needs anywhere near to exhaustion. Scientific irrigation will continue to add for another quarter of a century at least, probably for half a century, to the cultivable area of India, and consequently to the available field for&apos; settlement. The scheme known as the Triple Canal Scheme, although completed is not yet under full development. The great project called the Sind-Sagar Scheme, for reclaiming the waste lands on the east of the Indus, will take many many years before it comes into operation. The fighting races of India are mainly drawn from the north-western areas, and here, and not in East Africa, lies their natural and appointed home.5. German East Africa has a native population, of the Bantu race, of between 7 and 8 millions. I presume they have the first right to the soil. There is no reason why they should be extruded by any outsiders. If it be replied that there is no intention &apos;so to treat them, truth compels me to state that Indian masters or land-owners would not only not be more tolerant, but would almost certainly be less so to a negro population than would a white race. The racial prejudice between the dark skin and the black skin is, on the whole, greater than that between black and white. Of this the social habits of India itself and the attitude of Indians towards the submerged castes or classes of their own countrymen affords abundant evidence. By any such scheme of colonisation it is more than likely that the native African peoples would be the last to gain. The idea that the Indian constitutes a sort of physiological link or half-way house between the white man and the negro is, I believe, a chimera &apos; in thie context.6. Is it desirable to reproduce and set up in the African continent a replica of the social life and standards of India ? They will be a complete exotic in a strange land. India has developed its own type of national character and civilisation in its own environment. There it is assuming forms that are already sufficiently perplexing, and will become more so. Do we wish to add to the manifold African problems that will press for solution the creation of what would in time be another Indian State on African soil ?7. I have said nothing about the view of the white peoples who have spent so much effort and blood in the conquest of this part of Africa, and who, if the spoils are to be distributed within the British Empire, could hardly be expected to welcome an Indian migration, sharing or even depriving them of the rewards of victory.8. Neither have I said anything about those portions of the captured colony which are capable of colonisation by the white man. But, again, the handing over of these to an imported population from India would hardly be popular. There are few enough of these areas in Central Africa as it is. It would be doubtful policy to alienate any one of their number.9. These are a few of the reasons which lead me to think that we should pause before pronouncing hastily in favour of an Indian colony on a large scale in German East Africa. Of course, Indians would not be excluded from the country any more than they are from British East Africa, where the Khojas from India are a most prosperous and very wealthy community ; but that is a very different thing from handing over the entire country to Indian settlement.10. If the destiny of the captured German possessions is to be determined at the Peace Conference, it is for consideration whether such a proposal would be likely to meet with much support there. Might it not be regarded as a subtle device on the part of Great Britain to keep these territories for herself?11. Lastly, I ask the question whether India either aspires to be, or is qualified to become, a colonising Power. I cannot recall, when I knew it, any such demand put forward by her spokesmen. If they have changed their views, I would still urge that the exploitation of their own country-the industrial surface of which has barely been scratched-affords a better scope for an awakening national consciousness than experiments in another and alien atmosphere. As to the capacity of India for colonisation on a considerable scale (apart from petty trading and contract labour), that remains quite untested.0. of k.October 19, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
