<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/67/0 images: 292-298</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jThis Document is the Property.of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]hi (;i oPrinted for the War Cabinet,   October 1.918.SECRET. G.T.-6083.r jTHE LABOUR SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending the 23rd October, 1918.Sdmmary.Part I: General Remarks.Some recent developments of the Rank and File Movement are discussed.Part II: Press Comments.The opinion of the Labour press on military affairs, with special reference to the Peace Notes and the League of Nations ; on home affairs, with special reference to demobilisation, separation allowances, the shipwrights&apos; claim, and Sir John Simons Committee ; and on food is described.Part III: District Reports.On the whole the industrial situation is distinctly tranquil, though unrest prevails among aircraft workers and in the electrical trades.Part IV: Disputes.(a.) Involving a Stoppage of Work. There has been no serious strike during the week.(6.) Not involving a Stoppage of Work. The surface workers&apos; dispute continues, and threatens to become more serious; otherwise no important dispute is in progress.I.-General Remarks. Recent Developments of the Rank and File Movement.The progress of the Rank and File Movement has afforded some interesting developments during the past few months, and there are symptoms of a recrudescence of its activity after a time of comparative quiet. The fact affords justification for a short review of the present position.There are four chief centres of organisation. These are in constant touch, and may, in times of active agitation, combine for mutual support, but are distinct not only in entity but in policy. They are the rjational Amalgamation Committee and the Clyde Workers&apos; Committee for the workshops, the Scottish Miners&apos; Reform Committee, and the South Wales Miners&apos; Unofficial Reform Committee for the mines.There is also in process of formation a national organisation, named &quot;The Shop Stewards&apos; Workers&apos; Committee,&quot; which has not yet had time to function, and it is not clear whether, and, if so, how far it represents the regular, as opposed to the rank and file, shop steward.The National Amalgamation Committee has hitherto attempted with limited success to constitute itself the national shop stewards&apos; organisation, and it may be said to represent the Workers&apos; Committees elected by the shop stewards in the various industrial centres. Representatives from all these Committees attend its conferences, and its influence, though as yet not of great importance, appears to be increasing. As an outstanding example of this may be cited the fact that the Mersey Reconstruction Committee, a shop stewards&apos; organisation in Liverpool and Birkenhead, recently sub-
mitted its draft constitution to the National Amalgamation Committee for approval, thus recognising the superior authority attaching to the latter Committee. The bonds attaching the various Workers&apos; Committees to this national organisation can not, how-ever, be described as powerful, and as a rule local Committees resort to it only when they desire national action in support of a dispute, as, for instance, in the case of the embargo strike at Coventry. The National Committee is weak, largely for financial reasons. It contains, however, the brains of the Shop Steward Movement in England, and the question of strengthening its position appears to be only one of time, unless the constitutional Trade Unions are able to reassert their authority.The Clyde Workers&apos; Committee originally confined its activity to the workshops on the Clyde, but has recently adopted more ambitious views. It is now reported that its more prominent members have evolved a scheme to develop Shop Committees in Scotland generally, controlled by an executive and administrative committee, which it is proposed to designate &quot;The Scottish Council of Shop Stewards&apos; Committees.&quot; The policy of this body frankly is to develop extremist or &quot;rebel&quot; control of the workshops It is stated that the scheme is likely to meet with widespread opposition from the regular shop stewards, who form a large majority. It is interesting to note that, while the English National Amalgamation Committee confines its activities to factories, the Scottish Council will include representatives of the mines.The two Miners&apos; Reform Committees are not only in principle of the same nature, but are also in close and confidential touch with one another. Each is a &quot;ginger group&quot; within its Trade Union organisation, whose main object is not so much to embarrass the Executive of the organisation as to stimulate it to more decided progressive effort. How long this species of relationship between the Scottish Miners&apos; Reform Committee and the Scottish Miners&apos; Federation will continue seems questionable, as the former appears to be at least as important an element in the formation of the Scottish Council of Shop Stewards&apos; Committees as does the Clyde Workers&apos; Committee itself. The South Wales Unofficial Reform Committee has developed considerable strength since its success in connection with the Tredegar strike, but cannot be regarded as approaching the Scottish Committee in general influence and-power.An interesting feature of the Rank and File Movement is the political aspect evident in Scotland and in South Wales, while in England the National Amalgamation Committee and its constituents have stated that their aims are non-political. In dealing with the new constitution of the Mersey Reconstruction Committee the National Amalgamation Committee recorded that its interests were confined to matters within the workshop, and this policy has been evident in the leading Workers&apos; Committees, e.g., those of Barrow and of Manchester. In Scotland and South Wales, on the other hand, the interests of the various rank and file organisations appear to be largely political. For instance, at a miners&apos; conference held by the Scottish Reform Committee on the 12th October of six resolutions passed, one dealt with separation allowances, one with the Russian Socialist Republic, and a third with John Maclean. The Clyde Workers&apos; Committee is frankly pacifist, and called a conference in mid-September with the intention of uniting the workers in the workshops in Scotland in such action as would cause a cessation of the war. The attempt proved a complete failure, but the political intention was manifest.The increasing importance of the Rank and File Movement is evident by growing anxiety on the part of the Unions and by the measure of recognition obtained by the Shop Stewards&apos; Committees in various quarters. Of the former symptom there have been several outstanding instances. There have, for instance, been cases of protest against the alleged unconstitutional action of the Committees, of which a noticeable example was the attack made by Mr. Vernon Hartshorn on the South Wales Miners&apos; Unofficial Reform Committee. More important examples, however, are evident in the attempts which axe being made in various quarters to constitutionalise the movement either by affording it a recognised place within the Trade Union organisation, or by creating a separate mechanism to ensure more intimate, touch between the men in the shops and the Union machinery. Of the former nature probably the most complete example is that of the Oldham Provincial Operative Cotton Spinners Association, whose Executive Council made proposals for the formation of &quot; Shop Clubs &quot; in each firm or works, each of which should elect two representatives to. attend the monthly meetings of the Association, and should present to the Club official reports of those meetings. The scheme also lays down that each Shop Club should hold regular monthly meetings. Action to recognise the shop stewards and to utilise their services is also being taken by the carpenters, cabinet-makers, and joiners, which, if finally approved, will devolute considerable powers to the stewards.
An interesting instance of an effort to replace the functions of the Shop Stewards Committees and Workers&apos; Committees by amendment of the normal Trade Union procedure, is seen in the action taken by the National Conference of District Com-mittees in the Engineering Trade, which was held on the 8th September, and was attended by over 200 delegates, representing all parts of Great Britain. It was resolved to constitute a national organisation, representing the Trade Union District Committees, which should have its headquarters in London, and work through four provincial centres, &amp;c, Edinburgh, Leeds, Coventry, and London.The growing import; nee of the Rank and File Movement is further emphasised by the measure of recognition which it claims to have obtained both from the Government and from the employers. The Woolwich shop stewards, for instance, claim that the)&apos; have been recognised by the Ministry of Munitions, and that in the negotiations in respect of the London aircraft strike their assistance was accepted. That this recognition was definite and unqualified is certainly not the case, but the impression conveyed was such as to lead the Committee to believe that recognition had, in fact, been accorded.The outstanding instance of recognition by the employers, though here again it was of a modified kind, is the Coventry agreement between the Engineering Employers&apos; Federation and a number of Unions, which settled the strike of last November. Certain important Unions, including the A.S.E., refused to become parties. The agreement was, however, hailed by the rank and file in general, if not as entirely satisfactory, at least as admitting recognition of the shop stewards as an organisation apart from the Unions.Permanent strength of the Shop Stoward Movement in its present form is not established, but the growth of its power and the spread of its organisations indicate that it is meeting a need felt by the worker. Its importance certainly warrants and is now commencing to seoure the attention of the Unions, and the experiments which are being made with tht intention either1 of grafting the existing system on to the Trade Union organisation, or, alternatively, of amending the latter to secure in another way the legitimate aims of the Shop Steward Movement, are worthy of close attention. As a political power the movement has as yet shown little sign of strength, nor is it probable that it will develop in that direction, although the combination of the Clyde Workers&apos; Committee with the Miners&apos; Reform Committee may stimulate the political importance of the movement in Scotland. Provision for political progress in connection with industry is, however, generally available in the various socialist parties and the I.L.P., and to these it would appear that the Shop Stewards&apos; Movement will never be ah effective alternative.II. Press Comments.(A.) Military.Labour opinion on the Presidents notes is as usual hopelessly divided. The pacifist section is content for the most part to ring the changes upon the evils of secret diplomacy with its consequent entanglements and hindrances to peace. The &quot; Herald&quot; in an article headed &quot; Write to Lloyd George about it&quot; says that &quot; it is probable that the war would be ended to-morrow, but that the secret treaties have not been repudiated, and that Germany cannot consequently trust the Allies to behave fairly.&quot; It also casts doubts upon the Allies&apos; acceptance of the fourteen points, especially the one containing a reference to the freedom of the seas. The &quot; Herald &quot; is of the opinion that this accounts for the howl of rage with which the Jingo press welcomed the prospect of an early peace. The &quot;Labour Leader&quot; expresses itself in similar terms: &quot; The best comment upon the satisfactory character of the German reply to President Wilson, and the hope that it affords of a reasonable peace, is to be found in the frenzied protests in the Allied newspapers against the acceptance of the conditions laid down by Mr. Wilson, and agreed to by the Central Powers.&quot; The &quot; Labour Leader&quot; is further prepared to accept the German offer at its face value, and thinks &quot;that the view &quot; that it is merely a cunning and cynical device on the part of the enemy for withdrawing his retreating army in safety within his own frontiers is wholly discredited.&quot; The &quot; Workers Dreadnought&quot; concludes that the Allied Governments are determined to continue the war until they secure unconditional surrender, and thinks that the &quot;lust of victory is postponing peace.&quot;   The &quot; Call&quot; suggests that the real problem now facing
the Allies is whether the continuance of the war will not lead to a general revolu-.,tion, which would appear to be an eminently desirable consummation, seeing that &quot;a peace without a Eevolution means a capitalist peace, with the enslavement of the working classes.&quot; &quot; Justice,&quot; on the other hand, robustly argues for unconditional surrender, claiming that Germany has placed herself outside the pale of the law. The only questions for the Allies to determine are, the amount ol compensation that they shall demand, and the nature of the guarantees, which should include inter alia the transfer of the German navy and mercantile marine to the Allies.The &quot; British Citizen &quot; in an article on unconditional surrender proceeds to criticise President Wilsons fourteen points, arid somewhat resents the intervention of American diplomacy, especially in view of Britains efforts and France&apos;s sufferings. It declares itself opposed to the doctrine of the freedom of the seas, and suggests that what the Monroe doctrine is to America, maritime supremacy is to England.Mr. Alexander Thompson, writing in the &quot; Clarion &quot; makes an interesting sugges-tion for changing the balance of power in Germany against Prussia by encouraging the federation of the South German States, including Austria, with Vienna as capital.The League of Nations.Mr. Fairchild, in the &quot; Call,&quot; considers that the League of Nations, as envisaged by Earl Grey, would be an instrument of the highest potency for developing Imperialist capitalism, and claims that with the League of Nations should also go a league of workers, otherwise exploitation of the backward races and intervention in the affairs of weaker States will become the rule.The &quot;Labour Leader,&quot; under the above title, gives prominence to a speech of Gilbert Murray&apos;s delivered at Manchester, in the course of which he said that &quot; if we did not succeed in establishing a League of Nations, we should have Europe federated against us. Germany originally meant to form a sort of hegemony, in which she could hold lordship over Europe. She has given that up. What she is trying for now is a federation of European States, to which we shall not belong.&quot;(B.) Rome Affairs.Demobilisation.The &quot;Herald,&quot; in its Labour notes, alleges that the Government is utterly unpre-pared for peace, and thinks that many of&apos; the half-digested reports issued by Govern-ment Committees will only make confusion more confounded. The writer recommends that for a period of at least a year after the war no employer shall be allowed to lower the rate of wages including all additions made during the war. Any employer attempting a reduction should be liable to prosecution.Separation AllowancesThe agitation for a liberal increase in the amount of&apos;the separation allowance is. continued both in the &quot; Herald &quot; and the &quot; Labour Leader.&quot;The Shipwrights&apos; Claim.The &quot; Herald &quot; criticises the decision of the Committee on Production on the ground that the men&apos;s demands have been rejected, merely with a suggestion that they will be dealt with on a national scale. The refusal to grant anything, coupled with the victimisation of some of the men, hardly seems a statesmanlike course.Sir J. Simon&apos;s Committee.The &quot; Call&quot; views the appointment of Sir John Simon&apos;s Committee with anxiety, as it thinks the intention is to continue the measure of compulsory arbitration after the war, and it urges the workers to ensure that the right to strike in the transition period is not interfered with.(Q.).-Food.r &quot;Justice&quot; declares that 17,000,0001 have been lost through the Government purchasing bacon in American at 3d. and id. per lb. above the prices ruling in Chicago on the day of purchase. The remedy suggested is the establishment of communal shops eontrolled by citizens and workers. Instead of the Food Ministry and a horde of bureaucratic jackals, let us have a national Food Parliament, absolutely independent .of this jobbery and corruption.
] 11. District Reports.London and South-E astern.It is reported that considerable unrest still prevails among London aircraft workers, and trouble is also anticipated among the electricians.A suspicion has, it is said, been aroused among the aircraft workers that the Ministry of Munitions is seeking to reduce the present rate of pay. The reason for the suspicion is stated to be the belief that two of the best paying shops have had to discharge their men for lack of work, while a tirm paying a poor rate and employing many Munition volunteers has been ordered to double its output. The men are of opinion that the Munition volunteers are used to force down wages, and efforts are being made to induce them to resign.Unrest prevails both among the members of the E.T.U. and the Electrical Power Engineers&apos; Association. Although there is no likelihood of these two opposing unions working together, a strike on the part of the E.T.U. would place the latter body in a strong position to obtain concessions.A report has been received to the effect that trouble continues among the women at Woolwich. Extra pay for night work is demanded, but it is not anticipated that drastic measures will be adopted.Stubbs declared at Woolwich, on the 16th October, that his reinstatement in the Arsenal was now a certainty.West Midlands.No unrest is reported in this district. Dingley, who has entered into partnership with an experimental engineer at Coventry, complains that he can get no orders from the firms, and that he is being victimised.Yorkshire and East Midlands.At York the National Federated Engineering Employers and the Engineering Trade Unions have held a conference on the question of apprentices who are serving with the army; no agreement was reached and a further conference is to be held.It is reported that the Discharged and Demobilised Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Federa-tion at Sheffield, in conjunction with the Sheffield Workers&apos; Committee and Workers&apos; Socialist Federation, have issued a manifesto appealing to the workers to see that justice is done to discharged men and their dependants, and demanding increased separation allowances.The munition workers at Sheffield are beginning to express anxiety as to their prospects when the factories are closed down.The Leicester Labour Party has passed a resolution expressing its admiration for the Wakefield absolutists, and demanding their immediate release.North-Western.Considerable unrest is reported in this area, which is especially noticeable at the Aintree Aircraft Factory and at Messrs. Crossley&apos;s, Gorton.At a meeting of the Mersey Engineering and Shipbuilding Trades&apos; Federation, on the 15th October, it was decided to call a special meeting to deal with the question of the output bonus scheme at the Aintree factory. It appears that, although all the workers at this factory are in favour of the scheme, the officials of the Carpenters&apos; Cabinet-makers&apos; and Joiners&apos; Society oppose it, on the ground that no system of piece-work has been allowed in this district by the society for over twenty years. It is possible that this society may attempt to withdraw their members from the factory.Trouble is reported from Messrs. Crossleys, Gorton. It is said that the firm has recently stopped the special prices paid to the men employed on a job before the rate fixer had fixed its price. The men know that they have no legal claim to the extra rate, but they think the firm is taking the opportunity to lower prices (at the risk of a strike) at the present time, because the prospect of peace lessens the need for maximum output. They also complain that the newly-appointed rate fixer is fixing inadequate rates and is being backed by the management in doing so. Further, the men are being-induced to work their hardest by the promise of high wages, only to find that the firm, having ascertained the shortest possible time in which a job can be done, then give the work to a sub-contractor to be done at a cheaper rate.
Discontent is reported to prevail at Viekers&apos;, Barrow, owing to the refusal of the Committee on Production to grant an additional bonus of &apos;12s. (id. a week.At Messrs. A. V. Hoe, Manchester, the woodworkers, supported by the engineers, aro agitating for a uniform flat rate and a forty-seven-hour week.South Wales.The agitation for an eight hours&apos; day for surface workers is. assuming a more   -threatening  character.   The  Monmouthshire,  South  Wales and Forest of Dean Association of Enginemen, Stokers, and Craftsmen decided on the 19th October to take a ballot on the advisability of leadering fourteen days&apos; notice to cease work.The Executive- Council of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation has convened a meeting of the Council for the 24th October to discuss the Coal Controllers reply, which they declare must be ready by that date.The serious depletion of doctors, who are being called up for military service, may cause trouble among the miners. The Miners&apos; Federation thinks it would be advisable to avoid any farther reduction of the number of doctors in the district.Scotland.The situation in this area remains quiet, as far as strikes are concerned. The Shop Steward Movement has entered upon a period of activity, but is likely to meet with opposition in certain quarters among the workmen. The matter is dealt with in Part I.The decision of the Committee on Production regarding the shipwrights&apos; claim for a minimum, is stated to have caused much disappointment. Although the extremists are calling for drastic action, the majority, including men of military age, advocate a waiting policy until the revision of wages on the 28th October.IV. Disputes.The general situation is fairly quiet; there are no strikes of special importance in progress at present.(a.) Involving a Stoppage of Work.The Admiralty Labour Department only reports two fresh stoppages this week, although there are several cases of men refusing to work overtime.On the 14th October certain metal dressers and fitters ceased work at A. Ballantine&apos;s, Edinburgh, demanding a written guarantee that womens labour, introduced under a dilution scheme, will be removed after the war. The scheme and the question of a guarantee was explained to the men, and they returned to work on the 16th October.The strike of the electricians at Messrs. Harland and Wolffs, Belfast, reported last week, ended on the 14th October.The Ministry of Munitions reports that 3,681 workers were on strike, and five strikes remained unsettled on the 16th October.The sheet metal-workers employed at the Air Navigation Company (Addlestone) struck in sympathy with the sheet metal-workers at Vickers&apos;. The latter strike was reported in last vveek&apos;s report. Workers at both firms, resumed on the 16th October.Men employed on aeroplane wings at Messrs. G. H. Mortons, and at Messrs. J. Parkinson&apos;s, Liverpool, are on strike. They refuse to handle material to be used by men working under a payment by results scheme at the Aintree National Factory.The Goal Controller reports eleven new stoppages. In eight cases work has already been resumed.At one or two anthracite collieries in South Wales the mechanics have stopped work in connection with the demand for an eight-hours&apos; day.The War Office Contracts Department reports two fresh stoppages of minor importance.
Reported from other Sources.Two hundred and fifty women struck at Messrs. Anderson&apos;s Rubber Works, Bristol, on the 1.7th October, because certain other women refused to join a Union. The strike is supported by the United Garment Workers&apos; Union.On the 14th October a strike occurred at the Parkhouse Iron Ore Mine, Bigrigg. The majority of enginemen employed here had lately transferred from the Cum-berland En&quot;inemen&apos;s Association to the Cumberland Ore Miners and Kindred Trades Association. One engineman still refuses to transfer, and it is on this account that the men have struck.   The strike has spread to several mines in the vicinity.(b.) Not involving a Stoppage of Work.No cases of importance are reported by the Admiralty Labour Department.The Ministry of Munitions reports a few cases.A strike is threatened at Messrs. Sir William Angus, Sanderson and Company&apos;s works (Newcastle-on-Tyne), because certain sheet metal-workers object to the employ-ment of girls on what they regard as a skilled job. The firm is now engaging discharged soldiers and others who will be trained for the work.*The Goal Controller reports a meeting with the representatives of the Forest of Dean Owners and Miners to discuss the alleged victimisation of William Hoare (referred to last week). The men&apos;s representatives refused to accept as a settlement the owners&apos; offer to employ Hoare at a more distant colliery, but they have promised to lay this offer before the men.The War Office Contracts Department reports that a strike of cutters is threatened at S. Schneider and Sons, East London, unless the firm agrees to a reduction in the number of thicknesses cut.A conference is to be held on the 23rd October, at the Ministry of Labour, to discuss the hours of work and wages of the jute workers at Dundee.The Committee on Production heard thirty-five cases in London and twenty-six in Glasgow last week.These included (1) an application from Electrical Engineers in Lancashire and Cheshire for an advance of 3s. 6d. per week ; (2) an application from the A.S.E. for an advance of 20s. a week for all grades of chargemen employed in the Tyne shipyards ; (3) an application from the Amalgamated Society of Woodcutting Machinists in Scotland for an increase of 15s. a week for various grades of sawyers.The Chief Industrial Commissioner reports 201 new differences for the week ending 19th October. *Among them is the claim of the Tramway and Omnibus employes for a total war advance of 25s. over the pre-war weekly rates.G. H. ROBERTS.

</content>
</cab>
