<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 72-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IJSCHEJTDIRECTORATE OF INTELLIGENCEteport Ho .6.(Home Gffioe)Sootland Houoe, S.W.1, 4th June, 1919,A WEEKLY REVIEW OF THE PROGRESS OF REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS ABROADFRANCE ................Page belgium. SWITZERLAND GERMANY.... HUNGARY....ITALY......RUSSIA.....,POLAND......FINLANDNORWAY......SWEDEN......DENMARK1&quot;   2M    2&quot; 4&quot; 4- 6&quot; 8&quot; 8&quot; 8&quot; 9&quot; 9HOLLAND................     &quot; 10.Pa^SPAIN....................CHINA...................PERSIA.....................    &quot;JAPAN......................   &quot;TURKEY.....................   (:EGYPT...................INDIA...................SOUTH AFRICA............AUSTRALIA..................NEW ZEALAND................   S!CANADA.....................UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. ., SOUTH AMERICA (Argentine).. PERU.......................e10 11 II 11 11 12 12A1314 14 14 14SUMMARYThe Bolshevik Governments in Russia and Hungary are tottering.      Crowds of refugees are arriving, destitute and starving, at the Finnish frontier, and refugees are also pouring out of Hungary.   Their unoonsoious propaganda has had a very steadying effeot on the neighbouring oountries.Labour unrest both in North and South Amerioa has taken on a Bolshevik aapeot, and it is difficult to say how far this may go in Canada and tho Argentino.The Bolshevik movement is also travelling eastward through Asia, but here it is not so much tho Communist dootrine as the prospeot of anarohy and loot whioh is influencing the Moslem world.   The intrigues of the Young Turks are behind the most aotive of these movements.In South Africa, there is anxiety about the attitude of the natives.It has been ascertained that Ludwig Martens, the leader of the Bolsheviks in America, voluntarily registered himself as a German when in this oountry.    A photograph of the Register is being supplied to the Amerioan Embassy for transmission to the State Department.Since this report was written a big strike movement is developing in Franoe and it is said that 200,000 workers will be involved.
The feeling of hatred against the Germans is reported to be deolining in Far1b , and there is a talk of renewing commercial relations with Germany. ;The Socialist Labour oampaign&apos;against military inter-vention in Russia oontinues, and Bolshevik suooesses are applauded in the extreme papers, which are also pressing for amnesty for political and military offenders.    On this point, the Socialists were defeated in the Chamber, but with a smaller vote than heretofore.There is unrest among the miners, in the Loire and at Lyons and Marseilles, but no active trouble is anticipated immediately.    The unemployed problem at Calais and Dunkirk is still pressing.    On the whole, military morale appears to be good.A Society Called the &quot;Young Sooialist Federation&quot; has ,   been established at Lyons to teaoh revolutionary ideas to the children,    It has branches in Switzerland and is .,(.  - believed to draw its funds from that country.    The children are taught to admire the Bolshevik,doctrines,Violent Renunciation of the Allies in oonnection with the Peaoe Terms is subsiding.    The disposition is to accept &apos;. the European situation, and to claim territorial advantages in Afrioa - in East Africa by right of oonquest, and in the Congo on the grounds of equity.    Sir Herbert Samuel&apos;s inter-view with the Belgian Press appears to have done good.Eoonomio. conditions have Improved; retail prices have fallen, and, except In Antwerp. unemployed labour is being gradually absorbed.    The shortage of raw materials may be mitigated by the starting&quot;of the furaaoea at some of the large iron works.    There is said to be less discontent among/
(Foreign) - 2 -among the workmen.SWITZERLAND.For the present there appears to be no speoial-danger of a Bolshevik rising, though agitation oontinues.    The Bolsheviks profess to believe that the aneriCan soldier3 on leave are there to reinforce the Swiss army and the Police in case of trouble,Axelrod, who was arrested with Flatten at Helsingfors, was detained and searched by the Federal Authorities on his arrival at Bale, but nothing inoriminating wus found on him,GERMANY.Baron yon Rolshausen, of the German Legation in Copenhagen, has stated that the signing of the peaoe Treaty by Germany will be followed almost immediately by a Monarchi Counter-Revolution.    Public opinion is being prepared for a Military Dictatorship, but the favourite candidate Is Noske rather than von Lettow.    A Government crisis is almost inevitable on the question of the Peace Terms.   Two alternatives are being disoussed - a coalition of the Majority Socialists and Independents, or a Government of ths Independent Socialists exclusively.    The Majority Socialist want to get the best possible terms at the peaoe Conference, while the Independents are in favour of signing the Treaty at any cost, and trusting to the &quot;world revolution&quot; to abrogate it.    The result of the referendum is still doubtful but it is believed that the people are more or less evenly I divided on the question of signing the Treaty as it stands, IFollowing a report that a ftepublio of the Rhine had bei ,  proclaimed in Coblenz on May 27th, a general strike broke eg in Cologne and there was a large demonstration.Evidence is aooumulating that the German Government directed the Munich revolution through agents provocateurs.,
The ,fRote Fanno&quot; seems to have been under Government control, and an organisation called &quot;Vereinlgung zu Bekampfung dee Bolshevisms&quot;, an espionage Association oovering the whole of Germany, had exact information on every phase of the Munich riBing.   &quot;This Association is headed by Prussian Officers and works in close connection with the Government,It is reported that Leo Winz, working directly under Brookdorff^Rantzau. is getting Into touch with the leaders of the various Russian factions to work for his scheme of a German-Russian alliance.The metal workers of Dusaeldorf came out on strikewhile the Military Authorities were negotiating between thetwo Parties.   Ten of the strike leaders have been arrested,and others have been sent across the frontier into Germany,furnished with one day&apos;s ration.The &quot;Vbssisohe Zeitung&quot; reports from Dusseldorf that on the night of the 25th May an armed revolt was prepared in Dusseldorf, Duisberg, Mulheim, and other Rheinische-Westphaliun towns.   This aimed at the overthrow of theexisting Government and the proclamation of a soviet republic; the plan, however, was foiled by timely military intervention.There was a serious outbreak in ^lisenaoh on the-19th, resulting in the ilitreotment of officials and the liberation of convicts.   It was put down by the Militaryafter two days.Noske appears to be dissolving the Workmen*s and Soldiers&apos; Councils, gradually as Military Units are broken up or their strength falls below three hundred,   The Soviets attached to such Units are to be dissolved and replaced/
,.     replaced by Trustees (Vertrauensleute).   They are not allowed&apos;to publish special newspapers.   The Workers&apos; and ,    Soldiers&apos; Counoils which met in Berlin adopted a neutral ...  attitude as regards the signing of the peaoe Treaty.I, The prompt, measures taken by the Allies for dealing with the Tramway Strike in Cologne made a profound impressi on the Germans, who appear to approve of the British manner *      of dealing with Labour troubles.The only addition to be mads to the special report on Hungary, issued last Saturday isjthat Huysmans has stated in a letter that the Communists of Hungary are complaining that the Allied! Missions are compromising themselves in the counter-revolutionary movement.With true Hebrew cunning, the Communist Government is proposing to tender confiscated jewels in part payment of the Indemnity, in the hope that the Allies may either compromise&apos;themselves/, by receiving stolen property, or reject the offer, which they think will then relieve the ; &apos;. ;    Communists .of any -further, payment..For the past two days telephonic communication with Buda-Pesth has been interrupted. Crowds of refugees are crossing the frontier,.bringing stories of counter-revolutibeing imminent, .A wireless message from Buda- Pesth reports that all - &quot;hostages have been released,      ,.   .italy the Government, is sported to be weak, and to be unlikely to survive long after peace is signed.   Nitti, formerly Minister for the Treasury, is likely to succeed Jonnino; he is pro-American and is thought to be in a    &apos;position/Si
(Foreign.)position to obtain Ainerioan help for Italy.The feeling against England and France is by no means decreasing.   It is more pronounced against the French, but England is acoused of ousting&apos;Italy from the East, and the Italians feel justified in intriguing against her in Egypt and the Balkans as a reprisal.   It is thought that an ; alliance between Italy and Germany is not beyond the range of probability, and if Germany were to recover and again become a power, Italy would not hositu,te to rejoin the Alliance.   Prince Von Bttlow is said to be returning to &apos; Borne as soon as he is permitted. .The Italians are watching conditions in the Balkans very closely and are reported to be bent upon making secret alliances with either Iioumania or Bulgaria against Jugo-0Slavia.There is no immediate danger of Bolshevism\    the majority of Italians are afraid of it, and will approve repressive measures.   Nevertheless, serious labour troubles, developing into riots, are probable, as the food shortage is aoute.    These riots are unlikely to be anti-monarchical or Bolshevik.There is a report, which in one quarter is described as positive evidence, that the American Y.M.C.A. in Italy is   ; engaged in propaganda and espionage, that they preaoh dis-oontent to the sailors and advocate strikes for higher wages among the workmen.    The report is given for what it is worth, but it seems far more likely.that the indiscretions of a few irresponsible enployees of the Y.M.CA. have given rise to the report.       vMessrs. Ramsay Macdcnald and R. Buxton have left Rome for Milan, where they are to meet Longuet, to persuade the Italian Socialists to reconsider thoir decision to abandon the/
the 2nd International in favour of the Moscow International.^ RUSSIA.According to a report from Helsingfors, Lenin has declared a state of siege in Petrograd, and the inhabitants are fleeing en maBse to the Finnish frontier, taking their ohonoe of being allowed to cross it.    The Soviet Government is seriously thinking of removing to the Ukraine if Petrograe i3 oocupied.    The food question, in Petrograd is going from bad to worse.    All grain has been requisitioned, and only 36 lbs. a head per month is the ration left for the peasants. Knowing that this was going to happen, the peasants have determined to sow no more than what is actually wanted for their own immediate requirements.The mortality is such that it is now necessary to keep a waiting list for burials.    Coffins are practically unobtainable at 1,600 roubles, apd the people are being buried in rags.The ration of the Red Army soldier is l&apos;  lbs. of bread and half a herring a day, and he Is selling his ammunition and uniform for food.    A Moscow Bolshevik journal admits that the feeding and hygiene of the Red Army are in a very bad state .r&apos; - - , v.- ;:The Bible is now prohibited in Bolshevik prisons as a counter-revolutionary book.In the Bolshevik wireless it. i3 announced that Petrograci will not.be abandoned.The Karelian Front is quiet, but in the South the 8th Red Army seems to nave been wiped out, and insurrections are taking plaoe as the remnant retreats Northwards.The Bolsheviks admit an anti-Bolshevik rising in the Ukraine.if)-   On the East Front Koltchak&apos;s troops have reaohed the right bank of the Viatka.    Koltohak claimB that he isrestoring/
restoring order behind him.    On&apos; the other hand,, aooording to General Romanoffskyf at vladivostock the situation on the Volga is serious, sinoe the Bolsheviks are bringing up gun boats through the Itoriinsk Canal, and until the Siberian Army oooupies both banks of the Volga, one must not be too sanguine.There are dissensions among the leading Bolsheviks. &quot;Totiitoherine has fallen out with Zinovieff, and Trotsky is aoousing Lenin of weakness and disloyalty.    Lenin and Tohitoherine favour an understanding with the Allies: Trotsky and   Zinovieff are forrtsistanoe to the end.    With the fall of Bolshevism, pogroms of the Jews are not r unlikely.     In the smaller towns even now anti-Bolshevik organisations are being formed to carry out acts of terrorism against Jewish Communists,    Admiral Koltohak made an announcement to. the Jews at Ufa, East of the River Volga, that he would never allow the persecution of Jews.On May 23rd Jewish pogroms are reported to have broken out in Petrograd, and there was rioting in the streets after these were suppressed.    Peasant insurrections are universal^particularly in the regions nearest to Koltohak&apos;s advance.   Peasants are killing their steak for fear of confiscation by the Red Army, and only 20$ of the normal cultivated land is likely to be planted.    Terrorism is active against both the Left and the Right Sooial Revolutionaries.The religious movement is reported to be growing very fast;   it is a reaction against the Bolshevik atheism and has nothing political about it..Aocording to a wireless message of. ifay 31s^* emanating from Moaoow, the Bolsheviks have repudiated Communism in land.     This is of course due to the opposition of the peasants/
(Foreign)

peasants, which now menaces the whole Soviet system. The President of the Soviet Committee in Kalinin is elaborating a new land programme, based on the recognition of private ownership of land.

POLAND

A Moscow wireless telegram dated the 29th May states that Roumania and Poland have come to an agreement regarding Galicia, and that the Poles have already begun their advance into that country.

Jewish pogroms by General Haller&apos;s troops are reported from Czenstochow, and Sosnowice. The danger of alienating Jewish opinion in Allied countries if the Poles are not restrained is serious.

FINLAND.

According to the Esthonian representative in Berlin, the Esthonian Government will not make common cause with the Bolsheviks. The Social Democrats are really in line with the Russian Mensheviks, and the Labour Party may be looked upon as a Radical Democratic Party.

General Marinerheim&apos;s position is steadily growing stronger and it is generally recognised that his loyalty to the Entente cause has extricated the country from a very difficult position.

Norway.

The high rate Of wages, to which the present state of peace in Labour circles is due, cannot continue. No-one can afford to pay nearly a pound a day for unskilled labour. only necessary work is being done, and repairs are being neglected or postponed. Sooner or later there must be serious unemployment and a crisis.

Mr. Vidne
Mr. Vldnes, formerly Editor of the &quot;Socialdemokraten&quot;, has published an artiole protesting against the Bolshevik tendencies of the Socialist National Party.    The Socialist organs refused,to publish the artiole. -..- The -Norwegian Minister for Defenoe has announoed that he will, confer with the Left and Eight on reinforoing the garrison at Christiaiiia as a safe-guard against future trouble The proposal was strongly opposed by the Socialists.SWEDEN. ^ ...    ., ,..,;,:./;,..,,,,,-. v,,r,Expressing his views on the-peaoe. Terms, Air. Bran ting .&apos; -       . V&quot;.stated that, in his opinion,;.it was most important t^nt the question of compenssation should be settled in a spirit of conciliation.   as regards the restoration of France, he considered that Eisner&apos;s suggestion as^ to a voluntary corps of German workers for this purpose was the most Satisfactory, as this, would be an act of chivalry which, he was convinced, would be appreciated, in France. - :^Branting&apos;s. determined opposition to Bolshevism, makes people almost forget til at he is a Socialist.   The Swedish press realise that Branting&apos;iS a great national asset and are surrounding him with, a sort of hero worship.   He could probably be Prime Minister if he wished.Bolshevism has- not made great progress in the South of Sweden yet, but under the active exertions of the Women&apos;s Movement it is rapidly.spreaoing.-DENMARKTohitoherine has been notified from Denmark that Bolshevism is receiving feeble support.   He has ordered that some of his agents, inoluding two Americans, are to be paid off, &quot; ^ ,
SjPtfKThe extremists are very angry with the Government at the continuance of the prohibition of political meetings. On May 18th they passed a Resolution to blook the passing of any laws until the Constitutional Guarantees are restored. The Government i3 disturbed at this Resolution, for, in view of the numerous strikes and tho riots in Andaluaia, it isconsidered unsafe to rootore the Guarantees. r)Steps/, 1    (Foreign)The strike of dook labourers in Copenhagen lasted from! the 8th May.until the 15th May.   It began without hotioe being given, arid the Federated Trades Unions are threatening to expel the offending Union,   The strike is significant, as showing the growth of the Syndicalist section which could call astrike against the wishes of the Trades Union leaders,The Government is taking really active steps against the Bolsheviks, and it is rumoured that the &quot;Roomsoh Catholieke Aotie&quot;, recently established at The Hague as an anti-Bolshevil society, is subsidised by the Government, who have thus mobilised the Jesuits on their side.   The State Detective Force has been strongly reinforoed since the new Government has been in power.From an intercepted, letter, it appears that the revolutionary party io receiving large quantities of jewellery, which wea plundered during the riots in Germany.   These were handed over to Wijnkoop, the revolutionary leader., ,The Burgerwaoht is, of oourse, oondemned by the Labour Party, who huve drawn up a black list of shopkeepers and artisans, in order to boycott them.   As a counter-measure, the Contractor of Public Works has deoided[ to boycott labourers who are acting qgainet the Burgerwaoht.
Steps are being taken to alleviate the wheat shortage. The Socialists and Republicans appear to be winning the Elections.1     &apos;i.....mmA party of Central Asian Turki has arrived in the Kansu Province, bringing ten or fifteen gold bars, ranging from ten to fifteen Chinese ounces in weight.  The bars are stamped &quot;A.O.H.M. 3.&quot;   It is suggested locally that this is in connection with Bolshevik propaganda.mmA serious rising has occurred in South Kurdistan on ,;,  the Worth West Border.   The Gendarmerie have been defeated, wires have been out, and it is feared that British Officers and troops have been taken prisoners.   It is attributed to the intrigues of the Turkish Committee of Union and Progress.mm &apos; , ,Aooording to an American report, the Japanese are not intriguing with the Bolshevists,, and are inclined rather towards the Russians of the,old rogime. ,The German plan for re-modelling the Japanese Army is to send a Cadet Battalion as a Unit to show the Japanese the German system of organisation.   Tne Battalion will then be broken up arid distributed throughout the Japanese Army for instructional purposes.   Company-Officers are to reoeive 2,000 and Field Officers 3,000 marks monthly, and every Officer has a Ufe Insurance Policy for 15,000 -narks.   They are to prooeed to Finland, and thence through America to Japan, vTURKEYAccording to an Amerioan report, there is great tension in Constantinople, but no serious trouble is expeoted while the Allied troops and warships are at hand,A/
A new society is to be formed by the Young.Turks, to bedirected against the Allies in the Ottoman Empire.   This wilI take the place of the &quot;Ligue pour la defense des Droita des Ottomans&quot;,EGYPT.Everything.1s quiet in Egypt at the moment. The Nationalists are distributing leaflets violently abusing the members of the new Cabinet, who, by taking office, have acoepted the Protectorate.   &quot;Too low to be trodden on&quot;, and &quot;malignant souls, the devil48 off-spring&quot; are the least offensive of the terms applied to them.An Egyptian Sooialist Party, which is to be the Egyptian I -..  Section of the International Workers Union, is said by &quot;he Populaire&quot; to be projeoted in Paris.   Its Headquarters are not yet known.The Egyptian Delegation in Paris is expeoting valuable assistance from Cachih; Longuet has also expressed his sympathy.A-Syrian Mussulman named Samneh ia believed to be proceeding shortly to Odessa to stir up the BolBheviks,   His soheme is to bring about a general rising of the Moslem world against England, and he has approached two French Deputies to ascertain the attitude of the Frenoh Government if suoh a movement took place, urging that the Frenoh should do nothing to assist in putting it down. &apos;India.       . r^ ,     f.Since his return from Mandalay, Tilak has been working ,.to become head of all the Indian extremists, and it seems likely that he will suooeed.. ...The cry for a Mixed Commission of Enquiry to investigate the onuses of the reoent rioting is being kept alive.
The publication, of the- &quot;Bombay ^Chroniole-^ has been suspended, pending aobOptanoe of the conditions imposed by the Government, viz., to have all important--matter^censored day by day.According to information from Moscow, Trotsky has made an agreement with Barokatol, a member of the Indian National Congress, that the revolutionary movement in India shall begin in Bengal.Indian propaganda is to be started throughout Central Asia,   The Bolsheviks have gained a footing in the Merv Oasis, in Turklstan, which will enable them to carry out propaganda in Northern Persia, Turkestan, and Afghanistan,SOUTH AFRICA.according to the writer of a private letter during the recent Municipal strike in Johannesburg, the Strike Committee ran the Municipal &quot;services as a sort of Soviet.The merchants and largo store-keepers have come badly out of the Commission on Profiteering.   The net profits of many firms were trebled during the War, and the taxes were &quot;so light that they scarcely, felt them.A correspondent thinks that the native question is soon going to become serious.    Even the Mission natives are becoming less law-abiding.A Bill has been drafted whioh will strengthen the hands of the Government in.dealing with Bolshevism in South \frioa and incendiary propaganda among the. -natives. ,&apos;. Two men have been heavily fined in Cape Town for publishing seditious literaturefor). the natives, and one of the Bolshevik newspapers is to be prosecuted.AUSTRALIA..The strike in Sydney continues ond that at Melbourne is spreading.    Huge quantities of food stuffs are held up/
up at the wharves.    Many of the strikers in Sydney wish to return to work pending arbitration, but the Government has    % failed to give them the neoessary protection.    The trouble is extending to Queensland and Victoria,iiJli,There is political unrest throughout New Zealand, and a General Bleotion ia anticipated before the end of the year. There are rumours of the formation of a new politioal party with more advanced views.    The miners have been restless for Borne time and supplies of ooal are consequently short.     The general oomplaint is that the Government has failed to grapple with the difficult problems that have arisen sinoe the Armistioe.CANADA.The Government has refused to negotiate with the strikers until sympathetio strikes oease.    They recognise that the &quot;One Big Union&quot; movement moans the Dictatorship of Labour, So far, the railwaymen are sound, but there are strong indications of a general strike in Vancouver within the next few days, and if this happens, the whole of Western Canada may be involved.    At present there is no indication of an early settlement.UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.It has been ascertained that Ludwig Martens, the leader of the Bolsheviks in amerioa, voluntarily registered himself as a German when in this country. A photograph of the Register is being supplied to the Amerioan Embassy tor transmission to the sState Department.SOUTH AMERICA (Argentine)The Authorities have deoided to suppress the Bolsheviki newspaper,
newspaper &quot;The Red Flag&quot;.In spite of the labour unrest arid the feebleness of the Government, there is a feeling of oonfidenoe in the future of the country on account of its eoonomio wealth.    The President is conciliatory to the working man, and it is thought that his influence was a decisive factor when a Bolshevik Revolution seemed to be threatening.The strike movement in Buenos Aires is growing.Peru is sufferl?\g from an epidemic of strikes,    Lima and Callao are under Martial Law, and the number of casualti is over fifty.    On the 29th May the strikers blew up a small railway bridge.    Some time must elapse before con-ditions are normal. . &apos;B.H.T.

</content>
</cab>
