<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 89-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Goyernment.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  June, 1919.SECRET, G.T. 7420.THE LABOUR SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending 4th June, 1919.summary.   .Part I: The Demand for Control.Part II: Demobilisation and Resettlement: General Resettlement.Part HI: Press Comments: (1) Labour and Socialist Press. (A) Foreign Affairs : Russia, Hungary, President Wilson, Peace Proposals. (B) Home Affairs: Parliamentary Labour Party; Trade Union Congress and Triple Alliance; Triple Alliance and Parliament; Trade Unionism; Coal Mines Commission; Restoration Bill.(2) The Press on Demobilisation and Resettlement.Part IV : General Topics and District Reports.(1) General. Industrial Council; Coal Commission; Coal Mines; Textile Workers; Engineers; Police ; Bakers; Building Trade; Government Workers ; Municipal Workers; Bank Clerks ; County Court Clerks; Teachers ; Projected Amalgamations ; Conscription, &amp;c.; Income Tax.; 44-Hour Week ; Agricultural Wages Board ; Restoration Bill; Rail-way Shareholders ; International Labour Legislation.(2) District Reports.Part V: Disputes.(a) Involving a Stoppage of Work.(b) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work.Part I. The Demand for Control.This part of the Weekly Report during the last two weeks has dealt with the question of industrial power, first especially with regard to its growing dimensions among labour organisations, and secondly as regards the opportunities which the present developing situation may be expected to present for its employment. It may be worth while this week to make some observations of a more general nature.In the first place it cannot too strongly be pointed out that a rapid change is in fact coming over the whole face of industrial organisation, a change, that is to say, which bids fair so to alter the industrial world that the whole set of values hitherto in use may have to be swept away and replaced by something quite different. Economists have for a long time been pointing out the waning truth of the popular assumptions with regard to competi-tion and the existence of a competitive system as regards industrial enterprises, and the vReport of the Committee on Trusts which has just been issued gives point to their allegation. They find that there is &quot; at the present time in every important branch of industry in the United Kingdom an increasing tendency to the formation of Trade Associations and Combinations having for their purpose the restriction of competition and control of prices. Many of the organisations which have been brought to our notice have been created in the last few years, and by far the greater part of them appear to have come into existence since the end of the nineteenth century.&quot; A list of 35 such associations is then given, covering the iron and steel trades alone.  Twenty-five of these together cover 323 firms.(C 1800)   150  6/19 E&amp;SA
Such is the state of affairs on the employers&apos; side; and mutatis mutandis it may be said that there is a rapid movement in the same direction on the work peoples&apos; part. It is not perhaps generally realised that during the last few months there has been roughly an average of one important amalgamation every fortnight; federation too, is advancing equally rapidly, as are also working arrangements and agreements, with the same results as occur on the employers&apos; side, namely, the elimination of competition, or at any rate its transformation into something totally different from what it has meant hitherto.The first consequence of this has been the rapid growth of industrial power already referred to, until it now may be said to dominate the situation and threaten by its superior weight to upset the balance altogether. Since last week there has been another most striking example of the power of combination in the events connected with the threatened police strike. Here again, the history of the Coal Commission and of the Railway Negotia-tions was repeated with far from reassuring accuracy. It is stated, it is true, that the Government has stood firm and refused to recognise the Police Union, and this may be so in the technical sense ; but the fact remains that its whole action in the matter has amounted to a most pointed actual, if not technical, recognition of it. It cannot be regarded as an accident and certainly is not by those interested outside that demands for better conditions were met at the eleventh hour before a possible strike, and before a Committee appointed to go into this and allied matters had been able to report.But what then is the solution to this problem ? Is there any other solution under present conditions than to give way before the concentration of industrial or social power, and to give way as little and as gradually as possible ? It would appear that there is not; the situation is. fundamentally ill-balanced, and nothing but a complete change, either voluntary or involuntary, will suffice. It is here that the question of &quot;. control &quot; emerges, as presenting in some form or other what appears to be the only adequate solution. The only question is what form and what amount of control, for control is a very vague term. The minimum amount would appear to be denned by the consideration that it must be sufficient to develop such a sense of responsibility as will enable labour representatives when considering demands to be put forward to appreciate their possible results not only from the individual workman&apos;s point of view in the short period, but from the wider point of view of the general welfare, which is the individual^ point of view in the long run. It is clear, at once, that the extent of control envisaged, immediately at any rate, in the Whitley Report alone is below this minimum. The situation has developed since the Whitley Report was written. The Report provides machinery for enabling the workman to have some control over the conditions under which he shall work ; that is to say, given that so much has to be expended on him in the aggregate, he is to have some control in how it is to be expended; but in the matter of how much is to be allotted to him, the position is left vague, and this leaves in the mind&apos; the assumption that things will in this sphere remain more or less as they are for the moment, though possibly subject to a gradual transformation. But it is just this question of&quot; how much &quot; on which the big organisations are concentrating all their industrial power at the present time, and which they are forcing into the foreground as a matter of immediate concern ; and this opens up a vast area of consideration which, is left untouched at any rate by the more precise Whitley recom-mendations. It is for this reason that the Unions most conscious of their industrial powers, i.e., the miners, the railwaymen and the engineers, together with the advocates of State or Guild Socialism, have exhibited little sympathy with the Whitley Report. Yet even a minimum necessary in this sphere, without going so far as any of these recommend, would involve a transformation which, may be likened to the transformation from secret to open diplomacy, and involves similar difficulties to those encountered in that process. An absolute minimum necessary in this respect, that is to say, would appear to be throughout the whole field of industry the throwing open to the examination of workpeople or their representatives all the commercial and financial processes of business, and incidentally in the words of the Report on Trusts already quoted, the institution of &quot; machinery for the investigation of the operation of monopolies, trusts, and combines.&quot; If this is to be of any service, it must be done thoroughly, because the onus of proof in this matter, whether he likes it or not, lies on the employers&apos; side that nothing is being hidden for the purpose of cheating the workman of what he might get, if. he only knew about it. But it is doubtful if even this is not tqo low a minimum in the present situation, drastic and even impossible as such a step is regarded as probably by the majority of employers. Evidence is accumulating which goes to show that inflated industrial power coupled with lack of responsibility for any results of action taken are already having adverse effects on production. In the absence of&apos; any definite responsibility it is the formula used at the present time by representatives of labour that shorter hours with unaltered earnings and simple time-rates without any appeal to extra exertion in the way of bonuses do not have an adverse effect on output,
but the fact must be faced that, workpeople being after all human, this is simply not true. But it is difficult to see how such an unpleasant and unpopular fact can be adequately driven home by demonstration alone, and it may be the wiser and in the long run the only stable solution of the difficulty to concede something to the demands made by Labour itself along another line, that of control, and leave the truth to demonstrate itself by the visible and obvious working of cause and effect. As has already been pointed out, the situation to-day is fundamentally ill-balanced. Certain bodies of organised workpeople are, in fact, in a position to force certain results ; it is only a question whether they shall or shall not be exempted from responsibility for the consequences both before and after the fact. If they are not, it would appear that the gain will be immeasurable in steadying not only their aggressive action before, but also their resentment after, even though such a course is one of very great difficulty, OAving to the commercial considerations involved, to which labour is not accustomed. But the only logical alternative to this course is boldly to deny the assumption that these labour organisations are as strong as they appear to be, and prepare to shatter them in actual conflict. This, it may be remarked, would appear to be the attitude which, has been adopted by many employers, and it is one which must sooner &apos; or later lead to a struggle which can only be disastrous, whatever its upshot.Part II.-Demobilisation and Resettlement. General Resettlement.Recent events, notably the unfortunate incidents attending the demonstration in London of the Discharged Sailors&apos; and Soldiers&apos; Federation, have served to concentrate attention upon the extent of unemployment. The comments of the press, as a whole, show a tendency to ignore some of the broader aspects of the present position. A brief review of the general situation may therefore not be inopportune.Changes in unemployment can no longer be tested completely by statistics of the out-of-work donation, for the reduced scale under which the donation is payable to civilians, and the careful revision of policies now in progress, must be regarded as responsible in part for the decline during May in the number of policies on which payment was being made a decline which has brought the number down from about 1,093,000 to a little over 945,000.* But when allowance for these factors has been made, it is estimated that at least a quarter of the reduction can safely be attributed to a genuine improvement in the industrial situation. Behind this there lie s the cardinal fact that the great majority of those demobilised from the Forces or thrown out of civil employment have, within six months of the cessation of hostilities, been re absorbed into civil life. In the case of ex-members of the Forces the proportion reabsorbed is 82 per cent.; in the case of civilian workers it is a little lower 72 per cent. The unemployed balance, serious as it is, represents therefore only a fifth of the men demobilised, and three-tenths of the displaced civilian workers.Evidence from various quarters goes to confirm the belief that, for the present at all events, unemployment is beginning to ebb. The cotton trade of the North-Western division is showing considerable improvement, following on the withdrawal of war restrictions. The position is still sufficiently serious; of the men unemployed in the middle of May in this division 16 per cent, were cotton workers, and of the women over 40 per cent. But between the 9th and the 16th May the number of women completely unemployed is estimated to have declined by about a third, while a considerable decline in short time employment also took place. The Scottish jute industry and the manu-facture of paper, both of which were causing considerable anxiety, have shown signs of revival. To some extent this is also true of the lace industry of the Midlands. Mean-while housing and road-making schemes, and other municipal and public works, are coming gradually into operation, and bringing with them prospects of employment on a large scale in the building and engineering industries, in both of which unemployment is markedly diminishing. It may reasonably be hoped from this development work that will be found for the male general labourers who comprise from 14 per cent, to 19 per cent, of the unplaced men applying for work at the Employment Exchanges. In other less important directions reports are favourable.The improvement is reflected in frequently repeated complaints as to impediments in the development of industry which reach the Ministry of Labour from various parts of* Part time workers are included in each case.
the country. The disclosure of the Governments * financial plans and the withdrawal of many wartime restrictions have concentrated attention-on such factors as the general shortage of railway wagons and transport facilities, and the renewed suggestion that the further release of pivotal men is. necessary. The first complaint comes from all parts of the country. The second has been raised especially in the North-Western division, where it is stated that railway wagon builders and repairers, who have been discovered to be pivotal since the closing of the lists, are urgently needed. The view that pivotal men are needed is expressed also by employers in the hatting industry, which is doing unexpectedly well; and engineering firms, especially in the Yorkshire and East Midlands division, are badly in need of moulders of all types. The engineering industry is especially affected by the shortage of bar iron. The proportion of men in the engineering trades unplaced by the Employment Exchanges is high in every division except the North-Western, ranging from 8 per cent, of the men&apos;s live register in the South Midlands and Eastern division to 31 per cent, in the West Midlands division, where a large number of women engaged in engineering trades are also unemployed.The returns from nearly all divisions show that unemployment is high among men engaged on the conveyance of men or goods ; the proportion of such workers to the total number of unplaced men registered at the Exchanges varies from 14 per cent, in the West Midlands to 26 per cent, in the London and South-Eastern division. Probably the prominence of this class is in some degree significant; for in the main a general improve-ment in industry would appear latest in such occupations as these. Finally, in view of the outcry over the lack of domestic servants, it may be noted that in the Northern, Wales, Yorkshire and East Midlands, and South-Western divisions, women registered for domestic service form 51 per cent., 46 per cent., 42 per cent, and 33 per cent, of those unplaced, while in the other divisions the proportion varies from 14 per cent, to 27 per cent.Part III. Press Comments.(1) Labour and Socialist Press. (A)-Foreign Affairs.Russia.English and Allied policy towards Russia assumes a more prominent place in the discussions in the papers reviewed this week than does the Peace Conference. The trust-worthiness of the news which appears in the ordinary daily press about the Russian situation is doubted. Mr. F. W. Jowett in the &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; says : &quot; It is the * practice of the Foreign Office to give currency to any lie which seems to justify inter-vention on the side of property and privilege in Russia but to ignore or excuse cruelty and oppression on the other side.&quot; Mr. Norman Angell in the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; mairl-tains that Bolshevik atrocities, if there are any, cannot be the cause of intervention; because, he says, they were never considered a cause for intervention under the Czarist Government, and no atrocities are alleged against the Hungarian Soviet regime against, which, nevertheless, a war is being waged. Mr. Ramsay Macdonald in &apos;* Forward &quot; suggests that Allied policy is responsible for the chaos in Russia, and the &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; asserts that in Russia we are starving women and children by tens of thousands.. We are at war with Russia, says Mr. Ramsay Macdonald in &quot; Forward,&quot; because Russia is Social Democracy. Mr. Philip Snowden in &quot; Labour Leader &quot; doubts whether Kolchak will ever permit any truly representative assembly to meet or to assume government in Russia, and the &quot; New Statesman &quot; asserts that because Kolchak focusses in his movement all that is reactionary in Russia he is really Lenin&apos;s greatest ally. &quot; If there had been no Kolchak there would have been no Bolshevist Government in Russia to-day.&quot; Mr. Norman Angell in the &quot;Labour Leader&quot; points out that the result of our fight with Bolshevism is, in his opinion, an alliance with the monarchical, militarist and counter-revolutionary forces in Russia. Mr. Norman Angell may be said to express the general opinion of the I.L.P. papers (and of the more extreme &quot; Call &quot; and the &quot; Workers&apos; Dread-nought &quot;) when he says &quot; If British workers permit this destruction of Russia&apos;s,experiment in Industrial Democracy, and this alliance with Russian reaction, then they will have betrayed democracy.&quot; Mr. Hyndman in &quot; Justice &quot; regrets that British soldiers should have been sent to Russia to defeat the Bolsheviks ; he maintains that the time for inter-vention was in autumn 1917 or early in 1918, when intervention could have been managed without the despatch of a single British soldier.
6 3Hungary.Mr. F. W. Jowett in the &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; compares the policy of the Allies to Hungary with their policy to Russia, and the &quot; Nation &quot; asserts that the administration of Bela Kun maintains exemplary order and has organised much productive work. The attitude of the I.L.P. and other more advanced papers towards Hungary would seem to be identical with their attitude towards Russia ; but much less is said about Hungary, perhaps because England is less directly concerned and the news and information with regard to Hungary is much less voluminous.*President Wilson.Mr. Ramsay Macdonald in &quot; Forward &quot; expresses his pity for President Wilson, whom he believes to have come to Europe with good intentions. Mr. Philip Snowden in the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; continues his attack on him ; he regards the recent Presidential Message to Congress as &quot; another illustration of his rhetorical powers.&quot; President Wilson has supplied Congress, he says, with a paraphrase of the &quot; seductive promises &quot; of Mr. Lloyd George and other English statesmen. Mr. Snowden advises his readers to write to President Wilson and tell him what they think of the proposed Peace Treaty ; while Mr. Joseph King tin the &quot;Bradford Pioneer&quot; gives a sample letter of this kind, which he himself has addressed to the President. The &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; think that the resignation of some of the members of the American delegation &quot; will now dispel from the minds of all intelligent persons the last traces of belief in the imaginary President Wilson who was supposed to be the Archangel of Peace and Democracy.&quot; Mr. Robert Blatchford in the &quot; Clarion &quot; says that he never regarded President Wilson&apos;s programme as practicable or desirable. He is glad that it has been modified, but he has never doubted the President^ good faith, and he thinks it grossly unfair to single him out for censure. &quot; Reasonable men will regret he tried to do too much.&quot;The Peace Proposals.(a) German Counter-proposals. The &quot; Nation &quot; thinks that the counter-proposals of the Germans have been drafted with real statesmanship. The &quot; New Statesman &quot; thinks that they are as a whole more in accord with modern ideas of international right and the prospects of a stable peace than is the proposed treaty. The &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought &quot; thinks that Count Brockdorff-Rantzau has put the standpoint of International Labour more satisfactorily than has the Committee of Action of the Permanent Commission of the Second International in its manifesto.(b) Peace Manifestos. The &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; criticises Messrs. Ramsay Macdonald and Arthur Henderson for the statements they made at Amsterdam, when it thinks they should have known what the character of the Peace Proposals was likely to be. It complains that even now they and the Labour Party are deaf to German appeals. Mr. Ramsay Macdonald refers to the Oxford manifesto and describes its signatories as &quot; the innocent misleaders of opinion during the war and the ineffective protestors after it.&quot; The &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; publishes a manifesto from &quot; L&apos;Humanite &quot; over the signature Xinoviev which purports to be the opinion of the Third (Moscow) International. &quot;The Peace Terms strike a blow-at the international proletariat; the only deliverance for the oppressed is through the world revolution of the proletariat.&quot;(c) General. Mr. Norman Angell, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; gives his reasons why Labour should object to the Peace proposals. They will result, he says, in great military establishments, the effort to maintain which will mean in each state, the bringing to power of anti-democratic forces; this is incompatible with the development of industrial democracy. The price of the Peace therefore includes, in his opinion, the abandonment of Socialism and the failure of the fight for a more complete democracy. Mr. Arthur Henderson, at Woolwich, on the 4th May, outlined his position towards the Peace proposals. They were based, he said, on the principles which had caused the war, and were a breach of the armistice conditions, which was based upon President Wilson&apos;s fourteen points. Organised labour could accept no responsibilityv for them. (This remark is repeated by Mr. Ramsay Macdonald in &quot; Forward.&quot;) The workers must organise for their own deliverance, and must strengthen the international organisation of the democratic movement. The &quot; British Citizen &quot; says that the Peace Terms, though far from ideal, are tolerable and sane.
o(B)-Home Affairs.Parliamentary Labour Party.Mr. Philip Snowden, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; expressed his opinion that in the debate on the Second Reading of the Finance Bill, the Labour Party came off second best. &quot; Justice &quot; comments adversely on the absenteeism of the Labour members of Parliament, and says that the Labour Group is playing directly into the hands of the &quot; direct actionists.&quot; The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; (London Letter) says that the Labour Party has disappointed its supporters : that its action henceforward must be quick : that on matters of grave International importance it is inactive. But Mr. Philip Snowden, the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; (London Letter) and the Merthyr &quot; Pioneer,&quot; note with satisfaction the &quot; growing spirit of unrest in the left wing of the Party,&quot; and congratulate, in particular, Mr. Lunn and Mr. Hartshorn.Trade Union Congress and the Triple Alliance.The &quot; Nation &quot; says that the decision of the Parliamentary Committee of the Trade Union Congress not to call a special national conference will profoundly disappoint all who are looking to labour to save the country. &quot; Call&quot; criticises the Parliamentary Committee for having throughout the movement stood in the way ; it objects to the claim which it says the committee makes, to be Labour. It concludes by saying that the spirit of Democracy can only live in small groups and that the vital problem before Labour is to break up political and industrial democracy into its elements. The &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; asks whether the Triple Alliance is to accept this &quot; humiliating defeat&quot; or to use its overwhelming industrial power.The Triple Alliance and Parliament.Mr. Robert Williams is reported to have said at Merthyr Tydvil (in the Merthyr &quot; Pioneer &quot;) that he was prepared to take direct action to rid the country of conscription. The Merthyr &quot; Pioneer &quot; says that Parliament has failed because the workers have never taken their politics seriously enough, and does not think the conclusion a happy one, that industrial action alone can be relied upon to advance the cause of the workers. &quot; Rob Roy &quot; in &quot; Forward &quot; comments upon a statement of Mr. Robert Williams (that parlia-mentary government has ceased to be representative and that we must prepare for a Soviet government, analogous to the Russian institution) and says that, though he too, did not like the result of the last election, he is not so foolish as to say that representative government has thereby ceased. Mr. W. A. Appleton in the &quot; Democrat&quot; says that nothing can be more dangerous than an attempt to govern not only the internal, but also the external affairs of a nation by partisan industrial groups.Trade Unionism.The &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; applauds the decision of the Yorkshire Miners&apos; Association to expel from their membership Mr. J. Walton, M.P., and says that this decision means that the workers are beginning to rise up against the bureaucrats who have sold them, and that the rank and file are beginning to manage their own affairs. &quot; Justice &quot; has a sympathetic article on the Trade Union official. In this article, Mr. F. H. Edwards quotes the advice of a trade union secretary to a local organiser : &quot; compromise or you will loose your members.&quot; He calls for a sense of proportion in the criticism of trade union officials. In this connection it may be noted that an article in last week&apos;s &quot;Railway Review&quot; which was an explanation of the aims and workings of Trade Unionism made the same appeal, and did not make any reference at all to industrial action for political purposes. The &quot; Call&quot; quotes from the seventy-ninth quarterly report of the General Federation of Trade Unions a passage which says that concern has been caused by the tendency on the part of inexperienced trade unions to stampede executives, and that the Management Committee of the Federation are considering the advisability of an alteration of rules to strengthen the hands of executives against their less responsible members, and against those hostile to Trade Unionism &quot; who seek to fritter its resources by promoting ill-considered strikes.&quot;Coal Mines Commission. K&apos;&apos;Tne &quot;: Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; criticises the provisions of the Bill for Nationalisation of the Mines, which was presented in evidence to the Coal Mines Commission by Mr. W. H. Slesser (Standing Counsel to the M.FvG.B.), as not being democratic and as being contrary to the Soviet method. It was astonished at the proposal contained in the Bill for com-pensation for the proprietors of the coal mines.
Part IV. General Topics and District Reports.(1) General.The Provisional Joint Committee of the Industrial Council.The Provisional Joint Committee of the Industrial Council held a further meeting on the 29th May. The Minister communicated to them the principal clauses of the draft Bills for setting up a Commission to enquire into the fixing of minimum rates of wages. He explained that the Government did not consider that the Conference had a mandate to make recommendations affecting occupations which were not represented at the Conference, and that the scope of the Bill had accordingly been limited to industrial and agricultural occupations, and to that of shop assistants. The Committee asked a number of questions on points of detail, and requested that they might have time, to consider the terms of the Bills more carefully before expressing any definite opinions. Their general reception of the Bills appeared to be favourable, and it may be hoped that some definite agreement will be reached at the next meeting, which is provisionally arranged for the 13th June.Coal Commission.The Coal Commission held sittings on the 28th, 29th, and 30th May, and on the 3rd June. Mr. W. Straker (Secretary of ^the Northumberland Miners&apos; Association) gave evidence and submitted to a long cross-examination. Evidence was also heard from Mr. J. Winstone (President of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation), Mr. Joseph Shaw, K.C. (South Wales and Monmouthshire Coal Freighters&apos; Association), Sir Daniel Stevenson (Scottish Coal Exporters&apos; Association), Sir Keith Price, Sir John Mann, and Mr. W. Jenkinson (Ministry of Munitions), Mr. Edward Small wood (Chairman of the CoalRestoration of Pre-War Practices Bill.After the passing of the Bill, the &quot; New Statesman &quot; says that everything will depend on the wisdom with which the unions use the asset which the Bill places in their hands (namely, the legally enforceable claim to complete restoration). The representatives of both skilled and unskilled trade unions must, it says, come to an agreement together with regard to the changes which may be advisable, and present a common scheme to the employers.(2) The Press on Demobilisation and Resettlement.Demonstration of&apos;Ex-Service Men.The &quot;Daily Chronicle &quot;: (29th May) has no sympathy with the suggestion that the mass meeting of ex-service men in Hyde Park on the &apos;26th May, was inspired by agitators and Bolsheviks. It considers that the necessity for expediting plans for employment cannot be urged upon the authorities too often, &quot; for though private employers can do much, the onus does and will rest upon the Government.&quot;A different view is taken by the &quot; Spectator &quot; (31st May). It defends the Government which it claims is providing more work than any Government in this country has ever provided. It regards the disturbance in Parliament Square as a deliberate attempt &quot;by what is called Bolshevism, to set ex-service men at odds with the police, &apos;as representatives of the State authority, on the same lines as the attempt of the Triple Alliance to rope in the police.&quot;In the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; (29th May) Mr. Philip Snowden describes the demonstration as &quot; a painful commentary upon the pledges and promises given by the Government during the last five years.&quot;The &quot; Call&quot; considers &quot; the police attacks on the peaceful demonstration of discharged soldiers and sailors &quot; as an example &quot; of the ease with which one section of the working class can still be set to fight another.&quot; It regrets it cannot share the view of the general secretary of the police union that the fault lies with the Home Secretary and the Commissioner of Police. The members of the police union have some share in the mischief, and &quot; if fighting should become the rule, the police may come off second best.&quot;
Merchants&apos; Federation of Great Britain and member of the London Coal Committee) and Lord D&apos;Abernon. Evidence in respect of housing conditions was given by Mrs. Mary Hart of Wigan, Mrs. Andrews (Rhondda) and Mrs. Agnes Brown (Lanark). The Hon. IT. M. Fisher (New Zealand), Mr. Havelock Wilson, M.P., and Mr. William Cash gave evidence against nationalisation. Evidence was also given by Mr. George Rose (representing Coal Merchants and Factors), Mr. E. S. Williams and Mr. Percival M.uschamp (representing Colliery Managers), Sir John Maclaren, Mr. G. Henry Wright and Mr. W. F. Gardner (representing Chambers of Commerce), Mr. Joseph Shaw (Chairman of the Humber Coal Exporters and Shippers&apos; Association), Mr. Alfred Brooks (representing the London Waterside Manufacturers&apos; Association), Mr. F. N. Mills and Mr. A. S. Tallis (Mine Owners).Sir Auckland Geddes stated in the House of Commons on the 28th May that evidence would be taken on behalf of important consumers of coal before the Commission reported on the question of Nationalisation.The South Wales Siemen&apos;s Steel Association has decided to urge the Coal Commission to make no recommendations involving Government control in the production or distribu-tion of coal or coke in view of the necessity of cheap fuel for industry.Irish Goal Mines Commission.The first sitting of the Irish Coal Mines Commission was held on 30th May in Dublin. No evidence was taken.Goal Mines.The leading Colliery owners and representatives of the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain held a conference with Sir Richard Redmayne on the 28th May to discuss a claim for an increase in the amount payable for injury to workmen employed in coal mines. The mattter is still being negotiated.At a meeting of the Miners&apos; Federation Executive held on the 29th May, it was decided to urge at the Trades Union Congress that compensation pay should equal full pre-accident wage.Miners in South Wales are making a vigorous effort to &quot; squeeze out&quot; rival organisations, and to compel all colliery workers to join the Miners&apos; Federation. This campaign has already led to stoppages, because master hauliers and mechanics refused to transfer from the Master Hauliers&apos; Association and A.S.E. respectively to the Miners&apos; Federation; and the opinion has been expressed that many similar stoppages will take place, for the same reason, within the next few months. This campaign is, of course, part of a policy for gaining complete control of the mines. Without mechanics, mines are exposed to the danger of being flooded. If the mechanics remain at work when the miners strike, therefore, the owner is in a much stronger position to hold out.Textile Workers.The United Textile Workers&apos; Association at Manchester on the 30th May decided, that unless the employers meet their demand for a 461-hour week and a 30 per cent, advance in wages, they will strike on the 21st June.  This would probably affect over a quarter of a million employees.   A meeting between the employers and the men&apos;s leaders took place on the 4th instant, but no agreement was reached.Engineers.The Engineering Trade Unions have reached a provisional agreement with the Engineering and National Employers&apos; Federation on the subject of Shop Stewards and Works Committees. The composition of the Works Committees has been provided for by measures for the nomination and election of the members from the shop stewards by the whole of the workers in a shop.   The arrangement is subject to a ballot vote.The resolution passed by^ the Erith Shop Stewards against overtime while any member is in receipt of unemployment benefit continues to receive support from A.S.E. branches throughout the country. A.S.E. Shop Stewards in the Plymouth district are unanimously in favour of putting an end to overtime, piecework and the premium bonus system.
Police.The result of the ballot of the Police and Prison Officers&apos; Union, on the question of a strike to enforce the four demands enumerated in last week&apos;s report, was announced at a demonstration in Hyde Park on the 1st June. Out of 55,183 ballot papers, 48,863 were returned, and of these 44,539 favoured a strike. It was, however, announced that the strike would be postponed. The Irish police, on the advice of their Executive Council, followed the example of the English in deciding to defer action. Support for the police was promised by the Birmingham Trades and Labour Council, and other Labour bodies and Trade Unions. On the other hand, members of the Middle Class Union were urged to act as special police if necessary, but the Finchley Branch of the Federation of Dis-charged and Demobilised Sailors and Soldiers passed a strong resolution against the use of ex-service men as f&apos; blacklegs &quot; in case of a strike.Bakers.The Master Bakers and Confectioners passed a resolution on the 28th May &quot; that the removal of the Bread Control Order is urgently desired.&quot;Building Trade.At a meeting of Architects, Surveyors and Building Trade employers and operatives held on the 1st June, a constitution was drawn up for the Joint Consultative Board for establishing better conditions in the Building Trade.Government Workers.At the Annual Meeting of the United Government Workers&apos; Federation held on the 31st May, representatives were present from 20 Government Departments. Resolutions respecting wages, holidays, bonus, education and pensions were passed.Municipal Workers.The Poor Law Workers&apos; Trade Union is circularising Boards of Guardians, urging them not to recognise the decisions of the Conciliation Council for the Poor Law Service until its constitution has been officially recognised under the Whitley scheme.Bank Clerks.The Bank Officers&apos; Guild, at a meeting in London on the 29th May, passed a unanimous resolution requesting the Government to set up a Whitley Council.County Court Clerks.At the annual meeting on the 31st May of the County Courts (Clerks and Officers) Association, affiliated with the Civil Service Federation, it was decided to make represen-tations to the Government against the lowness of the pay of clerks and the restriction of the bonus.Teachers.The Scottish Men Teachers&apos; Association has issued circular letters to the members of the Educational Institute of Scotland urging them to oppose the principle of equal pay for men and women. A protest against this principle was also lodged by a meeting of the London Men&apos;Teachers on the 31st May.Projected Amalgamations.At a Conference representing all the Textile Unions in the British Isles (Wool, Cotton and other branches of the industry) it was decided to take steps towards amalgamation; and it was further proposed, when that was completed, to unite with the present Triple Alliance, and thus effect the formation of a Quadruple Alliance&apos;. It may be remarked, however, that Mr. Robert Williams has stated that he has no official knowledge of the latter proposal, and it may be doubted whether it would represent any gain in strength to the Triple Alliance. The textile trades have little in common with the trades in the Alliance, and, except in the Cotton Trade, are much less well organised.
With regard to the projected amalgamation of Engineering and Shipbuilding Unions proposed last year by the A.S.E., it is reported that as a result of a Conference at York (on the 28th and 29th May) of the Executives of fourteen Engineering and Shipbuilding Unions, a scheme of amalgamation is probable.Amalgamations are also stated to be projected (1) between the Boilermakers&apos;&apos; Society, the Shipwrights&apos; Society and the Blacksmiths&apos; Society ; (2) between the three largest societies in the Tailoring trade ; and (3) to unite all Blast Furnacemen&apos;s Unions in England and Scotland.An amalgamation has been completed between the Associated Ironmoulders and the Friendly Society of Ironfounders.Conscription, &amp;c.The Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress published on the 3rd June the report of the proceedings at their Conference with Mr. Bonar Law on conscription, &amp;c.  It bears the significant title &quot;-The Trade Union Movement and Political Issues.&quot;The decision of the Parliamentary Committee will be considered by the annual con-ference of the Transport Workers&apos; Federation at Swansea, and also by a conference of the Triple Alliance at Southport on the 24th June.The Old Ford branch of the National Union of General Workers has called on the Parliamentary representatives of the Union to demand from the Government dates when conscription will be abolished, &amp;c. Failing a satisfactory reply, members are asked to withdraw from Parliament.Income Tax.The South Wales Miners&apos; Federation Council at Cardiff on the 31st May considered a letter from the Chancellor of the Exchequer with reference to their recent resolution not to pay income tax till the exemption limit had been raised to 250/., and decided that the Chancellors letter was unsatisfactory. At the close of proceedings, the General Secre-tary, Mr. T. Richards, M.P., said that the miners hoped that other bodies of the working classes and also the suffering middle classes would bring pressure to bear on the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The movement for raising the exemption limit to 2501 has been supported by the London and District Committee of the Associated Blacksmiths and Iron Workers, the Boilermakers&apos; Society, and the South Leicester Colliery Workers.aa-Rour Week.The final figures of the ballot taken by the Federation of Engineering and Ship Building Trades on the question of approaching the employers for a 44-hour week without reduction in earnings are&apos;: For a 44-hour week, 513,000, against 15,000. Other demands for a 44-hour week recently reported include the Poor Law Workers&apos; Trade Union, the Bargoed Steam Coal Colliery, Port Sunlight Workers, and the Central Ironmoulders.Agricultural Wages Board.At meetings of the Agricultural Wages Board held on the 29th and 30th May, and the 2nd June, proposals were issued to fix special rates for the corn harvest in certain areas in England and Wales. The Board also decided to issue a notice of proposal to increase the minimum and overtime rates at present in operation for female workers of 18 years and over.Pre-War Practices Restoration (No. 3) Bill.The second reading of this Bill was carried without a division in the House of Commons on the 2nd June.It is stated that an amendment to this Bill is to be moved&apos;, on the suggestion of the London Society for Women&apos;s Service. It-will be to the effect that, whatever may be the regulations for the employment of workers in the trades affected, women who are qualified for the work shall not be debarred; and also that trades and processes which are in them-selves new, or are new to the country since the beginning of the war, shall not be included in the scope of the Bill. At a joint meeting of the Parliamentary Labour Party and the National Executive on the 4th June, a resolution was passed approving the Bill, and hoping that it would be passed without amendment.
Railway Shareholders Defence Association.At a meeting held in London on the 30th May, the British Railway Shareholders Defence Assciation was constituted. Its object is to guard the interest of all shareholders in British Railway Companies.International Labtiur Legislation.The Labour Party has just issued the memoranda of its advisory committee on Inter-national Labour Legislation.   The more important recommendations are : 1. A workman by crossing a frontier shall not thereby be a loser in such matters as health insurance, compensation for accidents and unemployment benefit.2. The Governments concerned should acknowledge their responsibility for the preven-tion and relief of unemployment.3. A common standard of inspection and a uniform minimum of factory legislation should be an essential part of international law.4. The clause in the International Labour Convention &quot;&apos; Employers and Workers should be allowed the right of association for all lawful purposes &quot; is not re-garded as satisfactory. &quot; Full recognition of Trade Unionism cannot be said to e&apos;xist in any country.&quot;There are sections on the &quot; S3amon&apos;s Chartar,&quot; Asiatic and native Labour, Women, and the machinery and structure of international Labour legislation.(2)  District Reports.London and South-Eastern.Unemployment. There is a satisfactory decrease in the unemployment recorded in this area, apart from any reduction due to the exclusion of short time employment figures and to the review of out-of-work donation policies by the Rota Sub-Committees of the Local Employment Committees. In the Newhaven area, labour is being absorbed at last by work on the road from Newhaven to Lewis, but in Sussex- there is general complaint that housing and road-repairing is retarded by lack of materials and plant.The City of London Employment Committee considers it a matter of urgent necessity that minimum rates of wages should be set up in each, trade, below which applications by employers should not be accepted by Employment Exchanges. Eastbourne and Brentford suggest that all Government contracts should contain the stipulation that the labour required should be obtained as far as possible locally through the Employment Exchange.General Industrial Situation. Labour is unsettled and the demand for the 47 or 48-hour week is growing. The woodworkers are endeavouring to extend the agitation for the abolition of piece-work to the metal workers. The tailors&apos; strike is apparently an expression of protest against unhealthy and disagreeable working conditions.South Midlands and Eastern.Unemployment.-!)!?, decrease in unemployment continues. Temporary increases at Chelmsford, Leicester and Watford are more than balanced by notable decreases at Ipswich, Letch worth and Reading, and no serious increase is anticipated in any particular area. The output of brick from the East Anglian yards is reported to be hampered by lack of labour, and there is a demand for three or four hundred women in the boot and shoe trade at Norwich. The East Anglian Institute of Agriculture is willing to provide training for discharged N.C.O&apos;s and men.South-Western.Unemployment. There is again a slight decrease in the unemployment figures in this division. Cheltenham shows a considerable reduction, but there is an increase at South-ampton and Bristol and an increase of unemployment is expected among the dockyard workers at Devonport. The prospect of employment in the Swindon district is still decidedly bad. Discontent is growing at the delay in re-opening H.M. Factory, Swindon. The demobilised men are becoming restless and the opinion is expressed that trouble is brewing. There is a prospect of a new industry being established at Cowes (I.W.) by Messrs. Saunders, the patentees of a special make of plywood, but this does not promise any imme-diate absorption of labour on a large scale. Road schemes, the estimated cost of which is  161,000, are to be taken in hand forthwith in Cornwall where there may be an increase of unemployment among the tin miners.
General Industrial Situation. The building trade agreement between the National Federation of Building Operatives, and the Southern Counties Federation of Employers is giving satisfaction in the ports, and attempts are being made to organise districts rates in Andover, Blandford and Ring wood.West Midlands.Unemployment.-She general decrease in unemployment continues to be general, but the situation is still serious at Cradley Heath and Wednesbury.General Industrial Situation. Deficiency of coal is stated to retard the absorption of labour in the tile industry. Financial assistance is also needed as some of the workings in the clay pits are under water to a depth of 90 feet and the firms concerned cannot meet the expense of pumping.Yorkshire and East Midlands.Unemployment. Unemployment is still serious at Bradford, Derby, Hull, Sheffield, Todmorden and the lace towns of Ilkeston and Long Eaton, but no heavy increase is anticipated in any particular area. The successful placing of unemployed women in the wholesale clothing trade has eased a somewhat acute situation at Leeds. In Nottingham, the unemployment of demobilised soldiers is serious, and the Employment Committee are pressing the municipal and county authorities to take instant action.General Industrial Situation. While the prospects of the engineering, chemical and woollen trades are brighter, and the cotton trade is recovering rapidly, there has been a recrudescence of political agitation. At Sheffield, the secret army enquiry has been used as a battle-cry by the extremists, and the Sheffield police seem more unsettled than those at either Leeds or Bradford. Corporation employees are very restless ; strikes have been threatened at Halifax, Huddersfield, Bradford and in the Electricity Department at Leeds. The Notts coalfield is disturbed by an aftermath of wage questions as to the bearing of the Sankey report on such classes as colliery clerks and brick makers connected with collieries. The building trade in Lincolnshire is rather unsettled, particularly in the county town, in Boston and in Spalding.North-Western.Unemployment. The unemployment figures continue to fall in every area of this division with the exception of Lancaster. It is still too early to estimate in what occupa-tions, chronic, as distinct from temporary, unemployment may be expected. The principal industries in the Ashton-under-Lyne and Stalybridge areas, cotton and engineering, show a decided improvement and the general outlook is regarded as promising. At Leigh the principal industries are in- a good position, with the exception of cablemaking, and at Bolton they show signs of improvement. A decided recovery is reported in the Burnley cotton industry. The retention of men in the Army who have been discovered to be pivotal since the 31st January, is specially affecting the Denton hatting industry, which shows an unexpected expansion.General Industrial Situation-Tike workers in the area are reported &quot; jumpy &quot; under the shadow of the anticipated crisis in the cotton trade, where the ballot has now shown a majority against the acceptance of the employers&apos; offer. The position of women workers has become the centre of discussion in the asbestos trade, and the Amalgamated Society of India-rubber, Cable and Asbestos Workers have demanded their expulsion from the trade.  Demarcation disputes are disturbing factors in Liverpool and Birkenhead.Northern.Unemployment. There is in this division, as in all others, a decrease in the number of unemployed recorded, both men and women, and the change-over to peace time conditions seems proceeding fairly satisfactorily in the industrial area between Tyne and Tees. On the outskirts of the area, it is proposed to relieve a local surplus at Blyth by encouraging fishing and canning industries. The labour situation in the isolated industrial area in Cumberland should be helped by the erection of new gas works at Carlisle at an estimated cost of  250,000. &apos;General Industrial Situation.-^-The ballot among the unions for a 44-hour week has resulted in an overwhelming majority in favour of the proposal, and negotiations are expected to open about mid-June. The bricklayers who refused to work overtime or during week-ends until this point was settled have referred to their members the sug-gestion of a joint committee to discuss the matter.   Blast furnacemen are agitating to
convert their present war bonuses into wage-rates, and it is understood that the Cleveland iron masters are prepared to raise the present base rate of labour, but to reduce the sliding scale. The movement to amalgamate the blast furnacemen&apos;s unions in England and Scotland is finding the disposal of the reserve funds a difficulty. There is considerable dissatisfaction among the railway men over the detailed application of the national agree-ment by the North-Eastern Railway Company. Housing and the payment of income tax are other grievances in the district. Mr. Adamson and Mr. John Hill, the Boilermakers&apos; Secretary, addressed a fairly large meeting in Newcastle on the question of the blockade, the Military Service Act, and the Russian campaigns.Wales.Unemployment. The decrease in unemployment continues, notably in the Flint area, and at Swansea, where the settlement of two strikes has reduced the figures. At Carnarvon and Cardiff, there is a slight increase. The placing of men in the quarry district of North Wales is steadily improving.The chief factors retarding resettlement are sectional strikes, the shortage of raw materials in the steel trade, difficulties as to workmen&apos;s trains in the Merthyr area, shortage of orders in the steel sheet trade, and uncertainty as to the cost of future building opera-tions by private enterprise. The surplus labour in the Merthyr area cannot be transferred to Ebbw Vale, where labour is urgently required, owing to housing conditions. The Merthyr labour exchange is trying to arrange for workmen&apos;s trains to run daily to Ebbw Vale. This would absorb 500 men immediately. The Employment Council have recom-mended that the Railway Executive be approached.General Industrial Situation. Labour is generally restless and inclined to break away from its agreements. The Welsh Tinplate Trade Council has considered the claims for advances and improved conditions put forward by the workers and their reaction on the command of those foreign markets where American competition is most acute. A corn-mission is to proceed to America to investigate conditions there. Meanwhile an order for 360,000 boxes of tinplates for the Far East, which has been secured after keen competition with the American manufacturers, should help to dimimish depression in the trade. In the coalfields, the miners are adopting a policy of &quot; squeezing out&quot; other unions, especially those of mechanics, who are being induced to enter the Miners&apos; Federation. Where this is done, the mechanics would refuse to repair the mines during a strike and would thus expose the workings to the risk of floods. Employers are protesting against a scheme for pooling wages among the trimmers of the South Wales ports, as reducing efficiency to the level of the least skilled or most troublesome, and encouraging trivial suspensions and delays. They propose, alternatively, a reorganisation of the trimming gangs. The demands for increased wages put forward by the dock-pilots, boatmen and riggers of the ports from Swansea to Newport has been refused by the employers, who offer to erect Concilia-tion Boards in each port, organised under a Central Board. This counter-offer has been refused in its turn.Scotland.Unemployment. The unemployment figures continue to decrease notably at Arbroath. Slight increases, however, are shown at Ayr, Dumfries, Galashiels, Kilmarnock, Oban, Stirling and Wick, and the unemployment remains serious in the large towns. A resolu-tion was passed by the Glasgow Employment Committee protesting against the employment of Asiatic labour on British ships when British seamen were unemployed. A proposal that Local Employment Committees be empowered to supplement the wages of trainees taken from the ranks of claimants to donation, which was passed at a public meeting in Inverness, was amended by the Employment Council and forwarded to headquarters. The matter is regarded as of immediate urgency as it is of primary importance that the number of recipients of the donation be reduced. Dumfries Employment Committee urge that apprenticeship schemes should embrace all trades, and should be extended to cover the cases of lads who enlisted voluntarily before becoming apprentices.General Industrial Situation. The major trades are quiet, and the dispute in the furniture trade has been composed by the intervention of officials of the Ministry. Some apprehension is expressed over the drift towards industrial action which characterises Clydesdale and Glasgow, where the Parliamentary Labour Party is becoming more and more discredited. On the other hand, the agitation in Glasgow for the release of the imprisoned strike leaders is falling flat, and an attempted monster demonstration attracted only a small crowd of about five hundred ; the Clyde Workers&apos; Committee is apparently waning in influence.
Part V.-Disputes. (a) Involving a Stoppage of Work.Miners.\Black Country.-Th.q strike of 260 working enginemen, stokers, mechanics, &amp;c, at Baggeridge and Himley Collieries and the Pensnett Railway with regard to the dismissal of Evan Parker, a winding engineman, has resulted in throwing out of work all the miners and all the men employed in connection with these undertakings as well as employees of the iron and steel works of Brierly Hall and district. By the 28th May, nearly 10,000 men were out of work, and Union officials state that they have the greatest difficulty in confining the dispute to South Staffordshire. As the pumping engines have ceased work, serious flooding of the clay and coal mines is feared. On the 30th and 31st, conferences were held at the Home Office between representatives of the owners and the men, presided over by the Deputy Inspector of Mines, but no settlement was reached, the men refusing to discuss the matter till Parker was reinstated.South Wales. With regard to the strike of over 1,000 miners at Bed was on the question of workmen&apos;s safety, a conference has been arranged at the Home Office.A dispute has broken out at Pwllbach (in the anthracite area) which threatens to involve the whole area, and at Blaengarw 800 workmen at the Ocean Colliery are on strike over griev-ances relating to the minimum wage.  At Clydach, 3,500 to 4,000 men a^e on strike.Derbijshire. The miners of Swanwick collieries, Alfreton, Derbyshire, struck work on the 28th May to enforce the inclusion of colliery clerks in the Sankey award. Their demands were met and the strike ended.Scotland. As a result of the dismissal of two men, over 300 miners struck work at the Polton colliery, Midlothian, on the 29th May.Tailors and Garment Workers.West End. The strike reported last week is now stated to affect 2,500 tailors. The United (Government Workers&apos; Union and the Amalgamated Society of Tailors are meeting on the 6th June to consider joint action in the matter. The Master Tailors&apos; Association has refused to discuss terms with the men, on the ground that they are flouting an award given as recently as last March, but it is willing to accept the arbitration of the Ministry of Labour. One or two firms have expressed their agreement with the men&apos;s demands.Norwich. Garment workers in the employ of two Norwich firms (numbering about 1,250), who struck work on the 28th May on an allegation of non-payment of the &quot; Stoker &quot; wage award, resumed work on the 2nd June, pending arbitration.Perth Dye Works.-The dispute reported last week (affecting 2,000 workers) has now been settled so far as Messrs. Pullars are concerned, the men having achieved practically their full demands. At Messrs. Campbell the position is somewhat anomalous, as the men were thrown out of work, as the result of a fire, before the expiry of their strike notices.Liverpool Demarcation Dispute.Owing to a difficulty of demarcation between labourers and boilermakers (affecting respec-tively the Liverpool Shipwrights&apos; Trade and Friendly Society, and the A.S.E.), 1,300 sealers, cranemen, &amp;c, are on strike at Messrs. Clover, Clayton &amp; Co. It is anticipated that unless a settlement can be arrived at by the 5th June the whole works will have to close down.Tugboatmen.The strike at Soutliampton has entered on its third week. The employers state that their hands are tied by National Wartime Board. The Company have attempted to find substitutes, but as the shipwrights are supporting the boatmen this has proved impossible. There is little likelihood of a resumption of the steamer service with the Isle of Wight before Whitsuntide.The Clyde tugboatmen&apos;s strike ended the 31st May : negotiations are to ensue.Woodworkers-: Premium Bonus and Piecework.No settlement of the strikes of woodworkers against the premium bonus system in London, Southampton, Gainsborough, and Basingstoke, nor of the strike against piecework at Lincoln, has yet been reported.Engineers, Sheffield. ^At the works of Messrs. had fields, Sheffield, 500 enginemen are on strike over a dispute about the 47-hour week. It is estimated that 5,000 men are thereby indirectly thrown out of employment.Bakers, Cork.The strike reported last week has ended, the men having been granted advances in wages..
Ex-Service Men.Leeds-Disabled soldiers and sailors to the number of 500, who have been in training under the Government scheme, came out on strike at Leeds on the 30th May, demanding  3 a week, exclusive of pensions, instead of the present rate of 27s. Qd. pension and 5s. Qd, bonus. They are supported by the Federation of Discharged and Demobilized Soldiers and Sailors, which is stated to be making a levy on its members by way of &quot; strike pay.&quot; Money for the support of the strikers has also been collected locally. The Ministry of Labour issued a state-ment in defence of the present scale of pensions and allowances, but this was declared by the strikers to be unsatisfactory. It is anticipated that the absentees will be invited to return or else terminate their training.School Teachers.Strikes of elementary school teachers against the existing scales of salaries are reported at Northampton, Peterborough, Pembroke, and Hey wood (Lanes).Municipal.The Merthyr municipal workers&apos; strike ended on the 31st May, after a two days&apos; stoppage. Negotiations are taking place. A strike of Corporation workers for a 44-hour week and increased wages is in progress at Morpeth.Building.Building Operatives are reported to be on strike at Lincoln, Boston, Totnes, Carnarvon, and various places in Ireland, the disputes being in most cases about wages.Colliery Brick Workers.. Sixty employees in the brickworks of the Powell Duffryn Company at Aberaman, members of the National Amalgamated Workers&apos; Union, struck on the 3rd June to enforce their demand for the equivalent of the Sankey award.Waste Paper Sorters.The strike at Messrs. Lendrums which began on the 27th May still continues. The firm have offered a 50-hour week and minimum rates of 58s. and 62s., but the men have declined this.Plumbers.Plumbers at St. Helen&apos;s and in the Potteries are on strike for a 44-hour week, and in districts of Ireland for a 48-hour week.Lock-Out.The lock-out at Ellesmere Port Cement Works, on the question of recognition, shows no signs of settlement.Other Strikes in Progress.Strikes for higher pay have been declared by the employees at Messrs. Stephenson, Blake &amp; Co. (typefounders, Sheffield), and the warehouse staff of the Star Tea Company. In the case of the latter, railwaymen and vehicle workers are said to be refusing to handle the Company&apos;s goods. The strike of,Scottish fishermen has extended, with the result that &quot;several cargoes of herrings have been wasted. Taxi-cab proprietors and drivers at Preston are on strike for increased fares. At Horbury, 1,000 railway waggon-builders have struck over the question of fines, and at Wakefield 1,500 fitters over conditions of employment.Other Strikes Settled.As a result of successful strikes, Ashford laundry workers have secured a 48-hour week, and Oxford bricklayers a 60-hour week; and substantial concessions on wages and hours have been secured by Rochdale members of the Association of Shipbuilding and Engineering Draughtsmen, which has thereby gained its first victory.(b) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work.Miners.North Staffordshire. Colliery clerks have now established their claim to the Sankey award. It is stated that about six firms -stood out, but 24 hours&apos; notice of refusal to pay the award to miners if clerks were not included brought about an understanding.South Wales. At Bed was a dispute has taken place on the same subject as caused a strike at Bargoed (see V a). A demand for shorter hours for surfacemen has also been put forward. The question of extra pay for week-end work threatened to become acute, but the suggestion of the Minister of Labour that the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation should lay the matter before Sir Richard Redmayne has been accepted. The monthly meeting of the Neath and Avon Valley District decided to press further in the matter.Nottinghamshire. The Miners&apos; Council has decided that all Colliery clerks shall be compelled to joint the Notts Miners&apos; Association.
All inquiries relating to this report should be addressed to :-Intelligence Division,Ministry op Labour, k Montagu House,Whitehall,London, S.W.LBurnley. There is a dispute in the Burnley engineering industry about the continual employment by two firms of women dilutees. The engineers in the whole district have threatened to come out in sympathy with the operatives of the two firms concerned.Liverpool Dockers and Overtime.With reference to the dockers&apos; dispute on overtime, on which the decision of the Congress at Galway was being awaited, Mr. J. Sexton, M.P., has informed the Liverpool Shipping Employers&apos; Association that as a result of the Congress the dockers were now willing to work four hours overtime (instead of two) after a completion of an 8-hour day, on consideration&apos; of the payment of a half-night&apos;s pay (9s. 3d.), and the allowance of a half-hour break for tea.Other Threatened Strikes,At Leigh the beamers, twisters and drawers, and at West Bromwich the Corporation &quot;motor-bus employees have threatened to strike on question of hours and wages.R. S. HORNE.

</content>
</cab>
