<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 202-202</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
From Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department, dlh June 1919. (Received 10th June at 11 a.m.)Secret. Afghanistan. Following from Chief Political Officer, Wazir Force, dated 7th June : &quot;Spin-warn is clear of enemy, and Afghan regular troops have reached Natun. The Sheratulla Torcame (?) Khel and Kabul Khel have fled lo Khost. It is reported that the lashkar of Wazirs and Mahsuds liave left Upper Daur.&quot; General opinion among the tribes involved is that they have been -betrayed by the Afghans. It is proposed within the next few days to carry out small punitive operations against Wazir villages which were deeply involved in the insurrection. Measures military and civil authorities proposed are to appropriate grain and bhusa stocks and to burn the villages.&quot; Khaddi was destroyed on 4th. General question of punitive measures in Tochi area is under consideration, and full report will be submitted later. On Derajat border Mullazai constabulary post attacked last night, and bazaar burnt by Bhiltanis, who have definitely joined Mahsuds.&quot; Following from Baluchistan dated 8th June. &quot;Two letters were received 7th June, first from (?) to myself dated evening 5th, couched in very friendly language, saying that he .had no intention of beginning war against British until our attack on Baldak. He then was obliged to collect troops and tribesmen toTight. But Amir&apos;s firman ordering cessation of hostilities having arrived, he informs me thereof, and presumes that hostilities will cease on our side also. Second letter is from (?) to General Commanding, Ohaman, dated 7th June. It is in exceedingly obscure language. First sentence described sorrow with which he received the strict, military terms contained in Soufront&apos;s first letter, and saying his mission is not to fight or attack. All the rest of (?) letter contains political arguments, gist of which is that. Great Britain has Islam against her and is weakened by resentment of her oppressed subjects, having to trust to troops whose hearts are not with her, and by being involved in difficulties with other great Powers. Result of this is that Britain&apos;s trifling with present embarrassment with Afghanistan has given Russia her oppor-tunity and Russian plenipotentiary has arrived Nazur-i-Sherif, while Russian (presumably Bolshevist) troops will shortly occupy Askabad and Mur. In proof of his assertion, he forwards, in original, report from Afghan General at Maimana reporting evacuation of Merv and Askabad by British arrival there of anti-Bolshevist Russian Colonel, who is making friends with Turkomans and intends fighting Bolshevists. (?) adds that he personally, unlike other wise men of Islam, does not hold that acceptance of British rule over Muhammad countries is heresy. In his opinion Russia is destroyer of Islam and only effect of strife between British and Afghanistan is strengthening of Russia. (?) considers that his mission was to go to Farah and Chakansur to make arrangements and return to Kandahar. If he does not succeed by negotiation, he is to take charge of all operations at Kandahar.&quot;Baluchistan reported on 8th J une that position in Zhob area is much the samo but the relief of Jandola reported to-day should automatically improve the situation in Zhob.

</content>
</cab>
