<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 204-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^^^*C /-1*--This Doc urnit is the Property ofntannic tViajesty&apos;G government from Viceroy, Wi Jane 1919. (Receivecj 10th June, .11 a.in.). 837 S. Secret. Afghanistan. Your telegram of 5th June. We learn with regret and some surprise that His Majesty&apos;s Government take exception to procedure and terms of our reply to Amir.   We were prompted by following considerations :  1. Having demonstrated our strength and intentions, having inflicted punishment on Afghan troops, on Jelalabad and Kabul, and having received prayer for peace from Amir, we considered it politic to terminate hostilities at the earliest moment possible consistent with maintenance of our prestige.2. If Afghanistan now drops out humiliated, tribal situation will at once cool and we shall be left with comparatively simple proposition to deal with piecemeal at our own time.3. Whole frontier is in condition of acute tension. It is already (been) blazing Zhob to Kurram and conflagration spreading from sea to Pamirs if war continues -indefinitely with inevitable reaction on internal India.4. Our troops at this season are exposed to intolerable heat and most unhealthy5. Continuance of war involves constant and large demands on you for technical troops and materials of all kinds.6. Had we delayed our reply to Amir&apos;s letter he would have concluded that we were implacably determined on war, and would grant no peace. He would have probably been led to cancel his orders to his, Generals suspending hostilities, and have taken further aggressive action, forcing on us thereby indefinite prolongation of war.7. Although Amanulla has been guilty of criminal folly, and begun badly, there is no alternative but to accept him, and to treat with him so long as he remains de facto ruler. History has shown futility of attempting to force, ruler of our own choosing on Afghan people. Fall of Amanulla would probably mean.chaos and anarchy leaving us no stable government with whom to make arrangements and react seriously on whole frontier situation.8. This appeared an excellent opportunity to show Moslem community in India that, though amply justified, we have no wish to wipe out or trample on neigh-bouring Moslem States as such. Line taken by us is best answer to prevalent calumny&quot; (? that) British policy now is to destroy Islam. Terms of our letter sternly and emphatically repudiated idea of misunderstanding and pinned respon-sibility to Amir&apos;s folly. We cannot see that it in any way outlines and delimits final peace conditions. What you regard as our unexpected clemency will certainly not be mistaken for weakness, and. may be greatly appreciated as generosity on the part of victors. Experience has shown that harsh (? threats) and peremptory communications merely irk without intimidating.. Armistice terms were fully considered and agreed to by our military advisers, who held with us that they were the best in all circumstances of the case.We. shall, of course, consult you freely regarding terms of final settlement; but we must plainly warn His Majesty&apos;s Government, if there is any idea of imposing-drastic conditions or exacting heavy reparation, that for that purpose we must continue war indefinitely and (at) advance and occupy Kabul and Kandahar. Probable result would be chaos and disappearance of all stable government, and open door to Bolsheviks, who, as we know, have already (? thrown out their) tentacles in this direction. We must, at the same time, be prepared to deal with general frontier conflagration, with its inevitable reaction on India. What we want of Afghanistan is peace and really friendly relations, with adequate safeguards for the exclusion of Bolsheviks and other hostile influences. These we hope we can now (? secure) if our advice is followed. There is really no halfway house between policy of complete subjugation of Afghanistan and policy of attempting to establish really friendly relations and mutual trust.conditions.

</content>
</cab>
