<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 239-255</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Is Document is Britannic Male!\\ BOX-XD OF AGRIGULTTJR.13 AiTI) FJSEOTIIS. -6.1. 7462 &quot;j,&apos;^ ^S^&amp;J    nor t f or weck end!ng JLOth Juno f[......1910 ^ JL-T. yOOD PRODUCTION&quot; PSPARriCTT. Tho Weather and Condition of Crops.The weather has again been dry and warm except on Wednesday hen some rain fell in almost all parts of the country,     In the fiorth-west, where six hours&apos; rain was experienced; almost all crops kre growing well, but in other parts of the country, where there were ght showers only, more rain is needed,     Tho drought has spoilt the prospects of a heavy strawberry crop in Hampshire, and all fruit /ould benefit by rain,,     Tho hay orop will be a light one,The weather conditions have again been ideal for the cleaning of fallows.Land Division.(i) LancL Settlement-..ABBllS^i2J^^^,^3^.^^Sy^J^S*    The following is a summary of a return obtained by the Board showing the number of applications received by Local Authorities;-Applications from - -LocalAuthorityService or jSjc-ggrv.No cofService Men11  ati 6 ns This o m Civj. utans,Total,No c0.f(^rp,?.f.o,            :.      Acreage.   .^5f2.f   Acreage. Applicant s ---Li- ; Appl lean bs ;-----------Appl ic^ntsr&quot;County Councils.Sagland .* .. *. &quot;/ales o o s.....County JBotou&amp;hs.England and. i CJj ^ L    O A    9   *    0 *    *Total England and Wales12,130 720448223i532 15,6734.1435,141 5009382.639 10j71665417,271   305.2211,22054126,3954.7 3713,293     243,354        5,734     94,059     19,032   337,41bAnalysis^of Applications,,     Returns have now been received from 41 County Councils showing chat of 15,650 applicants for small hold-ings 5,499 have been interviewed.     Of the number interviewed 4,121 (or 75$) have been approved.     The approved applicants comprise3,623 who require s^-all holdings amounting to 75/877 acres, and 293 who require Cottage Holdings amounting to 1,409 J- acres.Land Settlement through County Councils.   During the week the following purchases of land by County Councils under the Small Holdings and Allotments Act,, 1903, mainly for providing holdings for ex-service men,, were approved by the Board:-County.,Bedford H Cambs. - HerefordHer bs.ParishFlitton (Glebe)Histon, Old Farmpt. Downton Castle EstateBishops Hat fieldAcreage,1246881 69Purchase Pr i ce .4,145 5,050 3,600 2,100
County.	Parish.	Acreage .	Purchase			&quot;Price7&quot; .Herts.	Datchworth	29	700Isle of lilly	Iviepal	62	2,990Kent	Stone and Darenth	59	2,500do .	*7i lie sbo rough	24	650 and		timber    12	Norfolk	Potter Heigham, Hose Farm	128	4,500do.	T.&apos;]ast Rusfcon, Old Farm	55	2,150Somerset	Crewkerne, pt. Henley			Manor Estate	76	3,511 103.do .	Mar took, &quot;Hillside&quot; estate	113 timba	5,100 and r   180do.	Hutton, pt. Hutton Court			Ustate	32	2,000do.	Me are	61	2,550do .	Taunt on St. Jamea (Without)			and Kingston, Lower Portman			and Pickney and &apos;Vat or house			Farms	132 timber	6,400 and 124Warwick	Dunchurch	124 timber	5,400 and 4737ilts	Stratton St. Margarets,			Church and Ryle Farms	158	6,000Yorks, S.R.	Skirlaugh, Silver Hall			Farm	135	4,850The total area of land acquired or agreed to be acquired by County Councils since the 20th December, 1918, with the Board&apos;s approval is 28,637 acres, of which 26,610 acres are in England and 2,027 acres in Wales.     The following statement shows the dates on which vacant possession will be obtained:-Acres.Possession already obtained .,...... 4,124Michaelmas, 1919    .................. 7 ^ 818loth November, 1919    ............... 5233rd January. 1920................. 120Candlemas, 1920    ........... 4.644Lady Day, 1920    ................. . ., 5 j 1916th April, 1920    ......... 40?13th Kay, 1920    .................... 1,873Michealmas, 3 920    .................. 1,464November, 1920    .................... 134Candlemas, 1921       ................. 157Not yet ascertained   ............... 2,3.9228,637In addition, the 33oard have under consideration proposals by County Councils for the acquisition of 85,006 acres, including 6,553 acres which the Council^ propose to acquire by the exercise of compulsory powers.     Of this total 77,321 acres are in England and 7,685 in Wales.
QCompulsory Orderga     The Bedford County Council have made an order for the compulsory purchase of 70 acres forming part of Houghton Park farm, Ampthill.Offers of hand by Landowners.     The offer a received direct by -the Board in response tc the President&apos;s appeal to landowners for land suitable for small holdings number 194, comprising approximately 40,000 acres.     These are being dealt with as indicated below:-Acres.Declined without inspection ........ 40 offers representing 395Declined after inspection .......... 69Further particulars awaited     ......32Referred to Commissioners for inspection................... 28Referred by Commissioners to County Councils as prima facie suitable....................  &apos;16Declined by County Councils .......     3Withdrawn........................,___6194Farm,,gettlements administered by the Board.     The area of land acquired by the Board for the purposes of Farm Settlements remains the sane as last week (via. 12.012 acres).     The number of ex-service men at the Settlements is also unchanged.300 ev/es with lambs have been purchased and sent to the Pjmbrjey Settlement during the week.     There is plenty of grass on the marsh fields, but the hay is not likely to be a heary crop.     The horses are mainly engaged in getting land ready for turnips.At HoJ.heach potatoes are still being riddled.     All settlers are working satisfactorily and are busy among their own crops which generally are looking well.     Two more probationers will commence work during the present week.At Heath Hill the potatoes have now all been sold.     On the light portions of the estate corn crops are showing signs of drought.     16 heifers and one cow have been purchased and sold to settlers during the week,     One probationer has left the Settlement and his place has been filled by a local ex-Service man.13,150 10,1549,0451,836 254 ,.5,091 39^975
(ii) Work of Agricultural TSxecutive Committees.Cultivation of Land.     Last year Cheshire, Agricultural Executive Committee undertook wi th considerable success the cropping of about 84 acres of land at Dunham Massey in the occupation of the Army Ord-nance Department.     The Committee did not feel able to continue the cultivation this season, but they were successful in obtaining an offer from an adjoining farmer tc take a tenancy of the land from the Military Authorities, and with the help of the Committee satis-factcry terms were arranged.     Unfortunately, the Local Representa-tives of the Ordnance Department thought fit to impose what appear to be most unreasonable conditions on the cultivation of the land, including the erection of three miles of fencing, whereupon the prospective tenant withdrew his offer .     Strong representations have been made to the War Office, but so far without result, and it is feared, that even if the restrictions should be waived, the season will be too far advanced to allow of the land being put to its full use this year.The Hampshire Agricultural Executive Committee have for- . warded a copy of the trading Account of Dummer Down Farm (of which possession was taken early in 1917) for the 18 months ended Sep-tember 29th, 1918.      The Farm, which has been under the manage-ment of a bailiff working under the direct supervision of the Committee&apos;s Executive Officer, was in an extremely neglected con-diticn when taken ever by the Committee, the valuation being  2,638   15s, Od.     The expenditure during the period covered by the Account was  5,525. 17s. Id.     Sales of produce and other receipts realised  2.978. 16s . Od.     The valuation at the close of the Account of  6,463. Os. Od. showing the balance in favour cf the Committee to be  1,277. 3s. lid.The Cornwall,  Agricultural Executive Committee have been authorised to take possession of about 12-jj- acres of land forming part of a holding in the Parish of &apos;7arbstow, which has been left unoccupied for several months.     The Committee have pressed the owner to get the arable land cultivated, but nothing whatever has been dene, and no preparation has been made for its cultivation since last autumn.ElJ9SP5IljyPS -     The Devon Agricultural Executive Committee took proceedings against the occupying owner of a farm at Black-awton for refusing to give up poesession of the farm after the Committee had taken possession under Regulation 2M.     The Corn-mil tec had been dealing with this case since 1917, and had served Cultivation Orders on the occupier cf which no notice was taken. The farm was stated to be in a moat shocking condition, and bad apparently been entirely neglected for several years.     The Magis-trates imposed a fine cf  50 and costs.     Malt,for,,HomejJr e win&amp;. The Ministry of Joed have decided to allow malt to be sold for home brewing to all persons who were authorised to brew in the year 1916, and they have asked the I3oard   to undertake through the Agricultural Executive Committees the work of issuing permits to all such persons, and not merely to farmers and farm labourers requiring home brewed beer for harvest purposes .      The Board
have expressed the:.tr willingness to undertake the work, and the nocecw;.;-;/ vmrrcTtovJ. or.b have been sent to the Executive Committees. The Cor.ox tteeo arc g.&quot;1 Ten reaaonable discretion in regard to the relaxation of the e oiu;u o\o:is attached to the issue of permits in any case whoic strict adherence to those conditions would involve unnecessary hardship.(iii)     Land Drainage .$ayeney;.     The length from liendham to Hoxne Mill (about 8 miles)&quot;iiafa not been touched, as it is impossible to convey prison-ers to work there or to procure the erection of a camp within reach of the work.     &quot;/itfa this exception the upper part of the river has been cleaned and the work is satisfactory.     An, Order is being prepared setting up a drainage board for the river above Geldeston Lock.glint and Denbigh. .  Work-has been carried out on Rhuddlan Marsh, which has &quot;effected the substantial improvement of about 3.000 acres of land..     About 11 miles of rivers and streams in this area have been cleaned.The cleaning of Rhyl Cut (about 4 miles) has benefited some five square miles of country in the Prestatyn area, in which  750 has also been expended on cleaning subsidiary drains,     The money spent is being satisfactorily recovered.Other drainage work is in progress.Merioneth. Satisfactory results have been obtained from drainage work at Dysynni t Llanfrothen, Liar tech Ha:: eh and Her fa Mawr. Good crops are being grown on land which was of little value before the drainage work was taken in hand-(iv)   Tithe, Commons, Copyhold&apos; and Survey .A distinct increase has&apos; occurred during the last few weeks in the number of applications for enfranchisement of copy-hcld lands under the Copyhold Act, 1894, as shown by the following figures: -Week Ending . &apos;So. of Applications Received.1914 . 1918 . 1919 .May 12th 2 1 5 May 19th              &apos;                             1                   11Hay 26th                                           2                   5 6June 2nd                     v                    3                  3 18June 9th                                           w                   5 58 15 35.
&apos;&amp; The applications for redemption of tithe rent chargecontinue well above the average .of previous years, ay regards both number and amount of rentcharge involved0     Efforts are being mads&apos; to determine the amount of ,the consideration and give notice to the parties interestsd. in all cases of pouteharge accruing on the 1st July, in order that if possible the redemption money may he paid over before the end of the month and so pi&apos;event tho further accrual of tho annual, rontehargo after the:1st prox.     Ths matter is complicated, however, by the necessity in the great majority of cases for making enquiries as to the rates and land tax paid in respect of the r-eutcharges to be redeemed, the information supplied by the applicants for the red emotion being usually insufficient or oiiroliable.Five officers .loaned by the Director General of&apos;&apos;Ordnance Survey to assist the present Survey Section staff reported during the week and have commenced their new duties.     The assistance of those officers will greatly facilitate the speedy completion of the *-ery numerous matters which involve frcouont reference to the purvey Section for preparetion and examination of plans, etc.Commercial DivisionsPotashp     Arrangements for the distribution cf the potash acquired&quot;&quot;from Germany in exchange for food are under consideration, but a difficulty has arisen in fixing the price at which the material is to be soldo     The Agents of tho Alsatian Mines are offering to sell potash from Alsace at prices below .the cost to tho Geterrment of the German potash, and it &quot;/ill only be possible to fix a price sufficient to enable tho Government to recover its outlay if the existing import restrictions are mairisin-ocu    It is in. tho agricultural interest that the price should be stabilised as otherwise fertiliser makers and farmers will refrain.from buying until late in tne season in the hope of securing lower prices., and the total agricultural consumption is likely to be - less&apos; tjian...would. otherwise be the case.-.:r-H:?00-oJ.J2? SSt. r^ Jrlr Yliu&apos;?I19;--     Strong representations are being made&quot; ao&quot;Tb&quot;dVCays &quot;ill transport ard general inadequacy of the railway service.     Conferences on this question have taken place with the trade and representations have been mace to the Railway Executive,     Individual complaints are being enquired, into as they arise.     The Railway Companies are generally anxious to do the best they can under existing conditions,,Draft Reed Bill,   The draft Bill has been considered bv the Sects .7fLvYifbrtll7cmmi&apos;&apos;ttee and, with a few,, exceptions j approved by the&apos;.! in principle.     It has now been referred to a Sub-Committee of the Trade members of the main Committee for detailed, examination and criticism,     A meeting of the Cereal Seeds Advisory Committee has alio been called ,to consider the Bill so far as it affects cereal seeds,,Horticu] titral Divls ion *County Crgrinisatien... iLeicestershire,     The Horticultural Sub-Committee has been q   taken over en bloc by the County Council6
testing the value of different manures, and tasting vogeWDXBB ana f&quot;it for their suitability for the dleMiot   to De done in the county! the Committee should he enlivened end reformed.A meeting of the Distribution Sub-Committee of the Kortioul&amp;val Advisory Committee we.s held in the Conference Room on Friday, June 6th, when the following subjects were discussed.1.   (a)   Provision of Transport for conveyance of fruit and vegetables.(b) Re ton ef empties,-(c) Issue of notices to Fruit Growers and Salesmen.2.     Standardisation of non-returnable chip baskets and returnable wicker baskets *Cornwall.     In the TRinar Valley, strawberry picking lias commenced,     ^Agpj^ss are an irregular crop, Early Victoria alone promising r heavy crop,.    Apple Blossom:. Weevil has done muoh damage and reduced the yield generally.   .   urns, Cze&amp;m only are good. -Pea^s a light crop..Warwickshire,    During the week, 78 erchards and fruit gardens in Warwickshire were visited and found, to be generally planted in mixed line of about 20 yards apart, between which were grown small fruit or garden crops.     Intensive culture is not much practised and the larger gardens aiji in several instances very neglooted.Shippea Hill Training Schema.    During the week ending May 31st two men have joined the course and three have left.     &apos; wo of the latter from medical advice, and one has gone back to his old employment at a higher se.l.ary.     The effect of tho course is in practice to peleot \l) men who,, from their intelligence, perseverance and energy, would m&amp;ka good email-holder and on whom time and money for that purpose would not be wasted.    (?.) men y/ho could bs put on the labour market and vecemmanded *s being hard wording, strong, reliable, able to dig ard hoe etc.. with a general idea ef farm operations, and worth the rtrndard wage; but without sufficient intelligence and initiative to make small holders.   (.3) men who, from, various cause a.,. ars net suitable for either (l) or (2).7..Ml
Fruit Preservation.The Board1s Exhibit of Dried and Bottled Fruit and Vegetables has been staged this week at Messrs, Selfridge&apos;o Showroom in Oxford Street,A demonstration in Fruit and Vegetable Preservation was given at Harptree in Somersetshire,Small Live Stock,Poultry,?     The case of a Poultry Keeper being ordered by the Local&quot;Authorities to remove his fords has come to the notice of th .    BoardcPigs,   A further case of a Pig Keeper being requested by the Sanitary Authorities to remove his pigs from their present accommodation is being dealt withe-A number of applications have been received for the latest suggestions of the Board on Pig Feeding.Technical and Cultivation Division.Tractor SectioncDuring the week ended the 23rd May,, 2,919 tractors were in the hands of Committees and 1,048 of these were being operated under the New Tractor Scheme.     Of the 1.871 operated by Committees directly 365 were being gob ready for sale leaving 1,506 available,.     Of these 932 (or 62 per cent,) were in commission and were idle for only 2 per cent * of the tims on account of bad weather,     295 tractors were idle through lack of work. 263 were under repair and 16 were not being worked owing to labour shortage in England and Wales 6,579 acres were ploughed and 21,326 cultivated by 1,390 tractors giving an average of 4*8 acres and 15.5 acres respectively,..     The acreage dealt with shows a decrease over the previous week of 12 per cent., in the case of ploughing and 11 per cento in the case of cultivating^     The highest average acreage was again dealt with in Anglesey where 21 tractors ploughed 104 acres and cultivated 773;   average 5 and 37 acres respectively^The proposals of the Cardigan Committee to retain 17 out of 33 tractors have now been received and approved^The number of tractors to be retained by Committees is approximately 1,370 out of 4,100*Requirements and Disposal Section.During the week ended June 7th returns of sales have been forwarded by Kent, Herts, Oxon, Hereford, W.. Sussex, Worcester, Northants, Flint, Leicester, Warwick, Essex, Monmouth, Cheshire, Wilts, Somerset, Notts, Derby, Devon, Gloucester, Merioneth and Northumberland.ofThe returns show that the following have been disposed
1399 Tractors1895 Tractor ploughs1213 Miscellaneous tractor implements1604 Binders106 Mowers and reapers3450 Horse ploughs818 Drills1244 Carts and Lorries2960 Harrows and Cultivators1565 Rollers and Presses135 Potato Diggers49 Spraying machines3871 Whippletrees47 Threshing machines 433,437. 10* 7, has &quot;been realised in respect of the sale of the machinery and implements above enumerated, over  60,000 having been received during the week.Up to date 442 sales have been held for which 402 returns have been submitted, 54 further sale^s have been arranged and many others provisionally arranged.Good prices are maintained,,     Pordson Tractors still realise round about  200 and Titans from  150 to  200.     Binders, drills, carts and lorries continue to secure high figures.lor Be Section.6,180 horses have now been sold, the total amount realised being  401,870,     At York on the 5th June one horse made the record price of -200 guineas - the average for 67 horses sold at that sale being just over  100,     Other good averages were made at Nottingham where 45 horses made  81*     Grantham, 9 horses  90,     Denbigh,. 23 horses  79 and Lewes, 24 horses  78..     Arrangements are still being made in many of the counties for horses to be taken over for work on farms in the occupation of the Agricultural Executive Committees,, the price fixed being the average price obtained for horses in the countyc     These transfers are being completed   as quickly as possible,[earn Tackle Section. Tor the week ended 1st June returns have been received of work done by 257 sets of tackle and show the following results:-Ploughed 1,726 acres (6,71 acres per set).     Cultivated 31,919 acres (124.2 acres per set).     Harrowed 2,014 acres (7083 acres per set).     169 acres were, Mole Drained and 211 acres Rolled, giving a total of 36,039 Implement Acres.   (140*22 acres per set).Labour Division.Demobilisation.     The &quot;number of agriculturists demobilised during the seven days ended 4th June was 1,822, making the total number of such men released up to that date 229,120.Soldier Labour.    The number of soldiers remaining in or Id attached to Agricultural Companies at the end of the week ending 31st May was 16,080.
Women&apos; s Branch.This week the demand for the women of the Land Army is on the increase,,     Various counties were asked if they could supply a number of women in order to meet the large demand in Holland (Lines) &quot;but there was little effective response as the women are now required in their own Counties and even the promises from some Counties have had to he cancelled.Hostels are being opened at Spalding for the accommodation of the imported women in Ho].land,     Equipment is being supplied by the War Office, and the necessary staff is already appointed,.     It is hoped to open further hostels at Boston and &quot;Littleworth before the end of the months the Y,&quot;WUC,A, has undertaken to organise a Recreation Club and Light Canteen for members of.the Land Army who are to be employed in Huntingdon for flax pulling.In the Uast Riding a member of the Land Army has been appointed Milk Recorder at a salary of  140 a year.     She will work under the Livestock Officer of the County,It is reported from the Isle of Sly that an employer is lending capital to several of his women workers in order that they may take up small holdings while still in his employo     The women will work on their own land in their spare time with the help of his guidance and advice,?P3Le.k!jLJ ? ttut,cj3*   Women&apos;s Institutes have been given space for an&quot; Exhibit &quot;at the&apos; Royal Agricultural Society5 s Show at Cardiff. The exhibits will be drawn mainly from the Welsh counties, but produce is being received also from various counties in England,The Great Rollright (Oxford) Institute has arrangedm weekly collection of vegetables, fruit, honey, poultry. etc* About  6 a week is usually collected from produce which would otherwise be wasted.An Exhibition, primarily designed to emphasise the need for prevention of waste, is being held by the combined fomen&apos;s Institutes in Oxford,Ten Institutes were formed last week, making a totalof 1,102,
1 1 0 9100i PART II, - OTHER DIVISIONS.Animals Division.Swine-fever - 242 reports, 61 outbreaks. Mnthrax,    &apos; - 44 reports, 2 outbreaks. Rabies - 6 cases, 4 in Glamorgan, 1 in Devon, and 1 in Surrey;tat is, outbreaks have been confirmed in three out of the four Control Dogs Districts,    A satisfactory feature is that no case occurred itside what may be termed the dangerous area of each district.  . The uiber of reborts of suspected cases was 31.    The work in connection tli the reports and the control is still very heavy.Rats Orders. 1916-1919.On the 2nd inst, Messrs. Read and Boulenger attended a trial a rat poison at the London County Council, Horton Asylum premises, Bom.    The results will be noted as one of the series of tests sing made with a view to tabulating the relative value of various it destructives.On the 4th inst., an appeal was made to the Rats Branch by io Flax Production Branch for assistance in dealing with a plague of its at their Experimental Stations at Selby and Crowle where consider-ile damage has been sustained.    Mr. Read lias inspected the premises ; selby and given advice.The Local Authority of Hertfordshire have appointed a Rats fficer.    The following Counties have advertised for Rats Officers:-Cheshire, Lancashire, Surrey, and Kent.Veterinary Department.Swine-fever material was examined in 99 reported outbreaks.    In !swine fever was found to exist.Anthrax material was examined in 6 reported outbreaks. In 1 only vbb is disease found to exist.Anti-swine-fever serum.    1,000 c.c. were issued for distribution.Anti-abortion vaccine .    16,150 cc, (323 doses), were manufactured, it up in a suitable form, and despatched for use on infected farms. Agglutination tests of suspected blood were made in 6^stances.Miscellaneous specimens.    post mortem&apos; examinations were made on specimensT&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;   ^ ^Rabies.    During the v/eek in question 14 specimens have been famined from suspected outbreaks.ffi sher ie s Diyi s io n.Guaranteed Price for Pickled Herrings.    It is satisfactory to ecord that during the week the Cabinet, or rather, the Chancellor of to Exchequer, has reconsidered^the question of a guaranteed priced for ickled herrings, and, as a result of the urgent representations laid efore him by tho Board and the Scottish Fishery Board, has accepted to principle of a guaranteed price for all barrels remaining unsold
on the 15th September, 1910, up to a tot a],, of 400,000.     The price v/ill be such as will eliminate all margin &quot;of profit to the curers, and thus the fullest possible rate of sale before&apos;15th September v/ill not be retarded.    This decision has been communicated to the. Trade.9     ^raffi-o^pelays.,   Tho Board wexe represented at a very large Meeting of represents ives of the National Pish Association which met at the Cannon Street Hotel on the 4lb&apos;J&apos;or.e, for the purpose of passing a resolution calling upon the Go^rnment to deal with the grave delays which were occurring on the railways and between the railways and the markets, involving great loss of good food.     The resolution was carried unanimously, and it is understood that a Deputation from the Rational Fish Association v/ill be received by the Railway Executive Committee.     The Board&apos;s representative urged at the Meeting that the Association should endeavour to put up so.me definite concrete proposals for overcoming the delays in question.Fishory ?Ancalifrn.     A small Conference was held on Friday. 6th June, at which the Y,K,CA, wore asjwd to finance as an educational venture a small scheme submitted to the Board by Mr. Jar-vis a resident of Pevensey Bay, for the brm.ni.ng of about 10 demobilised soldiers v/ith a view to their taking up fishing as an occupation.     The Y.L.C .A. are considering whether this can be done, and in the meantime the Board are proceeding with their general scheme of fishery instruction, which v/ill not necessarily be confined to demobilised soldiers and sailors alone.Close Season for Oysters.     As a result of the Conference held during the week-ending 12In lay, 1919,. the Board have decided to. revoke Sea Fishing Order Ho, 5 made under the Defence of the Realm Regulations.    An Order has now been drafted which will come into operation immediately after the 14th June, b,y which a return will be made to the Status quo, as laid down by the existing Act of Parliament, viz., the Fisheries (Oyster Crab and Lobster) Act, 1877.Assistance in replacing Gear. A number of applications bydemobilised fishermen for assistance in replacing gear etc. damaged  -during their absence have bv-:en dealt with in conjunction with theMilitary Service (Civil Liabilities) Department.^ptpr^Install ations ,     The last of the long series of install atjens at Tabby has now, be? n completed.     The mechanic reports that the trial has been most successful.     The shipwrights who have been working at this port continuously for ten months are now being withdrawn.     The total number of engines installed here is ten, exclusive of two larger installations in which part of the work has been carried out elsewhere .iJSJhJ7ater^Fitsh,    The operations at the Spney Elver Depot are now over for the season and a full report on the results will be ready in a few days *     Briefly speaking, the results as compared with last year are;-Number erf Elvers applied , T.IWjZEah-      - -Cach^Peoej pt s .1918 1.35 1.215-2 000  130   3   91919 197 v   1i420,000  280   1   5From the number of elvers applied for in 191  , 150,000 should be deducted winch wen- not publicly applied for, but were taken by the Fresh Valer Fish Committee for experimental work.     The distribution may be taken, therefore, as showing a healthy expansion. Financially there v/ill be a small balance of about  7 on hand after expenses have been paid, but there are still a few trifling adjustments of a few shillings to make before the matter can be   &quot;definitely closed,o
a Intelligence Division.&apos;^    Public at ions Branch.     &quot;&quot; &quot; &quot;The number of applications for ordinary issues of the leaflets naa 345, in response to which 1,915 copies were despatched.     In addition, 16,520 copies of the leaflets were despatched to applicants for supplies in bulk for distribution.Applications were received for 301 copies of the three Bound Volumes of Leaflets, and 1,064 copies of the pamphlet &quot;How to Manage an Allotment&quot; were sent out.Ho. 45 of the &quot;Weekly Notes for Farmers&quot; was duly issued. These &quot;Notes&quot; are in increasing demand especially among v /members of &quot;Farmers&apos; Unions&quot;, and the weekly circulation is now 10,000.The usual number of enquiries bearing on agricultural matters was received from the public and from other sections of the Board together with correspondence forwarded by the attendants at the &quot;Corn Exchange Stands&quot; now under the Board1s control.Officers&apos; Training Branch. co Government Scholarships.Total applications recorded by Board   .....................   860During week   .............11Previously    ..............849Dealt with by Departmental Committee......................   825Awarded Scholarships   ............... 32To be recommended for Scholarships(in addition)    .....,..............   7Placed on Reserve Lists............ 22Refused    ............................606Outstanding for references etc......141Withdrawn by applicants............ 17Hot yet dealt with by Departmental Committee .........     35fes.idential Farm Training .Demobillsed No ^demobilisedOff i ce r s. 0 ^fleers.Total.telflS previously. fcKigK Previously.week.-----    week *-------4-Referred to 59 CountyCouncils 54 1,008 10 623 1,695 Started, and still intraining in 44 counties 65 444 - - 509 Pre1jmi nary ar rangement smade (in addition)                40          145 8          126             319Started but left training         1             2 3Refused                                       2           36 -           54             144Withdrawn                                  8           74 2           60            144Outstanding for interviews etc.     193 383                   576
1 o q100form Training,It is satisfactory to note that during the 4-J- months&quot;that this Scheme has been in effective operation over 500 &quot;officer pupils&quot; have actually heen placed in training in 44 Counties, whilst nearly 320 others have, in addition, &quot;been &quot;approved&quot; for training, and that only 3 have given up trainings     liuch credit is due to the County Council Committees and to farmers in making the Scheme a success;   County Council Committees have followed very satisfactorily the principles and machinery of local administration framed for their guidance by the Board.,    With a novel Scheme of this kind, fresh problems in connection with its administration arise almost daily.The fact that only 3 &quot;officer pupils&quot; have left their training indicates very careful selection &quot;of both candidates and farmers by County Committees, and also that Candidates who have been accepted under the Scheme are determined to adhere to agriculture as a calling,,     The fact that a candidate has been allowed himself to select for approval by the County Committee the farmer by whom he desires to be trained has undoubtedly been of great service in securing the friendly relations between pupil and farmer which are so essential to the success of the Scheme,County Committees have been asked by the Board to keep a close supervision over &quot;officer pupils&quot; whilst in training, and it will be necessary very soon for the Board to take steps to see that this is, in fact, being done0Several Committees are arranging for theoretical courses for &quot;officer pupils&quot; and one County (Leicester) has asked the Board to refund the railway fares of &quot;officer pupils&quot; attending such courses.     This request has, however, been refused,,Dependents&quot; Allowances.It has been decided, in consultation with the other Government Departments interested in the administration of the Scheme of Higher Education and Training of ex-Officers and men of like standing, that &quot;children&apos;s allowances&quot; may, under certain conditions be paid in respect of step and adopted children - equally with other children, but that the &quot;wife*s allowance&quot; cannot be paid in respect of e0g0 a widowed mother or other dependent of a candidate.General DivisiontFlax Production Branch.The absence of rain is being very severely felt by flax growers in all the Flax Centres, and dew-retting is practically at a standstill.Scutching will be commenced next weok in Fifeshire and at one or two of the new factories in Somerset,,A marked rise in the price of Linseed for crushing is P    noticeable during the last few weeks, and a good deal of seed which was unfit for sowing is being disposed of in a favourable market.Preparations are being made for an exhibit of Flax at the Royal Agricultural Society of England&apos;s Show at Cardiff.
191i t 10 /Boars *     356 &apos;70 27Bulls 728 187 28Heavy Horses 12  115 nilNumber in year Number approved Additional ended 30th in week ended sinceSept. 1918. 7th June.       1 Oct.,1918.(Societies(Members Herds Cows27 648 711 19.3821 76 82 3,00014 354 406 11,734i.lilk      t                    Number approved for Number approved inRecording ;                 year ended 30 Sept.1918. week ended 7 June.&apos;certificates            4161?     * nil(Registration            1523 nilJSrport of Stock.In week ended 7th June.13 Applications for the Export of  59 Horses were approved5 4 5 4do. do. do. do.do a 36 Cattledo. 194 Pigsdo. 44 Poultrydo. 232 SheepLlght Horas 3rg3dIng0No. registersd 1 Novembersince 918.do. do. do. do.No. registered in week ended 7 June.Registration of Stallions2,322The crop prospect s on the Hist ate continue to he satisfactory and there is nothing of importance to add to last woek&apos;s Report,    The position as to minerals has however come into some prominence.The British Sugar Beet Growers* Society bought the minerals as well as the surface rights of the Kelham Estate subject to a lease of the former to the Coal and Iron Development Syndicate, Limited, which expires in 1968, such lease providing for a minimum rent and a royalty on both coal and oil.    The Oilfields of England, Limited, of which the Syndicate is the parent Conpany. has the sub-lease of the Oil Rights and to this Company has been granted by the Minister of Munitions a licence to tore and get oil on the whole Estate under the terms of the petroleum Productism Act, 1918, but the site of any bore must be approved by the Minister of Munitions.It is proposed to ask the Minister of Munitions to consult the Board before giving approval in any case, in order that the sugar-beet interests and the oil interests may be arranged so that neither of the parties would be prejudiced.Live Stook Branch.Live Stock,Number subsidised       Total New Grants Number of Newduring year ended       or Renewals since Grants or31 Jtoch 1919. 1 April 1919. Renewalsi ......... approved inweek ended 7 Juns.
- Bo cnomi o e D1vi 6 i o n t   i\ &apos;it; 11 b t i a a 1&apos; E ran ofr .^According to the reports,, received en let June, thedry weather of May was generally favourable for ,faiming., opemtions 9   and enabled arrears cf work to he greatly reduced.    At the end of the month, however, i*ain wan badly needed for the crops.Most cf the weak&apos;s work of the Branch was of a routinenature, arkets Branch.Certificates were issued for the export qS 3 Horses and 1 Pig to Prance, 1 Horse, 26 Cattle and 6 Pigs to Argentina, and 161 Sheep to Canada4 Certificates for the export of forage to Jersey were alsc issued.    Many enquiries relating to the import regulations cf various countries wsre also dealt with.:ricultural Wages Board.An employer was prosecuted at Cranbrook, Kent, on 5th June for failing to pay the minimum wage to a worker l&amp;jr yea,rs of age, although the Orders relating thereto had been sent to him and an Inspector had informed him verbally.     A receipt for arrears duly signed by the worker but stating no sum, was sent by the employer to the,Board.   &quot;Afterwards it was ascertained this was only for a fraction of what was due.     The Defendant was fined  15 and ordered to pay  4. 7. 0* costs and the balance of arrears amounting to  1. 10. 7-g-d,     The bulk of the arrears had been paid after the summons had been served, before the hearing of the case,An employer was prosecuted at Llanilar, Cards, on 6th June.    The worker (;-?lso Secretary of a looal Branch ef the &quot;farm Labourers Union&quot; in Cardiganshire) was found on the visit of an Inspector to his employer on the   20th December, 1913, to be p.-id 24/- per week cash wages, plus board and lodging valued at 12/6 for a 7 day week of 63 hours.     The faimer refused to sign p declaration that he would comply with the Act and his conversation indicated that he was very hostile towards the Act*     The Worker stated that there was some dispute as to the wages due to him between the 9th September and the 12th November. He subsequently signed a form stating that as from the 13th November he had been paid 24/- per week in cash, together with full board for a 7 day week and lodging for 5 nights a, week, and that he received one cart load of potatoes per year.     Prior to the 13th November he had been paid    3S0 lt\ Oo per year in cash and in addition the above-mentioned advantages.     He paid his own share of Health Insurance.     His hours in summer wo3e 60 on weekdays and 2 on Sundays and in winter GO on weekdays and 3 on Sundays.     On the 3rd March he asked the Wages Board to take the matter up, pb he &quot;had not received ttie arrears of wag-js due to him.     He had been 14 years with hie pre.3cut employer and had previously received a yearling heifer every year, out tais h-d not been given last November,     iEie season his employer had treated him so badly was, he understood, because there was an agreement between his employer and tie Dth*r farmers of the district to punish him f ov having brought the Minimum Wage Act to the knowledge of his friends.,     His employer had triad to dismiss him since last Autumn but tne man who had agreod ta take his place, when he discovered the reason for t^e proposed dismissal, refused the job.     The Defendant was fined  3. ordered
to pay 3 guineas costs and arrears of wages amounting to  3.16,0.During the week 86 cases of complaint of non-payment of the minimum rates were received, the largest number from a Bingle county being 12 in the case of Essex.     Seventy-seven cases were sent to Inspectors for visit;   enquiries by correspondence were made in 222 cases; and 138 cases were completed.     Reports were received from Inspectors in 66 cases.New editions of 15/25-inch sheets were issued.The following special maps and diagrams have been prepared ar are in course of preparation for the Admiralty and War Office:-Maps for the Naval History of the War* Diagrams showing Zones of Linear Hrror. Atlas of Poland,Italy - Coast Report, Plates 4 and 6. The World - Limits of Naval Stations,1,824 special maps were despatched to various Government Departments at Home.Ordnance Survey.Secretary,,11th June, 1919,

</content>
</cab>
