<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 680-681</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IlIS DOCUMENT IS TIOS PROPERTY Of HIS BRIT AMI C M^IlllJ^mWMh)421SEC......R...I.1&apos;    / QG,To 7477.WAR CABINET.MILITARY SUPPLIES FOR SERBIA. (KnK o ran dura by the Chancellor. M, the Exchequer.)These supplies are provided at the cost of the British and French Governments.   &quot;The Treasury ask that they should now &quot;be terminated.(l)   Throughout the War Serbia has been financed by France and England jointly.   For the last 3 yeara the arrange-irient has Theen&apos; that Serbia receives the supplies required for ber Army and a cash allowance (9,000,000 fcs. a month) and the payment of the coupons of her debt.     The supplies to the Army are regulated by military conventions of February 1916 and July 1918.(2)   On grounds of fundamental financial policy the loans made to Allies &quot;for purposes arising out of the War are being brought to an end as speedily as possible.   By the end of this month these loans will have boon ended for Italy, Roumania, Greece and Belgium^     financial assistance in other forms and for other purposes is being and may continue to be provided to Serbia, but it is submitted that military loans should cease.(3)   The desire of the Army Council to continue these supplies after June 30th raises an important question of policy-The War Office officially ask that the Serbian Army be main-tained as a barrier against Bolshevism.    My information however is that the real reason why the Serbian Army is kept mobilised is very different.     Reports from Paris state that it is generally believed there that the Militarist Party in Italy has designs against the now Jugo-Slav kingdom, before that Kingdom can consolidate itself.   The Jugo-Slavs on their side wish to be in a position to maintain themselves by force of arms;   there is. also the possibility of hostilities between the Serbians and Roumanians as the result of an attempt to buy off Serbian ambitions on the Adriatic by giving them territory at the expense of Roumania.   lastly, it is currently reported that the Italians are secretly arming the Bulgarians (and also according to some accounts the Roumanians) with a view to embarrassing the SerbianPart of the above is rumour, but even though it is not all well founded, it is with a view to these considerations that future Serbian policy in the matter of tho use of its army will surely develop.Serbia  nows that its real danger is an encirclement by Italy, Roumania and Bulgaria, and they are not going to despatch their army on ventures, against Bolsheviks.In a situation so complex, I cannot see the justification for our sending military supplies to Benbleu  fa Xueme recently sent certain supplies to Roumania just as we have not yet ceased to assist Italy.     If we arm Serbia it is true that we may restore equilibrium, but it would be cheaper to arm no-one.. The proposal that we should furnish the Serbian Army with
(initialled)     A. CTEESASUBY.supplies for the purpose of keeping it molD-ili^ed axvti^-:Cru^30th would he, in my ju&amp;^j&amp;ntj ,.a mistake in itself and a dangerous precedent.   There must he some limit to the extent to which the money of the British tax-payer is need for military--vent ices in which h&amp; Uas no concern.     I would therefore propose to agree that further cash advances should he ma do between-en now and the end of the year up to 25,000,000 Francs (which is a suggestion made &quot;by M, Celier of the French Treasury), but that supplies in kind by the War Office should cease as from 30th Juner

</content>
</cab>
