<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/81/0 images: 689-689</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Hw Biitannja				Afghanistan.Following from Roos-Keppel, dated  12thFrom Viceroy, loth June 1919. (Received 14th, 11th a.m.)Clear the line. 871 S.    Secret. June:--&quot; Dera Ismail Khan district reports continuance of raiding and asks for more rifles for defence of (? villages). Matter referred separately. Bannii, Kohat and Hazara districts quiet, except Hangu sab-division some raiding. Kurram quiet. Political Agent is seeing Khoidad Khel Zaimnkt(s) jirga to-day. Peshawar city quiet; district fairly quiet. Badabher raided on two successive nights. On night of 10th instant one raider killed, six wounded. Last night raiders lost one killed and probably four wounded, two rifles captured ; villagers lost one killed, two wounded. Armoured car captured one escaping raider. Khyber quiet. Guard of armoured train brought in without ransom by elders of Kamrai A frid is. Many more letters being brought to Tirah by strange Mullah who cannot be identified. Purport of letters, (? which) Mullah states are from Amir, is that Amir still intends to carry on holy war and stories of peace negotiations have been started by (? British and) should not be believed. On the other hand Mullah Abdulla Kainbar Khel, who has just returned from Kabul, states that war is most unpopular there and that Afghans wish for peace as soon as possible. Afridis are much perplexed. Shahghassi Khwaja Muhammad Khan is touring in Niiigrahar among the tribes of the (? northern) slopes of Sufed Koh range (Mangals, Sangu Khel Shinvvaris, Kugiarhianis, &amp;c.) and is putting truce among thein and warning them to hold themselves in readiness for renewal of Jehad. He is making lists of fighting men and arms and is drawing up agreements with chiefs, to whom he is making lavish promises of honour and reward. Drought in Khyber iucreasing. All quiet north of Khyber. No fresh news from Malakand.&quot;Following from Baluchistan, dated 12th. June :  &quot; Between 8th and 1.0th enemy, comprising Wazirs, Shevannis, Mandu Khels and Abdullnua, reckoned to total 2,000, burnt good part of Sandeman bazar. Morning 10th June enemy made strong reconnaissance to test defences, intending to make grand attack that night, and were driven off by loyal militia outside perimeter and by machine guns, losing between 20 and 30. Whole enemy force held jirga that after-noon, and Wazirs, to consternation of local people, announced that they would retire, and jeered at Zhob tribesmen for thinking that they would fight Government without guns. &apos; Back of local rising seems broken, but no news of results of attack on Musa Khel.   Finnis at Gwal and Hyderzai reports all quiet up to Musafirpur.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
