<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 170-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1917.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 178.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, downing Street, S.W.,on Saturday, July 7, 1917, at 3&apos;30 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Milner, G.C.B.,G.O.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The following were also present:The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, KGGeneral Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.Field-MarshalViscouxT French of Ypres,K.P., G.C.B., O.M., G.C.V.O., K.C.M.G.,Commander-in-Chief, Home Forces.Lieutenant-General Sir D. Henderson,K.C.B., D.S.O., Director - General ofMilitary Aeronautics.The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, KG, M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., CM.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.Major-General Sir F. C. Shaw, Chief ofthe General Staff, Home Forces,Commodore G. M. Paine, C.B., M.V.O.,Fifth Sea Lord of the Admiralty.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Colonel E. D. Swinton, C.B., D.S.O., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.The Air Raid. THE War Cabinet met to consider the air raid that had takenplace on London the same morning.Field-Marshal Lord French reported that, according to suchpreliminary information as he had received, one bomb had struckthe old General Post Office. Some wooden buildings had beenstruck and the wireless telegraphy plant had been destroyed.Among other places where bombs had fallen, he mentioned CannonStreet, Tower Hill, Bermondsey, Fenchurch Street, White CrossStreet, and Walworth Road.The casualties reported up to date amounted to 26 killed and104 wounded, but these did not include casualties in the City.[1365-178]
One enemy aeroplane was claimed to have been destroyed byan airman in a Sopwith scout, but this information had not yet been checked. In addition, Commodore Paine reported that the royal naval Air Service had destroyed three German machines. no reports were yet available from Dunkirk. Two British machines were reported to have been destroyed.Lord French reported that the special squadrons temporarilylent by Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig, which had been stationednear Canterbury and at Calais, had-been withdrawn, as arranged, onthe previous day. No raid had taken place while these squadronswere in the country, except the attack on Harwich, but General SirDavid Henderson pointed out that, except on the day of the Harwichraid, there had been no flying day suitable for a long-distance raidwhile they were here. The War Cabinet felt, however, thatthe fact of an attack having been made on the day following thewithdrawal of these machines was a suspicious circumstance, whichpointed to an effective system of enemy espionage.Lord French gave the following particulars of the action ofthe aerial defence forces which he was able to dispose of: From50 to 60 machines were sent up ; these included 4 aeroplanes fromHendon, and 8 of the 12 Sopwith Scotits which had recently been allotted to him. The remaining 4 of the latter were out of actionon account of the necessary repair parts not being forthcoming.The remainder of the total employed were made up of machines of less value, and those available from the TrainingSquadrons.He pointed out that, on the withdrawal of the machines lentfrom the British Expeditionary Force, his system of defence wasa patchwork concern.The War Cabinet were of opinion that immediate steps must betaken to prevent a recurrence of these raids. Two methods ofdealing with this question were discussed namely : (1.) The maintenance   of an  efficient force of machines inEngland with which to repel attacks.(2.) Counter-attacks to be made on German towns, such asMannheim.It was suggested that the two methods were not inconsistent,provided that the necessary machines could be made available. a raid on a German town would undoubtedly provoke a retaliatoryattack, but, if additional defences had been provided, the enemy would fall into a trap.With a view to an improvement in the defence, GeneralHenderson said that a squadron, now forming and mobilising toproceed to France, could be diverted to Home Service. The wholesquadron, however, would not be available for a few weeks. Inconnection with counter-attacks, attention was drawn to the decisionon the 26th June (War Cabinet 169, Minute 3 and Appendix). Itwas recognised that the main obstacle to reprisals was the difficultyin meeting our necessities in all fields of aerial activity. The enemy had probably undertaken these raids owing to his failure to equalour aerial forces on the Western Front, in order to draw of four forces. It was essential to maintain our superiority in the field.It was also essential to provide an effective defence at home, since(as proved by our experience with Zeppelins) raids could be stopped,as effectively by destroying the enemy when he came, as by reprisals.If, when these two essentials were provided for, it was impossible tocarry out reprisals, the majority of those present considered that no attempt should be made.The War Cabinet decided that (1.) The War Office should. allot the squadron of suitablemachines now forming to home defence.
(2.) The War Office should recall two Fighting Squadronsimmediately, which should he placed at the disposal ofthe Field Marshal Commanding Home Defence, until theWar Cabinet sanction their return.(3.) The War Office should at once inform Field-marshal sir Douglas Haig that they would be glad if he couldspare enough machines to carry out an attack onMannheim ; but if he replied that this would completelydislocate his plans, then the matter should not be pressed.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 7, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
