<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 224-229</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.!Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1917.10  secret.WAR CABINET, 186.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on saturday, July 14, 1917, at 12*30 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair.)The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon ofEjedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present: The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. H. E. Duee, KG,M.P., Chief Secretary for Ireland (for minute 1).The Right Hon. Sir E. H. Carson, KG,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty (for minute 1).Professor W. G. Adams (for Minute 1).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, KGB., Secretary.Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Captain L. S. Amery, Assistant Secretary.Ireland: 1. THE Chief Secretary for Ireland recapitulated the inforina-Sinn Fein. tion contained in his memorandum (Paper G.T.-1261) (Appendix).The point on which he laid stress in that memorandum was that,since the release of the prisoners, de Valera and a small group ofSinn Fein leaders had advanced from the claim to a possiblerepresentation at the Peace Conference, to an avowed advocacy of physical force, and to taking steps which, if not dealt with, would inevitably lead to collisions with the authorities. In the three orfour days which had elapsed since the issue of that memorandumseveral incidents had occurred confirming the obvious intention ofthe Sinn Fein leaders to pursue such a policy, and de Valera haddelivered a speech in Dublin in which he had openly contemplateddirect co-operation with Germany. The Chief Secretary pointedout that there was a far larger number of young men in Ireland,owing to the cessation of emigration for the last three years, than ever before, and that practically all these were disaffected and werebeing invited to drill and arm. In his opinion the Sinn Feinleaders would either endeavour to resort to direct military force,as they did in Dublin last year, or, even without arms, overwhelm[1365-186] B
Police Barracks and Government offices of all sorts by sheer numbers.On the 11th and 12th July meetings had been held at DublinCastle, presided over by the Lord Lieutenant, at which GeneralMahon, General Byrne, and Colonel Johnson, as well as the Under-Secretary and the Irish Attorney-General, had been present. A*tthese meetings it was considered advisable that the powers of theExecutive should, after due warning, be seriously and consistentlyput into effect, and the temporary relaxation in minor matters whichhad occurred since the release of the prisoners should be terminated.The specific proposals of this Conference were (a.) That all persons inciting others to arm, drill, or organiseas a military force, should be proceeded against at once :(6.) That all cases of drilling should be dealt with by immediateprosecution by Court Martial :(c.) That the right of Police entry to meetings should be effectively enforced :(d.) That the Regulations prohibiting the wearing of uniformsand the carrying of weapons should be enforced when-ever necessary:(e.) That this stricter enforcement of the Regulations under theDefence of the Realm Act should begin after duewarning at a certain date.The Irish Attorney-General had apparently been present at only one of the Conferences, and he had since expressed to the chief secretary the opinion that the situation was not so serious as it seemed,that the measures recommended should be cautiously proceeded with, and that there should not be an embarking upon prosecutionsat large. He had also advocated more drastic dealing wirh the.Sinn Fein newspapers.The Chief Secretary asked for the guidance of the War Cabinetin dealing with the situation. He considered that he had sufficientpowers under the Defence of the Realm Regulations to break up, or at any rate destroy, the efficiency of the Sinn Fein organisation, byprohibiting its meetings, by taking possession of the premises used as Sinn Fein Clubs, by authorising the Military to take possessionof the printing press, and to stop the publication of any newspaperswhich published seditious speeches, and, if necessary, also arrestingand trying leaders, like de Valera, for their speeches.The War Cabinet considered what would be the effect of such proceedings on the prospects of the Convention, which is to open onthe 25th July. There was the hope that the Convention might havethe effect of bringing about the existence of a new central party of moderate men in Ireland, united in opposition to the lawless andrevolutionary propaganda of the Sinn Feiners. If anything were done before the Convention met which would force theNationalist members in the House of Commons to take up a lineof defence of the Sinn Feiners, which would preclude thiscoalescence of moderate opinion in the Convention, and possiblywreck the Convention itself, it would be a great misfortune. It was argued that it might be desirable, if possible, to carry on without anyovert incidents before the Convention met. On the other hand, itwas pointed out that the whole object of the Sinn Feiners was towreck the Convention, that they would try to provoke incidents, ifnot before the Convention met, then after it had met, and that the argument for postponing grappling with the situation would then be repeated on the ground that the Convention had not had time tosettle down.Sir Edward Carson argued that the worst possible policy wasone of pin-pricks, i.e., of sporadic acts of firmness which did notform part of a consistent policy applied to the whole of Ireland. Forexample, it was no use arresting de Valera unless the Governmentwere prepared to arrest every other speaker who made similarseditious speeches, and to maintain the arrests in face of any agitation in Ireland or the House of Commons.   In his opinion, two things
were essential: firstly,that the Sinn Feiners should not he in a posi-tion to secure arms or ammunition; and, secondly, that an effectiveSecret Service should be established in Ireland in order to anticipate the movements of the conspirators.With these views the War Cabinet were in general agreement,the Chief Secretary more particularly dwelling on the inadequacy ofthe present Secret Service arrangements and the difficulty of securinguseful agents.With regard to the general situation, the War Cabinet werein agreement that it was undesirable to provoke incidents byprosecuting de Valera or others for their speeches, but that it wasimpossible to allow overt acts of defiance of the law, which might now be suppressed by the exercise of a moderate display of force, todevelop into serious sedition which could only be dealt with by large forces and at a cost of bloodshed. It was felt that, while itwas difficult to define what constituted &quot; overt acts&quot; in general terms, the Administration should have no difficulty in deciding, inparticular instances, whether the intention was to defy the law or tobuild up a revolutionary organisation. Generally speaking, theWar Cabinet considered that prosecutions should, as far as possible,be avoided, where direct measures in the nature of preventive police or military action could take their place, although they realised that in certain cases a prosecution before two Magistrates mightbe preferable to a Court-Martial, whose nature was largelymisunderstood.The War Cabinet authorised the Chief Secretary for Ireland totake the following action : (a.) To put a stop, by police action, to marching or drillingmen in military formation, and to the wearing of uniformwhere it was obviously used iu connection with activesteps in revolutionary organisation.(6.) To enforce the existing Regulations under which specialpermission might be required for the conduct ofprocessions.(c.) Without interfering with the right of public meetingsgenerally, to stop public meetings w7here there were grounds of public safety, or of expediency, e.g., the interruption of traffic in a main thoroughfare, or aprobable breach of the peace, for doing so.(d.) To stop the printing of seditious matter by seizing the printing press of the journals concerned, and suppressingthem, if necessary, for the rest of the War.(e.) While not prosecuting speakers for general seditioussentiments, to take prompt action against any directincitements to violence against the Police or theAuthorities.(/.) To take possession of premises which were likely to beused for drilling or other illegal purposes.The War Cabinet considered that there was no necessity toissue any sort of warning with regard to the enforcement of these measures, but laid stress on the importance ofample police force always being present if any action were taken ; and on the importance of protecting and backingup the police in the execution of their duty.mesopotamia commission:Disciplinary action.2. The War Cabinet again briefly considered this question, and decided To adjourn the discussion until their next meeting.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.July 14, 1917.[1365-186]B2
APPENDIX.G.T.-1261. --Situation in Ireland.Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland.(Circulated with reference to War Cabinet 173, Minute 24.)1. I PROCEED as desired by the War Cabinet to deal with the letter ofSir Bryan Mahon dated the 25th June, 1917, on the question of public order in Ireland,and the covering letter of Lord French dated the 29th June, 1917.2. There is beyond doubt reason for great vigilance in dealing with the irish situation. That any definite change of method is required is not apparent to me. Norhas anyone yet suggested any change of method which would in my opinion be prudentor effective.   I will state my view of the recent facts and present position.3. The assembling of multitudes of people to welcome or to see the releasedprisoners was in inevitable result of the release, and of course produced politicalexcitement. The decision not to attempt &quot; to prevent these assemblies&quot; wasdeliberately taken. Looking back 1 think it was a right decision. The occasion wasavowedly one of amnesty. To have attempted to suppress demonstrations such as tookplace in Dublin would have resulted in violence and probably in bloodshed. Noresponsible person has yet suggested to me that it would have been a wise course,either in Dublin or elsewhere.4. Sir Bryan Mahon is right in saying there were in places displays of disloyaltyand of a spirit of insurrection. Certain incidents of molestation of small parties oftroops in Dublin and of the marching of bodies of men and display of Irish Volunteeruniforms also sprung up at the same time, and they gave cause for careful policearrangements, which I discussed with the police authorities when the incidentswere reported.5. I assume that Dublin and Cork are particularly referred to in the reference todisloyalty and a spirit of insurrection. The incidents in question in Dublin occurredabout a fortnight ago, and in Cork nine or ten days ago. The Chief Commissioner ofthe Dublin Police reported to me this morning &quot; there was no disturbance of public order in Dublin last week.&quot; From Cork I was informed yesterday that, at the end ofthe week in which disorders occurred, the extra police who had been brought to thecity were returned to their homes.6. The molestation of soldiers in Dublin has, I think, ceased. The ChiefCommissioner reported to-day that there had been no complaints in the past week.7. The risks involved in open-air meetings and in the systematic marching about -of men, whether in regular formations or otherwise, I discussed with Sir Bryan Mahon,the Deputy Inspector-General Royal Irish Constabulary, and the Chief Commissioner,when I was last in Dublin, and the matter was fresh, and, in view of possibleeventualities, I had drafts prepared on my return to London of &apos;amended Defence ofthe Realm Regulations to enable the Executive to deal with such demonstrations.These were adopted, and are in operation. In [case of need, the things in questioncan now be prohibited by the competent military authority.8. Two illustrations occur to me of the difficulty of deciding as to repressiveaction as to the prisoners. One of the ablest and most trusted of the Irish roman catholic Bishops said to me to-day, with regard to the released prisoners &quot; They would do the Government much more harm in prison than they can now they are at liberty.&quot;As to meetings, on Sunday evening last an immense open-air meeting to protest against the Convention and the &quot; Partition of Ireland &quot; was held in Phoenix Park.So far as I know no one thought of prohibiting it, and there was no disturbance of thepeace. I believe that a prohibition of this meeting would have produced scenes of disorder far worse than any which have occurred in Dublin since the rebellion.9. Outside of Dublin and Cork the release of the prisoners has, 1 believe, notbeen the occasion of serious disturbances. The reports of the Royal irish constabulary, which I have carefully read, showed in the rural districts a generalabsence of violence or of disorder which needed severe means of repression. Therewas, of course, excitement, and there were, in places, rebel cries and songs. This isno novelty.
10. Before considering the question of some possible change of methods, I mustrefer to the statement in Sir B. Mahon&apos;s letter that &quot; the chief factors in the organisationof the last rebellion were the unrestricted meetings that were allowed to take place.&quot;Neither Sir Bryan nor I was, I think, in Ireland during the rebellion. But all theevidence I have *been convinces me that the true cause of the rebellion was the toleratedexistence in Ireland for many months of armed and disciplined forces of Volunteers,whose leaders were able to launch them into belligerent action against the Governmentwhenever they thought fit to do so. These forces no longer exist, and unless they are permitted to revive I cannot see what serious insurrectionary movement is possible in face of an armed Constabulary of nearly 10,000 men and a military force such as thatwhich is now in occupation of the country.11. The question for immediate consideration at this time seems to me to be whether the Executive should issue a general prohibition of (a) Meetings, and(b) Processions,as well as a prohibition of such things as(c) The marching of men carrying hurley clubs a dangerous practice and of(d) The wearing of the Irish Volunteer uniform.I think (c) and (d) should be prohibited. I framed the new regulations in orderthat they might be. And being prohibited, they must at all costs be prevented. Ageneral prohibition of meetings and processions would I think be mischievous andprobably impossible of enforcement. At this moment, the Orange Lodges of Ulsterare claiming to hold their usual processions, and the prevalent opinion of the CountyInspectors of Royal Irish Constabulary is, as I gather, that it would be unwise to forbid them.12. Heretofore the course pursued since I became Chief Secretary has been todeal with acts of lawlessness when they occurred, and only to prohibit by generalprohibition things which must be and can be prevented, as for example, drilling. Iam opposed to any coercive action except that of which experience from day to dayshows the necessity and affords the justification. An attempt to suppress the merevexatious incidents of disaffection among a population of which a considerable section is notoriously disaffected will produce no good and would exasperate moderate Lishopinion.13. Lord Frenches letter takes, in my view, a rather alarmist view of the situation.&quot;Disturbances&quot; we must face in Ireland and deal with. &quot;Disturbance&quot; in theinsurrectionary sense, which calls for military action is no doubt talked of a great deal,but in my judgment is no more likely as a serious happening that it was a year ago.There is at this time in Ireland, as I believe, a large measure of active support for theGovernment among the Nationalist popvdation. This support I desire to justify and increase. It would certainly be alienated by any general scheme of coercion whichwas not plainly caRed for by previous dangerous action of the malcontents.14. I observe in Lord French&apos;s letter a suggestion that &quot; the hands of the GeneralOfficer Commanding in Ireland require strengthening.&quot; I shall be glad to know whatis this reinforcement which is desired. The existing powers of the Defence of the realm Regulations are enormous, and, I think, ample. The ordy restraint is that thecompetent military authority must necessarily be subject to some control of the civilExecutive that is, of His Majesty&apos;s Government. Under our Constitution that seemsto me inevitable.15. I ought to add, perhaps, that Lcannot recall any case at the moment in whicha recommendation of the Commander-in-Chief in Ireland as to specific action which ought, in his judgment, to be taken, has been overruled by civil authority.(Initialled) H. E. D.Julij 3, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
