<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 252-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
seciJi f \ farWAR CABINET, 191.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onFriday, July 20, 1917, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl curzon oe   The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M. P.^Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.        Thg Right Honj A- BoxAR LaW; m.p the Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,   Lieutenant-General the Right Hon J. C.G.C.B., G.C.M.G. Smuts, K.C.The following were also present : The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, K.C.B.,First Lord of the Admiralty.Admiral Sin J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., CM.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.Rear-Admiral A. L. Duff, C.B., assistant chief of the Naval Staff (for Minutes 1and 2).Captain R. Webb, R.N., Admiralty (for minutes 1 and 2).Captain Fisher, R.N., Admiralty (for minutes 1 and 2).Commander Henderson, R.N., Admiralty(for Minutes 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Shipping Controller (for Minutes 1and 2).Sir Leo G. Chiozza Money, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Shipping(for Minutes 1 and 2).The Lord Inchcape, G.C.M.G., K.C.S.I.,K.C.I.E. (for Minutes 1 and 2).Sir J. Ellerman, Bart, (for Minutes 1and 2).Sir Norman Hill (for Minutes 1 and 2).Mr. Joseph Davies (for Minutes 1 and 2).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary,[1365-191]Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1917.
Shipping Losses: 1. IN continuation of War Cabinet 183, Minute 2, and WarControl of Cabinet 184, Minute 1, the War Cabinet took into further con-Merchant sideration the points referred to therein.Shipping.  q regard to the question of cutting down the number ofmerchant ships employed, with a view to creating a reserve, theShipping Controller stated that, in view of the facts that (a) thedemand from the several departments was 600,000 tons per moath inexcess of the supply, and (6) we must bxvild up as soon as possiblereserves of cereals, ore, and oil, supply coal to Italy, and meet theRussian programme within the next three months, he did notconsider it practicable to cut down shipping.The War Cabinet approved this policy.With regard to the question of the redistribution of anti-submarine craft, Sir Norman Hill pointed out that the system he wished to advocate for the consideration of the War Cabinet wasthat only such ships should be employed as could be assured a fairmeasure of protection, and that the areas of concentration shouldbe abandoned. He pointed out that the adoption of a convoysj^stem must necessarily bring down imports, as it would result in less trips being made, but at the same time the ships would standa far better chance of not being sunk.As regards the question of what protection the admiralty could afford, the First Sea Lord referred to the paper he had written on the Destroyer Situation (Paper G.T.-.1408), in which he pointed out that the only three sources from which destroyers wereavailable were the Dover and Harwich forces, and the destroyersallotted to the Grand Fleet, and that the majority of the latter were already carrying out, in one form or another, trade protection.Further, that practically all other seaworthy destroyers were engagedin protecting commerce or troop transport.The question of using trawlers as convoying vessels was raised,and the Admiralty representatives pointed out that, though every endeavour was made in this respect with a view to selecting andregrouping the best trawlers for this purpose, any trawler convoy,on account of its slow speed, could not be as efficient as destroyers.With regard to convoys of this nature, i.e., convoys having a speed of only 7 knots, Rear-Admiral Duff mentioned that it was quiteconceivable that if attacked by submarines the convoy mightsustain a loss of three or four ships. It was added that the trawlerswould have to be provided with Naval Officers in command, as theirskippers are not in all respects qualified to take on convoying duties.With reference to any economy in the. strength of the convoys,the Admiralty held the view that, apart from reserves, 8 destroyersor 12 trawlers were required for a convoy of 20 merchant ships. If,in the case of a destroyer convoy, the number was reduced to 6, itwas considered that such would be an inadequate screen. TheAdmiralty informed the War Cabinet that a new system was nowbeing adopted, inasmuch as, when possible, three salvage tugsescorted each convoy through the danger zone, and were stationedastern, for the double purpose . of keeping off attacks from that quarter, towing disabled vessels, and rescuing the crews in case ofdisaster.Sir Norman Hill pointed out that the mercantile marine were strongly against any increase in the size of convoys, and that theview was prevalent amongst merchant captains that at an early dateslow boats would have to stop running unless convoys were providedfor them. As regards the faster craft of 14 knots and over, he strongly advocated that they should carry a gun forward as well asaft ; but it was pointed out by the Admiralty that a gun in the bowswas practically useless ; further, that all available sources had beentapped with a view to providing for the arming of merchantmen,and that the situation had vastly improved during the last sixmonths. Moreover, when all the merchant-ships were armed with one gun each at present there are some 16 per cent, still unarmed
Daily Bulletins. 2. Sir Norman Hill said that shipowners generally woidd beglad if they might be kept in closer touch with the new experiments in regard to submarine warfare which were being put into practice by the Admiralty. He suggested that daily bulletins, explaining the nature of the attacks and their results, should be sent to theAdmiralty Intelligence Officers at each port, and that these bulletinsshould be seen by the Marine Superintendents of the lines approvedby the Admiralty. Sir Norman Hill recognised the admirable work that had been done by the Chatham School. The ShippingController concurred in this view, and urged the further extensionof such schools, in order to bring the Admiralty and mercantileofficers in closer touch.[1365-191] it would be better, before putting two guns on each, ship, toreplace the small guns already on hoard some of the ships byweapons with longer range and greater powers of penetration.Admiral Duff proceeded to state the situation as regards thenumber of convoys. The Admiralty hoped shortly to have eightconvoys every eight days, and added that four of such convoys were now in steady running. It was proposed to utilise trawlers for the gibraltar convoy, which required an anti-submarine escort at eachend of the voyage, and it was hoped in the near future they wouldbe able to work up to two convoys per week from that port. Asregards the other two convoys, namely, one from Dakar and one fromthe United States of America, the Admiralty did not at present see their way to institute them, but by the end of August they hopedthere would be seven convoys working, bringing in a matter offrom 120 to 130 ships a week.It was stated that it was not at present practicable to provideconvoys for out-going ships. Owing to the better means of control thatprevailed in their case, it was possible to hold up the sailings as might be found requisite and despatch them in groups on routeswhich were known to be fairly free from enemy submarines, thusrendering tbe merchant ships less liable to attack.Sir John Jellicoe referred to the difficulty that was beingencountered at present in obtaining sufficient cruisers to bring theseveral convoys from the port of departure to the point in the more dangerous areas where they were picked up by the destroyerconvoys.The question was then raised as to whether it would bedesirable (a.) To have an adequate convoy for half the ships and noprotection for the remainder ; or(b.) To have an inadequate protection for the whole number.Commander Henderson, whose opinion was invited, stated thatin his view it was a matter which could only be proved by an extended trial, but that he personally thought (b) was the better course ; the fact that vessels were under control capable of being diverted by secret code was in itself a measure of protection.Sir Norman Hill stated that he would prefer that only the ships that could be adequately protected should be employed, and that theremainder should be laid up. The War Cabinet decided, however,that such a course of laying up half the ships was out of thequestion, and therefore the policy of providing as strong a force,either as convoy or patrol, as circumstances admitted should be pursued.Sir Leo Chiozza Money pointed out that if fewer ships were used in other than the North Atlantic route, the Admiralty might heable to bring more protection to bear upon the Atlantic convoys.
The War Cabinet decided that (a.) Some action, on the lines indicated by Sir Norman Hill,as regards daily bulletins, should be taken by theAdmiralty.(6.) Closer relations, in the form of Shipping Liaison Officers,should be instituted between the Admiralty and the mercantile Marine.It was pointed out that the Admiralty appeared to be grapplingmore successfully with the submarine situation at an earlier datethan they had anticipated, and the War Cabinet expressed the hopethat the Board would continue to impress on all Naval officers concerned the need of the closest co-operation between the navy and the Mercantile Marine, and of the adoption of a sympatheticattitude by such Naval officers with regard to the difficulties experienced by the Merchant Service in carrying out their duties tothe country.Ministry of Food: 3. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theStaff and &apos;  Food Controller (Paper G.T.-1377), and a letter from the FoodAccommodation.       Controller to the Prime Minister (Appendix), dealing with theBtaffing and organisation of the Department (a.) While recognising the great importance of an adequatestaff in the Ministry of Food, the War Cabinet found itimpossible, having regard to the vital war interests ofother Departments, to sanction the proposal that men should be surrendered to the Ministry of Food to the detriment of work of first-class importance in otherDepartments. They instructed the Secretary, however,to invite the favourable consideration by all Depart-ments of applications from Lord Rhondda for assistancein the development of his staff.(6.) The&apos; War Cabinet authorised an expenditure up to amaximum of 200,000L on local office staff and accommoda-tion by the Ministry of Food, subject to the approval ofthe Chancellor of the Exchequer.UnemploymentInsurance:proposed extension.4. The Memorandum on the Extension of UnemploymentInsurance, proposed by the Ministry of Labour (Paper G.T.-1429),was referred to the Chancellor of the Exchequer and Mr. Barnes for decision.Labour Disputes.5. The Memoranda on Labour disputes, by the Controller ofCoal Mines (Paper G.T.-1443), and Sir George Askwith (paper g.T.-1444), were referred to Lord Milner and Mr. Barnes for decision.-Norway. 6. In reference to War Cabinet 16S, Minute 13, and WarCabinet 173, Minute 10, the War Cabinet decided to appoint asmall Committee, consisting of Sir Edward Carson (Chairman) andGeneral Smuts,With representatives of the Admiralty, War Office,and Foreign Office,Colonel Swinton (Secretary),to investigate the position of Norway and other northernneutral countries in relation to the war, and to obtain from our Naval and Military Staffs full information as to their plans.
Man-Power:Men Employed inthe Admiralty.Trade War. 8. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum on TradeWar by the Foreign Trade Department of the Ministry of Blockade(Paper G.T.-1447), advocating the development of the policy under-lying the Statutory List and the taking of measures during the war to exploit the alarm already manifested by Germany at the idea of post helium trade war.The War Cabinet, while unwilling without further examinationto assent to the policy recommended in this document, approvedthat the Memorandum shoidd be sent to the British Ambassador atWashington.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 20, 1917.* This latter decision was actually taken in. the afternoon, but it is more convenient to group it with the morning&apos;s Minutes.7. In the absence of the Secretary of State for War, theSecretary, drew attention to a proposal that had been made at aConference on Man-power held .on the previous afternoon at10, Downing Street, that the Admiralty should furnish periodicalfigures as to the number of men in the -Navy on similar lines to the periodical statements furnished to the War Cabinet by the WarOffice.The First Lord of the Admiralty undertook to consider thisproposal and to report to the War Cabinet.It was further agreed that The Secretary of State for War should be asked to communicate to the First Lord of the Admiralty the form in which his statement should be-made, in order to compare with theArmy States.*
APPENDIX.Ministry of Food,My dear Prime Minister, Grosvenor House, W., July 20, 1917.IT is essential, if I am to set up the machinery for limiting food prices in timeto satisfy public opinion, that I should, within reasonable limits, be given a free*handin regard to expenditure.I propose, as I mentioned to you yesterday at Cabinet, to ask the local authorities throughout the country to help me, not only in regulating the distribution of sugar andother commodities, but to apply and enforce within their districts the control of allmiddlemen&apos;s profits between the producer and the consumer.I am satisfied that this can be done effectively, but it entails the establishment ofa vast organisation, and I cannot undertake it unless I am free to get the best men Ican for the work and to authorise such expenditure as may he necessary for theestablishment of the district offices.-r I have therefore asked the Chancellor of the Exchequer to authorise me, within a limit of say 200,OOOL, to engage such staff and office accommodation as may benecessary and to fix, without having to refer to the Treasury in each case, the scales of pay within the limits laid down for the Local Government Board^and other GovernmentDepartments of the. first class.The Chancellor will not withhold his consent to this proposal provided that youconcur, and in order that there may be no further delay I should be glad to have a brief note from you saying that you share my view.Yours sincerely,RHONDDA.

</content>
</cab>
