<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 304-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1917.SECRET.8tWAR CABINET, 200.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on tuesday, Jidy 31, 1917, at 11*30 a.m.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.L, G.G1.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Lieutenant-General    the    Right    Hon.J. C. Smuts, K.C.The following were also present : The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M., M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, KG.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar.General Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,KC.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.Lieutenant-General Str C. F. N. Macready,K.C.B., KC.M.G., Adjutant-General tothe Forces (for Minutes 1, 2, 3, and 4).Major-General H. A. L. Tagart, C.B.,D.S.O., Home Forces (for Minutes 1and 2).The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, K.C.B.,First Lord of the Admiralty.Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., O.M.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 1, 2,and 3).The Right Hon. John Hodge, M.P.,Minister for Labour (for Minutes 1, 2,and 3).Mr. H. W. Forster, M.P., FinancialSecretary, War Office (for Minutes 4and 5.)Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary,Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary,[1363-200]B
Soldiers&apos;and 1. THE War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theWorkmen&apos;s Adjutant-General, and submitted by the Secretary of State for War,Committees. on        formation of Soldiers&apos; and Workmen&apos;s Committees and theposition of Army Reserve munition workers and soldiers lent tomunition works.The representatives of the War Office explained that, largelyunder the influence of what had taken place in Russia, efforts werebeing made to induce soldiers to interest themselves actively in political agitation of a character likely to weaken the discipline ofthe Army. Cases had already occurred where meetings had beenconvened and addressed by soldiers, but, as there were grounds for thinking that the instigators were not -fully cognisant of theKing&apos;s Regulations, the offenders had been dealt with leniently.The relevant Regulation was that contained in No. &apos;451, which reads as follows : &quot;An officer or soldier is forbidden to institute, or take part in, any meetings, demonstrations, or processions, for party or political purposes, in barracks, quarters, camps, or theirvicinity. Under no circumstances whatever will he attend such meetings, wherever held, in uniform.&quot;The question was raised whether a soldier was free to stand asa Parliamentary candidate, and it was explained that, with the permission of his Commanding Officer, he could apply to the ArmyCouncil to waive the King&apos;s Regulations in the particular circum-stances, and this power applied to officers and privates alike.Reference was also made to the disturbances which had takenplace on the 28th July in connection with the breaking up of ameeting at the Brotherhood Church, Southgate, in which somesoldiers were alleged to have participated. Such disturbances, itwas pointed out, fell to be dealt with by the Home Secretary andnot by the Army Council, as they were breaches of the Civil Law.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) Soldiers could not be permitted  to join Soldiers&apos; and workmen&apos;s Councils; &apos;(b.) The King&apos;s Regulations must be strictly and impartiallyenforced ;(c.) The Secretary of State for War should arrange that public attention should be called by a question in Parliamentto the disturbances on the 28th July, and an announce-ment made that the Government intended to enforceCivil and Military Law regardless of whether the meetings were likely to be for or against the Govern-departments war policy.In reaching these decisions, the War Cabinet did not ovelook the fact that they would have to enforce their policy in all circumstances.Soldiers at 2. The War Cabinet considered, further, the special cases of munition Works.      Army Munition Workers and soldiers lent to Munition Works, whoare liable to be recalled to the Colours if they join in a strike andcease work.It was stated that some 22,000 were, actually soldiers in uniform; members of the Reserve were regarded as practicallycivilians. The arrangements at present in force are that, in the caseof a strike where the soldiers were likely to be molested, they would be withdrawn for protection to certain camps. Secret labour meetingswere being held in some centres, and resolutions were being adoptedpledging the men, in the case of a strike and the withdrawal of thesoldiers, to remain out on strike until the soldiers were returned.
Recently, during disputes at Barrow and Liverpool, efforts weremade, but only with small, success, to induce the soldiers to join with the,strikers..- These strikes were riot authorised by the union executives, but were organised locally.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) In the case of a properly authorised strike it was important to withdraw the soldiers from the district for their ownprotection, and also in view of pledges given by ministers that soldiers should not be used for purposes of intimidate-tion.(6 ) In the case of unauthorised strikes i e., those initiatedwithout the consent of the Trades Union Executiveconcerned soldiers joining with the strikers should be recalled to the colours.3. The War Cabinet decided that The secretary should arrange for the distribution of the weekly report of the Ministry of Labour in full, and of any specialreports from other departments throwing light on thelabour situation in the country.Ministry ofLabour:Weekly Eeport.Army Pay. 4. With reference to War Cabinet 198, Minute 11, the WarCabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of State forWar on the question of granting increases of pay to soldiers in HisMajesty&apos;s army (Paper G.T.- 15G2).Lord Derby explained that pressure was being brought by theGeneral Federation of Trades Unions on members of the House ofCommons with the object of raising the minimum pay of the privatesoldier to 3s. a day. This did not imply an addition of 2s, to everysoldier, but it aimed at bringing the lowest pay up to 3s. It was estimated that such a scheme would involve the country in anincreased expenditure of 120 millions per annum on the presentarmy strength.The War Cabinet was favourably disposed to some improvementbeing made in existing scales, and that, if possible, there should bespecial recognition of men who had served long periods at the front,but it was realised that differentiation, on the basis of length ofservice or character of service, or other similar test, was not easy.The War Cabinet decided to ask the following Committee Sir Edward Carson (Chairman),Mr. Stanley Baldwin, M.P. (Treasury),Mr. H. W. Forster, M.P., and a military representative(War Office),Dr. Macnamara (Admiralty),Mr. G. H. Roberts, M.P. (Board of Trade),Mr. T. Jones (Secretary),to consider the whole problem of an increase in the pay ofsoldiers and sailors, and report.5r- The Financial Secretary to the War Office informed the WarCabinet that he had gone to Bradford recently to investigate thesituation as regards the supply and distribution of wool.Mr. Forster undertook to submit to the War Cabinet, throughthe Secretary of State for War, a report on the subject atan early date.[1365-200]
The Western 6. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff read a communiqueFront. from  the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief in France, which stated that at 3&quot;15 A.M. that morning the offensive had been resumedby the forces under his command to the north-west of Ypres and north of the Yser. General Robertson stated that there were three*immediate objectives, which embraced a front of about 15 milesand a depth of about 2\ miles. Up to the time of the despatchof the communique the attack was progressing successfully, and thefirst objective had been achieved. French troops were co-operating in the attack. General Robertson explained, and demonstrated ona map, the nature and extent of the present undertaking.Eoumania. 7. Reference was  made   to   an   official communique by theRoumanian Commander-in-Chief regarding the offensive on theSouthern Front, and stated that so far 80 enemy guns had been captured.Russia. 8. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that he hadreceived a report from the Russian&quot; Commander-in-Chief describing the continued deterioration in the moral of the Russian Armies.He hoped to be able to make a stand on the line which was held byGeneral BrusilofFs Army before the latter made his big attack in19 lti. If they could not hold that line, the Russian and Roumanianforces to the south would be in danger of being outflanked. TheRussian Commander-in-Chief concluded his telegram with a strongappeal to the British Government to conduct at once a vigorousoffensive on the Western Front, in order to compel the germans to withdraw as many Divisions as possible from the East. general robertson said that, in his reply, he was urging the RussianCommander-in-Chief to use his utmost endeavours to arrest the retirement beyond the 1916 line. -The Chief of the Imperial General Staff read a telegram(No. 1166) from Major Neilson, which stated that a War Council,attended by Prime Minister Kerensky and several of the mostprominent military Commanders in Russia, revealed a considerable and serious vacillation in regard to the re-enforcement of discipline.Reference was also made to General Knox&apos;s despatch (B 3), datedthe 10th July, 1917 (Paper G.T.-1553), indicating the extent towhich indiscipline prevailed almost throughout the Russian Army,and the collapse of moral generally. Particular attention was drawn to a statement which had appeared in several Russian papers, thatGeneral Klembovski, Commander-in-Chief of the Northern Front,was reported to have said that the present offensive was all-important,as a winter campaign was impossible, and all the combatants would soon begin negotiating for peace.Bombino- Raid. 9- The First Sea Lord reported that a bombing raid was carriedout on the night of the 28th/29th on the rolling-stock in the navalareas of Thourout, Middelkerke, and Ghisteiles, and also on theBruges Osie Works.   All our machines returned safely.Submarines.10. The First Sea Lord stated that the Senior Naval Officer,Gibraltar, had communicated a report from torpedo-boat 90 to theeffect that she had attacked, and, she hoped, damaged, an enemy submarine with a depth charge, 6 miles south-south-west of CapeSpartel.
International 11. The First Sea Lord stated that he had been informed by naval Conference. Admiral Sims that the latter had received a telegram from theUnited States Government to the effect that, in order to take partin an International Naval Conference, which they considered shouldbe held, Admiral Sims and Admiral Mayo, the Commander-in-chiefoif the United States Atlantic Fleet, had been deputed by theGovernment at Washington to attend as their naval representatives.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 31, 1917.o

</content>
</cab>
