<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 394-397</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1917.SKOitET.80WAR CABINET, 215.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Wednesday, August 15, 19 L7, at 11*30 a.m.The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Lieutenant - General   the   Right   Hon.J. C. Smuts, K.C.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, CM.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,K.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar.The Right Hon. Sir Eric Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.Admiral Sir j. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., O.M.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.General Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.Major-General W. T. Furse, C.B., D.S.O.,Master-General of the Ordnance.Major-General Sir C. E. Callwell, K.G.B.Major-General F. C. Poole, C.M.G., D.S.O.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions.The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Shipping controller.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Threatened 1. THE Secretary of State for War reported  that Sir H.Railway Strike. Walker, the Chairman of the Railway Executive Committee, had informed him that, as a result of the railway dispute, theGovernment must be prepared for the possibility of a railway strike involving the stoppage of 75 per cent, of the trains. Thestrike would probably break out on Monday next, and might possibly be precipitated on Friday. He therefore raised thequestion as to whether, in view of the danger of the enemy taking[1365-215]
advantage of the disorganisation caused by the strike to make a raid upon the coast, the War Office ought not to recall forthwitha large number of the men lent for the harvest to the TransportWorkers&apos; Battalions, and other non-military occupations, in orderto fill up the units of the Home Army, as well as to stop anyfurther men leaving their units for the purpose of harvest work.After hearing the views of the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff, the War Cabinet decided, To take the risk of a raid, and not to interfere with thecurrent arrangements regarding the men being lent to agriculture.March-past of 2. The War Cabinet adjourned temporarily to witness theAmerican Troops.     march-past  of the American troops,  and  the  War cabinet authorised The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to send thefollowing message to his Excellency the american ambassador : &quot; The War Cabinet, who have just witnessed the march-past of four thousand five hundred U.S.A.troops, desire to express their admiration of themagnificent sight, and their deep gratification at thisstriking symbol of American resolve and Americanpower.&quot;Supply of Heavy 3. On re-assembling, the War Cabinet again considered the artillery to Eussia.   question of the supply  of  guns  to Russia (War Cabinet 214,Minute 4).General Poole pointed out that 80 per cent, of the Russianpeople were anxious for immediate jDeace, and that M. Kerenskyhad only a small minority behind him who were in favour of standing by the Allies, and that this minority depended to a verylarge degree upon the help and assistance of every kind which theAllies, particularly Great Britain and France, could now render them, not merely morally but materially. The continuedshipment of guns was regarded by the Russian Government as theall-important symbol of continued assistance. Wre had sent noguns from this country (other than the Midvale Howitzers fromthe United States, which were a Russian order paid for by theRussians subject to guarantee by the British Treasury, only the ammunition, sights, etc., for them being supplied by thiscountry) since last March. He recommended that some gunsshould be sent immediately, and at an)^ rate before the Archangelshipping season closed. The Archangel railway was now workingvery well, and no guns were being held up at Archangel. he admitted that these guns could not be used in the line this year,but the moral effect of sending some of the guns that we had promised them would be as good as the continued refusal to sendguns would be bad, if not disastrous.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff regretted that he feftcompelled to oppose the sending of any more heavy guns to Russia,and stated that of the 156 big guns already sent only 54 had beenin action to date. He added that he had recently diverted from france 6 batteries for Italy, 6 for Egypt, and 2 for Mesopotamia,and in his opinion it was vital that no more diversions should bemade from the decisive Western front.General Furse supported this view, and stated that Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig wanted every gun he could get forimmediate use. We were deficient by 190 guns of the properestablishment of 18-prs., and the 6-in. Howitzers for which russia was asking could be, and were being, most effectively used in
for the Seventeen Weeks ending July 29, 1917-	Estimated wastage.	Actual wastage.	Output of new and repaired guns.6-inch Howitzers 6-inch Guns 8-inch Howitzers 9-2-inch    ,,	547 77 136 102	142 50 41 27	456 46 186 75The corresponding figures for the last week of this period, when the offensive was going on in Flanders, w*ere as follows: i				Estimated wastage.	Actual wastage.	Output of new and repaired guns.6-inch Howitzers 6-inch Guns 8-inch Howitzers 9-2-inch , ,.	54 7 12 10	12 1 6 2	27 6 16 the also pointed out that it was only proposed to send 1,000rounds of ammunition with each gun to Russia, and that inFrance to-day the number of guns exceeded the ammunitionavailable for expenditure by those guns at the present rate ofexpenditure.   In the week ending the 29th July, no less than* After reading the draft Minutes the M.G.O. states that he can trace no corro-boration of these tables of figures.France for the work which the 18-prs. did. Field-Marshal sir douglas Haig had at the present moment in France 772 6-inchHowitzers.Lord Derby took the view that political considerations should give way to military, and that the one military consideration waswhere the guns would be best used, and he urged the War Cabinetnot to send any guns whatsoever to Russia. Pie laid stress on thefact that the Russian Government were urging the Allies toexercise all the pressure they could on the Western and Italianfronts, which, he pointed out, was not consistent with the despatchof guns to the Eastern theatre, where they would not be employedthis year.Lord Milner, who, since his visit to Russia, had watched thisquestion on behalf of the War Cabinet, dissented from this view.He stated that he had recent and definite evidence that the Russianfeelings in this matter were becoming embittered, and that wemust now either send more guns or justify to M. Kerensky the breaking of our promise to send guns. It was impossible totemporise any longer, and we must let the people who are keepingRussia in the war know definitely what we were going to do, one way or the other. The position in Russia was very serious, and,quite apart from the political point of view, in his judgment weshould lose the war from the military point of view if we did notkeep Russia in the war. Further postponement was equallyimpossible, and if anything was to be sent it must be sent at once;and he suggested that a telegram should be sent to M. Kerenskytelling him that orders had been given to ship two batteries atonce, and that more guns would follow in due course.Mr. Churchill stated that the wastage in big guns on theWestern front had been far less than had been anticipated, andthe fact of this saving of guns enabled us, in his opinion, to sparesome guns for Russia.   He submitted the following table: 
386,000 rounds of 6-inch Howitzer shell were fired; and for thecoming five or six months he regretted that the gun output wasahead of the possible output of 6-inch shell.Mr. Balfour said that the position appeared to him quite clear; we must act on the psychology of M. Kerensky and hiscolleagues in the Russian Government. In his opinion it waswell worth sending at least 20 heavy guns, however great our needin France might be, to keep Russia in the war. We had to balance the possible military loss of a small number of gunsagainst the possibility of large numbers of German and Austriandivisions being withdrawn from the Russian front to oppose usin the West, and, as far as he was concerned, he had no doubtthat the War Cabinet would be well advised to send the guns.One suggestion was that the sending of eight guns to Russiaseemed like a mockery, and that a telegram ought to be sent toM. Kerensky putting the whole position before him, explaining the value of our continued maximum offensive on the western front as affecting the pressure which the Germans could exerciseagainst Russia. We should tell M. Kerensky that, if he reallywished it, we would send two batteries at once, but that we intended to complete the whole of our promise of 150 guns assoon as the weather conditions on the Western front made itimpossible for our all-important offensive to be continued.The War Cabinet recognised that, from a purely military point of view, the balance of argument was in favour of the concentration of all available artillery on the fronts where theycould be employed during the present year. On a wider view ofthe question, however, they felt that the risk of discouragingRussia by a neglect to continue the supply of guns was too greatto be ignored. This consideration, though primarily political in character, was also inftportant from a military point of view,since the discouragement which might be produced by an entirecessation of the supply of additional heavy guns might prove animportant factor in influencing Russia towards a separate peace.They decided that (a) The Secretary of State for War should arrange to sendtwo batteries to Russia at once.(&amp;.) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should send- a telegram to the British Ambassador at Petrograd,communicating this information  and  explaining  tohim   the  whole   situation, for   transmission to M.Kerensky.The Pope&apos;s Peace 4. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs asked for theProposals. opinion of the War Cabinet regarding the answer to be given in^Parliament should the question of the Pope&apos;s Peace Proposal beraised on the Motion for the Adjournment.The Prime Minister pointed out that no definite reply could possibly be given until the Government had given the matter thevery fullest investigation, in consultation with all our Allies; andit was decided that No further reply could be given in Parliament upon thissubject until the matter had been the subject of further consultation.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,August 15, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
