<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 476-489</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
opWAR CABINET,  223.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onFriday, August 24, 1917, at 11&apos;30 a.m.Present:Mr. Bonar Law (in the Chair).The Right Hon.   the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Lieutenant-General    the    Right    Hon.J. C. Smuts, K.C.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P.The following weiThe Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil,K.C., M.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 3).General Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (for Minutes 4 to 12).The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minute 12).The Right Hon. the Viscount Cowdray,President, Air Board (for Minute 12).Lieutenant-General Sir D. Henderson,K.C.B., D.S.O., Director - General ofMilitary Aeronautics (for Minute 12).Sir W. Weir, Controller of-AeronauticalSupplies (for Minute 12).3 also present: The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty (for minutes 7 to 12).Vice-Adrniral Sir H. F. Oliver, K.C.B.,M.V.O., Deouty Chief of the naval staff (for Minutes 7 to 12.)The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Shipping Controller (for Minutes 1 and7).Commodore G. M. Paine, C.B., M.V.O.,Fifth Sea Lord of the Admiralty (for minute 12).Major J. L. Baird, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Air Board (for minute 12).Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally. Jones, Acting Secretary,Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.23&quot;   : ..- ti-,Brinted for the Wap Cabinet.   August,1917.SECRET. &quot;.
Ownership ofMerchant VesselsConstructed in theUnited States ofAmerica,&apos; 1.&apos; With reference to&quot; War Cabinet 222, Minute 1, Lord robert cecil stated that the Shipping Controller had taken objection to a proposed additional paragraph to the telegram sent to Lord North-cliffe, whereby expression would be given to our willingness to allow the United States to hold the ships in question after the war.Sir J. Maclay thought that such a suggestion would not influence the present position The War Cabinet referred the matter to Lord Robert Cecil andSir J. Maclay, to agree on a paragraph which would indicate to His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Washington that thesuggestion of restoring the ships after the war, or of time-chartering them, should only be made to the United StatesGovernment if he thought it necessary for the success ofthe negotiations, and in the last resort.KeportedConference at berne.2. Attention was drawn to statements which were appearing inthe press that a Conference between Allied subjects and enemyfinanciers and business men had taken place at Berne.Lord Robert Cecil stated that he had contradicted the rumourin the House of Commons, and that no passports had been issuedknowingly for such a purpose by the Foreign Office.The War Cabinet decided .. To ask the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs toendeavour to ascertain the facts.The War Cabinet were agreed that, if no such Conference hadtaken place, a public announcement to that effect shouldbe made.M. Huysmans. 3. The War Cabinet authorised Lord Robert Cecil to instruct His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Stock-holm to vise a passport for M. Huysmans, to enable him to visit the Belgian Government at Havre.Salonica.4. With reference to War Cabinet 221, Minute 5, the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff stated that difficulties were still being experienced with General Sarrail in connection with the reliefby French troops of the British Division, to be withdrawn. general sarrail was refusing to take over the line, and asserted that he couldonly place two cavalry regiments &quot;at the disposal of General Milne.There was some report of a small offensive being undertaken toprevent troops being sent to Roumania, and it was alleged that no more than this could be attempted owung to French troops having beengranted leave and to the inadequate manning of the Frenchbatteries.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to bring thematter again before the Cabinet in a few days&apos; time.The Eastern Front. 5. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported the receiptof two important telegrams from General Barter. The first of these,dated the 20th August, 1917 (Paper G.T.-1S28), stated thatGeneral Korniloff believed the Russian Government to be too weakto support his programme, and that he was contemplating vigorouspolitical action. He had decided to attend the forthcomingCongress at Moscow. He was strongly in favour of diplomaticpressure by the Western Powers as essential to the military andpolitical salvation of Russia. General Barter urged that if theAllied Governments intended to exert such pressure it should beapplied without a day&apos;s delay.
232Prisoners of 6. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff summarised theWar. position with regard to prisoners taken by the Allies and lost to theenemy during the Wrar (Appendix I).The War Cabinet decided that The Chief of the Imperial General Staff should prepare his statement in suitable form for issue to the press.The submarine campaign.7. The First Lord gave the War Cabinet some figures relatingto the Naval Appreciation of the Submarine Situation as regarded the numbers of German submarines engaged in operations. Fromthis report it appeared that the enemy&apos;s submarine campaign hadnot gained on us in the last three months, and that the destructiveeffort had not shown any increased percentage during that period.Zeebrugge.8. The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff reported an attack by coastal motor-boats carried out on the night of the 21st-22nd Augustat Zeebrugge, torpedoes being fired inside the Mole. All torpedoeswereobserved to explode.   All boats returned.A bombing raid was carried out at 3 a.m. on the 22nd Auguston Zeebrugge Mole, shipping, and batteries in vicinity.A bombing raid was also carried out on Ghistelles Aerodrome at&quot;30 a.m., man)- bombs being dropped. Bombs exploded near a westernshed, and a fire was started. All machines returned safely from both raids.Dunkirk Bombing 9- The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff reported that a bombingaics&apos; raid was carried out about 2 a.m. on the 23rd August on MiddelkerkeDump and Baversyde Dump.   A further raid was carried out at. 7 a.ml. on Houttave Aerodrome.   All machines and pilots returned safely from both raids.Submarines. 10. The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff gave the followingreports of submarine engagements : (a.) The Italian authorities report that on the 1 8th August two enemy submarines were attacked by aircraft near Pola,and one was sunk by six bombs; the other dived andescaped.The second telegram, dated the 21st August, 1917 (paper g.T.-1829), conveyed a summary of an important declaration madeby the Council of Union of Cossacks condemning the attitude ofthe Committee of Soldiers and Workmen in regard to the measures for the restoration of discipline proposed by General Korniloff. TheUnion declared General Korniloff to be the only General capable of restoring efticienc\7 to the Army and of delivering the country fromdisaster. In the event of General Korniloff being relieved of theChief Command, the Union declined further responsibility withregard to the attitude of the Cossack troops at the Front.A similar Proclamation had been issued by the Council of theKnights of St. George, which body, though less important than theCouncil of Cossacks, represented a large section of the best element in the Army.The War Cabinet decided that It was inadvisable at present to exercise any diplomatic pressurebeyond that agreed to in Minute 11 of War Cabinet 217.
(6.&apos;)&quot;&apos;. At 4-5Qp,m.. oh the 21st August trawlers sweeping the&quot; approaches of the Tay observed an explosion on the sideopposite to that which was being swept, followed by airbubbles and quantities of thick brown oil rising to the surface. Depth charges were dropped, the position wasswept, and the wire parted on an obstruction. Air and oil were still apparently coming to the surface on the5afternoon of the . 22nd. It is considered that thesubmarine has been destroyed. A German mine was destroyed by sweepers about the same position and time.(c.) H.M. sloop &quot; Viola&quot; reports having dropped two depth charges and damaged a submarine about 9 miles S.S.W.from the Lizard on the 23rd August.Attacks on enemy aircraft.; &apos;.Committee onAerial Operations.11. The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff stated that reports had been received from Dunkirk that at 3&quot;50 p.m. on 22nd August-four enemy aeroplane scouts were attacked and two driven down outof control.12. With reference to War Cabinet 181, Minute 3, the WarCabinet had under consideration the Second Report of the PrimeMinisters and General Smuts&apos;s Committee on Air Organisation and home Defence against&apos;Air Raids (Paper G.T.-l65S).((X-^4^i^J^^ &quot;2-The First Lord of the Admiralty said that, after obtaining theviews of the Commander-in-chief of the Grand Fleet, the Board ofAdmiralty had given its most careful consideration to the proposals&quot;put forward in the Committee&apos;s Second Beport. The Board were of opinion that there was a great difference between the services which the Royal Flying Corps renders to the Army in the field and those rendered by - the Royal Naval Air Service to theFleet and the auxiliaries working round the coast. In the caseof the former, good &quot; spotting&quot; and aerial reconnaissance areof great value to an army; but, if the air service was not good, it did not follow that a serious catastrophe would be caused. On the other hand, however, owing to the rapidity of movement at sea, faulty aerial or surface reconnaissance might easily have the most grave consequences. Reconnaissance madeby an aerial fleet takes the place of, or supplements, reconnaissanceby light cruisers, and, if full advantage is to be obtained from theair, it was essential that the closest co-operation and knowledgeof Naval warfare should exist between the. two Services. Especiallywas this so When Naval aircraft have to be carried on aeroplane-carriers or other war vessels. In the view of the Board, the trainingof the pilots and observers for operations with the Fleet was a far more difficult and lengthy matter than the training of similar officers for the Army, and that training already took more than twice aslong. It was essential that observers should have an intimate knowledge of types of vessels, not only of our own Navy,but of foreign Navies; and unless regrettable incidents, such as)wn submarines, were to take place, they mustthe bombingbe   in   theof our om tne closest possible touch with the Naval Commandsto which they are attached. They must also have a knowledge ofnaval tactical formation, as otherwise their use would be strictly limited. The Admiralty were very strongly impressed with thedifficulties of co-operation and limitation of responsibility in regardto an Air Service operating with fleets or squadrons which is notin every way a part of the Naval Service. They were of opinionthat, it is preferable for the proposed Air Ministry to continuetowards the Admiralty in the same relation as the Air Board standsto-day,. in. .so...fa.r...as..strictly fleet services are concerned, and they considered that for those services the introduction of a third ministry for the Air would exaggerate the complications of the co-operation
which already existed in joint undertakings where the Army and Navywere both concerned. His Department recognised, however, thatthere were strong reasons in favour of a definite development of air policy, and they accepted without question the views of those whohad investigated it that there is a definite futui-e for an aerialoffensive apart from the Army and the Navy. It did not, however,appear to them practicable that such operations should take placeover the sea without being part of the naval operations and undernaval command. Consequently, they considered that, at this stage,it would be perfectly simple for the Air Ministry to adopt itsproposed functions for the Army and for the Ministry independently,leaving the Royal Naval Air Service as it exists to-day, at any ratefor the course of the war. but continuing to act as suppliers of machines and spare parts, while the Navy continued to train its ownpilots and observers. The duties at present performed by the royal naval Air Service which are not of a purely naval character might,however, be handed over to the proposed Air Ministry. should there be serious objections, of which, the Admiralty were not aware,to the course proposed above, and should it be decided that thenaval aei&apos;ial work should be carried out by machines and pilotsprovided by the Air Ministry, the Admiralty considered that the AirMinistry should, from time to time, attach to the Navy suchair units as are deemed necessary by the Board of Admiralty,composed of machines of a design and specification laid down or approved by that Board, with pilots and observers also approvedby the Board, and trained to a standard and on lines laid downby the Board. It was also essential that, while such units are attached to the Navy, they should be solely under the command of the Board of Admiralty, not only as regards operations, but also as regards discipline, &amp;c. The Admiralty were of opinion that theabove conditions are absolutely essential if grave dislocation and serious clanger to the Fteet are not to take place. It was also clear to them that many real difficulties and important questions involvedin the creation of a new Service during the war will arise, and that,before fie principle is finally adopted, a detailed consideration ofthese intricate questions should be carried out by the Air Board,together with the Army and the Navy. The detailed recommen-dations would then receive further consideration.Lord Curzon, speaking from his experience as the first Presidentof the Air Board, pointed out that the First Lord&apos;s statementpresented two clear-cut alternatives : (a.) The establishment of an Air Ministry which would fulfil the present functions of the Air Board, at any rate forthe duration of the war; i.e., it woidd continue tosupply machines and spare parts, and adopting itsproposed functions to the Army and the Ministry indepen-dently, but leaving the Royal Naval Air Service as it is,except that the Ministry should supervise and controlsuch duties as are at present performed by that service which are not of a purely naval character.(6.) An Air Ministry constituted on the lines and provided withthe powers suggested in the report of the PrimeMinisters Committee.If the first alternative were accepted, matters would remain asthey were, and no real advance would be made. He himself was convinced of the necessity of an Air Ministry with full and indepen-dent powers, subject always to a reference to the Cabinet in theevent of friction between the Departments concerned. TheAdmiralty were, however, prepared, as the First Lord&apos;s statementshowed, to agree to the second alternative, subject to the provisionof certain safeguards. Paragraph 10 of the Committee&apos;s Reportrecommended that, in the event of the principle of an Air Ministry[1365-2231 C
being accepted, the details of the scheme foi&apos; the amalgamation ofthe two Air Services under the new Ministry should be worked outby a fresh Committee. The safeguards desired by the admiralty would be fully considered and adequately provided for, where necessary, by that Committee. He strongly urged the acceptanceof the second alternative.The President of the Air Board doubted whether there wasnot a tendencj&apos; to exaggerate the cleavage of opinion. It was generally agreed that after the war there must be a unified service under a Minister of the Crown, to control absolutely the existing air services. Separate training of personnel after the war could not becontemplated, though there would naturally be different classes oftraining. It was essential, in his opinion, that there should beno delay in settling what the functions of the Air Ministry were tobe. There was at present a certain natural rivalry between the twoAir Services which was prejudicial to efficiency and to the propersupply and distribution of output. It was not to be expected thatthere could be a genuine and complete co-operation between the two services unless the War Cabinet decided and announced that theServices were to be amalgamated. What was required was a centralauthority which would, determine how our airmen&apos;s services could be utilised to the best advantage. As Lord Curzon had pointed out, ifthe Admiralty and the War Office were not satisfied with the way in which their respective demands were met by the Air Ministry,they could bring their differences to be composed by the WarCabinet.The Minister of Munitions regarded the statement of the FirstLord as most reassuring. He himself strongly favoured theformation of an Air Ministry, but he foresaw that many problems would have to be faced which could not be easily solved. Speakingfrom his own considerable experience, he was confident that therewere natural and intimate bonds linking the two Services. he anticipated no great difficulty in combining the principle of a uniform Air Service with the recognition of the special needs of theNavy. When the two Services were merged into one, the personnel would consist of: (a.) Men who would make it their life-long profession..(6.) Soldiers and sailors who would be lent temporarily to theAir Service, but would return in due course to the Armyand the Navy.Mr. Churchill said that he fully agreed as to the. technicaldifferences in the training of military and naval airmen. He was in accord with the view of the First Lord, that the specialisedtraining of naval airmen demanded a longer period of tuition. OurAmerican Allies inclined to the view that victory would be achieved by the side which obtained complete command of the air. TheWar Cabinet had approved (War Cabinet 173, Minute 25) agreat and increasing extension of aircraft manufacture. Inorder to enable that expansion to be realised, he was arranging togive special priority to the output.of aeroplanes, and he was divertingskilled workmen, as well as material, from shell production to thisend. Fie considered that this development should be subject to, andguided by, the advice of a special Air War Staff, as adumbrated inthe report of the Prime Ministers Committee, who would evolve adefinite air-war plan, of operations. . Reverting to the question of thefuture of the personnel of the unified Air Service, he thought alarge proportion of officers and men must look to the Army and Navyfor their ultimate careers. The two Services could, however, be closely interwoven, and the exchange, and seconding of all ranks couldbe ai ranged without prejudice either to their interests or to those ofthe State.Sir William Weir indicated that tb.3 fulfilment of the aero-
233nautical programme of construction would necessarily influence theprogress of other supplies.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that the report of -the Prime Ministers Committee had been carefully considered by theArmy Council. That Council accepted in principle the proposal to institute a separate Air Service, but thought that it should be made clear that the War Office should be responsible for laying down theaircraft requirements of the Army, and they therefore suggestedthat paragraph 10 (6) should read : &quot; The Air Ministry shall from time to time attach to the navy and the Army such air units as are deemed necessary bythe Admiralty and War Office respectively for naval or military operations, &amp;c.&quot;General Robertson said that the Council felt convinced that manyreal difficulties and important questions such as rank, pay, pensions,discipline, recruiting, transport, stores, quarters were involved inthe creation of a new Service during the war, and they therefore considered that, before the principle was adopted finally, the air minister, assisted by any officers of the Navy, Army, and Treasurywhose help he might ask for, should have the details of the schemeworked out, and that this scheme should be referred to the Admiralty,the War Office, and the Treasury before submission to the WarCabinet for final decision. General Robertson said that he attached great importance to the question of the training required for Armypurposes, and he considered that Army interests must, in thisrespect, be safeguarded.After some discussion General Robertson consented not to press the Army Councirs proposed amendment. He hoped, however, thatthe amendment would be earefully considered by any Committeewhich might be appointed to draw up a scheme for the amalgama-tion of the Air Services and the formation of an Air Ministry.It was suggested that one of the many difficulties attending theformation of a separate and unified Air Service would arise from thefact that the physical strain imposed upon airmen by the excessivelyarduous nature of their duties, strictly limited the period of theiruseful activities in the field. Men would naturally be reluctant toenter on a career which might be closed when they were 30 or even25 years of age, unless General Staff or administrative appointmentsunder the Ministry were open to them, or the State was prepared tooffer them a substantial pension at a considerable cost to the publicpurse. On the other hand, it was pointed out that after the warthe strain would be infinitely less, inasmuch as every developmentof aircraft, in design and production^ gave increased security, andthat consequently the active career of airmen would be considerablyprolonged.The  War  Cabinet,  after  the   most  careful   consideration,decided : (a.) To accept iu principle the recommendations made in theSecond Report of the Prime Ministers Committee on AirOrganisation, as summarised in paragraph 10 of theReport;(b.) To appoint a Committee, to meet at once, to investigateand report on the arrangements necessary for the amal-gamation of the Royal Naval Air Service and the RoyalPlying Corps and the relationship between it and theAdmiralty and War Office, and the legal constitution and discipline of the new unified Air Service, and prepare the necessary draft legislation and regulations for submission to Parliament at the earliest possible date ;(c.) That no public statement regarding the above decisions should be made until the new Committee&apos;s Report hadbeen received and approved by the War Cabinet;
(d.) That the Committee referred to in (6) should consist of General Smuts  (as representing  the  War  Cabinet)(Chairman),Representatives of-The Admiralty,The War Office,The Treasury,The Air Board,in consultation, where necessary, with the Law Officers ofthe Crown ;(e.) That the utmost secrecy should be observed by all concerned___in regard to these decisions.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,August 24, 1917.
wc 22aAPPENDIX I.(See Minute 6.)Prisoners of War : Statement by Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Prisoners taken Last five daysSince July 31     ...,,    April 9     ...11By BritishFrenchItaliansBritishFrenchItaliansBritishFrenchItalians3,0007*60017,00010,500 &quot;7,60017,00046,100*&quot;43,700*40,00027,60035,100129,800Russians have taken ...Germans    ,,       ,,During whole war we have lost in all theatrestaken    ,,       ,,37,00041,000 on East Front56,500131,700* Germans.APPENDIX   II.(G.T.-1658.)--Committee on Air Organisation and Home Defence Against Air Raids.   (Second Report.)(For First Report, see G.T.-1451.)1. THE War Cabinet at their 181st Meeting held on the 11th July, 1917, decided(Minute 3) :-&quot; That the Prime Minister and General Smuts, in consultation with representativesof the Admiralty, General Staff, and Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief,Home Forces, with such other experts as they may desire, should examine : &quot;&apos;(!.) The defence arrangements for home defence against air raids.&quot; (2.) The air organisation generally and the direction of aerial operations.&quot;2. Our first report dealt with the. defences of the London area against air raids.The recommendations in that report were approved by the War Cabinet, and are nowin process of being carried out. The&apos; Army Council have placed at Lord Frenclfsdisposal the services of General Ashmore to work out schemes of air defence for this area. We proceed to deal in this report with the second term of reference : &quot; The airorganisation generally, and the direction of aerial operations.&quot; For the considerations which will appear in the course of this report we consider the early settlement of thismatter of vital importance to the successful prosecution of the war. The three mostimportant questions which press for an early answer are: (1.) Shall there be instituted a real Air Ministry responsible for all air organisationand operations ? . ;,j(2.) Shall there be constituted a unified Air Service embracing both the presentR.N.A.S. and R.F.C. ?And if this second question is answered in the affirmative, the third question arises [1365-223] D
(3.) How shall the relations of the new Air Service to the Navy and the Army bedetermined so that the functions at present discharged for them by theR.N.A.S. and R.F.C. respectively shall continue to he efficiently performed by the new Air Service ? -3. The subject of general Air Organisation has in the past formed the subject of acute controversies which are now, in consecpuence of the march of events, largely *obsolete, and to which a brief reference is here made only in so far as they bear on some of the difficulties which we have to consider in this report. During the initial stages of air development, and while the role to be performed by an Air Serviceappeared likely to be merely ancillary to naval and military operations, claims were put forward and pressed with no small warmth, for separate Air Services in connectionwith the two old-established War Services. These claims eventuated in theestablishment of the R.N.A.S. and R.F.C., organised and operating on separate lines inconnection with and under the aegis of the Navy and Army respectively, and provisionfor their necessary supplies and requirements was made separately by the admiralty and War Office to provide a safeguard against the competition, friction, and wastewhich were liable to arise, an Air Committee was instituted to preserve the peace and secure co-operation if possible. When war broke out this body ceased to exist, owingto the fact that its chairman and members nearly all went to the front, but after a time it was replaced by the Joint War Air Committee. The career of this body was,however, cut short by an absence of all real power and authority, and by politicalcontroversies which arose in consequence. It was followed by the present Air Board,which has a fairly well-defined status, and has done admirable work, especially in settling type and patterns of engines and machines, and in co-ordinating and controllingsupplies to both the R.N.A.S. and R.F.C.4. The utility of the Air Board is, however, severely limited by its constitution and powers. It is not really a Board, but merely a Conference. Its membershipconsists almost entirely of representatives of the War Office, Admiralty, and Ministryof Munitions, who consult with each other in respect of the claims of the R.N.A.S. andR.F.C. for their supplies. It has no technical personnel of its own to advise it, and itis dependent on the officers which the Departments just mentioned place at its disposal for the performance of its duties. These officers, especially the Director General ofMilitary Aeronautics, are also responsible for the training of the personnel of theR.F.C. service. Its scope is still further limited in that it has nothing to do either with the training of the personnel of the R.N.A.S. or with the supply of lighter-than-air craft, both of which the Admiralty has jealously retained as its special perquisites.Although it has a nominal authority to discuss questions of policy, it has no real powerto do so, because it has not the independent technical personnel to advise it in that respect, and any discussion of policy would simply ventilate the views of its militaryand naval members. Under the present constitution and powers of the Air Board thereal directors of war policy are the Army and Navy, and to the Air Board is reallyallotted the minor role of fulfilling their requirements according to their ideas of war policy. Essentially the Air Service is as subordinated to military and naval direction and conceptions of policy as the artillery is, and, as long as that state of affairs lasts,it is useless for the Air Board to embark on a policy of its owm, which it could neitheroriginate nor execute under present conditions.5. The time is, however, rapidly approaching when that subordination of the AirBoard and the Air Service could no longer be justified. Essentially the position of an air Service is quite different from that of the artillery arm. To pursue our comparison :Artillery could never fie used in war except as a weapon in military or naval or air operations. It is a weapon, an instrument ancillary to a Service, but could not be anindependent Service itself., Air Service, on the contrary, can be used as an independentmeans of war operations. Nobody that witnessed the attack on London on the 11thJuly could have any doubt on that point. Unhke artillery, an air fleet can conductextensive operations far from, and independently of, both Army and Navy. As far as can at present be foreseen, there is absolutely no limit to the scale of its futureindependent war use. And the day may not be far off when aerial operations, withtheir devastation of enemy lands and destruction of industrial and populous centres ona vast scale, may become the principal operations of war, to which the older forms ofmilitary and naval operations may become secondary and subordinate. The subjectionof the Air Board and Service could only be justified on the score of their infancy. Butthat is a disability which time can remove, and in this respect the march of events hasbeen very rapid during the war.    In our opinion there is no reason why the Air Board
should any longer continue in its present form as practically no more than a conference room between the older Services, and there is every reason why it should be raised tothe status of an independent Ministry in control of its own War Service.6. The urgency for the change will appear from the following facts.   Hithertoaircraft production has been insufficient to supply the demands of both Army and navy, and the chief concern of the Air Board has been to satisfy the necessary require&apos;ments of those Services.     But that phase is rapidly passing.   The programme of aircraft production which the War Cabinet has sanctioned for the following twelve monthsis far in excess of Army and Navy requirements.   Next spring and summer the position will be that the Army and Navy will have all the Air Service required in connection withtheir operations; and over and above that there will be a great surplus available for independent operations.   Who is to look after and direct the activities of this availablesurplus ?   Neither the Army nor the Navy is specially competent to do so; and forthat reason the creation of an Air Staff for planning and directing independent air operations will soon be pressing.   More than that: the surplus of engines and machinesnow being built should have regard to the strategical purpose to which they are goingto be put.   And in settling in advance the types to be built the operations for whichthey are intended, apart from naval or military use, should be clearly kept in view.This means that the&apos; Air Board has already reached the stage where the settlement of future war policy in the air war has become necessary.    Otherwise, engines andmachines useless for independent strategical operations may be built.   The necessityfor an Air Ministry and Air Staff has therefore become urgent.7. The magnitude and significance of the transformation now in progress are not easily realised. It requires some imagination to realise that next summer, while ourWestern front may still be moving forward at a snaiFs pace in Belgium and France,the air battle front will be far behind on the Rhine, and that its continuous and intensepressure against the chief industrial centres of the enemy, as well as on his lines ofcommunication, may form an important factor in bringing about peace. The enemy isno doubt making vast plans to deal with us in London if we do not succeed in beatinghim in the air and carrying the war into the heart of his country. The question of machines, aerodromes, routes, and distances, as well as nature and scope of operations,require careful thinking out in advance, and in proportion to our foresight and prepara-tions will our success be in these new and far-reaching developments. Or take again the case of a subsidiary theatre: There is no reason why we may not gain such anoverpowering air superiority in Palestine as to cut the enemy&apos;s precarious and limitedrailway communications, prevent the massing of superior numbers against our advance,and, finally, to wrest victory and peace, from him. But careful staff work in advanceis here in this terra incognita of the air even move essential than in ordinary militaryand naval operations which follow a routine consecrated by the experience of centuriesof warfare on the old lines.The progressive exhaustion of the man-power of the combatant nations will.moreand more determine the character of this war as one of arms and machinery ratherthan of men. And the side that commands industrial superiority and exploits itsadvantages in that regard to the utmost ought in the long run to win. Man-power in its war use will more and more tend to become subsidiary and auxiliary to the full development and use of mechanical power. The submarine has already shown whatstartling developments are possible in naval warfare. Aircraft is destined to work an even more far-reaching change in land warfare. But to secure the advantages of this new factor for our side, we must not only make unlimited use of the mechanical geniusand productive capacity of ouz&apos;selves and our American Allies. We must create thenew directing organisation the new Ministry and Air Staff which could properlyhandle this new instrument of offence, and equip it with the best brains at our disposal for the purpose. The task of planning the new Air Service organisation and thiukingout and preparing for schemes of aerial operations next summer must tax our air ,experts to the utmost, and no time should be lost in setting the new Ministry and staff going. Unless this is done, we shall not only lose the great advantages whichthe new form of warfare promises, but we shall end in chaos and confusion, asneither the Army, nor Navy, nor the Air Board in its present form could possiblycope with the vast developments involved in our new aircraft programme. Flithertothe creation of an Air Ministry and Air Service has been looked upon as an ideato be kept in view, but not to be realised during this war. Events have, however,moved so rapidly, our prospective aircraft production will soon be so great, and thepossibilities of aerial warfare have grown so far bej^ond all previous expectations, that[1365-223] E
the change will brook no further delay, and will have to be carried through as soonasialhthe necessary arrangements for the purpose can be made.8. There remains the question of the new Air Service and the absorption of theR.N.AiS. and R.F.C. into it. should the Navy and the Army retain their own specialAhvServices in addition to the air forces which will be controlled by the Air Ministry?This, will make the confusion hopeless and render the solution of the air problemimpossible. The maintenance of three Air Services is out of the question, nor, indeed,does the War Office make any claim to a separate Air&apos; Sexwice of its own. But asregards air work the Navy is exactly in-the same position as the Army; the intimacybetween aerial&apos; scouting or observation and naval operations is not greater than that between long-range artillery work on land-and aerial observation or spotting. If aseparate Air-Service is not necessary in the one case, neither is it necessary in theother. And the proper and, indeed, only possible arrangement is to establish oneunified Air Service which will absorb both the existing Services under arrangements which will fully safeguard the efficiency and secure the closest intimacy between theArmy and the1 Navy * and the portions of the Air Service allotted or seconded to them.9. To secure efficiency and smooth working of the Air Service in connection withnaval and military operations, it is not only necessary that in the construction of air-craft and the training of the Air personnel the closest attention shall be given to thespecial requirements of the Navy and the Army. It is necessary also that all air unitsdetailed for naval or military work should be temporarily seconded to those Servicesand come directly under the orders of the naval or army commanders of the forces with which they are associated. The effect of that will be that in actual workingpractically no change -will be made in the air work as it is conducted to-day, and nofriction could Prise between the Navy or Army commands and the Air Service allotted to them. -It-is recognised, however, that for some years to come the Air Service will, for its efficiency, be largely dependent on -the officers of the Navy and Army who are already employed in this work or who may in the future elect to join it permanently ortemporarily. The influence of the regular officers of both Services on the spirit, conduct,and discqDiine of the present Air Forces has been most valuable, and it is desirable thatthe Air Board should still be able to draw on the older Services for the assistance of trained leaders and administrators. Further, it is equally necessary that a considerablenumber of officers of both the Navy and Army should be attached for a part of their service to the Air Service in order that naval and military commanders and staff officers may be trained in the new arm and able to utilise to advantage the contingentsof the Air Forces which will be pub at their disposal. The organisation of the AirForce, therefore, should be such as to allow of the seconding of officers of the Navy and army for definite periods not less than four or five years to the Air Service. such officers would naturally, after their first training, be chiefly emplo&quot;ed with the navaland military contingents in order to secure close co-operation in air work with theirown Services. In similar fashion it would be desirable to arrange for the transfer of expert warrant and petty or non-commissioned officers from the Navy and Army to thenew Service.10. To summarise the above discussion, we would make the following recom-mendations: (1.) That an Air Ministry be instituted as soon as possible, consisting of a minister with a consultative. Board on the lines of the Army Council or AdmiraltyBoard, on which the several departmental activities of the Ministry will berepresented, this Ministry to control and administer all matters in connec-tion with, aerial warfare of all kinds whatsoever, including lighter-than-airas well as heavier-than-air craft.(2.) That under the Air Ministry an Air Staff be instituted on the lines of theImperial General Staff, responsible for the working out of war plans, thedirection of operations, the collection of intelligence, and the training ofthe Air personnel; that this staff be equipped with the best brains and practical experience available in our present Air Services, and that byperiodic appointment to the staff of officers with great practical experiencefrom the&apos; front, due provision be made for the development of the staff in response to the rapid advance of this new Service.I (3.) That the Air Ministry and Staff proceed to work out the arrangementsnecessary for the amalgamation of the B.N.A.S. and R.F.C. and the legalconstitution and discipline of the new Air Service, and to prepare the
necessary draft legislation and regulations, which could be passed and brought into operation next autumn and winter.(4.) That the arrangements referred to shall make provision for the automaticpassing of the R.N.A.S. and the R.F.C. personnel to the new Air Service,by consent, with the option to those officers and other ranks who are merelyseconded or lent of reverting to their former positions.There are legal questions involved in this transfer, and the rights ofofficers and men must be protected, but no dislocation need be anticipated.(5.) That the Air Service remain in intimate touch wdth the Army and Navy bythe closest liaison, or by direct representation of both on the Air Staff, andthat, if necessary, the arrangements for close co-operation between thethree Services be reviewed from time to time.(6.) That the Air Staff shall from time to time attach to the Army and the navy the air units necessary for naval or military operations, and such units shall,during the period of such attachment, be subject, for the purpose of operations, to the control of the respective naval and military commands.Air units not so attached to the Army and Navy shall operate under theimmediate direction of the Air Staff.The air units attached to the Navy and Army shall be provided withthe types of machines which these services respectively desire.--(7.) That provision be made for the seconding or loan of regular officers of the navy and Army to the Air Service for definite periods; such officers to beemployed, as far as possible, with the naval and military contingents.(8.) That provision be made for the permanent transfer, by desire, of officers andother ranks from the Navy and Army to the Air Services.11. In conclusion, we would point out how undesirable it would be to give too much publicity to the magnitude of. our air construction programme and the realsignificance of the changes in organisation now proposed. It is important for thewinning of the war that we should not only secure air predominance, but secure it ona very large scale, and, having secured it in this war, we should make every effort andsacrifice to maintain it for the future. Air supremacy may in the long run become as important a factor in the defence of the Empire as sea supremacy. From both these points of view it is necessary that not too much publicity be given to our plans and intentions, which will only have the effect of spurring- our opponents to corresponding-efforts. The necessary measures should be defended on the grounds of their inherentand obvious reasonableness and utility, and the desirability of preventing conflict andsecuring harmony between naval and militaiy requirements.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,August 17, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
