<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/3/0 images: 504-510</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
244Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1917,Secret81WAR CABINET, 226.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onThursday, August 30, 1917, at 1P30 a.m.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Bresent :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, KG,M.P.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, KG.,G.O.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes 1 to 7).Major - General F. B. Maurice, C.B.,Director, of Military Operations, WarOffice (for Minutes 1 to 7).The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart,,controller of Shipping (for Minutes 6to 8).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minute 10).Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., O.M.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and CMef ofthe Naval Staff (for Minutes 1 to S).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade .,for minutes 10 and 11).Mr. G. H. Wardle, M.P., ParliamentarySecretarv, Board of Trade (for Minute10).Sir W. F. Marwood, KGB.Trade (for Minute 10).Board ofSir H. Walker, KGB., Railway Execu-tive Committee (for Minute 10).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, KGB., Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Western Front. 1. THE Director of Military Operations reported that the effectof our continued bombardment was telling on the Germans. Sincethe 31st July they had employed 41 Divisions against 23 british divisions. They had withdrawn 31 Divisions and we had withdrawn15. The effect on the German reserves might be regarded, from our point of view, as very satisfactory.Of the 146 German Divisions that had been fighting during thepast three-and-a-half months, 122 Divisions had been heavilyengaged. In this connection, we had 40 Divisions that had notfought hard during the same period.
Italian Front. 2. The Director of Military   Operations  reported  that  the austrians had established their rear-guards with machine guns onthe western edge of the Chiapovano Valley and had withdrawn theirartillery to the eastern edge. The Italians were now getting up their artillery with which to knock out the Austrian machine guns.The Austrians had brought up ah their reserves. It was reportedthat one division was coming from the Austrian front.The question now was whether the Italians could get up theirguns and make a fresh start before the Austrians were ready forthem.With regard to the explosion of an ammunition dump at Udine,the Director of Military Operations said that only 8,300 rounds of heavy ammunition had been destroyed ; the remainder consisted ofgrenades, trench mortars, &amp;c. The result was not likely to have agreat effect on the military opeiations. The moral of the AustrianArmy was reported to be not good the prisoners who have beentaken say that if pressed their Army will retire to the eastern edge of the Chiapovano Valley. The present extent of the Italianadvance is 6 miles, and if the eastern side of the valley is reached,a total advance of 9 miles will have been achieved.Support to Italy. 3. With reference to War Cabinet 224, Minute 17, the WTarCabinet took note of the personal and secret telegram toSir Rennell Rodd, dated the 29th August, in reply to his telegramof the 26th August, agreed to on the previous day by the PrimeMinister, Lord Milner, and the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.    .Eussia. 4. The Director of Military Operations reported that the recentGerman advance in Russia was not appreciable and had no strategicsignificance. The serious side of the enemy&apos;s advance was theevidence afforded of the continued lack of moral on the part of theRussians.Convoys. 5, &apos;the First Sea Lord reported that a convoy escorted byH.M.S. &quot; Devonshire &quot; had been scattered by a gale. Only 6 shipsout of 20 remain with the convoy. The number of convoys had now been increased to 9 every eight days.Inter-Ally (;. With reference to War Cabinet 208, Minute 3, the First sea transport Lord raised the question of the Inter-Ally Transport Conferenceon eienee. which had been agreed on at the Paris Conference.Lord Robert Cecil pointed out the desirability of holding sucha Conference, and emphasised the need of perfect frankness, as wellas the importance of inviting French and Italian representatives if aConference was held with the representatives of the United States.The Director of Military Operations explained that at the paris Conference General Pershing had reported that the UnitedStates Government had proposed to transport everything required* , by their troops from the United States, and that one of the main.reasons for the proposal to hold this Conference had been to examinehow far the requirements of the United States of America could bemet from European sources of supply.The Shipping Controller said that in his opinion no good seemed likely to come from a Shipping Conference, for it was almost certainthat such a meeting would result in increased demands being made upon British shipping. It appeared to be one of those cases where we have nothing to get and everything to give.No decision was reached.
is.67. The Prime Minister said that M. Thomas had stated that about S0,000 tons of shipping were laid up in France owing to lackof steel plates for repairs which were necessary..The Shipping Controller undertook to find out the facts about this matter.Naval Guns for 8. The  War Cabinet had  before them   a   letter   from  the russia. Ministry of Shipping asking for instructions   in regard  to thedespatching of naval 14-inch guns to Russia (G.T.-1878).The Shipping Controller said that the six guns which were nowready could  be carried if shipped within the next three weeks,preferably at once, as suitable ships for carrying them were nowwaiting.The First Sea Lord said he considered that the guns would never be used. He reported that, in addition to these and other14-inch guns, Messrs. Vickers were also making 18-inch guns forthe Russians.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) With a view to a possible offer of exchange to Russia, theWar Office, in consultation with the Ministry ofMunitions and the Commander-in-Chief of the british expeditionary Force, should examine the situation andreport whether (1.) The guns could be usefully employed on theBritish Front.(2.) Heavy guns or howitzers desired by the russian army could be offered in exchange.(3.) Suitable mountings could be provided for landservice.(6.) If, however, the Russian Government insisted on the delivery of the guns, the shipment of them should bemade at the earliest possible moment.The War Cabinet attached importance to a very early investiga-tion of these qtiestions.Ship Repairing inFrance.Visit of 9. The War Cabinet had under consideration a telegram from lord Northcliffe Lord Northcliffe (G.T.-1875), in which he reported that he hadto Canada. accepted an invitation to visit Canada, and asked for instructions asto what reply he should give to Sir Robert Borden in regard to dealing with questions respecting the supply of tonnage and. itsincrease, the -provision of food supplies, particularly grain, flour,meats, and fats.The War Cabinet approved of &apos;A telegram sent by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, afterconsultation with the Prime Minister, in the followingsense:  &quot; The whole Canadian problem is a question of finance,and we think that Canada could set the position right to alarge extent by the creation of currency. In these circum-stances, do you not think it would be better either to postpone your visit till you can go in company with lord Reading or to make it, as you suggest, a visit ofcourtesy ?&quot;
Railway Labour 10. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the unrest. President of the Board of Trade in regard to railway labour unrest.Sir Albert Stanley briefly summarised the position : During the recent negotiations, which led to the immediatedemand for the institution of an 8 hours&apos; day being dropped, he had stated to the Society that he would use his good offices with the *Railway Executive Committee to secure that they would receivethe men&apos;s representatives and discuss other outstanding matters.The Railway Executive Committee had met representatives of the associated Society on the previous Friday, and it had then beenarranged that the Society should formulate an application. Theyhad now forwarded, for the consideration of the Committee, thefollowing : &quot; That 3s. 6d. per day be added to the 2s. 6d. per day warwages now paid to the locomotive drivers, firemen, cleaners, and electric motormen.&quot;This claim for an addition of 3.s. 6d. a day, to be added tothe 2s. Gd. per day war wages, would mean an over-all increase overthe pre-war wage of about 42s. or 43s. per week. The total suminvolved by the increase now asked for of 3s. 6d. a day war wage,would be about 37-^- million pounds if applied to all the railway men.The real difficulty in the position was that it was impossible to concede the Associated Society more than the National Union of railwaymen had already agreed to accept. Anything more givento the Society would produce an instant conflict with the NationalUnion, who had behaved very well. up to the present, whilst theSociety had not.The Railway Executive Committee were meeting representativesof the Associated Society on the following Friday, and it was not proposed to offer the Society more than had been accepted by theNational Union.The War Cabinet approved the proposals of the President ofthe i oard of Trade.Control of Matches. 11. The President of the Board of Trade reported that he was taking control of the match industry. There was a great shortageof matches and a good deal of profiteering, and it was hoped thatGovernment control would result in better distribution.The War Cabinet approved of this action by the President ofthe Board of Trade.Pope&apos;s Peace 12. With reference to War Cabinet 225, Minute 12, the WarProposals. Cabinet were agreed that President Wilson&apos;s reply to the Pope&apos;speace note  Appendix) contained passages to which they could not give unqualified assent, and that for this reason it was impossible toexpress official agreement on it.The &quot;War Cabinet decided That the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should inform the Allies that in view of the reply given by president Wilson, and the answer already sent by theBritish Government, of which a copy was sent to each ofthe Allies, it was suggested that no further reply should besent until the answer of the Central Powers was received,and that we should be glad to know if the Allies concurred.Labour Unrest.13. The War Cabinet authorised Mr. Barnes to show a Paperby Professor Arnold, of Bangor (G.T.-1849), to Mr. Mactavish, and ask him for his comments on the situation.
14. With reference to War Cabinet 221, Minute 13, Sir edward carson reported that a good deal of money would be required for thepurpose of propaganda in this country, perhaps as much as 100,000LIt was understood, however, that there was a good deal of oppositionto the use of public money for the maintenance of a cause to which acertain number (though a small one) of the tax-payers were opposed.He was uncertain as to Mr. Asquith&apos;s attitude towards this question.It was pointed out that Mr. Asquith&apos;s Government hadpermitted the use of public money to support Lord Derby&apos;s recruitingcampaign, to which the same elements had been equally strongly opposed.Sir Edward Carson undertook to sound the persons concerned on this subject.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,August 30, 1917. .   ...1
GAPPENDIX.To His Holiness Benedictus XV, Pope.In acknowledgment of the communication of your Holiness to the belligerentpeoples, the President, of the United States requests me to transmit the followingreply :-&quot; Every heart that has not been blinded and hardened by this terrible war mustbe touched by this moving appeal of His Holiness the Pope, must feel the dignity andforce of the humane and generous motives which prompted it, and must fervently wish that we might take the path of peace he so persuasively points out. But it wouldbe folly to take it if it does not in fact lead to the goal he proposes. Our responsemust be based upon the stern facts and upon nothing else. It is not a mere cessation of arms he desires ; it is a stable and enduring peace. This agony must not be gonethrough with again, and it must be a matter of very sober judgment what will ensureus against it.- &quot;His Holiness in substance proposes that we return to the status quo ante bellum,and that then there can be a general condonation, disarmament, and a concert ofnations based upon an acceptance of the principle of arbitration ; that by a similarconcert freedom of the seas be established ; and that the territorial claims of Franceand Italy, the perplexing problems of the Balkan States, and the restitution of Polandbe left to such conciliatory adjustments as may be possible in the new temper of sucha peace, due regard being paid to the aspirations of the peoples whose politicalfortunes and affiliations will be involved.&quot; It is manifest that no part of this programme can be successfully carried outunless the restitution of the status quo ante furnishes a firm and satisfactory basis for it. The object of this war is to deliver the free peoples of the world from the menaceand the actual power of a vast military establishment controlled by an irresponsibleGovernment, which, having secretly planned to dominate the world, proceeded tocarry the plan out without regard either to the sacred obligations of treaty or the long-established practices and long-cherished principles of international action and honour;which chose its own time lor the war ; delivered its blow fiercely and suddenly ; stoppedat no barrier either of law or of mercy; swept a whole continent within the tide of. blood, not the blood of soldiers only, but the blood of innocent women and childrenalso and of the helpless poor ; and. now stands baulked but not defeated, the enemy of four-fifths of the world. This power&quot; is not the German people. It is the ruthlessmaster of the German people. It is no business of ours how that great people came under its control or submitted to its temporary zest, to the domination of its purpose ;but it is our business to see to it that the history of the rest of the world is no longerleft to its handling. .&quot; To deal with such a Power by wray of peace upon the plan proposed by HisHoliness the Pope would, so far as we can see, involve a recuperation of the strengthand renewal of the policy; would make it necessary to create a permanent hostilecombination of the nations against the German people, who are its instruments ; wouldresult in abandoning the new-born Russia to the intrigue, the&apos; manifold subtleinterference, and the certain counter-revolution which would be attenrpted by all themalign influences to which the German Government has of late accustomed the world.Can peace be based upon a restitution of its power or upon any word of honour itcould pledge in a treaty of settlement and accommodation ?&quot; Responsible statesmen must now everywhere see, if they never saw before, thatno peace can rest securely upon political or economic restrictions meant to benefitsome nations and cripple or embarrass others, upon vindictive action of any sort, orany kind of revenge or deliberate injury. The American people have sufferedintolerable wrongs at the hands of the Imperial German Government, but they desireno reprisal upon the German people, who have themselves suffered all things in this war which they did not choose. They believe that peace should rest upon the rightsof peoples, not the rights of Governments, the rights of peoples great and small, weakor powerful, their equal right to freedom and security and self-government, and to aparticipation upon fair terms in the economic opportunities of the world, the Germanpeoples of course included, if they will accept equality and not seek domination.&quot; The test, therefore, of every plan of peace is this : Is it based upon the faith ofall the. peoples involved, or merely upon the word of an ambitious and intriguing
Government on the one hand, and of a group of free peoples on the other ? This is a test which goes to the root of the matter ; and it is the test which must he applied.&quot;The purposes of the United States in this war are known to the whole world to every people to whom the truth has been permitted to come. They do not need to be stated again. We seek no material advantage of any kind. We believe that theintolerable wrongs done in this war by the furious and brutal power of the ImperialGerman Government ought to be repaired, but not at the expense of the sovereignty of any people rather in vindication of the sovereignty both of those that are weak andof those that are strong. Punitive damages, the dismemberment of empires, theestablishment of selfish and exclusive economic leagues, we deem inexpedient and, inthe end, worse than futile, no proper basis for a peace of any kind, least of all for anenduring peace. That must be based upon justice and fairness and the commonrights of mankind.&quot; We cannot take the word of the present riders of Germany as a guarantee of anything that is to endure, unless explicitly supported by such conclusive evidenceof the will and purpose of the German people themselves as the other peoples of theworld would be justified in accepting. Without such guarantees, treaties of settle-ment, agreements for disarmament, covenants to set up arbitration in the place of force, territorial adjustments, reconstitutions of small nations, if made with theGerman Government, no man, no nation, could now depend on. We must await some new evidence of the purposes of the great peoples of the Central Empires. Godgrant it may be given soon, and in a way to restore the confidence of all peopleseverywhere in the faith of the nations and the possibility of a covenanted peace.&quot; Robert Lansing, Secretary of State of the United States of America.

</content>
</cab>
