<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/20/0 images: 215-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
               KLY REPORT&apos; ON RUSSIA.  XIII,                    16 July, 1917.The Success  of the Offensive.     The success of the offensive has undoubtedly come as a sur-prise not only to the outside world but also to Petrograd.  To mostpeople the task Kerenski had set himself was a superhuman one, andoptimism both in Russia and abroad  wai. seldom to be met with.  Itmay be well, therefore, to attempt  to analyse  (1) the objectstowards which Kerenski has been striving, and  (2) the secret ofhis:-; success.     (1) Kerenski1 s objects seem to have been threefold: -  ;               (a) To solve Russiars. internal difficulties by;                   getting together a strong revolutionary army.               (b) To show the Germans that they cannot base                 ;  their plans on the weaknoss of Russia.              - (c) To show the Allies that Russia1s war aims are   V                   not the product  of a weak and discouraged Russia.    ; Of&apos; these three objects the first Wo are gradually beingachieved, though their complete success depends on the next fewmonths..  The third object, viz. to  prove to the Russian peoplethat the carrying out of the offensive will help in the discussionof war aims,- will be put to the test  at the Allled Conference;inSeptember.  According to a telegram from Sir G.;Buchanan Mr Teresh-ohenko prophesied that the offensive  would last for about six weeks,,to be followed by a pause during August.  It was then to be,renewedon a larger  scale during September.  If this proves true thedifficult time will come during August when the people are no longerengrossed in the news from the front.  It is probable that duringthis period the Russian press will  chiefly be occupied with the
question of war aims.   A long drawn out controversy in the press onguch a subject is  hardly desirable, and it seems likely that theRus.8 ian Government w ill be anxious no t t o del ay the me e t ing ofthe Allied Conference.     (2) The secret of  Kerenski&apos;s success is to be sought in thekind of appeal he  has made to his people.  The main theme of hismost successful speeches has been that nothing that is worthhaving can be won  without suffering.  In this he reflects theteachings of Dostoyevski, and the response of the people has beenextraordinary.  It Is  worth noting that the Social Revolutionaries(i.e, the Russian  peasant Socialists) have been the most responsive,the more doctrinaire Marxists still holding aloof and refusing tobe carried on the  Wave  of enthusiasm.  It is true that theenthusiasm, in many cases amounting1 to hysteria, with which Russianaudiences have acclaimed their Minister of War may soon die down  :in the face of the hardships of war which no Government can immediately overcome.  At the same time, Kerenski has created such a pro-found impression that  it has no doubt already spread^ far beyondthe circle of those who have heard him speak.  It is possible thata Kerenski legend  may  grow up in the minds of the peasantry of .a kind to work miracles, the effect of whioh is incalculable.Finland and the Ukraine.     v;^;&apos;^;V^^^^!^:&apos;^&apos;;^v^&quot;i::-^*  -     While the situation in the Ukraine seems to have improved asthe result of a visit  paid by Messrs Kerenski, Tseretelli andTereshchenko, the  attitude of Finland is oausing serious anxietyand Ministers are  being sent to Finland to deal with the situationas best they can..   The Finnish Diet - in which the Social Democratshave a majority -  is not only refusing a loan, but is also on thepoint of declaring Finnish independence qu ite regardless of Russia.
The difficulty in dealing with Finland at present is due to thelack of Moderate Socialists there with whom Kerenski and Tseretellioan see eye to eye.  The Finnish Social Democrats are mostly.Bolshevik! or Maximalists and are unwilling to make any compromisewith the Russian Government,   There is little doubt that thetrouble in KT oust ad t was partly caused by its proximity toFinland.   The danger of the Finnish situation lies in theeffect it may have on the other nationalities.     German propaganda is very active in Finland and even analliance with Germany is talked of with very little beating about &apos;the bush.  German influence in Finland is largely due to the factthat nearly all the professors have been trained in Germany, and75 per cent, at least of the text books used by them are German.It may be added that all the architects, dentists, doctors, etc.have also had their special training in Germany, that most of theleading shops and  businesses either belong to German subjects orex-German subjects, and that a very large proportion of houseproperty in Helsingfors is also German.Jewish and Georgian Socialists.     The prominence of non-Russian Socialists on the ExecutiveCommittee of the C.W.S.D. has attracted some attention and has beenused by the enemies of that body to discredit its activities.For example, out of the 40 members of the Executive Committee thereare 10 Jews and 2 Georgians, while the president (Chkheidze) isalso a Georgian.  The position of the Jews in the Socialist partieshas been dealt with in a previous report, in which it was statedthat the majority of the Jews were supporting the more moderateparties.  The same may be said of the Georgian Socialists.     The Georgian Social Democratic party came into existence in
1904, adopting orthodox Marxism as its programme together with theredistribution of land among the peasantry.   During the years ofreaction its leaders,  Chkheidze,  Tseretelli  and others, identifiedthemselves with the Russians and were persecuted in the same wayas the Russian Socialists. .  A few days after the Revolution, onMarch 25, the Georgian Social Democrats held a conference atTiflis.  At this conference  a small group declared themselvesMaximalists, but &quot;the majority - supported later by Chkhenkeli(a member of the late  Duma)  - gave their support to the RussianMinimalist party.  There is  also a small Social Revolutionaryparty modelled on the  same Russian party, but without its importance.     National feeling  is so  strong anongst the Georgians thatthe Socialists, in spite of  the importance of their leaders, aregreatly outnumbered.  The strength of nationalist feeling in theCaucasus is shown by the fact that when the  Socialist leaders returnto their native country they become far.less international thanwhen in Petrograd.  In this  connection it is interesting to con-trast the strongly international attitude of Chkheidze In Petrogradwith that of Chkhenkeli in Tiflis.   Though  both were members of -the 4th Duma and belonged to the same party, Chkhenkeli now standsfar more strongly for  Georgian interests than his friend andcolleague in Petrograd.                                            R.A.L.                                              16.7.17.          .

</content>
</cab>
