<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/20/0 images: 253-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
70,  205Sag C R J T.G.T.^1446            &quot;WAR dABIHEST*                   - IRISH CpNVENTION.                    Note &quot;by Mr.. Duke.      &apos;-&apos; The announcement e made-, in the course of the last fewdays with regard to the constitution of and arrangementsfor the Irish Convention appear to  have considerably revivedpublic! interest In this undertaking.   Such information aeI have been able to. obtain lea^ds. me to think that the.Extremists in Ireland are by nb means content with theirpresent position in the matter and may even yet desire to gainadmission for some of&apos; their spokesmen at the sittings of theConvention.   It appears, therefore, to have been a wise decisionby.which the question of representation of the O^rien andSinn Eein interests was left open until the Convention meets.       Among a very large part of the active politicians inIrelarid there is an urgent demand that the Government shouldmake some announcement which will; secure them against beingcommitted by the proceedings of the Convention to some Irishsettlement which might be rushed ihrough the two Houses ofParliament and passed into law, although.in fact it might notbe a settlement satisfactory to a majority of the Irishelectorate.  &apos;: This wish takes the form generally of a demand.fora Referendum - a demand which has been systematically presentedday by day for some weeks in the editorial columns of the&quot;Irish Independent&quot;, the most widely circulated of the Irishnewspapers.                                 -       The reasons against the announcement of a ReferendumUpon any proposed Irish settlement are to my mind obvious,and I know that some of the advocates of a&apos;Referendum recognisethe force of these seasons.   I think, however, it wouldprobably facilitate the work of the Convention to a greatextent if at the earliest time possible an announcementcould be authoritatively made&apos; in Parliament which wouldpresent a safeguard to those representatives of Irishopinion who, as  I think, honestly fear, an attempt at a suddensettlement by agreement of the Convention and consequentlegislation without any reasonable certainty that thesettlement would command - the support or acquiesoence of themasses of the Irish, people...   I hope it may be found possibleto&apos;make such a statement as I have indicated in the course ofthe- present week.(Initialled)  H.E.D.18th July,  1917.

</content>
</cab>
