<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/20/0 images: 369-370</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/if]5      speqial Work of the Local aetfernment Board forWeek ending July 20th.  1917.     1.   Among other subjects which ha?e engaged the attentionof the Department are:*     (a)  the subject of Man-Power,  with special reference tothe general dissatisfaction strongly expressed throu^i theTribunals at the continued exemption of young men in protectedindustries, and the need for the adoption of measures for making v*all fit men below a specifled age available for service.    Ajoint memorandum  on the situation has been circulated to theWar Cabinet;     (b)  preparatory arrangements for the establishment  ofSpecial Tribunals to deal with appeals for exemption from militaryservice on the part of subjects of Allied states in this  country.rendered liable for service under the Military Service (Con^en-tlons with Allied States)  Act on the conclusion of Conventionswith the Allied States concerned.     2.   A Conference of Local Authorities with the foodController has been attended at which general approval was givento an organisation for the better distribution of food based onthe co-operation of Local Authorities^  and to a scheme for therationing of sugar through the same  ageney*     3.   A deputation of representatives of friendly Societiesand Insurance Committees has been received privately by the      ;President, with Sir Edward Cornwall,  on the subject of the Billto give new powers to Local Authorities in connection withMaternity and Child Welfare.     4*   Observations of Local Authorities in the MetropolitanPolice District on the Draft Order embodying a Scheme ofDistribution of Coal submitted to them last week are beingconsidered.
     5.   A. confidential Circular has been issued to Mayorsof Metropolitan Boroughs containing suggested  arrangementsfor avoiding any delay in bringing the machinery for alleviatingdistress into effective operation in the event of Air Raidsand for facilitating any measures required to be taken.     6.   Circulars have been issued -      (l)  to local Authorities generally impressing on         them the importance of observing the party truce         in co-opting members to fill casual vacancies         occurring while local elections are in abeyance;      (2)  to Guardians urging the desirability, in view of         the restrictions on travelling, of avoiding the usual         routine visits to inmates of institutions etc.,         chargeable to them in the absence of any special         justification for ttie visits.     7.   An Order has been issued under the Venereal DiseaseAct, 1917, putting in force in 15 counties and 21 county borou^isas from November 1st next, the provisions of section 1 of theAct which prohibits the treatment for reward of personssuffering from venereal disease by other than duly qualifiedmedical practitioners.   /Schemes for the gratuitous treatmentof persons suffering from the disease being in operation inthe areas in question.     8.   The Departmental Committee appointed to make a preliminaryexamination of questions likely to arise in connection with theRepatriation of Belgian Refugees have presented an InterimReport, which has been brougbt to the notice of the BelgianMinister, and other Authorities concerned.local Government Board,    20th July, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
