<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/20/0 images: 387-396</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Report for Week  ending Wednesday,  July  18,  1917,                         PART  L-ACTION  TAKEN.                        CONTROL OF SUPPLIES AND PRICES.     Dealings in Crops.  The 1917 Crop (Restriction) Order, 1917, dated July 13, 1917, prohibits dealings without a permit issued under  the authority of the Food Controller, in any wheat, barley, oats or  rye of the 1917 crop grown in the  United Kingdom, or in any potatoes  of the 1917 crop grown  in the  United Kingdom other than first and second earlies.. Private contracts for the sale or disposition of any part of the crops referred to  are  cancelled, and. any infringement of  this Order is made a summary offence against the  Defence of the Realm Regulations.     Local Distribution and  Control:  At a Conference with representatives of the Scottish County Councils Association held on July  17, it was  explained that  Lord Rhondda proposed to set  up some local  authority throughout the country for the purpose of directing the distribution and control  of  essential foodstuffs and  that he invited criticism of the areas proposed and of the constitution of the authority.   The view of the Association was that County  Councils should be  empowered to constitute local food committees, embracing not merely the Counties but all Boroughs tfith a population of less than 20,000 within the County, and that  these  Committees should be allowed to delegate, to sub-committees such  of their functions  as  could not  con- veniently  be; discharged ,directly.  Lord Rhondda  expressed  his desire that the Committees  should be  large enough  to  include  labour,  w^omen, and  :Co6perative representatives, and it was agreed that a further conference  should be held after the views of the representatives of the Boroughs had  been ascertained.        ;     Sugar.--No further cargoes of sugar have  been lost during the past  week ; and it may be regarded as a matter of congratulation  that the  time  which has  elapsed since  the latest submarine  loss  constitutes a longer period of  immunity-from such losses than has occurred since February  1st last,     The Royal Commission  on  the Sugar Supply have forwarded a Memorandum to the Food  Controller  stating  their preference  for  a  modification of the  existing machinery; for  theolistribution of sugar  rather than the setting up of an entirely new system.                         &quot;---.j:y;            .     - :i-     Lord Rhondda has received a cable  from Mr. Hoover stating that it is proposed. to set up a Sugar Commission in the United States for the purchase  and control of sugar imports, especially from. Cuba  and Java,  and inviting the  cooperation of the Allied Sugar Commission so  as  to avoid - competition in buying.   Lord Rhondda, in reply, promised to/cooperate in every  way possible, and,  in respouse to a  further cable, furnished particulars of the quantities and prices  of  Cuban, sugar  bought by the Royal Commission since 1915.               -             ENFORCEMENT OF ORDERS.      The improvement in the work done  by Local  Authorities  in enforcing  Orders continues.  The City  of Westminster has been particularly active.  / At the instance of the Ministry a special&apos; inspection of the hotels, restaurants, arid clubs in the Borough was instituted, in  regard especially to  the practice  under the Public Meals Order. Prosecutions have been instituted in several  cases, and convictions  obtained.  Of special interest are the cases against the Ritz Hotel,  Carlton Hotel, Hyde  Park Hotel, Arthurs&apos;and Sports Clubs.   In all cases the Defendants were  fined sums up to 151. A large number of  prosecutions for contraventions  of the  Orders are reported from Bethnal Green, and fines up to 201. have been inflicted&apos;.  Many cases are pending..      Activity in Urban and Rural Districts is  also increasing.  In  one case reported from Halifax a baker was prosecuted for selling bread under weight, and the difficulties of the Order were pressed by the Defence.-  The  Bench declared  that  the Defendant. had done all that he could to meet the difficulties, and dismissed the case.   It  appears      A (33)3143-3 Pk 1  50 7/17  E k S -                                           A
from the newspaper report that the deficiency in weight was very small, as 24 loavesgave  an aggregate deficiency of only 230 drachms.   It has  been impressed uponinspecting  officers that prosecutions for under  weight are not  desirable where thedeficiency is&apos;small.         ^    Instructions have been issued that  stale  bread should be sold at a reduced priceor given away if it cannot be  disposed of. in. the. ordinary course of business.  In-stances, however, have come  to notice where large quantities of damaged cake andbread coming from Military Canteens  have been sold  for. pigs&apos;  food.  In  one  suchcase reported from Middlesbrough, the  Chief  Constable is in correspondence with the:G-.O.C.&quot;of the District.   It is in contemplation to  empower Local Authorities to grantlicences for the disposal of damaged bread.             PART  IT.-SUMMARY OF THE FOOD  POSITION.    Though  the  food position for  the  week exhibits few changes as compared withthat of the previous week, there are two features which deserve emphasis :     (1) The heavy importation of wheat noticed during  the last few weeks, has not          .only been  maintained, but has increased, that of the present week  being           a record since the outbreak of war.  The total import of other cereals also           is slightly  higher than the weekly average of the present year. - .  (2) A new table  (Table  H) is appended showing  the detailed  results of the           enquiry into  the consumption of bread and hWr during the last four or           or five months.  In  it the variations in consumption are displayed both )-:&apos;:.  &apos;     for the different geographical districts and also.for London  and. the large           towns as contrasted with the smaller  towns  and the rural districts  taken           together.   It  will be seen from  the Table as  also from  the paragraphs           dealing with  it, that these variations are considerable.  Certain facts are           important.  Had the course  of  consumption  during the  present  year           followed that of 1916, the rate  for June would  have been higher than it      ...&apos;.,-. actually was  by 12 per cent.  Moreover, the June consumption is lower, in           1917 than  in 1916, whereas in the earlier months consumption was greater           in 1917 than in. 1916, with the exception  of May, when the two rates were          practically the same.  ... -                 &apos;..:&apos;.&apos;.&apos;-&apos; -  :            IMPORTS.    The importation  of  principal foods (Table A)* reached  the very  high figure of363,600 tons  in the week ending July 14th.   The  increase over the previous week(61,600 tons) is exactly accounted for by the great importation of wheat, which (withflour)  amounted to 267,000 tons; this  equals  three  times the weekly average forMarch this year and two-and-half times that of  the  pre-war year, 1913.  The weightof wheat and  flour imported in the  28 weeks  since  January 1st, 1917, is 3 per cent.greater than in the corresponding period of 1916.    The imports of beef, mutton, bacon and hams together amount to very nearly thesame as last week and are above the average for.the  year so far, but  the  aggregatesince January 1st is 60,000 tons (11 per cent.) below that for the corresponding periodlast year.  Last week  the imports of beef were  small, but  those of mutton showed aconsiderable increase.         .    Margarine arrived  in considerable quantities, though, there is still a deficit of10 per cent, on the year.   Only 20,000 tons of sugar were received. .    Barley, oats and maize together last week exceeded the average for this year, but&apos;there  is still a deficiency of 182,000 tons (12 per cent.) since January 1st as comparedwith last year.    &apos;                    -;                                 .      &apos;;&apos; &quot;               CONSUMPTION OF MEAT AND BREAD.    &apos;     ;  7 Meat- The supplies of dead meat entering the markets of London, Manchester,Glasgow, and Liverpool in the week ending July 7th (Table B),were 4 per cent, lessthan in the previous week, though slightly above the June average; they were 81 percent, less  than the corresponding week of-1916.  In London a further fall of 8 per-cent, is shown in the week ending July 14th.              1             * A new column is added showing tbe average weekly imports in 1913.
  :   On the.other hand the supplies of fat  cattle  at 51  markets for the week ending July 11th were 6  per cent, above the previous week, 8^- per cent, above the average of June, 1917, and 16 per cent, above the corresponding week last year and equal to the  average of June, 1916.  The supplies of fat sheep show a further rise of 10 per cent, over the previous week; they were 5  per  cent, more  than in the corresponding-week of last year, but 2 per cent, below the average of June last year.  The supply of pigs continues small.         .   -     Bread-In the  Report for the  week  ended July 7th preliminary  figures  were given as to the results of an enquiry  on  a large scale into the quantity of flour used by bakers or retailed in June, 1916, and in May and June, 1917.  In response,to forms issued to bakers and retailers, so selected as to include a large proportion of those in the principal towns and probably over a  third  in the smaller towns  and  the rural districts, 7,400  returns were received giving detailed information.  The aggregate amount of flour included in the  returns  for the weeks  in May, 1017, was nearly 1,000,000 sacks, that is over 25 per cent, of  the estimated consumption in the United Kingdom.  An examination of the returns shows that  the  principal divisions of the Kingdom are adequately represented and  that reasonable weight is  given to  both urban and  rural districts.     From these returns it appears that the consumption of  flour  and bread in June, 1917, was 51 per cent, below that of the previous month and 2 per cent, below that of June, 1916.  Detailed figures are given in Table H.     Consumption in the  various months  oil 1916 and 1917 is expressed by way of-percentage on the level of May, 1917, that being the first month of this year for which detailed information is available.     For April and May, 1916, and for March and ApriL 1917, returns  were obtained from 600  to  700 bakers, using some 200,000 sacks.  Comparison of this smaller sample with the new return shows that the  former, while approximately adequate for measuring  the movement in the country as a whole, was insufficient for  dealing with separate divisions.  Earlier figures,  depending on more restricted information are only sufficient to indicate the general  movement; these are placed in brackets in the following table.   --;;  ;  Combining the results of the various enquiries wc have the following table : -       RETAIL CONSUMPTION OF BREAD AND FLOUR (measured in Percentages                            -from May, 1917).                                        1916.        1917.January   -      -     .-      -      -             (98)February  -   .   -    &apos;  -     S      -  (94)         (103)March    -             -     - .      -  (99)         109April     -      -      -             -  99-         104May      -      - :     -    .  -      - 100         100June     -             -   &apos;   -      -  96-1          91-^    This table is substantiated by the records of stocks and imports.    Two features call for notice.  First, there has been a continual and nearly uniformfall from March to June of this year of 4 or 5 per cent, per month.   The consumptionin June was one-seventh (13 per cent.) less  than that in  March.  Second, the  courseof consumption in 1917 differs  markedly from that in 1916.  In the latter year  con-sumption in the period under consideration reached its highest point in  May, a slightfall taking place  in June, with the  result that consumption  from March to Junediminished by 2\ per cent.  On the other hand  in  1917,  as  already  pointed  out,consumption  fell steadily  from March.  Not  only so, but the consumption in June1917 was perceptibly lower than in June 1916, whereas in each earlier month of 1917it was higher than in the corresponding month of 1916, except in May, when the tworates coincided.                     ^    One striking fact emerges.  Had consumption in the present year  followed thesame course as in 1916, it would have been higher during June than it actually was,by 12 per cent.;  Nor in view of the-prolonged severity of the weather and the greatscarcity of potatoes (except in Ireland) would such a course have been surprising.Indeed, these factors by themselves, would  have made probable a more accentuatedand sustained advance than that experienced in the preceding year.  -
      .     : The detailed table shows that the change is not uniform throughout the country.      ;  The South of England and Scotland shows a slighter diminution from-May-of this year        than the average ;  this is balanced by  a great fall.: in London, Yorkshire, and the    I        &quot;North:  In the Eastern Counties- the Midlands, Lancashire, Wales, and in Ireland, the     .;   fall is   per cent., as in the country as a whole.  This variation is closely connected      -with the distribution of urbanand manufacturing population ;  in general, though not        universally, the  big towns show a considerable fall, the small  towns less, while the       . consumption in rural districts is unchanged or has risen.  In the aggregate the table        records a fall  of .7 or 8 per cent, in London and the large towns, and only 4 percent.       . in the rest of England and Wales.,        -    When comparison  is made  with. a year  ago. equally striking differences are        observed, and  the position is partly reversed.   The North and Scotland show least fall       . or even  a  rise,  London is far below the  former June level, while in the country        districts there is little change.                                                 -     - -:     In the North of England where home baking is widely practised, purchases of       . flour have: diminished about 12 per cent,  from May to June, while purchases of bread       : have not. changed:  : This is attributed;  in some .returns  to the difficulty of baking        the flour provided:                               ;           &apos; -  -                            &apos;           WHOLESALE PRICES.                    -            The only changes since, the last Report are  in the prices  of barley, rice, meat,        bacon, butter,  cheese, and: oilcake (Table  D.&apos;:i:&quot;).            The price of barley after  falling 6s.  in  four weeks has advanced Is. 5d. and        reached 70s. lOd.  Rice had been stationary at 28s. 6a7.  since April 14th, and has now        fallen to 27s. 9d.                                            -  &apos;              ^       &quot;-&apos;    British beef and British mutton have fallen 3s. and 8s. &amp;d. per cwt. respectively,        in continuation of decreases of 4s.-Qd. and 6s.  reported last week.  Beef  is still dearer       -than  at the beginning of  June  and 15 per cent, above the price of March and April..W; -  Mutton is back at the price of the beginning of May,  but 12 per cent,  above that of       - March and April. -            &apos;         -&apos;::.-&apos;\&apos;    -                 .           : The price of Argentine beef has fluctuated during the last  three monthsits        lowest price was 95s. at the end of April,  its highest 119s. at the end of June; it fell        to 103s. by July 4th, and  recovered to lU7s. last  week.  Argentine mutton has        remained very nearly at 95s. since the beginning of May.;           Danish bacon has continued to  rise  in price,  sharply  in  the  last  week, and its -        supply is very  limited:  Butter fell  during June, but has risen in  the past fortnight.      -  Cheese fell 4 per cent, in the week ended  June 11.   Oilseed cake has risen 8s. or 10s.        and is now about the level of the end of May.                   * An  additional column is inserted in this Table showing prices in July, 1914,0
..:..;r.      -.TABLE Av-IMPO.RTS  OF/PRINCIPAL FOOD AND FEEDING  STUFFS.Article.. - 1. : -	-Week &apos; -, ending July 7 th, 1917. . 2. :	Week . ending . July 14th, 1917. -; 3. &apos;	: Corres- .&quot; ponding &apos; Week, 1916.	Average&quot; Weekly &apos;: Net Imports4 in 1913... 5. &apos;	Average Weekly-- - -- &quot;Imports.&quot;.&quot;- &apos;		&quot;--&apos;/. Total Imports.						28 Weeks. from Dec. 31st, 1916, to July 14th, 1917. 6.	Corres- . ponding Period, 1916. 7.	23 Weeks from Dec. 31st, 1916, to July T4th, 1917. 8.	. Corres-jjonding Period, 1916. &apos; 9.1. Wheat -2. Wheaten flour 3. Beef (fresh, refrigerated and frozen). 4. Mutton (fresh, refrigerated and frozen). 5. Bacon - -6. Hams -7. Lard 8. Margarine 9. Cheese 10. Butter -&apos; 11. Sugar (refined and un-refmed). 12. Sugar,glucose Total -13. Barley -14. Oats - -15. Maize - . -Total All principal foods and feeding stuffs. 16. Ricef - - -----17. Oil seeds and nuts and ; kernels.^ 18. Oilseed cake 	Tons. . 184,090 15,505 8,213 1,138 8,615 . 930 842 1,646 5,045 1,154 35,064 2,303	Tons. 245,665 . 21,360 3,804 t 4,830 9,267. 854 503 3,122 4,627 1,128 18,372 1,723	: Tons. 109,025 9,010 10,124 3,612 6,291 988 1,687 2,541 3,745 1,847 38,883 1,752	Tons. 101,378 9,712 8,849 5,125 j 5,267 1,629 1,460 2,137 3,867 37,333 1,408 -	Tons. 114,256 10,379 5,091 2,774 j 8,166 V 1,199 2,516 2,150 2,642 2,616 23,982 .1,350	Tons. 109,620 10,790 6,486 3,344 7,905 1,642 2,632 2,422 2,103 2,156 31,651 1,238	Tons. 3,199,175 290,620 142,542 77,669 228,655 33,560 70,435 60,196 73,990 73,253 671,486 37,814	- Tons. 3,069,355 302,140 181,594 93,633 221,333 45,970 73,691 67,826 58,894 60,364 886,233 v ; 34,664	264,575	315,255	189,505	178,165	177,121	181,989	4,959,395	5,095,697	2,690 21,675 13,003	4,330 11,600 i 32,400	16,080 6,750 14,895	21,565 17,464 46,450	.7,469 8,534 30,650	16,385 12,572 24,202-	209,145 238,945 858,200	- 458,795 352,015 677,650	37,365	48,330	37,725	85,479	46,653	53,159	1,306,290 1	1,488,460	. 301,940	363,585	227,230	263,644	223,774	235,148	6,265,685	6,584,157	- * -	i .	  ,	 	4,215 24,447 4,639	10,S69 30,942 3,771	108,999 632,123 119,958	282,589 804,486 98,051    * Imports less re-exports of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind,    t The weekly- returns as to the imports of rice refer  to  &quot;Rice of all kinds,&quot; and  apparently include considerablequantities of rice-meal;  data from the Monthly Accounts  relating to Trade and  Navigation have therefore been substituted,and the figures given relate to the six months January to June.   In  1916 there,  were substantial re-exports of rice, averaging,in January to June, 3,699 tons per week, as compared with 474  tons in January to Juue 1917.    J Weekly returns are not furnished for these articles, and the figures given relate to the six months January to June.
Period.	Supplies of Meat entering . Central Maiket, London			... % Supplies of Meat entering.. \ &apos; Manchester Market. *&apos;&apos;			: Supplies of Meat entering Glasgow Market *			Weekly Average.; ,		Percentage Change from 1916.	Weekly Average. -		Percentage Change from 1916. Per Cent. -13-3	- Weekly Average.&apos; -		Percentage Cliauge &apos; from. 1916.	1916.	1917.		.1916.	1917. Ions. 709		1916.	1917.	: - - -:;[r- V January February - : -March. -April -May - - -June Week ended: 7th July-14th. July -	Tons. 7,550	Tons. 6,927	Per Cent. - 8-3	Tons. 818			Tons. .711	- Tons; 678	Per Cent. 4-6	7,152	5,793	-19-0	786	638	-18-8	697 :	620	-11-0	6,391	&apos; 5,855	- 8-4	781	655	-16 1	706	; 667	- 5-5	.6,022	5,622	-6-6	735	618 1 -15-9		. 656	613	- 6-6	5,509	4,977	- 9-7	623	592	- 5-0	557	576	\ 3-4	5,920	4,904	-17*2	; 627	584	-.6-9	549	565	-f 2-9	5,447. 5,698.	5,000 4,608	- 8-2 -19-1	664.	571	-14-0	557	501	-10-1Period. .	Supplies of Meat entering &apos; - Liverpool Market.			. \&apos; . Total.						Weekly Average.		Percentage Change from 1916.	-&apos;Weekly Average.				Percentage , &apos; Change from 1916. ;		1916.	1917.		1916.		1917.			January -February - . -March. -April -May - -June - - -Week ended.: 7th July- -.	Tons. 401	Tons. .366	Per Cent. - 8-7	: Tons. 9,480		Tons. 8,680		&apos; Per Cent. -&apos; 8-4		371	348	- 6-2	.9,006		7,399		-17-8		.338	340	4- 0&apos;6	8,216		.7,517		- 8-5		321	315	- 1-9	7,734		: 7,168		- 7-3		299	311	* 4-0	6,988 .		6,456		- 7-6		295	302	4-2-4	7,391		6,355		-14-0		,296	295 i	- 0 = 3	6,964		6,367		- - 8-6	* Calculated from returns as to numbers of carcases, &amp;c, and assumed average weights.TABLEC-SUPPLIES, OF FAT STOCK AT  51 MARKETS IN  GREAT  BRITAIN.; Period.	Fat Cattle.		&apos; Fat Sheep.		Fat Pigs. &quot;-		- Weekly -Average, 1914-16.	Weekly ^Average, 1917.	- &apos;. Weekly Average, 1914-ltj.	: Weekly Average, 1917.	Weekly. Average, 1914-16.	Weekly Average, 1917. &apos;January -. February -. - - . - -March - -April . - . - .; -May -. - V: -- --. - &apos; - -;June --: - [ -^Week ended : . 4th July - -. - -1 1 lL T.-.1 &apos;-&apos; - ---------&apos; -......... ....	17,285	15,927	66,604	63,349	16,446	13,843	17,515	16,919	64,-578	57,491	13,938	11,205	18,065 j 17,920		65,809	65.397	13,709	11,042	. 16,768	17,300	70,330	62,599	12,104	11,500	16,575	18,009	71,220	59,216	12,298	11,408	1 .15,722	14,491	76,119	60,997 .	11,391	10^647	&apos;. 13,340 &apos; 13,515 &apos;	14,787 -15,720	69,519. 71,535	67,924 . 74,914	10,332 .10,364	7,598 - 7,61211th tluiy - - . - -j.						TABLE B-STATISTICS  ILLUSTRATING CONSUMPTION  OF. MEAT.
        TABLE D.- WHOLESALE PRICES OF  CERTAIN FOOD AND FEEDING STUFFS.     The prices given in the first column  of  figures are the latest available in eachcase, and necessarily relate, to somewhat different dates in regard to different  articles.Those for imported cereals (other than rice) and for flour and for oilseeds and cakerelate actually  to Monday,  July 16th.&apos;  The prices lor  rice, sugar,  and  tea  relateto week ended  Saturday, July 14th; those for  beef,  mutton,  bacon,  butter,  andcheese to.the week ended Wednesday, July 11th, and those for home-grown cerealsto the week ended Saturday, July 7th.     The prices given for imported wheat and maize are Wheat Commission prices ;the prices for meat,  butter, and. cheese  are, taken from the Board of  Agriculture^Returns  of Market Prices; for tea, sugar, and rice from the &quot;Grocer&quot;;  and foroilseeds and  oilseed  cake from Broomhall and; the &quot;London Grain, Seed,  and OilReporter.&quot;           .            .         .	&apos; Latest Price.	Week before.	Month before.	1 ear before.	July 1914. .Wheat. - British (Gazette average), per - -&apos; - . qr. (480 lbs.).&apos; &quot; No. 3 Northern Manitoba (Liverpool), per qr. (480 lbs.) Flour - New war flour (London), per .- sack (280 lbs.). ::: .Country straight run (London), per sack (280 lbs.). Barley - British (Gazette average), per qr. (400 lbs.). ; . Canadian&apos; (London), per qr. . (400 lbs.). . Oats - British ^Gazette average), per qr. (312 lbs.). Maize . - Plate (London), per qr. (480 lbs.). Rice . - Rangoon and Bassein, per cwt. -Beef. .&apos; - English, per cwt. -Argentine, chilled, per cwt. Mutton - English, per cwt. . -Argentine, per cwt. . -. -. -Bacon - Irish, green and dried, per cwt. -Danish, per cwt. -Canadian, per cwt. - - . -Butter - Irish creamery and factory, .-. per cwt. . Danish, per cwt. - - ; -New Zealand, at London, per cwt. &apos;&apos; &apos; Cheese - Cheddar (English), per cwt. -Canadian, per cwt. - -Sugar - English refined, Tate&apos;s Cubes, No. 1, per cwt. Granulated, fine, per cwt. Tea (in bond, duty Is. per lb.)  Indian, Pekoe Souchong, per lb. Pekoe, per lb. -. Ceylon. Pekoe Souchong, per lb. Pekoe, per lb. -Oilseeds - Linseed, Calcutta, at London, -&apos;.-:. per ton. - : Cottonseed, Egyptian, ; at London, per ton. Palm kernels, at Liverpool, per ton.&apos; Oilseed cake, London made linseed, at London, per ton. Egyptian cottonseed, at London, per ton. Palm kernel, at Liverpool, per : ...&apos; ton.	s. d. 78 2 : 79. 0 61 6 61 3 70 10 55 1 75 0 27 9 133- 0 107 0 143 : 6 .94 6 - 152 0 139 6 .128 0 . 188 0 213 0 . 200 0 $138 0 53&apos; 9 46 9 lld.-ls. 3d. lld.-ls. M. lid.-Is. 3d. lid-Is. Qd. 595 0 380 0 520 0 430 O 330 0 302 0	s. d. . 78 . 1 79 0 61 6 61 3 69 5 55 2 75 0 28 6 136 0 103 0 147 0 95 0 152 0 122 0 127 0 185 0 209 . 6 198 0 $143 .6j 53 9 46 9 Ud.-ls.3d. Is. id. lld.-ls.3d. lid-Is. 6d. 595 0 380 0 520 0 422 0 320 0 302 0	s. d. 78 2 79 0 61 6 62 6 75 6 55 1 75 0 28 6 136 6 108 0 159 6 95 0 150 0 111 6 125 0 184 0 204 6 188 0 $163 6 I $140 0 j &quot;l61 0 .53 9 49 6 Is. i]d.-ls.ld. Is. Ud.-Is. (id. Is. 4d.-ls. 6d. Is. id.-ls.Xl,d. 600 &quot;0 380 0 520 0 417 0 317 0 325 0	s. d. 48 11 *44 6 f40 0. . 47 3 43 6 31 6 52 0 18 3 102 0 79 6 108 6 88 0 114 6 110 6 97 0 &apos; 151 0 171 6 170 0 5104 6 92 6 47 1 41 7 9\d.-is. iy. 9hd.-ls.2d. 9^d.-ls. Id 9ld.-ls. Id. 382 0 260 0 380 0 256 0 189 0 162 0	. s. d. 34 1 136 7. *27 0 f24 3 24 10 23 8 19 10 26 10 11 6 59 0 44 6 73 0 40 6 . 74 6 68 0 62 0 107 6 125, 0 115 0 70 6 62 6 18 0 16 41 Sd.-ls,2d. &quot;hd.9\d. l^d.-Is. 2d. 152 0 165 0 155 0 94 0* Town Households:   .. f Country.Whites.    % For old cheese.    $ For new cheese.    ^ No. 2.                                                        -            A i:
TABLE  E* STOCKS of the PRINCIPAL FOODS and FEEDING  STUFFS  in  the                                   UNITED  KINGDOM.Article.	July 1st, 1917.	- , -June 1st, 1917.	July 1st, 1916.	Stocks in the United Kingdom including esti-nated . , - Farm Stocks.		Wheat (including flour) -Barley Oats - - - -Beans -Peas - - - - - ; Maize Rice (including ground rice and rice flour)	Tons. 1,360,000 f 165,000 264,000 45,000 14,000	Tons. 1,128,000 f 174,000 302,000 40,000 16,000	ions. 1,486.000 f90,000 245,000 30,000 11,000	Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, &amp;c.			124,000 &apos; 90,000	156,000 78,000	148,000 $90,000Butter   -Margarine       -Cheese  -       -       -Meat: Beef (chilled and frozen)        Mutton (chilled and frozen)        Bacon  -        HamsStocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and          in Importers&apos; Warehouses.21,000 4,10011,10015,70021,50054,10021,00019,600 2,200 5,80018,20020,80052.30018,50011,100 4,300 8,80020,20017,60050,10019,800Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded    Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.TeaCoffeeCocoa  .  * The figures for wheat and flour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, mills, and bakers&apos;shops, as well asestimated stocks on the farms ; those for barley,  oats, beans, and peas include stocks in port granaries and warehouses andin mills, and estimated  farm stocks.   In regard to all other articles, home produce is, with very small exceptions, excluaed    t Excluding stocks held by maltsters.  Stocks in maltsters&apos; hands on 1st July 1917, were 195.000 tons.  ,  j Estimate based on Trade Circular.                                  &apos;
       TABLE F-PERCENTAGE INCREASE  IN RETAILFOOD  PRICES  IN THEUNITED  KINGDOM,  AT EACH  OF THE UNDERMENTIONED DATES,  AS COMPARED  WITH                      ./.&apos;  &quot;NORMAL PRICES  IN JULY  1914.&quot;  [Compiled from information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Article.1st Jan. 1915.Beef:-  British-Ribs          Thin flank  Chilled or frozen-        Ribs .-        Thin flank -Mutton :   British Legs          Breast  Frozen Legs        ... Breast   -Bacon, streaky.*  .  -Fish -         -  :  -Flour     -    -Bread    -    -Tea -  : -    -Sugar, granulated  . -Miik     - .   -Potatoes  -Margarine   .  -Butter, fresh   -    -Butter, salt    -Cheese,  Canadian or  U.S.*Eggs, fresh    -    -    All above articles 7-011-216-326-7 5-811-716-324-8 7-140-20-   -9   -3 15-8 13-6 67-0  6-7p6-l  4-4 13-8 12-1 10-0 63-418-3Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.1st July 1915.37-245-946-263-829-042 341-061176448402767 9t5 415163323-632-51st Jan. 1916.35-345-24663&apos;27:41&apos;41-62-3096 49-0 41-7 48-2 93-3 28-8 -\4-8  6-9 33-9 31-5 31-7104-9 44-91st July 1916. 60-4 80-6 82-7102-2 55 79 85120 37 80 4,1.44 50:2158-0 33-1108-6 17-5 31-7 32-3 51-4-4-8-7-4\-5-.7-6-345-360-81st Jan. 1917. 64-2 83-5 85-4101-2 58-7 84-2 86-4122-0 56-3131-1 88-5 73-3 50-9170-0 56-6121-7 25-0 72-9 70-6 74-8175-086-81st May 1917. 79-6110-9104-3134-5 74-3111-2109-8162-1 79-0138-4105-2 97-0 68-6171-7 60-8142-3 55-9 73-3 69-8121-777-597-61st June 1917. 86-6121-0112-0146-2 94-2133-8126-0180-9 79-5134-2109-2 99-7 73-1178-4 59-9143-8 68-1 67-0 66-5123-485-4101-91st July 1917. 96-1132-2119-6156-5100 0142-2134-4190-8 76-4127-1109-3100-3 73-7187-7 59-7144-3 73-5 64-7 65-3108-0 95-3104-3t Detchreast!nd &quot; S6ld0m        V- * l0CaHty the Ee^rns 1uote Prices for a^er kind locally representative.TABLE  G.-SUBSIDIARY FOODS.:-MONTHLY RATES  OF INCREASE  OF RETAIL PRICES      IN LONDON,  EXPRESSED  AS PERCENTAGES OF THE PRICES  IN JULY  1914.  [Compiled from information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Article.    Period,   July 1914 to December 1916.(Monthly Average.)Butter beans  -    -Haricot beans -    -Lentils  -Split peas, yellowOatmeal (Scotch)       -Rice (Patua)  -  .,  (Rangoon)    -Sago ......    -    ..  .  -Tapioca -    -    -    Arithmetical Average    Average of Principal      Foods in Table F. -14433-1-1-2-2-2-92-9January 1917.February 1917.131329202727565027251814402711-3 2-031 = 6 3-3MarchJ917. 66122 38 13 26803742-4 2-3April1917.107 56 37 27 12 14 30  932-4 3-2Mav1917. 93*100* 131818-0\ 4-3t UecreasT&quot;5 ^      ^ figures are based cover tie period between 1st June and 2nd July,June* 1917.27]4o\4025]2^272-lt2-4
 .:   TABLE H. CONSUMPTION OIVFLOURBY BAKERS  AND RETAILERS.Four weeks ended June 24th, 1916, and-May 26th and June 23rd, 1917.&apos; Distiict.* --&apos;	Number of -Returns.:	100 Sacks.			..&apos;: Percentages.				June 1917.	May 1917.	June 1916.	June 1917.	May 1917.	Jung 1916.UNITED KINGDOM : v -Total -1. London - - -, . -2. Southern -3. East and East Midlands - &apos;\-4. Midlands/: &apos;-&apos; -&apos;:&quot;.\-&quot;&apos;--5. Lancashire and Cheshire - - -6. Yorkshire - : - - -7: Northern - -; 8: Wales -. - - - -ENGLAND AND WALES:&apos; - Total - &apos; -SCOTLAND - - - - -: -IltELAND - - -ENGLAND&quot; AND WALES :  &apos; Boroughs, other than London, .. &apos; with population over 50,000. Smaller towns and rural districts	7,439	9,419	9,979	9,639		100	96^	-500 . 1,305 .707 1,004 679 742 649 663	1,178 1,028 638 1,164 1,097 738 . 815 415	1,285 1,061 668&apos; 1,224 1,155 821 885 435	1,303 1,070 646 1,188 1,121 709 817 428	92 97 95V 95 95 90 &apos; 92 -951	ioo ! 101 100 101 100 ! 97 100 1 97 100 97&apos;&quot; 100 i 86J TOO ! 92&apos; 100 j 9H		6,249 682 508	7,073 1,404 .... 942	7,535 1,449-995	7,281 1,391 967	94 &apos;.&apos; 97 95	100 100 100	96l2 96 97	1,250 4,499	2,895. 3,000	3,117 3,134	2,956 3,023	93 96	100 100	95 96                   * Contents of districts :-      -                     -1. County of London.    -                 ;          .....  --&apos;-.;.                      2. All counties South of the Thames, and Wilts, Somerset, and South-Western.                     - 3; Lincoln, Hunts. Beds, Herts, Middlesex, and  astern Counties.                      4: All counties not otherwise included.        .                      I!. Excluding Cleveland.                      7.. Cleveland, Durham, Westmorland, Cumberland, Northumber&apos;ahd, and Berwick.                    .  S. Wales and Monmouth.                                         -I  .

</content>
</cab>
