<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/20/0 images: 463-470</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J  SECRET.Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information.DGW/008.WEEKLY REPORT ON GREECE. VIII.(July 21,  1917).Salonika and for this purpose a conference was held at Keratsini&quot;on June 21 between two Ministers of either Government.    It was hoped that an agreement would be reached as to the removal of undesirable elements from the army and administration, and that the  Government  of Mr Zaimis, to which ciertain Venizelists might be added); would stay in office until this awkward moment had passed. It was \ however, found to be quite impossible for the tv/o sides to agree; and it became clear that no thorough-going change  could be expected so  long as Mr Zaimis remained in office.  Apparently from the  side of Mr Zaimis came a suggestion that an ex-Venizelist Minister, Mr Raktivan, a man of very moderate views, should form a transition Government, but this was most inacceptable to the Venizelist party.   Finally M. Jonnart took the bull by the horns: on June 24 he presented a note to Mr Zaimis demanding that tho Chamber elected on December 19, 1915, should at once be dissolved and the Chamber of June 13, 1915, should be summoned.  It was impossible for  Mr Zaimis to accept these terms, and he at once announced his indention to resign, an intention which he  carried out three  days later.   The King at once summoned Mr Venizelos to form a Government, most of  the members of which had hitherto  been members
     of the Cabinet of National Defence at Saloniki.          On the vhole the ohange was accepted with anpp  surprising     unanimity in Greece,  and the attitude of the- anti-Venizelist     press, which has become far more amenable as many of the     editors at once gave  up the direction of their papers on the     news of the abdication of King Constantine; has been, if not     enthusiastic, at least acquiescent.  On the King&apos;s departure     from Greece they had enjoined the nation not to cause any     disturbance since this was the wish of the martyr King.  &quot;He     would be a poor patriot who would put his personal or party     feeling above his loyalty to his Sovereign&quot;.   They clearly hoped*     ^owever, that Mr Zaimis would remain in office, and for this     purpose they preached &quot;reconciliation11;  perhaps the less     sincere elements among them hoped to carry on their anti-     Venizelist intrigues under the cover of Mr Zaimisf colourless  /     Government.    Mr Venizelos *. speedy return to power came as a     severe shook to them, but not nearly so severe as if it had been     at once imposed by M. Jonnart simultaneously with the departure     of King Constantino.  In fact; there has been little disturbance;-     Mr Venizelos had an enthusiastic reception on his arrival at     Athens on June 14/27 when he addressed the crowd from the balcony     cf the Hotel Grande Bretagne,  But for a few local riots, anti- ..     Venlzelist feeling has found little open expression., and on     July  2 the commanders of the various military forces in Central     Greece and the Peloponnese almost without exception took the     oath  of loyalty to King Alexander in the presence of Mr Venizolos.     The removal of the Greek Army from tho Peloponnese will begin     about July 26.   Though the anti-Venizeiists can hardly be     expected to welcome the new regime enthusiastically, they at((k    least acquiesee in it sullenly, for they realise it is the only
 one which can either suit the country or satisfy the Entente Powers;  In any  case they are leaderless and realise their powerlessness in face of the enthusiasm of  the people  as  a wholt  and the determination of the  Powers.   ; Ihe new Goviment is proceeding to take certain  very definite steps to emphasise its  character and the meaning of  the/change..:..      (1) Though, strictly speakingi: there are to be no &quot;reprisals&quot;, the Government holds that proper punishment must be inflicted on those  persons responsible for the  outrages  on Venizelists, particularly on  December 1 last.  The bodies of  many of the victims have been exhumed and it is intended to  try and punish those  responsible for these murders.    A strict  inquiry is  also being  held into  the conduct of those officers, ecclesiastics  and members of the civil administration who abused their official positions for party and personal ends.  Many of  the Generals are to be removed, as also Thcoklitos  (Metropolitan of Athens), and other members of the Holy Synod who were concerned in the ridiculous ceremony of anathema  some months ago.  The  law of immovability of  civil servants is  temporarily suspended in  order to purge the service of unworthy and incompetent elements.      (2) King Alexander is at present on his Throne only by grace of the designation of King Constantine  and  the approval of  the Protecting Powers.  Mr Venizelos has no intention of accepting this  as anything more than a working arrangement for the  time being He intends at once to proceed to the re-assembling of  the Chamber elected on June  13, 1915, and this,  it  is hoped, will  take  place on July 25.   In the Introductory  report accompanying  the decree recalling the dissolved Chamber  (a report drawn  up by  Mr  Repoulis, Minister of the  Interior, and signed by the Cabinet) occurs this passage: ,         ,     &apos;  ;;&apos;;:;-;V;-;:\v-;:;:;:
          &quot;The  Chamber  cannot be  dissolved if it finds itself     in disagreement with the Crown.   The  will of the people,     as expressed by the  Chamber, and not  that of the Sovereign,     regulates  the policy of Parliamentary Governments.   The     King is but a functionary  of the State whose actions are     strictly limited.     He is the hereditary head of a     Republic.     In Republican Monarchies such as Greece,.     whose constitutional liberties were obtained by the     people and not conceded by the Sovereign, any interpretation     of the clauses of  the Constitution that may from time to     time be required has to be made  by the people and not by     the Sovereign&quot;.So far King Alexander has made  some difficulties aboutsigning the decree, but there  is no doubt that Mr Venizeloswill insist fimrly on  thisV   He has  no Intention of leavingthe question of the constitutional character of the Monarchyin doubt, and intends  at the  earliest possible moment toproceed to the  election of a  Constituent Assembly which willsettle the question once and for all.   Meanwhile at the openingof the Chamber on July 25 the  Prime Minister intends to includein the Speech from the  Throne  certain statements clearing upbeyond a doubt the facts of King Constantine&apos;s final abdicationand King Alexander&apos;s  succession.  If  the latter refuses toaccept this speech, Mr -Venizelos foresees that it miy benecessary to replace  him by Prince Paul and a Regency.      (3) The international position of Greece has at once beenmade plain.  On June 29 the Greek Ministers at the Courts of thefour Powers of the Central Alliance were notified of theirrecall  and the consequent existence of a state of war between
 Greece  and the  Central Empires.  Mr Venizelos has announced his intention of  calling  up  the  classes of 1916 and  1917  for training  in a month or s  ix  weeks.  He states that  there are already 60,000  Greek  troops  in the field,  that the  levies from the  Islands will &quot;bring this  up to 100,000, and that eventually it is hoped to  mobilise  Greece1s full fighting strength. Thus, the question of war or pease has not been  brought up  as  a debatable subject,  but the Greek people finds itself  automatically at war.   Mr Veniselos, however, will presumably  be  wary as  to how  quickly he  applies the new levies to those parts  of the country where feeling has hitherto been strongly anti-Venizelist and  neutralist. Relations of  the Entente  Powers to the New Government.     The  change of Government at once entailed important conse- quences in the  attitude  of the Powers to Greece.      (1)  On June 15 the blockade was raised fend  Greece reoeived, under certain modifications, the status of a friendly Power. The  question  of food  supplies for the country is being dealt with. In future, supplies will  be  brought from India or Australia rather than from America.  As for the Greek shipping taken over by the Allies, some  feeling  has  been roused by the fact that the French propose to retain  some 20,000 tons of small coasting  vessels, leaving only  10,000 tons  at  the disposal of the  Greek Government. His  Majesty&apos;s charge  d!Affaires at Athens  suggests  certain, alleviating measures.      (2)  The  Greek Minister  of Marine was  very anxious that the  ships of  the Greek navy  taken over by  the French  naval authorities should at once be returned.  The French at first agreed  to hand  back 5 torpedo boats, retaining 12 destroyers at
Corfu.    Finally on July 18 Mr Venizelos  learnt officiallyfrom the French Government that  the  Greek ships In the Frenchservice would now be restored to the Greek Navy.     (3) M. Jonnart, before leaving  for France, declared himselfin favour of Greece1 s financial  needs being met by the EntentePowers, and an Anglo-French loan of   4,000,000 to Greece wasrumoured on July 9.     (4) Steps have already been taken to end as far as possiblethe Allied controls of various services.   It is hoped to dispenseentirely with the military control,  while the control of postsand telegraphs may be modified by the admission of Greekrepresentatives to their Boards.  For the present it is decidedthat the Allied representatives  should be authorised to concludewith the Greek Government temporary arrangements for the workingof their several controls, pending their final abolition.     (5) The withdrawal of Allied troops from Greek soil hasalready been proceeded with.   The French, on July 15, had alreadyagreed to evacuate before July 23 Athens, Piraeus and the Gulfof Corinth, though remaining at  Larissa.   (Owing to the limitedcapacity of the Greek railways it will take some 20 days towithdraw the French troops from Old Greece).    The Italianoccupation of Epirus, where French and Italian forces had nearlycome into collision, was particularly displeasing to the GreekGovernment, and various negotiations have been carried on by theHigh Commissioner, Mr Venizelcs  and the Italian Minister atAthens with a view to their withdrawal.   The Italian Governmentmade the object ion that the ir o ccupat ion was merely a c ounterwe ightto the French occupation of parts of Thessaly and Epirus, but
they agreed to withdraw their troops simultaneously with theFrench evacuation of occupied territory and the Ionian Islands -Corfu, Thasos (this,, however, is now being evacuated), Milosand the zone of the Saloniki armies excepted.    The onepoint which they were unwilling to give up was the corner ofland opposite Corfu guarding the Santi Quaranta Road,Mr Venizelos himself suggests that all French and Italiantroops should be withdrawn, but that, as General Sarrailintends to leave French cavalry patrols along the Larissa-Brallos-Ithea road, Italian cavalry might participate inthese patrols and also patrol the Santi Quaranta Road.Greco-Italian Relations.     If the Italian Government declines this proposal, Venizeloshas declared his intention of appealing to the Allied Powersas&apos;a whole.   It is absolutely necessary for him to get somesatisfaction on the subject of the Italian occupation ofEpirus before the Chamber meets, as there is universalindignation both among his followers and his opponents inGreece at Italy&apos;s action.   Mr Venizelos has done everything inhis power to conciliate Italy and to seek to remove Italianapprehensions as to Greek aims.  So long ago as Deember 1 lasthe gave an interview to the Secolo at Milan in which he setforth the point of view that Greek and Italian interestswere really not incompatible, but the Italian Censor onlyallowed it to appear on June 28, after seven months&apos;  prohibition.Similarly an interview has been given to the Secolo  byMr Mikhalakopoulos, the new Minister of Public Works, whichdwells on the necessity and naturalness of good relationsbetween the two countries.    Till, however, some proper
arrangement is reached over Bpirus  and  the  other  territorialquestions at issue  between Greece  and Italy, relations betweenthe  two countries  must remain strained.                                   v A.K.A.L.                                        21.7.17.i

</content>
</cab>
