<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/44/12 images: 88-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1944.SECRET.W.M. (44)141st Conclusions.Copy No.WAR CABINET 141 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Thursday, 26th October, 1944, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Minister for Civil Aviation.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel The Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Items 1and 2).The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of State.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.[28568-2]
WAR CABINET 141 (44).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      International Civil Air Transport   ....      ....      ....      ....     165Montreal and Chicago Conferences.Innocent Passage.American Leased Air Bases in the West Indies.2      Civil Air Transport    ..................&quot;..      .... 167Future Organisation.3      Street Lighting in the London Area        ............ 1684      Prisoners of War       ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      .... 1685      Ethiopia.................................. 1686      Post-War Army        ........................ 168
International 1.   The War Cabinet had before them two memoranda by theCivil Air Minister for Civil Aviation  (W.P. (44) 592 and W.P. (44) 593)Transport. setting forth the policy which the Minister proposed to pursue at the montreal and International Conference on Civil Air Transport at Chicago.CmcaS0 The Minister for Civil Aviation said that he hoped to haveConferences.    discussions with the Commonwealth delegates at Montreal before(Previous       the opening of the International Conference.   The reports which reference:      he had received from Montreal were, on the whole, encouraging.   ItW.M. (44) 136th seemed that agreement would be reached on the establishment of a conclusions,     Joint Empire Advisory Council and on the layout of Empire airMinute 4.)      routes; and although Canada would not join in a single Common-wealth Corporation to run all the Empire services, it seemed likely that there would be agreement on a combined company for theUnited Kingdom, Australia, New Zealand and India services.   a combined company might also be possible for the services betweenthe United Kingdom and South Africa.   The formation of these companies would make it easier to secure close working arrange-ments between the various Commonwealth services.Unfortunately-the leader of the Canadian delegation favoured the proposal, which it was feared that the United States Govern-ment would put forward, for a period of unrestricted competitionimmediately after the war, during which the United States wouldhave a great advantage over all other countries, to be followed bya distribution of frequencies in proportion to the traffic carried inthis period. We ought to oppose this suggestion, and to insist thatthe distribution of frequencies should be in proportion to passengers and freight embarked from each country. -The line which the Minister proposed to take was to make astrong effort to secure the agreement of the United States to aConvention covering frequencies, quotas and rates on the lines setout in the White Paper (Cmd.. 6581). If this failed,, we should not attempt to establish a Convention excluding the United States butembracing the Dominions and such foreign countries as were willingto join it, since this would be regarded :as a lining up of countriesagainst the United States. Rather, we should try to secure aConvention with the United States on a narrower basis coveringtechnical matters such as safety regulations and face the possibilityof dealing with frequencies, quotas and rates by means of bilateral negotiations. In this event he would attach great importance to ouracting in combination with the Dominions and not independently.We should also try in our bilateral negotiations to secure theadoption of standard clauses, so that in the course of time it mightbe possible to secure by a series of bilateral agreements very much the same results as would be achieved by a multilateral Convention.He would make it plain that.it would be a condition of anybilateral agreement between the United Kingdom and the UnitedStates that frequencies, quotas and rates would have to be covered,and he would in any event, for the reasont, set out in paragraph 9 of w.P. (44) 592, refuse to make any bilateral agreement while he wasin America.The following were the main points made in the ensuingdiscussion : (a) The Lord Privy Seal said that he was in general agreementwith the proposals made by the Minister for Civil Aviation. Itwas, however, most important that we should enter the international conference with the fullest possible support from the Dominions.If the Minister for Civil Aviation could meet Mr. Howe and could offer to make some concessions to, the Canadian point of view onrelatively minor points, it would, he thought, be possible to obtainthe support of the Canadian Government for our main thesis.With regard to the International Conference, our aim shouldbe to secure some agreement with the United States even though they were not prepared to go as far as we should like, since it was important that the International Conference should not break up with the United States and ourselves in disagreement. We must remember that the United States were in a very strong position.[28568-2] b 2
(b) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs emphasised the importance of avoiding a break with the Canadian Governmenton this issue. Rather than this, he would prefer to see a convention of more limited scope.(c) The Lord President of the Council said that, while he supported the view that we should attempt to get the greatestmeasure of agreement with the Dominions, he felt we should notneglect the support for our views which we might get from foreigncountries, and should not yield too easily to the American desire to exclude frequencies, quotas and rates from the proposed Convention.This view was supported by the Minister of Labour and NationalService.,(d) The Secretary of State for Air pointed out that therewould be support for the principles set out in the White Paper, notonly in the Dominions and among foreign countries, but also amongmany sections of public opinion in the United States itself. If theUnited States Government were not willing to enter into a Conven-tion governing frequencies, quotas ,and rates, he would be in favourof trying to reach agreement on a Convention which, so far as con-cerned ourselves, the Dominions and such foreign countries as were willing to agree to it, would govern frequencies, quotas and rates,but which the United States Government would join only in so faras it governed technical matters. He would like to see an attemptmade on these lines before we resigned ourselves to a policy ofbilaterial agreements.(e) In further discussion there was general support for thepolicy outlined by the Minister for Civil Aviation. It was agreed,however, that a further attempt should be made to bring theCanadian Government into line with the other Dominion Govern-ments before the opening of the International Conference.(/) The Prime Minister said that it was important that weshould lose no opportunity of developing air services between theUnited Kingdom and Russia. During the Moscow Conference a service between London and Moscow had been provided by Mosquitoaircraft and there was good reason to hope that the Soviet Govern-ment would be prepared to agree to a continuing service of thiskind if we would make available to them a number of Mosquitoaircraft which they might use for a return service between moscow and London. He hoped this request would be met and that every-thing possible would be done to establish free traffic between Russiaand the United Kingdom.Summing up the discussion the Prime Minister said that itwas clear that the policy outlined by the Minister for Civil Aviationhad the general support of the War Cabinet, who had the greatestconfidence in his ability to conduct the difficult negotiations whichlay before him. His first task would be to secure the highest possible measure of agreement with the Dominion Governments represented at Montreal. For this purpose he should seek an early interview with Mr. Howe with a view to obtaining as much support as possible from the Canadian Delegation at the International Conference,and avoiding any tendency on their part to yield to the UnitedStates suggestion for a period of unrestricted competition to befollowed by a distribution of frequencies based on the experience ofthat period.. At the International Conference he would contendfor the White Paper policy, but if it proved that the United StatesGovernment would not in any circumstances accept this policy, heshould not press the matter to the stage of open disagreement orattempt to secure a Convention with the Dominions and other foreign countries, which would exclude the United States. Ratherhe should try to secure agreement on a Convention of limited scopeto which the United States Government would be a party, and rely on securing our aims at a later stage by a series of bilateral agree-ments. Generally, he should not press the pace of the negotiations,and should not hesitate to seek fresh instructions from the War
InnocentPassage.American-.Leased air bases in theWest Indies.Cabinet should any point of difficulty arise. He would, of course,keep the War Cabinet fully informed of the course of the negotia-tions. His attitude to the Eire representatives who would beattending the Conference should be one of reserve.The War Cabinet-(1) Gave general approval to the policy outlined by the Ministerfor Civil Aviation in W.P. (44) 592, subject to thenegotiations being conducted on the lines indicated bythe Prime Minister.The War Cabinet next considered the &quot; Minister for CivilAviation&apos;s suggestion in W.P. (44) 593 that at the ChicagoConference he should try to get all countries, while maintaining the sovereignty of their own territorial air space, to agree to theright to innocent passage, i.e., to fly over a foreign country. He was satisfied that this would be in the interests of the British Empire.The Secretary of State for Air pointed out that in the white paper on International Air Transport we had been careful to makeit clear that all four freedoms of the air should be enjoyed by theStates ratifying the proposed new air convention, provided they accepted in full the rest of the convention. He doubted whether itwas wise to concede the right of innocent passage in advance of theconclusion of a satisfactory air convention on the lines which we had proposed.(2) The general view of the War Cabinet was, that in view ofour interest in securing the right of innocent passage,the Minister should have discretion to concede this rightif the other countries at the Conference were preparedto do likewise.The Minister for Civil Aviation said that the United StatesGovernment might ask that these air bases should be available for american Civil Air Lines. If a satisfactory comprehensive con-vention was agreed upon, this issue would not arise. If, however,we were driven back on bilateral negotiations, he thought that no concession should be made, and that he should state that thisquestion,- in common with other landing facilities, would be dealtwith in the bilateral negotiations which must follow at a later date.The War Cabinet-(3) Approved this suggestion.civil air transport.future organisation(previous reference:Minute 2.)* 2. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister for Civil Aviation (W.P. (44) 585), setting out his viewson the organisation of civil air transport.The Minister for  Civil  Aviation explained  that  it was unnecessary to reach a decison on this matter before he left for theChicago Conference, but that he would welcome a decision at an.M. (44) 132nd early date after his return.In discussion it was suggested that it would be a help if a report could be prepared showing what facilities would be required inthis country for international civil air transport and for internallines, together with an estimate of their cost. Whatever schemeof organisation for civil air transport was adopted would have totake into account the heavy running expenditure on facilities, andalso the capital expenditure involved, subject of course to appro-priate abatement in respect of capital expenditure incurred forwar purposes and subsequently taken over for civil air transport.The Minister for Civil Aviation said that he would give instructions for the necessary material to be prepared. On his return from the United States he would consult with the other ministers concerned and submit a report to the War Cabinet.
street lighting inthe london area.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 128thConclusions,Minute 7.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theHome Secretary and Minister of Home Security (W.P. (44) 577),reporting the position about street lighting in the London area.The Secretary of State for Air reported that the Chiefs of staff were preparing a reassessment of the likelihood and possible scale of air attack against the United Kingdom. He understood thatthis report would show a great decrease in the strength of theGerman long-range bomber force. The War Cabinet would be ina better position to deal with this matter when the revised assessmenthad been completed. *The War Cabinet &apos;Decided to resume consideration of this matter in afortnights time.Prisoners 4.   The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theof War. Secretary of State for War (W.P. (44) 554) covering a note sum-previous       marising the facts concerning the murder of prisoners of war by the reference:       Germans.   This note had been prepared to meet the request made toW.M. (44) 134th the Secretary of State by the War Cabinet on the 9th October.Conclusions, -p^ v^ar Cabinet-Minute 5.)Took note of this report.Ethiopia. 5.   At their meeting on the 20th October the War Cabinet(Previous had invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for the reference: Committee on Policy in Ethiopia to be re-convened in order toW.M. (44) 139th consider what further instructions should be given to LordConclusions,     De La Warr.Minute 2.)The War Cabinet now had before them a report from theCommittee (W.P. (44) 594) and authorised the Minister of state to send further instructions to Lord De La Warr, as regards the ogaden and the Reserved Areas in Harar, on the lines set out inparagraph 3 of the report.Post-War 6.   The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theArmy. Secretary of State for War (W.P. (44) 575) reporting the steps which he was taking to prepare plans for the reconstruction of theregular army during and after the war. The main point of thememorandum was the need for a decision, or failing that for an assumption for planning purposes, about whether some form of compulsory military service would be continued after the war.In discussion it was pointed out that there would be great advantage if this matter could be dealt with by agreement betweenthe three main political parties. It was also suggested that itwould be convenient if the matter could be dealt with, not inrelation to a single service, but to the general aspects of our defence policy after the war; and that the matter was one which could wellfee examined in the first instance by a Cabinet Committee.The War Cabinet-Agreed that this question should be examined by a CabinetCommittee, and took note that the Prime Minister wouldgive further consideration to its membership and terms ofreference.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,26^ October, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
