<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/5/36 images: 354-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)36th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT-UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 36 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1. on Thursday, February 8, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville ChamberlainThe Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air., M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. F. Hemming.Wing Commander W. Elliot.[20805]
WAR CABINET 36 (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. Page.1      The Air Situation     ........ ......   .,.........     2772      The Naval Situation..................     277First Canadian Division: third convoy.Norwegian convoys.Shipping losses.Attacks on U-boats.Proposed seizure of German supplies to U.S.S.R.3      The Military Situation        ...............     278S.S. Munster.The Western Front.Finland.Supply of Military information from Finland.4      Assistance to Finland ...       ...      ...       ...       ...       ...     278International Volunteer Force: Mr. Kermit Roosevelt suggested as Commander.5      German-Soviet Relations     ...      ...       ...      ...      ...     278Alleged cession to Germany by the U.S.S.R. of districts in Poland.6      The Far East: Relations with Japan      ...      ...      ...     279The case of the S.S. Asama Maru.7      Eire      ...       .....................     279Internal situation.8      Vote &quot; A &quot; Estimates.................. 2799      Bacteriological Warfare      ...      ...       ...      ...      ... 28010      War Cabinet Business ...       ...      ...       ...      ...      ... 280
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 35thConclusions,Minute 3.)1. The Secretary of State for Air said that, with theexception of three Fighter Patrols, there had been no operations by fighter or Bomber Command, or by the British Air Forces inFrance, on account of bad weather and visibility. Operations hadbeen hampered further by the bad state of our aerodromes, which,however, were improving.There had been little or no activity on the part of the enemy.A number of Coastal Command patrols had also been prevented by bad weather.At 0-53 hours on the previous day the crew of an Anson hadsighted an enemy submarine on the surface 32 miles north of CapeWrath. The submarine had submerged before an attack could be delivered. Two 100-lb. anti-submarine bombs had been dropped, oneof which was observed to have burst close to the submerged hull.No damage, however, had been seen.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.   ,.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 35thConclusions,Minute 4.)First canadian division:third convoy.Norwegianconvoys.Shipping losses.2. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the CanadianTroop Convoy, with its escort, had arrived on the morning of theprevious day.Attacks onU-boats.Proposed seizure of Germansupplies toU.S.S.R.The outward-bound Norwegian Convoy and its escort wereapproaching the Norwegian Coast. It had been arranged that thenext homeward-bound Norwegian Convoy should be run in two parts.The Estonian ship A nu (1,421 tons) had been mined in a prescribed area in the approaches to the River Tay during the night of the 6th-7th February. Thirteen survivors out of a crew ofnineteen had been landed.The British and Irish Steamship Company&apos;s Munster(4,305 tons) had been mined outside Liverpool at 6 a.m. on the7th February. The passengers and crew had been landed safely.The presence of German mines in this area was known, and achannel had been cleared. The accident had been due to the Munsterlosing her way in fog. On the suggestion of the Prime Minister, theFirst Lord agreed that the Admiralty should issue a statementgiving the facts, so as to correct the false impression which had beengiven in the Press that the loss of the Munster had been due toI.R.A. action.H.M.S. Delight had carried out an attack on a contact 20 miles east of the Orkneys, with no visible result, at 6 p.m. on the7th February.At 1-45 p.m., in a dense fog, the British Cable Ship Alert hadrammed and sunk the French Patrol Vessel Veteran off Cape GrisNez.   There had been no casualties.There had been no news of the two German ships believed tobe carrying munitions to Murmansk, but the search was continuing.i&quot;20805]
The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 35thConclusions,Minute 5.)S.S. Munster.The western front.Finland.Supply ofmilitaryinformationfrom Finland.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 34thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Secretary of State for War said that there had been59 Other Ranks on board the s.s. Munster (see previous Minute), all of whom had been saved.There was nothing to report from the Western Front.Soviet attacks on the Karelian Isthmus were continuing.Though these attacks were undoubtedly producing a strain on the finns, who enjoyed no respite, they were, at the same time, verydiscouraging to the Russians, who were suffering enormouscasualties. So far, the War Office had received no evidence thatthe Mannerheim Line was breaking, but accurate, up-to-date infor-mation was difficult to obtain. The Military Attaches were not allowed to visit the front line. Meanwhile, instructions had beentelegraphed to our Military Attache on the previous day to cable an appreciation of the present situation. It was hoped that furtherinformation would also be forthcoming from an Assistant military attache, who wa,s about to be sent to Finland, and from BrigadierLing, who would shortly be returning to that country.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Assistance to finland.Internationalvolunteer force.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 24thConclusions,Minute 4.)Mr. KermitRooseveltsuggested as commander.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 24thConclusions,Minute 9.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he hadreceived a letter from Mr. Gibson, of the Finnish Aid Bureau,asking whether there would be any objection to Mr. KermitRoosevelt being asked to take command of the International force which was being organised to go to the help of Finland. TheForeign Secretary said that he saw no objection from the political point of view.The Secretary of State for War pointed out that Mr. KermitRoosevelt held a commission in the British Army, and that serving officers had not been allowed to join the International Force. Hewould, therefore, like an opportunity to consider the matter further.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theSecretary of State for War to consult in regard to the reply to be sent to this application.German-Soviet 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionRelations. to telegram No. 65 from His Majesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires, Moscow,Alleged cession dated the 6th February, 1940, submitting a Report from Mr. Trantto Germany by and Mr. Russell, who had just returned from Lemberg. This Reportthe U.S.S.R. of  might be summarised as follows : districts in In spite of careful inquiries, Mr. Trant and Mr. RussellPoland. had been unable to obtain conclusive evidence of the presence(Previous of German armed forces in the Lemberg area.Reference: Information had been obtained from local residents, whoW.M. (40) 24th appeared to be reliable, that 40 long trains of German troopsConclusions, and material had crossed the  German-Soviet  frontier atMinute 5.) Przemsyl between the 21st and 24th January,  1940; that important German mechanised forces were now quartered inthe vicinity of Lemberg itself; and that it was possible thePolish oil fields were under German Military protection. Inaddition, a party of about 50 German officers were said to been gaged in repatriation work in the Lemberg area.
The Minister without Portfolio said that information receivedfrom secret sources suggested that the original reports of thepresence of German forces in this area had been exaggerated. TheGermans had taken over the oil fields, but it would be four months before these could be brought into operation.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.The Far East:Relations v/ithJapan.The ease of theS.S. AsamaMaru.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 34thConclusions,Minute 6.1)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he didnot attach undue importance to the statement which M. Arita, theJapanese Minister for Foreign Affairs, was reported to have madein the Japanese Diet to the effect that the handing over by us ofthe nine Germans was an instalment only. He had not yet receiveda report from Sir Robert Craigie on this point, but his feeling wasthat the Japanese Government, who were in a weak position, hadbeen anxious to get the debate in the Diet over with as little difficultyas possible, relying on the hope that, once the debate was out of theway, the demand in Japan for the return of the remaining germans would die down.Reference was made to an objectionable telegram whichReuters had sent to New York, reporting that we had apologised tothe Japanese. This matter had been considered in the ForeignOffice, and the Foreign Secretary undertook to ascertain whethera protest had been made to Sir Roderick Jones. He had taken stepsto ensure that the British Press presented the case in the properlight in the papers on the following day.The Prime Minister said that this telegram was calculated todo considerable harm in the United States.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Eire.internal situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 24thConclusions,Minute 9.)7. The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that hehad received a telegram from Sir John Maffey reporting that opinion in Eire was tense as a result of the execution of the Coventrymurderers on the previous day. It was a bad sign that the eire government wireless, which had hitherto refrained from quotingfrom the German wireless, had the previous evening repeated with approval an attack on this country&apos;s attitude to small nations madeon the German wireless two hours earlier. On the other hand,Mr. de Valera&apos;s own paper, the Irish Independent, had beenmoderate in tone, and had paid a tribute to Sir John Maffey. Thelatter thought that everything depended upon whether an incidenttook place within the next two or three days. If nothing untowardhappened in that period, Sir John Maffey hoped that the presentfeeling would die down.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Yote &quot; A &quot; 8.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, as agreed at theEstimates. previous meeting of the War Cabinet, he and the Secretary of State(Previous for Air had examined from the constitutional point of view the reference: propriety of the proposal to discontinue presenting to the House of w.M. (40) 35th Commons substantive Vote &quot;A&quot; figures. Discontinuance would conclusions, constitute a departure from the practice of the last 250 years. the minute 10.)      question involved was, however, one of practice only.    Discon-tinuance would in no way infringe the provisions of the Bill of rights.
In discussion, it was generally agreed that the alternative course of publishing a maximum figure considerably in excess of thereal numbers would not be satisfactory, since such maximum figures would be without meaning, but would, nevertheless, have significanceattached to them.The War Cabinet-(i) Agreed that the substantive figures of the officers and men for the Navy, Army and Royal Air Force should not begiven in the respective Votes &quot;A,&quot; but that, in lieu,there should be inserted the words &quot; such numbers ofofficers and men as His Majesty may deem necessary.&quot;(ii) Invited the Prime Minister to take an opportunity ofmentioning the matter to the Leaders of the Opposition.BacteriologicalWarfare.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 96thConclusions,Minute 10.)9. The Minister without Portfolio gave the War Cabinet ashort account of the precautions taken with regard to bacteriologicalwarfare. A Memorandum had been received from Sir FrederickBanting which took a somewhat alarmist view of the possibilitiesof this form of warfare. The views expressed in this Memorandumwere not, however, accepted by our expert advisers.The Minister added that he might shortly have to ask authorityfor a further programme of experiments.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.War Cabinet 10.   The War Cabinet agreed Business.That the Meeting on Saturday, the 10th February, shouldbe at 10-30 a.m.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,February 8, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
