<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/158/0 images: 522-526</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.      January 1923. ^ , ^CABINET.North-West Frontier Policy.I circulate for information the accompanying papers relating to North-Westpolicy.  -My colleagues are general^ aware that the question of the policy to he pursued in Wasdristan was under consideration last year.   In 1920 it had been decided that, the occupation of Central Waziristan was the best means of pacifying the country and of protecting the frontier. The military measures and road construction necessary for this purpose were authorised by the Secretary of State, the question of eventual policy being reserved for later consideration, but the tribes were informed that we intended to remain in Waziristan as long as we pleased, and to administer the. country on tribal lines.   In January 1922 the Government of India, in order to meet the exigencies of the financial situation, proposed the partial evacuation of the country by regular troops coupled with the. extended employment of tribal levies... This proposal, to which the Indian military authorities were strongly opposed, did not commend itself to the Secretary of State, and in the discussions which ensued various alternatives were put forward, and were submitted by him to the Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, over which Mr. Chamberlain presided.   The Sub-Committee made no definite recommendation, but indicated a preference  for the  full  scheme  of occupation originally contemplated, and  I communicated my decision in this sense to the Government of India in April 1922. The Government of India protested on the ground of the heavy charge which would be imposed on Indian revenues, and asked permission, while carrying out the initial steps of the scheme,&apos;to put up a less expensive alternative in three months&apos; time.   i agreed, and the Government of IhchVs alternative, set forth in a reasoned Despatch and supported by a Memorandum  by the Commahder-in-Chief,. was received in. August and approved by me, with Mr. Chamberlain&apos;s concurrence, on 7th September, hi essentials it was the same scheme as had been approved in April, i.e., it. contemplated the clomiuation of Waziristan by a garrison located in the centre at Razmak and by the construction of lateral roads from north, to south which would render the  movement of  troops comparatively easy in  the event  of raids  or disturbances.    It differed from it in that (1) the road programme was somewhat, reduced; (2) irregular troops were to take the place of regulars,in. support of tribal levies; (3) the possibility was contemplated that eventually the central garrison of regulars at Razinak might be replaced by irregulars, the. question being left open for. further consideration in the light of developments of aerial warfare.I followed up my telegram with a Despatch on 5th October, and, haying approved without modification the Government of Indians proposals, regarded the question, as finally closed. It was not therefore without, some surprise that on 21st, October I received telegrams from the Government of&apos; India and; Viceroy stating that Sir John Maffey, the Chief Commissioner of the North-West Frontier Province, disapproved of the policy of His Majesty&apos;? Government, stated that his views were shared by, a. large body of opinion on the frontier, complained that he, had: not been consulted,on the latest scheme, and was threatening to resign;; and. that the Government of India had accordingly decided that two of their number-Sir William Vincent and Sir; Muhammad Shall &quot;should payinformal visit to the frontier as soon as possible to, ascertain local opinion.&quot; The wisdom of this step was in my view open-to serious question. It was known immediately in Wa&apos;/.iristan,ancl the tribes, who had at. last begun.to believe that we intended to carry out our announced policy, at.once, at this sign of hesitation, began to make trouble again. However,, the two Members&apos; of Council came, saw and reported, and the, next, stage,is described in.the Government of India&apos;8 telegram, of 28th November and iny reply of 5th, December,, which are annexed.The report of, thetvyo Members of Council has now been received, and I have had the advantage of two long discussions,with Sir W. Vincent himself.   The. conclusion 6054     100   1.23SECRET.CP. 41 (23).
which &quot;I have reached is indicated in the draft below. The Government of,India, perhaps influenced unduly by their anticipations of criticism in the Legislative Assembly, wish to have recourse to the expedient of a Royal Commission in order.to strengthen their hands, Moreover, they propose that this body should examine, not any frontier problem in particular, but frontier policy in general, and should settle &quot;authoritatively&quot; the time-honoured feud between the advocates, of the &quot;close border&quot; policy and the.advocates of what used to he called the &quot;forward&quot; policy. It is, so far as I am aware, the first time that such a suggestion has &quot;ever been made, and it seems to me to have nothing to commend it. Moreover, my discussions with Sir VV. Vincent have led me to the conclusion, from which he himself would not dissent, that the only tangible issue to be placed before a Royal Commission resolves itself, on scrutiny into the question of constructing some 16 miles of road between Sararogha and Ladha.&apos;The matter is urgent. The belief that we are wavering has already created a situation which makes it impossible for the Government of India to withdraw some of the troops as contemplated in the scheme, and there seems to be no hope of its improving so long as the question is believed to be open. I therefore propose to send the draft telegram.I should add that, whatever difference of opinion there may be elsewhere, both the Political Resident, Waziristan, and the General Officer Commanding regard the sanctioned policy as providing the minimum consistent with safety.PEEL.23.rcl.january.iy 1923.From Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department, 28th November 1922.1395 S. Our telegram of 20th October, 1247. Waziristan. Our colleagues&apos; report has been received and exhaustively discussed with them in Council. Copy is being posted. They advise definitely against completion of circular road from Sararogha, via Dwatoi, to Razmak. They hold that technical difficulties of con-struction and maintenance, and consequent cost, will in all probability prove -considerably greater than has been estimated ; that Mahsuds, in their present temper, may be expected to offer active opposition to construction of the road, necessitating military occupations.; that it is more likely to act as an irritant than as a means of pacification; that, at best, it would only be a subsidiary line of communication with Razmak; and that, owing to its exceedingly vulnerable character, its use would always be dangerous and, at times of general excitement, impossible, except under military operations involving large forces, in view of the fact that after 2\ years of military occupation the Ladha line has to be heavily picketed, and in spite of military precaution, has been exposed to successful attack, and nobody can move a couple of hundred yards off it,-they are definitely against its permanent occupation by scouts, even as far as Sararogha, up to which point mechanical transport road has already been constructed.On similar groun ds they advise against the construction of a road from Jandola to Sarwekai. They ara doubtful Of the wisdom of holding Sarwekai itself by scouts, hut. consider that, if Wana is to be occupied, some means of approach must be preserved, and they advocate further consideration of alternative route via Gumal.While claiming considerable support for these views on frontier, our colleagues do not claim, that they are shared by all they interrogated. On the contrary, they found a sharp cleavage of opinion between the two schools of thought, even amongst the political officers. Most of those serving in trans-frontier agencies advocate adherence to existing policy in the main, if not in all details, while most of those serving in cis-frontier districts advocate the cutting down of trans frontier commitments and concentrating on internal defence. Division of opinion on Waziristau policy there has always been.&apos; It can be read between the lines-of the Report of Waziristan Committee last January. Since then, however, the cleavage has been widening,, because those in favour of some approximation to a&apos; close bolder policy have been reinforced by increasing financial stringency ; by/jhe Air Porce claim put forward by Salmond; and by primd facie evidence in their favour he has since produced in Kurdistan. Moreover, trend of our whole policy has become locally known, and a large body of local opinion has hardened against it, because it feels that security of life and property in the districts could be secured equally, if not more effectively, by less expenditure on cis-frontier defence.
What impressed our colleagues perhaps most on their tour was the prevalence of conviction, along the frontier, that our whole frontier policy is lacking in precision and finality, and the frequency of the reply to their questions that it is impossible to advise definitely on this or that element in the Waziristan problem unless it can be examined in relation to an established general frontier policy. And the same mi^ht be said of frontier questions elsewhere, such as occupation of Ohitral or the precise character of defence of Khyber.This is in accord with a conviction that has been gradually forcing itself upon ourselves, not merely in dealing with Waziristan, but with such momentous matters as the findings of the Military Requirements Committee and SalmoncFs Air Force proposals.   We have, throughout, felt gravely handicapped by the necessity of framing our recommendations piecemeal, and leaving their due correlation over to some future date, owing to the fact that we have not had before us a frontier policy, re-examined and re-adjusled to the very different conditions, military, political, and financial, which have arisen since the war, and the great change produced by war on the military aspects of the Russian problem.   Whole history of. this Waziristan case is a signal example of difficulties and dangers of postponing such correlation further. Since we recommended our final scheme for Waziristan we have accepted Salmond&apos;s scheme for increase of Royal Air Force in India, with a consequential acceptance of a reduction in the Field Force.   But the two schemes are not wholly consistent, and are, indeed, based on two contradictory contentions, the one on SalmoncVs contention that Waziristan can he controlled without ground troops, and the other on the contention that it cannot.   We are, therefore, unanimously of the strong opinion that no time should be lost in subjecting the whole frontier problem, in all its  ramifications, political and military, and in its bearing both on our new relations with Afghanistan and on our plan of campaign in the event of another Afghan war, to a comprehensive survey by a Commission, authoritative enough for its conclusions to carry conviction with His Majesty&apos;s Government and ourselves, and also with public opinion, both in England and in India, where the frontier question is provoking increasing controversy, owing to the great expenditure it involves.   Hence, nominations to Commission should rest partly with His Majesty&apos;s Government and partly with ourselves, and it would be essential that president, at any rate, should be a man whose personality and standing would command-universal respect.   We urge acceptance of this recommendation witn all earnestness on His Majesty s Government, for we feel convinced that Commission,, such as we propose, is the only practical means of securing satisfactory correlation of the many complex issues on which we are engaged, and the formulation of a general frontier policy which will be accepted by the two Governments and public opinion in the two countries for a reasonable number of years ahead.While awaiting His Majesty&apos;s Governments decision on this proposal, we have come to no conclusions upon this last report, but have decided to concentrate on what is immediately essential in the Waziristan scheme as sanctioned in your Despatch dated 5th October, Military, No. 63, namely, the evacuation of Ladha, and the consequential occupation of Razmak and the construction of the road thereto, together with the holding .of the Jandola-Sararogha road by scouts and Khassadars, and to leave in temporary suspense the construction of subsidiary roads from Sararogha to Razmak and from Jandola. to Sarwekai. Matheson and Pears have been strictly warned not to give tribesmen or others any inkling of tiny possibility of a change of policy, but at the same time to avoid language in further communications to the tribesmen that might be held to connote a promise to Razmak Wazir that our occupa-tion of Razmak means an assurance of this protection for all time.While we are unanimous upon our major proposal, Finance Member formally dissents from occupation of Sararogha by scouts, and holds that the occupation oi Razmak should be . strictly confined to military occupation necessary to assist evacuation of troops from Ladha, and that last links of the road to Razmak from Razani should not be undertaken.You will observe that while we have felt compelled to re-discuss the frontier policy, we have been careful to proceed with Waziristan policy sanctioned in your Despatch, save only in respect of road operations from Sararogha to Razmak and Jandola to Sarwekai, which would, in any case, take considerable time to do. Survey of neither has, so far, been completed. &apos;&apos; . :
From Secretary of State to Viceroy, 5th December 1952.4718. Private and personal. Your private and personal telegram and your Foreign and Political Department telegram of 28th November about Waziristan cause me considerable uneasiness. When you spoke in your telegram of 20th October of deputation of Vincent and Shall to the frontier to ascertain opinion on both sides 1 took you literally, and did not imagine that what was contemplated was an enquiry by two officials, who are not known to possess special qualifications for the task, into the policy which His Majesty&apos;s Government had so recently approved. Had I done so I should have, felt bound to take question to the Cabinet,&apos;who, I have no doubt, would have demurred to such enquiry, especially as the mere change of mind on part of Maffey must seem altogether inadequate reason for casting doubt on the policy.Now 1 am in doubt, what to do. I must of course await Vinceut&apos;s report, but judging from your description of it I do not think it will move Cabinet unless it contains in full opinions of frontier officers on which it is based. Cabinet will recognise that responsibility for advising me rests with Government of India, but if after close examination to which Waziristan policy has been subjected by highest authorities here and in India during past year they are asked to take so unprecedented a step as appointment of a Commission, they will claim to have actual opinion in their own language of local experts. If, therefore, you wish to persevere with the proposal I would ask you to send home these opinions as soon as possible.On the merits, following are the main difficulties \ see about a Commission :   (1) Personnel. It must presumably be small, highly expert body free from British and still more from Indian politicians, and 1 confess I do not know where to find the right men. (2) Proceedings of Commission must cause unsettlement up and down frontier and in Afghanistan, for everyone will know why it has been appointed. 1 need not labour point that one of our principal difficulties on frontier has &apos;been constant suspicion of instability of purpose. (3) Publication of Commission^ report, or at all events of reasons on which its recommendations were basedj would be impossible ; how then would it carry conviction ? (4) Your argument for a Commission seems to, presuppose existence of a homogeneous frontier presenting a single problem and capable of being treated by a single policy. But surely there is no such thing. We cannot argue from the Khyber to Waziristan, and considerations in favour of occupying Wand have no necessary bearing on Tirah or Chitral. (5) I do not know what facts not already Known Commission can be expected to elicit, and Government can hardly devolve on a Commission task of laying down its policy.I quite appreciate your difficulties with Inchcape Committee and Legislative Assembly, but as at&apos; present&apos; advised 1 am not convinced that appointment of Commission is right way of handling them, and I think it best to put&apos; my doubts before you at once. You will realise also that if frontier policy is thus reopened consideration by Cabinet of Indian Military Requirements Report must be indefinitely postponed, smce one of its fundamental assumptions will haye been removed.Draft telegram to the Government of India, Army Departmenp. I have carefully considered your telegram in the Army Department of 28th November, No. 1395, together with the report of Sir W. Vincent and Sir M. Shafi, which I have had the advantage of discussing with Sir W. Vincent himself, and with the approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government 1 now communicate to you the following decision.His Majesty&apos;s Government fully appreciate reasons for which your Government recommend that the whole frontier problem should be examined by an authoritative Commission, and no one realises more than they the evils of vacillation. But in their judgment frontier, with its widely differing geographical and ethnological conditions, does not present one single problem to which one single established general policy can be applied. On the other hand, His Majesty&apos;s Government are not aware of any problems on northern and central sections of frontier that press for solution. Occupation of Chitral is indeed expensive, and they might be prepared at a later date to examine proposals for withdrawal. But for the moment renewed Bolshevik attempts to open up communications with India from the north seem to make any diminution of British influence there inadvisable! As regards the Khyber, His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot foresee circumstances in which withdrawal arid tlieaban-donment of the railway would be approved or even recommended. Question, in fact, is narrowed to Waziristan.   But this question has been searchingly examined during
last year by the responsible military and political advisers alike of your Government .and of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and a definite policy has been recommended by the former and approved by the latter only four months ago. The A^incent-Shaii report and the personal evidence of Vincent do not disclose any new factor which calls for reconsideration of policy or suggest that..policy would gain in authority if it were supported by a Commission. His Majesty&apos;s Government are indeed painfully aware of the instability of expert opinion on such questions, but Commissions too are human, and. finality must be sought, if anywhere, in the decisions of those responsible for the government of the country.Further, His Majesty&apos;s Government are deeply impressed by impracticability after all that has passed of withdrawal from Waziristan. Not only would it involve grave breach of faith in view of assurances given by Resident Waziristan with your authority, but it seems clear that it could not be effected without tribal disturbances on a scale which might actually necessitate fresh invasion of country. Moreover, effect in Kabul would be most unfortunate.His Majesty&apos;s Government regret, therefore, that they cannot accept your proposals, and they request that you will now proceed to execute your policy with utmost vigour and determination, making it clear, both to your officers and to the public, that His Majesty&apos;s Government have no intention whatever of departing from it. In this con-nee tion I regret to have to call attention to leakage which has apparently taken place as shown by repeated telegrams from Peshawar and Delhi correspondents of Times, culminating in subsidised Reuter telegram dated 15th instant purporting to give substance of Maffey&apos;s evidence in camera before Inchcape Committee. Maffey is of course entitled to give his opinion to Committee, but whoever divulged it has committed gross breach of discipline, and 1 request that you will take all practicable measures to ensure that neither the views of your Government nor those of individual officers -are conveyed to the Press.

</content>
</cab>
