<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/158/0 images: 1152-1154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY CP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT]SECRET.CP. 86 (.g3). Copy No.       -C A B,,I H E T.The Protection of British Pishing Vessels in Worth Russian Waters.Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.I desire to draw the attention of my colleagues to the serious difficulty which has arisen with regard to the protection of British Pishing Vessels-in North Russian waters. The necessity for adequate naval protection is inoreaged by the ut,nw arrant able attempt of the Russian Government to increase the limit of territorial waters from three to twelve miles and their efforts to enforce this claim by seizing and detaining any non-Russian fishing vessels caught within the area of disputed jurisdiction.   Successive British Governments have always resisted previous claims for the extension of territorial waters beyond the limit of three m.iles3Although the fishing by steam trawlers off the North Coast of Russia is of comparatively recent   development, it has already become of considerable importance, and its cessation would have a serious effect upon both the fishing industry and the food supplies of this country.Owing to a variety of causes,- the principal of which is the gradual diminution of the stocks of fish in the North Sea and hone waters due to intensive fishing, the tendency is for British trawlers to go further and further afield in search of fish.
The following figures show the extent of this fishery^ the season for which lasts from October to May inclusiveSeason No*of Voyages.   Quantity caughtOwtsj_1907&quot;1914 (average per seasonfor 7 years),, 182 227,,0001915-1920 Mil                         Nil1920-21 7                         6,0001921-22   . 102 143,0001922-23 (to 20th January) 96                      96,-000The returns for the year 1921-22 would, no-doubt, have been greater but for the action of the Russian Government who, in assertion of their claim for a twelve mile limit of territorial waters^ arrested the two British trawlers &quot;Magneta&quot; ;and l! St 8 Hubert&quot; , This caused a set-back in the fishing until protection was provided in April and May by the Admiralty,   When the fishing was resumed In October 1922 the Admiralty detailed two sloops to protect the fishing, with the result that it was carried on on a much larger scale than in the earlier months of former seasons&apos;.For the past three months an average number of about 45 vessels have been employed; and this number would no doubt have been considerably increased during January but for the withdrawal -of protection by the Admiralty at the end of December.Although there has been no active interference on the part of the Russians,, the withdrawal of protection is having a sensible effect upon the catches as at this time of the year the bulk cf the fish are to be found between three and twelve miles from the coast, and many of the skippers are deterred from entering these regions and fish further   from the coast with the result that their catches suffer both in quantity and quality.If there is serious interference by the Russian Government with the vessels fishing., it is probable that a large number cf them will be withdrawn from these regions.   These vessels give employment to crews which number over 500 men, and, in addition, provide employment for at least double tha;t number ashore.   They also maintain the supplies of plaice in this country at a time when
it is very difficult.to obtain it from other sources. 746If the fishing had to be abandoned, a large proportion of these vessels would have to be laid up, as they would not be able to obtain profitable employment elsewhere.   They are specially constructed for use on distant voyages and cannot be used economically in home waters.    Practically the only alternative ground   open to them is Iceland, but the Iceland-caught fish is not of the same nature as that caught in the White Sea, and is generally suitable only for curing for exports   The vessels already fishing at Iceland provide enough fish to satisfy this demand and any considerable addition to their number would simply have the effect of causing a glut of Icelandic fish and making the whole fi;::,hihg in those regions unremunerative.I understand that no modern ship of war is suitable for service in North Russian waters and that a   suitable vessel can be obtained only by purchasing from the Mercantile Marine or by building one specially for the purpose,   I also understand that there is not sufficient margin in the Navy Votes to provide for such a ship.   I therefore submit that monies should be allocated specially to this purpose.and that a special ship should be built or acquired as soon as possible,Even if the difficulties with Russia were to come to an end the expenditure upon the vessel will not be wasted.   It is essential that the Fishery Protection Cruisers should be able to follow the fishing fleets wherever they go and such a vessel would find useful opportunities for service with the fishing fleets at Iceland and probable in the near future on the Newfoundland Banks and the West Coast of Greenland, to which it is probable that British fishing operations will shortly be extended.In addition to the needs of the fishing indaotry, I am informed that there are strong diplomatic reasons for the efficient protection of British shipping in North Russian waters,R. A..S,Bth February, 1923.

</content>
</cab>
