<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/158/0 images: 1202-1214</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT AMI 0 liiATE^TY ^b^aOVmm/f. C -Pc. 95 (23)(HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE). CARRIAGE OF GOODSBY SEA BILL. Note by the President of the Board off Trade.This Bill seeks to give effect to an agreed^code of rules .    The extent to which shipowners should be allowed to limit their liability for loss or damage to goods by the insertion of clauses in Bills of Lading has been a matter of dispute between shipowners and shippers over a long period.   The attached draft Bill seeks to put into effect a Code of Rules on which substantial agreement between shippers and shipowners has been reached.Ob3oot of Rules.   Since about 1880 the practice has, grown of inserting in Bills of Lading clauses which exempt shipowners from certain common law liabilities for the safe carriage of goods.   Shippers have represented that some of these clauses are unreasonable.   The intention of the Rules is to set out the liabilities which shipowners ought reasonably to undertake *His Ma3&apos;esty&apos;s Government are committed to legislation.     In February 1921 the Imperial Shipping Committee recommended the adoption of uniform legislation throughout tho Empire on this subject and indicated the lines on which in their opinion such legislation should be framed.   The recommendations were adopted at the Conference of Imperial Premiers in July, 1921.CABINET.-1-
Rules recommended as basis, of International Convent.!on.     Before effect could be given to these recommendations a set of Rules was adopted at the Hague at a Conference of shipowners, shippers, bankers, underwriters and other interests.     These Rules, known, as the &quot;Hague Rules&quot;, were not entirely in conformity with the recommendations of the Imperial Shipping Committee, but they were subsequently amended by agreement between the interested parties to conform substantially to the recommendations of the Committee.     These Rules, with certain alterations, were recommended by the delegates at the Brussels International Maritime Conference of October last, at which H.M. Government was represented, for adoption as the basis of a convention.   This basis forms the schedule to the aotached Bill.     A Report by the British Delegates of the proceedings at the Conference at Brussels in October last has recently been published by the Stationery Office.Provisions of Rules.     Articles 1 and 2 are pre-liminary Articles.     articles 3 and 4 define the liabilities out of which a shipowner may not contract and those from which he is exempt.     Under Article 3 he must exercise due diligence to provide a seaworthy ship.     Article 4 also provides for a maximum liability per package.     These articles carry out the recommendations of the Imperial Shipping Committee as to the precise definition cf the physical limits to the ship owners liability, and as to his maximum liability.Artiole 5 provides that a carrier may surrender his rights and immunities under Article 4.     This allows a measure of freedom of contract.
,      -   - 789article 6 allows the shipowner to make a special con-tract when goods are being carried under exceptional circum-stances.     This is in accordance with a recommendation of the   Imperial Shipping Committee.Provisions of draft Bill.     The Bill itself is intended only to give legal sanction to the Rules.Clause I limits its application to outward shipments -This is to avoid conflict of laws.     it may be observed that United States legislation and certain Colonial Acts apply to both outward and inward shipments.Clause II is necessary to repeal the implied absolute undertaking In British Common Lam to provide a seaworthy ship, as under the Rules the shipowner is only required to exercise due diligence to provide a seaworthy ship.Clause III-     It is necessary that Bills of Lading shall contain an express statement that their effect is subject to the provisions of the Rules in order that these Rules shall apply when cases are heard before foreign courtsMuch controversy has arisen over this question of the liability of shipowners.     It is mainly a matter for ship-owners and shippers to settle between themselves, and as they have arrived at substantial agreement it is desirable that legal effect should be given to the agreement to avoid further dispute.     As stated by the Imperial Shipping Committee uniform legislation throughout the Empire is desirable, but it is still more desirable to have inter-national agreement.     The Rules scheduled to the Bill have been recommended by the Brussels International Maritime Conference for adoption as the basis of an International Convention, and as they carry out substantially the recommendations of the Imperial Shipping Committee they meet the commitments of H.M. Government to legislate on this subject.P -.L1-G-.Board of Trade. , 19.2,23
[13 Geo. .5.]    Carriage of Goods: by Sea.1D R A E TOF ABILLTOAmend the&apos;law with respect to the carriage of a.d. 1923.goods by sea. &apos;WHEREAS at&apos; the International Conference on Maritime Law held at Brussels in October, 1922, the delegates at the Conference, including; the delegates: representing His Majesty, agreed unanimously to recom-6 mend their respective Governments to adopt as the basis of a convention a draft convention for the unification of certain rules relating to bills of lading :And whereas it is expedient that the rules contained in the said draft convention and set out in the Schedule 10 to this Act (in this Act referred to as &quot;the Rules &quot;) should be given the force of law:Be it therefore enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons; in this present&apos; 15 Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows :-1. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Rules Application shall have effect in relation to and in connection with of r&quot;&apos;es in the carriage of goods by sea in ships carrying goods from Schedule. 20 any port in Great Britain or Northern Ireland to any other port whether in or outside Great Britain or Northern Ireland.2. There shall not be implied in any contract for Absolute the carriage of goods by sea to which the Rules apply Worthiness 25 any absolute undertaking by the carrier of the goods to pot to be . provide a seaworthy ship. StwS35-3 A rules apply..
A.D. 1923.        3.-(1) Every bill of lading issued in Great Britain ProrTTon.    or -^or^nern Ireland which contains or is evidence of any as to bills    contract to which the Rules apply shall contain an of lading.    express statement that it is to have effect subject to the provisions of the said Rules. 5(2)-If any person, being a carrier of goods within the meaning of the Rules, or the servant or agent of any such carrier  .(a) fails or refuses to issue a bill of lading in accord-&apos; ance with the requirements of the Rules; 10or   ;  &apos;(&amp;) makes, signs or issues a bill of lading which contravenes or does not comply with the provisions of this Act and the Rules,he shall, in inspect of each offence, be liable on summary 15 conviction to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds.Short title, 4.-(l) This Act may be cited as the Carriage of saving, and   Goods by Sea Act, 1923.(2) Nothing in this Act shall affect the operation of sections four hundred and forty-six to four hundred 20 and fifty, both inclusive, [five hundred and two,] and five hundred and three of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1891-, as amended by any subsequent enactment, or the operation of any other enactment for the time being in force limiting the liability of the owners of seagoing 25 vessels.. (3) The Rules shall not by virtue of this Act apply to any contract for the carriage of goods by sea made before such day, not being earlier than the day of, nineteen hundred and twenty- , 30as His Majesty may by Order in Council direct.operation.
[13 Geo. 5.]    Carriage of Goods by Sea.schedule.Rules relating to Bills oe Lading.Aetiolb I. Definitions.In these rules  .....(a) &quot; Carrier &quot; includes the owner or the cliarterer who enters into a contract of carriage with a shipper :(ft) &quot; Contract of carriage &quot; applies only to contracts of carriage covered . by a bill of lading or any similar document of title, in so fax as such document relates to the carriage of goods by sea, including any bill of lading or any similar document as aforesaid issued under or pursuant to a charterparty from the moment at which such bill of lading is negotiated.:.....(c) &quot;Goods&quot; includes goods, wares, merchandises, and articles of every kind whatsoever, except live animals and cargo which by the contract of carriage is stated as being carried on deck and is so carried:(ct) &quot;Ship&quot; means any vessel used for the carriage of of goods by sea:(e) &quot;Carriage of goods&quot; covers the period from the time when the,goods are loaded on to the time when they are discharged from the ship :Ariiole II. Risks.Subject to the provisions of Article VI. under every con-tract of carriage of goods by sea the carrier, in regard to the 30 loading handling, stowage, carriage, custody, care, and discharge of such goods, shall be subject to the responsibilities and liabilities, and entitled to the rights and immunities hereinafter set forth..Article HI.35 Responsibilities and Liabilities.1. The carrier shall be bound before and at the beginning of the voyage, to exercise due diligence to  (a) Make the ship seaworthy: 35 A 2101520
A.D. 1923.        (6) Properly man, equip, and supply the ship :(a) Make the holds,  refrigerating and . cool chambers,, and all other parts of the&apos;ship in which goods, are&apos; carried, fit and safe for their reception, carriage and preservation. 52. Subject to the provisions of Article IV., the carrier shall properly and carefully load, handle, stow, carry, keep, care for and discharge the goods carried.3. After receiving the goods into his charge, the carrier, .or the master or agent of the carrier, shall, on&apos;demand of the 10 shipper; issue to the shipper a bill of lading showing among cllier things --       &apos;     &apos;(a) The leading marks necessary for identification of the goods as the same are furnished in writing &quot;by the shipper before the loading of such goods starts, 15 m provided such marks&quot; are stamped or otherwise shownclearly upon the goods if uncovered, or on the cases or coverings in which&apos; such goods &quot;are contained, in such a manner as should ordinarily remain legible until the end of the voyage ; 20(&amp;) Erther the number of packages or pieces, or the &quot;quantity^ or weight, as the case may be, as furnished iii writing by the &quot;shipper;(c) The apparent order and condition of the goods :Provided that no. carrier, master or agerit of the carrier, 25 shall be bound to state or show in the hill of lading any marks, number, quantity, or weight which he has. reasonable ground for suspecting riot accurately&apos; to, represent the goods actually received, or which ho has hadno reasonable means of checking.    - &quot;,&quot; &quot;     304. Such a bill of lading shall be prima&quot; facie evidence of .. the receipt by the carrier of the&apos; goods as therein described in accordance with paragraph 3, (a), (V), and (c).5. The shipper.shall.he deemed to have; guaranteed to the carrier, the accuracy at the time of shipment of the marks, 35 number, quantity, and weight, as furnished by him, and the shipper shall indemnify the carrier, against, all, loss, damages, and: expenses, arising or. resulting, from inaccuracies,, in such particulars. The right of the carrier to such indemnity shall; in no way limit his responsibility and liability under the contract 40 of carriage to any person other than the shipper.6. Unless notice, of. loss.or damage,and the general nature of such loss or.damage he given in writing to the carrier or his agent at the&quot; port of &quot;discharge, before Or&apos; at, the time of the removal of the goods&apos; into the &quot;custody of the person 45 entitled to delivery thereof under&quot; the contract&quot; of carriage,
[13 Geo. 5.] &apos;   Qarnage of Goods by Sea.such removal shall be primS facie evidence of the delivery by A. the carrier of the goods as described&apos;in the bill of lading.If the loss or damage is not - apparent, the notice must be given within three days of the delivery of the goods. 5       The notice in writing will not be admissible if the state of the goods has at the time of their receipt been agreed to be otherwise than as stated in the notice.In any event the carrier and the ship shall be discharged from all liability in respect of loss or damage unless suit is 10 brought within one year after delivery. of the goods or the date when the. goods should have been delivered.In the case of any actual: or apprehended loss or damage the carrier and the receiver shall give all reasonable facilities to each other for inspecting and tallying the goods.15 7. After the goods are loaded the bill of lading to be issued by the carrier, master or agent of the carrier, to the shipper shall, if the shipper so demands, be a &quot;shipped&quot; bill of lading, provided that if the shipper shall have previously taken up any document of title to such goods, he shall surrender20 the same as against the issue of the &quot; shipped&quot; bill of lading, but at. the option of the carrier such document of title may be noted at the port of shipment by the carrier, master, or agent with the name or names of the ship or ships upon which the goods have been shipped and the date or dates of shipment,25 and when so noted the same shall for the purpose of this. Article be deemed to constitute a &quot; shipped &quot; bill of lading..8. Any clause, covenant or agreement in a contract of carriage relieving the carrier or the ship from liability for loss or damage to or in connection with goods arising from 30 negligence, fault or failure in the duties andi obligations, provided in this Article or lessening such liability otherwise than as provided in these Rules, shall be null and void and of no effect.A benefit of insurance or similar clause shall be&apos; deemed to-35 be a clause relieving, the carrier from liability.Article IV.Rights and Immunities..1. Neither the carrier nor the ship shall be liable for loss or damage arising or resulting from unseaworthiness unless 40 caused by want of due diligence on the part of the carrier to make the ship seaworthy, and to secure that the ship is properly manned, equipped and supplied, and to make the holds, refrigerating and cool chambers and all other parts of the ship in which goods are carried fit and safe for their reception,35 A3
A.D. 1923. carriage, and preservation ia accordance with the provisions  A    of paragraph 1 of Article III.      1&apos; !     .    ,   -Whenever loss or damage has resulted from unseaworthiness, the burden of proving the exercise of due diligence shall be on the carrier or other person claiming exemption under this 5 section. -2. Neither the carrier nor the ship shall be responsible for loss or damage arising or resulting from-(a) Act, neglect, or default of the master, mariner, pilot, or the servants of the carrier in the navigation or in the iq management of the ship:(5) Fire, unless caused by the actual fault or privity of the carrier:p.; (c) Perils, dangers and accidents of the sea or othernavigable waters: 15(d) Act of God :(e) Act of war r(/) Act of public enemies :(g) Arrest or restraint of princes, rulers or people, or -seizure under legal process : 20(h) Quarantine restrictions :&apos;(i) Act or omission of the shipper or owner of the goods, Tiis agent or representative :(j) Strikes or lock-outs or stoppage or restraint of labour from, whatever cause, whether partial or general:   .    25(fc) Riots and civil commotions :(Z) Saving or attempting to save life or property at sea :(m) Wastage in bulk .or weight or any other loss or damage arising from inherent defect, quality, or vice of the goods: 30(w) Insufficiency of packing :(o) Insufficiency or inadequancy of marks:(p) Latent defects not discoverable by due diligence:(q) Any other cause arising without the actual fault or privityof the carrier, or without the fault or neglect of the 35. agents or servants of the carrier, but the burden of proof shall be on the person claiming the benefit of this exception to show that neither the actual fault or privity of, the carrier nor the fault or neglect of the agents or servants of the carrier contributed to the loss or damage.
r,[13 Geo. 5.] j   Carnage of Goods by Sea. 73. The shipper, shall not be responsible for loss or damage A.D. 1925&quot;.sustained by the carrier or the ship, arising or resulting from . -&apos;-  &apos; any cause without the act, fault or neglect of the shipper, his agents or&quot;his servants.5 4. Any deviation in saving or attempting to save life or property at sea, or any reasonable deviation shall not be deemed to be an infringement or breach of these Rules or of the contract of carriage, and the carrier shall not be liable for any loss or damage resulting therefrom.10 5. Neither the carrier nor the ship shall in any event be or become liable for any loss or damage to or in connection with goods in an amount exceeding 100Z. per package or unit, or the equivalent ,of that sum in other currency, unless the nature and value of such goods have been declared by the15 shipper before shipment and inserted in the bill of lading.&quot;This declaration if embodied in the bill of lading shall be prima .facie evidence, but shall not be binding or conclusive ob the carrier.By agreement between the carrier, master or agent of the 20 carrier and the shipper another maximum amount than that mentioned in this, paragraph may be fixed, provided that such maximum shall not be less than the figure above named.The rate of exchange shall be taken to be the rate ruling on the day of the arrival of the ship at the port of discharge of 25 the goods concerned.6. Neither the carrier nor the ship shall be responsible in any event for loss or damage to or in connection with goods if the nature or value thereof has been knowingly misstated by the shipper in the bill of lading.30 7. Goods of an inflammable, explosive or dangerous nature to the shipment whereof the carrier, master. or agent of the carrier, has not consented, with knowledge of their nature and character, may at any time before discharge be landed at any place or destroyed or rendered innocuous by the carrier without35 compensation, to the shipper, and the shipper of such good&apos;s shall be liable for all damages and expenses directly or indirectly arising out of or resulting from such shipment. If any such goods . shipped with such knowledge, and consent shall become a danger to the ship or cargo, they may in like manner be4,0 landed at any place, or destroyed or rendered innocuous by the carrier without liability on the part of the carrier except to general average, if any.Article V.Surrender of Rights and Immunities. 45       A carrier shall be at liberty to surrender in whole or in part all or any of his rights and immunities under these Rules;
Article VI. Special Conditions.    , 10Notwithstanding the provisions of the preceding Articles, a carrier, master or agent of the carrier, and a shipper shall- in regard to any particular goods be at liberty to enter into any agreement in any terms as&apos; to the responsibility and liability of the carrier for such goods, and as to the rights and immunities 15 of the. carrier in respect of such goods, or his obligation as to seaworthiness, so far as this stipulation is not contrary to public policy, or the care or diligence of his servants or agents in regard to the loading, handling, stowage, carriage,&apos; custody, care, and discharge of the goods carried by sea, 20 provided that in this case no &quot;bill of lading has been or shall be issued and that the terms agreed shall be embodied in a receipt which shall be a non-negotiable document and shall be marked as such.Any agreement so entered into shall have full legal effect: 25 Provided that this Article shall not apply to ordinary commercial shipments made in the ordinary course of trade, but only to other shipments where the character or&quot;condition of the property to be carried or the circumstances, terms and conditions under which the carriage is to be performed, are 30 such as reasonably to justify a special agreement.Article VII. Limitations on the Application of the Rules.Nothing herein contained shall prevent a carrier or a shipper from entering into any agreement, stipulation,.condition, 35 reservation or exemption as to the responsibility and liability of the carrier or the ship for the loss or damage to or in connection with the custody and care and handling of goods prior to the loading on and subsequent to the discharge from the ship on which the goods are carried by sea. 40A.U. 1923. provided such surrender shall he embodied in the bill of lading ,  ;) .   issued to the shipper.       &quot; :The provisions of these Rules shall not be applicable to charterparties, but if bills of lading are issued in the case of a ship under a charterparty they shall comply with the terms of 5 these Rules. Nothing in these Rules shall be held to prevent the insertion in a bill of lading of any lawful provision regarding general average.
[13 Geo. 5.]    Carriage of Goods by Sea.Article VIII.Limitation of Liability. .The provisions of these Rules shall not affect the rights and obligations of the carrier under any statute for the time being 5 in force relating to the limitation of the liability of owners of sea-going vessels. .
Carriage of Goods by Sea.DRAFTOP AB   ILLTo amend the law with respect to the carriage of goods by sea.XXXIX.   (2.)12th February 1923.35-^3

</content>
</cab>
