<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/24/0 images: 107-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)FUTURE OF THE EX-ITALIAN COLONIES IN AFRICA;PROVISIONAL POLICY OF HIS MAJESTY^ government memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe problem the Four-Power Commission charged by the Deputies ofthe Council of Foreign Ministers with investigating and reporting on conditions in the ex-Italian Colonies has not yet completed its work.      Meanwhile, however, our need for a British trusteeshipgiving us strategic facilities in Cyrenaica is paramount,  and our whole policy in regard to the disposal of these colonies must therefore be based on it.      The&apos;conclusion has moreover beenreached, in the course of full discussions between all theDepartments concerned, that our best chance of obtaining the trusteeship of Oyrenaica is to ask for a trusteeship of Libya asa whole.      This is because there is a strong movement, in north africa itself and throughout the Arab world, for the preservation of the unity of Libya, and unless we try to satisfy that movement(within the framework of a British trusteeship for the whole area)we cannot hope to induce the local inhabitants to adopt asatisfactory attitude when the Four-Power Commission investigatestheir wishes on the spot.     The Commission is due to arrive in tripolitania at the beginning of March, and it is thereforeurgently necessary to begin working on Libyan public opinion at theearliest possible moment.2. If, however, we are to ask for trusteeship of the wholeof Libya, we must do everything possible to safeguard theinterests of the Italians in Tripolitania and to satisfy Italiansusceptibilities and aspirations elsewhere in Africa.      TheItalians have been encouraged by both the French and the russians to hope that they may be given back Tripolitonio in the form of a united Nations trusteeship;    and if they are not compensatedelsewhere, the resultant disappointment will militate against those elements in Italy who are working with us for the inclusionof their country in a Western Union.Rec omm enda t i on s3. There are three main ways in which we can partiallycompensate Italy for not getting back Tripolitania:-S E C R E copy NO.CABINET(1)   By supporting to a large extent her claims for thereturn to her, on a trusteeship basis, of her formercolonies in East Africa;
(2)    By safeguarding the interests of Italians in-   Tripolitania under a British trusteeship of &quot;thatterri tory;(3)    By securing for Italy the maximum of general co-operation with ourselves and other colonial powers in Africa as a whole.1+. As regards (1), after careful consideration of allthe factors involved I have reached the conclusion that weshould be prepared eventually to support the Italian claims for trusteeship of the whole of Italian Somaliland and aconsiderable part of Eritrea,  including Massowah and Asmara(but giving Ethiopia as much as possible of the Coptic highlandsbehind Asmara, and the Danakil Coast with the port of Assab as anoutlet to the sea).     We should, however, first sound the americans and the French as to their ideas on Eritrea, and secureif possible that they rather than we should sponsor any proposalto divide up the territory on roughly these lines.5, As regards (2), I recommend that the following provisions should be made for the safeguarding of Italianinterests in Tripolitania:-(i)    We should give a large measure of local self-governmentto the groups of Italian farms;    these could be formedinto communes with wide powers all of which could continue under unified Italian economic control.(ii)    As regards internal affairs, we contemplate thatTripolitania would be under an indigenous governmentwith a considerable degree of internal autonomy (butprecluded from modifying by a mere majority certain provisions protecting minorities);    the Italiansshould be. represented in any higher assemblies, and special arrangements for communal representations should be made in order to guarantee Italianrepresentation proportionate to the size of theItalian population.(iii)    In matters of personal status, the Italians should havethe benefit of the existing (Italian) law,administered by the   ordinary judges, a number of whom would in fact be Italians.(iv)    The Italians should have full guarantees of freedomof speech and religious worship.      They should also,of course, be allowed to hove their own newspapers.(v)    We should guarantee to the Italian community that,as the largest minority, in the country, they wouldhave special and official representation at the headquarters of the Administration,  thus giving them direct access to the highest authority.(vi)    As regards future Italian immigration, the Palestineexperience shows that it would be most unwise to give any guarantee;    but in practice we should certainlyhope to be able to bring back the remainder of theItalians who were evacuated from Tripoli during thewar.      In addition, if friendly relations were established between the Arabs and the Italians locally,a certain amount of new immigration might be possible thereafter. .
6.     . As regards (3)  (Italian association in Africandevelopment generally), schemes for the recruitment of Italiansfor work in certain of our East African territories (includingthe trust territory of Tanganyika) have already been started.The numbers of men involved are of course very small at present,but as development schemes progress they may increase withincertain definite limits.      Compared with Prance, South America,etc., Africa (even were the Italians able to send as manyimmigrants to their former colonies as they could before the war)could never offer much scope for Italian immigrants,  and in anycase the schemes for recruiting Italian workers have to be onthe basis of repatriation because of the necessity of protectinglong-term African interests, but the welcome we give to Italianimmigrants is a factor which should not be left out of account.7. In addition,  if Italy receives a territory orterritories in East Africa under trusteeship,  arrangements could not doubt be made for her to take part:-(a) in the series of technical conferences which hovebeen set going on Anglo-French-Belgian initiativebetween all the administrations concerned in eachquestion in Africa south of the Sahara (French and belgian consent would be necessary):    and(b) in measures of economic co-operation on the lines ofthose which it is hoped will grow out of the talks with the French, the first of which is due to takeplace in February.      It has been agreed with theFrench that the talks shall concentrate in the firstplace on West Africa;    but it has always been intended that we should consider the possibility of similar-talks with other colonial Powers,  and there seems noreason why they should not be extended to coverEast Africa also.Developments along these two lines should be of practicaladvantage to the Italian administration in the trusteeshipterritory or territories of East Africa,  and should go some way towards convincing the Italian Government that we want to dealwith them on a basis of equality.Supporting arguments8. The claims officially put forward by Italy are ofcourse for the return to her on a trusteeship basis of all herformer African colonies.      There is, however,  reason to believethat few Italians have any hope of seeing these claims fullygranted, and that consequently the Italian Government would be reconciled to getting considerably less.      Moreover, as regardsthe question of the extent to which we con obtain a privileged position for the Italians in Tripolitania,  the Italian Governmentare well aware that limitations are anyhow imposed by theprinciples governing United Notions trusteeships (whethergranted to themselves or to others);    and that, under any arrangement conceivable, the welfare and fate of theircountrymen in North Africa would depend largely upon the goodwill of the overwhelming Arab majority - a good will whichcould not be guaranteed were the attempt made to secure forthe Italian minority a too-highly privileged position at the outset.
9. Much will of course depend upon the extent towhich the French and the Americans can he induced to support us in a scheme on the foregoing lines.      I think, however,that there is a fair chance of our being able to persuade them to accept it;    and that, with their help, the ItalianGovernment also could be made to see that it was ultimately to their own advantage.E.D.Foreign Office,  S.W.1..4th February, 1948


</content>
</cab>
