<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/24/0 images: 236-238</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cabinet a NATIONAL THEATREMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the Treasury have recently been approached on behalf of the national theatre Committee, which for some years has been trying to raise funds to build a non-commercial national theatre. The London County Council propose, as mycolleagues know, to devote a site on the south bank of the river to the purposesof a cultural centre. They propose themselves to build on this site a group ofconcert halls, and they are at present reserving space for a national theatre.The proposed National Theatre would replace the &quot; Old Vic,&quot; which was severely damaged during the war. The damage has been sufficiently repaired to enablethe theatre to be used for training purposes, a use which it is proposed to continue.2. The London County Council must be well aware that the sum now at thedisposal of the committee (about  70,000) is a mere fraction of the probable costof a suitable theatre (about  1 million), and their Town Planning Committeeare pressing the sponsors of the theatre to show that they have reasonable grounds for expecting to raise the .necessary funds. Lord Esher, who speaks for thesponsors of the theatre, thinks that the project can only be kept alive if theGovernment commit themselves to making it possible. He sees no prospect inpresent conditions of raising any further large sum from voluntary sources.3. The object of the scheme is to establish a theatre to be operated under public auspices, free from the considerations of private profit which have so largean influence on commercial management, in order to provide for the production ofShakespeare and other good drama in a national setting. I do not share the viewsof those who think that all theatres should be owned by the State or some other public body, since it would be difficult for any monopolistic owner to avoid inter-fering with the freedom to show any play at any theatre which, theoretically atany rate, now exists. But this does not mean that there is no place for a national theatre. The method of managing such a theatre would have to be worked outlater on. We should no doubt be guided by our experience of the various methods which have been so successfully developed by the Arts Council. I do not envisageanything in the nature of direct management by the State. But I do consider thatthe State could, and should, be prepared to provide a substantial part of the initialcapital cost. I look forward to the time when our economic situation will enable us to start building the theatre, and I should like to give the L.C.C. and theNational Theatre Committee the assurances necessary to keep the project alive.4. The question how these assurances are to be given is not altogether easy.The suggestion put to the Treasury was that Parliament should be asked to votemoney now which would be paid over at once to trustees under conditions thatwould keep it frozen until it were judged possible to release it. I could not see my way to do this. It would set a most important precedent, and I do not see how I could limit its application.5. The first alternative that suggests itself is that I should announce my intention to ask Parliament to vote money for the project at some future date.There would be no objection to this if there were any early prospect of making34952! -189!  . Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1948CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.    30CP. (48) 55l$th February, 1948
a start. But a start is hardly likely to be possible within the life of the present parliament, and I should hesitate to make a promise that it would fail to a future Parliament to honour, particularly as the project is novel and might be controversial.6, It seems to me, therefore, that the only way in which the L.C.C. and theNational Theatre Committee could properly be given any assurance of real value would be by legislation to the effect that if the L.C.C. make available, free of charge, a site for the purpose of a national theatre to any body of persons havingat their disposal moneys subscribed for the provision of such a theatre, and ifsuch a body submits to the Treasury proposals for building such a theatre, theTreasury may undertake to make, and may make, but of moneys provided byParliament, contributions not exceeding  1 million in all towards the cost ofcarrying those proposals into effect. The Bill need contain*no limiting date, butit would be necessary to explain that the purpose of introducing the Bill at thisstage was to give the necessary faith for detailed planning to be put in hand, butthat early realisation must not be looked for.7. If my colleagues agree, I would like to inform Parliament that the Gov-ernment are putting in hand the preparation of legislation on the above lines, and propose to introduce it in due course. I would agree the terms of my statement with the Leader of the London County Council and with Lord Esher.R. S. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,19th. February, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
