<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/24/0 images: 239-241</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 secret - Copy No.   30CP. (48) 5618th February, 1948CABINETTHE HOUSING PROGRAMMES IN 1948 AND 1949Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the present housing programmes for 1948 and 1949 are governed by thedecisions of the Cabinet (CM. (47) 81st Conclusions, Minute 4) that : (a) the amount of softwood timber available for use on the construction ofnew houses during 1948 should be 230,000 standards (sufficient to sustain a programme of 140,000 houses a year); and(b) that the total number of houses under construction in Great britain should be reduced to 140,000 by mid-1949 and that an equivalentnumber should be completed during that year.2. The actual rate of completion of houses has been much more rapidthan was expected when these decisions were taken and it is now reasonablycertain that some 200,000 houses will be completed during the course of thisyear. More timber will be required for this purpose than was previously assumedand the allocation for this year is being used up faster than was anticipated,to the prejudice of the housing programme for 1949.3. There is no prospect that the housing programme in Scotland can bebrought into balance by mid-1949 and the need for special measures arises onlyin England and Wales. The English share of the total of 140,000 houses under construction or to be completed for 1949 is 125,000. At the end of December1947, the number of houses under construction in England and Wales was 207,000and the number on contract, but not started, was 51,000. The number in thelatter category is unlikely to fall much lower, and On a running programme of125,000 a year would be some 45,000. On the present timber allocation it isnot possible to approve contracts on a sufficiently large scale to prevent the volumeof houses under construction shrinking so quickly as to make impossible thecompletion of 125,000 houses during 1949. By the end of this year, the numberof houses under construction in England and Wales will have fallen to rather,less than 100,000 as compared with a level of 125,000 to be reached only by mid-1949.4. With work on a relatively small number of houses being started month by month, the demand for bricks has fallen catastrophically. The decrease in demand has been accentuated by the need to approve contracts during recent months for many types of non-traditional houses, not using bricks, arising outof the fulfilment of obligations entered into by the Ministry of Health during1946. At present the annual demand for bricks is estimated to be running atsome 3,000 million as compared with an output of 5,000 million in 1947 and a.pre-war annual production of 7,000 million. With a running programme of140,000 houses per year and assuming no expansion in other forms of building,the requirements for bricks in 1949 would amount to 4,500 million. If relief is not immediately afforded for the brick industry some brickmaking capacity willirretrievably be lost to the detriment of the housing programme in 1949 andto building capacity, generally in subsequent years. While a contribution tothe problem of the brick industry may be made by stacking some of the currentexcess of output on sites or at works and by more extensive forward orderingby the major users, such measures are expensive and cannot afford a major34953----.-^-191Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1948
easement. Many of the difficulties now becoming evident in the brickmakingindustry will, within a few months, become apparent in a number of otherindustries producing different types of building materials.5. A too rapid decrease in the volume of house construction would alsointroduce a painful dislocation into the building industry itself. unemployment would be precipitated in many areas and the men so displaced could often notusefully be employed on other work, at such short notice. In any event manyof the men would be needed again at a later date for work on a runningprogramme of 12,000 houses per month. Timber yards will continue to carryheavy stocks of softwood timber for at least the next year and it would beanomalous if at the same time house building were allowed to shrink to sucha level as to produce heavy unemployment of building workers and a serious position in the brickmaking and other industries producing building materials.6. Owing to the time that normally elapses between the approval of a contract and the time when building work on the houses is actually started,an immediate decision is required if any relief is to be afforded to the brick-making and the building industries. An immediate increase in the rate of approval of new contracts would have an effect upon the volume of house con-struction only some five months later.7. At 31st December, 1947, the stock of softwood in this country, excludingsleepers and mining timber, was approximately 620,000 standards.Allocations are running at the rate of 980,000 standards a year.About one-half of the 1947 softwood imports were paid for in dollars andfuture levels of import depend very much on whether or not we receive marshall aid. If this aid is not forthcoming we shall have drastically to reduce oursoftwood imports and our consumption, and these changes will involve very severecuts indeed in a number of our programmes, including the housing programme,and very serious disruption of our industrial economy.On the other hand, if Marshall Aid is forthcoming on a reasonable basiswe can expect to continue softwood timber imports on a scale which will enable us to maintain our present levels of softwood consumption.The stock at 31st December, 1947, was considerably above a reasonableminimum working level, which is probably of the order of 350.000 standards.8. It is recommended that an additional 60,000 standards of timber be allocated during 1948 for housing. This further allocation would permit the starting of about 30,000 extra permanent houses and would allow house completionto continue at the present more rapid rate.To authorise this would be in accordance with the decision of the Cabinet notto take any action in anticipation of the failure of Marshall Aid such as would seriously disrupt our economy. Further, such a decision would not prejudice the review of the housing programme, which is due to be made in June 1948,when we should probably know what we can expect under the Marshall Aidplan.R. S. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,18th February, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
