<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/7/0 images: 45-78</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECi&amp;T WAR   CABINET. : : ^;G.T.. Ill &quot;Proposed Overland Route to Salonica. yia Cherbourgand Tarante.(Brief Summary of Mr. Calthrop [s Report.)One passenger train a day (to carry 1000 persons) can he running in. a month.   - ...Five trains a day carrying 1000 to 1400 tons of Btore3 in all can&apos; he run - in addition to the passenger train - in three months&apos; time.We must supply for above:-- 400 ooaches3,300 ten ten waggons182 locomotives132 drivers&apos;    132 firemen..By using the Port des Flamands at Cherbourg as well as the Bass in dn,; Commerce, and carrying out dredging and construction&apos; *f quays,  one passenger train a day and nine daily goods trains carrying from 2000-2400 tons could be despatched.     This tonnage would meet our requirements with regard to the Salonica Expeditieno-ry Force.Branch line work, dredging and construction of quays and rest camps must be done by -British and several thousand men will be required for the purpose..We must supply for tonnage, etc, referred to in para-graph 4 an extra:-2,700 ten ton waggons188 locomotives88 drivers88 firemen.  - -over and above that mentioned;in; paragraph 3.   -There ar e alternative schemes f or &apos; ?I aV   One passenger train daily ... (bj   One passenger train; daily and three daily goods trains 700-800 tons.At Tar an to a pier,  stores and sidings will have t&apos;6 be built, and, if vessels zf more than about 12 feet draught are employed,  stores and ammunition will have to be lightered,Waggpns.     These can be.provided from the British rail-ways at a pinchf;in     Sir E. Geddes &apos; view, hut 1 r, Calthrop thinks it impossible to provide 2000 covered.     The coaches would not be a serious difficulty, though the shipment of this class of stock is not an. easy matter./Locomotives.     The supply of these would be a serious question. -Shipping waggons, etc. to France.   We are already in oon-siderable arrears in our shipments of railway rolling stock to France on account of shortage of tonnage,  so much so that it is liable to react on the military situation there. (Tnt.ri   k -o a v
flKflreff^ WJ&quot; ^*TTT*....................I .KB fp*k    m   OKI Ii :: dVJlKEAIlI): JIOUTE   TQ .. SALONXpA,Mr. Calthrop has now investigated the feasibility of the proposed overland route from-Cherbourg to Taranto and. has reported that the provision of a service of one passenger train a day (to carry 1,000 persons) presents no-great difficulty and that the ultimate establishment of a goods service to carry2,000 tons of supplies a day (which would suffice for the needs of the British force) does not appear impossible.lie is of opinion that it should be possible for the passenger train to be actually running in a month, as it could run direct from the Gare liaritime at Cherbourg into the French station at Buffaluto (Taranto) as a temporary measure, and that the necessary works at Cherbourg and Taranto to enable 5 trains a day, carding 1,200 to 1,&apos;400 tons (I prefer to call it 1,000 tons) of stores, to be run, as well as the daily passenger train might be completed in three months,     -The development of the goods service up to 9 trains a day, required for.; the full scheme, is.dependent on the improvement of the Port des Flamands by dredging and construction of quays, and could only be gradually realised..     Mr. Calthrop believes that the improvements at-that Port would be of considerable help when demobilisation comes.The whole&quot;of the constructional work in connection with the scheme would have to&apos; be undertaken by the British. This includes .the establishment of rest camps at Cherbourg St. Germain au Mont d1 Or,.; Faenza and. Taranto, the building of sidings and storage at Les Flamands, the work on the Port des Flamands described above, and the construction of a branch
line from the Maritime Arsenal.at Tarahto.(to which.,the Italians are already making a line, which they say will he finished in the middle of March)-down to the water level on the south side of the Hare Piccolo together with a station and pier, sidings and sheds.     It is not possible at this stage to say what amount of labour would be required for these services but it would run into thousands of men.   . Mr, Calthrop does ,indeed express the belief that as the Italians are already engageoV - in railway work in the immediate neighbourhood, they could be . induced with a little pressure -to provide atleast the labour for the Taranto undertakings, but it should be clearly understood that this i s : as yet a ^ mat t er of con j e cture. -&apos;      -    -.?ith the exception of the locomotives for fotur marches- in:.Italy, - which would be supplied by the Italians, all the locomotives, passenger coaches and wagons must be found by ourselves.     It is true that&apos; the French are prepared to produce the coaches for the passenger train and the locomotives for 4 marches in Prance, but only on condition that they are immediately replaced by British coaches and locomotives of equal capacity.The following table shews the number of locomotives coaches, wagons,&apos; drivers and firemen that we shall have to supply, if it is decided to adopt the scheme:-
1 daily p^sssh-train./1 daily passenger train and 3 daily goods trains 700-800 tons1 daily passenger train and 5: daily goods trains. 1100-1300 tons.0 1 dailypassenger train and 9 daily goods trains, 2000-2400tonSc -400400400400200033006000228818237022881322202288132220Capacity at Cherbourg without additional harbour works.Ultimate capacity considered.The actual provision of the coaches would not be a matter of serious difficulty, though the shipment of this class of stock is by no means an easy matter.The total number of wagons to be provided for the full scheme is 6,000,     This is a large number, but i think that the British railways might manage it at a pinch.    Here, however, the shipping problem is very serious indeed.     The position of the Hord railway in France is such that we have undertaken to ship 20,000 wagons.from England within the next 5 or 6 months for the carriage of supplies for the British Armies in France.      The despatch of these wagons is absolutely essential to the efficient and successful conduct of opera--tions.      It had been hoped to despatch not less than 3,.000wagons
wagons a month, but during the first month the total did not reach 2,000 and it does not look as if there were any ..-&apos;-- immediate prospects of improvement.     The fact must therefore be faced that &quot;unless the Admiralty can allocate additional tonnage the despatch of wagons for the overland route to Salonica must either hamper and encroach on the despatch of wagons for the relief of the ftord system or must be itself considerably delayed.The most serious question of all is the question of locomotives.     The requirements of the ITord have already obliged us to make arrangements to send 370 locomotives from the British railways to the relief of that system, and orders for another 300 have been placed by us in England and America.     We had hoped to despatch 100 of the British locomotives a month, but here again we have been disappointed, for the number despatched in the first month was less, than 50 and the total number despatched up to date is only 65. -Moreover, the number of locomotives which it was agreed to supply to the French was based upon the understanding that they would be able to allocate about 500 locomotives for the service of the British Armies. It is now becoming clear that this number will not be forthcoming j and&apos; that those they can supply will be in such bad condition that it will be impossible to rely on the absence of engine failure.     It appears probable that to avert a breakdown of the service behind our line in France, we shall have to increase considerably the number to be provided by ourselves. ;   If in addition the British;railways are to surrender 200 or 300 1 beomotives for the overland route&apos;,: the strain upon them will be so great as to threaten to impair their efficiency, the assistance they have already rendered having only been madey\; nossible I
-5- &apos;  y]:^^^possible &quot;by a drastic reduction in their train service.7    As regards the shipment of the locomotives the same considerations apply as in the case of the wagons.For these reasons I would suggest that while the overland route to Salonica is not impracticable the conditions under which it must be created and worked, must in any case throw a heavy burden on the railway resources of this country and if unaccompanied by special efforts on the part of the Admiralty in the provision of tonnage, as to the possibility of which I can express no opinion, must be such as to re-act unfavourably on the military situation in Prance.(Sd.) W. Guy Granet.. d.d. g.M.R7 -22/2/1917.!
London &amp; North We stern Railway,General ManagerTs Office, Euston Station,. London, N.W4February 7 th ;1917. , PROPOSED OVEBLAITD ROUTE TO SALONIKA;:Sir, -&apos;With reference to letter from the Secretary of the War Off ice, dated January 9th&apos;/ 1917 i on the subject of the Mission to investigate the possibilities of an overland service for men and material between England and the Macedonian theatre of War, via a French.port on the English Channel and an Italian port in the South of Italy, I have the honour to inform you that, accompanied by Mr. L. W. Home, Superintendent of the Line,. London and Horth Western Railway, Commodore E. Unwin,V.C. C.M.G. R.H., Lieut. Colonel M. H. Knaggs, A.D.E. and O.S., Lieut. Colonel J, C. B. Statham, C.M.G-. D.D.M..S., Lieut. Colonel P. R. Macdonald, A.Q.M.G., and Major G. Walton, R.E, B.A.L.R.T., I have investigated the possibilities in conjunction with the French and Italian Military, Naval and Civil Authorities, and, in general terms, I can report that there is no great difficulty in respect of personnel, nor any insuperable difficulty in connection with a certain amount of stores.;Appendix Ho.1 gives a diary of the work of the War Office Mission.The respective ports are Cherbourg and Taranto, and the line of route to be observed is via the following meal-halt stations:-Surdon. Le Mans,Saint Pierre-des-Corps. (Tours);Saincaize0Paray-le-Monial.St. Germain-au-mont-d1 or. (Camp).Chambery...
ntinued. .:Chambery. Modane. :: Turin. Tortona. Parma.Faenza,    (Camp). Ancona.Castellammare. : Poggia. 3ari,: (See plan &quot;A&quot; attached; shewing route throughout). When the Mission left England, .&apos; I was under the impression that the route over the Italian portion of the journey would he down the west coast of Italy, but when we met G-eneral Piastri, Director; of Transportation, in Italy,- he stated that, in view of the heavy traffic down the west coast now, and the anticipated increase in the number of French . marches from one to four, the Italian Authorities would -require that our route should be down the Adriatic coast, I pointed out it appeared a more dangerous route so far as attack from the. sea was concerned, but General Fiastri stated, and the Italian Minister for War in Rome personnally assured me, that the line was amply protected by armoured trains, and that no danger had hitherto been encountered by the large Italian troop movements over the route.     The east coast has, -----  undoubtedly, the advantage in the matter of grades, and, from personal experience of both routes, is, in my opinion, in far better order than the west coast route. --:- :The total distance is 2,330 kilometres, equals 1,460 miles.The time occupied between Cherbourg and Tarahto, including meal and sanitary halts will be, roughly, 115 hours, to which will have to be added 48. hours occupied at two -rest camps suggested on the route.     Appendix isfo.2 gives a provisional through timing for the journey.-&apos;\[-  HALTS.
HALTS.-      The two intermediate rest camps suggested are at   . St. Germain-au-mont-d&apos;or and Faenza, these sites &quot;being selected as being the most convenient from the camping point of view, toge&quot;ther with a reasonable division of the&apos; journey between Cherbourg and Taranto.     Moreover, Faenza Is 60 kilometres from the Adriatic coast.The distances-are as follows:-Cherbourg to St. Germain-au-mont-d&apos;or - 840 kilometres - 40 hours St. Germain-au-mont-dfor to Paenza      -770        &quot; - 39     &quot;Paenza to Taranto -720        &quot; - 36     &quot;At the outset it was suggested that only one rest camp should be provided, in the neighbourhood of Modane, but, apart from the fact that Modane is a congested station, a rest camp at an altitude of 3,500 feet and at a place Y/hich, when we passed, was covered with several feet of snowt appears out of the question.     In the winter there are only about two- hours of sun per day.In Appendix Ho.3 will be found the actual sidings at the different stations which will be placed at the disposal of British trains, and, in every case, the necessary accommodation in connection with these halts can be provided.C H B R B 0 U R G. gHSOpgL, - After two days&apos; meetings with the Authoritiesmeof the 4    Bureau in Paris, we left for Cherbourg, whore we spent two days examining the accommodation required and available at that port for the proposed new line of communication and, after a very long discussion with the French Authorities, it was agreed that the personnel should be landed at the Gare Maritime, (see plan &quot;B&quot; attached^, either by the transport
going alongside, or by lighter from&quot;the transport, according to the draught of the ship employed on the service.The men will then be marched to a property called Chateau Tour la Ville, about 5 kilometres distance from the Gare Jtaritime, though, at the same time, it is as well to mention that trains can be despatched direct from the Gare Maritime to Taranto if it is found desirable to do so.As will be seen subsequently, the men will have to march, -after being through the rest camp, about three kilometres to be entrained for Taranto.JETIflJ! DU HQMET* -   With regard to. stores, and ammunition, while undoubtedly, the Jetee du Hornet, which the French-are now adapting for the use of their coal traffic, offers great&apos; attractions from the sea transport point of view, the strongest -possible objection is raised by the French Authorities to its ii3e, and I am of opinion that to prevent friction it is undesirable to press for the use of. this quay.     It is only fair to add that it is not conveniently situated in respect of: the new sidings required, nor can a store or camp be provided in convenient proximit; , and, apart from the ship transport, I cannot recommend it.BASS IN pU;COMFRCB.-  ^he French Authorities, however, would place at our disposal, for the exclusive use of British store ships, two berths, and, if necessary, three, in the Bassin du Commerce, and they suggest that, at any rate to start with, the stores and ammunition sent by this route should be limited to the capacity- of this Basin.     It is idle to suggest that this is an ideal site, or that the rail-accommodation alongside is all that can be desired.      In the first .place, it is reached by a lock, and vessels can only enter or leave within an hour before and an hour after high tide, and secondly, working;:/C:--;&apos;v-Ar-&apos;--.&apos;-;;V&apos;: -\---\^:^:^Cy^&apos;^^y^. with
ued.With two herths - day and night - some 1;200 to 1,400 tons only can he put over the ships    sides, into wagons, and despatched.;M YARDAT LBS FLAMANDS.- aThe French Authorities, however, insi st that, hefore transport of munit ions and store son any large scale at all begins, siding accommodation shall be put v-in for dealing with this traffic, and a site for this accommodation was agreed upon, about three kilometres from the Bass in du Commerce.     This will involve a new junction in the proximity of the Bassin&apos;du Commerce with the Cherbourg -Barfleur line, nnd another junction close to where the new sidings will have to be laid down.The French Authorities also stated that all they could do in connection with the new sidings would be to lay in the new junction points where required, and that both labour and material for the sidings and stores (these can be erected at the sidings) required by the British Authorities will have to be provided by the latter.     They would, however, place at the disposal of the British Authorities, a competent Engineer to assist with the work.The French;Authorities are agreed that we shall have the absolute control of these sidings, and do all the railway operating work there.A general idea of the sidings required at the new     : ; ard at Les Flamands is given in Appendix 2To.5 but I presume the details will be considered by the Director General of Transportation in France, when the Army Council decide to what extent this new line of communication is to be used. PORT DBS FLAMAI\IDS. -    I have already mentioned that the capacity of the Bassin du Commerce, working all the 24 hours, is in the neighbourhood of from 1,200 to 1,400 tons per day, but, having,h:&quot;h /. -vyv:v:;:h;aa-a::&apos;a-; -v^aa     -h?-&apos;am    in   .
iri mind that it has been suggested that 2,000 to 2,500 tons per day would he more in accord with the requirements of the British Authorities, we have examined the possibility of arriving at something like that figure, but this can only be done by the employment of additional berthing accommodation away from the Bassin du Commerce, namely, at the Port des Flamands,The accommodation at this spot, from the Marine point of view, is not good, and considerable expenditure would be involved in dredging and quays, and only by further careful study can it be decided whether it is a practicable position to bring Cross Channel steamers alongside at this place, or whether the work will have to be done by lighter.     The Admiralty will, no doubt, decide, after further studies have been made, what can be done, and I can only point out that, even if it is not possible to bring transports alongside, the use of this place as an auxiliary at least enables both sides of the ships in the Bassin du Commerce being unloaded at the same time, on the water side -into lighters which could be brought round to the Port des Flamands and unloaded there, but the lighters, too, vrould be subject to the same restrictions in resnect of the loc3c as the Cross Channel steamers,,I have previously nointed out that it would require the expenditure of a considerable amount of money to make the Port des Plamands convenient for unloading from either transport or lighter, but, as will be seen from the plan, it is well situated in respect of the site of the proposed sidings.The site for the sidings has been chosen to be as convenient as possible for the Bassin du Commerce, the Portdes
des Flamands, and for the rest camp.If it were possible, and thought desirable, to make the Port des Flamands available for transports, it offers the great advantage of being absolutely cut off from any interference by the ordinary traffic of the port of Cherbourg;    it will be independent of locks, and there would be, undoubtedly, great economy in time for the transports.I have not been charged to deal with the question of finance or cost in connection with the proposed new line of communication, but it will not be out of place for me to mention that this expenditure would enable Cherbourg to be used when the time of the do-mobilisation comes, also, would permanently improve the facilities of the port and railways,,TAR A: IT TO.PROPOSED SITE FOR YARD Al-ID QUAY.-   At Taranto we had conferences with the Italian Admiral in charge of the port, with the Military and Civilian Railway Authorities, and also with the French Base Officials.At first, some objection was raised to Taranto being used at all, due to congestion, but Admiral Cerri, himself, suggested a possible site, and we examined this,I should mention, however, to start with, that the Commercial Port (see plan &quot;Cw attached) would be quite convenient so far as ship transport is concerned, but it is     1; only reached through a very congested station, and I am convinced that   very serious delay would take place if traffic on this line of communication had to be worked to and shipped from the Commercial v-uays, and I do not recommend it,The Italian Government. for their own purposes.have
have constructed a junction on the line from Brindisi to Taranto at Nassisi, and have built a new railway from Nassisi -to .&apos;:&apos;;&apos;jffaiuto, which ift the station and pi -r,  constructed fortheir own troops going to Greece and Albania, and is now thepier and line used by th? French line communication;The Italian Authorities have, also, in course ofconstruction a line (which, it is stated, will be finishedby the middle of I-iarch) to their Marine Arsenal, and off thisline a ^Branch can be run down to &apos;the.-water level on the southside of what is called the Hare Piccolo.A pier,  stores and sidings can be built without difficulty, nnd a satisfactory site for a camping ground was foundin the neighbourhood by Lieut. Colonel J. C. Robertson, C.I.E. M.B.- I.M.S., who was attached to the Mission from Rome to Faensa on the return jo-arney.     It is right to add, however, that since reaching England I am told that it cannot accommodate 5,000 men.     The camping ground would be a mile or two away from Taranto, and well, cut off from that town, and there would bo no difficulty in conforming with the desire expressed by the Admiral that Officers and men should only be allowed to enter the town with special permission.To reach the water level, considerable cuttings would have to be done, but the waterside can be reached with nothing worse than a gradient of 1 in 70,If the Admiralty find it nossible to use boats of 12 pr 10 feet draught, with very little dredging they could come alongside, but if larger steamers are to be put on the station, the stores and ammunition will have to be lightered fro:: the pier to the ship, and the personnel, as is now done with the French, conveyed to the transport from the nier by
i nugd.lighter.     It was mentioned to me as an additional advantage, that light draught and narrow beam steamers could go through the Corinth canal.CONSTRUCTION,-   The Italian Authorities stated that they could not offer any assistance   either in labour or material for building the new station; though I think, with a little pressing, it would be found they will at least supp^ the labour both for the new connection sidings, and pier.The Ita]ian &quot;Railway Authorities have agreed to get out and supply a detailed level plan of the site for the new connection sidings.A general idea of the sidings required at the new yard at Taranto is given in Appendix No.5 but I presume the details will be considered by the Director General of Transportation in Prance, when the Army, Council decide to what extent this new line of communication is to be used0The new connection from the Brindisi - Taranto line is made at Nassisi, and the Italians have already decided to double the 1ine between Nassisi and the junction for the Italian - French station (Buffaluto).     The fact of working the trains via Brindisi entirely avoids the necessity for any of them going into Taranto station.It is not feasible, from an Engineering point of view, to construct a loop to avoid engines running round at Nassisi.HAgCKJJS.-   General Fiastri stated that, so far as the Italian lines were concerned, only four marches per day (including one personnel marche) could be given, unless the enginesfor
for additional marches (25 per march)     were provided by the British&quot;-&apos;Government;&quot;-    This,-taken with the fact that the maximum live load is rather less than 300 tons over the French railways, Us the limit is 500 tons gross behind the tender) would limit the daily despatch to something in the neighbourhood of 300 tons, unless the additional marches are secured over, the Italian railways,(A), PgRSOITIESL.-   So far as the personnel train is concerned,meColonel Maurier, Chef du 4     Bureau, Ministere de la Guerre, Paris, agreed that the French rolling-stock-&apos;should-work through from Cherbourg to Taranto, but demands the replacement of the passenger rolling stock for use in other parts of France by British stock.     With one personnel train per day of 24 bogie coaches, and allowing, after the experience of the French, 15 days for the round trip, some 360 to 400 carriages will be required,At a meeting which I subsequently held with Monsieur Claveille, (French Minister of Public Works) he stated that the French Government would be agreeable to provide the required stock, on the understanding that,- directly the service started, the British Government should commence shipping to France the necessary vehicles required for replacement.The Italian Authorities stated that they could provide Westinghouse fitted engines for our personnel trains, and I was glad to hear this, as it was not pleasant to contemplate our men having to travel in trains similar to those in which the French troops are travelling, with no continuous brake at all, and only a hand brake on the tender wheels of the engine.The
The Stench and Italian Authorities have agreedfurther to consider the question of accelerating the time for the personnel marche, and, if this could he done, while making the journey more easy., it should economise the amount of stock required for the personnel.(B) STORES.) - With regard to the marches for stores and ammunition, a division of the trains will be required in any event between Modane and Bardonecchiac which is the electrically worked portion of the Mont Cenis tunnelsThe French Authorities, who have the heavy gradient between St. Jean-de-Maurienne and Modane to cope with, are considering whether it would not be better, instead of putting three engines on the train from St. Jean-de-Maurienne to Modane, to divide at the first station and work through,  divided,  to the end of the Italian electric section, to avoid shunting at Modane, which is much congested.I have already stated that the French Authorities insis that no movement of munitions and stores can be made until the siding3 at Les Flamands (and this is equally true of the sidings at Taranto) are finished, and until the wagons, ordered from F-ngland to compensate for the French wagons which might be used on this line of communication, had arrived in France.Although Colonel Maurier agreed to supply the wagons if compensated by British wagons to be used elsewhere,at a later meeting Monsieur Claveille stated he thought the Italian Railway Authorities should agree to the British wagons working through. He further stated that the French Railways were taking risks and suspending their own regulations.: in respect of both couplings and brakes, and the Italians must do the same.
led..I am of opinion, however,  that what Colonel Maurier agreed to will not he interfered with,W.AGOII80 -      I have consistently urged that the French rolling stock should work through, and, if compensation there must be, it should be with wagons to work locally in France, and not over such a route as the proposed one.One of the difficulties which , undoubtedly, would arise in connection with the service, will be the provision of covered wagons.     It is hardly necessary to say that with this particular class of traffic passing covered wagons are a most 3 mp0 rt ant f eat ure ,I believe it to be an absolute impossibility for British cohered wagons in such numbers  as required (2,000 for three goods marches) being spared from the united Kingdom, having regard to the class of traffic which has to be transported in England at the present time,     Whether the Army Council can contemplate sending the stores and munitions in open wagons is, of course, a.matter beyond my purview.The figure of 2,000 wagons is arrived at as follows:-Each train is limited to 40 wagons - at 3 trains a day - and allowing 15 days for the round trip, and IQfy spares. KuGIKES,&apos; -        If there are only one personnel and three goods marches, the French require compensating with 83 engines, and 22 extra engines for every subsequent marche.     At one of the meetings they stated they required an engine which could take a load of 600 tons up a grade of 1 in 100.     It hardly seems fair that we should compensate them in this way, when the maximum load they propose to take is only 500 tons.Th ey
(13). itinued.They also want a Driver, Fireman and Fitter for every eftgine sent;     I took a note of their demand in respect of Engine Drivers and Firemen, hut held out no hope whatever in regard to Fitters,With regard to the Italian demand for 25 engines per marche in excess of four marches, the normal limit of weight per axle is 14 tons, &quot;but they are prepared to take 16, and they arc prepared to buy the engines outright.BRITISH COMPENSATION, -   Monsieur Claveille at the last conference we had stated that&quot;the French Authorit1es are studying the question of all the British compensating operating personnel (except at Cherbourg), locomotives, Carriages and wagons being utilised in the B.E.F. area in France, and of the line of communication between Cherbourg and Taranto being worked entirely by French rolling stock.BRAKE POWER, -   If, of course, this is finally arranged, all questions of brake-power are eliminated in respect of the route between Cherbourg and Taranto, but, if not, unless the Italian Government (and they shew little inclination to do 80) abrogate their regulations, it would require such an enormous amount of work to alter British goods stock that the initiation of the service will be postponed for many months.    The Italian regulation with regard to brake-power is that for every three vehicles one shall be braked, and braked in such a way that a rcan can apply the brake en route on every third wagon of the. train.     To avoid delay en route it is   obvious that trains must be marshalled in.accordance with the regulations of the Italian Railways before they leave Cherbourg.-     DATES
nued.^HiL01 9$$JMM$W1* m    5T6m what I have already said in this report it will he obvious that, under the most favourable conditions,  the service for stores and ammunition cannot be started under three months, but the exigencies of the circumstances&quot; might cause the Army Council to send the personnel overland at a much earlier date.     At Cherbourg this presents no difficulties, as trains can work direct to and from the C-are Maritime, and I suggest it should not be impossible, at least for a time, to do without the re3t camp at Cherbourg, and that the rest camps at St. Germain-au-mont-d&apos;or and Faenza could be rapidly provided, as well as the accommodation at the intervening halts. At the Taranto end, until the British station is complete, the British trains could work into the station -at present used by the French (Buffaluto), and the troops immediately sent by lighter on&apos;to a British transport of considerable size, which might be stationed at Taranto to accommodate men arriving there, when the transport service between Taranto and Salonika is interrupted from any cause; in fact, this ship would temporarily be a rest camp.     Neither the French nor Italian Authorities had any objection to offer to this.     I believe that if such a course is thought desirable, the personnel can be despatched overland within a month.Meanwhile, the plans of proposed accomrr.oda.tion at Cherbourg and Taranto should be approved as early as possible. AM3ULANC3 TRAIH,,-Lieut: Colonel Statham was very anxious that the question should be discussed of running ambulance trains on this route, but I.told him that really the subject was hardly ripe.     if the Army Council think it necessary to run ambulance trains, it merely means that on days when ambulance trains run
(15).    -ued.one of the four marches will have to he appropriated for this service, and the stores cut down a3 the Army Council decide. It should he remembered, of course, that ambulance trains cannot be used for troops from Cherbourg, to Taranto.     The provision of special ambulance stock&apos; will not minimise the difficulties that surround the situation.The question of convalescents and leave men being conveyed by the empty personnel train from Taranto to Cherbourg is a&apos;&apos;matter&apos;which the Array Council will, no doubt,  dispose of with the- French and Italian Governments.REPORTS,.;     It is understood that the Naval, (iuartermaster&apos; General Branch, Ordnance and Medical Officers are reporting Separately dn their,respective subjects.CONCLUSION. - It affords me the greatest pleasure to statethat the French and Italian Authorities, from Ministers- downwardsrwere &quot;most helpful, and I: would specially mention Colonol Maurier,.&quot; meColonel Meynial and the Officials of the 4-- Bureau in Paris,General Fiastri and Officers of the Department of Transport:in:   -Italy.     His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadors in Pari3 and Rome.affordedme every assistance...I feel under great obligation to Colonel Le Roy Lewis, British Military Attache in Paris, Captain&quot;.Kelly, &apos; R..N., British &apos;. Liaison Officer with the French Navy,, in Paris,.Colonel. Lamb, British Military Attache in Rome,   and Mr. Gapei &quot;Cure of British Embassy in Rome.The British Officers who accompanied me rendered valuable assistance, and I am especially indebted to Major G,. Walton, R.E.,  (who was the Liaison Officer between myself and the&apos;1 Military Authorities) whose untiring energy and ready resource werealways at my disposal.I have the honour to be,. -Sir,Your obedient Servant,.(Sgd.)       Guy Calthrcp. General Manager,-sectary London and North. Western- Railway UV&apos;a- Office,  S.W.
DIARY OP THE WORK OP THE WAR OFFICE MISSION.[ay - January 14th. jay - January 15 th.iday - January 16 th.esday * January 17 th.sday - January 18th.ay - January 19th. jrday - January 20 th.fay - January 21st ay - January 22nd.    v ^ay - January 23rd,(tesday - January 24th.pday - January 25 th.fay - January 26 th.pday - January 27 th.Left Charing Cross.Arrived Paris in morning. Called on K.B.M1 s Alphassador. By arrangement wi th H.B.M&apos; s-.,Mi 1 i tary   me --Attache, held meeting with Chef du -4 Bureau.me   -Furth;3r mooting, with Chef du -4-.; -Bureau. ,&apos; Meeting wi th Prench Minister of Public Works.Left for Cherbourg hy train in evening, . accompanied by French Officers,Gaiiie6.---.qn AdmIral Commanding.Port. Examined Port railway facilities.Heeting with all the local au thorities. ;Motored to, and inspected, Surdon and:.;&quot;, Le Hans stations.Motored from Le Mans to, and inspected, St. Pierre-des-COrps (Tours) and Bourges stations.;;Mo tore d fr om\Bourges to,. and in sp ected, -Saincaize, Moulins, Gilly,; and Paray-le-Monial stations.Motored from Paray-le-Monial to, and inspected, Lyon (where the Vice-Consul was se en) and Chambery s ta ti on s.Left in morning by train for Modane, where mee ting was held wi th General Piastri, Italian Director of Transport, who was on his&apos;way to pari s.--Mission then left for Rome by train.Arrived at Rome in morning.7 .Called on H.B.M,s Ambassador.By arrangement with H.B.M!s Military Attache, called on I talian Minister for War, and held mee tings wi;th I tali an Civil Diroc tor-Gerioral of -------.. Railways.Held fur ther nee ting wi th I talianCivil Director-General;of Railways.: Left in evening by train for Tarahto.Called on Admiral -Commanding the por t. Examined port and Railway facilities.
APPENDIX 1.Sunday - January 28th.Monday - January 29th.Tuesday - January 30th.Wednesday - January 31st.Thursday - February 1st.Friday - February 2nd.Saturday ** February 3rd. Monday. - February 5 th. Wednesday - February 7th,Meeting ,.wi th all the local authorities. ] Left by train for Bari and Foggia.Continued by train through Castellammare and Ancona to Faenza, where Lieut; Colonel Statham had inspected the proposed camp.Continued by train through Parma, Tortona, Turin to Modane.Arrived Paris by train in morning.Lieut: Colonels Statham and Hacdonald inspected proposed camp site at St, Germain-au-mont-d&apos;or, and arrived in Paris on February 1st.^-&apos;v-o^:k:/V&apos;:.&apos;\:\.^- meMeeting in morning with Chef du 4Bureau, and in afternoon with FrenchMinister of public Works, and Italian; D irector .6f Transportation.Met General Sir Eric Geddes at General Headquarters, B.E.F.Arrived London.Meeting of Mission in London.Complete report handed to Secretary, .   War Office.NOTE. At every place inspected en route, local authorities met the Mission, and gave all required information.
lice m Istres. IStation.Cherbourg	d	0.40Surdon	a	8.39i !    &quot;	d	9.44Le Hans	a.	.15.10ii	d	13.57St -Pierre-des-		Corps(Tours) .	a	lei. 50(i          it	d	20.07Saincaize	a	4.17ii	d	6 .22paray-le-		Honial	a	10.23it	d	11,12St.Germain-au-		mont-d5or	a	16.20St .Germain-au*mont-d&apos;or.	d	17 .35Chambefy	a	0.30ii	d	2.0lib dan e.	- a	7.0ii	d	8.30Turin(Triage)	a	13.50n           it	d	15 ,0 .Tor tona	a	19 .0 .ii	d	20.30Parma	a	1.0ii	d	2.30Faenza	a	6[30Faenza AncohaiiCastellammarePpgfeiaTiming.Time between stations.d .--;	10.0,a	15 .0.d i	16 .30a	21.30d	23.0.a	5.30) 8 hours. )) 4^- hours )5 hours. 8 hours. )) 4 hours.) )5 hours.) 7 hours.)&apos;:) 5 hours.)) 5 hours )4 hoursA% hours. 6 hours.) 5 hours.) 5 hours. )6i: hours.Time between camps.40hours39 hours
APPENDIX 2.pee in jetres.Station.Timing.Time between stations.Time betv/een camps.Poggia BariiiTarantod ad a7 .0.ll .612.3D 19.40) 4 hours )) 7 hours )34 hours
.     PARTICULARS 0? &quot;HALT&quot; STATIONS.3URD0N.     The line on the east side of the island platform will he used.     There is land adjoining sufficient for the erection of lavatories, &amp;c.    , There is a-small buffet on the station, which could be used by Officers. LE MANS.     The train will have to. stop at the passenger platform in the middle of the station, while refreshments are supplied.&apos;&quot; There - is a Prench Red. Cross S ta ti on, and a French canteen here. /v^U^-^SAINT: PIERRE DES CORPS.     No. 10 line will &quot;be usedi     With the removal of one or two / small buildings,: suf f icient space can be : found alongside this siding for the necessary kitchens, etc., without interfering with the building which already exists and is used as a rest hut for French troops on leave.There is a station buffet which could be used by Officers.     Drinking water at the station is limited, but a good supnly can be obtained for other purposes by running pipes from engine water tanks.SAINCAIZE,   A siding known as;&quot;Gimouille&quot;, access to which is obtained by backing trains from the station or goods yard, would be used for stabling train, and land; adjoining/access to which could easily be obtained by.removal of a hedge, was sufficient in area to give necessary accommodation for kitchens, latrines, &amp;c .     Good supply of water of indifferent quality for washing &amp;c. purposes..    Drinking water could be obtained by laying pipes from a pipe line leading to a reservoir a few hundred yards away.PARAY-LE-KQNIAL.   The line adjoining the platform nearesttiie goods sidings, to be used for holding train, and there is a
space at the Lyon end of the platform, sufficient and suitablefor necessary acCormiodationV ... There is. a buffet at the station,also drinking water, and good supply of water.for other purposes.CHAI.i53BY.   A line will be set apart, for the use of ourtrains.     There is plenty of water available.HODAIO.     A line will be set. apart for the use of our trains. -There is plenty of water available.IURIIT (Triage) .     This will avoid going; into Turin passenger station, and the line suggested is the last in; the Pascio Orti, Thi s line i s about 20 metres nor th of the main.. passenger lines from Modane - Alessandria, giving plenty of room for sheds, etc. TORTQUA.   The outside line on the north side was given as the most suitable, and there is sufficient room here, also, for small sheds.     Prinking water available.PARMA.    . The question of a garage siding at this stationi s being looked in to by the Railway Au thori ties.     Particulars notyet. to hand. ... . . &quot;&quot; . -AHCQIIa.     The most suitable garage line was voie 6, giving a distance of 5 metres for shelters between voies 5 and 6.     The proposed line runs just to the north of the wall of the passenger station.     There is plenty of drinking water available. CASTBLLAMMARE. ;. ; The: best 1 ine is voie 5, having 5 metres room on the wea tern side, all along the length of the train, for shelters between line 5 and a dead-end.     There are reservoirs   ... quite close, and:a pipe line would be necessary. ;: POGGIA.       Voie 8 is the best, with buildings between voie 8 and workshops.     There is plenty of water not fit for drinking. Drinking water, would, probably;; have to be imported by wagon. BARI. This station is at present being re-modelled,.andthe
the Railway Au tho.rities are looking in to the question of providing a suitable line for stabling the personnel train.
-:&apos;  STJMMARY OF RAILWAY&apos;&apos;RSQ.UIHEI.SITTS.ONE PERSONNEL TRAIN, worked by French stock throughout, -     and French engines Cherbourg to Modane - Italian :engines Modane to Tarahto, necessitates360 to 400 British passenger coaches. 22 Engines./ .    ^ -/ 22 Drivers.:   &quot;  &apos; /\&apos;:v:&apos; &apos;22 Firemen. &apos;?V&apos;^&apos;::-;--V:&apos;^being supplied to the French Railways.THREE GOODS MARCHES worked by French stock throughout, French engines - Cherbourg to Modane, and Italian engines - Modane to laranto,:necessitates ; 2,000 Briti sh wagons. &apos;   66 Engines.        .  - * 66 Drivers. 66 Firemen, -being supplied to the French Railways. FOR EVERY ADDITIONAL MARCKS/&quot;-;;-:650 Wagons,        :y^f-&apos;\y&apos; -   &apos; &apos; 22.Engines.   -        - -    &apos;     &apos; - -  .  -; / &apos;     &quot;        &apos;*22 Drivers,/;-- j/-.&apos;; V-. V-/&apos;y22 Firemen &apos;S;:-/;^^v&apos;:Vr-;v.;/;&apos;must be supplied to the French Railways and25 engines to the I talian&apos; Railways..\.V I he 11 al i an;: Ra ilway s ar e pr opar cd to buy Bri ti sh engines outright.,SIDING
-APPBITDIX 4.SIDItTG. AGCO:iIODA&apos; TQIT.CHERBOURG. Sidings required at L3S FLAKAIfDS to hold two ,days&apos;  supply of passenger coaches, and two days&apos;  suoolyof hgoods^wagons. :   Also two ;sidings for-iaarshallihg trains,, and si din.;;; alongside^, sheds for loading and unloading.storesA shunting neck, ,40 wagons in: length, with;., falling gradient towards sidings,;;;:h;&apos;v&apos;;;:;o;&quot;::;,&apos;.;A rdccordeciezi t connecting the lino alongside the .. las sin du Corner ce with the - Cherbourg - Bar flour line, together with a loop to hold 40 wagons.Also a line to connect the new sidings at Les -Plamands with the existing line at that place.ihehshed acCoDKiodation required by Depar.;taenis is SUPPLIES.       3001 x 40&apos;0KDHA1TC3-     Y   40&apos; x 180&apos; general stores,i   1,800 superficial feet explosives,partitioned into 200&quot;sq. feet, 700 sq. feet, 900 sq, feet..R;3.STOKES^A small postal and K,P.0. shed will also; he necessary. TARaxTIO . Sidings -to: hold one personnel. and: three goods   v.trains to he provided at the Kiah Level Junction, .wi th the Arsenal Line. aha:;:^\:;Y:-.Y y^y-r;-:&apos;\;i::::^:A reception road, and running ground road (both to hold 40 wagons)  to he provided outside the sheds, and two roads to hold 20 wagons each to he provided alongside  . loading stages of shed. a- .Al so, shun tin,: neck 40 wagon s . in1 eng th, The, shod accoi^noda t ion. required by - Department els: aiSUPPLIES. ) Double that at OUDihu-TCE. ,) Cherbourg.h:
RAILWAY ORGANISATI ON.FRENCH.     The line from Cherbourg to Le Mans is the Stat. railway, from Le Mans to Saincaize is part of the Paris - Orlean railway, and the line from Saincaize to Modane is worked &quot;by theP.L.M. railway.Each of these lines has its Commission de Reseau at Paris, with Sous-Commissions in the provinces.     The head-quarters at the Sous-Commissions,  so far as this new line of comrjunication is concerned, are atRennes   -   For the Cherbourg - Le Mans section.   Etat Rly: lours     -   Le Mans to Viarzon, exclusive. P.O.Rly:Orleans -   Viarzon - Saincaize,  exclusive. P.0.Rly:Nevers   -   Saincaize - Paray-le-Monial, P.L.M.Rly:exclusive.Lyon      -   Paray-le-Monial - Modane; P.L.M.Rly:ITALIAN.   All the Italian Railways are State, and their peace administration is for war purposes under General Fiastri, Director of Transportation for the Italian front, and Italian Railways generally.     He has as Deputy Directors of Transportation at Rome, Colonels Carpentieri and Massimo. Under these Deputy Directors at Rome are Military Commissions at Turin, Bologna and Naples (so far as this line of communication is concerned).Under the Commission at Turin are the Station Military Commanders at Modane, Turin, Alessandria, and Vogera.Under that at Bologna are the Military Station Commanders at Piacenza, Parma, Modena, Bologna, Faenza, Rimini, Ancona and Castellammare.Under that at Naples are the Military Station Commanders at Fog-La, Bari, Brindisi, and Taranto.At each of the stations mentioned above there are
The Italian Railway Authorities agree to place I tali an Mili tary S ta t i on Commanders at any o ther sta ti on s required by us, to act in liaison with our Transport Officers....        The Director General of State Railways is Commandateur de Corne.     The Deputy -Director General is Commandateur Berrinl, while Cowmandateur de Roberto is Director of Movement.&apos;-BRITISH TRANSPORTATION OFFICERS. ADMINISTRATIVE.     The Chiefs of the French and Italian Railways consider that the best liaison organisation for this British line of communication would be for a. representative ofthe Director General of Transportation to be in touch with theme4   Bureau at Paris, and for this representative to have a delegue at Rome in touch:with the Italian Director of Transportation there.     They have come to this conclusion, as, although the line of communication does not run through either Paris or Rome, all orders are given by the head military and civil railway directors in the respective capitals by telephone to the 1ocal authorities coneerned.     If the 1iaison representatives are in Paris and Rome,  telephonic communication, for British railway officers between these two places, and from ; the two capitals to the provinces, is very much simpler, and, also telegrams, code or otherwise, could be transmitted between Paris and Rome through the two Military Attaches.This is the liaison organisation at present adopted by the French   for their transport to Italy. .It would also be necessary for the representative of the Director General of Transportation to be in touch with the Headquarters of this line of communication, wherever these raay be sett I ed by the -Tar Office.BRITISH
2U FRAITCE.	Deputy Assistant Director	of Docks - Cherbourg.D.A.D.R.T. (and R.O.D.)	ii	Surdon.R.T.O.	Le Mans.R.T.O.	S t. Pi err e-des*-Corps.	(Tours). :R.1,0.	Saincaize. -R-.T .0.	- ;&quot;V-.J: Par ay-1 e-Mon ial i   :R.T.O.	St 4Germain-au-mont-d&apos; or.	7\:^:\--;^&apos;-,&apos;.;;T (Lyon).R.T.0V	Chanbery.R.T;0.    .                          ,	St. Jean-de-M&amp;urienne.R.T.O.	Modane.TTi ttATiY. .(.unde.r ;.thc dele^ue at Roinoh-, jK 1 0                                             .....Bar donee chi a. 1-   .R.S.O.                              .            . . - 1urin&apos; I :    H.1.0.                                       /.;.Iortana.... li.T.0.                                            Saenza. 1..tj f /\ Castellammare. I .  -  R.T.O.                                                                           &apos;R.T.O.                                                 .Bari&apos; ID.A.D.R.T&apos;.                                           Taranto. -Iv.:&apos;::-::;  D.A.D. Docks. IAt those stations where there are only meal-halts and that for one train of personnel a day, the simplestprocedure would be for the R.T.Os. to be responsible for the        1: feeding   IteftlSK TRAIT SPORT AT X ON OFFICERS.EXECUTIVE. The following Executive Transportation Officers are proposed in Prance and Italy-:-
APPENDIX 5.BRITISH TRANSPORTATION OFFICERS.feeding arrangements at those halts, and at certain stationsin the B.E.F. Area,     If, however,  there is likely to &quot;bo anOfficer of another Department at these meal halts, it shouldsuffice for the Transportation Department to have a Frenchspeeding N.C.O. for liaison railway work.     In these lattercircumstances it would he host to have an R.1.0. atTOURS IN (Surdon, Le Mans, St.pierre-(for Tours and Nev;rs CHARG3 (des-Corps (Tours),commissions). OF (Saincaize. (410 kilometres).LYON(for Lyon Commission).       &quot; (paray-le-Ivionial.(400 kilometres). (St.Germain-au-mont-d&apos;or.(Chambery.(St.lean-de-Maurienne. (Modane.TURIN (Bussoleno.(for Turin Commission)       0 (Turin.(320 kilometres). (Tortona.(Parma.FAENZA. (Faenza.(for Bologna Commission). (Ancona,(480 kilometres). fCastellammare.(Foggia.in addition to D.A.D.R.1. Cherbourg andD.A.D.R.T. - Taranto, in charge of Bari and laranto. (for Naples Commission).It is essential that all Officers and as many IT.COs. as possible should speak French,  and any Officers knowin Italian would be most useful in Italy.      The Italian Army should be asked to supply interpreters as required.Only the R.T.0&apos;s at Cherbourg and Taranto need heave technical railway experience.

</content>
</cab>
