<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/7/0 images: 84-84</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S 3* ORE T^-&quot; &apos; - WAR CABINETMEMORA!NDUM Oil: TIIE /PRCPOSES/llCEFlAgE - III THEPORTUGUESE. CONTjNG^THOW BEING- TRANSPORTED T0 FRANCE   :The Portuguese. Government has. -proposed(see telegram dated 23rd February,1917, from General Barnardiston to the Chief of the Imperial   General Staff) to increase the expedi-tlcnary. force now. he ing transported: to Prance from e-Divisi on&quot;: of.apprcxiamtely :.40,000 men to an: Army. Corps of about 53,CCO.; men-     7 British transports are at present employed in carry-ing the Portuguese troops and;the-proposed increase in the strength of the/force wil1 hecessitate each.vessel -making 7 trips in place of 5 for the original number.     Owing to the exposed;,route/followed^by: these-vessels&apos;:-they: can only he per-mitted to s ail with troops on &quot;dark - nights during the period of new moon^:;Practical-experience shows that it is only possible to rely on making :one trip with each transport during each lunar month....- The proposed move of sn Army Corps mil/;/.;-therefore not. be complete until the end of July.     During this period these 7 transports:&apos; are not available- for ; other duties, while, in order that; they may be escorted on passage, 4 des- .: V; troyers have had to be withdrawn from the ,0rand Fleet for the whole of this period.     The withdrawal of these valuable vessels from the Fleet for such a length/of time is a very serious: matter in itself, while, owing to,the. short nights, in MayJune and July, it is probable ,that further. destroyers, would be- necessary: in order to afford sufficient protection to those transports.The dilatory and unpractical:&quot;methods/&apos;of the. Portuguese. authorities render, -further delay not only possible&apos;but highly. probable.     The reports;received from;the: Naval Transport Officer at Lisbon contain many instances ofthe delays and  , difficulties: caused:by: the; ijiability; of the Portuguese to comply .with a pre-arranged programme, to appreciate the value of time or the necessity, for- maintaining discipline. , - Under these circumstances.there is grave reason to fear that the transport of this Army Corps.will drag on-throughout the. sum-mer months, keeping both destroyers and transports from more valuable and important duties.....   The behaviour of /the Portuguese troops whilst on board the transports-indicated a: lamentable lack -/of. discipline., and it /is suggested that, the strength .of. the Division should not be increased until eisperience /hasshewn that the troops possess fighting value. -Apart from this question, it is certain that it will .be extremely difficult to spare the transports, /and; impossible to provide:: the /escort of destroyers, as -everjr available :, ve ss el/of / this ;/type will be re quire d during the short nights to protect trade&quot;. y&apos;::&apos;y^r^^^^:--/.:::&apos;:::-:-ADMIRALTY, S.W.6th. March. 1917

</content>
</cab>
