<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/7/0 images: 261-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AIEBQAKP.Renort to the Calbinet.10th March, 1917.1.It has been decided to set up a special experton.Committee to investigate the causes of accidents occurring to aeroplanes in their expe&quot;trimental stage, and also to aeroplanes&apos; adopt eel for use in the Services ^here the cause of the accident is obscu-ce.proposal to set up a central design establishment under the Air Board for the trial of engines of ne-p design put forward by manufacturers.     It has been decided that this course might lead to a revival of the distrust manifested by the Trade of the trials hitherto conducted at the Royal Aircraft Factory and that it would be preferable to require manufacturers to set up testing benches of their ovn, complying with the Air Board1s requirements as regards accuracy, where their engines could be tested under supervision.3.      The increasing altitude at which aeroplanes are required, to fly produces the physiological symptoms commonly known as mountain sickness.     a conference of experts on the subject has recommended the   ! formation of a permanent Committee to study the matter and conduct experiments --ith a vie1? to overcoming the2.The Board, have had under consideration a
disabilities in question.     The Board have set up a Committee accordingly.4.     The Board have had under consideration a recomrnen-dation that an order should be placed in Australia for aeroplanes, seaplanes and engines with a view to developing the aeronautical industry in that Country. Ho decision has been arrived at pending further investi-gation of the subject.5.     The attention of the Board has been drawn to labourdifficulties in the aircraft manufacturing establishmentsin the London area, which have nor.? culminated at theimportant Works of Messrs. Peter Hooker,     The Controllerof Aeronautical Supplies has informed tha Board thatthere are signs of a strongly seditious and syndicalistelement at these Works and that firm action on the partof the Government which may lead, to a strike appears tohim necessary.     The question of tho action to be takenis one primarily for the Ministry of Munitions, butconcerns the Board, inasmuch as it may temporarily affectoutput of aircraft.The Board, after considering the particular class cfwork undortaken by Messrs. Peter Hooker1, Have expressedtheir concurrence with the opinion cf Sir William weir.6.     The Board have be n askod their viev;s as tc theproper functions of the Royal Aircraft Factory.     Theyhave re-affirmed the decision previously given that thedominating object of the Pactcry is research, but that itcan be employed at the discretion cf the Controller cf-2-
Aeronautical Supplies to undertake manufacture, in special oases, with a view to meeting emergency requirements or to make good a failure cf contractors.     It is also specially adapted for producing the first hatch cf machines of a new experimental type of R.A.F, design. 7.     The attention of the Beard has been drawn to the proceedings of the Committee which is considering the effect of the Military Service Acts upon the industries of the Country, with special reference to the aeronautical industry.     The Board have concurred with the view of the Controller of Aeronautical Supplies, who is a Member of the Committee, that it would be impossible to ask for the exemption of men engaged on aeronautical construction at large, as this would cover too much ground; but a list cf special trades has been drawn up and of the firms whose output is vital to our requirements.     This will be submitted to the Committee.     The Board expressed concurrence.8.     The Board have had. before them important requests ed   from the Russian Government for the supply of aviation r   material.     The Board have come to the conclusion that compliance with these requests must entail a ccrres-ponding reduction of the supplies to our own Forces, and they have not felt justified in promising compliance in the absence of special instructions from the T/ar Cabinet. A letter on the subject, dated the 8th March, has been addressed to the Secretary to the War Cabinet.-    (Signed)   H.P.HARVEY,Secretary to the Air Board.

</content>
</cab>
