<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/202/5 images: 326-340</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^DOCUMENT is THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCP(78) 75 COPY NO10 July 1978CABINETPOLICE PAYMemorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerINTRODUCTION1. I attach a paper by the Home Secretary and the Secretaries of Statefor Scotland and for Northern Ireland which was discussed by the MinisterialCommittee on Economic Strategy Sub-Committee on Pay Negotiations (EY(P))on Monday 10 July.    This memorandum records EY(P)&apos;s conclusions.AMOUNT OF THE AWARD2. The Edmund-Davies Report recommends average increases of theorder of 40 per cent in national rates of police pay, plus special allowancesof  650 a year for the Metropolitan and City of London Police (in addition tothe existing London weighting, currently  319 a year) and of  500 a year forthe Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) instead of the present  183.    TheCommittee recommend that these increases should be paid in full on1 September 1978, though they envisage the possibility of phasing, on which theGovernments position is reserved.    The Committee&apos;s recommendations takeaccount of the fact that the police are subject to a prohibition against striking,which the Committee strongly endorse.    We are committed to accepting theirrecommendations as to amounts for all ranks.    EY(P) recommend that thiscommitment should be honoured.    Some of us felt however that the prohibitionagainst striking should be written into any agreement with the police on pay.PHASING3. EY(P) recommend that the increases in national rates should be paid intwo equal instalments, on 1 September 1978 and 1 September 1979.    The firstinstalment would thus be of the order of 20 per cent on average, and wouldsubsume any going rate of increases in the next pay round.    The secondinstalment would be the remaining 20 per cent, but we also recommend (seeparagraph 6) that this should be topped up by reference to increases inearnings during the intervening 12 months.    We consider that theEdmund-Davies rates should apply in full for pensions purposes from1 September 1978.1
4. EY(P) did not reach agreement on the phasing of the London andNorthern Ireland allowances.    Most of us would prefer phasing, at least forthe London allowance, though we recognised that the exceptional circums-tances both in London and in Northern Ireland constitute strong argumentsfor immediate payment of these allowances in full.    There is a specialproblem with the RUC in that their allowance was the same as that for theArmed Forces until the Armed Forces1 recent pay increase.    TheSecretaries of State for Northern Ireland and for Defence are submitting aseparate note about the detailed linkages in this area.    EY(P) saw three mainpossibilities -i. To pay both the London and the Northern Ireland allowances infull from 1 September 1978.ii. To pay the increases in two equal instalments from 1 September1978 and 1 September 1979.    If we follow this course the effective ratesfrom 1 September 1978 will be, in London,   644 a year ( 319 Londonweighting plus half of  650) and in Northern Ireland,   341. 50 a year(the present  183 plus half the difference between that and  500).iii. To pay more than 50 per cent of the Northern Ireland increase on1 September 1978, while continuing to phase the London increase 50-50.The Northern Ireland increase could be either to  365 (to match therevised allowance for the Armed Forces) or to the full  500.The Cabinet is invited to decide which course to adopt.UPDATING5. The Edmund-Davies Committee recommend that on 1 September 1979and in subsequent years police pay for ranks up to Superintendent should beupdated in accordance with changes in the index of average earnings (newseries) in the previous 12 months.    For ranks above Superintendent theupdating would take account of &quot;changes elsewhere in the community&quot; as well(ie of changes in the pay of other jobs at comparable levels).    However, theyrecognise that in the years to come there will be changes in the police serviceand in outside pay mc/ements generally, and to take account of this theyrecommend that either side of the new negotiating body should be able topropose variations to the updating process.6. As to the 1 September 1979 updating EY(P) recommend that this shouldbe carried out by reference to changes in the average earnings index (and, forthe top ranks, other changes) as the Edmund-Davies Committee propose.This is necessary to maintain the value of the original award, in relation toaverage earnings, over the phasing period.    We also recommend that thisupdating should apply to all ranks of the police on the grounds of parity oftreatment through the Force, despite the fact that top-ranking police officersreceive salaries comparable to those of the Top Salaries Review Body group,for whom the Government has said that updating will not be automatic.
7. For the longer term, some members of EY(P) considered thatthe Edmund-Davies Committee&apos;s formula for up-dating constituted partof their recommendations on pay.    This meant that, under the terms of ouroriginal commitment to accept their pay recommendations, we should acceptthe use of their proposed formula for as long as both sides of the newnegotiating body chose to use it.    On the other hand, a number of us felt thatthe police could not realistically be guaranteed one particular place on thepay ladder forever.    We noted that the Edmund-Davies Committee themselvesenvisaged the possibility of changes in the up-dating process.    These changescould come at any time.    We hoped that the Government might rely on this toavoid committing itself to an indefinite acceptance either of the Edmund-Davies formula or of any other.8. When the decision on police pay is announced I think public attentionwill focus on what we are proposing for 1978 and 1979.    But we shall have tosay something about the longer term.    The questions for Cabinet to decideare:   should we commit ourselves to accepting the Edmund-Davies formulafor up-dating for so long as the new negotiating body wants to use it?    Orshould wc confine ourselves to some general expression of support for theprinciple of keeping police pay at the &quot;right&quot; level, without committingourselves to any particular formula for determining what that right level i6?REPERCUSSIONS9. EY(P) noted that the pay of Ministry of Defence and Atomic EnergyAuthority Police is linked to that of the British Transport and Port of Londonpolice, which, in turn is linked to the pay of the Home Department police.EY(P) recommend that the Edmund-Davies rates should not be appliedautomatically to these linked forces, but that each claim to follow theEdmund-Davies rates should be considered on its merits.ANNOUNCEMENT OF DECISION10.       EY(P) recommend that the Governments decision on the Edmund-Davies report should be announced as soon as possible, presumably by meansof a Parliamentary Statement, and that this should happen before thepublication of any White Paper about future pay policy.     This may run us intodifficulties with the timetable for printing the report, but we consider that ifnecessary the statement should be made before printed copies are available.D W HTreasury Chambers10 July 19783
POLICE PAY -Note by tho Home Secretary and theSecretaries of State for Scotland and Northern IrelandBackground . . - .In October 1977 the Police Federations accepted a 10% payincrease for Stage 3*   This settlement was coupled with the offerof an independent inquiry into police pay with the Governmentfirmly committed to accept its recommendations, subject only tophasing.   The terns of reference of the inquiry covered all ranksand the commitment was given to the Federations, the superintendentsassociations and the chief officers1 associations-   The Government1scommitment thus covers all the Committee&apos;s recommendations on pay.Tlie Committee which undertook the inquiry, under&apos;the chairmanshipof Lord Edmund-lOavies, was already reviewing police negotiatingmachinery.   The Committee have now submitted two reports;   one onpay and the other on negotiating machinery.Content of the Renprt2.     A summary of the Committee1 s report on. pay and a list of theirmain recommendations is at Annex A.   The Committee conclude thot to&quot;remunerate thepolice properly for their increasingly demanding workand to attract and more particularly retain the necessary manpowersubstantial pay increases arc required.   The new scales which theyrecommend are. in Annex B.   The recommended scales of pay amount toincreases over current scales of:   for constables from 29*7$ ip thefirst yearns service to 45.5% after 15 years;   for inspectors upto 40.4$:   for superintendents up to 38.5%;   for chief constablesof tho..largest provincial forces 4-2.3/-*   These recommendations takeaccount of-the uniqueness of the police role in society and therestrictions to which they are subject, including prohibition of&apos; the right to strike which the Committee strongly endorse.   Rent\.allowance would continue to be paid to those police officers notprovided with accommodation. .
^^^^ 1^1   I m0 ttm I ^  I   B        na3.     The rococnnended scales are national rates for the. wholecountry.   The Committee also recommend that the acute manpowerdeficiency in London on the one hand and the special difficultiesfacing members of the police service in Northern Ireland on theother should be recognised by the payment of a non-pensionableallowance.   For the Metropolitan and City of London Police thisshould be  650 a year (in addition to the existing London Weightingcurently  319 a year);   for the Royal Ulster Constabulary  300a year (instead of the present  183).4-.     The increase in the basic national pay bill would be of theorder of 40%.   The London and RUC allowances would add about afurther 3%.3-     The Committee1s recommendations are what they considerappropriate at 1 September 1978* which is 12 months after the lastsettlement in which all ranks be-low chief -officer received 10%under Stage 3*     The recommendations for chief officers alsorelate to 1 September 1978.    The Committee recommend that thisdate should replace their previous settlement date of 1 July andthat their link with local authority chief officers should not beretained.    The size of the recommended increases for chiefofficers reflects the Committee&apos; s recommendations that the 1006due to them this 1 July for Stage 3 should be postponed andincluded in the overall award recommended for 1 September 1978.--6o     The Committee say that it would be logical to implement therecommendations from 1 September 1978 but recognise that forwider reasons the Government may decide to phase the recommenda-tions, in which case they, urge that pensions should be calculatedfrom 1 September 1978 on the basis of the recommended salaries.7.     For the future they recommend that police pay should beupdated annually on the basis of changes in average earnings.They recognise, however, that the new negotiating body will needto be able to apply it flexibly.   In respect of chief officersthey recommend that regard should also be had to changes elsewherein the community.The Governments Response8.     The report has been eagerly awaited by the police and mustbe seen against the background of public concern about lav; andorder which will continue to grov; stronger&apos; as the electionapproaches.   To meet the justified concern and to stem thecontinuing loss of police manpower we need a settlement which willappear fair to both police and public.   It is desirable that theGovernment should retain the initiative by giving its responsein a Parliamentary Statement on the day of publication.   Thiscould be 19 July;   we understand, however, that other announcementsmay make the week beginning 24- July preferable.   - -
I -,&apos; &apos;..   I imm I &apos;.  w Si i       a9.     We are cQmuiit-ted-^&quot;to^. accept the -recommendations;   our only roomfor manoeuvre is&apos;.on.phasing.   Settlement for firemen, Armed Forces,doctors and /jdehtists-?&apos;-l&apos;33SRB.etc., have established a pattern ofnhasing increases. over-.two, years beyond.&apos;the Stage 3 settlement-From the&apos;point of.view of the nolice, and also from the point ofview of pay pojicy;. generally, there is advantage in keeping to thispattern,. which&quot; would imply dividing the police award betweenSeptember 1978 . and Sent ember 1979-   By comparison with the othersettlements, meqtioned, however, there is a quirk in the .Edmund Daviesrecommendations, in&apos; &quot;that, they already, include by implication anunspecified amount for Stage 4- in addition to the catching-upelement.   It is explicitly recommended that thc pronoscd ratesshould be-enhanced in- September.1979 by a percentage reflectingfurther movement in average earnings by then.10.     An important consideration in settling the phasing arrangements may be the timing of the announcement of the decisionin relation to the timing of announcement of general payarrangements for the period a  er-.. July 1978.   2?or example,if, when the -police pay decision is announced, it is, already publicly known that there will be a pay policy. for the period after July incorporating a guide-line of,*        say,. X nor cent, then it would be possible to award the-police X per cent plus one-half of thc balance of the&apos;   V        !Edmund Davies recommendation to take effect from::&quot;   September 1978, leaving the remainder of the recommendation,plus .any further development in average earnings, to be&apos;       implemented from September 1979*   Shis would indeed put... I. ;t]ie &quot;treatment of the police &quot;in the most exact similarity&apos;n.6ssible .to.that of Armed Forces, etc;.     y -       .     ----- -- -       - - ....... &apos; / , ..,&apos;        -if &quot;the police pay decision were, on the other hand,&apos;/-announced ahead of any announcement of future pay policygenerally, the-least inconvenient phasing arrangementwould be simply to split the recommendation 50 X 50between the two years (leaving an expectation that thesecond year payment would be enhanced in the light ofaverage earnings increases in the previous year).   Itcould be very difficult, with any alternative division,...     ..to avoid the, implication of some assumption about the;*&apos;.&quot;&apos;.&apos;appropriate Stage: 4 guide-line.-11.     rfhe large increases recommended for chief officers have to beconsidered in the context of the TSE3 recommendations and theirimplementation, together with other top salciries such as those inlocal government..  TSHB has a direct implication since the tonpolice salary, that of the Metropolitan Commissioner, is linkedto that of permanent secretaries.   The only change the Committeerecommends is to bring him into line with all other noliceofficers who are entitled to accommodation or rent allowance inlieu.
12.     In the view of the Home Secretary and the. Secretary of Statefor Northern&apos; Ireland the urgent, need to improve the&apos; London manpowerposition and the special difficulties in Northern Ireland constitutea strong case for paying the proposed London and RUC allov/ances infull from September 1978.   (As the Committee recognise, the RUCallowance of  500 would mean breaking the link with, the serviceman1sallowance which has recently been raised - for the service but notthe RUC - to  365)-&apos;  The Secretary of State for Scotland doubtswhether different treatment for the allov/ances can be&apos; justified ifthe main round is phased,.&apos; General pay. policy considerations wouldalso pointto&apos;treating the allowances on the same basis of divisionas the main settlement., ;13*   1 The Committee1 s recommendations for updating police pay willcause difficulties.   These recommendations stand apart from thoseon pay levels;   but the Governments commitment will be held by thepolice service to apply here as well..   Bearing in mind theCommittee&apos;s recognition that the new&apos;negotiating machinery musthave flexibility to adapt to future circumstances, it seemsacceptable to endorse the principle of updating recommended byby the Committee.       ... .&quot; . -;...... 2JC ...   axoon vgff y     - r&quot;   --        .;.14-.    . We believe that if there is phasing the Committee1 srecommendations safeguarding tensions, which follow the patternestablished in other cases, should be accepted.   Certainconsequent!als, such as the nay of police cadets and H.H. Inspectorsof Constabulary, flow from the Committee&apos;s recommendations.   Wcpropose- that existing linkages should be preserved.   Therecommendations will have repercussions on police forces for whichthe Home Departments are not responsible.   The Committee iscareful to make clear that it has not considered their claims.At present there is a linkage between Home Department police forcesand the British Transport and Port of. London Authority Police and,through these forces, to the HOD and AEA forces.   It will be forour colleagues concerned to consider later how the Committeefsrecommendations might affect these relationships.Conclusion 1   -&apos;15*     Wc invite our colleagues:    &apos;&quot;\(i) to agree that the recommendations of the Edmund-DavicsCommittee on pay should be implemented in two nhases,the first on 1 September 1978 and the second on1 September 1979;   and to determine the basis ofphasing;. ;* - - -(ii) to decide whether the special claims of. London and :theRUC justify paying these allowances in full onV,   .-.    1 September 1978; , &apos;   . (       r,::...:      -       . --   (iii) to endorse the principle of updating recommended by the&quot;Committee; &apos; :(iv)   to agree that the Governmenfs response should beannounced in a Parliamentary Statement, probably in theweek beginning&apos;24July.
Annex AEDMUND-DAVTES COMMITTEE REPORT:SUMMARY GF CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONSTerms of ReferenceThe Committee^ terms of reference on pay v;ere to considerthe levels of remuneration appropriate for the police in the lightof such factors as developments in responsibilities and workload,the stresses and dangers to which the police are exposed, the needto ensure adequate police strengths, and the restrictions to whichthe police are subject.The Role of the Police .    .2.     In their report, the Committee draw attention to the uniquerole of the police officer and the special features of his presentposition.    They mention the arduous and increasingly dangerous natureof his duties;    a workload which involves night duties and afrequent requirement to work at week-ends and on rest days;    andrestrictions upon his private life, including his ^lace of residenceand the ty^e of work in which members of his family are permittedto engage.    The Committee take account of the serious increase incrime, the increase in terrorism, and the demands and stressesimposed on the police by threats to public order, all of which havesignificantly increased -the risks of assault and injury.    They alsoconsider the increasing demands imposed by the steady increase intraffic volume, the flood of legislation in recent years and thera^id ^ace of technological change.The rir-&apos;ht to strike3.     One of the most important restrictions Placed upon the policeis the lack of the right to strike.    The Committee are firmly ofthe view that the police should not be given the right to strike,but they considered that the absence of this right constitutes aserious deprivation for any worker and should be borne in mindwhen determining the appropriate level of remuneration for thepolice.Pay of the federated ranks and superintendents4.     In recent years, the police service has been suffering fromserious manpower deficiencies:    the wastage caused by the resignationof experienced officers, at a time when the rate of serious crimehas been escalating rabidly, has been a particular cause forconcern.    The problem has been most serious in London and themajor conurbations, where seriously uncer-strength police forceshave had to corc not only with rising crime but also with increasingthreats to public order.    The Committee conclude that manpowerconsiderations call for a substantial -nay increase.5.     They considered whether the manpower problems of the worst-hitforces might be overcome by setting differential rates of pay forcertain forces.    They conclude, however, that it is in the interestsof the Police service as a whole to have a national rate of pay,-1-COMHDEN73AL
apart from special allov;anccs for London and the Royal UlsterConstabulary (see paragraphs 9 snd 10 below).6.     The Committee consider that the best solution to the currentmanpower problems of the police lies not only in providingappropriate pay scales for all ranks but also, in providing specialadvantages for long-service constables, designed to overcome theexisting problems arising from the wastage of experienced officers.Their proposals, v/hich involve an element of restructuring,accordingly provide the largest increase (45*5%) for constableswith over 15 years1 service, and the lowest increase (29-7%) forconstables in their first year of service.7.    Throughout the federated ranks (from constable to chief inspector)the highest point of each existing salary scale is the minimum ofthat of the rank above, and the Committee recommend that this shouldcontinue.    The fact that all ranks up to chief inspector qualifyfor overtime has, however, created an anomaly in respect of thepay of superintendents, some of whom earn less than chief inspectors,in the same force.    The Committee recommend that the presentarrangements, under which all federated ranks are eligible forovertime but superintendents are not, should continue.    They proposeto overcome the anomaly, however, by setting the lowest point ofthe superintendents1 scale  1900 higher than the highest Pointof the chief inspector&apos;sscale.    The pay scales recommended by theCommittee for all ranks are shown in Annex B.Pay of Chief Officers8.     At present the pay of chief officers of police is linkedto that of chief officers in local government.    Reflecting this,their settlement date is 1 July, not 1 September as for the restof the police service.    Differentials have become eroded to thepoint where the minimum for assistant chief constables is lessthan the maximum for chief superintendents.   The Committee concludethat a unified salary structure with a common settlement date forthe whole of the police service, incorporating realisticdifferentials between all ranks, is needed.    They believe thatthe unique duties and responsibilities of chief officers justifiesbreaking the link with local government chief officers.    TheCommittee&apos;s recommendations, set out in Annex 3, are for newsingle point scales for implementation on a new settlement dateof 1 September.    They involve considerable increases - mostlyin the range of 42% - 45$ on the present maximum - partly due tothe fact they have to include the stage 3 entitlement due tochief officers on 1 July.    There are higher increases for thethree lowest paid chief constables due to the fact that theCommittee recommend the amalgamation of the lowest populationbands.in the present chief constable salary structure. .   The toppolice salary, that of the Commissioner of Police of che Metropolis,is determined, by linkage with permanent secretaries,, by thetop Salaries Review Body.    The Committee accept that this isappropriate but recommend in his case, however, that the anomalyby which he alone of chief officers is not entitled to providedaccommodation or rent allowance in lieu should be corrected.-2-r.
-3-They also recommend that, in the event of different chasing for&quot;permanent secretaries&apos; salaries, the Commissioners salary shouldbe paid in phase with other police chief officers.9.     The Committee propose that deputy chief constables shouldreceive a salary of 8C% of that of their chief constable, insteadof 75% (subject to a minimum level) as at present.    This involvesincreases of some 5^% to 57%*    Assistant chief constables shouldreceive a national salary of  12,500 in -&quot;lace of the present rangeof salaries based on 67% of the chief constables salary subjectto a fixed minimum salary at the lower end.    This yields increasesin the range of 30% to 48%.London Allowance10.     Although the Committee come down firmly in favour of anational rate of &quot;nay for the police service, they recognise thatsteps should be taken to overcome the serious manpower shortagein the Metropolitan Police, v/hich is far worse than that in otherforces.    The current deficiency on establishment is 18% (as comparedwith 9% for England and V/ales as a whole) and is increasing, theloss of strength in the first four months of 1973 amounting to213, as compared with 233 in the whole of 1977-    The Committeeconsidered that, in view of the steady increase in crime, thesituation in London could become very serious without a markedincrease in -police strength and the proper enforcement of lawand order could be Placed in jeopardy.    They therefore recommendthat, in addition to the existing London allowance of  319 ^er year,which represents no more than normal London weighting, all ranksof the Metropolitan Police should be given a non-pensionableLondon allowance of  650 per year.Royal Ulster Constabulary11.     The Committee also decided that all ranks of the RUC shouldreceive a special allowance.    Since 1 A^ril 1974 a special dutyallowance of 50&quot; .per day has been ^aid in recognition of the specialdifficulties which service in&apos;the RUC entails for officers and theirfamilies.    The allowance has always been linked to the allowance-oaid to members of the armed forces serving in Northern Ireland,which was increased in April 1978 to  1 per day on the recommendationof the Armed Forces Review Body.    The Committee considered whetherthis link should be maintained and concluded that it should not,on the grounds that the police officer, unlike the serviceman, isstill ex-nosed to danger when off duty and that his exposure to theextraordinary stresses and hazards of duty in Northern Ireland iscontinuous, instead of being confined to finite tours of duty.They t&amp;erefore recommend that all -ranks of the RUC should receivea non-pensionable allowance of  500 Per year for the duration ofthe emergency.Rent Allowance12.   Under Police Regulations, all police officers must be providedwith accommodation free from rent and rates, or with a rent allowancein lieu.    The purpose of the rent allowance, which is non-pensionable,
is to ensure that an officer who provides his own accommodation isfinancially broadly in the same position as one who is providedwith free accommodation.    Rent allowance is therefore regarded asa reimbursement allowance and not as part of the officer1s pay.The Committee recommend that the existing arrangements shouldcontinue and they have taken account of this emolument in arrivingat the recommended pay scales.Implementation13.     The new scales which the Committee propose are those v/hichthey judge appropriate as from 1 September 1978*    They thus include,for the ranks below chief officer, an imquantified element inrespect of the normal settlement due on that date or, in the caseof chief officers, the stage 3 entitlement v/hich would normallyhave been payable on 1 July.    The ^Committee make no recommendationsas to phasing, although they recognise that the Government, forreasons outside the scope of their report, may decide to phaseimplementation.Updating of Police Pay14.       The Committee recommend that in order to prevent police payfrom once again falling behind, it should be updated annually inaccordance with changes in the index of average earnings (new seriesin the previous 12 months.    This basis should be used for updating,with effect from 1 September 1979, the salary scales recommended intheir report for all ranks from constable to chief superintendent.In the case of chief officers, the salaries recommended should beupdated in accordance with a combination of (i) changes in theindex of average earnings (new series) and (ii) changes inappropriate outside comparisons.15-       The Committee recognise that in the years to come therewill be changes in the police service and in outside pay movementsgenerally, and they are conscious of the need to ensure that their -recommendations for updating police pay do not impose an inflexiblesystem on the new negotiating body.    They accordingly recommendthat either Side in the new negotiating body should be able topropose variations to the updating process recommended.Pensionability16.       In recognising that the Government may decide to phase therecommended pay award, the Committee draw attention to the unjusteffect which phasing can have upon those who retire during theperiod of phasing&apos;.    They accordingly recommend that the phasingprovisions should be disregarded as&quot; far as pension rights areconcerned and that provision should be made for the pension of thosewho retire with a pension entitlement during the period of phasingto be based on the average pensionable pay v/hich they would havereceived had the award been fully implemented from 1 September 1978.-4-cohfid:^5tial
.17.     Following is a summary. of the main recommendations of theCommittee:(a) The police should not have the right to strike, but thelack of this right should be taken into account indetermining police pay;(b) there should be a national rate of pay, with specialallowance for London and the RUC;(c) there should be new pay scales for the federated ranks,with an element of restructuring designed to providespecial advantages for long-service constables;(d) there should be new pay scales for superintendents, withthe lowest point of the scale set at a level which willprovide for adequate differential over the highest pointof the chief inspectors1 scale;(e) the nay of chief constables should no longer be linkedto that of chief officers in local government;(f) deputy chief officers should receive 80% of the salaryof the chief officer, but there should be a singlenational rate of pay for assistant chief constables;(g) the existing arrangements for rent allowance should beretained, but the Commissioner should be entitled tofree accommodation, or a rent allowance in lieu, on thesame basis as chief constables;(h) the recommended ^ay scales for the federated ranks andsuperintendents should not be implemented until1 September 1978.    The annual review date for chiefconstables should be 1 September (instead of 1 July)so that the -nay of all ranks of the police service isreviewed on the same date;(i) the pay of the federated ranks and superintendentsshould be updated on 1 September 1979 in accordancewith changes in the index of average earnings duringthe past 12 months.    The pay of chief constables shouldbe updated on the same date in accordance with acombination of (i) changes in the index of averageearnings and (ii) changes in appropriate outsidecomparisons;(j)     it should be o^en to either side of the new negotiatingbody to propose variations in the updating process, inthe light of changes in the police service or in paymovements in the economy as a whole;(k)     if the proposed increases are phased, provision shouldbe made for the tension of those who retire with a pensionentitlement curing the period of phasing to be basedon the average Pensionable ^ay which they would have. received had the award been fully implemented from1 September 1978.-5- .
k		coimfh	DENTIAL	Annox BBasic	pay of police	officers						Rank L w	-	Existing basic pay (2)	Baoic pay . rococisended by Corrraittea (3)	Percentage incroaao (4)feblco.				than ono yoar&apos;o	3orvico	2775	3600	29.7* - &apos;2 yoars	n	2910	3850	32.3* - 3 yoara .	M	3195	A 300	3^.6&apos; - 4 years	N	3342	4400	33.4j * - 5 yoara	II	3483	4550	30.6* - 6 yoaro	tl	3483	4700	34.9^ - 7 yoaro	n	3483	4G50	39.2^ - 0 yoaro	ti	3403	5000	45.50 0 -12 yoaro	if	3630	5150	41.8^ -15 yoars	ii	3774	5450	44.4^ 15 yoaro	it	3910	5700	45.5				&quot;Qn ono yoar&apos;3	oorvico	3910	5450	59.1^ - 2 yoara	H	4134	5700	59.9- -3 yoaro	H	4350	5900.	35.6^ ** 4 yoaro	n	4350	6100	40.2^ - 5 yoaro	N	4350	625C	43.6.6 yoars	n	4350	6250	43.60/Or 6 years	n	4565	6250	37.0k^oro				naa ono yonr&apos;o	onrvieo	4565 *	6250	37.0* - 2 yoara	it	4812	&apos; 6450	34.0- 3 years	R	5055	6700	32.5* - 4 years	It	5055	6900	36.5? years	tJ	5055	7100	40.45 yoaro	N		7-V109	34. i
 L-Xnsroctors.13 than ono year10 servico1 s- 2 years H2-3 yoaro a3-4 years *4-5 yoaro B0vor 5 yoars &quot;153 than-ono yoarfo sorvico1-2 years *2-3 years H0vor 3 years n&apos;^LSu ro r i n t c nd 0 n 13,^ than ono year&apos;s service1-2 years &quot;2-3 years &quot;over 3 yoars &quot;Exiotin^basic pay(2)52955538578757875787603370747326761778398049826084908703Basic payrecommendedby Conaitteo(3)710073007500770079007900980010,05010,50010,55010,80011,05011,30011,550Percentageincrease(4)3 hi31.929.633.136.530.938.533.635.234.634.233.633.132.9Note:   Th** Comir.ittoe rocommond that all ranks in tVw Metropolitan Policeanil City of London Police should recoive  319 for London weightingand, in addition, n special non-penHenable I-ondonallowance of  650, designed to help overcome tho present manpower shortage.They also recocniond that tho ranks frora station sergeant to chiefsuperintendent in thooo forces, who currently recoivo hichcr pay - rangingfros  114 to  450 - than thoir provincial counterparts in recognition ofwider duties, should continue to rocoive tho existing differentials.COi      ElM 11 Aim
Population of arcs        Existing salary        Salary Percentagerin thou sends (ii^ apples) Pecomr. ended Increase forr&quot;&quot; &apos; By Committee officer onmaxi pic(1) (2) (3) (4)150 8731-9505    ) 74.6250 9934-10,708 J 16,600 55.0400 9934-11,434 ) 45.2500 10,660-11,797 17,000 44.1600 10,915-12,106 17,400 43.7725 11,224-12,398 17,725 4-3.0850. 11,516-12,691 18,150 43-01,025 11,809-12,933 13,675 4-3-81,200 12,101-13,276&quot; 19,000 43.11,600 12,39^-13,568 19,375 43*3-2,000 12,686-13,861 19,750 42.52,400 12,979-14,135 20,125 42.42,800 1?,253-14-,410 20,500 42.3Notes:1.     The existing salaries of chief constables are calculated on exactpopulation figures.    There is a 3-?c,int incremental scale.2.     The existing salary of deputy chief constables is 75% of thatof the chief constable, subject to a minimum scale of  8476 -  3723.The Committee recommend that the salary of deputy chief constablesshould be 80% of that of the chief constable.    This represents anaverage increase of 54-.2% at the maximum, with deputy chief constableson the lowest ^oint of the minimum scale receiving an increase of56.7%.3*     The existing salary of assistant chief constables is 67% of thatof the chief constable, subject to a minimum scale of  3456 -  3^0;. 3?heCommittee recommend that the salary of all assistant chief constablesshould be  12,500.    This represents increases ranging from 47.8% atthe minimum to 29*5% at the maximum.4.     The London forces have different chief officer ranks.    TheCommittee recommend increases of 33.7$ (from  3740 -  9172 to  12,725)for Commanders and up to 45.7% (from 13,297 to  19,375) for theMetropolitan Deputy Commissioner.   The salary of the MetropolitanCommissioner, linked to that of permanent secretaries, is at present -subject to TSRB -  18,883.    London weighting ( 245) is paid to Londonchief, officers except the Metropolitan Commissioner.    The Committeerecommend that it should continue to be payable to these officers,together with the recommended London allowance of  650.l1 A 5

</content>
</cab>
