<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/245/0 images: 215-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1933.SECRET.Copy No.   49CP. 308 (33).CABINET.162The Disarmament Conference, 1932.REVISE OF REPORT BY THE MINISTERIAL COMMITTEE. As approved by the Cabinet on December 20, 1933.*DURING the past week the Ministerial Committee on Disarmament have had under consideration Herr Hitler&apos;s disarmament proposals, and more particu-larly his communication of the 11th December (Appendix at the end of this document), an analysis of which is also attached (Annex I). They have had the advantage of the presence of Sir Eric Phipps, His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Berlin, at two meetings.2.   The Committee&apos;s recommendations to the Cabinet are as follows :  (1) That a further communication should be sent to the German Government for the dual purposes of eliciting further information and of rebutting certain unjustified statements in Herr PIitler&apos;s written statement. A draft of this communication is attached to this Report and is submitted for the approval of the Cabinet (Annex II).(2) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should take advantage of his forthcoming visit to France and Italy to get in touch with the French and Italian Governments in order to exchange views with them on the subject of Herr Hitler&apos;s communication. Some of the points which it is suggested the Secretary of State might at his discretion discuss with these Governments are set forth in Annex III. These are submitted for the approval of the Cabinet, it being understood that the Secretary of State should have the usual latitude in the conduct of his conversations.3. In addition to the above, the Ministerial Committee think the moment is approaching when it will be necessary to issue some kind of manifesto to the world setting forth the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United (Kingdom in the present stage of the Disarmament question. The precise content of the manifesto, as well as the form in which it should be published, can best be decided when the results are known of the new communication to Berlin referred to in recommendation (1) above and of the Secretary of State&apos;s visit to France and Italy. In order, however, that the Cabinet may be informed of the general scope of the proposed document, a preliminary and necessarily incomplete draft, pre-pared by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in the form of a Circular Despatch to our Ambassadors at various Capitals, is attached in Annex IV. This draft has not as yet been examined in detail by the Ministerial Committee, or amended, except in the penultimate paragraph.(Initialled)J. R. M.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, December 19, 1933.* Cabinet 70 (33), Conclusion 2.[9434]b
ANNEX II. Proposed Procedure The Next Step.WE have already instructed Mr. Newton, in Berlin, to inform Baron von JNeurath that His Majesty&apos;s Government are giving careful consideration to the German proposals of the 11th December.The next step would appear to be to give Sir Eric Phipps instructions, to be acted on when he returns to Berlin, on the following lines. (When this has been done and the answers have been obtained, but not before, we should be in a position to settle finally and issue the proposed manifesto (see Annex IV).)* It is to be noted that nothing is said in the written communication about tanks or aeroplanes. In conversation Herr Hitler lias professed to be content with G-ton tanks for Germany, and asks for an air arm equal to 25 per cent, of the total of Prance, Poland and Czechoslovakia. As for naval armament, he says that Germany does not seek in any way to build against Britain, but wants a few battleships.The Hitler Proposal of December 11.HERE, HITLER&apos;S written communication to Sir Eric Phipps of the 11th December follows up the preliminary proposals regarding disarmament made to Sir Eric Phipps, the French Ambassador in Berlin and the Italian Government.   It main points are as follows : (1) Ten-year non-aggression pact with all States surrounding Germany; each of these pacts would provide for the rejection of force in the settlement of questions at issue between Germany and the other party to the pact.(2) Germany refuses to take part in any disarmament conference, pendingthe recognition of her actual equality of rights. (3) Germany accuses Britain of having led other Powers to substitute asecond draft of the Disarmament Convention for the first draft which germany had herself accepted. (4) The German Government no longer believes that the highly armed Statesreally intend to disarm. (5) Germany alone has actually executed the Disarmament clauses of theTreaty of Versailles. (6) In these circumstances the German proposals are as follows : &apos;(a) Complete equality of rights.(b) An agreement of the highly-armed States not to increase theirpresent armaments.(c) Germany will, in practice, make only a moderate use of herequality of rights.(d) A general pledge to conduct war humanely and abandon use ofcertain weapons against civilians.(e) Equal, periodic and automatic supervision for all. (/) Ten-year pacts of non-aggression (see above).(7) Germany asks for 300,000 men instead of the parity figure of 200,000 of the British Draft; her justification being that the highly armed States will, under the German proposal, be left with their present effectives.(8) Germany asks for defensive weapons* only, which are to include guns of at least 155 mm.; she rejects samples.(9) Absorption of the Reichswehr in the short-service army over a period of years.(10) Maintenance of the S.A. and S.S., the verification of the non-military character of which will be one of the functions of periodic and automatic supervision.(11) If other countries decide on full disarmament, Germany will do the same.
The Ambassador should be instructed to make the following observations and enquiries. In so doing the Ambassador would make it clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government must not be understood to be expressing either approval or disapproval of the Hitler proposals, but they feel that in order that there may be the best prospect of ultimate agreement, it is important that these matters should be noted and cleared up.(1) His Majesty&apos;s Government gather from the German text that (a) The  proposed  non-aggression  pacts  cover  all  questions,   political,territorial and economic, arising between Germany and the European nations, particularly all States surrounding Germany.(b) Such pacts would not be inconsistent with the obligations of Membersunder the Covenant of the League of Nations.(2) His Majesty&apos;s Government understand, moreover, that the Chancellor has reaffirmed the whole of Germany5s obligations, under the Treaties of Locarno.(3) His Majesty&apos;s Government refute categorically the Chancellors assertion that other Powers under the leadership of Britain abandoned the British Draft Convention for a second draft. The action of His Majesty&apos;s Government and the nature of the suggestions made in October have been fully explained in public on several occasions, more particularly in the Secretary of State&apos;s speech in the House of Commons on the 13th November.(4) As regards the three propositions (a), (b) and (c), His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment do not dispute (c), but cannot agree to the implications of (a) and (&amp;). They would further remind the German Government that all countries represented at the Disarmament Conference accepted as a basis the British Draft Convention with its large measure of disarmament, and all those countries except Germany are ready to resume discussions at Geneva in January.(5) His Majesty&apos;s Government take note of the German Governments proposal that all States should accept &quot; an equal general supervision which shall examine and guarantee the observance &quot; of the engagements entered into. This supervision the German Government describe as &apos;&apos; an international, general and identical system functioning periodically and automatically.&quot;(6) His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot accept the arguments on which the German Government base their claim for 300,000 men, involving in its turn a correspondingly large total of arms. Apart from technical questions, so large a figure will be universally regarded as a most formidable increase and produce disastrous effects on the mind of Europe. In the British Draft Convention, parity between Germany and the metropolitan forces of France was proposed at 200,000 men. Parity on this basis seems to His Majesty&apos;s Government to be the proper comparison. In any case, the total French strength quoted in the German memorandum appears to be greatly in excess of the strength of the French metropolitan army as given in the League of Nations Yea?- Book.(7) His Majesty&apos;s Government take note of the German Governments renunciation from the outset of any offensive weapons which in the view of the latter might appear to threaten their neighbours. The German Government demand only &quot; normal armaments &quot; for defence, but these are to include 155 millimetre guns. His Majesty&apos;s Government would wish to be informed what are the categories of weapons included in the definition &apos;&apos; normal armaments &apos;&apos; and what are the quantities. Would, for example, such armaments include tanks and military aircraft, and, if so, in what quantities and of what categories ?(8) His Majesty&apos;s Government understand that the Eeichswehr will be absorbed in the new army over a period of four or five years. They would be glad to know how the peace organisation of the German army under Herr Hitler&apos;s proposal would compare with the three cavalry divisions and seven infantry divisions of the existing Reichswehr.(9) His Majesty&apos;s Government note that the German Government are prepared to assure, by a system of international, periodic and automatic supervision, that the S.A. and S.S. have no connection whatever with military matters, and assume that a similar assurance will be provided in respect of the new Labour Corps, of which no mention is made.[9434]
ANNEX III.Communications to France and Italy.THE Secretary of State might take advantage of his visit abroad to inform the French and Italian Governments of our reply to Herr Hitler&apos;s communication of the 11th December as contained in the instructions to Sir Eric Phipps-Annex II above.This action will show them what His Majesty&apos;s Government are doing. He can explain to them that the execution of Sir Eric Phipps&apos;s instructions, and the receipt of Herr Hitler&apos;s next reply (if any) will probably conclude, as far as His Majesty&apos;s Government are concerned, the parallel and supplementary efforts; and that His Majesty&apos;s Government will then consider their position and will, in any event, return to Geneva in January and take part in the Conference.The Secretaiy of State should emphasise the useful results already attained by His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s enquiries of the German Government. He might more especially draw attention, for example, to the passage in the German Note which states that &quot; these (non-aggression pacts) would fundamentally prevent by treaty any appeal to force between the European nations, in order to impose upon the Governments the obligation either to resolve difficult or critical problems by means of peaceful diplomatic intercourse, or, in the case of such intercourse being obviously impossible or fruitless, to put off the negotiations until general European appeasement permits a more dispassionate examination and judgment.&quot; The procedure adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Government has been directed to tying Herr Hitler down wherever we can without committing ourselves or the French or any other Government. This procedure has not involved any injury to French (Italian) interests. His Majesty&apos;s Government are completing these enquiries, and will inform the French (Italian) Government of the result. In these circumstances, His Majesty&apos;s Government do not wish to press the French Government to take any further action for the present if such action is embarrassing or distasteful to them.Such a communication will perhaps enable the Secretary of State to dispose of the French complaint that, while we informed them of the communications which were passing between us and Berlin, they had no means of knowing our object except from certain public statements.If the French raise again our attitude to rearmament, the Secretary of State could perhaps reply that we are as much opposed as anyone to increase of armaments which, indeed, might result in involving us. We are therefore anxious to see no increase, if any increase can be.effectively prevented.The central point of British policy is that we believe that agreement is much to be preferred to no agreement and breakdown. We feel that so strongly that we should think even an agreement involving some rearmament better than no agreement at all. The extent and nature of the rearmament to be considered can, however, only be judged after the completion of the present enquiries.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs will consider whether an opportunity could not be taken to press the French to make public the disarmament they contemplated in October.ANNEX IV. Suggested Circular Despatch.THE best method for making such a document public can be decided later. A manifesto issued from London, or a written answer addressed to Herr Hitler, are possible alternatives.   The form at present adopted is a circular despatch.The first seven paragraphs are fairly complete, but the essence of the document would be what is indicated in paragraphs 8 and 9.(To our Ambassadors at various Capitals.) Sir,1. On the 22nd November the Bureau of the Disarmament Conference unanimously decided that the work of the Conference should be suspended for a
period, in order to permit of parallel and supplementary efforts being carried on between different States, mainly through the diplomatic channel. During the last weeks this method has been pursued, and bi-lateral communications have taken place between various capitals. As a result, the points of view of certain Governments have been further defined, and some general propositions which they had previously advanced have taken a more concrete shape. Yet it must be admitted that, on comparing the attitudes thus disclosed, no firm basis of agreement at present emerges; and, while these diplomatic exchanges have undoubtedly cleared the ground and revealed the immensity and difficulty of the problem in their true proportions, the method recently followed cannot in itself produce a unanimous result and is in danger of exhausting its usefulness. Moreover, a resumption of the discussions at Geneva without any new directive suggestions is only too likely to lead to further disappointment.2. In these circumstances His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom consider that the time has arrived when they should make public their own attitude in the present situation, the gravity of which must be apparent to every thoughtful mind, and should thus make a further positive contribution, so far as lies in their power, to promote a reconciliation of views in a matter upon which the future of the world may depend.3. Before dealing with any specific proposition as to the measure or the regulation of armaments, His Majesty&apos;s Government must reassert the main objective to which all proposals on this subject ar^e directed. That objective is, as Article 8 of the Covenant declares, the maintenance of peace. Even though increase of armed strength may be actuated by reasons of defence, it is an index of fear of attack from another quarter, and a measure of the alarm and disquiet that exists between peoples. Conversely, a general agreement securing the limitation of armaments at the lowest practicable level would be the most effective and significant proof of international appeasement and of the mutual confidence which springs from good and neighbourly relations. Consequently, His Majesty&apos;s Government regard agreement about armaments not so much as an end in itself, as a concomitant of world peace and as an outcome of political amelioration. For this reason, they have always acknowledged the relation between the conception of equality of rights on the one hand, and of security on the other. For this same reason, they welcome the indications that Herr Hitler&apos;s recent proposals, whatever may be said of their precise content, are concerned not only with technical questions of armament, but with political guarantees against aggression.4. It follows from the above considerations that agreement is most likely to be reached on a broad basis which combines regulation of armaments with assurances in the political field. Protracted debates on disarmament in its purely technical aspect can lead to no conclusion, unless wider considerations touching the equality and the security of nations are borne in mind and provided for. Hence the British Draft Convention, which was presented at Geneva last March, and which has been approved as a basis by a unanimous vote which included both France and Germany, began with a &quot;Part I&quot; on the subject of Security, proposing methods of consultation for the purpose of determining an appropriate action in the event of a threatened breach of the Briand-Kellogg Pact. His Majesty&apos;s Government must emphasise that there is no valid ground for asserting that they have ever departed from the principles and purposes of the Draft Convention, or have sought to substitute a second and contradictory draft for it. The Draft Convention, as subsequent discussion has shown, requires to be amplified and adjusted to actual conditions, and any suggestions which have since been put forward for consideration have been tentatively advanced for no other purpose. But the underlying conceptions of the Draft Convention remain the standpoint of His Majesty&apos;s Government and could only be abandoned if and when a more acceptable alternative were generally agreed.5. But while His Majesty&apos;s Government are not prepared to depart from the lines of the Draft Convention without being assured that there is an alternative which would more readily lead to universal agreement, they are perfectly prepared to give unprejudiced consideration to new suggestions and to do their utmost to promote their general acceptance. The importance of attaining international agreement by any possible means is so great that no suggestions,
from whatever quarter they come, should be rejected merely because of a preference for a better solution which is in fact unattainable. An illustration lies ready to hand. It is sometimes urged that the solution of the disarmament problem lies in the immediate abandonment by all the world of all the weapons which the Peace Treaties withheld from the defeated Powers. But is such a solution in practice attainable at the present time ? And if it is unattainable, is all further effort to be abandoned on the ground that, having regard to the principle of equality, agreement necessarily involves some degree of rearmament in some quarters. His Majesty&apos;s Government, and the whole British people, are deeply and sincerely devoted to the cause of international disarmament; the action of this country since the Armistice, and the present position of its armaments in comparison with those of other Powers, are sufficient proof of the fact. In saying this, His Majesty&apos;s Government are not blind to the special needs and difficulties of others, whose own action in the matter of armaments must necessarily take account of national security. If they are to agree to reduce their armaments, they must be satisfied that the new agreement will meet their need for security by other means.6. In point of fact, the scheme of the British Draft Convention itself involves some degree of rearmament for those States whose armaments are at present restricted by Treaty. Germany, for example, in view of the numerical increase proposed in her effectives, would need quantities of rifles and machine guns in excess of anything provided in the Treaty of Versailles. And this is not all. His Majesty&apos;s Government have more than once publicly stated that an international agreement based on the admitted principle of equality in a regime of security necessarily involves that, within the stages provided for by such an agreement, the situation must be ultimately reached in which arms of a kind permitted to one State cannot continue to be denied to another. His Majesty&apos;s Government see no escape from this conclusion, and they do not seek to escape from it, for they are convinced that the best prospect for the future peace of the world would be provided by an agreement which recognises and provides for this parity of treatment, while it abolishes or reduces to the lowest possible level all arms of a specially offensive character, and provides by the most appropriate means available for a greater sense of security, without which substantial disarmament is impossible.7. Putting aside, therefore, as not immediately attainable the ideal of universal disarmament to Germany&apos;s present permitted level, the choice appears to His Majesty&apos;s Government to lie between three conceivable courses  (1) To reach agreement on a level which will involve the abandonment of certain classes of weapons by the most heavily armed Powers, while it necessarily concedes to all Powers a right to possess and use weapons in the permitted list.(2) To reach agreement on the basis that the most heavily armed Powers, while unable to disarm, will undertake not to increase their present armaments, while the right to possess such kinds of armaments is. conceded to other Powers.(3) To reach no agreement at all.As between these three results His Majesty&apos;s Government, in common with the rest of the world, would regard the third as an outcome fraught with so much danger for future peace as to call for the most strenuous efforts to avoid it. The second course is the one indicated in Herr Hitler&apos;s proposals as the most that can be hoped for. But His Majesty&apos;s Government would most earnestly press upon other Governments that the first course, which they most strongly prefer and regard as more in accord with the main object to be attained, should not be abandoned, but should be actively pursued.Shortness of time has prevented me from elaborating the following-paragraphs ; nor, indeed, would it be profitable to attempt to set down their exact, or even approximate, wording, until such time as we receive from Berlin the reply to the instructions to Sir E. Phipps, for which concurrence is now sought in Annex II. These paragraphs may, moreover, be affected by the course of my con-versations in France and Italy.
The outlines of the concluding paragraphs would, however, be roughly as follows :-8. This paragraph would examine the Hitler proposal, including, of course, his next reply to Sir E. Phipps, and point out in detail how much increase it involves both in men and material. It would urge that the attainment of equality with security would be better reached by means other than those actually contained in Hitler&apos;s last proposals. It would challenge the proposition that the most highly armed States have no wish to disarm.9. This paragraph would urge the importance of reaching some form of agreement. It might be suggested that France, perhaps, is inclined to attach too much importance to the idea that any agreement can only be reached by means of disarmament; while Germany should be urged to modify her attitude as to the amount of the armaments she is to possess. In this way a pointer might be given to a via media, and, if conditions were found favourable, a meeting of the parties concerned could be arranged to discuss the situation on this new basis. Such a meeting would be convened without prejudice to the rights of any country.10. The despatch would conclude by urging that along these lines agreement ought to be possible, and would reaffirm our determination td do our utmost to bring it about.
APPENDIXNo. 1.Sir E. Phipps to Sir John Simon.-(Received December 13.)(No. 1251.)Sir, *       Berlin, December 12, 1933.WITH reference to my telegram No. 290 of to-day&apos;s date, I have the honour-to transmit to you, herewith, translation of the Chancellor&apos;s reply to the private and unofficial letter which I addressed to Baron von Neurath on the 8th instant (of which a copy was forwarded to you in my despatch No. 1238 of that date).2. Herr Hitler&apos;s reply was handed to me at 1 o&apos;clock to-day by Baron von Neurath. Noticing its very official character, I remarked to his Excellency that I should nevertheless consider this document as private and confidential, like my communication was. Baron von Neurath, however, replied that it need not be considered to be confidential vis-a-vis of the other interested Powers.3. Baron von Neurath was in a great hurry, as he had left Signor Suvich waiting in the next room, but he rapidly read over the document to me in case I had any preliminary questions to ask.4. I remarked that in paragraph (I) it is only stated that Germany would be willing to conclude pacts of non-aggression with all her neighbours, whereas the Chancellor had mentioned certain other States to me on the 8th instant (see my telegram No. 282 of that date). Baron von Neurath replied that Herr Hitler would be quite ready to conclude such pacts with any other Power that wished.5. In connexion with the period within which the Reichswehr would be transformed into a short-service army (IV), I asked what period was contem-plated. Baron von Neurath replied four to five years; but said that that was a technical point which could only be settled by experts.6. I am sending copies of this despatch and its enclosure to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadors at Paris and Rome by post, and of the enclosure only to the American Ambassador, whom I have already warned, in case he should decide to cable to Washington the text of Herr Hitler&apos;s communication.I have, &amp;c.ERIC PHIPPS.P.S. I have shown the French Ambassador the text of the Chancellors; communication.: E. P.Enclosure in No. 1. Herr Hitler to Sir E. Phipps.(Translation.)Your Excellency, Berlin, December 11, 1933.IN the name of the German Government I have the honour to reply as follows to the enquiries addressed to me through your Excellency on behalf of the British Government: I. The German Government is ready to enter into agreements which stipulate the rejection of force for the solution of all European questions, and which can thus be of service to the maintenance of world peace. In view, however, of past experiences, the German Government would propose to choose a form which makes it both possible and easier for the Governments, as well before their own consciences as also before their peoples, to accept such proposals.
at the earliest possible moment. This consideration leads the German Govern-ment to believe that the general agreements as to limitation of armaments should be crowned by a system of reciprocal and general non-aggression pacts. These would in principle prevent by treaty any appeal to force between the European nations, in order to impose upon the Governments the obligation either to resolve difficult or critical problems by means of peaceful diplomatic intercourse, or, in the case of such intercourse being obviously impossible or fruitless, to put off the negotiations until general European appeasement permits a more dispassionate examination and judgment. In this way would be met the apprehension of the British Government that such treaties might, in the case of individual States, possibly result in internal conflicts [sic] with the constitution of the League of Nations; and, on the other hand, every guarantee for the maintenance of peace would be provided!The German Government is ready to conclude such pacts with all States surrounding Germany.II. With a view to bringing about real disarmament, or alternatively a limitation and equalisation of armaments, the German Government is ready to enter into negotiations with all individual nations or their Governments in regard to the various subjects and figures to be discussed. The German Govern-ment does not, however, intend to take part in any conference before the basic question of the actual equality of rights of the German Reich has been decided, or alternatively before this equality of rights has been recognised by the nations participating in the conference. For on this condition alone can the German Government be answerable to the German people for its participation in a conference. The practical issue of such a conference for Germany, as a Power to which equality of rights has not been granted in advance, would inevitably be the procedure which has been familiar to us for the last fifteen years, and could only lead to identical results. This would be neither tolerable for the honour of a great people nor useful to the cause of peace.It is, of course, true that the German Government acceded to the first draft convention of the English Prime Minister MacDonald, which had laid down that disarmament was the basis of the discussion. But it was not the German Government which abandoned this draft; but the other Powers, under the leadership of England, agreed amongst themselves upon a second draft. This last has, however, never been recognised by Germany.If the German Government now allowed itself to put forward a suggestion of its own, they did so out of a sense of responsibility and for cogent reasons. On the ground of its previous experience the German Government no longer believes that the highly armed States are, in fact, seriously determined to disarm. Various statements made by leading statesmen have confirmed this opinion. Without going in detail into the various reasons, there are two essential facts which cannot be neglected : (1) A reduction of the armaments of the other European States is, in effect, only to be envisaged if it is undertaken by all nations throughout the whole world. Nobody to-day, however, believes any longer in the possibility of such a general international disarmament.(2) The events of the last months make it appear more than doubtful whether measures of disarmament, even though they were earnestly intended by the Governments of certain countries, could be successfully laid before the Parliaments of those countries for ratification.For this reason the German Government finds itself unable any longer to cherish an illusion which is calculated rather further to confuse than to improve the relations between the peoples. Having regard to practical reality, the German Government therefore feels bound to make the following declaration : (a) Germany is the only State which has actually carried out the disarma-ment obligations imposed in the Peace Treaty of Versailles.(6) The highly armed States do not intend to disarm or feel themselves unable to do so.(c) Apart from other considerations, Germany has a right by some means or other to reach her equality of rights in relation to her security. [9434] c
In order to prevent a complete breakdown of the conception of disarmament and the limitless armaments race of all against all which would inevitably follow it, the German Government feel it their duty to put forward a proposal: ,     (1) Germany receives complete equality of rights.(2) The highly armed States mutually pledge themselves to make no further increase in their present armaments.(3) Germany becomes a party to this convention with the undertaking that she will, in practice, of her own free will, make only such moderate use of the equality of rights granted to her as could not be regarded as constituting any danger of aggression against any other European Power.(4) All States undertake certain obligations for the humane conduct of war or for the avoidance of the use of certain weapons of war against civilian populations.(5) All States accept an equal general control, which shall examine and guarantee the observance of these engagements.(6) The European nations guarantee each other the absolute maintenance of : : peace, by means of the conclusion of pacts of non-aggression, whichafter the lapse of ten years shall be renewed.III. Under these conditions, however, the demanded increase of the figure of 200,000 men, which was accepted in the MacDonald plan, to 300,000 is not only not considerable, but on the contrary represents rather a worse situation for Germany. According to the first draft convention of the British Government, Prance should have received on the continent, exactly as Germany, au allotment of 200,000 men. Since Prance is evidently not prepared to carry through this measure of disarmament, the ratio between Germany&apos;s demands to-day and the effective strength of France and the other European armies would become even more unfavourable. A total French strength of 651,000 men, which would be increased to about 1-2 million men by the States connected by friendship to France, would be faced by 300,000 men in Germany.In addition, the 9-6 million trained reserves in these States, to put against which Germany possesses practically nothing, represent a further security which could hardly be exceeded.Accordingly the demands for equality in armaments for Germany are more than moderate, particularly since the German Government, for its part, is ready to renounce from the outset any offensive weapons which might conceivably appear threatening even to the gigantic French defensive system. Germany, who on her side is completely defenceless, has more reason to complain of the offensive weapons of the surrounding States than the latter have for representing the defensive weapons demanded by Germany on her side as a danger. The German Government must categorically reject any idea of so-called &quot; sample &quot; weapons (&quot; Musterwaffen &quot;). There are weapons which we renounce from the outset and which we shall, therefore, not build, and there are weapons which are essentially necessary for the defence of a country, which we therefore cannot renounce and which we must accordingly insist upon as normal armament. The lowest limit for the calibre of the artillery could, therefore, for example, on no account be less than 15 cm.IV. The German Reichswehr will, of course, be absorbed in the new army. But its absorption or remodelling can naturally not be accomplished in one year but will require a series of years.V. The S.A. and S.S. are not military organisations. They are an inseparable component part of the political system of the National Socialist revolution and so of the National Socialist State. They comprise some 2  million men ranging from the eighteenth year to extreme age. Their only task is, by means of this organisation of the political masses of our people, to prevent for ever the return of the Communist peril. Whether this system can or will ever be abandoned depends upon whether this Bolshevik-Communist peril remains or is removed. With military matters these National Socialist organisations, which stand in opposition to the former Marxist Reichbanner and the Communist Red-Front League, have absolutely no connexion whatever. The attempt to bring the S.A. and S.S. into a military connexion with the Reichsheer, and to refer to them
as military reserve formations, originates with those political circles which see m the removal of this protective organisation of the National Socialist State the&apos; possibility of a new disintegration of the German people and thus a new advance towards the Communist goal. Just as the German Government would never take the liberty of proposing to the English Government the dissolution of a specified English party or of a particular form of organisation of such a party, the German Government must reject any demand for the putting into effect of such a wish in Germany. The German Government, when taking into account the military strength of other States, does not consider, in making its demands, any other formations than those of the actual army organisation. The German Government will also, in future, attach no political significance, which might affect its attitude, to such political, sportive or post-military societies as may be considered necessary in other States.VI. The Government of the German Reich is, as has been emphasised, ready, in principle, to agree to an international, general and identical system of control, functioning periodically and automatically. In order to prove the character of the S.A. and S.S. to be, as was emphasised above, that of political organisations for a general, spiritual and physical inoculation against the dangers of a Communist upheaval, the German Government does not decline to provide proof, in the course of this control, that this definition is being accurately adhered to. In conclusion, I will add once again, in the name of the German Government, the assurance that in the event of the other nations contrary to the expectation of the German Government deciding upon complete disarmament, the German Government declares in advance its readiness to accede to such a convention, and similarly to disarm, if necessary, to the last cannon and to the last machine gun.I avail, &amp;c.ADOLF HITLER.

</content>
</cab>
