<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/20/12 images: 100-103</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT?Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1941.SECRET. / Copy NoW.P. (41) 289.November 26, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.MINISTRY OF SUPPLY LABOUR REQUIREMENTS.Further Memorandum by Minister of Supply.I WISH to draw the attention of the Cabinet to certain points raised inthe Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service on Ministryof Supply labour requirements (W.P. (41) 285).1. It is stated that the short-term demand for women at Filling Factoriesamounts to 18,500. This ignores the fact that for many weeks now the Ministryof Supply has not received tlhe women it demanded, so that present needs mustconsist of normal demands for intake plus the accumulated deficit. It is for thisreason that the correct figure is 35,000.2. The total short-term demands for women for Ministry of Supply work should therefore be 55,510 (W.P. (41) 278), and not 39.000.3. It is stated that it is misleading to take wastage at Swynnerton as a percentage of intake. I must insist that it is not irrelevant to my chief endeavourat this factory, which is to build up its strength to enable it to fulfil its pro-gramme. The wastage in the past 3 weeks has been over two-thirds of the intake,so that the actual increase of strength in the period has been negligible.4. To say that the intake of women at Chorley, Kirkby, Risley andSwynnerton has been falling in recent weeks does not do justice to the facts.The weekly demand at these 4 factories is for 2,700 women. In each of the past2 weeks the combined intake has been under 700 women. This means, whenwastage is taken into account, that increase of strength is almost nil.5. The Minister of Labour states that 10,000 women a week are being placedin industry and the Women&apos;s Services as a result of speed-up of registrationsand interviews.6. I wish to draw attention to the weekly labour demands and placings of atypical sample of 300 firms working for the Ministry of Supply. The figures are taken from returns made to the Ministry of Labour. They show for the first week of September demands for 5,940 women, placings being 3,058; for the first week of October demands were 7,301, placings 3,013; for the first week ofNovember demands were 9,152, placings 3,027. The demand for women has there fore steadily increased in this period while placings have remained constant.The result is that while in September the Ministry of Labour was filling one-half,it is now meeting only one-third of these requirements.[23194]
7. It will be noted that the weekly demand for the first week of Novemberfor this group of firms is nearly equal to all the women now placed as a result ofregistrations and interviews. The demand figure given takes no account of thedemand of the Ordnance Factories for women, which amounts to 5,200 a week./! 8. It is clear that as the production programme reaches its full realisation,failure to supply the labour needed constitutes the main factor preventing itspunctual fulfilment.B.November 26, 1941.



</content>
</cab>
