<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/12/26 images: 426-435</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this dooument.MOST SECRET.COPY NO.OPERATIONS in norway.(previous reference:M. (40) 93rdinclusions,finute 47).W.M.(40)  95th CONCLUSIONS.  MINUTE 3.Confidential Annex.(17th April,  1940)THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said thata telegram had been received from Lord Cork, which showed that he and General Mackesy proposed to holdcertain positions on the approaches to Narvik, hutdid not intend to launch an attack until the snow hadmelted, which might not he until the end of the month.The matter had been discussed by the Military Co-ordination Committee earlier that morning.    They had agreed that an immediate assault on NaspfilS was most desirable.    The point had been made, moreover,  that the casulties in General Mackesy&apos;s force caused byexposure in the next few weeks might well be as severeas those which would be suffered in an immediate assault.A telegram had therefore been sent to Lord Cork andGeneral Mackesy which, while in no way over-ruling their judgment, put before them arguments in favour of anearly assault.    The telegram concluded &quot;Send us yourappreciation, and act at once if you consider right&quot;.The main developments in the situation inthe past 24 hours had been as follows:-(i)    A Norwegian battalion had been embarkedin British cruisers at Kirkenes   in theextreme North of Norway and was beingtaken to Narvik.    Nine Junker aircraft had been detected on a frozen lake north of Narvik and had been attacked.    One hadbeen captured and had been flown back toScapa.

NAMSOS.(il)   The transports containing the &quot;brigadefor Namsos (Brigadier Phillips&apos;s brigade)had been sent to Lillesjona which was thought to be less vulnerable to air attack.     These two transports had,however, been bombed throughout theprevious day.     Fortunately, no hits or damage had been sustained.     two battalions of this brigade had beentransferred to destroyers and had beenput ashore at Namsos.     The remainingbattalion had been embarked in S.S.CHOBRYand would land at Namsos during the coming  I-  night (7th/l8th)o     The other transport(a large liner) was on its way back toScapa.(iii)   The first demi-brigade of Chasseurs Alpinswere being sent to Nams s.     It was intended to disembark two ships there onthe 19th and two on the 20th Apr^l.(iv)   Captain Peter Fleming had been in touchwith the Norwegians at Steinkjer and had reported that they were in verv low spirits,!and that leadership was sadly lacking.(v)    General Carton de Wiart?  in command of theNamsos force; spoke of being able to beginhis thrust towards Trcadhjem on the 21stApril *    It Was to be hoped that a substantial [German force would be drawn off fromTrondhjem to meet it.ANLALSNES.(vi)   German seaplanes had been reported atAndalsnes on the previous day.H.M.S. CALCUTTA - an anti-aircraftcruiser - had been sent in to clear upthe situation, but had found a U-boat inthe harbour.     Being without asdics, theCALCUTTA had withdrawn.     Two destroyers were entering Andalsnes that day to clear up matters.     600 Marines - embarked in four sloops - (Force&apos;Primrose&quot;) would arrive at Andalsnes that night.     Theywould be followed by 1,000 of BrigadierMorgan&apos;s Brigade on the night 18th/l9thApril.(vii)   Five German destroyers had been reportedproceeding north up the coast through theLeads.     A force of cruisers and destroyers had been collected with a viewto intercepting them if they were proceeding to the Andalsnes area.(viii)   Information had been obtained as to a concentration of U-boats off the norwegian coast. This concentration was in the path of the four sloops and of theS.S. CHOBRY. The sloops - which werefitted with asdics - should be able totake care of themselves and the CHOBRYwas being escorted by two A.A. cruisers.A flotilla of destroyers had been ordered from the Western Approaches tocarry out an anti-submarine sweep against- 2 -

tine U-boat concentration., They would 6UOreach the area in about 48 hours&apos; time.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY then gave an outline of the plan for the landing at Trondhjem.The forces which were available for the operationwere as follows:One regular brigade from France (2,500 strong)1,000 Canadians.Behind this would be a reserve of about 1,000 menof Brigadier Lammie&apos;s Territorial Brigade who wouldbe used as an immediate reserve to exploit any successachieved in the landings made by the first flight.The Military Co-ordination Committee had been advised that the forces available were adequate and they had thought that the risks, although very considerable, werejustifiable.    The operation would be supported by thefull strength of the Fleet.    Two carriers would beavailable with a total of about 100 aircraft, including45 fighters.    The provisional date for the landingwas 22nd April.The second demi-brigade of Chasseurs Alpinswould not reach Trondhjem until the 25th April when itwas hoped that they v/ould be able to disembark at thequays in Trondhjem.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO enquire whether the Chiefs of Staff   were in agreement withthg plans decided upon by the Military Co-co-ordination committee as outlined by the First Lord.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF said that theChiefs of Staff were in agreement.  The operation was of course attended by considerable risks:    but the risks were not out of proportion to value of successif achieved.    The Military value of a success shouldnot perhaps be nated too highly, but it was clear that

the political and moral advantages which would result from the capture of Trondhjem, wouchd he very great.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed with this view.Roference was made to air cooperation in the mainattack.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said that thecomplete cooperation of the Royal Air Force in the attack was an essential part of the plan.THE PRIME MINISTER asked whether the suggestion which he had made the previous day of a landing to destroy Stavanger Aerodrome had been examined.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that thissuggestion was being followed up.The War Cabinet -Took note of the First Lord&apos;sstatement, and gave general approval to the plan of operations outlined.The Prime Minister refered to theimperative need for secrecy inregard to these operations,    Itwas agreed that for the time being no information in regard to them should be communicated to theDominions.r Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1.




</content>
</cab>
