<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/43/23 images: 188-193</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.. August 1944.SECRET. GoPy No*W.M. (44)107th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 107 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime MinistersMap Room, S.W. 1, on Wednesday, 16th August, 1944, at 12-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The following vThe Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The    Right   Hon.    the    Duke   of devonshire, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies &apos;(Item 2). ISir Gilbert Laithwaite,re also present:The Right Hon. the Earl of Selborne,Minister of Economic Warfare(Item 2).The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (Item 2).Sir F. A. Newsam, Deputy Under-Secretary of State, Home Office(Item 2).Under-Secretary (Civil).Contents.minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      Poland.................................     2782      Jewish Refugees        ............    &apos;........     * ....     278Hungarian offer to allow Jews to leave Hungary.[28099-1]
Poland. 1,   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed the(Previous War  Cabinet of &apos; the latest  developments  in  connection withEeference: assistance for the Polish underground forces in Warsaw.   TheW.M. (4-4) 106th discussion  and  the  conclusions  reached  are  recorded  in  theConclusions,Minute.3.)Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.jewish refugees.HungarianOffer to AllowJews to LeaveHungary.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 104thConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, sincethe War Cabinet had last considered Admiral Horthy&apos;s offer to theInternational Red Cross to allow certain categories of Jews to leaveHungary, there had been further discussions between the Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theAmerican Ambassador as to the terms of the declaration to be madejointly by His Majesty&apos;s Government and the United States Govern-ment. In the result, agreement had been reached, subject to approval by the War Cabinet and by the State Department, on anamended draft, a copy of which is annexed to these minutes.The amended draft differed from the original in two important respects : (a) Instead of accepting responsibility for &apos;&apos; all Jews &apos;&apos; per-mitted to leave Hungary, the commitment undertaken by His Majesty&apos;s Government and the United StatesGovernment would now refer only to the Horthy offer.That offer covered two specific categories of Jews, andthe maximum number involved was likely to be between60,000 and 70,000. Reports which had just been received as to difficulties of transportation suggested that, in fact,the number for which provision would have to-be mademight be much smaller.(b) The draft declaration approved by the War Cabinet on the9th August was to the effect that His Majesty&apos;s Govern-menfs co-operation with the United States Governmentin this matter would be &quot;to the extent of their resources.&quot; The United States Government had seenobjection to this qualification, but we had made it clearthat there were practical limits to the numbers withwhich we could deal. As the result of the parliamentary under-Secretary of State&apos;s negotiations, they had now given an assurance, subject to confirmation by the state department, that, after jointly using our capacity, theUnited States Government would take any balance forwhich we could not provide. The effect was that we andthe United States jointly accepted the Hungarian pro-posal, and would appear before the world as sharingalike. But actual demands upon us would not exceed the accommodation we could provide.He regarded the outcome of Mr. HaLTs discussions with theAmerican Ambassador as eminently satisfactory, and invited theWar Cabinet to approve the amended draft of the declarationapproved by them on the 9th August.The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the colonies said that the Secretary of State for the Colonies desired to make itclear that if Palestine became involved it would not be possible toprovide for more than 11,000 additional Jews in Palestine.The Chancellor of the Exchequer referred to the risk that at alater stage there might be criticism in Parliament or elsewhere ofthe fact that, while the United States and His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment were accepting a joint commitment, the heavier burden inrespect of that commitment might, in practice, fall on the UnitedStates. He recognised, however, that any such criticism would haveto be faced.
After further discussion, the War Cabinet *(1) Took note with satisfaction of the outcome of the negotia-tions conducted by the Parliamentary Under-Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs with the american ambassador.(2) Approved the substitution of the amended draft proposedby the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs for thedraft declaration approved by the War Cabinet on the9th August, subject to confirmation either by telegramor in writing from the State Department of their acceptance of it.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,16th August, 1944.ANNEX.Because of the desperate plight of the Jews in Hungary and the over-whelming humanitarian considerations involved, the two Governments areinforming the Government of Hungary through Intercross that, despite the heavydifficulties and responsibilities involved, they have accepted the offer of the hungarian Government for the release of Jews and will make arrangements forthe care of such Jews leaving Hungary who reach neutral or United Nationsterritory, and also that they will find temporary havens of refuge where such people may live in safety. Notification of these assurances is being given to theGovernments of neutral countries who are being requested to permit the entry of jews who reach their frontiers from Hungary.




</content>
</cab>
