<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 96-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The Right Hon. George Brown, M.P.,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Herbert Bowden,M.P., Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,Q.C., M.P., Secretary of State for theHome department the Right Hon. William Ross, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,M.P., Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,M.P., Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Frank Cousins,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, M.P.,Minister of power the Right Hon. Patrick gordon walker, Secretary of State forForeign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp.,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths,M.P., Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,M.P., Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, M.P.,Minister of Overseas development also present:The Right Hon. Edward Short, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr.;D. S. Laskey5376-3THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1964C.C. (64) Copy No.     366th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 5th November, 1964, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, M.P., Prime Minister
contents minute no.                                  Subject page 1     Parliamentary Business    ...............       32     Oversea Affairs     ..................      3United States of AmericaFranceCambodiaThe Sudan3     Commonwealth Immigration       ............       3
BusinessParliament in the following weekOversea 2-J The Foreign Secretary said that, in the light of his decisiveAffairs victory in the United States Presidential Election, President JohnsonUnited States might be disposed to adopt a firmer and more robust policy towardsof America the Governments of countries such as France, Indonesia and theUnited Arab Republic. This would be a welcome development. Itwas also satisfactory that President Johnson had made it clear that,in the process of renewing contacts with other Governments afterthe election, he would wish to consult the United Kingdom first.France The Foreign Secretary said that there were increasing indications that General de Gaulle might seek either to withdraw France fromthe European Economic Community (E.E.C.) and perhaps the north atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) or to frustrate any furtherconstructive activity by these bodies. Our most effective counter-action would lie in seeking to strengthen the European Free trade association (EFTA), particularly since morale in the Association was already low.Cambodia The Foreign Secretary said that both the Government of Indiaand the Soviet Government were pressing for the Geneva Conferenceon Cambodia to be reconvened. In answer to representations by theSoviet Ambassador in this sense he had pointed out that a priorcondition of such a meeting should be an effective demarcation of thefrontier between Cambodia and Vietnam. He had also indicated that he hoped the Soviet Ambassadors approach implied that theSoviet Government no longer intended to abandon their role ofco-Chairman of the Conference.Sudan The Foreign Secretary said that the recent revolution in theSudan seemed to be due partly to the endemic tension between theArab and Negro elements in the Sudanese population and partly togrowing dissatisfaction with military rule. It was disturbing that the civilian Government which had now been formed included fourCommunists, even though they did not occupy posts of critical importance. In these circumstances we must be alert for any threat to the important strategic facilities which we enjoyed in the Sudan;and Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Khartoum had already been instructed accordingly.The Cabinet Took note of these statements by the Foreign Secretary.Commonwealth      3.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Homeimmigration    Secretary   and   the   Commonwealth   Secretary   (C. (64)11)   on commonwealth immigration.The Home Secretary said that the Government were committed to reviewing, in consultation with other commonwealth governments, the method of controlling Commonwealth immigrationto this country but to maintaining the existing control in the interim.Since 1955, Commonwealth immigrants from countries other thanthe old Dominions now numbered some 600,000, to which must beadded a substantial natural increase. This had created potentiallyserious social problems and had intensified the strain on housing and other services. It was therefore in the interests of all parties thata strict control should be kept in force while these immigrants wereabsorbed fully into the community; and this appeared to be accepted in principle by the other Governments concerned. An indication ofParliamentary        1.  The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in
the potential inflow if the control was relaxed was provided by theexistence of some 330,000 applicants on the waiting list fornon-priority labour vouchers.Part I of the Commonwealth Immigrants Act, 1962, under whichthe present control was exercised, would lapse at the end of the yearand must therefore be continued in being by the annual expiring laws Continuance Bill. But it would be desirable that Government&apos; spokesmen in the debate should be able to indicate that theGovernment had already taken the first steps to give other commonwealth Governments the opportunity to discuss immigration control with us. The draft of a message to the other governments for this purpose was appended to C. (64)11. This message should confine itself to an offer of discussion and should not invite the otherGovernments to put forward proposals of their own, since we shouldnot expose ourselves to the risk of receiving suggestions which we might find embarrassing or impracticable. Meanwhile, however, itwould be important to review possible means by which the existing arrangements for control might be made more humane, particularlyin relation to the admission of dependants of immigrants already inthe country.Discussion showed general agreement with these proposals. Inaddition the following main points were made:(a) The review of immigration control should be reinforced bypositive steps to secure the full integration of immigrants into thecommunity in accordance with the undertaking given in The Queen&apos;sSpeech.(b) It would assist the Governments policy of promotingagreements with other countries for the mutual abolition of visasif the control could be confined to independent commonwealth countries, immigration from the remaining dependent territoriesbeing unrestricted. It was unlikely that this would result in any considerable increase in the number of immigrants, since the populations of the territories concerned were not large and voluntaryschemes of control were already in force in some cases.(c) Consideration should be given to the proposals recently putforward by the Prime Minister of Trinidad and Tobago for theprovision of training facilities for potential immigrants in their homecountries in order to fit them for employment in the UnitedKingdom.(d) The reference in the draft message to the problems of accommodating immigrants &quot; in large cities where work is available &quot;should preferably be omitted, since it was precisely theirconcentration in such cities which exacerbated social and housingproblems.The Cabinet (1) Approved, subject to the amendment suggested at (d) above,the draft communication to other commonwealth governments appended to C. (64) 11 and invited theCommonwealth Secretary to arrange for its despatchbefore the forthcoming Debate on the Expiring laws continuance Bill.(2) Invited the Lord President of the Council to arrange for theCommonwealth Immigration Committee to give furtherconsideration, in the light of their discussion, to themanner in which the Governments policy on commonwealth immigration would most appropriately be presented during the Debate.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,5th November, 1964.



</content>
</cab>
