<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 168-179</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1964C.C. (64)13th conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 3rd December, 1964, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, M.P.,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Herbert Bowden,M.P., Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Denis Healey, M.P.,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations (Item 4)The Right Hon. James Griffiths,M.P., Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,M.P., Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Fred Peart, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Patrick gordon walker, Secretary of State forForeign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,Q.C., M.P., Secretary of State for theHome department the Right Hon. William Ross, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,M.P., Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Frank Cousins,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, M.P.,Minister of power the following were also present:The Right Hon. Charles Pannell,M.P., Minister of Public Building and works (Item 4)Mr. Cledwyn Hughes, M.P., Ministerof State, Commonwealth relations office (Items 1-3)The Right Hon. Gordon Stott, Q.C.,, Lord Advocate (Item 3)/Mr.   John   Diamond,   M.P.,   chief secretary, Treasury (Item 3)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones,Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Item 3)The Right Hon. Edward Short, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. A. A. Jarratt5586-1
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Parliament     ...     ............     ...     ...       32     Oversea Affairs     ..................      3The CongoEuropeThe Sudanv 3     Burma: War Damage Claims      ............      44     700th Anniversary of Parliament.........      ...      5
CC. 13 (64)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.2. The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that thesituation in the Congo showed slight signs of improvement. Althoughthe forces of the Congolese Government were still unable to establish a firm hold on the territory through which they were advancing, theyhad rescued a further 140 hostages held by the rebels and might wellsave others. The Belgian Prime Minister, M. Spaak, with whom hehad recently discussed the problem of the Congo, had agreed withour view that some kind of political initiative should be organised in order to stabilise the situation and that this might well take theform of an attempt to arrange for representatives of the united nations and the Organisation for African Unity to be despatched to the Congo in order to attempt to organise local armistices, whichmight facilitate the adoption of more general conciliation procedures.We should also recognise that, while the Prime Minister of the congo, M. Tshombe, was disliked and distrusted by other african governments, no other politician in the Congo at the present timecommanded a similar degree of popular ^support; and we should therefore endeavour to persuade him not to press his attempt to end the civil war by force but to concentrate on establishing asystem of administration by consent over the greater part of thecountry. At the same time we should seek to avoid becoming involved too deeply in the internal affairs of the Congo in view ofthe very heavy demands for aid which would probably arise duringthe subsequent period of reconstruction.The Foreign Secretary said that he had ascertained fromM. Spaak that the Belgian Government would be broadly in sympathy with the proposals for the reorganisation of the atlantic alliance which the Prime Minister intended to discuss with thePresident of the United States during his forthcoming visit to washington. At the same time M. Spaak had left us in no doubt about the extent to which, in his opinion, the other european members of the Alliance were becoming subservient to the personaldominance of General de Gaulle, whose attitude was increasinglydetermined by antipathy to the United States.The Foreign Secretary said that the new Government of theSudan, by suspending our right to overfly Sudanese territory, had placed us in a position of considerable difficulty in relation to the reinforcement of- our positions in the Middle East and the Far East.As a means of bringing pressure to bear upon them to negotiate amore reasonable settlement we should slow down the provision of aid to the Sudan and should also try to enlist the support of otherGovernments, particularly the Government of India, whose interests would be liable to be especially jeopardised if we were permanentlydeprived of the use of the direct reinforcement route to the Far east which our right to overfly the Sudan had hitherto provided.a 2
Burma: War 3.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ChancellorClahnsT G^ ^ Excnecluer (C- (64) 23) on claims against the Crown arisingfrom damage caused to properties and installations during the warin Burma.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that there were severaloutstanding claims against the Crown, particularly by subsidiaries ofthe Burmah Oil Company, for compensation for properties and installations destroyed by the Crown in order to deny their use to theenemy during the Japanese advance in Burma in 1942. Cases hadbeen brought by the subsidiaries of the Burmah Oil Company in theScottish courts with a view to establishing, in the first instance,whether there was a legal basis for claims for damages. The firstjudgment had favoured the claimants; the Appeal Court had reversedthe decision; but recently the House of Lords had reinstated the firstjudgment on the grounds that damage suffered as a result of actscommitted under the Prerogative might in certain circumstances bethe subject of claims for compensation in the courts. As a result theway was now clear, in accordance with Scottish lav/, for thesubsidiaries of the Burmah Oil Company to pursue the substance oftheir claims by seeking to establish the facts which, in their view,entitled them to compensation. Although the decision of the Houseof Lords was theoretically limited to Scottish law, there might be far reaching^ implications in English law as well, since the House ofLords had said (obiter) that English law should be interpreted in thesame sense. Thus, whereas it had been believed hitherto that onlyunlawful acts committed under the Prerogative could be the subjectof claims for damages, it now appeared that some acts which werelawful at common law might give the persons affected a right to compensation which was in principle indistinguishable from the rightto damages in respect of unlawful acts.The claims of the subsidiaries of the Burmah Oil Companyamounted to  31 million, together with interest; but, if allowance was made for further actions which were at present stayed, the totalof all the claims involved was no less than  100 million. successive governments had made it abundantly clear to the claimants that theywere not in any circumstances prepared to entertain their claims. In1948 the then Government had made an ex gratia payment of 10 million to be distributed amongst those who had suffered loss in Burma, of which the subsidiaries of the Burmah Oil Company hadreceived approximately  4^ million. It had been stated at the time that no further payments would be made. Moreover, in 1962, afterproceedings had been started by the subsidiaries of the Burmah oil company, a warning had been addressed to all the companies concerned that, if they obtained favourable judgments in the courts,the Government would introduce legislation to indemnify the Crownretrospectively.In the light of the judgment by the House of Lords there were now three possible courses of action: first, to give a renewed warning to the claimants in the hope of deterring them from furtherproceedings; second, to allow litigation to proceed in the hope thatthe ultimate award of damages would be so small that no payment
700th 4.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the LordAnniversary President of the Council (C. (64) 24) about the 700th Anniversary ofParliament      Parliament.The Lord President said that he had discussed with the ministers immediately concerned the arrangements which might be made tocelebrate the 700th anniversary of the Parliament summoned bySimon de Montfort on 20th January, 1265. It was suggested that theoccasion might be marked by some simple parliamentary ceremony,either on the day itself if Parliament were sitting or, if not, as soonC.C. 13 (64)beyond the amount already paid ex gratia would be necessary; third,to introduce retroactive legislation in order to defeat the claims ofthe companies concerned. The claimants had ignored one clearwarning; and there seemed little chance that, having subsequentlysecured an initial success in litigation, they would be deterred by another warning. Nor was there any guarantee that the outcome oflitigation would be favourable to the Government, having regard tothe judgment of the House of Lords. The Legislation Committee had therefore recommended that the Government should make no further payments in respect of the claims involved and that retroactivelegislation to annul them should be introduced.In discussion there was general agreement with thisrecommendation. The latest information suggested that the claimantswould be in a position to institute proceedings on the substance oftheir claims between May and July of 1965. The legislation whichwould retroactively debar the claims would therefore need to beintroduced in the current Session; and, since the claimants would be obliged to expend considerable money and effort in preparing their case, there were strong arguments in favour of introducing thenecessary Bill at the earliest possible date if the Government werenot to be criticised not merely for promoting retroactive legislationbut also for delaying its introduction and so putting the companies to fruitless trouble and expense. Moreover, there would be political advantage in legislating as rapidly as possible in pursuance of the warning given by the previous Administration. Any similar claims by interests other than the subsidiaries of the Burmah Oil company would probably, by now, be time-barred under both English and scottish law. But in any event they could not be dealt with in theproposed legislation except at the cost of considerable delay in its introduction; and it was to be hoped that the legislation in respectof the subsidiaries of the Burmah Oil Company would suffice to deterany other companies who might believe that they had correspondingclaims from seeking to pursue them further. In view of the knownattitude of previous Governments on the question it was unlikely thatthe legislation would give rise to difficulties with foreign Governments.The Cabinet Approved the proposals in C. (64) 23.
as possible thereafter. The day might also be celebrated in schools;and a special commemorative postage stamp might subsequently beissued. More extensive celebrations might be held later in the yearto coincide with those already planned for June 1965 to mark the750th Anniversary of Magna Carta. These might appropriately follow the pattern of the arrangements made during the 46th Inter-Parliamentary Conference in 1957; and, if so, they would probablyentail expenditure of the order of  10,000- 15,000. Since the occasionwouid be mainly parliamentary in character, the general supervision of the arrangements should be undertaken by a parliamentary committee under the chairmanship of the Speaker. The Minister ofPublic Building and Works should be responsible for the detailed planning, in consultation with his colleagues and with outsideorganisation.The Commonwealth Secretary said that he hoped shortly to circulate to the Cabinet proposals for the creation of some form of commonwealth consultative assembly, analogous to a CommonwealthParliament; and, if. this project matured, the initial meeting of thenew body might be linked in some way with the proposedcelebrations.In discussion there was general agreement with the proposals inC. (64) 24. Although it might be maintained that the anniversary ofthe Simon de Montfort Parliament was of interest primarily to thiscountry, it would nevertheless be appropriate that other members ofthe Commonwealth, whose Parliaments derived from our own, shouldbe associated with the ceremonies in January. The Speakers of commonwealth Parliaments might therefore be invited to be present;and the occasion might provide a convenient opportunity to arrangefor them subsequently to meet under the chairmanship of the speaker of the House of Commons in order to discuss matters of common interest. The High Commissioners of other Commonwealth countries might also be invited to attend the ceremony in January. the celebration of the anniversary of Magna Carta in June would command wider international interest; and arrangements should therefore be made to associate the other members of theCommonwealth, and possibly the United States, with the festivities.If a Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers were held in 1965,there might be advantage in arranging it at about the same time. Itwouid also be for consideration what part should be played by theCommonwealth Parliamentary Association in relation to theceremonies both in January and in June.In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) It would be appropriate that the Hansard Society should be associated with the celebrations; and consideration should be givento providing them with financial assistance from the Exchequer forthe purpose.(b) A Committee under the chairmanship of the Master of the rolls had already made certain arrangements to commemorate the anniversary of Magna Carta. The Governments own proposals would need to be co-ordinated with these arrangements.
The Cabinet (1) Approved C. (64) 24.(2) Invited the Chief Secretary, Treasury, in consultation withthe Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, to considerwhether a grant might be made to the Hansard society in connection with the celebrations, in 1965, of theanniversaries of the Simon de Montfort Parliament andMagna Carta.(3) Invited the Lord President, in consultation with theCommonwealth Secretary and the Speaker of the Houseof Commons, to give further consideration to the other suggestions which had been made during their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,3rd December, 1964.
as possible thereafter. The day might also be celebrated in schools;and a special commemorative postage stamp might subsequently beissued. More extensive celebrations might be held later in the yearto coincide with those already planned for June 1965 to mark the750th Anniversary of Magna Carta. These might appropriately follow the pattern of the arrangements made during the 46th Inter-Parliamentary Conference in 1957; and, if so, they would probablyentail expenditure of the order of  10,000- 15,000. Since the occasionwould be mainly parliamentary in character, the general supervision of the arrangements should be undertaken by a parliamentary committee under the chairmanship of the Speaker. The- Minister ofPublic Building and Works should be responsible for the detailed planning, in consultation with his colleagues and with outsideorganisation.The Commonwealth Secretary said that he hoped shortly to circulate to the Cabinet proposals for the creation of some form of commonwealth consultative assembly, analogous to a CommonwealthParliament; and, if. this project matured, the initial meeting of thenew body might be linked in some way with the proposedcelebrations.In discussion there was general agreement with the proposals inC. (64) 24. Although it might be maintained that the anniversary ofthe Simon de Montfort Parliament was of interest primarily to thiscountry, it would nevertheless be appropriate that other members ofthe Commonwealth, whose Parliaments derived from our own, shouldbe associated with the ceremonies in January. The Speakers of commonwealth Parliaments might therefore be invited to be present;and the occasion might provide a convenient opportunity to arrangefor them subsequently to meet under the chairmanship of the speaker of the House of Commons in order to discuss matters of common interest. The High Commissioners of other Commonwealth countries might also be invited to attend the ceremony in January. the celebration of the anniversary of Magna Carta in June would command wider international interest; and arrangements should therefore be made to associate the other members of theCommonwealth, and possibly the United States, with the festivities.If a Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers were held in 1965,there might be advantage in arranging it at about the same time. Itwould also be for consideration what part should be played by theCommonwealth Parliamentary Association in relation to theceremonies both in January and in June.In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) It would be appropriate that the Hansard Society should be associated with the celebrations; and consideration should be givento providing them with financial assistance from the Exchequer forthe purpose.(b) A Committee under the chairmanship of the Master of the rolls had already made certain arrangements to commemorate the anniversary of Magna Carta. The Governments own proposals would need to be co-ordinated with these arrangements.
The Cabinet (1) Approved C. (64) 24.(2) Invited the Chief Secretary, Treasury, in consultation withthe Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, to considerwhether a grant might be made to the Hansard society in connection with the celebrations, in 1965, of theanniversaries of the Simon de Montfort Parliament andMagna Carta.(3) Invited the Lord President, in consultation with theCommonwealth Secretary and the Speaker of the Houseof Commons, to give further consideration to the other suggestions which had been made during their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,3rd December, 1964.




</content>
</cab>
