<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 200-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the PrimeMinisters Room, House of Commons, S.W.1, on Friday,18th December, 1964, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, M.P.,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Herbert Bowden,M.P., Lord President of the Council(Item I)The Right Hon. James Callaghan,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,Q.C., M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home department the Right Hon. William Ross, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,M.P., Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster (Item 1)The   Right   Hon.   FrankMinister of TechnologyCousins,The Right Hon. Frederick Lee, M.PVMinister of Power (Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. Patrick gordon walker, Secretary of State forForeign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Denis Healey, M.P.,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,M.P., Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Grossman,M.P., Minister of Housing andLocal Government (Items I and 2)The Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Barbara Castle,M.P., Minister of Overseas Develop-ment the following were also present:Mr. George Darling, M.P., Ministerof State, Board of trade the Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones,Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Items 1and 3)The Right Hon. Edward Short, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers miss J. J. nunn this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. December 1964C.C. (64) Copy No.    3 616th conclusions cabinet
contents minute no.                                     Subject page 1     Rent Bill      ...............     ......      32     Oversea Affairs      ..................      north Atlantic Treaty organisation the Congo3     Inquiry  into  the  Trade  Unions  and  Employers&apos;Associations        ..................      7
a 21. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of housing and Local Government (C. (64) 30) on proposals for aRent Bill.The Minister of Housing said that the Government were committed to repeal the Rent Act, 1957, but not merely to restore the form of control in operation before that Act. It would not be practicable to retain a control related solely to gross rateable value,since rateable values rapidly became out of date and assessmentswere so variable that to use them as the sole criterion would be liableto produce inequitable results as between one area or one type ofproperty and another. The objective should be to devise a flexiblemeans of fixing a fair rent in the light of a series of criteria, of whichgross value should be one while others might comprise the age andcondition of the property in question, any improvements from whichit had benefited, the character of the area and the general level of rents passing, subject to an overriding requirement that excessiverents attributable to scarcity would not be admissible. It was proposedthat a system of rent regulation on this basis should apply toprivately rented unfurnished property up to values of  400 (or possibly  350) in London and  200 in the provinces, these beingfigures which currently corresponded with the value limits which obtained before 1957. The Bill would apply the scheme to the whole country but would empower the Minister to withdraw by order areasin which rents were no longer influenced by scarcity. Existingde-controlled rents would be frozen at their present level; but itwould be open to either party to propose a new rent which, if agreed,would be registered as the fixed rent for a specified term. If theparties were unable to reach agreement, a rent officer would attemptto secure their acceptance of his own determination of a fair rent;and only in default of acceptance would the case be referred to arent assessment committee. New lettings would come within thesystem at an early stage, together with existing controlled rents assoon as the machinery was able to undertake the additional work.Since it would be important to a flexible system of this kind that tenants should have security of tenure, it was proposed that allindividuals within the ambit of rent regulation should have thesecurity now provided by the Rent Acts for controlled tenants. Butsecurity for a family&apos;s home was a basic right, which should besecured also to tenants outside rent regulation, whatever the valueof the property; and it was therefore proposed to provide that suchtenants should be entitled to a period of four weeks&apos; notice and shouldnot be evicted without an order of the County Court, which wouldhave power to suspend operation of the order for two months. Thesetenants would include tenants of publicly-owned property and alsoservice licensees, in respect of whom it might be necessary to givethe landlord special grounds for claiming early possession. There was some objection to giving the tenants of furnished premises a similarform of security; but, since the committee under the chairmanship ofSir Milner Holland were likely to report that the existing provisionsenabling rent tribunals to give tenants of furnished property security
up to three months did not prevent serious oppression by somelandlords, it might be necessary to provide additional protection.These and other matters were under consideration by the ministers concerned; and, if the Cabinet approved the scheme in principle, itwould be convenient for further proposals on matters of detail tobe considered by the Ministerial Committee on the Rent Bill underthe chairmanship of the Lord President.In discussion the following aspects of the scheme were considered:The basis of rent regulationIt was suggested that to allow rents to be assessed by rent officersand rent assessment committees, subject only to certain criteriaspecified in the statute, might result in considerable variation and insome areas might afford little protection against excessive rents.Moreover, if the registered rents for de-controlled properties were allowed to rise to levels substantially higher than those of controlledrents, the motive for putting illegitimate pressure on the tenants of controlled properties would remain. It might be possible to avoidboth excessive rents and wide variations by providing that rentsshould be based on a factor of gross values varying within a specifiedrange. On the other hand gross values were known to be an unreliablebasis for rent assessment; and the Milner Holland Committee inparticular were insistent that rents under the new system ought notto be determined by a rigid formula related to gross values. If theproposed system was to work effectively, flexibility was essential.Rents must be sufficiently variable to give a reasonable return on capital and to enable the landlord to keep the property in goodrepair; otherwise, the supply of properties available for letting would diminish. The objective should be to prevent rents rising to excessivelevels rather than to hold them at unrealistically low levels.Rent officersIt would be essential to a discretionary system that the rentofficers should be of sufficient standing and independence to inspire confidence. It would be administratively convenient if they were employed by local authorities; but consultation with localauthorities had disclosed a considerable difference of opinion on thedesirability of this arrangement, although many authorities wouldbe willing to assist in the recruitment of suitable staff to serve underrent assessment committees. This problem would have to beconsidered further in discussion with the associations of localauthorities.Service tenanciesIt was pointed out that the proposal to give security againsteviction raised particular problems in relation to service licenseessince, if an employee left his employees service, his accommodation would immediately be required for his successor. The National coal board, in particular, would be liable to be impeded in recruitingminers if they could not recover possession of accommodationoccupied by men who had left the industry. On the other hand theproposed   basic   protection   was   insufficient   to   redeem   the
a 3Governments firm pledge to ensure that agricultural tenants werenot evicted until alternative accommodation was available. It wouldbe impracticable, however, to implement this pledge by giving thetenant a legal right to alternative accommodation, since any arrangement whereby an evicted agricultural tenant would enjoypriority over other individuals on a local authority&apos;s housing listwould merely encourage eviction. The difficulty might be reduced,although not wholly removed, by conferring a right to alternative accommodation only on persons who had worked in agriculture fora specified period. The question would require further consideration.Furnished lettingsIn applying any form of protection against eviction tofurnished accommodation it would be necessary to take account ofthe position of members of the Armed Forces, the Foreign Serviceand others who were required to serve abroad for considerableperiods, during which they let their own homes. It was essential thatthey should be able to recover possession when they returned tothis country, possibly at short notice. It might be practicable to distinguish bona fide lettings of this character from the letting of accommodation in which the provision of a minimal amount offurniture enabled the unscrupulous landlord to deprive his tenants of the protection enjoyed by tenants of unfurnished accommodation.For example, the tenant might be given a right to seek a declarationfrom the County Court that the accommodation was to be treated for the purpose of protection from eviction as though it wasunfurnished accommodation.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Housing and Local Government (i) to give further consideration, in consultation withthe Minister of Agriculture and the Minister of power, to the problem of service lettings and, inconsultation with the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, the Secretary of State for defence, the Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations and the President of the Boardof Trade, to the form of protection from evictionto be provided for tenants of furnished accomodation;(ii) to consider, in the light of further consultation withthe associations of local authorities, theappropriate method of appointing rent officers;(iii) to bring before the Committee on the Rent Bill his conclusions on these matters and on other questions requiring consideration during thepreparation of the Bill.(2) Subject to further consideration of the points underConclusions (1) (i), (ii) and (iii) above, approved inprinciple the proposals in C. (64) 30.
Oversea 2.   The Foreign Secretary said that,  as  a result of the aliens discussions which he and the Secretary of State for Defence hadAtlantic Treaty conducted with other members of the North Atlantic treaty organisation Organisation (NATO) during the meeting of the Ministerial Councilof the Organisation earlier in the week, there was now increasinginterest in our proposals for the creation of an Atlantic nuclear force (A.N.F.). The French Government still maintained that this project would have a divisive effect on the North Atlantic Alliance;and their fears in this respect were endorsed to some extent by theGovernments of Belgium and Canada. On the other hand, the othermembers of the Alliance, including the Governments of the UnitedStates and the Federal Republic of Germany, had appreciated ourcontention that our proposals would ensure greater unity withinthe Alliance; and they were willing to allow them to be further examined. As a result there should no longer be any suspicion thatwe were deliberately seeking to protract the discussions or to evadea decision about the problem of promoting a greater degree of nuclear interdependence within the Alliance.The Secretary of State for Defence said that, the FrenchGovernment apart, there now seemed to be general agreement thatthe A.N.F. would be preferable to the original concept of a mixedmanned surface fleet, although the Federal German government might still need to be completely persuaded of this. We had made itclear that, even if such a fleet eventually had to be accepted as onecomponent of an A.N.F., the United Kingdom would not contribute to it. In addition, we had emphasised, with the full support of theUnited States representatives, the importance of injecting greaterrealism into the forward military planning of NATO. In particular,we had opposed the most recent suggestions for a large increase inthe force goals of the Organisation and had stressed the unrealismof the implied assumption that a prolonged war in Europe couldfollow a major nuclear exchange.The Foreign Secretary added that in separate discussions withthe French Foreign Minister, M. Couve de Murville, he had made considerable efforts to improve relations with the FrenchGovernment and to promote a more sympathetic understanding ontheir part of the objectives which our A.N.F. project had been devised to achieve. It was clear, however, that the French conception of the North Atlantic Alliance was basically different from our own and that, unless this divergence of view could be resolved, the continuing French hostility towards NATO would not be modified by such considerations as the choice between the A.N.F. and the mixed manned surface fleet or even the abandonment of bothprojects. M. Couve de Murville had admitted that the FrenchGovernment could offer no solution of their own for the problemof containing German nuclear aspirations within the Alliance; buthe had indicated that, unless NATO could be reorganised in a manner more acceptable to French views, the French government might be compelled progressively to dissociate themselves from thework of the Organisation.
The Congo The Foreign Secretary said that the situation in the Congo(Previous remained very precarious. It had now been ascertained that aboutCC (64) 13th 27 United Kingdom citizens and a few other British subjectsConclusions, remained in the territory which was still occupied by the rebels.Minute 2)      Meanwhile, the advance of the governmental forces had slackened;the initiative of the Organisation of African Unity to end the civil war seemed to have failed; and there appeared to be little likelihood of any further effective intervention by the United Nations. If thePrime Minister of the Congo, M. Tshombe would agree to broadenthe basis of his Government, there might be some hope of restoringstability in the country. But the United States and belgian governments, who were best placed to bring pressure to bear on him for this purpose, were unwilling to do so; and we ourselvesshould not become too deeply involved in this matter. In thesecircumstances, although we should continue to exert every effort to rescue the United Kingdom citizens who were still within the powerof the rebel forces, we could have no confidence that we should succeed.The Cabinet Took note of these statements by the Foreign secretary and the Secretary of State for Defence.Inquiry intothe trades union and employers&apos;Associations3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofLabour (C. (64) 29) about the Trade Disputes Bill and an inquiry into trades unions and employers&apos; associations.The Minister of Labour said that The Queen&apos;s Speech hadforeshadowed that a Bill would be introduced during the present session of Parliament to give workers and their representatives theprotection necessary for freedom of industrial negotiation. The needfor such legislation arose from the decision of the House of lords in the case of Rookes v. Barnard. The full implications of thatdecision were not clear; but it appeared that strikes of various kinds,not merely strikes in connection with the principle of the &quot; closed shop &quot; as in the case of Rookes v. Barnard, might be affected. TheTrades Union Congress (T.U.C.) considered that trade union officials were generally hampered in their activities by the effect of thedecision; and they had been pressing for an amendment of the law.This might be provided by a short Bill ensuring that in thecircumstances of a trade dispute it would not be actionable to threaten to break a contract of employment or to threaten to induceanother individual to break such a contract. The Bill should applyto proceedings instituted after it became law, even if they derivedfrom causes of action arising before that date. To this extent theBill would have a measure of retrospective effect. Proceedings whichhad been started before the enactment of the Bill, however, wouldbe settled in accordance with the state of the law as it was now.
The T.U.C., after considerable discussion, had agreed that an inquiry should be held into trade unions and employers&apos; associations.It should comprise the more important general problems ofindustrial relations as well as the specific question of trade unionlaw; and possible terms of reference for this purpose were annexed to C. (64) 29. The inquiry should preferably be conducted by a smallRoyal Commission, composed of independent members who wouldnot be representative of the interests of either employers or tradeunions. It was not certain, however, that the T.U.C. would beprepared to forego specific representation of the trade unions inthe membership of the Commission.Trades Dispute BillIn discussion it was suggested that the retrospective effect ofthe Bill might preferably be extended to comprise all legal proceedings which were in train at the date when the Bill becamelaw. It was the obscurity of the existing law which made the Billnecessary; and it would accordingly be appropriate that currentproceedings should be decided in the light of the clarificationprovided by the Act. Moreover, it would be right in principle toextend the degree of protection afforded by the Act to all persons whose position had been jeopardised by the decision of the Houseof Lords in the case of Rookes v. Barnard.On the other hand to make legislation in the field of individualrights retrospective to this extent would be liable to be held to be contrary to basic principles of justice. In particular,individuals who had incurred costs in litigating in accordance withthe current state of the law would have a legitimate ground of complaint; and this difficulty could not be remedied simply by providing in the Bill for the repayment of costs in such cases, sincethe individuals concerned might find themselves exposed to otherhazards, including the risk of legal action under the new legislation.In further discussion it was suggested that a possiblecompromise which might both avoid these difficulties and ensurejustice to all parties concerned might be to provide that the Billshould have retrospective effect to the date of its publication, inorder that individuals who instituted legal proceedings after thatdate should have clear warning of the possible consequences. Therewere precedents for such a degree of retrospection, including anumber of Finance Acts. It appeared, however, that provision forany degree of retrospection might make the Bill a hybrid measure;and this factor required further examination before a decision could be taken.Inquiry into trades unions and employers&apos; associationsIn discussion the following main points were made:(a) The terms of reference annexed to C. (64) 29 might be interpreted as implying that the inquiry would relate solely to theactivities of trades unions and employers&apos; associations and wouldnot extend to the wider field of industrial relations generally. Thiswould have the undesirable result that relations between trades
unions and firms which were not members of employers&apos;associations would be excluded. It could be argued that, providedthat this omission was rectified, there might be advantage in limiting the inquiry to relations between trades unions and employers&apos;associations; but there was general agreement that, on balance, the wider scope was to be preferred, particularly since it would befavoured by the T.U.C. It would be desirable to reconsider theproposed terms of reference from this point of view.ib) The injunction to the Commission &quot; to report&quot;, ratherthan &quot; to make recommendations &quot;, might be interpreted as undulylimiting their freedom of action. On the other hand it would be prudent to avoid any form of words which might expose theCommission to the embarrassment of having to reveal that they had failed to agree on specific recommendations. A requirement merely&quot; to report&quot; would not in practice limit their freedom to makeparticular proposals, if they felt able to do so.(c) The position of Northern Ireland in relation to the inquiry would require further consideration.id) Particular care should be taken to avoid any premature disclosure that the inquiry might be conducted by a RoyalCommission until this question had been finally decided and any formal action which might be required, including The Queen&apos;approval, had been completed.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Labour, in consultation with theLord Chancellor and the Attorney General, to consider,in the light of their discussion, the degree of retrospectionfor which provision should be made in the proposedTrade Disputes Bill and the extent to which, as a result,the Bill might be a hybrid measure.(2) Invited the Minister of Labour, in consultation with theLord Chancellor, to consider whether the terms ofreference for the proposed inquiry into trades unions and employers&apos; associations, as annexed to C. (64) 29,required amendment in order to make it clear that this inquiry would not be restricted to relations between theunions and associations, but would extend to the wider field of industrial relations in general.(3) Invited the Minister of Labour, in consultation with theHome Secretary, to consider the extent to whichNorthern Ireland might be associated with the proposed inquiry.(4) Agreed to resume their discussion in the light of the resultsof the action to be taken under Conclusions (l)-(3)above.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,18th December, 1964.




</content>
</cab>
