<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 276-291</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CC (65)7th conclusions this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1965Copy No.36CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on Friday, 5th February, 1965, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic Affairs (items-5)The Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. William Ross,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy  of lancaster the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of Technologym p,m p.The Right Hon. Frederick Lee,Minister of Power (Items 1-5)m p,The Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, m p.Secretary of State for wales the   Right   Hon.   The   Earl   of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m i\ Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, m p,Minister of Labour (Items 1-4)The Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of Overseas development the following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,m p, Minister of Health (Item 6)Mr. Austen Albu, mp, Minister ofState, Department of economic affairs (Items 5-7)The Right Hon. Charles Pannell, m p,Minister of Public Building and works (Item 5)The Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . A. A. JarrattMr. R. T. Armstrong
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Public Expenditure..................      32     Ministerial Travel..................      33     Oversea Affairs     ..................       3LaosVietnamUnited Nations4     Prices and Incomes Policy ............      45     New Town for Manchester       ..........      66     Prices and Incomes Policy ............       8Doctors&apos; pay     Farm Price Review..................     10
Ministerial 2.   The Prime Minister reminded the Cabinet that, now thatTravel ^Q major items in the Governments legislative programme were beginning to come forward in Parliament, it would be important for the Government to conserve their voting strength in the Houseof Commons. Ministers would appreciate, therefore, that there wouldbe little opportunity in the near future to undertake extensive traveloverseas; and it might be necessary, on occasion, to ask them to reconsider projects of this kind which were in contemplation.OverseaAffairsLaosVietnam(previous reference:CC (65) 5thConclusions,Minute 2)3. The Foreign Secretary said that the latest informationsuggested that the attempted Right-wing coup d&apos;etat in Laos hadbeen decisively defeated.The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that the Chairmanof the Council of Ministers of the USSR, M. Kosygin, had embarked on a visit to North Vietnam. The purposes of this mission wereobscure. But there were some grounds for supposing that the SovietGovernment were now anxious to anticipate the Government of communist China in providing additional air defence equipment to the Government of North Vietnam; and they might also be concerned to warn that Government afresh of the dangers of anyintensification of military action against South Vietnam which might bring them into direct conflict with United States forces. It was not impossible, therefore, that M. Kosygin&apos;s visit would prove to be theprelude to some new proposal for a negotiated settlement of thedispute between North and South Vietnam.In South Vietnam M. Huong, the head of the Government whichhad recently been overthrown by a military coup d&apos;etat, had soughtrefuge in the house of HM Representative. This had created a potentially embarrassing situation; but the military faction currentlyin power appeared ready to acquiesce.CC 7 (65)Public 1.   The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that he hadExpenditure approved arrangements whereby the Chief Secretary to the Treasury,while continuing to assist the Chancellor of the Exchequer in relationto a wide range of Treasury business, would have a specificresponsibility, under the general direction of the Chancellor of theExchequer, in the field of public expenditure. In this field the chief secretary would exercise full Departmental authority in dealing with individual issues; and any dispute would therefore have to bereferred for collective Ministerial decision, on the understandingthat the Chief Secretary would, of course, be invited to attend themeeting of the Cabinet or appropriate Cabinet Committee at whichthe issue in question was considered.
United Nations(previous reference:CC (65) 3rdConclusions,Minute 2)Prices and incomes Policy(previous reference:CC (64) 15thConclusions,Minute 5)4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the first secretary of State and Secretary of State for Economic Affairs(C (65) 16) reviewing the progress that had been made in establishing a policy for prices and incomes and describing the prospects for prices and incomes in 1965.The First Secretary of State said that he hoped by 10th february to have secured the agreement of the Trades Union Congress (TUC)and the four employers&apos; organisations to the establishment of aNational Prices and Incomes Board, to be set up in the first place under Royal Warrant. The Board would be charged with the dutyof examining particular cases of movements of prices and of incomes.The members of the Board would preferably consist of a tradeunionist, a representative of industry, an accountant, a lawyer andan independent individual to represent the general consumer interest.The TUC and employers&apos; organisations would also nominate panelsfrom which members could be selected to sit as assessors with members of the Board in dealing with particular cases. The board would work by means of a Prices Division and an Incomes Division,in such a way that each Division could deal with more than onereference at a time.While the Board was being constituted and staff were beingassembled, he would proceed to discussions with representatives ofthe TUC and the employers&apos; organisations and thereafter with theNational Economic Development Council (NEDC) on a &quot; norm &quot;for incomes and on the criteria for assessing individual movements of prices and incomes. The agreed criteria would be formallyconveyed to the Prices and Incomes Board and would be published.It was to be expected that the criteria themselves and the findings ofthe Board on particular cases would influence the decisions ofnegotiators, arbitrators and review bodies working within existing machinery.The Foreign Secretary said that the dispute about theapplication of Article 19 of the Charter of the United Nationsremained unresolved; and the General Assembly had once again been compelled to adjourn. When it reassembled in the following week it would probably decide to appoint a conciliation commissionin order to examine the constitutional and financial problems ofpeace-keeping operations in the future; and we should keep in close touch with the United States Government in endeavouring to secure for this commission the most favourable basis of operation. Therewas as yet no indication that the Soviet Government would co-operate in finding a compromise solution; but, provided that inthe last resort we stood firm on the basic principle enshrined inArticle 19, we should neglect no means of trying to save the general assembly from continuing deadlock and, perhaps, eventualdissolution.In discussion there was general agreement that furtherconsideration should be given to the possibility that we might need to take some positive initiative of our own in this connection.
The prospect of an increase of well over 5 per cent in hourlywage rates and of a rise of 3-2- per cent or more in the retail price index in 1965 was disquieting. But it would be essential to createand maintain confidence in the proposed new machinery if it was tobe of long-term value; and this would require that it should not beused in a way which would undermine confidence and that any changes in existing arrangements for the determination of prices and incomes should be introduced only very gradually. It would notbe realistic, therefore, to expect rapid or striking results.If the Cabinet endorsed these proposals, he would propose to announce on Thursday, 11th February, or as soon as possible thereafter, that agreement had been reached on the new machinery;to present as a Command paper the final version of the draft statement appended to C (65) 16; and to proceed with the action necessary to constitute the new Board.In discussion the following main points were made :(a) Paragraph 6 of the draft statement expressed the belief thatthe parties concerned would give the new Board voluntary-operation in its investigations of particular cases; but it also indicated that the Government would have to consider giving theBoard statutory authority for this purpose, if experience showed this to be necessary. In addition, paragraph 18 of the statement undertook that the Government would rely on persuasion and the pressure ofpublic opinion in order to ensure acceptance of findings andrecommendations of the Board and that they would resort to other methods only if they were convinced that the voluntary method had failed. These references had been agreed by the General Council ofthe TUC. The precise wording of the relevant paragraphs might bere-examined in order to ensure that the references to statutory powers were not over-emphasised and that the Government were seen to be free to employ &quot; other methods &quot; in order to secure compliance withan effective policy for incomes and prices. It might be sufficient, forexample, to rely, for the purposes of investigation, on the power tocall for accounts and other information with which the Board couldpresumably be invested by the Royal Warrant. Alternatively, a SelectCommittee of the House of Commons might be established to examineprices in the private sector, just as the Select Committee on nationalised Industries reviewed pricing policy in the public sector.(b) In this and other respects, however, the Government would retain the necessary freedom of manoeuvre since the initiative in referring particular cases to the Board would rest in their hands. Atthe outset it would probably be desirable to refer one or twooutstanding cases of price increases; on the incomes side, it might be best to start by referring cases where they appeared prima facie to be good arguments for an increase above the norm.(c) The relationship envisaged between the new machinery andthe existing machinery for dealing with wages and salaries in thepublic services was not clear. Employees in most public services had
long-established and well-defined machinery for negotiation or reviewof pay and for arbitration in the event of disputes. It might benecessary to reassure public opinion that the Government did not contemplate any precipitate interference with that machinery.(d) Certain nationalised industries had recently increased prices in order to achieve the financial objectives set for them by theGovernment in Cmnd. 1337. These industries were required to consult both the responsible Minister and a Consumer Council beforeincreasing prices. It would be important to bear these points in mindin considering whether to refer a price increase in a nationalised industry to the new Board, although there might well be cases inwhich nationalised industries would welcome a reference to theBoard as providing them with an opportunity to explain the reasonsfor their price increases to the public.(e) The maintenance of confidence in the new policy and machinery would depend on proceeding by consent. The gradualapproach which this implied suggested that the new machinery couldnot be relied upon to make any substantial contribution to the regulation of demand in 1965. It might be necessary, therefore, to rely on other measures if (as seemed probable) it was desirable to moderate the pressure of demand in that year.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the memorandum by the First Secretary of Stateand Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (C (65) 16)on the progress which had been made towards establishing a policy for prices and incomes.(2) Invited the First Secretary of State to announce theGovernments decision to establish the Prices and incomes Board as soon as agreement had been reached with the employers&apos; organisations as well as the TUC andto present to Parliament a Command paper on the linesof the draft appended to C (65) 16, revised to take accountof the points made in their discussion and as might otherwise be necessary.New Town for        5.   The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the FirstManchester     Secretary of State and the President of the Board of Trade (C (65) 13and 14 respectively) about a proposed new town for Manchester.The First Secretary of State said that the Economic development committee had been unable to reach agreement on the proposal toprovide a new town for Manchester. Exhaustive examination had shown that a limited degree of housing development at Risley wouldprovide some remedy for the problem of slum clearance in Manchesterbut that it would also be desirable to establish a larger new town atLeyland / Chorley, which would provide opportunities of employment as well as of residence. For this purpose, however, it would be necessaryto provide financial incentives of a kind currently available only inrelation to development districts. This would require additional
legislative authority and would admittedly represent an innovation ofpolicy as regards the distribution of industry; but the majority of themembers of the Economic Development Committee had beenconvinced that it would not be realistic to seek to postpone alldecisions about the encouragement of economic growth in the restof the country until the task of rehabilitating development districtswas complete.The President of the Board of Trade said that it must continueto be the Governments main purpose to make the fullest use of thecountry&apos;s labour resources and, therefore, to seek to persuade industryto establish new branches in areas of high unemployment. Thispurpose would be liable to be frustrated if industry were provided with financial inducements in relation to other areas as well. since it would be necessary, in any event, to formulate new legislation in thenear future in order to replace the Local Employment Acts, whichwould expire in March 1967, a review of distribution of industrypolicy as a whole had been put in hand; and it would be advisable to refrain from any commitment in respect of the proposed new townat Leyland / Chorley in anticipation of the outcome of this report. Theresults of the regional study of the North-West, which was currentlyin train, would also be relevant to the decision.In discussion it was suggested that a decision in favour of theproposed new town might provoke resentment in other areas of thecountry, particularly in Scotland and Wales, which had strongerclaims than Manchester to be provided with additional incentives to industrial growth. The drift of population from these areas was already serious and would be liable to be aggravated if theGovernment were to appear to attach greater importance to attractingindustry to an area where there was no comparable need to take special steps in order to bring unused resources into employment.Moreover, it would not be possible to take realistic decisions on the priorities to be observed in the distribution of industry until thenational economic plan and the accompanying regional plans hadbeen completed and the needs of the country could be estimated asa whole. Meanwhile it would be unjust to allow new growth points to be created on a piecemeal basis, in response to individual localpressures; and it might also be uneconomic to attempt to solve theproblems of Manchester in two separate stages i.e., initially by ashort-term and limited development at Risley and subsequently bya longer-term and more comprehensive development at Leyland/Chorley. It would be preferable to defer a decision until the comprehensive plan for the North-West of England had beencompleted; and it might then be seen to be wiser to concentrateresources primarily on large-scale development at Leyland/Chorley.On the other hand it was now urgently necessary to provide some means of expediting slum clearance in Manchester; and thedevelopment of Risley, although of only limited value in thisconnection, offered the best prospects in the immediate future,especially since it might be combined, in the longer-term, with the
development of Warrington on a twin-town basis. It would be very desirable, however, to provide, in addition, a new growth point nearManchester in order to demonstrate to public opinion that theGovernment were in earnest in promoting industrial developmentthroughout the whole country and that they were as concerned to stimulate growth in the North-West as in the South-East, in respect ofwhich they had recently announced their proposals.The Prime Minister said that it appeared to be generally agreedthat the balance of advantage lay in implementing the proposal fora new town at Leyland / Chorley, provided that this was presentedprimarily as the second stage in a plan to meet the housing needs of manchester (of which the development of Risley would be the first stage) and that no reference was made at this point to the possibility that the Government might seek fresh legislative authority to provide,in this and other similar areas, the financial incentives to attractindustry which should preferably be directed to areas of relatively high unemployment, such as Scotland and Wales. The industrialcontent of the new town should therefore be provided, so far aspossible, by the transfer of industry and offices from Manchester itself.The Cabinet Approved C (65) 13 on the basis indicated by the PrimeMinister in his summing up of their discussion.Doctors&apos; PayPrices and 6.   The Minister of Health said that the Sub-Committee on incomes Policy prjces anci incomes 0f the Economic Development Committee had invited him to report to the Cabinet their conclusion that recentrecommendations by the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos;Remuneration for an increase of about 9 per cent in the average net income of general medical practitioners should be accepted.The increase recommended by the Review Body would cost 5^ million in a full year, although the additional sum required in1965-66 would be between  1 and  2 million. The Review Bodyhad recommended that the additional money should be drawn uponso far as necessary to finance the introduction of new schemes forpartial direct reimbursement of certain practice expenses, to whichthe Health Departments attached importance as a means of encouraging good practice. Most of the  5^ million would be needed for this purpose; and the amount available for a general increase in remuneration would permit an increase of not more than 6d. in thecapitation fee. The recommendation on net income, which the review body related to the increase in workload resulting from the declinein the ratio of general practitioners to total population, woulddisappoint the profession, which had claimed an increase of about23 per cent in net income, costing about  15 million, together withseniority payments which would have cost about another  5 million.The profession would also be disappointed that the Review Bodyhad recommended that the additional remuneration should be directly linked with the schemes for reimbursement of practiceexpenses. It was therefore by no means certain that they would accept
the recommendations. If they did not do so, a serious situation would develop. If there was a risk of such a situation, however, the onusshould be seen to fall upon the profession, not on the Government;and this was an additional material argument in favour of theGovernments accepting the recommendations without qualification.The Review Body had also expressed the hope that theGovernment would consider sympathetically a revision of the termsupon which compensation for loss of practice goodwill was payable to doctors, whereby compensation would be payable at a fixed age,whether or not a doctor had retired. The Sub-Committee on prices and Incomes had considered that the Health Ministers should beauthorised to propose that compensation should be payable at theage of 70 only if the immediate additional cost of  H million in1965-66 could be met by savings elsewhere in National Health ServiceVotes. The Health Ministers had carefully considered this suggestionbut were unable to find savings of this order in their Estimates. Itmight therefore be desirable to inform the profession that theGovernment would pay compensation at the age of 70, whether ornot a doctor had retired, as soon as economic circumstances permitted.In discussion the following main points were made:(a) The proposed increase in net income was potentiallyembarrassing in relation to the incomes policy which the Governmentwere about to launch. The increase of 9 per cent would follow anincrease of 14 per cent in April 1963 which had been intended tosuffice for three years; and a further review of the pay of doctors and dentists in the National Health Service (including general practitioners) was due in 1966.(b) Moreover, the announcement of this increase would be liableto complicate the pending negotiations on the pay of school teachers in England and Wales. In particular, it would make it even moredifficult to insist that a three-year agreement for Scottish teachers,reached in April 1963, should be allowed to run its course. Theincrease could also be embarrassing in relation to the recent settlement in the engineering industry, which covered a period of three years.In any announcement, therefore, it should be emphasised that theincrease was linked to the increase in &quot; output&quot; resulting from thehigher workload of general practitioners and that it represented an incentive to schemes for improving general practice rather than anincrease in remuneration as represented by the capitation fee.(c) To promise payment of compensation at 70 &quot; when economic circumstances permitted &quot; might encourage the profession to press for the implementation of this promise after an unduly short interval;and, once the original concession had been made, there would subsequently be constant pressure to extend it by reducing the age at which compensation became payable. At most the Health ministers should indicate that in current economic circumstances it was notpossible for the Government to accede to the proposal but that theywould be prepared to reconsider it, without commitment, in12 months&apos; time.SECRET6551-3 bS
The Prime Minister said that the increase in net incomerecommended by the Review Body was potentially embarrassing inrelation to the Governments incomes policy. It was clearly difficult,however, lor the Government to reject the recommendation of anindependent Review Body, particularly given the present climate ofopinion in the profession. The general view of the Cabinet, therefore,was that the recommendation must be accepted.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the recommendations by the Review Body onDoctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remuneration on the remuneration of general medical practitioners should be accepted.(2) Invited the Health Ministers to indicate to the medical profession that, while the Government sympathised withthe motives for the suggestion that compensation for theloss of practice goodwill should become payable at a fixed age, whether or not a doctor had retired, they were unable in present economic and financial circumstances to make any concrete proposal but would be prepared,without commitment, to reconsider the matter in12 months&apos; time.Farm price review(previous reference:CC (65) 5thConclusions,Minute 4)7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster (C (65) 15) on the 1965 Farm Price Review.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster recalled that the farm Price Review Committee had been asked to consider the issues involved in the forthcoming Review and to make recommendations to the Cabinet both on the offer to be made initially and onthe maximum determination which would be acceptable. TheCommittee had been unable to reach agreement on these issues. TheAgricultural Ministers considered that the Governments openingoffer in the negotiations should be an increase of  3 million in thevalue of the price guarantees. This would be regarded by the farmersas a &quot; break even &quot; offer, since, on the basis of an increase in efficiencyestimated at  25 million, it would only suffice to cover the increase in costs which had taken place in the last year. Moreover, it wouldprovide no improvement in farmers&apos; incomes; and they would be bound to object to it in this respect, in view both of the assuranceswhich they had received from the previous Government and of theirown objective of increasing their income by 25 per cent in the threeyears beginning 1964-65. The Agricultural Ministers would, therefore,wish to be able finally to offer an increase in the guarantees of about 10 million; this, in their view would be a defensible offer, eventhough it was unlikely to achieve an agreed review.The economic Ministers considered that the Government should start by proposing the maximum permissible reduction in the valueof guarantees, amounting to  10 million. Some of them consideredthat this figure should also be the ultimate determination. they maintained  that  the  previous year&apos;s  determination had been
exceptionally generous in that it had increased farming incomes by15 per cent and the average farmer&apos;s income by more than that amount. Even over two years such an increase was inconsistent withthe Governments incomes policy.A minimum determination on these lines would imply thatthere would be no increase in the guaranteed price of milk, whereas the Farmers&apos; Union were expected to seek an increase of 6d. a gallon.The Agricultural Ministers would wish, either at the opening or during the course of negotiation, to be able to offer an increase of id. a gallon, which would imply an increase in the price of milk tothe consumer of ^d. per pint for four months during the next financial year. They feared that, in the absence of such an increasein the guaranteed price, milk production might decline to a point where seasonal local shortages developed. The total number of dairycows was now lower than in 1963-64 and the number of heifers incalf was declining. Moreover, the higher price and world shortage of beef increased the temptation to farmers to slaughter dairy cows forbeef and to substitute beef production for milk production. Theeconomic Ministers, on the other hand, suggested that the total increase of 3d. a gallon in the guaranteed price of milk in the lasttwo years had not yet had its full effect in increasing production.Moreover, liquid consumption accounted for only 70 per cent of farmsales of milk, the rest being used in the manufacture of milk products;and, while some margin between liquid consumption and farm saleswas necessary in order to ensure adequate and continuous supplies,the present margin was historically high. For these reasons anincrease in the guarantee should be conceded only if it became clear in the course of negotiations that to refuse it altogether would imperilsupplies of liquid milk.The future guaranteed price of fat cattle was also a subject of disagreement. The Agricultural Ministers felt that, in view of the continuing strong demand for beef on the world market and theabsence of any indication of an increase in supplies, it would benecessary to increase the guaranteed price in order to stimulateproduction. The economic Ministers, however, suggested thatimbalance in supply and demand in this field tended to correct itselfrelatively quickly and that financial inducements to increase production were unnecessary. Moreover, an increase in the guaranteed price of fat cattle without an increase in the guaranteed price of milkwould accentuate the risk that the emphasis of production wouldchange from milk to beef.The Governments negotiating position, however, would need tobe determined as much by the extent to which they were preparedto face a major dispute with the farmers as by these conflictingeconomic considerations. It would seem to be unwise to start the review with a minimum determination, since the farmers would be unlikely to be willing to continue negotiations at all on this basis. Itmight be preferable, therefore, that the Government should indicateinitially that, although there was a very strong case in presentSECRET6551-3 c
circumstances for proposing a minimum determination, they wereprepared to make &quot; without prejudice &quot; an offer of an increase of 3 million in the guarantees. It might be worth raising this figure to 10 million as the final offer, provided that the outcome of the review was agreed on this basis and was acceptable in other respects. Indefault of agreement, however, the Governments position would be fully reserved; and the Cabinet would need to consider the figure atwhich they would impose a determination. The decision on milkcould be allowed to evolve during the course of negotiations. But itwould be unrealistic to oppose a relatively small increase in the priceof milk when there had been significant increases in wages and priceselsewhere in the economy; nor was there any evidence to supportthe suggestion that the consumption of milk would fall if its pricerose by ^d. per pint.The Minister of Agriculture said that a negotiating position onthe lines proposed by the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancastercould be justified as reasonable in present circumstances. At an appropriate moment, possibly in the White Paper on the Farm price review, he would announce that a major inquiry would be held intothe costs of milk distribution; and this should help to offset criticism of any increase in the guaranteed price which might finally be agreed.The Chancellor of the Exchequer emphasised that the previous administration had reserved the right to make the minimum statutorydetermination in exceptional circumstances. At the present time thedemands for increased public expenditure were very great: and thesum of  20 million, representing the difference between the minimumpermissible determination and the final offer now proposed could beapplied to greater advantage elsewhere. Moreover, an offer &quot; withoutprejudice&quot; would be doubtfully appropriate to this type of negotiation, particularly since it seemed likely that the final settlement would be by determination rather than by agreement. Itwould therefore be preferable to open negotiations at a figure nearer the minimum determination and to be prepared, if necessary, to settleat no more than a &quot; break even &quot; offer of a  3 million increase in the guarantees.Discussion showed a division of view about the basis on whichthe Farm Price Review should be conducted. On the one hand it was argued that there would be no prospect of even beginning negotiationsunless the opening offer was on the lines proposed by the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster; and that an increase in the guaranteed price of milk was essential in order to ensure supplies of liquid milk and to prevent dairy cows from being slaughtered for beef. On theother hand, the need to secure economies was no less in the case ofagriculture than in the case of other programmes of expenditure which the Government had inherited. Moreover, an increase in the guaranteed price of milk would be liable to result in an increase of butter production; and this would be unwelcome to Denmark,New Zealand and Australia, who were our main suppliers. In any event the timing of any increase in the guaranteed price of milk would need very careful consideration in view of its possible effect uponwage rates which were determined by increases in the cost of living.
SEOUET13The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of opinion appeared to incline in favour of opening the farm price Review negotiations with an offer of an increase of  3 million in the guarantees; but views were divided about the figure at whichthe negotiations should be finally settled or determined. The farm price Review Committee should now consider the content of anincrease of  3 million in the guarantees; and the Cabinet should begiven a further opportunity to consider, in the light of the progress made in the negotiations, the final offer to be made.The Cabinet (1) Took note of C (65) 15.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster to arrangefor the Farm Price Review Committee to consider thebasis on which an initial offer of an increase of  3 million in price guarantees should be made in the Farm price review negotiations.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster to arrangefor the Cabinet to be consulted further, in the light of thecourse of the negotiations, about the final offer to be madeby the Government.Cabinet Office, S.W.15th February, 1965.




</content>
</cab>
