<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 312-321</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1965.cc (65) Copy No- ^ o10th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 18th February, 1965,at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. William R.oss, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, m p,Minister of power the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of Overseas development the following were also present:The Right Hon. Charles Pannell, m p,Minister of Public Building and works (Item 3)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr.   John   Diamond,   m p,Secretary, Treasury (Item 4)ChiefMiss Jennie Lee, mp, parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Public building and Works (Item 3)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend &apos;. P. rogers mr. R. T. Armstrong
contents minute no. subject      Parliament ......2     Oversea Affairs     ......VietnamEuropeUnited Arab RepublicTurkeyUnited NationsSouthern Rhodesia3     A Policy for the Arts4     Vote on Account 1965-66
oversea affairs vietnam (previous reference :CC (65) 9thConclusions,Minute 2)2. The Foreign Secretary said that in view of the increasingtension in Vietnam United Kingdom citizens in the more remoteareas had been privately advised either to move to Saigon or to leavethe country as unobtrusively as possible. There appeared to be no case, as yet, for a public warning to this effect. Meanwhile, therewere some indications that the Soviet Government might be morewilling than hitherto to reactivate the co-Chairmanship of the 1954Geneva Conference on Vietnam which they shared with ourselves.But, before there could be any question of our trying to turn this development to advantage in relation to a negotiated settlement ofthe dispute, the United States Government would have to indicate the type of negotiation which they would be prepared to undertakeand the prior conditions which they might seek to impose before embarking upon it. We remained in close touch with the UnitedStates authorities on these issues.Europe(previous reference :CC (64) 13thConclusions,Minute 2)The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that, during a recent visit to Brussels, he had held useful discussions with theForeign Minister of Belgium, M. Spaak, and the President of theCommission of the European Economic Community, ProfessorHallstein. M. Spaak had reiterated his well-known view that theUnited Kingdom should make a further attempt to become a memberof the Community. Professor Hallstein, however, had appeared totake a more pragmatic attitude to this question in so far as he had agreed that we should concentrate, for the time being, on seeking tocreate functional links between the Community and ourselves. Underpressure, M. Spaak had admitted that it might be unrealistic to suppose that Europe could be defended without the participation ofthe United States; but it was clear that he was still influenced to aconsiderable extent by the rival theory of General de Gaulle.United arab republic(previous reference :CC (65) 1stConclusions,Minute 1)The Foreign Secretary said that the discussions with the ambassador of the United Arab Republic (UAR) in London, whichhad been initiated by his predecessor, were continuing; and we might hope that they would prepare the way for a visit to Cairo by aForeign Office Minister in the fairly near future. Any improvementin relations with the UAR which might be achieved by these meanswould be welcome. But we must be concerned, at the same time,to avoid alienating the Government of Israel and arousing suspicionsamong certain other Arab States. The next stage of the negotiations would therefore be liable to be particularly delicate and to call forgreat discretion; and all members of the Government should be guided by the advice of the Foreign Office in establishing ordeveloping contacts with any representatives of the UAR.CC 10 (65)Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
Turkey The   Foreign  Secretary   said  that  the  recent   change   ofGovernment in Turkey did not necessarily foreshadow any significantmodifications in Turkish foreign policy. But the new regime did notappear to be very securely established; and, so long as this situationpersisted, there might be a rather greater risk of armed intervention by Turkey in Cyprus.United Nations(previous reference :CC (65) 7thConclusions,Minute 3)The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that, despite a rather ill-judged intervention by the Government of Albania, it now seemed probable that the General Assembly of the United nations would adopt the proposal that they should adjourn v/hile a specialcommittee considered the issues which had arisen in connection withthe proposal to apply Article 19 of the Charter of the United nations to certain member States which had not discharged their financial obligations in relation to certain peace-keeping operations. It wouldbe unfortunate that, as a result, the Assembly would probably not meet again until the autumn; and we must accept the fact that thisprolonged adjournment would involve some risk of the Assembly&apos;sgradual disintegration. On the other hand it seemed impossible thatthe Assembly should continue in session in the immediate future,since the various issues which it would discuss could not be broughtto the point of decision by means of a vote in the normal waywithout calling in question the basic issue of the validity of thesanction implicit in Article 19, which was itself the occasion for theappointment of the special committee. As soon as that committeewas in being, we should seek to take some public initiative in suggesting means by which the peace-keeping operations of theUnited Nations would in future be conducted on a more satisfactory basis. In the meantime, however, the Security Council would remainin session; and we should do our best to ensure that the variousspecialised agencies of the United Nations continued their work.SouthernRhodesia(previous reference :CC (65) 6thConclusions,Minute 3)The Prime Minister expressed to the Lord Chancellor andthe Commonwealth Secretary the Cabinefs good wishes for theirforthcoming visit to Southern Rhodesia.A Policy for 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the prime the Arts        Minister (C (65) 22), to which was appended a draft White Paper ona policy for the arts.The Prime Minister said that the draft White Paper was theresult of a review which had been undertaken, at his request, bythe Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Public Building and Works,with the help of the Ministerial Committee on Arts and Amenities.As a separate matter he had been considering the Governmentsadministrative arrangements for dealing with the arts and he had
decided that the time had now come to relieve the Chancellor cfthe Exchequer of the potentially embarrassing anomaly of being thesponsoring Minister in this context and that the Governmentsresponsibility for the arts should in future be centred in theDepartment of Education and Science. A statement to this effecthad therefore been included in the draft White Paper.The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Public Building and works, said that the main objectives of the proposed new policy forthe arts were to encourage greater regional and local enterprise inartistic activities, while maintaining the development of the nationalinstitutions; to give a particular impetus to the development of artscentres; and to provide additional assistance for first-class orchestras.In view of the present financial situation, the draft White Papercontained no reference to expenditure on new buildings for theNational Theatre or to the possibility of a pound-for-pound grant towards expenditure on the arts by local authorities, either of whichwould require substantial Government expenditure. The greater partof Government aid to the arts would continue to be channelledthrough the Arts Council. Agreement had been reached on a grant to the Arts Council for 1965-66 (excluding Covent Garden) whichwas higher by  665,000 than the grant for 1964-65. Of this grant 150,000 represented estimated expenditure on building projects, inpursuance of the authority to be given to the Arts Council to enterinto commitments on building projects up to  250,000 in 1965-66.But the increase in the general grant to the Arts Council (excludingCovent Garden) was little different from the increases in the threeprevious years and the Government might be open to criticism onthis account. On the other hand the authority to the Arts Councilto enter into commitments on building projects represented animportant new departure. Moreover, the White Paper indicated thatthe Government v/ould probably introduce Supplementary estimates for further additions to the Arts Council grant in 1965-66 in orderto provide for additional assistance to orchestras in the light of thereport of the Goodman Committee and for certain specialisedprojects which were being currently reviewed. If, however, it were possible, even at this late stage, to provide for a larger increase inthe Arts Council grant in the White Paper, this would constitute themost effective answer to any possible criticisms.The Chairman of the Arts Council, who had been informed in confidence about the Prime Ministers proposals for transferringresponsibility for the arts to the Department of Education and science, was anxious for it to be made clear that the transfer wouldnot diminish the Councils autonomy and their immunity from political influence or direction. It would therefore be desirable thata new sentence should be inserted in paragraph 78 of the white paper, to the effect that:&quot; The Council would continue to enjoy the same powers asthey have exercised hitherto and would in particular retain their full freedom to allocate the Grant in Aid made available tothem.&quot;
In discussion the following main points were made:(a) The references in the White Paper to the financial provision for the Arts Council in 1965-66 had been agreed afterextensive discussions between the Ministers concerned. DepartmentalEstimates, together with the Vote on Account, had been approvedon the basis of this provision and could not now be altered: the references in the White Paper should therefore stand as drafted. Theindication of the likelihood of Supplementary Estimates in 1965-66should constitute convincing evidence of the governments determination to increase support for the arts; and if the GoodmanCommittee could complete their report in the near future, it mightbe possible to give an early indication of the additional amounts which the Government would ask Parliament to provide.(b) The White Paper rightly emphasised the need for greaterregional and local enterprise and activity in the arts. Since much ofthe support for this purpose would be provided by the Arts Council,it would be desirable to ensure that new appointments to the council were made with the need to foster regional activity well in mind.(c) When responsibility for the arts was transferred to theDepartment of Education and Science, which had no responsibilities in Scotland, it would be important, as the White Paper indicated,to make appropriate arrangements to meet Scottish interests.(d) Consideration was being given to the possibility of extending to county councils the statutory authority, at present available onlyto municipal authorities, to spend the product of a 6d. rate onentertainment. Certain drafting amendments to paragraph 38 of theWhite Paper, which dealt with this matter, had been agreed between departments.(e) If the White Paper was to include, in paragraph 42, a listof arts festivals, it might be desirable to ensure that the list was ascomprehensive as possible.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that the White Paper should be issued and endorsed the policies which it described. For purposes of itspublic presentation particular attention should be drawn to theGovernments determination to encourage artistic development inthe regions and to the authority to be given to the Arts Council toenter into commitments on building projects, which was an important feature of the policy for encouraging regional development. At thesame time, in order to avoid any risk of lack of balance in perspective,it should be emphasised that the Government recognised, and would continue to support, the valuable work which was already being done, and would continue to be done, in the national institutions inLondon. It might be convenient that the White Paper should bepublished on Monday, 22nd February; but the precise timing of publication might need to be further considered in relation to otherannouncements which were due to be made on that day.The Cabinet (1) Took note that Departmental responsibility for the artswould be transferred from the Treasury to theDepartment of Education and Science.
4X(2) Approved, subject to the points made in their discussion,the draft White Paper on a policy for the arts attachedto C (65) 22.(3) Invited the Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of public building and Works, to arrange for publication of theWhite Paper on Monday, 22nd February, subject to confirmation, in consultation with the Leader of theHouse, that this would represent the most appropriateoccasion.Vote onAccount1965-66(previous reference :CC (65) 5thConclusions,Minute 3)4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C (65) 24) about the Vote on Account, 1965-66.The Chancellor of the. Exchequer said that the Vote on Account,to be published on 22nd February, would reveal that the 1965-66Estimates would amount to  7,134 million, which represented anincrease of 8 - 9 per cent in money terms, or 5 - 5 per cent in real terms.It would be important to mitigate, so far as possible, the adverseimpact of so large an increase on domestic and international opinion;and he therefore proposed, exceptionally, to introduce the Vote onAccount by making a statement in Parliament on the day of publication in the terms of the draft attached to C (65) 24. The main purpose of this statement would be to emphasise the governments determination to plan and control public expenditure, consciouslyand effectively, as the major element in the National economic development Plan.In discussion the following main points were made:(a) The proposed statement should be amended in order topresent public expenditure in clearer relation to national expenditure as a whole. Excessive expenditure in the private sector might incertain circumstances be no less inflationary than its counterpart inthe public sector; and it would not be in accordance with theGovernments economic policy to imply that public expenditure aloneshould be restrained.(b) The statement that public expenditure, excluding the investment of the nationalised industries, should be allowed to riseby 23 per cent in real terms between 1964-65 and 1969-70 mightbe embarrassing. It might prove impracticable to contain public expenditure at so precisely defined a level, except by means ofarbitrary reductions in other forms of expenditure. Moreover,according to the amount by which the gross national productexpanded, either a smaller or a larger increase in public expendituremight be found desirable.(c) The increase of expenditure forecast for 1965-66 referredto Vote provision and might therefore be misleading in so far asactual expenditure might well rise by a significantly smallerpercentage.
(d) The reference to defence expenditure should be expandedin order to indicate that, even in 1965-66, some economies wouldbe secured, as would be demonstrated in the Defence White paper which would be published shortly after the Vote on Account.(e) The reference to the particular burden imposed on thebalance of payments by certain items of Government expenditure,which was intended to refer primarily to defence expenditure, mightbe taken to foreshadow a reduction in oversea aid. The relevantpassage might be reconsidered from this point of view.The Prime Minister suggested that the draft statement shouldbe revised in the light of the discussion and should be further considered by the Cabinet at a meeting on Monday, 22nd February.It would be helpful in influencing international opinion if the first secretary of State were prepared to make a corresponding statement at the forthcoming meeting of the Council of the European free trade Association; and appropriate guidance should also be sent toour Missions abroad at the right moment.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to revise the draft statement appended to C (65) 24 in the light of thediscussion.(2). Agreed to consider the revised draft statement at a. subsequent meeting.Cabinet Office, SWA,18th February, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
