<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 356-367</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 196514th ConclusionsCC (65) Copy No.    3 cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday 4th March, 1965,at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. William Ross,Secretary of State for scotland p,The Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the Council (items-6)The Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. James Griffiths, mp,Secretary of State for Wales (items-6)The Right Hon. The Earl of Long-ford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, m p,Minister of Power (Items 2-6)The Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of Overseas  development the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins,Minister of Aviation (Item 4)The Right Hon. George Wigg,Paymaster General (Item 2)Mr. Cledwyn Hughes, m p, Minister ofState, Commonwealth relations office (Item 5)The following were also present:The Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Postmaster-General(Item 6)Mr. John Diamond, mp, chief secretary, Treasury (Items 1-4)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasurymp,m p,Secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. Rogers:        Miss J. J. nunn mr. R. T. ArmstrongSECRET6552-5 a
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Oversea Affairs     .................. 3Vietnam2     National Army Museum    ............... 33     Parliamentary Business    ............... 54     Soundproofing of Private Houses near London (Heath-row) Airport       .................. 55     Farm Price Review ...       ............... 86     Deductions of Union Subscriptions from Pay        ... 9v.
41OverseaAffairsVietnam(previous reference :CC (65) 12thConclusions,Minute 2)1. The Foreign Secretary said that we still awaited a response from the Soviet Government to the proposal which we had put tothem on 20th February, that, as co-Chairmen of the geneva conference, we should seek the views of the Powers concerned ona possible basis for a settlement of the conflict in South Vietnam.Meanwhile, the United States Government had informed thePresident of the Security Council that peace could be restored ifNorth Vietnam ceased to attack the South; and their case had been considerably strengthened by the recent capture of a ship carryinglarge supplies of munitions from North Vietnam to the Viet Cong inSouth Vietnam. The recent report by the International control commission on the situation had been marked by a clear division ofopinion. The Soviet Government, in accordance with their customin this respect, considered that, since it was not unanimous, itshould not be published. For our part, however, we favoured its publication.In discussion some disquiet was expressed about the publicposition of the Government, particularly in the face of growingParliamentary pressure, as long as we refrained from disclosing theinitiative which we had recently taken. There was general agreement,however, that the best course for the time being would be tomaintain our diplomatic pressure on the United States Govern-ment to agree to a conference of the Powers concerned.The Cabinet Took note of the statement by the Foreign Secretary.National ArmyMuseum2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Defence (C (65) 36) on the National Army Museum.The Secretary of State for Defence said that the National ArmyMuseum contained many items of great value and had attained thestatus of a national collection which was of interest and value outsidethe Army itself. It was at present housed in an old riding school inthe grounds of the Royal Military Academy, Sandhurst. But thesepremises were inadequate and could not be enlarged; and there wastherefore no alternative to moving the Museum elsewhere. TheCommissioners of the Royal Hospital, Chelsea, had offered a site inthe hospital grounds and  500 a month was being paid from privatefunds to retain this option. The capital cost of the lease and theerection of a new museum was expected to be about  1 million,which the Council of the Museum intended to raise by publicappeal. Promises of over  300,000 had already been secured. But the move would also involve increased costs of maintenance, amountingto about another  100,000 a year; and these would have to be met from public funds. The proposal might also be criticised on thegrounds that cultural activities should be dispersed from London.But the site at Chelsea was uniquely appropriate; and the general public could not be expected to contribute so willingly to the capital
fund if the Museum were moved elsewhere. The 18th June, beingthe 150th anniversary of the Battle of Waterloo, would be a suitablemoment for launching the appeal.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, advised that the museum shouldnot be moved to London. The additional cost to public funds of  100,000 a year for maintenance, although unwelcome, was not anoverriding factor. The major consideration was that institutions ofthis kind should, as a matter of national policy, be dispersed ratherthan centred in the capital. It was relevant that consideration wasalso being given to the establishment of a museum for the RoyalAir Force; and agreement to the move of the National ArmyMuseum to the Chelsea site would no doubt lead to pressure thatits RAF counterpart should also be established in London.Moreover, there was no certainty that the public appeal would be successful in raising the sum of  1 million which would be requiredfor the capital cost of the museum; and the Government might thenbe expected to subscribe the balance. But any exchequer contribution to the expenditure involved by the Museum would beless open to objection if it were sited, in accordance with the policyof dispersal, elsewhere than in London. If the Chelsea site were not used for the museum, planning permission had been given for theerection of a large block of flats on it.In discussion, it was suggested that cultural institutions of thiskind should, as far as possible, be dispersed from London both inorder to contribute to the relief of overcrowding in London and inorder to enhance the attraction of other centres of population. Onthe other hand the Chelsea site was uniquely suitable for the purposeenvisaged; and to locate the museum elsewhere would be liable to diminish public response to the appeal. Nor would it be consonantwith the Governments policy to approve, at this juncture, theconstruction of a large block of luxury flats on the site in question. Ifthe site were not brought into use, however, the deficit on the upkeepof the Royal Hospital would be liable to persist, with a consequentfurther call on public funds.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were on balance in favour of moving the National ArmyMuseum to the Chelsea Hospital site. A decision to this effect,however, must be conditional on there being no commitment on thepart of the Government to subscribe to the capital cost if publicsubscriptions fell short of the sum required. Moreover, no under-taking should be given about the date when permission might begranted for building to start, since this must be decided inaccordance with the Governments policy on the desirable level ofbuilding in London. Finally, there should be no suggestion that, as a corollary of this decision, the RAF Museum, if it were eventuallyfounded, might be sited in London. That issue must be decided onits merits at the appropriate time; and meanwhile the sponsors ofthe RAF Museum should not solicit subscriptions on the basis of anyassumption that the museum would be in London, since otherwise the Government might find themselves partly committed on thispoint.
Parliament 3.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Soundproofingof PrivateHouses near london(Heathrow)Airport4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster, as Chairman of the Home AffairsCommittee (C (65) 38) on soundproofing private houses near london Airport.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that the HomeAffairs Committee had been unable to reach agreement on proposals to assist householders in the neighbourhood of London(Heathrow) Airport to improve the insulation of their houses againstnoise. The volume of traffic and the use of jet aircraft at Heathrowwere increasing; and the level and incidence of noise in the area weresignificantly higher than in 1962, when the Committee on theProblem of Noise (the Wilson Committee) reported that many people living near the airport were already subjected to a greaterdegree of noise than they could reasonably be expected to tolerate.Restrictions had been imposed on the number of night flights by jet aircraft during the summer months; but there was increasing difficultyin enforcing them in the face of pressure from the airline operatorsand their Governments and it was estimated that, if the airlines&apos;requirements for night passenger and all-freight flights were to bemet, the number of jet flights between 11.30 p.m. and 6.30 a.m. inthe summer months would have risen by 1970 from the 3,500permitted for 1965 to 10,000. It would not be possible to allow anincrease on this scale unless measures were taken to reduce the impact of noise on householders in the area. It was accordingly proposed that a 50 per cent grant, up to a maximum of  100, shouldbe offered to owners or occupiers of houses erected before January1966 for improving the insulation of part of their houses. The grant would be available to persons living within an area defined by reference to the incidence and the intensity of noise and would bepaid, through local authorities, by the new Airports Authority. It was estimated that 40 per cent of those eligible would avail themselves of the grant and that the total cost would amount to 12\ million,which, amortised over 20 years, would cost the Airports Authority 220,000 a year. The necessary powers could be conferred on theAirports Authority by an amendment of the Bill establishing theAuthority, which was now before Parliament.The Cabinet (1) Approved C (65) 36, subject to the points made in the PrimeMinisters summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Defence to arrange for thesponsors of the proposal for an RAF Museum to beinformed of the sense of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up.
The arguments in favour of this scheme were partly social that householders should be protected against intolerable noise and partly economic that it was financially unsound not to use tothe full the facilities at Heathrow and that to restrict the growth oftraffic, particularly in freight, would .be disadvantageous to the economy. It could also be argued that, since the Airports authority would make a profit, no part of the cost of servicing the loanrequired to finance the proposed grants would fall on the taxpayerand that, since Heathrow was unique in the level of noise which itwas liable to generate, the scheme would not, at least for many years to come, expose the Government to irresistible pressure for similar concessions elsewhere. On the other hand it could be held that itwas unrealistic to suppose that the proposed scheme would prevent a public outcry against the unrestricted operation of jet aircraft; thatthe demand for grants, and consequently the cost of the scheme,would be greater than had been estimated; that the burden on theExchequer of providing the necessary loan could not be justifiedin present circumstances; and that, if the Government approved theproposed scheme in relation to householders, they would be pressednot only to introduce corresponding measures in the case of schools and possibly hospitals in the area but also to make a similarconcession to householders disturbed by noise from other sources.In discussion there was considerable support in principle for theintention to protect residents in the area most exposed to noise fromHeathrow. On the other hand, once the principle of compensationfor nuisance caused in the exercise of statutory functions was conceded, there would be demands for similar assistance not only from householders on the borders of the area prescribed for thepurpose of the proposed grant but also from individuals who claimed to suffer from other forms of noise. In the light of the progressiveintroduction of more powerful aircraft the level of noise at militaryairfields would approach that at Heathrow; and the arrangements which were necessary to bring heavy commercial traffic into citycentres created a volume of noise, particularly at night, from whichhouseholders might justifiably expect to be protected. Moreover,certain industrial processes which continued through the night were already the subject of complaint; and, although in respect of thesethere were legal remedies which were not available to householdersdisturbed by noise from airports, these remedies were of limitedvalue.It was suggested that, in view of the possible extension of thedemand for protection against noise, it would be desirable, before adecision was taken, to obtain estimates of the expenditure to whichthe Government might ultimately be exposed. On the other hand the problem had already been examined over a considerable period and a decision was now of some urgency, particularly since, if thecurrent opportunity to confer the necessary statutory powers on theAirports Authority were lost, it might be necessary to find time forad hoc legislation in a later Session. Even so, in view of the risk thatthe Goverment would be liable to be subjected to increasing pressure in future to provide protection against noise, it would be important to establish the principle that an undertaking whose operations
produced intolerable noise should bear their social cost;and consideration should therefore be given not merely to ensuring that the normal revenues of the Airports Authority were sufficientto service the proposed loan but also to the possibility of imposingadditional charges in respect of night flights by jet aircraft. this might, on the one hand, provide funds to meet any increase in thedemand for grants within, and on the borders of, the prescribed area and, on the other hand, provide an incentive for operators to keepnight flights to the minimum and, where possible, to make use ofGatwick Airport, and in due course Stansted, as an alternative toHeathrow. These courses should be explored, despite the fact thatit might be difficult to raise additional revenue, as distinct from introducing differential charges to discourage night flights, in viewof complaints from operators that the charges at Heathrow were already excessive.In further discussion the following points were made:(a) The proposed grants should not extend to individuals whomoved into the prescribed area after 1st January, 1966, even thoughthe houses in question might have been built before that date, since they must be presumed to have acquired them at a reduced price in view of their proximity to the airport.(b) It would be desirable to maintain pressure, possibly in concert with other Governments, on aircraft operators and manufacturers to find means of reducing the nuisance of noisecaused by aircraft.(c) Since it was unlikely, however, that the noise of jet aircraft could be reduced substantially, consideration should be given infuture to placing airports at a distance from residential areas and providing more rapid transport, possibly by monorail, into citycentres.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were in general agreement with the proposals set out inC (65) 38. But in view of the clear risk that those proposals might provoke demands for protection in other areas and against other forms of noise, it should be made clear that the cost of the grantswould be met ultimately by the operators; consideration should begiven to the imposition of additional charges to discourage excessiveuse of jet aircraft at night; and further thought should be given tothe question whether any further steps could be taken, perhaps inconsultation with other Governments, to encourage operators and manufacturers to find means of reducing the nuisance of noisecaused by aircraft.The Cabinet (1) Approved, subject to the point made at (a) above, theproposals in C (65) 38.(2) Invited the Minister of Aviation in consultation with theMinisters concerned, to give further consideration, in thelight of their discussion, to the possibility of imposing
additional charges on the operators of jet aircraft at night and of giving further encouragement to the operators and manufacturers of jet aircraft to find means of reducingthe nuisance of noise caused by aircraft.Farm price review(previous reference :CC (65) 7thConclusions,Minute 7)5. The Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food recalled that the Agricultural Ministers had been authorised, for thepurposes of the current Farm Price Review, to make the Farmers&apos;Unions an initial offer of an increase in the value of farm guarantees and production grants which, together with the estimated increasein efficiency, would suffice to cover the increase in costs over thelast year. The Cabinet had also invited the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster, as Chairman of the Ministerial Committee on the farm price Review, to arrange for the Cabinet to be consulted further, inthe light of the course of the negotiations, about the final offer tobe made by the Government.The Agricultural Ministers had now made an initial offer of anincrease of  4 million in the value of guarantees and grants, asauthorised by the Cabinet. The reaction of the Farmers&apos; Unions hadbeen strongly adverse. The Agricultural Ministers had therefore proposed in the Farm Price Review Committee that they should beauthorised to improve upon the initial offer, within a total limit ofan increase of  11 million in the value of guarantees and grants. Thiswould be a tenable position, which Agricultural Ministers coulddefend with better prospects of success than the initial &quot; break even &quot;offer. The Farm Price Review Committee had felt that some improvement in the original offer would be justifiable, if it was likelyto assuage the dissatisfaction of the Farmers&apos; Unions significantly;but they had considered that there was not sufficient evidence on thispoint to enable them to reach a decision. Subsequent informal discussions with the Unions, however, suggested that their more moderate elements would be disposed to adopt a reasonable attitude,if possible, and that an improvement of the offer on the lines proposed might, therefore, avert a major clash between theGovernment and the Unions.In discussion the following main points were made (a) A determination which provided an increase of  11 million in the value of guarantees and grants would represent about 20 million more than the minimum determination which waspermissible. This would constitute a significant and unwelcomeaddition to Government expenditure, for which provision wouldhave to be made in the Budget.(b) It would be desirable to avoid a&apos; major dispute with the farmers&apos; Unions, in the hope of preserving their goodwill in relationto the Governments long-term policies on agriculture.(c) Particular care should be taken to ensure that the changes proposed in the arrangements in connection with the price of pigsdid not add further to the total value of the increases in guaranteesproposed.
The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the Agricultural Ministers should be authorisedto improve upon the initial offer to the Farmers&apos; Unions, within a limit of a total increase of  11 million in the value of price guarantees and production grants.The Cabinet (1) Authorised the Secretary of State for Scotland, the Ministerof Agriculture, Fisheries and Food and the Minister ofState, Home Office, to offer to the Farmers&apos; Unions, forthe purposes of the current Farm Price Review, increases in the value of price guarantees and production grants notexceeding  11 million in total.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Ministerof Agriculture, Fisheries and Food to arrange for furtherconsideration to be given to measures to ensure that no additional Exchequer liability would be created as aresult of changes in the arrangements in connection withthe price of pigs.Deduction ofUnionSubscriptionsFrom Pay6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C (65) 35) about the deduction of unionsubscriptions from pay.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Union of PostOffice Workers (UPW) had recently renewed their request to thePost Office that arrangements should be made for the deduction of union subscriptions from pay. Earlier requests to this effect hadbeen rejected, since the UPW had been unable to persuade the other unions represented on the Staff Side of the National whitley council to join them in sponsoring the proposal. The Staff Side had now decided, however, to ask that the facility should be granted toany recognised Civil Service Staff Association which sought it.There were strong arguments in favour of acceding to this request. An arrangement of the kind proposed would be ofconsiderable benefit to large staff associations; it should be welcomed by management as offering economies in the time at presentconsumed by individual collection; and it should contribute to ageneral improvement in efficiency and productivity. Moreover, thepractice of deduction was growing in private industry and in the nationalised industries; and, provided that the arrangementsremained on an entirely voluntary basis, they could not berepresented as bringing any political pressure to bear on civilservants. Similarly, if a charge of 1\ per cent to cover the costs ofdeduction were raised against the staff association, there could be noquestion of the Governments permitting improper use of officialfacilities for political purposes. Such a charge might more plausiblybe sustained- as regards the political levy in cases where this was an element in the deduction. But this objection might be met by an
arrangement whereby deductions would be made on the basis oftwo rates, applicable respectively to those who authorised the deduction in full and those who wished it to be made net of the levy.If such an arrangement were accepted by the Staff Side as adequatelyprotecting their members against any risk of political pressure, theGovernment themselves need not be unduly concerned on the point.In discussion, there was some support for these proposals. Itcould be argued to be wrong that the Government, in their capacity as employer, should refuse to the unions a facility which an increasing number of employers were already conceding; and this consideration was particularly relevant in the case of the Post Officeunions, since the practice of deduction was already well established in the nationalised industries, with which the Post Office, despite itsformal status as a Government Department, had some affinity. the voluntary basis of the proposed scheme, together with the special arrangements envisaged in relation to the political levy, wouldprovide individuals with a sufficiently wide range of choice to enablethe Government to rebut any allegation that they were attempting to influence the political affiliations of public servants. On the otherhand, if they rejected the request, the pressure by the Post Officeunions for the establishment of the principle of the &quot; closed shop &quot;among Post Office workers could be expected to increase; and thiswould present the Government with a potentially embarrassingpolitical issue.On the other hand it could be argued that, however defensiblethe proposal might be on merits, it would not be so understood by public opinion, which might regard it as the first stage in a processwhereby the Government could, if they so wished, use the officialfacilities at their disposal to advance the interests of the LabourParty and, perhaps, to acquire knowledge about the politicalaffiliations of individual civil servants in so far as these weredisclosed by the arrangements for payment of the political levy. Theproposal would also be liable to be seen as an indication that theunions had some support from the Government in their attempts toestablish the principle of the &quot; closed shop &quot;; and to that extent theGovernment would be exposed to the charge that it was attempting to exert a degree of political coercion on its employees. Thissuspicion would not necessarily be dispelled even if the Governmentfirmly rejected the current application by the Post Office unions forthe establishment of this principle among Post Office workers.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theseconflicting considerations clearly needed further examination beforethe Cabinet could reach a decision.The Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for the issues raised by C (65) 35 to be considered in greater detail.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,4th March, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
