<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 530-541</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1965CC (65)31st conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 20th May, 1965,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, m p,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan, mp,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, mp,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of Overseas development the following were also presentThe Right Hon. Anthony Wedgwood i Mr. George ThomsonBenn,    m p,   Postmaster   General(Item 5)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,m p, Attorney-General (Items 3 and 4)Mr.   Richardm p, Ministerof State for Foreign Affairs (ItemsI and 2)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, TreasuryMarsh,   m p,   Jointmp,Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry ofLabour (Items 3 and 4)Secretariat:Sir Burke Trend&apos;     Mr. P. rogers miss J. J. Nunn
contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1     Parliament     .........     ......     ......      32     Oversea Affairs      ..................      3Dominican RepublicCyprusVietnam3     Race Relations Bill        ...............      4Conciliation Machinery4     Prices and Incomes Policy ............      7Salaries of the Higher Judiciary5     Televising of Parliamentary Proceedings      ......      8S
Parliament(previous reference:CC(65) 18thConclusions,Minute 1)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.The Cabinet considered the situation which might arise if theGovernment were defeated in the House of Lords during theConsideration of Commons&apos; Reason for disagreeing to the lords amendments of the War Damage Bill. It would be desirable inprinciple that the Government should indicate forthwith that they intended to invoke the Parliament Act in relation to this Bill andthat, until this procedure had run its full course, there would be noquestion of any payment being made from the Exchequer to theclaimant companies. But the practicability of a public statement tothis effect would need to be further considered in the light of the factthat the Scottish courts might deliver judgment in favour of thecompanies during the autumn and it might then be open to doubt whether the Government would be entitled to withhold the paymentdue in discharge of this judgment until they had succeeded inamending the law.The Cabinet-Invited the Lord Chancellor, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Lord Privy Seal, togive further consideration, in the light of their discussion, tothe attitude to be adopted by the Government if they were defeated in the House of Lords on the War Damage Billduring the following week.Oversea AffairsDominicanRepublic(previous reference:CC(65) 30thConclusions,Minute 3)2. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that the civil war in the Dominican Republic had been renewed and the militaryjunta appeared to have gained some advantage over the so-called&quot; constitutional&quot; faction. The United Nations had now sent arepresentative of the Secretary-General to the country; and thePresident of the United States, President Johnson, had also despatchedan official mission to assess the situation.In discussion it was suggested that this action by PresidentJohnson might indicate that the United States Government were beginning to realise that their military intervention in the DominicanRepublic, although originally justified by the imperative need to savehuman life as far as possible, was no longer so defensible now that itappeared to be directed to ensuring that any new government established there should be politically acceptable to the United States.Even so, they might be expected to continue to resist the suggestionthat the peace-keeping initiative originally promoted by theOrganisation of American States should now be formally brought under the aegis of the United Nations; but we, for our part, could not afford to oppose any move in this direction and must maintain ourview that the United Nations should be regarded as responsible for restoring peace and order in the Dominican Republic.
CyprusVietnam(previous reference :CC(65) 26thConclusions,Minute 2)The Commonwealth Secretary said that discussions were now in train between the Greek and Turkish Governments in a renewedattempt to devise some settlement of the communal dispute in Cyprus.But the President of Cyprus, Archbishop Makarios, had indicated thathe would resist any procedure which would exclude the Governmentof the Island from discussions to this end; and, as the most effective means of demonstrating his insistence on this point, he had requested the United Nations to arrange for their mediator, Senor Gallo Plaza,to return to Cyprus forthwith. In these circumstances it would bedesirable that, when the mandate under which the United Nationspeace-keeping force was stationed in the Island expired on 26th June,we should support its extension for a further period.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs informed the Cabinetthat the United States Government had recently suspended their air attacks on North Vietnam for a few days in the hope that theGovernment of North Vietnam would thereby be induced to open negotiations for a settlement of the Vietnamese war. But theGovernment of North Vietnam had rejected all the messages in whichwe ourselves and other intermediaries had urged them to takeadvantage of this opportunity; and the discussions which the foreign secretary had subsequently held with the Soviet Foreign Minister,M. Gromyko, in Vienna had made it clear that there was still nodisposition on the part of the Communist Powers to embark on negotiations directed specifically to a settlement of the dispute in vietnam. In these circumstances we must revert to our earlier intentionof trying to arrange informal discussions about the situation in vietnam under cover of a conference which would be convenedprimarily to discuss the neutrality and integrity of Cambodia; and itwas therefore encouraging that the latest indications of the attitudeof the other countries concerned provided some grounds for hoping that it might be possible for the Soviet Union and ourselves, asco-chairmen of the 1954 Geneva Conference on Cambodia, to issueinvitations for this purpose in the fairly near future.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.Race relations bill(previous reference:CC(65) 11thConclusions,Minute 5)ConciliationMachinery3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C (65) 77) on the incorporation in the Race Relations bill of provisions establishing conciliation machinery.The Home Secretary said that Clause 1 of the Race relations bill, which made it a criminal offence to practise racial discrimination in a place of public resort, had been criticised on the ground that itintroduced criminal sanctions into a field more appropriate toconciliation and that any infringement of civil rights should be amatter for the civil, rather than the criminal, courts. There was aconsiderable body of opinion in favour of providing a means ofconciliating the parties before legal action of any kind was invoked.
He had therefore undertaken in the debate on the Second reading of the Bill to consider the possibility of making arrangements for thispurpose and, if they appeared practicable, to amend the Bill in committee. After consultation with the Ministers principally concerned and a number of the Governments supporters he proposedto amend the Bill by providing for the constitution of a Race relations board, which would appoint local conciliation committees to investigate complaints of discrimination and to promote a settlementof differences, coupled with adequate assurances against the repetition of discriminatory conduct. If conciliation failed, the committee would report to the Race Relations Board, who would have power to applyto the local county court for an injunction restraining the individualwho was the subject of the complaint, on pain of committal forcontempt of court, from any further acts of discrimination. The board would be responsible for establishing Scottish conciliation committees;but it was thought more appropriate for any legal proceedings inScotland to be instituted by the Lord Advocate. The Board itself would have no responsibility for undertaking conciliation, whichwould rest entirely with the local committees, composed of membersof local authorities and other persons of goodwill. There would be strong pressure for the scope of the conciliation machinery to beextended to deal with discrimination in respect of housing andemployment; but it seemed desirable to adhere to the Cabinets earlier decision that such pressure should be resisted.In discussion there was general agreement that conciliation machinery should be introduced. It was suggested, however, thatconciliation was not necessarily incompatible with ultimateenforcement by means of criminal sanctions. Those who objected tocriminal sanctions, on the ground that they subjected the individualsaccused of discrimination to a taint of criminality, objected to theBill in principle; but the Governments attitude should be thatdiscriminatory conduct was so repugnant that it was right to regard it as a criminal offence. On the other hand there was considerable support in Parliament for the view that the retention of criminal sanctions would prejudice conciliation and exacerbate local tensions.The Bill already provided heavy criminal sanctions against incitement to racial hatred; but this was an offence against public order andmust be differentiated from an infringement of personal rights of a kind which constituted a primarily civil complaint.The introduction of conciliation procedure would undoubtedlyexpose the Government to strong pressure to extend the scope ofthe Bill to discrimination in housing and in employment, to which itwould be argued that conciliation was especially appropriate. But inthe field of housing it would be objectionable in principle and unacceptable to local authorities that non-elected bodies should beempowered to override the decisions of elected councils in the selection of council tenants; and in the field of employment the Ministry ofLabour were already achieving some success, through consultationwith employers  and trade unions, in reducing discrimination.
Moreover, the difficulty here lay less in a refusal to employ colouredlabour (except in cases where unions believed that an employerwished to use immigrant labour in order to depress wages) than in a refusal to concede it equality of opportunity of advancement. But itwould be inappropriate to attempt to deal with this attitude by a process of conciliation backed by recourse to the courts; and therewas no reason to think that a system of conciliation by conciliationcommittees without the use of sanctions would achieve greater successthan the procedures already employed by the Ministry of Labour.In further discussion attention was drawn to the fact that,contrary to the usual practice when a new civil offence was created,the victim of unlawful discrimination was not to be given the right tosue. This could hardly be justified on the ground that, if the right tosue were conceded, the courts would be overwhelmed by individualactions, since this appeared very improbable. But if it were sought tojustify it on the ground that what was in question was primarily amatter of public policy, it would be more appropriate for proceedingsto be instituted by the Attorney-General in accordance with the precedents of the Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1956, and the resale price Maintenance Act, 1964. This argument was reinforced by thefact that, although the Race Relations Board would not itself been gaged in conciliation, it would be responsible for the properfunctioning of the conciliation committees and its work might therefore be prejudiced if it appeared to the public in the role of aprosecutor. Moreover, since the provision confining the right to institute proceedings in Scotland to. the Lord Advocate wasunprecedented in the field of civil law, it would not be easy to justifymaking a distinction between England and Wales on the one handand Scotland on the other hand on the ground that the legal systemof the latter country required it.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that conciliation machinery, supported by civilsanctions, should be created on the lines proposed by the HomeSecretary but that the right to institute proceedings for an injunctionin cases where conciliation failed should be vested in the Attorney-General in England and Wales and not in the Race Relations Board.The arrangements for the appointment of the Board should be thesubject of further consultation between the Home Secretary and theSecretary of State for Scotland. Pressure for the use of the conciliation machinery to deal with problems of the housing or employment of immigrants should be resisted.The Cabinet Approved the proposals in C (65) 77 for the establishment ofa Race Relations Board, on the understanding that the rightto institute legal proceedings, where necessary, would be vested in England and Wales in the Attorney-General andnot in the Board.
,r5Prices and incomes Policy(previous reference:CC(64) 15thConclusions,Minute 6)Salaries ofthe HigherJudiciary4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the first secretary of State (C (65) 76) about the salaries of the higher judiciary.The First Secretary of State recalled that the Cabinet had previously agreed that legislation should be introduced in June orJuly in order to increase the salaries of the higher judiciary with effect from September. Subsequent discussion, however, had disclosed a division of view between the Ministers primarily concerned on theamount of the increase. This issue could conveniently be considered in terms of the salaries of High Court judges in England and Wales,although the proposals in question comprised a range of other judicialsalaries which would be increased proportionately. The salary of aHigh Court judge had remained at  5,000 a year since 1832 until 1954,when it was raised to  8,000 with the declared intention that the new rates should stand &quot; for a fairly long period, perhaps for a generation &quot;.There was thus some measure of anticipation in the rates fixed in1954; and it was generally agreed that, by 1958, these rates were stillcurrently appropriate. The Lord Chancellor had represented, however,in the light of increases in other comparable incomes since 1958, thatthe present salaries of High Court judges should now be raised by atleast 30-40 per cent, to a level of  10,400- 11,200; and he had emphasised, in justification of this proposal, the great importance ofmaintaining the unchallengeable independence of the judiciary, of avoiding any action which might appear to diminish the status of judges and of continuing to attract the best individuals to the Bench.The Chief Secretary to the Treasury, on the other hand, had taken the view that the salaries of judges must now be considered inrelation to the salaries of senior Ministers and Permanent Secretariesin the Civil Service and that on this basis a salary of  9,000 a year would be appropriate. In further discussion, however, agreement hadbeen reached between the Lord Chancellor, the Chief Secretary tothe Treasury and himself that they should recommend to the cabinet an increase to  10,000 a year (other judicial salaries being increasedproportionately) with effect from 5th April, 1966. This would represent an increase of 25 per cent, or a compound annual rate of just under 3 per cent, since 1958. If the Cabinet agreed, the date of theannouncement of the increases and of the introduction of thenecessary legislation might subsequently be decided in discussion between the Lord Chancellor, the Lord President of the Council and himself. Certain minor adjustments to the other proposals inC (65) 76 might similarly be settled subsequently by agreementbetween the Ministers concerned.Discussion showed general agreement with the level and timing of the increases proposed. It was suggested that there might be some advantage in delaying the relevant announcement until after the summer recess. It was agreed, however, that, having regard to theextent to which the Government were already committed in thisrespect, a public statement of their intentions could not be deferred for so long. Meanwhile, the judges might be informed in confidence of the Cabinefs decision.
The Cabinet Approved C (65) 76, subject to such minor amendments as might subsequently be agreed between the First Secretaryof State, the Lord Chancellor and the Chief Secretary,Treasury.Televising 5,   xhe Cabinet considered a memorandum by the LordParliamentaryProceedingsPresident of the Council (C (65) 75) discussing the desirability of arranging for Parliamentary proceedings to be televised.The Lord President said that the Cabinet would need to decide the attitude to be adopted by Government spokesmen in a debate onthis subject on a Private Member&apos;s Motion on 28th May. It would be technically possible to televise the proceedings in the House ofCommons; but at present this would require the installation of fourcameras and a considerable increase in the strength of lighting in theChamber. It seemed probable, however, that in 12 to 18 months&apos; timehighly sensitive miniature cameras would be developed by the british broadcasting Corporation (BBC), which would be easily concealedand would need only a slight reinforcement of the present lighting.A full Parliamentary service could be provided only by monopolisingthe fourth television channel; and it would be impracticable on this ground alone, quite apart from the fact that some  35 million ofcapital expenditure would be involved. But it would be possible to transmit the debates as part of the ordinary BBC Services on specialoccasions or to provide an edited review of the day&apos;s proceedings onthe existing services late at night. The cost of transmitting an editedversion within an existing programme had been estimated in 1960 at about  250,000 in capital expenditure and  60,000 a year in annualoutlay. No information was yet available about the cost of introducing the more sensitive cameras.It was necessary to consider the effect of televising parliamentary proceedings both on the conduct of the proceedings themselves andon the relationship between Parliament and the public. Experienceelsewhere suggested that the live broadcasting of proceedings wouldlower the quality of debates and would therefore damage the reputation of Parliament with the public. On the other hand it couldbe argued that, if the public could observe the House of Commons inaction, they would be encouraged to take a more active interest inthe debates on major and controversial topics and that most of theobjections to live transmissions would be avoided if an edited recordwere transmitted at the end of the day. The task of condensing the debate impartially would be difficult and might give rise to considerable political controversy but the BBC believed that theycould surmount these obstacles. They had therefore suggested thatthey should be permitted to conduct experiments in sound recordingsand subsequently in television, in order to give Members ofParliament an opportunity to consider whether the transmission of proceedings, either live or in an edited version, might be expected to enhance the prestige of Parliament and the public understanding ofpolitical affairs. If these experiments were permitted, it would benecessary to consider whether similar facilities should be afforded to independent television.
SECRET 9CC 31 (65)In the light of these considerations the Cabinet would need todecide whether, for the purposes of the forthcoming parliamentary debate, the Government spokesmen should maintain the attitude adopted hitherto, by declining to initiate action without a clear indication that this was the desire of the House or whether they should give an undertaking that the Government would consult the speaker and the Lord Chancellor with a view to promoting experiments onthe lines proposed by the BBC. It would no longer be profitable to pursue a third possible course of action, in the form of a proposal toappoint a Select Committee which could itself arrange for whateverexperiments it thought necessary, since the existing Select Committeeon Publications and Debates had now decided, with the agreementof the authorities of the House, that this issue came within its ownterms of reference. It seemed doubtful whether there was any strong demand, either inside or outside Parliament, for the proceedings ofParliament to be televised; and it might therefore be appropriate thatthe Government should initially confine themselves to indicating thatthey would take no action without a clear indication that this was thedesire of Parliament.In discussion there was some support for the view that changesin the relationship between Parliament and public opinion might provide stronger justification than had formerly existed for consentingto some degree of broadcasting of Parliamentary proceedings andthat the Government should therefore not adopt a merely negativeposture on this subject in the course of the forthcoming debate. Itwould nevertheless be appropriate that they should continue to refrain from expressing a definite view until it was possible to judgemore clearly whether Parliamentary opinion as a whole was in favourof exploring the question further. If so, it would be necessary in due course to consider whether any arrangements which might be madefor televising the proceedings of the House of Commons should alsoextend to the proceedings of the House of Lords.The Cabinet Agreed that in the forthcoming debate on the desirabilityof arranging for Parliamentary proceedings to be televisedGovernment spokesmen should confine themselves toindicating that the Government would not take any initiative in this matter but that they would be prepared to pursue it ifthis was clearly the general wish of Parliament.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,20th May, 1965.




</content>
</cab>
