<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 554-565</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1965CC (65)33rd conclusions copy No.    0 cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 15th June, 1965,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime Minister (Items 1-6)The Right Hon. George Brown, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic Affairs (In the chair for Item 7)The Right Hon. James Callaghan,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey,Secretary of State for Defencem p,m p,The Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden,Lord President of the Councilm p,The Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, mp,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, m p,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment (Items 1-6)The Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the  Right Hon. TomMinister of TransportFraser, m p,The Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of Overseas development the following were also present:The Right Hon. Margaret Herbison,m p, Minister of Pensions and national Insurance (Item 5)Mr. Richard Marsh, m p, joint parliamentary Secretary, Ministry ofLabour (Items 5-7)Mr.   John   Diamond,   m p,Secretary, Treasury (Item 5)chief the Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Mr. P. rogers miss J. J. nunn mr. J. H. Locke
contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1     Parliament     .....................      32     Oversea Affairs ...............       3VietnamUnited Nations Peace Keeping3     Public Expenditure..................       4Responsibilities of MinistersReview of Defence ExpenditureReview of Public Expenditure4     Economic Situation..................       5Trade Figures for May5     Workmen&apos;s Compensation &quot; Old Cases &quot;       ......       56     Transport Policy     ..................      7Road Transport7     Prices and Incomes Policy ......... 9
2. The Prime Minister said that the situation in Vietnam gavecause for grave concern, although there were indications that some further hopeful initiative might be possible before long.The Foreign Secretary said that the current discussions on financial contributions to the United Nations Organisation (UNO)in accordance with Article 19 of the United Nations Charter andon future peace-keeping procedures offered no prospect of success,owing to the irreconcilable difference of views between the nationsconcerned. It was now clear that neither the Soviet Union norFrance was prepared to make appropriate payments in respect of previous peace-keeping activities and the Afro-Asian countries were primarily concerned that meetings of the Assembly should be resumed without regard to the basic principles which were involvedin the dispute. Meanwhile, the financial position of the UNO was serious. In these circumstances, approval had been given to aproposal by the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Lord Caradon)that the United Kingdom should inform the Secretary-General thatthey would be prepared to pledge unconditionally a voluntarycontribution of $10 million as a positive indication of their support for the UNO and to help to restore it to solvency. This pledgewould be accompanied and followed by statements of our futureobjectives over the whole field of peace keeping. It was hoped thata number of other nations might be induced to make similarunconditional payments. The United States Government had beeninformed of our proposal and welcomed our initiative, though theywere not likely to take similar action at this stage. It would be appropriate for our statement to be made before the twentiethanniversary on 24th June of the establishment of the UNO, andprobably on the 21st June. Parallel statements would be made inParliament and at the Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers.This action implied the end of the current attempt to obtain agreement on the payment of contributions in accordance with article 19 and on the principles on which future peace-keepingactivities should be financed. It would, however, be a dramaticindication of our support for the United Nations where ourreputation was now high. It should lead to a substantial improvement in the general climate affecting the future of theOrganisation, which would provide the best prospect of reaching an acceptable compromise on the future approach to UN peace-keepingactivities. In particular, the pressure of Afro-Asian countries was likely to move in our favour and this factor might well influence the attitude of the Soviet Union.Oversea affairs vietnam(previous reference:CC(65) 32ndConclusions,Minute 3)United NationsPeace-keeping(previous reference:CC(65) 10thConclusions,Minute 2)Parliament 1.  The Cabinet were informed of the provisional programmeof business to be taken in the House of Commons in the following week.
The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Foreign Secretary&apos;sstatement.PublicExpenditureResponsibilitiesof Ministers(previous reference:CC (65) 7thConclusions,Minute 1)Review ofDefenceExpenditure(previous reference:CC(65) 9thConclusions,Minute 5)Revue ofPublicExpenditure(previous reference:CC(65) 11thConclusions,Minute 3)3. The Prime Minister said that the Minister without Portfolio(Sir Eric Fletcher) had been assigned specific Ministerial duties inthe Treasury in order to assist the Chancellor of the Exchequer andother Treasury Ministers at a time of exceptionally heavy pressure upon them. A note would be circulated to other Ministers on the division of responsibility between them.The Prime Minister said that the informal meeting at Chequersduring the previous weekend of the Ministers concerned with our defence expenditure and oversea commitments had givenpreliminary consideration to the measures which would be necessaryto enable defence expenditure to be reduced by 1969-70 to 2,000 million at 1964 prices. While it was clear that this wouldinvolve painful decisions on priorities, the meeting had disclosed abroad measure of agreement both that it should be achieved andon the way in which it should be pursued. Further studies were now being undertaken by the Ministry of Defence and would besubsequently considered with other Departments concerned with aview to the crystallisation of the issues in a form which would facilitate discussion, and the taking of decisions, by the Cabinet.The Prime Minister said that during July it would be necessaryfor the Government to consider the programmes of public expenditure between now and 1969-70. It would be helpful if,before they came to Cabinet, they were first examined and analysedby a small committee of senior Ministers who were notdepartmentally closely involved: he had therefore asked theChancellor of the Exchequer to act as Chairman of such acommittee and the following Ministers to be members:First Secretary of StateLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for ScotlandChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterMinister of labour minister of TechnologyChief Secretary to the treasury the Chancellor of the Exchequer would in addition discuss thedepartmental programmes with the Ministers directly concerned and recommendations would be made to the Cabinet as early aspossible in July.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.
EconomicSituation(previous reference:CC(65) 32ndConclusions,Minute 2)Trade Figuresfor MayWorkmen&apos;s 5.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ChancellorCompensation   of the Duch   of Lancaster (C (65) 82) on the position of men whobecame entitled to workmen&apos;s compensation before 1948.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that the social services Committee had been unable to agree on proposals for legislation in the current Session to improve the position of meninjured at work before 1948 who were compensated under theWorkmen&apos;s Compensation Acts at a level considerably lower thanthat of benefits under the Industrial Injuries Scheme. supplementary allowances introduced since 1948 had not wholly removed thisdisparity, and the allowances were not payable in all cases. Theprevious Administration had initiated investigations throughselected employers and trade unions into the practicability ofwidening the field in which the Industrial Injuries Fund could beused to supplement workmen&apos;s compensation, and proposals had now been worked out for absorbing the earlier arrangements and covering an additional category of men whose compensation was inadequate. The cost of rather more than  1 million a year wouldbe met out of the Industrial Injuries Fund and the necessary legislation would be short and uncontentious. The Minister ofPensions and National Insurance considered that the strong case for early legislation on social grounds was reinforced by the political4. The Prime Minister said that the trade figures for May,which would be published later in the day, were disquieting. Therehad been a substantial rise in imports, particularly of manufacturedgoods, and no rise in exports, with the result that the gap in thevisible trade figures was the worst on record. The position reflected the industrial situation which had been inherited by the Governmentand the fact that their longer-term measures had not yet had timeto be effective. It would be necessary to pay particular attention tothe manner in which the figures should be presented, since theirpublication would affect confidence in sterling. The trade gap forthe first five months of 1965 was hov/ever only half that of thesimilar period in 1964 and exports showed an increase of 4 per cent.Furthermore, the figure for imports undoubtedly showed atemporary increase as a result of the recent reduction of the importsurcharge to 10 per cent. The longer-term situation was thereforeless discouraging. Further consideration was being given by theMinisters immediately concerned to the manner in which we should deal with the situation.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that there had apparently been a leakage of information to the Press about thetrade figures and that the appropriate procedure of enquiry hadbeen instituted.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.
advantage of demonstrating the Governments intention to take action before the annual meeting of the National Union ofiMineworkers early in July and that of the Trades Union congress in September. It was known that the problem had been underconsideration, and both meetings were likely to be critical if no action had been taken. She found it difficult to argue that the moneycould not be found in the face of the forthcoming publication ofthe Government Actuary&apos;s Quinquennial Report on the industrial injuries Fund, which would show substantial and increasingbalances, and of the recent increases in the maintenance allowance for students. The Chief Secretary, Treasury, had been unable toagree, however, that a decision should be reached in advance ofthe review of public expenditure in July, since from a budgetarypoint of view there was no difference between expenditure out ofthe Industrial Injuries Fund and other forms of public expenditure.He considered that there was no analogy between the Minister^proposals and the cost of living increase given to students, which did not affect the forecasts of expenditure at constant prices onwhich the control of public expenditure was based. He also feared that the acceptance of this proposal would lead to increasedpressure on behalf of other classes, such as those with latent rights to workmen&apos;s compensation and old people not at present entitledto pensions.The Minister of Pensions and National Insurance said that theproposed Bill was unlikely to attract opposition or amendment andwould remove grievances on which there was strong feeling in mining areas and among their representatives in Parliament,without exposing the Government to repercussions, since thecompensation cases could be distinguished from both latent cases and non-pensioners. It was well understood among the miners that nothing could be done at present for the latent cases.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that he doubted whetherother pressures could in fact be resisted, and emphasised that itwould in any event be wrong to anticipate the review of public expenditure in respect of one among a number of proposals.In discussion it was pointed out that early legislation would bean encouragement to the mining industry in facing the problemsbefore it, in particular the more rapid closure of redundant pitswhich aggravated the difficulty of finding work for partiallydisabled miners. On the other hand, it would be wrong in principle to depart from the arrangements which had been made for establishing priorities in Government expenditure. It would not inany event be possible to pass the proposed legislation during thepresent Session, the programme for which was already overcrowded,and, since to announce the Governments intentions some months before a Bill could be introduced would be liable to attractcriticism, it would in the event of a decision in favour of theproposed scheme be preferable to defer any announcement untilshortly before the Conference of the Trades Union Congress inSeptember. It should be possible for a decision on the proposals tobe reached early in the review of public expenditure.
(previous reference:CC(64) 15thConclusions,Minute 4)Transport 6.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofPohcy Transport (C (65) 83) on the Governments attitude to the ReportRoad Transport  f ^  Geddes Committee on Carriers&apos; Licensing. Attached to thememorandum was the draft of an oral statement on the subject.The Minister of Transport said that the Committee had beenappointed by the previous Administration in October 1963 to review the present licensing system. They recommended its abolitionsince it had failed to achieve any of the relevant objectives ofGovernment policy, but proposed the introduction of permits toply in order to enforce safety requirements. There was generalagreement that the present system had serious defects and that changes would be needed but the Report was irrelevant to theGovernments aim of a co-ordinated transport policy. He therefore proposed to make a statement indicating that a total absence of regulation over road goods transport was unacceptable to theGovernment and that until an alternative to the present system wasdevised, the Government did not propose either to abolish it or to endorse it.The investigations now being undertaken by Lord Hinton onthe co-ordination of road and rail transport had so far proveddisappointing and had failed to provide the detail needed forinformed judgment on the problems of co-ordination. He had now asked Lord Hinton, in conjunction with British Railways and BritishNCC 33 (65)The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that,while the Cabinet were in sympathy with the proposal to improve the position of men who were inadequately compensated under theWorkmen&apos;s Compensation Acts, it was clear that there could be nolegislation in the current Session, and in these circumstances thebalance of advantage lay in deferring a decision until the review ofpublic expenditure and any announcement, if the decision were then in favour of the proposed scheme, until the autumn. In orderto reduce the interval between the passage of legislation and subsequent payments under it, however, the necessary preparatory work should be put in hand as soon as possible after theconsideration of the proposals in the course of the review of public expenditure, on the assumption that the necessary legislation wouldbe passed substantially in the form in which it was introduced.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the proposals for improving the position ofmen drawing compensation under the Workmen&apos;compensation Acts should be considered in the courseof the review of public expenditure.(2) Subject to Conclusion (1), invited the Minister of Pensionsand National Insurance to put in hand preparatory work with a view to bringing the new arrangements intooperation at the earliest practicable date.
Road Services, to do a detailed study of the movement of parcelsand sundries on which British Railways were on a turnover of 40 million currently making a loss of  20 million whereas BritishRoad Services were making a profit of some  3 million on a smallerturnover of some  20 million. This was the field in which the most effective short-term results might be found in the field of road-railco-ordination. He hoped the Report would be completed by August.This would still leave untouched, however, the wider problems ofsuch co-ordination.Discussion showed general agreement that the Report was unacceptable. The following points were also made:(a) The Committee had been asked to produce a report on the wrong questions.(b) The study of the parcels and sundries services should take account of the operation of the Post Office parcels service which alsoran at a loss.(c) The Ministry of Transport had commissioned an expertstudy on the question of relative track costs for road and rail whichhad not been covered properly in the Geddes Report.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that itwas generally agreed that the Report would have to be published and a statement made by the Ministry of Transport. It might bemore appropriate for this to be written rather than oral. TheMinister should also ascertain the cost of the Committee. Thestatement annexed to C (65) 83 should be revised to bring out more clearly that the Committee had been given the wrong terms ofreference and therefore did not make any real contribution to transport policy. The Government were seeking a positive policy for the co-ordination of road-rail transport in the interests of thecountry as a whole. It seemed clear that the one man enquiry byLord Hinton was no longer appropriate to the situation and itmight be desirable to bring it to a close as soon as practicable.Transport questions had an important bearing on many issues,including the handling of traffic in urban centres, regional development and even local government finance and it would bedesirable therefore to establish a Committee of Ministers on transport Policy. The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster might take the chair and it should function under the economic development Committee. A supporting committee of officials shouldalso be established and this might include some of the Governmentseconomic advisers.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Transport to arrange for the early publication of the Geddes Report and to redraft thestatement of Government policy annexed to C (65) 83 onthe lines indicated in the Prime Ministers summing upof their discussion.(2) Invited the Minister of Transport to ascertain the cost ofthe Committee.
(3) Invited the Minister of Transport, in consultation with thePostmaster-General, to arrange for the enquiry into the carriage of parcels and sundries to cover the operations of the Post Office in this field.(4) Took note that the Prime Minister would appoint aCommittee of Ministers, with a supporting official committee, to consider questions of transport policy.Prices and incomes Policy(previous reference:CC(65) 18thConclusions,Minute 3)7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the first secretary of State (C (65) 81) about the intensification of pressure on incomes and prices.The First Secretary of State said that prices had risen by over  per cent in the past year and that recent wage increases wereaveraging nearly 6 per cent. The movements of both were carefully watched overseas and had an important bearing on confidence in sterling. The Governments policy on prices and incomes was ingreat danger: it was essential that the position should be brought under control, and that the policy should be seen to be having aninfluence on individual cases.The National Board for Prices and Incomes was now inoperation. The report by the Board on road haulage rates shouldbe available early in July and that on both prices and wages inthe printing industry by mid-July. Urgent consideration was being given to references to the Board in several other cases, including theLondon Electricity Board tariffs, the Midland Bank employees&apos;claim, the claim for administrative and clerical workers in theelectricity supply industry and the atomic energy workers&apos; claim.Other cases would be considered later, including iron and steel and coal day workers. Difficult decisions would be involved and thefull support of Ministers would be necessary for the success of theGovernments policy.The Prime Minister (who was unable to stay for the discussionof this item) said that the position was extremely serious. If wagescontinued to outstrip the increase in productivity the resultantrise in prices would create a serious short-term threat to our external economic position and a longer-term threat to the country.It was particularly necessary to consider how best to achieve theabolition or mitigation of restrictive practices by both sides ofindustry. The Cabinet should give full support to the prices and incomes policy.In discussion there was general agreement on the seriousness ofthe situation and on the need for the Government to show itsdetermination to achieve the success of the policy. The followingpoints were also made:(a) It would be wrong to conclude from the figures for the first quarter of 1965 that wages and salaries in the public sector were
increasing more slowly than in the private sector. In the previousquarter the relative position had been reversed.(b) It was particularly disturbing that long-term wageagreements were being reopened.(c) The current rush of wage claims might be partly attributable to a desire to get them settled before the prices and incomes policy was fully effective. It was now important to call a halt to increasesnot justified by the terms of the agreed policy.(d) It would be important to convey more effectively to thecountry the facts of the situation. A quarterly statement toParliament about trends might be helpful.(e) It was particularly important to obtain understanding thatwhen taxes were increased and led to rises in prices such rises couldnot justify an increase in incomes.(/) The effect of the recent increase of social benefits was rapidly being eroded and it was important that the scheme for an income guarantee should be brought into effect before any further increase became inescapable.(g) It might prove impossible to obtain a settlement of the wageclaim in the atomic energy industry on the basis of the Governmentspresent offer.(h) The effect of holding prices in the nationalised industriesmight well result in their failure to achieve their financial targets.The First Secretary of State, summing up the discussion, saidthat there was general agreement that the situation was serious andthat the Government must show that it intended the policy on prices and incomes to be effective. Further consideration should begiven to all aspects of the problem by the Economic development committee. In the meantime it was important to seek to create thebest possible climate of opinion in which references could be madeto the National Board for Prices and Incomes.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the First Secretary&apos;s summing up and of thepoints made in discussion.(2) Took note that the First Secretary would arrange for theEconomic Development Committee to consider further the issues involved.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,15th June, 1965.
/


</content>
</cab>
