<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 728-737</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1965CC (65) Copy No.    3 848th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 16th September, 1965,at 3 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the   Right   Hon.   Lord   Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p,  Chancellor  of  the  Duchy  of lancaster the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. TomMinister of TransportFraser, m p,The Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of Overseas development the following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,m p, Minister of Health (Item I)The Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Maurice Foley, m p, Joint Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State,Department of Economic AffairsSecretariat :Sir Burke trend . D. S. laskey mr. J. H. Locke
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Local Government Finance        ............      3The Grant system     Oversea Affairs      ..................       7Kashmir
LocalGovernmentFinanceThe GrantSystem(previous reference:CC(65) 45thConclusions,Minute 4)1. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C (65) 125), setting out the conclusions reached by the Ministerial Committee on Local Government on proposed changes in the system of Exchequer grants to local authorities. they also considered memoranda by the Home Secretary (C (65) 126)and by the Minister of Health (C (65) 127), proposing that withinthe new system of grants there should be specific grants for certain services for which they were responsible.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the proposals inC (65) 125 represented the largest measure of agreement which ithad been possible to achieve in the Ministerial Committee on LocalGovernment Finance, of which he had been Chairman. They wouldgive effect to the Labour Party&apos;s undertaking during the lastElection to revise the system of local government finance and, inparticular, to restore a specific grant for the education services. TheCommittee had considered at length the possibility of establishingnew sources of local revenue in order to supplement the rates. Ithad become clear, however, that no other significant source of localrevenue could be found which would not in effect hypothecate actual or potential sources of Central Government taxation. Rates must therefore remain the major source of local revenue. The Committeewere still considering ways in which the rating system might be improved; and they would submit proposals for this purpose at alater date, ft was already clear, however, that, whateverimprovements might be made in the methods of raising rates, itwould be necessary to change the present system of government grants towards local expenditure in order to increase the proportionof local expenditure which was met by the Exchequer. The need foran adjustment of this kind was the more urgent since, although ratescurrently constituted a smaller proportion of both total taxation and personal incomes than before the war, they were now at a level which caused considerable resentment.The Committee therefore proposed that a system of exchequer grants should be introduced, representing 50 per cent of the cost of approved capital projects in all the main services. Except in thecase of highways schemes this would be an innovation. It would givethe Treasury greater control over local authority borrowings for capital expenditure; but it should also be not without attraction for local authorities, since it would reduce their difficulties in financingcapital expenditure and would reduce the loan charges which theywould have to meet.As regards the current expenditure of local authorities theCommittee proposed that the Exchequer grants should be fixed insuch a way that, over the country as a whole, rates need not increase,year by year, by more than the increase in national income. Thefigure for the total Exchequer grant, which would embody the novelconcept of a &quot; moving Exchequer guarantee &quot;, would be fixed inadvance after consultations with local authorities, although notnecessarily with their agreement. The scheme would not prevent
individual local authorities from increasing their expenditure at afaster rate than the average, provided that they were prepared to finance any additional outlay from the local rates. Nevertheless, itwould inevitably involve a rather greater degree of control by theGovernment over local authority commitments. The total exchequer grant would have to be distributed fairly between different localauthorities, bearing in mind their differing responsibilities and needs.For some services specific grants would be required, which shouldinitially be at the rate of 50 per cent; but the remainder of theExchequer contribution should be distributed as a general RatesSupport Grant on the basis of a formula designed to give somebenefit to every local authority but most where the need was greatest.It was therefore important that as much as possible of the exchequer contribution should remain available for the Rates Support Grant(which would replace the present General Grant, Rate DeficiencyGrant and Scottish Equalisation Grant) and that specific grants should be kept to the minimum. The strongest case for a specificgrant was presented by the education services, which constitutednearly half the total expenditure of local authorities. Since this burden was distributed very unevenly among them, the specificeducation grant should be apportioned by reference to a formulareflecting their differential needs. But the case for comparablespecific grants for the police, fire, child care and health and welfare services was less convincing; and the Committee had not felt ableunanimously to endorse proposals to this effect.If the Cabinet accepted the Committee&apos;s proposals, it would benecessary to carry further the preliminary consultations which hadalready been held with local authorities and to introduce legislation in the following Session, with a view to its being brought into effect as from April 1967. Central Government expenditure would beincreased; but, although this would necessarily imply some increasein the burden on the taxpayer, it would not involve any breach ofthe limit of 4  per cent average annual increase in public expenditure over the next few years which had been agreed by theCabinet, since this limit related to Central and local government expenditure taken together. The new scheme would provide a more reasonable basis for financial relations between Central and localGovernment for a further period, perhaps for a decade. But it couldnot be regarded as a permanent solution; and further changes inthe relationship would probably become inevitable.The Minister of Housing and Local Government said that most local authorities now appreciated the freedom which theyenjoyed under a system of general grant and would not be likely to welcome the introduction of any large number of specific grants.It was essential, therefore, to reserve as much as possible of thetotal Exchequer contribution for the proposed Rates support grant, since this would be one of the main instruments of relief for the poorer authorities.The Home Secretary said that he was particularly concerned to retain a specific grant for police expenditure. He had only limited powers to enforce standards of police administration throughout
the country, apart from the threat, implicit or explicit, to withholdthe grant; and the efficiency of the police services would inevitably be reduced if a specific grant were withdrawn. Public opinion wouldbe liable to be particularly critical of such a change in view of thepresent increase in crime and delinquency. It would also be desirableto introduce a specific grant for child care services, at least for the initial period while the Governments new proposals for these services were being introduced. The matter could be re-examinedwhen the new services had been satisfactorily established. As regardsthe fire services, the possibility of a specific grant might be left open until a special inquiry into these services which he proposed to institute had been completed.The Minister of Health said that, while he supported inprinciple the proposals in C (65) 125, it would be very desirablethat they should incorporate a specific grant for health and welfare services. In the absence of such a grant it would be assumed bylocal authorities that these services were now regarded by theGovernment as less important than the education services; and the momentum of development in health and welfare which had recentlybeen generated would be reduced. As a result the demands on health services operated by the Government would increase. Theburden of health and welfare services on local authorities varied aswidely as in the case of education; and the amount remainingavailable for the Rates Support Grant need not be diminished bythe introduction of a specific grant for these services if the level of specific grants were reduced from 50 per cent to 45 per cent or40 per cent.In discussion there was general support for the proposals inC (65) 125. But the size of the Rates Support Grant and the formula for its apportionment between different local authorities would be critical issues; and the co-operation of the authorities could not beassumed if this grant were seriously reduced by the introduction ofadditional specific grants.In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) A 50 per cent grant towards the cost of education services would appear lower than the 60 per cent grant which had been paid prior to its abolition by the previous Administration. Toincrease the grant above 50 per cent, however, would make tooheavy an inroad on the general Rates Support Grant. Moreover, a level of 50 per cent could be defended on the grounds that the specific grant would not represent by any means the whole of theGovernments support to education by means of the new proposals.(b) It was arguable how far the threat to withhold grant was an essential factor in maintaining the efficiency of the policeservices. If an additional sanction were required it might be preferable to invest the Home Secretary with further powers inrelation to the police functions of local authorities. On the otherhand the police services were in a unique category in so far as they
represented a function of Government to which public opinion was particularly sensitive.(c) The proposals involved a reduction in the rate of capital grants for certain types of highways schemes. This would undoubtedly lead to objections from some local authorities. Theabsence of specific grants towards current road expenditure,however, could be defended provided that the number of specific grants was kept to the minimum. But, if they were introduced onan unnecessarily lavish scale in relation to other services, therewould be pressure for the establishment of a specific grant forroads as well.(d) The proposal that there should be a specific grant for thecivil defence services might need to be reconsidered if the outcome of the current review of policy in this field suggested that it wouldbe preferable to leave local authorities to decide for themselveshow much expenditure to incur on this account than to provide themwith an incentive to maintain a given level of effort.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that therewas general agreement with the proposals in C (65) 125. As regardsspecific grants, it appeared right to concede such a grant in relationto the police services in view of the special considerations involved.But the case for other specific grants was not established, subjectto further consideration in the case of the civil defence services.Consultations with the local authorities should continue, with aview to the introduction of the necessary legislation in the next session. The Bill should include, if possible, any proposals for the reform of the rating system which might subsequently be agreed.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C (65) 125 for changes inGovernment grants to local authorities, subject to theintroduction of a specific grant for police services.(2) Agreed to defer consideration of the desirability of introducing a specific grant for the civil defence servicesuntil the current review of civil defence policy had beencompleted.(3) Invited the Minister of Housing and Local Government, inconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, theSecretary of State for Scotland and the other ministers concerned, to arrange for the preparation of legislation to give effect to the new scheme, for introduction in theforthcoming Session of Parliament.(4) Took note that the Ministerial Committee on LocalGovernment Finance would give further considerationto the possibility of effective improvements in the systemof rating, with a view to the incorporation of any proposals for this purpose in the legislation envisagedunder Conclusion (3) above.
Oversea AffairsKashmir(previous reference:CC(65) 47thConclusions,Minute 3)2. The Foreign Secretary said that at his meeting with theSecretary-General of the United Nations, U Thant, that morning the latter had said that his proposals for a cease fire had not beenacceptable to the Indian Government, who clearly wished to retaincertain areas in Pakistan which they had now succeeded inoccupying. The proposals had been equally unacceptable to theGovernment of Pakistan without an assurance that the united nations would deal effectively with the whole problem of thepolitical future of Kashmir. Nevertheless, U Thant was not whollydiscouraged; and he had it in mind, at the meeting of the security council to be held on 17th September, to propose the establishmentof a committee of the Security Council, consisting of the UnitedStates, the United Kingdom, France and the Soviet Union, whosegood offices would be at the disposal of the disputants. Thereafterhe would seek to promote a meeting between the Heads ofGovernment of India and Pakistan on neutral ground, whichwould also be attended by representatives of the committee.U Thant thought that this proposal might be accepted by theGovernments of India and Pakistan in view of an agreed statement by the then Prime Minister of India, Mr. Nehru, and President Ayubof Pakistan in November 1962 at the time of the Chinese attackon India, that they would be prepared to discuss Kashmir. If it proved impossible to establish a committee of the Security council with the membership proposed, an alternative might be a committee consisting of the Afro-Asian members of the Council; all three,however, were the representatives of Moslem countries and might therefore not be acceptable to India. U Thant had questioned the wisdom of any suggestion that the Security Council should propose an embargo on arms supplies to the two countries on the grounds that, since Indonesia and the People&apos;s Republic of China (whofavoured Pakistan) were not members of the United Nations, anyembargo of this kind might not appear impartial. He had it in mind,however, that the Security Council Resolution, in addition toproposing the establishment of the &quot; committee of good offices &quot;,should call for a cease-fire by a certain date. He had not dismissedthe possibility of a Commonwealth initiative in relation to Kashmir;but he had doubted whether it would be opportune until the united nations had had an opportunity to ascertain whether the procedure which he had in mind would prove fruitful.The Indian reaction to the proposed committee might be considerably influenced by the willingness of the Soviet Governmentto participate in its work. There could be no certainty on thispoint, since the attitude of the Soviet authorities remaineduncommunicative, although they had undertaken to consider our suggestion that they should co-operate with us in seeking to resolvethe dispute. We ourselves should be expected to indicate our attitude to the committee as soon as the proposal became public. On balancewe should probably give it immediate support.The Commonwealth Secretary said that the wording of anySecurity Council Resolution would need careful consideration in
view of the susceptibilities of India and Pakistan. But, withoutprejudice to the desirability of a Commonwealth initiative at a later stage, we should certainly support the current efforts of the united nations and should therefore endorse U Thanfs proposal.In discussion there was general agreement with these views.The Cabinet Took note of the situation in Kashmir.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,17th September, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
