<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 750-759</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1965CC (65) Copy No.    3 g50th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 7th October, 1965,at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe   Right   Hon.Lord chancellor lord   Gardiner,The Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, m p.Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Frederick LeeMinister of power m p,The Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the  Right Hon.  Tom  Fraser,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of Overseas development the following were also present:m p,The Right Hon. John Diamond, m p,Chief Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,m p, Attorney-General (Item 4)Mr. Walter Padley, m p, Minister ofState for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. D. S. laskey mr. R. T. Armstrong
contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1     Review of Public Expenditure   ............       32     Coal Industry        ..................       3Prices3     Oversea Affairs      ..................       6Indonesia4     Southern Rhodesia..................       6
Review ofPublicExpenditure(previous reference:CC(65) 33rdConclusions.Minute 3)1. The Prime Minister recalled that in June a small committeeof senior Ministers under the chairmanship of the Chancellor of theExchequer had been appointed to review public expenditure programmes to 1969-70 and make recommendations to the Cabinet.This group had completed its immediate task, but there would befurther tasks for such a group arising out of the review, and there might later be questions for consideration on the estimates for1966-67. With the agreement of the Chancellor of the Exchequer hewas therefore putting in hand arrangements to constitute a standingCabinet Committee with the same composition as the original group and with terms of reference:&quot; To consider and keep under review programmes of public expenditure; and to make recommendations thereon to theCabinet.&quot;The rights of individual Ministers would be safeguarded since issues were left for decision by the Cabinet.In discussion the Prime Minister undertook to consider asuggestion that one of the overseas Ministers (probably the foreign secretary) should be invited to serve on the Committee, but hereminded the Cabinet that it had been deliberately decided that thegroup should consist of Ministers whose Departments were notsubstantial spenders; it might be inconsistent with this principle toappoint one of the overseas Ministers to the Committee.The Cabinet Took note of the Prime Minister^ statement.CoalIndustryPrices(previous reference:CC (65) 45thConclusions,Minute 3)2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of power (C (65) 129) on the need for, and timing of, increases in theprices of coal.The Minister of Power said that the financial position of theNational Coal Board (NCB) had continued to deteriorate, with theresult that, even after allowing for the proposed capital reconstruction, which would relieve the Board of some  30 million of interest charges, their deficit in 1966-67 would not be less than 25 million if prices were not increased before 1st April, 1966. TheNCB had formally sought his consent last July to increases in theprices of coal, to take effect at the beginning of this winter. It had then been agreed to defer increases in the interests of theGovernments prices and incomes policy. The NCB would not wishto raise house coal prices during the winter. Their current proposal was therefore that house coal prices should rise from 1st April, 1966,and that industrial coal prices should rise from a date not later than January, 1966, by an amount which would reduce the deficit for1966-67 by  5 million. It had been proposed that no announcement about coal prices should be made at the present time and that thesituation should be reviewed in a few months time. He would,-S575-2
however, have to introduce a Bill in the House of Commons very early in the new session for the capital reconstruction that had beenagreed; this Bill would have to include proposals for dealing withthe deficit in 1966-67, and the Government would be exposed to considerable criticism if, having disclosed the NCB&apos;s current financialposition and put forward proposals for a capital reconstruction, theycould give no indication that steps would be taken to correct theindustry&apos;s position in the future.It had also been suggested that proposals for coal price increases should be referred not only to the Consumers&apos; Councils (inaccordance with the statutory requirement) but also to the national board for Prices and Incomes (NBPI). It was, however, arguable thatit would be embarrassing for the Government if that Board havinginvestigated the NCB&apos;s financial position and the reasons why price increases had been delayed, made adverse comments on these matters in their report. Moreover, he was anxious lest a reference to the NBPImight delay the implementation of price increases. His inclinationwould therefore be to accept the NCB&apos;s proposals for price increases,subject to the statutory procedure of consultation, and announcethem in the forthcoming White Paper on the Finances of the CoalIndustry, without referring them to the NBPI.The First Secretary of State said that there would be gravedisadvantages in announcing precise proposals for increases in coal prices nearly six months before they were due to come into effect. Ithad been made clear that the Government regarded the public sectoras required to participate in the &quot; early warning &quot; system for advancenotification of proposals for price increases and wage claims, andit would be difficult for the Government not to refer to the NBPIprice increases in so important a commodity as coal. In his view theright course would be for the White Paper on the Finances of theCoal Industry to be drafted so as to explain the proposals for capitalreorganisation and for dealing with the current year&apos;s deficit, andto say that further proposals would be made for ensuring the futureviability of the industry, which might well include increases in pricesearly in the following financial year; without giving precise figuresit could be made clear that such proposals would be referred to the nbpi and that the proposed legislation would be drafted on theassumption that the proposals would be approved by the Board.In discussion there was general agreement that, when theMinister of Power presented legislation for the capital reorganisation of the NCB, he would be bound to disclose the Board&apos;s current financial position. The Bill would have to be introduced early inthe new session of Parliament, and the proposed White Paper would need to be published before then. As soon as the current financialposition was disclosed the probability of price increases would bemanifest.The following further points were made in discussion:(a) It was important that increases in the price of coal shouldnot be deferred beyond 1st April, 1966, in view of the implicationsthat a continuing deficit would have for the 1966 Budget.
(b) It was suggested that the reference to the NBPI should bein general terms, seeking a recommendation on what the price ofcoal should be rather than endorsement for specific figures to be putforward by the NCB. It was, however, agreed that it would be preferable for the NBPI to base their review on specific proposals by the NCB.(c) A decision by the Government to refer specific proposals tothe NBPI might be taken as laying on that Board responsibility for decisions about the method of dealing with the coal industry&apos;s deficit(whether by increasing prices or through the Exchequer) which wereproper to the Government. On the other hand, now that theGovernment had decided to introduce legislation to give statutorybacking to the NBPI, it was important to demonstrate that prices and incomes policy was intended to apply no less in the public sectorthan in the private sector. It was unlikely that public opinion wouldbe satisfied that this was being done if so important a matter as anincrease in the price of coal were to be decided by the government without reference to the Board.(of) It would be preferable to refer the increases to Consumers&apos;Councils before referring them to the Board, even though this would clearly increase the likelihood that Consumers&apos; Councils wouldregister objections to the increases proposed. If increases were tocome into effect from 1st April, 1966, they would need to bereferred to the NBPI not later than 1st February, 1966 (this wouldbe consistent with the procedure which the First Secretary of state would shortly be proposing to his colleagues for handling references to the Board). It would therefore be necessary to refer the increases to Consumers&apos; Councils in time for the Councils to have made theirviews known by the end of January.(e) The increase in the price of industrial coal should be subjectto the same procedure as the increase in the price of house coal, eventhough this would mean deferring the increase in the price ofindustrial coal till 1st April and carrying the full amount of thecurrent year&apos;s deficit on the Exchequer.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that therewas general agreement that in the White Paper which set out theproposals for capital reorganisation the Minister of Power would be bound to disclose the NCB&apos;s current financial position and thus the probability of price increases. There was no reason why the white paper should not disclose that proposals for price increases had beenput forward earlier in the year and that the Government had asked the NCB to defer the increases in the interests of prices and incomes policy. The White Paper could go on to make it clear that theNCB would be making proposals for increases in the price of coal inthe coming financial year and that, in accordance with the machineryfor handling important proposals for increasing prices or incomes,the NCB&apos;s proposals would be referred to the NBPI after thestatutory procedure for consulting Consumers&apos; Councils had beencompleted. This procedure should govern increases in the prices both
of house coal and of industrial coal. It had to be recognised that the nbpi might criticise the deferment of price increases; but theGovernment had a good defence, which could advantageously be deployed in advance by the sort of reference which he had suggested should be included in the White Paper. It also had to be recognisedthat the reference to the NBPI would give the Board the opportunityof commenting on the requirement laid upon the NCB (as upon other nationalised industries) to earn a prescribed rate of return on their capital.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Power to proceed on the lines setout in the Prime Ministers summing up of the discussion.Oversea AffairsIndonesia(previous reference:CC(65) 1stConclusions,Minute 1)3. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Padley) saidthat during the recent attempted coup President Sukarno had been temporarily effaced, but he was now again playing the leading role.He had on the previous day presided over a meeting of the indonesian Cabinet which had included two Communist members and he would no doubt seek a reconciliation between the army andthe Communists which would preserve his own predominance. it did not appear that his illness had incapacitated him to the extent that had previously been expected. It was possible that the army,whose leading officers would no doubt be embittered by the murder of six Generals during the fighting, might now take action againstthe Communists. It was, however, too early to predict the outcome.SouthernRhodesia(previous reference:CC(65) 49thConclusions,Minute 1)4. The Commonwealth Secretary said that he had starteddiscussions at the beginning of that week with the Prime Ministerof Rhodesia, Mr. Smith, and a number of his Ministers, about theprogress of Rhodesia to independence. Mr. Smith maintained thatRhodesia had a right to independence on the basis of the 1961Constitution and that this right had been conceded at the time bythe United Kingdom Government. The facts did not support hiscontention nor had the 1961 constitution ever been intended as onewhich would continue after independence. Mr. Smith had accepted that the discussions should be on the basis of the five principlesproposed by Her Majesty&apos;s Government as a basis for independence.They were that there should be unimpeded progress towards majority rule; guarantees against retrogressive amendment of the Constitution;an immediate improvement in the political status of Africans;progress towards ending racial discrimination; and the need to satisfy the United Kingdom Government that any basis proposed for independence was acceptable to the people of Rhodesia as a whole.In practice, Mr. Smith had during the discussions rejected theseconditions, save for the last, which, he maintained, superseded theprevious four. It was proposed that further discussions under thechairmanship of the Prime Minister should begin that afternoon.
The Prime Minister said that it now appeared likely that thediscussions would end in deadlock. We could not withdraw fromthe five principles and it was probable in consequence thatMr. Smith&apos;s Government might make a unilateral declaration of independence (u.d.i.). Our planning for the action which would benecessary in that event was nearly complete. We should, however,bring the strongest possible pressure to dissuade Mr. Smith and his party from such a course and this would be supported by pressure from a considerable number of the most influential commonwealth and foreign Governments. The Government of South Africa was also thought to be advising the Rhodesian Government to avoidprecipitate action. Meanwhile, it was clear from reports which wehad had from the United Kingdom Representative at the united nations and also from the Foreign Secretary, who was now in new york, that, if there were a u.d.i., there would be an emotional outburstat the United Nations coupled with an immediate demand formilitary action. The Defence and Oversea Policy Committee had in discussion earlier that day taken the view that there could be noquestion of military intervention by United Kingdom forces in theevent of a u.d.i. and that we should seek to avoid military action beingtaken by a United Nations force. In any event we should be unwilling to make a United Kingdom contribution to such a force. Thequestion of a naval blockade of Portuguese African ports in the eventof Portugal assisting Southern Rhodesia might, however, be further considered.In discussion there was general agreement that there should beno military intervention by United Kingdom forces in the event ofa u.d.i. It was also the general view that we should seek to avoidcontributing a contingent of United Kingdom combat troops in theevent of military intervention by United Nations forces. It was recognised that the practice by which, save in the specialcircumstances of Cyprus, troops were not supplied for united nations intervention by the permanent members of the security council might help to avoid pressure upon us to do so. ft would,however, be difficult to withdraw our standing offer to providelogistic support for up to six battalions of a United Nations peacekeeping force and a decision on the extent of our participation couldonly be taken in the light of events. Furthermore, it might bedesirable for. United Kingdom forces to be provided to maintain thepeace in the event of a general breakdown of law and order in rhodesia. The point was also made that we must have regard to thepossible danger to United Kingdom citizens at present living in othercountries of Africa in the event of African feeling being arousedagainst the United Kingdom on the grounds that we had takeninadequate action to deal with a u.d.i.In further discussion it was agreed that in the event of a u.d.i.the United Kingdom should ban future purchases of Rhodesiantobacco by firms or persons in the United Kingdom. There was alsoagreement that it would be necessary to dismiss Mr. Smith&apos;sGovernment and that the balance of advantage would lie in the
United Kingdom Government formally assuming all the powers and liabilities of Government even although, at any rate at the outset,such action would be purely symbolic. It would be necessary to recall Parliament to pass an Enabling Bill which would provide theGovernment with adequate powers to deal with the situation, but itwould not necessarily be politic to suspend the 1961 Constitution. Itwould, however, be important to declare the existing Governmentillegal and to bring all possible influence to bear on all loyalRhodesians to remain loyal to The Queen.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the statements by the Prime Minister and theCommonwealth Secretary.(2) Agreed that in the event of a u.d.i. there should be no military intervention by United Kingdom armed forces and thatwe should seek to avoid United Kingdom participation,especially by combat troops, in any United Nations force.(3) Agreed that in the event of a u.d.i. there should be a ban on future United Kingdom purchases of Southern Rhodesiantobacco.(4) Agreed that in the event of a u.d.i. Mr. Smith and his ministers should be dismissed and that the UnitedKingdom Government should formally assume the full powers of Government in Southern Rhodesia.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,7th October, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
