<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/39/0 images: 822-833</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1965CC (65) Copy No.    3 657th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 4th November, 1965,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. James Griffiths, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, m p,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, m p,Minister of power the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the Council (items-5)The Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice, q c,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Lion. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment (Items 1-5)The Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Tom Fraser, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of Overseas Development
The following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,m p, Minister of Health (Item 4)Mr. George Thomson, m p, Minister ofState for Foreign Affairs (Items 1-4)The Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Postmaster-General(Item 6)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,mp, Attorney-General (Items 3-6)Mr. Maurice Foley, m p, joint parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState, Department of economic affairs (Item 4)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers miss J. J. nunn mr. J. H. LockeContentsMinuteNo. Subject page 1     Parliament     ............     ......... 32     Parliamentary Private Secretaries       ......... 33     Rhodesia       ............     ......... 34     Immigration    ..................... 45     Prices and Incomes Policy        ............ 56     Exchange Telegraph Company    ............ 9
ParliamentaryPrivateSecretaries2. The Prime Minister said that he had been concerned to observe that Parliamentary Private Secretaries were not alwayscontent to observe the necessary discretion in situations in whichstrong feelings were engaged and emotions tended to run high. this had been illustrated during the recent period of tension in relationto the Rhodesian situation; and, although no harm had resulted, itwould be unfortunate if a precedent were created in this contextwhich, if it were allowed to become established, could haveembarrassing results on some future occasion. He therefore proposedto invite all Ministers to draw the attention of their ParliamentaryPrivate Secretaries to the paragraphs in the Note on Questions ofProcedure for Ministers (C (64) 1) which provided them withguidance on the manner in which they should conduct themselves;and he hoped that Ministers would impress upon their ParliamentaryPrivate Secretaries that, before they intervened publicly in any matter affecting Government business, they should consult not onlytheir own Ministers but also the Chief Whip.Rhodesia(previous reference:CC(65) 56thConclusions,Minute 1)3. The Commonwealth Secretary said that it appeared that thePrime Minister of Rhodesia, Mr. Ian Smith, was committed to the concept of appointing a Royal Commission to ascertain the acceptability of independence, on the basis of the 1961 Constitution,to the people of Rhodesia as a whole. But he faced powerfulopposition within his own party, some of whose members clearlywished to make a unilateral declaration of independence (u.d.i.)immediately. Indeed, there was even an indication that one sectioncontemplated the establishment of Rhodesia as a Republic. We couldnot be certain that Mr. Smith would be able to withstand the pressuresfrom the extremists though there was reason to believe that the postponement of a u.d.i. as a result of the Prime Ministers visit had led to a widespread feeling of relief among the general body of europeans in Rhodesia and this might provide sufficient public support for Mr. Smith to enable him to do so. It would not in any event be open to us to make any further concessions in order to preserve Mr. Smith&apos;s position. There were also signs that the economy of Rhodesia was already being adversely affected by the prospect ofa u.d.i. The situation was still one of great delicacy.The Cabinet Took note of the Commonwealth Secretary&apos;s statement.CC 57 (65)Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.In the light of developments in the Rhodesian situation it mightbe necessary to postpone the Prorogation of Parliament from Friday,5th November, to Monday, 8th November, in order that there shouldbe only the minimum of interval between the Prorogation and theOpening of the new Session on Tuesday, 9th November.
Immigration(previous reference:CC(65) 42ndConclusions)4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C (65) 143) recommending the appointment of a committeeto review the law on immigration.The Home Secretary said that, in view of the omission fromThe Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament of a reference toa Bill on Commonwealth Immigration and of the need to renew theexisting powers in relation to both Commonwealth and alienimmigrants in the Expiring Laws (Continuance) Bill, it was desirableto announce in the Debate on the Address that it had been decidedto appoint a committee to review the law on immigration. The HomeAffairs Committee had concluded that it would be inopportune to initiate a comprehensive review of policy and of the general systemof control, preferring a committee with terms of reference limitedto the question of putting the existing temporary legislation on apermanent footing and conferring rights of appeal on immigrantsrefused entry or subsequently required to leave the country. they considered that neither the general system of control nor the problemof the short-term visitor should be within the purview of the inquiry.It was proposed that the inquiry should be undertaken by a departmental committee of five or six independent persons, of whomtwo or more should be legally qualified. The membership would bediscussed further with the Ministers principally concerned. A group of Ministers under the chairmanship of the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster (MISC. 86/1st Meeting) who had considered the termsof reference had recommended that they should be: &quot; To review thelaw affecting aliens and Commonwealth citizens who wished to enterand settle in this country (including the remedies available to thoserefused admission to, or subsequently required to leave, the country)and to make recommendations.&quot; On further consideration, however,it appeared that to require the committee to review the law mightopen the way to consideration of the policy on which the law was based, and it might be preferable to limit the terms of reference tothe operation of the power of deportation and the provision of rightsof appeal against it, although this might not entirely meet criticism on the deferment of the proposed Commonwealth Immigrants Bill.In discussion the following principal points were made:(a) The appointment of a committee to examine the powers which were criticised as illiberal should enable the Government to demonstrate that they intended to introduce permanent legislation as soon as possible and so to secure the extension of the existingtemporary provisions. On the other hand, the principal criticism ofthe existing law was directed, not against the powers of deportation,but against the power to refuse entry to persons who Wished to visitthis country for a short period without any intention of settling here,and the exclusion of these powers from the purview of the committeewas liable to be strongly criticised.(b) The question of the medical examination of immigrantsseeking entry to this country should not be within the committee&apos;spurview.
5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the first secretary of State (C (65) 141) about the proposed legislation on prices and incomes policy.The First Secretary of State said that work had been proceeding on the details of the legislation which had been approved in principle by the Cabinet on 1st September. The outline proposals for inclusion in the Bill had been approved by the Ministerial Committee onEconomic Development. But the Cabinet should be fully alive to thedifficulties which would inevitably arise, particularly as regards thecreation of new offences affecting trade unions and their members.The National Board for Prices and Incomes (NBPI) would be placedPrices andIncomesPolicy(previous reference:CC(65) 46thConclusions,Minute 1)(c) It was important that overseas opinion should regard thecommittee as wholly independent and that it should accordingly be presented as a committee appointed by the Government, and notclosely associated with the Home Office. The Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations and the Colonial Secretary should be consulted on its membership.(d) Members of the committee should include persons of knownliberal views, and the appointment of a leading trade unionist shouldbe considered. This would not necessarily involve appointing anindustrialist also.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were agreed that an independent committee should beappointed with narrow terms of reference to examine the existing powers of deportation and the provision of rights of appeal in respectof both aliens and Commonwealth citizens. The terms of reference and composition of the committee should be considered in the lightof their discussion as a matter of urgency by the group of ministers under the chairmanship of the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster,with the addition of the Attorney General, so that he might announce the decision to appoint the committee during the Debate on the address. If agreement could not be reached on the terms of reference,the matter should be brought back to the Cabinet on 9th November,and a decision should be taken in the light of the suggestions putforward by the group of Ministers on whether the membership ofthe committee should be announced at that stage.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that an independent committee should be appointed with narrow terms of reference on the lines proposed intheir discussion.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster to arrangefor the group of Ministers under his chairmanship, withthe addition of the Attorney-General, to give furtherconsideration in the light of their discussion to the termsof reference and membership of the committee.
on a statutory basis and would be given power to require theproduction of documents and to require witnesses to give evidence.It would be made an offence for any person to refuse to do so; butindividual trade unions might so refuse. In addition the Bill wouldprovide reserve powers, which would be brought into operation byOrder in Council, to require advance notification of price increases and pay claims and to impose a standstill on the introduction of price or wage increases. In particular, it would then become an offencefor an employer to pay higher wages while the NBPI was consideringthe terms of a settlement. It would therefore be necessary to dealwith the position which would arise if a trade union or its memberstried by industrial action to coerce employers to act in breach of the standstill. Although these problems would not arise in practice unlessthe reserve powers had to be put into force because of the inadequacy of the voluntary arrangements, it would be necessary to includeappropriate provisions in the Bill and to defend them in Parliament.The Ministerial Committee on Economic Development had considered whether the obligations could be placed on the employeralone and not on the trade unions and their members. But they hadbeen forced to the conclusion that this would appear to be anindefensible form of discrimination. The Attorney-General had subsequently suggested provisions which would to some extentmitigate the impact of the Bill in relation to trade unions; but thefundamental problem was inescapable It might be argued that these provisions would derogate from the legislation which had for longprotected trade unions against liabilities which applied to other bodies. There would undoubtedly be criticism on this account; butthere appeared to be no way of evading this problem.The Attorney-General said that in order to make the legislationeffective it was essential to make it an offence for an employer to actin breach of a standstill by paying higher wages before the NBPIhad reported. As the law stood, this would have the automaticconsequence that any industrial action taken by trade unions or individual workers to compel an employer to increase pay or toimprove conditions in breach of the standstill would be illegal andwould lay the union or workers open to actions for unlimited civilliability or to a charge of criminal conspiracy, both of which couldbe initiated by means of private prosecutions. He had therefore suggested that it should be made an offence under the Bill for tradeunions or their members to seek to compel an employer to act in breach of a standstill; but that the penalties for this offence shouldbe laid down in the Bill; and that the Bill should also provide thatno action would lie for any other civil or criminal liabilities in respectof such an act. In this way trade unions and workers would not be at risk of actions for criminal conspiracy or civil proceedings for damagesand would be liable, if found guilty, only for a fine. Moreover, theconsent of the Attorney-General should be required for allprosecutions under the Bill; and this consent would normally begranted only in cases of significant importance. It was not possibleto go further than this. The precise penalties would need furtherconsideration.
In discussion the view was strongly expressed that it would be unwise to proceed with the legislation in the light of its probable effect on the normal activities and procedures of trade unions andthe impossibility of operating it effectively. There v/ere manyindustries in which national wage settlements were of relatively little importance; and it was impossible to operate the proposed system in respect of local settlements without bringing to a standstill thenormal operations of major trade unions. It appeared that no provision for the exemption of local settlements affecting small numbers of workers was included in the Bill. But it would beimpossible to secure the notification of the mass of local claims which arose every week. On the other hand if an exemption clause were introduced it would encourage the fragmentation of wage claims toavoid the provisions of the Bill. In view of these serious practicaldifficulties in the way of operating the arrangements properly, the clear risk that certain trade unions might refuse to observe theprovisions and the generally retrogressive nature of the legislation in respect of trade unions, it would be wrong to proceed with theBill.On the other hand there was general agreement that theGovernment were committed in principle to introduce legislation onthe lines indicated in C (65) 141 and that the inevitable difficultiesmust therefore be mitigated as far as possible. As regards theproblems raised by local claims and settlements the Bill would include a power for the First Secretary of State to prescribe by Order the classes of claims and settlements (as well as the classes of goods and services) to which the Bill should apply. It was intended to give further consideration, in consultation with representatives ofemployers and trade unions, to the manner in which the provisionscould be effectively administered by suitable limitations on the types of wage claims and price increases which were to be notified; andthese administrative arrangements could be modified in the light of experience, ft would be an error to include specific exemptions inthe Bill itself. The Trades Union Congress (TUC) had been opposedto the inclusion of a formal exemption; and there was considerableevidence that many trade unions would co-operate fully in workingthe system and, indeed, were anxious to strengthen their authority over local questions. It was true that many local claims were notnecessarily notified to trade union headquarters. But the employerwould be under an obligation to notify local claims when he receivedthem; and it was expected that notification would normally be madeby the employer and not by the trade unions. Moreover, there was nothing to prevent the continuation of discussions and negotiationsduring the standstill period, provided that there was no question ofgiving effect to a settlement until the end of the period. although there would undoubtedly be difficulties, it would be wrong to assume that the system was completely unworkable.As regards the creation of offences and the imposition of penaltiesin relation to trade unions, considerable concern was expressed about
the effect even of the modified proposals suggested by the Attorney-General. Some trade unions or individual members might deliberatelyseek to challenge the law in order to enlist popular sympathy and support. On the other hand, the Opposition would undoubtedlycriticise the limitations suggested by the Attorney-General in respectof the actions which might be brought in relation to industrial actiondesigned to force employers to pay higher wages during the standstillperiod. It was suggested that the offences might be restricted to thosecommitted by trade unions and not extend to those committed by individual union members; but it was generally agreed that thiswould merely destroy the authority of trade unions in respect oflocal action by their members. It would be desirable, however, to draft the relevant clauses in the Bill with a view to minimising thedifficulties which would be created in relation to trade unions.As regards prices, difficulties would arise in respect of theexisting statutory arrangements for the approval of the prices ofcertain commodities, including steel, coal, gas and electricity. the relation between these statutory arrangements and the new proposals in the Bill needed further consideration.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thegeneral view of the Cabinet was that legislation on the lines proposedin C (65) 141 should be introduced in the new Session of Parliament.The First Secretary of State should now discuss further with theLord Chancellor, the Attorney-General and the Lord Advocate the issues raised during the discussion, particularly the various possible ways of mitigating the inevitable consequences of the Bill as regardsoffences and penalties in relation to the trade unions. The first secretary of State should then undertake informal discussions withrepresentatives of the TUC and the Confederation of BritishIndustries (CBI), which would include consideration of the provisions for enforcement. Thereafter the Ministerial Committee on economic development and, if necessary, the Cabinet should be given a further opportunity to discuss the precise provisions of the legislation.The Cabinet (1) Approved in principle the proposed legislation on prices and incomes summarised in Annex A to C (65) 141, subject tofurther consideration of its provisions in the light of thepoints made in their discussion.(2) Invited the First Secretary of State, together with the LordChancellor, the Attorney-General and the Lord Advocateto examine in particular the proposals in relation toenforcement and penalties.(3) Invited the First Secretary of State to arrange for thenecessary legislation to be drafted and to discuss itinformally with the Trades Union Congress and the confederation of British Industries.(4) Invited the First Secretary of State to bring before the ministerial Committee on Economic Development theprovisions of the Bill as they emerged after the further discussions contemplated in Conclusions (2) and (3) above
CC 57 (65)Exchange 6.   The Postmaster-General said that the Exchange TelegraphTelegraph Company operated a news-gathering service in a number of fields, insome of which it worked jointly with the Press Association. Whileits operations as a whole were profitable it had decided to discontinueits Parliamentary and general news service because they were running at a loss. This would result in the Press Association acquiring an effective monopoly in home news agency work and would makeabout 70 people redundant, of whom half were journalists.Intervention by the Government could only be justified on theground that the public interest was involved. This could not be sustained on the ground of redundancy and the Board of Trade took the view that this was not an appropriate case for reference to the monopolies Commission. The Post Office was concerned with theprovision and maintenance of facilities to permit goodcommunications and in 1934 had signed a Licence and Agreementwith the Exchange Telegraph Company to regulate relations withthem. It appeared that this agreement gave the Post Office power toacquire that part of the Company which was covered by the licence.There were various ways in which the services in the field ofParliamentary and general news hitherto operated by the Companymight be maintained, but it was too early yet to determine theappropriate solution. In these circumstances the best course wouldbe to enter into discussions with the Company to ascertain theposition more clearly and to consider whether and if so how it mightbe possible to maintain the services in question.The President of the Board of Trade confirmed that this wouldnot in his view be a proper case for reference to the monopolies commission, since only in the most limited sense would a monopolyresult from the action contemplated by the Company. Parliamentarynews, for example, was provided not only by the Press Association,but by a large number of newspapers. It would therefore be premature to enter into discussions with the Company on the possibility ofmaintaining their services in these fields and further time was required to consider the position.In discussion the Cabinet were informed of a report that the universal News Service had expressed its intention of expanding itsservice to cover those which were being abandoned by the ExchangeTelegraph Company. It was the general view that if this report wereconfirmed there would be no justification for government intervention. In such circumstances the best course might be for thePresident of the Board of Trade merely to make further enquiries into the position and to inform Parliament in answer to a question that afternoon in the House of Commons that he was doing so.The Cabinet Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Postmaster-General (i) to enquire into the position which would obtain in the running of Parliamentary and general news services
as a result of the withdrawal of the ExchangeTelegraph Company from these fields and of theindication that the Universal News Service mightcorrespondingly expand their services;(ii) to consider in the light of these enquiries what, if any,Government action was required.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,4th November, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
