<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/155/0 images: 1-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet. (\ /,SECRET..   FOREIGN COUNTRIES REPORT.No. 41.   20fch April 1921.con.tknts;Austria.-The Anschluss Movement. Brazil. The Sanctions.   Customs Duties.   &apos; China. Notes on the Political Situation. France. Proposed Tax on German Imports.Greece. Hew Ministry.    Situation in Albania and Epirus.   Reimposition of the Press Censorship.   Reconciliation of. Officers.Himgary--Ministerial Crisis.Italy.-Dissolution of Parliament.   The Porto Rosa Conference,   The z^greemeut with the Angora Government.Japan. The Turkish Prisoners of War.Persia. Provincial Government.   The Persian Gendarmerie.   Negotiations with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.Poland. The Silesian- Question.Russia. Siberia : Declaration of the Constituent Assembly. Serbia. General Wrangel&apos;s Army.Turkey. Opinion of the Deputies on a lasting Peace,    Expenses of the Sanitary Administration.United States of America. The Knox. Resolution.SO  27-3     120  4.21A
FOREIGN  COUNTRIES  REPORT.AUSTRIA.The Anschluss Movement. On 15th April Mr. Linclley reported [No. 108] that on the previous day the Chancellor had summoned the French, Italian and British representatives and informed them that the anschluss plebiscite in Styria and Salzburg had been postponed. The question, he said, was more serious in Tyrol, where the agitation was very strong. The Government was doing, and would continue to do, their best to cope with the situation.The Trench Minister had then informed the Chancellor officially that if the Austrian Government did not put an end to these manoeuvres the French Government would stop all relief from Trance and restore the Reparation Commission in its entirety. The Chancellor expressed gratitude for that communication, which, he said, would strengthen his hands.On I8th April Mr. Lindley telegraphed [No. Ill] the following translation of the communication made by the French Minister to the Minister for Foreign Affairs : In the event of the Austrian Government permitting on their territory the consummation (aboutisseinent) of the plebiscite manoeuvres encouraged by Germany, France will be obliged to abandon the support which she is giving to the Austrian Government and to maintain under the control of the Reparation Commission the liens which she holds under the treaty of St. Germain.Mr. Lindley added that he had asked the French Minister exactly what this threat meant in the event of the plebiscite being carried out in Tyrol, as seemed most probable, and. that he had replied that nothing would be done and France would continue to support the scheme of relief under the auspices of the League of Nations. He (the French Minister) considered that the threat had been useful, as the plebiscites in Styria and Salzburg had been given up and the Austrian Government had loyally and openly placed themselves on the basis of the treaty; and added that the French Government had made representations at Munich against the open propaganda carried out there in favour of tire Tyrolese anschluss.On the same day, .1.8th April, he also telegraphed [No. 110] as follows : A demonstration in favour of anschluss took place yesterday. About 15,000 persons participated and demanded from the Chancellor that immediate.preparations should be made for a plebiscite on the subject in all Austria in the middle of May.The Chancellor deprecated the demonstration as untimely and asked for patience. In a month&apos;s time it would, be clear what help was forthcoming from the Entente, and the question of an application to the League of Nations could then be considered. To, raise the question now was to embarrass Germany and to jeopardize a favourable solution of the Silesian and West Hungarian questions.Some of the demonstrators&apos; then tried to approach the French Legation, but were kept back by the police. The same thing happened before the Italian Legation, and, after the demonstration, before the German Embassy, which, owing to the proximity of the British Legation, produced a few hoots for our benefit; the crowd dispersed in pouring rain.BRAZIL.The Sanctions.  On 6th April Sir John Tilley telegraphed [No. 52] the following translation of an announcement in that day&apos;s Jornal do Gommereio : It is known that the allied conference which met in London at the beginning of the year laid down that goods imported from Germany by Entente countries might be paid for half in cash and half by means of a document which should be equivalent to a receipt given to the German Government for monies paid by them as reparation. This was equivalent to placing a burden of 50 per cent, on German exports, already heavily handicapped by a series of measures which, sometimes without conferring counter benefits on. the world in general, or even on the victors of the Great War, were hindering the commercial recovery of the defeated country.The decisions reached, by the conference not being of an obligatory nature, Germany, through her Minister accredited to Brazil,&apos;enquired, as to the opinion of our
&quot;Government with regard to them, and was informed in reply that Brazil did not intend to avail herself of them, or, in other words, that German imports to Brazil would be paid for entirely in cash.&apos; Our Legation at Berlin now reports that the liberal and level-headed reply of Brazil, an allied Power, has given rise to lively satisfaction, and the German Govern-ment has from that moment considered the possibility of abolishing of its own accord.^all taxes on Brazilian coffee. We neither asked nor begged for this-conipeusation, which augments the importance of the sound act of political economy with which Germany, conquered and afflicted, saw fit to respond to our disinterestedness.Customs Duties. On 16th April Lord Ourzon instructed [No. 5.1] Sir John Tilley -as follows : We take strong exception to the .accord by Brazil of lower rates of duty to any-country in regard to any commodity, seeing that goods from Brazil are admitted into the United Kingdom at the same rates of duty as goods from any other foreign-country, and: in the case of many important Brazilian exports, rubber, meat, grain and cotton, are admitted free. Nevertheless, as far as the practical effect of Brazilian preferences is concerned, much of the grievance felt by United Kingdom exporters would be removed if the Brazilian Government gave an assurance that the duties leviable on cement, paints, varnishes and rubber goods from the United Kingdom would be reduced to the level of those imposed on such goods of United States and Belgian origin, and that no further preference would be accorded to the United. States, Belgium or other countries in regard to these or any other articles withoutibeihg extended also to the United Kingdom.CHINA.Notes on the Political Situation.- On 5th April this intelligence report was telegraphed [No. 147] by Sir Beilby Alston : The tension between Stui-Yat-Sen&apos;s radicals and Chen-Chiurig-Ming&apos;s provincial -democrats of Canton continues to increase.There are indications of a grouping of the Yangtze provinces under the Hankow military governor, in opposition to the Fengtien and Ohihli factious, which still dominate Peking.The Chinese forces are being completely driven out of Mongolia, and the impossibility of any effective attempt to reconquer that country in the present divided -and bankrupt condition of China proper is becoming apparent.Local hostilities have broken out again in Szechuen and Kueichow.The central Government still profess to believe in the possibility of the early -convocation of the new Parliament, but the elections have so far been confined to the provinces controlled by the Fengtien and Chih.li factions, and public opinion is more likely to find expression in the first place through the provincial assemblies.The financial situation is again becoming acute with a corresponding increase in rumours as to the intentions of the military leaders, which provoked the issue on -3rd April of (? Manehus) denying the stories of the impending restoration of the monarchy.FRANCE.Proposed Tax on German Imports. On 12th April Lord Hardinge reported [No. 195] that it was becoming increasingly clear that the French. Government would experience great difficulty in inducing Parliament to accept the Bill regarding the 50 per cent, tax on German imports. At the financial commission of the Chamber .yesterday, 31 members out of 44 being absent, the proposal to examine the Bill in detail was only adopted after a long discussion, by three votes to two; eight abstaining; -and the &quot; reporter &quot; of the Bill has to ask the Government for further explanations before any progress can be made. The opposition was based on the almost universal feeling in France that the adoption of the measure by this country would severely handicap French commerce (which has urgent&apos; need of certain classes of -German goods) without any sufficient corresponding advantage.Lord Harding recalled the fact that M. Briand had definitely undertaken that as from 1st May the proceeds of the tax would be pooled in the common ^reparation account and distributed among the Allies according to the percentages settled at Spa last year. The French Government were therefore under a certain -obligation to make their views prevail and the Bill become law.
GREECE.New Ministry-owing  Sth April Lord Ministry had been, formed : M. GounarisM. Baltazzi -        -        -M. TheotokisM. StaisM. Taaldaris:M. Protopapadakis -      . -M. Zaimis   -Granville reported [No. 168] that a new:- President and J ustiee.- . Foreign Affairs.- -   -   War.- -   Interior.^   Communications.- Finance.- Education.Situation in Albania and Epirns. On .1.2th April Lord Granville telegraphed? [No.-172] as follows : . 1 asked the Minister for Foreign Affairs this morning for any information he-could give me regarding the situation in Southern Albania or Northern Epirns.He said that, having definite information of the persecution and ill-treatment of Greeks by Albanians, they had sent an officer to.complain to the Albanian authorities, and threaten that Greece would have to take active steps to protect these people if the persecution continued.There were rumours of an Albanian concentration of troops near the Greek frontier, the figure of. 6,000 to 7,000 being given, but the Greek Government had no-positive information. It was certain that the Albanian and Bulgarian comitadjis were in communication, which caused anxiety, but he did not himself think that there-was any immediate danger. There were between 6,000 and 7,000 Greek troops in Epirns, which he hoped were enough to deal with any danger which might arise. In reply to a question, he assured me that the Greeks would not move first, at least for the present.Reimposition of the Press Censorsltip.--hord Granville telegraphed [No. 1.73] on 14th April that a royal decree had been issued reimposiug the censorship in order to-prevent the publication in the press of false news from the front.The measure was submitted to the Chamber and met with considerable opposition as being a return to the Venizelist system, but was accepted, on the Government promising that it should only apply to news and not to comments.Reconciliation of Officers. According to a telegram [No. 274] sent by Sir Horace-Ruuibold on 15th April, General Harkigton has been informed by the Greek military mission that a complete reconciliation between Venizelist and Constantinist officers has practically been reached, and that the reinstatement of the former may be expected at once.He was also told at the same time that the weak response made by the Greek subjects in Constantinople to mobilization was due to defects in the machinery for this, which was now being remedied.HUNGARY.Ministerial Crisis. Mr. Holder reported [No. 104] from Budapest on 13th April that the ministerial crisis which had been simmering ever since the resignation&apos;of Dr. Crratz, due to the difficulty the Prime Minister found in selecting a new Minister for Foreign Affairs and in filling the now long vacant portfolio of the-Minister of the Interior, had come to ahead that day when Count Teleki tendered his resignation to the Government.His Highness had accepted this resignation provisionally, but it was hoped that some modus vivendi might be found at the last moment to prevent Avhat was otherwise bound to.be a long and serious Cabinet crisis.Telegraphing again [No. 105] two days later, he said that the crisis had been solved by the Governor definitely accepting the Prime MinisterVresignation, ,and appointing Count Stephen Bethleu as his successor. The Ministry remained practically the. same; but the vacant portfolios of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs and the Ministry of the Interior had been filled by Count Nicolas Banffy and Count Gedeon I?aday respectively.
ITALY.Dissolution of Parliament.-On Sth April Sir George Buchanau reported JjSio. 115] as follows :-The royal decree dissolving the present Parliament and providing for a general election on .15th May and the assembling of the new Parliament on llth June was. signed yesterday. It is prefaced by a long exposition of the reasons for the dissolution, the principal of which are the annexations of the new provinces and the change in foreign and domestic conditions since the last election, resulting from the treaty of Rapallo, the withdrawal of Albania, and the steps taken to reduce the deficit of the budget. The programme of the Government^ future policy is also outlined ; the foreign policy will be principally guided by economic aims, such as securing new zones of commercial, influence, new markets, new sources of raw materials and new fields for emigration.The Porto Rosa Conference. On 15th April Sir George Buchanan telegraphed [No. 125] the following proposed programme for the Porto Rosa conference which he had received from the Secretary-General of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs : (1) Method of the prohibition of import and export of certain categories of goods.Methods of licensing, customs clues and tariffs. (2) Method of promoting exports by Government action. (3) Method of distinguishing prices iu internal and external trade. (-1) Examination of the possibilities of suitable, compensation conventionsbetween the succession States concerning exchange of the most essentialproducts such as provisions, coal, coke, petrol, minerals and metallurgicalproducts.(5) Agreements for the fac.iliiat.ion of postal, telegraphic and telephonic com-munication between the/succession States. (6) Agreement for the amelioration of financial and banking relations (transportof money, method of cheques, free use of deposits, traffic in bonds, banking &apos; : &apos; &apos; affairs, &amp;c).(7) Agreements for the settlement of Austro-Huugarian State and private debts. (8) Agreements for the conversion of the crown from its old value into the newAustro-Hungarian values at a fixed rate of exchange. (0) Agreements for the acceleration of goods and passengers from one State&apos;toanother by the suppression of the present restrictions on transport betweenneighbouring States and transport in transit across intervening States. (10) Agreements about the possibility of transporting goods from one (two groupsundecypherable) States to another across the territory of a third. (LI) Agreements concerning (ft) Waggon circulation ;(b) Allocation of engines and waggons to be agreed to by the richer states in favour of the poorer ;(c) Repair of rolling stock;. (d) Restitution of waggons to private owners and free circulation of these waggons (tank-waggons, waggons of hiring companies). Sir Horace added that the Secretary-General in communicating the above programme bad stated that it was only a rough draft&apos; and that he might have to touch it up here and there. A similar programme had been submitted to the French Ambassador, and they had agreed to have a further meeting with the Secretary-General when they had received the views of their Governments.The Agreement with the Angora Government. The following, telegram [No. 127] was sent by Sir George Buchanan on 16th April: The Secretary-General, acting under instructions from-the Minister for Foreign Affairs, called my attention yesterday to a Reuter telegram in which it. was stated that though His Majesty&apos;s Government were not in a position to say whether the French version of the Italian agreement with the Angora Government was correct, it was clear that the agreement had an importance far beyond that of a simple economic convention owing to the fact that Italy had undertaken to assist Turkey to recover Smyrna and Thrace.The Secretary-General protested that the above telegram placed a false inter-, pretation on the terms of the agreement and represented Italy as having promised to afford Turkey material assistance, whereas the Minister for Foreign Affairs had only 27-3   - B
engaged to support Turkey&apos;s claims in the Supreme Council. This constituted no new departure, as his Excellency had always been in favour of restoring Thrace and Smyrna to Turkey,, and&apos;even had he never concluded such an agreement he- would have continued to press his views with regard to the revision of the treaty of Sevres on the allied Governments. The attitude which he had adopted in this matter was riot, as he had explained in the Chamber, inspired by hostility to Greece, but&apos; by the conviction that a prompt and definite settlement of the questions at issue would be to the advantage of the latter.JAPAN.The Turkish Prisoners of War (F.C.R., xl., p. 6 (under &quot; Greece &quot;)).-On 18th April the following telegram [No. 87] was sent to Sir Charles Eliot: The Japanese Ambassador here has invited us to support the request addressed by his Government to the Greek Government that the steamer Heiinei Maru, with Turkish prisoners, should be released and the prisoners surrendered to the Turkish Government at Constantinople, in. return for guarantees that they will not be ,allowed to join the Kemalist forces. We are replying that we desire.to maintain a strict attitude of neutrality towards the Greco-Turkish hostilities, and therefore regret that we cannot see our way to intervene as proposed, nor can we ourselves&apos; accept any responsibility for the prisoners if they are landed.at Constantinople; but that if the Greek Government accept the Japanese proposal, we shall be happy to transmit it to the Turkish Government through His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Constantinople.;[A similar telegram was sent to Sir Horace Rumbold.]PERSIA.Provincial Government. On 7th April Mr. Norman sent; [No. 207] the following-information : The Prime Minister lately instructed the officer commanding the gendarmerie in Khotrassan to keep a careful eye on the governor-general, who, being exceedingly corrupt, is naturally hostile to the new order of things although outwardly he accepts it.On 2nd April the officer commanding, without orders from Teheran, arrested the ^governor-general and a considerable number of local officials and notables, arid has also sent a force to Kuchan to arrest the governor there. The Prime Minister, while realizing that such action by the military creates a. dangerous precedent, recognizes that in the present case the results must be good. He has accordingly approved it, and will appoint a new governor-general.The present governor-general, who is brother of Vossuk-ed-Dowleh and. a capable official, is unpopular with the gendarmerie because he has embezzled their pay, along with most of the revenues of the province, which, although a 3&apos;ich one, remits no money to the central Government. -In continuation of the above, Mr. Norman telegraphed [No. 217] on 8th April as follows : His Majesty&apos;s consul-general at Meshed reports that several governors and all the leading landowners are now also under arrest or in hiding, and that the financial agent, a. Belgian, is demanding from them sums of 150,000 tomans and 50.000 tomans downwards, which doubtless represent their debts to the government. The gendarmerie, police and military are co-operating wholeheartedly, and 2,000 additional gendarmes are being enlisted.-:; Further action in the provinces by the Persian Government was reported [No. 228] by Mr. Norman on 1.5th April :-Ever since, the. coyip iTebatal 20th February 21st February Prince Sarim-ed-Dowleh, Governor-General of Kermanshah, has&apos;been suspicious of the attitude of the new Government towards him;.. His uneasiness was caused chiefly.by the news of the arrest of his relations at Teheran and. the knowledge that, his own*record:- was-not clean,, and was increased by the Prime Ministers demand for an account of his share in the sum of 131,000Z. drawn, in advance from 2,000,000?. loan..On 30th March I learnt that he was delaying his resignation only-until..die could -receive my advice and assurances that it would be safe for him. to come to Teheran. I was obliged to reply that .1 could give him no such assurances, for I knew the Persian Government had claims against him, and could not doubt that they would proceed against him as they had proceeded against Farman Farma. vOn 12th April I received through His Majesty&apos;s Consul at Kermanshah a message to the effect that the Prince was prepared to pay any sum to which the Persian
-&quot;Government was justly entitled as well as any reasonable sum as a gift if they were . in need of money, to come to Teheran, and.to submit to arrest if necessary.   He begged that lie might not be compelled to submit to the indignity of arrest in his own district. ^ -        -Before this very fair offer could be conveyed to the Prime Minister orders for the Prince&apos;s arrest had been unfortunately issued, and on 12th April he and his deputy . o-governor, Mufakhkbam-Al-Mulk, were seized by the officer commanding the gendar-merie when they assumed the military governorship of the town, and despatched towards Teheran. The step appears to have been clumsily managed, and the PrincVs guard fired on those (group omitted) had been ordered to arrest him, killing six unarmed kalhors of Amir Azam&apos;s party and wounding several, innocent people. The Prince and deputy governor are now on their way,to Teheran under an escort&apos; -commanded by Amir Azam. .......I. have already reminded the Prime Minister that the Prince is: under our protection, and will take in his case steps similar to those which 1 have taken on behalf of Farrcan Farma and his sons. The Prime Minister has promised that &quot;the demands which the Persian Government will make on the Prince will be equitable, and that as soon as they have been met His Highness will be allowed to leave the -country.   No other members of the late Ziles Sultan&apos;s family have been molested.The Persian Gendarmerie. In a telegram [No. 150] from the Foreign Office on &quot;9th. April Mr. Norman, was notified that the Swedish Minister in London had been informed that Hussein Khan, the Persian Minister in Madrid, had been instructed to proceed to Sweden to engage some 24 officers for service with the Persian gendarmerie. This information had been communicated by the Persian Minister, to whom the Secretary of State had expressed his surprise at such action in view of the past experience of the conduct of the Swedes in Persia. , ,Mr. Norman was requested to point out to the Prime Minister the confusion which, would be likely to result from the employment of diverse nationalities iii the -event of active operations, and to add that, for consequent difficulties, the Persian&apos; Government would only have themselves to thank.In confirmation of the first part of the above, the following telegram [No. 6S] from Sir George Barclay at Stockholm was received on 14th April: The Swedish Govern-ment have received a request through the Persian Minister in London For 25 officers &apos; for the Persian gendarmerie. The Swedish Minister in London has been instructed to ask for full particulars. They also understand that the Persian Government wish -to- employ British officers for the array, Americans for finance, and French for -education or agriculture.&apos;In reply to the Foreign Office telegram [No. 1.50] quoted above, Mr. Norman; telegraphed [No. 223] on 12th April that, as he had received no objection to the; proposal, already reported by him, of the Persian Government to engage Swedish -officers for the gendarmerie, he had presumed the acquiescence of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and had assented to the proposal subject to the condition that the officers to be engaged should be on the active list and free from the faults of Swedes already in the Persian service. , The Prime Minister, lie said, would have preferred to engage British officers, but thought it essential that the gendarmerie should be under neutral officers, as he believed the Russians would object to the presence of Persian troops; under British officers on their frontiers. He anticipated that unless a gendarmerie under officers other than of Russian nationality could be created in the frontier provinces the whole of northern Persia would eventually fall, as in .pre-war-days,, under Russian military control. He argued&apos; that as the gendarmerie, were not primarily intended for service against a foreign enemy, there was no great danger of confusion&apos; being caused by Swedish officers being brought into contact with Our own. :    &apos;&quot;A reply to Mr. Norman&apos;s telegram was despatched [No. 1G2J from the Foreign Office on 15th April, in which it was pointed out that while no objection had been laid against the employment of foreign officers in minor ministries, there had been no expression in favour of the possible employment of Swedes. Attention was called to the report of the Anglo-Persian Commission, in which emphasis had&apos; been laid on the objections to the continuance of the force of gendarmerie on the&apos; score of expense, &amp;c., and in the present impoverished state of the Persian exchequer these objections were considered to be very material. It was also mentioned that the Swedish Legation, in the absence of knowledge of details, held the view that it was improbable that officers on the active list would be allowed to enter the Persian service.4 27-3 G
Negotiations . with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.-The following telegram&quot; fNo. 233] was sent by Mr. Norman on Kith April:-1 presume that the Anglo-Persian: Oil Company have kept you informed of the course of negotiations on which their-representative in Mesopotamia has been engaged since his arrival here with the-Persian Government; with a view to the supply of their immediate financial needs. As a result of these negotiations the Company advanced, on account of royalties-payable at the end of this year, 50,0001. to enable the administration to go on until the arrival of the financial adviser.   The latter has already left Shiraz on his way to-Teheran, ;aud should have been here in a few days from now, but owing to a. recrudescence of brigandage on the road he has to travel by Persian carriage with an? .escort instead of by car, while a bridge near Kum, which forms the only direct;, communication between the capital and Ispahan, has been destroyed by flood, and will take some time to repair, so that, he cannot arrive for at least a fortnight longer.The Persian Government, therefore, urgently require, to enable them to carry on the Administration and meet necessary military expenses during that time, a furtherc 75,000L and the Company&apos;s representative has to-day telegraphed to his board their-request for this sum.I understand that on certain conditions, for the fulfilment of which the financial3 adviser&apos;s presence is necessary, the Company are prepared eventually to advance all&apos; the remaining 350.000Z.; but as regards the sum now in question, which is required by 19th April, it is impossible to await his:.arrival.POLAND.The Silesian Question.-Mi\ Max Muller sent the following telegram [No. 190], from Warsaw on 13th April: The Minister for Foreign Affairs informs me that the Polish Government are-sending to London, Paris and Rome deputations consisting of t? merchants) and: business men, to endeavour to influence, in favour of Poland, public opinion and the? decisions of responsible statesmen on the Upper Silesian questions.The delegates for London, who have been to see me, leave to-morrow evening.The Minister for Foreign Affairs will, in all probability, himself visit the three-capitals on a similar errand.I explained both to his Excellency and the delegates that, in my opinion, it was., rather late to undertake tlie-; task of influencing public opinion in England, though personal interviews with responsible statesmen might have some effect...The Minister for Foreign Affairs was evidently under no illusion as to the smalp chance of obtaining any practical result either through the deputations or even:, through his own visit.RUSSIA.Suikria.Declaration of the Constituent Assemhly-On 9th April M: Knisinochekoff,. Minister of Foreign. Affairs of the Far Eastern Republic, telegraphed to Lord Curzon a copy of the declaration which the Constituent Assembly of the Far Eastern Republic-had addressed to all the nations and governments of the world as follows : The two and half years of heroic struggle by the revolutionary people of the&apos; Russian Far East against the hated regime of the usurping atamans and their adherents has ended in a complete victory of the people.Owing to tiie international situation, and with a view to preventing the Far East from becoming a permanent base of warfare against Soviet Russia, the people of the Russian Far East have given up their sacred wish of an immediate reunion with their mother country Russia and have entered upon the course of establishing within the territory of the Russian Far East an independent sovereign republic.The independence of.this republic was recognized by the socialist federated&apos; republic of Russia in its Act of 14th May 1920.To form a Government and to enact the fundamental laws of the republic, the; Constituent Assembly was elected by the free will of the people of the Far Eastern-Republic expiessed by universal, equal, direct and secret ballot and by proportional&apos; representation with no distinction of nationality, sex or religion. &apos;Considering the creation of such a Government- as will secure the full lights of? the people by promoting stability and the complete freedom of the creative initiative&apos;-
D1of all citizens in the territory of the Far Eastern Republic to be its momentous task, the Constituent Assembly hereby solemnly declares to the entire world that:- - : - (I) The whole of the territory of the former Empire of Russia east of the River Selenga and Lake Baikal to the Pacific Ocean, including the regions of Baikalia, Zabaikalii, Amur, Priamur, the Maritime Province and the northern part of Sagalien Island, is hereby declared under the jurisdiction of the independent sovereign -democratic State, the Far Kastern Republic.(2) By virtue of an agreement the demarcation line between the Soviet Republic of Russia and the Far Eastern Republic is drawn as follows: From the River Selenga from its exit from Mongolia to the administrative boundary of the former Selengiu.sk Baieguzinsk and Verchene Udinsk counties, following the boundary of these counties to Lake Baikal, then eastward through the middle of Lake Baikal along the old boundary between the Yakutsk, Zabaikal and Amur districts to the watershed between the Rivers Kiran and Pesma, along the watershed&apos;of these rivers to the shores of the Okhotsk Sea and the Cape of Mejeland, including all the islands south of the Cape of Mejeland.(3) The sole masters exercising the sovereign rights within this territory are the people who inhabit it, and consequently the presence, of an armed force of a foreign power in their territory or interference by a foreign power with the internal affairs of the country is not only regarded as an encroachment upon, the rights of the Russian people in the Far East, but as an .ac&apos;t of gross violence and usurpation and. as a violation of fundamental international rights. . ,(4) All the treaty rights of the former Empire of Russia in the leased territory of the Chinese revert to the Government of the Far Eastern Republic, and are, therefore, subject to revision conjointly by the Governments of the Far Eastern Republic, the Socialist Federated Soviet Republic of Russia and the Republic of China.(5) Hereafter the supreme power in the territory of the Far Eastern Republic must belong to the people and no one else.(6) The form of government, the foundation of which the Constituent Assembly has been called to lay, will rest on the. principles of real democracy and self-government ensuring the sovereignty of the entire population and the irrevocable rights of the toiling majority whose will has been expressed directly through their representatives, elected according to the principle of universal, direct, equal and secret ballot and with due consideration to the principle of proportional representation, guaranteeing the rights of the minority.     . V .(7) Considering the individual self-assertion of the community and the free expression.of initiative, whether by individuals or groups, as a necessary condition of the development of the country, the Constituent Assembly, by abolishing all class distinction and privileges, guarantees all political freedom to the population such as personal * immunity, freedom of the press and speech, of meeting, union, strike, conscience and movement.(8) Corporal and capital punishment, the remnant of the old regime, are hereafter abolished.(9) Having set upon the peaceful reconstruction of the economic and political life of the country, the Constituent Assembly declares that the civil strife has ended and that all political offences are forgiven by the decree of amnesty, which the&apos; Constituent Assembly is going to issue without delay.(10) The institution of private ownership remains untouched, the Government guaranteeing full immunity to all citizens of the republic as well as to the citizens of foreign countries who may come to live there. The limitation of the rights of private property may be extended only in the interest of the general public and only in cases, provided by law. ., ;(11) Land being the vital force of the entire population, the natural resources of land and water are hereby declared the property of the people and therefore cannot become private property.&apos; Pursuing the economic policy of the open door and equal opportunities for foreign industry and. trade and endeavouring to resume economic relations with other nations on a basis of mutual exchange, the Government of the Far Eastern Republic will take every possible measure to make the terms appealing&apos; to foreign capital and foreign initiative for the development of the natural resources of the country without violating the sovereign rights of the people of the Russian Far East and the laws for the preservation of the rights of the workmen. &quot;,(12) All small national minorities in the territory of the Far Eastern Republic&apos; are hereby granted the right of autonomy which is considered as a necessary measure
for the independent development of their national capacity. On the basis of firm insistence upon their sovereign rights and by their incessant efforts to establish themselves oil peaceful principles, the people of the Far Eastern Republic will build their relations with neighbouring nations upon the foundations of mutual under-standing, respect, confidence and peaceful co-operation.. The Constituent Assembly continues its task with the belief in the creative power jpf the revolutionary people of&apos;the Ear East and in their readiness to defend their rights-and their peaceful labour.SERBIA.General WmngeVs Army.-On. 14th April Sir Horace Rinnbold reported [No. 2C6] that he had been informed by the Serbian representative that there was a good prospect of the Serbian Government taking 20,000 men of General Arrange!&apos;s army in the immediate future; the Serbian Government required, workmen and would, for instance, take ail the engineers in the army. The Serbian representative thought that the majority of the men selected would be Cossacks and that some of them would be used as frontier guards on the Albanian frontier.TURKEY.Opinion of the Deputies on a lasting Peace. Sir Horace Rum bold reported [No. 2-18] on 6th April that the deputies were agreed that the independence and future of the country could be secured by respecting the following principles, which represented the maximum, sacrifice which could be made to obtain a just and lasting peace, and that the continued existence of the Ottoman Sultanate and system could not be otherwise assured :--(l).;The fate of Ottoman territories peopled exclusively by Arab majorities and occupied by enemy troops at the time of the armistice, must be settled in accordance, with the free expression of the will of the local populations. Parts of the Empire, whether within or outside the armistice boundaries, inhabited by a moslem Ottoman majority, the constituent elements of which are united by. religious and cultural bonds, common ideals and mutual regard for each other&apos;s rights and social conditions, form a whole which cannot be divided in fact or in law.(2) In the case of the sandjaks of -Kara, Ardaha and Datum, which, on being left free, were re-united to the mother country by a popular vote, a further free popular vote can be taken if required.(3) The juridical status of Western Thrace must be determined in accordance with the views of the inhabitants expressed with full freedom.(4) Constantinople, capital of the Caliphate and the Sultanate, and the&apos; Sea of Marmora must be assured against all danger. Subject to this, any decision agreed upon between Turkey and ail the Powers concerned will be valid.(5) The rights of minorities, as defined in treaties between the Entente and certain other Powers, will, be recognized, in the confidence that moslems in the neighbouring couutries will enjoy the same rights.(6) As Turkey requires, like other Powers, full independence and freedom in order to evolve a sound administration and to develop economically, all restrictions on her political and financial development are rejected. The (? Turkish Governments) settlement of proved debts shall not be contrary to these principles.Expenses of the Sanitary Administration. On 18th April Sir Horace Rumbold. telegraphed [No. 281] that as the French Government had decided to cease, after the present month their monthly contribution of 25,000 francs to the expenses of the Turkish (&apos;? sanitary) administration, and. the British, and Italian contributions must (&apos;? consequently) also cease at the same-time, (? the possibility of) finding some other source of revenue to supplement that derived from the sanitary dues&apos; was under -consideration.UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. The Knox Resolution. On 14th April Sir Auckland; Geddes reported [No. 221] that on the previous day the Knox resolution had been introduced in a modified form providing for the termination of the state of war with both Germany and Austria-Hungary, but reserving all rights under the treaty of Versailles. All German property now held by the United States Government was to be retained until Germany should -have ratified the treaty, satisfying the United States claims since 31st July .1914. The-, last three paragraphs of the original resolution were omitted.

</content>
</cab>
