<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/155/0 images: 53-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]96Printed lor the Cabinet.iSECRET.FOREIGN COUNTRIES REPORT.No. 47.  13th July 1921.Contents.Afghanistan. Treaty with Persia.   Mission to the United States. Albania.-The Frontier Question.   Serbian Movements. , Argentine. Mission to Peru.Austria. The Question of Financial and Economic Reconstruction. China. Miscellaneous Intelligence Notes. France. Foreign Policy.Germany. Adjournment of the Reichstag.   The Budget. Silesia. The Situation.Greece. Turkish Prisoners.   The lsmid Incident.Italy. New Cabinet.Morocco. Tangier.Persia. Russian Influence. South Persia Rifles. Treaty with Afghanistan. Peru. Centenary Celebrations.Poland. Situation in Silesia.   Commercial Convention with Rumania. Rumania. Commercial Convention with Poland. Russia. Message from M. Chicherin. Serbia.-Serbia and Albania.Turkey. Prisoners of War.   General Harington and Mustapha Kemal. United States of America, The Anglo-Japanese Alliance.SO  30-2     120 7.21
FOREIGN  COUNTRIES  REPORT.AFGHANISTAN.Treaty with Persia. The following message from the Afghan Envoy at Teheran to the Afghan Envoy at Simla, was transmitted^ at the request of the latter, to Sir Henry Dobbs, our representative at Kabul, for delivery to the Foreign Minister there:  &quot; Our treaty with the Persian Government has been signed to-day before noon in an excellent way.&quot; This was reported by the Viceroy of India in a telegram [934 S.] dated 23rd June, received 28th June.[See also under &quot; Persia.&quot;]Mission to the United States. Sir Auckland Geddes telegraphed [No. 472] from Washington on 11th July that he had been informed by the State Department that the ostensible reason for the visit of the Afghan Mission was the establishment of an Afghan Legation at Washington. The matter did not appear to interest the Department very deeply.ALBANIA.The Frontier Question. On 4th July Mr. Eyres telegraphed [No. 19] from Durazzo that the Albanian Government had requested, that the frontier question should be referred to the foil meeting of the League in September, at the same time protesting against the League&apos;s refusal to discuss the matter on account of the Ambassadors Conference having taken it up. The Albanian Government based its demand on its fear of Italy, and the Italian Minister had informed them that they must settle outstanding questions if they wanted the support of his Government. Albania is willing to settle these matters; but nothing can be done until the demand for a naval base at Valona has been abandoned by the Italian Government.Serbian Movements. On 5th July Mr. Eyres reported [No. 20] that Serbian troops had occupied all the Gashi and Krasnich district as far as the River Drin ; and that it was feared they might occupy Puka. It was stated on good authority that a detach-ment had been sent to Fani to support Marka Joni, who was enrolling troops with money presumably. (? the Serbian Governments).ARGENTINE.Mission to Peru. Mr. Macleay telegraphed [No. 101] from Buenos Aires as follows on 5th July : The appointment of Monsignor Duprat as special ambassador to the Peruvian centenary celebrations was sanctioned by the Senate and confirmed by decree yesterday. A vice-admiral, a general, two civilian and. two ecclesiastical secretaries will make up the mission which is proceeding by 6ea in the Argentine cruiser San Martin. &apos; A squadron of cavalry regiments is being sent in a naval transport to take part in the festivities in Lima.The Norwegian, Swedish and Danish Ministers here who have been appointed to represent their respective Governments at the centenary celebrations are leaving to-day for Peru via Chili.AUSTRIA.The Question of Financial and Economic Reconstruction. On 4th July Lord Curzon sent the following telegram [No. 399] to Sir Auckland Geddes in Washington: At the conference of Ambassadors held in Paris on Friday, 1st July, the question, of the financial and economic reconstruction of Austria was discussed. There was. agreement in principle on the following points ; -(1) That the British, French and Italian Governments should jointly request the-United States Government to agree to the suspension of its liens on Austrian assets in respect of relief bonds until 1st January 1941, on the understanding that all other liens in respect of both reparation and. relief bonds are similarly suspended.
(2) That the United States Government should be asked not to raise objection to the participation of private American capital in the reconstruction of Austria.(3) That the American Government should raise no objection to the appointment by the Finance Committee of the League of Nations of an American, member on the Austrian committee of control.The Italian Ambassador was unable, under present political circumstances in. Rome, to express the full adherence of the Italian Government.The release of liens on the basis of the financial plan prepared by the finance committee has now been definitely agreed to by the majority of the Governments concerned, and the Committee has been assured of the participation of Sweden and Denmark &quot;and almost certainly of Norway and Holland in the temporary advances. Other countries are also expected to participate. Little difficulty is expected in -obtaining the release of liens by all the other countries concerned if the American -Government will announce its agreement. In particular such announcement would solve at once such difficulties as remain in regard to Italy.The plan for Austrian reconstruction has thus been brought up to the point where it is ready to be put into execution if the United States will release its liens and allow United States capital to participate. There has already been undue delay owing to Italy&apos;s attitude for the last six weeks. It would be foolish to conceal the fact that further delay will jeopardize the whole plan, and its failure would entail not only the loss of a very promising opportunity for international co-operation in the economic reconstruction of Europe, including the financial assistance from Scandinavia, &amp;c, -already promised, but would also lead to the final collapse of Austria, the results of which would be inconceivably disastrous both politically and economically.Please take all possible steps in concert with your French colleague, who is receiving a similar communication, to secure the definite adherence of the United States Government within the next few days. A delay of more than a week may well prove fatal.To this Sir Auckland Geddes replied. [No.-461] as follows on 6th July : I have discussed with the Secretary of State the matter of the suspension of the United States liens on Austrian assets in respect of relief bonds. The United States Government is wholly in favour of agreeing, to such suspension, (? but has not) got the legal power to do so and will not have such power until the bill now before Congress -empowering the Secretary of the Treasury to deal with foreign debts and foreign credits becomes law. It is improbable that the bill will pass without some amend-ment, but what changes will be made in. its machinery is unlikely to be foreseen. In the meantime the United States Government can do nothing except express its benevolent intentions.The United States Government has no objection and will raise no objection to the participation of private American capitalists in the reconstruction of Austria.The Secretary of State does not like the idea of an American being appointed by any committee of the League of Nations to the Austrian committee of control or to any other body, but f anticipate that this objection will be removed without much difficulty if Congress gives the United States Government power to suspend liens.I have been in consultation with my French colleague, and neither he nor I can suggest any steps other than those we have taken to persuade the United States to take immediate action. The real fact is that Congress, like the mass of the American people, is suspicious that Europe is inclined to believe it is being hoodwinked. All the talk of co-operation with Europe by well-meaning persons finds as yet little echo in the average American mind, and the United States Government is engaged in a - difficult task to persuade Congress to give it the powers necessary to make arrangements (?for) debts (?to be settled1) even on a business, let alone a charitable, basis.1 shall telegraph if anything is done to expedite the grant of power to the United -States Government to deal with such matter as liens.CHINA.Miscellaneous Intelligence Notes. Sir Beilby Alston reported [No. 259] as follows from Peking on 4th July :-The military governor of Fengtien is using his new appointment as commissioner of Mongolia to establish his own position in &apos;one group undecypherable) territories,
4jmd to extort more money from the central Government, but shows little sign of attempting to deal with the Mongolian situation.The military governor of Shen-si has not yet been ousted by the Chih-li troops, and the whole position of the trio of northern inspectors-general has been weakened by the mutinous outbreak at Ichang and Wuchang, which have discredited the-military governor of Hupei and his (? claim) to dominate the Yangtze provinces.Hostilities have broken out between Kwangtung and Kuangsi, and if the successes of the former continue the central China provinces may consider the moment opportune to unite with the southern provinces under the common banner of the province (group undecypherable) recently raised by Chekiang.FRANCE.Foreign Poi/c?/.-Telegraphing [Nos. 435, 438, 439] on 30th June, Lord Harding reported that the Foreign Affairs Commission of the Chamber of Deputies had adopted the following resolutions : (1) Germany. The Commission of Foreign Affairs counts on the Government to-ensure that none of the military or economic sanctions adopted in March and April, in regard to Germany shall be abandoned before the complete execution of the obligations in view of which they were applied.(2) Silesia. The Commission again draws the attention of the Government to the necessity of settling with the smallest delay the question of Upper Silesia in conformity with the stipulations of the treaty of Versailles, which contemplates the division of that province according to the result of the plebiscite by communes, taking into account the wishes expressed by the inhabitants as well as the geographical and economic situation of the districts concerned.(3) Middle East-The Commission considers that French policy in the East should aim at the re-establishment of peace, and that in consequence, after the refusal by the Greek Government to accept the arbitration of the Allies, France can, under no-pretext, lend that Government financial or military assistance of any kind whatsoever,, direct or indirect.The, Commission, in presence of the projects aiming at the establishment of the-Emir Feisal and the Emir Abdullah in Mesopotamia and Transjordania, reminds the Government of the hostility constantly displayed by these two emirs towards France, and draws attention to the difficulties which would be created by the realization of these projects.GERMANY.Adjournment of the Reichstag. The following telegram [No. 354] was sent by-Lord d&apos;Abernou from Berlin on 8th July : The Reichstag adjourned yesterday till 6th September.The closing debates have tended rather to strengthen the Government, which has two clear mouths to complete its programme of new taxation. It is surprising how little hostility has so far been expressed to the very drastic measures of financial reform, which have been proposed.I had a long talk with the Chancellor yesterday. He seemed generally hopeful,, but said nothing of salient interest. He leaves to-day for Breslau, where he is to-address a meeting of 12,000 people on the political situation.The Budget. This summary of the Budget, the figures being paper marks except where otherwise stated, was telegraphed [No. 360] by Lord cTAbernon on 9th July : -Expenditure : 131 milliards, of which 12 are for local expenditure.Revenue : Actual 48$- milliards anticipated, and when new taxes are in force for 1922, 80 milliards, for later years 80 to 100 milliards.These estimates do not include any result or modification of the coal tax.The expenditure of 131 milliards includes 12 milliards for local expenditure, as stated above.   It also includes : -(a.) a subvention of 19 milliards to railways and the post, which should gradually (V disappear).(b) 14 milliards food subsidy and various allocations, which should also disappear.. &quot;(c) 5 milliards for sundry  indemnities   to German  subjects, which should disappear after this year.
(d)19 milliards for the armies of occupation and commissions of control, whichmay be susceptible of reduction, (e) 33 milliards for reparation, which are supposed to represent the approximatevalue of 3&apos; 3 milliards of gold marks. The item of 3&apos;3 milliards will fluctuate with different factors, notably the rise or fall of exchange.It will thus be seen that while one cannot speak of solvency or of an assured future, the prospect is by no means hopeless provided that foreign credit is available to tide over the early years and provided Herr Wirth carries his programme without, essential reduction.Silesia.The Situation.- Mr. Max Midler telegraphed [No. 336] as follows from Warsaw on 9th July:-The Polish Government has addressed a note to the French and Italian Ministers and myself stating that the insurrectionary movement has been successfully liquidated, and complaining that the Polish population in the pacified districts is deprived of any effective means of protection against the numerous acts of violence on the part&apos;of the Germans.The Polish Government fears that these incidents may again arouse public opinion, and requests us to urge our Governments immediately to instruct their representatives at Oppe]n to expedite the organization of a police force such as would inspire confidence in the population.My colleagues are telegraphing in same sense to their Governments.GREECE.Turkish Prisoners. On 6th July Lord Granville reported [No. 377] that the-Minister for Foreign Affairs had assured him that the Greek Government were most anxious to get rid of the Turkish prisoners by any solution which would ensure their not going to reinforce Kemal; they had offered to release them in a neutral port, or to send them to Constantinople, provided that the allied High Commissioners would undertake to prevent their reaching Kemal; and they had also offered to release at once the women and children and the members of the Red Crescent, but the Japanese Government insisted on the release of all or none.He thought that the suggestion of sending a ship to Keratsini was good, and. promised to discuss it at once with, the officials of the Ministry of Marine.The Ismid Incident. This telegram [No. 396] was sent from Athens by Lord Granville on. 11th July :  The Minister for Foreign Affairs informs me that stringent enquiry is being made as to the events at Ismid; that according to information received so far Circassians and Armenians were solely responsible, although lie is prepared to believe that individual Greeks may have joined them ; that the troops were outside the town fighting the Kemalists; that a naval detachment was-sent to restore order, and succeeded pretty well after great difficulty ; and that the Moslem chief of police, who with some four thousand (? Moslems) accompanied the evacuated Greek refugees, lias expressed his admiration and gratitude, for the behaviour of Greek troops.He promises me a full report as. soon as received.ITALY.New Cabinet.  On 3rd July Sir George Buchanan telegraphed&quot;[No. 267], as follows : Signor Bonomi has succeeded in forming a Government with the support of the Catholics and groups of the Left consisting of Liberal Democrats, Social Democrats and Reformists. The Socialists will probably abstain from active opposition, but will not collaborate in any way or support. He may win over (group uhdecypherable)s of the Right. Active opposition will come from the Nationalists, the Fascisti, the Slavs, the Germans and the Communists. In the most favourable circumstances the new Government will only be able to count upon some 300 votes in the Chamber, so its position cannot be very secure.30-2 B
On 4th July and following days he telegraphed [Nos. 272, 27.5, 280] a list of the new Cabinet: Signor Botiomi, Piesident of Counciland Minister of Interior. Marchese  della   Torretta,  ForeignAffairs. Signor Girardini, Colonies. Signor Soleri, Finance. Signor De Nava, Treasury. Signor Gasparotto, War. Signor Bergamasco, Marine.Signor Corbino, Public Instruction. Signor Di Rodino, Justice. Signor Micheli, Public Works. Signor Beneduce, Labour. Signor Mauri, Agriculture. Signor Belotti, Commerce. Signor Raineri, New Territories. Signor Giuffrida, Posts and Telegraphs.The following telegram [No. 273] was also sent by Sir George on 4th July:  Signor Belotti belongs to the Liberals of the Bight, but his inclusion does not signify that Signor Bonomi has succeeded, in enlisting the support of the parties of the Right, who have decided definitely not to collaborate though not to go into opposition.The Government should be able to count upon a firm majority of 70 in the Chamber, while a number of other deputies are not irreconcilably opposed.The appointment of the Marchese della Torretta is said to be well received, and it is believed that the Nationalists and Socialists will adopt a tolerant attitude towards him.   The Catholics have given Bonomi wholehearted support.An interesting point is that Signor Beneduce has been a close collaborator of Signor Nitti, and his inclusion is considered a good move on Signor BonomPs part, as he would have been dangerous in opposition. Signor Giuffrida, a Social Democrat, is also a follower of Signor Nitti.The Catholics hold three portfolios (Justice, Public Works and Agriculture) ; the Liberal Democrats three (Finance, Treasury and New Territories); the Social Demo-crats three (Colonies, War and Posts); the Reformists two (President of the Council and Labour); the Minister of Marine and the Minister of Public Instruction are Senators, but have always been Liberals.The Ministry contains several good men from the practical point of view; but the opinion is generally expressed that it cannot be long lived.s    MOROCCO.Tangier [F.C.R., xlvi, p. 7].--The following telegram [No. 437] was sent from Paris by Lord Hardinge on 30th June : Some stir has been created here by the publication of the news that the Spanish Government sent in a note to the French Government on 27th June, protesting against the concession for port works at Tangier, granted by the Sultan of Morocco to the International Syndicate on 2nd June.According to the Paris press the Spanish communication was made here, but I learn on enquiry of my Spanish colleague that the note was handed to the French Ambassador at Madrid.There is a tendency to infer from the coincidence of the Spanish protest with the King of Spains visit to London that His Majesty&apos;s Government are behind it. The Temps however, in an apparently inspired paragraph, observes : &quot; It does not seem that the Spanish claim should be supported by England,&quot; and states the French ease as follows :  *The sovereignty of the Sultan over Tangier is complete, and. subject to no&apos; restriction as regards (? right to) grant concessions. The Spanish Government recognized the validity of the French argument by finally communicating with the Sultan&apos;s representative at Tangier in order to obtain the necessary authorization in recent incidents regarding the Ar Viol-Tangier cable and the &quot; Madrague.&quot; The port concession does not in practice involve any sacrifice of Spanish interests ; the French share in the syndicate is raised from 30 per cent, to 50 per cent, by the treaty of Versailles, which assigned to France the former German share; and all European colonies at Tangier, including the Spanish (Chamber of Commerce (sic)), approve the granting of the concession in the interests of the future of the port. The Spanish representations therefore seem to be platonic and cannot obstruct further friendly negotiations inspired by a keen desire to reach a solution harmonizing the Sultan&apos;s sovereignty, the special rights of France, and Spanish interests.
On 6th July Mr. Wingfield reported [No. 141] from Madrid that the Spanish press continued to urge the necessity for the settlement of the whole question of Tangier by means of. negotiations between Trance, Spain and Great Britain which France had so long been postponing. France, it was feared, would be disinclined, to pay clue attention to Spanish protests unless these were supported by His Majesty&apos;s Government, but the Spanish press was unwilling to believe that such protests would not be forthcoming since British rights and interests were also affected by the Sullan&apos;s action.PERSIA.Ruszian Influence [F.G.R., xlvi, p. 7.]-In a telegram [No. 357] dated 30th June, Mr. Norman stated that the facts of the Russian Ministers activities were universally known and undisputed in Teheran, although there were obvious difficulties in the way of obtaining documentary evidence, and objections to the use of oral evidence as supplied to him. Among matters not already reported by Mr. Norman in his despatches, were the information that the late Persian Prime Minister had been warned by the Russian Minister against co-operation with Great Britain; that the latter had told the Minister of War that he was prepared to finance the Cossack division on the sole condition of the removal of all British officers. The Russian Minister had also endeavoured to dissuade the Prime Minister from opening the Mejliss, on the ground -of some of the deputies being under British influence; and he had further adopted a threatening demeanour against the Persian Government should they think fit to -employ British officers and officials. Other facts connecting the Russian Minister with the various communist groups and affording evidence of their combined activities in exciting hostility against us were reported by Mr. Norman, all of which he -considered conclusive evidence of the attitude of the Russian Soviet Government.On 1st July Mr. Norman telegraphed [No. 360] that he had told the Financial Adviser that he deprecated any unconditional advances being made, on account of his deep- distrust of the present Persian Government. Money for the Cossack -division, which is certain soon to become a Russian instrument, would undoubtedly be misappropriated. Every reform initiated by the late Government had been annulled, and honest officials replaced by anti-British robbers. The Government on their own authority had dismissed British officers from the Cossack division, although they disclaimed power to take over the South Persia Rifles without the consent of the Mejliss. False accusations against the British legation had been published in a newspaper without reprimand. The Russian Minister was in close and constant touch with the Minister of War, and together they were likely- to over-throw the present Government.in order to appoint a Cabinet more servile to Russia and more openly hostile to us. Mr. Norman concluded by saying that we could no longer hope successfully to oppose Russian influence in Northern Persia, and that it was unlikely that we Bhould be in a position to do so until the people had experienced Russian Soviet administration and realized what it meant.&apos; South Persia Rifles [F.C.R., xliii, p. 6]. On 1st July the Secretary of State telegraphed [No. 268] to Mr. Norman his decision on the future of the South Persia Rifles. He had some difficulty in believing that the Persian Government, seriously entertained the idea of taking over the force, and &apos; was disposed to think that they were trading on the maintenance of the force being in our essential interest. Not-withstanding the possible dangers to British interests which had been pointed out by Mr. Norman, and the eventual expense of disbanding the force, further subsidies were out of the question. It was doubtful if the Persian Government would agree to the force being financed by the Bank of Persia or the Anglo-Persian Oil Company; moreover, encouragement could not be given to a British firm to finance a military force in a foreign country, in the circumstances it remained only to inform the Prime Minister that the funds at Mr. Norman&apos;s disposal must be devoted to the immediate disbandment of the force.Lord Curzon expressed his appreciation of the work done by the officers and non-commissioned officers, and desired Mr. Norman to convey a personal message to that effect to the Inspector-General and his command.Treaty, with Afghanistan. Mr. Norman telegraphed [No. 379] on 9th July as follows : A treaty with Afghanistan was signed 22nd June at Teheran. The gist is as follows :- Article 1.-Friendship. . Article 2. The usual privileges of diplomatic representatives. 30-2 C
POLAND.Situation in Silesia.- See under &quot;German)-.&quot;Commercial Convention with Boumania. -See under &quot; Rumania,RUMANIA.Commercial Convention with Poland.-On 2nd -July Mr. Millington Drake-telegraphed [No. 138] as follows : The commercial convention with Poland was signed yesterday by the Polish representatives and will be signed by M. Take Jonescu on his return here on Tuesday.The convention contains the most-favonred-uation clause - and establishes details-of reciprocal transport and transmission facilities.Poland is granted facilities for establishing &quot;commercial bases&quot; in the Danube ports, and it is stated that Poland, will probably choose Galatz and Braila, the one for imports and the other for exports.The convention is for one year, and will (? continue) (? automatically) until-denounced, (? when) three months&apos; notice must be given.Telegraphing [No. 147] again on 5th July Mr. Millington Drake reported that M. Take Jonescu had informed him that he had signed the convention, and that tire-actual text would not be published for the present; ifcontained no special stipulations other than those published in the press. M. Take Jonescu had added that the-. convention would have to be ratified by the Rumanian Parliament, and this could not be done during the present session. Ratification, could not, therefore, take place until the autumn.RUSSIA.Message from M. Chicherin. -The following message was telegraphed from Moscow on 11th July: Des organes de presse autorises de clivers pays publient la nouvelle que le-groupement de certaines puissances, denomme Ligue des Nations, aurait cre-e un - commissariat special dans le but de venir en aide materiellement aux emigres-&apos; riisses.   A cet effet 11. est propose a tous les gouvernements interesses de prendre-,^des decisions sur 1 &quot;utilisation des fonds du gouvernement russe a 1&apos;etranger.   Les gouvernements qui formeht le groupement, denomme Ligue  des Nations,  out 1&apos;intent ion cVemployer sans l&apos;autorisntion du gouvernement russe les sornmes qui.Article 3. Their respective subjects will be well treated and under the protection, of their representatives.Article 4. They will be amenable to local laws without interference by diplomatic or consular representatives.Article 5.&apos; The right to appoint consuls in important towns and commercial, centres.Article 6. Exemption of each other&apos;s subjects from military service and other-duties binding only on natives. -   Article 7. Extradition of non-political originals.Article 8. Agreements to be concluded as soon as possible in regard to trade-tariff posts and telegraphs.Article 9.---In case of war between one party and another State, the other party will not assist the enemy.Article 10. Disputes to be referred to arbitration in accordance with inter-national rides.Article 11. The treaty is in two copies in Persian.Article 12.--Ratification at Teheran or Kabul within three months or sooner if possible.PERU.Centenary Celebrations. See under &quot;Argentine.&quot;
TURKEY.Prisoners of War. On 8th July Mr. Rattigan telegraphed [No. 50-1] the following summary of Yusuf Kemal&apos;s reply to the Aga Khans message to the Minister for Foreign Affairs at Angora respecting the exchange of prisoners of war.The agreement signed by Bekir Sami was contrary to the previous decisions and instructions of the Grand National Assembly. The agreement was consequently unacceptable; firstly, because only a part of the Turkish prisoners of war were to be liberated ; secondly, article 2 thereof was contrary to Turkey&apos;s sovereign rights ; and, thirdly, Turkey was thereby deprived of all opportunity of safeguarding the lives and interests of its remaining prisoners of war.On the other hand, the Grand National Assembly has authorized the exchange of all Turkish prisoners against all British prisoners, and has already released a certain number of British subjects to correspond with the Turkish prisoners already released.After an appeal to the Aga Khan to recognize the justice of the Turkish attitude in the matter, the message concludes with thanks for his Highness&apos; intervention and the statement that happiness lies only, in the full and entire recognition of her independence within the limits outlined in the National Covenant.General Karingcon and Mustapha Kemal.&apos; On 5th July Mr. Rattigan telegraphed [No. 490] the following translation of the message sent by General Harington to Mustapha Kemal: I understand through Major Henry that your Lordship desires to lay before me certain views as one soldier speaking to another. If this is the case, I am authorized by the British Government to proceed in the battleship Ajax to Ineboli or Ismid to meet you any day convenient to you, and I am quite prepared to discuss the situation openly and frankly if you so desire. I am authorized to listen to your Lordship&apos;s-views and to report them to the British Government for their consideration. I. am not empowered to negotiate or speak on behalf of the British Government, but I am authorized to hear any views which you may wish to express. The proposed inter-view should take place on board the British battleship, when your Lordship will be received appropriately and enjoy full liberty until you laud. If you are in agreement please telegraph the date and hour which will suit you in order that the necessary; arrangements may be made.Telegraphing [No. 495] again on 7th July, Mr. Rattigan reported the receipt of-Mustapha KemaTs reply, which was thoroughly unsatisfactory, although polite.   He-lui appartiennent pour, secourir ses ennemis. Le Gouvernement de Russie, auquel appartiennent en realite les sommes visees, proteste energiquement contre 1&apos;acte arbitraire et de violence des divers gouvernements qui s&apos;enrpareraient a son insu,. et sans son consentement, des foncls lui. appartenant. Le peuple travailleur russe, clont la volonte est representee par son gouvernement sovietiste, a seul qualite pour; disposer des fonds qtii sont les siens. Le gouvernement sovietiste de Russie declare, en consequence, qu&apos;il ne recounaitra la legalite d&apos;aucun emploi qui serait fait de ses fonds a fetranger sans son consentement expres, et sa volonte ofnciellement exprimee. II- est a plus forte raison inadmissible que ces sommes soient employes a des buts hostiles aux gouvernement russe. L&apos;expeiience de ces dernieres annees a demontre que les organisations des emigres russes actuels a 1&apos;etranger sont toujours des groupements coutre-revolutionnaires depensant les fonds a leur disposition pour provoquer des attaques contre le territoire des republiques sovietistes. Tout secours distribue aux emigres russes par 1&apos;l&apos;entremise de leurs organisations devient, fatalement, en realite un secours accorcle a des agissements hostiles aux republiques sovietistes; Ce n&apos;est que par Tiutermediaire des organes attitres de la republique russe a 1&apos;etranger que des secours de ce genre peuvent etre distribues sans devenir une arme pour nuire a la securite de cas republiques. Le gouvernement russe proteste, done, formellement, non seulement contre 1&apos;utilisation de ses fonds a son insu, mais encore contre 1&apos;emploi qu&apos;en veulent faire les puissances formant le groupement denomme Ligue des Nations, qui est un acte hostile envers la republique russe.SERBIA.Serbia and Albania. See under &quot; Albania.&quot;
&quot;began by saying that the interview had been sought by General Harington, and that he was prepared to enter into pourparlers on the basis proposed by the latter&apos;s agent, Major Harvey. The Angora Government would negotiate on the understanding that, the national claims were recognized, those claims being entire independence and the complete liberation of national territory. The recognition of the principle demanded in the Angora note is out of the question, and consequently the incident was regarded as definitely closed.UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.The Anglo-Japanese Alliance. Sir Auckland Geddes telegraphed [No. 460] as follows: . In the course of conversation the Secretary of State informed me that up to to-day he had not communicated in any way with Mr. Harvey on the subject of the United States Governments attitude with regard to the Anglo-Japanese alliance nor had he passed on to him the suggestion of a possible tripartite declaration of policy of agreement with regard to the Far East.. I suggested to him that I. thought it important that Mr. Harvey should have some information on the subject of what the United States Government were thinking on such matters, and, after he had explained at length why he had not kept Mr. Harvey informed, he declared he would telegraph to him immediately.Mr. Hughes again told me quite plainly that the renewal of the Anglo-Japanese alliance, or the establishment of any special relations between the British and the Japanese, would, create an unfavourable impression not only in the mind of the American people but in that of the United States Government.I said that I hoped Mr. Harvey would be informed clearly of this fact, so that there might be no possibility of misunderstanding. ^ .

</content>
</cab>
