<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/195/16 images: 269-272</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 41 COPY NO      g&apos;)2 May 1977CABINETPAYMENT FOR VACCINE DAMAGED CHILDRENMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Social services. My colleagues will already have seen the memorandum (CP(77) 39)by the Chairman of the Home and Social Affairs Committee (HS) about theCommittee&apos;s recent discussion of a scheme of payments for those affectedby vaccine damage.2. I am convinced of the need for a very early statement accepting theprinciple of a scheme of payments, and I append a draft statement for theCabinet&apos;s approval.3. The main reasons for my view are these:i. The campaign for compensation is doing the Governmentconsiderable harm politically and will continue to do so until wecan get it called off.    It is undermining our reputation as a caringGovernment, and many of our supporters do not understand why weare resisting a claim which they see as obviously just.    There waswide agreement in HS that we should eventually have to givecompexcoation for vaccine damage.    If that is so, political considerations strongly favour an early announcement of our acceptance of the principle, rather than waiting for many monthsduring which the pressure will build up and the vaccinationprogramme be further damaged.ii. Unless the campaign is halted I do not think that thevaccination programme can be got going again.    It is vital that itshould be, especially because of the possibility of an outbreak ofpoliomyelitis this summer - an event for which many people wouldlay responsibility at the Government&apos;s door.    I accept that it is mainly the safety of vaccines which weighs with parents, and I hope to be able to give reassurance about this later in the month in thelight of the paper which is being prepared by the Joint Committeeon Vaccination and Immunisation.    But a constant barrage of1
of criticism over the compensation issue keeps fresh in people&apos;sminds the idea that vaccines can cause damage;  and while thisbarrage continues it will be impossible to restore confidence inthe vaccination programme.    Moreover, the Government&apos;acceptance of the principle of payments would help to dispose ofany suspicion that we believs that the number of cases of vaccinedamage to be greater than we have admitted.iii. I believe that even if a scheme of payments for vaccinedamage had in the event to be introduced in isolation it would bepossible to keep it as a special case and to avoid repercussionselsewhere.    The public is already strongly disposed to regardvaccine damage as a special case and we shall be able to make useof this.    We can also argue persuasively that vaccine damage calls for special treatment for public health reasons (in order to preventharm to the vaccination programme), and because, having promotedvaccination, Government has a degree of moral responsibilitytowards any who are damaged by it.iv. The report by officials rightly draws attention to thepractical difficulties which would be met in preparing a scheme.I do not underrate them;  but I do not for a moment believe thatthey are insuperable or that it would prove impossible to produce a satisfactory scheme if we decided that a system of payments wasnecessary.    It has after all been done in other countries.Moreover, although the cost cannot be precisely estimated, itwould clearly be relatively modest, especially if there were weeklyrather than lump sum payments.D EDepartment of Health and Social Security2 May 19772
annex draft STATEMENT ON PAYMENTS FOR VACCINE DAMAGEI am delighted to inform the House that the Government have decided toaccept in principle that there will be a scheme of payments for the benefitof those who are seriously damaged as a result of vaccination.   It will apply to existing as well as new cases.My hon Friend the Member for Stoke on Trent South, together with the Associationof Parents of Vaccine Damaged Children, has played a notable part in drawingpublic attention to the plight of the few children who, tragically, may havebeen damaged by vaccination.   My Ministerial colleagues and I have shared the widespread sympathy theBe cases have aroused.The House will understand that there were good reasons for the Government&apos;sreluctance to enter into a firm commitment before now. As I have explained in the past, this whole subject is being considered by the Royal Commissionon Civil Liability and Compensation for Personal Injury.But the Government has considered carefully the exceptional circumstancesof vaccine damaged children and, in view of the strong case that has beenmade on their behalf and the importance the Government attach to the vaccinationprogramme, we have decided that it would be right to make this clear commitment.It remains the case that the provisions of the scheme, including partictilarlythe criteria which oust be satisfied to establish entitlement, and the nature and the amount of the payments, cannot be determined until we have received and considered the Royal Commission^ Report.   Although it will therefore not be possible for any scheme for payments to be put into effect forsome time, I believe that this advance announcement of the Government&apos;intention will be welcomed by all sides of the House and by the public at large.2 May 1977


</content>
</cab>
