<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/70/0 images: 14-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(li yCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)mm mm mm mm mm mm mm mm mm mm mm m mm france mm mm mm -        m - - m iRESTRICTEDC.(54) 25424th July, 1954THE GENEVA CONFERENCENote by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues the annexedstatement by the Soviet Government on the Geneva Conference which was issued by Tass on 23rd July.A.E.Foreign Office, S.W.1.23rd July, 1954.COPY NOCABINET&quot;On 21st July the Geneva Foreign Ministers&apos; Conference,convened in accordance with the decision of the Berlin Conference, for examining the Korean and Indo-Chinese questions, ended its work.    Asa result of almost three months1 work, agreements have been signed whichwill terminate hostilities in Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia.    These agree-ments aim at solving important tasks connected with establishing and strengthening peace in Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia on the basis ofobserving the independence and sovereignty, the unity and territorial integrity of the three Indo-Chinese states, as stated in the final declaration,approved by the participants of the Geneva Conference.With the cease-fire in Indo-China, possibilities for an economicand cultural rise under the conditions of peace will open before the peoples of Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia, creating at the same time a basis for thedevelopment of friendly co-operation between them and France.Of greatest importance will be the decisions of the geneva conference on prohibiting the setting up of military bases of foreign government on the territory of Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia, as well asthe undertaking by these governments not to enter into any military alliancesand not to let themselves be used for the resumption of military activitiesor with the aim of realising an aggressive policy.    The decision of the geneva Conference on the carrying out of free elections in Vietnam during july, 1956 creates conditions for the national unification of Vietnam inaccordance with the national interests and aspirations of the wholeVietnamese people.
France &apos;s Positive AttitudeThis decision adopted as the result of persistent efforts fromthe democratic states means a defeat of those aggressive forces whichstrove to dismember Vietnam so as to transform south Vietnam into one ofthe places d&apos;armes of the planned new aggressive bloc in south-east Asia.A serious significance also lies in the agreement on the carrying out inCambodia and Laos of general elections during 1955, which, according tothe final declaration, will be held by secret ballot and under observance of the basic liberties.    One cannot but note that the adoption of suchimportant decisions was alleviated by the positive attitude adopted by theFrench Government dictated by the desire to act in accordance with thenational interests of France and taking into consideration the interests ofthe peoples of Indo-China.The results of the Geneva Conference confirm the confidence of the Soviet Government that at the present time there are no suchcontroversial questions in international relations which could not be solved by way of negotiations and agreements directed towards strengtheninginternational security, relaxing international tension and for safeguardingpeaceful co-existence of States irrespective of their social system.    the geneva Conference and its results have shown that important role in thesolution of controversial international problems which belongs to the greatChinese people and their State - the Chinese Peoples Republic.    TheChinese role at the Conference was new evidence of its influence and international prestige as a great power.    The Geneva Conference at thesame time showed once more that the attempts of aggressive circles ofsome States, and primarily the U.S.A., to remove the Chinese PeoplesRepublic from participating in the settlement of the most important inter-national problems are in complete disagreement with the interests of strengthening peace.    The Soviet Government considers that the agreementsreached in Geneva on the cease-fire and the establishing of peace in Indo-China, contributing to the relaxation of international tension, are therebycreating favourable conditions for the settlement of other unsolved importantinternational questions, which bear not only on Asia, but also on Europe,and first of all on such questions as stopping the arms drive and banning the atomic weapon, safeguarding collective security in Europe and settling theGerman problem on a peaceful and democratic basis.     The SovietGovernment declares that, invariably following its peaceful policy, it willcontinue with all determination and persistence its efforts aimed at a successful solution of these questions which undoubtedly would be animportant step on the path of lessening international tension, strengtheningpeace and international co-operation.In spite of the fact that some reservations exist in the agree-ments signed at Geneva, one must not under-estimate the entire importanceof these agreements because of the above-mentioned circumstances, and because it was possible to overcome at the Geneva Conference a number of difficulties which occurred as a result of the attitude adopted by therepresentatives of the U.S.A. who attempted to interfere with the successfulcompletion of the Conference^ work.The U.S.A. did not want, together with France, Britain, theU.S.S.R., the Chinese Peoples Republic, and other states, to take part in thejoint work which has ensured the establishment of peace in Indo-China.The Geneva agreements mark an important victory for the forces of peace and a serious defeat for the forces of war.    At the same time the Genevaagreements signify an international recognition of the national liberationstruggle and the great heroism of the peoples of Indo-China which has beendisplayed in that struggle.
/GThe fact that the Geneva Conference culminated in achieving the agreement among the interested countries, is a new proof of fruitfulnessof international negotiations provided there exists goodwill among theparties, and proof of the possibility of settling important unsolved present international questions in this way.    The Soviet Government welcomesthe success achieved at Geneva in solving the most important task - theestablishment of peace in Indo-China.    The solution of this taskcorresponds to the interests of peoples who are upholding their freedomand national independence, as well as the interests of all peace-lovingpeoples.Side by side with the most important task for the finalpeaceful settlement in Indo-China there also stands the urgent task forthe final peaceful settlement in Korea.    The Soviet Government, like theGovernments of the Chinese and Korean Peoples Republics which hadalready earlier displayed a noble initiative in the cease-fire in Korea, madeevery effort on their part towards achieving a successful decision on the korean question at the Geneva Conference.    However, as is known, the geneva Conference did not achieve positive results on this question inconsequence of the obstacles presented by certain delegations, and mainly from the U.S. delegation.    The Soviet Government considers it an urgent necessity to secure the speediest solution of the Korean question in theinterests of the national unification of Korea and in the interests of safeguarding peace in Asia and the world over&quot;.

</content>
</cab>
