<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/70/0 images: 38-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for. the. Cabinet.   August 1954The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.; 11 isissuedfor the personal use of top S^RfcT -V-,;C. (54) 2633rd August, 1954Copy-No.CABINETTWO-POWER MEETING WITH SOVIET government note by the Prime minister should be glad if my colleagues would consider the enclosed general observations in connection with the telegrams to and from Mr. Molotov already circulated.w. s. c.JO Downing Street, S.W. 1,2nd August, 1954.46583
1. The&apos; purpose of a Two-Power -Top-Level meeting with the SovietGovernment on neutral ground is to bring about a Top-Level Three- orFour-Power meeting in London. For this latter a gesture of goodwill isrequired from the: Soviet. This might either take the form of (!) anundertaking by the Russians to accept the Austrian Treaty on whichall the Soviet; terms-have, already been met, or (2). to participate ina co-operative spirit in President eisenhower&apos;s attempt to deflect&quot; tnerrno-nuclear power to peaceful and productive aims instead of world deductionwhere it is now heading. Either or both of these symbols of goodwillmust be forthcoming to give a chance of the United States being persuaded to accept the idea of the Head of their State and Government to participate in a Top-Level Conference at the present time (i.e., in the next few months).I believe; that($tie Russians would welcome the Top-Level meetings in theaforesaid order. Their reasons may well be:  [ First, that they are still far weaker in the tnermo-nuefear sphere, includingespecially power of hostile delivery.:; Secondly, that it is their interest and their wish to have an era of greatly;.  increased material comfort and prosperity, even though it may be, attended by a relaxation of Communist; theory enforced by policecontrol, ,arid./military&apos;-difciplih6 Testing on riorriial patriotism1.The inter-play of the party and military forces is at present intricate. Com-bined as they would be in war or under threat of war, they of coursegive absolute domination throughout Russia and her satellites to theKremlin Government. They are, however, fundamentally diverse, andeven opposed, in character, tradition and mood. Given a prolonged period of peace, or at least of &quot; non-war confidence &quot; and easement,one force might correct and modify the other. This process would notperhaps be harmful to the Free World.sh : 3:. These considerations have led me to believe that a (say) twerity years&apos; periodof &quot;peaceful co-existence &quot; although not settling things precisely oh paper, mightwell; create a new era in human thought.and temper favourable to the survival: of individual, liberty and the; healthy,evolution ,of human society^ This hope shouldnot be based on optimism about Communist or Russian good-faith, but only on a correct estimate of Russian self-interest.; : All..this of course has a constant andpowerful ally -in. the. widespread subconscious fear: of destruetidh. which.Sciencewill intensify. ro
PART II

4. Side by side with the above, and potentially and realistically more imminent is the argument which must be present in many American minds, namely:-

We alone have for the next two or perhaps three years sure and overwhelming superiority in attack, and a substantial measure of immunity in defence. Merely to dawdle means potential equality of ruin. Ought we not for the immediate safety of our own American people and the incidental rescue of the Free World to bring matters to a head by a "show-down" leading up to an ultimatum accompanied by an Alert?

5. This could be brought about by a war with China, even though unconventional weapons were not used in the first stage, or at any rate only the atomic. It is my opinion-for what it is worth-that the Kremlin would not in their present inferiority of thermo-nuclear power retaliate by opening the Third World War. They would give aid by ground and air forces to China, and in so doing would obtain a valuable hold on large Chinese territories which they have long coveted. At the same time, by boasting that they would not use their thermo-nuclear power (in reality weakness) they would command the moral and intellectual support of European and non-Communist Asian countries. This might so anger the United States that they would feel free to look after their own interests and use their own might in any way they thought fit.

6. If this happens the "show-down" leading up to an ultimatum would probably occur. Two alternatives are possible: first, the World War in which we and Western Europe might well be victims whatever we thought, said or did, but in which the United States would at present time be victors; or secondly, that the Kremlin would give in, yielding the satellites and effective one-sided control of unconventional weapons and armaments generally. The risk of total war would however be extreme and of all the nations involved the United States would suffer the least.

I should be glad if my colleagues would ponder over these issues in priority to everything else.

PART III

7. It is on this background that the comparatively minor procedure that I have proposed should be measured, namely: the Two-Power Top-Level meeting at some half-way house, leading if possible to a Three- or Four-Power Conference in London. It is clear that the Soviets would like this. While we must not be taken in or out-manœuvred, it is a mistake to assume that the Soviet motives are necessarily in all cases vicious, or that what is their natural self-interest is necessarily antagonistic to ours. Their régime is both complex and rigid. The Note proposing the International Conference to explore further their Berlin suggestions, which the leading N.A.T.O. allies rejected on the 7th of May, is in my opinion
f2nd August, 1954.W. S. c.a piece of routine hiachihe-made diplomacy. Having regard to the simple andcordial private telegrams I have interchanged with Mr. Molotov, it is clumsyin its timing. I understand that the Foreign Offices of the three countries towhom it was addressed, Britain, the United States, and France, are now engagedin writing an argumentative diplomatic refusal which may well take three weeksor a month. This delay is not inconvenient to us as it meets M. Mendes-France&apos;desire for an unostentatious pause to enable him to see what he can do aboutE.D.C. French agreement to this would of course greatly aid Dr. Adenauer&apos;sproblems which are certainly becoming more acute. There is also the holidayseason which must be treated with due respect,8. However, I understand that we may count on the Soviet routine Notebeing rejected and out of the way by the end of August. We must then review the situation in the light of existing facts, and my last telegram to Mr. Molotov(August the 1st) was intended to secure us the time and power to do so. these facts affect France and E.D.C., the United States and N.A.T.O., and also Adenauerand Dr. John. Unless a decisive and relevant change in the world situation arises from any of these, the Two-Power Top-Level meeting at a half-way house will stand as the only constructive proposal to an indefinite continuance of the cold war, relieved from time to time by diplomatic grimaces of the kind we have just received officially from Russia.

</content>
</cab>
