<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/70/0 images: 55-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)&quot;- --      -----secret.(54) 270 COPY NO.17th August, 1954CABINETABOLITION OF VISAS FOR GERMANS AND AUSTRIANSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department and Minister for Welsh AffairsFollowing their discussion on 29th July of the for*eign Secretary&apos;proposal that visas should no longer be required for German and Austrianvisitors to this country, my colleagues invited me to circulate a statementindicating the number of Germans and Austrians who had come to the UnitedKingdom in recent years for visits of less than three months (C. C. (54) 56thConclusions, Minute 6).2.        Separate figures for foreign visitors coming to the United kingdom for less than three months are not kept, but the figures given below show thenumber of Germans and Austrians who came to the United Kingdom in eachof the years 1951, 1952 and 1953 for visits not exceeding six months.    Thegreat majority of these visitors were allowed to land for three months orless.    I am also circulating, for comparison, similar figures showing thenumber of French, Italian, Belgian, Dutch and United States visitorsin these years.3.        The figures are:-	1951	1952	1953Germans	40,174	49,577	63,363Austrians	6,648	5,724	7,061French	102,715	99,612	111,979Italians	19,173	19,598	22,482Belgians	45,970	41,001	41,379Dutch	59,689	52,337	56,810United States citizens	120,876	156,658	177,7214.        The Cabinet agreed that, subject to any points Ministers might wishto raise in the light of these figures, German and Austrian nationals visitingthe United Kingdom for less than three months should no longer be requiredto obtain a British visa.    Although an agreement cannot be reached this year in time to affect holiday traffic, the Foreign Office is anxious to make astatement as soon as possible, and I should be grateful if my colleaguescould let me have, not later than 23rd August, any further points whichthey wish to raise.D.M.F.Home Office, S.W.1.16th August, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
