<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/70/0 images: 65-66</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(54) 274 COPY NO..26th August, 1954CABINETMEAT PRICES SINCE DECONTROLNote by the Minister of food the Prime Minister has suggested that I should circulate forthe information of my colleagues the attached copy of a minute sent tohim on 20th August at his request.G. LL-G.Ministry of Food, S.W.I.25th August, 1954.Prime Minister&apos;s Private SecretaryMeat Prices since DecontrolThe Prime Minister has enquired what advice was given by theMinistry of Food about the possible course of retail prices after thedecontrol of meat and for a note on the causes of the unexpectedlylarge rise.When we were considering decontrol the best trade advicewe could get was that the public would not pay more on average thanbutchers were charging under control.    The date of decontrol (5th July)was selected because supplies.of meat normally begin then to increase and it would be unlikely that if prices did get out of hand they would forlong remain so under ^he pressure of rapidly increasing supplies.The Ministry expected, however, that there would be increases inprices of the choicer cuts and of beef but that the poorer cuts andmutton might be expected to fall.    We advised the Economic PolicyCommittee (E.A. (53) 121) that an increase, of 2d. a lb. on beef,producing a 0. 27 point rise in the All Items Index, might be expectedalthough changes in other meat prices would probably average out.The cost-of-living index figures were collected on 13th July,that is only a week after decontrol. At that time wholesale prices infact straddled the old controlled price schedule but retail prices
6sr.showed on average an increase of 4d. per lb. thus producing the rise of1.1 point in the index to which attention has been drawn.There were several contributory reasons(a) The trade sought to increase its profit margins whichhad for long been restrained at levels not veryacceptable to it.(b) Butchers are presenting their meat more attractivelyby trimming bone and fat.     This means they mustcharge more.(c) It is possible that supplies have been less than expectedowing to there being plentiful grass which enablesfarmers to hold stock longer.(d) The imported meat which we have released from stock,although charged out at the same average price as before, has consisted of a higher proportion of betterquality than during the last few months of control.This has raised the general average of what in fact was on the market.Imported meat being released at this time is about a quarter ofthe total.    The Ministry has ample stocks and is endeavouring to adjustsupplies to the level of last autumn when there was evidently enough forthe public at the controlled prices then charged.    To overload themarket would increase the Exchequer liability to deficiency payments under the Agricultural Marketing Act, 1947.    In the first five weekssince decontrol the deficiency payments to producers totalled 3^ millions.    Furthermore, we must conserve our stock becauseseasonally there will be a lean period in the early months of 1955.The Minister of Food therefore proposes to continue thepresent policy of releasing imported meat stocks with caution inaccordance with the best estimates that can be made of the total require-ments of the market, and for the time being to. charge no more on average than the old control level.    From now onwards the home-killedsupply should increase rapidly, with a corresponding reduction inwholesale prices, but the butchers might be able to intercept some ofthis reduction and not pass all of it to the public.    The extent to whichthey might succeed in that depends on the housewife.(Signed) W.J.B. HOFKINSONMinistry of Food20th August, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
