<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/70/0 images: 79-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL25th August.COPY NO.f&quot;   ) 0CABINETBRITISH SO MALI LAND;    BAUD negotiations note by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs; circulate to my colleagues the annexed despatch recordinga conversation with the Ethiopian Ambassador about the Haudnegotiations.A.E.Foreign Office, S.W.1,26th August, 1954.The Ethiopian Ambassador asked to see me today and leftme the enclosed Aide Memoire on the dispute about Haud.     Herecapitulated the history of the dispute, referring to thewartime agreement of &quot;\3kh and the efforts which had been madesince then to reach a settlement.     He continued that the ethiopian Government wished now to conclude negotiations on thebasis of the 1897 Treaty and hoped that we would send outinstructions urgently to our Ambassador so that this could bedone.     It was really important that this negotiation should becompleted before the Emperor paid his official visit here.2.     I told the Ambassador that I was not myself familiar withthe details of this negotiation, but I would look into themand we would communicate further with the Ethiopian Governmentin the course of the next few days, either through him or through you.1-
IMPERIAL ETHIOPIAN EMBASSY,LONDONPRO MEMORIAThe Agreement of 19th December, 19*44, provided that &quot;whilethe war continues, it is not opportune to negotiate a permanenttreaty&quot; and, by its Article VII, Ethiopia agreed to place theterritory of the Ogaden under British Military Administration&quot;in order as an Ally to contribute to the effective prosecution of the war&quot;.     The question of tho Ogaden, therefore,constituted an integral part of the Agreement and was settledon a purely temporary and war-time basis0Since 19u7, discussions for the settlement of the questionof the Ogaden have been pursued on the basis of exchange of territories.     It was the desire of the British Government toobtain water wells and grszing lands for tribes of british somali land, whereas the Ethiopian Government desired a corridorto the sea so as to avoid interminable difficulties with theFrench over the Franco-Ethiopian Railway.     These negotiations have failed.     Over strenuous objection by the Ethiopian Govern-ment, the British Government referred these highly secretnegotiations to the French, with the result that all possibilityof a corridor to the sea had to be abandoned, the French basingtheir objection on the highly invidious Anglo-French-ItalianTreaty of 1906, and the British Government insisting upon thenecessity of recognising a French claim resulting from that so-called Treaty.     In addition, the British Government stated thatany territorial exchange would require a plebiscite.In view of these difficulties and of the unfortunateexperiences of the Sinclair Petroleum Company in carrying onprospecting operations in these areas remaining under british control, notwithstanding the provisions contained in an exchangeof notes appended to the Agreement of 194U,, in view, further,of the fact that the Ethiopian Government have now waited morethan eight years to complete negotiations on this subject andof the fact that the British Government had raised difficultiesin respect to every formula proposed, the Minister for ForeignAffairs, both verbally and by note of 13th May, 195*4-, indicated that the only remaining solution was the one to be sought alongtho lines of the Anglo-Ethiopian Treaty of 1897.Similar delays have been encountered in respect of the negotiation of a general treaty to replace tho temporary war-time Agreement of 19UJ4-.     After waiting for two years, following the close of tho war, tho Ethiopian Government submitted to the british Government a draft proposal.     Article 16 thereofprovided for the return of the Ogaden, which Ethiopia hasinsisted must be a sine qua non of any treaty negotiation.However, more than three years elapsed before any response wasforthcoming from the British Government.     The British proposal,when finally submittod at the end of 1950, was very short anddrafted in very general terms, and apart from leaving asidemany subjects covered in the Ethiopian proposal, providednothing whatsoover on the solution of the problem of the Ogaden.In tho meantime, the Minister for Foreign Affairs constantlypressed for action by the British Government on the treatyproposals and profited by his presence in London at various times during the years 19*4-8 and 191+9 personally to intervene to that end.     Notwithstanding these efforts, Ethiopia wasobliged to wait more than two years before the promised annexeswere forthcoming.     These were immediately examined by the
appropriate Ethiopian authorities who aro still awaiting replies to their comments from the British Govornmento     It was only-after an additional delay of throe years that another text of aBasic Agreement was submitted - only a few weeks before HisImperial Majesty&apos;s departure for the United States of America.This Agreement followed closely the earlier incomplete proposals submitted at the end of 1950 and, in particular, provided nothingwhatsoever on the question of the 0gadeno     This last draft treaty was promptly considered by the Ethiopian Government,notwithstanding the many preoccupations incident to His imperial majesty&apos;s trip to America, and it is still receiving active consideration.In view of tho protracted delays involved in thenegotiations on the Ogaden as well as on a treaty to replace anagreement which, by its terms, was designed to meet certainwar-time exigencies only, and in view of the impossibility of reaching any satiafactory basis for negotiation for the Ogadenother than tho treaty of 1897, the Ethiopian Government feelthat tho time has now come, nine years after the end of the war,and ten years after the signing of the war-time Agreement, toproceed at once to the simultaneous settlement of the questionof the Ogaden and of the treaty negotiations.26th August, 195Uo

</content>
</cab>
