<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/66/29 images: 198-201</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1945.SECRET.CP. (45) 29.Uth June, 1945.CABINET.UNITED KINGDOM MEAT POSITION AND NEEDS OF LIBERATEDTERRITORIES.Memorandum by the Minister of Food.IN CP. (45) 28 the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has drawn atten-tion to the needs of Liberated Areas. The Washington discussions assured to theAllied Countries of North-West Europe reasonable quantities of sugar, fats,cheese and milk products. If internal and sea transport permit there should be noshortage of wheat. Only in respect of meat can it be said that the washington talks failed to provide supplies for the Liberated Countries.2. In the case of meat the problem before the Minister of Production and myself was first to obtain sufficient meat to maintain a minimum level of con-sumption in the United Kingdom and, secondly, to provide supplies for liberated areas. We did our best to obtain both. We only just achieved the former : littlewas left over for the latter.3.   In consequence, it has been necessary for me -(a) to reduce issues of canned meat under the points scheme by 50 per cent.and. consequently, to cut the number of points which a person may usein a month from 24 to 20;(b) to cut down the issue of meat for manufacturing purposes by one-third;(c) to provide one-seventh of the Is. 2d. meat ration in the form of canned corned-beef for 5 months;(d) to cut the bacon ration from 4 oz. to 3 oz. a week;(e) to discontinue all issues of unrationed bacon.4. As the result of these measures the level of civilian meat (and bacon) con-sumption in the United Kingdom will fall from 114-8. lbs. per head (in 1944) to106-7 lbs. per head (for 1945). Pre-war it was 132-9 lbs. per head. Civilians inthe United States, Canada, Australia and New Zealand are all eating meat at ahigher rate than the United Kingdom. The figures for pre-war, for 1944 and1945, are estimated to be : Per head Per head Per headconsumption, consumption, consumption,pre-war. 1944- 1945.lbs. lbs. lbs.United States    .......      134-1 162-9 125Canada   .........       118-5 149 1 135Australia          ......      248-1 208-8 169New Zealand     ......      262-5 230 1925. If, therefore, the Liberated Areas are in a desperate plight for meat theUnited Kingdom is the last country from which they should seek supplies.6. At the Washington talks it was proposed that canned meat should immediately be withdrawn from civilian consumption in the United States,United Kingdom and Canada in order to help the liberated areas. The FTnitedStates were unwilling to adopt the suggestion before the fourth quarter of theyear; they might then make 100,000 tons available (&quot; if it was not required formilitary purposes.&quot;)   Canada was prepared to accept forthwith, thereby making[30048]^/    Copy No.
30,000 tons available for Liberated Areas. We did not adopt the full plan inthe United Kingdom, but the reduction of issues of canned meat under the pointsscheme will enable us to place 25,000 tons in a special reserve.7. The utmost contribution which the United Kingdom could make wouldbe this 25,000 tons of canned meat. If this is disposed of there is no prospect ofany but negligible quantities of canned meat being distributed on points duringthe first half of 1946. I should also have to further reduce the monthly numberof points from 20 to 16. I am unwilling to ask the people of this country tomake a further sacrifice when others are living so much better than they.8. If, however, as a result of a review of our service requirements, which isat present being made, a substantial reduction takes place and if we can get forthis country more meat than previously anticipated either from the dominions or from the Argentine, I will gladly make the surplus available for the liberated areas. This would defer the improvements in our civilian diet, which I long tosee, but it would not have the same depressing and disastrous effect as furthercuts.9. At the end of last year, under strong pressure from the United States,I was prevented from making a long-term meat contract with the Argentine. Iwas promised full diplomatic support both here and from the United States toprevent others (I actually named France and Belgium) from entering theArgentine market.10. There are many ways other than meat supplies in which France,Belgium and Holland need our help. It should surely be possible to bring upon these countries the pressure necessary to keep them from competing with us inthe Argentine without asking our civilians here to be content with even less meatthan they are now getting.11. I regard it as most important that similar pressure should be exertedon the Argentine Government.This matter is under discussion between the Foreign Office and the state department.The sooner such pressure is applied the better.My Director of Meat is on his way to the Argentine.The pressure should not only be to obtain their agreement to deal with theUnited Kingdom alone but also to make their contribution to the United Nationsby making more meat available for export. We estimate that the Argentinesare consuming something not far below 300 lbs. of meat per head per annum.j. j. Ll.Ministry of Food, W. 1,11th June, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
