<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/46 images: 506-527</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.V. G R E T./Iso Paper Ho.p. (40) 66COPY NO. war CAB.IHET.HOSTILITIES WITH RUSSIA:    ATTITUDE of Iran.Report by the Chiefs of Staff CommitteeoOn the 7th Fe&quot;february* the War Cabinet invited us -(a) To review our report on the vulnerabilityof Russian, oil supplies (Paper No.CoO.Sc(39) 142) ,in the light of Tehrantelegram No.  297* and -(&quot;b) To consider what action should he taken tofollow up the suggestions made by the iranian Minister in Telegram No. 29.On the 16th february we also received^ copies ofForeign Office Minutes dealing with the subject,,Iranian Proposals.2o It will be seen from Telegram No0 29 that the iranian Minister for War has approached our military attache unofficially(a) With a request for certain British aircraft to be supplied by the Spring, and -(&quot;b) To suggest that the time had come for iran and Britain to co-ordinate offensive plans for war against Russia.she necessarily stands low in the priority list for supply.Supply of Aircraft to Iran.Iran is only one of our customers for aircraft and*   W.Mo(40)35th Conclusions, Minute 9o/   Annex Ioj6   Annex II and I Ho

Our present policy is to give preference to Turkish andFinnish demands, which are the most urgent.      Our resources are limited and we see no prospect of &quot;being able to supplyIran curing 1940 with the 60 bomber and 20 fighter aircraft,of modern type,  suggested, by the Iranian Minister,Co-ordination of War Plans with Iran.4. We agree with the Foreign Office that two separateissues are involved, i.e.,(i)    the defence of our Middle East interestsagainst pc-impossible soviet ambitions, and -(ii)    the possible use of the Middle East as a base for attacks upon the Soviet Union.5. In regard to (i) above, the main Russian threat toour interests in Iraq, and Iran would iome from propaganda,which might lead to internal disturbances, and air attack. Wedo   norfc regard a Russian land advance through Iran as likely.If war broke out with Russia, we should immediatelyhave to send to Basra a force ad-equate to ensure the securityof the port of Basra and of the A.1.0.0.  oilfields areaagainst internal disturbance and air attack.      If no russian air attacks developed, and internal conditions in the arearemained quiet, there might be no necessity to move forcesinto Iranian territory.     It would., in fact, be desirable toavoid such a course in order to preserve Iranian neutralityuntil such time as we needed Iranian co-operation for offensive operations against Russia.      On the other hand.,if Russian attacks took place or subversive activity wasprevalent, we should move a force into the oilfields area,with or without Iranian consent.     In either event we see no reason to co-ordinate plans with the Iranian Governmentin advance.

6*        Further examination of the offensive action we might -take against Russia has confirmed our earlier opinion thatthe Caucasus is the one area in which Russia is reallyvulnerable and that this area might well be dealt with &quot;by   -air attack.7. The problem of air attack on the Russian oilfieldsmay be summed up as follows:- a)   Air attack on the Caucasian oilfields mustinvolve flight over either Turkish orIranian territory.(b) Our aircraft now in the&apos; Middle East cannotreach the Caucasus from bases in Iraq.;    norare   there any suitable aerodromes, withinthe necessary range, in Eastern Anatolia,where communications are in any caseextremely poor.(c) If, however, we had an advanced base at Tehran,our aircraft could attack Baku.     There is,therefore, much to be said from the air point .of view for obtaining Iranian co-operation.(d) Bomber squadrons in the Middle East tire tohe re-equipped with long-range aircraft,which will &quot;be able to attack the Russianoilfields from bases in Iraq..      This re-equipment is not, however, likely to becompleted until late this year and may befurther,  retarded If operations in Scandinaviadevelop.(e) Iraq, is not yet at war.      If we were to useIraqi air bases for an attack on the Baku area,it might cause internal trouble, in which case we should require some army forces to ensureat least the local security of our air bases in Iraq.8. If, therefore, we had to operate against the Russianoilfields in the near future, we should have to obtain the active assistance of Iran since, in view of our limitedstrength, we are unlikely .to be -able to send out long-rangeaircraft from home., -

9. We fully appreciate the Foreign office view that theprice of Iranian assistance would probably &quot;be heavy, both atthe time of the request and. also after the war.   We- fear, that,whatever the Shah asked for the future, he might at the timedemand the assistance of a British force for the defense ofnorthern Iran..     Y/hether or not such a force could be foundwould depend on the general strategical situation and theforces available.      The future is still too uncertain tojustify us in mortgaging force to help the Shah by embarking on co-ordinated war plans,  as suggested by the IranianMinister.In any case wo are averse to employing British forcesalongside so unreliable an ally as the Iranian, if it can be avoided..     For this reason we would prefer to operate against russia with long-range aircraft based on Mosul, although werealise that this may involve delay in attacking the Bakuoilfields and a consequent strengthening of the Russian air defences.10.        To sum up:-(a) There is no prospect of ou.r being able to sup-plyIran in 1940 with the additional aircraftsuggested by the Iranian Minister.(b) From the purely defensive aspect we do not need to co-ordinate plans, with the Iranian Government.(c) It would be an advantage if we could use Teheranas an advanced air base for attack . on the caucasian oilfields.     Y/e do not, however, wishto pay too high.a price for Iranian good-willand would prefer to &quot;co&quot;hfIne our assistance toIran to air forces.(d) We shall be able to operate against Baku from air bases in Iraq when our forces in the Middle Bastare re-equipped with long-ran^e aircraft.     Thiscourse w.oul;d be preferable to (e) above, butthe re-e^quipment is unlikely to be completed before the late summer.(e) It would always be possible to divert long-rangeaircraft from the Metropolitan Air Force for.operations against Baku.     Such diversion would necessarily depend on the situation in europe and would, in any event, take time.

Re conraendation.lie       For these reasons we do nat advocate the opening up of military conversations with Iran at present and recommend that, at least,, we await a more definite and official request from the Shah.12,-, Finally we point out that in this report wehave only dealt with the two specific questions whichwere remitted to us by the War Cabinet on 7th February(vide paragraph l), We are in the course of preparing a report on the much wider aspects of hostilities withRussia i,e0 , the action which the allies might takeagainst Russia nnd the action which Russia might takeagainst the allies.,(Signed)    C.L.N.  NEWELL.DUDLEY POUND.L,   CARR( for C, I, G,8, ).Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,23rd February, 1940.-D-

ANNEX IqFrom IRANcDecypaer*    Sir R. Bullard (Tehran).1st February, 1940.D.    9030 p.m. 1st Fehruary8 1940.R.    8.53 a.mo 2nd February9 1940.No.  296The Military Attache- called at the house of Ministerfor War 31st January at the request of the latter.    TheMinister unexpectedly gave the Military Attache&apos; completefigures of all kinds of aircraft in Iran and then asked for help in securing aircr aft- from -the United Kingdom which were needed by the spring for defence of Iran though it mightalready be too late.    The Minister said that he had instructedColonel Shaibani to order thirty Wellington bombers and thirtyBlenheim or Beaufort bomberso    Could delivery be expedited?The Minister agreed that Iran needed fighters-and said thatthirty Curtiss machines would probably be bought in theUnited States while Colonel Shaibani had been instructed to try to secure twenty Hurricanes in addition to fifteenpromised by His Majesty&apos;s Government.    The Minister indicated that Italian machines would probably not he bought because offinancial difficulties and of technical objection to theintroduction of another type of aircraft.    When the military attache&quot; suggested the need for a larger proportion of fightersthe Minister agreed, but insisted on the necessity to carry the war into the enemy camp and expressed readyness to sacrifice half of the bombing strength of Iran in order to destroy or damage Baku.    In conclusion the Minister speaking

ANNEX II.Cony of go reign Office., llinutes ou.gelirg.it.- - Te legrgm. ,,No489 ,of 1st February,  $ Q,This telegram raises(l)    the supply of aircraft to Persia, and(8)    the degree of help which His majesty&apos; s Governmentwould he willing to afford the PersianGovernment in the event of the latter&apos;s beinginvaded by the Soviet Union.\7ith regard to (l)  the question is under considerationby the Air Liinistry, but they do not hold out uuch hope ofthe possibility of supplying any planes of either Icind - atany rate as soon as the Persians evidently wish to have then..It is difficult enough to spare bombers in a good cause without trying to find them for Persia where, as the persians had been told over and over again, they must beless effective than fighters.Moreover, their attitude is that if there is. to beany question of using British aircraft for the defence of persia they would much prefer to have them used by theRoyal Air Force rather than by the Persian air force.The position is the same, -incidentally, in regard toother arms,   we are giving the Persians a credit for 5,000*000, but we have had to make it plain that this doesnot mean that we shall have any arms to sell under thiscredit for a considerable time to come.As regards (2) the conclusions of the War cabinet meeting of 7th February have reached the department,showing that the Chiefs of Staff have been asked toconsider: -(i)    their views as to the vulnerability of Hussionoil supplies in the light of this informationas to Iran&apos;s attitudes(ii)    what action should be taken to follow up theMinister of &apos;.7ar&apos;s suggestions.As regards (2) the a attitude of the Service Departmentshas hitherto been, I believe, that there is no hope of our being able to make available the forces necessary for thedefence of Tehran and the Iranian plateau generally and.that, whatever the Persians themselves might do to resist the invader, all the British forces could do would be tohold the roads leading from the plateau to Bagdad andKhuzistan.(where the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company oil-fieldsare situated)  if possible with the concurrance of thePersian Government, but if necessary without it.

The position may he different in regard to air operations, since aircraft could easily fly to northernPersia, could assist fro..: there not only in. the defence of persia hut also in the bombing of the oil-fields at Bakuand could be flown south again if the Soviet land troopsthreatened, their aerodromes.The extent to which such operations are a feasibleproposition is, however, uncertain.   In particular it mightnot be easy to carry out any project of this kind withoutconsiderable improvements to the existing aerodromes (andit must be remembered that if the aerodromes were improved,and subsequent^ captured by Soviet land forces they would facilitate the bombing of the Persian and Iraqi oil-fieldsby the Soviet air force).    In addition,  a considerableground organisation would have to be transferred to north persia and removed again when danger approached.In recent memorandum&quot; I. suggested that if Persiawere the subject of deliberate aggression and stood up forherself to the best of her ability&apos;, we should, for the sake of our prestige, hove to tell the world that although we might not while at war with Germany be able to ensurethe defence of northern Persia we regarded what the SovietGovernment had done as a casus belli    and held ourselvesfree tc take whatever xueasures we might at some future datethink necessary in regard to Persia as a whole:    and I also suggested that if the Persians asked us beforehand in allgood faith what we should do in such a case we should tell them more or less frankl5-r how we should reactsI understand that it is now our p^policy to damageSoviet interests wherever we can and that it would be agood thing if this opportunity of doing so could be exploited.    The trouble is that unless the Chiefs of Staffnow decide that we could react to Soviet aggression muchmore definitely and promptly than has hitherto seemed possible iueV,could accept a commitment to send substantialforces to north Persia directly the soviet forces attacked, and(B)    could meanwhile send arms and aircraft to Persiaon a really substantial scale,the Shah is unlikely to think our reaction very encouragimg.But if our probable reaction would be discouragingto the Persian Government even if they were only thinkingabout the possibility of our going to Persia&apos;s help ifattacked, it would be infinitely more- so, and quite inadequate, if there were any idea, of hoping that the Shallmight on the strength of it let us use his territory incertain circumstances for air attacks cm Baku, even beforePersia itself was attached,    In my opinion there is no hopeof this, unless the Service Departments could fulfil the shah&apos;s desires under both (A)  and (B)  above in the mostcomplete and categorical manner.    Probably we should haveto pay in other ways as well.

There is equally little jrospeot of the Shall allowingus to &quot;build up&apos; -an intelligence service in Persia while Persiais still unattacked, unless the Shah*s needs under (a) and.-(B) can be amply net.   v/e might get him to admit that withoutfull information about Soviet activities we could not give him adequate help when he needed it, and he might undertake toprovide us with such information himself.   But 1 am afraid Iam sceptical of much coming even of this much cooperation.The point is that the.e has been no &quot;change&quot; in the-Shah*s attitude.   It has always been sufficiently obviousthat.he would resist aggression if he could aiid that if wesat still long enough he would turn to us for help, provided this could be given or promised without compromising hisneutrality.   What he no dou&apos;.t wants now are secret discussions and secret assurances (which would, not, of course, have a deterrent effect on the soviet Union unless there wereleakages) .    He would he most unlikely to agree to an openassurance or alliance or any activities likely to offend theSoviet Union without the most explicit guarantee, which weprobably cannot give him.As a general observation I should like to add that the persians are likely to prove the most difficult and possibly even the most treacherous of allies,   he mast avoid puttingOurselves In their hands more than we car. possibly help.   Anycooperation between ourselves and the Persian Government willbe fraught with vexation at every step.    ITor must we expect that it will lead, to anything but further difficulties forour interests in Persia when the immediate danger has passed.There will be no question of gratitude, and although the precise course of events will depend upon the length of theShalif s life and the extent to which the Valiahd can make good,it. can be said that by and large the Persians will resent thefact that they were obliged to rely upon us in their hour of need and hold it against us.,   It is as well that we should realise these things fro... the outset.Apart from the substance of the question, there isalso the question of tactics.    The approach made to theMilitary Attache in Tehran is at present nothing but a feeler.If we do not respjond. too quickly or too fulsomely, the approach is likely to be repeated in increasingly clear terms.Prom man;- points of view it would be a good thing to makethe Shah come to us with a definite request before we respond,The position which we want to establish is that it is Persia,who is asking&apos; us for assistance and not that It is we whoare pressing our assistance on Persia.    It is quite possible,however,, that by the time tho Chiefs of Staff have reported.,a good many days will.have elapsed and a. more definiteapproach&quot; will have been :..ade.    There is therefore no need totake a decision about this point at present.It might save much discussion, later o:.i if the aboveconsiderations were sent semi-officially to the service departments and the latter ashed to take the::.&apos;, into account when briefing the Chiefs of Staff..V/e should no doubt keep the French and TurkishGovernment informed of what we do.(Signed)L. BAGGALLAY.- 9th February, 1940.

ANNEX III.I agree generally with the views expressed in mr. Baggallay&apos;s minute.   I will add: -(l)    In spite of the great efforts made by the Shah itis extremely dou tful whether the Persian Army could seriouslyresist any large scale attack, even with a position like thatof the Elburz mountains to assist them.(2)   As soon as any discussions with the Persians getbeyond a stage at which they can be confined to the Shahand one or two of his ministers it must be assumed that theywill become known to the Russians and Germans.(3)    I think we should be careful not to be toodiscouraging,  thus giving the Shah an e::cuse for taking theline that if no one can help him he has no choise but to makethe best deal he can with the Russians.    He would, certainly not like doing this but it is a possibility which we shallhave to bear in mind.I do not think we can proceed further for the momentuntil we get the views of the Chiefs of Staff on what is actually possible,,(Signed)    H.J.  SEYMOUR.ISth Pebruary; 1940.




</content>
</cab>
