<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/27 images: 130-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;. iW.P. (G)(4l)  27 COPY NO. feS28th February,. 1941aWAR CABINET(fe/^pCRATIOH fiP PRODUCTION^IN TKE^pNSUMER--.i^M-I^^STRIES r*Memorandum hy the Lord President of the Council,,10      The ever-increasing deroands of war production - forman-power, imported materials and productive capacity - canonly he met hy a progressive contraction of business in theindustries supplying purely civilian needs.The industries mainly affected are those covered hythe Limitation of Supplies Orders or hy the rationing of rawmaterials - e0 ga  textiles, hosiery, pottery, hoots and shoesand some others0In these industries there has already been somerestriction of output,  and substantial further restrictionsmust follow   when the new man-power programme &quot;begins to take effect,,    It is these industries which provide the main sources of factory-trained lahour for war production,2C      Left to themselves, many of these industries would seek to spread the reduced output over the whole of the firms normallyengaged in the industry - each factory working on a reduced scale of output with employees Working short time.    This would wasteman-power and productive capacity, and would inflate costs ofproduction,In present circumstances, when we need every ounce of productive capacity, we cannot afford to allow these industries to spread their reduced output on this uneconomic &quot;basis,,    TheLord President&apos;s Committee are unanimously agreed that we shoulddeclare,  and if necessary enforce,  a policy of concentratingproduction in these industries in a reduced number of factoriesworking full time.30      The nucleus of factories left in production should hesettled on a basis sufficient to produce the output required forGovernment orders, the greatest practicahle export trade and theminimum needs of our civil population.      The Government will helpthis nucleus hy safeguarding their requirements of lahour andvmt materials.4n      It is not proposed that the Government should pay any direct compensation to firms closed down in pursuance of thispolicy of concentration.    Each of the industries concerned willhe invited to formulate its own proposals for effecting thisconcentration, and these should include arrangements hy which the firms left introduction will provide some measure of financialrelief, hy pooling of profits or otherwise, for firms which areclosed down.      In calculating this relief,  account will of coursehe taken of any return ohtained hy factory owners through the diversion of their premises to war work,,-1-

The Government, for their part, will assist by taking all measures open to them to help these factories to re-open rapidly when circumstances change.      The Boardof Trade will maintain a list of factories closed down, andthe Ministry of Labour will keep records of workers trans-ferred so that they may be assisted to resume their oldemployment after the war.5.      This policy has been approved by the Lord.Presidents Committee, but it represents a new departureand its implications are so important that it seems desirable that the War Cabinet should be invited to give their covering approval.The President of the Board of Trade has it inmind to make a general statement of policy in the Houseof Commons next week;    and the Board of Trade, in association v/ith the Ministry of Labour, will then proceed to open discussions with representatives of.employers and workers in the industries concernedregarding the means by which the desired degree of concentration can best be achieved.(Intld.)    J.A.PRIVY COUNCIL OFFICE.


</content>
</cab>
