<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/19/0 images: 124-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
          Special Memorandum on the Bohemian Army.   VII*                       (6th July,  1917.)     The news in this morning&apos;s Russian official report,  to theeffect that the Czecho-Slovak brigade has in the recent fightingon the Russian front taken over 3,000 prisoners, draws attentionto the part already played by the  Czech prisoners captured bythe Russians - a part which is likely to  become of increasingimportance.     Arrangements have now been completed for the definiteestablishment of a Bohemian army,  with its own insignia,  flagsand organisation, from among the Czech prisoners in Russia,  andits despatch to theFrench front.    The first contingent  willarrive in France in the course of  the next few days.   It is hopedthat 30-40,000 troope in all will  be sent.   The initiative in thematter was taken by the Czech National Council of Paris,  underProfessor Masaryk.    negotiations  had been pending with the formerRussian government, but Mr.  Sturmer  had  always put obstacles in theway.   Mr. Stefanik, a distinguished member of the  Czech NationalCouncil and a prominent aviator in the French service;  was mainlyinstrumental in completing the arrangements with the Frenchgovernment.   The contingent is to be fully recognised as a distinct &apos;Bohemian army, a French general being assigned to it;  and it ishoped that it will be placed under the protection of all  the Alliesand that military representatives  from England,  Italy and Americav/ill be cent to join its Staff.     negotiations have been conducted between the Czech Council
     The small Czech colony in London,  which is enthusiasticallypro-intente,  placed itself at  the disposal of the War Officeimmediately upon the outbreak  of war.    After an interval  oftwo years arrangements were made for the acceptance  of Czechrecruits, and there lire now over 200 Czechs serving  in the Britisharmy. ,  The two secretaries of the London Czech Committee,  Mr.Kopecky and Mr. Sykora, ore in the R.G.A. and A.S.C  respectively.A special contingent of Czech  volunteers from America was  formedin the Canadian army last  year;  and the first batch  of these,200 strong, arrived in this country just in time to  take partin Paris and the Italian.ambassador in Paris,  for permission tosecure the Czech prisoners now in Italy - 10-12,000 in number.The Italian government has practically accepted the idea inprinciple, and it is hoped that the final arrangements will bemade in Rome next week.     Mr. Stefanik is at present in V/ashington on a similar missionto the American government.   The number of Czech and Slovakemigrants in the United States is estimated by the Czechs them-selves as well over a million.   Of these a considerable proportionare of course American subjects, and they will therefore berequired to join the American army.   But it is expected that noobstacle will be raised by the American government to the raisingof a Czecho-Slovak contingent among the non-naturalised Czechsand Slovaks af the States, and this might produce at least anotherdivision on a moderate estimate, perhaps even two divisions.     The total result  is the gradual creation of an independentBohemian army, which will be, and is intended to be, a realpolitical factor in the movement for Bohemian independence and  thedisruption of Austria-Hungary.
R.W.S.Win the V/hitsunday procession  organised by  the British Workers&apos;League  which demonstrated  before   the   French Embassy.     Meanwhile the  larger Czech colony in  France Was  allowedquite  early in  the war to  form   a special Czech  contingent inthe  French army.   Some of  its members-were decora&amp;ed both bythe Frennh and the   Russians  for&apos;their gallantry, and the   Czechsas a whol&amp; were  publicly thanked  ^oth in  the Senate and in  theChamber for  their  services  to   the common cause.

</content>
</cab>
