<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/19/0 images: 281-282</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
8 3 0 R jS T.,                                                  225Letter from Mr,- Ohas..v:S..,,;;Yate3- to Secretary, :,Vrar ^abinetv- - -                                         17; Prince of &quot;vales&apos;  Terrace,.                                                - Kensingtonv. H?,. 8,                                              6th July, 1917.Dear Sir.,        Thore is a question of. national importance concerningSpitzbergen which has been bandied about between the ForeignOffice and the admiralty for the-last Q months&quot;and as it seems..hopeless: to get ariy conjoint action I - hope  the ^ar Cabinet willtake the matter up and issue the necessary  Orders.        The case briefly is this:.-        Vie annexed Spitzbergen in 1614 in agreement with theDutch but never occupied it..   Of late years British Companies,and also Companies of certain other nations,.have oponed upmines in Spitzbergen to work; the deposits of the most valuablesteam coal that is found there, and largo quantities of thstcoal are now being tr&amp;nshipped to Norway and Sweden.   -        Hot long ago the German Press stated that Germany wantedcoaling atations at Spitzbargon and other places and It is saidthat Krupp^ formed a Company with culler of Rotterdam to getthese..   Germany has already acquired shares in Coal ulines atupitzbergen and possibly owns complete mines there, andapparently considers Spitzbergen to be so valuable from astrategic point of view that she even went  to the expense ofinstalling a - Vireloss Station there.        It is true that this/V/iroless Station, is said to haveboon dismantled but we have nothing to corroborate that andindeed nothing whatever to go upon but a statement by theNorwegian Minis tor,. and-. I-, have urged all along that we shouldsend a ship to Spitsbergen to, see to this and to take possessionof this German wireless Station und the Gertian Coal Mines as  aprize of war.:        The summer, is now slipping away and unless measureo.aretaken at; once the season will be over and the opportunity lost.        The Admiralty.refuse to move but - will not toll mo on  -what grounds the various Divisions such &amp;e  the Intelligence,Trade and Operations arc either for or against the proposal..        The foreign Office say;the metter. is postponed: pondinganotherConf are nee .regarding Spitsbergen after- tho war. - .        i y argument is-; that-.-if you allow Norway to claim, that  - -she has dismantled the German. Vitrolese. Station wo shall gointo th&amp; Conference withourhands tied:,., as we shall have alreadyconceded to Norway the faot that she was the party to dismantlethe German  irclsss S tat ion and: that the ownership, of the placebelongs to her whereas, as a matter of faot, I bolieve, thevdrelees Station is situated close to the British minefields.
                              - Z -        I do hope the War Cabinet, therefore, wijl take thematter into their ovm hands and order a ship to call atSpitzber.ge.ri without delay and seize the German Wireless^Stationand Coal Mines as a prize of -war and hoist the Britis-h. flag inplace of the German flag.        Unless measures are ta^en at one.a it seems to me  thatGermany will succeed in getting a hold oh Spitzbergen and. itsCoal Mines aftar the V.ar, and it is impossible to say howadversely that may not affect us hereafter when the new ice-.free route to Russia comes to be further developed.        Germany seems to be bent on trying to get there andnow is the time for us to prevent it.  -                                Yours truly,(Signed).   CH...S, S. YATSS.

</content>
</cab>
