<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/19/0 images: 320-321</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COAL    FOB    ITALY.     With reference to the last paragraph of WarCabinet 173, Minute 6, I have had the attached statementprepared showing the total quantity of coal shipped andto be shipped during the period 10th June to the 10thJuly, whioh should arrive in Italy in July, distinguish-ing tonnage under Italian control and tonnage providedby the British Admiralty.    The total quantity which,according to this estimate, should be received in Julyif no further losses occur, and subject to delays, is382,034 tons.    The requirements for that month, accor-ding to particulars which have been supplied bv theItalian Delegation of the Commission Internationalede Ravi t a moment, amount to 740,000 tons, (includingan extra 50,000 tons for the sugar factories), so thateven if the whole of the above mentioned quantity isreceived, there will be a deficit of 357,966 tons forthe month,  as it is understood that all reserve stocks,with the exception of the Italian Naval stores, havebeen virtually exhausted.                                        A.H.S.9th July, 1917.  -:
H, W. B.GOAL.          SHIPPED AND ALLOCATBD.      FOR JULY ARRIVAL IN ITALY FROM U.K.i.e. Shipments from 10th June to  lflth-Julju 1917.281ITALIAN GOVMMENT CONTROLLED TQffiUGB.   (a)  Direct  Shipments.              x  Italian nat ional  tonnage                 Neutral (time-chartered)                 British     11      &quot;                 Neutral (single voyage)                 Britishtt(b)  Via Blaye.ItalianNeutral52,71245,26816,72114,700 9,98712,02727,726139,388 39,753179,141ADMIRALTY SHIPMENTS.   1.Shipped in accordance with undertaking by the  Admiralty to deliver 50,000 tons monthly  for use of Italian Government.Directvia Blaye49,862 2,59452,4562.Coal shipped in compensation for delay occasioned  by ships returning with ore.                                       76,95076,950.3. / Emergency shipments (including 50,000 tons        allocated in accordance with decision        of Cabinet No.  173 of July 2nd).&apos;DirectVia Blaye80,800 2,80083,600Included  above are   x s.s. &quot;SCHERIA&quot; sunk with cargo of392,1472,504$ s,s. &quot;SOUTHERN&quot; ashore and  probably  total   7,609                                loss.    ^-^-^ 10,113Estimated July arrivals^;- 382,034

</content>
</cab>
