<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/19/0 images: 368-369</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.         *                        WAR OFFICE,                                              ;:7- LONDON, S.W.1.87/373.                                    10th July, 1917.         Sir,                In reply to your letter No. H.F.C.R. 5764 (A,A.),         of 2nd July,  I am commanded by the Army Council to inform         you that they are of opinion that a large number of the         aeroplanes at your disposal for night flying are capable,    .;  .   if properly maintained and handled, of dealing successfully    ...  with  Zeppelins of the-latest type.   These aeroplanes include         50 B.E.12, 8  Armstrong-Whitworth (160 h.p. Beardmore), and      7 ; 21 F.E.2.B..(to be flown as single seaters).  There remain       /  to be handed  over to you by Training Brigade 16 F.E.2.B. and         3 F.E.2.D., and.this transfer is now proceeding&apos;and will,&quot; it         is hoped, shortly be completed.        ^   .//                It is  hoped shortly to make alterations in the .      ;   engine (R.A.F.4.A) of the B.E.12 which will materially -         improve the performance of that machine.                I am to add that the question of possible  improve-         ment  in the performance of night flying aeroplanes has-been         referred to the Air Board for their consideration.                            I am,  ^&apos;77^7;7^                       Sir):;:^/7-^y                                     Your obedient Servant,                                      (Sd.) B.B. Cubitt.The Field Marshal    C ommanding- In-Chief,       Home Forces,            Horse Guards, S.W.1.
wmSECRET.H.F.C.R.5764 (A.A.)General Headquarters,   Home Forces,      Horse Guards,/W         London, S.W.2nd., July, 1917..VV:.&apos; Sir,                              V&apos;-&apos;::;-  -    -    ; yyvy-.\\.            Prom recent information it appears to be   --. conelusively e stabli shed that the latest type of. Zeppeliri; &apos;v -,.--/.can climb to 15,000 feet and at that height can attain:    a speed of from 60 - G5 miles in still air.   : 2.-  - .   It is.clear that&quot;the night machines at present    allotted for Home Defence are not capable of dealing    effectively with airships, of this type and it is probable    that in future attacks on this country, especially in    view of his recent losses, the enemy will only employ    his best airships. .           - I would therefore urge that night machines with.  :, capacity for,climbing.up to at least 15,000 feet and    sufficient speed at this altitude to overtake and out-    manoeuvre . the enemy may be supplied for Home Defence    night work as soon as possible,/.   3.The machines at present available for this purpose    are of. the following types : - .-rV.&apos;&quot; B.E.2.6.;     *B.E.2.E. . -;           ./.v                :. B.E.2.D.      ;B.E.12. ^ y  :                        F.E.2.B.     &apos;   -2/      4-5I am,The Secretary,,    War Office.sir-,   Your obedient Servant, (sgd.) French.        :.  Field Marshal,Commanding-in-Chief, Home Forces.

</content>
</cab>
