<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/19/0 images: 482-484</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;,-;vHAN POTO                               413                 -  Note by the Secretary. -.     The following pijptions of:this valuable Memorandum being ofa critical.characteri  are circulated confidentially to Members ofthe Vzv Cabinet only,,  as. I think they may be useful in the furtherconsideration of the Man-Power, question.                                      (Sgd)  M.P.A.H, , -   E. THE ADJUTANT GENERAL1S -IsQSMORANDuk.  (G.T., 965.  31st..May,).22.     There is a remarkable conflict between the opinions set out in   this memorandum and those  iven in Brigadier General Page Croft&apos;s &quot;memorandum (G.T.946).   The view taken by the latter is, speaking   broadly, that the Army does not make proper use of the men it has.23.     Some of the points made in the memorandum, require further ex-.   planation. .-24.  ... Thus, paragraph 9(a) states that the Y/ar Office have not ob-   tained the 30,000 agriculturalists who should have been available   at the end of January.  But this was to be merely an exchange.   Did   the War Office fail to carry out their 3ide of the bargain - to pro.   duce 30,000 substitutes?   In any ca3e the War Cabinet were not  res-   ponsible for the deficiency;  they did not stop the recruiting  of   general -service men from agriculture till a month after the memor-.   andum.was written.  (27th. June.W.C.145(9).)25.     Again, the shortage of coal miners referred to in section  (9)(h)   seems to require, explanation.   At the  meeting to  consider the   Rhondda Report (G.T.336)  it was recorded that &quot;Under existing ar- -   rangements 20,000 men  are. to be recruited by May  8th.......  arrange  -merits should be made for recruiting a. further 20,000 men between   May 8th. and the end of. July&quot;.  /The total quota from the. mine 3  was   reduced from 55,000 to. 20,000why had the Adjutant General only   secured 8, 500 by 20th,. .May? .  \(Continuation of G.T, 139.6)..
        The answer is given &quot;by the Coal Controller in G.T.1318.  The   system was altered, at the suggestion of the Director of Recruit-   ing on 8th. March, when a voluntary scheme was initiated.  This   did not end till 8th. May, and of course the full quota was not   forthcoming when the A.G.&apos;3 memorandum was written.  A &quot;post 4th.   August, 1914&quot; comb-out has been tigred, but this also is not suf-   ficient to produce the full quota;  and local committees of coal   owners and miners are nov? being set up to select quotas by ballot  . (G.T.1318).26.     The statement in section 9(c) is commented on in Sir Stephen..   son Kent1 s memorandum (G.T.11S0). llo account seems to have been   taken of 18,525 released under the Substitution Scheme;  the main   reason for the delay in recruiting these men was due to delay in   medical examination.   Moreover, the Ministry of Munitions returns   show that 3,750 left controlled establishments for the Army be-   tween l&amp;th. January and the 13th. April.   These seem to have been   left out of account.27.     Paragraph 10, has been contradicted by the Railway Executive   Committee,  who state that the 12,000 railway men had all been re-   leased early in March (G.T.1227).28.     There is an important omission in Sections 11 and 12.   As they   stand,  they imply that the War Office  submitted a satisfactory   estimate:;   whereas the proposal to review exemptions was dropped   because the War Office estimate showed that  it  was not  worth while   to set  up the proposed statutory body.   &quot;Possibly 25,000 would be   made available by the proposed statutory body...Unless  the  proposed   authority were empowered tc review the whole field of exempted   trades  and occupations,  its creation could not  solve the difficul-   ties.,......(Army Council Memorandum  dated  10th.  Feb.. 1917).29.     The statement on industrial compulsion  in  section  14,  requires   modification.   Compulsory National Service was  provisionally                                                        /adopted -
 adopted (W.C.7(l)  but  ms dropped (W. 0.11.1.)  pending the  result of voluntary  effort.   The Rhondda Committee  reported generally against compulsion 33  an immediate measure, -. although Lord  Bhondda and Sir D,- Shackleton  thought  it  necessary and the  Minority Re- port; stated that effective-and certain substitution on a voluntary basis would not be. secured (C1.Ti244)..-    -;.;     The. table- in.-Section 18-,  proves little  except  that there was delay in releasing, the.quotas.  It now: appears that they will be forthcoming in  all cases except from munition works,  where,  under. present conditions,:theMinister.of Munitions does  not anticipate - that more that  30,000  men will be oht*ined and that even if the existing barriers are  removed  by  negotiations with  the Trade Unions concerned,  the  full numbers could not be&quot;supplied (W.C.185)., SUMkARY- AND  CQNCLUSI0N3..;      It- will  be seen that the  position as regards Manpower is very intricate and hss passed through  manifold changes.   From the ob- scurity in which the whole position is clouded,  three facts are clear; - .      -                                              xy\ (1) The National Service Department ha.3 not  succeeded in ful**   filling the expectations formed of it: when it  was first  created.   (10th. report, &amp;.T.,1175),.. (2) The quotas  which have been fixed from time to time have,  in   practically every case, not  been forthcoming within the   time allotted. ; (3) There is  a  sharp conflict  of  opinion between departments whose   business is recruiting (War  Office and National Service  Depart-.   ment), and  those whose business is employing labour,(Admiralty   Board of Agriculture^. Shipping  Controller,  etc.)   The former -   are vail for a policy of a  &quot;clean cut&quot;,  whereby all men under   25 would be recruited regardless of  occupation.   The latter-are- &apos;   all for retaining men who are engaged on essential national.   wor&amp;.        &apos;           -       &quot; -X-X           &apos;                  .&apos;.   ;\  These conclusions are no .doubt trite and obvious;  but  they indicate the  rrot difficulties of the  problem, which assuredly : admits of no  :easy. solution..:                                                  0.M.H.. -                                                    13ti*, July, 1917

</content>
</cab>
