<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/137/0 images: 4-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(68) 71 COPY NO.30th April, 1968CABINETHOTEIj DEVELOPMENT INCENTIVES SCHEME:DRAFT WHITE paper note by the President of the Board of TradeI informed the House of Commons on 20th March that I wouldpublish a White Paper giving details of the Hotel DevelopmentIncentives Scheme announced in summary form that day,I attach a draft White Paper, taking account of comments on earlier drafts by the Working Party on Industrial Investment andthe Committee on Home Publicity.I invite rny colleagues to approve the White Paper for publicationas soon as possible.C. A, R. C.Board of Trade, S.W.1.30th April, 1968.....&apos;        A
HOTEL DEVELOPMENT INCENTIVESDRAFT WHITE PAPERWorld tourism is developing rapidly;    rising living standards,increased leisure and developments in air transport ensure that itwill continue to grow.     In the six years up to 1967, the number of overseas visitors coming to this country as tourists or on businessrose from 2\ million to 4 million, and their estimated expenditurehere rose from about  180 million to  245 million.      (Receiptshave not grown as fast as the number of visitors owing to the changingpattern of tourist traffic and the increasing number of shortvisits.)     By 1970 the number of visitors to this country may have risen to about 6 million and they may spend about  300 million.Fares paid by overseas visitors to British airlines and shipping companies also help our balance of payments.2.     We want the growth in the number of overseas visitors to thiscountry to continue since their spending here is an importantinvisible export.     At the moment, the total expenditure of overseasvisitors - including fares to British shipping and airlines -accounts for  1 in every  10 of the country&apos;s invisible earnings.We also need to cater successfully for the majority of people inthis country who still take all or some of their holidays in theUnited Kingdom.    There must be no lack of opportunity for them toholiday here as comfortably and as enioyably as they would abroad.Otherwise we should lose the &quot;import saving&quot; element in homeholidaymakers&apos; expenditure which, like earnings from overseasvisitors, assists our balance of payments.3.     Tourism is not one industry.      It covers many trades and activities:    the hotel and catering trades;    entertainment,cultural activities and sport;    transport, shops and other services;and all the facilities that enable visitors to enjoy the attractionswhich nature and history have given to this country.     Overseasvisitors, whether on holiday or not, share the same services and activities as our own people.The place of hotels in the economy4.     Adequate accommodation - with courteous, efficient service at prices which people are willing to pay - is crucial to thesuccess and growth of tourism and essential for business travellers,from home or overseas.     Not everyone stays in hotels.     Caravanningand camping are growing in popularity, and many people stay withrelatives and friends, in hostels or in rented accommodation.But of our overseas visitors, over 6070 spend at least part of theirstay in hotels, and 25% of all the nights spend here by overseasvisitors are passed in hotels.     This proportion may increase with the growth of inclusive tours to Britain - a type of holidaynormally based on hotel accommodation.     While, therefore, it isimportant that there should be sufficient tourist accommodation ofall types, it is essential that there should be sufficient hotel accommodation to keep pace with demand if tourism is to achieve its full potential.5.     Of the total spending by overseas visitors in this country it has been estimated that around  75 million a year is spent inhotels by overseas visitors here on business or for pleasure.The hotel industry will make its maximum direct and indirectcontribution to the credit side of the balance of payments accountonly if it can meet both business and holiday demand.fa-        The number of holidays taken by British people in thiscountry each year is about 30 million, and is therefore of majorsignificance to our tourist industry.     Accommodation to match1
changing tastes and needs is important to this large market.As well as catering for our own holidaymakers, hotel accommodationmust, of course, be available for businessmen travelling within this country and has a part to play in the expansion of industryin Development Areas.The need for more investment7.     Present information suggests that new hotel bedrooms arebeing provided at the rate of about 3,000 a year - with some5,000 beds.      But it is not known how many of these are additions to the amount of hotel accommodation and how many simply replaceaccommodation going out of use.      The British Travel association has estimated that, on the basis of expected tourism growth,there will be a serious shortage of hotel accommodation by 1970unless there is an early increase in the estimated rate of new building.      Pilot surveys carried out in Nottingham and Edinburghfor the Hotel and Catering Economic Development Committee and.the Scottish Tourist Board respectively support the forecast ofa shortage.8.     A shortage of hotel accommodation will not of itselfnecessarily lead to sufficient new investment unless the level ofprofitability to be expected is as good as that offered byalternative investment opportunities, with comparable risks.There is evidence that investment in hotel building is alreadylagging.      Some further insight into the problems of hoteldevelopment has been gained through the operation of the Boardof Trade experimental Hotel Loans Scheme.     This was introduced on a temporary basis in January 1967 to assist hotel developmentsoffering prospects of achieving increased earnings from overseasvisitors.     The experimental scheme closed for new applicationson 31st March,  1968.     Despite the limited  nature of the scheme,it has already provided evidence that the profitability of investment in new hotels is less than that of comparableinvestment in manufacturing industries.      Similar conclusionshave been reached by the Hotai and Catering E.D.C. whichcommissioned a study of the return on investment in new hotel accommodation published on 14th February,  (&quot;Investment in hotel sand Catering&quot;).9.     There is room for further study of the characteristics of demand, the general level of efficiency, and the ways in whichthis can be increased.     But the need for more investment is urgent.     The Government has, therefore, considered whatincentives could best be provided, to succeed the experimentalloans scheme, in order to stimulate investment in new hotel accommodation and to encourage the improvement of existingaccommodation to cater for growth and changing demand.10.   Advice on the form that C4overnment assistance might takehas been received from a number of bodies.     Trade associations,the Hotel and Catering E.D.C., the Hotel Loans Advisory Committeeand the British Travel Association were asked for their viewson the experimental loans scheme.     The suggestions which they made have been taken into account in formulating the proposalsdescribed below.11.    In particular the Government has carefully considered thereport of the Hotel and Catering E.D.C.,  (para.  8 above) whichrecommended that hotels should receive tax allowances for capital expenditure on buildings, investment grants for expenditure on plant and equipment,  and Government loans.     TheGovernment has concluded that tax allowances, the benefits ofwhich would be felt only over a period of time,  and only whenprofitability had been established, would not offer immediate2
help towards the financing of hotel development.      Nor is the investment grants system appropriate to the special circumstancesof the hotel industry,     The Government has therefore decidedto introduce a new system of hotel development incentivesspecifically designed to meet the special circumstances of the hotel industry and, in particular,  to stimulate investment inmedium and lower priced accommodation for which the need islikely to be greatest .Hqtel Deye-i-opment Incentives12.   The Government propose to give assistance towards thecapital cost of providing new hotel accommodation and theextension and improvement of existing hotels in Great britain in the following ways:(1)    Hotel development grants will be available for newhotels.;    for extensions to existing hotels which provide more bedrooms for letting;    and for someitems of fixed plant and equipment in connectionwith improvement schemes.(2)    Loan assistance will be available in appropriate cases towards financing new hotels,  and bedroomextensions and improvements to existing ones.Eligibility13.    Hotels and other establishments primarily concerned inoffering accommodation and meals overnight, or for longer periods,to travellers and visitors without their necessarily havingbooked in advance will be eligible for   consideration for grants and, in appropriate cases,  for loan assistance.      Establishmentssuch as clubs catering for restricted groups of people, or those which only offer accommodation on a longer term residentialbasis or only against advance reservations, will not be eligible.Moreover grants and loan assistance will only be available forestablishments which already,  or after taking advantage of thescheme, will regularly provide at least 10 bedrooms for the accommodation of travellers and short-term visitors and have at least one public room available for their common use at all reasonable hours.      In the area of the Greater London council the minimum requirement will be 25 letting bedrooms.      unlike the experimental loans scheme, the new scheme of assistance will not be confined to hotels which can show good prospects&apos;of significant overseas earnings.14.    Careful consideration has been given to the size of hotelwhich could qualify for Government assistance.      Both large and small establishments have an important part to play in providing accommodation.      The need to concentrate assistancewhere it will be most likely to yield appreciable results interms of additional accommodation dictates the need for somequalifying minimum.      This, however, must be set at a point which does not exclude hotels in rural areas, where demandthroughout the year may not be enough to justify a largeestablishment.     The minimum has also been selected to encouragesuitable hotels now below this size to expand their accomodation to at least ten bedrooms.Hotels in Development Areas15.    The Chief Secretary to the Treasury announced on 9th February 1968 an extension of the Development Commission&apos;activities to enable it to make loans to small hotels, guesthouses, etc. in rural parts of the Development Areas (excluding the area covered by the Highlands and Islands Development board
where similar arrangements already exist).     This loan assistance is being administered by the Development Commission through theCouncil for Small Industries in Rural Areas and may cover up to75$ of the total cost (building,  equipment, working capital) ofnew accommodation in hotels, guest houses, boarding houses and similar establishments, subject to a maximum loan of  25,000.This assistance is confined to establishments in rural parts ofDevelopment Areas, which normally include country towns having a population Of up to 10,000.      It will therefore primarilybenefit smaller establishments than those to which the HotelDevelopment Incentives scheme will apply.16.     The Government has also proposed to relieve hotels incertain rural parts of Development Areas from Selective employment tax by making them eligible for full refund of the tax from september next.    The establishments and areas to which this reliefwould apply are described in the Finance Bill now before Parliament.17.     In keeping with the Government&apos;s policy of giving special assistance to investment which will help expansion and employmentin the Development Areas, the new hotel development incentives willprovide for a higher rate of grant in these areas (see paragraph18(4) below).Rates of Grant Proposed18.     The rates of grant will be:-(l)    New hotels.    For new hotels, a grant will be payable of20% of expenditure on buildings and fixed equipment(excluding expenditure on the purchase of land and ofany existing buildings on the land) but subject to anupper limit of grant calculated on the basis of  1,000for each letting bedroom created by the development.(2)    Grants for extensions.    For extensions which provide notless than five additional bedrooms for letting, bringincthe total number of letting bedrooms to not less than ten(25 in the area of the G.L.C.), a grant will be payableof 2G% of expenditure on constructional work and fixedequipment (excluding expenditure on the purchase of laneand existing buildings) subject to an upper limit of 1,000 for each additional letting bedroom created bythe development.(3)    Improvement schemes.    A grant will be payable of 20%: ofexpenditure on purchasing and installing certain specified items of fixed plant and equipment (seeparagraph 23(b) below) in respect of expenditure on suchitems of not less than  1,000 in any one financial year of the concern claiming the grant.    Such grants will only be available in respect of hotels possessing atleast 10 letting bedrooms after the improvements havebeen completed (25 such rooms in the G.L.C. area).(4)    Development Areas. The rate of grant in these areas willbe 25% for all three forms of assistance, subject to anupper limit of  1,250 per additional bedroom in respectof new hotels and extensions.    Hotels in development areas will have to satisfy the other criteria ofeligibility for assistance including the minimumrequirement of ten bedrooms or more for letting.4
19. Examples of grant on new hotels, and extensions involvingfive or more additional bedrooms are given below: (Figures inparentheses are for Development Area hotels)	Cost of con-	Average				Mew hotels	structional work 8c fixed	cost Der	Maximum grant				equipment	bedroom				00 bedrooms	 1,000,000	 10,000	 100,000	( 125,000)		 150 bedrooms	     250,000	  5,000	  50,000	( 	62,500)	 120 bedrooms	       80,000	  4,000	  16,000	( 	20,000)	 Extensions bringing the		number of bedrooms to		1 0	or more	10 extra bedrooms	       50,000	  5,000	  10,000	( 	12,500)	 18   &quot;	       20,000	  2,500	     4,000	( 	5,000)	 ij   ti	       20,000	  4,000	     4,000	( 	5,000)	 Grant perbedroomNote   Grants will be calculated by taking the expenditure on construc-tional work - including for example, work on kitchens and publicrooms - and on fixed equipment, and dividing this by the numberof additional letting bedrooms provided to produce a &quot;cost perbedroom&quot;.    If this is under  5,000, the grant will be 20% ofthe total expenditure (25% in Development Areas).    If the cost per bedroom is  5,000 or more, the grant will be  1,000 ( 1,250in Development Areas) for each bedroom created by the development.Effect of new system of grants20.   The system of grants described above is designed to have its main impact on the provision of additional hotel bedrooms.The inclusion of a ceiling figure for the grant, related tothe number of bedrooms, has two purposes.    First it is designedto provide an effective stimulus to expansion of bedroomaccommodation.    Secondly, the limit has been set at a point which provides for the maximum rate of grant to be offered for accommodation at medium and lower prices, where profitabilitytends to be lower, and where, therefore, in the absence ofspecial assistance, investment is in greater danger of laggingbehind demand.    The further development of tourism from overseas and of holidaymaking in this country can be expected to produce a growing need for modern accommodation in these price rangesand growth in &apos;package holidays&apos; and inclusive tours is likelyto contribute to the same trend.Loan assistance21o   Although hotel development grants on the basis outlined above should act as a considerable stimulus to development,there could nevertheless still be difficulties for companies,particularly new enterprises which cannot charge their assets, in raising capital for the whole of the balance of theexpenditure involved.    In suitable cases loan assistance willbe available in addition to grants.    To qualify for considera-tion for loan assistance, the same criteria of minimum sizewill have to be met as for hotel development grants.5
22o    New hotel projects may be eligible for loan assistance towards expenditure on constructional work and fixed equipment(excluding expenditure on the purchase of land and of existing buildings) provided that such expenditure exceeds  20,000.Loans of up to 30% of this expenditure may be given;exceptionally, one of up to 40% may be payable in the case ofa new hotel to be built and operated by a small enterprise whichmay have special problems in raising capital.23-    Extensions and improvements to existing hotels whichhave or which would, on completion of the development, haveten or more letting bedrooms (25 in the G.L.C. area) may be eligible for loan assistance of up to 50% of expenditure onconstructional work and fixed equipment (excluding expenditureon the purchase of land and existing buildings), provided thatthis exceeds  10,000.Maximum amount and terms of loans24.    Loans will be made at Government lending rates.    Themaximum amount of loan which could be payable will be  500,000for any one project.    For new hotels, the maximum period ofloan will be twenty years.    In such cases there is anunremunerative period during construction and, possibly, in the initial operation of a completely new establishment.    Inappropriate cases, the commencing date for the repayment ofcapital may be deferred for up to three years;    and capitalisa-tion of interest for up to three years may also be permitted.For extensions and improvements to existing hotels, themaximum period of loan will be 1 5 years and no capitalisationof interest or deferment of repayments will be permitted.What is meant by &quot;fixed equipment&quot;25.    (a)    New hotels and extensionsIn the case of new hotels, and extensions to existinghotels involving at least five additional bedrooms for letting,the range of fixed equipment which may qualify for grant orloan assistance will be the same.    Fixed equipment in this context means equipment which is not easily detached by, forexample, mere unscrewing or unplugging.    It will include, forexample, fixed heating boilers and radiators;    ventilation-plant;    built-in piping;    service tanks and cisterns;    fixedbaths, shower units and basins;    fixed sinks;    sprinklersystems;    lifts;    built-in furniture.    It will not include, forexample, telephone, radio and television equipment;    publicaddress systems;    clocks and time recorders;    blinds andcurtains;    night storage and portable heaters;    moveablefurniture;    floor coverings;    loose furnishings;    crockery orkitchen utensils.(b)    Improvement schemes in the case of improvement schemes which do not qualifyas extensions to existing hotels because no, or less than five additional bedrooms are involved, grants will only be payable on a specified range of fixed equipment, and incidentalinstallation costs, provided that the expenditure involvedamounts to  1,000 or more in the financial year of the concernclaiming the grant.    The range of fixed equipment eligiblefor improvement grants will not be as wide as the fixed equipmentqualifying as part of a new hotel or extensions.    It will,however, cover major items of equipment such as fixed bathroomand lavatory equipment;    fixed centrally installed plant for water heating, space heating, ventilation or air conditioning;fixed centrally installed plant for water softening or filtering;fixed machinery or plant for the preparation, storage and servingon the premises of food and refreshment;    fixed mechanicallyoperated lifts, hoists, escalators and luggage handling equipment.6
Advisory Committee26.    The Board of Trade have been advised by an Hotel LoansAdvisory Committee in administering the experimental loansscheme/   This Committee, under the Chairmanship first ofSir William Slimmings C.3.E. and now of Sir Leonard Cooke, O.B.E.,has rendered valuable service to the Board of Trade and willcontinue to deal with outstanding applications under the experimental scheme.    The Committee will also be consulted about the details of the new scheme outlined in this paper-    Itis not yet clear whether it will be necessary to set up an advisory Committee in connection with the now scheme.What types of undertaking will be eligible27.    Subject to the exceptions set out below, grants will beavailable and loan assistance may be given to all persons(including companies, firms, partnerships and individuals)carrying out qualifying hotel projects and securing their operation as hotels for a minimum period.    (it is not theintention to preclude payment of grants or the giving of loanassistance in appropriate cases where the owner and operatorof the hotel are not the same person.)Local authorities28o    Grants and loan assistance under the scheme will not beavailable to local authorities.Nationalised industries29o    Some nationalised industries have, or may have, powers tobuild, operate, or invest in hotels.    The Government considerit desirable that the public sector should play its part inthe expansion of hotel accommodation on comparable terms withthe private sector.    Those nationalised industries which have powers to invest in hotels will therefore be eligible forhotel development grants on the same terms as the private sector.    They will not however be eligible for loan assistance under this scheme, nor will their subsidiaries be eligiblefor such loan assistance, since they have access to government loans under their own borrowing powers.Projects already in receipt of assistance from public funds30.    Hotel projects in respect of which an offer of government assistance has been accepted, whether by way of grant or loan,will not be eligible for consideration for grants or furtherloans under the new scheme.    For example, an applicant who hasalready accepted the offer of a loan from the Board of Trade underthe experimental Hotel Loans Scheme will not be able to claim agrant or receive a loan for the same project under the new scheme, even if the project might otherwise be eligible.    It isfor the applicants concerned to decide whether to continue with applications for projects already under consideration whichmight at a later date be eligible for consideration underthe new scheme.Tax treatment of hotel development grants31.    Hotel development grants will be treated for tax purposes as capital receipts in the hands of recipients, inthe same way as grants made under the Industrial development act, 1966.    This means that these grants will not give rise7
to a liability to Corporation tax or Income Tax, as the case maybe, Any element of grant attributable to fixed plant and equip-ment or to the alternation of an existing building incidental tothe installation of the plant or equipment will be treated asreducing the capital cost of these assets for the purpose of tax allowances.Period of Operation and Cost32.    The Government intend to introduce legislation as soon aspossible to provide the necessary powers for the payment ofhotel developmeng grants and for the giving of loan assistance.Subject to such legislation, hotel projects, which satisfy the criteria described in this paper, will be eligible for hoteldevelopment grants and for consider.ati.on for loan assistancewhere work on such projects begins on the site after 31st March,1968 and before 1st April, 1971, provided the project will becompleted by 31st March, 1973.    Temporary fencing work and siteclearance e.g. demolition of existing buildings, carried outbefore 31st March, 1968 will not render a project ineligiblefor consideration provided no new development work (including provision of utility services) has been undertaken on the sitebefore 31st March, 1 968.33-    Expenditure by the Government on grants and,  in appropriate cases, on loan assistance in any particular year will dependprimarily on the nature and timing of investment decisions bythe industry.    Grants will not be payable until a project hasbeen completed and the expenditure eligible for considerationverified.    Legislation will not be possible during the current session and it is unlikely for this reason that any paymentscould be made during the 1968/69 financial year.    Wot allinvestment in 1968/69 will be eligible for consideration if only because some of it will involve projects begun before the qualifying date.    Complete figures of capital investment in both licensed and unlicensed hotel accommodation in Great britain are lacking but investment may be running at an annual rate ofabout  15 million.    If investment were to rise to  20 million a year - of which perhaps  15 million might represent eligibleexpenditure - then grants could cost about  3 million.    Loanassistance would not be appropriate or even sought in every caseso the gross expenditure on loan assistance would be less than 5 million, all repayable with interest at Government lendingrates.34.    The Governmenfs legislative proposals will provide for grants and loans on the terms described in this paper for projectsundertaken within the period mentioned in paragraph 30.    TheGovernment may also wish to seek power to extend assistancebeyond that period, but any further assistance would notnecessarily be on the same terms or criteria.Administration35.    The proposed legislation will include the necessaryprovisions against abuse of the incentive scheme, includingpenalties for fraud.    It will also include power to imposeconditions on the making of grants, and to secure information and such undertakings as are necessary to avoid abuse.    Forexample, recipients of assistance will be required to ensurethe operation of the hotels for a minimum period and there willbe powers to secure repayment of grant in certain circumstances.Loans will be governed by the terms of loan agreements.8C0MFIDEMT5AL
Applications36.     It will not be possible for any applications for grants orloans to be accepted for consideration until Parliament has approved the necessary legislation, but applications will then beconsidered even though the project is already under construction,provided that it started after 31st March 1958.    Intendingapplicants should,  in the meantime, retain all documents andevidence which could help to establish eligibility and substantiateexpenditure.    The Board of Trade will announce in due coursedetails of arrangements for submitting applications but none willbe accepted until after the enactment of legislation.37.     The Board of T ade will consult the British Travel Association,the Scottish and Wales Tourist Boards, the Hotel and Catering EDC,and trade and other associations on the scheme before issuingmore detailed guidance and before applications are invited.    Inthe meantime,  no enquiries about individual cases can be answeredby the Board of Trade or other Departments until arrangements forsubmitting applications have been announced.Registration of Establishments33.     There is at present no comprehensive list of hotels in thiscountry,  showing the accommodation and facilities they offer, orthe prices they charge.    A number of organisations issueexcellent guides giving a selected list of hotels,  but there is a need for something more comprehensive, catering for   all tastes.Such lists of hotels would greatly help efficient marketing.39.     The Government therefore proposes that the legislation should include powers to require the registration of hotels and similarestablishments so that,  in due course, more comprehensiveinformation on hotels - and other accommodation as appropriate -will be available for the benefit of the tourist industry and thepublic generally.40.     The British Travel Association,  the Scottish and WalesTourist Boards and other bodies have done work in the field ofhotel classification.    The Board of Trade will seek their views,and those of other organisations, on the way in which registra-tion might best be introduced,  and information published,  on a self financing basis.    There is no intention of creating aGovernment monopoly of hotel guides;    information on location,size,  facilities and prices of hotels could be made available on a commercial basis to organisations wishing to publishselective guides.41.     In its further consideration of hotel registration,  theGovernment will wish to take account of work being done in thefield of hotel booking systems including the feasibility study of computerised systems being commissioned by the Hotel and catering Economic Development Committee.Looking ahead42,      The proposals for grants and loan assistance in this paperprovide a firm basis for the hotel industry to plan investmentto meet the challenge of tourism growth at home and from overseasas a new era in air transport approaches.    These proposals willmake investment in hotel development more remunerative and ease the problems of capital financing.
43.     But the industry must play its part in providing the rightkinds of accommodation in the right places to cater for growth and to make it easier for tourists to enjoy visiting all partsof the country, not just London or the best known tourismcentres.    There must be unremitting attention to service and efficiency.    The results of research carried out by Universities,the industry&apos;s Economic Development Committee, and by other bodies must be applied by individual hotel operators to their ownundertakings.44.      The Government is now considering what further measures maybe necessary to promote the development of a successful touristindustry, and whether these will call for organisational changes of any kind.    The arrangements for administering the hoteldevelopment incentives scheme will be determined in the light of decisions to be reached on these matters,    The Government intends to announce its conclusions later this year.Board of Trade,London,  S.W.1.\10


</content>
</cab>
