<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/10/0 images: 210-221</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY CP HIS BRITIJMIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET &apos;     .CP. (46)   223 COPY NO.7TH JUNE  1946CABINETFUTUEE OF THE RUHRMemorandum by the secretary of State forPcreign affairs circulate for the informationinteresting memorandum on the subject with regard to the future of the RuhrH.M. Ambassador in Paris.E.B.F or e i gn Off ice, S.W.1 *7TH JUNE 1946.MEMOKA.KDUM ON THE FUTURE  OF THE RUHRThere Is a danger that the problem of Germany may be misunderstood and the wrong solution adapted owing to afaulty approach.      Seeing the confusion that at presentexists,  the under tried frontiers,  the economic uncertainty,the danger of starvation,  the four zones and the lack of ,co-ordinated policy, the observer v/ith the best intentionsis apt to be misled  into believing that these immediate difficulties constitute the whole German problem and thatwhen they have been removed the problem will be solved.Similarly, after the 1914/1918 war the question of reparations loomed disproportionately large in the minds of those most concerned, a vast amount of time was spentand wasted on its consideration while the real problemescaped notice,  no attempt was made to solve it untiltoo late,  and  the result was world disaster.2.      It is my submission that the real problem which wehave to solve is not the condition of Germany in 1946but the condition of Germany In 1966. &apos;   The conditionof Germany in 1919 was,&apos;from many points of view,lamentable, but it was.not nearly so lamentable fromthe point of view of the rest of the world as was thecondition of Germany in 1939*     We should surely beforeall other things beware lest in endeavouring to improve the condition of 1946 which resembles that of 1919* wedo not end by recreating in 1966 a situation whichresembles that of 1939*..-f my colleagues anof British policywritten by

3.      In other words, before considering any of the details ofthe existing German situation,  we should  surely decide whatkind of a Germany we desire to see in existence at the endof a period of,  say,  twenty years, when the world as a whole will have largely recovered from the effects of the recentwar.      Dc we desire that there shall then exist a centralised,prosperous and powerful German state with a populationconsiderably larger than that of any other purely Europeancountry?     I cannot believe that smch-a consummation canrecommend itself to any human being whc is not a German.Nor con any human being,  even a German, doubt that such astate of affairs would entail another war.      The industrious,courageous, and  intelligent German people have two defeatsto avenge.     They came nearer to winning the second war thanthe first,  in spite of colossal blunders.      Many of them aredoubtless saying to themselves that these blunders will notbe repeated,  that it should prove easy to find a leadersuperior both to William Hohenzollern and to Adolf Hitler,and that on the third  occasion they will succeed.     the combined political wisdom of the  rest of the world shouldbe directed,  first and foremost,  towards ensuring that thisthird occasion shall never arise.A.      Now the first solution of the problem which appears tobe receiving favourable consideration in certain quarters isbased en the assumption that it may prove possible to create a Germany which shall be large, prosperous,  centralised and self-governing, but shall not be powerful.      This wouldcertainly provide a satisfactory solution if it were possible.But is it?     Can we imagine the existence in twenty or eventen years1  time of a united nation of sixty million Europeans,self-supporting and self-governed,  to whom the most elementaryof all rights,  the right  jf self-defence, would be permanentlydenied?      (The right of self-defence implies the right tomaintain forces sufficient for aggression, as armamentssufficient for defence against Russia would be ample foraggression against Czechoslovakia),.      Even if the imaginationbe capable of  such a feat,  a further effort will be required-of it, for even if we can Imagine such a right being deniedin theory wo have ye*k to imagine how such a denial in theorycan in practice be put into force.      We have recently hadproof of what resistance movements can accomplish even amongsta divided population,  even in countries occupied by an enemyprepared to exert authority with the most inhuman brutality.Imagine than the impotence of the mild and benevolent U.N.0.bo prevent sixty million resolute Germans from re-armingthemselves in secret.1&apos;j.      If,  therefore,  it be admitted that there cannot be alarge, prosperous, united Germany that is not also a powerful and therefore a dangerous Germany, common sense -would seem toindicate that the id ea of a large, prosperous, united germany should be abandoned,.      Nor need any tears be shed over itsabandonments     The union of Germany is a modern development,less than, eighty years old.      It is the creation of two men -Bismarck and Hitler - whose achievement the United Nationscan hardly wish to render permanent.      Since the German Reichhas existed  it has done nothing but harm in the world, and ithas dene the greatest of all harm to the German people.   7/henthe essential unity of the German people is insisted upon Itis often forgotten that even twenty-eight years ago,  althoughunity existed for the conduct of war,  there were still withinGermany a large number of separate governments,  separateparliaments,  separate kings and&apos;.ruling&apos; princes.

6,     The surest and simplest method of rendering Germanyharmless for all times is to remove from the control of thecentral German Government that part of Germany, namely the ruhr district, without which it is quite impossible for germany to prepare for war.      One of the two main arguments against this sure one; simple solution is that it. would create an. irredentist movement in Germany (see P.M.M. ,(1+6)  13)*      the answer to this argument is (a)  the union of Germany is ofsuch recent manufacture that it  still lacks thuse deep rootsfrom ,.hich genuine irredentism springs:    whereas artificialirredentism can always be created, (b) the Germans are adocile pro-pie and have for centuries been accustomed toaccept every form of brutal tyranny without protest,  (c)large portions of German inhabited territory have alreadybeen transferred to Poland bo that if there is any irredentistspirit iii Germany it already has full opportunity fordevelopments7*      Irredentiam is only one form of:&apos;discontent.      To create acontented Germany immediately is plainly impossible.      Theidea of leaving the Ruhr under German -Sovereignty is apparentlyto form part of a policy which will place the entire Ruhrindustry under foreign control.      Is such a policy likelyto find greater favour in the eyes  of Germans than political,separation?     It is dangerous to prophesy about psychologicaldevelopment and unwise to argue by analogy, but I believethat if Great Britain had been defeated in the war, we shouldnot have resented the alienation of the Isle of wight fromthe United Kingdom so much as the permanent subjection of theBritish coal industry f.  foreign control.0;.      The other main argument against the removal of the Ruhrfrom German sovereignty is that it would prove &quot;economicallydisastrous&quot;.      It is difficult for &apos; one who is not an experteconomist to understand why or to whom a policy should proveeconomically disastrous which would place an enormouslyproductive district under the -control of an international body charged with the duty of developing it for the benefotof Europe as a whole and more particularly of Germany.      Noris it clear whym economically:,  such an international bodycould produce&quot;satisfactory results so. long as Germansovereignty was maintained but can produce only disast.if that particular blessing is withdrawn.      Whey  should  theefforts of the United Nations be doomed to failure in circumstances where only the sovereignty of Berlin canensure success?9.      The idea of dividing economic control from politicalsovereignty is in theory illogical and in. practice can hardly succeed.    In backward countries where capitulationsexist or have existed the more civilised nations have often succeeded in exercising great influence, if not complete control,  over commerce and finance, while payinglip-service to the independence of the native Government.But the Germans are not a backward people and it seems that the whole case in favour of retaining Germansovereignty while exercising economic control is blow.skyhigh by the admission in paragraph 20 of Appendix I ofP.M.M* (h-6)  13 that the scheme &quot;depends for success on theco-operation and goodwill of the German Government, which by sabotage, by political or other pressure,  could reducethe Corporation&quot; (formed for running the industries)  &quot;toimpotence without even necessarily transgressing theprovisions of the charter,&quot;    If having survived 191V1918and 1939/191+6 we are still prepared to base our schemes

for the- future prosperity end peace of Europe on theco-operation and goodwill of the Gorman Government, we have certainly learnt very little by experience.10.    it may be objected that according to the Potsdam decisionswith regard to the level of industry it will not be permitted to. the United Nations to develop the Ruhr industries to their utmost,  and that instead of being an asset the Ruhr will prove a liability.    But in either case the profit cr losswill bo to the advantage or the disadvantage of Germanyand of Europe, and in cither case the responsibility will bethat of the United Nations,    Nor are the Potsdam&apos; resolutionseither as ancient or as immutable as the laws of the Modesand, Persians.    If they admit of moderation surely the firstplace in which to moderate them would be in a district whichhad ceased to be part of Germany and where nothing could-bebetter calculated than an improvement in the standard ofliving to reconcile the inhabitants to severance from thefatherland.11.    The Chiefs of Staff dismiss the French plan for the Ruhrsummarily.    They say that it &quot;only accentuates the disadvantages of the -3.I.P.S. plan.&quot;    But the main disadvantages of theE.I.P.S. plan are that it separates political sovereigntyfrom economic control raid that it is entirely dependentfor its success on. the goodwill of Germany.    Both thesedisadvantages are -avoided by the French plan.    The Chiefsof Staff Committee&apos;s paper is admittedly based on the assumptionthat &quot;Russia appears at present our most likely potential enemy&apos;.&apos;    I would suggest that this may possibly prove ashort-sight ed view, and I would recall that it was the same view that was held at the end of the former war and f or manyyears that followed.      It is true that - the Sovieticrepresentatives are at the present time proving difficultcolleagues,  and that this lack of co-operation giveslegitimate cause for anxiety, but once again we must bewareof the error of allowing existing difficulties to play too large a part in the formation of long-term policy.    It issurely possible to find, a loss sinister explanation ofRussian intractability than dreams of either world conquestor world revolution.    Russian statesmen are no doubt sayingto themselves that occasions such as the present, whenthe world is.in the melting pot,  occur not more than onceor twice in a century,,    The last occasion was in 191.9 whenRussia was not even ask-ed to the -party.    They are determinedthis time to help themselves to anything that they can lay their hands on, and above all to recover everything that belonged  ,to imperial Russia,    The past of groat peoples is not a badenxide to their future.    In its very short history the german empire has twice been responsible for. plunging first europe and then the world into war.    In the very long history ofRussia she has not once been guilty of. such a crime,  andit is difficult to believe that the apostles of thebrotherhood of man will rush in whore the Romanofs wereafraid to treafi..

12.    We have the choice between two policies     the.international control of industry within territory thatwill remain German,  or the severence of the Ruhr fromGermany.    I have suggested that the former policy isunprecedented and will prove impracticable.&quot;&apos; Neither ofthese objections can bo brought against the latter.    Eitherpolicy may later be abandoned as memories of the war fade,as the willito hold Germany down weakens.,  and as Gormannationalism reasserts itself.    But which of the two islikely to prove the more permanent?    When.in 1936 Hitlermarched into the Rhineland British public opinion wasunmoved,  and to the man in the street, who had not read the treaty of Locarno,  there seemed little&apos;harm in Gormantroops marching into German territory.    If,  on the otherhand,  they had been obliged to cross a frontier, however,ethnically unjustified that frontier might have been,public opinion would have understood, that somethingformidable ju:,nd occurred.    Equally inthe days to come therequest of a German Government to have control over Gormanf industry, conducted by German workers in German territory/I ) is likely to get a better reception than a demand to /-alter&apos; the frontiers of Europe. The latter is, on the face of it,, a casus belli, the former is net.13.    The policy of dividing&apos; the Ruhr from Germany has two further advantages:---    First, we should have France on our side;  secondly,  we should be able,  through whateverGovernment is established for the Ruhr,  to eradicate mostof the clandestine OrgariiSatlohs which it will not bepossible to check if Germany is allowed to maintain political control.    The Chiefs of Staff are fully alive to the dangerof throwing Germany into the arms of Russia, but they donot seem to have contemplated the possibility of Francebeing impelled in the same direction.    More than -fcwo yearsago General de Gaulle said to me:    &quot;If France does not getcomplete security after this war I know that the majorityof my fellow countrymen, will feel that it is going to happenagain,  that the English will always be too few and that the americans will always be too late,  and once more Francewill have to bear the brunt.    They will feel that theycannot face it again,  that the men of Munich and&quot;the menof Vichy were right after all,  and that their only hopeis to make the best terms they can with their easternneighbours rather than r ely&apos; upon the inadequate and. tardysupport of the west.&quot;   The French believe that they can never have security so long as the. Ruhr is governed from berlin.    I can see no possible hop.-:.: of satisfying theFrench demand, for security othernthan by politicalseparation of the Ruhr from therest of the Reich.    by such separation alone shall we secure a true alliance with France and the assurance of having her on our side .in the event of any future struggle.14.    Some may say, however,  that to have France on. our sideis of less importance than to have Germany with us. Thereare some strategists who believe that it would be wise tobuild up a strong Germany as&apos; a bulwark against Russia.    Butonce Germany becomes strong enough to service as a bulwarkagainst anybody she will bo strong enough to decide her own&apos;    policy,  and will she be more3ikely to turn her strengthagainst the east or the west?    To the east lie thelimitless- and largely barren plains of Russia,  stretchingout into Asia and &quot;the pacific Ocean,  inhabited by a population more: than twice as numerous as that of Germany;

to the est lie throe or lour little nations rich andfertile,  with numerous Atlantic ports through which theymaintain contact with their vast colonial possessions.Is Germany more likely to attack the loan giant or thefat dwarfs?15. - In other words,  the chances of Germany being with us ina-struggle are,  in my view,  very slight.    To build up germany or to favour political conditions under which her strengthcan be built up is,  I suggest,  to take the very gravestrisk.    At the same time,  wo should be alienating Prance andpossibly driving her into the arms either of Seamanimperialism or of international communism.    It appears to me,therefore, that strategically as well as economically thearguments for the political separation of the Ruhr fromGermany have immense force.16.    Our position in the Mediterranean will not. be so strong as it was after we have evacuated Egypt and have no direct and immediate control of the Sues Canal.    Throughthe Dardanelles,  through Yugoslavia and Albania,  theSoviet Union will have easy access to those waters.    ButGreat Britain will remain responsible for the defence ofthe Occident.    Ho scheme for such defence that has not thecomplete support raid does not inspire the confidence ofFrance can prove effective.    The&apos;further east that thedefence line is drawn the better, but to back Germanywhile neglecting Prance would seem almost as foolishas to back Poland while neglecting, Germany.    This was indeed the desperate policy to which, we were reduced in1939 owing to a series of errors,  of which the first andthe most fatal was the failure in 1919 to face thproblem,  which, was then,  as it remains to-day,  - howare we to stop Germany from doing it again?29TH MAY,  19h7


</content>
</cab>
