<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/5/0 images: 24-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;s GOVERNMENTTHE EMPLOYMENT OF GERMAN AND ITALIAN PRISONERS OFWAR IN GREAT BRITAIN.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service.1. As invited by the Cabinet on the 18th September (CM. (45) 33rd Con-elusions, Minute 3 (1)) I have, in the light of up-to-date estimates of the numbersof Prisoners of War required for employment in this country and of the numbersalready in this country or who could be transferred from Germany or Canada,given further consideration to the question whether Prisoners of War need be restricted to the employments referred to in paragraph 11 of CP. (45) 172.I make the following proposals : .(1) The Inter-Departmental Committee on the Employment of Prisoners ofWar should be instructed to arrange for the transfer of Prisoners fromall other employments to employment in one or other of the following catergories, the apportionment between the categories being determinedby the Committee (a) agricultural employment (including forestry);(b) employment on building and civil engineering work for various departments as shown in Annex A, including work of all kindson roads and in quarries;(c) employment on the handling of stores in Government depots(e.g., in connection with the housing programme) and on theremoval of stores from buildings urgently needed for other purposes;(d) employment by the Service Departments on work (includingremoval of defence works) which otherwise would have to bedone by sailors, soldiers or airmen and on camp duties and administration.(2) The transfer should be made at a steady rate over the next six months,the aim being to complete the transfers by the end of that period.(3) The Inter-Departmental Committee should report progress periodically,at intervals of not more than two months, to the Ministerial Committeeon Man-power.(4) To the extent that transport and accommodation permit, as many aspossible of the German prisoners being held on the Continent against our possible future needs and of the German prisoners in Canadashould now be brought here for employment.(5) The Minister of War Transport should be invited to present a report as soon as possible, in consultation with the War Office and theMinistry of Labour and National Service, indicating the steps whichwould have to be taken to make sufficient transport available tobring to this country from the Continent the full number of german prisoners who can be accommodated during the winter.Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1945.SECRET.Copy No.CP. (45) 305.26th November, 1945.CABINET.[30946]b
2.   There are set out in Annex A tables showing (a) how many Prisoners, both German and Italian, are available to us for employment, either immediately or subject to their being broughthere from Canada or Germany; and(b) how many Prisoners User Departments estimate to be required for employment here either immediately or in the course of 1946.In Annex B is a statement showing the allocation of the Prisoners already here.3.   Broadly, the supply and demand picture is as follows : Demand Prisoners now in employment and continuing to berequired by the Departments to which allocated. ...Additional Prisoners required : Immediately  ...........      ... 28,000By end of 1945.......      ...... 43,000During 1946   ............ 160,000Grand Total of Prisoners estimated to be required by departments in 1946Supply-Italian Prisoners now in this country  ...Employable German Prisoners now in this countryGerman Prisoners held here by United States Army andto be transferred to usGerman Prisoners in CanadaGerman Prisoners held in Germany against our possibleneed to bring them here for employment4. Unfortunately it would be seriously misleading to add up the &quot; Supply &quot;figures set out above and produce a &quot; Grand Total &quot; to compare with the 565,000estimated to be required.  This is so for the following reasons :-(a) The repatriation of Italian Prisoners is to begin, and when transport is available, after the harvest (see CM. (45) 53rd Conclusions,Minute 2). The 153,000 Italian Prisoners in this country are,therefore, a wasting asset.(b) The German Prisoners held on our behalf in Germany can only be broughthere to the extent that transport is made available for the purpose andto the extent that we can accommodate them. These two factors, taken together, will severely curtail the actual availability for employmentin this country over the next few months of the 225,000 prisoners weare holding in Germany.(c) It has been decided that &quot; White &quot; German prisoners of war shall bereturned to Germany, subject to replacements, to the extent to whichthey are called forward by the British Element of the control commission for Germany (see CM. (45) 45th Conclusions, Minute 2).There are approximately 20,000 of these Prisoners. Their replace-ments can only be found among the 225,000 Germans held on ourbehalf on the Continent. To the extent to which this happens, the availability of the 225,000 Germans to meet additional demands is reduced.. id) All the ardent Nazis held in this country are now in employment, butthere are some 20,000 German Prisoners (and this number may be substantially increased if we bring the Germans from Canada) who,under present policy, oannot be employed against their will, e.g.,officers, certain N.C.O.s, protected personnel. Many of these do infact agree to work but only if policy changes regarding theircompulsory employment could they be properly reckoned as part of theavailable &quot; supply.&quot; The question of policy involved is a difficult oneunder urgent consideration between the War Office and the ForeignOffice.5. The points referred co at (c) and (d) above are of minor importancecompared with (a) and (b). The number of Prisoners available for employmentin this country in the coming months turns primarily on how quickly the Italians334,000231,000565,000153,000182,00015,00033,000225,000
313go and how quickly the Germans come, and these are mainly matters of transport.The repatriation of Italians is to begin in December, and it is hoped that fromthe beginning of January 1946 it will be possible to repatriate substantial numbersof Italians. As regards Germans coming here, the position is, I understand, asfollows : Within three weeks of a decision, the transport to this country of theGermans in Canada could be started at the rate of 3,000 every three weeks. Therate at which Germans can be brought from the Continent depends on the availability of transport and on the priority given to this use of transport. It: isimpossible to estimate in advance the numbers who&apos; could be transported by theuse of transport not required for other purposes. In my view the aim shouldbe to bring into this country by March next year the maximum number who cansuitably be accommodated under winter conditions. I suggest, therefore, that a start should be made at once with the transport of Germans from Canada, andwith the transfer from Germany of such Prisoners as can from time to time be moved in transport not required for other purposes. If this is agreed andtransport can start in December it should be possible by March to transfer atleast 12,000 of the Germans from Canada to this country, and it may be foundthat more could be brought. There is accommodation in base camps for about50,000 extra Prisoners (over and above those brought as replacements for &quot; white &quot;Germans or Italians). After taking in the Germans from Canada there will,therefore, even during the winter months, be a considerable number of furtherplaces available to accommodate Germans from the Continent if only they canbe brought here. In view of the great importance of this source of man-power suggest that the Minister of War Transport should be invited to consider, inconsultation with the War Office and the Ministry of Labour and NationalService, how additional transport can be made available and to submit an earlyreport to Ministers.6. After the Spring, when the accommodation position can be expectedto be less difficult, the &quot; supply &quot; position will depend, on the one hand, on howquickly we can bring here the balance of the 225,000 German Prisoners we areholding on the Continent, and, on the other, how quickly the repatriation of theItalians proceeds. Amid all the uncertainties of the transport situation we cannot reasonably envisage the total Prisoner labour force eventually available for employment in this country exceeding by more than 95,000 the present force,i.e., the difference between additions in the shape of Germans brought here from canada and the Continent and transferred from the United States Army and losses in the shape of Italians and &quot; White &quot; Germans sent away. I have also made some allowance for a proportion of &quot; unemployable &quot; among the Germanscoming from Canada. On this basis we ought not to count on having a Prisonerlabour force in 1946 exceeding 430,000.7. Against this background we have to decide what instructions to giveas to the allocation of Prisoners between Departments. It will be at once apparent that all their demands, totalling 565,000, cannot be met. I remain of the opinionexpressed in CP. (45) 172, paragraphs 10-11. We cannot meet all demands and&apos;we should, therefore, aim at meeting those where the risk of industrial troublearises in any ease, but the risk will be substantially greater if we continue to employ Prisoners in small numbers in miscellaneous employments. Once troublestarted, it might easily lead to a sudden and acute, even if quite illogical,hardening in the public attitude towards the employment of Prisoners generally.My view remains, therefore, exactly as set out in paragraphs 10 and 11 of my previous Memorandum which I quote in full for ease of reference : &quot; (10) In my view it would be unwise to make plans which involve thecontinued employment of Prisoners on work which does not clearly satisfy the following conditions :  (a) the work is of first importance and urgency and will patently be of direct benefit to the public at large;(b) the lack of British labour suitable for and wishing to obtain such work is serious and undoubted.The adoption of any other policy would, in my view, lead to trouble at anearly date as more British man-power becomes available, and would carry with it a serious risk of jeopardising the employment of Prisoners on workof any kind.[30946] b 2
&quot;(11) If my colleagues agree that our general policy should be as suggested in the previous paragraph, it is necessary to consider whichemployments satisfy the conditions there set out. In my view, four employ-ments only satisfy these conditions, viz. : (a) agricultural employment (including forestry);(6) employment on building and civil engineering work;(c) employment on the removal of stores from buildings urgently needed for other purposes (see L.P. (45) 88, paragraph 18);(d) employment by the Service Departments on work (including removalof defence works), which otherwise would have to be done bysailors, soldiers or airmen and thus slow up the rate of release from the Armed Forces.The transfer of Prisoners from all other forms of employment to these fourwill undoubtedly be unwelcome to my colleagues in charge of the departments which would, as a consequence, lose Prisoners. We must, however, look atthe man-power situation as a whole. The use of Prisoners relieves the general shortage equally whatever employment they are allocated to. Thus, thetransfer of Prisoners to building and civil engineering employment will auto-matically reduce the demands which would otherwise be made on the british labour market for that work, and the benefit of that reduction will accrue to all other Departments including those from whom the Prisoners havebeen taken. I do not deny that there will be transitional difficulties and,in certain localities, where British labour is not immediately available insufficient numbers, difficulties which may be more than transitional. Forthis reason I do not suggest that the transfers should be made all at once and without due regard to special cases. Accommodation difficulties would,in any case, prevent this. My recommendation is that the general policyof transferring all prisoners now in this country to employments of the fourkinds set out in this paragraph be approved and that the Inter-DepartmentalCommittee should report to the Ministerial Committee on Man-powerperiodically, at intervals of not more than two months, on the progress made,the aim being to make the transfers at a steady rate, and to complete thewhole job in eight months, i.e., by the end of April 1946.&quot;It will, however, now be necessary to carry out this process in six months insteadof eight months.8. The number of Prisoners who would be required to meet the demands on this basis would be, so far as can be estimated,Agriculture and forestry    ...      ....      ...      ... 245,000Building and civil engineering      ...      ...      ... 120,000Service Departments (including camp duties and administration)  ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 120,000485,000The estimate of 120,000 on building and civil engineering provides for workof this kind for various Departments as shown in Note 2 at the end of Annex A.Provision is also made for work on roads and quarries included in Ministryof War Transports estimate of requirements. The above includes no specificallowance for employment of Prisoners on the removal of stores. A great dealof this work falls to the Service Departments and the estimate of 120,000 abovetakes account of the needs of this item. The number of Prisoners who can beemployed on this work by civilian Departments at any one time is comparativelynegligible. A small number of Prisoners may also be required in connection withthe handling of stores in Government depots in connection with the housing programme. Many of these are situated in remote districts on formeraerodromes.9. These demands, all on work of very real importance for which Prisonerlabour is eminently well fitted and where experience suggests that there islikely to be a minimum of public or trade union opposition, exceed the estimated total supply in 1946 of 430,000 (see paragraph 6 above). In so far as the supply at any time was insufficient to meet immediate demands, the problem would be one for settlement on the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Employment ofPrisoners of War.
51410. I would only add that my colleagues should note that these proposalsallow for a transitional period between now and the end of April next yearwhen the general labour supply position may be expected to have materiallychanged. There should, moreover, be a material easement of the position duringthis transitional period in that, during the winter months, the needs of theAgricultural Departments decline. The Inter-Departmental Committee will doubtless be able to ease the difficulties of other Departments during the transitional period, and pending the improvement in the general man-power position, by arranging loans of prisoners from the Agricultural Departments.This will, in particular, enable me, save where accommodation is not available,to provide the Minister of Fuel and Power with the number of prisonersrequired during the winter months for coal distribution and gas and electricity supply.G. A. I.Ministry of Labour and national Service, S.W. 1,2Qth November, 1945.ANNEX A.Supply.Italian prisoners now in this country (Note 1)      ......       153,000German prisoners now in this country and held by us,excluding those at present deemed unemployable owingto the Geneva Convention (Note 2)      .........      182,000German prisoners held here by United States Army and tobe transferred to us in due course      ...      ...      ...        15,000German prisoners in Canada (Note 3)        ...      ...      ...        33,000German prisoners held on the Continent against our possibleneed to bring them here for employment (Note 4)     ...      225,000Notes 1. The repatriation of Italian prisoners has been agreed by the Cabinet to begin after the harvest. The number of Italians in this country will therefore shortly begin to decrease.It is impossible to say how quickly the number will run down as this depends on the availability of transport.2. This figure includes the 20,000 &apos;&apos; white &apos;&apos; Germans whose return to Germany has beenagreed by the Cabinet, subject to replacements, to the extent to which they are called for by the British Element of the Control Commission for Germany.3. It is estimated that these prisoners can be brought here at the rate of 3,000 every threeweeks from within a few weeks of a decision to bring them being reached. It is certainthat a proportion of them will, under the current policy, be unemployable owing to the geneva Convention. A high proportion of the remainder are believed to be ardentNazis whose employment, except by the War Office, may be difficult to arrange.4. The availability for employment of these prisoners depends on the provision of transport to bring them from the Continent. If is estimated that they can be brought here atthe rate of 1,000 a day, from within a few weeks of a decision to this effect being reached.5. Until the spring, lack of accommodation will severely curtail the number of extra prisoners(i.e., over and above those coming as.replacements) who can be received here. Thereare not more, than 50,000 places vacant at present in Base Camps. A certain numbermore can no doubt be fitted from time to time into vacant places here and there in working Camps.
Demand.The following table shows how many prisoners, over and above their presentallocation, Departments are asking for (a) immediately, (&amp;) by the end of thisyear, (c) in the course of 1946 :  P.O.W.-in      P.O.W. inP.O.W.requiredUser Department. immediately.Admiralty     ...      ... 55Agriculture (E. &amp; W.) 3,000Agriculture (Scotland) NilAir Ministry (Service) 7,954Air Ministry (Main-tenance Units)      ... 550Aircraft Production NilFood    .......... 462Fuel and Power       ... 1,000G.P.0....... 117Health           ...... 2,000Supply          ...... 955Transport      ...... 3,900War Department    ... NilWorks          ...... 8,000Totals     ...... 27,993addition to(1) requiredbefore1946.NilNilNil2,000Nil150751,500NilNil4642,940Nil35,500addition to(1) and (2)required in1946.No estimatepossible50,00020,000NilNilNil33050018No estimatepossible4166,60018,00064,500Total.55C)53,00020,0009,9545501508673,0001352,0000)1,83513,44018,000108,000f)42,629160,364       230,9860231,000Total additional prisoners required as abovePrisoners now in employment and continuing to berequired by Departments to which allocated...      334,000Grand Total of Demands        ...      ...      565,000Notes (&apos;) These figures are subject to amendment and may be increased when Admiralty and ministry of Health estimates for 1946 are known.(2) This figure included some 52,000 prisoners required for civil engineering work (including such work as the demolition of Defence Works) on behalf of many different Departments asfollows :  Agriculture; Admiralty; Civil Aviation; Electricity Commissions; Education; Fuel and power; G.P.O.; Home Office, Health; Scottish Office; Supply; Trade; War Transport.ANNEX B.The present allocation of prisoners is asUser Department.Agriculture (including Scotland)Air MinistryAdmiraltyFood ......Fuel and Power   ...G.P.0.......Health      ......SupplyWar Office (including prisoners working for Directorate of Labour, those oncamp duties and W.D. and camp con-structionWar TransportWorks       ...Miscellaneous employment from BaseCamps, &amp;c.follows :-Italians.66,0009,8002,0506,1501,37015038014,40034,00014,2004,500Germans.108,7502,4001006,30032,1501,00027,0003,050Total.174,7509,8002,0508,5501,47015038020,70066,15015,20031,5003,050Totals153,000180,750333,750



</content>
</cab>
