<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/5/0 images: 332-337</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS TH&apos;B PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1945. 156SECRET. Copy No.  3.CP. (46) 338.IliA December, 1945. .CABINET.UNITED NATIONS FOOD AND AGRICULTURE CONFERENCE,QUEBEC.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate to my colleagues the attached despatch by the Minister of State,who headed the United Kingdom delegation, summarising the proceedings of theUnited Nations Food and Agriculture Conference held at Quebec from the16th October to the 1st November, 1945.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,11th December, 1945.REPORT BY THE MINISTER OF STATE.I submit herewith a summary report on the First Session of the Food and agriculture Organisation of the United Nations held at Quebec from the16th October to the 1st November, 1945, which I attended as delegate for theUnited Kingdom. Mr. Herbert Broadley, Second Secretary, Ministry of Food,was appointed Alternate Delegate. The debates on food and agricultural policy are not summarised in this report.Constitution.2. The Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture, set up by the HotSprings Conference in 1943, had prepared the agenda and documents for theConference. An efficient Secretariat had been assembled under Mr. Walter Sharpof the Interim Commission.3. The Constitution of the Food and Agriculture Organisation, which hadbeen drawn up by the Interim Commission, became effective with the signature ofthe required twenty members. In fact twenty-three nations had accepted andsigned the Constitution on the 16th October. As both Mr. Broadley and myselfwere unable to reach Quebec in time for the opening ceremony, Mr. Roger Makins.the United Kingdom Representative on the Interim Commission, signed on behalfof His Majesty&apos;s Government. When the session ended on the 1st November, theorganisation had forty-two members.4.   Mr. Pearson (Canada) was nominated Chairman of the Conference.5. General discussion began on the 18th October. Before the debate beganthe United States member read to the Conference a message of support from thePresident of the United States. In the general discussion the United Statesmember (Mr. Clinton Anderson, Secretary for Agriculture in the United StatesGovernment) made a particularly forceful speech proclaiming full supoort forthe Food and Agruculture Organisation by the United States Government.Notable contributions were also made by the members from Canada, Australia,South Africa, New Zealand and India.6.   It was agreed that French and English would be the working languagesand that English, French, Spanish, Chinese and Russian would be the officiallanguages.    Although the Soviet Union did not join the Organisation at theFirst Session, of the Conference, Russian was left in as an official language in[31039] b
accordance with the practice of the Preparatory Commission of the united nations.7. I arrived in Quebec on the 19th October and addressed the Conferenceon the 20th October. I declared that His Majesty&apos;s Government was resolved togive the work of the Food and Agriculture Organisation its full support. Istressed the fact that the Conference was setting up the first long-term Qrganisa-tion associated with the United Nations, and therefore establishing importantprecedents, but that it also had an opportunity of making an immediate contri-bution to the recovery of the world. I defined the task of the Conference asthree-fold: first, to establish the machinery of the Food and agriculture organisation, and here I stressed the importance of the closest possible integra-tion with other United Nations organisations. Secondly, to establish animmediate programme for the first Director-General. Thirdly, to direct theattention of Governments and peoples to the necessity of a long term programme for food and agriculture.8. October or November were chosen as months in which the conference should hold its Regular Sessions. The size of the Executive Committee was setat 15; and it was decided that the seat of the Food and Agriculture organisation should be in the same place as the headquarters of the United Nations Organsia-tion, and that, in the meanwhile, it should be in Washington. It was recom-mended that included on the agenda of the next session should be the integration of the rules of the Food and Agriculture Organisation with the rules of other united Nations organisations and the broadening of conditions of eligibility, for membership of the Executive Committee.9. It was agreed that the Food and Agriculture Organisation should usecommon services to be provided by the United Nations Organisation and thatthe United Nations Organisation should exercise advisory functions in regardto the Food and Agriculture Organisation budget. Discussions of finance ingeneral were tentative owing to the many uncertain factors. As regards staffing,it was agreed that the Food and Agriculture Organisaton should conform tothe general plan of the United Nations Organisation, and that its staff shouldbe part of the International Civil Service. The Director-General was given thegreatest possible discretion in the selection of staff.10. The Director-General was given full powers to establish relations withother non-governmental or inter-governmental agencies.11. I stressed the importance of the Food and Agriculture Organisationacquiring full control of the inter-governmental bodies which had been working in the field of the Food and Agriculture Organisation, and in respect of someof these bodies recommendations were adopted. I drew attention to the advantages of the organisation paying the travelling expenses of delegates to meetings, and suggested that the organisation should contribute to the expenses of missionswhich it sent out. I strongly emphasised the necessity of the Food and Agricul-ture Organisation being concentrated with the other special agencies at the headquarters of the Food and Agriculture Organisation. I also suggested asimplification of the machinery of Committees. Finally, I stressed the importanceof ensuring that the peoples of the world should know and understand the workof the Food and Agriculture Organisation, and I explained the intention ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government to submit a White Paper to Parliament about theConference. I further expressed my confidence that unofficial bodies, such asthe National Farmers&apos; Union, the Agricultural Workers&apos; Union, the TradeUnion Congress, the United Nations Association, and other interested agencieswould do their best to help in the task of giving due publicity to the Food and agriculture Organisation and to the Conference and its work.The Director-General.12. The appointment of the Director-General was probably the mostimportant single item on the agenda of the conference. After a general discussion the Chairman of the General Committee palled for nominations, and six nameswere submitted privately. As a result of an unofficial poll Sir John Orr emergedas the preferred candidate. It had been tacitly agreed before the meeting bythe United States and British Governments that the Director-General of theFood and Agriculture Organisation should be drawn from a small advancedcountry rather than from one of the great Powers, and this agreement had beenreaffirmed in a conversation between Mr. Clinton Anderson and myself.Mr/Anderson said that he would not suggest an American name, and I told mr.. Anderson that Mr. Louwes (Netherlands) was the preferred candidate of
8 -    157His Majesty&apos;s Government, but Mr. Anderson doubted his capacity. This doubt was shared by other members of the Conference. The emergence of Sir John Orrwas therefore rather embarrassing. I made it clear in the General Committeethat the United Kingdom Delegation had not put forward his name and its firstvote would be given to Mr. Louwes. I found that members of the Conferencefrom the Commonwealth were strongly in favour of Sir John Orr. I took thefirst opportunity of placing the situation before Mr. Anderson in Washington.He at first expressed, considerable opposition to the appointment, but, after consulting the United States Cabinet, he gave his support to the nomination,largely, I believe, owing to the advocacy of Mr. Henry Wallace, Secretary ofCommerce. There can be no doubt that the appointment was very well received,both in the conference and throughout the British and American press.Political Notes on the Conference.13. The Soviet A attitude. The Soviet Government sent a large and experienced delegation to Quebec headed by M. Sergeev. In addition, compara-tively large delegations from the Byelo-Russian and Ukrainian S.S.R. werepresent as observers. It was announced in the press on the authority of the soviet delegation itself, that authority to sign the Constitution had been received, andthe Soviet Ambassador in Ottawa arrived in Quebec for the purpose. soviet representatives took part in the Conference, on the understanding that they couldnot participate in any division or vote. But on the 27th October M. Sergeevinformed the Chairman that the Soviet Government would not join the organisa-tion for the time being and asked him to make a statement to this effect. Themembers of the Soviet delegation, who had obviously prepared carefully for theconference, seemed to be disappointed, and their relations with other delegationsremained cordial to the end.14. M. Mikolajczyk and the Polish Delegation were particularly active atthe Conference; M. Mikolajczyk made no secret of the fact that, apart fromhis interest in the Food and Agriculture Organisation, he found a reason to payoccasional visits to Washington convenient. But the Yugoslav delegationabstained from voting in plenary meetings; at the close of the session the Yugoslavmember wrote a letter to the Chairman saying that in reality he had been present only as an observer. Nevertheless the Yugoslav Government had formallyaccepted the Constitution and are legally bound by it.15. The Argentine observer applied to the Chairman requesting the admis-sion of Argentina as a member of the organisation. To avoid controversy theChairman persuaded the Argentine member to apply to the Director-General,who will submit the application to the next session of the Conference.Conclusions.16. The Conference was remarkably successful for three reasons. Firstly,the careful preparations which had been made by the Interim Commission;secondly, the experience and authority of the Chairman, Mr. Pearson; thirdly,the enthusiasm of most of the delegations for the subject. The United kingdom delegation was generally able to put into effect the instructions which it hadreceived. But in the next critical twelve months it must retain the initiativeon certain questions, and, in particular, in regard to the absorption of the Inter-national Institute of Agriculture in Rome.17. There can be no doubt that the Director-General has the enthusiasticsupport of all the members of this most harmoniously established organisation.It is particularly important that His Majesty&apos;s Government should give /theDirector-General every support in the next twelve months.P. J. N.-B.[31039]
APPENDIX I.SIGNATURE OF THE FOOD AND AGRICULTURE ORGANISATIONCONSTITUTION.Countries who signed the Food and A griculture Organisation Constitution.Australia.Belgium.Canada.China.Czechoslovakia.Denmark.Dominican Republic.Egypt.France.Greece.Honduras.Iceland.India.Iraq.Liberia.Luxembourg.Netherlands.New Zealand.Norway.Commonwealth of the Philippines.Union of South Africa.United Kingdom.United States.Countries who signed ad referendum to their Governments.Guatemala. Panama.Haiti. Peru.Mexico. Venezuela.Nicaragua.Countries who accepted the Constitution during the Conference and sentdelegations.Brazil. Poland.Colombia. Yugoslavia (who accepted butCuba. did not sign the Constitu-tion).Countries who accepted the Constitution but were not represented bydelegations.Ecuador. Paraguay.Bolivia. Uruguay.Countries who were represented by observers.Soviet Union.Countries who were members of the United Nations but were not members ofthe Interim Commission and who were invited to send observers.Syria    &quot;J applied for membership The Ukraine.\ and   were   admitted Byelo-Russia.Lebanon j   during the Conference. Argentina.
APPENDIX II.United Kingdom Delegation.Member Philip J. Noel-Baker, Minister of State, Foreign Office, London.A Iternate H. Broadley, Second Secretary, Ministry of Food, London.Associates R. F. Bretherton, Principal Assistant Secretary, Raw Materials Department,Ministry of Supply, London.P. N. R. Butcher, Assistant Secretary, Ministry of Health, London.C. H. Campbell, First Secretary, Embassy of the United Kingdom,Washington.H. G. Champion, Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, London; ImperialForestry Institute, University of Oxford.Sir Jack Drummond, Scientific Adviser, Ministry of Food, London.A. N. Duckham, Agricultural Attache, Embassy of the United Kingdom,Washington; Adviser, Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture.P. D. H. Dunn, Principal Assistant Secretary, Fisheries Department,Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, London.R. R. Enfield, Principal Assistant Secretary, Economics Division, Ministryof Agriculture and Fisheries, London.J. E. S. Fawcett, Assistant Legal Adviser, Foreign Office, London.A. Glen, Deputy Secretary, Department of Agriculture for Scotland,Edinburgh.R. Gushue, Chairman of the Newfoundland Fisheries Board, St. Johns.D. A. E. Harkness, Senior Assistant Secretary, Ministry of Agriculture,Northern Ireland, Belfast.H. O. Hooper, Assistant Secretary, Ministry of Production, British RawMaterials Mission, Washington.M. I. Hutton, Deputy Secretary, Ministry of Food, London; Head of BritishFood Mission in North America; United Kingdom Member of Combined food board, Washington.H. W. Jack, Assistant Agricultural Adviser, Colonial Office, London.J. A. Lovern, Senior Scientific Officer, Department of Scientific andIndustrial Research, London.R. Makins, Minister Plenipotentiary, Embassy of the United Kingdom,Washington; Member of the Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture.B. S. Platt, Director of Human Nutrition Research Unit, Medical research council, London.R. Rae, Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, Education and AdvisoryDivision, London.E. L. Sykes, Office of the High Commissioner, Ottawa.J. G. Tahourdin, Private Secretary to the Minister of State, Foreign Office,London.T. M. Wilson, Principal, Treasury, London.Advisers E. G. Gooch, President of the National Union of Agricultural Workers;Member of Parliament, London.Sir John Orr, Director of Rowett Institute, Aberdeen; Member ofParliament, London.J. Turner, President of the National Farmers&apos; Union of England and Wales,London.Joint Secretaries P. Chantler, Cabinet Offices, London.Kay M. Midwinter, Foreign Office, London.J. E. Wall, Director of External Relations, Ministry of Food, London.Assistant Secretary Sybil G. Bach, Ministry of Food, London.


</content>
</cab>
