<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/5/0 images: 354-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1945.SECEET.Copy -No.CP. (45) 341.Vlth December, 1945.CABINET.GERMAN PRISONERS OF WAR.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service.AS invited by the Cabinet on the 6th December (CM. (45) 60th Conclusion,Minute 5 (1)), I have, in consultation with the other Departments concerned,explored further the possibility of supplementing the supply of prisoner-of-warlabour in this country by bringing prisoners of war from the United States. since that date a new situation has arisen in respect of our holding of German prisoners in the British zone in Germany and I report on this below. In the light of myenquiries about the transfer of prisoners from North America and of the new situation in Germany, I make the following proposals : (1) The German prisoners in Canada should be brought to this country as quickly as possible, the aim being to have them all here not later thanthe end of March;(2) Every effort should be made to reach agreement with the United states authorities to enable us to begin bringing here as soon as possible as many of the German prisoners in the United States as we can transport and accommodate;(3) The Minister of Works, in collaboration with the Secretary of State forWar, should be invited to do everything possible to increase the accom-modation available for extra prisoners before the end of March above.the present estimate of 45,000;(4) The Secretary of State for War and the Minister of War transport should be invited to do everything possible to expedite the programme for repatriating Italians in order to increase the accommodation available up to the end of March for incoming Germans;(5) The Minister of Labour, in collaboration with, the other ministers concerned, should be invited, as a matter of urgency, to explore further the possibility of arranging for the maximum number of German,prisoners to be held in Norway for transfer to this country whentransport and accommodation are available;(6) The Minister of Labour, in collaboration with the Secretary of Statefor War, and the Ministers of War Transport and Works, should ensure that the necessary preparations are put in hand now to enable us to bring and accommodate here as quickly as possible after theend of March such German prisoners as we are then holding inGermany and Norway.Prisoners in North America.2.   The following prisoners are held either by us or on cur behalf in north america : &apos;CanadaUnited States33,000175,000208,000[31055]
3. The difficulties we have to face in bringing these prisoners here are dueto shortages of transport and accommodation.. Briefly, the position is as follows : Transport.(1) All the Germans in Canada (33,000) could be brought here by the endof March without difficulty. Thereafter, owing to the cessation ofthe Canadian repatriation programme, we could only bring any whowere left behind very much more slowly and possibly at the expenseof other commitments.(2) It is understood that the policy of the United States Authorities is toget all German prisoners, the 175,000 of ours and their own, out of theUnited States as soon as possible. Subject to negotiations with theUnited States Authorities (which, it is hoped, will not be difficult orprolonged), we could now start bringing the 175,000 prisoners inthe United States direct to this country. If only accommodation wereavailable for them here, a very large number, perhaps all, could,it is hoped, be brought here by the end of March. From then on,however, shipping will cease to be available to any material extentbecause of the cessation of the United States repatriation programme.* Moreover, it is probable that any prisoners not brought to this country by then, would have been sent back to Germany by the United states authorities in furtherance of their policy of getting rid of all prisoners from the United States as soon as possible.Accommodation.(3) Until the end of March it is estimated by the Ministry of Works andthe War Office that we can accommodate here no more than about45,000 extra prisoners. Over and above this we can accommodateGermans in replacement of the Italians who leave the country. Bythe end of March it is estimated that some 35,000 Italians will have gone. Until the end of March, therefore, we can bring to this country. from North America, owing to lack of accommodation, not more than80,000 Germans. Thereafter we cannot expect this source of supply to be any longer available to us.4. It is clearly right that we should make the utmost use of the prisoners in North America, and with this in view I make the recommendations inparagraph 1 (1) to (4).Prisoners in the British Zone in Germany.5. For some months we have been holding in the British zone in Germany225,000 prisoners against the possible need to transfer them here for employment.No transport has been available to bring them here up to now.6. It has always been recognised that the holding of these prisoners might lead to serious difficulties for the Control Commission (see CP. (45) 172, para-graph 1 (9) and paragraph 15). At the end of November this situation suddenlyarose in the following circumstances : 7. Primarily owing to lack of accommodation in the British zone inGermany, it has been and still is impossible to hold more than a small proportionof these men in prisoner-of-war camps. They have been held as disarmed troopsin concentration areas in the British zone controlled and administered by german officers and staffs under the direction of British formations. At the end ofNovember the policy Of holding this force in this way came under the strongestopposition from the Russians, who demanded that the other three Powers should send a mission to the British zone to see whether the Potsdam terms in regardto this matter were being carried out. At a meeting of the Control Council theRussians received some support from the American Commander-in-Chief and field-Marshal Montgomery telegraphed urgently seeking authority to disbandthese units. There was considerable publicity in the press about this incidenceand questions were asked in the House of Commons. A very early decision wasnecessary and, in face of the need to put ourselves right in relation to the potsdam Agreement, instructions, in which the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and I concurred, were sent last week to Field-Marshal Montgomerywhich provide as follows : (1) He is to proceed with the disbandment of the Germans held as disarmedtroops.
(2) He will take other steps to ensure that there are available in germany for transfer to this country the maximum number of german prisoners as from the end of March 1946. He is able to give aguarantee that the number of German prisoners thus available willnumber not less than 125,000, and there are excellent reasons for believing that the number will, in fact, not be less than 165,000.Every effort is to be made by the Control Commission to make thenumber of prisoners thus available as high as possible within theoriginal target figure of 225,000.8. It may prove practicable to arrange to hold in Norway for transfer tothis country, when transport and accommodation are available, some 30-40,000German prisoners now in that country. This possibility is being examined asa matter of urgency with the other Departments concerned. I am also in con-sultation with the Secretary of State for War and the Ministers of war transport and Works in order to ensure that the necessary steps are put inhand at once to enable us to bring and accommodate here as quickly as possible after the end of March such German&apos; prisoners as we are then holding inGermany and Norway. Until then we can bring none because, quite apart fromthe continuing transport difficulties, we shall need all the accommodation whichcan be made available in this country for the prisoners to be brought from north america. After the end of March the accommodation position here may beexpected to be materially easier, but it must be recognised that shortages oftransport and accommodation will almost certainly continue to restrict our capacity rapidly to absorb prisoners in large numbers from the Continent even after March.Allocation of available prisoners.9. If my proposals are approved it will be necessary to give early considera-tion to the question how prisoners are in future to be allocated between departments in the light of the new situation regarding the probable availability of prisoners in 1946, and I propose to submit a further memorandum on this very shortly. If we proceed as I propose, the probable position regarding the availability of German prisoners in 1946 can be summarised as follows : Germans now here and in employment     ...      ... 182,000Germans held here by United States Army and to betransferred to us         ...      ...      ...      ... 15,000Germans to be brought here from Canada and united States    ............... 80,000Germans  to   be   brought  here   from   Germany(probable figure)          ......      ... 165,000442,000Less &apos;&apos; white &apos;&apos; Germans who may be repatriated(see CM. (45) 45th Conclusions, Minute 2)   ...        20,000422,000Plus, possibly, German prisoners to be brought from norway   ..................   30-40,000452-462,000This compares with the numbers of prisoners in employment during 1945 of334,000 Germans and Italians, i.e., an increase in 1946 of anything from 90,000-130,000. The estimate in my memorandum of the 26th November (see cp. (45) 305, paragraph 6) was a total labour force not exceeding 430,000.G. A. I.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,17th December, 1945.


</content>
</cab>
