<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/3/21 images: 329-05 December 1939</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
Printed for the War Cabinet. December 1939
SECRET. - Copy No.
W.P. (G.) (39) 133.
WAR CABINET.
S U G A R A N D MEAT.
Memorandiim by the First Lord of the Admiralty.
I CIRCULATE a note on these subjects to my colleagues.
w. s. c.
December 5, 1939.
SUGAR.
W E were told early in October that stocks of sugar in the country, plus
sugar purchased, amounted to 10 months' consumption at normal rates, i.e., that
they would enable us to carry on till early in August.
It seems that under the continued threat of rations, 20 per cent, over and
above normal is still being purchased, which reduces the 10 months by over
7 weeks. An allowance for exports means a further reduction of 3 weeks, and
it now appears that the Queensland crop will not be delivered until the second
half of 1940, which cuts off another 2&#189; weeks. The position is aggravated by the
new demand for a floating stock of 250,000 to 400,000 tons, about 5 to 8 weeks
supply, to facilitate distribution.
Our stocks in October are thus reduced from 10 months supply to only
5 or 6 months' effective supply, while, the fact that our " stocks " will contimie
to arrive in the country until June means that we shall begin to run short in
January or February, unless further sugar is bought. It is in this way that the
case for early rationing is developed.
There are two points to be considered in relation to this. It the public
really continue buying at the rate foreseen, then, unless consumption also is
abnormal, everv family will, on the average, possess 4 or 5 weeks' supply of sugar
when the shortage occurs, say, 30^0 pounds. This is not a healthy or welldistribiitecl
form'of reserve. It is none the less a reserve.
A much more important point is, that is was obvious from the first that it
normal consumption was to be allowed to continue, foreign sugar would have to
he bouo-ht. One cannot live for 12 months on a 10 months' supply. If 2 months
consumption is required as a floating stock, 4 months' consumption of sugar was
Quired, say 700 000 tons costing &#163;8,400.000. This being so. it would not have
been difficult' to arrange the deliveries so that no shortage should occur until
October, when our own crops begin to be available.
On the other hand, the"Ministrv have now come forward with the arguments
that ifw can cut down the people's consumption of sugar, we can save shipping e
and foreign exchange. This is a matter not of food, but offinancial policy.
f20433]
MEAT.
I n the papers of the Home Policy Committee, considered in October, estimates
were presented according to which the home production and imports were expected
t o be practically normal. Since the population of the country has not changed
since the war, the only excess consumption arises from the fact that, averaged
over the year, say, 1,000,000 men more than usual have joined the Services and
are enjoying the abnormally high meat ration issued therein. The extra
consumption is about 4 per cent, of the total, and by itself is therefore no
argument for rationing meat. .
On the other hand, extra demands were made m order to build up a reserve.
I t was held that this was unnecessary, as we had well over a year's reserve in our
home stocks of cattle.
I t was further stated that there were commitments to the Jbrench of somewhat
uncertain amount. . .
According to the papers now presented, the position has altered somewhat, as
the farmers have been slaughtering their cattle (a) because the good grass enabled
them to fatten them quickly, (b) because of the failure to import feeding-stuffs
which affects this winter. Averaged over the next 6 months, a shortage of 12,000
tons per month (6^ per cent.) is expected owing to this.
For some not very clearly explained reason, a shortage of imports, amounting
to 10.000 tons a month (5i per cent.) is now predicted. Thus a shortage of
22,000 tons a month-about 12 per cent.betveen now and the 1st June is
foreseen bv the Ministry of Food.
The present stock of meat amounts to 70,000 tons, and the Ministry desires
in the next three months to build this u p to a reserve of 150,000 tons. This means
taking 27,000 t o n s - a b o u t 14 per c e n t . - i n each of the three coming months, but
nothing in the three after that.
I n addition, apparently (though here the figures are difficult to follow)
10 000 tons a month-about 5t per cent.^-are to be supplied to the French.
Roughly, therefore, the Ministry expect in the coming six months a denciency
which may, broadlv speaking, be accounted for as follows : '
Per cent.
Extra rations for 1,000,000 new men in Services ... 4
(a) Allocated to Reserve ... ... ... ... ... 7
(b) Supplies to French ... ... ... 5\
Diminution of Home Supply ... ...
(c) Deficiency in Import ... ... ... ... ... 5A
m
Items (a) and (b), amounting to 11-j per cent., are policy, and item (r) may
be pessimistic.
But obviously, if 28-^ per cent, less meat is distributed, the average
consumption must drop by about ^, say, from 28 oz. to 20 oz.
</content>
</cab>
