<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/6 images: 66-73</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 306.10th July, 1943.      -WAR CABINET.REBUILDING OF STALINGRAD.Memorandum by the Minister of Production.THE Soviet Ambassador has written to protest against the d gcisioh aboutthe rebuilding of Stalingrad conveyed to him by the Foreign Secretary (see.P. (43) 256). Annexed are copies of the Soviet Ambassadors letter and ofmy reply.O. L.Ministry of Prodxiction, \0th July, 1943.M. Maisky to Mr. Eden.My dear Foreign Secretary, 30th June, 1943.I must confess that I received your letter of the 17th June,No. N 3440/3186/38, with very considerable disappointment. The letter says:&quot; great though we recognise the needs of Stalingrad to be, you will certainlyagree that war production must come first.&quot; The letter further expresses theopinion that the programme of orders for Stalingrad &quot; is a very large one,&quot;although, as a matter of fact, this programme seems to me to be an extremelymodest one (one telephone exchange, five small mobile power stations, twohospitals). In reading your letter one cannot escape the impression that theAllied Supplies Executive have approached the request of Stalingrad in thespirit of an everyday routine business, and not very urgent at that. It looks asif the Allied Supplies Executive classified Stalingrad&apos;s request as one of the items in the great post-war reconstruction work which will include the restorationof hundreds of Soviet towns destroyed by the German invaders.I do not think that such an approach is justified. Stalingrad is not &quot;just one more of the Soviet towns which require restoration. Stalingrad is Stalingrad.Stalingrad is one of the greatest landmarks in human history as an unsurpassedexample of heroism and endurance, and as a turning-point in the present war.Indeed, suppose for a moment that Stalingrad in the autumn of 1942 wouldhave fallen : what would nave been the consequences % In this case the Germansmost probably would have been able to move north up the Volga, as Marshal Stalinindicated in his speech on the 6th November, 1942, with the most appallingconsequences for our defence. At the same time if Stalingrad had fallen theGermans would have moved down the Volga, swept through the Caucasus tothe Caspian Sea, occupied Baku, penetrated Iran, and moved towards thePersian Gulf and India. Simultaneously they would have overrun the wholeMiddle East and established their rule in Africa. Such would have been thevista of events that would have followed the fall of Stalingrad.But the superhuman courage and bravery of Stalingrad saved the worldfrom these grim prospects. Can we, under such circumstances, consider therequirements of Stalingrad as yet another routine order coming under thegeneral heading of post-war reconstruction? That would obviously be quiteinappropriate.  Stalingrad is quite an exceptional case and should be treated as[25719]Copy No.
such. Therefore it seems to me that, however pressing the war needs may be,there must be found a place for Stalingrad orders side by side with the war production within the framework of the British industries, and not at the bottom of the priority list but at the top.His Majesty The King showed a true appreciation of the quite unique status of Stalingrad in deciding to present this glorious city with a Sword of Honour.If I am rightly informed, this is the first precedent in your history that aSword of Honour has been bestowed upon a foreign town. Should the allied supplies Executive show less appreciation?Yours sincerely,J. MAISKY.Mr. Lyttelton to Soviet Charge d&apos; Affaires.My dear Minister, 7th July, 1943.THE Foreign Secretary has given me M. Maisky&apos;s letter of the 30th Juneabout the rebuilding of Stalingrad, because, as you know, I have now taken overthe Chairmanship of the Allied Supplies Executive.I am sorry to see from M. Maisky&apos;s letter that there appears to be a misunderstanding about the reasons which prompted the Foreign Secretary&apos;reply of the 17th June to the request that we should facilitate the placing ofcertain orders in this country for equipment to assist in the rebuilding of stalingrad.We have, as you will know, the utmost admiration in this country for theheroic defence of Stalingrad and are fully aware of the immense contribution which that defence made to our common war effort. But I am sure you would,on consideration, agree that it would be inconsistent with the spirit in which that defence was made, a spirit of subordination of all other considerations to thetask of defeating the enemy, for us to divert to the reconstruction of Stalingradresources which would otherwise be directed to essential and urgent war production. All our energies must be devoted to the prosecution of the war andthis, I am sure, will be as well understood by the Soviet people as it is by theBritish people.I fear therefore that we cannot alter our decision, but, as the foreign secretary told M. Maisky in his letter of the 17th June, we will put productionin hand so soon as the necessary labour, materials and productive capacity areavailable, and with this in view would be glad to discuss at once preparatorydetails.Yours sincerely,OLIVER LYTTELTON.







</content>
</cab>
