<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 86-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s GovernmentjPrinted for the Cabinet.  March 1922.SECRET.C.P.-3803.                                                                        o                                 CABINET.WEEKLY SURVEY  OF THE  STATE OP  IRELAND.             MEMORANDUM BY THE CHIEF  SECRETARY FOR IRELAND.    I SUBMIT for the consideration of the Cabinet my survey for the week ended the 27th ultimo.                       GENERAL STATE OF THE COUNTRY.Police Reports  of the Week.    As  stated in my  survey of last week, the number of outrages  reported by thepolice can no longer be taken as an index of the total amount of  lawlessness in thecountry. The Royal Irish Constabulary have now evacuated 474 of the 571 barracksheld by  them in Southern Ireland at the date of the Truce (the 11th July, 1921), and,outside  the six  Northern Counties, have practically ceased to function  as a police force.  Throughout the greater part of the country the Provisional  Government aremaintaining law and  order by the agency of the I.R.A., but in a  few districts suchas South Tipperary, where the extreme Republican section of that organisation is forthe moment in the ascendant, the authority not only of the Provisional Government,but also of the  present Dail Eireann Cabinet, is openly  flouted, and the conditions prevailing are something of the nature of a military tyranny.  In the Clonmel  district(South Tipperary) an attempt was recently made by a number of&apos; local tradesmen andshopkeepers to organise a meeting of protest  against the usurpation of civil authorityby a strong I.R.A. contingent whicli has established itself in. the evacuated militarybarrack of that town, and  is maintaining  itself by &quot;living  upon  the  country.&quot;Although the meeting was  suppressed by order of the I.R.A.  Commander, the factthat it was attempted to be held may be regarded as welcome evidence that the civilpopulation of Southern Ireland are not disposed to submit to violence and terrorism,and that the resort to such weapons to cornbat the Provisional  Government is notcalculated to advance the cause of the extremists at the  forthcoming elections.    The number of attacks upon the Crown Porces was much less than in recent weeks.   The only case of attempted murder was  the firing at a police constable atCastlerea, Co. Roscommon,  on the  20th ultimo. Fortunately the constable escapeduninjured, but I regret to state that his assailants have not been traced.  Apart fromthis outrage, the two most,serious breaches of the Truce were a raid upon the R.I.C.barrack at Kilkenny City on the 24th ultimo, in  which a quantity of  arms  andammunition, including a Lewis gun, 90 rifles, 108 revolvers and 8,019 rounds of small arms ammunition  were  stolen, and a raid on  Clonmel R.I.C. barrack on the  26thultimo,  resulting in the loss of 3 Lewis guns,  293 rifles and bayonets, 45 shot guns,230 revolvers, 206,500 rounds of rifle and 117,630  rounds of revolver ammunition,11 motor cars and a large quantity of clothing and other stores.  These raids were carried  out by the Clonmel brigade of the I.R.A., above mentioned, and one of their most unfortunate effects  will be to increase the difficulties of the Provisional Govern-ment in extending their authority over the South Tipperary district   It is clear thatthey could not have been carried out successfully without culpable negligence, if notconnivance, on the part of some members of the police garrisons, and a full enquiry is being held into the circumstances of both cases.   In the case of the Kilkenny raid,the arms were stored in an outhouse detached from the main building of the barrack.and the  raiders, if not assisted by treachery, must, have effected an entrance by stealthwithout being observed by the occupants of the barrack.  The raid on the Clonmelbarrack was carried out by a body of about 300 armed men, who obtained entrance to      [7974]
the barrack by the well-worn ruse of sending one of their  party  to  deceive  thebarrack orderly by impersonating a member of the garrison who was known to be out at the time.  The raiders  then rushed in in a body and overpowered the garrison(numbering about 100), all of  whom were unarmed, and then proceeded to remove thewhole store of arms and equipment contained in the barrack.   From the accurateknowledge of the interior of  the barrack displayed by the raiders, it is difficult to escape the suggestion that they werev aided in their enterprise  by members of thegarrison,  and this opinion is expressed, by the Deputy  Inspector-General in his report.    Two  arms raids upon private houses were reported during the week.   In one case, at Ramelton, Co. Donegal, one of the raiders was shot dead by the householder,a retired Colonel of the British army, and at a subsequent enquiry held by the I.R.A.the Colonel was exonerated from all blame and was given an assurance that he wouldbe fully protected against any attempts at retaliation.    Another interesting  sidelight  upon  the  present position  of the I.R.A. in southern  Ireland is furnished by the verdict of a coroner&apos;s inquest held at Milford,Co. Donegal, on the 23rd ultimo.   The deceased man, a civilian, was shot whileattempting to evade arrest, and the finding of the court was &quot; that  he was shot deadby Private        , I.R.A., in the discharge of his duty! &quot;                         STATE OF THE POLICE  FORCES.    The following figures show the present strength of the  Irish Police  Forces :                           Royal  Irish Constabulary.Strength on the 19th February, 1922    ...       ...       ...     9,169    Deaths during week      ...       ...       ...       5    Retirements      ...      ...       ...       ...     141    Resignations     ...      ...       ...       ...     Nil    Dismissals or discharges  ...       ...       ...       1                       Total wastage      ...     147Recruits         ...       ...      ...       ...     NilNet decrease     ...       ...       ...       ...     147      147Strength on the 26th February, 1922     ...       ...       ...     9,022    Note. The retirements represent the disbandment of 4 members of the Veterans&apos;&quot;Division and 137 members of the Regular Force recruited in Great Britain.  Thestrength of the Veterans&apos; Division is now reduced to 28.                         Dublin Metropolitan Police.    The strength of the Dublin Metropolitan Police remained unchanged  at 1,133during the week.                       THREATENED POST OFFICE STRIKE.    A formidable addition to the difficulties with which the Provisional Governmentfind themselves confronted is now impending in  the shape of a threatened strike ofthe operative staff of the Southern Irish Post Office.  The subject of the dispute is thewar bonus reduction, which came into force on the 1st instant under an agreement forperiodical revision of war bonuses made before the Irish Departments ceased to form part of the Imperial Civil Service.  The reduction is resisted on the ground that itis not  justified by the present cost of living, an argument  which,  of course, has no special application to Irish Civil Servants.  The Provisional Government appear  tobe determined to enforce the agreement, and have refused an offer by the Irish PostalUnion to refer the matter to a tribunal of Dail  Eireann.  An announcement issuedby the Union on the 28th ultimo states that the view is now held that a strike cannotbe averted.  &apos;                 PRESENT POLITICAL SITUATION IN IRELAND.    No further developments of the Southern Irish political situation have takenplace since the Ard Feis Agreement for holding  over the General Election until the drafting of the Free State Constitution has been completed.  Although  this agree-
ment at first sight had all the appearance of a tactical victory for Mr. de Valera, it isnow generally agreed that the postponement of the elections is not likely to have an adverse effect upon the prospects of the Free State Party, provided that the  Provi-sional Government is able to make full use of the three months&apos; delay to consolidateits position as the de facto Government of the  country and to effect a much-neededimprovement in its counter-propaganda to hostile criticism of the Treaty.  The firstproviso is the more important.   An election at the present time would be attended bya very  real danger of the intimidation of voters in the South-Western Counties bythe extremist section of the I.R.A., and this consideration was no doubt the main reason  which induced Mr. Griffith and Mr. Collins to assent to the delay.  It is not thought that Mr. de Valera or others of the responsible leaders of  the opposition would countenance the employment of physical force or intimidation  to defeat thefree expression of the will of the people, and public opinion looks to them to co-operate with the Provisional Government at least to the extent of averting this scandal.  Themost effective propaganda in favour of the Treaty  which has appeared for  several weeks is to be found  in the Lenten Pastorals of  the Irish Bishops issued last Sunday.Perhaps the most striking of these announcements was that of Dr. Fogarty, Bishopof-Killaloe, who roundly  stated that the bulk of the people were &quot; sick and tired ofwar &quot; and that &quot; unless they were careful they might find themselves one day withouteither Treaty or Republic.&quot; An  equally significant warning was that of Dr. Kelly,Bishop  of Ross, who stated that &apos;; if the police  and  soldiers  usurp  legislative orjudicial powers, they will slay  liberty,  and Ireland will be subjected to militarytyranny, which, next to mob tyranny, is the worst of all tyrannies.&quot;                                                                      H.  G:    Irish Office, Old Queen Street, S.W. 1.
STATEMENT showing Total Number of Serious Outrages from January 1,  1919, to                                   January 14, 1922.Weekly Totals to Week ended February 25, 1922, and Totals at that date.Nature of Outrage.	Totals from Jan. 1, 1919, to Jan. 14, 1922.	Week ended 						Totals to Feb. 25, 1922.		Jan. 21, 1922.	Jan. 28, 1922.	Feb. 4,1922. &apos;	Feb. 11, 1922. &apos;	Feb. 18, 1922.	Feb. 25, 1922.	Courthouses destroyed 11.1.0. vacated barracks destroyed R.1.C vacated barracks damaged .. R.I.C. occupied barracks destroyed R.I.C. occupied barracks damaged or captured Raids on mails .. Raids on coastguard stations and light-houses Raids for arms Raids on offices of rate collectors and Petty Sessions clerks Policemen killed Policemen wounded .. Policemen fired at, &amp;c. .. Soldiers killed Soldiers wounded . Soldiers fired at, &amp;c. Civilians killed .. .. Civilians wounded Totals .. ...	89 528 125 25 268 2,568 100 3,237 122 408 697 Not recorded 150 348 Not recorded &apos; 197 186	1 * * 3 8 2	* * 4 * * 2 6 * * 1 2	3 1 2	2 1 5 12 5 8. 2 1 1	1 1 5 1 2 1	8 . 1 2 1 2	89 524 125 25 270 2,569 100 3,248 122 417* 720f 158 .352 201 187	9,045	14	15	6	32	11	9	9,102    * This figure includes ten Special Constables.    t This figure includes twenty-three Special Constables.    I These  figures  do not, include casualties in Ulster  riots during period from June 1920 to the22nd November, 1921, the date on which Executive Authority was transferred by His Majest\&apos;s Govern-ment to the Government rf  Northern Ireland; twenty civilian deaths  occurred in the Londonderry  riots and 146 deaths in the Belfast riots.    N.B. The above  particulars do  not include outrages of a kind  which  are not now being committed,e.g., 119 raids on revenue offices, which occurred during the months of April and iVIay 1920,  and resulted  inthe destruction xif  many official documents and  much other public property.   They also  do not includeminor forms of outrages (e.r/., intimidation, cattle-driving, &amp;c.) or any outrages committed in Northern Irelandsince the 22nd November, 1921.O

</content>
</cab>
