<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 90-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3 3 0 R 31.0.P.-3804.                  0 A B I If El,                    g HE   IK A Q   T R E A T Y.           Circulated by the Secretary of State for the colonies.          .    -  PARAPHRASE T3LEGRAM from the High Commissioner                for Iraq to the Secretary of State  for  the                    Colonies, dated 27th February,  1922..            (Received Colonial Office 3/51 p..m. let March,  1922).    Ho.163 of 27thFebruary.          Treaty&apos;with Psisal.   As I informed you in my telegrams    815 - and- 816 (both) Faisal and Nagib&apos; and especially  the  latter    pressed with great insistence for definite abrogation of    mandate.     Major Young will be able to supploment  my reports    :in this resect.  -  Since receipt of your telegram  No. 87  I  have    discussed Subject fully with them and both verbally and in    writing have explained to them the position of  His  Majesty&apos;s    Government and your OTO point of view as set forth  in your    telegrams and letters.   In an attempt to oiroumvent senti-    mental diffio ult y I have also suggested alternative draft    treaties,&apos; but they maintain their previous attitude u. changed    in spite of all my efforts.          I have now-received from Faisal a long letter setting    .forth his final views.   He starts with his conversations    *ith you in London&apos; ani covers all the ground.   This letter    and our-discussions come to :this ;&apos;.&apos;- Faisal end Haqib are    definitely o:; the opinion that neither on line  indicated    by your modifications nor by alternative which you  propose  is    it possible for than to proceed with treaty,    It  is clear,    they contend, tiiat in either case it&apos; is still intended  to    maintain mandatory relation.   They are unvrilling to accept this in    principle, and it ma:ce.s no difference whether it la expressed    explicitly or in a camouflaged1 form.          Their view may be SAprssed in this way:  &quot;Our desiro    for Great 3ritain is si no ere our need for  friendship and
assistance is clamorous-   7/e want no one but Great Britain,but we want her not as a mandatory but as an Ally and friend,His Majesty King George, in telegram with which he honoured meon day of my accession seems to have contemplated this.  At thetime when the idea and conditions of r;Jxarae.tory&quot; were formulated by Entente powers they may hove been reasonable and possible.Since then, however&amp;r, much has happened, and - to mention only onechange - there has been an enormous increase in the strength of nationalist sentiment throughout islam.   Consequently intelligentopinion in this country can no longer willingly tolerate mandatoryrelation especially now that public have seen in what manner aparallel mandate has been interpreted or misinterpreted by Frenchfor whose prasenoe in Syria, with its effect on Asrsui tsa^aao,Great Britian is morally responsible.   If you will give us  a frankand free treaty and complete independence you will find that everything you need for preservation of your own position and interests and welfare of foreigners is yours; if, on the otharhand, you insist on &quot;the proposal to &quot;mandate&quot; us I and Naqibcannot accept Gdium and responsibility of being associated withsuch a polioy and you will need an army strong enough to impose yourwill upon an unwilling people.  If, in her own interests or becauseof her under takings towards-other Powers, Great Britain feelsobliged to insist on pressing upon Iraq, a treaty on line indicated by Secretary of Staters modifications His Majesty^ Governmentmay prefer (since I and Naqib cannot ,accept the task) to ask thenational assembly  when it is convened, to consider treaty.    Wecould not oppose such a decision but the only remit of such acourse would be, in our opinion, to let loose a storm of controversyupon the country and we oannot say what the result of reference orof the consequent delay would be&quot;.      In answer to above I have used the arguments                                                        with
with Tv-bi.cn you furnished rae in your -communications^and inaddition I have, arguod somewhat as follows :  If great britain and Iraq only were concerned, I am convinced that-JEtis&apos;&apos;Ma jo sty&apos;s Government would, if only for her own convenience,res-pond to Iraqrs aspirations towards freodom to utmost in &quot;-spite of proverbial danger of patching oil garments with newcloth provided that they.were left in a position of sufficientinfluence to safeguard their own reasonable interests and en-sure proper treatment of.foreigners.  In point of fact, how-ever, abrogation of raandato may well be politically impossi-blo for Croat Britain vis-a-vis her allies and League ofNations too, since other mandatories and interests cf those(1 group) may be affected by any action taken in regard toIraq.  In reply to this they express thir firm conviction that Groat Britain can cot rid of mandate if she wishes.  Thisis in spite of the views, policy ana arguments of His ISajesty^sGovernment which I have not failed, to place clearlybefore them.     My own comment is as follows:  Our attitude appearsto mo to. be weak, in this that premises on; which it. isbased, however sound at one time, are sound no longer, andI think we need to reconsider situation with all (1 group)on basis of actualities.     it the time when the Kandato relationship wasdevised it seemed reasonable and even benevolent in idea,name and form.  Since then, however, situation has changedgreatly.  On one hand wo find ourselves in a state ofincreasingly severe financial stress; on. the other hand astrong wave of nationalism is passing over oast.  Althoughowing to absolute necessity of reducing our expenditure and withdrawing our troops, we are no longer in a positioneither to fulfil our obligations u..ic&quot;ler mandate in directionof defence or to enforce it if people of Iraq are unwilling, ,;;e still seem to. cling/                           .-3-
oling to the idea that we are performing a duty to humanityby maintaining mandatory relation..  A oonside-rable^proportion,of people of Iraq, are no doubt inarticulate,  as for ihe rest, the moderate and pro-British party will find it verydiffioult to run counter to expressed opinion of Naqib andif we asked them to do so we Should be putting their loyalty to us to too great a strain, while it may be taken for granted that small but potent element of intelligentsia will support and out-vie the attitude of JPalsal.  When it became kno-nn that not only Faisal but our staunch supporter the Haqib had been unable to come to an understanding with His MajestyTs Government&apos;,the alternative of leaving the Treaty for consideration ofNational Assembly would I am convinoad offer no likelihood ofa different result.  We should have very strong public feeling against us by the time the Assembly mat and decision of assembly would I think be a foregone conclusion.  Moreover work generallywill be paralysed until Treaty is concluded or at all eventsuntil terms are agreed upon between King and&apos; ourselves, andthe question of British personnel, which hinges upon Treaty,.and the Organic Law will be hung up.  It seems to me, therefore,that before we go further His  Majesty &quot;s Government must re-view the situation seriously and come to a final decision onthis fundamental question of policy,  hegard being had toour admitted inability and disinclination to force any solution on Iraq, and with fresh experience of Ireland and egypt before us, it seems to me that, we must consider whether we are or are not in a position to go to our Allies and theLeague of Nations and say In effect;        &quot;In practioe we have fulfilled our mandatoryduties to Iraq for three years.  The form of -Mandate asfirst contemplated is now out of data and has moreover been                                    interpreted
interpreted by France as circumstances seened to her to demand, the League of Nations in still ineffective and meanwhile the internal situation irt Iraq has been developingquiokly and satisfactorily and v/e cannot stop this process.Our sole object is to do our duty by tho people of Iraqwhile maintaining sufficient influence to ensure that le/ri-legitimate British interests and welfare of foreigners in country are safeguarded.- We have never had any otherdeaigns in Iraq,  v/e consider that both from our own pointof view and that of people of Irafr this end can best beachieved if our future relations are formulated in a treatyof alliance (l group) as between two independent states.The terras which have been agreed upon between the two parties are now coLimunicatea (1  group).&quot;-  My object in expressingmyself so fully on such  a point (and I do so with greatdiffidence) is in order  that you may know in what directionI am thinking. . It&apos; is my personal conviction that it isonly in this- direction that we  oan expect to find success.Considering impossibility of adopting any costly policy inIraq it seems in view of attitude of British tax-payermore prudent to secure good-will of Iraqis by giving them what they want the onus  of failure thus remaining on them,than to adopt any policy which  would probably&apos; have  contraryeffect.:.       This refers to your tele gran ITo * &apos; 87 and subsequent

</content>
</cab>
