<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 118-120</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUM BNT  IS  THE PROPERTY ^r^HE BR IT A N SIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT .                            CABINET.                   UNEMPLOYI.GSNT RELIEF WORKS.JET,                             &quot; -5812,          MEM OR A KB DM PY THE MINISTER OF HEALTH.     L .G , 71.          I circulate for the Information of my colleaguesa summary of the reports on Relief Works undertaken by LocalAuthorities with assistance from the Unemployment GrantsCommittee, made as a result of the inspections so far under-taken in accordance with Conclusion 7 (b) of Cabinet 8 (22).A. MOND. March 7th, 1922.Ministry of Health,
           Inspectors Reports on..Unemployment Schemes.          Up to the 17th February 78 Unemployment Schemes harebeen  Inspected and reported upon by Inspectors of the Ministry.          The works inspected are distributed over all parts ofthe country, and apart from the fact that in almost all casesthe output is reported to be very considerably below normal -a result to beexpected having regard to the classes of men employed - the reports indicate that the works are generallybeing carried out properly and. efficiently and withoutdifficulties or disturbance.          There are very few cases where a Local Authority isdeparting - knowingly or otherwise - from either the conditionsof grant or the Ministry of Health approved plans.  In almost every case reported on, the men are engaged through theEmployment Exchange with the usual preferences to ex-servicemen and men with large families.          The effect on unemployment of a particular scheme;which may itself employ only a few men, is usually Impossibleto estimate; but in a large number of cases the Inspectorsreport that the combined effect of the various UnemploymentSchemes In a particular neighbourhood is felt in the creationof a better state of feeling amongst the unemployedf and in a stoppage of deputations and demonstrations.         &apos;The. following information regarding the schemesreported on is extracted from the reports:-  (1)  Of the 78 schemes, 19 are being carried out wholly by       contract, 5 partly by contract and partly by direct       labour, and 54 wholly by direct labour.  (2)  The work on the schemes Is in.all stages of progress;       10 schemes are completed, several others are hardly       commenced.  (3)  Intermittent labour is employed on 33 schemes.  The       length of continuous employment varies considerably.
     In some  cases  men are  on 2  days  and  off  2  days;   In others     they are kept  on for as  long  as  four weeks at  a  time.(4)   Quality  and output are reported  as both  normal In 20 cases     (14 contract;   5 direct  labour,  and  1 partly both) .    In     another  case carried out partly  by Contract and  partly by direct     labour,  quality and output  are both  normal for tho contract     portion, but output Is only 15%  normal in  the  direct labour     portion.   Quality Is  reported as below  normal in only 7 cases     (all direct labour).   Output is reported  below  normal in     43 direct labour schemes and  1 contract  scheme.&apos;(5)   Except  in the  case of  one Local  Authority, the labour  is     engaged  through the Employment Exchanges..   In thie. dafte     (7 schemes) the Local  Authority  and  the  Guardians have their     own Register of Unemployed.  Tho consent  *,f the Unemployment     Grants  Committee has been obtained to thi3 unusual procedure.(6)   In two  cases the Poor  Law scale  of relief  is so: high that a     man with 5 children would obtain west when not working than     when working.(7)   Only two Local Authorities  (Uxbridge U.D.;and  Leeds,)  wero     found to be breaking the wage conditions of grant.  This was.     due to  a misreading of a Circular,

</content>
</cab>
