<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 185-185</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property  of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.                                                                ASECRET.CP.  3825.THE  CABINET.ARMY ESTIMATES,  1922-23.Question   of  Inclusion  in  Army  Vote  A  of  Indian  (Native)      Troops  in  Iraq and  Palestine to  be  administered  by  the      Air Ministry.     MEMORANDUM BY  THE  SECRETARY  OE STATE FOR WAR.    The War Office has received from the Treasury a letter, dated 8th March, sayingthat &quot; My Lords are advised that  .  .   .  Indian troops employed in the Middle Eastshould continue to be  borne on Army Vote A, and I am to request that the council will give directions accordingly.&quot;    These directions are understood to  be the outcome of correspondence between theTreasury and the Air Ministry and of reference to the Parliamentary Counsel, who has apparently  advised the inclusion of these  troops in Army Vote A on the ground(natural enough in itself) that they cannot be regarded as part of the Royal Air Force.    From the War Office point of view, however,  I  desire  to protest strongly against this solution.  The War Office will have no responsibility for these Indian troops afterthe Air Ministry have  assumed control of Palestine  and of Iraq respectively ; all thefinancial and other arrangements are  to be made by the Colonial Office, with  the IndiaOffice direct, and  I am altogether opposed to these numbers being included in ArmyVote A as part of the Army establishments for which the War Office is responsible.    Suppose, for instance, that the Secretary of State for the Colonies should find  itnecessary in the course of the  year  to increase their numbers.   It  would  surely be intolerable that the Secretary of State for War should have to take  a SupplementaryVote for numbers  with which he has no concern whatever.    I hope the Cabinet will accept my view.   An immediate decision is imperative, asArmy Vote A is to be circulated on the 11th  instant.                                                                   L. W.-E.  THE WAR OEFICE,        9th March, 1922.(B22/105) 100  3/22  H&amp;S, Ltd. 9736wo

</content>
</cab>
