<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 247-270</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
  73 300TJI.JKE3! IS, 2KB PR0EBK2Y 03 HIS. 33tI AilKIC l^Ji.S2r^S ^Tir^filtr,:-)-^jft C  S E  Tv                            0 A 3 I N 1; &apos;2,G.P638S7v  -                  -MBK2IHG - 03? AMD f iMliC33  MINISTERS IN PARIS   PROVISIONAL Elf GUSH TEXTS  OS1  DOCUMENTS SIGNED :       BY FINANCE MINISTERS ON 11th ,kARCH,  1922.      15   COVERING NOTE BY FINANCE. MINISTERS               (PROVISIONAL TEXT.). &apos;      In tho Agreement,  of which tho text is attached, theFinance Ministers have  undertaken  a sattlamextft *f the questionswhich were  outstanding and arrived at: a oompleto understandingon the. various questions  raised in dealing, with repartition ofthe German payments.     In the course  of  their-discussions.. :the Finance Ministershero given attention to the general question-of. reparation&apos;.  the whole reached the  conclusion that in aoeordance-with the Treaty -of Versailles and the  declarations of the Governments, generallyspeaking, this question belongs exclusively&apos; to.the province Ofthe Reparation Commission,  but  they were unanimous in reognisi-&apos;ing that  it would, be essential  in  the interests of-the Govern-ments that they should  impress  upon their Delegates On theReparation Commission the  necessity of arriving as soon aspossible  at -concrete solutions.,. - Such solutions :should aim at sercuring  the payment of reparation,        both by restoringorder, to,  German finance under effective supervision,  and by enabling  Germany  ta-pay off part of the capital of her debt,  bythe issue; of foreign leans  to be secured on the produce of herOust cms or. such other of  the re sou ices of the  German  Empire as ;the .Beparati*nv Commission might Judge&apos;suitable:.     She  Ministers  further  discussed  the problems arising out ofthe war debts, due by the European.  Allies to each other.                    (Signed). Gv- TBOTIS.:. .   .                             CH. DE &apos; LASTEYEU,..                             R.S. HORNS .                             C. PEAJSfS. ;.,&apos;:-., .
      Tho Governments of Belgium,  France,  Great Britain,Italy anl Japan, respectively represented by the undersigned,nave agreed as follows:-                   A .R /T I, C LB.. JU     1. The payments to  be made by Germany on account  of thecents of the Armies of Occupation of Belgium, Great Britainand Franco, exclusive of the cost under Articles 8 to  12 ofthe Arrangement of the 28th June,  1919, shall as from  the 1sthay, 1922, be fixed at the following annual amounts :-      Belgian francs           -     .-1C2-,0.00,000  h.      Pounds sterling         -        2,000,000  ,      French francs.              .. 460/000,000  .2*   The above figures are fixed on the basis of the followingeffective strengths  :.-      Belgian Army              19,300      British Army              15,000      French Army               90,400They have been calculated on the&apos;basis of a total amount of220s000.000 gold marks.   Out of this amount a sum of10,950,000 gold marks has been allocated In respect of theBritish Army, representing a special allowance &quot;of 2 gold marksper man per day, to cover its higher cost.  The remainder,or 209,050,000 gold marks, has&apos;been divided in proportion tothe number of effectives&apos; as above stated.  The conversion ofthe sums.in gold marks so arrived at into national currencieshas boon made at the mean rates of exchange during the monthof December 1921.:3.   The sums definitely fixed above as the amounts to bepaid by Germany for the year commencing on the 1st May, 1922,may before the 1st hay in any subsequent year be revised forthe year commencing on ,+h.at &quot;date in accordance with thefollowing principles :-
(l)&apos; The total of those summon shall he increased if    the total effective strength of the three Armies    is increased in consequence of and hy a number    equal to the reduction of the American Army;  the    increase shall be proportional to the increase of    effectives regard being had,, in so far as it  may    he neae3T.sryt to the special allowance of 2 gold    marks per man per clay for the British Array.(2) The total of these sums shall be diminished if    the total strength of the three Armies is reduced..    The diminution shall be proportional to the    reduction in strength, regard being had,  in so    far as it may be necessary,, to the special allowance    of 2 gold marks per man per day for the Brit:.ah.    Army.-  If the British strength is reduced without    affecting the total strength, the total shall b.o    reduced by an amount equal to so much of tho  whole    sum produced by the special allowance of 2 gold    marks per man per day for the British Army as    Corresponds, to the number of effectives by which    that Army is reduced.         But no reduction shall be made so long as    the cost of the. three Armies,, calculated on the    basis of the French cost per head, with the    special allowance of 2 gold marks per man per day    In the case of the British Army, is not &quot;less  than the    total of the sums&quot; set out in paragraph 1.(3) If the cost in any one year of the three armies    together, calculated on the basis of the French    cost per head, with a supplement of 2 gold marks    per&apos; man per day in the case of the British. Army,.    is less than the total amount fined for that  year,.    the difference shall accrue to the benefit of    Germany in the shape of a reduction of the amount    payable for the following year.(4) Germany will, subject to the provisions in Article    2 below, pay the annual amounts in national    currencies fixed under paragraph 1 of this Article    to the Belgian, British and French Governments    respectively in twelhe monthly instalments.  The    Belgian,- British and French. Governments will, at    the end of each year commencing on the 1st hay    make the adjustments necessary to ensure that the    sum&apos;finally allocated to each of them for that    year shall correspond to the average effective    strength maintained during the year.(5) The Governments concerned will in ea.cn year com-    mencing from the 1st May 1922, decide upon the    total of the sums in paper marks required to    cover the cost of the services to be furnished    by Germany under Art idee 8-12 of the Arrangement    of Versailles of the 28 June 1919 and upon the    method by which this total sum shall he divided    among the three armies.(6) In the event of special military action of a  pre-    cautionary or coercive character being: decided    upon by the Allies powers the resulting?; expenses    shall be recovered from Germany bv the application    of Article 249 of the Treaty of Versailles in    addition to the amounts above mentioned.
       Tho Governments represented by tho undersignedconfirm the mandate which they have given to the ReparationCommission to recover the costs of the Armies of Occupation,and to draw up a separate account of such costs.    they further request tho Reparation Commission to take intoconsideration the obligations incumbent upon Germany, bothunder the Schedule of Payments and under Article 249 of theTreaty of Versailles when, in reply to the German llote of28th January, 1922, tho Commission determines the totalpayments to be made by Germany during the year 1922 in cashand in kind.       The Governments farther request the Commission todebit each of the Powers concerned in drawing up the accountof the amounts which are or may become due to it in respectof the cost of its Army of Occupation from 1st May,  1921,to 31st December, 1922, with the value of the deliveries in kind received by it during the same period, includingtherein the proceeds of the Gorman Reparation (Recovery)Act and of all similar legislation passed In accordancewith the decision of tho Allied Governments on 3rd March,1921.m
       Of  the total amount of deliveries in kind which germany will he called upon by the Reparation Commissionto nuke to the Allied Powers during 1922.. 65$ will be allotted to France and 35$ allotted to the other AlliedPowers.       For the purposes of this distribution the proceeds of the British &quot;Reparation (Recovery) Act&quot;, and of any similar legislation passed by other Allied Powers inpursuance of the decision of the Allied Governments ofthe 3rd March, 1921,  will bo treated as a delivery in kind.       The proportion f viz.35$) of tho deliveries in kind to bo made by Germany - during. 1922 Will, after deduettothe -share of Groat Britain fviz,24$ of the amount to be allotted to. Powers other than Franco), be divided betweenthe other Powers concerned in the proportions &apos;fixed by theSpa Agreement, subject to any adjustments which may berequired if one or more of the Powers concerned takes lessthan the amount of deliveries In kind to which it is entitled.       Out of the above-mentioned proportion of 35$ thereshall be allotted to  Italy a sum of 240 million gold marksJrttttlTli.] ilisg. including any amounts which may be made available as the result  of the  adjustments referred to above,       Tho Governments concerned will prohibit the re-export of deliveries  in kind received under the provisionsof this Article.
       Of the total amount of deliveries, in kind which germany will be called upon by the Reparation Commissionto make to the Allied Powers during 1922..  65$ will be allotted to Franco and 35$ allotted to the other AlliedPowers?       For the purposes of this distribution the proceeds of tho British &quot;Reparation (Recovery)  Act&quot;,  and of any similar legislation passed by other Allied Powers inpursuance of.the decision of the Allied Governments ofthe 3rd liar oh, 1921,  will ho treated as a delivery inkinds       The proportion (viz.35$) of the deliveries in kind to bo made by Germany during 1922 Will, after deduotinthe/share of Groat Britain ?viz,24$ of the amount to toallotted to. Powers other than Franco)., be divided betweenthe other Powers, concerned in the proportions fixed by theSpa Agreement, subject to any adjustments which may berequired if one or more of the Powers concerned takes lessthan the amount of deliveries in kind to which it is entitled.       Out of the above-mentioned proportion of 35$ thereshall be allotted to Italy a sum of 240 million gold markshfa^l!ll)l.iUig. including any amounts which may be made available as the result  of the adjustments referred to above.       The Governments concerned will prohibit the re-export of dolivofies in kind received under the provisionsof this Article.
       The  signatory  Governments represented  by the under-signed consent  to  the operation  for u ooriod  of three yoursof those  provisions  of the  Wiesbaden Agreement of&apos;tho 6thOctober,  1921,  to  which their agreement wis&apos;doomed  to qenecessary by tho Reparation Commission, and in particular of the provisions  respecting the passing of a credit toGermany and  a debit against France  for the value  of deliveriein kind offooted in execution of the Agreement,  subject tothe following conditions :&apos;       Cl)   the amounts of  tho deferred debits shall notexceed -.             350 million gold marks  In 1922,             750    &quot;      &quot;   ,r    &quot; 1923,             750    &quot;  . -  &quot;   &quot;    &quot; 1924.       (a)   the amount standing  deferred at the  end of 1924shall be  liquidated by Franco, v/ith interest  as provided forin the Agreement,  in  ten equal annual instalments beginningon the 1st&apos; May, 1926,  by set off. against sums due to. Frpncein each year out of reparation receipts, and  unless theoperation of the Agreement  is continued for a longer period by agreement among the.Allies, Prince, shall,  in no  year.-sub-sequent to 1926;,.; receive,.,,whether in cash or  deliveries,. sums which,, when  added  to  the said instalmentswou]d  result in france receiving in that.year more  than hor proportionate -share,, as determined  by I,.itor7.;&apos;,.llied .i.:,rcci:.ents,.  of the totalpayments by  Oeriiicihy in  tivct  yo;?.r,.. ino 1 uding- the instalmentsdue by Franco.
              ARTICLE  5,     The Governments signatory to -this Agreement-consent to  the putting into operation, subject to the approval of the Reparation Commission, of Agreements for deliveries in kind similar to  the Wiesbaden Agreement of  S October 1921-which may be concluded by any Power  participating In :reparation. provided -that the value of the deliveries in kind effected in virtue of  Annexes II to VI to Part VIII of the Treaty of Versailles and under such Agreements to be received by Powers  other than France  (Including  the proceeds of the British Reparation Recovery Act and of  any  similar  legislation passed by other Allied Powers In pursuance of the decision of the Allied Governments of the  3rd..- : arch, 1921)  shall not exceed $,5$ of the  total amount of deliveries in kind, which, Germany will  be called upon by. the Reparation Commis- sion to place in 1922 at the  disposal of the Allied Powers.
            ARTICLE__6.     Each Of the  Powers having a  credit  due  to  iton account of reparation  shall retain  for its ownuse, Up to the limit of.the.  share allocated  to  that power, withoxrt any obligation to  make  payments  inhash in respect thereof at any ,time, the value  ofany deliveries in kind, received up to  the 31st. ,December,1922, including the proceeds .of the BritishReparation (Recovery)  Act, and, of. any  similar legisla-tion passed h7 the other  Allied Powers.in pursuanceof the-decision of the Allied Governments of the3rd, March, 1921.&apos;      :.h,  ,-.     But subject  to  the provisions of  paragraphs.4and 5&quot; above and-- of any Inter-Allied. Agreement, already .entered into, the receipts of any Allied Power  inrespect of reparation  during 1922 together with interest thereon  at.the rate of;5 per  cent per  annumas from the 1st&apos;.  January, 1923*  .  shall  be taken in determining, the proportions&apos;of reparation receiptsdue &quot;to each Power In 1923 . and subsequent years.
               ARTICLE  7,     The GovernmentB- signatory to this Agreementtake note of the Agreement  reached on the 7th October,1921, between France and Germany in regard to theprice of coal delivered or  to be delivered by Germanyto France under Annex V. to Part VIII of the Treatyof Versailles, and agree thatGermany shall be creditedand France debited in resje ct of such coal in accor-dance with the provisions of paragraph 6 (a) of theabove-mentioned Annex.--     The Governments signatory to this Agreement will support&apos; the claim of Italy to benefit by the same conditions and in any case  Italy- will, be debited inthe accjount drawn up under Article 235 in respect ofthe coal received by Italy before the 1st May, 1921,In accordance with the provisions of paragraph 6 (a)of the above-mentioned Annex, any difference betweenthe debit thus fixed and the credit to be given toGermany being adjusted if necessary in accordance withthe provisions of Article 12 of this Agreement.
               ARTICLE  8.     Out of  the  total amount of the  cash pa7/-mentsmade by Germany  in 1921 under Article 5 of  the  schedule of Payment a, the  following payments  shall be made  inaccordance with  the provisions of Article 251 of theTreaty of-Versailles and the Interallied Agreement.of 16th June,  1919,- in regard to Belgian priority:  &apos;      (a)  500  million gold marks shall be allocated         . to Great Britain to be applied towards          payment of the- cost cf the British Army  of          Occupation before the 1st  May, 1921;      (b)  140.  million gold marks shall be allocated to        -  France-to&apos;be applied towards payment  cf  the ....      cost of the-French Army of Occupation before          the -1st May, 1921, : . .... The remainder of the above-mentioned cash  payments and  also cash  payments made after 1921 will be  allocated to Belgium on  account of tor priority until such  &apos;priority is  satisfied, with the - exception of the sum172  million  Italian lire at present  deposited with theBank of Italy,  which shall be allocated to Italy onReparation account.    , Any amounts  by which the above-mentioned sums of500  million  gold marks &quot;and 140 million gold marks  pay-able to Great  Britain  and France respectively eventuallyprove  to be  less  than the actual outstanding  costs ason that date shall be treated as debt, paTrable  to  GreatBritain and  France respectively  pari passu from thefollowing sources:-      (a) Before  the Belgian priority is  satisfied,cash receipts  accruing fo the Reparation Commission after1st  Ma:/, 1921, other  than the annuities  laid down  bythe  Schedule Payments;
     (b) After the satisfaction of the Belgian.priority, the first cash receipts accruing to theReparation Commission whether in respect of the annuities laid dovm in. the Schedule of Payments orotherwise.     ho interest shall be credited or debited inrespect of the adjustments under this Article.
ARTICLE  9.     In respect of the value of the Saar Mines the sumof 300,000,000 gold marks shall bo debited to Prance in distribution account In the same may as a delivery in kindmade on 1st January,  1922 and shall bo dealt with inaccordance with paragraph 6 of this Agreements   Shouldthe value of the Saar Mines as assessed-by the ReparationCommission prove to be higher than 300s000,000 gold marks ,the excess will bo liquidated by the distribution among thoPowers participating in reparation of &quot;C&quot; Bonds to thevalue of such excess taken from Prance&quot; s share ,in the total-series Of &quot;C&quot; Bonds.
                      ARTICLE  .10. . .     The United States, Great Britain and France will reoelvoon account of the special credit provided .far in the last .paragraph of Article 232 of the Treaty 6f Versailles a blockof Bonds of nominal value equal to the amount of this creditas determined, by the Reparation Commission.   This : blook ofbonds will be drawn from the general -total of the bondwdelivered by Germany under the provisions of the Schedule ofPayments. ..... The amounts of the bonds of Series &quot;Aw9  &quot;B&quot; &amp; &quot;C&quot;respectively in this block will,be, determined by the proportionof the total amounts of the bonds .of these series. -     This- clause in so; far as it relates, to the United Statesof America is subject to. the consent of the Government of theUnited States of America-&apos;
                                  11              II       .                                                            1                          AT&quot;-TO Iff 11.      The Reparation Commission will fix tho reparation debt of Austria and Hungary in accordance with Article 179 cf theTreaty of St. Germain and. with Article 16.3 of the Treaty ofTrianon.                    ,.                ,  ;       ; . .      Whatever total may he fixed by the. Reparation commission the amount to be divided among the powers participating inreparation shall be not less than the total of the value ofthe assets transferred by Austria, and Hungary under the treaties of St, Germain and Trianon.plus 6 milliards of goldmarks and the Bulgarian debt fixed by Article 121 of the .Treaty of Keullly^                           -  g      As soon as the Bonds of Series &quot;C&quot; have been ere ate d,from  the total amount shall be taken Bends to a nominal valueequal to the total debt arrived at above and distributed among tho powers, participating in reparation in proportion to the percentages fixed by Article 2 of the FinancialArrangement of Spa.      If at the time when the Bonds of Series &quot;C&quot; are createdtho Reparation Commission has not taken the decision providedf.oar in the first paragraph of this Article, it shall neverthe-less  distribute from tho whole of the Bonds of Series &quot;C,r Bondin proportion to the pore ontages fixed by Article 2 of theFinancial Arrangement of Spa and  for a total nominal amount of six milliards of gold marks plua the amount of the Bulgariandobt *      The Po-wors receiving payments in cash or in kind from austria, Hungary and Bulgaria shall return to the ReparationCommission for cancellation Series &quot;0&quot; Bends of the nomine!value of these payments.,      The method of payment for State properties situated inthe territories ceded by Austria  and Hungary and for the contribution to tho liberation expenses provided for under                                                     the..,n
the Agreements of the 10th September as modified by theAgreement of the 8th December, 1919, shall be determined in accordance with the principles sot out in tho annexedscheme.    The Powers concerned which are not parties to thepresent Agreement shall have the opportunity to adhere to the provisions of the Annex provided tor by thisArtie le.
                     ARTICLE  12.     With a view to adjusting say difference which may arise between the amounts credited to Germany and the amounts debited                 andto an Allied- Power/as a result of any Inter-Allied agreement in&apos; respect of deliveries in hind, brought to account underArticle -255, the distribution of Series &quot;0&quot; Bonds will beeffected in the following man nor t     It will be assumed that&apos; tho number of Bonds availablefor distribution is tho number arrived at after creditingGermany with the amounts debited to tho Allied powers inaccordance with any such Inter-Allied Agreement.     Each Power will receive out of this amount of Series&quot;C&quot; Bonds the ahare to which it is entitled under the SpaFinancial Agreement, but will be bound to cancel an amount of the                                         nominalSeries &quot;C&quot; Bonds so received equal to the         value of thedifference between the amount debited to such Power and theamount credited to Germany.     In accordance with the Spa Financial Arrangement Belgiumwill not be debited with any sum on account of the shipsallotted or transferred to her, and the above provision willnot apply to Belgium in respect of such ships.
                    - ARTICLE 12*  The present arrangement is made ui-der jreserrationany rights&quot; of the TJnitodStatoa of Araerloa.
     The Powers signatory to. the present Agreement will endeavour to secure the early adherence  to this  Agreementof the other Allied and Associated Powers concerned.          Paris, 11th March, 1922.For the Governments of&apos; Belgium &quot;   &quot;       &quot;      &quot;  Prance &quot;   &quot;       &quot;      &quot;  Ct. Britain &quot;   &quot;       &quot;      &quot;  Italy &quot;   &quot;       &quot;      &quot;  Japan
                          ANNEX.                     AUSTRIAN REPARATION.        AGHSELiSNT IN REGARD TO THE PROTOCOL OE 8 SEi*TEMBBR,19I9.         Tho Governments of Belgium,  Prance,  Great Britain,  Italy    and Japan: recognising; that it  is  desirable,  in view  of the    postponement  o? their claims for  reparation against  Austria    under tho  Treaty of  St., Germain,  that  a new provision in the    place of the.  Liberation Bonds  should bo made for  the discharge    of tho obligation of Italy,  the Serb-Croat-Slovene State  and    Roumania in respect  of, the expenses of liberating territories    of the former A us tro,-Hungarian Monarchy transferred  to them    and also for  the oayment. of the value  of  property and    possessions of that  Monarchy transferred  to them.         HAVE AGREED AS  FOLLOWS?1.  &quot;           Bonds of  Series WC* to be created and  delivered    under the  Schedule of. Payments notified to Germany under the   : Treaty of  Versailles, by the  Reparation Commission on the .5th    May, 1921,  to: an amount :equal  to  the amounts credited, or    which should  have been credited,  to Austria under the Treaty    of St. Germain in respect of property  and possessions of the    former Austro-Hungarian Monarchy  transferred and  of  deliveries    already made  by Austria or otherwise,  shall be distributed    between the Powers entitled to reparation in the:percentages    in&apos;which the  aggregate amount  received under the  head of    reparation, from Austria is to  be  divided according to the    provisions  of Article, 2(a) and (b)  of  the Agreement  signed    at Spa on-the 16th July 1920 and  any Agreements supplementary    to the Agreement.                                -19-
          Italy,  the Serb-Croat-Slovene State and Roumania shall discharge  their respective obligations for the payment of the  value of property and possessions of the former Austro-Hungarian Monarchy transferred to them under the Treaty of St.  Germain by surrendering to the Reparation Commission for  cancellation, Bonds of the whole.&apos;Series &quot;C&quot;9 above  mentioned,  part of the said Bonds to which they respectively, will be entitled,, to an amount equal in. capital value  to  the  capital value of, the property and possessions of  the /:.ustro-Hun6arian Monarchy, so transferred, to. them. respectively.    From the value of the property, and. possessions transferred to  Italy shall bo, deducted the total cost of the. Italian Armies  of Occupation in Austrian -territories. &apos;,      ; ,  Italy,  tho Sorb-Croat-Sloveno State;,and Roumania respectively  shall, discharge their obligations, arising under the  Agreements ,signed at St. Germain on the 10.th September 1919 and.,modified-at Paris , on the 8th. December 19.19 , for the payment of the  expenses of liberating territories of the former Austro-Hungarian Monarchy transferred, to -them, by handing over  to, the Reparation;,- Commis3ion Bonds of the said- Series. &quot;0&quot; part  of the said Bonds/which they respectively will be entitled,, to. ah amount equal; in capital,value to the amount ofgtheir  respective obligations, less..the percentages in which those  States-respectively.share according to the -repartition of-.the  said sums established by:;Art2- (,a) and (b)  of the Agreement signed, at Spa ..on, the : 16th July, 1920.        .  The  ^Reparation Commission shall divide the. Series &quot;C&quot;  Bonds handed ;Ov.er under the  last-preceding clause among the. Powers, other than the. Powers by whom the Bonds-are handed. over,  entitle d to share in reparation payments, in the , g,. same proportions  as the interest, of those, powers in,.     ... g bonds  to  be distributed under Clause 1 of this Agreement.
-     20 us.             Nothing in this Agreement shall effect the iis-      tributionof receipts f roiii-Hungary or Bulgaria on account      of. reparation or any adjustments to bo made of any Bonds of      the said Series &quot;0&quot; in consequence of such receipts.              - If one of the Powers to which territories of      Austria and. Hungary have  been ceded has not available      Series &quot;C&quot; Bonds in sufficient quantity to carry out the      adjustmonts provided for above,  the value of the possessions      which h&apos;-vo been transferred to such power - and its con-      tribution to the Costs of Liberation shall be discharged,      in so far as they, cannot  be  satisfied by the delivery of      Series &quot;0&quot; Bonds.,  in accordance  with the provisions      of the Agreement- of 10th  September 1919 as modified by      the  Agreement, of 8th December, 1919,6.         ...  .--  This Agreement cancels  all previous arrangements      between the- High Contracting Parties- -,hothor contained in the      said Agreements; of September and December 1913 or the      Agreement of Spa of the 1.6th- July 19 20 or otherwise, in    .,80 far as such arrangements  may be in conflict with the      provisions of this Agreement;               The . provisions, of Articles .2, 3 and 4 of this      Agreement shall not come  into, force until Czecho-Slovakia     : and Poland shall have discharged their respective obligations      under the said Agreements of September .10th and December 8th      1919, regard being had. in so fares Poland is concerned to      Article 10 of the Spa Agreement.
 HI&apos;  DECISION A3 REGARD ggRTAIW ggggjg OF OCOUFATIOH.         The Finance Ministers of Great Britain,Franco, Italy and Belgium have examined the question referred to the Allied Government by the ReparationCommission on the 3th March 1921 in regard to-,-     (1) the expenses resulting from the occupation    of territories outside the zone of occupation    laid down in the Treaty as a consequence of measures    taken  by the Conference in London in March 1921, -1     (2) expenses incurred in anticipation of similar    measures in the event of the ultimatum being rejected.         The Finance Ministers in the name of thairGovernments are of opinion that Germany should repay theseexpenses as costs of the Armies of Occupation-         It is understood that those expenses will besubject to scrutiny in the same way  s other costs cf the armies of occupation,Paris ,                           -: &apos; .&apos; -    11th March, 1922.
         IV,  LETTER TO MIU SOYDEN.     The Finance Ministers of Belgium,  Great Britain,  Francoand Italy to Mr, R,&apos;-7.,Boyden, the  Unofficial Delegate ofthe United States of ^merlca on the Reparation Ooiamission.Memorandum placed before us by yourself under date of March10th, regarding the payment of the costs of the american army of Occupation.         Your c oiBiauni cation has received our most serious consideration.   You will find enclosed the text of thearrangement signed at Paris to-day,    A special articlehas been added to this document iri order to meet thepoints with which tho memorandum is concerned.   While&apos;we have thus safeguarded all rights of the United Statesof America, whatever they may prove to bo, we are ofopinion that inasmuch as we are acting under the Treatyof Versailles to which the tfovmiment of the UnitedStates of America are no u a party, the question is onewhich concerns our respective- Governments and should beraised directly through diplomatic representations made by the Government of the United States of america to the Allied Governments.March 11th, 19 22Sir,&apos;.&quot;e have the honour to  acknowledge receipt of thWe havethe honour to be, Sir,Your ob ed ie nt Servants .,(Signed)   Go  THEUIISo(Signed)R.S.H0R.NE.,(Signed) C,,PEAJ?S.(Signed)C.L* de 1ASTEYRIE2 Whitehall Gardens,  S.7/.1.     March 14 th,  19 22,

</content>
</cab>
