<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 288-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S 2 0 B E T.&apos;   .....-i-iionta,To be dostroyed when replaced by a subsequent  number.G.P.  384/ASSAIL G            SECRET  ADMIRALTY     WEEKLY  INTEMGENOE  SUMMAHY.               (W. I. S.)       No.10. - 11th March,  1922.Issued by tho Naval Intelligence Division,Naval Staff,  Admiralty,  for  the  information            of -Recipients only.J        DISTRIBUTION.Sent by all British Route toCopiesBoard of Admiralty ............Dep.Sec,Naval Sec.,P.AfS,,                P.A.S.  (S).....Duty Captain..................The Cabinet ...................Secy.,Naval Board, Melbourne ..Secy..Naval Board, New Zealand.Director,Naval Service,Ottawa..PiA.N.A.0.  ********************Captain Segrave, R.N.,   Naval ^Representative,       League of Nations  ......Commanders-in-Chie f,    The Nore ..................    Portsmouth ................    Plymouth ..................    Scotland..............    Western Approaches ........    Atlantic Fleet............    N. America &amp; W. Indies ....    Mediterranean.............    China .....................    East Indies...............    Africa  ....................V.A.C., Ueserve Fleet .........Y.A.G.. 1st Battle Squadron  ...      1st Battle Squadron .....      4th Battle Squadron .....      Battle Cruiser Squadron .      1st Light Cruiser Sqdn...      2nd Light Cruiser Sqdn...      3rd Light Cruiser Sqdn... ...., Yangtse ................. .A,  Dl ?....................R.A. (S......................Commanding Of officer,HMS.&quot;Benown,,a. a.B.A.B.A.R.A.R.A.r,a.B.A.a.a.TOTAL (Distribution by        Copying Branch)10 4 140 2 2 1 11111111111111111111111185Admiralty Naval Staff;-    IoD,    ,000,*****Intelligence Officers:-  S.I.0Ys :-    Mediterranean .....    China .............    N. America    Ottawa ....Copies18 2 2 1*****  D.I.Ors :-    Portsmouth    Chatham ..    Davenport    Rosytn ...    Hull.....    Queenstown    Gibraltar    Malta ....    Cclcmbo ..    Singapore    Shanghai .    Wellington    Cape Town    Bermuda ..    Ascension ...3.N.I., MelbourneNvLoO., Hong Kong .NaY,0., Monte VideoN.7.C, Callao ....********** * * * *TOTAL (I.D.        Distribution)111111111i11111111111146
                         -i-                               217 To be destroyed when^roplaced^by^a subsequent number.                   SECRET ADMIRALTY           WEEKLY INTELLIGENCE   SUMMARY.                      (W. I,  s.)         No.10. - For week ending  11th March.1923.              PART I.    NAVAL  INTELLIGENCE.                     (MEAT - BRITAIN.&apos;MOYemeflts, Pi     Ships.6th March. H.M.S. &quot;DAUNTLESS&quot; arrived Gibraltar from Portland.11th March. H.M.S. &quot;ANTRIM&quot;  arrived Gibraltar from Las Palmas.Programmes of H.M.Ships.        _j___C&quot;  and  H,f32.  Cruise  in Home Waters and mediterranean in accordance  with following programme:- Combinedcruise to Soilly Islands and Milford Haven, and return toPortsmouth 17-27 April,   Leave  Portsmouth 23 May; Gibraltar25 May - 5 June; Visit Palmas Bay,  Sardinia and arrive Naples14 June.  Arrive Corfu 23 June; Malta 29  June - 10 July.Proceed to Rhodes, Suez,  Alexandria and Constantinople. LeaveConstantinople 30 July for Black Sea, Marmora and Aegean, arriv-xng Malta 29 Aug. for docking.   Due Gibraltar 24 Sept. andPortsmouth 18 Oct.        ]Mar.  On        H.M.S. &quot;ANTRIM&quot;.  Gibraltar 13-15 Mar.: Portsmouth 20        i relief by &quot;YAiMOUTH&quot;  to pay off for disposal.        H.M.S,, &quot;CALCUTTA&quot;.   Washington  Is. 3-4 Mar.; Fanning Is.4-5 Mar.; Christmas Is.  6-7 Mar.; Fanning  Is. -: Honolulu andHawaiian Is. 11 Mar,-2 A pi.; SanJ&amp;ansiiSQQ 10-16.April;  ^gan Diego 17-24 April: Libertad 1-5 May; Panama 8 lav; Colon8-9 May; Bermuda 14 May.  (Conveys District Officer, FanningIs., from Fanning Is. to Christmas Is.  and back),[Note: - &quot;CALCUTTA&quot; has  been delayed, having arrived Christmas Is. 11 Mar.),        HtM,S. &quot;LYCHNIS&quot;.  To be presented to Government  of  India.To be navigated to Bombay by new orew for &quot;ESPIEGLE&quot;,  supplemented by casual reliefs for ships on East Indies Station.  Leavesearly April (approx.).      L --.8, &quot;MESTOFT&quot;,  inmiffi!  and,&quot;WALLFLQTO&quot;.  LeavesSimonstown 20 Mar. for Algoa Bay, returning  to Simonstown 27 Mar.        lULR^imimny.  To  convey reliefs crew for &quot;CENTAUR&quot;to Gibraltar and also stoker reliefs  for Atlantic and Mediter-ranean Fleets.  Leaves Portsmouth 15  Mar., Devonport 16 Mar.(Arosa Bay 18 Mar.,  Gibraltar 20-22 Mar., Deyonport 26 Mar.,Portsmouth 27 Mar.).                          MUM.        The Danube is reported to be  clear of ice,        &quot;GLOWWORM&quot;,  &quot;LADYBIRD&quot; and M.L.196 left for Sulina on 9th March.  H.M.S. &quot;CONCORD&quot; left Constantinople on loth Marchfor Sulina with a new orew for &quot;GLOWWOBF, and will escort&quot;LADYBIRD&quot; back to Constantinople.
PAflT I,  NAVAL J.NMLIGMB,   (Continued)xUSSIA.        Blagk gea.  Ikaling with NatiopaliBJa.  The IftissianConsul at Batoum has been ordered to inform the Nationaliststhat they will bo given two &apos;Chasers.&apos;,  &quot;Smely&quot; and &quot;Silny&quot; andone motor-vessel, yDelfin&quot;.        In view of the Oreok blockade,  the Angora Government are anxious that all men-of-war handed over by the Soviets should beconsidered under the Bolshevik: Supreme Command and under theirproteotion, flying the Turkish flag aft and the Soviet flagat the main, and should remain in nussian waters.        The Angora Government have asked permission to dock the&quot;Preveza&quot; at Sevastopol in April,       Caucasian Patrol.  The following ships have beendetached to form the Caucasian Patrol Flotilla:-. Gunboat&quot;Toretz&quot; (Senior Officer); armed steamer &quot;413&quot;.; Chasers&quot;Bezposchadny&quot;, &quot;Bezstrashily&quot;, two M.,L!s of the &quot;Volga&quot; type -&quot;xfdis&quot; and &quot;Pantera&quot; (armed with 1 37-mm, 1 Maxim, Speed 14knots); Submarines &quot;A,G* 3&apos;J and Depot ship &quot;Georgi&quot;.  Thepermanent base of the &quot;Georgi&quot; is Tuapse,
PAtfT II.. - GENERAL INTELLIGENCE.                       ALBANIA.        Three of the  late Hegents have been  invited by theGovernment to leave Albania temporarily,  and have  done so.This is due to the fact that a plat to raise an armedrebellion in Northern Albania has been discovered  andsuppressed, in which  plot they are believed  to haveparticipated.                       GREECE.        In regard to  the question of the  &quot;Espoir&quot;, the GreekGovernment has suggested that the matter  be  referred to theLeague of Nations.  The French Government replied  that itwas willing to adopt  this proposal, provided that, untilthe case was decided, no French ships or cargoes should beinterfered with.  The Greek Government retorted that itcould not agree to the Kemalists being freely supplied withmunitions oi war for  such a long period,  so  the matter isstill at a deadlock.                       ITALY.        Confirmation  has been received of the happenings atFiume related in last week&apos;s summary.  It appears  that themembers of the Committee of Defence (composed of ex-Legionariesand Fascist!) had&apos;at  first no intention of starting a reyolu-tion, but  that their hands were forced by the intense indig-nation of  their followers at the murder of a young Fascista  namedFontana on or about 36th Feb.  it was accordingly decided to.overthrow  the Provisional Government,  This  was done with Vcomparative ease on 3rd March, an army of Fascisti, Legionaries,etc, attacking the Governor!s palace (which was defended bj;some 200 police) while a coastal motor boat, armed with a 3  \inch gun, bombarded it from  the sea.  Signor 7anella, seeing&apos;that resistance was hopeless, surrendered.  Casualties on bathsides amounted to five killed and about 20 wounded.       .  \        The insurgents&apos; demands were  then complied with, SignerZanellaisigning a decree of  abdication, and the police forcebeing disarmed; after which  a Revolutionary Committee took over the administration of the town and Signor Zanella wasgiven a safe-conduct to leave, which  he did concealed in an armoured motor oar.        On the news being received in Italy, d&apos;Annunziorsadherents  issued a manifesto deolaring the annexation of Fiumeto  Italy.  The Italian Government, however,  announcing thatits solo object is to restore order in Fiume, has sent SignorOastelli and a force of 500  police to Fiume for that purpose.Further, a communique has &quot;been issued stating  that  the  ItalianGovernment does not recognise the  present revolutionarygovernment and that, until a new government, has been set upconforming to the provisions of the Treaty of Rapallo, lawand order  will be maintained by.Signor Castelli and his police force.  Arms and ammunition  in the possession of  private persons are being confiscated .and  those who took  part in therecent disturbances are being expelled from  the town.  Fundsamounting  to 15 million lire have been placed at  Castelli&apos;disposal in order to assist  in the economic reconstruction ofFiume.
SEAflE IL  - BENGAL TNTPJ.T.T 0-?NflTC- J-Q r c ti on aPOLAND.        At the  request of  the  Chief of the  State  M.  Ponikowskihas formed a non-party government.   The majority  of  his formercolleagues consented to serve  under him again,.   The  opposition-.        Archangel Sector.  The British Trawler &quot;St.  Hubert&quot; ofHull has been arrested&quot;10t miles off land and taken  to Murmansk.This follows on the arrest of the Trawler &quot;Magneta&quot;  when fishing9f miles off Som Island.  The &quot;Magneta&quot; was subsequentlystranded during a gale while under arrest.  The Soviet Governmentclaim that territorial miters extend for a distance  of 12 seamiles,  and the question dates as far back as 1911 when a bill was introduced into the Duma to extend territorial waters tothis distance,  A representation has now been made to theSoviet Authorities demanding the immediate release of the&quot;St. Hubert&quot;,, an assurance  hat such interference will cease,and claiming damages in both cases.        Conditions at Murmansk are described by the survivorsof the &quot;Magneta&quot; as appalling,  The population, which is badlyclothed and fed, is mostly housed in the abandoned huts erectedby the British Expedition 1919/20, and sanitary arrangements are extremely bad.        Blaok Sea.  It  is reported from Constantinople thatGeneral Wrangel and his Staff have left Constantinople forBolgrade.        Siberia.  White  troops (Maritime Provinces republic)have withdrawn to Iman.  It is not anticipated  that the forcesof the Par Eastern fienublic will penetrate into the neutral zone.  The attitude oi  the Japanese is uncertain.        The whole  Cabinet has resigned (7th March)  as the  resultof Count Scmanones and two Ministers of his party withdrawingtheir support from the Government.        A new Cabinet has been formed under Senor Sanohez. Guerraas Prime Minister.has also been overcome.MJSSIA.SPAIN.

</content>
</cab>
