<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 433-434</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i This document is the property  of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.SECRET.                     .       38o.p.  3868.THE  CABINET.REDUCTION  OF  THE  CAVALRY.       MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.     The existing number of cavalry-regiments is  3 Household Cavalry regiments, i.e.,1st and 2nd Life Guards and the Royal  Horse Guards, and  28  Line regiments, i.e.,7 Dragoon Guards, 3 Dragoons, 12 Hussars and 6 Lancers.   Eacb regiment consists of3 squadrons.   A list, with dates of formation, is attached to this memorandum.     Under a decision made last year, 4 Line regiments are  in process of disbandment,which  should be complete by 31st March.  These are :                           5th Royal Irish Lancers.                          19th Royal Hussars.                          20th Hussars.                          21st Lancers.     In addition, a further  reduction of the equivalent  of  5 regiments  has  to becontemplated under the decision of the Cabinet on the Geddes Report.     On sentimental grounds,  great objection is felt to the abolition of any individualregiment, and various  proposals have been put forward with  a view to securing thenecessary reduction  by other  means.   Of these, I  think, the  following would oiler themost advantages and the fewest drawbacks :      The 1st  and 2nd  Life Guards should be  amalgamated  to form  1 regiment of 4squadrons, each  of the  existing regiments providing 2 squadrons to  be  entitled                         A and B Squadrons, 1st Life Guards.                        C and D Squadrons, 2nd Life Guards.     The composite regiment would be called &quot;The Life Guards.&quot;     In order  to compensate for  the  extra squadron of this  regiment, 4  Hotchkisstroops  (practically equivalent to one squadron) would be  reduced in the  Royal HorseGuards and the Life Guards.     The Line regiments should be classified in three grades as follows :      (1.)  Twelve at full strength.     (2.)  Eight consisting of a headquarters and 2 squadrons each.     (3.)  Eight (including the  4  regiments  now  being  disbanded)  consisting   of&apos; 1           squadron each.     Of the 10 Dragoon  Guards, and  Dragoon regiments, the Royals, the  Greys, the-King&apos;s  Dragoon  Guards and  the  Queen&apos;s Bays should  remain&apos; as &quot;they are, and theremaining 6 regiments  should be dealt with by amalgamating  the 3- junior  with  the 3senior,  the 3rd Dragoon Guards with the 6th Dragoon Guards, the 4th Dragoon Guardswith the  7th  Dragoon Guards, and  the  5th  Dragoon  Guards with the Inniskillings,2 squadrons of each of the  former being  retained and  1 of each of the latter.   Theamalgamated  regiments would  then be known as  the  3rd/6th and 4th/7th DragoonGuards and the  5th/6th  Dragoons respectively, being  treated as regiments for all purposes, but the third squadron of each would  retain the old name of its  originalregiment and be  called  the  6th and 7th Dragoon  Guard and 6th Dragoons Squadrons.respectively.     (B22/1U) 100  3/22 H&amp;S, Ltd.  9778wo
APPENDIX.LIST OF CAVALRY REGIMENTS IN ORDER OF DATE.Household  Cavalry.Royal Horse Guards1st Life Guards2nd Life Guards 1661I 1661 (as troops).\ 1788 (as regiments).                      Cavalut of the Line.  1st The Royal Dragoons  The Royal Scots Greys (2nd Dragoons) ..  1st King&apos;s Dragoon Guards  The Queen&apos;s Bays (2nd Dragoon Guards)..  3rd Dragoon Guards (Prince of Wales&apos;s) .  4th Royal Irish Dragoon Guards  ..  5th  Dragoon Guards&quot; (Princess Charlotte of Wales&apos;s)  The Carabiniers (6th Dragoon Guards)  ..  3rd The King&apos;s Own Hussars  4th Queen&apos;s Own Hussars  7th Dragoon Guards (Princess RoyaVs)  .. *5th Royal Irish Lancers  The Inniskillings (6th Dragoons)  7th Queen&apos;s Own Hussars  8th King&apos;s Royal Irish Hussars  ..  9th Queen&apos;s Royal Lancers.. 10th Royal Hussars (Prince of Wales&apos;s Own) 11th Hussars (Prince Albert&apos;s Own) 12th Royal Lancers  (Prince of Wales&apos;s) 13th Hussars 14th king&apos;s Hussars .. 15th The King&apos;s Hussars 16th The Queen&apos;s Lancers  .. 17th Lancers (Duke  of Cambridge&apos;s Own) .. 18th Royal Hussars (Queen Mary&apos;s Own)*19th Royal Hussars (Queen Alexandra^ Own)*20th Hussars..........*21st Lancers (Empress of India&apos;s)     1661     1678     1685     16S5     1 685     1685     1685     1685     1685     1685     16881689-1799  (re-formed 1858)     1689     1690     1693     1715     1715     1715     1715     1715     1715     1759     1759     1759     1858     1S61     1861     1861* In process of disbandment,     Similarly, of the 12 Hussar  regiments, the. 6 senior  would remain unaltered, andthe 3 next senior be amalgamated with the 3  junior, and of the  6 Lancer regiments,2 would  remain  and the  2 next senior be amalgamated  with the 2 junior in exactly the same way.     Promotion of officers  would be on a regimental basis.     The 28 Line cavalry regiments would then he reduced to 20 as follows :                     Seven Dragoons and Dragoon Guards.                    Nine Hussars.                  .  Four Lancers.                                                                              L. W.-E.  THE WAR  OFFICE,          22nd March, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
