<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 435-448</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT  IS THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS  BRI&apos;rANNIO majesty*S, GOVEft*:MEff&apos;T*CABINETjUNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BXLL.3CRST.Memorandum by tho Minis tor ofLabour.I circulate herewith a draft Unemployment insurance bill on the lines of the proposals recommended in theReport of the Cabinet Insurance Committee.     The draft Bill should be regarded as -subject to amendment on points of draiting and other modifications of detail; but as It is essential to introduce It withoutdelay., I have thought it best to circulate it in itspresent form rather than wait until all points of detailhave been settled.   The main outlines of the Scheme trillremain as set out in the draft subject of oourse to cabinet approval.     I shall be glad to have Cabinet authority tointroduce the Bill at the earliest possible date, and tocarry it through all its stages as a natter of urgency.,(Initialled)   T.J.M.Ministry of Labour.
Unemployment Insurance  Bill.ARRANGEMENT OE  CLAUSES.Clause. 1.   Rates of unemployment benefit. 2.   Rater of contribution. 3.   Termination of  second special period under 11 &amp; 12       Geo. 5. c. 1, and new special periods. i.   Provisions with respect to third special period. 5.   Provisions with respect to fourth special period. 6.   Calculation of contributions. 7.   Amendment as to Treasury advances. 8.   Amendment of section 12 (3)  of principal Act. 9.   Amendment of section 8 (5) of principal Act.10.   Power to call as witness husband or  wife of alleged      offender.11.   Amendment to section 27 of the principal Act.12.   Construction, saving, short title, commencement, and       duration.     SCHEDULE.95-2a
[12 GEO. 5.]     Unemployment Insurance.             1                       DRAFT                          or A                  B   I    L    L                           TO   Vary the rates of contribution and the rates and A-D- 1^2,     periods  of  benefit  under the  Unemployment     Insurance Acts, 1920 and 1921, and otherwise     to  amend those Acts and to repeal the Unem-     ployed Workers  Dependants  (Temporary Pro-     vision) Act, 1921.   BE  it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,       by  and  with  the advice and  consent of  the  Lords   Spiritual and Temporal,  and Commons, in this present   Parliament assembled, and by the  authority of the same, 5 as follows :        1. (1)  Unemployment benefit under the Unemploy- Bates of   ment  Insurance Acts,  1920 and 1921, shall, instead of ^tT,e7efit   being at the rates mentioned in paragraph 1 of the Second &apos;   Schedule to  the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920 (in10 this Act referred to as i( the  principal  Act&quot;), be  at the   weekly rate  of  twelve  shillings  for men, ten  shillings   for women, six shillings for boys under the age of eighteen,   and five shillings for girls under eighteen, or such other   weekly rates  as may be prescribed under the said para-15 graph 1  together with  such additional amount, if any, as   may be payable under the following  provisions of  this   section.       (2)  Where the person entitled  to benefit is a marriedt   man, or being a widower or an unmarried man has residing   with him any female person for the purpose of having the   care of his dependent children and  is  maintaining  that   person, or has and has had living with him as his wife any       95-2                A
2Unemployment Insurance.[12 GEO. 5.]A.D. 1922.  female person, or where the person entitled  to benefit is a          married woman who has a husband dependent on her, the          weekly rate of benefit shall be increased by a sum of five          shillings and where the person so  entitled has dependent          children the weekly rate of benefit shall be increased by 5          one shilling in respect of each such child :              Provided  that the additional sum of  five  shillings          shall not be payable in respect of  a wife or female person          who is in receipt of benefit (including benefit under any          special scheme), or who is in regular wage-earning employ- 10          ment, or  is engaged in any occupation ordinarily carried          on for profit.              (3) If any question arises as to whether any addition          ought to be made to the weekly rate of benefit in respect          of any wife or other female person, or any husband or 15          any child, that question shall be decided by the Minister.              (I) Paragraph 6  of  the   Second Schedule to the          principal Act (which limits the power of the Minister to          prescribe  rates and periods of benefit) shall have effect          as though for the words  from &quot; the rate  of benefit&quot; to 20          &quot; for women   both inclusive, there were substituted the          words &quot; or reduce any of the rates of benefit for the time          &quot; being in force by more than two shillings per week &quot;.              (5) This section  shall  come  into operation on the          thirtieth day of April, nineteen hundred and twenty-two.  25Rates of        2. Prom  and. after the twenty-seventh, day of:&apos;  April,contribution, nineteen  hundred, and twenty-two, until the end of the          deficiency period  as  defined  in  section sixteen of the          Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1921, the contri-          butions payable under the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 30          1920  and 1921, in respect of  employed persons by those          persons and. their employers  shall be at the rates set out          in Part L of  the Schedule to this Act, the contributions          so payable in respect of exempt persons by their employers          shall be at the rates set out in Part II. of the said Schedule, 35          and the contribution to be made  out of moneys provided          by Parliament shall be a contribution of such an amount          as may be determined by the Treasury to be approximately          equivalent, having regard to the estimated proportions in          which contributions are payable in respect of men, women, 40          boys  and girls, to  the  sum which would be produced by          weekly contributions paid in respect of insured and exempt
[-12 GEO. 5.]    Unemployment Insurance.3and nowspecialperiods   persons at the  rates specified in Part  III. of the  said  A.D. ii&apos;22.   Schedule.       3. (1)  Tlie provisions of Act No. 1 of 1921 and Act Termination   No. 2 of 1921  shall  have effect as though the  second of(fc^nd 5 special period denned in section nine of Act No. 1 of 1921 p^iod Ull(]er   were  expressed  to terminate on the sixteenth  day  of n &amp; 12   April, nineteen  hundred and  twenty-two, instead  of on Geo. 5. c. 1,   the second day of July, nineteen hundred and twenty-two.       (2) For the  purposes hereinafter in this Act mentioned10 there  shall  lie  two further  special  periods,  that is  to   say, the  period  from the  seventeenth day of April, nine-   teen hundred and twenty-two, to tire first day of  November,   nineteen hundred and twenty-two  (hereinafter referred   to as  &quot;the third  special  period&quot;), and the period from15 the second  day of   November,  nineteen  hundred  and   twenty-two,  to  the first day  of  July, nineteen hundred   and twenty-tliree (hereinafter in  this Act referred to as   &quot;the  fourth  special  period&quot;), the days  above-mentioned   being in all cases  inclusive. &apos;20     (3)  Paragraph  2  of  the Second  Schedule  to  the   principal Act  (which  provides  that  no  person  shall   within any insurance year receive unemployment benefit   for a period of  more than fifteen weeks, or  such other   period as may  be prescribed) shall not operate during25 the third and fourth special  periods, and shall after the   termination of  the  fourth special period have effect as   though  twenty-six  weeks  was  therein  substituted  for   fifteen weeks.       4.  (1)  Notwithstanding anything in the  Unemploy-  Provisions30 ment Insurance Acts,  1920 and  1921, or in this  Act, no  with respect   person shall be entitled  to receive benefit in the third  ^?a*  ^od6&quot;&apos;   special period for  a greater period in the aggregate  than  c&apos;a i:)erioc&quot;   fifteen weeks, and for the  purposes of this  provision any   benefit received between the fifth day of April, nineteen35 hundred and twenty-two  and the commencement of the   third  special period shall be deemed to be received in that   period.       (2)  If it appears to the Minister that, having regard.   to all the circumstances of the case, it is expedient in the40 public  interest  that  a person,  notwithstanding that  he   may  not otherwise be  entitled to receive benefit,  should   be  allowed  to receive  benefit during  the &quot;third special   period, the Minister may,  subject as hereinafter in this       95                   A  2
section provided, authorise the payment of benefit to that person as follows, that is to say :     (a) If the person applying for benefit did not receive        benefit for more than  sixteen  weeks  in the        aggregate  in respect of  the period between the 5        second  day of November, nineteen hundred and        twenty-one and  the  seventeenth  day  of  April,        nineteen hundred and twenty-two, the Minister        may authorise the payment  of benefit to that        person as follows, that is to say, he may authorise 10        the  payment of benefit  forthwith  for  periods        amounting in the aggregate to [six weeks], and        may at any time after the expiration of a  period        of not less than [three weeks]  from the end        of the  last period in respect of which  benefit 15        was payable, authorise  payment  of benefit for        further periods  amounting  in the aggregate to        [six weeks], and may  at any  time after the        expiration  of a  period of  not less than  [three        weeks] from  the end of  the  last  period  in 20        respect of  which  benefit was payable, authorise        payment of benefit for a further period of [three        weeks]:    (6) If the  person applying for benefit has received        benefit for more than  sixteen weeks  in the 25        aggregate  in respect of  the said  period  ending        on the sixteenth day of  April, nineteen huddred        and twenty-two, the number of weeks in  respect        of which  benefit  may  be  allowed  forthwith        under paragraph (a) of this  subsection shall be 80        reduced by the  number by  which the number        of weeks in respect of which benefit was received.        exceeded sixteen,  but without prejudice  to the        power of the Minister to authorise the applicant        to receive fifteen weeks  benefit in the aggregate 35        in the  third  special period, so,  however, that        after the applicant has received benefit in respect        of the  reduced  number of  weeks or has subse-        quently received benefit for periods amounting        in the aggregate to six weeks he shall not receive 40        any further benefit until after the  expiration of        a period of  three  weeks from the end  of the        last period  in  respect  of   which benefit was        payable.                                 .  .
[12 GEO.  5.]    Unemployment Insurance.       (3) For the purpose of qualifying a person to receive,  A.D. 1922.   within either the third or the fourth special period, benefit   up to the aggregate amount which may be authorised by   the Minister under this  Act, but for no other purpose,   there shall be treated as having been paid in respect of   him  such number of contributions as are sufficient so to   qualify him.        (1) The Minister shall not authorise any person to   receive benefit under this section unless that person proves10 that he is         (a) Normally employed in such employment as would            make  him an   employed  person  within  the            meaning of the principal Act; and        (/;) Genuinely seeking, but unable to obtain, whole-15          time employment;   and  also either that not  less than twenty contributions   have heen paid in respect of him under the principal Act,   or that, having regard, to the opportunities of employment   in his normal employment,  he  had  during  the  year20 nineteen hundred and twenty a  satisfactory record of   employment in some occupation employment  in which   would if. the principal Act had been in force during  the   whole period  of  his employment  have  made  Mm  an   employed person  within the  meaning of  that Act, or, in25 the case of a person formerly  engaged in Avar  service, who   ceased to be  so  engaged on  or  after the  first day of   January, nineteen hundred and twenty, that he had such   a record before becoming so engaged.        Eor the purposes of the  foregoing provision  the30 Minister may,  in the case of  any person in respect of   whom contributions have been  credited  under section   forty-one of the  principal Act, treat the service of that   person as a seaman, marine, soldier or airman at any time   since  the seventh  day  of November,  nineteen hundred35 and nineteen, as  if  it were employment  which, would, if   the principal Act  had been in force  during the period of   service, have  made that  person an  employed  person   within the meaning of that Act.r-&quot;      If any  question arises as to  whether  any  person40 satisfies the requirements of this subsection, the question   shall be decided by the Minister.
period A.D. 1922.      5.  (i) Notwithstanding anything in the Unemploy-Provbioiw   ment Insurance Acts, 1920 and  1921, or in this Act, nowith respect person shall, except as hereinafter provided, he entitled toto fourth   receive benefit in the fourth special  period for a greaterspecial     period in the aggregate than sixteen weeks.               5               (2)  If it appears to the Minister  that, having regard          to all the circumstances of  the case, it is expedient in the          public interest that a person, notwithstanding that he may          not  otherwise  be  entitled  to receive benefit, should  be          allowed to receive benefit during the fourth special period, 10          the  Minister may, subject  to and  in accordance with all          the conditions applying to the authorisation of the receipt          of benefit during the third special  period, authorise that          person to  receive benefit during the fourth special period          for periods not exceeding in the aggregate ten weeks.      15               (3)  For the purposes  of paragraph 3 of  the Second          Schedule  to the principal  Act  (which provides that  a          person shall not receive  more benefit than in the propor-          tion of one week&apos;s benefit for every six contributions paid),          every  contribution paid  shall during the fourth special 20          period be treated as equivalent to two contributions.               (4)  If it appears to the Minister that having regard          to  all the circumstances of the case  it is  expedient in          the  public interest that a person who has in the fourth          special period received unemployment  benefit for periods 25          amounting in  the aggregate to  sixteen weeks, should be          allowed  to receive benefit  for any further periods within.          that special period the Minister  may, but subject always          to   the  provisions of the  said paragraph  3,  authorise          the payment of benefit to that person within that special 30          period for further periods not exceeding in the aggregate          six weeks.               Any application under this  subsection for the allow-          ance of  further benefit may, if  the Minister thinks fit, be          referred to a local employment committee.               35 Calculation      6. For the  purpose of  determining  the amount ofof coiitiibuunemployment benefit to which, having regard to the pro-portion of benefit to contributions fixed by paragraph three off the Second Schedule to the  principal Act, any person is entitled at any time after the termination of the fourth 40special period, no account shall  be taken of any benefit which may have been received by that person at any timein respect of any of the special periods.             ..   .
[12 GEO. 5.]    Unemployment Insurance.        7. Section five of Act No. 1 of 1921 (which authorises  A.I). 1922.    the Treasury to  make advances  for the purpose  of dis- ^U10^iu10nt    charging the liabilities of the unemployment fund under iis to    the principal Act as amended hy that Act&quot;) as  amended Treasury  5 by section four of Act No. 2 of 1921, shall have  effect  as ^ivanocs.    though the reference in the said section five Ijo Act No. 1    of 1921 included  a reference to this Act, and as though    twenty-five million pounds were  substituted for twenty    million  pounds  as the  limit  on the  amount of the 10 advances under that section Avhich may be outstanding at    any time.        8. The proviso to subsection (3) of section twelve of Amendment    the principal Act  (which provides that such sum  as the 0j,  ^    Treasury may direct not exceeding one-tenth of  the rates (M()imf-all 15 therein mentioned shall be applied as an appropriation in    aid of the moneys provided by Parliament for the purpose    of the salaries, remuneration and  expenses  therein men-    tioned) shall have effect as though &quot; one-eighth&quot; was    substituted for &quot; one-tenth.&quot; 20     9. Sub-section (5) of section three of  the  principal Amendment    Act (which relates to disqualifications  for benefit), shall J?f section 8    have effect as if at the end of the sub-section there were ^] 0[(![&quot;&quot;el&quot;    added the  words &quot;as amended by the Blind Persons Act, no &amp;Vi    1920.&quot;                                                 Geo. 5.                                                           e. 49.) 25     10. The wife or husband of a person charged with,  an Power to .    offence under the principal Act may be called as a witness ,,a,11 11 *    either for  the prosecution or defence  and  without the Wl,ncss lu.&apos;*-            ....    1       t      -i                            and or wile    consent of  the person charged.                           of alleged                                                           offender.        11. Section  27 of the  principal Act, which relates Amendment30 to the granting of out-door relief to  persons in receipt  of 10 section 27    benefit, shall have effect as if there were inserted, therein &quot;J&apos;.)l,llJe^p1&apos;tm&quot;    the following subsection :         (2) In any case in which out-door relief has, pending            the  decision  of  the claim, heen  granted to  a35          person claiming  benefit, there shall, if the claim            is subsequently  allowed,  be repaid  out of the            Unemployment  Pund  to the  authority  which            granted   the relief  a sum equal to such amount            as that authority may certify to have been paid,40          subsequently to the date  as from which payment            of benefit was allowed, in excess of  the amount
A.D. 1922.          which would have  been paid if the person who                  claimed benefit had been in receipt thereof, and                  the amount so repaid shall be deducted from the                  benefit payable to that person.Construe-        12.  (1)  In this Act, unless the context otherwise tion, saving,  requires,; short title,        mi              ee        mi         i  -commence-        -*-&quot;ie expression   person  formerly  engaged  in  warment, and         service &quot; means any person belonging to the classesduration.          of persons to whom  the  scheme in force at the                commencement of  Act No. 1  of 1921 for paying                donation in respect of unemployment to discharged                sailors,   soldiers,  and  other  persons  applies, or                would have applied if it had continued in force ;               The expression  &quot;married man&quot; means  a  man who                has  a wife  who  is living  with him  or  is being ^                maintained wholly or mainly by him ;               The expression &quot; a dependent child &quot; means any child                under the age of fourteen years who is maintained                wholly or mainly at the cost of the person entitled                to benefit, or any child between the ages of fourteen 20                and sixteen who is  under full-time instruction in a                day school and is so maintained as aforesaid ;               The expression  &quot; child&quot; includes a  stepchild, an                adopted child, and an illegitimate child;               The  expression  &quot; local  employment  committee&quot; 25                 means any local committee to whicli questions may                be referred under subsection (5) of section  thirteen                of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920;               The expression &quot; the Minister &quot;  means the Minister                of Labour;                                     30               The  expression &quot;benefit&quot;  means  unemployment                benefit under Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920                and 1921.               The  expression  &quot; Act  No.  1 of 1921&quot; means  the                 Unemployment  Insurance Act, 1921,  and  the 35                 expression  &quot; Act  No. 2 of  1921&quot; means  the                 Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act,  1921.               Eor  the  purposes  of this  Act  a husband  shall be           deemed to be  dependent on  his wife if he is  prevented           by physical or  mental infirmity from supporting himself           and is being maintained wholly or mainly by her.
[12 GEO. 5.]  Unemployment Insurance.9        (2) If any question arises as to whether any person    is a person who was  formerly  engaged in  war service    within the meaning of this Act, that question shall be    decided by the Minister. 5      (3) The  decision of the Minister upon  any question    which, under  this Act  is to be decided by him, shall be    final and conclusive and  not  subject  to  appeal to any    court.        The Minister  may, if he  sees fit, refer  any such10  question to a local employment committee.        (4) Save as in this Act otherwise  expressly provided,    nothing therein contained shall  operate so as to deprive    any  person of, or to prevent any person from  receiving,    any  unemployment  benefit which  he  would have  been15  entitled to receive if this Act had not been passed.        (5) This  Act may be cited as the Unemployment    Insurance Act, 1922, and  shall be construed  as  one with    the  Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 and  1921, and    those Acts and  this Act  may be cited together as the20  Unemployment Insurance  Acts, 1920 to 1922.95J3
A.D. 1922.             ,     SCHEDULE.PART I.RATES OF CONTRIBUTIONS  BY EMRLOVEU PERSONS AND                     EMPLOYERS.                    Ordinary Rales.                      5   From tlie employed person for each week :        In the case of men -    -   -            Qd       In the case of women    -                Id.   From the employer for each week :        In the case of an employed person being            10         a man      -    -     -   -    -     -   lOd.       In the case of an employed person being         a woman   ------   Sd.        Rates in the ease of fersons under eighteen.   From the employed person for each week :              15       In the case of boys -----   4^cZ.       In the case of girls -     -   -    -     -   Ad.   From the employer for each week :        In the case of an employed person being         a hoy -------   od.      20       In the case of an employed person being         a girl -------                      PART II.RATES OE CONTRIBUTIONS BY EMPLOYERS IN  THE CASE             OF EXEMPT PERSONS.                   25In the case of an exempt person being a man,  for  -each week  -    -   -    -    -        8d.In the case of an exempt person being a woman,  for  each week  ------   7d.In the case of an exempt person being a boy,            30  for  each week  -    -   -    -    -     -   4d.In the case of an  exempt person being a girl,  for  each, week  ------   3ld.
[12 GEO. 5.]    Unemployment Insurance.11                          PART  III.     RATES OF CONTRIBUTION OUT OF MONEYS  PROVIDED                       BY PARLIAMENT.                         Ordinary Bates. 5     For every contribution  paid in respect of  a         man  -    -     -     -    -    -     -    -    GjfW.       For  every contribution  paid in respect  of  a         woman    -------    5 pi.            Rates in the ease of persons under eighteen.10     For  every contribution  paid in respect of  a         boy........Vsd.       For  every  contribution paid in respect of  a         girl  --------               Rates in the ease of exempt persons.15     For  every contribution  paid  in respect of a         man  -------   -    2d.       For every contribution paid  in respect of  a         woman    -------   \%d.       For  every contribution paid in  respect of a20       boy   -------    -   Id.       For  every contribution  paid in respect of  a         girl.  -    -    -    - &apos;   -    -    -    -    y.
Unemployment   Insurance.            DRAFT              OF A        BILLTo vary the rates of contribution and  the rates and periods of benefit under  the  Unemployment Insurance  Acts,  1920 and  1921, and otherwise to  amend those Acts, and to repeal the  Unemployed  Workers&apos;  Dependants  (Temporary Provision) Act, 1921.!iXCV.  (2.)22nd March 1922.

</content>
</cab>
