<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/134/0 images: 561-562</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic majesty&apos;s Government, and should be       returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.]               FOR  RP^ORD                    2                   FRANCS                              POLITICAL                Lord Hardinge. (Paris),                                March 25th, 1922.                D.   3.4.p.m. March 26th,  1922.                R,   7.15.p.m.March 26th,  1922.                 .....oOo----         Following for cabinet from Lord Ourzon:-         Marshal Foch and military experts returned    this morning with a report that rendered possible    a division of Thrace between Turks and Greeks    to advantage of latter0 French case was thereupon    entirely abandoned and  I was able to secure  a    line better than anything we had deemed possible.    Whether combatant parties and particularly Turkey    will accept is another  consideration.  Our offer    must be judged as a whole.         Under proposed arrangement allied occupation    is provided for on European shore  of Dardanelles.    Turkish sovereignty is  readmitted  on Asiatic shore    but broader demilitarised zone is  required  on that    side.  On European side tho whole  of eastern Thrace    is demilitarised whether it remains  Turkish  or    Greek and line between  the two states  is  drawn at    a distance from Constantinople sufficient in the    unanimous view of the military authorities to give    absolute security to  that city..         We then  considered and decided  upon  financial                                               terms   7S*3^nq3  ) col?s j...... De cypher,\C 11No.  173.
terms of new treaty which concede  to Turkey aliberty far beyond anything previously contem-plated or proposed, financial experts beingfortunately united on this point.  We also agreedupon a formula which satisfied Italian claims arising out of tripartite agreement.     This afternoon a sharp discussion aroseabout French claims under Franklin Bouillon agree-ment to provide officers under guise of instruc-tors for Turkish gendarmerie;  Monsieur Poincare&apos;was obliged to repudiate all claim to special treatment or monopoly.     Tomorrow wo resume discussion on future military forces of Turkey, agreement havingbeen reached that conscription cannot possibly be allowed.  I have submitted proposal aboutfiscal and judicial capitulations which willalso be discussed.     I have every hope now that we shall finishtomorrow night and that I shall be able to returnMonday,

</content>
</cab>
