<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/149/0 images: 159-170</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION  OF  THE  ATTACHED  WESTERN  AND  GENERAL                           REPORT  Nn.  85.                      PART II. FOREIGN AND  GENERAL.                          PEACE DISCUSSIONS (page 9).    &quot;Discussions,&quot; involving the participation of  two parties, have  ceased  since thenew treaty made by the Germans with  the Bolshevists, who are  thereby pledged tofight the Allies in the North of Russia,  and  to give up, on behalf of &quot; Russia,&quot; theprovinces of Livonia and Esthonia.  German  peace feelers in neutral countries (seeespecially under &quot; Switzerland &quot;) seem to be only the preliminaries to the elaborate peace offensive, expected to be launched in November, when the Reichstag is announced toreassemble.   The object will be to obtain by negotiation what  force lias failed toacquire.                               GENERAL (page 2).     The effect of the acceptance by neutrals of German sale-conducts for merchant ships is dealt with,  especially as affecting Sweden.                                A i.:.I HI) COUNTRIES.     China (page 2).  A  new President lias  been elected.  The retirement of  thePrime Minister is foreshadowed, as the Ministry has resigned.                                ENEMY COUNTRIES.                      &apos;  .     Auslrhi-Tlungary (page 4).--Representatives of  the&apos; Quadruple Alliance have met at Vienna to discuss questions, which seem from previous reports to be reaching an acute stage the Polish question, and the differences between Turkey and Bulgaria.King Ferdinand was present.     Germany (page 4). -Some  confirmation has  been received  of  reports that  the Germans ate  likely&apos; to abandon the Bolshevists,  who have served their  purpose so well.     Changes in the Chancellorship are  foreshadowed.     ddie report of Count Hertling&apos;s attitude towards the Prussian Franchise Bill is of interest, especialty his appeal to the members of the  Prussian  Upper Bouse to give way to the Equal Suffrage question, in order to save the Dynasty.  It will be  difficult, in view of their attitude, for Government speakers in the Reichstag  to maintain, as they did last year, that any power is in  the hands of German democracy.                                                                          [.P.T. o.
                               NEUTRAL COUNTRIES.    Chile (page 6). The  disablement  by the Germans  of  their  ships  in Chileanwaters lias caused dissatisfaction in the country.    Denmark  (page  G). Bolshevist propagandists, probably with German support,are at work against the Entente Powers.    Finland (page  6). The attitude  of  the present  Ministry is reported to beconciliatory to the Allies.   The  Diet  has  not yet decided upon the constitutionalcpuestion.   Should they approve of a Monarchy, the KaisePs  brother-in-law,  PrinceFrederick Charles of Hesse, is indicated as the first occupant of the throne.    Netherlands (page 7).- The composition of the new Ministry is announced.    The Foreign Minister has protested to  the  German  Government  against thepassage  of  military material over  the Limburg  railways, in contravention of theagreement of last April.    Spain (page  8).---Action has not yet been taken  in  response to German  U-boatoutrages.    Sweden,  (page 8). Germany is   applying   pressure   about  safe-conducts for merchant shipping, as affecting  Baltic voyages.   (See also under &quot; General.&quot;)    Switzerland  (page 8).-German propagandists  are   trying  to  make  capitalout of the promise, not yet fulfilled, to  relax their U-boat activities against neutralsby allowing vesse?to  carry goods to Cette for Switzerland.                                                                      G. G.  A.    September 12th, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]                              Printed for the War Cabinet.                          gSECRET.                                                       FOR  REFERENCE ONLY                 WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.                   No. 85.   Week ending 11th September 1918 (night).                      PART  IT. FOREIGN AND GENERAL.                                         CONTENTS.General.    Sinkings.  German safe-conducts.  A astro-Hungarian prisoners in hands of Czecho-Slovaks.Allied Group.    China. New President.  Probable modification of Japanese policy.   Collection of Customs revenue.      Tibet,    France. Views of M. Thomas ou an International Socialist Conference.    Italy. Jugo-Slav  question.  Projected release  of cotton for exportation to Switzerland.   Socialist      Congress.Enemy Group.    Austria-Hungary. Enemy conferences at Vienna.    Germany. The Chancellorship and  Government.  Germany and Russia.  War aims and method s      of the Crown Prince.  Prussian franchise reform and the monarchy.  Supply of clothing.Neutral Group.    Chile.  Damage to German ships.    Denmark. -Danish-Icelandic agreement.  Anti-Entente propaganda.    Finland. Finland and  the North.  Allied subjects.  Constitution. German commercial interference.    Honduras. Boundary dispute with Nicaragua.    Mexico. -Revolutionary movements.   The oil decrees.  Paper imports and silver exports.    Netherlands.--New Cabinet.  Transit of German military material.   Petroleum from Austria.    Peru. Surrender  of Ancon mutineers. Utilisation of German ships.    Spain. Attitude towards German submarine campaign.    Sweden. German safe-conducts for Baltic shipping.    Switzerland.   Swiss supplies.Peace Discussions (classified in text).(33)fi46o--2fc  Pk    100 9/18  K &amp; S             A
PART  II.-FOREIGN  AND  GENERAL.GENERAL.    Sinkings. According to the War Trade Intelligence Bureau, the total tonnageof 500 tons gross in the case  of  steamers, and 100 tons gross  in  the  case  of sailing-ships, reported lost owing to the malice  of the King&apos;s enemies  during the  periodAugust 30th-September 5th inclusive, was 50,328 tons gross,  of which 27.051 were british, as compared with 67,716 tons gross, of  which 43,920 were British, reported last week.    German Safe-Conducts.-At the  instance of the United States Government  the associated Governments have communicated a declaration  to the  Spanish, Dutch andScandinavian  Governments  regarding the acceptance of  German safe-conducts byneutral vessels.   The declaration  insists that such  &quot;safe-conducts,&quot;  improperlyso called, constitute  in  fact  a  threat to condemn or destroy any neutral shippingwhich refuses  to accept German  control.   They may thus operate to  deprive of theirneutral character vessels accepting that  control.    The   Associated  Governmentsreserve the right to deal appropriately with any such vessel.    It  is  ^considered  that   the  Swedish Government   would-be  violating   itsagreement (of May 29th see Reports Nos. 70-74) with the Allies if  it permitted  theacceptance of  any control tending to inrpecle the export to the  Associated Govern-ments  of  goods  manufactured with the  aid  of  materials  imported  under  theagreement  for that purpose.    (And see Reports Nos. 80. and 82-84;  also No.  79under &quot;United States.&quot;)    Austro-Hungarian Prisoners in Hands of  Czecho-Slovaks. Sir  H.  Rumboldreports that the Austrian Red Cross  has approached the Geneva Red Cross  claiming,under threat of reprisals, that Austro-Hungarian  prisoners captured by the Czecho-Slovaks in Russia and Siberia should be repatriated under the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk.The Geneva Red Cross has transmitted  this communication to the Allied Ministers,explaining to the Austrian Red Cross its inability to intervene in a political matter.ALLIED  GROUP.                                    CHINA.    New President. Sir J.  Jordan reports the election,  on September  4th, of HsuSIuh-Chang as  President of  the  Republic.   The  new  President is the senior civilmember of the  Northern Party, and  was Grand  Secretary  under the Empire.   his election by the new Parliament recently convened at Peking was almost unanimous.The Vice-Presidential election, however, is likely to  be postponed on account of competing claims.  The Cabinet has resigned, but will probably carry on its functionsuntil the  inauguration which takes place in October.   It is not yet clear what effect the election will have upon the existing internal dissensions, and upon the  attitude ofthe  Southern  Party and the old Parliament which  is now  assembled at Canton ;ostensibly  they are refusing to admit the validity of any action taken  by the new government.     Probable modification  of Japanese Policy. The Foreign Office  learns that thefall, of Tuan Chi-Jui&apos;s  Government is likely to coincide  with a  modification in theChinese policy  of Japan, which has hitherto been disposed to give  official  support tothe military element in Peking, while  permitting  financial  assistance (in  return for economic concessions)  to be given by unofficial agents  to the North in its struggle against the South.     Collection  of Customs  Revenue. Sir J. Jordan learns  from Canton that theMilitary Government  has appointed  two Chinese officials to collect Customs revenueon its behalf.  In order to prevent such local appropriation of  the Customs revenue
of the Southern ports to the detriment of foreign bondholders, the Foreign Office hasauthorised His Majesty&apos;s Consul-General at Canton to adopt certain measures suggestedby him.   The Southern Government has undertaken that the military authorities shallnot  resort to force.  The Military Government is having  recourse  to the customs revenue  for  its expenses, because  the Southern Parliament  is already absorbing themain part of the salt revenue.  Sir d. Jordan submits  that the Allied governments might well  take  this occasion to point out to the  Chinese people the  futility of continued internal dissension upon  their  welfare  and on foreign interests  in the-country ;  and to insist that the release of further Customs revenue  cannot  be con-sidored unless and until an earnest effort of reconciliation shall have been made by both parties.     Tibet. -Sir J.. Jordan  learns  that the Military Governor of Szechuen is taking-steps to release the garrison at Yachow for  service against the Tibetans.  He is  alsoabout to confer with  the Military Governor of Yun-nan at Chuiigdviiig.  This wouldseem to point to a rapprochement between the two provinces, tending  towards unitedoperations on the frontier.  (And see Imports Nos. 65, 76, 82 and 83.)                                    FRANCE.     Views of M. Thomas on an International Socialist Conference. M. Albert Thomas, &apos;the Socialist Deputy,  has published,  an  article  in  LTIumanite pointing out that theGerman  Majority Socialists have  (I) voted Avar credits ;  (2) merely abstained from voting for the Brest-Ditovsk Treaty ;  (3) feebly protested against the crushing of  theFinnish  Republic; (4) allowed the  people of  Russia  to  be enslaved;  (5) scarcelyprotested against the peace imposed on Rumania.  In the face of these facts M. Thomasdeclares  that,  much as he desires  an International Socialist Conference, a conferencein  which German  Majority Socialists  would take  part is impossible at the presenttime.  (And see Report No. 84.)                                     ITALY.    Jugo Stav Question. The Foreign Office learns that the polemics in the  Italiannewspapers regarding the dugo-Slav question are being used by the enemy  Press aspropaganda to prove to the dugo-Slavs how  strong is Italian hostility to their nationalaspirations and how little help they can expect  from the  Allies in their realisation.Signor Orlando is endeavouring to  accommodate the views  held  by Baron Sonninoand Signor Bissolati respectively upon this question.  . There is reason to believe thatBaron Sonnino has assented  to the formation  of a Southern Slav Legion.   (And seeReport No.  84.)    Projected  Release  of  Cotton  for Exportation  to  Switzerland. The  ItalianGovernment has assured Mr. Erskinc that in its negotiations for release of  cotton toSwitzerland (see Report No. 84) it is not overlooking the blockade  and  the interestsof the Allies ;  it declares that no cotton will be released without the fullest security,and states that it intends  by the agreement  to obtain definite possession of all suspectconsignments while releasing only  such cotton as is already the property of   bond  fideSwiss purchasers.    It seems likely,  that the 15,000 hales in question will in fact be consigned tothe S.S.S. for distribution to specified factories under  ail arrangement by which acorresponding output is supplied for Allied purposes.    Socialist Congress. A Press message from Rome (September 5th) states that thethree days&apos; secret session  of the Socialist Congress has come to an  end.    Three  resolutions  were submitted by the  three  groups, the  Extremist,  theCentralist&apos; Intransigent,  and the  Parliamentary  group.  The   resolution  of  the extremists obtained 14,015  votes, the  Centralist Intransigents 2,607, and the  Parlia-mcntary group 2,505.  ddre resolution which was adopted commended  the action ofthe Party leaders, expressed  the  thanks  of the  Proletariat to the  Socialist  paperAvanti, and its disapproval of the conduct of the  Socialist Parliamentary group since february 1917, especially the recent speech of  Turati  and of the  vote of  solidaritypreviously&apos; passed  by this  group,   ddie resolution finally urged  the  Parliamentary
group  strictly to submit to the,orders of the Executive, and proposed new penalties for insubordinate members, including expulsion from the party.   (And  see reports nos. 67-72 and 79.)                                    JAPAN.                              (See under &quot; China.&quot;) ,                                 NICARAGUA.                             (See under &quot;Honduras.)ENEMY  GEOUP.                             AUST RIA-HUNGA RY.     Enemy Conferences at Vienna. According to enemy Press reports, the following:persons assembled at Vienna last week :  the German Eoreigm Secretary, Admiral vonHirtze, and Under Secretary,  Baron von  Stmrmi; the Turkish Grand Vizier, TalaatPasha, and Under  Secretary for Foreign Affairs,  Reschad  Hichmet (accompanied bythe German. Ambassador  Count Bernstorff); and  the King of  Bulgaria with PrinceCyril.  Various conferences have  taken place; amongst other subjects, the polish question and the accommodation of Turkish and Bulgarian aspirations appear to havebeen discussed.                                  GERMANY.    The Chancellorship and Government. A report from Vienna (see under Austria-Hungary) to the Leipziger Tageblatt states that Count He.rtli.ng is to be replaced byDr. Solf (see Reports Nos.  65 and 84), and that Erzberger (see Reports Nos. 55, 65, 73,75, and 83) and Scheidemann (see Reports Nos. 54-59, 66, 70 and 76 ;  also Nos. 50-54and 67 under &quot;Denmark &quot;) are likely to enter the Government as representatives oftheir  parties.  The  Dusseldorfer Nachrichten  has  an  article on political intriguesagainst Hertling led by Erzberger, Richthofen and possibly Haussmann.    Germany and Russia. In connection with the opinion ascribed to Helfferich (seeReport No. 84) that Germany should abandon the Bolshevists and support a monarchistgroup in Russia, reports  received by the Foreign Office are  of some interest whichstate (1) that Kerensky and Czar roubles are being purchased in Scandinavia apparentlyfor German account, while Bolshevist roubles are not in demand: (2) that germany is now allowing the return to Warsaw of  various  Polish refugees  in Scandinavia,to whom such permission  has  hitherto been refused on account of their identificationwdth the imperial regime in Russia.     War  Aims   and   Methods   of   the   Crown  Prince. German  Wireless  ofSeptember  5th  reports  long  interviews  given  by the  Crown Prince  to repre-sentati ves of Az est  and  the  Neues   Wiener Journal.  To the former he  said:&quot; The word &apos; Victory &apos; must not  be understood to mean that we  are going to destroyour enemy, but only in  this way,  that  we  want to maintain   ourselves,  and  not allow  ourselves  to  be defeated.  Prom  the moment England entered  into the loqrthis was clear to me, and I have  said  it over and over again.&quot;  To the latter hesaid :  &quot; I have  never been of  opinion  that we could  crush  our enemies.  Also Ido not think  it desirable that our enemies  should be  destroyed,  because  in this world there is room enough for all  nations.&quot;     vorwarts asks why Kiihlmann was dismissed for putting forward a less extremeview  at a more appropriate time (see Reports Nos.  76 and 77), and  comparing theseexpressions with the  KaiseFs speech  of June  16th (sea Reports  Nos. 73  and 74)&quot;observes, &quot; This is something different from  a  conflict of  two  world philosophies,of which one must be absolutely overcome.&quot;
      The Feichsanzeiger announces thai; the Kaiser has now conferred upon fvfihlmaun. tire Order of the Red Eagle (First Class).      According to a Viennese telegram Admiral von Hintze, addressing representatives of the Austrian and Hungarian Press on September 5th, declared : &quot; One  of  my most important  tasks  is to  endeavour  to support  everything  that  may  in any  way bring an honourable peace  nearer,  In this endeavour intellectual weapons play as influential and important a role as the battlefield and diplomacy.&quot;      Prussian  Franchise lie,form, and the Monarchy.- According to a Berlin telegram of September 5th, Count Hertling, in opening the  discussion at the first meeting of the Constitution Committee of the Prussian Upper House, made the following observation regarding the Prussian  Franchise Bill: &quot;It  is mo  longer a question of Ministerial responsibility in the ordinary political sense.   Much,  more is  at stake.   Gentlemen, my honest conviction is that with this serious question the protection and preservation of the Crown and. the Dynasty arc at stake,   duereforo, try  to  find a road that leads to an understanding.  As has been already stated, the Government sees no possibility of approving the  Bill in the form it reached you from the Lower House.  I have already pointed  out in the Lower Bouse that I fully appreciated the honourable  geutlemeiPs scruples about the introduction  of General Equal Suffrage.  But, gentlemen, at the present time these scruples must, give way to greater tasks, namely, the protection of the  most precious treasures of our political, life, namely, the Dynasty and the Crown.&quot;      On.  this Vorwarls  remarks: &quot; Hertlings appeal to the Prussian Upper House on  the franchise question  is based  on the danger to the Crown and  dynasty which the rejection of  equal franchise would entail.   It would  have  been much better for a  convinced Monarchist, apprehensive of the welfare of the monarchy, to advise  the King to appoint a convinced champion of equal  franchise in. his stead a. man  wdio would force the equal franchise through against  all obstacles for the sake of people themselves and. not for  that of  the ruling  family.   Hertling wants electoral reform. by the Upper House for the benefit of  the Crown, but  we want  it by the  people  and for them.  There is an  abyss between t,he two views, and where  is the bridge ? &quot;     Criticising President  Wilsoifs message to Labour, the Wieiniselie Zeitung (Social. Democratic)  observes : &quot;  ....  Let us show the world,  by  deeds  that Wilson&apos;s definition of  the German mentality is wrong. . All. reports agree that liberal, internal. reforms would greatly  increase Germany&apos;s prestige and. improve  peace prospects. Idie  Western  world does  not  understand  Germany.  The  French, English,  and Americans consider the German  authority-state a  relic of  barbarism, and nothing has greater effect with  them  than  the talk of  Prussian autocracy and militarism.  Even neutrals  generally share  this view.   As long as these conditions  obtain, we  might have angels&apos; tongues and yet be unable to convince the  American workers  that Wilson is  a humbug,   ddie disgusting game the Prussian J linkers and  their followers  are playing with the Prussian Franchise  reform  is  quite sufficient&apos; alone to make  the great mas?  of  Americans believe the Presidents talk and  accept  even bis  worst exaggerations.&quot;     Dr. Friedberg, Vice-President of the Prussian Cabinet, speaking in the Franchise Committee  of  the Prussian &quot;Upper House,  stated  that  he  did. not  believe that a necessary sequel of the extension of the franchise would  be  the  Parliamentarisation of the Government.   The appointment of Ministers was a privilege of the Crown,  and so it would remain in the future.  (And see Report No. 79.)     Supply of Clothing. A report received (M.I. G B., No.  711) indicates that the supply of clothing for the German Army has so  far  been  maintained at  a  working, if  not wholly satisfactory,  standard, but that this  has been done  at the serious cost of depreciating the stamina, and, in  fact, gravely imperilling the health of the millions of  workers at home,  ddie maintenance of an adequate  supply for the army itself will after a few months be dependent on transport  facilities  from Russia.  Emphasis is laid  on the possibilities which economic pressure in  this  connection provides  for constraining the Germans to accept a suitable peace.     A further report (No. 712) states that the smuggling of clothes from Switzerland to  Germany and Austria is being  actively carried on, particularly by the relatives ofinterned prisoners.     Reference  has previously been made to a similar traffic from  Holland.6465-2bB
NEUTRAL GROUP.                                    CHILE.    Damage to German Ships. Sir E. Strange learns that the action of the germans in disabling their steamers in Chilean ports (see Report No. 84), is strongly criticised in Chile, particularly as in some instances the Chilean port authorities were prevented from  approaching the  ships when  the  explosions  were heard.  Apparently everyGerman steamship in  Chilean waters has been damaged with the exception of threewhich the Chilean Government propose to hire.                                  DENMARK.    Danish-Icelandic Agreement. In a Memorandum (G.T. 5025, dated September 4tli)upon  the Danish-Icelandic  Agreement (see Reports Nos.  50, 54, 67-7.1, 73, 74, 76,82, and 83), the Political Intelligence  Department points  out that the Agreement  isin the form of a draft proposal for a Danish-Icelandic  Constitution, which, if ratified,will como into force on December 1st.  The Bill is to come  before the Danish Rigsdagand the Icelandic Althing, and has further to be submitted to a plebiscite  in Iceland, inaccordance with the Icelandic Fundamental Law of June  1.0th, 1.915.   If it is passed itwill remain in force until the year 1940.   After that year, either the Rigsdag or theAlthing can at any time demand that the negotiations for the revision of the law be recom-meneed.   It nrayjbe taken for granted that the Rigsdag  will pass the Bill, and, as 3Soutof 40  members  of the Althing have voted in favour of the proposal,  it would appearcertain  that, unless public opinion in  Iceland veers completely round an unlikelycontingency the plebiscite  will, result  in. an overwhelming majority in support of  it.The continued control, to a large  extent, of Icelandic foreign policy by Denmark mayjjossibly  be the result of the promptings  of Mr. Borgbjerg (see Report No. 73) ; andthe Swedish Activist Stockholms Daghlad takes  care to  attribute  the  necessity for theAgreement to the schemes of &quot;certain Great Powers &quot;  which  would press Iceland intoa wholly &quot;separatist policy.   The clause allowing equal citizenship is in view&quot; of thegreater population of &quot;Denmark (31- million Danes as compared with 150,000  Icelanders) likely  to affect Icelandic nationality  rather than  the political  and economic life of denmark.    Anti-Entente Propaganda. Sir R. Paget reports that  the Bolshevist  version  ofrecent events  at Moscow and Petrograd.--containing allegations against the allied representatives has been appearing in the Social  Democrat  (as to which  see ReportNo. 54).   A Bolshevist Bress Bureau is  also  expected to start  operations  in Copen-hagen.   It will  probably  receive  German support and conduct  a campaign againstthe Entente.  The attention  of the Danish. Government  has been  called  to  these activities.                                   FINLAND.    Finland and the North. The Foreign Office learns that the German attack  onMurman is designed to begin in October,  and that the  Finnish troops will be requiredto participate.   The Germans have insisted that the Finnish Army shall be increasedto a minimum of 45,000  men, which  will involve the calling up of  several additionalclasses.  The Finnish  Military  Authorities opposed  this  increase (for  which theGermans have  guaranteed  payment)  and the troops still  object to joining, in the expedition.  The Germans are, however, determined to entangle Finland in  the war,and for that purpose are  spreading  reports  that the  British  intend  to  attack thecountry.     Allied Subjects. The Foreign. Office learns that British,  subjects in Finland arenow permitted   to draw money freely provided they  do not send it out of the country.The attitude of the  Finnish  Foreign  Ministry is  very conciliatory.   The  position ofAllied subjects in Finland may, however,  become very  serious if the Germans succeed in forcing a Finnish offensive.     Constitution. The  Foreign Office learns  that the Duke  of Hesse  is a likelycandidate for the throne of Finland.   The Finnish Press has, however,  published  an
announcement  from Berlin that  no German  Prince will accept the Finnish thronewithout sufficient  guarantees,  which can  only  be given after the political parties in the Diet have agreed on. the  question  of  the Constitution.  Under the heading,&quot;An International  Scandal,&quot;  the Swedish  Social-Demokraten &quot;reports that  at thelatest sitting of the Finnish Diet only one representative of the  Finnish Social-Democrat Party was present.  &quot;The rest  of  the Party&apos;s 93-members,&quot; the journalsays, &quot; had. either  fled,  from the country,  been imprisoned, or were dead.   Many ofthe Social-Democratic members of the Diet have been  imprisoned without any legalcause, and others forcibly hindered from attending the Diet.&quot;    German Commercial  Interference. It is reported (ALL 6 B., No. 71.2) that theGermans are not allowing orders for goods to be  given from Finland, to Scandinaviaor other countries except through German firms.   (And see Deport No. 84.)    (And sec under &quot; Sweden.&quot;)                                  HONDURAS.    Boundary Dispute with Nicaragua. Mr.  Barclay reports that the United  StatesGoA&apos;ernment has induced the Governments of  Nicaragua and Honduras to recall their troops from the disputed  area (see Reports Nos. 82-84) and to send representatives to Washington with a view to - the  discussion of the matter.  The State department will lend its good offices to assist in an agreement,  but not in a fresh arbitration.                                    MEXICO.    Revolutionary Movements. The Mexican Press of  September 4th announces the discovery of a plot against the Government and numerous arrests in connection thgre-with.   The plot, which Mr. Thurstan understands  to have been initiated by certain ofCarranza&apos;s own following, is said to have  aimed at  the  arrest  of Carranza and the capture of Necaxa by Caraveo.   Mr. ddrurstan  reports  rumours  of  revolutionaryactivity in various  parts of the country by Caraveo,  Aguilar, Barron, and Mexqueiro,and expresses the opinion that a combined movement is not improbable.  M. Pelaezis already threatening Tampico, the garrison  of which, has recently been strengthened by the arrival of Alvarez  and  300 men  (wrongly rumoured  [see Report  No. 84] tohave  joined  Pelaez),  while Caballero is stated  to have already seized  the Tampicowaterworks  at Camatole.   On September  9th the power lines from Necaxa to MexicoCity were cut  by rebels.  Owing to the depredations both of the rebels and thegarrison at Minatitlan, it is feared  that the refiner)- may have to be closed.    The  Oil Decrees. Mr.  Barclay  learns  that  the  new oil  decree (see reports nos. 81, S2  and  84) is now unlikely to  be carried into execution pending  an  appealto the Courts, which wdll probably occupy two months.    Paper  Imports  and   Silver  Exports. Mr. Thurstan reports  that the mexican government recently  decreed that the import tax on,paper should  be paid in  kindinstead of in specie, probably with the  object of  supplying the local German  Presswhich has suffered from American restrictions.   The United States Government hasnow placed  an embargo  upon the  supply  of  paper to Mexico, and  the mexican government is stated to  intend Lto prohibit the  exportation  of silver by way of retaliation.                               NETHERLANDS.    New Cabinet. Mr. Robertson reports that the official composition of the Dutch-Cabinet is annoimced as follows,:     Minister for Interior   -                     Jonkheer Ruys de Beerenbrouck.    Minister for Foreign Affairs       -       -   Jonkheer A. van  Karnebeek.    Minister of Justice     -        -         -   Mr. Pleemskerk.    Minister of Finance      -        -       -   Mr. S. de Vries.    Minister of War       ...   Jonkheer G. A. Alting van Geusau.    Minister of Inland Waterways     -       -   Mr. A. A. H. Ivonig.    Minister of Agriculture and Industries     -   Mr. van Ysselsteyn.    Minister for Colonies   -                     Mr. A.. F. Idenburg.    (And see Report No. 84.)
    Transit  of  German  Military  Material. Mr.  - Robertson  reports  that  ^he-Netherlands Foreign  Minister has  protested to the  German Government against thecontinued  passage of  military material  over  the   Limburg&apos;  Railways,  as being-contrary to the arrangement reached in April.   There has been no subsequent trafficof this nature.  (And see Reports Nos. 75, 76, and 83.)     Petroleum from Austria. The Dutch  Press reports that Austria is prepared tosupply Holland with 5,000 tons  of  petroleum,  ddie Foreign  Office is informed that.this offer is connected with unredeemed credit mentioned in Report No. 84.                                     PERU.    Surrender of Aneon Mutineers. Mr. Rennie reports the surrender of the A neon.mutineers (see Report No. 83).  ddie movement does not appear to have spread.    Utilisation  of  German Ships. Mr. Rennie reports  the  signature of a contract between the Peruvian Government  and the United States Shipping Board regardingthe utilisation of the German ships lying in Peruvian ports.                                    SPAIN.     Attitude towards German  Submarine Campaign. Pending  a decision by  theSpanish Government regarding German submarine outrages (see Reports Nos. 82-84-),the Ambassadors of the Associated Powers have  handed to the Spanish  Foreign.Minister  a copy of  their declaration  regarding German  safe-conducts  (see under&quot;General&quot;).  Negotiations  by the Italian Government for  the  purchase of enemy-ships in Spanish waters  have been suspended.   The Germans are working to persuade the Spanish Government (1)  that  the Allies  wish to involve  Spain, in the war,  and(2) that the seizure of German ships would, lead to serious internal troubles.     (And see under &quot; General &quot; and &quot; Switzerland.&quot;)                                   SWEDEN.     German Safe-Conducts for Baltic Shipping. According to the Swedish Press ofSeptember 7th, the German  authorities  are now demanding that all vessels engagedin Baltic trade, including small Finnish  fishing smacks which carry timber between.Finland and Stockholm, shall carry safe-conducts.                               SWITZERLAND.    Swiss. Supplies. Mr. Barclay reports that the United. States War Trade  Board isarranging that negotiations shall take place at Washington regarding  the  renewal ofthe Swiss-American agreement which expires  at the end of this month.  The ForeignOffice has instructed him to urge the importance of keeping  in touch with the Britishand French Governments, suggesting the preferability of Paris for that purpose. -  Inview of the tin desirability of the Swiss Government obtaining enemy tonnage in. Spain(and see under &quot; Spain &quot;), the Dutch East Indies or Chile, the British, French and UnitedStates  Governments are considering the question of  allocating to it tonnage at theirown disposal sufficient to lift its monthly requirements  ol:  grain.  German Wirelessof September 6th enlarges with much complacency upon the extension by Germanj^of safe-conducts to cover not only grain and a limited number of commodities (underthe agreement of April 24th), but also &quot; all important foodstuffs and luxuries as wellas the  chief  industrial and  raw materials &quot; carried  to Cette for  Switzerland,   ddieZuricher Post of August 31st is cpuoted as saying : &quot; We have at  least now a  proof that the German  Government is making  an  effort to mitigate the hardness  of u-boat  warfare and is  commencing to take  into consideration the vital interests of;neutrals.&quot;     (And see under &quot; Italy.&quot;)
PEACE DISCUSSIONS.     (N.B. Countries are now grouped in alphabetical order under this heading.)    General.- Peace &quot; discussions &quot; can hardly he so called  at  present as they  are confined to one side.  Nearly all proposals  for peace can he traced to German origin,and indicate the view of the military strategists that they have passed the culminatingpoint of offensive power, and  wish to mate peace  while they still hold immenseplunder and &quot;pawns &quot;for negotiation.   Switzerland appears to be the chief centre of activity at present, but indications also appear in Holland and other countries.    France. Lord  Derby, on September 4th, called  attention to an  article  byM. Thomas, in Humanite, in which reasons are given for  the  impossibility  of holdingan international  conference with German Majority Socialists.   (See under  &quot;France&quot;on page 3.)    Germany. While the  longing for peace  amongst  the  people  seems  to   beundoubted, there is  still a complete absence  of definition in  any official statementupon  the terms of peace.    In  the  Amsterdam  Tijd  (Catholic)  a report is published  (Sir  W.  Townley,September 6th) about the alleged intention of the Central Powers to initiate proposalsfor an armistice, after a private expression  of their willingness to consent to ViscountGrey&apos;s suggestions for  the establishment  of  a League  of Nations.  All  the  Dutchpapers reproduced the report on. September 6th.  The Tijd alleges that it originatedin Berlin, but Sir W. Townlfey does not believe this, and  is making enquiries.    German Wireless (see especially September 9th) continues to give prominence toLeague of Nations proposals.     Great  Britain. The  Ministry  of  Labour,  in a  report for the  week  ending  on  %September 4-th, draws attention, to subtle and misleading appreciations of the militarysituation in certain Labour papers (New Statesman and Workers&apos; Dreadnought).    It has been necessary to postpone  issuing  the Appendix on the  Derby Congressreferred to in last weelds report, to allow more time for compilation.     Holland. See under Germany and Switzerland.     &quot;Russia. According to German Wireless of  September 5th, the ratification of the supplementary treaty to. the Brest-Litovsk  Treaty took place  in Moscow on September2nd.  ddiis statement was corroborated in  Russian Wireless of the   same  date.  Idieterms have  been published  in the  British  Press ; also in  Russian Wireless ofSeptember 5th.   German Wireless  of September 7th and 9th advertises Germanophilcomments (doubtless of German origin.) on the treaty In  the Russian. Press.   Sir  M.Findlay (September  9th) also gave a short  precis of  the  terms.  The  main point isthat  the Bolshevists, claiming to act for &quot;Russia,&quot; undertake what amounts  to war against the Allied forces in  the north,   ddie Germans deprive Russia of Livonia  andEsthonia, in  addition to the large territories already lost.     Spain. See under Switzerland.     Sweden. Information received through Sir H. Rumbold  (September 3rd, received9th) alleges that the Swedish Government  will  abstain from any attempt at mediationbetween the belligerent Powers, for fear of alienating the sympathies of the EntenteAlliance.     Switzerland. Sir H.  Rumbold on September  3rd (received 9th) reported  on good authority&apos; that  discussion is proceeding in Swiss Government  circles about theFederal Council taking the initiative by declaring publicly that, in view of the changein the military  situation, they are ready to offer their services for initiation of nego-tiations &quot; for which  the time is now ripe.&quot;   It  is considered probable that  the Federal Council will soon be approached in this sense by the Central Empires, ddie  weightof Swiss opinion is reported to be against  the  probability of any Swiss official move.Early in August, the King of Spain and the President of the Council are reported tohave sent delegates  to Switzerland  to  sound German and Austro-Hungarian  agentsabout conditions of entry  into negotiations.   These  agents are credited  with  the reply that Germany would only do  so on the understanding  that no preliminarydemands  must  be  made,  previous  to  commencement of  actual negotiations.
                                         10                                   v,^v(Compare German demands  leading  to negotiation with  Rumania  (see  WesternReport  No.  55, page  14).)  The  Spanish  delegates returned  to  Spain  with the conviction, that no mediation  has any chance  of success at the present time.   (see also under Vatican.)    On  September  5th Sir Id. Rumbold pointed out that  when M. Troelstra made his statements, German representatives, including Heine  and Scheidemann, were inSwitzerland.  It was doubtless with  the object  of  making trouble  with the BritishGovernment that Troelstra made the  suggestion that representatives of the majority in the Reichstag should meet  the pacifists of Great Britain, and work energetically in both, countries to promote a peace, on  the lines originally put forward by  PresidentWilson.   In  a previous  telegram   (September 3rd)  Sir  II.  Rumbold   furnishedevidence of  the Germanophil sympathies of Troelstra.  German Wireless of September10th gives prominence&quot;to an  article in the  Vorwarts on the  &quot;failure  of  the peaceattempt&quot; by Troelstra.    There have been many references in the Press to the activities of German agents&quot;in. Switzerland, notably a Rome telegram in  The Times of  September 5th, giving the alleged peace  negotiation  terms,  on the  authority  of  Italian  correspondents inSwitzerland.    Ukraine. German Wireless of September 9th gives a full account of the KaisePsspeech at the breakfast to  the Hetman, and the Hetmau&apos;s  reply.   In the  speeches,which have  been reported in the Press, an attempt was made to prove that  the BrestUkrainian treaty was advantageous to  the Ukrainians.  (N.B. At  the time,  the treaty was freely advertised from the point of view  of the great economic  advantages to theGermans and .Austro-Hungarians, thereby wrested from Idle Ukrainian people.)    Vatican. According   to information   forwarded   by  Sir   II.    Rumbold.(September  3rd,  received  9th), the  Vatican  considers  that  all efforts   to  bring-about peace negotiations are  futile, pending the full effect  of American intervention in the war, and of the blockade of the  Central Empires.

</content>
</cab>
