<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/37/29 images: 228-235</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.June 1943.SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (43) 229.2nd June, 1943./&quot;WAR CA3INEVUNITED   NATIONS   RELIEF   AND   rehabilitation administration.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate herewith, for the information of my colleagues, the text of thedraft United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agreement as finally approvedby the Four Powers (viz., the United States, the United Kingdom, Russia and china).*2. The United States Government propose to circulate copies of the draft agreement to the other United Nations, for their consideration, in the course ofthe next few days, and to release it to the Press shortly afterwards. The precisedate has not yet been fixed and meanwhile this draft should continue to be treatedas confidential.2nd June, 1943.* An earlier Draft of the Agreement dated the 13th August, 1942, was circulated with . D.Board of Trade, S.W.1,W.P. (42) 478.[25531]b
Strictly Confidential.AGREEMENT   FOR   UNITED   NATIONS   RELIEF    and rehabilitation ADMINISTRATION.Draft of 15th May, 1943.THE Governments or Authorities whose duly-authorised representatives havesubscribed hereto,Being United Nations or being associated with the United. Nations in this war,Being determined that immediately upon the liberation of any area by the armed forces of the United Nations the population thereof shall receive aid and relief from their sufferings, food, clothing and shelter, aid in the prevention ofpestilence and in the recovery of the health of the people, and that preparation and arrangements shall be made for the return of prisoners and exiles to their homes, for the resumption of agricultural and industrial production and therestoration of essential services, to the end that peoples once freed may be preserved and restored to health and strength for the tasks and opportunities ofbuilding anew,Have agreed as follows :Article I.There is hereby established the United Nations Relief and rehabilitation administration.1. The Administration shall have power to acquire, hold and conveyproperty, to enter into contracts and undertake obligations, to designate or createagencies and to review the activities of agencies so created, to manage under-takings,and in general to perform any legal act appropriate to its objects and purposes.2. Subject to the provisions of Article VII, the purposes and functions ofthe Administration shall be as follows :(a) To plan, co-ordinate, administer or arrange for the administration of measures for the relief of victims of war in any area under the controlof any of the United Nations through the provision of food., fuel,clothing and other basic necessities, housing facilities, medical andother essential services; and to facilitate in areas receiving relief theproduction and transportation of these articles and the furnishingof these services so far as necessary to the adequate provision of relief.The form of activities of the Administration within the territory of amember government wherein that government exercises administrativeauthority and the responsibility to be assumed by the member govern-ment for carrying out measures planned by the Administration thereinshall be determined after consultation with and &quot;with the consent, ofthe member government.(b) To formulate and recommend measures for individual or joint action by any or all of the member governments for the co-ordination of purchasing, the use of ships and other procurement activities in theperiod following the cessation of hostilities, with a view to integratingthe plans and activities of the Administration with the total move-ment of supplies, and for the purpose of achieving an equitable distribution of available supplies. The Administration mayadminister such co-ordination measures as the member governmentsauthorize.(c) To formulate and recommend for individual or joint action by any or all of the member governments measures with respect to such related,matters, arising out of its experience in planning and performing thework of relief and rehabilitation, as may be proposed by any of the member governments and approved by unanimous vote of the&quot; central committee.Article II.Membership.The members of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administra-tion shall be the governments or authorities signatory hereto and such other
governments or authorities as may upon application for membership be admittedtheretpby action by the Council, or between sessions of the Council, by the central committee.Wherever the term &quot;member government&quot; is used in this Agreement itshall be construed to embrace such authorities as shall have signed the Agreementor shall subsequently become members of the Administration.Article III. -The Council.1. Each member government shall name one representative, and suchalternates as may be necessary, upon the.Council of the United Nations relief and Rehabilitation Administration, which shall be the policy-making body ofthe Administration. The Council shall, for each of its sessions, select one of its members to preside at the session. * -v2. The Council shall be convened in normal session not less than twice ayear by the Central Committee. It may be convened in special session whenever the Central Committee shall deem necessary, and shall be convened within thirty days after request therefor by a majority of the members of the Council.3. The Central Committee of the Council shall consist of the representativesof China, the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, the United Kingdom, and theUnited States of America, with the Director-General presiding. Between sessions of the Council it shall exercise all the powers and functions thereof. It shallinvite the participation of the representatives of any member government at those-of its meetings at which action of special interest to such government is discussed..It shall invite the participation of the representative serving as Chairman of theCommittee on Supplies of the Council at those of its meetings at which policies,affecting the provision of supplies are discussed.4. The Committee on Supplies of the Council shall consist of the members.of the Council, or their alternates, representing those member governments likely;to be principal suppliers of materials for relief and rehabilitation. The members shall be appointed by the Central Committee, with the approval of the Councilif it be in session and otherwise subject to its ratification. The Committee on.Supplies shall consider, formulate and recommend to the Central Committeeand the Council policies designed to assure the provision of required supplies.The Central Committee shall from time to time meet with the Committee on supplies to review policy matters affecting supplies.5. The Committee of the Council for Europe shall consist of all the membersof the Council, or their alternates, representing member governments of territorieswithin the European area, and such other members of the Council, representingother governments directly concerned with the problems of relief and rehabilitation-tion in the European area, as shall be appointed by the Central Committee, withthe approval of the Council if it be in session and otherwise subject to its ratification. The Committee of the Council for the Far East shall consist of allthe members of the Council, or their alternates, representing member governmentsof territories within the Far Eastern area, and such other members of the Councilrepresenting other governments directly concerned with the problems of relief&quot;and rehabilitation in.the Far Eastern area as shall be appointed by the Central.Committee, with the approval of the Council if it be in session and otherwise-subject to the Council&apos;s ratification. The regional committees shall normallymeet within their respective areas. They shall consider and recommend to theCouncil and the Central Committee policies with respect to relief or rehabilitationwithin their respecive areas. The Committee of the Council for Europe shall&apos;,replace the Inter-Allied Committee on European post-war relief established inLondon on the 24th September, 1941, and the records of the latter shall be made,available to the Committee for Europe.6. The Council shall establish such other standing regional committees as;it shall consider desirable, the functions of such committees and the method of&quot;appointing their members being identical to that provided in paragraph 5 of thisArticle with respect to the Committees of the Council for Europe and for the-Far East. The Council shall also establish such other standing committees asit considers desirable to; advise it, and, in intervals between sessions of theCouncil, to advise the Central Committee. ! For such technical standing com-[25531] b 2
mittees as may be established, in respect of particular problems such as nutrition,health, agriculture, transport, repatriation, and finance, the members may be members of the Council or alternates nominated by them because of special com-competence in their respective fields of work. The members shall be appointed by theCentral Committee, with the approval of the Council if it be in session and otherwise subject to its ratification. Should a regional committee so desire, sub-committees of the technical standing committees shall be established by thetechnical committees in consultation with the regional committees, to advise the regional committees.7. The travel arid other expenses of members of the Council and of membersof its committees shall be borne by the governments which they represent.   .8. All reports and recommendations of committees of the Council shall be transmitted to the Director-General for distribution to the Council and theCentral Committee by the secretariat of the Council established under theprovisions of Article IV, paragraph 4.Article IV.The Director-General.1. The executive authority of the United Nations Relief and rehabilitation administration shall be in the Director-General, who shall be appointed by theCouncil on the nomination by unanimous vote of the Central&quot; Committee. TheDirector-General may be removed by unanimous vote of the Central Committee.2. The Director-General shall have full power and authority for carrying-out relief operations contemplated by Article I, paragraph 2 (a), within the limits of available resources and the broad policies determined by&apos; the Council or itsCentral Committee. Immediately upon taking office he shall in conjunction withthe military and other appropriate, authorities of the United Nations prepare plans for the emergency relief of the civilian population in any area occupiedby the-armed forces of any of the United Nations, arrange for the procurementand assembly of the necessary supplies and create or select the emergencyorganization required for this purpose. In arranging for the procurement,,transportation, and distribution of supplies and services, he and his representa-tives shall consult and collaborate with the appropriate authorities of the united nations and shall, wherever jDracticable, use the facilities made available by suchauthorities. Foreign voluntary relief agencies may not engage in activity in any&apos;area receiving relief from the Administration without the consent and unlesssubject to the regulation of the Director-General. The powers and duties of theDirector-General are subject to the limitations of Article VII.3. The Director-General shall also be responsible for the organization and direction of the functions contemplated by Article I, paragraphs 2 (b) and 2 (c).4. The Director-General shall appoint such Deputy Directors-General,officers, expert personnel, and staff at his headquarters and elsewhere, includingfield missions, as he shall find necessary, and he may delegate to them such of his&apos; powers as he may deem appropriate. The Director-General, or upon his autho-rization the Deputy Directors-General, shall supply such secretariat and other staff and facilities as shall be required by the Council and its committees,including the regional committees and sub-committees. Such Deputy Directors-General as shall be assigned special functions within a region shall attend meetings of the regional standing committee whenever possible and shall keep itadvised on the progress of the relief and rehabilitation program within the region.5. The Director-General shall make periodic reports to the Central Com-mittee and to the Council covering the progress of the Administration^activities. The reports shall be made public except for such portions as theCentral Committee may consider it necessary, in the interest of the united nations, to keep confidential. The Director-General shall also arrange to have prepared periodic reports covering the. activities of the Administration within each region and he shall transmit such reports with his comments thereon to theCouncil, the Central Committee and the respective regional committees.Article V.Supplies and Resources.1.   Each member government pledges its full support to the Administra-tion, within the limits of its available resources and subject to the requirementsof its constitutional procedure, through contributions of funds, materials,
equipment, supplies and services, for use in its own, adjacent or other areas in need, in order to accomplish the purposes of Article I, paragraph 2(a). all such contributions received by the Administration shall be accounted for.2. The supplies and resources made available by the member governmentsshall be kept in review in relation to prospective requirements by the Director-General, who shall initiate action with the member governments with a viewto assuring such additional supplies and resources as may be required.3. All purchases by any of the member governments, made ousicle theirown territories during the war for relief or rehabilitation purposes, shall bemade only after consultation with the Director-General, and shall, so far aspracticable, be carried out through the appropriate United Nations agency.Article VI.;Administrative Expenses.The Director-General shall submit to the Council an annual budget, andfrom time to time such supplementary budgets as may be required, covering the necessary administrative expenses of the Administration. Upon approvalof a budget by the Council the total amount approved shall be allocated to the member governments in proportions to.be determined by the Council. each member government pledges itself, subject to the requirements of its constitutionalprocedure, to contribute to the Administration promptly its share of theadministrative expenses so determined.Article VII.Notwithstanding any other provision herein contained, while hostilities orother military necessities exist in any area, the Administration and its Director-General shall not undertake activities therein without the consent of the military command of that area, and unless subject to such control as the command mays find ^necessary. The determination that such hostilities or military necessitiesexist in any area shall be made by its military commander.Article VIII.Amendment.The provisions of this agreement may be amended by unanimous vote of theCentral Committee and two-thirds vote of the Council.Article IX.Entry into force.This Agreement shall enter into force with respect to each signatory on thedate when the Agreement is signed by that signatory, unless otherwise specified by such signatory.




</content>
</cab>
