<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/39 images: 448-457</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT -Printed for the War Cabinet.   April 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)94th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 94 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, April 16, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Secretary of State for War. Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.    Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade (Item 8).The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, K.C.,M.P., Postmaster-General (Item 8).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of State,Foreign Office.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Reith, M.P.,Minister of Information (Item 8).Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. K P. Donaldson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21163]
WAR CABINET 94 (40).Contents.minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     ..................     337Reconnaissance of Wilhelmshaven.Attacks on Stavanger aerodrome.Coastal Command activity.Reconnaissance of Bergen.General Carton de Wiart at Namsos.British air forces in France.2      The Naval Situation..................     338H.M.S. Eclipse.3      The Military Situation        ...............     338Norway.Western Front.4      Scandinavia     ...      ...       ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     339&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;Allied Mission to Sweden.Proposed visit of Admiral Sir Edward Evans to Norway.5      Italy     ........................     339Probable intentions.6      Western Front.....................     340Action to be taken in the event of Netherlands or Belgium beinginvaded.7      The Balkans    ..&apos;...................     341Visit to London of His Majesty&apos;s representatives.8      Flying Boats   .....................     341Diversion of civil flying-boats for military duties.
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 93rdConclusions,Minute 1.)ReconnaissanceofWilhelmshaven.Attacks onStavangeraerodrome.CoastalCommandactivity.reconnaissance of Bergen.General Cartonde Wiart namsos.British AirForces inFrance.1. The Secretary of State for Air said that the previousmorning two Blenheims had reconnoitred the Wilhelmshaven area.Three merchant vessels had been observed and one patrol vesselhad been attacked with bombs. No shipping had been seen atHeligoland.   One of our aircraft had failed to return.About noon on the previous day 11 Blenheims had attacked the aerodrome and seaplane base at Stavanger. A number of bombs had been dropped on the aerodrome, but it had been impossibleto observe the results owing to bad weather. The attack on the4seaplane base had resulted in direct hits on two seaplanes, bothof which had disappeared. It was probable that more aircraft hadbeen damaged.The previous night a force of 12 Whitleys had been despatched to continue the attacks on Stavanger aerodrome. Owing to weather conditions, only 7 Whitleys had reached the objective. Many hitshad been observed and a fire had been started at the northern endof the aerodrome which had been seen by a later pilot to be givingoff thick black smoke, like petrol or oil. Aircraft had also been seen on fire and a large fire had started near the junction of therunways.   All our aircraft had returned.The Secretary of State added that the general view was thata great deal of damage had been done to the aerodrome. incendiary bombs, 40-lb. bombs and also 250-lb. instantaneous and delayedaction bombs had been used.Six Blenheims had left early that morning to continue harassingattacks against Stavanger aerodrome.Reconnaissance of the Norwegian coast had been continue during the previous day and all the scheduled patrols had flownin spite of poor weather conditions.A Blenheim fighter had reconnoitred Bergen about noon theprevious day and had found the inside harbour empty and50 merchant vessels in the outer harbour. Seven enemy aircraft which had previously been reported there were no longer present.The unloading jetty facing west had been observed to be on fire and the railway termini empty. Desultory A.A. fire had been encountered, but apparently from only one battery. Neither shipsnor aircraft had been found at Bergen and the place had appearedto be rather deserted.A Hudson reconnaissance had sighted two enemy destroyers70 miles south-west of Lister Light on the previous afternoon, andhad attacked with bomb and machine gun, obtaining a close miss.One of our Hudsons had been engaged by Messerschmitts 110 inthe neighbourhood of Lillesand, east of christians and. All our aircraft on these missions had returned safely,During the previous night six Beauforts had successfully laidmines in the Jade approaches. Our aircraft had been challenged,but not fired at.   One had failed to return.A Sunderland machine had successfully landed at Namsos anddisembarked General Carton de Wiart, after being subjected toattack, in company with H.M.S. Somali, by six Junkers 88 for two hours. The aircraft had suffered superficial damage and had returned to its base at 2300 hours, bringing back 2nd LieutenantElliott, the GeneraFs A.D.C., who had been wounded in the kneeduring the attack.A successful reconnaissance of a part of the Rhine had beencarried out at dawn on the previous day. Considerable barge traffichad been seen but no road or railway movement and no bridgingwork.[21163]b 2
The Naval 2.   The First Lord of the Admiralty said that H.M.S. Eclipse,Situation. which had been damaged, was now on its way from Norway in tow(Previous of H.M.S. Escort.   The tow had parted during the previous night,Reference:        and the condition of H.M.S. Eclipse was not known.W.M. (40) 93rdConclusions,Minute 2.)H.M.S. Eclipse.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 89thConclusions,Minute 2.)A French report had stated that a pocket battleship had been seen on the evening of the 12th April being towed intoFrederikshaven in a sinking condition. This information talliedwith the attack by ELM. Submarine Spearfish on the 11th April.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 92ndConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Secretary of State for War said that, according toNorwegian reports, received from our Military Attache, two German cruisers were aground at Trondhjem and there were four destroyers in the harbour. The forts guarding the entrance werein German hands, but were thought to be extremely vulnerable to air attack. There were said to be 2,000 troops in the area, andreinforcements were arriving by air.The Norwegians held Namsos, Levanger and Steinkjer. Therewere reported to be 1,000 Norwegian troops at the last-namedplace, but their morale was not thought to be very high.In general, the Norwegians were suffering from lack of armsand munitions as all but one of their arsenals had been captured.The Prime Minister asked whether (apart from the purchaseof Mauser rifles in Belgium, which he understood was contemplated)steps could be taken to send rifles and ammunition to Norway fromthis country immediately. The speedy arrival of rifles andammunition from this country would have a most heartening effecton the Norwegians, even if only a few thousand rifles could be spared.The Secretary of State for War thought that it should bepossible to provide a certain number of rifles with ammunition.The War Office were already investigating the matter.The Secretary of State for War added that there were reportedto be 2,000 German troops in the Narvik area, some of whom weresaid to be using Norwegian uniforms.Western Front. A concentration of German troops was reported in the BlackForest. The War Office, however, did not attach much importanceto this report.The War Cabinet (a) Took note of the above statements.(b) Invited the Secretary of State for War to make arrange-ments, if possible, for the early dispatch of a consign-ment of rifles and ammunition to the Norwegian forces.The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 93rdConclusions,Minute 3.)Norway.
339w.ivi. m (my.Scandinavia.Allied mission to Sweden.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 93rdConclusions,Minute 5.)Proposed visit of Admiral sir edward Evansto Norway.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 92ndConclusions,Minute 8.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theAnglo-French Mission had now returned from Sweden, but had notyet submitted their report. The Mission&apos;s observations on themilitary side had already been communicated to the Chiefs of Staff,and, on the political side, there was nothing of substance to beadded to the information already in our possession.M. Coulondre had told him that the Mission had been of greatpsychological value and that the Swedes were in good heart.It was explained that the Swedish Government had objected toa member of the Anglo-French Mission going direct from sweden to the Norwegian Government. Admiral Evans had not, therefore,been able to visit the Norwegian Government. Admiral Evans hadall the personal qualifications necessary for effective liaison with,and for giving heartening advice to the Norwegians, and moreparticularly to the King of Norway. It was most unfortunatetherefore that he had not been able to go to Norway. A suggestionthat Admiral Evans should now fly to Norway at the earliestconvenient moment met with general approval.The War Cabinet Took note of the above statement, and approved theproposal that Admiral Sir Edward Evans should proceedto Norway with a view to maintaining contact with theKing of Norway.Italy. 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionProbable to the following telegrams bearing on the intentions of the Italianintentions.        Government :-(Previous Telegram No. 39 DIPP, dated the 14th April, from his reference: Majesty&apos;s Minister to the Holy See.   A violent scene was saidW.M. (40) 93rd to  have  taken  place on  the   12th  April  between  SignorConclusions, Mussolini and Count Ciano.   The cause was said to have beenMmute 8.) Count Ciano&apos;s refusal to accept the axiomatic certainty ofBritish defeat.Telegram No. 40 DIPP, dated the 15th April, from HisMajesty&apos;s Minister to the Holy See. Mr. Osborne&apos;s information was that Signor Mussolini was in a very bad mood, presumablyowing to the news of the British successes in Scandinavia.He was said to be obsessed by the desire to go to war and tobe liable to order an attack on Greece from Albania at any moment. The reasons given by Mr. Osborne&apos;s informant forSignor Mussolini&apos;s belligerent mood were :(a) His alleged promise to Herr Hitler at the Brenner Passthat he would throw in his lot with Germany.(b) His feeling that no country which had not taken partin the war could hope to profit by the peace.It was possible that the news of the latest German navallosses and of the British landings in Norway might exercise a deterrent effect on Signor Mussolini, but in his abnormalcondition of excitability he was capable of any folly.Count Ciano had taken to his bed after the violent scene of the previous week between Signor Mussolini and himself,but was not really ill.Telegram No. 41 DIPP from His Majesty&apos;s Minister tothe Holy See, dated the 15th April. Mr. Osborne referred toa report that Germany had exchanged one battery of powerfulSkoda coastal anti-aircraft guns for a considerable number,said to be in the neighbourhood of 50, of Italian submarines.This exchange seemed inherently unlikely. The submarines were said to have been already taken over by the German crewsand to be leaving Genoa and Leghorn on the 15th April for
Germany. There had, it was stated, recently been severalGerman submarines in the Mediterranean, but these had also left.Rome telegram No. 368, dated the 13th April, reporting that an Italian naval officer travelling from Naples to Spezziahad informed the Military Attached Secretary that aggressive action by the Italian fleet was imminent, but that it would becarried out in such a way that Anglo-French susceptibilitieswould not be affected. British Press correspondents in Romehad heard a similar rumour from three separate sources, two ofwhom were military officers, who had expressed sterndisapproval.Rome telegram No. 376 DIPP. dated the 15th April,stating that the Chef de Cabinet of the Italian Air ministry had given the impression to the British Air Attache that no special measures had recently been taken by the italian authorities which might lead one to suspect that signor mussolini was about to embark on a warlike adventure.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the general effect of these telegrams was undoubtedly pessimistic. It seemedmore likely than before that Italy would come into the war against us. There was, however, one interesting indication which told inthe opposite direction. The Rex, which was now homeward bound for Naples, had left New York on the 13th April and was due at gibraltar on the following day, the 17th April. The Conte diSavoia was due to sail that day from Genoa on her west-boundvoyage.The Prime Minister said that, while the situation had certainlydeteriorated, it was not necessary to take all Signor Mussolini&apos;sthreats literally. Threats of this kind formed part of the technique of the Dictators.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that Sir percy loraine was calling at the Foreign Office that day. He had beenunwell; if sufficiently recovered, he would be asked to return to rome immediately. It was unfortunate that we had no ambassador in Rome at the present juncture.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Western Front.Action to betaken if theNetherlands or belgium is invaded.(previous references:W.M. (40) 92ndConclusions,Minute 6, andW.M. (40) 93rdConclusions,Minute 10.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs reminded hiscolleagues that the French Government had suggested that theAllies should settle now the text :(i) of a communication to be made to the Belgian government at the moment of entry of Allied troops into Belgium,and(ii) of a public announcement to be made simultaneously.Sir R. Campbell had been told by M. Leger that morning thatGeneral Gamelin had made a suggestion that it would be well toinclude in the former communication a statement that, if Belgianforces co-operated, he (General Gamelin) might be able to cover thegreater part of Belgium, but that if they made difficulties he wouldbe obliged to push along the coast towards Holland and would leavethe whole of Belgium uncovered (telegram No. 126 DIPP from paris).M. Leger had thought that there would be no objection toadding a paragraph to the above effect, but Sir Ronald Campbellhad pointed out that it would weaken our case as set out in the communication, which was based on our confident assumption that,in the event of an attack on Holland, the Belgian Government would go to her assistance and would welcome the arrival of Allied forces.
M. Leger had at once agreed and had said that it would bebetter that the communication in the sense suggested by general gamelin should be made by him through the Military channels to theBelgian Military authorities, at the same time as the Govern-mental communication was made.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The Balkans. 7.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that his visit to London conversations with His Majesty&apos;s Representatives in the Balkanof His Majesty&apos;s countries had now concluded, and the representatives would shortlyRepresentatives, return to their posts. A record of the meetings and of the con-(Previous elusions reached would be circulated to the War Cabinet shortly.Reference: He was also preparing a Press Communique regarding theW.M. (40) 79th  conversations.   The communique itself could not be published untilConclusions,      the agreement of the French Government had been obtained, but he Minute 7.)        would arrange to let the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairshave a copy in the meantime.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Flying Boats.Diversion ofcivil flying boatsfor militaryduties.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 68thConclusions,Minute 3.)8. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Air (W.P. (G.) (40) 105).The Secretary of State for Air said that there were two newfeatures since the War Cabinet had discussed this matter on the14th March. The first was that, on account of operations in scandinavia, there was a much greater demand on the military flying boats available to the Royal Air Force for long-rangereconnaissance work, only 34 Sunderland aircraft being availablefor this service. During recent months 14 Service flying boats hadbeen lost, three or four of which had been lost during the past two weeks. It was clear that, with the development of operations in Norway, the demand for the services of flying boats for deep seareconnaissance would increase and not diminish.In the second place, a month ago it had seemed likely that thethree &quot; G &quot; boats would be ready for the operation of a civil flyingservice that autumn. It was now clear that the &quot; G &quot; boats wouldnot be ready for a passenger-carrying service that year. He had,therefore, come to the conclusion that it was necessary to divert thethree &quot; G &quot; boats for use by the Royal Air Force, with instructions that they were to be adapted for service use as speedily as possible.Owing to the period which would be occupied by trials, &amp;e, beforethe flying boats could be used for a passenger service, the boatscould be made available for Service use at an earlier date thanthey could be used for civil purposes. He, therefore, proposed thatthe Cabot and Caribou should continue in service with the RoyalAir Force, and that the three &quot; G &quot; boats should now be adapted for military purposes on the understanding that the modificationsmade would be such that they could be quickly re-adapted for civiluse if it should become possible to restore any or all of these boatsto civil employment.In reply to the Prime Minister, the Postmaster-General statedthat the British Trans-Atlantic Air Service was designed to create an Empire link between the United Kingdom, Eire, newfoundland and Canada, and that he understood that the French Governmentwere also anxious to see the establishment of a British service.The Secretary of State for the Dominions felt that, while therewould undoubtedly be disappointment in Canada if the initiation of the service this year were abandoned, it seemed clear that therewas no other course open to the War Cabinet but to accept theproposal of the Secretary of State for Air.
It was generally agreed that, in view of the new featuresmentioned by the Secretary of State for Air, the acceptance of thisproposal was a disagi&apos;eeable necessity.The War Cabinet-(i) Agreed that the Cabot and Caribou should continue in service with the Royal Air Force.(ii) Agreed that the three boats of the &quot; G &quot; type should nowbe made available for service with the Royal Air Force,with the necessary adaptations, on the understandingthat they could be re-adapted for civil use at short notice, in case any or all of them could be restored to civil employment.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,April 16, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
