<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 222-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CC (66)19th Conclusions36CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Wednesday, 20th April, 1966,at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Denis Healey,Secretary of State for Defencem p,The Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Rfght Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the following were also present:The Right Hon. George Thomson,m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster (Items 1-3)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. John Diamond, mp,Chief Secretary, Treasury (Items 3-5)Mr. Albert E. Oram, mp, Parliamen-tary Secretary, Ministry of overseas development (Item 3)Secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. rogers miss J. J. nunn mr. J. H. LockeTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1966Copy No.
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Parliament     .....................       32     Oversea Affairs      ..................       3Rhodesia3     Public Expenditure..................       3Control of Government Expenditure Overseas4     Parliament     .....................       6Select Committees5     Legislative Programme 1966-67   ............       9Companies Billi
SECRET 3CC 19 (66)Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.OverseaAffairsRhodesia(previous reference:CC(66) 18thConclusions,Minute 2)2. The Prime Minister said that a group of the ministers primarily concerned had discussed the Rhodesia situation earlier inthe week, at a meeting attended by the United Kingdom special representative in Central and East Africa (Mr. Malcolm MacDonald)and our Ambassador in South Africa. Our immediate concern wasto restrain the South African Government from permitting oil supplies to reach Rhodesia via South Africa on a greater scale than was current before the illegal declaration of independence, since wecould not hope for South African co-operation in a complete boycott.In Rhodesia itself it appeared that our economic sanctions might beproving more effective than had been the recent public impressionand there were some signs of dissension among the members of the rhodesia Front Party, but undue expectations should not be builton these indications. \\The Cabinet Took note of the statement by the Prime Minister.PublicExpenditureControl ofGovernmentExpenditureOverseas(previous reference:CC (66) 2ndConclusions,Minute 4 and cc (66) 3rdConclusions,Minute 7)3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C (66) 60) on the control of government expenditure overseas.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, partly because ofsome non-recurring expenditure by the oil companies and the effects of the Rhodesian situation, it was now unlikely that we should achieveour declared aim of bringing our oversea accounts into balance bythe end of 1966. In this situation a rigorous scrutiny was necessaryof all oversea expenditure by the Government. Over the past decadesuch expenditure had risen from about  200 million to well over 500 million. By far the greatest increase lay in the net military expenditure overseas; this was due less to an increase in grossexpenditure than to a reduction in United States and Canadianmilitary expenditure in the United Kingdom and the ending ofUnited States direct defence aid, but it had also been affected by the unsatisfactory agreements made with the Federal GermanGovernment by the previous Administration in respect of the cost ofmaintaining our forces in Germany. Expenditure on overseas aidhad also risen very substantially, as part of a deliberate policy.Expenditure on administrative and diplomatic activities overseas had risen from  25 million to  80 million over this period. Theappearance of the total figure for 1966 given in Table 1 of his paper was unduly favourable because &quot; long-term capital&quot; included theloan from the United States to pay for United States military aircraft:but this was of course counterbalanced by the provision that would
be necessary for repayment in later years. In this situation it was notonly essential to take specific steps to secure a reduction in the levelof Government oversea expenditure but also to refer to the government&apos;s intention in this respect in the course of his statement on the Budget. A thorough review should be carried out by officialsover the next few months of the possibilities of a reduction in all the items of oversea expenditure, leading up to a discussion by thePublic Expenditure Committee and then by the Cabinet in theautumn of 1966. Such a review should not start from the assumptionthat existing policies and practices must be maintained unaltered.Action should also now be started to implement the decisionannounced in the Statement on the Defence Estimates 1966: theDefence Review (Cmd. 2901) that our maintenance of forces inGermany was conditional on ways being found of meeting the foreign exchange costs involved. The present arrangements with the federal german Government covered less than half the foreign exchange cost of about  90 million a year. We should now open negotiationswith that Government for the payment by them of a budgetarycontribution of  50 million a year: in doing so we should make clearour wish to maintain forces in Germany and that our action arosesolely from our difficulties in respect of foreign exchange. We shouldalso begin detailed work on the implications of moving our forcesback to the United Kingdom and should allow it to become known that such a study was being undertaken. Reference should be madeto such an approach to the Federal German Government in his budget Speech where it could be set in the context of our economic position.In discussion there was general agreement on the need forspecial scrutiny of the Governmenfs programmes of expenditureinvolving oversea payments. Anxiety was, however, expressed thatsuch a review might reopen the decision recently taken by the Cabineton the level of expenditure on the Overseas Aid Programme overthe next five years: officials should not be asked to review the policieson which Ministers had already reached agreement. It might therefore be better to set a target for the reduction in overseaexpenditure and instruct officials to suggest alternative ways of achieving it, leaving Ministers to decide whether any changes in policy were justified by the need to economise in such expenditure.Particular attention should be paid to the possibility of reducing thenet cost to the balance of payments, for example, by a revisionrather than a reduction of the Overseas Aid Programme in orderinter alia to increase our tied aid. On the other hand, it was argued that to set at the outset a target for the reduction for total overseaexpenditure might prejudge the outcome of the review, since thedesirability of a reduction of any particular order could only bedecided in the light of its implications for our oversea policy and interests.There was general agreement that negotiations should be startedwith the Federal German Government for an increased offset to ourcosts in foreign exchange of maintaining forces in Germany butconsiderable doubt was expressed whether the procedure proposed
would be most likely to achieve our aims without grave damage toour other interests.In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) Calculations of net military expenditure made by the north atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) took account of receipts from private sales of arms overseas and of the costs of maintaining UnitedStates and Canadian forces in the United Kingdom, with the resultthat our net military expenditure overseas was calculated at littlemore than half the figure included in C (66) 60. It would thereforebe preferable to seek to negotiate directly with the Federal GermanGovernment on this matter rather than rely solely on multilateraldiscussion in NATO.(b) In considering the effects of bringing our forces back from europe to the United Kingdom full account must be taken of the implications for our economy and in particular of the burden onavailable land and on the construction industry which would be involved.(c) It would be unrealistic to expect that the Federal GermanGovernment would in practice be prepared to make a directcontribution of this order to the costs of maintaining our forces inGermany.(d) Any suggestion that we were seriously considering thewithdrawal of our forces on the Continent would gravely embarrassour discussions with the other members of NATO on the implications of the decision of the French Government to withdraw from NATOand would need careful consideration in the light of the government&apos;s policy in relation to other European issues.(e) There would be advantage in setting a date in our negotiationsafter which we would not be prepared to continue foreign exchange,expenditure on the present scale in connection with our forces inGermany since otherwise the negotiations might be interminable.(/) In considering our other oversea defence commitments, wemust maintain the timetable for their reduction which had beenagreed in the Defence Review, and must avoid any substantial new commitments, if our oversea expenditure were not to increase stillfurther.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that therewas general agreement that there should be a detailed andwide-ranging review of Government expenditure overseas, by officials in the first instance and subsequently by Ministers. Theterms of reference should be further considered in the light of thediscussion by the Chancellor of the Exchequer in consultation withthe Ministers concerned, including the Foreign Secretary and theMinister for Overseas Development when they returned to thiscountry from overseas. The terms of any statement about this review which the Chancellor of the Exchequer desired to include inhis Budget Statement should also be agreed with the Ministers
concerned. The Defence and Oversea Policy Committee should consider the implications of the Chancellor of the Exchequersproposals in respect of German support costs, on the basis of a reportfrom the Official Committee. No public reference should be madeat this stage to any studies which were carried out on the implications of bringing our forces back to the United Kingdom.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a review of Government expenditure overseasshould be carried out during 1966.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to give furtherconsideration in the light of the discussion to the termsof reference for this review, and to the terms of any public reference to it, in consultation with the Foreign Secretary,the Secretary of State for Defence, the commonwealth secretary, the Colonial Secretary, the President of theBoard of Trade and the Minister for overseas development.(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for theCommittee on Defence and Oversea Policy to give furtherconsideration in the light of the discussion to the mannerin which negotiations should be conducted with the federal german Government on the cost in foreign exchange ofour forces in Germany.4. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Lord Presidentof the Council (C (66) 59) to which was attached a copy of amemorandum which he had circulated to the Ministerial Committeeon Parliamentary Procedure about the wider use of select committees.The Lord President said that the Ministerial Committee under his chairmanship had considered a proposal put forward by thePrime Minister that, as an experiment, Select Committees composedof back-bench Members should be set up to investigate matters within the purview of particular Departments, such as the HomeOffice or the Department of Education and Science, with the objectboth of providing interesting work for back-bench Members and of implementing proposals which the Labour Party had put forwardwhen in Opposition for enabling Parliament more effectively to scrutinise the work of Departments. The Ministerial Committee werein general in favour of a greater use of Parliamentary committees,which they thought might take one of three forms: a Committee to inquire into such matters relating to the work of a particular department as might be referred to them by the House; a Committeeto inquire into matters referred to them, but not confined to aparticular Department; or ad hoc Committees to inquire intospecified topics. They considered, however, that, before anannouncement was made on the form which the experiment shouldtake, it would be desirable that they should examine the constitutionalParliamentSelectCommittees
and practical problems involved, since they foresaw that the greater use of Committees would stimulate a probably irresistible movement towards a series of specialist Committees somewhat on the lines ofthe Congressional Committees in the United States&apos; system ofgovernment, including Committees on foreign affairs and defence.The problems which they thought it desirable to consider included thepossible change in the relationship of Ministers to Parliament if aCommittee system were added to the existing arrangements forsecuring the responsibility of Ministers to Parliament; the additionalburdens that would be thrown on Ministers and the question whetherthey should be given compensating relief by other proceduralchanges; the possibility that Committees would develop into pressuregroups for increased expenditure by particular Departments; thequestion whether an informal procedure which enabled a Minister todiscuss problems frankly with a Committee might not be preferable to the formal examination of witnesses whose evidence was subsequently published; and the desirability of arranging forCommittees to be served by a secretary drawn from the department concerned in addition to a Clerk of the House, and possibly by outside experts. There was no doubt that the appointment of newCommittees would create further demands on the Parliamentarytimetable, since their reports would have to be debated at the expenseof the already limited time available for Government legislation. the ministerial Committee suggested, in the light of these considerations,that in the Debate on the Address the Prime Minister should refer in general terms to the Governments desire to find means ofenhancing the influence of Parliament on the formation of policy, but should, if possible, avoid putting forward at this stage any specificproposal. If, however, some such proposal were required, it might take the form of the appointment, experimentally, of a Committee toconsider a particular topic, for example the law on abortion. Itwould be desirable to mention at the same time the reform of theprocedure of the House of Commons in order to reduce the pressure to which both Ministers and Private Members were at present subject.The Prime Minister said that it was essential that in the new parliament the Government should take the initiative in promoting the modernisation of both procedure and machinery. For thispurpose the appointment of ad hoc Committees would not besufficient, and he preferred an experiment with Committees appointedto examine the affairs of particular Departments. The SelectCommittee on Procedure might later be asked to consider whetherexperimental Committees on these lines had proved their value. he doubted whether Committees would in practice become involved inparty controversy, or whether it would prove impossible to resist pressure to extend the system into the fields of foreign affairs and defence. There might well be advantage in devising an informalprocedure for the new type of Committee, and possibly in placinga Minister in the chair. It seemed undesirable, however, thatCommittees should make use of outside experts except as witnesses.At the same time as introducing experimental Committees, it would
be desirable to consider further reform of the procedure of the Houseof Commons in order to avoid the waste and misuse of parliamentary time, for example by eliminating all-night sittings and by carryinguncompleted Bills over from one Session to another.In discussion the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for education and Science said that they would have no objection to theappointment of Committees specialising in the affairs of their departments. Such a Committee could provide a useful forum forthe explanation of a Ministers policy and help to create informedopinion. In relation to the Home Office, it would be desirable toensure that the Committee did not embark on controversial and difficult subjects, such as immigration, but, equally, it should not be confined to topics suitable for Private Members&apos; legislation; it mighthave been useful, for example, to refer to such a Committee theproblems dealt with in the White Paper published in the previousParliament on The Child, The Family and The Young Offender.Possibly periodical discussion between the Minister concerned andthe Committee might be a more effective way of directing their workinto useful channels than an attempt to prescribe particular topics forconsideration.In further discussion there was general agreement that it wouldbe desirable to make greater use of Committees of backbenchers. Itwas suggested that the objectives both of occupying Members and ofgiving Parliament a means of supervising Departments could be served by the Estimates Committee if the selection both of its members and of the topics for its consideration were improved. Butthe general view was that it would be desirable to experiment with new forms of Committee which might either be appointed to inquire into matters concerning particular Departments, or into such matters as might be referred to them by the House from time to time. Itwas suggested that backbench Members were unlikely to be content to consider topics which were neither controversial nor central tothe problems of government; the new Committees would certainly be concerned with policy and it was not clear how in the long runthey could be excluded from the consideration of foreign affairs and defence. While the consideration of controversial topics was notnecessarily to be deplored, however, there was reason to hope that new Committees, like the Select Committee on the nationalised industries, would be able to deal with subjects in themselvescontroversial in a manner which would nevertheless result inconstructive reports. It might be possible to establish thatCommittees could not recommend increased expenditure. Theireffectiveness could be improved by providing Members with betterresearch facilities.It was further suggested that the Select Committee on Procedure,which had shown itself to be more interested in providing work forbackbench Members than in modernising the procedures ofParliament, was not the best body to consider either the success ofexperimental Committees or radical reforms of procedure in other
legislative programme,1966-67CompaniesBill ,(previous reference:CC (66) 18thConclusions,Minute 4)5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the President ofthe Board of Trade (C (66) 61) on the Companies Bill.The President of the Board of Trade recalled that at their meeting on 7th April the Cabinet had excluded the Companies Billfrom the programme of legislation for the 1966-67 Session. It hadbeen suggested in discussion that this Bill was no longer urgent andit had been criticised for implementing the more conservativeproposals of a generally conservative report: the general preferencehad been for introducing a much more ambitious Bill relating to companies in the succeeding Session.respects, and that both these matters should be considered by theGovernment through the Ministerial Committee on parliamentary procedure. It should be borne in mind that whatever was done inthe House of Commons would have implications for the House ofLords.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that an experiment in the use of Committees of backbench Members of theHouse of Commons might be attempted. He would ventilate a project of this kind during the Debate on the Address and would consider the terms of his speech in consultation with the lord president and with Ministers whose Departments would be affectedby any illustrations which he might give of the scope of the proposedCommittees. The question of devising an informal procedure forthe Committees and other practical points arising from an experimentshould be considered urgently by the Ministerial Committee on parliamentary Procedure, which should also examine in due courseits results. The means of modernising the procedure of the Houseof Commons and of facilitating the discharge of parliamentary business should also be considered by the Ministerial Committeeand subsequently discussed with the Leaders of the opposition parties. It would be preferable not to remit these problems to theSelect Committee on Procedure.The Cabinet (1) Took note that the Prime Minister would consider, inconsultation with the Lord President and other ministers concerned, the terms in which it would be announced,during the Debate on the Address, that the Governmenthad it in mind to initiate an experiment in the wider useof Committees of backbench Members of the House ofCommons.(2) Invited the Lord President of the Council to arrange for the ministerial Committee on Parliamentary Procedure toconsider the procedure which might be adopted by theproposed new Committees and other practical problems arising from the experiment; to examine the results ofthe experiment in due course; and to consider means ofmodernising the procedure of the House of Commons andof facilitating the discharge of its business.
Without the Companies Bill, however, the legislative programme for the first Session could be criticised as containing little whichcontributed to the aim of making industry more efficient. Nor wasthe criticism that the Bill was conservative well founded, since its provisions for the greater disclosure of information by companieswent substantially beyond the proposals in the Report of theCompany Law Committee under the chairmanship of Lord Jenkins(the Jenkins Report); in particular by abolishing all the exemptionshitherto accorded to private companies it was much more radicalthan that Report. Since the Bill had first been published, furtherprovisions of considerable importance had been added. It was certainly desirable to consider wider issues such as the proper placeof the company in the modern economy and whether there werelessons to be learned from recent developments in other countries,but this would inevitably be a lengthy process and could not becompleted in time to enable a wider Companies Bill to be introduced the following Session. Unless the present Bill were taken in thecurrent Session, there would be no legislation on the more urgentissues relating to companies for some three years; it would, therefore,be desirable to introduce the Bill in the first Session as soon as theBill on Industrial Development, relating to investment grants, hadbeen completed. Meanwhile, the consideration of a Bill oncompanies going wider than the Jenkins Report should continue.The Prime Minister said that discussion of the important issues raised by the President of the Board of Trade could not be completed in the time available for Cabinet discussion that morning. A further meeting should therefore be held early on the following day to enable a decision to be taken before the Debate on the Address.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion on the following dayCabinet Office, S.W.1,20th April, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
