<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 238-250</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1966CC (66) Copy No.    3 721st conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.I, on Thursday, 28th April, 1966,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p. Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations (Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, m p,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, m p,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, Secretary of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, m p,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, m p,Minister of power the following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,m p, Minister of Health (Item 4)Mr. Austen Albu, m p, Minister ofState, &apos; Department of economic affairs (Items 3 and 4)The Right Hon. Margaret Herbison,mp, Minister of Pensions and national Insurance (Item 3)The Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. rogers miss J. J. nunn mr. R. T. Armstrong
contents subject parliament     ............Rhodesia        ............Social Services        .........Ministry of Social Security BillPrices and Incomes PolicyDoctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remuneration
CONFIDENTIAL3Rhodesia(previous reference:CC(66) 19thConclusions,Minute 2)CONFIDENTIAL*2. The Prime Minister said that early in the previous week a message had been received from the Governor of Rhodesia thatMr. Smith, the leader of the illegal regime, wished to hold talks withthe United Kingdom Government. At that time his private secretary, Mr. Wright, was on his way to South Africa to assist our ambassador in representations which he was making to the SouthAfrican Government regarding oil sanctions against Rhodesia.Mr. Wright had been instructed to leave the aircraft at Salisbury for discussions with the Governor before going on to Pretoria. As aresult of his report on his talks with the Governor, he was instructedto return to Salisbury on Friday, 22nd April, and the Governor had then arranged a meeting between Mr. Wright, Mr. Hennings,Her Majesty&apos;s Governmenfs Representative in Salisbury, andMr. Smith. A further talk had been held leading to agreedarrangements for informal talks: these were directed only to seeing whether a basis for negotiations genuinely existed. The talks wouldbe without commitment on either side and in view of the obviousneed to avoid their being prejudiced by publicity, the utmost secrecymust be observed regarding their course.It appeared that our sanctions were having a greater effect in rhodesia than public opinion had recently been inclined to supposeand there had been some increase in unemployment amongEuropeans and some emigration by them to South Africa. the outcome of our action in stopping further tankers going to Beirawith oil for Rhodesia had clearly been a severe shock to the illegal regime, which had also been influenced by the unwillingness of theSouth African and Portuguese Governments to give them full support in evading our economic and financial sanctions. There was some evidence of a split amongst the members of the regime and itappeared that they now realised that they could not be successful inobtaining a tacit acceptance of the illegal declaration of independenceby sufficient countries to enable the country to maintain its economic progress. The most extreme members of the regime might,however, be prepared to accept a much lower standard of economic prosperity as a condition of maintaining their independence and itwas possible that they might seek to oust Mr. Smith and his lessextreme colleagues. On the other hand the imposition of sanctionshad rallied the general body of Europeans, including the moderateswho had opposed the illegal declaration of independence, in supportof Mr. Smith. No doubt in consequence of this position Mr. Smithwas unwilling to agree that it should be publicly known that theinitiative for these talks came from him.   We had in consequenceCONFIDENTIALParliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
accepted that the public announcement of the talks should not revealthis point, though no doubt it would be known in due course: andit was important to our interests that Mr. Smith should not now berepudiated by popular opinion amongst the Europeans. If, however,he were later ousted by the most extreme members of the regime,the situation which would then arise might allow us greater latitudeof action.It would be imprudent at this stage to count on a successful outcome of the talks, which must of course be based on the firmmaintenance of the six principles which the United KingdomGovernment had laid down as a condition of a settlement in Rhodesia.It was therefore all the more important that our sanctions should becontinued, and wherever possible strengthened, in the expectation that they would produce steadily increasing pressure on the illegal regime to accept our conditions.In discussion, concern was expressed that in the absence of any public statement that the initiative for the talks came from Mr. Smith,there would be widespread misunderstanding, both in the UnitedKingdom itself and particularly amongst African countries, that theUnited Kingdom Government had changed their policy. From thispoint of view it would be preferable to let it be known that theinitiative had been taken by Mr. Smith. It would also be desirableto make it clear that the visit to Salisbury the previous month ofMr. Duncan Watson of the Commonwealth Relations Office hadbeen concerned with the position of the Governor and of her majesty&apos;s .Government&apos;s Representative in Rhodesia and thatMr. Watson had only been authorised to be the recipient of any approach from Mr. Smith and not to hold talks with him. Therewas, moreover, some danger that the informal talks which had nowbeen agreed might imperceptibly develop into formal negotiations with would, contrary to the Governments policy, involve a recognition of the illegal regime. It was, however, the general viewthat despite these admitted dangers, this new development was to be welcomed and represented a success for the policy the Governmenthad pursued. In continuing the informal talks, it would be impracticable to declare publicly at every stage the governments position on all points in a manner which would avoidmisunderstanding by African countries: it was the eventual outcomewhich mattered and the maintenance of the necessary secrecy wouldbe justified by success, though meanwhile it was clearly of the utmost importance that all practicable steps should be taken to avoidmisunderstandings. Arrangements had already been made for commonwealth Governments to be informed of the position; and particular importance attached to the discussions which would beheld with President Kaunda of Zambia by the United KingdomSpecial Commissioner in Central and East Africa (Mr. Malcolm Macdonald) on his return from the United Kingdom in the courseof the next few days. Consideration was also being given to thepossibility of the Commonwealth Secretary visiting some of the mostimportant African capitals for discussions with leading Africanfigures.
Social ServicesMinistry of social SecurityBill(previous reference:CC(65) 70thConclusions,Minute 2)secret. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C (66) 66) and the Minister of Pensions and national Insurance (C (66) 65) on the timing of the introduction ofthe Ministry of Social Security Bill, the level of benefits to be paid under it, and the announcement that the new rates of benefit wouldbe financed partly by limiting the increase in national insurance benefits due to take place in 1967.Tfie Chancellor of the Exchequer said that under the timetable for the Bill as at present intended ats introduction would coincide with the Budget.   It would. be embarrassing, however, to have toThe handling of the day-to-day tactics in the forthcoming talkswould necessarily be the responsibility of the Ministers mostimmediately concerned; but any issues of principle would be a matter for discussion in the Cabinet itself. The United KingdomGovernment would, of course, maintain the six principles which theyhad laid down for accepting a settlement in Rhodesia; and there could be no recognition of the illegal regime or of the independencewhich it claimed. In considering the implications of the six principlesit was suggested that it should be borne in mind that these had been laid down before the illegal declaration of independence and thatthe present situation might enable the Government to ensure greaterparticipation by Africans in the Government of Rhodesia. It was recognised, however, that the dissension between Mr. Nkomo andthe Reverend Sithole, the leaders of the rival African parties, would inevitably complicate the question of such participation.It was also recognised that, while sanctions were imposing asteadily increasing pressure on the illegal regime, a number of themost extreme members of that regime would nevertheless beprepared to accept this rather than surrender their independence.Regard must also be had to the unwelcome strain which sanctionsimposed on the United Kingdom economy and particularly on our balance of payments and to the continuing risk of major damage toour position which would be caused if copper supplies from Zambiawere cut off or heavily curtailed.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theMinisters immediately concerned would be responsible for the tactical handling of the forthcoming talks but issues of principle would, as necessary, be considered by the Cabinet. In the course ofthese talks there might be from time to time public misunderstandingsof the position of the United Kingdom Government; but the riskof these must be accepted and would be more than justified by a successful outcome. Meanwhile, that success must not be prejudiced by premature disclosures.The Cabinet Took note with approval, of the Prime Ministers statement.
take account in the Budget of the additional expenditure of 26 million in the current year arising from the Bill, and it wastherefore important that it should not be introduced until about theend of May. If its introduction were postponed the other problemsdiscussed in the memoranda before the Cabinet could be left forfurther inter-Ministerial discussion.The Lord President said that the proposed timetable was basedon the necessity to secure Royal Assent before the Summer Recess.The publication of the Bill could be deferred until 4th May if theOpposition were prepared to agree to the curtailment of the timetable for consideration in Standing Committee, but further postponement would necessitate confining the Whitsun Recess to one week and taking the Committee Stage of the Bill on the floor of the Houseimmediately after Parliament reassembled.The Minister of Pensions and National Insurance said that itwas proposed to bring the new benefits into operation during thelast week in November. An interval of 16 weeks was requiredafter Royal Assent to allow for the reassessment of some 2 millionexisting beneficiaries and the issue to them of order books bearing the new rates, and for the initial assessment of the persons who, itwas hoped, would for the first time accept benefit under the new scheme. The programme had been very carefully considered andthere did not seem to be any way of reducing the period requiredfor this work.In discussion it was agreed that it was essential that the new rates should be paid in November, but it was suggested that it wouldnot be improper for the administrative processes to be put in handin anticipation of the passage of the Bill once it had received a third Reading in the House of Commons. It would be possible forthe Bill to be introduced immediately before Whitsun, to receiveThird Reading in the House of Commons before the summer recess, and to pass through the House of Lords in the autumn intime to receive Royal Assent by the third week in November. Itmight be feasible, if it seemed desirable on grounds of propriety, fororders bearing the new rates of benefit to be issued as the old bookscame up for renewal, but in separate books from those covering theperiod up to the change in the benefit. It would not be right to spendpublic money before Royal Assent on advertisements designed to attract new beneficiaries, but it should not be impossible to obtainenough publicity for the scheme through, for example, newspaperand television interviews to ensure that those concerned were made aware that they should come forward. Considerations should begiven by the appropriate officers of the Ministry of Pensions and national Insurance and of the Treasury to means of reducing therisk of criticism by the Public Accounts Committee. political criticism could to some extent be disarmed if the Minister of Pensionsand National Insurance announced on Third Reading in the Houseof Commons that, in order to avoid delay in bringing the benefitsapproved by the House into payment, the necessary administrative work would be carried on during the Recess.
CC 21 (66)The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were agreed on the importance both of bringing the newbenefits into payment by the end of November and of avoiding thepublication of the Ministry of Social Security Bill at a time when itwould be embarrassing to the Chancellor of the Exchequer. Theydid not in principle, however, see impropriety in the necessary administrative work being undertaken as soon as the Bill had beenapproved by the House of Commons, provided that no money was paid out in pursuance of the Bill before Royal Assent, either tobeneficiaries or in advertising the new scheme. Urgent consideration should therefore be given by the Accounting Officers of the Ministryof Pensions and National Insurance and of the Treasury to thepossibility of proceeding with the administrative arrangements assoon as the Bill had received Third Reading in the House ofCommons, which could be secured before the Summer Recess, andto any steps which might be necessary to avoid constitutionalimpropriety. It might be necessary, for example, to obtain a specialresolution of the House of Commons. The outcome of this furtherconsideration should be reported to the Cabinet in the following week.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the introduction of the Ministry of social security Bill should be postponed so as not to coincide with that of the Budget.(2) Invited the Minister of Pensions and National Insurance, inconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, toarrange for the urgent consideration by officials of thepossibility of undertaking, during the interval betweenthe Third Reading of the Bill in the House of commons and the receipt of Royal Assent, the administrative worknecessary to bring the new scheme into operation in thelast week in November and to report to the Cabinet inthe following week on any special steps which were considered necessary.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to consider further,in consultation with the Minister of Pensions and national Insurance, the questions concerning the level of benefits under the Bill and the statement on cost raised in C (66) 66.139SECRETPrices and 4.   The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Secretary of incomes Policy State for Scotland and the Minister of Health (C (66) 62) and by the doctors&apos; tincl \ \Dentists&apos; First Secretary of State and Secretary of State for Economic AffairsRemuneration and the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C (66) 64) on the remuneration(Previous    , of doctors and dentists in the National Health Service.^xsfcrcnccs *CCA65) 16th The Minister of Health raid that the Review Body on Doctors&apos;Conclusions and and Dentists&apos; Remuneration had made recommendations to theCC(65) 62nd Prime Minister on the remuneration of doctors and dentists in theConclusions,Minute 4) SECRET
National Health Service for the two years beginning 1st April, 1966.The total cost of the increases recommended was estimated at about 35 million, of which about  24 million was accounted for by increases to general medical practitioners. The Review Body had emphasised the difficulties of adopting comparability as a basis for settling doctors&apos; and dentists&apos; remuneration but had paid considerable attention to the losses of doctors from the junior ranks of thehospital service and from general practice, and to the increase inthe workload, particularly of general practitioners.The recommendations on hospital medical staff and on general dental practitioners could be regarded as broadly acceptable. Therecommendations for general medical practitioners, however, involved an increase of some 25 per cent in the estimated collective net income,plus additional payments for aspects of general practice not previously recognised which would raise the average increase in net income to over 30 per cent.He recognised the difficulty of accepting these recommendations for general medical practitioners in the present economic situation,both because of the implications for incomes policy and because ofthe cost. In his view, however, there were conclusive reasons foraccepting the recommendations in full. They came as the climax ofa period of 12 months&apos; unrest among general practitioners, beginning with the fierce protests at the Review Body&apos;s Fifth Report, the presentation of the Charter for the Family Doctor Service and the sending in of undated notices of resignation, still in existence, fromover 80 per cent of family doctors. In that situation the Cabinet had decided that no more money could be paid to the doctors before thecompletion of the Review Body&apos;s general review early in 1966. the profession had with difficulty been persuaded to limit the scope of direct negotiations with the Government to methods of payment andconditions of service, and to leave levels of payment for considerationby the Review Body. It had only been possible to achieve this byconstant reference to the independent position of the Review body and the weight which any Government must attach to their views.In a letter dated 16th March, 1965, the terms of which had beenagreed by the Cabinet, he had told the profession that he could not accept new levels of remuneration except on the recommendationof the Review Body. Against this background any tampering withthe Review Body&apos;s recommendations would be regarded by the profession as a breach of faith; it was likely to unite them in opposition to the Government, in circumstances where public sympathy would be on the side of the doctors rather than on the side of the Government. At least there would be a grave deterioration of relations between the Government and the profession, which had lately shown signs of beginning to improve. Any modification ofthe recommendations carried with it the risk that the great majorityof family doctors would leave the National Health Service; thegreater the modification, the greater the risk, while a modificationinsignificant enough not to carry too great a risk of mass resignationwould be unlikely to achieve a worthwhile saving of cost or reductionof embarrassment. Doctors who resigned from the National Health
CC 21.(66)   14QService would mostly be able to carry on, sometimes perhaps earningmore than under the National Health Service, by means of private practice and privately organised insurance schemes which had been developed to an advanced state of readiness. The consequences of mass resignation would be very serious:(i) The Exchequer would immediately be liable to repaydoctors&apos; superannuation contributions and to pay compensation for loss of goodwill to doctors whoresigned; these payments could cost from  60 million to 100 million.(ii) It would cost the Exchequer at least as much as the review body&apos;s recommendations, and probably more, to bringthe doctors back into the National Health Service once they had gone out.(hi) In the meantime the Government would find themselvesforced into reimbursing doctors&apos; fees for privatetreatment and costs of drugs for less well-off patients,without having any control over the levels of feescharged.(iv) It would be difficult, if not impossible, to revive general practice in the National Health Service.Unless the Government were prepared to face the prospect of destroying the National Health Service, the Review Body&apos;srecommendations should be accepted in full.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the First Secretaryof State and he did not wish to press that the Government shouldmodify the details of the Review Body&apos;s recommendations; but to implement forthwith a pay increase of some 30 per cent for general medical practitioners would destroy the Governments chance of persuading trade unionists to believe that the Government were serious in their pursuit of an incomes policy and in their statementsabout the economic consequences of large increases in remunerationthis year; nor could the high cost to the Exchequer of implementing the recommendations be ignored. The First Secretary and he therefore proposed that the recommendations should be accepted asthey stood but that the increased payments to medical practitionersshould be implemented in two stages, the first from 1st April, 1966,and the second from 1st April, 1967. He believed that in present economic circumstances public opinion would consider that this represented fair and generous treatment of the doctors, who wouldforfeit their claim to public sympathy if, in these circumstances, theywere so undisciplined as to take the extreme action of resigning fromthe National Health Service.In discussion it was pointed out that the Cabinet were being asked to take a decision on this question without having reviewed and agreed their general policy on the machinery for dealing withthe remuneration of public servants whose pay had hitherto been
determined by independent review at infrequent intervals. It wasurgent that this should be done, but meanwhile to override therecommendations of the Review Body would call in question thewhole position of other such bodies and of normal arbitrationmachinery in relation to incomes policy. It had to be rememberedthat there was a degree of retrospective adjustment involved in therecommendations. The Review Body had made it clear that theyhad heard evidence from the Department of Economic Affairs onthe bearing of incomes policy, and had stated that their recommendations were in their view consistent with the principles ofthe policy. Whatever the argument for appealing for moderationin the growth of higher incomes, it was difficult to justify a decision not to accept the Review Body&apos;s recommendations after havingaccepted both those of the Franks Committee on Higher CivilService pay and the increases for the Armed Forces, especially inview of the potential consequences to the National Health Service.On the other hand it was argued that acceptance in full wouldhave most serious consequences for the Governmenfs attempts toestablish the principles of incomes policy in the trade union field, andin particular on some of the negotiations now in progress. It wouldcertainly lead the university teachers to demand the appointment ofa review body to deal with their remuneration, and it would makethe schoolteachers more militant in pursuing the large claims theywere preparing.In further discussion the following points were made:(a) If a decision were taken to adopt the proposal of the first secretary of State and the Chancellor of the Exchequer, it might bedesirable for the Prime Minister to summon the representatives ofthe doctors to explain the Governmenfs position and seek theirunderstanding. On the other hand this might not be advantageous,since the decision would in practice be taken not by the leaders ofthe profession but by a ballot of doctors and by large representativemeetings which would not be amenable to influence of this kind.(b) It was suggested that a possible course might be to refer the review Body&apos;s report to the National Board for Prices and Incomes.This would be consistent with what had been done in the case ofthe Franks Report on Higher Civil Service Pay. This might, however,provoke no less serious consequences than the course proposed bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer, unless the Government were to commit themselves in advance (as they had done in no other case) toaccept the findings of the Board. This course would in effect takethe decision out of the hands of the Government; and in any event it would be mistaken to send the report to the Board unless theGovernment were prepared to implement the Review Body&apos;srecommendations if the Board approved them.(c) If the Government were to phase the implementation of thereport in the manner proposed by the First Secretary of State andthe Chancellor of the Exchequer, it would be inappropriate at the
CC (21) 66same time to canvass with the profession the possibility of changing the Review Body&apos;s terms of reference in order to associate them more closely with incomes policy. It would, however, be desirable in any public announcement to emphasise that the Review Body hadtaken consideration of incomes policy into account in formulatingtheir recommendations.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that on balance the view of the Cabinet was that the Government should accept the recommendations of the Review Body on levels of pay for doctors and dentists in the National Health Service but shouldimplement the increased payments to medical practitioners in two stages, one-half from 1st April, 1966, and the other half from 1st April, 1967. It should be emphasised that the Government wereaccepting the Review Body&apos;s figures for general medical practitioners(as well as for hospital medical staff and general dental practitioners)but considered that, in the light of overriding economic considerations,the increases for medical practitioners should be paid in two stages.While he would himself convey the Governmenfs decision toLord Kindersley (the Chairman of the Review Body), the Ministerof Health, in consultation with the First Secretary of State, theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of State for Scotland,should consider further the precise way in which this depision shouldbe implemented, and the timing and presentation of a public announcement, including the question whether it would be desirable for him also to see representatives of the doctors before anannouncement was made. The First Secretary of State should alsoprepare for consideration by the Cabinet proposals on the future status and functions of independent review bodies in relation to the government&apos;s policy on prices and incomes.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the recommendations of the Review Body onthe remuneration of doctors and dentists should beaccepted, save that the increases for general medical practitioners should be implemented in two stages, halffrom 1st April, 1966, and the other half from 1st April,1967.(2) Invited the Minister of Health, in consultation with theFirst Secretary of State, the Chancellor of the Exchequerand the Secretary of State for Scotland, to consider further the way in which this decision on phasing the; increases for general medical practitioners should be implemented,the future handling of the situation as a result of thedecision, and the timing and presentation of a public announcement.(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would convey the government&apos;s decision to the Chairman of the review body before any public announcement was made.
(4) Invited the First Secretary of State to prepare forconsideration by the Cabinet proposals on the future status and functions of independent review bodies inrelation to the Governmenfs policy on prices and incomes.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,28th April, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
