<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 294-304</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTYHER BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1966CC(66) r      Tvr       3727th Conclusions Copy Na     * cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.I, on Thursday, 9th June, 1966,at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic Affairs (items-3)The Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord Chancellor (Items 1-3)The Right Hon. Michael Stewart,mp, Secretary of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of Trade(Items 1-3)The Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of Transport (Items 1-3)The Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the Council (items-3)The Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Overseas Develop-ment the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the following were also present:The Right Hon. Frederick Mulley,mp, Minister of Aviation (Items 1and 2)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,m p, Attorney-General (Items 1-3)The Right Hon. John Diamond, m p,Chief Secretary, Treasury (Items 1and 2)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . W. A. nield mr. D. S. Laskey7141-1a
contents item                                     Subject page 1     Disclosure of Official Information     .........       32     Space Policy............      .........       european Launcher Development organisation     Industrial Disputes ...............       6Seamen&apos;s Strike4     Oversea Affairs      ..................       8IndonesiaNorth Atlantic Treaty Organisation
Disclosure ofOfficialInformation(previous reference:CC(66) 18thConclusions,Minute 1)CC 27 (66)confidential. The Prime Minister said that there had been a number ofrecent leakages of information to the Press. The report in The times of Friday, 3rd June, on the Governments decision about theEuropean Launcher Development Organisation (ELDO) had been particularly damaging on the eve of the North Atlantic treaty organisation and ELDO Conferences. There had also beenmisleading reports about the Governments intentions in regard tothe prices and incomes policy, which had probably had an adverse effect on sterling; and premature disclosure of the report by theCourt of Inquiry on the Shipping Industry had enabled the militantelements in the National Union of Seamen to bring pressure to bearon the union&apos;s Executive. There was an established procedure for investigating leakages of information; and the Cabinet might nowthink it right that, where necessary, it should include Ministers. Butinvestigation in retrospect was no substitute for discretion in contacts with representatives of the Press; and, although legitimate Pressguidance and briefing by Ministers should of course continue it remained incumbent on all individuals who enjoyed access toconfidential information to take particular care to safeguard it frompremature or improper disclosure.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministets statement.Space PolicyEuropeanLauncherDevelopmentOrganisation(previous reference:CC (66) 26thConclusions,Minute 5)secret. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Aviation (C (66) 75), to which was attached an annex bythe Attorney-General, about the Governments decision to terminateour financial commitment to the European Launcher development organisation (ELDO).The Minister of Aviation said that since the Cabinet had taken this decision it had become clear that its legal implications might bemore serious than we had supposed. In particular, it couldapparently be argued that, largely as a result of the views which theUnited Kingdom delegate had expressed during the negotiations with had preceded the original establishment of ELDO, we were under an obligation to share in the total cost of the initial programmeuntil it was completed and that we had no freedom of action to terminate our financial commitment by unilateral decision. If our decision to withdraw were challenged on these grounds and thischallenge were sustained in international legal proceedings, weshould have to be prepared to meet expenditure considerably greaterthan the sum of  15-5 million which the Cabinet had earlier beengiven to understand would represent the maximum cost of withdrawal.The extent of our further liability could not be estimated withprecision. At the minimum, it would be the sum representing ourpercentage contribution in respect of the uncommitted part of the initial programme, i.e., an additional  14-7 million, making a total7141-1a 2
liability of  30-2 million; but, if the other member States were unable to continue the initial programme without us andconsequential damages were also awarded against us on this account,we might have to pay not only a proportionate share of the cancellation charges but also some part of the expenses which theother States had already incurred in respect of the programme. Thealternative to accepting these risks was to maintain our participation in the ELDO-A programme and to accept its modification by theaddition of the new PAS programme. The latter was an additional programme, in respect of which no country had so far accepted any financial commitment. Its cost was estimated by the Ministry of aviation at  67-5 million; and, if we could persuade our Europeanpartners to reduce our contribution to 25 per cent from 1st January,1967, the amount which we should have to pay towards the cost of completing the intial ELDO-A programme and undertaking theadditional PAS programme would be about  42 million. This sumhad to be compared with the revised estimate of the expenditure which we might incur if we maintained our unilateral decision (towithdraw from the Organisation; and, since it might well proveless than the total cost of withdrawal as this must now be estimatedon the basis of the latest legal advice, it was for consideration whetherthe earlier decision should be maintained. In reassessing the relativeadvantages and disadvantages of the two courses, the Cabinet would wish to bear in mind the political difficulty of defending a decision towithdraw from the Organisation in order to save over a period of six years a sum which, it now appeared, could not exceed  12 million at the maximum.In discussion it was suggested that contacts with our otherpartners since the Cabinefs decision had been made known had indicated that their attitude to that decision would be even morecritical than we had originally expected. It was clear that, if were fused to continue to participate in the Organisation, we shouldrisk inflicting grave damage on our prospects of securing european co-operation in other technological projects to which we attached importance and that, in addition, we should provoke the suspicion that we were no longer in earnest in our professed desire to promoteEuropean collaboration in the widest sense. There were good reasons for supposing that our partners would consent to a reductionin our contribution to ELDO if we continued to participate in its programmes; and it would therefore be to our advantage, on balance,to take the initiative in indicating that we were prepared to remainin the Organisation on this basis, an initiative which we could take with less political embarrassment since the commitment which apparently prevented us from leaving the Organisation by unilateraldecision had been inherited from the Conservative Administration.On the other hand, the view was expressed that the ELDOenterprise had no justification in terms of economic or technologicalreturn on the investment involved and that, in the light of the continuing strain on our balance of payments, we should be illadvised to accept a continuing commitment of any size in respectof ELDO  projects.    Without  actually withdrawing from  the
7141-1Organisation, therefore, we should at least make it clear that wewould not be prepared henceforward to pay more than a minimalcontribution to its work. Indeed, it could be argued that we should press this argument to its logical conclusion, especially since thecharge of vacillation to which the Government would be exposedif they now reversed their decision to withdraw from the organisation would be so damaging that it would be preferable to maintain thatdecision without regard to the consequences. The risks to our otherco-operative European enterprises should not be exaggerated; our partners in Europe would judge each case on its merits in the lightof their own interests and we should be guided by the sameconsideration in deciding our attitude towards ELDO. For these reasons it might still be preferable to maintain our earlier decision and to withdraw from the Organisation completely.In further discussion it was suggested that it might be possibleto transfer to our partners the onus of taking the effective decision about the future of ELDO by offering to discharge our legalcommitment to contribute to the balance of the cost of the ELDO-a programme but refusing to participate at all in the subsequent PASprogramme. Since it was generally agreed that the ELDO-a programme itself would be of no economic value unless it wasmodified by the addition of the PAS programme, our partners might decide that in these circumstances they should abandon the PASprogramme and terminate the ELDO-A programme as rapidly aspossible. In that event we might hope to extricate ourselves fromthe dilemma at little greater cost than the original estimate of 15-5 million. Alternatively, however, if it were judged that thepolitical reasons in favour of our continuing to participate in ELDOprojects were overriding, we should not only insist upon a significant reduction in our proportionate contribution but should also attach to it an absolute money ceiling, which might well be approximately the same figure as the  42-5 million which was estimated to be thecost of our contribution to the ELDO-A and PAS programmes on thebasis of a reduction in our contribution to 25 per cent from 1st January, 1967. A provision of this kind would constitute anadditional safeguard against an escalation of costs beyond the presentestimate of  67-5 million for the PAS programme. It would alsobe salutary to stipulate that the ELDO programmes should be thesubject of an annual review and that the Organisation^ convention should be so modified as to enable member States to withdraw at these periodical &quot; break points &quot; if they saw fit to do so.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that the issues remained very finely balanced. But the preponderant view ofthe Cabinet was that the Minister of Aviation, in opening thediscussion at the meeting of the ELDO Council in Paris that afternoon, should re-emphasise the reasons for our reluctance toparticipate further in the Organisation but might indicate, inconclusion, that he would be prepared to recommend the UnitedKingdom Government to reconsider their position if our partnerswere willing to negotiate the further stages of the ELDO-A enterprise,
including the PAS system, on terms which we might find lessintolerable. We should continue to maintain, however, that the PASsystem constituted a new programme, which would have to be negotiated separately from the ELDO-A programme; and we shouldmake it clear that the conditions on which we would be prepared toconsider renewing negotiations for the completion of the ELDO-a programme and the addition of the PAS programme would have toinclude:(i) An early and substantial reduction in our future contributionto a figure which would not exceed 25 per cent and should, ifpossible, be less.(ii) In addition to (i) an absolute money limit, of say  40 million,on our contribution so calculated.(iii) An arrangement whereby the ELDO programme wouldhenceforward be reviewed annually and would incorporate suitablebreak points which would safeguard member States against anyautomatic commitment to escalating costs.Of these conditions (iii) was perhaps not one on which we should wish to break in the last analysis. But (i) and (ii) were essential andwould need to be so expressed that we could take advantage ofwhichever of them proved the more favourable in the light of actual expenditure.In making this offer, the Minister should avoid making any reference to our misgivings about the legal liabilities which we mightincur if we adhered to our intention to terminate our ELDOcommitment unilaterally. He should also refrain from accepting any definite commitment at this stage and should confine himself toindicating that he would be willing to advise the United KingdomGovernment to consider resuming negotiations if our partners were willing to do so on a basis which would satisfy our conditions.The Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Aviation to be guided by the PrimeMinisters summing up of their discussion at the resumedmeeting  of the  Council  of the  European  launcher development Organisation in Paris later that day.IndustrialDisputesSeamen&apos;s Strike(previous reference:CC(66) 26thConclusions,Minute 3)secret. The Minister of Labour said that the National Union of seamen (McManus) had resolved to reject the interim Report of theCourt of Inquiry on the ground that their claim must be met in fullwithout compromise. The owners had reluctantly agreed to acceptthe Report. The Acting General Secretary of the Trades UnionCongress (TUC), Mr. Feather, had called a meeting of the finance and General Purposes Committee for that afternoon which theExecutive Committee of the McManus would attend. The TUC were likely to press the McManus to accept the Courfs recommendations as areasonable offer.   If, however, the Union were adamant, the full
General Council of the TUC would be called for the followingTuesday, again with the Executive of the McManus available fordiscussion. But it would be premature to base optimistic expectationson these discussions in view of the extent to which the militant factionin the McManus appeared to be in control of the union&apos;s policy.The Prime Minister said that by rejecting the Courfs report and appearing to challenge the community, the McManus were now in danger of gradually forfeiting public support. It was doubtfulwhether the membership of the Union had much enthusiasm for thestrike, particularly since the coastal trade seamen had now beenliving for over three weeks on  3 a week strike pay, as againstnormal earnings of about  20 a week. On the other hand, therewas still considerable militancy, due to the past frustrations of theUnion; and it was not easy to assess what would be the effect of theReport on the strike.In discussion the following points were made :. (a) Although the strike was reaching the stage when other unionsmight be involved, the TUC had no powers to regulate the decisionsof individual unions. They had only the right to intervene bypersuasion where a dispute seemed likely or had broken out.(b) The General Secretary of the McManus had made it clear to theMinister of Labour that it would be of no avail to seek to reconvenethe Annual Conference of the Union, although the Minister wouldgive this possibility further consideration if the intervention of the tuc proved unsuccessful.(c) The recommendations of the Court of Inquiry would resultin an award which would be only marginally above the norm underthe prices and incomes policy, which need not now, therefore, become an issue in the strike.In further discussion it was suggested that the recommendationsof the Report could be regarded as being in fact less favourable tothe seamen than the owners&apos; last offer. In particular, the Report had recommended against the increase of 12s. 6d. per month in efficiencypay offered by the owners. It was not easy to see how the Unioncould be expected to resume work on such a basis, especially sinceUnited Kingdom seamen were less well paid than those of other european nations. It should not be assumed, therefore, that other unions would not support the McManus, especially when the likelyresponse from the International Transport Workers&apos; Federation tothe McManus appeal became apparent. On the other hand, it was pointedout that, while the proposals in the Report were slightly less favourable than those of the owners in respect of the first year, thosein respect of the second year were more favourable. Moreover, theReporfs proposals would take effect in two years instead of three;it recommended a rather higher number of days of paid leave than was contained in the owners&apos; last offer; and it conceded theprinciples of the 40-hour week and of week-end overtime pay forwhich the strike had been called.
On these grounds it could be argued that it was incumbent onthe Government, having set up an impartial Court of Inquiry and received from it a Report embodying fair and reasonablerecommendations, to accept the Report and to ask for the strike tobe terminated on the basis of the Reports findings. Such adeclaration of the Governments attitude should be made at once.It would not prejudice the efforts of the TUC; indeed, it mightinhibit their attempt to resolve the dispute if the Government didnot declare their support for the Report publicly and promptly. If,despite the continued efforts of the Government and the TUC, theUnion did not accept the Reports findings but sought to extend andto intensify the strike, it would be clear that they were determined to challenge the Governments policies and it would be theGovernments duty to take any actions necessary to maintain thepublic services and to limit the damage to the economy.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that it wasthe view of the Cabinet that a statement should be issued that afternoon on behalf of the Government calling on both parties to thedispute to accept the proposals of the Court of Inquiry; and hewould make the necessary arrangements for this purpose. In themeantime the Ministerial Committee on Emergencies should continueto limit emergency action by the Government to cases of clearnecessity, pending further efforts to bring the strike to a conclusion,and should seek to avoid any measures which could be regarded asprovocative.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministets summing up of their discussion.Overseas AffairsIndonesia(previous reference:CC(66) 24thConclusions,Minute 2)secret. The Foreign Secretary said that on his way to Canberra forthe meeting of the South-East Asia Treaty Organisation he wouldbe passing through Bangkok and had hoped to have a meeting therewith Mr. Adam Malik, Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Ministerof Indonesia. Mr. Malik could not however leave Indonesia andthe question therefore was whether he should visit Djakarta on his way back from Canberra for a meeting with Mr. Malik. In the new situation now prevailing in Indonesia the balance of advantageseemed in favour of such a visit, subject to three conditions; thatthere was no recrudescence of hostilities between Indonesia and malaysia; that the Indonesian Government had not failed to ratify the agreement with Malaysia reached at Bangkok; and, that the visit would not damage Mr. Malik&apos;s position in Indonesia, of which mr. Malik himself would be the best judge.The Commonwealth Secretary said that in his view it would be unwise for the Foreign Secretary to commit himself to a visit toDjakarta before Indonesian confrontation against Malaysia was over;this might strengthen President Sukarno&apos;s position in opposing the
North AtlanticTreatyOrganisation(previous reference:CC(66) 24thConclusions,Minute 2)The Foreign Secretary said that at the meeting of the north atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) in Brussels decisions had beenreached about the relocation in the Benelux countries or in germany of the military headquarters which were under notice to leave France.The French Government had not asked that the North atlantic council should leave and the French Foreign Minister had indicated that they would be glad if the Council remained in Paris but wouldnot oppose a move. If the Council stayed in Paris it would bedivorced from all immediate sources of military advice. Nevertheless,some members of the Fourteen, particularly Denmark and Canada,were hesitant about a move for fear of offending the French. Astatement had been agreed stressing the importance of close co-operation between the political and military authorities in NATO,agreeing on a study of alternative sites for the Council, deferring afinal decision pending discussions with the French Government on other matters and calling for a meeting of Ministers in October. it seemed likely that the French would be very uncompromising in thediscussion on other matters and the final decision would probablybe in favour of the North Atlantic Council leaving Paris.On the position of the French forces in Germany, the FrenchGovernment had proposed that apart from bilateral discussions withthe German Government about the status of their forces other issuesshould be discussed only between their military authorities and thoseof NATO. This was not acceptable to the Fourteen Powers sincethe role of the French forces and arrangements for their co-operationwith NATO both in peace and in an emergency were essentiallyend of confrontation. Moreover, if there were a setback in thenegotiations between Malaysia and Indonesia the Malaysians wouldbe inclined to blame this on the Foreign Secretary&apos;s visit to Djakarta.The Secretary of State for Defence said that he thought the risks involved in the visit were worth taking. He would like to consult the Foreign Secretary about the possibility of a military adviseraccompanying him to Djakarta since this might afford an opportunityfor direct discussions with the Indonesian military authorities.Summing up the discussion the Prime Minister said that thegeneral view of the Cabinet was in favour of the Foreign Secretary&apos;proposal that he should visit Djakarta, subject to the three conditionshe had mentioned.The Cabinet (1) Agreed with the Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposal that he should visit Djakarta, subject to the conditions he had mentioned.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary and the Secretary of State for defence to consider whether a military adviser should accompany the Foreign Secretary.
political matters. The French had finally agreed that these issuesshould be discussed in the North Atlantic Council but their attitude in such discussions was likely to be very obstructive. The bilateraltalks on the status of the forces would begin on 13th June; theirprogress would depend on progress in the political discussions andno agreement was likely to have been reached by 1st July when theFrench forces would be withdrawn from NATO. The status of theFrench forces in Germany would thereafter be covered by someprovisional arrangement.If matters developed in this way the French people might begin to have doubts about the implications of General de Gaulle&apos;s policy.We wished to keep France in the Alliance, but it was doubtfulwhether the French attitude would be reasonable on the issues whichmust be resolved and their declaration that they wished to remainan ally of their allies might prove to have little substance. our essential objective was that NATO should remain efficient andworkable, with France if possible, but without her if necessary.Relations with Eastern Europe had also been discussed and aconsiderable range of opinion was apparent amongst the Fourteenon the possibility of making progress. It had been agreed that each country should endeavour to improve relations in such minor but still significant fields as travel, trade, cultural relations, etc. On thecentral issues, such as German reunification, it was recognised thata united approach was essential and there was some fear thatGeneral de Gaulle, during his visit to Moscow, might try to makebilateral arrangements with the Soviet Union, although these wouldin practice remain without effect so long as other NATO countries were not associated with them. Proposals for improving East /west relations, including the possibility of a European conference, wouldbe further discussed in the North Atlantic Council. The french foreign Minister had stated that no new or spectacular developmentwas to be expected from General de gaulle&apos;s visit to Moscow, butthere was no indication of General de Gaulle&apos;s real intentions asregards the visit.The Cabinet (3) Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,9th June, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
