<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 311-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1966CC (66) Copy No.   3 129th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 16th June, 1966,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, Secretary of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p. Minister of Overseas Develop-ment the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Frank Cousins, m p,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, m p,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey,Secretary of State for Defencem p,m p,The Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, m p.Minister of power the following were also present:Mr. Roy Mason, m p, Minister of State,Board of Trade (Item 3)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,mp, Attorney-General (Item 3)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. W. A. Nield
contents subject parliamentary BusinessOversea Affairs     ......IndonesiaSouth ArabiaSeychellesNigeriaIndustrial DisputesSeamen&apos;s Strike
CC (29) 66CONFIDENTIALParliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Oversea AffairsIndonesia(previous reference:CC(66) 27thConclusions,Minute 4)secret. The Foreign Secretary said that there was reason to behopeful that the recent discussions between representatives of theMalaysian and Indonesian Governments at Bangkok would leadto an end of confrontation, but the outcome was still uncertain.Meanwhile, there had been military clashes in Sarawak in whichAustralian troops had been involved and there was as yet no evidence that the Indonesians were withdrawing their forces fromthe frontier areas or giving up military activity. President Sukarnowas also still opposed to the ending of confrontation. There had,however, been large public demonstrations in Indonesia in favourof the Bangkok Agreement.His own projected visit to Djakarta would, of course, have tobe cancelled if there were to be further military incidents in Borneoindicating the continuation of confrontation, but it was hopeful that,when the possibility of the visit had been mentioned to Mr. Malik,the Indonesian Foreign Minister, the latter had immediately made it known that the Foreign Secretary would be visiting Indonesia at mr. Malik&apos;s invitation.The Commonwealth Secretary said that there had been certaininternal political disputes in Malaysia which might be exploited byIndonesia if there were not a real desire on the part of the latter to end confrontation.South Arabia(previous reference:CC(66) 26thConclusions,Minute 6)The Foreign Secretary said that increased financial aid had been offered to Federal Ministers amounting to capital aid of  5-5 million and additional recurrent aid of  2-5 million a year, on theunderstanding that their own contribution to the total cost of theFederal security forces would not fall below the present figure of 2-2 million. We were also prepared, in principle, to increase thisaid somewhat if the States of the Eastern Aden Protectorate wereto enter the Federation. Although the Federal Ministers would still have liked a defence agreement with the United Kingdom, they appeared to be reasonably satisfied with the offer of aid which hadbeen made.Seychelles The Secretary of State for Defence said that in response to therequest of the Colonial Government for assistance in dealing withdisorder arising from a strike, one of Her Majesty&apos;s frigates had landed 50 seamen and these might be reinforced by a further 100marines later that week.Nigeria The Commonwealth Secretary said that there was strong opposition in the North to the recent constitutional proposals for a
unitary government put forward by the Military Government of nigeria; there was in consequence the possibility of disorder andriots which would threaten the position of that Government.The Cabinet-Took note of these statements.IndustrialDisputesSeamen&apos;s Strike(previous reference:CC(66) 28thConclusions,Minute 1)secret. The Prime Minister said that since the Cabinet had last discussed the seamen&apos;s strike he and the Minister of Labour had held discussions with the Finance and General Purposes Committeeof the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and subsequently with the negotiating committee of the National Union of Seamen (McManus).Later, they had seen representatives of the shipowners. The NUSnow appeared to be less concerned with their demand for animmediate move to a 40-hour week than with the retention oftheir existing leave rights in respect of Sunday working. They alsoappeared to be convinced that productivity could be so increased as to enable overtime to be reduced without any loss of output.The shipowners had felt unable to offer any compromise with theunion; but they had offered a concession whereby seamen would beentitled to take an additional day&apos;s leave in respect of each eight hours overtime worked instead of receiving overtime pay. This offer,which represented only an extension to the seamen of an agreementalready in force in respect of the Merchant Navy officers, wouldinvolve no additional cost and would not, therefore, involve any departure from the principles of the settlement recommended by the interim Report of the Court of Inquiry under Lord Pearson.In the light of these exchanges with the union and the employersit remained important that the Government should not themselvessuggest any concessions which would make a settlement more expensive than the proposals in the Interim Report. nevertheless it might not be inconsistent with this objective to suggest that leaveentitlement in respect of Sunday working might be restored ratherlater in the year in so far as the Court of Inquiry found, in the second stage of their investigation, that compensating economy could, andwould, be secured by the implementation of additional measures toincrease productivity, whether by a reduction in overtime, aredefinition of existing demarcations of function or otherwise. But,even if it proved possible to resolve the present dispute on some such lines as these, it was apparent that there was a need for a more radical and searching examination of the structure and organisationof the shipping industry; and there might be advantage in promoting a review of this kind as soon as the Court of Inquiry had completed its work.In discussion some concern was expressed that any initiativetowards a settlement of the kind suggested by the Prime minister might convey the impression that concessions of substance, involving a further increase of wage costs beyond those recommended by theCourt of Inquiry, would be acceptable to the Government, with all
CC (29) 66the damage to the Governments policy on prices and incomes whichwould certainly ensue. Moreover, the proposals in the InterimReport of the Court of Inquiry could only be reconciled with theprices and incomes policy if overtime were reduced by two hours a week within the next 12 months, as the Court had recommended;and this increase in productivity, which had still to be achieved,must not be allowed to rank as the justification for any further improvement in the terms of a settlement such as would berepresented by the reinstatement of some measure of Sunday leaveentitlement. Any new concession of this kind would need to bejustified by the implementation of measures to secure an additionalincrease in productivity. Doubts were also expressed whether,despite the views put forward by the McManus, an actual reduction inovertime worked would be popular with the seamen themselves,since, given the conditions of life at sea where leisure facilities werenecessarily limited, they might well prefer in many cases to workadditional overtime and so to increase their earnings for the voyage.In further discussion, it was the general view that, while it was important that any initiative on the part of the Government shouldbe made only in response to an indication on the part of the NUSthat they were now seeking a settlement of the strike, it would nevertheless be neither unreasonable on merits nor inconsistent withthe Governments policy on prices and incomes if it were to be made clear that the Government accepted that the McManus might reserve their right to propose an increase in leave entitlement beyond that proposed in the Interim Report of the Court of Inquiry, providedthat any such increase was no more than was justified by an increasein productivity, which would need to be additional to the reductionof two hours overtime already contemplated by the Interim Report.In further discussion the following additional points were made:(a) It might be helpful if the Court of Inquiry consulted theassociation of Merchant Navy Officers in addition to the shipownersand the McManus.\\(b) It would be necessary for the Proclamation of Emergencyto be renewed by the following Wednesday if the strike had not been settled by then. Regulations under the Proclamation would have tobe approved by both Houses of Parliament within a period of seven days thereafter; and this might entail a full day&apos;s parliamentary debate.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were concerned that any settlement of the dispute shouldnot involve an increase in wage costs going beyond that implicit inthe proposals of the Interim Report of the Court of Inquiry. they agreed, however, that, provided that the Government took no new initiative save in response to an indication by the McManus that theyno longer sought to insist on the complete acceptance of their terms,it might be proposed that, in addition to the concession of additionalleave in lieu of payment for overtime which had been suggested bythe shipowners on the previous evening, consideration should be
given later in the year, after the further report of the Court of inquiry on productivity, to an increase in the leave entitlementenvisaged by the Interim Report to the extent that this was justified by any increase in productivity actually achieved over and abovethe reduction of two hours overtime contemplated in the InterimReport. The Cabinet also agreed that, after the Court of Inquiryhad completed their work, there might be an advantage in promoting a searching investigation into the structure of the shipping industry,comparable with the recent enquiries into the aircraft and vship-building industries. Together with the Minister of Labour he wouldpursue further discussions with those concerned in the dispute in thelight of these conclusions.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office, SWA,16th June, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
