<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 392-395</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CC (66)37th conclusions this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  September 1966Copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 19th July, 1966,at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, Secretary of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth relations the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the   Right   Hon.ofThe   earl longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Overseas Develop-ment the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,mp, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,mp, Minister of health the Right Hon. Frederick Mulley,mp, Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Prentice,mp, Minister of Public Building and works the Right Hon. Margaret Herbison,m p, Minister of Pensions and national insurance the Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Postmaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. W. A. nield mr. D. S. laskey mr. R. T. Armstrong7159-2
subject the Economic Situation
secret the EconomicSituation(previous reference:CC (66) 36thConclusions,Minute 3)The Cabinet had before them Notes by the Secretary of theCabinet (C (66) 106, 107, 108, 109, 110, 111, 112, 113, 114 and 115)on the economic situation.The Cabinets discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately in the bound volume of Most Confidential Recordheld by the Secretary of the Cabinet.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,20th July, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
