<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 514-528</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. January 1967CC (66) Copy No.   3648th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W1, on Thursday, 29th September, 1966.at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p. ! The Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs j    First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Herbert Bowden,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth Affairs (Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,mp, Attorney-General (Items 1-3)The Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Niall MacDermot, qc, mp,Financial Secretary, Treasury (items-5)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend . W. A. nield mr. D. S. laskey mr. K. barnes mr. R. T. Armstrong7443
ContentsItemSubjectPage1Oversea AffairsNigeriaFalkland Islands32Rhodesia33Prices and Incomes Policy ...part IV of the Prices and Incomes Act4     Docks   ...............     ...     ...     ...     10Employment and pay     Iron and Steel Nationalisation............     13Salaries of Members of the Corporation
&apos; ,  2943OverseaAffairsNigeria(previous reference:CC(66) 41stConclusions,Minute 3)FalklandIslandsSECRET1. The Prime Minister said that the situation in Nigeria was serious. There seemed little prospect of further progress in theconstitutional conference; there were threats of secession by theEastern Region and a risk of pre-emptive action by the centralauthorities. We would be ready to give any help we could, throughthe provision of our good offices, to reach a settlement; the need for urgent action to evacuate British subjects in Nigeria could not be excluded.The Colonial Secretary said that 18 armed men had forced anArgentine civil airliner, on which there was also a number of innocentpassengers, to land in the Falkland Islands. The situation had beenbrought under control by the guard of six Royal Marines stationed inthe Falklands, backed by the local home guard, and the armed menwere confined near the aircraft. It was intended to return the innocentpassengers to the Argentine on a British merchant vessel which wouldbe calling at the Falkland Islands on 3rd October; it was not howeverconsidered safe or practical to send back the armed men on this small vessel. A British warship could reach the Falkland Islandsfrom Simonstown in about 11 days and the armed men could bereturned to the Argentine on this. Further incidents of this sortmight well occur and it might be advisable to increase the size of thegarrison on the islands.The Foreign Secretary said that the Argentine Government haddeplored the incident and expressed their intention of institutingproceedings against the armed men. He would explore with theColonial Secretary and the Secretary of State for Defence thepossibility of inviting the Argentine Government to send one of their ships to take off the armed party if this could be done withoutprejudice to our claim to sovereignty over the islands. There was every advantage in seeking a quick and amicable settlement since this might assist our longer term objective of resolving the dispute with the Argentine over the islands.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.SECRETRhodesia(previous reference:CC(66) 46thConclusions,Minute 1)2. The Commonwealth Secretary said, that during his visit to salisbury he had had five meetings with Mr. Smith. The first meetingat Government House on the morning of 20th September, at whichhe and Mr. Smith had been accompanied only by their Secretaries,had been concerned mainly with modalities. He had suggested thatthe Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; communique might be taken7443
as the basis for discussion, but Mr. Smith had said that he was notinterested in the Commonwealth and had referred to the recentupheavals in the Commonwealth countries to the north, such asGhana. At the second meeting in the afternoon, at which the attorney-General was present, Mr. Smith had brought with himMr. Lardner Burke. Mr. Smith had made it clear that he was notprepared to discuss the question of a return to constitutional rule until he knew what the constitutional arrangements would be for the grantof independence. He had suggested that there might be differentconstitutional approaches or even a new constitution, but Mr. smith had claimed that this would be a waste of time and that they should work on the basis of the 1961 Constitution. Mr. Smith had rejectedout of hand a number of other suggestions, for instance a group of commonwealth constitutional experts or a mission of commonwealth prime Ministers. He had ruled out the possibility of an Act of Unionbetween the United Kingdom and Rhodesia or the presence of asmall British military force in Rhodesia. He had claimed that a royal Commission on racial discrimination would be unnecessary and that there was no need to review the Land Apportionment Act.There had been some discussion of electoral arrangements andMr. Smith had been prepared to contemplate some extension of the african franchise. He was not however ready to accept effectiveentrenchment of the essential provisions in the Constitution and it was clear that he was insisting on the Rhodesian Government retaining a&quot; braking mechanism &quot;, through the creation of new constituencieswhich would be won by Europeans, in order to prevent the achievement by Africans of majority rule if, in the opinion of the rhodesian Government, this would be premature.The third meeting on the morning of 21st September had beenheld at Mr. Smith&apos;s insistence in the Police Mess Hall. There hadbeen some discussion about the return to constitutional rule andMr. Smith had argued that this could be done in 24 hours and thatthere would be no need for any interim government. Mr. Smith hadclaimed that the present Rhodesian Government and Parliament hadbeen legally elected under the 1961 Constitution and that there wasno need for any radical change; if the Africans were prepared toco-operate in working the 1961 Constitution there was a good prospect that they would achieve majority rule after two or threegeneral elections. He had pointed out to Mr. Smith that a return to constitutional rule on this basis would be totally unacceptable to theUnited Kingdom Government.Mr. Smith had suggested the creation of a Senate, composed of12 European and 12 African members, and of arrangements wherebyconstitutional changes would require a 75 per cent majority in a combined vote of the Senate and House of Representatives. In theorythis would give the African members a blocking minority, but inpractice this would not be so since six of the African membersof the Senate, according to Mr. Smith&apos;s proposal, would berepresentatives of the Chiefs who were dependent on and paid bythe Rhodesian Government.
At the end of the meeting he had given Mr. Smith the UnitedKingdom&apos;s statement of the points of agreement and disagreement.In the afternoon, when he and Mr. Smith had met alone, the latter had adopted a somewhat less rigid line but had made no concreteconcessions. He had proclaimed his anxiety for a settlement but had said that he should not be pressed too hard.During the next four days, while Mr. Smith was attending the rhodesia Front Conference, he and the Attorney-General had hadmeetings with some 96 people representing a wide cross-section ofRhodesian opinion. Representatives of Rhodesian business hadadmitted that sanctions were having an effect, but claimed that therewas much evasion. Some of them had said that, if mandatorysanctions were imposed, they would give full backing to the illegal regime. African trade unionists had not protested against the policyof sanctions, but had complained that their effect, particularly asregards unemployment, was being felt more severely by the Africansthan by the Europeans. He had tried to establish what the reactionwould be to the declaration of a republic; as far as the RhodesianArmed Forces were concerned it seemed likely that a few officers would resign but that there would be no serious move by the forces against the regime; some of the judges would probably also continueto work with the regime.His last meeting with Mr. Smith had been on the evening of26th September when Mr. Smith had presented the Rhodesianstatement of their position. This envisaged five stages: agreement on constitutional arrangements; a Royal Commission to ascertain the acceptability of these arrangements to Rhodesian opinion; a generalelection; the return to constitutional rule; the grant of independence.Throughout all these stages it was clear that the existing government,with Mr. Smith as Prime Minister, would remain in power. He had made it clear that this was wholly unacceptable and that the returnto constitutional rule must come first. Other matters would also require settlement, such as the release of the African leaders nowdetained or restricted and the removal of censorship.The impression he had formed was that Mr. Smith was nowseriously concerned about the situation but that he was still in thehands of his extremists, however much he might personally wish torid himself of them. But he now knew the United Kingdom&apos;s requirements and the gravity of rejecting them. The door had notbeen closed and there was still a chance that Mr. Smith might lead the country back to legality. He alone had the authority to do so,although the extremist minority in the Rhodesia Front might refuseto follow and thus split the party. Even if a settlement were achievedthe outlook was not encouraging. Any settlement could only work with African co-operation; and the African parties, ZAPU andZANU, were still obstinately divided. African co-operation might,however, be forthcoming if the African parties could see the prospectof achieving majority rule within a definite number of years. Of the
European community some 30 per cent might be opposed to the regime; but the moderates were weak and irresolute. Owing to the regime&apos;s propaganda and censorship most of the Europeans wereunaware of the United Kingdom Governments position and stillbelieved that we were insisting on majority rule immediately after independence.He proposed that there should now be a further study by theCommonwealth Office of some of the ideas which had been putforward with a view to drawing up a statement of our minimum requirements within the terms of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos;communique. This should be considered by the Ministers principally concerned and then by the Cabinet and should be made known in rhodesia before the anniversary of the illegal declaration of independence on 11th November. It would also be necessary to take all possible steps to ensure that Rhodesian opinion was fully informed of the United Kingdom Governments position.In discussion there was general agreement with theCommonwealth Secretary&apos;s proposal that a new statement of theUnited Kingdom Governments position should now be prepared.This would set out our minimum requirements for a settlement andwould draw attention to the rejection by the illegal regime of thealternative proposals which the Commonwealth Secretary had discussed with them. The statement should make it clear that themain difference between the United Kingdom Government and the illegal regime was one of principle and did not turn on no more thanthe detail of some individual constitutional provision; experience had shown that constitutions could be easily and quickly changedafter independence and that no measure of entrenchment couldprevent this. It was therefore essential that our position should beseen to be based squarely on the six principles, particularly the first,which required unimpeded progress to majority rule, and the fifth,which stipulated that the final settlement must be shown to be acceptable to the people of Rhodesia as a whole. Rather thandefinitely accepting or rejecting our offer, the illegal regime might seek to prevaricate as in the past. We should, however, be operatingwithin the timetable laid down in the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos;communique; Mr. Smith could not delay matters beyond the end ofNovember and, if the terms had not been accepted by then, thefurther measures contemplated in the communique would follow. Ifthe offer met with outright rejection before then, w should be free to consider the adoption of further measures before the deadline of30th November.There was also general agreement on the need to ensure that public opinion in Rhodesia was more fully informed of the UnitedKingdom Governments position. We faced the choice of continuing to work for a negotiated settlement, although the chance ofMr. Smith&apos;s accepting our terms seemed very small, or of preparingnow for a final breakdown of our attempts to reach agreement withthe illegal regime. If we adopted the second hypothesis, we shouldlot only seek to convince public opinion in Rhodesia that our terms
were reasonable but should also try to impress on them all the possible consequences of rejection. But we should need to exercise great care in mounting any propaganda operation of this kind. In particular the use of any threats might only unite European opinion more firmlybehind Mr. Smith; and in any case we should not threaten anything which we were not prepared to perform. Moreover, the effect ofsuch a campaign must be considered in relation not only to Rhodesiabut also to other neighbouring countries and to opinion in the UnitedKingdom itself. The position of the South African Government wasnot yet clear; but the possibility that they might still influenceMr. Smith to accept a reasonable settlement should not be excluded.It was important, therefore, that we should continue to work withinthe terms of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; communique; andthe consequences of failure to reach a satisfactory settlement were so serious that we should not at this stage abandon hope of persuading the illegal regime to accept our offer before the deadline of30th November.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that therewas general agreement that further study should be undertaken onthe lines indicated by the Commonwealth Secretary, who should alsoconsult other Ministers, as appropriate, on the best means of makingknown to public opinion in Rhodesia both the true nature and extentof our proposals and the possible consequences if they were finallyrejected by the illegal regime. The results would be considered bythe Ministers principally concerned and thereafter by Cabinet. Thesituation in Zambia also required urgent consideration since coal supplies from Rhodesia were not being maintained owing to shortageof wagons on the Rhodesia railways. This might result in an earlyreduction of copper production in Zambia. Interdepartmentalconsideration should be given to this problem as a matter of urgency;and the possibility of increasing supplies by providing railways wagonsfrom the United Kingdom or by means of an airlift should be examined.The Cabinet-Invited the Commonwealth Secretary:(i) to arrange for the preparation of a statement of the UnitedKingdom Governmenfs position on the lines agreed intheir discussion;(ii) to  arrange,  in  consultation  with  other  Ministers  as appropriate, for an examination of the best means ofmaking known to public opinion in Rhodesia both the true nature and extent of our proposals and the possible consequences if they were finally rejected by the illegal regime;(iii) to arrange for interdepartmental consideration, as a matterof urgency, of the supply situation in Zambia.
8CONFIDENTIALCONFIDENTIAL3. The Cabinet considered a note by the First Secretary ofState and Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (C (66) 137), towhich was attached a note on the various courses open to theGovernment if the Association of Supervisory Staffs, Executives andTechnicians (ASSET) were successful in their court case againstThorn Electrical Industries Limited.The First Secretary of State said that the court actions pendingwere described in his note. In addition, the National Society ofPottery Workers were threatening legal action, and the national joint Council for the Electrical Contracting Industry were seekinglegal opinion on the implications of deferment of pay increases whichwould shortly become due, since both sides of the Council were concerned at the possibility that individuals might take legal action ifthe increases were deferred. 200 employees would be directly affectedby the result of the Thorn case, but on 3rd October the company were due to pay an increase under a three-year agreement to another5,000 employees, and the company would be consulting the Ministerof Labour, in the light of the court action, on the course they should follow.It had been suggested that, if the case went against them, as wasto be expected. Thorn might pay the increase to the worker in whosename the action had been brought but not to others in a comparableposition. Another suggestion was that Thorn should give notice to terminate the contracts of employment of the workers concerned.Both these courses, however, seemed likely to lead to industrial action.The company would be reluctant to adopt either of these suggestions,and it was not proposed to press them to do so.The Government would need to consider, in the light of the courtcase, what action to take on Part IV of the Prices and Incomes Act.The only immediate result of an Order in Council implementingPart IV of the Act would be to bring into operation Section 30,indemnifying employers against legal action for withholding inpursuance of the standstill the implementation of a wage increase.It would also confer upon the Government power to give directionsunder Section 27 on prices and to make Orders under Section 29 on wages; but these powers would become operative only when specificOrders were made in particular cases. Section 30 would not have. retrospective effect, and if it were desired to prevent the payment of wage increases by Thorn it would be necessary to make an order under Section 29. Such an Order would require the company fromthe date of the Order not to pay wages higher than those in payment on 20th July, but it would not be possible to require the repayment of increases in wages which had been paid out before the date of theOrder.One course might be for the Government not to take any actionfollowing the Thorn case, in the hope that this would not lead towidespread breaches of the voluntary working of the prices and incomes standstill. The other course would be to start consultations with the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and the Confederation ofPrices andIncomesPolicyPart IV of thePrices and incomes Act(previous reference:CC (66) 44thConclusions,Minute 3)
British Industries (CBI) on the activation of Part IV of the Act. TheGovernment were committed to consulting the TUC and the CBIbefore activating Part IV of the Act; even if these consultations tookplace next week, it would be unlikely that Part IV could be inoperation until the following week. It would be necessary to arrangefor a meeting of the Privy Council in order to make the necessary order in Council.If the decision were to bring Part IV of the Act into operation as soon as possible, the question would arise whether an Order should then be made under Section 29 of the Act. There was a danger that,once one such Order had been made, the voluntary working of the standstill would break down. It might therefore be preferable, evenif it were decided to bring Part IV into operation as soon as possible,not to make any Order under Section 29 until it became clear that without such an Order the standstill of wages would break down.In discussion the following points were made:(a) With the introduction of the statutory powers in Part IV ofthe Act, some of these responsible for decisions on prices and incomeson both sides of industry might feel that the need for their co-operation with the Government in the voluntary working of thepolicy was diminished or even eliminated. It would be a pity to incurthis risk by activating Part IV of the Act before the voluntary workingof the policy could be seen to be in serious danger of breaking downand it might well be preferable not to activate Part IV merely becauseof an adverse result in the Thorn case.(b) There were political reasons for postponing an Order inCouncil implementing Part IV of the Act until after the House ofCommons had resumed, if this could be achieved without giving theappearance of indecision on the part of the Government.(c) There was a danger that a decision to bring Part IV of theAct into operation would be interpreted as an attack on wages andnot on prices. It would be desirable to make it clearer to the public that the only immediate effect of bringing Part IV into operation wasto indemnify employers against action for breach of contract if theywithheld wage increases in pursuance of the standstill, and that thepowers to prevent or reverse price or wage increases would come intooperation only on the making of further specific Orders under sections 27 and 29. A decision to activate Part IV should be presented as being made necessary by the result of the Thorn case (if that wereadverse) in order to provide the indemnity against cases of breach of contract necessary to preserve the voluntary working of the standstill.Should the time come to make.Orders under Section 27 or Section 29,it might well be desirable that the Government should be seen to betaking action on prices as well as on wages.(d) Information about increases of prices and wages at a centralpoint, which should presumably be in the Department of economic affairs.b
10 confidential the Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that therewas general agreement that, if the court action went against Thorn,the First Secretary of State should enter into consultations with the tuc and the CBI, in which he should indicate that the Governmentwere seriously contemplating the possibility of bringing Part IV ofthe Prices and Incomes Act into operation and should invite theirviews. If following these consultations the First Secretary of Stateconsidered that Part IV of the Act should be brought into operation,he would bring the issue back to the Cabinet for a decision. A public announcement at this stage should say no more than that theGovernment were consulting the TUC and the CBI, though it wouldbe advantageous to give background guidance on the lines indicatedin discussion on the limited legal effect of bringing Part IV intooperation without any additional Orders or directions being made,if this guidance could be given without undesirable consequences,such as implying that a decision had already been taken or was about to be taken. The First Secretary of State should arrange for theDepartment of Economic Affairs to collect information about allcases of actual or claimed wage and price increases; other ministers concerned with particular sectors of the field should take steps tomake sure that the Department of Economic Affairs were kept fully informed. This information would form the material upon which decisions on the use of statutory powers under Part IV of the Actwould be based. Periodic reports should be made to the ministerial committee on Prices and Incomes, and if necessary to the Cabinet.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that, if the forthcoming court action went againstThorn Electrical Industries Limited, the First Secretary ofState should enter into consultations with the TradesUnion Congress and the Confederation of BritishIndustries and make a public announcement on the lines indicated in the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the First Secretary of State to arrange for thecollection of information on increases of prices and wageson the lines suggested in discussion and in the PrimeMinisters summing up, and to circulate periodic reports to the Ministerial Committee on Prices and Incomes, andif necessary to the Cabinet.CONFIDENTIALDocksEmploymentand Pay(previous reference:CC(66) 17thConclusions,Minute 7)4. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the First Secretaryof State and Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (C (66) 135)and the Minister of Labour (C (66) 136) on employment and pay inthe docks.The First Secretary of State said that the Minister of Labour had now received reports by Sir George Honeyman on objections to thedraft revised Dock Labour Scheme and by a committee under
7443cCC 48 (66)Lord Devlin on the changes of pay needed as a corollary to theintroduction of permanent employment in the docks. No special problems arose on the Honeyman report, but the Devlin proposalspresented problems from the point of view of incomes policy. these were for increases amounting to 6 per cent of the wage bill whichwere firmly tied to the changes in working practices that wouldaccompany full decasualisation. The resulting improvements of productivity would not justify increases of more than 6 per centin earnings, and even so the whole benefit of the improvedproductivity would be going to the employees. Devlin had, however,proposed the introduction of weekly modernisation payments, addinga further 10 per cent to the wage bill, not related to further increases in productivity but simply in order to ease the acceptance of the modernisation scheme on which decasualisation depended. the ministerial Committee on the Reorganisation of the Docks had taken the view that it would be difficult to justify so substantial an increasewithout countervailing and specific improvements in productivity,either during the period of severe restraint or indeed thereafter. Theyhad therefore concluded that the Government could commend theDevlin recommendations in principle only if the modernisationpayment was made conditional upon definite and specificimprovements in productivity and the elimination of restrictive practices, over and above the changes directly associated withdecasualisation. Lord Brown, the Chairman of the NationalModernisation Committee, took the view that this, though animportant modification of the Devlin proposals, would constitute abasis for negotiation. There would, however, undoubtedly be difficulties, since the Devlin Committee had envisaged that restrictive practices not directly associated with the casual labour system wouldbe the subject of further productivity bargains in individual ports.On the timing of the changes, the Ministerial Committee on there organisation of the Docks had agreed that this should be left open for the time being, though it would in his view be impossible tointroduce these changes during the period of severe restraint.The Minister of Labour said that he agreed with the first secretary of State that the Government should press the industry todeal with restrictive practices other than those directly associatedwith decasualisation in the context of the proposed pay settlement.None the less it must be recognised that this represented a modification of the Devlin proposals. It was in his view extremely important to take no step that might jeopardise the decasualisationprogramme, and it would be desirable that he should have somefreedom of manoeuvre in the negotiations that would follow the government&apos;s acceptance of the Honeyman and Devlin reports. Theannouncement which he proposed to make, a draft of which was attached to his memorandum, would enable him to see what measureof support the Government could obtain in the industry for the approach which the Ministerial Committee on the Reorganisation ofthe Docks had suggested, and to press for action on the National
and Local Modernisation Committees leading to firm and bindingdecisions on those restrictive practices, the elimination of which wasa prerequisite of decasualisation and the proposed pay settlement.The Government would be able to consider in the light of the progressof negotiations how to pursue the matter, but he feared that, if theGovernments initial announcement were as tightly worded as theFirst Secretary of State&apos;s memorandum suggested, there was a real danger that negotiations on decasualisation would break down andthat there would be threats of industrial action in the docks.The Financial Secretary, Treasury, said that the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer was concerned about the possible impact of a pay settlement on the lines proposed upon the Governmenfs policy on prices and incomes, bearing in mind that the proposed modernisationpayments could not be reconciled with the criteria envisaged for theperiod of severe restraint or indeed for the subsequent period. Itwould be hard to justify increases of the order proposed simply as an inducement to dockers to accept changes for which they had been pressing for a long time. He suggested that it would be preferable for the fifth sentence of paragraph 5 of the proposed draft announcement to read: &quot; Implementation of these changes must ofcourse also be governed by the provisions of the prices and incomesstandstill and by the criteria which still have to be settled for pay increases during the period of severe restraint and thereafter &quot;.In discussion the following points were made:(a) It was suggested that the draft announcement should be lessspecific about the timetable for legislation on nationalisation. It waspointed out, however, that the timetable had already been made public, and that there need be no objection to restating it in this announcement.(b) The draft announcement did not include any reference to Icompensation for employees of the National Docks Labour Boardwho were declared redundant on nationalisation. The Chairman ofthe Board was anxious for some reassurance to his staff on thismatter, but the inclusion of such an assurance in the forthcomingannouncement might cause unnecessary alarm among dockers. TheMinister of Labour would endeavour to persuade the Chairman ofthe Board that this assurance could be conveyed privately to representatives of the staff concerned, and would include a referenceto this in the public announcement only if it proved necessary to doso in order to satisfy the Chairman of the Board.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were impressed by the need to leave the Minister of labour with freedom of manoeuvre in what would be difficult negotiations.They agreed that the Government should accept the Honeyman andDevlin reports in principle, and approved the draft announcement in the form of the draft attached to the Minister of Laboufsmemorandum (subject to the minor points made in discussion), onthe understanding that the Minister of Labour would make every endeavour to persuade the two sides of the industry to link the elimination  of restrictive practices,  other than those directly
CONFIDENTIALIron and SteelNationalisationSalaries ofMembers ofthe Corporation(previous reference:CC (66) 33rdConclusions,Minute 2)5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of power (C (66) 133) on the salaries to be paid to members of theNational Steel Corporation.The Minister of Power said that he was in the process of settingup an Organising Committee to prepare the ground for the NationalSteel Corporation. The task facing the Corporation was of suchmagnitude that it would be important to find the best possible peoplefor the Corporation. He proposed formally to invite Lord Melchettto accept appointment as Chairman of the Organising Committee,and subsequently of the Corporation, at a salary of  16,000 a year.He had ascertained that Lord Melchett, even though his presentearnings totalled around  20,000 a year, was prepared to acceptassociated with the casual labour system, with a pay settlement onthe lines of the Devlin proposals. The Minister of Labour would nodoubt report to his colleagues upon the progress of negotiations and upon the success of his endeavours.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Labour:(i) to arrange for the publication of the Honeyman and Devlinreports on 3rd October, 1966;(ii) to announce the Governments acceptance of the reports inthe terms of the draft statement annexed to his memorandum (C (66) 136), subject to the minor points made in discussion;(iii) in his subsequent negotiations with the two sides of theindustry to be guided by the views expressed by the ministerial Committee on the Reorganisation of the docks and the point made in the Prime minister&apos;s summing up about the need to the greatest extent possibleto associate with the proposed pay settlement the elimination of restrictive practices other than thosedirectly associated with the casual labour system;(iv) to keep the Ministerial Committee on Prices and incomes and the Ministerial Committee on the Reorganisation ofthe Docks, as appropriate, informed of the progress of negotiations, particularly in respect of the willingness ofthe two sides of the industry to associate the elimination of other restrictive practices with the proposeddecasualisation pay settlement;(v) to seek the agreement of the Ministerial Committee on prices and Incomes in due course to any proposals forGovernment approval of the nature and timing of pay and other changes resulting from negotiations betweenthe two sides of the industry.
appointment on these terms in view of the current economic situation.But he, as well as other prospective members of the organising committee (who would not be committed to membership of theCorporation), saw some difficulty about finding suitable candidates for membership of the. Corporation from within the steel industry,if salaries of full-time* members were limited to the range of salariespaid to full-time board members in other nationalised industries.The average salary of directors in the steel industry was over  15,000;and in Richard Thomas and Baldwin, Ltd. (RTB) the Governmenthad approved salaries of  15,000 for the chairman,  12,000 for the managing director and amounts ranging from  10,000 to  8,000 forother members of the board. At this stage the Minister proposed tosuggest to Lord Melchett that appointments to the organising committee should be made ad hoc, and to inform him that the salaries of members of the National Steel Corporation had yet to bedetermined by the Government; but in due course he might have toask the Cabinet to approve salaries higher than those paid to full-timeboard members in other public corporations, at least in one or twospecial cases.In discussion, while there was general agreement that LordMelchett should be offered a salary of  16,000, it was suggested thatthere might be advantage in dividing this figure into a salary of 15,000 and allowances of  1,000, on the lines of the emoluments paidto the Chairmen of the British Overseas Airways Corporation. Itwas pointed out, however, that this might well create an undesirableprecedent; moreover it might well be important that the actual salaryrate should be higher than the  15,000 paid to the Chairman of RTB.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that Lord Melchett should be offered a salary of 16,000, on the understanding that the Government should be in no way committed as regards the salaries of those who would serve under him, either on the Organising Committee or in due course onthe National Steel Corporation.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the Minister of Power should formally inviteLord Melchett to serve as Chairman of the organising committee, and subsequently of the National steel corporation, at a salary of  16,000 a year.(2) Agreed that the remuneration of other members of theOrganising Committee should be determined by theMinister of Power, the First Secretary of State and theChancellor of the Exchequer.(3) Agreed to determine the rates of salary for members of theNational Steel Corporation at a later date.(4) Invited the Minister of Power to ensure that in the meantimeno commitment was given to Lord Melchett on salaries for other members of the National Steel Corporation.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,29th September, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
