<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 598-612</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1967CC (66)55th conclusions copy No.   ^ cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on Wednesday, 9th November, 1966, at 9.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, mp,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Secretary of State for commonwealth affairs the Right Hon. Denis PIealey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for EducationScienceThe Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy Seal (Items Iand 2)The Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe   Right   Hon.   Lord   Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Lord President of the Council(Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Secretary  of State  for the home department the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Minister of Overseas Develop-ment the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,mp, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of Transport (Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, mp, Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Postmaster-General (Item 3)The Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. W. A. nield mr. D. S. laskey mr. R. T. Armstrong
contents item                                   Subject page 1     Rhodesia       ..................... *2     Europe............             ......... &apos;3     Decimal Currency   .................. 12Coinage
Rhodesia(previous reference:CC (66) 51stConclusions,Minute 4)secret. The Commonwealth Secretary said that the reply fromMr. Smith, the head of the illegal regime in Rhodesia, to ourstatement of terms for a settlement had been received on 5th November. It was cleverly drafted to give the impression of a move in our direction, but gave no satisfactory answer to the mostimportant points in our statement. It offered to extend the &quot; B &quot; Rollfranchise to all Rhodesians over 30; but cross-voting would be abolished and the Africans would thus lose the influence they couldexercise on the &quot; A &quot; Roll seats. It also offered to entrench the15 &quot; B &quot; Roll seats, but this was a concession of no real value. Therewas a new proposal, which could be represented as giving effect tothe sixth principle, for the creation of 15 reserved seats for Europeans.One of these would be created each time the Africans gained an&quot; A &quot; Roll seat and the practical effect would be substantially to defer the date on which Africans could hope to obtain a majority inthe Assembly. The entrenchment of Section 37 of the Constitution,which governed the creation of new constituencies, was rejected; the&quot; braking mechanism &quot; would thus be preserved and the rhodesian government of the day would be able to create more &quot; A &quot; Roll seats and delay further the achievement of majority rule. the reply insisted that in the Senate there should be six representativesof the Chiefs and six elected African members instead of three Chiefsand nine elected Africans as we had proposed; the Chiefs were paidby the Rhodesian Government and could be expected to vote withthe European members. Our proposal for an increase from 15 to 17in the number of &quot; B &quot; Roll seats was declared to be unnecessary and undesirable. An external authority such as the Privy Council, as thefinal court of appeal for amendment of the entrenched clauses, was rejected. The reply offered to consider, but no more, the questionof a Royal Commission to examine land apportionment and racial discrimination. Our proposals for the return to legality were notdealt with at any length but it was made clear that the ascertainmentof Rhodesian opinion on the constitutional arrangements, as providedfor in the fifth principle, would have to take place while the illegal regime was still in power. The reply concluded with an invitationfor the Commonwealth Secretary to visit Salisbury with full authorityto negotiate with the illegal regime.At a meeting on the previous day of the Ministers primarily concerned it had been agreed that the reply amounted to a rejection of our terms. It had also been agreed that there were decisivearguments against a visit by him to Salisbury and that the idea ofa meeting between the Prime Minister and Mr. Smith, either in rhodesia, in the United Kingdom or elsewhere, would be whollyinappropriate. We must therefore accept that a breaking point hadbeen reached, but it had been felt that there would be advantage, inorder subsequently to clarify the United Kingdom Governmenfspublic position, in putting certain questions to Mr. Smith designedto elicit clear answers on some of the key issues. The first question might deal with the &quot; braking mechanism&quot; and ask whether
Mr. Smith accepted unimpeded progress to majority rule or whether he insisted that it must remain in the power of the Europeans todetermine the pace of African advance in order, in his own words, toprovide a safeguard against premature African rule. The second question might ask whether he accepted our proposal for a broadbased interim Administration representative of all races in Rhodesia;and the third question might be related to the way in which the fifth principle would be applied and whether he accepted that theascertainment of Rhodesian opinion should take place only afterthe return to constitutional rule, the removal of censorship and therelease of the detainees.There would be advantage if the United Kingdom Governmentspublic statement on the reasons for the break (an outcome which wemust assume, on the basis that the answers would prove to benegative) could be deferred until we had the answers to thesequestions. Publicity might, however, be given in Rhodesia at anytime to the terms of our offer and the Rhodesian reply and we should then need to make our statement immediately. He was in touch withthe Lord President about the necessary arrangements and the timetable for the statement which would have to be made inParliament and for the issue of a White Paper.In discussion there was agreement that Mr. Smith&apos;s replyamounted to a rejection of our terms for a settlement. Under our proposals it was calculated, on the best assumptions that could bemade, that the Africans would achieve a majority in the RhodesianAssembly after two or three general elections. Under thearrangements proposed by the regime, with the phasing in ofadditional European seats, this date was likely to be postponed fora further two elections or 10 years. Moreover, by reserving the rightto increase the number of constituencies under Section 37, the minority Rhodesian Government could delay the achievement of majority rule indefinitely. It had been the view of the previous, aswell as of the present, Administration that the 1961 Constitutionwas not in itself a basis for independence; the illegal regime nowrejected the additional safeguards which had previously been proposed and were insisting on a further retrogressive condition inthe shape of the &quot; braking mechanism &quot;.In further discussion there was general agreement that questions should be put to Mr. Smith on the lines proposed by theCommonwealth Secretary. These might best be drafted in such away as to force him to give clear negative answers, although it mustbe recognised that he would attempt to prevaricate. It was also important that any quotations from the statement of the regime&apos;position, such as references to &quot; premature African rule &quot;, should be clearly attributable to Mr. Smith in order to avoid the regime&apos;ssentiments, if taken out of context, being attributed to the UnitedKingdom Government. It should also be made clear in the UnitedKingdom Governments public statement that the question of the&quot; braking mechanism &quot; was not the only point of disagreement inrelation to the future constitutional arrangements.
Europe(previous reference:CC (66) 54thConclusions,Minute 4)secret. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the foreign secretary (C (66) 149), on a programme of action to enable theGovernment to obtain the information necessary to decide their future policy towards the European Economic Community (e.c.),and by the Commonwealth Secretary (C (66) 150) on the consequentconsultations with the Commonwealth Governments.The Foreign Secretary said that in his summing up of the cabinet&apos;s discussion on 3rd November the Prime Minister had outlined the following programme of action:(i) After consultations with the Governments of the european free Trade Association (EFTA) a conference of Headsof Government of EFTA to be called in London in earlyDecember to consider the steps to be followed in furtherapproaches to the e.c..(ii) An announcement, probably at the same time as theannouncement of the conference, reaffirming the government&apos;s willingness to join the Community onappropriate terms and stating that the Prime Ministerand himself would accordingly make a series of visits tothe Heads of Government of the Six to make our requirements clear and to ascertain theirs.(iii) A full statement of the Governmenfs attitude to Europe tobe made by the Prime Minister at the January meetingof the Consultative Assembly at Strasbourg.(iv) The visits then to be carried out, in order both to explore the conditions of membership and to press for aforthcoming attitude by the Governments of the Six toThe Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that hewould arrange for the text of the regime&apos;s reply to be circulated tothe Cabinet. The Cabinet agreed that the reply amounted to arejection of a settlement on any terms which we could accept. Wemust therefore prepare for a break but there would be advantage inclarifying the position for public presentation by putting the furtherquestions which the Commonwealth Secretary had proposed. the text of the questions should be drafted in the light of the points madein their discussion. In the event of prior publication in Rhodesiaof the terms of our offer and of the regime&apos;s reply the statement ofthe United Kingdom Governmenfs position would have to be made immediately.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to arrange for furtherquestions to be put to the illegal regime in Rhodesia onthe lines indicated in their discussion.
the Kennedy Round of tariff negotiations. For theformer purpose it would be necessary to have an agreedformula on the Governments attitude to the Treaty of rome, which would no doubt be on the basis of qualifiedacceptance, as amplified in the Annex to his memorandum.(v) Urgent studies to be made by officials both of the &quot; Javits &quot;plan for an economic association between the UnitedKingdom, the United States and certain members oi theold Commonwealth and of the prospects of the UnitedKingdom continuing without any new form of association.(vi) Consultations with the Governments of the commonwealth and of the United States in regard to our further movestowards Europe.It was arguable that if there were to be a meeting of the Headsof Government of EFTA countries there should be a similarCommonwealth Meeting, but there was the fundamental differencethat our partners in EFTA were all in Europe and all potentialmembers of an expanded e.c.. It might therefore be felt to besufficient to notify the Commonwealth Governments, the Governmentof the Irish Republic and the Government of the United States of our intentions, shortly before the announcement of the EFTA Conferenceand of the forthcoming visits. In doing so, we should need to make clear to Commonwealth Governments that the policy represented a continuation, at a higher level, of that which the Government hadpursued over the previous few months, that there was no question ofan early negotiation for entry into the Community and that theGovernment were not committed to such a course.In considering the terms of the Annex to his paper, on astatement of the Governments qualified acceptance of the Treaty of rome, it was necessary to bear in mind both that the qualificationsdetailed in the Annex did not purport to be exhaustive, but only tocover the most important aspects and also that we might hope, andshould need, to negotiate not merely transitional arrangements should we join the e.c., but also certain permanent adaptations ofthe present arrangements in the Community. The position of NewZealand, for example, would be a point of fundamental importanceto us.The Commonwealth Secretary said that at the Meeting theprevious September of Commonwealth Prime Ministers we had undertaken to give Commonwealth Governments information on theprogress of exploratory discussions relating to our further movestowards Europe and to consult them at all stages of any negotiations.If a special meeting of the Heads of Governments of the efta countries were convened at short notice, only a few weeks after therecent meeting of the EFTA Council at Lisbon, commonwealth governments might suspect that there had been a significant changein our attitude towards joining the e.c. and might urge that aMeeting of Commonwealth Ministers might be held.   This would
not, however, be advantageous to us, though we must takeCommonwealth Governments into our confidence and assure themthat we should seek to safeguard their essential interests. It wouldalso be desirable to inform the Governments of the Six in general terms that we should need to know whether terms at least as good as those negotiated by the previous Administration in 1962 could beassumed for Commonwealth countries in Asia, Africa and the carribbean, as well as special safeguards for New Zealand.Discussion was focused upon the following main points:(a) It would be difficult to prevent the process of probing fromdeveloping into one of negotiation, since we should be asking theGovernments of the Six how far they would be prepared to go tomeet us, and they would equally ask us how far we would go to meet them; we should then be close to negotiation, at a time when we were still economically weak. The Ministers or even the Governments ofsome of the Six countries with whom the exploratory discussions would be held might no longer be in office when the time came for negotiations, so that the indications they had given of the terms we might expect to secure might prove to be misleading. Our enquiriesmight well encounter unforthcoming reactions from the Governmentsof the Six, so that the eventual effect on the strength of the economy and the morale of industry in this country would be discouraging.On the other hand it was pointed out that there was general agreement that we could not rest longer upon the position reached in theprevious consultations, that the information so far available was insufficient for a decision in principle whether to apply for entry tothe Community, and that the necessary information could only beobtained by further direct enquiries at the highest level. Until these enquiries had been completed there could be no consideration of whether we should apply for entry or what the minimum terms would be that we could accept. The possibility that the Ministers ofthe Six countries whom we had consulted might not be in officewhen the time came for negotiation did not necessarily involvediscontinuity of policy and was a risk which was present in anyprolonged discussion. If our explorations indicated that we couldnot expect to secure acceptable terms, this would admittedly have a damaging effect on the economy; but this effect would be worse ifthe Government appeared indecisive in the course they wished to take.(b) The statement of the issues of policy in the Annex toC (66) 149 should have regard to the fact that the consultations wouldbe the beginning of a long bargaining process. At this stage our requirements should therefore be set higher. In particular, weshould not say that we were ready to accept the Treaty of Romeprovided certain of our conditions were fulfilled; we should not go further than accepting its objectives, because our essential requirements could not be met within its present terms. these requirements related, in addition to the provisions on freedom for capital movements and the common agricultural policy, to theabsence of freedom to use direct restraints on imports during balance
of payments difficulties, and to the powers of the Commission itselfto intervene in the conduct of our national economic policy. Onthese matters, which were of crucial importance for our capacity to plan our economy, the language of the Annex was not sufficiently strong and specific: we should make clear, for example, that wecould not accept the common agricultural policy as it now stood andthat the conditions of our entry must safeguard commonwealth interests at least to the same extent as had been done prior tp thetermination of the negotiations in 1961-62. It would, therefore, be wrong to suggest in the proposed talks that there were only two important areas of difficulty. On the other hand it was pointed outthat in previous Ministerial discussions it had been the general viewthat the areas of greatest difficulty were those of the freedom ofcapital movements and the common agricultural policy, and it wasa main purpose of the proposed talks to explore these fully. Asregards the supranational powers of the Commission in the field ofeconomic policy, in previous discussions it had been recognised that whilst the Treaty of Rome did provide such powers, their exercise bythe Commission was not in practice such that we need feel serious concern on this score, though it was certainly a point to be explored,particularly with the French. It had also been the general view thatthe restraints imposed upon our economic planning powers by ourposition as a major trading nation had been found to be at least as great as, if not greater than, those we might expect to experienceunder the Treaty of Rome. In general, if the conditions of entry asset out in the Annex were amended as proposed, the consultationscould not be expected to achieve any useful result. Moreover, as theForeign Secretary had emphasised, the Annex did not purport to beexhaustive.(c) The programme for action would also, it was urged, involveundesirable and unnecessary risks in three main respects. First, itwas premature; it would be some time before our economic recoveryhad made sufficient progress to warrant our opening discussions withthe Governments of the e.c., especially as these discussions might come close to negotiation. Second, a meeting of the Prime ministers of EFTA in December would afford scope for exaggerated concern for the interests of their countries and so for requirements upon theUnited Kingdom to endeavour to safeguard these interests. Third,a declaration of intent would be preferable to the proposal for high level visits to the Governments of the Six countries as a means ofmaking clear our attitude to the Community; after such a declaration,we could pursue our explorations of the likely conditions of entryby means which would reduce the risk of speculation andcommitment. On the other hand it was urged that our economicweakness had been over-emphasised and was not such that we couldnot afford even to make enquiries. Indeed, sterling had recently beena stronger currency than the franc, and there was now more reasonto accept the view expressed at a previous meeting of the Cabinetthat an overt move by the Government towards the community would have a good effect on business confidence both externally andinternally, provided it were made clear that there was no question
of our entering under conditions or on terms which would prejudice the strength of the economy and the value of sterling. As regardsthe proposed meeting of the Prime Ministers of EFTA, we were nolonger under the restrictive obligations of the London Declarationof 1962, the meeting would be a meeting of Prime Ministers of efta countries in London under our aegis, and not a meeting under the aegis of EFTA itself, and we could expect that the Prime ministers would be more likely to be content if they were fully and directlyconsulted in advance in this way than if consultations were carriedout by less direct methods at a lower level. There also seemed noreason to alter the view expressed in the Cabinefs earlier discussions that a series of visits to the Governments of the Six would be preferable to a declaration of intent followed by explorations at a lower level, not only as a better means of acquiring the informationwe required, but also because a declaration of intent was likely to be either too categoric (and so concede much of our negotiating position), or so qualified as to fail to emphasise the more positiveapproach to membership of the Community which it would be its purpose to convey.In further discussion it was pointed out that the exploratoryconsultations which had gone on for many months had reached thelimit of their usefulness, and it was known that Ministers had accordingly been considering the Governments position, first at themeeting at Chequers and subsequently in Cabinet. Despite the differences of view which had been expressed in regard to both theprogramme and the policy set out in the Foreign Secretary&apos;s paper,the Government must now publicly declare its position and clarifyits attitude towards joining into the Community. The choice beforethem was limited; no &quot; Atlantic alternative &quot; to membership of theCommunity was in sight at present, and it would not be practicable for the Government to announce that they did not intend to seekmembership of the Community, but to continue without seeking any alternative association, with inevitably greatly reduced international commitments, until it had been made clear that membership of theCommunity was not open to us save on unacceptable terms. a conclusion about our attitude to membership of the Community wasthe more necessary in view of the prospect of an early breakdown ofthe Rhodesian talks which might have serious implications for our balance of payments. A statement by the Government on our attitude to membership of the Community on the lines proposedcould be expected so to reduce uncertainties and increase confidenceat home and abroad as to put the Rhodesian development in its proper perspective. There would also be less anxiety at the proposedexploration of the conditions of entry, if this were on the basis thatthese conditions might include, on points of particular difficulty forus, not only transitional provisions, but also more permanent arrangements, perhaps by means of a protocol of accession such asmember countries had negotiated, and as was provided for underthe terms of the Treaty of Rome.
The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion, saidthat on balance the Cabinet agreed with the Foreign Secretary^paper and Annex as a steering brief for the intensified explorationwhich had been proposed, subject to the qualification the foreign secretary had made that it was not exhaustive and that we should need to negotiate certain permanent adaptations in the arrangements under the Treaty of Rome, as well as suitable transitional provisions.It would also be desirable to emphasise the importance of the finalsentence of the Annex, on the need to seek through appropriatechannels some long-term arrangements for the sterling balances,though this was not a matter for negotiation with the Heads ofGovernment of the Six as such. The statement of the Governmenfsposition which would now need to be made in Parliament should be approved by the Cabinet and he would circulate a draft for discussionaccordingly. There would no doubt be general agreement that theGovernment should not subsequently be drawn into public discussion in the United Kingdom of detailed aspects of our position in the investigations, or in any subsequent negotiations which might takeplace with the e.c., since to do so would merely weaken the government&apos;s position in those negotiations. At the end of theexploratory discussions which he and the Foreign Secretary would undertake, the Cabinet would then have to decide whether the terms which we might reasonably hope to obtain in formal negotiation were adequate to justify our joining the Community, including the questionwhether, if it proved that permanent adaptations of the arrangementsmade under the Treaty of Rome could not be secured, lengthytransitional provisions would sufficiently safeguard our interests.Meanwhile, the Cabinet had taken no decision on whether or not we should in due course apply to join the e.c. or on whether weshould start negotiations to that end.On the basis of the Cabinefs agreement on the policy to befollowed in the immediate future, it was now necessary to considerthe detailed procedure which should be adopted. From the point ofview of opinion both at home and abroad there would on balancebe advantage in a very early statement of the Governmenfs position.A suitable occasion for what would necessarily be a speech of some length would be the speech which he was due to make at the lord mayor&apos;s banquet on the following Monday. If that were agreed tobe appropriate it would be necessary first to make a concise statement in Parliament on the Governmenfs policy: in that event thestatement would have to be made the following day. It would accordingly be necessary, if this timetable were agreed, to convey to the other Governments of EFTA that evening our invitation to aconference in London and also to inform them of the broad terms ofthe statement which the Government proposed to make. Therewould also need to be, perhaps in the course of the following morning, and immediately before the Parliamentary statement, a communication to all Commonwealth Governments of theGovernment^ proposals, perhaps in terms which might vary according to their degree of interest in the issue. The Governmentsof the United States and of the Irish Republic should also be informed
of these in advance. The precise date of the meeting of the Heads ofGovernment of the countries in EFTA would be a matter for subsequent discussion with them but we might aim to hold this earlyin December.In discussion on procedure it was suggested that it would be premature to make a statement of the Governments position on thefollowing day, both because this might appear inadequate notice toour partners in EFTA of the decisions which the Government hadtaken since the recent meeting of the EFTA Council in Lisbon andalso because they might wish to have had longer notice of our intention to invite them to an early conference. It was, however, thegeneral view that while it was certainly necessary to have effectiveconsultation with the other Governments of EFTA on the line ofpolicy which the Government would adopt in subsequentinvestigations with the Governments of the e.c., and on how thoseinvestigations should be conducted, it would be an unreasonablerestriction on our freedom of policy to consult them on the terms ofthe Governments Parliamentary statement. Nor, indeed, did itseem probable that this would be expected by the other governments in EFTA: on the contrary they would welcome our undertakinginvestigations on the lines that had now been agreed and they wereprincipally concerned that we should consult them about the detailsof these investigations. They could, therefore be expected to welcome an invitation to a conference for this purpose. It might, however, benecessary to take special steps in respect of Sweden in view of therecent discussions between the First Secretary of State and theSwedish Minister of Commerce and it might prove necessary to send a representative of the First Secretary of State to Stockholm for thatpurpose. On these aspects there was general agreement with theprocedure which the Prime Minister had proposed.In subsequent discussion the Foreign Secretary said that further thought would be required of the timetable for the visits to the capitalsof the Six. It would be desirable that the first of these should takeplace after the EFTA conference and before the meeting of the consultative Assembly in Strasbourg in January. The visit to Parisshould be neither the first nor the last. Ideally, the visit to Bonnshould take place first, but this might be precluded by the uncertaintyover the position of the present Federal German Government. Inthat event, the first visit should take place to the capitals of the benelux countries. Visits might then follow to Bonn, Paris and rome, in that order: but there should be no visit to Brussels fordiscussion with the Commission at this stage. He would circulate a paper to the Cabinet for further discussion of these aspects.The Cabinet (1) Approved C (66) 149 and C (66) 150, subject to theamplification of the Annex to C (66) 149 indicated by thePrime Minister in his summing up of their discussion.
confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C (66) 148) on proposals for the new decimalcoinage.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the proposals of the ministerial Committee on Decimal Currency, based ultimately uponthe recommendations of the 1961 Committee of Inquiry on decimal currency under the chairmanship of the Earl of Halsbury (theHalsbury Committee), were:(i) The new minor unit should be called a penny (in the transitional period, new penny), not a cent.. (ii) The sequence of coin denominations in the new system should be \, 1 2, 5, 10 and 50 new pence. It would bebe possible to introduce a 20 or 25 new penny coin later,if the need arose.decimal currency(previous reference:&apos;  CC (66) 13thConclusions,Minute 5)Coinage(2) Agreed that a statement should be made in the House ofCommons on the following day on the position of theGovernment in relation to the European economic community.(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would circulate for their consideration on the following day the draft of such astatement.(4) Invited the Foreign Secretary to inform forthwith the other member Governments of the European Free trade association that a statement of the Governments policy would be made the following day and to invite the Headsof Government to a conference in London early inDecember.(5) Invited the Foreign Secretary to inform the other member governments of the European Free Trade association and the Governments of the United States of the broadterms of the Governments statement of policy shortly before it was made in the House of Commons.(6) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to inform all commonwealth Governments, in terms which might vary according to their degree of interest in the issue, andthe Government of the Irish Republic of the terms ofthe Government statement simultaneously with itsannouncement, or shortly before it was made.(7) Took note that the Foreign Secretary would circulate a paper on the modalities of the visits by the PrimeMinister and himself to the capitals of the Six.(8) Invited the First Secretary of State, in consultation with theForeign Secretary, to arrange for a representative to visitStockholm immediately with a message for the SwedishMinister of Commerce on the lines agreed in their discussion.
CONFIDENTIAL-(iii) The \, 1 and 2 new penny coins should be of bronze, inweight /value relationship, of the sizes recommended bythe Halsbury Committee.(iv) The 5 and 10 new penny coins should be of cupro-nickel,of the same size as their present-day equivalents.(v) A new 50 new penny coin should be introduced instead ofthe 10s. note.(vi) The halfpenny should be withdrawn before decimalisationand should not be replaced by a quarter penny in thedecimal system.In discussion the proposals were generally agreed and thefollowing points were made:(a) The main case for replacing the 10s. note with a 50 newpenny coin was that the average life of 10s. notes was becomingshorter and the cost of maintaining their issue was as a resultincreasing steadily. Over the years, therefore, the cost ofmaintaining a note issue would be larger than that of maintaining the equivalent issue of coins. A change to a coin might, however,give rise to some public confusion, and the public might in the eventprefer to continue to use notes for this denomination. Furtherconsideration should therefore be given to the possibility of the 10s.note being withdrawn somewhat later, so that there would be a period during which 10s. notes and 50 new penny coins would be in circulation together and there would be an opportunity of assessing the public preference.(b) The loss of the present halfpenny would have some effecton prices in the food and certain other trades and there would be some tendency to round up prices that included the odd halfpenny.On the other hand traders would have several years to prepare forthe withdrawal of the halfpenny, and there would be scope foradjustments in quantity or size to offset price changes, up or down.Some quantities would in any case be due for change, in the processof the change to metric systems of weights and measures. It would,however, be necessary for the Government and the Decimal CurrencyBoard to carry out a sustained effort to minimise any increases inprices as a result of the withdrawal of the halfpenny. A particular problem for the Post Office would be that an increase of a newhalfpenny in the letter rate would bring in  30 million, which mightbe more than the Post Office required at any particular time. this problem could, however, be overcome without the necessity of having a new quarter penny coin by issuing stamps in denominations of anew quarter penny and selling them in pairs.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet endorsed the conclusions of the Ministerial Committee onDecimal Currency, subject to further study by the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Decimal Currency Board of the possibility ofthe 10s. note being withdrawn somewhat later, on the lines suggested
14CONFIDENTIALin discussion. Some misgivings had been expressed about theproposal to withdraw the halfpenny and not to replace it with a new(decimal) farthing. It was clear that the retention of a new farthingwould add to the difficulty and cost of the change to a decimal currency, and it seemed likely that the need for the present halfpenny(or a decimal equivalent) would continue to diminish. The objectionsto withdrawing the halfpenny could be overcome or avoided in a variety of ways, as suggested in discussion. The general view wastherefore that a policy decision should now be taken to demonetisethe halfpenny in 1970 and not to replace it in the decimal system.If in 1970 the expectations on which that decision was foundedseemed not to be being realised, it would at that stage be open tothe Cabinet to review the decision before the halfpenny wasdemonetised.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to consider further,in the light of advice from the Decimal Currency Board,the possibility of retaining 10s. notes in circulation,together with the new coins of 50 pennies, for a time afterdecimalisation, in order to give an opportunity ofassessing public preference as between a note and a coinfor this denomination.(2) Subject to Conclusion (1), approved C (66) 148.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,9th November, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
