<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/41/0 images: 627-642</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1967CC (66) Copy No.    3657th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 15th November, 1966, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, mp,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Herbert Bowden, m p,Secretary of State for Common-wealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, First Secretary of State and secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Douglas Houghton,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,m p, Minister of Overseas Develop-ment the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Anthony Wedgwood Benn, m p,Minister of Technology757a -1a
The following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,mp, Minister of health the Right Hon. Frederick Mulley,m p, Minister of Aviation (Item 2)The Right Hon. Reginald Prentice,mp, Minister of Public Building and works (Item 2)Mr. Edward Redhead, mp, Ministerof State, Department of education and science the Right Hon. Margaret Herbison,m p, Minister of Social Security(Item 2)The Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Postmaster-General (Item I)The Right Hon. John Diamond, mp.Chief Secretary, Treasury (Item 2)The Right Hon. John Silkin, mp. kParliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. W. A. nield mr. L. errington mr. K. barnes mr. R. T. ArmstrongContentsItem                                     Subject page 1     Prices and Incomes Standstill   ............       draft White Paper on Prices and Incomes Criteriaduring Period of Severe RestraintPay in the Public Services and Salary Reviews in private IndustryArrangements for Publication2     Public Expenditure, 1967-68      ............       8DefenceCivil DefenceOther Oversea ServicesRoadsRailways DeficitAssistance to Agriculture and IndustryAviation and SpaceHousing Subsidies and GrantsHousing InvestmentResumption of Discussion
prices and IncomesStandstillDraft white paper on prices andIncomesCriteriaduringPeriod ofSevereRestraint(previous reference :CC (66) 56thConclusions,Minute 5)secret. The Cabinet considered two memoranda by the first secretary of State and Secretary of State for Economic Affairs,covering a draft of a White Paper on Prices and Incomes Criteriaduring the Period of Severe Restraint (C (66) 167) and on thetreatment of pay in the public services during the period of severe restraint (C (66) 156).Draft White paper the First Secretary of State said that in paragraph I 2 of thedraft, the last sentence indicated the measure of agreement whichhe had reached in his consultations with representatives of the confederation of British Industry (CBI) and the Trades UnionCongress (TUC), but it was still possible that the General Councilof the TUC would have difficulty in accepting the present wording.It might therefore be necessary to modify the sentence in the lightof further information about the attitude of the TUC, but it wouldbe important to retain some reference to the extent of agreement reached if further consultations warranted this.The last sentence in paragraph II 5 set out the circumstances inwhich increases of prices might be permissible during the period of severe restraint. In previous drafts this sentence had referred toexceptional circumstances in which the receipts of an enterprisewere not adequate without some increase in prices to enable it toundertake &quot; desirable investment&quot;. The CBI had objected to theword &quot; desirable &quot; on the grounds that the Government could notbe the judge of the desirability of investment projects; they had,however, been prepared to accept the phrase &quot; necessary investment &quot;,which was acceptable from the Government^ point of view.Paragraph IV 16 contained an indication of what the criteria for incomes would be after the end of the period of severe restraint.While the first sentence was generally acceptable, the TUC had feltdifficulty in accepting the rest of the paragraph because they thoughtthat it prejudged the results of consultations about future policy on incomes which were yet to take place. The White Paper shouldmake clear the need for continued restraint after the first half of1967, but if the retention of the paragraph (other than the first sentence) would provoke a hostile reaction from the TUC, it wouldbe better to omit it. The essential point could in any case be madein public statements accompanying publication of the White Paper.In discussion the following points were made:(a) Paragraphs II10-12 on the obligations of firms to give priornotification of increases of price to the appropriate department should be more precise. Earlier drafts had explicitly requiredprior notification of proposed price increases from firms employing100 workers or more. There was some danger that, if therequirements were not precise, firms would increase prices becausethey had not appreciated what their obligations were. On the other
hand, if the obligation were specifically confined to firms employing100 workers or more, smaller firms might regard themselves as free to increase prices. The First Secretary of State should consider further with the President of the Board of Trade whether the paragraph should be expanded to set out more clearly therequirements for prior notification.(b) The statement in paragraph IV 6 that the Government would continue to give a high priority to measures designed to meet familyneeds might need to be reviewed in the light of the cabinets discussion on the next item of their agenda on the introduction of ascheme for family endowment. It was further pointed out that paragraph IV 6 did not specifically refer to the compression ofdifferentials which would necessarily follow the granting of increases to the lowest paid workers. As now drafted, the paragraph couldbe interpreted as meaning that the lowest paid workers in each industry would be eligible for pay increases; this was not theintention. It might help from this point of view to refer throughoutthe paragraph (not just in the first sentence) to &quot; the worst-offmembers of the community&quot; rather than to &quot; the lowest paid workers &quot;. On the other hand, it was argued that the paragraphmade the essential point that any increases would have to ,be confined to the lowest paid. The effect of the criterion as set outin the draft would be to throw on to the unions the responsibilityof choosing between accepting the compression of differentials orforfeiting increases for their lowest paid workers. If claims to restore differentials were pressed after an increase had been grantedto the lowest paid, it might be necessary to invoke the compulsory powers under Part IV. There were dangers in elaborating the paragraph further and it was doubtful whether the phrase&quot; worst-off members of the community&quot; would in practice be interpreted more restrictively than the phrase &quot; lowest paid workers &quot;.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion on thisparagraph, said that the general view of the Cabinet was that thepresent wording of the paragraph should stand, except that the reference to measures designed to meet family needs would need tobe reviewed in the light of the Cabinefs decision on the introductionof a family endowment scheme. It would, however, be desirable in the public presentation of the White Paper to make the pointclearly that it was not the intention to allow increases to the lowestpaid workers in each industry, and that any increases would be conditional on the acceptance by other workers of the resultingcompression of differentials.(c) In the penultimate line of paragraph IV 11 it was suggestedthat the phrase &quot; a subsequent commitment &quot; meant a commitment to a subsequent increase. The paragraph should be amended tomake the meaning clear.(d) On paragraph TV 16, dealing with the criteria after June1967, there was general agreement with the proposal by the first secretary of State that the paragraph (other than the first sentence)should be omitted if its,retention would provoke a hostile statement
Pay in thePublicServicesand SalaryReviews inPrivateIndustryfrom the TUC. If the passage in question were omitted, it might also be necessary to redraft the last sentence of paragraph I 5. Itwas suggested that in paragraph IV 16 that Government shouldtake credit for the stabilisation of the cost of living achieved duringthe standstill period; the general view, however, was that this point would be better made in the public presentation of the White Paper.(e) On paragraph IV 18, it was suggested that the reference inthe first sentence to the application of incomes &quot; criteria&quot; topensions was not sufficiently clear, and it was generally agreed thatit would be preferable to say that the &quot; same considerations&quot;applied to proposed increases in pensions as applied to proposed increases in employment incomes. A similar amendment shouldbe made in the third sentence of the paragraph.The First Secretary of State said that the problem of pay in thepublic services was linked to that of the treatment of salary reviewsin private industry, and decisions on the one would affect the line to be taken on the other. The difficulty arose from the fact thatincrements of a fixed amount within a pre-determined scale, of the type common in the public services, had been excluded from the standstill. The predominant practice in private industry was to review the salaries of managerial and executive staff at present -determined times but to leave to the employees discretion theamount of any increase granted; and no discretionary increases ofthis kind had been permitted during the standstill. The CBI had pressed strongly for such increases to be allowed during the periodof severe restraint and had argued that if this were not done, thosein private industry would be getting less favourable treatment thanpublic servants. If no concession were made, it had to be recognisedthat employers might adopt various devices to get round theprohibition, and it would be difficult to invoke the powers underPart IV to deal with the salaries of individuals. Moreover, thosefirms who observed the severe restraint criteria would be at risk of losing their staff to other employers who were less scrupulous. Onthe other hand, in most cases salary reviews in private industry were made at the end of the year; if no increases were allowed inthese cases during the period of severe restraint, this would simplyimpose a six months&apos; deferment which corresponded to the generaldeferment under the standstill provisions. The staff affected bysalary reviews were not among the lowest paid. If any concessionwere made to the CBI in this matter, the TUC would be bound topress for corresponding treatment for manual workers. If theGovernment were to resist any concession on salaries in private industry, there was all the more need to ensure severe restraint inthe public services.The Ministerial Committee on Prices and Incomes had reached a substantial measure of agreement on the treatment of the public services, as set out in his memorandum. They had agreed on thetreatment of both non-industrial and industrial civil servants. Inaddition to civil servants, there were a number of cases of other public service employees where there were commitments to review
pay from an agreed operative date before 30th June, 1967, but where the amount of any increase was yet to be determined. the ministerial Committee had agreed in the case of all these groupsthat no increase should be actually paid before 1st July, 1967, except where it was justified under the proposed criteria for the period of severe restraint, and that where increases after 1st July, 1967, wouldbe substantial, they should be paid in instalments. There was alsothe problem of whether to allow retrospection where increases were granted to these groups after 1st July, 1967, and here also there wasagreement on two of the three groups of employees concerned. First,there were those with an agreed operative date before the beginningof the standstill; the Committee agreed that for this groupretrospection to a date six months after the agreed operative date should be allowed. Secondly, there was a group of employeeswhose agreed operative date fell during the period of severe restraint; the Committee agreed that in these cases there should beno retrospection. There was, however, a difference of view aboutthe degree of retrospection to be allowed in the case of the thirdgroup i.e., those whose agreed operative date fell between 20th July,1966, and 31st December, 1966. There were three possible courses in relation to this group:(i) To allow no retrospection at all. This would be the most desirable course from the point of view of maintainingsevere restraint generally.(ii) To allow retrospection to a date six months later than the agreed operative date in all cases. The number of employees involved was 325,000 and if retrospectionwere allowed for such substantial numbers, there wouldbe a danger of undermining the whole policy of severe restraint.(iii) To allow no retrospection to cases in this group with the sole exception of the police: the police would be allowedan increase on 1st July, 1967, retrospective to theiragreed operative date plus six months, which would meanretrospection to 1st March, 1967.His view, which was shared by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,was that course (iii) should be adopted provided it was possible to confine exceptional treatment to the case of the police; if this couldnot be done, then course (i) should be adopted.The Home Secretary said there was a strong case for allowingretrospection in the case of the police. Wastage in the police force was now running at a level 50 per cent higher than last year. Whilethe rate of recruitment was reasonable, it was the loss of trained men which presented the most serious problem. Course (iii) would raise an acute problem as regards the Fire Service who would press for equivalent treatment. He was, however, satisfied that it wouldbe possible to resist such a claim by the Fire Service and he accordingly recommended the adoption of course (iii).In discussion it was suggested that the police were not the onlycase deserving exceptional treatment.   Equally strong arguments
could be put forward for allowing retrospection to other groups ofworkers, for example in the National Health Service where some ofthose concerned were among the lowest paid. Public service pay,in accordance with existing agreements, was regulated on the basisof &quot; fair comparisons &quot; and this necessarily involved retrospectionin determining their pay. If during the period of severe restraintno increases were to be allowed on grounds of comparability andif in addition the degree of retrospection were to be severely limited,the effect would be to penalise the public sector as compared with private industry. Course (ii), which would allow retrospection in allthe cases in question, was therefore the right course to adopt.On the other hand it was argued that to allow retrospection inall these cases would mean that increases would be paid in respectof the period of severe restraint, the amount of which was not determined by reference to the proposed criteria for that period.This could undermine the whole policy of severe restraint. in considering whether a limitation on the degree of retrospectionwould unduly penalise the public sector it should be rememberedthat public service employees had greater security of tenure thanstaff in private industry and this was of some importance in presentcircumstances. If retrospection were allowed to all the cases inquestion, it would become impossible to resist the demand for a concession on discretionary salary reviews in private industry, whichwould in turn lead to strong pressure by the TUC for correspondingtreatment for manual workers. It should be possible to defendmaking an exception in the case of the police: they would still not receive any increase until 1st July, 1967, by which time it wouldbe two years and nine months since their last increase.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion,said that the balance of view in the Cabinet favoured the third ofthe possible courses outlined by the First Secretary of State.Paragraph IV 11A should be accordingly retained in the draft white paper and paragraphs IV 12B and C should be omitted. A specific reference to the treatment of the police should be added to paragraph 11 A, after consultation between the First Secretary ofState and the Home Secretary. The First Secretary of State should consider further whether paragraph 11A should be left in the sectionof the draft dealing with existing commitments generally, or whetherit should be moved to the section which related to the public services.There was general agreement that no provision should be made inthe White Paper for discretionary increases in salaries in the private sector during the period of severe restraint.Arrangements On timing, there was general agreement that the White paper or Publication g^^i^ published in the early part of the week beginning21st November, but it would be desirable to avoid publicationcoinciding with any major announcement on Rhodesia. It wouldbe appropriate for the First Secretary of State to make a statement in Parliament immediately before publication.
public expenditure,1967-68(previous reference :CC (66) 43rdConclusions,Minute 3)secret. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer, covering a report by the ministerial committee on Public Expenditure (C (66) 158), and memoranda by the Minister of Social Security (C (66) 161), the Secretary ofState for Education and Science (C (66) 166) and the Minister of housing and Local Government (C (66) 168).The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the report of the ministerial Committee set out proposals for containing the rate of increase of public expenditure, which was now well in excess of the planned rate of 4  per cent per annum. In 1967-68 it would riseby more than 8 per cent (at constant prices) above the level of1966-67, unless the increase were curtailed. Defence expenditurehad been restrained, so that the increases were solely on civil expenditure, which had been rising must faster than outlays in therest of the economy. A considerable shift in the use of resourceshad already taken place between the private and public sectors, andwas being financed by increasing taxation each year and restrictingany general increase in the level of personal consumption. TheCommittee considered that attention should now be turned to thequestion whether the Governments present priorities for expenditure were right, and to the need to leave room, when the time came forreflation, for first priority to be given to expenditure which woulddirectly benefit productivity, exports, and import saving.The planned rate of increase in public expenditure of 4  per cent per annum on constant prices was equivalent in 1967-68 to  526million. Against this Departments had proposed increasesamounting to  1,037 million, and the Committee recommended aThe Cabinet (1) Agreed that where there were existing commitments to review the pay of public service employees from anoperative date falling between 20th July, 1966, and31st December, 1966, increases resulting from thesereviews should not be paid until after 1st July, 1967,and should not be retrospective, except in the case of thepolice where retrospection to 1st March, 1967, shouldbe allowed. *(2) Agreed that no provision should be made in the white paper for discretionary increases in salaries in private industry during the period of severe restraint.(3) Invited the First Secretary of State to revise the draft white paper annexed to C (66) 167 on the lines agreed in discussion.(4) Invited the First Secretary of State, in consultation with theLord President of the Council, to arrange for publicationof the White Paper in the early part of the week beginning21st November, and to make an announcement inParliament immediately before publication.
The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals of the Ministerial Committee on public Expenditure that defence expenditure for 1967-68should be limited to  2,149 million.The Home Secretary said that he could achieve savings of 2 million in the expenditure proposed on civil defence as hithertodefined. This reduction would not necessarily, however, be adequate to enable the Civil Defence budget to absorb the cost of the HomeDefence Force, unless the rate of recruitment for that force were such that there would be considerable under-expenditure on theestimate for 1967-68. Otherwise, in order to restrict total civil defence expenditure on that basis to  22 million it would benecessary to abolish the Civil Defence Corps. This would not be acceptable in present circumstances, nor would it be justified on thebasis of the priority to be accorded for civil defence purposes tothe Corps on the one hand and the Home Defence Force on theother.In discussion it was agreed that the future development of theHome Defence Force should be further considered by the Secretaryof State for Defence and that thereafter the Ministerial Committeereduction of some  277 million in these. This allowed  50 million for additional programmes, against which claims for  92 million,mainly in respect of additional housing investment and provision forchild poverty, still remained to be considered. The preparation ofthe estimates now made it urgent to take decisions on theCornmittee&apos;s proposals, set out in Annex C of their report, forcontaining the increase in public expenditure. It might be convenient to go through these proposals item by item.Defence The Secretary of State for Defence said that he would seek to achieve the proposed reduction of  50 million in expenditure in1967-68. It must, however, be recognised that this involved afurther cut in the already reduced rate of expenditure which hadbeen agreed in consequence of the Defence Review. Furthermore,unlike the proposals in respect of nearly all other Departments, it represented a reduction in the existing rate of expenditure and notin programmes which would, even after the reductions proposed,still provide for an increase on the expenditure for the current year.There were, moreover, serious practical difficulties in reducing expenditure quickly in a field like defence, in view of its relativeinflexibility.In discussion it was urged that in view of the damaging effectof the reductions which were proposed in other programmes thereshould on a balance of priorities be a yet further reduction in defence expenditure. It was, however, the general view that a further reduction would be impracticable in the coming year and that inany event reductions in defence expenditure could only be effectedas part of an orderly programme, carefully worked out over aperiod of time.
on Home Defence should consider how a total budget for civil defence of  22 million in 1967-68 could best be allocated.Meanwhile, the provision of that amount in the estimates was agreed.OtherOverseaServicesRoadsRailwaysDeficitThe Cabinet-(2) Approved the proposals of the Ministerial Committee on public Expenditure that civil defence expenditure,including the expenditure on the Home Defence Force,for 1967-68 should be limited to  22 million.(3) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the ministerial committee on Home Defence to consider, in the light ofthe discussion, how this expenditure should be allocated.The Foreign Secretary said that he accepted the reduction of 4-5 million proposed in the provision for oversea information,though what would amount to a further reduction could not beaccepted in consequence of any additional charges on this headthat might arise from any changes that might later be agreed on the vote for the Department of Education and Science, e.g., in respectof university fees which would affect students from overseas,including those assisted by grants from the United KingdomGovernment.In discussion it was urged that a reduction of this order wasunjustifiable having regard to the need for increased expenditureon information services to counter the effect on our influence of the prospective reduction of our defence commitments. It was, however,the general view that the reduction proposed should be accepted.The Cabinet (4) Approved the proposals of the Ministerial Committee on public Expenditure that expenditure on other overseaservices for 1967-68 should be limited to  108-9 million.The Minister of Transport said that she accepted the proposalfor a cut of  6-2 million in the expenditure proposed for theconstruction and maintenance of minor roads and car parks.In discussion it was emphasised that expenditure on roads, like that on defence, required to be planned several years ahead;without this it was impossible to achieve economy in the constructionof roads. A substantial part of the programme of major roads wasrelated to motorways, though the proportion devoted to urbanroads was increasing each year. So far as Scotland was concerned,the proposed reduction would affect important roads as well asminor ones within a development area.The Cabinet (5) Approved the proposals of the Ministerial Committee on public Expenditure to limit public expenditure on roadsto  497-2 million in 1967-68.The Minister of Transport said that the proposed reduction of 5 million in the railway deficit in 1967-68 could only be achieved by selective increases in charges, starting within the period of severe restraint.
In discussion it was pointed out that, whilst the railway deficit for the United Kingdom might be the lowest in Europe, it wasrising substantially each year; the loss of coal receipts might continueto be a substantial factor as natural gas replaced solid fuel. It wassuggested that the proposal that some of the new gas pipelinesmight be laid alongside railway tracks would be worth investigation.The Cabinet (6) Approved the proposal of the Ministerial Committee on public Expenditure that the prospective level ofexpenditure on the railways deficit should be reducedby  5 million in 1967-68.(7) Invited the Minister of Power and the Minister of transport to investigate the possibility of laying gas transmissionpipelines alongside railway tracks.Agreement was expressed with the Committee&apos;s proposals forthe limitation of public expenditure in 1967-68 in respect of farmstructure, ports, airports, other transport, assistance to industry,other agriculture and industrial research in respect of technology andatomic energy.The Cabinet (8) Noted that as a result of delay in the passage of the agriculture Bill, expenditure on farm structure in 1967-68would be  2-7 million less than was provided for in the basic public expenditure programme, and approvedproposals of the Ministerial Committee on public expenditure for the limitation of public expenditure in1967-68 as follows:  millionPorts        ...      ...      ......      ...     32-7Airports    ...............      24 other transport   ............     36-5Assistance to industry:Board of Trade............ 57-6Aviation        ............. 46-other agriculture ...      ......... 84-4Industrial research:Technology      ............ 32-0Atomic Energy Authority (sea)    ... 59-5Aviation and The Minister of Aviation said that he accepted a reduction of space  2. ^ rnillion, but the further reduction of  2-1 million proposed would entail the abandonment of the BLACK ARROW programme on space technology. He had already accepted a reduction of this programme from an estimated expenditure of  43-7 million to 26-5 million over eight years: its abolition would mean that wewould no longer be in a position to carry out any effective nationalAssistanceto Agricultureand Industry
work in space technology, nor effectively to support our commitments to international organisations such as the european space Research Organisation and the European launcher development Organisation. Nor should we retain the capacity to evaluate launcher techniques. This course might therefore entaildamaging consequences for us in a field of unknown potentiality.In discussion it was recalled that the Ministerial Committee on science and Technology had on balance agreed that the black arrow programme should in principle be carried out, on theground that we should retain a national capability in this sphere,subject to the consideration of the expenditure involved in the lightof other programmes of public expenditure in 1967-68. considerable doubt was, however, expressed about the justification for this expenditure in view of the reductions which were envisaged in other programmes.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion,said that it would be desirable for the Cabinet to have before them the range of considerations which had led the ministerial committee on Science and Technology to come to their view on theimportance of the BLACK ARROW programme. He would arrangefor the relevant papers to be circulated to the Cabinet and fordiscussion on this item of expenditure to be resumed after thediscussion of other items.The Cabinet (9) Agreed to resume consideration of expenditure as industrialtechnology (aviation) after discussing the remainingproposals of the Ministerial Committee on public expenditure.The Minister of Housing and Local Government said that hewas prepared to accept all the proposals of the Public expenditure committee, save for the suggestion that the introduction of the option mortgage scheme should be postponed from October 1967to 1st April, 1968, for new as well as for existing borrowers. TheCommittee proposed a total saving of  15 million on the optionmortgage subsidy, as compared with the figures in the basic programme. This was made up of:  7-5 million resulting fromthe inevitable delay in introducing the scheme, which could not now come into operation before October 1967;  4-1 million for the deferment from October 1967 to 1st April, 1968, of rights of existingborrowers to switch to option mortgages; and  3-4 million fordeferment from October 1967 to April 1968 of the introduction ofthe scheme for new borrowers. The introduction of the scheme hadalready been delayed because of the general election. A seconddelay could have unfortunate consequences, and could even lead anumber of potential house buyers to defer purchases, in the belief that better terms would be available later.In discussion it was argued that further deferment of theintroduction of the option mortgage scheme would reduce yetfurther the rate of private house building.   On the other hand it
was pointed out that those who entered into mortgages before theintroduction of the scheme would have the right to switch when thescheme came into operation. While it was desirable to have thescheme in operation without undue delay, there was no overridingreason for preferring October 1967 to April 1968 and there mightbe advantage from the point of view of confidence overseas in the deferment proposed.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion,said that on balance the Cabinet accepted the proposal of theChancellor of the Exchequer that the introduction of the optionmortgage subsidy should be deferred, for new as well as for existingborrowers, until 1st April, 1968. It would however be important,in order to avoid damaging effects upon the housing programme,publicly to emphasise by all appropriate means that those whoentered into mortgage commitments before 1st April, 1968, wouldbe able to switch to the option mortgage scheme, if they so desired,after that date, and need not therefore defer arrangements for buyinghouses on mortgage.The Cabinet (10) Agreed that the introduction of the option mortgagesubsidy scheme should be deferred until 1st April, 1968,for new as well as for existing borrowers.(11) Approved the proposals of the Ministerial Committee on public Expenditure that expenditure on housing subsidies and grants in 1967-68 should be limited to  220-8million.The Minister of Housing and Local Government said that unlessaction was taken now to increase approvals for public sector housing in 1967, it might well be that no more than 400,000 houses, or evenfewer, would be completed in Great Britain in 1968. In that event the chances of achieving the Governmenfs declared target of500,000 houses in 1970 could be seriously prejudiced. There was a danger that completions in 1968 would be less than in 1967, and very little higher than in 1964. It was expected that in 1967220,000 houses would be started in the public sector, and 180,000 inthe private sector. Current forecasts for the private sectorrepresented a serious decline from the levels of previous years,attributable largely to the inability of potential customers to getmortgages from the building societies. In order to offset the effects of this in 1968, he proposed that 15,000 approvals should be addedto the programmes for local authorities in England and Wales, and2,800 approvals should be added to the programme for new towns,in 1967-68.The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that the cabinet&apos;s approval had originally been given for 150,000 starts for localauthorities in England and Wales for 1966, and 155,000 in 1967.The Cabinet had subsequently authorised a further 11,000 approvalsin 1966, bringing the figure for that year up to 161,000. The Minister
of Housing was therefore proposing not only that the programme for 1967 should be higher by 5,000 approvals than the original programme in 1966, but further that an extra 15,000 approvalsshould now be added (apart from the additional approvals proposed for new towns). In his view this proposal rested on assumptions about private housing which took insufficient account of the volatilityof performance in this sector: though the number of starts in private housing had declined substantially, it could well revive at short notice if additional finance became available, and particularly ifinterest rates fell at all. Moreover it would be premature to take decisions to add to the public sector housing programme in advanceof a review of housing needs, which might suggest the need for some adjustment in the overall target of 500,000 houses in 1970, and inadvance of the review of longer-term priorities in public expenditure to which the Public Expenditure Committee would shortly beproceeding. It was arguable that, if a shortfall in private housingreleased resources which could be made available for public expenditure, they would be better employed on other programmesthan housing. Studies were now nearly completed showing thatthe cost to the Exchequer of a house in the public sector housing programme was approximately twice as great as that for a private house, after allowing for tax relief on mortgage interest, though there was no significant difference between the cost to the exchequer of a private house and a local authority house built for sale,provided that it was sold reasonably quickly.In discussion considerable support was expressed for the viewthat it would be difficult for.the Government to go back on the pledge to reach a total of 500,000 houses in 1970. The need forthis number was however under review interdepartmentally, taking account of local authority programmes for demolition and of varioussociological factors. There was some reason to think that localauthorities were demolishing houses which still had some years of useful life in them. It was hoped that this review would be completed by the end of the year. If as a result of that review it was decidedthat the target of 500,000 houses in 1970 should stand, the case foran immediate addition to the public sector housing programme would be considerably strengthened. It was suggested that in themeantime nothing should be done that would prejudice theprospect of achieving that target; but it was pointed out that decisions on the number of public sector approvals for 1967 neednot be taken yet. It was suggested that insufficient attention wasbeing given to the possibility of reducing the interval betweenapprovals and completions in the public sector housing programme.It was also suggested that on the basis of previous experience itmight be over-optimistic to expect an early revival in private housingstarts. One possibility in these circumstances might be to give greater encouragement to local authorities to build houses for sale.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion,said that he would call a meeting of a group of Ministers (MISC 113)to give further study to problems of the housing programme. Thegroup should have before them a memorandum showing the
Resumptionof Discussioncomparative cost to the Exchequer of houses built by local authoritiesand privately built houses. They should consider whether enoughwas being done to reduce the interval between approvals andcompletions of local authority houses. They should also seek toestablish a greater measure of agreement among the ministers concerned on the housing prospects for 1967 and 1968. In themeantime the Cabinet should take no decision on the proposal bythe Minister of Housing and Local Government for additions tothe public sector housing programme in 1967-68, a final decisionon which could be deferred for a time and taken in due course inthe light of the-longer-term review of housing needs and of thefurther study by the group of Ministers of housing prospects andforecasts. At this stage no provision should be made in the public expenditure programme for the additional approvals proposed bythe Minister of Housing and Local Government.The Cabinet (12) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for ameeting of a group of Ministers (MISC 113) to undertakefurther consideration of matters relevant to the housing programme, on the lines indicated in his summing up oftheir discussion and to report to the Cabinet in due course.(13) Agreed that for the present no additional provision shouldbe made for public sector housing investment in thepublic expenditure programme.The Cabinet (14) Agreed to resume their discussion of the public expenditure programme for 1967-68 at a subsequent meeting.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,15th November, 1966.


</content>
</cab>
