<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/26/43 images: 416-435</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENTSECRET.W.P. (42) 313(Also G.O.S. (42) 353)July 23, 1942Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND  key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war cabinet weekly RESUM](No. 151)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 July 16th, to0700 July 23rd,1942[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET. . Copy No.W.P. (42) 313(Also G.O.S. (42) 353)July 23, 1942TO BE KEPT  UNDER LOCK AND  key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 151)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 July 16th, to0700 July 23rd,1942[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.1. H.M.S. Welshman has landed stores at Malta. Naval forces havebombarded Mersa Matruh, and naval aircraft have been operating in the battlezone. A German U-boat has been sunk off Cape Finisterre. Snipping losses,which continue to be heavy, have occurred chiefly in the West Indies and caribbean.Northern Waters.2. It is now known that 21 ships were sunk in the outward bound convovto Russia and one is still unaccounted for.Horns Hy&amp;uBrs.3. Light craft engaged an enemy convoy off Cape Gris Nez on the 21stand one flak ship was set on fire and others damaged. The convoy turned, back and re-entered Boulogne.   One M.G.B. was lost.Enemy aircraft unsuccessfully attacked a tanker escorted by light craft inthe Channel and one F.W. 190 was destroyed by ML. 118 on the 17th.Mediterranean.4. H.M.S. Welshman arrived at Malta on the 16th with stores for thegarrison and civil population. She reports that she was first sighted at 1320on the second day out from Gibraltar and that twenty-eight planes in all attackedher. However, she suffered no damage, in. spite of several near misses and a bomb which exploded under her keel. H.M.S. Welshman sailed from Maltaat 1950 on the 18th. She was shadowed for eight hours the following day by enemy aircraft, and at 1415 a combined attack by five Ju. 88s and fifteen S.M. 79torpedo bombers was carried out. The ship sustained two very near misses fromone bomber and one miss close ahead by torpedo. There was no casualty nordamage affecting steaming.   Welshman arrived Gibraltar on the 20th.The enemy are now making use of Tobruk and Mersa Matruh, as well asBenghazi, for seaborne supplies.The shipping and harbour at Mersa Matruh were bombarded by H.M.Destroyers Dulverton, Hurivorth, Eridge and Beaufort on the nights of 17th, 18thand the following night. -H.M. Cruisers Dido and Euryalus and four destroyers also bombardedMersa Matruh on the night of 19th/20th. An E-boat sweep by H.M. DestroyersDulverton and Aldenham. was carried out and two E-boats were driven off.The Suez Canal was open to restricted traffic during the week.. Naval Albacores from Alexandria have continued to maintain their maximum scale of night bombing, the targets attacked include enemy motor transport in various sectors of the battle area and enemy shipping at mersa matruh. Spotting for the bombardment by FI.M. Ships of the harbour and shipping at Mersa Matiuih was carried out.On the 21st, H.M. Aircraft-Carrier Eagle, escorted by two cruisers and three destroyers, flew off 29 Spitfires, 28 of which arrived Malta : one crashed on takingoff. Naval aircraft from H.M.S. Eagle provided reconnaissance and fighterprotection for the squadron and cover for the Spitfires when taking off.Albacores and Swordfish from Malta were in operation during the weekagainst enemy vessels and on reconnaissance over Italian ports.During the week 20,847 tons of French merchant shipping passed Gibraltarwestward and 38,464 tons passed eastward under escort.Pacific.5. Three Japanese destroyers are reported sunk in the Aleutian Islands by .S.A. forces.Anti-Submarine Operations.6. A German U-Boat was destroyed by a Lancaster and a Whitley aircraft on the 17th north-west of Cape Finisterre.Twenty-seven other attacks have been reported during the week, 16 by aircraft and 11 by surface craft.  A promising attack was made by H.M. Sloops
Goiieston and Wellington. In none of these cases was there definite evidenceof destruction. Of these attacks, twelve took place off the North American coast,eleven in the West Indies and Caribbean, three north of the Azores and one offthe Shetlands. Nineteen of the attacks were carried out by U.S.A. forces. AU-Boat was shelled by a shore battery in the Bay of Fundy.Enemy Intelligence.German.7. Tirpitz, Scheer and Hipper are still in the Narvik area and the pocketbattleship Lutzoiu, with the light cruiser Koln, are at Trondheim.Italian.There has been little convoy traffic between Italy and North Africa in thecourse of the past week, but there are indications of a resumption of this traffic on a large scale in the very near future.Japanese.On the 4th July a convoy arrived in the Solomon Islands and since that dateJapanese preparations in that area have been advancing rapidly, particularly onGuadal canal island where wharves have been built and an aerodrome is being prepared. The Japanese are carrying out daily air reconnaissance of Nauruand Ocean Island and the Gilbert Group.U-Boats.. There are about 70 U-boats operating in the Atlantic and there has been an increase in attacks on convoys. There is considerable activity roundTrinidad, three or four are off Key West, seven German and three Italian havebeen working between Bermuda and the Bahamas, and some in the St. LawrenceRiver. U-boats have also reappeared in the Freetown area. Japanese U-boatshave been active off the S.E. coast of Australia. -Protection of Seaborne Trade.8. During the week ending midnight 19th/20th 1,095 ships, including283 Allied and 18 neutral have been convoyed. Of these 234 ships were in oceanconvoys and 861 in British coastal convoys. One anti-aircraft ship, 55 destroyers-(including two U.S.A. destroyers), and 78 sloops, cutters and corvettes were employed on escort duty.Imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy during the week ending the 18th July totalled 362,500 tons, compared with 961,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average of 621,000 tons for&apos; the past ten weeks. Ofthe week&apos;s imports 73,000 tons were oil of various grades.Imports into the United Kingdom during June totalled 2,131,100 tons,including 40,500 tons from Eire.Imports under the Ministry of Food programme were : grain and pulses567,800 tons; fodder 200 tons; meat 120,100 tons; oilseeds, nuts and fats 178.200tons; sugar 56,300 tons; dairy produce 45,100 tons; fruit and vegetables 27,300tons; fish 23,200 tons; tea, coffee and cocoa 14,400 tons; miscellaneous foods,13,300Tbeer, wines and spirits 700 tons; total (including 36,600 tons from Eire).1,083,200 tons.Imports under the Ministry of Supply programme were: iron and alliedmetals 421,900 tons; non-ferrous metals 84,600 tons; timber 121,900 tons; textiles145,200 tons; paper and pulp 68,400 tons; acid and fertiliser materials 46,800 tons;miscellaneous 81,200; total 970,000 tons.Imports under the Board of Trade programme were: tobacco 8,700 tons;aircraft 1,300 tons; other vehicles 9,300 tons; machine tools 1,200 tons; othermachinery 5,400 tons; miscellaneous 48,100; total (including 3,900 tons from Eire)77,900 tons.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.9. U-Boats attacked a southbound convoy off the Azores, one ship beingsunk and another torpedoed; also an eastbound U.S.A. convoy off Bermuda,from which one ship was sunk.
oMILITARY SITUATION.Egypt.General.14. In the Northern Sector our successful attack on the Tel El Eisa ridgeembarrassed the enemy considerably. The enemy counter attacked, and for atime succeeded in driving us back from the Ridge, but we eventually occupied thewhole feature, and extended the scope of our attack to the South.In the Central Sector, on the Ruweisat Ridge, the enemy made unsuccessfulefforts to drive us to the east.Most of the week&apos;s activity was in the Northern and Central Sectors inthe vicinity of these two features.In the Southern Sector, our patrols were active and our forces maintainedcontact with the enemy on the general line El Qattara-El Taqa plateau.Late on the 21st July we attacked in the Central Sector with our armourfollowing up the attack, and the next day we attacked along the whole front, withour main effort in the Central Sector. No complete picture of these attacks isyet available.Daily Narrative.15. l$th July. A counter-attack by our forces early in the day in theNorthern Sector recaptured the whole of the Tel El Eisa feature, taking betweenIn addition reports have been received of U-Boat attacks on 11 ships, seven of which were sunk.   Six of these occurred in the West Indies and Caribbeanone off Bermuda, one off Freetown and three in Australian waters near Sydney&apos;One ship was attacked by a surface raider in the Indian Ocean, 1,500 miles west of Fremantle.  ...Aircraft attacked an East Coast convoy on the 19th and also shipping [nthe Channel on the 17th.British Minelaying.10.   Aircraft laid mines off the Dutch coast and in the Bay of Biscay area.Enemy Minelaying&quot; and British Mines weeping.11. Enemy aircraft laid mines on one night of the week between Ramsgateand Great Yarmouth. Surface craft laid mines off the French coast, off theNeedles Channel, and off Worthing. 60 magnetic and four acoustic mines havebeen destroyed during the week.The mine totals (including those in foreign waters) are 2,501 magnetic;1,315 acoustic, and 1,444 moored.Mines have been reported off Alexandria, Cyprus and Cape HatterasTJ.S.A.Enemy Merchant Shipping.12. One German and two Swedish ships totalling 4,102 tons are reportedmined in the Sound and two Swedish ships, totalling 7,082 tons, mined in the heligoland Bight.A German tanker of the &apos;&apos; Altmark &apos;&apos; class sailed from Nantes between the26th June and the 7th July, and has not been located in any of the other biscay ports.  She may be acting as a supply ship to submarines or as a raider.Shipments of iron ore from Bilbao and neighbouring ports to Bayonne andBordeaux which had been continually increasing were lower in June. The fleet of small motor and sailing ships employed in this traffic now consists of elevenDutch and twelve French.vichy Merchant Shipping.13. During the first six months of the year 202 Vichy ships totalling630,849 tons passed through the Straits of Gibraltar eastbound, and 192 ships of616,967 tons passed through the Straits westbound. The bulk of this traffic is engaged in trading between France, French Morocco and French West Africa,and is under Vichy naval escort the whole time it is outside the Mediterranean.
200 and 300 prisoners. Heavy enemy bombing attacks and shell-fire, however,enforced our withdrawal from the southern knoll. In the -evening our forcesthrust southwards and secured the low ridge Tel El Makhkhad (about 8 miles west of El Alamein) and then pushed on to capture Sanyet El Miteiriya (4 milesfurther south). In the Central Sector the enemy launched two attacks&quot; supportedby tanks, in the course of the clay, near the western end of the Ruweisat Ridge.Both of these were repulsed and at last light the enemy force was seen to beretiring westwards. It is claimed that 25 enemy tanks were destroyed during theday&apos;s fighting. Towards evening in the Southern Sector patrols &quot;of our mobileforces were pushing out to the west.16. 17th July. After counter-attacks by enemy infantry and tanks our forces withdrew from the positions they had gained at Sanyet El Miteiriya andconsolidated their positions at Tel El Makhkhad. The enemy delivered two further attacks with infantry against the Ruweisat Ridge during the day. on each occasion the attacking troops came under heavy fire from our artillery andwere repulsed. In the Southern Sector our forces advanced westwards and werein contact with the enemy on the general line El Qattara-El Taqa plateau.17. 18th July. Indian troops advanced westwards along the RuweisatEidge and though counter-attacked by enemy forces including tanks, were able tomaintain their positions.   Patrols were very active.18. 19th july. There was little change in the general situation. some slight progress was made in the Tel El Eisa area and in the south a column ofour troops were indecisively engaged with the enemy on the eastern edge of theElTaqa plateau.19. 20th July. The day was on the whole quiet. The enemy appeared tobe on the defensive. The only change in the general line of the front was to thesouth of El Alamein where our forces made a slight local advance. Patrolactivity continues.20. 21st july.- The day was generally quiet until the evening. During the night our armoured car patrols operated westwards of the positions held by the1st South African Division but found little to report. At last light we advanced in the Central Sector with the object of securing the general line of the easternedge of the Deir El Chein depression to point 63 at the western end of theRuweisat Ridge, and thence south. Our armour followed up this advance to meet any enemy counter-attack which might be forthcoming. To assist this attacka small subsidiary attack to the north of the Ruweisat Ridge was mounted by the1st South African Division. To the south an attack was put in on the Taqaplateau.21. 22nd July. In the Northern Sector. Australian infantry with tank sup-port made important gains at Tel El Eisa and to the south of Tel El Makhkhad.In the Central Sector,- our infantry reached their objectives everywhere,although casualties were high and in some instances severe. One armoured force,which advanced through the infantry, was brought to a halt and had later towithdraw. A second armoured force after being held up by minefields was again advancing in the evening.In the south, pressure was maintained and some advance made.22. Italian Forces. During the last week the Italians have suffered heavy casualties in prisoners, more especially in the area west of Alamein. They havenot fought well, and have not only allowed themselves to be captured, but also on more than one occasion, their guns with them.The Russo-German Campaign.(An outline map showing operations in Russia is enclosed in this Resume)Central Sector.23. It is probable that the Germans have now eliminated the salient whidhhad been held by the Russians for many months in the areas south-west of Rzhev.Mopping-up operations may be continuing there. Russian pressure north and north-east of Orel appears to have ceased.
Southern Sector.24. In the Voronezh area the initiative has passed to the Russians, who arelaunching heavy attacks against the bridgehead thrown by the Germans acrossthe Upper Don at that point. The Russians may have had some success but theGermans still retain one bridgehead. South of Voronezh the Germans appear tobe in possession of the western bank of the Upper Don as far as Bogucbar.South of Boguchar they have thrust south-east towards, the Lower Don, whichthey.have probably reached east of the River Donets. West of the Donets,in thie area between that River and the railway Kamensk-Rostov, the germans have thrust directly southward, doubtless with the intention of moving on Rostovfrom the north-east and the north. They claim also to have launched a comple-mentary attack on Rostov from Taganrog, but so far this appears to have been only a holding operation.Caucasia.25. The Germans have extended their bombing of Caucasian ports south-ward; and a combined operation against Caucasia is still to be considered possible.Summary.26. The Russians are trying hard to expel the Germans from the onlybridgehead still remaining over the Upper Don namely, at Voronezh. TheGerman thrust south-eastwards towards the Lower Don has placed the russian forces in great danger of encirclement west of Millerovo. They appear, however,to have succeeded in extricating themselves to some extent. Equally, the Germanthrust southward on Rostov threatens with encirclement the Russian forces southand west of the Donets. There are indications, however, that they are being withdrawn, but Rostov itself is seriously threatened by the German concentricattacks.Far East.South-West Pacific Area:27. The Allied forces in the New Guinea area have been reinforced by an australian infantry brigade.Various islands in the Eastern Netherlands East Indies have now beengarrisoned by Australian and Dutch units in order to maintain and re-establishjDutch sovereignty.South Pacific Area.28. The American military authorities formally took over operationalcommand in Fiji from the New Zealand forces stationed there, on the 18th July.AIR SITUATION.General.29. Bomber Command aircraft made a heavy and successful attack onDuisburg.Six power stations in northern France were damaged by Bostons.Our aircraft in Egypt continued to give close and effective support to our land forces, and inflicted heavy losses on the enemy.Successful attacks were again made on enemy shipping in the Mediterranean.United Kingdom.30.   Fighter Command flew 735 defensive sorties by day, and 245 by night.There was an increase in enemy activity against this country. Fifty-fiveaircraft flew overland compared with 35 last week. Three were destroyed andtwo were damaged by night fighters.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.31. Fighter, and Bomber Commands despatched 624 and 136 sorties respectively, compared with 1,185 and, 89 last week.
A total of 83 bombers was despatched against targets in North-west germany, the largest single operation being an attack by Stirlings on theFlenderwerk shipyard at Lubeck where, despite bad. weather conditions, threehits are claimed on the submarine slipways and thirteen in the Dockyard. other targets attacked were Essen, Wesel, Emden, Bremen, Duisburg and Osnabruckbut no outstanding results are reported.In Northern France and Belgium, a number of power stations were attacked by Bostons operating in pairs. Six of these attacks, which were carried out from about 100 feet, appear to have been particularly successful, namely atPont a Vendin, Choeques, Mazingarbe, Lille (Sequedin), Langerbrugge and nearBethune, and it is probable that in each case severe damage was done to essentialequipment.Our fighters over Northern France were mainly engaged in harassingoperations in which Mustangs of Army Co-operation Command also participated.Our losses during the week were eight bombers, three Mustangs and nineSpitfires of which three pilots are safe. One enemy fighter was destroyed, threewere probably destroyed and four were damaged.Night.32. Bomber Command aircraft operated on two nights, against Duisburgand Vegesack respectively. Against the former, about 300 aircraft were despatched and the attack was carried out in favourable weather conditions and,with the help of flares, the target was clearly identified. About 400 tons of H.E.(which included 63 x 4,000 lbs. and 137 x 2,000 lbs.) and 150 tons of incendiaries were dropped, and later arrivals reported large fires spread over the town and the dock area.At Vegesack, where the objective was the naval shipbuilding yards, conditions were considerably less favourable and heavy cloud was encountered over the target area. About.240 tons of H.E. and incendiaries were dropped, but, apart from afew fires, no results could be observed.From these operations, 16 of our bombers are missing.Intruder operations by Fighter Command aircraft were on a small .scale anduneventful.Coastal Operations.33. Coastal Command flew 404 sorties, of which 33 were on convoy escort.Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Command involved 895 sorties.Very little enemy shipping was sighted during the week and no sinkingsare claimed.Hurricane bombers damaged a 1,000-ton vessel off the Brest peninsula. Offthe Cherbourg peninsula, a small merchant vessel was set on fire and two flak ships were damaged.Interceptions off our coasts resulted in three enemy aircraft being destroyed and five damaged.Sixty-six sea mines Were laid in enemy waters by aircraft of Bomber. Command.Mediterranean.Egypt and Libya.34. Although hampered by dust storms, our air operations were again ona large scale. In the week ending the 20th July, 3,373 sorties were flown hy our aircraft, compared with 3,297 in the previous week.Enemy landing grounds, M.T., tanks and other military targets werecontinuously attacked by light bombers and fighter bombers by day, and by wellingtons and Naval Albacores &quot;by night. Considerable damage was caused to aircraft on the ground and to tanks and motor vehicles.Two daylight attacks by Bostons and Kittyhawks, and one night attack by wellingtons and Naval Albacores on landing grounds in the Fuka and El Dabaareas were particularly effective. Of the 160 aircraft on the landing grounds,about 70 were either destroyed or damaged. During one of these attacksfour Ju. 52s (troop-carrying aircraft) and one Ju. 87 about to land were shot down by fighter bombers.    i
Our fighters carried out a large number of reconnaissances and offensive patrols. Several enemy formations were intercepted. One of these, consistingof thirty Ju. 87s escorted by twenty Me. 109s, was forced to jettison its bombs. bFive night attacks by a total of 180 Wellingtons, 19 Halifax and threeU.S.A. Fortresses, and two daylight attacks by 19 Liberators were made onTobruk. Two merchant vessels, one of 10,000 tons, were hit and two others anda tanker were set on fire. Large fires were started in the dock area and near alarge M.T. concentration. Other Wellingtons laid mines in Tobruk and mersa matruh harbours.In the three weeks ending the 22nd July, about 1,300. tons of bombs were dropped on Tobruk.Liberators, Naval Albacores and U.S.A. Fortresses bombed shipping atBomba, Bardia and Mersa Matruh.Enemy aircraft were more active&apos; during the past week. The bombereffort was directed mainly against battery positions, tanks and mechanical transport in the El Alamein area. Little bombing of targets in the back area was attempted, and no bombing or minelaying operations were reported either at Alexandria or in the Canal Zone.In all these operations our fighters destroyed 19 enemy aircraft, probably destroyed ten and damaged 30.   We lost 32 aircraft but two pilots are safe.Malta.35. Enemy activity against the Island was on a much smaller scale. About50 bombers escorted by 150 fighters attacked, compared with 130 and 260respectively last week.The main target was Luqa Aerodrome where three aircraft were damagedon the ground.Our fighters destroyed eight enemy aircraft, probably destroyed three and damaged six. A.A. guns destroyed a further three. We lost five Spitfires, but three pilots are safe.A further carrier-borne reinforcement of 28 Spitfires reached Malta onthe 21st.&apos;Crete.36. Liberators bombed shipping in Suda Bay. Fires were started on thepier and on two medium-sized ships, and a near miss was made on a large ship.Heraklion harbour was also bombed.Sea Communications..37. A 7,000-ton merchant vessel accompanied by two destroyers was attacked south of Corfu by Beaufort &apos;s escorted by Beaufighters. Three hitswith torpedoes are claimed on the merchant vessel and one of the destroyerswas probably hit.A small tanker, two schooners and three barges escorted by two aircraft were attacked by Beaufighters off Sidi Barrani. Two barges were set on fire,the tanker was damaged and one of the enemy aircraft was destroyed.Beauforts made torpedo attacks on a 6,000-ton merchant vessel in SollumBay and later off Mersa Matruh, but results were not observed.Near misses were made by a Maryland on two vessels of 3,000 and 6,000 tonsnorth-west of Tobruk, and by a naval Swordfish on an E-boat west of mersa matruh.A large number of reconnaissances were flown of aerodromes and harboursin Sicily, Sardinia and Southern Italy and of Italian and North African waters.Russia.. 38. The main area of German air operations has moved southwards insupport of the army between the Don and the Donets.. Bombing attacks havebeen made on troops retiring across the Don and in the Rostov area, and againstcommunications. Attacks on Black Sea ports have continued, and are reportedto have extended as far south as Poti, 35 miles north of Batum.Bombing has been resumed in the Murmansk district.
Burma.39. Seven small-scale attacks were made on targets in Akyab and itsvicinity. . Bombs were also dropped on Kalewa (twice), on three places in theMyittha valley, and on river craft on the Mayu and Kaladan rivers. TwoELS.A. bombers attacked the aerodrome at Myitkyina, where hits were madeon the runway and storehouses.R.A.F. and U.S.A. aircraft dropped supplies on two occasions for chinese troops in the Shingbwiyang area; in the latter part of the week these operations were suspended owing to monsoon conditions.Pacific Zone.40. On the 21st, an enemy force consisting of four transports and four destroyers off Buna (New Guinea) was attacked by five U.S.A. bombers. Onetransport was hit. During the following night, enemy landings took place and15 attacks comprising 57 sorties were made by U.S.A. aircraft. One transportof about 9,000 tons is believed sunk, a barge was sunk, a destroyer was hit anda float plane was probably destroyed.Five U.S.A. Fortresses attacked and caused considerable damage at Rabaul,and single U.S.A. aircraft bombed Salamoa and Kieta aerodrome (BougainvilleIsland).A Fortress reconnoitring the Tulagi area was attacked by three float planes,two of which it destroyed.   An enemy fighter was destroyed by a Hudson.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.By Day.41. The only serious damage suffered during the week was at the works of the Hoffman Manufacturing Company at Chelmsford on the 19th, whereworkshops were hit and extensive damage was done to roofs by blast. At thesame time minor damage was done to Marconi&apos;s Wireless Telegraph Company&apos;sworks.On the 17th a few bombs were dropped at Brixham about noon and latersome fell at Dagenham. Only slight damage was done at each place. On the18th eight people were killed and several houses damaged at Littlehampton;slight damage was done near Ventnor on the 21st, and Brighton pier extensionwas damaged by bombs on the 22nd.By Night.42. On the 21st/22nd a few bombs were dropped in Lincolnshire, Norfolkand Suffolk. Only minor damage was done and there were no casualties. Onthe 22nd/23rd eleven people were killed and houses damaged at Cromer.Casualties.43. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 hours the22nd July are 17 killed and 26 seriously injured.
APPENDICES I, II and III, will be published monthly.APPENDIX IV.Enemy Shipping Losses as assessed to 30th June, 1942, wereNationality.	Sank, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously Damaged.		Damaged.		Total.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross    I ^ Tons.    !*0&apos;		Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German    ...       ... Italian Other enemy shij,s and ships useful to enemy Total    ...	433 472 141	1,822,606 1,968,684 248,649	136 89 18	364,078 429,735 46,246	245 92 18	775,283 461,484 61,916	814 i 2,961,967 653 1 2,859,903 1771    356,811		1,046	4,039,939	243	840,059	355	1,298,683	1,644	6,178,681The table does not include losses inflicted on the enemy by our russian allies, which are estimated at about 752,000 gross tons sunk ; nor does it include losses inflicted on Japanese shipping in the Far East and Pacific, which, up to30th June, are estimated to number 95 ships sunk or about 380,000 gross tons.In addition there is about 256,000 gross tons of Axis shipping which hasbeen taken over by South American countries.APPENDIX V.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.17th. MX. 157 damaged by aircraft in the Channel. 1st-M.G.B. 328 sunk in Dover Straits.21st. M.G.B. 322 and 601 damaged in Dover Straits.The following casualties to Naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 6 killed, 9 missing, 8 wounded.Ratings: 23 killed, 19 missing, 19 wounded.
Provisional operational aircraft battle casualties for the period: dawn, Thursday,16th July, to dawn, Thursday, 23rd July, 1942.British.Bombers...Fighters ...     ....Coastal   ...Army Co-operation total enemy.BombersFightersMiscellaneousTotalMetropolitan Area.In the Air....       ... 2412&apos; ..;    ...       42423 pilots are safe.Destroyed.42ProbablyDestroyed.12On the Ground.Damaged.5712British.I Bombersj FightersOthersMiddle East (including Malta).In the Air.12331On the Ground-Total      ......       ...... 464 out of 6 of a bomber crew and 1 crew and 8 pilots of fighters are safe.Enemy.Bombers  ...fighter miscellaneous destroyed.13154ProbablyDestroyed59Total    ...      ...        32 14Of the above total 3 were destroyed by A.A.Damaged.926136Far East.British and Allied..  BombersFighters   ...OthersTotalEnemy.Bombers  ...       ...Fighters   ...MiscellaneousTotalIn the Air.NilOn the Ground.Destroyed.12ProbablyDestroyed.nil damaged.,Notbs. (a) No account is taken of enemy aircraft destroyed on the ground in any theatre.(b) No account is taken of British Naval aircraft casualties.
APPENDIX YII.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week :-Wilhelmshaven. Photographs taken on the 13th July after the attack onthe 10th are of poor quality and were not taken for purposes of damage assess-ment.  Nevertheless, the following more severe items of damage can be seen : (i) On the north side of the Tirpitz Hafen the engineering workshop andthe smithery of Deutsche Werke have been severely damaged,(ii) On the west side of the Bauhafen, the armour-plate shop and four other buildings in the Marine Werf t are gutted,(iii) On the east side of the Bauhafen, six or seven large sheds, probably shipstores and workshops, are gutted, and there is damage to three otherson the north side of the Strombau Hafeh.Paris. At the Lorraine Dietrich Works 200 engines for fast motor-boats and 52 airplane engines were completely destroyed. An indication of the effectof the attacks in the Paris suburbs has been received in that the Berliet automobileworks now stops work at 2200 hours, the night shift having been cancelled andthe A.R.P. strengthened.Juvincourt. As a result of the attack on the 30th/31st May three hangarsin the aerodrome, one containing aircraft and the others equipment and stores,were destroyed. During the attack on the 1st/&apos;2nd June several direct hits were obtained on the runways.







</content>
</cab>
