<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/74/0 images: 18-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUlviENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JESTY JS GOVERNMENTSEC PETCj(55) 52 COPY NO.21st February, 1955CABINETRATING AND VALUATIONMemorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerUnder the Local Government Act, 1948 a new valuation  or ratingwas to come into force in April, 1952 and quinquennially thereafter,,    Thisvaluation was postponed to 1953 because the work was not complete.    then it was postponed to 1955 because the basis for valuing houses was not work-ing satisfactorily, and then it was postponed until April, 1956, the reasongiven in Parliament being that new legislation was necessary to deal withthe nationalised Gas Board and for improvements in the machinery.    Thisis the legislation which is in the programme for this sessionQ20        If the legislation were to be postponed, the new valuations would bepublished in October, 1955, unless a further order postponing the introductionof the new valuations, were made0    It would therefore almost certainly benecessary to-make such an order.3.        There are two main reasons for regarding a further postponementas most unfortunateo(i)     The Inland Revenue, who have to make the new revaluation,also have the task bf amending the current valuation lists.These lists in law should be on the basis of present-dayletting values.    But the current valuation lists date back tothe 1934 revaluation, and there is a marked disparity between that valuation and current valuesD    In cases where new valuaations have had to be fixed (new and altered properties) the inland H.evenue felt that it was necessary to avoid disparity and made current valuations broadly on the 1934 basis.    Thiswas at first agreed by Local Authorities, but recently theyhave become increasingly restive.    Liverpool and Sheffieldhave made their own valuations for the central business areas and put them forward for rating purposes as they are entitledto doc    Other large cities are likely to follow suit.    Theposition is rapidly approaching at which, if the new lists arenot introduced, the Inland Revenue will either have to makecurrent valuations on a markedly different basis from theexisting valuations, or be shown with increasing clearnessnot to-be observing the law.    In fact, if the Inland Revenue donot have the new basis they may well have to seek statutorycover for their present practice which would raise just asmuch controversy, if not much more, than the Bill now inthe programme.

(ii)   A second reason for proceeding with the Bill is that thedistribution of the Exchequer equalisation grant, which depends on average rateable value per head, is heavily andunfairly distorted.    This is becuase widely varying levels of assessment were adopted by Local Authorities on thelast revaluation in 1934.    Birmingham, who adopted a lowbasis of valuation, are receiving a large Exchequer granton the basis that the lowness of the valuation indicates theirneed, whereas Liverpool and other towns in the North ofEngland, who valued at more realistic levels,, are gettingpractically nothing at all, on the grounds that the level of the valuation suggests they have no need.    As between birmingham and Liverpool the contrary position is the equitable one.4.        The programme under the new Bill is so arranged that the newvalues are not disclosed until April, 1956 when new rate demands are made.,and therefore the ratepayer will not see his increase of valuation until hesees it in conjunction with the reduction of poundages which would naturallyaccompany an increase of total valuations05.        I have all along seen the advantage of the wider room for manoeuvrewhich would be given by introducing a fresh order further to postpone thevaluations.    But, in view of the course of action already pursued by theGovernment, and of the arguments above, I have regretfully come to theconclusion that to postpone the valuations might intensify trouble, ratherthan clear the ground.R.A0B.Treasury Chambers, S. W. le19th February,19550

</content>
</cab>
