<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/74/0 images: 1-2</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 *1&lt;~JcJCi ZiJsl (*h~) m\\\mBTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT ^kmW^L\W -itiii&apos; Printed for the Cabinet*-  February 1955       &lt;**&apos; J| BBHWW}  I CONFIDENTIAL,^!&apos;.ffe^-r -i^u Copy&apos;** 31ABB 2/February, 1955   $$4 ^L\mm\^fl CABINETANGLO-INDIAN RELATIONSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations^^fl   I I think my colleagues may be interested to see the letter below from our^L\w High Commissioner in Delhi, which throws a very revealing light on Mr. Nehru. BBBi SWINTON.^^B  I Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,fffM 18th February, 1955. -Vfli February 11th, 1955.One of the distressing points about the resignation of T. T. Krishnamachari BB_|^^fl        I [as Minister of Commerce and Industry] is that it takes away one of the very fewpeople who are prepared to stand up to Nehru when they think he is going off^^fl the rails. It has been clear for some time that we can no longer count on 3333m^L-U Deshmukh [Minister of Finance] to do this effectively, and I am afraid that [the ^^B^^B  fl death of] Kidwai will also be a serious loss from this standpoint. In fact the Cabinetw333M looks like degenerating more and more into a collection of &quot; Yes-men,&quot; and if BBB^^B T.T.K.&apos;s successor, as is commonly expected, is chosen from the ranks of &quot; safe &quot;^Hf party men, I fear that the immediate outlook for United Kingdom economic ^^B33333 interests may not be too rosy.^k-M Incidentally, T.T.K. in his recent talk with me was very revealing about Nehru.B He has the greatest admiration for Nehru and thinks that both India and the W333M33333 United Kingdom must consider themselves very fortunate to have had him here BBB^L-W at this difficult time.  He has watched him grow in stature year by year, and^k-W  3M everyone, whether agreeing with his policies or not, would now admit that he is a33333 big man.  But in consolidating his hold on the affections of the Indian masses, BBB^^B and in gaining increased confidence thereby, he has grown increasingly touchy^^B   H and sensitive, and impatient of opposition.  It is thus no use now attempting to33333 oppose him in the Cabinet or to put a different point of view to his own; he just BBH^^B shouts one down and none of the other Ministers dare intervene. Accordingly he^^BJ H (T.T.K.) had developed an alternative technique; this was to get hold of Nehru33333 for a few minutes on the day before the Cabinet meeting and give him a very^^B brief note of the main points of importance, while leaving it of course to his^^B| judgment to decide on the best line of action.   This technique had on many33333 occasions worked like a charm, Nehru accepting T.T.K.&apos;s points and developing^^B them far more effectively than T.T.K. could have done himself.  But of course^^B this technique could not always be relied upon, and when Nehru clearly took am\mm\   mm wrong line the only hope, in default of reasonable discussion in the Cabinet, was^^B to have matters out with him privately and alone. On such occasions he was often BBB^^B surprisingly humble and was always prepared to hear the other side; the importantBBB thing was that he must never be opposed before other people.
Continuing, T.T.K. said that Nehru had iniiriense charm and magnetism and mwas at times quite irresistible. But he had one very marked personal defect, namely,that he was &quot; incapable of love.&quot;  By this, T.T.K. meant that, though he hadX t&quot; at;deep affection for his daughter and his grand-children, he had precious little for^^^fl anyone else and he was quite incapable of entering into the thorigJro/ieiftfB^Mct^^^h personal problems of other people. In other words all the affection, revejehqe ahd&quot;admiration which flowed to him was in effect a one-way traffic, and this was &quot;a real^^^fl tragedy as it made him a lonely man, set a limit to his personal contacts and^^^H sometimes distorted his judgment.^^^h 1 think there is a lot of truth in this comment.As T reported in my telegram No. 126, T.T.K. was very scathing aboutDeshmukh, whom he evidently now regards as a broken reed.  On the managing^^^h agencies, he thinks that there may still be time for some improvement to be madein the Select Committee&apos;s proposals.  I told him that the Chancellor would bespeaking to Nehru in London on this subject, and he threw out a hint that it mightbe quite helpful if the President of the Associated Chambers of Commerce^^^h [Mackinlay] were to follow this up by direct representations to Nehru on his^^^H return (I have passed on this hint to Mackinlay).  In general he thought that^^^H his resignation might do some good, if only in making the Government realisethe need for caution; and he felt, too, that once he was out of the way Nehru^^^H and Deshmukh might find it easier to make concessions to private enterprise thanthey would do if he was still in office (when such concessions would be representedas a victory for his point of view).He said finally that he wanted to warn me also about the role now beingplayed by the Central Statistical Institute, which had now become a passion ofNehru&apos;s. In his view the Institute was a very dangerous body and wanted careful^^^H watching.  It was largely composed of people from behind the iron curtain, and^^^H was in fact a nest of Reds. The head man (Mahalanobis) was a charlatan, but he ^^^1^^^H had underneath him two men of undoubted brilliance; both had Russian affilia-^^^H tions and one never knew what they were planning and advising. There was also ^^^b^^^H a Cambridge man called Goodwin.^^^H I am making some enquiries about the Institute and shall be writing further ^^^b^^^H as to this. T.T.K. also complained about the visits of Left-wing economists fromthe United Kingdom (we have just had Balogh in Delhi, and Joan Robinson ishere now) and asked whether we could not get out some sensible middle-of-the-road^^^H man to supply a corrective. We will think about this too.^^mt PA. CLUTTERBUCK.I - &apos; \|. I^^^^^^B ^^^^^^

</content>
</cab>
