<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/74/0 images: 85-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mMIDDLE EAST DEFENCE:   THE TURCO-IRAQIAGREEMENT AND REVISION OF THEANGLO-IRAQI TREATY OF 1930Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs as ray colleagues know, Turkey and Iraq signed a Pact of mutual Co-operation for defence, of which the text is annexed, (Annex I),on 24th February.    It has since been ratified by the Turkish and IraqiParliaments,,    The Pact is open to accession by any other State activelyconcerned with peace and security in the Middle East region,,    The IraqiPrime Minister has expressed the hope that the United Kingdom will accedeas soon as possible,,    I believe that it is in our best interest to do so.    i therefore seek the consent of my colleagues to open negotiations to thisend,2. Ever since the Iraqi Prime Minister, Nuri Said, first informed us last year of his intention to conclude with his neighbours a Treaty for mutual defence, we have encouraged him in his efforts.   It has been our care to ensure that this Treaty should provide first, a framework for futuredefence co-operation between the Western Powers and the countries of theMiddle East;  and secondly, an instrument which will enable us to replace the existing Anglo-Iraqi Treaty of 1930, which expires in 1957, by a new defence agreement more acceptable to public opinion in Iraq,,    With the useof modern weapons the whole Middle East including the Persian Gulf requires to be defended on the frontiers of Iraq.    This can only be done in co-operation with local forces.    Since we can no longer expect to keep armed forces in Middle Eastern countries under the old system of unilateral Treatyrights, we have to work out this co-operation on a new basis0     Thefacilities which we can obtain on this basis in Iraq are therefore a vital part,of Middle East defence,,Turco-Iraoi Pacti.......i   ii   i    a,      ii-     i3. Article 1 of the Pact provides for the co-operation of theParties for their security and defence, and for special agreements betweenthem to give effect to this co-operation, thus affording us an &quot;umbrella&quot; underwhich we. can negotiate a new defence agreement with Iraq.    Article 5provides that the Pact shall be open for the accession of other States andthat any acceding S^irse may conclude special agreements under Article 1with one or more of the Parties.    Article 6 provides for a permanentcouncil of ministers to be set up when at least four powers become Partiesto the Pact, and thus form the nucleus of what may later develop into a defence organisation for the Middle East.    At the time of signature theTurkish and Iraqi Prime Ministers exchanged letters, agreeing to work inclose co-operation for the carrying out of the United Nations resolutionsCOPY NO.SECRETCa(55) 7014th March5 1955CABINET

\[(oconcerning Palestine.    These Resolutions of 1947 envisage a much smallerJewish State than Israel has in fact Da come a and are not in accord with her majesty!s Governments present policy towards Palestine0    The Exchangeof Letters is not, however, an integral part of the pact, and when we accede to the Pact, I propose to make it clear that we are in no way committed toor associated with themeAccession of other States4a There is no immediate prospect of any other State accedingto the Pacts    The United States are unlikely to accede in the immediatefuture.     It is the long term aim of the Turkish and Iraqi governments that the other Arab States should eventually participate0    The Governmentsof Egypt and Saudi Arabia have, however, come out strongly against it, andare trying to organise an opposition camp.     The Syrian Government ha.sfallen, for the time being at least, a victim to Egyptian cajolery, briberyand threats.    The Lebanese and Jordan Governments are more favourably disposed but, owing to Egyptian pressure, are unlikely to accede for sometime.    Pakistan has welcomed the Pact and we hope that they may accedein due course,,    France too may wish to accede, but it is doubtful whetherthis would be welcome to Iraq or Turkey, although the Turkish Governmentprofess to be ready to accept France.    The Persian Government arefavourably disposed but have no immediate intention of acceding.Accession by the United Kingdom5. By acceding to the Pact the United Kingdom would undertakeobligations to co-operate with Turkey and Iraq for their security and defence;but these would be less far reaching than our existing obligations to those two countries under the North Atlantic Treaty and the Anglo-Iraqi Treatyof 193 0 respectively.    The later accession of some or all of the countries mentioned in the preceding paragraph might (unless it is desired that ourinstrument of accession should specifically exclude them) extend our obligations e. g. to Persia or the Levant States.    I believe we must accept this potential commitment in the general interests of securing an effectiveMiddle East defence arrangement.    We were prepared to do so three yearsago when v/e hoped to establish a Middle East Defence Organisation.Defence Facilities in Iraq6. Once we have acceded to the Pact, we shall be in a positionto conclude a new defence agreement with Iraq0    Preliminary talks on thesubstance of such an agreement took place in Iraq on 22nd February betweenthe Iraqi Prime Minister and Chief of Staff and H.M. Ambassador and theCommander-in-Chief,  Middle East Air Forces.    I was also able to discussthe matter with the King and Crown Prince of Iraq and the Prime Ministerduring my visit to Bagdad on 4th March.    The Iraqis accept our assessment of the potential military threat to Iraq and the measures needed to counter it.They agree in principle that we should enjoy the following defence facilities which are considered essential by the Chiefs of Staffs-(a) Prestocking in Iraq of equipment including petrol and oil for the use of British land and air forcesin war,(b) The establishment of an air warning system.(c) Maintenance stores and workshops at appropriateplaces with some British personnel.
us(d) The stationing in Iraq of RoA0F0 ground staff for visiting British squadrons,(e) Joint training and close integration betweenthe air forces of the two countries(f) The free passage over Iraq of R0A,Fo aircraft,and staging facilities0(g) The provision of Iraqi guards for Britishinstallations in Iraq0(h) The establishment of a mine-watching service in the Shatfc-el-Arab,The Iraqis made the following reservations on the air bases?-(a) Habbaniya and Shaiba should be under overfallIraqi control, though British ground elementswould remain there under British command,(b) No particular British air squadron should be permanently stationed in Iraq, but there would beno difficulty over the virtually continuous presenceof one or more British squadrons under the guiseof joint training with the Iraqi Air Force, provided they were not always the same ones0It is satisfactory that the Iraqis have come so far as this on the difficult question of air bases and I think we should be wise to settle for thearrangement they propose, which meets our essential requirement,70 The Iraqi Prime Minister has also made it plain that he willask for modern weapons for the Iraqi air and land forces to be provided and paid for at least in part from British or American sources, and that thisis likely to be an essential factor in the negotiations.    The United StatesGovernment is already giving military assistance to Iraq on a limited scale.If we are to maintain our position in Iraq and ensure that the Iraqi forcescontinue to use British arms and equipment, I think we must ourselves makea similar contribution.    If the Iraqi forces are not equipped with the sameequipment as our own forces, the lines of communication and supply in war would be liable to break down.    We are already concerned at Americanattempts to supplant us in this field,   Jn spite of our present understanding with the United States that the Iraqi forces should continue to look primarily to the United Kingdom for equipment and training, we must expect theseattempts to continue,.    We cannot resist them effectively so long as the arms they supply are free, while ours have to be paid for,    I therefore propose that we should devote the payments which the Imqis have declaredthemselves willing to make for installations to be transferred to Iraqicontrol, to the establishment of a fund on which Iraq could draw for theacquisition of arms from the United Kingdom,New Anglo-Iraqi Agreement0o In negotiating this new agreement, we have to be careful not tooffend Iraq nationalist sentiment which was responsible for the failure of our last attempt to conclude a new Treaty with Iraq - the Portsmouth Treaty of1948e    It is therefore proposed that we should conclude s-
(a) An agreement between Governments in general terms which would terminate the Anglo-IraqiTreaty of 1930s provide for full military co-operation between the two Governments in war,and for mutual facilities.? combined training and joint planning in peaceQ    The general characterof this agreement would, we hope, make itacceptable to Iraqi public opinion.,    The IraqiPrime Minister gave me the draft of such anagreement during my visit to Bagdad0    &quot;We havenow prepared and sent to Bagdad a new text,based on the Iraqi draft, but revised to provide more effectively for the requirements of our common defence.    Annex II is a copy of thisrevised draft,(b) Supplementary Exchanges of Notes, dealing withessential points of detail, such as arrangementsfor prestocking, an air-warning system, the equipment and training of the Iraqi forces, thefuture of the Assyrian Levies, and of the Assyriancivilian community, etcD(c) If necessary, subsidiary administrative arrange-ments between Departments of the United Kingdomand Iraqi Governments, dealing mainly with procedure and matters of detail 09o The instruments under (a) and (b) above would be legally binding on the two Governments and would require to be published andregistered with the United Nations,    The subsidiary arrangements under(c) above, which would not be binding between the two Governments, might ifnecessary be concluded later.    They would not need to be published in Iraq?but we should reserve the right if necessary to inform Parliament of their general contento10, It would be our aim to produce in this way a complex of agreements which will prove acceptable to Parliamentary and public opinion in Iraq, and so endure;  and at the same time enable us to assure parliament that we have secured all the necessary facilities and arrangements to enable us to carry out our part iix the defence of Iraq and of the Middle East atany time0Recommendationsllo I ask the authority of my colleagues to open negotiations tothe following endsg-(a) Our accession to the Turco-Iraqi Pacto(b) The conclusion of a bilateral agreement on thelines of the annexed draft between Her Majesty!sGovernment and the Government of Iraq inaccordance with Article 1 of that Pact, to terminate the Treaty of 1930,
(c) The conclusion of subsidiary agreements inthe form of Exchanges of Notes or of departmental arrangements to provide forthe detailed operation of the agreement at (b)Q(d) An arrangement with Iraq whereby the sumspaid for the British installations in Iraqshould be used to establish a fund for the supplyof arms to Iraq,A0E,Foreign Office, S.W.1.14th March, 1955.\
-ANNEX IPact of Mutual Cooperation between Iraq and. Turkey,Whereas the friendly and &quot;brotherly relations existing between Iraq, and Turkey are in constant progress, and in orderto complement the contents of the Treaty of Friendship and GoodNeighbourhood concluded between His Majesty the King of Iraq, andKis Excellency the President of the Turkish Republic signed inAnkara on the 29th of March which recognised the fact that peace and security between the two countries is an integral partof the peace and security of all the nations of the world and,in particular, the nations of the Middle Ea;.t and that it is thebasis for their foreign policies.Whereas Article II of the Treaty of Joint Defence andEconomic cooperation between the Arab League States provides thatno provision of that Treaty shall in any way affect, or is designed to affect, any of the rights and obligations accruing to the contracting parties from the United Nations Charter;  andhaving realised the great responsibilities borne by them intheir capacity as members of the United Nations concerned withthe maintenance of peace and security in the Middle East regionwhich necessitate taking the required measures in accordancewith Article 51  of the United Nations Charter;  they have beenfully convinced of the necessity of concluding a pact fulfillingthese aims and for that purpose have appointed as theirplenipotentiaries; His Majesty King Faisal II, King of Iraq.His Excellency General Nuri Said, Prime Miniver.    His ExcellencyBurhan Din Bashayan, Actirs? Foreign   Ministers   HisExcellency Mr, Jalal Bayor? President of the Turkish Republic.His Excellency Adnan Menderes Prime Minister. His Excelleiie?rFuad Koprulu Minister of Foreign Affairs, who having communicatedtheir full powers, found to oe.in good and due form, haveagreed as follows^Ar tide 1 a consistent with Article 51  of the United Nations Charter,the high contracting parties will cooperate for their security and defence.    Such measures as they agree to take to give effectto this cooperation may form the subject of special agreements with each other.Article 2aIn order to ensure the realisation and effect application ofthe cooperation provided for in Article 1 above,  the competent authorities of the high contracting parties will determine themeasures to be taken as soon as the present pact enter s   intoforce. These measures will become operative as soon as they havebeen approved by the Governments of the high contracting parties.Article 5oThe high contracting parties undertake to refrain from any interference whatsoever in each others internal affairs.    Theywill settle any disputes between themselves in a peaceful way inaccordance with the United Nations Charter.
Article UoThe high contracting parties declare that the dispositions of the present pact are not in contradiction with any of theinternational obligations contracted by either of them with anythird state or states-,    They do not derogate from, and cannotbe interpreted   as derogating from, the said international obligations.    The high contracting parties undertake not toenter into any international obligation incompatible with thepresent pact.Article 5,This pact shall be open for accession to any member stateof the Arab League or any other state actively concerned withthe security and peace in this region and which is fully recognised by both of the high contracting parties.    Accessionshall come into force from the date on which the instrument of accession of the state concerned is deposited with theMinistry of Foreign Affairs of Iraq..    Any acceding state partyto the present pact may conclude special agreements inaccordance with Article 1, with one or more states partiesto the present pact.    The competent authorities of any accedingstate may determine measures in accordance with Article 2.These measures will become operative as soon as they havebeen approved by the Governments of the parties concerned.Article 6.A permanent council at ministerial level will be set upto function within the frame-work of the purposes of thispact when at least four Powers become parties to the pacta    Thecouncil will draw up its own rules of procedure.Article 7oThis pact remains in force for a period of five yearsrenewable for other five year periods.    Any contracting partymay withdraw from the pact by notifying the other parties inwriting of its desire to do so,  six months before the expiration of any of the above mentioned periods, in which case the pactremains valid for the other parties.Article 8,This pact shall be ratified by the contracting parties and ratifications shall be exchanged at Ankara as soon aspossible.    Thereafter it shall come into force from the date ofthe exchange of ratifications.    In witness whereof, the saidplenipotentiaries have signed the present pact in Arabic,Turkish   and English, all three texts being equally authenticexcept in the case of doubt when the English text shallprevail.    Done in duplicate at Bagdad this second day ofRajab 1374 Hijri,  corresponding to the 21+th day of February 1955(Signatures)0
Exchange of Letters,(1) Excellency, in connexion with the pact signed by ustoday, I have the honour to place on record our understandingthis pact will enable our two countries to cooperate in resistingany aggression directed against either of them and that inorder to ensure the maintenance of peace and security in theMiddle East region we have agreed to work in closecooperation for effecting the carrying out of the United Nationsresolutions concerning Palestine.    Accept, Excellency, etc.,etc..Signed Nuri al Said.To His Excellency Adnan Menderes, Prime Minister of Turkey,Bagdad,(2) Bagdad 2kth February 1955.Excellency, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt ofYour Excellency&apos;s letter of today&apos;s date,&apos;which reads as follows:1 In connexion with the pact signed by us today, I have the honour to place on record our -understanding that this pactv/ill enable our two countries to cooperate in resistingany aggression directed against either of thera and thatin order to ensure&apos;the maintenance of peace and security in the Middle East region we have agreed to v/ork in closecooperation for effecting che carrying out of the united nations resolutions concerning Palestine&apos;.I wish to confirm my agreement to the contents of the saidletter.Accept, Excellency,  the assurance of my highestconsideration,x  (Signed) Adnan Menderes,\To His Excellency, Prime Minister of Iraq., Bagdad.
ANNEX IIDi^^AnglQ-Iyaqi AprcementThe Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain andNorthern Ireland and the Government of the Kingdom of Iraq.:Considering that the United Kingdom has acceded to the pact of mutual co-operation &quot;between Iraq and Turkey, signed at Bagdadon 20th February, 1955:(Being determined to seek a peaceful solution of disputes in accordance with the United Nations Charter and to resistaggression against either of them;)Considering that the Pact provides for co-operation betweenthe Parties to it for their security and defence;    and desiring to make a special agreement in accordance with theprovisions of Article 1  of the Pact;Have agreed as follows:-Article 1The Treaty of Alliance between the United Kingdom and Iraqsigned at Bagdad on 30th June,  1930, with the Annexure and Notesexchanged,  shall terminate from the date when the present agreement comes into force.Article 2The Government of Iraq, by the present Agreement, undertakeno obligations beyond the frontiers of Iraq.Article 3.The Government of Iraq assume fully responsibility for thedefence of Iraq, and will command and guard all defence installa-tions in Iraq.Article hIn accordance with Article 1 of the Pact, there shall be close co-operation between the armed forces of the twoContracting Governments.      This co-operation shall include joint planning combined training and the provision of such facilities as may be agreed between the two Contracting Governments.Article 5The two Contracting Governments shall co-operate with aview to the maintenance of the Iraqi armed forces at all timesin a state of efficiency and readiness for the defence of Iraq.
Article 6 in particular, the Government of the United. Kingdom shall,at the request of the Government of Iraq, do their best:(a) to afford help to Iraq (i) in creating and maintainingan effective air force by means of joint training and exercises in the Middle East area, and (ii) inthe efficient maintenance and operation of such air-fields and other installations as may from time totime be agreed to be necessary^(b) to join with the Government of Iraq, in (i) establish-ing an efficient system of warning against air attack(ii) ensuring that equipment for the defence of Iraqis kept in Iraq in a state of readiness, and(iii) training and equipping the Iraqi forces for thedefence of their country;    and(c) to make available in Iraq technical personnel of theBritish forces for the purpose of giving effect tothe provisions of paragraphs (a) and (b; of thisArticle,Article. 7Service aircraft of the two countries shall enjoy stagingand overflying facilities in each others&apos; territories.Article 8In the event of an armed attack against Iraq or of anyother situation, including the threat of an armed attack, which,in the opinion of the two Contracting Governments, endangers thesecurity of Iraq, the Government of the United Kingdom shall make available assistance, including if necessary armed forces,for the restoration and maintenance of the security of Iraq, andthe Government of Iraq shall invite the Government of the UnitedKingdom to deploy in Iraq the necessary armed forces.      TheGovernment of Iraq shall provide those forces with thefacilities and assistance necessary for them to co-operate effectively with the Iraqi forces,,Article 9(a) The present Agreement shall come into force onsignature.(b) Subject to any modifications or amendments that may beagreed by the two Contracting Governments, theAgreement shall remain in force so long as both iraq and the United Kingdom are Parties to the Pact..In witness whereofDone at Bagdad, this day of1955.

</content>
</cab>
