<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/74/0 images: 96-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  March 1955Copy No.    63CABINETLOCAL GOVERNMENT REORGANISATIONMemorandum by the Minister of Housing and Local government year ago my predecessor submitted to the Cabinet a memorandum entitled&quot; Operation Round-up &quot; (C. (54) 111), which included an outline of proposals for local government reorganisation. This was referred to the Committee on LocalGovernment Reform which came to the conclusion (L.G. (54) 4th Meeting, Item 2):(a) that legislation during this Parliament was not practicable;(b) that the Government^ proposals should be included in their electionprogramme; and(c) that individual Corporation Bills could not continue to be held up on theground that the Government contemplated early legislation.2. In regard to (a) and (b) there is no difficulty. But on (c), I wish to consultmy colleagues about the line I am to take on the three Corporation Bills (Luton,Ilford and Poole) which will be coming up for Second Reading in about ten days&apos;time.3. On my appointment to this Office last October, I had a meeting, as iscustomary, with the representatives of the Local Authority Associations. among other subjects, we discussed local government reform, on which they were deeplydivided. The representatives of the boroughs advocated a general extension ofthe one-tier county borough system, involving the disappearance of counties and county districts over a large part of the country. On the other hand, therepresentatives of the counties and the urban and rural districts recommended aconsiderable extension of the two-tier county system and the consequent abolitionof many independent county boroughs.4. I told them that, in my opinion, it would not be fruitful to embark on anyextensive measure of reorganisation unless there were broad agreement among localauthorities on the changes to be made. To my surprise, they immediately repliedthat, rather than see this problem indefinitely shelved, they would be prepared tomake a fresh attempt to agree among themselves upon some more limited proposalsfor reorganisation, within the framework of the existing structure.5. I naturally welcomed this change of attitude; and, in order to facilitate the discussions between them, I agreed to take the chair at three further meetings.I explained that the Government must, of course, reserve its position in regard toany conclusions they might reach.6. As a result of these further talks, the representatives of the Associationshave agreed together upon compromise proposals covering many of the main issuesupon which they had previously been divided.7. These compromise proposals conform fully with the principlesrecommended by my predecessor to the Cabinet (see Annex A). While not involving any change in the basic structure, they contain a number of importantrecommendations for the improvement of local government organisation and forthe removal of existing causes of friction. They include, in particular, recommenda-tions for the adoption of revised principles and procedure for promotions to county Borough status.47792SECRETC. (55) 7114th March, 1955
8. The proposals also include a recommendation that, in principle, thereshould be some redistribution of functions between the County Councils and county District Councils. However, the Associations are not as yet agreed among themselves upon any actual recommendations on this aspect of the problem.Since the services concerned are the responsibility of various Ministers, thesequestions were left over for separate discussion with them.9. The representatives of the Associations have also asked that there shouldbe a review of local government finance. The Chancellor of the Exchequer and theSecretary of State for Scotland and I consider that a review of this kind by theGovernment is, in any case, likely to be necessary before long; and we are examining what its scope should be.10. So long as the Local Authority Associations were acutely divided, itwould have been very difficult to formulate a policy on local government reform,which stood any chance of general acceptance. However, this task is now greatlysimplified by their decision to try and reconcile their differences.11. But if the progress towards agreement is not to be endangered, prematurepolitical controversy must be avoided. It is, therefore, desirable that the associations should not publish the new proposals sooner than is necessary. Inany case, I do not expect that they will be in any hurry to do so. If, however, thethree Corporation Bills go forward, the whole subject of local government reformis bound to be keenly debated between the protagonists of the boroughs and the counties. On the other hand, it may well be that, having regard to the progressof the discussions, the promoters would be willing to withdraw their Bills. the associations are likely to advise them in that sense.12. Accordingly I suggest making a statement on the lines of the draft at annex B, which includes the following points:  (a) There is no prospect of legislation on local government reorganisation this session.(b) The Local Authority Associations have now managed to agree uponcommon recommendations for changes in the structure of localgovernment.(c) Their agreement does not extend to the question of the distribution of functions which has been left over for discussion with the ministers concerned.(d) When these further discussions are completed, the Government will consider the proposals as a whole.  Meanwhile, it reserves its position.(e) The Associations have also asked for a review of local government finance;and this is being considered by the Government.if) In order to avoid prejudicing the progress of these discussions by public controversy, it is hoped that the three Corporations will agree towithdraw their Bills for the time being.D. S.Ministry of Housing and Local Government, S.W. I,12th March, 1955.ANNEX A&quot;OPERATION ROUND-UP&quot;Extract from Cabinet Paper (C. (54) 111) dated 24th March, 1954, byMR. macmillan (then minister of housing and local government)APPENDIX I.-STRUCTURE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT&quot; All kinds of schemes have been put forward to recast the structure. Somereformers have suggested a two-tier system throughout with the upper tier on a regional basis. At the other end there are the one-tier extremists who want thewhole country organised into &apos; single purpose &apos; authorities.&quot;The Boundary Commission, a statutory body set up in 1945 and wound upin 1949, proposed in their 1947 Report to keep the present structure. But anumber of the smaller county boroughs were to be abolished and absorbed into
the two-tier system, becoming &apos; most-purpose &apos; authorities with more functionsthan other county districts but less than they had as county boroughs. TheCommission also proposed radical alterations in county boundaries including thecreation of several new urban counties in the great, conurbations and the amalgamation of some small counties.&quot; Finally, there are the proposals recently put to me by four of the Associations(the Counties, Urbans, Rurals and Parishes). These accept the present mixedsystem but propose a drastic reduction in the number of county boroughs and propose to put the conurbations on a two-tier basis. These proposals will not be acceptable to the county boroughs; the Association representing them and thenon-county boroughs will doubtless propose an extension of the one-tier system.&quot; It is obvious that left to themselves the interested parties will never produce an agreed scheme. If anything is to be done the Government must make up itsown mind about it. What is more, we cannot put off a decision for ever; quite apart from the pressure from the Associations to do something about this problemgenerally, we are faced with private Bills for county borough status, which upto now have been staved off by praying in aid the fact that the Associations were themselves not ready with their proposals. If we do not announce soon our intentionof producing a comprehensive scheme we shall have to let each decision be madepiecemeal, i.e., by way of Private Bills.&quot; Assuming that the present structure should be retained as the basis of any scheme, my approach to this problem would be on these lines:  (1) We would examine the counties and consider whether there are any whichshould no longer be retained as independent units.(2) We would examine the claims of existing county boroughs to retain theirstatus; some of the small ones might be demoted. We would alsoexamine the claims of large county districts (including non-county boroughs) to become county boroughs.(3) The London County Council and the Metropolitan Boroughs are aseparate problem and we would leave them alone for the time being.(4) We would look at the conurbations (including the rest of Greater London)and seek a solution according to the particular circumstances. Wewould not willingly interfere with the government of the great cities;but in some cases the area might be organised on a two-tier basis. in others, the right answer might be to divide it into county boroughs.(5) In the light of decisions taken on the matters mentioned above, we would arrange for the boundaries of the administrative counties to be reviewed and settled.(6) We would ask each county to review its.county districts on lines laiddown by me and to submit proposals for reorganisation. The aimwould be to secure districts, with rural and urban populations, capableof exercising comparable powers and duties; and to eliminatedifferences between boroughs, urbans and rurals.(7) As regards functions, one of our objects in any reorganisation would beto avoid the division of responsibility entailed in complex schemes of delegation. In short, we would try to get as clear a division as possible of powers and duties between the counties and districts.&quot;ANNEX BLOCAL  GOVERNMENT  ORGANISATIONDraft Statement by the Minister of Housing and Local Government1. Last year, in the Second Reading Debate on the Luton. Corporation Bill,my predecessor promised that before any further Bills for conferment of CountyBorough status came forward, the Government would inform the House whetheror not they were in a position to introduce legislation for the reorganisation of localgovernment in England and Wales.2. Far-reaching proposals of various kinds were published by the LocalAuthority Associations about a year ago. There were two sets of proposals; those
r * tput forward on behalf of the borough councils and those put forward on behalfof the county, urban and rural district councils and the parish councils. the boroughs advocated a general extension of the one-tier county borough system,involving the disappearance of counties and county districts over a large part ofthe country. On the other hand, the counties and the urban and rural districtsrecommended a considerable extension of the two-tier county system and the consequent abolition of many independent county boroughs.3. Last November I discussed this problem with the representatives of theLocal Authority Associations. After hearing expositions of their differing attitude onthe lines of their published memoranda, I told them that, in my opinion, it wouldnot be fruitful to embark on any extensive measure of local government reorganisation, unless there were broad agreement among local authorities inregard to the changes to be made. In the light of this, the representatives of theAssociation said that, rather than see this problem indefinitely shelved, they wouldlike to make an attempt to agree among themselves upon a more limited measureof reorganisation, within the framework of the existing structure.4. To facilitate the discussions between the Associations, I agreed to takethe chair at further meetings it being understood that the Government must, ofcourse, reserve its position in regard to any conclusions they might reach.5. I am glad to say that, as a result of these talks, the representatives of the associations have agreed together upon common proposals covering many of themain issues upon which they had previously been divided.6. These proposals, while not involving any change in the basic structure,contain a number of important recommendations for the improvement of localgovernment organisation and for the removal of existing causes of friction. they include, in particular, recommendations for the adoption of revised principles and procedure for promotions to County Borough status.7. The proposals also include a recommendation that, in principle, thereshould be some redistribution of functions between the County Councils and theCounty District Councils. However, the Associations are not as yet agreed on what changes should be recommended. Since the services concerned are theresponsibility of various Ministers, these questions have been left over for separatediscussion with them.8. As soon as these talks on functions have been held, the Government willexamine the proposals as a whole; and in due course a further statement will bemade to the House.9. I should add that the representatives of the Associations have also asked that there should be a review of local government finance. My Right Hon. friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer (and the Secretary of State for Scotland) and Iconsider that a review of this kind by the Government is, in any case, likely to benecessary before long; and we are examining what its scope should be.10. I am asked about the attitude of the Government towards the threeCorporation Bills, which are on the Order Paper. The difficult and delicatediscussions which are now proceeding would, of course, not be made any easierby controversial public debates at this juncture. Therefore, although there is obviously no possibility of Government legislation on this subject during theremainder of this Session, I hope that the three Corporations concerned will, in thegeneral interest, earnestly consider withdrawing their Bills for the present. Byagreeing to postpone their own individual projects, they will be helping to advance the prospect of local government reform for the country as a whole.11. Finally, let me say that the Government is greatly impressed by the efforts which the Local Authority Associations have been making to reconcile their differences, and I feel sure that Hon. Members in all parts of the House will do whatthey can to help bring this issue to a satisfactory conclusion.

</content>
</cab>
