<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/16/13 images: 202-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET&apos;- CQp/NO,      3^u^P.  (41) 90. \ /Tjrd April 1941.    .WAR    CABINET.PROPOSED EXTENSION OF THE BAN ON VISITORS TOCOASTAL ARFAJT &apos;--:-Joint Memorandum by the Home Secretary and minister of Home Security and the Secretaryof State for War.1. On military grounds a ban on visitors was imposed last summerunder the Defence Regulations to a coastal strip from Berwick toPeaceheaven, from Havant to Abbotsbury and to the Isle of Wight.At the request of the Civil Departments the ban on the north ofthe Wash and the ban from Havant to Abbotsbury were lifted inDecember, but it has been maintained on the coast from the Washto Peacehaven and to the Isle of Wight.      In March a ban onvisitors was imposed for the first time on the coast fromPeacehaven to Littlehampton, again on military grounds.2. The military authorities now propose a ban on visitors to acoastal belt from Berwick to the eastern edge of Lyme Regis while maintaining the ban on the Isle of Wight.      This is an extensionof the ban imposed last summer in the following respects:-Peacehaven to Littlehampton (already in force),Littlehampton to Havant,Abbotsbury to Lyme Regis (which is just in the County of Devon.)From the point of view of civilian interests,  there is strong objection to a further extension of the visitors ban beyond theareas to which it is already applied.      The arguments for and against the ban are set out below.3. (a) The threat of invasion is not less serious today than it was last summer and from the military point of view it is essential toreduce to&apos; a minimum the numbers of people in the coastal area.It is not practicable to evacuate large additional numbers ofpersons still resident in the are:, north of the Wash and west ofNewhaven, but steps should be taken to exclude non-residents whovisit holiday resorts solely for pleasure.      Unless this is done,the free passage of reserves may be seriously embarrassed byrefugees, particularly those travelling by road in private cars,and additional stocks of food and petrol in the coastal area arelikely to fall into enemy hands.(b) If visitors are allowed it will be more difficult to preserve the secrecy of defences which are now being resited.Guards cannot be provided in sufficient numbers to prevent access to beaches, and the Army could not accept responsibility for the risks which visitors would run from minefields.(c) We must continue to impress upon the public the threat of invasion.    Permission to visit the coastal area may suggest to thePublic mind, that the threat is not serious.

4.  (a) From the civil point of view a ban on visitors will ruinmany of the householders and other private interests in the areasaffected.      Further severe damage will be done to the financial structure of local government and Exchequer assistance may benecessary.      These self-inflicted wounds on the body politic canonly be justified on the strongest overriding grounds of national security.(b)  If the immediate threat of invasion is serious enough to warrant a ban on visitors,  the question may be raised of personspreviously evacuated to these coastal areas,have now been removed from the greater part ofwhich the visitors ban at present applies, butmothers and children are still left, mostly inEvacuated&apos;Sonsthe area tosome evacuatedthe hinterland.mostlyThere are substantial numbers in the coastal strips to which itis now proposed to apply the ban.      The figures are as follows:-Unaccompaniedchildren.Mothers andChildren.(i)(ii)In areas the ban .applies.to whichilreadyProposed new stripnorthwards fromthe Wash7,2.7,412,7194,l8l(iii)  Proposed new strip-West war as fromLittle hempton12//1527,415.55,7H14,596.28,296(c) The problem of finding sufficient accommodation in thepresent reception areas is already acute 2nd the Minister ofHealth considers it essential to continue to use parts of the coastal belt to which it is now proposed to apply the ban asreception areas,  both for further organised parties and forfurther persons who make arrangements for themselves.      Forexample,  the coastal strip west of Littlehampton is the only practicable reception area for Portsmouthit would lead to very seriously;excluded from Dorset.aifficultiiand Southamptonif London were met(d) For these reasons whatever decisions may be taken asregards casual visitors the Minister of Health would stronglydeprecate any ban on sending further evacuated persons to theareas now in question and even more strongly any suggestion thatevacuated persons already there should be moved.(e) In view of the curtailment of holidays the number ofholiday-makers is likely to be considerably less than usual, butrestrictions on holidays for war workers should not be imposedif it can be avoided.      The objections to private cars might bemet by extending the existing prohibition on the use of cars near the coast.5. The question submitted for decision is whether the military considerations in favour of the proposed extension of the ban onvisitors must be regarded as outweighing the civilian objections.Z2lA. April 1Q41.D. M,

AlnwickTynemouth, S. ShieldsSunderlandHartlepoolsVISITORS BAN1.PresentProposedImportant Areasincluded in new proposals when the&quot;ban should hestrictly enforced.o&amp; Leeds4&amp; ManchesterWhitbyScarboroughf.&apos; Bridlington\Hull-^-K. Lynn     Norwich -.LowestoftCol.   &amp; -Harwich, Bristol,w BathSoyihampton-. ft/&apos; South endMargated RamssateMaidstone ^t)over.*-&quot;Folkestone.--   Rye v&quot;Brighton   Hastings&quot;lot t x e fiamp^Sn^&quot;EastbourneGrimsbyAbbotsburyWeymouth

Alnwickh 3Tynemouth,, S. Shields&quot;a  Sunder landHajrtleooolsWhitbyVISITORS BANPresentProposedImportant Areasincluded in new proposals when the&quot;ban should be strictly enforced.&apos;LV.ar: LeedsManchester^t-j Scarborough.-V&apos; Bridlington\HullLowestoftCol.      .HarwichS s, Bristol.y BathSouihainptontt/&apos; SouthendMargateo RamsgatoMaids t one oi^Uover.*-&quot;FoIke stoneRye&quot;BrightonLot t? e Eamp^rSn&quot;Eastbourne%me Regis.,AbbotsbUryWeymouthLGrimsbyK. Lynn     Norwich-Hastings




</content>
</cab>
