<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/15/5 images: 58-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1941.SECRET. / Copy NoW.P. (41) 32.February 16, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.OPERATIONS IN LIBYA.Note by the Secretary of State for War.I CIRCULATE, for the information of my colleagues, the annexed telegram which has been received from the Commander-in-Chief, Middle East, regardingthe operations in Libya.D. M.War Office, S.W. 1,February 16, 1941.(1/41035)* -H1FOR reasons operational secrecy no previous publicity given activitiesarmoured division. At your discretion these can now be broadcast. Successphase operations starting Sidi Barrani and culminating Benghazi has been due in large measure to ascendency moral and material established by armoured division over enemy from very outset Italian declaration of War. From wordgo armoured division took offensive and, with the exception of period duringwhich they were withdrawn for strategical reasons to allow Italian forces tostretch themselves across frontier to Sidi Barrani, they have consistently attacked.In early days units of armoured division penetrated and temporarily clearedtracts of hostile territory running into thousands of square miles. Graduallythey were pressed back by establishment successive defended localities by forcesnumerically superior as ten to one employing artillery twenty or thirty to one.Result, this extraordinary moral ascendency evident every stage of operationsleading to capture Benghazi. If British armoured units even in small number-appeared to threaten line of retreat, first Italian impulse was to hesitate andthen assume defensive instead of trying to break through. Using different methods of surprise bold use of numerically inferior forces worked time aftertime. Spectacular finish to this phase epitomises not only dash of its leaders and determination tenacity of troops, but it also speaks volumes for quality andstandard of British equipment. For nearly eight months armoured division hasbeen employed without rest. Vehicles which had already withstood strainprotracted operations in worst possible conditions sand and heat were able in last dash to make final and protracted burst which completely surprised enemy.Weight for class Italian tanks, many of them newly delivered from manufacturers,proved no match for British products.  Other (? facts) value of long and carefully[22230]
directed individual and collective training, physical fitness, individual intiativeand contribution by workers at home to victories in the field. Publicity may alsobe given to activities of long-range desert patrols. Italian garrisons at Kufraand other desert posts provided amongst other duties L. of C. for interchangeItalian aircraft between Libya and Italian East Africa. Kufra also constitutedpotential threat to Nile Valley soon after declaration war, long-range desertpatrols formed under leadership major, now lieut.-colonel. Bagnold with nucleusscattered Englishmen who in peace time made their hobby exploration of LibyanDesert. Within six weeks of inception, patrols composed picked officers and menNew Zealand forces and Royal Armoured Corps started their activities. in conditions of indescribable hardship these patrols constantly scoured desert,shooting up convoys, destroying petrol dumps and generally harassing Italiandesert garrisons. Immediate result was cessation of normal supply convoys,increase Italian garrisons and many other comings and goings. Having achievedfirst object our patrols in concert Free French commenced operations in (? FedAn). Story of our action with French co-operation at Murzuk, our capture ofTraghan and other lesser posts has already been told by General Catroux.Original personnel have now been augmented by volunteers from British units and Rhodesians. In company with French, operations by our long-range desertpatrols are now in progress about Kufra. As further tribute to British work-manship, noteworthy that vehicles by these patrols have now covered total distancehalf a million miles without loss of single vehicle from mechanical breakdown,this is all the more praiseworthy if realised that for obvious reasons patrolsunable use recognised tracks and have found their own ways over sand seas,uncharted desert, outcrops of rock and other difficulties previously consideredby most seasoned explorers to be totally impossible. As final note, service oftransport drivers throughout all operations in Libya in desert Sudan and Kenyamerits special mention. Their work has been magnificent. Undeterred byperpetual sandstorms, by bombing, by shortage of water and other physicaldifficulties our transport drivers British, from Dominions, India, Cyprus andCape have never failed to support their comrades in fighting line by deliveringtheir loads at right place and time. Road maintenance of vehicles has beenabove reproach, courage and devotion to duty admirable.



</content>
</cab>
