<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/34/8 images: 50-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
	JrVVl.		1.9	43.. \								:SECEET.CO. BE^KBPT..: UNDER LOCK AND KEYt is requested that special eare may be taken toensure the secrecy Of this document war CABINET 54 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Wednesday, April 14, 1943, at12 15 p.m.Present:The Eight Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Eight Hon.. C. E. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Eight Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Eight Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Eight Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Eight Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Eight Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Eight Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Eight Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for . Burma(Item 3).The - Eight Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Eight Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt,, M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Eight Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel the Eight Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Item 8).The Eight Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Eight Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief of-Naval Staff (Items 1-2).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges .Mr. Norman Brook.
Contents.-Minutetfo. Subject. page 1      Supplies to Turkey    ....      ........     .....   &apos; ....      ....    2172     Naval Construction Programme     ....      ....      ....      ....    217Effect of replacing Fleet destroyers by additional frigates..3     Burma ...     .....      ....       -      ........      ....      ...    217Future Policy.
conclusions minute 1.)Reference:       the requests made and., on certain items, represented a - very smallW M (43) 51st proportion of the reserves available in the Middle East. If sent in,its, present form, this list was bound to make a most unfavourableimpression on the Turkish Government,  and would have a damaging effect oh our policy towards Turkey.! the Secretary of State for War said that the list had beencompiled on the basis of, estimates provided by our Military Attach!,in Ahgora regarding the capacity of the Turks to absorb thesestores.: The PHme Minister suggested that it would be a mistake topresent a list drawn up on that basis. The right procedure wouldbe to include in the list the maximum amounts which we could spareand to inform the Turkish Government that these stores wereavailable for transfer to them as soon as they could arrange to take them 6ver.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the list of stores to be supplied to the TurkishArmy should be examined by the Allied; Supplies Executiveat their meeting that afternoon.A Report should be made which would be considered .atan ad hoc meeting to be held, under the Prime MinistersChairmanship, later in the week.Naval .construction programme.Effect of replacing Fleetdestroyers by-additionalfrigates.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 47thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. At their meeting on the 1st April the War Cabinet had invited the First Lord of the Admiralty to consider whetheradditional frigates and corvettes could be substituted for some ofthe Fleet destroyers included in the Naval Construction Programme.The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty (W P. (43) 145), who, after reviewing the organisation of the shipyards and fitting-out facilities, had come to the conclusion that the small proportionate increase inescort-strength-which would result from this proposed change inthe Programme would not compensate for the proportionatelygreater loss in Fleet destroyer strength and the disadvantageouseffects on warship production.After a short discussion, the War Cabinet-(1) Decided not to press the suggestion that additional frigates and corvettes should be substituted for some of the destroyers included in the Programme.(2) Approved the whole of the New Construction programme as set out in the Memorandum by the First Lord of theAdmiralty (W.P. (43) 122).Burma. 3.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFuture Policy. Secretary of State for Burma (W.P. (43) 131). The Memorandum(Previous stated that, in order, to provide^a basis for the direction of our reference: political warfare towards Burma, *as well as to facilitate recon-W.M. (42) llltli struction planning, decisions in principle were required now on theConclusions,      following questions :-Minute 3.) - (i) The terms of a general statement of His; Majesty&apos;governments eventual policy of self-government in burma. . -       ;:&apos; ::,,:&apos;/v&apos;\;: *- (ii)- our.-ihtentipri:-:to-&apos;repair material damage &apos;.arid..&apos;to- recon-^ struct the economic and social life of Burmai;&apos; (iii) The control to be exercised by His Majesty&apos;s government during the interim period while restoration and recon-struction were proceeding with our assistance, and thelength of such interim period.       v;;,&apos; 1
(iv), The steps- to be taken during, this period to prepare theground for :the transfer of, responsibility to Burmansunder a fully self-governingConstitution.The following were.the main points in discussion :-;(a) As regards (i), the Prime Minister thought there was horeason to add. anything to the declarations on thismatter which had&apos;already been made.(6) As regards finance, :the Treasury had already given anundertaking (which covered^ the; Colonial Empire and burma)&apos; that His Majesty?s Government would be readyto give what assistance they could (in conjunction withsuch common fund or organisation as might beestablished internationally) for the restoration of destruction or damage of property and goods so far as this was beyond the territory&apos;s resources.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was unwilling to go beyond this statement, or to say anything which might imply that Burma was to be given a preferential position. This, view met with general support from the War Cabinet.(c) As regards the interim period after the phase of militaryreoccupation, the view generally expressed was that theGovernor could be informed that he could make plans on the assumption that when Burma had been reoccupiedthere would have to be a period of direct rule.(a) The view was expressed that it would be undesirable toadopt a detailed programme, such as that outlined inthe Paper by the Secretary of State for Burma, as abasis for political warfare activities. We could be out-bidden by the Japanese on the programme outlined,while any public statement at this stage as to certain items in the programme (e.g., the fixing of a limit of seven years for the interim period of direct administra-tion by His Majesty&apos;s Government through theGovernor) might well give us the worst of both worlds.The War Cabinet&apos;s Conclusions were as follows: (1) It was premature to reach a decision on a detailed policysuch as that outlined in the Paper by the Secretary of.&quot; State for Burma.- .(2) No objection wias seen, however, to the Governor being; informed, forhis own information and that of his staff:-.in planning,that after the Japanese had been evictedfrom Burma; His Majesty&apos;s Government would have to resort to a system of direct rule^ during the period of reconstruction.- : 1(3) No promises of financial help should be held out beyond those already given.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,April 14, .1943^
\


</content>
</cab>
