<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/58/7 images: 106-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cc(76) 7thConclusionsCOPY. NOCABINET33CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 26 FEBRUARY 1976at 11.30 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime MinisterRt Hon Edward Short MP**wd President of the council* Rt Hon Roy Jenkins MP^cretary of State for the Home DepartmentHon Anthony Crosland MP^RtSecretary of State for the EnvironmentJ* Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn MPdietary of State for Energyjj6 Rt Hon Barbara Castle MP^cretary of State for Social Services^* Rt Hon Peter Shore MP8*c**plenipoteniary of State for TradeJJ* Rt Hon William Ross MP**cretary of State for Scotland?* Rt Hon Merlyn Rees MP^ctetary of State for Northern IrelandTheRt Hon Harold Lever MPacellor of the Duchy of LancasterRt Hon Fred Mulley MP^*etary of State for Education and ScienceJj6 Rt Hon Robert Mellish MPJiarnentary Secretary, treasury the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy seal the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp minister for Overseas development the Rt Hon John Silkin mp minister for Planning and Local Governmenti
ALSO PRESENTTtu* Rt Hon David Ennals mp minister of State for Foreign and CommonwealthAffairsSECRETARIATSir John hunt mr G R DenmanMr T F Brenchley (Item 2)Mr W I Mclndoe      (Item 1)Mr W R TomkysCONTENTSItemSubject1.PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS2.FOREIGN AFFAIRSRhodesiaii
parliamentary affairs. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.AFFAIRS2. The Cabinet considered Rhodesia. Their discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately.rhodesia previous reference:CC(76) 6thConclusions,Minute 3Cabinet Office26 February 1976
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ government copy NO      33CABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION annex cc(76) 7th Conclusions Minute 2Thursday 26 February 1976 at 11. 30 am the MINISTER OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AND commonwealth affairs (MR ENNALS) said that Mr Smith had twice sent indirectmessages to the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to the effectthat he thought that the time had come when it would be useful tohave some British involvement in his negotiations with Mr Nkomofor a constitutional settlement.    The Foreign and commonwealth secretary had sent a telegram to Mr Smith seeking clarification ofhis attitude and emphasising that he could see no value in british participation unless Mr Smith were ready to make substantial concessions.    Characteristically, Mr Smith had sent anambiguous reply but the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary hadjudged that it contained enough positive elements to make it worthwhile to explore his position further, but with no commitmentwhatsoever.    This explained the choice of Lord Greenhill as anemissary to Mr Smith: he was neither a Minister nor an official,so there could be no suggestion that he could commit the Government.His brief was to see whether there was any significant movement on mr Smith&apos;s part, but on no account to become involved in the talks between Mr Smith and Mr Nkomo; for that reason he was to avoidmeeting them both together.    It was highly probable that whenLord Greenhill returned, probably this weekend, he would bring back a negative report.   If however he reported positively theGovernment would need to examine the next step very carefully.In particular it would be necessary to consult the African Presidents,especially President Kaunda of Zambia and President Nyerere ofTanzania, and the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary might askMr Ennals to carry out this consultation: if so, he would not see Mr Smith.    Meanwhile news had just reached the Foreign and commonwealth Office that Mozambique was about to imposeeconomic sanctions on Rhodesia,    If true, this would raise some political problems particularly in relation to the size of our aid toMozambique following economic damage which that country mightsustain as a result of imposing sanctions.FOREIGNae,fairsRhodlesiaPreviousReference:CC(76) 6thConclusionsMinute 3ft
In discussion it was argued that it had been unwise to sendLord Greenhill to Rhodesia.   All the signs were that Mr Smith wastrying to manoeuvre us into a situation where we would be committed to protecting the White Rhodesians, whilst a speech which he had just made indicated no real change of heart towardsmajority rule.    On the other hand, it was argued mat the decisionto send an emissary in response to Mr Smithes feelers was the onlyone open to us.    We had a vested interest in a settlement leading to early majority rule: and also a vested interest in such asettlement being reached by peaceful means.    We were stillresponsible internationally for Rhodesia, and it was only right to find out what Mr Smith had to say.    The prospects were not howeverpromising and if Mr Smith himself were ready to make genuineconcessions he was likely to be rejected by more extreme membersof his party.    It was significant that there had been no criticism from President Kaunda or President Nyerere of Lord Greenhill^mission.In further discussion it was suggested that Mr Smith, by offeringconcessions, might manoeuvre us into an apparent diplomatictriumph in achieving through us a settlement with Mr Nkomo: andhe would then insist on our responsibility to police the agreement.However, it had been made clear that there could be no question ofa tripartite agreement: if he had concessions to make he must make them directly to the African leaders, and not through us.Any wider conference was also not in sight at present.Alternatively Mr Smith and Mr Nkomo might reach agreementthrough bilateral negotiations and then ask us to recognise the resultant Rhodesian government.    This would require a verydifficult decision on our part, since it would be a case not only ofour recognising the government but of our legitimising it, whichcould not be done without legislation in Parliament.    We should need to consider very carefully whether the agreement reached hadsufficiently widespread African support, not only among the differentRhodesian factions but in Africa as a whole.There would also be great dangers if no agreement was reached between Mr Smith and the African leaders.    In the event oflarge scale fighting we might be faced with an appeal from theWhite Rhodesians, no doubt supported by some members of theConservative Opposition, to send troops to protect the whitepopulation of Rhodesia on the basis of a &quot;kith and kin&quot; argument.It had been made absolutely clear to the Rhodesians and to the world that no British Government would commit British troops to supportthe minority in Rhodesia against the majority.    Mr Ennals had repeated this point in the House of Commons on 24 February.   Apartfrom this objection of principle, our own defence cuts, together with
the lack of staging posts and likely difficulties in securingoverflying rights, made military intervention in Rhodesia evenmore impossible now than at the beginning of the Rhodesianrebellion.    There was also a real danger that the unity of african countries was breaking up, with some moving into a pro-Communistand others into an anti-Communist camp, as had happened over thequestion of Angola.    The dangers of Chinese and Cuban involvementwould be very great: but we would have to stand aside from fighting in Africa of whatever sort,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet was not being asked to agree to British intervention inthe negotiations between Mr Smith and Mr Nkomo,    Lord GreenhiU&apos;mission was purely exploratory, and Mr Ennals had made the positionvery clear in his statement to the House of Commons on the previous day.    The Government would have to assess the situation in thelight of Lord GreenbillS report and further discussion ofhypothetical scenarios at this stage would not be profitable.    Therewas however general agreement that there could be no question ofBritish military intervention.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister *summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office26 February 1976

</content>
</cab>
