<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/160/18 images: 376-379</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&quot;S government cp(71) 153 COPY NO g210 December 1971CABINETUPRATINGS OF NATIONAL INSURANCE benefits memorandum by the Secretary of State for Social services. Despite the uprating in September there is already mountingpressure for the next uprating to be advanced well before its expecteddate of October 1973.    By February or March next year the purchasingpower of the pension is likely to have fallen below its value at the time ofthe 1969 and 1967 increases.    There is widespread uneasiness aboutfurther price rises over the next two years exacerbated by fears of theeffect of entry into the European Economic Community (e.c.) and theintroduction of value-added tax.    There are demands from both sides of the House for annual upratings and the Opposition are likely to commit themselves to this,2. In our White Paper &quot;Strategy for Pensions&quot; (Cmnd. 4755) we under-took to legislate for biennial upratings which would at least preserve the purchasing power of the basic pension.    This would give statutory form to the practice followed for a number of years and would be consistent withthe treatment of public service pensions which are now statutorily tied tobiennial upratings.    We have also undertaken to protect pensioners againstthe effect of joining the e.c..3. We had to bring forward this year&apos;s uprating and I am nowconvinced that it would be politically impossible to try to make pensionerswait two years for their next increase.    Indeed, in my view we shall notbe able to postpone beyond next autumn a further increase in national insurance benefits and we must prepare the way for this now by announcingour adoption of annual reviews as a general policy.    Biennial reviews nolonger carry conviction as honouring our commitment to protect the purchasing power of benefits,40        In addition to protecting the real value of pensions more effectively,annual upratings at fixed dates would have many advantages.    They wouldease the repercussions of entry into the e.c. and bring us closer to thepractice of the Six.    They would avoid the unsatisfactory &quot;ups and downs&quot;which are inevitable so long as we have annual upratings for supplementary benefit and biennial upratings for other benefits.    Those on supplementary benefit do not get the full amount of the biennial increase because they have
already had part of it in the preceding year.    This always damages the credit accruing to the Government for a pension increase.    A move to annual upratings would stand us in good stead if we took the initiative earlyenough.    Delay would switch credit to the Opposition who could plausiblymaintain that we were simply yielding under pressure.5. My Public Expenditure Survey Committee (PESC) programme allows for upratings in October 1973 and October 1975,    The provision would permit the value of the main benefits to be restored on each occasion to what it was at the previous uprating, and would allow a small marginfor real improvement in 1973 and a rather larger margin in 1975.    a margin is needed if the level of pension is not to lag far behind the risingstandards of living of the rest of the community.    I also need provisionfor extending the attendance allowance and for other selective improvements which we must continue to make.    I do not think, therefore, that we can afford to cut into the margin.    Nor can savings be made on the programme for health and the personal social services.    We must, therefore, accept that annual upratings would represent a continuing extra cost compared with my PESC programmes.    The Annex shows the cost through the PESCperiod of restoring the value of the pension annually instead of biennially;most of this cost would fall on contributions.    This would leave for later consideration the provision which should be made for real improvementsincluding, in particular, the need to extend attendance allowance.    since i am sure we should in any case need to uprate supplementary benefit in1972 and 1974 at the expense of the contingency reserve, the true extra cost of my proposals is smaller than indicated (see Annex),6.        I understand that annual reviews would almost certainly requiresimilar treatment for public service and Armed forces pensioners and because of our previous undertakings this would involve simultaneouslyreducing from 60 to 55 the qualifying age at which increases may be payable.    Together these two changes would cost some  20 million a year, but more initially, given the present rate of inflation,    I alsounderstand that an uprating next autumn would create difficulties for the inland Revenue which could only be overcome by waiving the tax due on the extra pension paid between the operative date and the end of the tax year *a loss of revenue of some  6- 13 million in 1972/73 depending on the amount and the operative date of the increase.7.        Annual reviews would not involve any increase in permanent staff inmy Department; the work would be done mainly by overtime and casualstaff,CONCLUSION86        We shall, I am sure, be obliged to increase national insurance benefits next autumn and adopt an annual cycle of upratings thereafter.To gain full credit we need to announce the move to annual reviews quickly.I would propose to present these major improvements as further steps inthe Governments policy of giving practical help to the elderly and othervulnerable groups in the community,    I seek my colleagues&apos; agreement to this course.K department of Health and Social Security9 December 1971
IiANNEXPRICE PROTECTION OP THE PENSION -ADDITIONAL COST OP ANNUAL UPRATINGS  million at 1971 Survey prices1972-73 1973-74 1974-75 1975-76107 102 78 72Notes 1      On the assumption that supplementary benefit would in any case beuprated in line with prices in 1972 and 1974 (see para 5), theadditional cost of annual upratings of pensions in line with prices would be lower, as follows:-  million at 1971 Survey prices1972-73 1973-74 1974-75 1975-7675 70 5W 492 The above figures are calculated on current PESO assumptions of price rises, with the amount of the uprating doing no more thanrestore the value of the pension ie with no rounding or safety margin:-Assumed price rises Increase in standard rate of pension20 Sept 1971-1 Oct 1972           6.3$ 37*8p            on 1 Oct 1972^1 Oct  1972 - 1 Oct 1973           4.4$ 28.1p            on 1 Oct 19731 Oct  1973-1 Oct 1974           4-4$ 29.3p            on 1 Oct 19741 Oct  1974 - 1 Oct 1975           4.4$ 30.6p            on 1 Oct 1975


</content>
</cab>
