<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/50/45 images: 526-529</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet. June 1944.SECRET.W.P. (44) 295.3rd June, 1944.GREEK GUERILLA MOVEMENT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I CIRCULATE for the information of my colleagues a summary of a reportby Major Bathgate, one of our Liaison Officers, who recently returned to Cairoafter spending eight months in Greece. Major Bathgate was in Greece from june 1943 to February 1944 and he spent most of this time in the Lakka Suleiarea. This is a small part of Epirus lying on the west coast of Greece justsouth of the Albanian border. It is almost entirely an E.D.E.S. area and major Bathgate&apos;s report is therefore mainly concerned with Zervas and bisforces. Before leaving Greece, however, he walked right across the country,through the main E.L.A.S. strongholds, and was evacuated from the east coast.He therefore had a good opportunity of studying E.L.A.S. as well as E.D.E.S.A. E.Foreign Of/ice, 3rd June, 1944.ANNEX.Summary of Report by Major Bathgate.Zervas is a leader of a generous and even kindly nature, courageous andmentally hard to shake. The only real complaint I have ever made about himis his disregard of even elementary organisation in which.he fails completely.He hopes for the best but employs a crowd of useless officers because it woulddisturb the peace to fire them. Probably intense laziness is the key to hischaracter, coupled with a belief that talk, patience and conferences will settleeverything satisfactorily. In his own odd and peculiar fashion he is something of a patriot. After the war he would, probably make a suitable Governor ofEpirus, in that he has been forced to visit the greater part of the villages there,which has certainly never been done in peace time by any other responsible Greekfigure in that area.The E.D.E.S. movement is mainly kept going by a few able officers. Zervashimself now relies on Major Agoras, an outstanding personality among theguerillas and a very fine man anywhere. Agoras has Royalist tendencies. Inthe Lakka Sulei area itself the two officers who command the five hundred or soguerillas are extremely capable, while the area commander is a useless nonentitywhom Zervas has never made up his mind to dismiss.When the E.D.E.S. forces have failed militarily this can be attributed tothe following causes : *(a) poor discipline, bad officers and lack of determination;(6) bad communications;(c) no knowledge of any simple patrol system;(a) no knowledge of even, simple infiltration methods. They believe in linesof battle and mountain ridge to ridge formations;(e) long, useless typewritten orders talking of -regiments and other non-existent formations, all duly numbered and copied to prove, I imagine,certain points after the war.12384   [27579] -Copy No.WAR CABINET.
The following are my comments on the Andarte (guerilla) movement as awhole (i.e., E.L.A.S.,. E.D.E.S. and their other small organisations:  There have been many moments when I have wondered whether Andartes orAbyssinians are the more offensive and ineffectual persons, but there does exista percentage of worth-while material in this rather farcical movement which holdssuch a very small portion of the Greek population, and which has brought somuch misery to Greece. Our Mission has kept this movement alive, and unlessBritish troops control matters in the towns after the German evacuation, Iforesee the tragedy going really deep into all Greece.It seems to me that we owe a debt to Greece over the whole Andarte movement,and that it is in our interests and morally binding upon us, to scrap the wholeaffair when the Germans are driven out. This can only be done by British troops and a few young and very active commanders.I feel that Zervas&apos; influence at the end of the war over his bands is bestsummed up by a remark of my interpreters : &quot; He will find it hard to get aman to carry his bag for him.&quot;The majority of Zervas&apos; good or bad officers are pro-King. But with Aresand E.L.A.S. it will be a very different story. Their system of terror is even now nicely established in the mountains, as I saw in my final trek from one sideof Greece to the other.Middle-aged men and women are forced to carry &quot; kalamboki &quot; (maize) fordays across mountains and deep snow to feed Ares&apos; forces. Nothing is paid for;the whole civilian population is working to keep these rebels supplied.At Veneto on the East coast I met a boot manufacturer, who has a factory at Volos. He had been coerced out of the town and was virtually an E.L.A.S.prisoner. He told them that he had no leather to make boots for them. Hisposition when I left was more or less &quot; Find the leather or else !&quot;E.L.A.S., politically, are now a well-organised gang of terrorists. Ares,their leader, has many brutal murders to his credit and he is quite ruthless. He,too, has probably tucked away many British sovereigns against the day whenGreece will be too hot for him.Ares and these bands have only been allowed to grow and thrive through our policy and, we have saddled Greece with these troubles. It is up to us to rid herof them, and all Andartes bag and baggage.



</content>
</cab>
