<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/12/8 images: 144-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special  care may be taken toanagram the secrecy of this document.ASSISTANCE to finland.(previous reference;W.M.(40) 62nd.Conclusions,Minute 7).W.M. (40) 63rd CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 4.Confidential Annex.(8th March, 1940).THE FSIME MINISTEH recalled that at themeeting of the War Cabinet on the previous day it hadbeen agreed in principle to tell the Finns that wewere prepared to send them 50 bomber aircraft, but thatthey must make up their minds quickly whether theywere going to make an appeal for Allied assistance ornot.    The Foreign Secretary and himself had been authorised to draft a telegram to Helsinki on theselines.    Before they had had time to draft this telegram,however, two new circumstances had arisen.   The first was the receipt of a Report from the Chiefs of Staff(ff. P. (40) 86), which was now before the War Cabinet,in which the Chiefs of Staff said, in effect, that thedespatch of 50 bombers to Finland could only bejustified on military grounds, if it offered a reasonable prospect of achieving our principal military objective,which was the control of the Galivare ore field.   TheChiefs of Staff had, however, recognised that political considerations outside this sphere   were involved in thisquestion.    The second new development was an interviewwhich the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; had had with the Finnish Minister in London, an account of whichwas contained in w,P, (40) 88,    It appeared from what. Gripenberg had said that the Finnish Governmentexpected to receive shortly from the Soviet Government

the minimum terras on which the Russians v/ereprepared to make peace,    They were not hopeful ofbeing able to accept these terms, but they did not wish to make their appeal until they had had timeto see whether acceptable terms emerged from the ensuing discussion.    They therefore begged forfurther time, but hoped that we would continue our preparations for intervention on their side.The latest date which the Finns suggested for their appeal was the 12th March, and from this it appeared that their situation was not sodesperate as to demand an immediate answer to their request for bombers0     In   these circumstances; it seemed right that the War Cabinet should have afurther opportunity of reconsidering their previous decision in the light of the Report by the Chiefsof Staff and of M. Gripenberg&apos;s communication,,The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs had circulated a draft telegram as a basis fordiscussion (W. P. (40) 87).Wcm telegram No. 132 from Helsinki, itappeared that the Finnish Government had now received from the Soviet proposals for peaco whichmight form a basis for discussion.    These were probably much the same as M. Maisky had given toMr. Butler in&apos; London, but perhaps somewhat less favourable.   No doubt the Finns were consulting the swedes, who would be pressing them hard to accept.iThe,Finns probably felt that these terms were toostiff and they wanted as much time as possible inorder to try and get the Russians to give them a- p.-

more reasonable settlement.    If in the end thisshould not prove possible, they would probablyappeal to us for assistance,THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGNAFFAIRS agreed with this appreciation of thesituation.    He emphasised that the attitude of the finns during their negotiations with the Russiansmight well be very largely influenced by the line which we took towards them.   We could either encourageasd stiffen them, or, by adopting a rather negative attitude, we could weaken their will to resist.Referring to the possibility of Swedish co-operation,he drew attention to Stockholm Telegram No. 106 DIPP.,in which Mr, Mallet reported that he had emphasisedto the Crown Prince our determination togive all assistance possible to the Finns, and had pointed out that Sweden held the key to the despatchof help on a considerable scale.   The Crown Princebad clearly indicated that we could expect, no active co-operation from Sweden.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR doubted whether it was worth while sending any assistance tothe Finns unless it took the form of substantialhelp in all arras such as would enable them to wintheir war against Russia   The Finns must feelthat their position was, in the long run, hopeless^They could look for no help from the Swedes, andeven if we sent 50 bombers, this would merelypostpone the day when they would have to surrender,-3-

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs suggested that the attitude of the finnish government to our proposed offer of bomber aircraft would depend largely on their estimate of the urgency of the Russian desire to make peace,    if theRussians were really anxious to end the war, thepresence of 50 bombers on the Finnish side would bea valuable asset to Finland during the process of negotiation.THE LORB PRIVY SEAL emphasised thepolitical importance of doing something in response to the Finnish request for bombers.    There would bean outcry against us, not only in this country butthroughout the world, if the Finns subsequentlymade it known that they had appealed to us forbombers, and that, as we had refused them, they had had no other course open toithem but to surrender.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the communication we should make to the Finnish Govern-ment should be on the following lines;-&quot;We understand you have opened negotiationsfor a settlement with the Russians.    Ifyou can reach an agreement which is satisfactory from your point of view, thatends the matter.    If, however, you feelyou cannot accept the Russian terms and youdecide to appeal for our assistance, you must act quickly.    Unless we receive suchan appeal soon we cannot keep open our offer of assistance;   the expedition whichwe have prepared will be broken up and theforces used for other purposes.    If you doappeal, we will undertake to send you 50bomber aircraft at once.    Whether or not we shall in addition be able to get Alliedland forces through to you will depend onthe attitude of Norway and Sweden - we will do our best to shame them into allowingour troops to pass through.

A communication on these lines would, he felt, meetthe point made by the Chiefs of Staff, that thedespatch of the bombers could be justified as theprice of an appeal by Finland, which was an essentialprerequisite of the whole plan of intervention in scandinavia.   At the same time he agreed with theLord Privy Seal that the political considerations mustnot be under-rated.   There was not only the positiveeffect of our making such an offer, but the negativeeffect of a refusal on our part,   v/e should certainly be held up to obloquy if we sent a flat refusal.   TheFrench were plainly very anxious to do something for Finland on political grounds.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR observed thatwe might well find that the only effect of sending 50valuable bombers would be that the Finns would be ableto make slightly better terms with the Russians, butthat their resistance would not in fact be continuedany longer.   For this object we should be runningserious risks at home.THE PR ME MINISTER agreed that the case for sending the bombers was weak from the military pointof view.   He did not feel there was much chance ofour Scandinavian expedition coming off, but it was quite clear that unless the Finns did make their appeal,there was absolutely no chance at all of the expedition.    It was conceivable that the Finnishappeal might stir up public opinion throughout theworld, and in Scandinavia, to such an extent that theSwedish Government might fall and be replaced by another which would be prepared to co-operate with us.

THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER saidthat he fully appreciated the unwillingness of theSecretary of State for Air to lose 50 bombers from our own Air Force, but he felt there was an over-whelming case, on political grounds, for making a communication to Finland on the lines proposed bythe Prime Minister.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRSquestioned whether it was necessary to insist onthe Finns appealing for assistance by Allied land forces.     It must be recognised that the chances ofour being able to send assistance in this form were now very faint.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the proposedtelegram need not necessarily be our last word, buthe would not like merely to say &quot;We will let you have 50* bombers, but we hope you will appeal for allied land reinforcements&quot;.     He wanted to make sure that the Finns did appeal.     If, of course,the negotiations between the Finnish Government andthe Soviet broke down completely, we might lateroffer Finland the bombers to keep them going.THE FIRST SEA LORD said that the First Lordof the Admiralty was very anxious that the idea ofsecuring the Galivare orefield should not be given up, unless and until we encountered actual resistancefrom the Scandinavians.     The First Lord felt that,if we failed in the end to give effective help to finland, we should certainly lose prestige;   butthis loss would be very much less if our expeditionhad actually arrived off Narvik and then turned backowing to Scandinavian resistance^     It would be a

mistake to cancel the expedition altogether merely because the Swedes said they..would not co-operate.The arrival of the expedition might change the atmosphere altogether, and we might find that the scandinavian peoples were, after all, prepared toco-operate, despite what their Governments had said.The First Sea Lord therefore suggested that the telegram should make it clear that we would not abandon the idea of the expedition merely becausethe Scandinavian Governments refused in advance our request for passage.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed that the telegram to Finland should be so worded as to keep this open.THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCEsupported the idea that the expedition should not heabandoned merely because the Scandinavian Governmentsrefused their permission in advance.     He thoughtthat we should send &quot;test&quot; forces to the Norwegianports, and, if they were successful in getting ashore,the remainder of the expedition could follow afterthem.arrangements required to despatch the 50 bombers to finland.wouIdT&quot;be^po8Sible To &quot;despatch 8 lohg-nofeeoT Blenheimson the first suitable day after the llth March,The remaining 42 (which would be taken from Blenheimsearmarked for the Scandinavian expedition) would be short-nosed Blenheims, and could all leave by the20th March.     The use of Blenheims earmarked for the scandinavian expedition would mean that if, after all, the expedition was sent, the squadrons to accompany it would be some 14 days late in arriving,The discussion then turned on the detailedTAFF said that/&amp; ,

assuming that the expedition left on the earliestpossible date.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that immediate steps should be taken to prepare aduplicate air contingent for the expedition, toreplace the bombers to be sent to Finland.     Thedelay in their despatch would have to be accepted.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF said that upto date no Royal Air Force personnel had gone to finland as &quot;volunteers&quot;;    they had only been dispatched in the guise of employees of theaircraft manufacturing companies.     He proposedthay the first 8 Blenheims should be ferried        aacross and handed over to Finnish pilots.   Butthe Finns wanted complete crewb^^^^^^ 3^^ws^&amp; to be sent as &quot;volunteers&quot;.It would take 10 to 12 days to make the necessary arrangements to demobilise/Royal Air yPorce personnel for these aircraft and to despatch them throughthe Finnish Volunteer Organisation.     Personneldespatched in this way would operate as members ofthe Finnish Air Force, and presumably we should haveno responsibility for their maintenance in Finlandor for medical arrangements.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the bomber aircraft we were sending would be no use unless we sent our own personnel with them.     He thereforefavoured the despatch of Royal Air Force personnelas &quot;volunteers&quot;.     We should not be responsiblefor their maintenance, but all their rights in accordance with the ordinary regulations

6f the Service would in fact be secured to them.The practice of &quot;non-intervention&quot; in Spain couldbe followed to ensure that we did not necessarilybecome involved in hostilities with Russia throughsending personnel from the Armed Forces to Finland.Some discussion followed on the effecton our own air strength of despatching 50 Blenheimaircraft.     Information was given as to our -u*^u^&amp;&amp; oatpit of Blenheims and wastage.    It was pointed out thatin the light of war experience it had been foundnecessary to form additional squadrons in fighter command for night defence and convoy protection work.This represented an additional and imforeseen call onour Blenheim resources.It was suggested that the loss of theaircraft being sent to Finland might be offset tosome extent by shutting down on deliveries of aircraft to foreign countries such as Greece,Yugoslavia and Roumania.     82 aircraft had been ordered by these countries, apart from 42 Battles.These countries might be pressed to foregodeliveries in order to help Finland, in the same way as Turkey had given up Bofors guns orderedfrom Sweden.THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCEgave the following details of aircraft being sentto Finland.     A total of 144 had been promised.Of these, 30 Gladiators and 23 Blenheims had arrived in Finland, 1 Blenheim having crashed en route.     17 Gauntlets, 17 Lysanders, 11 Hurricanesand 5 Rocs were in transit and would be arriving at various dates during the next four weeks. Theremainder had not yet left this country.   He had no precise - information as to the French aircraft whichwere be.?ng sent.     No French bombers, however, had yet reached.Finland;   they were only startiijg dust

now.   Nor had. any French fighters arrived.The War Cabinet agreed-(i) To invite the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to despatch atelegram to Helsinki, drafted inthe light of the discussionrecorded above.(ii) To authorise the Air Ministry to make.immediate arrangements to enable thefollowing aircraft, with the necessaryoperational and maintenance personnel,and with the necessary ground equipment,to be despatched to Finland, if it&apos;were so decided(a) 8 long-nosed Blenheims, on thefirst possible day after 11th March;&apos;(b) 42 short-nosed Blenheims, by 20thMarch.    (These a ircraf t would betaken from those at present being prepared for the Scandinavianexpedition).(iii) That -(a) such of these aircraft as wereavailable for despatch before the operational personnel had beenobtained should be flown over by royal Air Force ferry pilots and handed over to Finnish crews to operate in the first placej(b) subject to the qualification in (a)above, the aircraft should be flownover and operated in Finland bydemobilised Royal Air Force personnelacting as&quot;volunteers&quot; in the Finnishservice.(iv) That, while such personnel shouldnominally fight as part of theFinnish forces - the Finnishauthorities being responsible for maintenance of the force and medicalarrangements   -   all rights of suchpersonnel in regard to pay, non-effective benefits, etc., should besecured to them.(v) To authorise the Air Ministry to take immediate steps to replace any aircraft,equipment and personnel withdrawn, underthe conclusion (ii) above from the air component prepared for the Scandinavianexpedition.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UMBER LOGIC MMB KEY.Il   MOST SECRET.It is requested that special care may be taken tooasMiPe ftbo secrecy ofi this doounmemt.COPY NO. /W.M.(40) 63rd CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 5tConfidential Annex.(8th March.1940).YAL MARINEERATION.reviousference:li,(40) 61stnclusions,nute 7). he War Cabinet had before them a Report,in the form of an aide memoire by the Chiefs ofStaff, on the Royal Marine operation, a copy ofwhich is attached (Appendix i).THE FIRST SEA LORD informed the WarCabinet that the Fifth Sea Lord had gone over toFrance on the previous day, and had seen general gamelin.    He had explained to him what we proposedto do, and when we proposed to start.    general gamelin had said that he was in favour of theoperation in principle, but that he thought itnecessary to consider carefully whether it shouldnot be combined with some other major, but notspecified, operation, and whether it should be donenow.    He was holding a meeting of the Chiefs ofStaff of the French Armies on Sunday, and theFrench Cabinet would meet to consider the matter on Monday,    The Fifth Sea Lord would attend theformer meeting, and a report of what took place would be given to the War Cabinet on Monday morningcSome discussion followed as to what theFrench attitude was likely to be, and it was .suggested that it might be desirable tobring pressure to bear on the French Governmentto   agree to   the plan. It was thought

beet, however, to await the meeting of the FrenchStaffs before taking any action with the FrenchGovernment.     There might be a delay of a day or twoon the time-table suggested by the Chiefs of Staff,but this could be accepted since the naval operation was not dependent on the moon.     It was recognised,however, that the longer the operation was postponed,the more chances there were of the secret leaking out.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF explainedthat the special mine required for dropping fromsiswaft would not be available in sufficientepa&amp;Wfe&amp;esi .&quot;by the March moon to justify startingtfee loyal Air Force portion of the operation.From the military point of view, the Chiefsof Staff would prefer that no warning of our action should be given, though they recognised that, onhumanitarian grounds, some, notice would be required.They recommended that this should be limited, to 24 hours.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, for political reasons, some notice would be indispensable.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS,referring to paragraph 12 of the Chiefs of staff report, said that, although there were some objectionsto making a general declaration covering all waterways,and thus possibly disturbing neutrals in areas whichwere not, in fact, to be attacked, he recognised thatthe military advantages of a wide declaration wereoverwhelmingly strong.       He had prepared a draft declaration, copies of which he handed round the WarCabinet.       This declaration was a very much shortenedversion of the declaration which the War Cabinet had

approved in connection with the proposed, acjtion-ojxNorwegian Territorial Waters, following on theALTMARK affair.The War Cabinet then considered the draft declaration, and agreed upon a number of amendments.A copy of the draft, as finally approved, is attached,(Appendix II).THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he proposed, after the notice had been made public, to inform all adjacent neutral countries,through the diplomatic channel, of our intentionsthough he would like to give the President of theUnited States an intimation in advance.     The declarationcould be communicated to the French Government on sunday, in time for their meeting the following day.The War Cabinet: -(i) Took note of the Report by theChiefs of Staff.(ii) Took note:(a) That the French militaryauthorities would be considering the proposed operation on Sunday, 10th March,and that a report of theirproceedings would be availablefor the War Cabinet on Mondaymorning, 11th March.(b) That the French Cabinet wouldbe meeting to consider theproposed operation, and thereport of their military advisers, on Monday, 11th March.(iii) Approved the draft declaration, asamended in the course of thediscussion, and invited the foreign secretary to communicate it to theFrench Government in time for their meeting on Monday 11th March.(iv) Agreed that a decision as to when theNaval operation could start, must be deferred, pending information as tothe views of the French Government.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.

-SECRET-C..O.S.UQ)  260(S)?TH MARCH. 1940.WAR CABINET.CHIEFS OF STAFF COiSilTTEE.ROYAL MARINE OPERATION,AIDE-MEMOIRE.3eWe were requested by the War Cabinet&quot;to review the proposed operation and toreport to the War Cabinet, with particular reference to the following aspects(a) How much notice should be given beforethe operations begin, so that neutraltraffic can gain a place of safety.(b) The timing of the various phases of theoperations, having regard to theimportance of avoiding the premature disclosure of a new, and possibly decisive,weapon.(c) Possible enemy reprisals.&quot;2.        We have examined the operation in detail and we agree that it holds out promise of important-results, and should be carried out as soon as possible,Amount of notice required.3-        Under The Hague Convention, relative to the laying of automatic submarine contact mines, it is forbidden(Article l) to lay unanchored automatic contact mines,unless they be so constructed as to become harmless onox IV.M. (40) 6lst Conclusions, Minute 7, confidential annex.

hour at most after the person who laid then has ceased to control them.     Belligerents are also bound (Article5) to notify the danger zones as soon as militaryexigencies permit, by a Notice to Mariners, whichmust also be communicated to the Governments throughthe diplomatic channel.     No period of warning is laiddown, though we have followed the practice of givingfrom 48 to 96 hours ourselves.4. It would appear from the preamble to thisConvention, which reads as follows:-&quot;inspired by the principle of the freedomof the seas as the common highway of all nations&quot;that the Convention could not be held to apply torivers and waterways in the enemy&apos;s country, which arenot international highways.     If this view is correct,no warning would be required before the laying of mines in these waterways, since any neutrals in enemy territory must take their chance of being involved in military operations.     From the military point of viewwe should, of course, prefer that no warning should begiven.5. If it be decided that, for humanitarian reasons,some warning is desirable, the length of xvarning to begiven is governed by the following considerations:-(a) A mine introduced near Karlsruhe would take 18hours to reach Mannheim, which is the highest point atwhich neutral barges are believed to operate.(b) If 24 hours&apos; notice were given, there would thus be a period of 42 hours from the warning before thefirst mine reached Mannheim.(c) If Dutch barges at Mannheim started movingdownstream on receipt of the warning, they v/ould have42 hours start over the mines.     It would take them 65 hours to clear German territory under the .influence of the current alone, but with any kind ofmotive power this time would be much reduced.     Theywould in any case be moving downstream at least as fast as the mines which would be following them, and shouldeasily maintain their lead.(d) On the other hand, if only 24 hours&apos; notice isgiven, neutral barges, who might reasonably expect the attack to come from the air, would imagine that theyhad not got time to escape from bombing aimed at thelower reaches of the river.     For this reason, it mightbe desirable to give 48 hours&apos; warning.(e) The giving of 48 hours&apos; warning, however, wouldgive more opportunity for the enemy to penetrate the secret, and take precautionary measures.

6.        We conclude that, from a military point ofview, the ideal would be to give no warning, butthat, if warning must be given, it should be limitedto 24 hours.Timing of the Operation.7.        Vie recommend the following time table:-11th March. 8 p.in.12th March.    8 p.m.March Moon Period.(i.e. week beforeand week after fullmoon).April Moon Period.May Moon Period.Issue of warning declaration.Naval operation begins ata rate of 300 a night,settling down to 1,000 aweek.Royal Air Force do notbegin operations, unless aGerman offensive appearsimminent, or unless someother special reason makes it essential, (see para. below)..Royal Air Force beginoperations in the Rhine.Royal Air Force beginoperations in canals andestuaries.8.        We do not recommend that the Royal Air force should start in March, as they will not have had sufficient time for training;    nor will their supplies of mines be in sufficient quantities.   Itwould be better to wait till they can operate at full pressure in April.9.        We nevertheless consider that the navaloperation should start on 12th March.     The soonerthe traffic is interrupted the better, and the scale of the naval operations is large enough to cause theenemy very serious dislocation, and c:.n be sustainedindefinitely.The effect of enemy retaliation.10.       The enemy might retaliate in due course onthe English rivers, though he has not any meansof inserting mines in them except from the air.Lighterage traffic on the Thames and Humberestuaries is of considerable importance, but the scale of defence of those areas should be sufficient to       oprevent any heavy scale of minelaying.     We believethat transport on the waterways in France is of greatimportance, but it is for the. French to say whether

they consider that German retaliation in kind would cause them more than inconvenience.11.       We do not believe that the operation ofdropping mines from the air would bring on unrestrictedair warfare.     The Germans cannot be looking for an excuse for indiscriminate bombing, as they have nothesitated to indiilgs in the bombing of civilians inPoland301 in passenger liners, when they thought itsuited them.     We therefore conclude that the fear of-reprisals or retaliation should not deter us fromcarrying out the operation.Form of proposed public declaration.12.       An important point arises in connection withthe public declaration which will have to be made to announce our intention.     We are faced with the alternatives of declaring the Rhine only as a dangerousarea, or of including in our announcement all thenavigable waterways of Germany.     From the military point of viex? we recommend that the declaration shouldbe as wide as possible to cover all waterways, for thefollowing reasons(a) The need for a subsequent declaration when we propose to extend operations to canalsor the Danube would be avoided.(b) As soon as the nature of the attack isrevealed, neutrals may be frightened offthe Danube , which would be to our advantage.(c) The Germans would have to dissipate theirprotective arrangements.It should be noted that the German estuaries are allcovered by our existing announcement, made at thebeginning of the war.(Signed)     C.L.N. NEWALL.&quot; DUDLEY POUND.&quot; EDMUND IR0NSID3.Cabinet   War Room.

APPENDIX   II.Draft Declaration.In recent weeks the German campaign by submarine, aircraft and unnotified mines againstmerchant shipping of all nations has been intensifiedand has been carried out in defiance of the recognisedrules of war, frequently in circumstances of thegreatest barbarity and on many occasions without there being the slightest justification for interference ofany sort with the ship.2.     Whilst the greatest losses have recentlyfallen upon neutral shipping, allied vessels have also suffered from this policy of destruction, a new development of which is the bombing of fishing boats and the machine-gunning of their crews.     Even light-ships, which by international usage are treated as non-combatant, have been with their crews ruthlesslyattacked.3.     In view of this German policy, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom and the FrenchGovernment have decided that so long as it is continuedthey will take action to restrict navigation on Germaninternal waterways and they desire, in consideration ofand by way of warning to non-combatants and neutrals,to give previous advice of their intention.       they accordingly give notice that, as from 8.0 p.m. (20 hours)Central European time on March        all the internalnavigable waters of Germany will constitute an areadangerous to shipping.




</content>
</cab>
