<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/102/0 images: 197-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C. (60) 109 COPY NO._V11th July, I960CABINETWORKING CONDITIONS IN SHOPS, offices and OTHER PREMISESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for theHome department the Ministers primarily concerned with working conditions inshops and offices have been considering whether the Government should introduce comprehensive legislation on the subject during the present parliament.    Our conclusions, which have been endorsed by the HomeAffairs Committee are as follows.The case for legislation2. There are at least two main reasons for legislation.     First, on merits, there is no question that in many of these premises there is a realneed for improvement, which will not be effected except under legislation.Second, our hands have been to some extent forced by Mr. Marsh&apos;s OfficesBill, which has already been passed by both Houses.    The Bill is unsatisfactory in itself, in particular because it leaves everything to regulations, and has been widely recognised as such both in parliament and by outside interests such as the British Employers&apos; Confederation and,to some extent, the Trades Union Congress, who have asked to meet meto discuss the question of comprehensive legislation.    Moreover, since theBill covers only part of the ground it is certain to be followed by other,equally unsatisfactory, Private Members&apos; Bills unless we undertake to legislate comprehensively ourselves.3. I recognise that by no means all of our own supporters will welcome more legislation in this field - though the desire for comprehensivelegislation was expressed by some Conservative backbenchers in theproceedings on the Offices Bill.    The requirements of the legislation might, moreover, be a burden on small employers in particular;  a compromise which was at one time considered, which would reduce both thecost and the political impact of the legislation - that is, to confine its application to new buildings - is not acceptable because it would apply only where the need is least.    The legislation would, however, be framed soas to avoid as far as possible any sudden or undue burden;  for instance,there would be provision for a general period of grace for requirementslikely to involve substantial structural alterations, and for further defer-ments or exemptions in the case of individual premises at the discretion of the enforcement authority.-1-
4. On balance, we are satisfied that we ought during the present parliament to introduce a comprehensive Government measure, for whichit is agreed the Minister of Labour should be responsible.Timing5. Politically, it would have been advantageous to deal with a controversial Bill of this kind as early as possible in this Parliament, butthe pressure on next session&apos;s programme is so heavy and, with the wideconsultations that will be required, the Bill will take so long to get intosatisfactory shape, that we think we should plan to introduce it in the next session but one (1961/62).6. But an early announcement - if possible before the summer recess - of our intention to legislate is highly desirable.    This willrelieve us of the obligation, which we could not otherwise avoid, to under-take wide but fruitless and indeed misleading consultations on the basis of draft regulations under the Offices Bill.     In addition, as a result of therecent Liverpool fire, pressure for legislation for improved fire precautionin shops and similar buildings is likely to build up and will be verydifficult to handle without a firm undertaking to introduce comprehensivelegislation in which proper provisions can be made in this field.Scope of the legislation7. If we are to legislate at all we must certainly cover shops and offices.    A draft Bill was prepared some time ago dealing with conditionsin railway premises and we think that these must also be included, thoughcareful consideration will have to be given to minimising - e. g. , by theprovision of a relatively long transitional period - the effect on the finances of the British Transport Commission.8. This leaves, in the field covered by the Report of the Committeeof Enquiry into Health, Welfare and Safety in Non-Industrial Employment(1949) under the Chairmanship of Sir Ernest Gowers, theatres and other places of indoor entertainment, private catering establishments, roadvehicle and coal depots and dental mechanics&apos; premises.    Ourpreliminary view is that there is a case for including the first, but thatall these marginal cases should be considered again by the Inter-Departmental Working Party of officials who have already reported to ministers on shops, offices and railway premises.Enforcement9. The Home Affairs Committee were agreed that enforcement of the legislation in relation to Crown, local authority and factory offices and probably to railway premises, should be given to the factory inspectorate.    They also felt that there was much to be said for entrustingto the Factory Inspectorate enforcement in all other premises to whichthe legislation would apply;  but that in view of the difficulties, including-2-
recruitment, that this might raise and the arguments that could be advancedfor enforcement by local authorities, as recommended by the Gower&apos;s committee, this question should be considered further by the Minister ofLabour, the Minister of Housing and Local Government, the Secretary ofState for Scotland and myself, and a provisional decision reached fordiscussion with the local authorities.10. The Committee further agreed that the question of responsibilityfor enforcement of fire precautions should be remitted for further consideration to the  working party of officials.Shop hours11. The existing law on shop hours is so unsatisfactory that it ought not to be allowed to remain on the Statute Book indefinitely;   and ona number of points it is in urgent need of reform.   But experience of the1956/57 Shops Bill has shown that reform is not practical politics.   Wetherefore have in view outright repeal of the present statutory restrictionson weekday stops hours, which it seems clear are no longer needed for thebenefit of shop assistants (or indeed small shopkeepers).   But repeal islikely to be controversial and we therefore recommend that, before afinal decision is reached, political soundings should be taken.Recommendations12. I accordingly invite my colleagues to agree:-(a) That comprehensive Government legislation on working conditionsin shops, offices, railway premises and possibly certain other premisesshould be prepared for introduction by the Minister of Labour in the1961/62 session.(b) That the Governments intention should be announced as soonas possible.(c) That the question of the application of the proposed legislation to other classes of premises covered by the Gowers Committee&apos;s report and the question of responsibility for enforcing fire precautions shouldbe considered further by the working party of officials.(d) That the Minister of Labour, the Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment, the Secretary of State for Scotland and I should reach a provisional decision on enforcement of the proposed legislation fordiscussion with the local authority associations.(e) That the question of repealing restrictions on weekday shop hoursshould be further explored.R. A. B.Home Office, S. W. 111th July, 1960-3-

</content>
</cab>
