<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/102/0 images: 248-268</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINETTHE CONSTITUTIONAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE COMMONWEALTHNote by the Secretary of the cabinet at the Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers in May it was agreed thata group of officials from six Commonwealth countries should review theconstitutional development of the Commonwealth, with particular reference to thefuture of the smaller dependent territories, and make an analysis, with alternative suggestions, for consideration by Commonwealth Governments.By direction of the Prime Minister, the report of this group is circulated here with for consideration by the Cabinet.Copies of the report have been sent to other Commonwealth governments for their consideration.(Signed)     NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,10th August, 1960.57516Printed for the Cabinet.   A ugust I960C. (60) 122 . Copy No.   7411th August, I960

Copy No.l 7 4THE CONSTITUTIONAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE COMMONWEALTHReport by a Group of Commonwealth OfficialsIAt their Meeting in May 1960 the Commonwealth Prime Ministers agreedthat a group of senior officials (from the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia, NewZealand, India and Ghana) should be appointed to review the constitutional development of the Commonwealth, with particular reference to the future of thesmaller dependent territories, and to make an analysis, with alternative suggestions,for consideration by Commonwealth Governments. We were appointed inpursuance of this decision. The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom kindlyarranged for the facilities at &quot; Chequers &quot; to be placed at our disposal for thepurpose of our meeting, and we met there from 17th to 23rd July, 1960.We are forwarding our report through the United Kingdom Government forconsideration by the Governments of all the member countries of theCommonwealth.2. The member countries of the Commonwealth constitute a free associationof independent sovereign States, all of which have, in varying degrees, the followingcommon characteristics a certain weight of population; political, financial andeconomic viability; the ability to play a role in world affairs and to carry weightin world councils; and the capacity for self-defence, at least against local acts of aggression. It is, in short, a relatively small group of relatively large countries.This fact has had an important influence on the character of the association andon the relations between its members.3. The members of the Commonwealth have found their association to beof considerable value to them, both severally and jointly. Each of them has felt,in varying degrees, that its own position and influence in the world have beenenhanced by its membership of this association; and the Commonwealth has itselfbeen able to exercise a valuable influence in world affairs.The strength and cohesion of this association have been enhanced by the processes of consultation between its members on matters of common concern.The full exchange of information and views between the member countries has done much to create, or to reinforce, a common approach to many of theinternational problems which are of concern to them. At the centre of these processes of consultation are the Meetings of the Commonwealth Prime ministers themselves, which have always been characterised by a frankness and intimacyof discussion unparalleled in international gatherings. These occasions for free and informal discussion of the international problems of the day, and the opportunities which they provide for personal contacts, have been highly valuedby the Prime Ministers of the member countries of the Commonwealth. Theyhave become one of the strongest links in the chain of Commonwealth consultation.4. This atmosphere of intimate discussion could be impaired if the membership of the independent Commonwealth were very greatly enlarged. Anincrease in its size would not significantly affect the processes of day-to-dayexchange of information and consultation through official channels. Nor would it involve any dramatic change in the character of Commonwealth meetings,whether of Ministers or of officials, on technical matters such as finance, economicsor education. It is the special nature of the Meetings of the Commonwealth PrimeMinisters themselves that is most likely to be impaired by any large increase inthe numbers attending.Our task, as we have interpreted it, has been to try to forecast the extent towhich the membership of the independent Commonwealth will grow over thenext decade, with particular reference to the smaller dependent territories; toconsider how far the accession of new members may alter the character of commonwealth co-operation and of Commonwealth Meetings, especially Meetingsof Commonwealth Prime Ministers; and to examine alternative means by which,despite these changes, the value of the Commonwealth association might be preserved.57414b
:   r 115.   By the end of 1960 the member countries of the Commonwealth willotal 11: Population(millions)United Kingdom................ 51Canada    ..................... 18Australia..................... \0- new Zealand     .................. 2-south Africa      ...............      ... 14-7India       ..................... 397-5Pakistan..................... 84Ceylon     ..................... 9-2Ghana     ............      ......      ... 6-7The Federation of Malaya      ...      ......... 6-3The Federation of Nigeria      ............ 366. Annex I of this report contains a list of all the dependent territories of theUnited Kingdom and of other members of the Commonwealth, together with a map and notes on their population and their present constitutional position.7. The Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, with a population of8 millions, is in a special position. By long-standing agreement the Prime Ministerof the Federation is invited to attend Meetings of Commonwealth Prime Ministers,but the Federation cannot achieve Commonwealth membership in the full senseuntil it has attained independence. Its future is at present under consideration;but we have assumed, for the purposes of this report, that a Central african federation in some form will remain in being.8. Over the next few years five territories with characteristics similar to thoseof the existing member countries will cease to be dependent on the UnitedKingdom and are likely to apply for Commonwealth membership. These are:Population(millions)Sierra Leone     ......      ............ 2-3The Federation of the West Indies    ......... 3Tanganyika       .................. 8-8Kenya     ..................... 6-4Uganda   ............      ......... 5-7It is assumed that these countries, on any view, would be admitted to commonwealth membership.For Sierra Leone the date of independence has already been fixed April 1961.The Federation of the West Indies may achieve independence towards the end of1961 or early in 1962. Tanganyika might reach that goal not long afterwards.The rate of progress of Kenya and Uganda towards independence is less easilypredictable.9. We now turn to the smaller dependent territories. These vary widely in population and in constitutional status. Some are likely to qualify for independence within the next few years, but it is hard to forecast the pace or the exact pattern of constitutional growth of the others. In general, however, it would be wise toassume that the rate of advance towards self-government or independence is likelyto accelerate rather than slacken. In some cases therefore, even thoughindependence is not at present foreseen within the next decade, it would not be safe to assume that the territories will be content to rest on internal autonomyfor so long. With these reservations in mind we have found it convenient for thepurpose of our study to group these territories in the following categories:10.   Territories whose independence is already assuredCyprus     ............      550,000      August 1960Western Samoa.........      100,000      January 1962British Guiana       .........      520,000      No date fixed
Cyprus will become independent on 16th August, 1960. The Cypriot leaders have indicated that the new Republic will probably wish to apply for membership of the United Nations and of the Commonwealth. Cyprus presents special problems, not only because of its small size, but because of its close relationship with two countries outside the Commonwealth Greece and Turkey. Annex IIcontains a summary of the main considerations for and against the admission of cyprus to Commonwealth membership. It will be for the member Governmentsof the Commonwealth to weigh these considerations if an application for membership is made. It is however relevant to our enquiry to note that, if Cyprusis admitted to membership of the Commonwealth, this will for the first timedemonstrate that small countries need not be excluded from commonwealth membership because of their size especially if they have first attained membership of the United Nations.Western Samoa. The Government of New Zealand have promisedindependence to the trust territory of Western Samoa by the beginning of 1962. Shewill then be constitutionally qualified to apply for membership of the United nations and of the Commonwealth. It does not necessarily follow, however, that she will wish to exercise her right to apply for membership of either. The New zealand government foresee a possible solution in the form of a Treaty relationship underwhich Western Samoa, after achieving independence (which will necessarily includeresponsibility for her own external affairs and defence), would ask NewZealand to conduct her external relations and defence. In that event she wouldprobably not apply for membership either of the United Nations or of theCommonwealth though she would wish to retain all the privileges and benefits shealready enjoys through association with the Commonwealth.British Guiana. At the Constitutional Conference held in March 1960 theUnited Kingdom Government promised that British Guiana should achieveindependence; and, although no actual date was fixed, the probability is that she willbecome independent by about .1963. It is possible that she might eventually accede to the West Indies Federation, but the promise of independence was not made conditional upon her doing so.11.   Territories which are likely to seek independence within the next decadeSingapore has complete internal self-government with a locally appointedrepresentative of the Sovereign. The Government of Singapore are not at presentseeking any change in the present status; but in a country with a young and politically-minded population ther^ is bound to be mounting pressure for independence. Singapore might achieve this initially as a separate unit, but might ultimately become part of a wider Malayan Federation.Malta enjoyed internal self-government until 1958, when the constitution was suspended. Steps are now being taken towards an early restoration of representative Government. The political situation and personalities in Malta makeit unusually difficult to forecast what may happen, but here again the possibilityof independence must be taken into account.British Honduras is likely to attain internal self-government within 5 to 10 years.But the situation is complicated by the long-standing claim by Guatemala tosovereignty over British Honduras and by the fact that, when British Guianabecomes independent, British Honduras will be the only remaining Britishdependency on the American continent. The people of British Honduras have made it clear that they do not wish to sever the British connexion certainly they do not want to be swallowed up by Guatemala. The territory is not viable as anindependent nation. After the West Indies Federation and British Guiana have become independent (whether or not the latter has joined the Federation) internal and external pressures for the independence of British Honduras are bound to grow. The best solution would be for British Honduras also to join the West IndiesFederation. This possibility is constitutionally open to her, but at present it findsno favour in British Honduras.PopulationSingapore  ...MaltaBritish HondurasAden Protectorate1,470,000320,00080,000660,00057414b 2
Aden Protectorate. Although at present the Rulers are more preoccupied withconsolidating the newly formed Federation, the pressure of events in the Middle Eastgenerally, and the recent independence of Somalia, might well lead to a situationwithin 10 years in which a demand for independence became irresistible. In that event Aden Colony would probably be left to follow its constitutional development as a separate unit.12.decade.Territories which are not likely to aspire to independence within the nextAden Colony      ......Bahamas    .........Basutoland ......Bechuanaland ProtectorateBermudaBruneiFijiGambiaGibraltarHong KongMauritius   ...North BorneoPapua and New GuineaSarawak    ......Seychelles  ......SwazilandTonga       ......Zanzibar   ......Population140,000130,000640,000300,00040,00070,000360,000280,00025,0002,680,000610,000400,0001,830,000630,00040,000240,00060,000300,000Of these it is possible that at some stage Brunei, North Borneo and Sarawak might seek to join in a wider Malayan Federation.Zanzibar seems unlikely to aspire to independence on her own, but might wellseek attachment to one of the independent East African territories or to a Federationof those territories if one came about.For the Gambia, the possibilities would seem to be either absorption into the neighbouring territory of Mali, or some form of association with Sierra Leone, orcontinued dependence on the United Kingdom with full internal autonomy. Atpresent the people of the Gambia are strongly opposed to any idea of absorptioninto Mali.If Western Samoa became a member of the United Nations and of theCommonwealth (see paragraph 10 above), there would almost certainly be pressure for similar Commonwealth treatment from Fiji and Tonga and possibly others.In Hong Kong there are no signs of any general demand for constitutional advance.13. In addition there are various small and scattered islands in which no constitutional questions of significance are likely to arise. These include, forexample British Solomon Islands.Gilbert and Ellice Islands.New Hebrides Condominium (Anglo-French).Virgin Islands.Falkland Islands and Dependencies.St. Helena and Dependencies.Cook Islands (New Zealand).Nauru (Australia).
14. To sum up, it would seem that we must count on (i) the certain additionof five new Commonwealth members (Sierra Leone, the West Indies, Kenya, Ugandaand Tanganyika); (ii) the probable addition of Cyprus, British Guiana and singapore; and (iii) the possible addition of the Aden Protectorate, british honduras, Malta and Western Samoa. Thus, taking also into account a central african Federation in some form, the total Commonwealth membership may risewithin the next decade to a minimum of 17 or a maximum of 24.15. Eventually, the problem may be simplified to some extent by merger orfederation between Commonwealth countries.Among the larger countries, the problem of numbers is already being eased bythe principle of federation in Malaya, Central Africa and the, West Indies. And,although the East African territories will initially apply for commonwealth membership as separate units, it may be that they may thereafter combine together ina Federation which would send a single representative to Commonwealth Meetings.Among the smaller dependent territories, as indicated above, there are alsopossibilities of amalgamation. British Honduras and British Guiana may eventuallyagree to join the Federation of the West Indies. Zanzibar may link itself with an east African Federation or with one of the existing East African territories.Singapore and the Borneo territories may in the long run form part of a wider Malayan Federation. The Gambia may join with one of its neighbours.Mergers of this kind, which resulted in a smaller number of more viable units,would tend to simplify and strengthen, constitutionally and practically, the links between the various countries of the Commonwealth.16. Even so, on the forecast we have made, it seems likely that in 10 years&apos;time the number of Commonwealth members could well be double what it is to-day.Ill17. In this part of our report we examine a number of suggestions which havebeen put forward with the object of preserving, despite increasing numbers, theintimate character of the Meetings of Commonwealth Prime Ministers. Theseare:(i) The recognition of a constitutional status short of independence (in thisreport described as &quot; Statehood&quot;) which would provide a specialCommonwealth relationship for smaller territories.(ii) The exclusion of countries below an arbitrary limit of size fromrepresentation at Meetings of Commonwealth Prime Ministers.(iii) An arrangement, on the analogy of the Security Council, by which the meetings of Commonwealth Prime Ministers would comprise a certainnumber of permanent members and an additional number of temporarymembers chosen in rotation.(iv) The development of a system of regional Commonwealth Meetings, bywhich the smaller countries would participate only in the regionalgatherings and not in the main Meetings of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters.(v) Certain changes of procedure at Meetings of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters which would help to preserve the essential character of thoseMeetings, despite an increase in the number of countries represented.18. These suggestions, though they have the same objective, approach it by different routes.The first assumes that, within the Commonwealth, independence will continueto carry with it the right of attendance at Meetings of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters. On this basis it seeks to limit the size of those Meetings by making it more attractive to smaller territories to rest in a status short of independence.The second, third and fourth of these suggestions would introduce what wouldbe a new principle namely, that membership of the Commonwealth would not automatically carry with it the right of attendance at Meetings of commonwealth prime Ministers. Under these suggestions no attempt would be made to restrict thegrowth of Commonwealth membership; but only a limited number of members would be eligible, at any time, to attend Commonwealth Meetings at the highest level.
The fifth suggestion involves no structural change. It assumes that theconstitutional development of dependent territories will be allowed to take itsnatural course, and that countries attaining independence will qualify for commonwealth membership and for attendance at Meetings of commonwealth prime Ministers. It contemplates however that, to meet the consequent increase in numbers, there should be some changes of procedure in the conduct of thoseMeetings.&quot; Statehood &quot;19. It has been suggested that the smaller dependent territories might be less likely to press for independence and Commonwealth membership if, when they had reached the stage of full internal autonomy, they could be afforded increasedrecognition and Commonwealth association. It has been suggested that on this basis they might be content to rest for some time in a status in which, whileenjoying full internal autonomy, they continued to look to a member nation ofthe Commonwealth for the conduct of their foreign relations and their defence.20. The position of such States might be modelled on the present constitutionof Singapore or Tonga. Singapore is fully responsible for its internal affairs; it hascertain entrustments in the field of foreign affairs, notably as regards trade andbilateral relations with neighbouring territories; it enjoys local citizenship; it is called the &quot; State of Singapore &quot;, and it has as its constitutional head a locallyappointed representative of the Sovereign. In Tonga the local Ruler is in treatyrelationship with the United Kingdom. While the country enjoys a very largedegree of internal autonomy, its external affairs and defence are subject to control by the United Kingdom Governments.21. States in this position would not be recognised as members of theCommonwealth, but would be entitled to share (normally on a reciprocal basis) thebenefits relating to trade, finance, citizenship, &amp;c, v/hich members enjoy. Theywould be entitled to attend Commonwealth meetings on subjects within their jurisdiction, but not the Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings or other meetings primarily concerned with foreign affairs or defence. They would not belong to the united nations or other international associations of a political character, but might wellbelong to specialised organisations whose purposes could be implemented within thepowers of self-government they possessed.22. The precise legal attributes of such States and the relation between themand the member country conducting their foreign relations and defence might differ in one case from another, and need not concern us here. What is essential is thattheir international status would be recognised to be less than that of fully sovereignStates and that, in consequence, they would be ineligible for membership of theCommonwealth. Arrangements would, however, be made to render this situation as attractive as possible for them by permitting them to enjoy as many as possible of the benefits of association with the Commonwealth.23. If successful, this effort to make the final stage of the path towards full sovereignty more attractive and acceptable would help to keep the number ofmembers of the Commonwealth within manageable limits at least for a time. Itwould enable such States to receive certain of the marks and privileges normallyreserved for fully independent nations, while at the same time relieving them of thecost, obligations and distractions involved in carrying on foreign relations and providing for their external defence. It would enable such States gradually toextend their external relations from a single parent country to other countries ofthe Commonwealth and also to certain foreign countries in respect of subjects ofspecial interest.24. On the other hand there would be disadvantages in adopting a deliberatepolicy on these lines. Most of the smaller dependent territories likely to seekindependence and Commonwealth membership in this decade, as noted in Part ii of this report, are unlikely to be willing to defer this demand in exchange for agreater measure of recognition within the Commonwealth. In particular, this solution would not meet the needs of either Cyprus or Western Samoa; for bothof these have already been promised independence as fully sovereign States.Moreover, a deliberate effort to render the final stage of dependency more attractive might well appear to be a device intended to delay constitutional andvance for countries which were ready for it. In many quarters it would be represented as nothing more than &quot; Colonial &quot; status under another name. It would thus seem
to be inconsistent with the declared policy of successive Governments of the UnitedKingdom to develop their dependent territories through to full independence. the closer association with the Commonwealth of these self-governing but not fullyindependent States might also confuse their position with that of Commonwealthmembers, and might have the effect of obscuring, in foreign eyes, the trueindependence of members of the Commonwealth and the true nature of theCommonwealth itself. Finally, an attempt to create a class of territories of thiskind under some generic description might attract the criticisms usually levelledthroughout the Commonwealth at a &quot; two-tier &quot; system.25. For these reasons it may be considered inexpedient to adopt a deliberatecourse of identifying as a separate class those dependent territories which, whileenjoying full internal autonomy, rely on a member country of the Commonwealthfor the conduct of their foreign relations and their defence. Even so, many of theattributes of this status are likely to be applicable to individual territories in the penultimate stage of their constitutional advance to independence, and it may be appropriate at that stage to accord some measure of Commonwealth association to them.Limitation of Privileges of Membership for Smaller Independent Territories26. As a means of limiting attendance at Meetings of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters, we have considered whether smaller territories which attain independencemight be accorded all the privileges of Commonwealth membership except that ofattendance at these Meetings. The smaller countries would have to be indentified in some clearly recognisable way, for instance by size of population or by theamount of their gross national product. It has been suggested that a line might bedrawn at a population figure of 1 million. Above this line countries wouldhave the right to attend Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings: below it they would not. Inall other respects however all the countries would, as members of theCommonwealth, have equal rights. The effect of this particular solution would be(at present levels of population) to restrict the size of Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings toabout 18.27. The advantages of this method of approach are these. It is simple andreadily understandable. It is completely objective. It would provide a means whereby the smaller territories on attaining independence could remain within theCommonwealth and enjoy the traditional range of Commonwealth marks and privileges, including membership of standing Commonwealth bodies and attendance at all meetings save those of Commonwealth Prime Ministers. They would alsobe eligible for membership of the United Nations.28. The main disadvantage of this solution is that, although all the countries would have equal international status, the fact that some of them would be deniedthe privilege of attendance at Meetings of Commonwealth Prime Ministers would attract the criticism levelled at &quot; two-tier &quot; systems. It has been an acceptedprinciple of the Commonwealth that its members have equal rights and privilegeswithin the Commonwealth regardless of their size; and this solution would offendagainst that principle. It could also be held to be illogical for countries which had achieved membership of the United Nations on equal terms with other commonwealth members to be denied a similar position within the Commonwealth.Finally, it seems unlikely that many of the smaller countries would be prepared toaccept membership on these terms. This view is confirmed by the reaction of theCypriot leaders to the suggestion of a special form of association for Cyprus.29. With the object of mitigating these objections two further suggestions have been put forward.(i) That attendance at Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings should be determined onthe same sort of basis as the membership of the Security Council of theUnited Nations.(ii) That there should be regional Meetings of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters, in which the smaller countries could take part as equals,preceding the central Meetings of the Prime Ministers of the largercountries.It is claimed that these suggestions would give smaller countries an opportunityof making their views known in the highest councils of the Commonwealth.
30. System of Rotation. If the analogy of the Security Council were followed, the Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings would comprise the Prime Ministers ofthe larger Commonwealth countries, plus the Prime Ministers of a specified numberof smaller countries selected on some system of rotation. The main advantageclaimed for this proposal is that it would keep the Prime Ministers&apos;Meetings down toa more manageable size and at the same time go some way to satisfy the aspirations of the smaller countries, each of which would have in turn an opportunity of sending their Prime Minister to the central Meetings on equal terms with the largercountries. The suggestion is, however, open to serious objections. First, it wouldnot avoid the &quot; two-tier &quot; criticism. Secondly, it would introduce a rigid formulainto Commonwealth procedure which has always been characterised by itsinformality and the absence of rules of procedure. Thirdly, the analogy of theSecurity Council is in any case misconceived since this body is the executivecommittee of a much larger organisation, whereas the Meetings of commonwealth prime Ministers are the deliberative Council of the independent Commonwealth asa whole.31. In any event this sort of solution would be inappropriate to thecircumstances of the Commonwealth as analysed in Part II of this report. If forexample the line between larger and smaller countries were drawn at a populationfigure of 1 million it seems likely that by 1970 there would be 18 larger and amaximum of six smaller countries. It would hardly be worth while to introduce a system of rotation for these six smaller countries in order to reduce the size ofthe Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings from 24 to, say, 20. Admittedly, there would bemore merit in the suggestion if it were proposed that the permanent element inthe Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings should be limited to the present number. But it isimpossible to imagine any tolerable criterion of selection which would achieve this result without involving the displacement of some of the existing members.Thus, if population were still to be the criterion, countries like New Zealand and malaya would have to be displaced from permanent representation as largercountries achieved independence; and other countries likely to command significantstatus in the world (Sierra Leone, the Federation of the West Indies and Uganda)would never be permanently represented.32. Regional Meetings. The &quot; regional&quot; solution has several variants butessentially it is that the Prime Ministers of all independent Commonwealth countriesin a particular region, irrespective of size, should hold regional meetings at various times between the central meetings of Commonwealth Prime Ministers. the advocates of this system contemplate that problems arising at such regionalmeetings which could not be resolved locally, or were considered to be of widerimportance, would be reported by the Prime Ministers of the larger countries tothe next central meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers.33. On the forecast made in Part II of this report about the constitutional development of the dependent territories to independence over the next 10 years,regional groupings might by 1970 be somewhat as follows:(a) canada the West Indies FederationBritish GuianaBritish Honduras(If the last two were independent outside the West Indies Federation)(b) The Union of South AfricaA Central African FederationGhanaNigeriaSierra LeoneKenyaUgandaTanganyika
(c) IndiaPakistanCeylonThe Federation of MalayaSingaporeAden Protectorate(d) australia new Zealand  .Western Samoa34. The position of the United Kingdom would be somewhat curious. A&quot; region &quot; consisting of the United Kingdom, Malta and Cyprus would make littlesense. On the other hand the United Kingdom could legitimately claim to belong to all regions because she would still have in each region dependent territorieswhose interests on the basis we are discussing would not otherwise be represented at the regional meetings.35. In theory a solution along these lines might seem at first sight to have someattractions. Closer analysis suggests, however, that it has a number of disadvantagesboth in principle and in practice. The motive for introducing a system of regionalmeetings is to make it possible to limit attendance at the central meetings to thePrime Ministers of the larger Commonwealth countries. It would not obviate thenecessity of establishing some criterion for discriminating between thoseindependent countries which would qualify for attendance at the central meetings and those which would not. In this respect, therefore, although constitutionallyeach country would be co-equal with the others and in no way subordinate one toanother, the system would be open to criticism as a &quot; two-tier &quot; system. On theother hand, if all the independent Commonwealth countries were entitled to attend the central Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings, there would cease to be any purpose in organising regional meetings.36. In practice it seems very doubtful whether sufficient topics of importancecould be found to make purely regional meetings of Prime Ministers worth while.Commonwealth countries are already heavily involved in regional conferences and organisations of various kinds, including both Commonwealth and foreign States.It seems unlikely that the Prime Ministers of the larger Commonwealth countries would welcome an obligation to attend yet more meetings, especially since this proposed type of regional meeting would be organised primarily in the interestsof the smaller countries. Any important subject of regional interest could moreusefully be discussed in a meeting which comprised all the independent countries of the region and not merely Commonwealth countries. Moreover, the PrimeMinisters of the smaller Commonwealth countries are not likely to regardattendance at such regional Commonwealth meetings as an adequate substitute forattendance at central meetings. The real value of the Commonwealth lies not in itsregionalism but in its transcendance over regionalism.37. In some quarters, however, the proposal for regional Commonwealthmeetings has been seen as providing a possible opportunity for the Chief ministers of the dependent territories to be brought into closer association with theindependent Commonwealth countries in the region. In principle, the objections which apply to the attendance of dependent territories at central meetings of commonwealth Prime Ministers would seem to apply with equal force to theirattendance at regional meetings. So far as concerns representation of the dependent territories at a lower level than Chief Minister, there are already plenty of opportunities of regional co-operation in international bodies, e.g., CaribbeanCommission, the Commission for Technical Co-operation in Africa south of theSahara (C.C.T.A.), the South Pacific Commission, the Colombo Plan, and throughassociate membership of various United Nations and specialised agencies; andthe United Kingdom Government have already developed means of associatingtheir dependent territories with the work of functional Commonwealth conferencesby including advisers from those territories in the United Kingdom delegation.These arrangements could be developed and improved in respect of those territories which have full internal autonomy if, as suggested in the final sentence ofparagraph 25 of this report, some of the privileges mentioned in paragraph 21 wereaccorded to them.SECRET57414 c
Possible Procedural Changes at Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings38. In the preceding paragraphs we have examined various suggestions for restricting the increase in the number of Commonwealth countries enjoying theright of attendance at Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings. Whatever their merits, these suggestions seem to be aimed at meeting a somewhat different situation from thatwhich, on our analysis, is likely to arise at least in the next 10 years or so. Theywould be more appropriate, if acceptable on other grounds, to a commonwealth in which a large number of the smaller territories had become members i.e., a commonwealth whose membership was not only very numerous but also contained a relatively large proportion of smaller countries.39. The pattern indicated by our forecast is very different. The analysis inparagraph 14 suggests that by 1970 the membership of the Commonwealth willhave increased from the present number of 10 to, at most, a total of 24. Of these17 (namely the existing members plus Nigeria, Sierra Leone, Central african federation, Federation of the West Indies, Kenya, Tanganyika and Uganda) arecountries which could not on any reasonable criterion be excluded from the full range of the privileges of existing members, including attendance at Prime Ministers&apos;Meetings. To these 17 would be added, at the most, seven of the smaller territories.In other words, the smaller territories would form less than one-third of the group.40. We have considered how far it would be possible to retain the elements of essential value in the Commonwealth relationship with an increase inmembership of this order, on the basis that all the new members would enjoy fullprivileges, including attendance at Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings.41. An increase in membership on this scale should not seriously affect thevalue of much of the day-to-day Commonwealth co-operation mutualconsultation, economic and other similar conferences, and the multitudinousactivities of private associations. Indeed, in many economic and other functionalmeetings it is already the practice for a number of the more advanced dependent territories to be represented under the wing of the United Kingdom delegation,and the increase in total numbers should be manageable.42. The serious problem is that of the Prime Ministers&apos; Meetings. these meetings are a unique element in the Commonwealth association, and their valuederives very largely from the personal relations between the Prime Ministers andthe frankness and informality of their discussions. Without some proceduralchanges it will be difficult to maintain this essential character of the Meetings ifthere is a substantial increase in the number of Prime Ministers attending.Certainly, with a membership of 20 or more, Meetings on the present model,where most of the discussion takes place in plenary session with three advisersattending each Minister, would become unwieldy; there would be something like100 people in the conference room. Indeed, it may be that, with the existing and immediately prospective membership, the plenary sessions are already in some danger of losing their intimate character.43. As the membership of the Commonwealth increases, various changes inthe organisation and procedure of the Meetings will need to be adopted if their special quality is to be preserved. The following suggestions are submitted forconsideration:(a) There might be fewer plenary sessions, and more meetings of a limited number of Prime Ministers on particular subjects.(b) At certain plenary sessions in .1960 the Prime Ministers alone sat at the table, with all advisers behind (normally one adviser sits with eachPrime Minister). This practice might be extended.(c) Prime Ministers have on occasion met without advisers. They might wishto do so more frequently; the arrangements at Marlborough house would facilitate this.(d) As the number of Prime Ministers increases, they might wish to reservemore &quot; free &quot; time for informal contacts outside the Meetings.44. We have also considered whether, as the numbers grow, some modification in the general nature of the agenda would contribute to the maintenance of thecharacter and efficacy of the discussions. It is the convention of these Meetingsthat there is no fixed agenda in the sense of a rigid programme, and we should not wish to suggest that this conception should be abandoned or that the existingfreedom of discussion should be curtailed. It may be, however, that the content of
the agenda as accepted at recent Meetings will in future, as the number of PrimeMinisters increases, prove somewhat too wide and general for effective and fruitfuldiscussions. The constitutional items are, of course, precise and obligatory. But inthe discussion of foreign affairs, instead of a general review of the international situation at large, it might help if consideration could more often be focused on specific subjects of special and current interest. It might on occasion be appropriate to remit such subjects for preliminary discussion to smaller groups of PrimeMinisters as envisaged in the suggestion made in paragraph 43 (a) above.In the discussion of economic matters, Prime Ministers might wish to concentrate attention on those problems which have a direct political content, since there are now opportunities for full consideration of economic questions at theregular meetings of Finance Ministers.45. If these suggestions were adopted, they would call for a somewhat more detailed advance preparation of the agenda and the programme of Meetings than hitherto.46. In our examination of the problem remitted to us we have throughoutassumed that it is a major objective of policy to find a place in the Commonwealthfor the smaller dependent territories if and when they attain independence. It wouldbe a frustration of much that the Commonwealth stands for if, on attainingindependence, a small country, however warm its Commonwealth sentiments, found the terms on which it could remain in the Commonwealth unacceptable andpreferred to leave it. In such circumstances these countries would proceed to independence outside the Commonwealth, would be accepted for membership ofthe United Nations, and would start their international life without the help and support that Commonwealth association can give them, and possibly withresentment against the Commonwealth which had rejected them. It would seemparadoxical if the Commonwealth, whose members have held out independence asthe goal for their dependent territories, were more restrictive in its requirements for membership than the United Nations.47. The suggestions that we have examined in this report under the headings of &quot; Statehood&quot; and &quot; Limitation of Privileges &quot; all contain the danger that,presented with the alternatives of remaining in the Commonwealth with somethingless than the full privileges of membership or of leaving the commonwealth to become an independent foreign State, most of the possible aspirants for independence within the Commonwealth might opt for the latter course.48. The only sure way of avoiding this danger would be to grant full commonwealth membership to all territories, irrespective of size, on theirattainment of independence. This is also the solution which, in principle, is mostconsistent both with the aspirations of the new nations and with the general ethos ofthe Commonwealth. It would, however, be a weighty argument against this courseif the consequent enlargement of Commonwealth membership made it impossible inpractice to maintain the essential value of the Commonwealth association as we know it.49. To judge how far the growth in membership is likely to endanger thecharacter of Commonwealth co-operation requires a forecast of the extent and nature of that growth. In Part II of this report we have made such a forecastextending over the next 10 years. We limited our analysis to this period because we felt that it was the longest for which it is profitable to plan or for which it ispossible to make other than purely speculative guesses. Our own conclusion is that,over that period at any rate, the increase in numbers may not be unmanageable.If that conclusion were&quot; accepted by Governments it should be possible to maintainthe essential character of the Commonwealth association and at the same time tocontinue to accord the full privileges of membership to dependent territories which,on attaining independence, desire to claim them.IVChequers,23rd July, 1960.(Signed)NORMAN BROOK.R. B. BRYCE.ALLEN BROWN.A. D. McINTOSH.M. J. DESAI.A. L. ADU.57414c 2
ANNEX IDEPENDENT TERRITORIES OF THE UNITED KINGDOM AND OFOTHER COMMONWEALTH COUNTRIESTerritory PopulationAden Colony        ......... 140,000Aden Protectorate......... 660,000Present Constitutional PositionElected majority in legislature and quasi-ministerial system.Western and Eastern Protectorates comprise23 States in treaty relationship with her majesty&apos;s Government, who are responsiblefor defence and external affairs and canadvise on internal matters. Ten States in western Protectorate have formed a federation.Bahamas      ...      ...      ...      ... 130,000      Legislature comprises a wholly elected lower house and a nominated Upper House.Executive Council includes unofficials, butthere is no ministerial system.Bermuda      ............ 40,000British Guiana       ......... 520,000British Honduras   ......... 80,000Brunei        ............ 70,000Christmas Island    ......... 2,000(Indian Ocean)(Australia)Cocos and Keeling Islands        ... 650(Australia)Cook Islands        ......... 20,000(New Zealand)Cyprus        ............ 550,000Falkland Islands and Dependencies 3,000Federation of Rhodesia and 8,000,000NyasalandFiji    ............... 360,000Gambia       ............ 280,000As for Bahamas.Elected majority in legislature and ministerialsystem.Elected majority in legislature; ministerialsystem to be introduced shortly.Protected State in treaty relationship with her Majesty&apos;s Government, who areresponsible, for defence and external affairs and advise the Sultan on other Governmentmatters through a High Commissioner.Governed by the Commonwealth Ministerfor Territories acting through a localrepresentative.As for Christmas Island.Legislative Assembly with elected majority.Since the 1959 London Agreement the governors responsibility for administration has been shared with a TransitionalCommittee comprising Greek and turkish cypriot Ministers.Unofficial but not elected majority in legislation-slature; Executive Council includes unofficial members, but there is no ministerial system.In Federal matters the Federation is self-governing, subject to existence of UnitedKingdom reserved powers, mainly in relationto Federal legislation, and to the ultimate responsibility of the United Kingdom forits external relations. In territorial matters the Colonial Secretary retains his responsi-bilities in Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland,while there are United Kingdom reserved powers under the Southern Rhodesiaconstitution.Official majority in legislature; ExecutiveCouncil includes unofficial members, butthere is no ministerial system.Elected majority in legislature and ministerialsystem.
Territory PopulationGibraltar     ............ 25,000High Commission Territories(a) Basutoland    ......... 640,000(b) Bechuanaland Protectorate ... 300,000(c) Swaziland     ......... 240,000Hong Kong............ 2,680,000Kenya         ............ 6,400,000Malta............... 320,000Mauritius and Dependencies      ... 610,000Nauru         ............ 4,000(Australia)Norfolk Island       ......... 1,000(Australia)North Borneo       ......... 400,000Papua and New Guinea   ...... 1,830,000(Australia)St. Helena and Dependencies    ... 5,000Sarawak      ............. 630,000Seychelles     ............ 40,000Sierra Leone         ......... 2,260,000Singapore     ............ 1,470,000Tanganyika............ 8,790,000Tokelau Islands     ......... 2,000(New Zealand)Tonga         ............ 60,000Uganda       ............ 5,680,000Present Constitutional PositionElected majority in legislature and membership(i.e. embryo ministerial) system.Executive Council with official majority and legislative Council with unofficial majorityhave recently been set up.Advisory Councils but no Legislative orExecutive Council.European Advisory Council and SwaziNational Council but no Legislative orExecutive Council.Official majority in legislature and no electedelement; Executive Council includesunofficial members, but there is no minis-terial system.Elected majority in legislature and ministerialsystem.Until 1958, Malta enjoyed virtual internal self-government. Under the present interimconstitution the administration is carried on by the Governor assisted by a nominatedExecutive Council.Elected majority in legislature and ministerialsystem.Trust Territory. Full powers of admini-stration and legislation are vested in the administrator.Administrator with elected advisory council.Official majorities in legislature and executive;no elected element or ministerial system.An unofficial majority will be introduced in the legislature later this year.Legislative Council with official majority, andall-official Executive Council.Executive Council with official majority, andan Advisory Council. There is no legislature,and the Governor alone makes laws.Elected majority in legislature; the executiveincludes elected members but there is noministerial system.Official majorities in legislature and executive.An almost entirely elected legislature and ministerial system.Full internal self-government.Unofficial majority in legislature (it will be an elected majority from September 1960) and ministerial system.Administered since 1948 as part of NewZealand.Protected State in treaty relationship with her Majesty&apos;s Government, who areresponsible for defence and external affairs and must be consulted on certain othermatters.Unofficial majority in legislature (it willbecome an elected majority in 1961) and ministerial system.
TerritoryVirgin IslandsWest Indies Federation(Antigua, Barbados, CaymanIslands, Dominica, Grenada,Jamaica, Montserrat, St. Kitts,St. Lucia, St. Vincent, trinidad and Tobago, Turks and CaicosIslands)Western Pacific High commission territories(British Solomon Islands,Gilbert and Ellice Islands, new hebrides Condominium)Western Samoa(New Zealand)ZanzibarPopulation Present Constitutional Position8,000     Elected majority in legislature and membership(z&apos;.e. embryo ministerial) system.3,100,000 Federal legislature comprises a wholly electedLower House and a nominated Upper House.There is a ministerial system and cabinet government is likely to be introducedshortly. The unit territories enjoy varying degrees of internal self-government.200,000 There are no Legislative or Executive councils in these territories and Government is entirely in official hands. Legislative and executive Councils with official majoritieswill probably be set up shortly in the BritishSolomon Islands.100,000 Trust Territory. Cabinet Government. HighCommissioner remains responsible for defence and external affairs until December1961.300,000     Official majorities in legislature and executive.A Constitutional Commissioner is now inZanzibar; his report is likely to lead to an elected majority in the legislature and a ministerial system.Note. Since some doubt exists as to the precise status of South-West Africa, the territory is not included in this Annex.July 1960.


ANNEX IICYPRUSCyprus is due to achieve independence on 16th August, 1960. Given her smallsize and population and the fact that her close links with Greece and Turkey wereto be further strengthened under the Treaties of Alliance and Guarantee, thepreliminary United Kingdom view had been that Cyprus would not be a suitablecandidate for membership of the Commonwealth and that, if the people of Cypruswere, after independence, to seek to maintain their links with the Commonwealth,this might best be achieved through some special form of association. some doubts about this solution were expressed by other Commonwealth Governments,but it was generally agreed that it should be explored in discussions with theCypriot leaders.2. These discussions were held in January 1960. The Cypriot leaders then made it clear that full membership was the only basis on&apos; which they would beprepared to recommend that their country should remain within theCommonwealth. The United Kingdom Government agreed that, should anapplication for membership be received from the Cypriot House ofRepresentatives, they would, without in any way committing themselves tosponsorship, arrange for it to be considered by the other member Governments.3. The United Kingdom Government also undertook that the legislationproviding for the independence of Cyprus should be cast in a form which wouldenable the new Republic to receive, in the interim period before its Commonwealthstatus was finally determined, the same treatment under the laws of the UnitedKingdom as is accorded to member countries of the Commonwealth. It was atfirst thought that these provisions conferring Commonwealth treatment need apply only for a period of nine months, within which time it was considered that any decision for or against membership of the Commonwealth would have beenreached. Later, however, United Kingdom Ministers decided that no such time limit should be imposed. The legislation is, therefore, now in a form which would,subject to the will of the United Kingdom Parliament, allow an independent cyprus to continue indefinitely to enjoy under United Kingdom law such Commonwealthprivileges as the receipt of Commonwealth preferences and the treatment of Cypriotcitizens as Commonwealth citizens. Thus, it will not now be essential for cyprus to achieve membership in order to ensure the continuation of such treatment in theUnited Kingdom.4. Even so, it is likely that Cyprus will apply for Commonwealth membership.This issue will probably be debated by the Cypriot House of Representatives shortly after independence.5. The arguments in favour of granting membership to Cyprus may besummarised as follows:(a) A significant section of opinion, especially in the United Kingdom, would regard the granting of Commonwealth membership to Cyprus at herexpress desire as the culmination of a process of reconciliation withthe Cypriots which would reflect credit, not only on the UnitedKingdom, but on the Commonwealth as a whole.(b) Although it was made clear to the Cypriot leaders that membership wasnot in the gift of the United Kingdom alone, but was a matter for decision by all the member countries of the Commonwealth, the Cypriotleaders are likely to have gained the impression that commonwealth governments would be sympathetically disposed. Rejection of anapplication would be regarded as a rebuff in Cyprus and would embitterrelationships possibly to an extent that would jeopardise the effective use of United Kingdom defence facilities.(c) The Cypriots attach considerable importance to the material benefitsarising from their Commonwealth association. Although, in relationto the United Kingdom, virtually all the practical advantages of membership are now to be made available to them for an indefinite period, this might not prevent them from harbouring a grudge if anapplication for membership were rejected.
(d) If Cyprus were admitted to membership of the United Nations, any doubt as to her international status would have been removed. It would thenseem illogical to suggest that, while Cyprus was qualified for united nations membership, she had not adequate status for membership ofthe Commonwealth.(e) An important and possibly undesirable precedent would be set if anindependent Cyprus, without becoming a member of theCommonwealth, continued indefinitely to enjoy the material benefitsaccorded to members under the laws of the United Kingdom andpossibly other member countries.6. The arguments against full membership may be summarised asfollows:(a) The membership of the Commonwealth has until now consisted of countries of at least moderate size, capable of exercising a valuableinfluence in world affairs. Cyprus would be the first small country,incapable of exercising such influence, to be admitted and its admissionwould constitute a precedent making it difficult to exclude other smallcountries, because of their size.(b) The special Treaty relationship of Cyprus with Greece and Turkey; thepresence of Greek and Turkish troops; and the right of intervention of the guaranteeing Powers constitute an external association such as no other Commonwealth member has.(c) The admission of Cyprus to Commonwealth membership might have theeffect of introducing tensions between Greece and Turkey intoCommonwealth counsels.(d) The goodwill of the local inhabitants, important for the effective operationof the United Kingdom bases, is not likely in the long term to bedetermined by the fact of Commonwealth membership.July 1960.
(d) If Cyprus were admitted to membership of the United Nations, any doubt as to her international status would have been removed. It would thenseem illogical to suggest that, while Cyprus was qualified for united nations membership, she had not adequate status for membership ofthe Commonwealth.(e) An important and possibly undesirable precedent would be set if anindependent Cyprus, without becoming a member of theCommonwealth, continued indefinitely to enjoy the material benefitsaccorded to members under the laws of the United Kingdom andpossibly other member countries.6. The arguments against full membership may be summarised asfollows:(a) The membership of the Commonwealth has until now consisted of countries of at least moderate size, capable of exercising a valuableinfluence in world affairs. Cyprus would be the first small country,incapable of exercising such influence, to be admitted and its admissionwould constitute a precedent making it difficult to exclude other smallcountries, because of their size.(b) The special Treaty relationship of Cyprus with Greece and Turkey; thepresence of Greek and Turkish troops; and the right of intervention of the guaranteeing Powers constitute an external association such as no other Commonwealth member has.(c) The admission of Cyprus to Commonwealth membership might have theeffect of introducing tensions between Greece and Turkey intoCommonwealth counsels.(d) The goodwill of the local inhabitants, important for the effective operationof the United Kingdom bases, is not likely in the long term to bedetermined by the fact of Commonwealth membership.July 1960.

</content>
</cab>
