<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/102/0 images: 281-282</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL ,        j^g(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)COPY NO. S C?CABINETCOLOURED IMMIGRATIONMemorandum by the Secretary of Statefor the Home department in view of the present extent of coloured immigration from the west indies, and of the strong representations about it which have been made tome by Members on both sides of the House, I think it right to bring thematter to the notice of my colleagues.2.      The net inward movement of West Indian immigrants in the first six months of this year has been about 19, 500, with over 4, 500 in each ofthe last three months.    If immigration this year continues at the recentrate, the net intake this year will be well over 40,000.3.      On the whole, the West Indian population is law-abiding, butpressure on housing, jealousy and other factors create a dangerous situation.     The danger of racial disturbances continues in Notting Hilland one or two other areas of London, but fortunately there has been norecent trouble.     The present volume of unemployment among West Indiansis not high - about 9,000 in a total coloured population of 250,000.    Itis certain, however, that if immigration continues at its present levelthe volume of unemployment will increase;   and it only requires a slightfall in the general level of employment in this country to create a veryawkward situation indeed.4.      I have been in continuous touch with the Colonial Secretary and his department about the problem.    Efforts have been made, and are continuing, to persuade the West Indian Governments to discourageemigration;   but it seems clear that these efforts are not likely to reducethe level of emigration to this country significantly so long as we have full employment.5.      We have frequently considered in the past the possibility oflegislation restricting the right of entry to immigrants who are fit andhave a job and a house to go to.    Such legislation would clearly have toapply to the whole Commonwealth and the Irish Republic, though inpractice it would probably be necessary to use it only against colouredimmigrants.    It would be impracticable to enforce it against the Irishin the absence of any immigration control between the United Kingdom andthe Irish Republic.-1-C. (60) 12819th July, I960
6.      Legislation of this sort would be controversial, and would represent a considerable breach in the doctrine that the United kingdom is the mother country to which all citizens of the Commonwealth havefree access.    I continue to hope that administrative pressure may, if itdoes not provide a solution, at any rate reduce the flow of West Indianimmigrants;   but, if this hope is not realised, I am afraid that it may benecessary for us to give further consideration to the case for some measure of statutory control.R. A. B,Home Office, S. W. 1.18th July, I960.-2-

</content>
</cab>
