<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/102/0 images: 334-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C (60) 138 COPY NO.   V3rd October, I960CABINETTHE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON the prorogation OF parliament note by the Secretary of State for the Home department i circulate, for the consideration of the Cabinet,a first draft of The queen&apos;s Speech on the Prorogation ofParliament.R. A, B.Home Office, S. W.l.3rd October, I960
SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OF parliament my Lords and Members of the House of commons.      /This year has brought Me the great happiness of my Sister&apos;smarriage. /2.     A number of visits have reinforced the deep friendships existing between My People and peoples overseas.3, In April I had the special pleasure of welcoming to London thePresident of the French Republic and Madame de Gaulle. I have beenhappy to greet here the King and Queen of Thailand and, ten days ago,the King and Queen of Nepal.4.     I was glad that the President of Peru was able to meet membersof My Family when he came here in February and that I was myself ableto receive the President of the Argentine Republic.5.     I was deeply touched by the warmth and sincerity of the reception accorded to My Husband when he visited New York in June,to open the British Exhibition.6.      My Mother has visited the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasalandto open the great Kariba Dam.    The enthusiastic welcome which Shereceived throughout her journeys in the Federation gave as much pleasureto Me as to herself.7.      The visits of members of My Family to the Caribbean were avivid reminder to all My peoples in that area of their links with theCrown and with My people in the United Kingdom.8,      My Government have supported the work of the United nations and its agencies and My Prime Minister made an important contributionto this year&apos;s session of the General Assembly.   My Government have continued to play their full part in the North Atlantic Alliance and otherregional pacts.-1-SECRET
9.      They have continued to take part in the Geneva Conference onthe Discontinuance of Nuclear Weapons Tests, in which progress has beenmade towards agreement on the prohibition of tests under effective inter-national control.   Theyplayed a leading role in the Ten-Nation Committeeon Disarmament at Geneva and supported the resolution of the united nations recommending the earliest possible resumption of international legislation for disarmament.10.    Meanwhile My Armed Forces have continued to contribute to peace and order throughout the World.11.     By the signing of the Antartic Treaty last December, the twelvegovernments concerned, which include My own and those of the UnitedStates and the Soviet Union, have agreed to co-operate in the peacefuluse of the Continent in the interests of science.12.    This year has seen steady constitutional progress in theBritish Commonwealth of Nations.   I was most happy to meet, in May,the Prime Ministers and other representatives of Commonwealth countriesTheir meeting revealed a wide measure of agreement on internationalproblems, notably on the need to lessen world tensions and to promote theeconomic and cultural progress of the less developed countries.13.    I have given My assent to an Act which established the SovereignRepublic of Cyprus, retaining for the United Kingdom certain Base areas and other military facilities in the island, and My Government look forward to a long and active friendship with the new Republic.14.    Two other countries for which My Government in the UnitedKingdom have hitherto been responsible have achieved independence.In June I surrendered My jurisdiction and withdrew My protection fromthe Somaliland Protectorate, confident that the long tradition of friendshipbetween the British and Somali peoples will continue and flourish.-2-SECRET
15.    And this month Nigeria became the eleventh Member of theCommonwealth.   My Husband and I have very happy memories of ourvisit to that great country five years ago and we, together with my government and all My people in the United Kingdom, extend to my people in Nigeria our warmest good wishes for the future.16.    I have given My assent to an Act which reflects the decision ofthe Government of Ghana to adopt a Republican Constitution.17.    My Government in the United Kingdom have continued to givefinancial help to the overseas territories for which they are responsible,including loans and grants for development, welfare and reconstruction.18.    Acts have been passed enabling the United Kingdom to take partin the Commonwealth Scholarship and Fellowship Plan and making possible a freer   movement of students and teachers between this country andthe rest of the Commonwealth.19.    My Government have also published their plan for My OverseasCivil Service, providing greater security for its members and making it easier for territories which achieve self-government to retain themin their employment.Members of the House of Commons20.   I thank you for the provision which you have made for the public services.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons21.    As part of their policy to assist the development of overseas countries, My Government have joined the new International development association and are contributing substantially to its resources.22.    They have ratified the Convention establishing the european free Trade Association, and have taken part in negotiations forremodelling the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation withthe United States and Canada as full members.
23.    Support for home agriculture and for the fishing industry hasbeen maintained.   My Government have introduced improvement grants for horticultural producers &quot;and their co-operative marketingassociations.24.    /they have continued their efforts to reach a just and reasonable of the problems of the breadth of the territorial sea and offishery limits which were left unresolved by the failure of the second world Conference on the Law of the Sea./25.   An Act has been passed to help provide additional opportunities for employment in those areas where high and persistent unemploymentexists or is threatened.26.    h y Government have announced a substantial increase in the road programme.   An Act has been passed to facilitate enforcement of the lawon road traffic and to amend the law on parking and traffic regulation.27.    An Act has been passed to improve me arrangements forlicensing air services and to ensure that all airline operatorsmaintain high standards of safety.28.   An Act has been passed to give effect to the main recommendationsof the Royal Commission on Betting, Lotteries and Gaming, by providingfor the registration of bookmakers, permitting the establishment oflicensed betting offices, and replacing the outmoded law on gaming byprovisions more acceptable to modern public opinion.29.    The law relating to charities has been consolidated and reformed,to enable the best use to be made of charitable resources for the benefitof the community.30.    Measures have been taken to make legal aid and advice more widely available.   The right of appeal to the House of Lords has been extended to criminal . cases and the law relating to contempt of courtamended.-4-SECR.ET
2 231. An Act has been passed which will give added protection to thosewho invest their savings in building societiesi32.    An Act has been passed to control the location and conditionsof caravan sites and to strengthen the procedure for enforcing planning control in England and Wales.33.    In Scotland the law on mental health has been modernised andnew provision made for the care of those afflicted in mind.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons34.    I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.October, I960-5-

</content>
</cab>
