<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/102/0 images: 350-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1960C. (60) 1414th October, I960Copy No. 5 3CABINETMEANS TEST ON STUDENTS&apos; GRANTSMemorandum by the Minister of education the Committee on Grants to Students under the Chairmanship ofSir Colin Anderson reported eleven in favour of abolishing the Means Test and four in favour of keeping but relaxing the Test. The relevant estimates of cost are:1958-59University awardsGrants to studentsin teacher training colleges, &amp;c.Cost on present basis  millions17Additional cost of recommendations :Majority   Minority22  millions6-75-8  millions4-53-5Cost on present basis  millions29381969-70Additional cost of recommendations :Majority     Minority  millions11-56-5  millions7-55-0Total3912-58 06718-012-52. These figures assume that our decision on University Awards wouldhave to be applied to students at teacher training colleges and other institutions of further education. They differ from those considered by the Education PolicyCommittee because it is now understood from the Board of Inland Revenue thatthe withdrawal of the income tax child allowance hitherto assumed to operateover three years could be effective in only two years.3. Compared with the total cost of education ( 740 millions), the differencebetween abolition and a relaxed Test will not appear to be of decisive importance.4.   The decision is therefore more one of principle and of politics.5. The question of principle turns on whether the parent or the student shouldbe regarded as the proper person to whom to look for the payment of university education. If the parent is the proper person then the Conservative principle ofnot giving money to people who can afford to pay comes into play, and the parentcould be helped by other means, e.g., through the Budget. But the great majorityof 18-year-olds to-day regard themselves and are so regarded by their parents asgrown up and no longer a proper charge on the family income. What we do aboutthe Means Test wiil be looked on as expressing our view of the dependence orindependence of the 18-year-old boy or girl.6. If the Means Test goes for the parent, the student will still be requiredto make a contribution, should he have a private income, equal to the amount bywhich his income exceeds  100.7. Educationally I favour the abolition of the Means Test because I believe it will result in more able children being kept at grammar schools since their further education would be free.57826
Ministry of Education, W. 1,4th October, 1960.8. The politics are almost all one-way. The Liberal Party has declared forabolition. All the resolutions at the Labour Party Conference are for abolition.So are all eight of the resolutions at our Party Conference. A ConservativeBack-Bench group of 10 members who have been studying educational policy areunanimous in asking for abolition.9. The students are vociferous and most other educational bodies who havegiven: me their views are for abolition.10. The Headmasters&apos; Conference have just voted 96 to 6 in favour ofabolition.11. At Scarborough we shall have to make a statement of our views. the educational Policy Committee considered this and, with the agreement of theChancellor of the Exchequer, it was decided that I could say that the Governmentneeded more time in which to consider this issue. They did not exclude thepossibility of abolition; they were clear that at the very least the means test wouldhave to be radically changed to make the contributions begin later and rise moregradually.12. Since the Educational Policy Committee met the pressure has increased,and holding as I do myself that the student should be treated as grown-up, I amasking my colleagues to consider whether it is wise only to stall at our party conference.D. E.

</content>
</cab>
