<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/65/11 images: 165-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET-DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT(79) HthaclusionsCOPY NO75CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 8 MARCH 1979at 10. 30 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon James Callaghan MPPrime Ministerie Rt Hon Michael Foot MPird President of the Counci]The Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-JonesLord Chancellorle Rt Hon Merlyn Rees MPjcretary of State for the Home DepartmentThe Rt Hon David Owen MPSecretary of State for Foreign andCommonwealth AffairseRtHon Shirley Williams MPcretary of State for Education andience and Paymaster GeneralleRtHon Eric Varley MPcretary of State for Industryie Rt Hon Roy Mason MPcretary of State for Northern Irelande Rt Hon John Morri s QC MPcretary of State for Wales* Rt Hon Albert Booth MPcretary of State for Employment[e Rt Hon Lord Peartti Privy Seal*Rt Hon John SiUdLn MP&quot;&quot;ister of Agriculture, Fisheriesi FoodThe Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn MPSecretary of State for EnergyThe Rt Hon Peter Shore MPSecretary of State for the EnvironmentThe Rt Hon Bruce Millan MPSecretary of State for ScotlandThe Rt Hon Fred Mulley MPSecretary of State for DefenceThe Rt Hon David Ennals MPSecretary of State for Social ServicesThe Rt Hon Joel Barnett MPChief Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Roy Hattersley MPSecretary of State for Prices andConsumer ProtectionSECRET
SECRETeRtHon William Rodger s MPcretary of State for Transporte Rt Hon John Smith MPcretary of State for TradeThe Rt Hon Stanley Orme MPMinister for Social SecurityThe Rt Hon Harold Lever MPChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Michael Cocks MPParliamentary Secretary, TreasurySECRETARIATSir John HuntMr W I MclndoeSir Clive RoseMr M D M FranklinMr D B SmithMr D E R Faulkner(Items 1, 2 and 5)(Items 3 and 4)(Items 3 and 4)(Item 5)(Items 1 and 2)CONTENTSSubjectPARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSINDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSIndustrial Action affecting the Scottish CourtsThe &quot;Times&quot; and &quot;Sunday Times&quot; newspapersFOREIGN AFFAIRSVietnamHong KongRhodesiaMiddle EastChinaCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSEuropean Monetary System and the CommonAgricultural PolicyDEVOLUTIONOutcome of the ReferendaPage11133344iiSECRET
CONFIDENTIALj&amp;IAMENTARY1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons during the following week.MISTRIAL.klRSastrial Action:cting theittish Courts2. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND said that hehad so far avoided introducing emergency legislation to deal withthe problems created by the selective industrial action being takenby members of the Society of Civil and Public Servants (SCPS) andthe Civil and Public Services Association (CPSA) in the ScottishCourts.    The strike was, however, now in its second week, andpressure for legislation was increasing.    It would soon be essentialto make provision for the extension of time limits if rights orproceedings were not to lapse, and to regularise the position in otherrespects.    He therefore proposed, subject to the agreement ofcolleagues concerned, to announce before the weekend his intentionto introduce legislation on these matters,    A meeting of theMinisterial Committee on Economic Strategy, Sub-Committee on PayNegotiations (EY(P)) had been arranged for that afternoon at whichthe industrial action by the SCPS and CPSA would he discussed, butthe outcome was unlikely to have any immediate effect on theScottish Courts.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said that theSecretary of State for Scotland, in consultation with the otherMinisters concerned, should consider urgently the need for andscope of an emergency Bill for the purposes which the Secretary ofState had indicated.    The industrial action by the SCPS and the CPSA,in Scotland and elsewhere, would be discussed by EY(P) that after-noon and an approach to Mr Len Murray (General Secretary of theTrades Union Congress) in respect of the Scottish Courts could beconsidered if it seemed likely to be helpful.The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister1 ssumming up of their discussion.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that after^ay Times&quot; prolonged negotiations an agreement had been signed early thatl&apos;spapers morning by representatives of the management and of the five unionsinvolved in the dispute at Times Newspapers Ltd.    It would becomeeffective if subsequently endorsed by the Board of Directors and bythe executives of the unions concerned.    It provided for theimmediate re-engagement of those staff whose contracts had beenterminated as a result of the dispute, and for their full reinstate-ment at the point when the newspapers resumed publication. Duringthe period between their re-engagement and reinstatement, finalagreements would be concluded on such matters as workingCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALarrangements, staffing levels and the application of new technology:the issues had been identified and there would be timetables withinwhich they would be resolved.    Reductions in manning levels wouldtake place according to an agreed programme and would be voluntarywith generous compensation for staff made redundant.    There was agood chance that the agreement would be accepted by both sides inthe dispute;  resistance was likely to be strongest in the NationalGraphical Association but if their members accepted the agreementit could be hoped that members of the other unions would do thesame.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet warmly congratulated the Secretary of State forEmployment on his handling of the negotiations and on their outcome,which had been possible only because he had gained the full trust ofboth management and unions.    It was important that the agreementshould be kept strictly confidential until it had been considered bythe Board of Directors and the executives of the unions concerned.The Cabinet -2.       Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALE1GNAIR3-amrioussrence:79) 10thelusions,ate 53. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatin an effort to find some way of promoting a peaceful settlement inVietnam, we had recently taken the initiative in suggesting to theother four Permanent Members of the Security Council that theremight be a case for reconvening the 1954 Conference on Indo-China.There was no implication that we would wish to see the co-chairmanship continued and it would be necessary to enlarge themembership.    But the 1954 Conference seemed a useful basis fromwhich to start.    The Prime Minister had written to the PrimeMinister of Australia, Mr Malcolm Fraser, and the Prime Minister ofIndia, Mr Morarji Desai, on similar lines and had also spoken toPresident Carter.    Since we had taken this action the Chinese hadannounced their intention to withdraw and had actually begun to do so,and the Vietnamese had responded positively to a Chinese invitationfor direct bilateral talks.    These developments had occurred beforethere had been time for any considered reaction to oar initiative.Before the Chinese withdrawal, there was a chance that the Russiansmight have responded favourably.    This was now less likely since,following the withdrawal, any conference would be bound to concentrateprimarily on the Vietnam invasion of Cambodia.gKongTHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY reported that theGovernor of Hong Kong had accepted an invitation from the Chinese tovisit Peking.    This was a welcome move.    The climate was probablybetter now for trying to make some arrangements about Hong Kong&apos;sfuture than it had ever been.Bsiaviouserence:10thelusions,ate 5THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that theSecurity Council debate on the African Group&apos;s resolution about theApril elections was likely to end in a vote that day.    The presenttext of the resolution was unacceptable both to us and the Americans,particularly because of the operative paragraph which sought to preventany State from sending observers to the elections.    We hoped to beable to get away with abstention, accompanied by an explanation ofvote, but we might have to veto.    The Ministerial Group on SouthernAfrica had discussed this question earlier that day.    They hadconcluded that some Conservative Members of Parliament werecertain to go to Rhodesia during the elections and there would beadvantage therefore in ensuring that some Labour Members went too,so that the Opposition would not be alone in having first hand reportsof what took place.    If there was strong pressure in the House ofCommons to send a Parliamentary delegation, the Government wouldconsider this, but it would be preferable to encourage Labour Membersto go on some other basis, possibly under the auspices of anindependent organisation.    It was probable that the United StatesCongress would send a delegation to observe the elections.    But itwould have to be recognised that anyone who did go would be taking a3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALmajor security risk in travelling round the country. TheMinisteriax Group had also concluded that we should begin to encouragethe idea that after the April elections there would need to be furtherelections under international supervision, in which all the NationalistParties should participate.    There were however already signs ofserious divisions within the regime and it was clear that the conflictbetween the Matabele and the Shona would create major problems inthe future.Eastlionsitence:19) 10thtlusions,ste 5THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that theEgyptian Prime Minister had recently told him that he thought thenegotiations would end in agreement.    But problems would arise isubsequently over negotiations about Gaza and the West Bank. Someway would have to be found of getting the Palestinian LiberationOrganisation (PLO) co join in these negotiations and we should have tofind a basis for dealing with the PLO without however according themrecognition.    The policy of going for a bilateral agreement was a highrisk one.    If Egypt was unable to gain the support of other Arabcountries, the situation could be dangerous.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had heard nothing directly aboutPresident Carter&apos;s intentions.    His visit to Egypt and Israel was abold move which was characteristic.    It was to be hoped that theground had been adequately prepared in advance.    There had beenreports in the Press that the Americans intended to maintain amilitary presence in the area and, if true, this would serve a usefulpurpose in reassuring not only the Israelis but also other Middle Eastcountries.    A bilateral agreement would certainly carry risk.; but itwas arguable that total breakdown would represent an even greaterrisk.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that his visit hadachieved most of the objectives which had been set for it. Theindustrialists accompanying him felt that it had been valuable inopening up new opportunities.    The fact that we had been able to signan agreement for trade amounting to about  7 billion had proved agreat stimulus.    Several contracts had been concluded or broughtnear to completion, for example, for coal-mining equipment and civilaircraft.    There was no doubt that British businessmen would have towork very hard to secure contracts, but there was certainly businessto be had.    One problem which would need to be resolved concernedaccommodation arrangements for resident British businessmen.There was a great lack of suitable accommodation and British firmswould depend a great deal on support from the British Embassy,The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary was looking into thisproblem and it might be necessary to set up some special organisation.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALHe was told that the turn out of Chinese leaders to meet him wasunprecedented.    He had seen Prime Minister Hua and also theForeign Minister.    He had avoided any further commitment onHarriers at this stage:  and had spoken on agreed lines about theChinese incursion into Vietnam without incurring resentment.The Prime Minister Hua had expresjed the hope that the PrimeMinister would find time to visit China and was looking forward tothe Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary&apos;s visit.The Cabinet -Took note.MUNITYAIRSpeanetary Systemthe Commonculturalcyousrence:&quot;9) 8thlusions,1 54. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat, as a result of the discussions in the Agriculture Council on5/6 March, the French had now lifted their reserve on the introduc-tion of the European Monetary System (EMS).    After consultationwith him, the Minister of Agriculture had successfully resistedpressure from other member states to subscribe to arrangementsfor reducing monetary compensatory amounts (MCA&apos;s) which wouldhave weakened our stand on a freeze on Common AgriculturalPolicy (CAP) prices.    Thanks to solid support from the ItalianMinister of Agriculture, we had not been totally isolated.   Now thatthe link between EMS and MCAs had been broken we should expectmore support from the Commission for our stand on common prices.We should nevertheless be unpopular with other member states andit was important to maintain a solid Government stance. TheMinisterial Committee on European Questions would be meeting laterin the day to consider the outcome of the Agriculture Council and hewould report to the Prime Minister in preparation for the EuropeanCouncil on 12/13 March.    President Giscard would probably now tryto make the start of EMS the formal centrepiece of that meeting.Discussions about the Council&apos;s dispute with the European Assemblyover the Budget for 1979 had been referred to a meeting of the Councilof Budget Ministers on 20 March.    President Giscard would push hisproposal for an Euro/Arab/African conference.In a brief discussion, the importance of building up the case forgreater economic convergence within the Community was stressed.If we were to aim at correcting the present imbalance in theCommunity Budget within 3 years, it would require massive reductionsin our annual net contribution and the sooner this started happening thebetter.5CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatwe would want the coming European Council to deal with some of themajor Community problems.    It was still his intention to concentrateon the CAP at the March meeting but to put down a firm marker aboutthe convergence issue.    This would need then to be brought to acrunch later with adequate preparation and the maximum chance ofsuccess.The Cabinet -Took note.6CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALf0LUTIONcome of:Referendatio-us ;,rence:79) 10thelusions,tel5. THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was not necessary for theGovernment to react quickly to the referenda.    It was entirelyreasonable to allow time for all the Parties to reflect on the resultsand declare their attitudes to them.    There was a statutory duty to-lay draft Orders for the repeal of the Acts and the Orders would haveto be laid.    But the timing of this required careful consideration.Although there appeared to be a growing acceptance that the commence-ment of the Scotland Act should not be contemplated on the basis of thereferendum result, the actual repeal of the Act raised quite differentissues, particularly against the background that a majority of thevotes cast in the Scottish referendum had been for its implementation.The objective might be to explore in the interval between laying theOrders and their debate whether agreement could be reached throughdiscussions with other Parties on the possible amendment of theScotland Act and on administrative arrangements which could providesome measure of d3volution to Wales.In discussion it was agreed that the result of the referendum inScotland did not orovide a sure or acceptable basis for the implementa-tion of devolution in Scotland as proposed by the Scotland Act and thatthis was accepted even by Government supporters who had alwaysbeen firmly committed to devolution.    The Conference of the ScottishCouncil oi the Labour Party, which began that evening, would notembarrass the Government by demanding the implementation of theAct.    But the repeal of the Act, particularly if supported by theGovernment or achieved by the votes or abstentions of Labour PartyMembers, would have immediate consequences for the continuedexistence of the Government and would operate to the advantage ofthe Scottish National Party in a General Election.    A free vote on therepeal Order would split the Parliamentary Labour Party.    As forWales, the repeal of the Wales Act would have to be accepted, althoughit would be important to maintain a commitment to devolution and toconsider whether alternative proposals could be announced to improvethe government of Wales.In discussion of the prospects for inter-Party talks, it was suggestedthat the Conservative Party would not be in a strong position, giventheir clear commitment to the consider ation of all proposals fordevolution on an all-Party basis, if they continued to maintain thatParliament must now first reach conclusions on the repeal of theActs.    This could nevertheless remain their position and, if so,inter-Party talks could quickly founder.    The Liberal Party couldbe expected to be ready to enter discussions, but they would want topropose a system of proportional representation for a ScottishAssembly and to suggest a reduction in the number of Scottish MPsat Westminster.    The Scottish National Party would also welcomesuch changes on which a Government concession was not possible.On the other hand, the Scottish National Party would not accept anyweakening of the Government1 s proposals for devolution and the onlycourse would be to explore whether, on their own view of theirelectoral prospects, they would be prepared to continue discussions7CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALfor some time.    It had to be expected that inter-Party talks ondevolution would be no more productive now than when attemptedpreviously, but so long as they continued, the prospect remainedof avoiding the Scottish National Party voting with the Oppositionon any motion of confidence.    It was nevertheless doubtful whetherthe Ulster Unionists and Plaid Cymru would be prepared to abstainon such a motion and the Liberal Party was committed to seeking anearly General Election.In further discussion it was suggested that talks should begin withthe other Parties before the draft repeal Orders were laid. Oncethe Orders were laid, the pressures for their debate would be strongand the Government could not escape announcing its intentions onthem.    To enter discussions before the Orders were laid wouldallow a better assessment to be made of the attitudes of other Parties,the time at which the Orders might best be laid and the position whichthe Government should adopt for the debates on the Orders, Onepossibility could then be to ask Parliament to reject the repealOrder   for the Scotland Act on the Government undertaking not tointroduce a commencement order in this Parliament,    This wouldnot rule out the subsequent repeal of the Act by new legislation, andthis could be made clear.    It was probable that the Liberal Partyand the Scottish National Party would be found ready to support sucha proposal and there would be good grounds for urging theGovernments own supporters who were opposed to devolution not togo against the majority view of both the Labour Party and the Scottishpeople on so critical a matter.    On the other hand, it was argued thatthe laying of the draft Orders could not be long delayed; theGovernment must not appear to be seeking to avoid in any way thestatutory duty which the Acts imposed.    Although some statement ofintention would be essential once the Orders were laid, this could beto propose discussions to all other Parties on devolution in the lightof the referenda.    This would provide the possibility of postponingdebates on the Orders for some time and allow a more consideredview to be taken of the attitude the Government should itself adopt forthe debates.    Essential to this process would be consultations witjiinthe Parliamentary Labour Party in which it was already evident onall sides that the issue of devolution need not be determined quickly.Although it was recognised that only the Government could providetime for debate on the repeal Orders once they were laid, in furtherdiscussion it was noted that the Conservative Party could seek tosecure an early debate by a motion of censure and might secure amajority.    This risk might be pre-empted if the Government tabledits own motion of confidence containing a continuing commitment todevolution at a time when maximum support for such a motionappeared in prospect and whilst minority Parties were still preparedto continue in discussions with the Government on devolution.    On theother hand, it was suggested that the support of the Liberal Partycould not be assured in a vote of confidence and any firm commitmentto devolution would be divisive among the Governments supporters.8CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet should resume their discussion on 15 March.    At that timesome clearer assessment might be possible of the likely attitudesand intentions of the Scottish National Party and the Scottish LabourParty.    The Cabinet had ag reed that it was not necessary to movequickly in announcing the Governments intentions on devolutionfollowing the referenda, but he would again make clear in the Housethat the Government would not seek to avoid the statutory obligationto lay repeal Orders and he would be ready to indicate that thelaying of the drafts would not be long delayed.    In the resumeddiscussion, consideration could again be given to what was to besaid when the draft Orders were laid and the prospects for inter-Party talks. A decision would then be necessary on when the Ordersshould be laid.The CabinetTook note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.Cabinet Office8 March 19799CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
