<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/31 images: 244-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of most secret copy No.W.P. (43) 431.4th October, 1943.WAR CABINET.ARMOURED TRAINING AREAS FOR UNITED STATES FORCES in southern  COMMAND.Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.1. THE proposals put forward in the memorandum by the Secretary ofState for War (W.P. (43) 429) will have a very serious effect on food production.1 append a note giving some details of the agricultural practice in the areas con-cerned, of the food produced and of the class of farmers affected. There is nodoubt that the use of these areas for armoured training will also have a gravepsychological and political effect in the counties concerned.2. It is noted that the proposal to apply Defence Regulation 52 may resultin the areas not being entirely lost to food production, but there is some dangeriu taking the Wolds Training A close analogy.  While it may be true thatin that area 60 per cent, of the 1943 harvest is likely to be gathered and that thisjustifies user under Defence Regulation 52, with the consequent paymentof compensation to farmers for damage done, it must be remembered that theWolds Area was not made available for armoured training until the 1st june last, when the crops were established and all cultivations, manuring, &amp;c, hadbeen carried out in the normal way without military interference. Moreover, itis understood that two Armoured Divisions only have been training over the100.000 acres comprising the Wolds Training Area, whereas if the proposals under consideration are carried into effect, five American Armoured Divisionswill be training over approximately 160,000 acres, apart from the area available on Salisbury plain. The areas will, therefore, be subjected to more extensivemilitary user and it is to be expected that the salvage of crops will work out at a lower percentage than in the case of the Wolds. Further, it must not be over-looked that the sheep and the greater part of the cattle had to be cleared off theWolds area, thus entailing a loss of food production which is not reflected in a percentage figure as regards the harvest salvaged.3. From the appendix to this memorandum it will be seen that live-stock,and particularly dairy-stock, occupy a prominent part in the agricultural pictureand the loss of milk production from these areas would be a very serious matter.4. Reference to the Secretary of State for War&apos;s memorandum will make itclear how the procedure adopted in regard to the provision of training facilitiesfor the American Forces places me in a very difficult position. The provision of accommodation, neV or existing, is apparently the first step undertaken and when this has been arranged (without necessarily referring to my Department) ademand for land for training in the vicinity comes forward automatically. Butat this stage considerations of quartering make it impossible to vary the locationsfor training and if, as in the present case, there is not sufficient land of little or noagricultural value in the vicinity, it follows that serious prejudice to food pro-duction becomes inevitable.[26184]
5. As regards the proposals for provision of areas for American troopsother than Armoured Divisions, ihis will inevitably result in further interferencewith food production but not to anything like the extent which is certain in thecase of the Armoured Divisions, and subject to proper safeguards and discussionof details between the Departments concerned, I would not feel justified in raisingobjection at this stage.6. While I appreciate that, if there is an overriding decision that theAmerican Armoured Divisions shall be stationed in this country, then training facilities must be provided, I feel bound to express regret that it has not beenfound possible to arrange for such facilities on areas already available to the war department for training purposes which total 9,648,000 acres in Great Britain,including some 3,000.000 acres in England ancl Wales.7. I am already faced with the &quot;Overlord&quot; proposals for naval assaulttraining which I realise are vital, but will probably entail the surrender of 75,000acres or more, including a substantial area of good agricultural land, and if theAmerican proposals are approved, it will mean that my efforts to maintain, andeven increase in the future, the 1943 level of home food production will be seriously affected.&quot;(Initialled) R. S. H.Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries,1th October, 1943.APPENDIX.Armoured Training Areas for United States Army.The total area now required (excluding Salisbury Plain) is set out below.Summary.Plan.	County.	Description.	Already taken under D.R. 51.	Proposed Area.	Total. Acres. 19,020 9,350 18,500 14,600 11,140 10,000 30,000 22,500 22,100B C D E , ( G H	Wilts Wilts Wilts Wilts Wilts Wilts Berks Glos Oxon	Wylve  ... Wylye......... Collingboiirne ... Calstone and All Cannings Marlborough Aldbourne Berkshire Downs Temple Guiting Hook-Norton   ...	Acres. 6,480 2,310 7,400	Acres. 12,540 7,040 18,500 14,600 3,400 10,000 30,000 22,500 22,100		Total		16,530	140,680	157,210It will be appreciated that food production is affected over a larger areathan that required by the Military because, in certain instances, only parts of farms are taken, e.g., in Wiltshire the farm schedules show a total of 79.1&quot;25acres (excluding land held under D.R. 51) as against the area of new land of66,080, a difference of 13,045 acres or 16-5 per cent. On the other hand, inBlock A the farm schedules figure is less than the total area, which is accountedfor by the &quot;Great Ridge&quot; area of approximately 3,500 acres not appearing in the farm schedules. In order to give a true picture of the effects on foodproduction, the figures quoted below refer to the whole of the farms affected asextracted from the farm schedules.4Wiltshire.The Wylye A reas (Blocks A and B). The new land proposed to be takencovers an area of 20,000 acres affecting 52 farms containing 3,000 head of cattle,including 36 dairy herds (1,425 milking cows), 5 being attested, and 12,120 sheep-The 20,000 acres include Arable 10,500 acres, approximately 52-5 per cent.--Pasture 4,500 acres, approximately 22-5 per cent. Rough grazing 5,000 acres,approximately 25 per cent.
This area comprises rolling country with practically all the ploughable highland now under cultivation with lower slopes of excellent arable running downto good water-side pastures. The area includes some of the very highly productivevale land running through the Deverills. These two blocks are occupied by men ofthe highest agricultural standing, including Messrs. R. Stratton, J. M. Stratton,Major Morrison, M.P., Messrs. Pond, Jeans, White, &amp;o, names known throughoutthe agricultural world.The villages of Stockton, Sherrington, Codford, Upton Lovell, Gorton, SuttonVeny, and the Deverills lie within or on the outskirts of these areas, with conse-quent hardship to the inhabitants should the agricultural industry be seriously affected.The Colling bourne Area [Block C) affects approximately 21,000 acresbounded on the S.W. by Salisbury Plain and its Northern boundary forms thehigh land overlooking the Pewsey Vale. The Eastern half of the area includesmuch of the Wexcombe property, farmed by Mr. Hosier, one of the best knownfarmers in the county, and runs up to the Hampshire boundary.Fifty-four farms are affected. These contain approximately 12,500 acres of arable, 5,000 acres of pasture, 3,500 acres of rough grazing, scrub andwoodland.Stock carried includes 46 dairies (2,000 milking beasts), 2,000 other cattle and between 2,000 and 3,000 sheep.This area is not of the highest quality land but is mostly in the hands ofgood men and is well farmed. Many good samples of barley have been grownon this area.Land on the Northern boundary of this area is occupied and farmed withthe Pewsey Vale holdings, from Manningford in the West to Grafton in the East,and by divorcing the areas the Pewsey farms would be seriously affected.Calstone, All Cannings and Marlborough Areas (Blocks D and E). The new proposals affect 21,000 acres. Block D can best be described as open rollingcountry. Block E is really the Southern slope of the &quot;Marlborough downs slopingdown to the Kennett Valley. The whole area is well farmed; much of the landformerly poorish pasture and used for young stock and sheep, has been broken up and is now producing heavy cereal crops. The area includes some of themost highly farmed land in the county, pedigree cereal crops being grown. the names of Swanton, Osborne, Farthing, Maundrell and Horton are synonymouswith good farming.The arable acreage is 9,849. while the grassland of 11,000 acres includes somegallops and downland unsuitable for ploughing. Thirty-two farms are affected.The stock carried includes approximately 4,000 head of cattle including 24 dairies(approximately 1,600 dairy beasts), 5,000 sheep. The sheep include ram breed-ing flocks of Hampshire Down sheep.Aldbourne Area. As regards that portion of Block F situated in Wiltshire,some 15,000 acres will be affected. Of this area some 8.000 acres are arable, 3,500acres pasture and 3,500 acres rough grazing (high down land). 25 farms are affected, these being occupied by men of the highest category and include MajorBland, Captain Brown, Messrs. Hickman, Wilson, Bomford, Peploe, &amp;c.The stock comprises 2,000 head of cattle, including 1,000 dairy cows, 21dairies, 5,300 sheep including ram breeding flocks of Hampshire Down.This is an area of excellent land very well farmed.Berkshire.Block F situated in Berkshire comprises some 30,000 acres stretching fromBishops Down in the West across the Lambourn Downs, Wantage Down, IsleyDown to the East Isley Abingdon Road which forms the Eastern boundary. / Thearea stretches from West to East for approximately 14 miles. The average depthis approximately 3^ miles.73 farms will be affected. Approximately 25,000 acres are arable and 5,000acres pasture.The major portion of the area is thinnish soil over chalk, but there are usefulareas of clay with flint, rather more productive.The cultivation of the area has been much improved since the outbreak ofwar. The average-size farm is over 400 acres, 17 being over 700, with 6 over the1,000 acres mark. Many well-known agriculturists farm in this area, 5,000 acresbeing part of the Lockinge Estate owned and occupied by Mr. A. T. Loyd,Chairman of the Berkshire War Agricultural Executive Committee.
The stock carried includes 4,734 cattle and 12,833 sheep, many of the dairy-herds being attested. The sheep include many ram-breeding flocks of HampshireDown.The fact should be stressed that the proposal relates to the high arable andstock-rearing areas, but 36 farms are left with thin low-lying areas and equip-ment. making this area entirely uneconomic if run alone, and consequentlyproduction from land not actually in the proposal will also be seriously affected.Gloucestershire.The block marked G comprises some 22,000 acres. The land is, in general,of fairly good quality of the Cotswolcl type, and very good crops of corn are grown.The pasture land varies from moderate to fairly good. The stock carried includes640 milking cows and 1,650 other cattle, a large proportion of which are dairyanimals reared for sale for the purpose of milk production outside the area.Considerable reclamation and regeneration of land has been carried out in thearea, not only by the Gloucestershire War Agricultural Executive Committee, butby two business men Mr. Victor Riley, the motor manufacturer, and Mr. JamesBourne, of Messrs. Bourne and Hollingsworth and the farming of other laudhas been considerably improved since the war. Large areas more or less ranchedfor young stock and sheep before the war are now under cultivation.The northern end of the area and a strip of land about 5 miles wide runningfrom Guiting Power to Sevenhampton are mainly arable and of better qualitythan the remainder. Alternative land to these areas, of lower agricultural value,is available west of Charlton Abbots to Cleeve Common, and then south toWhittington.Oxfordshire.The Hook Norton area (Block H) comprises approximately 22.100 acres, ofwhich 10.853 acres are arable and 9,799 acres pasture. Here is an area of littlefarms (191 being affected), an average size of approximately 115 acres. Many ofthe farms are undulating in character with brashy soil, excellent sheep and barleyland, but of late years the occupiers have been turning more and more to dairyingand cattle-rearing.A larsre head of stock is carried; 155 of the 191 farms run dairies, the totalstock carried being 1,678 head. Young stock number 4.328, sheep number12.242. and there are some on most of the farms with some very excellent pure-bredOxford Down flocks.Summary.(Excluding land already requisitioned under Defence Regulations.)County.	Area.	Farms.	Arable.	Pasture and Hough Crazing.	Dairy Cattle.	1 Other    ! Q1 Cattle.   ! Sheei)&apos;	Wilts...... Berks ... Glos...... Oxon   ...	Acres. 79.125 30,000 22,000 22,100	163 73 70 191	Acres. 40,997 25,000 13,300 10,853	Acres. 38,128 5,000 5,300 9,800	5,838 2,316 640 1,678	6,860 2,418 1,650 4,328	24,685 12.S33 6,150 12,242	153,225	497	90,150	58,228	10,472	15,256	55,910



</content>
</cab>
