<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/253/0 images: 562-574</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. SECRET.CP. 22 (35) COPY NO.       ^ &apos;CABINET. STATE OF TRADE - DECEMBER, 1954.Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate to my colleagues a summary of the reports submitted to the Board of Trade Advisory Council on the state of trade in December, 1934.W.R.Board of Trade,28th January, 1935.11
A.O. 314,BOARD OF TRADE ADVISORY COUNCIL.State of Trade, December. 1954,Summary of reports submitted by members of the Board of Trade Advisory Council (supplemented in some oases with statistical information from other sources).Overseas trade.    Imports in December 1934 at  63.3m., showed practically no increase over the imports in December 1933. Exports of United Kingdom produce and manufactures were  34.3m. compared with  30.4m., while re-exports were  3.6m, as compared with  4,0m,    Imports in the year 1934 were  732,3m, as compared with  675.0m. in the previous year and total exports  447.4m. as compared with  417.0,    The excess of imports over exports for the year was  285.0m, and for 1933  258.0m.Employment.     Tho employment position in December showed some improvement as compared with a month earlier.    The total number of persons on the registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at 17th December was 2,085,815, a decrease of 34,970 as compared with 26th November.The main variations were:-The estimated number of insured persons aged 16-64 in employment at 17th December was 10,248,000.     This was 36,000 more than at 26th November, 1934, and 237,000 more than a year before.London- 8,952* 112- 2,507337- 19,914- 9,321* 5,893* 56South Eastern South Western Midlands ....North Eastern North Western Scotland ....Wales
Employment continued to Improve in the coal mining, cotton and motor vehicle industries and the distributive trades.      Some improvement was also recorded in general engineering, hat and cap manufacture, the glass bottle industry, printing and bookbinding, and hotel, boarding house, etc, service.On the other hand there was a further decline in the building industry and in fcinplate manufacture, and reductions in employment also occurred in the pottery, boot and shoe, woollen and worsted, hosiery and leather industries.Rail Traffic.    During the four weeks ended 30th December, railway traffic receipts showed a decrease of  170,000 (1.5$) as compared with the corresponding   period of 193?.    Passenger and general merchandise traffic showed increases of 1.3$ and 0.5$ respectively, but there was a decrease of 809$ in coal, coke and patent fuel.    For the year ended 31st December the total receipts amounted to  148.9m, as. against  143.9m.  in 1933.Road Traffic.    Motor vehicles newly registered in November amounted to 25,778, an Increase of 3,677 (16.6$) over a year ago.     The increase comprises 2,878 private cars and 799 other vehicles.      In the same month 1,962 motor cycles were newly registered, an increase of 14.5$ over the previous November.Shipping.    The index number for shipping freights for December (1913 = 100) was 80.77 and is slightly less favourable than in November last (83.68) and in December a year ago (87.95).      The preliminary estimate of the amount of tonnage laid up at ports in Great Britain and Ireland on the 1st January is 878,000 net tons.    This io a slight increase over the figure for 1st October last (818,000 tons) but a sLibstantial decrease as compared with
a year ago (1,340,000 tone).The amount of tonnage under oonstruotlon in the United Kingdom on 31st December was 597,000 gross tone as against 304,000 at 30th September last and 332,000 tons a year ago.      The amount of tonnage commenced in the December quarter was 93,000 tons as against 177,000 tone in the September quarter.Banking and Finance.     In December, the supply of money was adequate to requirements generally at -g$.    The seasonal increase in the note circulation took the total to the record figure of  405.2m.   Perhaps to counteract the possibility of a consequent stringency, the issue of Treasury bills was restricted, the Government borrowing on Ways and Means Account, and a rise in rates was prevented. Bill rates at the beginning of the month were       to ^ for December bills and a minimum of 9A&amp;fc for longer maturities. By the 10th, when the Banks restricted purchases In view of the end of the year, rates had settled down to between -gfo and but little business was done.      The averagetender rates for Treasury bills moved between ll/2d.^ on the 7th and 6/6d.$ on the 28th.The principal foreign exchanges moved steadily against sterling.     With the investment demand for American currency it was impossible to keep the dollar down, yet it was noticeable that the dollar-franc rate was kept firmly belovj the point at which gold would leave France.It is probable that although foreign acceptanoe business Is expanding in come directions,  the volume of trade financed by bills on London is showing   little increase.    The tendency for countries to meet their urgent needs by barter agreements and the exohange restrictions in operation make remittances in respect of trade and other debts progressively more difficult.      There are no signs of any revival as yet
*5 r? &apos;1in the flow of new capital to debtor countries.    Prices in the &quot;Gold Bloc&quot; countries, particularly Prance, are still falling, and recently wholesale prices in the United States of America have again shown an upward tendency,    The under-valuation of the dollar, however, both in terms of sterling and gold currencies,  is still apparent.      The appointment of a new Governor in the Bank of France is taken to mean that the Government intend to create a more effective short-term money market through which it can finance its temporary requirements more cheaply.Coal.      The average weekly output of ooal during the 13 weeks ended &quot;22nd December was 4,600,000 tons aa compared with 4,431,000 tons in the same quarter of 1933, an increase of 3.81;$.     The average number of persons employed during this period was 767,200 as against 767,800 a year before.Home consumption of ooal and coke in November was Qf0 higher than in November, 1933.      Exports in December at 3,074,860 tone were 25,000 tons more than the year earlier. Increased tonnages were consigned to Sweden, Germany, Spain and Italy, but exports to Denmark. Norway and Prance showed a decrease.      The industry welcomes the withdrawal of the embargo on British coal entering the Irish Free State.Iron and Steel.    There was the usual seasonal contraction in business in December but the continued activity of the home consuming industries, together with the Government&apos;s shipping policy and the heavy re-equipment projects of the railways, make the outlook satisfactory. The output of pig-iron in 1934 was 5,978,500 tons as compared with 4,136,000 in 1933$ while the production of steel ingots and castings was 8,859,700 tons as compared with 7,024,000 tons.    At the same time imports have increase and are causing some apprehension,
^n Sootland, the outlook is promising,    Good orders are in hand and consuming industries generally are well supplied with work.      Further shipbuilding orders have been placed on the Clyde and export trade also shows signs of revival.    On the Korth-East Coast, certain large works had to continue operations throughout Christmas and idle plant is to be put into operation.      Contracts for the delivery of Cleveland pig-iron have been entered into for the whole of 1935.    Export to India should improve and an order for 8,000 tons of plates has been received from Russia,    In Sheffield, basic steel production continues at a record level and additional furnaces are to be started.    There has been a seasonal fall in acid steel, but the demand for special steels has been well maintained, especially from the motor industry.    In South Wales the slow recovery continues.    A good level of activity in the heavy steel section seems to be assured.&apos; Tinplate exports in recent weeks were slightly above those of -a year ago, but there has been a decline on the year ac a whole, and the Improvement in production must be attributed to the growing use of tinplates in the home canning industry.Engingering.      In certain sections the improvement in trade reveals a tendency to slow down but no decided check is evident.      In electrical engineering, orders from abroad and contracts in connection with the Grid and the growing needs of industry for electrical equipment make the outlook promising.      Business was maintained in the machine tools section and the exhibition in London has brought many enquiries.      Business in motor cars is in advance of the same period last year and the Olympia Cycle and Motor-Cycle Exhibition produced over  2 m. worth of orders.    Substantial orders for railway rolling stock have been placed recently on home account and overseas business has improved.The employment position among members    of the Amalgamated Engineering Union has been fairly stable in recent months.
*5 9QO) ki dMachine Tools.       Exports of machine tools in December were valued at  161,000 as compared with  59,000 a year ago and  137,000 in December, 1932.    Exports to Russia amounted to  54,000 as against  3,000 a year earlier, but the trade feel some concern at the slow rate at which orders are coming from that quarter in view of the Trade Agreement. The trade with Prance will be damaged by the difficulties of the Oitroen concern.Light Metal industries.    In non-ferrous metalp most firms have good orders in hand;    copper prices have been steadier in anticipation of the efforts to bring about a curtailment, of output.    A fair amount of business is passing in tin, which is under strict control.      The price of spelter is extremely lowj    lead shows little change.    Most metal small-ware factories are busy, especially in iron and steel wire goods;     but German competition is being felt in brass wire goods.     Fishing tackle trades continue to be well occupied.      The outlook for architectural metal work has slightly improved, while the press work and enamelled hollowware industries are busy.      In the tool, and loG&apos;::, ,an(3- allied trades and also in the foundry industry conditions are satisfactory.Electrical Industry.      During December 1,557 m. units of electricity were produced as compared with 1,536 m. the year before.      The increase in production In 1934 over 1933 amounted to 14^t.       Orders received for heavy plant continued at the improved level of recent months, South Africa continuing to be the best export market.      Home orders for light material continued to expand and exports show a considera-ble advance on last year.Cotton.      The improvement in production during October and November was not maintained during December,
Weekly deliveries of raw cotton to spinners were .74 million lbs. less on the average than in November.    The prices of most of the principal classes continued to advanoe during the month.     Spinners generally failed to maintain their margins during the month, except possibly in the case of high quality Egyptian yarns.    The ballot in the spinning section in connection with the redundancy scheme showed a satisfactory majority in its favour and steps are being taken co invite offers for the sale or sealing of spindles. The plan to set up a new Cotton Spinners&apos; Association with compulsory powers did not receive sufficient support and was abandoned.The export trade in December was disappointing. Exports of yarns were lower than in November last or in December 1033.    The decline as compared with November was due largely to smaller shipments to Scandinavia but the German and Argentine markets improved.    Exports of pieoe goods at 161 m. sq. yards were lower by 12 m. square yards than in November.     Exports to the Colonies were generally lower and those to South Africa also dropped.     New Zealand was, however, a better market, while shipments to Turkey rose considerably.     Exports to Switzerland, Morocco, Columbia and Argentine all decreased.Wool.      There was some decline in the general activity of the industry as a whole during   -December as compared with the previous month and there was a slight rise in unemployment. Wool prices continued to show a downward tendency.    Exports of wool tissues in December show an improvement over the previous months, but those of tops and yarns slightly decreased.       Reports indicate that orders both on home and export account are scaroe and the immediate outlook offers little expectation of any sustained improvement.
*5 nSilk.      In silk spinning there was no improvement either in the home or export trade during December; spinners were affected by the rise in prioe of raw silk and by Japanese competition in silk tissues.      In the weaving branche trade was quiet over the Christmas holidays and, moreover, strong competition is being felt from Japanese imports. Competition from Prance has also grown recently and In rayon goods there is in operation in that country a scheme of rebates paid by spinners of rayon yarn to manufacturers of piece goods for export.ChemicalThere was a seasonal deoline in December in deliveries of alkalies and of chlorine products to the home market but the exports of both these products were good.     The demand for dyestuffs was on the same level as at the end of 1953; total sales for the year show a slight improvement.     The demand for rubber chemicals, detergents etc. has been much better in the home market and slightly better in the export market.     Among coal tar products creosote oils   have been in exceptional demand but the market for pitch   is still unsatisfactory.    Enquiries for pharmaoeutica1 preparations which should lead to contracts in the new year have been comparatively numerous.Soap, Oils and Kindred Industries.      There has been rather more activity in soap     at cheaper price levels. There was a seasonal improvement during December in the margarine market, but for the year the volume of ttirnover shows a reduction of about 13^ as compared with 1952. In the case of edible oils and fats,  there has been fairly active forward buying and prices have been increased.    The volume of turnover in raw material production for December was slightly below that of the year previously, but business for the year shows an increase of 5^ in turnover over 1933. Trading conditions are satisfactory,
3*3 ^Cement.     While world cement exports for the ten months ended 31st October show an increase of 6.7$ over the corresponding period of 1925, exports from the United Kingdom have improved to a larger extent, the corresponding percentage being 11.4$.     Competition in overseas markets from Jugoslavia, Denmark and Germany continues to be intense. The British manufacturers are disturbed at the possible effects of the German policy of compensation trade.paper.     The demand was more lively than was the case twelve months ago and the seasonal demand for the Christmas trade was well maintained.     The year 1934 has shown a pronounced increase in activity in the paper-making industry as a whole * due to the increased demand for paper arising from the general revival in trade.Retail Trade.     The value of retail sales in November was 3.9$  greater than in November, 1933.     The principal increases recorded were in boots and shoes (6,5$), furnishing (5.7^) and men&apos;s and boys&apos; wear (5.3$).    The improvement in total sales was experienced in all areas. Every area except the West End of London showed an increase in the sales of foodstuffs.     In non-food departments the largest increases were recorded in the South and North of England and in Scotland, and in food departments Scotland fared best with an increase of 6.4$ followed by the suburbs of London with an increase of 5.4$.Co-operative trade.       The Co-operative Wholesale Society&apos;s sales for the four weeks to 8th December showed an increase of 11.6$ as compared with the corresponding period of last year.    The weighted average of the wholesale prices of seven of the principal commodities showed a decrease of 1.3/5 as compared with a year ago and a weighted average of ratal! prices have increased by 0.53$.The trade of the Scottish Co-operative Wholesale
C) n rySociety in December showed an increase of some 3$ over the corresponding period of 1935.      It is thought that stocks in the retail trade Ixave been abnormally low during 1934 and that individual purchasing has also been restricted because of the fear of unemployment, and there is a general feeling that 1935 will bring increased trade to all departments.Canadian trade.      The recovery in economic conditions continued in November.      The index of wholesale prices was stable at 71.2 against 71.4 in the previous month.    The index of the physical volume of business   showed a slight rise, however, at 96.5 compared with 95.9.    Shipments of copper amounted to 45.5 m. lbs., the largest total in the history of the industry, and asbestos exports also showed an increase after seasonal adjustment.      Exports of nickel and zinc, however, were at lower levels.    The level of production of foodstuffs was maintained.    Timber operations were more active; newsprint production showed an advance, and the export of boards and planks also showed a more than-seasonal increase.       The output of both pig iron and steel was somewhat below the previous month and the automobile trade was dull pending the introduction of new models.Australian trade,       The total imports during November amounted to  7.9 m.  (Australian currency), being  1,1 m, more than a year ago.     Of the 2,172.000 bales of wool received into store since 1st July, 827,000 have been sold or shipped.      The corresponding figures a year ago were 1,231,000 out of 2,108,000.      Wheat and flour shipments since 1st December have been equivalent to 6,591^000 bushels of wheat as against 4$ 529.000 bushels a year previously.    Butter exports since 1st July amount to 43,100 tons against 41,000 a year ago.
South American Trade.Argentina.     The official trade figures for the first 11 months of 1934 show an increase in value of exports of 31.48$ and of imports of 24.70$ as compared with the same period of 1933.      These figures indicate a real improvement, even after allowing for inflation of the 1934 figures to the extenc of about 20$ due to the depreciation of the peso.The yield of the new wheat crop is uneven, but maize prospects are excellent.     There is little variation In the exchange position.     It is clear from the report of the Ministry of Finance on Exchange Control for the ten months ended 30th September that the Government have been taking more than their necessary requirements In exchange and have built up a large sterling reserve.Brazil.    There is some anxiety about the position of the national finances.     It is reported that a Brazilian Government Mission has left for New York, London and Paris for the purpose of negotiating a further reduction in the rate of interest on her foreign debts.The coffee market is dull and business is restricted.Chile.     The Chilean Government have devalued the peso from the equivalent of 3d. gold to l^d. gold, which is about 96 pesos to the  1 sterling at present exchange rates. This devaluation has little effect on current commercial payments since they are negotiated through the Barter Exchange market.      The Exchange Control Commission has ruled that future imports from Japan can be paid for only out of the proceeds of Chilean exports to that country.      It is hoped that this will check the dumping of Japanese goods.Peru.       Peruvian manufacturers of cotton goods have, in view of the increasing Japanese competition, decided to submit proposals for the Introduction of the quota system for foreign imports.
9&apos; 9 rt) (J uBolivia.       Foreign trade is expected to decline as the result of the 20fa reduction in the tin export quota assigned to Bolivia by the International Tin Cartel.

</content>
</cab>
