<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/253/0 images: 597-601</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S DOCUMENT IB THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT) ..I 0 RET.,-P. 38 too; *COPY NO.   W t.c3GAB IN E T.OCXCulITTEK ONTHIRD INTERIM REPORT.1. &apos;      At their Meeting on the 19th December, 1934,  (Cabinet 47 (54) Conclusion 9) the Cabinet had &quot;before them a revised, draft of the Sketch programme for the Silver Jubilee Celebrations. The Cabinet took note of the fact that at an Audience with His Majesty The King that evening the Prime Minister would convey to His Majesty the views of the Cabinet on the Sketch programme.     At their Meeting on the 30th January, 1935, the Cabinet Committee were informed by the Lord Chamberlain of His Majesty&apos;s wishes in regard to a number of points on the Programme.      The Committee felt that it was desirable that a further Communique should now be issued forthwith for general information, containing more detailed, particulars as to the Celebrations In London.      The Committee also agreed that the Communique&apos; should at the same time give a general Indication * to Local Authorities as to the character of the Celebrations outside London.A draft of the proposed Communique, with the Sketch Programme annexed, is attached hereto and is submitted for the approval of the Cabinet.S.       The Cbirus.it tee re commend.&apos;(a) That, in the event of this Communique, together with the Sketch Programme, receiving the approval
of His Majesty The King and of the Cabinet they should be published without delay.(b) That a filial decision be taken,  subject to TheKing&apos;a assent, as to the date of the Naval Review at Spithead.(.N.B.    It is proposed that the words shown in square brackets in the attached Sketch Programme should not be published at the present  stage.)Signed on behalf of the Committee JOHN GILMOURChairman.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. 1st February, 1935.
DRAFT PRESS COMMUNIQUE.The Secretary of State for the Home Department issues the following communique  :-Silver Jubilee.The King has been graciously pleased to approve the accompanying Sketch Programme of certain events to take place in London and elsewhere in connection with the Celebrations of His Majesty&apos;s Silver Jubilee in the coming Summer,,As already announced,  it is The King&apos;s desire that the Celebrations should be on a local basis.      In response to the numerous requests for guidance which have been received from Local Authorities,  the Secretary of State suggests that authorities might include in their programme something in the nature of a Fete or Carnival, with street decorations and illuminations, and that an entertainment for children should be a feature of the Celebrations.It is also announced,  for general information,  that no applications for invitations to the Thanksgiving Service at St. PaulTs Cathedral on May 6th, -can be entertained.Home Office.February, 1935.
SILVER JUBILEE CELEBRATIONS.Revised Sketch Programme for Celebrations in London, His Majesty theKing&apos;s visit to Edinburgh, &amp;c.1. Monday, May 6th.11-30 a.m. Thanksgiving Service at. St. Pauls. [Representative congregation of about 4,000. Eull dress with trousers. Those not in possession of uniform, evening dress with trousers.]State Drive to and from St. Paul&apos;s. [Streets lined by representative Service detachments, Navy, Army, Air&apos; Force, Territorials, &amp;c] &quot;      - ;:A bout 6 p.m. The King&apos;s Broadcast Message to the Empire.Evening. Chain of Bonfires throughout the country;   illuminations;Buckingham Palace, St. James&apos;s Palace and Park, and many other public buildings to be floodlit.2. Wednesday, May 8th.11-30 a.m. Reception at St. James&apos;s Palace of the Diplomatic Corps and Representatives of the Empire.   [Levee Dress.]The Prince of Wales represents the King at a ceremony at Cardiff.3. Thursday, May 9th.11-30 a.m. Presentation of Addresses from both Houses of Parliament in Westminster Hall.   [Morning Dress.]Evening. State Dinner. &quot;4. Saturday, May 11th.Afternoon. Drive through North London (weather permitting). [The route to include Hyde Park, where detachments of the British Legion, Boy Scouts, St. John&apos;s Ambulance Brigade, and other organisations will be drawn up.   Levee Dress.]S. Sunday, May 12th.Thanksgiving Services in all churches.6. Tuesday, May 15th.Evening. Ball at Buckingham Palace.7. Saturday, May 18th.Afternoon. Drive through South London (weather permitting). [Levee Dress.]8. Monday, May 20th.Evening. State Dinner.9. Wednesday, May 22nd.Evening. Reception and Ball at Guildhall. [Evening Dress with Decorations.]10. Saturday, May 2Sth.Afternoon. Drive through East London (weather permitting). [Levee Dress.][11102]
* [See, however, Report of Cabinet Committee CP. 28 (35).J.11. Friday, May 31st.Morning. Levee.    , ...........12. Monday, June 3rd.Trooping of the Colour.13. Saturday, June 8th.Afternoon.-Drive through West London (weather permitting).   [Levee .....   Dress.]14. Thursday, June 13th.Evening. Ball at Buckingham Palace.15. Tuesday, June 25th.Third Court.16. Wednesday, June 26th.Fourth Court.17. Saturday, July 6th.Air Force Review at Mildenhall and Duxford.18. Tuesday, July 9th.Morning.- Investiture.   [Levee Dress.] *19. Wednesday, July 10th.Morning. Investiture.   [Morning Dress.]20. Saturday, July 13th.Military Review at Aldershot.21. Wednesday, July 17th.*Naval Review at Spithead.22. Saturday, July 20th.Police Review in Hyde Park (Provisional).23. Thursday, July 25th.Garden Party at Buckingham Palace.24. Celebrations in Scotland in August.The King will break his journey to Balmoral at Edinburgh and will drive through the streets [which will be lined by representative detachments of the Services, including Scottish Territorials and Boy Scouts.]

</content>
</cab>
