<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/253/0 images: 671-681</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MENT IB THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)BVISE.COPY. NO,-A 1-C A B I N E TSTATEMENT RELATING TO DEFENCE.The accompanying final revise of the Statement Relating to Defence, to he issued in connection with the House of Commons Debate on March 11th, as approved &quot;by the members of the Drafting Committee appointed by the Cabinet on February 25th, is circulated for information.This Statement will be published as a Command Paper on Monday, March 4th,  and copies will be available for Members of 30th Houses early on the afternoon of that day.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.\, &quot;Whitehall Gardens,  SAW, 1. , 2nd March, 1935.
STATEMENT RELATING TO DEFENCEISSUED IN CONNEXION WITH THE HOUSE OF COMMONS  DEBATE ON MARCH n, 1935Presented by the Prime Minister to Parliament by Command of His Majesty March 1935LONDONPRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2;   120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; York Street, Manchester 1 ;  1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any Booksellerr935 Price      NetCmd,
Statement relating to Defence. Issued in connexion with the House of Commons Debate on March 11, 1935.For some years when the Votes of the Defence Services have been debated in the House of Commons, the suggestion has been made that their consideration should be preceded by a Debate on Imperial Defence as a whole. The Government have always beei sympathetic to this proposal, but it has not been found possiblf hitherto to adopt it. In the present year the case for some such pro cedure is stronger than it was in past years, for the reason that tin course of events has rendered unavoidable an increase in the tota Defence Estimates, and it is hoped to be able to provide an opportunity] for the discussion of Imperial Defence. The following notes an circulated, not to supersede the /White Papers accompanying tin Estimates of the Defence Departments, but in order to indicati generally the policy of the Government in Imperial Defence, am the reasons for the increase.I.2. The establishment of peace on a permanent footing i the principal aim of British foreign policy. The first am strongest defence of the peoples, territories, cities, oversea trade and communications of the British Empire is provided by th maintenance of peace. If war can be banished from the world, thes vast and world-wide interests will remain free from the dangers o attack, and the great work of civilisation and trade will proceei unhampered by the fears that have hindered their progres from the earliest recorded times until to-day. That is why ever British Government is bound to use its utmost endeavours to mamtaii peace.3. In recent years the chief methods by which His Majesty&apos; Government in the United Kingdom have pursued the establishmen of peace on a permanent footing have been as follows : (1) By unswerving support of the League of Nations, which Hi Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom regard as essentia machinery for promoting the preservation of peace by facilitafcinj and regularising the means of international co-operation.(2) By the promotion, in co-operation with other nations, o international instruments designed to produce collective security ant a sense of security among the nations. Among the more importan may be mentioned : (a) The Briand-Kellogg Pact of 1928 for the renunciation b; every signatory of war as an instrument of policy.
8412(b) The Quadruple Pacific Treaty and the Nine-Power Treaty regarding the Par East, both designed to promote peace in that area and in the Pacific.(c) The Locarno Treaties, designed, - by- a - system of mutual guarantee, to maintain the peace in those&apos; countries of Western Europe, to the situation of which this country has never been and can never be indifferent.The latest development in this direction is the Anglo-French proposal of the 3rd February for regional and mutual arrangements to deter aerial aggression and thereby provide additional security from sudden attacks from the air.(d) Various proposals for increasing security in Eastern Europe and the Danube Basin, with special reference to the maintenance of the independence and integrity of Austria. These involve no military commitments, direct or indirect, by this country.(3) By efforts to promote international understanding in general,&apos; and in particular to bring back into the comity of nations all the countries which have been enemies in the late war. Successive Governments in the United Kingdom have taken a leading part in such measures as the- suspension of the Penalties provisions of the Treaty of Versailles; the election of late enemies to membership of the League of Nations, including, in the case of Germany, permanent membership of the Council; the evacuation of the Bhineland five years in advance of the date fixed by the Treaties; the gradual rationalisation and virtual settlement of reparations at the Lausanne Conference of 1932; the Saar plebiscite; the action in connection with the Disarmament Conference referred to below in (4).(4) The reduction and limitation of international armaments in order to promote the work of pacification and steadily to. reduce the means of making war. The best known instances of disarmament are the Washington Treaty of 1922 and the London Naval Treaty of 1930, both of which, in accordance with their provisions are to form the subject of an International Conference during the present year. After six years of preparation the Disarma-ment Conference, promoted by the League of Nations,- opened at Geneva on the 2nd February, 1932&apos;, . and ever since the present Government have sought unremittingly to obtain a successful result. In pursuit of this object they have been foremost among the nations in taking the initiative as, for.example, to mention only a few instances, their declaration in connection with Germany&apos;s claim to equality of rights, of the 17th November, 1932 (Cmd. 4189); the British draft Convention of the 16th March, 1933 (Cmd. 4279), and their proposals of January 1934 (Cmd. 4498).4. Hitherto, in spite of many setbacks, public opinion in this country has tended to assume that nothing is required for the maintenance of peace except the existing international political machinery, and that the older methods of defence-navies, armies
and air forces on which we have hitherto depended for our security in the last resort are no longer required. The force of world events, however, has shown that this assumption is premature, and that we have far to go before we can find complete security without having in the,background the means of defending ourselves against attack. Nations differ in their temperaments, needs and state of civilisation. Discontent may arise out of various causes, from the recollection of past misfortunes, from a desire to recover past losses or from pressure occasioned by the increase of population. All these are fruitful sources of friction or dispute, and events in various parts of the world have shown that nations are still prepared to use or threaten force under the impulse of what they conceive to be a national necessity; and it has been found that once action has been taken the existing international machinery for the maintenance of peace cannot be relied upon as a protection against an aggressor,5. The National Government intends to pursue without intermission the national policy of peace by every practicable means and to take advantage of every opportunity, and to make opportunities to make peace more secure. But it can no longer close its eyes to the fact that adequate defences are still required for security and to enable the British Empire to play its full part in maintaining the peace of the world.&apos; II.6. During the years that all parties in this country have been seeking to carry out the policy outlined above, there has been a steady decline in the effective strength of our armaments by sea and land. In the air we virtually disarmed ourselves in 1919, and, subsequently, from time to time postponed attainment of the minimum air strength regarded as necessary to our security in the face of air developments on the Continent. It is not that British Governments have neglected to keep themselves informed of the position. Every year the state of our armaments has been anxiouslj considered, and if risks have been run they have been accepted deliberately in pursuit of the aim of permament peace. Again and again, rather than run any risk of jeopardising some promising movement in this direction by increasing expenditure on armaments, Governments have postponed the adoption of measures that were required when considered from the point of view of national defence alone. In this way we have taken risks for peace, but, as intimated by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in the debate on the Address on the 28th November, 1934, &quot;disarming ourselves in advance, by ourselves, by way of an example has not increased our negotiating power in the Disarmament discussions at Geneva.&quot;7. Parliament and people, however, have been warned again and again that serious deficiencies were accumulating in all the
III.8.   Last midsummer the position was as follows : (1) The Disarmament Conference had virtually come to a standstill. Further negotiations, it was clear, would be hampered by the fact that Germany was not only re-arming openly on a large scale, despite the provisions of Part V of the Treaty of Versailles, but had also given notice of withdrawal from the League of Nations and the Disarma-ment Conference. Japan also had given notice of withdrawal from the League. All the larger Powers except the United Kingdom were adding to their armed forces.(2) Detailed and prolonged examination had been made into the serious deficiencies that had accumulated in our defence forces and defences.- It had been established that, unless a programme was put in hand to re-condition them and to bring them up to date, the country and the Empire would no longer possess an adequate standard of defence. If, therefore, in spite of all our efforts to keep the peace, an aggression should take place directed against ourselves, we should be unable to secure our sea communications, the food of our. people or the defence of our principal cities and their population against air attack. Moreover, the great value of the Locarno Treaties to this country is their deterrent effect on would-be aggressors. This is being seriously weakened by the knowledge, shared by all the signatories, that our contribution, in case our obligation is clear to us, could have little decisive effect. The same consideration would, of course, apply to any other method of collective security to which we might be parties.9. In the above circumstances, His Majesty&apos;s Government felt that they would be failing in their responsibilities if, while continuing to the full, efforts for peace by limitation of armaments, they delayed the initiation of steps to put our. own armaments on a footing to safeguard us against potential dangers. A co-ordinated programme was drawn up for re-conditioning our defence forces and defences. In the case of the Navy (whose strength is limited by Treaty) and Army, these programmes involve for the most part a process of supplying technical deficiencies, providing up-to-date equipment and [11248] b 2Defence Services, and that our desire to lead the world, towards disarmament by our example of unilateral disarmament has not succeeded. We have not contributed thereby to general disarma-ment, and are approaching a point when we are not possessed of the necessary means of defending ourselves against an aggressor.
adequate personnel and reserves of war material, without which our forces could not defend our vital interests against an aggressor nor co-operate in any system of collective security.10. In the case of the Royal Air Force alone was an appreciable increase of units deemed immediately necessary, and for this reason it was announced in Parliament on the 19th July, 1934, and debated by the House of Commons on the 30th July, and by the House of Lords on the 14th November. Increases will also be necessary in the anti-aircraft defences provided by the Army.11. On the 28th November, 1934, His Majesty&apos;s Government drew public attention to the re-armament on which Germany w engaged, and announced a speeding up of the increases in the Air Force already decided upon. The action of His Majesty&apos;s Government did not, of course, imply condonation of a breach of the Treaty of Versailles. It merely noted and made public, as a first step, what was known to be proceeding.12. This re-armament, if continued at its present rate, unabated and uncontrolled, will aggravate the existing anxieties of the neighbours of Germany, and may consequently produce a situation where peace will be in peril. His Majesty&apos;s Government have noted and welcomed the declarations of the leaders of Germany that they desire peace. They cannot, however, fail to recognise that not only the forces but the spirit in which the population, and especially the youth of the country, are being organised lend colour to, and substantiate, the general feeling of insecurity which has already beeiv incontestably generated. Nor is the increase of armaments confined to Germany. All over the world, in Russia, in Japan, in the United States of America and elsewhere, armaments are being added to. We could not afford to overlook all these increases, and so have had to begin to meet our deficiencies, but have been anxious not to make the provisions for necessary defence merge into a race in armaments strength.IV.18. If peace should be broken, the Navy is, as always, the first-line of defence for the maintenance of our essential sea communica-tions. Our special problems of defence arise firstly, from the dependence, of this country for its existence on seaborne supplies of food and raw materials, and secondly, from the unique conditions of the British Empire, its world-wide distribution, and the fact that all parts of it are, to a greater or less extent, dependent on communica-tions by sea for their well-being, or in some instances for their very existence; furthermore, in the last resort, it is on the transport of adequate forces and their supplies by sea that the different parts of the Empire rely to resist aggression and to ensure the security of their interests and the integrity of their territory.
Tims it is that the security by sea passage to this country, as ffell as to and from all parts of the Empire, forms the basis and foundation of our system of Imperial defence, without which all other measures can be of but little avail.14. So long as the Navy is strong enough to perform this task, and the other defence services are equipped to co-operate in the defence of ports and of the narrow seas, our food supplies will be safeguarded; the Members of the British Commonwealth of Nations will be able to render each other mutual support to the extent that each may decide, and the trade of the different parts of the Empire, both with one another and with the rest of the world, will be maintained. Failure to make sufficient provision for the Navy and the other Defence Services would, in the event of war, reduce supplies to the point of starvation, render impossible mutual support within the Empire, lead to a cessation of trade, and inflict incalculable suffering on the community.15. Developments in the power and range of air forces have increased the vulnerability of this country. This is an added burden of defence, but, when it- has been borne, the protection of the sea communications of these Islands as well as of the rest of the Empire remains. The growing power of air forces, however it may have changed other conditions of warfare, has still left our merchant ships on the vast ocean spaces as open to naval attack as before. The necessities of naval defence remain therefore unaltered.16. The Main Fleet is the basis upon which our naval strategy rests, but the cover it can provide is rarely complete, and it may always be expected that detached enemy units may evade the Main Fleet and carry out sporadic attacks on territories and trade. To deal with these attacks, considerable numbers of cruisers are required over and above those forming part of the Main Fleet.17. In the Main Fleet the capital ship remains the essential element upon which the whole structure of our naval strategy depends. The age of our battleships renders it necessary to commence their replacement at an early date, but the extent of new construction will be subject to any agreement reached at the forth-coming Naval Conference. The advent of air attack in its present form was unforeseen when our existing battleships were designed, but their anti-aircraft armament is being increased to enable them (o perform their primary function.18. The strength of the Navy, as already mentioned, is at present fixed by the Washington and London Naval Treaties which are clue for reconsideration this year. Divergencies in national points of view have developed since the negotiation of those treaties, as evidencod by the recent notice by Japan to terminate the Washington Treaty, and by the programmes effected and contem-plated by some of the European.Powers.
19. It is the hope of His Majesty&apos;s Government to secure an arrangement that will avoid competition in naval armaments whilst leaving us free to maintain a fleet at the strength necessary for our absolute requirements. This involves a calculation of the number of ships of each type which together make up the fleet, and it is essential that the minimum numbers so calculated should be maintained. It is equally essential that our fleet should be kept up to date in all respects, including a sufficient and highly trained personnel, adequate provision of aircraft (which are becoming more and more important to the Navy), the most modern weapons, repair facilities, and the necessary reserves of fuel, ammunition and stores of all kinds at convenient bases. Without these facilities, or if out ships are less well equipped than those of possible enemies, all money spent will be wasted, -as the ships cannot perform effectively their defensive functions. Ineffective defence means not only waste, but defeat.V.20.   The bases and fuelling stations of the Fleet and the harbours where merchant ships are loading and unloading require defences I against sea-borne and air attack on scales that vary with their geographical position and the other circumstances of each port, j Without these defences, the docks, repair facilities, fuel, stores, as well as merchant ships in port, would be liable to destruction or I capture, and the action of the Fleet might be paralysed.21.   At  the  present  time  the  defences  of  our  ports need I modernising.   Under present day conditions the defence of ports j involves  concerted action between  the  three  Services,  but I heaviest expenditure falls on War Office votes.22. The Army estimates, besides providing for the improvement I and installation of coast defences on a considered scale of priority, make provision for a large expansion of anti-aircraft defences. In addition, the army requires to be modernised by the provision of up-to-date equipment, mechanisation, transport and reserves of war material of all kinds which have fallen below required standard If these essentials are not provided, our Army, if ever called upon for action, would find itself inadequately equipped, with an insufficient reserve of ammunition, and exposed to heavy loss, suffering and possible disaster which might have been avoided by reasonable foresight and expenditure.VI.23.   The Eoyal Air Force has, as its principal role, to provide j (with the co-operation of ground defences) for the protection of the United Kingdom and particularly London against air attack.   It also provides Air Forces for general defence purposes in the Middle East,
India and the Far Bast, as well as for co-operation in Coast Defence (a subject which is being closely studied by the three Defence Services in co-operation at the present time); and, in addition, furnishes specially trained and equipped squadrons for co-operation with the Army and a proportion of the Fleet Air Arm personnel for work with the Navy. The Air Squadrons at home provide, in addition, a reserve of air squadrons for employment in any part of the world in an emergency.24. Technical development in the air is taking place very rapidly in respect, for example, of such matters as speed, height, endurance, carrying capacity and potentialities for destruction. The range of territory on the continent of Europe from which air attacks could be launched against this country is constantly extending and will continue to extend; and if, in war, an enemy were in possession of the countries bordering the Channel, the area of Great Britain liable to his attacks would be still further increased. The weight of the attack would be much greater, owing to the quicker &apos;&apos; turn round &apos;&apos; of the bombers and their increased bomb load at shorter ranges. The increase in speed, range and height accentuates the difficulty of obtaining warning in time to bring defensive aircraft into action in favourable conditions to repel attacks. For these reasons the importance of the integrity of certain territories on the other side of the Channel and North Sea, which for centuries has been, and still remains, a vital interest to this country from a Naval point of view, looms larger than ever when air defence is also taken into consideration.25. The problem of air defence is occupying the attention of the Air Ministry and other Departments concerned. Up to now, however, the only deterrent to an armed aggressor has seemed to be the possession of adequate means of counter-attack. In view of the time required to provide the necessary forces, and the obscurities of the international situation, no Government mindful of its responsibilities could neglect to provide such defence as it deemed necessary to secure (he safety of the country.26. As was stated in the House of Commons on the 30th July, 1934, His Majesty&apos;s Government intend to develop, simultaneously with the defensive preparations of the country&apos;s armed forces, pre-eautionary measures designed specifically for the protection of the civil population and the safeguarding of essential services against the effects of bombing attack from the air. Corresponding action has already been taken by most of the countries on the continent of Europe, and, by common consent of all those who have studied the subject, this is an essential complement to defensive measures in order to reduce, so far as possible, the inevitable losses and suffering that must result from air attack.27. The Government desires to emphasise that the measures now proposed.are elastic.   They will not only be subject to frequent
review in the light of prevailing conditions, but may from time to time be adjusted in either direction if circumstances should, in the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Government, warrant any change.28. To summarise, peace is the principal aim of British foreign policy. The National Government intend to forward this object not only by methods adopted in past years support to the League of Nations, security agreements, international understanding and inter-national regulation of armaments but by any other means that may be available. Notwithstanding their confidence in the ultimate triumph of peaceful methods, in the present troubled state of the world they realise that armaments cannot be dispensed with. They are required to preserve peace, to maintain security and to deter aggression. The deliberate retardation of our armaments as part oi our peace policy has brought them below the level required for the fulfilment of these objects, especially in view of the uncertainty of the international situation and the increase of armaments in all parts of the world. An additional expenditure on the armaments of the three Defence Services can, therefor-e, no longer be safely postponed.J. B. M.March 1, 1935.wt3/35 ko.p. 11248 gp. 340

</content>
</cab>
