<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/253/0 images: 685-686</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cC A B I 11 JS T.HOUSING  I SCOTLAND) BILL - PROPOSAL yOHjuaBsMC,Memor&amp;naum by the See ret ary of^ St at e for Scotland.Since the publication of the Housing (Scotland) Billrepresentations regarding the rating of unoccupied property nave been made by bond holders and property owners which nave much impress ad Government supporters in Parliament,,      These representations have come from areas in the West of Scotland. The difficulty is particularly acute in areas wiaere rates ars hi git.in Scotland wnereas in England there is no corresponding liability, The decrowding provisions of the Bill will in the future result appreciably and increasingly in the transfer from one and two-apartment houses throughout the country of families who require to be aoeOfnmodatea in larger nouses according to the standard laid down in the Bill;    and this in turn will result in one and two-apartment nouses becoming left without tenants.      There will no doubt be an offset to tnis througn readjustment of population which will make the smaller houses available for families of  v. three persons or less,      A number of these small nouses will also be pulled down when old sites in the centre of towns are redeveloped.       A considerable number of small nounss will however become unoccupied, and there appears to be some unfairness in continuing to charge rates on such empty nouses.      Virtually none of these smaller nouses in Glasgow are unoccupied at present.Owners9  rates are payable on unoccupied house propertyGeneral /
General compensation for smaller houses which so become unoccupied is clearly out of tne question, hut a relief on the rating point could it is thougnt he given within the scope of the Bill0      The particular point would be met by the inclusion in the Bill of a provision exempting from owners rates unoccupied houses of one and two-apartments.      It is txxis group of nouses wnieh will be mainly affected by the proposed decrowding legislation.I desire authority to include tnis provision inthe Bill.Before the Bill reaches Committee I should propose to consult with representatives of the local authorities on the matter,      Any objections which they nay raise canD I thinks be very largely met t, since any loss in respect of owners rates on the property vacated will  be offset by the increased rateable value accruing from the number of houses erected with the aid of Government subsidy under the Bills      It is tne erection of those larger modern houses wnich will lead to tne smaller nouses being unoccupied.Tne ministry of healtn and the Treasury have no observations to offer on the course proposed.(Id.) G.P.CoScottish Office 8Whitehall , S.W010 15th February, ly550

</content>
</cab>
