<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/112/0 images: 97-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)52C.(63) 1913th February, 1963COPY NO.cabinet memorandum by the Lord President of the Counciland Minister for ScienceV/hile I am in general agreement with the views of the Ministerof Aviation and the Postmaster General as set out in C. (63) 16there are certain points to which I wish to draw special attention: -1.      In my view, it is essential that we should develop thecapability of making and launching satellites for communications, and other purposes.    I, therefore,warmly support the recommendations at 3(f).    I am glad to say that the Chief Secretary has already agreed to a programme of research and development, which willenable us, in due course, to design and construct theAriel III satellite.      But we shall need to go further,and in any negotiations with the United States we should insist on being able to use communication satellitesdesigned and made in this country, or designed and madein collaboration with European and commonwealth countries, such as Canada and Australia.2.      If we can secure, within a world-wide system, the right to launch United Kingdom (or European) satellites usingUnited Kingdom built, or European Launcher development organisation (ELDO) built,rockets, this would meet our needs, provided that we are satisfied that when theUnited States say that they envisage &quot;international collaboration in construction, ownership, and management&quot;,the United States are, in fact, prepared to give othercountries a sizeable, independent, share in launching and making satellites, and that this share is big enough to makea viable production and launching programme.    there seems to me to be at least a doubt whether a systeminvolving 20-24 satellites, and 3 replacements a year,would provide what we need.   I think that we need toobtain firm assurances on this, and not only &quot;the chanceof providing part of the system&quot; (paragraph 3(b) ofC.(63) 16).
3.      If it emerges in negotiation that this cannot be secured, weshall be faced with a choice of going into the United Statesworld-wide system with no satisfactory assurance, ordeveloping an independent system, which we are advisedis unlikely to be economic, at any rate at first.4.     If we were not prepared, as proposed in paragraph 3(c) ofc. (63) 16 to seek to establish our own system if satisfactory terms cannot be obtained, the future of theEIjDO launcher would become very problematical.    Ifthe European Space Research Organisation (ESRO) werethe only customer, the cost of ELDO launchers to ESROmight well be prohibitive.    The agreements for both these organisations have been signed but not ratified.    While Iam not suggesting that we should alter our policy towardseither of these organisations, I should be glad to knowwhether it is agreed that our attitude to them should remain unchanged in the light of the breakdown of the Brusselsnegotiations, and in the light of the satellite communica-tions problem.HAILS HAMOffice of the Lord President of the Counciland Minister for Science, S. W. 1.13th February, 1963


</content>
</cab>
