<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/112/0 images: 100-108</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1963C. (63) 20 Copy No.14th February, 1963CABINETVISIT TO THE NORTH-EAST OF ENGLAND, 4th-8th FEBRUARY, 1963Note by the Lord President of the Council and Minister for science circulate, for the information of the Cabinet, my report on a visit to theNorth-East of England from 4th to 8th February, 1963.HAIL SHAM.Office of the Lord President of the Counciland Minister for Science, S.W. 1,13th February, 1963.2097
VISIT TO THE NORTH-EAST OF ENGLAND, 4th-8th FEBRUARY, 1963REPORT BY THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL and minister FOR science . These notes are preliminary and to some extent tentative. I will beasking my team of officials to prepare a full, and long, report digesting the immensemass of material which we acquired during our tour of the North-East.2. The tour itself was an immense success; I was personally greeted withwarmth amounting to enthusiasm. But to have with me a range of officials froma comprehensive selection of Ministries offering individual local authorities experthelp and advice on almost every conceivable subject will, I think, itself achievegreat results. It is an experiment in Government which may be worthwhilerepeating here and elsewhere. I propose to make another visit in March, mainlypicking up themes we have missed the first time.3.  General leadershipThis is a region which is sadly lacking in local leadership of the right quality.There are local grandees, like the Duke of Northumberland, who does immenselygood work in the countryside, but does not touch industry. There are localindustrialists who carry out their own responsibilities extremely well, but who dolittle, and have been largely excluded from, local government. The result is thatMr. Chetwynd&apos;s organisation, the North-East Development Council, althoughdoing a good job, has practically no industrial backing, has little insight into thereal problems of industry, tends to underrate the problems of Tees-side, and thecoast, and suffers from a tendency towards political exhibitionism, which, however,it controlled during my visit. There would be a place for a &quot; Brecon &quot;-type figure for the North-East and resident there, if the right man could be found. But this must await further decisions on Government organisation.4.  Industry is the key it is necessary to present our plans in a warm and human kind of way.Moreover, if we are to make the area attractive, we must avoid a strictly economicapproach, and be seen to aim at the improvement of the entire quality of lifethroughout the North-East.There are very good ideas available for the improvement of communications,town planning, culture and education and amentities, to which I will return, andof which we should make use, and which I regard of great importance in creating a brighter future for the region. But the key issue is industry, the revival ofthe heavy industries on which the region now depends, and will to a large measurecontinue to depend, and the diversification of industries by the introduction, and extension, of light industries, for which the region offers ample opportunity,although emphasis will require to be placed on training the necessary skilled labour -at least in some of the engineering skills, probably in some buildingskills technicians and top management. The re-introduction by improvedamenities of an adequate cultured middle class is a crying social need.5.  We must make certain political decisions to achieve economic resultsDiscriminatory economic results are only obtained by discriminatory political decisions. We have committed ourselves to a 4 per cent national growth rate,but are also committed, in principle, to some attempt to bring the high unemployment areas up towards the standards of the rest of the country. Thesetwo commitments are complementary since the National Economic DevelopmentCouncils programme pre-supposes that a good deal of the extra growth will comefrom making fuller use of the under-employed resources in the North-East andother similar areas. In actual fact, however, with the exception of one or two points of growth like Newton Aycliffe, growth in the North-East is and in theabsence of special measures is likely to remain at a slower rate than the rest of thecountry.  It follows, therefore, that a really massive effort is required if we are toSECRET2097 A
achieve anything fundamentally worthwhile. A very great deal of public, local and private money will be required, and this will not be forthcoming unless weweight the scales in favour of the high unemployment areas in a number ofdifferent ways, which, if we were simply aiming at being fair, we could not justify.We shall, therefore, have to take political decisions, which will meet with a quitelegitimate resistance that we shall have none the less to overcome.6.   We must forecast for successA further, and vital, general point relates to our method of civil service andpublic authority forecasting. At present we tend to estimate future requirements\e.g., the birth rate for the purposes of school building; energy, for the purpose ofbuilding generating stations; traffic density, for the purpose of road building) onactual past performance, with an allowance for , growth justified by pastachievements.Such methods may be the best we can do, but are by their very nature basedon the assumption of the failure of our present policies, and they can equally ensurefailure. For some purposes we must throw our hearts over the fence. Assumetotal success and plan for that requirement; we may otherwise unwittingly ensurefailure. For instance a failure to build sufficient power stations owing to a failure to forecast requirements adequately in advance can be a means of ensuring failure.It is not perhaps a coincidence that the National Economic Development Councilreports that one of the two industries which may be incapable of living up to the4 per cent target in 1966 is the electricity industry.7.   Incentives for the NorthA third general point I must make is that if we are to succeed some fiscal,economic or budgetary device must ensure that we can secure growth in the areasof high unemployment without creating a roaring inflation in Surbiton. Theparticular device chosen is perhaps outside my terms of reference to recommend,but it is not simply a question of incentive. It must actually discriminate in favourof these areas as a matter of national necessity if we are to achieve a success. Adevice of this kind, difficult as it is, is a conditio sine qua non. My own preferencewould be for tax concessions of an exceptional kind for investment in the area,coupled with massive Government subventions for local authority social investment,and not only by subsidising interest payments for temporarily non-productiveexpenditure.8.   Industry in the North-East(a) Acceleration of Government OrdersI begin with industry, because it is crucial, although perhaps it is not the logicalpoint of entry into the system. We will, however, not achieve success in the shortrun unless an increased measure of prosperity is brought to existing industries, steel,shipbuilding, chemicals, construction and, although only a measure of protectionis available here, coal.(b) The acceleration Of Government purchasing and investment programmeApart from chemicals, the best prospects are for steel, since by advancingGovernment and local plans for works of construction, bridges, tunnels, buildingsusing steel frames (which are beginning again to compete With concrete) and for steel products (e.g., cranes), we can inject a measure of demand straight into theindustry. Our general measures to stimulate the economy must also, indirectly,help the heavy industries by increasing the demand for industrial products. Ido not know if it has been sufficiently realised how far accelerating Governmentprogrammes generally will help existing industries, light and heavy. Reyrolles,for instance, could bring into employment some hundreds more workmen by an acceleration (justified on purely economic grounds) of the C.E.G.B. and areaelectricity boards&apos; programmes; On a purely local level, the North-EasternElectricity Board and the Northern Gas Board could bring forward at least half amillion pounds worth of works. But Government buying generally could belegitimately accelerated to help the North-East. I think we should, send officersof the purchasing departments to the high unemployment areas to study how farorders could be placed there.   Examples of this: pyrexware; clothes; cranes;
telephone equipment. A large number of extra jobs could be brought into theHartlepool-Sunderland area by the acceleration of G.P.O. programmes for the installation of telephones (which are in any event money earners). PurchasingDepartments would need to be given instructions about the degree of preference to be given to suppliers in the region and I am taking this point up with the Treasury.9.   Likely persistence of unemploymentWhen all is said and done the unemployment in the area is likely to provepersistent. All the evidence is that when, and if, the heavy firms do return totheir peak production at least 25 per cent of the labour declared redundant willnot be re-employed. Coal will continue on the way down, so, owing to technicalimprovements, will chemicals, although LCI. could help by bringing in newdivisions to occupy the space made empty by dismantling their coking plants.Shipbuilding shows no signs of revival for two or three years at least. Diversificationis therefore necessary both in the short, and the long run.10.   Measures for diversificationIn order to achieve the diversification of industry thereby required I would recommend the following:(a) Reopen the Team Valley Trading Estate for BOTAC assistance (on the travelling distance doctrine).(b) Declare Killingworth within a development district (unemployment 8 percent and the local colliery is about to close down). Alternatively (but less satisfactorily) apply the &quot; travelling distance &quot; doctrine here.(c) Build more advance factories, but at a limited number of estates. Aycliffeis clearly right, but owing to their desperate situation Hartlepool shouldhave a programme of advance factories. My advice from the local Boardof Trade officials was consistently to the effect that availability is oftena decisive criterion for visiting industrialists. Special help should begiven to Darlington while the redundancy from the railway workshopscontinues, which will (I would hope) not be long.(d) The whole of Tees-side or at any rate a great part of it should be declareda development district. Unemployment is high, and in my opinion islikely to be persistent. ((1) Built-in productivity improvement will prevent re-employment; (2) LCI. running down; (3) Cleveland IronMines closing; (4) Dorman Long carrying passengers; (5) serious femaleunemployment situation; (6) shipbuilding not likely to look up yetawhile.)11.   Shipbuilding and repairingIt is difficult to know what can be done for shipbuilding. I have already mademost of the following recommendations. I continue to attach importance to all of them.(a) Accelerated naval construction, for fighting ships and auxiliaries.(b) A nuclear merchant ship, or ships.(c) Nuclear submarines.(d) Development contracts for unconventional merchant ships.(e) Scrap and build, and impose some sort of fiscal sanction or incentive to discourage shipowners from selling redundant tonnage, e.g., to the greeks. Redundant tonnage should be scrapped not thrown on themarket. Any scrap and build scheme should be a scheme to encourage the regular replacement of tonnage by shipowners rather than a &quot; crashprogramme&quot; to stimulate a flood or orders.(/) The Russian oil deal.I attach a good deal of importance to encouragement to shipyards and repairingyards to use the present slackness to invest in new facilities, e.g., new dry and gravingdocks. Ships are getting bigger and the old facilities will soon tend to be inadequate.One measure would be to reduce the &quot; writing off &quot; period for new dry docks, etc.,from 50 to 20 years.SECRET2097 a 2
Measures should be taken to get the new British Ship Research association on its feet, including if necessary a more generous pump-priming grant from theDepartment of Scientific and Industrial Research.The Hartlepools application for assistance for a second repairing dock in itsremaining yard should, owing to the desperate situation there, be looked onfavourably.  The dock will be needed.12.   CoalI am in my own mind convinced that the Durham coal-fired power stations should be built this year or next. It would be better to do it the year after ifneither of these is done. It will take five or six years to build, and no current will therefore be produced much before 1970. It is admitted that by 1972 the stationwill be required. The alleged reason against it is that the current will not bewanted before 1972 and that if so it will require an extra high tension line southat a cost of  3 million. But this line too will be built anyhow sooner or later;it is part of the 400-kV. supergrid. If our plans succeed the power will, I ampersonally convinced, be wanted by 1970 or earlier. I have explained my reasonsfor this to the Economic Policy Committee. In particular I question whetherthe C.E.G.B. have calculated the future requirements on the basis of the successof our plans (as they must) or on past achievement, in which case they will bothassume, and produce, failure. I strongly suspect that if this station is not builtour plans will fail for want of electric power. The construction of the station,its switchgear, etc., will bring additional work to the district. Advantages ofbuilding now are that the cost will be less and the pressure on investment resourcesrequired to meet the 4 per cent target of the National Economic development council will be less now than in 1967.13.   Industrial trainingSpecial efforts should be made to improve industrial training in the area.Skilled labour is short, at least in the light engineering trades, and, if we succeed,will be short in the building trades as well. We shall not succeed unless we havea bigger cadre of skilled labour on which to build.(1) What is wanted is new drive behind the Regional Training Council, with government money available in advance of the legislation envisaged by the White Paper.(2) New group apprenticeship schemes. The two LCI. schools are onlyhalf full and Dorman Long have many spare places at theirs. TheGovernment should finance unemployed apprentices, and retraining ofadults.(3) Fresh and more vigorous arrangements for the retraining of adults toinclude conversion courses within a single skill to reach new degrees of skill or new applications of skill.14.   EducationThere is a good deal to be done in the educational field apart from school building. Fresh training facilities would be valuable especially in the light of localteacher shortages. Schemes for the provision of a College of Advanced Technology(perhaps federal, Sundefland-Newcastle (Rutherford College)) would be valuable.This depends upon the provision of adequate courses, but a Ministry of Educationofficial on the spot could help with the liaison necessary to produce these. It ispossible that a teacher training college in Tees-side might be envisaged.I think something must be done drastically to support the youth service inthe region. Areas of high unemployment have distinct problems, their own,especially when this coincides with the &quot; bulge &quot; (odious expression). Cannot we put in some professional leadership and premises? Cannot we also give limitedsupport of some kind to the Churches especially if all Churches agree?15.   Communications -These are of vital importance since they are directly within our power.
RoadsWe should still further accelerate our road programme, giving special attentionto the A19 (with connexion from Al to Midlands), the roads at each end of the tyne tunnel, and the spine road serving the Killingworth-Cramlington complex.There are plenty of local road-building programmes which can be accelerated.The tentative long-term programme of the Ministry of Transport should beaccepted and pushed forward as quickly as possible.In addition, in preparation for much longer-term developments the Al toEdinburgh should be surveyed and planned as a double-track system, and the A69which connects with Carlisle should be surveyed for development as a first-classroad.16.  Air communicationsIt is important that Wolsington airport should be developed. The public havealready shown appreciation of its services to an extent greater than other internalairports. I would envisage it becoming an international, but hardly anintercontinental, airport in due course.Wolsington does not conveniently serve the Tees. A second airfield is required.There is a potential airport better than Wolsington in Middleton St. George -a fighter station at which some civil landings are allowed, but not scheduled services.I am asking the Air Ministry how, // they were directed to do so, they wouldrearrange their programme so as to allow Middleton St. George to be used forscheduled flights and to what extent safety and security would be in jeopardy.At present it is said to be impossible. If it cannot be done another alternative(e.g., Usworth) should be reported on.17.  PortsIt is extremely important to do something about Teesport, Sunderland andthe Hartlepools. For Dorman Long and LCI. to remain competitive facilitiesmust be provided for really heavy ore carriers for the former, and really heavytankers for the latter, to come up. The ore carriers must be able to tie up oppositeDorman Longs (with a 40-foot draft in the long run); the tankers need not tieup at all; they require sheltered water and an adequate turning circle, but not aberth; there is, I should have said some possibility, which should be investigated,of the coast being more suitable than the estuary (tankers discharge into a flexiblepipeline).  The 100,000-ton tankers may need 50 feet or 60 feet of water.The Teesport Commissioners, though with an efficient official staff, are themselves an unwieldy body of 28 under Sir Eustace Smith mostly represented bylocal authorities (who do not always know whether they are coming or going).Urgent consideration should be given to making them more handy. The existingTeesport Development Scheme is in two stages.Stage 1Completion of Lackenby Docks and deepening to 34 feet with a 1,000 feetturning circle.   Cost  2 - 875 million, four years to complete.This would be sufficient for ships up to some 30,000 tons d.w.t., compared with20,000 tons at present..Stage 2       - v:r;; &apos;    &quot; &apos; /The deepening to 40 feet up to Dorman Long berth at Eston with a 1,200 feetturning circle. Channel widened to 800 feet. Cost  5-268 million, ten years tbcomplete. &apos;    &apos;:The Minister of Transport has proposed meanwhile to assist financially theTees Conservancy Commission to complete stage 1 quickly, and I recommendstrongly that his proposals should be accepted. They are already under examination by officials.
18.   OilLCI. use, or shortly will use, 1 - 6 million tons of oil a year as raw material fortheir chemical plant. It is at present imported as a light fraction. We should ensure that the oil companies put a refinery and a pipeline in at Tees-side. Refinerycapacity should be at least 4 million tons per annum.19   Hartlepools and SunderlandWe must help the Hartlepools; otherwise they will wither. The question ofmaking them the oil port should be examined without prejudice against them. Inthe meantime, it would pay to improve the facilities of Hartlepools and Sunderlandas coal exporting ports to the South.20.   The TyneI have not studied the Tyne as a port yet. My superficial impression is thatit is pretty old-fashioned. Unless they have vastly improved, the British Railwaysarrangements for the reception of tourists to and from Scandinavia (by the admirableBergen and Fred Olsen lines) are a perfect scandal, and British Railways should be told so.21.   HotelsI am extremely anxious that hotels of modern design should be built for commercial purposes in Newcastle and on the Tees. They should include modernconference and banqueting rooms, and showers as well as baths. We should consider whether planning permission applications of brewers to build the odiousconventional little beer houses they have been putting up should be used as meansof inducing them to build hotels more adventurous in design with bedrooms withbaths.   There is also a need for &quot; motels &quot; and perhaps a holiday camp.22.   The local authorities the local authorities must be encouraged to push on with all sensible schemesregardless of cost. They are extremely timid and lacking in self confidence, or, inthe main, robust and effective personalities. There is no danger whatever of theirover spending. It is quite the other way. But I would not underwrite theirschemes for wisdom or their designs for taste. They should be encouraged tobe both bolder, more imaginative and more broad minded. They turn awayindustrialists and nationalised industries by their pedantry and intellectual rigidity.For instance plans for an administrative headquarters in Newcastle for the gas board have financial approval but are bogged down in a planning squabble withNewcastle CB. Streets of derelict houses are standing in Newcastle near to thecentre which ought to have been knocked down years ago.The present scheme permitting the expenditure of  15,000 has outlived itsusefulness. The financial limit is fiddling and the time limit needs extending.The localities need vast improvements in general infrastructure and housing,and in general amenities immigrant enterprise is to be encouraged. I believe theMinistry of Housing and Local Government should put in Government appointedteams to provide leadership.We must grasp the nettle of the re-development of town centres in existingcentres of population. The local authorities must be persuaded that there is money in re-development and that the interest and financial resources of some of the bigreal estate developers must be won.  But we will have to provide the leadership.23.  Newton AycliffeThe question of the development of Newton Aycliffe should be settled as soonas possible either by allowing it to expand to 40,000 or thereabouts or, and inmy view preferably, by planting another new community of 20,000 in theneighbourhood.24.   Government officesThere should be acceleration of the building of new offices in Newcastle forthe Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance.
There should be a new branch office in Newcastle for the D.S.I.R.I believe that at any rate for a time there should be offices of the Ministryof Housing and Local Government and Ministry of Education in Newcastle,and probably other Ministries-as well as Labour and Board of Trade. Theyshould not be amalgamated into a sort of St. Andrews House. But it would be useful and nice to bring them together under one roof in new and attractivepremises, under the general supervision of Mr. Leckie.I should establish a small desk in these offices. There may be room for a&quot; Brecon &quot; type Minister of State here as well at a later stage.25.  The universitiesThe two universities need more rapid expansion. The Treasury should discuss with U.G.C. the means of this. I am considering whether the Governmentshould not place a major social studies research survey of the region to be carriedout by a team of professionals from Government Departments, the two universities and local government.26.  The North-East Development council the Chetwynd Organisation should be used as an instrument for publicisingthe region. It is not equipped to conduct research, and has no significant industrialbacking. We should encourage it to think, and plan, regionally, but local authorities(who finance it) have made it plain that they will not allow it to blossom perhapsas far as it could or should.27. This is in the nature of a progress report, and certain of my tentativerecommendations will call for a series of co-ordinated decisions on our planning for the region as a whole. It is important that where I have suggested actionwhich can be taken in advance of this we should decide and announce our intentions quickly. This is necessary to maintain the momentum of the exerciseand to put the region in good heart.HAILSHAM.Office of the Lord President of the Counciland Minister for Science, S.W. 1,13th February, 1963.


</content>
</cab>
