<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/112/0 images: 168-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINETREPRESENTATION OF THE VATICAN IN THE UNITED kingdom memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Cabinet last considered the question of Vatican representation in thiscountry in February 1960 (C.C. (60) 13th Meeting, Minute 4). They found thatthe arguments for and against a change of representation were evenly balancedand they decided to defer a decision.2. In the three years that have elapsed since then there have been profoundchanges in the world situation; Her Majesty&apos;s Government are drawing very muchcloser to Europe, most of Africa has been emancipated and the need to defendWestern ideals against Communism in the emergent countries all over the worldhas become more pressing. In these circumstances it would probably be to our advantage from a political point of view, in Europe and in the world at large, ifwe could put our relations with the Vatican on the same footing as the other majorEuropean Powers. It could&apos; also be of considerable practical benefit to us to havean Internuncio in London since it would enable us to maintain contacts with the vatican which the archaic set-up in Rome makes impossible for our representativesthere. Such contacts would permit closer co-operation in the general struggle against the spread of Communist influence, in which the Catholic Church is active,and they might also help us to enlist the support of the Vatican in our efforts tosecure better treatment for Protestants in Spain and other Catholic countries where they suffer from disabilities. This is a matter to which public opinion inthis country attaches great importance.3. The arguments against having an Internuncio here are also weighty butnot as weighty, in my view, as they were when the Cabinet last considered thismatter. Christians of all denominations are becoming increasingly interested inChurch unity. The House of Commons debate on Church of England affairs inDecember showed that religious matters can be considered in this country withoutnecessarily arousing old passions. There have been visits to the Pope not only by Her Majesty The Queen but also by the Archbishop of Canterbury, theModerator of the Church of Scotland and the President of the MethodistConference. These visits by leading churchmen represent a development ofhistorical significance.4. For all these reasons I think that the balance of advantage now lies infavour of accepting an Internuncio (with the rank of Minister) as Vaticanrepresentative in this country.H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,21st February, 1963.2122THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. February 1963C. (63) 26 Copy No. 5222nd February, 1963


</content>
</cab>
