<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/112/0 images: 240-242</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1963C. (63) 44 Copy No.   5211th March, 1963CABINETNATO NUCLEAR FORCE AND EUROPEAN policy memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs at Nassau the Prime Minister and the President agreed to use their best endeavours to develop a NATO Nuclear Force in the closest consultation withtheir NATO allies. Initially this Force will consist of existing nuclear forces,strategic and tactical. As time goes on, new weapons will replace old (e.g., UnitedKingdom Polaris submarines will replace the United Kingdom V-bombers) anda new component may be introduced in the shape of internationally-owned andinternationally-manned surface ships or submarines armed with Polaris missiles.This component is often described as the mixed-manned force or, in United Statesterminology, the multilateral force.2.   For the initial Force, the arrangements we favour are as follows:(a) Composition. In addition to the United Kingdom V-bombers and theUnited States contribution of three Polaris submarines, we would liketo include a wide range of tactical nuclear weapons: both aircraft and missiles. In this way the Europeans who have, or will shortlyhave, nuclear delivery vehicles (though not, of course, the warheads)would participate from the outset.(b) Command. SACEUR would be in command of the Force, having forthis purpose a special Chief of Staff or Deputy with an internationalstaff provided by the nations contributing to the Force.(c) Targeting. The targeting of the Force must be co-ordinated with theSAC plans, the detailed targets being worked out between SACEUR&apos;international staff and the SAC staff at Omaha.(d) Political   Control. A   Nuclear  Trusteeship   Group,  comprising   thePermanent Representatives of the countries contributing to the Force,would exercise peace-time supervision over the Force and givepolitical guidance to the military authorities.3. United States interest centres on the mixed-manned component. a united States Mission under Mr. Livingston Merchant is now visiting Brussels,Bonn and Rome and will be in London for discussions with the Minister ofDefence and myself on the 12th and 13th March, At these meetings we hope to elucidate the United States ideas on the mixed-manned component. We alsohope to hear the results of Mr. Merchants soundings in other European capitalsand to consider with his mission what contribution we ourselves could properlymake to the mixed-manned force. I shall give my colleagues an oral account ofthe meetings. We have already said that as we are contributing the polaris submarines our contribution would have to be strictly limited; perhaps the provisionof some contingents for the mixed crews.4. In the meantime, the United Kingdom Permanent Representative has given the Council our ideas in so far as these were agreed with the United Statesduring recent discussions in Washington: that is to say, on the military aspects(see paragraphs 2 (a), (b) and (c) above), but leaving on one side for the moment the question of political control.2217
5. The Council is therefore aware of the way in which we see the immediate steps to be taken on the military side to give effect to the Nassau Agreement onthe NATO Nuclear Force. Our efforts to ensure that an early start can be made towards giving the Europeans a greater voice in the nuclear policy of the alliance and our own contribution of the V-bomber force seem to have been generally welcomed by our European allies. These moves fall into place as part of ourgerieral policy, after the end of the Brussels negotiations, of strengthening our european connexions within the framework of the Atlantic Alliance. Thus theaction we are taking to follow up the Prime Minister^ initiative at Nassau enablesus to give practical effect to the need both for strengthening NATO itself andfor strengthening Europe&apos;s position within NATO.6. I propose myself to attend the North Atlantic Council on 20th march to explain our policy along these lines. By that time we shall have seen mr. Merchant and the members of his mission and I hope that it will then bepossible, against the general background of our Atlantic and European policy, tosay something about the way in which we shall hope to see the political controlof the NATO Nuclear Force developing. If Mr. Merchant has in fact succeeded in securing commitments from European countries to take part in the mixed-manned force, I see no reason why this need conflict with our own ideas on political control.  We see this as a continuing process.7. I told the Secretary-General and the United States Government of my intention to attend the Council on 20th March. Sir Evelyn Shuckburgh is alsotelling the Council and I am hoping that it will be possible for several of our friends among the European Foreign Ministers also to attend, so that this occasioncan be used to demonstrate our view of the proper position of Europe as an integral part of the Atlantic Alliance.H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,11th March, 1963.


</content>
</cab>
