<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/112/0 images: 267-269</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
At their meeting on 7th March (C. C. (63) 15th Conclusions,Minute 5) the Cabinet agreed to consider at a later meeting theform and scope of a possible inquiry into the rating system.2.      It is probable that the Opposition will put down for a Supply days motion on rating;  and they might put one down in terms similarto that put down by our own supporters (which asks in effect for thecost of education to be transferred by stages to the Exchequer, andfor a full inquiry into new methods of raising revenue for localgovernment services).3.      The Opposition might force a debate next week;  we shall not know till Wednesday.4.      If we are going to concede any kind of investigation we mustnot do it on or following a motion by the Opposition.     We should haveto get a Question put down by one of our own supporters in advance and announce it then.5.      Sooner or later we shall have to look at the probable course oflocal government expenditure and its implications for the rating system.     This being so there might be advantage in saying now thatwe are going to do it and starting it later this year.    The alternative is to stand firm and say that we see no need at all for any inquiry into rates at present.6.      If we do decide to have an inquiry I think the object should be mainly, if not entirely, to expose the facts;  what local government;expenditure must be expected over five to ten years;  the impact onthe rates given that the Exchequer contributions continue in the same proportion as at present;  the impact of rates on different classes of rate-payers in different areas;  perhaps also the practicability of alternative sources of local revenue - which should expose that thereare no practicable alternatives other possibly than a local incometax.7.      I would not exclude the possibility that such an inquiry might also look at the methods by which the big Exchequer grants are givento local authorities and consider whether there are better ones.That however needs further thought;  and also consultations withthe representatives of the local authorities.C. (63) 4612th March, 1963CABINETRATESMemorandumibY^he Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for Welsh Affairs-1-
8.     Such an inquiry could not I think be internal.    It would haveto include some people from local government and one or twooutsiders.    Possibly an independent chairman would be unavoidable.But I would not propose at this stage to say anything about the composition of the inquiry.9.      The immediate choice then is this:  to announce - before any Opposition motion can be debated - our decision to have an inquiry into the trend of local government expenditure and the implications for the rating system;   or to stand firm and offernothing.K. IMinistery of Housing and Local Government,Whitehall, S. W. 1.12th March, 1963


</content>
</cab>
