<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/44/37 images: 538-545</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Cj^w t2**J *.HtJl o^jfajTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 587.27th December, 1943SUMMARY OF OPERATIONS OF BOMBER COMMAND FOR FORT-NIGHT ENDING 1200 HOURS, SUNDAY, 19th DECEMBER, 1943.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.Unfavourable weather conditions and the full moon period permittedonly one heavy attack, which was made on Berlin on the 16th/17th December.Summary of Operations. a ircraftTarget. Date. Despatched.Berlin ............      16/17 December        496Abbeville     ...      ...      ......      16/17      ,, 36In addition, 106 aircraft were despatched on small harassing raids on german towns and 113 mines were laid.Operations.Berlin (I6th/17th December).Crews&apos; reports indicated that this attack, made by a force composed entirely of Lancasters, achieved a fair concentration. Night photographs were taken and,although cloud conditions made it impossible for them to be plotted, an examina-tion indicates that very large fires were started.Results of Previous Raids.Berlin (22nd/23rd, 23rd/2Uh, 2Qth/27th November, 2nd/3rd December).Although it is not yet possible to assess the devastation caused in these raids,information from intelligence sources shows both the severity of the material damage caused and the chaotic conditions created in the transport services and administration of the town. For a time, passengers in main-line trains travellingto the city were forced to get out at places some 20 or 30 miles distant and complete their journey on suburban trains. Whole streets were blocked withwreckage, and material damage is severe both to important industries and to thecentral and fashionable quarters.One of Berlin&apos;s most famous show places and restaurants, the Haus Vaterlandin the Potsdamer Platz, has been destroyed and an important area in theindustrial and working-class district of Moabit bounded by the Putlitz andHuttenstrasse has been almost completely destroyed. The Wittier bakery near the Lehrter Station, believed to supply half the bread for the city, was destroyedwith all its stocks of flour, causing a serious breakdown in the food distribution.Reports continue to arrive of other damage, of which the following are the mostimportant items : (i) Buildings in the Tirpitz Ufer containing the Admiralty and sections ofthe General Staff completely destroyed.(ii) The main assembly hall for tanks in the Berlin-Karlsruhe ArmamentWorks collapsed.(iii) The General Motors plant at Tegel very severely damaged.(iv) The largest gasometer in Berlin at Tegel burnt out.(v) A large number of range-finding and precision instruments for aircraft,guns and. submarines destroyed by a fire in the Werner Works, whichburned for two days,(vi) The Berliner Maschinenbau locomotive and torpedo component worksseverely damaged.[26632]Copy No.WAR CABINET.
(vii) Damage, the extent of which is not yet known, to the followingengineering, electrical or armament works-A.E.G., RheinmetallBorsig, Ludwig Loewe, Blaupunkt, Bergmann and Siemens.Leipzig.It is reported that in.the raid of the 3rd/4th December the main station was destroyed and within a distance of 1,300 yards the lines and the signalling systemwere wrecked. Fires were completely out of control in the centre of the city partly because units of the Leipzig fire brigade had been called to Berlin.Stuttgart.In the raid of the 26th/27th November, very heavy damage was caused inthe suburb of Zuffenhausen. One of the principal Bosch works was hit and theHirth Motor Works (engaged on research and development of aircraft engines)was severely damaged.M odane.A first interpretation of day photographs taken on the 18th December showsthat the raid carried out on the 10th/ 11th November was highly successful. TheInternational Station has been completely destroyed, and there are a large numberof incidents on the marshalling yards to the west. No endeavour appears to havebeen made to repair the damage. Ground sources have reported that one line isnow open, but it is not possible to confirm this from the photographs.Repairs and Reconstruction.Hamburg.Comparing photographs taken up to the 9th October with those taken a fewdays after the last heavy attack on Hamburg on the 2nd/3rd August, the firstimpression is that major repair work has been entirely limited to the shipyards,hospitals and a few factories. Less demolition work has been carried out in theheavily -devastated areas in the eastern parts of the city, which remain derelict,than to the western districts, where there appears to be some resumption of normal life and activity.In the dock area, repairs to the shipbuilding yards, particularly those ofBlohm and Voss and of Howaldts Werke A.G., were seen to be in hand soon after the raids. The latest photographs show that with the exception of a bargebuilding-yard in Veddel which was almost completely destroyed, all shipyardscovered appear to be active. Very few of the damaged warehouses are being-repaired, and stores and materials can be seen dumped at points along thequayside.The Rhenania Ossag Mineral Oil Refinery is one of the factories undergoingsubstantial repairs, and it is noticeable that priority has been given to factoriesproducing copper and metals, precision tools and chemicals rather than to those engaged in the production of food-stuffs and in other industrial activities.Of the public services damaged, two power stations a,nd a gas works areactive again, and two electricity sub-stations show signs of repairs. The railwayshave been sufficiently repaired to enable some train services to operate, and a fewtrams and buses can be seen in the cleared main thoroughfares.Mining.The following mining successes are reported  5th August. The Swedish Frans Gorthon (1,822 G.T.) was damaged bya mine while on passage from Nordenham to Stockholm.12th A ugust. The Oostende 29 and the Oostende 33 were mined and sunk.8th October. A Sperrbrecher arrived in La Pallice with mine damage.8th November. The German Dresden (5,567 G.T.) returned to BordeauxjU&apos;&quot; with mine damage.4dh November. A Danish motor vessel of 492 tons, with a cargo of peat,was mined and sunk North of Grenaa.5th November. The motor sailing vessel Energi, with a cargo of lignite,was mined off Aageleje whilst en route from Aarhus to Copenhagen.5th November. The fishing vessel Noekken of Copenhagen was minednear the Swedish coast en route to Laessoe.25th November. Fishing cutter H.130 of Hunsted was mined 4 miles .E. Gillelge (S.E. Kattegat)-.- A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, 27th December, 1943.







</content>
</cab>
