<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 4-4</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 4(49)						17th January 1949 (3.45 pm)



		1.	Meat Ration.					[Enter J.S.



J.S.	Bad enough to put 2d of bully into 1/= ration.

	Grave to fall below 1/= over all.  Never done during war.

	Safe to run canned stock down to 10.000 t. but only if we are assured we can re-build in winter/spring of 1949/50.

	Advise therefore 2d of bully pro tem and review in 2 months, in light of Miranda discussions.

	Announce tonight. Guidance to Lobby on lines tht. we aren’t going to be blackmailed by Miranda – ready if need be to cut Argentine meat altogether.



P.M.	Other sources



A.V.A.	Pork from Holland and Denmark.



J.S.	Getting pig meat fr. Denmark in form of bacon – 90% of their exports.



R.S.C.	No alternative to immediate action. No decision for future.

	Warn public of dangers ahead.  Importance of effective publicity – putting it firmly at Argentine door.

	No announcement tonight. See Lobby first and follow up with considered announcement tomorrow.



A.B.	Disadvantages of Lobby mtg. if full announcement made.



J.S.	Either full statement and short conference or vice versa.



H.W.	Cuts will be lasting and may be worse. Consider re-arrangemt. of food subsidy.  Reduce subsidy on meat. Wd. seem tht. total value wasn’t being cut.  And other foods (eg. dear fish) wd. be encouraged. Shdn’t Ty. and M/F. consider eg. rise of 2d in 1/= and putting money saved into subsidy of other foods.



R.S.C.	Politically too difficult. Unless we have to pay Miranda more.

	That wd. give us an excuse.



	Agreed : announce Tuesday in terms to be settled in agreement with Ty.

								            [Exit J.S.

		2.	Palestine.



E.B.		a)  Have considered this morning’s discn.  Suggest we tell U.S. we are 		willing to recognise Israel if they will recognise T’jordan. Then try to 		get both done simultaneously.

	Am consulting other Govts. interested in recognition of Israel.

		b)  General strategy and policy re M/East.  Have bn. unable to get U.S. 			concurrence.

	Asked U.S. recently if they wd. support this.

	If it cd. now be announced tht. there is Anglo/U.S. understanding over M/E. as a whole, it wd. help us with Muslim countries.

	Suggest I now press them to agree to such an announcement now.

	These 2 things wd. give us a new slant in policy.



A.B.	Need to act quickly before pol. kettle here boils over.



E.B.	Will try to report to Cab. on Monday next.



A.	Debate in H/L.  Swinton has agreed to lay off Palestine.



A.V.A.	Statement in H/L. on recce’s. Shd. A.H. answer?



E.B.	Try to restrict it to operational point.

								[Enter Att. Gen.



		3.	Anglo-Norwegian Fishery Dispute.



T.W.	Agreemt. signed last Friday. But industry haven’t bn. told.

	They won’t therefore be ready to accept Yellow Line.

	Negotiators have done their best.  We shall have to decide on that, wthr. industry like it or not. Ask for authy. for 3 Ministers to decide in light of discussion this pm. with the industry.



Att.G.	Right to accept this Yellow Line if it follows pretty well the existing modus vivendi line.



	W’out prejudice to future action.



T.W.	Don’t want to take any further decision for today.





		4.	North West Atlantic Fisheries Convention.



T.W.	Cd. have handled by F.A.O. but Spain cdn’t come in to that.

	U.S. have therefore handled it by separate convention.

	Want therefore to send small delegation to keep these waters open to us in case Bear Island goes dry of fish.

R.S.C.	Shdn’t we protest at this way of handling the ques.



T. W.	See App. B.  Delegn. may be asked to invite further instrns. if they can’t get all they want.



N.B.	Separate standing organn. to handle matter wh. is for F.A.O. is wrong.

	Go to this mtg. but try to work it back into F.A.O.



T.W.	F.A.O. haven’t taken exception.



E.B.	Typical of our diffies with U.S.A.

	Memo. approved.

	Register at least formal disapproval of procedure.





		5.	Royal Commission on Divorce.



P.M.	M. Odie M.P. will ask me to appoint R. Commn on divorce law.



J.	Sooner of later will have to be R. Commn. eg. artificial insemination.

	But v. diff. – and prefer p’pone until after election.

	Agitation (small) by Marriage Reform League – mainly urging that separation alone shall be ground for divorce on appln. of deserting party.



P.M.	Press : Cap. Punishmt. : Betting :  Enough?



	Aim at postponement.		Agreed.



	“May be at some later date it may be right to institute some form of enquiry”.



</content>
</cab>
