<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 6-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 6(49)							24th January 1949



		1.	Defence Estimates 1949/50.		[Enter Service Ministers.



A.V.A.	Some terminals – tho’ reduced by £40m.

	Total estimate £760 reached after 3 downward revisions, from original estimate of £833 m. by Service advisers.  C/E. said £700 m. was all we cd. afford + £12 m. for addl. cost of Service pay.

	Man power (paras. 11-14).  Commitments extended in time : man power related to £712 m. wd. have increased on balance and impaired readiness to “fight with what we have”.  Demobilised 5½ m. since end/war : and absorbed over 1 m. several hundreds of thousands having passed in and out.

	Totals show air-lift separately.  Air Miny asked tht. this be borne on F.O. Vote

	Ty. opposed that, on principle and also because elements in W.O. Estimates for Berlin effort.

	Cost in current year £730 m. or more via 693 m. previously estimated(?).  £760 m. involves reducg. average strengths several thousands below C.O.S. minimum – aiming at 750.000 target for March ’50. Some cuts also in emergency re-equipment p’mmes. Admy. emergency p’mme can’t so easily be separated from long-term : can’t quantify the cuts.  Air Miny won’t be v. serious.  W.O. – a severe pruning.



	Even so : R.N. addl. – 66 aircraft new, overhauls, de-gaussing cable, boom equipmt. clothing for reserves.

	Army – prodn. of new tanks (Centurions 82), overhaul of older tanks, ammunition (special categories), wheeled vehicles (v. small), repair of vehicles (large), AA. gun overhaul.

	R.A.F. – 251 jet fighters(addl), signals, stores for reservists, spares.

	Oil stocks.  Allowed to go v. low. P’mme. means cutting steps intended to build them up again.

	Taking some risks in going down to this figure. Tried to make cuts in least dangerous directions.



P.M.	Bulk expenditure large : controversy over small marginal sums : but these are the re-equipmt. and modernisation items. Cdn’t cuts be borne elsewhere? Satisfied tht. larger “overheads” are irreducible.

	Have bn. living on stocks. Have given much to Allies etc. Renewals now inevitable.  Obsolescence.

	Forces abroad unusually large – must have large adminve tail.  More costly therefore than corresp. nos. at home.



	Balance ratio. 3 Services. Can’t be changed overnight.

	Length of time to re-equip : long lag for ships and aircraft, cpd. Army equipment.



	Diff. therefore to get adjustmt. in propns of expenditure wh. we shd. have liked to see.

	Need to combine planning ahead, present needs, possible early emergency.

	Commend Estimates to Cab. Further cut of few millions wd. involve disproportionate loss of efficiency.



A.W.	R.A.F. Propn of amateurs and pros.  Any way of enabling R.A.F. to consist wholly of regulars? More economical.

	Oil stocks are reserves as much as dollars. Prudent to build them up – and count as asset.



A.H.	The 8.000 is conscript element if we cdn’t have Estimate.  At present 10.000.



R.S.C.	Accept Estimate with reluctance because heavy financial load.

	But must continue autumn emergency p’mme: and this + increased costs means this Estimate isn’t larger than last years’.

	At same time, I pressed need for co-ordinated plan. Asked for it by next May. If we can then have proper review, we may be able to say wthr. we are getting best value for money spent.



A.V.A.	Support that.  Have tried myself.  But fair to say that, while overset by cuts (autumn ’47), then emergency addns. (autumn ’48), they have had to concentrate on short-term problem.

	Now expect report to D. Cttee. by May.



A.B.	Commn. betwn. Budget and p’mme submd. to O.E.E.C.  That assumed 5% of natl. income wd. go to Defence : 7% to social services. And if any improvemt. it is to go to industrial equipmt. This was our announced pattern.  If we increase Defence expre. and preserve rest of pattern, social services will suffer.



R.S.C.	Defence was assumed at last years’ figure : 7%. But warning given tht. necessary increases wd. affect pattern.

	Hope it may be found fr. increased natl. income.  £693 to £760 increase need not affect pattern of proportions.



A.B.	Then increased productivity isn’t to go to industrial equipment.



R.S.C.	We said increased availability for capital investment wd. go to industry.

	Our published p’mme didn’t assume as great an increase in natl. income as we shall in fact get.



A.	x/. in para. 4 of memo.  In R.A.F. greatest need is for long-term offrs. and greatest impediment is married quarters.  This is last economy we shd. make. What economy is proposed?



A.H.	Not touching married quarters or living condns. generally.



A.V.A.	On 833 m. the Services cd. have made better provision.

	£8½ m. total as cpd. £5½  in current year on accommn.



E.Sh.	True.  But in relation to p’mme the provision is inadequate. We shall have to cut, home and overseas.

	I reserved my posn. Because of co-ordinated plan.  When we get that, we may be able to economise largely. May have bearing on these figures.

	W.O. estimate £348 m. + £6 m. for increased pay.  That wasn’t extravagant bid. On R.S.C. total we had to come down to £315 m. at gt. risk.

	Cdn’t have that. We scraped again – down to £306 m. That was irreducible. Now I’m being asked to take even less. The figure now is not closely related to p’mme : it’s a target.  Can be accepted only on assumption tht. on a/c of increased appropns in aid we balance the books.  We must spend £306 m. and sell more stores to balance our a/cs.

	Our commitments are increasing. eg. Malaya.  May be we shall have to re-inforce to get cleared up.  Esp. because of trouble on Siamese border.

	Berlin is costing us £400.000.  Aqaba will cost us money.

	Finally, Cs-in-C. warn me of discontent because of lack of m. quarters for officers. We shall have to act and spend. Tented accommn. widespread in F. and M/East.

	What of Cyrenaica? Can’t have a contented Army w’out spending on this.

	Man power report.  Discussed with Ministers. Concln: we must provide civilian labour for chores.  On Estimates, however, we have had to curtail this.



R.S.C.	Can’t proceed on basis of Minister declaring tht. he will exceed his Estimate and ask for Supplementary.  Proposing this year to rule out supplemies except on policy change.



H.	This represents cut of £31 m. on original estimate. Bound to affect both my emergency p’mme and m. quarters p’mme.

	R. and D. p’mme included in my total. Also Fleet Air Arm, wh. is now ⅓ of personnel.

	Two commandos for M/E. to help W.O. 

	No provn. for new ships – only going on with ships laid down earlier.

	Cut of £¼ m. in housing p’mme.



H.M.	Ty. concln. is wise.

	We are in gt. diffy. in believg. tht. all poss. economies are made in Services.

	Cd. business men or industrial consultants help?



P.M.	Done so already on M. Power Cttee.

	Wd. like W.O. organisation itself to be reviewed.  Surplus (post-war) of senior officers. That is now being examined.



A.V.A.	Increases for W. Union and similar new organisations.



J.	Relativities. Surprised more isn’t spent on R.A.F.



H.	Admy. overhaul (manning) by outside Cttee.



A.H.	We have had several such Cttees.



	Estimates approved.				[Exit Service Ministers.





		2.	Palestine.



E.B.	Done my best. But pledged to Arabs for more than 100 years (?) Acute phase of Pal. problem has started intense Arab nationalism – among the younger men. Need therefore for caution.



	Arabs haven’t had a square deal from U.N. – will say so on Wed.

	Must therefore pay attentn to both sides, not Jews only.

	Consulted Ibn Saud. His secret view has always bn. tht. Anglo/U.S. policy shd. be settled and imposed.  Asked him earlier to propose to Arabs negotiation for settlement. Told him we are now considering de facto recognn of Israel.  He replies : we are quite wrong if we suppose Jews will settle down w’in any frontier.  That sums up view of all Arabs.

	Supply of arms to Arabs.  Apart fr. war, requd for internal security : and they are nervous of that now. Fr. promised supply Syria with rifles etc. on understandg. won’t be used in war v. Jews.



	We have held up all supplies to T’jordan – tho’ ammunition in Amman now under our control. Have refused requests fr. Egypt.

	Advice fr. Arab countries : recognition of Israel will complicate our diffies.

	Have always believed in settlement by negotns.



	Consulted Comm. and W. Union countries. Canada and S. Africa have given it already and recognise T’jordan (in a way).  Australia wants to do it – not before 28/1.  N.Z. wants to do it – after Cabinet decision. India prefers federal solution : realises now recognn. may be necessary but isn’t ready to do it yet because of relations with Moslem world. Pakistan strongly opposed : wd. put premium on aggression.  Ceylon not ready yet to recognise.



	French.  Wanted agreemt. before recognising.  May settle today : and if so will recognise.  Benelux stress need for acting together : suggest it shd. be discussed at mtg. later this week.



	Ty. points outstanding also.  Shd. we wait and settle those first? Or give de factor recognn., settle before de iure win recognn.



		Is it proper to recognise while U.N. resolns are being flouted? eg. 			troubles over Dutch disregard of U.N. resolns in Indonesia.



	With these warnings I recommend:



		a)  Keep in step with W. Union Govts.

		b)  Don’t outrage Arabs by yielding to Press campaign.



	Therefore : I wd. prefer to announce only tht. we are consultg. Comm. and W. Union Govts. with a view to ascertaining possibilities of giving de facto recognition at an early date. [Read a careful formula.

	M/East is essential to our defence. If it goes, money voted under item 1 will be wasted. Important therefore to show that in this Comm. countries and W. Union countries are acting together with us. This is at least as important as Anglo/U.S. agreement.

	Also want to avoid x. purposes with Pakistan.  The 2 ends of Moslem world Turkey and Pakistan are v. important.  Which way will they lead the Moslem world?  We may be sowing seeds today.

	Believe in Moslem revival.  Can’t assume it will be friendly whatever we may do.

	Counsel caution accordingly. To prevent outraging Moslem world.



P.M.		Austr. Cab. meet Thurs. N.Z. on Weds.



N.B.	They don’t want us to go ahead of them.  Good case because earlier they were restrained only by us.



T.W.	Do we contemplate condns  like French?



E.B.	No : wd. be thought to be designed for delay.  Wd. prefer to have negotiations betwn. de facto and de iure.



J.	U.S.?



E.B.	Believe they will give de iure recognn to Israel : T’jordan tomorrow if elections in Israel go well.

	Asked them for joint decln. on M/E. policy.  But they wanted to tie it up with what we had done in Palestine.  And I therefore dropped it.



A.B.	Unfortunate tht. announcemt. shd. now be p’poned.

	One reason we had in mind was to avoid seeming to do it under Parly. pressure.

	Does E.B.’s formula mean tht. if India and Pakistan won’t recognise, we won’t?



E.B.	No.



R.S.C.	No one can doubt meaning of E.B.’s formula.

	It is wise to avoid doing this in a way inconvenient to our associates.



E.B.	Will try to get France to p’pone any unilateral recognition until we can indicate intentn to try for genl. W. Union agreemt. to recognise.



H.M.	Support the formula. Shd. satisfy H/C.



A.W.	R. declns of anti Zionism?



E.B.	R. will switch over soon to support of Arabs.



A.B.	R. will always make effective inroads into countries with primitive econ. organn.

	That is why they will have success in Arab States.

	That is why I doubt if any possibility in modern world of any effective homogeneity in Moslem world or any strategic unit.



	Our problem is now to extricate ourselves with least damage.

	Diff. Parly. decn.  Unwise to decide today to send arms to Arabs.

	If informn. to that effect leaked out, our Parly. diffies wd. be v. gt.

	I have no confidence in Iraq etc.  Pouring money down drain.  If we have to secure our oil, we may have to act, but not by buttressing Arab States.



P.M.	Remember our obligns.  Also how J. have bn. receivg. arms etc. thro’ the Truce.  How can we stand well with Asiatic nationalism if we don’t see fair play.



R.S.C.	eg. non intervention in Spain.



H.D.	How urgent is this? Ques of timing.



E.B.	Ready for Def. Cttee to examine urgency of need and what is required for internal purposes.



H.D.	Can’t we clear recognition first?



	Agreed :  E.B.’s formula for debate.

		    Def. Cttee. can consider applns. re supply of arms to Arab 	    States.



	Warning re leakages of Cabinet discussions.





		3.	Resumption of Austrian Treaty Negotiations.



		Agreed.





		4.	Lynskey Tribunal: Report.



C.E.	Vote Office Tuesday at 6 pm.

	Copies for Ministers can be obtained fr. H.O. at that hour.

	On Thursday H.M. will be pressed to give a day for Debate.

	I can’t attend Cab. on Thursday.



R.S.C.	84 page report. Won’t M.P.’s want a little time to read and consider.



H.M.	Don’t think we need promise debate as early as next week. Followg. week wd. do.



R.S.C.	Sooner the better – avoid repeated discussions.



A.B.	Agree : get it out of the way.



</content>
</cab>
