<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 24-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 27(49)							13th April 1949



		1.	Parliament.					[Enter W.W.



H.M.	Business for week after Easter Recess.

	Mogg’s Motion today (about row on M/Food speech in Meat Debate). Ought to be cleared off Order Paper.  He won’t press it to a Division. We must resist it.

	Precedent : E. Benn’s motions of censure on Speaker in a Budget debate.

	Not really analogous.



A.W.	Milner won’t want to speak.



H.M.	I wasn’t there. Cd. P.M. take debate? 



P.M. 	Willing if available.

	Dock Strike.  If an emergency has to be declared Parlt. must be recalled in 5 days.  No powers likely to be requd until 20th Apl. – then Parlt. wd. have to be recalled on Mon vice Tuesday.



						[Enter B., J.S., Att Genl., C.P.M.

						[Exit W.W.



		2.	Dock Strike.



G.A.I.	Read latest report.  Slight increase in no. of strikers.

	Continuity rule : one gang sees job thro’: if a Stevedore is missing whole gang stops.  Trying now to get agreemt. to T. &amp; G.W. men being added there.



A.W.	Glasgow has declined to come out in sympathy.



C.E.	a)  Executive steps – as in memo.

	Police report this is being used by Comms. to sabotage E.R.P. by disrupting essential services.  Aim = spread it and keep it going for 8 wks.



	b)  First official legal strike since end/war.  This Union is trying to bring others out in support.  Inadvisable to take criminal procdgs. v. individual strikers.  But injunction against leaders? (para. 6).



	c)  Investign into condns at docks (para. 7), and search for remedies.



Att.Genl.	We are hoist with own petard. Chance of civil procdgs. less because repeal of 1927 Act.  But, three conceivable possibilities –



	i)  Member of Union cd. apply for restraint v. strike pay as illegal use of funds.



	ii)  Bd. or employers cd. bring action for damages and injunction for procurg. breach of contract.



	iii)  I might claim injunction qua illegal acts tending to injure public.



	No precedent in resp. of strike.

	But value doubtful unless it is thought a court decn tht. strike is illegal wd. impress strikers and cause them to drop it.

	Criminal procdgs. cd. be taken v. leaders, not individuals.  Aiding and abetting or conspiracy.

	Expediency.  Doubtful. eg. our speeches on repeal of 1927 Act.

	But, if we don’t act, this war-time legn will be a dead letter.

	This is not a case in wh. I wd. prosecute w’out being assured by my colleagues there is no pol. objn. to prosn.



G.A.I.	No doubt this is deliberate attempt by Comms. to create trouble for pol. reasons.



A.B.	I favour legal action v. leaders at Cttee  But have concluded tht. Unions case is so weak tht. they won’t be able to sustain it.

	Risk : our action might give them a further card to play in getting strike continued.

	Suggest therefore b’cast by G.A.I. to put issues to strikes and prevent spreading.

	Fact tht. lightermen have decided not to come out is decisive in my view. (against advice of their executive, who had pledged their support).



	Support para. 7.



P.M.	cf. Bridges in Australia.



A.V.A.	Will be test case of our willingness to protect interests of State.

	Advise civil procdgs. at least, if not criminal.

	Otherwise shall be criticised for not mtg. this challenge to Govt. authority.



Att.G.	Civil wd. be for employers.  It is criminal procdgs. wh. State wd. be said to be under duty to take.



H.M.	This is the first illegal official strike.  If we ignore that, how shall we meet future threats.  Can’t leave it for more than 2 days or so.



A.W.	This is a clear issue.  The next example may not be.  Here is the chance to act.



J.	Are we sure we can get a conviction?



Att.G.	Depends on evce – speeches made.  Charge under D. Rgs. for counselling and procuring contravention of Order.

R.S.C.	How do we expect this strike to end, if we don’t take any action?



A.B.	T. &amp; G.W.  Union are v. it: their men will prob. go back.  That reduces volume.



R.S.C.	What will Bd. do?  Will they terminate contracts?  Or take the men back?



G.A.I.	a)  Conflict between T.&amp;G.W. and Stevedores Union.

	b)  Latter are anti. Govt.

	c)  Latter want to see end of de-casualisation scheme.



B.	Support A.B.’s view.

	Strike isn’t going too well for St. Union.  Lightermen’s decn.  Decn of T.&amp; G.W. U. to suspend continuity rule may mean tht. many come back, to fresh gangs.

	T. &amp; G.W.U.  Stevedores will frighten Stev. Union.

	M/T. preparing for Govt. action on Wed. next.

	Support para. 7.  Hope it will be done this time.  If T. &amp; G.W. Union members realised scheme was in danger, they wd. come to their senses.



P.M.             x/ G.A.I. shd. b’cast tonight.  No B.B.C. objns shd. be entertained.



A.V.A.	This is official T.U. strike and illegal.  Failure to prosecute will make it v. diff. for any other T.U. leader to restrain illegal action.



Att.G.	If you don’t prosecute this time, you won’t be able to do so in future.



P.M.	But no need to hurry prosecn.  Must see wthr. evidence is available.



	Att.Gen. and H.O. to prepare the case for a prosecn.

                    y/	M’while if asked in H/C. wthr. prosn will be taken, say “this is being looked into : collectg. the facts”.  Later: volunteer : “under active considn”.



		(H.O. memo.  approved.  Announcemt. re troops can be 	included (in b’case tonight (19 pm)

		(x/ and y/ approved.

                       Agreed (On policy, inexpedient to start a prosecn before Wedy.

		(But start procdgs. on Wed., unless circs. have so far changed 	(as in opinion of P.M. warranted further delay.

		(Repeat G.A.I.’s  b’cast on news at intervals up to Fri. a.m.





		3.	Meat Ration.



J.S.	30.000 t. needed in May/June if further cut is to be avoided.



R.S.C.	Mexican statemt. erroneous – they are ready to be paid in sterling.

	Took note : another report after Easter.

H.D.	Announcemt. tht. we have clinched Austr. meat deal wd. stiffen our public and discourage Argentine.



R.S.C.	Have suggd this already to Chifley.



							[Exit J.S., B



		4.	International Labour Conventions.



H.M.	I.L.O. is a menace.  Where is our Parly. freedom?  They are turning out too much. eg Art. 2.  N.C.B. even now are decling. to recognise a staff union.  L.a. closed shop.

	Why ask this stuff about N.I.  Why not say simply : doesn’t apply in limited sphere of N.I.



A.	Cut Annex B. 



Att.G. 	1st three paras wd. suffice.



J.	This may be a Comm. Charter. eg. Minute 2.  We might have to bring in legn inconsistent with Art. 2.



	Discn adjourned.





		5.	Political Processions in London.



C.E.	 Shall endorce it on 1/5.



R.S.C.	Give warning tht. it’s illegal.



</content>
</cab>
