<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 25-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 29(49)							27th April 1949



		1.	India.



P.M.	Wish to report on P.M.M. talks.

	Earlier – agreed : keep India in and preserve Crown link as far as possible.

	Not easy to get agreement.  Reached, however, this concln – read out declaration.

	Discussion over “Head of Commonwealth”.  Adjusted by agreed Minute.

	Basis of others’ membership “not hereby changed”.  Agreed Minute requested by Pakistan.



	Agreed minute regarding Preferential Treatment.

	Our main ques : a year ago it seemed unlikely India wd. accept any real link with Crown.  Little in 8 Points.  But India has come a long way.  May not be fool-proof : but something to stand upon.



R.S.C.	Constructive views of Malan.  V. striking.  Due to his reasonableness that “H. of C.” has bn. accepted.



J.	Congrats. to negotiators.

	Obvious blemishes.  Assume this is agreed, however.  Pity effort not made to remove blemishes.

	Regret lack of consultn.

	1)  War.  If India attacked, we shd. be morally bound to help.  Does India accept same obligation?  Made worse by concluding flourish.

	Shd. have bn. extended to “all matters of common interest” – so as not to eliminate war.



P.M.	Can’t expect India to accept oblign which others don’t.

	The “flourish” comes fr. Balfour Rpt. of 1926.



N.B.	Cdn’t have faced substantive ques.

	Main anxiety was over f. policy.

	Settlement is generally acceptable to all P.M.’s.



H.D.	Views of older Doms.



P.M.	a)  Anxious to keep India in.  b) Anxious to re-affirm allegiance of others.

	This has bn. met by declaration.



H.D.	What will King’s relation to Indians ; in fact.



P.M.	None.  India is a republic : recognise him only as Head of an association of which India is a member.

	Ceremonial relations might be developed, as time goes on.



R.S.C.	Must now evolve attributes for the H. of C. – a new conception.



A.V.A.	Done better than I had hoped.

	On J.’s  1) no real changes.  Shall have to negotiate with India bi-laterally on defence.  This gives atmosphere for it.



A.B.	Remarkable achievement.

	Significance of language depends on reality of commn.  This gives a bridge if the compulsions draw us closer.



T.W.	Nehru has come a long way.



Att.G.	Politically admirable.

	Lawyers will ask what it means.  Symbol meant somethg. when all owed allegiance.  Court might say tht. it meant nothing on this Indian relation.



P.M.	We recognised that.

	Were prepd to fight a case, even on basis of republic with no Crown commn.



A.W.	Reality more important than words.



N.B.	Gratitude to Krishna Menon.



		(Release of announcement – to Press.

		(Promise early facilities for debate in H/C.





		2.	Syria.



E.B.	Proposed recognition of new Govt. 27th.



</content>
</cab>
