<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 44-44</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 48(49).				25th July, 1949.



1.	Dock Strike.                    [Enter  W.W:  J.S., G.S., H.G., P., 

			                  H.McN., D.J., E.E.B.     



C.E.	Can be terminated by O. in C. – proclamn – wh. automatically 

		revokes E. Regs.

	But the 2 Dock Labour Bds. meet to-day:  and Ammon is 

		unpredictable.

		Wants to make examples of some men. Wd bring trouble again.

	Maxwell therefore recommends no procln or dispersal of troops until

		after these mtgs.

	May I have discretion to act on knowledge of out-turn of mtgs.



A.B.	Bd. can’t act w’out assent of Emergency Cttee.



C.E.	Not sure if Ammon mayn’t let decisions be known.



A.B.	Shd. we not formally tell Bd. tht. action needs confirmn of Em. Cttee.



H.M.	Yes:  otherwise they may assume emergency is over.



G.A.I.	Don’t think Bd. will follow awkward lead by Ammon.

			Agreed:  M/L. to inform Bd. (in terms:  Emergency will be

			               declared at an end as soon as possible, but

			               m’while they can take no action w’out confirmn

			               by Em. Cttee.  Telephone &amp; confirm by letter.)



W.W.	A short debate on ending of Emergency.  Either Tuesday or Thursday.

		As soon as O. in C. is made.



H.M.	We made a reply to King’s message, tho’ it wasn’t necessary.

		Will or may be said that we shd. send a reply on the termination.

	Such a reply is debatable.

	Opposn may want a debate - &amp; may use Supply Day on Tuesday.





	2.	Railway Dispute.



G.A.I.	V. complicated &amp; delicate.

	4 separate applns to 4 sets of employers – for wage increases.  And 

		reported a dispute to M/L.  I ruled there were 4 disputes, each to

		be handled under own procedure.

	4 Unions concerned.  I consulted them on methods of handling it.

		One suggn was a 5-man Bd. of Conciliation, whose recommns wd.

		be accepted as binding.  The Union repves assented.  Three

		Unions did.  But Fedn of Shipbldg. &amp; Eng. Trades wdn’t accept 

		a) binding nature of Bd.  b) wanted to use own machinery.

	I therefore offered Bd. for all save shipmen.  Two Unions accepted.

		N.U.R. wanted it to cover all or none.  But are meeting to-day

		to consider.  N.U.R. are mainly semi-skilled:  don’t cover bulk

		of craftsmen.  So ques. of relative rates is trouble.



H.M.	Right to exclude shopmen – who wd. have big repercussions in other

		industry.  But why didn’t M/L. exclude them from the outset.





	3.	Mining:  Dispute by Colliery Winding Men.



G.A.I.	3 months’ since notice given – leaving them right to strike.

	Real issue:  who has right to represent interests of Winding-men.

	Wages haven’t kept level with deputies.

	Right to speak direct to N.C.B. instead of thro’ N.U.M.

					          [Exit  W.W.



	4.	Meeting of Commonwealth Finance Ministers.



H.W.	Two parts – Ministerial &amp; official.

	All agreed tht. Ministerial discns had bn. helpful.

	Tribute to Ty. officials.

	Part III is notable agreemt. in principle.  But will take time to produce

		Effects - for in many cases their machinery is slow. eg. licensing

		for 12 months.

		Shan’t see much results during next 3 months.

	Dispelled pipe-dreams about ways of avoiding dollar cuts.

	Canada:  their line wasn’t satisfactory.  Their theories are dangerous.

		They expect us to find means of financing Canada’s deficit with 

		U.S.  Afraid of associatg. themselves with our dollar cuts. 

		Cling to fallacy tht. because they have a deficit with U.S. they

		can do nothing to help Commonwealth.

	Subsequent official talks – useful on substitn for dollar imports:  e.g. all

		save I.P. &amp; S. Afr. have agreed to import no more U.S. cars.

		Textiles, machinery, tractors also discussed.

			-   dollar earnings.  One or two things can be done.

	Seek approval of recommns to govts.  These weren’t publd.  In the

		main a brief for W’ton talks.  Believe other Govts. will accept.

		Then R.S.C. can speak for sterling area.

	Shd. they be shown to U.S. Adminn.  R.S.C. isn’t worried about 

		leakage.  Much of it wd. be helpful.  Wd help U.S. to prepare for

		Sept. talks.  All Comm. Govts. must agree to it.  Delegns will urge

		Govts to agree.



J.S.	Food.

	Wheat:  we cd. help India.  If Cab. authorised me to buy sterling wheat

		fr. elsewhere.  But, before we release nearly ½ m. tons to India, 

		want to be sure we can get it from elsewhere.       Approved.



H.W.	Quantities contingent on Australian harvest.



J.S.	Meat &amp; Butter.  We think these are bad examples of good principle.

		Butter prices in U.S. are so low that A. &amp; N.Z. wdn’t be able to 

		sell any.  And our supplies wd. be endangered.

		Meat also is expected to drop in autumn to U.S. support price.

	We don’t think there’s anything in these.



H.W.	R.S.C. wd. agree.  Tallow also.  May lead to break-down of rationing

		in S. Doms.	Agreed:  drop these.



J.S.	Sugar &amp; tea.  We can do what is asked here.



A.B.	Canada’s prosperity is cause of our troubles.  Wheat price is too high.



H.W.	We have recognised tht. sooner or later we shd. have to face Canada.

		R.S.C. wants to do it early in Sept. talks.

                   x/	Suggest offls. shd. prepare &amp; submit to Cab. a separate brief on the 

		whole ques. of commercial relations with Canada.



A.	What practical proposals.  What do we want them to do?



J.S.	Take sterling payment for the wheat.



H.W.	Hold sterling:  introduce import discrimination against U.S.

			Agreed as at x/.  E.P.C. this week.



P.M.	But remember that time is short.

	Can you wait until Sept?  To put suggn tht. Canada shd. accept part

		payment in sterling?



H.W.	Let memo. come to E.P.C. &amp; we can then consider earlier action than

		Sept.

			Recommendations Approved.

			Consent given to Commn to U.S. (thro’ O.F.).





	5.	The Dollar Situation.



P.M.	Figure in para. 6 was 46.8.



D.J.	And next week likely to be 70.



P.M.	Are they going to do anything quick to help before Sept.



H.W.	Resuming stock-piling.

	May be more favourable to India’s appln to I.M.F.  Tho’ decn can’t

		be taken until I.F.M. mtg. in Sept.



A.	Drain to Belgium.  We decided to stop buying Belg. steel.  When will

		it take effect?



H.W.	These paymts. relate to fiscal year ended 30.6.49.

	The new I.E.P.S. shd. rule out paymts. in gold from 1.7.49. onwds.



D.J.	We didn’t agree to stop buying Belgian steel.



A.V.A.	Belgium is down 25% in prodn &amp; emplt. is dropping fast.  They must

		accept new form of paymt. from us.



H.W.	They have done.



H.D.	Does what H.W. says accord with para. 13 of memo.



D.J.	Misleading to suggest we are at end of gold paymts. to Belgium.

		I.E.P.S. shd. cover us:  but can’t be sure.



H.W.	Still	a)  Firm limit of $40 m. p.a. fr. all Europ. countries.

		b)  Balances.



A.B.	Wiser now to rely on I.E.P.S. for protection.



P.M.	Para. 16 means we shall be at rock bottom on reserves before Sept.

		talks begin.  300 m. at end/Sept.

	“I was under impn ” tht. somethg. wd. be done by U.S. to hold posn

		m’while.  I am worried about the time-table.



H.W.	Standstill decisions.  Won’t take marked effect until 4th quarter.

	Time lag on exports payments.



H.M.	Most alarming situation.



A.V.A.	Reserves will be Nil by end/Jan.



P.M.	“Whole show put off until September.”



H.W.	Asked Ty. if there was danger of crisis of confidence, as in ’47.

		They said not many danger factors wh. cd. cause actual run on

		sterling.  American countries have done their damage in Apl. –

		when they turned their sterling into dollars.  Now it is U.S.

		importers slow to pay their bills etc.  Even that can’t go much

		further.



H.G.	Agree it’s not as dangerous as ’47.

	But risk of a big run, if it were thght. we were going to devalue soon.

	Shd we bring this up to E.P.C., after further discn in Ty.?         Agreed.



A.	Can’t U.S. buy more?



H.W.	Some commercial buying has re-started.  Tin &amp; prs. diamonds.

	Stock-piling of rubber has started.



	Recommend O.F. takes up-to-date apprecn:  urge intensification of

		stock-piling.  Appropns have now bn. voted.



P.M.	Canada?



H.W.	High-level message to Canada to start stock-piling.



H.W.	Appendix.

	15 m. higher exports (U.K.) in 2nd quarter.  This shows real cause is

		drop in U.S. purchases, not failure of U.K. to keep down costs.

	Generally – agree posn is critical.  But it’s no worse than we knew it to

		be at E.P.C. mtgs. on 24/6 and 1/7.  And Ministers then thought

		nothing wd. be gained by doing other than wait for Sept.



P.M.	But I thought Snyder wd. agree to some interim holding action.  That’s

		why I’m worried now.



McN.	No evce of help coming fr. W’ton or even of realisn in State Dpt. of

		seriousness of our situation.





H.M.	Don’t agree that no-one was realistic at E.P.C. mtg.

	I gave a warning.  And even now no-one a [sic]   



</content>
</cab>
