<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 67-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 4(50).				7th February, 1950.



	1.	Agricultural Review.	[Enter  J.S.



T.W.	a)	Targets.  Figures more realistic.  Para. 5.  Wheat = 2½ m.

		acres vice 2¾.  Yields are rising:  so we shall prob. get same

		amount – with less expense on incentive.  Potatoes also – we

		shd. gain money:  v. slight risk if season is bad.  Milk = 1952

		target already reached.  Proposed to raise it – shall get higher

		figure. 



R.S.C.	Shd. we go a little higher than 2½ m. for wheat – to avoid 

		appearance of retreat.  e.g. 2.600.000.  To keep up pressure to

		grow wheat.



A.	Support that.  Tho’ you won’t prob. get more than 2½ m. acres.



T.W.	Wd. accept 2.550.000.  Above 2½ m. you get into less prod. land.

			Agreed:  2.550.000 acres.



J.S.	Potatoes:  high target at guaranteed price is diff. to work.  Last year

		too many &amp; had to feed to stock.  This year we shall be a bit

		short, with rather larger target acreage.  Is it wise to imply to

		farmers tht. we have enough?



T.W.	V. small risk, given reasonable weather.

	Tradl growing areas have E worm (?).  Cutting down non-traditional

		areas helps tradl to recover. 



R.S.C.	Only just short this year.  If year had bn. good we shd. have lost

		much money thro’ feeding to stock.

	Real risk:  can you get imports to fill deficiency when you need ‘em.



T.W.	½ m. acres more than normal pre-war year.  Nearly 80% higher.

			Agreed:  Potatoes are recommendd.



R.S.C.	Milk.  Do nothg. to encourage further expansion.



T.W.	W’drawal of feeding stuffs subsidy will tend to discourage.

			Agreed.



R.S.C.	Timing of Review.  Are we really going to start on 13/2?  If so, 

		announced about 20/2 tht. we are going to do down farmers.



T.W.	Prelimy discns of figures will take several days.



R.S.C.	Electoral suicide.



P.M.	Negotns of this kind ought not to take place under shadow of Election.

		That can be said.  Decns shd. be left to new Govt.

		Not fair to next Govt., whatever it is.



T.W.	Will try to confine discns to clearing ground on figures etc., up to 23/2.



P.M.	No:  don’t start at all.



T.W.	N.F.U. expect mtg. to start on 13/2.



P.M.	P’pone considn of memo itself until after Election.



R.S.C.	Agree:  then no leakage is possible.



P.M.	And re-call all copies of memo.



R.S.C.	Discns on facts cd. start on 24/2.  Decns cd. follow.



		P.M. to settle terms of announcemt:  public or to farmers.

						[Exit  J.S.



	2.	Bamangwato Tribe.  Chieftainship.



N.B.	Telegram this a.m.  Moved faster than I thought it would.

	Newspp. say Seretse told Tribe:  Kwatla held:  D. Mail report is

		fullest.  Seretse has said he will be away for 3 weeks.

	C.R.O. think this means he knows he won’t carry on as Chief.  He will

		come home &amp; force us to refuse confirmn.

		I will see him on Monday:  &amp; if he won’t w’draw I shall tell him

		I can’t consult Cab. until after Election.



					[Enter  E.B.

	3.	Germany.



E.B.	Sitn in Berlin – elements of trouble again.

	R. dual policy.

		a)	annoyance:  holding up transport.

			U.S. were stupid to intervene &amp; gave no notice to us &amp;

			French.  We were caught unawares.

			R will rub it in.

	Confce in F.O. y’day.  Decided tht., if anythg. like return to normal, 

		we shd. avoid all provocative action.

		b)	E. Germ. Govt. have not bn. returng. goods &amp; are out of

			equilibrium with West on trade agreemt. made some time 

			ago.  Don’t know what Steele did.  Want to avoid becoming

			embroiled.  M’while W. Germ. Govt. have given orders to 

			stop delivery of steel because not getting return under barter

			deal.

	M’while U.S. have bn. talkg. big about restoring air-lift.  Can’t do that,

		w’out much prepn.

	Must avoid panicky action.

		Ask Cab. to leave this to me – consultg. R.S.C. so long as he is

			available.  Brian Robertson will be here on Thursday.





	4.	Indo China.



E.B.	Before Colombo talked to French &amp; hoped to clear this before 

		Colombo ended.

	But cdn’t press it too far with Nehru.  He was v. emotional about

		French  i) Over Pondicherri.  ii) Over Fr. failure to get ahead

		with real transfer of power in Indo China.  Ratificn was in fact 

		put off until 30/1 – in spite of their earlier assurances to me.

		Nehru believed French wd. let us down.

	Cdn’t therefore get concerted policy.

	Warned French thro’ Harvey tht. there was a risk tht. Stalin wd. do a

		deal over Manchuria &amp; help China to create ring of satellites

		going right into S.E.A.  I cdn’t get Fr. Govt. to realise dangers.

	Denning &amp; M.M. still urged me to recognise Bao Dai.  I was reluctant

		because Fr. dilatoriness.  Also gathered Canada wd. follow us in

		recognising Bao Dai:  but didn’t know what U.K. public opinion 

		wd. be.

		Then Statesman &amp; other Leftists came out v. Bao Dai.

		If I went ahead, &amp; Fr. hadn’t ratified – Fr. Socialists might vote			v. ratificn.  V. awkward for our Election.

	Decided not to act until I had seen Schuman.  By then R. had

		recognised “Hoochymin” (“Hoo Chin Mow” !!)

	Legal posn not clear – is it a State.

	Cdn’t get assurance wtr. &amp; if so how U.S. wd. recognise.

		This a.m. told (telegram) Truman has approved recognn  w’out		qualification.

	French pressed me to recognise on Sat.  Told them Cab. decn was

		necessary.

	But, after all this, I believe it is essential to give recognn now.

		Then to concert with Fr. &amp; U.S. firm stand comparable to ours		in H. Kong.

	Fr. Parlt. have now ratified.  And Socialists voted for it.



N.B.	M.M. has seen N.Z., A. &amp; Can. Ministers on way home.

	Spender favours early recognn.  Doidge will follow U.K.  Pearson

		will follow U.S.

	Asian. members are the trouble.  Nehru admits Hoochymin is Comm. 		but think Bao Dai shd. reach accommn with him. They doubt

		reality of transfer of power because Fr. reservations.  This is

		mainly because Fr. reservns with India over Pondicherri.

		Bajpai has said in terms they will not recognise any regime in

		Indo-China.  Don’t think they will criticise us.

	Pakistan.  May be brought to recognise Bao Dai.



E.B.	Don’t press Ceylon to do it.  Makes them look like satellite.

	May get Egypt or Iran to do it.



N.B.	M.M. thinks it’s w. recognn that matters to Bao Dai now.

			Agreed:  U.K. to recognise Bao Dai’s regime.





	5.	Hong Kong:  Tramway Strike.



N.B.	Tramway strike in H. Kong.  Is it due to low wages?

	cf. oil cos. at Abadan.  Said to be Comm. stunt.  But when condns 

		improved it disappeared.



C.J.	Earlier, danger of spreading to other utilities.  This checked.  Attempts

		at settlement – conciliation etc., - have failed.



A.V.A.	Intelligence rpts. support view tht. this strike was organised by Comms.



E.B.	But it’s where somethg. is wrong tht. Communists can exploit it.

		Is there a good M/L. man out there?



C.J.	Good Labour Dpt. – M/L. adviser went out – and T.U. offl. from U.K.

		is out there permanently.



E.B.	T.U. officials are not good at conciliation work.  Are you sure you

		have out there a man who is good at conciliation work.



C.J.	I will look into that. 		



</content>
</cab>
