<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/7/0 images: 76-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 13(50).				29th March, 1950.



	1.	Circulars on Civil Defence.



C.E.	P’poned because Election.

	Routine ques. only.  Advisable they shd. issue.

	Sr. Off. M/H. and H.O. discussg. genl. circular pointing out tht. 

                     x/	these &amp; similar circulars don’t imply tht. Govt. consider war

		to be imminent.



H.M.	Sooner the better.

	Pamphlet on Atomic Warfare – more serious.  Public will have to 

		know soon.



C.E.	That is being re-drafted so as to bring defence next to dangers in each

		section.



H.M.	This shd. come to Def. Cttee.



A.B.	Cleared for security:  no need for D.O.

	Politics are for Cab., not D.O.



C.E.	Proposg. to  ask P.M. to write Foreword.



H.McN.	Wise to make a statement before issue of circulars – by P.Q.



C.E.	Wd. rather draw attention in H/C.  Better send circular at x/

		simultaneously.

			Agreed.





	2.	Corporal Punishment.



C.E.	Press getting better.

	But want to promise in H/L. to collect case histories of men since

		Cadogan Rpt. analysis – wh. didn’t go beyond 1930.



H.M.	Be sympathetic.  Public are worried.



J.	L.C.J. doesn’t want law changed too quickly.  Wants more time to

		see effects.



E.B.	Remind Judges tht. they must accept verdict of Parliament.





	3.	Naturalisation Policy.



C.E.	Have for some years bn. reviewg. policy of natg known Comms.

		Fuchs case, &amp; its revelation of attitude twds. oath of allegiance,

		brings this to head.

	Fellow-travellers &amp; crypto’s are perhaps worse.

	No announcemt., but for some time shall follow line indicated in

		para. 4.  Same for Fascists.

	Act of discretion.  H.O. don’t have to give reasons.



J.	Agree.



E.B.	Glad to know there will be no announcemt.

		Don’t discourage applns.  Gives us informn of value.



A.B.	Presume this means merely tht. H.O. will look more closely into

		para. 4 cases.

			Noted with approval.





	4.	Colombo Conference:  Economic Development in S.E.A.



E.B.	Had to try to get Austr. to take the lead (!) because I thought that an

		organisation in U.K. wd. be too far away.

	Agree to conference &amp; date.  Ques:  level of representn.

		I believe it wd. be mistaken to leave this at offl. level.

		I recommend Minister &amp; competent officials.  Mr Macdonald or

		his repve shd. also be there.

	What Minister?  Not from H/C.  I fancy Lord Macdonald.

		Well-briefed &amp; supported fr. Singapore &amp; Whitehall – he shd. do.



P.M.	Agree.



G.W.	Also agree.  Aside fr. politics, the work to be done at this mtg. is 

		mainly for officials.  But agree now we had better send Minister

		esp. from U.S. pt. of view.



E.B.	Might combine both ideas – by sending Offls. out for prelimy work.



R.S.C.	Nothg. publishable will emerge – may be disappointg. if Ministers 

		appear to have failed.  On merits, offls:  but if E.B. think Minister

		essential on pol. grounds I have nothg. to say.



P.M.	Minister – in case new Govts. of N.Z. &amp; Austr. think we are hanging 

		back on that a/c.

			Agreed   -   Macdonald to go.





	5.	Indo-Pakistan Relations.



G.W.	Fundamental trouble:  P.’s fear that I. will eventually attack her.

	Kashmir has bn. worst.

	But econ. relns v. serious now – they prob. provoked the Bengal

		situation.

	Wrong for us to intervene at this moment, by P.M. message.

		Must hold that important card in reserve.

	Kashmir:  Nehru subject to 2 opposite pressures.  Patel &amp; others have

		urged settlement.  That is helpful.

	Immediate issue – Security Council resoln.  India has accepted this.

		Big advance.  But reservations wh. cd. amount to a rejection.

		Must m’tain our pressure – for reservations wd. enable them to

		wriggle out.  Problem:  P. will say this is not acceptance:  do we

		insist on clear acceptance:  or do we say – let Mediator go, for I

		will find it diff. to reject his advice.  Sure we shdn’t press on I. a

		particular individual.  For the rest, inclined to press for clear 

		acceptance.  Tho’ India is in ugly mood.  Believe, however, it

		wd. be more dangerous still to wobble now.



P.M.	Not so gloomy.  Real chance of getting Mediator out.  Don’t prejudice

		that by insistg. too much on dotting every i.

	Solution of Kashmir wd. bring other problems into line.

	Don’t insist on individual.  Don’t insist on clarificn of reservns.



A.	Support P.M.’s view.



R.S.C.	So do I.



E.Sh.	C.O.S. have discussed with C.R.O.  J.P. are now considerg. a plan.



G.W.	The Indian reservn is not a small point.  It is a major point about

		demilitarisation.  We shall risk obscurg. the main bone of 

		contention.



R.S.S.	Get the Mediator out &amp; let him advise Sec. Council on this ques. as

		well as others.



H.McN.	Put it on Lie tht. this is a big advance &amp; it’s up to him to adjust

		wording so that man can go out.

 			Agreed:  Build on what India has done, not on what 

			               they have reserved.



</content>
</cab>
