<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/18/28 images: 280-289</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1&apos; S GOVERNMENT)SECRET.W.P. (.41)8,05.(AlBO 0.0.3.(41)52,61.27TH AUGUST,   1941, - COPY fOvwar cabinetstaff c0itver3at ions with the turks.Report by, thp. Chiefs off staff Gojm.iittep.the War Cabinet55In accordance with the instructions offwe have, considered the suggestion made by the foreign secretary that we should, be rather more specific than hadbeen contemplated in the previous instructions as to theextent of the fighter force which we could make availableto Turkey.not poito thessible to givemaximum scalethe Turks any positiveof the support we could3, It isassurance asafford them.      Subject however, to the agreement of the commanders-in-Chief in the Middle East, to whom we have alreadytelegraphed, we suggest that the following should be addedto paragraph 3(f)  of the instructions4&quot; which we have sent for the conduct of these Conversations&quot;Preparations should be made to receive a force of2 Heavy Bomber Squadrons6 Medium Bomber Squadrons8 Fighter Squadrons1 A.C.  Squadron1 G.R.  Squadron1 Squadron Torpedo Bomberswhich we intend to send to support turkey providedsituation in the Western Desert permits.Plans should be made to receive a first contingent off4 Fighter Squadrons which will be sent on aero daywhatever the situation, elsewhere may bo.&apos;great George Street, S.W.I.,&apos;27th August, 1941.(Signed)      DUDLEY POUND*-JOHN Go DILLcWILFRID FREEMAN&apos;*   -(V.O.A.S. )as. W.M.(41)86th Conclusions;4- Annex,iihute 4.

ANNEX.TELEGRAM TO C commander-IN-CHIEF . MIDDLE EAST.Following from Chiefs of Staff No. 154. &apos;G. in C. Middle Easfs Telegram No.. O/8786O of2/8 to War Office and 0/88231 of 3/8 to military attache j, Ankara.Paragraph 1.We are in general agreement with your proposedagenda for forthcoming Staff Conversations with Turks subject-to the following amendment.    We suggest Item (g) shouldbe amended to read -Quote   Area of operation and disposition ofBritish forces in concerted plan of defence includingspheres of activity of British and Turkish Air Forcesunquote.Paragraph 2.The character and extent of the assistance we will offer has been carefully examined by the Chiefs ofStaff with the Prime Minister in the   Chair.    The Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of Supplyalso attended the meeting.    It was agreed that general line tobe taken by our Delegation in talks with Turks should be asfollows -(a) If you are pressed by Germany and resist by force of arms, we will make common causewith you, and come to your help at once with substantial forces.   You will become apartner in the immense resources of the british Empire and the United States ofAmerica.(b) Our essential object in the Middle East isthe destruction of the German Africa Corps,and the reconquest of Cyrenaica.    Once we&apos;have accomplished this s we can shift nearlythe whole of our weight to your front.(c) It seems to us extremely unlikely that germany could stage a&apos; full-scale attack on you beforethe 1st November, and probably not till the spring of 1942.    To be on the safe side, let us take 1st November, 1941, as zero day.(d) By that date we should be able to send you ifyou are attacked four Divisions and at least one Armoured Brigade.    All of these formations.would be complete with all modern equipment,including A.T. Artillery.

(e) The precise extent and character of our air support must depend on the general situation,particularly in the Western Desert, when the call comes.    But you may rest assured thatit will he considerable.    We are &quot;building upvery powerful air forces in the Middle East.Before the end of.this year we should have1000 first-line aircraft in regular actionhacked &quot;by consider able reserves;    and maintained continuously from Britain and america;    and this number will rise to 1250first line in action during 19^2.(f) Out air forces will however &quot;be totally unableto operate effectively in your support, unlessyou give us immediate facilities for preparing the necessary aerodromes, and establishing the necessary ground organisation.If you. will let us take a leaf out of theGerman hook in Bulgaria, and send in thenecessary technical personnel in plain clothesto get to work on the aerodromes at once, the considerable air forces which we will send toyou will be able to operate with maximum effect from the outset.   Without these facilitiesthey will be relatively useless.(g) We will provide anti-aircraft artillery on aconsiderable scale for the defence of our ownformations, and of the aerodromes which youallot to us.(h) we will increase and accelerate the despatch to you of equipment and other war material,and you shall have a share of the considerablesupplies which are already being shipped. direct to the Middle East from the U.S.A.As an immediate and special consignment, weare sending you 100 3*7 A.A* guns from england.Paragraph 3*Offer of A.A. guns referred to in paragraph 2. (h)above should not be volunteered in first place, butDelegation should keep it up their sleeves as bargaining counter.Paragraph U*Conversations should not take place untilGeneral Auchinleck . and Air Marshal Tedder have returnedto Cairo and have explained above instructions toour Delegation.   Later date suggested in paragraph 2of your Telegram No. 0/88231 therefore appears suitable.

Paragraph. 5*Foreign Secretary suggests that one way of&quot;bringing about improvement in relations between theSoviet Union and Turkey would be for our representativesduring Staff Conversations to take opportunity ofpreaching to their Turkish opposite numbers importanceof political rapprochement with Soviet Union.   They shouldassure the Turks that they have nothing to fear fromimperialistic claims by Russians in respect ofDardanelles or Caucasian Frontier. &apos; At same time theyshould do all they can to convince Turks that in -recommending rapprochement between Turks and Sovietit is not our intention or wish to push Turks into war prematurely or against their better judgment.    our only object is to see Turkish political and military position strengthened as it mil be by mere factthat she is on intimate terms with her Northern neighbour.Paragraph 6.Please pass to Minister of State.




</content>
</cab>
