<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/164/1 images: 5-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(72) 76 COPY NO11 July 1972CABINETEUROPEAN COMMUNITIES:  PARLIAMENTARY scrutiny of DRAFT INSTRUMENTSMemorandum by the Lord President of the council, On the Second Reading of the European Communities Eill theChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster acknowledged the need for special arrangements to apprise Parliament of draft instruments of the european communities before they go to the Council of Ministers for decision.    he proposed an ad hoc Committee of both Houses to consider the most suitablemethod of ensuring adequate Parliamentary scrutiny of these draftinstruments.    The Opposition, having failed to amend the Bill on this point,may shortly agree to an ad hoc Committee.    Otherwise the Select Committeeon Procedure may take up the question.2, The Ministerial Committee on Parliamentary Procedure are agreedthat the binding nature of Community instruments raises special problems for Parliament.    It cannot overturn an instrument once made and thereforeneeds an opportunity to influence the decision, but without compromising theGovernments negotiating posture.    The problem centres in practice on thedraft instruments proposed by the Commission to the Council of Ministers;they number 300-400 a year at present.3.        The Committee reviewed four possible courses:-a. We could propose no special arrangements in a Communitycontext, and review the position in the autumn when we have therecommendations of the Joint Committee under Lord Brooke on united Kingdom delegated legislation.    The ordinary procedures of Parliament will certainly enable Members to exert influence onthe more important drafts, but they are hardly adequate by themselves for all drafts.    The offer of an ad hoc Committee, andthe debates on the Bill, have shown a general desire in parliament for additional arrangements.    The Committee do not recommendthis course.b. A &quot;Sifting&quot; Select Committee might be set up to make a quickappraisal of draft instruments and pick out those requiring theattention of Parliament.    But such a Committee on its own would create pressure for debates on the Floor of the House which couldnot be satisfied, and it might therefore tend to pursue its enquiries1
as if it were a full Select Committee (see d. ).    The Committeedo not recommend it as a solution on its own.c. A Commons Standing Committee would be an extension of the traditional procedures on the Floor of the House and would seek to influence Ministers directly, without being so inquisitorial as to embarrass the Government in its negotiations.    Any Member wouldbe allowed to attend, so that constituency and other special interestscould be represented and there would be less risk of Communitymatters being dealt with in isolation.    (A Standing Committee to debate United Kingdom statutory instruments may well be recommended by Lord Brooke&apos;s Committee).    On the other hand,a Standing Committee would not be as independent as a full SelectCommittee and might be thought to lack sufficient bite to ensureadequate Parliamentary control.d. A Select Committee with the usual inquisitorial powers,would go furthest to satisfy those who feel strongly about the lossof Parliamentary control.    It could be a Joint Committee of bothHouses (although the Opposition might not agree to this).    But a powerful, independent body could cause serious problems andembarrassment for the Government of the day.    Governmentwitnesses might have to choose between a refusal to answer theCommittee&apos;s questions and a frank disclosure of Governmentattitudes which would restrict the subsequent negotiating position,A Select Committee would consist of a small number of members who might not always represent general Parliamentary opinion.    Itwould involve in an acute form the unde sir ability of consideringCommunity issues separately from general Government policy -unless the rest of the Parliamentary Committee system wereremodelled at the same time, eg. to provide a general system of specialist and pre-legislation Committees.4,        A majority of the Ministerial Committee on parliamentary procedure were on balance in favour of a Standing Committee in principle,combined with a preliminary Sifting Committee,    There are arguments infavour of a Select Committee as an eventual possibility, if the parliamentary committee system were remodelled at the same time.    But a StandingCommittee would be the most natural extension of Parliaments power to influence Ministers by debate, without the risks which a Select Committeewould involve for the Government.    Even this solution should be approached cautiously;  a final decision should await the outcome ofLord Brooke&apos;s Committee and should then be put forward as a trialarrangement.    We should explore the possibility of the Standing Committeeand the Sifting Committee being Joint Committees of both Houses.5.        I invite the Cabinet to agree that Ministers should be guided by thispreference for a Standing Committee, with a preliminary Sifting Committee,when giving evidence to the Parliamentary Committee which considers thissubject.R CPrivy Council Office11 July 1972


</content>
</cab>
