<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/16/12 images: 192-201</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THB PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAMNIG MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT/TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care, may he , , .taken to ensure&apos; the secrecy of this document.&apos;SECRETff.F.(U) 89.APRIL 20, 1920,WAR. CABINET. EXTENSION.OF &quot;SINK AS SIGHT&quot; ZONE IN THE MEDITERRANEAN.Memorandum &quot;by the First Lord of the Admiralty.On the 20th February the War Cabinet&apos;.approved my proposal that H4M.Ships and.aircraft should he permitted to sink at sight,any vessel, navigating within an area in the -Central Mediterranean.The Commander-in-Chief, Mediterranean has now.proposed that in viewof the changed situation in the Mediterranean,&apos; the dangerous area should he extended to include the whole of the Adriatic and the Aegean except Turkish territorial waters and that the eastern limit of the area should be extended to a line joining Cape Khelidonia, inTurkey, to Ras-el-Kanais in Egypt.     The Italian and German governments have already declared the Adriatic, north of latitude 2fl051&apos; N andthe Eastern Mediterranean and Aegean, dangerous to navigation.2.     Two German ships have already passed the Dardenelles andproceeded to Salonika and in view therefore of the extreme urgency of giving our forces freedom to attack this enemy supply line totheir army in Greece I have, with the concurrence of the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, authorised the Commander-in-Chief,Mediterranean to put his proposals into effect pending coveringapproval &quot;by the War Cabinet, which I now seek.     Our informationshows that no neutral shipping navigates in the area concerned apartfrom, an occasional ship, proceeding by arrangement with us from turkey to Port Said and which of course will not be interfered with&quot;by our patrols.
3. - Advance notification of our, intentions has; been made tothe Russian ajia7Turkisn-&apos;Gbverments,:&apos;and in view of the danger ofthe enemy sending supplies to. the Dodecanese from Thrace-in shipsusing Turkish territorial waters, the Turkish Government have&apos;,beeninformed that we. look .to them to ,deny the use Of the territorial waters of Asia Minor to German and other Axis vessels. If they are unableto do this we should be compelled to take action ourselves if necessaryin Turkish territorial waters to prevent supplies reaching the dodecanese.4.     I attach (Annexe i) the proposed Notification to neutral governments and the instructions to the commander-in-Chief,Mediterranean (Annexe II).A.V.A.ADMIRALTY, S.W.1.April 20.1941.
NOTiriCATIOI-t gQ HEUTPJJj G-OVEHrSlEJMTS.The German  aid Italian Governments having recently announced that the Eastern Mediterranean, the Aegean Sea andthe greater part of the Adriatic are dangerous to shipping,His Majesty1s Government give notice that the limits of thearea in the Mediterranean which they declared dangerous to shipping in February, 1941 ace extended to the eastward along the coasts of Libya and Egypt frorn^Benghazi to Ras-el-Kanais, thencein a 02z4.0 direction to a point three miles I8O0 from GapeKhelidonia in Turkey, thence along the limits of Turkish territorial waters to Greek territory, thence along the coasts of Greece,Albania, Yugoslavia and Italy to Gape Sta Maria di Leuca in Italy,lat: 39048! N.Long: 18g22&apos; E.  (approximately),     All waters within this area are dangerous to shipping and any vessels disregardingthe terms of this notice will do so at their risk and peril.

Addressed : C in C. Mediterranean. -    .Repeated  V.A. MaltaF.O.C.N.A.. S..p...vfcPoroe ,Hr       i, .....v s-Air Ministry.From Admiralty.Navigational warning is being broadcast at   .......G.M.T.in following terras : -The German and Italian Governments having recently announcedthat the Eastern Mediterranean, the Aegean Sea and the greater part of the adriatic are dangerous to shipping, His Majesty&apos;s Government give notice thatthe limits of the area in the Mediterranean which they declared dangerous to shipping in February, 1941, are extended to the eastward along the coasts. oof Libya and Egypt from Benghazi to Ras-el-Kanais, thence in a 024- direction,:-&apos;-)&quot;&apos;&apos;:&quot; o     .   &apos;to a point 3 miles 180   from Cape Khelidonia in  Turkey, thence along thelimits of Turkish territorial waters to   Greek territory, thence along the coasts of Greece, Albania, Yugoslavia and Italy to Cape Sta Maria di Leucain Italy.    Lat: 39     48&apos;N Long: 18     22TE (approximately).   All waters within this area are dangerous to shipping and any vessels disregarding the terms ofthis notice will do so at their risk and peril,2,                      Request you will arrange for similar broadcast to be made not before...........G.M. T,3. Within this area aircraft, surface ships and submarines mayattack at sight any vessel navigating without our permission.   Turkishterritorial waters are to be respected and care is to be- taken to avoidinterfering with Turkish coastal shipping which, on account of navigationaldifficulties in some areas navigates outside territorial waters,4, H.M. Representatives at Angora,and Beirut, are beinginstructed to inform you and Headquarters, R.A.F. Middle East 24 hours inadvance of the time of sailing, route, speed, tonnage and chiefdistinguishing features&apos;of a jay neutral ship which is permitted to navigatein this area.5&apos; One neutral ship, has beear chartered by United KingdomCommercial Corporation to carry chrome ore from Pethiye in Turkey to port said and proposal has been made that Turkish ships should engage in this/traffic...........
traffic.        As there is no British consul at Fethiyey&apos;advance notification of each shipfs sailing would be difficult.   Request therefore&quot; tha&apos;t you &quot;willmake any arrangements you consider necessary\with H.Jvli -Ambassador, Angora,for routeing these ships.

traffic.        As there is no British consul at Fethiyey&apos;advance notification of each ship&apos;s sailing would he difficult.    Request therefore&quot; that you &quot;willmake any arrangements you consider necessary\with H.1u -Ambassador, Angora,for routeing these ships. . .  .



</content>
</cab>
