<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/271/0 images: 242-256</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)SECRET.C-P..,.223l37 ) . COPY NO ,C A B I N E T. ANGLO-PORTUGUESE RELATIONS. Note by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Cabinet at their meeting on the 21st July, 1937,   (Cab.31(37)) approved the conclusions of the Committee of Imperial Defence on the subject of the Anglo-Portuguese Relations (CP. 189(37)) which in-cluded, inter alia, a recommendation that &quot;the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should have authority to sound the Portuguese Government as to whether they would welcome the despatch of a military mission to Portugal&quot;.2. At the beginning of August the PortugueseAmbassador informed the Foreign Office that his Govern-ment had requested him to express their full approval of the above suggestion^3. I now circulate,  for the consideration of myc o 11 e ague s:,- - &apos;(i)   A Report prepared by the Deputy Chiefs of staff Sub-Committee during the recess, containing recommendations as to the general scope of the Mission, its composition, the duration of its visit to Portugal, and the allocation of cost,      This Report has received the approval of the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.(ii)    A Memorandum by the Chiefs of Staff themselves containing more detailed recommendations as to the scope and functions of the Mission.
4. The matter is of some urgency since, if the Missionis to leave by the date recommended, i.e. the end of October, the Foreign Office ought to be enabled to put up definite proposals to the Portuguese Government without further loss of time.(Intdn) T.W.H.. I.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, 30th September, 1937.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   Septembe?&apos; 1937&apos;.SECRET. CCS. 623.(Also Paper No. D.C.O.S. 48 (Final Copy).)COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.MILITARY MISSION TO PORTUGAL. (Previous Paper No. CCS. 611.)Report by the Deputy Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.AT their 297th Meeting held on the 15th July, 1937, the Committee of Imperial Defence considered a report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee on Anglo-Portuguese relations importance from the strategical point of view (Paper No. CCS. 602, also C.I.D. Paper No. 1336-B).Amongst the conclusions recorded, which were approved by the Cabinet on the 21st July, 1937, was one recommending that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should have authority to sound the Portuguese Government as to whether they would welcome the despatch of a military mission to Portugal, and, in this connection, we have had under consideration a letter from the Foreign Office to the Deputy Secretary, Committee of Imperial Defence, which is attached hereto as an Appendix.It will be seen that the Portuguese Ambassador has intimated to the Foreign Office that his Government have expressed their full approval that a British Military Mission should visit Portugal.We have discussed this question with Sir Robert Vansittart and the Portuguese Ambassador and on the assumption that a Military Mission will be despatched in the near future we submit our recommendations in regard thereto.Scope of Mission.2. We consider that, as regards the Air Force, provided the Portuguese authorities are prepared to receive the necessary advice from the Mission, there is room for great improvement in the organisation of the Portuguese Air Force and the proper employment of its units. It might be possible to persuade them to organise one or two units which, in an emergency, could work from Cape Verde Islands and the Azores, in conjunction with the British unit stationed at Freetown. There is also scope for advice in regard to anti-aircraft defence, including the establishment of an observer corps. On the naval side the most important aspect is the defence of Portuguese harbours and approaches which, even if not required for use by Great Britain, must be denied to the enemy. On the army side there are some grounds for thinking that advice might suitably be given on Portuguese war plans.3. We suggest that the Joint Planning Sub-Committee should be instructed to review the ground to be covered by the Mission, particularly in regard to the advice to be given to the Portuguese regarding their own organisation and plans, the measures to be recommended to them which would be of value to Great Britain, the extent to which the defence plans of Great Britain could be disclosed and the facilities which Great Britain could offer for training and the study of defence problems generally.[15900-1]Copy No.
24. In the discussions with the Foreign Office, the Portuguese Ambassador referred to the inclusion in the Mission of some &quot; younger officers &quot; from the British Forces. We do not consider that this would be practicable, but contact could be established with &apos;&apos; younger officers &quot; as a result of arrangements that niight be completed by the Mission for the attachment of officers from each country to the units in the other country, and for the attendance of Portuguese officers at training courses in this country. Considerable facilities exist in this country for the attachment of foreign officers for training, although the Admiralty do not altogether view with favour the training at sea of such officers, nor would they be disposed to allow them to attend the course for Naval Observers. Neither the Admiralty nor the Air Ministry at present receive foreign officers at their Staff Colleges.5. We consider that the most useful step in regard to future contacts would be the appointment of attaches at the respective Embassies. The proposal to appoint a Royal Marine Officer as attache at Lisbon has been suspended pending the outcome of the present proposals in regard to the Mission. The appointment of a Portuguese attache&quot; in London would provide a channel through which, if the Portuguese Government were so disposed, the defence problems of that country could receive continuous consideration from British Service Departments.6. As regards the supply of material, we are of opinion, that in view of the existing demands and priorities, caution should be exercised by the Mission in regard to encouraging the placing of orders in the United Kingdom for further material. With this end in view it will be necessary for the Mission to be fully acquainted with the situation regarding our general rearmament programme.Composition of Mission.7. We understand that the Portuguese Ambassador expressed a wish that there should be a head of the Mission of Flag or equivalent rank. Although he expressed some preference that the head of the Mission should be an Army Officer, we suggest that, as the Admiralty are prepared to make available a Rear-Admiral who is a Gunnery Officer, this Officer should be appointed the head of the Mission and Naval representative. We suggest that the Army and Royal Air Force representatives should be an Officer of the rank of Colonel and Group Captain respectively. In view of the language difficulties we also suggest that it would be advisable to include in the Mission a Second Officer from each Service with language qualifications for interpreting and cipher work.Duration and Date of Visit.8. We are of opinion that in the first instance the Mission should be despatched to Portugal for a period of three months, with a possibility of this period being extended, during which the situation should be explored. After this period, the Mission should return to the United Kingdom and report, so that a decision could then be taken, as to the necessity for and scope of, a permanent Military Mission to Portugal. We suggest that the Mission should be ready to proceed to Portugal early in October 1937.Cost of Mission.9. Having regard to the circumstances in which the Mission has originated and the basis on which approval has been given to it by the Committee of Imperial Defence and the Cabinet, we consider that its object would be defeated if the Portuguese Government were expected to meet the cost. This point has been emphasised in the discussion between the Portuguese Ambassador and Sir Robert Vansittart. We therefore suggest that the cost should be borne by His Majesty&apos;s Government.10.   Our recommendations are summarized below and we request (a) That our recommendations be approved in principle, and(b) That authority be given for an approach to be made to the FinanceBranches of the Departments concerned on the assumption that the Military Mission will be despatched to Portugal early in October 1937.
Summary of Recommendations. 11.   We recommend that (a) The scope of the Military Mission should be (i) - to establish personal contact with the Portuguese Authorities and arrange, within the limits approved by the Chiefs of Staff, for the continuation of such contacts after the return of the Mission;(ii) to give such advice as may be desirable on defence problemssubmitted to them by the Portuguese Authorities; (iii) to examine and, if possible, improve the facilities that might be r available in war to Great Britain as indicated in C.I.D. PaperNo. 1336-B of the 9th July, 1937.(b) That the Joint Planning Sub-Committee be instructed to prepare general . instructions, for approval by the Chiefs of Staff, covering thefollowing points : (i) the advice to be given by the Mission on the Portuguese defence organisation and their plans in war; (ii) the measures which Portugal could take to improve facilities available for Great Britain in a war in which the latter is engaged;(iii) the extent to which the Mission may disclose to the PortugueseAuthorities the British defence plans and various contingencies;(iv) the arrangements to be suggested for the visit of Portugueseofficers to this country for the study of defence problems either by attachment to units, or attendance at training courses, or at the Staff Colleges.&quot;(c) Composition. That the head of the Mission should be a Rear-Admiral and the Army and Royal Air Force represented by a Colonel and Group Captain respectively, a Second Officer from each Service, with language qualifications to be added for interpreting and cipher duties.(d) Duration and Date of Visit. That the Mission, in the first instance, should be of an explanatory nature and proceed to Portugal for a period of three months, early in October 1937.,(e) Cost of Mission. That, subject to the approval of the appropriate financial authorities, the cost of the Mission should be borne on the Votes of the Departments concerned.(Signed)R R L.H. HAINING. E. C. PEIRSE. E. HOLLAND(for D.C.N.S.).2 Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, September 7, 1937.THIS REPORT HAS BEEN APPROVEDCHIEFS OF STAFF.BY THE THREE
APPENDIX.Copy of a letter from the Foreign Office to the Deputy Secretary, Committee ofImperial Defence.14944/25/36.Foreign Office, August 13, 1937.I AM writing to let you know that the Portuguese Ambassador called at the Foreign Office a few days ago to inform us that his Government had requested him to express their full approval of the suggestion which had been made to them that a British Military Mission should visit Portugal.It was agreed that October or November would be the most suitable moment for such a visit and that the intervening weeks could well be employed in taking the necessary preparatory measures. We are of opinion, and I trust that you will agree, that any announcement of the decision to send a Mission to Portugal-would at this stage be most unwise. We should receive immediate enquiries from the Press and elsewhere in regard to the scope and aims of the Mission, and we should find it difficult to give any satisfactory answer until due consideration had, in fact, been given to the whole matter by everyone concerned. We will inform Dr. Monteiro accordingly if you agree.Dr. Monteiro again mentioned the Mission in the course of another conversation on the 10th instant, and was most emphatic on the point that its scope should be well defined beforehand, that it should include some of our younger officers and that it should lead, above all things, to much more frequent contacts, whether by visits of British officers to Portugal or invitations to Portuguese Officers to come over here and study our system and methods.Lord Halifax has asked me to inform you of the state which the proposal has now reached and to suggest that the Chiefs of Staff should now prepare a plan of the Mission&apos;s composition and programme for consideration by the Committee of Imperial Defence in order that no time should be lost.May I mention the following points which had occurred to us as being worthy of consideration for inclusion in the Mission&apos;s programme : (1) With reference to the report of the Sub-Committee of the Chiefs of Staff, the Mission might, if the Portuguese Government agree, examine what facilities would be available to us in war time of the kind indicated in that report and how far the existing facilities could be improved by collaboration between the two Governments;(2) In the event of agreement on (1) above, the Mission should consider what His Majesty&apos;s Government could offer in return for the above. Among other things, consideration might be given to a large increase in the facilities at present extended to Portuguese military and naval officers for study in this country and, in particular, opportunities for senior officers to study our defence organisation with a view to adapting the lessons to be learnt from it to Portugal&apos;s own requirements;(3) Consideration might also be given to the question whether His Majesty&apos;s Government could be of any help to the Portuguese staff in working out Portuguese defence plans against attacks either from a great European Power or from Spain against the mother country or her overseas possessions in Africa and the eastern Atlantic.I need hardly say that the above points have not been considered in any detail in this office, and I only bring them to your notice in case you should think them worthy of inclusion in the Mission&apos;s programme.Yours sincerely, (Signed)        GEORGE MOUNSEY.Colonel H. L. Ismay, C.B., D.S.O.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   September 1937.SECRET. Copy No.C.O.S. 625.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.MILITARY MISSION TO PORTUGAL. (Previous Paper No. CCS. 623.)Memorandum.Origin of the Mission.IN April 1937 the Foreign Office, in a letter* to the Secretary, Committee of Imperial Defence, raised the question of the value of the Anglo-Portuguese Alliance, pointing out that German and Italian influences were at work in Portugal, and that British propaganda on the same lines did not exist. Further-more, the Portuguese Government appeared to be dissatisfied at the apparent unwillingness of His Majesty&apos;s Government to co-operate more closely in matters concerning the defence interests of the two countries. The Foreign Office therefore asked the Committee of Imperial Defence, to investigate the strategic importance of Anglo-Portuguese relations and to consider the possibility of despatching a British Military Mission to Portugal.2. During discussion by the Committee of Imperial Defence t it was pointed out that Portugal stood only fifth in priority for delivery of war material, Egypt, Iraq, Afghanistan and Belgium coming before her. After discussing the value of Portugal as an ally, it was decided that the Foreign Office should keep open with Portugal the question of sending a Military Mission pending the submission by the Chiefs of Staff of a detailed report on the strategical value of the alliance. Note was also taken that the question of supply of war material to foreign countries would be discussed with the War Office.3. In July 1937 the Chiefs of Staff issued their report,! the conclusions of which read as follows :  &quot;We conclude that the importance of maintaining our alliance with Portugal has increased with the development of air power, owing to the fact ... that, from the air point of view, the mother country and her Island possessions in the Eastern Atlantic are admirably situated either for the defence of or attack on our seaborne trade. ;&quot; We cannot. forecast the outcome of the Spanish civil war, but since a return to the old and innocuous regime appears unlikely, it may well be that the availability of facilities and anchorages in Portuguese waters, alternative to Gibraltar, will prove of greater value to our Navy in the future than in the past.&quot;Elsewhere, in Africa and the Far East, it is important that no strong : Foreign Power should be permitted to develop a predbminant influence in Portuguese territory.&quot; From every aspect, therefore, we confirm the view that the maintenance of our alliance with Portugal is of great importance.&quot;* C.I.D. Paper No. 1320-B. f C.I.D., 292nd Meeting, Minute 4. j C.I.D. Paper No. 1336-B. [15900] B
24. The Chiefs of Staffs report was considered by the Committee of Imperial Defence.* As regards sending a Mission to Portugal, discussion showed that such a Mission would have little to offer so far as the early supply of war material was concerned. The Navy had, however, already rendered considerable assistance to Portugal, having built no less than 17 ships for her since the war, and there; was probably not much more that could be done in that direction. Moreover, the immediate Portuguese requirements now appeared to be for artillery and aero-planes. The Army had also, as recently as February 1937, supplied ammunition to Portugal, while the Admiralty and Air Ministry had foregone certain items of their rearmament programme in order partially to meet a Portuguese request for A.A. armament. The Army could offer no more equipment to the Portuguese. The Air Force would be able to&apos; render little more than token assistance within the next twelve months, though subsequently more might be done. Hence, on the material side, the Mission could offer little equipment at present. Nevertheless, it would be of value in advising what equipment the Portuguese should have, and where they should place their orders.5. In the course of the discussion it was noted that the question of the appointment of one or mOre whole time Service attaches to Lisbon had been under consideration by the Service Departments. None of the latter considered that the appointment of a whole time naval, military or air attache was justified either on the grounds of necessity or expense, but a proposal for the appointment of a Royal Marine Officer, who would act as attache on behalf of all three Services, had been under consideration. With the appointment of the military mission, however, this proposition is temporarily in abeyance.6. The Committee of Imperial Defence finally. endorsed the conclusions of the Chiefs of Staff, quoted in paragraph 3 above, and, in view of those conclusions decided that, owing to the importance o&apos;f counteracting the growing influence of Germany and Italy in Portugal, the despatch of a British Military Mission would, on political grounds, be desirable; and consequently, to recommend to the Cabinet that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should have authority to sound the Portuguese Government as to whether they would welcome the despatch of a Military Mission to Portugal. The Cabinet approved the above conclusions at a Meetingt held on the 21st July, 1937.7. As a result of enquiries addressed to the Portuguese Government, the Portuguese Ambassador, at the beginning of August 1937, informed the Foreign Office that his Government had requested him to express their full approval of the suggestion which had been made to them that a British Military Mission should visit Portugal.The object and scope of the Mission.8. His Majesty&apos;s Government are sending the Military Mission to Portugal with the object of co-operating more closely than heretofore in Portuguese defence preparations in view of the necessity for maintaining the alliance in the face of Italian and German influence.9.   The scope of tihe Mission is confined to the following measures : (a) Establishing personal contacts with the Portuguese authorities and suggesting how these contacts might best be continued after the return of the Mission, e.g., by the appointment of one or more Service attaches.(b) Making arrangements or suggestions for visits or attachments of portuguese Officers in this country including the appointment of one or more Service attaches to London.(c) Studying Portuguese defence problems and offering or arranging toprovide advice on any questions concerning defence and rearmament which may be submitted to them by the Portuguese authorities.(d) Studying the measures which Portugal could take to improve facilities available for Great Britain in the joint defence of the two countries in a war in which they are engaged as allies.(e) Obtaining from the Portuguese authorities any useful military informa-tion which&apos; they may be ready to give.10.   The duration of the Mission is for three months in the first instance.* C.I.D./297th Meeting, Minute 6. f Cabinet 31 (37), Conclusion 5.
Advice to be given by the Mission on the Portugtiese Defence Organisation and their flans for war.16. Advice which may be solicited by the Portuguese authorities may fall into two categories : (a) Advice on major problems, e.g., the defence of Portugal and her possessions or the measures which she could take towards re-organisa-tion and rearmament, and. (6) Minor Service questions, e.g., tactical questions or the comparative merits of various types of equipment.It might well prove impracticable for the members of the Mission to prepare very full reports, which the answers to questions falling under category (a) above would require, without access to the records and facilities existing at their respective Service Ministries at home.In this case it might, therefore, be better that the Mission should collate all the data with a view to the subsequent preparation of a report in the United Kingdom. It will, however, undoubtedly be necessary for the members of the Mission to be prepared to give answers to questions falling under category (6) and they should consult their respective Ministries on these points before leaving this country.[15900] b 2Method of working.11. The head of the Mission will, under the instruction of our Ambassador to Portugal, be free to settle the procedure of the Mission as he may judge best.12. The limited scope which it is possible to give the Mission and our inability to offer any material quantity of the equipment required for Portuguese rearmament make the task of the Mission difficult. The success of the Mission will be governed largely by the extent to which the Portuguese authorities can be encouraged to ask for advice. More progress is likely to be made if these authorities can be made to feel that the initiative is coming from them than if advice is offered gratuitously by the Mission. The Portuguese Ambassador in London recently said that what was needed.was an understanding handling of his nation. The Portuguese become only more and more stubborn when subjected to compulsion or patronage; while they are extraordinarily amenable to a treatment based on good fellowship and friendly interest.13. The Mission will have to combat the impression, which the Portuguese seem to have gained, that Great Britain no longer takes any interest in Portuguese affairs and regards them as a class &quot; C &quot; nation.The possibility must not be overlooked that the Mission may be received with a certain amount of animosity by the Service Departments in Portugal, which, while themselves notoriously Fascist in sympathy, believe that we favour the Reds in Spain. The Mission are also likely to meet Germans and Italians in Portugal who may be hostile and inquisitive. Discussion with the Foreign Office before the Mission leaves England should equip members with arguments and propaganda with which to meet these situations.14. It is likely that advice may be sought on points which require the opinion of specialists in particular branches of the Services. The Mission should make it clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government would, on the request of the Portuguese Government, be ready to do all that was within their power in the way of obtaining specialist opinion or even by arranging for specialists to visit Portugal to report to the Portuguese Government on specific problems.15. The head of the Mission will address reports to the Ambassador. An interim report on the progress of the Mission will be required four to six weeks after the arrival of the Mission in Portugal. A final report is to be submitted on the termination of the work of the Mission. Members of the Mission will be authorised to communicate direct with their respective Ministries on matters of a purely technical nature.
Measures which Portugal could take to improve facilities available for Great Britain in the joint defence of the two countries in a war in which they are engaged as allies. 17.   Naval.- The most important naval facilities that Portugal could offer -would be the use of&apos;her harbours.   The denial of these facilities to an enemy would also be important.   Hence any measures that Portugal could take to improve the defence of her harbours, anchorages and their approaches in the Mother Country and overseas possessions, particularly in the Azores and Cape Verde Islands, would be of great value.   The port of Lisbon is of primary importance in this connection, as being an alternative to Gibraltar should circum-stances ever deny us the use of the latter.18. Air Force. Portugal&apos;s chief assistance to the Royal Air Force in the event of war would consist of the provision of air bases both in Portugal and her Atlantic Islands; these would fill in gaps on our strategic air routes and act as bases from which we could protect seaborne trade. Portugal could also give valuable assistance by denying her own territory and dependencies to our possible enemies.19. Army. Except in the very unlikely event of a British force landing in Portugal to co-operate on land with the Portuguese army, no facilities would be required in Portugal for the British Army.In order, however, to ensure the security of those Portuguese ports and anchorages which the Royal Navy might require to use and those air bases which the Royal Air Force might need, it would be important that the necessary A/A and coast defences should be provided. It would also be to our interest that the security of these bases should, so far as possible, be considered in the plans for the action of the Portuguese army in the event of invasion.The extent to which the Mission may disclose to the Portuguese authorities the British defence plans on various contingencies.20. British defence plans for specific wars should not be discussed with the Portuguese authorities.In general the Mission must be guided by the principle that anything which they say or write to the Portuguese authorities is liable to reach other countries.Members of the Mission, before going to Portugal, should be informed by their respective Departments of any questions which should not on any account be discussed with the Portuguese.This need not prejudice the success of the Mission&apos;s conversations with the Portuguese defence authorities, since the relative geographical positions of the two countries and their dependencies are such as to make them strategically valuable one to the other in almost any circumstances which may arise.A memorandum on the importance of Anglo-Portuguese relations from the strategical point of view and extracts from a letter from the Portuguese Ambassador in London to the Permanent Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, in which the former gives a Portuguese viewpoint, are attached as Appendices I and II respectively. These should be used by the Mission as a general guide when discussing strategical problems with the Portuguese, but their contents should not be quoted in any such discussions.Arrangements for visits of Portuguese officers to this country to study defence problems.21. Naval. The present Admiralty policy is to exclude Foreign naval officers from the Naval Staff College, and from training in seagoing fleets and squadrons. Training of foreign officers in our Navy is thus restricted to the instructional establishments and tenders, and this policy should be followed in the case of Portuguese officers.22. Army. The Mission should be in possession of the list of army units and schools to which the attachment of foreign officers is permitted (Secret Document A.4341). In the case of the Portuguese seeking attachments not normally allowed for foreign officers, special consideration to each specific application could be given, but considerations of secrecy make it impossible to recommend much relaxation of the normal restrictions.
23. Air Force. The Air Ministry would be prepared to receive Portuguese Air Force Officers on courses with the Royal Air Force up to a maximum of about four officers per annum on long courses, provided that Treasury sanction for extra places under our &quot; Free &quot; scheme was forthcoming.Attachments to the Staff College and the Fighter squadrons are not permitted: officers could, however, be attached to an Army Co-operation squadron and to some Bomber squadrons.Courses at which foreign officers could be received include courses in Army Co-operation, Navigation, Engineering and courses of flying at Flying Training Schools and Central Flying School.Preparations by the Mission prior to its departure.24. Apart from the general strategical aspects which are covered in Appendices I and II, members of the Mission, before leaving this country, will require to become fully conversant with Service policy in respect of minor Service questions referred to in paragraph 16 (b) above.Information on the following points, together with any others which the Departments concerned wish to discuss, provided that they fall within the scope of the Mission as defined in paragraph 9, should, therefore, be the subject of discussion between the Mission and Departments : Service Departments.(i) The present position regarding facilities and defences at Portugueseharbours and any measures which could usefully be taken to improve them.(ii) The existing air facilities in Portugal and her island possessions and how they could be improved.(iii) The anti-aircraft and coast defences at Portuguese bases.(iv) Relevant information which Departments can give to the Mission withregard to the supply of armaments and aircraft.(v) Service attachments of Portuguese Officers in England and the appoint-ment of Service attaches to both countries.(vi) The  ways  in which the  Mission  can  assist  in  connection withintelligence.The Mission will also require to be informed by the Foreign Office and the Department of Overseas Trade upon the following points : Foreign Office.British foreign policy in relation to Portugal and the mutual obligations of the two countries under the Anglo-Portuguese Treaties, foreign propaganda in Portugal and the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government to the Spanish Civil War.Department of Overseas Trade.Assistance which the Mission can give in connection with Industrial Intelligence and the measures which the Portuguese might take to build up an armaments industry in Portugal.The necessary consultations with the Foreign Office and Department of Overseas Trade will take place under arrangements made by the Admiralty.(Signed) C. L. NEWALL.W. M. JAMES(for C.N.S.).R. H. HAINING(for C.I.G.S.).2 Whitehall Garden/, S.W. 1, September 29, 1937.[15900]
APPENDIX I.Memorandum on the Importance of Anglo-Portuguese &quot;Relations from the strategical Point of View.General Strategical Considerations.SINCE Portugal seems unlikely to become an important military Power, it cannot be anticipated that her active military participation as an ally would at any time add materially to the strength of our forces. Nevertheless, the military facilities, existing and potential, which her territory both at home and abroad would offer to the armed forces of Great Britain or any other belligerent would prove of considerable value in war.2. The strategical value of an alliance with Portugal, therefore, lies in the fact that it enables us to make use of these facilities and at the same time denies their use to a hostile Power. In order to assess the degree of importance which should be attached to our alliance with Portugal, a brief examination is made of existing facilities and the extent to which their use by ourselves or by an enemy would affect us in war.Portugal and her possessions in North- West A frica and the Eastern A atlantic.3. In 1912 the Admiralty expressed their views upon the naval strategic aspect as follows :  &apos;&apos; If ever the alliance is terminated by action on either side, we should make it a cardinal point of our subsequent policy to see that no maritime State such as France or Germany replaces us and thus obtains the right to use the Cape de Verdes, the Azores or Portuguese Guinea, either as a Sovereign Power or as an ally of Portugal. &quot;We should prevent at all costs the transfer of these particular possessions to any strong Naval Power.&quot;The Foreign Office held that the only satisfactory method of meeting these requirements was by the maintenance of the alliance; and they reaffirmed this view when our relations with Portugal were reconsidered in 1927, although at that time the German menace was, for the time being, eliminated.4. Since that date certain developments in Europe, such as the rearming of Germany, the civil war in Spain and the new attitude of Italy, have tended to increase the importance of our alliance with Portugal in relation to naval strategy. The outcome of the Spanish struggle cannot yet be foreseen, but it might well result in the establishment of a strong Spanish Government with views quite different from those which obtained under the old regime in which no real threat to our position at Gibraltar seemed likely to arise.5. If, indeed, a revival took place in Spain on lines similar to that which Mussolini has achieved in Italy, it might be found that in war not only could the use of Gibraltar be denied to us, but the passage of our shipping through the Straits might be made extremely hazardous. In these circumstances, the alternative facilities which Portugal possesses might well prove of great value to our navy.6. In addition to the above considerations, accoxmt must to-day be taken as to how an alliance with Portugal affects our air strategy. At the best Gibraltar, with its one restricted aerodrome, would be an unsatisfactory link in our air route to Africa and the East in time of war, and the additional facilities which Portugal could provide would be extremely valuable.7. The Azores, Madeira and the Cape Verde Islands form a triangle through which a large percentage of British sea-borne trade normally passes. The use of air facilities in these islands would therefore be of considerable value to us in trade protection. At present these facilities are limited in scope, but the French, in particular, are anxious for them to be developed further. On the assumption that we should benefit from such facilities in war, our policy should be to encourage any such development as far as this lies within our power.
8. The denial of the use of potential bases is just as important in air strategy as in naval strategy; and the views which the Admiralty expressed in 1912 in relation to potential naval bases apply to-day with equal force to existing and potential air bases in Portugal and to her possessions in the Eastern Atlantic and North-West Africa. The scale of attack upon British interests which a hostile air Power could maintain for any length of time from such bases, other than in the Peninsula itself, would, however, depend upon whether that Power could reinforce these bases by direct flight from its metropolitan air force, and the extent to which bombs and fuels had either been accumulated in peace or could be shipped in spite of our sea power.Portuguese Territory in the Far East.9. Among Portuguese possessions in the Far East are Macao, in South China, and parts of Timor Island.The former possesses a recently dredged harbour, protected by 4 miles of breakwater, accommodating vessels drawing up to 20 feet. There is a small naval dockyard (no dry dock), at which minor repairs can be carried out. There is a landing ground at Macao, and seaplanes could operate from the vicinity of the outer harbour. We have recently intervened successfully to prevent a concession at Macao for the development of further air facilities being given to the Japanese.Timor Island is an important landfall in the air route between Australia and Singapore.The only landing-ground at present in use is in Dutch territory, but sites exist in Portuguese territory which could be developed into landing grounds. Since an attitude of strict neutrality on the part of the Netherlands would be to our advantage in the event of war against Japan, a landing ground in the Portuguese part of Timor Island might prove most useful.Portuguese East A frica and Angola.10. These territories adjoin the former German colonies in Africa, and are, therefore, easily accessible to German &quot; peaceful penetration&quot; through the medium of her overseas Nazi organisations. The existence of a strong hostile element in these areas in time of war might prove a considerable embarrassment both to ourselves and the Government of the Union of South Africa, although it could hardly constitute a threat to the security of that Dominion or Rhodesia. So long as the Anglo-Portuguese alliance exists, therefore, the potential danger from German influences in these territories can more easily be counteracted.Conclusions.11. The conclusion reached is that the importance of maintaining our alliance with Portugal has increased with the development of air power owing to the fact that, from the air point of view, the Mother Country and her Island possessions in the Eastern Atlantic are admirably situated either for the defence of or attack on our seaborne trade.It is not possible to forecast the outcome of the Spanish civil war, but since a return to the old and innocuous regime appears unlikely, it may well be that the availability of facilities and anchorages in Portuguese waters, alternative to Gibraltar, will prove of greater value to our navy in the future than in the past.Elsewhere, in Africa and the Far East, it is important that no strong Foreign Power should be permitted to develop a predominant influence in Portuguese territory.
APPENDIX II.Portuguese Embassy,London, July 20, 1937.My dear Sir Robert Vansittart,I AM firmly convinced that the interests of the Anglo-Portuguese alliance-require that the military organization and armed strength of Portugal should be such as to enable her to serve the common cause efficiently should the occasion arise.A logical corollary to this principle is that Great Britain can hardly be indifferent to the problem of Portuguese rearmament; further, that the more active the collaboration which the Portuguese Army is able to lend to the cause of our two countries, the greater that interest will be.I am thus led to the conclusion that it is necessary to prepare that collabora-tion carefully beforehand, in order that it may attain the greatest possible efficiency.I am of the opinion that now, more than ever before, the Anglo-Portuguese alliance is a vital element of security to the British Empire, and, simultaneously, to Portugal.   It is an essential element of common defence.If you look at the map, you will easily see that the great lines of communi-cation between the United Kingdom and the British Dominions and overseas possessions may without difficulty be dominated by sea and by air from Portuguese territory.   There are three positions to be considered at the present time :  (a) The Portuguese coast, in the Mother Country.(b) The port of Lisbon.(c) The line Lisbon (or Lagos)-the Azores-Cape Verde Islands.To these should be added, in certain eventualities, the port of Lobito and its railways connection with the Indian Ocean (Beira).Should an eventual common enemy ever obtain possession of any of the three positions mentioned, the danger to Great Britain during a conflict might be of the gravest character. Imagine for one moment that during the last war the enemy had succeeded in gaining a foothold in any of them from which to carry on the fight at sea. Would the easy and constant passage first of arms and munitions which came from the United States in such large quantities, and, later, the actual transport of troops, have been possible in such circumstances ? Would it have been possible to maintain, without grave difficulties and risks, the regular supply of food to the troops at the front and even to the civil population of the British Isles ?I sincerely believe that questions such as these give ample food for thought..In recent years the development of aviation and the political changes which the World has witnessed have considerably enhanced the military value of the geographical positions I have indicated.Practically the whole of that part of the Atlantic which concerns Europe can be dominated by air from the Portuguese coast, the Azores, Madeira, and the Cape Verde Islands whilst the entry to the Mediterranean may be dominated from the coast of Algarve.Besides, Africa has become for France a vital source of military power. Should, for any reason, the route across the Mediterranean be cut or rendered difficult, the great French African army would have to sail up the Portuguese coast to come to the aid of the Mother Country. What if that army were unable-to pass ?Suppose now, for one moment, that the Reds are victorious in Spain, and that in consequence the country, at least at first, is broken up into various more or less rival republics. How many complications in the Mediterranean are logically to be imagined, with all or some of these republics subjected to the influence, if not to the immediate dictatorship of Soviet Russia in particular  as is naturally to be foreseen, judging by what is taking place in Catalonia-and with attempts made later to weld them into the great Iberian Soviet Republic ? Portugal would, unfortunately, have to play a fundamental role in struggles to-
which this hypothetical victory would give rise. In view of the strategic importance of the Iberian Peninsula, Russia would be led, by the expansionist forces which to-day inspire her policy, to transform it into a fortress from which to dominate Europe. The facts point to such a result. I believe that those who think Russia will abandon the field without endeavouring to extract from her victory in the Peninsula natural and easily-obtained advantages are very far indeed from reality.On the other hand, once the Communist and Anarchist forces are defeated in Spain, that country will, on regaining its unity, naturally seek, above all else, to recuperate its lost strength, to recover its prosperity, healing in peace-time the wounds inflicted by the war. All its traditions and basic interests will tend to become uppermost in the minds of its rulers, and it must not be forgotten that neutrality is the first political principle of a United Spain. As a result of this neutrality, my country will be the outpost of Europe in so far as the Mediterranean and the Atlantic Ocean are concerned.In these circumstances, a Portuguese nation which is disarmed or disorganised in the military sense, and open to a surprise attack by a common enemy, may be likened to a sword suspended over the British Empire. Many there are who see it thus, and I am only surprised that in this country the matter should not be attentively faced.Well armed and with an efficient military organization allied to the fighting qualities which her sons have revealed through centuries of struggles Portugal can be a great rampart of the cause embodied in our ancient alliance a kind of trench along the seaboard.It seems to me, therefore, that it is no exaggeration to affirm that Portuguese military organization and rearmament constitute problems in which the British interest is truly involved, just as the Portuguese interest is closely bound to the question of British armed strength.Consequently, the value of Anglo-Portuguese military collaboration, in the circumstances covered by the alliance, depends, on the Portuguese side, on two factors of great importance, among others : in the first place, it depends on the strength at Portugal&apos;s disposal for the defence of the strategic positions which she holds in the world, and, secondly, on the contribution which she is in a position to make, under the terms of the alliance, to an eventual military collaboration with the British Army.In the event of a sudden attack to admit the worst possibility Portugal&apos;s inability to oppose immediate resistance may result in the temporary or permanent loss of one or more of the positions I have indicated (with consequences which it is not difficult to imagine both to the life of Great Britain and to that of my country), and in the need to re-take them. The lines of communication of the British and Portuguese Empires might for a time or for the duration of hostilities be threatened or even cut; more or less important forces would, according to circumstances, have to be diverted from the great centres of the &quot;conflict. Who knows with what sacrifices such forces could be so diverted, if at all 1In view of the gravity which the matter may assume &apos;&apos; de quoi demain sera-t-il fait ? &quot; it seems to me that it would be only prudent to deal with it at leisure, by organising in peace-time that which concerns our two countries and which should be ready and mature at the outbreak of hostilities. Otherwise it may be too late.My Government have long been conscious of the importance of this problem, and have long been in touch with His Majesty&apos;s Government concerning it.****** What is the position to-day ?Our two armies are almost completely ignorant of each other. Each is being organised independently of the other.&quot;7T TV&quot; VV&quot; *R&quot; &quot;7v*Yours very sincerely, (Signed) ARMINDO MONTEIRO.Sir Robert Yansittart,G.C.M.G., K.C.B., M.V.O.

</content>
</cab>
