<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/48/49 images: 614-617</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT 273Printed for the War Cabinet.  April 1944. ,JsL4&quot;Zv&quot;&quot;SECRET. Copy No.   oW.P. (44) 199.12th April, 1944.,WAR CABINET.% -COMMERCIAL POLICY.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.THE scheme for Commercial Policy looks mainly to the long term, but is designed, to take careful account of the difficulties of the Transition. The long-term aim provides a standard to which the arrangements necessary in the transition can be related: without this aim, the temporary expedients may become permanent and we may miss this chance of establishing an orderedframework of trade relationships, which would be so greatly to our interest. Inthis respect there is much in common between the schemes for commercial and formonetary policy. It is, in fact, unlikely that either scheme would work withoutthe other.2. The proposals for Commercial Policy, as they stand after the recent conference with officials of the Dominions and India, contain suggestions for thereduction of tariffs and preferences. But Article VII provides that the economic arrangements to be made must be &quot;mutually advantageous,&quot; and there can beno question of preferences being reduced except in return for a widespreadreduction of all forms of trade barriers, including not only the American but other high tariffs, and including not only tariffs but other import restrictions.3. The proposals are designed to leave room for adequate protection of our industries and agriculture by various means. Those methods (such as tariffs and import restrictions) which raise prices to consumers would be subject to limitation.Subsidies, which do not raise prices to consumers, would not be subject to international limitation. Other methods (such as the levy-subsidy arrangements under the Wheat Act or imports through State-trading) would also be permitted,provided they were not used to raise prices to the consumer by more than a specified amount.4. Accordingly, I recommend that we should now accept, in principle andas the basis for further negotiation, the commercial policy scheme as it has emerged from the series of discussions between United Kingdom, Dominion and united States officials.5. If the War Cabinet approves this recommendation, we must contemplatefurther conversations soon between United Kingdom and United States officials.These, if successful, might bring Commercial Policy to the point already reached -in the monetary discussions, at which a joint Statement of Principles expressesthe general lines of agreement at the official level on the major points at issue.Questions of publication, parliamentary discussion and negotiation with a widercircle of nations do not arise at this stage.6.   The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs points out (W.P. (44) 192)fithat we should now reach decisions on these issues, in preparation for the forth-coming meetings with the Dominion Prime Ministers.   I share this view and suggest that we tell them that our view is that expressed in paragraph 4 above.7. I also invite my colleagues to approve the annexed note on commercial policy, which would serve to guide our conversations with the Dominion PrimeMinisters and to assist officials in the next stages of their work on this subject.H. I).Board of Trade, 12th April, 1944.[27264],A
&apos; ANNEX.Note on Commercial Policy.1. Tariffs and Preferences. If, as now seems probable, the limitationof tariffs by. means of a tariff ceiling should not prove feasible, we should insist,at least as a first step, upon a graduated cut, which reduces high tariffs substan-tially and moderate tariffs only moderately, and leaves low tariffs untouched.Preference margins should be narrowed by applying this principle of tariffreduction to non-preferential rates of duty, leaving preferential rates unchanged;but we should seek acceptance for the principle that no preference margin need bereduced below 5 per cent, ad valorem. There should be no raising of preferential&apos;rates of duty, except that we must be free to raise revenue duties. For infantindustries a temporary measure of special tariff protection should be permitted,under proper safeguards as to its amount and the period within which it mustbe reduced.2. Quantitative Restrictions. On the basis of an objective criterionrelating to the level of, and movements in, our monetary reserves, we must be free to defend our balance of payments by restricting imports to any extent necessary,and without reference to the level of previous years&apos; imports.3. Subsidies. We must retain freedom to protect home production bymeans of subsidies to any extent we please. Levy-subsidies must be allowed,provided that the levy does not exceed the rate of duty permitted under thetariff rules. Export subsidies as such should be banned, except, perhaps, incertain exceptional and clearly defined cases.4. State-Trading. State-trading must be fully permitted, provided that itis not misused for the purpose of introducing discrimination or excess protection.In particular, room must be left for long-term contracts and bulk purchases.5. Membership of the Proposed Commercial Policy Organisation. Thearrangements should not come into operation until a minimum nucleus of states have adhered. The benefits of the reductions of trade barriers should notbe extended to non-participating countries, except in. return for equivalentconcessions on their part. .i6. Transitional Period. The reductions of tariffs and preferences and theother obligations of the proposed Commercial Policy Convention should comeinto force at a specified date, except that countries should be free to impose an import programme for a further period to be defined. Thereafter, the quantitative regulation of imports should be governed by the conditions envisagedat 2 above for the defence of the balance of payments.Board of Trade, 12th April, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
