<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/43/0 images: 22-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government/]Printed for the Imperial War Cabinet.   April 1917.SECRET.Proces-verbal0 of Second Meeting of Imperial War Cabinet, held at 10, downing street, S.W., on Thursday, March 22, 1917, at 11*30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Viscount Milner, G.C.B.,G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.The Right Hon. &quot;A. J. Balfoor, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Sir Robert L. Boiiden,G. C. M. G., K. C., Prime Minister of Canada.The Hon. Sir G. H. Parley, K.C.M.G.,Minister of the Overseas Military Forcesof Canada.The Right Hon. W. F. Massey, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.The Right Hon. Sir J. G. Ward, Bt.,K.C.M.G., Minister of Finance andPosts, New Zealand.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C., Minister for Defence,Union of South Africa.The Right Hon. Sir E. P. Morris,.K.C.M.G., Prime Minister of Newfound-land, a .The following were also presentThe Right Hon. the Lord Robert Cecil,K.C., M.P., Minister of Blockade.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby,K.G., G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War.Major-General F. B. Maurice, C.B.,Director of Military Operations, WarOffice.The Hon. Sir J. S. Meston, K.C.S.I.,Lieutenant - Governor of the united provinces, India.Colonel His Highness the Maharaja sir ganga Singh, Bahadur, G.C.S.I.,G.C.I.E., A.D.C., Maharaja of Bikaner.Sir S. P. Sinha, Member-designate of theExecutive Council of the Governor of bengal.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.    !Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B.,O.M., G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord of theAdmiralty.The Hon. R. Rogers, Minister of PublicWorks, Canada.The Plon. J. D. Hazen, Minister of marine and Fisheries, and of the naval service, Canada.Mr. H. C. M. Lambert, C.B., ColonialOffice, Secretary to the Imperial war conference.Mr. Philip Kerr.Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A.Major L. Storr, l  . 4 . .   . 0     x   .Captain L. S. Amery, M.P., J Assistant Secretaries.* Mr. Balfour desires to record the fact that owing to his absence from the United Kingdom he has-been unable to correct the proof of his statement.[4-28-2 b] B
The Prime Minister. I will now ask Mr. Balfour to give his statement on foreignpolicy.Mr. Balfour. I do not think it is necessary really for me to say much about either of the two important foreign countries, America and Russia, at this moment, becauseabout America some of the gentlemen here have more direct knowledge than is possessed by the Foreign Office. The Canadian representatives have a knowledge of Americawhich we hardly possess. I think the course of events seems to be quite clear now.America is slowly and reluctantly, but, I think, certainly, coming into the war, and only history can say whether President Wilson was wise or not wise in keeping back the inevitable movement, or the movement which has turned out to be inevitable,through all these months, or whether he would have done better from his point of view and from ours to have come in soon after the sinking of the &quot; Lusitania.&quot; But I thinkAmerica is coming in. Putting aside the effect that America may have on the conditionsof peace, she can help us materially from the naval as well as from the financial pointof view. As regards man-power, I dare say there will be a large number of Americanvolunteers who will come over and strengthen the armies on the Western Front,probably, chiefly the French, but that we cannot foresee. On the naval side I say nothing, because that, I suppose, will be dealt with by the First Lord of the Admiralty,but I take it in the main that their naval assistance will be that of relieving the ships that we have in the Western Atlantic, taking over that work and allowing our ships todo our own business in our own waters.As regards Russia, we have already discussed the situation, and I think the Cabinetunderstands it as well as anybody can understand this rapidly moving cinematograph ofRussian politics. The real thing that is important to us, I think, is to know whether,if, as we hope, the reasonable and moderate Reformers win, they will be able successfullyto administer the country. If you look back upon Russian history you will see that everygreat movement of reform has come when the administrative inefficiency of the autocracyhas been followed by some great calamity. The Crimean war, which broke the heart ofNicholas I, was immediately followed by the greatest of all revolutions, the freeing of theserfs, and other great legal reforms of the early reign of Alexander II. The calamity of theJapanese war was followed by the establishment of the Duma, and the administrativedisgraces of the present war are followed by the revolution which is now going on before our eyes. But we have to notice that while the general feeling of disgust and discontentwith the inefficiency of the autocracy has always been able to produce these reforms, wehave never had the opportunity of seeing whether the democracy will be able to do what the autoeracj- utterly failed to do, which  is to administer this enormous country andto organise it for purposes either of war or peace. The total failure of the autocracy isamazing if you look back, and my fear is whether these new people will do much betterthan the old. In Russia there is no middle class. Corruption has eaten deeply into their vitals, and we must not hope for too much. It seems certain, however, that theycannot do worse than their predecessors. - I think that is quite clear:The Central Powers, as we all know, have an enormous military advantage over usin their central position. - They have a corresponding advantage from the point of viewof their aims. Germany dominates the aims of the whole of the Coalition against us,but none of the other Powers have aims which are inconsistent with or even divergentfrom those of Germany. Austria, for example, has, or bad in the earlier days of the wax,nothing except to gain by German successes. Germany&apos;s desire to press on in the east was not only good for Germany, but for Austria. Turkey, of course, was promisedhegemony in the Farther East, which certainly, when it came to the point, germany would never have allowed her to exercise. But Turkey felt that her objects wereidentical with Germany; so there has been, not only a central direction, but a centralmotive. Now, we and our Allies, on the other hand, are not only not contiguous with each other, but we are as widely separated as we well can be. Our most important Ally,next to France, is Bussia, and we cannot get at Bussia. Even to take away a singleindividual or a single mission from Bussia is a matter which the Admiralty hasseriously to consider, and steps for which they have to work out with the utmostcaution. Japan is at the extreme end of the world. We are separated geographically ;but there is a much more important separation, and that is the separation of tempera-ment, and the separation of history and tradition. It is really an extraordinary thingon which to reflect that, of the five Great Powers now fighting on the Entente side,Japan and Russia were in death-grips about ten or eleven years ago. France and england were on the edge of war more than once, and on more than one subject, untilthe Entente arrangement was finally made in the yeax 1904.   Italy was actually joined
31!by treaty with the Central Powers as a counterpoise to France and Russia, whilst we and russia were regarded as almost traditional enemies. I remember quite well, in the firstdays of the Committee of Imperial Defence   which started in the year, I think, 1902or 1903 we worked out the many problems with which the Empire was then faced.What were they ? How to prevent Russia getting to India, and how to deal with awar with France. That was twelve or more years ago. Now the change which has beenbrought about largely by German ambition backed by German diplomacy which is the worst diplomacy in the world has welded all these nations into one coalition determined to put down this world tyranny. We have to accept the fact that residues of the oldcondition of things must to a certain extent remain, and one of the diplomatic troubleswhich we have to deal with, for example, is the eternal jealousy between Italy andFrance. It is curious that these two Latin nations (one of which owes so muchto the other, because, without France, Italy would hardly have gained her unity)cannot get on with each other. We are the link between the two. I thinkif you were to ask the First Lord of the Admiralty, he would tell you that one of our difficulties in the Adriatic is that the French will not work under the Italians. we ourselves are quite ready to do so. We have sent ships to help them, and our shipswork under an Italian admiral; but the French will not do this. In the eastern mediterranean there is jealousy at this moment which is hampering our diplomacy Ido not say in a serious way, but it is vexatious aud irritating. Greece, which is thescandal of contemporary diplomacy, is a scandal because three nations the French, theEnglish, and the Italians are trying to manage her, all of whom have divergent views.The Italians detest M. Venizelos I do not know why but they appear to think that under M. Venizelos Greece might attain to a position of influence in the JEgean Sea,which is inimical to the ambitions of Italy. Merely as a characteristic mark of what is going on, the Italians have been sending troops to Corfu, but nobody knows why. Wecannot get any explanation. The French say, &quot;Cannot you send even a corporal&apos;sguard, so that the British flag may be hoisted there as well as the French, the Greek,and the Italian ?&quot; Broadly speaking, however, everything is working well with theexception of these little elements of discord, which are very vexatious to the ForeignOffice, but which I hope will not profoundly modify the general course of the war.I do not want to go at length into the question of Japan, because that is too large,but perhaps I ought to say a little about it. The great dominions and the UnitedStates of America are naturally, and I think rightly, jealous of Japan&apos;s obtaining anyfooting within their territories. Japan, on the other hand, at present quite genuinelybelieves that what has been the sheet-anchor of her policy for the last twelve years,namely, the British alliance, is still the sheet-anchor of her present policy, and shestill clings to that. Of course, we are talking quite privately, and I do not think we canconceal trom ourselves that there is in every quarter of the Eastern world a certainuneasiness as to whether Japan is in the future going to try and play the part in thoseregions which Prussia has played in Europe whether she is not going to aim at some kind of domination. That fear hangs over the world. I do not venture to give any opinion on that at all. Lord Grey held the view that if you are going to keep Japanout of North America, out of Canada, out of the United States, out of Australia, out ofNew Zealand, out of the islands South of the Equator in the Pacific, you could notforbid her to expand in China. A nation of that sort mttst have a safety-valve some-where; and although I think Lord Grey carried his doctrine to excess, I think there is something in it.   I do not, however, propose to touch further on this question.As regards the immediate future of the war I have myself no doubt that Japan,with an eye to her own interests, is quite genuinely helping the Allies, and helping themto the best of her ability. She is making money so, unlike the a&apos;est of us, she isdoing well; but I do not think we ought to underrate the services she has given or theservices she is giving, and the present administration, so fir as I can judge, is incom-parably more reasonable in its Chinese policy than the Ministry which immediatelypreceded it. They are making great professions of leaving China to work out her ownsalvation. Whether these professions will be carried out to the full remains to be seen,but certainly I have not observed anything at present which ought to inspire us withsuspicion. I do not believe suspicion is well placed. The only reason for : which Imention this is that, I am told, at this moment the Germans still have hopes ofdetaching Japan. That telegram which was sent to Mexico, and which produced allthat excitement, you remember, suggested that Mexico should act as a intermediary between Japan and Germany. I do not know whether you have that in your minds.The plan was to bring in Japan on the German side.I believe that was one of Germany&apos;s extraordinary blunders which she is always
making, and I do not myself look forward with the least apprehension to anything that japan is likely to do during the course of the war.If I turn from these considerations, which affect the Allies, to the diplomatic relations between the Allies and the Central Powers other than the immediatemilitary relations, the most important question is, Are the Terms of Peace towhich we are committed of a kind which are unnecessarily going to prolong thewar ? There is no doubt that Germany, as we have heard to-day, is in very greatperil. How are they keeping up the spirits of their people ? They are keepingthem up in two ways : They are saying, in the first place, that England willsuccumb under the submarine warfare. They are saying, in the second place, &quot; you must go on fighting at whatever sacrifice, because, if you do not win, our enemies are determined not merely to beat us, but to destroy us &quot; ; and every nation worth anything,of course, will right to the last crust of bread and to the last cartridge, if its actualdestruction is going to be the result of an unsuccessful war.The practical destruction of the Turkish Empire is undoubtedly one of the objectswhich we desire to attain. The Turks may well be left-1 hope they will be left--in amore or less independent position in Asia Minor. If we are successful, unquestionablyTurkey will be deprived of all that in the larger sense may be called Arabia; she willbe deprived of the most important portions of the Valley of the Euphrates and the tigris; she will lose Constantinople; and Syria, Armenia, and the southern parts ofAsia Minor will, if not annexed by the Entente Powers, probably fall more or less under their domination.If we turn from Turkey, however, to Austria, the position is somewhat different.According to rumours, which you must all have heard, Austria is so exhausted thatshe would desire to have a separate peace; but, again, one of the difficulties about a &apos;separate peace is, What, by the terms as interpreted in our Note to President Wilson,will be left of Austria if we do make a separate peace ? We have entered into treaties with Italy, Roumania, and Serbia, all of which affect Austrian territory. Italy, who came into the war in April, I think it was, of 1915, opened her mouth rather widely:that is Italy&apos;s way; and.she not only got the Allies to promise her Italia Irredenta,the populations bordering upon her frontier, who are of Italian origin, speak Italian,and possess Italian culture, but she asked also for parts of Dalmatia, which neitherethnologically nor for any other valid reason can be regarded as a natural part of Italy.Her justification, however, was not ethnological, it was purely military, or rather, naval.Italy is very unfortunately situated in the Adriatic : she possesses the whole of thewestern seaboard of that sea, but along her coasts from Venice to Brindisi there reallyis nothing which deserves to be called a harbour at ail. But opposite, threatening her,within easy striking distance, and within a few hours&apos; steam, there is the coast ofDalmatia, with its islands and its harbours contrived by nature to suit modern sub-marine warfiire, and it is most natural that Italy should say: We should like, in ourown interests and for our own protection, to possess this coast. Except from that military point of view I am not aware that it is easy to justify handing over the dalmatian coast, which is not Italian, to Italy. But there it is; it is in the Treaty towhich we are bound. We, the French, the Russians, and the Italians, are bound to each other never to make peace without the other, and among the conditions which wehave mutually promised are these cessions of territory which, so far as Italy is concerned,I have just described.If you turn to Serbia, we promised Serbia Bosnia and Herzegovina, and I thinkthat is a most legitimate promise. They are of the same race, of the same language, andlargely of the same religion. They are not old provinces of Austria : they were Turkishprovinces up to the treaty of 1878 in the full sense of the word, and after 1878until 1908, when Austria broke through the Treaty of Berlin, they were still Turkishprovinces in name, though not in administration, or in any other substantial sense.Still, they are not old provinces of Austria, and if Austria lost them nobody could saythat Austria was destroyed. If you go a little further, north and ask how you are going to freat  he Slav population, which also speaks the same form of Slav language,the Croat and other Slav communities to the south of the Danube, you undoubtedly are going to make a great breach in the traditional Austrian Empire. But I am not aware that we are by treaty bound in any sense to do that.The Prime Minister. The promise to Serbia was conditional.Sir Robert Borden. Did we promise anything more than Bosnia and Herze-govina ?
Mr. Balfour. We promised an outlet to the Adriatic.  -The Prime Minister.--&quot;We wanted Serbia to give up a certain portion ofMacedonia to Bulgaria, and then we said, if you do this, when the settlement comeswe will give you these provinces the population of which fare more or less akin to your own. If the war is won by the Allies, then we will give you access to the adriatic.Mr. Balfour. I do not see that, so far as Italy and Serbia are concerned, it canbe said that even if we had the sort of peace we liked it. could be said that we had destroyed Austria, certainly not historic Austria, the Austria of the eighteenthcentury, in any sense of the word at all.When you come to our promises to Roumania, and our promises in connectionwith Poland, in regard to which I shall speak presently, the case is different. Wepromised Roumania, if she came in, that that part of Hungary which is predominantlyRoumanian in race and in language, should be handed over to Roumania. There arepeople who say that there are Roumanians in Hungary who do not wish to be handedover to Roumania. I do not know whether that is. true or not; I should doubt it.But at all events it is undeniable that to take away the Roumanian part of Hungary,namely, Transylvania, and hand that to Roumania, is to break up historic Hungary.That does touch the historic Kingdom of Hungary.As regards another historic kingdom with an important past, Bohemia. Bohemiais predominantly Slav in language and in civilisation. It differs, of course, from theSouthern Slavs, from the Serbs for instance, in being Roman Catholic in religion and inspeaking a language of a variety of Slav which is very different from that spoken bytheir brothers further south. It has a history and a tradition of its own. It has been quite abominably used by Austria in this war. If all accounts are true, Bohemia has ahatred of German civilisation and German propaganda which is intense and, I think,inextinguishable. Whether, however, all these feelings could not be adequately satisfied by giving Bohemia some form of autonomy in the Austrian Empire I am not so clear.I happened to meet, a few months before his assassination, the poor man who wasthe beginning of all our troubles. He was then heir to the Austrian Throne, and hehad a view that the only way to keep Austria together was to make it a triple Stateinstead of a dual State.At present it is a dual State, which is the Austro-Hungarian Empire. He wanted to make a third element in the Empire, namely, a Southern Slav. It seems to me thatif you make it a quadruple Empire and gave Bohemia autonomy, it would be a verycurious construction, but not more curious than Austria has been through all thesecenturies, and it might really meet the views of the populations without absolutelydestroying Austria as history knows it. But I am afraid that does not touch theRoumanian difficulty ; I do not see any way out of that at present.With regard to Poland, I do not think you can call the Polish part of Austria infact, it would be absurd to call it a part of historic Austria it became Austriau becauseFrederick the Great, Catherine. II, and Maria Theresa chose to cut up Poland anddivide it among themselves. Galicia is not part of historic Austria, and might and ought to go to the Poland of the future. But what is the Poland of the future ? That,I think, is now, as it has been ever since the great crime of partition was accomplished,the greatest crux of European diplomacy. A very distinguished Pole came to see meyesterday, whose name I will not even venture to pronounce [Lord R. Cecil:&quot; M. Dmowski &quot;], but he is a man of very high character and great position. He is anardent advocate for a completely independent Poland, which should include all thePoles. But I asked him : &quot; What relations does the Poland that you desire, the PolishPoland that you desire created, bear to the Poland of 1772, the year of the firstpartition ?&quot; &quot; Well,&quot; he said, &quot; I quite agree you cannot precisely follow those oldfrontiers.&quot; Part of what was then Poland is more Russian than Polish the easternpart of it and we could not ask that it should be taken from Russia and handed overto Poland. On the other hand, there is a part of Upper Silesia which had been taken from ancient Poland before the partition ; Frederick the Great, in fact, took it from austria.&quot; That,&quot; he said, &quot; is quite genuinely Polish.&quot;I think he said BO per cent, of the inhabitants of the Polish area of- Silesia werePoles by birth and Poles by languages; and, in his view, that ought to be added to poland.Then I said to him, &quot; Well, what about Dantzig ?&quot;[428-2 b] &apos; C
Dantzig, as you will remember, is one of the old Hanseatic towns, and undoubtedlysubject to its municipal independence it was part of the Polish kingdom. But I suspectmyself it has been practically German for many centuries ; it is certainly predominantlyGerman at this moment. The country immediately around it, or a great deal of thecountry in its immediate neighbourhood, is just as Polish as other parts of Poland; atany rate, more than 50 per cent, are Poles. But here comes the difficulty. He said,without Dantzig, Poland is impossible. Dantzig is the one outlet, the one adequateoutlet to the sea, which the restored Poland would have, and unless you are preparedto give back Dantzig to Poland it is useless to try and create a really flourishingmodern State. Of course, you will remember, Dantzig belonged to Poland at the timeof the partition. In fact, it belonged to Poland after the first partition. Frederickthe Great was content not to take it at that time, because, he said, with great truth,that :&apos; anybody who has the Vistula, or the upper waters of the Vistula, will becomein time the owner of Dantzig; &quot; as indeed he did become ; but still, I think everybodymust admit that to take away Dantzig from Germany would be to deprive Germany ofa town which is predominantly German ; for (if you have the map in your mind) it cutsoff Konigsberg, and all East Prassia from the rest of the Prussian State, and therefore,undoubtedly, that is a thing which would touch German emotions and German interestsvery quickly. Konigsberg and East Prussia would become a kind of enclave, separate from Germany, but remaining German, embedded in a Polish and Bussian framework.The difficulties of that are very great, but you see you are in a dilemma, according tomy friend, whether Poland is absolutely independent, as he desires, or whether it becomes an autonomous State, bound more or less closely to Bussia. However thatmay be, whether you include Dantzig or not, any idea of making a Poland which doesnot include Posen is, in his view, destroying Poland. On the other hand, Posen is atpresent a very integral part of Germany, and Germany no doubt would feel that ifPosen were taken by a Power, which was potentially a Great Power, it would bring it very close up to the gates of Berlin. And yet, supposing we are successful, can we allowthis war to come to an end without doing something substantial to get rid of the ,Polish scandal ? It is true that Poland brought it upon herself. If Poland had under-stood the elements of reasonably good Government, the idea that she could be parti-tioned like an inert mass, as she was, is out of the question. But that is in the past,and it is quite possible that the Poland of the future will be a useful member of theEuropean community; but until she is satisfied you will have this nucleus of bitterdiscontent, and a nation going back to great and glorious memories, when it was themost powerful State in Eastern Europe. I frankly admit that when the Germans saythat we are fighting for a cause which means their destruction, it is true in onesense ; we are not destroying a German Germany, but we are trying to destroy therather artificial creation of the modern Prussia, which includes many Slav elementswhich never belonged to Germany until about 140 years ago, and ought really not to belong to Germany at this moment.I am afraid I am merely stating difficulties ; I am sorry to say I am not solvingthem. If we are not successful in the war, there is no hope of solving them. If thewar is a drawn battle, these great causes, I am afraid, will never be satisfactorily dealtwith by us. If Ave win triumphantly, then we shall be able to deal with them. let me-return for a moment to my Polish friend. He urged me very strongly to make apublic appeal now on behalf of Poland. I do not know whether the members of theCabinet remember that the allusions in our answer to President Wilson&apos;s note inregard to Poland wrere of a rather half-hearted character; I think what we said was,the Czar had announced his good intentions. But, on our own behalf, I do not think we were very clear or certain. The reason was that we could not get the Czar to agreeto anything stronger. It was all-important that the note to President Wilson shouldbe a unanimous note ; in fact, if it had not been a unanimous note it would have beenworse than useless. We could not get a unanimous note treating Poland in a decisiveand independent spirit. The Czar made it quite clear that he considered that was aquestion of domestic policy for Bussia, and whilst he was quite ready to have a reference made with regard to freedom for Poland, and self-government for Poland, he was notprepared to admit that it was our affair.   Pie thought it was his affair.&quot; Now,&quot; said my Polish friend, &quot; that the Czar has gone, the Entente nations oughtto announce publicly that they are going to establish an independent Poland; and ifyou do not do that,&quot; he said, &quot; there is great danger that the Germans may succeed inthe future in doing what they have failed to do in the past, which is to raise a polish army.&quot; -His view was, that the recruiting of this Polish army had largely failed because
the magnates, whether ecclesiastical or lay, in Poland, had taken the oath of allegiance to the Czar and were not prepared to break it. The Czar has gone, the oath has gone,and he declared that his view was that the constant pressure of Germany, after thisparticular doubt had been removed, might succeed in producing this great addition toher man-power. If it did, the effect upon the Allied cause would undoubtedly be mostserious. He put the numbers down at between 700,000 and 1,000,000. SupposingPoland came in, in that way, on the side of the Central Powers, and supposing Russiafell into disorganisation and military chaos, the whole of the position in the East wouldbe changed disastrously for the worse. Whether we are in a position to proclaim our intentions with regard to Poland, and whether if we did it would have the effect whichhe says, I do not know; I think very likely it would. I put this question to him :&quot; The Czar has gone, and with the Czar one obstacle may have gone; but can you askthis new Russian Government to begin its career by handing over what the Russiansregard as an indisputable part of their territory ?&quot;He seemed to think it would be possible. I confess I have my doubts. I amsending an account of this conversation to Sir George Buchanan, and I shall be interested to hear what he says about it.Personalty, from a selfish Western point - of Anew, I would rather that Poland wasautonomous under the Russians, because if you make an absolutely independent Poland,lying between Russia and the Central States, you cut off Russia altogether from theWest. Russia ceases to be a factor in Western politics, or almost ceases. She will be largely divided from Austria by Roumania. She will be divided from Germany bythe new Polish State ; and she will not be coterminous with any of the belligerents.And if Germany has designs in future upon France or the West, I think she will be protected by this new State from any action on the part of Prussia, and I am not at allsure that that is to the interests of Western civilisation. It is a problem which hasgreatly exercised my mind, and for which I do not see a clear solution. These aredisjointed observations in regard to Poland : they lead to no clear-cut recommendation on my part. I am not pleading for a cause - -I am trying to lay before the Cabinet thevarious elements in the problem as they strike me.The next branch of the subject on which I have anything to say is the smallerneutrals.Sir Robert Borden. Is there any point about Belgium ?Mr. Balfour. With regard to Belgium, I think I can very shortly describe theposition to the Cabinet. It is more an economic than a diplomatic problem. I take it, that whatever we fight for, we fight for the restoration of Belgium to her oldlimits, and her old condition of independence and - prosperity. The Belgian minister has more than once been to me and has put to me this problem. He says : &quot; All of us, every nation, will, after the war, have to face a whole series of new and dim cultquestions, social, economic, military ; the upsetting of everything is so complete, thatthere is not a nation in the world that will not have to face a new set of things, and do their very best to soive the problem raised.&quot; AH that is true of Belgium. -but what is true of Belgium, is true to some extent, of no other country. Unless theAllies will, while the war is going on, make preparation to help Belgium, when peacecomes, even though its independence be restored and its old frontiers established, she* will be left derelict; it is an industrial community, thickly populated, depending forits very livelihood and bread for its people upon mining and upon manufactures.The Germans have not only overrun the country, but they have taken away all themachinery, all the raw material, they have practically taken away everything for the carrying on of the elementary economic effort of the country, and it is impossible forBelgium to make itself agam a going concern unless the Allies are prepared at themoment of peace, at the first moment possible, to pour in the raw material, to supply the machinery to make Belgium, in other words, something like what it was beforetheGermansoverwhelmed.it. I have no answer to that; I believe what he said isperfectly true, and I believe the appeal which the Belgian Minister makes to theAllies is one which ought to be considered. We are overwhelmed with work ; myOffice can do nothing ; I am not sure what Office ought to do it. So great is the pressure that 1 have not had time to put this case before the Prime Minister and oursmaller Cabinet. I only circulated an account of my conversation with the BelgianMinister; but the question must be raised and it must be faced. I think it is one ofthe most important things, outside the war itself, but how is it to be done, other ministers and other Departments must say.
Sir Joseph Ward. In regard to that restoration of machinery, do you mean priorto the rebuilding of the devastated Belgium ?Mr. Balfour.^-1 think we ought to be able to pour it into the country if we can.The Prime Minister. It is impossible for the simple reason that all our availablemanufacturing capacity is put into urgent war work. If we have anything to spare we put it into agricultural work.Mr. Massey. We might make America do it.The Prime Minister. There is a proposal of that kind.Mr. Half our. Perhaps I should add that in my view, the notion which is going through the German mind that they can restore Belgian independence enough to satisfy the world, and yet keep a grip upon Belgian economic life and Belgian ports, I regard as absolutely inadmissible. I think that is almost as bad as annexing Belgium, and Iwould fight against it to the last drop of my blood.   I do not think that is arguable.As regards the neutrals the small neutrals, I mean Sweden and Royalist Greece,which must be regarded as more or less hostile ; Spain and Holland, which I think arefriendly; but more doubtful, Norway and Denmark, which are certainly very weak,especially Denmark there is a gx*eat deal of important diplomatic work and ForeignOffice work done with these countries ; bat most of that work really belongs to myeolleague, the Minister of Blockade, and measured by telegrams it is far greater, Ibelieve, than that of all the other Offices of State put together; but he will make astatement upon the subject. I do not believe I have anything more to say except this one observation.Mr. Austen Chamberlain. Are you going to say anything more about Germanaims in the Middle East and their consequence to us ?Mr. Balfour. I feel intensely upon that question. It was referred to, I think, bythe Prime Minister in his statement the day before yesterday, but I am quite ready tosay something about it if you think it desirable. This war has been described, and quite accurately I think, as a war against the world domination of Germanj^, but Ithink that Germany after all was not equally anxious to have world domination inevery direction at one and the same time. What Germany wanted to do was not tomake every country equally subservient to her economic designs ; I think her economicambitions in these later years were largely directed, not, of course, wholly, but largelydirected to developing the communications between Germany, through Austria, throughsubordinate States like Bulgaria and Turkey to the Persian Gulf and ultimately toIndia and the Far East. All the German literature of the last ten years is full of thesedreams. Germany has borrowed a great deal from Napoleon, almost always the worstthings of Napoleoifs.These are the dreams and they have eaten very deeply into the social imaginationof the whole community. They picture to themselves Asia Minor, the Valleys of theEuphrates, and the Tigris ; and beyond, India and the East; they picture that as- ahappy field where German enterprise can reign undisturbed. They found Great Britainand the United States had got before them in entirely new countries. South Americathey were nibbling at, but they had never made up their minds to deal with it. Butthey thought they had a really fair field in these Oriental regions, and I believe that itwas within their power to do it. I believe that if they were successful in this war theywould do it, and that their success would undoubtedly adversely affect the BritishEmpire. I will not say the British Empire would fall, I do not think it would, but itwould have a very severe struggle for existence and the whole balance of the world&apos;strade and the world&apos;s power would be altered. The dominions like Australia and NewZealand would be in an entirely different position from Avhat they are now. india would be in an entirely different position from what it is now, and I am not at all sure that among the dangers of German domination, which every country has to fear, theparticular dangers that arise through their being able to establish an unbroken avenueof influence from the North Sea to the Persian Gulf is not the greatest of all. I think,whatever else happens in the war, that recent events have upset that dream, and I donot think that things could possibly go so badly that Germany could piece together thescattered fragments of this structure which they are striving to complete. In that particular I think we have been successful. I wish I could feel that our success was as complete in other fields of operations, and that we could look forward with equal
confidence to breaking the designs of Germany in Europe as I hope we have been nowin breaking her designs in Turkey and the Middle East generally.Mr. Massey. Can you tell us anything with regard to the French provinces of alsace and Lorraine?Mr. Half our. The importance of Alsace and Lorraine is two-fold. In the first place,if we could transfer them back to France we should, I think, do something to improve the equilibrium of Europe. You would remove a population which does not wish to be under Germany to France, which it does wish to be under. You would further increasethe population of France relative to the population of Germany, which undoubtedlymust make for the equilibrium of Europe, and because it makes for the equilibrium ofEurope, makes also for the peace of the world. Then there is another point. SinceAlsace and Lorraine wei*e taken by Germany, means have been found to utilise the greatiron deposits of Lorraine to. an extent which makes them a very formidable adjunct toGermany&apos;s industrial power. I frankly admit that I should very much like to see thesegreat fields of industrial enterprise restored to their original owners. Germany&apos;sstrength in coal and steel is an absolutely new phenomenon, you must, remember, sincethe war of 1870 ; and it is one of the most formidable factors in her success in this war.The Prime Minister. And it is one you cannot touch by the blockade.Mr. Balfour. I was told that when war broke out, Germany had a greater powerof producing munitions at the moment than the whole of the rest of the world puttogether. She owed that, of course, partly to her desire to be prepared in a militarysense, but partly to these enormous resources which she had developed since 1870, ofwhich the iron- and coal-fields west of the Rhine are an important part; and, therefore,from that point of view as well as from the more strictly political and diplomatic pointof view, I should be most desirous to see Alsace and Lorraine restored to France. I amtold that the French are not so eager about them as they were. Or let me put it ratherdifferently: I am told that the war-weariness in certain sections of French society inconsequence of their terrific losses and the general burdens which the war has thrownupon them are so great that if they could get an honourable peace, even without Alsaceand Lorraine, or even a small fragment of Alsace and Lorraine, they might be content to take it. But, personally, I should be very disappointed if this war ends withoutthe complete restoration of the ancient frontiers of Prance.The only other thing I have to say is that if German atrocities have really had animportant diplomatic effect. I think that when Lord Robert Cecil comes to speak hewill tell you how great an effect upon allied diplomacy has been the terrorism which germany has inspired and produced in Holland, Denmark, and Norway. Thesecountries are trembling at the German terrorism. They hate Germany, they hate the domination of Germany, but they feel that if they quarrel with Germany th^y will beas Belgium is, and that is undoubtedly a very great diplomatic weapon in the hands ofGermany.   It is painful to have to admit it, but I think it is true.The Prime Minister. I am sure we are very much obliged to the Secretary ofState for. Foreign Affairs for his most illuminating exposition. I do not know whether any members of the Cabinet would like to ask any further questions.Mr. Austen Chamberlain. I should like to amplify what the Secretary of state has said about the Middle East. He has said, and I think it is a fact of greatimportance, that this war in its origin was an Eastern war, which broke out over a dispute in the Balkans. That was not an accident; I think it was because the domination of the Balkans was a vital feature of Germany policy. German policy since the German Empire was founded and German political feelings have waveredsomewhat between two lines of thought. Bismarck, the founder of the German Empire,was opposed to colonial expansion, and held off from it as much as he could. I rememberbeing told in Germany nearly thirty years ago, when Bismarck was still Chancellor,that if he had given way at all, even at that time, to the policy of German, expansionit was our fault, and it was due to an English work, Seeley&apos;s &quot;Expansion of England,&quot;which had produced an enormous effect there. One school of thought has looked tooversea colonies ; another school of thought-and I think it has been a growing school of thought-has looked to what I would call an &quot; overland influence,&quot; to the bringingunder German control, through the link of Austria and the Balkans, of the whole ofthe Middle East-It will be clear to the Cabinet that the more certainly we have defeated Germanambition to found an oversea Empire, the more vital to them will be the creation of[428-2 b] D
this &quot;overland&quot; Empire. I am not speaking of it as being a German colony, but asbeing an Empire throughout which the German will will prevail, the development ofwhich is carried out by Germans, the Governments of which are influenced, supported,and controlled by Germans. I think that school of thought has grown increasingly in strength in Germany with the progress of the years. I think that the success ofGeneral Smutss campaign, and of the other campaigns that have been waged in Africa,must necessarily concentrate the Germans more and. more on that aim. Even while weare at war the German papers high-class, scientific papers are full of developments of this theme: of the importance to Germany of maintaining this clear and connectedsphere of influence right through the Balkans, right through Asia Minor, down to the boundaries of Egypt in the South, with her hand on the Suez Canal, down to theEastern frontiers of Persia and the boundaries of Afghanistan and India on the East.The Cabinet knows the pseudo-scientific, if not scientific, method with whichthe Germans pursue such matters as these. Here is a single sentence from anarticle by a leading German publicist which, I think, throws some light on thisquestion : &quot; If the alliance between Central Europe and the East can be broken up,English world-power is saved; if not, even tolerably favourable terms of peaceelsewhere will hardly compensate.&quot;They have looked to consolidating this great German influence in the middle east as the source through which they could draw all the raw materials of which theyhave need, and to the establishment of a great field for the investment of Germancapital. Through this territory they would also construct strategic railways, so thatthey could, at any moment, menace us on the Suez Canal and our direct communicationwith Australasia. They could also menace us in India, and could at any time stir uptrouble on the Indian frontier and involve us in a heavy campaign there. It is there-fore of vital importance to us that we should permanently frustrate the effort ofGermany to secure hegemony in the Middle East, and that we should cut the communications between the Central European Powers and the East which they have sought to dominate. I felt that this was a matter of such importance to the BritishEmpire that the Cabinet would pardon me for referring to it.Sir Joseph Ward. That is one of the great considerations of the Constantinoplequestion.Mr. Austen Chamberlain. - Essentially it is. Perhaps it is hardly necessary that Ishould add that the Sultan of Turkey is, of course, the head of a religion as well as beingthe Sultan of Turkey. We have proclaimed from the first, as we were in duty bound, thatwith his religious position we had nothing to do. That who was to be the Caliph ofthe Mahommedans was a question which Mahommedans alone could settle. But if the sultan remained the Caliph and were no longer, as he has been in the past, the friendand ally of this country, looking to us for protection, but the humble vassal, throughthe Young Turk party, of the ambition of Prussia, that would, of course, create anadditional danger to our position in the East.The Prime Minister. Do you know whether there has been a public announcementhere as regards Constantinople ?Lord Milner. It was made in Russia.Mr. Massey.-Statements have been made over and over again that Constan-tinople and the Dardanelles should go to Russia.Mr. Austen Chamberlain. I lay stress upon the fact that the turning of theTurks out of Constantinople is, in my opinion, a fact of interest to us, because theyhave become the mere handmaiden of German ambition.Mr. Bonar Law.--According to a telegram received from Russia, it is reportedthat a, Socialist member of the Russian Government said that they did not wantConstantinople. There is always the possibility that, if Turkey were not compelledto give up Constantinople, she might be prepared to break away from Germany.Mr. Balfour. Speaking of Japan, they have of course got a free press. There is a class of people in Japan who attack the British Alliance ; but according to some of the speeches made by the Government of Japan the other day, it was quite distinctly saidthat they regarded that as an essential part of their policy.
lbMr. Chamberlain. There has been a party, or a certain number of people in Japan,who have argued that the British Alliance is now working badly for them ; that herein this world-war was their opportunity to work their way in China, and what preventsthem is their obligation under the British Alliance.General Smuts. I should like to be quite clear on the point as regards the AdriaticCoast. Do our arrangements provide that Austria should be completely cut off fromthe sea in the future ?The Prime Minister. Not altogether.General Smuts. -So that the future Austria would have an outlet ?The Prime Minister.-! think she must have that; she will have Flume.Mr. Balfour. I should like to fake this opportunity of expressing satisfaction atthe idea of the Jewish lot being improved in Bussia.Sir Eobert Borden.-We have a considerable number of Jews in Canada who haveconducted themselves very well during this war, and they have come to us with repre-sentations urging that so far as can be possible the question of the improvement of the lot of the Jews in Bussia should be pressed.Lord Robert Cecil. Some months ago private representations were made to Bussiaby His Majesty&apos;s Government, but nothing was ever made public.Mr. Massey.   I think every Overseas representative has been approached by theJewish community with regard to the Jews in Bussia.   I am in sympathy with them.Mr. Balfour. I am a Zionist, but I do not know whether anybody else is.Lord Milner. It is impossible to go into that now. There is one question I shouldhave liked to have decided to-day in regard to the published war aims of our alliance ;there is a point as to whether they are not calculated unnecessarily to prolong thelength of the war. I think that might be one of the difficulties we have to make up our minds about.Mr. Balfour. It is not worth while considering until the Central Powers, insteadof merely nibbling as they are now, really show that they want peace.Lord Milner. I mean we ought to clear our own minds. Supposing the CentralPowers are much more disposed to peace than at present, are we going to continue thewar in order to accomplish such- secondary objects as the question of enlargement ofJugoslavia and an extended Poland ?Mr. Balfour. They may come and say, &quot; We will give Italy the Italian-speakingplaces, and she shall go round the head of the Adriatic, and we will give Serbia Bosniaand Herzegovina, and we will really try and make a liberal arrangement aboutPoland &quot; ; but I do not think that the Germans will give up Poland. I think you willhave to fight for that.Mr. Chamberlain.-Tha,i is the home of the Prussian Monarchy.The Prime Minister.-!? you decide a question of that kind now you may offendthe Italians.Lord Milner.-! am not suggesting that there should be any announcement of our policy, but I do think that as time goes on we shall find ourselves in difficulties if wehave not some idea in our own minds what is the relative importance of the secondaryobjects for which we are fighting.The Prime Minister.-T)o you not think every day alters the situation, and thatyou cannot form any definite opinion at present ?General Smuts. Is it not better to talk over these things later ?The Prime Minister. I think that is so. Meanwhile I shall postpone the Besolu-tion which I intended to put before the Cabinet.o




</content>
</cab>
