<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/43/0 images: 36-47</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ITIik Bocnmeiit;ls&apos; the Property^of His Britannic Majesty toemmeiallPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1918.SECRET.IMPERIAL WAR CABINET.Shorthand Notes of the Fifteenth Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet, held in london at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on Tuesday, June 11, 1918, at 12 noon.Present:The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon.  Austen Chamberlain,M.P.The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M., M.P.,Secretar\? of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of Statefor War.The Right Hon. Sir Robert L. Borden,G.C.M.G., K.C., Prime Minister ofCanada.The Hon. N. W. Rowell, President of the privy Council (Canada).The Hon. A. Meighen, Minister of theInterior (Canada).The Hd*h. J: A. Calder, Minister of Immi-gration and Colonisation (Canada).The Hon. Sir Edward Kemp, K.C.M.G.,M.P., Ministry of Overseas MilitaryForces of Canada.The Right Hon. W. F. Massey, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.The Right Hon. Sir Joseph Ward, Bt.,K.C.M.G.Zealand.Minister  of Finance, NewLieutenant-General the Bight Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C., Minister for Defence(Union of South Africa).The Hon. H. Burton, K.C., Minister of railways and Harbours (Union of SouthAfrica).The Right Hon. W. F. Lloyd, K.C.,Prime Minister of Newfoundland.The following were also present:GeneralD.S.O.Staff.Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B.,, Chief of the Imperial GeneralMajor-General   F.   H.   Sykes,   C.M.G.,Chief of the Air Staff.Hope,  C.B.,Rear-Admiral    G.  P.   W.Deputy First Sea Lord.The Right  Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bt.,Minister of Shipping.Mr. H. C. M. Lambert, C.B., ColonialOffice.Mr. Philip Kerr.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Lieutenant-Cplonel L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colon el. L. S.. Amery, M.P., Assistant Secretary.[543-1]B
THE PRIME MINISTER : I had better say something in review of the situationsince we separated last year. Later on the Foreign Secretary will review the position from the point of view of foreign policy. Then the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff will give a considered and detailed review of the military situation some timenext week, when the Australian delegation will be here.Since we separated last year neither our hopes nor our fears have been realised.First of all we had great hopes of the revival of Russia. We were building a gooddeal upon&apos;the revival of the military power of Russia under democratic control ; we hoped that after the few months of confusion, which necessarily ensues after a great,upheaval such as was witnessed in Russia, the democratic leaders there would be ableto build up a more efficient army than the one which the Czar commanded. Probablyone-third of the military power of Austria was absorbed by Russia, and at least a fullthird, if not more, of the military power of Germany. Germany had, I think, about.1,000,000 troops in all on that front.GENERAL WILSON : Yes, I think so ; probably more.THE PRIME MINISTER: In that ease it would have been more than one-third.Our hopes of success this year depended entirely upon the extent to which Kerenskiand the other revolutionary leaders were able to reconstitute the Russian Army.Unfortunately as the year went on it became increasingly evident that, we Avere to be disappointed in that respect. On the 9th November there was another great revolu-tion, the Bolshevik Revolution, which completely changed the situation. They, first of all, practically disbanded their army ; they then managed to hand over a veryconsiderable quantity of material, stores, guns, and ammunition to the Germans, andthen they made peace.   Consequently we were confronted with a new situation.This situation was a very serious one, because it meant the release of the million more or less good troops which Germany had at her command on the Eastern front,and which, as long as the Russian Army was in being, the Germans had to keep therebecause they were just, as uncertain about what would happen in Russia as we were.You never know what will happen in a great country in the fever of revolution. Atany moment it may go to pieces ; at any moment you may get a military revivalthrough which the country becomes a greater military power than ever, as happened in France during her Revolution ; consequently the Germans, as long as there was any uncertainty about it, kept their troops in the East. Finally, however, came theBrest-Litovsk peace. Then they decided there was nothing much to fear from Russia,and they sent their divisions as rapidly as the railway arrangements would conveythem across to the Western front, and it became clear to us that there was going to bea great attack in that quarter.That was the first disappointment with which we were confronted. The secondwas the American Army. Here I want to talk quite freely, and naturally when I makea statement of this kind there will be a good deal which I shall have to mention which&apos;may disappoint you as it has disappointed us, but I have got to do it in order tocomplete the narrative. About these matters we have not been able to speak in public at all. The American Army undotibtedly is our worst disappointment. america has been in the war now since the 2nd April, 1917. It is true that they had a very smallarmy ; I forget what it was, but it was numbered by a few tens of thousands. Still,they had a nucleus ; they had also been training officers, and they had a good officers&apos;training school there. America is a country of enormous resources. They promised aslate as October of last year that, by the spring, we should have seventeen american divisions complete in France, each nearly double the strength of the present British orGerman division. That would be the equivalent of about thirty German divisions, asfar as numbers are concerned. That obviously would be a very formidable reinforce-ment. I cannot say that we depended entirely upon that number of seventeen. we made an allowance, because we have been disappointed ourselves so often. Very often,we have expected to get so many rounds of ammunition, and we have found that the contractors have failed. It is very difficult to work quite up to estimates, but we cer-tainly relied upon ten or twelve American divisions. That would have made a seriousdifference, because, when the battle began, the forces were approximately equal, and, ifwe had had ten to twelve American divisions there, that would have been the equivalent of about twenty German divisions, which would have made all the difference in theworld. However, when the battle began there was only one American division in theline. That division had only been put in a fortnight before the battle began. Therewere also three divisions out of the line, not quite fit to put in. That was a seriousfalling off from the estimates which had been given us by the American War Office,
and there is no doubt at all it made the position of the Allied forces in France much worse than it would have been if the Americans had realised only half their promises.They had practically no artillery, and no aeroplanes at all. I remember, at a meeting which was held here at the beginning of December of last year, when representatives of practically every branch of the United States Government were present, they gave an account of what they were likely to produce. I remember, when we came to aeroplanes,there was a sense of disappointment at the promises, because we had heard a good dealabout the enormous output of aeroplanes we were to expect from America. When theytold us that, by the month of May, they would only be turning out 1,000 aeroplanes amonth, we were disappointed. General Sykes can tell us how many they have actuallyturned out.GENERAL SYKES: There are practically none in France yet.THE PRIME MINISTER : These are things we cannot talk about in public, butit is right at an Imperial War Cabinet that the representatives of the Dominions should know exactly what the position is. With regard to artillery, I think that the positionis practically the same, is it not ?GENERAL WILSON: Yes.THE PRIME MINISTER: They would not take our guns. If they had takenour guns from Bethlehem, Midvale, and other works, which were actually manufacturingthem, they could have got their guns far earlier. It would have been the same if theyhad used the French guns, for they had been manufacturing tubes for the French guns.But they wanted their own guns, and the result has been, I believe, that they have notyet turned out any guns at all, and now they are dependent upon the French and our-selves for their artillery. And this is the great manufacturing country of the world!This gives you the extent of the American failure to realise anticipations, and I think we are entitled to say that, although we knew perfectly well that the Americans couldnot turn out 50,000 aeroplanes, everybody here did think they might have turned out,000 a month, and when they talked about turning out enormous numbers of artillery,though we knew they would not do that, we anticipated that they would have turned out some. Again, when they talked about having seventeen divisions in France, we certainly thought that they might have half that number at the time. But they hadnot. That accounts a good deal for the fact that when the great battle began theforces were equal. If we had had reasonable ground for believing that the americans would have failed us altogether, we would have risked our industries and would have cut down our rations to one-half, and done all sorts of things in order to put the verylast man into the field, but as the battle was going to be a battle of endurance we didnot feel justified in doing that when we were expecting American aid to that extent.That is the second disappointment. The first was the Russian collapse, which releasednearly 1,000,000 Germans from that front; the second was that America, which had promised us 450,000 men in the field by the spring, had only 100,000, even if youinclude the three divisions behind the line, and they were not equipped, and had to be equipped with the aid of British, or rather of French, artillery. Of these 100,000 only27,000 were in the line.Another factor in the present situation for it is much better that we should havethe whole of the truth about what has happened the enemy was better trained.During the months when the whole strength of our army was engaged in a very doubtful enterprise, having regard to the collapse of Russia and the very bad weather,the Germans were training their reserves, and since this battle began we have seenthat what has told far more than numbers is superior training. Take this battle, ofwhich the Chief of the Imperial General Staff has just given us the latest news Thesuperiority of numbers there is not very marked when you take into account the factthat the French are holding defensive positions which they had taken weeks, and very nearly months, to prepare, and the fact that here there was no surprise. We knewlast week that an attack could be anticipated in this quarter. The German troops arevery highly trained ; they are adopting tactics which are novel in this war, but which,if General Smuts will allow me to say so, are not unknown to some friends of his  really the kind of tactics which the Boers practised with extraordinary skill in SouthAfrica. By these tactics the enemy sends a thin screen of riflemen in this casemachine-gunners forward, taking advantage of every little bit of cover. A case was given to me the other day by a French Minister of how three German machine-guns got behind a French position, and the first notice the French had of their presencewas the rattle of machine-guns.   The Frenchmen had no idea how many there were.
Three machine-guns rattling away gives the impression of a considerable force. It is what is known as infiltration, which is undoubtedly the old Boer policy of attack by avery small number of riflemen dominating the positions held by the other party. Bythis means they were able in the last great attack to drive back the French 20 or30 miles with very slight losses. It was done by that process of sending highly skilled,highly trained, and highly intelligent machine-gunners forward, and by a process ofinfiltration through the woods, which at this time of the year specially lend themselvesto-this kind of tactics, of turning positions. This is a lesson which we shall certainly have to learn and take to heart when our turn comes to make the attack in return.Finally, there is one other factor to be noted, and that is the united command-There is no doubt at all that it was a very important fact. The Germans are operating with one great force, and with one great strategic conception. In spite of the lessons of three or four years of war, we were very largely operating in sections, with threearmies the French, the British, and the Italians and, although there were negotia-tions between the armies, and arrangements were made for mutual support, that is adifferent thing from acting as one great strategic whole. Some of us did our best to remedy this defect, for we always felt what might happen. There cannot be a betterillustration than what happened last year. In the late summer we threw the Avhole ofour strength into an attack on the German army. At that&quot; time the Allied forces^onthat front, I should say, numbered something like three to two. It is quite clear nowfrom what the Germans have accomplished that that superiority was adequate to achieve very great strategic results if it bad been properly handled. But what happened ? We attacked with the whole of our strength. The French, on the otherhand, were opposed to that policy. General Petain resisted every proposal for ageneral attack upon the German line. His view was we ought to wait until this year till the Americans came. It is not a question of whether he was right, or whetherField-Marshal Haig was right. There is a good deal to be said for both. They wereperhaps both right, and perhaps both wrong. One thing is clear, that they bothsuffered from the fact that they took different views, and that they acted on thosedifferent views. If General Petain had thrown the whole of his strength, as Field-Marshal Haig did, into an attack on the German lines, I think it is very likely thatgreat results might have been achieved. But when General Haig acted and general petain did not, the Germans concentrated their reserves where the attack was coming,and the result was there was practically no progress made, and the losses wereenormous: That is one of the illustrations out of a good many of what the Allies have suffered from the fact that we have been operating with three or four armies instead of operating with one great army. There is no doubt that in this battle also we suffered from that. The reserves were disposed as you would have expected them to be disposed if there were two armies instead of one, and they certainly were not placedwhere they would have been if these had been located as one army. We were ofopinion that the attack was coming on Field-Marshal Haig. That was the view of thepresent Chief of the Imperial General Staff. He expressed that opinion in January ;in fact, he predicted that the attack would come from a force of about 95 german divisions which is exactly what happened on a very wide front. The Chief of theImperial General Staff expounded this at a Council at Versailles at which I was present,and at which Lord Milner was also present, but General Petain said : ie No, the attackwill come in the Champagne, or partly in the Champagne and partly on your front.Your best plan is to have your reserves behind your front, and we will have our reserves behind ourselves. Anyhow, I must have my reserves here,&apos;otherwise, if aGerman attack is delivered here, what will happen to my army?&quot; That was notGeneral Foch&apos;s view, and it was not the view of the Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Their view was that there ought to be one united reserve of 30 divisions, which wouldbe an army of manoeuvre either to support an attacked army, or to make a counter move.Unfortunately we were dealing with two different armies. It was impossible to reconcilethese two divergent views on what was going to happen in time, and unfortunately therewas a good deal of controversy, which came up in the House of Commons, which alsodelayed matters, and before things were put right there came this terrific blow on the21st March, and it was found that our reserves were scattered all along the lineinstead of being brought into one united command, where they could have been throwninstantly into the battle. It is never clear for the first few days of a battle what will be the full extent of the attack. It was not clear at first about the attack of the21st March. For some days General Petain was of opinion that there was going to bea big attack in the Champagne, and therefore he kept his reserves there. However, afew days after the battle began, Lord Milner went to France to represent the War
Cabinet, and be and M. Clemenceau, acting with the full consent of the respective governments, appointed General Foch as General-in-Chief of the Allied Armies.That was a great improvement, because up to that time you had to conduct negotiations between two armies, and that obviously takes time. Field-Marshal Haigmay take one view ; General Petain, on the other hand, may take another, quite&apos;sincerely, and with a good deal of reason, because the enemy moves are difficult to anticipate. Aeroplane observation up to the present has not been able to discoverwhere the enemy&apos;s concentrations are immediately before a battle. Therefore, eachGeneral had good grounds for saying that the attack is coming on his front.Therefore you get two Generals with no co-ordinating authority, each having to convince the other that the attack is coming on his front. Compromises in politicsmay be all right, but compromises in war are fatal. That is why we set up thisunited command. United command to-day is not the same thing by any means as itwould have been if it had been set up six months earlier. The enemy has had anunited command the whole time. There has been one staff, one brain, working for months, thinking out problems and preparing to carry out ideas. General Foch, onthe other hand, has been pitchforked at the hour of disaster into the position ofGeneral-in-Chief. He has to meet by improvisations, the results of careful study and preperation on the part of the enemy, and I think it is right that it should be said in defence of General Foch, that his task is very different from that of ludendorff&apos;s, who,has thought all his plans out months beforehand, whereas General Foch has just beenput there a fortnight after the battle began, to make the best of a rather difficult position. The battle was, as you all know, largely a surprise for the Vth Army; itwas not such a surprise for the Illrd Army. The result was that the Ilfrd Army was better prepared, and, in fact, would have held its own completely had it not been thatit had to retreat because of the Vth Army.Perhaps you would like to hear a little more as to what we have done since the battle began. We have poured a great many troops info France. In course of a littleover a week we sent across the Channel 180,000 men. The Shipping Controller is tobe congratulated upon having achieved such a fine record. We have brought divisions from Italy and from Egypt. At this point I think I ought to say how much we owe toIndia. Had it not been for India, which made special efforts to increase and strengthen our forces in Mesopotamia and Egypt, it would have been impossible towithdraw divisions as we did in Egyyt in order to strengthen our forces in France.With regard to the objectives of the enemy, the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff will say more about that later. His primary objective was probably to divide our forces, and, after dividing them, to hold one army whilst destroying the other eitherholding up the French Army and destroying our Army, or holding up our Army anddestroying the French. His alternative objective is, probably, to destroy our reservesbefore his own are exhausted, and then to overwhelm the remains of the Allied armies.Our military problem, therefore, is very largely a question of lasting out for the nextcouple of months, because by that time the American reserves will have come to our aid. Our new crop will also have arrived under the two Man-Power Bills which we,carried, one in January and another in April. The first was delayed very considerablyowing to the labour troubles. We could not get our men out of the mines and munition works because of the resistance of the trade union leaders, or rather the shop stewards,and there was a great deal of delay on that account; but by the month of August our new crop of men will be coming in. In order to maintain our forces, we have had tocall up men up tq 50 years of age. Then we made an urgent appeal to the Dominions,and they have responded with the readiness and with the loyalty which they havedisplayed to the Empire throughout the whole of the war. But with all these appealswe shall have a very critical time during the next six weeks or couple of months.With regard to the part to be played by America, perhaps I ought to say one ortwo things which have not appeared in the papers. A few days after the battle, whenAmerica began to realise thoroughly how. serious was the predicament of the allied cause, we sent an appeal to President Wilson for 120,000 infantrymen and machine-gunners per month for three months with a view to brigading them with British troops,our losses being enormous. They had been heavier than had been anticipated in any document that had ever been submitted to us by those responsible for raising men.These documents were prepared upon the basis of the experience of three years.Nothing in the. experience of the last three years coidd justify us in expecting lossesapproximating to those which we have sustained. The retreat of the Vth Army, andthe retreat of the Army in the North were productive of very heavy casualties. Thesame thing exactly occurred with the French when the attack burst on them.[543-1] C
That is one feature of this campaign, that these rapid retreats cause exceedinglyheavy losses to the Allied Armies, because the. enemy captures whole battalions.Further, when you lose prisoners, they are a double loss ; you generally expect50 per cent, of ihe casualties to return, but when men fall into the hands&apos; ofthe enemy they are lost for the rest of the war they are wiped out. Thenumber of prisoners captured was very considerable, both in the Vth Army and in theNorth,, and therefore our casualties have been equal to those which, according to previous experience, would have occurred in, perhaps, four or five months of active warfare.In order to make up these losses we had not merely to drain our depots depotswhich we thought in the ordinary course would have sufficed to carry on for three or four months until we had reached the next crop of our men but we had to appealto America to send machine-gunners and infantry over in order to be brigaded withour troops. We had the guns and we had the necessary appliances, and the Americanswe thought would supply the necessary man-power to maintain the Allies&apos; armies untilour own troops came in. The idea was that after being three or four months in our army they would gradually be withdrawn to form divisions of their own, by which time, August, our own men would have come in and,we could re-form, our own divisions.President Wilson, responded without any loss of time, and his answer was beyond ourhighest expectations. He said he would send 120,000 not merely for three months,but for four months. They have since been coming in steadily. I believe some260,000 have arrived during the months of April and May. This month we shall probably get another 175,000 infantry and machine-gunners, so that by the end ofJune we shall have well over 400,000, not all machine-gunners and infantry, it is true,but just as many of these as it is possible to absorb. The Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff has already told you what use has been made of these. General Pershingformed two or three divisions of his own, and where the Americans had only one division in the line at the beginning of the offensive they have now seven. some have been in the fighting and done uncommonly well. Five more American divisions with French or British artillery, I understand will be taken into a quiet part of theline, and will, probably be in the fighting line by the beginning of July. As far asman-power is concerned they are extraordinarily useful at the present moment.* The losses of machine-guns and guns of other calibre, which have been very heavy,have been made up readily out of our own reserves. The losses which are moredifficult to make up are the losses of infantry and artillery men and the losses of railways. No doubt the Chief of the Imperial General Staff will point out the extent towhich we have suffered in that respect. You need only look at that map to see thatAmiens, the main line from Paris, has been practically cut off. By this last advanceone or two other lines have been cut off. therefore we have got to use subsidiary lines,along the coast and elsewhere, which take a much longer time and do not carry asmuch material.I do not know whether it is premature for us to consider what would happen ifthe enemy were to succeed. Whether he succeeds or not depends entirely on thetenacity with which the French, British, and American troops hold the lines for thenext two or three months until the man-power of the enemy is exhausted and ours hasincreased. If the enemy were to succeed in either destroying the British or the french army or in throwing us back on the Channel ports, some very serious problems would arise. We should have to decide whether we should fall back on the ports or abandon the ports and join the French in defending the lines further south. We might evenhave to consider what would happen if the French were to be defeated altogether, whetherthe British Empire and America jointly could do what Britain alone did in the days of Napoleon continue the conflict, making full use of their command at sea, until they had worn down the enemy and re-created the European Coalition against theGerman power. That may and probably never will arise. If it does arise, thencertainly the Allied attitude towards Japan would have to change very considerably.Japan would have to be brought in to the full extent of her power and on an equal footing with the rest of the Allies.But, whatever happens, the essential fact of this as of every other war is the command of the sea ; and here one is glad to be able to point out that the fears whichwe shared at our last Imperial War Cabinet have not been realised. You will allrecollect I will not say the predictions of Admiral Jellicoe, but the apprehensions to. which he gave expression when you were here last year. The losses were very heavy.We lost between 500,000 and 600,000 tons in April. The world loss of tonnage,was between 800,000 and 900,000 tons, and if it had gone on at that rate the Allied powerto win the war would have been very considerably crippled, even if we had not been
hamstrung altogether. That is why we devoted very much time at our last imperial war Cabinet to the consideration of measures for meeting that very grave menace,because it was quite clear if the submarine campaign succeeded the Allies wouldcompletely fail in the war. As you will remember, much of our time last year wasgiven to the consideration of measures for combating the submarine attack of theenemy by the restriction of imports, by the increase in shipbuilding resources ofthe Empire, and by the improvement of the methods for successfully attacking the submarines. I ought to thank Sir Robert Borden and the Dominion which herepresents for the assistance which they gave us, particularly in regard to lumbercompanies. That saved hundreds of thousands I am not sure if it was not millions of tons of imports to this country, \vhich made a very considerable difference in our shipping capacity. Owing to the steps which have been taken at one time or anotherthe position is-1 am not at all sure I could not say restored, but, at any rate, it certainly has been restored to this extent, that the submarine attack of the enemy has ceased to be a menace to the Allies. During the last two months the workTs outputof tonnage has exceeded the losses. In April the excess in output over losses was26,000 tons. This was the first month when there was a turn of the tide. During themonth of May the ,surplus of output over losses was 138,000 tons. This month, Ithink, we have every reason to believe that the surplus will be even more. That showsthat, so far as the submarine is concerned, it has ceased to be the menace it was when you were here last year. The way in which the Navy have coped with it is, I think,one of the most creditable pieces of work in the whole history of the British Navy. Itis really a very remarkable accomplishment when you consider how extraordinarilydifficult it was to chase these submarines over the wide seas. You have been crossing the seas yourselves. A periscope, after all, is only like a bottle a very small thing to watch for, perhaps, a mile or two miles away from the ship, and it is to me a marvelhow the British Navy have been able to cope so successfully with it that last monththey destroyed three times as many submarines as were turned out by the Germans.&quot; The number of German submarines lost or destroyed, as ascertained during May, wasthree times the number added to the German submarine fleet.&quot; That, is the report which I have just had from the Admiralty.   That is a very remarkable achievement.Also, since we met last year, the Turkish Army in Mesopotamia has been pratically destroyed as a great fighting force, and that is important from the point ofview which I shall just glance at later on. We have captured a very considerable part perhaps the most important part of Palestine. That is important, not merelyfrom the point of view of the great historical -associations which attach to that country,but from the point of view also of possible future developments, because Palestine isthe.great bridge-head in that part of the world. Moreover, the difficulties which theGermans would experience in attempting to recapture it would be very great, because it is a very defensible country. The celerity with which General Allenby capturedJerusalem was a surprise to everybody. This means that if we were to be thrown backas an Empire upon our old traditional policy of utilising the command of the sea inorder to cut off our enemies from all the sources of supply and from all possible meansof expansion, north, east, south, and west, Palestine would be invaluable, as would alsobe Mesopotamia. There are the two lines which Germany had been looking forward toas a means of circumventing, as it were, our command of the sea. They thought ofthe Baghdad Railway as a means of getting to the East; they thought of the railwaythrough Palestine as a means of getting to Egypt, and through Egypt to Africa. Therewe have cut them off, and these two successes which occurred during last year,although, for the time being, they have not loomed as large as the gigantic events which have taken place in the West, may turn out to be even more eventful than thosegreat battles, because if the Germans ever try to get through in these directions, theyhave got very long lines of communications and only a single line of railway throughvery difficult country with steep gradients, and it would take them a very long time soto improve those railways as to make it possible to amass adequate forces in that partof the world to cope with the resources of the British Empire. Meanwhile, we aredeveloping the power of India for attack &quot;and defence, and as our sea communications are improving, I think we may depend upon it that we shall be able to do more thanhold our own in that part of the world, whatever happens.What we have to devote our energies to iioav is, first of all, the winning of thisbattle. Naturally that is what we have to concentrate our strength upon and it is mainly a problem, so far as we are concerned, of throwing more and more men intothe battle line. The Secretary of State for War and myself, the other day, werereckoning what troops had been sent to France since the beginning of this conflict,[543-1] &apos; D
that is, the number of men who have been put into the battle line who were not in the-battle line before. The battle began on the-21st March, and we reckon, taking thenumbers that we have put into France, the numbers we have withdrawn from egypt and from Italy, the numbers that the French have put in, the numbers that the americans have put in, and here I am not reckoning those which have been brought by Sir Joseph Maclay in his ships, I am only thinking of those which have been actuallyput into the battle line the total that has been put in represents something like700,000 men since the 21st March. We have to continue putting in as many men aswe possibly can, more especially during the next couple of months. We are considering various means of increasing our supplies of men ; the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff will be able to tell you a good deal about that. We should like to hearfrom the representatives of the Dominions what they can contribute, and we shall alsohear from the Secretary of State for India what contribution India is likely to be ableto make.Beyond the problem of winning this particular battle is the great problem of winning the war. To that also I hope we shall be able to devote some time and thought. There is one advantage of the German offensive. There is no doubt thatthey have shown what can be accomplished on the Western front by troops properlytrained and skilfully handled. They have accomplished a great deal with approxi-mately equal forces. By next year we ought to have a very considerable superiority inmen and material, and what they can accomplish with equal forces we certainly oughtto be able to achieve with superior forces. Whether the forces we shall then be ableto throw into the battle line will be superior will depend largely upon the Americans.We sent a telegram to America from our last Supreme War Conference at Versailles by the way, I ought to say a few words about the creation of that Council, which has played a very important part in co-ordinating the resources of the Allies at that council it was decided to make an appeal to America to raise an army of 100 divisions.Well, an army of 100 American divisions woxxld be the equivalent, I should say,perhaps, of about 130 or 140 German divisions.GENERAL WILSON : Yes, about that.PRIME MINISTER : A joint note was presented to President Wilson with that demand. He not merely considered it with great favour, but he hoped that figure would be exceeded. It involves the raising of 300,000 fresh men every month for atleast nine months. It looks now as though he were taking steps to carry out that greatprogramme. But it is also essential that the British Empire should be adequately repre-sented in that great army next year, not merelyin order to achieve the purpose of the campaign, but also in order that the Empire may be able to claim its fair share in the victory which I think is within our grasp if we each of us make the necessary effort,because if ever we come to a Peace Conference the fact that we have great forces behindus will count when we come to a settlement. Therefore it is very important that every part of the Empire should make a special effort, not merely during the next two months,but that it should make a special effort to contribute to the raising of a great armyworthy of the Empire in the great final effort to win the war. Meanwhile, other steps are being taken. Germany is powerful very powerful; probably more powerful than ever. The blockade, which is reducing Germany&apos;s power to feed its populationadequately, is not having its full effect, because the people have had their spiritssustained by the victories the Germans have won in the West But Germany is theonly Power in the alliance of our foes about which that can be said. Austria-Hungary,in spite of her Russian victories, is much worse off than she was. I have dweltwithout any reserve upon the gloomy side of the campaign, because it is right thatwhen we begin our business we should know the whole truth, and therefore I havenot kept back any fact, however gloomy and depressing it may be. On the other hand,it is equally important that we should dwell upon the facts that are encouraging andwhich cheer us, because they also affect us, and it would be quite impossible for us todischarge our duty unless we know the facts in this respect, too. The facts in regard-Germany&apos;s allies are full of hope. Austria-Hungary is suffering very severely from lack of food, and probably even more from lack of organisation of her food.You are dealing with a country that has not got the same organisation as germany boasts, and which consists of races hostile to each other and jealous of eachother,-so that there is a lack of cohesion which is becoming more and more apparentas the pressure increases. The Magyars are supposed to be hoarding food, and whilstthey themselves are living in comparative affluence, the Slavonic and even the Germanpopulations are suffering severe privations.   This is creating a very bad feeling
between the Austrian Germans and the Magyars, and these are the only two races un austria which have the slightest desire to continue the conflict. Together they onlyrepresent two-fifths of the population of Austria ; three-fifths of the population ofAustria is completely hostile to the war and to the objects of the war, and sympathisefar more with the Entente Powers than with Germany. That is becoming more andmore manifest. I think on the whole we did not. make the best use of that great fact,but within the last few months we have considerably improved our propaganda. Nowthere are millions of very skilfully written leaflets being distributed in Austria, andespecially among the Austrian troops on the Italian front, which are having a veryconsiderable effect. The hostility of the Slavonic races to Germany and to Austria ismade quite clear by the Czecho-Slovak prisoners in Russia. They are actually formingan army to come over to fight on the Western front. The French have succeeded&apos; in organising about 50,000 or 60,000 Czecho-Slovak prisoners, and about 15,000 havealready arrived at Vladivostock. The importance of this consists not merely in thefact that you have a considerable number of additional men who are going to fight onour side, but in the indication which it gives of the attitude of the Austrian peopletowards Germany and towards Austria itself. It is very remarkable that, although itis now the month of June and the French and ourselves have withdrawn very con-siderable numbers of troops from Italy, Austria has not yet attacked Italy, We havebeen hearing every day of a great offensive which is being prepared by Austria&apos;, butAustria seems to be in no hurry to commence it, and the reason is supposed to be thatthe Slavonic battalions are not very anxious to fight, and the Magyars object to thewhole of the fighting being done by them and by the German population of Austria,without the assistance of the others.All that is very hopeful, and it means that if we succeed in holding up theGermans, if the German offensive does not attain the object which the Germans have in view the destruction of one of the two armies, or of both, or the capture of theChannel ports -then anything may happen in Austria. There is no doubt that thepopulation of Austria is in a revolutionary frame of mind. &apos; It is really exactly as ifthree-fifths of the population of Great Britain and Ireland were Sinn Feiners. That is really the comparison. You know the trouble we are now having in Ireland, whichhas a population of 3^ millions which is a little seditious and hostile, but un austria you have three-fifths of the population which is in exactly the same frame of mind. For the Allies that is very hopeful. To a very large extent the same thingapplies to Turkey and to Bulgaria. I am dwelling now upon these things because theyare the elements of our ultimate success. There are the gloomy things of to-day andto-morrow, of this month and of next month, but on the other hand there are the brightand the cheering things which I think are growing in our favour from day to day, andwhich, if we succeed in getting through the tunnel as it were-the rather dark tunnelwe are passing through now will bring us out into the full light of a very brilliantday. With the command of the sea, with disintegrating forces on the other side, wehave an increasing strength of our own. We have America which had only one division in March, next year promising 100 divisions, about 2,700,000 men, that is one great factor.We have Austria almost breaking up to-day, every day getting worse because the Ukrainehas been a disappointment. The fact that Russia is so thoroughly paralysed, although itis a source of weakness to us, is a source of weakness to the enemy, also because nobodyin that country will cultivate more of the land than is necessary to meet his own needs.No one is going to cultivate the laud with a&apos;view to making profits, because the countryis in disorder and results are uncertain. Therefore, Germany and Austria, which weredepending upon the Ukraine to supply them with great reserves of food, will find them-selves without them. All that is going to tell if we manage to get through the monthof August. That is why we must make a great and special effort to hold back theGermanic Power during the next two or three months. If we do that, I think every-thing afterwards will be in our favour. The tide will probably go on ebbing, ebbing,ebbing until the month of August. So long as it does not ebb to such an extent as tostrand the ship, then the tide will flow again, and the vessel will begin to float on thehigh seas afterwards. Then will come the great problem of recreating Russia, and&apos;this is another of the questions upon which I hope to get full discussion here. TheForeign Secretary will tell you the special difficulties in regard to that, and especially thedifficulties about intervention, especially by Japan, and the attitude of America towardsthat problem, which will have to be discussed by the Imperial War Cabinet. Therepresentatives of the Dominions, especially of Canada, Australia, and New Zealand,will probably be in a better position to express an opinion upon that than we are,because we are so remote from that problem. The colour question does not disturb us as it disturbs you.
I do not know whether it will be necessary for us to consider once more thequestion of peace aims-the peace conditions about which the War Cabinet authorisedme to make a statement upon the 5th January last. You will remember that two orthree days later President Wilson also made a statement very largely on the same lines. There is some talk of a proposal from Germany. There is no doubt at all thatGermany would like at any rate, that the politicians in Germany would like a peaceat the present moment. They would be selling out at the top of the market. I donot believe that it is possible for. Germany or ourselves to accept any terms whichwould be possible for either of us at the present moment. Germany could not proposeterms, with her armies victorious, which would be acceptable to the Allies, and I amperfectly sure that we should not accept any terms which Germany might contemplatenow in present condition. The general idea is that she will probably make a proposal which would involve her getting a huge compensation in the East for any sacrificesshe might make in the West. It is a matter for discussion beforehand as to what theviews of the Dominions would be upon a proposal of that kind: I am not going toexpress any opinion at the present moment, except to this extent, that I am firmlyconvinced that a settlement of that kind would mean a renewal of the conflict when itsuited Germany. It would leave her strong ; it would leave her triumphant; themilitary power there would be supreme and would be dominating the German Empire,and whenever she wanted to recover her lost colonies, whenever she wanted harbourslike Antwerp and Dunkirk, whenever she had a recrudescence of her Easternambitions, whenever she wanted to get through the Persian Gulf and Palestine, andwhenever she was ready for another fight, unless Germany is beaten now, therewould be another war.I must apologise to you for the very lengthy review of the situation.o



</content>
</cab>
