<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/43/0 images: 64-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Document is&apos;the Property^of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.!0    &apos; Printed for the Imperial War Cabinet.   June 1918.SECRET.IMPERIAL WAR CABINET,Shorthand Notes of the Seventeenth Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet held inLondon at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on Friday, June 14, 1918, at 12 noon.Present:The Prime Minister oe the United Kingdom (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., CCS.I., CC IE.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Austen Chamberlain,M.P.The Right hon a. J. Baleouk, CM.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State fur the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Vescount Milner. G.C.B.,G.C.M.G., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,J.C.B,   M.P.,   First   Lord    of   theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Robert L. Borden,G.C.M.G., K.C., Prime Minister ofCanada.The Right Hon. W. F. Massey, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.The Right Hon. Sir Joseph Ward, Bart.,K.C.M.G., Minister of Finance, NewZealand.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon.j. C. Smuts, K.C., Minister for Defence,Union of South Africa.The Hon. H. Burton, K.C., Minister of railways and Harbours and of Finance,Union of South Africa.The Right Hon. W. F. Lloyd, K.C.,Prime Minister of Newfoundland.The Hon. Sir S. P. Sinha, Member of theExecutive Council of the Governor of bengal.Major-Generai His Highness Sir Bhu-pindar Singh, Maliindar Bahadur,G.C.I.E., G.B.E., Maharaja of Patiala.General   Sir H.  H.  Wilson,   K.C.B.,D.S.O., Chief of the Imperial Staff.Rear-Admiral   G.   P.   W.   Hope,   C,B.,Deputy First Sea Lord.The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Minister of Shipping.Major-General   F.   H.   Sykes,   C.M.G.,Chief of the Air Staff:The Right Hon. W. S. Chuk chill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions.Mr.&apos; H. C. M.  Lambert, C.B., ColonialOffice.The Hon. A. Meighen, Minister of theInterior, Canada.The  Hon.   J.   A.   Calder, Minister  of immigration and Colonisation, Canada.The Hon. N. Rowell, President of the privy Council, Canada.Mr. Philip Kerr.Lieutenant-Colon el Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. S. Amery, M.P., Assistant Secretary.[543-31B
GENERAL SMUTS : Prime Minister, I should like to join with my colleagues the Prime Ministers from the other Dominions in expressing my appreciation of thestatement that you made to us last Tuesday. It was a very important statement; very clear and comprehensive, hut very grave, grave almost to the verge of pessimism, but Ido not think it was graver than is warranted by the facts of the case. I listened also with deep interest, as all of us did. to the statements made by the Prime Ministers ofCanada and New Zealand in regard to the war effort of their respective Dominions. Ithas been a most remarkable effort, and in listening to it I was almost filled with envy.The effort of South Africa has been of a different kind. Whilst these Dominions have concentrated their main effort in the theatre in the Wrest, South Africa has been largelyresponsible for dealing with the German colonies on the African Continent, and in doing so we have sent to the front, both to South-W^est and East Africa, between 60,000 and70,()00 men. Atthe same time we sent a small contingent, consisting of an infantry brigade,and two brigades of heavy artillery to the Western front, and all that we have since beenable to do in this particular theatre has been to maintain these comparatively smallunits. Then also the policy we have followed in regard to assisting the British Empirehas been somewhat different from that of the other Dominions, the policy of the otherDominions has been to keep their men together in Dominion units, whereas we in SouthAfrica, for various reasons, partly political, have favoured the other policy of lettingour men come over in large numbers to join British units and so get mixed up with british troops. The result has been that probably larger numbers of South Africans arenow mixed up with British units on the Western front than are to be found in SouthAfrican units. As you know, we have had some forms of political trouble in SouthAfrica which are peculiar to us, and it is these troubles that have kept G-eneral Bothaaway from this Imperial Conference to my very great regret. Mr. Burton tells me thaton the whole conditions are improving in South Africa, and that, under General Botha&apos;smanagement, we need not look forward, whatever alarming reports may be circulated,to any trouble from South Africa in the near future.Now, Prime Minister, in your very elaborate statement you reviewed very fully thevarious causes which have co-operated to give the Germans a superiority on theW7estern front in their offensives this spring and summer. You showed how the collapse of Russia has enabled the Germans to transfer about 1,000,000 men fromthat front and to reinforce themselves to that extent on the Western front. You alsoshowed how the belaterlness of the American effort, to which we had looked forwardthis summer as a very important reinforcement, has also handicapped us. the single command of the German armies has been another most important element of success on their side. Finally, you referred to their superior training, especially inregard to open warfare, as one of the causes of their success.In referring to your statement, the Prime Ministers of Canada and New &quot;Zealandmade some critical remarks which I think make it desirable for me to refer shortly to themilitary policy that we have followed apart from the facts that you have mentioned.I wish to say a few words on the broad features of our military policy during theTasttwelve months since we last met. I think it is all the more necessary to refer to this,because in your statement which you made to the last Conference in April 1917 youadumbrated a military policy -which was very different from the one which we actuallyfollowed. Nothing struck me more in listening to the Prime Ministers statement inApril of last year than his insistence on the fact that during 1917 we should follow thepolicy of conserving our resources for. the great effort which was to come in 1918, andin the debates which arose subsequently I several times came back to this point,which struck me as the most important statement made by the Prime Minister. we know, as a matter of fact, that that policy since then has not been followed ; that, sofar from 1917 having been a year of conserving our resources, it was a year of themost expensive offensives for us, and the question arises : Why there has been thisapparent change of policy, and why the policy that was foreshadowed by thePrime Minister in the spring of 1917 was not followed ? There are two main reasonsfor this change, so far as I know. The first and minor reason was the collapse ofRussia and our effort to keep Russia going. I remember that in the spring and summer of 1917, when Kerensky was at the head of the Russian Republic, continual appealswere made to us to prevent the Germans from finally crushing Russia, to give thembreathing space, and to enable them to reorganise their armies for the offensives theypromised, and which, in a small degree, were actually attempted. That was a reason, a minor reason, for our change of policy in the summer of 1917. Theother, and much more important reason, was the advice given us both by our navaland military advisers, that we should begin an offensive in order to clear the Flanders
coast. The naval&quot; advice at that time was very clear on that point, that if the Germansremained in possession of Zeebrugge and Ostend up to last winter and this summerthe position in the English Channel would become untenable, and that, from a navalpoint of view, there was the greatest urgency for clearing the Flanders coast and. forour occupying Ostend and Zeebrugge, which the Germans were using as submarine and destroyer bases for their operations in the English Channel. That was the navaladvice.The military advice was just as emphatic : that we could advance in Flanders ;that our army was in a fit and in a sufficiently strong condition to do it; that we hadevery reasonable prospect of success ; and that by the end of 1917 we would probably have advanced 20. or 30 miles, would be in possession of the Belgian coast, and wouldbe in an advantageous position to resume the offensive in 1918. So much importancedid the War Cabinet attach to this question of policy, that a small Committee, whichultimately became practically the War Cabinet, was appointed to deal with this questionof war policy. The question of the military policy that we should pursue during the summer and autumn of 1917 was very thoroughly discussed and reviewed by thisCommittee. I believe that yesterday a document was circulated to the Prime ministers which gives a record of the tenth meeting of the War Policy Committee in June,1917. ft is one of the most important State documents of this country. I cannotlay sufficient stress on its importance and on the importance of its secrets being jealouslykept, for it is only with the object of putting every card on the table that this documenthas been circulated at all. No doubt you will have already observed from it thesearching examination to which this policy, suggested to us by the naval and militaryauthorities, was subjected. The Government was filled with misgivings ; the PrimeMinister especially had the very greatest misgivings about this policy, and you will see in the document that he argued the point in the presence of the naval and militaryauthorities most fully. He explained to them that, in the last resort, the Governmentwas bound, in. regard to matters strategic, to follow the advice of its expert military advisers, but that, as the matter was of the gravest importance, and the Governmenthad misgivings, he wanted to place before them all the considerations on the other side of the question, so that they might weigh allthe circumstances before tenderingtheir final advice to the War Cabinet. He pointed out to them that the french -oporation which had been promised for the proposed operations might possiblyfail. In fact, it had failed to materialise on a previous occasion, in the attack onthe Messines Ridge, in which the French had promised to co-operate on a part of their line. They had not carried out their promise. The Prime Minister pointed out that achange had come over the tactics of our Allies ; that when General Nivelle wasCommander-in-Chief of the French Army an offensive strategy was followed ; but hehad been dismissed, and had been succeeded by General Retain, who was essentially defensive man, and whose tactics avoided all great offensives, and amounted only toa punch here and a punch there against the enemy, just&apos; sufficient to keep the enemybusy, without any attempt at a large comprehensive offensive. Under General Petain&apos;command of the French Army the Cabinet did not expect there would be any largeco-operation with an offensive on our part. The Prime Minister stated his fears onthat point. He also pointed out that, with Russia paralysed and out of the fighting and with France probably on the defensive, we should be alone in conducting a mostbloody offensive against the German Army. He pointed out that our losses would very likely be enormous and would cripple us for the future, and there was grave danger that we would finally get to the Peace Conference with our army so seriously reduced and crippled that our influence at the Conference would be very seriously impaired.He also pointed out that, judging from our previous experience of offensives, our success very likely would. be limited, and that with a limited success there would be,especially if that success were secured at a great loss of life, a very serious loss of credit and prestige for us. It would be seen that we had attempted a great thing, but hadessentially failed in achieving our object, and the reaction both of our own moral andon the moral of the enemy would be very great. He also pointed out that the terrainwhich was being selected for this great offensive in the North was singularly unsuitableto a great-prolonged offensive owing to the muddy character of the country. he went on to suggest certain alternatives which the Staff should consider. He suggested the adoption of what are called &quot; the Petain tactics,&quot; that is, instead of a very greatoffensive leading to very bloody losses, we should make small attacks here and there and so keep rip the moral of our own men while really conserving our resources for1918.   That was his first suggestion.Secondly, he suggested, for the consideration of the General Staff, an Italianoffensive.   The Prime Minister pointed out in his statement on Tuesday that Austria
was at present tottering well, she was tottering even then. The Italian Army was then in good form, and there was every chance, with our assistance, of dealing a crushingblow at Austria, and so achieving a great military success; and with that militarysuccess he suggested there should be a combined diplomatic offensive, and as the resultof the two it might be possible to get Austria out of the war, with very far-reachingconsequences for the whole of the Allied cause.He also suggested, at the same time, a great offensive against Turkey, which mighthave a far-reaching effect on Turkey, and might take, not only Austria, but also Turkey,out of the war at the same time. Well, as you will have seen from this document, thewhole matter was argued most elaborately, and all the misgivings of the Governmentwere urged, and all the considerations of the other side were explained to the navaland military authorities ; but finally these authorities came, after a full consideration, tothe conclusion that this offensive was, on the whole, the best scheme on the horizon,and that it should be tried. And it was tried ; with the results that we all know.Instead of advancing to the Flanders coast we advanced only about four or five miles.Our losses were enormous in that advance. The conditions soon became indescribable.What Sir Robert Borden described here yesterday was only part, of the situation thatarose on that front in its later stages, when General Currie appeared on the scene atPasschendaele. We lost hundreds of thousands of men. As General Currie statedmany batteries disappeared in the mud, whilst others remained with only one gun.No wonder that when he appeared on the scene, it had become indescribable. I donot think it was due so much to the confusion in the British Army as to the naturalconsequences of this vast effort under those impossible conditions. The same with theNew Zealanders. The New Zealanders also appeared at a later stage in.the struggle,and when Mr. Massey thinks that his men were sent to a useless slaughter, he hasto bear the whole situation in mind. All that I can say is that the New Zealandersappeared in this offensive in its later stages when it had already become impossibleto achieve success. Finally, an end was put to this offensive by (MR. BARNES :&quot;The weather.&quot;) No, not by the weather, but by the German offensive against theItalians, and the necessity which arose to assist the Italian Army, to prevent Italy from being overrun. I think that is a true statement of the facts as they arose. Wenever reached Ostend; we never reached Zeebrugge, but only the first ridge, and thevery first objectives which had been marked out by our High Military command in this operation were not reached in their entirety, with losses such as we all knowto-day.It is remarkable that with a change in our naval policy the situation from thenaval point of view has been largely retrieved. What the army could not- clo in sixmonths&apos; struggle, at a loss of half a million men, the navy, operating with very smallforces, in two nights completely achieved, and Ostend and Zeebrugge were sealedup and rendered useless, as far as we know- entirely useless to the German fleet,for the present. The success which was secured by this effort makes one sometimesthink of what might have happened if the same naval policy had been followed on other occasions, and the utmost use had been made of our incomparable navy.SIR ERIC. GEDDES : If I may interrupt.   That is only a temporary success..PRIME MINISTER : Then let us do it again.GENERAL SMUTS : If this new spirit, which is also the traditional spirit of theNavy, were followed, then I clo not think it will be necessary in future for the Navy tocall on the Army to see it through its difficulties.PRIME MINISTER: I am reminded by the Secretary that the War PolicyCommittee recommended the study by the Admiralty War Staff of operations such as a were adopted as regards Ostend and Zeebrugge.GEN ERAL SMUTS: That is so. That was the situation at the end of 1917,at which time the Army was really in a deplorable condition. Our men had been worn out by asummer and autumn of the most ceaseless, bloodjr, and muddy fighting in this wholewar, and reached the end of that year tired, decjmated in numbers, with their moralseriously impaired, and the situation for us very, very serious indeed. The new draftswhich had been hurried forward from time to time were imperfectly trained, and thatmade the position still more serious for the future. That was our side of the picture.On the German side, again, you had Russia, which had completely collapsed.The Russian&apos; Army had disappeared or disbanded, with this consequent hugeaccumulation of enemy forces on the Western front;   We saw then that 1918,- instead
of being the decisive year, as the Prime Minister had anticipated in April 1917, was going to be a year of the most critical defence for us and our men. Our men, although in a tired and, I think, disheartened condition, were set to dig trenches and to put upwire entanglements, and of course, Sir Robert Borden can well understand, it was almost asking too much of human nature. We know, as a fact, that over certain partsof our line the defences were not in the best condition. The officers in many caseshad to make a choice either of training their men because hundreds of thousands oftheir own recruits were in an untrained condition or digging trenches. Some chosethe alternative of digging trenches, others of training their men ; in either case themen had been brought to a condition which was most deplorable. Then the german offensive started last March, and we know the results. The military policy which hadbeen foreshadowed by the Prime Minister here, and which had been strongly urged onour military advisers, had not been followed, with consequences, temporary consequencesno doubt, but, so far as they went, very lamentable for us. I have laid stress on this,Prime Minister, not because I want to make any indictment whatever against ourjnilitary experts or High Command. Nobody has a higher opinion of our military command than I have, but 1 think the full facts should be known. Some of us who do not sit at the War Cabinet every day see continuous statements in the press aboutdisagreements between the Government and the Higher Command, and of intriguesthat are continually going on on the part of members of the Government against theHigh Military Authorities. There has not been that intrigue, but there have beenthese continual differences of point of view the Government always leaning in one way and the military advisers leaning in another way which have led to this state ofaffairs which T have described.Happily we have secured certain advantages during the same period which Ithink will be of a far-reaching character. As the result of the efforts made mainly bythe Prime Minister and Lord Milner, we have now established a single command,which is going to be a very serious factor in our future success. I think we must putthat to our credit as a very valuable item.Another very important thing that we have to keep in mind is that we have finallyasserted our naval supremacy and our command of the sea by the practical elimination ofthe.submarine peril. You may remember last year during our discussions the verydespondent way in which the First Sea Lord then spoke about the whole question ofnaval supremacy. In fact, I sometimes came under the impression that we had lostcommand of the sea, and no doubt, with the gravity of the situation as it then existed,those apprehensions may have been justified ; but they have now disappeared. Ourcause has for its corner-stone our supremacy at sea ; if that is in question, we cannotlook forward to victory, but as long as that is secure as it is now beyond all manner of doubt-1 think we can look upon that result, for which we have to thank ourAdmiralty administration, as a most important one to set on the other side against theGerman military achievements. Lastly, we have this most important factor for thefuture, that the American Army is now really appearing on the scene. But 1 Avillrefer to that later.The Prime Minister said in his statement that the next two or three months willbe the most critical period for us in the whole war. I agree with him. The Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff has explained to us the small amount of ground which wecan still give without &quot;seriously endangering the position of our armies in France.The object of the enemy in this great offensive has been to deal a smashing blow at us and to achieve decisive results before the American Army can appear on the scene.He attempts to achieve this object in various ways. He wants to separate the twoarmies, the British and the French, to pin the one clown and to deal effectively and finally with the other, and his efforts so far have been in furtherance of these objects.We, in the meantime, by our inferior numbers and other disadvantages, are forced totake the defensive, and to take a defensive in which we cannot give much ground,because of the limited area which is still left us, and because of the proximity of theenemy forces to Paris, and the Channel ports. It is on these grounds that thesituation will be so very dangerous until the American forces are strong in the field..No doubt the next few months will be our greatest danger. But I do not think thatis the only clanger. There are others. In this country, as no doubt you will havenoticed, the temper of the people has improved enormously. I remember what theBritish temper was in the summer of last year ; the doubt, the vacillation, thehesitation, the difference of opinion, that existed then. All that has disappeared.You may go to any part of this country, and you will find that the temper of thepeople has hardened and is now as firm as it could be, and I am sure that the harder[54o 3] C
the blows struck by the enemy, the more resolute and the more determined this people will be to see the business through.It is an undefeated people ; for better or for worse they have never been defeated,and they do not know defeat. The nation has that spirit that the greater, the dangerthe more determined they are not to give in. The Americans will have the sametemper, and they will show perhaps even a greater spirit in the struggles that are coming. But it is not the same with the French, and that is the other danger which we have before us. What the result will be of a victorious offensive by theenemy during the next two or three months upon the French moral nobody canforetell. The French so far have been superb; there is no doubt about it. Theyhave suffered beyond belief. They have suffered enormous casualties ; their country hasbeen devastated ; the best parts are in possession of the enemy ; yet in all thatsuffering and in all that loss they have shown a spirit for which no one can possiblygive them too much credit. In this spirit they are bearing up. But whether they willkeep it up when the enemy&apos;s guns are in full range of Paris we do not know. Weonly hope and trust that the spirit of this country and the spirit of America, and the,pouring in of the huge American army into France, will be sufficient to keep themgoing, not only for the next three months, but for the period which will followthereafter.Another point which I wish to refer to, and which is of very grave importance, is thetraining of the American officers and Staffs. It is not a question of numbers ; no doubtwe are getting a huge American army in France ; they are pouring in at the rate of a quarter of a million men per month. At that rate we shall soon have an enormousAmerican army in France. But, as I have said, it is not a question of numbers. Wehave the lesson of the American Civil War to teach us that it took the Union morethan two years in order to train Generals and to train Staffs to deal with themagnificent and incomparable material that they had in their men. The danger thatI foresee is that even when in a few months&apos; time we have a big American army inFrance we shall not have trained officers and we shall not have trained Staffs to handlethat great instrument of victory. I would impress in the strongest way possible on our Imperial General Staff that they should devise every step possible towards thetraining of the American officers and the American Staffs. If that is not done, thenthis American effort is also going to be wasted, and we are going to meet next year with another grave disappointment behind us. The story has been told to me ofexperimental tests made in France by the marching of one American division to aparticular point and how their Staff dealt with the problem, and everything wentwrong. This has alarmed me ; makes me think that the most important point now is that our Staff should devote its attention to trying to help the Americans to traintheir officers and their Staffs for the work in hand. Besides this our own training isalso a very important matter. The Prime Minister, in his statement, gave us as thefourth cause of the German victory the superiority of their training. I am sure he did not exaggerate the importance of this matter of training. The fact is that we have largely become trench mad ; trench warfare has taken possession of our minds. But itmust be remembered that trench warfare is merely a passing feature of the situation.Trench warfare was a great thing only so far as the opposing armies were of equalstrength, and when one could not move the other ; and both dug themselves in andawaited the onslaughts of its opponent. We have learned now&apos;by repeated experiencethat with superior artillery you can shell the enemy out of any trenches, and if you have sufficient force left to follow up your artillery effort you can go on in openwarfare. We did it at Cambrai. The enemy did it in the Russian campaign, in the warsaw campaign, and also repeatedly this summer against us in France. Descriptionshave been given me by officers who were in our Ninth Army Corps as to what happened to the French Army on the :2.7th May on the Chemins des Dames. It is quite clear that on the first day the enemy, by a tremendous artillery fire, demolished theFrench line, and after that the French did not know how to deal with the situationbecause they were not trained for open warfare, and the enemy marched on until theygot to the Marne with very little opposition. The same thing had happened to our troops on the 21st March, because we were not versed in the methods of open warfare,and the enemy divisions had been trained for the purpose. I foresee the most seriousdangers for us not only in the defence, but also when the time comes for us to take the offensive. We shall not know how to fight in the open, and the result, even with thebest armies and with incomparable resources, will be that we shall not be able to attain victory. It is not only, therefore, a question of training American officers andmen but our own men in the methods of open warfare, and especially in the elective-use of machine guns, for both defence and offence.
What Sir Robert Borden said &quot;about the machine-gun organisation of theCanadian Army Corps we all know to be true. The machine-gun organisation of theCanadian Army Corps is the best in the whole of the British Army. They havea large mobile reserve of machine guns which they can send in a body, just asif they were artillery, to any point of the front, and with which they can deliver thehardest knocks to the enemy at any selected point. I am sure our whole machine-gun organisation will have to be improved if we want to rival the Germans in their use of that arm.I have made these remarks, Prime Minister, because I think we can win this Avar.We have military resources which are superior in every respect to those of the enemy.We are superior in man power, in munition power, and in every form of war power,and in addition we have a united command which is a big step towards success.SIR ROBERT BORDEN : Are the Americans subject to that united command ?GENERAL SMUTS : Yes, the Americans, the Italians, all the important armieson the Western front are subject to that united command. What we want is improvedorganisation, improved training, and superior leadership, in which the Germans so farhave beaten us. And if, by our united efforts, we are able to the fullest extent to effect this superior organisation, training, and leadership, and with our unquestionedsuperiority in resources, I have no doubt that we can reverse the situation in 1919.I thought the Prime Minister was going far last year when he spoke of the victory in19IS ; but this year we are shifting it another year further on. At any rate, let usmake certain that 1919 is going to be a year of decisive success for us.MR. LLOYD: I am putting in a written statement to cover the efforts made byNewfoundland, for the purpose of this record. I will not make an oral statement thismorning to the Cabinet. 1 will, however, just remark that after the appeal for more men from His Majesty&apos;s Government made early in April last, the new found land government issued an Order in Council prohibiting unmarried men leaving thecountry. Some weeks later, when the Legislature met, the Military Service Act waspassed, and on the 24-th May it was set clown for men to report under it. Before thatdate, however, some 1,200 men voluntarily enlisted as they did not wish to beconscripted.MR. MONTAGU : As I have circulated a very full statement in regard to india do not wish to add anything to it to-day.SIR S. P. SINHA : Prime Minister, I do not wish to take up much time of theWar Cabinet, especially as I have no suggestions of such a useful kind as have beenput forward by the previous speakers. If therefore I speak at all, I clo so only withthe desire to impress upon the War Cabinet the necessity for giving such further assistance to India as will enable her to put forward her powers in the prosecution ofthe war to the fullest possible extent. As is seen from the Prime Ministers statementplaced before us, we have been trying, both before the Prime Ministers appeal of the2nd April last as well as after, to do our very utmost that our capacity will allow.Whereas, before the war our intake of combatants was only about .15,000, the totalnumber of combatants enlisted during the year ending the 31st March, 1918, was about276,000; that is very nearly twenty times what it used to be before.THE PRIME MINISTER : Have you the figures for the previous year?SIR S. P. SINHA : No. Unfortunately I did not think that the Secretary ofState for India would ask me to address the Cabinet this morning.MR. CHAMBERLAIN : The year before was a great improvement on the previous year.SIR S. P. SINHA: As regards recruits, we have made a progressive improvementsince the beginning of the war. Besides the 276,000 already mentioned, we haverecruited about l),000 Imperial Service troops, and 159,000 non-combatants, making agrand total of 444,000.THE PRIME MINISTER: Is that for. 1917-18?SIR S. P. SINHA : That is so.THE PRIME MINISTER : Would you mind putting in, later on, the figures asregards recruits since the beginning of the war ?[543-3] D
SIR S. P. SINHA : Certainly. We have been able, not only to maintain theforces overseas, but a large number of new units have been formed during the year,and full provision has been made for the equipment and for the necessary drafts for maintenance.Then, since your appeal of the 2nd April, we are adding to the forces in Egypt16 Indian infantry battalions at once, in addition to the .1 1 to be despatched from india towards the end of May. We are also supplying to Egypt divisional troops forone division, so that the immediate result will be the release of several british battalions for France. In addition to the above, we have a scheme in preparation forthe recruitment of at least 500,000 fighting men for the twelve months commencing onthe 1st June, 1918, and it has been found that after allowing for the usual wastage oftroops in India and providing drafts, we shall have sufficient men to supply the personnel of 91 battalions of Indian infantry, 21 companies of sappers and miners,14 batteries of mountain artillery, 7 squadrons of cavalry, and 7 -divisional signalcompanies. To render these forces efficient that is the reason I venture to address the War Cabinet it is necessary that the Home Government must be prepared to giveIndia a liberal allowance of staff and regimental officers, particularly of officers ableto speak to the Sepoy in his own language, and also a very large number of medical officers. Perhaps it maybe considered that we ought not to require the latter, namely,the medical officers, but the fact is, unfortunately, that in India we have not a sufficient number of medical schools and colleges to train sufficient officers to meet the reqiure-ments of our own civil population. Lvery available medical man has been absorbedfor work in the army, even to the extent of denuding the civil population of the verylittle medical help that is available for them at the best of times. So far, therefore,Sir, as the question of men is concerned, we have increased our recruitment twentytimes what it formerly was, and I think this year it is going to be thirty times morethan what it was before the war. I hope it will be realised that India is trying to dothe best she can, in so far as supplying man-power is concerned. I think 1 ought totake this opportunity of saying also, on behalf of the princes of India, that their contribution in this respect has been most magnificent, and if my colleague theMaharajah of Patiala will pardon me, I should like to mention his name in particular,because his contribution in this respect is more than that of all the Indian States puttogether.As regards materials, here again we have been severely handicapped by reason ofthe past policy, with regard to which I am not going to say anything now. - We havenow got a Munitions Hoard, and we are trying to manufacture as fast as possible allthat is required for the army in India, Egypt and Mesopotamia, and in East Africa,and so far we have been able to do a great deal in that respect; but here again we areterribly handicapped by reason of the want of two things : firstly, plant ; and secondly,skilled expert advice. In this respect I venture to ask the Prime Minister to do allthat is possible in the way of giving the assistance that we are in absolute need of andin the way of plant and skilled expert advice.THE PRIME MINISTER: The Minister of Munitions will no doubt take note ofthis request.MR. CHURCHILL: Yes.SIR S. P. SIX HA : With regard to finance, lest it might be considered that I was doing it in a boastful and vainglorious spirit, I will refer at length to the contributionsalready made by India, including the 100,000,000Z. voted last year. Here again i venture to ask lor assistance from the British Government to enable us to do more inthe way-of finance than we have been able to do up to the present. We have bought,materials for the British Government, as well as for the American Government and theAllies,.to the extent of about 13O,000,000Z., and this year I think the estimate is another70,000j()00i. or 80,000,000L    But for this we cannot get paid in cash.We shall no doubt be paid eventually, but the result of it is that the bullion andcoin are depleted and we are faced with the gravest currency crisis, in consequence ofwhich we may have to declare our currency notes inconvertible. If that situationactually does arise the result will be disastrous ; our credit will be gone ; and it willbe generally believed in the bazaars that the British Kmpire is bankrupt, and if we buyanything at all we shall have to pay at least double the price that is paid at present.It will therefore be most detrimental to the interests, not only of Great Britain, but ofher Allies if this position is allowed to continue. We have begged time after time forassistance in the matter of silver and gold being sent to us from England, but hitherto
y -    *we have not succeeded. I desire to impress upon you, Sir, the absolute necessity ofgiving us the very little help we require, which is only for a short time, in order thatthe Government of India may be able to tide over the grave crisis with which they are faced.I am sorry I have been longer than I thought, but I thought it my duty to placethese matters before you in the hope that the assistance will be forthcoming.MR. LONG : As far as the statement in regard to the Grown Colonies is concerned,they have, I think, come well through. Of course their main contributions are dividedinto men, money, and gifts in kind. The principal source of recruitment is from menwho constitute the i departments which are administrating the Colonies, and the menamongst the white population and the native population. In several Crown Coloniesthey have had compulsory service, in the Straits Settlements, and in East Africa, togive only two instances.MR. BONAR LAW: I think the Straits Settlements were the very first in theEmpire to have compulsory service.MR. LONG : Yes, that is so. On the whole I think we have sent as many menas can be spared from the administration. In some cases, of course, compulsory service would not be of any value, because the men who would be compelled to servewould not be suitable for fighting purposes, especially out of their own country, butthey have made most valuable contributions, as you know, in regard to labourbattalions, and in providing men for military duties other than purely combatant work.So far as I know, I do not think that any one of them has failed to do its share in thisdirection, while the contributions as regards gifts in kind and money have been quiteremarkable. Among them I think it ought to be mentioned that the presents sent us by native chiefs, although small in amount, are remarkable as proofs of the loyaltyand devotion of these men, and as evidence of their appreciation of thebenefits they receive from the British Government and their desire to remain under British rule. Quite lately we have, in response to telegrams sent to the governors of the different Crown Colonies, had most remarkable expressions ofopinion, especially in West and East Africa, expressing their profound devotion tothe British Crown and Government for the benefits derived in the past, and a very strong desire to remain under the British Crown. Not only that, but they have pointedout to us that the services which they have rendered to our troops where &apos;there hasbeen fighting, as in the case of Togoland or the Cameroons, or in other parts of Westor East Africa, have been very great and very unselfish, and that thereby they haveexposed themselves to this great risk : that, if they were not to be under British rule in the future, in their belief that is the opinion formed by those who are connectedwith the Governments residing there -they would be. severely punished by theGermans for the invaluable assistance which they have given to us, and it is impressed upon us by them and by residents of all kinds, not merely by Government officials and people connected with educational movements or religious movements or tradingmovements, but others, that these people feel that in a moment of difficulty they have come forward and rendered invaluable services. General Smuts can speak with muchgreater authority than I can of the services rendered by natives acting as carriers andsuch like. They are fully alive to the fact that if they are handed back to their lategovernors it Avillmean most bitter reprisals, involving terrible suffering for them andtheir wives and children. That is, briefly, a record of what has been done in theCrown Colonies, and what has happened there. The campaign in German East africa is rapidly, I think, drawing to a close. There is now only a small body of german troops, who are very mobile, and the country lends itself to warfare of the kind ofwhich they seem to be masters. They are very evasive, but every bod)7 seems to thinkthat we are approaching the time now when we ought to complete this campaign. Onthe whole I think that the Crown Colonies have done their share in both men, money,and gifts in kind, and deserve well of the Empire.THE PRIME MINISTER: We have had a series of very remarkable andsearching statements. In so far as they refer to the efforts made by the various partsof the Empire they are highly gratifying. I should like to dwell on the contributionsmade by the Dominions,, by India, and by the Crown Colonies later on. considerable attention has been devoted to an examination of the military situation, and to searchingout the reasons why the hopes of 1917 have not been realised, and how far it is attributable to something over which we have no control, and, what is much more practical, how far our failure to attain the height of our hopes has been attributable to
causes which are removable by an effort now. Sir Robert Borden initiated a momentousdiscussion on that subject. As the representatives of the Dominions, which have contributed so largely to the struggle, have raised such large issues, before we decide what course of action to pursue, I think it is necessary for us to hear the representativesof the Commonwealth of Australia, as they also have made a very considerable contri-bution, and my suggestion to the Imperial War Cabinet is this, that after the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff has made his statement on Tuesday, we should invite thePrime Minister of Australia to continue the discussion.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,June 14, 1918. ;o



</content>
</cab>
