<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/33/0 images: 21-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (59) Copy No.3rd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,. on Thursday, 29th January, 1959, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland..The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd.M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.Also present:Mr. Martin Redmayne, M.P., lord commissioner, Treasury (Items 1-3).Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1959
contents minute no.SubjectPage1Parliament32Cotton33Egypt3Financial Negotiations.4     Indonesia ......5      Dominican Republic6  &apos; The Netherlands......K.L.M. Services to Singapore.7     Middle East      ......Kuwait.
Cotton.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 86thConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Prime Minister said that, although the recent judgment of the Restrictive Practices Court on the price-fixing agreementoperated by the Yarn Spinners&apos; Association would increase thedifficulties of the cotton textile industry in the short term, it should provide an additional stimulus to the eventual reorganisation of theindustry on a sounder and more economic basis. The Cotton board had been assured that any support which the Government could give them in their endeavours to this end was at their disposal. Theyhad, however, indicated that they would prefer themselves to prepare an initial plan of reorganisation for each section of the industrybefore associating the Government with any further discussions. this understanding would be recorded in an exchange of letters which itwould be desirable, subject to the agreement of the Board, to publish.It was important that the Government should, in addition, be seen tobe taking active steps to assist the industry and further consideration should be given to the measures which might be adopted for thispurpose, whether in the form of supplementary Government ordersfor textiles or otherwise.The Cabinet Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Lord President, the Minister of Labour and theEconomic Secretary, Treasury, to examine the scope forspecial action by the Government to assist the textile industry.Egypt.financial negotiations.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 2ndConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that some progress had been made in overcoming the obstacles to the signature of the Anglo-Egyptian financial agreement which had recently beeninitialled in Cairo. The Egyptian Government had now agreed toaccept a British representative in Cairo, with appropriate status and authority, to assist British claimants in assessing the damage sustained by assets which had been sequestrated. But we had still not reached agreement with the Egyptians on the extent to which propertyoriginally sequestrated had subsequently been Egyptianised.Uncertainty on this point would materially affect the adequacy of thecompensation which individual owners of Egyptianised assets would receive, since the owners of sequestrated assets should, under theagreement, recover possession of their property and should not,therefore, be entitled to compensation from the lump sum to be paidby the Egyptian Government. The facts involved appeared to begenuinely in doubt and a further period would be needed in which to clarify them. The simplest course might, therefore, be to suggest tothe Egyptian Government that, if further enquiry revealed that theassumption about the extent of sequestration on which the financial agreement had been based was invalid, the position would need to befurther reviewed by the two Governments and that, in the event of disagreement, we for our part would be prepared to accept the arbitration of Mr. Black, the President of the International Bank for reconstruction and Development.In discussion there was general agreement with this suggestion.The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Foreign Secretary, to arrange for a further attempt to bemade to reach agreement with the Egyptian authorities onParliament. 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.
outstanding points under the provisional Anglo-Egyptianfinancial agreement on the lines indicated by the foreign secretary in their discussion.Indonesia.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 2ndConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Foreign Secretary said that there appeared to be grounds for supposing that the Indonesian Government might launch an attackon Dutch West Guinea in the near future. The sympathies of theWestern Powers would naturally be enlisted on behalf of the dutch government while the Soviet Union would inevitably supportIndonesia. As a result, the tension which we had sought to localisewould be liable to assume an international complexion; and we must seek, in concert with the United States and Australia, to avert this risk. Meanwhile we had agreed with the Dutch Government thatthe difficult question of the supply of arms to Indonesia by theWestern Powers should be further discussed in the North atlantic council.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement.Dominican 5.   The Foreign Secretary said that the Dominican RepublicRepublic. were seeking to place orders in the United Kingdom for the supplyof arms, including 12 patrol ships, and had indicated that, if theywere enabled to do so, they would probably place with british manufacturers additional orders for a considerable quantity of electrical equipment for civil purposes. We should not lightly forgothis opportunity to increase employment in this country and to enlargeour trade. But there were obvious objections to providing arms to adictatorship which was regarded with suspicion in the Caribbean andin Latin America and had given sanctuary to the leaders of theoverthrown Governments of Cuba and the Argentine.In discussion there was general agreement that we should becautious in responding to these overtures. It might be possible tojustify supplying the patrol vessels, provided that they were unarmed,on the ground that they were needed for recognised purposes of customs enforcement. Alternatively, it might be preferable to defera decision for the time being but to offer to review the situationafter an interval, in the hope that the Dominican Government would still be disposed to place the orders for civil equipment in thiscountry. These possibilities would need to be further examined inthe light of the importance of avoiding any action which might increase tension in the West Indies or give the new Cuban Governmentany ground for supposing that we were assisting the DominicanGovernment to promote a counter-revolution in Cuba.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to give further considerationto the extent to which it might be possible, without political embarrassment, to arrange for the Dominican Governmentto place orders in this country for arms and civil equipment.TfaeNetherlands.K.L.M. services to Singapore.(previous reference:C.C.(59)2ndConclusions,Minute 2.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (C. (59) 11) about the services operated by Royal DutchAirlines (K.L.M.) between the Netherlands and Singapore.The Foreign Secretary said that until the Indonesian crisis in late1957 K.L.M. had operated three services a week to Indonesia throughSingapore and two other services through other points. In order toassist them after their exclusion from Indonesia, we had agreedthat all five services might temporarily terminate at Singapore
despite the fact that K.L.M. had previously had no rights of termination at that point. With the agreement of the Dutchauthorities, these services had been reduced to three a week inFebruary 1958, in the light of the decline in the traffic. More recentlyit had become necessary, in accordance with the normal principles governing the grant of air traffic rights, to require a further reduction to one service a week from 1st March, 1959. The Dutch Governmenthad protested against this decision and had suggested that, pending a review of the technical and commercial considerations involved,K.L.M. should continue to operate two services a week to Singaporeuntil 1st November. There was no case for so long a postponement of the reduction in the services. But the prestige of K.L.M. wouldbe a sensitive issue in the forthcoming election in the netherlands and it was for consideration whether, in order to relieve the political embarrassment of the Dutch Government in the immediate future,we should offer some further concession. It might be desirable, forexample, to announce that we were prepared to defer action for afurther month, i.e., to 31st March, and that before that date we would again review with the Dutch authorities the statistical evidence onwhich our decision was based. In that event, however, it would bedesirable to warn the Dutch Government at the outset that we were unlikely to modify that decision at the end of March.In discussion it was suggested that action of this kind would beseen to be dictated by political considerations and that, in terms ofour own civil aviation interests elsewhere, it would be dangerous toallow it to be supposed that we were prepared to decide questionsof traffic rights on other than strictly commercial grounds. other questions of civil aviation policy were at issue between the dutch and ourselves, particularly the extent of the Dutch entitlement to operate a trans-Atlantic service based on London Airport; and if some concession to Dutch opinion was necessary, it would be preferable to suggest that, without initially modifying our decisionon the K.L.M. services to Singapore, we should discuss with theDutch authorities the whole of our relations with them as regardscivil air services. As a result, the Dutch might be persuaded that itwould be to their advantage to accept the proposed reduction in the k.L.M. services to Singapore in return for a greater measure of security as regards their trans-Atlantic services.On the other hand, K.L.M. occupied a unique place in Dutchpolitical sentiment. The Dutch Government had sustained a seriousreverse in Indonesia and, in the difficult situation in which they were now placed, it was not unreasonable that they should expect theWTestern Powers to make some allowance for political considerations in the negotiation of their air traffic rights. For the same reason theywould probably object to entering into comprehensive discussions,the purpose of which would appear to them to be an attempt to reach some general settlement which would involve a diminution of theirtraffic rights as a whole. It might therefore be wiser to offer thema technical discussion confined to the Singapore services alone,particularly since there appeared to be a genuine disagreement on the statistical data involved.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that it wasto our advantage to offer the Dutch Government such politicalsupport as we could provide without any substantial sacrifice of ourown interests. There was little doubt that it would eventually benecessary to require the Dutch authorities to reduce the K.L.M.services to Singapore to one a week. But the second service mightbe allowed to continue for a little longer on the understanding thattechnical discussions would be opened with the Dutch interestsforthwith in an endeavour to secure agreement on an objectivestatement of the commercial considerations involved in the dispute.The offer of such discussions should be made to the Dutch
Government with the minimum of publicity; and we should avoiddrawing attention to the fact that for the time being the secondK.L.M. service would be allowed to continue.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that Royal Dutch Airlines should be allowed, asunobtrusively as possible, to continue to operate for afurther period two air services a week terminating at singapore, on the understanding that technical discussions would be arranged between the British and Dutchauthorities in order to clarify the commercial considerations which we regarded as justifying our decision to require a reduction of these services to one aweek in the near future.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to settle with the Minister ofTransport and Civil Aviation the terms in which the dutch government should be invited to take part in thediscussions indicated in Conclusion (1) above.7. The Foreign Secretary said that it was inevitable that Kuwaitshould gradually develop an international personality of its own.Hitherto we had dissuaded the Ruler from joining the Arab League;but he had recently indicated that he might find it expedient to yieldto internal pressure for the establishment in Kuwait of consular representatives of other Arab States. Such representatives v/ould actas focal points for intrigue against the Ruling-House and the interestsof the United Kingdom; and there could be no guarantee that the ruler would not eventually be compelled to join the Arab League inaddition. The Middle East Committee, who had considered thematter on the previous day, had therefore come to the conclusionthat we should initially seek to maintain the existing situation for aslong as possible but that, if the Ruler felt obliged to make some concession to Arab nationalism, it would be preferable that he should join the Arab League, with whose activities he was already to someextent associated, than that he should accept Consular representatives from other Arab States. The Ruler should now be informed of thisrecommendation; and our final decision should be taken in the lightof his reaction.In discussion there was general agreement with this proposal.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct the political resident, Persian Gulf, to inform the Ruler of Kuwaitthat, while Her Majesty&apos;s Government would deprecateany unnecessary change in the external relations betweenKuwait and foreign States, they would regard it aspreferable, if some concession to local sentiment was inevitable, that it should take the form of accession byKuwait to the Arab League rather than the establishment in Kuwait of Consular representation of other Arab States.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion in the light of the responseof the Ruler to the communication to be made under conclusion (1) above.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,29th January, 1959.MiddSe East.Kuwait.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 80thConclusions,Minute 7.)


</content>
</cab>
