<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/33/0 images: 35-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SSCISETTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1959C.C. (59)5th conclusions copy No.   31CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W.1, on Thursday, 5ih February, 1959, at 4-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Harold WAtkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General. &apos;The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions and national Insurance (Item 2).Mr. Julian Amery, M.P., parliamentary under-Secretary of State for theColonies (Item 1).Mr. C J. M. Alport, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations (Item 1).Sir Edward Boyle, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Education(Item 2).Mr. Martin Redmayne, M.P., lord commissioner, Treasury (Item 1).Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.
contents minute no.                                      subject      Statement on Defence, 1959 ...2     Pensions .........
Pensions.(previous references:C.C. (59) 1stConclusions,Minute 5 andC.C. (58) 87thConclusionsMinute 6.)2. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of memoranda by theChancellor of the Exchequer, the Minister of Defence and theMinister of Pensions (C. (59) 2, 5 and 4) on Service widows&apos; and warwidows&apos; pensions.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had been considering whether it would be desirable to promote early legislation to amend the Pensions (Increase) Act, 1956. Since that year thecost of living had risen by only 7 per cent., compared with the 14 percent, increase between the Acts of 1952 and 1956; and this might suggest that there was relatively little case for a new Pensions(Increase) Act in the near future. On the other hand, there was likelyto be a further increase of 1 or 2 per cent, in the cost of living withinthe coming months. Moreover, pensioners who had retired after 1952did not benefit under the Act of 1956; and in their case, therefore, thecost of living would have risen by considerably more than 8-9 per cent,since their pensions were fixed. If an increase in the pensions of retired public servants was likely in any event to be unavoidabletowards the end of the year, it might be advisable to take advantage ofthe current period of relative stability in costs and prices by introducing the necessary legislation in the near future. If so, theBill might follow broadly the lines of the 1956 Bill, although theincrease should perhaps be weighted in favour of those who had beenlongest retired. In all, some 500,000 people would benefit and, onthe basis of an average increase of the order of 7 per cent., theadditional expenditure involved would amount to about  8 millions a year, of which  2 millions would fall upon local authorities.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were disposed in principle to favour early legislation on this matter. On the other hand, the broad considerations of social justice would need to be weighed against the fact that an increase in the pensions of public servantswould undoubtedly have repercussions on the pensions paid by the nationalised industries and might intensify to some extent the incipientpressure for an increase in National Insurance retirement pensions.The Cabinet then considered the proposals of the Minister ofDefence that pensions at the rate of one-third of their late husbands&apos;pensions should be provided not only for the future widows of men now serving in the Forces but also for the future widows of servicemen now retired; and, in addition, that the pensions of existing service widows should be increased by an average of 10 per cent.The Minister of Defence said that the Government had acceptedthe relevant recommendation of the Advisory Committee on Recruiting(the Grigg Committee) in relation to the widows of men now servingand it would be indefensible not to adopt the same formula for the widows of Servicemen now retired, particularly since the GriggCommittee had intended their recommendation to apply to bothcategories of widow. He was also under growing pressure to grantstatement 1.  The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theon Defence, Minister of Defence (C. (59) 14) covering a draft of the Statement on1959. Defence, 1959.The Cabinet considered the Statement paragraph by paragraphand approved a number of textual amendments.The Cabinet Approved the draft of the Statement on Defence, 1959,subject to the amendments agreed in their discussion.
some increase to existing widows. This might be linked with aPensions (Increase) Bill, although the amount of the increase wouldnot necessarily be the same.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, although it mightbe necessary to consider some improvement in the pensions of existing service widows if a Pensions (Increase) Bill was not introduced in thenear future, any concession in this respect would be liable to haveextensive repercussions and would require careful examination. Itwould be less embarrassing to adopt the proposal of the Minister ofDefence in respect of the future widows of Servicemen now retired,although even this would represent a breach of the principle, whichhad always been maintained hitherto, that improvements in service pensions should be limited to men still serving at the time of their introduction.The Minister of Pensions said that his proposals to grant acomforts allowance of 10s. Od. a week to war widows over the age of70 and to introduce a disregard of 10s. 6d. of war widows&apos; pensions for National Assistance purposes would, if approved, be more appropriately announced in conjunction with any improvement inthe position of Service widows than with a Pensions (Increase) Bill.The Prime Minister summing up the discussion, said that it wouldbe preferable to go no further at this stage than to accept the proposal of the Minister of Defence to extend the application of the GriggCommittee&apos;s recommendation to the future widows of retiredServicemen. This might suitably be announced in the forthcomingWhite Paper on Defence. An increase in the pensions of existing service widows had not been recommended by the Grigg Committeeand this suggestion, together with the Minister of Pensions&apos; proposalsfor war widows, should be considered in greater detail in the context of a further discussion of the desirability of introducing early legislation to amend the Pensions (Increase) Act.The Cabinet (1) Authorised the Minister of Defence to announce in theforthcoming Statement on Defence, 1959, that theGovernments decision that in future the widows of servicemen would receive pensions at the rate of one-thirdof their late husbands&apos; retired pay would apply both tothe widows of men now serving and to the widows of menalready retired.(2) Agreed to resume at a subsequent meeting their discussionof:-(i) the case for early legislation to amend the Pensions(Increase) Act, 1956;(ii) the proposal in C. (59) 5 that some increase shouldbe made in the pensions of existing Service widows;(iii) the proposals in C. (59) 4 for improvements in thepensions of war widows.(3) Invited the Minister of Defence to settle with the Chancellorof the Exchequer the terms of interim reply to any demandfor a public statement on the.pensions of existing Servicewidows.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,6th February, 1959.


</content>
</cab>
