<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/33/0 images: 85-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (59)12th conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1, onThursday, 26th February, 1959 at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home department and Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService (Items 6-9).The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. D. Ormsby-Gore,M.P., Minister of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 1-4).Mr. J. D. Profumo, M.P., Minister ofState for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.The Right Hon. The Earl of Perth,Minister of State for Colonial Affairs(Items 6-9).The Right Hon. Sir Reginald Manning-ham-Buller, Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Items 3^4).Mr. F. J. Erroll, M.P., economic secretary, Treasury (Item 5).Secretariat :Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.Mr. J. S. Orme.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1959
contents minute no. subject     Pariiament      ............2     Prime Ministers Visit to Moscow3     Guy Burgess    ............4     Alan Nunn May        .........5      Egypt.........Financial Negotiations6     Indonesia        ............7     Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland8     Cyprus   ...      ............Amnesty TermsArchbishop Makarios9     Industrial Disputes     .........London Airport
primeministers visit to moscow.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 1ConclusionsMinute 10.)*2. The Home Secretary said that as a result of his initial discussions with the Soviet leaders in Moscow, the Prime Minister had formed theimpression that the Soviet Government were still obsessed by the riskof encirclement and were particularly apprehensive of a revival ofGerman power. They also believed that, although the Westernlth Powers did not wish to precipitate a war, they had deliberately createdan atmosphere of international tension and had hoped that they couldturn to their own advantage the internal divisions among the soviet leaders. Mr. Khrushchev was anxious that the Western governments should realise that they had been mistaken in entertaining expectationsof this kind. He had shown no inclination to modify his earlier proposals that Berlin should be declared a free city and that peace treaties should now be negotiated with the two German Governments.He had continued to maintain that questions such as the reunificationof Germany were separate issues, which should not be linked withthe future of Berlin; and he had expressed the suspicion that theWestern Powers, by seeking to insist on a comprehensive discussion ofall outstanding issues about Germany, were seeking to involve theSoviet Union in detailed and protracted negotiations which would preclude any simple and rapid solution of the immediate problem of berlin. The Prime Minister had indicated in reply that, if the policyof the Soviet Government was really as inflexible as Mr. Khrushchevhad indicated, the position was serious.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Since the opening of the discussions both Mr. Khrushchevand President Eisenhower had made public statements reaffirming,without any substantial modification, their respective policies towards germany. It was still possible that the Soviet leaders would modify their intransigent attitude during the later stages of the discussions.They were not likely to do so, however, until the last possible moment(b) Public opinion in this country was becoming aware that anyexpansion of trade between the United Kingdom and the soviet union would depend on our importing Soviet oil in greater quantitiesand that the main difficulty in the way of an arrangement on theselines lay in the reluctance of the oil companies to co-operate in any scheme which might reduce their profit margins. In these circum-stances the Government would be liable to find it increasingly difficult to defend a failure to reach a satisfactory understanding withthe Soviet Union about trade.(c) The Prime Minister had conveyed to President Eisenhower,General de Gaulle and Dr. Adenauer his impression ofMr. Khrushchev&apos;s general attitude. It was for consideration whetherthe other members of the Commonwealth should now be informed, inappropriate terms, of the course of the discussions so far.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Home Secretary to send, on their behalf, a message of good wishes to the Prime Minister, emphasisingtheir continuing concern for the success of his missiondespite the initially discouraging response of the soviet leaders.(2) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary, in consultation withthe Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Ormsby-Gore), to arrange for appropriate messages to be sentto the other members of the Commonwealth, informing* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.secret parliament. 1.  The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.
them of the course of the Prime Ministers discussions withthe Soviet leaders.(3) Invited the President of the Board of Trade to inform thePrime Minister of the implications of the increasing publicawareness in this country of the extent to which an Anglo-Soviet trade agreement would depend on our increasing our imports of Soviet oil.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of State for Foreign Affairs (C. (59) 35) about Guy Burgess.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Ormsby-Gore)said that it had now been confirmed that insufficient evidence was available to enable the authorities to prosecute Burgess if he returnedto the United Kingdom. Moreover it would be impossible to delayhis entry into the country for any length of time on the ground thathis identity was uncertain. Burgess had now sought from the PrimeMinister in Moscow an assurance that, if he visited his mother in thiscountry for a month, he would be free to return to the Soviet Unionat the end of this period. The Prime Minister had suggested that heshould defer his answer until his own visit to Moscow was drawing toa close, and that he should then confine himself to a statement that theGovernment were not prepared to give Burgess any travel facilities.In discussion there was general agreement with this proposal. Itmight, however, be appropriate to inform the Prime Minister that,since Burgess could in fact enter this country without difficulty evenif we refused him travel facilities, our refusal would have to be defended, if necessary, on grounds of public policy. If, therefore, itwas necessary to reply to Burgess at all, it might be desirable to add a warning that the Government had no power to give him the assurancefor which he had asked. For example, there was no means of preventing a private individual from prosecuting him forhomosexuality. Nor could the authorities be expected to refrain from instituting proceedings if further evidence of an offence underthe Official Secrets Acts became available while he was in this country.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C. (59) 35.(2) Invited the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs to informthe Prime Minister in Moscow of the lines on which itwas suggested that he should reply to the application byGuy Burgess for a safe conduct to enable him to visit theUnited Kingdom.Guy Burgess.(previous reference :C.C. (59) 10thConclusions.Minute 5.)Alan NunnMay.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 10thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Ormsby-Gore)said that it had now been confirmed that Dr. Alan Nunn May was nolonger associated with subversive activities. There were therefore no grounds on which we could justify a refusal to issue to him the passport for which he had applied.The Cabinet Agreed that the application by Dr. Alan Nunn May for apassport should now be granted.Egypt.financial negotiations.(previous reference :C.C. (59) 11thConclusions,Minute 1.)5.   The Cabinet had before them:  (i) A Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer to which was annexed a draft of the statement to be made in Parliament when theAnglo-Egyptian Financial Agreement was signed, together with adraft of Notes for Supplementary Questions (C. (59) 36): \(ii) A Note by the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs(Mr. Profumo) on the extent to which it might be desirable to provideassistance to owners of property in Egypt in order to enable them
to recover their assets after the signature of the Financial Agreement(C. (59) 37).The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that Mr. Black, thePresident of the International Bank, had informed him by telephonefrom Cairo that the Egyptian Government had now agreed thatbuilt-up land should be treated as sequestrated, not Egyptianised,property. Since this concession should be to our advantage, inrelation to the Smouha estates, it should make the Agreement more easily defensible to public opinion. Subject, therefore, to, any furtherconsideration which might be necessary in the light of the more detailed message which Mr. Black had promised to send, we now had no option but to sign the Agreement forthwith; and theEconomic Secretary, Treasury, should proceed to Cairo as soon aspossible for this purpose.In discussion it was suggested that we should not finally commit ourselves to signing the Agreement without more precise knowledgeof the extent of the modification in the interpretation of theAgreement which Mr. Black had succeeded in obtaining. The draft parliamentary statement annexed to C. (59) 36 necessarily referred tothe difference of opinion on this matter which had developed betweenthe Egyptian Government and ourselves and indicated that we had agreed that signature of the Agreement could now take place in thelight of &quot; further information &quot; which had been provided by theEgyptian authorities to Mr. Black. It would have been preferable that the Egyptian Government should have offered us some writtenassurance about the manner in which the Agreement would be interpreted in relation to the various categories of land involved. Butif, as seemed likely, they were not prepared to offer more than an oralundertaking about their intentions, the Government would not find iteasy to convince the House of Commons that an assurance of this nature was sufficiently valid to justify their signing the Agreementunless they were able to explain in some detail the nature of the&quot; further information&quot; which Mr. Black had now obtained. Inparticular, they would be exposed to the criticism that they had accepted a payment of  27^ millions by the Egyptian government without knowing with certainty the precise total of the claims whichwould have to be admitted against this sum. On the other hand, theGovernment had agreed with Mr. Black that his present visit to Cairowould be a preliminary to the signature of the Agreement; and,whatever might be the exact form of the understanding which he had reached with the Egyptian Government, they could not now withholdtheir signature without breaking with Mr. Black himself. While,therefore, it might be desirable that the Economic Secretary, beforesigning the Agreement, should verify with Mr. Black personally theresult of his discussions with the Egyptian authorities, he should beauthorised thereafter to sign it, provided that the text remained aswe had hitherto understood it to be.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) The draft Parliamentary statement indicated that the claimedvalue of the sequestrated properties which would be returned to theirowners, was well over  100 millions. But it did not disclose that thevalue of the Egyptianised properties, in respect of which the egyptian government would pay a lump sum of  27^ millions, was estimated to be of the order of  35-45 millions. It might be necessary for theGovernment to admit this fact; and in that event there was advantage in retaining the reference to the value of the sequestrated assets, as indicating the very considerable amount of British property whichwould be recovered under the Agreement. On the other hand, toindicate the value of the sequestrated assets but not the value of theEgyptianised assets might merely invite suspicion of the adequacy of
the sum of  27^ millions; and it was for consideration whether itwould be wiser to omit from the statement any estimates of value,both for the sequestrated and for the Egyptianised properties.(b) It would be preferable, in the concluding words of the draft statement, to refer merely to &quot; the settlement which has now beenreached &quot; rather than to &quot; the satisfactory outcome which has nowbeen reached.&quot;(c) Our objective should be to sign the Agreement on28th February and to inform Parliament of its terms on 2nd March.It was important that the White Paper, containing the text of thevarious documents involved, should be available when the statement&apos;was made. The Egyptian authorities should, if possible, be dissuadedfrom allowing the details of the Agreement to become known untilParliament had been informed.(d) The Agreement might be critically received by publicopinion; and pressure was liable to develop for supplementarycompensation to be provided from the Exchequer. Such pressure would need to be resisted for as long as possible. On the other hand the Government should adopt as generous and sympathetic an attitude as possible towards requests (ry owners of property in Egyptfor assistance in recovering their assets. For example, they mightundertake to pay the fares of individuals who would need to visitEgypt, at least in those cases where hardship would otherwise result.It was also for consideration whether we should offer assistance to persons who found it necessary to retain the services of an agent inorder to prosecute their claims to recover their property, to dispose of unwanted assets and so forth. Messrs. Toplis and Harding had expressed their willingness to act in this capacity; and it might bedesirable for the Government to contribute to some extent to theexpenditure involved. There was no case, however, for the provisionof free legal aid to claimants. Legal advice would be available to theowners of assets both from the British Property in Egypt Section inLondon and from the Property Office in Cairo. This should suffice to meet all reasonable needs; and it would be inadvisable for theGovernment to encourage ill-founded litigation against themselves by offering to pay the expenses involved.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to inform the HomeSecretary of the further information to be received fromMr. Black, the President of the International Bank, of theextent to which the latter had succeeded in clarifying thedispute with the Egyptian Government about theinterpretation of the provisional Anglo-Egyptian financial agreement in relation to certain categories of land.(2) Subject to such further action as might be necessary in thelight of Conclusion (1) above, invited the Chancellor of theExchequer to arrange for the Economic Secretary,Treasury, to proceed to Cairo and, after verifying withMr. Black the result of his latest negotiations with theEgyptian Government, to sign the provisional Anglo-Egyptian Financial Agreement on behalf of the UnitedKingdom Government.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to announce theterms of the Agreement in the House of Commons on 2nd March in a statement on the lines of the draft annexed to C. (59) 36, as amended in their discussion.(4) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for a white Paper, containing the documents comprised in theAgreement, to be presented to Parliament simultaneously with his statement on 2nd March.(5) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Profumo),
Indonesia.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 3rdConclusions.Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Profumo) (C. (59) 38) aboutIndonesia.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Profumo) said thatit would be necessary to seek to obtain endorsement by the north atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) of our proposal to grantlicences for the export of arms to Indonesia unless the suppliesinvolved were likely to increase to a dangerous extent the offensivepotential of the Indonesian forces. This policy would be unwelcome to the Dutch Government; and there would therefore be advantage in conveying to them an assurance (the text of which had beenapproved by the Prime Minister at an earlier stage) that, although wecould not enter into a commitment to provide them with military support, we would do everything within our power to assist them inother appropriate ways if the Indonesian Government were to resort to force in prosecuting their claim to Netherlands New Guinea. Atthe same time we should inform the Indonesian Government that wehad noted their declaration that they intended to abstain from the useof force; and that we counted on them to maintain this policy. Theterms of these statements had been disclosed to the Governments ofAustralia and the United States. The Australian Prime Minister had replied that the Commonwealth Government fully appreciated thepractical nature of our proposed assurance to the Netherlands. TheState Department had noted our proposals; and the fact that theyhad raised no objection could be taken as an indication of UnitedStates support, having regard to the similar assurance which theUnited States Government had themselves given to the Dutch. Ourmessages to the Dutch and Indonesian Governments would beprivate; but the former might wish to make some public reference in the Netherlands Parliament to the fact that they had receivedcertain assurances from the United Kingdom Government.In discussion there was general agreement with these proposals.It was suggested that it would be consistent with our proposed policy on the supply of arms to Indonesia that we should now restore to someextent export credits guarantee cover in respect of exports to indonesia. In the light of the poor credit standing of the Indonesian government, however, this proposal would need to be examined in greater detail.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C. (59) 38.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theCommonwealth Secretary, to give further consideration tothe desirability of providing export credits guaranteecover, in certain cases, for exports to Indonesia.to give further consideration to the extent to which theGovernment should undertake to provide assistance to owners of property in Egypt in making the necessary arrangements in relation to their assets and to settle a formof words in which the Governments decision on thisquestion could, if necessary, be announced during the debate on the Agreement.
Indonesia.(previous reference :C.C. (59) 3rdConclusions.Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Profumo) (C. (59) 38) aboutIndonesia.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Profumo) said thatit would be necessary to seek to obtain endorsement by the north atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) of our proposal to grantlicences for the export of arms to Indonesia unless the suppliesinvolved were likely to increase to a dangerous extent the offensivepotential of the Indonesian forces. This policy would be unwelcome to the Dutch Government; and there would therefore be advantage in conveying to them an assurance (the text of which had beenapproved by the Prime Minister at an earlier stage) that, although wecould not enter into a commitment to provide them with military support, we would do everything within our power to assist them inother appropriate ways if the Indonesian Government were to resort to force in prosecuting their claim to Netherlands New Guinea. Atthe same time we should inform the Indonesian Government that wehad noted their declaration that they intended to abstain from the useof force; and that we counted on them to maintain this policy. Theterms of these statements had been disclosed to the Governments ofAustralia and the United States. The Australian Prime Minister had replied that the Commonwealth Government fully appreciated thepractical nature of our proposed assurance to the Netherlands. TheState Department had noted our proposals; and the fact that theyhad raised no objection could be taken as an indication of UnitedStates support, having regard to the similar assurance which theUnited States Government had themselves given to the Dutch. Ourmessages to the Dutch and Indonesian Governments would beprivate; but the former might wish to make some public reference in the Netherlands Parliament to the fact that they had receivedcertain assurances from the United Kingdom Government.In discussion there was general agreement with these proposals.It was suggested that it would be consistent with our proposed policy on the supply of arms to Indonesia that we should now restore to someextent export credits guarantee cover in respect of exports to indonesia. In the light of the poor credit standing of the Indonesian government, however, this proposal would need to be examined in greater detail.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C. (59) 38.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theCommonwealth Secretary, to give further consideration tothe desirability of providing export credits guaranteecover, in certain cases, for exports to Indonesia.to give further consideration to the extent to which theGovernment should undertake to provide assistance to owners of property in Egypt in making the necessary arrangements in relation to their assets and to settle a formof words in which the Governments decision on thisquestion could, if necessary, be announced during the debate on the Agreement.
Federation of rhodesia and nyasaland.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 81stConclusions,Minute 8.)7. The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said that in thelight of the current disturbances in the Federation of Rhodesia and nyasaland, he had decided to postpone his visit to Nyasaland for constitutional discussions. But he would adhere to his intention to visit East Africa in the following week; and it might be possible for him to proceed to Nyasaland thereafter. The situation in theFederation was confused: a state of emergency had been declaredin Southern Rhodesia and similar action might shortly becomeunavoidable in Nyasaland.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that there was some reason to suppose that the recent riots in the Federation had been carefully planned and had been deliberately directed againstEuropeans. The white people in Nyasaland, whose safety remained the direct responsibility of the United Kingdom Government, mightbe in some danger; and steps should be taken urgently to ascertain what reinforcements could, if necessary, be made available to thesecurity forces. In particular, it was for consideration whethercertain helicopters and light aircraft, which were due to be withdrawnfrom Cyprus, should be transferred forthwith to Nairobi.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval of the decision of the Minister ofState for Colonial Affairs to defer his visit to Nyasalandfor constitutional discussions.(2) Invited the Minister of State for Colonial Affairs, inconsultation with the Commonwealth Secretary and theMinister of Defence, to submit to the Home Secretary that day an appreciation of the security situation in theFederation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland together with proposals for the despatch of such reinforcements asappeared to be necessary.Cyprus.(previous reference :C.C. (59) 11thConclusions,Minute 2.)AmnestyTerms.Archbishop Makarios.8. The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs informed theCabinet that the EOKA leader, Colonel Grivas, had made it known that he would not undertake to discontinue his terrorist activities in cyprus unless satisfactory arrangements were made foT the future ofhimself and his followers. The Greek Foreign Minister, M. Averoff,had suggested that he might visit Cyprus in order personally to escortColonel Grivas back to Greece. It would be desirable to convinceM. Averoff of the objections to any suggestion that terrorists shouldbe allowed to leave the Island with a show of honour and ceremony;but, since it was desirable that the EOKA leaders should be removed from Cyprus as soon as possible, it might be advisable to include inthe forthcoming statement about a general amnesty an undertaking that arrangements would be made for these men to leave the Islandunder safe conduct, on condition that they would not return withoutthe permission of the Government of Cyprus. It would be necessary,however, to ascertain that this proposal would be acceptable to theTurkish Government.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that, subject to the concurrence of the Governor of cyprus and the Turkish Government, the EOKA leadersmight be allowed to leave Cyprus under safe conduct,provided that they undertook not to return to the Islandwithout the consent of the Government of Cyprus.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Profumo) said thatM. Averoff had suggested that selected Greek students should be sentto Cyprus to take part in the public celebrations in connexion withthe return of Archbishop Makarios to the Island. The TurkishGovernment had raised no objection to this proposal, provided thatthe number of students involved was small.   It now appeared,
industrial disputes.(previous reference :C.C. (58) 63rdConclusions,Minute 5.)london airport.The Cabinet (2) Agreed that no objection need be raised to the proposal ofthe Greek Government to send 800 Greek students to cyprus to take part in the celebrations in connexion withthe return of Archbishop Makarios to the Island.(3) Invited the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs(Mr. Profumo) to arrange for the Turkish Government tobe informed of the circumstances in which we hadacquiesced in this proposal.9. The Minister of Transport and Civil Aviation said that theBritish Overseas Airways Corporation were proceeding to give effect tothe recommendations of the Committee of Inquiry into the causes and circumstances of the recent dispute at London Airport. Action hadalready been taken to ensure that shop stewards would not hence-forward devote the whole of their working time to trade union affairs;and the Corporation intended to take further steps to promoteincreased efficiency in their engineering department. It had beenestablished that the cost of maintenance work carried out by thedepartment was twice as great as that of the Corporation^competitors; and, after an expert investigation and full consultationwith the staff organisations, the Corporation proposed to declare2,000 posts redundant. The consequent dismissals would, however,be spread over a period, and compensation would be paid where appropriate.In discussion there was general agreement that the corporation were right to proceed with the proposed reorganisation. It waspossible, however, that subversive elements would take this opportunity to renew their attempts to disrupt the working of london airport, and the situation should be kept under close review.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Transport and Civil Aviation tokeep under review developments at London Airportfollowing the action to be taken by the British overseas airways Corporation to reorganise their engineeringdepartment.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,26th February, 1959.however, that arrangements were being made for some 800 studentsto leave for Cyprus. M. Averoff considered that they would not constitute a significant addition to the very large number of Cypriotswho were expected to congregate in order to welcome the Archbishopon his return; and he was prepared to ask the Bishop of Kitium toemphasise to all those concerned in the celebrations the importanceof exercising proper restraint on this occasion. In these circumstances it would be difficult for us to sustain an objection to the proposal; butit would be desirable to explain to the Turkish Government that we,no less than they, had been misinformed about the scale of the enterprise.


</content>
</cab>
