<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/33/0 images: 165-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (59)23rd conclusions copy No. 3 2CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 14th April, 1959, at 11 am.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon.. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon, Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd,M.P., Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right  Hon.  Ernest  Marples,   The    Right   Hon.    Sir    ReginaldM.P., Postmaster-General (Item 6).        Manningham-Buller,   Q.C.,   M.P.,Attorney-General (Item 8).The Right Hon. W. R. Milligan, Q.C.,   The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,M.P., Lord Advocate (Item 8). Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Mr. C. J. M. Alport, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations (Item 7).Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. F. A. Bishop.Mr. M. Reed.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1959
contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1     Germany        ...............     ......       3Discussions with French Ministers.2     Disarmament    .....................       3Geneva Conference on Nuclear Tests.3     Anglo-Soviet Trade    ..................       34     Parliament............     .........      45     Cotton........................       46     Post Office      ...      ...      ......      ...     ....... 4Future Status.7     International Development Association     ......... 68     John Waters    ......      ......... ... 7
Germany.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 22ndConclusions,Minute 2.)discussions with french ministers.Disarmament.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 81stConclusions,Minute 3.)geneva conference on nuclear Tes&apos;.s.Anglo-SovietIf  Trade.* I. The Foreign Secretary made a brief report to the Cabinet onthe discussions which had been held with the Prime Minister and theForeign Secretary of France during their visit to London.In these private bilateral conversations the French Ministers hadnot maintained inflexibly the declared official position of the FrenchGovernment on the Berlin problem. They had been prepared todiscuss constructive proposals for a new agreement on Berlin and had seemed ready to contemplate the possibility that some concessionsmight be made (e.g., on the use of West Berlin as a base for espionageand propaganda) as the price for a new agreement supported by widerinternational guarantees. This suggested that in the forthcominginternational negotiations the French would be more accommodatingthan might be supposed from their published declarations, which hadevidently been made mainly for the purpose of showing solidaritywith the West German Government. It was also clear that theFrench Ministers accepted the need for a conference of Heads of governments and would co-operate in treating the forthcoming meeting of Foreign Ministers as a means of preparing for such aconference. There now seemed little risk that the French wouldprecipitate a crisis in Europe by taking an unduly rigid position in thenegotiations between Foreign Ministers.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.2. The Foreign Secretary said that, in order to forestall a freshRussian initiative, the United States Government had thought itexpedient that new proposals for the regulation of nuclear tests shouldbe put before the Geneva Conference when it reassembled on13th April. After consultation with the United Kingdom government they had reaffirmed their readiness to proceed with the considerationof a comprehensive agreement if the Soviet Government wouldabandon their insistence on a veto and adopt a less intransigentattitude on voting procedures; but they had proposed that, if theSoviet Government were not prepared to come to terms on that basis,the Conference should instead proceed to conclude a limitedagreement for the prohibition of nuclear tests in the atmosphere, upto a distance of 50 kilometres from the earth. A limited agreementof that kind could be enforced without elaborate control machinery,and would suffice to control those tests which were most dangerous to health ; and research could be continued into the possibilities ofestablishing an effective system of control over tests made eitherunderground or at higher altitudes in space. The initial reaction ofthe Soviet delegation at Geneva to this proposal had beenunfavourable ; but this was only to be expected and they werepresumably seeking instructions on it from their Government. Greatpublic interest was being shown in the work of the geneva conference ; and, if it failed to lead to any international agreement,it was important that the responsibility for this failure should be seen to rest with the Soviet Government.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.3. The President of the Board of Trade made a report to theCabinet on the results of the discussions which he had been holdingwith the Soviet Ambassador in London on the proposal that a tradeSECRET
4SECIrlETmission from the. United Kingdom should visit the Soviet Union. Inthe course of those discussions he had made it plain that the UnitedKingdom could not change their system of trading for the purpose ofincreasing the volume of Anglo-Soviet trade ; that they were notprepared to authorise the import of oil from the Soviet Union ; andthat, if the trade between the two countries could not be balanced,the gap must be bridged by ordinary commercial credits. recent experience had shown that there was scope for increasing the volumeof Anglo-Soviet trade on normal credit terms. During the past week the Soviet Government had placed large orders with two firms in theUnited Kingdom on commercial medium-credit terms. In the lightof these preparatory conversations in London the Soviet Governmentwere anxious that a mission from the United Kingdom should visit the Soviet Union, under the leadership of a senior Minister ; and itwas desirable that we should now inform the Soviet Government thatwe were prepared to send such a mission as soon as the necessarypractical arrangements could be completed.After discussion it was agreed that this mission should be led atthe outset by the President of the Board of Trade, though his placemight be taken in the later stages by a junior Minister ; and that themission should include at least two representatives of UnitedKingdom industry.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary and the President of the Boardof Trade to concert the detailed arrangements for thedespatch of a trade mission from the United Kingdom tothe Soviet Union.Parliament. 4.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Cotton.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 22ndConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The President of the Board of Trade said that, in the lightof informal soundings of the Chairman of the Cotton Board, he had now met representatives of the cotton industry. He had informedthem that the Government were prepared to make grants towardsthe cost of the elimination of redundant capacity and of re-equipment and modernisation to the extent of 66-f per cent, for redundancy and25 per cent, for re-equipment ; and that, on the basis of estimatesprovided by the industry, such Government assistance would be ofthe order of  40 millions. The representatives of the cotton industry had expressed the view that the Governments offer was reasonable and practicable and had undertaken to report it to their ExecutiveCommittee. There seemed to be a reasonable prospect that theindustry would accept the offer: it was hoped that their decisions would be known by the end of the week. Meanwhile the necessary legislation was being drafted.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the President of the Boardof Trade.Post Office.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 53rdConclusions,Minute 1.)Future Status.6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Postmaster-General (C. (59) 67)on the future status of the Post Office.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the changes whichhe and the Postmaster-General now proposed would emphasise thecommercial nature of the Post Office&apos;s functions and were a logical
development of the measure of financial independence granted to itin 1955. The central point of the proposals was the establishmentof a statutory trading fund, managed by the Postmaster-General, whoalone would be accountable for it to Parliament. There would be noannual authorisation of Post Office expenditure by Parliamentthrough Estimates. But Parliamentary control would be retainedthrough authorisation of the salaries of Post Office Ministers, scrutinyand debate of the Post Office accounts and annual report,authorisation of new capital by Money Bills, and control over all tariffchanges by negative resolution. These changes would require legislation, which could not be introduced during the current session ;but it was proposed that a White Paper describing the changes shouldbe published at an early date.The Postmaster-General said that the proposed changes would contribute materially to the efficiency of the Post Office as a tradingconcern by dispensing with Treasury control over details ofexpenditure, and with the need to maintain two sets of accounts andto prepare detailed estimates which bore no realistic relation to the trading functions of the Post Office. They would, moreover, avoid the misleading impression given by the Budget statement, where anycash surplus held by the Post Office had at present to be shown as a profit.Discussion showed that there was considerable support for theprinciple of the changes proposed, although it was suggested that a body with the status of a public corporation but staffed by civilservants might be regarded as somewhat anomalous. On the otherhand it was recognised that the proposals involved constitutionalinnovations which might prove unpopular with Parliament: theywould, in particular, involve a complete departure from the twolong-established principles that Government receipts from any sourcemust be paid into the Consolidated Fund and that no government expenditure may be incurred without the specific authority ofParliament. The suggestion that the Postmaster-Generats powers todraw on the new trading fund should lapse annually unless renewedby affirmative resolution might mitigate this objection but might not satisfy Parliament, especially since the Governments supporters were at present inclined to press for more, rather than less, control overnationalised industries. Moreover, since the proposed changes would be regarded as an important indication of the Governmentsthinking on the future of the nationalised industries, they ought tobe harmonised with the proposals which were in process of beingworked out for changes in the organisation of particular nationalised industries and in the relation of the nationalised industries with theGovernment and with Parliament.In further discussion it was pointed out that the  5 millionscontributed annually by the Post Office to the Exchequer representedapproximately the sum which, but for its exemption, the Post office would pay by way of national taxation of all forms. The alternativesuggested by the Chancellor of the Exchequer was that the Post office should be required to contribute to the Exchequer a sumproportionate to that paid in direct taxation by the general run ofprivate industry and commerce, measured in terms of its turnover.It was agreed that this question and the future basis of payment foragency services provided by or to the Post Office should be further considered independently of the main issue.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that there could be no question of effecting any major changes in the status of thePost Office during the present Parliament. Any changes announcedas part of the Governments future programme must be related totheir proposals for the nationalised industries and should be furtherworked out in co-ordination with those proposals as they developed.
InternationalDevelopmentAssociation.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 17thConclusions,Minute 5.)The Cabinet Invited the Lord Privy SeaJ, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer (or the Financial Secretary, ^.Treasury), the Minister of Labour, the Minister of Power, 0&quot;*the Minister of Transport, the Postmaster-General and theChief Whip, to consider the proposals in C. (59) 67 for thefuture status of the Post Office, in the light of the examination which was already being made of theorganisation of the nationalised industries.7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (59) 65) discussing further theadvantages and disadvantages of United Kingdom membership ofthe proposed International Development Association.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it was not yet clear whether the Secretary of the United States Treasury, Mr. Anderson,would recommend that the Association should be established on thescale originally proposed, namely, with an initial capital contributiontotalling $2,000 millions or on half that scale. The United StatesState Department favoured the larger scheme and hoped that theUnited Kingdom Government would support it ; and it might wellbe to our advantage to do so. Our main objective should be toencourage the United States Government to maintain the outflow of dollars to the rest of the world, despite the domestic pressure thatwas being brought to bear on them to decrease it. It was true that,in the light of our present and prospective commitments, and of theneed to maintain the level of the reserves, we should aim to earn acurrent surplus of the order of  450 millions per annum for the years1960-62. But the establishment of the proposed Association oughtto enable us to gain in additional exports more than the amount ofour initial contribution. This hope was borne out by our experienceof the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development,which had so far lent to the Commonwealth as a whole more than five times the amount of the United Kingdom subscription, and also by the fact that the proportion of United States Mutual Aid fundsspent on American goods had steadily fallen ever recent years, whilethe proportion of such funds spent on United Kingdom goods had increased.In discussion the following main points were made:  (a) Colonial territories had not obtained as much advantage from the International Bank as the independent commonwealth countries. But, if we stipulated that the principles adopted forlending by the proposed Association should be such as to ensure thatColonial territories received a reasonable share of the developmentfunds, and if we reserved the right to review the arrangements if this result was not in practice achieved, the position of Colonial territories under the Association should be adequately safeguarded.(b) We had already undertaken substantial commitments for capital assistance to Commonwealth Governments. It would beregrettable if our ability to meet these commitments was jeopardisedby the effort of participating in the proposed Association. * But, asit was expected that our balance of payments would in fact be assisted by the additional exports which we should gain by its establishment, there was good reason to hope that this danger wouldnot arise.(c) The establishment of the Association would enable us to   Cavoid contributing more to the Special United Nations Fund for economic Development. Mr. Anderson shared the view that the funds operated by this organisation would not be used to the best advantage.
8. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theSecretary of State for Scotland (C. (59) 66) covering the Report ofthe Tribunal appointed to enquire into the allegation of assault onJohn Waters and the action taken in connexion therewith by theCaithness police.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that, as regards the alleged assault, the Tribunal had found that there was not sufficient evidence on v/hich the two constables concerned could have been convicted by a Court. But they had found that Constable Gunn hadstruck the boy a biow of moderate force and that this action, althoughtaken under provocation, was wrong. The Tribunal had also expressed disapproval of certain other actions of the constables inconnexion with the alleged assault, and had found, on possiblysomewhat slender evidence, that Constable Harper had wronglyattempted to get the allegations withdrawn for a money payment.As regards the action taken by the Caithness police authorities, theTribunal had found that this had been all that it should have been.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that he proposed to publish the Report and evidence on Wednesday, 15th April, and tomake a short statement to Parliament summarising the findings.This raised the question what, if anything, should be said about thepossibility of disciplinary proceedings against the constablesconcerned. Whether such proceedings should be instituted was amatter for the Deputy Chief Constable to decide, on behalf of theChief Constable as the disciplinary authority. He himself, as secretary of State, was the appellate authority. A decision aboutinstituting disciplinary proceedings was complicated by the fact thatthe findings of the Tribunal were, at least in part, based on evidence given by the constables on an assurance by the Lord Advocate thatcriminal, proceedings would not be brought against them in respectof their conduct in relation to the matters which the Tribunal hadinvestigated. It was also complicated by the fact that in circularsissued in 1943 and 1955 the Scottish Home Department had advisedpolice authorities that, where it was decided that there was insufficientevidence to justify the institution of criminal proceedings, the disciplinary authority should not bring disciplinary proceedings inrespect of the same offence. Although this did not wholly exclude the possibility of disciplinary proceedings, it made it very difficult totake any action to advise the police authorities about the institution of any such proceedings. It might be that the Chief Constable, orthe Deputy Chief Constable on his behalf, would seek advice fromthe Chairman of the Association of Scottish Chief Constables. Butin all the circumstances, and bearing in mind his appellate function,the Secretary of State did not himself propose to give any guidance in this matter to the police authorities.John Waters.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 9thConclusions,Minute 2.)The Prime Minister said that, with a view to maintaining theoutflow of United States capital, and to avoid the danger that future&apos;0 United States loans might be more closely tied to the purchase ofUnited States goods, it seemed to be in the interests of the UnitedKingdom to participate in the establishment of the proposedAssociation on the lines suggested by the Chancellor of theExchequer. The scale of the project, and of the United kingdom contribution to it, should be left for later decision in the light of thefurther discussions with Mr. Anderson in the course of his forthcoming visit to this country.The Cabinet Approved the recommendations made in C. (59) 65.
The Lord Privy Seal said that, in view of the difficulty of explaining the position about the possibility of disciplinaryproceedings, it was doubtful whether a formal statement toParliament should be made. It might be better for the Report to bepublished on Thursday, 16th April, and for this to be disclosed inthe course of the Business Statement which he would make in theHouse of Commons that day. Any necessary guidance could begiven subsequently to Lobby correspondents.In discussion it was pointed out that, in view of the assurancegiven to the two constables by the Lord Advocate at the Tribunalsrequest, there could be no question of criminal proceedings against them. It might strictly be possible for disciplinary action to be takenin respect of the constables&apos; behaviour, other than the allegedassault ; but, apart from the fact that the assurance given by theLord Advocate might be regarded as applicable also to disciplinary action, there would be a general recognition that it would not now bepossible for the constables to secure a fair hearing before adisciplinary authority. It was therefore for consideration whetheradvice could be given to the Chairman of the Association of ScottishChief Constables to ensure that the Deputy Chief Constable shouldhave it in mind that the Tribunals Report made it virtually impossiblefor the constables to obtain a fair hearing in disciplinary proceedings.There was, however, no easy way of giving any such advice.Moreover, there was a reasonable prospect that the police authorities would, of their own accord, decide not to take disciplinary action.It was the general view of the Cabinet that, on balance, it would be best not to give any advice about this matter to the police authorities concerned.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the Tribunals Report and evidence should bepublished on Thursday, 16th April, and that this shouldbe disclosed in the Business Statement to be made inParliament on that day.(2) Agreed that no advice about the institution of disciplinaryproceedings should be given to the police authorities concerned, but that it should be made clear to Lobbycorrespondents that the question of such proceedings wasa matter for decision by the Deputy Chief Constable onbehalf of the Chief Constable as the disciplinary authority.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,14th April, 1959.


</content>
</cab>
