<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/33/0 images: 353-358</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1959C.C. (59)50th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 1st September, 1959, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Harold W Atkinson,M.P.,   Minister  of  Transport and civil Aviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.! The Right Hon. viscount lord Chancellor.Kilmuir,The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.Also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. M. Reed.
contents minute no.SubjectPage1Visit of President Eisenhower to Europe32Economic Situation43     Crime    ..................      ......       4Approved Schools.Prisons.4     Legislative Programme: 1959-60.............       55     Cotton   .................      ......       5o
1. The Prime Secretary recalled that, when on 29th July theCabinet had last reviewed the international discussions on Berlin,they had considered that a meeting of Heads of Governments couldbe deferred until the autumn if it were understood and announced thatthere would be an early meeting of Western Governments and aSummit meeting before the end of the year. In the event the FrenchGovernment had opposed the idea of holding a meeting of western governments before Mr. Khrushchev&apos;s visit to the United States, and president Eisenhower had decided to hold instead a series of bilateraltalks in London, Paris and Bonn. After a short visit to Bonn he was now spending five days in the United Kingdom before going on to paris; and this visit had provided an opportunity for a valuableexchange of views, not only on the German problem, but on a numberof other questions of current concern.The Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary made a report tothe Cabinet on the talks which they had held with president eisenhower and his Secretary of State, Mr. Herter, at Chequers on29th-30th August.On the problem of Germany President Eisenhower had said thathe had pressed Dr. Adenauer to adopt a more flexible attitude andto consider new methods of ending the existing deadlock. He had warned him that the Western Powers could not expect to be ableindefinitely to maintain the existing position in Berlin and that, evenif agreement could be reached on a moratorium, this must leadeventually to some new arrangement. He had also urged him toaccept some system of increasing contacts between East and west germany.On the prospects of a Summit meeting, the President had been less encouraging. He was reluctant to agree to such a meeting unless he was satisfied that it had some prospect of producing fruitfulresults; and he still insisted that he must be able to see some&quot; progress &quot; towards a settlement before he could agree to attendsuch a meeting. He hoped however that, during his forthcoming visit to the United States, Mr. Khrushchev might be able to give himsome indication that a meeting of Heads of Governments would produce fruitful results, and in that event he would be ready to contemplate that a meeting should be held before the end of the year.Meanwhile he recognised the importance of avoiding any opendisagreement with Mr. Khrushchev; and he hoped that theforthcoming visits would serve to reduce tension.On nuclear tests the United States Government were stillunwilling to conclude any agreement for suspension which could notbe effectively enforced, and they would not on that account be readyto enter into a comprehensive agreement which covered undergroundtests. They were, however, prepared to undertake to make no furthertests until the end of the year. Meanwhile, the Geneva Conferenceon Nuclear Tests had been adjourned until 12th October; and it was hoped that, during this recess, the Russians would study the newscientific data relating to the detection of underground tests.The United States Administration were not in a mood to make concessions to France. They had shown themselves unwilling to promise support over Algeria, unless the French Government putforward a liberal policy containing a firm prospect of independence.The Prime Minister had, however, impressed upon the President theimportance of the French Colonial achievement in Algeria and thedifficulties of securing steady constitutional development in a multi-racial society difficulties which were not peculiar to Algeriaand also arose in other parts of Africa. If the French Governmentcould be persuaded to put forward a policy of pacification followedby an opportunity for the inhabitants freely to choose their own formVisit ofPresidentEisenhowerto Europe.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 49thConclusions.)
of government, it might be possible for their Allies to support this and to defeat any hostile resolution in the United Nations Assembly.The atmosphere in the Assembly would not however be improved bythe protests which would be made on behalf of African territories,including Nigeria, against the French proposal to hold a nuclear testin the Sahara. It would be convenient if discussion on this point could be merged in a general debate on disarmament.During the Presidents visit the opportunity had also been takento exchange views on a number of other questions, including thecurrent situation in Laos, the procedures for handling United Nationsdiscussions on the general problem of disarmament, the future of theUnited States base in Trinidad, the United States tariff on woolimports, the projected loan by the International Bank for thedevelopment of the Suez Canal and the problem of Anglo-american military planning against possible contingencies in the Middle East.On all these questions discussion had shown that the views of the twoGovernments were closely in accord.The Cabinet Took note of this report on the results of president eisenhower&apos;s visit to the United Kingdom.Economic 2.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, as the rate situation. interest on short-term Government loans was now higher in the(Previous United States than in the United Kingdom, there had been some reference: transfer of funds across the Atlantic.   In addition, the IraqC.C. (59) 45th Government had drawn down their sterling balances by someConclusions,  30 millions.  Despite these factors our reserves showed an increaseMinute 4.) 0f  jo millions during August.   This  could  be  regarded  as satisfactory.The Cabinet (1) Took note of this statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer.The Cabinet had a brief discussion on the report of theCommittee of Enquiry into the Monetary and Credit System, underthe Chairmanship of Lord Radcliffe. The report contained a valuableanalysis of the system, but it made few positive recommendations.It was unlikely to provoke political controversy.The Cabinet-(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to circulate to hiscolleagues a summary of Press comment on the Radcliffereport.The Minister of Labour said that the August figures ofunemployment showed an increase of 32,000 over July. Unemploy-ment among adults had, however, fallen by 6,000 and the net increase was due to the registration at employment exchanges of young people who had left school at the end of the summer term. A high proportionof these would be placed in employment within a few weeks, and the september unemployment figures were likely to be satisfactory.The Cabinet (3) Took note of this statement by the Minister of Labour.Crime.ApprovedSchools.3. The Home Secretary said that he had appointed Mr. VictorDurand, Q.C., to hold an enquiry into the recent disturbances at the approved school at Carlton, Bedfordshire. This incident wassymptomatic of the indiscipline current among young people; andthis was a general problem which ought to be tackled imaginativelyin the next Parliament.
legislative programme:1959-60.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 44t!Conclusions,Minute 4.)4. The Home Secretary said that steps were being taken toensure that a number of Bills would be ready for introduction at thebeginning of the next session of Parliament. In particular, it was important that the Betting and Gaming Bill and the Distribution ofIndustry Bill should be read a second time before Christmas. On theformer, however, a proposal of the Jockey Club for a levy on theturnover of bookmakers was giving rise to difficulties, and he proposedto invite the Home Affairs Committee to give further considerationto this aspect of the problem. On the latter Bill a number of policy decisions remained to be taken.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the Home AffairsCommittee to give further consideration to certain issueson the Betting and Gaming Bill.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Ministerof Labour, to expedite decisions on the questions of policystill outstanding on the Distribution of Industry Bill.Cotton.(previous reference:CC (59) 26thConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The President of the Board of Trade said that the proposalswhich were being put forward for the contraction of the cottonindustry substantially exceeded the estimates formulated at the timev/hen the Cotton Industry Bill was prepared. While this would increase the cost of the scheme to the Exchequer and might makenecessary special steps to deal with consequent unemployment, itwould mean that the industry would be reduced to a size compatible with real efficiency.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the President of the Boardof Trade.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,1st September, 1959.Prisons. The Home Secretary also referred to a proposal of the PrisonCommissioners to establish an open prison at Ford, Sussex. Theneed for additional open prisons was urgent, but this particular proposal had aroused much local opposition, in particular from alarge school for girls in the neighbourhood. Although the HomeAffairs Committee had concluded that it should be approved, theHome Secretary now felt that it would be preferable to defer for thetime being any announcement of this decision.The Cabinet Took note with approval of these statements by the HomeSecretary.


</content>
</cab>
