<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/33/0 images: 430-438</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SS ETdETTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1959C.C. (59)61st conclusions copy No.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 3rd December, 1959, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Lord President of the Council and secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord Privy Seal and Ministerfor Science.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Aviation.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The   Right    Hon.    Lord    Mills,Paymaster-General.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The  Right  Hon.  Ernest  Marples,M.P., Minister of Transport.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord Carrington,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 7).Sir   Jocelyn   Simon,   Q.C.,   M.P.,Solicitor-General (Items 2, 6-7).The Right Hon. Derek Walker-Smith,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Health(Item 5).The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury.Secretariat:
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Parliament       .....................       32     Interception of Communications    ............       33     Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland    .........       3Advisory Commission.4     Foreign Affairs..................      ...      4Antarctica.Anglo-Soviet Relations.5      Noise Abatement       ..................      46     Inter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation ...       57     Law of the Sea.....................       68     Police........................       7Royal Commission.9     Middle East    .....................       8Kuwait.
Communica-tions.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 76thConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Home Secretary said that some public anxiety had beenaroused by the fact that information which the Reading police had obtained by listening to a telephone conversation had been disclosed in disciplinary proceedings before the General Medical Councilagainst a Dr. Kenneth Fox. He had arranged to make a statement about this in the House of Commons that afternoon. He thenproposed to make three points which should go some way towardsallaying public anxiety. First, he would make it clear that the policehad not on this occasion been tapping a telephone conversationwithout the knowledge of either of the parties to it. The police hadin fact taken a transcript of the conversation with the knowledge and consent of the woman initiating the call, by use of the privateexchange at her place of residence. This was a practice frequentlyfollowed by the police in obtaining evidence of certain types of crime, e.g., blackmail. Secondly, he would explain that this action had been taken by the police, not in connection with the disciplinarycharge against the doctor which subsequently came before theGeneral Medical Council, but in the course of police enquiries intothe possibility of bringing a criminal charge arising from the death ofone of the doctor&apos;s patients. Thirdly, he would make it plain thatthe police had not voluntarily made the transcript of this conversationavailable to the General Medical Council: they had been requiredby subpoena to produce it as evidence in the disciplinary proceedings and could not have refused to comply with the subpoena unless theCrown had been prepared to claim privilege in respect of it. TheLaw Officers had advised him that this could not have been done without extending the classes of case in which Crown privilege is claimed.In discussion the view was expressed that, even when these factshad been brought out, some feeling was likely to persist that evidenceobtained by the police in criminal investigations should not beavailable for use in disciplinary proceedings before a professionaltribunal. It was, however, agreed that on this point the HomeSecretary could not do more than point the dilemma that this situation could only have been averted at the cost of extending thearea in which Crown privilege is claimed and by drawing attentionto the disadvantages which would follow, in private litigation, if that area were further enlarged.The Cabinet-Took note with approval of the general lines of the statement which the Home Secretary was proposing to make in theHouse of Commons that afternoon on the proceedings of theGeneral Medical Council in the case of Dr. Kenneth Fox.Federation o  3.   The Prime Minister said that, since the Cabinefs lastRhodesia and discussion on 10th November, he had done his utmost, in consultationNyasaland. with the Commonwealth Secretary and the Colonial Secretary, toAdvisory make it possible for the Labour Party to participate in the work of commission. the Centra! African Advisory Commission.   In the course of his0 (Previous exchanges with the Leader of the Opposition it had become evidentReference: that opinion within the Labour Party was divided on this questionC.C. (59) 57th anci that there were some v/ho were unwilling that the party should conclusions, participate in a Commission which was not explicitly authorised to minute 3.) consider alternatives to the continuance of Federation.   In the parliament. i    the Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
4se sretstatements which he had made about the scope of the Commission^enquiry he had gone as far as he could to meet that point of viewwithout losing the support of the Federal Government; arid he hadfinally felt obliged to inform the Leader of the Opposition that hep\could go no further in that direction. It now seemed likely that theVLabour Party would decline to participate in the work of theCommission. In that event the Government would have to decide whether the United Kingdom Parliament should be represented onthe Commission solely by Privy Counsellors belonging to theConservative Party, or whether an attempt should be made to find some Parliamentarians with Left-wing views who would be ready toserve despite an official boycott by the Labour Party. There wouldbe no advantage in adopting the second alternative unless people could be found who were likely to make the Commission more acceptable to African opinion. The Prime Minister said that, on balance, he was at present disposed to favour the first alternative.Discussion showed that there was general support in the Cabinet forthat view.Later in the meeting the Cabinet were informed that the leader of the Opposition had come to the conclusion that the Labour party would not be able to participate in the work of this Commission.The Cabinet Took note of the Prime Ministers statement.Foreign Affairs.Antarctica.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 41stConclusions,Minute 2.)Anglo-soviet relations.4. The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that, as a resultof the Conference held in Washington, a treaty had now been concluded on the peaceful uses of Antarctica.The Foreign Secretary also informed the Cabinet that a culturalagreement between the United Kingdom and the Soviet Union had now been concluded as a result of the discussions which had been proceeding in London with the Soviet Minister for Cultural Relationswith Foreign Countries.The Cabinet Took note of these statements by the Foreign Secretary.Noise 5.   The Lord Chancellor reported that, at their meeting onAbatement. 27th November, the Home Affairs Committee had approved aproposal by the Minister of Health that a committee should beappointed &quot; to examine the nature, sources and effects of the problemof noise and to advise what further measures can be taken to mitigateit&quot;. There was some pressure on the Government, both in and outside Parliament, to take action for the abatement of noise; and,in view of this and of the complexity of the problem, there was agood case for the appointment of a committee of enquiry. TheMinister of Health had to answer a Parliamentary Question on thesubject, on behalf of the Minister for Science, on 7th December andthis would be a suitable opportunity to announce the government&apos;s intention to appoint the committee.Discussion showed that there was general agreement with thisproposal. The danger that the committee might make recommenda-Qtions which would prove unduly expensive might be mitigated bycare in securing a suitable chairman. The Minister for Science shouldtake formal responsibility for the committee, but it could be servicedby the Ministry of Health.
Inter-GovernmentalMaritimeConsultativeOrganisation.6. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Ministerof Transport and the Attorney-General (C. (59) 178 and 179) aboutthe membership of the Maritime Safety Committee of the Inter-Governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation.The Minister of Transport said that when the Organisation setup a Maritime Safety Committee in January, 1959, Liberia andPanama were not elected to it, in spite of United States support fortheir candidature. The United Kingdom had taken a leading partin opposing their election. We had argued that these two countries were not suitable for election to the Committee, and that in any case they should not be elected to it automatically. Neither country had any organisation for enforcing safety regulations in their ships..Although they both had a large registered tonnage, the registrationarrangements were little more than a formality and it did not follow that they were &quot; ship-owning nations &quot; in any real sense of the term.The Assembly of the Organisation had now decided that the questionwhether the Maritime Safety Committee was properly constitutedshould be referred to the International Court of Justice. If we wereto maintain our position, it would be necessary to submit amemorandum to the Court before 5th December.The Law Officers took the view that the legal arguments insupport of our case were extremely weak. But, even if this were so,it was important for our international prestige and for the interestsof ship-owners and seafaring unions in this country that we shouldcontinue to argue that Liberia and Panama were unsuitable for membership of the Committee. It was therefore desirable that amemorandum explaining our views, which had already been circulatedto the other important maritime countries who had supported us,should be submitted to the International Court without delay.The Solicitor-General said that the Law Officers thought that thelegal arguments in support of our case were so weak that we shoulddamage our reputation with the International Court by submittingthem. It did not follow that because Liberia and Panama had nosafety organisation that they were not interested in maritime safety.The large registered tonnages of the two countries were legally inthe ownership of companies registered there, even though the beneficial ownership lay elsewhere. It did not seem possible to argue that, under the terms of the Convention, the fact that therewas to be an election for the membership of the Committee meant that these countries could not be automatically elected. Moreover,the argument that it was to be presumed that the Assembly had acted in accordance with the requirements of its constitution could not beaccepted as sound.Discussion showed that it was the general view of the Cabinetthat, even if the legal arguments were not very convincing, it was desirable to maintain our position before the International Court,since the other maritime countries which had supported us so farwere looking to us to maintain our opposition to the election ofThe Cabinet (1) Endorsed the conclusion of the Home Affairs Committeethat a committee of enquiry should be appointed on theproblem of noise.(2) Authorised the Minister of Health to announce theGovernments intention to appoint a committee on this problem.
Panama and Liberia. It was further suggested that the legalarguments were not necessarily as weak as had been suggested. Therewas some evidence to show that the Governments concerned withthe establishment of the Organisation had intended ownership to brxconstrued as beneficial ownership. Moreover, our opposition to thC/election of Liberia and Panama to the Committee was founded onthe substantial argument that the registration of shipping companies in those countries was only a convenience and that it operated againstthe interests of maritime safety.The Cabinet Approved the proposal put forward by the Minister ofTransport in C. (59) 178.Law of the Sea.       7.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the(Previous        Lord Chancellor (C. (59) 177) reporting the latest developments in reference:       preparation for the next International Conference on the Law ofCC. (59) 56th   the Sea.Conclusions,Minute 5.) The Lord Chancellor said that we had been successful indissuading the United States from committing themselves to supportthe Canadian proposal for a territorial sea of six miles plus a furthersix miles of exclusive fishing jurisdiction, supplemented by the negotiation of bilateral agreements for the continuation of historicfishing rights in the outer zone. It had, however, emerged from recent discussions that our own preferred solution a six-mile territorial sea plus a further six miles of exclusive fishing jurisdiction subject tothe indefinite preservation of historic rights was unlikely to command the necessary two-thirds majority at the next international conference. The Ministerial Committee therefore recommendedthat, in order to avoid the extension of the territorial sea to twelvemiles, we should support a solution which would provide for fishing rights to cease in the outer six-mile zone after a period long enoughto avoid disruption of the fishing industry say, 15 to 25 years. Itwas important that we should not admit openly that we wereprepared to abandon our own preferred solution, since this would encourage other Governments to support more extreme demands.But we should seek, through the United States Government, tosecure support for the modified formula now proposed as a fall-backposition at the Conference. The majority of the Committee were infavour of authorising the Attorney-General, who would shortiy bein Washington for another purpose, to take the United states authorities fully into our confidence for this purpose.The Minister of Agriculture said that, while sympathising withthis view, he was apprehensive of the political difficulties in which theGovernment would become involved with the fishing industry in thiscountry if it now became known that we were prepared to accept theless favourable formula now proposed. He would therefore prefer that the Attorney-General should confine himself at this stage todisclosing this to the leader of the United States delegation on a personal and confidential basis.In discussion it was agreed that in all the circumstances we mustbe prepared to accept the recommended formula as a fall-backposition. Acceptance of the six-mile territorial sea would admittedly,lead to difficulties over access by our military aircraft to certainour overseas possessions; but it was clear that the six-mile limit was now the narrowest for which we could hope, and there was a real danger that, unless we could secure support for some compromise proposal, a limit of twelve miles might result from the Conference.
Police.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 58thConclusions,Minute 3.)RoyalCommission.8. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C. (59) 176) recommending the appointment of a RoyalCommission on the police.The Home Secretary recalled that at an earlier discussion theCabinet had authorised him to announce that the Government were considering the possibility of a general enquiry into the police. this announcement had been widely welcomed and, after consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of State forScotland, he was satisfied that nothing less than a Royal commission would suffice. The scope of the Commission should include therelations between the police and the public and also between thepolice and local and central government. It should not includedetailed conditions of police service, which had been the subject ofa relatively recent enquiry, but its scope should cover the broad principles which should govern police pay. The Opposition had proposed that it should cover also such questions as methods of criminal investigation and the Judges&apos; Rules; but these were mattersof law which would require study by a different kind of body.In discussion there was general support for the proposal torecommend a Royal Commission on the police. It was suggestedthat this might include one Member of Parliament from either sideof the House, representatives of Scotland and Wales and of the TradeUnion movement, and a member having experience of the principlesof remuneration in the public service.The Cabinet Approved the proposal in C. (59) 176 for the appointmentof a Royal Commission on the police.As regards tactics, it was important that the United states delegation should at some stage become officially committed to theformula recommended by the Ministerial Committee. This mightnot be practicable unless the fact that the United Kingdom would alsoaccept it could be made known to other countries. Nevertheless, if at all possible, we should avoid for the present disclosing our positionto other Governments.Summing up the discussion the Prime Minister said that the attorney-General should be authorised to inform Mr. Dean, the leader of the United States delegation, personally and in confidence,of our willingness to fall back on this formula. It. might be suggested to Mr. Dean that he should approach other Governments on thebasis that we were not at present prepared to abandon the six-mile territory sea plus six miles&apos; exclusive fishing subject to the indefinitepreservation of historic rights but that in his own opinion we couldbe persuaded to fall back on the modified formula. If, however,Mr. Dean considered that support for the fall-back formula couldnot be mobilised without disclosing to other Governments that wewere prepared to accept it, the Attorney-General should seek further instructions.The Cabinet (1) Endorsed the proposal in C. (59) 177 that we should accept,as a fall-back position, a six-mile territorial sea plus sixmiles&apos; exclusive fishing subject to the preservation of historic rights for a relatively long period.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for instructions tobe sent to the Attorney-General, in accordance with thePrime Ministers summing up of the Cabinefs discussion.
Middle East.Kuwait.(previous reference:C.C. (59) 3rdConclusions,Minute 7.)9. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (C. (59) 174) about the extent of United Kingdomjurisdiction in Kuwait.The Foreign Secretary said that the Ruler of Kuwait was seekingour agreement to terminate or at least substantially to modify the&quot;present position of dual jurisdiction in Kuwait. As in other persian gulf States, and as a result of the rudimentary state of administration and justice when relations were originally established with Kuwait,the United Kingdom still had the right of jurisdiction there over british subjects and over all foreigners, other than the subjects ofthe Ruler and nationals of Muslim States, excluding Pakistan. the ruler had wished for some time that Kuwait should develop aninternational personality of its own and, in the interests of maintainingfriendly relations, we had agreed to a number of steps in that direction,including the entry of Kuwait into the Arab League. If we were toretain the Ruler&apos;s confidence, we should be well-advised to agree tosome reduction of our jurisdiction. On the other hand, theadministration of justice in Kuwait was still comparatively primitive.For instance, conditions in prisons there would be extremely hard forEuropeans. Moreover, if we were to cede jurisdiction, certain countries would proceed to establish consulates in Kuwait.In the circumstances, it seemed right to accept the objective ofultimately relinquishing our jurisdiction. We should, however, try to relate the cession of our jurisdiction to the progress made by the ruler in introducing suitable civil and criminal codes and courts oflaw. Meanwhile, as an earnest of our intentions, we could cedejurisdiction to the Kuwaiti tribunals which were being set up underthe Labour Law, the Maritime Code and the Port Rules, all of whichwere reasonably well defined.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that this progressivecession of jurisdiction would not affect the rights of the UnitedKingdom Government to conduct the foreign relations of Kuwait. Inpractice, there was little alternative but to accept the gradual reduction of our internal jurisdiction there, and it was greatly to be preferred that this reduction should be effected in agreement withthe Ruler and in step with the introduction of reforms.The Cabinet Approved the proposals put forward by the foreign secretary in C. (59) 174.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,3rd December, 1959.


</content>
</cab>
