<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/169/0 images: 444-453</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. ) C R E I. 0 A B 1 H E T., 542(24). 3*fDRAFT CONVENTION PROVISIONALLY ADOPTED BY THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE RELATING TO -(1) NIGHT BAKING,(2) WEEKLY SUSPENSION OF WORK IN GLASS IMANUFACTURING PROCESSES, (S) EQUALITY OF TREATMENT IN REGARD TOWORKMEN&apos;S COMPENSATION.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.I desire, with the concurrence of the Minister of Labour, to obtain an immediate decision as to the course to be pursued in regard to the draft Conventions above mentioned which were provisionally adopted by. the International Labour Conference last Summer.   These Conventions will come up for final confirmation at the Conference next May, and Governments are entitled to propose amendments designed to facilitate ratification, provided notice of these amendments is sent to the International Labour Office by the 19th January next.(l)    NIGHT BAKING.The draft Convention prohibits the baking of bread, pastry and other flour confectionery for a period of at least seven consecutive hours including the interval between 11 p.m. and 5 a.m. (or where it is required by climate or season, between 10 p.m. and 4 a.m.).   It applies to proprietors as well as to workers and to all classes of premises, but not to home baking.   The wholesale manufacture of biscuits is excluded.Night work is already prohibited in most European countries, but in this country it is not subject to restriction so far as men are concerned.   Previous to 1914, night baking had (except in Scotland where tnere was practically no night baking) become&apos;&apos; fairly general in the larger bakeries in industrial areas, but
during the war, as a consequence of the Bread Order prohibiting the sale of bread which had not been made at least 12 hours, it stopped almost altogether.    After the war there was strong opposition by the Trade Unions.to a return to pre-war conditions and in 1919 as a serious dispute had developed, a Departmental Oommittee was appointed to inquire into the practice.This Committee which was preeided over by Sir William Mackenzie, X. C. and included the present Minister of Agriculture, unanimously reported (Omd0 246 ) in favour of prohibiting night work between 11 p.m. and 5 a.m. subject to various exceptions. The Oommittee did not find it established that the night work had been &quot;unduly detrimental&quot; to health, but they found that it does involve serious interference with normal social and family life - night work in baking differs from night work in all other trades, except the newspaper trade, in that the men work six nights a week throughout the year, never changing to day work as is customary in continuous processes where work is done by day and night shifts^   Further, they came, to the conclusion that provided certain exceptions were permitted, the practical difficulties could be overcome without serious hardship and the supply of bread and confectionery &quot;reasonably fresh at reasonable time&quot; would not be interfered with.   On the question of cost, the Oommittee found that &quot;apart from the capital expenditure which may have to be made by firms with insufficient plant for the trade they are doing, and who are consequently working both day and night shifts,, the abolition of night work will not generally add to the cost of manufacture, whilst owing to the better supervision exercised on day shifts, a larger output per worker may be obtained^&quot;A Bill to give effect to the Committee&apos;s recommendations was introduced by the Home Secretary in May 1920, but was opposed and made no progress;    and the present position is, roughly, that night baking is now carried on to much the same extent as before the war.
At the International Labour Conference the Government representatives supported the draft Convention in principle, but sought - though without much success - to have it amended in conformity with the recommendations of the Committee.    The main points on which the draft Convention goes beyond the proposals of the Committee are -(l) It applies not only to bakeries under the Factory Acts but to all premises including hotel and restaurant kitchens.(2)&apos; It prohibits night work not only for the operative but also for the master baker, whether working on his own account or employing others, whereas the Committee recommended merely that the Secretary of State should bo empowered-by Order to extend the prohibition to the master baker in particular districts on the application of the employers and workers in that district.(3) It defines &quot;night&quot; as a period of not less than ? hours (to be fixed by a competent authority in each country) which shall include the&apos; period between 11 p.m. and 5 a.m. or where climate or season requires it, the period between 10 p.m. and 4 a.iru whereas the Committee&apos;s recommendation was prohibition of night work for the period between 11 p,m. and 5 a.m.It seems clear that the draft Convention ought not to be supported unless it is amended on the points above mentioned but that if this is done, there are strong grounds in favour of accepting it.    The objection to night work on the ground of its interference with social and family life is indisputable and it seems clear from the Committee&apos;s Report and from the fact that even now night baking is not by; any means a universal practice, even1 in the large - towns, that the practice is not essential to meet the needs of the public.    The most nerious consideration is the possibility that the re-organisation night lead temporarily
to some increase in the cost of broad.    The National Confederation of Employers&apos; Organisations, who have protested against the adoption of the draft Convention, lay great stress on this point and refer to a passage in a Report of the Linlithgow Committee    (Cmd. 1971) where the Committee state that they &quot;are informed&quot; - it does not appear by whom - that the discontinuance of night baking would &quot;necessitate the baker either giving up the manufacture of other goods, such as cakes and biscuits,  thus putting to no effective use the heat remaining in the ovens, or, alternatively, enlarging his plant so that both bread and confectionery could be manufactured simultaneously.    In either event, the cost of baking, and therefore, the price of the loaf, would be increased&quot;.   On tho other hand, there is the finding, already quoted, of the Departmental Committee who specially investigated the point and one of whose members, Mr. Webster Jenkinson, C.B.E., Chartered Accountant, who had been Controller of Factory Audits and Costs at the Ministry of Munitions and Chief Liquidator of Munitions Contracts, had been specially appointed for the purpose.   There is also the fact that the master bakers appear to have made very little of this point before the Committee.    Nor is there any evidence to shew that the price of bread is higher in districts where night baking is not carried on than elsewhere.It would appear from conversations which have taken place with the Director General of the Belgian Ministry of Labour that if we move amendments to the Convention on lines above indicated, we shall have the support of the Belgian and Swiss Governments, and there would bo a good prospect of   (-getting the Convention licked into shape.   On the other hand, if we adopt a merely negative attitude, the Convention will probably be confirmed in its present form, and though not ratified now, will remain open for ratification at any time by any subsequent Government,,    This is a contingency which it would bo unwise to leave out of account..
On the whole I recommend, with the concurrence of theMinistry of Labour, that we should decide to accept theConvention provided it is amended on the above points, butthat in notifying our amendments we should intimate that while .His Majesty&apos;s Government would be prepared to adopt theConvention if it were amended on the lines indicated, they are bound to call attention to the present high cost of living inGreat Britain and the recent rise in the cost of food and tothe fact that they have recently appointed a Royal Commissionto investigate the present prices of food.   In these circumstancesthey feel that it would be impossible for them to undertake tobring into actual operation any change in the present system which might affect, even though only for a brief period, thegeneral cost of production, by any specified date.(2) WEEKLY SUSPENSION OP WORK IN GLASS MANUFACTURINGPROCESSES..Article 1 of this draft Convention provideo that work shall be suspended for 24 consecutive hours per week in glass manufacturing processes where tank furnaces are used (in tanks the glass must be kept constantly in a molten state on Sundays as on other days) and Article 2 requires that in principle this suspension shall take place on Sunday or any other day already established by the legislation, traditions or customs of the country or district.   Article 3 authorises each State to allow exceptions for work which has necessarily to.bo carried on continuously for technical or economic reasons and for certain preparatory, complementary or repair work.    Article 6 provides that workers who in pursuance of Article 3 are employed on Sunday, shall be given a weekly rest on some other day of the week;    but this   is qualified by words referring to the Convention of 1921 concerning the weekly rest in industrial establishments which would apparently enable a State to exempt any process from the operation of this Article.In so far as the effect of these Articles would be to
secure that every worker employed in the processes in question is given a weekly rest of 24 hours and that so far as possible this rest is given on Sunday, the draft Convention would deserve the. support of His Majesty1s Government.    The work carried on in glass manufacture is admittedly arduous and with few exceptions all the workers employed in the glass work in&apos; this country (other than furnacemen and men employed on repair work) do in fact enjoy a weekly rest which, except where the production of glass is carried on continuously, is naturally given on Sunday.    In a few works, namely, those with expensive automatic or semi-automatic machinery the actual production of glass (not merely the maintenance of the furnaces) is carried on continuously throughout the weekend, but in some of these the conditions are peculiarly favourable for the men.   For example, in one of the largest works the work is carried on by four shifts of workers whose hours are so arranged that on an average no worker is engaged for more than 42 hours per week and each worker gets every fourth Sunday off and during every period of 12 days has two complete breaks of 48 consecutive hours.   On the Continent, however, the weekly rest is by no means so commonly enjoyed and the effect of a properly drafted Convention, if generally ratified, would be to level up to some extent the conditions abroad with the conditions at home.As was pointed out, however, by the British representatives -at the Conference, the provision in Article 1 requiring a suspension of work on Sunday, with consequent stoppage of machinery, goes much beyond the object of a weekly rest.    Such a requirement is obviously open in principle to the greatest objection.    It is not only unnecessary to the particular object in.view, which should be a rest for \the individual worker and not a rest for the machine, but it is also out of harmony with the general objects of the International Labour Organisation as : laid down in the Treaty and with the principles generally observed in British legislation, which seek to protect the worker
BOlwithout unnecessary interference with production.   Further, in order to render the provisions of Article 1 tolerable, it became necessary to allow for exceptions on an extensive scale and under Article 5 each State is given an absolute discretion to exempt almost any process or class of work.   In the case, however, of an industry like glass which is the subject of keen international competition, this untrammelled power of exemption is in itself most obnoxious.   The practical effect would be that whenever one State exempted any particular process, ,every other competing State would feel bound to allow a similar exemption, and thus any value the Convention might have from the workers1 point of view, would be gradually destroyed.This was pointed out to the Conference by the British Delegate who, in voting for the Convention, said - &quot;We will vote in favour of the draft Convention as it now stands, with a view to keeping the subject alive only.   We do not think the draft Convention contains very much of use to anybody, but we very much desire to keep the subject alive, in the hope that at some future date something will emerge from this Convention to help the people concerned&quot;.Strong representations have recently been made by the &apos; National Confederation of Employers&apos; Organisations against the acceptance of the principle involved in Article 1, and so long as this principle is maintained, I am clearly of opinion that we ought to oppose the Convention.   In my view, which I under-stand is shared by the Minister of Labour, we could only accept tho Convention if the Conference could be induced to substitute for Articles 1, 2, 3 and 6 simple provisions .to the effect that every worker (subject to an exception for men employed on Sunday for a short period on repair work or in connexion with the furnaces) should be allowed one day&apos;s rest per week and that so far as practicable this rest should be given on Sunday.The employers would prefer that the Convention should not even contain a direction that the rest should be given on
Under this draft Convention each State undertakes to grant to workers who are nationals of any other State which has ratified tho Convention the same treatment regarding Workmen1s Qompensation as it grants to its own nationals.   States which ratified the Convention and which do not already possess a Workmen&apos;s Compensation system undertake to institute such a system within three years. this draft Convention was supported by the British Government at the last Conference and (subject to a small drafting amendment) it appears satisfactory.   It is based on the principle of reciprocity and is therefore in accordance with the views expressed by His Majesty&apos;s Government at the ImperialSunday.   The workers, however, attach great importance to the principle of the collective rest and their claim on this point appears to me to be not unreasonable.   Moreover, the general Convention concerning the weekly rest day adopted by the Conference in 1921 recognises the principle of the collective Sunday rest and 1 am advised that the Conference would not accept the present Convention unless it included some provision on the point.The employers have also suggested the insertion of a provision that the Convention shall not be binding on any State unless and until it has been ratified by the chief glass manufacturing countries.   If, however, the draft Convention is amended on the lines indicated above, I hardly think that any such safeguard is really necessary.   It is always, I understand, open to any State when ratifying the Convention to stipulate that the obligations shall not take effect until certain specified States have also ratified.I recommend that notice of amendments on the above lines should be given and that our support to the Convention shouldbe conditional on the acceptance of these amendments.(3) EQUALITY OF TREATMENT IN REGARD TO WORKMEN1S COMPENSATION.
Oonference in 1923;    and if it is generally accepted, it should prevent the occurrence of cases such as have been experienced in the past where a Continental country has declined to extend the benefit of their Workman&apos;s Compensation laws to British subjects. The British Acts already accord the same treatment to aliens as to British subjects.   Ho objection has been taken to the Convention either by the British Employers&apos; or British Workers&apos; representatives and i recommend that His Majesty&apos;s Government should accept it.GENERAL.I should add that the Minister of Labour (with a representative of the Home Office) received a deputation from the Confederation of Employers&apos; Associations on the above matters during last week.    The Confederation expressed very definite opposition to the ratification of the Night Baking Convention and criticised the terms of the Glass Convention. In the Minister&apos;s view, however, the objections taken by the Employers seem to have been based rather on a general distrust of the activities of the International Labour Organisation as a whole than upon the merits of tho Conventions in question.    His view is that these Conventions, if amended in the form suggested above, would not be as strongly opposed by the trades directly concerned.I would observe,, in regard to the general attitude of the Employers that they tend to take the view that the International Labour Office was the home of international faddists and that the ultimate effect of its deliberations is to fasten upon us decisions which we keep and which our trade rivals have no intention of so doing.    The distrust of the Organisation which they have evinced seems to me at least to merit investigation and suggests the necessity of careful consideration by the Government of the International Labour policy.    i therefore make the two following proposals to the Cabinet ;-
&apos; B0416th December,  1924.9Z82-91.(a) That the Cabinet should authorise replies to be cent to Geneva, with regard to the three Conventions now in question, upon the lines in the memorandum;    and(b) That a Cabinet Committee to consider the generalGovernment policy on International Labour affairs should be constituted early in the new year.   The&apos; composition of that Committee could be discussed at a later date.   It is, however, to be clearly under-stood that the Committee would not be troubled with the ordinary routine work affecting international Labour business as between Departments, which is carried on by the International Labour Committee presided over by the Parliamentary Secretary of the Ministry of Labour.W.J.H.

</content>
</cab>
