<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/169/0 images: 454-456</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAWHC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)copy noE C R E T.CPi 543 (84) icabinet.IMPERIAL ECONOMIC POLICY COMMITTEE.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the above Committee held at 10, Downing Street, S.&apos;&apos;;,, on Monday, 8th December, 1924, at 5.0 p.m.PRESENT:-The Prime Minister. (In the Chair).The Right Hon. W.S. Churchill, CH.,M.P,, Chancellor of the Exchequer.&quot;he Right Hon. Sir Philip Lloyd-Breame, K.B.E. ,M.C.,,M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. L.S. Amery, Mi Pi, secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Minister of Health.Thomas Jones............. . ............... Secretary to the Committee
The Committee considered the attitude which theGovernment should adopt in regard to preference in the debate on the Address and hud before them:-A memorandum on the Anglo-Greek Commercial Treaty by the President of the Board of Trade. CP.515 (24)andA Memorandum on the same subject by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesCP.525 (24). IThere was general agreement that the .Governmentshould confirm their intention of giving effect toresolutions of the Imperial economic Conference and the pledges given in the General election but should statethat the precise method of giving effect to the advantagesoffered to the Dominions and the Colonies by the prefer-ential treatment of canned fish, apples and currants wasbeing examined and that definite proposals would be madeon the introduction of the Budget.The Committee were agreed:-(a) That the Resolutions of the Imperial Economic Conference should be carried out except as regards canned fish, apples and currants,(b) That the method of bounties did not offer. a satisfactory method of dealing with these commodities.(c) That the proposals for developing the marketing of Imperial products outlined to the Committee by the President of the Board of Trade should be further examined by the Interdepartmental Committee with a view to putting definite proposals before the Imperial Economic Committee,it being understood that the Chancellor of the Exchequer was prepared to provide a sum equivalent to what a bounty on Empire apples canned fish and currants would, have cost the Treasury.HOTS. &apos; .^Vhile -In agreement with the foregoing, the Chancellor-of the Exchequer thinks that with regard to the duties onhoney, dried or preserved druit and lime juice, it should still remain open for .later consideration whether it isworth while emb&amp;rfcLag on &apos;the argument that these commodities-1-
are not food, for the sake of the comparatively small issues involved and whether it would not be better to pay the equivalent value of these to the Dominions into . the fund for marketing Empire produce in the same way as is to be done with the other duties.     This would effect a great simplification of argument, procedure and finance, and by securing larger funds for the marketing policy make that a really powerful weapon for Imperial trade.Whitehall Gardens, 3.W.I. 9th December,  1924.

</content>
</cab>
