<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/169/0 images: 488-492</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT).secret C R E T.CABIN El.C.P. 551. ( 4). \iNEW ROAD AND BRIDGE PROGRAMME. . )     /Report of Unemployment Committee.1.       The Unemployment Committee have recnntly had under consideration proposals submitted to them by the Minister of Transport for devoting the sum of approximately  6,000,000,representing the estimated net surplus revenues of the Road Fund for the period ending 31st March, 1930, to the carrying out of a further bridge and. road programme. The nature of the proposals is fully explained in the Ministers Memorandum dated 3rd December, 1924, (C.U.714), -a copy of which is attached hereto. ,        As a result of further consideration of the proposed allocation of the available surplus the Committee considerthat it would be prudent to retain in hand a sum of  1,000,000to be provided by reducing the suggested allocation forthe reconstruction of trunk roads in the Highlands ofScotland from  2,000,000 to  1,000,000.3.        The Committee recommend the Cabinet :-fl) To authorise the Minister of Transport to allocate the  6,000,000 estimated net surplus revenues of the Road Fund up to 31st March 1930 as follows :-(i)      632,450   ...     ... Newcastle-GatesheadBridge.(ii)    . 650,000   towards the construction and reconstruction of bridges estimated to cost  1,000,000 in all.(iii)      700,000   towards the enlargement and improvement of 1st and 2nd Class Roads and the construction of new roads of Classification value estimated to cost  1,200,000 in all.
(iv)    2,000,000   for reconstruction of trunk roads for which  5,000,000 was previously provided.,(v)    1,000,000   for similar purposes in the Highlands of Scotland.(vi)    1,000,000   in reserve.(Intd)       L.W.B.H.B. HOWOEDH)    T . t C.W.G. EABY. ) Secretanes.whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. 23rd. December, 1924.2o
ABILITY OF ROAD FUND TO FINANCE FURTHER SCHEMES FOR THE RELIEF OF UNEMPLOYMENT.Memorandum by the Minister of Transport.In aocordanoc with the Committee^ instructions (C.U.79th Oona.) I have considered what further programme of Road and Bridge works could be undertaken in addition to the programme of such works approved by the late Government in the early part of the year,   this programme ia now estimated to cost  14,000,000 against the original figure of  13,500,000. towards which  10,400,000 (estimated) will be contributed by the Road Fund.This commitment was entered into after consideration of a Joint report by the late Financial Secretary to the Treasury and my predecessor (CP.268 (24)) as to the extent of the additional liabilities which the Road Fund could properly incur.In view of the continued find striking increase in the number of motor vehicles licensed, I am advised that the estimates of the revenue for motor taxation for future years may safely be inoreased.The present oatiinate of the revenue for 1924/25 is  16,25X1,000, and I estimate that this will increase until it reaches, in tho year 1929/30,   20 millions.In this calculation I have made no allowance for substantial remissions of duty and the acceptance of these proposals by the Government will preclude any such reductions unless the revenue expands even more rapidly than is at present anticipated.Allowing for the statutory deductions and the minimum for requirements for purposes other than programmos of works eooolerated for unemployment, the total of the available surpluses from 1925/26 to 1929/So will be  18,150,000.SECRET. 0.U.714.
-e- EllThe liabilities outstanding on the 31st of March next, including those arising under the 13^ million programme, and the additional  1,000,000 anticipated for Rural Roads, will exceed the assets of the Fund at that date by approximately  12,160,000 representing the extent to which revenue is being antioipated. The surplus revenues now estimated to acorue during the next 5 years - i.e. up to the end of tho financial year 1929/30 - will be sufficient to meet this exoess and to leave  6,000,000 approximately available for further work.The calculations given in CP.268 (24) proposed to anticipate part of the revenue of 1930/31, but in view of the many important schemes whioh are now in various stages of investigation I should prefer for the moment not to anticipate revenue more than 5 years ahead.A sum of  632,450 is required towards the cost, estimated at  973,000, of the Newcastle - Gateshead Bridge for which the Treasury has agreed that provision should be made out of future revenue.    Tho grant has been promised and should, I think, be made a first charge on the revenue anticipated.My proposals for allocating the remainder of  5,350,000 are as followst-(a)  650,000 towards the construction and reconstruction of bridges estimated to cost  1,000,000 in all.(b)  700,000 towards the onlargement and improvementof 1st and 2nd Class Roads and the construction ofnew roads of Classification value estimated to oost 1,200,000 in all. (o)    2,000,000 for reconstruction of trunk roads forwhich  6,000,000 was previously provided, (d)    2,000,000 for similar purposes in tho Highlands ofScotland.I think that the Rood Fund will have to find thewhole cost of the Highland Schemes but It is possible that in other districts the schemes may attract contributions from the Local Authorities.
I am advised that all those proposals oan be put in hand at a comparatively early date.It will be aeon that in round figures a Road Fund contribution of  5,350*000 is estimated to ftuffioe to initiate works oosting in all  6,200,000.     The addition of the latter sum to the late Government^ pre gramme of  13,600,000 (revised to  14 millions) would raise our total programme to a round figure of about  20,000,000.My proposals are of course subject to an extension of the Treasury guarantee of fin&amp;nolal &quot;cover&quot;, on the lines approved in oonnexion vrith previous programmes, to the amplified programme now reoommended, but as the additional commitmentb are to be met out of new revenue and the rate of expenditure under the old programme is slower than was expected my proposals are not likely to involve any increased risk of the Treasury &quot;cover&quot; being actually required.(Signed)     WILFRID ASHLEY.3rd December, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
