<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/169/0 images: 510-511</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet. December 1924.SECRET. CP. 554 (24).CABINET.THE ECONOMIC POWEK OF JAPAN.Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues a note on the Economic and Financial power of Japan, which appears to have a bearing on the discussions which are to take place in the Committee of Imperial Defence.W. S. C.Treasury Chambers, December 29,1924. &apos;The Economic Power of Japan.1. Japan, for all her 59,000,000 inhabitants, is a very poor country, mainly agricultural.In 1921 the mining and industrial population numbered 2,100,000 (of whom 900,000 were women). This is a very low proportion of the total population, and industrial wages also are very low. In 1922, the latest year for which statistics are available, the prevalent rates appear to have been from 2 to 3 yen* (4s. to 6s.) a day. These low wages are a sign of low productivity per head. For example, in coal mining 267,614 employees produced in 1921 26 million tons of coal, or less than 100 tons each. In this country the output per head in 1923 was 240 tons. The most ^important Japanese industry is textiles, which employed 946,000 operatives in 1921. The output per head appears to have been approximately 1,780 yen ( 178). Exact statistics of the output per head in this country are not available, but it cannot be much less than  300.2. This difference in productivity is not entirely due to deficiencies in the workpeople. It is partly due to the insufficient capital in Japanese industry (e.g., there are still many hand-looms). The scarcity of capital is illustrated by the very high rates of interest. Short-term industrial debentures usually cost 10 per cent., and first mortgages 12 per cent.In these circumstances it is clear that out of the slender resources of the country only a restricted proportion can be made available or 1&apos; mobilised&apos;&apos; through the channels of finance. A test of capacity in this direction is supplied by the income tax. The tax is imposed at various rates on different categories of income, and on some it is heavily graduated, but the predominant rates appear to be, from 5 to 1\ per cent. The yield of the tax in 1922-23 and preceding years averaged about  20 millions. (For 1924-25 the estimated yield is much less, owing to the earthquake.) Roughly, it may be estimated that an income tax of Is. in the   would yield  15,000,000. Comparison with the yield in this country (nearly  60,000,000 for each shilling) shows how far Japan is from our standard of wealth. Japanese railway revenue in. 1921-22 was  44 millions.  That of Great Britain in 1921 was  218 millions.[12452]* The yen is taken at 2s. throughout.
3. The budget position for the last few years has been as follows (in millions): - 	Ke venue.	Expenditure.	Surplus (4-) or Deficit (-).1919-20 1920-21 1921-22 1922-23 (estimated) 1923-24 (estimated)	  133 129 137 131 128	117 136 149 KiO 137	- 2 - 19 - 9In the period 1919-23 the debt grew from  258 millions to  381 millions. The increase of  123 millions far exceeds the borrowings disclosed in the budget. Even if railway loans be omitted, the increase has been from. 169 to  241 millions.The expenditure on armaments has been :  million.1919-20     ...............      541920-21 1921-22 1922-23 1923-2465 73 65 48These figures include extraordinary expenditure.4. The budget for 1924-25 has been greatly affected by the earthquake reconstruc-tion expenditure. The expenditure is estimated at  161 millions, the cost of defence being reduced to  43 millions. Revenue is  128 millions and the deficit  33 millions.5. The material damage resulting from the earthquake of September 1923 is&quot; variously estimated at from  250 to  1,000 millions. Even the lower figure (which is the more probable) is very formidable.Till 1923 the Japanese had succeeded in nursing their credit in international markets very effectively. They had particularly made a point of maintaining their currency, and had protected it with very large reserves of gold and foreign exchange. For some years before the earthquake, however, their position had been gradually weakening.Reserve of Specie and Foreign Exchange.(In   millions.)	At Home.	Abroad.	Total.December 1920    .   ..	110	107	217December 1921	122	86	208January   1923	121	61	182December 1923	121	4)	165- During this period the exchange had been allowed to drop 2 or 3 per cent, below gold parity (though the exchange on London was always above par). After the earthquake the Japanese did not feel themselves strong enough to keep up their currency, and they let the exchange drop. It is now 23 per cent, below the gold par.6. Japan&apos;s last foreign loan ( 25 millions here and  30 millions in America) cost her 6 per cent, at 87-1. This was floated in February 1924, and was largely for renewals in respect of two sterling loans of 1905, which mature in 1925. The total maturity outstanding was about  35,000,000, and a large proportion (possibly as much as half) still remains to be dealt with-in addition to any new borrowing for earthquake reconstruction.7. It seems certain (a) that Japan can only raise a very limited amount of money either from the foreign investor or internally; (6) that she does not possess any very large reserves of taxable capacity. She is poor, and her existing taxes are comprehensive. Besides the income tax and the usual system of customs and excise duties on liquors, &amp;c, she has a complicated business tax yielding  4 millions and a textile consumption tax yielding  5 millions. The whole yield of taxation (including net yield of monoplies) is estimated for 1924-25 at  95 millions.

</content>
</cab>
