<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/30/0 images: 280-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1956SECRETCM. (56)27th ConclusionsCopy No.CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.I.on Tuesday, 10th April, 1956, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime MinisterThe Most Hon. the Marquess ofSalisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C, M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. the Earl of Selkirk,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. the Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for CommonwealthRelations.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Minister of Works.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions andNational Insurance (Item 5).Dr. the Right Hon. Charles Hill, M.P.,Postmaster-General (Item 6).The Right Hon. Sir Reginald Manning-ham-Buller, Q.C, M.P., Attorney-General (Item 8).The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Item 9).The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of State for Colonial Affairs(Item 7).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. P. R. Odgers.49936 1
ContentsAfo.                                      Subject Page1 Middle East ..................... 3Arab-Israel Dispute.2 Disarmament   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 43 Parliament       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 54 Parliament ..................... 5Remuneration of Members.5 Family Allowances .................. 56 Post Office Finance .................. 67 International Labour Organisation............ 78 Capital Punishment .................. 79 British Transport Commission ............ 810     Kashmir........................ 8#
3CM. 27 (56)MiddleEast.(PreviousReference:CM. (56) 24thConclusions,Minute 5.)Arab-IsraelDispute.1. The Foreign Secretary said that during the past few daysthere had been a series of frontier incidents between Egyptian andIsraeli troops in the neighbourhood of Gaza. The Secretary-Generalof the United Nations had been instructed by the Security Councilto undertake a mission to the Arab States and Israel with a view topreventing any extension of hostilities. In support of this action bythe United Nations President Eisenhower had issued a formalstatement that the United States would observe its commitmentswithin constitutional means to oppose any aggression in this area,and was likewise determined to support and assist any nation whichmight be subjected to such aggression.The Foreign Secretary said that there was some ambiguity aboutthis statement. It might mean that the United States Governmentwere seeking to place more emphasis on United Nations action thanon action under the Tripartite Declaration of 1950. In most quarters,however, it had been accepted as a firm statement calculated to deterfurther aggression by either party to this dispute. He thereforerecommended that a public statement should at once be made onbehalf of the United Kingdom Government in which we wouldwarmly welcome President Eisenhower&apos;s declaration and associateourselves with it. He would at the same time tell the United StatesGovernment privately that we were assuming that this declarationapplied both to action within the United Nations ana to action underthe Tripartite Declaration.The Cabinet approved the Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposals. Indiscussion the following points were raised :  (a) We should be careful to avoid committing ourselves to anyunilateral action under the Tripartite Declaration. In this matterwe should be ready to do no less than the United States; but, if theywere in fact moving away from a policy of action under theDeclaration to one of action within the United Nations, we shouldhold ourselves free to conform with that movement. Our objectivewas to prevent an outbreak of hostilities. There would be littlepublic enthusiasm in this country for the employment of Britishtroops, on either side, in a war between Arabs and Israelis.(b) If the present tension in the Gaza Strip led to war, it mightbe difficult to determine which side was the aggressor. The Cabinetwere informed that it was the United States&apos; intention, in that event,to invoke the United Nations procedure under which both sides wouldbe invited to disengaae their troops. Under that procedure, if eitherside failed to act on such an invitation from the Security Council, itwould be deemed to be the aggressor.(c) The Foreign Secretary said that he might be asked inParliament what plans had been made for military action in this areaon behalf of the Governments of the United Kingdom and the UnitedStates. The United States Government would be unwilling toauthorise any reference to joint military planning. He was, therefore,disposed to say that planning was well advanced to discharge theobligations undertaken by the United Kingdom Government, whetherunder the United Nations or under the Tripartite Declaration.In discussion it was pointed out that, while the militarypossibilities had been reviewed, little progress had been made informulating actual military plans. The military conversations inWashington had hitherto proceeded slowly, though there were nowsome signs of a greater sense of urgency on the American side. Itseemed preferable therefore that the Foreign Secretary should declineto be drawn into discussion of the state of military planning. TheFrench Government might now, however, be asked what action theywould be prepared to take under the Tripartite Declaration. TheForeign Secretary could then at least say that consultations wereproceeding between the three parties to the Declaration.49936 1 b 2
4(d) The best practical step which could be taken to reduce therisk of hostilities in this area was to arrange for some further supplyof arms to increase the defensive strength of Israel. Some furtherfighter aircraft were being supplied to them from this country andfrom France, and some might also be sent from Canada. In addition,the Israelis had recently asked if we could send them some Centuriontanks. It did not, however, seem desirable that we should supplyoffensive weapons to the Israelis in present circumstances, especiallyin view of the current situation in Jordan. It would be better toexplore the possibility of providing them with some anti-tankweapons.(e) We should for the present avoid any public admission thatfurther supplies of arms were being sent to Israel. This was a reasonfor avoiding, if possible, an early debate in the House of Commonson the situation in the Middle East. This consideration might bebrought to the notice of the Leader of the Opposition.The Cabinet (1) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to issue a public statementwelcoming the declaration made by President Eisenhoweron the dispute between Egypt and Israel.(2) Took note of the steps which the Foreign Secretary wasproposing to take to ensure conformity of policy andaction in this matter by the Governments of the UnitedStates and the United Kingdom.Disarmament.(PreviousReference :CM. (55) 31stConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet of the courseof the discussions at the current meeting of the Disarmament Sub-Committee of the United Nations. The Soviet Government had nowproduced a new disarmament plan, which they would doubtless seekto exploit in their propaganda. He therefore thought it desirable thathe should make a statement in the House of Commons, in reply toQuestions which had been tabled for answer on the following day,putting this plan into proper perspective and drawing attention toits main defects. It lacked precision on the vital question of control,and it contained no provision for nuclear disarmament.In discussion misgivings were expressed about the turn whichthe discussions in the Disarmament Sub-Committee were taking.From our point of view it was important that no internationalagreement prohibiting or limiting the manufacture of nuclear weaponsshould come into force until we ourselves had adequate stocks ofthese weapons. Hitherto our position in this respect had beensafeguarded by the reluctance of the Soviet Government to reach anyagreement for the limitation of conventional armaments. Our flankwould, however, be turned if the Russians produced acceptableproposals for limitation of conventional armaments; for we shouldthen be subject to heavy pressure to accept prohibition of furthermanufacture of nuclear weapons.In further discussion it was argued that international agreementon a comprehensive plan of disarmament was unlikely to be reachedfor several years. Meanwhile, we should continue to press for acomprehensive plan and effective machinery for control.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider, in the light of theCabinet&apos;s discussion and in consultation with the LordPresident and the Minister of Defence, the terms of thestatement on disarmament which he proposed to make inthe House of Commons on the following day, and to submitthe draft of this statement for the Prime Minister&apos;s approval.
5CM. 27 (56)Parliament. 3.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.The Chancellor of the Exchequer would open his Budget on. 7th April. The general debate on the Budget resolutions and on theeconomic situation would be held on 18th and 19th April, and wouldbe concluded on 23rd April.Parliament.Remunerationof Members.(PreviousReference :CM. (56) 22ndConclusions,Minute 5.)4. The Lord Privy Seal said that there had been some prematuredisclosure to the Press, apparently from Opposition sources, aboutthe project which he had mentioned to the Cabinet on 13th Marchfor dealing simultaneously with the remuneration of Members ofthe House of Commons, salaries of junior Ministers and expenseallowances for Peers. This disclosure might impair the prospects ofpersuading Government supporters to accept this project. He wouldhave to take further soundings about this among Governmentsupporters. It was, however, unlikely that early action could nowbe taken on the lines which he had previousy envisaged.There was general agreement that it was urgently necessary toincrease the salaries of junior Ministers and that it \/as desirable thatthe whole project should be carried through before Parliament rosefor the summer recess. In the meantime every effort should be madeto prevent Government supporters from voicing opposition to it.*5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (CP. (56) 95) on family allowances and the breadsubsidy.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he wished to announcein his Budget statement that the remainder of the bread subsidy wouldbe discontinued on a definite date later in the year. The effect ofthis on people with larger families could be mitigated by an increasein family allowances. The Government had already decided to passa Family Allowances Bill during the current session; and he proposedthat the opportunity should be taken to include in this Bill provisionfor increasing family allowance by 2s. a week for third andsubsequent children. The cost of this increase would be about 10 millions in a full year. The discontinuance of the remainder ofthe bread subsidy would save  20 millions in a full year. He hopedthat both changes could come into effect on 1st October.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) This change might not be specially popular with Governmentsupporters, but it was sound social policy.(b) This proposal, though it would add little to its length, wouldincrease the importance of the Family Allowances Bill; and if thechange was to come into operation by 1st October, the Bill wouldneed to be passed before the summer recess.(c) The Minister of Pensions said that, if too much emphasiswere laid on the link between the increase in family allowances andthe discontinuance of the bread subsidy, this would sharpen thedemand for a similar concession to pensioners.id) The Minister of Education said that, in connection with thecurrent review of the future trend of expenditure on the socialservices, he had been considering plans for reducing the subsidy onthe school meals service. This service had always been linked withfamily allowances; and it would be expected that any substantial* Originally recorded in a Confidential Annex.  1   3FamilyAllowances.(PreviousReference :CM. (56) 14thConclusions,andCM. (56) 24thConclusions,Minute 8.)
6reduction in this subsidy should be accompanied by some com-pensating increase in family allowances. This expectation wouldbe enhanced if the discontinuance of the bread subsidy had previouslybeen linked with an increase in family allowances. In these circum-stances it might be worth considering whether changes in the schoolmeals service could not also be announced in the Budget statement,together with a somewhat larger increase in family allowances thanthat now proposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Cabinet  0(1) Agreed in principle that the remainder of the bread subsidyshould be discontinued from 1st October, 1956, and thatsome change in family allowances should be brought intooperation at the same time in order to offset the effect onpeople with larger families.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to consider, inconsultation with the Lord Privy Seal, the Minister ofEducation and the Secretary of State for Scotland,whether it would be expedient to enlarge this scheme soas to cover at the same time the changes which were nowcontemplated in the school meals service.Post OfficeFinance.(PreviousReference :CM. (55) 35thConclusions,Minute 8.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thePostmaster-General (CP. (56) 94) submitting proposals for meetingthe additional expenses of  20 millions which would fall on the PostOffice as a result of recent increases in wages and salaries and othercosts.The Postmaster-General said that he hoped in the coming yearto provide  5 millions towards this increase by means of economies,increased efficiency and reduction of his budgetary surplus. Hisproposals for finding the remaining  15 millions were set out inAppendix A to CP. (56) 94. The first question for decision by theCabinet was whether the ordinary letter postage should be raisedfrom 2\d. to 3d. or whether increases should be made in the ratesof printed papers and samples. The former measure would raise 6 millions, but the Post Office were already making an annual profitof  10 millions on the letter postage, and an annual loss of  4 millionson printed papers and samples. To increase the charges for bothcategories would mean raising more money from the postal side thanwas necessary. To increase the letter postage would take timebecause of the preparations involved. It would also be difficultpolitically. For these reasons he would prefer to increase the ratefor printed papers and samples, which would yield  3   9 millions inthe coming year.The Cabinet agreed that the ordinary letter postage should notbe increased. It was confirmed that no increase would be made inthe overseas rates for printed papers and samples.The Postmaster-General said that the other point on which hewould welcome guidance was whether the poundage rates on postalorders should be increased. In Annex A of CP. (56) 94 it wassuggested that the rate for 6d. and Is. postal orders should be raisedto Id. and that the rate for orders for 1*. 6d. to 55. should be raisedto 3d. This might cause a brisk public reaction, since postal ordersof low value were much used in connection with competitions andbetting. It would be possible to raise the  1 million extra revenuerequired by making a further increase in the cheap evening rate fortrunk telephone calls. The cheap evening rate was causingincreasingly heavy traffic,requiring provision of additional trunk lines.It would be justifiable to remove the maximum limit of 2s. proposedin CP. (56) 94: this would mean in practice a maximum charge of2s. 6d. for cheap evening trunk calls.
7CM. 27 (56)There was general agreement that no increase should be made inthe poundage on postal orders and that the necessary money shouldbe found by increasing the revenue from cheap evening trunk calls.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals for increased telephone and postalcharges put forward in C.P. (56) 94, subject to the deletionof the proposed increases in the poundage on postal ordersand to the removal of the upper limit of 2s. on the costof trunk telephone calls at the cheap evening rate.(2) Authorised the Postmaster-General to make a summaryannouncement of these changes on 11th April, in a replyto a Parliamentary Question, and to circulate the fulldetails in the Official Record.InternationalLabourOrganisation.(PreviousReference :C.C. (54) 9thConclusions,Minute 12.)7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Labour (C.P. (56) 93) regarding an International LabourConvention (No. 101) on holidays with pay for agricultural workers.The Minister of Labour recalled that in February, 1954 theCabinet had decided not to ratify this Convention on the ground thatthe powers of Agricultural Wages Boards to fix holidays with paywere not obligatory and that, although the Boards had in factexercised these powers, it might be thought inconsistent with theirdiscretion for the Government to assume an obligation to enforcethe Convention. The Trades Union Congress had subsequentlyasked that this decision should be reconsidered because of the extentto which it was being misrepresented by Communist-dominatedorganisations abroad. In view of this the Minister now recommendedthat the Government should ratify the Convention.The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said that the ColonialOffice supported this proposal. The application of the Convention toColonial territories could be made dependent on local conditions.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the Government should ratify the InternationalLabour Convention (No. 101) on holidays with pay foragricultural workers.(2) Invited the Minister of Labour to consider whether theannouncement of this decision need be made by presenta-tion of a White Paper or whether it would suffice to makea short statement in reply to a Parliamentary Question.CapitalPunishment.(PreviousReference :CM. (56) 20thConclusions,Minute 2.)8. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland (C.P. (56) 92) onthe attitude which the Government should take towards amendmentsto be moved during the Committee Stage of the Death Penalty(Abolition) Bill.In the course of a preliminary discussion some doubts wereexpressed about the specific recommendations made in paragraph 15of this memorandum. Thus, while it was desirable that theGovernment should show their readiness to protect policemen andprison officers from the risk of violence, the retention of capitalpunishment as a penalty for murders of specified classes of personswould introduce into the law the conception of degrees of murder, towhich the Government had hitherto been opposed. Moreover, if inrelation to these or other amendments the Government gave definiteadvice to the House, they woud find themselves in an embarrassingposition if on a free vote the decision went against the advice which
8they had given. Opinion on this question in the House of Commonswas changing, and some of the Government supporters who hadpreviously favoured abolition were now prepared to consider somecompromise. Some of them, for example, had indicated theirreadiness to accept the amendment tabled by Sir Hugh Lucas-Tooth,which would have the effect that capital punishment would be retainedfor murder committed by a lethal weapon in the course of burglary,house-breaking or robbery, or by a prisoner serving a life sentence.Acceptance of this amendment would, however, leave the law in ananomalous condition. The promoter of the Bill might indeed regardit as a wrecking amendment and, if it were carried, might decide notto proceed further with the Bill.After some further discussion the Cabinet agreed that, beforedecisions could be taken on the questions raised in CP. (56) 92, theLord Privy Seal should discuss with the Ministers most directlyconcerned the tactics for handling the Committee Stage of this Bill.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to discuss the tactics for handlingthe Committee Stage of this Bill with the Lord Chancellor,the Home Secretary, the Secretary of State for Scotland,the Attorney-General and the Chief Whip.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion of this question at a latermeeting.British 9.   The Minister of Transport recalled that at their meeting onTransport        13th March the Cabinet had agreed that one-half of the increases inCommission.    freight charges proposed by the British Transport Commission should(Previous        be deferred for an experimental period of six months, after whichReference:      the Government would review the Commission&apos;s financial positionCM. (56) 23rd  in the light of the progress made in securing greater efficiency andConclusions.     economy.   Since then he had sought the advice of the permanentMinute 5.)       members of the Transport Tribunal, acting as a consultativecommittee, and he had now received from them a report whichadvised, not only that the full increase in freight charges originallyproposed by the Commission was justified, but that even with thisadditional revenue and that from other smaller increases in chargesthe Commission had little prospect of meeting their statutoryobligation of securing a sufficient revenue to meet their costs, takingone year with another, and of establishing and maintaining a generalreserve.    The  Minister  of  Transport  was  due  to  answer aParliamentary Question on the following day asking what advice hehad received from the Transport Tribunal,  and it would beimpossible to avoid making the report public.   This would drawattention to the financial difficulties under which the Commissionwere labouring. He thought that at the end of the six months&apos; periodit might be advisable to publish a White Paper setting out themeasures which the Transport Commission had formulated in theinterval to increase their efficiency and to improve their financialposition.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Minister of Transport.Kashmir.(PreviousReference :C.C. (52) 103rdConclusions,Minute 4.)10. The Minister of Defence said that he would be representingthe United Kingdom at the forthcoming meeting of the Council ofthe Bagdad Pact in Teheran. It was likely that Pakistan&apos;srepresentative, possibly with support from the representative ofTurkey, would seek to persuade the Council to discuss at this meetingthe problem of Kashmir. It could be argued that this was of-interestto the Council, since Pakistan might be unable to fulfil her obligations
9CM. 27 (56)under the Pact if she had to protect herself against aggression fromIndia. The Commonwealth Secretary had asked that he shouldprevent this subject from being discussed at the meeting. He wouldlike, however, to know how far he should go in opposing its inclusionin the agenda or in the communique.In discussion it was pointed out that it would give great offenceto India if, after the reference to Kashmir which had&quot; been included inthe communique of the last meeting of the Council of the South-EastAsia Treaty Organisation (S.E.A.T.O.), this question was againdiscussed by the Council of another regional defence pact. On theother hand, it would be a mistake to press our opposition to thepoint of end angering the solidarity of the members of the Bagdad Pact.It might be helpful if a personal message were sent to the Governor-General of Pakistan stressing the disadvantages of attempting toventilate this problem at the Teheran meeting. The Minister ofDefence should also do his best, at the meeting, to dissuade othermembers from raising the question. If, despite these efforts, it wereraised, it was desirable that as little as possible should be said aboutit in the communique which should not, in any event, go further onthis point than the communique* of the last meeting of the Council ofS.E.A.T.O.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to send a personalmessage to the Governor-General of Pakistan urging himto use his influence to prevent Pakistan&apos;s representativefrom raising the question of Kashmir at the forthcomingmeeting of the Council of the Bagdad Pact in Teheran.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence to deal with this question, atthe Teheran meeting, on the lines agreed in the Cabinet&apos;sdiscussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.I,10th April. 1956.

</content>
</cab>
