<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/30/0 images: 329-334</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1956SECRETCM. (56)34th ConclusionsCopy No.CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.I,on Tuesday, 8th May, 1956, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. the Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for CommonwealthRelations.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C, M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft.M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The  Right Hon.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. the Earl of Selkirk,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.Patrick Buchan-The  Right  Hon.  Patrick BuchanHepburn, M.P., Minister of Works.The following were also present:The Most Hon. the Marquess ofReading, Q.C, Minister of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir Reginald Manning-ham-Buller, Q.C, M.P., Attorney-General (Item 1).The Right Hon. Lord Strathclyde,Minister of State, Scottish Office(Items 2-3).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. H. O. Hooper.Mr. J. M. Wilson.49937 4
ContentsMinuteNo.                                      Subject Page1 Prince of Hanover .................. 32 Nationalised Industries ................ 3Parliamentary Control.3 Automation ............... ...... 44 Malta ........................ 55 Cyprus ........................ 6
3CM. 34 (56)Prince of 1.   The Cabinet were informed that the Court of Appeal,Hanover.       reversing the judgment of the High Court, had recognised the claim(Previous        by Prince Ernst of Hanover to be a British subject by virtue of anReference :      Act of 1705 (4 and 5 Anne, Chapter IV). This decision would extendC.C. (55) 19th   British nationality to about 400 other European nationals, mainlyConclusions,    Germans, and might throw doubt on the validity of certain marriages.Minute 9.)      In view of the consequences involved it was considered that the issueshould be determined on the highest legal authority, and it was there-fore proposed that the case should be taken on appeal to the Houseof Lords.In discussion doubts were expressed about the need to undertakean appeal against the judgment of the Court of Appeal. It wasagreed that the considerations on both sides should be exploredfurther. On this issue the Lord Chancellor could properly beconsulted; for, if the case came to the House of Lords, the LordChancellor would be unable to take part in the judicial proceedingssince he had joined in earlier Cabinet discussions on the matter.The Cabinet Invited the Lord Chancellor to consider, in consultation withthe Home Secretary and the Attorney-General, whether anappeal should be made to the House of Lords against thejudgment of the Court of Appeal on the claim of PrinceErnst of Hanover to British nationality.NationalisedIndustries.ParliamentaryControl.(PreviousReference :CM. (56) 32ndConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Lord PrivySeal (CP. (56) 114) proposing the appointment of a new SelectCommittee on the nationalised industries.The Lord Privy Seal said that it would be difficult to resist thegrowing political pressure for increased Parliamentary control overthe conduct of the nationalised industries. There appeared to bethree possible solutions. The first was to provide further time forDebates and Questions in the House of Commons. This was unlikelyto satisfy the present demand, and in any event it would be almostimpossible to make further time available, particularly during thecurrent session of Parliament. The second was to appoint a StandingCommittee. He could not recommend this course; for, in the presentstate of opinion on this subject, it would not be practicable to securea Government majority in such a Committee. He himself believedthat the only practicable solution was to appoint a new SelectCommittee of eleven members with simplified terms of reference onthe lines proposed in paragraph 10 of CP. (56) 114. There wasadmittedly a risk that, even with these terms of reference, the Com-mittee would project its discussions from past fact to future policy.This risk could, however, be mitigated by the safeguards set out inparagraph 11 of his memorandum. Proposals on these lines wereacceptable to the Minister of Transport and the Minister of Fuel andPower. If the Cabinet endorsed them, it was for considerationwhether they should not be announced before the forthcoming debatein the House of Commons on the coal industry.In discussion there was general support for the proposals putforward by the Lord Privy Seal. Though the activities of this SelectCommittee were likely to prove embarrassing to the Governmentfrom time to time, this was the most acceptable means of meetingthe political pressure for further Parliamentary control over theconduct of the nationalised industries.In discussion the following particular points were also made:  {a) It might still be desirable on occasions to appoint specialexternal committees to report on particular aspects of the nationalisedindustries on the lines of recent reports on the electricity and coalindustries.49937 4
4(b) It would be important for the Select Committee to establishand maintain harmonious relations with the nationalised industries.From this point of view the choice of a suitable Chairman was ofspecial importance.(c) The Committee might be able to help the nationalisedindustries in the recruitment of suitable staff by giving more publicityto the careers that were available in these industries.(d) The Select Committee would assume, in respect of thenationalised industries, functions comparable to those discharged bythe Public Accounts Committee in respect of direct Governmentexpenditure. It would therefore be appropriate that it should becalled the &quot; Nationalised Industries Accounts Committee.&quot;(e) The Chancellor of the Exchequer confirmed that he would bewilling to arrange for a Treasury official to assist the new Committeeas proposed in paragraph 11 (b) of C.P. (56) 114.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C.P. (56) 114 for the appointmentof a Nationalised Industries Accounts Committee.(2) Invited the Prime Minister to announce the appointment ofthis Committee before the forthcoming debate on the coalindustry in the House of Commons on 10th May.Automation. 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Ministerof Labour (C.P. (56) 113) on the responsibilities which it would beappropriate for the Government to assume in regard to the problemscreated by the increasing development of automation in industry.The Cabinet also had before them the draft of a statement on thissubject which the Minister of Labour proposed to make in reply toParliamentary Questions that afternoon.The Minister of Labour said that there was a genuine fear amongindustrial workers that the increasing introduction of automation inindustry would endanger their livelihood. Both the United Statesand the Soviet Union had decided that the problems to whichautomation would give rise were sufficiently important to justify thecreation of special Government machinery to handle them. In thiscountry the primary responsibility for solving the problems ofredundancy and adjustment which would arise from the increasinguse of automation should rest on industry, but the Government mustbe seen to be taking a continuing and active interest in the socialand industrial effects. He had attempted in his draft statement toindicate a sympathetic approach on the part of the Governmenttowards these problems without undertaking responsibilities whichit would not be appropriate for the Government to assume. Hebelieved, however, that the Government would have to assume somedefinite obligation in connection with the effects of technologicalchanges on employment and, subject to his colleagues&apos; approval, heproposed to strengthen his draft statement in this sense. He also feltthat a Minister should be placed in charge of the proposed inter-departmental Committee which was to be set up to co-ordinate theGovernment&apos;s action in this field.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The development of automation should be welcomed. Itwas essential to our survival as a leading industrial Power that weshould be prompt to make full use of all the newest industrialtechniques.(b) Industry must accept the main responsibility for findingsolutions to the problems of adjustment to which automation wouldgive rise. A highly developed system of joint consultation alreadyexisted in most industries and it should be brought into play for this |
5CM. 34 (56)purpose. Automation had already been introduced into severalindustries, e.g., the chemical industry, without creating problemswhich the industry itself had not been able to handle.(c) The primary responsibility of Government was to ensure,through economic and monetary policy, that demand remained at ahigh level so that alternative employment would be available forworkers made redundant by automation. The Government&apos;sresponsibilities in connection with the direct effects of automationwould be residual in character and would be exercised mainly in theprovision of technical education and training, and in making availablethe facilities of the employment services for workers who wouldhave to change their employment. It was agreed that the draftParliamentary statement should be amended to show more clearly theresponsibilities which would rest on the Government and industryrespectively for meeting the problems which automation would cause.id) Further thought should, nevertheless, be given to the rolewhich the Government would be expected to play in this field. Therewould be time for such an examination, for the problem would notbe discussed with industry and the trade unions in the National JointAdvisory Council until the next meeting of the Council took placein several weeks&apos; time.(e) There would be considerable Parliamentary interest in anystatement which might be made on this subject. It had been proposedin a Private Member&apos;s Bill, which had been introduced in the previousyear but had made no progress, that a widely representativeAutomation and Electronics Committee should be established toconsider the consequences arising from automation. This proposalmight well be revived.The Cabinet (1) Approved in principle the proposals in CP. (56) 113, subjectto their further examination on the lines indicated inparagraph (d) above.(2) Approved, subject to amendment in accordance with thepoints recorded in paragraph (c) above, the draft statementwhich the Minister of Labour proposed to make in replyto Parliamentary Questions that day.(3) Invited the Minister of Labour to submit, for considerationby the Cabinet at their next meeting, a draft reply to theQuestions on this subject which the Prime Minister wasdue to answer on 10th May.Malta.(PreviousReference :CM. (56) 26thConclusions,Minute 6.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the ColonialSecretary (CP. (56) 110) summarising the legislative and other stepswhich would need to be taken to give effect to the recommendationsof the Round Table Conference on Malta.The Colonial Secretary said that the memorandum had beencirculated for the information of the Cabinet. Its purpose was toclarify a number of constitutional points which had caused someuncertainty. It was designed in particular to remove themisapprehension that the recommendations of the Conferencecould not constitutionally be implemented unless they were supportedby a two-thirds majority vote in the Malta Legislature. The Cabinetwould also wish to know that the prospects of reaching agreementwith the ecclesiastical authorities in Malta had now improved asa result of the influence which Lord Perth, a member of the RoundTable Conference, had been able to exert during a private visit tothe Island.The Cabinet-Took note of CP. (56) 110 and of the statement made bythe Colonial Secretary.
6Cyprus.(PreviousReference :CM, (56) 30thConclusions,Minute 2.)5. The Cabinet were informed that the Governor of Cyprushad decided not to recommend that the prerogative of mercy shouldbe exercised in favour of either of the two Cypriots who were nowunder sentence of death for murder. His decision would be announcedthat morning. It would doubtless arouse some feeling, and attemptsmight be made to raise the matter in the House of Commons. Formany years past the prerogative of mercy in respect of crimescommitted in Colonial territories had been exercised by ColonialGovernors. That did not wholly exhaust the Sovereign&apos;s prerogative;but it would in any event be out of order for Parliament to debatethe exercise of the prerogative.The Cabinet-Took note of this statement by the Colonial Secretary.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,8th May, 1956.0

</content>
</cab>
