<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/30/0 images: 624-634</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1956SECRET Copy No&gt;CM. (56)68th ConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.I,on Wednesday, 3rd October, 1956, at 10-45 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. the Marquess of Salis-bury, Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,- Minister   of   Housing   and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. the Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor (Item 11).The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for CommonwealthRelations.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education.The   Right   Hon.   Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Minister of Works.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions andNational Insurance (Item 3).The Right Hon. Anthony Nutting,M.P., Minister of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 1-10).Dr. the Right Hon. Charles Hill, M.P.,Postmaster-General (Item 1).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury(Items 1-4 and 9-11).Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. H. O. Hooper.Mr. P. R. Odgers.50638 1B
ContentsMinuteNo. Subject Page1 Opening of Parliament.................. 3Facilities for Television.2 Cyprus ......... ............... 3Constitutional Reform.United Nations.3 War Pensions ...... ............... 44 East/West Trade       ... ................ 4China.5 Tariff Policy ...... ............... 5Meat.6 Australia ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 6Trade Talks.7 Christmas Island        ... ............... 78 Morocco ...... ............... g9 International Bank and International Monetary Fund     ... 8Meeting at Washington.10 Commercial Policy     ... ............ 9Consultations with Commonwealth Representatives.11 Suez Canal ...... ......... jq
3CM. 68 (56)Opening ofParliament.Facilities forTelevision.(PreviousReference:C.C. (53) 46thConclusions,Minute 5.)1. The Lord President said that, at the Prime Minister&apos;s request,he had considered an application by the British BroadcastingCorporation for facilities to televise the Opening of Parliament. Herecalled that the previous Government had decided in 1953 that thetelevising of this ceremony should be discouraged. He believed thatthe considerations which had weighed with them then were stillconclusive. If the Speech from the Throne were itself televised, therewas a real risk that the Sovereign would appear to be drawn intopolitics. If on the other hand, the television programme omitted theSpeech, it would convey no impression of the real purpose andcontent of the ceremony. He therefore recommended that no facilitiesshould be given for televising the Opening.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were in agreement with thisview. The additional point was made that any facilities granted tothe B.B.C. would have to be extended to the Independent TelevisionAuthority and to the newsreel companies, and that there would begreat practical difficulties in finding room for all the apparatusrequired, whether in the Royal Gallery or in the Chamber itself.The Cabinet Agreed that no facilities should be given for televising theOpening of Parliament; and took note that the PrimeMinister would so inform the British BroadcastingCorporation.Cyprus. 2.   The Colonial Secretary said that the recent recrudescence of(Previous terrorism in Cyprus had had a most disturbing effect on public opinionReference: in the Island. This had seriously impaired the prospects for any earlyCM. (56) 66th progress with constitutional reform.   Lord Radcliffe had, however,Conclusions. gone some way in formulating his constitutional proposals; andMinute 3.) Ministers would wish to consider his proposals after his return fromConstitutional Cyprus. The Governor contemplated that a comprehensive statementReform OI Government policy would be issued soon after Lord Radcliffereturned to London.In discussion it was agreed that the suggestions made by theGovernor in Cyprus telegram No. 1992 should be considered in detailby the Colonial Policy Committee. The view was expressed that nofurther progress towards constitutional reform could properly bemade until order had again been restored in the Island.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Colonial Policy Committee to consider, in thelight of Lord Radcliffe&apos;s proposals for constitutionalreform in Cyprus, the suggestions made by the Governorof Cyprus in his telegram No. 1992 of 2nd October.United Nations. The Cabinet then considered a memorandum by the Minister ofState for Foreign Affairs (C.P. (56) 226) regarding the intention ofthe Greek Government to seek an opportunity, at the next meeting ofthe Assembly of the United Nations, to debate the application of theprinciple of self-determination to Cyprus.The Cabinet were informed that the Foreign Secretary wassatisfied that it would be impossible to prevent this item from beinginscribed on the agenda of the Assembly. That being so, he proposedto follow the alternative course of tabling a second item for discussioncharging the Greek Government with incitement to violence andterrorism in Cyprus.In discussion the Cabinet were assured that this course could befollowed without prejudicing our claim that the United Nations werenot entitled to discuss matters falling within the jurisdiction of amember country.50638 1 b 2
4The Cabinet (2) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to table, for discussionat the next meeting of the Assembly of the United Nations,an item charging the Greek Government with incitementto violence and terrorism in Cyprus.War Pensions. 3.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Minister(Previous of Pensions (C.P. (56) 212) recommending that additional allowancesReference:       should be paid to certain categories of disabled war pensioners.CM (56) 20th jne Minister of Pensions recalled that the Cabinet had agreedConclusions, jn jyjarch tnat he should investigate the case for paying someMinute 4.) additional allowance to pensioners of the First World War whosedisabilities became more burdensome with advancing age. He nowrecommended, with the support of medical opinion, that an additionalallowance, varying according to disability, up to a maximum of \5s.a week should be paid to disabled pensioners over the age of 65. Ifthis were done it would not be possible to ignore the claims ofyounger pensioners who were suffering from very serious disabilities,and he therefore proposed that corresponding provision should bemade for these cases. These were the two categories of pensionersover which public and Parliamentary opinion was most exercised.He was satisfied that the additional provision which he now proposedwould not lead to pressure for the further extension of social servicebenefits.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, before assenting tothese proposals, he would wish to view them in the context of theconcessions which might have to be made to war pensioners andretirement pensioners over the next year or so. He would like tohave an opportunity to consider this wider question in consultationwith the Minister of Pensions and the Minister of Labour. Hewould, however, be ready to reach decisions on the particularquestions raised in C.P. (56) 212.The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultationwith the Minister of Labour and the Minister of Pensions, toconsider the proposals in C.P. (56) 212 in the wider contextof other possible claims on behalf of war pensioners andretirement pensioners, and to report to the Cabinet beforethe end of the Parliamentary recess.East/WestTrade.China.(PreviousReference:CM. (56) 50thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theForeign Secretary (C.P. (56) 221) regarding a suggestion of theUnited States Government that the use of the exception proceduresunder the arrangements for control of trade with China should berestricted until the end of 1956.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that, since theGovernment&apos;s announcement on 14th May of their intention to makemore use of the exception procedures, there had been a considerableincrease in exports to China. We were now under considerablepressure from the United States Government to restrict this flow oftrade, but there were indications that when the ConsultativeCommittee met in December the United States Government would beready to adopt a more liberal interpretation of the controls. TheForeign Secretary therefore proposed that the United StatesAmbassador should be given a genera! assurance that until theDecember meeting we would proceed more slowly with the use of theexception procedures, particularly in regard to those items previouslyon the embargo list for Soviet countries.
5CM. 68 (56)In discussion there was general agreement that we should notaccept any definitive commitment to limit our trade with China: therecent easing of restrictions had been of particular value to our motorindustry and had been specially welcome to Malaya. The UnitedStates Government had agreed in January to review the controls onthe China trade, and the recent intimation by the United StatesAmbassador represented no new offer. On the other hand, withoutannouncing any change of policy, it would be possible to ensure byadministrative action that our use of the exception procedures wasnot accelerated between now and the end of the year, and it wasagreed that an assurance on these lines could be given to theAmerican Ambassador. The lists of items concerned should beexamined by the Board of Trade and the Foreign Office, but no itemsneed be debarred which were not embargoed for supply to Russia.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs to informthe United States Ambassador that we would notaccelerate our use of the exception procedures in relationto the China trade controls between now and the end ofthe year.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs, to arrangefor a review of the items affected.Tariff Policy.(PreviousReference:CM. (56) 35thConclusions,Minute 11.)Meat.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (56) 219) reporting arecommendation of the Economic Policy Committee that, in order toprovide a basis for the conclusion of a satisfactory settlement of ouroutstanding trade problems with Australia and New Zealand, theGovernment should be prepared to offer a preferential tariff on meat.The Minister of Agriculture said that, as a consequence of theeconomic policies now being pursued by the new ArgentineGovernment, a steady increase in the supply of Argentine chilled beefcould henceforward be expected. Both Australia and New Zealandwere seriously concerned at the prospect of losing their traditionalshare of the United Kingdom market for meat. Experience hadshown that, with Argentine supplies flowing in quantity, uncontrolledcompetition in imported meat resulted in depressed prices;competition had not been uncontrolled before the war, when it hadbeen regulated both by a quota system and a tariff. This tariff wasstill in force, but its ad valorem incidence had now fallen to about4 per cent. As we were precluded by our commitments under theGeneral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade from reintroducing a quotasystem for meat, a preferential tariff with an ad valorem incidencerelated to the current value of money represented the only meansopen to us of assisting Australia and New Zealand. The authorityof the Cabinet was sought for a preferential tariff of 15 per cent.; atariff of 10 per cent, would, however, be offered in the first instanceand the higher figure would be put forward only after furtherconsideration by the Committee of Ministers who were in charge ofthe trade talks with Australia. Nevertheless, the possibility must beforeseen that even a tariff of 15 per cent, would prove inadequate toregulate the flow of imports from Argentina in favour of the twoCommonwealth countries concerned and that, notwithstanding ourinternational commitments, the restoration of a quota system mighthave to be contemplated at a later date.In discussion the following points were made (a) Some disquiet was expressed over the prospect that a tariffon meat might lead to a rise in the cost of living. Although thesuccess of the Government&apos;s economic policies depended on keeping
6the cost of living as stable as possible, the prices of such basicnecessities as bread, milk, rents, fares and coal would all have risenwithin the last year as a result of decisions taken by the Government.The proposed tariff on meat would not come into effect immediately,but it would be taken into account in formulating wage claims assoon as the proposal to impose it became known. It was important,therefore, that the announcement of the Government&apos;s intentionto impose a tariff on meat should not follow closely on the removal ^of the bread subsidy but should be deferred for as long as  possible.The Minister of Agriculture said that, as the price of meat hadbeen falling, it was doubtful whether the proposed tariff would causean increase in the cost of living of even -6 per cent, as had beenestimated. It seemed likely that meat prices would fall by more than15 per cent.(b) The purpose of the proposed offer of a preferential tariff onmeat was to forestall a request from New Zealand for a review ofthe Ottawa Agreements and to enable us to secure the re-negotiationof our onerous long-term meat agreement with Australia. It was alsohoped that, in return for the proposed tariff and the offer regardingwheat which we might be able to put forward, we should succeed inretaining the greater part of the preferences which we now enjoyedin the Australian market for our exports of capital goods. From thetrade point of view, these advantages would be a very satisfactoryreturn for the proposed tariff.(c) In any public announcement regarding the proposed tariff,emphasis should be laid on the fact that it was designed to restorethe traditional position which Commonwealth suppliers had enjoyedin the United Kingdom market, and that, notwithstanding the tariff,Commonwealth meat would continue to enter this market freely.The point should also be made that the Commonwealth countriesconcerned had a valid case under the Ottawa Agreements, from whichwe derived reciprocal benefits for support of the kind proposed.The Cabinet Approved, subject to the points made in their discussion,the proposals in paragraph 12 of CP. (56) 219 regarding apreferential tariff on meat.Australia.Trade Talks.(PreviousReference:CM. (56) 52ndConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Agriculture (CP. (56) 224) regarding the basis on whichdiscussions should be resumed with Australia with the aim ofreaching a comprehensive trade agreement. The memorandumrecalled that the talks had been adjourned in July to enable HerMajesty&apos;s Government to examine how best to secure wideropportunities for the expansion of Australia&apos;s traditional exports tothe United Kingdom, in particular of wheat. The possibilities hadsince been considered of imposing quota restrictions on imports ofwheat and flour from all sources other than Australia, of introducingstatutory control over the composition of the loaf and of chargingcountervailing duties on imports of subsidised wheat, but there weresevere objections to all of these. There remained the possibility ofsecuring a voluntary arrangement with the millers and the grain tradethat they should use their best endeavours to take a specifiedminimum quantity of Australian wheat, and it was proposed toresume the negotiations on this footing. Any such arrangementwould however have the disadvantages of running counter to theGovernment&apos;s policy of freeing trade from Government interferenceand of tending to increase prices; it might lead to requests for similartreatment for other commodities or for other countries; and it wouldnot be welcome to the home farmers in that the millers would not beable to increase their present commitment in respect of English wheat,
7 CM. 68 (56)or to the Canadians who would regard the arrangement as discrimin-atory. Such a &quot; best endeavours undertaking could amount in thelast resort to some 850,000 tons of Australian wheat. This would,however, fall short of the Australian demand of a guaranteed marketfor 1   1 million tons. The only means of increasing our offer wouldbe to persuade the compounders of animal feeding stuffs to take, say,150,000 tons of Australian wheat, but they would require a subsidy tocompensate them for the higher price involved. The technicalproblems involved were being urgently examined in consultation withthe trades concerned.The Cabinet also had before them a memorandum by thePresident of the Board of Trade (C.P. (56) 225) supporting theresumption of negotiations on the basis outlined in C.P. (56) 224 andurging that study of the possibility of importing Australian wheat foranimal feed should be completed as soon as possible.The Minister of Agriculture said that he did not favour theproposed voluntary arrangement because of the disadvantages towhich his memorandum referred. He could not, however, see anysatisfactory alternative. Discussions were now in progress with thecompounders of animal feeding stuffs, but it might prove impossibleto arrive at a workable agreement. He doubted whether the anxietiesof the Australian Government regarding the market for Australianwheat in this country were really shared by Australian producers.The Australian Government had, however, chosen to make a majorissue of the market in wheat, and the preferences which our exportsenjoyed gave them a powerful bargaining weapon.The President of the Board of Trade said that we should not atthis stage rule out the possibility of taking further supplies ofAustralian wheat for animal feed. Wheat was the vital factor in thetrade negotiations with Australia; and, if we desired to retainguaranteed preferences of the order of 10 per cent, on capital goods,we might well have to be prepared to take more than 850,000 tons ayear of Australian wheat. It was important, therefore, that a detailedscheme should be worked out so that the Cabinet might be able tochoose between such a scheme, with all the difficulties which it mightinvolve, or the loss of our preferences.There was general agreement that negotiations should beresumed with the Australian Government on the basis of a &quot; bestendeavours &quot; undertaking of up to 850,000 tons a year of Australianwheat in return for satisfactory undertakings on the Australian side,and that examination of the possibility of importing further quantitiesof Australian wheat for animal feed should be completed as a matterof urgency. This examination should cover the question whetherlegislation would be required.The Cabinet Approved the proposals made in C.P. (56) 224 and 225.ChristmasIsland.7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theColonial Secretary (C.P. (56) 196) on the future of Christmas Island.The Colonial Secretary recalled that the Prime Minister ofAustralia had asked in March that, in view of the uncertaintyregarding future political developments in Singapore, ChristmasIsland should either be transferred to Australia or should be detachedfrom Singapore and administered separately by the United Kingdom.There were no historical, social, racial or economic reasons why theisland should continue to be administered by Singapore. On theother hand, its economic and strategic importance to Australia wassuch as to provide a very strong case for the Australian request. Ifthe Cabinet agreed in principle that Christmas Island should no
8longer be administered from Singapore he would explore with theGovernor of Singapore how best effect could be given to this. In anyevent it would be necessary to negotiate a financial settlement withthe Government of Singapore, which at present received about 130,000 a year from the Island in the form of royalties from theworking of phosphate deposits.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Australia would be quite willing that Christmas Island shouldbe administered as a separate United Kingdom dependency. It was,however, too small to justify a separate Colonial administration as apermanent measure.(b) There could be no question of compensating the Governmentof Singapore for the transfer of administration. It was recognised,however, that it would not be possible to deprive Singapore of therevenue which its Government at present enjoyed from the Island,more particularly when the grant of full internal self-government wasin prospect.(c) No expense ought to fall on the United Kingdom Govern-ment The Government of Singapore might, however, continue toreceive the present revenues from the Island for so long as thephosphate deposits were being worked, less all reasonable costs ofadministration.There was general agreement that Christmas Island should besevered from the administration of the Government of Singapore andthat a financial settlement should be made on the lines discussed.Whether or not the Island should subsequently be administered byAustralia or as a United Kingdom dependency would require furtherconsideration.The Cabinet (1) Agreed in principle that Christmas Island should be severedfrom the administration of the Government of Singapore.(2) Invited the Colonial Secretary to discuss with the Governorof Singapore the steps that should be taken to this end,both as to method and timing.(3) Agreed that the financial arrangements should be as set outin paragraphs (b) and (c) above.(4) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to inform the PrimeMinister of Australia (and the Government of NewZealand as necessary) of the Cabinet&apos;s decision.Morocco. 8.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theForeign Secretary (C.P. (56) 217) proposing that negotiations shouldbe opened with the Moroccan Government for the renunciation of theUnited Kingdom&apos;s remaining capitulatory rights inside Morocco.The Cabinet-Approved the proposals made in C.P. (56) 217.Internationa]Bank andInternationalMonetary Fund.(PreviousReference:CM. (55) 32ndConclusions,Minute 2.)Meeting atWashington.9. The Chancellor of the Exchequer reported to the Cabineton the meetings of the governing bodies of the International Bankand the International Monetary Fund which he had attended inWashington in the previous week.It had not been the practice of the International Bank to tie theloans which they made to Governments for development work tocontracts to be placed in the country or countries supplying, throughthe Bank, the capital for these loans. In spite of the calls which mighthave been made, as in the case of the Kariba Dam, on the resourceswhich we ourselves contributed to the Bank&apos;s investment funds, hewas satisfied that we had on balance benefited from this system of
9CM. 68 (56)&quot; untied &quot; loans. He had, however, arranged to have this questionre-examined in case a &quot; tied &quot; system might, in certain circumstances,be more advantageous to us.The rules of the Bank had hitherto provided that the contractswhich the Bank financed should be let by international tender, fromwhich no country, whether a member of the Bank or not, wouldbe excluded. As a result of their experience over the proposedHigh Dam in Egypt, when there had been some risk that the contractfor a project partly financed or underwritten by the InternationalBank might be awarded to the Soviet bloc, the Bank had decided toamend their rules to provide that tenders for contracts which theyfinanced would henceforward be accepted only from firms of membercountries.The Bank were also considering a further amendment of theirrules to enable loans to be made to finance suitable projectsundertaken by private enterprise. This was to be welcomed.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had offered noresistance to Egypt&apos;s request to draw on the International MonetaryFund, in order to avoid prejudicing our own position should it provenecessary for us to have recourse to the Fund. As a result of theSuez dispute the reserves had declined significantly in August and inSeptember. This decline was attributable, not to any disequilibriumin the balance of trade, where the position remained fundamentallyhealthy, but to a certain reluctance in oversea financial centres toretain balances in sterling while the international situation remaineduncertain. If this decline were to continue, the resources whichwould be available to us in the International Monetary Fund wouldbe a valuable support for sterling.The Cabinet Took note of these statements by the Chancellor of theExchequer.Commercial 10.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that during their visitPolicy. to Washington in the previous week the President of the Board of(Previous Trade and he had explained to Commonwealth representatives theReference: proposals for a free trade area in Europe and had circulated aCM. (56) 66th memorandum describing them. It had been made clear that theConclusions, United Kingdom Government were not committed to these proposalsMinute 2.) and had no intention of reaching a decision until other Coramon-wealth countries had been consulted and given adequate time toconsultations colder them. The proposals had, however, been accorded a n surprisingly friendly reception by the Commonwealth representativescommonwealth present m Washington. Canada, whose attitude was speciallyRepresentatives. irnp0rtantj raised no objection to the proposals and seemed inclinedto favour them. She could be expected to base her attitude on theextent to which, in her judgment, they would be likely to lead to thestrengthening of the United Kingdom economy to a point whenrestrictions on dollar trade could be removed, fn regard to tariffs,she would be concerned to retain the preferences which her exportsenjoyed over American goods in our market. The main interest ofother Commonwealth countries, despite some references which weremade to their developing industries, lay in maintaining their marketin the United Kingdom for agricultural products. New Zealandhad taken up a characteristically helpful attitude and had indicatedher willingness to follow the lead and judgment of the UnitedKingdom. India was more exercised over Asiatic than Europeancompetition in our market. The discussions disclosed, however, thatCommonwealth countries generally were especially concerned tosecure an adequate volume of investment capital for their develop-ment, and their attitude towards the proposals would be determinedlargely by their judgment whether they would be likely to lead to a50638 1 c
10greater accumulation of investment capital in the old world for thedevelopment of newer countries. There was some fear lest, as aresult of the proposals, the investment resources of the UnitedKingdom might be diverted away from the Commonwealth andtowards Europe.It had unfortunately not been possible to maintain strictconfidence about these discussions and distorted accounts of theplan had appeared in the Press. In order to correct any misconcep-tions which might have been gained, both in regard to the plan itself %and our attitude towards it, he proposed, with his colleagues&apos;approval, to make an official statement on the matter at a Pressconference that afternoon.Some disquiet was expressed in discussion that the Governmentshould be faced with little choice but to make a public statementabout proposals which were still under consideration and on whichthe Cabinet had not yet reached a decision. The proposed statement,of which the Chancellor of the Exchequer read relevant extracts,would however make it clear that the Government intended to takeno decision on the matter until consultations both at home and withCommonwealth and European countries abroad had proceededfurther. The statement would also set out the fundamentalconditions on which we must be satisfied before we could contemplateentering a free trade area in Europe, viz., the exclusion of agriculturalproducts from the scope of the agreement, and the preservation bothof the interests of Commonwealth agriculture in the United Kingdommarket and of the system of Commonwealth preferences. It wasagreed that, as matters had developed, it was on balance desirablethat a corrective statement on these lines should be issued.The Cabinet (1) Took note with approval of the statement of the Chancellorof the Exchequer on the discussions which had takenplace with Commonwealth representatives in Washington.(2) Authorised the Chancellor of the Exchequer and thePresident of the Board of Trade to make a publicstatement on the lines he had proposed to representativesof the Press that afternoon.Suez Canal.(PreviousReference:CM. (56) 67thConclusions,Minute 5.)11. *The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet of the resultsof the conversations which he and the Foreign Secretary had heldwith French Ministers during their visit to Paris on 26th and27th September.The Prime Minister said that he was impressed by the vigour ofM. Mollet&apos;s Government and their uncompromising attitude towardsthe Suez situation. They were determined that Colonel Nasser&apos;saction should not go uncorrected. They believed that, if his ambitionswere not checked, the political as well as the economic future ofEurope would be in jeopardy. For they feared that, in that event,existing regimes in other Arab States would collapse and the MiddleEast would pass under the influence, not so much of Egypt, but ofthe Soviet Union. If that happened, Europe itself would be at themercy of the Russians. It was for these reasons that the French wereimpatient at the obstacles which were preventing the Western Powersfrom imposing a satisfactory settlement on the Egyptian Government.They were especially resentful of the attitude of the United StatesGovernment, many of whose statements were calculated to encouragethe Russians to believe that they could, without undue danger, supportColonel Nasser in an intransigent attitude. There was indeed a riskthat the Soviet Union might conclude a pact of mutual assistance withEgypt. If that happened, it would become much more hazardous toattempt to impose a settlement of this dispute by force.* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.
11CM. 68 (56)The Prime Minister said that it was difficult to forecast the courseof the forthcoming discussions in the Security Council. There nowseemed less reason to believe that the Egyptian Government wouldconsider a solution on the lines which Mr. Krishna Menon hadcanvassed during his recent visit to London, and there were noindications of the attitude which the Egyptians were likely to adopt inthe Security Council. If they continued to be obdurate, world opinionmight be readier to support a recourse to forceful measures. If theyoffered to negotiate, the task of achieving a satisfactory settlementwould be more difficult and more protracted. In either event theweeks ahead would be critical; and the Government&apos;s task had notbeen made easier by the public statements made by Oppositionleaders in this country and by members of the United StatesAdministration.In discussion the following points were raised:  (a) The view was expressed that a solution might yet be foundon the genera! lines suggested by Mr. Krishna Menon, if means couldbe found for supporting a scheme of that kind by effective sanctions.(b) On the other hand it was recognised that our objectives wouldnot be fully attained if we accepted a settlement of the Suez Canaldispute which left Colonel Nasser&apos;s influence undiminishedthroughout the Middle East.(c) There was little doubt that, among the Arab peoples of theMiddle East, Colonel Nasser&apos;s prestige was increasing. And therewas evidence that he was already seeking to foment discontent withthe existing regimes in other Arab countries. Disturbing reports hadbeen received of dissident movements in Libya, Saudi Arabia andIraq.{d) Among the leaders of organised labour in this countryopinion was hardening against the use of force as a means of securinga settlement of the Suez dispute. If it became necessary to haverecourse to force, industrial trouble must be expected, especially inthe docks and in the coal mines. On the other hand, there wassome evidence that among the workers themselves there was moresupport for the Government&apos;s policy than might be assumed fromthe public statements of their leaders.The Cabinet-Took note of the Prime Minister&apos;s statements and of thepoints raised in the discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.I,4th October, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
