<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/30/0 images: 697-700</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1956SECRET Copy No.CM. (56)76th ConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Wednesday, 31st October, 1956, at 12 30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime MinisterThe Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for CommonwealthRelations.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. the Earl of Selkirk,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Minister of Works.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,   The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Q.C., First Lord of the Admiralty. Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Nigel Birch, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air. Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.50746 2
ContentsMinuteNo. Subject Page1 Parliament ............... ...... 32 Suez Canal ..................... 3
JCM. 76 (56)fariiament. 1.   The Lord Privy Seal said that the leaders of the LabourParty had decided to table a Vote of Censure for debate on1st November, and had asked that the Prorogation of Parliamentshould be postponed until 5th November. He suggested that heshould try to secure their agreement to Prorogation at 4 p.m. on2nd November.The Cabinet a Invited the Lord Privy Seal to seek the agreement of the  leaders of the Labour Party to the postponement of theProrogation of Parliament until 4 p.m. on 2nd November.Suez Canal.(PreviousReference:CM. (56) 75thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. After the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on 30th October a meetinghad been held in London with the Prime Minister and ForeignMinister of France at which agreement had been reached on the termsof the communications to be addressed to the Governments of Egyptand Israel. These communications called upon both sides to stopall warlike action, by land, sea and air, and to withdraw their forcesto a distance of ten miles from the Suez Canal. The EgyptianGovernment were also asked to allow Anglo-French forces to movetemporarily into key positions at Port Said, Ismailia and Suez, inorder to separate the belligerents and to guarantee freedom of transitthrough the Canal by the ships of all nations. A reply had beenrequested within twelve hours; and it had been made clear that, ifat the expiration of that time one or both Governments had notundertaken to comply with these requirements, British and Frenchforces would intervene in whatever strength might be necessary tosecure compliance. These communications had been delivered tothe Egyptian and Israeli representatives in London shortly before4-30 p.m. on 30th October. Before midnight on that day the IsraeliGovernment had replied that they would accept these requirementsif they were accepted by Egypt. A few hours later the EgyptianGovernment had replied that they were unable to accept therequirements.The Prime Minister said that in these circumstances theCommander-in-Chief of the Anglo-French forces had been authorisedto put into operation the approved plan for enforcing compliancewith the requirements of the two Governments. At dusk that eveninghe would begin air operations designed to cripple the Egyptian AirForce.The Minister of Defence recommended that a public warningshould be issued during the day advising civilians in Egypt to keepclear of airfields. This would help to reduce civilian casualties; and itwas not open to any military objection, since it would not disclosewhich airfields were to be attacked.Information had, however, been received that United Statescitizens were being evacuated from Cairo to Alexandria, during thenext twelve hours, by a road which ran through the Cairo Westairfield, which was one of the targets to be attacked. It was forconsideration whether the general warning which was to be issued wasa sufficient safeguard against the loss of American lives in thisoperation.In discussion it was agreed that every effort should be made topostpone the attack on this particular airfield until the evacuationof these United States citizens had been carried out. If this partof the operation could not be postponed, a special warning should besent to the United States Ambassador in Cairo.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for the issue of apublic warning advising civilians to keep clear of allEgyptian airfields.
4(2) Invited the Minister of Defence to defer, if possible, the attackon Cairo West airfield until the evacuation of UnitedStates citizens from Cairo had been carried out.(3) Agreed that, if this part of the air operation could not bepostponed, the Foreign Secretary should arrange for theUnited States Ambassador in Cairo to be warned at oncethat United States citizens should not be evacuated toAlexandria that evening by the road running throughCairo West airfield.(4) Took note that the Foreign Secretary would hold in readiness,for immediate issue if need arose, a warning to the SyrianGovernment that any Egyptian aircraft which wereallowed to use Syrian airfields would be liable to beattacked.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,1st November, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
