<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/33/0 images: 196-196</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government \From Sir P. Cox, 16th November 19J 7. [Addressed to Secretary of Stair for India, repealed to Foreign, Delhi, His Majesty&apos;s Minister, Teheran, and copy to (lateral Officer Commanding-in-Chief, Baghdad.)(Received at India Office ISth November, 10 a.m.)Last year, when trouble tlireatened on the 1&apos;akhtiari road, the issue of 600 rifles to the Illkhani was approved by His Majesty&apos;s Minister, the Government of India and Army Commander, and they were sen! to Ahwaz and deposited for safe custody in military charge.The Illkhani resigned shortly afterwards and the matter consequently remained in abeyance.Recently, in connection with our political relations with the Hakhtiaris and decision that we should support friendly (? elements), His Majesly&apos;s Minister, acting on recommendation of His Majesty&apos;a Oonsul-General, Ispahan, and Captain Xoel, has asked that 300 rifles and60,000 rounds be despatched to the present Illkhani Sardar XalTar, on whom we depend lor keeping Ahwaz-Ispahan road open and lor opposition to any possible Turko-Gerinan incursion. In this connection, His Majesty&apos;s Minister wired as follows :  &quot; It would, I think, be politic to let Sardar Zallar have the rilles. He is, I believe, the most sincere of all Khans in his friendliness for us and would do his best to intercept German agents and keep road open. I hope General Officer Commanding will consent to give them.&quot;This was laid before General Officer Commanding-in-Chief with full explanation and an expresion of the hope that lie would withdraw his objections. lie, however, replies that &quot; since lie has been in command he has consistently maintained the principle that arms should not, be distributed to tribesmen, and he is not prepared to depart from that principle in this instance. As he is responsible for maintaining area in question in a tranquil state, it would in his opinion be most unwise to distribute arms to individuals who, as is well known, may be with us to-day and against us to-morrow.&quot;As the question also affects political situation within sphere of His Majesty&apos;s Ministerand outside that of this Force I do not feel justilied in accepting this disposal of the matter without reference to His Majesty&apos;s Government and I request that they will issue such orders as they may deem necessary.

</content>
</cab>
