<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/33/0 images: 326-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A^A.B.153/43.AIR BOARD. Report to the Cabinet.24th November, 1917.rai 1.      The Board have been approached from more than onecy.      duarter with requests for permission to attempt to fly&quot;an aeroplane from America to this country.     The most serious of these proposals is from Mr. Handley Pagej the designer of the well-known large bombing machine bearing his name.The chief difficulty in giving effect to the proposal does not lie so much in the distance, which no doubt could be traversed by an aeroplane of the Handley Page type, as in the navigational problem and the absence at the present time bf any satisfactory means of taking an observation from an aeroplane, although instruments for the purpose are in course of development.The scheme would require the co-operation of the Admiralty in the form of the assistance of a certain number of patrol vessels.     The Board have carefully considered the matter and have come to the conclusion that the advantages to be derived from the successful accomplishment of the project would hardly counterbalance the risks at present Involved and would not justify a request to the Admiralty for the assistance in question.2.      The attention of the Board has been drawn to the prominence given by the Press to reports of flying accidents in this country.     This prominence is not justified by the number of accidents and has a detrimental effect on recruiting for the Royal Flying Corps..The following figures are of interest.    From the 1st January to 8th November, 1917 there were 298 fatal accidents during training for the Royal Flying Corps.     The distance flown was 37,270,000 miles, that is, one death for, each 125,067 miles flown, which is the equivalent to slightly -over five flights round the world.The Press Bureau, at the request of the Air Board, have issued a circular to the Press on the subject.ply. 3.      Deliveries of engines and aircraft have been as follows;Engines Aeroplanes SeaplanesTotal for the week ending 17th NovemberTotal for October 1917 Total for October 1916418*13081894 562354** 948137163333*** 90 100*Including 67 from France, 16 from America and 15 from Italy. **Including 5 from France. ***Including 4 from Iranee.(Signed) H.P.Harvey.Secretary to the Air Board.

</content>
</cab>
