<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/33/0 images: 426-428</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
27/Oen.J.-o./6622.WAR CABINET. Recruiting; for the Army,^4&apos;v;/Hemorand\im by the Secretary of State!!?EBllL ,    for War.&apos;**^iS^--v^V --------------I circulate a letter on the subject of Man-power received from the Field liarshal Commanding-in-Chief in France, which hears upon the note on the subject of Recruiting forwarded to the Y/ar Cabinet on 24th November.-   (G.T.2751).DERBY.28th November, 1917.COPY. -No. 0.B./1851.A.GENERAL HEADQUARTERS, British Armies in France. 24th November, 1917.Sir,I have the honour again to draw the attention of the Army Council to the very serious situation which is likely to arise in regard to man-power in so far as it concerns the British units of the British Armies in France.2,     In my letter No.a/67 (0,1) of the 2nd instant, I submitted a brief review of the situation, together with an estimate of the number of reinforcements which would be required from England prior to llarch 31st, 1918, if the British Armies in France were to be maintained up to establishment.3.     In War Office letter No. lSl/France/45 (A.6.2.) of the 3rd instant, which crossed my letter referred to above, certain facts in regard to the number of British reinforcements which will become arailable during the ensuing year were forwarded.   The figures contained in this letter have been oarefully examined.Phe; Secretary, War Office,London, S.W.
4.     Assuming that six divisions will be despatched to Italy, and that reinforcements for these divisions will have to be provided on the scale laid down in War Office letter Ho.033/2^06 (A.G.1.) of the 3rd November, it is evident from calculations based on previous experience that the British Infantry in France will be approximately 250,000 or about 40/&apos; below establishment on the 31st March next.5.    It will be fully recognized that under such conditions not only will the offensive power of the British Armies in France be completely paralysed, but their defensive power will also be curtailed, and they will not be able to hold the same amount of line as heretofore.6.     I am not aware whether the prospects of the supply of men have improved in any way since the beginning of the month, but whatever the, prospects, I   feel convinced that future policy in regard to this question should be governed by the two following factors, namely:-(a) The necessity of bringing such formations as do exist up to establishment by the 31st March next and of maintaining them at their establishment thereafter.(b) The advisability of making as little change as possible in the internal organization of a division,7.     In regard to (a), experience shows that the fighting value of units and formations depends greatly on their&quot;&apos;strength and on the rapidity with which casualties can be replaced. Conversely the moral of units which are consistently under establishment is, as a rule, low,8.     In regard to (b), although as a result of the experience gained in the war, some slight changes in the composition of a division have been made from time to time- e.g., the amalgamation of Brigade and Divisional Ammunition Columns, the reduction of the Divisional Artillery, the addition of Pioneer Battalions which have been proved to be essential - the division, practically as it stands, has formed the basis of our Organization which has now existed ffcr many years and which has stood the test of tima, and war.   I am strongly opposed to any drastic alteration or reduction in the composition or organization of a division, as it would undoubtedly create considerable dislocation throughout the Army both tactically and administratively.   Moreover, any reduction in the present establishment would be extravagent in bo far as staffs are concerned, and the question of finding commanders and staffs is becoming increasingly difficult.I am convinced that the retention of our existing organization combined with the maintenance of units up to establishment will prove to be the truest form cf economy in regard to man-power,9.     Should, therefore, any reduction of the fighting forces on the Western Front become necessary owing to the want of men, I am strongly of opinion that such reduction should be effected by the breaking up of such a number      divisions, together with their affiliated maintenance units, as will ensure the remainder being kept up to establishment.
10.     The following faots speak for themselves.(a)   From the figures given and the instructions contained in the War Office letters quoted in the margin, it is calculated that there will he a deficiency of 248,226 men in British Infantry units on the 31st March next.   Assuming that there will he 46 British Divisions in France the total strength of the Infantry will he 317,849, and the average strength of hattaliens 542 other ranks.(h)   3y breaking up one division, it is calculated that, with divisions at their present strength and excluding tradesmen and category &quot;Bn men, approximately 10,200 nAtt men will become available for transfer to infantry;   of these some 7,200 will be fully trained infantrymen.The abolition of a Corps Headquarters would release some 1,200 men, -Thus, a reduction of a complete Corps of 3 Divisions would immediately release about 32,000 men and subsequently would free a proportionate number of reinforcements.(c) Unless more men can be made available immediately, the maximum number of divisions in which all infantry battalions can be brought up to establishment by 1st April is 31.(d) In order to do this, however, it will be necessary in the first instance to break up 5 Corps and 15 Divisions as the completion of the units mentioned in (c) is dependent on the release of these men,11.    My plans fir holding the line and the dispositions of the troops for the Mnter depend on this matter being settled now.    Moreever, arrangements cannot be made for divisions to take.their turn for rest and training out of the line until the number of divisions to be maintained has been decided, whilst divisions themselves oannot train properly if they are very much below establishment.   It is all important that no time 3hould be lost to put into effect such measures of re-organization as may be considered necessary, and if the additional men to keep divisions up to their establishment will not be forthcoming, I shall be glad if I might be informed as early as possible in order that I m&amp;y forthwith submit definite proposals for the disbandment of certain divisions.Meanwhile, I truBt that the gravity of the situation, and the effect the shortage of men has already^ had, and will continue to have, on the conduct of the campaign on the Western Front, is fully appreciated by His Majesty&apos;s G-overnment.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Sgd.) D, Haig,Fie Id-Marshal, Commanding-in-Chief, -British Armies in France.121/Franoe/ 4 (A.G.I.) 24th Oct. 121/Prance/ (A.G,2,)of November, 033/2706 3,1. )of November,..

</content>
</cab>
