<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/33/0 images: 448-448</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^$frt JtH^ 1 7i I his Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty^ Government.)OPERATIONS.391SECRET,Prom      General Delme-Radcliffe, Italy. To C.I.G,Sa, War Office.Handed in 4 a,m.28,11c17Received   7.-55 a3m028 oils17.768.        November 27th.        Situation evening,3rd Corps.       No change.   Slight artillery activity,1st ArmyArtillery activity, but no further attack. Enemy tooK&quot; advantage of fog to place Y/ire entanglements in front of Italian positions on Maletta Davanti?4th Army,        27th Corps,   It is confirmed that enemy&apos;s losses in engagement on Col Berretta yesterday were very heavy, and that he was pushed back a considerable distance by-the pursuit of the Italian troops,       It is reported enemy * s troops employed in this attack had been well supplied with liquor before it and many were very drunk *       34- prisoners wore tske-n including an officer,,       The Aosta Brigade the 94th Regiment Infantry and the Toe Brenta Battalion Alpini particularly distinguished themselves.18th Corps,      Concentration of enemy were reported at head of V, Stizzon and in neighbourhood of Pontana Secca -       19th. Corps, Enemy is entrenching on northern side of crest of Monfenera and is bringing up trench mortars.      His working parties were bom-barded by Italian artillery *        A German deserter came In.-, Another arch of Vidor Bridge was blown up by Italians last night,3rd Army.There was considerable artillery activiValong the front I1th, 13th and 23rd Corps,    Enemy?s artillery.onfired at Italian front line positions, at batteries in act: and at houses and villages without doing very much damagea Italian artillery fired at a foot-bridge near Vendrame at the villages and farmhouses on left bank of where enemy1s movements had been reported and also on enemyss lines of communication,on.Italian 15th Corps being now reformed will be moved up the 29th to support troops holding Mt, Grappa Mt, Fenera line.Weather is fine but cold and on Mt. Grappa troops are suffering a good deal as there are 15 to 20 degrees fan, of cold at night; a considerable part of troops are still without mountain clothing and equipment while no hutments have yet been completed.

</content>
</cab>
