<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/65/0 images: 30-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SojjjRfflS DQctlMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCAB.1NE i l)&apos;r r-nRECORD copy .(54) 10 COPY N11TH JANUARY, 1954CABINETo3lTHE PROBLEM OF SECURITY IN europe memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign AffairsGeneral ConsiderationsThis will be one of the main subjects raised by the Russians inthe general setting of preventing the revival of German militarism.    The three western Governments have given much thought to the problem since thePrime minister&apos;s speech of 11th May and are prepared to discuss it in ageneral way but without entering into detailed negotiation until the Russiansshow themselves ready to discuss seriously the problems of Germanreunification.    The course proposed below was generally agreed at the Bermudameeting in December,2. The Russians have built up a most effective security system oftheir own in Eastern Europe.    Their basic objective now is the withdrawal ofthe U.S.A. from Europe,    Their position has therefore been (i) that the Germansettlement should lead to the withdrawal of Western armed forces, andparticularly American forces, from Germany;  (ii) that all foreign bases shouldbe eliminated;  and (iii) that the European Defence Community (E.D,C.) andthe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.) should be abandoned.The Russians are likely to pose as the champions of &apos;Europe for the Europeans&quot;,including themselves but not the Americans,3. Despite the N*A,T,0. j the Western Powers have not yet completedan equally effective security system of their own.    It must be completed byassociating Western Germany in the common effort and so denying the potential resources of a reunited Germany to the Soviet Union and preventinga reunited Germany from playing off the Western Powers against the Russiansor vice versa .    We realise however that the completion of our own securitysystem might disturb the Russians and we are therefore ready to consider further assurances which could be given to the U.S.5.R,   These would be additional to the existing assurances (a) in the United Nations Charter,(b) in the essentially defensive character of the N.A.T.O, and the E.D.C.,and (c) in the Anglo-Soviet and Franco-Soviet Treaties,4, Discussions with the Russians on the basis of a new pact of mutual assistance or of non-aggression might arouse false hopes in the West.They would give the Russians the opportunity to put forward unacceptablecounter-proposals and thus to drag out and confuse the negotiations.      inpresent circumstances therefore the best and safest course of action would bea unilateral declaration at the proper time defining the general policy we intend to pursue.-1
Proposed Declaration5. We have sought to make this as far reaching as possible and toleave no doubt of the sincerity of our intentions.    We have in mind a declaration by the German Federal Government (Annex A) together with a Declaration by theGovernments of the United States, United Kingdom and France, endorsing thatof the German Government (Annex B).    Dr. Adenauer has stated that he isprepared to make a Declaration in the terms suggested and has no objection tothe Draft Declaration to be made by the three Governments.    The only out-standing issue is the reluctance of the Americans to go as far as we and theFrench consider desirable in Section (Z) of the last paragraph of the tripartite Declaration.Tactics6. The use to be made of the proposed Declaration must depend onthe course of the Berlin meeting.    The advantage of a Declaration in this formis that no negotiation is required.    It can be used independently of Sovietreactions, either at Berlin or at a later stage.    While we must make our general, position clear at Berlin, i. e, that we intend to complete our own security system but on a purely defensive basis, we should avoid getting toodeeply involved in the security question at the start of the conference.We should only reveal our position in more detail if the Russian attitudeshows that they are genuinely prepared for a German settlement on acceptableterms.7. If the Russians propose a formal pact we should point out thatthis could only follow on a German settlement which had defined Germany^eastern frontiers.    We should resist any Soviet proposal for the demilitarisation of Germany, since this would leave a vacuum in central europe and would involve the withdrawal of Allied forces from Germany andthe abandonment of the E.D.C. and the N.A.T.O.   We should equally resist any proposals for partial demilitarisation, e. g. the withdrawal of Soviet troopsbehind the Oder-Neisse line and of Anglo-American troops behind the Rhine,or for limitation of forces in Germany, as these would not solve any of ourbasic political problems and would have grave military disadvantages forthe West.    If the Russians propose quadripartite control of German re-armament, we could point out that past experience shows that an imposedcontrol system is unlikely to be effective.    A solution could only be sought in the context of a broader agreement on the limitation and reduction ofarmaments.    Meanwhile, the E.D.C. provides the most acceptable safeguard.In general we should avoid allowing ourselves to be put on the defensive.If the Russians make their usual accusations against the N.A.T.O, and theE.D.C., we should point to the network of alliances imposed by Russi?on the Satellites and to the rearming of Eastern Europe, including eastern germany.A.E.Foreign Office, S.W.1. ,10TH JANUARY, 1954.
37-ANNEX ADECLARATION BY THE GERMAN FEDERAL, GOVERNMENTThe German Federal Republic undertakes to accept the obligations of the Charter of the United Nations and in particular of Article 2 thereof;Considering that the provisions of the Treaty establishing theEuropean Defence Community relating to the integration of forces and pooling of resources and armaments of the member States on the European continentpreclude any individual armed action in Europe on the part of these States;Undertakes to refrain from any action likely to revise or impaireither these provisions or the strictly defensive character of the european defence Community of which the forces cannot be employed except against an armed attack;Undertakes in consequence in no case to have recourse to force and to resolve by peaceful means any disputes which may arise between the federal republic and other States.ANNEX BDECLARATION BY THE GOVERNMENTS OF THEUNITED STATES, UNITED KINGE- 1M AND france the Governments of the United States of America, thw United Kingdomof Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the French Republic,Being resolved to devote their efforts to the strengthening of peace inaccordance with the Charter of the United Nations and in particular with theobligations set forth in Article 2 of the Charter(i) to settle their international disputes by peaceful means insuch a manner that international peace and security and justice are not endangered;(ii) to refrain in their international relations from the threat or use of force against the territorial integrity or political independence of any State or in any other mannerinconsistent with the purposes of the United Nations;(iii) to give the United Nations every assistance in any actionit takes in accordance with the Charter, and to refrain from giving assistance to any State against which theUnited Nations may take preventive or enforcementaction;(iv) to ensure that States which are not Members of the united nations act in accordance with the principles of the charter so far as may be necessary for the maintenanceof international peace and security;
Having regard to the purely defensive character of the Atlantic AlHancewhich is manifest in the North Atlantic Treaty, wherein they reaffirm theirfaith in the purposes and principles of the Charter of the United Nations andtheir desire to live in peace with all peoples and all Governments, and undertaketo settle their international disputes by peaceful means in accordance with theprinciples of the Charter and to refrain, in accordance with those principles,from the threat or use of force in their international relations;Considering also that the very structure of the European defence community provides assurances that its forces cannot be used for purposesof aggression, and that the provisions of the Treaty establishing the Community,which relate to the integration of forces and the pooling of resources and armaments of the member States on the European continent, preclude any individual armed action in Europe on the part of these States;TAKE NOTE that the Federal Republic of Germany has, underArticle 3(l) of the Convention on Relations between the three Powers and theFederal Republic signed at Bonn on May 26, 1952, agreed to conduct her policyin accordance with the principles set forth in the Charter of the United nations and by a declaration dated has undertaken in no case tohave recourse to force contrary to those principles, but to resolve by peaceful means any disputes which may arise between her and other States;DECLARE THAT(1)    in their relations with the Federal Republic they will follow the principles set out in Article 2 of the United nations charter;^&quot;United States version -(2)    they will regard any recourse to force in violation of the undertakings noted above as a threat to the integrity andunity of the European Defence Community, and consequentlyto their own security.    They will therefore act in accordancewith Article 4 of the North Atlantic Treaty in particular withrespect to withholding support from the Government concerned;and, to the extent that they consider necessary to this end,will regard themselves as released from their commitments to itjJ7^United Kingdom-French version -(2) they will regard any recourse to force in violation of the under-taking noted above as a threat to their own security.    any government  having recourse to force in this manner j in violation of the undertakings under the E.D. C. Treaty, willbe deprived by the three Governments of any form of military support and aid; and they will regard themselves, to theextent that they consider necessary to this end, as released from their commitments to that Government,    Finally, theywill act in accordance with Article 4 of the North atlantic treaty with a view to taking any other measures which theymay deem appropriate^/(3) will act similarly in case a unified Germany should have recourse to force to modify the frontiers settled by thetreaty of peace;(4) they will use their best efforts to obtain the association ofthe other member States of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisa-tion with this declaration.   .

</content>
</cab>
