<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/65/0 images: 84-84</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret. (54) 2118th January, 1954CABINETWAGES AND prices memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service the Cabinet agreed on 18th December, 1953, to increase the prices of butter,cheese, beef and pork from 21st February, 1954, and to defer till January furtherconsideration of whether there should be some increase in the price of bread ormilk (C.C. (53) 80th Conclusions, Minute 3).2. I understand from the Minister of Food that it will be necessary to make an announcement on 28th January of the price increases which it is proposed shouldtake effect from 21st February. I am so concerned about the effect of making suchan announcement at that time that I am asking my colleagues to reconsider thequestion.3. My colleagues are aware of my general misgivings on the effect whichincreases in food prices are bound to have on wages. I do not propose to repeat the arguments set out in my paper on wages and prices (C. (53) 276) beyondobserving that arguments based, on the increase in food prices have been freelyused and strongly pressed in prosecuting current wage claims, and that the economic consequences of current disputes are to be measured not only by the changes in wage levels which may result, but by the embitterment of industrial relations whichthese struggles entail.4. When the Cabinet reached its conclusion on 18th December it was notpossible to foresee the situation which will exist on 28th January, when the decision is due to be announced. The settlement of major wage claims in a number ofimportant industries has been slower than anticipated and since the threatenedrailway strike just before Christmas there have been a sharpening of conflict anda deterioration in the climate of industrial relations which may have significantpolitical implications. On the crucial claim of the engineering and shipbuilding industries the trade unions did eventually agree to defer industrial action pendingthe reports of the Courts of Inquiry now sitting. One of the principal arguments which the Courts will have to take into consideration is that relating to the cost ofliving and in particular to the cost of food. To make an announcement at this juncture of increases in the price of essential foods would, in my opinion, be highlyinjudicious.5. I agree that I should be unlikely to regard any date for such a move ascompletely suitable, but I regard the proposed date as so obviously unsuitable thatI ask my colleagues to consider deferring it.W. M.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,18th January, 1954.Copy No. 7 I45519Printed for the Cabinet. January 1954

</content>
</cab>
