<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/65/0 images: 151-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)secret- CABINET office(54) 34 RECORD COPY copy no. fcj30th january, 1954cabinetEMPLOYMENT OF COLOURED PEOPLEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister fcr Welsh affairs at their meeting on 18th December, 1952, the Cabinet invited me to arrange for officials of the Department concerned to examine thepossibilities of preventing any further increase in the number of coloured people seeking employment in this country (C.C,(52) 106th Conclusions,Minute 7).    I have recently received the report of an inter-departmentalCommittee which I set up to enquire into this matter and which has reviewed the general position arising from the continued immigration intoGreat Britain of coloured people from the colonies.2. It would obviously be impossible to discriminate openly.againstcoloured people as such in administration or legislation in the field ofemplovment.    After a thorough examination of the possibilities theCommittee have come to the conclusion that it is not practicable to take steps to prevent coloured people obtaining employment once they are in thiscountry.    Any action to that end would have to be directed to preventingthem or discouraging them from entering the United Kingdom in search ofemployment.    There is, of course, no power in law to prevent any british subject entering and remaining in the United Kingdom.3. In accordance with Ministerial directions, such administrative action as is possible to discourage immigration of coloured people into thiscountry from the colonies has been taken over the last few years.    Forinstance, special action has been taken in colonial territories to make stowingaway on ships more difficult by tightening dock control.    The governmentsof West African territories have taken special steps to hinder the issue ofpassports and travel documents to men not known to follow regular employ-ment and whose financial position is not sound.   In those colonial territories from which most of the coloured immigrants come publicity hasbeen given to the fact that accommodation over here is hard to find andunskilled workers often have difficulty in getting employment.    In thiscountry immigration officers have been given instructions to require strictproof of British nationality and to refuse leave to land to stowaways and others who cannot produce written evidence that they are British subjects.4. The general effect of these measures has been to reduce by morethan half the number of coloured stowaways who succeed in entering theUnited Kingdom, but stowaways represent only a small part of the problem.It is possible that the measures have had a slight effect on the numbers leavingcolonial territories as fare-paying passengers to settle in this country but itwould appear that they have reached the limit of their effectiveness and thatthere are no further steps which could be taken administratively in this field.    The great majority of coloured migrants now settling in this country
are fare-paying passengers from the West Indies.    The governments of theWest Indian territories have been unwilling to put restrictions on the issue ofpassports to British subjects who appear to be entitled to them and it wouldseem that in any case such action would require legislation which is notpolitically practicable.    It is not to be expected that administrative measuresalone will do much to prevent an influx to the United Kingdom, with itsbetter employment prospects and social services, of coloured people from colonial territories with employment problems.5. The conclusion is, therefore, that there is no effective meansof stopping this influx without legislation which would give power to control immigration of British subjects to this country by giving immigration officers authority to refuse leave to land, as in the case of aliens, and would confer a power to deport to their place of origin British subjects from over-seas who failed to abide by the conditions attached to the grant of leave toland.    There could be no question of seeking such power to deal only withcoloured people:  it would have to be a power which could be exercised inrelation to any British subject from overseas.    Not only would such legislation be a complete break with the traditional principle that any BriJishsubject has a right to enter freely and remain in the United Kingdom but theadministration of the control would put a greatly increased burden on the immigration service, and also on the Ministry of Labour if, as wouldprobably be thought desirable, some system of regulation of the employmentof British subjects from overseas was adopted as part of the arrangements.The need to grant leave to land to British subjects arriving at ports in thiscountry would lead to much greater delay in clearing travellers through the controls and would undoubtedly give rise to much resentment.6. There are no statistics showing the number of coloured people in this country but an estimate made by the police in April, 1953, which isbelieved to be somewhat conservative, was that there were then about40,000 coloured people in Great Britain compared with about 7,000 beforethe war.    The immigration service have kept records of coloured peoplecoming from the colonies to this country to seek employment in the last fewyears and these, taken with other statistics of the number of Indian andPakistani seamen who desert their ships, show that coloured migrants haverecently been entering this country at the rate of over 3,000 a year.    Thereis no reason to expect any reduction in this figure and there is no power toprevent these people entering no matter how much the number may increase .Nevertheless, these figures do not seem to me to justify any departure fromthe view which has hitherto been taken that so far no such evil consequences of this immigration have appeared as would amount to a case for legislationdirected against the immigration of British subjects, with all the politicaland administrative difficulties to which it would give rise.7. There is, however, one aspect of the matter to which I would callspecial attention.    There have recently been several references in thePress to cases in which coloured men have been convicted of living on theimmoral earnings of white women in London and suggestions have been made that there are many such cases.    Figures which I have obtained from theMetropolitan Police do show that the number of coloured men convicted forthis offence is out of all proportion to the total number of coloured men inLondon and the police say that the Practice is much more widespread thanthe number of convictions would appear to indicate since the police havenot the manpower needed to carry out the necessarily detailed investigations
in every suspected case.    It has been suggested that there should belegislation to give power to deport from this country British subjects from overseas convicted of sarious criminal offences, of which this would be one, and it is true that many of the objections to taking a general power tocontrol the immigration of British subjects would not apply to such ameasure.    My own view is, however, that a case has not been made out for taking even a limited power of this nature.    Without it there is always the risk that the details of some particularly sordid case will becomepublic and that we shall be criticised for permitting such a state of affairs to continue when the existence of a power of deportation might have prevented it.    While, therefore, I am not myself in favour of taking sucha power I have thought it well to raise the point for the consideration ofmy colleagues.D.M.F.Home Office, S.W.1. ,29TH JANUARY, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
