<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/65/0 images: 195-207</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I?Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1954SECRET CABINET OFFICE:     c     N(KRECORD copy . (54) 4615th February, 1954 CABINETEAST/WEST TRADENote by the Prime minister a Committee of Ministers under my Chairmanship has considered, in the lightof the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on January 18, the possibility of extending trade withthe Soviet bloc. The Committee&apos;s conclusions and recommendations are set outin the attached report.I submit for the Cabinefs decision the four points of policy summarised inparagraph 10 of the report.I believe that the time is ripe for a new approach to this problem. I wouldnot at this stage dismiss the possibility that we may be able to persuade the UnitedStates Administration to face the task of justifying a new policy to their congress and public. Our best chance of doing so is to renew personal contact withMr. Harold Stassen, the Director of the Foreign Operations Administration. Ifthe Cabinet share my view, I will send him a message suggesting that he should come to London in the near future to discuss this problem in person, unless he thinks that by so doing he would weaken the influence which he can exercise on itin Washington.w. s. c.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,12th February, 1954.
EAST/WEST trade on January 18 the Cabinet discussed the advantages which would flow froman extension of trade with countries in the Soviet bloc. They decided that, in preparation for a fresh approach to the United States Administration, UnitedKingdom Ministers should first formulate a policy consistent with the new strategichypothesis of a prolonged period of international tension without major war andshould see how that policy would work out in terms of a revised list of the goods which should continue to be denied to the Soviet bloc. It was then suggested thatthe revised list should be framed on the principle that we should in future denyto the Soviet bloc only goods of direct military value (C.C. (54) 3rd Conclusions,Minute 5).2. The current embargo lists have since been reviewed by a Committee ofMinisters under the Prime Ministers Chairmanship. The Committee have foundthat the strict application of the principle suggested by the Cabinet would remove from the embargo lists certain machine tools and other goods which would help the Russians to reduce the lead which the Western Powers now have over themin some important technical developments necessary to modern war. The exportof such goods to the Soviet bloc might make a significant difference to the war-making capacity of the Russians, and would certainly provoke criticism from publicopinion in this country. The Committee therefore decided that the range of goods which should continue to be subject to embargo should include not only goods of direct military value but also some which, though not of direct military value, hadan indirect military importance of such significance that their export to the soviet bloc should continue to be prohibited.3. The existing lists have been revised on that basis, with the followingresult:  &apos;(i) No reductions are proposed in the Munitions List and the Atomic EnergyList. These Lists were already confined to goods of direct military value.(ii) It is proposed that the Embargo List of Strategic Industrial Goods shouldbe reduced from 263 items to about 135.(iii) It is proposed that quantitative controls (Part II of the Industrial List)should be abandoned.* These controls at present apply only to items which are of lesser importance to the Soviet war potential.4. A revised version of the Embargo List for Industrial Goods is set out inAppendix I. This contains 133 items. The Committee are agreed that the exportof all these items to the Soviet bloc should be subject to embargo. Two furtherquestions are, however, submitted for decision by the Cabinet:  (i) Should copper be added to this List?(ii) Should we also add to the List three further types of machine tool whoseexport to the Soviet bloc was criticised by Conservative speakers when this question was the subject of political controversy in 1950?5. Copper. The considerations affecting copper are set out in Appendix II.They may be summarised as follows:  Copper is important to the electrical industry in peace, and in war is extensivelyused in the production of military equipment and munitions. The developmentof the Soviet electrical industry is known to be lagging, partly because of shortageof copper; and the power-generating system would be a weak link in the chain of Soviet industrial production in war. The Soviet bloc depends on imports for about 20 per cent, of its peace-time requirements of copper. The Defence Depart-ments argue that, by continuing to restrict these imports, we could hamper the. development of the Soviet war potential and also prevent the accumulation of war reserves.Against this it is argued that the peace-time uses of copper are so numerousthat it must be regarded as a basic industrial product; and that it would be inconsistent with the new policy now proposed to deny copper to the Sovietcountries for the purpose of hampering &apos;the development of their electrical industry,* Subject to the Cabinefs decision on ships, on which a memorandum will shortly be circulated by the First Lord of the Admiralty.
which is an essential part of their general economic structure. It is also argued that, as they already command 80 per cent, of their peace-time requirements of copper, the Soviet authorities could readily arrange, if they wished, that their military needs of copper should be met in full by rationing its civilian uses. Ifthe current embargo were lifted, sterling area countries could expect to secure a significant share of this new market for the export of copper, both as a raw material and in semi-fabricated form.The majority of the Committee considered that the balance of the argumentslay in favour of excluding copper from the revised Embargo List.6. Machine Tools.-The revised Embargo List contains a number of types of machine tool selected by the Minister of Supply as having an indirect military importance. The Cabinet are, however, invited to consider whether three furthertypes of machine tool should be added to the List, viz.: - -(i) Remaining types of vertical boring and turning mills, of which some typesare already included.(ii) Large centre lathes.(iii) Large planing machines.Of these, the first could be used in the manufacture of gun turrets and jet enginerings; the second in the turning of gun barrels; and the third in the manufactureof tanks and gun mountings.The argument against including these items is that, though used in themanufacture of munitions, they are also of general value in ordinary industrial production. They have no greater military significance than some of the items which we should propose, under the new policy, to free from embargo. Two ofthem, viz., (ii) and (iii) above, have not hitherto been subject to embargo, but onlyto quantitative control; and, if they were included in the revised Embargo List, itwould be more difficult to justify that List in negotiation with the Americans asreflecting the new principle which we wish to apply.On the other hand, these types of machine tool featured prominently in the controversy between the political Parties in this country in 1950, regarding theexport to Soviet countries of machinery capable of being used to increase itsindustrial war potential, at a time when we were in urgent need of machine toolsfor our own rearmament programme. They were specifically mentioned byConservative spokesmen in the Debate in the House of Commons on September 18,1950, as among the heavy machine tools which should not be exported to theSoviet bloc.7. The items which the Committee would propose to exclude from the existingEmbargo List are set out in Appendix III. In the negotiations which will have tobe undertaken with the United States Government and other members of the paris group, we shall probably be under pressure to restore to the Embargo List some ofthe items whose exclusion is here proposed. If, for the sake of securing interna-tionai agreement, we are compelled to add to our short list additional items whichare of little strategic importance, it is desirable that we should choose for thispurpose items which are also of little commercial significance to us. The list inAppendix III has therefore been classified in three groups goods in which there is unlikely to be any export trade from the United Kingdom to the Soviet bloc; goodsin which our export trade is unlikely to be large; and goods in which we might havean important export trade with the Soviet bloc.8. The Committee have considered how these proposals could best be presented to the United States Government. They recommend that the revised list should be put forward as representing a new policy appropriate to a new situation.We should make it clear that, if a new Embargo List of this Character were adopted,we should be ready to publish it and to enforce it strictly by all means within our power, including transaction controls. If at the outset we related our revised list toa new&apos; conception of policy, we should have established an initial position fromwhich we could afford to make concessions, by adding to the list items which areof little trade importance to us, if we found that the Americans were unwilling to goas fast as we would wish in moving over to a new policy. And, later on, if thesituation should improve, we could reassert our full claim.9. It is agreed that any approach made to the United States Government atthis stage should be limited to the question of trade with the Soviet Union and itsSatellites in Europe. The time has not yet come to review the policy governingtrade with China.
10.   The following points are submitted for decision by the Cabinet:  (i) Should copper be included among goods to be denied, on strategicgrounds, to the Soviet bloc (paragraph 5)?(ii) Should the revised Embargo List include the three additional types of machine tool which featured prominently in the controversy in 1950(paragraph 6)?(iii) Is it agreed that it would be a reasonable policy in present circumstances that countries represented in the Paris Group should now be free to export to the Soviet bloc any goods save those included in the MunitionsList, the Atomic Energy List and the revised List of Strategic IndustrialGoods set out in Appendix I (subject to the decision on (i) and (ii)above)?(iv) Do the Cabinet agree that this revised list should be presented to. the americans as the result of applying a new policy consistent with thenew hypothesis of a prolonged period of international tension withoutmajor war (paragraph 8)?
Revised Version of Embargo List of Industrial GoodsItem No. Brief DescriptionMetal Working Machinery1001 (part)   Vertical boring and turningmills as specified.1002 (part)   Jig boring machines.1006 (part)   Deep hole drilling machines and drills.1009 Vertical inverted spindle drilling machines.1019 Contour profile grinders.1021 Jig grinders.1022 Lap radial grinders as specified.1024 Spline grinders.1041 (part)   Automatic lathes as specified.1043 Combination boring and turning lathes.1044 Combination lathe, drilling and milling machines, specially designed for mobile military workshops or naval craft.1051 Spar millers.1053 Armour plate planers.1065 Military-type jigs, fixtures and accessories. .1072 (part)  Presses, mechanical or hydraulic, as specified.1073 (part)   Wire, tubing and strip machinery as specified.1084 Machine tools using spark erosion or ultra-sonic vibration.1085 Balancing machines.1086 All machines and equipment specially designed for manufacturingarmaments and implements of war.1087 Broaching machines.1088 Gear-making machinery as specified.1090 Profiling and duplicating machinery as specified.Chemical and Petroleum Equipment1102 Ammonia oxidation equipment as specified.1103 Anti-biotics production equipment as specified.1106 Centrifugal solvent extractors.1109 Freeze-drying equipment.1110 Gas-liquefying equipment and equipment for handling liquefied gas.1118 Nitrators.1131 Pumps (except vacuum pumps) as specified.1132 Vacuum pumps as specified.1133 Corrosion resistant valves and cocks.1153 Fuel production equipment as specified.Electrical and Power-Generating Equipment1201 (part)  Electric furnaces as specified.1210 Searchlight control units.1255 Marine diesel engines as specified.General Industrial Equipment1305 (part)   Sendzimir type rolling mills.1325 Excavating and earth-moving equipment, specially designed forairborne transport.1355 Radio valve manufacturing machinery.1380 Compressors and blowers as specified.1385 Industrial diamonds as specified.1386 (part)  All tools incorporating diamonds.1388 Dynamometers as specified.1390 Graphite as specified.
Transportation Equipment1401 Floating docks.1405 Ice-breakers as specified.1410 Tankers; tank barges, whaling factories.1415 Warships as specified.1425 Batteries (submarine).1430 Cables for harbour defence.1435 Minesweeping equipment.1450 (part) Four-wheel-drive vehicles.1485 Gyro-compasses and repeaters.1490 Aircraft landing mats.Electronics and Precision Instruments1501 Communication equipment specially designed for aircraft use.1502 Communication equipment using infra-red radiation or ultrasonicwaves.1507 &quot; Jamming &quot; apparatus.1509 (part) Location apparatus as specified.1510 Location apparatus (under-water).1512 (part) Radar and radio navigation equipment as specified.1514 Pulse modulators as specified.1515 (part) Radio direction-finding equipment as specified.1516 Radio receivers (panoramic).1518 Telecontrol equipment for pilotless aircraft and guided weapons.1520 V.H.F. radio relay equipment as specified.1521 Amplifiers as specified.1522 Antennae pattern recorders as specified.1525 Co-axial cables as specified.1527 Transformer and choke laminations as specified.1528 Frequency meters as specified.1531 Radio field strength meters as specified.1532 Radio-frequency signal generators.1533 Radio spectrum analyzers as specified.1537 Special tuned circuits as specified.1544 Diodes and triodes as specified.1548 Photoelectric cells as specified.1549 Photomultiplier tubes..1555 (part) Television camera tubes.1558 (part) Electronic valves as specified.1563 Sensitive balances (including electronic).1565 Computers, electronics.1569 Electrometers.1573 Impedance-measuring apparatus as specified.1579 (part) Microscopes as specified.1582 (part) Optical curve generators as specified.1584 Oscilloscopes (cathode ray) as specified.1585        . High speed cameras.1590 Micro-flash equipment.1591 Spectrographs, spectrometers and monochrometers as specified.1592 Strain gauge recording equipment.1593 Short time measuring equipment.Metals, Minerals and their Manufactures1601 (part)   Ball and roller bearings as specified.1605 Iron powder as specified.1615 Munitions components and materials as specified.1635 (part)  Alloys containing molybdenum, tungsten, cobalt, &amp;c, as specified.1636 Aluminium hard alloys for aircraft construction in specified forms.1648 Cobalt as specified.1649 ....... Columbium as specified.1653 Germanium and compounds.
Metals, Minerals and their Manufactures (continued)1658 (part)   Molybdenum as specified.1668 Tungsten wire and filament.1670 Tantalum as specified.1671 Titanium metal.1672 Ferro-thorium; ferro-uranium.1679 Zirconium as specified.Chemical and Petroleum Products1701 Detonators as specified.1702 Hydraulic fluids, synthetic.1703 Stabilisers for explosives as specified.1725 Furfural, furfuryl alcohol, tetrahydrofurfuryl alcohol.1727 Glycols and their compounds.1729 Hexamethylenetetraline.1731 Hydrazine, -hydrate, -salts.1732 Hydrogen peroxide over 50 per cent, strength.1737 Methyl isobutylketone.1741 Nitroguanidine.1742 Guanidine nitrate.1744 Pentaerythritol, -tetranitrates.1748 Picric acid.1751 Polytetrafluroethylene.1755 Silicon organic compounds as specified.1756 Sodium azide.1764 Trifluorochloroethylene.1773 (part)   Gasoline (motor and aviation).1789 High octane blending agents for aircraft fuels as specified.Rubber and Rubber Products1820 Pneumatic tyres and tubes of a kind specially constructed to bebullet-proof or to run when deflated.Additional Items Agreed for Embargo(a) Plant for producing titanium metal.(b) Diesel engines of 50 h.p. and above with a high content of non-magnetic material.(c) Fishing vessels with characteristics which make them suitable for naval use.(d) Merchant ships with similar characteristics.(e) Merchant ships of over 15 knots speed.(/) Passenger ships.(g) Coasters of under 1,000 tons.(fi) * Certain machines specially designed for manufacture or testing ofelectronic components.(/) *Certain machines and equipment specially designed for making ormeasuring gas turbine blades.* Revised and more specific definitions to be agreed between Departments concerned before inter-national discussions begin.
APPENDIX IICOPPERReport by the Interdepartmental Security Export Controls Working PartyWorld Production and ConsumptionThe following table shows world smelter production and consumption ofvirgin copper in 1952 (the Soviet bloc being excluded):-Production	Country	Consumption(thousands of tons)		(thousands of tons)985	United States	1,291377	Chile	26292	Northern Rhodesia	Nil202	Belgian Congo	Nil200	Canada	117192	Germany	215106	Rest of Europe	35193	Japan	92163	Rest of World	146Nil	United Kingdom	3482,610		2,586Supply Position in the Soviet bloc2. Soviet bloc production has been rising steadily and in 1952 reached an estimated total of 411,000 tons. Planned production for 1955 is 634,000 tons butthe bloc has recently been unable to fulfil the planned rate of increase and it islikely that production in 1955 will fall far short of this figure.3. Soviet bloc imports are estimated to total at least 100,000 tons a year.Little of this is imported direct from producing countries, most of it being shippedthrough devious channels and at premium prices.4. The total quantity of copper available to the bloc in 1952 can, therefore,be estimated at about 500,000 tons.Consumption in the Soviet bloc5. There is abundant evidence that the Soviet bloc countries are very short of copper (for example, not only are they willing to pay high prices for imports butthey are taking various measures to develop substitutes, especially in the electricalindustry). They would no doubt use more copper if they could get it, but it isnot possible to estimate the maximum amount.6. There is no information about the way in which copper is assigned to various uses in the bloc, but the electrical industry is no doubt the greatest user.Some indication of the quantity required for peace-time defence uses may be derived from the experience of the United Kingdom; out of 550,000 tons consumedin the United Kingdom in 1952 (a peak year in the defence production programme),some 100,000 to 150,000 tons were estimated to be required for the defenceindustries.7. No estimate can be given of the amount of copper the bloc would needin war but here again some indication can be derived from our own experience.In the peak war year of 1942, United Kingdom consumption was 820,000 tons asagainst some 350,000 tons in 1938.Case for and against an Embargo on Copper8. The defence view is that copper merits embargo because of its importancein the electrical industry and its extensive use in war in the production of military equipment and munitions. The development of the Soviet electrical industry isknown to be behind schedule, partly because of shortage of copper. The power-generating system would be a weak link in the chain of Soviet industrial productionin war. -
9. In war-time, the consumption of copper increases enormously and by rarthe greater part of it is used for direct military purposes; in the last war our con-sumption of copper doubled and half of it was spent in ammunition.10. The bloc is very short of copper and appears to be dependent uponimports for about 20 per cent, of its supplies. If there is no restriction on itsimports, the bloc will be free to develop its war potential not only by assigningmore copper to industry but also by building up the very large reserve it would need in war, when all imports would probably be stopped.11. Against this it is argued that the peace-time uses of copper are so multi-farious that it can only be regarded as a basic industrial product and that, eventhough it plays a vital part in war-time production, this is equally true of other products of general utility which we should not think of embargoing. Further, itwould be inconsistent with the principle on which the present embargo list is basedto include copper in order to hamper the Soviet bloc electrical industry, which isno more than a sector of the bloc&apos;s general economy. Even though copper produc-tion in the bloc is behind schedule, supplies are adequate to meet the currentneeds of defence production.12. Copper is now becoming much more plentiful outside the bloc and itwill become increasingly difficult to make our controls effective, even if they arereinforced by the general imposition of transaction and transhipment controls.These additional controls would, of course, interfere with the free operation ofthe London Metal Market.13. The removal of the embargo on copper in its primary forms would enablethe sterling area to obtain a substantial increase in exports to the bloc. But thepresent embargo also covers semi-fabricated forms, such as wire and strip, whichare widely used in the electrical and other industries. Freedom to sell semi-fabricated copper products would probably result in a large increase in UnitedKingdom exports of manufactured goods for these industries.
APPENDIX IIIItems Proposed for Exclusion from the Embargo List Arranged inOrder of Trade ImportanceI. No Exports LikelyThese are items which are either exported by the Soviet bloc or are notexported by the United Kingdom: - Item No. Brief DescriptionElectronics and Precision Instruments1541 Cathode ray tubes as specified.1552 Rectifier or amplifier tubes (cold-cathode types).1577 Meteorological sounding balloons.1583 Oscillographs, recording.Metals1630      Scrap iron and steel.1645      Cadmium.1646     Calcium.1661      Nickel as specified.1667      Strontium as specified.Chemicals and Petroleum Products1710 Aluminium chloride (anhydrous).1713 Barium nitrate; barium chromate.1716 Carbon black.1717 Ethyl cellulose.1745 Calcium and potassium permanganate,1758 Styrene; dichlorostyrene; polydichlorostyrene and certain products.1770 Crude petroleum.1771 Diesel oil.1772 Fuel oil.1773 (part only) Gasoline (motor and Aviation).1774 Kerosene.Synthetic Rubber1801      Synthetic rubbers as specified.II. Exports Impossible to Forecast but Unlikely to be Large(e.g., not more than  1 million per annum in the near future)These are items for which there is no record of more than occasional soviet bloc attempts to purchase in the United Kingdom:  Item No. Brief DescriptionChemical and Petroleum Equipment1107 Chlorine production equipment as specified.1112 Hydrogen-producing equipment as specified.1113 Hydrogenation equipment as specified.1116 Methanol oxidation equipment as specified.1120 Certain specified items of chemical processing equipment.1124 Sulphur burners and pyrites roasters.1127 Water-treatment equipment, industrial.1140 Vacuum insulated containers for liquids or liquified gases.1141 Stainless steel tanks as specified.1145 Gauges for pressures over 100 atmospheres.1151 Oil-refining equipment as specified.1152 Oil and natural gas-production equipment as specified.1155 Heater return bends for petroleum refineries.
!c0Item No. Brief DescriptionElectrical and Power-Generating Equipment1202 Electrodes for underwater cutting.1265 IIC marine engines, out-board, over 50 h.p.General Industrial Equipment1301 Casting equipment as specified.. .1310 Electro-static separators.1311 Sintering equipment.1350 Carbon-black manufacturing plants.1360 Spinnerets as specified.1375 Air-conditioning units, packaged.1381 Core drill bits.1395 Electro-static precipitators.Transportation Equipment1470 Railway flat cars as specified.1475 Railway tank cars as specified.1480 Railway well cars as specified.Electronics and Precision Instruments1505 Ionosphere recording apparatus.1555 (part only) Television camera tubes.1558 (part only) Electronic valves as specified.1561 Absorption meters, infra-red.1567 Densitometers.1571 Geophysical prospecting equipment as specified.1578 Micro-hardness testers.1579 (part only) Microscopes as specified1582 (part only) Optical curve generators as specified.1589 Resistors, temperature-sensitive as specified.1594 Voltmeters as specified.1596 Warburg apparatus for the examination of living tissue.1598 X-ray and electron diffraction equipment as specified.1599 X-ray tubes, 1,000 P.K.V. and over.Metals, Minerals and Manufactures1620 Platinum products as specified.1641 Bismuth.1666 Sodium..1675 Vanadium as specified.1680 Asbestos (strategic grades).1691 Mica (strategic grades).Chemicals and Petroleum Products1704 Rubber-compounding agents as specified.1719 1: 2-Dibromcethane.1720 Dinitrotoluene solids and oils.1723 Ethyl Benzene.1739 Monochlorobenzene.1747 Phosphoric acid catalyst.1750 Polyethylene.1752 Potassium tetroxide.1760 Thallium bromoiodide.1761&apos; Titanium tetrachloride.1766 Vanadium compounds.1775 Reference fuels.1780 Lubricating oils and greases.1786 Additives for motor oil..  1787 Liquid gum inhibitors.1788 Tetra-ethyl lead, fluid and certain mixtures.1793 Hydraulic fluids, petroleum base..1796 Coke and coke flour.
III. Exports Likely to be of ImportanceThese are items which the Soviet bloc either bought before controls were intro-duced or have attempted to buy since. Estimates of trade per annum likely in thenear future are shown against each group of items.Machine Tools1008 Unit-head type drilling machines as specified.1016 Internal cylindrical grinding machines as specified.1025 Thread grinding machines.1072 (part only) Presses, mechanical or hydraulic as specified.1071 Forging machines as specified.1007 (part only) Multi-spindle drilling and/or tapping machines  asspecified.1018 Crankshaft, crankpin, cam and camshaft grinders as specified.1001 (part only) Vertical boring and turning mills as specified.1003 Horizontal combination boring, drilling and milling machines asspecified.1036 Crank- and camshaft lathes.1041 (part only) Automatic lathes as specified.1073 (part only) Wire, tubing and strip machinery as specified.1023 Roll grinding machines.1038 Relieving lathes.1015 External cylindrical grinding machines, centreless.1017 Surface grinding machines, multi-spindle.1070 Forging hammers as specified.1090 (part only) Profiling and duplicating machinery as specified.1089 Honing and/or lapping machines.1035 Axle lathes.1037 Hollow spindle (oil country type) lathes.1040 Turret lathes as specified.1042 Surfacing and boring lathes as specified.1060 Cam-operated thread cutting machines as specified.1074 Thread rolling machines.1027 Grinders for broaching tools.1020 Gap gauge grinding machines.1050 Thread milling machines as specified.1061 Pipe threading machines as specified..    1026 Combined internal and external grinding machines as specified.1052 Combination miller and planer as specified.1085 Dynamic balancing machines as specified.1091 Shaving machines.These Machine Tools are arranged in order of decreasing importance from thecommercial point of view. If all of these items are de-controlled, exports shouldtotal approximately  1 - 5 million per annum.Rubber and Rubber Products1802      Masterbatch.1821      Pneumatic tyre casings; truck, bus, off-the-road and industrial typesas specified.1822     Pneumatic tyre casings for soil compactors of 10 tons or over.1840     Water lubricated bearings.1845      Rotary drilling hose, high pressure.Miscellaneous1910      Optical glass as specified.1920     Paper or synthetic film for dielectric use.
Chemical and Petroleum Equipment1101      Acid concentrating equipment as specified&apos;1123      Sulphur extraction equipment.1130     Compressors as specified.1134     Electrically controlled automatic valves.1135      Pipe valves for working pressures of 900 ormore p.s.i.1146     Moulding machines for plastics.1150      Oil well drilling and exploration equipment as specified.1154     Welded or seamless steel casing, tubing andline pipe as specified.These are miscellan-Carbonaceous items, some of^ importance in otherexport industries. Ex-ports should totalmillion per annum.*-4Electrical and Power Generating Equipment1201      (part only) Electric furnaces as specified1250      Condenser tubes.1256 . . Diesel engines as specified.1260     Electric motors over 1,000 h.p.v Exports should total[     million per annum.General Industrial Equipment&quot;1    Exports   of rollingMetal rolling mills (all types) and controls. I mills  and  equipment13051315 Tinning units, electrolytic.1302 Crucibles, artificial graphite.1321 Tractors, petrol or diesel as specified.1330 Calenders (rubber working).1331 Masterbatch mixers.1332 Tyre-curing presses as specified.1351 Mining equipment &quot; Rocker &quot; shovels.1374 Abrasives as specified.1386 (part only) Tools incorporating diamonds.1387 Wheels   and   other   tools   incorporatingdiamond abrasives.\ should total   millionJ per annum.Exports should total J million per annum.Electronics and Precision Instruments1509 (part only) Location apparatus as specified.1512      (part only) Radar and radio navigationequipment as specified.1515      (part only) Radio-direction-finding equip-ment as specified.1517      Radio  transmitters  and  components  asspecified.1519      Telephone and Telegraph equipment asspecified.1575     Leak-detecting, instruments.1586     Pyrometers as specified.1587      Quartz crystals and plates.Exports should total&apos; i million per annum.Metals, Minerals and their Manufactures1601 ... ......(part only) Ball and roller bearings as&quot;&apos;    specified,,., , . ^1635      (part only) Alloys containing molybdenum, f  100,000 per annum.tungsten, cobalt, &amp;c, as specified.       J , ...Exports should totalEstimates of exports resulting from decontrol of the above List I items totalbetween&apos; 3 million and  5 million per annum. If, in addition, List II were abolished, it would result in greater exports, themosf important itembeing powers-generating plant/ ,

</content>
</cab>
