<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/29/13 images: 86-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  September 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (42) 433.September 26, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.GERMAN ARMY CASUALTIES.Note by the Prime Minister.I circulate, for the information of my colleagues, the following note byLord Cherwell, which I sent for comment to the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff, regarding casualties suffered by the German Army.W. S. C.10 Downing Street, S.W.1,September 26, 1942.GERMAN LOSSES.AN agent who has had access to the German State Insurance Companies&apos;figures reports that the losses of the Wehrmacht between the 1st January, 1942,and the 1st July, 1942, are as follows : I-Killed (447,142)-(a) Killed in action............... 218,193(6) Died from wounds     ............ 80,977(c) &quot;Died of illness............... 128,118(d) Killed by accident     ............ 9,846(e) Suicides.................. 10,008[24400]447,142
TL-Wouncled and Sick (915,682)-(a) Fit for service ...(b) Unfit for service(c) Sick with expectations of complete cure(d) Sick remaining invalids after cure ...(e) Wounded fit for service after treatment(/) Wounded unfit for service after treatment(g) Self-inflicted wounds ...285,355471,12039,89049,34734,93 018,24016,820915,682III. General Losses (Killed and Invalided) Killed .............Men unfit for service mentioned in II 447,142471,12049,34718,24016,8201,002.669From the beginning of the war until the 1st July. 1942, the figures are notavailable in detail, but the total is given as 3,463.523.This includes all members of the Wehrmacht but no civilians. So far as Ican see the figures are reasonably consistent with our experience in the last war,though the proportion of wounded, permanently unfit, is higher. It is of interest that there were 10,000 suicides and nearly 17,000 self-inflicted wounds in thefigures, which seems to me inconsistent with high morale.September 20, 1942.The above report is of interest.We have always considered the figures from the German State insurance companies&apos; records to be genuine. As regards the four categories of killed,died of wounds, gross casualties and permanent casualties they agree very closely with our estimates for the same period; and in all categories we consider them generally reasonable.2. The proportion of sick and wounded who are permanently unfitaccording to the Insurance Companies&apos; figures is 61 per cent. This is very high in comparison to the figure we have accepted in the past i.e., 30 per cent.,and it is possible that lightly wounded, who are treated in the forward area,have not been included in the Insurance Companies&apos; figures.CHERWELL.
September 25, 1942.A. F. BROOKE, C.I.G.S.3. According to the Insurance Companies the number of suicides in thisperiod works out at approximately 2-85 per annum per thousand. this compares with a rate of 0-27 for the previous two years and four months ofwar in earlier reports from the same source. These combine to produce anaverage figure for the Army during the whole war up to date of 0 73. Therate, amongst the male population of Germany in 1936. was 0-41.4.   We have no means of comparing the figures for self-inflicted wounds.5. The high rate of suicides and self-inflicted wounds now shown is mostinteresting but in view of the known performance of the German Army againstthe enemy, we wonder whether fear of the Gestapo may not have been a majorcontributory factor.Comparative totals.W.O. Insurance1st Jan., 1942, to 30th June, 1942. estimate.     Co.&apos;s figures.Killed and died of wounds    ...... 339.000 299,170Gross casualties from all causes     ... 1,636.000 1,362,824*Permanent casualties (killed, died andinvalided)     ............ 1.012,000 1.002,6691st Sept., 1939, to 30th June, 1942.Permanent casualties (killed, died andinvalided)     ............      3,850,000        3.463,523* May exclude lightly wounded, treated in forward area.




</content>
</cab>
