<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/67/18 images: 260-275</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TSECRECUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT0 a|18th COPY NO    0 yionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 1 MAY 1980at 9. 30 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon Mar garPrime Mi(Hon William Whitelaw MPary of State for the Home DepartmenttHon Lord Carringtonry of State for Foreign andonwealth Affair stHon Sir Keith Joseph MPtary of State for IndustrytHon James Prior MPary of State for EmploymenttHon Peter Walker MPter of Agriculture, Fisheries and FoodtHon George Younger MPtary of State for ScotlandtHon Humphrey Atkins MP&apos;ary of State for Northern IrelandtHon Norman St John-Stevas MPsHor of the Duchy of LancastertHon David Howell MPtary of State for Energy&apos; Hon John Biff en MPSecretary, Treasuryet Thatcher MPlisterThe Rt Hon Lord HailshamLord ChancellorThe Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MPChancellor of the ExchequerThe Rt Hon Francis Pym MPSecretary of State for DefenceThe Rt Hon Sir Ian Gilmour MPLord Privy SealThe Rt Hon Michael Heseltine MPSecretary of State for the EnvironmentThe Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MPSecretary of State for WalesThe Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MPSecretary of State for Social ServicesThe Rt Hon John Nott MPSecretary of State for TradeThe Rt Hon Mark Carlisle QC MPSecretary of State for Education and ScienceThe Rt Hon Angus Maude MPPaymaster GeneraliSECRET
SECRETTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTtHon Norman Fowler MPer of Transportul Channon MPter of State, Civil Service DepartmentsThe Rt Hon Michael Jopling MPParliamentary Secretary, TreasuryEarl FerrersMinister of State, Ministry ofAgriculture, Fisheries and FoodSii Derek RaynerCabinet Office (Item 4)SECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMi M D M Franklin (Items 2 and 3)Mr P Le Cheminant (Item 4)Mr P J Harrop (Item 1)Mr R L Wade-Gery   (Items 2 and 3)Mr W N Hyde (Item 1)Mr D J L Moore       (Item 4)CONTENTSSubj ectPARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSSocial Security Bill: Option Mortgages forPurchase of AnnuitiesSiege of Iranian EmbassyFOREIGN AFFAIRSUnited StatesIranCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSCommunity BudgetCIVIL SERVICE MANPOWER AND COSTSPageSECRET
CONFIDENTIALENTARY    1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House or Commons during the following week.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES said thatduring the Committee stage of the Social Security Bill in the Houseof Lords there had been considerable support for an amendment toenable elderly people, who mortgaged their houses in order topurchase an annuity, to obtain through the option mortgage schemethe equivalent of tax relief on their mortgage payments, even thoughtheir incomes were too small to make them liable to income tax.While the amendment was totally irrelevant to the main purpose ofthe Bill, a similar amendment might be passed at Report stage.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthere should be urgent consideration by the Ministers concerned ofthe merits of the proposal and of the line that the Governmentspokesman should take during the Report stage of the Bill and, ifnecessary, during the Commons&apos; consideration of Lords&apos; amendments.The Cabinet -1. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer,in consultation with the Secretary of State forthe Environment and the Secretary of State forSocial Services, to consider the attitude theGovernment should take to the propo sal thatoption mortgages should be available to elderlypeople wishing to mortgage their existing housesin order to purchase an annuity.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE HOME DEPARTMENTr,ibassy      informed the Cabinet of the latest position at the Iranian Embassyin Princes Gate, about which he would be making a statement to theHouse of Commons that afternoon.    Three gunmen had seized theEmbasry the previous afternoon, taking about twenty people hostage,including one Metropolitan Police Officer and two BritishBroadcasting Corporation staff who were in the Embassy applyingfor visas at the time.    The gunmen were threatening to blow up theEmbassy and the Iranian hostages at noon unless their demands forthe release of prisoners held in Iran were met.    The MetropolitanPolice were in contact with the gunmen by land-line, and weredealing with the situation by the means found successful in previoussieges.   Their task had been made more difficult by the failureovernight to cut off all normal telephone communication to and fromthe Embassy, but this had now been done,1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALThe Cabinet -2.        Took note.2.        THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat the resignation of the United States Secretary of State,Mr Vance, was a matter for regret.    His successor,Senator Muskie, was not well known outside the United States, buthe seemed more likely than some of the alternative candidates(such as Mr Christopher, who lacked standing, or Mr Brzezinski)to exercise the moderating influence on United States foreign policywhich had been characteristic of Mr Vance.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatfollowing the failure of the United States rescue attempt there wasno evidence of xenophobic backlash among the Iranian people.While the staff of the British Embassy in Tehran had been reduced,the Ambassador himself had returned there on 24 April. TheEuropean Council at Luxembourg on 27-28 April had confirmed theintention to proceed with sanctions against Iran, althoughdiscussions were continuing about their scope, particularly inrelation to current contracts.    The Government remained firmlyccmmitted to passing by 17 May enabling legislation under whichsanctions could be imposed.   Asa minimum such legislation wouldneed to have passed the House of Commons by that date.In the course of a brief discussion it was noted that the Government&apos;supporters in the House of Commons disliked sanctions but werealso aware of the overriding need for Alliance solidarity. Supportcould be expected from all but a handful of them, provided that theissue of compensation could be avoided by exempting currentcontracts.    The Leader of the Opposition remained willing tosupport sanctions for the sake of maintaining the solidarity of theAlliance, but the attitude of many of his supporters was hardeningagainst them, not least on grounds of general anti-Americanism.Opposition support for the Sanctions Bill could not therefore becounted upon.    The position in the House of Lords might also provedifficult.    Meanwhile opinion in international banking circlesincreasingly underlined the damage which would be done to theworld monetary system and the position of London as a financial2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALcentre if any attempt were made to sequester Iranian assets here.This was an area where Britain had much more at stake than herpartners.   As regards commercial contracts, however, the French,Germans and Italians all stood to loje more than the British.The Cabinet -Took note.3. THE PRIME MINISTER said that a sequence of events hadled to the issue of the United Kingdom net contribution to theCommunity Budget not being discussed until the second day of theEuropean Council in Luxembourg on ?,7-28 April.    During thepreceding Friday she had had a visit from Signor Cossiga, thePresident of the Italian Council of Ministers, who had previouslyseen President Giscard d&apos;Estaing of France.    President Giscardhad put forward some promising new proposals which would haveset an absolute ceiling on the size of our net contribution for aperiod of years irrespective of the growth in the overall CommunityBudget and subject to review at the end of the period.    From asubsequent telephone conversation with President Giscard it wasclear that, whereas we were unwilling to make any movement onagricultural prices and sheepmeat in advance of a Budget settlement,the French wanted decisions on Common Agricultural Policy (CAP)prices, sheepmeat and fisheries before settling on the Budget. Asa result, it had been agreed that parallel meetings should be heldover the weekend of the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) and agroup of officials to deal with the budgetary question.    In the event,the French representative did not join the group of officials untilSunday morning and then had no authority to put forward any Frenchideas.   As a result, the European Council at its first session on27 April had discussed other matters.    It was only after dinner,during which foreign affairs were discussed, that she was able toobtain agreement that the official group should resume effectivediscussion that evening.    When presented, the ideas put forwardby the French representative were considerably lees attractive thanthose originally suggested by President Giscard.    In the meantime,the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) had reached agreement amongthe other eight Member States on proposals to increase agriculturalprices by an average of 5 per cent, with increases of 4 per cent onmilk and sugar.    These proposals and related measures wouldincrease agricultural expenditure by 1, 000 million units of account(mua) and would thus raise still further the proportion of theCommunity Budget devoted to agriculture.    The other MemberStates were also ready to agree on a common organisation of the3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALmarket for sheepmeat which involved intervention, the use ofexport rebates (which would have disrupted New Zealand markets),and differential prices in favour of French producers.   It wasagainst this background that there had been a protracted negotiationon our Budget contribution.   We had eventually been offered alimitation of our net contribution to about  325 million but only forthe year 1980.    In a subsequent proposal, our net contribution in1981 would have been limited to about  550 million.   She had feltthis latter figure was too high, and that it was not possible to settlefor an arrangement which covered only one year.    The unwillingnessof France and Germany to agree to precise figures beyond two yearsarose from their preoccupation with the increasing burden,specially on the Federal Republic, compared with other MemberStates for whom it represented only a reduction in their net benefit.An alternative proposal which would have given us a refund of1, 000 mua for the first three years and 800 mua for the followingtwo years was not acceptable because it did not give us adequaterelief.When deadlock had been reached on the Budget question, theEuropean Council had gone on to discuss agricultural prices,sheepmeat, fisheries and energy on each of which we had beenisolated.    France and Germany had wanted us to agree to increaseNorth Sea oil production in times of crisis.    But the biggest disputehad arisen over fisheries on which we were being asked to reaffirmthe principle of free access in terms which would be unacceptableto the fishing industry.    In the absence of any agreement on theseissues, the European Council had not reverted to the Budget questionand had ended with no agreed communique on any of these points.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that theEuropean Council had been a missed opportunity.   Had it beenpossible to make more rapid progress earlier in the meeting, andto organise the negotiations in such a way as to allow for properconsultation and reflection, a settlement might have been possible.It would now be difficult to persuade the others to maintain theoffers they had made.    Chancellor Schmidt had told him that inproposing a reduction of our net contribution to  325 million hehad offered double the authority he had had from his Cabinet andthat, if it had been accepted by us, he might have been faced withthe resignation of his Finance Minister.    Others were feeling sourar.d upset.    He did not therefore think that the prospects of resumingnegotiations on the same basis were very bright.    He would howeverbe putting suggestions to the Prime Minister as to how we shouldproceed in the immediate future.4CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD saidthat the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) would be meeting on5-6 May.    There would be considerable pressure to adopt theproposed price increases by majority voting, thus setting asidethe Luxembourg compromise which had no legal force.   It appearedthat the Commission had now decided to maintain its support forthe 5 per cent price increase in spite of its earlier proposals forlower price increases and the reservation which had been expressedthat it was doing so only in the context of an overall politicalsettlement.   It was unreasonable for the Commission, who werein favour of reform of the CAP, to give way to pressure from othersin advance of a solution to the Budget issue.    We should warn ourpartners that any attempt to call into question the Luxembourgcompromise would create a very serious situation. Alternatively,the Commission might be asked to agree that the new prices shouldbe implemented nationally with the Community recouping thefinancial consequences once the Budget question had been settled.This would put us in the intolerable position of financing othercountries&apos; surpluses on a basis to which we had not agreed. Ourrefusal to accept the agricultural price settlement was the strongestcard we had to secure a satisfactory Budget settlement.In a discussion on CAP prices, it was suggested that the positionof the Commission was not yet clear.    During the discussions atthe European Council, Mr Roy Jenkins had made it plain that theCommission would never have tabled the revised price proposalshad it not been for the need to settle the Budget issue at the sametime.    The Commission did not appear to have addressed itself towhat its position would be if there was any question of voting in theCouncil.   If it seemed likely that efforts were being made to settlethe Budget issue during the next few weeks, the possibility of votingon agricultural prices might not arise until nearer the end of May,at which time the new agriculture prices would have to come intoeffect or the existing Regulations be prolonged.    The French andthe Italians both wished to secure devaluations of their Greencurrencies.   If these were agreed to at the forthcomingAgriculture Council, they would enable those Governments to givesome immediate increase to their farmers and thus reduce thepressure for early implementation of the higher common prices.The Luxembourg compromise had formed the essential politicalelement at the time of this country&apos;s decision to join the EuropeanCommunity and if it were called into question now, the politicalconsequences would be very serious.    We should consider urgentlywhat needed to be done through diplomatic channels during the nextfew days.5CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALOn the other issues, the following points were made -a. Budget.    The period covered by any Budgetagreement, including the arrangements for its review, wasvital.    If it was not possible to get agreement on figuresbeyond two years, we should seek agreement on a mechanismdesigned to create an acceptable outcome for the third year.b. Fisheries.    There would be serious politicalconsequences if we accepted unsatisfactory provisions onaccess and quotas.   The Commission had not yet producedproposal8 on quotas which would be acceptable to us and nomeeting of the Council of Ministers (Fisheries) had beenfixed.    The arrangements for access and the treatment ofthird countries would need to be very seriously consideredin order to safeguard the interests of the fishing industry,which was already in serious economic difficulties,especially the deep water section of the fleet.c. Sheepmeat. The arrangements agreed would be atouchstone as to whether or not there was any real desirewithin the Community to reform the CAP.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said theCabinet endorsed the position which she and the Foreign andCommonwealth Secretary had taken at the European Council. Whathad been on offer in Luxembourg had not been acceptable. Urgentconsideration would now be given to the next steps.   We should notdespair of a satisfactory outcome before or at the next EuropeanCouncil in Venice on 12-13 June.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.6CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALISERVICE       4.        The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofOWER. State, Civil Service Department (C(80) 24) about Civil ServiceOSTS numbers and costs, and a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet(C(80) 25) to which was attached a ndnute by Sir Derek Rayner tous the Prime Minister on the efficiency of central Government,sees:18th The Cabinet&apos;s discussion and conclusions are separately recorded.isions 4 and19thisionst5Cabinet Office1 May 19807CONFIDENTIAL
  f SECRETOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCABINETCOPY NOLIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEXCC(80) 18th Conclusions, Minute 4Thursday 1 May 1980 at 9. 30 amThe Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of State,Civil Service Department (C(80) 24) about Civil Service numbersand costs, and a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet (C(80) 25) towhich was attached a minute by Sir Derek Rayner to the PrimeMinister on the Efficiency of Central Government.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, despite the successive savings inmanpower already agreed and the continuing and strenuous efforts ofMinisters to promote efficiency in their Departments, Civil Servicenumbers were still higher than at any time in the life of the previousConservative Government.    If the Government was to fulfil itsManifesto commitment and satisfy the expectatione of its supporters,it would need to bring numbers down to the level of twenty years ago,by a combination of reducing functions and improving efficiency.The papers now before the Cabinet made proposals for acomprehensive programme to this end.SIR DEREK RAYNER said that there was impressive evidence fromthe reviews so far undertaken by Departments that the work ofcentral Government could be done more effectively and with lessstaff and less cost.   It was also clear that there was a strong willin the Civil Service to promote reform, and a good deal of enthusiasmand talent, particularly in middle management and in the lower ranks,which had a contribution to make if it could be engaged effectively inthe work.    But if progress in lasting reforms were to be made,Ministers themselves would have to be actively involved in theprocess.    Clearly they had far wider responsibilities pressing upontheir time and attention; but unless they were ready to show an activedesire for and interest in improved efficiency, no lasting reformwould be achieved.    To be able to do this, each Minister must knowthe costs of the activities of his Department, and could not abdicateresponsibility for what was done in his name.    He must also attend,SECRET
SECRETand be known to attend, actively to the welfare of his staff. Inthis connection it had to be said that, though conditions variedgreatly, there were too many large concentrations of excessivestaff where inadequacy of the office aids available and unsatisfactoryworking conditions were leading to very high rates of staff turnover.THE MINISTER OF STATE, CIVIL. SERVICE DEPARTMENT, saidthat the decisions which the Government had taken so far had led toreductions in Civil Service numbers from 732, 000 in 1979 to705, 000 now, with the prospect of reaching a total not much over670, 000 by the end cf this Parliament.    This was not sufficient.Sir Derek Rayner&apos;s findings, and the work already completed byDepartments, illustrated the scope for further substantial savings.He recommended, therefore, that the Government should announcenow that their aim was to reduce the Civil Service to no larger than630, 000 by the end of this Parliament.    If achieved, this would bebelow the previous lowest post-war figure of 640, 000 in 1961. Toallow for some increase in staff in particular areas where it mightprove unavoidable, the target should include a small contingencymargin of about 10, 000 which the Civil Service Department wouldadminister.    To meet the net target of 630, 000 each Departmentshould aim to save Z\ per cent of staff numbers in each of the years1981-82, 1982-83 and 1983-84 in addition to the savings that hadalready been agreed.    Within these targets an effort should be madeto reduce numbers in senior grades, on which progress had beenpoor so far; and each Department should reduce its posts atUnder Secretary and above by 10 per cent between April 1979 andApril 1982.    He was convinced that the target of 630, 000 wasfeasible.    Nearly 250, 000 staff were likely to leave the CivilService anyway over the next three years.    There would berelatively little need for compulsory redundancy.    The target wouldgive Departments an opportunity to plan and to phase reductionsover a three-year period.    But it was essential to announce thetargets now, both to give an impetus to making further savings andto remove uncertainty in the minds of staff.In discussion the following main points were made -a.        While Ministers had to be closely and activelyconcerned in savings and improving efficiency, it wasimportant that this should not be allowed to detract fromthe responsibility which fell upon their PermanentSecretaries,    Otherwise there was a danger of failing toachieve lasting benefits.    The Prime Minister&apos;s intentionto discuss the Government&apos;s objectives for Civil Servicemanpower savings with Permanent Secretaries collectivelywould be very helpful in this respect.2SECRET
SECRETb. If Ministers and Permanent Secretaries were to beable lo be as effective in management as they would wish tobe, it was necessary for them to have greater freedom fromcentral control.    They need3d to be free to move staff, togive incentives to individuals, and to make early retirements,without the constraints of regulations and controls imposedby the Civil Service Department.    Similarly it was importantto change the present relationship between Departments andthe Property Services Agency.   As it was, Departmentswere neither knowledgeable about their own accommodationand related costs, nor in a position to make improvementsthey considered necessary or savings they considered feasible.The present system of rigid annual financial allocations alsoinhibited useful change, and a measure of flexibility couldlead to significant savings in fhe longer term.c. Individual Departments had identified important savingsand developed new techniques of management: the experienceof the Department of the Environment, as described to theCabinet by the Secretary of State, was particularly interestingand valuable.    It would be helpful if these, together withSir Derek Rayner&apos;s ideas, could be drawn together centrallyand then made generally available.   In this way good practicecould be spread and Departments could learn from theexperiences of each other.d. While there was general agreement that theGovernment should set itself the aim of reducing CivilService numbers to 630, 000 by the end of this Parliament,and that no levels or grades in the Service should beexcluded from the programme of reductions, it was not clearthat a series of annual departmental targets was in presentcircumstances the best way to achieve this aim. Targetsof that kind were valuable as  purs to action and yardsticksof progress, but they severely limited the scope forflexibility in achieving the aim, both as to timing over theperiod between now and the end of the Parliament and as todistribution between Departments.    Moreover, experiencesuggested that staff were more responsive to cuts if theyfelt that proposals had first been worked out with care andin depth.    There was a danger that, faced with imposed,and apparently arbitrary, targets, they would regard the newproposals as simply the next instalment in a series of ad hocdecisions by the Government.    In this event their co-operationmight be lost and savings made harder to achieve. AllDepartments would need to make equal effort to improveefficiency and reduce functions, and all would have to contributeto the savings required; but some would inevitably need to be3SECRET
SECRETable to contribute less than others: it was unrealistic toexpect that identical percentage cuts could be applied acrossthe board without regard to the functions of individualDepartments.e. It was suggested that the announcement of a decisionto reduce Civil Service manpower further by a definiteamount might have a damaging effect on Civil Servicemorale.    On the other hand it was argued that, if the Cabinettook such a deci sion, it was likely to become known even ifit was not formally announced.    There was a strong casefor removing uncertainty among staff about the Government1 sobjectives and a firmly stated target for the life of aParliament would achieve this, besides being popular in thecountry.    There was considerable slack in the system andprogress in reducing this had so far been disappointing. Atarget announced now would be both a stimulus and ayardstick against which to measure further progress.f. It was likely that the constraint of cash limits coulditself lead to further squeezes on manpower numbers inlater years.   Reductions for this reason should not be regardedas additions to but as a contribution towards the proposedoverall target.    The precise interrelationship would need tobe considered further.    Further thought should also be givento whether the proposeo contingency margin was adequate todeal with significant changes in circumstances, such asrising unemployment.    A larger contingency allowancewould provide greater flexibility in achieving the overall aim.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that there was scope for further reductions in CivilService numbers, and that the objective should be a Civil Serviceof no more than 630, 000 by the end of this Parliament.    She wouldconsider further with the Minister of State, Civil Service Department,the terms and timing of an announcement of this decision bearing inmind the desirability of making the announcement before theopening of the Annual Conferences of the main Civil Service unions.This pointed to a statement in the following week.    The Cabinet wasnot minded to adopt annual targets for each Department as a meansof achieving this aim: it was recognised that some Departmentswould be able to make proportionately greater savings than othersthough each should contribute.   The savings should be achieved bothby cutting out and simplifying functions and by further improvementsin efficiency.   Each Minister should now review the functions andefficiency of his Department, and then send to the Minister of State,Civil Service Department his plans for reductions in the staff4SECRET
SECRETemployed by his Department over the period to 1983-84. TheMinister of , tate, Civil Service Department, should +henco-ordinate the detailed plans with a view to ensuring that theyprovided a basis for reaching the overall target.    Each Ministershould also send to the Minister of State, Civil Service Departmenta description of the management practices and techniques used inhis Department to control staff numbers.    The Minister of State,Civil Service Department should then summarise these in a paperwhich would be made generally available to Departments in orderthat experience could be shared.    The Cabinet would consider at alater stage further proposals, and progress reports, from theMinister of State, Civil Service Department and Sir Derek Rayner.The Cabinet -1.        Agreed that -a. the Government should aim at reducing thelevel of Civil Service manpower to 630, 000 by theend of the present Parliament (in effect, by1 April 1984);b. provision should be made within this aim fora contingency margin, which might need to be greaterthan the 10, 000 proposed by the Minister of State,Civil Service Department, to allow for increases ofstaff made unavoidable by external factors (such asrising unemployment);c. the consequent reduction would need to beachieved flexibly, both as to timing and as todistribution among Departments, rather than by asystem of annual departmental targets;d. savings in manpower should be sought bothby cutting out and simplifying functions and by furtherimprovements in efficiency.2.        Invited each Minister in charge of a Departmentto put in hand, in consultation with the Minister of State,Civil Service Department, and Sir Derek Rayner asappropriate, a detailed review of the functions and activitiesof his Department and the preparation of a plan for cuttingout and simplifying functions and improving efficiency, andto report progress regularly to the Minister of State, CivilService Department.5SECRET
SECRET3. Invited the Minister of State, Civil ServiceDepartment, to provide advice and assistance as requiredfor the proposed departmental reviews and plans, and toco-ordinate and monitor progress reports fromDepartments, with a view to maintaining the necessarymomentum in reducing functions and improving efficiencyand to reporting to Cabinet from time to time on progresstowards the agreed objective.4. Invited the Minister of State, Civil ServiceDepartment -a. to arrange for the programme of worksummarised in Annex D to C(80) 24 to beimplemented, and for the Civil Service Departmentto discuss with each Department ways of simplifyingits manpower intensive activities;b. to report to Cabinet in due course on theuse of the grading structure (Annex E to C(80) 24));c. to report to Cabinet by the end of July 1980on pay, promotion and retirement policies in theCivil Service;d. to ensure that management experience andthe best management practices in individualDepartments, and experience resulting fromSir Derek Rayner&apos;s work, were effectivelydisseminated, and to report progress to Cabinetin due course.5. Took note with approval that the Prime Ministerhad commissioned a programme of work by theChancellor of the Exchequer, the Minister of State,Civil Service Department, and Sir Derek Rayner on therecommendations in Sir Derek Rayner&apos;s minute attachedto C(80) 25.6. Took note with approval that the Prime Ministerwould give Permanent Secretaries an account of theGovernment&apos;s proposals and enlist their support forthe programme of improving management and efficiencyand reviewing departmental functions.7. Took note that the Prime Minister would announcethe Government&apos;s aims and proposals in a statement inthe House of Commons the following week,6SECRET
SECRET8.        Invited the Minister of State, Civi] ServiceDepartment, to inform the Civil Service Trades UnionsStaff Side of the Government&apos;s proposals shortlybefore the Prime Minister made her statement, withthe assurance that it was the intention to keep compulsoryredundancy to a minimum.Cabinet Office2 May 19807SECRET

</content>
</cab>
