<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/221/0 images: 15-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic MajestyTs Government,ECRST.CABINET.NO ...... P.103(31)INTERNATIONAL LABOUR DRAFT CONVENTION CONCERNING THE MARKING OF THE WEIGHT ON HEAVY PACKAGES TRANSPORTED BY VESSELS.Joint Memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Minister of Labour.1.    We desire to invite the attention of our colleagues to this Draft Convention, which was adopted at the Twelfth Session of the International Labour Conference held at Geneva in 1989.2.     The Draft Convention proposes that any heavy package of 1,000 kilograms (one metric ton) or more gross weight consigned for transport by sea or inland waterway shall have its gross weight plainly and durably marked upon the outside before it is loaded on a ship or vessel.      In exceptional cases where it is difficult to determine the exact weight, the Draft Convention provides for national laws or regulations allowing the approximate weight to be marked.      The obligation to see that this requirement is observed is placed solely upon the Government of the country from which the package is consigned and not on the Government of a country through which it passes on the way to its destination, and it is left to national laws or regulations to determine whether the obligation to mark the weight shall fall on the consignor or on some other person.3.     The object of the proposal is to protect the dock worker against the dangers to which he is exposed through the collapse of cranes used to lift heavy packages of unknown weight, which exceed the capacity of the crane.     Accidents due to this cause not infrequently happen with serious results to workers employed in the vicinity.
4.     In reply to the questionnaire addressed to them on thesubject, H.M. Government stated that they would be in favourof such a provision, if practicable, and at the Conference theBritish Government Delegates voted in favour of the DraftConvention.   The British employers&apos; representative at theConference voted against the Draft Convention, alleging thatits proposals were unworkable, and that it would be impossibleof enforcement.In the course of the discussion preceding the vote,Sir Malcolm Delevingne, a British Government Delegate at theConference who was also Chairman of the Committee of theConference which considered the matter,said&quot;The value and importance for the prevention of accidents of the practice which is embodied in this Draft Convention is generally recognised, and has not I think been questioned by any party in the Committee over which I presided.     It is generally agreed, I think, that provided the adoption of the Convention is found to be practicable, and also provided that it is adopted by a very large proportion of the maritime countries, or the countries which engage in overseas trade, it would be of considerable value for the prevention of accidents through the over-loading of the machines engaged in the lifting and lowering of goods.I think, however, it is desirable to emphasise the fact that the utility of the Draft Convention will depend to a very large extent on its being adopted by a large proportion of the States which engage in such trade.&quot;5.     The German Minister of Labour has approached us on the question of ratification, and the matter was discussed at a Conference with German Government Officials in London.    The German view agrees closely with that&apos; expressed by the British Government Delegate at the Conference, and it was agreed that, subject to the approval of the two Governments, steps should be taken by Great Britain and Germany to ascertain&apos;the intentions of the Governments of the chief exporting countries of the world as to the ratification of this Draft Convention-The Governments to be approached would include those of the principal European countries, the British Dominions and certain
South American countries.     It is very desirable that if the Draft Convention is to &quot;be ratified ,by the principal States Members of the International Labour Organisation, the United States of Amerioa, although hot a member of the Organisation, should also aot in conformity with the practice of other exporting countries, and it is proposed that steps should also be taken to ascertain whether the United States Government would be prepared to require the weight to be marked on heavy packages exported therefroni*   We accordingly recommend that the Government should approve the proposal to ascertain the intentions of other countries in this matter.6.-    Legislation would be necessary to enable H.M. Government to ratify this Draft Convention and in approaching the Governments of other countries on the question of ratification it would obviously be necessary to indicate the attitude of this country.     We recommend that they should be informed that H.M. Government would be prepared to introduce the legislation necessary to enable them tj&apos;o ratify the Draft Convention if it be found that the countries whose adhesion is necessary to make it practically effective are prepared to ratify it.J *!R * G a23rd April, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
