<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/221/0 images: 215-220</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet, May, 1931.SECRET.Copy No.   5CP. 117 (31).THE CABINET.REPORT BY THE VICE-CHAIRMAN OF THE IMPERIAL WAR GRAVES COMMISSION ON HIS VISIT TO INDIA, IRAQ, SYRIA, PALESTINE AND EGYPT.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.I circulate extracts from a report by Major-General Sir Fabian Ware, Permanent      45 Vice-Chairman of the Imperial War Graves Commission, who has just returned from   General a visit of inspection to our War Cemeteries and Memorials in India, Iraq and the Near     ?930 East.   I hope these will interest my colleagues in the Cabinet.   The very beautiful and reverent work of the War Graves Commission is deeply impressive in Europe, and must be doubly so to the Eastern mind.   A sketch map showing the distribution of the war cemeteries is attached.T. S.The War Office,loth May, 1931.On the invitation of the Government of India, I attended the Inauguration Ceremonies at New Delhi on 9th to 14th February, as representing the Imperial War Graves Commission, who had had some share in the erection of the Indian War Memorial Arch ; the Commission had agreed to the Viceroy&apos;s suggestion that on this Arch should be engraved the names of those 13,516 missing who lost their lives on or beyond the North- West Frontier and for whose commemoration in some such form the Commission was responsible. The unveiling of this Arch by the Viceroy was marked by a solemnity and grandeur worthy of the occasion. At the opening of the ceremony I expressed the Empire&apos;s enduring gratitude to India for the part she had played in the Great War, recalled the spirit of free co-operation promoting real financial partnership in which the work of the Commission had been carried out in the past and would continue, and emphasised the principle of equality of sacrifice, which had formed the basis of the Commission&apos;s policy of honouring the dead. At the conclusion of the Delhi ceremonies I proceeded on a tour which had been arranged for me by the Commander-in-Chief, and visited the war graves in different parts of the country.Starting from Peshawar (where there are two cemeteries) I visited the Khajuri and went through the Khyber Pass to the Afghan Frontier ; I then went on to Malakand. Everywhere I found the war graves maintained with soldierly pride and reverence and nowhere was this more striking than in the little well-cared for cemeteries in the Khyber Pass itself, and high up on the frontier hills at Malakand.Among the other cemeteries I inspected were those at Mardan (the headquarters of the Guides), at Agra, at Bombay, and at Karachi. These were all admirably maintained, both the artistic level of the monuments and the horticultural treatment being above the standard of an average public cemetery in England. It was a disappointment to me to find that the war graves had not been marked with the Commission^ pattern of headstone, India thus being the one exception, literally of any country in the world, in which this Imperial monument is not seen. It is regrettable that this Imperial link should not have outweighed all other advantages in the minds(B31/8)   70   6/311   W.O.P.   5656This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.
of the branch of the Indian Army concerned, but I am in communication with the present Commander-in-Chief whose sympathetic reconsideration of the matter is assured.From Bombay I proceeded by sea to Basra, this being the first opportunity I have had of being away from London long enough to visit the war cemeteries on the old Mesopotamian battlefields. Even now the visit had to be a hurried one, but thanks to the excellent arrangements made I was, in eight days in all, able to go up the river to Amara and Kut, thence to Baghdad, and then across the desert to Damascus.It is not often realized that our losses in Mesopotamia were greater than in any other of the war areas, with, of course, the exception of France and Flanders. The dead have now been concentrated in five cemeteries : Basra, Amara, Kut, Baghdad and Mosul, there being Indian cemeteries also in each of these places. How very many of these graves had to be collected from old trenches on desert battlefields, will be told in detail in the Commission&apos;? records ; that so many were recovered and identified is due to several officers who themselves took part in the campaign.To deal with our prisoners of war first, whose unsurpassed sufferings have been described by Sir Arnold Wilson in a chapter of his book &quot;Loyalties&quot; one of the most harrowing stories ever told of British soldiers. Their graves, scattered throughout Asia Minor, were sought our. and whenever found the remains were brought back for sepulture in Baghdad. There they rest in a large plot some 500 of them. On their last journey they received a spontaneous salute as they passed through Syria, the French garrisons lining the streets and presenting arms. I am arranging for this plot in the Baghdad cemetery to be marked with a special inscription.The Baghdad cemetery is also distinguished from others as here is seen the only departure in the whole of the Commission^ work from the principle of equality of treatment. In the centre of the cemetery is the grave of the Commander-in-Chief, Lieut.-General Sir Stanley Maude, surrounded by hundredls of officers and men who served under him. The very special circumstances and the site of the grave justified, in the opinion of the Commission, its being marked by a special memorial which forms a central architectural feature.While on the one hand this cemetery has to be protected from the occasional floods when the Tigris overflows its banks, on the other hand there is no regular water supply which makes it possible to grow trees or to carry out any but the most meagre horticultural treatment. In this connection, the local Committee, which I met at Baghdad with the High Commissioner, Sir Francis Humphreys, in the chair, unanimously agreed that, while our cemeteries in Iraq were in fact desert cemeteries, they would best express the sentiment which attached to them if we made of them oases. This immediately suggests their being planted with palm trees, and instructions were therefore given to our staff gradually to carry out a scheme of planting. I am glad to say that I have hopes that this water difficulty has been overcome. For I had a very interesting audience with King Feisal ; he expressed deep sympathy with our work, saying among other things that the present prosperity of his country was due to our sacrifices and to our dead commemorated in these cemeteries, for which his people showed, and would continue to show, the utmost respect; and subsequently he assured Sir Francis Humphreys that he would personally arrange for an adequate suppfy of water to Baghdad Cemetery.At Basra and Amara, at both of which there is a quite effective display of flowers and shrubs in some parts of the cemeteries, I have given instructions for a gradual extension of horticulture. I am convinced that the sweetening of the soil and the constant ordinary gardening attention to the soil, which will be necessitated for any satisfactory growth of trees and plants, will incidentally overcome the ravages made in the headstones by the salt and other deleterious matter in the existing soil  ravages before which some of the headstones are crumbling away and no certain remedy for which has been discovered by the highest authorities on the preservation of stone.The cemetery at Kut seemed to me an almost perfect example of what our cemeteries should and might be in these arid surroundings. To reach the cemetery one walks from the river front through the narrow streets of the town, lined with not unpicturesque houses of mud brick ; the monotony is suddenly broken by regular green iron railings between stone gate posts. As one approaches these a grove of palm trees is disclosed, among which are rows of white headstones, the well-Known Cross Of Sacrifice and the massive Stone of Remembrance. A few simple flowers here and there add a touch of colour.    The news rapidly spread that British people
were visiting the cemetery and while we were in it there were rows of Arabs seated on the ground outside watching us, quietly talking to one another but giving every evidence of respect. I have in the course of my work for the Commission taken part in many ceremonies ; I have never been at one at which I felt that the British Empire was being so judged by its attitude to its dead, and I came away convinced that, of all the work.which the Commission have carried out in different parts of the world, none was more important than the simple and dignified, but enduring, expression which they had given among these alien races and religions of the Empire&apos;s gratitude to those who had upheld her honour among them, and that nowhere is it more essential that there should never be any apparent symptoms of forgetfulness of them such .as a falling off in the constant and daily guardianship of their graves. That the Arab gardeners in charge are alive to their responsibility is somewhat naively shown by their occasionally embarrassing claims to superiority over their neighbours as &quot; K.G. Five men.&quot;The imposing &quot; Missing &quot; Memorial, commemorating 4 l,04cS who have no known grave, on the river front at Basra, seemed to me to be rendered less effective by the iron railings, built right across its front for its protection. I was assured by the local British civilians and by officers of the Air Force that there was no reason whatever for this precaution and with this our Committee in Baghdad entirely agreed ; so I gave instructions that these railings should be removed and replaced by a low hedge ; also that an inscription should be carved on the monument visible to -ships passing it and indicating what the monument stood for.The Indian cemeteries in Iraq I found disappointing. In accordance with the wishes of the Indian Government, the headstones, or temporary marking which had been placed on the graves of those for whom, as in the case of Hindus, cremation was not a religious requirement, were removed and the cemeteries treated as &quot; desert cemeteries.&quot; I have reason to think that this decision was dictated by an unnecessary misgiving as to the records of the Indian Army which has proved exaggerated. I am therefore discussing some permanent record of the names in each of these cemeteries. Meanwhile, I have arranged for planting with palm trees and shrubs to be gradually carried out. At present they compare unfavourably with the Commission^ Indian cemeteries in Europe, which are as impressive and beautiful as any of the war cemeteries in France and Flanders. The correction of this defect, in carrying out which I am assured of the fullest sympathy of the Indian Government, would alone justify my tour of inspection in the Near East.Crossing the desert by car, I visited the British war cemeteries at Damascus, Beirut, Haifa, Jerusalem (where in our cemetery on the Mount of Olives I saw the headstones which, by agreement with the Commission, the German Government has erected on their graves, and which, while being distinctive, harmonize with the general architectural treatment), Ramleh, Beersheba, Gaza and Deir-el-Belah. On my return from my last visit to the East in 1929 I reported fully on these cemeteries. I need therefore only say here that there was a general and most satisfactory improvement in the appearance of all these cemeteries due to the steady planting of trees, shrubs and flowers. Even at Beersheba, where drought and an exceptional visitation of locust had destroyed all growth, a very pleasing effect had been secured by the planting of geraniums.At Jerusalem I met our local committee under the chairmanship of the High Commissioner, Sir John Chancellor. I found here, as in Iraq, the greatest pride shown in our cemeteries and evidence of a constant watchful and helpful interest. In all the places I visited, I found from the Visitors Books that there was a continual flow of British visitors in surprisingly large numbers, the greater part local people but a considerable proportion from overseas.From Deir-el-Belah I took the train for Cairo, on -the way visiting Kantara Cemetery. At Cairo, I met our local Committee and went fully into the question of the form of Convention as to the maintenance of our war cemeteries, required to supplement any treaty between the British and Egyptian Governments. This has been the subject of discussion for a long time between the Foreign Office and the Commission, and it was the suggestion of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that I should discuss the matter personally with the High Commissioner on my visit to Egypt. It is difficult to express adequately the indebtedness of the Commission to the Committee for the infinite pains they have taken in this matter, and it will give great satisfaction to the Commission, and particularly to the representatives of Australia and New Zealand, to hear of the understanding arrived at with the Committee and the High Commissioner on this vexed question which has, in the past, caused them much anxiety.
I found everywhere on the part of the local Committees some disquietude as to-the future maintenance of the war cemeteries ; this I was able entirely to allay by explaining the conditions under which the Endowment Fund of  5,000,000 was being established and the progress already made, the Dominions having very nearly completed their full contributions. This gave great satisfaction and evidently relieved them of a real anxiety. I was also received by King Fuad while in Cairo and he showed much interest in our war cemeteries and the construction carried out since he had last given me an audience in 1920. I was able also to remove any doubts he had as to the cost of their future maintenance by explaining the state of the Endowment Fund.FABIAN WARE.20th April, 1931.P.S. I may add that on the way out to India, I visited our cemetery at-Port Said. At Aden 1 went ashore and inspected the cemetery and, in consultation with the representative of the British Resident, decided that our Memorial to the Missing there should take the form of tablets in the hall of the admirable local War Memorial on the sea front,, rather than that of an independent and not as imposing a monument near by.On the way back I visited three of our war cemeteries in Northern Italy. I found them in very good order and increasingly visited by Italians. Among those who have made special visits to pay formal respect to our dead are Prince Umberto and Signor Mussolini.



</content>
</cab>
