<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/221/0 images: 367-437</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT.P.135(31)CABINET.Copy No,State of Trade - April 1931.Memorandum fry the President of the Board of Trade.(Based on reports made at the meeting of the Board of Trade Advisory Council held on April 16th).The reports for April indicate very little change in the general situation.     There has been a further decrease of 61,000 or 2.4 per cent, in unemployment, but this has been confined to men temporarily stopped, and there was little improvement in the basic industries.     The improvement in the woollen industry has been maintained, but the position of-the cotton industry has deteriorated.     There were a number of references to the reports of the recent Economic Missions and especially to the advice given by the Prince of Wales since his return, but it was pointed out, in connection with textiles, that if this country is to turn to the manufacture of cheaper and less durable goods in future, very substantial changes involving heavy financial outlay will have to be made in machinery and in factory lay out.Comparing April this year with April 1930, domestic exports have decreased in value by 30.6 per cent., and imports by 16.6 per cent.     The percentage decline in exports, however, was less than that for the first three months of the year.As has already been stated, there was a decrease during April of 61,000 in the total of unemployed.     The estimated number of insured persons in employment rose between the 23x--d March and 27th April by 89&apos;,5O0 to 9,356,700, being 553,300 less than at the corresponding date in 1930.-1-
In order to obtain a proper comparison in the case of railway receipts, it is necessary, owing to the different incidence of Easter, to combine the two months March and April, and, so doing, we find that total receipts for the 9 weeks ending May 2nd were 9.4 per cent, below those for the corresponding period of 1930;    the separate figures for coal, goods, and passenger traffic were 6.4 per cent.,  12.4 per cent., and 8 per cent,  respectively.     The figures for tonnage of freight traffic are only available up to February, but they show a reduction compared with February, 1930, of 4,808,000 tons or 17.7 per cent.     Reference was made to the ever increasing tendency of freight traffic to go by road - iron and steel, and even coal, for distances up to 20 miles, are carried in this way now.     The Railway Companies themselves carry by road, but mainly through subsidiary companies, in which their investment is not more than  8,000,000, compared with a total railways capital of  1,200,000,000.     Another factor disturbing to the railways, though an economy from the point of view of the country as a whole, is the tendency to send gas direct by pipe line to industrial centres, viz., Nottingham and Sheffield.      In the case of Nottingham, this saves the transport of 27,000 tons of coal per annum.There was some improvement in employment in the coal mining industry during April, the percentage unemployed having fallen from 27.4 on March 23rd to 26.1 on April 27th.    No general improvement is re-ported, however, and it is stated that Continental competition is, if anything, keener, and prices lower.     Coal shipments in April amounted to 3,600,000 tons only, which is 820,000 tons less than in April last year. The Northumberland Collieries, which had been accumulating very large stocks of small coal have reduced their minimum prices for these coals by 2s,6d. a ton in order to meet Polish
competition and it is hoped that an increase of business will result, though apprehension is felt as to the possible disturbing effect upon buyers of any reduction in coal prices at this time.      There were no complaints during the month regarding the operation of the schemes under Part I of the Coal Mines Act, 1930, which may be taken as an indication that these schemes are now working fairly smoothly-.The position of the iron and steel industry is stated to be, if anything, slightly worse than a month ago,      Ov/ing to the incidence of Saster, the output of steel cannot be compared with last year, but pig iron is comparatively unaffected by the holiday, and this shows a decrease of 6 per cent. Steel plants all over the country are stated to be working at from 30 to 45 per cent, only of capacity.     There are, moreover, no signs of a revival of orders at home, and on the Continent there has been a further fall in prices for export which British manufacturers cannot follow and which does not appear in any way to be stimulating demand.      Canada remains the only fairly good market.     Some encouragement, however, may be gleaned from the import and export figures for April:    imports in quantity were the lowest and exports the highest recorded since November last, and although imports still exceed exports, the gap has been becoming smaller since December, and last month was only 5,500 (or, if we take account of the small re-export trade, 4,800)  tons. The value of the exports is, of course, much greater than that of the imports.The condition of the foundry section of the iron and steel industry continues to be very serious.     Last month the unemployment percentage was 32.82,  (compared with 12.28 in April, 1930), and in Scotland it was as high as 42.The shipbuilding report is again one of unrelieved gloomy Employment further declined, and no orders of any importance have been placed.     Nor, apparently, is there any likelihood of improvement in orders for some time to come, the figures of laid up tonnage in the United Kingdom in April being the highest
n a (&quot;*       **      3 0 5yet recorded (15.1 per cent, of the gross tonnage of the United Kingdom is reported to be laid up.    Of all flags, some 10,000,000 tons gross is laid up all over the world).    During April there was a large export of grain from the Argentine, but freight rates remain practioally stationary at a level at which modern economical ships go out in ballast rather than lie up.     Russian chartering has stopped for the time being.Employment in the general and marine engineering industry has again deolined;   moreover, the conferences of employers and employed which have been considering the state of the industry in order to arrive at agreed measures for improvement have broken down.      There was a slight improvement in employment in the motor vehicle industry.   Ho change compared with last month is reported in the electrical industry.During April, orders were placed in this country by the Egyptian, Indian, and Rhodesian railways, and some good orders (one valued at  100,000)    connected with electrification have been placed for work in this country.   An order for the supply of aero engines to the Finnish Government has been obtained by a British firm in the face of French and American competition.    Some orders from abroad such as one from Russia for the electrical equipment for rail mills ( 200,000), and from Spain for the complete equipment for a steel works, illustrate the tendency of other countries to supply their own finished products.Conditions in the non-ferrous metals industry are very depressed.    Prices in some cases have fallen to fresh low records, but without stimulating consumption.There was a further seasonal improvement In employment in the building industry, but unemployment is still high in spite of the fact that this is the best period of the year for building.    Costs have also been brought down very considerably, though it was pointed out that several firms dealing in building materials such as bricks, cement, paint, have been paying high, sometimes very high, dividends.    Russian competition in this sphere was reported in the shape of 11,000    oors shipped
through Finnish and Esthonian ports.    Satisfaction was expressed at the setting up by the Ministry of Health of a Committee to consider the regulations for the use of steel in building.After the small improvement during the last two month-,, unemployment in the cotton industry rose in April from 36.5 per cent.  (March 23rd). to 38.2 per cent.  (April 27th).    The price of the raw material declined during the month and American cotton was only about 1^-d. a lb. more than Indian j at that margin, however, Lancashire has bought satisfactory quantities of Indian cotton.    Russian cotton (of good quality) was imported on a considerable scale during the first quarter of the year and alchough imports during April were small, it is said that further large supplies will be ready for delivery in due course.      The home trade in printed goods has been somewhat better and the report from the dyestuffs industry records a better demand for dyes for textiles.    In India the boycott is reported to be as severe as ever, but exports of cotton piece goods to India were higher in April than in March, though still less than half the exports in April, 1930. Figures were put in showing that the consumption of piece goods per head in India had in 1929-30 nearly reached, at 16 yards, the highest pre-war average, 16.28 yards per head, but whereas then (1913-14)  the imports were to the home output as 3 to 2, this proportion had by 1929.-30 been reversed,  roughly 2-4- to 3-jj. Business in China is hampered by the difficulty of arranging credit facilities and by the change over of the duty to a gold unit basis which at present increases the burden of  the tariff. There are reports of considerable Japanese activity in the cotton piece goods market of Uganda.Employment dn the wool textile industry again improved, but the raw material has declined somewhat  ;n value and no further general improvement in the industry is reported.
Machinery activity in April was, however,  2,9 per cent, more than a month earlier, 1.5 per cent, less than a year ago. Japan bought a record quantity of wool in Australia this season and Japanese competition in this trade in the future is feared.There is a somewhat better tone in the hosiery industry than a few weelts ago, but reports vary from district to district and, generally, activity appears to be below normal for the time of year.There was no appreciable ohange in the chemical trade, though there has been, as stated above, a better demand for dyes for textiles and the demand for heavy chemicals for the east and for fertilisers is satisfactory.    Russian competition is complained of in Brazil.    Efforts to effect a scheme of standardisation for the chemical industry have been successfully completed by the establishment of the Chemical Division of the reorganised British Standards Association which is to be styled the British Standards Institution.llormal seasonal activity is reported in the boot and shoe industry.The price of imported wheat rose appreciably during the month.    Russia is not offering much wheat at present, but good supplies are coming from the Argentine and are available, in Australia where there however, less pressure to sell; India is offering wheat which will compete with Australian wheat.    Canada and the United States are shipping somewhat less o,ving, it is understood,  to the unwillingness of shippers to accept the low prices ruling in Europe.The Co-operative and departmental stores continue to report an increased volume of sales compared with last year, coupled with a decrease In values.    Decreases in retail prices are now stated to be about equal to the decreases in wholesale prices.
The reduotion in the re-discount rate of the Federal Reserve Bank from 2 per cent,  to 1-g- per cent,  effected an important change in the monetary position here and after being &quot;pegged&quot; at 29/l6 per cent, at the beginning of the month the re-disobunt Rate in this country fell by \ per cent,  to 2s/is per oent,       notwithstanding this fall, however, the London Ratea remain relatively higher than the corresponding Rates in New York and Paris and It is important that this position should be maintained in order to keep foreign money invested here until our foreign trade improves enough to provide sufficient credits abroad to balance the exchanges-    New Capital Issues in April were abnormally low.The report on India states that, generally speaking, prices are now about pre-war level, raw materials being somewhat below the level and manufactured goods somewhat above.    Indian exports of pig iron in 1930 increased substantially both to the United Kingdom and to the United States of America, but this was more than off-set by a very large falling off in exports  to Japan,    Incidentally, it was pointed out that, contrary to popular belief,  the export of pig iron from India to the United Kingdom is a very long-standing trade, dating back to the first half of last century.V7.G.Board of Trade.30th May,  1951.
I H D B X.Australian Trade .................................... 53Boots and Shoes............................,........ 25Building ............................................ 10Chemicals...........................................    1Ooal  ................................................    8,25,41Colonial Trade ......................................    9,47Co-operative Trade.................................. 17&quot; &quot;      in Scotland...................... 15Cotton.............................................. 14,22,24.38Electrical Industry................................. 37Employment.......................................... 34Engineering...................................... ...    8,13Pood................................................ 15,17Hosiery............................................. 23,50Indian Trade........................................ 13,40Iron and Steel......................................    5,8,28,51Money..................................*............ 32Motor Vehicle iiegistratlons......................... 38Non-Ferrous Metals.................................. 42Railway Traffic .....................................    3,37,52Retail Trade ........................................ 26Rubber Boots and Shoes .............................. 54Russia, Trade with.................................. 59,46Shipbuildins ........................................    7,11Shipping............................................    6,29South American Trade;  ................................    55V/heat...........................................----    7,16,18,46Wool................................................ 20,33,45Statistical Data.................................... Annex.
MEETING OF THE BOARD OF TRADE ADVISORY COUNCILCHEMICALS.DR. CLAYTON:    Conditions in the chemical industry have not shown any particular change in recent weeks.    As regards heavy chemicals, the demand for alkali during March shewed no improvement, either in the home trade or for export.   Sales in China, Japan and India are reasonably satisfactory, consider-ing the political situation in those countries.   With regard to India, there is no news of any substantial remission of the anti-British boycott, and the recent Increase in customs duties is another disturbing factor.    Further Russian competition is reported from Brazil.The demand for mineral acids is still extremely poor, due, in the main, to the Inactivity of the iron and steel Industries.   The demand for chlorine products is suffering, to some extent, from depression in the paper industry, which appears to have increased recently.    This is offset, to a certain extent, by a rather better demand by the rayon industry.During March, demand for sulphate of ammonia In the United Kingdom was stimulated considerably by good weather, and good buying occurred in the North of England and in Scotland. Deliveries during March, however, were considerably lower than those during the corresponding month of 1930.   Throughout April there was a satisfactory demand in Scotland and Ireland, but a falling off in England and Wales, particularly in the South.   Deliveries for April also show a decline on those for April, 1930.In regard to export, the demand in Spain has shown marked improvement following heavy rains which have been esq? erienced after a prolonged spell of dry weather.    Sales have scarcely been affected by the recent political upheaval.    That, of course, is a few days old.   There has been a sharp fall In the value of the peseta, and the consequent tendency to restrict the granting of credit may reduce the volume of business. Sales in the Far East and in other export markets are considered satisfactory.Some improvement has occurred in the main dye-using trades.   Consumption of.cotton oolours has increased appreciably, indicating that the ill effects of the lockout referred to last months- are wearing off.    This improvement is evident In all classes of colours which find use in the cotton trade.   Dyers still complain, however, that they are working from hand to mouth, and find that they have to deal extensively with small orders - one or two pieces to a shade - which is naturally uneconomical.With regard to the rayon trade, although the imports or rayon hosiery have increased very much in comparison with the early part of last year, and exports have declined, production of yarn compares favourably with that ruling last year, and has shown considerable Improvement during the past few weeks.    It&apos;is hoped that*See A.C. 222, page.1.-1-
this improvement will he reflected in the demand for dyestuffs.    Speaking generally the home demand for dyestuffs is a fair reflex of the conditions in the textile trades in the United Kingdom.As far as export is concerned, sales of indigo compare unfavourably with last year, hut the sales of other dyestuffs show an increase.    So far no dislocation of business in Spain can be traced to the recent political developments in that country.The Budget proposal to increase the duty on hydrocarbon oils by 2d. per gallon will have a serious effect on two chemical manufactures which use turpentine as an essential raw material, via. camphor and terpineol.    The new synthetic camphor industry in this country has been struggling to compete with the natural material from Formosa and the German synthetic product, and the addition of the 2d. per gallon to the existing duty of 4d. will be a very severe handicap, as the duty adds 12s.4d. per cwt. to the cost, an addition which the German industry does not have to face.   The reduction in the price of turpentine in the past few years does not affect the position, since our competitors have benefitted equally by these low prices.    In the case of terpineol, we have steadily lost export trade since the duty was first imposed in 1928.     The Association of British Chemical Manufacturers wish to press for a drawback equivalent to the duty to be allowed on all turpentine used in the manufacture of chemical products for the following reasons:-(l)   All the turpentine has to be imported and cannot be made in this country.(2)   No other raw material can be used in its place.(3)   Drawback on export of the product cannot be secured since the turpentine has lost its chemical identity.(4)   The extra cost of the duty imposes a serious handicap in the Industry both in home and foreign markets and militates against the development and expansion of these new key industries.(5)   The total gallonage affected is at present about 65,000;    the loss to the revenue would only be some  1,600 per annum and no administrative difficulty should arise in supervising the claiming of drawback in the two factories concerned.The negotiations which were initiated a year ago in regard to chemical standardisation were successfully completed last week, - hen the inaugural meeting was held of the Provisional Council of the newly constituted Chemical Division of the organisation which will in future be known as the Standards Association of Great Britain.     The Association of British Chemical Manufacturers has taken the leading part in this movement from the chemical side, and, with the cordial co-operation of the British Engineering Standards Association, it has been possible to evolve a scheme of organisation which should meet the standardisation needs of industry as a whole. There will be four co-equal and autonomous divisions for engineering, chemistry, buildings and textiles.
The Council of the Chemical Division is fully representative of all the various interests involved and with the spirit of loyal co-operation which has characterised the proceedings to date, should soon be in a position to co-ordinate and accelerate the work of standardisation in the chemical field and to do for chemistry what the British Engineering. Standards Association has done and is doing so successfully for engineering.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE:    I listened to the passage about camphor with great interest.    I gather that there are two firms, not one ?DR. CLAYTON: Two.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE; But there is one predominating concern?DR. CLAYTON: I do not know that.    The Association gave me those particulars and asked me to put them before you.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE: No turpentine remains in the finished product?DR. CLAYTON: Ho.    It has been changed into camphor or this terpineol, which is not turpentine.   It is not the same product, and so the drawback would have to be given on the turpentine that goes into the factory.    There iB no turpentine in the f ina.1 product.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE: We promised to look at that point.    It Is the familiar difficulty of trying to meet one small case without landing ourselves in difficulty probably with others, but I will have a look at that again.DR. CLAYTON: Thank you.RAILWAYS.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD: There is no change to report as regards the general tendency in the railway industry.    The receipts of the Railway Companies, over the 18 weeks to the 2nd May, show a general decrease of  5,750,000 or 1G%.    That is not all equally distributed.   The worst group of traffic is merchandise which shows a decrease of 14$, coal a decrease of 7f-? , and passenger traffic a decrease of 7%.   The figures for the last 4 weeks ending 2nd May are rather difficult to judge from because of the different incidence of the Easter holidays last year and this year.    They show, however, over the 4 peeks a decrease of 101$; roughly speaking, the same as in the whole year, though it affects the different descriptions of traffic differently.The most discouraging feature about that is that it was about the end of March last year when the increasing tendency in railway receipts cee,sed and was replaced by a decreasing tendency:    so that for the month of April we are comparing
tl the figures this year with the figures on a lower basis last year.   We had hoped that, when that time came about, the receipts this year and last year would approximate more to one another.   As a matter of fact, the deoline of 10%, which took place in the first 3 months of the year, is continuing throughout the 4 months, and looks like continuing during the current month,I have the particulars of the receipts of the German rail revenues and they are down by  8,500,000 over the same period aa compared with  5,750,000 in this country.   Other people apparently we as unfortunately placed as we are.Among particular incidents, I may say, that we have recently had an import of fully manufactured Russian doors at Hull   amounting to 200 tone, or 11,000 doors, which are coming now from Finnish and Esthonian ports, not from the Russian ports direct.There has been a tendency in Nottinghamshire and South Yorkshire to transport gas from coke ovens at the collieries by pipeline to gas works In the towns, and I have a note that just recently the Nottingham Gas Works have been supplied with gas direct by pipeline from the Pinxton coke ovens, and are reoeiving about l^r million cubic feet daily.   That, of course, is an economical movement in the direction of getting the best user of waste products, but it Is an unfortunate one from the railway point of view.   In that particular case it means the loss of something like 27,000 tons of coal per annum.   It Is of course a tendency which has, I think, gone still further in the Sheffield district where the coke ovens are supplying gas direct to Sheffield.   I am afraid it is another case where the Railway Companies have got to bow before the tendencies of the times.   We have to search for our consolation elsewhere.The best consolation I can find this time is In a very different field.   Our Import of cut flowers from the Hook of Holland shows an Increase of 100% as compared with last year. During the season we have imported close on 3,000 tons of out flowers from Holland as compared with 1,460 last year.   Even that is not muoh consolation to the country because it is all Import and very largely replaces cut flowers from Lincolnshire,MR. WALMSLEY? Do you know what the percentage drop was in the case of Germany?SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:    I cannot tell you that but I think It is certainly higher than in this country.MR. VARLEYf Oan you say whether motor road transport is taking the higher class of goods such as furniture?SIR RALPH WEDGWOODS   Tes, they have attacked those classes of goods long ago.   They got quite a large proportion of the higher, class goods such as furniture.   That was one of the first things they went for.   We are getting some of that baok by making special arrangements, partly by oarrying it ourselves by road.   They are now, of course, attacking the lower class goods:   manufactured iron and steel la going In quite considerable proportions by road.   Even coal is beginning to go by road for distribution up to 20 miles.
MR. VAHLEY:    I should have thought the lower class goods v/ould not have paid the motor traffic and the oharges incidental thereto.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:    The low class goods, no.   The railway rate there is much lower, and hitherto It has not paid the motor trade to attack that class of goods.PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OF TRADE:   Do I understand that all the figures you have quoted to us are on the purely railway basis, that they do not relate to anything you are doing now in road transport?SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:    So far as we carry it ourselves it will be in, but of course the carryings of the omnibus companies or haulage companies that we are interested in financially do not come in, and it is in that direction that we are developing mostly our interest in road haulage.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE:      I gather that the railway amalgamations are making pretty steady progress in building up these interests in road transport.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:   Yes, but those are all by means of subsidiary companies.    Their receipts do not figure at all in our receipts.    Our share in those concerns merely comes in in the form of a dividend at the end of the year so far as the finance is concerned.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE:    That would be taken into account in any strict analysis of the railway position?SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:   Yes.     Of course it iB relatively a very small thing.     The whole railway investment in passenger road transport   at the present time, does not amount to more than  8,000,000, and that oompares with a total railway investment In railways of  1,200,000,000.IRON AND STEEL.MR. WALMSLEY:       I have a very uninteresting report. Things are slightly worse, if anything, than they were a month ago.In pig iron the production in April was 323,200 tons against 357,100 in Llarch.      Steel was 397,400 tons in April against 500,100 tons in Maroh.     That big drop is accounted for to some extent by the holidays. In pig iron the holidayo do not affect tho production, and the drop was about 6% calculated on a daily rate.Three blast furnaces went out of operation during the month, two are going to be lighted up, I believe, on the North East coast, but I should not be at all surprised if one or two others have to go out during the ourrent month.The excess of imports over exports during April was only 5,500 tons.      Imports fell from 210,500 tons in March to 193,400 tons In April.     Exports rose from 170,300 tons in March to 187,900 tons in April.     It happens that the April exports were the highest wo have had for 6 months.
Generally, steel plants over the country are working at anything from 30% to 45% - in one or two odd cases 50% of capacity.   There are no signs of any improvement at all In most of the trades on which we depend for our custom, such as shipbuilding.   Constructional work maintains a fairly steady level, but nothing like full capacity.   The only export market which is of any interest to us at the moment appears to be Canada, and orders from there are coming forward on a moderate scale.Unfortunately, since last month&apos;s report, there has been a further considerable fall In Continental prices, and today1s quotations are in some cases well below the low records of 6 months ago.   These further falls in prioe on the Continent have had no apparent effect in stimulating demand, and It is still a puzzle to us to know why the Continental makers continue to fight in this absurd way, reducing their prices well below cost of production.   It is still going on, and there does not seem to be any sign of a check at present.SIR WILLIAM CLARE LEES: With regard to Continental selling below the cost of production, does that apply to what they sell Inside their own country?MR. WALKSLEY:   No.    In the majority of cases the Continental makers have the benefit of protection in their own country, and their prices at home are considerably higher than their export prices.   In Germany, for instance, where the steel makers give what are known as R.V. rebates to German consumers of steel who use that steel for export, those R.V. rebates are, according to the description of steel, from say 20/- a ton up to 50/- a ton.   They are actual ly al lowing 5G/.-* a ton on some ,s-teeX which they supply &quot;to their home mist omere-when-t-he- -finished material is destined for export.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE:    To what market has any part of the Increase in the exports last month gone?MR. WALMSLEY:    I think Canada accounts for some of it, and South Africa accounted for some rail material.    Those are the only two I can think of where there has been any increase^.SHIPPING.SIR ERNEST GLuVER:    I have nothing very interesting to say.    There is certainly no Improvement to report.The freight index number as a matter of fact is one point up, at 85 compared to 100 in 1913.In outward business in this country there has been a slight upward movement In freights to the Mediterranean,*The April returns show that the exports of rails to South Africa increased from 12,ou0 in March to 21,000 tons in April; plates aid sheets showed good   increases also, especially galvanised where the figures were March 15,685; April 27,205.
Apparently they need to cover certain contracts, but that improvement has rather petered out since.As far as coal to South America is concerned, there has been no movement at all, and rates are only at a level equivalent to going out in ballast.With regard to general cargo, I understand there Is a little more hope in the Midlands, resulting largely I think from the Buenos Aires Exhibition.   So far, it has not manifested Itself at all in any improvement in freights on general cargo either to South America or South Africa.Coal shipments remain at a low level, about 3,600,000 in April, and about the same figure in March, which is about 1 million tons less than the same period a year ago.In homeward grain chartering, the demand from Russia, which was so strong a few months ago, seems to have come to an end.    There has been a   very large export of grain from the Argentine, rates remain practically stationary, and are just at a level which Induces modern economical steamers to go out to the Argentine in ballast rather than lie up.    There is no profit but there Is no more loss than Is involved in lying up.As far as the East is concerned, we are hoping for an Improvement from India, but it has not come yet, and a very small amount of chartering is doing.   Prom Australia rates remain much about the same.   There have been a few trans-actions, and further shipments are expected.As far as America and Canada are concerned, there was an indication of activity a month or so ago, but that has rather disappeared also, and the impression we haVe is that the shippers of grain from America and Canada are not prepared to face the loss involved in the low prices in Europe.As far as sugar from Cuba Is concerned, the market remains very dull with very little doing.SHIPBUILDING.So far as cargo ships are concerned, shipbuilding is at zero.    I am told that one small coasting trade vessel of about 200 feet in length has been placed during the month.In spite of what has been attracted to South America, the amount of laid up tonnage remains enormous..    I am putting in figures-&quot;&apos;- to show that In thi3 country 3 million gross tons British tonnage are laid up, and the estimate made for the whole world, including about 1-1 million American tonnage which will never go to sea is something like 10 or 11 million tons -an enormous figure.MR, VARLEY:   Why will   that American tonnage never go to sea again?SIR ERNEST GLOVER:;   They were ships largely built in war time to fill an urgent/demand for tonnage.    They were built hurriedly, and large numbers of them have already been scrapped and this is the remnant which has been lying up for years, and they simply never will   go to sea.*See page 29.
MR. VARLEY:    They are simply awaiting the time for &quot;breaking up?SIR ERNEST GLOVERi    That is all.SIR WILLIAM CLARE LEES:    Is the practice of the Brazilian Government, of levying a heavy duty on bunker coal still a source of loss to shipping in that part of the world?&quot;When we were on the Mission, we did not feel that we could make much of a grievance about the duty on coal for internal consumption, that was rather a domestic question, but we did feel a serious grievance in their charging so heavy a duty on coal for bunkering.SIR ERNEST GLOVER:    The consequence of that is that as at Rio we have to pay a very high price for bunker coal, we avoid bunkering at Rio.IRON AND STEEL.MR.  CHADY/IOK:    The production of iron and steel castings remains in a very depressed state still.      In the Scottish area, covering the whole of ScotL and, up to 19th April,  1930 there were 13.8$ -unemployed and on 18th April, 1931 42.14$.     On the North East Coast,  baking in Leeds and other parts of the West Riding of Yorkshire, in April 1930 there were 13.56$ unemployed, and on April 18th, 1931, 37,19$ In Lancashire and Cheshire, in April, 1930 there Were 12.7% and in April,  1931 27.83$.      In the Southern Counties, inclusive of the Midlands, there were 8.37$ in April, 1930 and 23.83$ on 18th April, 1931.     Taking the whole of the country and contrasting the figures of the two years, there were 12.28$ unemployed in April 1930 and 32.82$ on 18th April., 1931,     Those figures* give some indication of the position . in the industry at the present time.Apart from that a very serious position has arisen in the general engineering industry.      It had been hoped that something would have been done to put this industry -upon its feet.     Both sides, employers and employees, have got down to this particular question of late,  investigating    the whoLe position, but I am sorry to say that they have not been able to arrive at anything satisfactory to both sides.     At the present moment the position is very strained, and one cannot at this time definitely state what is going to happen.    It is very regrettable, but there the position is.MR. WALMSLEY:    I asked, two or three meetings ago,t whether there was any information available as to the effect of foreign competition in the way of the ordinary castings. I do not know whether you have any information?MR.  CHADWICK:    The only information we have is to the effect that the conditions in Continental countries are not the same as in. this country.     With regard to imports, the Department was good enough on the last occasion the question*See page 28.see Minutes for February (A.CO. 220.p. 21).
was asked to place a note at the bottom of the re-port stating what the import of castings was on that occasion.*SIR RALPH WEDG/WOOD:    Is there any tendency for the manufacture of castings to move further South?     Does Scotland still maintain its predominance in that respect?MR.  CHADWICK:    Scotland, in the past,was chiefly engaged round about the Clyde with shipbuilding and the like, heavy engineering.,     The heavy side of the trade at the present time is in a very depressed state.       The heavy tools are not being made to-day that were made in the past.     The engines used in the vessels are not of the same character to-day as they used to be.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:    What about the castings industry for houses, and so on - light castings?     Is that thriving more in the South than in Scotland?     Is there any tendency for it to move South?MR.  CHADWICK:    No.     There is a firm at Croydon which supplies those types of castings, and at Luton, but the great home of the light castings trade is still Falkirk.COLONIAL TRAPS.MR. VEENON:    I will put in a report.**     Most of it consists of figures, but there are a few things which I think the Council might like to hear something about.-With regard to the Tin Restriction Scheme, we have figures of ocean shipments of tin from Malaya in March and April which show 6,179 tons in karch and   7,900 tons in April.     The output of tin and tin ore at 72,&apos;a was 4,500 tons in March and 4,600 tons in April.     Under the Tin Restriction Scheme, Malays is restricted to nearly 54,000 tons a year out of a world production of 145,000 tons or 37.19^.     That represents very nearly 4,500 tons per month, which is the maximum she is allowed to produce and export. Therefore it appears that in March and April exports were largely in excess of the quota, and will have to be reduced in subsequent months.     The scheme came into force on 1st March,     The object of the scheme is of course to keep up the price of tin and to prevent violent fluctuations in it.     The price of tin on 2nd March was  123^2.6.      It fell to  113,18.9 on 8th April, to  111.6.3 on 16th April. Then there was a slight recovery, and that was followed by a further fall to  103 on 4th May.     The present price is about  105.We have a report from Uganda on the subject of trade mainly in cotton pi...ce goods, which lays great stress on Japanese competition and says that in the cheaper lines Japanese imitations   of Lancashire prints are being sold at a price of about lOJis to 30,a below that of the things which they imitate, and apparently Japanese competition is getting the markets there.* Imports of castings of iron and steel in the rough for the first 4 months of 1931 were 2,925 tons valued at  62,896 i.e.  very much below the figures for the corresponding periods of 1930 and 1929.**See page 47.
*he rubber statistics show that for the first three months of this year there has been a decrease of 17,000 tone In the exports from fialaya as compared with last year,   as a matter of fact, the exports in march were actually higher this year than last year but for the three months there has been a decrease of nearly 17,000 tons.    Nearly all our other figures show the kind of drip in exports and imports which one would expect.   Of course these figures are values, and therefore it is partly due to a fall in prices.   We have complete figures for the year for Kenya and Uganda.   The exports decreased by 1-1- millions, the imports decreased by rather more.    Northern Rhodesia is an exception,   I have only the figures for 10 months to 30th October, but owing to the mineral development going on there, there is an actual increase.   The exports show an increase of nearly  25,000 for the 10 months.   The imports  show a very large increase of  1 million, which of course represents the process of development of the copper nines in that area. For Sierra Leone 1 have the figures for the first 2 months of this year, and they show a decrease of exports of  100,000 and in imports of nearly  60,000.   The figures for Nigeria are getting very serious.   I have only one month of this year, but the decrease in exports for the single month iE over half a million, and the decrease in imports  932,000. For Cyprus I have figures for two months, which show decreases of exports of  70,000, and imports  64,000.   Ceylon figures are also very serious.   Down to the end of   February, the total decrease in exports was  982,000 while the decrease in imports was  1,569,000.MR. VaRL.vY:    In what type of imports has the decrease occurred in Nigeria and Sierra Leone?MR. VxRNON:    I have not the details, but of course what it generally represents is a large fall in export prices of a rather earlier period, and therefore a decreased purchasing capacity on the part of the native population of Nigeria.    I have not the detailed figures for the ditferent classes of goods.   Generally speaking, the Import reduction lags slightly behind the export figure.BUILDING.toR. J3ARR0N:    The building industry, unfortunately, has not shown the recovery that usually comes at this period of the year.    The total number of unemployed according to the latest returns was 137,029 or 22.5 per cent, of the industry.* While that Is a slight reduction on the previous month it is 6.5 per cent, higher than a year ago, and as this is the best period of the year for building work there seems to be little likelihood of any material improvement this year.Building costs are down considerably, and that fact coupled with the avoidance of any labour trouble In the industry should encourage potential clients to proceed with buildings that&apos;may be necessary or are already overdue.* This is the figure for march 23rd; the figures for April 27th are 162,314 or 19,5 per cent, compared with lo.9 per cent, on April 2ath last year.
One hopeful feature which may be of interest also to the steel industry, is the fact that, on the initiative of the steel makers, a very influential and widespread Committee has been set up to enquire into the effect of the building by-laws on the expansion of the building industry.   As one can visualise, the by-laws wero drafted and put into operation long before steel was used in the building industry, and it is&apos; stated that buildings where steel is used at the moment are carrying a safety load 100$ more than is nocessary.     As a matter of fact some figures comparing. American buildings with our own, show that, according to the by-laws in London particularly, you require to have practically double the margin of safety in steel structures that you have in America.   As I say, on the initiative of the steel industry, a Committee has been set up to advise the Minister of Health as to how, not only in this matter but on general matters, the by-laws may be brought up to date. That may have a stimulating effect on the industry.It is rather curious to note, ooinoident with the decline In the building industry, the undoubted prosperity of some of tte concerns connected with it.     Many of the concerns manufacturing or supplying materials used in the building industry are quite flourishing.     I have quoted a few, but it oovers the whole of the materials.    The London Brick Company and Porders, who are practically the main brick suppliers of the Industry, paid a dividend of 20$, which was slightly down from previous years. British Portland Cement paid 15$, which was also on a par with previous years.    Patent victoria Stone, which is ooming greatly into use - artificial stone - paid a dividend of 50$,     The International Paint Company - Dr. Clayton was commiserating with them in connection with some of the ingredients they use, such as turpentine - paid a dividend of 12$.    The Maidenhead Brick and Tile Company, whioh is a very large concern, paid a dividend of 70$, and also had some bonus shares added and put a large sum to reserve.     That dividend was down from the previous year, when they paid 90$.     I may say that these figures are taken from &quot;The Economist&quot; so that I am hoping that they are correot.     The New Merton Board Mills paid a dividend of 15$, the Bath and Portland Stone firms 25$, and Pinchin Johnson, connected with the paid industry, alBo 22^$.     So that it is rather curious that while the industry is so depressed those industries which are connected with it in such a way should have such a time of prosperity, and I would commend it to whichever Department has the oversight of these things, to make some enquiry into that matter.SHIPBUILDING *In regard to shipbuilding, it is quite true that shipbuilding, I think, hts reached a state when it is almost impossible to see anv bright snot in it, but in this connection I should xxke to ask you to use your good offices in a matter which may seem somewhat outside the%coPe of this Council.   It is common In the shipbuilding industry, as in some other industries, to prepare the minds of the work people for a time beforehand for reductions of wages.     That is quite a legitimate idea, 1 suppose,
t5 2 J.on the part of employers generally, hut I think that in the shipbuilding industry in particular, as in some others lately, it has gone beyond the point of real utility and may cause considerable harm to the industry - quite unintentionally, I am sure.     The shipbuilding industry has a tradition that prior to a suggestion of reduction of wages there should be quite a long period of preliminary talks.   In normal times that may be quite all right, because both sides understand the mentality of the other and ore not too much concerned at what is said, but in this instance, and in connection with some other industries, it has gone much further.    Hot content with meeting the representatives of the workers and telling them the horns truths that are necessary, they have taken to broadcasting very nicely got up pamphlets showing the terrible state of the industry.     The engineering employers did it shortly since.     How the shipbuilding people have got out this nico little attractive pamphlet, which is not marked private or confidential, and which is really a report of the address of the President of that body to the workers a few weeks ago, but which, in the hands of outside people, in the hands of competitors in foreign countries, would, I think, create the impression that the shipbuilding industry is practically down and out.      I do not think that is at all the intention of the pamphlet, but I do think that it. has gone to a very great extreme.     It is bad enough to have reports of after-dinner speeches, which are all the more gloomy the more sumptuous the banquet usually, but really, when it comes to distributing this in thousands - thousands are being distributed broadcast over the country - showing.the terrible condition of the industry, then I think that some department, which may give friendly advice to the industry, should counsel them, if you will excuse my quoting an old Scottish proverb which I need not translate to you, that &quot;It is an ill bird that fouls its own nest&quot;, and I do think it is not necessary for this extravagant propaganda to be distributed amongst the workers in the industry.    The workers, as I am sure you will agree, know the state of the industry.    Unfortunatoly, they know it only too well.    On the Clyde, where I come from, thousands are wandering round from one yard to another, besalging foremen on the road to their work, trying to get a job.    They know the state of the industry.    It Is not necessary to go to this length of elaborate extravagant propaganda to tell the world that the shipbuilding industry is down and out.I may be out of place in mentioning that, but I hope that, through your good offices, it may at least be brought to the attention of those in authority.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE:    Not at all.    The whole object of this Counoil is to get a very frank expression of opinion.    I will look at the pamphlet.SIR ERNEST GLOVER:    May we ask by whom;the pamphlet is issued?MR. BARRON:    By the Shipbuilding Employers Federation. I do not want to mislead the Council.       It is sent in bulk quantities of thousands to the headquarters of tho various Trade Unions.     They are supposed to distribute them to the members, but you can understand that it is impossible to keep a thing like that private and confidential to the members.
MR. OHADWICKs Following what Mr, Barron has said with regard to this question of pamphlets, I thought it would be out of place to mention it here at all, and so I did not touch upon it, but it is quite true, as Mr. Barron says, that the Engineering Employers have followed the same procedure to the extent of issuing two different pamphlets on recent dates.   those pamphlets have been circulated to all classes of public bodies apart from those people oonoerned in the Industry, and It is quite true to say that these pamphlets have anything but a good effect upon the people in the industry.   They have been issued in many instances long before the position has been dlBcussed between the parties oonoerned, and they have oreated an impression in the minds of a good number inside the industry that it has been a way of getting behind the position by creating an atmosphere for a reduction of wages and alterations in the conditions of labour that apply at the present time.INDIA.MR. LINDSAY!   The level of prioes in India have not fallen by very much during the last month or two, and shows oertain indications of stability, of oourse with minor fluctuations between different commodities.I should just like to quote one or two eases showing how we stand as compared with pre-war.   Food grain prices, which are of course a very high proportion of our local production, are 18% below pre-war, the basis being prices in July 1914, oil seeds 11$ below pre-war, raw cotton 6% below, hides and skins 24%. below, and raw jute actually 56% below the pre-war price.   Cotton manufactures are 29% above, tea is 1Z% above, and sugar 26% above.   The net result is that our general price level for all commodities 1b just about pre-war, showing the raw materials below and the manufactured goods generally above 100 level.In the import and export trade I am glad to be able to report that our adverse balance of trade during February has been converted Into a plus balance again for March, showing a more normal relationship between the two.There has been some talk about our exports of pig iron to this country, and I Bee that during 19?0 our exports to the United Kingdom were pretty largely increased.   They increased by nearly 7?,000 tons, and our exports to the United States of America increased by 40,000 tons, but against those two increases it must be remembered that our trade with Japan is falling off rapidly owing to the increase in local production in Japan - I think from ore imported from Australia. In our exports to Japan we have lost 185,000 tons during 1910 aB compared with 1929, so that our exports to other destinations do not make up for our loss to Japan.   The opinion is often expressed that this trade is rather new, but that is not at all the oase!    our trade in pig Iron with this country is, in faot, of very long standing.   Between the years 1850-67, oharooal pig iron of excellent quality, the output of the Iron works at Porto Novo,   was regularly Imported into the United Kingdom and extensively used for
rs 9-file purposes at Sheffield and also for railway carriage tyres.   At a meeting held in Sheffield in 1859 it uas predicted that &quot;India would ultimately become one of the largest sources from which Sheffield would dra?f her supplies of raw material&quot;.   An outstanding monument to the quality of Indian pig iron of that period is to be found in the Britannia Tubular Bridge across the Menai Straits, which is constructed of this material.    Pig iron of this particular class was not produced in India for many years, until the Mysore Government built its iron works at Bhadravati a few years ago.    The pig iron at present imported from India is, of course, not smelted with charcoal but with coke obtained from the Bengal Coalfields.In regard to cotton, our prioes have fallen during the last 3 months parallel with the fall In American prices but not quite so rapidly.    The result is that the margin between Indian staple cotton and American middling cotton is now down to about Tg-d, putting American at 5-g-d and No. 1 fine Oomra at 4d.    At that margin we are able to do satisfactory business, of which Lancashire has taken full advantage.The imports into India of British goods have fallen from 105 crores in 1929 to only 74 in 1930,  that is to say a drop of 31 crores, but I should like to point out that roughly half of that is due to cotton piece goods.   Apart from any question of the general fall in prices,  the fall in Imports of British cotton piece goods and cotton yarns was something like 16-1 crores of rupees, accounting for half of the total fall in the imports from the United Kingdom.As the cotton piece goods trade is of some interest at the moment as regards the trade with India.    I have brought up to date the statistics which are published in Appendix IV of the Report of the Indian Tariff Board on the Cotton Textile Industry, and I will put in that statement so that the details may be on record&quot;&quot;&apos;, the net result is - comparing 1900 List with 191&apos;-1914 - the last pre-war year - and then with 1929-1930,  the last year for which complete figures are available - during 1900 there were available for consumption in India 2,878 million yards of which about 1,000 million were local production and 2,000 million Imported, giving an average per capita consumption of 10 yards per head on a population of 294 million.    By 1913-14 the   per capita consumption had gone up from 10 yards to 16,28 yards.    That consumption was the highest it has ever been in India.    Subsequent years show a decline in the per capita consumption.    During the war there was a decline until we come to the year 1919-1920 when the consumption was a little less than 9. yards.    The figures have struggled up again during the past few years and the latest complete year, 1929-30, shows that the per capita consumption is about 16 yards, still a little less than what it was in 1913-14 but undoubtedly showing that there is an improvement in general consumption in India.    I need not add that the production of the Indian mills has increased very considerably and makes up a higher proportion of that 16 yards than used to be the case. During 1929-30 the Indian mills and hand loom production available for local consumption was 3,689 million yard3, out of a total of over 5,500 million yards.    I will put in a statement, Sir. See page&quot;4*0&quot;. &apos;
SIR RALPHT&quot;W3DGW0CD:      Is it the case that of the consumption of cotton piece goods in India about 10 yards out of 16 are supplied locally?       It seems to me to work out somewhere round about that figure.MR. LINDSAY:      It is roughly 3  local to 2 imported.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD.    I suppose in the early year in which you reached the figure of 16 yards per capita, a larger proportion was from outside?MR, LINDSAY: The proportion then was 2 home produced to 3 imported.MR. VERNON. Do your figures show a large increase of Japanese imports of piece goods into India? Is it largely a case of the Japanese ousting British piece goods?Mr. LINDSAY:    That has happened, certainly in the greys, not so much in the whites, and slightly in the colours, but the greys are the line into vhich the Japanese have made such very big inroads.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:    So that the English import has suffered not only from the growth in local manufacture but from the growth of Japanese imports?MR. LINDSAY:    Yes, and, of course, not only from those causes but also from the general decline of purchasing power which has naturally affected most seriously the higher priced goods, the finer goods.SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:    I gather from your figures that the consumption per individual now is about 16 yards, which is about the maximum.MR. LINDSAY:    It is just short of the maximum of 1913-14, but it shows a higher proportion of the coarser goods than of the finer.CO-OPERATIVE trade mr. CAIRNS:     During the past month Co-operative Trade in Scotland has undergone little change from the conditions which have been ruling of late.    Expressed in terms of money the sales of the Wholesale Society have been approximately ten per cent less than a year ago, whilst the quantities of the principal articles of food in constant use have been approximately five per cent more.Regarding sugar the information that the,Chadbourne scheme to restrict crops for the next five years was as good as signed by the countries concerned had no effect upon prices and the price of granulated is ls.l d. per cwt. less than it was a year ago.       In fact so little buying is being done that the market. Seems to be looking for a further reductionIn the price :ef Butter t,hc fluctuations during the month nave been narrow wi&apos;th the price tending downward. The price of Danish for this week is the lowest recorded since 1913.     Our trade, which may be regarded as typical of
that existing in the industrial areas of the country is composed, of nearly 75 per cent. Danish.    The growing consumption of Empire butter at the expense of Danish which has been a feature of the trade for months has received a check at the moment by the price of Empire approaching nearer to that of Danish.     Irish butter is arriving only in small qufntitles, and the quality is very good.That the consumption of margarine relative to that of butter depends upon the comparative prices of the two and that there is a wide margin of preference in favour of butter are two points clearly reflected in the present demand for these commodities.     Consequent upon the greater fall in the price of butter the qi antity being sold is nearly ten per cent, more than it was a Vear ago, while the quantity of margarine being sold is seven per cent. less.New home-made fodder cheese, Cheddar and Dunlop, are poor in quality as compared with New Zealand which is the best value in the market, the finest are being sold at 51/-per cwt., for coloured, and 49/- for white.   The best of the home-made cheese is being sold at 52/- per cwt. which is 14/- less than the price for the same month last year.Eggs with production at the maximum point continue to be plentiful and cheap and cold storing and pickling are absorbing a large proportion of the supplies, though not to the same extent as last season in view of the heavy losses that were then incurred on preserved eggs. -During last month a strong demand arose for Irish smoked hams and prices advanced 15/- per cwt.   Our factory at Inniskillen is meeting with a scarcity of pigs and higher prices have to be paid to obtain supplies.     American hams are also being held for higher prices.     Ayrshire and Irish bacon remain at the former prices any tendency towards an advance being restrained by the abundant supplies of continental bacon.In the course of the month there has been a considerable improvement in the value of wheat.     Canadian has advanced ls.6d., South American 2s.6d. and Australian 4s.6d. per qr. The feeling of our buyers is that as yet this cannot be reckoned as a consolidated advance.   The market will be agitated from time to time by weather reports and if these are more favourable than otherwise,, they in conjunction with the huge stocks that are overhanging the market will have the effect of producing a reaction.   Our flour mills are showing a considerably increased output but as the retail societies are still finding a reduced demand for bread we impute the larger trade of the mills to the successful competition of home-milled with imported flour owing to the higher prices that have been obtainable for offals.Scotch oats will now be scarce for the remainder of the season and they are still advancing in price.      7.15s.Od. to  8 per ton is now being paid for them at country stations. Many farmers in the North are continuing to buy foreign oats to eke out their supplies, and large quantities of Russian have been shipped to various north country ports.The price of home oatmeal   is naturally advancing in price though it is being held back by supplies of Canadian and German of which Canadian is the cheaper.
It is noticeable that the consumption of rice, lentils, peas and kindred cereals is larger than formerly, being doubtless stimulated by their cheapness, as 2d. per lb. and less for more than single lbs.   Is now a general rate for these foods in the retail trade.Last month saw the first arrival of Audtjralian apples for the season.    They were in excellent conditibn and moderate in price, and with American almost finished they found a ready market *At the Pish Department, Aberdeen supplies have1 been large, and prices low, but owing to the cheapness of eggs the demand has been sluggish.During the month supplies of milk were fairly plentiful with the price lower in Glasgow than it has been since 1913. Our price to farmers is lOd. per gallon, and low as it seems, another fact worth noting Is that for New Zealand butter and cheese at their present prices the farmers of that country would require to provide milk at 4d. per gallon. The order against the use of preservative in oream has now extinguished our trade in cream, for which we kept a large creamery In the extreme South of Scotland.   We still maintain the creamery though the best we can do for the farmers is to give them a manufacturing price of 5d. per gallon for their milk.Our sales of coal for the month were 43,766 tons, an increase of 1,593 tons, the average price was 19/- per ton at the pit.In the Drapery,Boot and Furniture Departments, with their auxiliary factories, the sales and transfers are nearly ten per cent less than they were a year ago, and again the diminution is largely oaused by lower prices for the goods.At the Jute Factory, Dundee, comparatively little business is being obtained.     However, we received lately from some Co-operative Danish Bacon Factories an order for 113,000 wrappers for bacon.    It has been hinted that we got the business for the reason that the Danes are anxious to show a good record of purchases from this country as being some return for the large British purchases from Denmark whioh are said to embrace fully 90 per cent of her agricultural exports.MR. VARLEY.    Our experience is very much like that of our Scottish friends.    I might emphasise one or two points to show an increase in trade though there is a decrease in money values.    For instance we have a decrease of 5% in our butter so far as money is concerned, but in weight an increase of 17\%*      In flour we have a small decrease of 2,1% in weight, but in value a decrease of 41,8%.      Other articles convey the same picture.    I would
just like bo point out that the decreases in wholesale prices are now just about equal to the decreases in the retail prices.    In respect of butter generally the values have receded slightly during the past five weeks, Danish has receded 5/66.- Swedish 7/- and Finnish 3/6d. per cwt. Germany is not operating to the same extent as previously and only takes the contract quantity to which it is tied, which appears to be qxiite sufficient for requirements. On the other hand Belgium, France and Switzerland are now taking regularly from Denmark.    Sales of Empire butter have increased in percentage very largely, compared with the amount of trade we do in Danish, especially in the North of England. Values are much lower today as compared with la3t   year. Danish is cheaper by 17/6d   Swedish by 18/6d. Finnish by 18/-, New Zealand by 25/6d. and Australian by 27/- per cwt., so that Australia and New Zealand have come down 8/- to 10/- per owt. more than Danish and Finnish.In anticipation of possible inoreased taxation under this year&apos;s Budget orders to sugar refiners over-taxed their capacity and in order to check sales for pre-Budget delivery they advanced prices 6d. per cwt. between March 27th and April 9th.      This advance was not warranted by world market conditions and the day after the Budget, which brought no change in taxation, they came down 3d. A further 31. reduction has been expected but so far It has not materialised.    This week delegates from Cuba, Java and the Continent meet in Brussels for final signature by all participants of the international five year restriction convention.    The effect of this remains to be seen.The tea market ha3 been very strong and active for all descriptions during the past month, unquestionably due to the approach of the Budget and the Press reports of a possibility of the Chancellor re-imposing the duty on tea, thus causing inoreased clearances and heavier orders from all parts of the country.   Buying has been active and general, particularly for finer grades of Ceylon which, with an improvement in quality, have realised a substantial advance in price.    Common grades have continued firm and medium and good medium descriptions have advanced in price, with good demand and active buying.    The market closed generally firm.Potatoes which a year ago you could scarcely sell and were fetching extremely poor prices today are fetching good prices and English potatoes have advanced in price very sharply and the increased prices are being practically maintained today, although at the moment there appears to be just a slight weakening.Wheat has advanced about 2/&amp;d. per quarter during the month, showing a natural reaction from the extremely low rates to which prices fell.     The carry-over into the new season will be greater than ever.In Canada the enquiry into the marketing of grain is about completed but nothing very important has been revealed, and not much change is expected.    Canada still fights hard to maintain prices.    In the United States of America the Farm Board has sold its holdings on seaboard and in the Gulf to two large firms, with a view to getting on with
the disposal of the wheat by exports to Europe *   Millers in the United Kingdom are refusing to buy except on sample, and the firms concerned have accepted this condition^.    The wheat being very old makes the condition desirable from the standpoint of the receivers and millers of the wheat,    Russia is not offering much wheat at present, and there is some imoertainty as to future intentions.    fund will be required and can best be obtained by exports of wheat.    Some movement during the next three or four weeks is hoped for.    Good supplies are still available in Australia where the financial position i3 not quite so distressed. Pressure to sell is less keen.    India is offering wheat for May/June shipment which will compete with Australian. The Argentine continues a steady selling policy and more trade on the Continent helps to maintain prices.An enormous crop of maize has been harvested in the Argentine, and heavy shipments are being arranged.    Prices being very low it will secure a good business throughout Europe during the   next few months.Then to come to the Drapery side of our business, there has been a better tone during the last two months and whilst last year&apos;s sales figures have not been reached from a monetary point of view, the decrease at the present time is below the percentage fall in values;   further, it should be borne in mind that people purchase lower quality goods.Wool prices are firm, and the present foeling cannot be considered unsatisfactory.    With ootton, however, t/e obvious difficulties continue.     -Trade conditions in the Manchester area in woollens, readymades, outfitting and sports have not changed very materially within the month of April.Progress is difficult and the Immediate outlook not very encouraging.    Buyers continue the policy of buying only for present requirements,  and the demand for cheap grades of goods is still particularly noticeable.Trade in boots and shoes during the past month has been very disappointing, and is certainly not coming up to expectations.    Decreases are shown in all sections and reports from Societies are to the same effect.There is no deviation from March in the Markets position.During April business in general furnishing has been quite brisk, particularly in the carpet Department and with C.W.S. Tyseley Productions, but figures continue to show a decrease which haB been brought about owin;   to the reduced values.    There is also a demand all round for lower priced goods, and Societies&apos; Buyers are now ordering in smaller quantities than usual.We have our usual small export to co-operative societies all over the world.    The only fairly large sum is to Centrosojus,  to U.S.S,Rc, where our exports have amounted to  102,897 during the month.SIR ERNEST GLOVER:    Can Mr. Varley tell us whether the import of Russian butter has affected the price of butter in this country at all?MR. VARLEY:    My impression is that the import of Russian butter as noted in the newspapers is very much-exaggerated.    &apos;&apos;re have been advancing through our credit department on certain exports and they do not approach anywhere near the figures that are given in the papers.
Pi S% Tt HI *3PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OF TRADE:    On these exports to Russia what credit terms are you offering now?jViR. VARLEY:    You mean the period.   Generally round about nine months or twelve months.   We keep within those two periods if we possibly can.PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE:    What proportion of cash payment do you get?MR. VARLEY:    It all depends on the peculiar circumstances of the case.    As far as butter is concerned, we advance before the butter is shipped to enable them to get it from the farms in Siberia down to the shipping port.   Then we advance more when it gets into port and we advance up to 80?&apos; when it becomes a bill of lading.    They are very interesting and rather curious    some of our conditions with them.WOOL.ALDERMAN TITTERINGTON:    There has been no further improvement in the wool-textile industry during the past month.    The turnover in fully-manufactured goods is below normal, mainly owing to the very poor export trade.    Merino combers and botany spinners have continued to be well employed, but there is less pressure for deliveries.   Crossbred combers and spinners are still very short of work.The quietness of business has bcren accentuated by the easier tendency in wool values.   The decline in fine wools has been comparatively slight, but crossbred wools have shown a fairly marked fall,    Most classes of wool, however, are still appreciably above the lowest point.The difficulty of passing on the advance in raw material is shown by the fact that tops are relatively cheaper than wool, and yarns relatively cheaper than tops.   At the same time, the wool season is now drawing to a close and there are no outstanding accumulations of wool except in New Zealand,    This rapid clearance of the wool clips, in spite of the under-employment of machinery, is a very satisfactory feature.Japan has bought a record quantity of wool in Australia this season- which adds point to the recent report of the British Economic Mission with regard ts the growth of the wool industry in that country.The general feeling in the trade is that although the worst of the depression has been seen, recovery will be a slow process,    more export trade is urgently needed, but the only important market where there are immediate possibilities of expansion Is China, and of course the difficulties in that country are well known.Just one reference to the published Report of the Economic mission.    I suppose most of the trade opinion at the moment is very interested in it and one is naturally watching the opinions expressed by all concerned as to how to apply the information whicn has been gained by that Mission.    His Royal Highness the other evening expressed a view on a similar point
. which the Economic mission had already emphasised, that is, the desirability of producing a fabric to meet the price market which will be characterised by being less durable and more colourful.   Well, Sir, whilst those opinions have been expressed in public, they imply very material alterations in the construction of the trade and In the technical side of the manufacture.    If the woollen and worsted trade is to direct its attention to a less durable fabric It implies almost a complete reconstruction of its techniquec    It implies, first of all, the utilisation of shorter wool fibres which hitherto have not engaged our attention and the processing of those shorter wool fibres means almost a complete substitution of the machinery in the industry in order to produce the yarn which will be the basis for a fabric which will have a softer handle and will be less durable and admit of more colourful treatment. The bulk of the people in this room are -wearing worsted fabrics which are of a durable character.   That, of course, is the outstanding quality about the trade in Yorkshire, but if we were to&quot; meet the greater demand for the less durable fabrics it would imply a very material alteration in the construction of the trade which directly and indirectly would involve an enormous expenditure of money in plant and equipment and in the layout of those plants.Passing from the commercial aspect of the trade for the moment to the general industrial side, the Trade Association and the Unions of the Textile Trade which twelve months ago had a difference of opinion with the combined employers on tho waciaillan Report, are engaged in discussions as to the desirability or otherwise of coming to agreements regarding wages and so on in the industry.   That is at the moment under consideration.    The trade has expressed a diversity of opinion.   The outcome of it one does not know because it is &quot;so wrapt in mystery&quot; that one cannot forecast the result.The Dyers&apos; Agreements in which we are interested, covering some 80,000 employees in the dyeing and finishing on the cotton and wool side of the trade, have been approaching a conclusion.    The actual Wages Agreement has been more or less applied, involving a reduction of 6.51$ in the gross earnings of most of the operatives either on piece or day rates and at the moment we are entering into a discussion regarding the formation of a common agreement to cover the conditions of employment as distinct from mere questions of wage scale regulations.   We are involved in the wool textile trade in Scotland in a dispute Involving the wool textile employers, the outcome of which is still in doubt.MR. VARLEY:   Would Alderman Titterington tell us how the trade in woollen and worsted goods is now going with Canada and the United States?ALDERiviaN TITTERIIJGTOH:    I have no available statistics at the moment on that particular point.-::-The Monthly Trade Returns give the exports of woollen and worstedtissues individually to the more important countries.    They showdecidedly low figures for April, 1931 in the exports both to Canada and to the U.S.A.
The difficulty with us in the textile trade is that statistics are not available and, as you know, Sir, the difficulty in compiling an;/ particular Item is that one can get it if one makes enquiry for it, so that I should like notice of any question of that sort and I would willingly supply the information and get the particulars at once.PRESIDENT 03? THIS BOARD OP TRADE:    I would like to welcome Sir William Clare-Lees to-day.SIR WILLIAM CLARE-LEESi   The outstanding event during the last few days in the North of England has been the visit of His Royal Highness to Manchester.     It was a very notable meeting and a very remarkable meeting and one that one was extraordinarily proud to be able to take part in for more than merely trade reasons.     It was a great success.     The organisation was very well carried out.     It was a most difficult thing to allocate seats and so forth, but something like 4,000 people heard the Prince either directly or in the adjoining hall.      I think the lesson one brings from that speech, which Alderman Titterington has just referred to, is the fact that in quite a number of industries, not merely in the textile industry, we shall have in this country to face the fact that, being the first in the field so many years ago, we have established methods of production and types of goods, machinery and so forth, and that when we were supplying 70$ or 80$ of the intake of the various parts of the world of those things we were able to maintain our own choice of production.      It seems quite evident that the drift on the Continent and in the 3ast has been towards making articles of a different material in a different way, durable enough for peojile with very changing tastes and leaning more to rapid change rather than durability, and I think we must in this country face up to that, difficult as it is because the financial difficulty is very great in a depressed industry in finding the money to make those mechanical changes.     I think that is the underlying lesson, not merely of the Prince&apos;s visit, but other Missions which the Board of Trade and the Department of Overseas Trade have organised.     I think we must keep on addressing our minds to that and pursue it, because I think the recovery of the proportion of the world&apos;s trade for this country largely depends   on our adapting ourselves to those changed methods because I do not believe the world is going to change and adapt itself to us.I have one or two reports from various places.     Prom Liverpool, the prices of cotton have been somewhat down on the last month because, as you know, both the Egyptian Government and the American Government are involved in the cotton of their respective countries.     It is a most depressing and disturbing influence.     Nobody knows exactly what they are going to do or when they are going to try to clear their liabilities.     Egyptian cotton has come down a penny during the last month and American cotton about id.      It is rather significant that one half of the raw cotton in Liverpool at the present time is non-American, very different from what it used to be.*   Mr. Lindsay referred to the fact that Lancashire was turning herself to Indian cotton.     That is one of the tendencies&apos;to which I have already referred, the using of a lower grade article.     It means mechanical change.       It means some change in manipulation and perhaps some variation   in the* Imports of raw cotton in 1913 totalled 2lf million centals of which 16 million centals came from the U.S.A;    in 1929 the imports were nearly 15^ million centals of which nearly 85 million centals came from the U.S.A;    in 1930 the imports were nearly 12 million centals of which over 5:7 million centals came from the U.S.A.
3*^ 9durability of the fabric itself, but Lancashire is tending to use a rather larger quantity of that lower class material.The import of palm oil and palm oil kernels into Liverpool from Vest Africa is no greater in the first four months of this year than last, but into the whole country, that is to say including Hull and London, there has been a very considerable increase.     For the four months ending April 1930, 1,322 tons of palm oil were imported into the United Kingdom whereas 7,300 tons were imported during the last four months.     Of course it is at a lower price, but the interesting thing is this, that the people are producing larger quantities although the prices are lower and one is hopeful that those larger volumes, which mean harder work for less money out there, will increase the buying power in a few years time and that perhaps the West   Coast trade will benefit.     I believe that one of the features of world recovery when it comes will be the fact that the growing population of Europe and the rest of the world will be taking larger   volumes at lower prices,    giving an increased purchasing power to the raw material producing nations all over the world.     That appears to be taking place in this particular commodity and I think it will extend to other things.     That is perhaps the most hopeful note I have from Liverpool on those particular   lines. Another point which rather bears on world tendencies at present is in the report dealing with prime lamb;    they say the demand is all that could be desired - that is a most happy state for any industry - and that if supplies were on a more moderate basis values would undoubtedly be extremely satisfactory.     So that there again they are finding the constantly increased productive power pressing on the market and depressing prices in spite of quite a good demand in that particular thing.In the Widnes area employment figures are rather better in April than they were in March,      It is only fractional but still it is perhaps 2 to 3$ more employed than there were a month ago.From the Leicester area I have a report that the prospects for quite a number of factories in the immediate future are a little brighter.     They say there is very little alteration in the styles and colours but momentarily the demand is rather better.     Hosiery they report as still below normal, but slightly better in tone than a few weeks ago. Incidentally they remark. Sir, and I pass it on to you, how disappointed they were that they did not get any safeguarding reference in the Budget.      They refer to neater styles being the tendency of modern fashion and they report that building is about the same as last month and that there is a little improvement in the retail tradex generally speaking, in that area.In Lancashire, of course, our great preoccupation at the present time added to all our other troubles is India. There is a tremendous wave of feeling throughout every section of the community in Lancashire on the subject of the Indian boycott and it takes two forms.     Some people feel that the arrangement which the Viceroy made with Mr. Gandhi was not sufficiently tight and not sufficiently carefully drawn to protect the interests of this country.     Others take the view
9 9 9 O O i)that if that arrangement, or bargain, whatever it was, was indeed drawn in order to protect this country&apos;a interests then there is a definite breach of faith on the part of those in India who are not carrying it out.     One of those two facts must be true because there can be no doubt that we are suffering quite as intensively, perhaps more intensively, from the effects of the boycott to-day than we were before and it is quite evident that the local interests in Bombay and Allahabad are benefiting very greatly by combining their interests with political prejudice greatly to the advantage of native mills in India.     It Is a very serious thing for Lancashire quite apart from all other questions and we have plenty of questions to deal with besides that, but that is so fundamental, and unless the markets of India can be reopened to Lancashire productions we have very little prospect of employing very much more machinery than we employ at present.PRESIDJSNT OP THE BOARD OF TRADE.   That concludes our proceedings this morning.     I should like to say again that Mr. Qillett and I and our colleagues at the Board of Trade are very grateful to all of you for your continued help with these reports on trade matters.     Thank you very much.(The proceedings terminated).
jsiR. BANT ON JONES aent tho following report:-Tho output of Coal in the United Kingdom for the four weeks ended at April 25th was as follows:-week ending April 4th ........... 3,845,000 tons.&quot;    11th........... 3,384,000     &quot;18th........... 5,024,000      &quot;&quot;    25th........... 4,862,000     &quot;The average output for the thirteen weeks January 51st to April 25th was 4,575,000 tons as compared with 5,170,000 tons for the corresponding period last year, an average decrease of 595,000 tons a week.The number of persons employed in the industry for the week ended at April 25th was 868,700, and the average for the thirteen weeks ended at April 25th was 874,900, as compared with 955,700 for the corresponding period last year.     The output per person per week for the thirteen weeks has declined from 5.41 tons to 5,23 tons,  compared with the same period last year.tUnemployment for the month of March was 27.4$ as against 22.5^ in February and an average for 1930 of 20.5^.The quantity of coal exported from the United Kingdom in Larch was 3,404 . 000 tons*. as compared with 3,353,000 tons in February (an increase of 51,000 tons), and 4,570,000 tons in march 1930 (a decrease of 1,166,000 tons).The average price per ton f.o.b. in March was 15/9, as compared with 16/1 in February, and 15/5 in January.Some exports to particular destinations are given below compared with the monthly averages for 1913.March 1931.       Monthly Averages 1913,.Scandinavia......... 225,000 tons 825,000 tons.Belgaurn &amp; Holland ... 417,000     &quot; 337,000   &quot;France.............. 983,000     &quot; 1,065,000   &quot;All destinations .... 3,404,000     &quot; 6,117,000   &quot;BOOTS &amp; SHOES.MR. BOSTOCK sent the following report  am glad to be able to report more activity in the main centres, due largely to  seasonal causes.     For most manufacturers the busiest time of the year lies between Easter and vhitsun.      Ihere were many complaints prior to Easter as to the v/ay the larger buyers had withheld their orders, and therefore greater activity now was to be expected.     How long it will last is another matter.t This comparison takes no account of variations in the numberof days worked per week, * Excluding shipments to the Irish Free State.
Leicester reports trade generally as patchy, with &quot;buying of a hand-to-mouth character, and few firms can see more than a few days ahead.     Northampton is similarly situated.     Orders are coming to hand more freely, and prompt deliveries are required.      Similar reports come from Norwich, Northamptonshire, Leicestershire and other centres.Export trade for the first quarter of the year shows a falling off of 837,000 pairs in quantity and  559,639 in value, as compared with the corresponding three months.I am able to submit the following report as to production:-SIR WOODMAN BURBIDGE sent the following report;-The table for retail trade during March shows results which prima facie appear favourable, but have to be interpreted with certain qualifications..*     Excluding sales of food, which now represent 60,o of the total and v/hich were down by 5C3^6 on the month,  total sales exceeded those in March last year by 4.7/o.      It must be remembered, however, that not only was the weather favourable but the figures included practically all the pre-Easter trade which in 1930 came into   April.      The comparison,  therefore, owing to the variation in the date of Easter, must be regarded to some extent as fictitious.      A favourable feature was that stocks (at cost) were reduced by 9,o, and it is noticeable that this favourable comparison between stocks and sales has occurred every month since the returns first began to be made..Before dealing with April trade I would like to refer to the important addition which has been made to the monthly reports by the inclusion of returns from the Co-operative Societies.      The total turnover on which these percentages are based is now very substantial, and unquestionably constitutes a really representative sample of the retail trade of the country;    important additions, however, are constantly being madet.During March sales in the American Departmental Stores, according to the Federal Reserve Board, decreased by 3,&apos;o whereas in this country the Departmental Stores alone showed an.increase of T/a over last year,      The April figures,when they become available, will certainly make an unfavourable showing-, and it is possible that a falling off in sales of as much as 12i&apos;  may be reported,. This result,again, is not so unfavourable as it appears at first sight,  as apart from the heavy fall in prices the figures this year have to be compared with the pre-Easter trade which last year came* This table is not reproduced as it appears in page 559 of the Board of Trade Journal for April 30th. -J anuary February March .,Dpz. P rs. 663,060 761,990 777,720RETAIL TRADE,
into April.     In addition to this, however, the weather during April was undoubtedly not favourable to retail trade. The true comparison should be between the three months -February, March, and April - as compared with the corresponding period last year, and it is likely that when all the figures are available a falling off of about 3$ will be shown.     In the circumstances, and in view of the experience abroad, this result cannot be regarded as unfavourable.
IRON AND STEEL.MR.  0HADT7IOK handed in the following table:-NATIONAL ONION OF FOUNDRY WORKERS. TtCSLY SUMMARY OF DISTRICT MEMBERSHIP AND NUMBER OF MEMBERS UNEMPLOYED.APRIL 1950. TO APRIL 1931.MEMBERSHIP.District.19 April,! 26 July,.1 18 Oct1930.1930.1930.24 Jan., 1931.18 April, 1931.Totals6,505 7,268 7,997 5,78827,5386,462 7,302 7,894 5,70427,3626,348 7,137 7,798 5,61526,3986,239 7,038 7,779 5,55426,6106,127 6,859 7,732 5,37426,092UNEMPLOYED.j&apos;&apos;&apos;&quot;&quot; strict.        i 19 Apr., !   1930. j	District Percentage Unemployed 19,4.30.	26 July, 1930.	18 Oct. 1930.	24 Jan. 1931.	18 Apr., 1931.	District Percentage Unemployed 10.4.31.i	13.8  &apos; 13.56 12.7 8.37	1,354 1,257 1,238 629	1,874 2,016 1,659 977	2,262 2,351 2,168 1,211	2,582 2,551 2,152 1,281	42.14 37.19 27.83 23.83f     V&quot;   1 &quot;, Totals ..j   3,385 i 1 &apos;t   -........&apos;	-	4,478	6,526	7,992	8,566	-Percentage Unemployed   19th April, 1950,    -   12.28 &quot; &quot; 18th April, 1931,    -    32.82
SHIPPING.this ERNEST GLftVSR handed in the following tablesj-TABLE I.INDEX NUMBER OF SHIPPING FREIGHTS.19S0 a 100.      1915 - 100.April 1931............      19,90 85.04March 1931  ............      19.68 84.10April 1930  ............      19.43 83.03LAID UP TONNAGE   Tonnage laid up at ports of Great Britain and Ireland.Principal Ports. All Ports.British and British andForeign Foreign-net tons. net tons.1st April,  1931  .........    1,557,456 1,890,2341st January  1931  .......    1,331,147 1,593,2471st April, 1930  .........        892,154 892,154April,  1931. April, 1930. March, 1931. Tons. Tons. Tons.Coal exports  ....    3,602,504       4,422,799        5,612,584Bunker Coal shipped for vessels engagedin Foreign Trade.  1,138,008       1,214,388       1,187,300BUNKER COAL PRICES.    Special Durham Bunkers f.o.b. Newcastle.s.  d.Average 19121&apos; ......    14. 0&quot;        1927  ......    16. 3&quot;        1928  ......    15.  3l1929  ......    17.  2&quot;        1930  ......    15.  9i-1931.January ........ 17. 0February ....... 14. 9March.......... 14. 9April  .......... 14, 9Figures for Tonnage under construction are the so; e as those given on page 17 of A.C. 222.
ACCORDING TO AGE AND GROSS TONNAGE.Division of T tonnage.	Under 5 yrs. Gross tons. (00)	5 and under 10 years Gross tons (00)	i 10 and under 15 years Gross tons (00)	; 15 and under 20 years Gross tons (00)	20 and under 25 years Gross tons (00)	25 years and over. Gross tons. (00)	Total. Gross Ton3. (00)100 &amp; under 500 gr. tns.		6	15	3	3	48	75500 &amp; under 1,000 gr.tns.	7	28	114	13	32	92	.2861,000 &amp; under 2,000 gr.tns.	56	392	295	236	311	250	L,B402,000 &amp; under 4,000 gr.tns.	443	719	1.141	1,253	748	1,142	5,4464,000 &amp; under 6,000 gr.tns.	1,127	1.419	4,094	2,963	1,414	798	11,8156,000 &amp; under 8,000 gr.tns.	612	1,179	1,706	1,001	298	288	5,Q848,000 &amp; under 10,000 gr.tn&amp;.	627	444	902	602	333	370	3,27810,000 &amp; under 15,000 gr.tns.	120	673		564	390	125	1,87215,000 &amp; under 20,000 gr.tns.	-	516	313	-	168	-	99720,000 oc over		MM	**		247		247TOTAL		5 376	&apos;    8,580	6,635	3,944	3,107	30,640to to
TOTAL TONMAGE LAID UP IN EACH DIVISION OF AGE AMD SIZE CORRESPONDING TONMGE OWNED BY THE UNITED KIMGDQmIN TABLE 1 COMPARED WITHON 30TH JUNE, 1950.Division of Tonnage.	Under 5 years. %	5 and under 10 years of	10 &amp; under 15 years to	15 &amp; under 20 years $	20 &amp; under 25 years %	25 years and over. %	Total %100 &amp; under 500 g.t.		-0.8	0.9	0.2	0.3	2.0	0.9500 &amp; under 1,000 g.t.	1.0	2.5	12.6	2.1	6.9	7.7	5.81,000 &amp; under 2,000 g.t.	3.1	13.4	14.0	15.5 - -	25.5	13.8	13.52,000 &amp; under 4,000 g.t.	9.5	14.5	27.4	35.5	30.0	35.2	23.64,000 &amp; under 6,000 g.t.	6.2	11.8	24.2	27.3	30.0	25.6	18.06,000 &amp; under 8,000 g.t.	7.8	10.1	19.4	14.7	16.1	18.7	13.28,000 &amp; under 10,000 g.t.	17.2	12.9	21.5	19.6	25.2	46.3	19.910,000 &amp; under 15,000 g.t.	3.1	12.6	-	17.0	21.2	12.6	10.915,000 &amp; under 20,000 g.t.	mm	12.1	23.8	-	32.9	-	10.720,000 &amp; over		**		-	44.6		2.9TOTAL	6.5	10.9	20.4	19.7	24.7	19.2	15.1Ca5 C22
MONEY .MR. GQODENOUGH sent the following reports-An Important change has taken place in the monetary position in this country, as the result of the reduction in the Re-Dlsoount Rate of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York on the 7th instant, from 2% to 1%;%.   This has been followed by a reduction in London in the market rates of discount and the quotation for 3 months&apos; fine Bank Bills has fallen about that is to say, from 2.8A6$ toabout 2.5/16%* the higher rate of 2.e/l6^ having been to a very considerable extent the result of the rate being &quot;pegged&quot; in the market at that level.   The fall in the New York Bank Rate had been preceded by decreases in the market rates for discount in New xork.   Notwithstanding the sharp fall in the London Discount Rates above referred to, the London Rates are still relatively higher than the corresponding Discount Rates both in New York and Paris. The lowering of the rates in London has, however, caused a weakening in the Foreign Exchange position, but aB compared with a month ago, Sterling is standing better to-day in relation to most of the principal foreign currencies.Credit supplies in the London Short-Loan Market have been fairly comfortable, the rates for day-to-day advances being for the most part about 1^% to 2%%, although at the end of April there was a shortage of supplies, and the Market was borrowing temporarily from the Bank of England. This temporary shortage of funds was reflected in the Bank of England Return of April 89th last, when Bankers&apos; Balances with the Bank stood at the exceptionally low figure of  48.9 millions, as compared with an average of about  65 millions in the year 1930.The Bank of England has secured an addition to its holding of gold through purchases in the open market at the statutory minimum price, but the increase has been partly offset by earmarking? of gold to a considerable amount, probably on account of Argentina.   The gold holding in the Issue Department of the Bank of England on the 6th instant amounted to  147.5 millions, which is an inorease of over  2 millions as between that date and the 15th April, the day before the last meeting of this Council.The statement of the London Clearing Banks for April shows a sharp fall in the holding of bills to  211 millions as compared with  240 millions in March.   The higher discount rates In London compared with New York and Paris, already mentioned, have attracted short term funds from abroad and have also tended to restrict the supply of bills for discount In the London Market.   Advances by the Eanks showed an increase of  4 millions, in oontrast with a decrease last year for the month of April of  7 millions, as compared with the previous month in each case.The Stock Exchange has been depressed except for British Government Stocks and certain of the better class Investment securities, which have moved upwards.   PrioeB of most other securities have further declined during, the month.
There Is no clear Indication judging from appearances as they present themselves to the Banks, of any real improvement in the industrial and economic situation.SIR GUT GRANET sent the following reportMonetary conditions have generally been more comfortable than the previous month, although for a few days around the end of April there was a period of scarcity which was, however, dispelled by the May dividend disbursements.   The market Discount rate remained &quot;pegged&quot; at 2/16% until the 8th instant when the announcement that the New York Federal Reserve Bank had reduced its official discount rate to 1-1$ was received in London.   This reduction brings the official discount rate Into line with the cheapness of money in the American market and is the result of the depressed economic conditions which have been ruling there for some time.The reduotion of American money rates should have strengthened the value of pounds sterling in the foreign exohangee, but in faot it has weakened slightly owing to a fall of about \% in the market discount rate here on the relaxation of the recent control by the Bank of England. This reaction indicates the necessity of maintaining the discount rate at a level sufficiently attractive to keep foreign money invested here, and it will be necessary to continue this policy until our foreign trade improves enough to provide sufficient oredits abroad to balance the exchanges. However, call money has been firm during the last few days and while it remains so there Is little danger of the discount rate slipping, away.In the Stock Exchange the markets, with the exception of the gilt-edge market and certain gold mining shares, have been weak on the poor results shown for the past year, and the uncertain outlook for the future.New Capital Issues for the month of April amounted to about  7,000,000 of which about  700,000 was in respect of British Industrial undertakings.   The above total is about one-third of the amount raised during the same month last year,WOOL.MR. HAMILTON sent the following reportThere ha-s hardly been the least change worthy of note during the past month.   The usual seasonal Improvement has been of the slightest character, the most recent figures available Bhowing a machinery activity of 66.9% being an increase of 2*9% over a month ago, and a reduotion of 1.5%. compared with a year ago.    No statistics are available of stocks of raw material, but the monthly figures published in Germany are usually considered to be fairly reliable.   The
most recent figures from this cource read as follows;-Stooks of Combed Wool on the Continent.(in tons).Merinos. Orossbreda.       Total.April,  1930........      10,840 10,162 21,002March,  1931........      12,679 9,151 21,8*0April,  1931........      14,131_9,00?_23,154Change oompared with March 1931...      -KL,452 - 148 +1.304which shows that 1,304 tons more Combed Wool were available for spinning than a month ago.During the past month the only market in the World to show any real sign of activity was Japan.    This fact coincides with the report published by the Mission to the Par East that Japan was likely soon to become a seriouB competitor of this country in Wool Textiles, just as she was already In Cotton good.    Japan has been a very active buyer of wool in Australia, and she has had the advantage over European and American producers that in her case cheap raw material plus cheap labour enable her to put her textiles on the market at approximately pre-war prices.Rumours of a proposed wapes cut are current in Yorkshire, but no labour trouble is anticipated for the moment. The announcement of an Increase of 2/ld. in this year&apos;s Bradford rates has tended to increase the depression, especially in merchanting sections of the Industry where derating plays but a small part.EMPLOYMENT IN APRIL,  1931.MR. HILTON sent the following reportFigures are not available for the first Monday in April (Easter Monday) but for the succeeding two weeks the numbers unemployed decreased by over 67,000 as compared with the end of March.   There was however a slight increase in the last week of the month.   The total on the registers of Employment Exchanges at 27th April was 2,520,11? as oompared with 2,581,030 at 30th March.The net fall of 60,917 between those two dates was accounted for by an increase of 5,805 in the numbers wholly unemployed, and a decrease of 66,722 in the numbers temporarily stopped.   The increase in the wholly unemployed seems to have been due to the addition of school-leaverB at the end of the Easter term.The number of men on the Register decreased by 67,820, the number of women decreased by 2,134 and the number of juveniles increased by 9,037.    This latter increase ?^as of course due to the addition to the live register of the Easter school-leavers.In every Division except Wales the numbers unemployed fluctuated during the month and the net variations between
30th March and 27th April were as follows:-London, South Eastern andSouthwestern.................. -   7,363Midlands.......................... - 25,423North Eastern..................... - 16,680North Western..................... - 10,166Scotland........................... -   2,036Wales............................. -f       751Among the principal industries employment declined slightly &quot;between 23rd March and 27th April in general and marine engineering,  shipbuilding and ship repairing and in the cotton industry.     There was a seasonal improvement in the building trade and there was also some improvement in coal mining, motor vehicle manufacture, the wool textile industry and the distributive trades.The total number of insured persons in employment at 27th April, 1931, is estimated provisionally to be about 89,500 more than at 23rd March but about 553,300 less than at 28th April, 1930.ESTIMATED NUMBERS OF INSURED PERSONS AGED 16 to 64 IN EMPLOYMENT.Date.illEstimated Numbers Insured.Numbers Unemployed,Differencebetween Cols.2 &amp; 3 (to nearesthundred).141Estimated number in employment after deducting from Col, 4 3^% of the numbers in Col. 2 to allow for sickness * and other unrecorded non-employment exclusive of temporary holidays,Including persons directly involved in trade disputes. (5)Excluding persons directly involved in trade disputes, (6)rd March... th April .,12,290,0001&quot; I2,310,000t2,586,700 2,515,5009,703,300 9,794, 50J9,273,200 9,363,7009,267,200 9,356,700* The sickness rate has been taken at an estimated annual mean; it has not been possible to allow for Seasonal Variations.t Provisional figures.
IavtirAjGE WEEKLY NUMBERS ON THE REGISTERS OP ;jaa?LOYM-&apos;JTT EXCHANGESIN GREAT BRITAIN. 19 8 1.Wholly Unemployed,			Men.	Boys. I    Women.		Girls, !		Total.pays	ended	26th Jan. ..	1,472,264	60,724	390,132	50,494	1,	975,614	it	25rd Feb. .,	1,486,916	60,125	407,443	51,329	2,	005,813	it	30th March,.	1,489,933	54,947	407,178	45,696	1,	997,754	it	27th April*,	1,460,860	58,979	402,222	48,508	1.	970,569			Temporarily Stopped.								Men.	Boys.	Women,	Girls.	Total.	ays	ended	26th Jan. ,,	401,519	12,289	211j380	14,946		640,134	ii	23rd Feb. ,.	403,973	12,687	192,025	13,060		621,745	it	30th March..	442,270	13,685	161,042	10,667		627,664&quot;	ii	27th April*	386,915	11,771	152,785	9,633		561,104				Total.							Men.	Boys.	Women,	Girls.	Total.	I gays	ended	26th Jane  0.	1,873,783	73,013	601,512	65,440	2,	613;748;u	ii	23rd Feb.	1,690,889	72,812	599,468	64,389	2,	627,558is	it	30th March,,	1,932,203	68,632	568,220	56,363	2,	625,418ii	ii	27th Aprils.	1,847,775	70,750	555,007	58,141	2,	531,673* Figures not available for 6th April (Laster Monday).
ELECTRICAL INDUSTRYSir Hugo Hirst wrote to say that the amount of business done in the Electrical Industry during the past month has not shown any change, and that conditions in the Industry are in no way different to those described in his last Report.RAILWAY TRAFFIC.SIR CYRIL HUROOMB sent the following report and tables:-During the four weeks endsd 3rd May, 1931, the railway traffic receipts of the four amalgamated companies^ were  1,346,000 less than in the corresponding period of 1930 which included the Easter holidays.     This decrease is made up as follows:-Decrease   per cent.Passenger train traffic .......... 1,003,000          16.75Freight train traffic:Merchandise, minerals and livestock......................... 3 34,000             6.96Coal, coke and patent fuel ..... 9.000_0.56Total............................ 1.346.000 _10.14The receipts for the eighteen weeks ended 3rd May, 1931, compared with the corresponding period of 1930, shew a decrease of  5,747,000 made up as follows:-Decrease   per cent.Passenger train traffic .......... 1,592,000 7.08Freight train traffic:Merchandise, minerals and livestock ........................ 3,145,000 14.06Coal, coke and patent fuel..... 1.010.000_7,.855,747,000__9.96The figures of each of the four companies are set out in the attached statement.Complete statistics are available only to the 28th February, 1931.     These shew that in the month of February, 1931, the number of passengers (excluding season ticket holders) conveyed over all standard gauge railv/ays in Great Britain except the London Tubes and Metropolitan District Railway was   4,753,356 less than in the corresponding* For the separate figures for the four Railway Companies see page 52.
period of 1930, a falling off of 7j? per cent.     Passengers conveyed at standard or ordinary fares decreased by 1,868,123 (13.1 per cent) and those conveyed at workmen&apos;s fares by 2,122,95.5 (10.6 per cent).The tonnage of freight traffic in February,  1931, was 4,807,979 tons less than in the corresponding period of 1930, a reduction of 17 67 per cent.     Decreases in the tonnages of individual commodities include the following:-Tons per cent.Coal, coke and patent fuel ..... 2,719,662 15.iron ore  t...................... 495,620 48.iron and steel ................. 465,137 33.9Limestone (other than for roadmaking)  ...................... 171,517 41.6Pig Iron ,...................... 106,620 36.4Timber ......................... 91,358 20.8MOTOR INDUSTRY,The number of motor vehicles (excluding motor cycles) newly registered in March, 1931, was 708 less than in the corresponding period of 1930,     This decrease is made up as follows:-Description of Vehicle.	Increase (*&quot;) or Decrease  (-)		No. - 775 - 194 13 +    274	Per cent. - 4.1 - 3.5 - 1.2 -f 58v4					-    708	-    2.7Motor Cycles newly registered in March,  1931, showed a decrease of 3,968 (53.8%) compared with March,  1930.COTTON,MR. LENNOX LEE sent the following report:-The month of April, although particularly active as regards discussion of means for the improvement of the Cotton Trade, proved disappointing from the point of view of actual business.     The conditions in the raw material market deteriorated.      In the American Section there has been little incentive to operate for a rise in the commodity and although prices are 30 to 40 points above the level reached in the middle December they are 50 to 60 points lower than the highest quotations reached this year.     During the month there was a drop of approximately 36 points.     Egyptian cotton prices have also fallen and are over a penny per pound less than a month ago.     Despite the fact that restrictions on the planting of
Sakellaridis have come into operation, fully good fair Sakellaridis on the spot at Liverpool on April 1st was quoted at 9,30d. whilst on April 29th the price was 8.20d.I have &quot;been unable to ascertain the effect in the market of the new Russian Cotton. It is said 300,000 bales will be ready for delivery in due course.Spinners have naturally been affected by the trend of prices for the raw material and, with large stocks in hand, some amount of forced selling at low prices has resulted.The weakness of the raw material market has also been reflected in the cloth section,  and buying has been from hand to mouth, reaching only a disappointingly small volume.Hopes of a larger trade with China have not been realised and business with that market has been hampered by the difficulties which Dealers are said to have experienced in securing the necessary credit facilities.     This in turn has caused importers to be left with stocks which can only be sold at a loss.      The change of the Chinese Customs Duty to a gold unit basis is also proving a handicap to importers,  in so far as the present low value of the Tael increases the burden of the tariff.Although a slightly better tendency was shown for a short time after the Irwin-Ghandi Agreement the position in India still remains very disappointing.     During the month Karachi, Madras and some of the up-country markets bought more readily but no appreciable replacement business Was done for either Calcutta or Bombay.     The high tariff, the reduced purchasing power and, above all,  the political uncertainty are serious handicaps in the way of a recovery of Lancashire&apos;s trade with this market.     The total imports of cotton piece goods into British India for 193Q shows a decrease as compared with 1929 of 650 million yards, of which 482 million yards was at the expense of the United Kingdom.The improvement in the exchange brought about a feeling that there would be a corresponding improvement in the Import trade of the Argentine, but, with the further political trouble and the consequent fall in the exchange,  these hopes were not realised and demand from that market has not shown any marked increase.     Stocks are, however, reported to be low and with more settled conditions business should increase.      Business with Brazil has remained quiet and until there is a better demand for its products no great improvement is expected in the import trade of this market.     The improvement noted last month in the business with Colombia has been maintained, but business with Chili has fallen away.     Some improvement is reported to have taken place with the Continent but exports to the Near SJast have fallen further.Orders for Australia and New Sealand have been booked to a moderate extent and the home market has shown some seasonal expansion.Business in the bleaching trade is reported to have been maintained at about the same volume as during March, with receipts of cloth at about the same level and deliveries slightly bettern      In the printing section- of the trade, overseas demand has continued unsatisfactory and many plants are running not more than half capacity, and in some cases not more than one-third.     Firms catering for the home trade have generally speaking been better employed, but even here
orders have been from hand to mouth.     In the piece goods dyeing section business with shipping markets has continued to decrease, although the home trade is reported to have shown some slight improvement.COTTON PIECE GOODS IN INDIA,MR. LINDSAY handed in the following figures:-Statistics to complete App. IV to 1927, Report of Indian Tariff Board on the Cotton Textile Industry:-	Imports of foreign piece-goods .p.	2,003I4-	3,197I0,	1,919El,	hs,)	7133-01;--so431Iths,)&quot; Re-exports&quot;&quot; of foreign piece-goods .	Net Imports.128	1,875155	3,04222	1,89714	699Exports ofIndian piece goods.Ill 130 13374Production of) Indian mills.!422 1,164 2,4181,868Balance ofIndian piece goods available for consumption1,003 2,102 3,6892,842Balance of foreign and indian piece goods available.2,878 5,146 5,5863,541Production of hand looms,total Production.692 1,068 1,4041,048tPopulation.294 316 3501,114 2,232 3,8222,916Consumption per capita.Yards, 9.80 16,28 16
HOB-FERROUS METALS.CAPT. LYTTLETON sent the following report:-Conditions in the trade generally are very depressed. Prices, In the case of Spelter, are the lowest every recorded, and those of Copper, Tin and Lead, if adjusted to the changed value of the pound sterling, are also at low records.In the Birmingham area it is exceptional to hear of any firms working at more than half capacity.     The galvanising Industry in South Wales is stagnant and fresh orders are negligible.     The Tinplate trade is very unsettiedj   notices have been posted at the Elba Works, which normally employ 1,000 men and which consume 400 tons of Tin per annum.    In the Liverpool area there is some slight improvement in the cable trade, but in the galvanising industry conditions are more deplorable than ever.Generally it may be said that the low prices are not stimulating consumption, and the feature which has characterised the market in Non-Ferrous Metals for some time past still continues, namely, that consumers are only buying from hand to mouth for their immediate requirements.COAL.SIR WALTER SAINE handed in the following Report:-There has not been the slightest sign of any improvement in any section of the Coal Trade during the past months.    So keen is the competition for business, that very low prices are being taken.       To an ever-increasing degree, another element of competition is being encountered, namely that the foreign Importer in connection with Public Tendering, is very frequently quoting prices below those which he receives from this side.     Attempts are then made, too often most successfully, to further depress the British prices in the effort of the Foreign Importer to cover without loss.   Of course, it must be recognised that v/ith the world slump, and the general anxiety there is amongst the people in every trade, to maintain their businesses until better times come, the position to which I have just referred has necessarily become very accentuated.     Nevertheless,  it is a feature which is making the situation even more difficult.The Northumberland Collieries have, during the past month, reduced their limitation prices for Small Coals by 2/6d. per ton. They were undoubtedly much too high in comparison with Polish prices, with which these Coals are continually in competition. It is hoped that the result of this reduction will be that we may see a large Increase In business for this class of Coal, which has become a drug on the Market, and of which immense stocks have been accumulated.    It is estimated that there are over 500,000 tons of Northumberland Smalls in stock on the ground at the various Collieries.There is one feature about this necessary but drastic reduction which has taken place in Northumberland Smalls, - hioh
at once produced a state of alarm in the minds of Exporters -and this was that the Foreign buyer would argue that if one class of Coal has been reduced, a reduction in the prices of other Goals would follow, and thus a further state of uncertainty would prevail, because the attitude of the Foreigner is that he does not care what price he has to pay for his Coals, provided that he is assured, as far as is reasonably possible, firstly that his competitor will not buy on more favourable terms, and secondly that there will not be a general fall in prices.GENERAL.So far as general Trade is concerned, it is pleasing to record that generally speaking, the fall in prices of certain commodities at any rate, has either ceased, or else is falling very slowly.It is diffioult to see any sign of any important improvement in Trade.     Shipbuilding and Engineering, for instance, in which the North-East coast is so largely engaged, is in a deplorable condition, and no signs of orders are forth-coming.     However, should the present demand for tonnage for long-distance voyages - i.e. the River Plate - continue, we shall probably witness a change of feeling by the Autumn, and enquiries for tonnage will probably follow.     However, entrepreneurs have become so depressed, that It will take some considerable time to get them to adopt an enterprising attitude.ENGINEERING.MR. ROWLAND sent the following report and list of contracts:-There are one of two factors - in part seasonal - which indicate that an upward turn of the curve may come about before long.      The statistics for March show that there was a slight diminution of the extent of unemployment in the country as a whole, attributable in the main to seasonal improvement in certain industries.    Unfortunately the unemployment percentages for the engineering trades again increased, but not by so great an amount as in February, except in the case of marine engineer-ing.    Unemployment also increased in coal mining, iron and steel and ship-building industries during March.Foreign trade returns for March were again disappointing. Tmports, both of iron and steel and of machinery again advanced, whilst the export figures, particularly of machinery, were poor. Some consolation is afforded in that the import average value per ton of machinery is tending to fall, whilst the corresponding export price has increased, although this may be merely a temporary tendency.The output figures of pig iron and crude steel were well maintained in March, in comparison with immediately preceding months, but compare.unfavourably with the position this time last yoar.The slump which has taken place, both in exporte and imports during the quarter to the end of March, as measured against the corresponding quarter of last year, is revealed by the declared export value having fallen from  47,000,000 in 1930, to
 30,000,000 in 1931, representing a decline of 36$.    The declared value of imports has fallen from  25.6 millions in 1930 to  17.1 millions in 1931 - equal to a drop of 33$, but in terms of equated volume of trade, as compared with 1924 values, the decline is considerably less at 22% owing to falling price levels during the year,Engineering Contracts Information for March-April, 1931.1,     Messrs. Sir William Arrol and Company, Limited, have received a contract for the supply of overhead electric travelling and other types of cranes for the Madras and Southern Mahratta Railway.2.     A contract has been secured by Messrs, C.A. Parsons and company, Limited, of Newcastle-on-Tyne for the supply of three turbo-alternators for the   United Provinces Electric Supply Company, India.- &apos; ^   .     &apos; .-. -3.     Messrs. P. &amp; W, MaoLellan, Limited, have secured an order for the supply of steel bridgework for the Egyptian State Railways-4,     The Metropolitan-Cammell Carriage, Wagon and Finance Company, Limited, of Birmingham have received a contract for the supply of two eight-wheel well wagons of 40 tons capacity for the Rhodesia Rail\?ays.    They are Intended to carry heavy plant from the port to the copper fields of N. Rhodesia.5.     Messrs. Metropolitan-Vickers Electrical Company, Limited, havereceived an order for the supply of electrical equipment for blooming and rail mtflls for Russia, The contract is said to be worth  200,000.. &apos; &apos; &quot;6.     A contract for the supply of boiler plant to the value of 50,000 for Russia has been awarded to Messrs. Babcock and Wilcox Limited.7.     Messrs. Mirrlees, Bickerton and Day Limited, of Stockport,have secured the contract for supply of engines from 50 to 180 B.H.P., to Oeylon, India, Federated Malay States, and the Alexandra Waterworks.8.     Messrs. Armstrong, Siddeley Motors, Limited, of Coventry, have been awarded a contract for the supply of &quot;Jaguar Major&quot; aero engines to the Finnish Government.    The order was obtained in the face of French and American competition.\9.     Messrs. Hollings and Guest, Limited, have in hand some large orders for machinery, including two horizontal sludge pumps for the Birmingham Tame and Rea District Drainage Board and two pumps for the Coventry Corporation.    The firm supplied recently a big crane for the Great Western Railway Company at Smithfield Market, London, and have a large press and accumulator on order for the Admiralty.10.     The We11man Smith Owen Engineering Corporation, Limited, have recently received a repeat order from the Continent for eight Wellman-type L. lOg- mechanical gas produoers.    During the past twelve months the company have supplied 30 producers&quot; to Continental users for service in steel, glass and zinc-smelting works.
Do11.    The Newcastle-upon-Tyne Electric Supply Company has awarded to The Metropolitan-vickers Electrical Company, Limited, a contract for four bO-cycle turbo-alternators for their power stations.12.    Contract awarded to General Electric Company, Limited, for complete equipment of four aub-stations of London Electric Railway Company,13. Messrs. Johnson and Phillips Limited, have received an order for H.T, transmission lines and distribution transformers for Norwich Rural Electrification Scheme,14,    The contract for the refrigerating plant for the new Cunarder building at Clydebank has been placed by Messrs. John Brown and Company, Limited, with Messrs. J. &amp; E. Hall, Limited,-of Dartford.15.    Messrs. British Insulated Cables, Limited, of Prescot, have received a  100,000 order for overhead transmission lines to link up the no- Clarence Dock power scheme at Liverpool, forming part of the North-west England and North Wales grid ax^ea.16.    The Brightside Foundry and Engineering Company, Limited,Sheffield, has completed for a Spanish steelworks, which specialises in the rolling of large sections and joists for constructional purposes, the manufacture of an electrically-equipped rolling mill with all requisite equipment.17,    Messrs. Ashrnore, Benson, Pease and Company Limited, haverecently received from the U.3.S. ;. important orders for bla3t-furnace plant, including two pig-casting machines (double-strand type; to be installed on the blast-furnace plants at Kuznetsk and Magnitokorski.    Also for the U.S.S.E. the firm has an order for four automatic hot-blast temperature-control outfits for use at the same plants.18,    It is announced jointly by Mr. Saul G. Bron, traderepresentative of the U.3.3.R. in Great Britain, and Sir Philip Hash, ohairman of the Metropolitan-Vickers Electrical Rxport Company, Limited, that a technical agreement, extending over a number of years, has just been signed between the Soviet Government and the Metropolitan-Vickers Electrical Company, Limited, under which the latter has agreed to provide expert technical assistance in the manufacture of steam turbo-generating plant, condensing plant, heavy electrical plant,  industrial motors, switchgear, etc, which are to be built in Russia in the works of the All-Union Electro-Technical Combine.    The plant manufactured will extend to the largest capacity required for the generation and distribution of electricity, and it will be employed in connection with the five-Year Plan of industrial development.19.    It is reported from Nanking that the Board of Trustees of theBo;?er*&quot; Indemnity has decided that part of the funds, amounting to over  3,500,000, now in the Hongkong and Shanghai Bank in London, shall be immediately appropriated for the purchase of railway material in England.20.    The Pearson and Knowles Engineering Company Limited, has secured in open competition a contract for tne making and galvanising of transmission-line towers for the South-west England and South Wal63 electricity scheme, and for two towers, 500 ft, high,  to carry transmission-lines across the River Thames at Dagenham.
3^&quot; n 34WOOLLEN AND WORSTED INDUSTRY,ALDERMAN TITTLRIHGTON handed in the following table:-s:Tops:-ave rage.........h carded ...,........Is prepared ,.........ex Numbers:-ol..................ps..................over:dford Conditioning ouse (mill.lb.;   .....oyment:used v/orkers........infls:sted industry .......lien Industry .......jjbrts:s (mill, lb.) .......sted yams (mill,  lb) ftillen and Worsted tissues (mill. so., yds. )Current figures.April, 1931.24d 17d Hid62 743.7March, 1931,25^d 19 d 12 d62 744,5 72, 876,4 83, 52,4 1.96.7February, 1931.24d16,Vdlid56 653.9 70.072.6 80.22.41.79.increase or decrease ........on a year ago.__April, 1931.4^d 4^d 4 d16 17- 0.3.March, 1931.Idl d2d16 13* 0.1- 5.3- 9.1 -13. 2-0.1- 0.6- 3.0February, 1931.- 4^d- 5jd- 4jd28 26- 0.3- 8.9-14.1 -15.3* 0.4- 1.0- 4.9Jlanatory notes:ees:    Bradford prices of tops at end of month, jdex Numbers:    &quot;Weekly Wool Chart&quot; monthly averages;    basis, July,  1914. ladford Conditioning House:    Weight of tups dealt with, corrected for length of working month, ployment:    100 minus percentage unemployed (Ministry of Labour), mings:   Returns for employers for a given week, compiled as a &quot;chain&quot;index number;    basis, January, 19 26. Iports:   Board of Trade returns, corrected for length of working month.
Q K C*J t) JRU3SI0 BRITISH GRAIN EXPORT ASSOCIATION LIMITED.SALES MADE SINCE LAST BOARD MEETING 23.3.31.Wheat.................. 103,683Barley................. 5,556Oats................... 5,458Maize .................. 841Peas................... 4,866Linseed Cakes .......... 2,500Sunflower Cakes ........ 500Lentils................ 484Sunflower Oil.......... 650Cottonseed ............. 2,436.TOTAL........... 126,974Crystal Sugar .......... 16,650Tons.itHGRAND TOTAL SALES TO DATE PROM 1st JULY,  1930 TO 7th MAY, 1931.Commodity,Contract.percentage.Shipped,Contracts Unshipped.wheat.................Barley................Oats..................Maize.................Peas..................Glucose...............Cotton Cakes..........Linseed Cakes .........Sunflower Cakes .......Lentils............. &quot;Castorseed ..........Cottonseed ............Soya Beans............Cotton Oil ............Sunflower Oil .........Mogarar Seed ..........Tons.1,324,666 231,588 181,124 23,735 14,627 74 5010,098 525 3,012 1,000 28,436 10,500 1,880 7,150 301,338,49572.05$ 12.69,5 9.85$ 1.29$ .80$ . 01$ .01$ .55$ .03$ . 16$ .05$ 1.55/d .57$ . 10$ . 39$1,324,398 230,078 179,443 23,735 12,477 74 4810,130 25 3,012 1,000 27,771 10,500 1,880 7,150 _50.100.0C$1,331,751Tons.1,064 700 2,0002,140&apos;500 6657,0691,838,820Total sales of Crystal Sup;ar......, 156,850 Tons.Sold C.W.S.....  179,501 Tons Wheat.5.075     &quot;   Barley.184,574      &quot;
BP&quot; f*MR. VERNON handed in the following statement and tables:-UGANDA.The following is an extract from a further report on the cotton piece-goods situations-Trade has been fair, and a fair quantity of business has been passing for the Eastern Province side.     As reported before it is Japanese goods that are mainly concerned and they seem to hold the market in the cheaper print lines.     A firm in the trade writes &quot;Japanese goods continue to come forward at prices which are 10)6 to 30^-i below that of goods of which they are imitations.     This applies not only to piece goods but also to various sundry lines such as glass, china, and faney goods&quot;.      It is reported that a very old established firm is closing down in Kampala shortly. - L. Besson.CYPRUS.The detailed figures of trade now available for the year 1930 shew that the Colony derived 27.8;6 of its imports from the United Kingdom;    an increase of 1.5)6 jver the 1929 percentage. The percentage of Exports to the United Kingdom in 1930 was 20. lira as against 19. IJa in 1929.TRADE RETURNS.The following tables contain the latest Trade Statistics for the following territories.-   Kenya and Uganda, Northern Rhodesia, Nigeria, Sierra Leone, Ceylon and Cyprus.Exports.	1929.	1930.	Decrease or Increase.Kenya and Uganda.........., Northern Rhodesia Sierra Leone (2 months) ....	  7,020,668 720,875	  5,482,679 745,715	  -1,537,989 4-      24,840	1930. 219,837 p 1,757,311 212,888 4,383,565	193 lo 112,688 1,237,571 141,693 3,401,283	- 107,149 - 519,740 71,195 - 932,282			
Import a.	1929.	1930.	Decrease or Increase.	Percentage from United Kingdom,					1929.	1930.Kenya and Uganda .. Northern Rhodesia (10 months) ...... Sierra Leone (2 months) ........ Nigeria (January).. Cyprus (S months).. Ceylon (3 months)..	  7,850,286 2,859,058	  6,221,519 3,919,400	  -1,628,767 +1,060,342	40 Not ava	40 ilable.	1930. 245,362 1,369,802 251,804 4,594,679	1931. 188,852 437,086 187,213 3,025,417	56,530 -    932,716 64,591 -1,569,262	Not ava 70 Not ava it	ilable, 1     45 ilable. itThe following table contains comparative statistics for British Malaya connected with rubber for the period 1st January to 31st March, 1931:-Table/
BRITISH MALAYA,	Comparative Ruhher Statistics.									&apos; Foreign Imports,			Gross Exports.			Domestic Exports.	Stocks in Hand.	Exports to United Kingdom,Month.	1930. Tons.,	1931, Tons.	h- Increase - Decrease	1930. Tons.,	1931c Tons,	* Increase. - Decrease.	1931, Tons,	1931, Tons,	1931.To 31st March .......	11,773 12,960 13,236 37,969	11,029 9,672 12,009 32,710	-   744 . -3,288 -1,227 -5,259	52,535 48,947 47,320 148,802	41,579 41,951 48,589 131,919	-10,956 - 6,996 -t-1,269 -16,883	33,075 33,477 ?	48,306 48,164 48,300	20 21 17 average 19.3
HOSIERY.&quot;MR. WALKER sent the following report:-Leicester,    While production figures and sales are still below normal&quot; for this time of the year there is a slightly better tone in some branches.      In view of restricted spending power no immediate improvement is anticipated.Great disappointment is felt in the industry at the lack of any reference to Safeguarding in the Budget,Neater styles and more sombre shades seem likely to be fashionable and a great variety of colours are now used both for i?omens&apos;  outerwear and is-ens1 half hose,      In footwear dark shades are being worn and all shades of green and dark reds are fashionable for outerwear.Loughborough.    A plight improvement in trade is reported although conditions are still very moderate.      Short time is still being worked in most branches, workers engaged in Art. SilK Hose being chiefly affected, but all sections are feeling the very heavy importation of foreign goods.Nottingham,    Owing to the unsettled weather conditions, business in summer underwear and in outerwear is slow.      Stocks of these goods, both in the wholesale and Retail, however, are net believed to be of large dimensions, and in consequence with the advent of more seasonable weather, a considerable improvement should be noticeable.At this time of the year business in Cashmere Hose tends to slow down, and the present Is proving no exception.The volume of business in full fashioned pure silk hose, however, continues to be quite good, whilst manufacturers making Hose of other materials are experiencing keen compe ti ti on from abroad.As regards the fancy Half Hose section, a fair demand is being met with.The volume of business passing in Bathing Costumes, especially.-  those made of wool   is good.In the Shipping trade business remains quiet,Hlnckley. There is no additional news to give in regard to the s oate of trade in Hinckley and District.The unemployment returns are slightly better.Though we keep buoying ourselves up with the idea that things are     little better, or are likely to be a little better in the near future, the actual figures taken from returns show no improvement...;ansflaid.    There is a slight improvement in trade in this district this month, quite a number of orders having been placed for Autumn delivery, in cashmere hose and half hose, both fashioned and seamless, but competition is still extremely acute and prices are cut to the bone.The fashioned pure silk trade is not quite so good, apparently due to production having caught up with the demand and also &quot;to the continued slump in the price of pure silk.-50-
Hawi ck.    The trade for Spring has been very poor and there is more unemployment and idle machinery than ever before at this season of the year.      There is yet no sign of improvement and none is looked for until the general trade of the Country improves.extracts from report handed in by iSR. WALMSLEY and not read at the Meeting&quot;In some areas it is stated that the abundance of scrap is militating against the demand for Pig Iron, and in the Lancashire area it has been reported that scrap has been offered as low as 35/- per ton&quot;.........&quot;in Scotland Steel production remains at about 25 to 30 per cent of capacity and while orders have been a little more plentiful, comparatively speaking, during the last few weeks, there are signs that they have even now run their course.      The shipbuilding yards are still in the same plight as regards lack of work and it is seldom heard that an order has been placed, and any orders for ships which have been secured recently have been without exception for very small ones and are not likely to make much impression on the existing conditions.      Canada continues to give a fair measure of business and it appears that the trade Mission at present in the Dominion has met with some success and as a result orders have been placed&apos;in this country.In the  tinplate trade in South Wales demand is poor and is equivalent to about 48 per cent of capacity.     The Galvanised Sheet market continues very depressed.&quot;
SIR R. WEDGWOOD handed in the following table;-RAILWAYTRAFFIG RECEIPTS.4 weeks ended 2nd May, 1931 and decrease compared with 1930.Aggregate for 18 weeks ended 2nd May, 1931 and decrease compared with 1930.135 ,R, IS * R, IR.  , ijtal , ..Estimated Receipts  000&apos;s. 1,221 1,811 835 1,1184,985- 240- 374- 169- 220-1,00316 \ 17 16f 164.I6f 5,117 7,642 3,406 4,73720,902- 491- 544- 298- 259-1,592854landise. ,E.R..R........fatal1,439 1,925 800 301129 175 30if6,222 8,354 3,385 1,256-1,074 -1,448- 502- 1214,465-    33419, SIT-3,145141 14^ 138114and Coke.o iL o R o     o o * * 9iS*H*   o o * * oWo      *******:&apos; ?0&quot;oQl    o o o o q o954 992 411 123+32 36 29 16i154,495 4,861 1,902 602- 421- 163- 455 * 292,48013F11,860-1,0108^191 57*11 Railwayceipts.L.E.R.  .....I.S.R......I.R.      .....Potal3,614 4,728 2,046 1,54211,930- 401- 513- 228- 204-1,34610n10111 io4,15,834 20,857 8,693 6,59551,979-1,986-2,155 -1,255 -    351-5,747114 12410
AUSTRALIA,SIR FREDERICK YOUNG sent the following report:-Cablegram received from the Prime Minister&apos;s Department,Canberra, 9th May, 1931,WOOL.Sydney clearances for April satisfactory at rates representing decline of 5 per cent on best March rates. Possibility of increased eastern trade benefitting Australian wool industry.     During first ten months of season nearly 694,000,000 lbs. wool disposed of at average price of 8*75 pence per lb, making value sales for season  25,295,046; total held in store at end April 141,530 bales,WHEAT...Strong tone prevails in wheat market and disinclination amongst sellers to part with stocks at present prices.     Large quantities shipped Japan this season and excellent reports received regarding qualityaFLOURcFlour export business still substantial and market firm large quantities being shipped to East and steady business being done with Egypt.DAIRYING.Butter production on decline but Victoria and Queensland continue to have surpluses available for export.      Of total shipments of 2,579,560 boxes 2,306,200 boxes forwarded to United Kingdom,RICE.Prospects of coming rice harvest favourable. Following on recent trial shipment to Canada which favourably reported cn further shipment 500 tons being forwarded same destination.,TIMBER,Conference Australian timber interests decided prepare grading standards for export organised effort to be made by timber industry to advertise to Oversea   buyers range of Australian hardwood timbers suitable for commercial use,LEATHER TRADE.Increased activity apparent recent months in Australian leather export trade,BANK CLEARINGS,Sydney January 1st to May 4th  332,058,793, being an increase of  10,281,610 compared with last year,     Melbourne  227,359,323, being a decrease of  44,569,319.
3pTRADE.Exports March valued  9,-871,109 (Australian Currency) decrease  4,929,445 compared with last year. Wine months  75,719,137 &quot;being a decrease of  22,279,049.Imports March  4,195,406 (British currency) being a decrease of  6,282,682.     Nine months  51,425,207 being a decrease of  55,696,141.REVENUE CUSTOMS.Aoril  1,997,202 being a decrease of  644,093.      Ten months  24,082,113 being a decrease of  12,935,559.POSTAL.April  980,321 being a decrease of  81,991.      Ten months  10,837,649 being a decrease of  349,837.RUBBER BOOTS AND SHOES.SIR GEORGE BEHARRELL sent the following report: -Condition of Home Market.      The Home Market is flooded with foreign products from low labour rate countries, principally Poland, Czechoslovakia and Japan.     The Japanese particularly are sending in goods and offering them at prices below the prime cost of materials and labour.The attention of the Department of the Board of Trade should be called to the fact that apparently the Japanese Government has come to an arrangement with manufacturers of Rubber footwear that they shall work at maximum production and lower labour rates, and the Government is taking the responsibility for the disposal of their surplus production.In Summer footwear, Japanese goods have already captured a large amount of trade owing to their extraordinary prices which in some eases are half those of the home manufacturers.In winter goods, particularly Rubber boots,  they are this season for the first time showing samples and securing large orders at prices which cannot even be considered by British manufacturers.Export Market.    This is being affected in a similar manner by Japanese goods which have captured practically the whole of the Indian and Eastern trade.     They are also capturing a ma^or share of the South African trade.     So far as Central Europe and the near East are concerned, they are also being seriously attacked by Soviet goods at extraordinarily low prices..It may be pointed out that where duty is being paid on an ad valorem basis,* Japanese goods are paying in some cases something like one-third of the duty British goods are payingAd valorem duties in the Dominions are,  for the most part, levied on the internal market value in the country from which exported.
owing to tlie alleged lower home consumption value.     There is some doubt, however, as to whether the home consumption price in Japan is not considerably higher than the export price, but&quot;this has not so far been determined.As a case in point, in South Africa a cheap British shoe pays a duty of 6d per pair on home consumption value of 3/8d, while a similar shoe of Japanese make pays a duty of 2.70 on a stated home consumption value of 91.     A British shoe lands at 2/4d per pair while a Japanese shoe lands at l/2d.Principal lines in demand at the moment are Summer and Sports products.Buyers are holding back from purchasing Winter goods owing to the uncertainty caused by low prices quoted for Eastern and certain European products.The future outlook is decidedly pessimistic in view of the invasion of the home market by foreign and Eastern products.The British Empire Trade Exhibition closed in Buenos Aires on the 27th ef April after a most popular and successful run of six weeks, the number of visitors having exceeded a million and a half.     The prevailing depression affected immediate orders but the exhibitors report promising enquiries.     Selling arrangements are being revised and improved, and the prospects for increased Anglo-Argentine trade immediately local conditions improve are considered to be extraordinarily good.The elections in the Province of Buenos Aires have created an impasse as between the Radical and Conservative parties.     A General Election has been called for November - the time necessary under the Constitution - and it is expected that before this takes place arrangements will be made between the two parties to secure the return to power of the better elements.Labour conditions have been fairly satisfactory, a heavy maize crop having absorbed a good deal of the surplus labour.The Chilean Government has decreed substantial reductions in the pay and pensions ox&quot; the Army, Navy and Civil Service, and further increased the income-tax and the taxes on matches and beer, in the hope that decreased expenditure and a larger revenue will enable it to adjust the deficit in the Estimates.      Taxes have been established ranging from 3$ to 25$ on fiscal salaries.      The complementary income-tax has been doubled on incomes over 20,000 pesos.     Modifications have also been made in the Stamp law, as follows:-SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.MR. 5&apos;OLLETT HOLT sent the following report:-ARGENTINA,CHILE.Local bills............. 40 centsBills payable abroad ...... 60     &quot;Bills drawn abroad ....... 20     &quot;Stamps on cheques now .... 20 cents.-40 cents oer 1,000 pesos. 60     &quot;        11 11        &quot;ii        ti ft        tiFurther taxation affects cement one peso per 60 kilos.
URUGUAY.The difficulties of balancing the national budget are as evident in Uruguay as elsewhere at the present time.     Various expedients have been put forward but no definite results have so far been achieved.It is estimated that at the end of the present financial year, say on the 30th June next, the deficit will amount to  1,300,000.     The total expenditure for the financial year will amount to about  13,000,000.A representative of the Uruguayan Government is said to be negotiating with France, England and Germany for the temporary-suspension of the service of the Uruguayan Debt,     At the end of 1930 the total indebtedness of Uruguay was about  58,000,000.Arising out of the discussion regarding the depressed financial position, the Board of Directors of the State Bank have published an appeal to the public, through the local press.     The appeal draws attention to the need for economy on all sides and points out that the Country cannot triumph over the circumstances if the same life is led by her citizens as in times of prosperity. Personal and individual sacrifice is called for in all directions and by all grades of society.GOLD PAYMENTS..:Gold remittances to foreign countries due this year for the service of Federal, State and Municipal loans amount to  32,582,076,  viz:-LXPBNDITURS.The Provisional Government are continuing their investigations towards the reduction of expenditure.      It is held that the budget estimates for 1931 must be reduced by some  7,500,000.LOWER REVENUE.The total dues paid through the Rio Customs House b between 2nd January and 7th April last amounted to  1,600,000, compared with  2,500,000 collected during the same period last year,    This decline in revenue receipts of  900,000 indicates a more severe restriction than was anticipated in the budget estimates., and under present conditions of stagnant trade and low exchange which impede importation there seems little chance of any material improvement from this source of revenue.      Hence the necessity of further economies which the Government is imposing on all public departments.PISCALI5ATI0N OF BANKS.As a result of conference v/ith local Bankers and with Sir Otto Niemeyer, the Minister of Finance decided to abolish the policy of fiscalisation hitherto in force, as from 1st April, andBRAZIL,To Great Britain ... &quot; United States of 15,390,200America ...........To France ..........&quot; Holland .........5,071,800 1,261,840 148,336.
3fx iO 00Banks are now free to oj)erate In exchange both locally and in foreign markets.     Some minor restrictions are still imposed, and buyers of drafts are required to submit evidence of their need to remit;    the Bank of Brazil will exercise the function of supervising exchange operations in substitution for the Inspector of Banks.qofpee..On the SOth April there were commenced in Rio a series of conferences between representatives ox the world&apos;s coffee producing countries, convened to examine the whole question of production and supplies.     No definite news has so far been published as to the results of the various meetings but the Brazilian Government have agreed to impose forthwith an export tax of ten shillings per bag on all exported coffee.PERUWith the object of reducing unemployment, the Government have pushed forward public works schemes and the construction of workmen&apos;s dwellings.      They have also decreed a new series of special taxes as follows:-One per cent ad valorem on exports and imports;    2 per cent on the profits of all credit, commercial, industrial and insurance companies;    1 per cent on income produced by shares, bonds and mortgage investments;    and increase of 25 per cent on private motor-car licences;    a ten per cent tax on cigarettes.
Reprinted from The Board of Trade Journal dated April 30, 1931.TABLES ILLUSTRATING THE ECONOMIC POSITION IN THE UNITED kingdom table I. GeneralCapital Issues. idland Bank Statemcnts)-United Kingdom purposes .Overseas purposes   ...Total-All purposesPer cent, of 1924 ...clearinos.     m .ntry Chequo and Provincial-gland and Wales)-verage amount dailyrer cent, of 1924 .....receipts (Gkeat tain)-Averago amount daily per cent, of 1924 ......wholesale prices-board 01 Trade Index Nchberways - Freight Traffio (Great Britain).(o) Coal, Coke and Patent FuelPer cent, of 1924......(d) Other Minerals and General Merchandise    ......Per cent, of 1924 ......mpping   Entrances and Clearances with cargoes in the Foreign Trade (a) Entrances.........Per cent, of 1924 ......(6) Clearances.........Per cent, of 1924 ......[Shipping Freights  Chamber of Sliipping Index (2)Per cent, of 1924 ......External Trade-(o) Net Jmjrorts-Value as de-clared        .........Value at 1924 pricesPer cent, of 1924 ......(6) British Exports   Value as declared     .........Value at 1924 pricesPer cent, of 1924 ......(c) Net Imports of Raw Mate-rials Value as declared   ...Value at 1924 pricesPer cent, of 1924 ......Industrial Production  Board op Trade Index Humber ...Employment (Great Britain)  (a) Estimated number of insured workers (aged 16-04) in ern-ployment (5).........Per cent, of 1924 ......(H Numbers of insured workers (aged 10-04) unemployed ...Monthly AveragesPer cent, of 1924Unit of Measurement	Year 1924	Year 1929	Year 1930	Jan.-Mar., 1930	April-June, 1930	July-Sept., 1930	Oct.-Dec, 1930	Jan.-Mar., 1931Million  &apos;s.	7-4	13-3	10-6	12-1	12-5	6-3	11-6	7-1n	11-2	7-8	9-1	11-1	11-6	3-0	10-5	8-0,,	18-6	21-1	19-7	23-2	24-1	9-3	22-1	15-1	100	114	106	124	130	50	119	81Million  &apos;s.	15-5	15-2	14-0	15-0	14-3	13-2	13-6	13-5	100	98-2	90-5	96-7	92-4	85-2	87-7	80-7Thousand  &apos;s.	115	132	134	129	131	129	149	130	100	116	117	113	114	113	130	113	100	82 1	71-9	76-9	73-4	70-7	67-0	64-million net ton mileB.	825 100	785 95-0	741 89-8	810 98-2	670 81-2	709 85-9	777 94-2	- (1) -	763	788	744    ;	782	754	718	722		100	103-3	97-5	102-4	98-8	94-1	94-6-	Million net tons	4-01	5-23	5-31	4-64	5-53	5-86	5-21	4-43	100	113-2	115-1	100-6	119-8	126-9	113-0	96-0	5-44	5-72	5-49	5-36	5-52	5-79	5-27	4-53	100	105-2	100-9	98-6	101-5	106-5	96-8	83-2	100	83-9	64-6	63-6	61-7	66-2	66-8	67-million  &apos;B.	94-8	92-7	79-8	86-3	77-9	75-1	80-2	64-2	94-8	108 1	105-6	107-0	102-0	98-8	115-0	100-6	100	114-0	111-4	112-8	107-6	104-2	121-4	106-2; ft        -	66-7	60-8	47-5	54-7	46-9	45-4	43-1	34-4	66-7	72-3	59-2	66-7	68-3	06-7	65-2	46-2	100	108-3	88-7	99-9	87-4	85-0	82-7	69-2	27-0	23-8	17-7	22-S	17-2	15-5	15-8	13-0	27-0	30-4	27-3	81-6	20-1	22-5	29-0	20-5	100	112-8	101-1	116-9	96-8	83-5	107-6	98-3	100	111-8	103-3*	110-9	103-1	99-4	99-0*	(1)Millions	9-51	10-21	9-76&quot;	10-02	9-87	9-69&quot;	9-48*	9-2	100	107-3	102-6*	105-3	103-7	101-8*	99-6*	.96-8Thousands	1,137	1,224	1,927	1,552	1,784	2,050	2,317	2,595	100	107-8	169-5	136-5	156-9	180-8	203-8	228-2Mar., 1930Feb., 193117-0 9-4 26-4 14214-7 95-0131 114796 96-5814 106-74-84 105-0 5-33 98-085-8 j- (3)53-9 j- (3)21-0 j- (3)(4)9-98 104-91,641 144-45-9 13-7 19-6 10513-2 85-1127 11163-9716 86-7620 81-.4-01 86-94-23 77-757-8 (3)31-8 (3)10-6 (3)(4)9-22&apos; 97-0*2,617 230-2ID Information not yet available. (2) Published by courtesy of tho Chamber of Shipping of the United Kingdom and of the Statist Companu, Limited. ... m.     , (3) The calculation of tho value of the imports and exports at 1924 prices is only made quarterly.W the calculation of tho Index Number of Industrial Production is only made quarterly. (5) Allowance is made for sickness, etc., and for trade disputes. &quot; Provisional.Provisional.(302)3790(3020)  Wt250   5/31   E &amp; S
TABLES ILLUSTRATING THE ECONOMIC POSITION IN THE UNITED kingdom table II. Particular Teades		Monthly Averages								Items	Unit of Measurement	1  Year 1924	Year 1929	Year 1930	Jan.-Mar,, 1930	April-June, 1930	July-Sept., 1930	Oct.-Deo., 1930	Jam-Mar., 1931	Mar., 1930l. Coax Mining  (a) Quantity of saleable coal raised............ Per cent, of 1924 ......	Mill, tons	22-3 100	21-5 96-6	20-3 91-2	22-6 101-7	19-3 86-8	18-8 84-4	20-5 92-1	19-2 80-1	22-4 100-7(6) Quantity of coal export-ed U)............ Per cent, of 1924 ......	Mill, tons	6-14 100	5-02 97-8	4-57 89-0	5-00 97-4	4-51 87-8 .	4-41 85-8	4-37 85-1	3-47 67-6	4-78 93-1(c ) Percentage     of     Insured Workers wholly unemployed. Percentage    of    Insured Workers temporarily stopped.		H	12-1 4-3	13-3 7-2	10-2 3-3	12-3 8-5	14-9 10-1	15-8 0-7	16-2 6-9	10-4 4-12. Iron and Steel  (a) Crude Steel Output Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, tons	683 100	805 117-7	608 89-0	791 115-8	663 97-0	651 80-6	428 62-6	463 67-7	826 120-1(6) Pig Iron Output   ...... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, tons	609 100	632 103-7	516 84-8	641 105-3	599 98-4	443 72-7	383 62-9	338 55-4	666 109-3(c) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		20-6	18-9	32-8	22-9	29-1	35-2	44-4	44-1	24-83. General Engineering-Percentage of Insured Workers Unemployed.........		15-9	9-7	17-2	12-7	15-1	18-3	22-8	25-8	13-04. Electrical Engineering  (a) BEAMA Index of Activity (2) Per cent, of 1924		10O	107-0	108-0	116-4	109-0	109-4	97-5	84-1	118-8(6) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		5-0	4-4	7-9	5-7	7-2	8-0	10-9	14-6	0-05. Electricity   Generated   by authorised undertakers in Great Britain............ Per cent, of 1924 ......	Mill. Kw.-hrs.	508 .  100	858 169	906 178	1,010 199	788 155	780 154	1,049 207	1,062 209	967 1906. Shipbuilding (3)  (a) Merchant vessels under con-struction at end of Quarter... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Mill, grogs tons	1-44(4) 100	1-45 101-1	1-20 87-4	1-61 112-2	1-39 96-7	1-12 77-6	0-91 63-2	0-69 48-2	1(6) Merchant vessels commenced during Quarter       ...... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, gross tons	263 100	412 157-1	237 90-4	427 162-5	230 87-8	101 61-2	132 50-3	242 92-1	(c) Percentage     of     Insured Workers   in   Shipbuilding, Ship repairing, and Marine Engineering Unemployed ...		27-4	21-0	29-3	22-0	25-5	30-9	39-8	46-6	23-67. Base Metaxs  (a) Copper available for manu-facture (5) (6)        ...... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou. ton3	9-4 100	11-3 120	10-9 116	8-2 87	11-6 124	13-0 139	10-8 115	8-7 92	9-4 101(6) Percentage     of    Insured Workers Unemployed		12-3	8-8	16-1	11-0	14-0	17-1	21-0	26-3	12-78. Cotton  (a) Raw Cotton delivered to Mills............ Per cent, of 1924 ......	MiU. lbs.	118 100	124 105	91 77	119 101	91 77	66 56	90 76	85 71	110 930) Percentage     of    Insured Workers Unemployed		13-8	13-2	37-0	23-8	37-3	44-7	43-0	40-6	27-19. Wool Textile Industry  (a) Index of Wages Paid.  Per cent, of 1924 ... (6) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		100 7-0	90-3 13-2	77-6 23-1	83-9 20-0	73-8 21-8	75-7 25-5	76-7 25-3	70-6 29-3	83-3 20-910. artificial Silk  Production of Yarn and Waste Per cent, of 1924......	Mill. lbs.	2-11 100	4-74 225	4-06 193	4-27 203	3-78 ISO	4-24 201	3-96 1S8	3-83 182	3-87 18311. Natural Silk  Deliveries for Home Consump-tion (7)       ......... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou. lbs.	(8) 180 100	266 148	263 146	255 142.	287 159	244 136	265 148	283 167	217 12112. Crude  Rubber  available  for manufacture (6)        ...... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, tons	1-90 100	5-96 313	6-18 325	6-88 309	5-27 277	7-08 372	6-51 342	7-33 385	6-99 36713. Building  (a) Plans  approved  by   146 Local Authorities in Great Britain, estimated cost  (i) Dwelling Houses.   Per cent, of 1924 (ii) Other Buildings  and additions and alterations to   existing   buildings. Per cent, of 1924 (&amp;) Percentage     of    Insured Workers Unemployed : (i) Building (ii) Public   Works   Con-tracting, etc.......		100 100 10-3 17-0	117-5 140-5 13-1 22-8	124-2 135-7 16-2 25-3	120-0 116-7 17-5 26-9	139-9 136-3 12-9 25-9	115-9 122-6 14-4 25-0	120-9 137-3 20-4 29-8	106-S* 121-8&apos; 24-9 82-9	109-0 135-7 15-S 27-3(1) In addition the quantity of coal Bhippcd as bunkers in the Foreign Trade averaged 1,474,000 tons per month in 1924 and 1,301,000 tons ptrjM In 1980. (2) Published by courtesy of the British Electrical and Allied Manufacturers&apos; Association. (3) The figures relating to shipbuilding arelished at quarterly intervals. (4) Including an average of 62,000 gross tons on which work was suspended. (5) The ilgures given do not iduuithe available Bupply the metal produced from imported ores, matte, etc. (6) i.e., Net imports, less additions to warehouso stocks or plus roauuym warehouse stockB.      (7) The silk content of tho cocoons and waste has been estimated at one-third of their full weight.      (8) Estimated,     * i- rovis.ou.ii.


LATEST STATISTICAL DATAj (Information received up to 26thLatest,A month earlier.Capital Issues in Great itain (Midland Bank statement): United Kingdom purposes.......Overseas purposes.............nk Clearings:ountry Cheque and Provincial -Week ended........................ercentage of Advances to Depoeits(London Clearing Banks )...........ney Market:ink Rate..........................irket Rate 3 months1 Bank Bills... file count (3 months&apos; treasury bills).............*..............rices: Wholesale &quot;Board of Trade&quot; Index Ho. (1924 * 100):Food..........................Materials.....................Total.........................ilways Receipts - week ended -Goods Traffic (Gross).............Passenger Traffic (Grose).........ternal Trade:Het Imports ......................*ritish Exports...................Net Imports of Raw Materials......[flipping - Entrances and Clearances ifdth cargoes In the Foreign ffrade:Entrance s...... ...............Clearances *...................Shipbuilding:Vessels under constructions:*World .........................United Kingdom................Vessels commenced -World.........................United Kingdom................Vessels laid up in &quot;United Kingdom ports (latest figures at present available):British.......................Foreign...................* * - *Employment: Unemployment:Unemployment on live Register (inc. per sons on short time receiving benefit)..............froduction:fCoai^ output during week ended......Pig Iron ^Toput in month........Average per calendar day...........Crude steel output in month........Apl. .1,371,000 316,0001,637,000May.16. 77,155,000 Apl. 54.3Ivtay^ 22.2k% 1.19s.11,95dJApl. wMay 16, iiAplApl.67.7 61.5 63.6  .1,71S,700 1,218,20063,431,792 32,432,523 12,444,619Het tons. 4,592,253 4,654,612Gross tons. Mar.31     1,999,866 &quot; 693,814ii nApl.l.241*863 32,685Set tons. 1,367,252 22,982 .7,442,000 6,005,00013,447,00079,514,000 53.29*3!    ! &amp;M%    j 2.10s.11.33d.66.8 62.1 63.7  .1,853,000 1,245,50065,226,413 33,939,491 12,990,133Net tons. 4,782,271 4,664,370Gross tons. Dec.31.2,326,08^ &quot; 903,90J420,663 131,99*May 11. Wholly un-employed,1,353,927 Others...    678,584May 9 Apl.2,532,511Tons. , . 4,573, 00 323,200 10,775 397,400Net tons, Jan.!. 1,570,113 &quot; 23,1311,862,99: 698,06,2,561,051Tons. 3,384,40 357,101 11,51 500,10-irlncluding tonnage on whichlStatistics Department, Board of Trade, 26th May, 1931.
,TICaL DATA.tip to 26th way, 1931).ponth rller. .7,442,000 6,005,0003,447,000At corresponding date in1930.9,514,000 53.2L0s.ll.33d.66.8 62.1 63.7  .1,858,000 1,245,50035,226,413 153,989,491 L2,990,133!Net tons. 1 4,782,271 I 4,664,370tiroes tons. 31.2,326,086 903,902420,661 131,995Net tons, jl. 1,570,115 23,13211,890,000 9,381,00021,271,00088,907,000 56.425/l6$  2.3s.5.74d.77^6 72.6 74.4  .1,895,860 1,317,30076,071,647 46,861,461 16,895,531  tNet tons. i 4,979,211 I 5,253,859-  -Gross tone. 3,265,929 1,614,993356,801 426,5701929.Net tons. Apl.1.384,180 11 7,9741,862,991 698,06311,173,280566j2052,561,054:        1,739,485iTons.   I 3,384,400i 357,100j 11,519!500,100!&apos;   1 iTons. 4,936,800 619,600 20,650 696,100 .28,756,000 6,012,00034,768,00096,662,000 56*353/8   - 5.8s.2.06d.88.5 80.7 83.4  .2,052,800 1,755,50093,752,283 60,244,405 25,179,196Net tons.5,155,824 5,517,352Gross tons. 2,837,812 1,357,375660,639 362,358Net tons. Apl.1.233,115 &quot; 3,127805,769 298,8951,104,662Tons. 5,107,600 611,300 20,377 808,6001924. .2,937,000 1,868,0004,805,00091,632,000 48.83y8  3.18.6.93*1.95.0 101.5 99,2  .2,105,861 1,538,53574,393,037 62,866,926 16,378,105Net tons. 4,066 .,569 5,288,618Gross tons. 2,516,504 1,473,629431,606 227,786Net tons. Apl.l.    391,337 &quot; 19,0231,026,138Tons. 5,219,600 618,400 20,613 711,500age on will oh work was suspended.No.10/1931

</content>
</cab>
