<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/221/0 images: 575-576</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1931.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.     38CP. 146 (31).CABINET.MEMORANDUM.I CIRCULATE herewith, for the information of my colleagues, a memorandum on the subject of the International Agricultural Mortgage Credits Company, which the Commission of Enquiry for European Union decided at its recent session to set up in connexion with its study of the problem of granting agricultural credits.A. H.Agricultural Credits.After careful consideration the Committee of Enquiry for European Union has decided that an International Agricultural Mortgage Credits Company is to be set up, with its headquarters at Geneva.The purpose of the company is to obtain capital from financial centres, and to lend money to the central banks of the borrowing agricultural countries in Central and Eastern Europe, which would in turn relend it on security to cultivators of the soil.The capital of the international company is to be  10 million, of which 1 million would be issued to start with.In addition, there is to be a special reserve fund of  1 million, which will be contributed by all the Governments who are parties to the convention setting up the company, on a scale based on the contribution of each to the budget of the League. The contribution of His Majesty&apos;s Government, in the event of their becoming parties to the Convention, would be about  120,000. The special reserve fund is to be deposited in the Bank for International Settlements, and eventually repaid, with interest, out of the profits of the international company.The Treasury considered the scheme as a whole to be a very sound one, since it seemed to offer the best chance of inducing European creditor countries, including France, Holland and Switzerland, to lend abroad. During the conversations between the British and French Treasuries in January last, when the loss of gold by London to Paris had reached disturbing proportions, it was agreed that it would be most desirable in the general interest for France to resume foreign lending on an adequate scale. But it has hitherto proved very difficult to bring this about. Agricultural mortgage credits, however, are a form of investment which appeals particularly to Continental investors, being thought, to be comparatively free from political risks.The only feature of the scheme about which His Majesty&apos;s Government felt some doubt was the obligation to contribute to the reserve fund. Mr. Walter Smith, at the meetings of the sub-committee, urged that any contribution to the reserve fund should be optional in the case of parties to the convention who were not direct beneficiaries. This proposal was, however, strongly opposed, on the ground that the beneficiaries under the convention were small and relatively poor States, who would be unable by themselves to make large contributions to the reserve fund, which was considered to be an essential feature of the scheme.The proposals of the sub-committee were adopted by the Committee of Enquiry for European Union and by the Council during their recent sessions. At the meeting of the European Committee, which adopted the convention, I expressed my approval of the scheme as a sign of progress in the solution of the economic5911   [5555]
crisis in Europe, but foresaw certain difficulties from the point of view of the United Kingdom and undertook to lay the matter before His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment for further consideration as soon as I returned to London. In the meantime I was unable to sign the convention.The convention has been signed by the representatives- of- sixteen States, including France, Italy and Germany. Several of those who signed said that the ratifications of their Governments would depend on the convention being widely accepted. Thus Dr. Curtius said that &quot;he&quot; did not wish his signature to depend expressly on the British signature, but ratification (by Germany) would depend on ratification by the following countries : France, Italy, Belgium, Switzerland, Holland and Sweden.&quot;In accordance with the undertaking which I gave to the committee, I submit the matter to my colleagues and recommend acceptance of the convention by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom on the following grounds : (1) It has for some time been recognised that credit difficulties, and, in particular, the reluctance of certain States possessing large gold reserves to make foreign loans, are an important element in the present economic crisis. The present convention aims, in a small, but important field, at facilitating the granting of credit to those countries where it is most required.(2) The proposed contribution of  120,000 to the reserve fund is an extremely small item compared with the other financial commitments of His Majesty&apos;s Government. Moreover, it is not an item of ordinary expenditure, but rather an investment. It will carry interest and, if the International Mortgage Company achieves the success which we hope for, will be repaid in due course.(3) The main object of the scheme is not to encourage cereal production, but to assist the peasants of Central and Eastern Europe, who are at present in many cases only able to obtain credit on exorbitant terms from local lenders, and to enable them to change over to other forms of agricultural production. The countries concerned are customers of the United Kingdom for maufactured goods, and any general increase in their purchasing power will, therefore, be beneficial to us. Moreover, any diversion of their activities from cereal to other forms of production will be beneficial to our own cereal farmers and to those of the Dominions.(4) The scheme is the only constructive proposal yet evolved by the Committee of Enquiry for European Union for mitigating the economic crisis. It would create an unfortunate impression and might diminish the influence of His Majesty ^Government in pressing other positive economic policies upon European States, and even, later on, in urging the need for disarmament-if the success of this first scheme were jeopardised by our refusal to make the small contribution required from us in order to bring it into operation. In view of the attitude of representatives of other Governments, it is doubtful whether a sufficient number of ratifications will be obtained to bring the convention into force at all, if His Majesty&apos;s Government decide to abstain.(5) The economic situation in Europe is^serious, and the political situation is also disquieting. Lack of credit is one of the principal causes of difficulty in the Centre and East of Europe, and such a scheme as this may, if put into operation quickly, produce a much more than proportional effect in reviving political confidence, which is the first essential condition of economic revival. In such circumstances we cannot afford to pursue a policy of non-co-operation.A. H.Foreign. Office, June 2, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
