<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/221/0 images: 591-593</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC UA^ESTy^GGVEP^mT0.9.148(31). G*py No, \      n-&apos;^   1 J^B S WE T. wAGRiOU^^RA^L.m(jJT?J4LS4TIOjQ ^IXL. Mgmeyandum &quot;by the, Seo^tajyy, of State fog Scotland.1.   Reference is made to the Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries on the alterations made in the Bin by the House of Lords,3,   The Ministers note on gjafffeJE.. of the Bill S3*s MgLJ$S3 .* ^B.vm^n0tJl^&amp;mQ^^T^i^ji^   aff rag^and,, Re ^ e Qgidi tig, ainjg. jgf Neglected Land), represents broadly the case &amp;a it affects Scotland.     Clause I (Large Seals Farming) is perhaps of leas importance in Scotland than in England - otherwise t have nothing to add to the observations of the Minister in regard to this Part of the Biil03.   With regard to Part -U. of the Bill JjSmall Heldingg and Allotments) the position in Scotland differs from that in England and the amendments of the House of Lords affeot Scotland to a lesser degree.     Of the points mentioned by the Minister those in paragraphs(83  jmprt^ojkJ&amp;cl^ (10)(13) Qompulqery pqooedure, do not apply to Scotland. Paragraphs (11)  ilS&amp;JUsA^S Jn&amp;lmion^t3SrJiS^l^P-^-3^&apos; apply to Scotland as to England and 1 agree with the views of the Minister on these points-Paragraph (IS) MojiexJ^mit also applies to Scotland and t agree that this should be resisted as a breach of/
of privilege of the House of Commons,     If it ware not to be resisted, X should ask to be given the oppor^ tunity of discussing the provision for Scotland,, as the limits inserted in the Bill by the house of Lordse viz.;-    10,000,000 for England and  750,000 for Scotland do not follow any recognised basis of allocation and represent a provision for Scotland&apos; muoh smaller than that to which she is entitled on any basis.Apart from the above points dealt with by the Minister there is one matter entirely Scottish which should perhaps be mentioned.     The Department of Agriculture for Scotland have powers to constitute small holdings for ordinary applicants on the Estates of Private Proprietors.     In the Bill as it   left the House Qf Commons t similar powers were given to the Department to constitute holdings for the classes or applicants mentioned in the Bill.     This power has been deleted by the House of Lords leaving the Department power to constitute holdings for unemployed persons p etc. , on lands acquired for that purpose   but,.,,not on iilM-JiMldil-.itf..J?;^^ Power to constituteholdings on the lands of private proprietors will probably be pressed for by the Liberal Party and al^ though so far as the Department are concerned the power would be little used 1 am inclined on the grounds of maintaining the existing powers of the Department unimpaired to recommend that it be reinserted in the Bill.Subject to the above observations, I agree with therecommendations/
^aeommendations and conclusions of the Minister of Agriculture.WM. ADAMSON.0.0&apos;ttlBh Office. 9th June , 19SI.

</content>
</cab>
