<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/1/0 images: 164-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty V Government.]      printed for the use of the Cabinet.   January 1917.SECRET. *    51[To be returned to the Secretary, 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.JWAR CABINET, 25.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, on Tuesday,January 2, 1917, at 11*30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner, I The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.In attendance:The Right Hon. the Lord Hardinge op Penshurst, KG., G.C.B., G.C.S.L, G.C.M.G.,G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O., Permanent Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Major C. L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Greece. 1, THE Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that,Attended in connec-   according to his information, the withdrawal of Greek troops fromtion with Minutes   Thessaly was proceeding at a reasonable rate.Mr. A. J. Balfour,S.of S. for ForeignAffairs.The   Earl   Derby, ,S. of S. for War.Sir E. Carson, FirstLord of the Ad-miralty.Mr A. Chamberlain,S. of S. for India.Admiral Sir J. RJellicoe, First sea lord of the Ad-miralty.Commodore   L.Hidsey,   FourthSea Lord of theAdmiralty.
2. The First Sea Lord reported the loss of the transport&quot; Ivernia,&quot; with some 78 officers and 1,760 men on board. Accordingto the latest information, three destroyers were standing by, so it was hoped that a considerable number of the drafts and crew might bepicked up. The transport was torpedoed off the north-west corner of Crete.Transport Services 3. The First Sea Lord reported that six transports were lyingto India. at Plymouth to convey some 15,000 troops to India, Durban, HongKong, and elsewhere. He understood that the troops proceeding toIndia were intended to relieve Territorial units In that country for service in Egypt. In view of the large number of transports andescorting vessels locked up in such services, he hoped that the WarOffice would only continue them if absolutely necessary.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff was under theimpression that the First Sea Lord was mistaken. At his request,the First Sea Lord undertook to place himself in directcommunication with the War Office on the subject.The Loss of a transport in theMediterranean.Mr.    Henderson&apos;s 4. Mr. Henderson reported that he had attended the SocialistVisit to France. Conference in Paris, at which&apos; it was clear that there is a consider-able development of pacifist leering. The elections for the Con-ference Committee for drafting resolutions showed a majority of 21,with a pacifist minority of 18. Finally, a section of the pacifistsminority abstained from voting, and therefore the majority appearedlarge, but it was only secured by the abstention of the Longuet vote.Longuet has been leading a movement for peace. If the German ar american note had held out any hope for the restoration of Belgium,the Longuet group would have been very dangerous. They haveweakened on Alsace-Lorraine. On the whole, and as compared withexpectations, the Conference may be regarded as satisfactory, andthere was a declaration in the resolution to assist the Governmentin the prosecution of the war.Mr. Henderson reported that he had been invited by M. Thomasto address the munition workers in France. Many of these workersbelong to the Longuet group, who are the middle party not theextreme paciGsts.5. The War Cabinet had before them a note by the Secretaryof State for War, proposing a scheme for the construction of ferry-boats which will carry railway trains across the Channel withoutany handling of trucks or their contents.   (Appendix I.)Lord Derby and the Fourth Sea Lord gave the following additional details : (1.) The service  proposed  was  between  Richborough  and.Dunkirk, Calais, or Gravelines.(2.) The great advantage of the scheme is that it will interferewith no other port.-  (3.) It will be possible to load waggons at the munition works and convey them on the ferry-boats.Both the Admiralty and the Shipping&apos; Controller- were ofopinion that the scheme required further consideration.The War Cabinet referred the proposal for examination in thefirst instance by the Admiralty, the War Office, and theShipping Controller, in concert.Ferry-Boats forCross-ChannelTransport Service.
&apos; The Anglo-French-ftalian Conference.6. The War Cabinet decided That Lieut.-General Sir Henry Wilson should proceed to Italyfor the forthcoming Conference, not as a member, but in attendance, in order to enable him, as our Senior military representative at the forthcoming Conference in Russia,to keep in touch with the latest developments.Proposed campaign in Palestine.India&apos;s Share in theWar.7. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff, dated the 29th December, 1916, on aproposal to undertake a campaign in Palestine during the winter,with the object of capturing Jerusalem. The Note was accepted inprinciple by the War Cabinet.The last paragraph of this Note (Appendix II) gave rise to a discussion on the question of India&apos;s share in the war (see Minute 1&amp;3of the Meeting held on the 1st January, 1917, Paper War Cabinet24). The Secretary of State for India stated that the Governmentof India had agreed to do their best to raise additional units,subject to the following conditions : (a.) That the British units in Frontier Divisions should be keptat full strength.(6.) That the necessary rifles and equipment should be supplied from Engla,nd.(c.) That certain British officers of the Indian Army, now serving in France, should be returned to India to officer the newbattalions.(d.) That certain garrison battalions should be sent out toIndia to replace Territorial units in that country.The War Cabinet decided That the Secretary of State for India and the Secretary of Statefor War must make all necessary arrangements forpressing forward the raising of the new Indian battalions,so that they may be ready by August next for theoperations mentioned in the Note of the Chief of theImperial General Staff.Propaganda: Inrelation to thePeace Notes.8. At the suggestion of the Secretary of State for War, theWar Cabinet decided^-That action should be taken by the existing organisations for propaganda to ensure that the Replies of the Allies to theGerman and American Peace Notes should be publishednot only in the press of the principal cities of the UnitedStates but also in the provincial press.Propaganda :General.9, With reference to Minute 4 of the Meeting held on the 9thDecember, 1916 (Paper War Cabinet 1), the War Cabinet, without waiting for the full investigation of the question (which cannot takeplace until the various Departmental memoranda are ready),decided in principle That it was desirable that a separate Department of State shouldbe set up to deal with the general question of propaganda,but no decision was taken as to its composition.
Heavy Ordnance:Delays in Output.Attended   in   con-nection   with   thissubject:Major-General W.T. Furse, Master-General of the ordnance.Lieut.-Col. W. C.Symon, Ministryof Munitions.Mr. C. Ellis, Minis-try of Munitions.10. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported to theWar Cabinet that the most recent returns indicated a very seriousfalling off in the output of heavy ordnance, e.g., that only 191 gunsinstead of 225 would be ready during the present month, and 185instead of the 247 anticipated in February. The representatives ofthe Ministry of Munitions pointed out that the provision of guns for merchant ships had reacted on the production of artillery for theArmy, and requested that they might have an opportunity to verifythe figures.The War Cabinet directed the Ministry of Munitions carefullyto verify these figures, and to telegraph the latest infor-mation on the subject to the British Ambassador in Rome,for the information of the Prime Minister.British Minister at 11. The War Cabinet discussed the question of British repre-The Hague. sentation at The Hague.The Permanent Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs undertook to place the Minister-Designate in immediate personalcommunication, with the Prime Minister, in order that he might be informed of Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s views as to thespecial functions he must be prepared to undertake.(Initialled) D. LI. G.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 2, 1917.
APPENDIX ILExtract from a Note by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, dated December 29,1916, on a Proposal to Undertake a Campaign in Palestine during the Winter withthe object of Capturing Jerusalem.^ &quot;Tt- &quot;fe17. In the opinion of the General Staff, an offensive in Syria should not be under-&apos; taken until next autumn, and in the meanwhile our commitments in the minor theatresshould be reduced to the minimum in order that our maximum effort may be made inFrance. At the same time, we should Complete our preparations in Egypt for an offensive in Syria in the autumn of 1917.If the War Cabinet approves of this policy, Sir A. Murray will be directed toestablish himself in such a position as can be held defensively during the summer withthe minimum force and is at the same time suitable as a starting-point for an offensivecampaign in the autumn. He should be told that, as many troops as can be sparedfrom India, Mesopotamia, and East Africa will be sent to him as soon as circumstances permit, and instructed to be ready to send such white troops as he can spare, after thebeginning of March, to France.oChannel Ferry.(Note by the Secretary of State for War.)EXPERT investigation of the whole problem of cross-Channel transport has shownthat the only satisfactory solution is the construction of ferry-boats which will carryrailway trains across the Channel without any handling of trucks or their contents.The saving of time, labour, and money will be enormous.Such ferry-boats could be constructed in about six months from date of placing orders, if priority is assigned to the work. Even if hostilities should be over beforethe boats were ready, they would be of the greatest possible use in demobilisation, andalso for commercial traffic after the war.The Transport Department of the Admiralty has had the plan explained to it bySir Cuy Granet, and is in favour of it, but has asked for time for further consideration.In view of the extreme urgency of the whole Channel transport question, theCabinet is asked to approve the assignment of priority to the construction of four ofthese boats, assuming that the Admiralty does not find it necessary to withdraw itsprovisional concurrence.Cost, about 200,0001. each boat.(Signed)      DERBY.War Office, January 1, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
