<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/1/0 images: 194-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.[To be returned to the Secretary, 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.]WAR CABINET, 30.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, downing Street, S.W., on tuesday, January 9, 1917, at 1T30 a.m.Present :l   .   The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.In attendance:Major-General F. B. Maurice, C.B., Director of Military Operations.Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, Acting Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel E. D. Swinton, D.S.O., R.E., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Loss of H.M.S.&quot; Cornwallis.&quot;Attended in connecrtion with thisQuestion;Admiral Sir J. E.Jellicoe, First sea lord of the Ad-miralty.1. THE First Sea Lord, in the course of his usual statement,reported that His Majesty&apos;s Battleship &quot; Cornwallis &quot; had been blown up off Malta by mine or torpedo. He also reported the lossof three small craft.In regard to the publication of the news of the loss of the&quot; Cornwallis,&quot; the War Cabinet decided that: Information of the event should be communicated to the pressafter receipt of details.Eabegh:The Arab revolt .Water Supply.2. The First Sea Lord read extracts from a telegram receivedby the Admiralty from the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, inwhich it was reported, as the result of aerial reconnaissance, thatwater existed 20 miles to the east of Rabegh.Eestrietion ofImports.3. Lord Curzon reported that the Committee under his chairmanship appointed by the War Cabinet on the 21st December,1916 (War Cabinet 13, Minute 12), had held two sittings, and would shortly present a Preliminary Report to the War Cabinet. It had appointed an Inter-Departmental Sub-Committee to go further intothe question of what imports should be restricted, and to submitalternative programmes, one on the basis that imports should be restricted to the extent of 250,000 tons per month, the other basedon a restriction rising to 500,000 tons per month. This Sub-Committee(This -Document    tlje property of His Britannic jfflaaest/s Government.]Printed for the use of the Cabinet.   January 1917.
was to sit daily;&quot; for-a-fortnight; and at the end of that time tofurnish a report to Lord Curzon&apos;s Committee, for submission tothe War Cabinet.. 4. Lord Curzon added that he had received from Sir albert stanley a proposal to submit to the Privy Council Office, forapproval by the King at a meeting of the Council on the10th January, an Order in Council prohibiting the import of anumber of articles of different natures, some important and someunimportant. Lord Curzon desired the authority of the WarCabinet before the issue of the Order in Council. Certain objections were raised to restrictions being placed on some of the imports which had been specified by the President of the Board of Trade,e.g., the First Sea Lord stated that electric torches were an absolutenecessity to the navy. The Director of Military Operationsconcurred as regards the army.The War Cabinet decided that: The question of issuing the Order in Council should be deferred until the return of the Prime Minister, when the Presidentof the Board of Trade would be invited to give his viewson the subject before the War Cabinet.Blockade of Greece.Attended in connec-tion with thisQuestion:Lord Bobert Cecil,Min. of Blockade.5. Lord Robert Cecil drew attention to the fact that theblockade of Greece which was being carried out might result in thestarvation of the-Venizelists. There were, however, objectionsagainst allowing Greek ships to leave port, and there were difficulties in the way of requisitioning Greek ships. He was ofopinion that measures should be taken to provide food for theVenizelists, but to do this hardly seemed within the province ofthei Foreign ; Office or of the Ministry of Blockade. It was not-clear: to him,what Department should undertake these measures.Lord Robert Cecil added that he was of opinion thatthe matter should be undertaken by a Committee.The War Cabinet decided that Lord Robert Cecil should consult with the Admiralty andM. Gennadius and direct the Departments concerned tocarry out the necessary measures.Guns for Merchant . ft.: The War Cabinet had before them telegram No. 1948 of theShiPs- 22nd December, 1916, to Sir R. Rodd, at Rome (Appendix I) andtelegram No. 10 (D.) of the 3rd January, 1917, from Mr. Grahame,at,Rome (Appendix II), dealing with the subject of supplying guns for the protection of merchant ships.The;War Cabinet decided that- No action could be taken in the matter.
SeparationAllowance.Attended in connec-tion with thisQuestion:Mr. Walter Long,M.P., Secretaryof State for theColonies.Mr. Gr. N. Barnes,M.P., Minister ofPensions.&apos;Mr. H. W. Forster,M.P., FinancialSecretary, WarOffice.Sir Charles Harris,Assistant Finan-cial Secretary,War Office.Mr. S. H. Lever,Financial Secre-tary to theTreasury.Munitions for russia:Congestion on the trans-siberian railway.Attended in connec-tion with thisQuestion ;Dr. C. Addison,M.P., Minister ofMunitions.Major-Gen. C. E.Callwell.7. A Report on Separation Allowances, dated the 8th January,1917, prepared by the Committee under the Chairmanship ofMr. Long, and agreed to by all the members of that Committee, was before the War Cabinet:It was decided that Consideration of this Report should be deferred to Wednesday,the 10th January.8. A telegram dated 5th January, 1917, referring to thissubject, received from Vladivostock (Appendix III), was consideredby the War Cabinet. It appeared that the congestion on the Trans-Siberian Railway was due rather to the want of proper traffic control in Russia generally than to the shortage of rolling stock ; thatthe best chance of bringing about an immediate amelioration of theexisting state of affairs was for the British Mission, about to proceed toRussia, to attempt to - convince the Russian Government of thenecessity of improving the traffic control ; and that it would bedesirable for some British railway expert to take the matter in hand.An invitation for such an innovation, however, it was thought, shouldemanate from the Russian authorities, and the best way for this tobe arranged would be for the head of the British Mission to approach the Emperor himself.The War Cabinet decided that :-Lord Milner&apos;s attention should be directed to this matter, andthat General Headlam, who would represent the technicalside of munitions on the Mission, should be equipped with,the necessary information.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 9, 1917.(Initialled)A. B. L.
Guns foe, Merchant Ships.Paraphrase of Telegram from Foreign Office to Sir R. Rodd (Rome) No. 1948 (D)of December 22, 1916.TELEGRAM for General DalTOlio from Minister of Munitions :-&quot; Question of the arming against submarines of this country&apos;s merchant ships is,as you know, of the most vital urgency, and this Ministry have now been asked as amatter of the greatest importance to help in providing, for that purpose, a largenumber of guns. We want to obtain, if possible, by July, nearly 2,000 guns suitablefor this purpose from one source or another. I am sorry to say that this Obligationnecessitates a considerable sacrifice of some other parts of our programme in respectof guns. At the War Cabinet yesterday, it was suggested that I should enquire from you as to what help you could, in this matter, possi bly render us. I should thereforebe very glad of an early reply on this point ; and also of information as to any steps taken or about to be taken by Italian Government for the supplying of their ownmercantile marine with guns.&quot;APPENDIX  II.Guns for Merchant Ships.Paraphrase of Telegram from Mr. Grahame (Rome), No. 10 (D), of January 3, 191 7TELEGRAM received from General DaLVOlio for Minister of Munitions, replies to your telegram No. 1948 : &quot; In the matter of arming Italian merchant vessels, the situation at, present standsas follows : &quot; 198 are armed.&quot; 240 are not armed.&quot;  40 have applied for guns.&quot; We have in course of construction 500 3-inch anti-aircraft and naval guns, andwe hope to turn out 80 per month from month of March. In view of above figures,and also of further imperative need of arming various points on the coast againstsubmarine attacks, I much regret we can supply you with no anti-aircraft guns. Theabove-mentioned coast-defence system comprises 240 guns already possessed and138 more still under construction ; but the system is as yet by no means complete.&quot;APPENDIX III.Congestion on the Russian Railway from Vladivostock.Telegram No. 149, from Major Dunlop to General Gallwell, dated January 5, 1917.(149,)M Y 148. Very serious situation created by extreme shortage of trucks. Averagedaily despatch during week ending 30th December was only thirty-five of 16 tons each.Consequently, great danger of delay of munitions, which are continuing as before tocome from Japan, and are now arriving in very large quantities from New York.Stated by Governor-General, who was here recently, that there is no hope of earlyincrease in supply of wagons, and that for improvement in future only chance lies insanctioning of Russian order for wagons and locomotives. With a view to possibleexertion of influence in the matter, he wished me to give you this information.o

</content>
</cab>
