<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/1/0 images: 282-291</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majeaty&apos;s fiownuaeat.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1917.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 42.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, on Tuesday,January 23, 1917, at 5 p.m.*Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon orKedleston, K.G., G.C.S.L, G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.In attendance:The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies (Minutes 1 to (i).The Right Hon. Sir George Cave, K.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for the home department (Minutes 7 to 14).The Eight Hon. R. AIunro, K.C., M.P.,Secretary for Scotland (Minutes 1 to 14;.The Right Hon. the Lord Rhondda,President of the Local GovernmentBoard (Minutes 1 to 6).The Right Hon. R. E. Prothero, M.V.O.,M.P., President of the Board ofAgriculture (Minutes 1 to 14).The Right Hon. the Lord Devonport,.Food Controller (Minutes 1 to 5, 7 to 14).The Right. Hon. Sir Joseph Maclay,Bart., Shipping Controller (Minutes 7to 14).The Lord dAbernox, E.C.M.G., ChairmanCentral Control Board (Liquor Traffic)(Minutes 7 to 14).    .Mr. W. F. Marwood, C.B., Board of Trade(Minutes 7 to 14).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. G. M. Young, Assistant Secretary.Iieport by FoodController onBread, Meat, audSugar.1. THE War Cabinet had before them a Report by the FoodController, dated the 11th January, 1917 (War Cabinet paper g.-108).The Food Controller reported that the statistical position doesnot warrant the enforcing of rationing at present.The War Cabinet decided, however, that the question shouldbe examined, in the first instance, from the point of view of theamount of tonnage which could be saved by rationing.Sugar.2. With a view to a decision as to the adoption of a ration forsugar, the Food Controller undertook to give the War Cabinet an* Discussion on the lirst five Minutes took place at War Cabinet Meeting No. 41 held at noon of thesame daj&apos;.[L365-42] B
estimate of the amount of tonnage requirements on the basis of12 oz. per head per week, or alternatively on the basis of S oz. per head per week.The War Cabinet agreed with the Food Controller that a betterdistribution of the existing sugar supplies was necessary. TheFood Controller announced his intention of investigating thisquestion as soon as his appointment to the Chairmanship of theRoyal Commission on Sugar Supplies was confirmed.Wheat.3. The War Cabinet approved the recommendation of the FoodController that, having regard to the great dependence of the poorerclasses on bread and the impossibility of substituting other formsof food in their case, it was undesirable to adopt a system of rationing of bread at present.Meat.4. The War Cabinet also approved the recommendation of theFood Controller that, at present, there should, be no meat ration, asthe total quantity imported only amounts to 250,000 tons, and thequantity that could be saved only amounts to 110,000 tons.ProposedProclamation onPood.5. The Food Controller undertook to submit to the WarCabinet a Proclamation indicating the quantities of food per headto which the general public should endeavour to reduce their consumption, with an intimation that, if this suggestion was notcomplied with voluntarily, compulsion would follow.Man-Power:Agriculture.6. The Secretary of State for the Colonies reported that theConference (see War Cabinet 41, Minute 6) had met and decided tomake the following recommendations : 1. The decision of the War Cabinet that 30,000 men should be released from Agriculture for general service by the endof January should not be modified.2. Field-Marshall Lord French will find 15,000 substitutes from home Defence Units, and the War Office will find 15,000substitutes from among men surplus to their require-ments.3s Military rep resgii tatives will be instructed to furnish names and particulars of farmers and farms requiring labour to the War Office and the Horse Guards.4. The President of the Board of Agriculture will furnish theWar Office with lists of areas -where special arrange-ments for the provision of Labour are required.5. The Director of National Service should take power toenable him to remove men from gardening and similaroccupations, one-third of whom should be supplied to6agriculture.The various women&apos;s associations should be pressed tosupply women substitutes, and all necessary steps tothis end should be taken immediately by the Board ofAgriculture.7. Any pledges given in Parliament from time to time whichinterfere with the mobility of Labour should be with-drawn in Parliament in accordance with the decision ofthe late Government.
These recommendations are subject to two reservations : (a.) That the decision as to the risk of a raid should be takenby the War Cabinet, and Field-Marshal Lord Frenchrelieved of all responsibility.(b.) That the case of Scotland should be considered separately in the light of proposals which have been submitted bythe Secretary for Scotland, to the Prime Minister, andthe Secretary of State for War.The War Cabinet decided To approve the above Report, and instructed the President of theBoard of Agriculture to prepare, in consultation with theSecretary of State for War, a statement, for publication inthe Press, of the measures to be taken.[Sr)The President of the Board of Agriculture enquired whether,in addition to the 30,(00 men to be taken from Agriculture, the adjutant-General would be entitled, under the terms of War-Cabinet 41, Minute 4, to enlist boys of 18 from Agriculture. TheWar Cabinet decided That the President and the Secretary of State for War should,if possible, settle the matter in consultation between themselves.The War Cabinet decided : That the President of the Board of Agriculture should prepareAgriculture : a scheme for providing farmers, through local banks, withCredit for Farmers. credit for the purchase of seed, fertilizers, and feeding-stuffs,on the security of the harvest of 1917, which the Govern-ment have contracted to purchase.M7. The    War    Cabinet   had   before   them   the   followingRestriction of Memoranda :-Liquor Traffic. Memorandum by Lord d&apos;abernon (War Cabinet Paper G. 116;.(War Cabinet 33, ,. Sir A. Stanley (Appendix I).Minute 3, and ,, Central Control Board  (Liquor Traffic)Appendix II.) (Appendix II).Sir G. Cave (Appendix III).Tt was decided that the Food Controller should restrict thesupply of brewing materials so as to reduce the output of beer byBeer- 25  per cent, on the 1915 standard, in addition to the existingreduction by 15 per cent.,on that standard, making a total of 40 percent.*8. It was decided that there should be a simultaneous and.       similar  reduction   by  the   Chancellor of the Exchequer in theV ines and Spirits.    quantities 0f wjne8 au(j spjrIts released from bond.Malting.Forestalnient.9. The Food Controller was authorised to stop further maltingby an Order under the Defence of the Realm Regulations as soon asa sufficient amount of malt has been made to produce the reducedquota of beer that will be permitted.10. The Chancellor of the Exchequer was instructed, in orderto prevent forestalment, to prohibit or restrict, as soon as possible,the withdrawal of spirit from bond prior to the 1st April, 1917.This would be done under the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1915, Section 15.* At a subsequent conference with the Prime Minister it was arranged that this reduction should be a reduction of 30 per cent, on the 1916-17 output, which was equivalent to a further 25 per cent, on the 1915 standard.
Taxation.Proposed DrinkBill.11. The Chancellor of the Exchequer undertook to consider theimposition of fresh taxation on beer, wines, and spirits, with.a viewto reducing demand to the level of the restricted supplies.12. The Home Secretary &quot;was instructed to prepare a Bill, afterconsultation with the Food Controller and the Chairman of the liquor Control Board, to give effect to the above decisions in so faras legislation is found to be necessary.Extension of area under liquor control Board.Transport of Beer.13. The Home Secretary undertook to consider the question of including in the draft Bill a clause extending the area under thecontrol of the Liquor Control Board so as to cover the whole of theUnited Kingdom.14. The War Cabinet considered that it was highly desirable to curtail the railway transport of beer. The President of the Boardof Trade was therefore instructed to consult leading brewers with aview to confining deliveries to definite districts contiguous to thebreweries. No action, however, should be taken in this directionbefore the issue of the order by the Food Controller referred to in minute (9), as it is important that information regarding theGovernments policy on this question should not leak out.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,January 24, 1917.(Initialled)L). LI. G,
Memorandum by Sir Albert Stanley.Carriage of Brewing Materials and of Beer by Rail.. ASSUMING that an annual reduction can be effected in the use of brewingmaterials amounting to 500,000 tons of barley,3H,(fOO tons of grits,66,000 tons of sugar,a total saving in transport of 600,000 tons would be effected. This is equivalent to2,000 tons each working day, and at 8 tons per waggon is equivalent to 250 waggonloads per day. These waggons will take at least one dav in transit and another inunloading, and the saving therefore would apparently be 500 waggons.A reduction of 33 per cent, in the number of barrels brewed would, it is estimated,result in an annual reduction in output of 8,000,000 barrels, equivalent to 26,666 barrels aday. An average waggon load is 18 barrels, so that if these barrels had all to pass by rail, nearly&apos; 1,500 waggons would bo necessary, making up 30 trains.Again, assuming that waggons will take one day in transit and another inunloading, the saving under this heading would apparently be 3,000 waggons, and, ifthe traffic moves in train-loads, 30 engines.On this basis the total saving would be 3,500 waggons and 30 locomotives. Butthis is an outside estimate, as a large part of the beer traffic is carried by road vehicles,and a portion of the brewing materials by canals. We have no means of ascertainingwith any exactness the proportion of the traffic which is so carried.January 15, 1917,APPENDIX II.Memorandum by Central Control Board (Liquor Traffic).1. THE Board have had under their consideration the Food Controllers proposalto issue an Order for a large reduction in the output of beer in order to save barley and other materials for food.2. For the reasons given in the accompanying memorandum (Enclosure 1), theBoard have come to the conclusion that a 50 per cent, reduction at one stroke would cause hardly less irritation and unrest than a policy of total prohibition ; and theywould not be prepared to accept responsibility for the effects of so drastic a measureon social order. The Board assume, however, that some large reduction is immediatelynecessary, and they desire to represent that, if auy such reduction is made, a policy ofState purchase, introduced eiiher simultaneously or as soon as possible, provides atonce the most effective and the most equitable modus operandi. In arriving at this conclusion, the Board have been influenced by the following important considerations : (a.) The issue of an Order on the lines now proposed necessitates a scheme for anadequate complementary reduction in the consumption of spirits ; and, inthe Board&apos;s opinion, the framing of a practical scheme for this purposemay present insuperable difficulty, unless tbe State assumes control of the stocks of spirits and responsibility for their distribution to the consumer.(6.) The Order will inevitably result in a large increase of selling prices of beerand spirits, and the whole of this increase will apparently go to the brewerand the spirit dealer, instead of going, as it ought, ,in large part to theState in: relief of the loss of Excise Revenue incurred through decreasedconsumption.
(c.) If the Order is to come into operation with a minimum of inconvenience to thepublic, it will be necessary to take steps to ensure that the decreased amountof raw material available for brewing is used to produce the greatest possible volume of beer for sale ; and, with this object in view, it will benecessary to compel a general reduction of gravities, and it will probably befound advisable temporarily to prohibit the sale of high gravity beers. Ifthe State buys out the Trade, this and other regulating measures could atonce be taken ; but, if the Trade is not bought out, such measures would naturally be regarded as unfair and oppressive by those sections of theTrade whose goodwill was thereby damaged or even destroyed.(d.) A reduction of total barrelage should make it possible to release a number ofmen for war-work. But the full advantage of this economy could not beobtained except by concentration of breweries and other wholesalebusinesses ; and, without State purchase, such concentration would not be practicable.(e.) Similar considerations apply when the question is looked at from the point ofview of the economic use of transport, and of the economic distribution of available supplies of raw material.(/.) No scheme for the distribution of beer and spirits will be satisfactory whichis limited to control of the wholesale trade. In order to preventalternations of &quot; rush&quot; drinking and drink famine, the final distributionfrom the retailer to the consumer must also be regulated.3. The Board understand that they are under direction to examine and report tothe War Cabinet on the best means of effecting a reduction in the consumption. ofspirits corresponding to that which is contemplated with regard to beer With thisobject, they have carefully considered whether arrangements could be made by whichwithdrawals of spirits from bond would be limited to a proportion of the amountactually withdrawn by respective wholesale dealers in the previous year. Notwith-standing the difficulties indicated in the enclosed Report (Enclosure 2) from Sir ArthurTedder, the Board believe that it would not be impossible to devise emergency measures which could be applied to the distribution of spirits up to the point at whichthey reach the wholesaler. But even if such measures were practicable, they wouldnot be effective, since it is the distribution from the wholesaler to the retailer, and fromthe retailer to the consumer, which is at once the largest and the most difficult part ofthe problem. On the retail side, reduced consumption might be secured by compulsorydilution or by the stoppage of sales on certain clays in the week ; but the present powers of the Board are insufficient to enable them to apply either of these measuresto the whole of the United Kingdom, and so far as dilution is concerned, it must beremembered that a compulsory reduction to 30 degrees under proof has already beenprescribed as from 1st February in the areas scheduled by the Board, and that furtherdilution, to be effective, should be gradual. To secure an immediate and largereduction in the consumption of spirits, it is essential that retail selling prices shouldbe largely increased. Under present conditions, an increase of prices can be immediately affected by the imposition of a heavy increase of duty.4. The Board desire to point out that large stocks of spirits may be withdrawnfrom bond immediately on the publication of a restrictive Order, whether applicable tobeer alone or to beer and spirits, or even in anticipation of such an Order. They have themselves no power to deal with such a situation, but they feel strongly that thenecessary arrangements for preventing excessive clearances should at once be perfected.Enclosure 1.Note as to the Probable Consequences of an Order for a 50 per cent. Reduction in output of Beer.1. The standard gravity of beer, on which duty is based, is 1,055 degrees (waterbeing 1,000). During the last two years there has been a marked tendency towards areduction of gravities of beers placed on sale in consequence of (a) increase oftaxation. (6) the Restriction of Output Act.,
Total      ....... .... 22,000,0005. Given a reduction of gravity as indicated above, which can only be secured bya compulsory Order, there will still be a deficit of some 8,000,000 bulk barrels ascompared with 1916-17. This delicit will inevitably result in alternations of drinkingand drink famine unless the reduction of gravities is accompanied by an increase of retail selling prices suilicient to reduce consumption to the prescribed level.6. Theoretically, the object desired by the Food Controller can be achieved in three ways : (a.) By retaining beer at its present gravity, and charging a prohibitive price for it;(6.) By selling beer at its present price, and reducing its gravity to an inacceptablylow level;(c.) By reducing beer to what may be described as bedrock gravities (e.g., 1,045degrees bitter and 1,035 degrees mild), and charging for such beer a substantially higher price than is now charged.7. \a) and (6) may both be dismissed as impracticable.8. We are therefore left with alternative c), and the figures given above suggestthat it, would be desirable, in the interests of social order, to attempt a smallerimmediate reduction than the Food Controller now proposes.Enclosure 2.Limiting Consumption of Spirits.Report by Sir Arthur Tedder on mr. Stevensons suggestiou that the maximum clearances permissible from customs and Excise Warehouses should be limited to 50 per cent, of the daily averagecleared by each Distiller or Merchant d urmg the year ended 31st March, 1916.[Note.- Mr. Stevenson had written that &quot;it is quite possible that the Customs and excise Department may argue that this is a very difficult thing to do, but as against that contention I would point out that it already has a precedent as, previous to one ofthe Budgets, an order was issued by the Chancellor of the Exchequer limiting theclearances to the daily averages for the previous three months, in order to obviate anyfoiestalment by clearances of large stocks.&quot;]On the occasion referred to this Department (Customs and Excise) was aware that it was not practicable to control the issue of goods to individuals based on averageclearances, and this was not attempted ; attention was therefore paid only to the totalclearances from each warehouse, it being left to the warehouse proprietors to allocate the restricted quantities to be delivered to individuals.[1365-42] D2. Standard barrelage for vear ended the 31st March, 1916, 30,000,000 barrels.Bulk &quot; ,, 32,000,000(Average gravity being 1,052 degrees )Standard barrelage for year ending the 31st March., 1917, 26,000,000HBulk (estimate) ,, ,, ,, ,, 30,000,000^Assumed average gravity being 1,048 degrees.)3. The Food Controller proposes for 1917-18 to allow materials sufficient for only15,000,000 standard barrels.   This restriction necessarily involves (a.) Reduction of gravities;(b.) Increase of selling prices.4. If gravities are reduced to the extremely low level of 1,045 degrees for bitterand 1,035 decrees for mild beer, an allowance of 15,000,000 standard barrels will suffice to produce the following bulk barrelage (on the assumption that about three-fourths of the total sales are at 1,035 degrees) : i3iilk barrels.4,000,000 standard barrels at 1,0-15 degrees ...       5,000,00011,000,000      ,, ,,        1,035    ,, ...     17,000,000
- So far as the revenue was concerned this was satisfactory enough, hut it createdgreat dissatisfaction among the merchants, and we were inundated with complaints.Some of the warehouse proprietors protested strongly at being required to allocate the deliveries to individuals.We still hold that it is wholly impracticable for this Department to carry out ascheme of limiting the delivery of spirits froin warehouse by individuals based ontheir average daily clearances for a stated year. The revenue accounts are not kept in such form as would give the information necessary ; we are hot concerned with the ownership of spirits in warehouse, and when they are cleared, we only concernourselves with obtaining the duty and authorising the removal of the spirits to adestination requested by the warehouse-keeper ; it is quite unnecessary for us to knowwho is the merchant who owns the spirits, and in the majority of cases we are quiteignorant on the subject.Mr. Stevenson says he thinks that &quot; if any attempt is made to administrate theallocation of the daily average to the retailer, it will only lead to trouble.&quot; I am not sure what is meant by administrating the allocation ; but from tbe next paragraph I gather that he means he would leave the allocation of supplies to the retailer to becarried out by the wholesale merchant, which he seems to consider an advantage. Theadvantage would be very questionable, as the result would be that some retailers would get full supplies, enabling them to sell in full quantity as before, while others wouldbe able to get little or nothing. The wholesaler would, of course, run up his prices^selling only to those who were willing to pay the price. I should say, however, that itwould not be practicable for us to control the issue of spirits to the retailer.Mr. Stevenson proposes the year ended the 31st March. 1916, as the standard. Inthat year (in March particularly, but also at other times during the year) there wereheavy forestahnents, and many merchants, e.g., all the great blenders, increased theirclearances heavily in the expectation of a rise in the duty. It is probable that the clearance for the year ended the 31st March, 1917 (Supposing there is no forestallingbefore that date) will be only some 63 per cent, of the quantity cleared in the yearended the 31st March, 1916. This great drop in clearances during the current year isin part due&apos; to forestalments in 19)5-16.Shortly, first and foremost, it is impracticable for this Department to controldeliveries on the lines suggested, and the warehouse-keeper could not reasonably berequired to do so ; it was only withextreme difficulty that, very roughly, he estimated the average individual clearance for three months ; not to mention the great labour which would be entailed if it were practicable, and I doubt the possibility of his being able to do it at all with any exactitude for a whole year ; secondly, if the scheme were practicable it Would be inequitable in its working: thirdly, the year ended the31st March, 1916, would probably leave the big men with aright to clear as much asthey could sell in the coming year, as their clearances in that year will have been largely in excess of their actual needs, so that, bearing in mind the fact that any limitation such as that suggested would mean appreciation of value and increasedprofits, they would actually stand to gain by such a hmitatiozi.Note. This scheme differs somewhat from that of which I spoke on Saturday,though it is on the same lines. There are other objections to and difficulties inherent in the proposal, but it does not appear necessary to enter into further details.(Signed)      A. J. T.January 16, 1917.APPENDIX III.Memorandum by Sir George Cave.Drink Control.1. THE War Cabinet having approved in principle the proposals of the FoodController, it is necessary to consider the difficulties which arise in giving effect tothose proposals, and the manner in which these difficulties can best be met.2. The first objection taken to the proposed further restriction of brewing is thatthis restriction will reduce the supply of beer below the demand, and so will giverise to alternate &quot; rush drinking and &quot;drink famine,&quot; with resulting disorder anddiscontent.
*One way of meeting this objection is to encourage dilution. I understand that,in the houses under the control of the Liquor Control Board, the gravity of beer hasbeen gradually reduced to 10&quot;38 ; but dilution to this extent could not be enforcedgenerally without destroying the goodwill of those brewers who brew heavy beers,such as Bass, Guinness, and Worthington. Probably the best course will be to leavethe question of dilution to be solved by the trade ; but, if necessary, the control ofthe, Board (which already includes almost the whole of the Kingdom) could be madegeneral, and they could be left to deal with the question of gravity with a due regardto the position of the brewers of heavy beer.3. But dilution cannot be carried beyond a certain point; and, if the output of beer is reduced by 50 per cent, below the 1915 output, it may be that a point will bereached at which further dilution is impossible, and the demand for beer cannot bemet. It is understood that a reduction by 40 per cent, would be accepted as reasonableby some at least of the brewers, and it will be for the Cabinet to determine whetherthe full 50 per cent, reduction is necessary.4. Secondly, it is common ground that, in order that the reduction in the outputof beer may not lead to increased consumption of spirits, the output of spirits shouldalso be reduced. This can olny be effected by restricting the release of spirits frombond ; and if that is done, it will be necessary to find some machinery for allocatingthe reduced output of spirits among the different merchants and distributors.5. For the above purpose, the following course of procedure is suggested : (a.) To prevent forestalment, prohibit or restrict, as soon as possible, the with-drawal of spirit from bond prior to the 1st April 1917. This would bedone under the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1915 ;(6.) Any person wishing to withdraw spirit from bond on or after the 1st April,1917, must furnish full particulars of the total quantity of spirit withdrawnby him from bond during the year ending the 31st March, 1917, givingdates, quantities, amounts of duty paid, place and description of bondedstores. After verification of these particulars by the Customs and Excisea permit would be issued to him to withdraw from bond during the subsequent three months and until further notice, in periods of threemonths, one-fourth part of 50 per cent, (or whatever may be the proportionprescribed) of the total withdrawals during the previous year;(c.) This permit could be endorsed by the Customs and Excise at any bondedstore, and would leave the dealer at liberty to withdraw spirit fromwhichever store he wished ;(d.) Should a dealer in any period of three months withdraw less than the quantityallowed by his licence, the balance not cleared could be withdrawn during a subsequent period ;(e.) The person applying for a licence might be required to undertake to make afair allotment among his customers (being merchants or distributors) of theamount withdrawn.The Customs and Excise authorities recommend that the year 1916-17 shouldbe taken as the basis, and not any earlier year, and effect has been given to thisrecommendation in the above proposals.6. No system of allocation would prevent the supply of spirits from falling belowthe demand; and this difficulty may perhaps be met by enforcing the dilution ofspirits to a prescribed figure. This could be carried out gradually by the liquor control Board if (as suggested above) their powers Avere extended over the wholeKingdom.7. The third objection taken to the proposals of the Food Controller is that theproposed reduction, while greatly reducing revenue, would put an additional profitinto the hands of the brewers and dealers in spirits.   This may be true, but I know of&quot;no remedy other than (a) additional taxation of the trade or (b) State purchase, both ofwhich matters are outside the scope of this memorandum.8. For the above reasons I recommend that : (1.) The Food Controller should at once act upon paragraph 1 of his report ;(2.) The Chancellor of the Exchequer should forthwith act upon paragraph 5 (a) ofthis memorandum.;(3.) Instructions should be given for the preparation of a Bill for giving effect tothe Food Controllers proposals as to the output of beer, with such modifications as may be adopted by the Cabinet, and for restricting therelease of spirits from bond upon the lines of paragraph 5 (6) to (e) of thismemorandum ;
(4.) The question of extending the area under the control of the Liquor control board should be considered.o&apos; . . v,Note. If a measure of State purchase should be resolved upon, the Bill for thatpurpose may possibly take the place of the Bill recommended in (3).I have discussed the subject-matter of this memorandum with Lord Devonpori andLord D&apos;Abernon, and I think that they are in agreement with it.G.C.January 22, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
