<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/1/0 images: 368-373</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   February 1917.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 53.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, on Saturday,February 3, 1917, at 1T30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.The Right  Hon. the  Earl Curzon opEjedlkston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.In attendance :The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, CM., M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(for Minutes 1 to 8).The Right Hon. the Lord Hardinge of penshurst, K.G., G.C.B., G.C.S.I..G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O.,Permanent Uncler-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 8).The Right Hon. the Lord Robert Cecil,KG, M.P., Minister of Blockade.The Right Hon. Sir A. H. Stanley,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. the Lord Cowdray,President of the Air Board (for Minute 1).The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty (for minutes 6 to 8).Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B.,CM., G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 1 to 8).Captain Webb, R.N., C.B., Director ofTrade Division, Admiralty (for minutes and 8).Commander T. Fisher, R.N. (for minutes aod 8).Major-General F. B. Maurice, C.B.,Director of Military Operations (for minutes 1 to 5).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, Assistant Secretary.*Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.* Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.* Attended for Part of Proceedings only.Air Board. 1. AFTER some discussion with Lord Cowdray, the President ofthe Air Board, the War Cabinet adhered to their decision of theprevious day (War Cabinet, 52, Minute 4) that the Air Board&apos;smemorandum should not be published at present, ft This memorandum appears as Appendix I to War Cabinet, 52.[1365-53] B
Greece:Blockade.2. The War Cabinet authorised the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs to propose to the French Government that the blockade of greece should be raised. The Cabinet take note that, even if this is done, no supplies can reach Greece for three weeks. Having regardto the manner in which the Greek Government is carrying out itsengagements, they consider that, if the blockade is not raised, wemay become exposed to a charge of breach of faith with the GreekGovernment.Control Arrange-ments.3. In regard to the alleged concealment by the Greeks of armsand munitions in Thessaly, the Director of Military Operations statedthat information had been received from General Phillips to theeffect that search had been made in churches and other buildings forhidden arms, and that none had been discovei-ed.Mesopotamia. 4. The Director of Military Operations reported   a  furthersuccessful operation in the region of Kut-el-Amara.Portugal. 5. The First Sea Lord stated that four transports conveyingPortuguese troops had arrived at Brest escorted by four Britishdestroyers, but owing to two destroyers having been damaged by heavy seas, and that repairs involved docking, there wouldbe some delay in the provision of a convoy for the transportsconveying the remainder of the Portuguese contingent, necessitatinga postponement of its departure.Hospital Ships.6. In consequence of the receipt of contrary advice by lord curzon&apos;s Committee on the question of reprisals in regard to hospital Ships, the War Cabinet reversed their decision of theprevious clay, that hospital ships should sail without lights (WarCabinet, 52, Minute 3), and decided that : Hospital Ships should, until further orders, sail with theirpresent lights.The representatives of the Admiralty fully concurred in this last decision.Blockade of theUnited Kingdom,France, and Italy:Detention of neutral Shipping.7. The War Cabinet again considered the questions which ariseout of the German declaration of blockade, more particularly in con-nection with the provisional detention of neutral ships in our ports.Complete information is not yet available to show the number of neutral ships in ports in India, the Dominions, and the Colonies, but from later information it appears that the number of neutral ships in the ports of the United Kingdom is not 360, as stated in theMinutes of the previous Meeting (War Cabinet, 52, Minute 5), but,including a large number of small vessels, is 600.The War Cabinet decided that: (a.) The general policy for the moment should be to continue- the detention of neutral ships in our ports, but to presson with negotiations with the owners, taking advantageof the present panic to make the best possible bargainfor obtaining the use of the ships. Such exceptions tothe general policy should be made as are necessary fordiplomatic reasons, and, more especially, no action should be taken which would be liable to exert an adverse influence in the United States of America.
8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs undertook to write a despatch to the United States of America pointing out the bearing of the German proclamation of blockade on the doctrine ofthe freedom of the seas.Control of Canals. 9- The president of the Board of Trade asked the War Cabinetto consider the desirability of adopting a system of State controlof certain of the more important inland waterways on the same principle as was adopted in the case of the railways. He stated,that at the present time the canals were losing men either formilitary service, or owing to the fact that the financial condition ofthe canal companies did not enable them to pay large bonuses, andthe men were drawn away to higher-paid work. This did not applyto railway-owned canals. The result was that many barges hadbeen laid up, and the traffic on the canals was being reduced. TheMinistry of Munitions had reported that the maintenance of the traffic on certain canals was urgently required, and experience gained during the present hard frost&apos; had shown that the railwaycompanies could not cope with the traffic thrown on them by the closing of the canals.The War Cabinet asked the President of the Board of Tradeto prepare a full Memorandum on the subject for their early consideration.(Initialled) A. B. L.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,February 3, 191.7.[1536-53](6.) The arrangements for carrying out this policy wereremitted to Lord Robert CeciTs Interdepartmental Com-mittee on shipping questions, which was given full powers to release any ships they considered desirable,including those in the ports of India, the Dominions,and Colonies, and to make arrangements with individualshipowners as quickly as possible. The War cabinet decided that Mr. Royden, or some other representativeof the Shipping Controllers Committee, should be addedto this Committee, which is composed of CommanderT. Fisher, of the Admiralty, Mr. C. Hipwood, of theBoard of Trade, and Mr. H. Knatchbrdl-Hugessen, ofthe Foreign Office.(c.) Sections (A, 1), (B), (C), of the Memorandum entitled&quot; German Blockade of Neutral Shipping &quot; (Appendix),should be adopted for their guidance by Lord RobertCeciTs Interdepartmental Committee. The remainder of the Memorandum was left for further consideration.(d.) If any Neutral Governments enquire our reasons fordetaining the ships, no answer should be given before themeeting of the War Cabinet on Monday, 5th February.(e.) The Minister for Blockade should arrange for a rigorouscensorship of information in regard to our action indetaining the ships.(/.) The Minister for Blockade should keep our Allies postedwith full information of the action we are taking inregard to this matter.
APPENDIX.German Blockade and Neutral Shipping.A. Neutral Vessels calling voluntarily at United Kingdom Ports for Examination.I. All now in United Kingdom ports to be released, except (a.) Ships carrying grain, nitrate, &amp;c, for Denmark and Holland, until it is seen whether we shall continue to get our supplies from Denmark and Holland.(&amp;.) Belgian Relief ships (owing to the risk to these ships and to the uncertainty as to the ultimate disposal of their cargoes, in view of the present positionbetween the United States and Germany).II. As to future calling, no exemptions to be allowed. This is vital to theblockade, and should, if necessary, be enforced by measures enabling the Prize court to condemn all vessels failing to call. If neutral Governments refuse to allow vessels to call, as many as possible should be captured and condemned. If the attitude neutrals renders it possible and advisable, an arrangement could, perhaps, be made forvessels to call at Gibraltar, Dakar, Bermuda, and Halifax as required, instead of at a united Kingdom port. Vessels calling at these ports would be directed to proceednorthabout along a predetermined course outside the war zone. Any vessel out ofthis course to be liable to condemnation. Machinery for dealing with vessels wouldhave to be set up at tbe ports named. Concurrently with this, the Navicert system should be extended to all neutral countries. (It would have to be remembered that difficulties might arise if a vessel had to be diverted, e.g., from Bermuda to the UnitedKingdom to discharge prize cargo. The Contraband Committee have not been consulted.)B. Neutral Ships Engaged in Allied Trades.I. Ships on Time Charter to Allied Charterers  and  in general Ships tradingbetween Allied Countries.To be released, but each case to be dealt with on its merits with due regard topossibilities of vessels sheltering in neutral ports..II. Neutral Ships Bound for Neutral Ports.To proceed if fixed back with important cargoes, but only as and when similarvessels arrive in British ports.Until the situation develops, it is difficult to see any more expeditious method.Anything of this kind would have to depend on arrangements with individual owners(see following paragraph).III. Arrangements with individual Owners to be proposed direct to them asfollows :  (a.) Purchase of all suitable ships at values quoted in scheme for reinsurance ofIS orwegian ships, which range from 35Z. per ton deadweight in the case ofnew ships downwards according to age.Payment to be made in sterling according to arrangement to be madeby Treasury.(6.) Transfer to British flag.IV. War Insurance to be provided. (See Appendix 1, draft telegram to stockholm, The Hague, Madrid, Rio, Montevideo, and Buenos Aires. Norway,Denmark, and Greece have separate insurance schemes.)
Appendix I.Draft Telegram explaining Proposed Insurance Scheme.Foreign Office, February , 1917.German proclamation as to new submarine campaign may have effect in neutral countries of causing anxiety among shipowners as to insurance, and may cause ratesof premium to be raised far above those required by real risk. His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment recognise this, and are prepared, as a temporary measure, to provide warinsurance on the hulls&apos;of neutral vessels engaged in carrying essential cargoes, suchas foodstuffs, munitions, material for munitions, and coal, to Allied ports on thefollowing conditions :     &apos; ...1. The values to be insured to be : Per GrossKegistered Ton.Ships built between-  1875-1881 inclusive .. .. .. . . . . .. 251882-1890     ,, .. .. .. .. .. .. 801891-1900     ,, .. .. .. .. .. .. 831901-1905     ,, .. .. .. .. . . .. 851906-1910     ,, .. .. .. .. . . ..871911 and upwards .. .. .. .. .. 40V. If these proposals fail, neutral ships in Allied ports to be requisitioned.VI. Bonuses to be authorised to officers and crews of neutral ships arriving inUnited Kingdom ports with essential cargoes.   (Appendix 2 gives proposed rates.)VII; Consuls at neutral ports to be instructed to report all cases of ships layingup. Where a ship is laid up in a neutral port, ships in Allied ports under sameownership to be requisitioned. His Majesty&apos;s representatives concerned to be informed and instructed to use their discretion as situation develops as to making this threat.VIII. Preparations to be made for manning with British crews neutral ships which may be requisitioned, condemned, or purchased. Reserves available for thispurpose to be ascertained, and possibility of increasing these reserves by substitutingoriental seamen for British seamen in suitable trades.&apos;0. Neutral Ships in Ports Abroad.These should be dealt with in the same manner as neutral ships in ports in theUnited Kingdom. The Colonial Office and India Office should be informed accordingly.D. Iron-ore Supply.Suitable British ships now plying from East Coast ports to French Channel portswith coal to be ordered to sail to French Bay ports with coal and return with iron-ore,This is necessary in order that neutral ships may be employed as far as possible in theChannel trade which is less dangerous and less easily escaped from than the Baytrade.E. Action of Allied Governments.French and Italian Governments to be informed of action taken and asked to share in costs of insurance scheme and generally to adopt measures similar to thosetaken by His Majesty&apos;s Government.F. All arrangements to be in the hands of a Joint Committee of Foreign Office,Admiralty, and Board of Trade, acting through the appropriate Depart-ment. Ministry of Munitions to be represented on all matters in whichthey are concerned, and kept constantly informed of proceedings ofCommittee.[For the sake of brevity and clearness the reasons prompting these recommenda-tions have not been stated in full. It is suggested that, if necessary, they could moreconveniently be given verbally.]
In the event of the owners desiring to place any insurance on owners&apos; account(other than freight actually at risk), in excess of the above values, the sum to be soinsured must be declared to the underwriters when the main risk is offered for acceptance.2. Ships engaged in the following voyages may be insured at the rate ofpremium stated : Per cent.(a.) United Kingdom to north coast of Prance ,, .. .. 2(6.)      ,, ,, French Bay ports       .. .. .. ..2*5(c.)      ,, ,, Gibraltar and French Mediterranean       .. ..    3-5(tf.)      ,, ,, West Italy, Sicily, and British Mediterranean portsother than Gibraltar . .. 5(e.) French, Spanish, or Portuguese Atlantic ports to United Kingdom or&quot;Northern France       . . . . .. .. ..2*5(f.) Mediterranean ports to United Kingdom or French Atlantic or channel ports .. . . . . -. . .. .. 5 ,(g.) America to Italian ports west of Sicily     . . .. .. 5(A.) America to French Mediterranean and Bay and to the west coast ofUnited Kingdom       .. .. .. .. .. 315(i.) America to French Channel and east coast of United Kingdom ..    5(,/.) Ballast voj&apos;age from North France to United Kingdom        .. 2(&apos;&amp;.) Ballast voyage from port of discharge to port of loading for the purposeof loading an approved cargo .. .. .. .. 1The above rates are nett absolutely.3. Owners must agree to instruct their masters to comply strictly with all ordersgiven by British authorities regarding sailing, ports of call, routes, &amp;c.it. Underwriters reserve to themselves the right to refuse insurance on anyparticular ship.5. These arrangements are only temporary, but for the convenience of charterersseven days&apos; notice will be given of withdrawal, or of any variation in the terms or conditions.6. The insurance will not cover any claim arising from capture, seizure, arrest,restraint, or detainment except by the enemies of Great Britain.7. Insurance excludes ail claims due to delay.8. Insurance on the above terms can be effected by the owners&apos; representative inthis country on application to the Commercial Union Assurance Company, ItoyalExchange, London. Full details must be given of the cargo to be carried whenapplication is made for insurance. Premium must be paid in cash in exchange for insurance policy.Appendix II.Bonus.Bonus to be paid to captains, officers, and crews of neutral ships which bring fullcargoes of foodstuffs other than fruit, munitions, or materials for munitions, to theUnited Kingdom:  Captain       .. .. ..          .. .. ..          .. ..    1001st mate     .. .. ..          .. .. ..          .. ..402nd   ,,       .. .. ....... .. ...        .. ..251st. engineer.. .. ..          .. .. ..          .. ..50. 2nd    ,,     ... .. ..          .. .. ..          .. ..     303rd     ,,     .. .. . .          ., .. ..          .. ..     254th    ,,  &quot;   .. .. ..          .... .________ . ... ..... ..     20Seamen and firemen .. ..          .. .. ..          .. ..     10Other ratings in proportion. The total bonus for an average ship would be 450Z.to 500Z.o

</content>
</cab>
