<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/1/0 images: 504-509</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   February 1017,SECltlOTWAR CABINET, 73,Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at LO, Downing Street, on Monday,February 19, 1917, at 11-30 a m.Present:Tire Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right  Hon. the  Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.In attendance :The Right Hon. A. J. Baleour, M.P.,O.M., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (for Minutes 1 to 13).The Right Hon. the Lord Hardinge oePenshtjrst, KG., G.C.B., G.C.S.I.,G.C.M.G., G.O.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O.,Permanent Under Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 13).The Right Hon. the Earl oe Derby, KG.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes 1 to 11).Maurice,- C.B.,Operations  (for major-General   F.   B,Director  of  MilitaryMinutes 1 to 11).. .The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty (for-   Minute 11). : ,&apos;Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B.,O.M., G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 1 to 10).The Right Hon. H. E. Duke, K.C., M.P.,Chief Secretary for Ireland (for Minutes11 and 12).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade (for minute 14).Mr. W. F. Marwood, C.B., Board of Trade(for Minute 14).The Right Hon. A. H. Illlngworth, M.P.,Postmaster-General (for Minute 14).The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Controller of Shipping (for Minute 14).Sir H. Walker, K.C.B., Chairman, Rail-way Executive Committee (for MinuteM)- &amp;   -::......Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Colonel E. D. Swinton, C.B., D.S.O., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.
The Western -Front.Champagne.1. THE Director of Military Operations reported that theGermans had during the previous week secured a position of sometactical importance in the Champagne, which the French had not succeeded in regaining.The Ancre.2. The Director of Military Operations explained that the tactical importance of the success gained by the British on theAncre on the 17th February was due to the fact that a footing hadbeen gained on the ridges commanding Miraumont.Enemy Itein^brce-ments.3. The Director of Military Operations reported that two more german divisions had been located on the Western Front, onehaving been withdrawn from Roumania and the other being a newdivision reconstituted from troops already on the Western Front.In addition to these, an extra German division had been located in Alsace, having been moved there from the German front east ofVerdun, making a total enemy reinforcement of 4 divisions and1 cavalry division during the last few months in Alsace.Casualties.Mesopotamia.4. The War Cabinet expressed a wish that, in future, a dailystatement of casualties should be furnished to them by the WarOffice.&apos;5. The Director of Military Operations reported that, following on the successful, action in the Dahra Bend (where the Britishcasualties had been only 540), an unsuccessful attempt had beenmade to storm the Sanna-i-Yat position on the Tigris, in which ourestimated losses had been 500 men.The War Cabinet authorised the Secretary of State for War to convey to General Maude their congratulations on his recent success in the Dahra Bend.Submarines.6. The First Sea Lord reported several actions with enemy submarines, including one in which the enemy submarine had been sunk by a vessel of the &quot; Q&quot; class which had previously been torpedoed by it. The &quot;Q&quot; ship was subsequently beached. one german officer had been saved and taken prisoner.Loss of a Transport7. The First Sea Lord reported the torpedoing of a 11,000-tontransport, the P. and 0. ship &quot; Berrima,&quot; while proceeding toLondon, after landing troops at Devonport.Damage toDestroyers.8. The First Sea Lord reported that four destroyers had been damaged by collision during the fog.Convoys. 9. The First Sea Lord stated that the Admiralty were going into the question of convoys, and that he had himself arranged tosee a number of Naval Officers and &apos;Captains of merchant vesselswho had experience in this subject.10. The Secretary of State for War read a letter he had receivedfrom Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig, referring to the interviewpublished in the French Press, and indicating that he had received and conversed with certain distinguished Frenchmen, as he hadbeen requested to do by the Propaganda Department of the ForeignField-Marshal sir douglas Haig&apos;sAlleged Interview.
Office. He had received these gentlemen as deputies and not asjournalists, and had consequently spoken with them quite freely,without intending that the subject of the conversation would appear in the press, or, indeed, supposing that it would be published.In regard to correspondents generally, tbe First Sea Lordexplained to the War Cabinet the very difficult position in which,according to his experience, a Commander-in-Chief was placed byreceiving visits from journalists.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs reminded the WarCabinet of the controversies which had taken place between themembers of the War Committee and Lord Kitchener, owing to the objection of the latter to any form of publicity. As the result ofthese discussions a regular system of visits by journalists to thehigher Naval and Military Commanders had been instituted.The Prime Minister read extracts from a message he hadreceived from Lord Northcliffe, pointing out that the Frenchgentlemen who had interviewed the Commander-in-Chief were tohis knowledge most honourable and straight men, and that thereforegreat care should be taken as regards tbe shape of any reply thatmight be given in the House of Commons to questions on thesubject, for fear of offending the French, and causing more troublethan had already been occasioned.After discussion of the different aspects of the case in point,the War Cabinet decided that Any reply to a Parliamentary question on the subject should be postponed pending the arrival of a special messengerconveying a written report, who had been sent byField-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig, and who was then on his way to London.Lord Northcliffe should be asked to meet the Prime Ministerand Lord Curzon, in order to furnish, if possible, anyfurther information on the subject of the note he had had sent to Mr. Lloyd George.Ireland.11. The Chief Secretary for Ireland explained that a situation,of some danger had recently been created in Ireland by the actionof some of the men who had been released from imprisonment.The General Officer Commanding-in-Chief held definite views onthe subject of the treatment of these men, and had power to dealwith them under the Defence of the Realm Act. The chief secretary had his own views of the matter, and was ready to takethe responsibility for anything that might be done. At the sametime he desired to place the matter before the War Cabinet before taking action. The number of men concerned amounted to 31,all of whom were known to have been engaged actively in theseditious movement. He thought that actual peril would only arise in the event of arms being landed, but that it would be veryconducive to the preservation of peace if these men were deportedfrom Ireland.   The War Cabinet authorised The Chief Secretary for Ireland to arrest and deport to GreatBritain certain notoriously seditious persons, on the under-standing that if they should return to Ireland without permission they would at once be rearrested.Mr. L. Ginnell,M.P., Mr. P.Plunkett, M.P., andFatherjOTlannigan.12. The Chief Secretary for Ireland further explained that he wished for authority to instruct the Commander-in-Chief in ireland as to the action he should take in regard to Mr. Ginnell, M.P.,Mr. Plunkett, M.P., and Father 0&apos;Flannigan, who were very active in fomenting trouble.   The War Cabinet decided that The Chief Secretary for Ireland should instruct the Commander-in-Chief in Ireland to take no action for the present in
regard to these persons who were reported to he engagedin promoting sedition.Sale of Waggonsfor ExportUse of Empty-Private Waggonson ReturnJ ourneys.Shortage ofLighterage.13. In reference to the printed report of the dardanelles commission, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs broughtto the notice of the War Cabinet certain objections, from theForeign Office point of view as regards policy, to publishingparagraph 121 (a) as it stood.Lord Curzon drew the attention of the War Cabinet to anotherportion of the Report which he considered should not be publishedfor somewhat similar reasons.It appeared evident that the Report could not be publisheduntil certain Departments had seen it, in order to guard against thepublication of any details that it was inexpedient to make known,and the War Cabinet decided that-The Foreign Office, the Admiralty, and the War Office should,after perusal of the Report of the Dardanelles Commission,forward any recommendations they had to make as to the omission of any portion direct to the Secretary of the WarCabinet, who should then invite the Dardanelles Commis-sion to sanction these omissions. The suggestions to bemade by these Departments should be confined to sug-suggestions for omissions which were absolutely necessary inthe public interest, and should not extend to any additions to or alterations of the text.Shortage of labour on: Canals,LocomotiveRepair,Cartage,The Loading and unloading ofWaggons.14. The War Cabinet had under consideration the first sum-mary of the Report of Mr. Illingworth&apos;s Interdepartmental Com-mittee (Appendix I). The Postmaster-General having explainedcertain details of the Report, the War Cabinet came to thefollowing conclusions on the different headings of the summary,taken seriatim: I.It was decided that the sale of British railway waggons forexport should be prohibited, except under license issuedby the Board of Trade.II.It was noted that, as stated by the President of the Board ofTrade, machinery was being set up by the Board of trade for the pooling of private waggons ; and it was agreed thatthe Board of Trade should, seek powers to enable theRailway Companies to load empty privately owned vehicleson the return journey.III.It was decided that the Secretary of State for War should be requested to submit a note explaining why the 10,000 menpromised by the War Office at the meeting of the WarCabinet held on the 21st December, 1916 (War Cabinet, 13,Minute 8), had not been released for the Transport Workers- Battalion as arranged, and it should be pointed out to him that serious difficulties had arisen from the failure in thesupply of these men, of whom the Shipping Controllerstated he had only 6,000 at his disposal.IV, V, VI, and VII.It was decided that as all these points labour on canals,locomotive repair, cartage, and loading and unloading ofwaggons at ports and destinations were questions of shortage of labour, the Secretary of Mr. Hlingworth&apos;sInterdepartmental Committee should confer or communicate with the Director of National Service and the War office on the subject.
Unloading ofWaggons.Storage in the open.Transit Sheds andDock Sites.It was noted that the President of the Board of Trade stated,that he was preparing machinery to enable the railwaycompanies to take drastic measures to enforce the promptunloading of waggons at destination in order to put as top to the present practice of utilising waggons asdep6ts.It was noted that the Shipping Controller stated that he would. take up the matter, through the Port and Transit ExecutiveCommittee, as to the possibility of dumping raw and semi-raw materials in the open, where necessary, to relievecongestion, having special reference to materials belongingto the Ministry of Munitions.It was decided that the Secretary of Mr. Illingworth&apos;sCommittee should consult with the Secretary of State forWar in regard to the release by the War Office of anytransit sheds or dock sites in use by the Government forany other than the purposes for which they had been designed.(Initialled)D. LI. G..2, Whitehall Gardens, SJFebruary 19, 1917.W.,
Unloading of Ships and the Clearing op the Congestion of Docks.(First Summary of Report of Mr. Illingworth&apos;s Committee.)I. Prohibit sale of British waggons for export, except obsolete ones.PI. Give Railway Companies the right to use empty private waggons on return journey during the war.III. Shortage of lighterage caused by difficulty of making lightermen work inthe Port of London.IV. Shortage of labour on Canals, which throws more work on the RailwayCompany.V. Shortage of labour for repairing engines.   In some cases more than double the normal amount of engines out of use through this cause alone.VI.  Shortage of carting facilities at port and destination through shortage ofdrivers.VII.-Difficulty of loading and unloading waggons at port and destination onaccount of shortage of labour.VIII. That measures should be taken and, if necessary, Railway Companies giventhe power to enforce the prompt emptying of waggons at destination.EX. It would relieve the situation if raw and semi-raw materials, which wouldtake no harm from exposure, w^ere dumped in the open at ports ornearest available spot.   At first it is proposed to apply this only to goods belonging to the Ministry of Munitions.X. That every case of a transit shed or dock site at any of the congested ports in use by the Government for other than its designed purpose, bere considered with a view to its release.This is a summary of what are the most urgent points that can be dealt withimmediately. A full detailed report will be issued later, which will also contain the minor points which the Committee recommend should be attended to.(Signed) .    ALBERT H. ILLINGWORTH, Chairman.February 16, 1917.(Passed unanimously.)o

</content>
</cab>
