<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/1/0 images: 542-551</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property ,.of His Britannic Majestys Government, jPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1917.SECRET. ;     r*262WAR CABINET, 80.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, on Monday,February 26, 1917, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of Kedleston, K.G-., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.In attendance :The Right Hon. A. J. Baleour.. CM.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Lord Hardtnge oePenshurst, K.G., G.C.B., G.C.S.I.,G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O.,Permanent Under Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 9).The Right Hon. Sir A. H. Stanley, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade (for minutes 7 to 11).Commodore L. Halsey, C.B., C.M.G.,Fourth Sea Lord of the Admiralty (for minute 11).Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B.,O.M., G.C.V.O., First Sea, Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 1 to 6).The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies (for Minute 11).The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D., M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes10 and 11).Major-General Sir G. M. W. Macdonogh,K.C.M.G., C.B., Director of military intelligence, War Office (for Minutes 1to 6).Sir R. H. Rew, K.C.B., Permanent Secre-tary, Ministry of Food (for Minute 11).Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, Assistant Secretary.Colonel E. D. Swinton, C.B., D.S.O., Assistant Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.
1. THE Director of Military Intelligence reported the withdrawalof the German forces on both sides of the Ancre along the whole front of the British 5th Army, and the consequent advance of our troops.He explained the details and advantages of the positions gained by us,and the fact that the Germans by this movement were in no bettertactical position than they had been.Mesopotamia. 2. The Director of Military Intelligence read out telegrams from the General Officer Commanding the troops in Mesopotamia,reporting the successes gained on the 23rd and 24th February, and explained the situation on the map. The War Cabinet decidedthat The Director of Military Intelligence should hold backpublication of the communique prepared by the Director ofMilitary Operations, and bring before the War Cabineton the morning of Tuesday, the 27th February, a communique incorporating the latest detailed information,and a draft of a reply to be given in both Houses ofParliament to questions on the subject.*The western front: The Ancre.Greece. 3. The Director of Military Intelligence read extracts fromtelegram No. 100 of the 24th February, 1917, from Lord Granville,reporting the massacre of some French Sengalese troops by Greekirregulars.After some discussion, in which the divergence&quot;of the policies ofthe French, the Italian, and the British in Greece was brought to notice by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Loid Hardingereferred to telegram No. 201, dated the 25th February, from Paris,Volo and Larissa.     urging the occupation of Volo and Larissa.The First Sea Lord stated that he was opposed to the occupationof Volo, because it implied an increase of front and a demand fortonnage which would not be available He drew attention to thefact that the people who pressed for the occupation of this place were those who were not responsible for the provision of the sea transport.The War Cabinet decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should telegraph to.the Prime Minister to the effect that a long telegram hadbeen received from the French again urging that Volo andLarissa should be occupied by the Allies, and to remindhim that the Admiralty and AVar Office were both opposedto the scheme, which the lack of tonnage made impossible.. Submarines. 4. The First Sea Lord recounted the Naval actions and losses ofthe previous three days. He also gave details of the sinking of theGerman submarine U 83, off the coast of Ireland, and stated that the cunard steamship &quot; Laconia &quot; had been torpedoed 130 miles off theFastnet Bock.Raid on the East 5. The First Sea Lord reported a German destroyer raid on theCoast. South-East Coast during the night of the 24th-25th February,against the North foreland, Ramsgate, and Margate, and the factthat mines had been laid off Folkestone Gate.* Owing to its being reported that a Turkish communique was being published inthe foreign press, acknowledging the evacuation of Kut, the Chancellor of theExchequer subsequently decided to make a statement to the House on the 26th, and authorised the Director of Military Intelligence to issue the War Office communique assoon as that statement had been made.
Publication ofShipping Losses.6. In reference to a decision reached by the War Cabinet at theMeeting held on the 20th February (War Cabinet, 75, Minute 3), theWar Cabinet decided that The First Sea Lord should, after a week, place before the WarCabinet a statement of losses for the week, and a corres-ponding statement of the losses day by day during the sameperiod, when the question of the form in which the lossesshould be made public would again be considered.Russian Reser-vation to theResolutions of the paris EconomicConference.Restriction ofImports: TheProhibition of theImport of Luxuriesfrom France.7. In reference to Foreign Office Memorandum No. 260703,dated the 1st January, 1917 (Appendix I), and to the decision reached at the Meeting of the War Cabinet held on the 2nd February,1917 (War Cabinet, 52, Minute 8), it was considered that, thoughthe British Government could not but acquiesce in the proposednon-adherence of the Russian Government to the conclusions reached at the Economic Conference of the Allies held in Paris in June,1916, it should not accept responsibility for, nor give approval to,this course, but should express a guarded acquiescence. The WarCabinet decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should, with theconcurrence of the French Government to this course,inform the Russian Government that the British  andfj^ench Governments took note of the reservations madejfij^th. e Russian-Government in its own interests.8. The War Cabinet had under consideration a letter of the 24thFebruary from the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to theSecretary of the War Cabinet (Appendix II), and decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should telegraph tothe Prime Minister to the following effect: That to impose restrictions on the import of luxuries from France would present great difficulties in face of the agreement made byMr. Runciman, and to ask the Prime Minister if he couldsettle the question on broad lines with M. Briand, or, ifnot, whether a French Minister or Ministers could come toLondon to discuss the matter.The Order of the Q. Referring to the decision reached by the War Cabinet at british Empire.        the Meeting held on the 9th February, 1917 (War Cabinet, 60,Minute 3), the War Cabinet decided that The Report of Sir Frederick Ponsonby&apos;s Committee should be circulated and considered by the War Cabinet before afinal decision on the subject of the proposed BritishEmpire Order was reached.Product^ .  u10oJn/Wd t0 tho ProPosal by the Secretary of the Admiraltyte- of the 23rd February, 1917, for the formation of an Interdepart-mental Committee to deal, with and co-ordinate the work of thethe various Departmental Committees considering the question ofpetroleum products (Appendix III), the War Cabinet passed theproposal to form an Interdepartmental Committee, subject to theterms of reference being agreed to by the Departments concerned.
*restriction ofImports:Vegetables andFruit for the Fleet.11. The War Cabinet had before them correspondence betweenthe Fourth Sea Lord, Lord Beresford, the Secretary to the VegetableProducts Committee, and the Secretary of the War Cabinet, dealingwith the effect that restrictions on the import of vegetables and fruitfrom overseas might have on the supplies to the fleet. The WarCabinet decided that The consideration of this question should be deferred until its meeting on Tuesday, the 27th February.The Effect of theRestriction on theDominions,Colonies, Allies,and Neutrals.* In reference to the decision reached by the War Cabinet at the Meeting- heldon the 21st February, 1917 (War Cabinet, 77, Minute 14), and the note thereto, theSecretary of State for the Colonies desired it to be recorded that he associatedhimself with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in dissenting&apos; from thedecision.(Initialled) A. B. L.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,February 26, 1917.
Economic Conference.THE Russian Government nave signified to His Majesty&apos;s Government and to theFrench Government that they can only consent to ratify the resolutions of theEconomic Conference held in Paris in June last if it is agreed to sign at the same time a secret declaration to the following effect: &quot; The undersigned delegates of France, Great Britain, and Russia, being duly authorised to do so, have agreed that, in the elaboration of the measures necessary forthe execution of the resolutions adopted by the Economic Conference of the Allies heldat Paris in June 1916, each of the three Governments will take into account the specialeconomic conditions of its country, and the exceptional position which it accords tocertain categories of enemy subjects. It is fully understood that this declaration mustbe considered as forming an integral part of the instrument signed by the delegates,and that it will consequently be recognised as being ratified by any instrument ratifying the resolutions adopted by the aforesaid Conference.&quot; The present declaration will not be published.&quot; Done at Paris,&quot; &amp;c.2. On being asked by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Petrograd to explain more precisely the scope of the proposed Secret Declaration, the Russian Government statedthat it meant that they associated themselves generally with the decisions of theEconomic Conference, but reserved to themselves the right not to carry them into effect in cases where their application would be directly detrimental to Russian interests.3. It is obvious that this declaration enables any of the three Governments to disregard the Paris resolutions, either in part or altogether, if it chooses, but it ispractically certain that the Russian Government will not ratify the resolutions without this reserve.   The French Government are ready to sign the declaration.4. A Cabinet decision is required as to whether His Majesty&apos;s Government should express their readiness to sign the Declaration, and as to whether the other AlliedGovernments, notably the Japanese and Italian Governments, should also be invited todo so.   The Russian Government are pressing for an early reply.Foreign Office, January 1, 1917.Annex.Memorandum communicated by Count Benchendorff, October 2, 1916.SAISI de la question de la ratification des conclusions de la Conferenceeconomique, le Consent des Ministres, s&apos;associant pleinement avec le principe de lanecessite de decider des mesures de nature a mettre obstacle aux empietements del&apos;Allemagne, dans 1&apos;avenir, sur le terrain economique, a pourtant du prendre enconsideration les conditions speciales dans lesquelles se trouve la Russie conditionsqui different en plusieurs points de celles qui predomment. en Angleterre et enFrance.Ce point de vue n&apos;a pas echappe a la Conference elle-meine, qui en a tenu compteen redigeant avec grande prudence certaines de ses resolutions : telles une partie des articles lcr et 3.
Le Conseil des Ministres a, par consequent, opine dans le sens d&apos;une reserveexpresse, permettant a chacune des Puissances de se guider d&apos;apres les particulariteseconomiques de leur pays lors de 1&apos;etude des mesures destinees a mettre en pratiqueles resolutions de la Conference.Le Conseil pense que dans le but meme de maintenir la pleine solidarite entre lestrois principales Puissances qui ont participe a la Conference, 1&apos;Angleterre, la Franceet la Russie, il nest pas opportun de forrnuler cette reserve dans le texte meme de la[ communication officielle portant la confirmation du Gouvernement Imperial desresolutions de la Conference, comme l&apos;a fait le Gouvernement italien.Le Conseil s&apos;est arrete au projet de proposer aux Gouvernements britannique etfrancais la signature d&apos;une declaration confidentielle separee, dont le texte se trouveci-joint annexe. Cette declaration, en formulant la reserve en question, se prononcecontre celles des resolutions de la Conference qui limitent 1&apos;application de cesresolutions a certaines categories de sujets des pays ennemis auxquels leur race donneune situation privilegiee.M. Stuermer desirerait etre informe si le Gouvernement du Roi consentirait a lasignature aussitot que possible de la declaration en question.Des que ce document, qui n&apos;est pas destine a la publication, sera signe, leGouvernement Imperial procedera a la ratification du texte des resolutions de la conference, sans mention dans le texte de la ratification de la declaration en questionPour le cas ou les Gouvernements britannique et francais jugeraient opportund&apos;inviter les autres Puissances alliees a, la signature de la declaration, le GouvernementImperial n&apos;y verrait aucun obstacle.Ambassade Imperiale de Russie, Londres,le 25 septembre, 1916.Projet de Declaration eonfidentielle.Les soussignes, delegues des Gouvernements de France, de la Grande-Bretagne etde Russie, dument autorises a cet effet, se sont entendus que lors de 1&apos;elaboration des mesures a prendre pour 1&apos;execution des resolutions adoptees par la Conferenceeconomique des Allies tenue a Paris en juin 1916, chacun de ces Gouvernementstiendra compte des conditions economiques speciales de son pays ainsi que de la situation exceptionnelle qu&apos;il accorde a certaines categories des sujets ennemis. R estbien entendu que cette declaration doit etre consideree cornme faisant partie integralede 1&apos;acte signe par les delegations et qu&apos;elle sera, par consequent, reconnue commeratifiee par tout acte ratifiant les resolutions adoptees par ladite Conference.La presente declaration ne sera pas publiee.Fait a Paris, &amp;c.Londres, le 19 septembre/2 octobre, 1916.(2.)     .-,Viscount Greii to Sir G. Buchanan.(No. 2373.)(Telegraphic.) Foreign Office, October 12, 1916.Your telegram No. 1476 of 21st September: Russian Government and ParisEconomic Conference.Russian Ambassador here has communicated to me text of confidential declaration,and, before deciding whether they can concur, His Majesty&apos;s Government would likesome explanation of its precise meaning and purpose. The terms are so wide that if accepted without qualification they might in effect nullify all the resolutions.You should ask Minister for Foreign Affairs accordingly.
(40Board of Trade to Foreign Office.Sir, Board of Trade, December 23, 1916.I am directed by the Board of Trade to acknowledge the receipt of your letter ofthe 7th December, and its enclosures regarding the adhesion of the RussianGovernment to the recommendations of the Economic Conference of the Allies, whichwas held in June last.The Board note that the addition of a declaration in the terms of the second paragraph of the Russian Governments note, copy of which accompanied your letterof the 28th September, is apparently the only condition on which it is possible tosecure Russian adhesion to the recommendations in question, and in the circumstances it would seem to be difficult for His Majesty&apos;s Government to do otherwise thanacquiesce in the decision of the Russian Government, even though the proposed declaration has, in the Board&apos;s opinion, undoubtedly a weakening effect. It wouldappear that the French Government share these views. The Board are, however,disposed to suggest for Mr. Secretary BalfouFs consideration that before the consent ofHis majesty&apos;s Government is given to the declaration the matter should be referred tothe Cabinet.I have, &amp;c.H. FOUNTAIN.M. Cambon to Viscount Grey.L&apos;Ambassadeur de France a Petrograd a fait part au Gouvernement russe de1&apos;inte^ret qu&apos;attacherait le Gouvernement francais a voir ratifier les decisions de la conference econoniique avant la prochaine reunion des delegues techniques.Or, le Gouvernement russe a prescrite a son Amhassadeur a Londres de fournir au gouvernement britannique toutes les explications utiles sur le sens et la portee desreserves formulees a Petrograd. Au cas ou ces explications ne paraitraient pas denature a hater la solution, l&apos;affaire serait portee a nouveau devant le Conseil desMinistres russe et examinee avec le desir d&apos;aboutir a une prompte ratification. Si, aucontraire, le Gouvernement britannique se trouve d&apos;accord avec le Comte Benckendorff,la ratification russe serait immediate.M. Paul Cambon a ete charge de demander a sa Seigneurie le Vicomte Grey si unaccord a pu s&apos;etablir a Londres sur ces reserves russes.Le Gouvernement francais estime que 1&apos;interet de hater le plus possible 1&apos;adhesiondefinitive de la Russie semble devoir 1&apos;emporter de beaucoup sur le souci d&apos;obtenird&apos;issue des precisions et des assurances susceptibles de retarder et peut-etre meme derendre impossible la ratification recherchee.Dans 1&apos;opinion du Gouvernement fran^ais, les reserves formulees par le Gouverne-ment russe impliquent pour celui-ci, dans 1&apos;application des principes poses par la conference, le droit d&apos;adapter aux conditions particulieres du commerce, de 1&apos;industrie,de 1&apos;agricxdture, de la marine marchande russes, les resolutions auxquelles la signaturede ses delegues font associe en juin dernier. Dans ces conditions ces reserves n&apos;ontpas une portee aussi restrictive que celle qui leur est attribute par le gouvernement britannique.Quoiqu&apos;il en soit, M. Briand attacherait du prix a etre informe aussitot que possibledes echanges de vues intervenus a ce sujet entre sa Seigneurie le Vicomte Grey et leComte Benckendorff.M. Paul Cambon saisit, &amp;c.Ambassade de France, Londres,le 2 decembre, 1916.
APPENDIX II.(Private.)My dear Hankey, Foreign Office, February 24, 1917.THE French have telegraphed in very strong terms both to the Board of Tradeand to the Foreign Office saying that the Runciman agreement about luxuries cannot possibly be altered without consultation between the parties.I confess I see no answer to this contention ; and from a letter I have had fromRunciman it is quite clear that, while he would never have considered his arrangementincapable of modification, he would only have modified it after negotiation.Now, negotiation in our case was practically impossible, for the Cabinet onlydecided on Wednesday night to prohibit those luxuries which do not require muchtonnage. As the Prime Minister made his statement at 12 o&apos;clock on Friday morning,no communication with the French was practicable.This consideration, however, is not likely to appeal to the French. What answerare we to give them ? Neither Sir Albert Stanley nor I see any method of avoiding the negotiations now demanded without acting in a discourteous and almost violentfashion to our Allies.On the other hand, if we are to negotiate, it is very difficult to see how thenegotiations are to be conducted. The French have asked Sir Albert to go to Paris todiscuss restriction of imports among other matters. Can we allow him to go to paris and yet so limit his powers of negotiation as practically to confine him to theungrateful task of insisting on the fait accompli ?I think it would be a useful thing if the Cabinet were to consider this question onMonday. The Prime Minister will be away, and will, I fear, be very much occupiedbefore then, but if you could show him this paper it would be an advantage.Let me add that any concession made to France, will of course, have to be extendedto other countries in respect of goods of the same character.Yours ever,(Signed) ARTHUR JAMES BALFOUR.APPENDIX III.Petroleum Products.Proposed Interdepartmental Committee to deal with and co-ordinate the workof the various Departmental Committees.My dear Hankey, February 23, 1917.THE First Lord and Dr. Addison have been discussing the question of thepresent position as regards the business connected with petroleum products, and theyare agreed that there should be an Interdepartmental Committee to deal with and.co-ordinate the work of the various Departmental Committees at present dealing withthe subject.A conference between the-Departments&quot; concerned has been held, and a generalagreement has been reached as to the conditions under which the Committee is to workand as to the Terms of Reference.Sir O, Buchanan to Mr. Balfour.(No. 117.)(Telegraphic.) Petrograd, January 28, 1917.My telegram No. 1928 : Economic Conference.Minister for Foreign Affairs has again asked me to press for an answer. Question,is one which ought to be settled while Conference is in session here.
Looking to the important functions which the Interdepartmental ^Committee will&apos; have to exercise, the First Lord thinks that, hefore it is finally agreed to assemble theCommittee, the question should be mentioned to the Prime Minister for his approval,and he may consider it of sufficient importance to bring before the War Cabinet.I enclose a copy of a memorandum summarising the scheme, and, if desired, I cansupplement it by further papers giving more details.I shall be obliged if you will let me know, as soon as possible, what the PrimeMinister may decide, as there are one or two questions which urgently call forconsideration and decision, particularly the communication by Lord Cowdray on thesubject of the sale of British share in the oil interests in Mexico to Americans.Believe me, &amp;c.(Signed) W. GRAHAM GREENE.P.S. Please do not regard the &quot; reference &quot; as final, as the other Departments may desire to modify it.Sir, Admiralty, S.W., February 23, 1917.I am commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaintyou, for the information of the that at a Conference held at the Admiralty on Thursday, the 15th instant, to discuss aproposal originating with the Minister of Munitions for co-ordinating the policy of theDepartments and Committees now dealing with questions arising out of the supply anddistribution of petroleum products, an agreement was arrived at which is contained inthe accompanying memorandum based on the notes of the meeting already circulatedto the representatives present.2. My Lords understand that the conclusions arrived at commend themselves tothe authorities of the various Departments represented, and that on receipt of thisofficial communication steps will be taken at once to give effect to that same and toappoint a representative or representatives of the Department on the interdepartmental committee proposed to be set up.3. It is hoped, therefore, that as soon as the views of the Prime Minister havebeen ascertained the Committee may be assembled without delay to deal with matters which are now pressing for decision. Among these is a communication from lord Cowdray with regard to British oil interests in Mexico which calls for early consideration.I am, &amp;c.__:_&apos;_- JProposed Central Interdepartmental Petroleum Committee.At present the various questions affecting the supply and distribution of petroleumare dealt with by several Departmental Committees, which are in sufficiently close touch with each other, and there is no central body to co-ordinate the activities ofthese Committees and exercise a general supervision as to policy.The Committees in question are : 1. The Committee for the Regulation of Petroleum Supplies on which theAdmiralty, War Office, Board of Trade, and Ministry of Munitions are represented, and which reports to the Ministry of Munitions. ThisCommittee deals with the maintenance and proper distribution of petroleumsupplies other than those directly imported for Government use.2. The Petrol Control Committee, which reports to the President of the Board ofTrade. The Government Departments which are users of petrol are not represented.3. An Interdepartmental Committee, which sits at the Colonial Office and onwhich the Admiralty is represented. It deals with questions of oilexploration throughout the Empire, but mainly in the Crown Colonies.The view of the Ministry of Munitions was that the appointment of a bodypossessing co-ordinating and, where necessary, controlling functions in regard topetroleum matters was a pressing need, and that an Interdepartmental Committee
should be appointed with authority to consider and decide upon the action] desirable,and give instructions to the Departmental Committee concerned. The Interdepart-mental Committee would deal not only with questions immediately arising out of thewar, but would take such action in regard to-oil supplies generally as might benecessary in view of conditions likely to prevail subsequently.In order to give effect to this view, which was concurred in by the various departments concerned, it is proposed that an Interdepartmental Committee should beestablished under the chairmanship of Mr. E. G. Pretyman, Civil Lord of theAdmiralty, to consist of representatives of the following Departments, viz. : 2 admiralty.2 War Office.2 Board of Trade.2 Ministry of Munitions.1 Colonial Office.1 Controller of Shipping (Transport Department).Representatives of the Foreign Office and India Office would attend when questions affecting those Departments came up for discussion, and the Committee would also be assisted by technical advisers.The Interdepartmental Committee would he kept in close touch with the Depart-mental Committees through the representatives of the various Departments or byinviting the attendance of members of the Departmental Committees at meetings of theCentral Committee.It would be open to the Interdepartmental Committee to propose modificationsfrom time to time in the present functions of the various Committees, to suggest theappointment of new Committees, or to appoint Sub-Committees to deal with or toexamine various aspects of this subject, which is already of the highest importance and which is likely in the near future to lead to questions of the greatest urgency.The Interdepartmental Committee would keep in touch with such bodies as theBoard of Fuel Research, which has just been appointed.. Terms of Reference.To consider all questions of Petroleum Products and make recommendations as tothe best means of securing the necessary supplies and their distribution, and toco-ordinate and superintend the policy of Departmental and other Committees dealingwith various sections of the subject.

</content>
</cab>
