<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/203/3 images: 23-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government copy no cp(78) 7811 July 1978CABINETLOW INCOMESMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer. In connection with paragraph 20 of the draft White Paper on PayPolicy (CP(78) 76), I was asked to circulate a note on the low-paid and onaction taken by the Government in recent years to help them.MAKE-UP OF LOW-PAID2. As paragraph 20 points out, the majority of those on low incomes are entirely dependent upon state benefits.    For people in employment, theDepartment of Employment produced figures in September 1977 for thoseearning less than  40 a week (excluding overtime):  although the absoluteamounts will have changed, the relative positions should be much the same.Of the 1. 8 million or to full-time adults falling within this category. 80 percent are women, few of whom are likely to be the main source of income fora poor family.    This leaves 300, 000 men:  but a significant proportion ofthese are unlikely to be family breadwinners.    This is broadly confirmed bythe figures - some 80, 000 with a take-up rate of 75 per cent - of familieswhere the head is in employment and eligible for Family Income Supplement(FIS), since the threshold level for a family with one child is  43.80.3- Thus low earners supporting families are a small proportion of thelow-paid.    It is impossible to make special provision for these under paypolicy without extending this to all of the low-paid, for whom special treat-ment is not necessarily justified, and would be self-defeating to the extent that it led employers to substitute capital for labour.    Phases 1 and 2 of paypolicy, because of the cash underpinning, provided the greatest benefit inPercentage terms for the low-paid:  but past experience clearly demonstratesthat the higher-paid then seek to restore differentials, thus removing thistemporary advantage.    Further, any substantial concession to the low-paidcould only be accommodated within pay policy by a corresponding reductionin the overall figure for settlements.    This would lead to a further erosionof differentials with skilled workers, when all the pressures have been toprovide flexibility to allow them to be restored.
LOW INCOME RECIPIENTS DEPENDENT ON STATE BENEFITS4. Since 1976 those dependent on state benefits have had their positionmore than restored to their 1974 level in terms of purchasing power; and throughout the period regular upratings have generally protected them fromrising prices.    Those on retirement pensions, in fact, have never sufferedeven the slight fall in real income from uprating to uprating which affectedsome others dependent on state benefits.    The rise in the married couples1retirement pension to  28 last November meant an improvement in purchasing power of over 15 per cent, compared with that prevailing at theprevious Government1 s last uurating, to  12. 50 in October 1973. Thosedependent on long-term benefits other than retirement pensioners have alsoimproved their position under this Administration.    Single parents receivinglong-term supplementary benefit, for example, have experienced a realimprovement in their position of almost 7 per cent (between October 1973 and november 1977).    Short-term beneficiaries have also received realimprovements in their benefits:  the short-term supplementary benefit ratefor a family with two children was taken to a level 4 per cent higher in real terms in November 1977 than that prevailing in October 1973.LOW INCOME FAMILIES IN WORK5. The incomes of poor families in work remain substantially dependenton state support.    The main improvement in family support has been the phasing in of Child Benefit from April 1977, which will be complete by April1979.    This not only extended direct support to the first child but, bysubsuming the values of Child Tax Allowances, was of special help to thosefamilies where the head of the household was below the tax threshold. Infact, the increase in the value of Child Benefit to  4 from April 1979 will mean that the cash level of family support per child will be at its highestever for most families.    Support for one-parent families has also been substantially improved:  Child Interim Benefit for one-parent families was introduced in April 1976 at a rate of  1. 50;   the introduction of Child benefit in April 1977 was accompanied by a special 50p increase for the first child ofone-parent families, and this was doubled to  1 in April 1978.    In November1978 this will be doubled again to  2.6. Low income families in work have also been assisted by the twoupratings of FIS last year (there will be a further increase this November);and by last year&apos;s substantial increase in the income limits for free school meals (estimated to bring a further 500, 000 children into eligibility). Theneeds allowances for rent and rate rebates are also uprated annually, to maintaining the value of this type of support to those in work.
While the particular effect of each of these changes  thlow income families cannot be easily identified, the positiontwo children on half average earnings has improved by over 5 per cent ui real terms between May 1975 and May 1978, and by around 6 per cent over theperiod if means-tested benefits are included.D W treasury ChambersU July 1978

</content>
</cab>
