<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/13 images: 96-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s government 50 v printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1943.The circulation of this pamr has been strictSuJimited. It is issued for the personal use oi^r^^.. ^Q^^^^.-MOST SECRET.Copy- Nor33W.P. (43) 413.22nd September, 1943.WAR CABINET.MILITARY OCCUPATION OF GERMANY.Memorandum by the Chiefs of Staff.AT their Meeting* on the 16th June, 1943. the War Cabinet discussedproposals submitted by the Foreign secretary and the Minister of aircraft production^: for the occupation of Germany after her defeat, It was then agreedthat this question required further examination.2. The Post-Hostilities Planning Sub-Committee are new examining theproblem with a view to formulating plans for the military occupation of Germany.The matter is also of primary importance in relation to plans now being preparedfor our return to the Continent in the event of a German collapse, and also affectsplans for demobilisation.3. The Chiefs of Staff realise that a firm policy regarding the occupation ofGermany is not likely to be decided upon until after the forthcoming discussion between the Foreign Secretaries of this country, the United States and Russia.4. Nevertheless, the Chiefs of Staff ask that they may be given early guid-ance concerning the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government on the following points to enable us to complete our plans for the return to the Continent, and to direct the activities of the Post-Hostilities Planning Sub-Committee and Civil AffairsDirectorate of the War Office :  (a) Does His Majesty&apos;s Government desire to achieve the partition ofGermany by force ? Alternatively, is it the intention to preserveGermam&apos; as a single State, or without carrying out a compulsorypartition, to encourage any separatist of particularist tendencieswhich may spontaneously develop ?(&apos;&amp;) Is it the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government to establish a united nations Military Government (on the lines of A.M.G.O.T.) over thewhole of Germany, or is it the intention to confine Allied military government to the minimum area rendered necessary by operational requirements ?(c) Is it the policy that, for purposes of military occupation, each of the three powers, i.e.. Great Britain, United States, and the U.S.S.R.. should be allotted zones for which they will be primarily responsible, or, alter-natively, that the occupying forces should be composed of contingentssupplied by the various nations ?The Chiefs of Staff are not in favour of the employment at anystage of the occupation of mixed forces comprising contingents* W.M. (43) SOth Meeting, Minute 1. f W.P. (43) 217. $ W.P. (43) 243.[26118]
supplied by the various United Nations in any one zone, since wecousider that this would inevitably lead to friction and to difficultiesof control and organisation.(d) Should Austria be considered as a part of Germany, or should it betreated as a &quot; liberated &quot; rather than an ex-enemy Power? Further,does His Majesty&apos;s Government favour the ultimate transfer of east prussia to Poland? If so. would there be any political objection toPolish forces being used from the start for this military occupation?(Signed) A. E. BROOKE,C. F. PORTAL.  .N. SYFRET (V.C.N.S.).Offices of the War Cabinet. S.W. 1.22nd September, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
