<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/85/13 images: 107-117</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



COPY NC

CABINET

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet

held at 10 Downing Street on

THURSDAY 2 APRIL 1987

at 10.00 am

PRESENT

The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP

Prime Minister

he Rt Hon Viscount Whitela*^ })

ord President of the Counci&gt;^/^-N\

he Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP

lhancellor of the Exchequer ?OAYS

he Rt Hon Peter Walker MP

Secretary of State for Energy \V/y

he Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MP \0

Secretary of State for Wales ^

he Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP

Secretary of State for Social Services

he Rt Hon Michael Jopling MP

linister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food

he Rt Hon Lord Young of Graffham

Secretary of State for Employment

he Rt Hon Kenneth Clark QC MP

aymaster General

he Rt Hon Malcolm Rifkind QC MP

Secretary of State for Scotland

The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MP

Secretary of State for Foreign and

Commonwealth Affairs

The Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP

Secretary of State for the Home Department

The Rt Hon George Younger MP

Secretary of State for Defence

Vjhe Rt Hon John Biffen MP

XTLwrd Privy Seal

^ThepR^ Hon Tom King MP

S&amp;cr^^ary of State for Northern Ireland

The^R^fou Nicholas Ridley MP

Secre^^r^of State for the Environment

The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker MP

Secretary of State for Education and Science

The Rt Hon Jc^vnMttcGregor MP

Chief Secreta\^ 3rr-aasury

The Rt Hon Paul ^Ch^jjir&amp;i MP

Secretary of Statevf^^rade and Industry

The Rt Hon John Moore MP

Secretary of State for Transport

ALSO PRESENT

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP

Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury


SECRETARIAT

Sir Robert Armstrong

Mr D F Williamson (Items 2-5)

Mr J B Unwin (Item 5)

Mr A J Langdon (Item 1)

Mr N H Nicholls (Items 2-4)

Mr S S Mundy (Item 1)

contents

Item 1. 2.	Subject parliamentary affairs FOREIGN A&amp;JAjScS	Page 1

	Prime mnister&apos;s Visit to the Soviet Union, 28 March to 1 April 1987	1

	Chad ^	3

		3

	Visit of Mr Walid/^rjfebJ.att to London	4

	Iran/Iraq &lt;^^^\ Greece/Turkey	4 4

3.	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS &lt;^^^&gt;	

	Agriculture l/s*^	5

	Republic of Ireland Proposals oja^mrvy-Free Goods	5

4.	STATEMENT ON THE DEFENCE ESTIMATES 198^&lt;&lt;r&gt;	5

5.	OPENING THE JAPANESE MARKET \\	6




1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House

of Commons in the following week.

FOREIGN V/

iFFAIRS

&apos;rime

linister&apos;s

risit to the

loviet Union,

!8 March to

April 1987

yf[-x   THE PRIME MINISTER, reporting on her visit to the Soviet Union from

/^r^Barch to 1 April, said that the Soviet authorities had done

^ev^j^hing possible to ensure its success.    They had agreed to every

raqua^fc when drawing up the programme; and throughout the visit she had

be&lt;^aei^prded unfailingly courteous and generous treatment. Her

prog^&amp;ame^ad included a visit to Zagorak Monastery, a visit to a Moscow

housiw&lt;x tate, meetings with Dr Sakharov and leading Soviet

intellectuals and had concluded with a visit to Georgia.

She had had over nine hours of wide-ranging, detailed and candid

discussions wijA-^he General Secretary of the Communist Party of the

Soviet Union^/MrWikhail Gorbachev, culminating in a private dinner

party.    She h\^h rKa separate two hour meeting with Mr Ryzhkov, the

Soviet Prime Mii/fstdr.

During her meeting^^^rt Mr Gorbachev, she had explained the reasons for

Western apprehensioi^s^tothe Soviet Union (referring inter alia to

Soviet interventionsM&apos;fi^jjkc ho Slovakia and Afghanistan).    The West

welcomed Mr Gorbachev&apos; S/C^rafri tment to internal reform but still awaited

signs of change in SovieH^ejmernal policies.    Mr Gorbachev had said that

the Soviet Union was notNfe23^t^g actively to promote world communist

domination; but the Soviet^Unw&gt;&amp; believed in its system and therefore

believed that its inf luence^oju^tf extend.    This was a significant

statement. /

In discussion of arms control,  sh^nk &gt; welcomed the abandonment of the

link between an agreement on interss^diai.e range-long range forces (INF)

and the Strategic Defence Initiativ^^^ll).    Although,  for reasons of

verification,  the global abolition ofXo^would have been preferable to

an arrangement which permitted the retf^mtion by either side of 100

systems,  such an agreement was acceptable provided that it included

constraints on shorter-range systems,  to which the United Kingdom was

vulnerable, and provision for immediate follow-on negotiations.    It was

also important that the West should have the /KfgVt to match Soviet

shorter-range systems.    Mr Gorbachev had disaareesL arguing for a freeze

on shorter-range systems.    She had dealt robustJTy^vJvth his attempts to

claim that NATO aircraft with dual nuclear and iWnV^i^ional capability

should be taken into account, and had drawn atten^w to the substantial

conventional imbalance,  in the face of which the detep^Xt power of

nuclear weapons was essential to the West&apos;s security^^sX v

On chemical weapons (CW),  the Prime Minister had contrlk^fyshe United

Kingdom&apos;s destruction of its stocks 30 years previously yifcjj^Hae

enlargement and modernisation of the Soviet chemical stock WV^

Adequate verification, which was crucial to a CW agreement)0wmij3 not be


easy, but the United Kingdom had put forward proposals on this aspect.

Mr Gorbachev had indicated that the Soviet Union was ready to

^ co-operate.

*^X)n strategic systems, the Prime Minister had expressed support for 50

^jper cent reductions by the Soviet Union and the United States.

^ilt&apos;Gorbachev had been adamant that no agreement was possible without

/^flWraints on the United States SDI programme.    The Prime Minister had

^arg^aNd against this, pointing out that it was sensible to conduct

r sea&lt;5kh to establish whether or not a SDI system was feasible. Actual

deg y&quot;B*xit i  space must be a matter for negotiation.

On huTO^rights, on which he was clearly sensitive, Mr Gorbachev had

taken aXtough stance, seeking to riposte by referring to Northern

Ireland and the unemployment situation.    But he had undertaken to look

positively at the individual cases that had been brought to his

attention. The Erime Minister had stressed that the extent of Soviet

compliance wi/unvne Helsinki accords on human rights would be regarded

as a touchstoS$ ^a -~likely Soviet observance of agreements on arms

control. (C^s)

A number of region  t7/^ues had also been covered, including Soviet

support for Libya aod/jpfa^ia.    Mr Gorbachev had refused to admit that the

Soviet Union supplied/aS^psX^nd training for international terrorists.

The Soviet authorities I^rD^jen fully co-operative over the Prime

Minister&apos;s television bro^d^aVK. which had been shown in full.    She had

been pressed by her three interviewers especially hard on the

issue of nuclear weapons, an^i^juy taken the opportunity to set out in

full the key facts of the str&gt;m g4^. balance and to recapitulate the

arguments for the retention of\jkicl&gt;ar weapons, which had ensured

continuing peace with security.  &lt;^saw&quot;esult, Soviet public opinion had

been exposed to one of the fullest^jfpositions of the Western position

it had ever experienced. ^-\Cv

The Prime Minister said that Mr Gorbaotn^v had been confident and was

clearly in control.    Her discussions wroh him had been the fullest that

she had ever conducted with a world leader, and they had provided a

unique opportunity to put over the Western position on a wide range of

issues at first hand.    Discussion had been fr^kvand forthright; but

despite combative episodes and tough discusswnis^ he atmosphere had

remained friendly throughout.    It was noticeaDrffVCnm: the Soviet

leadership tended to be the victims of their owJ\vp^pj&gt;aganda; and on some

issues they were seemingly ignorant of the facts. &gt;Wa. number of

occasions, Mr Gorbachev had sought to score propagaa Kpfaints, but she

had stuck to a patient exposition of the facts and ff^Jps^e^ out full and

reasoned responses.    The Soviet system had not fun dame n ft&amp;x changed and

should not be expected to do so; and living standards w^re^axvd would

continue to be a great deal lower than in the West.    The\cWHg s that

Mr Gorbachev was setting in train would take time to come vrft^T^ffect.

But they represented a turning point; and she had made it c^ean^bhat she

wished Mr Gorbachev well. i//^


THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that he had had separate and

extensive discussions with the Soviet Foreign Minister, Mr Eduard

Shevardnadze.   These had covered similar ground to the Prime Minister&apos;s

,  discussions with Mr Gorbachev, including in particular human rights. A

&quot;^memorandum had been signed on culture, information and education,

^C^pgether with agreements on space co-operation; on upgrading the hot

/WjAe between London and Moscow; and on sites for new Embassies in both

/Jpdpbtals.    There had also been encouraging progress over trade,

ij*j il!yiing the success of John Brown Engineers and Constructors Limited

rfi amfiing a contract to construct a  100 million polypropylene plant,

ov^^SfiTlth the Soviet authorities had shown themselves especially

he lpWy^Wlr Shevardnadze had invited him to revisit Moscow.

In discission, there was agreement that the visit had afforded an

invaluable opportunity to convey an authoritative account of the Western

position direct to the Soviet leadership.    This process should be

further develpg^ds.    It was clear that the Prime Minister&apos;s television

broadcast hadVmad^ a deep public impression; she had been seen as

someone who caiid^kssionately for peace.    Her public appearances had

been unique f or fa W es tern leader in the Soviet Union, and had drawn huge

and enthusiastic^erj^was.    The visit had clearly been a great success,

and its impact,  irf^th^Soviet Union,  in the United Kingdom and

internationally, had^e^mprofound.

The Cabinet - &lt;&quot;^^^)

1.      Warmly welcomea^fejfe^isit by the Prime Minister

and the Foreign and CMrafcQpwealth Secretary as a

positive and constructN^e^fjfep in furthering

relations with the Soviet /Tfrfi&apos;wn, and wished the

Soviet Government and people&gt;e^kry success in the

process of political, econowlc^a^d social development

which the new leadership had &lt; g ^n train.

Chad

&apos;revious

Reference:

)C(87) 12.3

V

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY reported that, although the

recent Chadian successes against Libyan forces^-cspresented a blow for

Colonel Qadhafi,  the President of Libya, his/s^cVVity apparatus was

effective and his imminent overthrow was unli^Ljkr-NJ? ranee was taking

seriously Colonel Qadhafi&apos;s threats of terroris^ac^ion against her.

Jhina

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that he had/^^\a useful

meeting, for the fourth time within a year, with the Ch*f ei;ajForeign

Minister, Mr Wu Xueqian,  in Berne the previous week,  largfejv^ \&gt; discuss

Hong Kong issues.    He had sought to dispel Chinese suspic i^a^oothe

issue of direct elections in Hong Kong.    There had also beei^^^/


discussion of internal developments in China, and bilateral and

international issues.    Such meetings helped to add to the United

Kingdom&apos;s authority in Soviet eyes.

Visit of

Mr Walid

Jumblatt to

London

JREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the leader of the

hg&amp;aru&amp;e Druze Community, Mr Walid Jumblatt, had visited London the

pre^roy&gt;vweek, when he had met the Minister of State, Foreign and

ComiSed^Salth Office, Mr Renton, and the Archbishop of Canterbury,

Dr Ru^oA/^^ Mr Jumblatt, who had been responsible for the security in

Beirutvft the Archbishop&apos;s Special Representative, Mr Terry Waite, had

no fresn^information on his whereabouts nor any suggestion for securing

his release.

Iran/Iraq

Previous

Reference:

CC(87) 5.4

THE FOREIGN AND ^OM^MVEALTH SECRETARY said that tension had eased in

the Gulf.    Followi*r^^mA United States protest to Iran,  there were no

signs that she contenro ^ed immediate military action.    He had had a

constructive discusS3^&gt;*f\5&amp;the situation with the Soviet Foreign

Minister, Mr Eduard Shev^^roadze; and the Chinese Foreign Minister,

Mr Wu Xueqian, had deniMJ^ n&quot;yt his Government had supplied SILKWORM

missies direct to Iran.   \Jo*repxieration was being given to further action

in the United Nations Secur^^^^puncil.

Greece/Turkey

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECrTTtajJ*&apos;*said that a potential crisis had

arisen in the Aegean Sea the previa^s^^J^ek, following the Greek

Government&apos;s nationalisation of an orJL^lgdJd in waters disputed between

Greece and Turkey.    Turkey, which had ^&quot;ferpreted the decision as

designed to extend Greek influence witn\jn these waters, had authorised

petroleum licences within them and despatched an exploration vessel to

the scene.    Fortuitously, the Turkish Prime Minister, Mr Turgut Ozal,

had been in London and the Foreign and Commonw^a^ih Secretary had spoken

to him twice on the subject.-  Mr Ozal&apos;s decisufori \)o hold back the vessel

had defused the situation.    A way would have ctt^tf^-vfeund to seek a

solution to the problem of the Aegean continenta^_sx Li.

The Cabinet -

2.      Took note.


AgriculXXrV/

3.     THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that the

Agriculture Council on 30-31 March had opened the discussion on the

Commission&apos;s proposals for agricultural prices and related measures in

1987-88.   This had indicated that the negotiations were likely to be

Nboth long and difficult.    The Germans had taken a harsh line in

/Gpposition to the proposals.    It was possible that a settlement would

 ^ftyythe end be reached only by voting the Germans down, which would be

MjjeV^y;ontentiou8.

Republic of

Ireland

Proposals on

Duty-Free

Soods

THE S^^TARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said that the new Government

in theVlepublic of Ireland had presented a budget which, although

otherwise containing the expected cuts in public expenditure, also

contained a new provision changing the rules on duty-free allowances.

The effect woutJtNbe to make it no longer possible for people from the

Republic of 1/el^.d who crossed the border for a day&apos;s shopping trip in

Northern IreliMDd/^ESNbenefit from the present duty-free allowances on

importing theirfcurxnases into the Republic of Ireland.    This would

seriously damageV-tif^denefits which the Northern Ireland economy and the

United Kingdom ExcM^W^. gained from the present arrangements. He

understood that theOjJrravlic of Ireland would need a derogation from the

Community Directive mwrwr to make this change.    The United Kingdom&apos;s

interest was clearly tiyj^e the change.

The Cabinet -

Took note.

STATEMENT ON

[HE DEFENCE

ESTIMATES 1987

Previous

Reference:

X(86) 14.3

4.      The Cabinet considered a memorarfovmby the Secretary of State for

Defence (C(87) 5) on the Statement o^W Defence Estimates 1987.

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE saicrthat the underlying theme of the

Statement was one of continuity of policy.    It reflected developments in

arms control negotiations and the domestic debate on North Atlantic

Treaty Organisation strategy and Trident.    Ttfe&apos;ljoatement repeated the

previous year&apos;s warning that difficult decisx^as^ray ahead in

reconciling aspirations with the money available^   jHe proposed to issue

the Statement on 6 May, with a popular vers ion, ^rt V&gt;fft would be available

free of charge.    If this was criticised, attentiotj/yau^d be drawn to a

recommendation made by the Select Committee on Defe^p^^hat a low-cost

popular version of the Statement should be issued, awf\ cKthe

Committee&apos;s welcome for the issue of a previous popular/&gt; r*sion free of

charge. ^xO/

In discussion,  it was noted that the draft Statement wouldf^WnoSre

further amendment,  in particular to reflect the Prime Minis^er^*/visit

to Moscow.


THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the Cabinet

approved the draft Statement on the Defence Estimates 1987, subject to

any further detailed drafting amendments which should be forwarded to

the Secretary of State for Defence by 6 April.

The Cabinet -

fy^&lt;\^Invited the Secretary of State for Defence to arrange

&gt;&gt;vlor tne issue of the Statement on the Defence

^&apos;&apos;&apos;jratimates 1987, together with a popular version

^^he^eof, as he proposed.

OPENING THE

JAPANESE

MARKET

previous

Reference:

fC(87) 12.3

5.     The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of State for

Trade and Indus^rv (C(87) 6) on Opening the Japanese Market.

THE SECRETARY\^J ^TE FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY recalled that his

memorandum was cfyrcuiated in response to a request by the Cabinet

following discus^fco^&amp;t their previous meeting.    The United Kingdom&apos;s

general aim was toympxyyiv the Japanese market to British goods and

services.    There weyg/&amp;&amp;0 two specific aims:  to gain early access to

Japan for British fi^f^^aX institutions and services and to ensure that

Cable and Wireless pic y2?$K got a fair deal in the current negotiations

on Japanese telecommunic^r ^onte.    The three aims might call for different

means of action.

On general issues of trade \Ktp/&lt;Jkipan,  it was necessary to proceed as a

member of the European Commurfe&apos;f^xOQn financial services the Financial

Services Act provided powers t^^fetB^e or revoke authorisation in the

United Kingdom if reciprocal acce^sNi foreign markets were denied to

United Kingdom firms.    British compiles had had some success in

establishing a presence in banking igSM&amp;fyix securities in Japan, but major

obstacles had been put up against acceA^o the Tokyo Stock Exchange.

The Parliamentary Under Secretary of Wte, Department of Trade and

Industry (Mr Howard) would be in Tokyo^he following week and would be

energetically pressing the case for such access.    He now proposed to

make forthwith the Orders necessary to bring into effect the powers of

the Financial Services Act in relation to baiU^JSgXand insurance. The

powers in relation to investment could not bd*(brdpght into effect

immediately.    If the Japanese did not produce^-^y^tthe time of the

further official talks scheduled for May, a sat$^f#c ery timetable for

access for United Kingdom firms to the Tokyo StocTC^Khange, the

Government would then have to decide whether to use /tHw /powers on

reciprocity in the Financial Services Act. &lt;!s$^&gt;

On C&amp;W,  the situation was changing.    Clearly the Japana&gt;^5fMiistry of

Posts was opposed to a separate consortium with C&amp;W parr&amp;j*M don which

would have the use of a new trans-Pacific cable.    The JapanXs^X

Ambassador had informed him that a new proposal was being p\nepVi fed in

Tokyo, under which the two consortia competing for the Japan^e^^

telecommunications business would be merged.    In the new conso^Mv


about 60 per cent would be allocated to a large number of small

companies and 40 per cent would be divided equally between eight major

companies including C&amp;W which would also have a seat - whether executive

s. or not was not clear - on the board.    It seemed likely that C&amp;W would

voot consider this good enough but in the absence of the Chairman abroad

\s*ff considered that the Government should not prejudge their decision.

yfjfLythe result was unsatisfactory for C&amp;W, the Government would have to

/^&gt;&lt;mvider possible courses of action.    He had set out possibilities in

pirarg^aph 10 of his paper.    He recommended in favour of a.    in relation

t^t^ecommunications, although the effect might not be great. Points

k* ch^5^    were the responsibility of other colleagues.    He did not

hims^yy^ayour them.

On open^ig up the Japanese market more generally, he had set out in

paragraphs 14 and 15 of C(87) 6 the action which might be taken by the

European Community.    Some changes in the Commission&apos;s present proposals

and some care ^ijr^the choice of products would be necessary but, subject

to this, he ffaVou^ed tougher measures against the dumping of components,

unbinding Commulyi^yNtariffs as justified by the enlargement of the

Community, and awnp^jable action to avoid diversion if the United States

acted against Japafl^aef exports.    He also favoured reactivating the

complaint against &lt;tfaQ KOunder Article XXIII of the General Agreement on

Tariffs and Trade ((SA^fT^Xbut he could not be sure that this would be

fully supported by ocfieiy&amp;&amp;intries.    He had also referred in

paragraph 15 of C(87) 6^[SKa^tion without further recourse to GATT.

That would be a drastic ^xfeiyjand there would be serious consequences if

the United Kingdom attempVe^^Kbut failed to achieve it because of lack

of support. VC^/^

In discussion the following poyW^were made -

a. The case for making fo ^riwi^h the Commencement Orders to bring

into effect the reciprocity p^w^r-&amp;-\in the Financial Services Act in

relation to banking and insura^rr^^was strong.    It was also

desirable that action on requesty^^ar authorisation for Japanese

companies in the financial servicers field should not be brought to

a conclusion at least until it was^clear whether the visit of the

Parliamentary Under Secretary of State, Department of Trade and

Industry,  to Tokyo had led to a time table^- or improved access for

British firms to the Tokyo Stock Exchanflfe^~\\

b. On C&amp;W the Government should not preerfipt\he views of the

company in respect of the expected announceqejw^ln Tokyo of revised

proposals.    It was not yet clear what the coi^rarw^s management role

in a new consortium might be or whether any as^&amp;ap^e about the

next trans-Pacific cable could be relied on.    I^/T^e^result was not

satisfactory,  it would be right to decide to take r^^ftxocity into

account in deciding whether to grant telecommunicavCemjlicences to

foreign companies and in the telecommunications appaJ^bra\approva Is

procedure.    The remaining suggestions in paragraph 10^*^0^87) 6 on

intellectual property, air services, work permits and ifyarfD

purchases should not be pursued. ^C^^S\


c.     A recent negotiation on airline services with Japan had given

good results for the United Kingdom.    From 31 May there would be

ten flights a week on each side, of which six would be non-stop.

For the first time British Caledonian Airways would be operating to

Japan.   A large part of the traffic between London and Japan

originated in Japan.    The new arrangements would substantially

increase the revenue of the two British airlines.    It would be

\ extremely damaging to suggest that any flights should be

?transferred from Heathrow to Gatwick or otherwise to call in

^^ffciestion the recent agreement.

&gt;/  Penin8 tne Japanese market the Foreign and Commonwealth

^fo^retary would follow up with European Community Foreign Ministers

tfifat weekend the scope for action on dumping of components,

unwinding of tariffs, measures to avoid trade diversion and the

implementation of Article XXIII of GATT.

e. It /wouM be useful also to follow up the suggestion made by HM

Ambassaa^q^/ ^kyo, that there were certain new products such as

digital audjfo \ape players on which the Japanese industry was

staking a gxE&gt;f^deal and to which some special scrutiny might be

applied. &lt;/y&apos;L^&gt;

f. Probably th^e^r&amp;atest pressure on Japanese business so far had

come from the rise/wj/bhe value of the yen.    The present stance was

broadly to maintaiq^he) Jcurrent relationships between the major

currencies.    It couNfc^jr^orthwhile, however, to sound out quite

informally some Commu&lt;fz^sV\^plleagues and also the United States

about the possibility o^jL^joacerted action to bring about a further

rise in the yen. I

g. The press was still tajx ru &gt;in terms of a trade war.    It was

important to avoid a mismatchr^bVt&gt;?een the tone of press and public

comment and the more limited fiJSol^&amp;cives and actions which the

Government had in mind. v//^

h. There was substantial externa^ investment by Japanese

institutions and companies in prospect.    They would,  for example,

be major investors in Eurotunnel.    It wasimportant that nothing

should be done to deter or divert elsewh^r&quot;e\\the potential benefits

from such investment in the United KingWom.Y 

THE PRIME MINISTER,  summing up the discussion, the Cabinet

agreed that - ^bO

a.      Orders to bring into effect the reciproci^^T^V^rs in the

Financial Services Act in relation to banking and wm rance should

be made immediately.    The Parliamentary Under SecF^a^y\ of State,

Department of Trade and Industry (Mr Howard) shoula^jwr^A in Tokyo

for a clear timetable for access for United Kingdom ^rafe^o the

Tokyo Stock Exchange.    In the light of that, the GoverwnepJ^would

decide whether to take action under the Financial Servi&lt;  ^^C}t. In


the meantime applications from Japanese financial service companies

for authorisation to trade in the United Kingdom should not be

brought to a conclusion.

b. The case of C&amp;W was a test of Japanese willingness to open up

their market.    The latest Japanese proposals did not seem

j\promising, but the Government should await the views of C&amp;W. If

2^he result were judged unacceptable,  the Secretary of State for

y/ptade and Industry should take reciprocity into account in deciding

^ ^\elecommunications licences to Japanese companies and in the

^S^ep^immunications apparatus approvals procedure.    The remaining

wmS in paragraph 10 of C(87) 6 should not be pursued.

c. On opening up the Japanese market the options on dumping of

components, unbinding Community tariffs and measures to avoid trade

diversion^ s  out in paragraph 14 a.  to c. of C(87) 6 should be

pursued.ff InMaddition, the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary

should sV^d^JtsX other Community Ministers about the possibility of

reactivati/| aoiion under Article XXIII of GATT.    The suggestion of

other retalva3&gt;M$ action without recourse to GATT should not be

followed up. ^iL^

d. The possib special scrutiny of other administrative

action on imports pC^GSl products of particular interest to

Japanese industry srfymlin be further examined by officials under

Cabinet Office chairm^^^^p.

The Cabinet - ^t^f/

1. Invited the Foreign a*ra^C^bmonwealth Secretary,

the Chancellor of the Exche^e&apos;r.ajid the Secretary of

State for Trade and Industry J^p^e-^guided by the Prime

Minister&apos;s summing up of their^^fJyussion.

2. Invited the Secretary of the\Cabinet to arrange

for the further official discussioir referred to in the

summing up.

Cabinet Office

2 April 1987



</content>
</cab>
