<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/2/32 images: 454-457</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C (P ? 5*fffilS IX3CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GQvERMMEMT)aSECRETW.P.    (R) (39)   72WAR   CABINET.SUPPLY AND PRODUCTION.CIVIL DEFENCE REPORT NO. 2.REPORT BY THE MINISTER OF HOME security for OCTOBER, 1959.Supplies and production for the schemes of Civil Defence in themain have proceeded according to programme during the month of Octobers,But* nevertheless, the heavy demands for the Fighting Services are now beginning to affect the rates of delivery for Civil Defence supplies?and it is anticipated that the position will tend to worsen in the coming months.    The aim of the Department was to bring its programme of suppliesof shelters and other A.R.P. equipment near to completion by March of next year and thus to make way in the field of productive activity forthe growing demands of the Fighting Services, but the immediate needs will prevent its achievement.   Moreover, the general position of Civil Defencesupplies is less advanced than it might have been owing to the diversion of stocks and current supplies to meet requirements of the FightingServicesj Allies and other Government Departments.    These contributions have been made possible by the fact that orders for Civil defence requirements were initiated well in advance of war.   Since the outbreakOf    war, the following quantities have been supplied to the War Offices-Civilian respirators;     500*000 were despatched in September at therequest of the Polish Government.   They are now in Istambul,and have been offered to Turkey.Steel helmets;     100,000 have been transferred to the War Office,who have also been enabled to take up to about 60*000 a week fromthe contractor allotted to Civil Defence requirements.Service respirators; The Department has accepted half of the weeklyallotment of output to which it would have been entitled on normalprinciples of allocation .Light Oilskin suits and Oilskin gloves;       The whole of the department s share of production for 4- weeks at the beginning of war wassurrendered to the War Office.   This represents a loss of about90,000 suits and 70,000 pairs of gloves.Gumboots;   The Department had the benefit of contracts for 300,000pairs of boots a week.   Under an arrangement made a few weeks ago*60*000 a week are to be   diverted to the War Office.   In additionCOPY NO 6 ;--7

9^his O-2-10,000 pairs of small size boots have been transferred tothe War Office from stock.Sandbags:     Since the 1st September, 45 million sandbags have been supplied to the War Office and the other Service Departments,and this quantity is thus a direct curtailment of supplies available for civil defence.Steel Shelters.Despite the delivery of Ig- million shelters to householders,there is still a large unsatisfied demand.   Over 400,000 applications from the vulnerable areas are held and 800,000 more are expected,including applications from would-be purchasers.   Deliveries during thepast fortnight have decreased, owing to the requirements of sheet steelof the Field Forces, which has necessitated an immediate reduction of4 per cent.in the rate of supplyo   Part of the needs are being met byimported supplies.    Further expansion of production in this country withinthe essential period is not possible and larger cuts may have to be made tomeet the growing needs of the Fighting ServicesoRespirators.The position of the various items is satisfactory, except of thesmall children&apos;s and babies1 types. Increased supplies of these twotypes have however been received this month, and 31 per cent, and-46 percent.respectively of the essential needs have been met.Emergency Hospital and Evacuation Supplies.The position during the month has generally improved,and it can be regarded as on the whole satisfactory.


</content>
</cab>
