<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/32 images: 532-551</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 lTT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANillC MAJESTY&apos; S GO VERNiiENT)2 T)(U0)32 , Copy No.   ^WAR    cabinet economic WarfareEighteenth Weekly Report submitted by theMinister of Economic Warfare covering the periodlhth January - 21st January 19UO.(Previous Report:    Paper No. W.P.(R) (1+0)22(Initialled) R.H.C.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.

War Trade Negotiations and Relations with^t^ljDountries.There have &quot;been no outstanding events duringthe week.      Good progress has been made with the negotiationsfaith the Greek Delegation in London and progress with the[negotiations with the Swiss Government which are takingplace in Berne has also &quot;been satisfactory.      But there havebeen difficulties in the negotiations with the Danishrelegation, and the outlook for the conclusion of the agree-ment with Norway is not very hopeful.      The Italian Govern-ment have rejected the proposals made to them for a form ofWar Trade Agreement,  and the clearing and shippingnegotiations in Rome are also hanging fire.2. The position in the various- countries if&quot;briefly as, follows: -SWEDEN.3. A large amo\int of work of a preliminary character in preparation for the first meeting of theAnglo-Swedish Standing Commission has been done withMr. Wallenberg, who has handed over particulars of theSwedish import programmes for 1940 in respect of a largenuraber of important commodities.      When these programmeshave &quot;been agreed,  they will simplify the exercise of our contraband Control and our Export Licensing arrangements.A-The preliminary work accomplished makes it appear that the Swedish Government have been administering the terms of the Agreement, and particularly theoperations of their Export Licence Commission, with a praise-worthy degree of strictness.5- Mr. Wallenberg has reported that his Govern-merit have appointed a representative to come to this country&amp;r,-d act as liaison between the Swedish Government and the-4-llied Governments in connection with food and feeding-stuffs.SO/&apos;

s to co-ordinate the purchasing arrangementsconcerned as contemplated hy the War Trade Agreement.i--iV.V &apos;AVTipXWi-,-.&apos;6. The Norwegian Delegation have returned toOslo, where a representative of the Ministry of economic warfare will arrive on the 25th January.7.  It appears from the speeches of the Norwegian-ri:ne Minister and the Minister for Foreign Affairs atthe opening of the Storting that, whatever impressionmay have been made on the Norwegian Trade Delegation in;.ondon, the Norwegian Government intend to cling to theirprinciples of neutrality.      It is hy no means certain,therefore, that the negotiations for a War Trade agreement that have been pursued in London can he successfullyconcluded in Oslo.        It is a had sign that the Norwegianshipowners are not carrying out the Shipping Agreement.Their attitude may well he due to instructions from theNorwegian Government who are doubtless using this methodto bring pressure on us to enter into the kind of War TradAgreement that they would like to have.dgjmagk.8. A draft War Trade Agreement has been presented to the Danish Delegation who have replied withwritten counter-proposals.      The reply shows that we areat variance on a number of essential points.      The date foblocking sterling payments for hacon and &quot;butter has beenagain extended to allow negotiations to proceed for aPayments Agreement.      The question of making some con-cessions to the Danes is under consideration in the light0i their plea that execution of the Payments Agreement ini t&quot; cpresent form would cause the Germans to interfere with-anish food ships.ICELAND/

-D-9.  The British members of the Joint Standing-&quot;omiriittee&apos;, part of which will sit in Reykjavik and partin London, have now &quot;been appointed.10.  It is hoped that the French Government willalso appoint their Consul in Reykjavik as a member.11. Licences for export from United Kingdomstocks have been granted, for considerable quantities ofraw materials  required by the Finnish Army Command,      these include wool to replace the stocks of wool destroyed during the bombing of Turku (Abo) by the Russians.,12.  Measures continue to be taken for expediting the passage through the Contraband Control of consignmentsfor Finland,  including one cargo of war material from Italy.BALTIC STATES.13-  In view of the increasing transport difficulties the volume of trade between the United Kingdomand the Baltic States is steadily falling.lu-  The date of the arrival in Lond.cn of theLatvian Trade Delegation has not yet been fixed.      There is reason to believe that the projected visit of the EstonianTrade Delegation in London will be abandoned.3SLGIUi,i.15. The French Government have approved the termsof the special arrangements for Jute,  cotton and hemp.If possible the terms of those special arrangements will bebrought into operation without waiting for the conclusionof the negotiations for the other special arrangements.^pRLANDS.16.  Negotiations are at present held up while theNetherlands Delegation obtain instructions on various points.SWITZERLAND.

17.  Further meetings have taken place in Berneduring the past week betv/een the Commercial Secretary, his-reach colleague and the Swiss experts.      Discussions onthe Lists to he attached to the War Trade Agreement have proceeded satisfactorily,  and negotiations are reaching an advanced stage.13.  The Swiss Trade Delegation have returned toLondon and have resumed negotiations with the Treasury andthe Board of Trade.greece;.19. Negotiations with the Greek Delegation are continuing and a draft War Trade Agreement and list of quotas for Greek exports to Germany,  together with the other textsinvolved, have been accepted provisionally by the Delegation,;.t the last meeting, however,  the Delegation communicateda message from General Metaxas requesting a further assurance from His i(lajesty&apos; s Government as a condition for the con-elusion of the Agreement,      This would he to the effect  thatif the conclusion of the Agreement led to the completeinterruption of Greco-German trade (affecting exports toGermany such as tobacco which His ulajesty&apos; s Government arenot interested in stopping), His Majesty&apos;s Government would.n;ake up the losses to the Greek economy which this wouldinvolve.      The question of how u&apos;enerai Lie tax as    request isto be treated is now under consideration.20. Owing to the refusal of th^ xto&quot;5rc.i.i.l      -r . ,..rw,e--&quot;0 approve long term contracts for- the sale of petroleum,  or&apos;-o issue export licences for purchases already made and the-ported establishment of a commissariat to take control ofj*e whole Roumanian industry,  it has been decided to bringosBible pressure to bear on the Roumanian Goyernment morder/

rcler to induce a more reasonable attitude-      This pressureffi 11 take the form of withholding supplies ordered in thiscountry by Roumania, the refusal of export licences, andthe withdrawal oi oners made for the amendment of the clearing agreement.      No concessions will be made toSoumania unless she takes the necessary measures to enablethe friendly oil companies to export to any destinationthey desire.    Certain facilities will on the other handbe offered to the Roumanian Government for the use of a proportion of the proceeds of oil sales to the United.kingdom , for the purchase of armaments in third countries,provided our requirements are met.      Proposals designedto reduce the price of Roumanian oil while the Danubere;r,ains frozen have been approved.ITALY.21. The proposals for a War Trade Agreement on thebasis of &quot;quantitative guarantees&quot; (see paragraph 26 oflast week&quot; s report) have been rejected by the ItalianGovernment.      Reproached by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador withturning down constructive proposals for an alleviation of contraband control without suggesting any alternative,mCount Giano - somewhat to the alarm of his advisers -suggested a State guarantee against the re-export to theenemy of goods admitted by the Contraband Control.      Thisproposal, which presents certain obvious disadvantages, isnow under examination,22. Meanwhile,  as the negotiations in regard tothe clearing and shipping agreements were also hanging fire,th-e Master of the Rolls returned, to London for consultations.23- Indications are not wanting that Sir P.Loraine&apos;communication on the subject of sea-borne coal from Germany&apos;* ee paragraph 27 of last week&apos;s report) has convinced then authorities that we mean business.      But it now seems clear that we shplbe obliged to take part at least of/

27. Official statistics published in Egypt show the result of the control of Egyptian cotton exports up toDecember 27th.      The position appears to he satisfactory.Exports to neutral countries adjacent to Germany have notbeen excessive, hut have been maintained at a normal level]and in spite of the fact that no cotton has &quot;been exported to Germany, Poland or Czechoslovakia since the outbreak ofwar. increased purchases by the United Kingdom,  India,Canada and France have enahled Egypt to export as much as70,000 bales more during the period Septemher 1 to December27, 1939 than during the corresponding period in 193o.IRAN/f the agricultural produce which Italy,  if her imports ofn from Germany are cut down, will no longer he ahle toplace in that country.2k-  Detailed negotiations over the new Clearing-Agreement are proceeding.25. So long as the peseta remains at its present level, it is probable that traders will continue to attemptdeals with this country on a &quot;barter &quot;basis.      It has &quot;beententatively suggested by our Delegation that where the purchaser on this side is His Majesty&apos;s Government,  suchdeals might be allowed and might he handled through the clearing.      The question of principle as well as thepossible modus operand! are being studied in relation to a specific proposal which was put &quot;before the Delegation.26. We have not yet heard that the modified. war trade proposals have been put to the Spanish Government.In the meantime, a Franco-Spanish trade agreement has been signed and French wheat is already on its way to Spain.This agreement carries no War Trade provisions.EGYPT.

28c    Reports show that Germany is active in securingrranian products,  in particular cotton and skins.29-    The wolfram position has been thoroughlyreviewed,  and it is clear that in spite of local transport and other difficulties there will he a considerable excess over allied needs.    Consideration is being given to thequestion of inducing the United States to attach this excess,under as strong control as possible, as security for anyloan which the Chinese Government may be able to negotiate.sovRUSSIA.30.    The Soviet vessel &quot;Selenga&quot;. bound from Manilato Viadivostock, has been intercepted and taken to Hong Kongfor contraband examination.    The cargo includes 1,190 m.tons of wolfram ore,  596 m.  tons of antimony ore and 98 tonsof tin .      Apart from the possibility that goods forViadivostock may ultimately reach Germany,  the question ofthe treatment to be accorded to this cargo on a Soviet vesselbound for a Soviet port is clearly one of considerable political importance.GONTRABAMD   CONTROL.31.    During the week ending 20th January,  80 newcases of. ships were dealt with and 33 previous cases,  inregard to whose cargoes or items thereof enquiries had beencompleted, were disposed of.32.    In 52 cases entire cargoes were released., either on first consideration or after enquiries,33-    The system under which advance copies of manifest:cf cargoes are received and considered before the shipsarrival at ports in this country resulted, during the week under review, in 38 cases being so dealt with and in 25 cases

ships concerned being released by the Committee .-b.feet merely to the formal checking of the originalInifests on their arrival at the Control Bases.      Inedition to these immediate releases,  in 10 other caseshe Committeefs decision to release was given within 5 daysi less of the arrival of ships at the Control Bases.&apos; ICERTS.3a.    Since the introduction of the Navicert system3,18/4. applications for navicerts have been received up to tie 20th January.      Of these 9? 530 have been granted and553 refused, while 3? 271 are pending or have not yet beenresented for consideration.EXPORTS.35.    During the week 13 ships have been examined athe Control Bases and released without reference to i.i.e.V7\ ,have been reported, h of which were released afterinvestigation;    the cargoes on the remaining 3 are beingdetained pending enquiries,      A Finnish ship containing armsor Finland was quickly released.36.    Applications for exemption are being received in large numbers and during the week 33 export passes were granted.      Over 200 applications were refused.      In a great number of cases the applicant claimed that the contractalleged to have been made before the date of the Order inCouncil was an uF.O. B.&quot; one, but that payment had in factteen made after November 27th.      The Committee refuses such applications since the purchaser was not compelled under the&quot;terms to make any payment before delivery.37.    In answer to a request for an explanation ofthe refusal of an application for exemption, the Committeereplied that it is not its practice to give detailed reasonsf the decisions taken on such applications.-orAn/!

38.    An application on behalf of the Shanghai power company to import machinery of enemy origin valued  26,700,which if granted would result in  37,920 accruing to british manufacturers which had been refused by the Committee on 10thJanuary, v/as reconsidered and granted.39.    The Committee has approved the importation ofarms of enemy origin into Afghanistan and has agreed con-ess si ons as regards export control of the trade between theGreek mainland and Greeic Islands.


</content>
</cab>
