<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/53/0 images: 342-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS THE  PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTY 1 S. GOVERNMENT ) .CABINET    51  (26).iieeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10,Downing Street, S.W.I. , on THURSDAY,September 16th, 1926, at p.m.Stenographic Notes of a Meeting between .HlsHajestyrs Ministers and the Mining Association,,held on Monday,  September 6th,  1926, at,15 pom.(CP. 326 (26)    -    Circulated herewith).Correspondence between the Mines De partmentand the Mining Association.(CP.  327 (26)    -    Circulated herewith).Copy of letter from the Chancellor of theExchequer to the Chairman of the mining association.(CP. 328 (26)    -   Circulated herewith).Copy No.AGENDUM.COAL SITUATION.(Signed)M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary,  Cabinet.U Gardens, S.W.I.ept ember,  1926.
IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC i.iAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .Copy No.CABINET    51  (26).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.1., onTHURSDAY, September 16th, 1926,. at 3.0 pom.PRESENT:-The Right Hon.. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (In the Chair).Hon.it Cave, G .C.1.1.G.,lancellor.Hon.liam Joynson-Hicks,Secretary ofor Home Affairs.Hon.ing Worthington-Evans,,E.,M.P., Secretarye for War.Hon.bridgeman, M.P.,ord of the Admiralty.Son,iGilmour, Bt.,D.S.O. ,2cretary for Scotland.ion.iur Steel-Haitland,Minister of Labour.iVe Right Hon.. L   W.S. Churchill, C.H.,K.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C.lf.G.,LI.P., Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliff e-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E., first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.P.,Attorney-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:Lt.-Col. The Right Hon*G.R.  Lane-Fox, M.P.,Secretary, Mines Department.(For Conclusion 1).&apos;A- Harikey, G.C.B..............,..................  Secretary
L*      The Cabinet had before them the following documents relating to the Coal Situation:-Stenographic Notes of a Meeting between his Majesty&apos;s Ministers and the mining association, held on Monday, September 6th,1926, at 3.15 p.m, .     (CP. 326 (26)).Correspondence between the Mines department and the Mining Association.    (CP. 327 (26))*Copy of letter from the Chancellor of theExchequer- to the Chairman of the mining association.      (CP. 328  (26)).Copy of letter from the Chairman of theMining Association to the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer.      (CP. 329 (26)).The Chancellor of the Exchequer gave theCabinet a full account of the present positionin regard to the coal strike,  and of what had occurred since the Cabinet last met.      The salient features were as follows:-    the continuation ofthe strike;    the increasing gravity of its effects on trade and the consequential menace to the exchanges not only to-day, but even afterthe strike and before manufacture has reachedthe stage of output;    the inevitable discomfortto the whole community when cold weathersupervenes;    the various stages of the negotiations the first approach from the Miners&apos; Federation;the warning of the Mining Association to theGovernment that they had told the Miners&apos;Federation that they would not again enter on national negotiations;    the offer of the Minersto enter into a national conference on thebasis of &quot;reduction of labour costs&quot; and theirprivate assurances that these included discussionof wages and hours;    the subsequen-   interview with the :.ine Owners, and their final refusal,after consultation with the districts,  to enterinto national negotiations.
There was general agreement on the partof the Cabinet that it was essential to clear- upthe present position by some action designed ifpossible to secure an early return to work onprovisionalthe basis of/district settlements, or in thelast resort by demonstrating unmistakablywhere the onus of refusal of a reasonable lay.The President of the Board of Trade developed to the Cabinet a plan for securing these objects,which had been discussed at the Goal Committeethat morning     (Appendix).      This scheme met with general approval except on one point,, namely,as to what the sanction should be in theevent of a refusal on the part of the owners tocarry out the award of the proposed arbitral tribunal.-     The suggestion was made that,instead of the President of the Board of Trade&apos; proposal (involving legislation),  that in that event the owners should, be precluded from taking advantage of the Eight Hours Act, except on condition that they carried out the award,  it wouldbe better to make the award of the arbitral tribunal conclusive,  on the lines of the trade board legislation.      Objections were raised tothis proposal and the matter was felt to requir efurther exploration.The ^rime Minister expressed his intentionof at once seeing ,r. Evan Williams, the Chairmanof the Mining Association,, with a view to ascertaining whether in all the circumstances, andin view of the vital national inte.ests involved,the Association would not waive their objections
to some form of National settlement combined with District Settlements.After a prolonged examination of thewhole question, the Cabinet agreed:-(a) That the conduct of further and immediatenegotiations should be left in thehands of the Prime Minister, and such his colleagues as he chose to associatewith him, and that these negotiations should be conducted on the basis of thePresident of the Board of Trade1s scheme(Appendix), subject to further and immediate examination of this scheme by the Cabinet Coal Committee, andsubject in particular to -(b) Further detailed examination of thequestion of the sanction by the coal committee, which was asked to report further to the Prime Minister on thisquestion.
2.      The attention of the Cabinet was called,as a matter of urgency, to a telegram from . the British Minister in Peking, No. 314,  dated(26),^5,       15th September,  1926, and a telegram of September13th, from Hong Kong, advocating naval actionagainst Canton to close the ports of Canton andSwatow.      The Cabinet were informed that theproposals contained in these telegrams werebeing discussed by an Interdepartmental Committee.The Cabinet agreed:-&apos;That if a decision was urgently required,the Prime Minister should summon suchMinisters as were within reach of London,and that they should be empowered to takea decision on behalf of the Cabinet.hitehall Gardens, s.Vf.l.16th September,  1926.
E T(26) Zli.APPENDIX.COPY NOCABINET.COMMITTEE ON REPORT OF ROYAL COMMISSIONON THE COAL INDUSTRY.THE COAL NEGOTIATIONS.Memorandum by the President of the Board ofTrade. &apos;In order to decide on the next step in the coalnegotiations,  let us first be clear what our objectsare and then decide what,  in the  conditions -existingto-day, is our best course.      Our objects are these:-1.   To secure a rapid and general return to work.2,    To secure a fair and economic settlement.3.    To maintain the prestige of the Government.This last is necessary not merely from a political point of view but also in order that the Governmentmay be able to act effectively at any time.What is the real position to-day?1.     We have made a fair proposal to both sides.     We have laid down in general terms what we think s&apos; ould be the relation between a National Agreement and DistrictSettlements,      V.e believe t at these proposals afford thebest way of arriving at a fair settlement and promoting the efficiency of the industry.      These proposals confromto the recommendations of the Royal Commission.2.      Our proposals  ..ave in fact been rejected by both theMiners and the Mine-owners.      It is true that the Minershave not actually rejected the proposals in terms sincethe Chancellor&apos;s letter.     They naturally waited for the
dOwner a to do this for them.     But there is little doubtthat if v,e succeeded in getting a conference the Miners&apos;Federation would refuse our terms&apos;,5,     The Miners have been unreasonable all through,4,     The Owners have, on the whole, been reasonable uptill the last few weeks.      Their refusal to accept any formof National Settlement is unreasonable, but we must face the fact that it is very definite.5,     We have lost that control of the conduct of affairs which we should have retained, if we had insisted on theOwners agreeing to our terras before we passea the eight hours Act.In these circumstances what action should we take?;/e could of course coerce the Owners now, but this is opento the following objectionsI.     We might find that after great difficulty and delaywe had coerced the Owners into accepting something whichthe Miners&apos;  Federation then rejected,      This would put usin a foolish and impotent position,2,     It is doubtful how far we should have public  support,think public opinion is still supoorting the Owners, notecause the public think the owners wise or reasonable,at because they believe that Snu.th and Cook are hopelesseople to deal with and that any National Agreement made by then, would only be a basis of future trouble.There would be great deify in securing a general returno work, and there would be a hold-up of a sectional returno v;ork in the various districts.The  Bill        ch we should have to carry would be a
difficult Bill; and many of our party would be unwillingsupoorters, because they would. mistrust the Bill (a)on its merits and (b) on its results.It would of course be possible, for us to do nothing;but this would be very damaging politically.      We shouldbe admitting defeat at the hands of the Owners on an issue where we still believe that we are right and theyare wrong.Is it not possible to find a middle course whichwill secure the three objects       which I have set out at thebeginning of this memorandum, and which will regain forthe Government some control over the conduct of thenegotiations?      I suggest tentatively the following course:^1.     We should say that we have made proposals which webelieve to be sound, and which conform to the Report ofthe Royal Commission;    but both sides have shown themselvesunwilling to accept our proposals.&apos;     We cannot compel mento work or owners to operate their pits,2,     The great object is a settlement by agreement, and provided it is a rapid, fair and lasting settlement itdoes not matter at all in what way it is attained.3.     We think that both sides have been unreasonable; butthe Miners&quot; leaders have been far more unreasonable than theOwners; and the impossible attitude adopted by Smith and Cookwas largely responsible for the Owners&apos; refusal to consider aNational Agreement.4.     We have always held, as the Royal Commission found,that District Settlements are necessary.      We - gree withthe Royal Commission that District Settlements shouldbe based on general principles nationally agreed andshould probably be subject to a national review.
5      Facing the position as it is to-day, the best course is for each district to negotiate its own DistrictSettlement.      This need not and shall not preclude arational review of the settlements when they are made.If the parties cannot agree,  the Government representingthe nation, has the right and the duty to see, as faras it can, that  the settlement is a fair one.6.     The Government would set up an independent tribunal to which miners dissatisfied with a local settlementmay appeal, but it would be a condition of appealingto that tribunal that they should go back to work onthe best terms they can obtain by district negotiations.70     If the arbitral tribunal supports the settlement,which in case of dispute would in effect be the ownersbest offer, the Government would take no further action and public opinion would be satisfied that the miners in that district had got a fair deal.      If,  on the otherhand, the tribunal made an award giving the miners in a district better terms than the owners had offered,  theowners would be precluded from taking advantage of the eight Hours Act,  except on condition that they carriedout the award.8.      If the parties agree upon an arbitral body otherthan that set up by the Government,  that  body wouldtake the place of a Government Tribunal.     A  centralBeard of Review would have been established, and.theGovernment could drop out.(Intld.)    P.C-L.14.9,26.

</content>
</cab>
