<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/36 images: 408-415</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  April 1940.SECRET. Copy No. AW.M. (40)91st Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 91  (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Saturday, April 13, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The    Right   Hon.    Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Sir FIorace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.Th&amp; Right Horn Anthony EdeN) M.P.,wA fTfl i rp -The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet - Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General  Sir  W.  Edmund  Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21145].b
WAR CABINET 91 (40).Contents.minute no.                                      Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     ..................     305Royal Air Force activity.Attacking of Stavanger aerodrome.2      The Naval Situation..................     305Naval activity.Air attack on Narvik.British landing at Narvik.Occupation of the Faroe Islands.3      Operations in Norway...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     3064      Western Front ...      ...      ...........       ...       ...     306Action if the Netherlands or Belgium is invaded.5      Italy     .....................      ...     306Probable intentions.6      Sweden ...      .:................      ...     307Attitude of the Swedish Government.7      Supreme War Council ...............     307Meetings of the Supreme War Council: Anglo-French Secretariat.8      War Cabinet Arrangements ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     307
The Air 1.   The Secretary of State, for Air said that the Royal air situation.;,        Force had had rather an unlucky day.(Previous ,. ; Early on the previous morning an aircraft of the CoastalEeference:        Command had reported two German battle-cruisers and one cruiserW.M. (40) 89th  in ;a position 140 miles North-West of Horns Reef.   It had been conclusions,      decided to carry out a bombing attack on a heavy scale and a forceMinute l.)        consisting of 23 Blenheims, 45 Wellingtons and 24 HampdensE.A.F. activity.   (02 aircraft in all) had been despatched.   Owing, however, to badvisibility over the sea, the target had not been found.    TheFlampdens had sighted and attacked two German destroyers, butthe results were not known.   This formation had then flown to thecoast and had sighted two cruisers in christians and Fjord.   Whileflying up the Fjord, they had been attacked by Messerschmitts, andas a result of the engagement, 5 Hampdens had been shot downand one more had failed to reach home.   Two Messerschmitts hadbeen shot down, and probably a third.A force of six Wellingtons had run out of the clouds and had found themselves over Stavanger. They had been attacked by german lighters and a running fight had ensued for 100 miles.Three Wellingtons had been shot down and a fourth had failed toreach home. Two, or possibly three, Messerschmitts had been shot down.As a result of the operation, therefore, we had lost 10 bombers and the Germans had lost certainly four, and probably six fighters.While weather conditions over the sea had been bad, there hadbeen good visibility over the land. From our point of view, the weather conditions could hardly have been more unfavourable.The Secretary of State said that he felt that there were one ortwo points regarding the orders given to the bomber force which required clearing up; as for example whether the orders given were sufficiently precise to stop the aircraft going into the Fjords, if the weather was unfavourable and whether the scale of attack had beenout of proportion to the target. He hoped the War Cabinet woulddefer any discussion until he had had time to receive fuller reports.Attacking of The First Lord of the Admiralty hoped that the Royal AirStavanger Force would continue to harass Stavanger.   He suggested that aaerodrome. succession of small-scale attacks would gi^eatly hold up the establish-ment and development of the air base by the Germans. He thoughtthat it was of the greatest importance that the Germans shouldnot be left undisturbed.The Chief of the Air Staff said that the matter was under examination, and that he would report on it to the Military Co-ordination Committee at their meeting that afternoon.The Secretary of State for Air, referring to a question by thePrime Minister at the Meeting of the War Cabinet on the previousmorning, said that incendiary bombs were unlikely to prove effective against modern all-metal aircraft.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The Naval 2.   The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the Fleet wasSituation. operating between Trondhjem and Narvik.     Destroyers working(Previous close in shore had been loudly cheered by the inhabitants of someEeference-. of the villages. A destroyer patrol had been established at theW.M. (40) 89th entrance to Narvik.Conclusions,Minute 2.)Naval activity.Air attack on Aircraft from H.M.S. Furious had attacked the German shipsNarvik. in Narvik on the previous day.   Five destroyers and 11 merchant ships had been sighted. Two of the destroyers had been hit oneof them severely.[21145]b 2
British landing at Narvik.Occupation ofthe Faroe&apos;Islands.One hundred and forty of the crew of H.M.S. Hardy hadeffected a landing at Ballenger in the Vest Fjord and would presumably endeavour to make contact with the Norwegian forces.Contact had been made with a Norwegian submarine in VestFjord. The cruisers Glasgow and Sheffield, with destroyers, had reported that they were at Aalesund, which was in Norwegianhands. The nearest Norwegian troops were at Andalsnes, the railhead at the head of the Romsdal Fjord.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that a German pocketbattleship had been reported at Aalesund. One of our ships,however, had now reached Aalesund and had found this reportto be unfounded. The First Lord proceeded to give details of theships proceeding to Narvik.A report bad now been received from the submarine Truant ofthe attack made by her on 9th April on a cruiser of the Koln class.It was believed that this attack had been successful. Particularswere given of other attacks carried out by submarines in theSkagerrak. A torpedo attack had been carried out by 20 Skuasagainst ships in Bergen; a munition store had been blown up, but no other successes were claimed. All our aircraft, except one, had returned safely.The occupation of the Faroe Islands had been carried outsuccessfully.It was now believed that the cruisers koln and Emden had been sunk.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Operations in norway.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 90thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. In connection with the preceding Minute, a discussion tookplace regarding possible operations in Norway. A record of this discussion, and of the conclusions reached by the War Cabinet, is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Western Front.Action if theNetherlands or belgium is invaded.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 90thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theprevious evening he had telegraphed to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador,Paris, instructing him to make the communication to the FrenchGovernment agreed upon at the meeting of the War Cabinet heldin the afternoon. (Telegrams 79, &quot;80 and 81 DIPP.) Atelegram had now been received from Sir Ronald Campbell (No. 107)reporting that M. Reynaud agreed in principle to our proposals,both as regards the air action and as regards the Royal marine operation, in the event of Germany invading Holland and/or belgium. M. Reynaud undertook to give a definite reply that day after consulting his colleagues. No answer had yet been given byM. Reynaud to the question we had put to him on the subject of theproposed joint communication by the British and French Govern-ments to the Belgian Government.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Italy.probable intentions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 89thConclusions,Minute 6.)5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said thatMr. R. A. Butler, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,, liad had a long conversation the previous day ata luncheon party with Signor Bastianini, the Italian Ambassador,who had assured him that we need expect no &quot; decision definitive.&quot;
Sweden.Attitude of theSwedishGovernment.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 89thConclusions,Minute 5.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said thatM. Bohemann, Secretary-General of the Swedish Foreign Office,had called at the Foreign Office the previous day and had stated thathe was authorised to give a definite assurance in the name of theSwedish Government of their decision to resist any german demands for facilities calculated to infringe Swedish sovereignty,and a fortiori that they would resist any attack that Germany mightlaunch against their country.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Supreme WarCouncil.Meetings of theSupreme WarCouncil: Anglo-FrenchSecretariat.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 77thConclusions,Minute 1.)7. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (40) 124) relating tothe proposal made at the Sixth Meeting of the Supreme WarCouncil that the Council should hold more frequent and regular meetings, and that the question of the formation of an AlliedSecretariat should be examined.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the Foreign Secretary should approach theFrench Government on the lines suggested in paragraph 5of his Memorandum.War Cabinet 8.   It was agreed that the War Cabinet should meet at 11-30Arrangements.    Qn the following day (Sunday, the 14th April).Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,April 13, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
