<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/1/2 images: 37-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

Printed for the War Cabinet.  September 1939.

SECRET.

W.M. (39). 2nd Conclusions.

Copy No.

TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.

It is requested that special eare may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.

WAR CABINET 2 (39).

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1, on Monday, September 4, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.

Present :

The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).

The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.

Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon. Lord Chatfield, Minister for Coordination of Defence.

The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha, M.P., Secretary of State for War.

The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt, M.P., Lord Privy Seal.

The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.

The    Right    Hon.    Winston S.

Churchill, M.P., First Lord of the

Admiralty. The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood.

M.P., Secretary of State for Air. The   Right   Hon.   Lord Hankey,

Minister without Portfolio.

The following were also present :

The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P., Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs (Items 1-10).

The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (Item 11).

The Right Hon. Walter E. Elliot, M.P., Minister of Health (Item 11).

Sir Horace J. Wilson, Permanent Secretary to the Treasury.

Admiral of the Fleet Sir Dudley Pound, First Sea Lord and Chief of the Naval Staff (Items 1-10).

The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home Department and Minister for Home Security (Item 11).

The Right Hon. John Colville, M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland (Item 11).

The   Right   Hon.   Ernest Brown,

M.P., Minister of Labour (Item 11). Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril Newall,

Chief of the Air Staff (Items 1-10). General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,

Chief of the Imperial General Staff

(Items 1-10).

Brigadier J. N. Kennedy, Deputy Director of Military Operations, War Office (Items 1-10).

Secretariat : Sir Edward Bridges. Major-General H. L. Ismay. Colonel L. C. Hollis, R.M. Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N. Mr. W. D. Wilkinson. Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.


WAR CABINET 2 (39).

Contents.

Minute

No.                                   Subject. Page

1 Turkey........................ 11

2 Italy........................ 11

3 The Far Eastern Situation  ...      ... ...... ... 11

4 Attitude of the Dominions 

South Africa   ...        ...        ...        ...        ...        ... ... 12

Eire......... ............... 12

5 Report on the Air Situation 

Operations on 3rd September ...        ...        ...        ... ... 12

Operations contemplated on 4th September    ...        ... ... 12

Inter-Allied Operations in Support of Poland ...        ... ... 12

6 Naval Situation 

Sinking of Steamship Athenia and Steamship Blairbeg ... 13

Convoy System          ...        ...        ...        ...        ... ... 13

7 Army Situation 

A.D.G.B. and Field Force   ;............ ... 13

Military Situation in Poland   ...        ...        ...        ... ... 13

8 Arrangements to provide Ministers outside the War

Cabinet with Information      ...      ...      ... ... 13

9 Purchase of Neutral Shipping       ...      ...      ... ... 14

10 Financial Measures 

Exchange Control       ...        ...        ...        ...        ... ... 14

Gold Reserves...        ...        ...        ...        ...        ... ... 14

11 National Registration 

Food Rationing          ...        ...        ...        ...        ... ... 14

12 Closing of Theatres and Cinemas   ...      ...      ... ... 14

13 Appointment of Home Policy Committee ...      ... 15

OK


11

W.M. 2 (39).

Turkey. 1.   THE War Cabinet was informed that the Turks were

(Previous        increasing their demands for financial help, and that until these Eeference:       demands were met they were unlikely to sign the Franco-Anglo-W.M. (39), 1st   Turkish Agreement.   There were other ways by which we could Conclusions,      offer them help, but the crux of the question was their insistence on Minute 8.)       a gold loan.  It was not thought that the French, notwithstanding their ample gold reserves, would help us in this matter, although it was to their interests as much as to our own that we should keep Turkey within our orbit.   It was pointed out that in two or three months&apos; time Polish resistance might be broken and that this would be followed by a long period of stalemate on the western front.  The only door by which we could get at Germany would be through Turkey and Roumania.   It was vital that the conclusion of the Turkish Agreement should not be held up owing to financial considerations, although we should, of course, make the best arrangement possible.

The War Cabinet agreed 

(a) that on military as well as political grounds it was of the utmost importance to conclude the Agreement with Turkey as soon as possible;

(&amp;) that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, in consultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, should arrange for the despatch of a telegram to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Ankara explaining the difficulties regarding a gold loan to Turkey, and the various ways in which we could afford help to Turkey, and instructing him to ascertain tlhe terms on which Turkey could be induced to sign the agreement.

Italy. 2.   A short discussion took place on the position of Italy, of

which the main points were as follows : There was good reason to believe that Mussolini was as anxious to avoid becoming involved in war against us as he was to keep out of a war with Germany. If we issued an ultimatum demanding that he should show his hand as a neutral, it would merely throw him into the arms of Germany. Italy (had further to go now than she had in 1914 before sne would be induced to throw in her lot with us, desirable as this ultimate object might be, with all its consequences regarding fleet dispositions in the Mediterranean- and the ability to tighten the blockade on Germany. Any rationing scheme to be imposed on Italy would require tactful handling. When the Ministry of Economic Warfare took up the question of rationing Italy, due regard would have to be given to the political aspect.

The War Cabinet took note of this statement, and agreed that, before any plan to be drawn up by the Ministry of Economic Warfare for rationing Italy was put into operation, the implications from the political point of view should be fully considered.

The Far Eastern 3. Reference was made to the position of Japan and to the Situation.        need for ensuring her neutrality.

The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs explained that certain delays had occurred in handing over the four men accused of terrorism to the local Court, but that he expected that they would be handed over before long. Any suggestion of the revival of our Alliance with Japan, even as a long-term objective, would need to be very carefully considered from the point of view of its effect upon tine United States of America. Tentative soundings had been made in Washington with a view to effecting a comprehensive agreement with Japan with regard to the position in China. The War Cabinet took note of this statement.

[19967]


12

Attitude of the Dominions.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (89), 1st Conclusions, Minute 5.)

South Africa.

Eire.

4. A telegram from the High Commissioner in South Africa was read out showing that the Union Cabinet had split on the neutrality question, that it was probable that Parliament would be dissolved, and that a general election would take place.

Eire had declared her neutrality, and her attitude was set out in a message that had appeared in The Times that morning. No more recent information was available. In this connection, the importance of the availability of South Irish ports, e.g., Berehaven, as a base for naval forces, was stressed.

Report on the Air Situation.

(Previous Reference:  W.M. (39), 1st Conclusions, Minute 2.)

Operations on 3rd September.

Operations contemplated on 4th September.

Inter-Allied Operations in Support of Poland.

5. The Chief of the Air Staff made a statement on the operations on the previous night under two headings : (a) operations against German ships reported in the North Sea, (b) dropping of leaflets. As to the latter, during the night aircraft had distributed propaganda leaflets over Hamburg, Bremen and the Ruhr. One aircraft was at present missing. They had encountered no fighters, and only ineffective anti-aircraft fire. There had been considerable confusion caused by reports from different sources in Holland of the passage of aircraft said to be approaching Great Britain, and some of these might have been aircraft returning from dropping leaflets. Their courses had been studied, and it was certain that they had not flown over Holland. Further reconnaissances had been ordered for to-day, to discover the whereabouts of the German Fleet, and bombers were standing by. The Advanced Air Striking Force was in France, and nearly ready to operate, though at reduced intensity.

The War Cabinet took note of this statement.

The Chief of the Air Staff said that he had been presesd by the French to employ the Air Striking Force in collaboration with the French Army. He was opposed to any such action at a time when the French Army was not undertaking active operations. It was important to conserve the resources of the Air Striking Force, so that it would be ready to meet any great emergency, such as heavy air attack on this country, or an attempted break-through in France.

The First Lord of the Admiralty pointed out that the main German effort was concentrated against Poland, and every means possible should be employed to relieve the pressure. This could be done by operations against the Siegfried Line, which was at present thinly held. The burden of such operations would fall on the French Army and our Air Force.

It was generally agreed that a combined plan for an operation against Germany to relieve the pressure on Poland was a vital necessity, and that the Chiefs of Staff should make immediate contact with General Gamelin, with a view to concerting the action of the French and British Forces. It was thought that a telegram should be despatched forthwith to General Gamelin, suggesting that the Chief of the Air Staff and the Chief of the Imperial General Staff should come over to France to meet him that afternoon for a preliminary discussion. This meeting would serve to discover the French Army Plan, and the best means by which our Air Striking Force could collaborate could then be devised. After the Chiefs of Staff had conferred with General Gamelin, it would probably be desirable for the Prime Minister to meet M. Daladier, so that the Inter-Allied policy for the conduct of the war in the next few months could be settled. These meetings would be the first steps towards the setting up of the permanent machinery for the conduct of the war.   In the meanwhile, the French should be assured that we were


13

W.M. 2 (39).

more than willing to co-operate with our air forces in the coordinated plan, but that we did not propose to undertake sporadic bombing which would lead to no permanent military result, but would cause unnecessary loss of aircraft. The French should be asked to conform, and not to employ their air force in the manner which they had suggested to the Chief of the Air Staff until a plan had been agreed.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

(1) That the Chiefs of Staff should at once see General Gamelin,

and should discuss matters with him on the lines set out above:*

(2) That as soon as the Chiefs of Staff had agreed upon the

inter-allied plan of operations, the question of an early meeting of the Supreme War Council should be considered.

Naval Situation. q The First Lord of the Admiralty reported that steamship Sinking of A thenia, outward bound with 300 Americans on board had been sunk S/S Athenia 200 miles North-Westof Ireland at 2 p.m.on the 3rd September, 1939. and S/S It was understood that the passengers and crew were in the ship&apos;s

Blahbeg. boats.  Two destroyers were hastening to the rescue and should be

near the scene.   The occurrence should have a helpful effect as

regards public opinion in the United States.

The steamship Blairbeg had been sunk 70 miles North-West of

Ireland.   H.M.S. Renown had detached her anti-submarine escort

of two destroyers to the rescue. Convoy System.       The War Cabinet were informed that the routeing of merchant

ships was in force, but the convoy system had not yet been started. Reference was made to the statement in the Joint Anglo-French

Declaration that we should abide by the Submarine Protocol of 1936.

Germany was one of the Powers which had adhered to the Protocol.

Army Situation. 7. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported on the A.D.G.B. and position as regards the air defences of Great Britain and the date Field Force.       f arrival in France of the Field Force.

Military situa- The Chief of the Imperial General Staff gave the War Cabinet

tion in Poland, a picture of the Military situation in Poland, as he saw it. The concentration of as many as 32 German divisions in Slovakia had come as a surprise. The country between Slovakia and Poland was, extremely difficult for military operations, and presented administrative problems of great magnitude. If the Germans were able to carry out their plan, the Poles would have to face an attack in enormous strength from the South.

The Chief of the Imperial General Staff expressed the personal view that the crushing of Poland by Germany in a few weeks was most improbable.

Arrangements 8.   The Prime Minister raised the question of supplying

to provide information as to the situation to Ministers who were not members

Ministers out- of tihe War Cabinet.  One suggestion would be that weekly appre-

side the War ciations on the situation should be prepared by the Chiefs of Staff.

Cabinet with Another suggestion was that occasional Meetings should be held

Information. of Ministers to inform them of the position.

(Previous Both these suggestions met with approval, and the War Cabinet

Reference: agreed 

W.M. (39), 1st That the Prime Minister should make such arrangements

Conclusions, as he thought fit in this matter.

Minute 1.)--

* The telegram despatched to General Gamelin is attached as Annex to these Conclusions.


14

Purchase of 9.   The Secretary of State for War raised the question whether

Neutral action was being taken, as in the last War, to purchase neutral

Shipping. shipping.

The War Cabinet agreed 

That the attention of the President of the Board of Trade should be drawn to this matter.

Financial 10.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that Exchange

Measures. Control had now been established, and that it was intended tq Exchange establish the Dollar rate at just about 4 Dollars to the Pound. His Control. Majesty&apos;s Government would now be the market, and would say at

what rate we would buy and sell Dollars. If the Pound was kept at a figure below 4 Dollars, we might exasperate the United States and there would be a risk of a sharp rise in prices.

Gold Reserves. j7^ Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it was proposed

shortly to take certain steps in regard to our gold reserves, which he explained to the War Cabinet. These steps would be taken under powers conferred by Finance Regulations made under the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act.

The War Cabinet took note of this statement.

National Registration.

Food

Rationing.

11. The War Cabinet had before them a Joint Memorandum by the Minister of Health and the Secretary of State for Scotland (CP. 192 (39)), in which a decision was asked for on certain matters arising in connection with the National Registration Bill now before the House of Commons.

The War Cabinet were informed that the salient points were :  i

(a) the recommendation of the Minister of Health and the Sec-

retary of State for Scotland that National Registration Day should be fixed for the Friday in the fifth week from the present date, viz., the 6th October:

(b) the recommendation of the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lan-

caster that Food Rationing (which was an essential feature of Food Control) should be brought into force in three weeks from the present date.

The suggestion was made that it might be possible to bring National Registration and Food Rationing into operation simultaneously, in which event the introduction of Food Rationing would be greatly simplified. After discussion it was agreed that Food Rationing could not be postponed long enough to make the simultaneous introduction of the two measures possible.

The Minister of Health informed his colleagues that it was not his intention to make any reference to the question of food rationing during the passage of the National Registration Bill.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

(i) that National Registration Day should be fixed for the

Friday in the fifth week from the present date, viz., the 6th October:

(ii) to consider at a later date the separate question of when Food Rationing should be introduced.

Closing of 12.   It was suggested to the War Cabinet that the closing of

Theatres and theatres and cinemas, if continued indefinitely, would have a bad Cinemas. effect on public morale.    There was no light relief to be obtained

from the programmes now being given by the B.B.C. Later on, when troops came home on leave, they would expect to find entertainment provided for them.


15 W.M. 2 (39).

It was pointed out that, in the uncertainties of the present stage of the war, it would not be justifiable to encourage crowds to gather in public places, particularly in Central London. On the other hand, it was suggested that there was a case for permitting places of entertainment to open in the hours of daylight, and possibly also in the suburbs after dark.

The Home Secretary was invited to consider the matter in consultation with the Secretary of State for Air, the Police Authorities, and the B.B.C.

Appointment of 13. The Prime Minister suggested that, in addition to the Home Polioy Home Security Committee, a Second Committee of the War Committee. Cabinet (which might be called the Home Policy Committee) should be set up to consider all domestic questions which required the cooperation of more than one Department or which were of such importance that they would otherwise call for consideration by the Cabinet. The Committee should have a wide discretion in dealing finally with questions on which agreement was reached, and should refer to the War Cabinet only such large questions of policy as required Cabinet sanction or questions on which they had been unable to reach agreement. The Home Policy Committee would deal with all the social services, including education, and other domestic topics such as the maintenance of trade and industry and agriculture. Perhaps the most important functions of the Committee would be in connection with the attitude of labour; it must be anticipated that considerable political importance would be attached throughout the war to the wage situation (especially in relation to the question of profits, cost of living, &amp;c).

Acute questions would also arise in connection with any measure for the conscription of labour that might be decided upon.

The Prime Minister said that the new Committee would, in fact, deal with all questions affecting the Home Front other than the questions directly related to Civil Defence Which would be dealt with by the Home Security Committee.

In a word, the Committee would be given the task of considering the effect on general War Cabinet policy of any new domestic requirement that might arise.

There would be work for the Committee in the near future in connection with the issue of the Regulations under the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act. Such Regulations ought to be examined by a body with a general viewpoint.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

To appoint a Home Policy Committee consisting of the following : 

The Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair),

The Lord Chancellor.

The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security.

The Secretary of State for Scotland.

The President of the Board of Trade.

The President of the Board of Education.

The Minister of Health.

The Minister of Labour.

The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.

The Minister of Transport.

The Minister of Food.

The Minister of Information.

The Postmaster-General.

The Financial Secretary to the Treasury.

Richmond Terrace, S.W.I. September 4, 1939.


16

ANNEX.

(Most Secret.)

To be sent by War Office in cypher to Military A ttache in Paris.

FOLLOWING for General Gamelin

&apos;&apos; British War Cabinet are very desirous of co-operating at once in any effective military and air operations against the German forces on the Western Front. They therefore consider it vital that immediate agreement should be reached between the Franco-British Military and Air Authorities-as to the part which their respective forces are to play.

&apos;   The Chief of the Imperial General Staff and the Chief of the Air Staff will arrive in Paris this afternoon to discuss such arrangements with you personally. It is hoped that British Chiefs of Staff will be able to return here to-night with a view to placing immediate proposals before the British War Cabinet, and that similarly you will be able to place agreed proposals before your Government at once. Meanwhile the British War Cabinet trust that the French Air Force will refrain from any action until decisions have been reached as to the policy for the use of the Air Forces. It is hoped that this will be concerted as the result of this afternoon&apos;s meeting between yourself and the British Chiefs of Staff.&quot;

(Sighed)        H. L. ISMAY.

Approved by the Prime Minister 1 p.m. (Initialled)     H. L. I.

September 4, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
