<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/197/0 images: 50-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]                   Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1928.   -Copy No.    28CABINET.IRON AND  STEEL.              MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER  OF LABOUR.                     [Previous Paper CP.  239 (28).)    THE following is an attempt  to  consider the claim of the Iron andSteel Trade for safeguarding entirely on its  merits and to  suggest a lineof action.    The trade claim that  their existing capacity can produce the whole ofthe iron  and  steel  now  imported,  and  that, if they are  given  theopportunity of  making a substantial  part  of this, it will lead  to acheapening of their existing production by 10/- to 15/- per ton.    This may be true and some  reduction of their  costs  will obviouslyresult.  But it is not enough.   It is really absurd to imagine that  all theusers, of steel, from makers of heavy  machinery to  the small hardwaremanufacturer (many of them already pressed  by foreign competition), willnot raise a cry for protection in their turn a demand to which there canbe no logical refusal.  Already Mr. Morris is telling me that he could buy the whole engine of a Gowley car in the United States for less than hecan buy the steel in this country.    .    The main justification for the grant  or refusal  of  safeguarding will depend on  whether the industry will use the shelter so  given  as  anopportunity for reorganising itself or not.   It is no condemnation  of ironand  steel  makers  that they  have  difficulty in  reorganising.   But  thegeneral opinion (x)  is  that reconstruction is  necessary  not only  of  the plant (with possibly  two or  three  exceptions), but  also as regards the grouping of companies themselves.    (x) If there is any question of the truth of this opinion (and perhaps in any case),it would be advisable  to obtain a comprehensive statement of the state of the principalcompanies.  The statement should be of approximately the same bind as, say, Morgan&apos;S would require for considering a  merger.  It-  would require a first-class British accountantof the  calibre of  Sir W. McClintock, and the  best  available  consulting engineers,including preferably  a foreigner.    (J7995)SECRET.CP.  255 (28).
    One great obstacle to remodelling  plant  is of course the need for aising new capital  and the difficulty of getting it.  This will be dealtwith later.    Another difficulty has been  the unwillingness, as I am informed, ofthe industry to concentrate.  Of  course, there  must  be great difficulties involved in the complexity of  the  interests possessed by  different com-panies as was evident in the  Vickers-Arm strong case.  But the unwill-ingness goes  much beyond that, and in  some  cases has  amounted toindividualism run riot.    Still  more  short-sighted  and  still  less defensible  has  been  thejealousy of the chief deposit banks.   It has been a bar to  progress alikein the cotton trade and in the iron and steel  trade.  At any rate, my ownimpression  to this effect was confirmed  in each  case by a  most capableperson  of inside knowledge.   If  the banks would form a consortium todeal with the situation they could be an  invaluable influence for good.    At the present moment,  however, the stress of circumstances isforcing a change of attitude both on  some of  the iron and steel companies and on the Banks.   There is a greater readiness now than at any timehitherto for the Steel Companies to come together and for two or more ofthe Banks to co-operate in considering the possible fusion of companies with a view to facilitating the process.   The situation, that is  to  say, isripe.   A push from outside may have  a decisive effect.   On  the  otherhand, any promise of safeguarding or other  alleviation, which  may ease the pressure, will undoubtedly retard the whole movement and awake theold reactionary individualism.    I believe the above statements would be  amply justified on  investiga-tion.   But the points  are  so vital that  they should be put beyond doubt.It is  no use, however, to  question  witnesses before a large Committee.Statements made there are not the same as  statements  made outside.But valuable information could be  got  confidentially from some  of  theFinance Houses  and Accountants and  confirmed or modified by private conversation with interested parties.    If  and when  it is made  clear that the  above  description of  thesituation is true, I suggest that the proper course is :     (1.) For the Prime Minister to ask the Chairmen  of the Big Five tomeet him and to tell them frankly  that the system of private Bankingreally stands on trial according as  they use their position to-day: thatthey must agree together to treat  the situation as a national problem andto deal unitedly with the iron and steel Companies.(3)    (2) It will also be necessary to make it clear to them beyond possibility of doubtthat they will not stand to gain a penny piece from Government action.  They have-made  large loans (most of which, no doubt, they  have written  off) to&apos; the  Companies.In any sound  reconstruction these loans  will have to be scaled down like other liabilitiesor capital of many of the  Steel Companies.  The first reaction of  he Banks would nodoubt be to try and load the loss on  to  the Exchequer,  unless it is made quite clear tothem that this would not be possible.
     Before taking this  step it would doubtless be  wise to consult theGovernor of the Bank of England and one or two  other leading men inthe  City as to the best way of putting the matter before the five DepositBanks.     (2.) If the Banks assent to Government  action, a deputation shouldbe called of  the Iron and Steel Companies.  They would need  to be toldquite frankly that  they must  be prepared both to  amalgamate whereadvisable  and  to reorganise plant  where necessary.   They  should  beinformed that some measure of help analogous  to &quot; trade facilities &quot; willbe forthcoming to enable them to get fresh capital, but only (1)  if recon-struction is  agreed to and not otherwise, and (2) for purposes  of  a soundreconstruction  scheme.  Further,  unless  they  are willing  as a  body toagree  to reconstruct,  no  measure  of  safeguarding will be   considered at all.(3)     If  this  course is followed, care must be taken not  to involve theGovernment in  any way in deciding or suggesting what  amalgamationsare desirable.   The  complexities will be very great,(4) and a Governmentis not  fitted to deal  with  them.  The proper  people to deal with this are (1) the Companies themselves, (2)  the Deposit Banks,  as  their  help and  influence is essential, and possibly (3)  the Issue Houses or financiersof the type of Szarvasy, with whom the formation of mergers or the issueof new capital is part  of their regular business.  There may or may notbe a consortium of these elements to deal  with  the  situation.  It is not necessary to prejudge this point.  The part of the Government should, belimited (1) to pressing them to undertake the job  and (2) through someappointees to approve the  schemes submitted, both  on their technical(5)and  financial sides.    (*) Keconstruction can also be facilitated in other ways.  The question of stamp dutyis said still to require simplifying.  An amalgamation should also be given the benefitof any wear and tear allowances possessed by any constituent company.    (4) In some cases the physical separation of certain assets,  while desirable, may bevery  difficult.  In other cases connected interests have to be considered.   Some  companiesown  coal-mines:  others own or have an interest  in industries which  afford  an  outlet for the product.  One  important Works is itself  owned by a shipbuilding  Company.-Again, the various Companies which  would come into the same group differ enormouslyin their  shareholding, and debentures and other liabilities.   Furthermore, the present financial position of a concern may be no measure  of its earning power  as a member ofan amalgamation.  All these  difficulties can be surmounted, but they are not work fora Government.    (5) The technical side may  present difficulties.  It is obvious that if  Governmenthelp  is given to obtain capital for reconstruction, it  must be devoted to the most suitableplant and lay-out possible.  At present one iron master  asserts his  contempt for the plant of another.   When some of the existing  companies are amalgamated  no  doubtthere will be a pooling of ideas within the group.   But this does not take  us  the wholeway.   At  some stage in the process the Government will  almost  certainly have to-employ some  small technical body probably two British  engineers  and a  foreignerassociated with them.
    If such reconstructions are undertaken, then and only then is it acase for safeguarding.   The-reactions of a safeguarding measure should be worked out  meanwhile,  including the draft  of  a tariff  applicable  tomanufactures of iron  and steel;  the  exceptions, if  any, which must  bemade, and the consideration of the effect on agriculturists.                                                 (Int.)       A. S.-M.Ministry of Labour,   July 23, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
