<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/197/0 images: 89-124</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                                     7&apos;P,f/TYir.TJjffiMr ..IS .?H^g^FECTY^QF this BRIT ANN IMAJESTY^  GOVERNMENT.SECRET.                                              COPY NO  28__CP.267 (28)                                CABIN  EYT.                                Trade Outlook.                 Note by the  President of  the Board of  Trade.              I circulate,  for the  information of  my colleagues,  reports        which I have received from members of my  Advisory Council,        regarding the trade position and prospects.              There  is no improvement in the  general position.   Indeed        the position has somewhat  deteriorated, as  the  normal  seasonal        slackening  has  added  itself  to the previous slump in orders.              Almost the only  hopeful feature reported is the        increased activity in China.   Larger purchases have been made        in chemicals, textiles  and special steel.  Engines are being        ordered for river  boats on the Yangtse.   The volume of trade        may not be  great,  but the  relative improvement  is remarkable        and is an indication  of future possibilities.              In some trades the slackness  is a reflection of a world        depression.  In textiles,  both cotton and woollen, the hold        up in orders is almost universal,  and this  appears to  be  true        of shipbuilding as well.   In steel, on the  other hand,  reports        show  that foreign  firms are  well booked up  with orders.              The Board  of  Trade have been  trying, with  the assistance        of the Ministry of Labour, to collect and combine the  best        available material which will give an accurate  appreciation of        the present position,  and  which will serve  as the best basis  to   ---   make  a forecast for the future,   As  a result  I  attach  a        series of tables giving a  number of  indices of  productive and        commercial  activity.   Monthly or  quarterly averages of        1927  are taken  as  the basis  of comparison,    I  propose to keep        these tables up-to-date, and to circulate them  from  time  to        time.                                               P.C-L.        Board  of Trade.        10th  August, 1928.
  COKPir-BIfllAL.THE TRADE OOTLOOK.Nest meeting of the Council......................     1Statistical Information ..........................     1Coal.............................................     1Iron and Steel...................................     2Non-Ferrous Metals...............................     4Engineering ...............-.......................     4Electrical Engineering ...........................     5ifotor 1-ianufacture................................     5Cotton...........................................     6Wool.............................................     8Artificial Silk..................................     9Chemicals........................................    10Gas Industry.....................................    10General Trade....................................    10Shipbuilding and Shipping........................    12Railway Traffic ..................................    13Employment.......................................    14Australian Trade.................................    15,Indian Trade.....................................    15Trade in China.................................16South American Trade.............................    17Statistical Data .................................  Annex.
HBXTMSETINCJ OF THE COUNCIL.   THE PRESIDENT referred to the Inquiry he had sent to themembers as to the date of the next meeting,   A choice ofSeptember 26th and October 10th had been offered and mostof&quot;the members had indicated a preference for October 10th,He proposed, therefore, to fix the meeting for that day.STATISTICAL INFORItATION.   THE PRESIDENT observed that he had had tables prepared and circulated, containing some additional statistical information,which he hoped would be of assistance in forming an appreciation of the present condition and probable courseof trade.   The tables contained actual figures ofproduction, employment etc., for each month of the presentyear and the monthly averages of the quarters of last year andthis.   Index figures had also been calculated for the various items in each of these periods comparing them with the monthly average for 1927.   In the second part of the tables, theprincipal trades had been dealt with separately and these included buildingj  regarding new capital issues he was having a more detailed analysis made.   There was oneunfavourable figure, to which special attention might be drawn;in the net imports of raw materials, reduced to a volumefigure, given on page 2, It would be observed that the indexfor the June quarter was down to 87.3, whereas In thecorresponding quarter of last year it was 94.9.     He proposed having these tables kept up to date and circulated with the minutes of the meetings.                            COAL.   Ml. WARHAM had again to give a gloomy report of the coalindustry.  Production was lower.   The weekly output of coalin the United Kingdom, during the three weeks ended July 14th,was 4,347,000 tons for the week ended June 30th, 4,471,000tons for the week ended July 7th, and 4,310,000 tons for theweek ended July 14th.   The output for the week ended July14th was only B2,S% of the March 1925 weekly average basis,compared with 88.2/i In the previous month.   The number ofpersons employed in the industry for the week ended July 14thwas 80,4/v calculated on the same basis.   Unemployment forthe month of June was 25.7%, as against 21.1% In lay, and.3Jo in iferch 1926.   The quantity of coal exported from great Britain was rather less in June, 1928, being 4,345,643tons as against 4 .,487,032 tons in May.   The value per tonshowed a slight increase, being 15/8d for June as against15/7d for ifey, although there was no increase In market prices owing to variations in quality.   The exports fromGermany and Poland for June were not yet available, but theoutput in the Ruhr in May was 11,740,000 tons, an increaseof 200,000 tons, and in Poland it was 3,007,000 tons, anincrease of 74,000 tons.   Their output had been Increasing,while unfortunately ours had been going down.   The financialcondition of the industry in this country was growing steadilyworse and the continuous losses which were being made were becoming &amp; very serious problem.&apos;   Further conversations
Id                          CONFIDENTIAL.                         COAL (CONTD.).had taken place with regard to the future of the Industry In theUnited Kingdom, and an attempt was now being made to draft adefinite scheme, but it did not seem likely that any scheme would be accepted without protracted negotiations between thevarious districts and collieries concerned.   They were,however, now trying to get on with this, and they had greathopes that something might come of it.   They very muchwelcomed the relief in railway rates which was to come intooperation In December.   It would be a considerable assistanceto the trade.IRON AND STEEL.   MR, BOND said that production figures both of iron and steelshowed a continued decline in June in spite of the increased prices for continental steel.      The decrease compared,withMay amounted to 27,800 tons in pig iron and 43,000 tons in steel, the output for June being 055,700 tons or pig iron and709,500 tons of steel;  this In spite of the fact that theimports of iron and steel In June only amounted to 210,400tons as compared with 237,000-tons in May.   This reductionin imports was, however, artificial, and due to the Antwerpdock strike.   Now that the strike was settled, the importfigures for July would be awaited with considerable interest.The holiday season had commenced and iron and steel worksthroughout the country were taking the fullest advantage ofclosing down for as long as possible In order to meet the increasing depression.   In Scotland ten furnaces had beendamped down during the holidays which under normal conditions should have remained in operation although it was hoped thatthey would be able to resume operations later.   In theCleveland area two more-furnaces had been put out, leaving onlythirty in blast in this district, a decline of ten since thebeginning of the year.   In the Midlands conditions were alsodepressed.   On the West Coast the Workington Company had onlya rail mill in operation, and the Barrow Hematite Company were closed except for the hoop department.   The Continentalindustry reported full order books, with firm prices, and therewas considerable enquiry for semi-finished manufacturingmaterial from British consumers.   Some re-action against new business was claimed to be the result of the deferred applica-tion of the Government de-rating proposals, consumers holdingthe view that the producers must, in their present depressedcondition, pass this on to their customers.   These proposals must involve a reduction in prices and their long defermentwas having the reverse of a stimulating effect at present,it was desirable, in view of the Increasing unemployment andtne possibility of this continuing to increase throughout theautumn and winter of the  present year,  that the Governmentshould anticipate the application of their full de-ratingproposals.   So far as the iron and steel  industry was  an index, the unemployment problem must become progressives and increasingly serious.                                    y                               -2-
COAL (CONTD. ).had taken place with regard to the future of the industry in theUnited Kingdom, and an attempt was now being made to draft adefinite scheme, but it did not seem likely that any scheme would be accepted without protracted negotiations between thevarious districts and collieries concerned.   They were,however, now trying to get on with this, and they had greathopes that something might come of it.   They very muchwelcomed the relief in railway rates which was to come Intooperation In December.   It would be a considerable assistanceto the trade.IRON AND STEEL.   MR, BOND said that production figures both of iron and steelshowed a continued decline In June in spite of the increased prices for continental steel.      The decrease compared,withMay amounted to 27,800 tons In pig iron and 43,000 torts in steel-, the output for June being 563,700 tons of pig iron and709,300 tons of steel;  this in spite of the fact that theimports of iron and steel in June only amounted to 210,400tons as compared with 237,000*tons in May.   This reductionin imports was, however, artificial, and due to the Antwerpdock strike.   Now that the strike was settled, the importfigures for July would be awaited with considerable interest.The holiday season had commenced and iron and steel worksthroughout the country were taking the fullest advantage ofclosing down for as long as possible in order to meet the increasing depression.   In Scotland ten furnaces had beendamped down during the holidays which under normal conditions should have remained in operation although it was hoped thatthey would be able to resume operations later.   In theCleveland area two more-furnaces had been put out, leaving onlythirty In blast in this district, a decline of ten since thebeginning of the year.   In the Midlands conditions were alsodepressed.   On the West Coast the Worklngton Company had onlya rail mill In operation, and the Barrow Hematite Company were closed except for the hoop department.   The ContinentalIndustry reported full order books, with firm prices, and therewas considerable enquiry for semi-finished manufacturingmaterial from British consumers.   Some re-action against new business was claimed to be the result of the deferred applica-tlon of the Government de-ratlng proposals, consumers holdingthe view that the producers must, in their present depressedcondition, pass this on to their customers.   These proposals must involve a reduction in prices and their long defermentwas having the reverse of a stimulating effect at present.It was desirable, in view of the Increasing unemployment andthe possibility of this continuing to increase throughout theautumn and winter of the  present year,  that the Governmentshould anticipate the application of their full de-ratlno;proposals.   So far as the Iron and steel  industry was an index, the unemployment problem must become progressively and increasingly serious,                                   &apos;                               -2-
IRON AND STEEL (CONTD. )   THE PRESIDENT observed that the possibility of a hold-up inorders, owing to the deferment of rate relief, had been advanced in one or two quarters.   On the other hand he had been told thatno importance was attached to it.   His own view was that, if,as Mr. Bond  had always said, people were living from hand tomouth, it was not practicable to hold up orders for nine months.   MR. BOND said that the view he had expressed was that of theNational Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers.   He wasnot himself engaged In the heavy Iron and steel Industry.     The sheet and tinplate trades were busy, and had been working to full capacity.   The enquiry in both trades, had,however, fallen off recently;  probably in the tinplate industrythey had been producing more than consumption warranted.   Thetrade would stop for ten days this month and for a further two weeks In the following three months, which It was hoped wouldbalance production and consumption,,   A bad feature, was that theyhad practically lost the French market altogether.   MR. FUGE. wrote:-     &quot;There is little change to report as against the conditionsof last month.   The pig Iron trade is still in a very depressedstate.   A shortage of orders and low prices is reported fromall districts. &apos;    A closing down of further blast furnaces onthe North East Coast is reported, leaving 30 in operation in theCleveland area.   Unemployment has continued bad.   With regardto steel products, the trade was In an uncertain position, withoutprospects of improvement for the next couple of months.     &quot;The tinplate and galvanised sheet trades are in a fairlygood position, the former especially showing a material improve-ment over the past few months.   In general, the heavy branchesof the steel industry have nothing to report of a satisfactorycharacter either at present or In their prospects so far as these can be visualised.&quot;                             STEEL.     SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR reported the home trade in general steel and engineers&apos; tools to be very bad.   They were only doing about20% of the normal trade at the moment, and two firms had failedin Sheffield recently.   The European trade was also bad, theFrench market having quite dried up.   We had not lost thatmarket to Germany or to any other exporting country.   The french had started a big steel works and were supplying their own demand.The P.L.Pi. had been making exhaustive tests of high speed steel,and some of our steel was submitted and&quot; came out as high as anyother, but when it came to prices, we were 50% out on theexchange In Paris, so the orders had been retained in France.
                            STEEL (CONTD.)Canada and South America were good;  they were the bright spots,,particularly Canada.   Australia was 20% behind last year.China, in soite of all the troubles, carried on and they were doing a very fair trade there and were getting paid.   Japan wasslowly setting better and making steady progress.   In theUnited States a flaw had been found in the tariff and,following a case in the Courts there, high speed steel was nowpaving duty at 20% instead of 40%.   The U.S. Treasury had power, however, to rectify the matter by decree and no doubtthey would do it.     The alloy trade was good.   Exports for June and July were better than for some time.   Russia had been buying a good dealof alloys.   Curiously enough, the steel trade was being effected chiefly in the higher class quality, where we were holding our hand while new melting methods were being, tried.Sir A, Balfour&apos;s own firm were making experiments with a viewto reducing costs, but the great difficulty was that  the bulkmedium steel trade was only fair, and it was difficult to carryon while the expenses were heavy all over.   He did not think there was a chance of improvement until October.                         NON-FERROUS METALS.   SIR CECIL BUDD stated that In the base metal trades there hadbeen a little more movement lately in one or two directions, buthe saw no signs of a real change.   The copper and brassindustries were moderately well employed, mainly with homeorders;  metal making was still good, but the lighter wire tradewas dull.   Lead manufacturers were moderately busy, tin plateswere good, but galvanised Iron was down.   In the aluminiumalloys, in which there was an increasing trade,this country waskeeping well ahead and was taking Its full share In the increaseIn that particular branch of the metal trade.   In the speltermaking industry we were now, in technical matters, level with, ifnot ahead  of, the continent and, if we paid the same wages asBelgium, we should beat them commercially.   It was, however,the first time within&apos; living memory that we had been technicallytheir equals.                              ENGINEERING.   SIR ERNEST PETTER wrote^ .  lThe relevant statistics for the month of June again indicatethat the position of the engineering industry is not at allsatisfactory.   It Is, however, favourably placed in relation tothe other heavy industries.   Thus, to take the employmentstatistics first of all, whereas the general Index of unemploymentrose during June from 9.9% to 10.8&amp;,  the figure for theengineering industry as a whole Increased only from 9.3  to 9.4 .General engineering actually recorded a decline of one decimalplace, while electrical engineering remained constant.   Theincrease in unemployment for the industry as a whole is entirelyattributable to the marked retrogression in marine engineering and constructional engineering which sections reflect the slump in the shipbuilding and building trades respectively.
SIR PHILIP NASH wrote:-      I can only repeat that there has been no material changeexther way in the electrical position, but in my opinion we are getting nearer to greater activity in the home market.   AS I have     be ore/ 1 **** had the Impression, and still have it, that orders for heavy electrical plant will improve gradually from september onwards.1                                     &apos;. MOTOR MANUFACTURE.   SIR JOHN THORNYCROFT reported that in the motor industry, while a certain number of firms were doing quite well, . ost of thosewho had tried for a big output had not been able to sell up to                               corporation-iFIDENTIAL.                             ENGINEERING (COBTD)     &quot;The coal-mining industry has further receded In output and in employment.   The same is true of shipbuilding, andis further evidenced in the quarterly statistics Issued by LloydsRegister (see below).   The Iron and steel industry showedreduced outputs for the month and slightly Increased unemployment,but it is to be noted that the foreign trade balance In iron andsteel products showed a further slight improvement.   The exportsof machinery and other engineering manufactures are again themost pleasing feature of the month&apos;s statistics.   Exports  ofmachinery amounted to 53,328 tons as compared with 50,031 tonsIn May.   T3he increase in June over May occurred principally intextile machinery, but was actually spread over most items.     &quot;It Is probably unnecessary to comment in detail on the statistics of production and foreign trade for the first sixmonths of the year.   The most outstanding feature from our pointof view is the greatly increased export of machinery comparedwith other years.   The total for the six months, amounting to292,299 tons, Is easily in excess of any other post-war year,and equal to 84.4/3 of the corresponding period In 1913.   Barringunforeseen developments, 1928 is certain to be a record post-war year in machinery exports.&quot;   MR. RICHMOND wrote: -     &quot;it is somewhat monotonous to have to report that thoconditions In marine engineering show little alteration  fromthose noted in the last few months.   The usual lull during the holiday period Is now over, and yards and engine shops in thenorth have resumed work, and unless more contracts are forthcoming,the autumn will see a distinct falling off in employment.Overhaul and repair work continues in fair quantity.   enquiries are fairly numerous, but prices are still very poor, and work isbeing quoted at rates which do not cover full charges.   Comparedwith a year ago, the employment situation as a whole Is ratherbetter, but the. outlook Is depressing, and there are few indica-tions to encourage hopes of improvement.&quot;                           ELECTRICAL ENGINESRING.
MOTOR MANUFACTURE (CONTD.)their expectations.   There were far too many cars of foreignmanufacture coming Into the country and, no doubt, had it notbeen for safeguarding, quite a number of firms would have been obliged to close  down.   There had been no marked change in exports, and competition in most places abroad was becoming more severe both for heavy vehicles and for cars.   A member of hisfirm, who had been visiting Australia, reported that Americanmanufacturers had greatly strengthened their position since hewas there four years ago.   Few of the British firms who had made efforts to get a share of the market had been successful,and one, which claimed to have the biggest manufacturingfacilities at home, had made a loss of  250,000 on theirAustralian business during the last few years.     Makers of marine motors of the smaller types were feelingAmerican competition at home as well as abroad, as were alsothe makers of semi^DIesel engines.   American car manufacturers,he thought mainly with a view to advertising their makes, hadbeen supplying their motors specially adapted for boat work at very low prices and all round the English coast this summer therewere to be found high speed American-built boats fitted withChrysler and other car engines.   If they were not built in theirown country, those who owned large yachts had generally come toEngland for them.   It was, therefore, rather a significant thing that the German yards were building six large Diesel yachts(for which about   400,000 had been paid) for American owners,who had recently  passed through English waters.COTTON.   SIR KENNETH STEWART  observed that a little progress&apos;wasbeing made and v/ould be registered soon.   It was still unkno?mhow many of the mills would come into amalgamation, because thedifficulties were so great with regard to calls and such things.     The monthly average yardage of cotton piece goods exported from Great Britain up to June this year had been 343 million yards.   The monthly average export during the four years1923/26 was 351 million yards, so that there was only a difference of 8 million yards.   That Is to say our export business had remained fairly steady in quantity in recent years.Generall - speaking, other export countries had remained equallysteady,   Italy and Germany and Poland had shown almost equaldecreases;  Japan, France and Czecho-Slovakia were going ahead.There were very few countries where we were not the principalsuppliers, though we had not the monopolistic position we had had In pre-war days.   Japan was beating us In China, where herdifferent methods of manufacture and merchanting had given hera great start.   While she was not so definitely ahead of usanyv/here else, she was challenging our position in several other markets such as Malaya, Slam, the Dutch East Indies,Egypt and East Africa.   The United States was beating us in thePhillipine Islands and Canada, in the former case owing to thetariff protection, and in the latter owing  to propinquity.
COTTON (COirTD. ).France and Germany had gone ahead in the coarser qualities andwere sufficiently good even to affect our better qualities aswell.   Elsewhere we 7/ere ahead of other countries.   The total exports of the world were, perhaps, approximately the same asIn pre-war days, but we were not getting the share of it weused to have.   The principal losses we had sustained had beenin staple goods where nrice was the principal factor.   in anumber of cotton goods price was not the principal factor, butin the big bale goods it was.   In Isanchester they did notdesnair of being, able to make a fight against foreign competitorwhen the distractions of financial difficulties were out of theway.   These financial difficulties existed almost wholly Inthe spinning section of the trade.                                      A.     Exports of cotton goods this year had been decliningsteadily since  March, and there was nothing very cheering toreport about the business of the last month.   No market, had shown any special activity, in fact there had been a great dealof apathy. &quot; Extreme  caution had been shown in all offersreceived and business had been poor, so far as he could  judge,for  our competitors as well as ourselves.   it was Impossibleto forecast the future even from day to day.   Any feeling ofconfidence in prices might start a burst of buying, though the,present state of quiescence might easily last another fewmonths.   That  was owing to the extreme uncertainty of the rawmaterial position.   The acreage in America, which dominatedthe whole position, was fairly large this year.   It was about46 million acres against 48 million acres, which was as high asit had ever been, and the next two months would show whataverage price,  between 9d and 17d cotton would be to thebuyer.   The possible margin was very great, and, as spotcotton was now  llfd, there was room either way for a bigdifference in price in the raw material alone&quot;.   The result was that everyone was afraid to commit themselves to anyproduction- at all, and therefore a state of quiescence might continue in the cotton trade, even though quite good ordersmight be accumulating pending the restoration of confidence.   IvK. LSS wrote:-      There is nothing of a satisfactory nature which I v -report.   The bread and cheese trade is certainly no betterthan xt was a month ago;  business coming in is insufficient to *ceen spindles and looms going.  &quot;In the fine trade businesscontinues to be held up, and I should estimate that at the&quot;moment there is not more than enough orders coming forward toIn       PI^ MoM?erJ at 7iorlz-   Egyptian cotton has fallen in price 2xd per pound since the last meeting of the Council,
CONFIDENTIAL.                         COTTON (CONTD. )but buyers generally are of tbe opinion that it is not yet ona safe level, ana will not risk placing orders in weight.     &quot;The Nelson dispute is over, but we have a more extendedone threatened In that of the Ramsey Mill.   The members of theCouncil will have read the facts of the case in the press.There is no doubt that unless the workpeople of this millcompose their differences we shall have the whole trade standingon August 11th.   These unnecessary disputes do harm to thetrade that can hardly be calculated, and greatly impede theefforts v,e make for improvement in employment.     &quot;I hear that the attempt to form  a big combination inthe American section is almost certain to be successful, butthere are as yet no details available  and until these are- made public it Is impossible to hazard an opinion as to the likell-hood of Its sucoess in working.     &quot;I trust that after the holidays  I may have a more cheerfulaccount to give of the cotton textile  trade.&quot;                             WOOL.   MR. AYKROYD reported that the difficult position which had existed in the textile trade during the last six or eight monthsstill continued.   In the early part of the year statistics had indicated that we were likely to have  a short  supply  of woolduring the latter months of the year,  but actually, owing tothe difficulty of correctly estimating the demand, the trade had anticipated requirements that had not  matured, and in consequenceof this was having a bad time.   Since the last meeting of theCouncil the position had become gradually worse and moremachinery was standing in every section of the industry then .had been standing a month ago.   Wool  was undoubtedly too dear,and the problem was how to obtain a lower level of values.Between the May and the July sales of  wool In  London, Yorkshirehad one of the quietest periods since  1925, but in spite ofthis prices changed very little.   They were in the position of having to buy their raw material against the competition of theworld and to sell their goods, manufactured at very high costs,against keen competition.   A larger supply of raw material,together with the stabilisation of continental currencies, whichmust ultimately increase foreign costs, would undoubtedly beof assistance to the British Industry.   in the wool combingsection there was approximately ten per cent, less machineryrunning than last month.   Tops were accumulating and theoutlook was very discouraging.   In spinning no new orders had come xorward since Easter and the position was gradually gettingT^r!e\  Normally, the orders for next season would be pllcedin September, October or November, but, of course, a good dealdepended on the level of values at that time.   The ordersmight be withheld If values, in the opinion of the buyers,were too high.   In some sections of the trade, notably the single yarn trade, many firms that had business to keeo themrunning for several months were having to  resort  to short  time                              -.8-
WOOL (CONTD.)owing to lack of particulars.   On the other hand, the makersof high-class goods in the Huddersfield district were stillkeeping busy on special lines.   The manufacturers in the dresstrade in the Bradford area were In a very bad position.   Inthis section of the industry the position was decidedly worse than In 1925.   ifcre firms were working four to five days aTree1&apos;: than was the case a month ago and only approximatelyforty per cent, of the machinery was running.   In the Yeadonand Guiseley districts the Manufactuers1 Association reportedthat every mill in the district was on short time and only about thirty-eight per cent, of the machinery was running.   InDewsbury there was no alteration to report since June, except the tendency for things to get gradually worse.     The general outlook was difficult to gauge, for mostmarkets were withholding purchases.   Canada, Japan and Germany,all of whom had been expeeted to come Into the market, were still holding back and it looked as if no change In policy could be expected until the new season&quot;s supply came on themarket and formed a baste for the future.   An outstandingfeature was that the same position obtained in most of thecontinental centres;  in Germanyp France Belgium and Italythere had been a suspension of new orders since Easter.   Itappeared that the world demand for wool textiles had decreased.As to the remedy for the present position, Mr. Aykroyd believedIn co-operation rather than amalgamation.   Amalgamation in the textile trade had not proved altogether effective, because Ithad not brought prices down, but put them up.   In practicemost of the big mills that had set out to work right throughfrom ravr material to manufactured goods had had to work theirspinning and manufacturing departments independently, owing tothe varying demand for yarn for different purposes.   On theother hand he had found co-operation amongst firms in the samesection to be successful, and In the yarn trade they had beenable to agree to conversion costs at a very low level.   he agreed, however, that his argument was one rather againstvertical than horizontal combinations.ARTIFICIAL SILK.   MR. ADDISON reported that in the home market they were in theusual slack season.   The Leicester and Nottingham districtswere rather quiet and the reports from Yorkshire, the Bradforddistrict and so on, were still very bad.   The usual summerholidays now taking place In Lancashire, coupled with the factthat buyers were watching the possibilities of the Americancrop very closely, had a tendency to curtail business.   Asregards overseas markets, there was a steady demand for allhigh class yarns, but there was Increasing evidence thatproducers of the lower grade yarns, both In this country andon the Continent, were dumping their inferior products in someof the cheaper markets like India, and taking any price theycould get for them.
CHEMICALS.       HILL wrote-:-      Ehere is no       chemical idecidedly quiet.&quot;     &quot;There is nothing of importance to report with regardto the chemical industry,  business has been steady butGAS INDUSTRY.   SIR D.  MILNE 7/ATSON observed that the prices of by-productsgenerally were sagging, and there was nothing very fresn toreport.   The most serious thing possibly was that coke stocks were increasing rapidly, and with large new installations of coke ovens there was-a danger of serious overproduction  xnthe country.   Already London had to export half a millxon tonsof coke.GENERAL TRADE.   SIR GILBERT VYLE observed that the reports made.to himconfirmed, generally, those given by the Council.   A gooddeal of the extra unemployment now was probably due toseasonal work, yet around the Midlands and in some other placesthere was still a number of industries which were very wellemployed indeed, and some comfort was to be derived from the many personal reports he had received of improved and continued business.   In his own ,particular business of themanufacture of weighing machines, they had had in the last quarter a good period, both in the home and export markets.Retail Trade.   SIR FOODMAN 3URBIDGE  wrote:-     &quot;The month of June, upon which I am now reporting, showslittle change from the month of May except for the fact that anumber of half yearly sales, -/ere started&quot;by the big Storesearlier In the month than in previous /ears, and whilst theydid not do the volume of additional business anticipated,this early start had the effect of holding off the public frompurchasing pending the commencement of the other half yearlysales.   The sale reports, therefore, for the latter part ofJune were rather poor - the great rush of business upon theimprovement in the weather not taking place until the first orsecond week in July.     &quot;The report given last month in regard to the depressionin certain collier;- districts can this month be added to by stating that conditions have become generally worse for the retail trades, the greatest difficulty being the largeoutstanding amount of credit given to customers - their inability to repay rapidly, and the consequent difficulty of
GENERAL TRADE (CONTD.)Retail Trade (Contd)the retail trader to pay his wholesale suppliers.   In Cardiff,however, and in certain other cities in the mining areas, thelarger retail houses report improvement in the volume of their business, but with no increase in the number of employees.     &quot;Ruddersfield, Barnsley, and the V-est Riding of Yorkshire,generally report a decrease in turnover as compared with thePrevious year, ranging from the lowest 9.5?i to one storeshowing 33 l/3rd&apos;i&apos; decrease.   Employment In the industry isgenerally the same, the decrease being reporter to oe in thefashion goods, and dress material departments, although in somecases this may be accounted for by the fact that many of them,as distinct from stores, in other centres, have set back thedate of their sales a few days, and this volume of business willnot appear until the July report.     &quot;There is a general increase in most districts in thefurniture trade, but this is largely accounted for by thecontinued increase in hire purchase.   The furniture trade inLondon reports improvement In the medium class trade, with aslight decrease in the turnover in the most exclusive sectionof the trade.     &quot;Suburban London stores all report Increase in turnover,with little change in the number of people employed, but this is mainly due to the continued efforts of these houses to improve their premises and their service, and also by the fact thatthey are advertising increasingly.   !:e find&quot; It difficult atthe moment to give very accurate reports in regard to somehundred large distributing houses, owing to the fact that they?/ere purchased by various Combines recently, and are being-organised.   Inmost cases, they are showing tremendousIncreases in turnover, with greater economies in administration,and no increase in the number of staff employed.   information in regard to such houses will be more valuable to the AdvisoryCouncil next year.     &quot;Retail food trades are reported to be generally steady,the volume of business remaining approximately the same as inthe previous month.   There has, of course, since the end oflast month, been a great Increase in the volume of fashionbusiness which has enabled most of the large distributinghouses to, at any rate, clear their stocks, although they willnot make the same amount of gross or net profit as they wouldhave done had the season not been shortened by bad weather.i:                     Co-operative TTholesale Society.   Ml. HAYHURST wrote:-     &quot;During the month of July satisfactory sales have been recorded, particularly in the grocery and provision side  of ourousiness.     &quot;Egfts.   Market for Irish eggs  has been firmer.
                     GENERAL TRADE (CONTD.)             Go-operative Wholesale Society (contd.)     &quot;Sugar,  Recent news of the sale to the United Kingdomof a fairly large &quot;block of Cuban raw sugar advanced themarket, and prices for refined were advanced generally.After heavy buying, after an advance,markets turned on thequiet side and then toned up somewhat,     &quot;Elour.  The wheat market has been somewhat weak,probably in sympathy with declines in America and Canada.     &quot;Cheese.   Both Canadian and New Zealand have beensteady&quot; at slightly lower rates, whilst Cheshire has been rather quiet in demand, with country markets firm.     Hl heat.   After the sharp advance in the early part oflast weeTE7&quot;as a result of Russia buying,, the market has shown a sagging tendency, on the subsiding of the demand and better weather reports generally.     &quot;Trade in the Drapery and Aixied sections has been of asatisfactory character, and 1 do not know of any specialfeature to mention.     &quot;Tea.   The market continued on much the same lines asat last report  good quality tea met with keen competitionat firm prices.     &quot;Coffee.   The auctions have been suspended until themiddle&quot; of&quot; August for the annual vacation, but the earlierauctions were only showing small supplies.   Costas stood out as the best coffees on the market.   The efforts of theplanters in British East Africa were rewarded by good pricesbut the quality of the offerings&apos;were very inferior.     &quot;Cocoa,   Until September there will be no furthercrops- for sale In West Africa and whatever is for sale athome or in  America or Hamburg, is the surplus of lastseason&apos;-s main crop.   A feature of the season recently closedat Lagos was the great improvement in the quality of thebean due, in no small measure, to Government control andexamination,&quot;SHIPBUILDING AND SHIPPING.   Ml. ALEXANDER SHAW stated that the index number of shinningfreights in June was 24.51 as compared with 100 in 1920 and26.91 in June 1927.   It was true there had been an increase from 23,97 in the index   since iVIav and the anticipatedbumper wheat crop in Canada had undoubtedly helped to stiffenfreights a little.   On the other hand the 1aid-up tonnagewas considerably greater than it had been at this time lastyear9 495,866 tons on the 1st July this year as,, compared with420^,164 tons on the 1st July last year.   He agreed, however, that a certain amount of laid-up tonnage was tonnage whichhad been replaced by the very considerable orders which hadbeen executed in the course of the last fifteen months.The usual procedure was to sell the old tonnage for breaking up in this country or, more commonly,  to foreigners for
SHIPBUILDING AND SHIPPING (CONTD. )breaking up.   The tonnage under construction in the unitedKingdom in the quarter ending 30th June was 1,202,610 andabroad 1,457,852 tons.   As regards tonnage commenced,although the figure for the last quarter was 278,983 tonsin Great Britain and Ireland as compared with 437,112 tonsa year arco, yet the amount of tonnage commenced abroad was260,^01 tons as compared \tlth. 336,503 tons a year ago.The total tonnage commenced in the world for the quarterending 30th June of this year was 539,884 tons as comparedwith 773,615 tons in the same quarter last -rear, showing thatthe anticipations of shipowners of better conditions hadnot been realised and that there was a distinct falling offin shipbuilding.   THE PRESIDENT suggested, with regard to the figures for ship building in the printed tables circulated to the Council,that it would be useful to have the figures for foreignbuilding inserted as a note for comparison with the homefigures.   ivi*. Shaw agreed.   SIR ERNEST PSTTER wrote:-     &quot;The latest statistics of shipbuilding Issued byLloyds Register show that while during the quarter ended3Cth June, 403,000 tons of shipping were launched, only279,000 tons were commenced, so that the volume of tonnageunder construction  has fallen still further to1,205,000 tons.     These data alone are sufficient tooonfirrn the pronounced ebb of the tide in shipbuilding..activity which is clearly demonstrated in the latestunemployment statistics for the industry.   It is significant that the proportion of ships under construction in Britain to the world total has no?; fallen well below505,.   The tonnage of shipping idle in British ports has gone up from 363,000 tons at 31st March to 496,000 tons at 30th June.   The shipbuilding employers1 wages offerhas now been accepted by the five outstanding craft unions.51RAILY/AY TRAFFIC   3ft. HURC0:-B said that the state of railway traffic was fairlywell known.   For the four weeks ended 22nd July, the totalreceipts of the four groups were down by about  1,250,000as compared with the similar four weeks&quot; in 1927.   The decreaseaffected all the companies;  coal accounted for about 475,000 of it, passenger traffic for about  42 5,000, and thebalance was represented by merchandise and minerals (other thancoal).   As regards the tonnage of particular traffics, thelatest figures were those for Hay, but the comparison with theprevious May was affected by the incidence of Whitsuntide.The fall in the receipts for Ivfcy, 192s, compared with May, 1927,for the lower class of minerals and the lower class of merchandisewas nearly ,2200,000 or about 12 ner cent.
EMPLOYMENT.   MR, PHILLIPS stated that unemployment figures had gone &apos;.from bad to worse;  they had increased by 90,000 during the?month, and were now about 250^000 above a year ago.   the indications were that the recent increase had been fairlygenerally spread.   There was, however, a certain amountof Inflation as compared with a year ago from variouscauses, which might account, at the most, for 33,000 outof the quarter of a million.   There seamed also to beindications, although the industrial analysis was not yet available for July, that unemployment was spreading totrades outside the four or five which previously providedmost of the unemployment.     Mr. Phillips sent in the following table of insuredpersons in employment.Monthly Statistics of insured persons    aged 16 to 64 In employment.*estimated number ofinsured -oersonsaged 16 to 64Inclusive. Number of insured persons aged 16 to 64I Inclusive unem-!ployed (includ-Iing Two monthsIFile of lodgedjbooks).i Difference between Columns 2 &amp; 3  (to nearest hundred.)28.&quot;estimated number oF&quot;&quot;&quot; insured persons aged 16  to 64 inclusive in  employment,  after deducting from  Col.4 3-J  per cents  of the numbers in Col-2 to allow for -sickness -x and other unrecorded n on--employment, exclusive of  tern- , ioJ*ary holidays._^            ITx oTud ing&quot;            persons            directly  nciuding persons directly involved in trade^disputes.involvedin tradedi s put e s.Jan.  : 11,590,000 t?eb.  :11,599,000 Yaarch; 11,608,000 t1-pril! 11,617,000 f--ay   i 11,626,000 tJune  : 11,635,000 tJuly  111,644,000 f 1,227,435 1,191,08111,095,062 1,093,195 1,123,989 1,223,113 1,315,10010,362,60010,407,90010,512,90010,523,80010,502&apos;, 00010,411,90010,328,900 9,957.00010,001looo10,106,60010,117j20010,095.10010,004^700 9,921,400 9?954,000 9,996,90010 j 101,6 CO10,116,20010,092?1C0 9,983,700 9,920,400*  The sickness rate has been taken at an estimated    annual mean;  it has not been possible to allow    for Seasonal Variations.f  Provisional figure.
AUSTRALIAN TRADE.     MR.  SANDERSON mentioned that  at  this  time  of year  in Australia the wool clip was being  shorn  and  the harvest reaped, and consequently it was a  time when  there was a oertain amount  of apprehension by  producers  both  in  regard to  selling and  prioes.  Conditions generally this season were quite good, except in portions of Queensland, New  South Wales  and South Australia, that is in the  drier parts of the back country.   The amount of wool  received into store for the year ending 30th June last was E,446,780 bales  and the  amount sold 2,381,042  bales, including 23,282 held  over.  The  Sydney sales  would open on  the 20th August,  so  there would  soon be an  opportunity  of gauging the level of values.  A good  harvest was anticipated, but it was very early yet to speak  with any confidence on that.  A considerably larger area had  been planted and good reports had come  in  from  nearly  all the States.     42-2- million bushels of wheat  had been exported  this season up to date, and 264,000 tons of flour.   The exports of as  compared with  1-f million in the previous year.   The total imports into the Commonwealth for  the year ended  30th June last were  146 million, showing a  decrease of  16 million on the previous year, and the exports  were   138  million, showing a decrease of  3 million on the previous year.  Bank clear- disturbances  had increased  in Sydney by seven million  sterling and decreased in Melbourne by forty-two million  sterling.   The population on the 31st March was six and a quarter million, which was an increase of one hundred  and twenty-two  thousand during the year.  The Development  and Migration Commission had approved projects involving an  expenditure of sevenmillion,  a large portion of which would be applied to western Australia where a considerable area  of wheat-growing- land had been thrown open,  or would be thrown open in the  fall. One smaller item of  interest was that a new shipping company had been formed with a view to the  reduction  of inter-State freights.   It remained to be seen what success would &amp;e achieved.                       INDIAN TRADE.     MR. LINDSAY said that although India was at present inthe middle of the slack season there were one or two items toreport, of interest and importance.  with regard to the waveof labour unrest passing over India at present, this was not really due to- industrial unemployment, and he thought therewere already signs that it was passing away. The monsoonwas at present half way through and so far was excellent.If it continued as it had begun,  it would be the eighth goodmonsoon in succession.     A question had arisen between India and Japan on thesubject of the latter&apos;s prohibition of the import of rice,whichwas quite possibly intended as a  reply to the alterationlast year in the Indian duty on cotton yarns.  India hadintroduced a variation of their duty on imported yams,  which
CONFIDENTIAL.INDIAN TRADE (CONTD. )had the effect of discouraging those yarns (mainly Japanese)which were In most serious competition with yarns produced bythe Bombay mills.   Japan had threatened, as a reprisal, to put an extra duty on Indian pig iron, but that had not been carriedout.   While there was nothing to link up the present prohibi-tlon on the import of Indian rice with the cotton yarn duties,there was little doubt as to their connection.   The trade agreement between Japan and India, which dated from 1905,contained no provision guarding against import prohibitions orrestrictions.   On the other hand an agreement of 1924 between japan and Siam debarred either country from imposing anyprohibitions or restrictions - with a few recognised exceptionson the trade of the other.   The brunt of the recent import prohibition therefore fell on Indian rice.   At the geneva conference of 1927 on the Import and Export ProhibitionsConvention, Japan had claimed a reservation on this subject and her claim had been accepted.   Mr, Lindsay had, however, stated the Indian view at the recent Conference of July 1928 and he understood that, when the Convention was brought into effect,the Japanese prohibition would have to be re-considered If the diplomatic representations now being made failed to achieve their object meanwhile.     Another point of interest was the complaint of Javacompetition with Indian tea.   The explanation of thiscompetition appeared to be, quite simply, that India had found it did not pay to grow a medium tea, and had been turning to.the finer qualities, so that the medium tea had to be produced by mixing fine and coarse teas.   That had brought Javaprominently on to the United Kingdom market, as they supplieda cheap, strong, highly coloured tea which was useful forblending purposes.TRADE IN CHINA.   SIR JOHN THORNYCROFT mentioned that his firm had donebusiness for a good many years In China in supplying marineengines and boilers, there being in Shanghai a number of chinese shipbuilding yards that could build hulls, but couldnot make the machinery.   After the war that business continued and they sold about  100,000 worth of boilers up to abouteighteen months ago.   They had imagined, with the disturbances in China, that there -was not a likelihood of getting muchbusiness for many years, and that there would be difficultiesin getting paid and so on.   He was pleased to say, however,that they had been mistaken in that, as within a fortnight ofthe cessation of actual fighting they had received orders forboats to be put down In the various shipyards on the Yangtse.Apparently the people now in power in China were in a positionto get the country going more quickly than was&apos;generallyanticipated.   Sir John felt It was up to the british manufacturers to act promptly, because there was no  doubt thatthe Americans were very anxious to jump our claim.
                                                                   no(TRADE IN CHINA ^C^NTp,J   SIR D.  MILNE &quot;JATSON confirmed what Sir John Thornycroft saidas to the  possibilities of trade in China and mentioned thatChina had  bought twice the quantity of sulphate of ammonia forfertilising purposes this year that it had bought last year.Prices were generally lower than a year ago, out that did notaccount for all the increase.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.   MR, HOSE wrote:-      &quot;In his message to Congress delivered at the end of June,the President of Argentina stated that the general revenue ofthe Republic for the fiscal year 1927 amounted to $655,558,583(paper), against expenditure of $651,934,,237 (paper), th-as showing a realised surplus of $3,624 ,,346,,   The Governmentsfinancial policy, which includes the balancing of the Budget,the consolidation of the floating debt, the active supervision of revenue collection, and the strict control of public expenditure, has resulted in the establishment of normalconditions in the National Treasury, there having now been fourconsecutive periods in which an excess of revenue over expenditure has been realised.   During the year 1927, an amount of$261,415,072 (paper) of the floating debt of the Republic wasconsolidated, while new operations to the extent of $14^,566,819were  effected so that the total floating debt was reduced from$655,488,629 at 31st December, 1926, (including  181,225,175(paper) owed by the State Railvrays), to $408,440,376 (paper).The total consolidated internal and external debt at 31stDecember last was $2,155-,5I8.,098 (paper), as against$1,845,844,777 at the end of 1926.   Dealing with agriculturalconditions, the  President stated that considerable progress was being mace, especially in regard to the employment of themost modern and efficient methods.   This is exempllfled in theuse of seeds specially suitable for the varying conditionsexisting in different districts, and also in the substitution of mechanical traction for the old methods.   Shipments of theprincipal grains in 1927 amounted to 15,502,000 tons, ascompared with 9,373,000 tons in 1926.    Referring to the railway situation, the President stated that the returns of both goods and passenger traffic showed fresh high records for 1927, thetotal volume of goods carried during that year having been52,928,000 tons,&quot;and the number of passengers 149,507,000.Gross earnings aggregated $234,886,000 (fold),  representing anincrease of 8,79&quot;per cent, on those for 192a, while operatingexpenses were $202,992 .,000 (gold) P an increase  of 9,77 percent.   The net earnings amounted to $81,894-000 (gold),  being6,43 per cent, greater than those in 1926.     &quot;The returns of Argentine foreign trade for the first five months of 1928 showed continued expansion in the total value  ofimports, as compared with the aggregate figures for the  corres-ponding period of 1927.    The actual figures (which represent&quot;real&quot; and not Customs values) compare as  follows:-
CONFIDENTIAL.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE (CONTD.)Exportsrt SurplusJan.- May,1928.  72y904,000481,848,000108*944,0001927.327,959,000477,422,000149,463,000A substantial Increase has occurred during the current year in imports&apos; of textiles and textile manufactures, in fuels andlubricants, Iron and iron manufactures, and also in machinery and vehicles *   The other main groups of imports, with theexception of foodstuffs, all showed expansion, although to a lesser extent.     &quot;The general commercial situation continues satisfactory,while conditions in the agricultural areas are also favourable.The sowing of wheat continues, and is nearing completion in theCentral and Northern zones.   It i3 reported that; an increasedarea has been sown to wheat this season, and both the early andlate-sown crops are progressing favourably.   The picking of maize is finished, but shelling has been delayed in some areas on account of wet weather.   Although the dock labourershave resumed work at Rosario de Santa Pe, the general labour situation remained unsettled, and the congestion existing atthe Port has tended to restrict chartering business and exportsof grain.     &quot;Despite some restricting of retail sales in the Centraldistricts of Chile, a generally favourable undertone continuesin the commercial markets, and total -wholesale orcers during june appear to have been somewhat greater than in thepreceding month.     &quot;Revenue receipts during the first five months of 1928exceeded expenditure by approximately $7,500,000.   customs revenue in that period amounted to &amp;23&apos;5,235a000, as comparedttith only $175,274,000 in the first five months of 1927.Export duties yielded $136,602,000, of which $132^572,000represented nitrate export duties, and the yield of importduties amounted to $91,656,000.     &quot;The production of Chilean Nitrate of Soda in the period july, 1927, to June, 1928, aggregated 25-470,626 metricquintals, as compared with 13,127 ,,853 metric quintals in thepreceding nitrate year.   Sales of the fertiliser since theintroduction of free^selling on 14th April, 1927, up to15th July, 1928, amounted to 3,750,641 metric tons, of which615,305 metric&quot;tons were for delivery after June, 1928.     &quot;in general, the business situation in Brazil continuessatisfactory.   In the import markets, a good demand isreported for engineering supplies for road construction andespecially for iron rods for reinforced concrete.   There isalso an increasing demand for general Iron goods, stocks ofwhich are insufficient to meet local requirements.   weather conditions recently have been extremely favourable for thepicking of coffee, and experts place th* quantity of the 1928-29 crop available for export through the port of Santos at between 6% and 7 million bags, while it is calculated that notmore than two million bags are available for shipment through
SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE (CONTD. )Rio de Janeiro.  Ultimately, the exportable surplus throughSantos may possibly exceed eight million bags.   The Santoscoffee market has recently been quiet, but the fact that stocks are at present approaching the maximum allowed under the Inter-State agreement may cause entries to the Port to be discon-tinued for the time being.   The Coffee Institute claims thatits propaganda is producing good results, &quot;Inasmuch asdeliveries for consumption during eleven months of the 1927-28season totalled 22,008,000 bags, against 19,651,000 bags in theprevious season.     &quot;The picking of the  Peruvian cotton crop, which was re-tarded owing to the late summer, has been proceeding actively,and, except In the South where drought has been experienced,producers generally are reported to be satisfied with the stateof the crops.   Reports from the North state that the harvest inPiura is excellent, growers there having successfully overcome the insect pests from which the plants have suffered very muchin the past.   The tone In the Peruvian sugar market has been somewhat dull recently, while general commercial conditions inthe Republic are comparatively quiet.     &quot;Prospects for the coming coffee crops in the CentralAmerican countries appear to be generally satisfactory.   InNicaragua, the plantations have benefitted recently from copiousrains, and the blossoming of the trees is now finished.   It Isanticipated that the total Nlcareguan output of coffee for thecoming season will be about 200,000 bags.   T/hen current ship-ments have been completed, the total exports during the presentyear are likely to amount to about 260,000 bags, and on this basis the coming  crop would be about 60,000 bags short.   Itmust, however, be borne in mind that the production of coffeefor the current year has been unusually heavy, so that, in thecircumstances, the outlook for the coming season may beconsidered normal.   In Guatemala, there has been a good demandfor next-season  coffee, and European buyers appear anxious tomake contracts for delivery up to as far ahead as February and march, 1929.   It was estimated at the beginning of July thatsome 350,000 quintals had been sold to arrive, practically allthese sales having been effected at higher prices than themaximum paid last season.   In Venezuela, weather conditions have continued very favourable for the approaching coffee harvest,the outlook for which remains distinctly promising.   prospects for the next cocoa crop are also very satisfactory, and recentreports indicate that a good yield may be anticipated.   Itappears probable that supplies from the new crop will become available about December of this year, which will be much earlier than was the case last season.     &quot;The situation in Mexico has been entirely overshadowedby the assassination of the President-Elect,  General Obregon,and, while the extension of disorder would appear to have been averted, the outlook remains extremely obscure.&quot;
Some leading statistical data indicating;  toe trend of  the Scone                (Information received up  to date  of  circulationEmployment: Unemployed  on Live  Register (inc. persons  on  short  time receiving benefit)......................... I Railway Receipts week ended  -J  Goods Traffic  (Gross)......., J  Passenger Traffic  (Gross)...,***************Production: Goal  output  during week ended Pig Iron output during month. Steel output during monthPrices: Wholesale &quot;Board of Trade&quot; Index No.(1913*100):   Food...............................   Materials..........................   Total____,.........................International  comparison of Gold Prices 1924 * 100,  United Kingdom.(Board of Trade).....  France..............................  Belgium.............................  United States........,..............  Italy...............................United Kingdom Trade+4- Net Imports.......................... Exports (Dome stic Produce),...,....,.Vessels laid up  in United Kingdom ports:  British.............................  Foreign.............................Shipping Freights: Chamber of  Shipping Index No.  (1920 * 100)........................Postal Receipts  - Daily Average s**.-..........................Bank Clearings: Country Cheque  and Provincial,  week ended..........................Percentage of  Advances  to Deposits (London Clearing Banks)..............New Capital Issues in Great Britainff (Midland Bank Statement): United Kingdom Purposes.............. Overseas purposes....................                        Total.........Money Market: Bank, Rate............................Market Rate 3 months&apos; Bank Bills.....  viscount (3 months&apos; Treasury Bills)..Latest.30th JulyWholly un-employed..Other.....827,200477,8001,305,0003rd August 1,804,700 *    tf    2,721,30028th JulyJulyJuly Tons.4,165,000  537,800  666,900152,8134.9141,1June (July 77.1) 77,9July1st JulyJuneJune    97,1   106,9    99,5    75,6     87,015,03660,885,097 Net Tons,   491,720     4,146 24.51  124,5784th Aug. 100,893,000June           53,5July      24,165,000          17,655,000          41,820,0003rd Aug.  -4-1$  &quot;      43A6-4i;*  &quot;      4,4s.2.60d.A monthearlier.783,496433,982 1,217,478B- -1,822,9001,814,100 Tons.4,347,100  563,700  709,500157.5134.9142.6       78.4       98.1      106.9      100.5       75.9            87,898,4211   59,472,4881             1    Net Tons.I1 Api. 349,4041       13,9511    23,97        123,669]     116,915,0(1   55.225,405,OC15,967,0-:41,372,00     4%% 3.14s.0.25d ^-Approximate weekly average for July  1913. -$Monthly average for 1913.-M-The figures for 1913 represent the external  trade of  the  British Isles  ad:   trade of Great Britain and Northern Ireland with the  Irish Free State  iss-K-Teiegraph and telephone receipts, Savings  Bank,  and Money arid  Postal  OrdettExcluding direct borrowings by the British Go\-ernment  for national  purposf   arising from the capitalisation of  reserve  funds and  undivided  profits., I   securities previously held in the United  Kingdom,  short-dated bills  soiJ   and loans by municipal and. county authorities except  in  cases where  thei   subscription.  The figures are based on the prices of issue.
fa of  the gjocmomlo  si tuaiiorx in  Great britain of circulation of Minutes).								A month earlier.	At corresponding date in -				1927.	1925.		1913.783,496 433,982	662,191 457,637		-	No comparable data.   1,189,000 1,705,900 Tons. 5,134,000* 855,000f 638,600f Average for 1913 -100.1,217,478	1,119,828		1,197,631	  &quot; 1,822,900 1 1,814,100 Tons, 4,347,100 563,700 709,500 157.5 134.9 142.6	  1,516,100 2,397,900 Tons. 4,836,600 645,800 687,100 153.7 135.0 141.4		  1,989,700 3,040,400 Tons. 4,524,400 492,700 590,400 164.3 ) 152.8 ) 156.9 )	78.4 98.1 106.9 100.5 75.9   87,898,421 59,472,488 Not Tons. 1 Apl. 349,404 13,951 23.97   123,669   116,915,000 55.2   25,405,000 15,967,000	77.6 96.6 107.8 95.6 76.6   85,699,496 56,121,131 Net Tons. 413,835 6,329 26.91   120,321   92,577,000 54.0   16,336,000 18,558,000		85.9 84.2 69.8 105.4 92.2   87,342,990 64,826,369 Net Tons. 753,721 23,458 23.66   115,191   83,672,000 52,1  , 8,775,000 7,761,000	Avge.for 1913, 54.6 15.6 (Apl.1914) 12,7 66.5 14.1   53,472,834 47,164,702 Avge,for 1913 a 23,40 No comparable data.   44,224,600   Avgeafor July-Sept. 1913 (Economist) 1,756,900 8,230,300, 41,572,000	34,894,000	16,536,000		9,987,2003H/L6 -3f$  3.14s.0.25d.	45/16$  4.6s.5d.	4  - 45/16$  4.5s.0.44d.		4%tish Isles as a unit; in the other figures shown theFree State is included as external trade.d Postal Order business are excluded^national  purposes, shares issued to vendors, allotmentsled profits, issiies for conversion or redemption ofed bills sold in anticipation of long-term borrowings,es where there is a specified limit to the total
00o&quot;                                                            TABLE  A.-GENERAL.New Capital Issues, Transport, Baw Materials, Production  Employment, occ.                   Year 1927 and January-June. 1928.PART I. ACTUAL FIGURES.Items.	Unit of Measurement.	Monthly Averages.						Year 1928. !							Jan.-Mar., 1927.	Apr-June, 1927.	July-Sept., 1927.	Oct.-Dec, 1927.	Jam-Mar., 1928.	Apr.-June, 1928.	Jan.	Feb.	Mar.	Apr.	May.	June.1.1 New Capital Issues (Midland Bank Statements)  (a.) Home Issues .. (i.) Overseas Issues 2. Railways- Freight Traffic-(a) Goal, Coke and Patent Fuel (b) Other Minerals and General Merchandise .. 3. Shipping-Entrances and clearances with Cargoes in the Foreign Trade  (a.) Entrances (b.) Clearances 4. Net Imports of Raw Materials  (a.) Value as declared : .... (b.) Value at average prices of 1927 .. 5. Postal Receipts Average amount daily .. 6. Employment  . (a.) Estimated number of Insured Workers in Employment .. .. ,. (b.) Insured Workers Unemployed .. .,	Thousand  &apos;s &quot;1 Thousand f J ton miles \ &quot;1 Thousand f j net tons \ Thousand  &apos;s n Thousands	17,,828 9,820 873,563 782,641 4,634 4,982 28,527* 30,600* 119,386 9,857 1,242	16,470 9,113 731,749 798,406 5,108 5,360 21,395 22,200 121,174 10,094 1,029	7,203 6,852 778,467 772,969 5,425 5,657 20,322 18,600 121,657 10,079 1,067	17,179 20,439 774,031 774,682 5,029 5,168 23,328 22,200 139,006 10,038 1,130	18,486 15,968 782,701 757,477 4,497 5,036 25,301 22,900 125,699 10,022 1,173	20,595 12,489 5,136 5,354 21,301. 20,400 124,852 10,072 1,147	14,178 19,616 800,734 704,890 4,578 4,958 24,955 126,696 9,957 1,227	22,627 5,245 738,268 745,766 4,171 4,768 23,797: 122,406 ,10,002 1,195	18.652 23,044 809,100 821,775 4,741 5,381 27,151 127&apos;,995 10,107 1,096	10,628 7,978 657,182 706,928 4,836 4,864 21,979 126,310 .10,117 - 1,093	25,752 13,523 5,284 5,499 ; 22,548 123,669 10.095 1 1,124	25,405 15,967 5,288 5,699 19,376 124,578 10,005 1,225* The figures for January-March 1927 include an average of over  2 million in respect of coal and coke, imports of which in 1927 were practically confined to these months.
; TABLE A.-GENERAL-^ (continued).PART II.-INDEX NUMBERS.-MONTHLY AVERAGE or 1927 4 100.  I\1 v . ;. . i Items;	Unit of Measurement.	. &apos; , &apos; Monthly Averages.						Year 1928.								Jan-Mar., 1927.	Apr.-June, &apos;. 1927.	July-.. Sept., 1927.	Oct.-Dec, 1927.	Jan.-Mar., . 1928.	Apr-. June, 1928.	Jan.	Feb.	Mar.	. Apr.	May.		June.1. New Capital Issues (Midland Bank Statements)  &apos; - (a.) Home Issues .-.&apos;, ... (i.)&apos;Overseas Issues 2; Railways-Freight Traffic-(a.) Coal,. Coke and Patent Fuel (b.) Other Minerals and General Merchandise .. 3. Shipping&apos; Entrances and Clearances with cargoes in the foreign trade  ! (a.) Entrances (J.) Clearances .. 4. Net Imports of Raw Materials : Volume 5. Postal Receipts-average amount Daily 6. ^Employment  (o.) Estimated Number of Insured Workers in ........ Employment (S.) Insured Workers Unemployed	For units1 of measure-ment on ; which the [ Index Numbers are based see Part I	121-5 85-0 &apos; 110-7 100-1 91-8 94-2 i 130-8* 95-3 98-5 111-2	112-3 78-9 92-7 102-1 101-2&apos; 101-3 94-9 96-7 100-8 92-2	49-1 59-3 98-6 98-8 107-&apos;5 106-9 79-5 97-1 100-6. 95-5	117:1 176-9 98-0 &apos;. 99-0 1 99-6 97-7 - 94-9 110-9 100-2 101-2	126-0 138-2 99-1 96-8 89-1 95-2 97-9 100-3 - 100-1 105-0	140-4 108-1 101-7 101-2 87-3 99-6 100-6 102-7	96-6 169-7 , 101-4 90-1 90-7 93-7 ibi-i 99-5 110-0	154-2 45-4 93-5 95-3 82/6 90-1 97-7 99-9 107-0	127-1 199-4 1021-5 1051-1 93-9&apos; 101-7 102-1 100-9 98-1	72i-4 69-0 1 83-2 90/4 95-8 91-9 100-8 101-0 97-9;	175-5 117-0 104-6 103-9 97-7 100-8 100-6		173-2 138-2 104-7 107-7 99-4 99-9 10.9-6to* See Note against Item 4 of Part I.
TABLE B. PARTICULAR  TRADES.PART I. ACTUAL FIGURES.Items.	Unit of Measurement.	Monthly Averages.						Year 1928.							Jan-Mar., 1927.	April-June, 1927.	July-Sept., 1927.	Oct-Dec, 1927.	Jan.-Mar., 1928.	April-June, 1928.	Jan.	Feb.	Mar.	Apr.	May.	June.1. Coal Mining  (o.) Quantity of saleable coal raised .. (5.) Unemployment-Insured Workers  Wholly Unemployed .. Temporarily stopped... 2, Iron; and: Steel Trades  (a.) Steel Ingots made .. .. .. (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers 8. Base Metals  (a.) Copper consumption^) .... .. .. (5.) Unemployment in Base Metal Trades 4. Cotton Trades  (a.) Raw Cotton delivered to Mills .. (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers 5. Woollen and Worsted Trades  (a) Index of Wages Bill. See Part II. (6) Unemployment Insured Workers 6. Artificial Silk Yarn, Straw and Waste: Duty paid deliveries  (a) Home made (J) Imported .. ... .. 7. Natural Silk Raw and Silk Yarns: Duty paid - deliveries.. 8. Crude Rubber Supplies-Net Imports adjusted for Stock variations 9. Paper-making Materials 	Thous, tons ......Tons Tons Thous. Centals Thousand lbs. o Tons	22,086 134,175 67,147 835,700 37,973 11,866 4,861 1,602 49,105 26,370 2,415 187 281 4,038	20,620 114,756 106,288 827,300 35,758 11,628 3,963 1,845 39,782 23,075 2,994 245 357 3,933	20,420 133,409 196,475 702,400 38,697 11,116 3,797 1,219 54,550 22,431 3,487 288 304 2,587	20,948 138,399 79,131 667,500 45,409 12,109 3,600 1,252 63,089 17,603 3,968 231 421 4,375	21,429 143,670 65,216 728,000-41,095 12,351 3,664 1,380 51,920 18,398 4,005 221 462 4,700	18,951, 163,288 85,689 -702,100-42,277 12,310 3,676 1,246 61,384 22,155 2,916	21,547 138,538 72,645 626,200 42,195 13,520 3,596 1,321 54,742 20,977 3,624 192 484 0-478	20,654 144,449 70,993 764,400 39,525 8,585 3,699 1,366 49,159 18,113 4,238 &apos; 281 467 6,496	22,087 148,023 52,009 793,300 41,566 14,949 3,697 1,454 . 51,858 16,105 4,153 190 436 8,081	18,211 159,597 42,294 644,100-43,077 8,932 3,649 1,264 56,581 - 16,991 4,421 197 398 2,215	19,682 161,300 84,290 752,700 41,656 14,857 3,660 1,264 55,315 20,839 3,734 276 407 3,773	, 18,959 168,966 130,483 709,500 42,097 13,140. . 3,720 - 1,210 72,257 28,636 * * 2,760Imports (8) of Wood Pulp  (a.) Chemical .. (6.) Mechanical	H	40,228 59,302	49,773 62,122	46,950 90,701	55,948 71,884	33,278 40,792	38,537 64,939	47,007 41,862	26,342 31,428	26,486 49,087	25,404 53,537	46,289 50,985	43,917 90,296                           (*) The figures given do not include in the available supply the metal produced from imported ores-.............--------......------------........,  (2) The increase of stocks in this month exceeded the net imports.                           (8) Total Imports, re-exports of wood pulp are, in practice, unimportant in amount.
:TABLE B-PARTICULAR TRABES-CecmtiW).Items.	Unit of Measurement.		1 Monthly Averages. i,:						Year 1928.											Jan.--Mar., &apos; 1927.	Apr.-June, &apos; 1927.	July-Sept, j &apos; 1927.	Oct.-Dec, : 1927.	Jan-&quot;Mar., &apos; 1928.	Apr.-&apos; June, - 1928.	.&apos; Jan.		Feb.		-Mar.		Apr.	-May.	June.10.&apos; Generals Engineering  . ( Unemployment Insured Workers 11.&apos; Electrical Engineering  -(a.) BEAMA&apos; Index; of Production-See Part II. s (i.). Unemployment-^Insured Workers .. 12. Building- &apos;- j (a.)&apos;Plans approved by 146 Local Authorities in Great Britain Estimated Cost-&apos; (I.) Dwelling Houses &apos;.. j (II.) Other Buildings and additions and . alterations to existing buildings.. (b.) Unemployment Insured Workers  (I.) Building : (II.) Public Works, Contracting, &amp;c. ..	Thousand fs		76,820 4,988 3,754 1,793 95,133 32,528	59,738 3j946 1 .3,329 2,388 53,343 24,344	55,806 i 3,685 2,984 1,923 63,479 24,865	57,564 .3/424 3,229 2,027 111,638 31,185	55,473 3,667 3,232 2,083 114,786 33,256	54,82,1 ; 3,738 77,023 .28,040	55,806 3,655 - .2,176 1,817 137j40i 35,278		55,77 . 3J70 / 3,88 2,14 118,99 34,02	) I 1 2 5	54,84 , 3;64 : 3(63 .2,29 87(96 30,46	4 i 6 D 1 1	55,791 . 3,642 i &quot;3,054 , 1,921 80,916 28,959	54,483 :3,750 3,514 . 2,292 72,283 27,557	.54,189 . .3,823 &apos; 77,869 27,603The following figures relating to shipbuilding are actual aggregates for the quarterly periods,; not mont										ily averages:- &apos;&quot; i ; * , , - i - ;;							13. Shipbuilding  (a.) Merchant&apos;Vessels&apos;under construction at end of Quarter .. .. (J.) Vessels commenced during Quarter (c.) Unemployment-^-Insured - Workers-Ship-; . ^building and Marine Engineering	Thousand Gross Tons	j	ri 1,217 580 78,537	1,390 437 57,338	&apos; 1V536 370 51,332	1,580 377 48,500	- 1,441 .342 45,346	: 1,203 . 279 53,185	43,46	J	44,69	i	47,87	1	49,802	1,-.. I 51,933	57,820
PART II. INDEX  NUMBERS. MONTHLY AVERAGE OF 1927  - 100. 1. Coal Mining       (a.) Quantity of saleable Coal raised  ..      (J.) Unemployment Insured workers-            Wholly unemployed            Temporarily stopped 2. Iron and Steel Trades       (a.) Steel Ingots made      (b.) Unemployment Insured workers 3. Base Metals-      (a.) Copper consumption (!) .. &apos;  &apos;   (J.) Unemployment in Base Metal Trades 4. Cotton Trades-      (a.) Raw Cotton delivered to Mills   ..      (J.) Unemployment Insured Workers 5. AVoollen and Worsted Trades       (a.) Index of Wages Bill   .....  (b.) Unemployment-Insured Workers 6; Artificial&apos; Silk Yarn, Straw and  Waste       Duty Paid deliveries           (fi.) Home made       ..       ..      &quot;.-,     &apos;  *   lb.) Imported ..       .&apos;.       .. .7.: Natural Silk-Raw and Silk Yarns-            !      Duty Paid deliveries       ..       .. 8. Crude Rubber Supplies       Net Imports adjusted for Stock variations.    .. 9. Paper-making   Materials Imports  (3) of  Wood      Pulp-          (a.) Chemical  ..       ..       ..          (J?.) Mechanical10. General Engineering       Unemployment Insured  workers11. Electrical Engineering       (a.) BEAMA Index of Production (*) .......      (b.) Unemployment Insured workers12. Building-  .                .   .      (a.). Plans approved by 146 Local Authorities in       &apos;     Great Britain               Estimated Cost       ........... --;                 (i.) Dwelling Houses                (ii.) Other Buildings  and additions                      and  alterations  to  existing                      buildings For unitsof measure-  ment on which the  various   Index Numbers are basedsee Part I105-1103-0 59-8110-2 96-2101-6119-9118-3 95-1 96-7117 3 75-1 78-8 82-5108-2 83-4 83-5122-9 94-7124-4112-9 98-1 88-1 94-7109-1 90-6 99-6 97-7 99-3 77-0101-0103-2 93-1103-0104-8105-4103-2 87-5&apos; 95-6104-4 98-4100-2117-5 97-2102-5175-0 92-6 98-1 95-2 93-6 90-0105-6100-2100-3108-4121-1 89-3 69-3 97-4127-7 89-3109-6 91-989-94-6 99-6106-4 70-5 88-0115-0103-7 92-4122-2102-1 78-7123-4 97-2123-4117-2116-0101-2 92-1 91-2 8o-497-T99-7102-0110-4 58-1 96-0104-2105-7 90-4101-9100-6101-6 82-2124-5 93-0135-5125-969-057-577-291-497-2102-5 90-2125-5 76-3 92-6107-1105-4 90-7 92-0118-9100-3; 99-178-479-991-593-2102-5106-4 64-7 82-6107-0115-8 88-7 97-5106-0 99-8 93-8.112-7 80-9141-997-559-089-377-291-165-589-4 98-3111-0 63-3100-8100-2 73-5 91-2100-9 95-2101-8; 81-0131-8118-0136-9174-054-644-389-376-392-3116-8105-4105-1113-7 46-3104-6105 -3128-0 91-2107-4100-4103-3 72-0129-1 80-1127-8216-554-969-187-878-190-9109-4112-7122-6 37&apos;7 85-0109-2 76-5 90-0 93-4109-6102-2 76-0137-5 83-0116-7 59-352-775-489-373-790; 891-994*5 93-6123-9 75-1 99-3105-6127-2 90-3 93-4107-1100-9 93-2116-1116-3119-4101-196-071-887-269:3&apos;93; 5105-7112-8 90-2129-8116-2 93-6106-7112-5. 917 89-4140-0 97-8128-0 73-9 91-1127-2 86:7. 95-38.                                   For Notes Q), (2) and (&apos;), see page 3.(*) The figures are derived from those issued by BEAMA, which are calculated to a basis of- 100 for the year 1920.
TABLE  B. PARTICULAR TRADES-(continued).........  ........ -... ..........Items; ---........&apos;......&quot;&quot;&quot;	Unit of Measurement.	Monthly Averages;						, Year 1928. .							Jam-Mar., 1927.	Apr-June, 1927.	July-Sept, 1927.	Oct-Dec, 1927.	Jam-Mar., 1928.	Apr.-&apos; June, 1928.	Jan.	Feb. -	Mar.	Apr. ;	May. j	June.12.&quot;Building-(continued). (i.) Unemployment Insured workers  (i.) Building .. &apos;*.. &quot; .. (ii.) Public works, contracting, &amp;c.	For Units of measure-ment on ?&apos; which the-various Index Numbers are based see Part I	117-6 115-2	66-0 86-2	78-5 88-1	138-0 110-4	141-9 117-8	. 95-2 ! 99-3	169-8 125-0	147-1 120-5	108-7 107-9	100-0 102-6	89-4 &quot;&apos; 97-6	96-2 97-8The following figures, relating to shipbuilding, are for the quarterly periods, not monthly averages:  -													13: Shipbuilding-(a) Merchant Vessels under Construction at end of Quarter (5) Vessels Commenced during Quarter (c) Unemployment Insured Workers, Ship-building and Marine Engineering	See Parti	85-0 131-4 133-3	97-2 99-1 97-3	107-4 83-9 87-1	110-4 85-6 82-3	100-7 77-5 76-9	84-0 63-2 90-2	73-8	75-8	81-2	84-5	88-1	98-1
FLUCTUATIONS DURING THE PERIOD HAY 1927 JULY 1928
cFLUCTUATIONS DURING THE PERIOD MAY 1827  JULY 892
Statement regarding the export trade position made at themeeting of the Advisory Committee to the Department of overseas Trade held on Wednesday, the 18th July, 1928.     SIR GILBERT VYLE (Hardware Metals, etc.) said that itwas difficult to offer any concrete report regarding general trade conditions, but there was a slow and steady improvementin export trade.   There was, however, a lack of replenishingorders and it was therefore difficult for traders to lookahead.   In his view there was no reason for pessimism andthose firms who were adapting their products to the needs ofthe consuming markets were reaping the benefit of theirenterprise.     MR. EMS LEY  (Worsteds) stated that conditions in theworsted industry had during the last two months been bad;this might be partly seasonal, but was due also to a generalanticipation of a fall in the price of raw material.   Asa result buyers were holding off the market not only inthis country but everywhere, conditions in the U.S.A. beingworse than here.   Eastern trade had fallen off and therewas more unemployment in his industry than had been the case for some time past.&apos;     MR. MCEWEN  (Wholesale Co-operative Society) said thatthe tariffs in Spain were responsible for a considerable lossof business to British traders who were being pushed out ofthe market.   He had recently been in South Africa, where on every hand he met complaints that British firms were not disposed to modify  their products to meet the requirementsof the market.   Mr. Hacking stated that this criticism wasone which was received frequently from abroad, and to whichincreasing attention was being paid.     MR. PARKER  (Boots and Shoes) said that prices of rawmaterials were still, high, but fortunately their overseas tradewas not being affected by this position, as competitors were suffering in a similar manner.   The black spot on the indusrty was Australia, and  they seemed to be unable, owing to theoperation of the tariff, to secure business with the Common-wealth.   The tariff was imposed not only on boots and shoes,but on leather,  and exports to that country had been reducedto a minimum.     MR. GRAY-BUCHANAN (Iron, Steel, General Merchant Trade)said in regard to iron and steel and building materials, theywere now entering upon the seasonal slackness in trade, and business was being  conducted on a hand to mouth basis.  Stocks,however, were low abroad and he thought we might look to a revival in the future.   He referred to the Australian company which had been formed by Dorman Long &amp; companies*y Ltd. andHoskins &amp; Co., Ltd. and said that statements were being madein the Australian Press that eventually the commonwealth would be independent of outside sources of supply in regard toiron and steel.   British pig iron prices, were now belowcontinental quotations, British makers quoting 56/- to 59/-per ton, while continental manufacturers were asking 59/- to62/- per ton.   With regard to steel billets, however, thecontinental price was  4. 15s. while the British price was 6. 7. 6d.   As  sectional material intended for Australia had,in/
if I IE NT IAL .-2-in order to obtain the benefit of the preference, to berolled from British steel, it was a difficult matter owingto the great difference in the price to secure business-India was obtaining better prices for her raw products andconsequently larger quantities of goods were being imported.     LT.COLONEL KITSON CLARK  (Mechanical Engineering) saidthat in the locomotive trade  conditions were definitely goingagainst us.   Australia was producing her own locomotives andIndia was buying in the cheapest market.   Their difficulty was that their prices were too high owing partly to the factthat they had no home market, the Railway Companies buildingtheir own locomotives.   Employment was very bad in this industry.     MR. HOLROYD (Cotton Spinning) stated that the Americansection of the cotton industry was about as bad as it couldbe and perhaps the only consolation was that the depressedcondition seemed to be common to all manufacturing countries.An additional difficulty was  the uncertainty with regard tothe United States crop.   Enquiries were, however, beingmade and everything possible  was being done by his federation and the Manchester Chamber of Commerce with a view to gettingto the bottom of their troubles.   In the Egyptian Section,in the fine counts, business  was fairly good.   In the mediumcounts the position was not so satisfactory.     MR - THOMPSON  (Manchester merchant) agreed with Mr. Holroydthat there had been a set-back in the cotton trade, but he was of the opinion that this was  not a permanent condition.   he stated that action was being  taken with a view to facing thedifficulties of the industry  and endeavours were being made to  -regain lost markets.     COLONEL LYELL  (Public Works Contractor) stated thatthe point of view of the public works contractor was not clearly understood in Government Departments and they wereoften accused of lack of initiative in pursuing export business.It cost a great deal to put the necessary plant on the spotwhen undertaking an engineering contract and unless there wasa likelihood of other work being secured the business proved to be unremunerative.   Further, in new countries, particularly,there was always the danger of opposition from vested interests.If, however, there was any really good business going the publicworks contractors were prepared to do their best^to obtain it.He thought that chances of business being obtained in Brazilwere good, but prospects.were not so favourable in the Argentine.Mr. Hacking stated that recently he had noticed a change inthe reports of the situation  in the Argentine, which seemsd muchmore optimistic.     MR. BRUCE GARDNER (Iron  and Steel) said that the pig irontrade was in a depressed condition.   The production had fallen to 565,700 tons, while there were only 141 blast furnaces inblast, a drop of seven on the previous month.   The blast furnace figures compared with 176 this time last year;  148in 1925 and 185 in 1924.    The production of steel ingots had fallen to 709,000 tons as against 752,000 tons in May and747,000 in June, 1927.   The  June exports of tinplate- whichtotalled. 54,000 tons were the highest for 34 months and comparedwith 44,000 in June, 1927, and 39,000 in June 1925.In/
In the galvanised iron section of the trade there was nothing to complain about and makers were in a comfortable position.In the tin plate and galvanised sheet industries makers werein close touch with one another and were very well organised.In the heavy steel industry they were unable to compete on price and works were struggling under a load of underproduction.     MR. WOOLCOCK (Chemicals) stated that, as compared withJune, 1926 and 19^7, a steady but small advance had beenevidenced in June 1928.   This was a hopeful sign and wasinspiring confidence and one feature of the improvement wasthat the increases, though not large, were continuous.Increased exports had been made of tartaric acid, ammoniumsulphate, bleaching powder, coal tar products (in particularcarbolic acid and creosote), potassium and sodium chromates.There was a noteworthy expansion of export trade in dyes andintermediates, and also painters&apos; chemicals.   On the otherhand, there had been a falling off in exports of glycerineand sodium compounds.     MR. JOHNSTON (Pottery) said he had nothing satisfactory to report of the pottery industry, which was now occupying aconsiderable worse position.   In comparing the- May tradereturns with those for the corresponding month of last year,he pointed out that the exports of general earthenware andtiles had fallen.   In regard to sanitaryware exports had advanced by 15 to 20 per cent, in volume, but actually the values showed a drop of 15 to 20 per cent.   This was due tothe fact that prices had had to be reduced to obtain thebusiness.   The imports of sanitaryware and tiles had increased,in the case of the former by over 50 per cent.   The fine chinaindustry had obtained a safeguarding duty and he thought thatthey would reap the benefit now that the large imports prior tothe levying of the duty were almost absorbed.  - In the generalearthenware trade new competition was being experienced from czechoslovakia, Germany, France, Belgium, and Holland, and application would be made shortly under the safeguarding procedure.     MR. GORDON (Acting Indian Government Trade Commissioner)reported that the monsoon had commenced favourably, but that itwas too early to predict the character of the season.   The juteforecast estimated that the area would be down by 200,000 acresor 6% and as a result prices were maintained.   The&apos; industrialtrouble in the Bombay cotton mills still continued.   May wasa prosperous month for Indian trade, the balance in India&apos;s favour being Rs. 6,05 lakhs against 30 in the previous month andRs. 1,76 lakhs in the corresponding month of last year.     MR. CAMBIE.(Overseas Banking) said that his experience relatedmainly to .(Janada and he thought that that Dominion was on the eve of greater prosperity.   Crops were looking better at this time of year than for some years past, and it was possible thatthey would have the heaviest crop in history.   This would have important repercussions on this country, since much of the money would be spent here.   One thing that had impressed him in his conversations with Canadian business men was when they wantedquality they came to this country.                                                       MR./
     MR.  DODWELL (China Merchant Trade) said that tradewith China was more hopeful than trade in China.   Improvementwas toeing maintained in the South, but not in the Worth,where there was a tendency to wait and see what the Nationalistswere going to do in regard to customs and tariffs.   he understood that two Nationalist representatives were over here now for. the purpose of meeting prominent people with aview to improving relations between the two countries.

</content>
</cab>
