<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/197/0 images: 223-224</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government,Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1928.SECRET.                                                    Copy No.,.O.P.  287  (28).&apos;    28CABINET.NORTHERN IRELAND  UNEMPLOYMENT  INSURANCE  AGREEMENT.             MEMORANDUM BY  THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER.    ON  the  10th  February,  1926,  an Agreement  was made between the british treasury and the  Government of Northern Ireland to keep the Northern IrelandUnemployment Fund in parity with the British Unemployment Fund by  means ofspecial payments from the Treasuries of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, ofwhich approximately two-thirds are contributed by the British Treasury.   Owing tothe dependence of Northern Ireland on Shipbuilding and the Linen Trade, unemploy-ment  is  relatively higher  than in Great Britain,  and this is  likely to  continue,although the position is much better than it was in 1925-26.  The British Treasury&apos;spayments were  706,000 for 1925 (half-year),  880,000 in 1926 and  290,000 in 1927.    2.  The Government of Northern Ireland have asked that the Agreement, whichis due to expire on the 15th March, 1930, may be made permanent during the next session.  In return, they are willing to undertake to repay on the 31st March, 1929, 424,000 of  the pre-1925  Debt of the Northern Ireland  Unemployment  Fund (atpresent  3,424,000) and to pay off the balance of  3,000,000 in yearly instalments of 100,000.  This Debt carries interest at 5 per cent. ( 170,000), of which the british treasury contributes about two-thirds ( 113,000) under the Agreement.    3.  There is great force in the view of the Northern  Ireland Government thatthey  should  be relieved of a  great  part  of  the  burden  of isolating  from  theUnemployment Fund of the United Kingdom a population with a relatively  high rateof Unemployment, and I do not consider that it would be  reasonable to  refuse tocontinue  the Agreement of 1926.  By settling  the question now,  we obtain animmediate payment towards reducing the pre-1925 Debt and, in effect, save  14,000(two-thirds of the 5 per cent, interest on  424,000) in 1929.    4.  I attach a draft of the  Agreement which  I propose to conclude.   It willrequire confirmation by  a one-clause Act of Parliament, both here and in Belfast.Our legislation must be passed by about the 1st March, 1929, in  order to enable theNorthern Ireland Parliament to confirm the Agreement in time for the payment duethereunder on the 31st March, 1929, to be made.    5.  The cost of renewing the Agreement to the British Treasury will depend onthe state  of employment in both Countries from  the 1st April, 1929, onwards; under existing conditions the cost would be about  300,000 to  400,000 a year, diminishinggradually as the Interest ( 113,000) on the pre-1925 Debt decreases with the repay-ment of the debt.                                                                 w.  s. c.    Treasury  Chambers, S.W.1,          October 4, 1928.                           -  DRAFT AGREEMENT.    Whereas an Agreement was made between the Treasury and  the Ministry ofFinance for Northern Ireland on the 10th February,  1926, and confirmed by the parliaments of the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland with a view to assimilat-ing the burdens on the Exchequer of  the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of       [18245]
Northern Ireland per head of populations in respect of unemployment insurance, andwhereas the aforesaid Agreement expires on the 31st day of March, 1930.    The Treasury and the Ministry of Finance for Northern Ireland being desirousto continue the provisions of the aforesaid Agreement after the above-named; date,have entered into the following further Agreement :     1. The  provisions of Articles  1 to 8 of the Agreement of the  10th February,1926, shall continue to apply after the 31st day of March, 1930.     &apos; &apos;&apos;        . -    2. The  Government of Northern Ireland  will write  off  424,434  from theSuspense Deficit on the Unemployment Insurance Fund  on the 31st March, 1929,and will write off a further  100,000 on each succeeding 31st March  until the entireSuspense Debt is extinguished.    3. This agreement shall not come into operation until confirmed by Acts of the parliaments of  the  United Kingdom and Northern  Ireland, but  upon being soconfirmed shall apply so long as such Acts are in force.

</content>
</cab>
