<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/197/0 images: 236-246</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i 9is Document 1 s the property of His Brite^lc maximum jesty^ (kreeironsnt. CRET.                                                   GO.PY; NO. .  4^0. P.291(28).                          GAB I N E JP..                  &apos;  REDUGTION  OF  ARMAMENT S-          THE ANGLO-FRENCH NAVAL LIMITATION PROPOSALS.           Note by the First Lord of  the Admiralty.             In accordance with the instructions  of  the Cabinet,  I     circulate the appended note on the history  of recent  negotiations     for promoting a reduction of armamentss  and  some  replies  of  the     contentions contained in the American Noto,  and the many     unfounded suspicions raised by the Press  In  U.S.A.  and ignobly     supported by a considerable section of our  Press.             In drawing up this paper the Admiralty  have not framed     It In the form of a reply to the  American Note, and I am  not     myself in favour of sending a. reply to that  note  before the     Presidential Election.   At the  same time I  feel  most acutely  that     we are placing this country at a  very serious disadvantage by  not     giving to the public a frank explanation  of  the steps which  led     to the Anglo French proposal.             The American -Ambassador  when he  visited the Foreign  Office     as reported in a letter of the 18th September to  Mr.Chilton  seems     to have understood the reasons for our action,  but to have been     most adverse from any publication of them.    This  Is  easily     understood as the American position looks reasonable  KO long as     the mystery of the Anglo French negotiations Is kept  up.,   As  soon     as light Is thrown upon these proceedings, then the straight-     forwardness of our action in making -another  effort to assist this     Preparatory Commission and the fact that  the proposal was made     by the French and not by us, will stand  out  clearly,  and  the     obstinacy of the U.S.A. in refusing to discuss  any plan which  calls     for some sacrifice on their part  as well  as  on  that of other                                                                  nations/
nations will become apparent and put them in a much lessflattering light. -        From what little information we have been given, theJapanese Government seem to have agreed to discussion on theAnglo French lines, and, If that Is so, the sooner it Is publicljknown the better.        No attempt seems to have been made to accelerate a reply from Italy, but they have had a very long time to make up their minds,  and their dilatoriness Is an Insufficient reason fordenying ourselves the right of having the truth declared openly,Moreover the French are pressing for it.        I can find no adequate reply to the questions *  Whatwas the Anglo French question to which the American note-recently published  was a reply?   and how are the public toform any opinion on the answer without knowing the question?        I feel very strongly that without a reply being sent tothe U.so. note by the French or us, the history of what hastaken place between England and France ought to be made knownwi tho ut d e1ay o        The publication should be in the form of a statement andexplanation of the proposals to which the thS.A. note was a reply,  not of a reply to the U.S.A. note0W.  G.   B.ADMIRALTY a5th October, 1928.
          THE  ANGLO-FRENCH NAVAL LIMITATION PROPOSALS.     Historical.              It may  be  stated  that  at  the  beginning of this year no     concrete advance had been made sines  the  Washington Treaty     in  the direction of naval limitation.,  That treaty limited only     the  larger and  most powerful types  of ships,  namely,  capital     ships and aircraft carriers.   It  left unlimited all other     surface  vessels up to  the powerful  type of cruisers of 10,000     tons displacement  carrying an  8-inch  gun  armament.   It also     left unlimited  all submarines.              Siaice the  signing of that treaty  efforts have been     made, in accordance with  the requirements of the Treaty of     Versailles,  to  reach agreement in regard  to an extension of the     field of naval  limitation.   To this  end.  the Preparatory     Commission of the  League  of Nations has been working with the     object of preparing a  formula  which would be generally     acceptable and  could form the  basis for the naval clauses of the     convention which would finally have to be considered at the     Disarmament  Conference.              At an early stage of its  proceedings the Preparatory     Commission brought to  light two opposing  views as regards the     formula  for  naval  limitation,  namely, the British draft     proposals in which naval  limitation v/as to he effected by close     classification  and limitation  of  numbers  within each class,     and the  French  proposals  for limitation on a total tonnage     basis only,  giving complete freedom of construction within     that total tonnage. Division.ol0.192S.
        Generally speaking it may &quot;be said that America and Japanlent their support to the British proposals as   &quot;total tonnagecontained the germs of eventual competition and  would not lesseninternational suspicion, uneasiness and mistrust.&quot;   Italysupported the French proposals which, in their opinion, allowedgreater freedom and allowed them to keep their total tonnage lowwhilst permitting adequate construction of the types of vesselsbest suited to their financial and political  conditions.        Without entering Into the details of  subsequent discussionsit may be said that up to the meeting of the  PreparatoryCommission in March 1928, the only advance which had been made, towardsreconciling those opposing theories was that  we  on our part hadmodified our position that numbers should form the basis of limitation within classes and had accepted a  tonnage basis,whilstFrance had agreed to divide total tonnage into four groups, twoof which, namely, capital ships and aircraft  carriers, were already defined under the Washington treaty,  and two others,?namely, vessels under 10,000 tons and submarines.  A provision in the French proposals however giving freedom as desired&apos; to alter tonnage between divisions on giving one year&apos;s notice madethe proposals, actually little different to a  total global tonnage,and the gap therefore between the British and French thesesalmost as large as ever.        Italy never departed from her original attitude on globaltonnage.   Moreover at the naval conference which took place atGeneva between Great Britain, U.S.A. and Japan it was found that although Great Britain and America might be agreed on the general principle that naval limitation should be proceeded with under asystem of strict classification,  they were unable to agree as to  thepractical application of that principle.         /  Mr. Gibson at the 19th public meeting of the            3rd session of the Preparatory Commission 1927.
                      *?  3  rr        The British need for numbers of cruisers could not be reconciled on a satisfactory tonnage basis with the Americanneed for size.        As a result of the many discussions at meetingfe of thePreparatory Commission and the Geneva three-power conference,the failure to attain common ground for agreement made itapparent that the various interpretations of national needs for security, which forms the basis of limitation, could not as yet be expressed In too rigid a formula.        It was evident that within any scheme of limitation if agreement was to be reached at present to enable the Powers togo forward to a disarmament conference there would have to be ameasure of freedom for the expression of national requirements.Position in 1928.        Ii was to this aspect of the matter that H.M. Governmentdevoted Itself subsequent to the meeting of the preparatorycommission in March last, and conversations took place betweenthe French and British representatives with the object ofbridging the gulf indicated above.  When as a result of these discussions a French proposal was put forward for consideringnaval limitation on the lines of extending existing limitation,at the same time leaving freedom in less powerful types of vesselsit was felt that such a proposal, representing as It did anextension of the benefits of the Washington Treaty, would, if adopted, advance the cause of disarmament; and since under theproposal nations would have freedom to determine their particularneeds as regards security, it was thought that there was apossibility of reaching general agreement on this difficult problem.The present proposals.        After consideration the British and French Governmentsfelt  justified in proceeding on these lines, and in placing beforethe chief naval powers for their consideration proposals for a                                                   scheme/&apos;
scheme of limitation confined to -        (1)  Capital Ships.        (2)  Aircraft Carriers.        (3)  Surface vessels 10.000 tons and under              mounting guns of over 6&quot; and up to              8&quot; in calibre.        (4)  Submarines of over 600 tons displacementsleaving the present freedom in regard to other types.        A provision was inserted In the proposals fora clcn owl edging the sovereign rights of the different  Powersto build to the same maximum tonnage in Categories   (3) and(4), Categories (1) and (2)  being,, for the present,regulated &quot;by the Washington Treaty whilst a further  provisionallowed for the actual maximum tonnage in each of Categories(3) and (4) being fixed by agreements        It was believed that embodied in this compromise between &quot;global tonnage&quot; on the one hand and &quot;strictclassification&quot; on the other were considerations for theparticular needs of tho naval powers as these had been statedIn argument both at the meetings of the PreparatoryCommission and the Geneva three power conference.        Prance and Italy who desired, for financial  andpolitical reasons, freedom in their building programme, weregiven, under the proposals, a large measure of such  freedom.On the other hand... Groat Britain, Japan and the U.S.A. who desired classification obtained an extension of the classification already in force consequent on the WashingtonTreatysUa 11ed States arid Crulsers .        As regards the United States her experts had statedthat owing to her geographical&quot;position, separated from othercontinents by wide oceans,  and the lack of oversea bases,American needs required Cruisers of large radius of action,and that these requirements were not met by the smaller typeof Cruiser proposed by the British Delegation at the ThreePower Conference at Geneva.
        Bearing this in raind a smaller class regardsdisplacement was not introduced into the present proposals,the only restriction being in the maximum size of the guncarried, namely 6 inches..   Consequently the United states would under the proposals retain complete liberty to constructall her cruisers of the maximum-tonnage of 10,000 tons allowedunder the Washington Treaty.        The maximum radius of action possible under theWashington Treaty could therefore be obtained.        The imputation therefore in the American memorandum that the same proposal which was made at Geneva for a smallercruiser carrying a 6 inch gun was being repeated in thepresent proposals is not correcta  On the contrary the present proposals while limiting the number of ships carrying 8  inch guns allow for a large cruiser of 10,000 tons, if necessarygiving a radius of action greater that that of any cruiser nowin existence or projected.Ax-med Merchant Graisers *                                 -        A further objection, Trtilch it was understood atGeneva the United States had to a smaller type cruiser carrying a 6 inch gun, was the potential reserve of cruiser strength which the British had in their mercantile marine.  this objection has been met in the present proposals by allowingfreedom to the United States in the construction of lesspowerful cruisers which they might consider necessary in viewof the British, strength in merchant vessels.        It was recognised in framing the proposals that  an argument had been developed in the United States that the factthat a merchant ship could mount a gun of 6&quot; calibre necessitatedthat a cruiser should carry an 8&quot; gun armament.   The present proposals, it is true, did not ta.ke this argument into account                                                         as /
                                                          1 09                                                          J. W hi                     -  6  - &apos; .  .as It was believed, to be technically incorrect and would  notbe supported by instructed naval opinion.   A merchant vesselfrom its nature is not a fighting vessel and cannot  be made into  one capable of engaging with  success a cruiser carrying a 6&quot; gun.   Protection for personnel, protection for vitalmachinery, protection for magazines and control positions, firecontrol arrangements, torpedoes, are ail lacking In  the armed merchant cruiser.  Whatever, therefore, may be the valueattached to armed merchant cruisers mounting 6&quot; guns - theirfighting power Is not such as to necessitate in a cruiser agun of greater calibreo6 Inch gun In Cruisers.        At Geneva the American delegation argued for a cruiser class carrying an 8&quot; gun armament, the total  cruisertonnage being limited to about 250,000 to 300,000 tons.   TheBritish delegation argued that British requirements necessitat-cd a number of cruisers, and that if the 8&quot; gun armament  wasthe armament carried by all cruisers, our numbers could not  bemet on a low tonnage..  Further, the expense would be  high.        Accepted naval opinion has been, and Is, that if  allcruisers are to be permitted to mount 8&quot; guns,  then  the cruisers of all nations must carry this armament.  The 8&quot; gunwas accepted at Washington, but Its necessity is not  borne outby experience *  In the Interests of disarmament, the  size of guns should be kept as low as possible consistent with security and If there is to be no limit in this, the  most powerful type of cruiser,  the only result will be an  Increaseinstead of a reduction in expenditure.        We pressed,  therefore,  for limitation of the8gun type and the Introduction of a smaller type  mountinga 6&quot; gun by which British requirements could be met on a lowertonnage and at less expense.                                                          This/
                     -  7  -      0                           IS        This proposal for a cruiser class limited to cruisers of about 7,000 tons and below was not acceptable to the UnitedStates for the reasons given.        Under the present proposal,  whilst meeting theobjections of the United States in this respect, an endeavouralso has been made to meet- the British requirement by limiting the 8&quot; gun cruiser class and introducing a class&apos;of the sametonnage limits but carrying a gun 6n and below.  This will permit of our building 6&quot; small cruisers if we wish and Tilth agreater feeling of security than if the gun armament were not limited since,although under the proposals,other Powers in this class may build larger ships to meet their requirements, alarger gun cannot be carried.Submarines.        In regard to submarines, Great Britain and America bothstand for total abolition.  The other naval powers do not agreeand claim that in certain respects the submarine meets their particular requirements more efficiently than other classes ofvessels said that, therefore, they require a large proportionof their tonnage to be devoted to submarine construction.        The trend of naval discussion at Washington in 1922 andsubsequently has further indicated that neither on total abolition nor on a total tonnage limitation is agreement likelyto be obtained.        In the present proposals account is taken of the twodiametrically opposing standpointsc   A compromise is suggested,limitation being confined to the larger submarine, givingfreedom to nations who felt that their particular needsnecessitated numbers of submarines,  to construct such vesselsunder 600 tons.                                                         It /
ri  8        It was believed that.some compromise was necessary if agreement was to be reached between the two divergentviews and if submarine limitation was to be advanced.        For this reason we were prepared to accept the compromise.  Although the smaller type might not be suited tothe United&quot;States owing to her lack of oversea bases, thefreedom to build this type by other nations would not be aserious danger to her owing to her geographical position.Against Great Britain however all submarines large or smallbuilt by European Powers can be used offensively.  It wastherefore hoped that if we could, bring ourselves to accept this risk it was not one that the United States need refuseFuture Progress.        For the reasons given in the foregoing argument thopresent proposals, which are the outcome of all the discussions and conferences since Washington, represent an endeavour to advance naval limitation on an agreed basis, keeping in mind the naval needs of the different Powers and that the basis of limitation rests on the feeling of national security recognised in Article 8 of the Covenant of the League of Nations *        The American note of 28th September ends with a reference to the &quot;general plan&quot; of the American proposal atthe Geneva Conference and a suggestion that the needs of thenaval powers &quot;could be accomplished by permitting any of thepowers to vary the percentage of tonnage in classes withinthe total tonnage, a certain percentage to be agreed upon.If there was an increase in one class of vessel it should be deducted from the tonnage to be used in other classes&quot;.        Such a proposal does not reconcile, it is believed,the different needs of the naval powers as is attempted inthe present proposals, and is probably too rigid for those powers desiring a large measure of freedom.   Nor is it seenhow such a proposal will meet the British desire to effect                                                   e c on economy/
9195economy in the burden of armaments,  whilst maintaining navalsecurity.        Our experience has led vis to believe that the best prospect of arriving at a disarmament convention lies in preparing the ground for a convention embodying furtherextensions of the Washington Treaty in not too rigid a formula,leaving a degree of freedom for the expression of nationalneeds, and trusting that in the future further extension andmore rigid limitation may be possible owing to the improvedfeeling of security.        This was the aim in accepting the present proposalsfor extending the Washington Treaty to include the two nextmost powerful typos of war vessels.Note:-   Neither Great Britain,  Japan,  Prance or         Italy wish to continue building the         expensive 10,000 ton Cruisers; it is the         endeavour of the United States to force         on these Powers this large increase in         armaments which is not justified by war         experience^

</content>
</cab>
