<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/2/24 images: 324-337</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET;/,P.(RQ(39) 6k.Copy No.V/ A R    cabinet economic WarfareThird Monthly Report on the situation inGermany submitted by the Minister of economic warfare covering the period October 1st - October 31st(Previous Report:    Paper No, W.P.   (R)(39) 30)(Initialled)    R.  H.  C.Richmond Terrace, S.        1.November 2nd,  1939o

1 8. ft1 d JECONOMIC WARFARETHIRD MONTHLY REPORTON THE ECONOMIC SITUATION IN GERMANY,   COVERING THEPERIOD OCTOBER 1st to OCTOBER 31st 1939.Information now &quot;beginning to come in throws a good dealof light on Germany?s present economic situation.    The indirectevidence is perhaps of greater value, being less liable to aconscious or unconscious distortion by propaganda or as a relief to personal feelings,  while it is less likely to be a meredescription of local conditions, unrepresentative of the Reichas a whole .2.    INTERNAL CONDITIONS.The change so far brought about by the war in the dailylife of the average German is relatively not much greater thanthat in the life of the average Englishman,    Nevertheless,  sincethe average German began the war under economic conditions con-siderably the more stringent; his approach to the point where those conditions are no longer bearable is correspondinglynearer,  save in so far as his psychological training and outlookmay enable him to endure greater privations-3-        Ob ? last report drew attention to the dangerously low level of certain rations.      Some minor increases in the scalehave occurred,  a possibility foreseen, but there is now evidencethat in cities and crowded districts,  in Berlin,  the Ruhr,  andparticularly Vienna,   supplies available on v.ie spot do not always suffice to meet the authcrised demand.      On the otherhand, while the rationing system is rigorously applied in thelarger industrial towns,  in country districts there is virtually no system at all,  though conditions differ markedly from dis-trict to district,  varying with the local temperament and.politic?&apos;   conside.ations,      food queues are starting, dispersed,however,   in Dresden by a simple expedient.      The waiting women

1 e iJL \J JLare taken in police vans some distance out of town and left towalk home.hc       On the whole,  however, any apparent shortage of foodstuffsor of other domestic commodities such as soap,  is due toinefficiency in the distributing arrangements rather than to an actual national shortage,   though evidence of immediate anxietyover the fat supply is indicated by the urgency with which German&quot;buyers in adjacent neutral countries are instructed to purchasefats at any reasonable price,  so long as delivery is guaranteed.5.    EXPORT TRADE.Another factor contributing to local shortages of foodstuffs and consumption goods for domestic use is the exportation of these commodities and the re-exportation of imported foodstuffs for thepurpose of obtaining exchange..      In spite of a great scarcity inGermany, Dutch merchants are complaining that large consignments of soap have been dumped at very low prices in Holland,      Coffeeand tea, unobtainable in many German districts,  are being sold to Switzerland from stocks at Hamburg and Trieste.      Wheat has been freely offered in Belgium and Czech sugar in the Balkans,6,       Exports are being pushed by every conceivable means.    Anintercepted cable,  passing between the South American agent of aGerman firm and his principals, well reflects the object of thispolicy.      The agent urges his principals to hold out the hope offurther deliveries on condition that outstanding debts are paid;&quot;ho this&quot;,   says he,   &quot;even if delivery is quite impossible,  other-wise no-one will pay&quot;.      Considerable sales are recorded of goodsmanufactured from domestic raw materials,  rayon, machinery,  iron,steel,  zinc,  and even armaments,  though some of these last arecaptured Czech and Polish weapons.Nevertheless,   the German export drive is not uniformlysuccessfulc      It is now clear that there was little reality behindProdigal offers to supply all kinds of goods involving Germandeficiency/

IS?deficiency materials.      Whereas goods,  contracted for before theoutbreak of war, are still being delivered, complaints are&apos;becoming common about delays,  quality and prices of goods more recently offered,      Two separate incidents have come to noticeof an actual recall to Germany of consignments previously des-patched, which consisted largely of copper and cotton.    In sofar as trade with contiguous neutrals is concerned,  other thanthose whose exchange is an urgent necessity to Germany, a newtechnique is developing.      Manufactured goods containing deficiencymaterials are to be delivered only against the return of an equivalent quantity of the materials concerned.8c       There is also evidence that the clearing system is notworking as smoothly as in peacetime, particularly in the Balkans,where sales resistance is increasing.      Some of the commercialmessages going to Berlin are quite peremptory in tone.      ABulgarian supplier offers sunflower seeds at a high price.Payment must be made in dollars;    the bargain must be clinchedwithin 2b hours.      Roumania demands dollars from Germany.    the swiss refuse to supply foodstuffs outside the clearing,  though in parenthesis it must be recorded that they have agreed tofund the heavy German debt in the clearing until the end of thewar,9.       A most interesting aspect of German export trade, nowdisclosed by intercepted correspondence,  is the German expectation-tation early in the war that we should,  on one pretext or another, decide to seize German exports on the High Seas.    Thatwe have not done so is a blessing almost too good for them tocrodito      They nevertheless assume that we will take this actionsoon and are trying to make hay - or rather exchange - while thesunshine lasts,10&quot;  INDUSTRY AND STOCKS..,Further evidence is now available that our pre-war estimateof/

1 p 1-f o J0f German stocks of some important deficiency materials mayhave been too liberal.      There is statistical evidence notonly that the petroleum situation may become  acute next spring,but also that the iron situation may soon after be little lessdifficult.      Efforts to obtain copper, brass,  lead and cottonsuggest some  real anxiety for the future.      It is doubtful ifwell-informed business circles place much reliance on substan-tial help from the U.S. S.R.  being received in time.      A fewfactories,  including at least one munitions works, were held up for a period from lack of raw materials,  while reports ofdisturbances and delays in the Ruhr,  though much influenced bywishful thinking,  are now too numerous to discount altogether.11,      It would,  however, be a grievous error to suppose thatthe German industrial machine is on the verge of a breakdownyet.      So far as can be seen there is no reason to anticipatesuch a thing before next spring,   at the earliest.    Moreover,whether this situation will or will not develop in the futuremust depend to a very great degree on our ability meanwhileto prevent Germany obtaining additional supplies of her defi-ci ency c ommodities,12.     Hours of won,  are long.    Overtime pay has been abandoned.Labour shortages, particularly in the skilled trades,  are evidentfrom advertisements in the Press,  though there is also evidenceof some unemployment in the Ruhr,  probably in the semi-luxurytrad.es.      Bulgarian workers are to be imported to Vienna.German women from 16 to 60 have been virtually mobilised.Young German women have been repatriated from Poland for workin armament factories.,    Agriculture is to have first claim uponthe labour of other Poles and. prisoners of war.      The olderindustrialists prophesy woe, but the system carries on, with every evidence of its ability to continue tc do so for thepresent;.    And yet in this as in other respects the Germany ofto-day is not  the Germany of 191k but rather th; t of 1917.13.   INTERNAL/

1&apos; .** *J. o &amp;Measures adopted internally to provide wartime financeall bear the stamp of expediency and short-range ideas.     the banks are obliged to take up at relatively low rates of interest&quot;Wehrmachtverpflichtungscheinen&quot; with a maximum term of sixmonths.      The improbability that firms concerned will be ableto meet these on maturity renders them no more popular than their high sounding title.      The prepaid tax certificate systemappears to have broken down and there are some grounds forthinking that the farmers will not receive in cash the autumnpayments due to them.      A suggestion to this effect has,however, been accompanied by an announcement that a recentfurther levy upon the Jews will be earmarked for the relief of&quot;farmers suffering from foot and mouth disease and other dis-abilities&quot; .lb.      Taxation has increased heavily, but the burden appears to fall more hardly on the &quot;bourgeois&quot; than on the upper income levels.      Reichsbank returns show a decline in the note circu-lation below any figure hitherto announced during the war, Never-theless, the extent of fin;ncial control now operating in Germanyrenders banks, businesses and stock exchanges little more thanbook-keeping devices and makes all normal criteria dangerouslymisleading in appraising German financial conditions.    In general,however,  it is evident that the mass of the population retainsits marked fear of inflation,      A critical point is likely to arise if this fear leads to a non-cooperative movement and aflight into commodities which will render inevitable an uncon-trollable rise in prices.15- AND DEVI SEN,.Our previous report suggested that the figure of Germany&apos;sreserve of gold and devisen lay between AO and 75 millionsterling.      Further research allows us to estimate her totalforeign exchange resources at the outbreak of war at a maximum of 60/

of 60 million sterling.      Moreover, there is good reason tobelieve that only 15 million sterling of this sum was represented by foreign exchange.    If correct, this goes far towards explainingsome of the more unusual German transactions, though other reasonsmust be sought for a payment in dollars of twice the value of aMexican-owned cargo of chick-peas lying at Rotterdam.      Thisparticular deal was followed hy a reported sale of oil hy the mexican Government for delivery to German order.16.     Apart from such special incidents with a directly warlikeend in view, German exchange transactions in general disclose a steady purpose.      Every effort possible is being made to createcredits in those countries upon which Germany must chiefly relyfor her supplies of deficiency materials in face of Allied NavalControl.    Balkan purchasers are required to  settle in SwedishKroner.    Guilders are demanded from the Argentine and Venezuela,Swiss Francs from Siam,  and European currency as well as dollarsfrom Japan and Iran,      Moreover,  the Swiss Bank Corporation,  theRotterdamshe Bank Vereeniging,  the Hollandsche Bank Unie and theSvenska Handelsbanken are conspicuous among neutral businesshouses in opening credits to finance German imports from overseas,the majority of which the  cables freely state are to be shippedvia Italy.17.      The complex exchange problem is under the direction of Dr.Blassing, formerly of the Reichsbank and the Bank of InternationalSettlement and probably the ablest of Dr.Schacht&apos;s lieutenants.ALlied diplomatic and naval action,  if relentlessly pursued, may go far to thwart his plans to use adjacent neutral countries as achannel for vital supplies from overseas, but any measures takento reduce German exports through successful competition orseizure would materially hasten their defeat.


</content>
</cab>
