<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/19/41 images: 456-463</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1941.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (41)105th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 105 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime ministers room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, October 23, 1941, at12-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.j The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.&apos;The following were also present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and&quot; Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secretaryof State for the Colonies.Captain the Right Hon. H. D.Margesson, M.P., Secretary of Statefor War.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[23049]
WAR CABINET 105 (41).0ContentsMinuteNo.Subject.page 1 -     Naval, Military and Air Operations................     107Air Operations.Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations:U.S.S.R.Yugo-Slav rebellion.Casualties and damage.3      B.B.C.........      ........................     108Broadcast to Prance.5      France  ................................     108Fulfilment of undertakings by Great Britain.6      Finland, Hungary and Roumania   ....      ....      ....      ....     108Air Raids1084Air Bases in the Pacific108
107W.M. 105 (4d).Najal, Military 1. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following information in and Ate amplification of Cabinet War Room Records Nos. 779-781 -Operations.Summary of aircraft losses since the 20th October : (previous reference:W.M. (41) 104thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.naval operations.Shipping Losses.MilitaryOperations.U.S.S.R.YugoslavRebellion.Home Theatre Enemy 17 destroyed.4 probable.7 damaged.Otir Own 13 Fighters.20 Bombers.3 Coastal Command Aircraft.Overseas Theatre Enemy 1 probable.1 damaged.Our Own 8 destroyed.7 damaged.In Home Waters one small vessel had been hit and twoprobably hit. In the Mediterranean two enemy merchant vessels had been set on fire and one schooner, carrying ammunition,destroyed. Two promising attacks had been made on submarineson the 21st and 22nd October. Naples had been attacked on the night of the 21st/22nd with satisfactory results.Of forty-nine enemy aircraft which had operated against thiscountry on the previous night (not all over land), three had certainlybeen destroyed and one probably.During the previous three days, excluding the U.S. ship Lehigh,4,000 tons of shipping had been sunk and 8,000 tons damaged.On the Northern fronts there had been no change. South ofLeningrad the Germans had crossed the River Volkhov at twoplaces, but their attacks had been held. There had been heavy fighting in the Kalinin sector.In the Central Sector a break-through near Mohaisk had beenheld. In the Kharkov area there had been no change, but thesituation was difficult in the Donetz Basin. The Germans hadwidened their front north of the Sea of Azov by the capture ofStalin, and their attack on the Crimea had been renewed.General Zhurkov was now in command of the Central sector and Marshal Timoshenko of the Southern Sector. MarshalsVoroshilov and Budenny were being employed in raising newformations.The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairsenquired if we were in a position to inform Yugoslav authoritieswhether we could give any help available to those forces who had raised the standard of revolt in Yugoslavia.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that telegramshad been sent to the Commanders-in-Chief in the Middle Eastimpressing on them the importance of affording help.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.[23049]
Air Raids. 2.   The Minister of Home Security reported that on the nightCasualties and of the 20th/21st some twenty enemy aircraft had flown across the damage. North Midlands and South Lancashire areas.   The casualties had(Previous been 12 killed, 118 injured.   On the night of the 21st/22nd some reference: 40 machines had attacked Tyneside and Tees-side, the casualtiesW.M. (41) 102nd being 31 killed and 49 seriously injured.   On the previous nightConclusions, Merseyside, North Wales and the West Midlands had been attacked.Minute 3.) The casualties so far reported had been 5 killed and 7 injured.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement. .B,B*C- 3.   The attention of the War Cabinet was called to a broadcastBroadcast to by the B.B.C. to the French people on the previous night, urgingPrance. them not to take rash action.The Minister of Information was invited to enquire into thematter, bearing in mind that it was not the policy of the WarCabinet to discourage individual acts by French patriots against their German oppressors.Air Bases in the 4. The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignPacific. Affairs said that the American Ambassador had approached theForeign Secretary in regard to the establishment of air bases in the pacific, for an air route from Honolulu to the Philippines. the ambassador had suggested that, if the matter could be settled inprinciple, arrangements could then be made for officials of the war department to make contact with local officials in the Pacificterritories concerned.After a short discussion, in the course of which the Secretaryof Sta,te for Dominion Affairs said that it would be necessary to approach the Dominion Governments in this matter The War Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with theMinisters concerned, to arrange for the issues involved tobe carefully examined and a considered recommendationsubmitted to them.France.Fulfilment of undertakings by great Britain.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 59thConclusions,Minute 7.)Finland,Hungary and roumania.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 104thConclusions,Minute 6.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (G) (41) 114) explaining that afull record of the facts regarding our pre-war obligations to Franceand the steps taken to give effect to them had now been prepared,but that it was undesirable to publish any public statement on thesubject at the present time.The War Cabinet expressed agreement with this view.6. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum on thissubject by the Foreign Secretary (W.P. (41) 245).In this Memorandum the view was expressed that thearguments against declaring war on these three countries wereoutweighed by the importance of not rebuffing or discouraging ourRussian allies.The Home Secretary gave particulars of the number of aliensof the countries concerned in the &quot;United Kingdom, which were asfollows : FinlandHungaryRoumania5003,7002,700
Plans had been agreed between Departments as to the steps tobe taken as regards Hungarians and Roumanians in this country if war was declared. As regards Finland, there were between 200and 300 Finns serving either in British ships or in Scandinavianships chartered to the British Government who were willing tocontinue in this service so long as there was no outbreak of war.If, however, war was declared, they could not continue to serve inthe British service. It did not, however, follow that they wouldhave to be interned.The general view of the War Cabinet was that the disadvan-tages of declaring war on these three countries were considerable.No action could, however, be taken, or any final decision reached,until we had consulted the United States of America and theDominions.The point for immediate decision, therefore, concerned theterms of the communications to be sent to the U.S.A. and theDominions. The general view of the War Cabinet favoured a balanced statement of the position, making an enquiry as to theviews of those Governments, but without expressing any decidedpreference for declaring war on Finland, Hungary and Roumania.The Foreign Secretary was invited to prepare draft telegrams to the United States and to the DominionGovernments (the latter in consultation with the dominions secretary) and to submit them to the Meeting of the WarCabinet to be held on Monday, the 27th October.Great George Street, S.W. 1,October 23, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
