<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/145/0 images: 90-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PPv.QPER.TY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(69) 13913th October, 1969COPY NO.CABINETNORTHERN ireland note by the Secretary of State for the Home department i circulate for the information of my colleagties the text of the communique issued affer my discussions on the 9th and 10th October withthe Northern Ireland Government.L. J. C.Home Office, S.W.1.13th October, 1969
ANNEXCOMMUNIQUE ISSUED FOLLOV/ING THE.HOME.....SECRETARY VS,DISCUSSIONS &quot;glTH. THE NORTHERN IRELAND GOVERNMENT&quot; OS 9TH AND 1OTH OCTOBERDuring bis second visit to Belfast the Home Secretary,Mr. James Callaghan, accompanied &quot;by the Minister of State,Home Office, Lord Stonham3 attended a series of meetings withthe Northern Ireland Cabinet on 9th and 10th October,2,    The Ministers of both Governments expressed their appreciation of the work of the . Army in the very arduous tasks it has had toundertake in support of the civil power,3, The Ministers discussed the report on the recruitment,organisation, structure and composition of the Royal ulster constabulary (R.U.C.) and the uister Special Constabulary(U.S.C.) submitted to the Northern Ireland Minister of HomeAfiairs by the Advisory Committee under the Chairmanship ofLord Hunt. Northern Ireland Ministers informed the HomeSecretary that:-(a) They accepted the principle of a civiliarised andnormally unarmed Royal Ulster Constabulary-(b) They agreed that, subject to further consideration ofits composition, a   Jolice Authority should be constituted,representative of the community as a whole, to whichthe Inspector-General of the RaU.C. should, beaccountable.(c) They agreed to a closer association of the R.U.C. with british police forces.     Further discussions will takeplace with the United Kingdom Government as to how this may be achieved.     In this context the Home secretary is anxious to devise arrangements for mutual assistance between the R.U.C. and British polics forces in suchmatters as training facilities, the secondment of personnel and the temporary reinforccaont    of theR.U.C. in emergencies.(d) They accepted in principle that the police should be relieved of all responsibility for prosecutions, andthat a system of independent public prosecutors should beadopted.Co)   Ihey agreed that tho U.S.C. should &quot;be replaced by two&apos;newforces(i)    a volunteer reserve for routine police dutiessuch as traffic control;   and(ii)    a locally-recruited military force to protectkey installations and to undertake such othertasks as might be necessary to guard againstthe threat of armed guerilla-type attacks.
This force will be commanded by the GeneralOfficer Commanding, Northern Ireland, who willwork in the closest consultation with theGovernment of Northern Ireland, through a security Committee presided ovex1 by theMinister of Home Affairs0ij.0    In conveying these decisions, Northern Ireland Ministersstated that they considered it essential that:-(a) The adoption of the principle of an unarmed police force should in practice depend upon assessment ofthe security sitxxation as it exists throughout NorthernIreland and in particular areasD(b) The arrangements for the raising of a new securityforce should be set an foot without delay and onceconstituted there sho ild be no change in that forcewithout the fullest consultatioh with the Governmentof Northern Ireland.(c) The U.S.C., as at present organised,  should remain in being until a fully effective security force was available to replace it0(d) The vital interests of the Northern Ireland Gover-nmentin the defence of the province should be recognised by continuing arrangements for the fullest consultation as to the policy for use of the new force, and(e) A fully adequate military garrison should be maintained in Northern Ireland and there should be effective machinery for the swift deployment of army units inNorthern Ireland including units of the new locallyrecruited force, in the event of any thxteat to security.J5o   The Home Secretary, on behalf of the United Kingdom Government *gave assurances that these requirements would be fully metvithin those fields for which the United Kingdom  Government]were responsible.j6o    Northern Ireland Ministers informed the Home Secretary thatMr, J, a. Peacocke had submitted his resignation as Inspector-general of the RJJoC. and that to succeed him the Minister ofHome Affairs had recommended to the Governor the appointment:] of Sir Arthur Young, Commissioner of the City of LondonjPolice.     The Home Secretary expressed his complete confidenceIin this appointment and shared the Northern Ireland GovernmentsI appreciation of the generous action of the Corporation of LondonI in agreeing to release Sir Arthur Young.-2-
7,    The Ministers reviewed the present economic and industrialprospects of Northern Ireland in the light of an appraisalb/ a mission of representatives of Whitehall departmentsundertaken at the invitation of the Northern ireland government o80    They noted that the direct effects of recent disturbanceson trade and industry had proved to be limited in extent and of short duration.     They re-affirmed that the achievement of an acceptable rate of industrial expansion remained an essential element in the future economic development of the province,,9,    The Northern Ireland Government welcomed the full and &amp;aerous support of the United Kingdom Government in makingpossible the decisions that they had taken following the reportof the United Kingdom mission to maintain the momentum of industrialinvestment8     The Ministers noted that, while the rate of promotion of new jobs in 1969 had been in line with presenttargets, a source of concern to potential investors was the availability of a satisfactory assurance against loss in theevent of further disturbance.     To provide an immediateassurance to new manufacturing projects, it has been decidedto introduce for a limited period a scheme of free compensationagainst damage arising from riot or civil commotion, includingconsequential loss, which would form a supplement to new agreements for assistance under the Industries Development Acts,,10,  To encourage a still higher rate of expansion, it has beendecided, for a period of three years, to increase by 5 per cent the rates both of investment grants and of grants payable underthe Industries Development Acts.     This means that the standard rate of investment grants payable without employment test willbecome 45 per cent, with a rate of grant of up to 50 per cent for projects offering worthwhile additional employment.     these measures are estimated to cost some  3 th0 in a full yearBThe Ministers agreed that the Northern Ireland Government should indicate their intention, at a further cost of some  1 05 m0 to retain for a further year until April 1971 the additionalselective employment payment of 7s o 6d. a man per week, which1 is to be discontinued in Development i*reas in Great Britain! from April 1970.11.  These measures have particular relevance to the linger term economic prospect.     The Ministers agreed that meanwhile thej Prospects for employment in the coming winter, particularlyin certain localities, remained a matter of great concern.     Iti has accordingly been decided to initiate a programme of works costing up to  2 m. for the relief of unemployment this winter,I The w^rks will be mainly concerned with roads, forestry and landI reclamation, as well as amenity schemes and tourist developmentj WQrk in outlying areas.     This will provide some 2,500 new jobs.
120    The Home Secretary reiterated the close and continuinginterest of the United Kingdom Government in the economic well-being of Northern Ireland which could be promoted only by thefullest co-operation &quot;between the two Governments,     The presentdecisions fell within the existing framework, of financial arrangements between the two    Governments,,     He affirmedthe intention of the United Kingdom Government to cover the agreed capital requirements of Northern Ireland on a continuingbasis,13.   The Ministers discussed the reports received by the NorthernIreland Government from the joint working parties which had reviewed the adequacy of present practice or pledged commitment to ensure:(i) The promotion of good community relations by methodsincluding the prohibition of incitement to religioushat red0(ii)   The avoidance of any discrimination in any formof public employment.(iii)   The fair allocation of houses by public authorities.1h.   A Minister of Community Relations had been appointed and aBill to set up a Community Relations Commission had already received a Second Reading in the House of Commons.     The dutiesof the Commission would include encouraging the establishment ofharmonious community relations and advising Northern ireland ministers on questions relating to community relations.     TheCommission would be authorised to assist local bodies concernedwith community relations, to provide training courses, to promoteconferences, and to undertake research.15.   A Bill had been introduced to establish a Commissioner forcomplaints to deal with complaints of maladministration (whichwould include religious discrimination) by local authorities or public bodies.     It will be the duty of the Commissioner to investigate complaints, to attempt to conciliate the two parties and, if that proves impracticable, to indicate what remedy isrequired to provide a fair settlement to cure the effects ofthe maladministration.     He will have power to compel the attendance cf witnesses and the production of papers.     Not onlymay an aggrieved person seek remedies in the courts as an ultimatesanction but an injunction may be sought in the High Court to restrain a local or public body from any continuing course ofmaladministration.16.   The Government of Northern Ireland have decided to introducean anti-discrimination clause in all Government contracts.17.   Northern Ireland Ministers indicated their intention of keeping under review the adequacy of the existing law againstincitement.-h-
180   The Minister of Community Relations will he considering what further action to prevent discrimination in other fields mightbe desirable0     Northern Ireland Ministers had approved aseries of detailed recommendations designed to reinforce the safeguards against discrimination in public employment and agreedthat consultations should be set on foot at once with the variousemploying authorities and staff associations.     The main pointsdecided were:(a) The Joint Working Party found, that the Civil Serviceof Northern Ireland deservedly enjoys a high reputationfor fairness and impartiality in Its employment practices and is open to criticism in only a few minor aspects0Action will be taken in respect of these,,     The powersof the Northern Ireland Parliamentary Commissionerfor Administration will he extended to personnelmatters In the Civil Service.(b) In those parts of public employment where the Governmentare not the direct employer, each employing body willbe required to make a declaration that its aim is tohave equality of employment opportunity without regard to religious or political considerations,,(c) Every public body should have an approved code ofemployment procedure.     Discussions will take placeimmediately with the iGcal authority associations andwith statutory bodies.(d) A permanent statutory Local Government Staff commission will be established with strong advisory powers toassist local authorities in the selection of candidates for senior and designated appointments9 and a continuing duty of reviewing appointment procedures.While the structure of local government is being reviewed these functions will be assumed by an interim commission acting on a non-statutory basis.(e) The idea of a Public Service Commission, concernedwith certain aspects of staffing throughout the public sector, including both local government service and the6ivi3 Service, raises far-reaching questions but willhe further studied with a -tfiew to a report being put before the Northern Ireland Government as soon aspossib le.19a   The Joint Working Party on Housing Allocations, as well asdealing with methods of allocation, also brought to notice the much wider problem of the housing programme:    the waiting lists,the age of much of the existing stock, and thus the great needfor urgent schemes of redevelopment.-5-
20o   In its work on the development programme for the next fiveyears the Government of Northern Ireland have concluded thatan expanded housing programme is essential on social and economic grounds for the future welfare of Northern Ireland.21.   The Working Party had found that despite excellent recent^progress by the housing authorities which compared veryifavourably with that in Great Britain there are still substantialS shortages in mapry areas.     Moreover, on present evidence theSproportion of outworn houses needing replacement, which isibelieved to number some 100,000, is substantially higher thanthat in England and Wales.     No more than 3*500 were dealt withlast year in Northern Ireland.     The Government have concluded&quot;that this is an emergency situation requiring emergency measures,they have therefore decided reluctantly that local authorities arejnot geared - and cannot be geared - to handle such a task andI that the best hope of success lies in the creation of a singlepurpose, efficient and streamlined central housing authority;l(helped by the development commissions in their own areas) to tackle this most urgent problem.22.   This difficult decision was taken by the Government only aftermuch anxious thought and advice from various bodies.      TheGovernment are convinced that the disadvantages are clearlyioutweighed by the advantages to the whole community to be derived;from a much larger housing programme.      It was recognised by thejHome Secretary that this decision to set up a central housing(authority would have financial consequences which will be urgentlydiscussed between the two Governments.23.  Both Governments recognise that private enterprise has a major role to play and the Northern Ireland Government will consider what further measures might be taken to stimulatejprivate house-building.     The financial cost of such measurespill be examined by the Ministry of Finance and the  Treasury injthe normal way,?h.  The Northern Ireland Government declared their intention thatthere should be a phased transfer of housing to the central[authority and it would immediately enter into discussions with thejfjocal Authority Associations,   tire&apos; Staff Associations andpe Housing Trust on the many complex problems which will arise,jso as to ensure that there is a smooth transfer and no disruptioniof current housing programmes.     Among the many advantages not
previously referred to which will &quot;be gained from this new initiative the Government foresee: a common public authorityrent structure throughout Northern Ireland:    Improved mobility,which is the key to regional development,-    an end to allegationsabout sectarian discrimination in housing allocations;    the attraction of more high-quality professional and administrative staff to housing work and the opportunity to use modern,efficient management techniquesj    economies of scale;organisation of contracts to ensure a steady demand on housingcontractors and thus more efficient building;    elimination of unnecessary variety coupled with greater opportunities for research and experiment;    the introduction of advanced estate management throughout the country which will be in the hands of qualified housing managers;     but above all a new opportunityto solve Northern Ireland&apos;s housing problems in the foreseeable future.25.   The Home Secretary endorsed the finding of the Joint working party that the Ministry of Developments model points scheme wassoundly based and supported the measures being taken by theNorthern Ireland Government to have it adopted by all authoritiesduring the interim period.26,   The Northern Ireland Government proposed to mount a survey of the condition of the housing stock in Northern Ireland inorder to establish objectively the extent to which housing conditions vary in different parts of Northern Ireland and toenable objective comparisons to be made with those in England andWales.27.   It was recognised that the decision to set up a centralhousing authority had important consequences.     Firstly, a concerted housing drive will require the assured provision ofwater and sewerage and their organisation on a scale and instep with house-building;    j?.oad programmes to suit;    and above all the prompt release of land for housing estates, redevelopmentand attendant social and recreational services.     Secondly, the consequent shape and size, and especially the staffing of local councils without housing functions will have to re-assessed,together with the implications for the social services at presentdischarged by local government - health, welfare, child care,education and libraries - whose future administrative structureis also under review.28.   To-those ends, the Government of Northern Ireland proposedto set up a review body which would be broadly based and include representatives of the two main religious denominations as wellas of business, professional and trade union interests to review in conjunction with the Ministries-- in Northern Ireland and localauthorities current proposals for reshaping local administration-7-
and to advise on. the most efficient distribution of the relevantfunctions under the Parliament and Government of NorthernIreland.29.   The United Kingdom Government recognise the validity of thoseconsequences of the major decision on the housing drive and fully support the proposal to set up a review body on local administration.30    The Ministers of both Governments agreed that the decisionsmade following the report of the Police Advisory Committee,together with the measures designed to stimulate the economy of the province, and the steps taken by the Northern ireland government to ensure a common standard of citizenship constituted a comprehensive programme of reform which gave to all citizens of Northern Ireland the opportunity to live in harmony and prosperity and deserved the full support of everyone.10th October 1969-8-CONRDENTBAL


</content>
</cab>
