<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/145/0 images: 158-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(69) 148 COPY NO.28th October, 1969CABINETINDUSTRIAL RELATIONS bill memorandum by the First Secretary.of State and Secretary ofState for Employment and ProductivityIt was agreed by Cabinet at its meeting on 9th October(CC(69) 47th Conclusions, Minute 4) that a comprehensive industrial relations Bill should be introduced in the forthcoming parliamentary session?  and that the Industrial Relations Committee should consider in detail which of the proposals outlined in the White Paper &quot;In Placeof Strife&quot; should be included in this BilL    The Social services committee had already agreed that the legislation to amend trade dispute disqualifications for unemployment benefit should be includedin the National Superannuation and Social Insurance Bill.    Since thatmeetings the Industrial Relations Committee has discussed proposals  put to them (Annexes I and II) and has agreed that a Bill on the linesof Annex I should be prepared - subject to further consideration of thetwo matters discussed below.Inducement of a breach of a commercial contract; the problem of the secondary boycott2.      In the White Paper, the Government expressed agreement withthe Donovan Commission^ recommendation that strike leaders shouldbe protected from any legal action for inducing a breach of any commercialcontract (not just a contract of employment),,    An ameniment of this kind would mean that there would be a clarification of the law which would makeit plain that &quot;secondary boycott&quot; activities are lawful.    The arguments infavour of carrying out the undertaking in the White Paper are these-(i) In some measure secondary boycott activities are already legal and a skilful and well-informed trade union leader can usually manageto avoid any liability for legal action,(ii)  There are a number of anomalies in the existing law which shouldbe removed for the sake of clarity and consistency,
(iii) Action falling short of the White Paper proposal would antagonisethe Trades Union Congress (TUC) and open a flank to hostile amendments which would be difficult to resist.,30      While the force of these arguments was acknowledged by theIndustrial Relations Committee,, it was pointed out nevertheless thatthere were powerful arguments against proceeding with the government proposal in the White Paper,    It was suggested that the clarification ofthe law would have the practical effect of extending the immunity of secondary boycott activities;  and this would be widely interpreted as an encouragement to official and unofficial strikers to prosecutetheir interests.    This could have serious economic consequences,4,      The Ministerial Committee on Industrial Relations requiresmore time to consider this important question,,    It will be meetingagain on 29th October tor thi^ purpose and I sha.!l report on the outcomeorally to my colleagues,,Requirements concerning auditors of superannuation funds5,      The Industrial Relations Committee suggested that I should consider incorporating in the Bill the White Paper proposal relatingto audit and superannuation requirements.    These requirements wererecommended by the Chief Registrar of Friendly Societies in his evidence to the Donovan Commission, and were endorsed by the Commission in itsReport,    Their practical effect would be to strengthen and supplement theexisting financial requirements of the 1871 Trade Union Act by applying toregistered trade unions and employers&apos; associations the more rigorousobligations which Friendly Societies and similar institutions have tosatisfy.    Under the proposals, all trade unions and employers&apos;associations would have to keep their accounts in a form similarto that required by the Friendly and Industrial and Provident SocietiesAct 1968 and the annual return would have to be accompanied by a copyof the accounts and balance sheets and by the auditor Js report (fororganisations over a certain size, the audit would have to be performed by a qualified auditor).    The proposals concerning superannuationschemes are designed to ensure that members of trade unions and employers&apos; associations have access to reliable information aboutthe viability (or otherwise) of new and existing superannuation schemes,6,      These proposals could be embodied in the Industrial relations bill without great difficulty as an extension to existing obligations onorganisations voluntarily registered under the Trade Union Act 1071,The fact that the proposals are modelled on requirements which alreadybear on Friendly Societies means that no new questions of principle arebeing advanced; and this should make the form of the requirementsgenerally acceptable,,    Nor does the enforcement of these requirementsinvolve the introduction of new penalties; organisations registered underthe Trade Union Act 1871 are already subject to penalties of the same Jcxdas it would be necessary to provide for in an Industrial Relations Bill0-2 &quot;*
There should therefore be little ground for opposition from the TUC onthis score,    Nevertheless, in view of their extreme sensitivity on thematter of rules and any extension of registration provisions I proposefirst to consult them and not to press this minor point if it were to leadto a major row.    V/ith mis proviso.- I recommend that the industrial relations Bill should include provisions concerning the appointmentof auditors and the examination of superannuation funds.Conclusions7.      Subject to the. conclusion to be reached on the inducement ofa breach of a commercial contracts I invite my colleagues to agreethat I should now start consultations with the TUC and the confederation of British Industry on the proposed scope of the Bill and should put inhand the preparation of a Bill containing the items in Annex L.8. I also invite my colleagues to agree that authority should be givenfor the confidential preparation of legislation on the topics in Annex III.B, A0 C.Depaitment of Employment and Productivity, S. V/.1.28th October, 1969
annex.   INOTE ON THE MAIN ITEMS FOR INCLUSION IN a comprehensive INDUSTRIAL REL ATIONS bill the main items proposed for inclusion in a comprehensive IndustrialIllations Bill may be conveniently grouped under the following headings:A, The extension and reform of collective bargaining.B, Protection of the individual employee.C, Changes in existing law governing trade unions and industrial disputes.D, Other possible items., THE EXTENSION AND REFORM OF COLLECTIVE BAR&amp;AININS-, Putting the Commission on Industrial Relations (C.I.R.) on a statutory basisAt present the C.I.R. has the status of a Royal Commission, and it would beossible to continue on this basis if administrative and financial considerationsere paramount.   But if the Commission is to have some important statutory functionsfor example, holding ballots and making recommendations in relation to recognitioniroblems) and if it is to have the necessary standing it will be desirable to maketa statutory body (cf., the National Board for Prices and Incomes).   The T.U.C.ay.be lukewarm about giving statutory powers to the C.I.R;   and could, in particular,lehostile to the proposal to empower the C.I.R. to conduct a ballot in aaognition dispute.!i  Pov/er to make recognition ordersIt is proposed that the Secretary of State should be able to make an order,in the recommendation of the 6.1.11., requiring an employer to recognise and negotiateiith a union.   If the employer refused to obey such an order, the union would havethe right unilaterally to refer a claim for arbitration by the Industrial Court.In inter-union recognition disputes, the T.U.C. would normally assume the mainresponsibility for resolving the problem;   and there would be a reference to the(&apos;I.R. of such disputes only if the T.U.C. failed to find a satisfactory solution,&quot;the employer refused to adopt the T.U.C.&apos;s formula (or, perhaps, if the disputeinvolved non-affiliated unions).   These powers are likely to be important torelatively weak unions, or unions operating in sectors of industry where in the past*wnisation has not been extensive (for example, the white-collar sectors).   Thel&apos;&apos;.C, will in general welcome powers to compel employers to recognise trade unions;^ will look very closely at the way such powers are to be applied in inter-unionignition disputes./3.    Disclosure of
i    Disclosure of information to unions by managementIt is proposed that there should be a general obligation on employers tomake available to the unions with whom they negotiate information which isnecessary to make a reality of collective bargaining.   The Bill might also providepower for the Secretary of State to make regulations specifying the kinds ofinformation which employers should make available.   The disclosure of information is obviously an important aspect of &quot;good faith&quot; in negotiations, and will becomemuch more important as the centre of gravity of collective bargaining moves from industry to company level.   Unions cannot be expected to play their part in productivity bargaining without a reasonable knowledge of the plans, operations and costs, etc. of the companies with whom they negotiate.   This proposal shouldbe welcomed by the T.U.C.k&apos;   Amendments to the Wages Councils act the Department have in mind a number of amendments to the Wages CouncilsAct which will have the effect of making it easier to abolish Wages Councils, andwhich would also be intended to support and encourage the development of genuinecollective bargaining in Wages Council industries.   These changes have been pressed by the T.U.C. and will be generally welcomed by tho trade unions.5.   Trade Union Development SchemeIt is proposed to establish a fund, to be administered by the C.I.R., whichwould provide financial assistance to unions in implementing plans for rationalisingtheir organisation and improving their services to members.   Such assistance might in certain circumstances facilitate mergers or amalgamations.    It could also beused to support additional training courses for trade union officials;    or toenable a union to extend and rationalise its office facilities.   The T.U.C. hasbeen wary and unenthusiastic in its reception of this proposal;   but the G-eneralCouncil will probably acquiesce in any provisions to give effect to the proposal.B.   PROTECTION 0? THE INDIVIDUAL EMPLOYEE6&apos;   The right to belong to a trade unionIt is proposed that it should become a term of all contracts of employmentthat the employer is not to do anything to deter or obstruct an employee frombelonging to a trade union, or to penalise any employee on account of his trade&quot;W-on membership (for example, by refusing to promote him).   This contractualterm will be enforced by actions brought by employees before the IndustrialTribunals, which will have power to award damages (the basis on which damages, /should
should be assessed is still under consideration;   there have been a number ofreservations expressed about the earlier proposal that damages should be a fixedsum regardless of the circumstances).   The T.U.C. is naturally favourable to aprovision of this nature, though the General Council may doubt whether it willhave a major impact.1-    Unfair dismissalsEmployees are to have the right to compensation or reinstatement if dismissedfor &quot;invalid&quot; reasons (for example, trade union membership or participation in trade union activities;    or on grounds of race, colour, sex or marital status, etc.)or where the dismissal cannot be justified by reasons connected with the capacityor conduct of the employee or the operational requirements of the business.    TheT.U.C. are known to attach a great deal of importance to these provisions, whichwill undoubtedly be a major part of the Bill.   Although accepting the majorprinciple involved, the C.B.I. has a number of reservations on the detail.8.    Extension of the jurisdiction of the Industrial TribunalsThe jurisdiction of the Tribunals will have to be extended to enable it toconsider cases brought under Items 6 and 7 above.   It is also proposed to extend their jurisdiction to cover other legal disputes arising out of the terms of individual contracts of employment, and other statutory rights which the employeepossesses.   This vail mean in practice that the Tribunals will replace theordinary courts in the majority of disputes between the individual employee and the employer which cannot be satisfactorily resolved under grievance procedures.   TheT.U.C. has expressed fears that, in practice, the Tribunals might tend to inhibitthe development of collective bargaining and satisfactory grievance procedures by encouraging employees to go direct to the Tribunals if they feel aggrieved.   they therefore consider that the extension of the Tribunals&apos;  jurisdiction should belimited to items 6 and 7 above.,9.   Amendments to the Contracts of Employment ActIt will be desirable to take the opportunity afforded by this legislation tomake a few amendments to the Contracts of Employment Act;    for example, to increasethe period of notice to which long-service employees are entitled, and to widen thescope of matters covered in the written statement which an employee receives onJoining a firm.   The LUX. have in principle welcomed the Government proposal./C.     CHANGES5.
0,    CHANGES IN EXISTING- LAW GOVERNING- TRADE UNIONS AND INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES10.  Modification of Section 4(4.) of the 1871 Act and Amendment of the definition of a trade unionAgreements between employers&apos; associations and trade unions are not normally directly enforceable because, as a result of the wording of Section4(4), the courts are not free to enforce agreements between one trade union and another (and many employers&apos; associations are trade unions within themeaning of the lav/).    If we amend the definition of a trade union - as thefhite Paper proposed - it is probable that Section could be left as it is,since employers&apos; associations would then no longer be trade unions in law.The T.U.C. would nonetheless want it made quite clear that as the White Papersuggested - agreements between employers&apos; associations (or employers) and a trade union or trade unions were to be directly enforceable only if there was an express written provision in the agreement to that effect (the Conservativeview is that collective agreements should be assumed to be legally enforceableunless the parties agree otherwise).11.   Enabling a union to be sued in tortAs the law stands at present, a trade union (though not its officials) isalmost completely protected from actions in tort.    In principle, it is bothunjustifiable and unnecessary that unions should be able to avoid any liability for torts which have nothing to do with industrial action and are not committed in furtherance of a trade dispute.    It is therefore proposed to amend Section 4of the 1906 Act to restrict tho protection to torts committed in contemplationor furtherance of a trade dispute.   This will make it possible, for example, foran action to be brought against a union for such civil wrongs as libel,negligence, conversion, etc, committed in its name by its officials.    So longas the concept of &quot;furtherance of a trade dispute&quot; is broad enough, the T.U.C.is unlikely to resist a provision of this nature.12.   Protection of inducement of breach of a commercial contractThe existing lav/ is unclear and ambivalent in its treatment of secondaryboycott activities (i.e., bringing pressure to bear on one employer inPursuance of a dispute with another).    Some forms of pressure are regarded aslawful, whilst others may give rise to liability in tort (though an employerhas to take action against the trade union officials, rather than the unionitself),   For example, if a trade union official threatens strike action (even after due notice) against an employer who is a customer of the employer in/dispute6.
dispute with his union, the official will be committing a tort if the intended or probable result is a breach of the commercial contract between thetwo employers;   whereas if he instructs the employees of tho customer employer to withdraw their labour, the official will usually not be liable to be sued(so long as the employees give due notice.)    The secondary boycott has been most commonly used in recent years as a weapon to secure recognition - cf.,the attempt by the Clerical and Administrative Workers&apos; Union to securerecognition from the British Steel Corporation by talcing action againstClayton Dewandre and Rolls Royce.   Potentially, however, it is a weapon whichcan be used in a variety of industrial situations to secure, by indirectpressure, concessions from an employer.   The trade unions therefore attach agreat deal of importance to an amendment of the 1906 Act which would legalisesecondary boycott action and protect union officials (or anyone else) whoinduces a breach of a commercial contract in the course of an industrial dispute.D.    OTHER POSSIBLE ITEMS FOR INCLUSION IN THE BILL13.   Registration of collective agreementsFollowing the recommendation of the Donovan Commission, the Departmenthave taken steps to secure the registration by the larger companies of theircollective procedural agreements with trade unions.    So far, registration hasbeen on a voluntary basis;    and a satisfactory response has been received fromthe firms approached.   It may, however, be desirable to take powers to make regulations requiring employers (or specified categories of employers) to register their procedure agreements.   This would mean that registration wouldnot automatically become a statutory obligation, but could be made so if thepresent voluntary arrangements proved unsatisfactory or inadequate.H.   Friendly Society rulesIt was intended that the proposed interim Bill should contain a clauserendering invalid any rule of a Friendly Society which precluded membership ofthe Friendly Society on the ground of trade union membership, or whichdiscriminated against trade union members in the provision of benefits.   Thisprovision was primarily intended to nullify the trade union bar which hasbeen operated for a number, of years by one particular Friendly Society, theForemen and Staff Mutual Benefits Society.   In recent months, however, thisSociety has decided to drop the rule to which the unions objected - probablylargely as a result of a Private Bill sponsored by the Association of/Supervisory7.
Supervisory Technical and Managerial Staffs (A.S.T.M.S.) which prevented theJ.S.M.B.S. applying its anti-union rule to members of the A. S.T.M.S.    Since noother Friendly Society is known to have any anti-union provision in its rules,it may now be unnecessary to include any special provision in an industrial relations Bill.15,   Appointment of Workers&apos; Representatives to the Boards of Companies.The Government promised in the White Paper to consider whether it mightbe necessary to remove legal obstacles to the appointment of workers&apos;representatives to the boards of undertakings.   Discussions on this question with interested departments have not yet taken place;   but it may provedesirable to include some provision which would facilitate experiments in theappointment of worker-directors.8.
ANNEX IIPROPOSALS IN THE WHITE PAPER WHICH ARE NOT TO BE proceeded with AS A RESULT OE THE JUNE AGREEMENT WITH THE T.U.C.1,    Powers to impose penalties on unions for&apos; a breach of a recognition orderin an inter-union recognition dispute.2, Establishment of an Industrial Board.3, Power to impose a conciliation p^use.b Power to order a strike ballot.5, Trade union rules and registration (see Annex III).6. Creation of a new Registrar of Trade Unions and Employers&apos; Associations.7.    A requirement that trade unions should appoint professional auditors andadopt certain safeguards in relation to superannuation funds.8.    Appointment of an independent appeals body to hear complaints by individuals of unfair or arbitrary action by trade unions (see Annex III).
ANNEX IIITRADE UNION ACCOUNTABILITY:    SUPERVISION QE RULES and provision FOR INDEPENDENT APPEALTrade union rules and registrationIt would be a requirement that all organisations coming within thescope of a revised definition of a trade union should, subject to minorexceptions, be registered with a new office of Registrar of Trade unions and Employers&apos; Associations and should be required to submit to the registrar (within a stated period of time) a set of rules adequatelycovering a number of specified subjects.    If a union failed to registeradequate rules within the period allowed, it might be subject to a financial penalty imposed by a specially appointed Tribunal.    It wouldalso be the Tribunal&apos;s responsibility to decide, in cases of disagreement between the Registrar and a union whether a rule was adequate i.e. clear,in accordance with natural justice, and covered the specified subjects.Appointment of an independent appeals body in order to ensure that any trade union member (or would-be member)aggrieved at an action or decision taken by his union should, in the last resort, bo entitled to have his complaint heard by an independent tribunal there might be established an independent appeals Tribunalcomposed of a legally qualified chairman and two trade union representatives.   Any complaint would in the first instance be referredto the Registrar, who would be required to investigate it thoroughly and,if necessary, make a recommendation to the union if he believed the complaint to be justified.   If the recommendation (for example, for compensation, reinstatement in or admission to membership, mitigationof a penalty, etc.) was not accepted by the union, the complaint wouldbe submitted to the independent appeal Tribunal for binding adjudication(subject always to appeal on a point of law).    Financial awards by theTribunal against the union would be enforceable through the civil courts;    other types of award (for example, admission to membershipor a requirement to hold a frush election) would probably have tobe enforced by a threat of a financial penalty if the union failedto comply with the award.10.


</content>
</cab>
