<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/50/1 images: 6-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1945.SECRET?W.M. (45)38th Conclusions.Copy No.WAR CABINET 38 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, 3rd April, 1945, at 11-30 am.&apos; Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The   Right   Hon.Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Lord   Woolton,The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of. Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of State,for Foreign Affairs.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.minute no.12Contents.Subject.International Aspects of Colonial Policy ....World Organisation ....      ....    &apos; ....Non-Permanent Members of Security Council.Obligations of Members.Guarantee of Territorial Integrity.Guarantee of Political Independence.Domestic Jurisdiction. .  control of Enemy Powers.World Organisation   ........      ....relations with International Labour Organisation.Page230232[29831-6]
International 1.   The War Cabinet had before them Memoranda by the LordAspects of President of the Council, as Chairman of the Armistice and Post-Colonial War Committee (W.P. (45) 200) and the Secretary of State forPolicy. Foreign Affairs (W.P. (45) 208) on the International Aspects of(Previous        Colonial Policy,Reference: The. War Cabinet were informed. that, in view of develop-W.M.(44) 172ndments which had occurred since-they considered this subject in.Conclusions,&apos; December 1944, the Secretary of State for the Colonies thought itMinute 5.) was no longer practicable to. proceed with the proposals which hehad originally put before the War Cabinet in W.P. (.44) 738. his reasons for withdrawing those proposals for the time being were stated in detail in his Memorandum. annexed to W.P. (45) 200.In these circumstances he now recommended : -(i) that we should agree to the continuance of a mandatorysystem in respect of existing mandated territories and territories removed from the enemy, but should not agreethat the mandatory system might be extended to &apos;&apos; anyother territory which might voluntarily be placed under trusteeship &quot;;(ii) that the existing mandatory system should be modified asshown in the Appendix to W.P. (45) 200;(iii) that Dominion Governments should be informed, in thediscussions preliminary to the San Francisco Conference,that we hoped to limit the discussions in washington and San Francisco to the points mentioned at (i) and (ii)above; that the plan proposed in W.P. (44) 738 wouldbe withdrawn for the time being; and, in particular,that the proposal for the establishment of an Inter-national Colonial Centre would be dropped; and(iv) that in the preliminary conversations with the UnitedStates Government we should urge that discussions onthis subject at San Francisco should be confined to thesettling of a general formula, detailed discussions beingdeferred for later consideration by a smaller body.Discussion first turned on the question whether the mandatorysystem should be extended to &apos;&apos; any other territory which mightvoluntarily be placed under trusteeship.&quot;In the first place, it was agreed that in the discussions atWashington and at San Francisco it should, be made clear beyond any doubt that in this phrase &apos;&apos; voluntarily &apos;&apos; meant by the will ofthe Power exercising sovereignty over the territory concerned and.not at the option of the territory itself. Where territory was underthe control of some Government outside the territory, whether asa Colonial dependency, or as a mandated territory or otherwise,no question could arise of its being placed &quot;under trusteeship &quot;unless a request that it should be so placed was made by thatGovernment.The next question was whether, as proposed by the Secretaryof State for the Colonies, we should decline to&quot; agree that themandatory system might be extended to &quot; any other territory whichmight voluntarily be placed under trusteeship.&quot; On this point, theSecretary of State for the Colonies said that it would clearly be y &quot; within tne powers of the new World Organisation-to arrange for a mandatory system to be applied to territories voluntarily placed&quot;under trusteeship,&quot; and there was no need to make specific provision to this effect. To make specific provision would imply that there was some intention to make use of that provision. Inthat event, we should be forced, in order to allay anxieties in our colonial dependencies, to- make it clear that we had no intention of using this provision in respect of any territories under our control.On the other side, it was contended in the Memorandum by the* Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (45) 208) that theYalta Agreement on territorial trusteeship committed us to agreeing that, if any system of territorial trusteeship were set up, it should apply to &quot; any other territory which might voluntarily be placed
231W.M. 38 (45).under trusteeship &apos;&apos;; and that we were not at liberty to inform the americans or anyone else that we should be opposed to the acceptanceof this principle.In discussion it was pointed out that the essence of the Yaltaagreement on territorial trusteeship was to limit the scope of thematters to be discussed. The phrases used in the agreement were all limiting phrases, with a view to restricting the scope of thediscussion; and they could not properly be invoked as committingany of the parties to the agreement to a particular view on any ofthese points. These were all points for discussion, and there was nothing in the agreement to prevent us from putting forward inthose discussions any arguments which we thought it proper to advance under any of these heads.   *The Prime Minister endorsed this view of the matter; and said .that he could not be committed to the view expressed in paragraph 3of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s Memorandum (W.P. (45) 208).Discussion then turned on the urgency of sending representa-tives to Washington for preliminary conversations on this question with the United States authorities before the opening of theConference at San Francisco. :The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that his repre-sentatives should leave for Washington at once if they were to arrive in time for these conversations. On the other hand, the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs said - that on these issues therepresentatives of Dominion Governments ought to be given anopportunity, if they so desired, of consulting their Governments, inthe light of the forthcoming discussions at the British Common-wealth Meetings, and for this purpose an interval of three or four days was necessary.In these circumstances it was agreed that the Colonial office representatives should proceed to Washington immediately afterthe discussions with the Commonwealth representatives on the 4thand 5th April; and that they should be. given their instructionsthereafter by telegram in the light of any views subsequentlyobtained from Dominion Governments.The War Cabinet (1) Agreed that in the discussions at Washington and at theSan Francisco Conference the argument outlined by the. Secretary of State for the Colonies at &quot; X &quot; above might properly be put forward in connection with any pro-posal to extend the mandatory system to territoriesvoluntarily placed under trusteeship.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to ensure&apos;that our representatives made it clear beyond doubt, in -these discussions, that provisions relating to territories&apos;&apos; voluntarily placed under trusteeship &apos;&apos; applied only where the request for &quot; trusteeship &quot; was made by thePower exercising sovereignty over the territory.(3) Subject to (1) and (2) above, approved the recommenda-tions made by the Armistice and Post-War Committeein W.P. (45) 200.(4) Agreed that the Secretary of State for the Colonies mightarrange for his representatives to leave for the proposed conversations in Washington, immediately the discus-sions with the Commonwealth representatives on the4th and 5th April had been concluded, on the under-standing that instructions would be telegraphed to themlater in the light of any views expressed by DominionGovernments on the questions at issue.
world organisation. -(previous reference:W.M.(45)24thConclusions,Minute 2.)Non-PermanentM.emDers ofSecurityCouncil. -ill. The War Cabinet considered Memoranda by the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs (W.P. (45)205) and the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (W.P (45) 209) on various points con-nected with the proposed World Organisation on which the view&amp;of the War Cabinet were sought in preparation for the preliminary discussions with representatives of Commonwealth Governments.The War Cabinet first discussed the questions raised in w.P. (45) 205 on the election of non-permanent members of the, Security Council. 1The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that all theDominion Governments recognised the special position of the fivepermanent members of the Security Council. Difficulty would, how-ever, arise over the allocation of the six non-permanent seats. Inorder to meet the views of the Canadian Government, the UnitedKingdom delegation at Dumbarton Oaks had pressed for a provision that, in elections to the non-permanent seats, due regard should bepaid to the contribution of the members of the Organisation towardsthe maintenance of international peace and security and towardsthe other purposes of the Organisation. This proposal had been rejected by the delegations from the United States and the U.S.S.R.The Canadian Government proposed to raise this issue again; andhad suggested that, in addition to the Great Powers, there shouldbe a class of secondary Powers who would be eligible for election to the Council more frequently, or possibly for. longer periods, thanStates which had less to contribute to the maintenance of security.It was known that this proposal would not be favoured by the SouthAfrican Government, who considered that the issue raised by canada should be left to be settled by the good sense of the world organisation in actual practice rather than by any attempt to definea special class of secondary Powers.A possible solution would be to draw up a short list of&quot;middle&quot; Powers and to provide that of the six non-permanent members of the Council, four should be elected from this list. the list tentatively suggested was Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Canada,India, Mexico, Netherlands, Poland or Ukraine. Of the remainingtwo seats on the Council, one would be allocated to the Latin-American countries and the other to the remaining members of theOrganisation. .The. Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that he didnot like this solution of the difficulty since it involved diserimi-nating between some Commonwealth countries and others. If, how-ever, it was found in the preliminary discussions with representa-tives of the Commonwealth Governments that there was general support for some such provision for the representation of secondaryPowers, he would be prepared to invite their views on the questionwhether a solution on these lines should be put forward at san francisco. .        .:The main points made in discussion were : (a) These difficulties could more readily be overcome if the membership of the Security Council were increased to, say, .fifteen.With a larger Council it should be possible to secure an informalagreement that, as a matter of practice, one Dominion Governmentwould always have a seat on the Council.As against this, it was pointed out that the efficiency of theCouncil would be impaired if its size were increased. It &quot;was thegeneral view of the War Cabinet that, for.this reason, every effort should be made to avoid any increase in the membership of theCouncil.(b) A list of secondary Powers which, like that set out inparagraph 11 of W.P. (45) 205, contained three Governmentswithin the British Commonwealth, was unlikely to meet withgeneral acceptance at San Francisco. At the same time, it would cause difficulties within the British Commonwealth, since it involved discriminating between one Commonwealth Governmentand another. ..
233W.M. 38 (45).obligations of Members.-Guarantee of&quot;territorial integrity.Guarantee ofPoliticalIndependence.In discussion, it was suggested that a better basis for election to the non-permanent seats on the Security Council would be toprovide that all members of the Organisation other than the fiveGreat Powers should be equally eligible, but that the six non-permanent seats should be filled by electing one Member State from each of the six main territorial groups, viz., Europe, Asia, Africa,Australasia, South America and,North and Central America.The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs tosuggest, in the preliminary discussions with represeUta-tives of the Commonwealth Governments, that a solutionof the problem of filling the six non-permanent seats onthe Security Council should be sought on the lines indi-cated at &quot;X&quot; above.In paragraph 15 of W.P. (45) 205, the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs drew the attention of the War Cabinet to the comments of the Canadian Government on the proposal that theSecurity Council of the World Organisation should&quot; be empoweredto determine what measures not involving the use of armed force should be employed to give effect to its decisions, and to call uponmembers of -the Organisation to apply such measures.The Canadian Government had suggested that these decisionsof the Security Council should be made binding in the first instanceonly on States which were represented on the Council, and thatStates not so represented should be required to take positive actiononly when the decision had been endorsed by a two-thirds majorityof the Assembly.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that the alteration suggested by the Canadian Government would cut at theroots of the proposals for giving to the new Security Council fulland effective powers for the preservation of international peace and security.The War Cabinet-(2) Agreed that the proposals of the Canadian Government for limiting the obligations of members of the world organisation must be resisted.The War Cabinet next considered the points raised in theMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(W.P. (45) 209).The first of these was that the draft Charter of the new &quot;world organisation contained no specific guarantee of territorial integrityon the lines of Article X of the Covenant of the League of Nations.The absence of such a guarantee was likely to be criticised by manyof the smaller Powers; and such criticisms had already been expressed publicly by Australia and New Zealand.The War Cabinet, were reminded that the inclusion.of this guarantee in the League Covenant had given rise to great difficulty;and had exposed the League to the criticisms that it guaranteed forall time frontiers which there were no legal means of changingwithout the consent of the State concerned. In the earlier discus-sions there had been agreement among the representatives of theUnited States, U.S.S.R. and the United Kingdom that a rigid. provision of this kind left no sufficient scope for Treaty revisionand should be avoided.It was suggested that any proposal to add a guarantee of territorial integrity should be resisted mainly.on the ground thatthere could be no question of the Security Council changing anyfrontier unless by the requisite majority it decided that this was essential in-the general interests of preserving international peace and security. -,. draft Charter equally contained no guarantee of thepolitical independence of Member States; and the Governmentsof Australia and New Zealand were likely to press for the inclusionof such a guarantee.- It was suggested in the Memorandum that
on this point a concession might be.made, if there were general support for the proposal; but the wording of such a guaranteewould need careful consideration since, unless it were suitablyqualified, &quot;it might involve recognising the full and immediate:independence of India. &apos; .In discussion, it was suggested that if we were to maintain,our objection to any guarantee of territorial integrity it would bedifficult also to oppose the demand of some-Dominion governments for a guarantee of political independence. - On the other hand, itwas pointed out that, in addition to the difficulty about india which was mentioned in the Memorandum we might find itembarrassing to press the suggestion that the new &quot;World Organisa-tion should guarantee the political independence of territories such,for example, as the Ukraine.. In any event, would it be&quot; possible to define, for the purposes of such a guarantee, what was meant by- &quot; political independence &quot; VThe. general view of the War Cabinet was that Ministersconducting the preliminary conversations with representatives of&quot;Dominion Governments should bring out the grave difficulties involved in giving any guarantee of political independence; andthat every effort should be made to dissuade Dominion Governmentsfrom pressing this suggestion at the San Francisco Conference.Domestic Further consideration would be given at San Francisco to theJurisdiction. question of disputes arising out of matters which by internationallaw are solely within the domestic jurisdiction of the State con-cerned. It was agreed that the United Kingdom delegation shouldtake the line that the Charter should not give any member of theUnited Nations, the right to require that a dispute or situation arising out of matters within the domestic jurisdiction of a member state should be submitted to settlement by the World Organisation;but that, if such a dispute or situation constituted a threat to themaintenance of peace or security or led to a breach of the peace, itshould be open to the Security Council to take such action as itmight deem appropriate.It was pointed out in discussion that this proposal would not. in practice confer any additional powers on the Security Council;for it must in the last resort have the right to take measures.; necessary to secure international peace and security.Control of It was suggested in the Memorandum that the new WorldEnemy Organisation should be excluded from control of enemy or ex-enemyPowers. States only for the period of the military occupation; and that thereafter the Organisation might be invited by the permanent members of the Security Council to assume general and ultimate responsibility for preventing aggression on the part of the ex-enemy states. -It was agreed, in discussion, that this line might be taken by the-- United Kingdom Ministers in their discussions with representa-tives of Commonwealth Governments; and that, subject to these discussions, the same line should be taken by the United kingdom delegation at San Francisco. &quot; .The War Cabinet-(3) Subject to the views recorded above as regards a guarantee1of political independence, approved the&quot; proposals in w.P. (45) 209 as a basis for the discussions with repre-sehtatives of the Commonwealth Governments.
W.M. 38 (45).World-Organisation.RelationswithInternationalLabourOrganisation.(Previous.:Eeferenoe:W.M.(45)37th-Conclusions,Minute 4.)3. The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum (W.P.(45) 194) by the Minister of Labour and National Service regardingthe place of the International Labour Organisation in relation tothe new World Security Organisation.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that, afterConsultation with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs andthe Lord President of the Council, he invited the War Cabinet toagree that the United Kingdom delegation at San Francisco should endeavour to secure agreement on the points set out in his memorandum. These could be summarised very briefly as followsThe International Labour Organisation should be recognised as animportant instrument through which to. pursue the aims set out inArticle V of the Atlantic Charter. It should be formally associatedwith the new World Organisation, and given opportunities, no less favourable than those which it had enjoyed under the League ofNations, for making its views heard in the deliberations of the new organisation., It should not be required to submit to overridingdirections by the Economic and Social Council or the general assembly itself; arid should continue to have the right tocommunicate direct with Governments. There should be noencroachment on the measure of financial autonomy which it.nowenjoyed. Finally, the governing body of the I.L.O. should be invitedto send representatives to San Francisco for consultation on any matters affecting the I.L.O., and decisions on those matters shouldbe taken only after consultation with those representatives.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that theproposals in his Memorandum would command general supportamong organised labour and employers in this country.The War Cabinet-&apos;   - &quot;Agreed that the United Kingdom delegation at san francisco should seek to secure agreement on the points setout in W.P. (45) 194 regarding the place of the Inter-national Labour Organisation in relation to the new world organisation.   -Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,3rd April, 1945.




</content>
</cab>
