<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/48/11 images: 138-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
if ITHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTlPrinted for the War Cabinety&quot;March 1944._:_aWAR CABINET.DRAFT REPORTS BY THE INTERIM COMMISSION ON food and AGRICULTURE.Memorandum by the Minister of State.THE Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture set up by the HotSprings Conference to draft a constitution for the permanent Organisation for food and Agriculture has now produced two draft-reports (Appendices I and II)covering a Constitution of a Declaration of Principles. The report on theConstitution (Appendix II) is yery long and I need only draw the attention ofmy colleagues to paragraphs 18-23 and 41-83, which cover the scope and functions of the permanent Organisation for Food and Agriculture.2. These documents have been examined by a committee of officials andtheir recommendations are contained in the annexed note (Annex). broadly speaking, the committee&apos;s view is that, while the Interim Commission^ reports are not exactly in the terms which we should have liked if we had drafted thementirely ourselves, they are generally satisfactory to our interests, providedthat suitable vigilance and leadership are exercised by those who will representus on the permanent Organisation so that its activities are kept on the properlines. The committee has therefore recommended that, if other governments are prepared to accept these reports, His Majesty&apos;s Government should do like-wise. If, however, other Governments put forward amendments to the draft constitution, our delegate on the Interim Commission should refer home for instructions. This would also clearly give him the opportunity to press for oneor two amendments which, as indicated in the committee&apos;s note, we would liketo secure.3. It would, indeed, be idle to expect that documents emerging from a body on which, forty-four countries are represented should contain the precisewording which we ourselves would have used. But I am. satisfied that theirsubstance is in general accordance with our interests. I therefore ask mycolleagues to endorse the recommendations contained in the annexed submissionby officials.R. K. L.Foreign Office, S.W. 1, 16th March, 1944.secret. \      /- Copy No.     ^ cW.P. (M) 161.. V16th March, 1944.ANNEX.submisssion to minister of state.1. The United Nations Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture,established in pursuance of Resolution 2 of the Hot Springs Conference, has now prepared the two draft Reports to Governments of which copies are attached.(Appendices I and II.)2. The status of these documents is that the Interim Commission has fully discussed and provisionally approved them, and has deferred final action on themto enable delegates to consult their Governments.. Decisions are now required asto whether the United Kingdom delegate should be instructed to press for any modification of the draft Reports before signing them, and as to whether lord halifax should be authorised to sign on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, with or without modification, the Declaration incorporated in the First Report and theConstitution appended to the Second Report.[27100]
3. These documents have been considered by the Departments concerned, inconsultation with our representative on the Interim Commission, and, subject tothe observations that follow, we recommend that Mr. Twentyman be authorisedto sign the Eeports, and to state to the Commission that His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment is prepared to accept the draft Declaration and Constitution and toauthorise His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington to sign them at theappropriate time.4. While the documents submitted do not in all respects attain the high standard of drafting which it would be desirable to have in documents of such importance and it would be unreasonable to expect that they should and while they contain some ambiguities and reflect some compromises, we are agreedthat these should not in practice prove very serious, and that unless the repre-sentatives of other Governments show signs of wishing to reopen the issue, the documents should be accepted by His Majesty&apos; Government in their present form.Draft Declaration.5. The only point about the Draft Declaration to which we wish to draw attention is the inclusion of the words in the second sentence- by which the signatories accept and endorse the resolutions of the Hot Springs Conference.His Majesty&apos;s Government have not hitherto gone further towards endorsing theresolutions of the Hot Springs Conference than the statement made by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs in the House of Commons on the 6th July,1943, in which the following are the relevant sentences : 1&quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government recognise that the resolutions were drawnup in the light of the widely differing physical, political and economicconditions of the various countries represented, and that the application ofthe resolutions passed by the Conference will depend on these differences.For their part, His Majesty&apos;s Government have no hesitation in accepting the resolutions and the obligation to give effect to them in so far as they apply to conditions in the United Kingdom. They will also gladly co-operate with other Governments in seeking ways to give effect to those resolutions which call for concerted action. They will commend the resolutions to theGovernments of His Majesty&apos;s Colonies, Dependencies and overseas territories.&quot;This formula was carefully considered and was approved by the War&apos; cabinet before the statement was made (W.M. (43) 9.1st Conclusions, Item 1). It was stated in the Memorandum by the Foreign Secretary for the War Cabinet(W.P. (43) 275) that acceptance of the resolutions in these terms would avoidsubsequent criticism for failure to carry out some particular resolution designedto meet conditions which did not obtain in this country. If His. Majesty&apos;sGovernment now accept the formula in the draft Declaration the protection givenby the more cautious formula employed by the Foreign Secretary will no longer be present. Departments consider that while it might perhaps have been preferable- to maintain the previous formula, it would not be desirable at thisstage to take the initiative in pressing for an amendment in the draft Declaration.No one can reasonably expect His Majesty&apos;^ Government to give effect toresolutions which do not apply to conditions in the United Kingdom. If in thefuture there is criticism in the House of Commons or elsewhere, because some particular resolution has not been implementd in precisely the form in which itwas drafted, it would probably be sufficient to argue that action taken in thiscountry was based on a reasonable interpretation of the application of theresolution in question to conditions here.The Report and Constitution. ,6. It was the intention of His Majesty ^Government that the permanent organisation should be primarily a scientific and advisory body in the field offood and agriculture, which would acquire an honoured place among international institutions by the soundness of its technical work and the wisdom of its advice.It is a matter for satisfaction that our representative on the Interim commission has been very largely successful in securing that this conception is written intothe report and the Constitution, despite; insistent pressure on the part of anumerous body of the less responsible and less well-informed delegates on the interim Commission&apos; to clothe the permanent Organisation with executive functions. It has been necessary, in order to compromise with and deflect this pressure, to admit some passages in the Heport which we should have preferrednot to be included, and to accept some provisions in the Constitution which might
conceivably be interpreted as giving the permanent Organisation wider powersthan we should wish it to exercise. It was clearly impossible, in the drafting of a constitution which by general assent and under Ministers&apos; instructions was to beflexible and not rigid, completely to prevent the inclusion of some provisions thatmight at some time be misused by the Organisation. Our representative is satisfied that there is no such present intention, and we are of opinion that thispotential danger can be provided against only by leadership, influence andvigilance on the part, of our representatives on the Council and ExecutiveCommittee of the Organisation and among its senior officers.7. Apprehension has been felt by some of the Departments most, closely concerned that the Interim Commission might be persuaded to recommend thatthe permanent Organisation be given direct administrative functions in relation. to the . provision of international credit and to international commodityarrangements. There has been, in fact, strong pressure in this direction, andit is satisfactory to find that neither in the Report nor in the Constitution isit proposed that the permanent Organisation should have any direct aclministra-tive functions in these fields. The Constitution includes, among the functions ofthe Organisation the function &quot; to promote the adoption of international policies &quot;in relation both to credit and commodity arrangements. This provision isintended to mean that the Organisation can properly seek to influence the Govern-ments of the United Nations to agree upon international measures, to be realisedthrough agencies other than the permanent Organisation, and, by thus specifyinga restricted function in the Constitution, to prevent it from exercising any widerfunction in these fields. This may be regarded as acceptable compromise in viewof heavy pressure referred to above. The report is also satisfactory in that the interim Commission recommend that separate international institutions shouldbe set up to deal with international investment (including agricultural credit)and international commodity arrangements. It recommends that the permanent organisation should be represented on the governing body of such institutions- so that it may advise on the food and agricultural aspects of their work. Thisis an important and satisfactory recommendation. There is, however, also a recommendation in the report (see paragraph 80) that, in the event of specialinternational bodies not being set up in these fields, consideration should be givento the discharge of executive functions by the permanent Organisation itself.This is one of the passages which we should have preferred not to have, but itshould not in itself lead to embarrassment, since, if Governments fail to agree on the setting up of special international bodies in these fields, they are unlikely to agree to recommend that the permanent Organisation should undertakeadditional responsibilities of this character. Provided, therefore, that the termsof the report are a reliable guide to future activities on the part of the permanent organisation, all should be well. At the same time there is a possible danger in that the Constitution (which must be read by itself) might be interpreted aspermitting the permanent Organisation to shift the emphasis of its work fromthat of an advisory body to that of an executive authority without it being necessary to secure a new mandate from Governments. Undesirable as this is,Departments feel that it would be better to rely upon the Council and officials of the Organisation being sensible rather than to attempt to redraft the Constitu-tion. It would be difficult to secure adequate safeguards against the possibilityof such a shift in emphasis in the work of the Organisation without introducinginto the Constitution a general rigidity which in the long run would be inimicalto the success of the Organisation,8. The Ministry of Supply, with an eye to its concern with commodity policy for raw materials, is apprehensive that the Organisation will feel tempted to undertake work on the processing, distribution and regulation of non-foodagricultural products which would be better done in other ways and more properlybelongs to other international organisations which are likely to be set up. It is recognised that the agricultural responsibilities of. the Organisation must cover both food-stuffs and non-food agricultural products. But whereas its responsi-bility for nutrition is likely to carry its activities into the field of processing,distribution and regulation, it seems desirable that in this field they should belimited to food-stuffs. Articles I and XI (e) and (g) of the Draft Constitutionread against the background of paragraphs 20, 22, 31 (iii), 58, 60 to 63 and 70of the Draft Report might at some time in the future be held to justify a widerinterpretation of the Organisation^ functions. This will have to be resisted.Other Departments too are concerned lest the Organisation may undertake work, related to their own spheres of responsibility, which more properly belongsto other institutions.[27100] b 2
9. The proposed grant of diplomatic privileges and immunities in articles VII 4 and XVI 2 has been specially considered by the Foreign Office,Inland Revenue, Customs and Excise and Treasury in the light of legislationcontemplated by His Majesty&apos;s Government to cover this aspect of the establish-ment of a number of new international bodies. The draft Constitution in tworespects asks for more than we are prepared to give (viz., immunity from suitin respect of acts by subordinate staff outside of official duties and immunity from income tax on salaries of nationals in their own country and on income of subordinate staff outside their salaries) and in two respects for less.Mr. Twentyman thinks it unnecessary, however, to advise an alteration in thescope of the contemplated legislation. It would suit us best if he could get an addition to the Constitution at the end of Article VII 4 as follows : &quot;or alternatively to accord to those other members of the staff those immunities and facilities which may hereafter be accorded to equivalent members of the staffof other public international organisations.&quot; Failing such an addition, HisMajesty&apos;s Government may find it necessary to legislate expressly giving to permanent Organisation and its staff the fuller facilities provided in its draft constitution. To accord special favours to permanent Organisation for food and Agriculture as an exception in general legislation on the subject of the privileges of international bodies would clearly be attended with great difficulty.But it may well be that this would be the only amendment proposed andmight consequently put the United Kingdom representative in an invidious light,especially as this particular provision is one on which the smaller countries are particularly susceptible. Article VII4 as drafted already contains a phrasedesigned to enable His Majesty&apos;s Government and other Governments to fulfilacceptance of the Article by legislation on the lines we already contemplate viz.,&quot; in so far as it may be possible under its constitutional procedure.&quot; This phraseis not in the form we should have ourselves used for but we thinkthat Mr.&apos; Twentyman may perhaps rely on it to release him from proposing theforegoing amendment provided he makes it clear that legislation on these subjectsis under consideration in this country, and that His Majesty&apos;s Government wouldbe bound by its constitutional procedure to act within the limits of that legislation.10. In paragraphs 127 and 128 of the Report it is suggested that the budget of the Organisation for the first five years of its existence might average$5,000,000. Since this sum could hardly be spent in the first year the budgetshould be fixed at $3,500,000, of which $2,500,000 should be held as a capitalfund to meet unusual expenses in the establishment of the Organisation. Weconsider that these figures -are somewhat too high. In the nature of things,however, the whole question of the budget of the Organisation and the scale of contributions will have to be reconsidered after the war when the european governments can commit their countries. We consider, therefore, that the presentrecommendations should be accepted.11. We therefore recommend that Mr. Twentyman should be instructed to sign the draft Report and to state that His Majesty&apos;s Government are preparedto accept the draft Constitution. We consider, however,, that, if the representa-tives of other Governments put forward amendments to the Constitution, adifferent situation would arise and, in those circumstances, our representative should refer home for instructions.British Leadership in the permanent Organisation.12. In conclusion we wish to emphasise the great importance of the UnitedKingdom and the other members of the British Commonwealth doing whateverthey can to exercise effective leadership in the Organisation for Food and agriculture when it is set up. This will involve finding competent officials for its-staff and sending strong representatives to meetings of the Council and of other )Committees set up by the Organisation. Such leadership will help in two ways :It will help positively by making the Institution one which really does assist inthe achievement of its aims, which is manifestly to our advantage; it will helpnegatively by preventing the Organisation from embarking on enterprises forwhich it was never intended and which are likely to cause embarrassment to us and to other Governments. It will be seen from the foregoing paragraphs thatthe proposed Constitution is sufficiently flexible to allow of abuse if the affairs of the Organisation are badly conducted. The best safeguard we can provide against its abuse is the provision of first-class permanent staff and strong british representation at Council and Committee meetings.
APPENDIX I,DRAFT FIRST REPORT TO THE GOVERNMENTS OF THEUNITED NATIONS BY THE INTERIM COMMISSION on food AND AGRICULTURE.The United Nations Conference on Food and Agriculture recommended(Recommendation II) that its constituent Governments and authorities&quot; recognise and embody in a formal declaration or agreement the obligationto their respective peoples and to one another, henceforth to collaborate in raising levels of nutrition and standards of living of their peoples, and toreport to one another on the progress achieved.&quot;2. The Conference further, in paragraph 4 (b) of the related Resolution,required the Interim Commission to formulate and recommend for considera-tion by each member Government or authority the formal declaration or agreement referred to in the above Recommendation, and specified with greater particularity the obligations to be recognised by the declaration or agreement.3. The Interim Commission has accordingly formulated the aecom-accompanying  Draft Declaration and recommends this Declaration for acceptance by its constituent Governments.4. The Commission further recommends that as soon as each Govern-ment has accepted the Declaration it should without delay so inform theExecutive Secretary of the Commission, and at the same time empower itsprincipal representative in Washington to sign the Declaration on itsbehalf, with a view to arrangements being made at an early date for theDeclaration to be executed in a single act signed in common on behalf ofall the participating Governments.Draft Declaration by the United Nations.The United Nations Conference on Food and Agriculture, assembled inMay 1943, agreed unanimously on principles and methods by which to achieve freedom from hunger and want.The undersigned Governments and authorities, having considered theEeports and Resolutions of the Conference, hereby accept and endorse its recommendations.They, therefore, solemnly pledge, to their own peoples and to one another, that they will work separately and together to the end that wantand ,the fear of want shall be progressively abolished.For this purpose these Governments and authorities will take all measures within their power:To raise the level of nutrition and the standard of living of the peoplesunder their jurisdiction.To improve the efficiency of agricultural production and distribution.And they resolve:To co-operate for the achievement of these ends and for this purpose.to establish a permanent organisation for food and agriculture.To report to one another through this organisation on the measures taken and the progress achieved.In witness whereof the undersigned representatives, being duly authorised, have signed the present Declaration.
APPENDIX II,DRAFT SECOND REPORT TO THE GOVERNMENTS OF THEUNITED NATIONS BY THE INTERIM COMMISSION ON food and AGRICULTURE.TABLE OF contents. The Interim Commission A.- Constitution and Terms of Reference    ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 6B. Expert Advisers........................ 8II. Introduction     ...      ...      .........      ...     .,......,      ...     9III.-The Food and Agriculture Organisation oe the United Nations^-A-Purposes and Functions        ...      ...      ......      ...      ...      ... 101. Research     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      .,,      ...      .... 11(a) Sources of information......      ......      ...      ... 11(b) Range of subject matter        ............... 122. Dissemination of knowledge   ...      ...      ,......,.      ... 12(a) Publications        ...      ......      ............ 13(b) Education .................. ,    .... - 13(c) Library and enquiry services............... i43. Advisory functions        ...      .................. 14(a) Typical cases and procedure  ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 14(b) Advice and recommendations on other problems...      ... 154- Fisheries, forestry, and non-food agricultural products (a) Fisheries and marine products        ...      ...      ...      ... 16(b) Forestry and forestry products       ...      ...      ...      ... 16(c) Non-food agricultural products      ...      ...      ...      ... 175. Agricultural credit       ....    &quot;...............      ... 176. Commodity arrangements       ...      .........      ...      ... 187. Administrative functions       ...      ......      ...      ...      ... 19B. Constitution: 1. Nature of the Constitution     .........      ...      ...      ... 202. -Membership...     ...      ...      ...      ...     ..........      ... 203. Limitations on powers of the Organisation and on obligations of Members        ...      ...      ...      .........      ...      ... 20C. Administrative Structure and Management    ...      ...      ...      ... 211. The Council......      .........      ...      .......... 212, The Executive Committee      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 213. Standing advisory committees ......      ...      ...      ... 214. General and special conferences       ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 225. Director-General ...      ...      ...      ......      ...      ...      ... 226. Staff ...      .....................      ...      ... 227. Regional and liaison offices     ...      ,.............. 228. Organisation and methods of work   ...      ...      ...      ...      .., 23D. Relations with Other Organisations 1. Other international bodies   &apos; ...      ......      ...      ...      ... 232. Regional and national organisations        ............ 24E. Expenses.............................. 25F,-Miscellaneous.-1. Legal status ........................ 262. Interpretation of Constitution        ......      ...      ...      ... 263. Languages ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... .26G. Need for Early Action,..      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 27Appendix I.-Draft Constitution        ...      ...      .........      ...      ,..    28Appendix II. Members ofthe Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture    32I. THE  INTERIM   COMMISSION.A. Constitution and Tesms of Reference.The Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture was establishedby the United Nations Conference on Food and Agriculture held inMay 1943 at Hot Springs, Virginia, for the purposes stated in the following recommendation:  &apos;&apos; Whereas:&quot; 1. Freedom from want is difficult to achieve without concerted actionamong all like-minded nations to expand and improve production, toincrease employment, to raise levels of consumption, and to establish greater freedom in international commerce;&quot; 2. The successful carrying out of the recommendations of theConference in the field of production, distribution, and consumption of food and other agricultural products in the post-war period will be the mostimportant prerequisite for the achievement of freedom from want, andrequires the creation by the Governments and authorities here representedof a permanent organisation in the field of food and agriculture; therefore
53&quot; fhe United Nations Conference on Food and Agriculture&quot;recommends:&quot; 1. That the Governments&apos; and authorities here represented recogniseand embody in a formal declaration or agreement the obligation- to theirrespective peoples, and to one another, henceforth to collaborate in raisinglevels of nutrition and standards of Hying of their peoples, and to reportto&quot; one another on the progress achieved;&quot; 2.   That the Governments and authorities here represented establish a permanent organisation in the field of food and agriculture; and&quot; Resolves : , &apos;&quot;1. That, in order that every practicable step may be taken to attainthese and the other appropriate objectives set forth in the declaration and specific recommendations of the Conference, an Interim Commission forcarrying out the recommendations of the United Nations Conference onPood and Agriculture be established;&apos;&apos; 2. That each of the Governments and authorities here represented beentitled to designate a repfeseritative on the Interim Commission, and thatthe Interim Commission be installed in Washington&apos; not later that the15th July, 1943;&quot; 3.   That the Interim Commission perform its work with due regard. tri the exigencies of the war, through such form  of organisation and personnel as it may deem appropriate; and formulate regulations coveringits expenditures arid submit to the member - Governments and authoritiesa budget aria allocation of quota contributions;&apos;&apos; 4. That the functions of the Interim Commission be to formulate and recommend for consideration by each member Government or authority (a) A specific plan for a permanent organisation in the field of food and agriculture;(b) The  formal  declaration  or  agreement  referred   to  in  the  firstrecorilrriendatioriv in which each pariiciparit shall recognise&apos; itsobligation--(i) To raise the levels of nutrition and standards of living of itsown people;(ii)&quot;- To improve the efficiency of agricultural production anddistribution;(iii) To co-operate, so far as may be possible, with other nations for the achievement of these ends;(iv) To undertake to submit periodically to the other participants,through the permanent organisation, reports on the action taken and the progress achieved toward these ends;(c) Such proposals Or&apos; reports as are necessary to give effect to therecommendations of the Conference;&quot; 5.   That in the preparation of a plan for the permanent organisation the Interim Commission give full consideration to the following:  (a) The&quot; relation of the permanent organisation to, arid riiethods of.associating it with, other institutions, national as well as inter-national,   which   already  exist   or&apos;  which   rriay   hereafter   beestablished, iri the&apos; field of food arid agriculture arid in relatedscientific, economic arid other&apos; fields&apos;;(b&apos;) Provision for membership iri the permanent&apos; organisation, in due course, of Goverrinierits riot represented on the InterimCoriiMission;&apos;&quot;6. That in considering the functions arid duties to be assigned to thepermanent organisation the Interim Commission take into&apos; account-&apos;(a) The proriiotidri of scieritifiic, technological, social, and economicresearch;(6) The collection and dissemination of information- and provisiori forthe exchange of services;(ci) The   suferriissidri   io   member&apos; - Goverrimerits   and   authorities   of recommendations for action with regard to the following:  (i) Nutrition;(ii) Standards  of&apos; adnsuiription of food and other agricultural products;(iii) Agricultural production&apos;, distribution, arid conservation;(iv)- Statistics and economic&apos; studies in the field- of agriculture and food, including the study Of the relation of agriculture to world economy;-.
(v) Education  and extension work in the field, of food  and agriculture;(vi) Agricultural credit;(vii) Problems of agricultural population and farm labour;&quot; 7. That the Interim Commission further consider the desirability ofassigning to the permanent organisation functions in the field of-(a) Development of agricultural resources and orientation of production,where necessary;(b) Agricultural commodity arrangements;(c) Agricultural co-operative movements;(d) Land tenure;(e) Other subjects on which recommendations have been made by theConference;&quot; 8. That the Interim Commission also consider the initiation of preliminary statistical investigations and research into the problems withwhich the permanent organisation will deal;&quot; 9. That the Interim Commission be deemed to have been dissolvedwhen the permanent organisation has been established;&apos;&apos; 10. That the Government of the United States of America be invitedto take whatever preliminary action may be necessary for the establishmentof the Interim Commission after the United Nations Conference on food and Agriculture has completed its work.&quot;2. Delegates to the Interim Commission were designated (Appendix II),pursuant to paragraph 2 of the above Resolution, by the Governments ofall the United and Associated Nations, and the Commission was convenedin Washington on the 15th July, 1943. The Commission now presents its second Report, which has the unanimous concurrence of its constituentDelegates.B. Expert Advisees.6. The Commission felt itself to be in need of technical advice in regardto many of the subjects referred to it by the resolutions of the Hot SpringsConference. It therefore decided to ask certain distinguished scientists andeconomists conversant with problems of nutrition and agriculture to act inan advisory capacity. These experts constituted the Scientific and EconomicPanels which advised the Commission on the scope, functions, and methodsof operation of the permanent organisation on food and agriculture. It is appropriate to record in the forefront of this Report the Commission^ deepappreciation of their invaluable assistance. The panels were composed asfollows:  Economic Panel Chairman:  Mr. H. R. Tolley  (United  States),  Chief,  Bureau ofAgricultural Economics, United States Department of Agriculture.Professor H. F. Angus (Canada), Economics Department, university of British Columbia.Dr. Antonin Basch (Czechoslovakia), formerly Head, Research andEconomics Department, National Bank of Czechoslovakia; general manager, Union of Chemical and Metallurgical Industry, 1934.Professor J. D.  Black (United  States),  Professor of Economics,Harvard University.Mr. R. R. Enfield (United Kingdom), Principal Assistant Secretary,Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries.Professor A. G. B. Fisher (New Zealand), Professor of InternationalEconomics, Royal Institute of International Affairs, London.Dr. Alexander Loveday, Director of Economics, Financial and TransitDepartment, League of Nations.Mr. Ansgar Rosenborg, Economic, Financial and Transit Department,League of Nations.Professor T. W. Schultz (United States), Professor of AgriculturalEconomics, University of Chicago.Scientific Panel-Chairman: Professor J. A. Scott.Watson (United Kingdom), Professorof Rural Economy, Oxford.Dr. E. C. Auchter (United States), Administrator of agricultural research, United States Department of Agriculture.Dr. G. S. H. Barton (Canada), Deputy Minister of Agriculture.Dr. F. G. Boudreau (United States), Chairman, Food and NutritionBoard, National Research Council.Dr. R. E. Buchanan (United States), Director, Agricultural Experi-ment Station and Dean of Graduate School, Iowa State College.Dr. Andrd Mayer (France), Professor and Vice-President, College deFrance.
Professor  L.  A.   Maynard   (United   States),   Professor of   AnimalNutrition, Cornell University.Dr. Paris E. Menendez (Paraguay), Director of Central Laboratory,Ministry of Agriculture.Dr. T. H. Sheu (China), Vice-Director, National Agricultural ResearchBureau; Member National Resources Commission.Dr. R.  D.  Sinclair (Canada),  Dean  of Agriculture,  University ofAlberta.Dr. M. L. Wilson (United States),  Director of Extension, UnitedStates Department of Agriculture.4. These expert advisers have contributed in large measure to thedischarge by the Commission of the duties laid upon it, by their instructedand comprehensive advice on the problems referred to them and. by thedevotion and energy which they have given, separately and in co-operation,to their voluntary task. The Commission cannot too highly commend their services or -too fully recognise its own indebtedness to them. It records with satisfaction that their advice on all the matters referred to them wasunanimous.5. The Commission has utilised the, services of consultants from other organisations, national and international, to assist in certain phases of its work. It particularly desires to record its appreciation of the assistancerendered by Mr. C. Wilfred Jenks, . Legal Adviser of the InternationalLabour Office, who has contributed unstintingly of his experience and skillin the preparation of the Draft Constitution...   II.-INTRODUCTION.6. It is unnecessary to the purposes of this Report to include in it anygeneral statement of the important considerations supporting the proposals and policies embodied in the Final Act of the Hot Springs Conference.It is appropriate, however, to state briefly here the general considerations of which the Commission has been mindful in formulating its recommenda-tions, so far as they relate to the circumstances under which therecommendations are made, the conditions under which effect will be givento them, and the general purposes they are designed to achieve,7. In the struggle for food, mankind has been indifferently successful.If millions have enough, more millions have too little, and many starve.This had been thought to be inevitable, but we now&quot; know that it is not.Recent discoveries and developments have made it possible under certain conditions for all men and all nations to achieve freedom from hunger,which is the first step toward freedom from want. Indeed, we can nowexpect to do much more than be free from hunger. The way is open tomove towards new levels of well-being which men have hitherto thoughtunattainable. - -8. First among the developments that have made these things possible is progress in scientific production. The natural sciences have shown ushow to increase the productiveness of the land. The nature of the soilhas been explored, and methods of management have been developed tomaintain and increase its fertility. Great progress has been made in&apos; thebreeding of both crops and livestock, and strains have been created thatare far more productive than their predecessors. At the same timescientists have found new and surer ways of combating diseases and insectand other pests that constantly menace the food supply.9. Along with progress in these fields, immense strides have been madein the development of tools and machines to do work formerly done by handlabour, so that it is now possible for one man to till enough land and produce enough food to feed many more people than before. equally important have been developments in handling, processing, storing, andtransporting foods which make it possible to overcome many of the formerhandicaps of season and distance.10. The result has been to open the way for greatly increased produc-tion from the same primary resources, a more even distribution of the supplyof food both geographically and over periods of time, and finally a release. of large numbers of people from the. production of food. These people could produce other things and perform other services needed by their fellow men.11. While these developments have, been in the making the physicalnature and needs of human beings have also been explored. The advances in the science of nutrition within recent years have been comparable in importance to the earlier discoveries in bacteriology, which opened the wayto control many deadly or handicapping diseases. Chemistry and physiologyhave given us. a vast, amount of new knowledge regarding the relation offood to human well-being. We now know that certain diseases, which affectimmense numbers of people, are caused solely by failure to get enough ofthe right kind of food. We know what foods the human body.needs notonly to prevent these diseases but to build resistance to many others,[27100] c  .
lengthen the span of life, favour the birth of healthy children, and raise thepower of many individuals to do physical and mental work formerly thought to&apos; be beyond their innate capacity.12. Moreover, the frontiers of scientific discovery are constantlyexpanding and opening opportunities for further progress.13. Thus mankind is equipped with new knowledge, the heritage of all men. A new mastery over the forces that determine human well-being ispossible, which men and nations can exercise, if they will, to better the lot of the vast majority of people. But to put this knowledge to full userequires forethought and action adequate to the ends desired.14. The modern knowledge of nutrition must be shared, in simplepractical terms, among increasing numbers of people until it finally reachesall. The modern knowledge of production must be shared among theworld&apos;s farmers. Producers must be enabled to get the materials andtools, and to apply the methods, necessary to increase the world&apos;s production-tion to the point where all can have enough food. Those released from agriculture by its increased efficiency must be enabled to find useful workin other pursuits. Workers in cities and towns must be enabled to getthe products they need from an expanding agricultural production; that isto say, industry and other forms of production, as well as the domestic andforeign trade of all countries, must likewise expand. Each nation must give earnest consideration to the adoption of policies designed to ensuresufficient food to those who, for one or another reason, are at so great a disadvantage in the economic system that they cannot obtain the means for reasonable nutrition. Finally, research, which has already accomplishedso much, must be stimulated and made even more responsive to the need of discovering ways of reconciling the changing numbers of the world&apos;speoples and the quantity of things produced and distributed to meet their requirements.15.   Scientific   developments   have  shortened  the   distances   between countries untilf all are now near neighbours.   Thus the discontent or theoverweening ambition of one profoundly affects^ all others, strife at one place- ban quickly become world-wide, and co-operation is thrust upon us if theworld is to avoid being brought ultimately to the verge of ruin.16. But these same scientific developments will enable us to achievemany things through co-operation that were thought impossible before, and among them is freedom from want of food. No nation can hope to achieve this by depending solely on its own effort, for none can any longer insulateitself from the disastrous effects of things that may be done by other nations. But in a world in which distance has shrunk and the pace ofevents has quickened, each nation can reinforce what others do far more readily and effectively than in the past. The possibilities for good haveincreased as greatly as the possibilities for.evil. We can now reasonably expect to solve the problem of freedom from want if all will act together.17. Progress will necessarily be gradual. Men do not readily adjusttraditional ways to new conditions, and there are many obstacles to be overcome. But a start can be made at once. Changes in the economic and social arrangements of nations will be needed. The redirection would notbe wholly new; it is in line with an evolution that has been hastened inour time.III.-THE  FOOD AND AGRICULTURE ORGANISATION OF THEUNITED NATIONS.A. Purposes and Functions.18. In pursuance of paragraphs 4 (a), 5, 6, and 7 of the Resolutionquoted in paragraph 1 of this Report, the Interim Commission recommendsfor the approval of its constituent Governments the Draft Constitution(Appendix I) of a permanent organisation for food and agriculture,hereinafter referred to as the &quot; Organisation.&quot;19. The remainder of this section of this Report is devoted to anexposition, supplementing the Draft Constitution, of the purposes and functions of the permanent Organisation as the Commission has envisagedthem, and of its structure and organisation, its methods of working, itsrelationship with other organisations, national and international, and theneed for its early establishment. References at the ends of paragraphsare to the corresponding Articles of the Draft Constitution.20. Throughout this Report references to the purposes, functions,duties, and powers of the Organisation are to be interpreted as extending to fisheries, marine products, forestry, primary forestry products, fibres, andother non-food agricultural products.    [Art. XVII.]21. - The purpose of the Organisation as set forth in Article I of theDraft Constitution is &quot;to promote the  common welfare by furthering
separate and collective action by the member nations to raise levels pfnutrition and standards of living, to secure improvements in the efficiency of the production and distribution of all food and agricultural products,to better the condition of rural populations, and to contribute towards an expanding world economy.&apos;&apos;22. The means to be employed will include the promotion of research,the dissemination of knowledge, the exchange of services, and the making of recommendations for international and national action, in which theOrganisation might in some cases be directly involved, with regard to theimprovement of nutrition;; the production, distribution, and consumptionof foods and of fibres and other agricultural products; and the develop-ment and conservation of agricultural, forestry, and marine reso\irces.[Art. X, XL] -23. These are important and far-reaching undertakings. They shouldbe envisaged as far as possible in their entirety, so that their interrelation-ships may be clearly seen. But the Organisation will have to developgradually and it will probably be a considerable time before it will be ableto cover the whole field described in this Report. It should be established at the earliest practicable date since there are matters falling within its scope which call urgently for action.1. Research.24. One of the principal functions of the Organisation will be to promoteresearch in the fields relating to its work as a means of meeting the needs and helping to solve the problems of the peoples of its member nations.Competence and persistence in the search for knowledge, and fairnessand courage in promoting its application, will establish a solid basis forrecommendations and action.    [Art. XL].25. A vast amount of knowledge in the fields to be covered by theOrganisation already exists. To be more widely and effectively used, itneeds to be adapted to local conditions and re-examined as conditions change.In addition, new knowledge must be sought.26. A great diversity of research in the natural and social sciences issuggested by the range of subject matter and the sources of informationdiscussed in later paragraphs. While continually safeguarding andfostering the freedom of inquiry necessary to science, the Organisationcan do much to stimulate such research throughout the world; suggest andinitiate projects, in many of which several institutions in more than one country might co-operate; co-ordinate such projects whenever possible;arrange for the use of procedures that would give comparable results; and keep research workers informed of one another&apos;s progress. The organisation should facilitate .the exchange of personnel among institutions and thecollection and exchange of important biological materials-breeding stocks,for example and in some cases lend the services of members of its owntechnical staff to an institution or a country. Whether the organisation should supply equipment or give direct financial aid to research institutionsis a matter of policy to be determined by the Council. The question shouldbe left for future decision whether, by arrangement &quot;with the Governmentsprimarily concerned, the Organisation should establish research stations ofits own.   [Art. XI, XIII.]27. In sum, the Organisation should lead in stimulating, promoting,and, where appropriate, conducting research focussed on world needs in food, agriculture, forestry, and fisheries. To carry out these and other functions, it will need to assemble a great deal of information from all parts of the world. But it should not only gather data; it should find, out and say what they mean.(a) Sources of information.28. One of the principal sources from which the Organisation willgather information will be the periodic reports made by member nations inaccordance with Resolutions II, III, and XV of the Hot Springs Conference,In order that these reports may serve as a basis for concerted planning and action by the member nations it is important that they give the informationneeded for drawing an accurate picture of the conditions in any countryand throughout the world in regard to nutrition, food consumption, produc-tion, and the factors influencing them. The Organisation, being chargedwith the responsibility of obtaining and making use of these reports, istherefore given&apos; the right to determine the lines on which they will be made and to arrange that they be furnished promptly.   [Art. XII.]29. The regular collection and systematic presentation of relevantstatistics obtained from member nations and international authorities willbe fundamental; and continuity in the statistical series collected will be important to insure accurate interpretation of current and future trends.The Organisation should receive regularly all published statistical material,[27100] c 2
and should also have access to unpublished material relevant to its work.The basic statistical data in many countries are very imperfect. TheOrganisation should devise effective methods for obtaining more accuratestatistical information at minimum expense, and should also make theservices of its technical staff available to any Government needing assistancein organising or improving national statistical services. New methods ofsampling, for example, which have recently been developed, are known and used in few countries.   [Art. XI, XII, XIII.]30. All other relevant sources of information should be used, includingthe results of special inquiries and surveys, or the work of special committeesset up by the Organisation; reports and other material&apos;obtained throughregional and liaison offices of the Organisation; information furnished by national nutrition organisations, by any agencies that may be set up underthe auspices of the Organisation, and by research institutes and scientificsocieties; and reports and other material obtained through reciprocal arrangements with other international authorities     [Art. XIII, XV.](b) Range of subject matter.31. The range of subject matter covered by the research, fact-finding,and interpretative work of the Organisation will include all the branches ofthe natural and social sciences relating to food, nutrition, agriculture,forestry, and fisheries. It may be useful to list some of the particularlyrelevant subjects as a means of sketching in broad outline the scope ofthe activities that would contribute to the main purpose of furtheringimprovements in production, distribution, consumption, and nutrition. Theimportance of the interrelationships of the different fields and of collaboration with other institutions should be emphasised at all times.(i) Natural sciences including human nutrition in relation to health,animal nutrition, biochemistry, plant and animal genetics, plant and animal physiology and pathology, soil chemistry and physics,entomology, mycology, bacteriology, and meteorology,(ii) Technology including management, selection, and breeding inrelation to crops and livestock; animal feeding and care; soilfertilisation, drainage, irrigation, and other conservation anddevelopment measures; protection of crops and livestock fromnatural enemies; agricultural engineering; processing, storing,and transporting food and other agricultural products.(iii) Economic organisation of agriculture including the production andsuccessive stages in the distribution, marketing, and consumptionof food and other agricultural products; the co-ordinatedexpansion of consumption and production; the efficiency of factors of production in terms of physical output and cost per unit; methods of reducing costs of production and distribution;scale of enterprise; economical use of labour and machinery;provision and use of credit; demand and prices; gross and net income in relation to output and consumption; trends andfluctuations in production, prices, incomes, and other factorsbearing on the relation of agriculture to the general economy;domestic and international trade and other aspects of national and international economy, with special reference to their bearing on food and agricultural problems.(iv) Other   social   factors including   food   habits   and   customs,   thedistribution of population between agriculture and industry,population movements, land tenure, consumer and producerco-operatives, and rural organisation generally; rural schools andother rural institutions; rural roads, communications, and ruralelectrification;  rural housing, sanitation and amenities.(v) Public measures of regulation and assistance:   In modern Statespublic authorities legislate so extensively in regard to standards and practices, and provide aids of so many kinds in connectionwith the matters included in each of the preceding sub-paragraphs,that investigations in these fields by the Organisation are too broadto be covered by any list. They would relate, among othermatters, to special planning techniques, legislation affecting theeradication of deficiency diseases, measures for improving the dietsof vulnerable groups, regulations for control of plant and animaldiseases and pests, grading and standards of market and nutritivequality, subsidies for production or consumption, commercialpolicies, and measures for increasing consumption . by thedistribution on special terms of accumulated stocks.2. Dissemination of Knowledge.32. The need to make useful facts about nutrition and the consumption and production of foods far more widely known is so great and so essentialto progress that promoting the dissemination of knowledge is to be given
equal emphasis with research. The Organisation should employ variousmeans to this end as the need arises. The development of a programmeof publication will be important from the beginning. Promoting education in the fields relating to the Organisation^,work will be another importantactivity.    [Art. XL](a) Publications.33. A considerable variety of publications will probably be needed,some for official or professional use, some designed to meet the needs ofparticular groups of producers and consumers and those of the general public. High standards should be the aim in every, case. Duplication ofwork adequately done by others should be avoided, and the possibility ofco-operative ventures should be fully explored; the Organisation might do much by this means to promote world-wide co-ordination of efforts forexample, in the preparation and publication of scientific abstracts.[Art. XIII.]34. It is not possible at this time to forecast exactly what publicationsthe Organisation will find it useful to issue. Among them might be aperiodic summary based on the reports by member nations; a periodic worldsurvey of the state of nutrition, consumption, and production together withan analysis of the determining factors, with special attention to interrelateddevelopments and the policies of different countries; a periodic digest orreview of legislation and administrative rulings relating to food, agriculture,forestry, and fisheries; abstracts, reviews, and bibliographies of scientificliterature; regular bulletins dealing with crops, production, trade, stocks,prices, and other data and their interpretation; and a journal or journalscontaining articles for the general reader oh problems and progress in the fields covered by the Organisation. It will clearly be essential to publishan authoritative and comprehensive year-book of international statistics.[Art. XI, XII.](b) Education.35. The publications of the Organisation will be educational in a broadsense. It should also promote more specific educational activities in several important fields, with the central purpose of furthering improved nutritionand adequate production and consumption on a world-wide scale.   [Art. XL]36. With a View to raising the standards of professional services and making them more widely available, the Organisation should be prepared toassist governmental and other agencies in planning for expansion or improve-ment of the work of institutions of learning in the fields related to its work.It should be in a position to serve as consultant to institutions on courses of study and methods of training. It might well act as a clearing-house ofinformation on facilities for study and research in institutions throughoutthe world. It should encourage and facilitate the exchange between countries of students, teachers and professional workers.   [Art. XL]37. To what extent, and in what ways, the Organisation will be ofassistance to educational institutions other than those at the university orprofessional level cannot be foreseen at present. Nations differ widely intheir educational systems, which are peculiarly a matter of national concern.But while the rural school system should be one of the most important factors in improving rural life, it is in fact in most countries at a disadvantage in comparison with urban school systems; and in both urban and rural schools there are great and often unrealised opportunities forteaching young people elementary but important facts regarding foods andnutrition. Despite the difficulties involved, the Organisation should be ableto perform a useful service by advising on suitable courses of study,promoting adequate teacher-training in appropriate subjects, acting in a consultative capacity, assisting in surveys and studies to determine neededimprovements, and in other ways.   [Art. XI.]38. Various countries are interested in furthering adult education,particularly of the kind exemplified by agricultural extension, homedemonstration, and similar services. Such services depend largely on localinstructors and leaders who give personal counsel and assistance anddemonstrate methods to help producers and home-makers apply theprinciples of good farming, food preparation, nutrition, and home economics,or domestic science, in their daily work and living. The Organisation shouldbe prepared to assist Governments in determining the need for these services; to promote adequate training of workers, including opportunities for study in other countries when this would be advantageous; and to assist in other ways in widening the usefulness and improving the methods and standards of such services.   [Art; XL]39. The Organisation will be interested in improving the effectivenesswith which adult educational services could use such channels as news-papers, radio, and motion pictures to spread practical information. Inaddition, it should furnish authentic information for the public regardingits own activities.   To what extent it should elaborate services of its own,
designed specifically to furnish material for the press, radio, and otherpopular media will depend upon the course of its development. whatever may be done in this field should be safeguarded with unusual care againstthe risk of exploitation and misrepresentation for purposes of commercial orother propaganda.   [Art. XL](c) Library and enquiry services.40. As the work of the Organisation becomes . widely known, it willprobably be called upon to answer a large volume of enquiries on manysubjects. Furnishing adequate information in response to these enquirieswill in itself be an important service in disseminating knowledge. partly for this purpose, and also for its other work, the Organisation will need an extensive library, kept fully up to date.   [Art. XL]3. Advisory Functions.41. Much of the work of the Organisation will be of an advisorycharacter. This will include making recommendations ranging from asuggestion on some minor point to drawing up and submitting for approvalan elaborate programme of action on a complex problem; and from advicegiven to a single member nation or even a single institution to advice givento all member nations.   [Art. X, XL]42. The Organisation should have this wide scope in its advisoryfunctions to enable it to achieve the objectives of the Hot SpringsConference. It is, however, a much more delicate matter to give advice on some subjects than on others. Special procedures are provided by whichthe Council of the Organisation may formulate and adopt formal recom-mendations to Governments. In addition, a wide variety of advisory services may be developed of a less formal character,   [Art. X, XL]43. The effectiveness of advice and recommendations depends on the qualifications of those who give them, the adequacy of their preparatory work, their understanding of variations in local conditions, and their ability to enlist the co-operation of member nations. The organisation should progressively establish its connections and build up a staff with a wide range of qualifications and experience. The Organisation will thus be equipped to take the initiative in formulating recommendations designed to stimulate action by one or more nations or international authorities. Itsinitiative in making suggestions and offering advice to nations individually and collectively would be especially useful in cases in which co-ordinatedaction is required in several fields or by a number of countries. For a variety of reasons, a nation may feel itself, inhibited from initiating a discussion of problems, the solution of which appears to demandmodifications of the policies of other nations as well as of its own. In suchcases, particularly, the Organisation would be in a favourable position to initiate discussions and make recommendations.   [Art. X.]44. The advisory work of the Organisation would in appropriate cases be done in co-operation with other international authorities in related fields.[Art. XIIL](a) Typical cases and procedure.45. The Organisation should be ready and willing to meet requests fromone or more States for advice in regard to policy or for other assistance.The extent to which the Organisation&apos;s advice in regard to the problems of individual countries will be required will of course vary greatly as between countries in different stages of agricultural and economic development. Butimprovements resulting from, sound advice given to particular countries will in the long run redound to the common benefit, and by their general as well as their particular effects will promote the basic purposes of theOrganisation,   The following might be typical cases and procedures: .(a) In some cases an international convention, in the sense of a formal agreement to be ratified by a large number of nations, would bethe most effective instrument to accomplish the desired objective.Or the Organisation might frame a model code or form of treaty as a guide to member nations. Either of these methods would be suitable for agreements on such matters as the standardisation of terms, assaying samples, biological material of various kinds,weights and measures, containers, certain trade practices, methodsof appraising the nutritive values of foods and the adequacy ofdiets, and measures for preventing the spread of diseases or ofpests;    [Art. X.](b) In other cases the Council would act by means of a resolution orby adopting reports embodying proposals for action. Such aresolution or report might call for common action by the nationsaffected, the acceptance of common or related policies or changes
in policy, or the creation of an institution for the common use and benefit of a group of nations.    [Art. X, XV.](c) Raising the nutritional level of the population will in many countriesinvolve long-range programmes including the expansion andreorientation of production, the building up of food processingand consumer-goods industries, the improvement of markets, andthe expansion of such services as transportation and electric power. Complementary shifts in the production and trade of othercountries would often be required in such cases, and outside capital and technical assistance might be needed. The Organisationcould perform a useful function by helping to determine the needfor such far-reaching developments, drawing up plans, co-ordinatingaction by various countries, presenting the case for loans frominternational credit agencies, and furnishing advice and technical assistance in other ways.   [Art. X, XI, XIII.](.d) Similar but even more difficult problems occur in the case of countries or regions in which such developments and improve-,ments cannot materially relieve the poverty and malnutrition oflarge masses of people in a reasonable time. In some regionschronic poverty is in part the result of age-old traditions, highnet rates of reproduction of populations, and the lack of education,the inadequacy of roads and communication facilities, and theabsence of opportunities for industrial employment. these problems are not insoluble, but they require long-continued effort and the co-operation of many agencies. The Organisation should play a leading part in such long-term efforts. Where famine isa recurrent risk the Organisation should obtain information onprobable requirements and sources of supply, and facilitatearrangements with the Governments of member nations or with appropriate international agencies for finding the necessary men,money, and materials, free or on special terms.   [Art. XI, XIII.](e) Another type- of problem concerns areas where climatic or other factors have led. to specialisation in the production of one or afew export products. Every practicable effort should be made inthese areas to diversify production, grow more food, and providealternative employment. Usually, however, the solution of the.problem requires the enlargement of foreign markets for theexport products of the area.(b) Advice and, recommendations on other problems.46. In addition to dealing with the problems discussed so far, theOrganisation would furnish advice and make recommendations in many other cases, some of which will be of a more or less routine nature. Theinitiative in making proposals might be taken by one or mOre member nations or by the Council. Suggestions might be made to the Council bygeneral or special conferences, by the advisory committees, by the ExecutiveCommittee, and by the Director-General. The Executive Committee shouldbe especially well qualified to act as an intermediary for proposals for action to be considered by the Council, which in turn would submit recommendations to Governments. The Director-General would not make recommendations directlv to a Government unless it requested him to do so.[IV, V, VI, X.]47. Although a distinction is drawn throughout this discussion betweenthe initiation of proposals by Governments and by the Organisation, thepoint should not be over-emphasised.: To exercise its functions effectively,the Organisation would necessarily develop close working relations with governments in the course of which suggestions and advice would naturally be exchanged.   [Art. XL]48. The Organisation will be in regular communication with Govern-ments in connection - with their reports and statistical and other returns.Governments will both ask for and expect to be offered suggestions for action on their part which will amplify the information supplied and makeit comparable for the various countries; In response to requests, theOrganisation might furnish expert advisers who, together with local officials and technical personnel,, would constitute special committees or missionsauthorised to investigate and report in accordance with their terms ofreference. In general, such enquiries would have in view the making of recommendations for action.   [Art. XI, XII.]49. Similarly, the Organisation would increasingly have occasion to mapout surveys and other undertakings for example, a world agriculturalcensus, to&apos; be repeated at intervals-to be carried out in co-operation withthe Governments concerned. For these surveys, too, special committees ormissions made, up in part of local representatives would be effective machinery, and useful advice might be expected frequently to result. TheOrganisation would also- have regular advisory relations with nationalagencies such as nutrition committees and research councils.   [Art. XI.]
:. 50. In addition, collecting and disseminating information would in.themselves involve indirect advisory work which would have considerable influence. Each nation would be given the benefit of the experience of others, objectively examined as a subject of common interest. The forceof example should lead Governments to find out more about conditionsaffecting their own people, and stimulate them to introduce measures for improvement which have succeeded elsewhere, and, equally, to guard against the repetition of mistakes.4. Fisheries, Forestry, and Non-Food Agricultural Products.(a) Fisheries and marine products.51. Fisheries furnish a considerable part of the world&apos;s food supply;in &apos;some areas they are more important than agriculture as a source offood. Vitamin-rich oils extracted from the livers of cod, sharks, and otherfish have in recent years assumed great importance in nutrition andtherapy. Fisheries also furnish important by-products, such as fertilisermaterials, protein feeds for live-stock, industrial oils, leather, and variouschemicals. The technical and economic problems of&apos; those engaged infishing require largely similar treatment to the problems of those engagedin farming. Improving the production, handling, storing, processing, anddistribution of fish is vital in any concerted effort among nations to .raisethe nutritional levels and the standard of living of populations.52. Few, if any, types of food production yield returns, as quickly asdoes fishing. This fact will be of special significance after the war when there will be a general scarcity of animal proteins. During 1939-43, as during 1914-18, fisheries have been substantially replenished, and at theend of the present war well-stocked fishing grounds will constitute one ofthe world&apos;s few reserves of protective foods.53. The work of the Organisation in this field would follow the same general pattern as in agriculture, including research, education, advice, and recommendation. It should examine the possibilities for expansion of present fisheries, since in many parts of the world known marine resourcescould without harm be exploited much more intensively to supply food forhunlan beings, feed for live-stock, and materials for industry. It should encourage systematic exploration for virgin marine resources and evaluate the possibilities of their development. It should encourage the setting upof additional research laboratories to study biological, economic andtechnical problems related to the fishing industry throughout the world.[Art. XL]54. In their migrations among the waters of the world, fish have noregard for national boundaries. The conservation and wise and equitable useof fishery resources is therefore in many cases peculiarly a matter for inter-national agreements, treaties, and conventions. It would be the duty ofthe Organisation to help to formulate and to propose such international arrangements. It should also perform functions in relation to credit, whichwill be needed for the development, expansion, and rehabilitation of manyfishery enterprises, similar to the functions suggested elsewhere in thisReport in connection with agriculture.   [Art. X, XL]55. As in the case of agriculture, the Organisation should take thenecessary steps for co-operation with other bodies-in particular, theInternational Labour Organisation, which is concerned with the social conditions of fishermen; the Council for - the Exploration of the Sea(Copenhagen); the North Atlantic Council on Fishery Investigations(Ottawa); and the several bodies administering international fisheries.[Art. XIII.](b) Forestrij and forestry products.56. Forests occupy approximately 22 per cent, of the land surface ofthe earth. They play so important a part in the conservation and building up of soil and water resources that it is impossible to plan conservationmeasures on any extensive scale without including forest management and frequently afforestation in the plans. In most countries forestry andfarming or grazing constitute possible alternative uses of much of theland, and a significant part of the forest land in many countries is owned or operated by farmers. Indeed, forests are perennial crops, natural orman-made, and their products compete with or supplement other farm products for certain important uses. Farmers-are among the larger users of forest products, especially for fuel, building, and equipment. For these reasons many countries include forestry as a part of agriculture in theirgovernmental organisation.--.-57. World forest supplies have been altered by the war. New supplyproblems have been created and new uses developed. In some countriesprogress in improved methods of forest management and utilisation isbeing made at a faster rate than ever before.   Thus there are now especially
urgent reasons to consider forestry in world terms and to take concerted action to bring about ^ more efficient growing, processing, and distributionof forest products, the balancing of production and distribution with needson a world scale, and the prevention of disastrous overuse of forest resources in some countries while those of other countries go to waste for lack of effective demand, to the end that the world&apos;s forest resources may make their full contribution to the needs and the well-being of the people ofevery nation.58. As in the case of food and other agricultural products discussed inthis Report, these objectives would be accomplished through international co--operation in bringing all branches of science to bear upon the biological,technological, economic, social, and other problems involved in theproduction, distribution, and use of primary forest products; in establishing a factual basis upon which nations, individually and in concert, could buildpolicies and programmes; in helping to work out such programmes; andin promoting widespread education and public understanding of forestryproblems. The Organisation^ work in forestry would thus closely parallelthat in other fields.   [Art. X, XL]59. The Commission recommends that, in accordance with the situationin each case, the Organisation should establish close working relations withany existing international agencies concerned with forestry.   [Art. XIII, XV.](c) Non-food agricultural products.60. A considerable part of the world&apos;s agriculture is devoted to theproduction of commodities other than foods. These products are of special importance because of the contribution they make to the money income of farmers since most of them require processing and are sold as rawmaterials for cash. Some of them are necessities of life; others contributein an important measure to human health, dignity, and well-being. TheOrganisation should accord these products consideration commensurate with their importance to agriculture and to social welfare.61. Fibres constitute one of the major groups of non-food products.Of these some, such as cotton, wool, linen, and silk, are consumed mainly in clothing and household goods; others, such as jute, hemp, abaca, sisal,and henequen, are used in the form of bags, ropes, cords, and nets. other categories of non-food products include the oils and fats used in paintsand soaps; hides, skins, and furs used in clothing and in industry;beverages and beverage materials; and tobacco. It is characteristic of most of these products that their markets are international in scope andthat consumption increases and decreases with fluctuations in generalprosperity. Of many, also, production over the world tends in peacetimeto run ahead of effective demand, with a resulting depression of the living standards of producers. At the same time many of these products areespecially subject to inter-commodity competition, including the increasingcompetition of synthetic materials,62. Existing information on consumption capacity and effective demandfor some of these products in different countries, and on the relation of consumption levels to standards of living and levels of well-being, is meagreand inadequate compared with the same information in relation to food and nutrition, In sponsoring, organising, aiding, or conducting researchdesigned to develop more complete information, the Organisation will havean opportunity for service to consumers and producers. While suchfundamental facts are being sought, however, much can be done to increase and broaden the consumption of many important products for example,clothing, household textiles, paints, soaps through a general expansion of world economy, including agriculture, industry, and trade.    [Art. XL]63. The functions and activities of the Organisation will in the natureof the case include non-food as well as food products, with respect to suchmatters as agricultural organisation, agricultural credit, commodity arrange-ments, scientific and economic research, and education.   [Art. X, XL]64. The Commission recommends that, where appropriate, theOrganisation should establish close working relations with other publicinternational organisations concerned with non-food agricultural products.[Art. XIII.]5. Agricultural Credit..65. The Commission has given careful thought to the functions thatought to be performed by the Organisation in the domain of agriculturalcredit. It is manifest that the basic purposes of the Organisation willnot be achieved unless international credit for agricultural projects is madeavailable and effective on a considerable scale, and it follows that the promotion of a wise and liberal administration of international agriculturalcredit is among the-major concerns of the Organisation. . Such, an administration, indeed, is important not only to world agriculture but to[27100] d
world economy, and the doctrine of an expanding world economy, to which,at the Hot Springs Conference and elsewhere, the majority of governments have subscribed, is unlikely to be realised in the absence of sound policyand practice in regard to international agricultural credit. Investmentsdirected towards the improvement of agricultural methods should bringquick returns in increased production, and this would not only be reflected in inrproved nutrition but also in increased international trade. Indeed,that jiortion of international investments which may be directed towardsagriculture may bring about quicker effects upon world economy than largersums needed for longer term developments.66. The Commission conceives, however, that international credit and investment, whether related to agricultural or industrial development orto other purposes, would most suitably be administered by a single inter-national authority charged with the appropriate functions in respect of all such purposes. It recommends that such an authority be established byagreement between the Governments concerned, and that adequate arrange-ments be made for including the provision of agricultural credit among its functions. It further recommends that the Organisation, or in the event ofits not being established in time the Interim Commission itself, should berepresented at any international conference that may be convened for thepurpose of setting up an international credit and investment authority.67. Credit will be needed for many agricultural developments forexample, the re-equipment of agriculture, mechanisation, land reclamation,irrigation, afforestation, and increased storage, processing, and marketingfacilities for agricultural products. Agricultural credit should, however, be interpreted not only as covering its conventional forms but also as includingcredit for adjustments in other parts of the economy in the interests ofagricultural reorientation and better standards of nutrition..68. The Organisation will have a direct concern with all these matters,and it is clearly appropriate, if it is to be enabled to exercise an influence in its own field commensurate with the purposes for which it is established,that it should be recognised as a complementary body to the internationalcredit and investment authority with specific functions in regard to agricultural credit.   [Art. XL]69. The specific functions relating to agricultural credit which theCommission recommends should be assigned to the Organisation are asfollows [Art. X, XI, XIII] :-(a) The Organisation should participate in the management of the inter-national credit organisation through representation on its governing body, in order to provide for due consideration of agricultural interests in the determination of general international credit and investment policies.(6) Applications for international credit for an agricultural purpose should be considered by the international credit authority only after examination by the Food and Agriculture Organisation andin the light of its recommendations.(c) In appropriate cases, and if the Food and Agriculture organisation should so recommend, the borrowing country should be required,as a condition of the loan, to avail itself to the fullest extent, inregard to the projects for which the loan is granted, of thetechnical services and advice of the Organisation.6. Commodity Arrangements.70. Eesolution II 7 (6) of the Hot Springs Conference instructed theCommission to consider the desirability of assigning to the Organisationfunctions in the field of agricultural commodity arrangements. TheCommission has recognised the important role which such arrangements canplay in (a) co-ordinating internationally diverse or conflicting national price and marketing policies and programmes; (b) eliminating excessive fluctua-tions in prices; (c) mitigating some of the effects of trade cycles; (d) main-taining adequate supplies for consumers; and (e) ensuring markets forproducers while promoting desirable adjustments in agricultural production.Commodity arrangements for non-agricultural&apos; products have a similar role to perform, and to secure fairness of treatment, avoid confusion, and establish consistent policies, the Commission recommends to its constituentGovernments that international commodity arrangements for both agricul-tural and non-agricultural products be co-ordinated under.tthe supervision and direction of a single international authority. The Commission furtherrecommends that principles governing international commodity arrangementsfor all classes of products should be formulated by a special: international conference, and that thereafter there should be established-an international authority to review in the light of experience the application of the principlesso formulated and to co-ordinate and&apos; supervise the administration of individual commodity arrangements.
71. The Commission recommends that the Organisation, or in the eventof its not being established in time the Interim Commission itself, should participate in the international conference which it proposes should be held to formulate the principles to&apos; which all commodity arrangements should conform. It further recommends that the Organisation should berepresented on the directorate of the proposed international authority andshould be associated, where appropriate, with the working operations ofthat authority through mutual consultation and reference.    [Art. XIII.]. 72. As in the case of international agricultural credit arrangements, theOrganisation will have an important, though not an exclusive, concern in international agricultural commodity arrangements. The organisation should be entitled to propose particular commodity arrangements to theproposed international authority, or in the absence of such an aiuthority to governments, and to suggest the provisions of the arrangements soproposed. Similarly, the Organisation should.be entitled to propose thatany existing agricultural commodity arrangement should be modified orterminated.   [Art. X.]73. The Organisation will have a special competence and interest^ inregard to such arrangements as they promote or hinder better orientationof production through, agricultural adjustments and whether they may be effective in providing opportunities for supplying consumption needs fromthe most efficient sources of production. On its own initiative, or in response to requests either from the general administrative authority orfrom the individual commodity control concerned, the Organisation mayconduct enquiries regarding any international agricultural commodityarrangement, and . should furnish to Governments, to the international commodity authority, or to any authority dealing with an individualcommodity arrangement, information, analyses, or advice.   [Art. X, XL]7. Administrative Functions.74. In carrying out the duties already outlined, the Organisation will necessarily undertake certain administrative work.75. In certain circumstances the Organisation might perform adminis-strative functions in connection with a wide range of international conventions or agreements on such matters as those already mentioned. Itmight also, in agreement with the countries concerned, perform or organise-, services of an international character, such as the control of locusts andother plagues, or the search for and distribution of biological materials forthe control of predatory insects and noxious weeds.   [Art. X, XL]76. The Organisation would be free to accept and administer endow-ments or gifts for the furtherance of its work, being careful to ensure thatthe terms are not such as might cause embarrassment to the Organisation.[Art.. XVI.]77. The Organisation would be empowered to expend, if it should sodecide, part of its funds, contributed by member nations, to establishfellowships for training expert workers or carrying out research projects, tofound research institutes, or to make grants-in-aid for other purposes. Insuch cases its funds should be used, however, only for projects that have a regional or world significance and that would not be undertaken without such assistance.   [Art. XL]78. To the fullest possible extent the Organisation should utilise thefacilities and resources of other organisations, both national and inter-national, for the achievement of its purposes, and iri general should becautious about undertaking the supervision or administration of executiveagencies in fields related to its work.   [Art. XIII.] -79. The Organisation should.be entitled to consider any proposals thatmight be made or itself to make proposals for the distribution on specialterms, to those whose consumption is relatively very low, of abnormalstocks of food or other agricultural products; and it should be empoweredto assist other international bodies in administering such schemes. Thenecessity of co-ordinating such proposals with the policies of other bodiesshould be borne in mind, together with the risk that such action mightdelay necessary basic economic adjustments by giving producers an induce-ment to continue production despite the lack of effective demand for their output.   [Art. X,.XIIL]80. Much of the foregoing discussion assumes that other internationalauthorities will be created with administrative responsibilities in relatedfields, and that the Organisation will promote its own purposes by main-taining close and co-operative association- with these other authorities.A different situation would arise if such other authorities were not set up:If Governments were prepared to authorise the Organisation to fill, in wholeor in part, some of the gaps created by the absence of such other authorities,there would be a case for its undertaking further executive responsibilities.[Art. XIII, XV.][27100] d 2   &apos;
81. In particular, the Commission has recommended that the con-stituent Governments establish international authorities to deal with international credit as a whole, and with commodity arrangements as awhole, including agricultural credit in the one case and agriculturalcommodity arrangements in the other. If, however, such internationalauthorities should not be established, or if their effective operation should be unduly delayed, the Organisation would undoubtedly find itself seriouslyhampered in the promotion of its primary purposes. The Commission hasthe confident hope that this situation will not arise. If it should, theCommission conceives that it would be the duty of the Organisation torepresent to Governments that appropriate international credit andcommodity arrangements, applying to the agricultural field alone, shouldbe made. In that event, it would no doubt be appropriate to propose thatthe administrative functions involved should be performed directly by thePood and Agriculture Organisation itself.   [Art. X, XL]82. Collaboration with the United Nations Eelief and EehabilitationAdministration also has its administrative aspects, especially in relation to agricultural rehabilitation. The Organisation might well have functions to perform in connection with rehabilitation work that may need to becontinued beyond the life of the Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.The Draft Constitution of the Organisation permits it to assume suchresponsibilities at the appropriate time.   [Art. X, XI, XIII, XV.]83. The Organisation may initiate or concert plans with Governments,in co-operation with other appropriate international bodies, for the procure-ment and distribution of supplies of food and producers&apos; goods to relievefamine resulting from floods, droughts, earthquakes, or other calamities.[Art. X, XI, XIIL]B. Constitution.1. Nature of the Constitution.84. The Draft Constitution is so framed as to provide for the essentialpowers and duties of the Organisation as envisaged in Section III A of thisReport; to give scope for development within existing provisions accordingto circumstances; and to permit of considered amendment to meet undeter-mined future conditions, including more particularly the future framework of international organisations.2. Membership.85. Original membership is accorded to the nations represented at theHot Springs Conference, as and when the Constitution is accepted by their governments; but provision is made for the admission of other nations to membership, with full rights, duties, and obligations, by&apos; a two-thirds majority vote of the representatives of all the member nations.   [Art. II.]86. In view of these provisions, acceptance of the Draft Constitutionby twenty Governments is deemed to be necessary and sufficient for itsentry into force. In reaching this conclusion, the Commission ha3 had inmind the desirability, for the reasons indicated in Section III G of thisReport, of bringing the Organisation into active operation at the earliest practicable date, and also the circumstance that under present conditionsof communication acceptance by the Governments of several of the united nations may be deferred for a considerable time.   [Art. XXII.]87. Initial membership is for a period of not less than seven years.Because of the adverse and fluid conditions arising from the war and itsaftermath, with which the Organisation will have to contend during theearly stages of its development, it is thought that seven years is not too longa period for any nation to pledge its adherence and support.   [Art. XX.]88. Provision is made for withdrawal of membership by any membernation after the expiration of the initial seven-year period, withdrawal being subject to fulfilment of financial obligations to the date of withdrawal.[Art. XX.]3. Limitations on Powers of the Organisation and onObligations of Members.89. Adequate work covering the entire field indicated in this report will be only gradually achieved. Any change in functions which wouldinvolve modification of. the provisions of the Constitution requires a two-thirds majority vote of the representatives of all the member nations,and no such modification can impose a new obligation on any membernation without its consent.   [Art. XXI.]
90. The particular obligations undertaken by member nations, byacceptance of the Constitution, are as follows:  \(a) to make specified reports to the Organisation [Art. XII] ;(b) to contribute to the expenses of the Organisation [Art. X7X] ;(c) to accord appropriate diplomatic privileges to the Organisation and members of its staff [Art. VII] ;(d) to respect the international character of the responsibilities of theOrganisation^ staff [Art. VII].91. As indicated in paragraph 89 of this Report, the Draft Constitutionspecifically provides that a new obligation cannot be imposed upon anymember nation, by amendment of the Constitution, unless that obligationis formally accepted by that member nation.   [Art. XXL]92. Subject to this restriction of the power of member nations to imposenew obligations on each other, and to the further restriction that no amend-ment of the Constitution involving a new obligation shall take effect, evenas among member nations prepared to accept it, unless two-thirds of all the member nations shall have accepted it, amendments may be made, and may take effect, on adoption by a two-thirds majority vote of all member nations.[Art. XXL]C. Administrative Structure and Management.93. The success of the Organisation will depend on the quality, honesty,and usefulness of its work. It should be equipped to perform the wide range of duties proposed in the Final Act of the Hot Springs Conference,and should accordingly be readily adaptable to changing circumstances.The Governments of the member nations should be able promptly and effectively to determine its programme of work. The work done should beso widely known as to assure the full backing of public opinion and be ofsuch high quality as to command the respect of all professional workers.The Organisation should be in a position to keep itself fully informed of theneeds, policies, and practices of member nations, and to draw on the advice and services of scientific and administrative experts throughout the world.The staff should be highly competent in the different fields of activity of theOrganisation; and its character should be genuinely international.1. The Council.94. In order to assure the largest measure of responsible direct control to member Governments, the Council should consist of representatives ofthose Governments. It would be advantageous if Governments were toadopt the practice of nominating to the Council responsible Ministershaving authority in the appropriate fields of activity, accompanied by persons with special knowledge in matters of food, agriculture, and publichealth.   [Art. III.]2. The Executive Committee.95. The . Executive Committee will facilitate action in the intervalsbetween meetings of the Council. Its members will be nominated byand its powers specifically derived from the Council. The Draft Constitutionempowers the Council to delegate to the Executive Committee any powersother than those prescribed in paragraph 2 of Article II, paragraph 1 ofArticle VI, Article X, Article XIV, and Article XXI. The Commissionregards it as important that the Executive Committee should be composedof persons who, by virtue of their administrative experience or other special qualifications, can contribute to the attainment of the purpose of theOrganisation. Subject to this primary consideration, the membership ofthe Executive Gommittee should reflect as varied as possible an experienceof the different types of agricultural economy of the world. The draft constitution provides that there shall not be more than one member of theCommittee from any member nation.   [Art. IV.]3. Standing Advisory Committees.96. In order to keep the Organisation in close touch with currentscientific and economic thought and practice, the Council should appointstanding committees which would have continuing responsibility to advise the Council on the various aspects of the Organisation^ work. Suchadvisory committees should consist of persons selected on the basis of their qualifications as scientists, technical experts, or economists, or becauseof special experience, and may include representatives, of international organisations working in related fields.   [Art. V.] , &apos;97. These committees should meet several times a year. They wouldbe invited to comment on any subjects referred to them by the Council
or the Director-General and would also be entitled to initiate proposals.Their reports would be submitted to the Council and would frequently bepublished.98. It may ultimately be found necessary to establish a standing advisory committee corresponding to each main division of theOrganisation. At the beginning, however, it is proposed that advisorycommittees should be established for nutrition, for the scientific andtechnical aspects of agricultural production, for economic and socialquestions, including agricultural co-operation and social welfare, and forstatistics.4. General and Special Conferences.99. The Commission considers it important that machinery should beprovided whereby the Organisation could be in close touch with publicopinion, receive suggestions in regard to its work, and obtain the supportof representative bodies actively concerned with food and agriculturalquestions. The Draft Constitution provides, therefore, that the organisation should convene general, technical, regional, or other special conferences forthe purpose of bringing together representatives of responsible groupsconcerned with the fields of activity of the Organisation. A general conference might be in the nature of a forum in which problems, experience,and points of view would be discussed, suggestions brought forward, andrecommendations made which the Organisation would take into account inshaping its programmes of work. Governments would see that the delegations from their countries to such a general conference were fullyrepresentative of the interests involved; indeed, it might be possible in some countries for national conferences to be held at which the delegations wouldbe nominated. The Council might itself invite representatives from inter-national bodies. The Council would make the preparatory arrangements forsuch conferences.   [Art. V.]5. Director-General.100. The Director-General will be the responsible head of the Organisa-tion. He will be responsible for selecting and organising the staff, andwill direct it in the carrying out of the functions of the Organisation, and inthe execution of the policies adopted by the Council.   [AH. T/I, VII-]6. Staff.101. The staff should be competent in all of the branches of knowledgerequired to give a solid foundation to the work of the Organisation. It shouldbe drawn from different regions and, subject to the overriding considerationof competence, should collectively represent as many geographical areas as possible. Members of the staff should receive their instructions exclusivelyfrom the Organisation. Senior members of the staff should receive diplomaticprivileges and immunities, and other members of the staff should be accordedall the facilities and immunities accorded to non-diplomatic personnelattached to diplomatic missions.   [Art. VII.]102. An Organisation of this nature must grow and adapt itself tochanging circumstances. From one point of view, it is desirable that theOrganisation should move with caution. It must make its weight felt by theexcellence of its work and the high standard of its contributions. It should play a great part in guiding policies relating to nutrition and agriculturethroughout the world, but it cannot do this with its own staff on a big scaleall at once; for a fully functioning and efficient organisation cannot be built in a day. The Organisation will have a difficult course to steer. It muston the one hand be in a position to take vigorous action in the critical period just after the war when conditions are fluid and before vested interests have become established. On the other hand, it must follow a policy of careful- development, involving the painstaking study of its complicatedproblems. Those concerned with its creation must be fully alive to these considerations. The solution may be found initially in calling temporarily tothe aid of the Organisation experts from universities and from nationalorganisations who would be unable or unwilling to devote more than a relatively brief period to international work.103. The Organisation would therefore be well advised to make a numberof temporary appointments at the outset while taking ample time to choose the permanent staff carefully and awaiting the release from war service ofpersons of the ability and training neede&quot;d for its work.7. Regional and Liaison Offices.104. To facilitate much of the work described it would be desirable forthe Organisation to have liaison offices in convenient centres in various partsof the world to keep in touch with conditions in a single country or a regionincluding several countries.  In some cases it might be desirable to establish
regional offices. Such partial decentralisation would better enable theOrganisation to take full account of the diversity of conditions with which itmust deal and to maintain close association with public authorities and scientific and other organisations whose co-operation in its work will berequired.   [Art. IX.]8.&apos; Organisation and Methods of Work.105. The Director-General will need the assistance of such officials as atreasurer, a legal adviser, and a director of personnel. The heads of divisionsor departments, or whatever may be the title of the main administrative units, might constitute an administrative board responsible to the Director-General, or their collective relationship might be less rigidly defined. TheDirector-General would rely on the standing or special committees appointedby the Council to advise on various aspects of the work.106. The number or precise nature of the divisions required to handle the work cannot be determined at present. Each principal field of workmight constitute a division for example, human nutrition; the sciences and technology of agriculture, forestry, and fisheries; economic and socialquestions; statistics; education; and publications. Subdivisions might bemade in a number of ways.107. Arrangements for co-ordinating the work of the divisions, onwhatever basis they may be created, will be especially important, since theproblems to be dealt with in most cases demand simultaneous attack from many sides. For example, a problem of regional soil conservation, one oferadicating a deficiency disease, or one of shifting production to more-needed crops in a given area might demand the combined work and specialknowledge of every division. A unit of the Organisation experienced inco-ordinating the findings of specialists in many diverse fields might presenta unified set of recommendations giving due weight to the different elements of the problem.108. This kind of approach should characterise all the work of theOrganisation. It should bring every necessary skill&quot;to bear so that a givenproblem might be solved not only adequately but without the delays likelyto result from an unco-ordinated piecemeal attack.109. A major part of the Organisation^ work, as has been made clear in the earlier discussion, would be to define problems that should be attacked and to assist those most closely concerned in planning the necessary action and carrying it through successfully. In many cases the most suitablemethod would be to appoint a committee of experts, drawn in part from thestaff of the Organisation and in part from local or other especially qualifiedexperts and administrators, to investigate, report, and recommend possible courses of action; in some instances such a committee would be sent outon a field mission. Making use of such temporary committees would have great advantages. It would not be possible for the Organisation itself tohave a staff large enough to deal with all aspects of the great range of matters within its scope. The committees would provide flexible machinery and a greatly widened range of personnel to meet specific needs; they would serve to stimulate local interest and the active participation of local authorities,who would in many cases serve on the committees. Each committee wouldbe dissolved when its work was accomplished.   [Art. V.]D.-Relations with other Organisations.1. Other International Bodies.110. It is important that international agencies should pursue relatedcourses, and that their activities should not conflict. The nature and degreeof closeness of association required amongst international authorities willdiffer in different stages. Even when the general structure of future inter-national organisation is agreed upon and the basic relationships amongstauthorities determined, scope must still be allowed for relationships todevelop. Accordingly, the Draft Constitution enables the Organisation toenter into agreements with other public international organisations defining the distribution of responsibilities and methods of co-operation.   [AH. XIII.]111. The Draft Constitution permits the Organisation to fit into any future general framework of international authorities that may be agreedupon; assures freedom for it to work with other international authorities,present or future; and. in particular enables it to invite representatives ofother international authorities to participate, without the right to vote, inthe meetings of the Council.   [Art. Ill, XIII, XIV.]112. There are certain international authorities which now exist and withwhich the Organisation should agree on provisional working relationships.
113. The Organisation, will have a long-term interest in the field in whichthe United Nations Eelief and Rehabilitation Administration has immediate action responsibilities. The resolutions of the Hot Springs Conferencerecognise that a transition will have to be effected between the concertedarrangements of the United Nations in regard to food and other supplies,during and immediately following the war, and their policies in shapinglonger-term adjustments of agricultural production Snd levels of foodconsumption.114. At the first meeting of the Council of the Relief and rehabilitation administration, held, at Atlantic City, a resolution was adopted statingthat &quot;the work of UNRRA will be confined to the short-term problems of relief and of the beginning of rehabilitation &apos;&apos;; that it was important thatthe action taken in the relief period &quot; should not hamper the long-termagricultural reconstruction programmes &apos;&apos;; and that therefore the relief and Rehabilitation Administration and its Director-General &quot; should take every necessary measure to secure the closest association between its ownwork and the activities of the Food and Agriculture Organisation and between their respective staffs and standing committees.&quot;115. Arrangements should also be reached whereby the Organisationmight at the proper time draw upon the records and experience of theUnited Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, which will haveinvaluable information on food and agricultural conditions in many partsof the world. Similarly the Organisation should arrange to procure fromwartime inter-governmental agencies, such as the Combined Food Board,Middle East Supply Centre, and the various military authorities concernedwith civilian affairs, all data which have a bearing on the work of theOrganisation. For example, the recent study of the comparative levels offood consumption in various countries made by the Combined Food board should prove of great value.   [Art. XIII.&apos;]116. The Interim Commission intends to submit separately recom-mendations regarding the International Institute of Agriculture.117. The Governments concerned will probably in due course considerthe future organisation and adaptation of the work now being done bythe League of Nations and its various committees and sections in connectionwith a general settlement of the structure of international authorities afterthe war. &quot;Working arrangements should meanwhile be established betweenthe Organisation and those agencies connected with the League which areactive in related fields.118. The resolutions of the Hot Springs Conference contemplate thatthe Organisation should convene periodic meetings of representatives ofnational nutrition organisations or committees, and the proceedings would presumably be reported to the Council. The contemplated reports bymember Governments would also presumably include accounts of thework of these organisations, together with a statement of progress other-wise achieved in nutritional matters. It is further contemplated that theOrganisation would periodically publish a summary of member Governments&apos;reports. By a resolution adopted in 1937, the League has practicallyidentical responsibilities, and the Governments of the nations that are members of the League were requested to furnish corresponding reports.Joint technical committees might with advantage be set up, therefore, toarrange for the orderly assumption by the Organisation of activitiespreviously developed by such other agencies.   [Art. V, VII, XIII.]119. There are a number of subjects in which the Organisation,following the recommendations of the Hot Springs Conference, will havean interest in common with that of the International Labour Organisation,and others in which their interests will be closely related. Conditions ofagricultural labour and work in the field of co-operative organisations arecases in point.120. The International Labour Organisation has adopted a number ofconventions and recommendations concerning agriculture, and has appointed a .committee concerned specifically with agriculture. Labour conferencesof American States and the first Inter-American Social Security Conferencedealt with the extension of social services to farm families; and a permanentcommittee on migration for settlement has been proposed under the auspices of the International Labour Organisation. The Food and agriculture organisation should agree with the appropriate authorities of the Inter-national Labour Organisation on arrangements for co-operation in regardto these subjects.   [Art. XIII.]2. Regional and National Organisations.121. The Organisation will need the co-operation and support not only of Governments and other international authorities but also of regional and national scientific and economic institutions, both public and private,which are concerned with food and agriculture. Experts from regional and national institutions might be appointed as members of the standing
advisory committees of the Organisation; members of the staffs and researchworkers from these institutions should be associated for varying periodswith the work of its special committees; and the Organisation shouldentrust tasks to these institutions and engage in joint undertakings withthem. It should explore the possibility of concluding arrangements with appropriate institutions whereby they would carry on work on behalf of theOrganisation or in association with it.    [Art. XIII.]. 122. Precedents of the kind exist. For example, the health organisation of the League of Nations entrusted to the National Institutefor Medical Research (London) the custody and distribution of internationalstandards for many biological preparations and other related tasks; anda Conference on Rural Hygiene in the Far Bast selected the NutritionResearch Laboratory at Conoor, India, to act as the centre for research innutrition in that region.123. There are advantages in having abstracting and other information services supplied as far as possible by institutions that are already doingoutstandingly good work of this kind. The Organisation should therefore seek arrangements whereby certain present information services, which areextensive and valuable, might receive wider circulation and perhaps beextended to those parts of the field which are not now covered. TheOrganisation should explore such possibilities, for example, with theappropriate authorities of the Imperial Agricultural Bureaux, the PasteurInstitutes, and Inter-American Institute of Agricultural Sciences, and national research councils or academies in various countries.   [Art. XI, XIII.]E. Expenses.124. Under the provisions of Articles X and XIX of the draft constitution the Council is empowered to approve annual budgets for eachfinancial year after that in which the Organisation is established and todetermine the apportionment among member nations -of the required totalcontributions thereto.125. In regard to both these matters, however, it will be convenientthat specific proposals, relating to the year in which the Organisation is established, should be formulated- in advance by the Interim Commission,both to provide the Organisation with a financial basis for immediateoperation and to afford the Governments of the United Nations an indication of the measure of financial obligation involved at the outset by acceptanceof.the Commission^ proposals.126. The Commission has accordingly prepared provisional estimates,based on varying hypotheses, of the expenses likely to be incurred by theOrganisation during the first five years of operation. For this purpose ithas drawn on the experience of existing international organisations and hashad the assistance of a number of their officials.127. After careful consideration of provisional estimates so prepared,the Commission recommends that the average expenditure by theOrganisation during the first five years should be estimated at about$5,000,000 per annum.128. Considerably less than this amount is likely to be spent in thefirst year, however, by reason of unavoidable delays in the recruitment of the necessary expert staff and in the initial preparation of operationalplans. The Commission, therefore, recommends that the budget of theOrganisation for the first financial year be $3,500,000 and that up to$2,500,000 of this amount be earmarked as a capital fund to meet theunusual expenses involved in getting the new international organisationstarted and to provide funds at the beginning of each financial year beforenational contributions have been fully received.129. The Commission has found it difficult to devise a wholly satisfactoryscale of apportionment of expenses. It has considered whether such a scale might be formulated, based on such factors as capacity to pay modified,e.g., by the desirability of maximum and minimum limits to contributions,the importance of agricultural production, national income, foreign trade, &amp;c. If this could have been done and if-world conditions werenormal, such a scale might have been adopted by the Council for an indefinite period, or, at least, for the five-year period referred to above. the abnormal circumstances created by war and enemy occupation, however,and the impossibility of knowing when they will terminate, render itimpossible to formulate a scale&apos;which is likely to- be regarded as satisfactoryexcept for a very short rperiod. During the first or \second year theCouncil probably will wish to consider, in the light of the conditions thenprevailing, the equity of the scale which the Commission now recommends.This scale, recommended for temporary use, is based upon a&apos; relationship[27100] e
among the member nations growing out of that accepted by them in respectof pre-war international organisations, but adjusted as follows:  (a) the assumption of 56-5 per cent, of the allocations by the UnitedStates, the United Kingdom, the Soviet Union, and China;(6) the scaling down of the allocations, as a measure of temporaryfinancial relief, for those countries that are occupied by the enemy,or that have, in consequence of the war, suffered from major economic disasters;   and(c) the placing of certain countries on a uniform minimum allocation.The result of (6) and (c) has been substantially to increase the temporaryallocations to the remaining countries. When world conditions improve,the proportions allocated to these countries will have to be correspondingly reduced.130. Accordingly, the Commission recommends that the following scalebe accepted by the Governments concerned for application during thefinancial year in which the Constitution comes into force and have soprovided in Article XXVI of the Draft Constitution:  AustraliaBelgiumBoliviaBrazilCanadaChile ......ChinaColombiaCosta Rica ...Cuba ...&quot;Czechoslovakia-DenmarkDominican RepublicEcuadorEgypt        ......El Salvador......EthiopiaEranceGreeceGuatemala  ...HaitiHondurasIceland &apos;IndiaPercent.332829460615507105714062050573052969380505050525IranIraqLiberiaLuxembourgMexicoNetherlandsNew ZealandNicaraguaNorwayPanamaParaguayPeruPhilippines. ...PolandUnion of South AfricaU.S.S.R.United Kingdom   ...United StatesUruguay     ...VenezuelaYugoslavia  ...TotalPercent.-71-4405-051-871-381-15-05-62-05-05-71-251-192-3110-0015-0025-00-58-58-71100-00F. Miscellaneous.1. Legal Status.131. The Draft Constitution gives the Organisation the legal capacity,commonly accorded to corporate bodies, under municipal law, to concludecontracts, to own and deal with property, to accept endowments or gifts,and generally to perform legal acts appropriate to its purposes.   [Art. XVI.]132. The Organisation is further given the immunities and privilegescustomarily accorded by member nations to each other, and as a corollary of the bestowal of these immunities, the Council is required to make provision for the adjudication by an administrative tribunal of disputeswith its staff, which in the absence of the Organisation&apos;s immunity from suitwould be the subject of ordinary legal process.   [Art. XVI.]2. Interpretation of Constitution.133. Provision is made in the Draft Constitution for the reference toan appropriate international court of any question or dispute concerninginterpretation of the Constitution, in such manner as may be provided byrules to be adopted by the Council.   [Art. XVIII.]3. Languages.134. The Draft Constitution leaves the question of official languages tobe determined by the Council. Pending such determination, it is providedthat the business of the Organisation shall be conducted in English.[Art. XXIV.]
G. Need for Early Action.135. The Commission has given earnest consideration to the questionwhether the Organisation should be brought into being at an early date, orwhether its establishment should be deferred until after the war.136. There are undoubtedly considerations in favour of the latteralternative. During the war, and probably for a considerable period there-after, it will be impossible for the Organisation to recruit all of the highlyqualified personnel essential to full operation. It is a matter of the greatest importance that the Organisation should not begin its work without theinspiration and direction of men of the highest calibre and competence intheir fields. The success of the Organisation will depend on the quality&apos;,honesty, and usefulness of its work, and on the extent to which, by its work,it can make its disinterested authority and influence felt. A false startwould mean a handicap from the beginning.137. During the war, also, many of the Governments and other bodieswith which the Organisation would work will be so preoccupied with othermatters as to be unable to give it- complete co-operation.138. These are valid considerations to a realistic view-; but a realisticview calls for- deeper analysis. In the period immediately following the cessation of hostilities there will be many serious problems in nutrition,food and agriculture, in many parts of the world, calling urgently forsolution. This period will be characterised by conditions of fluidityparticularly favourable to the adoption of sound and thoroughgoing measuresto meet these problems. There will be both need and opportunity for thekind of international advice and influence which it is the purpose of the.Organisation to provide. It would be lamentable if none were to beprovided. Indeed if this unique opportunity to realise some of the highpurposes of the Hot Springs Conference were to be lost and the fluidityof the immediate post-war period were to be allowed to become set andrigid with the growth of vested interests, it might prove impossible, formany years to come, to give effect to the purposes of the United nations as expressed in the Final Act of that Conference. To delay the beginningwould be to delay the whole programme.139. Personnel must be assembled; co-operative relationships must beestablished with organisations and Governments; problems of nutrition andof the production and distribution of foods and other products must be clearly defined and studied, and their relative urgency must be determined;a considerable amount of information must be collected and analysed. Insum, a good deal of preliminary work will be needed to make theOrganisation a going concern, ready to discharge its responsibilities.140. These considerations greatly outweigh the argument against-starting at this time. The Commission believes the main difficulty assembling an adequate staff can be,overcome by developing a carefully selected nucleus of permanent personnel aided by a group of competentexperts employed on a temporary basis in other words, loaned by Govern-ments and institutions. This might be desirable in any event; under presentconditions it is the most practical procedure.141. In the light of these considerations and because it is mindful ofthe dangers of a return to national policies of self-sufficiency, the Commis-sion urges its constituent Governments to take, with a minimum of delay,the action required to-enable the Organisation to be brought into effectiveoperation, on a nucleus basis if necessary, at the earliest practicable date.The sooner it is established, the sooner will it be able to bring to bear uponpost-war problems of reconstruction the disinterested, international, andinstructed advice and influence the provision of which is the essentialpurpose of the Organisation.142. The considered view of the Commission is that, whatever thedifficulties, the Organisation should be established as soon as possible, andthat Governments in a position to do so should make every contribution intheir power, by releasing suitable personnel and otherwise, towards making it an effective and authoritative nucleus for dealing with both immediate and longer-term problems of adjustment in food and agriculture. TheCommission so recommends.[27100]
APPENDIX I.   :Dkaft Constitution of the Food and Agriculture Organisation op the united nations.The United Nations being determined  &apos;To work separately and together to the end that want and the fear of wantshall be progressively abolished;To take all measures within their power to raise the level of nutrition andthe standard of living of the peoples under their jurisdiction;To improve the efficiency of agricultural production and distribution ;and being resolved To co-operate internationally for the achievement of these ends;hereby establish the Food and Agricultural Organisation of the United Nations,hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Organisation,&quot; which shall be governed by theprovisions of this Constitution, and through which the United Nations agree toreport to one another on the measures taken and the progress achieved.Article I (Purpose).The purpose of the Organisation shall be to promote the common welfare byfurthering separate and collective action by the Member nations to raise levels of nutrition and standards of living, to secure improvements in the efficiency ofthe production and distribution of all food and agricultural products, to better theCondition of rural populations, and to contribute towards an expanding world economy.Article II (Membership).1. The original Members of the Organisation shall be such of the nationsspecified in the attached Schedule as accept this&apos; Constitution in accordance withthe provisions of Article XXII.2. New Members may be admitted to the Organisation by a vote concurred in by a two-thirds majority of all the members of the Council. Admission to theOrganisation shall involve the obligation to comply with all the provisions of this constitution.Article III (The Council).1. There shall be a Council of the Organisation on which each Member nationshall be represented b3&quot; one member of the Council.2. Each Member nation may appoint an alternate and associate members ofthe Council and advisers to the members of the Council. The Council may makerules concerning the participation of associate members and advisers in its proceedings.3.   No member of the Council may represent more than one Member nation.4.   Each Member nation shall have only one vote.5. The Council may invite any public international organisation which hasresponsibilities related to those of the Organisation to appoint a representativewho shall participate in its meetings on the conditions prescribed by the Council.No such representative shall have the right to vote.6.   The Council shall meet at least once in every year.7. The Council shall elect its own&apos; officers, regulate its own procedure, and make rules governing the convocation of sessions and the determination of agenda.8. Except as otherwise expressly provided in this Constitution or by rules madeTjy the Council, all matters shall be decided by the Council by a simple majorityof the votes cast.Article IV (The Executive Committee).1. The Council shall appoint an Executive Committee consisting of not lessthan nine nor more than fifteen members or alternate or associate members of theCouncil or their advisers who are qualified by administrative experience or other special qualifications to contribute to the attainment of the purpose of theOrganisation. There shall be not more than one member from any Member nation.The tenure and other conditions of office of members of the Executive committee shall be subject to rules to be made by the Council.2. Subject to the provisions of paragraph 1 of this Article, the Council shallhave regard in appointing the Executive Committee to the desirability that its membership should reflect as varied as possible an experience of different types of economy in relation to food and agriculture.3. The Council may delegate to the Executive Committee such powers as itmay determine, with the exception of the powers set forth in paragraph 2 ofArticle II, paragraph 1 of Article VI, Article X, Article XIV and Article XXIof this Constitution.4. The members of the Executive Committee shall exercise the powers delegated to them by the Council on behalf of the whole Council and not as representativesof their respective Governments.5. The Executive Committee shall appoint its own officers and, subject to any decisions of the Council, shall regulate its own procedure.Article V (Other Committees and Conferences).1. The Council may establish technical and regional standing committees andmay appoint&apos; committees to study and report on any matter pertaining to thepurpose of the Organisation.2. The Council may convene general, technical, regional or other specialconferences and may provide for the representation at such conferences, in such manner as it may determine, of national and international bodies concerned withnutrition, food and agriculture.
Article VI (The Director-General).1. There shall be a Director-General of the Organisation who shall be appointedby the Council by such procedure and on such terms as it may determine.2. Subject to the general supervision of the Council and its ExecutiveCommittee, the Director-General shall have full power and authority to direct thework of the Organisation.3. The Director-General or a representative designated by him shall participate,without the right to vote, in -all meetings of the Council and of its ExecutiveCommittee and shall formulate for consideration by the Council and the ExecutiveCommittee proposals for appropriate action in regard to matters coming beforethem.Article VII (Staff).1.   The staff of the Organisation shall be appointed by the Director-General inaccordance with such procedure as may be determined by rules made by. theCouncil.2. The staff of the Organisation shall be responsible to the Director-General.Their responsibilities shall be exclusively international in character and they shallnot seek or receive instructions in regard to the discharge thereof from any authority external to the Organisation. The Member nations undertake fully to.respect the international character of the responsibilities of the staff and not to seek to influence any of their nationals in the discharge of such responsibilities.3. In appointing the staff the Director-General shall, subject to the paramount importance of securing the highest standards of efficiency and of technicalcompetence, pay due regard to the importance of selecting personel recruited on as wide a geographical basis as is possible.4. The Government of each Member nation undertakes, in so far as it maybe possible under its constitutional procedure, to accord to the Director-Generaland senior staff diplomatic privileges and immunities and to accord to othermembers of the staff all facilities and immunities accorded to non-diplomaticpersonnel attached to diplomatic missions.Article VIII (Seat).The seat of the Organisation shall be determined by the Council.Article IX (Regional and Liaison Offices).1. There shall be such regional offices as the Director-General with the approvalof the Council may decide.2. The Director-General may establish offices and appoint officials for. liaison with particular countries or areas.Article X (Functions of the Council).1. The Council shall determine the policy and approve the budget of theOrganisation and shall exercise the other powers conferred upon it by this constitution.2. The Council may by a two-thirds majority of the votes cast adopt recom-mendations concerning questions relating to food and agriculture to be submittedto Member nations for consideration with a view to implementation by nationalaction.3. The Council may by a two-thirds majority of the votes cast adopt conven-tions concerning questions relating to food and agriculture to be submitted to member nations for consideration with a view to ratification by the appropriateconstitutional procedure. Each Member nation which ratifies such a convention shall take such action as may be necessary to make effective the provisions of theconvention in accordance with the terms thereof.4. The Council shall make rules laying down the procedure to the followedto secure1-(a) Proper consultation with Governments and adequate technical preparation. prior to consideration by the Council of proposed recommendations andconventions;  and(b) Proper consultation with Governments in regard to relations between theOrganisation and national institutions or private persons.5. The Council may make recommendations to any public international organisation regarding any matter pertaining to the purpose of the Organisation.6. The Council may by a, two-thirds majority of the votes cast agree todischarge any other functions assigned to it by Governments or provided for byany arrangement between the Organisation and any other public international organisation.Article XI (Functions of the Organisation).1.   The functions of the Organisation shall be:  (a) To  collect,   analyse,   interpret   and   disseminate  information   relating tonutrition, food and agriculture;(6) To promote scientific, technological, social and economic research relatingto nutrition, food and agriculture;(c) To promote the improvement of ediication and administration relating tonutrition, food and agriculture, and the spread of public knowledge ofnutritional and agricultural science and practice;(d) To promote the conservation of natural resources and the adoption of improved methods of agricultural production;(e) To promote the improvement of the processing, marketing and distributionof food and agricultural products;(/) To promote the adoption of policies for the provision of adequate agricul-tural credit, national and international; &apos;(g) To promote the adoption of international policies with regard to agriculturalcommodity arrangements; .[27100] F 2
(/(,) To furnish such technical assistance as Governments may request;(i) To organise, in consultation with the Governments concerned, such missionsas may be needed to assist them to fulfil the obligations arising from their acceptance of the recommendations of the United Nations Conference on food and Agriculture; and0) Generally to take all necessary and appropriate action to implement thepurpose of the Organisation as set forth in Article I.Article XII (Reports by Members).1. Each Member nation shall communicate periodically to the Organisationreports on the progress made toward achieving the purpose of the Organisation setforth in Article I, and on the action taken on the basis of recommendations andconventions adopted by the Council.2. These reports shall be made at such times and in such form and shall containsuch particulars as the Council may request.3. The Director-General shall submit these reports, together with analysesthereof, to the Council, and shall publish such reports and analyses as may be approved for publication by the Council together with any reports relating theretoadopted by the Council.4. The Director-General may request any Member nation to submit information relating to the purpose of the Organisation.5. Each Member nation shall communicate to the Organisation, on publication,all laws and regulations and official reports and statistics concerning nutrition,food and agriculture.Article XIII (Co-operation with othq? Organisations).1. The Organisation shall act in close co-operation with other public inter-national organisations with related responsibilities.2.   Subject to the provisions of Article XIV, the Council may enter into agree-ments with the competent authorities of such organisations defining the distributionof responsibilities and methods of co-operation and shall maintain  such joint. committees with  such  organisations  as  may  be  necessary to&apos; assure  effective co-operation.3. The Director-General may, subject to any decisions of the Council, enterinto agreements with other public international organisations for the maintenanceof common services, for common arrangements in regard to recruitment, training,conditions of service, and other related matters, and for interchanges of staff.Article XIV (Relation to any General World Organisation).1. The Organisation shall, in accordance with the procedure provided for inthe following paragraph, constitute a part of any general international organisa-tion to which may be entrusted the co-ordination of the activities of international organisations with specialised responsibilities.2. The Council shall approve arrangements for defining the relationship of theOrganisation to any such general Organisation and, notwithstanding the provisionsof Article XXI, such arrangements may, if approved by the Council by a two-thirds majority of the votes cast, involve modification of the provisions of this constitution.Article XV (Supervision of other Organisations and Creation of New Agencies).1. The Council may approve arrangements placing other public international organisations dealing with questions relating to food and agriculture under thegeneral authority of the Organisation on such terms as may be agreed with thecompetent authorities of the organisation concerned.2. The Council may establish such agencies as may be necessary to performany function pertaining to the purpose of the Organisation and confer upon them the legal capacity necessary for the satisfactory discharge thereof.Article XVI (Legal Status).1. The Organisation shall have legal capacity to conclude contracts, to acquire,hold and convey property, to accept endowments or gifts, and in general to assumeand discharge obligations and perform any legal act appropriate to its purpose.The acquisition of real property by the Organisation within the territory of anyMember nation shall be governed by the law of that nation.2. The Government of each Member nation undertakes, in so far as it maybe possible under its constitutional procedure, to accord to the Organisation allimmunities and facilities which it accords to diplomatic missions, including inviola-bility of premises and archives, immunity from suit and exemptions from taxation.&apos;3. The Council shall make provision for the determination by an administrativetribunal of disputes relating to the conditions and terms of appointment ofmembers of the staff.Article XVII (Fish and Forest Products).In this Constitution the term &quot;agriculture&quot; and its derivatives includefisheries, marine products, forestry and primary forestry products.Article XVIII (Interpretation of Constitution).Any question or dispute concerning the interpretation of this Constitution orany international convention adopted thereunder shall be referred for determina-tion to an appropriate international court or arbitral tribunal in the mannerprescribed by rules to be adopted by the Council.
Article XIX (Expenses).1. The expenses of the Organisation shall be borne by the Member nations inthe proportions decided by the Council.2. Each Member nation shall, upon its acceptance of this Constitution, be underobligation to pay as its first contribution its proportion of the annual budget for the current financial year.3. The financial year of the Organisation shall be the 1st July to the 30th Juneunless the Council should otherwise determine. The annual contributions of each member nation shall become due for payment on the first day of the financialyear.Article XX (Withdrawal).Any Member nation may give notice of withdrawal from the Organisation atany time after the expiration of five years from the entering into force of this constitution. Such notice shall take effect two years after the date of itscommunication to the Director-General of the Organisation subject to the Membernation&apos;s having at that time paid its annual contribution for each year of its membership, including the two financial years following the date of such notice.Article XXI (Amendment of Constitution).1. Amendments to this Constitution involving new obligations for member nations shall require the approval of the Council by a vote concurred in by a two-thirds majority of all the members of the Council, and shall take effect onacceptance by two-thirds of the Member nations for each Member nation accepting the amendment and thereafter for each remaining Member nation on acceptance by it.2. Other amendments shall take effect on adoption by the Council by a voteconcurred in by a two-thirds majority of all the members of the Council.Article XXII (Entry into Force of Constitution).1. This Constitution shall be open to acceptance by the nations specified inthe attached Schedule.2. The instruments of acceptance shah be transmitted by each Governmentto the United Nations Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture, which shallnotify their receipt to the Governments of the nations specified in the attachedSchedule. Acceptance may be notified to the Interim Commission through a diplomatic representative, in which case the instrument of acceptance must be transmitted to the Commission as soon as possible thereafter.3. This Constitution shall come into force upon the receipt of twenty notifica-tions of acceptance by the United Nations Interim Commission on Food and agriculture..4. Acceptances, the notification of which is received after the entry intoforces of this Constitution, shall become effective upon receipt by the interim commission or the Organisation.Article XXIII (First Session of the Council).The United Nations Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture shall convenethe first session of the Council at a suitable date after the entry into force of this constitution.Article XXIV (Languages).Pending the adoption by the Council of any rules regarding the languages, thebusiness of the Council shall be transacted in English.Article XXV (Temporary Seat).The temporary seat of the Organisation shall be at Washington unless theCouncil should otherwise determine.Article XXVI (First Financial Year).For the financial year in which this Constitution comes into force, the budget,and the proportion thereof to be borne by each Member nation, shall be as setforth in the Second Report to the Governments of the United Nations by the interim Commission on Food and Agriculture.Article XXVII (Dissolution of the Interim Commission).On the opening of the first session of the Council, the United Nations interim commission on Food and Agriculture shall be deemed to be dissolved and itsrecords and other property shall become the property of the Organisation.Done at Washington this day of ,one thousand nine hundred and forty , in the English language, ina single copy which will be deposited in the archives of the United Nations interim commission on Food and Agriculture until the coming into force of this Constitu-tion and thereafter in the archives of the Food and Agriculture Organisation ofthe United Nations, and of which authenticated copies will be transmitted to theGovernments of the nations enumerated in the attached Schedule and of Membersadmitted to the Organisation by the Council in accordance with the provisions ofArticle II.In witness whereof we have appended our signatures:-
Schedule referred toAustralia.Belgium.Bolivia.Brazil.Canada.Chile.China.Colombia.Costa Rica.Cuba.Czechoslovakia.DenmarkDominican Republic.Ecuador.Egypt.El Salvador.Ethiopia.France.Greece.Guatemala.Haiti.Honduras.Iceland.the Draft Constitution.India.Iran.Iraq.Liberia.Luxembourg.Mexico.Netherlands.New Zealand.Nicaragua.Norway.Panama.Paraguay.Peru.Philippine Commonwealth.Poland.Union of South Africa.Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.United Kingdom.United States of America.Uruguay.Venezuela.Yugoslavia.APPENDIX II.Members op the Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture.L. B. Pearson (Canada), Chairman.P. I. Tchegoula (U.S.S.R.), Vice-Chairman.P. W. Tsou (China), Mice-Chairman.Australia :F. L. McDougall, Economic Adviser tothe Australian High Commissioner,London.Belgium :Viscount Alain du Pare, minister to the United States.Charles Leonard, Agricultural Attacheof the Embassy of Belgium, Washing-ton.Bolivia :Rene Ballivian, Commercial Counsellorof the Embassy of Bolivia, Washing-ton.Brazil :Carlos Maximiano de Figueiredo,Minister Plenipotentiary to theUnited States.Canada:L. B. Pearson, Minister Counsellor ofthe Embassy of Canada, Washington.Chile :Carlos Campbell del Campo, Com-mercial Counsellor of the Embassyof Chile, Washington.China :P. W. Tsou, Senior Adviser to the ministries of Food and of Agricultureand Forestry of China, Washington.Colombia :Guillermo Suarez, Commercial Attacheof the Embassy of Colombia, Washing-ton.Costa Rica :Carlos Manuel Escalante, ambassador to the United States.Don Luis Cruz,  Agricultural Attacheof   the   Embassy - of   Costa   Rica,Washington.Cuba :Felipe Pazos, Commercial Attache ofthe Embassy of Cuba, Washington.Czechoslovakia :Jan Vaclav Hyka, Commercial Counsel-lor of the Embassy of Czechoslovakia,Washington.Dominican Republic :Rafael A. Espaillat, CommercialAttache of the Embassy of theDominican Republic, Washington.Ecuador:Captain Colon Eloy Alfaro, ambassador to the United States.Emilio A. Maulme, commercial counsellor of the Embassy ofEcuador, Washington.Ramon de Ycaza, Commercial Attacheof the Embassy of Ecuador, Washing-ton.Egypt :Anis Azer, Commercial Counsellor ofthe Royal Legation of Egypt,Washington.El Salvador :Carlos Adalberto Alfaro, First Secre-tary of the Embassy or El Salvador,Washington.Ethiopia :Yiirna Deressa, Vice-Minister ofFinance.French Representative :Andre Mayer, Professor and Vice-President, College de France.Christian Valensi, Financial Counsellorof the French Mission to the UnitedStates, Washington.Greece:Kyriakos Varvaressos, Governor of theBank of Greece.Cimon P. Diamantopoulos, ambassador to the United States.Guatemala :Francisco Linares-Aranda, second secretary of the Embassy of Guate-mala, Washington.Haiti :Elie Garcia, First Secretary of the embassy of Haiti, Washington.Honduras :Julian R. Caceres, Ambassador to theUnited States.
Iceland :Thor Thors, Minister to the UnitedStates.India :Sir   Girja   Shankar   Bajpai,    Agent-General for India, Washington.T. B. Creagh Coen, First Secretary to, the Agent-General.Iran :Dr. Ali Akbar Daftary, Counsellor ofthe   Imperial - Legation   of   Iran,Washington.H.  Hadjeb-Davallou,  First Secretaryof the Imperial Legation of Iran,Washington.Iraq :Darwish Haidari, Director of theCentral Agricultural ExperimentalStation, Bagdad.Liberia :Gabriel L. Dennis, Former Secretary ofthe Treasury.Luxembourg:Hughes Le Gallais, Minister to theUnited States.Mexico :Rafael de la Colina, Minister-Counsellorof the Embassy of Mexico, Washing-ton.Vicente Sanchez Gavito, Counsellor ofthe Embassy of Mexico, Washington.Netherlands:M. P. L. Steenberghe, President of theEconomic,   Financial   and  ShippingMission   of   the   Kingdom   of   theNetherlands..  L. A. H. Peters, Agricultural Attacheof the Embassy of the Netherlands,Washington.New Zealand :Walter Nash, Minister to the UnitedStates.G. S. Cox, First Secretary of the Lega-tion of New Zealand, Washington.Adviser:B. R. Turner, Second Secretary,Legation of New Zealand, Wash-ington.Nicaragua :Dr. Alberto Sevilla Sacasa, Secretaryof the Embassy of Nicaragua,Washington.Norway :Anders Fjelstad, Delegate of theRoyal Norwegian Government forAgricultural Affairs in the UnitedStates.Panama:Ricardo A- Morales, Counsellor of the embassy of Panaimi, Washington.Paraguay:Paris E. Menendez, Director of CentralLaboratory, Ministry of Agriculture..Peru :Juan Chavez D., Minister-commercial counsellor of the Embassy of Peru,Washington.Phillippine Commonwealth :Joaquin M. Elizalde, Resident Com-missioner of the Philippines to theUnited States.Urbano A. Zafra, Commercial Assistantto the Resident Commissioner.Amando M. Dalisay, Research Analyst,Philippine Commonwealth, Washing-ton.Poland :Wieslaw Domaniewski, commercial counsellor of the Embassy of Poland,Washington.Union of South Africa :A. T. Brennan, Director and DeputyHead, Union of South Africa Govern-ment Supply Mission, Washington.-W. C. Naude, Attache of the Legationof South Africa, Washington.J. A. Siegruhn, Commercial Attache ofthe    Legation    of    South    Africa,Washington.Union of Soviet Socialist Republics :P. I. Tchegoula, Chairman of the All-. Union    Combine    &quot; Eksportkhleb,&quot;and   Member   of   the   GovernmentPurchasing Commission of the soviet union in the United States.Adviser:B. I. Groudinko, Foodstuffs Depart-ment Purchasing Commission ofthe Soviet Union in the UnitedStates of America.United Kingdom:Edward Twentyman, Second Secretary,Ministry of Food.Advisers :Redvers Opie, Economic Adviser,British Embassy, Washington.J. A. Scott Watson, AgriculturalAttache, British Embassy, Wash-ington.P. H. Gore-Booth, British Embassy,Washington.United States of America :Paul H. Appleby, Under-Secretary ofAgriculture.Uruguay:. Juan Felipe Yriart, First Secretary ofthe Embassy of Uruguay, Washing-ton.Venezuela:Marco A. Falcon Brincefio, commercial counsellor of the Embassy ofVenezuela, Washington.Yugoslavia :Branko     Cubrilovich,     Minister     ofAgriculture.George Radin, Special Representativeof the Yugoslav Government.The Danish Minister :Henrik de Kauffmann, Minister to theUnited States.Count     Benedict     Ahlefeldt-LaurvigFinancial  Counsellor   of  the  RoyalLegation of Denmark, Washington.J. Rechendorff, Secretary of the RoyalLegation of Denmark, Washington.EXECUTIVE SECRETARY OF THE COMMISSION:Howard S. Piquet.






</content>
</cab>
