<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/46/20 images: 198-213</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
$THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1,944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (M) 70.2%a! February, 1944.WAR CABINET.AUSTRALIA-NEW ZEALAND AGREEMENT OF 21st JANUARY, 1944.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I have not hitherto circulated to my colleagues any paper with regard tothe recent Canberra Conference between Australia ar^d New Zealand, as it-seemed premature to do so until the comments of Sir Ronald Cross had beenreceived. But these have now come in, and I feel that the Cabinet will wishto have some general assessment of the position, as it has now developed. Forpurposes of reference, I attach the text of the Agreement between the Govern-ments of Australia and New Zealand, signed at Canberra on the 21st January,1944 (Annex 1). I also annex a telegram since received from the PrimeMinisters of Australia and New Zealand in which they ask for our views on certain aspects of the conclusions of the Conference (Annex 2).2. The preliminary history of this conference, so far as we are concerned,is as follows. At the end of November I heard, indirectly, that the australian government had invited the New Zealand Government to a conference to discusspolitical and strategic problems of the Pacific. On the 28th December, Dr. Evatt,the Australian Minister of External Affairs, announced publicly the impendingvisit to Canberra of Mr. Fraser, the New Zealand Prime Minister, for theConference. On the 30th December the Australian High Commissioner in London,at Dr. Evatts request, communicated to me an extract from the published state-ment. This was the first official intimation to us of the Conference from either government. On the same day, the United Kingdom flight Commissioner in new Zealand telegraphed that Mr. Fraser had informally asked him to obtain an indication of our own attitude. In reply, I telegraphed that our under-standing here was that this was a preliminary mutual consultation betweenAustralia and New Zealand in order to define their attitude towards future arrangements in the South and South-West Pacific before consultation with ourselves and other foreign countries concerned; that in view of our close and direct interest in that area we assumed that the two Governments intended todiscuss these matters with us before foreign countries were brought in, andthat an occasion for such consultation would be provided by the projected PrimeMinisters&apos; meeting in London.3. While the Conference was proceeding, our High Commissioner inAustralia saw the Prime Minister of Australia and obtained from him his personal assurance that any announcement of the results of the conference would contain a statement that the next step would be discussion with the UnitedKingdom Government. In fact, however, the conclusions of the conference were published without any such statement being made by the Australian and NewZealand authorities.4. After the Conference was over, Sir R. Cross had an interview withdraw. Evatt. Dr. Evatt told him that the primary reason for holding the Conferenceat this particular time derived from anxiety on the part of Australia and NewZealand concerning United States attempts at infiltration in non-AmericanPacific Islands south of the Equator and &quot; anxiety concerning similar tendenciesm Australia and New Zealand.&quot; A second motive, Dr. Evatt said, derived fromthe view held by the Australian and New Zealand Governments that the UnitedKingdom Government tended &apos;&apos; to concede too easily proposals made by the[26807] B
United States of America in relation to the Pacific.&quot; As an instance of this,Dr. Evatt referred to the Cairo Conference and the concessions there made to china on which, in Dr. Evatt&apos;s view, Australia and New Zealand should have&quot;been consulted beforehand.. Dr. Evatt also informed Sir P. Cross that he waslooking to the United Kingdom to help him to hold the international conferencein the Pacific proposed in Clause 34 of the Agreement, and expressed the viewthat, if the United Kingdom would send appropriate Ministers to this conference,the United States Government would also attend.5. I feel bound to regard it as unfortunate that the two governments should have organised and carried out this Conference and published its conclusions without any prior consultation with us, having regard to our ownimmense interests in the Pacific and the bearing of the Conference on so manygeneral questions in which we are vitally concerned. It is, moreover, regrettablethat no clear statement has been made locally to the effect that consultation with us here at the forthcoming Prime Ministers&apos; meeting would be the next step inthe consideration of these questions. Nevertheless, on a broad view. I feel thatthe Conference may well have some useful results. From the aspect of defence,it is clearly to the good that Australia and New Zealand should have statedpublicly that they have a primary interest in the defence of the Pacific. this declaration may be extremely valuable when we come to arrangements for thepost-war period. Moreover, in advocating the principle of regional collaboration in the Pacific between all the Governments concerned, they have in effect adopted the ideas which we had been considering here and which the Colonial Secretaryenunciated in his statement in the House in July last. Finally, so far as theConference implies closer sympathy and co-operation between Australia and NewZealand themselves, that is all to the good. In fact, it seems to me that theconclusions of the Conference should help to provide a useful basis for furtherconsideration of these questions, provided that the two Dominion Governments donot seek to rush prematurely into international discussions.6. &apos; The immediate question before the Cabinet is what reply is to bereturned to the telegram from the two Prime Ministers of the 26th January. Iwould propose to consult the other Departments principally concerned and prepare a reply. This must necessarily be of a somewhat interim nature. I take it that my colleagues will, in particular, wish to discourage the Australian andNew Zealand Governments from taking immediate steps to implement theproposal in paragraph 11 of the telegram for holding an international conferencein the Pacific about the middle of the year. I take it that we shall not be readyto take part in such a conference at the present stage. Not only would it be premature when so many of the territories are still in enemy occupation, but thelocal arrangements to be agreed upon in the Pacific can evidently not be considered in isolation from the other general post-war defence and security arrangements which still have to be negotiated. Many of these wider issues will need to be dealtwith here and at Washington before the details of any subsidiary regionalarrangements in the Pacific can be agreed upon. It seems essential that theAustralian and New Zealand Governments should not issue invitations to any international conference at any rate until after the discussions between the PrimeMinisters here. I should, therefore, if my colleagues agree, propose to indicate to the Prime Ministers of Australia and New Zealand that we should not favourtheir taking any further steps in the matter until we have had the opportunityof personal discussions with them in London. The position is one of somedelicacy. Dr. Evatt is no doubt delighted with the success of the Canberrameeting and with the lead which Australia and New Zealand have given, and hewill be likely to resent anything that he may regard as grandmotherly restraintby the mother country. But I feel that we must make our position clear before he takes any further steps. If the Cabinet approve the broad lines of this reply,I will, in consultation with the other Government Departments concerned, prepare a draft for the approval of my colleagues.Dominions Office,2nd February, 1944.
ANNEX 1.AGREEMENT BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND NEWZEALAND, 21st JANUARY, 1944.(Telegraphic Text.)His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Commonwealth of Australia and HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the Dominion of New Zealand (hereinafter referredto as the two Governments) represented as follows:  The Government of the Commonwealth of Australia by :The Right Honourable John Curtin, Prime Minister of Australia and minister for Defence,The Honourable Francis Michael Forde, Minister for. the Army,The Honourable Joseph Benedict Chifley, Treasurer and Ministerfor Post-war Reconstruction,The Eight Honourable Herbert Vere Bvatt, LL.D., K.C., Attorney-General and Minister for External Affairs,The Honourable John Albert Beasley, Minister for Supply and shipping,The Honourable Norman John Oswald Makin, Minister for the navy and Minister for Munitions,The Honourable  Arthur  Samuel Drakeford,  Minister for Air  and minister for Civil Aviation,The   Honourable   John   Johnstone   Dedman,   Minister   for   WarOrganisation of Industry,The Honourable  Edward John Ward, Minister for Transport and minister for External Territories,The Honourable Thomas George de Largie Dalton, High Commissionerfor Australia in New Zealand, andThe Government of the Dominion of New Zealand by:The Right Honourable Peter Eraser, Prime Minister of New Zealand,Minister for External Affairs and Minister of Island Territories,The Honourable Frederick Jones, Minister of Defence and minister in charge of Civil Aviation,The  Honourable   Patrick  Charles  Webb,  Postmaster-General   and minister of Labour, andCarl August Berendsen, Esq., C.M.G., High Commissioner for NewZealand in Australia :having met in conference at Canberra from the 17th to the 21st January, 1944,and desiring to maintain and strengthen the close and cordial relationsbetween the two Governments do hereby enter into this agreement.Definition of Objectives of Australian-New Zealand Co-operation.1. The two Governments agree that as a preliminary provision shall bemade for fuller exchange of information regarding both the views of each government and the facts in the possession of either bearing on matters ofcommon interest.2. The two Governments give mutual assurances that on matters which appear to be of common concern each Government will so far as possible bemade acquainted with the mind of the other before views are expressedelsewhere by either.3. In furtherance of the above provisions, with respect to exchange of views and information, the two Governments agreed that there shall be themaximum degree of unity in the presentation elsewhere of the the views ofthe two countries.4. The two Governments agree to adopt an expeditious and continuousmeans of consultation by which each party will obtain directly the opinions of the other.5. The two Governments agree to act together in matters of common concern in the South-west and South Pacific areas.6. So far as compatible with the existence of separate military ctim-mands the two Governments agree to co-ordinate their efforts for the purposeof prosecuting the war to a successful conclusion.Armistice and Subsequent Arrangements.&apos;7. The two Governments declare that they have vital interests in allpreparations for any armistice ending the present hostilities or any part thereof, and also in arrangements subsequent to any such armistice, and agree that their interests should be protected by representation at thehighest level on all armistice planning and executive bodies.T26807] b 2
8. The two Governments are in agreement that the final peace settle-ment should be made in respect of all our enemies after hostilities with all of them are concluded.9. Subject to the last two preceding clauses the two Governments will seek agreement with each other on the terms of any armistice to be concluded.10. The two Governments declare that they should actively participate in any armistice commission to be set up.11. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Commonwealth of Australia shallset up in Australia, and His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Dominion ofNew Zealand shall set up in New Zealand, armistice and post-hostilitiesplanning committees and shall arrange for the work of these committees tobe co-ordinated in order to give effect to the views of the respective governments.12. The two Governments will collaborate generally with regard to the location of machinery set up under international organisations, such as theUnited Nations Eelief and Rehabilitation Administration, and in particular,with regard to the location of the Par Eastern Committee of thatAdministration.Security and Defence.13. The two Governments agree that within the framework of a generalsystem of world security a regional zone of defence comprising the South-west and South Pacific areas shall be established and that this zone shouldbe based on Australia and New Zealand, stretching through the arc of islandsnorth and north-east of Australia to Western Samoa and the Cook Islands.14. The two Governments regard it as a matter of cardinal importance that they should both be associated, not only in the membership but alsoin the planning and establishment of the general international organisation,referred to in the Moscow Declaration of October 1943, which organisation is based on the principle of the sovereign equality of all peace-loving Statesand open to membership by all such States, large or small, for the mainten-ance of international peace and security.15. Pending the re-establishment of law and order and the inaugurationof a system of general security, the two Governments hereby declare theirvital interest in the action on behalf of the community of nations, contem-plated in Article V of the Moscow Declaration of October 1943. For thatpurpose it is agreed that it would be proper for Australia and New zealand to assume full responsibility for policing or sharing in policing such areas inthe South-west and South Pacific as may from time to time be agreed upon.16. The two Governments accept as a recognised principle of inter-national practice that the construction and use in time of war by any Powerof naval, military or air installations in any territory under the sovereigntyor control of another Power, does not in itself afford any basis for territorialclaims or rights of sovereignty or control after the conclusion of hostilities.Civil Aviation.17. The two Governments agree that the regulation of all air transport services should be subject to the terms of a convention which will supersedethe Convention relating to the Regulation of Aerial Navigation.18. The two Governments declare that the air services using theinternational air trunk routes .hould be operated by an international air transport authority.19.   The two Governments support the principles that:(a) full control of the international air trunk routes and the ownership of all aircraft and ancillary equipment should be vested in theinternational air transport authority, and(b) the international air trunk routes should themselves be specified inthe international agreement referred to in the next succeedingclause.20. The two Governments agree that the creation of the international air transport authority should be effected by an international agreement.21. Within the framework of the system set up under any suchinternational agreement the two Governments support:(a) the right of each country to conduct all air transport services within its own national jurisdiction, including its own contiguousterritories, subject only to agreed international requirementsregarding safety facilities, landing and transit rights for inter-national services, and exchange of mails,(6) the right of Australia and New Zealand to utilise to the fullest extenttheir productive capacity in respect of aircraft and raw materials for the production of aircraft, and
(c) the right of Australia and New Zealand to use a fair proportion oftheir own personnel, agencies and materials in operating and maintaining international air trunk routes.22. In the event of failure to obtain a satisfactory international agree-ment to establish and govern the use of international air trunk routes,  lietwo Governments will support a system of air trunk routes controlled and operated by Governments of the British Commonwealth of Nations under government ownership.23. The two Governments will act jointly in support of the above-mentioned principles, with respect to civil aviation, and each will informthe other of its existing interests and commitments as a basis of advancingthe policy herein agreed upon.De-pendencies and Territories.24. Following the procedure adopted at the conference which has justconcluded, the two Governments will regularly exchange information andviews in regard to all developments in, or affecting, the islands of the Pacific.25. . The two Governments take note of the intention of the australian government to resume administration at the earliest possible moment ofthose parts of its territories which have not yet been re-occupied.26. The two Governments declare that the interim administration andultimate disposal of enemy territories in the Pacific is of vital importanceto Australia and New Zealand and that any such disposal should be effectedonly with their agreement and as part of a general Pacific settlement.27. The two Governments declare that no change in the sovereignty orsystem of control of any of the islands of the Pacific should be effected,except as a result of an agreement to which they are parties or in the termsof which they have both concurred.Welfare and Advancement of Native Peoples of the Pacific.28. The two Governments declare that, in applying the principles of the atlantic Charter to the Pacific, the doctrine of trusteeship, already applicablein the case of the mandated territories of which the two Governments aremandatory Powers, is applicable in broad principle to all colonial territories in the Pacific and elsewhere, and that the main purpose of the trust is the welfare of the native peoples , and their social, economic and political development.29. The two Governments agree that the future of the various territories of the Pacific and the welfare of their inhabitants cannot be successfullypromoted without a greater measure of collaboration between the numerousauthorities concerned in their control and that such collaboration isparticularly desirable in regard to health services and communications,matters of native education, anthropological investigation, assistance innative production and material development generally.30. The two Governments agree to promote the establishment at theearliest possible date of a regional organisation with advisory powers whichcould be called the South Seas regional Commission and on which, inaddition to representatives of Australia and New Zealand, there might beaccredited representatives of the Governments of the United Kingdom andthe United States of America and of the French Committee of national liberation.31. The two Governments agree that it shall be the function of suchSouth Seas regional Commission as may be established to secure a common policy on social, economic and political development, directed towards the advancement and well-being of the native peoples themselves and that inparticular the commission shall:(a) recommend   arrangements   for   the   participation   of   natives   in administration in increasing measure, with a view to promoting the ultimate attainment of self-government in the form most suited.to the circumstances of the native peoples concerned,(b) recommend   arrangements   for   material   development,   includingproduction, finance, communications and marketing,(c) recommend arrangements for co-ordination of health and medical services and education,(d) recommend arrangements for maintenance and improved standards of native welfare in regard to labour conditions and participation ofnatives in administration and social services,(e) recommend   arrangements   for  collaboration   in   economic,   social,medical and anthropological research, and(/) make and publish periodical reviews of progress towards the develop-ment of self-governing institutions in the islands of the Pacific andin the improvement of standards of living, conditions of work,education, health and general welfare.[26807] b 3
Migration!32. In the peace settlement or other negotiations, the two governments will accord one another full support in maintaining the accepted principlethat every government- has the right ,to control immigration and emigrationin regard to all territories within its jurisdiction.33. The. two Governments will collaborate, exchange full information and render full assistance to one another in all matters concerning migrationto their respective territories.International Conference Relating to the South-ivest and South Pacific.34. The two Governments agree that as soon as practicable there shouldbe a frank exchange of views on the problems of security, post-war develop-ment and native welfare between properly accredited representatives of theGovernments with existing territorial interests in the South-west pacific area or in the South Pacific area or in both, namely, in addition to the twoGovernments, His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, theGovernment of the United States of America, the Government of the Nether-lands, the French Committee of National Liberation and the Governmentof Portugal, and His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Commonwealth ofAustralia should take the necessary steps to call a conference of the Govern-ments concerned.Permanent Machinery for Collaboration and Co-operation betweenAustralia and New Zealand. .i35.   The two Governments agree that:(a) their co-operation for defence should be developed by (i) continuous  consultation in  all defence matters  of mutualinterest,(ii) the organisation, equipment, training and exercising of the armed forces under a common doctrine,, (iii) joint planning,(iv) interchange of staff, and(v) the co-ordination of policy for the production of munitions,aircraft and supply items and for shipping to ensure thegreatest possible degree of mutual aid, consistent with themaintenance of the policy of self-sufficiency in localproduction,- (b) collaboration in external policy on all matters affecting the peace,welfare and good government of the Pacific should be securedthrough the exchange of information and frequent Ministerialconsultation,(c) the development of commerce between Australia and New zealand and their industrial development should be pursued by consultation and in agreed cases bv joint &quot;olanninp,(d) there  should  be   co-operation   in   achieving  full   employment  inAustralia and New Zealand and the highest standards of social security, both within their borders and throughout the islands ofthe Pacific and other territories for which they may jointly orseverally be wholly or partly responsible, and(e) there should be co-operation in encouraging missionary work and allother activities directed towards the improvement of the welfare ofthe native peoples in the islands and territories of the Pacific.36. The two Governments declare their desire to have the adherence tothe objectives set out in the last preceding clause of any other government having or controlling territories in the Pacific.37. The two Governments agree that the methods to be used for carryingout the provisions of Clause 35 of this agreement, and of other provisions ofthis agreement, shall be consultation, exchange of information and, whereapplicable, joint planning. They further agree that such methods shall include :(a) conferences of Ministers of State to be held alternately in Canberraand Wellington, it being the aim of the two Governments that these conferences be held at least twice a year,(b) conferences of departmental officers and technical experts,(c) meetings of standing inter-Governmental committees on such subjects as are agreed to by the two Governments,(d) the fullest use of the status and functions of the High commissioner of the Commonwealth of Australia in New Zealand and of the HighCommissioner of the Dominion of New Zealand in Australia,(e) regular exchange of information,(/) exchange of officers, and(g) the development of institutions in either country serving the commonpurposes of both.
Permanent Secretariat.38. In order to ensure continuous collaboration on the lines set out inthis agreement and to facilitate the carrying out of the duties and functionsinvolved, the two Governments agree that a permanent secretariat shallbe established in Australia and in New Zealand.39. The secretariat shall be known as the Australian-New ZealandAffairs Secretariat and shall consist of a secretariat of the like name to beset up in Australia and a secretariat of the like name to be set up in NewZealand, each under the control of the Minister of External Affairs in thecountry concerned.40.   The functions of the Secretariat shall be :(a) to take the initiative in ensuring that effect is given to the provisionsof this agreement,(b) to make arrangements as the occasion arises for the holding of con-ferences or meetings,(c) to carry out the directions of those conferences in regard to further consultation, exchange of information or the examination ofparticular questions,(d) to co-ordinate all forms of collaboration between the two Govern -men is,(e) to raise for joint discussion and action such other matters as may seem from day to day to require attention by the two Governments,and(/) generally to provide for more frequent and regular exchanges ofinformation and views, these exchanges between the two Govern-ments to take place normally through the respective high commissioners.41. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Commonwealth of Australia andHis Majesty&apos;s Government in the Dominion of New Zealand each shallnominate an officer or officers from the staff of their respective high commissioners to act in closest collaboration with the Secretariat, in whichthey shall be accorded full access to all relevant sources of information.42. In each country the Minister of State for External Affairs and the resident High Commissioner shall have joint responsibility for the effectivefunctioning of the Secretariat.Ratification and Title of Agreement.43. This agreement is subject to ratification by the respective Govern-ments and shall come into force as soon as both Governments have ratified the agreement and have notified each other accordingly. It is intended thatsuch notification will take place as soon as possible after the signing of thisagreement.44. This agreement shall be known as the Australian-New ZealandAgreement, 1944.Dated this twenty-first day of January, One Thousand Nine Hundred and forty-four-Signed on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Dominion ofNew Zealand.Signed on behalf of His MajestyV Government in the Commonwealthof Australia.
ANNEX 2.Telegram No. 22 of 25th January, 1944, from the Australian Government to theSecretary, of Slate for Dominion Affairs.Repeated to New Zealand Government, No. 14.Following is joint telegram to United Kingdom Government from PrimeMinisters of New Zealand and Australia. Repeated to New Zealand Governmentfor information :  (Secret.) The Australian and New Zealand Governments desire to invitethe attention of United Kingdom Government to particular aspects of theAustralian-New Zealand Agreement signed at Canberra on 21st January, copiesof which were given to United Kingdom High Commissioner at Canberra and australian accredited representative at London for transmission to UnitedKingdom Government. At outset the two Governments wish to emphasise to united Kingdom Government that the holding of this conference and the discus-sions and decisions resulting therefrom wrere fully in accord with principles of free consultation between individual members of the British Commonwealth ofNations and that the strength and unity of the British Commonwealth is in the forefront of the policy of both Australia and New Zealand.1. We would invite particular attention to objectives of Australian-NewZealand co-operation as defined in Clauses 1-6 of the Agreement.2. Armistice and subsequent arrangements. The Australian and NewZealand Governments greatly appreciate the detailed information which has been supplied by United Kingdom Government with regard to armistice preparationsand subsequent arrangements in connection with the war in Europe.We are in agreement that our interests should be protected by representation at highest level on all armistice planning and executive bodies and that we shouldactively-participate in any armistice commission to be set up. So far as europe is concerned, and in explanation of the desire to be associated with armisticearrangements in that theatre, both Governments base their attitude on the factthat twice within our generation we have been involved in war as a result ofhostilities arising in Europe. While we look forward to exchanging with UnitedKingdom Government the fullest information as to armistice and subsequentarrangements in connection with the war in the Pacific, we feel that no time shouldbe lost in undertaking detailed preparations in this sphere and that Australiaand New Zealand should be directly associated with this work at the earliestpossible date.Meanwhile our two Governments have agreed that post hostilities planningcommittees (similar to those already established in United Kingdom and Canada)should be set up in Australia and New Zealand, and will arrange for the workof these committees to be co-ordinated.Our two Governments are in agreement that no final peace settlement shouldbe made in respect of any of our enemies until after hostilities with all of the mare concluded.3. United Nations Relief Administration. Our two Governments haveagreed that it is most desirable that the Far Eastern Committee of the united nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration should be located in Australia.4. Security and Defence. The two Governments are in agreement that within the framework of a general system of world security a regional zone ofdefence comprising the South-West and South Pacific areas should be established and that this should be based on Australia and New Zealand, stretching throughthe arc of islands north and north-west of Australia to Western Samoa and theCook Islands.We feel that it would be a great mistake if it were now agreed to confine the planning and establishment of the general international organisation referred toin the Moscow Declaration of October 1943 to the four signatory Powers we regard it as a matter of cardinal importance that Australia and New Zealandshould both be associated in the initial stages with the elaboration of any general international system.Our two Governments have declared in the agreement that they have a vitalinterest in the action on behalf of the community of nations contemplated inArticle V of the Moscow Declaration and are therefore ready to assume responsibility for policing or sharing in policing such areas in the South- west and South Pacific as may from time to time be agreed upon.
975Our vital interest in this matter is obvious. The future security of both ourcountries is dependent, subject to a general system of world security, on thearrangements to be made for the control and &quot;defence of the South-West andSouth Pacific areas and these arrangements will inevitably be affected by the interim arrangements immediately following the reconquest of the NetherlandsIndies and contiguous territories. Australia and New Zealand feel that they mustbe closely associated with all decisions and measures taken in this importantformative stage and desire subject always to consultation and agreement with theother Governments concerned : (a) that Australia have full responsibility for thepolicing of Portuguese Timor, Australian New Guinea and the Solomon IslandsProtectorate, and (b) that Australia have a share in the responsibility for thepolicing of the Netherlands Indies particularly Java, Dutch New Guinea andalso the New Hebrides. As regards Pacific Islands in general south of theEquator we believe that responsibility for policing should primarily be with theUnited Kingdom, Australia and New Zealand, though it is realised that regardmust be paid to the position of the United. States which already has a naval base in Tutuila. We assume, however, that the United States will wish to undertake a substantial share of responsibility for policing the islands north of the Equator.We regard it as essential that such arrangements should be made as part of ageneral scheme and not piecemeal. We have closely examined the means ofproviding a permanent instrument of security in the South-West and SouthPacific areas and believe that a zone of defence could be established by agreement among the Governments concerned, i.e.. United Kingdom, Australia and NewZealand, United States, Netherlands, France and Portugal (see Section II below).5. Disposal of war-time installations. In regard to the post-war disposalof installations the two Governments accept as a recognised principle of inter-national practice that the construction and use in time of war by any Power ofnaval, military or air installations in any territory under the sovereignty or controlof another Power does not in itself afford any basis whatsoever for territorialclaims or rights of sovereignty or control after the conclusion of hostilities. Thetwo Governments were firmly of the opinion that in view of subsequent difficultieswhich may well arise on this question a declaration of principle at an early stagewas necessary. Obvious illustrations of the international practice occur in thecases of Iceland and the Azores.6. Civil Aviation. As regards the clauses in the agreement on civil aviationit will be noted that in the event of failure to obtain a satisfactory international agreement to establish and govern the use of international air trunk routes thetwo Governments will support a system of air trunk routes controlled and operated by Governments of the British Commonwealth of Nations under Governmentownership. We would emphasise our firm adherence to principle of internationalGovernment ownership control and specification of trunk routes to extent defined in the agreement and our firm belief that the alternative of British Commonwealthtrunk routes should be put forward only in case every effort to achieve inter-nationalisation fails.7. Dependencies. There was a comprehensive interchange of information and views on war-time developments in the Pacific Islands particularly regardingthe following : (a) Development of bases, airfields, &amp;c.;(b) War-time administration;(c) American activities;(d) War-time collaboration between Australia, New Zealand, and other powers and the local administration.(e) Effects of war on native labour, social life, standards of living, &amp;c.Under (b) was included the action taken by Australia in regard to pre-reparations for resumption of administration in Nauru, the war-time administra-tion of New Guinea and Papua and the function of the Combined Civil AffairsCommittee. On the last matter the Australian Government informed the NewZealand Government that inquiries had been made in London and that thestatus and functions of this Committee were being reconsidered. The two Govern-ments agreed that if the scope of the Civil Affairs Committee were extendedto the South and South-West Pacific area they would desire direct representationupon it. They would also be glad to have any information as to arrangements the United Kingdom Government contemplates for the interim administrationof its Pacific Island territories.  The Australian Government is prepared to make
available for this purpose a number of (experienced officers and is prepared to institute immediately an emergency course of training for suitable qualified men.8. War-time administration and post-war disposal of enemy territories.The administration and disposal of enemy territories, particularly the JapaneseMandated Islands, are also of the greatest importance to Australia and NewZealand. The two Governments have set out in the agreement that &quot; the interimadministration and ultimate disposal of enemy territories in the Pacific are of vital importance to Australia and New Zealand and that any such disposal shouldbe effected only with their agreement and as part of a general Pacific settle-ment.&quot;9. In regard to the possibility that changes of sovereignty might be suggested in the South-West and South Pacific, the two Governments declared&quot; that no change in the sovereignty or system of control of any of the islands of the Pacific should be effected except as a result of an agreement to which theyare parties or in the terms of which they have both concurred.&quot;10. Welfare of native peoples. The agreement declared that in applying the principle of the Atlantic Charter the doctrine of trusteeship is applicable in broad principle to all Colonial territories in the Pacific and elsewhere, and thatthe main purpose of the trust is the welfare and advancement of the nativepeoples.We have agreed to .take the initiative in promoting the early establishmentof an Advisory Regional Organisation. This proposal is in accord with sugges-tion made by the Secretary of State for Colonies in his statement in the House ofCommons on the 13th July, 1943, and the similar suggestion contemplated atthe time when Lord Halifax discussed with Mr. Cordell Hull the possibility of ajoint Anglo-American Declaration on post-war Colonial Policy. It is suggestedthat this Advisory Body, which might be called the &quot; South Seas RegionalCommission,&quot; should comprise, in addition to representatives of Australia andNew, Zealand, representatives of the Governments of the United Kingdom andthe United States, and of the French Committee of National Liberation.Our view is that it should be the function of such a South Seas RegionalCommission to secure a common policy on social economic and political develop-ment directed towards the advancement and well-being of the native peoplesthemselves. The establishment of the Commission along the lines set out in clause 31 of the agreement is receiving further consideration here, and welook forward.to exchanging views in detail with the United Kingdom Govern -ment.11.   Conference relating to South-West and South Pacific.The two Governments have agreed that as soon as practicable there shouldbe a frank exchange of views on the problems of security (see last paragraph ofSection 4 above), post-war development and native welfare between properlyaccredited representatives of the two Governments with existing territorialinterests in the South-West Pacific area or in the South Pacific area or in both,namely, in addition to the two Governments, His Majesty&apos;s Government in theUnited Kingdom, the Government of the United States, the Government of theNetherlands, the French Committee of National Liberation and the Governmentof Portugal and His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Commonwealth of Australiashould take the necessary steps to call a conference of the Governmentsconcerned.In this connection the Australian and New Zealand Governments are agreedthat it will not be practicable to hold a conference of this kind until some time after the forthcoming conference of British Commonwealth Prime Ministers inLondon. It is proposed to hold the conference at Canberra about the middle ofthe year and invitations will be issued later.12. Permanent machinery for collaboration and co-operation betweenAustralia and New Zealand. We invite particular attention to articles of our agreement relating to machinery for co-operation in defence (Clause 35 (a)) andClause 36).13. As an immediate step towards further action in implementing thedecisions of the conference both Governments would appreciate the views of theUnited Kingdom Government on matters referred to in this telegram.







</content>
</cab>
