<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/43/0 images: 76-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE   PROPERTY OF, HIS  BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  November 1950SECRET             Sufi;    SsSSISn SStlSSoo Copy No. 32CP. .(50) 263.     .,                                                          7 ; 77&apos;, &apos;&quot; .7fA November,, 19SQ. (I&amp;ms srfT   noiiqm-rou oJ gnitalsi w*J k-;--: 0j tfeixsCABINETPREVENTION OF CORRUPTIONMemorandum by the Attorney-general it may be remembered that on 6th April, 1949, I circulated a memorandum(CP. (49) 78) suggesting the desirability of a small amendment in the Preventionof Corruption Act, 1916. That Act facilitated the proof of corruption, always avery difficult matter, in cases where money had been paid to a person in the employ-ment of a Government Department or a public body by a person holding or seeking a contract with that Department or body. In such a case the statute provided thaton proof of the payment of the money, the onus of proving that it had not been paid corruptly shifted from the prosecution to the person who had paid the money or received it, as the case might be. I had the support of the Lord Chancellor, theLord Chief Justice, the Home Secretary and the Director of Public Prosecutionsin suggesting that the scope of the Act should be extended to cases where a licenceor permit was being sought or had been obtained from the Department or bodyconcerned.2. It was, however, considered that the time was inopportune for such an amendment of the law since, following the then recent enquiries before the so-calledLynskey Tribunal, it might be taken to involve some reflection upon GovernmentDepartments.3. Another inadequacy in the provisions of the 1916 Act has now come to notice in connection with police investigations which have been taking place intoallegations of corruption in the British Broadcasting Corporation. These have brought to light several cases where money has in fact been paid by artistes holdingor seeking contracts with the B.B.C. to officials of that body in circumstances which,to say the least, are suspicious. There is, however, no positive proof of corruptionand unless the 1916 Act can be relied upon no prosecutions can be instituted. Butthe 1916 Act does not apply since the B.B.C. is not a public body within the mean-ing of that Act, the term being defined as referring to a public authority which, ina strict sense, the B.B.C. is not. Quite obviously bodies like the B.B.C. should be within the scope of the 1916 Act and it is only by a technical incident of draftingthat they are not.4. I therefore suggest that the presumption under the 1916 Act should beextended to cover all statutory or charter corporations whether they are &quot; public authorities &quot; in a strict sense or not. There is indeed something to be said for extending it to all public companies and for my own part I would like to see suchan extension, since I believe it would have a very salutary effect on corrupt prac-tices. The special provisions of the 1916 Act were, however, applied toGovernment Departments and public authorities because they are in a sensemonopolists. As they have the exclusive right or duty to enter into contracts orgrant licences for particular purposes there is the great danger that those seekingsuch contracts or licences will resort to bribery because there is no rival organisation to which they can apply. The 1916 Act was intended to be, and in fact has been, a protection for Government Departments and public authorities against the dangerof attempts to bribe their employees. The same protection is obviously desirable39617
in the case of statutory or charter corporations which are also monopolists butthe case is not so strong for extending it to all public companies.5. If it is agreed that this amendment in the law should be made I should liketo renew my suggestion that the opportunity should be taken of introducing alsothe small amendment suggested in my previous paper and referred to in paragraphs1 and 2. The political reasons which made that amendment inopportune at thetime no longer exist.6. I think I must impress on my colleagues the great difficulty which at presentexists in enforcing the law relating to corruption. The small amendments now sug-gested would provide some alleviation.H. W. S.Royal Courts of Justice, W.C. 2,1th November, 1950.



</content>
</cab>
