<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/43/0 images: 312-319</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MA JEST YrS GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP.(50) 28728TH NOVEMBER, 1950CABINETCOAL EXPORTSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer on 17th November, the Cabinet agreed (C M. (50) 75thConclusions, Minute 3, Conclusion(3) of the Confidential Annex) that theMinister of Fuel and Power should arrange for the examination by officials of the distribution of a further cut of coal exports, should thissubsequently become unavoidable, on two alternative assumptions -a cut of . 5 million tons and a cut of 1 million tons.2. It was subsequently arranged that this examination shouldbe carried out by the Overseas Negotiations Committee, and I now circulate for the consideration of my colleagues a report which theCommittee have prepared.3. I agree with the conclusions of the Committee inparagraph 6 of the report.H. G.COPY NO.  J ZTreasury Chambers, S. W. 1. ,28TH NOVEMBER, 1950.

COAL EXPORTSReport by the Overseas Negotiations Committee1.     introduction the Cabinet agreed on 17th November (CM. (50) 75thConclusions, Minute 3, Conclusion (3) of the Confidential Annex) that&quot;no further cuts should be made for the present in exports of coal, butthat the Minister of Fuel and Power should arrange for the examination by officials of the distribution of a further cut, should this subsequentlybecome unavoidable, on two alternative assumptions - a cut of . 5 million tons and a &quot;cut of 1 million tons&quot;.    The Cabinet&apos;s intention was that thesecuts, if necessary, should be made within the remainder of the Winter CoalPeriod, i. e. up to 30th April, 1951.2.    proposal the Overseas Negotiations Committee, who have been asked tocarry out this examination, recommend that any required savings should besecured by(a) imposing in the case of Certain countries absolute cuts over the wholeof 1951 on the coal exports which the United Kingdom would otherwise send them.(b) to ensure that the savings are made in that period slowing updeliveries to all, countries in the period up to 30th April,1951 (followed by deliveries at a somewhat higher rate).The Committee&apos;s recommendations as to these absolute cuts are shown in thefollowing table, compared with (i) the coal exports which the committee consider these countries should receive on the basis of a total cargo exportavailability of 7.4 million tons in the calendar year 1951, (ii) estimateddeliveries for 1950.&apos;000 tons1CountryEstimatedDeliveriesin 1950Presentprovisionalallocationfor 1951Allocationif . 5 m. tonscut is imposed(cut shown In brackets)_Allocationif 1 m. tonscut is imposed(cut shown In brackets)_Germany	455	250	0	(	250)	0Eire	1,540	1,000	.1,000	(	- )	850Denmark	1,770	1,000	950	(	50)	850Sweden	1,250	750	700	(	50)	700Norway	385	250	250	(	- )	200France	1,415	650 800	650	(	. - )	600Italy	1,543		750	(	50)	600British Military				(	50)	Areas	40	50	0			other countries						(on which no						absolute cuts						would be	k, 002	2,650	2, 650			2,650imposed)						(250)(150)(150)( 50)( 50)( 50)(200)( 50)TOTALS 12,400  &apos; 7,400 6,950    (450),     6,450    (950)

The balance of 50,000 tons will be made up by a shortfall of 50,000 tons in supplies to Canada, which is expected for transport reasons i. e. the seasonal nature of transport in the St. Lawrence,   The direct cargoexports would thus amount to 6. 9 million tons with a . 5 million ton cut andto 6, 4 million tons with a 1 million ton cut,3,    CommentIn making these recommendations, the Committee have takeninto account the following points.(a) It is necessary to have regard to such factors as the essential supplies which we obtain from other countries, our trade agreement obligations, and the grades of coal we supply.(b) The amount of coal we supply to each of the non-organisation for European Economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.) countries is, in general, comparatively small, and would make no appreciable contribution to the present problem.   the exceptions are Argentina, Spain and Canada and theCommittee&apos;s reasons for suggesting no absolute cuts inthese cases are as follows:-Argentina.   The provisional allocation of 750,000 tons for1951 is only half the amount which Argentina would expect toget under the Trade Agreement and the Committee do notthink it advisable at the present juncture to add to thedifficulties which would be caused by imposing a still greater cut,Spain. Supplies of iron ore and pyrites may be endangeredeven by the present allocation of only 400,000 tons for 1951.Canada.    The considerations which preclude a cut are that canada is both a dollar and a Commonwealth country andthat we know that she attaches special importance to themaintenance of coal supplies from the United Kingdom.As explained above, the Committee are in any casecounting on a shortfall in deliveries for transport reasons.The result is that the cuts fall principally on O.E.E, C. countries.4,     General effectsThe general effects of a cut of either . 5 million tons or1 million tons cannot be precisely assessed.   Even if these additionalcuts can be avoided, the heavily reduced availability of coal for exportsalready envisaged must cause a serious deterioration in our bilateralrelations with other countries.   It is not possible to say more than thatthe additional cuts would worsen the position, and with greater severityin the case of the 1 million tons cut.5,     Breaches of commitmentsEven if these additional cuts were not made, the reducedavailability of coal for exports will involve certain breaches, of commitments.The additional cuts, however, would involve further breaches in regard to-the Irish Republic and Germany,

(i) Irish Republic;    Under the Trade Agreement of 1948, which runsuntil 1952, we are committed to supply not less than 1. 57    .million tons of coal, coke and manufactured fuel, and itis considered that within this total the obligation is tosupply 1.4 million tons of coal.   The provisionalallocation of 1 million tons of coal for 1951 (seeparagraph 2) would itself therefore be a breach of theagreement.   The proposed reduction of supplies by afurther 150,000 tons, if a 1 million ton cut is imposed,would make the breach more serious.(ii)   Germany.     The present allocation of 250,000 tons (see paragraphalready    involves a breach of contract as there is a carry-over into 1951 of 320,000 tons, which we contracted tosupply in 1950.   The Committeers proposal, however,involves a complete cessation of exports to Germany in1951, and therefore a complete breach of contract.   It isnot thought that the Germany economy would be seriously affected, but Germany would be the only country to whichwe were refusing any coal whatsoever, and the national coal Board emphasise that this would increase their needfor full protection from His Majesty&apos;s Government either bya direction to stop exports to Germany or by a refusal of export licences.6.     ConclusionsIf an additional reduction of exports of coal by either . 5 million tons or 1 million tons should be unavoidable in the period up to30th April, 1951, the Committee&apos;s conclusions are therefore that -(i)  the absolute cuts recommended in columns 4 and 5 of the table in paragraph 2 should be imposed for the whole of 1951 onthe countries named in the table;(ii) the deliveries to all   countries in the period to 30th April, 1951,should be slowed up (followed by deliveries at a somewhat higher rate) so that the required saving is effected in thatperiod;(iii)  protection of the National Coal Board against any action for damages for complete breach of contract in the case ofGermany will be required in the form of either a directionby His Majesty1 s Government to stop exports to germany or a refusal of export licences.24th November, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
