<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/43/0 images: 520-525</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF-HIS BRITANNICJMAJESTY&apos;5 GOVERNMENT)S E C R E T*2CP.(50) 308 COPY NO^1,1 TH DECEMBER, 1950CABINETWASHINGTON TALKg,Note by the Secretary of the CabinetOn the instruction of the Prime Minister I attachfor consideration by the Cabinet a draft of the statement the will make in the House of Commons on Tuesday, 12thDecember, T 950, on his conference with President Truman.(Signed)   NORMAN brook cabinet Office, S.W.1,11TH DECEMBER, 1950,

WASHINGTON TALKSDRAFT OF A STATEMENT TO BE MADE BY THEPRIME MINISTER IN THE HOUSE OF commons on TUESDAY, 12TH DECEMBER, 1950The House will have seen the communique issued after my talks with President Truman in Washington.     I do not think that I need add very-much to this description of what passed between us.     I should like to take this opportunity of expressing my gratitude to President Truman foragreeing so readily to see me at very short notice, for devoting so much time to our conversations and for the very cordial reception which he andall his collegues gave me.2. The atmosphere of our meetings was both frank and friendly.We covered a wide range of topics political, military and economic, and Ibelieve we made progress on all of them.     It was not our purpose, and indeed it would not have been appropriate for us, to try to enter intospecific agreements,     Our object was to reach the greatest possible degreeof identity of view in our approach and this   we  achieved in very large measure.     On Korea and the Far East we were agreed on the immediatecourse which our representatives at the United Nations should follow;   onthe necessity to prevent the extension of the conflict and on our long rangeobjectives.     The House will have njticed that there is one point of difference recorded in the communique  - the difference between theattitude of our two governments to recognition of China and Chineserepresentation in the United Nations.     We did not expect that this differ -ence could be resolved in talks lasting only a few days;   we did not attemptto avoid this issue in our talks nor to gloss it over in the communique.But this point of difference only serves to emphasise the underlyingunity of our objectives in world affairs as a whole.3. The United States Government share nur view that despite the gravity of the issues facing us.all in the Far EasVthe defence of Europeremains the first task of all the members of the Atlantic community.

Here the way is now open for the vary early appointment of a supreme commander of the European integrated force and I am convinced that inpresent circumstances no other single step could do more to accelerateprogress in building up defensive strength in the west.4. But the President and I recognised that co-ordinated planning in the military field would fail in its purpose if it were not matchedequally by co-operation in economic affairs.     We discussed inparticular the difficulties which have arisen in the supply of rawmaterials and laid the basis for common action to ensure that oureconomies can face successfully the new tasks withwhich they are confronted.5. As far as the use of the atomic weapon is concerned I cantell the House that I was completely reassured by my talk on thismatter with the President.6. I would add that I believe my talks with the President will prove to be of service in all these fields not only to our two countriesbut also to the countries with whom we are associated in the Common-wealth and in the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.7. In all these matters our overriding purpose has been toprevent war and we stand ready at any time to seek a real settlementof our differences with others, if they are also ready to enter intogenuine discussions.


</content>
</cab>
