<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/43/0 images: 612-617</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.C,P,(50) 319 COPY No3214TH DECEMBER, 1950CABINETSOVIET PROPOSAL FOR A MEETING OF THE COUNCILOF FOREIGN ministers note by the Secretary of the cabinet at the meeting of the Cabinet to-day (CM. (50) 86th Conclu-sions,&apos; Minute 3), the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed the Cabinet that the United States and French governments had proposed various amendments to the draft reply to theSoviet note of 3rd November, circulated to the Cabinet as annex A of C. P. (50) 312.   The Foreign Secretary handed round in Cabinet a copy of a revised draft reply to theSoviet note in which the proposed amendments had been incorporated and underlined.A copy of this revised draft is attached.(Signed)   NORMAN brook cabinet Office, S. W..1. ,14TH DECEMBER, 1950.(THIS. DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MA JEST Y&apos;S&apos;     GOVERNMENT)

His Majesty&apos;s Embassy have the honour to acknowledge the receiptof the Note of 3rd November, 1950, of the Soviet Ministry of Foreign Affairs.This Note enclosed the text of a declaration published in Prague on22nd October, 1950, and proposed a meeting of the Council of foreign ministers of the United States of America, United Kingdom, France and the.U.S.S.R, to consider the question of the execution of the provisions ofthe Potsdam Agreement regarding the demilitarisation of Germany,2, His Majesty&apos;s Government have consistently abided by theprinciple set out in the Charter of the United Nations that internationalproblems should be settled by peaceful negotiation.   His Majesty&apos;sGovernment take this occasion to re-affirm their adherence to this principle.This is in full accordance with the recent General Assembly resolutionsupported by His Majesty&apos;s Government which calls attention to thedesirability of consultations which would help to allay existing internationaltensions.        Far from having any aggressive intentions towards the soviet union, His Majesty1 s Government are inspired by a genuine desire to put anend to the existing international tension and will spare no effort to achieveso highly desirable an end.   They are prepared, on the basis and in themanner set out below, to explore with the Soviet, United States and French.Governments the possibility of finding a mutually acceptable basis for ameeting of Foreign Ministers of the four countries.3. His Majesty&apos;s Government have studied with care the Note ofthe Soviet Government of 3rd November, 1950.   They have been obliged to note with regret that the basis proposed in this Note is not such as to holdout the prospect of a real settlement.   The Soviet proposal to examinethe question of the demilitarisation of Germany will not suffice to remove the causes of the present tension.   The only German military force which exists at present is that which has been for many months established inthe Soviet Zone, and which is trained on military lines with artillery and tanks.   If the participation of German units in the defence of western germany is being discussed, it is solely because Soviet policy and actionshave compelled the other nations to examine all means of improving their security.   Contrary to the entirely false allegations contained in the Praguecommunique, His Majesty1 s Government, in common with the Governments ofFrance and the United States of America, are determined never, at any time or in any circumstances, to allow Western Germany to be used as a base for aggression.   His Majesty&apos;s Government have no feeling of confidence thatthe same is true of that part of Germany under Soviet occupation, in viewof the rearmament taking place in Eastern Germany referred to above.4. Nor is it possible to envisage a just settlement of German problems on the basis of the Prague communique.   This communique contains no new or constructive features and the solutions proposed therein have been rejected by the majority of the German people.   It does little more thanreiterate in substance earlier proposals which proved, after exhaustiveexamination, to offer no basis for a constructive solution of the german problem.   With the object of ending the present division of Germany, HisMajesty&apos;s Government, in conjunction with the French and american governments, have for their part more than once made proposals for restoring German unity by means of free elections held under international supervision.   These proposals were sent by letter by the three high commissioners to the Head of the Soviet Control Commission on 25th Mayand 9th October, 1950.   No. reply has been received.REVISED DRAFT OF THE REPLY TO THE SOVIET NOTE OF3RD NOVEMBER, 1950

5. The serious tension which exists today springs neither fromthe question of the demilitarisation of Germany nor from the Germanquestion as a whole.      It arises primarily from the general attitude adopted by the Government of the U.S.S.R, since the end of the war andfrom the consequent international developments of recent months.   TheGovernments of the four Powers would be failing in their responsi-bilities if they were to confine their discussion to the narrow basisproposed by the Soviet Government.   Questions related to Germany and austria would obviously be subjects for discussion.     But His Majesty&apos;sGovernment believe that any discussions  should also include theprincipal problems whose solution would make possible a real and lasting improvement in the relations between the Soviet Union and theUnited States of America, Great Britain and France and the elimination of the causes of present international tension throughout the world.6. His Majesty1 s Government are prepared to designate anofficial who, together with representatives of the Soviet, American andFrench Governments, could examine the problems referred to in thepreceding paragraph.   If this examination reveals a mutually acceptablebasis for a meeting of the Foreign Ministers of the four countries, theserepresentatives would then recommend to their Governments a suitableagenda.   It would appear that the presence of therepresentatives of the above-named Governments at the seat of theUnited Nations in New York presents the most convenient opportunity to conduct such preliminary discussions.7. His Majesty&apos;s Government would be glad to learn the viewsof the Soviet Government concerning the proposals set out in the presentnote.


</content>
</cab>
