<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 135-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
11I.F.G.79/S.COPY Ho.2.-General Headquarters, Inter-Alliod Independent Air Force.The Secretary, Air Ministry, LONDON.In continuation of my I.F.G.79/S of the ls.t *f October, 1013, I submit the following report on tho operations of tho Independent Force during October, 1918.Weather&apos;. &apos; - - Tho weather conditions throughout tho month have&apos; been extremely unfavourable.    Pro &quot;longed periods of mist, fog, and low cloud, by day. and by night, have frequently precluded even.short; distance -ra:ds   and on very few occasions has it been possible, to undertake long distance -operations.    ,On 10 days and 22 nights no operations have been carried out owing to. adverse weather conditions.* , -Increases, .&apos;- No new Squadrons have arrived during the month,of The Headquarters of the .85th -Wing arrived on October the5 renflth*   5th:and is -stationed -at &quot;ROVILLE.     On October 19th the-Headquarters of the - 88th&apos;Wing/Arrived, and has commenced operations from BETTONCOTJRT with NoS. 110 and 45 SquadronsThe, replacement of I),11.9*3 with D.H.9a. machines in No.99 Squadron lias progressed slowly. Thoy now have &amp;ix D.H.Da&apos;s, but as,yet have not operated with this type.-&apos;t;Distant&apos; &quot;:;  &quot;During, the month, the following long distanceRaids.        raids.-h,avei been carried out;-.-.;  - . 3y day     - TREVES&quot;. aAISSRSLAUTERN- and PIRMASENS,Factories in the neighbourhood of FRANKFURT, - :        and BONN.   ,   .By night * CODLHNZ, WtESBADEN, KAISERSLAUTEHN,, MANNHEIM,...   ; - ... kc and WORMS,. ;;   -; ,/,-;    &apos;     . \       .&apos; &apos; - - -        .  ,v ...   &quot;Brief. details, of some&apos;&apos;of&apos;the &apos; above-mentionedraids are appended.:- ..   ---V 4(a)., -  TREVgG. , .        * \.   &quot;    &apos;    .On October 1st, two&apos; formations of No.vllO Squadron set out In an attempt t&apos;o roach COLOGNE.     Owing to clouds, the first&quot;formation returned with their bombs. The second formation managed to got as far as TREVES, beyond which the clouds became more dense.     They dropped their bombs through a hole&quot;in:the clouds over TREVES, tho. results being unobserved.,.&apos;/ &apos; ,&quot; *(b) KAISBRSLAUTBRN .and^PIRMASENSVOn the*15th of&apos; October, two &quot;formations of No. 110 Squadron left, again for COLOGNE.     The weather was fine, but very hazy, and tho visibility was very poor. Heavy fighting commenced before the formations reached TREVES, and owing to this and to&apos;the bad visibility, the leader decided to drop bombs at KAISERSLAUTERN.
o**    Cj    -The results were unobserved owing to the closeness of the fighting.   &apos; 1&apos;wo of the machines were no hoavily attacked over KAISERSLAUTERN that they wero* unable to release their bombs, and dropped, them at I-PIRMASBNS on the return journey.     As a result of \\ fighting, six of the enemy were destroyed or driven down out of-control.    Pour of- our machines did not return,On tho night of October 21/22nd, orders were issued for four Randley-Pagos, each carrying one 16;.) lb. bomb, and four others with full loads of B.I. bombs, to attack KAISBRSLATJTERK*     Three of tho machines with the 1650 lb. bombs reached their objej.tive and dropped their bombs from 5,000, 7,000, an4 8,000 feet. The fourth heavy-bomb carrier returns! with rigging trouble. Only two of the machines carrying B.I. bombs reached KAISERSLAUTERN. All \ heavy bombs appeared to burst with good results, anj when the last machine left the objective five large fires were burning,KAISER&amp;LAUTERN was again attacked on the night of the 23/24th October by one machine of No.fcI5 Squadron, which dropped one 1650 lb, bomb and two 11! lb, bombs, BFactories in tho neighbourhood of FRANKFURT.On&apos; the &quot;21st October, 12 machines of too.110  qua:-left to attack COLOGNE, or as alternatives, COBLENZ or EHRANGE,     The lines were crossed at 16,000 feet and a compass course flown over and through cloud. The wind appears   to have increased from the West during the flight, and the RHINE was crossed and mistaken for the MOSELLE.     Shortly after crossing \ Rhine, a dense bank of clouds was encountered at Y\ feet.     The leader fired a red light, and, with hisformation well closed up, endeavoured to descend it the clouds.     The formation then got muoh split up Two of the machines climbed and flew South-west until they came out of cloud, and dropped their bombs on Railways and a Factory (apparently in the neighbour^ Of FRANKFURT), and both returned safely to their aerodrome.     One other machine followed the loader 1l he came out of cloud at about 11,000 feet, when the leader signalled the %ash-outu and continued to des Three other machines returned and landed in the dark various places near the front line.     The remaining seven machines did not return.    According to report! received from the German Wireless some of these mach: appear to have dropped their bombs in the Valley of LAHR,(d) OOBLENZ,CrTthe night of the 23/24th October, one machln ,   of No.216 Squadron attacked COBLENZ, dropping one 55ij lb, and eight 112 lb, bombs from a height of 4,400 flP(e) WIESBADEN.Vn the same night, a machine of No.97 Squadron dropped one 1650 lb, and four 25 lb., bombs into WIESfl which was brilliantly lighted at the time.(f) MANNgSIM,The Badische-Anilin und Soda-Fabrik Works and tho OPPAU at MANNHEIM have boon attaoked three times during the month.On the night of the 23/24th, one machine of No.2 Squadron dropped fourteen 112 lb, bombs.
On the night of the 28/29thvOctober, one machine of No. 97 Squadron reached this objective and dropped one&apos; 1650 lb, and two 112 lb. bombs.On the night of the 29/30th; seven Ilandley-Pagos reached this objective and dropped over four tons of bombs.     The majority of the bombs tell well among the&apos; works buildings, and a large fire was started.On tho same night the Lanz Works at MANNHEIM were attacked by one Handley-Page with fourteen 112 lb, bombs from 3,000 feet,&apos;(g) BONN.BONN&apos; Munition Factories were bombed by six-D.H.4a of No.55 Squadron on the 31si October,     One 230 lb, and ten 112 lb, bombs   fell from 16,500 feet in the town on each side of the Railway,Railways. At tho request of tho Marshal, Commanding in chief tho Allied Armies, several attacks on Railway objectives had been made in co-operation with attacks made by the French and American Armies on the CHAMPAGNE Front.   Over 50 tons of bombs have been dropped during the month, and very considerable damage has been caused at METZ, MEZIERSS and SAAREBRUCK Stations.     The Railways at OFFENBURG wore heavily bombed on the night of October 29/30th.Blast The Blast Furnaces at BURBACH have been attackedFurnaces,, four times, and those at R Of ABACK onoc.On the night of the 23/24th October one maohine of No.100 Squadron dropped one 1650 lb., bomb in the ; Works at SAAREBRUCJC, with excellent results.   The pilot of this machine reported a balloon barrage at 7,000 feet around the target.     These Works were again bombed on the night of 29/30th October.Aerodromes. During the month, 18 tons of bombs have been,       ,    (jp0ppe,j on aerodromes., On October 15th, one D.H.4. of No.,.56 Squadron flew under and through low clouds to FRESOATY Aerodrome. From a height of 40 feet the pilot dropped one 112 lb. bomb Into the  -Zeppelin hangar and observed all the windows to be bloY/n out.     His second 112 lb. bomb fell and exploded in another hongar.     Men and horses were machine-gunned on the ground, both suffering casualties.     The machine returned undamaged.     This aerodrome has been attacked six times, and MORHANGE five times.^HAGGENAU Aerodrome has been bombed twice by ni ht&quot;, and BUHL was successfully attacked by Nos.09, and, &apos;,     , 104 &quot;Squadrons on the 31st October.Co-operation The co-operation with the French and Americanswith the   in their attack between REEI MS and VERDUN, which was French     begun &quot;in1 September, was continued this month.   - The chief and objectives were the Railways at ilEZIERES, TIIIQNVILLE anilAmerican   METZ, and FRESCATY Aerodrome, and these were heavily Armies.    bombed on every available opportunity. -Nearly.40 tons of bombs wore dropped on METZ-SABLON, 6l tons on KEZIERE3, over 5% tons on THIONVILLE, and 7ir tons on FRESCATY Aerodrome.
On the 24th October, a request was received fit Marshal Poch for the Independent Force to co-^p^*na,to t the French and Americans in attacking from the air the HIRSOH, MEZIERES, LONGUYON. Railway System. The large allotted to the Independent Force were the junotions $ LONGUYOH and ECUVIEZ (East of MONTMEDY),Until the night of the 28/29th October clouds and mist prevented &apos; &quot;these targets from being reached, 01 that night both were heavily bombed.9, Hostile Until the last few days of the month the enemyAerial      has shown little bombing activity.     After the period Activity   the moon the weather cleared, and during the last thro I during      days of the month hostile machines in small numbers an the Month, dropping small quantities of bombs have been comparat!active.     None of our aerodromes has been attacked. Ineffective raids have been oarried out against an Amorican Supply Depot at GOLOMBEY, and a few bombs weil dropped in the neighbourhood of the 6th Aircraft Park VEZELISE on the night of October 29/30th, without eff(Our formations continue to encounter the oner; in large numbers whenever they cross the line, and th I has been heavy fighting on several occasions.   On the I of O0t,ober, No. 104 Squadron in their attack on METZ.. SABLON were attacked by 15 hostile machines, three of which they destroyed.     One of our machines was brour down.   On the same day, and over the same objective, No.99 Squadron were attacked by 16 of the enemy.   On this occasion all cur machines returned, having drivel down one of the enemy.     On the 29th October, 13 maor of No.lO*i Squadron encountered 40 of the enemy over JAMETZ Aerodrome.     In the fighting four hostile aerc planes were destroyed and many more were&quot;driven down [j damaged.    We lost one D.H.9.10, Aerodrome The ground work on the aerodromes is practice and Gamp complete and has enabled me to dispose of the Canadijjj Con- Forestry Companies and a proportion of the other label struction to the British Expeditionary Force.11. Inter-Alltod       Ot ,he IMh October Instruoflione w&amp;re receivip Indepencr relative to the constitution of the Inter-Allied ent Air   Independent Air Force, and confirming my appointment Force.     as Commander-in-Chiof of the Force.Statistics. Appendix &quot;A&quot; is attached, showing the hours^flown, bombs dropped, etc, during the month.(Sd). H.Trenchard.Major General, Commanding-in-Chief, Intor-Allied Independent Air Force.1st November, 1918.
APPENDIX ttA&quot;.HOURS FLOWN.INgSPEHDENT.FORCE, R.A.F.OCTOBER, 1918.October 1st to 51st,.1018,Ilrs,Day      1,827Night      629 TOTAL,Kins. 512,456      51BOMBS DROPPED.1650 lb. 550 lb, 230 lb, 1.12 lb,  . 40 lb. 25 lb. Cases B..X,11 25 125 1,34712626WEIGHT.Tons    Cwts.&apos;   Qrs,    Lbs, 97       14 3       21PLATES EXPOSED.584HOSTILE MACHINES DESTROYED ..5HOSTILE MACHINES DRIVEN D0r/N0TB MACHINES HISSING,1514OUR MACHINES WRECKED.D.H.4, D.H.9. D.H.9a. H, P,7 1321 18TOTAL.      59

</content>
</cab>
