<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 142-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
t!8 Document is the Property oflrJ-     - &quot; ajestVs Government,1 fi&apos;QSEC RE T, Copy No,SERIAL NO. 17.l NOTES ON THE AMERICAN ARMY,i. . . General.There are now 41 American Divisions in Prance, 39 of which are under General Pershing, and 2 of which are attached to B,E,F.Of the Divisions under General Pershlng, 27 are trained, (i,e, capable of being put into the line), 6 are Depot Divisions. 5 Combat Divisions v/hich have recently arrived are on L,of.C,, and 1 Combat Division is being used as labour troops.The personnel of 2 Depot Divisions and of the 5 Combat Divisions on L,of,C, have had to be absorbed into the 4 other Depot Divisions, owing to the replacements required for the fighting Divisions being considerably more than was anticipated,One Regiment of the 85*p&apos;d (Depot) Division has been sent to Italy, and one Regiment of the 85th (Depot) Division Is In North Russia,In addition there are 12 Battalions of coloured troops with the French, and various administrative and Lines of Communication troops,The following is a summary of the number of American forces in, or en route to, Europe on 30th OctoberI In France.General Pershingfs Army - 39 Divisions, )Administrative Units, etc, )7,&apos;ith British - 2 Divisions, Casual, ivledieal      ... i,b*y,    .r Engineer and. Aviation Units, )11 Z or general Per s h 1 nr&apos; s Army.England     -   awaiting sHipment ...   13,590 )En&quot;&apos;route) -   England.............. 70,869 ),.,     162,754to     ) -   France.............   78,295 )III With French.&apos;  12 Battalions coloured troops....................      23,188IV In Italy.TTjnTantry Regiment and various hospitalunits..............................,..........        5,386V In U.K.Training and duty...............................      21,148VI In North Russia.I Infantry Regiment........................,,,,_5,225Total.......... 2,065,4952,   Shipping.The total troops despatched from America during October was 186,000 as compared with 254,000 in September. Of the former number 112,000 were carried In British tonnage.The Estimated Shipment for November is 225,000, of whieh 88,000 will be replacements, 2 Divisions complete and the balance of one Division partly shipped in October will also be included,3,   Distribution,
Distribution.The First and Second American Armies have 24 American Divisions,     1 Division is with the Frenoh 4th Army and 2 divisions are with the French Army In Belgium.     The VII Corps in tho VOSGES has been relieved by a French Corps.Operations..(a) The First American Army has been engaged on operations of great importance during the past week.    On 1st November, it attacked, in conjunction with the 4th French Army on its left, -from the ME USE to CHAMPIGNEULLES,    The enemy resistance for the first two days was stiff, especially on the flanks, but good progress was made,     The enemy subsequently commenced to withdraw along the whole front and progress became rapid, and on November 6th the Americans had reached the west bank of the MEUSE every-where as far as SEDAN.     On 4th November they also succeeded In crossing to the east bank of the MEUSE at BRIEULLES and have since enlarged this bridgehead.During these operations about 6,000 prisoners were captured (mostly on the first two days) and great quantities of material.The American Staff appears to have gained by their former experiences as the arrangements made for this battle seem to have been good and not only in the battle area but also in the back areas and lines of communication everything went well.The American divisions m Flanders were also engaged along with the French and British in the attack east of COURTRAI on 31st October.(b) The 2 Divisions of the II Corps attached to the British are still out of the line.* Casualties.No casualty statement has been received this week.AS.

</content>
</cab>
