<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 225-226</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS POPUP&apos;!? .TS THE PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY13 GCTODOTT) .SECRET. G ,T , 6^57.WAR CABINET.DEMCBI L I Z A T. I ON.(I)   p r ojpo d e d: amp. 1 g am a t icn of Minis tries of munitions and Re const x*uoti p,n..(11J   C o mmu ni oat ion &quot;t o Fed e rat ion of Br itish In duat r ie s of Governmenf proposals re civil demobilisation,0opy of letter from Acting Director, Federation of BritishliicTus^rreli; To&quot;The Trl me*IfilVisle&quot;r&quot; &quot;     *.....&quot;Federation of British Industries, 39, St. James&apos; s&apos; Street, London, S.VT. 1*6th November, 1918.Sir,I am directed by the Federation to transmit to you copies cf two resolutions which have been passed by the Organisation and Management Gommittee dealing with two aspects of the problem of reconstruction.   The Federation regards the subjects touohed upon in these resolutions as&quot;of the very greatest importance, and they would be glad if you would arrange^  to receive a deputation to discuss the subject   with you at as early a date as possible,   cn hearing from you Yfhat date and time will suit you to receive the deputation the necessary arrangements will be made immediately,Yours faithfully,The Rt. Hon. avid Lloyd George,M.P. 10 Dp wn trig Street,(Sgd.)    CHARLES TENFYSON,Acting Director.
(II)The Federation urges upon the prime Minister that before any announcement be made with respect&apos;to civil demobilisation, the effect of which may seriously disturb the industries of the country, full information of the Government&apos;s proposals be communicated to the Federation, and a deputation be reoeived and heard before any such publio announcement be made, and before any action be definitely deoided upon.That in view of the probability of the imminent applioa-tion of the Break Olause in Government contract&apos;4, owing to the early cessation of the manufacture of munitions and the oonse-quent fact that the Ministry of Reconstruction ia now beooming the most important of Government Departments, the Federation urges upon the Prime Minister the advisability that the Ministry of Reconstruction should be united with the present Ministry cf Munitions, and that these two departments should be under one united head of commercial experience, and that they should be given full executive powers.

</content>
</cab>
