<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 258-261</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MO  Q : i iTelegrams-&quot;SHIPMINDER, VIC, LONDON.&apos;13,y&apos;s Government.? n iAny further communication on this subject should be addressed to The Secretary,Ministry of Shipping,St. James&apos;s Park, \   CAfi/JJ^ London, S.W. 1,and the fblrcflyiagSouiiiber quoted.2.3.MINISTRY OF SHIPPING, -November, 1918.In continuation of my letter of the 4th instant I am directed by the Shipping Controller to report, for the inform-ation of the Viar Cabinet, as follows :-1.        FINANCE.During the week ended the 2nd instant the sum of  620,643 was paid in compensation for loss of requisitioned ship making a total of  36,940,034 paid on this account since the 1st April, 1918.TONKAGE LOSSES ,^:D GAINS.The casualties to British vessels of 500 gross tons and upwards reported during the week ended the 2nd instant were one vessel lost by enemy action and three by marine risk, making a total loss of 10,035 gross tons.During the same period the total number of new vessels, British built, brought into service were 12 vessels of 57,138 gross tons, making a net gain of 8 vessels of 46^403 gross tons. one of the casualties mentioned occurred while the vessels were in convoy.     10 homeward bound convoys consisting of 184 ships and 7 outward bound convoys having been escorted safely through the danger zones since my last report,saiPfl&amp;rrrs pv fuel oil in double-bottoms akd dijil-p taksb.Total Quantity loaded to date ... 1,001,414 tohsTotal delivered to date &quot;     lost &quot;     &quot;&quot;     on passage962,346 tons17,392 &quot;21,678 &quot;1,001,414 tonsTH8 SECRJSTAEiY, WAR CA3IIET.
In view of the improved Admiralty stock position, and the urgent need for additional general cargo space, it has been agreed that for trie present fuel oil will cease to take priority over other cargoes in tne double-bottoms of Transatlantic vessels the fitting of further vessels has also been suspended.     Steps are being taken however .to ensure that shipments and fitting may immediately be resumed in case of necessity.It may be of interest to note that the cessation of these shipments co/cides in point of time witn the attainment of the &quot;million mark&quot; in the total quantity loaded since July 1917 - the inception of the scheme, and also with the attainment by the Admiralty of&quot; their minimum reserve stock for the first time during the war. hlDRiRAL SUPPLIES,The supply of tonnage for Iron Ore during September and October has been maintained at 550,000 tons.     Ironmasters1 stocks in United Kingdom appear to be satisfactory.The urgency for coal in rranee has necessitated the return of tonnage from the Bay of Biscay ports but the reduced quantity of iron ore available in North Spain also favours this policy.For the first time a cargo of manganiferous ore from Sinai has now been shipped.     then the war commenced, the Germans were almost ready to start shipments from this mine.A considerable proportion of space in mineral steamers will be required for fruit during the next three months from South Spain under the terms of the Anglo-Spanish commercial agreement.CKMGB IE VIA R ^11U AT I Or;.This department is in constant touch with the Tar Office on the question of what services can be suspended or stopped now in view of the changed conditions, and -,v;.iat services can be suspended later in certain eventualities..e./
SHIPPING- ADJTJSTMEHTS.C0NSSQU3CT ON ARMISTICE VjII&apos;H TURKEY. $0Vessels have been allocated for the conveyance ofabout 6,000 troops and 1,000 horses to the Dardanelles and constantinople.It is expected that the landing of stores on the bulgarian coast trill shortly ceass when Constantinople isopened as a base.SUPPLY OF&apos; ARmY IK SYRIA.Arrangements are now satisfactorily established forthe maintenance of supplies by sea to the British troops in syria.CONVEYANCE OP BRITISH PRISONERS 0?&apos; WAR PROM TURKEY. *The transport &quot;EMPIRE&quot; which has been specially toldoff for conveying Indian Prisoners of ttar from Turkey to Egypten route to India will leave Egypt within the next day or two.British Prisoners of Mr who are not cot cases will be carried in a special transport to Taranto from Egypt while cot cases will be brought to Egypt by hospital ship.MOVE OP FRENCH REFUGEES FROM HOLLAED.Two passenger carrying vessels are being lent to theFrench for the conveyance of French refugees from Flushing toDunkirk in view of the large numbers accumulated in Holland andthejrr pitiable conditions.REPATRIATION OP TiOMEg AMD CHILDREN FPX&amp; THIS COUNTRY.The Admiralty have, in view of the submarine position, temporarily removed the restrictions on the conveyance of women and children by sea in order that as many women and children as possible may be repatriated before demobilisation commences, so as to relieve to some extent the strain that will then be thrown on our s hi shipping re s ource s,EXCHANGE OF BRITISH AND GERMAN PRISONERS OP WAR. The twenty-seventh exchange has taken place.     387 British      u prisoners and 41 British women and children were disembarkedat/
at Boston on the 1st instant, and 102 German prisoners and 27 women and children embarked on the 2nd and 3rd instant.STORES FOR THE BRITISH jW IN FRANCH.In the week ending 2nd November there were discharged in France 177,376 tons of Military stores as compared with 200,328 tons in the previous week.I am,Sir,lour obedient Servant,(Sgd.) JOHN ANDERSON

</content>
</cab>
