<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 288-289</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[ZlJI S DOCUMENT ID THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY * 8 GOYEBIIMBNT] SECRET. WAR CABINET,G. T, 62:76..CEREAL PRICES   FOR   19.19.emorandum by the President of the Board of Agriculture and fisheries the President of the Board of Agriculture, the Secretary for Scotland, and the Chief Secretary for Ireland, concur in asking that an announcement should he immediately issued that the prices for controlled cereals to he paid to farmers for the harvest of 1919 should be not less than those fixed to be paid to farmers for the harvest of 1918c     In the United States, President Wilson (see the &quot;Times&quot; for September 4th, 1918, page 5, column 6, at the end) has issued a proclamation guaranteeing to farmers the same prices for the 1919 wheat crop that were guaranteed for the 1918 crop*     He has further promised that a Government enquiry into the increased cost of labour and supplies shall be made, ,1nd that such an increase in the 1918 prices as that enquiry shows to be necessary    will be made in 1919*A similar guarantee of prices is -asked for by Britishfarmers.     In view of President Wilson&apos;s proclamation, no fall in wheaj prices is naturally likely to occur in 1919*     But farmers are well aware that the Government, by increasing the subsidy on bread, and by free carriage, could knock prices down to the level of the minima fixed by the Corn Production Act.     They therefore ask that the prices paid them in 1918 snould be guaranteed them for 1919*Without this assurance it is certain that less corn will be grown, more land fallowed, and less labour employed.     The Agricultural Executive Committee all over the country are showing great anxiety, and the County organisations threaten to go to pieces * The confidence which has been gradually established in the minds of the farmers will be lost.The Pood Controller declined to increase wheat prices in 1918 in spite of the loss caused by weather, mainly on the ground, which was strongly urged by Lrrd Reading, that President Wilson had
?* Rfa    Mrefused a rise to American farmers, and that the granting of any rise to British farmers would prejudice hi3 position^    That decision was, for that reason, accepted in this country*     Now that President V/ilson has given a grantee of prioea not less than those of X918., and a promise that they will bo raised if it is found necessary to meet increased costs of production, the argument from the American situation is strongly turned against the Food Controller-.-Since the issue of President Wilson1a proclamation, the Board of Agriculture has strongly pressed the Food Controller to announce the minimum prices for cereals for 1919*    After prolonged negotiations, the Food Controller has decided that  the ques&apos;;&apos;.^1 is not one for him, but for the Treasury *The season has already far advanced.    No further time can bo lost.    The point is therefore submitted to the Cabinet for dec i si on i14th November, 1918*%. Bi PROTHEBO.

</content>
</cab>
