<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 348-355</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property ofofckphtne: -Victoria 8210.!0 Sowest, London.BOARD OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES.To avoid delay, address all ccmmunicaiions to food PRODUCTION DEPARTMENT,72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. (1).13th November, 1918.Sir,V&apos;f - &apos;-&quot;   &apos;   &apos; -I&apos;beg to submit the following Report on the work of the t/ Pood Production Department for the week ended 12th November 1918.-rv &quot;-;&quot; .....      -   The Weather and Condition of Crops,,;-- - Dry weather accompanied by cold winds and frost at night- - was-experienced-throughout the greater part&apos; of the country during&quot; the- past week.-   Considerable progress&apos; has been made in the lifting of -potatoes&apos;&quot;&quot;and-the pulling of-roots, both of which&apos;crops are about the average, and in most cases comparatively free from disease., --u.&apos; &quot;      A-&apos;good-deal of: corn has been sown on light land, and those crop&amp;&apos;wh-ich&apos; are already coming up look well.   Heavy land is still- vsadden &quot;and cannoi be cultivated to any extent.LOCAL ORGANISATION DIVISION. Work of Agricultural Executive Committees. The following are examples of the work of AgriculturalExecutive Committees which have been reported during the week:-t ......Middlesex - By arrangement with the military authorities the,... Committee undertook last March the cultivation of an area of about 14f acres on Hounslow Heath, a grant for the purpose being made by the Department.     A most favourable report on the work done has now been received.     The land, which was rough heath covered with I    bushes and undergrowth, had., been cleared by May, ploughed, . manured and planted with potatoes, and part of the land has yielded 10 tons to the acre.     There has been very little disease&apos;     ,        , &apos; &apos; \       .&apos;.      It.&apos;:-&quot;&apos;-&quot;&apos; .    &apos;    &apos; &apos;  - &apos; &apos; &apos; &apos;- .S.
among the crops and the greater portion is realising  7*10.0. and  7 per ton.   In addition to procuring an increase in the. foe supply^ the scheme has succeeded financially.     There is every prospect of an even better result next year when it is hoped to provide fer the cultivation of a further 12 acres. Prosecutions -   The owner-occupier of a farm at Hulcot in Buckinghamshire was served with an order by the Executive Commit directing him to mow 44 acres of his grass land and plough it. ir   Jeffort having been made to comply with the order, the owner was j prosecuted and the Magistrates have convicted and imposed a fin of  75 for each offonce, making a total of  150, including cost: A farmer at Tur Lang ton in Leicestershire has been fined  50 fc: having failed to comply with a cultivation order served upon hicj by the Executive Committee.A farmer at Steeple Ashton in Wiltshire has been fineci  10.10.0. and costs for a similar offence.   TWO farmers in &apos; Breoonshire have been fined  30 and  20 respectively for not haij carried out the orders of the Executive Committee. Determination of Tenancies - During the week 1 Order has been rail by the ^oard determining a tenancy on account of bad farming in respect of 130 acres.Land Drainage.in i in   ..i -i    il- i......        i. hi VrlmiNorfolk - The .Committee are commencing work on the upper reachei of the Wissey.Yorkshire, East Ridlnff - This Committee have carried out substantial work on several of the channels which carry the drainage of the valuable lands flanking the Humber on the North work of cleaning the Greenoak Goit was completed in 1917, and considerable benefit,was done thereby tt an area of about 2,000 acres. The work ,cost approximately  600, and the whole of this
expenditure has now been recovered from the persons interested. Tiork on the Bellasize Drain was completed last month, the area benefited in this case being approximately 4,000 acres.   Considerable difficulty has been experienced in this district owing to the treacherous nature of the sandy clay soil.     The drain is now stated, however, to be more efficient than it has been for the last 70 years.    The work has cost  1,200, and the recovery of the expenditure is now being undertaken.    The water in the Market V/eighton Canal (which forms the outfall of the River Foulness) has been substantially lowered by the regulation of the lock gates at the mouth, and the Committee are carrying out the cleansing of the canal In the place of the Drainage an4 Navigation Commissioners. Certain of the main subsidiary drains have been cleansed and the cleansing of others is being carried out.    It is expected that about 20,000 acres will be benefited by this work when completed.    The clearance is also being carried out of the Kilpin Pike which forms the main putfall of the powden system of drains. Yorkshire, West Ridings    The Committee are carrying out&apos;repairs to the Awkley and Blaxton drainage near Doncaster under the powers op a parish award.- in addition to the numerous drainage works that they have already completed or have in hand.HORTICULTURAL DIVISION, Horticultural $ub-Committee3.-    A&apos; Conference of representatives of Horticultural Sub-Committees, at whioh 51 counties were represented, was held in Ltndon on the 6th November,   The relations that should exist between Horticultural Sub-Committees and Agricultural Executive Committees was defined, and the future work of the Sub-committee was discussed.Allotments Section.      During the week 31 local authorities have agreed to acquire 275 acres (3,884 allotments),   VJest Ham and Watford are providing for over 400 additional, allotments,&apos;   Greenwich
Iand Huddersfield for 300;   Epsom, Farnham, Normanton, and Bootlo for over 200;   Maiden and Coombe, Morley, Oxford, Marsden Ashton-on-Mersey, and Rhymney for ovor 100.Fruit Section.     The Department are taking steps to secure the       t standardisation of stocks used for grafting apples,     Investigations! carried out at the Wye Experimental Station at East Mailing have supplied means whereby growers may identify their apple stocks and see that they are true to name.   It is hoped to secure a basis for experimental work, and an improvement In fruit production by encouraging nurserymen to select only those stocks which have been shown to be the best for the purpose of grafting. Marketing Organisation.   30 counties now possess registered SocietiJ cr are otherwise fully organised for Marketing.     1Q counties are preparing to register Societies, or have already made other arrangements for marketing.    Local markets have been established in four counties... Certain County Marketing Societies are in commUnication with the Directors of National Kitchens with the&apos; object of securing the purchase by the. National Kitchens of the surplus produce collected by the Societies.    This arrangement is already in prsict in West Middlesex and ,the County Society finds a ready market for its produce in this direction-^In Surrey, the Marketing Organisation has 47 branches at work, and a jam factory In full working order.    The Society is making arrangements for the production of farina from diseased and under-sized potatoes9Market Garden Produce.   At a conference convened by the CheshireInHorticultural Sub-Committee and attended by the Department&apos;.s Inspectors the subjects of the improved cultivation of allotments, the working of the soil, green manuring, and successional cropping, were consideredt     It was agreed that all instruction in the county should be co-ordinated under the Divisional Inspectors of the Department *ciei:0leIdn, o
TECHNICAL DIVISION. Broadcast Wheat Sowing.     The modern.method of sowing wheat viz. by irilling, is not adapted for wet weather, consequently the efforts of farmers to get on with this work arc seriously hampered by rainy weather, I in the present season.   Attention ha3, therefore, been drawn to tho practice successfully adopted on many of the heavier wheat lands, of jroadcasting the seed on tho furrow and harrowing it In.   Another method *o which the attention of farmers has been drawn is one occasionally followed on free-working soils after certain crops, of braod-casting the seed on the surface and immediately ploughing it in under a shallow furrow Seed Testing Station.   During the month of October, approximately 2,500 samples were received for testing, making a total of 4,750 for the first three months of this season, 2,500 of which have been wheat samples.   A :considerable number of pea and bean samples are now coming to hand.   It jay be noted that runner and dwarf French beans are, on the average, of jioor germinating capacity.   Italian red clovers aro being received in considerable numbers this season, and as a rule have a high germination.LABOUR DIVISION.jlarvest Labour.   The number of soldiers specially released for harvest! -iork and still out on farms is 3,362.The military authorities have granted an extension of furlough ,0 these men for a further period of 14 days, where such extension is fiecessary for the in-gathering of the remainder of the harvest.   In the :ase of Lincolnshire, //hero a large acreage of potatoes still remains to ie gathered, an extension of one month&apos;s furlough has been granted.In view of the backward state of the potato harvest in the lolland division of Lincolnshire, and the altered military conditions, the iepartment have asked the War Office to make available immediately an Additional 250 soldiers for ;vork in this county.5,488 prisoners of war under the migratory gang scheme are Imaged on potato lifting.[old 1 or Labour.   2,223 skilled ploughmen have been released to date on &apos;iio months&apos; agricultural furlough to assist with the autumn cultivations.ill these men have been placed on farms.   In view of the cessation oft.hostilities, it is hoped to secure, at an early date, an increase in the
number of these ploughmen, as tho existing organisation enables soldiers! to bo placed out with farmers very rapidly and can be made use of pending demobilisation.Threshing Machine Drivers.   The War Office have issued instructions that! all threshing machine drivers, irrespective of category, who are with  \b the Home Forces are to be released immediately on agricultural furlough, These men will be sent to the Agricultural Distribution Centre serving their county of origin. It Is expected that about 250 drivers will be made available under this arrangement which should remove all further fear &quot;of lack of labour for threshing this year1s,crops.Women&apos;s Branch.Employment. There is still a shortage of woman labour, but the balance between supply and demand is being maintained as well as possible. A certain surplus was anticipated this weok, but an unexpected demand for root pulling has come in. The large demands for women for threshing in Kent have been met, with the exception of 50 women. It is hoped to be ab to supply this number quickly, in order that the skilled milkers employe on threshing may be withdrawn, their services being urgently required in various parts of the country. The places of these women will be filled b: others who are now working in potato districts but will shortly be roleaiMembers of the Land Army have done good work in connection witl potato lifting. In the West Riding, for example, many farmers are anxious to engage permanently some of those, who, in the first .place, were only engaged as seasonal workers. In the Amcotts district of the Isle of Axholme, women, have already lifted 235 acres of potatoes. women&apos;s Institutes. Increased interest is being shown by the various County Councils in the Women&apos;s Institutes movement, and much help is beii obtained from these bodies in regard to lecturers and instructresses..The Secretary of the Agricultural Education Sub-Committee of tl Wiltshire County Council has offered the services of a cheese instructrel for Women1 s Institutes during the winter months. Two lecturers on dairyi&apos; will also be placed at the disposal of the Institutes by the County Conn The Secretary of the Agricultural Education Committee of the County Coun in East Sussex lately convened a conference, at which representatives fr( other County Councils attended. The best means of meeting the demands fr Women&apos;s Institutes for lecturers on agricultural subjects v/as discussed.
CULTIVATION DIVISION. Tractor Scheme.   The following statement shows tho position with regard to the provision of tractors, machinery and implements for the week ended 9th November, 1918:-No. consigned   Total No. during week.    with bounties.Tractors............... 39 4,&apos;191(2 withdrawn)Ploughs ................ 42 5)409During the week ended 25th October, 23,476 acres were ploughed, 166 acres were cross-ploughed and 2,217 acres cultivated. Steam Tackle.    The acreage dealt with during the past week is as follows:-   ploughed 14,295 acres, cultivated 1,863 acres, harrowed 211 acres, mole-drained 104 acres, rolled 167 acres.    Total 16,640 acres.Harvest Work.    One additional threshing machine has been consigned to a County Agricultural Executive Committee during the week, making the total number of machines with the counties&apos;- to date 355.SUPPLIES DIVISION. Wire Netting.    A considerable release of wire netting will now take place owing to the reduction of military requirements, and it will no doubt be possible to meet the needs of forestry and agriculture through.the usual channels of trade. Price of Ryegrass Seed.    A conference has been held with repressn-tatives of the principal seed houses in order to discuss the present high prices of ryegrass seed.    The crops in 1916 and 1917 were small, and the &quot;carry over&apos;1 of old seed to the present season has been negligible.      A fair average crop has been harvested this yecr, but the shortage of old seed, the high standard1 of quality set by the Testing of Seeds Order and an increased home demand which began exceptionally early, have all contributed to the inorease in price.    The seedsmen point out that a stoppage of export would cause a still further rise in price.    The Continental demand is&apos; for comparatively low grade
send, and if the shipment of this were prohibited, seedsmen wouldbe forced to add the price of this class of seed, which isunsrlocble in the United Kingdom, to the higher grades for whichthere is a home demand.   It was suggested that export shouldbe $llowed freely of seed of the 1918&apos; cron below 92 per cent in \    - ...... .  .. jpurity, and of all seed of the 1917 and&apos;earlier crops.Sited Jflieat., , The,selected seed wheat secured by the DepartmentTor distribution to farmers is now in agents&apos; hands.Seed &quot;Potatoes.     Enquiries Have&apos;&apos;bo&apos;en received by the Departmentfrom the French Government with regard to supplies ;of seed potatoes of the 1918 crop.     Information has been supplied asto varieties and approximate prices.  . Arrangements have .beenmade for the shipment of a small consignment of &apos; seed I for. thePortuguese, Government,Wart,.DiseaseThe revised list of approved immune varieties of potatoes is now ready for issue and will be distributed.for theinformation.of growers in infected .areas.,. At the Ormskirk Exhibition there, hps even-a- larger andmore interesting collection of potatoes than those of former years,A selection of immune varieties has already been exhibited at manchester, Swansea and Bridgend, and,will.be shown;.at Cheltenham,Walsall, Leeds, Sheffield,,,Bradford and tUewqastle-iOn-Tyne. .. ,. Arrangements . have been made .for the provision at thes,e Exhibitionsof advice to growers on the selection and culture of immunevarieties........., .   ., , .... .t ..Spraying. The Department are making arrangements, whereby an ,additional,.quantity of horse-drawn machines will be made availablefor.the spraying of.potatoes of the.1919 crop, and with this objecthave invited Agricultural Executive Committees to notify them of theminimum requirements for next season-,..    .... . ... .  ......I am,Sir,    : &apos;Your obedient Servant,......  Juo&amp;Ma -f&amp;Xit&amp;stffi&apos;&quot; director-General. &apos;&quot; The Rt. Hon. Rowland-E. Prothero, M.P. President of the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
