<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/69/0 images: 363-364</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/      jf/.   any zvisuLiPcat-war Overseas Garrisons. Memorandum for War Cabinet by the Secretaries of State for War and India.90Ji-i j1,      In a paper submitted to the War&apos; Cabinet on the 26th January last my predecessor aekod for authority to call for volunteers from the present armies to re-engage to serve for short terms of service after the war, and in doing so to promise that the present rates of pay, and of separation and other similar allowances, should bo continued to those who entered into such-a re-engagement&apos;.   When Lord Derbyts memorandum came before tho War Cabinet the question was raised whether the Indian Government should not be referred to, as tho principal demand for volunteers would be for service in India whose requirements (all ranks) after the war are on the best information at present available estimated at 78,000 out of a total of 142,000 for all Overseas Garrisono.   The War Cabinet, therefore, ordered that that Government should bo consulted.Accordingly, the Secretaries of State for vrar and India in consultation with tho Government of India, have now otnsidered tho steps necessary tc provide the garrison of India on the return of peace,   It is evident that, where the future of the military forces of the Empire is in so many respects uncertain, it is only possible to proceed upon purely provisional lines. Their recommendations are giren in paragraphs-2 - 5 below.2*     Strength.   It should be assumed for present purposes that the British force to be maintained in India will remain at about the pre-war strength, say ?8,000 all ranks.3*     Pay.     Tho rates of pay granted for the period of the War to all ranlcs should bo continued to the garrison of India for a limited period.   It is certain that the numbers for the new jgarrison cannot bo obtained from the survivors of tho old Regular Army, so that it is necessary either to start enlisting men for the future army at once, or to induce men now in the ranks to remain for a time.   The first alternative would involve tho impossible task of settling in advance the conditions of service cf the Army of the future.   Tho second alternative involves the difficulty that, as the men now induced to remain pass out of the ranks others will come in to replace them, serving on the future (presumably different) terms, so that there will be men saming side by side under different conditions-.     But this is inevjJaple and must be faced. &apos; &apos;/-^--The Secretaries of State for War and India are fully convinced that to ask men&apos; now in the ranks to extend their service on reduced rates of pay would be to court complete -,.   ,failure,4.      pther Conditions.   It is considered that after so -prolonged a war, the orTer of the continuance of present rates of pay would not by itself suffice to retain a sufficient numbor of men,    Further attractions aro therefore necessary;   and it is highly desirable to avoid the risk of obtaining an insufficient number of volunteers at tho first offer and having to begin a process of bargaining for higher terms0   It is bottor, in the circumstances, to risk putting the attractions rather higher than might prove necessary.     The propoaals undor this head are:
(i) That men he invited to citend for one, two or three year a after the one. of the war, the oh j act being to obtain tqual numbers in these categories, so that the replacement of these men by others enlisted under the new permanent conditions may proceed smoothly.(ii) That bounties and furlough be offered. On extension for one year:   100 rupees bounty.On extension for two years: 100 rupees a year bountyand two months&apos; -home furlough, On extension for three years: 150 rupees a year bountyand three months&apos; hone furlou the furlough boin;,&apos; given, if possible, before joining up in India.(iii) That a bonus in lifu of passage home be given to men who prefer it.   The object of this is to leneen the pressure on shipping and at the same time to get the services of the men required for India at an earlier date.(iv) That single men may be taken, if obtainable in preference to married men but that free passage to and fro,-. India be given to the families of such married men as are taken.   It is not intended that this privilege should be commutable for a money bonus.(Sd)   MIL&amp;2R, MONTAGU.I ask for authority to provide the necessary Colonial Garrisons on similar lines mutatis mutandis.(Sd)   MILK3R.14/ll/lS.

</content>
</cab>
