<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/3/20 images: 327-06 December 1939</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC IvUJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT
COPY NO. (3 -
WAR CABINET.
REPORT
CP THE MINISTERIAL SUB-C0MMITTE OP THE HOME POLICY COi,3aITTI35
'" ' ON
SUPPLIES OP WHEAT AND OTHER CEREALS.
In accordance with paragraph 12 of our first
Report (Paper W.P.(G)(39) 129) we submit to the War
Cabinet for consideration at the Meeting to be held on
Wednesday, 5th December., 1959, at 4.30 p.m. the following
Report on Supplies of Wheat and other Cereals.
2. We attach (Appendix) a Memorandum on the subject
by the Official Sub-Committee, which we have examined end
with which we find ourselves in general agreement. We
offer the following comments in explanation and amplification
of that Memorandum.
Stocks of Wheat.
3. We agree with the Official Sub-Committee that it
is dangerous to take as the basis of calculating the stocks
of wheat the total stock in the country, including the home
crop and that the only safe and reliable basis is to take
the amounts of wheat in the Flour Mills and the Port
Granaries. It is, for example, impossible to predict v/ith
accuracy when the home harvest will become available as
this must depend on uncertain factors relating to threshing,
such as the weather and the availability at the time of the
requisite amount of skilled labour and machinery. Moreover
it is impossible to forecast to what extent the shortage of
imported and other animal feeding stuffs may result, in

practice, in farmers using home grown wheat to feed t h e ir
stock. It should also be noted from the Table appended
to the Memorandum of the Official Committee that by t he
end of March, 1940, the Home crop will have become
exhausted.
Rate of Consumption of Wheat.
4* We agree with the Official Sub-Committee t h a t the
position of our wheat reserve from now until the end of
March will be unsatisfactory and may give rise t o s e r i o us
anxiety if, for any reason, there is any considerable
reduction or delay during that period in the import
programme for cereals. The consumption of wheat, which
is normally 500,000 tons a month, has been assumed t o r i se
to 545,000 tons a month, a figure which allows for some
increase in the demand for bread consequent on the
rationing of sugar and other foodstuffs from January
onwards.
5. It will be observed that if the programme
forecasted by the Official Sub-Committee is fulfilled we
shall attain by 31st March next a stock of wheat e q u i v a l e nt
to 13 weeks supply a figure which tn the Great War the
War Cabinet considered the minimum, below which supplies
should never fall. In view of this consideration and of
the risk of loss and damage from enemy action we t h i nk
that a reserve of 13 weeks supply of wheat in the M i l l s and
Granaries should be regarded as a minimum.
Measures taken to meet the Situation.
6. The War Cabinet will observe that in order to
increase the quantity of wheat in the Port Granaries and
Flour Mills the home crop of wheat has been brought under
control and from 1st December two-thirds of all t h e wheat

sold from uhe farms will go to the Flour Mills.
7. The Ministry of Shipping have also agreed to allocate
for cereals the full requirement of 880,000 tons of
shipping per month and as much above this as possible, to
enable stocks to be raised to a safer level. We are
informed by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries that
the threshing of the home wheat harvest may be delayed by
the absence with the Forces of certain skilled men who may,
in all, number a few hundreds. We recommend that the War
Office should be asked to release at once for the period
up to 31st March; 1940, men whether serving at home or in
France who are certified by the County War Agricultural
Executive Committee to be needed for threshing operations
this winter.
8. On page 5 of their Memorandum the Official Sub-
Committee refer to two ways in which the wheat position
could be further improved:(
i) by extending the rate of extraction of flour;
and/or
(ii) by concentrating, so far as practicable, on the
import of wheat and reducing the imports of
animal feeding stuffs.
9. As regards (i) v/e think this is a measure which
might be kept in reserve for use at short notice in a real
emergency but that at the moment the need for resorting to
it has not arisen.
1 0 . As regards (ii) we agree with this suggestion on the
understanding that the matter will be reviewed by the
Ministers of Food and Shipping from time to time and that
in implementing the arrangements due regard will be had to
the expression "so far as practicable".
1 1 . We recommend the War Cabinet to accept the
conclusions contained in the Report of the Official

Sub-Committee subject to the comments and. suggestions set
out in this Report and in particular those contained in
paragraphs 7 (release of skilled threshers in the Army)
9 (flour content) and ID (concentration, so far as
practicable, on import of wheat and review thereof at
the end of the year).
(Initialled) S.H.
CHAIRMAN.
easury Chambers,
5th December, 1939.

ppgTMgWT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAI71'TIG MAJESTYjS GOVERNMENT).
IS
COPY NO.
WAR CABINET
HOME POLICY COMMITTEE.
MINISTERIAL COMMITTEE ON POOD POLICY.
Memorandum by the Official Sub-Committee on Sup-plies of Wheat
and other cereals.
T. This Memorandum is submitted for the information of the
Ministerial Committee on Pood Policy and is a summary of the facts
of the present position as regards stocks and supplies of wheat,
flour and other cereals. In addition it contains in the last
paragraph certain suggestions upon which Ministerial decisions
appear to he necessary.
II. STOCKS.
The stock of wheat in the flour mills and port granaries
on the 18th of November amounted to 6 3 0 , 0 0 0 tons, or rather less
than si;; weeks' supply for human consumption. It is estimated that
at the same date there was left on the farms 8 6 0 , 0 0 0 tons of wheat,
or about seven and a half weeks' supply. Stocks of flour in the
mills and public warehouses and in the hands of bakers and retailers
were estimated at 2 7 3 , 0 0 0 tons, or about three and a half weeks"
supply, making a total stock in the form of wheat or flour equivalent
to 17 weeks' supply., The stock of wheat in the mills and the port
warehouses included the balance of the Government Security Stock
, 0 0 0 tons) created before the outbreak of war,. About 161, 0 00
terns of that Security Stock have been passed into consumption.
The low stocks in the mills and port warehouses combined
'ith the uncertainty regarding the ports to which convoys will be
Erected, make it extremely difficult to keep all the flour mills
inning, and, in fact, some of the mills in the West of Scotland
r1^ in the South-east of England have been stopped for a few days.

The experience of the past month has brought out clearly the
danger of looking only at the total stock of wheat in the
country, including the home crop, rather than at the amount in
the mills and the port granaries. The latter constitutes the
effective working stock, because wheat on the farms is not
readily usable and can only be threshed relatively slowly,
especially in bad weather.
Stocks of maize, barley and other cereals in the mills
and port warehouses amount only to a few thousand tons and, as
regards imported cereal feeding-stuffs, we are living entirely
from hand to mouth. Of the home crop of barley about 500,000 tons
remain on the farms, but it is estimated that unless brewing and
distilling are curtailed, nearly the whole of this will be required
by the brewers and. distillers, apart from the amount needed for
seed. An inter-departmental Committee is considering the
question of diverting grain from brewing and distilling for
animal feeding and its report is about to be circulated to
Ministers.
The greater part of the home crop of oats, amounting to
about two million tons, still remains on the farms and, owing to
bad threshing weather and the fact that farmers are holding it for
higher prices, supplies are coming forward very slowly.
n i RATE
OF CQHSUI-.IPTION.
The average monthly requirements of imported cereals
amount to 880,000 tons. This is based upon the average consumption
of the past five years. It must be remembered, however, that the
demand for cereal feeding-stuffs is somewhat higher in the period
from October to April than in the other months of the year. Of
the total requirements, the round figure of 500,000 tons per month
may be taken as the normal amount of wheat needed for human

consumption, the balance being, apart from small quantities of
peas, beans, etc., entirely animal feeding-stuffs. Requirements
of maize amount to 290,000 tons and barley to 75PO0O tons per
month.
IV. PROSPECTIVE ARRIVALS OF IMPORTEDCEREALS.
It is now too late to add to the quantity of imported
cereals which can arrive in this country before the 31st of
December. The arrivals in sight would leave the stocks of wheat
at the ports and in the mills at that date only about one weekTs
supply better than they are at present (i.e. rather less than
seven weeks' supply), but it is hoped that this position will be
improved by wheat brought into the mills from the home crop.
The arrivals of cereal feeding-stuffs before the end of December
will amount to about 50 per cent, of the imports required for
current consumption at this time of the year.
V. MEASURES TAKEN TO MEET TPIE SITUATION.
The most urgent need is to increase the quantity of
v/heat in the port granaries and in the flour mills. To this end
the home crop of wheat has been brought under control and from
the 1st December two-thirds of all the v/heat sold from the farms
will go to the flour mills. The proportion has been put at
two-thirds rather than 100 per cent, firstly to avoid cutting too
drastically into the home supply of feeding-stuffs, and secondly,
so as not to interfere with the seed trade. It is estimated that
this measure should provide at least 100,000 tons of wheat per
month for the flour mills up to the 31st of March.
The Ministry of Shipping have been asked to allocate
for cereals in future the full requirement of 380,000 tons of
a e
consumption of wheat flour since the outbreak of v/ar
shows an increase of 10$ due, it is thought, to increase
Qf stocks by bakers.

shinning per month, and as much above this as possible, to enable
stocks to be raised to a safer level. In the meanwhile, orders
have been given that, for the time being, all possible ships
shall be loaded with wheat to the exclusion of other cereals.
It will not now be possible to raise the December loadings or
the December and January arrivals to the full level. If the
programme of loading 880,000 tons of cereals per month is fulfilled
from January onwards, the total arrivals between the
beginning of the year end the end of Llarch may,apart from losses
and abnormal delays, be expected to amount to two and a half
million tons. Of this total, some 2,000,000 tons will be wheat
and the balance (about 500,000 tons) other cereals. This, together
with the amount brought into the mills from the home crop should
place the stock of wheat in the port granaries and the mills at
about thirteen weeks1 supply by the end of March, or rather more
than the quantity which was held at the outbreak of war. It is
considered that such a stock in the mills and port granaries is the
minimum with which we could safely face the spring and summer
months when there will be no home crop left.
In addition to the above measures, arrangements have
been made to import wheat from France on a repayment basis, the
wheat to be replaced later. Under this plan it is hoped that
100,000 tons of wheat may arrive from France during the next six
weeks, and it is understood that under normal loading arrangements,
imports from France could not be more rapid than this. Negotiations
are nearly complete for a further 200,000 tons to be shipped as
early as possible in 1940. There is a large surplus in France
which may not be needed at all if next year's crop does not fail.
An investigation, therefore, is in progress by the Ministry of
Shipping to ascertain whether, by improving loading facilities at
French ports, larger quantities of wheat can be obtained in this I Way,

VI. FURTHER STEPS V7HTCH MIGHT 3B TAKEN.
The 8 8 0 , 0 0 0 tons a month referred to above is the
bare minimum quantity of cereals which must arrive in this
country if (i) the stocks are to be raised to thirteen weeks1
supply by the end of March, and (ii) as much as 50 per cent,
of normal supplies of imported cereal feeding-stuffs are to be
available during the intervening period. The table in the
Appendix shews the estimated stock position of wheat at the end
of each month December, 1 9 3 9 ? to March, 1 9 4 0 , by which date the
stock will have reached, the level which is regarded as the
minimum required for the Spring and Summer months. After the
end of March the stock position should still further improve
if the import of cereals can continue at the level of 880,000 .
tons a month, of which at least 500,000 tons is wheat for human
consumption.
It is obvious that the position of our wheat reserve
between now and the end of March will be unsatisfactory and may
give rise to serious anxiety if, for any reason, there is any
reduction or delay during that period in the import programme for
cereals.
The only means by which this position could, be further
improved are:(
i) By extending the rate of extraction of flour; and/or
(ii) By concentrating, so far as practicable, on the
import of wheat and reducing the imports of animal
f e e d ing-s tuff s.
Both of these courses involve the reduction of the
quantity of feeding-stuffs available for livestock.
As regards (i), the' normal rate of extraction is 10%;
the present rate is 7 3 ^ ; it could be raised at short notice to
8$. At 80Jo the loaf would, be noticeably darker than at present, *
he quantity of wheat required for flour would be reduced by
ahout 5 0 , 0 0 0 tons a monthc Offals for animals would, be reduced
^ approximately a like quantity.

As regards (ii) it would not be economic to alter
arrangements already made for the lifting of cereals for feedingstuffs,
but it would be practicable to give instructions that
wherever there was a choice of cargo during the next three months
wheat should be given preference over maize or other cereals.
In the view of the Official Committee both courses
(i) and (ii) are worthy of serious consideration as temporary
measures in the existing situation and are, therefore, submitted
for decision by Ministers.,
2nd December, 1 9 3 9 .

5
STOCK OF WHEAT IN THE FLOUR MILLS AND PORT GRANARIES.
Stock at 3 r d September. 1 9 3 9 .
Stock at 18th November, 1 9 3 9 .
Estimated arrivals to 3 1 s t December
From the Home Crop to 3 1 s t December
Estimated consumption to 3 1 s t December
Stock at 3^st December, 1 9 3 9
Estimated arrivals, January, 1 9 4 0
From the Home Crop, January
Estimated consumption, January.
Stock at 3 1 s t January, 1940
Estimated arrivals, February
From the Home Crop, February
Estimated consumption February
Stock at 29th February, 1 9 h 0
Estimated arrivals, March
From the Home Crop, March
Estimated consumption, March
Stock at 31st March, 1940.
Thousands
of Tons.
1.36k
635
850
1 5 0 1,635
750
885
6 6 0
130
1,675
545
1,130
6 6 0
130
1,920
5k5
1,375
6 6 0
130
2,165
545
1,620
Weeks1
Supply
12
11
13
IQTJh The above figures include 100,000 tons of wheat
expected to arrive from France before 3 1 s t December but
not the further 200,000 tons mentioned in paragraph
V (page k) of the Memorandum,

</content>
</cab>
