<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/2 images: 54-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IIP...										A077:ile:^&apos;l		111Hfc-is-i&apos;ocpds^*t&amp;*-!7jX3!?i?.ii &apos;est?e-May-.Ibe 4memo fio dgsipgq^ of Clans (todsmoat.is3HCONCLUSIONS-of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at W Downing Street,- -  S.W.t,mThursday, November 2, 1939, at II-30a.m.&quot;Present.:.&apos;:&apos;&apos;The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The: Right Hon. Sir, John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha,M.P., Secretary of&apos; State for War.The Bight Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt^iEP., Lord Privy: Seal.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAJffiairs;The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAd-miraltyiThe Right Hon. Sir Kjngsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfblio.Tie Bight&apos; Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for the&apos;:&apos;&apos;Ponie Department and&apos;-Minister- of-&quot;Home SecHrity.: -The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,- President :of . the , Board, &quot;of Trade.    (item.a),. ;&apos;.&apos; .&quot; :&quot;&apos;:.Mr, B. - Hg Ckosssv M.P., Minister ,for economic Warfare (Item 8).al of &apos;ih.G Melt Sir Dudley::   u i ^ViS-a Loid and Chief ofThe Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 1-7).The Right Hon. Sir John Gilmour,Bt., M.P., Minister of Shipping(ItemS).Sir Horace J. Wilson, Permanent;;:. Secretary to: the Treasury.General iSir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial-General Staft(items l-Tjf;meat
BARContents.Wo.1 The Air Situation     ...      ...      ...      ....... ...      XI2 The Naval Situation ... .&quot;.   ............ ...    -113 The Military Situation       ...      ... ...114 Staff Conversations with Belgium ...     ...     ... ...     H5     Germany \-    ...      .........      ... .--      HInternal situation. -6     visit of Dominion Ministers.........     .:.     ...11despatch of Expeditionary Forces from Australia and New&quot;&apos; Zealand.7     Leakage of information to Germany...     ......     ....     ...     13Control of communications with Eire and Northern Ireland.8     Proposed War Trade Agreement with Sweden   ...      ...     14Swedish exports of iron ore to Germany.Agreement for chartering Swedish shipping.
The ? (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 67th Conclusions, Minute 1.)

1. The Secretary of State for Air said that there was no air activity of special importance in report.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

     ------------------------------------------------

The ? Situations. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 67th Conclusions, Minute 2.)

2. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that little of importance had occurred in the previous twenty-four hours. Somewhat confused reports had been received of a British ship having been either attacked or sunk to the eastward of Halifax, Nova Scotia, but the Admiralty were not prepared to accept the reports without further confirmation.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

     ------------------------------------------------

The Military Situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 67th Conclusions, Minute 6.)

3. The Secretary of State for War said that two more Landwehr divisions had been identified in the Saarbrücken area. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff had heard from General Gamelin that the Germans had begun to thin out their troops from the front line, presumably for rest or training in the back areas. The French had followed suit.

The War Cabinet took note of this statement.

     ------------------------------------------------

Staff Conversations with Belgium. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 47th Conclusions, Minute 5.)

4. The Secretary of State for War said that information had been received from the French Military Attaché in London that the Belgian authorities, as the result of apprehension of a German attack, had asked the French what their attitude would be to a Belgian request for Staff Conversations.

The War Cabinet took note of this above statement.

     ------------------------------------------------

Germany Internal situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 67th Conclusions, Minute 15.)

5. The Secretary of State for War said that a report had been received which tended to support the rumoured resignation of General von Branchitsch and his replacement by General von Reichenan. The latter was believed to be persona grata to the Nazi Party.

    ------------------------------------------------

? Despatch of Expeditionary Forces from Australia and New Zealand. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) ?th Conclusions, Minute 6.)

6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, at the Meeting held with the Dominion Ministers the previous day, it had been clear that Australia and New Zealand were most interested in the attitude of Japan, and India in the attitude of Russia.

The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that Australia and New Zealand would require little encouragement to send expeditionary forces overseas in the near future. The announcement that Canada was sending troops over in the near future had obviously had a marked effect. At the outset of the war we had advised Australia and New Zealand not to send troops overseas while Japan&apos;s attitude was uncertain, and they were anxious to know whether we could now reassure them as to Japan&apos;s attitude.

[20259]                                            B 2
In the ensuing discussion, there was general agreement that in view of the great improvement of the situation vis-à-vis not only Japan but also Italy, Australia and New Zealand could surely be given a strong lead to send troops overseas.

The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, while subscribing to this view, thought that it was desirable to obtain an Appreciation of the position from our Ambassador in Tokyo, and also from our Ambassador in Washington as to probable United States attitude in the event of the Japanese sending a raiding expedition against Australia or New Zealand.

The First Lord of the Admiralty thought that it was desirable to impress on the Dominion Ministers the flexible state of our Naval dispositions compared with those of the last war, when, owing to the threat of a strong German Fleet, we had been forced to hold the great bulk of our capital ship strength in Home Waters. At most, Australia and New Zealand had nothing more to fear than a tip-and-run raid, to repel which land forces were not required.

The Prime Minister thought that we should tell the Dominion Ministers the immense importance which we attached to the presence of Dominion troops in France. The effect of their presence on the Western Front on the Empire, on the French, on neutrals and on the Germans would be out of all proportion to the number of troops engaged.

The Chancellor of the Exchequer thought that one of the impalpable influences restraining Japan was the solidarity of the Empire, which would be so clearly demonstrated by the presence of Dominion troops in the European field.

The Secretary of State for War said that he would give the Dominion Ministers the details of our scheme for building up our military strength, and would ask them how soon, and to what extent, they might be prepared to send divisions overseas. It was contemplated that the Dominion formations would be sent overseas for equipment and final training. He understood that the australians were attracted to the idea of carrying out their training in the Middle East.

The War Cabinet--

(1) Invited the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence to tell the Dominion Ministers, at the Meeting later in the day, that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom attached the utmost importance to Dominion troops being sent to Europe in the ensuing months.

(2) Agreed that the Ministers from Australia and New Zealand should be informed that, in view of the improvement in the situation vis-à-vis Japan and Italy, His Majesty&apos;s Government thought that it would now be safe for those Dominions to send troops overseas.

(3) That the Dominion Ministers should also be informed that it was proposed to seek confirmation of this view by obtaining appreciations of the situation vis-à-vis Japan from our Ambassadors at Tokyo and Washington.

(4) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to obtain the appreciations fererred to in ?
? of Information to Germany. Control of communications with Eir and Northern Ireland. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 67th Conclusions, Minute 5.)

7. The Minister without Portfolio informed the War Cabinet that, in accordance with the invitation which they had extended to him at their 66th Meeting, he had assemble a meeting under his Chairmanship, comprising the Secretary of State for War, the Secretary of State for Home Affairs, and the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, to examine the question of the possible leakage of secret, information through Eir. The First Lord of the Admiralty had been good enough to attend the meeting and they had also had the benefit of the presence of the Chief Censor.

The Minister without Portfolio gave a detailed account of the consideration which had been given to this problem by his Committee, and of the conclusions which they had reached.

A record of this account and of the discussion which ensued is given in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.

The War Cabinet agreed :--

1) That the Secretary of State for War should arrange for the existing arrangements for listening-in to all telephone  conversations between Great Britain and Eire to be extended forthwith to telephone conversations between Great Britain and Northern Ireland.

(2)That the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs should approach the High Commissioner for Eire with a view to all cable traffic ex Eire being routed through London, where it should be scrutinised by the British Censorship authorities.

(3) That the Secretary of State for War should arrange for the Illicit Wireless Interception Organisation to supply the necessary apparatus and personnel in Eire for the detection of possible short-wave wireless transmitters in that country.

(4) That, on the evidence so far available, there was no justifi-cation for going beyond the statement that Eire might be presumed to be one of several sources of leakage of information to Germany. It was therefore undesirable at this stage to go to the length of imposing telephone and telegraph censorship on all traffic from Great Britain to the whole of Ireland on the lines of the censorship now imposed on traffic to continental countries, and also the application of a rigorous control of passenger traffic, since this would result in the risk not only of losing the useful co-operation which now existed between the censorship authorities in this country and Eire, but also of arousing considerable criticism and antagonism in this country.

(5) If, however, the arrangements under (1) to (3) above failed to stop the present leakage of information of military dispositions in this country, consideration should be given to the further measures referred to in (4).

(6) That the Admiralty should consider what steps could be taken to prevent the despatch of secret information by means of wireless from neutral ships on leaving ports in this country.

(7)That the Secretary of State for War should arrange for the German broadcasts to be studied by the Security Service, in co-operation with the General Post Office and the Ministry of Information. All statements in those broadcaste which had any bearing on enemy espionage activities in this country should be transcribed and analysed.  This analysis should cover past as well as future broadcasts.

(8) That The Secretary of State for War should submit a Report on the suggestion that extensive prohibited areas should be created in localities where special importance
was attached to keeping secret the presence of movements of Naval and/or Air Forces.

(9) That a very high priority should be given to the manufacturing and manning requirements of the Illicit Wireless Interception Organisation.

(10) To invite the Committee on the Leakage of Information, under the Chairmainship of the Minister without Portfolio, to collate reports on the action taken in accordance with the above conclusions, and to submit a Report to the War Cabinet.

     -------------------------------------------

Proposed War Trade Agreement with Sweden, (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 53rd Conclusions, Minute 9.)

Swedish exports of iron ore to Germany. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 31st Conclusions, Minute 11.)

8. The War Cabinet had before them Memoranda by the Minister for Economic Warfare arising out of his negotiations with the Swedish Mission, Paper W.P. (G)(39) 61, dealing, with Swedish Exports of Iron Ore, and Paper W.P. (G.) (39) 62, setting out a summary of proposals for a War Trade Agreement.

The Minister for Economic Warfare asked the War Cabinet to approve the conclusion of a War Trade Agreement on the lines of the draft set out in his Memorandum. The proposals in regard to Swedish exports of iron ore to Germany were the most important feature of his negotiations with the Swedish Mission. It was clear that the Swedes were willing to be good neutrals, but, out of fear of Germany, they would not run any risk of taking action which the Germans could regard as un-neutral in our favour. We could not get ah agreement more favourable to us than the draft proposed, and the only alternative would be to conclude no agreement, which would be greatly to our disadvantage.

He outlined the proposals set out in his Memorandum and pointed out that under them we should retain all our belligerent rights; that we should deprive Germany of all overseas supplies witin our control and would limit other imports from Sweden to the 1938 level; that we should be interfering with Germany&apos;s plans for expanding her trade with adjacent neutrals (there was evidence that she had in mind in mind to form a trade bloc extending from the Balkans to the Northern countries); and that we should obtain for ourselves imports from Sweden of ferro-alloys, which were of great importance to us for war purposes.

It was clear that the Swedes intended to be extremely helpful on all the practical measures necessary for enforcing the agreement, for instance, by giving us copies of all relevant documents, and enabling our agents to make local enquiries. They were anxious to issue only a general communiqué in regard to the agreement and not to publish its terms, but there was no doubt that its main lines would become known to the other Governments of the Oslo group and it was therefore specially important that it should form a satisfactory precedent. Negotiation for a War Trade Agreement with Germany were being began in Stockholm, but the Swedes had promised not to make any arrangements in this connection which would contravene their draft agreement with us.

In answer to questions, the Minister for Economic Warfare explained that there was no mention of transit trade in the proposed agreement which permitted us to import commodities through Sweden, e.g., far from Baltic countries. The agreement was in certain respects less favourable than that offered us by Italy, because Sweden was in a very strong position through her possession of important ? products outside our control.
abaffy&apos;shipping?to theSent tf&amp;ttltySro-^iifdeaSSt&apos; annum wouldJje-,available.ProbaIt wasi generally agreed that the proposed agreement repre-sented an; extreme negotiations.The War Cabinet accordingly agreed :-(iV to approve the proposal of the Minister for EconomicV WaVfare as set out in his Paper W-P. (G.) (39) 61, toaccept a somewhat indefinite assurance in regard toSwedish exports of iron ore as a necessary.conditionof securing a satisfactory War Trade Agreement;(ii) to approve the conclusion of a War Trade Agreement withthe Swedish Government on the lines proposed by theMinister for Economic Warfare in his paper.P. (G.) (39) 62, it being understood that the con-currence of the French Government would be obtained.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,November 2, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
