<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/160/5 images: 146-154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNICMAJESTY&apos;3 government cp(7I) 140 COPY NO29 November 1971CABINETCONCORDEMemorandum by the Head of the Central policy review StaffI attach a memorandum setting out the views of theCentral Policy Review Staff on the Concorde project.Signed   ROTHSCHILDCabinet Office29 November 1971CONFIDENTIAL
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp (71) 140CABINETCONCORDEMemorandum by the Central Policy Review Staff (CPRS)introduction Concorde is a commercial disaster. It should never have been started. On 30 November, 1971, it had cost the British government an irrecoverable  350 million. If continued, development and production will cost us at least  475 million more ( 392 millionpresent value) from 1971-75. Concorde will make little money forits manufacturers and precious little, if anything, for the airlines whobuy it. The total liability to the United Kingdom alone could be&quot;oinorc than  572 million excluding the written off  350 millionmentioned above.*2 At the moment, the British Government is getting the worst ofboth worlds having to pay up and getting no credit for doing so.3 The decision whether or not to abandon Concorde must start fromwhere we are now much of the milk is already spilt. There are threearguments against cancellation which the CPRS reluctantly regards asconclusive. They are:(a) Given   President   Pompidou&apos;s    personal   commitment,cancellation would have to be precipitated by unilateralBritish withdrawal. This would do great harm to Anglo-French relations and, before 1 January, 1973, mightimperil Ratification. British withdrawal after that datemight seriously hinder co-operation with France.(b) Cancellation in 1972 would destroy 26,000 jobs in theUnited Kingdom, when unemployment and, possibly,redundancy rates will be high. Redeployment may bevery difficult.(c) Now that the public believes Concorde is a spectaculartechnological success, cancellation would be a severe,almost emotional, blow to the average man and womanin the United Kingdom. The CPRS believes this is a realconsideration, if only from the point of view of gettingpeople to work and enjoy it.* Some of the financial figures in this memorandum may, in due course, haveto be revised; but not, we think, to the extent of affecting the Recommendations.
THE &quot; FUNDAMENTAL REVIEW &quot;4 If what is said above is accepted the Government need not andshould not wait until after the &quot; Fundamental Review &quot;, in February,March or, perhaps, April 1972, before publicly making its position clear. There are two reasons for this: first, although more information will be available about Concorde&apos;s performance inFebruary 1972 than in December 1971 there will still be many important questions unanswered. Secondly, the main purpose of the&quot; Fundamental Review &quot; is to enable us to withdraw unilaterally witha minimum risk of the French persuading the International court to award substantial damages against us. In the light of what is said in paragraph 3 this argument is irrelevant.4.1 This is not to say that the next &quot;Fundamental Review&quot; and subsequent analogues are valueless. On the contrary, they providethe venue for policy discussions including bilateral cancellation, if some new blow should make this desirable.WHAT IS THE WORST THAT COULD HAPPEN?5 Apart from possible defects about which nothing is at presentknown, Concorde noise raises the spectre of it being banned from american airports with concomitant repayment of all option money and progress payments, and cancellation of the project. The CPRSdoes not believe such a &quot; sudden death &quot; situation will arise; but if it did, bearing in mind the indemnity clauses which all airlines mayinsist on in their contracts, the loss to the Government would be asshown in the following table:UNITED KINGDOM DEVELOPMENT AND PRODUCTION COSTS,150 CONCORDES  million7972 1973 1974 1975Cancellation on 1 April 35 99 148 193Cumulative    ...... 35 134 282 475Present value of  475 million at 10 per cent discount,  392 million.Calculations from 30th November 1971.the loss on 1 April, 1973, just after Ratification, may seem to be ofspecial interest. But if we cancelled unilaterally, we might haveto pay substantial damages to the French. If the damages amountedto one-third of the total French expenditure on the project (which isconceivable), nothing would be saved by cancelling the project as opposed to continuing it.5.1 A further cost, not taken into account above, because it will benegotiable- at the time, concerns cancellation charges paid to UnitedKingdom contractors which could, by 1975, amount to  40 million.In addition, the unemployment consequences of cancellation might
cost the Exchequer  20 million net in transfer payments, while theresources lost as a result of this unemployment have been valued at about  30 million.WHAT IS MOST LIKELY TO HAPPEN?6 This depends on the number of Concordes sold and at what price.So far as numbers are concerned, the CPRS believes that the british aircraft Corporation^ estimate, which at times has been as high as250, is grossly optimistic. Cooper Brothers suggest that about 160aircraft will be sold at fre million each,  0 - 4 million above the figureindicated to option holders. Cooper Brothers also suggest that after40 aircraft have been sold, the price of the aircraft could be increasedwithout affecting sales, to restore the profit for the manufacturers,though it would be impossible to pay the R. &amp; D. levy. The CPRSfears that the Cooper Brothers estimate of  4^ million per aircraft for a run of 160 may be optimistic; and that the figure may turn out to be nearer  13/rnilTion. Furthermore we have doubts whether 160Concordes will be sold: the number might be nearer 60.6.1 On the basis of the Cooper Brothers estimates and assumptions,the cumulative revenue from the sale of spares might balanceproduction losses by 1990, in undiscounted terms. Discounted at10 per cent, however, there will be a considerable present value loss.6.2 If the Government adopts the line and can get the French toagree that the Concorde selling price must recoup all production costs, contain a levy on R &amp; D, and provide a normal profit, thewhole project will become an even greater commercial disaster thanat present: because no airline would buy Concorde at the price thatthese conditions imply.WHEN WILL CONCORDE GO INTO SERVICE ?7 The manufacturers believe that tests on the first three productionConcordes will be completed by May 1974 with certificationand delivery to airlines in October 1974. The CPRS believes these estimates are optimistic and that delivery will not take place until1975. This is taken into account in the figures given in paragraph 1.WHAT OTHER PROBLEMS ARE THERE?BOAC8  BOAC claims that the inclusion of Concordes in their fleet willaoo involve a &quot; loss&quot; of &amp;5 million from April 1975-April 1980.  the validity of this claim cannot be judged until the time comes, since it rests on the untested extent of Concorde&apos;s passenger appeal.  If
BOAC is right, this loss will have to be met by the Government.The CPRS believes, however, that there is scope for a moreimaginative marketing approach to Concorde on the part of BOAC,based on an incentive scheme. We hope to revert to this matter indue course. But apart from any incentive scheme, the CPRS hopes that those concerned will insist on attention being paid to specialConcorde passenger amenities* so that the message &quot; EveryConcorde passenger is a VIP in a hurry&quot; comes through loudand clear.NOISE8.1 We have referred to the noise problem in paragraph 5. It isnot certain that Concorde will conform with Heathrow or KennedyAirport noise limits without jeopardising some other essential flyingcharacteristic such as range. Nevertheless the very low frequencywith which it will land and take off suggests that Concorde mayget away with its noise. Purchase of Concordes on advantageous terms by an American airline might help to ease the noise problem at Kennedy Airport and elsewhere in the United States.SAFETY8.2 The CPRS has made a careful study of Concorde&apos;s safety and,within the limits of the information available, is satisfied with onereservation the ability to ditch Concorde in the sea without killingall the passengers. Since this is a requirement of the British, Frenchand American Aviation Authorities, it is, needless to say, under activestudy.POLLUTION8.3 Black smoke on landing and take off will not present anyproblems in production models; nor will ozone in the stratospherepoison the crew or passengers. Galactic radiation will be no more of a hazard, and probably less, than it is to subsonic aircraft. the cprs commissioned a special study which showed that Concordewill not fry people on earth by interfering with the protective ozonelayer in the stratosphere, as claimed by an American professor. Butpollution charges, however unjustified, will damage Concorde&apos;sprospects and a campaign of public reassurance on environmentalissues is essential. The International Congress on the Environment,at Stockholm in 1972, would be an excellent occasion to start theball rolling.* Some obvious examples are: Concorde Superbuses, with Customs, immigration,refreshment and anti-bomb/hijacking arrangements on board, direct from central london to the aircraft; more passengers instead of ovens to heat up pre-cookedduck, beef, etc. (caviare and other sandwiches instead); air-ground radio service for passengers; Concorde lounge, with Customs and free drinks for arrivingpassengers; free Concorde ties, sample attached, for each passenger; speciallyselected stewardesses; and a free ticket for every 200th (?) passenger.
ORDERING PATTERN8.4 BOAC and Air France will probably place their orders in mid-1972 and Air France will do so first unless Ministers commit themselves whole-heartedly to the project. The CPRS believes that air France should not be allowed to beat BOAC to it. A possible and very troublesome situation would arise if about 35 Concordeswere ordered between mid-1972 and end-1973, and there were thenan ordering gap. It is very difficult to envisage a contingency plan to take account of this eventuality, but it is obvious that we shouldminimise the manufacture of Concordes and their rate ofmanufacture, to the extent that this is compatible with maintaining the labour force at its present level and not an increased one. this implies that authority to manufacture must to a certain extent be tied to orders received.STRETCHING9 This refers to improving Concorde, over the years, to the limit of its technical capacity. The decision to go ahead is not a formalcommitment to stretch Concorde. But it would be prudent to regard it as a decision to stay in the supersonic business. If the historyof subsonic jets is any guide, Concorde may be more readily soldif the airlines are confident that it will in due course be followed byimproved versions. The cost of stretching is very uncertain, as is theextent to which it could be offset by price increases. But there wouldcertainly be a large bill, running into hundreds of millions of pounds,for the Governments to pick up. The undesirability of trying to put the Stretch question under the carpet is well illustrated by thefollowing telegram from Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Paris(22.10.1971):&quot; When I saw M. Pompidou yesterday, he said he thoughtthat Concorde would sell all right, but at a loss. ThoughConcorde &apos; Mark I&apos; would turn out to be an expensiveoperation, he had great hopes that in due course a biggerand quieter &apos; Mark II&apos; would scoop the market.&quot;M. Pompidou is not, we believe, aware of the vast expenditureimplied by his remarks.MANAGEMENT STRUCTURE OF the concorde PROJECT10 The chains of command have presumably been designed to meetthe needs of Parliamentary accountability and the need for Anglo-French parity (see Annex A). From the point of view of commercialefficiency they are a nightmare and a farcical one at that. Anycompetent businessman could re-cast the organogram in Annex Ato make it sensible. So a new look is necessary.
&quot; TECHNOLOGICAL FALL-OUT &quot;11 The CPRS does not believe that projects of this magnitudecan be justified, even in part, on such grounds; and it would be wise to avoid the technological fall-out argument in any promotionalactivities.RECOMMENDATIONS(a) The Government should commit itself whole-heartedly andpublicly to Concorde, with a professionally run sales and publicity campaign. Diplomatic and all other means available should be used and action should not be deferred until after the &quot; FundamentalReview &quot; in 1972.(b) Keep the number of Concordes manufactured and their rate ofmanufacture at the minimum compatible with maintaining the labour force at its present level. Manufacture to be tied, so far as possible,to orders received.(c) Concorde should be sold at a subsidised price, at any rate initially.(d) Incentive scheme to be imposed on BOAC.(e) Special study to be made of passenger amenities for Concordepassengers.(/) Study possibility of selling Concorde to an American airline onadvantageous terms as an insurance against noise problems in theUnited States.(g) Paper on Concorde, with particular reference to absence of pollution, at International Congress on the Environment, at stockholm in 1972.(h) Ensure that BOAC does not order Concordes later than AirFrance.(i) Concorde management structure to be revised.APPROXIMATE RESOURCE ALLOCATIONOne 2,000 megawatt nuclear power stationChannel TunnelMaintaining BAOR for two years100,000 houses200 multi-role combat aircraft
Annex AORGANISATION OF THE CONCORDE PROJECT(showing levels at which communications are made)(1) (2)The FirmsCorporate DirectoratesUnited Kingdom and French MinistersRolls-Royce/SNECMABAC/SNIASCommittee of DirectorsSecretary of State for Trade and Industryand Minister for Aerospace;with french Minister of TransportProject Management -Concorde Directing CommitteeUnited Kingdom	FranceVice-Chairman	ChairmanDirectors for:	DirectorsTechnical	for:Production	TechnicalCommercial	Production	CommercialJointly carried outbyM. Ziegler (SNIAS)andMr. G. Knight (BAC)United Kingdom	FranceDeputy	secretary	Aerospace	Director of AirController of   ^	transport aircraft	systems	(MOD/PE)	Project directorDirector-	General	STAEHer Majesty&apos;s	(technicalTreasury	director)	Director of	Aero-	Construction	Minister of	FinanceProgramme Directorate-Programme Directorate-Concorde Management BoardcomprisingProject directors of Rolls-Royceand SNECMAcomprising the project directors of BAC and SNIASUnited Kingdom FranceDirector-General Project directorDirector STAe represen-Assistant Secretary tativesCESOJoint ProjectEngine product supportcompany acting jointlyfor Rolls-Royce andSNECMASpecialist Working GroupsDirectorate drawn from BAC and SNIAS 1			Technical Production Commercial Contracts Flight tests After sales		Technical Commercial							


</content>
</cab>
