<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/39/0 images: 26-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT  IS   THE   PROPERTY OF  HIS  BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENT   j printed for the Cabinet.   March 1950SECRETCopy No. 32CP. (50) 55dOth. March, 1950CABINETECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT IN THE MIDDLE east memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate herewith for the information of my colleagues a report on recenteconomic and social development in the Middle East.As shown in the paper on Middle East policy (OP. (49) 183) which I circulated on 25th August, 1949, one of the main threats to the Middle East,which in peace and war is an area of cardinal importance to the United Kingdom,is the danger of disintegration due to the backwardness of many Middle Eastcountries and the opportunities thereby provided for Communist penetration.We have therefore sought to encourage and assist Middle East Governments tobring about improved social and economic conditions. A Development division was formed for this purpose in the British Middle East Office, which was set upin 1945. The experts attached to the Division have played an important partin preparing the way for economic and social development in the area.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,28th March, 1950.38501b
ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT IN THE MIDDLE EAST1949SUMMARYFrom the end of the war until the beginning of 19-19, progress was slow,mainly for political reasons, but partly also owing to the need for basic surveywork. During 1949 conditions became much more propitious and a real advancebecame possible.2. The Middle East (Official) Committee was reconstituted in March, andthe possibilities of economic and social development throughout the area werecarefully examined, The Committee&apos;s interim report, recommending a basis for action, was approved by the Economic Policy Committee of the Cabinet, and was subsequently discussed in Washington with the State Department and theInternational Bank, who expressed their general agreement.3. In the autumn, the United Nations Economic Survey Mission for theMiddle East visited the area and, as a result of its interim report, the general assembly approved the inauguration of a programme of works relief projects and set up a new Agency (the Near East Relief and Works Agency) to carry out this programme as well as to administer direct relief to Palestine Refugees for alimited period. The Survey Missiohs final report recommended that, in additionto the works relief projects, an immediate start should be made with 4 &quot; pilotdemonstration projects&quot; in Syria, Lebanon, Jordan and Arab Palestine.4. Meanwhile, considerable progress took place in individual countries. in persia, the American consortium Overseas Consultants Incorporated completed their final report on the Seven-Year Development Plan, and a special PlanningOrganisation was set up to carry it out. In Iraq the British Irrigation Develop-ment Commission completed its survey of the country&apos;s long-term needs and two major flood-control projects were put in hand. Our loan of  1 million to Jordanfor development projects (work on which has now started&apos;) gave the impetusnecessary for the establishment of the Economic Survey Mission, the effect of whose work is not confined to Jordan but extends to Syria and Lebanon and even to the Middle East as a whole. As regards the Nile Water Projects, preliminary work on the Owen Falls scheme has begun. In Egypt itself work has continued on the Aswan Dam Electrification Project. Considerable capital development,unfortunately not in every case wise, has taken place in Saudi Arabia.5. In general, during 1949, the first stage of development that of prepara-tory surveys was largely completed and the second and third stages those of detailed surveys and of the actual execution of projects were reached. To meetthe needs of these stages, provision was made during the year for investment iromexternal sources in Middle East development on a substantial scale. We arrangeda railway loan of  3 millions to Iraq and the International Bank have agreed to open negotiations with Iraq for a loan of $8-4 millions for flood control andirrigation projects. We invested  1 million in development works in the Jordan.The Seven-Year Plan in Persia is at present being financed out of British oilroyalties, and expenditure for 1949 is likely to have amounted to some  17 millions.The Near East Relief and Works Agency will, under its budget, spend $34-7millions ( 12-3 millions including our loan to Jordan) on relief works. Finally,it has been estimated that under the American and United Nations technical assistance programmes, which were initiated during the year, between $6 and $10millions may become available for technical assistance to the Middle East in1950-51.6. These developments are reflected in the volume of British exports to theMiddle East which increased from  20-5 millions in 1938 to  74-5 millions in1946, to  113 millions in 1948 and  126-5 millions in 1949. It is estimated thatallowing for the post-war rise in prices this represents a threefold increase.7. The outstanding development during the year has been the commitment of the United States to play a direct and an important part in the developmentof the area, through their participation in the solution of the Arab refugee
problem, and through the &quot;Fourth Point&quot; programme. The specialised agencies of the United Nations and the International Bank have also played an increasing part in the development of the area. ;8. Our own contribution in initiative and impulsion and also in technical assistance (in particular through the British Middle East office) has been great.Even in the field of finance it has been considerable, in spite of our economic difficulties, and it is hoped that our further participation in economic and socialdevelopment, e.g., in the programme of. relief and works to be executed by the newAgency, will be the maximum which our resources will allow. Only in this waywill our part in the economic development of the Middle East be commensurate with our position in the area and not fall unduly short of American efforts.T. E. EVANS.I.-GENERALFrom the end of the war until the beginning of 1949, progress in the field ofeconomic and social development in the Middle East was slow. This was due,first, to the unsettled political situation in the area, culminating in the Palestinewar, and, secondly, to the necessity for carrying out the necessary preliminarysurvey work to serve as a basis for the subsequent preparation of detailed plans.Between 1946 and 1948 surveys were undertaken, for example, by the DevelopmentDivision of the British Middle East Office in most Middle East countries; by theBritish Irrigation Commission in Iraq; by Sir Alexander Gibb and Partners in syria and the Lebanon; and by an American consortium Overseas ConsultantsIncorporated in Persia.2. During the first months of 1949 the atmosphere began to change. Withthe end of the Palestine war and the growing menace of social unrest within andof Communist pressure from without, individual Middle East Governments were beginning to devote greater attention to the problems of economic and socialdevelopment and to accept more readily outside assistance. At the same time theUnited States Government and the United Nations and its Agencies showedthemselves increasingly prepared to assist in the development of the area. Agreat impetus to press ahead with development was given by the plight of the-800,000 Palestinian refugees, of whom a very large proportion will have to beresettled outside Israel. Finally, with the completion of the initial surveysreferred to above, the second stage of development that of detailed surveys ofparticular projects-and the third that of the actual execution of projects was reached, in some countries. In these circumstances it was possible for sub-stantial progress to be made during 1949, and despite our own economic difficultieswe were able to play a considerable part in promoting this progress.3. In order to enable us to meet the demands of this new situation, theMiddle East (Official) Committee, which had been set up in December 1945 but had remained largely inactive, was reconstituted in March 1949, under the chair-manship of Mr. M. R. Wright, Foreign Office, as one of four regional com-mittees reporting to the Official Committee on Economic Development (Overseas).During the ensuing months a detailed examination of development plans andpossibilities in each Middle East country was put in hand, and on 8th november the Economic Policy Committee of the Cabinet approved the Committee&apos;s interimreport, which recommended that His Majesty&apos;s Government should encourage and assist a number of particular projects in the area. In the same month, Mr. Wrightand Mr. T. E. Evans (Head of the Middle East Secretariat, Foreign Office), visitedWashington for informal discussions with the State Department and the Inter-national Bank. Both the Department and the Bank expressed their desire to makea positive contribution to the economic development of the Middle East and their general agreement with the programme outlined in the interim report. The state department pointed out, however, that at the present stage of United States policy the&quot; United States Governments ability to give direct economic assistance to theMiddle East was confined to the &quot; Fourth Point &quot; programme, which providedfor technical assistance only and would not involve the supply of capital from government sources for the financing of development, and to the implementation38501 b 2
of the recommendations of the United Nations Economic Survey Mission forprojects which wOuld provide work relief for the Arab refugees (see paragraph 4below).4. Meanwhile, the State Department and we had since the spring been examining in close consultation the urgent and difficult problem of the future ofthe Arab refugees. In August, at our joint instigation, a United NationsEconomic Survey Mission was appointed &quot; to examine the economic situation inthe countries affected by the recent hostilities &quot; and in particular &quot; to facilitate the repatriation and resettlement of the Arab refugees.&quot; Experts from theBritish Middle East Office played an important part in the work of the Mission indeed, without their experience and knowledge its task could not have beencompleted in the comparatively short space of four months.5. The Mission recommended that direct relief should be supplemented,and gradually superseded, by a programme of relief works in Jordan, ArabPalestine, Syria and Lebanon covering terracing, afforestation, road development and minor irrigation works which would be of benefit to their long-term develop-ment generally. On 8th December the recommendations of the Mission were approved by the General Assembly and a &quot; United Nations Relief and WorksAgency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East &quot; established. The total costof the programme was estimated at $54-9 millions ( 19-7 millions), of which.$34-7 millions ( 12-3 millions) was required for works relief and $20-2 millions( 7-2 millions) for direct relief.8. The Economic Survey Mission&apos;s final report was published on 28th Decem-ber. In this report the Mission emphasised the importance of a cautious approach to Middle East development and urged that sound progress could only be achieved through the development of indigenous resources by improved methods of pro-duction and through the acquisition by the Middle East Governments andnationals themselves of essential training and experiene. It was recommendedthat each Middle East Government should establish a National development board, and that, in addition to the Relief Works Programme provided for underthe General Assembly Resolution of 8th December, four &quot; Pilot DemonstrationProjects &quot; should be put in hand at once, in the Lebanon (Survey of the LitaniRiver basin), Syria (reclamation of the Ghab swamps), and Arab Palestine andJordan (unified development of the basins of the Wadis Qilt and Zerka). funds to begin the two latter projects should be made available by the new Agency andthe remainder of the cost of all the projects should be borne by the Governmentsconcerned with, if necessary, help from the international community or individualfriendly Governments. The total cost to the Governments is estimated at  6-millions, and the development of the Litani basin, which is expected to be put inhand when the Survey has been completed, may amount to  10 millions.7. We had since November been in close consultation with the State Depart-ment regarding the application to the Middle East of the &quot; Fourth Point,&quot;technical assistance programme and the United Nations expanded programme of technical assistance to undeveloped areas, both of which are expected to comeinto operation in the course of this year. It has been estimated that under these programmes between $6 and $10 millions may become available in the first year for the Arab countries for the provision of expert advisers (including firms ofconsultants), research workers, technical equipment (other than capital equip-ment) and training and educational facilities abroad. It is essential that these programmes should supplement and not supplant our own contribution to thetechnical development of the area; the State Department are in agreement with us that the Middle East can absorb all the technical assistance that is likely tobe available to it from every source. We consider that our effective contributionwill lie, first, in the services of the Development Division of the British middle east Office, which the State Department do not intend to duplicate, and theexpansion of which we are now considering; and secondly, in filling quickly the150 or so vacancies which at present exist for British experts under the middle east Governments. At present great difficulty is being experienced in findingcandidates for these posts. It is considered that this difficulty can be resolvedpartly by arranging secondment from Government departments, universities andother institutions-this is now being explored with the authorities concerned-and partly by supplementing the salaries offered in certain cases-and theTreasury nave now agreed in principle to this.      &apos; r       &apos;
8. During 1949 there was an increase in British exports to the Middle East.The total value of our exports to the area (including Persia and the italian colonies), which amounted in 1938 to  20 - 5 millions and in 1948 to  113 millions,reached the figure of  126-5 millions in 1949. (Allowing for the post-war risein prices this represents roughly a three-fold increase since before the war.) Alarge proportion of the increase shown during the year was accounted for by oil company equipment. Apart from this, the significant expansion has been in Iraq,where British contractors have obtained orders for a number of important develop-ment schemes. In Egypt, owing to the Companies Law and the difficultiesgenerally placed in the way of British firms by the Egyptian Government, no progress was made in obtaining contracts for capital projects and our commercialposition in fact deteriorated during the year. Our exports to Persia remainedsteady during the year and there are considerable prospects of expansion ascontracts come forward under the seven-year plan. During the coming year thereare likely to be increased opportunities for British trade in connexion with the projects described in this paper, but at the same time increased competition fromthe United States must be expected when the provisions of the &apos;&apos; Fourth Point&apos;&apos;programme for encouraging American private investment, and providing largenumbers of American technicians, come into force in the Middle East.II.-INDIVIDUAL  COUNTRIES(a) IraqThe British Irrigation Development Commission, which was appointed in1946 by the Iraq Government, completed its survey of long-term irrigation develop-ment plans for the country in the summer of 1949. It recommended a programmeof works for the next half-century which, at a total estimated cost of  88 millions( 2 millions per annum) could add about 9 million acres to the country&apos;s existingirrigation area of 8 million acres, and ensure complete flood control of the Tigrisand Euphrates. Meanwhile, two major projects for flood control and water storagein this programme were already put in hand : works for the Euphrates at LakeHabbiniyah were undertaken by the British firm Balfour Beatty, at a cost of- 2 millions; and the British consulting engineers to the Iraq Government werecommissioned to prepare detailed specifications for the first stage of major works for the Tigris in the Wadi Tharthar depression, estimated to cost  7 millions.The Iraq Government also established contact with the International Bank for a loan of f8-4 millions for these works.Progress in railway development schemes was also made in Iraq during thepast year, and to cover the expenditure on these schemes His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment arranged a loan of  3 millions to the Iraq Government through the ExportCredit Guarantee Department.Acting on our advice and on that of the International Bank, the IraqGovernment prepared legislation to set up a Central Development Board, towhich it is hoped that a British Secretary will be attached.(b) EgyptOne of the most important events in the economic development of Egypt sincethe war was the exchange of notes which took place in Cairo on 30th and 31stMay, in which His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Egyptian Government agreed&quot;in accordance with the spirit of the Nile Waters Agreement of 1929, to theconstruction of a dam at Owen Falls in Uganda for the production of hydro-electric power and for the control of the waters of the Nile.&quot; The egyptian government, in a separate note, also placed on record the Egyptian PrimeMinisters declaration, made on 19th May, that the Egyptian Government would&quot; welcome the participation of the Sudan in the projects for the control of theNile which are now under consideration.&quot;Since then, with the approval of both Governments, contracts have been placed by the Uganda Electricity Board for the construction of the dam, preliminary work has already begun at Owen Falls, and it is hoped that the foundation-stonewill be formally laid in the course of the summer of 1950. Notes have still to be exchanged regarding the assessment of the compensation (between  3 and  4millions) to be paid by the Egyptian Government for damage to lakeside interests
caused by the heightening of the dam. The precise wording of these notes is still under consideration by the Egyptian Government and the East AfricanLegislatures. It has, however, already been agreed that in any case Sir AlexanderGibb and Partners should be nominated as the assessors.Since the conclusion of the Owen Falls Agreement His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment have applied constant pressure in an effort to have negotiations opened,with the participation of Sudan technicians, regarding the Lake Tana Project.This endeavour has not yet succeeded, largely as the result of the egyptian government^ insistence on treating the question of the Sudan&apos;s participation inthe proposed negotiations as a political issue.Preliminary work continues on the Aswan Electrification Project, and manycontracts have already been placed by the Egyptian Government. The future ofthe project is, however, still obscure. The placing of the valuable civil engineeringcontracts has twice been postponed (on the second occasion until May 1950), andthe new Egyptian Minister of Public Works is believed to be contemplating a radical revision of the project, in order to reduce its cost, which is at present estimated at  18 millions, and which already greatly exceeds the estimateoriginally made by the Commission set up after the war.(c) PersiaIn May 1949 the Persian Government established a planning organisation to administer the 21,000 million rials ( 240 millions) seven-year plan of economicand social development. Overseas Consultants Incorporated (O.C.I.), an Americanconsortium of firms with which the British firm, Sir Alexander Gibb and Partners,is closely associated, submitted to the Persian Government detailed recommenda-tions for the implementation of the plan. Subsequently, the O.C.I. signed a contract with the plan organisation providing that it should act as consultants tothe organisation for the execution of the plan. The O.C.I. are providingtwelve resident expert advisers, and additional technicians are being appointedby the Persian Government to executive posts in the planning organisation. Thesealready include four senior British experts the first to be employed in Persiasince the war.Apart from the reorganisation of government-owned concerns and theprovision of financial assistance, mainly in the form of additional capital, tocertain Government and private enterprises, the work of the organisation duringthe current financial year has been confined to the execution of certain high priority projects, including the extension of the railway system to Tabriz andMeshed and the ploughing of the Moghan Steppe in Azerbaijan. The totalexpenditure for the year is likely to amount to some 1,600 million rials (about 17 millions).Under the seven-year plan law of February 1949, the work of the planorganisation is to be financed from Anglo-Iranian Oil Company royalties. Inaddition the Persian Government hope to obtain assistance from the international bank, to which they have already applied for a credit of $45 millions.(d) JordanIn March 1949 we decided that it was necessary that we should give some financial assistance to the Government of Jordan in order to ensure the economic stability of Jordan and Arab Palestine, and that this assistance should take theform of an interest-free loan of  1 million for development projects which wouldalso provide for resettlement of as many Arab refugees as possible.. A list&quot; of projects, comprising construction of roads and of houses for refugees and certainagricultural research and experimental schemes, mainly in the Jordan valley,was drawn up in the autumn, in consultation with the Economic Survey Mission(since it was considered important that these projects should dove-tail into theCommission^ works relief schemes) and work has now started on them. At ourinstigation the Jordan Government set up a Central Development Board with one British official on it to co-ordinate and supervise the execution of the projects.On our advice, the Jordan Government, in the summer of 1949, engaged the Britishfirm of Sir M. MacDonald and Partners to survey the Jordan Valley and toprepare plans for the development of its irrigation possibilities. The report,which will shortly be available, will be of great value to the Jordan Governmentin connexion with eventual negotiations with Israel on the utilisation of Jordan
waters. Israel&apos;s own plans, or at least the grandiose Hays-Savage Project for&quot; T.V.A. on the Jordan,&apos;&apos; take only the barest account of Jordan&apos;s needs.During the year an Italian-Jordan Company was formed with ourencouragement for the exploitation of Jordan&apos;s extensive phosphate deposits.Production and export on any significant scale will not, however, be possible untiltransport facilities through Haifa are available.The problems of communications and the development Qf the port of Aqabahave also been studied.(e) SyriaWorks relief projects on which refugee labour will, it is hoped, be employed,cover rcadmaking, swamp drainage, aerodrome and port construction, reafforesta-tion and terracing and the excavation work connected with the Aleppo watersupply project (which involves bringing water from the River Euphrates over a distance of some 50 miles). The pilot demonstration project recommended by theEconomic Survey Mission involves the unified development of the Ghab plainin the Orontes Valley, and includes drainage, irrigation and the developmentof hydro-electric power at a cost of between  5 and  6 millions.Work on the specifications for the important Aleppo water supply project,which will cost about  3 millions, continued during 1949. Much progress wasalso made on the modernisation and expansion of the country&apos;s telephone system;the new automatic exchange in Damascus has been inaugurated.(/) LebanonWorks relief projects envisaged for the Lebanon are concerned with irrigation.The pilot demonstration project recommended for the Lebanon is the survey, witha view to unified development, of the Litani Valley. The survey, which willtake one year, will cover flood control, drainage, irrigation, soil conservation andutilisation and the development of hydro-electric- power. The execution of the project once the survey is completed will probably cost  10 millions.In the course of 1949, progress was made on the South Lebanon irrigationscheme and on the construction of the new Beirut (Khalde) aerodrome. Theirrigation scheme, which utilises the waters of the Litani, was begun in 1945under British military auspices and the main tunnel was bored by engineers ofthe South African Forces. It will permit the perennial cultivation of an area of12,500 acres of the coastal plain, along which the main canal extends for a distance of 40 miles.The newly extended oil refinery at Tripoli, which is intended to cater for thepresent needs of the Lebanon and Syria, has been opened.Tenders for the Beirut and Tripoli automatic telephone exchanges have beensubmitted.The Lebanese Government has announced that credits amounting to 10 millions will be devoted to a six-year development plan covering irrigationand water supplies, agriculture, public health, education, &amp;c.(g) Saudi ArabiaDuring 1949 the Saudi Arabian Government continued to press ahead witha number of capital development schemes road and railway construction, electrical -fication, telephone installations, port and airport development, &amp;c. some of themsound and some of them, such as the half-finished railway from Damman toRiyadh, of doubtful economic value. Several large contracts have been awardedto American firms, but a substantial number of smaller contracts have also been awarded to British firms.Saudi Arabia is now earning about  35 millions per annum in foreign exchangefrom her oil royalties and pilgrim traffic. Excessive expenditure on the capital development schemes (which are at present absorbing about  10 million of foreign exchange a year), combined with the personal extravagance of the Royal court and administrative corruption, reduced the country, by the end of 1949, to a stateof bankruptcy.Nevertheless, there were some signs during the year of a more realistic out lookand of a desire to promote social as well as development projects.   Two senior
British health experts were appointed to reorganise the quarantine administration,and their recommendations for improving the country&apos;s health services generally are likely, to be accepted; A Directorate of Agriculture has been set up and hasmade a promising start.(A) Persian GulfThe formation of a British Company (with local participation) for thedevelopment of the rich South-Arabian fisheries is being actively pursued withthe Muscat authorities. Close attention has been given to the problem of inducingthe rulers of the oil producing States-Bahrein, Kuwait and Qatar to spendtheir oil revenues on sound development projects, and to invest their surpluses insuch a way that they could be used for the development of other areas in theMiddle East.



</content>
</cab>
