<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/39/0 images: 68-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
y      o 9jjIS DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY*S   GOVERNMENT H1   *    i; &apos;       Printed for the Cabinet.-: vA^pril 1950SECRET   . &quot;...  ;&apos;\&apos;jbopy;;No.32CP. (50) 591st April, 1950CABINET&apos;points rationing : &quot; \:Memorandum by the Minister of food the Points Rationing Scheme has become a matter on which i feel it essential to secure the judgment and views of my colleagues in the light of our general social and economic policies. 12. For reasons which i shall give, i have myself, after thorough examination,reached, the conclusion that on balance we must bring the scheme to an endforthwith.  i can suggest no convincing alternative. i A,.3. Many foods have been taken out of the scheme Over the last two years,and several of those that remain are now so plentiful that we shall soon not onlybe able to deration them, but will be compelled to do so, if we are to avoid a growing clamOur of complaint about goods piling up on the grocers&apos; shelves, whichconsumers want, but cannot get because they have not enough points. Unless wedo something soon about this, we shall face a series of quite serious scandals.;:4. We could, of course, take these goods out of the scheme altogether. Butif we do, we shall be running an expensive State rationing machine and involving the distributive traders in complicated and expensive work for the purpose merely of rationing, by points, a small range of goods. We should have to reduce thenumber of points quite drastically and thus, by so doing, practically destroy thewhole virtue of the idea, which lay in a comprehensive range of choice.5. To reduce the scheme to a point where it would cover only a small range of goods, and a small number of points for each consumer, while retaining, as wemust, the whole apparatus of points rationing, wouid, in my judgment, bring; thewhole idea of rationing into serious and unanswerable disrepute. &apos;6. Despite the risks, therefore, I am myself satisfied that it is more prudent to do away with the scheme altogether without further delay, The risks ofpublic disquiet about attractive and much-needed goods accumulating, as theyare, on the shelves of every grocer&apos;s shop are, i am convinced, much greater thahthe risks of some unsatisfied demand tor certain categories of goods. At leasti am, myself, more ready to answer those complaints than those which i knoware On the point of bursting out because of the frustration aroused by seeing goodson the shelves when the points quota has been spent. .7.   The commodities at present within the scheme fall into three groups :-(a) canned beans, canned milk, shredded suet, canned meat;(b) rice, syrup and treacle, sweet biscuits, table jellies;(c) canned fish, dried fruit, canned fruit, mincemeat, &quot; ,8. The items in group (a) are now plentiful and apart from some varietiesof canned meat we have no choice about their release before the next rationingperiod, for stocks will pile up in the shops if they remain on points. Those ingroup (b) are not yet plentiful enough to give certainty that demand can be metfully at current prices, but if there are shortages they are quite small. By38511
2contrast, the commodities in group (c) are scarce and must remain so for sometime to come. It is this latter group which will cause our most awkward problemif we abandon the scheme.f&quot; ;i; 9- But I must tell my colleagues that I will not worry unduly about this if could have the assistance of the Treasury with dollars to get some extra sugarfor making sweet biscuits and table jellies.10. 9,000 tons, or 970,000 dollars&apos; worth, would, I think, go a long way tomeet the immediate demand for these foods if they become unrationed. &quot;-.11. And, given that range of points goods in adequate supply, I feel satisfiedthat we could handle the situation, despite some shortages of certain goods, in sucha way as to avoid a repetition of our experience with the derationing of sweets.12. I recognise the possible objection to this proposal. It is an abandonment of a scheme which the public accept as a safeguard against individuals andcaterers obtaining more than a fair share of scarce foods. It is certainly truethat a release of this kind could be understood as a move in favour of those withthe larger purse, and it is also true that some goods will, for a time, not be readilyobtainable. On the other hand, of course, the scheme has never assured a supplyof any particular food to every housewife.; . 13. These are all weighty objections, not lightly to be dismissed. But wehave a problem here, not of abundance, but of the existence of stocks which justcannot be taken up if the limiting factor is the number of points.: 14. I suggest to my colleagues that we must face this problem in a spiritof realism. If we do, I am sure we will be convinced that the balance of argumentis on the side of ending the scheme.15. I think myself that the removal of the irritation, annoyance and frus-tration caused to every housewife of every class, by both the inadequacy of herpoints and the complicated business of spending them in the best way, is a socialgain which far outweighs the irritation which might arise from the transitionalshortages and other disadvantages I have mentioned.M 16. We must also consider the advantages of bringing to an end themachinery of administration which points rationing requires. We should savemore than 1,000 Ministry of Food staff, and, what is even more important, a vastamount of unproductive clerical work for both wholesalers and retailers. Wewould find it difficult convincingly to argue that this machinery should be kept in existence merely to ration by points the few remaining goods which are not yetfreely available.17. It is proposed, of course, to retain the Unit Voucher System through which we secure the fair distribution to retailers of canned fish, canned fruit anddried fruit according to the number of their registered customers. For the rest,the consumption of syrup by trade users will still be controlled by permit, to secureretailers supplies. This, in effect, would retain &quot; points rationing &quot; on a whole-sale basis, leaving the retailer to share out the scarcer goods to his customers. Ifit is argued that this is &apos;&apos; under the counter &apos;&apos; distribution, one can only reply that it is happening now anyway with all the scarce points goods, and will cometo an end as quickly as we build up, by extra sugar, &amp;c, adequate supplies.18. For all these reasons, therefore, I feel it my duty to ask my colleagues to approve the end of points rationing, the announcement to be made on Thursday,20th April, and the scheme to end on Sunday, 23rd April.M. W.Ministry of Food, S.W. 1,1st April, 1950.     : ;



</content>
</cab>
