<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/39/0 images: 340-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(jlIS DOCU-ME&amp;T IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; SGOVERNMENT)secret.P. (50) 90 COPY NO.29TH APRIL,  1950CABINETLICENCES FOR THE ERECTION OF NEW HOUSESMemorandum by the Minister of health in accordance with the Cabinet&apos;s decisionof 1?th April (CM. (50) 21st Conclusions, Minute 2(2)),I submit for the approval of my colleagues a draft ofthe statement on the erection of houses under licencewhich I propose to make in the House in reply to anarranged Question.2. The statement relates to England and Walesonly.      The Secretary of State for Scotland, whom Ihave consulted, feels that since he made his announce-rnent on the proposition that private building should be permitted to the extent of one in ten as recently as28th March it is still too early for hirn to reconsider the position.A. B.Ministry of Health, S. W. 1 ,29TH APRIL,  1&apos;950.

To ask the Minister of Health whether he has any statement to make on the erection of houses under licence in the light of thedecision of the Government to remove the cut in the housing programme.Yes,, Sir.      The Government have considered the provision which ought to be made in the programme for houses to be built bythe local authorities for letting and for houses to be built for owner occupiers under licence.     Experience has shown that in very many districts the claims of those lit the most urgent need of housesmake it necessary that at least nine-tenths of the houses builtshould be Council houses.      In other districts, however, those inthe most urgent need of homes may include a greater proportion ofpersons who wish to build a house for their own occupation.      each authority should, consider for itself the numbers and needs of thetwo types of applicant.       In order to enable each Council to take account.of the circumstances of its district the Government havedecided to restore to housing authorities the discretion to issuelicences up to a maximum of one-fifth of their allocation wherethey ore satisfied that this is justified by the needs of the applicants.      I am prepared to consider exceptionally applications from local authorities for permission to exceed the figure of one-fifth where I am satisfied that this course is necessary in thelight of the evidence as to the proportionate numbers and needs ofthe applicants for Council houses, and of the applicants for licences.It sometimes happens that an applicant living in one dis-trict desires to move to another district and to build a housethere for his own occupation:    by this means a better distributionof housing may be brought about by the release of the house inwhich he at present lives.      I am ready to authorise arrangementsfor making licences mobile,  and to agree in such cases that a licence can be issued by the authority in whose area the house isto be built on the understanding that the licence will be chargeableagainst the quota of the authority for the district in which theapplicant at present lives.      A circular is being issued to localauthorities and a copy will be placed in the Library.


</content>
</cab>
