<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/39/0 images: 414-416</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET copy No: 3 2CP. (50) 10010*A May, 1950.CABINETINCREASE IN RATES OF NATIONAL INSURANCE CONTRIBUTIONSMemorandum by the Minister of National Insurance1. Under the National Insurance Act, 1946, the current rates of contribu-tions payable by insured persons and employers are due to be increased as from monday, 1st October, 1951.2. The increase is 4rf. for men and women over age 18, and 2d. for boys and girls below that age. Generally, employed persons (Class 1) will pay half theincrease and their employers will pay the other half. The self-employed and non-employed (Classes 2 and 3) will, of course, have to pay the whole increase them-selves. The principal rates of contributions now in force and those which will come into force on 1st October, 1951, are set out in Appendix I to thismemorandum.3. The object of providing for the increased rates of contributions is to relieve the Exchequer of some part of the heavy increase in expenditure on national insurance benefits in future years, due almost entirely to the growth inthe cost of retirement pensions. Details of the growth in the number of pensioners and in the cost over the next 30 years are given in Appendix II. It is noteworthythat although the special increases in contributions would bring in increasedincome for a time, the Government Actuary estimates that the contribution incomeby 1978 will be no more than it was at the beginning of the scheme, mainly as aresult of the rising proportion of pensioners in the population.4. The rates of contribution in force at any time are printed on all national insurance cards, and it will accordingly be necessary to show the increased rates on all cards which will be current on or after 1st October, 1951. The earliestseries of cards affected will be those which will cover the period from December1950 to December 1951. In view of the large supplies involved the printing order for this series of cards will have to be issued in May 1950, and the distribution ofthe cards to the public will start in the second half of November 1950.5. It is probable that most insured persons have forgotten that increasedrates of contributions are,due to come into force in October 1951, and that theremay be a good deal of opposition to increases in rates of contributions which arenot accompanied by increases in rates of benefits. On the other hand, the futurecommitments of the national insurance scheme are formidable. It is estimatedthat the total annual Exchequer liability to the Insurance Fund will rise to about 420 million in 1978 as compared with  140 million provided in current estimates.The increases in contributions now under consideration come into force automatic-ally under existing legislation.6.   In all the circumstances I propose, subject to the approval of the Cabinet,(i) to proceed with the arrangements necessary for bringing the increased ratesof contributions into force on 1st October, 1951, and (ii) to take steps to explain to the public in November 1950, and subsequently, the reasons for the increases.38706-:-7&quot;^Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1950
7. These proposals were discussed on 5th May by the Lord President^Committee, who approved them (L.P. (50) 5th Meeting, Minute 2), but agreed that,in view of the possibility of political embarrassment, the Lord President shouldmention them to the Prime Minister. The Prime Minister has asked that I should bring the; matter before the Cabinet. .,,, v .E. S. .Ministry of National Insurance, S. W. 1,IWh May, 1950.APPENDIX  IA. Present Rates of Contributions		Class 1*		Class 2	Class 3	Employer	Employe?	Total			s.    d.	s.    d.	s.    d.	s.    d.	&apos; s.    d.Men     ......	4      2	4    11	9      1	6      2	4      8Women	3     3	3    10	7      1	5      1	3      8Ipysf    ...	2      5J	2    101	5      4	3      7	2     9 \ -Girlst   ...	1     11	2      4	4      3	3      1	-.   2     3  .iB. New Rates qf Contributions on and from 1st October, 1951	Class 1*					Class 2	Class 3	Employer		Employee	Total				s,	d.	s.    d.	s.	d.		s.    d.Men     ......	4	4	5   : 1	9	5	6     6	5     women	3	5	4      0	7	5	5      5	4     0   -Boysf    ...	2	6*	2    11*	5	6	3      9	2    11    -Girlst   ...      ...	2	0	2      5&quot;	4	5	3      3	2   5* Industrial Injuries Insurance contributions are included,t Under the age of 18.APPENDIX note on the Growing Cost of Retirement Pensions and Widows&apos; benefits in his Report on the Financial Provisions of the National Insurance Bill, 1946(Cmd. 6730), the Government Actuary estimated the expenditure on retirement pensions and widows&apos; benefits at ten-yearly intervals during the first thirty yearsof the scheme, as followsRetirement Widows&apos;Pensions Benefits  million   million1948*...............      238 221958       ...      ............      301 35.1968       ...      ............      421 421978       ......               ...      ...      501 40* The estimates assumed that the scheme would have been in operation throughout 1948.
The main reason why the cost of retirement pensions and widows&apos; benefits ismore than doubled in 30 years is that the number of beneficiaries increasesc fromover 4 million in 1948 to over *1\ million in 1978. This increase in the pensionedpopulation is partly due to the growth in the total population of pensionable age,which is expected to be one-third greater in 1978 than in 1948, but a further mainfactor is the inclusion in the pensioner population, after the scheme has been inoperation for ten years, of classes of persons who were not insured prior to the inception of the universal scheme and are not represented in the pensioner popula-tion at the outset. A contributory factor in the increase of cost is the grant ofincrements of pensions by virtue of contributions paid after the attainment ofpensionable age; this factor will not be fully operative in the initial stages ofthe scheme.The increase of contributions which will take effect in October 1951, is esti-mated to produce an additional  16 million at 8^ per cent, of unemployment (whichis the level adopted by the Government Actuary on Government instructions asthe basis of the finance of the National Insurance Scheme) or  17^ million at thecurrent level of under 2 per cent, of unemployment. The Government Actuaryestimates, however, that although this will for a time result in an increase in theincome from contributions, that income will by 1978 be no more than it was at thebeginning of the scheme.

</content>
</cab>
