<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/32/50 images: 432-435</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   December 1942.SECRET.Copy No.    S/CW.P. (42) 620.December 31, 1942.WAR CABINET.DIRECTIVE TO MINISTER RESIDENT AT ALLIED headquarters in NORTH-WEST AFRICA.BY direction of the Prime Minister, the attached Directive to the minister resident at Allied Headquarters in North-West Africa is circulated for theinformation of the War Cabinet. The Directive has been approved by thePrime Minister.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,December 31, 1942.Mr. Harold Macmillan, M.P., has been appointed Minister Resident atAllied Headquarters in North-West Africa.Mr. Macmillan&apos;s primary function will be to report on the political situationand future plans for the territory, and to represent to tihe Commander-in-chief the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government on political questions. His reports willbe addressed, to theJPrime Minister.He will work in the closest touch with his United States colleague,establishing relations of confidence and amity with him.He is not at present accredited to any French authority. The present french administration in North Africa is treated by the Allied Commander-in-Chiefas a temporary de facto local administration. Mr. Macmillan&apos;s relations withthe French authorities will accordingly be of an informal character.Mr. R. M. Makins, of the Foreign Office, will accompany Mr. Macmillan ashis assistant and will act for him should he at any time be absent from Algiers.Mr. W. H. B. Mack, of the Foreign Office, has for some time past held thepost of British Civil Liaison Officer on General Eisenhower&apos;s staff. He willcontinue to hold this appointment and will not join Mr. Macmillan&apos;s staff, though he will look to him for guidance on any political matter affecting the interests ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government.Mr. Macmillan will superintend the activities of such British civilian expertsas may be appointed to collaborate with the United States authorities in french north Africa.His Majesty&apos;s Consular Officers in French North Africa will be instructedto repeat to Mr. Macmillan the political reports which they address to the foreign secretary. Mr. Macmillan may communicate direct with them when necessary,and they with him.Signed)) E. E. BRIDGES.Secretary of the War Cabinet.[24833]




</content>
</cab>
