<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/264/0 images: 28-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY  OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)GRET.P. 231  (36)CABINETBLIND PERSONS.Copy No        Memorandum by the Minister of Health.          I have had under consideration for some timelegislation to amend the Blind Persons Act, 1920, and circumstances have arisen Y\rhich, in my opinion, render itdesirable that a decision should be taken at once.          The main object of the Bill would be to reduce theage at which a blind person becomes entitled to a pensionfrom 50 to 40.  This proposal has been pressed for someyears, and in his Election Address in 1929 the Prime Ministergave a pledge In the following terms:-          &quot;Pensions are provided at the age of 50 for such           as have not sufficient means of their own to be           independent, but since at that age it is difficult,           if not impossible, for a blind person to take           advantage of the training facilities provided, the           Government have come to the conclusion that           pensions should be made available earlier in life,.           and if they should be returned to power they will           introduce legislation to make the pensionable age           40 instead of 50&quot;.My Advisory Committee on the Welfare of the Blind have made representations to the same effect,          The gross additional expenditure involved isestimated at  150,000 to  160,000 a year for the UnitedKingdom..  The estimates are  130,000 for England and  Wales; 18,000 for Scotland; and  5,000 for Northern Ireland.There will ultimately be a reduction in the Block Grant toset off against this expenditure,  amounting in England andWales to about  25,000 a year.          The Bill would also contain provisions to carryfurther the principle established in the Local Government1.
                                                                   take place in October by the National League for the Blind,, whichBjis affiliated to the Labour Party and to the -Trades Union Congress.The plan is apparently that marchers from various parts of thecountry should converge on London and present a petition to theGovernment asking for State pensions of 27/6d. a, week for allblind persons from the age of 13, irrespective of other means,and for the acceptance by the Exchequer of 75$ of the cost ofmaintenance of blind persons.   I have consulted the Home Secretary&apos;and it is clear that there are no practicable means of stoppingthese proceedings through the agency of the Police.   Thepossibility has, therefore, to be faced that the efforts which Iam making through other channels may fail, and. it would clearly be most undesirable, if the march takes place, that the NationalLeague should be able to claim, as they did in 1920 when a similarmarch took place, that it secured further concessions to blind persons.   Moreover, my &apos;efforts to stop the march might well be assisted by a prior announcement about the Bill.          I wish, therefore,  to bo in a position to announce assoon as possible and before the march takes place or is finallyarranged, that the Government, as a result of their ordinarysurvey of social conditions,  have decided to introduce next                                                                   1Session a Bill to improve the position of blind persons under the  jBlind Persons Act, 1920, which will include a reduction in the     I                                                                   1pension age from. 50 to 40.    The Chancellor concurs in these       I                                                                   Iproposals.K.W.                                   I29th August, 1936,                                                                   act, 1929, of removing blind persons from the Poor Law and to overcome difficulties which have arisen under the present law in                                                                   IBBconnection with the definition of &quot;ordinary residence&quot;.            i          I wish to raise this question at once in view of the.     ;                               &quot;                                   BPmarch of blind persons on London which is now being organised to   I                                                                   I

</content>
</cab>
