<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/264/0 images: 113-120</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C/ ****  - /ITHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT. SECRET.                                                COPY MO. 4^ CP. 250.(56).                       CABINET.               STATE OF TRADE - AUGUST, 1936.        Note by the president of the Board of Trade.     I circulate to my colleagues a summary of the reports submitted to the Board of Trade Advisory Council on the stateof trade in August, 1936.W.R.Board of Trade,   29th September, 1936.
CONFIDENTIAL.A.C.360.BOARD OF TRADE ADVISORY COUNCIL. STATE OF TRADE - AUGUST, 1936.Summary of reports submitted &quot;by members of the Board of Trade Advisory Council (supplemented in some   cases by statistical information from other                  sources).     OVERSEAS TRADE.  Imports in August at  66.1 m. were 6.9 m. more than in August, 1935.   Nearly 70$i of the risewas in food and raw materials.   Of the increase of  2.1 m.in manufactured goods,  417,000 related to iron and steel and manufactures thereof and a similar figure to oils, fatsand resins.  Exports of United Kingdom products,  35.3 a, $were  375,000 more and re-exports,  4.4 m., were  170,000more than in August, 1935.     EMPLOYMENT.  The total numbers of unemployed persons on the.registers at 24th August, 1,613,940, was 38,132fewer  than at 20th July.   The main variations were:-  London........ - 3,891  North Western. + 4,057  South Eastern. 4-   243  Northern..... -    98  Southwestern. + 1,399  Scotland .....-11,654  Midlands ..... - 5,516  Wales ........ - 7,379  North Eastern. -15,293     The estimated number of insured persons aged 16-64in employment was 10,961,000,  66,000 more than, at 20th july and 500,000 more than at 26th August, 1935.   There was asubstantial increase in the coal-mining industry and some improvement in building and public works contracting,general engineering, the iron and steel tube industry, andin linen, boot and shoe and cocoa, chocolate etc.manufacture.    Employment declined in tailoring,dressmaking, the shirt, collar, etc, industry and the distributive trades.
     RAILWAY TRAFFIC.  in the five weeks ended 5th Augustrailway traffic receipts increased by  695,000 (4.07^)compared with the  corresponding period of  1935.  passenger traffic increased  by 5.04^. merchandise, minerals and livestock by       and coal, coke and patent fuel by 5.86/S,     SHIPPING.  Freight rates have been, well maintained.The Chamber of shipping ind.ex number of freights (1913 - 100)was 93.85 as against 88.42 in July and 78.25 a year ago.     BANKING.  Money was extremely easy throughout august and the banks were steady buyers of bills  from the marketat 10*,  The Treasury bill rate varied between 10/5.95d.and 10/7.31d.  The note circulation reached a new high levelof  454.4 m. on August 5th.   The Bank of England continuedits purchase of gold.   Market prices fell gradually,ranging between 138/8d. and 138/2d. per ounce.     The franc was weak against sterling,  the spot rate                      1,         15.fluctuating between 76/15 and 76 /52  while the threemonths&apos;  forward rate averaged slightly over 5 francsdiscoivnt.   The New York rate was steady around 5.02,     COAL. The average weekly output of coal during the13 weeks ended 22nd August was 4.05 m. tons as comparedwith 3.97 m. tons  in the corresponding period a year ago -an increase of 2^.  The average number of wage-earnersemployed was Ifi less than a year before.  Exports in Augustamounted to 2.75  iru tons as compared with 3.45 m. tons inAugust,  1935.    There vrere no exports to Italy as comparedwith 279,000 tons a year ago.  Other countries taking lessincluded Canada,  Egypt, Spain and Denmark.   The chiefincreases were to Finland and Switzerland.
     ENGINEERING.  General activity further increased andthe volume of new business booked was very satisfactory.   the stimulus of the re-armament programme is now being felt.Exports of machinery were valued at  3.12 m. as compared with 3o0l HU in August, 1935c     MOTOR INDUSTRY.  The number of motor vehicles newlyregistered in July was 34s359 - 4,091 more than a year ago;.the increase in private cars was 2,537.   The production ofprivate cars and taxis in June was 29,968 as against 23,567 inJune, 1955, and the production of commercial vehicles increased from 7,018 to 9,262.  Exports of new private cars and chassis inAugust amounted to o,605 and of new commercial vehicles andchassis to 1,512 - 12.9^ and 55.lv respectively more than inAugust, 1935c  178 complete new private  cars and taxis wereimported as compared with 297 a year ago,     LIGHT METAL INDUSTRIES.  Activity in the non-ferrous metalsindustry was maintained despite the holiday season and prospects are encouraging.  Large orders for tools continue to be placedand complaints regarding deliveries are  not infrequent.  Thecutlery trade improved and brisker conditions are anticipated,.The press-work trade continued exceptionally busy and steadybusiness was reported in enamelled hollow-ware.  Output in thelock and allied trades was high.  Conditions in most other-branches remained satisfactory.     ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.   The general  increase in activity was maintained.  The index of heavy engineering orders (both home and export) was higher than in August, 1935.  Consumptionof electricity amounted to 1,332 m.  units - 12% more than ayear ago.
                                                  e r: from the exceptionally high level reached in July. Average weekly deliveries of raw cotton to spinners were 23.6 m.  lbs.  against 27.4 m. lbs,  in July and 20.0 m. lbs.  in August, 1935.   The decline was felt in all sections  of the spinning trade.    Raw cotton prices fell sharply following the publication of the official estimate  of the American crop.   Yarn prices fell, though  to a  lesser extent.   Yarn exports at 11.7 m. lbs.  were  1.6 m.  lbs.  less than in July (due principally to smaller G-erman purchases) and .2 m.  lbs.                                                             w less than in  August, 1935.   Exports of piece-goods at 159 m.  sq.  yds were 17 m.  sq.  yds less than in July and 2 m.  sq.  yds  less  than in August, 1935.  The decline as compared with July was spread over most important markets but there were substantial increases in exports to Colombia I and French West Africa.      SILK ,AND ARTIPICIAL SILK,   Demand for rayon yarns has been encouraging and a good Autumn season is anticipated.   Business in staple fibre remained quiet. Enquiries for rayon fabrics were fairly  satisfactory, exports of all-rayon fabrics showed an  increase as compared  with August,  1935,  but exports of rayon yarns declined.      Demand for silk piece-goods  was poor,  chiefly owing to  extremely  low prices accepted  by  Lyons manufacturers,      WOOL,  There was  little  change in  general  activity during  August,   Imports  of yarns  and tissues declined as  compared -with July but exports  of tops  slightly increased.  Raw wool prices  hardened,   A very fair seasonal demand is being felt in the&apos;woollen section,but i*reports from the worsted section are not encouraging.
      HIDES AND LEATHER.  Hide  markets on the  whole  were  very- active and values  steadily improved.  Conditions  in  the light leather trade in general were quiet, hut there was fair activity in certain  sections  of the  heavy leather  industry.      CHEMICALS. Home  sales of alkalies,  though less  than in previous months, were satisfactory.   Exports fell slightly. Deliveries of chlorine products and  mineral  acids  were maintained at a satisfactory  level.    Sales  of industrial nitrogen products  this year are well in  advance of those in 1935.   Home sales  of  dyestuffs  again showed  an increase over last  year.   Home sales of fertilizers are  nearly 70% greater this  season than last (due to purchases  for  forward  delivery being much higher  than   at the  corresponding date  a  year ago). Exports have  decreased,  due largely  to  the cessation of sales to  Spain,   Sales of wood distillation products were  very satisfactory.      POTTERY.  Sales of general  earthenware in July showed a little  improvement as compared  with  June.  Demand for chinaware was normal  and home demand for  glazed wall and hearth tiles continued  good.  Sales of sanitaryware of fireclay showed a very  satisfactory increase over July, 1935, hut sales of sanitaryware  of earthenware declined.  Exports of pottery were greater  than  in July, 1935.     BUILDING-.  The situation in the  building industries continued favourable.  The value of building plans approved in July  showed a  substantial  increase as compared with a year ago.     RETAIL TRADE.  The money value of retail sales in July was 5.8% greater than in July, 1935.  Sales of food and perishables rose by  9.4% as compared with an increase of 8.5% for February-July.    Sales of other merchandise rose by 2.4% as comparedwith an  increase of 3.9% for February-July.  Preliminaryfigures for August  show similar increases.
      CANADIAN TRADE.   Economic  conditions  improved  further in July and business  activity increased.  Wholesale prices were higher than at any time  since the  beginning  of 1931.  Compared with July,  1935, exports of wheat  more than  trebled in value, while exports of aluminium,  cattle, cheese,  pulp and paper, copper and  asbestos showed considerable increases.  After seasonal adjustment newsprint production reached a  record for the  post-war period.   Iron and  steel and automobile production declined as  compared  with  June.      AUSTRALIAN TRADE. 79,581 bales of wool were received into store in July as compared  with  95,327 in July, 1935, the quantity sold or shipped being  1,755 and 1,901 respectively. &quot;Wheat and flour shipments  from  1st December  to 28th August were  equivalent to  76.3 m, bushels of wheat as against 78.4 m. a year ago.   Butter shipments from 1st July to 29th August amounted to  5,724  tons as  compared with 4,025 tons a year ago. Imports  of merchandise during July amounted to  10.47 m. (Australian  currency) as compared with  8.07 in. a year before.      SOUTH AFRICAN  TRADE. Imports in June were 24.5^ greater than  in  June,  1935,  Exports (excluding gold) were  3.1% more despite  a virtual cessation of  sugar and maize shipments.   Both output and exports  of gold were  greater than a year ago.   Coal production advanced by 18.8$ over June,  1935.      SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.     Argentina.  A feeling is prevalent that prosperous times are ahead.  The value of the peso has recovered further.   G-rain prices were erratic, due mainly  to  speculative  operations; the maize, wheat and linseed markets were strong at  thebeginning of August,  but weakened later.   The wool  market was dull.  The freight market was active.   Exports  in  January- July  1935, were 13% and imports      in value  less than a year before.                         -6-
      Brazil.   Brazil&apos;s  share  of the world coffee trade declined appreciably  during January-July, 1936 as compared with a year ago,  although  her actual deliveries were only slightly less. Cotton  shipments were slightly more in volume in the first half of  1936 than a year before.   The value of total exports in June was higher than in any month  (except last January) in recent years.      Chile. The exchange position in respect of sterling and United  States  dollars continues extremely difficult.  Imports from  Germany during the first half of 1936 were more than double the value of imports in the corresponding period of 1935:  United Kingdom imports declined.      Peru.  Exports in January-June, 1936, were 12% and imports lb^%  in value  more than a year before but exports greatly exceed  imports and the favourable balance of trac ;  increased noticeably.      Colombia.  Substantial reductions have been authorised in the import duties on certain products.   The value of exports was 7% more  and imports 9% less in the  first half of 1936 than a year before i.     Uruguay.  weather seriously affected stock rearing and agriculture.   The export of wheat was prohibited.     Ecuador.  Exchange  control has been re-imposed.   Activity slackened noticeably in  most classes of  business.

</content>
</cab>
