<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/264/0 images: 146-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1936.SECEET.                                                         Copy  No.CP. 254  (36).CABINET.      PALESTINE.THE POLITICAL SITUATION.           Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.    I CIRCULATE herewith, for the information of the Cabinet, a copy of aSecret  Despatch from Sir Arthur Wauchope, dated the 12th September, 1936,regarding the political situation in Palestine and the question of the deportation of the Mufti, together with a copy of a Secret Despatch which I sent to the HighCommissioner in reply on the 1st October.                                               (Initialled)       W.  0.  G.    Colonial Office, Downing Street,            October 2,  1936^        Secret Despatch from the High Commissioner for Palestine of                            September 12, 1936.(Secret.)(Reference No. CF/704/36.)            High Commissioner for Palestine,Sir,                                        Jerusalem,  September 12, 1936.    DEFINITE changes in the situation in Palestine have been caused  partly by the unfortunate manifesto of the Supreme Arab Committee published on the30th  August;  but  chiefly by  the  substance  of His  Majesty&apos;s Governments.declaration of the 7th September, which has, I hope, at last convinced the  Arabsthat the statements disseminated by their leaders that success was almost achievedand that His Majesty&apos;s Government were about to make concessions were devoidof all foundation.    2.  During the last two months two contrary  forces  have been influencing the general situation.  First, the bulk of the people have been growing daily moreweary of the strike and the consequences of continued disorder, though no leadershitherto  have had the courage to voice this feeling and so put themselves in opposition to  the  nationalist  spirit  which  continues   strongly  anti-Zionist..Second, large numbers of the population are perfectly ready to continue fighting,more especially as they receive assistance in men and arms from over the border..The matter of leadership is not simple, as some people imagine.   Every smalltown has its own National Committee, and these are by no means always willingto carry  out the  instructions of the Supreme  Committee.   The members of thelatter are only united by their strong  feelings for  the National cause,  and are greatly subject to the  influence of  the Shabab and other extremists.   Of thisCommittee the Mufti is President and exerts the greatest  influence.    3.  As you know from my private and personal telegram of the 18th May,.one of the main reasons that decided me that it would be  inopportune to deport      [13878]
 the Mufti was that, if deported, his position would be taken by a successor more extreme than himself.   My decision was  also influenced  by the considerations that      (1) If deported, his successor and followers would raise the religious cry and           either close the mosques or cause violent speeches to be made at every           Friday prayer.     (2) His  deportation would rouse feelings in neighbouring Arab countries,           and cause extremists in these countries to give support to the armed           bands in Palestine.   The Istiqlal party in Trans-Jordan and elsewhere           would certainly have taken the opportunity to voice extreme Pan-Arab           ideas, and possibly have caused a rising in that country.     A third  factor, however, is now coming into &quot;play, a factor which I have been disappointed not to see before, that is disgust with the leaders who have achieved no success in forcing Government to accede to their demands.     This disgust is not outspoken at present, but it is real, and it is  concentrated naturally by large numbers on the Mufti as the head of the Supreme Arab Committee, and encouraged by  his  many enemies.     4.  When in past years I have reported that the  Mufti hfe acted well by Government,  and when until recently 1  have  emphasized the importance of his negative action in not raising the religious cry in many ways that were open to him,  I  have  always admitted  that I could  never forecast  his future attitude towards Government.     In  spite of  his  position  and prestige,  the  Mufti  is  no real leader;  he constantly allows himself to be pushed  along the line of least resistance.  He never dares to be left alone in the dark.     During  the past few months I have felt  it wiser that I should not see the Mufti or other members of the Supreme Arab Committee-, as such meetings might have  given   the impression  both  to them and  to  the public that  the  High Commissioner was anxious to enter into negotiations or make some compromise in order to end the strike and armed resistance.   Consequently, I have not been able to exercise any influence over the Mufti.     These last few weeks my Intelligence  shows that for one reason or another the Mufti has adopted the line  of urging his followers to continue  the struggle until certain  of the Arab demands have been met; this attitude is clearly shown by the deplorable manifesto of  the Higher Committee dated  the 30th August.     5.  In the meantime it is important to record the  changing attitude of the other parties.  The so-called moderate party, headed by Ragheb Bey Nashashibi,has always been and still is hostile  to the Mufti&apos; s party, but during the last five months  this  party has under pressure of the  prevailing National feeling main- tained the united front on the Supreme Arab Committee.  By professing an even greater  enthusiasm for extreme  measures than the Mufti, Ragheb Bey has until the last few weeks attempted to  manoeuvre the Mufti into embarrassing positions in which he-would of necessity come into conflict with the Government.     But now a large body of Arabs,  including Ragheb Bey and many of his party, including also many who have any  stake in the country, are weary of the strike and the consequences of prolonged disturbances.  This body of opinion is growing daily stronger and this fact together with the feeling of disgust with a discredited leadership have made the moderates  of all parties anxious to seize any opportunity to put an end to  the present situation.     But what is more significant is the changing attitude of Auni Bey Abdulhadi, leader of the  Istiqlal party in Palestine.   Formerly he told me  the Arabs having nothing but their lives to lose would  fight  to the bitter end.  Now he acknowledges it would be to the interests of the Arabs that the strike and all acts of violence should cease.    Furthermore, I believe that  Arab rulers outside Palestine, whose sympathiesthe Mufti enjoyed until a month ago, now feel that the people of Palestine have been led along a track that will eventually bring  them to disaster; and for this the Mufti is largely responsible.     Consequently at home and abroad the power  and influence of  the Mufti has greatly waned.    I am therefore convinced that the Mufti  could be deported without raising;a fraction of  the disturbance such an act would have aroused a month ago.  Nor
-do I believe that his deportation now would necessarily entail someone still more extreme filling his place.  It is possible that his deportation now might well leadto the strengthening of more moderate counsels.    Before  arriving  at a final decision  I  shall await  the  results of my next meeting with the  Supreme Arab Committee; your  instructions as to possibleconsultation with Arab Kings,  and your decision as to the Seychelles.    I shall  also consult General Dill, because if Martial  Law is  declared at a fairly early date I advise that the deportation of the Mufti or others should be ordered by   the Administrator  of  Martial  Law,  rather than by  the HighCommissioner.    It is in my opinion, and that  of my advisers, essential that,  if deported, the mufti should remain out of Palestine for a period of years sufficient to ensurethat his own prestige evaporates and his successor  in  office acquires  influence and authority, which would be greatly enhanced if the much-needed reforms inthe constitution of the Supreme Moslem.  Council and in the administration ofAwqaf were carried out meanwhile.  It has always been my definite opinion thatto allow His  Eminence to return to Palestine after a few months&apos;  absence, withheightened prestige and the halo of exile, would be fatal to the  future peace ofthis country.                                I have, &amp;c.                                   ARTHUR WAUCHOPE,                                          High Commissioner for Palestine. -Secret Despatch from Secretary of State for the Colonies to High Commissioner                        for Palestine, October 1, 1936. (Secret.)                                     Colonial Office, Downing Street, Sir,                                                October 1, 1936.     I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the  receipt of  your secret despatch of the 12th September regarding the political situation in Palestine and the question of the deportation of the Mufti.     2.   I  entirely endorse the opinions expressed in the concluding paragraphs of your despatch, and on the assumption that powers are delegated to the General Officer Commanding under the Palestine Martial Law (Defence) Order in Council at an early date, I  consider that the  deportation  of the Mufti  or  others, if desirable in the circumstances then prevailing, should be ordered by the General Officer Commanding  rather than by the High Commissioner.   I also agree that in the event of the Mufti&apos;s  deportation, it is essential that he should remain out of the country for a period of years  sufficient to  ensure that  his own prestige evaporates, and  that his successor or successors in his various offices acquire influence and authority.     3.   But the question  of procedure  will need careful consideration.   Haj Amin-al-Husseini is  (a) Mufti  of  Jerusalem,  and,  as Mufti, Chairman of  the Wakf Committee in virtue of Section  10 of the Supreme Moslem Council Order of 1921; and  (b) permanent President  of the Supreme  Moslem Council,  with administrative control over the Sharia Courts.  If he is merely deported and noother action is taken,  he will presumably retain all these offices.     His appointment as Mufti is a purely religious appointment, with which, Iunderstand, the Government of Palestine were not concerned.   Unless the Moslemreligious authorities  themselves depose  Haj Amin and  appoint a  successor asMufti of Jerusalem, it would seem that a change could only be effected by special legislation,  but I should be apprehensive of the effect of such procedure  uponMoslem opinion generally.     If it is thought that the situation demands  the deportation of the Mufti, and,as a consequence, his removal from the  office of  President of the Supreme MoslemCouncil and from the offices of Chairman of the Wakf Committee, this could nodoubt be effected, as an emergency measure, by amendment of the provisions ofthe Supreme Moslem Council Order  of  1921  relating to the appointments of president of the Council and Chairman of the Wakf Committee.     It has,  however, been the considered policy of Government hitherto to grant the Moslems in Palestine a large measure of independence in such matters as the
 constitution of the Supreme Moslem Council, the administration of the Sharia Courts, and the control of Wakf funds.  Amendment of the  Supreme Moslem Council Order of 1921, which is clearly desirable, has been envisaged, but it has always been contemplated, .and, indeed, an undertaking  was authorised by the Secretary of State in 1928, that representative Moslem opinion would be consulted in the matter.     I shall be obliged if you will give this matter early consideration and inform me what consequential action you think should be taken in the event of its being decided to deport the Mufti.   It may be that in present  circumstances the only practicable course would be for Government to pass special legislation for the removal of Haj Amin-al-Husseini  from the office of President of the Supreme Moslem Council, and for amendment of Section 10&apos; of the Supreme Moslem Council Order of 1921, under which the Mufti of Jerusalem acts as  Chairman of the Wakf Committee, and to enable the High Commissioner  to nominate a successor or successors  for a limited term to these offices; leaving for future consideration, when the position in Palestine is stabilised, the question of the permanent organi- sation of  the Supreme Moslem Council.   But, even  such  provisional legislation might itself have very serious repercussions, and  I should certainly wish to have your considered advice before action is taken.    4.  In any event,  I should be glad to have information as to the present position in regard to the administration of Wakf funds under the control of the Mufti.  The financial settlement reached between the Government of Palestine and the Supreme Moslem Council in connexion with the commutation of  tithe included the  acceptance by the  Council of certain conditions.   The  Council agreed to submit to Government a signed copy of the audited accounts of the Council for the five years ended the 31st December, 1931, and for the year ending the 31st December, 1932, as soon as audit was completed, and thereafter year by year within four months of the close of each financial year.  Further, the Council agreed to submit to Government  for information before the  1st January, 1933, balanced estimates of revenue and expenditure of the Council for the year ending the 31st  December, 1933.  Finally,  the  Council  agreed to make  immediate arrangements with the Treasurer for the adoption by the Council of the accounting system and financial regulations of Government as from the  1st January, 1933. It was made clear to the Council that the payment of the agreed annual sum in respect of commuted tithe was  dependent upon observance by the Council of these conditions.  In replying to this despatch you will no doubt let me know whetherthe conditions  accepted by the Council have been complied with, and whether, inyour opinion, Government  ought to take further steps with  a view to securing stricter financial control of Wakf funds.                                              I have, &amp;c.                                                    W. ORMSBY GORE

</content>
</cab>
