<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/264/0 images: 150-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET .Copy no cp. 255(36)CAB I I E T .FACTORIES BILL.Memorandum- by the Home Secretary.1.My colleagues will recollect that in the Debate on the address on the 3rd December, 1935, the Prime Minister announced the intention of the Government to promote a new Factories Bill.Replying to a complaint from the leader of the Opposition thatthere was no mention of factory legislation in the King&apos;s Speech,he said:-         &quot;There is a piece of reform that we are most anxious     to get on with, and that is a Bill for the revision and     consolidation of the law relating to the safety, health     and welfare of factory workers.   Legislation on that     subject has been examined and contemplated by many     Governments, not even,  I believe, excluding the Labour     Government.   We hope and purpose to introduce that Bill     in our second Session2.        In the following month I received a deputation from theTrades Union Congress General Council, who emphasised thenecessity of up-to-date legislation, expressed their greatgratification with the Government declaration, and offered their assistance and co-operation.3.        The Prime Minister&apos;s announcement has since been thesubject of frequent reference in Parliament.   For example,  itwas made use of by Government Spokesmen in Debates on theEducation Bill, mdre particularly in resisting attempts to include in that Bill provisions fixing maximum hours of employment forjuveniles.   On the 25th May (Official Report, Col. 1947 etc.)the Attorney General said that the Government had promised tobring in, during the next year,  a Factories Bill laying down hoursof work, and some subsequent speakers emphasised the importance of
                                                         lib                          -2- carrying the Bill through and not  (as in  the  case of some previous Bills of the kind) merely introducing it.   In the House  of Lords on the 30th June Lord De La Warr  (Col. 305) intimated that the  Government were not trying to evade the problem of juvenile hours and said that the Government had already promised to introduce a Factories Bill in the following year,  though it would not cover all the classes  of employment then under discussion.   Again, references to the Government&apos;s intentions were made in the debate in the House  of Commons on Home Office administration on the 30th July, when the need for revising and extending the Factory Acts in various respects was emphasized. 4.        In these  circumstances I have felt justified in - instructing my Department to undertake a  considerable amount of work preparatory to the Bill, and to get  into touch in a preliminary way (without, of course,  committing the Government) with representatives of employers and workmen;  and after reviewing previous  draft Bills in the light of experience they have sent to the national Confederation of Employers&apos; Organisations and to the Trades Union Congress General  Council&apos; confidentially for comment a statement summarising the effect of the main proposals the inclusion of which in the Bill is provisionally under  consideration. 5.        An amending and consolidating Factories Act is,  of course, long overdue.   The Act of 1901 (which,  though amended in some respects by later Statutes,  remains the principal Act)  containsmany provisions which are either obsolete or inappropriately framed under modern conditions.   It requires a thorough overhaul both in detail and on various matters cf substance - notoriously as to the hours for women and young persons,   The present  previsions as
to hours are of an antiquated character and urgently in need of amendment.    On the one hand they allow much longer hoursthan are at present generally worked - they permit a 12 hourday with l  (in textile factories 2) hours off for meals anda 60 hour week (55-jjs- in textile factories), and strong complainthas been made  that with improving trade a number of firms,instead of spreading the employment, are reverting to longerhours and are  employing women and young persons up to or almostup to the maximum permissible hours.   On the other hand, theprovisions are in several respects unduly rigid and tend to hamper modern  developments (e.g. in the fruit and vegetablecanning industries).   Indeed,  in some cases the Inspectors have of recent years had to turn a blind eye to breaches of the law.The law is also needlessly complicated - for example, by subtledistinctions between factories and workshops and between different classes of factories.   Further, the safety and healthprovisions fall in many respects below the standards observed in the better  managed works and there are some striking omissions(for instance, there is no provision as to factory lighting);while prospects of legislation repeatedly held out but notmaterialising  have prejudiced administrative action for securingimprovements.6.        I should therefore be glad to have Cabinet authorityto continue with the preparation of the Bill and have it draftedat the earliest possible date with a view to its being mentionedin the King1s  Speech and introduced early in the Session.7.        Until my consultation with employers&apos;  and workers&apos;organisations  has further developed, it is not possible to putforward definite proposals as to what the Bill should contain, butI contemplate  that it should be largely based on the Factories
                                                           4 AO                                                           llO9th October,  1936.Bills of my predecessors and that its main objects would he to revise the existing provisions in regard to safety, health, welfare and hours of employment in conformity with modern standards and tore-define and in some respects extend the scope of their applicationAs regards hours of employment, it is suggested that the provisions should he based on the 48 hour week with some allowance for over-time for women and young persons over 16 and with special latitudein certain industries or processes .   The two shift system ofworking has,  of course,  been dealt with in an Act passed this yearand I should not propose to re-open that question at all.8.        It  would be useful to me if a small Cabinet committee could be appointed,  whose help I could invoke on specific points of difficulty arising in the preparation of the Bill.                                       J.S .

</content>
</cab>
