<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/264/0 images: 314-316</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
hJ x *JTO  BE KEPT  UNDER  LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to    ensure the secrecy of this  document.MOST SECRET.CP. 264 (56).FINAE COPY.COPY NO,$1                      CABINET.     THE  KINOr3 SPEECH ON THE  PROROGATION OP PA^LIAF^NT                    5&apos;0TH- OCTOBER,  1956,                  Note by the  Secretary.         The  accompanying final copy  of  the Xing&apos;s speech on the Prorogation&apos; of Parliament  is  circulated forinformation  and  record.                        (Signed)  M.P.A.  IIANXEY.                             Secretary to the  Cabineto, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,27th October, 1956.
The  King&apos;s Speech on the Prorogation  of Parliament.                  FRIDAY,  OCTOBER 30TH,  1936.MY LORDS  AND MEMBERS  OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS :    I AM  addressing you for the first time as your Sovereign.  I desire beforeall to express once more My deep appreciation of the  sympathy which has been extended to Me and to My dear Mother in every part of My dominions.  I havebeen profoundly touched by the universal expression of the affection and respectwith which My beloved Father was regarded. I am well assured that the memoryof King George&apos;s life of devotion and unremitting service will  long live in thehearts of His people.    My relations with foreign Powers continue to be friendly.    On the 26th August a Treaty of Alliance with the King of Egypt was signed in London by delegates representing My Government and the Egyptian Govern-ment.  It is My earnest hope that this Treaty when ratified will be the beginningof a new era in which the friendly co-operation that  has marked the relationsbetween My country and Egypt in the past will be confirmed and strengthened.    A Conference was held  at Montreux in the  summer for the revision of theStraits Convention of Lausanne.  The successful outcome of this Conference, towhich I am pleased to think  that My Government contributed, has set a happyexample for the future.    The Assembly of the League of Nations have recently opened an enquiry intothe working of the Covenant, and My Government, which remain firmly attachedto the principles of the Covenant of the  League, have made known their viewsupon the manner in which its application might be improved.    My Ministers have been engaged in negotiations for a meeting between theFive Powers signatory to  the Treaty of Locarno on the basis of the agreement reached by My Government and the  Governments of  France and  Belgium inLondon on the 23rd July.  These negotiations are continuing.                                        .    I have viewed  with concern and anxiety  the events in  Spain during thelast  three  months.   My Government  have spared no  pains to  promote  and encourage humanitarian efforts to mitigate the suffering of the people of Spain.My Navy has  acted in accordance with its  high traditions in relieving the distresscaused by these disturbances.  It has been the consistent policy of  My Governmentto attempt to localise this unhappy struggle,  and with this  end  in view theyseconded the initiative of  the French Government for  a non-intervention agree-ment and have energetically co-operated in its negotiation and application.    My Ministers were glad to be able, in conjunction with the Government ofthe United States of America, to lend their co-operation to the scheme for there-adjustment of the value of the French currency.  I trust that the measures taken recently by the French and several other Governments will pave the way for a further improvement in international trade.MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS :    I thank you for the provision you have made for the public service.    I thank you for the arrangements you have made for the maintenance of the honour and dignity of the Crown.    13954
MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF  COMMONS :     The measures  essential for improving and  strengthening all three  of  Mydefence forces, which were laid before you this year, have been steadily pursued.     I rejoice at  the further marked increase in trade and employment  duringthe year.   I  note) with much  gratification, that unemployment generally  is stilldiminishing  and that employment  has reached the  highest level  ever  recorded.Schemes for the amelioration of the conditions in those districts where the problemof unemployment still presents special difficulties have continued to  engage the close attention of My Ministers and of the  Commissioners appointed  for those areas.     Steps have been taken to  reduce the rate of contributions under the generalunemployment insurance scheme.    Regulations relating to unemployment assistance and measures for bringing to an end the period of standstill which has existed since February, 1935, receivedyour approval in  July, and will come into effect in November.    The development  of  the national health services  has  received the close.attention of My Ministers.  Good progress has been made in the  clearance and replacement of slums, the surveys of  overcrowding required under the housing acts, 1935, have been completed by local authorities, and  the work of providingnew  accommodation under  those Acts  has been begun.  The high rate  of houseproduction in general has been well maintained.    Acts have been passed  for the improvement of the maternity services  by  theprovision of an organised service of salaried midwives, and for the consolidationand amendment of the law relating to public health.    I have given My assent to a Bill  to amend the  law in England and  Walesrelating to compulsory school attendance and  to assistance  from public fundstowards expenditure on voluntary school buildings; and also to a Bill providingfor the raising of  the school-leaving age in Scotland and for certain improvements in the educational system, in particular  as regards children suffering fromphysical and mental defects.    Action has been taken, in co-operation with Local Authorities, to improveand extend the provision of physical education in the schools.    Measures have  been enacted providing for a solution of the problem of titherentcharge upon a permanent footing, and for the maintenance of the beet sugar industry as part  of the general agricultural  policy of this country.   Assistanceto the cattle and dairying sections of the agricultural industry has been continued.    An Act has been passed for insuring agricultural workers against unemploy-ment, which will  enable such workers, if unemployed during the coming winter,to receive benefit.    I have given My assent  to Bills to  facilitate  the  elimination of surplusproductive capacity in the spinning section of the cotton industry, and to continue for a further year  the temporary subsidy  granted to  tramp shipping  in 1935.Steps have been taken to enable the selling arrangements of the coal industry tobe co-ordinated.    A number of other measures of public utility have been added  to the statute book.    In bidding you farewell, I pray that the  blessing of Almighty God may rest upon  your labours.

</content>
</cab>
