<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/264/0 images: 467-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
all this DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.     I circulate a memorandum prepared by the Board of Tradeafter interdepartmental discussion.   M. Rueff.  the french representative, will return to London in a few days tocontinue his exploratory talks.     It is necessary for us to decide whether the possiblestimulus to action by France and other Powers outweighs the dangers of multilateral negotiations and of their possiblefailure.   If we are to go further, we must also decide onthe method and, in particular, on the suggestion thatM. van Zeeland should be asked to take soundings.SECRET.O.P.277(56).INTERNATIONAL ACTION TOWARDS RELAXATION OF           OBSTACLES TO TRADE.Note by the President of the Board of Trade.W.R.Board of Trade,23rd October,  1936.
   Ijaternational Action towards relaxation of obstacles to trade.                M em c r an dura by the Board of Trade.   1. The  joint Anglo-French-American Declaration of September 26th stated  that the three Governments &quot;attach the greatest importance to action being taken without delay to relax progressively the present systems of quotas and exchange controls with a view to their abolition.&quot;  The recent League of Nations Assembly adopted a  resolution strongly endorsing the policy set out in the Three- Power Declaration and recommended &quot;all States to organise,without any delay, determined and continuous action to ensure its application.&quot;   2, His Majesty&apos;s Government have purposely refrained from making suggestions as to the form which international co-operation for this purpose might take, feeling that the initiative should properly  come from the 1 devaluing&apos; countries, particularly France, which has the most extensive system of quotas ever known.   At the Assembly the French privately suggested that a conference should  be held limited to those Towers which had adhered to the Three-Power Declaration with a view to developing trade among those countries.   In view of the objections raised by the United Kingdom representativesf the French did not proceed with this proposal.   Recently,  however, M. Rueff,  of the French Ministry of  Finance has visited London, and in conversation with Sir F.  Leith-Ross,  has outlined a further idea,  viz. that some agreement might be reached between the &quot;free currency&quot;  countries to  abolish their industrial quotas as bet^enritjieiaselves.  3, M.  Rueff did not  ap )ear to have gone at all deeply into his idea,  and has now returned to Paris to explore  certain aspects of  it.   He expressed  his willingness to  return to London towardsthe end of October for further consultations and. it is  desirablethat before then H.M.  Government1s attitude in  the matter shouldbe  settled as far as possible.   Accordingly the  matter has  been discussed at a meeting under the  Chairmanship of  the FinancialSecretary to the Treasury,  at which Sir.F.Leith-Ross and officials *See telegrams Nos.123 and 129 to Geneva, annexed.                         -1-
 of the Treasury, Board  of Trade and Foreign Office were present. The following  points  emerged  in the discussions at the meeting.   4. There  are three  possible methods for relaxing quotas:-      (i) unilateral  action by the countries concerned;     (ii) bilateral agreements;     (iii)  a multilateral agreement or agreements. Unilateral  action by  the devaluing countries is not likely to go far, at  any rate in present conditions;  such steps as they have already  taken  in this direction are insignificant.   The present French Government appear genuinely anxious to secure some measure of  liberation  of international trade, but they are faced with strong opposition at  home to  any large scale relaxation of their quotas:  this  opposition they might be assisted to overcome if there were  some appearance of effective end concerted international action for  the  alleviation of exceptional trade obstacles.  5, Of  bilateral agreements  it may be said that they are the only means  by which it has been found possible in the past tomake any impression on barriers to international trade.   As a means of bringing about the relaxation of quotas,  they are likely to  be slow  and  piecemeal in their results,  but the use of this method,  as  opportunity serves, is by no means to be excluded,  S, Such possibilities as there may be of bringing about some early and large-scale action seem to lie in the multilateralmethod.   But the difficulties involved in this must not be overlooked.   Previous attempts to reduce trade barriers bymultilateral action,  such as the League  of Nations Convention forthe Abolition of Import Prohibitions and Restrict ions  of 1927,*and the  &apos;Tariff Truce1 negotiations of 1930-31,  were completefailures owing to the diverse situations of the various countries and the  impossibility of getting them to &apos;march in step&apos;.    Inmultilateral negotiations the pace is  that  of the  slowest;   thecomplexities tend to become unmanageable and the resultant
 The following points emerged in the discussions at the meeting.  4. There are three possible methods for relaxing quotas:-      (i) unilateral action by the countries concerned;     (ii) bilateral agreements;     (iii) a multilateral agreement or agreement s* Unilateral action by the devaluing countries is not likely to go far, at any rate in present conditions;  such steps as they have already taken in this direction are insignificant.   The present French Government appear genuinely anxious to secure some measure of liberation of international trade,  but they are faced Yrilth strong opposition at home to any large scale relaxation of their quotas:  this opposition they might be assisted to overcome if there were some appearance of effective and concerted international action for the alleviation of exceptional trade obstacles.  5. Of bilateral agreements it may be said that they are the only means by which it has been found possible in the past tomake any impression on barriers to international trade.   As a means of bringing about the relaxation of quotas,  they are likely to be slow and piecemeal in their results, but the use of this method, as opportunity serves, is by no- means to be excluded.  6. Such possibilities as there may be of bringing about some early and large-scale action seem to lie in the multilateralmethod.   But the difficulties involved in this must not be overlooked.   Previous attempts to reduce trade barriers bymultilateral action, such as the League: of Nations Convention forthe Abolition of Import Prohibitions and Restrictions  of 1927and the &quot;Tariff Truce&apos;  negotiations of 1930-31,  were completefailures owing to the diverse situations of the various countries and the impossibility of getting them  to Tmarch in step1.    In.multilateral negotiations the pace is  that of the  slowest;  thecomplexities tend to bocome unmanageable and the resultant
agreements almost always founder in a sea of  reservations andconditional ratifications.   7.  This country has a number of quotas which need  to beconsidered from the point of H .1VL Government&apos;s possibleparticipation in any multilateral negotiations.,  These are (1)the agricultural quotas, (2) the duty-quotas  on iron and steel,introduced in connection with  the international cartel and aimed at restricting imports from the non-cartel countries, and (3) the textile quotas introduced in the Colonies to  deal with japanese competition,.  Particular justifications can,  of course., beadduced for each of these, but they would be  open to attack inany international discussions and would need  to be excluded fromthe scope of any international agreement.   8.  Further difficulties will arise in any international discussions as regards the position of Germany and Italy.  germany is quite unlikely to withdraw her exchange control in presentconditions, and the same is true of the Italian exchange and import restrictions, notwithstanding the devaluation of the lira.Politically the Foreign Office regard it as most important toavoid any appearance of an economic front directed against German;/and there would also be danger from the economic point of view in H.M. Government&apos;s being drawn as a consenting party into adiscriminatory &apos;club,*   On the other hand, the French Governmentare known to be unwilling to remove their quotas in favour of countries which retain exchange controls, and some otherGovernments will probably take the same line.  It has beensuggested that the difficulty might be overcome if any agreementbetween the &apos;free currency&apos;  countries were open to the adherenceof Germany and Italy, but this would presuppose the willingness of the latter countries to drop their restrictions, which in factthey are quite unlikely to do at present.   9.  However, notwithstanding these various difficulties,  thepresent seems the psychological moment&apos;  for attempting some                        &apos; -3-
action in the international  sphere, and it is felt that thepossibility of a multilateral agreement ought to he explored.H.M. Governments participation in any such agreement should hesubject to the conditions that (a) broadly speaking, they shouldnot he called on to do more than maintain their present &quot;non-exclusive&quot; import policy:  (b) that their agricultural quotas,iron and steel duty quotas and Colonial textile quotas must hepreserved and (c) that any agreement should not he exclusiveor discriminatory but should at least he open to the accession ofGermany and other countries which have not free exchanges.  Theobject to he aimed at should, in general, he the enlargement ofquotas rather than their complete abolition, which, particularlyin the case of coal, would he likely to injure United kingdom interests.   10.  In view of the risk that a &apos;multilateral1 attempt mayfail, and since a public failure would mean a serious set-hack,the ground should he carefully prepared beforehand by means ofprivate  soundings before any international meeting, howeverinformal, is called together.  A large international conference is clearly ruled out, and association with the League of Nationsmust also be avoided if there is to he any chance of german participation-  It might he appropriate that, as suggested byM.   Rueff, &quot;the Belgian Prime Minister, Mo van Zeeland, should he asked to undertake soundings.  He urged, at the July Assembly ofthe League of Nations, the importance of reviving international trade as a means of appeasement and should he well-placed toundertake the task of approaching other Powers, especially Germanyand Italy, should it be decided that such an approach should bemade - a question which will need further consideration in view ofthe present political state of Europe.  Subject to the resultsof this further consideration, it is suggested that M. van Zeelandmight be asked to sound (a) the &apos; free currency&apos; countries and(h) Germany, Italy and perhaps a few other countries still
  possessing exchange restrictionso   The object of his  soundings  would he to ascertain whether there was a sufficient  probability  of the countries concerned participating in an agreement  for the  progressive abolition of quotas and exchange controls to  make it  worth while to summon an international committee of experts  to  work out a draft agreement in detail.   The United States  Government would need to be kept informed at all stages and.  given the opportunity of participating should they desire to  do so oBoard of Trade,   23rd October, 1936.
                                                      .317                                                 ANNEXE  Tele gram No.123 to  Geneva. Cypher telegram  to British Delegation (Geneva).    Foreign Office, 4th October,  1936.     3.0 p.m. No.123.     Geneva telegrams Nos.  146 L.N and 79 and CO Saving.     Following from the Chancellor of the Exchequer for mr. Morrison,    You can assure French Delegation that we entirely approveand that you will be  prepared publicly to support the objectivewhich they have in view, namely the progressive relaxation of thepresent system of quotas and exchange control with a view to theirabolition.    But I am seriously concerned about proposals for a conferenceoutlined in 146 L.N.  which  appear to present some very dangerouspossibilities and I regret to see that statements have appeared in the  telegraphic news to the effect that agreement has alreadybeen reached on most  points with the British Delegation which willsecond the French project.    The French must understand that wecannot be rushed into decisions which might have fair-re aching..results without full  consideration and consultation beforehand.    I sincerely hope, therefore, that in the interests of theco-operation which we both desire, they will refrain from proposing a conference or making other proposals for international action until we have had time to communicate our views.   These will be forwarded as soon as  possible after discussion with President ofthe Board of Trade, but I cannot promise anything for Monday.    Meanwhile, for your own information, it seems to me that muchharm may be done by a conference unless preceded by full and careful consideration not only of the matters for discussion, but of the parties to be  summoned,,   The proposal to include Russia
me likely to produce the worst impression in the two lattercountries, already resentful and suspicious of the Three power declaration on currency.   I should fear that any hasty statementmight finally destroy  all chance of the proposed. Five power conference as well as any efforts which may he made (and to which,we understands the French Government attach much importance) to restore the cordiality of.Anglo-Italian relations.    This telegram has been seen by president of the Board, ofTrade who entirely agrees.    Repeated to Washington No.,522 and en clair to Paris (Saving)No.32.
Telegram No.129  to  Geneva.Cypher telegram  to  British  Delegation (Geneva)   Foreign Office,  6th October 1936, 6.00 p.m.No.129.IMMEDIATE.    Following from Chancellor of Exechequer and President, Boardof Trade,  for Mr.  Morrison.    Your telegram  No.153.  1. We  fully agree with the line taken.   The question of aConference,  involving inter  alia the whole position of Germany,cannot be  decided  without  full consideration and consultations betweenthe three  powers and for the present we are not prepared, to commit ourselves  to any Conference.  2. You. will bear in mind the distinction between the countrieswhich have devalued and therefore have ground for reducing tariffs and removing restrictions  and those countries like ours who areliable to  feel the effect  of increased competition from the devaluedstates.    You appreciate also and should emphasise the essential difference between our quotas and those of continental states.  3. You might emphasise to  the French that we have already made our contribution to general  recovery in undertaking to refrain from.monetary or commercial retaliation and at the outset we wish to knowwhether  the French and other governments which have now devalued.would be ready (as the result, in M. Bastide&apos;s words of the disappearance of control over commerce and foreign exchange) to make further  reductions of tariffs and enlarge or abolish further quotaswithout  asking us  for any  change in our policy.  4. we  think that any public reference to a Conference would be disastrous unless  and until  definite agreements have been reached between  states which the Conference could ratify.   The peal burden                               -1-
of action lies with those states which have  hitherto  felt  themselvesobliged to protect their currencies  by the existing restrictions on trade.  5. If it appears that any basis for  a successful conference is likely to exist we think Anglo-French preliminary  discussions could best take place in London.  We  accept French suggestion  of sending a preparatory message to United States  Government  providedwe see  the draft and approve it before despatch.    Repeated to Washington No.329 and  to Paris  No,86  Saving  (by Bag).

</content>
</cab>
