<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/225/0 images: 162-167</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1931.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy- No.     9CP. 310 (31).CABINET.[C 9083/172/62] No. 1.Sir John Simon to Lord Tyrrell (Paris).(No. 2908.)My Lord, Foreign O^ice, December 4, 1931.THE French Ambassador called on me this evening and handed to me the enclosed note from M. Briand expounding in seven paragraphs the position of the French Government in regard to the problem of reparations. He told me that copies of the note were being contemporaneously delivered to the other Governments concerned in the matter. I asked him if this included America and Germany, and he said that he supposed so, but was not sure.M. de Fleuriau went on to say that M. Briand contemplated that there would be a conference of Governments following as soon as possible the report of the Advisory Committee. He thought it should take place some time in January. I asked if any proposals were being made as to the place of meeting. The Ambassador replied that Biarritz had been mentioned, but that the Germans thought this was too far away; the same would apply to Cannes. M. de Fleuriau mentioned no other place, and I gathered that this question was quite open. He added that M. Briand hoped, after we had studied, his note, that there might be an opportunity for some consultation or exchange of views between the French and British Governments on the subject before the conference was held. I thanked him for his communication and promised that the note would be carefully studied without delay.Passing to another subject, I mentioned to him his suggestion that a deputation of French experts should come over to London and see the Board of Trade next Monday on what he had described on an earlier occasion as &quot; commercial negotiations.&quot; I said I was sorry if there had been any misunder-standing as to this, and he at once made light of this aspect of the matter. In order to make the position entirely plain, I gave him an aide-memoire, of which I attach a copy.M. de Fleuriau said that in the circumstances he thought that the deputation would not be coming over next week, but that he hoped that later on, say in January or February, some meetings could be arranged which would be useful. He said that he had been anxious to arrange for some such meetings last October, but could not at that time propose it on his own responsibility. If that had happened, it might have prevented action being taken which had raised trouble since he did not tell me what he referred to. Even if such meetings did not produce agreement, they still had a valuable effect in improving our relations and might enable the avoidance of irritating and unintended consequences. The Ambassador is evidently strongly impressed with the desirability of keeping in close touch on these matters, though he realises that at the moment the suggestion of such negotiations is premature.I am, &amp;c.JOHN SIMON.6105   [6285]
Enclosure 1 in No. 1.Le point de vue franqais dans la question des Reparations.AIT moment ou le Gouvernement allemand vient d&apos;adresser a la Banque des Reglements Internationaux la demande de reunion du Comite Consultatif special prevu par le Plan Young, il convient de definir la position du Gouvernement francais au regard du probleme des Reparations :1. Les grandes lignes en out deja ete traeeesdans la communication publiee a Washington, le 25 Octobre, et qui a marque la communaute de vues des Gouverne-ments francais et americain sur les points essentiels de la question. Ce communique porte notamment:&quot;Nous avons examine .... 1&apos;effet de la depression sur le reglement des dettes intergouvernementales, nous reconnaissons qu&apos;avant 1&apos;expiration de l&apos;ann e de suspension Hoover, un arrangement couvrant la periode de depression economique peut etre necessaire, arrangement sur les termes et conditions duquel les deux Gouvernements font toutes reserves. L&apos;initiative de cet arrangement devrait etre prise par les Puissances europeennes, principalement interessees, dans le cadre des accords en vigueur avant le 1&quot; juillet 1931.&quot;Pour eviter tout malentendu, il convient de noter que le Memorandum remis par le Gouvernement allemand a la B.R.I., pour demander la convocation du Comite&quot; Consultatif, s&apos;il a ete soumis au prealable au Gouvernement francais, n&apos;a pas ete redige d&apos;accord avec ce dernier et ne 1&apos;engage pas.Les modifications intervenues a la demande du Gouvernement francais ont eu pour seul objet d&apos;eviter que la France se trouve dans 1&apos;obligation d&apos;elever des reserves a 1&apos;encontre de tel ou tel passage du memorandum. Elle garde done son entiere liberte d&apos;action et d&apos;entente avec les autres Puissances creancieres.2. L Allemagne demeure liee par les engagements qu&apos;elle a librement et solennellement contracted a La Haye. La procedure exceptionnelle suggeree en Juin dernier par le President des Ltats-Unis, sous la pression des circonstances, n&apos;apporte, aux termes memes des diflerentes notes du Gouvernement americain, aucune atteinte a la validite des accords anterieurs. Aussi bien le communique de&apos; Washington prevoit-il 1&apos;ouverture des negociations &quot;dans le cadre des accords existants.&quot; En recourant a la&apos; procedure institute par le Plan. Young, en vue d&apos;obtenir, a 1&apos;expiration du Moratorium Hoover, les allegements que peuvent exiger ies circonstances, le Reich a pris une initiative qui, dans son interet meme de deb&apos;rapporteur de bonne foi, doit ecarter toute equivoque sur la validite de ce plan.3. Dans sa demande de reunion du Comite Consultatif, le Gouvernement allemand insiste sur le fait que les facilites de paiement prevues par le Plan Young ne reponclent plus a. la situation, actuelle.Tout en observant que 1&apos;Allemagne porte pour une large part la responsabilite des difficultes financieres dans lesquelles elle se debat, le Gouvernement franrais est pret a admettre que la crise economique, dont 1&apos;amplitude et 1&apos;acuite, quelles qu&apos;en soient les causes, depassent toutes les previsions, puisse motiver un amenagement egalement temporaire du Plan Young-lie a un arrangement relatif aux dettes intergouvernementales.line transformation radicale du Plan Young, pour tenir compte de difficultes serieuses, mais temporaires, ne saurait toutefois se justifier; un nouvel examen de la situation de la capacite de. paiements permanents de 1&apos;Allemagne, a snpposer qu&apos;i.1 soit jama is necessaire de reviser h cet egard les conclusions dji Plan Young, ne serait :l&apos;ail!eurs en aucun ens possible en periode de crise aigue.Aussi ramcnagement a intervenir devra-t-il avoir une duree limit.ee a la periode de depression et, pour se tenir dans le cadre du plan, ne pas depasser deux annees, delai de moratorium maximum prevu par les accords rle La Haye.4. L&apos;enquete du Comite Consultatif special pourra porter sur les demandes du Gouvernement allemand, sur r.ense.mble de la situation economique et financiere de 1&apos;Allemagne, compte tenu de tons les elements qui 1&apos;affectent, la question des dettes privees de 1&apos;Allemagne etant un de ces elements.Le probleme que cette derniere question soul eve doit demeurer toutefois distinct de celui des Reparations et sa solution, qui incombe sur le plan prive&quot; aux
debiteurs allemands et aux creanciers etrangers, relevede la competence du Comite. Tout en etant traites parallelement, ces deux problemes ne doivent pas etre confondus.Pour sa part, la France s&apos;est toujours gardee cVengager a courts termes, pour des montants importants, ses capitaux en Allemagne et d&apos;assumer les risques qui etaient la contrepartie de benefices immediatement recherehes. Elle ne saurait prendre aujourd&apos;hui, a son propre compte, les consequences d&apos;une politique qu&apos;elle n&apos;a pratiqu^e que dans une tres faible mesure.Par ailleurs, on ne doit pas perdre de vue que le Plan Young et les accords de La Haye, en commereialisant la partie inconditionnelle des annuit^s de reparations, ont de ce fait assimile cette tranche, sans en modifier 1&apos;origine, aux dettes exterieures de droit prive du Reich.La France ne saurait accepter qu&apos;une priorite quelconque fut attribute au probleme des dettes privees par rapport a celui des Reparations et du regime qui interviendra a 1&apos;expiration du Moratorium Hoover.5. Aussi bien le probleme a resoudre se pr&amp;ente-t-il, de 1&apos;avis du Gouvernement francais, d&apos;une maniere plus generale.II s&apos;agit de savoir si le Reich affirmant sa volonte de respecter ses engage-ments dans toute la mesure de ses possibilites, des solutions peuvent etre trouvees qui restaureront sa circulation et permettront, par la-meme, la reprise de 1&apos;activite economique financiere normale, non seulement en Allemagne, mais dans tous les pays interess^s.La tache du Comite Consultatif, conformement aux stipulations du Plan Young, consistera done essentiellement dans 1&apos;etude approfondie de la situation allemande presente, sous Tangle, non pas de la eapacite de paiement permanente, mais des possibilites de relevement de 1&apos;Allemagne.Cet examen, qui devra faire toute la lumiere indispensable pour permettre 1&apos;adoption ulterieure de decisions graves, devra porter tant en ce moment sur les charges budgetaires, sur le poids de la cette Publique, charges fiscales, analyse des depenses et particulierement des differentes categories de subventions allouees par le Reich a 1&apos;industrie, que sur les charges de la Reicbsbank et de 1&apos;industrie et sur les questions monetaires, comme revaluation et 1&apos;utilisation des ressources en devises de 1&apos;Allemagne et surtout cles avoirs allemands a 1&apos;etranger.Le Comite devra en definitive degager par voie de conclusions generales les mesures a prendre par le Reich pour restaurer son credit, les Gouvernements gardant la responsa^bilite du choix des decisions a prendre dans le domaine des reparations pour rendre possible la realisation de ces mesures.Ee Gouvernement francais envisage favorablement a cet effet la reunion d&apos;une conference intergouvernementale.6. Si le Gouvernement francais a la ferme volonte de conserver, lors de cette conference, le solde qui doit lui revenir sur les paiements au titre du Plan Young, pour les reparations de ses dommages de guerre, cette volonte&quot; n&apos;exclue pas, le moment venu, la recherche, pour une duree tempora^&apos;re^ des modalites de paiement que se reveleraient indispensables pour concilier les divers interets en presence, notamment dans la voie des reparations en nature ou sous la forme de prets oomraerciaux et mobilisables consentis h 1&apos;economie allemande au moyen d&apos;une fraction des annuites inconditionnelles clues pendant la periode de depression.Sous cette reserve et conformement aux dispositions du Plan Young, les annuites inconditionnelles, dont le caractere tant definitif que commercial a ete maintenu dans les accords de La Ha)re, ne sauraient etre remises en question.7. Aux termes du Memorandum des Puissances creancieres joint au Plan Young, la revision des annuites allemandes ne peut intervenir qu&apos;en cas de reduction des dettes interalliees. cette reduction devant etre bonifiee pour partie au Reich, pour partie aux Puissances creancieres. Comme 1&apos;arrangement temporaire a intervenir, les conclusions des experts qui le precederont devront etre subordonnees k 1&apos;accord du Gouvernement americain pour une reduction adequate cles annuites de dettes de guerre.Le Gonvernement francais est d&apos;ailleurs pret a. abandonner a FAllemagne la totalite de la part lui revenant sur la bonification pr6vue au Plan Young, si les autres Puissances sont disposees a consentir le merae sacrifice.
Translation of Memorandum handed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs-by French Ambassador, December 4, 1931.:!    : .     .       . . French Point of View on Reparations.THE German Government having requested the Bank for, International Settlements to summon the Special Advisory Committee provided for in the Young plan, it is desirable to define the position of the French Government in regard to the problem of reparations.1. The position of the French Government has already been outlined in the statement published in Washington on the 25th October, which recorded the, similarity of the views held by the French and United States Governments, on the essential points of the question.   This communique states in particular : :. &quot; We have examined the effect of the depression on the settlement of inter-governmental debts; we recognise that prior to the expiration of the Hoover year of postponement an arrangement covering the period of business depression may be necessary, an arrangement as to the terms and conditions of which the two Governments make all reservations. The initiative in this matter should be taken by the European Powers principally concerned within the framework of the agreements prior to the 1st July, 1931.&quot;In order to avoid all misunderstanding, it should be noted that although the memorandum addressed by the German Government to the Bank for International Settlements requesting the summoning of the Advisory Committee was previously submitted to the French Government, it was not drawn up in agreement with the French Government and is not binding upon them.The sole object of the modifications introduced at the request of the French Government was to avoid the possibility that France might find herself obliged to make reservations regarding any particular passage of the memorandum. France therefore retains complete freedom of action and full liberty to reach agreement with the other creditor Powers.2. Germany remains bound by the engagements which she has freely and solemnly undertaken at The Hague. The exceptional procedure suggested last June by the President of the United States under the pressure of events, does not, as is shown by the actual terms of the different notes from the United States Government, affect in any way the validity of. previous agreements. Moreover, the Washington communique foreshadows the opening of negotiations &quot; within the framework of existing agreements.&quot; In having recourse to the procedure set up under the Young plan with a view to obtaining at the expiration of the Hoover moratorium the reductions which circumstances may make necessary, the Reich has taken a step which, in its own interests as a loyal debtor, should remove all ambiguity as to the validity of that plan.3. The German Government, in their request for the meeting of the Advisory Committee, insist on the fact that facilities of payment envisaged in the Young plan no longer correspond with the present situation.While pointing out that Germany must bear to a large extent the responsi-bility for the financial difficulties which she is combating, the French Govern-mentare prepared to admit that the economic crisis, unforeseeably widespread and severe as it is, may afford grounds for an adjustment (which must also be temporary) of the Young plan combined with an arrangement regarding inter-goveriimental debts.: &apos; A radical transformation of the Young plan with the object of meeting serious but temporary difficulties could not, however, be justified; moreover, supposing that it should ever become necessary to revise the conclusions of the Young plan regarding Germany&apos;s permanent capacity to pay, a fresh examina-tion of that capacity would not in any case be possible during a time of acute crisis. ^Thus, any modification to be made must be limited in time to the period of depression, and, in order, that it nsay remain within the framework of the plan.
must not exceed two years, which is the maximum period of moratorium provided for under The Hague Agreements.4. The. enquiry of the Special Advisory Committee may hear upon the requests made by the German Government, and on the whole economic and financial situation of Germany, account being taken of all the elements which affect the hitter, the question of Germany&apos;s private debts being one of those elements.The problem raised by this latter question should, however, remain distinct from that of reparations, and its solution, which, in the domain of private rights, is a matter for the German debtors and the foreign creditors, is within the competence of the committee. While being treated on parallel lines these two problems must remain separate.For her part France has always abstained from venturing her capital to any important extent in short-term credits in Germany, and has avoided the future risks involved by such quest for present profits. France could not sjwulder the consequences of a policy which she has only followed to a very small pxtent.Besides, it must not be forgotten that the Young plan and The Hague Agreements, by commercialising the unconditional part of the reparations annuities, have thereby assimilated tliis part of fhe debt, though without modifying its origin, to the private foreign debts of the Jieichi.France cannot admit that any priority whatsoever should be accorded to the problem of private debts as against that of reparations, and of the regime which will come into force on the expiration of the Hoover moratorium.5. The problem to be solved may also, in the opinion of the French Government, be regarded from a wider point of view.The question is whether, assuming that the Reich expresses its determination to respect its undertakings as far as lies within its power, solutions can be found which will restore Germany&apos;s currency circulation and will&apos; thereby allow the resumption of normal economic and financial activities not only in Germany but in all the countries concerned. [The task of the Advisory Committee, in accordance with the provisions of the Young plan, will therefore consist essentially in a detailed study Of the present situation of Germany from the point of view not of permanent capacity to pay. but of the prospects of aiding Germany&apos;s recovery.This investigation, which should shed light on these questions to the extent necessary to permit important decisions to be reached later, ought to deal in present circumstances not only with budgetary expenses, the burden of the public debt, fiscal charges, the analysis of expenditure, and particularly of the diffez-ent kinds of subsidies granted to industry by the Reich, but also with the obligations of the Reichsbank and of industry and with monetary questions, such as the valuation and utilisation of Germany&apos;s foreign exchange resources and, above all, German holdings abroad.The committee should, in short, elucidate by means of general conclusions the measures to be taken by the Reich to restore its credit, while the Governments must remain responsible for the decisions to be taken in regard to reparations in order to make it possible for such measures to be carried into effect.The French Government view with favour the calling of an inter-governmental conference for this purpose.6. While the French Government are firmly resolved to keep, at this conference, the net surplus (&quot; solde&quot;) to which they are entitled out of the payments under the Young plan on account of reparation for war damages, that intention does not preclude an enquiry at the appropriate moment into methods of payment which may be found necessary for a limited period to reconcile the various interests at stake, particularly reparations in kind or commercial loans susceptible of being issued to the public to be granted to German economy from part of the unconditional annuities due during the period of depression.With this reserve, and in accordance with the terms of the Young plan, the question of the unconditional annuities, the final and commercial character of which was maintained in The Hague Agreements, cannot be reopened.7. According to the terms of the concurrent memorandum of the creditor-Powers annexed to the Young plan, revision of the German annuities cannot take place except in the case of a reduction of inter-allied debts, the benefit of such[6285] c
reduction accruing partly to the Reich and partly to the creditor Powers. Both the temporary arrangement to be made, and the preliminary conclusion of the experts, will have to be dependent on the United States Government agreeing to an adequate reduction of the war debt annuities.The French Government are, moreover, prepared to give up to Germany the whole of their share in the net benefit which they would receive under the Young plan if the other Powers are prepared to make the same sacrifice.Enclosure 2 in No. 1. Aide-memoire.HIS Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom have given careful consideration to the communications made by the French Ambassador on the 13th November, the 1st December and the 2nd December on the subject of commercial negotiations between Great Britain and France.His Majesty&apos;s Government of course remain ready to hold any useful discussions at the proper time with the representatives of the French Govern-ment, and the Board of Trade will be glad to receive the French delegation if it is still desired that they should come to London on Monday, the 7th December. His Majesty&apos;s Government are, however, doubtful whether a later meeting might not be more useful to all concerned. The emergency action taken by His Majesty&apos;s Government under the Abnormal Importations Act is not to be regarded as a part of the settled fiscal policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government, but has been necessitated by the immediate situation in this country. On the other hand, the subject of future British fiscal policy is not sufficiently advanced for negotiations to be fruitful, so that, while the Board of Trade would be glad to meet the French delegation next week if they decide to come to England, His Majesty&apos;s Government are anxious that they should not feel disappointed if more cannot be accomplished at this stage.For these reasons His Majesty&apos;s Government would suggest, for the consideration of the French Government, that it may be found that a more appropriate time for discussion will arise laterDecember 4, 1931.6

</content>
</cab>
