<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/225/0 images: 201-202</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.](Printed for ihe Cabinet.   December 1931.)SECRET.CP. 313 (31). Copy No.........9CABINET.Eligibility of Indian Cadets for appointment to Sapper andMiner Companies.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.In 1927 it was decided, on the recommendations submitted by the Government of India on the Skeen Committee Report of that year, to admit Indian Cadets to the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich, with a view to their qualifying for appointment to the technical branches of the Indian Army such as Sapper and Miner companies and Mountain Artillery batteries. The following conclusion was recorded in para. 27 of CP. 326 (27), dated 22nd December 1927, and approved by the Cabinet: &quot;In principle there is no objection to the admission of a limited number of Indians to Woolwich, provided that the British standard of admission to and proficiency at Woolwich is rigidly insisted on. Thus, an Indian would only be eligible for appointment to an Indian Service Engineer or Artillery unit if his place on the passing-out list would have qualified him for the Royal Engineers or Royal Artillery had he been a British Cadet.&quot;A system of competitive examination has been established in India at which the papers are identical with those set simultaneously at the Army Group Examination held in this country, except for a few minor adaptations which are considered appropriate to the case of Indian candidates. Thus, every Indian candidate who succeeds in passing into Woolwich must have attained the same qualifying standard as is required in the case of British candidates. Since the examination was instituted six Indian candidates have passed into Woolwich, of whom two are due to pass out at the end of the current term. It is contemplated that an Indian cadet who is accepted for eventual appointment to the Indian Sappers and Miners should, on passing out of Woolwich, undergo the same training as British cadets who are commissioned into the Royal Engineers, viz. that he should undergo a preliminary course at the School of Military Engineering, Chatham, and should then proceed to Cambridge and obtain an Honours Degree in Mechanical Science.But the condition laid down in the last sentence of the decision quoted above is likely to prove somewhat too rigid in practice. If it is to be enforced, the eligibility of Indian Cadets for appointment to Indian Sapper and Miner companies will be governed, not by any fixed standard of qualification, but by the degree of competition prevailing at any given time among British candidates for appointment to the Royal Engineers ; and at present this competition is keen. The spirit of the decision would, to my mind, be observed if a standard of qualification were laid down for Indian aspirants to Sapper and Miner appointments which need not necessarily be related to the standard set tip by competition among British Cadets. The letter of the decision is, however, explicit; and for that reason I submit that it should be altered to the extent shown below.It has been provisionally agreed in consultation with the War Office and the Government of India that an Indian Cadet at Woolwich may suitably be regarded as eligible for appointment to the Indian Sappers and Miners, provided that he has obtained 7U per cent, of the aggregate of marks obtainable throughout the Royal Military Academy course in both Mathematics and Science, and that he is specially recommended by the Commandant as likely both to benefit from the postgraduate course at the School of Military Engineering and to take the required Science Degree at Cambridge.These conditions will probably prove suitable ; but I think it would be better to avoid stereotyping them in the form of a Cabinet decision. It would be enough to lay down as a general principle that special conditions should be prescribed by the Secretary of State for India, in consultation with the War Office and the Government
of India, in regard to the eligibility of Indian Cadets at Woolwich for appointment to Sapper and Miner companies, and I ask that this principle may be approved.It is not considered that similar conditions are necessary in the case of candidates for appointment to Indian Mountain Artillery units, since in their case success in passing into and out of Woolwich should be a sufficient guarantee in itself of their standard of attainment, and moreover, the question of their fitness to undergo an exacting test such as an Honours course at Cambridge does not arise.The new conditions would apply only to Indian candidates for the technical branches of the Army who have been or will be hereafter admitted to Woolwich. The whole question of the method of training of Indian candidates at a central institution in India will, of course, require separate consideration, but it does not arise in this connection.India Office,9th December 1931.S. XL

</content>
</cab>
