<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/49/33 images: 272-275</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 233.29th April, 1944.V &apos;WAR CABINET/FREE SIAMESE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.WITH reference to the Foreign Secretary&apos;s Paper W.P. (44) 208 about theissue of a declaration regarding Siam, I think that the War Cabinet will wishto take into special consideration the telegram received last month from theAustralian Government on the subject, a copy of which is annexed hereto.It will be seen that the Australian view is very doubtful regarding thedesirability of the immediate issue of a declaration, and in particular that theyare anxious that we should not undertake any commitments regarding Siamwhich would prevent future security arrangements in South-East Asia.I should like to suggest that it might be useful if a convenient opportunitycan be found for this point to be discussed with Mr. Curtin while he is here.C.Dominions Office, S.W.A,29th April, 1944.ANNEX. -(Telegram from Australian Government to Secretary of State forDominion Affairs of 2 th March, 1944.(No. 73.)YOUR telegrams D. Nos. 265 and 266 [giving text of proposed declaration].1. We assume declaration is proposed for political warfare purposes, andwould be glad if we could be informed more fully of reasons for making adeclaration. Timing would be important, and we are not aware of circumstances which would make early declaration appropriate.2. Last paragraph of telegram D. No. 265, however, suggests that draft declaration might also have purpose of sounding United States attitude to futureof Siam.  Any indications received would interest us.3. In regard to content of declaration, Australian Government is ingeneral accord with policy of re-establishing Siam as a free and independent state. Considering, however, our direct and vital interest in the post-war settle-ment in South-East Asia, especially in provisions for security, we feel it should always be in mind in any dealings concerning Siam that there should be nocommitments regarding Siam&apos;s independent statehood which would hinder orpreclude satisfactory arrangements to ensure strategic requirements of security in this region. We are also concerned that independence should not be interpreted to the prejudice of arrangements for collaboration in development and welfare.4. We would hope that at the International Conference contemplated inArticle 34 of Australian-New Zealand Agreement opportunity would be taken to exchange information and views on position of Siam as part of a general Pacificsettlement.[27373]




</content>
</cab>
