<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/4/0 images: 90-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[TM3 Document is the Property of Hfe Britannic Majesty&apos;s Goveyani-BDt.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1917.SECRET. TO^J1WAR CABINET, 232.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onThursday, September 13, 1917, at 1T30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, HP. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of   The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E. M.P.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P. LieutenanoGeneral the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord R. Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.General Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (for Minutes 1 to Id).Brigadier-General B. E. W. Childs,C.M.G., Director of Personal Service(for Minute Id).Vice-Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss. K.C.B.,G.M.G., M.V.O., Deputy First Sea Lord(for Minutes 1 to 14).i Mr. E. G. Pretyman, M.P., Admiralty(for Minute 15).The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies (for Minutes12 to 16).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.French Ministry. 1. THE Acting  Secretary of  State  for   Foreign  affairs reported that M. Painleve had formed a Ministry which includedno Socialists, and consequently excluded M. Albert Thomas.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated, however, thathe had received information to the effect that there might be another hitch in the proceedings before the Ministry was definitelyformed.Guns for Italy. 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported a message from General Cadorna expressing his thanks for the artilleryreinforcements which the Allies had jointly agreed to send to Italy.The guns might have left France in a week&apos;s time.
^3%: 3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that therciga jjront. available information indicated  that the  Germans were notadvancing in the Riga region, but that a concentration was takingplace at Jacobstadt, further south. The fact of their not advance-ing might be attributed either to their intention of saving men orto their inability to pursue their advantage owing to the impossibility of moving off the roads and to other transport difficulties.Roumanian Front. 4. On the Roumanian Front the moral of the Russian army was very low. The soldiers of the 6th Army were threateningto go home if peace was not signed by the 15th of this month.Caucasus Front. 5. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported  that,according to his latest information, the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos;Committees had taken charge of the telegraph office at RussianHeadquarters in the Caucasus. The British Military Represen-tative there reported that his communications were liable tointerruption.Arrest of Generals. 6. With reference to the Press reports that Russian generalshad been arrested, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff reportedthat only one general, namely, General Denski, commanding theSouth-West Army, had been actually arrested ; the other generals,although nominally arrested, remained in command.The Situation inRussia.7. With reference to War Cabinet 231, Minute 3, the WarCabinet noted that the action taken-by them to urge M. Kerenskyand General Korniloff to come together had anticipated the recom-mendations of the British Ambassador at Petrograd and GeneralBarter.Soldiers&apos;Dependants.8. The War Cabinet had their attention called to an articlem the &quot; Daily Chronicle &quot; in regard to the alleged meanness of theWar Office in dealing, for instance, with soldiers&apos; wives, who, whenthey have to go into the workhouse hospitals, have their separation allowances and allotments stopped.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to ascer-tain the opinion of the Finance Department of the WarOffice on the subject, and to bring their views to the WarCabinet on the following day.Submarines.bombing operations.9. The Deputy  First  Sea Lord gave an  account of thesubmarine situation.   He reported that one of our aeroplanes had dropped bombs on an enemy submarine in the North Sea, and it-was hoped that the submarine had been sunk, though it was not definitely proved.10. Admiral Wemyss reported the bombing of Bruges andZeebrugge, including one direct hit on a large destroyer alongside the Zeebrugge Mole.
National War 12. With reference to War Cabinet 221, Minute 2, attentionMemorial Museum,   was drawn to the publication in the &quot; Daily Telegraph &quot; and othernewspapers of an article giving details of the proposals which hadbeen set forth in the Secret Paper G.T.-1650.The War Cabinet instructed The Secretary to write to Sir Alfred Mond, stating that theattention of the Cabinet had been drawn to the fact thatthe proposals, which were sub judice. had been widelydivulged to the newspapers, evidently with an attempt to capture public opinion, and inviting him to endeavour toascertain how the leakage occurred, and to report theresults of his enquiries to the War Cabinet.Prevention of 13. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theExport of Printed War Office and Department of Information in regard to theMatter. prevention of export of printed matter (Paper G.T.-1332).The War Cabinet decided To refer this question  to  a Committee, composed  of  thefollowing : Sir Edward Carson (in the chair).Sir George Cave.Lord Derby (or his representative).Lord Robert Cecil (or his representative).Leave for New 14. The War Cabinet had under consideration a memorandumZealand Troops. by the Secretary of State for War in regard to leave for NewZealand troops after three years&apos; service (Paper G.T.-1973). Inthis paper the views of the Adjutant-General were set forth, to theeffect that if leave after three years&apos; service, on the scale of sixmonths from the departure from the Front until return, or twomonths&apos; leave of absence in the United Kingdom or France for those Avho did not wish to take it in New Zealand, were to be givento New Zealanders, irrespective of the military situation at theFront, the same measure must be meted out to all troops,Dominions or British, ,with the result that the force at the Frontwould be completely depleted. If the privilege was confined tothe Dominion troops a spirit of strong antagonism would, in theopinion of the Adjutant-General, spring up between the Britishand Dominion troops, and might result in bloodshed.Admiral Wemyss reported  that  the Admiralty were  alsoopposed to the scheme of leave for New Zealanders as proposed.The War Cabinet decided That the Secretary of State for the Colonies should send atelegram to New Zealand presenting the views of theAdmiralty and War Office : the two latter departments to forward the material for the telegram to the Secretaryof State for the Colonies.Mexican Oil 15. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum (PaperProperties. , G.T.-2000) in regard to preventing the sale by Messrs. S. Pearsonand Sons of their Mexican oil properties to purchasers in Americaor elsewhere.Naval Situation in 11. Admiral Wemyss reported that an enemy  cruiser andBaltic. destroyers had attempted to enter the Gulf of Riga, but had been driven off by the Russian batteries. With regard to the RussianFleet, there was no change in the situation. The Russian fleet was still in the Gulf of Finland, behind minefields.
A suggestion was made that the Prime Minister should beasked to see Lord Cowdray on the subject.It was strongly urged that there should be legislation to givethe Government power to deal with these and other cases of sales of property to foreigners.Lord Robert Cecil stated that he had a similar question tobring forward with regard to the sale of copper mines. He under-took to bring the Law Officers&apos; opinion on the general question tothe War Cabinet on the following day.Inadequacy of 16. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum byHousing &quot; Mr.   Barnes   (Paper   G.T.-1758)   drawing   attention  to   the accommodation.      inadequacy of housing accommodation in Barrow and certain parts of Scotland and Wales.Mr. Barnes reported that at Barrow the Ministry ofMunitions were putting up 250 houses, but these were onlyintended for munition workers, and did not by any means providefor the needs of the district. A shocking report had been received as to the conditions at Barrow, Avhere the population during thewar had risen from 60,000 to 86,000, and where even before thewar the housing conditions had been serious.The War Cabinet decided That Mr. Barnes should consult with the Ministry ofMunitions and the Local Government Board on thesubject, and bring the question again to the WarCabinet.(Initialled)      A. B. L.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,September 13, 1917.Q

</content>
</cab>
