<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/4/0 images: 106-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]   -    g ^Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1917.secret war CABINET, 235.59Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Tuesday, September 18, 1917, at 11*30 a.m.Present!:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right. Hon. Sir Edward Carson,K.C., M.P. (for Minute 13).Lieutenant-general. C. Smuts, K.C.the    Right    Hon.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. A. J. balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs. -Major-General Sir G. M. W. Magdonogh,K.C.M.G., C.B., Director of military intelligence.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India (for minute 13).The Right Hon. John Hodge, M.P.,Minister of Pensions (for Minute 12).Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B.,O.M., G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff (for Minutes 1to 11).The Right Hon. T. J. Macnamara, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Admiralty (for minute 13).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minute 13).Sir Charles Harris, K.C.B., AssistantFinancial secretar-, War Office (for minutes 12 and 13).Colonel W. Dally Jones, C.M.G., Acting Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.The Russian Front. 1. THE Director of Military Intelligence reported that therewas no fresh news in regard to the fighting on the Russian front.A serious aspect of the general situation was that a large numberof Austrian prisoners had been escaping; no fewer than 9,000Austrians had returned to their own lines on the sector of the ThirdAustrian Army alone.With reg-ard to Riga operations, very few Russian prisoners had been taken, but there had been 10,000 deserters.Protection of 2. The Director of Military Intelligence read a telegram, datedBritish Embassy at the 15th September, 1917, from the British Military Attache at petrograd.! Petrograd stating that the Minister for Foreign Affairs at Petrogradhad asked what steps had been taken for the safety of the Embassy,[1365-235]
having regard to the 1&apos;act that war had been declared by the new government on the Soviet, and that trouble was expected in theimmediate future. It was not considered desirable to have a Russianguard posted outside the Embassy, for fear of exciting attention.Since last Tuesday, however, there had been a guard of Britishairmen and gunners, who, when General Korniloffs force hadmarched on Petrograd, had been withdrawn from Tsarskoe Selo and district.Arabia. 3. The Director of Military Intelligence reported the receipt ofa message from General Wingate announcing that a force of turks had been defeated by the Sherif Shakir, a relative of the King of the hejaz, on the railway line north of Medina.Uoumania. -1. The Director of Military Intelligence pointed out that our information in regard to operations in Roumania was faulty, because: all communication had been cut off during the last week, and theonly information obtainable was that derived from the Russiancommuuiques. As far as was known, however, there was no indication of an enemy offensive on that front. It appeared thatthe greatest risk for Roumania lay in the event of the failure of theRussian troops to support the Roumanian flanks.The Italian Front. 5. The Director of Military Intelligence stated that one and a half divisions were definitely known to have come from Galicia tothe Isonzo front, and perhaps one more division. The Italians hadnot attacked lately, but they had repelled a strong Austrian attackon the 16th September on the Bainsizza Plateau.Air Offensive. 6. The First Sea Lord reported that a successful bombing raidon Ghistelles Aerodrome had taken place. All our machines had returned safely.Convoys. 7. The   First  Sea Lord reported that the total number ofmerchant-ships at present under convoy amounted to 353. Thesteamship &quot; arab is,&quot; which had been lagging behind her convoy,had been torpedoed and lost, although the convoy was only proceeding at a speed of 6 knots. The failure of the &quot; arab is &quot; to keep up withthe convoy was probably due to a foul bottom.German 8. The First Sea Lord reported that the Germans had now gotSubmarines. more submarines operating than ever before, but it seemed improbable that they woxdd be able to keep up this effort. It was possible thatthis increased concentration might have some connection wuth recentGerman &quot; peace-kites.&quot; It was satisfactory that up to date thesuccess of the enemy submarines had not been commensurate withtheir increased numbers.Mine-laying. 9. The First Sea Lord reported that the new pattern of ourmines was satisfactory, but that he had nothing like enough of them.There were 100,000 mines on order, but of these only 400 were atpresent delivered ; it was hoped that 2,000 a month would beobtained during the next two or three months, working up to amaximum of 9,000 a month. Should the latter figure be realised,however, there would not be enough mine-layers to lay such a quantity. - The United States Government had been appealed to for;assistance in the matter of mine-layers, but they had only got two. of these vessels.
QOW.C. 235Battle-Cruisers. 10. The First Sea Lord said that the battle-cruiser situation was likely to become most serious. From information received it was expected that in 1919 the Germans, who were laying down battle-cruisers only, would have ten&apos; battle-cruisers, of which all exceptone would be superior to our nine, and four or five of our vesselswould be of no great, comparative value. He was proposing to ask the War Cabinet in the near future whether the work which hadbeen stopped on battle-cruisers could not be recommenced.In this connection the possibility of purchasing battle-cruisersfrom the Japanese was discussed. While the general opinion wasthat it seemed unlikely that the Japanese would be willing to sellbattle-cruisers, it was suggested that they might be willing to exchange battle-cruisers for battleships.British Exhibits toAssist LibertyLoan in America.Soldiers&apos;Dependants.Proposed Increaseof Soldiers&apos; and sailors&apos; Pay.11. The Chancellor of the Exchequer reported a telegram from lord Reading asking for some Tanks to be sent over to America forpurposes of exhibit, to assist in the raising of the Liberty Loan.The Director of Military Intelligence undertook to look intothis question.In this connection the First Sea Lord reported that the americans were also asking for a submarine captured from theenemy.The War Cabinet decided that If a German submarine was sent, it was of importance that itshould be one captured by the British and not by theFrenc .12. With reference to War Cabinet 232, Minute S, Sir CharlesHarris explained the present arrangements for dealing with soldiers&apos;wives and dependants who have to enter workhouse infirmaries for medical treatment. It was true that the separation allowances werestopped, but, on the other hand, when a woman enters the infirmary the allowance to her children is raised to the rate for motherless children.The military authorities had taken over so many of the civil hospitalsthat there often was no alternative for women requiring medicalattendance other than to enter a workhouse infirmary. The LocalPension Committees were authorised to contribute to the maintenanceof the home when the mother was in the infirmary. The Guardians,who raised the question, desired the continuation of the allowances in order to charge the women for maintenance.The War Cabinet decided To refer the matter for report to a committee, to be convenedby the Minister of Pensions, consisting of representatives of : The Admiralty. 4The War Office.The Treasury.. The Local Government Board.The Pensions Ministry.13. The War Cabinet had before them the First Interim Report,of the Committee appointed to consider the question of increasingthe pay of soldiers and sailors (War Cabinet 200, Minute 4), togetherwith a summary of the Report in a form arranged for publication(Paper G.T.-2046).The chief criticism offered on the Report was that it failed to differentiate between the men serving abroad and at home, and between the men abroad who were in the firing line and thoseserving at the base.Sir Edward Carson, the Chairman of the Committee, said thatthis problem had been gone into fully by the Committee, who had
decided that it was impossible to make the differentiation suggested.The administrative difficulties involved were enormous.Mr. Montagu said that a similar attempt had been made by the demobilisation Committee in dealing with the question of gratuities,and had been abandoned for the same reason.Sir Chaides Harris said such a proposal would necessitate thatthe pay offices should keep in constant touch with the individualmovements of very large numbers of men, and this at a time whenthe pay offices were staffed in a great measure by thousands ofinexperienced and untrained girls. The proposals, even as they stood, would place a tremendous strain on the machinery.General Macdonogh said that men were better off pecuniarilywhen in France than when in this country, and that it was important to help the men when home on leave.Dr. Macnamara explained that the demand for increased payhad arisen at home and not at the Front.* It was impossible to contemplate scales of pay comparable with those enjoyed by theDominion troops, or to go the length of the demand for 140,000,000Z.put forward by the General Federation of Trade Unions. He was certain that the proposals of the Committee would be widelywelcomed, and would go a long way to check the present agitation.Mr. Montagu said he had forwarded a copy of the proposals tothe Viceroy of India, and had stated that it was, in his view, hardly possible to oppose them on the ground that they involved a freshburden of about 1,000,000Z. per annum on the finances of India.The Government of India may reply that when they undertook tobear a share in the expense of the war they had not foreseen this new expenditure. Mr. Montagu added that he would communicate to the Cabinet the reply of the Viceroy, and, in the meantime, would leave the question of the incidence of the burden for subsequentdepartmental arrangement.The Chancellor of the Exchequer emphasised the heavy strain on the country&apos;s finances involved in the proposals, following, asthey did, upon a guarantee of perhaps 50,000,0001. on account ofthe provision of the ninepenny loaf. Apart from this consideration,the general principle was one which certainly appealed to him.The War Cabinet decided To approve the recommendations of the Report, subject to theconcurrence of the Prime Minister, and the Secretary wasrequested to prepare a revised draft of a notice to thepress announcing the Cabinet&apos;s decision.The War Cabinet further decided that The proposals should come into operation for the Army as fromthe 29th September. 1917, and for the Navy as from the1st October, 1917.(Initialled)        &apos; A. B. L.2t Whitehall Gardens, 8,W.,September IS, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
