<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/4/0 images: 256-267</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.65WAR CABINET, 259.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S. W. on$Monday, October 29, 1917, at 11-30 a.m.   :Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair) (for Minutes 1 to 6).The Right  Hon. the Earl Gurzon of The Rio-ht Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (inKedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E (for the Chair) (for Minutes 7 to 13).Minutes I to 0). The R.ght Hon   &amp;R   Qarsq^ k C)The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner. M.P.G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. George N. Barnes, M.P.The following were also present :The Right Hon. A. .1. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby,KG., G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War.Major-General F. B. Maurice, C.B.,Director of Military Operations.Major-General Sir W. T. Furse, K.C.B.,D.S.O., Master-General of the Ordnance(for Minutes 11 and 12).Major-General E. B. Ashmore, C.M.G.,M.V.O., Home Forces (for Minutes 11,12, and 13).The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.Admiral Sir J. 11. Jellicoe, G.C.B., O.M.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 11,12, and 13).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, KG, M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minute 13).Sir E. R. Henry, G.C.V.O., K.C.B., C.S.I.,Commissioner, Metropolitan Police (for minute 13).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A- Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.[maximum Document is the Property of His Britannic majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1D17.
The Invasion of 1. THE Prime Minister drew the attention of the War CabinetItaly, to a document he had handed in at the Rome Conference held onthe 5th-7th January, 1917, in which he had urged the importanceof the preparation of Allied defensive schemes of co-operation on theItalian front to meet such an attack as had recently occurred(Paper G.-106, paragraphs 23 and 26) (Appendix I).Lord Derby stated that he had seen the Italian Ambassador,who admitted that the Italian troops on the Bainsizza Plateau hadbeen of inferior quality.The Director of Military Operations explained - the situation from the point of view of the War Office, and stated that the italians had had due warning of the attack, and had known a week ago thata probable objective would be in the vicinity of Tolmino. Further,they had had information as to the German force, namely, five divisions, which had been transferred to Italy. General Maurice addedthat General Cadorna had informed us in his telegram of the 21stOctober that the attack was coming ; he had communicated theimminence of it to his troops, and had said, further, that he was confident of being able to meet it. This telegram had been communicated to the War Cabinet. Owing to the very difficultcountry on the Tolmino front, General Cadorna was of opinionthat an attack there would be checked without difficulty, and was holding that front, in consecpuence, lightly. General Cadorna hadfifteen divisions in reserve, which was double the number that were used by the Germans and Austrians in their Tolmino offensive.These divisions, however, were on the southern part of the front,and, owing to the fact that most of the roads in that districtrun east and west, it had been very difficult to get troops to reinforce the Tolmino section. General Maurice said that the attack in some respects resembled that carried out on the Asiagofront on the 16th May, namely, the attack was made clown thevalleys, with a view to isolating the troops in the intervening hills ;that the attack had been facilitated and preceded by heavy dis-charges of gas down the valleys, which were effective inasmuch asthe Italian gas masks were inefficient. He added that we badinformed the Italians of this and offered to supply them with others, but they had declined. As the result of the gas attack and the isolation of troops on the mountains, a panic had started in the 4th Corps, which spread to the Second Army, with theresult that the Italians had not fought. General Maurice statedthat a communique had been received from General Cadornaaccusing some of the Italian troops of cowardice, but that these words had been deleted by the &quot;Italian Embassy before the com-munique was issued to the press. The Director of MilitaryOperations informed the War Cabinet that our own arrangements to assist the Italians in an emergency, which had been drawnup many months ago, had been completed in detail within four hours of the receipt of orders to send assistance. He statedthat the Italians had good defensive positions behind theirpresent front, on to which they could retire, but that whether such would be held must necessarily depend upon whetherthe Italians would put up a fight. General Cadorna indicated that his intention was to hold the line of the Tagliamento.General Maurice added that the Third Army were not beingheavily pressed, and were retiring in good order. As regards a cessation of the Austro-German offensive, he wras of opinion that its progress might soon be delayed in view of the fact that the germans were now getting far from their only railhead, which ended atTolmino. General Maurice stated that the Italian army couldroughly be divided into two parts, namely, the Northern Italians,who fought well, and the Southern Italians, who were useless.It was the Southern Italians who showed cowardice in the valleyson either side of Monte Nero.Lord Derby stated that he had asked the Italian Ambassador,
nSubmarines. 2. The First Sea Lord reported that a seaplane had attacked anenemy submarine off the Algerian coast, and that there was a proba-bility of the attack having been successful.Loss ofH.M.S. &quot; Orama.&quot;3. With reference to War Cabinet 254, Minute 8, in connectionwith the sinking ojE H.M.S. &quot;Orama,&quot; the First Sea Lord informed the War Cabinet that the United States destroyer &quot; Conyngham &quot;what, in his opinion, would be the effect on the Italian nation of theserious reverse, and had been informed that his view was thatit would create a tremendous wave of patriotic feeling; thatSigner Orlando would become Prime Minister, and that SignorGiolitti would take a patriotic line now that Italian territory wasinvaded. . it, was clear that the Italian defeat had been largely dueto insidious enemy propaganda in the army, on the lines of theRussian Revolutionists. As to the results at the. front, it was aquestion how far this enemy propaganda had been allowed to spread. General Maurice informed the War Cabinet that the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff, before leaving for Italy, had asked him to convey a message to the War Cabinet that it would facilitatehis work if the Italian Government was informed of the earlyvisit of General Robertson, who was going to consult withGeneral Cadorna on the situation.The War Cabinet requested The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to communicateforthwith with the British Embassy at Rome as toGeneral Robertson&apos;s visit.Lord Derby informed the War Cabinet that Field-marshal sir Douglas Haig had appointed Lord Cavan to command the forcethat was being despatched to Italy, and stated that further troops will be held in readiness for despatch if such was found to benecessary.The War Cabinet expressed theirappreciationof theactionof Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig in making this selection and in releasingfirst-rate divisions for service in Italy. The Prime Minister thoughtit desirable that the Italians should be informed as to the actualtroops that were being sent, so that, with their knowledge of theirreputations, they might be encouraged in their efforts. He indicated the point of concentration of the British force.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was requested to telegraph at once to the British Ambassador at Paris, asking himto give the British Government immediate notice if the Frenchintended to publish the fact that they also were sending reinforce-ments to Italy, in which case the War Cabinet decided that thequestion of a similar announcement in this country should beconsidered.Lord Derby stated that General Dessino, the Russian military attache, had written a letter for publication, the point of which wasto the effect that the Italian disaster could not be attributed to military causes arising out of the Russian revolution. GeneralDessino was very upset at his letter not being passed for publication.The War Cabinet requested The Secretary of State for War to circulate a copy of GeneralDessino&apos;s letter, so that it might be considered before any steps were taken to publish the same.The members of the War Cabinet expressed their appreciationand approval of the prompt decisions taken by the Prime minister on their behalf during the previous forty-eight hours.
had attacked the submarine that torpedoed the &quot; Orama,&quot; and had dropped depth charges on her. As wreckage had appeared, thedestruction of the submarine appeared probable.Naval Air Activity.4. With reference to the communiques which have appeared of late in the newspapers as to the bombing raids which haare beencarried out on enemy railway junctions and aerodromes, the WarCabinet requested The First Sea Lord to supply them with a summary of thenaval air activity during the past month.Air Offensive. 5. Jn connection with the bombing of enemy towns, Lord Derbystated that such operations had been severely handicapped by densefog and other unfavourable weather conditions. He had arranged to obtain daily reports of operations of this nature, and wouldforward such reports to the War Cabinet as soon as received.ProposodAnglo-french conference atBoulogne.6. With reference to War Cabinet 254, Minute 5, the PrimeMinister informed the War Cabinet that he had received a request from M. Painleve intimating that the French authorities wished todiscuss with us an extension of the British front in Flanders, andalso the situation on the Italian front.The War Cabinet decided To consider this request at an early date.Food Supply inFrance and italy .7. With reference to War Cabinet 257, Minute 1, the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs stated that he had been interviewed by both the French and Italian Ambassadors, who had pointed out thevery serious state of affairs in their respective countries with regardto the food question.Lord Milner stated that, he had been dealing with this matter,and that a preliminary statement was now being prepared, and assoon as he had received the final statement he would comnmnicatewith the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.Shipping Losses.8. With reference to the War Cabinet 241, Minute 14, the FirstLord stated that he considered it undesirable at present that theform in which the shipping losses are communicated to the public should be changed.The War Cabinet decided that-No change should be made until the matter had been further considered by the War Cabinet.Shipping Situation.9. Mr. Balfour brought to the notice of the War Cabinet the seriousness of the shipping situation, as set out in a report by theMinisiry of Shipping (Paper G.T.-2386) and his covering note(Paper G.T.-2412). He pressed upon the War Cabinet the fact thatthe most optimistic estimate stated that in 1918 there would haveto be a reduction of no less than 8,000,000 tons in our imports ascompared with 1917, which meant that if our imports of munitions(15,000,000 tons) and foodstuffs (14,000,000 tons) were maintained at the same level next year as this, we should not be able to importin 191S a single ton of anything else whatever, either in the natureof raw material or manufactured articles. Quite apart from the bearing this situation had on the enquiry he was making, inaccordance with the Prime Ministers wishes, into our resources for
next year, he urged that the position as set out by the Ministry ofShipping should be investigated further, so that the necessary cutting down in imports should begin as soon as possible, and the necessarydata&quot; arrived at to enable us to prepare a forecast as to what will be our resources in munitions for next year.It was stated that there were indications that in 1918 the americans would require to use the whole of their munitionresources so as to supply their own forces on the Western Front.In regard to Mr. Balfour&apos;s suggestion for the preparation of a programme for a further curtailment of imports, it was pointed outthat it had not been found possible to adhere to the previousprogramme. In a single period of three months, for example, theactual imports had exceeded the estimate loy no less than 2,000,000tons. The Tonnage Priority Committee reviewed the situation everymonth, and endeavoured to regulate the imports according to theshipping available for two months in advance. Even their estimates,however, were widely departed from in practice, owing to the exigencies of the shipping situation, and it was necessary to leave a very wide discretion to the Shipping Controller. In thesecircumstances, doubt was expressed as to the value of a furtherprogramme of restrictions.No decision was reached.Proposed Mission 10. Sir Edward Carson stated   that, iii   the   course of histo Roumania. examination into the question of Propaganda, the desirability of aBritish Mission to Roumania had been strongly urged upon him.The difficulty was to select a suitable person to act as Head of theMission. He thought that the Roumanians should be more clearlyinformed of the efforts we are making to assist them the War Cabinet approved the suggestion in principle, and requested Sir Edward Carson to consult further with Lord Milner andMr. Balfour with a view to deciding the desirability ofsuch a Mission, and the selection of personnel.Release of Guns 11. The War Cabinet had under consideration an admiralty for Anti-Aircraft Memorandum (Appendix II, Paper G.T.-23S0), which the FirstDefence of London. Lord had undertaken to have prepared in his Department for their information (War Cabinet, 250, Minute 2 ; \Var Cabinet, 253,Minute 7), regarding the further supply of guns by the admiralty for the London defences. They were reminded that the Navy hadalready released forty-eight anti-aircraft guns, not including thefour mounted at Chatham, for the defence of London.The First Lord said that the view had been expressed atprevious meetings that it was highly doubtful whether any moreanti-aircraft guns could be handed over without grave risk. TheNavy had already released to the War Office both guns andaeroplanes which weie practically indispensable. The germans were reported to be constructing submersible craft of a much larger. type with long-range guns, while our recent returns of shipping losses showed a recrudescence of successful activities by hostilesubmarines.It was pointed out that the question really was of the relative importance to completing (a) London barrage, and (6) the defensivearming of our merchant shipping.General Ashmore said that Lord French&apos;s wish was to fill inthe four existing gaps in the barrage and to thicken the barrage at certain points. In reply to a question he stated that, as theexpression of his personal opinion, that the additional twenty-fourguns were not absolutely vital at the present moment to the securityof the London area. It was suggested that, rather than interfere[1365-259] C
with the defensive arming of - merchant ships, anti-aircraft guns.might be withdrawn from other fronts, e.g., France.The Master-General of the Ordnance said that, as regardsthe additional twenty-four guns now required for the London defences,the principal difficulty was in regard to their mountings, and thenecessary mountings to replace those removed from merchantshipping, if the Cabinet so decided, could not be ready until theend of next March.The War Cabinet decided that In the circumstances the Admiralty should not be required tosupply the additional twenty-four anti-aircraft guns for theLondon defences.Eepair of Anti- 12. The Minister of Munitions pointed out that the wear anaAircraft Guns. tear of anti-aircraft guns was at present very unevenly distributed.These guns were used both for home defence against air raids and anti-aircraft defences on the various fronts, and for the defensivearming of shipping. During the previous month and the period ofthe harvesters moon, the guns of the London barrage had been subjected to a very severe test. Raids conducted on five or sixsuccessive nights might place the guns of the barrage completelyout of action. While not himself a great believer in the efficacy ofthe barrage system of defence against air raids, he thought theabove was a possibility which required the most serious consideration.He strongly advocated, as a measure to meet this emergency, thatthere should be a free and constant interchange of anti-aircraft gunsso that there might be no undue strain upon any particular set of guns, and for purposes of repair, so that the life of each gun mightbe equally prolonged so far as is feasible. His Ministry had made aUarrangements to deal with the relining of such guns, withinpractical limits.The War Cabinet concurred in this view, and decided that The Minister of Munitions should take the necessary action togive effect to his proposal, in concert with the admiralty and the War Office.Air said Warnings 13. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the home in London by Secretary, submitting a Memorandum by the  Commissioner   of night. Police (Paper G.T.-2I07) (Appendix III), asking for a decision as towhether (a.) The present system of night warning should be maintained;(b.) It should be maintained, but be supplemented by allowing the local authorities to sound sirens ; or(c.) The system in use by day of firing high explosive soundbombs should be extended to the night.The Commissioner said the present system was described in his Memorandum of the 25th October, 1917. The Police received information of an impending air raid from the Military Authorities ;on this he first communicated with the necessary personnel ofconstables, regular and special, who then took air raid action,i-e., disseminating the warning by means of constables on foot, oncycles, or in motor-cars, carrying &quot;Take Cover&quot; placards, going through the streets sounding whistles, bells, or horns. He nextassembled relief parties at some 200 stations, and afterwards actedto the best of his judgment as circumstances demanded.Sir George Cave stated that the use of bombs by day wasnecessary, as ordinary signals were drowned by the noise of the traffic. Sound bombs by night, however, would be mistaken for enemy bombs   or  gunfire, and  cause  unnecessary alarm.   The
difficulty was to devise means of giving warning which, would enablepeople to find the best shelter available, and at the same time notdrive people out of their houses. During the present moon, whenno raids had so far been carried out, people were already takingcover in the evenings in Tube Stations, and this was bound to causeillness if the cold weather continued. This probability, moreover,would be much accentuated if loud warnings were given. If, onthe contrary, no warnings were issued by night other than by the&quot;Take Cover&quot; system of constables with placards, whistles, &amp;c,the public would complain that, whereas they had provided for theremoval of their families from the upper floors to the basement,these precautions were useless unless the inhabitants were properlyaroused.It was pointed out that syrens were used at Dunkirk and else-where, where raids were almost of nightly occurrence, and that thissystem had also obtained in Hull, to the considerable dislocation ofindustry.It was also pointed out that syrens were constantly used at allhours of the day and night for calling up the various &quot; shifts &quot; in munition Factories.The War Cabinet agreed that what they had to determine was,which was the more likely to entail a greater risk : (a.) Losses to people who had no opportunity of taking shelter,if no warnings by bomb or syren were given ;(6.) Losses due to exposure and to accidents&quot; caused by the congestion of a frightened populace crowding into TubeStations and other cover, if such warnings were issued.After due consideration the War Cabinet decided that The present system should be maintained.2, Whitehall Gardens, London, S.W.,October 29, 1917.
APPENDIX I.Extracts from (G.-106) Memorandum handed by the Prime Minister to the delegates at the Conference at Rome on 5th, 6th, and 7th January, 1917.23. LEAVING the Balkans, let us look at the Italian front. Here there are two possible contingencies ; one defensive, the other offensive. If the enemy should, as suggested above, concentrate his manoeuvre armies against the Italian front, it would afford a great opportunity for the Allies. Should the enemy adopt this course, thepresumption is that he will gamble upon the stupidity and lack of mobility of theAllies. Unquestionably, he regards us as stupid and lacking in initiative we Britishmost of all. Let us take advantage of this amiable belief. The enemy will base theplan of attack on the assumption that he has to meet a force of so many Italian heavy guns, some of which he knows to be of old type, and lacking in mobility. If he electsto attack on this front, we propose that the Allies should concert their own plans sothat instead of meeting the artillery armament that he calculates for, he shall findhimself confronted with a vastly superior armament of Italian guns reinforced byBritish, and, we should hope,French, heavy artillery with theirown personnel. The objectof the Allies is to kill Germans. We can put them out of action just as well on theItalian as on the Western front. By adopting this plan we might well convert areprdse into a route just as the Germans, by massing artillery on the Roumanian front,converted the Roumanian invasion of Transylvania into an utter defeat. We ask our allies to examine this proposal in a sympathetic spirit, and, subject to the approval ofthe Conference, we propose that orders should be given to our respective General Staffs to work it out in all its technical details, including the elaboration of railwaytimetables, and the arrangements for the necessary gun emplacements and communi-cations.26. Such, then, are the problems which we think the Governments and the General Staffs should consider, namely : (3.) The development of defensive and offensive scheme of co-operation on theItalian front.APPENDIX II.     &apos;G.T.-2380. --Supply of Guns by Admiralty for, Defence oi- London.Admiralty Memorandum for the War Cabinet.IN connection with the request which has been received by the Admiralty fromthe AVar Office for the supply of an additional twenty-four guns for use in thedefence of London against enemy aircraft, the Board desire that the War cabinet should be aware of the serious effect which compliance with the War Office requestwould have upon the programme of defensively arming merchant-ships.The Admiralty have already provided, for the defence of London, 16 3-inchH.A. guns, which would otherwise have been used for defensively arming merchant-ships, and twenty-two guns which were .taken from the number allocated to new construction and reserves. There are no more available from the latter source, and ifany further guns are to be supplied they must be guns which are allocated to the defensive arming of merchant-ships.It will be remembered (Admiralty memorandum 2.10.17) that, in view of theshortage of steel, it w7as decided that a programme of one gun only per merchant-shipshould be adopted, and at the present time there are 2,179 merchant-ships of over 1,500 tons gross register, which require arming orre-arming with 4-inch or larger guns.981 merchant-ships of 1,500 tons gross register and  under, which  requirere-arming with 3-inch or smaller guns.1,028 merchant-ships which are entirely unarmed.
The rate at which the arming and re-arming of merchant-ships is being carriedout has averaged sixty-two ships per week during the last four weeks, but it isanticipated that an increased delivery of guns will enable seventy-five shipsper week to be armed and rearmed in the near future. It will, therefore, take at leasttwelve months to complete the programme so far as regards existing ships without taking into account the requirements for new construction.The attached table gives particulars of British merchant-ships which have had tocapitulate after action with enemy submarines during the last four months owing totheir gun having been outranged, and does not include ships with inadequatearmament which have been sunk otherwise than after a gun action.Events have proved that the defensive armament of merchant-ships is a very important means of defence against enemy submarines, and it is anticipated that difficulties of couvoy in the winter owing to bad weather, and the prospect of largersubmarines which are now building, operating at greater distances, will more than ever necessitate a merchant-ship relying on her own resources, that is, mainly on hergun power.The submarine is at present the enemy&apos;s most effective weapon against us, andthe Board desire to point out that in their view there is considerable danger of too great optimism prevailing in regard to the submarine campaign situation, and thatany further reduction in, or postponement of, the programme for defensively armingmerchant-ships is to be very strongly deprecated, as it must almost certainly result inan aggravation of the injury which the enemy&apos;s submarines are inflicting upon theAllied cause.(Signed) E. GEDDES.October 24, 1917.Particulars of British Merchant Ships armed with guns of a less calibre than 4-in.Sunk during the months of June, July, August, and September 1917 as a resultof being Outranged by the Enemy.Date.	Ship.	g i oss Tonnage.	Gun.June      3 4 8 S 9 10 11 19 21 27 Julv      5 10 10 August   1 6 28 September	Island More . . Manchester Trader Isle of Jura Oheltonian Achilles Scottish Hero lieuha Brookby Lord Koberts Tong Hong .. Cuyahoga Stoic (fishing&apos; vessel)  .. King- David  . . Llanduilno Rosemoiuit Whitecourt Nil	3.04 g 3,938 3,809 4,426 641 2,205 1.S7S 3/79 4.166 2,184 4,j8s 79 3.679 4,1S7 2.304 3.67S Nil	6-pr. (Hotuhkiss). 3 H.A., Mark III. 12-pr. 12-cwt. 13-pr. 12-pr. 12-cwt. (Jap.). 12-pr. 12-cwt. *y :? 6-pr. (Hotchkiss). 13-pr. 12-pr. 12-c\vt. (Jap.). 12-pr. S-cwt. la-pr. (Q.f.). Nil.APPENDIX III.Air-Raid Warnings in London by Night.I SUBMIT a memorandum by the Commissioner of Police on the above subject and ask the War Cabinet to decide (a.) Whether the present system of night warnings should be maintained, or(6.) Whether it should be maintained but should be supplemented by allowinglocal authorities to sound sirens, or(c.) Whether the system in use by clay of firing high explosive sound bombs shouldbe extended to the night.[1365-259] D
I agree with the Commissioner as to the inadvisability of using the sound-bombsat night. These form an excellent warning by day, when the streets are congested andthe roar of the London traffic drowns all other sounds, including the most powerfulsiren: But to use them at night, when there is comparative quiet and the tise of thesebombs would give the impression that a bombardment of London is proceeding, would cause unnecessary alarm and might lead to serious consequences. When these bombs were first used by day, two persons of weak physique are said to have died of heartfailure.The use of sirens would not be open to the above objections. They would, as theCommissioner says, reach the inmates of all houses and would not improbably causesome persons to leave their houses and incur danger in the streets. But there is awidely diffused feeling among the public that when a raid is impending they areentitled to be told the truth, and that those foolish persons who upon being warnedrush into danger have only themselves to blame. The prudent householder says : &quot; Ihave made careful arrangements for getting my family into the basement of my house(or some other safe place) when a raid is threatened, and when the authorities know the raiders are coming 1 ought to have the information so that I may take the measures required for the protection of my household.&quot; And he is not satisfied by the answer that, if the information is given, other people will act foolishly.I believe that a siren is actually sounded at Woolwich Arsenal, which is heard overa considerable area of London; and the local authorities at Leytonstone and some other places have set up a system of warnings by siren, and refuse to discontinue it. to forbid these local warnings without setting up some other form of public warningwould lead to great dissatisfaction:If it is decided to allow and encourage the local authorities to give warning bysiren (a.) They should be prevented from using the siren before the &quot;take cover&quot;notice issues.(6.) A regulation shotdd be made forbidding the use of sirens for other purposesduring the hours when they are intended to be used as air-raid warnings(these hours should be fixed, e.g., in winter from S p.m. until 6 am., the sound bombs being used at all other times).(c.) The public should be strongly cautioned against leaving their houses onhearing the warning.G. CAVE.October 26, 1917.Air-Raid Warnings in London.Memorandum by tJie Commissioner of Police.After each raid the controversy as to the form in which warnings should be givenis invariably revived, and it would be satisfactory if a decision upon the point weregiven by the War Cabinet, as this would be deemed authoritative and accepted byeverybody.At present from half an hour before sunrise until half an hour after sunset,warning is given by the discharge from selected centres of two sound signals. at other times the warning is disseminated by the Constabulary, regular and special, on foot and on cycles or in motor cars, carrying the &quot; Take Cover &quot; placards, who circulatethrough the streets sounding their whistles, bells, or horns, and calling out &quot; TakeCover.&quot; The placards carried by the cars and cycles are illuminated so as to be visiblefrom a distance. Experience justifies the statement that so far as clearing the streetsis concerned this, method has proved quite satisfactory. It may be added that it is veryeffectively supplemented by other indications to people actually in the streets. Tram-cars turn down&apos; their lights ; pedestrians in the vicinity of the river bank see the TowerBridge carriage-way lifted up ; elsewhere they see fire engines proceeding to allottedstations, the Constabulary and members of the Air Raid Relief parties, and ambulancesand other motor transport assembling. In brief, the indications are so numerous thatsome of them cannot fail to reach even the most unobservant.Though this warning may be deemed to be quite sufficient for the purpose of informing persons in the streets, it is urged that it does not reach the occupants of allhouses, and some of them may be anxious to leave their homes for shelter in theneighbourhood or to proceed from upper to lower rooms for greater security.
oThey demand therefore that the warning shall he given by sound-signals, the sound of which will necessarily reach everybody, indoors as well as out of doors ; andit may be admitted that, if the method of giving the warning by day were adopted forthe dark hours, this object would be achieved.The objections to this course are very weighty. Firing sound-signals at nightwhen most people are in their homes would, more especially in districts occupied bythe working classes, create great alarm, in places amounting to panic. A number, farin excess of the accommodation available, would rush for shelter ; children, half clad,would be dragged out of their beds and taken out into the streets, and possibly bestill there when the guns begin to lire, not having found room in the shelters. the weather is becoming colder, and if many raids take place under such conditions therewill be a heavy toll taken of child-life, as the result of the exposure to which childrenwill be subjected.Besides the children, there are the inmates of hospitals to be considered, alsowomen in delicate health, old persons, persons with weak hearts or in bad health, orrecovering from sickness and so forth, all of whom might be very seriously affected bythe alarming sound for it is an alarming sound of the signals that are fired by day.The justification for firing them by day is that the streets then are greatly congestedwith people, and that an instantaneous and emphatic warning is required to enablethem to be quickly emptied. At night-time conditions are different, and the streetsbeing less congested, can be cleared in time by the means now adopted, which causeno special alarm to the category of persons above referred to.An alternative proposal that finds favour with many is that the warning at nightshould be given by sirens to be set up by the various local authorities, of whom thereare 121 in the Metropolitan Police district. There can be no doubt that if this system is set up there will be many instances of premature signals, some of which will betaken up by adjoining districts, with the result that the public will be unnecessarilydisturbed.The siren would certainly be less alarming, but, as its sound would reach theinmates of all houses, the effect would be to impel great numbers of persons, moreespecially in the poorer districts, to rush for shelters which do not exist. It is, i venture to urge, most desirable that the people sin add remain in their houses. what has to be combated is the conviction of so many of them that any public building, suchas a Town Hall, library, or police station is so infinitely more secure than their homesthat, at any risk, they must get there.Tube stations, goods depots, warehouses, and the basements of well-built factories are certainly quite secure ; but where working class residential districts are not centres of industry, these secure shelters do not exist, and such shelters as are available are insufficient in accommodation, and at best only makeshifts which, in many instances,are splinter proof only, and in this respect very little better than private houses. Atthe present time there is a marked insufficiency of even this imperfect air-raid shelterin a great number of densely populated areas, and in such circumstances no measureshould, I venture to submit, be taken which will have the effect of bringing into the street people for whom there is no shelter accommodation.We are gradually Increasing this accommodation, and we have it now for about1J millions ; but it is very badly distributed, some areas having much more than theyreally need, others much less.Weighing all these considerations, and having regard to what I know of the stateof mind of the people in the East End, who in the past have suffered much from raids,and whose nerves in consequence have been greatly strained, I am not desirous to see any change made which might have the effect of aggravating their existing restlessnesswithout adding to their security.It will be necessary when this decision is taken to have power to compel localauthorities to come into line and to refrain from taking independent action not formally authorised. At present two or three local authorities contemplate actionwhich, if carried out, may create great confusion and possibly result in ahum. Anorder under Regulation 12 (6) Defence of the Realm Regulation would meet this.E. R, H.October 25, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
