<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/4/0 images: 398-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1917.SEC 1 JET.64WAR CABINET, 281.Minvtes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onFriday, November 23, P)J7, at IP30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The  Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The Right Hon. SirM.P.E. Carson, KG,The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J.&apos; Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.K.G., G.O.V.O.for War.the Earl of Derby,C.B., Secretary of StateGeneral Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minute 1). *vThe.Right Hon. H. E. Duke, KG., M.P.,Chief SecretaryMinute 1).for    Ireland    (forThe Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of the Ad-miralty.Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., O.M.,G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief ofthe Naval Staff.Rear-Admiral Sir W. R. Hall, KC.M.G.,C.B., R.N., Director of IntelligenceDivision, Admiralty.The Right Hon. Lord Rhondda, FoodController (for Minute 2).Mr. G. W. Roffley, Ministry of Food (for minute 2).The Right Hon. R. Munro, KG, M.P.,Secretary for Scotland (for Minute 1).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, KGB., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.
The Liquor Trade :Publication ofFinanceCommittee&apos;sEeport.Release of Winesfrom Bond.WITH reference to War Cabinet 157, Minute 15, the WarCabinet had before them the report of the Liquor Trade finance committee for England and Wales/together with a covering uote bythe Home Secretary dealing with the question of the publication ofthe report (G.T.-2600).The War Cabinet decided that-Inasmuch as the reports of the Committees which were dealingwith Scotland and Ireland had not been received, it wasinadvisable to publish the report for England and Walesat present.2. With reference to War Cabinet 287, Minute 16, the W7arCabinet had before them a memorandum by the Food Controller onthe release of wines from bond. 1The War Cabinet decided that The release of wines from bond should be without distinctionof quality, and should be on the basis of the figures for theyear 1916.dardanelles commission :Second Report3. With reference to War Cabinet 256, Minute 9, the WarCabinet were informed that, on the 16th December, Sir Ian Hamiltonwill have been unemployed for two years and will, in consequence,be automatically placed on the retired list. After this it would bedifficult for him to be employed again on military duty. Further,Lord Justice Piokford was prepared to put in writing that there was nothing in the Report of the Commission to warrant the exclusion ofSir Ian Hamilton from military employment The Prime Minister agreed to discuss the matter further withthe Secretary of State for War.Russia.4. With reference to War Cabinet 2&apos;80, Minutes 6 and 7, theChief of the Imperial General Staff read a telegram from ColonelE. L. Spiers, M.C., based on a message received from the french minister at Stockholm, which stated that Kharkov had been captured by General Kaledin, and that General Alexeieff and M. Miliukovwerewith him. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that hewas being pressed by influential Poles in this country to urge HisMajesty&apos;s Government to send a message of encouragement to thePoles in Russia, and to co-operate with the Polish National Council.The War Cabinet requested Sir Edward Carson, in consultation with the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs, to obtain from Dr. Harold Williamsinformation as to the present situation in Russia.The Western Front.5. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff informed the WarCabinet that in the region of Cambrai the Germans had brought uptwo divisions and a few battalions. No news had yet been received of the number of guns captured in the recent action.The Invasion ofItaly.6. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that therewas no fresh news of importance frOm the Italian front. TheItalians were holding their own. The Germans had sent a speciallyassembled division of Jagers to the North. Otherwise there hadbeen no increase on that front. Information had been received that three divisions out of eight, which had been lost sight of, and whichit was thought might have been transferred to Italy, were still onthe Russian front.
Guns for Italy. 7. The Prime Minister called attention to the supply of heavy guns for the British Divisions serving in Italy. A report had reached him that the French had as many heavy guns as we had gunsaltogether. The French were said to have 600 guns as comparedwith 250 guns with our troops. It, was most important that ourmen should be adequately supported, in order to keep our lossesdown.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff did not believe the disparity was as great as reported, and undertook tofurnish the War Cabinet with the exact figures.East Africa. 8. With reference to War Cabinet 279, Minute 3, the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff said that General Von Lettow hadcontrived to elude General Van Deventer, but some 52 Germans hadbeen captured, and there could hardly be more than 150 Germansleft at large.Palestine. 9. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that aYeomanry division and two divisions were advancing towardsJerusalem, and had taken a hill 5,000 yards north-west of jerusalem.Submarines. 10. The  First  Sea  Lord   reported  that  the &quot; Merops&quot; hadengaged and claimed to have destroyed a submarine thirty milesfrom Belle Isle, in the Bay of Biscay. A report had also beenreceived that, after the completion of one of our new minefields, an explosion had lately taken place, which was thought might be dueto a submarine coming into contact with mines.GermanElectrically-Controlled Motor-Boat.11. The First Sea Lord reported that an electrically-controlledmotor-boat had been encountered making for the Belgian coastpatrol vessels. Our ships had &quot;jammed their wireless,&quot; and she had not been seen again.Future military policy.12. The War Cabinet had a preliminary discussion on future military policy, with a view to the discussion arranged for Monday next, the 26th November.In the course of the discussion the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff said that there was some evidence to show -that theposition of the Germans was worse than we were sometimes inclined to think. For a long time past they had tried no serious offensive in the West, but this might be due to the U-boat plan of winningthe war ; they had not pushed their advantage on the Russian front,bttt this might be in order to leave the Russians to fall to piecesthemselves ; still, their offensive against Roumania had not beenpersisted in, and they had sent only some six or seven divisions tothe Italian front, and these had possibly been called for by the austrians, owing to the weakness of their own divisions. Thefailure to exploit the Italian debacle was significant. A month had elapsed since they had sent troops to Italy.A telegram had been received from General Plumer raising noobjection to the delay, of the two British divisions, but adding thathe&apos; had already informed the French and Italians that we were sending six divisions in all.    .. i . . , .   ,; .
On the. whole, it was difficult to explain the cessation of the offensive against Roumania and the failure to exploit the Italiandebacle except on the ground of inactivity, and the Chief of theImperial General Staff thought that Germany&apos;s military power was probably a good deal less and the condition of the Austrian armiesa good deal worse than we had thought to be the case.It was pointed out, over against this view, that Hindenburg haddefinitely announced the adoption of a defensive policy, Germanyhaving all the territory she required.2, Whitehall Gardens, S W.,November 23, 1917.o

</content>
</cab>
