<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/4/0 images: 456-459</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CTMs Document is the Property of His Britannic M^8sty&apos;s GymmmsLlPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1917.SECRET.WAR  CABINET, 291.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Chancellor of the ExchequersRoom, House of Commons, on Tuesday, December 4, 1917, at 5&apos;30 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl curzon of kedleston, K.G., G-.C.S.L, G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Lieutenant- general. C. Smuts, K.C.the    Right    Hon.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J. Baleour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord R. Cecil, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Blockade.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Supreme WarCouncil.1. SUBJECT to the following Minutes, the War Cahinetapproved the resolutions taken by the Supreme War Council at versailles on Saturday, the 1st December, 1917 (I.C.-36) (Appendix.)They affirmed their desire that aH Departments should consist-operate in furnishing the information required for the work ofthe Supreme War Council, and should make suitable arrangements to this end.The Secretary stated that he understood that the War office had already made arrangements for the transmission of the military information required.Mr. Balfour stated that the Foreign Office were considering thebest method of their co-operation, in view of the great secrecy ofmany of the subjects. Sir George clerk had been temporarilyattached at Versailles to assist Lord Milner for a few days, and onhis return a scheme would be drawn up providing, possibly, for a regular liaison officer between the British Section at Versailles andthe Foreign Office.The War Cabinet approved the arrangement made by theSecretary that, without prejudice to the special arrangements madeby the War Office or Foreign Office, the War Cabinet Secretariatshould act as an agent in London for the collection and transmission ofinformation on behalf of the Supreme War Council.The TransportProblem.2. The War Cabinet discussed at some length the proposal ofthe Supreme War Council that the whole question of inter-Alliedtransport by land and sea should be examined by a single expert.[1365-291]
there is no difference of opinion in principle as to the greatdesirability of an examination of this problem. Difficulties,diqw-ever, were recognised to exist on the personal side, and the question was adj adjourned. q. : f&quot; &apos;2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., &apos;   *December 5, 1917.APPENDIX.The following resolutions were passed by the Supreme WarCouncil: 1. They instruct their Permanent Military Advisers toexamine the military situation and to report their reconnnenda-tions as to the future plan of operations.2. In order to provide the Supreme War Council with thematerial for their examination the Governments representedundertake : (a.) To supply the Supreme War Council with all such information of a general political and departmentalcharacter as is available for the war discussions oftheir own Cabinets or War Committees. This will include decisions of the Cabinets and War Committeesrelating to matters connected with the conduct of thewar.(&amp;;.) To instruct their Ministries of War and General Staffsto furnish the Permanent Military Advisers with theirviews and policy, with frequent regular statements ofthe order of battle and dislocation of their own and allied forces, and immediate notification of transfers of larger units from one theatre of operations toanother; with frequent regular statements of the orderof battle and dislocation of enemy forces, with thereports embodying their conclusions as to enemy man-power, material and enemy conditions generally, andwith immediate notification of important transfersand concentrations; with regular reports as to thestrength of their own forces and memoranda, on man-power, situation and prospects; with regular reports ofthe existing and prospective position in regard to warmaterial and military transportation. Commandersof the forces on the various fronts will, in order to save time, repeat their daily communique direct to theSupreme &quot;War Council. Their more important reports,-as well as those of Heads of Military Missions andMilitary Attaches, will be forwarded to the supreme war Council through the respective General Staffs.The whole of the above information to be furnished with the least possible delay, in order that the military representatives shall be able to discuss the questions that will be raised at the Supreme War Council witha precise and up-to-date knowledge of the general military situation, and in complete touch with theviews of their own military authorities.(c.) To instruct their Ministries of Marine (Admiralty) and shipping to furnish the Supreme War Council withreports, memoranda, and appreciations bearing on thegeneral condition of the war, and more particularly on problems affecting the transportation of troops and supplies.(d.) To instruct their Foreign Offices to supply the supreme war Council with a general appreciation of the diplo-
3 W.C. 291... , :, matic situation at the present time, and henceforwardi&apos;f f.Jf v J*&apos;&quot;:-r -&apos;vi-^: j; ^tbtTurnish^ regularly; ,ahd; in the most  expeditiousf&apos;.ij ; t .5,.;:.;. ihiahner&apos;-possible^ &quot;full information, whether receivedby despatch or telegram, on all diplomatic matters inany way connected with the war.(e.) To instruct their Departments dealing with munitions,aviation, man-power, shipbuilding, food (stocks, pro-duction,.-and distribution), and finance, to furnish allthe information necessary to enable the Supreme WarCouncil to appreciate the situation from these respec-tive points of view.3. In order to facilitate the reception and distribution ofthe information referred to above, each Section of the supreme war Council will comprise a Permanent Secretarial Staff.4. The Permanent Secretarial Staffs of the respective countries will, in concert, organise a Joint Secretarial Bureau forthe production and distribution of the notices, agenda, protocols,and proces-verbaux of the meetings of the Supreme War Council,and for such other collective business as it may be found desirableto entrust to it.The Italian Front. 5. The   Supreme   War   Council   instruct   its  permanent military Advisers to study the immediate situation on the italian front from the offensive as well as the defensive point of view, andto report to it as soon as possible at any rate, within the nextfortnight. The Permanent Military Advisers are directed to make their requests to the Governments concerned for all the informa-tion they require, and the representatives of the respective Govern-ments undertake to arrange that the information shall be furnishedat once.The Transport Pro-l:kv.u : (a) G-eneral;(&amp;) As affecting: theItalian Front.6. The Supreme War Council decide that it is desirable thatthe whole question of inter-Allied transport by sea and land shallbe examined by a single expert, who shall report to it on thesubject at the earliest possible date. It agreed that,, if theBritish Government can spare his services, Sir Eric Geddesshould be designated to carry out this investigation, and that, inthe first instance, he shall examine the transportation problem as affecting the Italian and Salonika situations.The representatives of the respective Governments undertaketo give instructions to their technical experts and administratorsto collaborate with Sir Eric Geddes, or, if his services cannot bemade available, with such other expert as may be mutually agreedupon.The Belgian Army.The MilitarySituation in the balkans.The Supply of greece.7. The Supreme War Council instruct their permanent military Advisers to examine and report on the utilisation of theBelgian army, and authorise them to apply to the Belgian Govern-ment, on their behalf, to furnish a report on the state of Belgianman-power.8. The Supreme War Council decide: (a.) To recommend to their respective Governments that theimmediate food and other essential requirements of greece, the promised military equipment, and thenecessary means for transporting the same shall besupplied as a matter of military urgency.
(&amp;.) That its Permanent. Military Advisers shall follow up thequestion of the supply ; and equipment of the Greek&apos;i army.       - , , ,i , , *     &apos;(c.) That its Permanent Military Advisers shall study andreport on the military situation in the Balkans, on thebasis of information to be furnished by the Govern-ments concerned.(d.) That the Governments concerned shall make the neces-sary financial advances to enable Greece to mobilisenot less than nine divisions, and the Supreme WarCouncil further requests the financial delegates ofFrance, Great Britain, and the United States ofAmerica to make, at once, the necessary arrangementsfor supplying Greece with the sum of 700,000,000francs, in the course of the year 1918, so as to clearoff arrears amounting to 175,000,000 francs, and toenable Greece to mobilise immediately not less thannine divisions.

</content>
</cab>
