<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/4/0 images: 522-527</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His -Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]    257Printed for the War Cabinet.   December 1017.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 299.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., on Monday,December 17, 1017, at 11*30 a.m.\ Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The  Right Hon.  the Earl Curzon of ! The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Kedleston, K.Q., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner, ! m,    TJ. , :  v      Q n.^^i n r\ xf o n mr n The Right Hon. Sir Edward Carsoit,(t.O. B., (j.O.M.Ij. !     K C   M PThe Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M. P.The following were also present: The Right Hon. the Lord Hardinge orPenshurst, KG., G.C.B., G.C.S.I.,G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O.,Permanent Uncler-Secretary of State forForeign AffairsThe Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,. G.C.V.O., C.B., secretary of State for. War.Lieutenant-General Sir C. F. N. Macready,K.C.B., K.C.M.G., Adjutant-General tothe Forces (for Minutes 15 and 16).Major-General Sir G. M. W. macdonogh,K.C.M.G., C.B., Director of military intelligence.Major-General Sir R. D. Whigham,K.C.B., D.S.O., Deputy Chief of theImperial General Staff (for Minutes 15and 16).Sir A. C. Geddes, K.G.B., M.P., Ministerof National Service (for Minutes 15 and16).The Right Hon Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 15 and 16)-Vice-Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, K.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., Deputy First Sea Lord(for Minutes 9, 10, and 11).The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 15and 16).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade (for minutes 15 and 16).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minutes 15 and16).Mr. P. Lloyd Greame, Ministry of NationalService (for Minutes 15 and 16).Captain L. S. Amerv, M.P.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.
TheWestern Front:Accident to LeaveTrain from Italy.The Invasion ofItaly.Moral of italian troops.1. THE Director of Military Intelligence reported that a leavetrain, containing French troops on leave from Italy, had beenderailed at St. Michel de Maurienne at midnight on the12th instant. Traffic had been suspended for forty-eight hours.The question was asked whether this railway accident might bea case of sabotage. The Director of Military Intelligence repliedthat this was not known, but the French and Italians were taking all necessary precautions to protect the Mont Cenis tunnel byinstalling electric light and mounting guards, &amp;c. It was not unlikely that the enemy were trying to cut the communications between France and Italy.2. The Director of Military Intelligence reported the receipt ofa telegram from General Plumer, dated the 15th December, 1917,to the effect that the enemy&apos;s artillery had been very active againstthe Northern sector. The&quot; Italians had been forced to draw back from Col Beretta, which was an important point. The Italiancounter-attack had failed, but they proposed making another. Theenemy&apos;s attacks had been very persistent, but the Italian commandwere not discouraged.   There were now indications of snow.3. The Director, of Military Intelligence said that a telegram had been received from General Plumer, reporting considerablelocal fighting, with varying success. General Diaz was generallysatisfied with the situation, and greatly pleased with the reports asto the state of the moral of the troops which he had had from his army commanders.Italian Situation:Message to he sentto Italian PrimeMinister.4. With reference to M.P.G. 4 (3), the Director of military intelligence read the proposed message to be sent by the PrimeMinister to the Italian Ambassador for Sisraor Orlando, in which itwas indicated that German reinforcements were going to Francerather than to Italy, and that since the 23th October only one german division had been actually sent from Russia to the italian front. The message also added that there were now 65 british battalions in Italy and 54 French.After some discussion, the War Cabinet (a.) Approved the proposed message, but requested the Directorof Military Intelligence to insert an additional paragraphon the subject of the artillery position on the italian front. A copy of the message, as sent, is reproduced inAppendix I.(6.) In this connection, they also instructed the Secretary to telegraph to General Wilson to find out what the artilleryposition was on the Italian front.Palestine.5. The Director of Military Intelligence said that general allenby had reported that he had advanced his left centre one anda half miles north-east of Ftamleh. Another Turkish division was reported on the 20th November passing south from Damascusen route from the Caucasus. It was therefore possible that general allenby might meet near Nablus two more divisions, of which one might be Germau The number of rifles in a Turkish divisionamounted to from 4,500 to 5,000. The reason why the Germans hadnot arrived on tlie scene earlier, in order to prevent General Allenbycapturing Jerusalem, was probably that these particular german divisions had only been formed in Germany during September, andtheir advanced units did not leave Germany until the 20th October,arriving in Constantinople on the 7th November.
6. With reference to War Cabinet 296, Minute 5, the Secretaryof State for War reported that he bad heard from the Chief of theImperial General Staff, who was in France, that General Allenby&apos;reply does not assist very much.After some discussion as to whether another telegram should besent to General Allenby on the subject, the War Cabinet decided&quot;that  :The matter should wait until the following day, when the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff would be back in London.7. The Secretary of State for War reported the receipt of atelegram from Sir William   Robertson, who requested that the.Cabinet might give some time on the following day for the discussionof the question of an immediate extension of the British line on theWestern front.The War Cabinet instructed The Secretary to arrange accordingly, when drawing up theAgenda for the following day.8! With reference to War Cabinet 292, Minute 8, the Secretaryof State for War reported that everything possible was being doneby Sir Douglas Haig to expedite the Enquiry in regard to the battle of Cambrai.In view, however, of the importance of knowing the result ofthe Enquiry in time for the House of Commons Debate on Thursday,the 20th instant, the War Cabinet requested The Secretary of State for War to telegraph to Sir douglas haig asking him for a report on the matter by nextThursday.Shipping Losses. y. The Deputy First Sea Lord made the usual statement, ofShipping Losses.Exploiting recentSuccess.The Western Front:Extension of BritishLine.Battle of Gambrai:Inquiry.10. With reference to War Cabinet 298, Minute 15, the deputy first Sea Lord reported that a telegram had now been received fromthe Commander-in-Chief of the Grand Fleet in regard to thisdisaster. It appeared that our two destroyers, the &quot; Partridge &quot; andthe &quot; Pellew,&quot; were attacked by three enemy destroyers. The&quot; Partridge &quot; was sunk with all hands : the &quot; Pellew &quot; was damaged,but got into Norwegian waters safely. The remaining enemydestroyer proceeded to the rear of the convoy and suak it. TheBritish ships which were ordered to cover this convoy, although they received an emergency signal from the &quot; Partridge,&quot; had arrived too late, and an inquiry.was being held in this connection. The german ships appeared to have got back safely. The Deputy First Sea Lordreported that a full account of the disaster to the Scandinavianconvoy would be included in the First Lord&apos;s statement in the Houseof Commons that afternoon.China. 11. The Deputy First Sea Lord said that the Commander-in-Chief, China, reported that, owing to long absence of foreign gun-boats, the Chinese were less careful of foreigners&apos; lives. At Shaszea British steamer had been fired on and then boarded by troops, whothreatened to shoot the master unless the money carried on board was handed over. The master refused, and the ship was finallyallowed to uroceed. The Deputy First Sea Lord reported that ithad been decided, in consequence, to send two of the bigger gunboats,[1385-299] B 2ScandinavianConvoy.
at present up-river in Mesopotamia, to China, having regard to the&apos;:fact that the force of gunboats in Mesopotamia was considered to be larger than was necessary.Mesopotamia and palestine.12. The Director of Military Intelligence read to the WarCabinet the information which had been supplied to the pressdescribing the recent operations in Mesopotamia and Palestine.The War Cabinet were informed that there had been considerabepublicity given to the fall of Jerusalem, and that the event had produced a marked effect throughout the world.Roumania.13. With reference to Foreign Office telegram No. 765, dated(-the 11th December, 1917, from Sir G. Barclay, confirming an identictelegram sent to Paris, London, Rome, and Washington, lord hardinge read a draft reply prepared by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (Appendix II). Lord Hardinge stated that theItalian reply had gone further than the reply suggested byMr. Balfour.The War Cabinet decided that-The telegram as prepared by Mr. Balfour should be sent toSir G. Barclay ;and instructed Lord Hardinge to communicate its contents to the FrenchGovernment that afternoon.Russia.14. The War Cabinet were informed that no confirmation ofthe alleged capture of Kaledin by the Bolsheviks had been received.Man-Power.15. The War Cabinet had before them a draft Report pre-pared by the Secretary for the Cabinet Committee on Man-power(Paper M.P.C.-14).Lord Derby undertook to supply revised and additional estimatesrequired by the War Cabinet. nThe consideration of the Report was adjourned until that afternoon.Statement in the 16- The War Cabinet considered whether a full statement on house of Commons,   man-power policy should be made in the House of Commons onWednesday or Thursday next, or adjourned until after the Recess.It was generally agreed to be undesirable to make such astatement this week, more especially as there would not be time for negotiations with the trade unions, to whom certain conditionalpledges had been given by Mr. Asquith and Mr. Arthur Henderson.2,. Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,December 17, 1917.
APPENDIX I.Note for the Italian Ambassador.PLEASE inform the President of the Council that the British War Cabinet iswatching the situation in Italy closely. So far they have been unable to obtain any definite information of a further enemy concentration on the Italian front, though sucha concentration is not improbable. On the other hand, reports from a variety ofsources have been received to the effect that the enemy intends to transfer large bodies of troops to the Franco-British front, and definite and precise information has beenobtained that since the 28th October nine German divisions have been moved from theRussian to the Franco-British front, while during the same period definite information has been obtained of the move of only one German division from the Russian to theItalian front. At the present time there are four French and two British divisions in reserve on the Italian front which have not yet been engaged since their arrival in Italy,and the fifth British division is completing its arrival. This brings the number of&quot;British battalions in Italy up to sixty-five as against fifty-four French battalions, andthe fifth British division is being followed by additional heavy artillery, arrangementsfor the despatch of which, have been completed. In view of the lateness of the season,which makes operations in tbe mountains increasingly difficult and dangerous to theenemy, and of the fact that, in addition to the large Franco-British reserves, the Italianreserves are being rapidly reconstituted, the War Cabinet trust that the forces now in italy will suffice to meet any effort which the enemy may make, but as to this they arein constant communication with the Commander of the British Forces in Italy, who hasbeen instructed to report if he considers further reinforcements necessary.December 16, 1917.APPENDIX II.Telegram to Sir G. Barclay (Jassy).AS stated in my telegram of the 15th, His Majesty&apos;s Government are deeplyimpressed with the courage and loyalty of the Roumanian Government and army, and fully recognise the extreme gravity of their position should a united Russia conclude a separate peace with Germany and Austria. Meanwhile, however, this has notoccurred; and though there is apparently little or nothing to be expected of theRussian army for purposes even of organised defence, it does not appear certain that every province is prepared tamely to acquiesce in German domination, if and when theGovernment at Petrograd should advocate surrender at discretion. His Majesty&apos;aGovernment feel that, deplorable as is the course pursued by the Bolshevik party, itwill be worse than useless to attempt to modify it. by an appeal to tactics. If theRussians are resolved to fight no more, the pledges of the late Czar will not modify their determination. But this does not relieve us of the dutyT of supporting theRoumanian army by all the means in our power.Geographical reasons preclude us from sending men, but we are supplying moneynot merely to Roumania but to all the regions in Southern and Eastern Russia wherethere is the least hope that the people are prepared either to aid the Roumanian armyor to fight for their liberties against the common enemy, whether German or Turkish.We know of no other or better way of aiding the gallant Roumanian army, nor hasany other way been suggested to us. If it fails, and if that army is plainly in immediate peril of complete isolation, we cannot require it to carry on a hopeless-struggle. This would complete the ruin of Roumania, and would not help the Allies.In such circumstances there would be nothing left but to destroy the military stores andequipment, and make the best terms possible for the army, the country, and thedynasty. But this tragic consummation can only be contemplated in the last extremity,which even at the worst should not occur until the armistice comes to an end,In the meanwhile every effort should be made to establish relations with any forces-which for local or other reasons are unwilling to acquiesce in a policy of generalsurrender.A. J. B.December 16, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
