<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/17/30 images: 282-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His.-Brxta^oic. Majesty&apos; s Government.SECRET. TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND lug,W.P. (41) 157July   10th, 1941.       It is requested th8.t special/care may betaken to ensure the secrecy\pf this document.    - Copy -No...WAR CABINET.EXTENSION OF SINK AT SIGHT ZONE IN BAY OF BISCAY-.&apos; &apos; Memorandum &quot;by the First Lord of the Admiralty.The Cabinet last October (\Y,M. 280(40)f approved proposals for theextension of the then existing Bay of Biscay &quot;sink at sight&quot; zone, with theresult that it now runs from a point 20 miles v/est of the Scillies too o46 30&apos;N 7 W and thence diagonally to the border between France and Spain.The present area, therefore,&apos; has a depth from the French. Coast of about 90&apos;off Ushant and 140&apos; in the-centre of the Bay, but there is little depth in theSouth East corner.    It has been found in &quot;practice that south of Ushant owingto the enemy&apos;s control of the air, this zone does not give our submarinessufficient sea room, particularly in the south.    Since the enemy warshipsoperating in the Atlantic use the Bay ports, and since there is a considerablemovement of enemy supply ships in and out of the Bay, besides a certain numberof enemy merchantmen,. I consider it important to strengthen the. hands of oursubmarine commanders by widening the field of their opere-tions.Our submarines report that enemy shipping tends to enter the Bay,either by a northerly route between 47Q and 480N or by a southerly routebetween 44Q and 460N.    I propose that they should be authorised to sinkshipping at sight in all waters of the Bay, East of .12QW and between theparallels of 49 N and 44015&apos;N,    I further propose that this authority shouldbe given without notifying the area as dangerous to shipping.We have not before created a&quot;sink at sight&quot;zone without public declaration, but in November last the Cabinet approved my proposal- to lay asurface mine-field off the Little-Sole Bank, as a trap for enemy U-boats withoutdeclaration of the .area.. Part of the&apos; Northern sector of. the zone now x^roposedhas therefore already been made dangerous to shipping without declaration.My reason for asking the Cabinet to accept the sacrifice of principle involved in making no notification is that if our intention to extend the
existing area is announced,.the enemy will easily guess our motive and at onceroute his supply ships close to the Spanish coast.    By making no declarationwe hope, to.obtain several initial successes before he discovers what we are doing, and our own strict attitude in the past may help us in this respect. ;The justification for this departure from principle is that no neutralship will in fact be endangered.   Mo ship ever approaches the United kingdom from the south west except under the guidance of the Royal Navy.    Spanish ships- do not trade with&apos;Eire, and no ocean-going ships sail direct to North Spanishports.   All shipping visiting these ports is thus in fact coastal shipping, andthe lower limit of the new zone-&apos; by allowing 30 miles of free water off the NorthSpanish Coast leaves a wide margin of safety for all honest shipping.    The mainrisk, if any, is that an occasional Spanish fishing vessel may enter the zone,but the few fishing vessels that have&apos;; come under our&apos; notice in these waters havegiven us,reason to suspect that they were undertaking reconnaissance on behalfof the Germans.    Our own submarines would be unlikely to waste torpedoes orammunition on fishing vessels not acting sus-piciously.    But as an extra pre-caution I propose to give instructions that any vessel identified as Spanishis to be allowed to pass in safety.Our own fishing vessels have long since been warned that it is dangerous to fish south of 50oN.    A western limit to the zone of 120&apos;./ will notendanger our OYvn trade but will cover all likely submarine dispositions now andin the future for watching the approaches to the Bay of Biscay,I appreciate how important it is at this moment not to give any cause for offence to Spain.. But as long as no Spanish vessel is sunk - and this isprovided for by my proposals - the absence of any public declaration will assist in preventing any reaction from the Spaniards,   iloreover, the enemy1 s brutalmethods of warfare disentitle him to any consideration. - J.1 ask the Cabinet to approve these -prPP03als.,   - - A.V.A.A3MIBA1TI,&apos; S.W.1.   .-.lOthi - 19U.



</content>
</cab>
