<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/156/0 images: 68-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]Printed for the Cabinet. 9 secret.british empire report.No. 10.   4th February 1920.Contents.General.The General Labour Situation.   Survey of Industrial Disputes.Crown Colonies, Protectorates, &amp;c.Fiji. Indian Labourers&apos; Strike.Egypt. The Prime Minister and Sirri Pasha. The Order of Succession to the Sultanate.India.Letter to the King from the Amir. Viceroy&apos;s Letter to the Amir. Scare-mongering Press Reports. All-India Congress at Amritsar. The All brothers and the Caliphate. Moderate Congress in Calcutta. The Moslem League. The Hunter Committee.   Labour Unrest.The Dominions.Canada.-Immigration Conditions.   Trade with the West Iudies.Australia,-Harvest Conditions. Purchase of Dairy Produce. The Fruit Crop. Prohibition of Imports and Exports.New Zealand. Purchase of Meat and Dairy Produce. Purchase of Wool. Profits on Sale of Wool in England. Prohibition of the Importation of Czecho-Slovak Glassware.South Africa. The Budget. Lord Buxtohs Governorship. South Africa and the Royal Family.   Indians in the Transvaal.   Rates of Exchange Question.
[These two paragraphs are taken from the Report on the Labour Situation issued by the Ministry of Labour for the week ending 28th January 1920.]The General Labour Situation. Evidence has accumulated during the &quot;week that the recent pause, in the development of the great questions in which Labour is at present vitally interested will be followed within the next few weeks by events of the first importance. The issue on Avhich developments on a large scale are likely to occur is the nationalization of the mines. The present campaign of educational propaganda, which is now being prosecuted with increased vigour and determination,, comes to an end on the 8th February, and indications are now being given of the procedure which Labour may adopt on its conclusion. Mr. Hodge&apos;s statements on the matter are referred to elsewhere. But the nationalization issue is complicated by the fresh demands which the miners advanced in their interview with the Premier on the 28th January, and the whole question of policy with regard to the mines will be discussed in the next few days by the Miners&apos; Federation, the Labour Party and the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Onion Congress, in preparation for the action to be taken in Parliament and at the special Trades Union Congress. In view of this, the question of the respective merits of industrial and political action is again being discussed ; and in this connection it is of some interest to note that a convention of the rank and file movement has been summoned to take place previous to and during the Congress in order td make clear the policy of the rank and file in regard to the questions which the Congress will discuss. As this convention has been called on the initiative of the National Administrative Council of Shop Stewards&apos; and Workers&apos; Committees, its influence will be in the direction of extreme action.Survey of&apos; Industrial Disputes.-From the standpoint of industrial dispute, the present situation is more tranquil than it has been for many weeks. The ironuibulders&apos; strike has been brought to an end through the acceptance by a majority of the men of the terms agreed upon at the receut conference, and a threatened lock-out in the sheet metal trade has been ayerted by the decision of the men to remove an embargo with regard to the payment for,overtime and the handling of repairs. At the moment the only stoppages of, work of any importance are those clue1 to local disputes at Swansea, where the engineers employed in ship-repairing yards have struck to enforce a demand for a weekly minimum wage of 51., and at Glasgow, where the employees of the Subway Railway are still on strike. An early settlement of the latter dispute is expected, but the former will probably prove more difficult, owing to the fact that local variations in different trades are involved. The most important demand which has been, made during the week is that of the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation for an advance of 10s. per week in the wages of all adult road transport Workers, with the exception of tramway and omnibus drivers and conductors. The discussion of this question is expected to proceed on the lines of amicable negotiation between the parties concerned.CROWN COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, &amp;c.FIJI.Indian Labourers&apos; Strike. Some telegraphic correspondence has recently taken place between the Governor of Fiji and the Secretary of State for the Colonies on the subject of a strike of the Indian labourers. It appears that the majority of Indian workers at Suva and centres on the south coast of Viti-Levu have struck, but that there has been practically no disorder, and the leaders have assured the Government that the strike is intended as a peaceable protest against the high charge cost of. necessaries in comparison with the prevailing rate of wages.EGYPT.The Prime Minister and Sirri Pasha. On 1st February Lord Allenby reported [No. 89] that the Prime Minister had spoken to him very seriously of the difficulties of his position. The attempt to assassinate Sirri. Pasha, after the attempt on himself, had very much shaken him, indeed both of them. He, Lord Allenby, had clone what he could to encourage him; but he felt that the Prime Minister had retirement in his mind, and if that came about it would necessitate the Ministry&apos;s resignation.
The Order of Succession to the Siiltanale.-Referring to the letter addressed to the SultanFouad- on his accession, Lord Allenby, in a telegram [No. 90], dated 1st February, points out that the order of succession to the Sultanate was postponed for later decision. As Her Highness the Sultana is expected shortly to give birth to an infant, Lord Allenby has discussed with the Prime Minister, and through him with, the Sultan, the procedure to be observed should the infant be a son.The proposal of the Sultan is to issue a Sultanian order announcing the birth to the Council of Ministers. The order will also be communicated to the High Commissioner and to diplomatic agents. This order will be framed in accordance with the situation, and no mention will be made of an heir to the Sultanate. The event will be celebrated by a public holiday, and salutes of 21 guns will be fired in the principal centres.Lord Allenby is submitting the draft of a letter of congratulation which he proposes to address to the Sultan on receiving notification of the birth of a son. The birth of a daughter will call for no felicitations.INDIA.Letter to the King from, the Amir. -On 29th January the Viceroy reported [No. 110 S.] that two days previously an Afghan envoy had handed him a letter for His Majesty the King from the Amir, the letter being dated 14th January. In it the Amir said, that he washed to call attention to a Moslem question which concerned Great Britain more than any other nation. The question of the Caliphate was a matter with which no one but a Moslem had any right to interfere; and for five centuries it had been recognized that by Islamic law the Holy Places should be under the control of the Caliph. Not only the material, but also the spiritual welfare of human beings should be considered by the Great Powers, under whose control destiny had placed the whole world, and if this were not done the result would be the continuance of war and bloodshed. The sorrow and concern of the Moslem world was shared by Afghanistan, and he himself was at one with all Moslems in regard to the question of the Caliphate and the Holy Places.The Viceroy added that the word used for &quot;Holy Places&quot; would include Jerusalem, Damascus and Baghdad. He suggested too that no reply should be sent until an answer to his own. letter of 17th January had been received. Mr. Montagu informed him on 3.1st January that he agreed with this suggestion, and that mean-time only a formal acknowledgment was necessary.Yiceroy&apos;s Letter to the Amir - On 19th January the Viceroy reported [80 S, that he had written to the Amir on the lines suggested by the Secretary of State [B.E.R., ix., p. 2], and that the letter should reach Kabul a few clays later.Scaremonger ing Press Reports. Referring to a telegram received from General Malleson, in which the latter complains of the harm clone by misleading London telegrams which are scattered broadcast by the Bolsheviks as evidence of the terror in which we are supposed to be living, the Viceroy telegraphed [No. USS] on 28th January that the Indian Government endorsed General Malleson&apos;s views as regarded India.All-India Congress at Amrhsar. On 7th January the Viceroy telegraphed the following abstract of the resolutions passed by the All-India Congress at Amritsar :  First thanks Bis Majesty the King Emperor of India for Royal Proclamation and welcomes visit of His Royal Highness the Prince of Wales. Understood that in Subjects Committee great disappointment was expressed at the omission of all expression of sympathy with Punjab victims. Second set forth grievances of Indians in South Africa, especially Transvaal, calling for the protection of Indian rights in East Africa, Third related to Fiji indentures; thanks Mr. Andrews for services in Punjab, Fiji and elsewhere. Fourth thanks Sir Sankaran Nair for resignation as protesting against Government policy in Punjab. Fifth vindicates refusal of Congress Sub-Committee to co-operate with Hunter. Committee in the Punjab enquiries, this being moved by Gandhi, who condemned mob excesses while emphasizing grave provocation which led to outburst of mob frenzy. Sixth urges General Dyer be immediately relieved of command, and records opinion Government of Punjab and Government of India responsible for delay in publishing authoritative statement on Jallianwala Bagh incident. Mrs. Besant. in moving this resolution, stated condemn a-tion of officials followed from framed statements; she appealed to the audience toA2 .
purge all racial hatred aud trust in British justice. Seventh calls upon His Majesty&apos;s Government to relieve Sir Michael.0&apos;Dwyer of. membership of Army Commission as preliminary to legal action against him ; this motion supported by speeches of great violence, in which stated Sir Michaehs brutal ill-treatment of Punjab had shaken good faith of people in British justice. Eighth condoles with victims of disturbances, English and Indian. Ninth resolves to acquire site Jallianwala Bagh for nation, under trustees, to be used as memorial to perpetuate memory of those killed and wounded on 13th April. Tenth urges upon Secretary of State for India to advise His Majesty to veto the Rowlatt Act; Eleventh protests against Indemnity Bill as being passed while matter was still sub judiee in the face of unanimous protest of Press and people. Twelfth hopes that fullest effect will be given to letter and spirit of Royal Proclamation. Thirteenth, in view of the fact that Lord chelmsford has completely forfeited the confidence of the people of this country, this Congress humbly beseeches His Imperial Majesty the King to be graciously pleased immediately to recall His Excellency; understood that in Subjects Committee this motion was strongly opposed by Mrs. Besant, who was, however, outvoted by the Madras Extremists, headed by Satyamenthi. In open Congress only opposition came from B. N. Sarma, who stressed difficulties which Viceroy had been compelled to encounter, and emphasized value of his services to India. Fourteenth, (a) that this Congress reiterates its declaration of last year that India is lit for full responsible Government, and repudiates all assump-tions and assertions to the contrary, wherever made; (b) that this Congress adheres to resolution(s) passed at the Delhi Congress regarding constitutional reforms and (&apos;? is of opinion that) Reforms Act is inadequate, unsatisfactory and disappointing ; (c) that this Congress further urges that Parliament should take early steps to establish full responsible government in India in accordance with principle of self-determination. Asa concession to those who were not prepared to condemn the Reforms Act root and branch, following addition was made to the resolution : (d) pending sitch intro-duction, this Congress trusts that so far as may be possible they will so work the reforms as to secure the early establishment of full responsible government, and this Congress offers its thanks to the Right Hon. E. S. Montagu for his labours in connexion with the reforms. Understood that in Subjects Committee Mrs. Besant fought hard for more cordial welcome to reforms. In open Congress she introduced amendment begging people to take advantage of the new scheme. This was lost. Gandhi also opposed original motion. Being unwilling to condemn scheme, he agreed to compromise already mentioned, but Mrs. Besant pressed her amendment, which was lost. Fifteenth expresses thanks to Labour Party at home. Seventeenth urges imperative necessity of repeal of the Press Act, the Defence of India Act, 1915, and the Rowlatt Act.The Viceroy had already telegraphed on the previous day in regard to the Congress as follows: Although the Royal Proclamation was well received by all classes at the Amritsar Congress and the prompt release of political offenders gave general satisfaction, neither of these had any appreciable effect on the presidental speech of Pandit Moti Lai Nehru, which was extremely bitter in tone and had been circulated in advance to the newspapers. The speech gave the most prominent place to the Punjab disturbances, and a very lukewarm reception to reforms. The more important political prisoners, including Lala Har Kishen Lai, Chaudhuri Ram Bhuj Dutt, Safi-Uddin, Kitchlew, Satya Pal, on release proceeded straight to Amritsar, where they were accorded an enthusiastic reception. Their speeches showed no trace of gratitude for release. The Ali brothers also arrived during the course of the session, and delivered speeches of extreme violence. Speeches both at the Congress and the League were all unconciliatory in tone aud revealed the irreconcilable attitude of the extremists. Mrs. Besant, endeavouring to secure a more cordial reception for the Reform Scheme, made a quid pro quo speech, but received practically no support. Sarma was the only prominent politician who ventured to oppose the resolution for the recall of the Viceroy. The noticeable feature of the Congress proceedings was the studied (?)endeavour to keep alive the susceptibility occasioned by the Jallianwala Bagh incident. At this spot speeches were repeatedly made in violent language, photographs were taken, and the people encouraged to take away small portions of earth as sacred emblems, and arrange-ments are being made to purchase the land for the erection of a memorial, a dispensary, and a hall. The general effect produced by the Congress proceedings on moderate opinion in India is summed up as follows in Allahabad Leader of 4th January:  &quot; The Congress, judged not only by its resolution on reforms, but also by its proceedings generally, fully kept up its reputation for extremism. It has ceased to be an assembly where reasonable sound judgment can be expected to prevail.&quot;
The Ali Brothers and. the Caliphate. Or. 14th January the Viceroy reported that the Ali brothers had arrived in Delhi on the 9th, and had been accorded a triumphant reception. They had received a great ovation from the people and had addressed a public meeting from the dais arranged as ship, S.S. Liberty. On account of the tumult prevailing it was difficult to obtain a reliable or connected report of their speeches. According to one report they appealed to the religious feelings of the people, who should not allow the house of God to be dishonoured. The time was that for practical work, and they should make it plain to the Viceroy and the Secretary of State that if they wished 40 crores of Moslems to remain citizens of the British Empire, they should treat them according to the dictates of Islamic law. According to another report they appealed mainly for Hindu and Moslem unity, and advised the people to make the best of the present situation. After their reception they proceeded to Jamma Musjid, where prayers were said, and the brothers again made a short address to the crowd. At (?) Amritsar, Shaukat Ali was appointed President of the All-India-Caliphate Conference, and in that capacity he has approached the Viceroy with a view toleaxlinga deputation on the Caliphate question. The request has been provisionaUy granted, but the Ali brothers are reported to have left Delhi before the arrangements were completed. A movement has been started to bestow on them a purse of three lakhs, and it is believed that a tour has been undertaken to promote subscriptions.Telegraphing again on 20th January the Viceroy said : The Mohamedan Press is becoming increasingly outspoken regarding the Caliphate. Arrangements are being made in various places for the reception of the Ali brothers. They are reported to have spoken less violently&apos; at Lahore, on the 12th instant, than they did at Amritsar. Great stress is laid on the necessity of Hindu-Moslem unity to achieve the common object. Numerous Hindu meetings have thanked the President of the Moslem League for his advice to his co-religionists to abstain from cow-killing.Moderate Congress in Calcutta. On 7th January the Viceroy telegraphed the following abstract of the resolutions of the Moderate Congress, Calcutta : First, as in the [? Amritsar] Congress number one. Second thanks Secretary of State for India and Lord Sinha for carrying through reforms proposals. Third regrets omission of some measure of responsibility in central government, but welcomes Government of India Act, 1019, as definite and substantial step towards progressive realization of responsible government. Aggressors, all sections of community, European and Indian officials and non-officials whole-heartedly to co-operate in successfid working of Act. Fourth deprecates delay in settlement of Turkish peace terms, and urges determination of question without contravening principle of justice and national integrity. Fifth urges trial of officials who acted unreasonably in disturbances, and reparation for hardships caused by undue severity. Sixth advocates safeguards in regard to future introduction of martial law, with deputation to England if necessary. Seventh protests against treatment Indians South Africa. Eighth urges necessity placing defensive organization of country on national basis by opening King&apos;s commissions to Indians on liberal scale; admission Indians freely all arms, artillery, navy and air forces, organization of territorial army and provision of adequate military training. Ninth advocates subjects Indian States settled in British India be eligible for franchise and election Legislative Councils. Tenth advocates organization of Liberal Party to work for success constitutional reforms following policy of co-operation promoting good understanding between various communities aiming at higher standard of national efficiency by means of administrative reforms, increased education, improved public health, economic development, and amelioration of backward classes. Liberal Associations in all parts to be component parts National Liberal Federation.The Moslem League. On 6th January the Viceroy reported that the Moslem League was entirely under extremist influence and had become a mere echo of the Amritsar Congress, repeating most of its resolutions with additions regarding the Caliphate.The Hunter Committee. Telegraphing on 6th,&apos; 14th and 20th January, the Viceroy reported as follows in regard to the Hunter Committee : (1) The Punjab leaders released in accordance with the Royal Proclamation wired last week to Lord Hunter that they would now be willing to lead their own and other evidence before the Committee, and suggested that they should be permitted to recall official witnesses for cross-examintion if necessary. Pandit Malaviya, on behalf of the Congress Sub-Committee, telegraphed to the same effect.   Lord HunterA 3
Greplied that the Committee had sat at Lahore for over six weeks and had completed the hearing: there : full opportunity was given for the presentation of uon-official evidence and that it was open to their counsel to cross-examine witnesses during that period.   For these reasons he was unable to accept the suggestion.   &apos;(2) The decision of the Hunter Committee not to have evidence led by the Congress leaders is the subject of adverse comment by the Congress Sub-Committee, &apos; which considers the attitude of the Hunter Committee erroneous and a matter of painful surprise. The ground for rejecting the offer of the Congress Committee, that the Hunter Committee had already passed six weeks in Lahore, is criticized as not only irrelevant but symptomatic of something disquieting. The Bombay Chronicle considers the decision to be lamentable, ungracious and unfair. Comments on General Dyer and the retention of Sir M. 0&apos;Dwyer continue. The publication of the Committee&apos;s report will be the subject of renewed agitation.(3) The Hunter Committee has concluded its sessions at Ahmedabad and. begins work at Bombay on the 13th. M. K. Gandhi, the most important witness at Ahmedabad, explained the essence of the Satyagraha movement as being not essentially antagonistic to the Government. He condemned the action of the mob at Ahmedabad and Virangaum. The trouble in Ahmedabad was anti-Government, but he could not say if anti-European. The authorities acted with restraint at Ahmedabad, and the work of the special tribunals was clone consistently with the laws of civilized justice. The levy on the poor people of Ahmedabad and Nadiad was not justified.(4) The Hunter Committee has concluded its sessions at Bombay, the last witness being Sir M. 0&apos;Dwyer, who was examined in camera. His examination extended over two clays. It is understood that the Committee will proceed to Agra to prepare the report, which may be expected about the middle of February.Labour Unrest. Telegraphing on 6th January the ATceroy reported the existence of considerable labour unrest, saying : The Central Provinces report that there is no doubt that the workers of the Empress mills objected to the closing of the mills on the peace celebration clay and wished for work, but the manager refused permission. On Christmas Day the mills struck. The strike had been carefully organized ; but there were no disturbances and no demands were formulated, the men being ignorant as to the reasons of their strike. It was said to have beemengmcered for political reasons on account of peace clay ; but later information shows that the strikers returned to work unconditionally.Bombay reports a serious strike on 2nd January among the mill hands. Altogether 31 mills are out, as well as the Great Indian Peninsula Railway workshops at Matunga. The strikers at the Sassoon spinning and weaving mills broke in the gate and then assaulted the European management; the assistant manager fired with a revolver in self defence, but did. no damage. The manager, was slightly injured. The mill hands demand the immediate payment of the bonus promised for 7th February. The railway workshop hands, following suit, demand a bonus similar to other mill hands, also free passage to their homes and a 15 per cent, rise in wages. The meeting of the Committee of the Mill Owners&apos; Association, held, on 2nd January, had no information as to the cause of the strike. There have been no disorders other than that mentioned above.Telegraphing again on 14th January he said : The strike of the Bombay mill hands continues, and now involves over 80 mills and two lakhs of workers. It has spread to the Bombay oil mills and flour mills and to the Burma Oil Company, involving about 20,000 employees. The demands of the Mill Hands&apos; Association were formulated on the 5th as follows : (1) A further increase of 50 per cent, in wages, equal to 80 per cent, advance on pre-war wage.(2) A 10 hours&apos; day.(3) Payment of the bonus within 10 days of resumption of work. (4) Payment of the money-wage before the 15th of each succeeding month. There was some difference [? of opinion] as to holding out for [? an] eight hours&apos; [? day].   The mill-owners have also combined, and have agreed as follows : (1) Action not to be taken by individual owners.(2) No payment shall be given for the days employees are on strike and noticeof this shall be given to men. (3) The General Committee of Mill Owners to consider the question of calcu-lating the bonus clue.
-Increasing signs of disorders and more cases of shop looting have been reported officially. The mob attacked a mixed picket of military police accompanied by a magistrate, the magistrate, the lorry driver and others of party being hit with stones. &quot;The magistrate ordered the crowd to disperse, and on their displaying a defiant attitude&apos; gave orders to disperse the crowd by force, The sergeant and one private then fired -one round each, killing one rioter and seriously injuring another. Order was imme-diately restored and no signs of disorder have since occurred.On 20th January the Viceroy reported that there was no improvement in the situation and that the strike showed a tendency to spread.THE DOMINIONS.CANADA.Immigration Conditions. The High Commissioner was informed by the Director -of Information at Ottawa on 21st January that during the twelve months ended 30th November 1919, 114,000 immigrants entered Canada, of whom 54,600 came from the United Kingdom, and 52,100 from the United States. Mechanics, artisans and labourers entering Canada before March next are required to have in their possession $250 in cash in addition to transportation to their destination, but this provision does not apply to those going on to farms. If married, immigrants of the above classes must have an additional $125 for each son or daughter over eighteen years of age, and $50 for each child between five and eighteen years old, as well as transportation to their destination.Trade with the West Indies. On 28th January the High Commissioner was also informed from the same source that Mr. F. H. Keefer, M.P., Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for External Affairs, was on his way to the West Indies to attend a conference which had been called with the object of promoting trade between Canada and the Islands.AUSTRALIA.Harvest Conditions.[B.E.R. ix, p. 5]. On 21st January the Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Governor-General of Australia that the Royal Commission on Wheat Supplies had carefully and sympathetically considered the proposals outlined by the Prime Minister of the Commonwealth, but, owing to the difficulty of securing the necessary wheat in North America, and to the grave apprehension of labour disputes in Argentina, it finds that to sacrifice wheat in Australia would endanger the supplies of the United Kingdom. The expectation of drawing an alternative supply from South Russia had been entirely dispelled, whilst Indian export was still doubtful.Tonuage had already been allotted to load the very large part of the wheat still remaining to be shipped from Australia, and further tonnage had been arranged to load the balance as quickly as possible.In these circumstances, and as the United Kingdom was by far the largest customer for Australian wheat, the Royal Commission on Wheat Supplies regretted being unable to agree to forego any of the wheat supplies already purchased in Australia, and felt that they were justified in asking that if necessary the other outside markets should be temporarily sacrificed by Australia rather than the United Kingdom.The case would be different if there were an actual shortage of wheat in Australia for local requirements, but it had not been gathered from the telegram of 10th January that such shortage was likely to exist if necessary the action to guard against undue export to other destinations were taken by the Commonwealth Government.Purchase of Dairy Produce. On 29th January the Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Governor-General of Australia that he regretted that it was impossible to say at present whether His- Majesty&apos;s Government would wish to continue the contract purchase of Australian butter or cheese after the expiration of the present contracts at the end ol: August next.   The Food Controller, however, had
enquired what prices producers would he prepared to accept for next season&apos;? export-able surpluses in the event of His Majesty&apos;s Government deciding to continue the control of these commodities beyond that date.The Fruit Crop. The allocation of. insulated space for shipping Australian fruit has been the subject of telegraphic correspondence between the Governor-General of the Commonwealth and the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Telegraphing on 24th January the Governor-General said that Mr. Hughes had advised him that 1,600,000 cubic feet insulated space allocated for Australian fruit had been distributed and had been found to be wholly inadequate to meet the growers&apos;Tequire-ments. Unless a similar additional quantity of space, namely, 1,000,000 cubic feet, could be made available, he feared, that the growers must suffer a heavy loss. It would be greatly appreciated if further space could be made available for fruit. Cold storage had been, reduced, and from the information available he considered, some meat space might be given temporarily to fruit, which cannot wait; this would greatly benefit the fruit growers and would not unduly penalise the meat exporters.In a later telegram dated the 30th January, the Governor-General stated that Mr. Hughes advised him that further investigations confirmed the opinion that ships could be temporarily released from carrying meat, that the fruit crop was exceptionally heavy, and that more fruit space was essential. Otherwise, the results must be most disastrous to fruit growers. The Commonwealth Government desired to know also whether it would be possible to arrange for some insulated space for grapes from Western Australia.The Secretary of State for the Colonies replied on 4th February as follows:  The Board of Trade have agreed to the immediate allocation cf further 808,000 cubic feet insulated space for Australian fruit. On the understanding that the freight rate is based on the apace occupied, there is no objection to the shipment of grapes in this space, which is allotted for any fruit requiring cold storage.Prohibition of Imports and Exports. The Governor-General of the Common-wealth reported in a telegram, dated 3rd February, that the Commonwealth Government had issued a proclamation on 14th January prohibiting the importation, directly or indirectly, from Germany, Austria-Hungary, Turkey and Bulgaria, of goods which owe more than 5 per cent, of their value to the labour and/or the material of these countries, and goods bearing avoided or suspended trade marks. A proclamation had been issued on the same date prohibiting export to the above countries Importation would be allowed of goods the produce or manufacture of Gzecho-Slovakia and other States which have been removed from the jurisdiction of Austria. Exportation would, be allowed similarly. The same policy would be adopted with reference to those States which it is proposed to remove from the jurisdiction of Turkey. The Commonwealth Government would be glad if His Majesty&apos;s Government would cable the present position in this connexion. Advice was desired as to (1) what parts of Turkey will be placed under mandate to the Allied Governments; (2) what provinces, if any, are at present being administered by the Allied Governments, and what provinces remain under the control of the Government, of Turkey.NEW ZEALAND.Purchase of Meat and Dairy Produce [B.E.R. ix., p. 6]. On 22nd January the Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed to the Governor-General, of New Zealand informing him that His Majesty&apos;s Government had decided not to enter into further contracts for the purchase of meat after 30th June 1920.Telegraphing again on 29th January he said that the Food Controller had inquired as to the prices New Zealand producers would be prepared to accept for next season s exportable surplus of butter and cheese in the event of His Majestys Government deciding to continue the control of these commodities after the expiration of the present contract [31st August].Purchase of Wool [B.E.R. ix., p. 6]. On 23rd January the Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Governor-General of New Zealand that His Majesty&apos;s Government did not contemplate extension of the wool contract beyond 30th June next.Profits on Sale of Wool in England. On 22nd January a telegram was received from the Governor-General of New Zealand, reporting that the public Press in that Dominion was publishing startling reports,. emanating from London, with regard to&apos;
alleged enormous profits being madfe in England on New Zealand wool; and adding that his Prime Minister would be obliged if the Colonial Office Wouid ascertain when it, would be possible for the Director of haw Materials to make a definite statement in -connexion with the 50 per cent, share of profits which belonged to the New Zealand sheep farmers.Prohibition of the. Importation of Gzechn-Slovdk Glassware.; On 28th January the Secretary of State for the Colonies sent the following telegram to the Governor-General -of New Zealand : The Gzecho-Slovak Charge d&apos;Affaires has recently enquired regarding the prohibition, stated to exist, on the importation into New Zealand of glassware from -Czecho-Slovakia, known in trade as Gableuz goods and manufactured in Northern Bohemia. Your Prime Ministers telegram of 1st November to the High Commis-sioner indicates that the New Zealand Government has hitherto been unwilling to encourage trade with Czechoslovakia, but in view of the fact that Czecho-Slovakia was recognized as an Allied nation so far back as August 1918, has signed Treaties of Peace as one of the Allied and Associated Powers, and is an original member of the League of Nations, His Majesty&apos;s Government hope that the New Zealand Government will feel able to discontinue any restrictions specially designed to hamper trade with Czecho-Slovakia. The same remark applies to trade-with the other friendly new States, viz., Poland and the Serb-Crrtat-Slovene State, if any similar restrictions are still in force in New Zealand.Your Government will appreciate the unfortunate consequences which might result from any policy which placed hindrances upon the resumption of export trade by these friendly States in view of their present economic difficulties.SOUTH AFRICA.The Budget. Telegraphing from Pretoria on&apos; 29th January, ReuteFs agent reported that at an election meeting held there Mr. Orr, the Minister of Finance, had remarked that, in spite of an increased expenditure of 2,000,OOOL on public war services; if any new burdens were imposed in the next budget they would be extremely light.Lord Buxton&apos;s Governorship. ReuteFs- agent telegraphed from Johannesburg on 28th January, saying that Lord Buxton had that day laid the foundation stone of a medical school in connexion with the Witwatersrand University College; and that at a luncheon party prior to the ceremony the Alayor, proposing the Governor-Generabs health, had alluded to His Excellency&apos;s forthcoming departure, and said that he had risen triumphant above the difficulties during, perhaps, the most difficult and trying period of South African history.South Africa and the Royal Family. In the course of his speech the Mayor of Johannesburg also said that it was most gratifying to hear of His Majesty&apos;s keen., interest in South African affairs, and His Majesty might be assured of a warm welcome-in Johannesburg for any member of his family.Indians in the Transvaal. ReuteFs agent reported from Johannesburg on 26th January that a representative of the British Indians in the Transvaal had started for England for the purpose of submitting to Mr. Montagu, the Secretary of State for India, a statement of the grievances of Indians in South Africa. This representative will afterwards sail for India to call attention to the position in the Transvaal.Rates of Exchange Question. On 28th January ReuteFs agent telegraphed from Capetown, saying: Despite the fact that the controversy on the rates of exchange question is almost, incomprehensible to the general public, the recent statement made by Mr. J. YV. Jagger, in which lie urged that the rate of exchange should be allowed to fall to its natural basis by removing the prohibition on the export of gold specie, is attracting great attention because of its bearing on the cost of living and the holding out of hope of a reduction in prices. It is likely to figure prominently in the coming election, a remarkable development of which has been that in the Malmesbury division, the Nationalist candidate has retired in favour of Mr. J. Van cler Horst, the prominent Capetown financier, who is well known to be staunchly in favour of the Allies as regards the war.   Mr. Van der Horst, who is an Independent Reformer, is opposing
Mr. Malan, Minister of Mines, and says he is au Economic Reformer. His views are-in general agreement with Mr. Jagger&apos;s pronouncement. This is one of the most piquant incidents in South African political history. Mr. Jagge.r&apos;s views are being-discussed in all the provinces, and are meeting with stout, opposition from prominent Transvaalers.Mr. Reynolds, the banker, says nobody will probably quarrel with Mr. Jagger&apos;s natural exchange in theory, but it is quite impossible in the present abnormal situation. He believes it would penalize capital coming from England, thus retarding new industries, while investment capital would leave South Africa. He emphasizes that it would be greatly disadvantageous to the exporter and concludes by defending the increased issue of bank notes, declaring that this could not be described as &quot;inflation,&quot; since it is a perfectly normal increase, clue to the increased price of commodities.To-night Mr. Jagger vigorously replies to his critics and quotes the figures of greatly increased issues of bank notes and the holding of only 8 per cent, of bullion. He declares that this position-uncomfortable for banks is the result of their over-trading as measured by their gold resources, and by their so regulating the exchange that, gold is only procurable from England at a loss to themselves. Now the banks are coming to the Government to save them, he says, and they want to go on issuing bauk notes as they themselves think fit, but such issues would result in a further increase of prices. &apos; Mr. Jagger rebuts the suggestion that a natural exchange would mean the export, of investment capital. On the question of fresh capital for South Africa, he points out that money is much cheaper in South Africa to-day than in London.Replying to assertions that the exporter may be penalized 50 per cent., he says that would mean that the English paper pound had dropped to the value of ten shillings and that prices had risen in England accordingly. He asks if South African con-sumers must suffer accordingly, as they certainly must if the present system is maintained. He concludes by saying that he - desires to see South Africa progress, but on sound lines. Inconvertible currency would enable the banks largely to increase advances, thus causing speculation, higher prices and reaction, like the financial crisis in South Africa in 1882-86 and 1904-08. He is anxious, if possible, to avoid a third crisis. He realizes the seriousness of the position caused by the cost of living and says that the Union wants to check the ever-continuous rise in prices.

</content>
</cab>
