<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/156/0 images: 233-244</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]Printed for the Cabinet.96secret.BRITISH EMPIRE REPORT.No. 25.   1st September 1920.Contents.Great Britain.The Labour Situation.Colonies, Protectorates, &amp;c.Egypt, Proposed Policy. Palestine. Trans-Jordania. Mesopotamia. Military Policy.India.Situation on the Frontier.   The Viceroy&apos;s Weekly Reports. The Dominions.League of Nations, and Imperial Cabinet.   Disposal of German Naval Material. Canada. League of Nations.   Imperial Cabinet.   Miscellaneous. Australia. Imperial Cabinet.     Austrian Debts.    German Consular Repre-sentation.New Zealand. Butter.   Wool.   Imperial Cabinet.South Africa. Lord Buxton.   League of Nations.   Imperial Cabinet.so 20-1     120   9/20
GREAT BRITAIN.The following paragraphs are taken from the Reports of the Ministry of Labour for the weeks ending 18th August and 25th August, and give a general survey of the situation for the respective weeks : The Labour Situation. The situation remains comparatively quiet as far as actual strikes are concerned. As regards the future, it is generally expected that the ballot of the Miners&apos; Federation will go strongly in favour of a strike.In the political sphere, the week has been notable for the display of unanimity on the Russian-Polish question by the National Labour Conference on the 1.3th August, who gave a mandate to the Council of Action, and for the proceedings of the Council- of Action themselves in the execution of the mandate. This significantly includes a positive demand for immediate peace, and recognition of the Soviet Government.An interesting feature of the week has been the initiation of a fresh campaign for the resettlement of ex-Service men.The Prime Minister stated in the House of Commons on the 16th August that there were indications that the amount of unemployment during the coming winter might be&apos;in excess of that usually caused by seasonal depression. He announced the appointment of a Cabinet Committee to consider the position.: [18th August..]The centre of interest has shifted more to the industrial side of the labour-situation. The result of the ballot of the Miners&apos;Federation on a strike to enforce the demand for reduced prices and increased wages will be officially declared on the 30th August. The Food Controller made a statement to the Press, on the 24-th August, on the preparations which are being made by the Government to maintain the food supply in the event of the ballot being favourable to a strike. A national crisis has also arisen in the engineering industry out of the Penistone dispute. In both instances, other powerful unions will be seriously affected, and there are indications that an attempt may be made by these unions to bring some influence to bear in the interests of industrial peace.On the political side the National Council of Action have adopted for the present 1 a waiting policy. At the same time, much activity is being devoted to the organization of demonstrations and the perfecting of local machinery.COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, &amp;c.EGYPT.   .Proposed Policy. On 21st August Lord Curzon informed [No. 750] Mr. Scott that Lord Milner had handed to him a document the full text of which would be immediately telegraphed to him. Mr. Scott was also informed that copies of the document had been given to Adli Pasha for communication to Zaghloul ancl the members of his delegation. Attention was called to the fact that the policy indicated had not yet been considered by His Majesty&apos;s Government, and that the absence of the Prime Minister and of many members of the Cabinet must necessarily oblige its consideration to be deferred. The document was sent to Mr. Scott for, his information ancl, that of the Egyptian Government on that clear rmderstanding. The main points were likely to become generally known, because they would probably form the basis on which Zaghloul and his friends, who were acquainted with them, would conduct their operations, but they were not intended for publication.The full text of the document referred to above is contained in the following-telegram [No. 751], which was despatched to Mr. Scott on the same date : The accompanying Memorandum is the result of conversations held in London in June to August 1920, between Lord Milner ancl the members of the Special Mission to Egypt, and Zaghloul Pasha and the members of the Egyptian Delegation, in which
-conversations Adli Pasha also took part. It outlines a policy for the settlement of the Egyptian question in the best interests, both of Great Britain and Egypt.The members of the Mission are prepared to recommend the British Government to adopt the policy indicated in the Memorandum, if. they are satisfied that Zaghloul Pasha and the Delegation are likewise prepared to advocate it, and will use all their influence to obtain the assent of an Egyptian National Assembly to the conclusion of such a Treaty as is contemplated in Articles 3 and 4.It is clear that, unless both parties are cordially united in supporting it, the policy here suggested cannot be pursued with success.Memorandum.1. In order to establish, the independence of Egypt on a secure and lasting basis, It is necessary that the relations between Great Britain and Egypt, should be precisely defined, and the privileges and immunities now enjoyed in Egypt by thecapitulatory Powers should be modified and rendered less injurious to the interests of the country.2. These ends cannot be achieved without further negotiations between accredited representatives of the British and Egyptian Governments respectively in the one case, and between the British Government and the Governments of the capitulatory Powers in the other case. Such negotiations will be directed to arriving at definite agreements on the following lines-3. (1) As between Egypt and Great Britain it is proposed that a Treaty should be entered into, under which Great Britain will recognize the independence of Egypt as a constitutional monarchy with representative institutions, and Egypt will confer upon Great Britain such rights as are necessary to safeguard her special interests and to enable her to furnish the guarantees which must be given to foreign Powers to secure the relinquishment of their capitulatory rights.(2) By the same Treaty, an Alliance will be concluded between Great Britain and. Egypt, by which Great Britain will undertake to support Egypt in defending the integrity of her territory, and Egypt will undertake, in case of war, even when the integrity of Egypt is not affected, to render to Great Britain all the assistance in her power, within her own borders, including the use. of her harbours, aerodromes, and means of communication for military purposes.4. The proposed Treaty will embody stipulations to the following effect: (i) Egypt will enjoy the right to representation in foreign countries.   In theabsence of any duly-accredited Egyptian representative, the Egyptian Government will confide its interests to the care of the British represen-tative. Egypt will undertake not to adopt in foreign countries an attitude which is inconsistent with the Alliance or will create difficulties for Great Britain, and will also undertake not to enter into any agreement with a foreign Power which is prejudicial to British interests.(ii) Egypt will confer on Great Britain the right to maintain a military force on Egyptian soil for the protection of her Imperial communications. The Treaty will fix the place where the force shall be quartered, and will regulate any subsidiary matters which require to be arranged. The presence of this force shall not constitute in any manner a military occupation of the country, or prejudice the rights of the Government of Egypt. ;(iii) Egypt will appoint, in concurrence with His Majesty&apos;s Government, a financial Adviser, to whom shall be entrusted in due course the powers at present exercised by the Commissioners of the Debt, and who will be at the disposal of the Egyptian Government for all other matters on which they may desire to consult him.(iv) Egypt will appoint, in concurrence with His Majesty&apos;s Government, anofficial in the Ministry of Justice, who shall enjoy the right of access to the Minister. He shall be kept fully informed on. all matters connected with the administration of the law as affecting foreigners, and will also be at the disposal of the Egyptian Government for consultation on any matter connected with the efficient maintenance of law and order. .(y) In view of the contemplated transfer to His Majesty&apos;s Government of the rights hitherto exercised under the regime of the Capitulations by the ( various foreign Governments, Egypt recognizes the right of Great Britain to intervene, through her representative in Egypt, to prevent
the application to foreigners of any Egyptian law now requiring foreign: consent, and Great Britain on her side undertakes not to exercise this, right except in the case of laws operating inequitably against foreigners.Alternative.In view of the contemplated transfer to His Majesty&apos;s Government of the rights hitherto exercised under the regime of the Capitulations by the various foreign Governments, Egypt recognizes the right of Great Britain to intervene, through her representative in Egypt, to prevent the application to foreigners of any Egyptian law now requiring foreign consent, and Great Britain on her side undertakes not to exercise this right except in the case of laws inequitably discriminating against foreigners in the matter of taxation, or inconsistent with the principles: of. legislation common to all the capitulatory Bowers.(vi) On account of the special relations between Great Britain and Egyptcreated by the Alliance, the British representative will be accorded an exceptional position in Egypt, and will be entitled to precedence over all other representatives.(vii) The engagements of British and other foreign officers and administrativeofficials who entered into the service of the Egyptian Government before the coming into force of the Treaty, may be terminated at the instance of either the officials themselves or the Egyptian Government,, at any time within two years after the coming info force of the Treaty. The pension or compensation to be accorded to officials retiring under this provision, in addition to that provided by the existing law, shall be determined by the Treaty, In cases where no advantage is taken of&quot; this arrangement, existing terms of service will remain unaffected.5. This Treaty will be submitted to the approval of a Constituent Assembly, but it will not come into force until after the agreements with foreign Powers for the closing of their consular courts and the decrees for the reorganization of the Mixed Tribunals have come into operation.6. This Constituent Assembly will also be charged with the duty of framing a new Organic Statute, in accordance with the provisions of which the Government of&quot;Egypt will in future be conducted. This Statute will embody provisions for the Ministers being responsible to the Legislature. It will also provide for religious toleration for all persons, and for the due protection of the rights of foreigners..7. The necessary modifications in the regime of the Capitulations will be.secured by agreements to be concluded by Great Britain with the various capitulatory Powers. These agreements will provide for the closing of the foreign consular courts, so as to -render possible the. reorganization and extension of the jurisdiction of the Mixed Tribunals and the application to all foreigners in Egypt of the legislation (including legislation imposing taxation) enacted by the Egyptian Legislature.8. These agreements will provide for the transfer to His Majesty&apos;s Government of the rights previously exercised under the regime of the Capitulations by the various . foreign Governments.   They will also contain stipulations to the following effect: (a) No attempt will be made to discriminate against the nationals of a Power which agrees to close its consular courts, and such nationals shall enjoy in Egypt the same treatment as British subjects ;(6) The Egyptian Nationality Law will be founded on the jus sanguinis, so that the children born in Egypt of a foreigner will enjoy the nationality of their father and will not be claimed as Egyptian subjects;(c) Consular officers of the foreign Powers shall, be accorded by Egypt the same--status as foreign Consuls enjoy in England ;(rl) Existing treaties and conventions to which Egypt is a party on matters of commerce and navigation, including postal and telegraphic conventions, will remain in force. Pending the conclusion of special agreements to which she is a party, Egypt will apply the treaties in force between Great Britain and the foreign Power concerned on questions affected by the closing of the consular courts, such as extradition treaties, treaties for the surrender of seamen deserters, &amp;c, as also treaties of a political nature,...
whether multilateral or bilateral, e.g., arbitration conventions and the various conventions relating to the conduct of hostilities. (b) The liberty to maintain schools and to teach the language of the foreign country concerned will be guaranteed, provided that such schools are subject in all respects to the laws applicable generally to European schools in Egypt.(/) The liberty to maintain or organize religious and charitable foundations, such as hospitals, &amp;c, will also be guaranteed.The treaties will also provide for the necessary changes in the Commission of the Debt and the elimination of the international element in the Alexandria Board of Health.9. The legislation rendered necessary by die aforesaid agreements between Great Britain and the foreign Bowers will be effected by decrees to be issued by the Egyptian Government.A decree shall be enacted at the same time, validating all measures, legislative, administrative or judicial, taken under martial law.10. The decrees for the reorganization of the Mixed Tribunals will provide for conferring upon these tribunals all jurisdiction hitherto exercised by the foreign consular courts, while leaving the jurisdiction of the native courts untouched.11. After the coming into force of the Treaty referred to in Article 3, Great Britain will communicate its terms to foreign Bowers and will support an application by Egypt for admission as a member of the League of Nations.With reference to these proposals, the following telegram [Circ. No. 49] from the Foreign Office was circulated to His Majesty&apos;s representatives at the principal capitals in Europe, and at Washington, on 26th August: In case exaggerated reports appear in the Press with regard to recent develop-ments in the Egyptian situation, it may be well for you to be accmainted with the following facts : As a result of negotiations between Lord milner&apos;s Mission and Zaghloul and his associates, certain heads of agreement have been arrived at, the substance of which was more or less correctly published in the Times of 23rd and 24th August. These terms have not yet received the approval or the consideration of His Majesty&apos;s Government.Certain of ZaghlouPs associates are returning to Egypt to endeavour to obtain the support of the Egyptian people for an agreement on the lines proposed. If they are successful, ancl if His Majesty&apos;s Government approve, it will then be necessary for a treaty to be negotiated by properly appointed representatives of His Majesty&apos;s Government ancl of the Sultan of Egypt. Nothing in the terms of the proposed agreement will interfere with the modification of the Capitulations and abolition of consular courts, the negotiations with regard to which yon should endeavour to expedite as much as possible.Nor does the agreement affect the Sudan.PALESTINE.Trans-Jordania, Telegraphing [No. 207] on 22nd August, Sir Herbert Samuel reported, his visit on the 20th to Es Salt, where he was welcomed by the Arab population. He received numerous deputations from towns, villages and tribes of the neighbouring district ancl southwards to Akaba, all asking for British administration. At a meeting held on the following day, Sir Herbert set forth the lines on which the British administration of Trans-Jordania might be established, all of which were warmly received. Sir Herbert reported that it was impossible that the desire for British administration could be more definite and unanimous.On 26th August Lord Curzon telegraphed [No. 110] to Sir Herbert Samuel that any extension of their responsibilities in Arab districts was contrary to the desire of His Majesty&apos;s Government, who could not go beyond a very limited assistance to a native administration. There must be no question of establishing any British administration in Trans-Jordania. All that might be done at present was to send a few suitable political officers, who would receive special instructions on the lines laid down in Foreign Office telegram [No. 80] of 11th August. The duties of these 20-1 B
officers, as indicated therein, were to be confined to the encouragement of local self-government and to giving advice to the people when they asked for it. Assistance was to be given in the formation of municipal and district self-governing bodies, and no opportunity was to be lost of encouraging tradewith Palestine, which, it was to be emphasized, is the natural outlet for Trans-Jordania.In acknowledgment of the above, Sir.Herbert reported [No. 224] on 27th August that he had established officers at Es Salt, Ammam, Kerak. Irbid and Jarash, with instructions strictly in conformity with the lines laid down.MESOPOTAMIA.Military Policy. On 26th August the Secretary of State for War despatched the following telegram to General Ealdane, Commanding-in-Chief the Forces in Mesopotamia:  I take this opportunity of sending you my earnest good wishes for the. success of the difficult task you are discharging. The Cabinet have decided that the rebels &apos; must be quelled effectually, and I shall endeavour to meet all your requirements. We have arranged to send, you the additional 19 battalions from India. The third air squadron should shortly be available for action, and I have to-day ordered the fourth air squadron (the 55th) from Constantinople to Basra with all speed. Thus, by the middle or end of October you should be possessed of effective striking forces, and a vigorous use of these to put down and punish disaffection, combined with the policy of setting up an Arab State, should bring about a better situation.I shall be glad to hear from you if you have any further needs, though, of course, you know how severely strained our limited resources are.INDIA.Situation on the Frontier. On 26th August the Viceroy reported that the situation on the Iiazara border between Mansehra and Oghi had become unsettled, as a result of the Caliphate agitation. As a precautionary measure, at the request of. the Chief Commissioner, troops from, the Abbottabad district had been sent into the affected area.   According to the latest reports the situation was improving.The Viceroy&apos;s Weekly Reports. The following reports were sent on 21st August and 27th August: I. (21st August.) To prepare the ground for a special session, of the All-India Congress Committee in September, the Provincial. Congress Committees were invited to express their views on non-co-operation. In Madras no decision was arrived at. Patna decided in favour of non-co-operation, but many members challenged the decision. In Lahore non-co-operation was carried by a majority of votes. In Bombay it was approved. The Bengal Committee has also passed a resolution, moved by Bipin Chandra Pal, recording the. opinion that non-co-operation in the sense of passive resistance is a perfectly constitutional weapon in the political struggle between the people and the Government, and is the only effective weapon left to the former; that the practical working out of this principle should, be left to each province; that as auxiliaries to the non-co-operation campaign, attempts should be made to establish arbitration courts and national education institutions, and to revive the Swadeshi and. boycott movements, but that the boycott should not extend to the new legislative bodies, which demand the presence of members prepared to resort to non-co-operation within the Council. These represent extremist views, and are generally disapproved by the moderates. Mr. JSf. D. Metha has withdrawn his name from membership of the reception committee of the special congress in view of the adoption of the non-co-operation resolution by the Bengal Provincial Committee.2. Meantime, Gandhi, touring in Madras, upholds non-co-operation as constitu-tional so long as it is without violence ; he has made an appeal to lawyers to suspend practice, and evolve law and order through the institution of Panchayat courts. He appealed to people not to send boys to schools, which were mere factories for manufacturing clerks and Government servants; he appealed to people not to seek
-election in the Legislative Council and to boycott the visit of the Prince of Wales.He urged Mussulmans to stand single-handed, and to make it impossible for the -Congress to give any other verdict but in favour of non-co-operation. B. C. Pal,, speaking in Calcutta before the Provincial Congress Committee referred to above, indicated two ways of obtaining national freedom : (1) revolution,which was impossible; (2) peaceful conciliation, ecpiatly impossible; non-co-operation was the only weapon left, by which he meant passive resistance. He did not support GandhPs four stages, but two stages : (a) refusal to give social honour to title holders, and (b) complete reduction, of the social value of Government service.3. Approximately 30,000 muhajarins migrated to Afghanistan, mainly from the rural tracts of the Peshawar district, but the excitement has spread to Bannu, Kohat and other districts. The orders from Afghanistan came at a time when feeling was beginning to run dangerously high, and to affect Government servants, including the police. The general tension appears to be slackening and the position is distinctly better. Zafar Ali, tlie editor of the Zaminclar paper, Lahore, has been refused permission, to enter the North-West Frontier Province. The Sincl leader advises no further migration for the next two months owing to the difficulties of the journey and the [excessive heat. The Central Caliphate Committee, Bombay, inter alia resolved, in spite of some opposition, that the Hijrat movement be controlled and supervised by the Central Caliphate Committee, for the purpose of which a Hijrat Sub-Committee should be formed. Small numbers of muhajarius are beginning to return from Afghanistan with graphic tales of the hardships endured alter passing Landi Kotal. They say that a strong barrier has been erected across the Khyber Pass to prevent further unauthorized entry into Afghanistan, but&apos;the delegation of the Peshawar Caliphate Committee have beeu allowed to start for Jelalabad to confer with General. Nadir Khan. The general situation in Peshawar remains unchanged in the matter of the orderly conduct of the muhajarius, but religious excitement continues. The situation is otherwise quiet, although the tone of the vernacular Press continues unchanged. The non-co-operation movement and the Hijrat movement gain little support in Bengal, the United Provinces, Delhi, and the Punjab, although the Hijrat movement is being energetically canvassed in Delhi, and efforts are being made to despatch a large party early in September. The Hijrat movement, however, for the time being is broken by the action of Afghanistan.The appointment of Tej Bahadur Sapru, Law Member, is well received, the Leader of Allahabad describing it as a matter of special and particular satisfaction. Lord Sinha&apos;s appointment is severely criticized in the Independent as destroying the independence of the Indian Executive Council, and applying the policy of Akbar, but is generally very well received by the rest of the Press, both English and Indian.Severe floods have occurred in Midnapur causing immense damage, over 20 villages have been inundated, and the crops totally destroyed; relief measures are In progress.   The Orissa districts are also affected, but to a smaller extent.II. (27th August.) Gandhi ancP Shaukat All have toured Madras, and after the special congress contemplate a tour in Bihar and Orissa and the United Provinces. In Madras they secured a few more resignations of titles by bullying tactics, Gandhi on one occasion refusing to eat or speak with his hosts until he received four resignations. Shaukat Ali is inciting the younger enthusiasts to bring pressure to bear by means of public insult and humiliation. These tactics are expected to produce a reaction. Gandhi&apos;s speeches have contained nothing exceptionally violent, although inherently seditious and disloyal. Nothing has been done by the Govern-ment of Madras to interfere with the tour. Shaukat Ali makes little concealment of his approbation of stronger measures if GandkPs programme of non-violence fails.Bombay.- The Provincial Congress adopted non-co-operation. Detailed reports regarding resignations in Sind by reason of Pir Mahbub ShalPs arrest show 19 clerks, (? two) teachers, (? six honorary teachers), five peons, 10 honorary magistrates, 10 gun licensees, 12 students. The highest officer resigning one assistant surgeon. In Ahmedabad, Shaukat Ali in canvassing resignations met with a blank refusal. He advocates the Hijrat, followed by a Jehad conjointly with the central organization of the Hijrat, including a triumphal procession of muhajarins, but the closing of the frontiers and the reports given by muhajarins, returning in large numbers from Afghanistan, of the hardships endured on the way, the treatment received and the prohibition against participation in a profession, will largely nullify this. The Central Caliphate Committee is willing to hold a conference with Calcutta at the
time of the special congress and league. They may (? reiterate parliamentary enthusiasm). Abdullah Harun of Karachi suggested turning the Aligarh students into itinerant preachers in the likely event of the college closing through internal pressure on the authorities to refuse a Government grant-in-aid.Sind.. Pir Mahbub Shah has signed an unconditional renunciation, and no&quot; conditions have been imposed on him under section 401 C.P.C. on release. His declaration was as follows: &quot; What I am reported to have said at Tando Mohamed &quot; meeting is true. Having repented, I pray that Government will be pleased to &quot; pardon me for my offence. I promise for the future not to make, any speeches. &quot; of this kind, and to remain obedient and loyal to the Government.&quot;Bengal, There is considerable diversity of opinion as to non-co-operation, and. when the principle of resolutions was adopted there was silence as to the practice.United Provinces. The Provincial Caliphate Deputation has started touring.. There have been local attempts to induce honorary magistrates ancl title holders to-resign, but these efforts failed save in three or four cases. There is a growing bitterness in the tone of the Press, and the withdrawal of Indian troops from. Mesopotamia is urged,The United Provinces Provincial congress adopted non-co-operation, and resolved to boycott His Royal Highness The Duke of Connaught, but it is doubtful how far this-is not mere bluff.Bihar and Orissa. The Provincial Caliphate Committee has decided to push the Hijrat programme, being hopeless of non-co-operation in the province being realized,., and a Hijrat Committee has been formed. Wild rumours regarding intending muhajarins are in circulation. Actually 12 names have been registered. The Hijrat has no chance in Bihar and Orissa. It is anticipated that Mohamedans will exercise the right of Kurbani as usual.Delhi. The Caliphate workers are trying hard to persuade the people of Delhi not to pay the indemnity levied by the local administration on the city, and. when property is attached by the Government, not to buy it.North-West Frontier Province. The situation on the Hazara border is unsettled, ancl. hostile demonstrations are anticipated. This is clue to the Caliphate agitation and the Hijrat excitement in the Mansehra tahsil. A flying column has been sent from Abbottabad, and detachments of troops, as prompt action was reported neeessarv in the Mansehra tahsil, where at the instigation of the Maulvi Muhammad Ishag and. other ringleaders the agitation assumed dangerous proportions. Orders have been issued by the Oommander-in-Chief to invoke the aid of the Nawab of Arab, ancl to-arrest Ishag ancl the ringleaders if necessary, and in any case not to allow them to escape over the border. The latest report is that the situation has been improved by the presence of the troops all is quiet.2. Generally speaking, non-co-operation has been nominally adopted in principle by most of the Provincial Committees, but is not likely to be taken up in practice owing to the wide divergence from Gandhi and the Caliphate Committee, on the one hand, and the bulk of nationalist objection on the other. Consideration of incon-venient details will be avoided. We have already asked Local Governments to prosecute persons inciting to violence, or attempting to seduce troops, ancl we propose to follow this up by a letter, again urging the necessity of vigorous action in this direction. The Government of Bombay has prosecuted three or four persons as such, and we believe the Punjab Government contemplate similar action against some provincial agitators.3. The Viceroy&apos;s opening speech at the autumn session, of which a summary was;, telegraphed home by Reuter on 20th instant, was well received, and there is a more friendly feeling in the air, Patel ancl Malaviya being absent.   The Press has com- -mentecl favourably on the Viceroy&apos;s plea for peace, although the extremist organs, harp on the point that no peace is possible until the Punjab officers are punished,, ancl the Caliphate wrongs are righted.
League of Nations, and Imperial Cabinet.-On 19th. August the Secretary of State for the Colonies sent the following communication to the Governors-General of Canada and South Africa, the Officer Administering the Government of New Zealand, and the Governor of Newfoundland : The Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia has enquired by telegraph whether it would be - possible to arrange for a meeting of the Imperial Cabinet after the conclusion of the.meeting of the Assembly of the League of Nations next November, in order to discuss questions to be submitted to the Imperial Conference, or Cabinet, some time next year. After consultation with Mr. Lloyd George,.1 have-replied that I am communicating the suggestion to the other Dominion Governments,&apos; and that His Majesty&apos;s Government will be [very glad to hold meetings of the Imperial Cabinet, if they wish to send representatives to London at that time.Please let ine know by telegraph as soon as possible your Governments views.[See under Australia, p. 10.][The replies received to the above will be found under the headings of the respective Dominions.]Disposal of German Naval Material. The following message from the Secretary of State for the Colonies was telegraphed to the Governors-General of Canada, South Africa, the Officer Administering the Government of New Zealand, and the Governor of Newfoundland on 21st August: My Despatch dated 25th March, Dominions 126. It has now been decided that no credit shall be given to Germany for floating docks or other material surrendered as compensation for warships sunk, and therefore any such material which it may be possible to allot to Dominion Governments will be handed over free of charge. It is considered necessary that the material available should be used in the best interests of the whole Empire, the first claim being that of the navy, and allocation for non-naval purposes, either in the United Kingdom or in the Dominions or in the Colonies, being considered with reference to the merits of each case. It is suggested that the Dominion Governments should appoint representatives to discuss with the representa-tives of the Departments concerned here, how any material available should be allotted. I should be glad to learn whom your Ministers appoint for this purpose. Details of the material to be surrendered have not yet been settled, as only a small part of the original German offer has been found serviceable, and alternative material has been mentioned to the German authorities.Canada&apos;.League of Nations. On 25th August the Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed to the Governoi-General as follows: I now learn from the Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia that bis suggestion that the Commonwealth should be represented at Geneva was.conditional upon other Dominions being represented by. their respective Prime Ministers, in which case he would endeavour to come also. I should be glad to hear from you as soon as possible. The Prime Minister of New Zealand cannot attend this year.[See under &quot;Dominions,&quot; above.][A telegram in the same terms was sent to the Governor-General of South Africa.]In reply to the above the Governor-General announced on 28 th August that the Canadian Prime Minister would not attend at Geneva.Imperial Cabinet. Referring to the proposal put forward in the Secretary of State&apos;s telegram to the Dominions, dated 19th August, the Governor-General sent the following on 30th August: I am informed by my Prime Minister that it will be impossible for him to attend the proposed meeting this year of the Imperial Cabinet. My Government are doubtful whether the proposed constitutional Conference can with advantage be held in the New Year. They are impressed wdth the importance of the issues to be discussed, and if possible determined, at such a Conference, and they think that their consideration at the Conference should, in the Dominions at least, 20-1 C
be preceded by tbe fullest opportunity for discussions by the people concerned as represented in Parliament and also in the Press.Miscellaneous. Tbe following items of information have been reported from the Department of External Affairs at Ottawa : 1. Tbe Dominion Bureau of Statistics at Ottawa estimates that the Canadian wheat crop will this year reach a total of 202.338,000 bushels, or 71,000,000 bushels more than the 1919 crop. Oats are expected to yield 497,000,000 bushels, or 102,000,000 more than last year. The crop of flax seed is likely to amount to 12,850,000 bushels, or nearly double last year&apos;s yield.2. The immigration returns for the six months ended 30th June show 68,000 arrivals during that period, out of which 37,000 were from the United Kingdom, 25,000 from the United States, and 6,400 from other countries.AUSTRALIA.Imperial Cabinet. On 13th August the Governor-General transmitted to the Secretary of State for the Colonies the following message from the Prime Minister:  I should be glad to be informed firstly, as to the probable duration of the meeting, and secondly, whether it would be possible to arrange for a meeting of the Imperial Cabinet after the conclusion of the League of Nations meeting, in order to discuss those questions which are to be submitted some time next year to the Imperial Conference, or the Cabinet.In reply to the foregoing the Secretary of State telegraphed on 19th August as follows : -With reference to your telegram of the 13th August, please inform your Prime Minister that the League of Nations Secretariat find it difficult to estimate how long the first meeting of the Assembly is likely to last. There is a long agenda, and the Secretariat think that the meeting might continue as long as four or dive weeks, and cannot last less than a fortnight.I am communicating to the other Dominion Governments the suggestion of your Prime Minister that an Imperial Cabinet should be held in London after the Assembly, to discuss questions to be submitted to tbe Imperial Conference, or Cabinet, next year, and IBs Majesty &apos;s Government will be very glad to hold meetings of the Imperial Cabinet, if the Dominion Governments wish to send representatives to London at that time. We shall be glad in any event, however, to take the opportunity of discussing informally with your Prime Minister the matters referred to, and any others out-standing. ,Consequent on this reply the Governor-General transmitted the following message from the Prime Minister on 23rd August: I am afraid my telegram was not quite clear. What I intended to suggest was that if the Prime Ministers of other Dominions were going to Geneva, I would in that case endeavour to come also, so that we might meet in London afterwards to deal (group undecypherable) all those matters which it is suggested should bo dealt with next June. This would obviate our coming to London in the New Year. -If the other Dominions are not going to be represented at the League, of Nations by the Prime Ministers, the proposed meeting could not, of course, take place.Austrian Debts. Referring to the telegram from the Secretary of State to the Dominions on 7th August [B.E.R., xxxiv, p. 7], the Governor-General telegraphed as follows on 26th August: The Government of the Commonwealth of Australia have decided not to adopt the clearing office scheme for the adjustment of Austrian debts.German Consular Representation [B.E.R., xix, p. 10]. On 30th August the Governor-General transmitted the following repfy to the enquiry from the Colonial Office, dated 1st June: The Government of the Commonwealth of Australia does not approve of the appointment of a German Consular representative in Australia.
NEW ZEALAND.Butter [B.E.E., xxiv, p. 11]. With reference to his telegram of 9th August, the Secretary of State for the Colonies sent the following to the Officer Administering the ^Government of New Zealand on 17th August: In view of the representations of the High Commissioner, and in order to encourage the production of butter, the Food Controller now makes the following final offer for the exportable surplus of New Zealand butter, to be delivered to store in New Zealand up to 31st January 1921 : for butter graded 88 points and over, .14Z. per cwt. f.o.b. ; for butter graded below 88 points, the price to be reduced by Is. 6d. per cwt. for each point below 88.In acknowledging this message the Officer Administering the Government telegraphed on 26th August as follows i-Tile Prime Minister met the New Zealand Butter Committee . on 25th August and was informed that, the Committee would recommend the producers to accept the prices offered by His Majesty&apos;s Government, including the existing terms of payment, storage, &amp;o, provided the term of the contract is extended to cover butter manufactured up to 3ist March next, and that a free and unrestricted market in the United Kingdom is granted for New Zealand butter manufactured after that date. The producers also require that sales and contracts made or entered into with buyers in the United States of America and Canada prior to 21st August 1920 be allowed to be completed, the estimated total quantity covered by such sales and contracts being 2,000 tons. In view of the protracted nature of the negotiations, my Ministers will appreciate a reply by telegram, if possible within one week.On 27th August the Secretary of State sent the following reply : His Majesty&apos;s Government agree to extend the offer to cover the butter delivered to store in New Zealand up to 31st March next, and raise no objection to the completion of contracts made prior to 21st August with the buyers from the United States of America and danada. Subject to unforeseen contingencies, a free market is contemplated in respect of the exportable surplus after 31st March.Wool [B.E.R., xxiv, p. 11].-In continuation of the correspondence on this subject, the Officer Administering the Government transmitted the following on 21st August: &apos;At a representative conference of wool-growers held on 18th August it was decided to request the High Commissioner for New Zealand to select two suitable men in England as New Zealand representatives, to confer with the Ministry of Munitions. The Prime Minister will be glad, therefore, if the nominees of the High Commissioner for New Zealand could be accepted by the Ministry of Munitions as nominees of the Government of New Zealand. My Ministers desire me to convey the thanks of the Government of New Zealand for the opportunity afforded of appointing these representatives in connection with the disposal of Government wool.Imperial Cabinet. Referring to the telegram of 19th August from the Secretary of State [see under &quot; Dominions,&quot; p. 9], the Officer Administering the Government sent the following message on 24th August: Regarding the meeting iii November of the Imperial Cabinet, Mr. Massey fears it will not be possible for him to be absent dining the latter part of this year from New Zealand, but my Prime Minister will endeavour to make other arrangements for the representation of New Zealand at the meetings, should they be held as suggested by Mr. Hughes.SOUTH AFRICA.Lord Buxton, -The Secretary of State for the Colonies transmitted the following message to the Governor-General on 19th August:-Before your departure from South Africa, I desire on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government to express to you bur high appreciation of the services which yoti have rendered to the Empire throughout your period of office as Governor-General of the Union and His Majesty&apos;s High Commissioner for South Africa. It has been your lot to fill these high offices during the most momentous period of our history, and we recognize with admiration the
untiring energy and excellent judgment which you have brought to bear on the difficult problems with which you were continually confronted. From every quarter we have had testimony to the regard and esteem, in which you are held alike by the Governments and the people of South Africa, and we are sure that they will join with us in cordial recognition of the good work you have done for their country, ancl in, wishing you all happiness and success in the future.I beg that you will transmit a copy of this message to your Prime Minister with, an expression of my hope that he will give publicity to it.In acknowledgment of the above Lord Buxton replied. on 20th August: I thank you for your telegram of 19th August. I appreciate most highly the message from His Majesty&apos;s Government. It has given me the greatest pleasure ancl satisfaction. My period of office here has been of the utmost interest to me, and so far as I may have been successful in carrying out my duties, it has been clue to the unfailing-support and encouragement I have received throughout from the Governments and&apos; peoples of the Union of South Africa, ancl in the High -Commission Territories. I. cannot be too grateful for the confidence you and your predecessor-s have reposed in. me throughout my term of office.League of Nations. [See under &quot; Canada,&quot; p. 9.]Imperial Cabinet. On 27th August, the Governor-General telegraphed as follows ::  With reference to your telegram of 19th August [see under &quot; Dominions,&quot; p. 9], the Prime Minister will not be able to attend the meeting of the Assembly of the League of Nations, and South Africa wall be represented either by another Minister or by the. High Commissioner. The Prime Minister will be unable to attend therefore the meeting of the Imperial Cabinet suggested. He thinks the danger is, if other Prime Ministers attend now, that some of them will not attend next year the much more important meeting, and that this would be most regrettable.

</content>
</cab>
