<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/156/0 images: 338-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet. ()gSECRET.BRITISH EMPIRE REPORT.No. M.   5th January 1921.Contents.Great Britain.Relief of Unemployment.Colonies, Protectorates, &amp;c.Reuter Service.Egypt. Protest from Tauta.India.The Frontier Situation.   Mission to Kabul.   The Viceroy&apos;s Weekly Reports. The Dominions.Proposed Agreement with the Government of Germany regarding the Restitution of Property.   Proposed Meeting of the imperial Cabinet.Canada. The Overseas Settlement Committee.   Miscellaneous.Australia. Incident at Broome.   Wool.New Zealand. Wool.      -South Africa. Dissolution of the House of Assembly.   Reuter Service.   General Smuts&apos; Election Tour.
GREAT BRITAIN.Relief of Unemployment. The following paragraph is taken from the Report of the Ministry of Labour for the week ending 1st January 1921 : The situation with regard to unemployment continues to cause great uneasiness. The measures which the Government propose to take with a view to mitigating distress were outlined by the Minister in the House of Commons on the 21st December. They involve the drafting of not less than 50,000 ex-Service- men into the building trades; the con-struction of arterial roads ; the amendment of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, by making it possible, up to the 31st March 1921, for unemployed persons in insured trades to receive eight weeks&apos; benefit irrespective of the number of contribu-tions paid in respect of them ; and the establishment of a central committee to administer a fund of 3,000,000L which will be allocated to the local authorities for the inauguration of relief works. This committee will be known as the Unemploy-ment Grants Committee.       , 1COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, &amp;c.Renter Service [B.E.R., xxvii, p. 8]. On 24th December the Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Governors of Kenya and the Uganda Protectorate, the British Resident at Zanzibar, and the Governors of Nyasaland, the Straits Settle-ments and Hong Kong, that the special Renter service of 6,000 words per month was being continued for three months from 1st January on the existing conditions.EGYPT.Protest from Tanta. On 20th December the following telegram, with numerous signatures, was sent from Tanta: -We, the undersigned representatives of the merchants, engineers, doctors, notables, members of the municipal council of Tanta, Egypt, protest strongly against the protectorate that was declared on 18th December 1914, in spite of the wishes of the Egyptian people. We are heart and soul with the Egyptian delegation, and do not agree to any official pourparlers unless the declaration of the protectorate be withdrawn.   .INDIA.The Frontier Situation [B.E.R., xxxiii, p. 2], Telegraphing [No. 22-1] on 16th December the Viceroy reported the probable advance at once of the Wana column, owing to the inability of the peace party among the Waziris to induce the hostile section to. adhere to the proposed settlement.On 20th December the Viceroy telegraphed [No. 562] that operations had been resumed in consequence of the failure of the Wana Waziris to comply with our terms. In their advance to Dargai storage on 16th December the Wana column had met with some sniping, resulting in a few casualties, while a column from Fort Sandemau, intended to re-occupy the posts of Mir Ali Khel and Minghal Kot, had reached Brunj without opposition. On 23rd December the Wana column was reported as having advanced to Karab Kot on 19th December with slight opposition. The Fort Sandeman column re-occupied Mir Ali Khel without incident on 18th December.On 30th December the A^iceroy reported [No. 226] that all was quiet at Wana, small parties near Kotkai having been dispersed with some loss to the Waziris.
Mission to Kabul [B.E.R., xxxiii, p. 2]. Referring to the decision to send a mission to Kabul under Sir Henry Dobbs, the Viceroy reported on 29tli December that he had received a reply from the Amir, dated ten days earlier, in which the latter expressed great pleasure that his proposal had been agreed to. Arrangements were being made for the reception of the mission on the Frontier on 5th January. The Amir&apos;s reply concluded with the expression of an earnest desire for friendship.The Viceroy&apos;s Weekly Reports. The following reports were sent on the 23rd and 30th December : -I. (23rd December). Bombay.-It has been reported that the moderates, the extremists and the Labour party are preparing a memorial to the British Cabinet for a fresh declaration of policy, to the effect that India will obtain full responsible government within a specified period ; will ask for the repeal of repressive legislation, and for sterner Government action against military and civil officers criticized in connexion with the Punjab disturbances. Tilak institutions are being opened in nearly all the principal towns, but at the same time the students&apos; situation is improving. The establishment of such institutions is due to a desire to show respect for Tilak in a concrete form, rather than on account of the secession of students from Government-aided institutions. Some intercepted correspondence shows con-siderable divergence of opinion regarding the support to be given to Kidwai, now editor of the Islamia News, formerly the Muslim Outlook. Mohamed Ali declared that no funds should be provided, while Shaukat Ali and Abdul Bari urged the immediate cabling of funds.Madras. In continuation of my telegram of 11th December, this is a fuller report of the Buckingham mills riot in Madras. There has been a lock-out at the mills since 20th October, since when no regular employee has been at work ; coolies, however, are being taken daily to the mills to keep things in order and to unload consignments. At the end of October, complaints were made of assaults on these coolies by the regular hands, police protection was asked for, and a guard was posted at the mills. The police were withdrawn on an assurance being given by the mill hands that no violence would be attempted. The undertaking was observed throughout November, but on 2nd December a cart sent for supplies was attacked and looted. Police guards were placed on lorries carrying coolies from (? the harbour) to the mills.On 8th December one lorry was attacked and three coolies were injured. Again on the 9th, a lorry attacked the police who were attempting to arrest the assailants. On the evening of the 9th, a larger escort was detailed to escort the lorries. One lorry was attacked by large crowds with stones ; the police, armed only with lathis, succeeded in arresting two assailants. Several constables and the driver of the lorry were hit with stones, and one man was severeby wounded. On the second journey from the mills, there was a more persistent attack, aud the Deputy-Commissioner of Police ordered fire to prevent the men from being overwhelmed. Three rounds were fired, and the crowd dispersed. At night a further journey had to be made. A lorry con-taining the Commissioner, the Deputy-Commissioner and three European mill em-ployees, was stoned violently, and again three rounds of buckshot were fired. The lorry stopped to see whether any of crowd had been hit, but it would have been dangerous to disperse the force, and no casualties were found in the immediate vicinity. Sixteen persons were wounded ; 8 men, 1 woman and 6 boys who have since been admitted to hospital. One died shortly after admission, and another on the 12th. Eleven of the 16, including the boy whose death was first reported, are, or have been, mill employees. It is reported by the Madras Government that they have no doubt that the firing was absolutely necessary. The police on all these journeys .were submitted to. the most trying form of attack. Nearly all of (? them) were frequently hit by stones-some seriously but disciplinewas maintained throughout, and recourse to the use of firearms was postponed to the utmost extent compatible with safety. A warning would have been futile, as it would have been inaudible in the uproar prevailing. There have been no further disturbances since the 9th, and the harbour coolies are able to proceed to the mills and (&apos;? back) without molestation. An objectionable article appeared in the Independent newspapier, Allahabad, accusing the Commissioner of Police of the deliberate intention of taking out his men to murder labourers. We have suggested to Madras that they should instruct the Commissioner of Police either to prosecute or to sue the editor for defamation.Bengal. The elections passed off quietly, but all the results have not yet been j-received.   Gandhi&apos;s visit has had no practical effect, and the situation in the schools
and colleges is steadily improving. An attempt is being made by C. R. (? Das) to-pack the Nagpur congress with delegates opposed to the full programme of non-co-operation. The strikes in the Howrah jute mills are ended. No further developments are reported in the mining area. Mr. Fazlul (sic) Huq, presiding over the Bengal Mohamedan conference, denounced the boycott of the schools, and described the movement as immoral, unjust and selfish. It would reduce Mohamedans in India to a position of political helots.United Provinces. The centre of political attention has been the elections. In the contested constituencies 33 per cent, of the electors voted. Although the non-co-operators were active, nothing untoward occurred beyond the disturbances at Meerut and Agra reported last week. The new Council will be fairly evenly divided between legal practitioners and landholders. Gandhi and the non-co-operators were-completely defeated at the court of the Hindu University; they also failed at the-Allahabad College.Punjab. Taken as a whole, the elections passed off satisfactorily. In political centres the non-co-operators succeeded to some extent in dissuading voters from going-to the polls, but in the rural areas their influence was less felt and the smallness of the voting is attributable to lack of canvassing, to apathy and to the exigencies of agriculture. The Lahore disturbances have already been reported. Strenuous efforts, are being made by the extremists to boycott Government-aided educational institutions.. Much excitement has been created, but owing to the absence of suitable substitutes for the existing schools, the movement is likely to remain Unpopular. Khalsa College, Amritsar, and Islamia College, Lahore, have been reopened. The situation as regards the Sikhs continues to deteriorate. A Sikh dewankekl at Jullundur, lasting six days, was attended by the principal extremist leaders, and very violent speeches, advocating the full programme of non-co-operation were delivered. The prominent speaker, a Sikh agitator, for whose arrest for sedition a warrant had been issued, is now a fugitive from justice, but he has been actively assisted by the disaffected Sikhs of the neighbourhood. On the strong representation of the local Government, which regards the situation in the Sikh districts as critical, we have decided to apply the Seditious Meetings Act to the whole of the Lahore and Jullundur divisions, but have rejected the request that the local Government should be empowered to proclaim any district in the Punjab, as going beyond the necessities of the case, and dangerous, as it might provoke widespread disobedience which would be difficult to deal with. Police officers are freely5 insulted at public meetings, and threatened, and find it increasingly difficult to obtain an accurate record of speeches. With the exception of the Jullundur division, however, the feeling in the rural areas is reported to be almost untouched by the political agitation.Delhi. (? Much) disturbed for the causes reported in last week&apos;s telegram. Four leading obstructionists are being prosecuted for their part in the disgraceful incident attending the funeral of Khan Bahadur Maulvi Abdul Ahad. A. demonstration took place on .10th December, in Junta Masjid (?word omitted) Imam, due to fatwas in favour of non-co-operation announced at the ulema conference last month ; Hakim -Ajmal Khan deplored excesses by social boycott, especially the conduct at the funeral and the demonstration against the Imam, and publicly reprimanded the populace at the mosque. The trial of the four persons is followed with close, interest by the-public. The caliphate paper currency is in considerable circulation in the city and the schemes propounded for the provision of caliphate silver has backing. The proceeds of the sale of the paper is to be devoted to the minting of caliphate rupees, professing to be of slightly greater value than the standard rupee. They will be banked at the caliphate committee&apos;s offices and issued in exchange for note issues. There has been no issue of coins yet so far as is known. There is no doubt that Delhi is one of the (? centres) of sedition, and that it is more prevalent here than anywhere else. We are considering what action, if any, will lie required to counter this during the Duke&apos;s visit. A strike occurred amongst the employees of the Delhi Electric Light and Tramway Company, but the cause was mainly industrial though there was a political undercurrent. The management has been able to continue the lighting, and the Government power-house is not affected.North-West Frontier Province.--Political interest has centred in Peshawar-There has been an appreciable widening of the cleavage between Hindus and Mohamedans since the visit of Colonel Wedgwood. At a meeting convened to condole over the death of Maulana Mahmud-ul-Hassan, the caliphatists openly accused
0the Hindus of lukevvannuess ; and the Hindus displayed little or no tendency to associate with national non-co-operation.Bihar and Orissa. GandhPs tour in Bihar and Orissa appears to have had little effect, though he addressed large audiences, in Ghamparan, and at Patna promised complete swaraj- within nine months. We had had some disquieting reports of the situation in the coalfields, but the strike in the Standard Colliery Company came,to an -end on the 12th, the management promising a 20 per cent, increase. If the mining association grant the same increase in the other collieries a general strike in the coal -fields in the near future is unlikely, discontent being confined to the more highly-paid skilled labourers, who in the first instance were granted an increase of pay proportionately less than that granted to the unskilled and low paid labourer. The local Government has the situation well in hand, and has made arrangements in advance to deal with the emergency, should it arise, while avoiding any premature display of force. The Government of Bihar and Orissa and the Bengal Government are in communication -so as to ensure harmonious action. The latest information is that Gandhi is directing his emissary, a so-called swami, to leave the coalfields.General. Gandhi has denounced the social boycott, but has declared that his followers should take absolutely no part in functions during the Duke of Connaughts visit. Both parties work for the Nagpur congress C. R. Das and the Bengal leaders making a determined attempt to oust Gandhi, but the latter will not give way easily. -On the whole, however, non-co-operation does not appear to be meeting with any large measure of success except in parts of the Punjab and Delhi, though his influence over the masses is gaining strength. Colonel Wedgwood caused considerable excitement in his visit to Burma, among the students. He has followed up his previous attack on the Punjab Government, replied to by (sic) that Government, whom he charged with jerrymandering the constituencies, by another and more (? detailed, attack. The main charge relates to the increase in communal representation presumably the Sikh representation, is meant residential qualification for candidates, grouping of urban areas, segregation of the latter from the rural areas, official representation of landlords, and the extension of the franchise to headmen. We are asking the Punjab Government to reply.II. (30th December). The week has been relatively quiet, politicians waiting on the congress meeting.   The brief press report of the congress received shows that .22,000 delegates were present with many visitors.   The prominent congressmen attended.   Great enthusiasm prevailed, on the opening day, though some disorder and -confusion, and in the &quot; subjects &quot; discussion and afterwards more disorder ; e.g., in the Bengal delegates&apos; camp a scuffle occurred in which some delegates were slightly injured, the majority being opposed to a programme relating to the boycott of -educational institutes.   The general &quot; subjects &quot; Committee meeting of yesterday was engaged in an animated discussion of GandbPs resolution for the change of the congress creed, i.e., the attainment of swaraj by all legitimate and peaceful means.   A report is current that while moderate thinkers are against the change, the other party would go much further, advocating a republic in India.   The sub-committee^ recommendation, embodying important portions of Gandhi&apos;s resolution, was eventually carried by a large majority.   The outstanding point in the presidents opening speech on the 26th was that the people of India must demand the fulfilment -of the original compact, by which the rulers are bound to give full responsible government, by an instrument in writing, including a declaration of fundamental rights and a constitution similar to that of the United Kingdom and the Dominions. The British system of parliamentary responsibility, in his view the best, should be created immediately in India by letters patent or instructions to the Secretary of State ; he characterized the statement in the preamble of the Government of India Act, 1919, that it was for the British Parliament to grant responsible government, and that the British must judge the time and measure of the gradual steps proposed in this behalf, as a preposterous and extraordinary claim which Parliament could not advance. Dealing with non-co-operation, he maintained that GandhPs movement violated no constitution, whereas the British system of administration (is) based on non-co-operation of the conqueror against the conquered.   As to the items in the programme (corrupt group) he considered the renunciation of titles a small matter and, that the renunciation of honorary offices should not include the surrender of magistracies or judgeships.    As the pledges of the reforms scheme were questionable, the boycott of elections could not be regretted.   He indicated the dangers of non-co-operation : (1) the discipline imposed should not imply absolute surrender of private24-1 li
judgment; (2) the propaganda carried on should not create great animosities,. e.g., between the advocates and the opponents of non-co-operation.He was in favour of the British connexion if compatible with honour, or on equal terms. He examined the. alleged Indian grievances: (1) Repressive legislation; (2) the Punjab disturbances; (3) the Caliphate ; (4) the treatment of Indians in the colonies; ancl (5) inadequate reforms. He thought non-cooperation the proper weapon to use to secure from England a fulfilment of these demands, but objected to the boycott of educational institutions ancl to the withdrawal of lawyers from practice. Arbitration courts could not supersede the organized tribunals. He described his own programme as nation-building in earnest, to he-effected by developing and perfecting the congress organization so as to bring about, the unification of the people and the establishing ancl augmenting the national spirit by educating the masses, collecting large funds, and empowering a special committee to look after the different lines of activity. But he attached the greatest importance to (two corrupt groups) of the questions, namely, to the employment (of) means of converting not only the personnel of the Executive-Government, but also non-official exploiters to the new angle of vision.There is little to report from the provinces; the latest reports received dealing with events prior to the congress. Bengal report a good deal of intimidation of voters during the elections, mainly confined to general appeals, though some students, interfering with voters, had to be arrested ; they were released with a warning. The small polling among the Mohamedan electorate was due to the apathy and obscurity of the Mohamedan candidates as much as to non-co-operation. The situation in the schools and colleges is steadily improving, and there are indications that parents are-exerting their authority. Gandhi and Shaukat Ali&apos;s tour before the congress fell extremely flat, and it is doubtful if enough subscriptions were raised to pay for the trip. Gandhi opened the National Institution on the day of his arrival, but the effect of his speech was small; and Muhammad Ali&apos;s open avowal of an intention to-destroy the existing schools and colleges before others were ready, frightened the extremists and provoked a protest from the Amrita Bazar Patrika newspaper. Non-co-operation in practice may be said to be dead in Bengal; Gandhi is regarded with veneration, but his programme is regarded with the tolerance extended to children&apos;s games. Colonel Wedgwood interviewed the extremist leaders in Calcutta, but his advice was not palatable, and he is viewed with a certain amount of . suspicion by Bengali politicians. In the Central Provinces there has been some--what more political activity than usual during the last fortnight owing to the congress at Nagpur. In some districts paid lecturers were employed to disseminate non-co-operation, and attempts have been made to spread the movement to villages, but they have met with little success ancl the pleaders refuse to surrender their practice. There have been some manifestations of a little unrest in some schools at a few centres, but as yet there has been no real response to the call of boycott.Jinnah, a believer in non-co-operation, addressing the students of Fergusson College, Bombay, expressed the view that Gandhi s move was premature and his programme harmful and impracticable in the present state of political consciousness, ancl urged the students to take no active part in politics. Khaparde also issued a memorandum on non-co-operation showing that the avoidance of contract -with the de facto Government affords no training ground for the development of the political sense, and, while it may strengthen the power of endurance, it cannot breed energy or resourcefulness or practical wisdom.A report of the conference of the peasant delegates from the United Provinces shows the growing strength of the agrarian movement referred to in a previous weekly telegram. Resolutions condemning landlords&apos; high-handedness, pressing for the complete deletion of the ejectment laws from the Statute Book, approving the special congress non-co-operation, ancl urging (? the repeal) (? the grant) of mortgage ancl sale right in peasant holdings, were passed.The appointment of Chintamani and Sapru has been well received except in extremist circles, but the selected ministers in Madras have been criticized on the-ground that the persons selected represent only one communal section. The appoint-ment of executive councils of four members in Bombay ancl Madras has also been criticized.
THE DOMINIONS.Proposed Agreement with the Government of Germany regarding the Restitution of Property [B.E.R,, xxxiii, p. 9]: On 16th December the following telegram was sent by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Governors-General of Canada, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa, and the Governor of Newfoundland with reference to his telegram sent on 16th December : It will be observed that the proposed agreement with the Government of Germany as worded refers to &quot;British nationals&quot; without qualification as to the country of residence. The established policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government is to hold that rights conferred by existing commercial treaties on British subjects generally enure to the benefit of all British subjects, even if connected by birth or residence with a part of the Empire to which the treaty does not apply ; but this standpoint cannot be adopted in the case of new treaties if the foreign Power concerned objects and the objections cannot be overcome. In the present case it seems clear that the Government of Germany will object to the benefit of the agreement enuring to British nationals resident in a part of the British Empire wdiose Government does not confer reciprocal privileges, and in the circumstances it would be difficult to overcome such objections. But if British nationals resident in self-governing Dominions are to lie treated as outside the scope of the agreement, it is desirable, in order that the position under existing treaties may not be prejudiced, that this result should not appear to be a corollary to the exclusion of the Dominions from the scope of the agreement, but rather as the outcome of a special arrangement. It is considered that this could best be effected by an exchange of notes stating specifically that it is agreed that the stipulations of the agreement relative to British nationals cannot be invoked in respect of British nationals ordinarily resident and British companies incorporated in a part of the Empire to which the agreement does not extend.Proposed Meeting of the Imperial Cabinet [B.E.R., xxx, p. 6.] The following telegram from the Governor-General of New Zealand was received by the Secretary of State for the Colonies on 2-lth December :-My Prime Minister wishes me to state, for the information of the Imperial Prime Minister, that he regrets that, unless some-thing of serious moment should occur which would make his attendance at the meetings of the Imperial Cabinet particularly essential or desirable, it will not be possible for him to leave New Zealand next year. The fear of an industrial upheaval is his main reason for this decision.CANADA.The Overseas Settlement Committee.-On 21st December the Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed to the Governor-General as follows : His Majesty&apos;s Government are anxious to consult at an early date with the Governments of the self-governing Dominions as to the possibility of initiating on a large scale a policy of State-aided settlement within the Empire based on mutual co-operation between the Governments concerned.The objects in view would be to meet the exceptional conditions which have resulted from the war, to distribute and use the population of the Empire to the best advantage, to develop the cultivation of land and other natural resources, and to ensure that the largest possible proportion of the population likely to leave the United Kingdom in the near future should be attracted to the Dominions and be available to strengthen and build up their national life, and not be diverted to foreign countries.His Majesty&apos;s Government trust that it may be possible to arrange a special conference on this question early in the New Year and that the Canadian Government will be able to appoint a representative at this conference. February is suggested as a convenient date.Senator Millen of Australia is already over on this side to initiate a new and enlarged policy of settlement which the Commonwealth Government propose to develop, and would presumably represent Australia. He can stay here until the end of February or, if necessary, the end of March. If the Canadian Government can be represented, the Governments of New Zealand and South Africa will be also invited to appoint representatives.
Miscellaneous. The following items of information have been communicated by the Department of External Affairs : (1) The total immigration into Canada for 1920 reached 150,000, of whom 80,000 came from the United Kiugdom and 50,000 from the United States. The total immigration into Canada during the 23 years ended 1920 is 3,700,000, of whom 1,367,000 came from the United Kingdom.- (2) Sixty United States manufacturing firms during 1920 announced their intention to build or acquire branch factories in Canada.AUSTRALIA.Incident at Broome. The following telegrams were received on the&apos; dates mentioned from the Governor of Western Australia :-(1) 21st December.-In the north-west of Western Australia a serious conflict has occurred between the Japanese of Broome, 1,000 strong, and the Koepangers [a mixed seafaring population, mostly Malays], and apparently white men are also involved. It is reported in the evening newspapers that the British of Broome demand the deportation-tion of Japanese as being detrimental. The pearl industry (several groups unde-cypherable) must, aggravate the situation. The towns are being guarded by returned soldiers and practically all the wdiite residents have been sworn in as special constables. &apos; My Premier has asked the Commonwealth Prime Minister,to send a man-of-war, but so far no answer has been received. If, not presumptuous, might I suggest privately that a British man-of-war might visit Broome- quickly, as if in ordinary routine, if one is in the neighbourhood ? Unless the situation is carefully watched, it is difficult to know what may happen. Several deaths are reported. I have telegraphed to the Governor-General of Australia.(2) 22nd December.-1, am informed by my Ministers that the condition of affairs at Broome is considerably improved. Two Japanese have been killed and several wounded, several whites and other natives have been wounded.(3) Same date. Althoughmy Ministers hope that matters at Broome are quiescent, the^ evening telegrams describe the Japanese attitude as most hostile. Replying to the request of the Premier for a warship the Prime Minister declares that, as all warships are in Sydney, he is unable to send a warship, to Broome under 14 days. IP is also stated that the white population at Broome have telegraphed to the Prime Minister to send a warship.   The coloured population is largely in excess at Broome.(4) 23rd December. Recent reports are quite satisfactory.The Governor-General also telegraphed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies on the same subject, his telegram being received on 27th December :-Referring to the telegram of 21st December from the Governor of Western Australia to you on the subject of a riot amongst the aliens at Broome, my Prime Minister informs me that the Premier of Western Australia on 21st December communicated with him suggesting the despatch of a warship, but promised to furnish information later. The Prime Minister stated in his reply that all warships are at present in the vicinity of Sydney and that to reach Broome it would - take 14 days, but the Commonwealth Government is awaiting the further advice promised by the Premier. My Prime Minister states that the next advice received by him was a copy of the GovernoFs telegram of 21st December to you through my responsible Ministers when arrangements were made to send PLM.A.S. Geranium. This vessel left for Broome yesterday, where, I understand, that order has now been restored; the Japanese and Malays are not permitted to mix. One hundred Japanese having comjDleted their indentures leave Broome to-day by S.S; Minderoo; a number of Japanese have been arrested, for exciting to riot and carrying firearms, the firearms being delivered up to the authorities.Wool [B.E.R., xxxiii, p. ill], Referring to the Prime MinisteFs message transmitted by the Governor-General on Sth December, the Secretary of State for the Colonies sent the following telegram on 31st December :-The following is for your Prime Minister from the Minister of Munitions :  Immediate and anxious consideration has been given to your telegram of Sth December,   ft is recognized by His Majesty&apos;s Government that Australia is deeply
interested in the methods to be adopted for realizing the heavy carry-over wool now held by His Majesty&apos;s Government, and that naturally much anxiety is caused amongst the Commonwealth wool growers by the very great fall in wool prices, and. the difficulty in selling wool at any price. It will, however, be equally realized by the Commonwealth Government that great anxiety is caused to His Majesty&apos;s Guvern-ment, and to the British public, by the depressed condition of the textile industry in this country, which involves much unemployment. You will also know that British public opinion is strongly opposed to the formation of combines or trusts which may have injurious effects on the consumer. Your proposals, therefore, can only be accepted by His Majesty&apos;s Government on the condition that completely satisfactory assurances are given that the operations of the association will be conducted with due regard to the legitimate interests of the British consumer, and to the maintenance and, if possible, the increase of the trade relations in wool and wool prochrcts already existing between Australia and this country. I am glad to say that I am led to believe, by recent exchanges of views between this Ministry and Sir John Higgins&apos; committee, that the required assurances regarding the policy of the association will be readily forthcoming. His Majesty&apos;s Government will also have to stipulate that the cany-over wool shall be sold by the association as promptly as market conditions will permit. It will be further stipulated that at any time the agency arrangements may be revoked by His Majesty&apos;s government if the conduct of the association^ business gives ground for dissatisfaction. Subject to this being arranged, which. I believe Sir John Higgins&apos; committee will readily agree to, His Majesty&apos;s Government have decided to accept in principle your proposal to liquidate the Australian section of the imperial wool purchase account at the earliest possible date, and to hand over to the Commonwealth Government half of the surplus assets, ascertained to exist on the agreed settling day, in final settlement of the reciprocal obligations under the three wool purchase contracts. Subject to an agreement being-arrived at between Sir John Higgins, representing the wool growers, and the Minister of Munitions on certain important details, which are at present being discussed direct by telegram, His Majesty&apos;s Government are also willing to assent to the formation of the British Australian wool realization association. His Majesty&apos;s Government are willing that their half of the Australian carry-over wool shall be sold through the agency of the proposed association. I request that the acceptance of your proposals shall not at present be announced publicly. Before.this is done it is desired to arrive at a complete agreement with Sir John Higgins&apos; committee on all the essential details. It is hoped, moreover, to arrange with the consent of all parties that the New Zealand carry-over wool shall be also sold through the agency of the proposed association. I duly received your telegram of 6th December, but it is superseded by the later message.NEW ZEALAND.Wool [B.E.R., xxx, p. 9]. The Governor-General telegraphed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies on 3rd January as follows: The Government of New Zealand is going closely into the present-day wool position, having regard to its vital bearing upon the financial position of the producers, and of the Dominion as a whole. The sales lately held in New Zealand have resulted in only a relatively small proportion being realized, at prices which are extremely reasonable, even under existing conditions. A greater quantity could have been sold had not the growers generally stood firm for reasonable prices. My Government appreciates highly ihe present action of the Director of Raw Materials in holding up the market in England, thus aiding the sale of the current New Zealand clip, and greatly assisting the producers in meeting a difficult position, The Government of New Zealand sincerely trusts that, in. the possible event of any change of control, His Majesty&apos;s Government will take such steps as will ensure without doubt that the New Zealand wool it is holding will continue to be strongly held, with full regard to the necessities and the proper interests of the growers, -who even under the best conditions of realization will necessarily have to face serious difficulties for a few years to come until the existing accumulation can be cleared off. It must be borne in mind that consequent on the increased cost of labour and of all the material required to be purchased by producers, the purchasing power of a bale of wool under current conditions is probably less than at any time during the present generation, while the New Zealand producers are further handicapped by high shipping freights 24-1 C
for all produce. The Government of New Zealand, while realizing the difference-between New Zealand and Australian conditions, is watching with keen interest the negotiations now in progress between His Majesty&apos;s Government and Australia in connexion with control of sale of Australian wool.   (See also under Australia, p. 8.)Referring to his telegram of 5th November [B.E.R., xxx, p. 9], the Secretary of State on 4th. January despatched the following message from the &quot;Minister of Munitions for the Prime Minister of New Zealand :   .You will no doubt be greatly interested in the following details regarding the negotiations now going on with the Commonwealth Government relative to carry-over wool. On 7th December unanimous resolutions were communicated to Mr. Hughes by a representative conference of wool growers. He adopted these resolutions and immediately cabled to His Majesty&apos;s Government urging their acceptance. The Australian proposal is briefly as follows : (1) That wool purchase contracts should, be finally liquidated by the payment of the balance of profits to the. Australian wool growers in kind, i.e., half the stock of wool and half the surplus cash to be handed over. Roughly the Australian share is estimated at 900,000 bales of wool valued at,000,000L sterling.(2) That these Australian assets should be capitalized at about 20,000,000L sterling in the form of a British Australian wool realization association, individual sheep farmers being handed paid-up scrip in lieu of a cash dividend.(3) That the British half of the Australian wool, namely about 900,000 bales, should be sold through the agency of the proposed association who would charge a selling commission calculated to cover working costs.Bis Majesty&apos;s Government will probably accept the proposal, in spite of considerable criticisms from certain sections here, because they realize how difficult the position of wool growers now is, and they are most reluctant to refuse any facilities within their power which it is thought may improve matters. As you are aware, the position, of the New Zealand section of the wool account is radically different from that of the Australian section. The undistributed profits, on New Zealand wool are estimated at a little under 8,000,000L before writing down stocks, but it is feared that the loss on present stocks estimated to cost, approximately, 22,000,000 ., will substantially exceed the undistributed profits on wool sold since 31st March 1919. In these circumstances, as the entire proceeds of the wool in hand will, be insufficient to cover the advances made by His Majesty&apos;s Treasury unless a remarkable improvement in the wool market takes place, no further dividend is likely to be available for your wool growers. 1 feel no doubt that you will be satisfied that the Australian proposals would indirectly contribute to improve the market for New Zealand wool. His Majesty&apos;s Government feel that, in the event of the proposed association being established next month, it will be proper to hand over to that association the sale of the New Zealand wool, under proper safeguards that the sale shall be conducted to the best advantage and to the entire satisfaction of His Majesty&apos;s Government, the agency arrangements being revoked if these conditions are not fulfilled. On this important matter, I shall be glad to have your observations as early as possible. For the present please make no public statement.Your telegram of 3rd January has been received and communicated to the Minister of Munitions.SOUTH AFRICA.Dissolution of the House of Assembly.  On 31st December His Royal Highness the Governor-General telegraphed to the Secretary of State for the Colonies that the Bouse of Assembly had been dissolved by proclamation that day. Nomination day was fixed for 14th January, and polling day for 8th February.Renter Service. The telegram printed above under &quot;Colonies, &amp;c,&quot; was also sent to the Governor-General.General Smuts&apos; Election Tour. ReuteFs agent telegraphed as follows from Capetown On 29th December: The Prime MinisteFs great election tour is making a deep impression throughout the Union.    At Carolina, in the Transvaal, where General Smuts had a great
reception, he made a most eloquent appeal for a broad and statesmanlike outlook by t-he nation, as against any policy of national selfishness.Referring to the part he had played in the Leagne of Nations, he remarked that his opponents said the League would be a failure, and they said his work in South &apos; Africa would also be a failure, but he thought they were both going to be a great success, because if the League of Nations failed, then the world had failed, and human nature had failed. If they were unable to have peace, goodwill, understanding and magnanimity among the white people of South Africa, then South Africa was not only a failure, but was doomed and had no future. He also declared that if the nations of Europe failed to develop mutual respect and goodwill, European civilization was doomed.The policy of the late General Botha and himself, a policy of conciliation, was bound to succeed, and the policy they had been following in South Africa had been followed in other countries-in England itself and in America,&apos;a hotch-potch of peoples. Yet the United States would lead the world; it was going to be far and away the greatest country on earth, and in another century it would be the greatest mainstay of the white races of the world.

</content>
</cab>
