<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/85/0 images: 590-594</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I. AGRICULTURE......mil I III.....       ......1* Traotor Operations.-   Harvesting;   Wages of Men.The Board have fixed the rate of wages, etc., to he paid to tractor workers engaged in harvesting operations during the forthcoming season, aa follows:-In cases where the farmers board and lodge the men the 17/6 ordinarily allowed to the men for subsistence will be paid to the farmers.2. Inspection of $rowing Crops of Imnune Varieties of Potatoes.Over 1,800 applications have been received for the inspect: sion of Crops of potatoes of the immune varieties - representing an acreage of about 18,000.The Inspectors have in most cases begun work in their respective districts.-&apos;3. Harvest Labour.The Scottish Command have intimated that soldiers in Home Units may be released on short leave for harvest purposes, provided such leave does not Interfere with the soldiers1 duties and subject to the soldiers being employed in the district where their Unit is stationed.    Farmers are to make application direct to the Officer Commanding any Unit in their district.II. LAND SETTLEKEBT *1. Applications for Small Holdings.The total number of applications received by the Board for New Holdings and Enlargements of Holdings up to 30th June, 1919, (including applications made by service men) is 12805, an increase of 1354 since 31st March.    A table is appended showing the distri: distribution of these applications according to counties.The number of applications received from service men up to 26th July is 1874 of which 479 have been interviewed and reported on.    As indicated in a previous report, however, it Is not practic: mbl? at present to indicate the exact number of applications from soldiers and sailors aa many of the applicants indluded in the aggregate of 12805 served in the Army or Navy after tney applied to the Board.Up to 30th June, 1919 the Board have provided applicants with 628 New Holdings and 491 Enlargements of Holdings, a total of 1119, The locality of these settlements is indicated in the annexed statement.Wage s......Subsistence, 3  per week.,17/6  w   &quot;   when not boarded byfarmer.Bonus6d an acre for acreage cut over 25 and under 30 acres and 1/-per acre for acreage cut over 30 acres, in any one week.
2* Small Holding Colonies Acts, 1916-18,Negotiations for the acquirement of the Estate-of Phantassie (East Linton, Haddingtonshire) were advanced. The area is 610 acres, and present rental is  1250.3* Small landholders (Scotland) Act, 1911.Application has been made to the Land Court to fix the fair rents of five holdings to be constituted on the farm of lybster, Caithness by agreement with the Proprietors, the Office of Woods.
Returns of Numbers of Applications for New Holdings and Enlargements received up to and including 30th June, 1919.*..............- Oouhty.	New Holdings.	Enlarge-ments *	Aberdeen	109	17	126Argyll	1151	380	1531Ayr	209	1	210Banff	26	8	34Berwick	67	1	68Bute	64	48	102Caithness	409	54$	752^iaokmann&amp;n	13	1	14Dumbarton	61	3	64Dumfries	168	5	193Elgin	54	16	i          70Fife	126	3	129Porfar	77	4	81Haddington	32	MM	32Inverness	1979	1401	3380Kincardine	43	3	46Kinross	12	1	13Kirkcudbright	77	1	78Lanark	386	3	389linlithgow	45	MM	45Midlothian	189	1	190Nairn	8	1	9Orkney	165	145	308Peebles	36	2	38Perth	209	35	224Renfrew	114	1	115Hoes &amp; Oromarty	1195	703	1898Roxburgh	120	10	130Selkirk	31	*****	31Stirling	57	1	58Sutherland	438	831	1269Wigtown	164	5	169Zetland	385	604	989 II!	8,227	4,578	I1 12,805
III.     DEMOBILISATION OP AGRICULTURAL WORKERS *The figures to date are as followsNo. of men        No. of Men applied for. released?Aberdeen	1289	1170Argyll	411	354Ayr	464  ;	419Banff	312	271Berwick	274	254Bute	107	94Caithness	237	202Clackmannan	34	30Dumbarton	72	55Dumfries	473	405Elgin	267	&quot;   829Fife	419	380Forfar	512	451Haddington	266	239Inverness	524	430Kincardine	309	282Kinross	45	38Kirkcudbright	221	203Lanark	556	493Linlithgow	112	97Midlothian	327	277Nairn	60	50Orkney	415	375Peebles	93	77Perth	557	478Renfrew	215	191Ross	321	283Roxburgh	338	314Selkirk	55	50Shetland	285	255Stirling	160	131Sutherland	132	119Wigtown	275	23310.1278929
Return of the number of Applicants granted New Holdings and Enlargements of Holdings up to 30th June, 1919.New; gnlarge-Holdings * merits.Argyll	152	94Ayr	38	Banff	wmw mm	1Bute		1Caithness	70	95Dumbarton		1Dumfries	29	*n *mHaddington	29	****Inverness	139	inKincardine	2	Kirkcudbright	00	mtm *mLanark	5	*****Midlothian	16	Orkney	17	41Peebles	7	Mm *mPerth	26	8Renfrew	6	-Ross	14	28Roxburgh	17	&quot;pi *mSolkirk	12	*****Stirling	1	 Sutherland	17	56Wigtown	21	*****Shetland	2	55628491

</content>
</cab>
