<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/85/0 images: 641-644</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCULiPilT 13 TUB PROPERTY OF HIS Bid TANS 10&apos;, MA JSSTYr S GOVERMBN.TSEC RET.W AS    0&apos;A 3 X..M E T.&apos;THE FUTURE Off THE MIKE.-Memorandum ly^the Sec re tr.ry of Sta Ve^foj^Indi a.I have not been able to attend, the Cabinet meetings at which this guostion has beou discussed, as the Joint Committee on the Government of India Bill unfortunately precludes ray attendance- for the moment at Cabinet meetings.    But I am bound to state in a few words the anxiety which I feel at the trend of the discussion which is apparently adverse to the Majority Report of the 3anisey Commission.The plan of dealing with a threatened strike byinitiating an enquiry into the claims on which the unrestis based is not uncommon;   it usually commands the approvalof thinking- men;   and on more than one occasion it has provedsuccessful.   The proper method is to my mind to say frankly:&quot;I cannot give you what you ask at once, but I can promise that your claims shall be considered, Dim after consideration shall be in a position to say how far your grievances are(justified and how far the remedy for which you ask comments it.-self to me.&quot;It was in pursuit of this policy that the Sankey Commission was appointed and was accepted.      The Corn-mission was then constituted to contain six men who might be expected to take the view of-the.miners, six who might not, who wore employers, and an impartial chairman.   It is a form of composition of a body wrlnh is very familiar in India.     There, an equal-number -of Indians and officials often-deliberate to act on  one body and are presided over by a chairman specially chosen to hold the balance.     In the result -n this case, allthe six miners held together and succeeded in carrying *with/
with them the impartial chairman.     Am I right in thinking that it is now contemplated that this chairman shall he thrown ovor and that therefore the Majority Report of the Commission la to he rejected?     If so, the consequences are likely to he very serious, for never again in the case of industrial trouble will a Commission bo acceptable,     Wo are breaking the instrument we have- so often used.This seems to me a grave consequence, far exceeding in importance careful calculations as to political results.     It is really a question of the good faith of government machinery as it has been&apos;understood. When the Government appointed the Commission and constituted its membership, it seems to me that there was an implied undertaking that the policy of the Government would embody the results of the Commission&apos;s deliberations, that is to say, the report of the majority of&apos; the Commission.So far as I am able to judge the situation, the whole future prosperity of our country depends on coal output, and coal output depends on the goodwill of the men.It seems to me that the men are absolutely determined that they will not mine any longer for private profit, and that no share in the management will compensate then for any solution which puts profits into private pockets.     They have now found themselves in a. majority on the Commission and have put forward the only solution of the question which will give them what they ask for, i.e. working for public profit. If that solution is now rejected, they will not onlybe
India. Of flee., So&quot;?/,,2md August, 1919abe left with the ill-Trill caused by the disappointment of their hopes and the rejection of their plans, but their feeling will be accentuated and embittered by a belief that thoy have been led into aocepting the enquiry device only to find at the end that it carries thera no further and that all the investigations1 are to them of no avail, because the government, having invited them to co-operate in the enquiry * rejects the resui&amp;of the Investigation.If I am noi mistaken in believing that the trend of discussion is towards the acceptance of the ttacMiam Report, then I find myself still more perplexed.5 For the Government, after discarding the proposals of the majority, is apparently to accept the proposals of the smallest minority, a minority of one.  And apart from this question of numbers, these proposals seem to me to be unlikely to achieve assent, because while on the one hand they maintain private profit, they limit it in such a way that the stimulus usually put forward as the advan-tage of private enterprise disappears.The triple result is that,the men do not get what they want as the guarantee of their good-will, the mining companies lose perhaps the most valuable stimulus to their effort, and procedure by enquiry is very heavily discounted.   Is not this an alarming picture ?, (Intd)   E.S.M.
WAR CABira,Tli-o i,tt ached paper (G.i% 7870 )   ia circulated for discussion at the Meeting to be held at 10 DOv-nirig St. on Tuesday, 5th August 1919 at 11.30 a.w2 Whitehall Gardens S.r?., August 2nd 1919.

</content>
</cab>
