<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/85/0 images: 668-669</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majestys GovernmentmmWAR CABINET.USE OP GOVERNMENT MOTOR OARS.12Z761MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.The following are my proposals in regard to motor cars used by Government 57 OfficesH.Q.1. A clear distinction, must be drawn between (a.) Bulk provisions of motor transport vehicles and spare parts. (6.) Running of cars and vehicles, e.g., provision of personnel, administration, repairs, &amp;c.As regards (a), this should be centralized in the Ministry of Supply, whose functions are bulk provision.As regards (b), centralization is impracticable for the reasons given below.2. Motor transport is as&apos;much,a part of the Army proper all over the world as was the horse transport which it has largely replaced. This becomes clear if we contemplate an Army taking the field. The personnel must be soldiers, there must be arrangements for maintenance, including the necessary repair shops, and there necessarily has to be a section in the War Office concerned with administration generally. The same is true of the Admiralty and the Air Force.3. I therefore contemplate as a permanency three organizations, each with a motor transport service, the Navy, the Army and the Air Force.Possibly at a later date the Army and the Air Force organization may be combined, and I am keeping this in view.   I do not think it is possible at present.Although these, arrangements may seem open to objection, I hope the Cabinet will not&apos; brush them aside without acquainting themselves with some of the practical difficulties which would otherwise arise and which I think are insurmountable.4. As regards Government departments other than the above Service departments, the War Office could arrange for the provision of cars and civilian drivers, and I think that this would be the most economical arrangement. The administration would be undertaken by the section of the War Office which must exist as part of the Army Organization.The conditions would be as follows : (a.) From a date to be fixed, say 1st October, all such motor cars and civilian drivers would be supplied by the War Office from a pool, the size of which would be fixed by the Treasury after receiving the estimated requirements of the departments.No vehicle would be drawn from this pool, except on a voucher on the same lines as a railway warrant.   The cost of the services rendered by the pool would be charged against the departments concerned.   In the case of . ( the India Office, where the cost is chargeable to Indian Revenue, thenecessary cash settlement would be made in the usual manner.(6.) A strict definition of official duties for which such vouchers are applicable would be drawn up, and this would exclude conveyance from home to office or vice versa, except in the case of a special emergency. It would further exclude the use of the vehicle by any person not connected with, the public business in hand.5. A system is proposed by the Quartermaster-General whereby General Officers and others in Commands who require a motor car for their public duties shall be entitled to use it, when not required for such duties, for private purposes on payment pf 5/. a month. This does not fully represent the value of the amenity, but I doubt whether, under present conditions of prices, taxation and pay, General Officers would be able to afford more, and it is desirable in the public interest that a clear rule should be established which can, in fact, be kept without leading to abuse.
6. I would apply a similar principle in dealing with cars of Ministers. The cars would be provided by the War Office, but with civilian drivers under the arrangements made for the provision of the pool.In this case, however, there is no reason for not charging the whole value of the private services rendered by the cars. I would, therefore, allow individual cars for personal use to be drawn from the pool on the basis of two-thirds of the cost being   borne by the State and debited to the Department concerned in respect of public duties, and one-third by the Minister in respect of private work. This would work out at about 2007. to 250?. a year, according to the size of the car. In addition, a certain extra payment would have to be made to the driver in consideration of private work. I believe Parliament would view such a treatment of the question as reasonable and proper, particularly in view of the urgent calls now made on Ministers, and the fact that if provision is made by the &quot;War Office as I propose, no new department would D8 necessary, and the cost confined to the lowest limits.iih August, 1919.WINSTON S. CHUECHILL.

</content>
</cab>
