<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/46/5 images: 46-49</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of....................MOST SECRET. Copy No. 5illW.M. (hh) 53RD CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE confidential Annex;(20th April, 192+1+ - 6.2+5 p.m.)FINLAND(previous references.M. (2+h) 2+ythConclusions,Minute 2)THE PERMANENT UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE FORFOREIGN AFFAIRS read to the War Cabinet the text,which he had just received from the Soviet Ambassador,of the Finnish reply to the Russian peace terms andof the reply which the Soviet Government proposed toreturn.     The Finnish reply was to the effect that,while they were very anxious to be on friendly terms with their great neighbour, the proposals which hadbeen put to them embodied certain things which weretechnically not possible of accomplishment, thatthey were hardly consistent with their existence as astate, and imposed a burden exceeding the extent oftheir powers.     They were therefore unable to accept them.The reply proposed by the Soviet government took note of the rejection of the terms of armisticeput.forward as a basis for a settlement, and of thefact that the Finnish Government had discontinuedthe negotiations for an armistice.     Before despatchingthis reply the Soviet Government enquired whether his Majesty&apos;s Government had any remarks concerning it,THE PRIME MINISTER felt that the Russianterms were not unreasonable, except as regards the indemnity proposals which were very severe.     It was for consideration whether this point might not betouched on in our reply.      Our sympathy for the Finnswas bound to be conditioned by the fact that, after receiving many benefits from the Allies,  they had deliberately decided to take sides with Hitler.It,was pointed out, on the other hand, thatthe Finnish reply, so far as could be judged from thetranslation, had not narrowed the issue down to thatof.the indemnity, but appeared to have rejected as awhole the terms put forward by the Soviet Government.After discussion THE PRIME MINISTER suggestedthat the reply should be that we much regretted thatno solution had been reached and were grateful to theSoviet Government for keeping us informed.    Had the breakdown been on the narrow issue,   of the indemnityproposals,   we might have submitted some observations to theSoviet Government, but as the Finnish reply appearedto reject the terms put forward generally, we had noobservations to make.The War Cabinet -Approved the terms of the reply suggestedby the Prime Minister at &apos;X&apos;.Offices of the War Cabinet.S.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
