<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/151/0 images: 68-73</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS government cp( 70) 33 COPY NO     029 July 1970CABINETTHE &quot;SECOND FORCEr AIRLINEMemorandum by the President of the Board of trade. We are committed to encouraging the creation of a *second force1independent airline.    The only way in which such an airline can be created in the foreseeable future is through the purchase of British United Airways(BUA) by Caledonian.    For this purpose it will be necessary to secure sometransfer of routes from the two Air Corporations.2.        Caldeonian are confident that they can finance the purchase of BUA(which involves a total commitment of about  32 million) provided they cansatisfy their existing and potential shareholders that routes will betransferred to the new airline on a scale sufficient to yield an additionalprofit before tax of about  800, 000 in 1971, or a rather higher figure if theroutes are not transferred until 1972 or later.    This would mean the transferof routes yielding a revenue of about  5- 6 million in 1971, compared with british Overseas Airways Corporation^ (BOACts) total current revenue of 200 million.    boac&apos;s profits are likely to be affected to a greater extentproportionately as total profitability looks like declining over the next fewyears.3,        The Chairmen of the Air Corporations have made it clear that theirBoards will not agree voluntarily to give up routes.    It follows that if theGovernment wants to go ahead it will have to use its statutory powers.Once these-powers are invoked there is no reason to believe the Corporationswill not co-operate,-4.        The Lav/ Officers have confirmed that I have powers the exercise ofwhich would result in a transfer of routes from BOAC (and perhaps, to a lesser extent, from British European Airways) to Caledonian,    There is noprecedent for the use of these powers for this purpose and we may be criticised for bypassing the ordinary Air Transport Licensing Boardlicensing machinery.    The ordinary control over Nationalised Industryinvestment will enable me to stop BOAC acquiring BUA.1
5.        The situation has been deteriorating rapidly recently in two respectsfollowing leaks to the Press.    3UA has been losing traffic since people are unwilling to book on an airline which might cease operations soon.    the morale of BUA employees is poor and there are signs that it may worsenrapidly.    Secondly, in pursuit of a claim for complete parity of pay andconditions with the Air Corporations, the unions have threatened to go on strike from 3 August.6.        After an exceptionally profitable year in 1969 BUA*s profits havesharply declined and these could become substantial losses if current uniondemands for parity of pay and conditions with BOAC were conceded.    In this situation Sir Nicholas Cayzer might possibly decide to put BUA into liquidation or to concede complete parity in order to avoid a strike.    IfBUA were to be liquidated there would be no certainty that Caledonianwould be able to pick up the routes that would enable them to operate as aTsecond forcet airline, since all airlines would be able to bid and theordinary long drawn out licensing procedures would have to be used.Moreover, in these circumstances, it would be much more difficult tojustify the transfer of some BOAC routes to Caledonian,    In the resultingconfusion and uncertainty CaledonianTs present financial backers would almost certainly lose Interest,7,        If on the other hand BUA continued operations but conceded completeparity the new airline resulting from a Caledonian purchase of BUA wouldhave greater difficulty in attaining the profitability It needs to attractcontinuing financial support.    This concession might make the purchase ofBUA impossible for any airline except BOAC.    Caledonian would be pieparedto pay comparable rates for comparable work, which in effect means parityin basic rates but intend to negotiate with the unions to secure comparableproductivity agreements (and possibly some staging of their increasedcommitments).    This is a different matter from proceeding to Immediateparity in pay Irrespective of productivity.8.        In the face of these risks I felt that I ought to make an immediatestatement on the lines of the attached draft.    When the ministerial committee on Economic Policy considered this statement on 27 July therewas general agreement that the Government should pursue vigorously its policy of fostering the ^second forcet in spite of strong opposition from thetrade unions and the Air Corporations,   It was, however, essential to getboth the timing and the context of the statement right,    The statement, ifissued too early, might prejudice the chances of securing an early agreement to end the dock strike.    It would also be a great pity If the1second force&apos; airline came to be publicly suspect as one run on cheaplabour, or if its launcMng coincided with strikes in BUA and in the air corporations.    E at all possible the BUA pay claim should be publicly seen to be a quite different issue from the *second force1.2
9,        As matters are developing, however, I consider that we should notdelay our statement any longer, because of the risk that precipitate action by Sir Nicholas Cayzer or by the BUA employees might jeopardise the wholeconcept of a tsecond force1 airline,    I understand that Caledonian areprepared to move quickly to comparable pay for comparable work and thereis evidence to suggest that, faced with a Government decision, the unions would negotiate with Caledonian as the prospective employer and would notforce an immediate strike on 3 August,    There have been suggestions thatMr Clive Jenkins might call out Air Corporation staff to prevent a transferof routes,    I do not think we can concede to such pressures,10,       It is also for consideration whether I should be authorised to say thatthe Government will not, in any event, be prepared to approve a purchaseof BUA by BOAC.    Sir Nicholas Cayzer has continued to hope that, in thelast analysis, the Government would approve such a purchase and for thisreason he has not been as forthcoming as he might have been in his dealings with Caledonian,   A statement on these lines would force both him and theunions to be more realistic in their dealings with Caledonian,    On the otherhand, the hope of an ultimate sale to BOAC may be one of the factors whichwill deter him from going into liquidation,    I think we may have to make such a statement, but I would prefer to hold it until it is shown to be essential.CONCLUSION11,        I therefore seek the agreement of my colleagues to the Issue of theattached statement without more delay.    It would have the effect of enablingCaledonian at once to start negotiation with BUA and to start discussing withthe unions as the prospective *second force1 airline the standards of pay and productivity which should apply,    I should like further to have authority totell Sir Nicholas Cayzer, should this prove necessary, that the government do not intend to permit BOAC to purchase BUA if the deal with Caledonianfalls through.    We must be clear,, however, that this could increase thepossibility that BUA might be put into liquidation, with the consequencesoutlined above.    We may have to take this risk.M A C NBoard of Trade SW128 July 19703
ANNEXCIVIL AVIATIONA SECOND FORCE INDEPENDENT AIRLINEThe Government wish the private sector of the civil aviationindustry to be given the opportunity to form by amalgamationa &quot;second force&quot; airline that would fill the role of secondflag carrier on major international routes as well as sus-taining extensive charter services.    Such an airline,combining the resources and skills of British United andCaledonian, could provide a powerful additional source ofairline management and innovation;    its existence would permit the licensing of a second British carrier on thoseinternational routes such as the North Atlantic where thisshould increase the traffic carried by British airlines;and it could serve those domestic routes where it was desirable to offer the public a choice of airlines.2.     The Government accept that such a new airline, if it canmeasure up to its task, should be given preference over otheroperators in the licensing of new scheduled routes that would contribute to a viable route network, in the licensing of asecond carrier on existing scheduled routes or in any sector of the market (such as long-haul inclusive tour charters)where there may for a time be room for only a limited numberof operators.   Where the new airline is licensed to serve a domestic route jointly with another operator, they accept theneed progressively to relax any restrictions on the frequency of services.   They also accept that some exceptional transferof routes from the public sector - and possibly some rational-isation, including an exchange of routes t- will be necessaryin the initial stages, though not as a continuing process, ifthe new airline is to have a sufficient basis at the outset.3.     BOAC1s total revenue is about  200m.    Forecasts of inter-continental traffic point to an expansion of about 14% a yearup to 1975.   Against the background of such growth a modesttransfer of routes from BOAC to the new airline, representingsomething of the order of l\% or 3% of their current annualrevenue, would have small impact on boac&apos;s continuing expansion.Both revenue and employment will continue to increase.   Thereturn on the public investment need not be unduly impairedso long as the routes transferred from either Corporation didnot significantly affect the overall efficiency of their opera-tions.4.     The Air Corporations must remain our principal flagcarriers bearing as in the past the main weight of thiscountry1s civil aviation effort.   The routes to be transferredmust therefore be so chosen as to combine with the overallnational interest the maximum benefit to the viability of thenew airline with the least impact on the Air Corporations.1
5.     The civil aviation industry has been subject to muchuncertainty since 1967 and it is desirable that matters should be brought to a conclusion without further delay.The Government are considering legislation based on therecommendations of the Edwards Committee for changes inthe regulatory machinery;    they accept, in principle, theestablishment of a licensing authority whose decisions willbe governed by a formal statement of policy which will reflect,among other things, the considerations set out in this white paper.   However, the Government consider it important that thenew airline should be formed as quickly as possible and shouldhave new routes to serve by the summer of 1971.   They would prefer the arrangements for the transfer of routes to be made through normal licensing procedures after discussion with the airlines concerned.    They accept, however, that the air corporations will not willingly give up even a small sector of their routes.    If necessary, therefore, pending the new legislation, they will be prepared to use their powers underSection 3(5) of the Air Corporations Act 1967 and underSection 1(3) of the Civil Aviation (Licensing) Act 1960,to ensure that the intended outcome is not unduly delayed.6.     It is in thebest interests of the industry and of thecountry that a stable and viable solution should be foundquickly.    In particular it is in the interests of those whowork in BUA and in Caledonian that the new flag carrier shouldhave the strength and opportunities that will enable it to movequickly towards terms and conditions of employment comparable with those offered by the Air Corporations for comparable work.)&quot;l2


</content>
</cab>
