<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/166/14 images: 173-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(72) 139 COPY NO      685 December 1972CABINETDESIGNATION OF BRITISH MEMBERS OF THE EUROPEANPARLIAMENTMemorandum by the Lord President of the council. The Treaty of Accession gives the United Kingdom an entitlementof 36 seats in the European Parliament,,    Article 138,1 of the Treaty of rome provides that &quot;the Assembly shall consist of delegates who shallbe designated by the respective Parliaments from among their members in accordance with the procedure laid down by each member State&quot;,-2. If the Opposition agree to send delegates to the european parliament, the distribution of places would, on a basis of Partymembership in the Commons, be 18 Conservative, 17 Labour andone Liberal.    The Conservatives could be composed of 12 membersof the House of Commons and six peers,3. The Parliamentary Labour Party are likely to decide on 13 Decemberwhether or not to send delegates. They will probably decide not to do so,and the Government will need to take a view on whether or not their placesshould be filled.4, From the point of view of our position in Europe there is something to be said for not leaving the places totally unfilled.    We could, if we wished, either designate Labour Members and peers who were willingto accept nomination or we could fill up the 36 places with extraConservatives, Liberals and cross-bench peers.    On the otherhand it would be very invidious from the internal political pointof view to interfere substantially in the Labour Party&apos;s internal affairs;  and if their seats in the European Parliament were visiblyempty the Labour Party might be encouraged to adopt a co-operativeattitude towards Europe earlier than they might otherwise have done,5, At the margins of the problem the Liberal Party have asked ifthey could have three places which they would fill with two Liberal peers and one Liberal member of the House of Commons.    In view of theirconsistently co-operative attitude over Europe there is something tobe said for allowing them, to have two places on the understanding thatthey might well have to lose the extra place as soon as the Labour Party
agreed to send delegates.    The Lord Privy Seal has said that he would very much like a good cross-bench peer to be designated to fill one of theempty places.    My colleagues will wish to consider this suggestion.6. We also need to consider how the designation of the British membersof the European Parliament should be effected.    I propose that this shouldbe done by a Resolution of each House of Parliament.    Such Resolutions,which would be debatable, would have to be adopted before the christmas recess.CONCLUSIONS7. I invite my colleagues -a. To agree that the Conservative representation in theEuropean Parliament should be 12 members of the House ofCommons and six peers.b. To agree that, if the Labour Party decline to send delegates to the European Parliament, the Government should not (subject toc. and d. below) seek to fill their places.c. To agree that, as long as the Labour seats are unfilled, asecond place should be made available to the Liberals,d. To consider the desirability of appointing a good cross-benchpeer for the period that the Labour seats are unfilled.J privy Council office December 1972


</content>
</cab>
