<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/36/30 images: 332-335</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   April 1948.SECRET./Copy No.W.P. (43) 180.April 28. 1943.WAR CABINET.INDIA.JUDGMENT OF THE FEDERAL COURT OF INDIA INVALIDATINGMY colleagues may wish to be informed in greater detail of the recent rulingby the Federal Court invalidating Defence of India Rule 26. under whichthe Congress leaders and the majority of those arrested during the disturbancesof last Summer have been detained.The Federal Court ruling was given on an appeal which the Bombay HighCourt permitted to be made to the Federal Court on a contention that the Defenceof India Act, 1939. was ultra vires by reason of the absence of an entry in the seventh Schedtde to the Government of India Act covering &quot; Defence of India/7The Federal Court rejected this contention, but proceeded to decide the appealon another point raised during the hearing, namely, the validity of Rule 26 ofthe Defence of India Rules made under the Defence of India Act. The groundon which the Court appears to have held Rule 26 invalid is thus briefly stated ina telegram from the Viceroy : &quot; The Rule provides for detention with a view tothe prevention of prejudicial action, while Clause (x) covers only reasonablesuspicion that a person has acted, is acting, or is about to act prejudicially.&quot; Thepoint appears to be that the Rule as framed enables a Provincial Government to detain a person without any real suspicion that he was about to act prejudiciallybut merely to prevent him from doing so and thus exceeded the terms of Section 2(2) (x) of the Act to which it was held to be related. The Court also made otherobservations on the drafting and application of the Rule. A copy of the relevantpassages of the Act and of Rule 26 is annexed.On the necessarily brief information so far available, it seems to me thatthe Bombay High Court erred badly in certifying that the case before it involvedany substantial question of law as to the interpretation of the Government ofIndia Act within the meaning of Section 205 (1) of the Government of India Act,which requires such a certificate to enable an appeal to be carried to the FederalCourt. Further, the judgment of the Federal Court seems to me to be open to question in its apparent failure to give effect to the dominant words ofSection 2 (2) of the Defence of India Act &quot; without prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred by sub-section (1) &quot;&apos; but although on the face of it thiswould appear to offer good ground for an appeal to the Privy Council it is obviously essential for political reasons and in the interests of public security toset immediately at rest any doubts as to the validity of the orders under whichthe Congress leaders and some thousands of their followers have been and stillare detained.I have, therefore, given my approval to the Viceroy&apos;s proposal that anordinance should immediately be issued amending Section 2 (2) (x) of theDefence of India Act so as to bring it into full conformity with Rule 26 of theDefence of India Rules, and alfeo validating with retrospective effect all orderspreviously made under the Defence of India Rule 26.RULE 26 OF THE DEFENCE OF INDIA RULES.Ml-IMORANDUM  BY THE SECRETARY OF  staff.  FOR  INDIA.L. S. A.India Office,April 28, 1943.[25365]
APPENDIX.Extracts from the Defence of India Act. 1939.Powers to 2. (1) The Central Government may, by notification in themake rules. official Gazette, make such rules as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for securing the defence of British India, the public safety, the maintenance of public order or the efficient prosecution of war. or for maintaining supplies and services essential to the life of the community.(2) Without prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred by sub-section (1), the rules may provide for. or may empower any authority to make orders providing for. all or any of the following matters, namely : ^ff ^ 4^ &quot;fe &quot;St(x) the apprehension and detention in custody of any personreasonably suspected of being of hostile origin or of having acted, acting or being about to act, in a mannerprejudicial to the public safety or interest or to thedefence of British India, the prohibition of such person from entering or residing or remaining in any area, andthe compelling of such person to reside and remain inany area, or to do. or abstain from doing, anything.Restriction of movements ofsuspectedpersons,restrictionorders tinddetentionorders.Extract from Defence of India Rules.26. .(1) The Central Government or the Provincial Govern-ment, if it is satisfied with respect to any particular person thatwith a view to preventing him from acting in any mannerprejudicial to the defence of British India, the public safety, themaintenance of public order, His Majesty&apos;s relations with foreign powers or Indian States, the maintenance of peaceful conditions intribal areas, or the efficient prosecution of the war it is necessaryso to do. may make an order /g\    * * * * *(b) directing that he be detained.*    -       * * * *



</content>
</cab>
