<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/97/0 images: 251-290</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9 A 9DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)^   R ST. COPY NO.C A B I N E T_7 (59)   &quot;Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, 15th FEBRUARY, 1939,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS.2.   PALESTINE   -    (if required)(Reference Cabinet 6 (39) Conclusion 8)3.    CONGRESS AND THE INDIAN STATES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.CcP. 44 (39) - circulated herewith.4&apos;    CIVIL DEFENCE SERVICES      COMPENSATION FOR PEACE TIME.    INJURIES 0(Reference Cabinet 4 (39) Conclusion 2)Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.CP/. 42 (39) - circulated herewith.5.    CONCLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.3rd Conclusions (39) of Committee of Home Affairs -to be circulated.(a) -Patents, and. Designs (Limits of Time) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 34 (38) Conclusion 4)Memorandum by the president of the Board ofTrade, covering draft Bill.H.A. 7 (39) - already circulated.(b) Local Government Superannuation Bill.(Reference Cabinet 2 (39) Conclusion 11)Memorandum by the Minister of Health,covering draft Bill.H.A. 8 (39) - circulated herewith.
6c    PRIVATE MEMBERS\ BILLS.For Friday, 24 th Februaryf .19.59*(a) Shops Bill.    Second Readingo    (Mr0 Leslie (La.))(Reference Cabinet 16 (37) Conclusion 9)(b) Highways Protection Billn    Second Readings(Mr. Henry Strauss -(c))(Signed)     E.E, bridges secretary to the Cabinet.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.10th February, 1939*
P. R E T.COPY NO.CABINET 7(59)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,15th FEBRUARY, 1939, at 11.0 a0m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Prime Minister. (in the Chair).ie Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,G.C.V.O. , O.B.E., K.C., M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.ie Right Hon.Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor.te Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.Cx.,&amp;.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs.le Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E., K.G.,M.P., Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.tie Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.le Right Hon.W.S. Morrison, M.C., K.C, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.ie Right Hon.L. Hore-Belisha, M.P. ,Secretary of State for War.te Right H0n.John Colville, M.P., Secretaryof State for Scotland.te Right Hon.The Earl De La Warr, Presidentof the Board of Education.te Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.The Viscount Runciman,Lord President of the Council,The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., CCS.I.,G.B.E., CM.G., M.P. , Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon,  -Sir John Anderson, G.CB. ,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., M,P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland, CC.SXG.C.I.E., Secretary of Statefor India and B\irma.Admiral   of the Fleet the right on. Lord Chatfield, G.CB.,CM. , K.C.M.G., C.V.O., Ministerfor Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G. , D.S.O.,M.C, First &quot;Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right H0n.B.L. Burgin, M.P.,Transport.The Eight Hon.Sir Reginald Dorman-Smith, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.Minister of-p Edward E, Bridges, K.CB. , M.C.,............Secretary.
CABINET      7(59).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held onWednesday, the 15th FEBRUARY, 1959, at 11.0 a.m.ionNo. Subject. Page.1. ITALY. 1.2. .    HOLLAND:Possible German Invasion. 2.3. GERMANY. 3.4. THE FAR EAST:    Japan and China;Occupation of Hainan. 4.5. CHINA:Financial Assistance to. 5.6. SPAIN:Recognition of General Franco&apos;s Government.      6.7. ANTI-COMINTERN PACT. 15.8. THE GENERAL ACT. 16.9. PALESTINE. 17.10. INDIA:Congress in the Indian States. 21.11. CIVIL DEFENCE SERVICES :Compensation for peace-time Injuries. 25.12. THE PATENTS AND DESIGNS (LIMITS OF TIME) BILL.    51.13. THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT SUPERANNUATION BILL. 52.14. THE SHOPS BILL. 33.15. THE HIGHWAYS PROTECTION BILL. 34.
9 C91. THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said he understood that Signer Mussolini was expected to make an important speech on Sundaynext.     He thought that it was for consideration whether, if some Minister was engaged to speakbefore Sunday night, he might include in his speech some reference to the declaration madeby the Prime Minister in the House of commons on the 6th February as to our relations with france.     For example, it might be said thatthis declaration was of a formal and gravecharacter and had behind it the approval of thewho 1 e country.The Cabinet agreed:That the Chancellor of the Exchequerwho was due to make a.speech onThursday, 16th February, should consult with the Prime Minister andthe Foreign Secretary in regard tothis suggestion.(previous reference:Cabinet 6(39), Con-clusion 5:.)
9 ^a vj&apos; *jpossibleGermaninvasion.(previous reference:Cabinet 6(39), Con-clusion 6).said that he had seen the Dutch Foreign minister on the previous day.     A record of the conversationwould be circulated in due course.     Briefly,Dr. Patijn did not attach great importance tothe rumour of a possible German invasion of Holland,and had made it clear that if Holland was invadedthe Dutch would resist.The Foreign Secretary added that he hadnot said very much to Dr. Patijn as to our position,except to point out that we ?/ere almost as nearlyinterested as the Dutch themselves in themaintenance of the integrity of Holland.     Thisremark had fitted in rather well with certainideas cf Dr. Patijn&apos;s as to Pacts of Non-Aggression on the Belgian model with Holland&apos;s.neighbours.      It appeared that Dr. Patijn was mainly anxious about the position of the DutohEast Indies and the recent Japanese occupation ofHainan (See Conclusion 4 below).The Cabinet took note ofthe above.
3.      THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that a report had been received from our military Attache in Berlin, dated 24th January,reporting certain signs of military activity inSouth Germany.,     There was, however, nothing whichdefinitely portended military activity on a large scale, or even partial mobilisation, in February.A Paper from the War Office Intelligence Section,dated 8th February, reported that, beyond general military measures aiming at placing Germany in as.high a degree of readiness for war as was possible without mobilisation, there were no measures pointingto military action West, East or South.     The military attache at Berlin, after a visit to Vienna inFebruary, had no confirmation of any large-scalemilitary activities in that areaoContinuing, the Foreign Secretary invitedattention to General Temperley&apos;s article in the &quot;Daily Telegraph&quot; of the 13th February, the general effect ofwhich was to indicate some reduction in the temperature,.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE addedthat he had now definitely been Invited to Berlin onthe 17th March in connection with the discussions between United Kingdom and German industrialists.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs then read out extracts from a Jfote by Mr. Kirkpatrick,in regard to Herr Hitler&apos;s Reichstag speech on the30th January.     Evidence had accrued that the reference in Herr Hitler&apos;s speech to a long peacehad been a last minute interpolation, and that the portion about Colonies and Great Britain had been verymuch toned down.     There were also indications that persons in inner Nazi circles recognised that thefeeling of the German people was now very strongly against war.
The Cabinet took note of this statement.apan and China,Occupation ofainan,(previous reference:Cabinet 57(38), Con-clusion 1.)said that his colleagues would have seen the reportof the Japanese landing on Hainan Island,     The french had made representations to the Japanese Government,and we had supported their representations^     TheJapanese Government had replied that the occupationwould not last longer than was dictated by military needs, and that Japan had no territorial designs onthe Island,     It did not appear that there was anyfurther action which we could take in the matter.
said that he was still awaiting news from Washingtonas to the parallel action which the United StatesGovernment might take in the event of our deciding to proceed with the Chinese Currency StabilisationLoan proposals*     In the meantime, H.M* ambassador in China continued to confer with General Chiang-Kai-shek, and the various methods of dealing withthe proposal were under examination departmentallyby the Treasury and Foreign Office*In discussion, several Ministers expressedthe view that it was undesirable that a decision onthis matter should be long deferred and that action on our part coming after the occupationof Hainan by the Japanese, would have considerable effect.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE saidthat he understood that the Chinese had maintainedthe value of their currency for s ome months bylieans of a revolving fund of  500&quot;,000.     It was evident, therefore, that the proposed loan of 3 millions was likely to prove of substantial assistance to them0The Foreign Secretary undertook to bringthe matter before the Cabinet at the next weekly meeting, whether or not an answer had then beenreceived from the United States
6,        The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by--theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (CP. 46(39))in which he summed up recent developments of thesituation in Spain0     There was now no doubt as tothe final issue in the Spanish civil ware     So long,however, as His Majesty&apos;s Government maintained theirpresent attitude towards General FrancorsAdministration, they were impotent to promote one ofthe principal purposes of British policy in Spain,namely, the effective combating of German and Italianinfluence with General Franco&apos;s regime*     He had therefore reached the conclusion that there was verymuch more to be gained than there was to be risked, byearly recognition of General Franco^, which should beunconditionalo .   The matter was urgent, as otherGovernments were rapidly moving in the same direction.In the circumstances, the Secretary of SBtate urgedthat, subject to agreement with the French, a decision should be taken to inform General Franco that HisMajesty&apos;s Government were prepared to accord him full recognition and to accredit an Ambassador to himwithout delay.     As an act of courtesy, prior noticeof our intention might be given to our ally Portugal,which was Spain&apos;s only other neighbour,,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that in his view the most important point inthe Memorandum was the argument in paragraph 7, thatthe final outcome of the Spanish war could not be ,in dispute, and that the sooner we recognised general franco and thus combated the growth of German andItalian influence with General Franco&apos;s regime   the better.     He also attached importance to acting in concert with the French,,At the same time, after discussing the matter with the Prime Minister on the previous afternoon,-6-
(Tf     C)f-j d Uhe now wished to make, one qualification to. the proposals in his Memorandum.    That qualification was that ifwe could avoid the political misrepresentation whichwould attend early recognition of General Franco&apos;sGovernment9 without incurring any serious delay, weshould do so.    If it should prove possible to persuade the Republican Government to stop fighting of theirown volition, this Y/ould greatly ease the difficultiesin the way of recognition.Accordingly a telegram had been sent the previous night to our representative at Burgos (No. 115).    In this telegram Sir R. Hodgson was asked to inform general franco of the indications that we had received that theSpanish Government would be willing to cease hostilitiesif General Franco would give assurances on three points:(l) the withdrawal of all foreign volunteers;(2) reprisals;(3) the freedom of the Spanish people to choose the future regime in Spain.It would be observed that this telegram did not mentionrecognition, or that we were considering the grant of recognition immediately hostilities had been broughtto an end.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs then set out the recent developments as regards France.A telegram had been received from our Ambassador in Paris^the previous evening (No. 6l)9 which stated that the ministerial Council had decided to send M. Berard backto Burgos officially.A subsequent message (No. 62) had been receivedfrom Paris to the effect that M. Berard would proceedto Burgos on 16th February, and would return to Parisearly next week after discussions with Generals Franco
and Jordana.    If General Franco accepted the proposalswhich were to be put forward by Mr- Berard, a date would be fixed for simultaneous recognition of general franco&apos;s Government by France and Great Britain.   this plan had been accepted by the French Council ofMinisters on the previous day.Continuing, the Foreign Secretary said his conclusion was that, subject to consultation with theFrench and to the situation developing as anticipated,he thought we should await General Francofs answer tothe Spanish Governments offer to cease hostilitieson certain conditions.    If, however, negotiations wereprolonged, or the Spanish Government proved obdurate,then we should be prepared to recognise General Franco&apos;sGovernment on the basis set out in hiB memorandum.The Foreign Secretary informed his colleagues of the reaction to his proposals which he had obtainedfrom three members of the House of Commons.   Two hadbeen in favour and the third had thought that, whileit was wrong to encourage the Spanish Government to resist, it would be equally wrong for us to recogniseGeneral Franco&apos;s Government unless we obtained someundertaking in regard to reprisals.In the discussion which ensued, THE CHANCELLOR .OF THE EXCHEQUER referred to the difficulties with which -the French Government would be faced in regard to property removed to France by the Spanish Government. Hethought that we might be faced with similar difficultieshere, but these difficulties would not be nearly so serious as those facing the French.    Of the three points;mentioned in paragraph 14 of the Foreign Secretary&apos;smemorandum, he attached particular importance to repri-sals.   He thought that we should be in a far stronger
  &apos;Q Uposition if we could get it on record that general franco undertook to abstain from reprisals and showmercy.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that General Francohad already stated that he would abstain from general political reprisals9 but that justice would be done on those who had committed crimes.   The real difficulty was likely to arise in the interpretation to be placedon this undertaking.   For example, Signor Barriobero9President of the People&apos;s Tribunal at Barcelona andMadrid9 had been condemned to death.    While general franco&apos;s Government no doubt regarded him as havingcommitted crimes in sentencing Nationalists to death,their action might be regarded in other quarters as areprisal.   His own view was that we could not usefullyintervene on behalf of those persons to whom prima facieit might be thought that General Franco should showclemency.THE PRIME MINISTER said he was not clear whether we were, in fact, keeping in step with the French.   TheFrench were proceeding on the basis of recognising general franco, subject to certain conditions, whereas we favoured the surrender of the Spanish Government on terms whichwould open the way for recognition.   There were thus two possibilities: one was that General Franco v/ould acceptthe offer of the Spanish Government   to surrender on certain conditions - in which cases presumably we should recognise him at once.    The other possibility was thatthe French v/ould obtain the assurances they asked for from General Franco.    In that event, was there not a risk that we should be asked by the French to recogniseGeneral Franco at once.    If the Spanish Government were on the point of surrender, it might be desirable that weshould not be tied up too closely with the French^ since it might be better that we should defer action for a day or so, in order that our recognition might follow andnot precede the cessation of hostilities.-9-
The discussion then turned to thequestion of belligerent rights0THE MINISTER OF HEALTH enquire whether recognition could be granted withoutaccording belligerent rights to General Franco.In his view it was somewhat illogical toproceed to recognition without having passed through the immediate stage of recognising theexistence of a war by granting belligerentrights oTHE FOREIGN SECRETARY thought it wasa pity to complicate a relatively straight-forward position by introducing the questionof belligerent rightseTHE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF defence pointed ou  that? since the outbreak of war when the 5^e^9?ge^^ had had command of the sea,we had declined to give them belligerent rightsand had adhered consistently to ihat policy -ev^a*THE LORD CHANCELLOR thought that therewas some difficulty in granting full recognition to General Franco and, at the same time,maintaining that he had no right to blockade,for example, Valencia,,     He thought that whatever international jurists might say general franco would, in fact, do soQIn regard to the Minister of Health*spoint, we had only refused to recognise theSpanish civil war as &quot;a war&quot; in a&apos;purely technicalsense from the point of view of international law.From the point of view of internationallaw, there was much to be said for the view thatRepublican Spain no longer had In existence a
recognised working Government whereas NationalistSpain had such a Government and was also inpossession of five-seventh&apos;s of Spain.Prom the point of view of a lawyer hewould much prefer that we should accord de factorecognition to General Prance     In practice nodoubt the point was not of material importance,since it was possible to accredit a Minister orAmbassador to a State which was recognised de facto.THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR HOME affairs and THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION affairs thought that if we were now to recognise general franco, we had better do it in one stage, and notto start with de facto recognition and proceedlater to de Jure recognition.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that,in the case of Abyssinia, we had been concernedwith the conquest by a foreign Power, and therewas a good deal to be said for accordingde facto recognition in such a case;   but he didnot agree that the same considerations appliedto the victor in a civil war..THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR thoughtthat there was great political advantage in notaccording recognition until the Government troops had surrendered,.     If, however, this could notbe brought about forthwith,, then we should obtainthe full advantage of the situation by accordingde jure, recognition to General Franco without undue delay.
o n oTHE PRIME MINISTER said that he thought the viewof the Cabinet was clearly that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentshould recognise General Franco&apos;s Government very soon.Equally, his colleagues would all prefer that the surrender of the Spanish Government troops should precedethe recognition of General Franco.      If, however,  theSpanish Government was obdurate or negotiations wereunduiby prolonged,    he suggested that the Foreign Secretary,in consultation with himself, should be authorised torecognise General Franco&apos;s Government in conjunctionwith the French Government, should the course of eventsmake such action- desirable before the next weekly meeting of the Cabinet.On the other hand, if the surrender of theSpanish Government troops was imminent, it would be worth while to run a little risk by delaying a day or so in order that surrender might precede recognition.The Cabinet agreed to this course.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE said hethought it should be clearly understood whether this conclusion involved the grant to General Franco of belligerent rights.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that we had consistentlymaintained the right to protect our shipping on the high seas, and had denied the right of the Insurgent forces to attack our shipping in territorial waters.     Weshould continue to maintain that position, but he doubted whether the practical effect would be great..
THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR THE COLONIES said that,while he agreed with the course proposed, he attached great importance to obtaining^a unilateral statement -fse-rfr-^nci&apos;*a3t^5W-4-ieia on the points referred to in paragraph 14of the Secretary of State&apos;s paper.The discussion then turned to the question whetherit would he desirable to discuss these proposals with theOpposition Leaders.The view generally taken was that this course might prove embarrassing.     For example, the discussion with theOpposition Leaders might proceed on the basis that wewere attempting to secure certain undertakings fromGeneral Franco&apos;s Government;    and in the event we mightnot succeed in obtaining them in full.There was also the point that the opposition leaders could hot adopt a moderate attitude in thismatter without exposing themselves to criticism fromtheir own extremists and that it was therefore unlikelythat consultation would appreciably affect the attitudeof the Opposition,,      It was agreed, however, that itmight be desirable to tell the Opposition Leaders what was proposed so soon as a decision to recognise general franco&apos;s Government had beon tajken.The Cabinet agreed.-(l)    That it was desirable that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should recognise general franco&apos;s Goveiriment in the near future,,(2)    That, if possible, recognition should follow surrender by the Spanish   Governmentforces but that if the Spanish GovernmentAuthorities proved obdurate and negotiations were prolonged,  it might be necessary that recognition of General Franco&apos;s Governmentshould precede the cessation ofhostilities.
(3)    To authorise the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, in consultation with thePrime Minister, to despatch the necessarytelegrams to give effect to these decisions.(4)    To authorise the Primo Minister and theForeign Secretary, if events should makeit necessary that General Franco should he recognised before the next weekly meetingof the Cabinet, to take the necessary action without further reference to theCabinet.(5)    That the Dominion Governments should be kept informed of the action proposed and thatthe President of the United States shouldalso be informed of our general intentions in this matter.(6)    That as regards belligerent rights we should adhere to the present position that neither side was entitled to exercise belligerentrights against third parties.
o p c*7. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGNAFFAIRS said that on lOth February Sir robert craigie had telegraphed (Telegram No. 128 fromTokio) that he had been informed that the JapaneseGovernment had decided to reject the proposalsof Germany and Italy to convert the anti-CominternPact into a formal alliance.     There was however some indication that Japan was preparing draft counter-proposals with the same object in view.The Cabinet took note of the above.
8. THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGNAFFAIRS thought that his colleagues should heaware that as a result of discussions that had.taken place during the previous week, theFrench Government had agreed to a suggestion which We had made to them, that while we shouldnot withdraw from the General Act for the PacificSettlement of International Disputes, we shouldmake our continued adherence to the Act subjectto a reservation regarding our position in timeof war.     Action on these lines had already teentaken by H.M. Government in the United Kingdom andby the French Government-,The Cabinet took note of this statement.
n f oPALESTINE. 9.      THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR THE colonies said that since the last meeting of the Cabinet it(previous reference:   had been found possible to bring the two separateCabinet 6(39), Con-   Delegations of Palestinian Arabs into a singleelusion 8. )Delegation.    The Conference had now settled down toFrR-tl3^) 5*      separates ^discussions between British representatives and,the representatives of the Arabs and of the Jewsrespectively.In the discussions with the Arabs therehad been considerable talk on general principles.Attention had at first been concentrated on thepassage in the McMahon correspondence, which was regarded by the Arabs as confirming their claim to palestine.    He hoped that before long the discussions would take a somewhat more practical turn. At themoment the Palestine Arab Delegation were pressing for the immediate recognition of an independent ArabGovernment in Palestine.    The Delegation, whilepersonally pleasant to deal with, had adopted a veryintransigent attitude.The Delegations from the neighbouring arab countries had not adopted a very helpful line.This was mianly due to General Nuri&apos;s insistence on making an unqualified statement of sympathy with theArab case.    He had been restrained from doing this for several days, but had finally insisted on making this statement.    As a result, it was inevitable that the representatives of the other neighbouring arab States should follow suit.    The representativesof Saudi-Arabia had already done so, in a reasonablymoderate statement, and the others would follow suitshortly.
While this had been their public attitude,in private the representatives&apos;of the Arab states had all indicated that they were in favour of asettlement by compromise.    The position was wellexemplified by the statement of Fuad Bey Hamza whosaid that while their hearts were with the PalestinianArabs-, they had brought not only their hearts, butalso their heads, to London.    The Prime Minister&apos;stalks on the previous day with the representativesof the neighbouring Palestinian Arabs had been of thegreatest assistances(At this point Lord Halifax left theMeeting.)In the small hours of that morning he had seen the representatives of the neighbouring arab countries in private, and had given them as a basis for private discussion the proposals set out in thereport of the Palestine Committee, including Plan (A)to deal with the immigration problem.    It had been clear that these proposals had come as a severedisappointment to the representatives of the arab states, and General Euri had started arguing in favourof the full Palestinian Arab claim.    fuad Bey Hamzawanted Jewish immigration completely stopped for aperiod of three or four years, after which it might perhaps be re-started if the Hewish refugee problemhad not by then been solved.    After a long discussion,the representatives of the neighbouring Arab states had agreed to take the proposals away and discuss themamong themselves.    The Egyptian representative had stated afterwards that he thought that the proposals- 18 -
9 &apos;&apos;i nrepresented the basis  of agreement with slightmodifications, hut he (the Colonial Secretary) thoughtthat this was over-optimistic.In dealing with the representatives of theArab States,  it must be remembered that they (likethe Jews) had a very good case.    Further, they had avery difficult delegation of Palestine Arabs to dealwith; and they were very hard bargainers.As regards negotiations with the Jews,discussion had so far been mainly confined to one particular aspect, namely, the strategic importanceto this country of maintaining friendly relationswith the States neighbouring on Palestine.He hoped to get down to more practicaldiscussions that evening, when he proposed to put tothe Jewish representatives the proposals in the reportof the Palestine Committee,  including plan (b) forimmigration.    The Foreign Secretary had made a most effective appeal to the Jewish representatives on theprevious day.    The main point which he had made wasthat the Jews would come best out of this matterif they took     a    really generous line themselves.On the whole, the atmosphere had been more friendly than he had expected.    While this wasencouraging, it was clear that the two sides were still very far apart.THE PRIME MINISTER said he was sure that his colleagues would recognise the difficultyof the negotiations in which the Colonial secretary was engaged, and the great demands which would bemade on his time.    At the same time, his colleagues
would also note with satisfaction the friendly-atmosphere which had been maintained, which offeredgood promise for the future.The Cabinet took note ofthis statement.
fji &quot;M OINDIA.Congress andthe indian states.(previous reference:Cabinet 2(59) Oon-clusion 6).10.       The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for India (C.P.-44 (39))informing them of organised agitation,, accompaniedby violence in some cases, which had been started bythe Congress Party, with the object of compellingthe Rulers of the Indian States to grant responsible government in their territories.     The end in view was to force the Rulers to agree that theirrepresentatives in the Federal Legislature shouldbe chosen by election, instead of by nomination,which was the only method by which the congress party could secure a majority in the federal legislature.     If this were achieved, the congress leaders believed that they could make it verydifficult, if not impossible, for the Governor-General to exercise the special powers vested in him,by the Government of India Act,     The policy adoptedby His Majesty&quot;s Government towards questions of constitutional reform in the States was that thenature of the changes was a matter for the Rulersthemselves, but that they would be given theprotection to which they were entitled, under theirtreaties, against violence and disorder.     TheViceroy was advising the&apos; States to stand firm, butit was clear that there was a danger of Mr, gandhi and the Working Committee of Congress calling out theCongress Provincial Ministries as a protest.    If we failed to support the Rulers, they would be driven to make the best terras possible with Congress, whileit was possible to do so.- SI -
10.       The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for India (C.P.-44 (39))informing them of organised agitation, accompaniedby -\aolence in some cases, which had been started bythe Congress Party, with the object of compellingthe Rulers of the Indian States to grant responsible government in their territories.     The end in view was to force the Rulers to agree that theirrepresentatives in the Federal Legislature shouldbe chosen by election, instead of by nomination,vtfiich was the only method by which the congress party could secure a majority in the federal legislature.     If this were achieved, the congress leaders believed that they could make it verydifficultP if not impossible, for the Governor-General to exercise the special powers vested in him.by the Government of India Act.     The policy adoptedby His Majesty&apos;s Government towards questions of constitutional reform in the States was that thenature of the changes was a matter for the Rulersthemselves, but that they would be given theprotection to which they were entitled, under theirtreaties, against violence and disorder.      TheViceroy was advising the States to stand firm, butit was clear that there was a a.anger of Mr. gandhi and the Working Committee of Congress calling out theCongress Provincial Ministries as a protest.    If we failed to support the Rulers, they would be driven to make the best terms possible with Congress, whileit was possible to do so.
The Conclusions arrived at by the Secretary ofState and the Viceroy, for which the fox-mer sought theagreement of his colleagues, were summed up at the endof the Memorandum as follows:-(l) We are bound by 6ur treaty obligations tothe States to support them(2) If we failed to support the Rulers now aland-slide would, be inevitable, the Rulersseeking to make their peace with theCongress while there was time.(5) For a number of reasons we could not allow ourselves to be influenced by the resignation of the Governments on a matter with which,under the Government of India Act, they haveno concern.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA said that hewould like to give his colleagues some of the background of the present situation.     Since the late summer of1937, Provincial Autonomy had been working successfullyand there had been considerable speculation as to theprospects of Federation.     It was freely said in certain quarters that,  just as Congress had given way and had worked the Provincial Assemblies so, when the time came,they would work Federation.   The opinion had grown that,this was in effect the intention of the Right Wing of congress, and the result had been to make the LeftWing more violent.   To meet this situation, and toshow that they were as good Nationalists as the LeftWing, the Right Wing had thrown themselves into a campaign against the Ruling Princes, with the idea ofcompelling them to introduce responsible governmentin their States.   The object of this campaign was clearly to capture sufficient seats to enable congress to secure an absolute majority in the federal legislature.
The first question to he settled was what our policy should be towards the question of constitutional reform in the States.     Our present policy on thismatter was set out in paragraph 4 of his Paper, whilethe justification for it was dealt with in paragraph 7.That paragraph, however, only dealt with the juridicaljustification, based on the contractual relationsbetween the Ruling Princes and the Paramount Power.Two further arguments could be adduced as justificationon grounds of expediency.     The first was that it was undesirable that there should be a Congress majority in the Federal Legislature.     The second was thatMoslem opposition to Congress was becoming stronger,since Congress was regarded as a purely Hinduorganisation.The Secretary of State quoted instances to illustrate the Moslem opposition to the congress party.     In particular, the All-India Moslem League,at a meeting a month ago, had passed a resolutioncondemning the attitude of Congress in conductingagitation in the States, and had said that if this attitude continued, they would have to intervene.A further complication in the situation wasthat, if it was decided to support the Ruling Princes,it would be necessary in many cases to rely on theco-operation of the Provinces, on whom calls wouldhave to be made to supply police.     The Provinceswhich had Congress Party Ministries, would clearly be opposed to such action.      It was however, significant that in a case in which help had been despatched tothe Ruler of a small State in Central India, the punjab Province, which had a Moslem Prime Minister,had willingly provided the police force required.
T *1 Afa i \*The first question to toe settled was what our policy should be towards the question of constitutional reform in the States.     Our present policy on thismatter was set out in paragraph 4 of his Paper, whilethe justification for it was dealt with in paragraph 7.That paragraph, however, only dealt with the juridicaljustification, based on the contractual relationsbetween the Ruling Princes and the Paramount Power.Two further arguments could be adduced as justificationon grounds of expediency.     The first was that it was undesirable that there should be a Congress majority in the Federal Legislature.     The second was thatMoslem opposition to Congress was becoming stronger,since Congress was regarded as a purely Hinduorganisation.The Secretary of State quoted instances to illustrate the Moslem opposition to the congress party.      In particular, the All-India Moslem League,at a meeting a month ago, had passed a resolutioncondemning the attitude of Congress in conductingagitation in the States, and had said that if this attitude continued, they would have to intervene.A further complication in the situation wasthat, if it was decided to support the Ruling Princes,it would be necessary in many cases to rely on theco-operation of the Provinces, on whom calls wouldhave to be made to supply police.      The Provinceswhich had Congress Party Ministries, would clearly be opposed to&apos; such action.      It was however, significant that in a case in which help had been despatched tothe Ruler of a small State in Central India, the punjab Province, which had a Moslem Prime Minister,had willingly provided the police force required.
- e% fj rt.6 toFinally, the Secretary of State touched onthe prospects of a &quot;break between ourselves and theCongress Party over this matter.     It might be significant that Subas Bose, a Left Winger, had recently been electedas President of Congress,Until after the meeting of the Congress working committee which was to be held in the second week ofMarch, it would not be possible to say whether thisindicated a general swing to the Left,     Indicationswere not wanting that Mr, Gandhi would endeavour to treat the campaign against the Princes as a smoke-screenbehind which to maintain the unity of the Party byensuring that all the energies   of the Left Wing weredevoted to a usampaign against the Princes,Continuing, the Secretary of State said thatthe Governors of the Provinces had been warned ofthe possibility of a split with Congress.     His own view was that Congress would not make a thoroughbreak, but that a break might be expected in the twoGovernments who were in closest contiguity to the indian states most concerned.     If so, this would give furtherroom for manoeuvre,THE SECRETARY OP state FOP HOME AFFAIRS and THECHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER both expressed the view thatit was essential to act on the lines proposed by theSecretary of State for India.     Attention was drawn to-the pledges which had been given to the Princes over along period of years, and to the fact (pointed out inparagraph 14 (-2) of 0,Po 44(39)) that, if we failed tosupport the Rulers now, a land-slide would be inevitable-.The Cabinet approved the course proposed by the Secretary Of Statefor India in paragraph 14 of his memorandum, which is summarised above.
CIVIL defence services.Compensationfor Peace-timeInjuries.(previous reference:Cabinet 4(39), Con-clusion 2.)II. The Cabinet.had under consideration a Memo-randum by the Lord Privy Seal (CP. 42 (39)) putting forward proposals for compensation to members of theCivil Defence services in respect of death or disable-ment attributable to injuries sustained by volunteersin the course of peace-time training.     He attached as appendices to his Memorandum two Schedules showingthe terms at present in force under the InsurancePolicy Schemes as compared with those he now suggested.The effect of his proposals on lump-sum payments ondeath, the principle of which should be retained, wereshown as follows:-Comnensation Payment for Death.Auxiliary Firemen.A.R.P. Volunteers.For widow with oneor more dependent children.For widow withoutdependent children.For a motherlessdependent child or children.For other relativeswholly or mainlydependent. 600 400 300not exceeding  300 1,000 700 500not exceeding  500In respect of specified injuries representing eithertotal disablement or a measure of permanent partialdisablement, the Lord Privy Seal suggested the following terms, to be applied both to A.R.P. volunteers and toAuxiliary Firemen:-Total disablement -  5 a week for six months,and thereafter the following pension rates, which were slightly lower thanthose now contemplated under the War Code:-30/- a week for a single man.35/- a week for a man with wife.40/- a week for a man with wife and one dependent child.With an additional allowance of 3/-a week for each additional dependentchild up to a. maximum total allowance of 49/- a week.
9 7n   !fa 8   IFor permanent partial disablement, proportionaterates would be paid:    also reimbursement of &apos;ireasonable medical fees.      The Lord Privy Sealproposed, however, that Auxiliary Firemen alreadyenrolled should be given the option of retainingtheir existing terms if they so desired.The Lord Privy Seal proposed that the risks of compensation should he carried by theGovernment, and not, covered by insurance.Finally, the Lord Privy Seal called attention to possible repercussions of therates he proposed on other compensation ratespayable for peaoe-time injuries in the Servicesand under Workmen&apos;s Compensation.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL  said these proposals were complementary   to   the rates of pay in timeof war for volunteers serving whole-time in civil defence which had been approved by the cabinet a fortnight ago.     The present proposals, however,related to compensation in respect of death ordisablement attributable to injuries sustained byvolunteers during training in peace-time.     Indealing with this matter, he had been faced withthe difficulty that he could not start with aclean slate.      Some time past, two insurance schemes had been in force:    one for A.R.P. workersin general, and the second for Auxiliary fire service into which 100,000 men had already been recruited.     It was also necessary to relatethe proposals to the existing scales ofcompensation in other spheres.      The matter hadbeen exhaustively discussed at a series of meetings with representatives of the Treasury and otherDepartments concerned.- 26 -
d n o&amp; i 0The Lord Privy Seal said that he would have liked to have assimilated the benefits payable under the twoscales, either by scaling down the rate of the AuxiliaryFire Service, or by scaling up the rate of the A-R.P.Volunteers or by finding an appropriate halfway house. .It was clear, however, that he would be faced with great difficulties if the launching of the National Servicecampaign coincided with a marked reduction in theterms offered.     He was also advised that any substantial increase in the rates applicable to A.R.P. volunteerswould give rise to serious difficulties.     While,therefore, it had been found possible to reach substantialsimilarity in the terms between the two schemes generally,there remained a wide divergence as regards the amountspayable in death benefits.     It was, of course, illogicalto have different rates of death benefit in the twobranches of the Service.      The difference, however, couldbe justified by reference to the exceptionalrisks to which the Auxiliary Fireman was exposed inundergoing training.In dealing with this matter, steps had beentaken to amplify the scheme of compensation which was at present somewhat unsatisfactory, so as to provide asuitable basis for a Government scheme of compensation.For example, the existing terms for a long period of disablement were not satisfactory.The scheme had been discussed informally withrepresentatives of the Trade Union Congress and theFederation of Employers&apos;  Organisations.      The formerargued vigorously that the death benefit of the A.R.P.volunteers should be scaled up to the figure paid to the auxiliary Firemen, while the latter body took the oppositeview.     He anticipated that, although the scales differedin material respects from other schemes of compensation and were thus bound to invite contrast, there would beno serious criticism except in regard to death benefits.- 27 -
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR wished to inviteattention to the course which events had taken since theNational Voluntary Service campaign had been inaugurated.At the meeting of the Cabinet held on 1st February hehad drawn attention to the fact that persons employed inthe Ordnance Factories in reserved occupations would receive wages varying from 42/- to 5 5/- a week, whereasvolunteers for A.R.P. duties received  3 a week.     Thecorresponding rate for a territorial was 47/3 a week, ofwhich 14/- represented payment in cash.The compensation proposals now proposed were inevery respect more favourable than those of the FightingServices.     Under the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s scheme, the widowof an Auxiliary Fireman, who was killed in training, would receive  1,000 in cash and would be eligible for a pension under the State Contributory Schemes for Widows Pensions.The widow of a territorial soldier was not eligible fora pension under that scheme and received no lump sum payment, but we^34- rpcei vgT-a pension of 17-/6- a wo ok -fgem-fife- p-e^^r^- Jp Alv-i Opf*^*.   Sy 1O/6   a, cu-cjL4c iL. cAijLaL&amp;L-sS. cx^eL it6ffi^e^r&quot;*whcrci^^Again, under the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s proposals,an A.R.P. volunteer who was disabled would receive  3a week whereas a Territorial who was disabled received32/6 a week if he was invalided out of the Servicealtogether.The campaign of National Voluntary Service had had adyense effects/on recruiting for the TerritorialArmy-/  -The figures for/London showed a fall of 2 r per cent.He did not wish to oppose the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s suggestion,&apos;but he claimed that the Services should not be lessfavourably treated.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR   appreciated theLord Privy Seal&apos;s difficulties and thought we were in danger of getting into the position we had been in at the
fa o 0end of the last war, when those who bore the burden ofthe danger were less well treated than those who remained in comparative safety.     He thought that the position ofthe Defence Forces must be reserved.     He had no doubt thatthe Chancellor of the Exchequer was alive to the needs ofthe situation.In reply to the Prime Minister, THE SECRETARY OFSTATE FOR WAR and THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said thatthey were unable to confirm the statement in paragraph 13of CP. 42 (39) that an assimilation of the Services&apos; codesto that proposed by the Lord Privy Seal would not costmore than  80,000 a year0THE MINISTER OF LABOUR said that it would not be too easy to obtain general acceptance of the Lord privy seal&apos;s proposals.     Further, there was strong feeling inthe country that the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Schemes were in need of revision.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR HOME AFFAIRS saidthat he thought it would be desirable to take the line thatthe present proposals were     quite      outside the sphere of the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Acts and that they should notbe in any way related to the terms of those Acts.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that thepresent proposals were the result of thrashing out thematter between the representatives of the Treasury, the lord privy Seal&apos;s Department and the Defence Departments.     Theposition was admittedly unsatisfactory, but he found himself in agreement with the view that the scales put forward werethe least which could be offered in the circumstances.As regards the possible repercussions on the Services, hewas willing that these should be examined on the assumptionthat the cost would be found to be in the neighbourhood ofthe figure of  80,000 mentioned in paragraph 13, and didnot amount to some much larger sum0
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND referred tothe position of Special Constables.     At the present time,compensation could be paid to them in respect of injurysustained on duty but not while in training.     It was thought desirable that they should be allowed to trainwith the Regular police Force and that this aspect of thematter should be watched.This was agreed to.The Cabinet agreed:(a) To accept the proposals set out inthe Lord Privy Seal&apos;s memorandum(CP. 42 (39)) for compensation to members of the Civil defence services in respect of death ordisablement attributable to injurysustained by volunteers in the courseof peace-time training:(b) That the question of any consequentialrevision of the rates of compensation payable in peace to members of the armed Forces of the Crown (regularor auxiliary) should be further examined inter-Departmentally.
*5 Q 9iO OTHE PATENTS and designs (LIMITSOp TIME) BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 34(38), Con-clusion 4. )12.     The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum igythe President  of the Board of Trade (H.A.-7 (39))covering the draft Patents and Designs (Limits ofTime) Bill, the object of which was to amend certain provisions of the Patents and Designs Acts, 1907-1938, relating to the statutory time limits withinwhich certain actions precedent to the grant ormaintenance of a patent must be performed:    togetherwith the following recommendation to the Cabinetthereon by the Committee of Home Affairs (H.A.C.3rd Conclusions (39), Minute 2):-&quot;To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of Lords of the Patents and designs (Limits of Time) Bill in the formof the draft annexed to H.A.-7 (39),subject to. any drafting or other minor alterations that may be found necessary or desirable.&quot;The Cabinet approved the above recommendation and agreed that the Bill was suitable for introduction in the House of Lords.
q q *1fa O dm LOCALkivsbmetutRVPffiANNUA-PION BILL.$(PreviousiReferenoe:[Cabinet 8(39),[Conclusion 11),13.       The Cabinet had under consideration aMemorandum by the Minister of Health (H.A.-8 (39)),covering the draft Local Government SuperannuationBill, the object of which was to effect certin minor amendments to the Local Government SuperannuationAct, 1937, and the Local Government Superannuation(Scotland) Act, 1937:    together with the following recommendation to the Cabinet thereon by theCommittee of Home Affairs (H.A.C. 3rd Conclusions (39),Minute 3);-&quot;To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of Commons, with a view toits passage into law before the 1st April,1939, of the Local Government SuperannuationBill in the form of the draft annexed with.A.-8 (39), subject to any drafting orother minor alterations that may be foundnecessary or desirable.&quot;The Cabinet agreed to this recommendation.
9 q A&amp; q %THE SHOPS BILL. 14.       The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to -(previous the Shops Bill, introduced in the House of CommonsReference:Cabinet 16 (37), by a Private Member and down for Second Reading on conclusion 9).Friday, 24th February, 1939.It was agreed that this Bill shouldbe opposed, and that the arrangements in this connection should be concertedbetween the Secretary of State for HomeAffairs and the Minister of Labour.
o rA 0 0THE HIGHWAYS       15.     The Cabinet had under consideration thePROTECTIONBILL. Highways Protection Bill, introduced in the HouseF.R. &quot; 0^ Commons ^y a Private Member and down for SecondReading on Friday, 24th February, 1939,As the Bill had not been printed,it was not discussed.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.15th February, 1939*

</content>
</cab>
