<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 248-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYjS GOVERNMENT)C.(65) 66 COPY NO.   5929th April, 1965CABINETMemorandum by the Minister of technology the memorandum by the First Secretary of State (C.(65) 65), oncomputer purchases for the Administrative Departments of the Secretaryof State for Scotland and for the Royal Aircraft Establishment,Farnborough, raises issues which extend beyond these two immediatecases, and it would not be appropriate to consider them in isolation.Other cases posing similar questions will follow.    The Minister ofPensions, for example, will shortly have to choose the first of a  seriesof computers for his regional offices.    American suppliers are, Iunderstand, likely to be strong contenders for this contract.2.      In all of these cases the decisions we reach must be seen to be consistent with our policy on computers.    We have announced that weconsider a flourishing British computer industry to be an essential element in our plans for the modernisation of British industry and commerce;  and we have announced a whole series of measures designedto achieve this.    The purchase by the Government itself of foreigncomputers when adequate British machines exist would be bound, in my view, to suggest that we are not serious in our intention to support theBritish manufacturers.    It would be widely taken as evidence of our lackof confidence in British computers.    We can hardly urge others to usemachines that we are not prepared to use ourselves.    Much more is at stake than the loss to the British manufacturers of one or two particularorders.3.       These considerations are reinforced at this time when our policieare new, when the British computer industry is making a determined -and perhaps final - effort to meet foreign competition, and when we are about to undertake, following the Prime Minister&apos;s initiative with theFrench President, an examination of the possibilities of fi*uitfulcollaboration between our computer manufacturers and those interestsin France who want to escape from the American domination of theindustry.4.       When we drew up our proposals for the support of the computer industry it was then believed that British computers were broadlycomparable in performance and price with those of foreign ones- and thatthe main handicap to sales was our inability to provide software.    Atthat time it did not appear that price was a sufficiently cogent considera-tion to recommend any discrimination in the provision of computers forGovernment use.    Since then, evidence has accumulated to show tha.british manufacturers cannot offer the larger computers, costing about 500, 000 or more, as cheaply as their American competitors.    two important causes for this are the benefit of long production runs for thelarge American home market;  and the Federal and State Authorities

CONFIDENTIAL .       4practice of buying the computers they need from an American supplier JL .unless his quotation exceeds that of a foreign supplier by at least 50 percent.    We must now consider to what extent our procurement practicesneed amendment.5.      It would be consistent with our policy of support for the Britishcomputer industry if, when procuring computers for use by GovernmentDepartments, British machines were purchased unless:-(a) no British machine can meet the requirement;  or(b) there would be serious delay to the start of -work(say two years);   or(c) there is a gross disparity in the price tendered tothe Stationery Office (say 25 per cent or more).6.       The adoption of these criteria need not affect the confidence ofusers and manufacturers in the objectivity of the technical adviceavailable from the Ministry of Technology&apos;s Computer Advisory Service.We can make it plain that for Government purchases other, wider,considerations have to be taken into account.    We should also make itclear that while we were in no position to impose our criteria on otherusers in the public sector, we would hope that they would follow our lead.There are already welcome signs that some users, e.g. the greater london Council, are ready to use British computers in preference to american even at some additional cost.7.       It may be argued that this more direct line of support for theBritish manufacturers would produce the undesirable consequences offeather bedding.    This risk is minimised by the fact that government orders do not form a major share of the market.    It would be reducedeven further by making it clear to the British manufacturers that these special measures of support were intended to help them re-establish and consolidate their competitive position over, say, the next three years andwould be subject to review in the light of their own efforts.8. It may also be argued that to give this measure of preference tothe British manufacturers would be challenged as being contrary to our general commercial policy. I very much doubt whether this is a serious risk. In any event, I believe a convincing case for Government supporton the lines I suggest can be made on the grounds of the key important*tanceto technological advance in our industry and commerce of a flourishing,independent computer industry.9.       I recognise that the adoption of the criteria, proposed inparagraph 5 could not be long concealed.    Indeed I would see no pointin attempting to do so and we should be prepared to announce thempublicly in the House.10.      I therefore ask my colleagues to agree that:-(a) the contract for the computer for the Scottish departments should be placed with International Computers a.ndTabulators Limited (I. C. T. );(b) the invitation to tender for the Farnborough computer shouldbe confined to I. C. T. , English Electric and ElliottAutomation;; and(c) decisions on future purchases of computers for use by government Departments should be based on the criteriaset out in paragraph 5 above.F c ministry of Technology, 3. W.l.29th April, 1965       CONFIDENTIAL;,..S




</content>
</cab>
