<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 300-303</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property ofher britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.  May 1965C. (65) 72 Copy No.     597th May, 1965CABINETTRADE DISPUTES BILL: QUESTION OF RETROSPECTIONMemorandum by the Attorney-GeneralThe purpose of this memorandum is to invite the Cabinet to approve a proposed amendment of the Trade Disputes Bill, whichwill shortly be considered by the House of Commons at Report stage.2. The effect of the Bill, as at present drafted, will be thatcauses of action which have arisen, but in respect of which no legal proceedings have been instituted, before Royal Assent will be decided in accordance with the provisions of the Bill and not in accordancewith the law as it now is. There will thus be some measure of retrospection, in that a potential plaintiff whose right of action hasaccrued before the Bill becomes law may lose that right.3. When this topic was previously considered by the Cabineton 21st January, 1965 (C.C. (65) 3rd Conclusions, Minute 4), it was thought that this degree of retrospection was unlikely to be strongly criticised and would not cause unnecessary difficulties in Parliament.Since then, however, the strength of opinion against retrospectivelegislation has been reinforced during the debates on the war damage Bill. I think it most undesirable that the Government shouldbe exposed to further attack by the Opposition on this issue andon grounds far more favourable to the Opposition. The retrospectiveelement in the Bill has already been strongly criticised in StandingCommittee, and an Opposition amendment, which will allow threeyears for the commencement of proceedings, has been put down forReport stage. Quite apart from the probability of further criticismin the House of Commons, it is likely that the House of Lords wouldseize the opportunity to reopen the issue of retrospection and thatthe passage of the Bill would be delayed.4. In these circumstances, I regard it as essential that the Billshould now be amended to reduce the element of retrospection. i therefore propose that the Bill should permit proceedings to be instituted within six months of Royal Assent in respect of causes ofaction which have then accrued. This would reduce from six years to six months the period within which proceedings could otherwise be brought. There is precedent for a limitation period of six months to be found in the law relating to proceedings against the estate of adeceased person.5693
5. This proposed amendment in my view will have littlepractical effect, as it will only relate to causes of action which arisebefore Royal Assent, and in respect of which no proceedings havethen been instituted. There are unlikely to be more than a very few cases, if any, which fall within this category. But the importance ofthe amendment is that it will enable the Government to forestallfurther criticism that it is playing fast and loose with the principlethat retrospective legislation can only be justified in most exceptional cases.6. I recommend that the proposed amendment should beintroduced at Report stage in the House of Commons.F. E. J.Law Officers&apos; Department,7th May, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
