<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 350-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property ofher britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1965C. (65) 78 Copy No.    5 928th May, 1965CABINETCOMPUTER FOR THE SCOTTISH DEPARTMENTSMemorandum by the First Secretary of State and secretary of State for Economic affairs at the meeting of the Cabinet on 6th May (C.C. (65) 28thConclusions, Minute 6), I was invited, in consultation with theSecretary of State for Scotland, the Minister of Technology and other ministers concerned, to arrange for the procurement of the computersfor the Scottish Departments and the Royal Aircraft Establishment,Farnborough, on the lines indicated by the Prime Minister.2. In view of the considerable delay already suffered and thepublic commitment by the Scottish Departments to have the Scottishcomputer in operation by 1st April, 1966, the Prime Ministeremphasised that any revised offer made by a United Kingdom-ownedcompany should not only be reasonable in cost in comparison withthe offer already made by International Business Machines Limited(I.B.M.), but also satisfy the Governments requirements as regardsdate of operation.3. I attach a note by officials evaluating the revised offers whichhave been made by International Computers and Tabulators Limited(I.C.T.), and English Electric Leo (E.E.L.) for the Scottish computer.The Ministry of Technology were unfortunately unable to agree withthe recommendation of the other Departments involved. I.C.T. are clearly not able to meet our requirements. E.E.L. have made tworevised offers. The cheaper of these will cost about 10 per centmore than the original I.B.M. offer both in terms of initialcapital cost and of total cost over an assumed operational period of seven years.4. It seems clear, moreover, that, at best, E.E.L. wouldnot be Operational before 1st September, 1966; and this allowsno margin for the almost inevitable teething troubles. I.B.M., on theother hand, have undertaken to have their equipment in operation by 1st April, 1966, and they have made such an ample allowance for contingencies that it seems clear we can rely on their undertaking.5. I ask my colleagues to agree, therefore, that the I.B.M. tender for the Scottish computer should be accepted forthwith.G. B.Department of Economic Affairs, S.W.1.27th May, 1965.5757
COMPUTER &quot;FOR SCOTTISH DEPARTMENTSNote by officials at their meeting on 6th May (CC. (65) 28th Conclusions,Minute 6), the Cabinet had before them memoranda about the procurement of computers for Government Departments.The most pressing case for consideration was the computer forthe Scottish Department.which must,be in operation by 1st April,1966, if public undertakings to hospitals and educational authorities(on the basis of which they are working) are to be fulfilled.Summing up the discussion, the Prime Minister invited the first secretary of State to arrange for the procurement of the computer forthe Scottish Departments on the following basis. United Kingdomcompanies should be given a second opportunity to tender;/on thebasis of a realistic target price, and if one of them proved able to makea satisfactory offer and to meet other requirements as regards date of operation, etc., then it might be awarded the contract. Otherwise itwould be necessary to accept the I.B.M. tender.Two United Kingdom-owned companies, I.C.T. and E;E.L., were invited to submit fresh tenders. They were asked whether they would increase the amount of equipment of services which they would beprepared to provide for the original target price of  400,000 or whetherthey would reduce their price for the equipment and servicespreviously offered for  400,000.I.C.T. made marginal alterations in price and offered some increase in capacity but made it clear that the installation would notbe in working order before 1st June, 1966, and probably not until sometime after that date. This company therefore clearly cannot meet therequirements laid down.E.E.L. made two fresh offers. One for approximately the originaltarget price of  400,000 but with extra equipment; the other for areduction of  34,000 in the cost of equipment originally offered. both these new offers are more costly than I.B.M.&apos;s original offer. Theadditional cost of the lower of them is shown in the Annex.As regards the date of operation, although the new E.E.L. offerscan provide equipment by 1st April, 1966, two reasons have been advanced why it cannot be operative by that date. First, designs forthe air conditioning plant, etc., have been commissioned (and completed) to cope with I.B.M. or I.C.T. machines. These designswould now need to be altered to meet the greater requirements of theE.E.L. equipment. Ministry of Public Building, and Works have estimated that, at best, this would delay installation and operation ofE.E.L. by five months. Secondly in the view of the Scottish office the number of analysts and programmers that E.E.L. can provide is inadequate to enable the installation to be in operation on time.
On this basis the E.E.L. equipment could be in operation by 1st September, 1966, though the Ministry of Public Building and works estimate leaves no safety margin for possible hitches. On theother hand, I.B.M. have undertaken to have their equipment inoperation by 1st April, 1966, and their timetable includes a usefulmargin of about three months for unforeseen contingencies.The Ministry of Technology considered that the additional costof about 10 per cent and the delay of five months which the E.E.L.tender would involve should be accepted as within the margin ofpreference to be accorded to United Kingdom-owned manufacturersin the procurement of computers for Government use. They alsobelieved that, if exceptional measures were taken, it should be possibleto reduce the time required to get the E.E.L. equipment installed and into operation.The Treasury, the Department of Economic Affairs, the Board ofTrade the Scottish Office and the Stationery Office, on theother hand, were satisfied that E.E.L. would not be able to providea working installation by 1st April, 1966, and recommend that the stationery Office should be authorised to purchase forthwith for theScottish Departments the I.B.M. machine, which would be available on time at a substantially lower cost; and, in the view of the scottish office, would also offer operational advantages.Annexcost comparison between e.e.l. and i.b.m. installationsfor scottish departments 000E.E.L. I.B.M.Capital (equipment, installation,     1,067 975programming)Cost of delay.........        90 -Running costs over seven years     2,349 2,290Spare capacity.........       900 hours per 1,200 hours perannum annumEXCESS COSTS OF E.E.L. OVER I.B.M. CAPITALISEDOVER SEVEN YEARSCapital..................Estimated value of difference in spare capacityCost of delay...............Running costs...............331,000 92,00090,00090,00059,000Thus the total excess cost of the e.e.L. over the i.b.m., capitalised over a periodof seven years, is  331,000, or just over 10 per cent of the total cost (capitalisedover the same period) of the i.b.m. installation.
COMPUTER *FOR SCOTTISH DEPARTMENTS: : &apos; Note by officials at their meeting on 6th May (C.C. (65) 28th Conclusions,Minute 6), the Cabinet had before them memoranda about the procurement of computers for Government Departments.The most pressing case for consideration was the computer forthe Scottish Department.which must-be in operation by 1st April,1966, if public undertakings to hospitals and educational authorities(on the basis of which they are working) are to be fulfilled.; :Summing up the discussion, the Prime Minister invited the first secretary of State to arrange for the procurement of the computer forthe Scottish Departments on the following basis. United Kingdomcompanies should be given a second opportunity to tender,on thebasis of a realistic target price, -and if one of them proved able to makea satisfactory offer and to meet other requirements as regards date of operation, etc., then it might be awarded the contract. Otherwise itwould be necessary to accept the I.B.M. tender.Two United Kingdom-owned companies, I.C.T. and E.E.L., were invited to submit fresh tenders. They were asked whether they would increase the amount of equipment or services which they would beprepared to provide for the original target price of  400,000 or whetherthey would reduce their price for the equipment and servicespreviously offered for  400,000.I.C.T. made marginal alterations in price and offered some increase in capacity but made it clear that the installation would notbe in working order before 1st June, 1966, and probably not until sometime after that date. This company therefore clearly cannot meet therequirements laid down.E.E.L. made two fresh offers. One for approximately the originaltarget price of  400,000 but with extra equipment; the other for areduction of  34,000 in the cost of equipment originally offered. both these new offers are more costly than I.B.M.&apos;s original offer. Theadditional cost of the lower of them is shown in the Annex.As regards the date of operation, although the new E.E.L. offerscan provide equipment by 1st April, 1966, two reasons have been advanced why it cannot be operative by that date. First, designs forthe air conditioning plant, etc., have been commissioned (and completed) to cope with I.B.M. or I.C.T. machines. These designswould now need to be altered to meet the greater requirements of theE.E.L. equipment. Ministry of Public Building, and Works have estimated that, at best, this would delay installation and operation ofE.E.L. by five months. Secondly in the view of the Scottish office the number of analysts and programmers that E.E.L. can provide is inadequate to enable the installation to be in operation on time.
On this basis the E.E.L. equipment could be in operation by 1st September, 1966, though the Ministry of Public Building and works estimate leaves no safety margin for possible hitches. On theother hand, I.B.M. have undertaken to have their equipment inoperation by 1st April, 1966, and their timetable includes a usefulmargin of about three months for unforeseen contingencies.The Ministry of Technology considered that the additional costof about 10 per cent and the delay of five months which the E.E.L.tender would involve should be accepted as within the margin ofpreference to be accorded to United Kingdom-owned manufacturersin the procurement of computers for Government use. They alsobelieved that, if exceptional measures were taken, it should be possibleto reduce the time required to get the EEL. equipment installed and into operation.The Treasury, the Department of Economic Affairs, the Board ofTrade the Scottish Office and the Stationery Office, on theother hand, were satisfied that E.E.L. would not be able to providea working installation by 1st April, 1966, and recommend that the stationery Office should be authorised to purchase forthwith for theScottish Departments the I.B.M. machine, which would be available on time at a substantially lower cost; and, in the view of the scottish office, would also offer operational advantages.AnnexCOST COMPARISON BETWEEN E.E.L. AND I.B.M. INSTALLATIONSFOR SCOTTISH DEPARTMENTSWOOE.E.L. I.B.M.Capital (equipment, installation,     1,067 975programming)Cost of delay......... 90 -Running costs over seven years     2,349 2,290Spare capacity.........       900 hours per 1,200 hours perannum annumEXCESS COSTS OF E.E.L. OVER I.B.M. CAPITALISEDOVER SEVEN YEARS Capital...........................      92,000Estimated value of difference in spare capacity.........      90,000Cost of delay........................      90,000Running costs........................      59,000331,000Thus the total excess cost of the e.e.L. over the I.B.M., capitalised over a periodof seven years, is  331,000, or just over 10 per cent of the total cost (capitalisedover the same period) of the I.B.M. installation.




</content>
</cab>
