<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 540-551</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.(65) 86 COPY NO. j jj29th June, 1965CABINETHOME DEFENCE AND THE TERRITORIAL army memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home DepartmentIntroductionIn the co-arse of considering what home defence measures arerequired in the period up to 1971-72, the Ministerial Committee on civil Defence have reviewed the usefulness of the reserve Army(Territorial Army and Array Emergency Reserve II) for home defence,in connection with the study which is being made by the Ministry ofDefence of the future requirement for reserve forces.     The purpose ofthis memorandum is to report our views, which are not unanimous, onthis question.The Reserve forces.       The Reserve Army as at present constituted would provide about161,000 men for home defence on mobilisation;  this number includesabout 84,000 reservists, most of whom are ex-national servicemen who,under the Army Reserves Act 1964, will be available only until 1969.About 152, 000 are in units of the Territorial Army divisions v/hich under existing arrangements will be at the disposal of the civil authorities.They are not earmarked in advance for any particular tasks, except for12-13units (9,000 men) for fire-fighting and about 1, 000 men for signaland administrative tasks at the regional seats of government.3.       The Territorial Army divisions would be prepared to perform a wide variety of tasks in support of the civil authorities;  their primaryrole would be likely to be helping the police to maintain law and order in circumstances which might involve a widespread breakdown of civilauthority.4.       The Territorial Army costs about  35 million a year.    TheA.rrny Emergency Reserve costs a further  3 million, making a total annual cost for the non-regular Army reserves of  38 million.    If theReserve Army were reorganised on the assumption that no units were tobe retained for home defence purposes, there would be a saving ofabout  20 million a year.5.       In addition to the Reserve Army, up to 20,000 Royal Air Forcereservists are earmarked for support of the fire service.     The needfor this commitment to continue is under separate review.     Thesereservists are also ex-national servicemen whose liability under existing legislation will expire in 1969.-I-S EC RETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

Regular Forces6.       Under present plans some personnel from the following regular forces might be available to support the civil authorities after an attack,although home defence would not be their primary role:-(a) Royal Navy.   All naval personnel not required for conduct of active operations.    The numbers available would be small.(b) Army.(i)   personnel of regular field Army units remaining in theUnited Kingdom after overseas reinforcement:  these wouldnot at present exceed 15, 000;(ii)    any personnel of static base units who could be madeavailable (present strength approximately 40,000).(c) Royal Air Force.    All personnel not required for air operations,or for the transport of forces or for communications.     The total strengthof the Royal Air Force in the United Kingdom is about l6r 000 officersand 78, 000 airmen and airwomen.7.      Although the total numbers of all three Services available mightbe substantial, any estimate must be speculative, and in any event thereare large areas of the United Kingdom, particularly the west and north,where no regular Army forces are located.    Only a small proportionof the Army personnel would, be in field force units and upon these there might be prior calls.Home Defence Review committee.       The general approach of the Committee of officials currentlyexamining home defence requirements has been that the reduced threat of attack provides scope, in the period up to 1970-71, for cutting down the existing programme, with emphasis being given to measures whichcould be expected to make a really significant contribution to nationalsurvival and to those which could be valuable in an emergency, but requirelittle or no expenditure in peace.    The Committee recognised that thereserve forces could give much valuable assistance to the civil authorities after an attack, but, on the basis of their general approach,which the Ministerial Committee subsequently endorsed, they did netconsider that the expenditure of a large annual sum on an organisation which did not appear to them to be of the first importance for nationalsurvival could be supported on home defence grounds.9.       There was considerable support for this view when the first report of the Committee of officials was recently considered by the ministerial Committee on Civil Defence.    The reduced threat of attack, particularly in Europe, and the fact that reliance is placed onthe deterrent policy for the defence of the United Kingdom, were thought to be very relevant.    If further steps were necessary for thepreservation of law and order in an emergency, the best course, itwas suggested, might be to put further emphasis on police plans and perhaps to secure the support of other regular peace-time services.It should prove possible for the Post Office to take over the work of the1,000 Territorials Allocated to signal work.8EGRET

Regular Forces6.       Under present plans some personnel from the following regular forces might be available to support the civil authorities after an attack,although home defence would not be their primary role:-(a) Royal Navy.   All naval personnel not required for conduct of active operations.    The numbers available would be small.(b) Army.(i)   personnel of regular field Army units remaining in theUnited Kingdom after overseas reinforcement:  these wouldnot at present exceed 15, 000;(ii)   any personnel of static base units who could be madeavailable (present strength approximately 40,000).(c) Royal Air Force.    All personnel not required for air operations,or for the transport of forces or for communications.    The total strengthof the Royal Air Force in the United Kingdom is about 16; 000 officersand 70, 000 airmen and airwomen.7.      Although the total numbers of ail three Services available mightbe substantial, any estimate must be speculative, and in any event thereare large areas of the United Kingdom, particularly the west and north,where no regular Army forces are located.     Only a small proportionof the Army personnel would be in field force units and upon these there might be prior calls.Home Defence Review committee.       The general approach of the Committee of officials currentlyexamining home defence requirernents has been that the reduced threat of attack provides scope, in the period up to 1970-71, for cutting down the existing programme, with emphasis being given to measures whichcould be expected to make a really significant contribution to nationalsurvival and to those which could be valuable in an emergency, but requirelittle or no expenditure in peace.     The Committee recognised that thereserve forces could give much valuable assistance to the civil authorities after an attack, but, on the basis of their general approach,which the Ministerial Committee subsequently endorsed, they did notconsider that the expenditure of a large annual sum on an organisation which did not appear to them to be of the first importance for nationalsurvival could be supported on home defence grounds.9.       There was considerable support for this view when the first report of the Committee of officials was recently considered by the ministerial Committee on Civil Defence.    The reduced threat of attack, particularly in Europe, and the fact that reliance is placed onthe deterrent policy for the defence of the United Kingdom, were thought to be very relevant.    If further steps were necessary for thepreservation of law and order in an emergency, the best course, itwas suggested, might be to put further emphasis on police plans and perhaps to secure the support of other regular peace-time services.It should prove &quot;possible for the Post Office to take over the work cf the1, 000 Territorials allocated to signal work.

10.     The Ministry of Defence support the conclusion of the HomeDefence Review Committee and have proposals under consideration for reorganising the Reserve Army for military duties overseas on theassumption that no units are retained for home defence purposes, with consequent savings of up to  20 million a year.    If it were decidedthat a home defence role for the Reserve Army must be retained, these plans would need to be completely recast, with consequent further delay in settling the future of the Reserve Army and at the cost of forgoinga substantial part of the savings which might otherwise be achieved.The primary advantages of military forces for home defence purposes,namely discipline and a cohesive organisation, would be difficult tosecure if reserve units were raised purely for assistance to the civil defence services.    Their main role would still have to be, ostensiblyat least, combat duties, although lower standards could be set for recruitment, equipment and training.    However, the Ministry ofDefence see serious objections to trying to raise a &quot;second class&quot; forceof this nature, which might adversely affect volunteering for ReserveArmy units required for purely military duties.    Furthermore, anysavings that might result would be very much less than could beachieved by dropping the home defence role.    For example, if, as hasbeen suggested, a home defence force of 40,000 men, with a warestablishment of 30, 000, were to be raised, the expected annualsavings on the Reserve Army of  20 million would reduce to about 8-10 million.     The Ministry of Defence would be unwilling to forgothe larger saving, and would wish the cost of maintaining reservistsfor home defence purposes, if required, to be met outside the defence budget.11.      But some members of the Ministerial Committee urged theretention of the Territorial Army, primarily for home defence purposes, on the ground that the possibility of preserving public order would be seriously imperilled if it were disbanded.    Existing plans for police man-power in war provide for 160,000 persons with full policepowers (regular police, special constabulary, recalled ex-police officers and cadets).    Even with the reinforcement of the 150,000soldiers in the Territorial Army, and with assistance from the regular forces of all three Armed Services (paragraph 5), the police assessthat they would be gravely short of man-power.    Without TerritorialArmy support the difficulties facing the police in an emergency wouldbe extremely grave and the possibility of preserving public ordergreatly reduced.    There appears to be little prospect of providingfrom other sources comparable reserves of active, trained anddisciplined man-power.    In all recent assessments of the measuresto be taken in the aftermath of a nuclear attack, a high priority hasbeen shown to be necessary for the maintenance of law and order,jrailure to check lawlessness and disorder would increase the like-lihood of a breakdown in public control and administration, which  /culd prejudice the distribution of food and essential resources tosurvivors and put in jeopardy the survival of the nation as an organisedentity.Conclusion12.     &quot;We were not able to resolve these issues and we accordinglya.greed to report the opposing views for a decision, which is urgently required by the &quot;Ministry of Defence to enable future requirements forreserve forces to be formulated.    The alternative courses which appear to be open are:-

(a) to accept that expenditure on the reserve forces of the Armycannot be justified solely on home defence grounds and toexamine the possibility of making other arrangements whichwould not involve the use of the Reserve Army to assist thec -lice in the event of nuclear attack on the United Kingdom(paragraphs 6 and 9);(b) to retain the home defence role of the reserve forces of theArmy, with the consequent loss of a saving of up to  20 million a year, depending cn the scale of forces to be provided(paragraph 10).F.S.Home Office, S. W. 1.28th June, 1965




</content>
</cab>
