<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 552-559</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
sfeCREIt-US DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC majesty&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(65) 87 COPY NO.     5 929th June, 1965CABINETFINANCIAL. POSITION OF THE COAL industry memorandum by the First secretary of state and secretary of State for Eccaomic AffairsThe Economic Development Committee at its meeting on28th June, 1965 discussed proposals by the Minister of Power for improving the financial position of the Goal Board;  and in particularproposals for a capital reorganisation.    It was generally agreed that action was needed;  and that in view of the atmosphere in the coalindustry it would be desirable for an announcement to be made ofGovernment action before the Conference of the National Union of mineworkers (N. U.M. ) on 6th July.    There was however comedifferences of view about the details of the action to be taken.    Inview of this and of the importance of the subject I was asked to reporton the problem to Cabinet.The coal industry&apos;s difficulties2.       Over the last few years the market for coal has contracted from220 million to about 190 nmllion tons a year and there is no doubt it is going to fail further.    If it goes down to (say) 175 million tons in 1970,about 240 pits will have to be closed.    This will involve a run down inthe labour force of about 28, 000 a year, nearly as fast as in recentyears.   There has been no general price increase for three years andthe National Coal Board are now operating at a loss: their budget for1965-66 is now showing a probable deficit in the region of  50 million.It is therefore essential to get the coal industry&apos;s financial position ona satisfactory long-term basis.The need for a capital reorganisation3.       The Coal Board have liabilities to the Exchequer of some 900 million on which they are expected to pay interest charges of over 40 million a year.4.       Of this about  90 million represents accumulated losses arisingmainly as a result of decisions in past years not to put up prices asmuch as was necessary to cover costs.    Of the remaining  800 million 150 million or so represents colliery and coke oven assets which aretoday of little or no economic value (i.e. which are actually makingcash losses or are expected to do so very soon).    A further 150 million represents assets which are of very doubtful value andare expected to become valueless in the next few years.-1-

5.       The plain fact is that after the war the Coal Board wasencouraged to invest large sums in order to expand output to220 million tons a year or more.    The decline in the market has leftthem with excess capacity and with many high cost pits which were thought to be needed to get the tonnages required.Proposals for capital reorganisation6.      Everybody is agreed that the coal industry cannot be expectedany longer to meet the capital charges on the present capital structure.7,       The Economic Development Committee agreed unanimouslythat the  90 odd million of accumulated deficits and the  150 oddmillion representing assets which are already worthless (say 250 million in total) ought to be written off immediately, at a costto the Exchequer of about  25 million a year.8.       The general view of the Committee (the Treasury reservingtheir position) was that a further  150 million, representing assets which everyone recognises will in a few years be of little or no value,should also be written off immediately, at a cost to the Exchequer ofabout another  15 million a year.9.       The Coal Board would be content to write off the  150 millionnot immediately but over the next few years provided they were relieveof interest charges on the  150 million at once (at an immediate costto the Exchequer of i.7j million).    The Committee felt that to relieve the Coal Board of interest charges on some of their capital would bean unfortunate precedent.    Since it seems inevitable that thefurther writing off will have to be made over the next few years,there would be a lot to be said for writing the full amount off atonce and getting the maximum immediate effect on relations withthe N. U. M.10.     The Treasury, on the other hand, are concerned about theadditional cost to the Exchequer of writing off the additional 150 million immediately.    If, however, it is agreed that something more should be done they prefer writing off to waiving the interest payments.Effect on prices11.      The Minister of Power told the Economic development committee that even if the whole  4-00 million were written offimmediately it would still be necessary for the Coal Board to make some price increases this autumn.    But the size of the increases would obviously be less.    Thereafter smaller price increases wouldbe needed from time to time.Subsidies and closures12.     The Economic Development Committee also discussed thepossibility of giving some specific subsidy to the Coal Board fora limited period on the condition that the Board and the N. U. M.committed themselves to a definite programme of speeding up thenecessary closures.    The subsidy might start at  10-15 million andtaper off to nothing by 1970.    The Committee was divided on the merits of this appi*oach.- 2-3EGRET

9  ti 613.     The arguments in favour are as follows -(a) It is going to be hard to get the Board and (particularly) theNational Union of Mineworkers to press ahead as fa.st as isnecessary with the closure programme.    Some additionalincentive is needed to get them committed.(b) The subsidy could be presented as a contribution to the costs of phasing the closure programme on social grounds asagainst immediate closure, which would be the reaction of privately owned industry to uneconomic pits.(c) Such a subsidy would still further reduce the need forimmediate price increases.14.     The arguments against such a scheme were -(a) It would be difficult in practice to run down the subsidies and they would indeed tend to encourage the mineworkersto press for keeping uneconomic pits open.    If this happened it would increase the Coal Board losses, andintensify pressure on the Government to continue and increase subsidies.(b) The Coal Board are strongly opposed to subsidies;  andwould be content with the capital reorganisation scheme.(c) Losses themselves are a powerful incentive to closureswhich are delayed not on social grounds but because theBoard has to consider the effect on relations with itsworker s.15.     The majority of the Committee thought nonetheless that itwoiild be worth while exploring with the Coal Board the possibilityof a scheme designed to commit the Board and the National Union of mineworkers to an accelerated closure programme.Summary16.     I ask my colleagues -(l)     To agree that a capital reorganisation of the Coal board should be undertaken.    (The necessary legislation couldbe included in a Bill which will in any case be needed inrelation to the Board&apos;s borrowing powers.)(2)    To agree that the amount to be v/ritten off should be  400million immediately.(3)    To authorise exploration with the Coal Board and theN. U. M. of a scheme under which tapering subsidies wouldbe given related to the losses of uneconomic pits and tiedto a definite scheme for speeding up closures of these pits.(4)    To agree that we should seek to keep to the minimum theincrease in coal prices this autumn.G. B.Department of Economic Affairs, 3. 7/. 1.29th June, 1965




</content>
</cab>
