<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 564-567</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
5 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)59C.(65) 89 COPY NO. _-30th June, 1965CABINETFINANCIAL POSITION OF THE COAL, industry memorandum by the Financial Secretary to the treasury have some brief comments to make on the First Secretary ofState&apos;s paper (C.(65) 87).2.       There is no difference between us over objectives, which are to relieve the Coal Board of interest charges on its capital which it cannot reasonably be expected to meet and to facilitate the early closure of uneconomic pits.3.       A write-off of  400 million means in present circumstances thatthe Chancellor has to find  40 million more in taxes in the first year.Furthermore, it would be difficult to defend   to Parliament the writing-off now of  150 million in respect of assets which will only become of little or no value in the years to come.    Nevertheless, the Chancellorprefers this to a waiver of interest and v/ould agree if the Cabinet feelfurther relief to the Coal Board is essential.4.       The question of a sxtbsidy linked to closures is quite different.In all the talks which officials have had wi h the Coal Board the latterhave been emphatic that, while capital reconstruction, is necessary, thepayment of further money cannot affect the closure programme.    Theproblems are managerial and social,5.       As the First Secretary of State states in paragraph 13(a) of his paper, the hope is that the addition would provide an incentive to theNational Union of Mineworkers.    But it is hard to see how it v/ould bepossible to get a sufficiently tight agreement to be effective.    Moreover,the cost of this rather speculative possibility (a figure of  10- 15 millionnext year has been suggested, falling to nil after four years) would fallon Votes and would make more difficult the decisions shortly to bereach on public expenditure.6.       Moreover, subsidies might prove in practice to be an actualdisincentive to closures.    They would be a very dangerous road to starton.    No-one can foresee the future demand for coal for sure and wewould find it difficult to stop the subsidies while there were stilluneconomic pits left once the subsidies had been started.    There isalso every possibility that we should be setting a precedent which couldwell be prayed in aid by other industries.    This is too open-ended a commitment to shoulder in present circumstances.: N. MacD.Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1.29th June, 1965




</content>
</cab>
