<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/121/0 images: 594-601</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9 o(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OE HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOvT^JMENT)COPY NO. &quot;CABINETCOMMONWEALTH IIIMMIGRATION:   VOLUNTARY LIAISON COMMITTEESMemorandum by the Lord President of the CouncilIn my memorandum C.(65) 90 I have set out proposals by theCommonwealth Immigration Committee for restricting the flow of commonwealth immigrants and reducing the evasion of controls, which, in the form approved,will need to be incorporated in a Yftiite Paper to be issued before the summer recess.     In addition to this, the Tfiaite Paper should announce positivemeasures for further Government action to speed up the integration of commonwealth immigrants already in this country and remove so far aspossible the social tensions to which their concentration in certain areas has given rise.2.     The Commonwealth Immigration Committee are considering proposals inthe fields of education, employment, housing and health.     Meantime we seekapproval for general proposals, designed to encourage the development orestablishment of voluntary liaison committees in each local authority area where substantial numbers of Commonwealth immigrants have settled, and tostrengthen the existing machinery at national level for dealing with theproblems arising from Commonwealth immigration.3.     Existing voluntary liaison committees, representing voluntary bodies,the local authority and the immigrant community, provide a focal point forefforts to relieve social problems and tensions.     The Committee believethat the Government should give some positive help to these liaisoncommittees quickly, as an uncontroversial and inexpensive way of showingour determination to help those local authorities with problems arising fromthe presence of large numbers of Commonwealth immigrants in their areas.4.     It is clear that there is need for a closer co-ordination of effort atthe national level.     we therefore propose that the present national committee for Commonwealth Immigrants and Commonwealth Immigrants AdvisoryCouncil should be replaced by a new National Committee.     We are consultingLady Reading, the Chairman of the Commonwealth Immigrants Advisory Council,to obtain her co-operation and that of the members of her Council, in

(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNIvIENT)C JJ5L91 COPY NO. -6th July, 1965CABINETCOMMONWEALTH IMMIGRATION:   VOLUNTARY LIAISON COMMITTEESMemorandum by the lord ^eaident^of^jtlig^ CouncilIn my memorandum C.(65) 90 I have set out proposals by theCommonwealth Immigration Committee for restricting the flow of commonwealth immigrants and reducing the evasion of controls, which, in the form approved,will need to be incorporated in a Yflaite Paper to be issued before the summer recess.     In addition to this, the YiThite Paper should announce positivemeasures for further Government action to speed up the integration of commonwealth immigrants already in this country and remove so far aspossible the social tensions to which their concentration in certain areas has given rise.2.     The Commonwealth Innigration Committee are considering proposals inthe fields of education, employment, housing and health,     Meantime we seekapproval for general proposals, designed to encourage the development orestablishment of voluntary liaison committees in each local authority area where substantial numbers of Commonwealth immigrants have settled, and tostrengthen the existing machinery at national level for dealing with the .&apos;problems arising from Commonwealth immigration.3.     Existing voluntary liaison committees, representing voluntary bodies,the local authority and the immigrant community, provide a focal point forefforts to relieve social problems and tensions.     The Committee believethat the Government should give some positive help to these liaisoncommittees quickly, as an uncontroversial and inexpensive way of showingour determination to help those local authorities with problems arising fromthe presence of large numbers of Commonwealth immigrants in their areas.4.     It is clear that there is need for a closer co-ordination of effort atthe national level.     We therefore propose that the present national committee for Commonwealth Immigrants and Commonwealth Immigrants AdvisoryCouncil should be replaced by a new National Committee.     We are consultingLady Reading, the Chairman of the Commonwealth Immigrants Advisory Council,to obtain her co-operation and that of the members of her Council, In

4* 0 6setting up the new body.    With, increased financial support, the new national Committee!s functions would be to issue advice on particular problems, provide an increased information service, promote research andstimulate and co-ordinate local effort.     It should also be able, \vherenecessary, to recruit and train staff who could be made available as fulltime paid officials for the local voluntary liaison committees, withsalaries paid from Government funds.     It would be a condition that theliaison committee was fully representative of local voluntary effort, andthat the local authority concerned was prepared to provide office accommodation and secretarial support.     In areas where existing liaisoncommittees already employed full-time staff arrangements might be made to paythem their salaries on the same conditions.     A provisional estimate of thetotal cost of this scheme is  70,000 per annum.The Cabinet1s approval for these proposals is now sought.H.B0Privy Council Office, S.W.1.6th July, 1965-2-COMFIDEEWSAL




</content>
</cab>
