<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/195/0 images: 152-154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 jDOOUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OF HIS 3RITANNI0 MAJ5STY * S GOVERNMENT). ^ORE To                                              OOPY NO. 168 (28).cabinet.ADEN POLICE FORCE.     By direction of the Prime Minister theaccompanying extract from tho Draft Minutes of  the235th Meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence is circulated to the Cabinet for consideration in  connectionwith Item 3 on tomorrow10 Cabinet Agenda.                      (Signed) M.P.A.HANKEY,                           Secretary to the Cabinet.iitehall Gardens, S.vv&apos;,1.  May 22nd, 19 28.
[This Document is the Property of  His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]    Printed for the Committee of  Imperial Defence.   May 1928.SECRET.                                                    Copy No.  28COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the DRAFT Minutes of the 235th Meeting; held on May 22, 1928.******                        (4.) ADEN  POLICE  FORCE.     THE COMMITTEE had under consideration the question of the police force in Aden.     SIR SAMUEL HOARE said that ever since the Cabinet had decided that the Air Ministry should take over the responsibility for the Aden Garrison, efforts had been made to effect the agreed reductions;  but the extraordinary inefficiency of the Aden Police Force had proved a powerful obstacle.  So long as  that state of affairs continued, it was scarcely possible to withdraw the one Imperial Battalion that remained.  The border line between police and military security was a very narrow one; and  experience in Iraq had  shown that  an  efficient  Police  Force was an essential auxiliary to air control.  If the hoped for economies were to be effected, it was necessary that this state of affairs should be remedied as  quickly as possible. The difficulty lay in the fact that this,  like many other Aden questions, was tied up between a number of  Departments.   With a view  to  putting the matter on an efficient basis,  the  Air  Ministry had  made the  proposal that  the Colonial  Office should take over the administration of the Aden Police from  the Government of India. This proposal had been put forward in no spirit of criticism of the Govern- ment of  India, but in  order to  obviate  the delay  that  was  inevitable if  that Government continued  to  manage the business.  And there was another point. The Government of India had announced their intention of recruiting for the Aden Police in India.  This arrangement would be  very expensive, and might render it impossible to effect the savings that had been anticipated.  In all the circumstances of the case, he recommended  that, as  an exceptional measure,  the Colonial Office should take over the Aden Police.     MR. AMERY agreed that early action ought to  be taken to secure an efficient Police Force in  Aden, but he was not so sure that he agreed with  Sir Samuel Hoare&apos;s estimate of the financial position.  The  India Office were the Department responsible for the civil administration of Aden, and it was therefore difficult for them to handover the responsibility  for  the Police to  the Colonial Office.  He put forward thefollowing  alternative suggestions :  Either the Police in Aden  should  be regardedas Military Police, on the score that Aden was a garrison town.   In that event india would pay one-third of the cost, and the balance would be a charge on the british exchequer. Alternatively, a part of the Police  Force in Aden might be on a militarybasis, and be employed more  on  the lines of levies, while the remainder were on a civil basis.  He asked whether the Secretary of State  for India would be preparedto entertain the idea of a Military or semi-Military Police Force  in Aden.    THE  PRIME MINISTER suggested that this very involved question might bereferred to the Oversea Defence Committee for immediate examination and report.[17706A]
    SIR SAMUEL HOARE said that various Inter-Departmental Committees hadalready considered it, but, through no fault of their own, had been unable to arriveat any decision.    LORD BIRKENHEAD said that it was too long a question to argue in thisCommittee.  Constitutional principles were involved, and he could not divest himselfof the responsibility attached&apos; to his office.    THE PRIME  MINISTER thought that in these  circumstances  the  problemought to be examined by a Cabinet Sub-Committee.                                 CONCLUSION.    The COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE agreed-        To recommend to the Cabinet that the question of the steps which should    be taken to  secure an efficient Police Force at  Aden  should be referred  to a    Cabinet Committee for examination and early report.-V-          :Sfc           -i-          -ifc           Jfe           Jfr.&quot;vv-          -JY-           vv     -     -iv           w           *2,  Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1,       May 22, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
