<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/195/0 images: 433-439</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government. JPrinted for the  Cabinet.  June 1928.SECRET.Copy No.   28CP.  198  (28).CABINET.UNEMPLOYMENT  AND  OVERSEA  SETTLEMENT.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OE  STATE FOR DOMINION  AFFAIRS.    IN view  of the  gravity of  the  unemployment situation  in  the coal  miningindustry,  I have  requested the Oversea  Settlement Committee  to  prepare theaccompanying Memorandum in order  to show how much can be done to relieve thesituation by means of oversea settlement and at what cost.  It will be seen from theMemorandum  that it should be  possible to settle overseas each year the followingnumbers drawn from the distressed mining areas, viz., 7,000 single miners, 2,500miners with their families  (say,  10,000 souls), 2,500 boys and 2,000 single women,or 21,500 souls in all, at a total net cost of  601,000, or just under  28 per head.    In addition to this, it will be necessary, in order to make the prospects overseasattractive, to incur, as from 1930, recoverable expenditure of  300,000 a year, andalso  to  incur  capital expenditure of, say,   3,000,000  for development purposes,spread over a term of years.    The total expenditure on the relief of unemployment in this country by theState,  the  local authorities, employers and employed  has been,   on an average,approximately  85,000,000 a year ever since the Armistice.  Of the  total unemployed at the present  time, about 20 per cent,  is in  the mining areas.(Confidential.)    The Industrial Transference Board have prepared certain Notes for the PrimeMinister dealing with the surplus miners in the coal mining industry.   The Notesmake it clear that the Board regard the situation as a grave one and consider theadoption of a &quot; really effective policy of oversea settlement &quot; as the best means ofdealing with it.    I quote two extracts from the Notes :     (1.)  &quot; We have already no hesitation in recording the view                (a) that the problem of surplus miners is of so grave a character as           to necessitate urgent attention and action on the part of the Government;               (b) that immediate attention  is necessary on  two  lines affecting           particularly the younger men and boys, viz. :                     (i) the extension of training and  transfer at home,  and                   (ii) the  undertaking  of a  really  effective  policy  of  oversea               settlement.&quot;    (2.)  &quot; It is our deliberate conclusion that the only plan which has the possi-           bilities of  giving  an  immediate chance  of self-dependence to large           numbers is migration to the oversea  Dominions on  a greatly increased           scale.  It is very many years since emigration for large numbers of people           from, this country has had to be regarded from the standpoint of economic           necessity, but we are compelled to draw this  inference  from the facts.  .         before us.&quot;L. S. A.Dominions Office, Downing Street,          June 20, 1928.[17834]B
     On the presumption that similar views and recommendations will be put forward in the board&apos;s Report, I have thought it advisable, in anticipation of that Report, to obtain from  the Oversea  Settlement  Committee a statement showing within what limits, and at what cost, an intensive oversea settlement policy can be used to combat permanent unemployment in the coal mining areas.  This intensive effort would, of course,  proceed pan passu with the ordinary activities of oversea  settlement work and would not affect any attempt which may be made to secure a general reduction in the third-class ocean rates.     The total  number of miners engaged  in the coal  mining industry is about 1,200,000.  Of these,  it may be estimated that about 675,000 are of an age suitable for settlement overseas, that is, between  18 and 40 years of age.  The  number of miners wholly unemployed on the 23rd April  is 160,000.  The number of men working less than full time is  450,000, equivalent  to the loss of the full  time work  of 100,000 men.  The total number of men wholly or partially unemployed is, therefore, 610,000.  Of this total it may be  assumed that about  350,000  are  between  18 and 40 years of age.     The number of miners from whom settlers can be recruited lies therefore some- where between 675,000 and 350,000, depending upon whether it is  considered that recruiting  for settlement  overseas can be successfully  undertaken  from  the whole body of miners of a suitable age, or only from those whose employment is  precariousor non-existent.     If,  therefore, about 150,000 miners could  be settled overseas,  it is. obvious that the whole problem of  the  pressure of unemployment upon the coal  areas would be completely  altered.     Intensive effort to encourage  an oversea  movement from mining areas  wouldbe incomplete if it did not encourage the movement of boys and single women.     Boys under 17, according to the  Industrial Transference Board&apos;s Notes,  form &quot;the most tragic  part of the problem, and  the  most  serious  in its ultimate consequences.&quot;   Here, again, if at least 4/5,000  boys  could  be  dealt  with, theposition of those leaving, school in the area would be pro tahto improved as the coalindustry must import some boys.     The number of single women  in receipt of the Unemployment Benefit in themining areas amounts to 13,000.  It is known, however, that this is only a portionof the total number  of such women  there who are unemployed.     It will be seen  from the above that the  number of  the mining population from whom overseas settlers, can be recruited is a very large one.  The estimates  set out below are intended to show for each category  : -     (1.) Under scheme  A, what can be attempted at once (i.e., to  be,  largely in           operation in 1929) given               (1) on the part of the miner,  readiness to settle on the land overseas;               (2) on the part of  the Dominions, readiness to  accept miners on a           largely increased scale.     (2.) Under scheme B, what can be done  in future to  develop a larger policy of           oversea settlement, given the necessary funds and the necessary readiness           on the part of the miners and the  Dominions.     Before discussing settlement  schemes it is necessary to make  certain pointsclear      (1.) There are  no  openings  for miners, as such, in  the Dominions.   Further,           the Dominions  can only  be  induced to take miners  as agricultural           labourers in any numbers if they fit in with their approved employment           or development schemes.     (2.)  The number  of openings  in Australia  for trained agricultural workers           throughout the year is  not continuously more than 250  a month, 150 a           month for  Western Australia, and 100 a month for New South  Wales.           The New  South Wales Government  will  not  accept miners,  even if           trained.     (3.)  Unmarried trained men can be taken by Canada from  the 1st March to           the  end of July  in  practically unlimited numbers,   and  unmarried           untrained, men can be taken for  Canada in considerable numbers from           the 1st March  to the middle of April, and in limited numbers from the           middle of April to the end of May.   It is to take full advantage of this           &quot;open&quot; recruiting season in Canada that the schemes set out below are           framed,
     (4.) Married men can be taken &apos;for Caiiada only^ -               (i)  if trained or possessing some agricultural experience;               (ii)  if &quot;housing accommodation oh the farms is available.     N.B. It is easier to move  families to  Australia than  to  Canada,  because         assistance to proceed to the former Dominion is not  restricted to those who         are going on to the land,  but is also available for those going into industry.     (5.) If an intensive campaign is to succeed, it will be necessary for His Majesty&apos;s           Government to provide (a) the whole cost of any training schemes, under-           taken in connection with it by a Government Department (as is at present           the case in respect of the two Ministry of Labour  Training Centres) and           not less than 75 per  cent,  of the cost  of any schemes undertaken  by           voluntary societies or  local  authorities; (b)  provide  the whole  of  the           necessary  allowance for  families during the period that the father  or           other wage-earner  is undergoing training &quot;for overseas;  (c) in certain           cases to provide the whole of the outfit and incidental expenses, as well           as  adequate provision for publicity and recruiting.     The following  estimates of costs divided into schemes -A and  B as indicated above have been discussed and agreed with the departmental  representatives on the oversea Settlement Committee of the  Treasury, the Ministry of Labour and  theMinistry of Agriculture, in so far  as these Departments are respectively concerned.                                   I.-BOYS.Scheme A.     2,500 boys can be trained and sent overseas annually.  1,000 of the boys wouldbe trained at eight  Municipal Training Centres, of  which two are in existence, one at Newcastle and one at Liverpool. - Four more at Hull, Cardiff,  Bristol and Glasgowwill soon be started.  At each  centre 150-200 boys can be trained yearly.  At someof them, e.g.,  at Hull and Glasgow, not more  than  50 per cent, of  the boys will  bedrawn  from  distressed mining areas.    At no  centres  will  the  boys be  drawnexclusively from the distressed areas, but eight or more hostels  can  easily be  in fullwork next year.     500 would  be trained  by the . Salvation  Army, 1,000  would  be  taken outuntrained, 500 of  them by voluntary organisations and 500 by the DominionAuthorities under existing schemes.     The cost under the above scheme would work out at                              11,000 for training,              5,000 for capital expenditure on new centres,           - 27,500 for passages,             10,000 for outfits and incidental  expenses  on journey,              .7,500 aftercare  overseas,*             61,000 Total.Scheme B.    The number of 2,500 boys could be easily doubled,  and probably more than doubled, in a comparatively short time.  What is required is publicity, the encourage-ment  of voluntary societies, especially those voluntary societies which themselvesarrange to conduct personally and place parties  of boys overseas,  and the increase oftraining hostels.                               II. SINGLE  MEN.Scheme A.    It should be possible each year to settle 7,000 single  miners overseas, viz., 3,000with agricultural training, 3,000 (untrained, but tested), under the quota allowed tothe Canadian railway companies,  500 directly employed  under Government schemesnow under consideration, and 500  with sufficient agricultural experience to pass  theDominion tests.    *! The provision of aftercare for boys  is of first importance, but it  is possible that with an increasingmovement of boys this charge might be reduced.       [17834]                                                       B %
    To train the first 3,000, four training centres, i.e., Claydon and Brandon andtwo new Ministry of Labour Training Centres, will be required.  These will provide accommodation and training facilities for 5,000 men, of whom 3,500 might be miners,half single and half married.  Of the 1,250 single men remaining to be trained, 400will be  trained at Municipal Training Centres during the rush period to Canada.500 will be trained in co-operation  with voluntary societies, and  350 at the WarOffice Training Centre at Chiseldon.    The testing of the 3,000 untrained men will for the most part be carried out bymeans of five weeks&apos;  courses on existing forestry operations  under the forestry commission, supervised as regards testing by the Ministry of Labour.    The cost under the above scheme  should work out at:             -          44,700  for training.          22,500  for testing.          40,000  for capital cost of new centres.         130,000  for passages (of which  29,000 will be recoverable).          21,000  for outfits and incidentals.                                    !         258,200 Total.Scheme B.    If more than 7,000 single miners were to apply for overseas settlement, a freshsource of training would have to be found.   It is suggested for this purpose that men might be trained with private farmers.  While there are very obvious difficulties,  andit is not practical to forecast with any degree of confidence the number which mightbe so  trained or, indeed, to gauge the value, of such training, it is probable that incertain districts the qualifying training might be given, provided     (1)  there is some  small payment to the farmer;    (2)  there is no displacement of existing labour;    (3)  the training fulfils the minimum requirements of the Canadian Government,          i.e.,  pToughing and milking.    So far as can be  foreseen it is possible that up to 4,000 additional men might perhaps be given training in  this way at a cost of, say,  110,000.  But  obviouslymuch will depend upon the attitude adopted by farmers on  this question.    Apart from the above, there is a good  chance, but  not any certainty,  that it maybe possible to help a number of miners to go to Canada  in  August  to wox&apos;k asharvesters, with the  prospect  of  finding  permanent work  in  the  Dominion.An arrangement of  this  kind  was made  by  the  Shipping Companies  in  1923,when about 12,000 harvesters  were recruited in this country, of whom about 9,000remained permanently overseas.   There are prospects of  a bumper harvest thisseason, and the authorities at Ottawa  have themselves suggested that the oversea settlement Committee should approach the Shipping Lines with a view to arranginga scheme. It is understood that men from the mining areas would be more acceptableas harvest workers to the Dominion Authorities than men  from other industrial centres.  I am  approaching the Shipping  Companies with  a view to arranging ascheme for taking;;over at special rates 5,000, or, if  possible, more, harvesters, ofwhom. 75 per cent, should be recruited in the mining areas.    The whole scheme should be undertaken by the Shipping Companies, withoutovert  intervention by His Majesty&apos;s Government, but it will be necessary to reimbursethe Shipping Lines for the passages of miners and others who are unable to pay thecost of their  passages and incidental expenses.   This may be roughly computed at 15 per man.   Thus, assuming that 5,000  men were recruited and that all requiredthis assistance, a sum of   75,000  would be required,  plus some provision of, say, 5,000, to safeguard the Shipping Companies against losses on rejections, misfits, &amp;&apos;c.                              &apos; III. FAMILIES.Scheme A.       :    2,500 mining families might be dealt with, viz., 1,000 under schemes for erectingcottages for farm workers in Canada and 500 under similar schemes in Australia;500 under a scheme of exploratory migration under which the bread-winner will goto Canada to work on a farm in advance of his family; 500 under arrangements for
placing families made by the Canadian Railway Companies and other Governmentschemes.    The training of these 2,500 heads of families could be carried on as follows :1,750 at the Ministry of Labour Training Centres, 500 at the War Office Centre atChiseldon and 250 by the Salvation Army.  The cost would approximately be :         130,000 for housing schemes.          68,000 for training and subsistence.        130,000 for passages ( 7,500 recoverable) (including allowance for return                    fares for &quot;exploratory migrants&quot;).          31,000 for outfit and incidentals.        359,000    Total.Scheme B.    The Canadian Government have a Pioneer Settlement Scheme under considera-tion, which aims at securing and placing a thousand miners a year, at a cost of  300(repayable) per family to the Home Government.    It is probable that considerable developments will be made under cottage schemes in Canada.  The Federal Government have expressed themselves ready to co-operate,there is hope  for action on the part of some of  the Provincial Governments, and negotiations are well advanced with certain voluntary societies.  Cottage scheme shave the advantage that, once erected, the cottage serves as a training place for morethan one  family, e.g.,  under a scheme  now being considered  with  the  ScottishImmigrant Aid Society, it is proposed to contribute one-half the cost of the cottage( 100), in return for a  guarantee  by the Society that the cottage will be kept in astate of repair for 20 years,  and during that period used as a  training place for notless than 10 families.                            IV. SINGLE WOMEN.    2,000 women could be recruited, trained and sent overseas annually at a cost of 59,600, viz. :-                            22,000 for training.            34,000 for passages.              3,600 for outfits  and incidentals.             59,600  Total.    Recruiting  can  be  carried  out by  Voluntary, and  Religious Associationsco-ordinated  under the  Women&apos;s Branch of the  Oversea Settlement  Committeeworking in co-operation with the Ministry of Labour.    Training can be carried out by Day Centres under  Ministry of Labour orResidential Centres  under the Oversea  Settlement Department, and (to  a smallextent) educational institutions.                                  PART II.    Part I has dealt with the machinery and  cost of training, moving and settlingminers in the Dominions.    Part II suggests Schemes for inducing     (a) the miners to settle overseas;    (b) the Dominions to accept miners at the rate of 10,000 per annum to begin          with, and at a higher figure if the initial schemes are successful.    Two things appear certain, viz., that unless there is a background of land settle-ment behind the schemes set out in Part I, there will be a grave danger of opposition.in the Dominions, and,  unless the miners see a chance of permanently improving their positions, they are not likely to agree to exchange  the certainty of the &quot; dole &quot;and the possibility of a return to high wages at home, should mining conditions.improve, for agricultural wages overseas.
    Australia. Those who go to Australia will, for the most part, be settled underthe Australian Loan Agreement.  There is reason to believe that in the near future the Chairman of the Development and Migration Commission will submit schemes          (a) for developing and settling a new wheat area in Western Australia;         (b) for irrigation;         (c) for housing.    At the present time no expenditure for land settlement outside the agreement is contemplated in Australia.             .    In Canada, where the majority of the miner settlers will find their home, it issuggested that  a scheme or  schemes should be  considered  in conjunction with theFederal or the  individual Provincial Governments for the development of whollyor partly undeveloped areas on the general lines of the Australian Loan Agreement,with these important differences :     (1.) Money advanced by the British Government  for development should be           repayable.                      -    (2.) British labour should be used for development work in  proportion to the           amount of capital subscribed.                        -    (3.) Land should be reserved for British settlers either free or at  prairie value,           i.e., pre-development land prices.    It is impossible to  define exactly either the form or the cost of a land settlementscheme or schemes in Canada at this stage;  It must  be pointed out,  however, thatthe Oversea Settlement Committee is already committed to  1,500,000 of irrecover-able expenditure under the  Australian Loan  Scheme, and to nearly  1,000,000recoverable under the land settlement schemes in Canada, and it is doubtful whethera thousand miners have been settled under both these schemes taken together.    It is  calculated that  a sum only slightly in  excess of these  two figures taken together should meet the primary development costs of the block of land required forthe first six years of^settlement under Scheme A.    Peace River  District. One of the most promising areas for a land settlement and development scheme  worked in  conjunction with the Federal  or provincial government is  in the  Peace River District in the Province of Alberta.  In this district there is a block of 40,000,000 acres of land,  mostly unalienated by the Stateand, except on the Southern  boundary, almost wholly undeveloped.   This areacontains large tracts of land of a very high fertility, with a climate tempered in winter by the Chinook wind,  and eminently suited to settlers from this country.    The Province is well  disposed to a co-operative scheme of development.    Land Settlement Loan. It is further suggested that  adult settlers, married orunmarried, should be promised by the British Government a loan of   100 towardsestablishing themselves upon the land after.they have worked not less than twoyears for wages and have themselves saved,a similar sum.-  &apos;  Following the lines and safeguards of  a scheme for  Boy settlement-arranged between the Canadian  and British Governments in 1927, the number of such grantsmight  be limited to, say, 3,000 in any one year, that  is a  maximum yearly commit-ment of  300,000 beginning in 1930.  It is improbable that more than one-third oreven one-fourth of the miners will avail themselves of  this  land settlement loan, andthe yearly outlay should, in practice,  be lower than  300,000.  It is  possible that,as in the boys&apos; scheme, the Dominion  Government may  make some  contribution.In any case, it will no  doubt be willing to use its large and efficient land settlementstaff to administer the scheme.    It  would hardly be  possible for His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to confine the proposed bonus to miners, nor would such a proposalcommend  itself to the Dominion  Authorities.   Administratively,  however,  muchmight  be done to restrict the bonus to the distressed mining areas by  concentratingupon those areas in the recruiting campaign.
SUMMARY.Cost of Proposed Schemes in Part I for the Oversea Settlement of Miners.-	Housing Scheme.	Training and Testing.	Passages.	Incidentals.	Total.2,500 boys 7,000 single men 2,500 families 2,000 single women . Recoverable Harvesters for Canada (5,000 men)	  130,000	  16,000 107,200 68,000 22,000	  27,500 130,000 130,000 34,000	  17,500 21,000 31,000 3,600	  61.000 258,200 359,000 59.600	130,000 100,000	213,200	321,500 36,500	73,100	737,800 136,500	30,000	213,200	285,000	. 73,100	601,300 80,000					681,000    It will be seen that under the above schemes (Scheme A) the cost for training,passage and  incidentals is approximately  24  for a boy,  37 for a single man, 142 for families (averaging four souls) and  30 for single women.    Under Scheme B the cost for boys, men and single women would be rather less,but for families, if provision for the Canadian Pioneer Scheme is included, the cost would be about  150 above the figure given above.                       Cost of Proposals under Part II.    The cost of the proposals under Part II, to provide for the movement covered inScheme A,  should  amount  to  300,000 Na year (recoverable), the first paymentcommencing in 1930,  together with a  capital  sum of,  say,   3,000,000 for  landdevelopment spread over a period of years.o

</content>
</cab>
