<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/128/0 images: 223-226</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)(this c(67) 24 COPY NO,      15 010th March, 1967CABINETFAMILY endowment memorandum by the Minister of Social security in his memorandum (C(67) 23) the Chancellor of the Exchequerproposes that a final decision to increase family allowances should be deferred until the results of the special review of public sector expenditure will be available.The proposal in my memorandum C(67) 7 was for a family allowance increase to operate from April. 1968 associated with areduction of income tax child allowance designed to ensure that thebenefit of the increase was concentrated on families below thestandard-rate tax level.     This was approved in principle by theCabinet on 23rd February (CC(67) 9th Conclusions, Minute 4) and theChancellor of the Exchequer, the Minister without Portfolio and I were invited to arrange for a more detailed examination of the implications.If further action is now to be suspended until midsummer or perhaps until the autumn, when as indicated in the last paragraph ofC(67) 23 we can expect to see the pattern of 1968-69 precisely, allprospect of getting the scheme into operation by April, 1968 will be lost.    While there would be no difficulty about a simple increase in family allowances (which could if necessary be put into effect within three months of a firm decision), the associated tax adjustments, andany changes in the family allowances and tax systems necessary tobring them more closely into line, raise a number of detailedproblems calling for careful examination by my Department and theDepartment of Inland Revenue and probably further decisions by ministers.    I understand that the Inland Revenue Department has to begiven some weeks for the preparation and issue of firm instructions to staff on any changes in the amounts of, or conditions for, tax allowancesbefore the annual recoding begins in the autumn.     Legislation will haveto be drafted for introduction early in the new session.     This makes it essential to take firm decisions not merely on the principle but on allthe details of the scheme, as well as to complete consultations withthe Trades Union Congress (TUC) and the Confederation of BritishIndustry (CBI), by July at the latest.
4.     Attention has been concentrated on child poverty for a long timenow.    Informed opinion is seriously (and rightly) concerned about it,and we have given repeated assurances that it is receiving urgent consideration.    We have already announced that half a million children are living below the supplementary benefit level, and the results of theofficial survey will be published in June showing this and also showing that there are many more children living not far above that level.At about the same time we shall be announcing general increases in social security benefits to take effect in the autumn.    We shall at that point undoubtedly be heavily criticised if we are proposing to do nothing about family endowment until April, 1968, and I remain strongly of the view that we ought then to announce an interim increase in family allowances to come into force in the autumn and to be subsumed in thegive-and-take scheme in April, 1968.    If we were to ha.ve no such plan to announce, criticism would intensify to an intolerable extent, even if no changes were made in the charges for school meals and welfare milk.5.     It is true, as the Chancellor says, that a give-and-take scheme with a 10/- increase in family allowances would entail additional expenditure of  160 million, but I would reiterate my belief that therealistic approach is to look at tax allowances and family allowancestogether and not separately.    (This was the approach with regard toinvestment allowances and investment grants. )   We specificallypromised in our election manifesto to &quot;seek ways of integrating more fully the two quite different systems of social payment - tax allowances and cash benefits paid under National Insurance&quot;.    Both tax allowances and family allowances are intended to give help to families  with children as against those without.     Together they are complementary,providing a flexible means of deciding how such help should be given.6.     I really cannot see that an arrangement which leaves the familyof the standard rate tax payer with virtually the same income as beforehas in any way diminished his taxable capacity;   and to the extent thatfamilies below the standard rate range are receiving improved family allowances, their taxable  capacity has, prima facie, increased.What we are in effect doing is using the built-in incomes test of theincome tax system to direct help to those families who need it.     Thenet effect of the 10/- scheme is to concentrate the help on approximately2 million lower-paid families with two or more children - in particular,to give the full benefit of the increase to those of the 160,000 familiesbelow the supplementary benefit level who have two or more children,and to the many other families who are not far above that level(300, 000 families are above that level but less than  3 above it) andwho will still be outside the taxpaying range after a give-and-takescheme has been introduced.7.      The Chancellor says that when the time comes to take adecision on family endowment the Cabinet should face the whole issueof income testing.     This I understand to refer to a direct income test,against which the Cabinet decided on 23rd February.    I would againremind my colleagues of the strong practical objections to such a testfor a benefit paid to families where the father is in full-time work - inparticular, the resentment if would cause and the disincentive effectit would have,    I set out these objections fully in C(66) 183, and my views have been subsequently reinforced by the strong opposition toincome testing expressed to me by the TUC.-2-
8.      In view of the necessity to reach an early conclusion if a give-and-take scheme is to operate in April, 1968, I would urge mycolleagues to confirm their decision of 23rd February in favour of theprinciple of my proposals, and to authorise the working-out of detailsby the Departments concerned.M.H,Ministry of Social Security, W. Cc 2.9th March, 1967-3-CON FIDE NTS AL


</content>
</cab>
