<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/128/0 images: 291-294</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
l0cUMENT is THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT)C(67) 2813th March, 1967COPY NO.06CABINETHOUSING: PUBLIC AUTHORITY HOUSING PROGRAMME 1967ENGLAND AND wales memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer as the Minister of Housing and Local Government and theSecretary of State for Wales have pointed out in C(67) 25, I do not feel able to accept that any immediate increase should be authorised in thetotal of public authority housing approvals for 1967.2.      The present authorised programme has already produced asubstantial increase since 1964 in Public Sector house building.    It also provides for a continuing increase year by year both in the number ofhouses completed and in the volume of housing work under construction.It is designed to provide about half of the target of 500, 000 houses in1970 and it is not running behind schedule.3.     Unfortunately the increase in the Public Sector has so far been largely offset by the fall in private housing.    But the Private Sector is beginning to pick up.    In October last, the speculative builders forecastthat they would start building only 179,000 houses in Great Britain in1967; in January, they forecast 204, 000.    Since then I have announced the easing of credit restrictions J  and the Building Societies are now ina position to step up their mortgage lending.4.      The probable speed and scale of the expansion in private housebuilding is difficult to estimate and current forecasts of likely performancein 1968 are bound to be tentative.    But the Official Committee on Housingestimate that, if allowance is also made for the planned increase in thePublic Sector, total completions should rise by 5-15, 000 this year and bya further 25-30,000 in 1968.    This would give a United Kingdom totalof between 427, 000 and 442, 000 houses completed in 1968.    The detailed figures are given in an Annex to this note.5.      When we authorised the local authorities1 programme for 1966,we recognised that this was going above the target that we had setourselves, and this was accepted as a means of boosting the programme for the time being.    This we have succeeded in doing.    To have 155, 000as the programme for 1967 is merely to return to the course which was originally agreed.    I recognise that it may mean that some localauthorities will not be able to build as many houses as they would be physically capable of building.    But this condition is not peculiar tothe housing programme;  and any claim for housing must be considered
against the other pressing demands for public expenditure for other programmes.    The purpose of the current review of public expenditure is to enable us to do this and to reconsider priorities over the next fewyears, with the aim of reducing civil public expenditure by 200- 300 million.below the basic programme for 1970-71.    One of the major points for discussion in that review will be the present target of500, 000 housess and in my view it would be quite wrong to anticipate the decision on that point by adding to the housing programme now.6.      In the shorter term, the proposal of 7, 000 additional approvalswould add about  9 million to the high level of public expenditure inthe current year.    It would also add some  11.4 million in 1968-69,and I must warn my colleagues that all the indications are that, becauseof the sharp increase in total expenditure which is entailed by our existing policies, we shall shortly have to consider seriously theproblem of limiting the increase in public expenditure in that year.7.      I must therefore ask my colleagues not to authorise any increase in the Public Sector housing programme in advance of thecurrent review of public expenditure.L. J. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,13th March, 1967-2-
ANNEXAPPROVALS (ENGLAND AND WALES)				Local Authorities	New Towns	Total1964 Actual	139,500	5, 000	144,5001965      &quot;	152,700	8,400	161,1001966	163,900	5, 520	169,4201966 Authorised	161, 000	8, 700	169,7001967          &quot;	155,000	10, 500	165, 5001968          &quot;	162,500	11,200	173, 7001969	170,000	10, 950	180,9501970         &quot;	170,000	10, 000	180, 000The authorised total shown for 1966 includes the extra 11, 000which were approved in April (3, 500) and July (7, 500) of that year.A further 2, 900 were issued on the local authority side to offset the short-fall of a similar amount on New Towns.COMPLETIONSThousands1964   1965   1966 1967        1968       1969- actual - - forecast  -Great Britain -Public 156     168     180 186 210 220Private 218     214     205       205-215   205-220      ?TOTAL	374	382	385	391-401	415-430	?Northern Ireland	10	9	11	.    (11)	(12)	(12)TOTAL UK	384	391	396	402-412	427-442	?Addition now proposed (England and Wales					1.75	5.25


</content>
</cab>
