<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/128/0 images: 612-615</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property ofher britannic majestvs governmentPrinted for the Cabinet. April 1967C (67) 45 Copy No.  6 87th April, 1967CABINETPARLIAMENTARY PROCEDUREMemorandum by the Lord President of the council the Ministerial Committee on Parliamentary Procedure have considered the First, Second, and Fourth Reports of the SelectCommittee on Procedure and I now seek the agreement of theCabinet to the recommendations of the Ministerial Committee that:(1) The proposal of the Fourth Report of the Select Committeeon Procedure for an experiment in voluntary timetablingof the Finance Bill, backed by a new Sessional Order,should be adopted (paragraphs 2-3).(2) The Speaker should be authorised by resolution of the House,to set, at his discretion, a maximum length for anyspeeches at any stage of any debate (paragraphs 4-5).(3) The proposal in the Select Committee&apos;s Second Report forshortening the period of notice of the subjects of private members&apos; Motions should be accepted, but decisions onthe other proposals in that Report relating to urgent andtopical debates should be deferred until the SelectCommittee have completed their work (paragraphs 6-7).Finance Bill Procedure2. In their Fourth Report of this session the Select Committeeon Procedure discussed three possible changes in the handling of theCommittee stage of the Finance Bill (a) committing the whole Billto a Standing Committee, (b) dividing it between a StandingCommittee and Committee of the whole House, and (c) keeping theCommittee stage on the floor of the House but applying a voluntarytimetable to it. There were advocates within the Committee of eachof the first two changes but the Committee plainly doubted whethereither would commend general support in the House. On (c) theywent on to say, however:&quot; Both those Members who favour sending all or part ofthe Bill to a Standing Committee and those who believe thatno change should be made are . . . prepared to support an experiment in voluntary timetables for proceedings in the house and requiring a new Sessional Order . . .&quot; (i.e., an Order to7791
allow Ministers to move a Resolution which could be debatedfor a short time setting up a Business Committee of the typeprovided for in Standing Order 43 with power to determine the number of days to be allotted to the Bill and its further stages and the allocation of time within the overall total).3. The Ministerial Committee on Parliamentary Procedurewere agreed that this proposal for a voluntary timetable should beaccepted on an experimental basis and without prejudice to more radical changes in the future. It would make for greater certaintyin the Finance Bill timetable, should avoid late night sittings, and could provide a precedent for the subsequent introduction oftimetabling for all Bills. The proposed new Sessional Order, thoughit would enable the Government fully to protect its position if agreement on a timetable through the usual channels could not beobtained, would be more likely to be used (if it had to be used atall) in circumstances when such an agreement, having been obtained,subsequently broke down.Length of speeches4. The Select Committee&apos;s First Report of this session included a recommendation that speeches by back-benchers be limited to 15minutes, and that front-bench speakers be invited by resolution ofthe House to limit themselves to half an hour. In the debate on procedure on 14th December, 1966, I said that we proposed toconsider this further in the context of the report on SO 9.5. The Ministerial Committee were opposed to this proposal on the ground that it would appear to create first-class and second-class Members and that it could be unfair to the back-bencherwho was leading the attack, for example, on an opposed Private bill or on a particularly contentious Order. Instead, the ministerial committee recommend an experiment whereby the Speaker shouldbe authorised by a resolution of the House to declare, at any time inany debate, that he intended to limit all speeches to a specified lengthduring a period also specified by him. It would be open to himto extend the time in any individual case if a Member was undulyinterrupted. I understand that the Speaker would be willing to operate such an arrangement.Urgent and topical debates6. The main recommendations in the Select Committee&apos;second Report of this session are:(1) Relaxation of the operation of Standing Order 9(a) Motions to adjourn the House for which leave is given under this order should be debatable, at the Speakersdiscretion, at the beginning of business on thefollowing day.(b) The Speaker should be freed from following precedent,and required to give no reason, in admitting orrefusing debates under SO 9.
(c) The rules for debates under SO 9 should be relaxed,e.g., so that they may include reference to mattersexcluded by the rules of adjournment debates, andany matters which could be brought within the scopeof Ministerial action.(2) Opposition opportunities for urgent debatesThe Opposition should be able to take up to four halfdays on urgent debates with a limit of one such debate ina calendar month; these days would be drawn from their29 Supply days.(3) Private Members&apos; time(a) There should be a shorter interval between the choice of Private Members&apos; subjects and debate (the presentintervals average 16 days).(b) Friday morning sittings should run from 10 a.m. to5 p.m. to allow two debates.(c) Monday evening debates on topical subjects selected bythe Speaker should run for two hours (instead of half an hour).7. The Ministerial Committee recommend that, apart from theproposal to shorten the period of notice of the subject of private members&apos; Motions, a decision on the proposals outlined in thepreceding paragraph 6 should be deferred until the Select Committeehave completed their work and a balance can be struck betweenchanges which would work to the benefit of Government and opposition respectively.R. H. S. C.Privy Council Office, S.W.1,5 th April, 1967.


</content>
</cab>
