<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/161/0 images: 199-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CIRCULATED TO THF CABTNF.T.Os^The Marquess  Curzon  of Kedleston to theMarquess of&apos; Crewe&apos; (Paris).FOREIGN OFFICE.July 10th. 1923.My Lord,     The French Ambassador has just left me after a con-versation of a very amicable character.   He came not,as it appears, to protest in the smallest degree againstthe line of action of His Majesty1s Government which Iindicated to him the other day,  hut rather to find outexactly what is contemplated, and to. give me M.Poincare&apos;views with&apos;regard to it.   He expressed the hope thatthe statement to he made in both Houses of parliament on Thursday would be of a generous character towardsFrance, and would not in any way give encouragement to berlin.&apos;     I said that I hoped it would satisfy this defini-tion, because the main object of the statement was toindicate that His Majesty1s Government had definiteviews on the matter, that they could not any longerforbear from making a public statement of them, and indeed that they hoped to continue in close agreementwith the whole of their allies,  although if this were found to be impossible, they would be compelled tostate&apos; and to strike out a line of their own.-     We then proceeded to the next step,* and here Iindicated with absolute precision that our intention was to submit a draft reply to the last German note.Somewhat to my surprise, the Ambassador no longercontested the feasibility,  or even the desirability,of sending such a reply.   The only point upon whichhe insisted was that the initiative in sending itcould
could not possibly be taken by the French government,  aniM. Poincare would absolutely decline, in the present state of affairs, to take the initiative in a discussionwith Berlin.   But if we submitted our ideas of  whatthe reply should be, which he understood was our proposal, M. Poincare would not refuse to join in the reply, provided that it was one that was acceptable to French policy and to French opinion.   On the otherhand if he was unable to join, he would not havecompromised himself.     Though the Ambassador somewhat glossed over thispart of his remarks, I cannot help recording my  viewthat it marked a considerable advance on anything which he has been previously authorised to say to me.In reply to his.question how long would be requiredfor the preparation of this note, I said that it was difficult at the present stage to answer,  but I  hopedthat it might be possible to formulate it in a week to ten days after the statement in Parliament onThursday.     The Ambassador enquired particularly whetherthe latter statement would contain any forecast  of whatthe contents of the proposed note would be.    I  saidthat I could hardly reply definitely, because we were still engaged in the Foreign Office on the preparationof the Thursday text, but my general desire would beto avoid anticipating anything that would moreproperly belong to the note,
      I  then  told the Ambassador, what I think I had not indicated to him at  our previous interview, that inasmuch as  the  question at issue was one that Was not merely raised  by the German Note, or that related to the German side  of the  question, but was a question, - I was speak- ing of  the whole Reparations issue, and that of the inter Allied  debts - which concerned the Allies primarily and directly, and in some cases did not touch the Germans at  all,  we should at the same time consider it our duty to  address to the French government a reply to the com- munication,  or aide-memoire, or note verbale, or what- ever  it ought to be  called, of June 14th, which the Ambassador had handed to me at our last meetings      At this point I said that I was at a loss to under- stand why so much fuss was made of the degree of secresy which ought  to be attached to it.  The Ambassador had, at  our  last meeting, wrapped it up, so to speak in a covering as  though it were a secret and unquotable thing. He  had  particularly  requested me not to reveal in public that  I  had received  it, and yet the very next day I read  in all  the French newspapers that this very communi- cation, dated June 14th, had, by the orders of monsieur poincare, been handed to me by him.  These nuances, and formalities  I was quite at a loss to understand.
     The Ambassador frankly admitted theirabsurdity and allowed that the case had been altered by the revelations made at Paris.     Anyhow, I went on to say, we should address a formal Note to the French Government in replyto the points that were made in that communi-cation, and we should take advantage of theopportunity to put before, not the French alone,but the whole of our Allies, our views upon thelarger issues that were raised, and that could nolonger be indefinitely postponed.     At this stage His Excellency intervenedto give me an answer to a question that I hadhinted at,  rather than put,  on a previous occasion,  namely, whether the French government regarded the question of future security as being raised by the present issue, or whether they had any wishes, or ideas, to present to us on thepoint.                                    I i QIC Q * * * a 9 4
     Here,  reading from a Blip of paper, which was obviously a communication from fl/LPoincard, he saiddefinitely that the French government did not regard the question of the Ruhr as in any way bound up withthat of security.   They had not raised, and theydid not now desire to raise that, question.   their occupation of the Ruhr was designed for economic pur-poses solely, and had no relation to the question of security for France, which was dealt with and defined by the clauses of the treaty relating to that problem,      While accepting this explanation, I went on tosay that he must not think that we would at any time be Indisposed to discuss the matter if the Frenchgovernment desired to put it forward.   I had onlyrefrained from doing so because it seemed to mesomewhat invidious to suggest to the greatest millitary power In Europe that her frontiers required some additional defence to that which her own armies couldprovider,   His Excellency said that no  danger could arise from the German side for many years.      The Ambassador then went on to say that the dis-cussions on  the Pact last year had really broken downbecause we had refrained from returning a reply to thelatest full  communication that we had received fromM.Poincare*&apos; on the subject,,      I disputed the historical accuracy  of this state-merit, and remarked that the discussions had been de-slsted from, partly because neither party appeared tolike the Pact In the form in which it had been proposed                                                 at
at Cannes, partly because1 It was held by us, and was originally held by M.poincare  himselfj that it wouldnot be desirable to pursue the matter until the groundhad been cleared of all the various points of difference between Prance and Great Britain, and partly because we gathered from the organs of public opinionthat the French government had ceased to attach value to the project.      I added further that, should the French . govern-ment at any time in the future desire to bring their &apos;views to us on the question of security^ we should beglad to consider them in a friendly spirit,      The conversation ended as it began, in a veryamicable way, and I drew from it the conclusion thatthe French government are beginning to be a littlenervous about the possibilities of a separation fromourselves.                     (Signed) CURZON OF KEDLESTON.

</content>
</cab>
