<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/161/0 images: 475-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This l)ocument is  the Property of His BHbnnic Maje$ty&apos;s Goveramentr]- -                  Printed for the Cabinet.  July  1923.SECRET.C.P.-346 (23).a 9 5 (TSCABINET.SUB-COMMITTEE  OF THE  COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL  DEFENCE ON                NATIONAL  AND IMPERIAL DEFENCE.                    CO-ORDINATION OF THE DEFENCE FORCES.                       Memorandum by  the Chairman.     ALTHOUGH the Committee on National and Imperial  Defence has reached the final stages of its enquiry, I regret that we shall not be able to present the final Report to the Cabinet before the Recess, owing to the heavy demand made by other urgent questions on the time of my colleagues and myself.     2. The Cabinet have already taken decisions on Interim Reports and Resolutions submitted by the Committee in regard to         The strength of the Royal Air Force for Home Defence,        The Relations of the Army and the Air Force, and  I am  submitting to my colleagues,  in a separate Memorandum, the Committees recommendations on the Relations of the Navy and the Air Force in regard to Fleet Air  work.     3. There is one other question of great public interest which was included in the Committee&apos;s Terms of Reference, and on which it is possible that my colleagues will think that a statement should be made before Parliament rises.   I refer to the Co-ordination of the Defence Departments.     4.  A large part of our enquiry has been devoted to this question in regard to which  we  obtained   Memoranda from the  following  authorities  outside the Government Service:             Lord Middleton.            Lord Haldane.            Major-General Seely.            Sir Eric Geddes..            Field-Marshal Sir William Robertson.            Lieutenant-General Sir Aylmer Hunter-Weston.   -            Major-General Sir  John Davidson.            Major-General Sir  Frederick Sykes.We also discussed  the question  very fully with the Chiefs of Staff  of  the  three fighting Services.&apos;   5. :The Committee&apos;s recommendations, which I submit to the Cabinet on  their behalf,  are as follows:      . ,!l    (1.) It is undesirable and impracticable to supersede the Ministerial heads of the          three Fighting Services by making them  subordinates of a Minister  of          Defence; the alternative plan for an amalgamation of the three Service          Departments is equally impracticable.                  ;    (2.) On the other hand, the existing system of co-ordination by the Committee of          Imperial Defence is not sivfncient to secure full initiative  and responsi-          bility for defence as a whole  and requires to be defined and strengthened.      [10400]  1^ (0 Q tl.^^    a!  &apos;;             &quot;&apos; &apos;;  5&quot;&apos;r
 (3.) Under the existing system the Committee of Imperial Defence, an advisory       and consultative body,  enquires  into and  makes  recommendations in       regard to the issues of defence policy and organisation which are brought       before it.  The power of initiative lies with the Government Departments       and with the Prime Minister. (4.) Thtssystem,  though invaluable up to a point, does not make any authority,       except the Prime Minister,  who can only devote a small part of his time       and attention to defence questions, directly responsible for the initiation       of a consistent line of policy directing the common action of the three or       any two of the three Services, taking account of the reactions of the three       Services upon one another. (5.) While,  therefore, the existing system  of departmental initiative should       continue, the responsibility  for the wider initiative referred to above in       conclusion (4) should  also rest  with the Chairman of the^Committee of       Imperial Defence acting under  the general direction of the Committee of       Imperial Defence and with  the assistance of the three Chiefs of Staff. (6.) In accordance with the terms of the Treasury Minute of the 4th May,  1904,       constituting the Committee  of Imperial Defence in its present form, the       Committee of  Imperial Defence should continue to consist of the Prime       Minister, as President, with such other members as, having regard, to the       nature of the subject to be discussed,  he may from  time to time summon       to  assist him.  &apos; In pursuance of a  decision  by the Prime Minister, the       Committee places on record that the following should be members:            The Chairman (Deputy to the Prime Minister).           The Secretary of  State  for War.           The Secretary of  State  for  Air.           Tile Pirst Lord of the Admiralty.           The Chancellor of the Exchequer,  or the Financial Secretary.           The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.           The Secretary of State for  the  Colonies.           The Secretary of  State  for India.           The Chiefs of Staff of the three Fighting Services.           The Permanent Secretary  of  the  Treasury as  head of the  Civil:               Service.       Other British or Dominion Ministers of the Crown and other officials, or       persons having special  qualifications, will be summoned by the.President       according to the nature of the business.(7.) The  functions  of the Chairman of  the  Committee of  Imperial  Defence       should be:        (i.) To  preside over the Committee of Imperial Defence in  the absence             of the Prime Minister.       (ii.) To  report to the Prime  Minister (when he himself has not presided)             and to  the  Cabinet  the  recommendations of  the Committee  of             Imperial Defence.       (iii.) In  matters of  detail,  to  interpret the  decisions of  the Prime             Minister and the Cabinet thereupon to the Departments,concerned.       (iv.) Assisted by the three Chiefs of Staff, as laid down in conclusion (5)             above, to keep the defence situation as a whole  constantly under             review so as to  ensure that defence preparations and plans and             the expenditure thereupon, are  co-ordinated and framed to  meet             policy, that  full information as to the changing naval, military             and air situation may always  be available to the Committee  of             Imperial Defence and that resolutions  as to the  requisite action             thereupon may be submitted  for its consideration.(8.) It should be  laid down that, in addition to the function of the Chiefs  oi       Staff as  advisers on questions of sea,  land or  air policy respectively,  to       their own Board or Council,  each of the three Chiefs of Staff should  have       an  individual and collective  responsibility for advising on defence policy       as a whole, the three constituting, as it  were, a Super-Chief of a  War       Staff in  Commission.   In carrying out this  function they should  meet      together  for   the  discussion  of  questions  which  affect  their  joint      responsibilities.
 (9.) Questions relating to co-ordination of expenditure may be entertained by       the Committee of Imperial Defence when  referred to it by the Cabinet.       The Committee (subject to any directions by the Cabinet) should consider       such questions in the light of the general  defence policy of the Govern-       ment and of the strategical plans drawn up to give effect to that policy       in time of war.(10.) The Secretariat of the Committee  of Imperial Defence should continue to ,       act as  liaison officers between  the Chairman of the Committee and the       Service Departments.   The staff of the Committee should be strengthened.       by the  addition of an Assistant Secretary  to be nominated by the Prime       Minister on the recommendation  of the Secretary of State for Air, whose       status  will  be identical  with  that  of the  three  existing Assistant       Secretaries nominated by the Prime Minister on the recommendation of       the Secretary of State for  War, the Secretary of State for India and the       First Lord of the Admiralty.(11.) The Standing Defence Sub-Committee  should  be suppressed and its past       proceedings should be  merged  into those of  the Committee of Imperial       Defence.                                                      (Initialled)       S. 2,  Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,        July 27, 1923.&apos;

</content>
</cab>
