<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/161/0 images: 753-765</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS D0OUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S ^9                    GOVERNMENT,                           0 &quot;3 ^                           CABINET.        RETRENCHMENT  OF  LEAGUE OP NATIONS SZPENDIOJURB.           /&apos; O,72(23),   *-&quot;*    MEMORANDUM  BY  THE FINANCIAL SECRETARY TO THE  TREASURY.     1.  The League of Nations came into being on 10th January,1920, but its first year of full activity was 1921.   its expenditure has been                 1921         1922         1923       1924               Expenditure. Expenditure.  Budget.   Budget.                                                        Secretariat and Special    492,500       403,000      604,000   529,000* OrganisationsPermanent Oourt of Intermation- al Justice.     13,500        51,000       75,000    78,000International Labour Organi- sation         880,000        71,000      328,000   887,000Washington Conference       1,000forking Oapital Fund               -            -          80.000   101.000   TOTAL        787,000       725,000    1,087,000   995,000           The British contribution being roughly 10ft of thewhole, it will be seen that the league is oosting this countrysome  100,000 a year.  Moreover, owing to default in payment by certain countries of their contributions, a deficiency occurswhioh has to be made up by extra payments nominally recoverablefrom the sound States.   Contributions amounting to 2,556,000francs remain unpair for the years 1921 and 1922.           The British Empire, as a whole, pays about one-quarter of the total expenses and there have been Indications
 that certain of the Dominions have grown restive at the - size of their contributions.          The expenditure of the League until recently has shown a marked tendency towards expansion and, while effortshave been made towards economy in the last few months, theyhave been markedly inferior to the reductions effected inthe national budgets of Great Britain and some othercountries,     2.    There are certain functions which the League hasto perform under the Peace Treaties, e.g. in connectionwith Mandates.  There are, in addition, many practical tasks which the League is exceptionally qualified to undertake,e.g. the restoration of Austrian finances.  But there remainsa considerable volume of optional expenditure on matterslike the elaboration of international statistics and roving-enquiries of an abstract character.   Much money can be wasted on international enquiries precisely because theyare international ana involve expenditure on travelling,translation, etc., which no individual -country would undertake.          The attention of the British Government has forsome time been particularly directed to the cost of theInternational Labour Organisation and in paragraphs 3 and4 below a brief aocount is given of what has been effected in the direction of economy and what it is suggested canbe done further.   It is believed that, with sufficientpressure, the expenditure of this organisation couldwithout sacrifice of efficiency be reduced to  800,000by 1925.
           But there is no reason why Great  Britain  should confine her efforts towards economy to the  ease  of  the   T^SiA International Labour Organisation.    It is  neoessary to consider the expenditure of the League as a whole,  and this is done in paragraphs 5 to 11*             International Labour Office.      3.   The International Labour  Office is managed by  a governing body,  of which one-half of the members represent Governments, and the other half employers and work- people.   The Budget is preipared by the staff, oonsidered by a  Finanoe Committee an4\ then sent to the Governing Body whioh is the real souroe of authority.  The Budget is passed to the Supervisory&quot; Commission of the League  and is others  BUbjeoted  to oritidism and passed to  the Assembly of the League.   The Labour Offioe  Budget is not considered by the Council of the League,      4.   Pressure by Great Britain to reduce the estimates of the organisation on account of the  general financial stringency not having met with success, and enquiry by Mr,A,W. Waigon,  Establishment Officer, Ministry of Labour,  was arranged in February last, Mr,Watson reported that extravagancies existed both in the method and use of personnel,  and he made specific recommendations  for a reorganisation which  would reduce the ourrent expenditure of over 5,000,000 franos for  staff alone by at least 30$ to 40^,    This report was  made  to the Director and while certain  minor recommendations were adopted the complete reorganisation was not carried out. The Finance Committee refused to  pass the report to  theGoverning Body.          The reductions actually accomplished are indicated irt the  following statistics:-
Salaries of International, Labour Organ!eation,         &quot;                                                      Pres.   Budget of 1923                               5,088,712      &quot;   &quot;  1984                               4,418,295          A reduction of 610,417 francs or-12$.          She International Labour Office themselves  state in a note to the Budget Estimates that the limitationsintroduoed in 1924 are only a &quot;first step&quot; in the reorganisation and the removal of parasitic growths.   A further reduction by1925 of 1,400,000 franos under this head should not beimpossible.   To this, an automatic reduction in the salary billin view of the fall in the cost of living may add 250,000 franos.          But Mr,Watson,s investigation was oonfined to thequestion of internal organisation only in the matter of staff and prooedure;  it is olear that by an overhaul of the manifoldend extensive activities of the organisation and by a striotorinterpretation of the duties of the office under Part XIII ofthe Treaty of Versailles very much larger economies oould besecured.   Thus the restriction of the number of commissions and. enquiries and of the output of printed matter ought to be easy to effect as well perhaps as the reduotion or elimination of branch bureaux in tho various Capitals.   Many detailedlines of possible economy elsewhere are also noticeable.   the precise form of retrenchment need not be selected in detail by great Britain,   But it is sufc&amp;ested &quot;that a Budget of fivemillion franos for 1925 is sufficient for the needs of a oompaotefficient and reasonably active labour bureau, representing a reduction of 1,942,295 francs on the Budget as now proposed for 1924.          Effective action oan only be taken by the assembly and it is suggested that the British representatives shouldreceive instructions to demand the reduotion referred to above as a condition of acceptance of the Budget now proposed for
OTHER EXPENDITURE OF LEAGUE OP NATIONS.        56^      (5)  The essential control over policy rests with the Annual Assembly which determines the different tasks to he undertaken by the League.          The budget for the League proper is drawn up by the Secretariat and submitted to a body called the Supervisory Commission containing 5 representatives chosen from countries not represented on the Council of the League.   Great Britain is thus not represented on the Supervisory Commission except that a semi-official exchange of views ooours regularly with Lord Meston who represents India,,   The Budget after donsideratioh by the Supervisory Commission passes to the Council of the league and thence to the Assembly where it is dealt with first by the ^Fourth Committee&quot; and then by the full Assembly.  It has no binding power unless and until approved by the latter,     (6)  It is open to any member of the Assembly to submit proposals involving expenditure  and, if the Assembly approves,  it becomes the duty of the League officials to oarry out  such proposals.  The difficulty of subsequently securing economy during the detailed examination of thebudget is  precisely that the officials examined are able on nearly every point to reply that the policy has been approved by the  Assembly.   It is useless to complain that policy is  determined by the Assembly:  there is no alterna- tive.&apos;  But circumstances change rapidly, and it seems an                           -5-s   Resolutions involving expenditure have to bo submittedto the Finance Committee before they are voted on by theAssembly,  but the Finance Committee is too large and inexperta body to  criticise expenditure effectively,,
element of weakness In the present system that no part ofthe organisation seems to pbssess power to call for a definitesuspension or postponement bf particular items of work untilthe matter can again be considered by the next Assemblyor is charged with the duty of directing attention of theAssembly to expenditure which has become otiose sr has soexpanded as to appear to reduire further consideration.          It must be borne in mind that the organisationof the league on its official side is looser than that ofe.g. a British Government Department.,   Thus the International sbour Office ia outside the control of the Secretariat.Moreover within the Secretariat itself the General Seoretarydoes not possess the complete control over his subordinateswhich is vested in the Permanent Secretary of BritishGovernment Departments, for the various Chiefs of Sectionhave direct access to and frequent communications with theAssembly and Council on the special matters with which theyare entrusted.-     7.   Under existing conditions, substantial economiescan only be effected by action in the Assembly itself.  Themeeting next Assembly in September may offer an unusuallyfavourable opportunity for effeoting reforms inasmuch asthe influence of Prance is at the present time beingstrongly exBroised in the direction of reducing expenditure,     8.   While there are various minor points on whicheconomy can be effected in detail, these could for themost part be asalt with readily by the existing machineryof the Supervisory Commission.  The prospects of largeeconomy depend on persuading the Assembly to take one orother, or both, of the following steps:-      (a)  to ration the different tranches of the league          in bulk;                           *
   (b)  to give directions for the establishment  of        an Economy Committee charged with the task        of suggesting economies in carrying out        the existing policy, and also empowered  to        Buggest changes of policy by which        substantial economies could be secured.   9.-   Setting aside the International labour Organisation,the Permanent Court of International Justice, etc,  theexpenditure of the League proper amounts to  529,000,.   ttis difficult, at the present stage, to name a definitefigure&apos; to which this expenditure should be limited,  or even to indicate in what particular Sections economies should beeffected,   It may be observed, however, that strongcriticisms have recently been made by the Supervisory Com--mission on the subject of the expenditure, e.g.  of the transit and International Health Organisation, though,under present arrangements, it would seeh that nothing islikely to be done unless Great Britain raises the matter in the Assembly.   A Note is attached (Appendix III) on the transit Organisation, and it would certainly seem thateconomy is possible there.   But material  is laoking forany complete  examination in detail of the League expenditure.(b)   that an attempt to introduce a new        Economy Committee would probably be&apos;        resented by the Council of the League        and the governing body of the Inter-        national labour Organisation as tending        to usurp their functions.   10.   Accordingly,  it seems inevitable,  if the attempt  tosecure econojay is to be pursued,  that some  definite figure should be named as the limit to League expenditure in 1S25,If we assume that the International Labour OrganisationDespite this difficulty, it would seem :-(a)that it is undesirable to attempt to  ration the International Labour  Organisation without attempting any  similar restriction on League expehdi-  ture generally;
expenditure can be reduced to 5,000,000 francs ( 200,000)and that the expenditure on the Secretariat can be reducedby 10% (He. from  529,000 to,  say,  475,000), the total figure for the League expenditure, including the Inter-national Court of Permanent Justice,  could be put at 750,000, excluding any sum required for the working capitalfund.   (ll)   It is proposed that the British delegates at theAssembly should be instructed to propose that for 1625 theexpenditure of the League,  excluding a sum if any requiredfor the working capital fund, should be limited to atotal of  750,000, of which, not more than  200,000 shouldbe allotted to the International Labour Organisation.As previously indicated, other countries,  notably Prance,appear also anxious to secure economy.   To give the pro-posal its best chance of success in the Assembly, it wouldbe very important to secure the support of otheff importantmembers of the League through diplomatic  channels&apos;before theAssembly meets.
APPENDIX-  I.Analysis of the expenditure of the Secretariat and special organisations of the League of Nations in               the Budget for 1924*.    ,          **** **.**)-****** ******** ****** *- ******** ****** ****** ****** (*.                                                      iAssembly aiid Council Session                        26,000General Services of the Secretariat                257,000Loss on Exchange                                     4,000Buildings etc. (Capital expenditure)                 6.OOP   Total - Secretariat etc,                        333,000   Special Organisationsc        A,   Per.m&amp;nent,Administrative Commissions &amp;  Kinoriti.es             15,000Economic and Financial                              61,000Mandates                                             8.000Transit                                             16j000International Health Organisation                   28*000Special Questions:  Women &amp; Children,                    Opium, etc,                      7,000Reduction of Armaments                               8.000                                                  141,000        B    Temporary.Reduction of Armaments                             SO,000International Blockade Committee                    2,000International Bureau                                4,000High Commissariat for Refugees                     t 6.000                                                   32,000        C.   Unforeseen Expenditure                20.000   Total - Special Organisations                  193,000Total - Secretariat &amp; Special Organisations       526,000
          The  following  are  exariploB  sawinc  the  range  of undertakings of  the  International Labour  Office:-          Advisory Committee on Anthrax          Emigration Commission          Unhealthy Prosesses Commission          Advisory Committee on Traffic in Women                                   and Children          Conference of  Factor;&apos;&apos; Inspectors          Committee on Keck Cargoes (in Paris)          Advisory Committee on Agriculture          conference of  Labour Statisticians          Enquiry into Unemployment          Enquiry into Standard of Working Class Life          Enquiry into Production.Publications.       The Printing alone of  the  InternationalLabour Office  publications is estimated for 1924 to cost500,000 francs (in 1922  it cost as much as 791,000 francs),The publications include a Weekly Bulletin,                           Monthly Review (170 pages),                           and a mass of Studies and Reporton various general and technical subjects in variouslanguages, and Records,  Proces-Verbaux, circulars,Questionnaires,  eto,
A P P 3 IT D X XIII.Transit Seotion.Expenditure in 1921     u31,600u19228,800Budget for192319,800 (plus  12,000        special expenditure)II192415,800The Transit Organisation deals, with&apos; all questions referred to the League in accordance with Article 23(e) ofthe Covenant under whioh Members of the League undertake tosecure and maintain freedom of communications and of transitand equitable treatment for the commerce of all Members ofthe League.   It also deals with the artiolee of the variouspeace treaties which plaoe under the jurisdiction of theLeague questions relating to transport, portB,, waterwayB, and railways.   The Budget for 1923 included a special item of 12,000 for a general conference,  &apos; The Supervising Commissionreduced the budget by  3,300 and expressed the desire that theAssembly should consider the total suppression of the subheadproviding for expenditure required in order to carry out theduties entrusted to the League by the Genoa conference, -  this duty was that of examining the progress achieved in carryingout the recommendations of the Fourth Conraissioi (Transport)of the Genoa Conference concerning the facilities for inter-state transport.   The League have given a temporary appoint -ment to General Manse, who was British Railway Expert at the paris Conference,   If this work were discontinued there wouldbe a further saving of  1,200,   The Budget includes  2,000for a regional conference which might perhaps be postponed untilhappier-times.   The permanent staff consists of six (3 super-ior, 3 clerical), anu there is considerable expenditure ontravelling which is probably inevitable,.11.This
          This organisation is a good example  of a servicewhioh gives indefinite room for expansion if a free rein isgiven to the experts,  hut which could he very  considerablycurtailed in the interests of economy if only  absolutely necessary work were undertaken such as the arbitration of disputes submitted to  the Committee,  and the duty of advising the League on definite questions submitted to  it,  or actuallyarising under the Peace Treaties,1/8/23.                                     W.J-H.r   12
     Owing to the diminution of information resultingfrom the holidays no report will he issued nest week:any matter of importance will be the subject of a special report. -

</content>
</cab>
