<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/53/0 images: 272-273</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1952CONFIDENTIALCopy No.    g JC. (52) 21025th June, 1952CABINETADMIRALTY AND WAR DEPARTMENT PROPERTY IN BERMUDAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesThe Admiralty and War Department property in Bermuda covers an areaof about 830 acres. The land for the Dockyard was acquired in 1795 at  50 anacre; the War Department land was acquired in the 19th Century at pricesbetween  50 and  100 an acre. This property is now surplus as the result of theclosing down of the Dockyard and the withdrawal of the Garrison. I have beenunable to reach agreement with the other Ministers concerned on the arrangementsfor its disposal.2. The Bermuda Government wish to take over all this property. Theirrepresentatives have been over here, and the facts emerging from the negotiationsare summarised in C. (52) 211.3. There is no agreed valuation of this property, nor any possibility ofobtaining one. The Bermuda representatives did not accept the original War Officevaluation of  3 million or the later offer of  1,850,000, and they made it clearthat their own offer of  650,000 represented the most which they considered theBermuda Government could afford, or, indeed should be called upon to pay, ona reasonable valuation, taking into account only the commercial factors. It istrue that Bermuda has reserve funds of about  1 million and practically no publicdebt, but its whole economy, based on the tourist traffic, is a precarious one. Inany event, the dockyard is a doubtful commercial proposition. There would beheavy maintenance costs for two or three years, and it would thereafter be acontinuing liability, unless some commercial use can be found for it. No suchuse has yet been found. The value of the military barracks is considerably affectedby the obligation (which Bermuda would be very glad to accept) to maintain thisproperty as barracks against the possibility of a return of the garrison.4. In view of the gap between the two figures, there is little hope of a corn-promise, and the possible courses of action seem to be:  (a) acceptance of the Bermuda offer;(b) piecemeal disposal of the properties by the War Office and Admiralty.5. There are legislative restrictions on the sale of property in the Colonyto non-Bermudians; thus the net return, if Her Majesty&apos;s Government attemptto dispose of the property piecemeal, would almost certainly be considerably lessthan the lowest price we have put on the property ( 1,850,000), and might wellprove to be no more than the Bermuda offer of  650,000. But the main argumentsin favour of course (a) are political. The closing down of the dockyard and thewithdrawal of the garrison, following the leasing in 1941 at His late Majesty&apos;sGovernments request of approximately 1 / 15th of the total area of the Island tothe United States for Air and Naval Bases, has aroused deep misgivings amongthe people of Bermuda about our interest in the Colony, and the maintenance oftheir links with this country. They will be embittered if Her Majesty&apos;s Government,having no further use for this property which was acquired under legislation fordefence purposes, now ask Bermuda to pay a price based on development andpresent-day values as against that originally paid for the land. We were assured42461
by the Bermuda representatives that such a proposal would give rise to great resent-ment and would strengthen the hands of those Bermudians who favour a closerfinancial and even political relationship with Canada.6. I do not therefore think that the counter-offer made in the course of thediscussions here should be put forward officially to the Bermuda Government. if their offer is not to be accepted, it will be necessary to tell the Bermuda Govern-ment that, in our present financial position, we cannot afford to let them have thisproperty at the price which they offered and that we shall have to make other arrangements for disposing of it, in which we would hope to have their co-operation.7. I recommend that we should accept the Bermuda offer of  650,000. Itwould, I think, be well worth foregoing the possible (but speculative) advantages of piecemeal disposal, even in our present financial difficulties, to keep the good-will of the people of Bermuda. The Colony has at no time received any financial help from the United Kingdom Government for development or any other purpose.It has, on the contrary, made a signal sacrifice for Western defence by the provisionof land for United States Bases; it is making a voluntary contribution of about 40,000 a year to United Kingdom defence costs; and it is at present contributingsome $11 million a year to the sterling area dollar pool. If we insist upon regardingthis as a purely commercial transaction, we are unlikely to gain anything likethe estimated sums mentioned, we shall have to wait a long time for our money and we shall run the risk of long-term disadvantages far&apos; outweighing, in myopinion, any possible financial gains.O. L.Colonial Office, S.W.1,25th June, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
