<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/53/0 images: 119-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
m f/SSthis document is the property of her britannic  majesty&apos;s  governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1952Copy No.   73CABINETTRANSPORT bill memorandum by the Secretary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and power as requested by the Cabinet on 26th June (C.C. (52) 63rd Conclusions, Minute6), the Committee on Transport Policy have considered outstanding points on thedraft Transport Bill and I now submit a final draft (print No. 163-6). I call atten-tion to the following points:  scotland . We have considered the suggestion made by the Secretary of State forScotland in C. (52) 205 that the Bill should provide for the appointment of a ScottishCommittee to assist the British Transport Commission in Scottish matters. In theview of the Transport Policy Committee, such a body would be unnecessary whilethe reorganisation of the railways is being worked out. It would-be redundant once the Scottish railway authority has been set up, for the Scottish Area TransportUsers&apos; Consultative Committee will still be in existence. - Further, the Bill nowprovides that the Scottish Consultative Committee shall have direct access to theMinister of Transport (Clause 27 (3)) and that it shall be empowered to concern itself not only, as at present, with railways, but also with road passenger services,which in Scotland are provided by companies controlled, through shareholding, bythe British Transport Commission.   (Clause 17 (8).)3. We understand that the existing Scottish Consultative Committee has not made a very impressive showing, and has hardly been sufficiently in touch with local needs and opinions. These defects can be cured by improving the member-ship of the Committee and by setting up subordinate local bodies. Both these stepscan be taken administratively, under existing powers, by the Minister of Transport,in consultation with the Secretary of State for Scotland.4. We have discussed the matter fully with the Secretary of State for Scotland,and we understand that he now regards the views expressed in C. (52) 205 asadequately met by the arrangements described in the preceding paragraphs.The Ministers Powers of Direction5. The Bill as now drafted includes no provision modifying the powers ofgiving directions to the Commission conferred upon the Minister of transport by Section 4 (1) of the Transport Act, 1947. But those powers might be insufficientduring the period when immediate effect is being given to the Bill. A non-co-operative Commission might, without some such spur, greatly delay, if notfrustrate, the intentions of Parliament. In particular much time might be lostover a deadlock between the Commission and the Road Haulage Disposal board to be established under Clause 2. The Transport Policy Committee have, therefore,agreed that there should be inserted in Clause 3 a provision which will enablethe Minister to resolve any such deadlock by giving a specific direction to either the Commission or the Board in the event of a dispute. Such a power would be purely transitory, and would be spent once immediate effect had been given tothe Bill.424869SECRETC. (52) 2181st July, 1952
Charges Schemes6. In accordance with the suggestion made to the Cabinet on 26th May,Clause 19 (2) (d) of the Bill as previously before the Cabinet has been omitted.The Bill therefore no longer requires charges schemes to provide for prevent!&quot;^vthe making by the Commission of &quot; unduly low &quot; charges. Instead, a new pi &quot;vision has been inserted (Clause 20 (2)) which gives a right of appeal to theTransport Tribunal by any undertaking which considers that the railways. are.deliberately trying to put it out of existence by uneconomic undercutting.7. As for the remainder of the former Clause 19, we have had to balanceconflicting views. The broad object, as set out in paragraph 14 of the White Paper,is to ensure that greater latitude is given to the Commission so as to enable therailways to quote competitive rates. Representatives of trade and industry attach great importance to the rights they have under existing law to object to specialrates. But the Commission would like all restrictions removed and, indeed, tobe free from the requirement to prepare charges schemes at all. While we cannotgo so far as this, we realise that some of the existing restrictions on competitivequotation by the railways date from a time when circumstances were very differentand the railways had almost a monopoly of transport. As now drafted, Clause 19will, as before, require charges schemes to provide for maximum charges; and willhave the effect of enabling charges schemes to relieve the railways of certain existing restrictions on the extent to which charges may be reduced, and of removing theexisting rights of traders to object to special rates. Clause 20 (3) will, however,maintain the provisions of the existing law preventing the Commission from giving&quot; undue preference &quot; and requiring them to give &quot; equality of treatment.&quot;Railway Interests in Road Transport8. Since the draft Bill was considered by the Cabinet the Transport PolicyCommittee have made one other alteration of substance. A provision has nowbeen inserted (Clause 17 (6)) enabling the Minister, if he thinks fit, to require theCommission to divest themselves of majority shareholdings in road passenger transport, undertakings. These holdings have been greatly increased sincenationalisation, so that the Commission now have a virtual monopoly in certain parts of the country, notably Scotland. The new provision will enable the Ministerto break the Commission^ monopoly, if that should be thought desirable. It isnot suggested that the power should be exercised immediately. It will, however,be available against recommendations which may well result from the proposed inquiry into the working of the licensing system for public service vehicles set up under the Road Traffic Act, 1930.conclusion. Subject to any minor or drafting amendments, I ask my colleagues to approve the draft Bill circulated with this memorandum, and to agree to its presentation in the House of Commons in the week beginning Monday, 7th July.Great George Street, S.W.1,1st July, 1952.
CONFIDENTIALTransport bill arrangement OF CLAUSESCarriage of Goods by RoadClause1.   Disposal of Commission^ existing road haulage undertaking.2.   Road Haulage Disposal Board.3.   Sales of transport units.4.   Transfer of transport units to companies under control of commission.5.   Disposal of property otherwise than in transport units.6.   Commission^ vehicles to require licences but to be free fromtwenty-five mile limit.1.   Repeal, as from appointed day, of provisions relating to twenty-five mile limit.8.  Amendments as to grounds for granting or refusing licences.9.   Supplemental provisions as to preceding sections.The Transport Levy and the Transport Fund10.   The transport levy.11.   Establishment of Transport Fund.12. Payments to Commission out of Transport Fund for loss on disposal of road haulage undertaking.13. Payments to Commission out of Transport Fund in respectof loss of railway revenue due to transfer of traffic fromrail to road.14.   Supplemental provisions as to three last preceding sections.Re-organisation of Railways15.   Re-organisation of railways.16.   Approval and amendment of re-organisation schemes.Road passenger transport, trade harbours and port facilities17.   Repeals and amendments relating to the Commission&apos;s functions with respect to road passenger transport.18.   Trade harbours and port facilities.Charges19.   Amendments as to charges schemes.20.   Special provisions as to charges for carriage of goods.21.  Amendments of Cheap Trains Act, 1883, s. 6.22.   Power of Commission to make general increases of charges in advance of alteration of charges schemes.163-6 A
Amendments as to general duty and constitution of Commission,etc.Clause23.  Amendments as to general duty and constitution of Corn-mission, etc.24.   Miscellaneous amendments as to functions of Commission.?.Pension rights and compensation to employees25.   Provisions as to pension rights.26.   Compensation to officers and servants.Miscellaneous and General27. Amendments as to Consultative Committees for Scotlandand Wales.28. Amendments as to Coastal Shipping Advisory Committee.29. Amendments as to Transport Arbitration Tribunal.30. Repeal of s. 7 and s. 114 of Transport Act, 1947.31. Administrative provisions.32. Interpretation.33. Short title, extent and repeals.Schedules :First Schedule Rights of obtaining licences for five years for goods vehicles free of charge.Part I Vehicles comprised in transport units.Part II Goods vehicles of Commission.Second Schedule Rates of Transport Levy.Third Schedule-Provisions of the Transport Act, 1947,repealed.
D RAFTof aBILLtoRequire the British Transport Commission to dispose of a.d. 1952the property held by them for the purposes ofthe part of their undertaking which is carried onthrough the Road Haulage Executive; to amend the law relating to the carriage of goods by road and to provide for a levy, for the.benefit of thesaid Commission and for other purposes, on motor vehicles used on roads ; to provide for the re-organisation of the railways operated by the saidCommission and to amend the law relating to thepowers, duties and composition of the said Commis-sion; to repeal certain provisions of the Transport Act,1947, and to amend other provisions thereof ; toamend section six of the Cheap Trains Act, 1883; andfor purposes connected with the matters aforesaid.BE it enacted by the Queen&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and Commons, in this present parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5 Carriage of Goods by Road1. (1) Subject to the provisions of this Act, it shall be the Disposal of duty of the British Transport Commission (in this Act referred Commission^to as &quot; the Commission &quot;),&apos; to dispose, as quickly as is reason- exaffi ,ably practicable, of all the property held by them for the pur- undertaking610 poses of so much of their undertaking as is at the passing ofthis Act carried on through the Road Haulage Executive.The part of the undertaking of the Commission referred to&apos;in this subsection is hereafter in this Act referred to as &quot; theexisting road haulage undertaking &quot;.163-6A 2
15&amp;16GEO. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2W52 , - (2) Pending the disposal of the property mentioned in sub-section (1) of this section, it shall be the duty of the Commis-sion to carry on the existing road haulage undertaking in such manner as may appear to them to be expedient for the pur-pose of enabling the said property to be disposed of without 5delay and on the best terms available, and without avoidabledisturbance of the transport system of the country.(3) Subject to the provisions of this subsection, sections thirty-nine to fifty-one, section fifty-four, section fifty-five and sub-section (2) of section sixty of the Transport Act, 1947 (which 10relate to the acquisition of certain road transport undertakingsby the Commission), and any notice of acquisition given underPart III of that. Act before the passing of this Act, shall cease to have effect:Provided that this subsection shall not affect the operation 15,      of. the said provisions, in relation to or in connection with any transfer effected before the passing of this Act in consequenceof any notice of acquisition under the said Part III.i(4) Nothing in this section shall be taken as. restricting thepowers, conferred on the Commission by section two of the 20f Transport Act,&quot; 1947, and, accordingly, the Commission may provide, continue or develop any services or facilities for the carriage of goods by road which are provided by them other-wise than as part of the operation of the existing road haulageundertaking. 25. (5) The references in this Act to the property held by theCommission for the purposes of the existing road haulage under-taking are references to . (a) property which at the passing of this Act is held bythe Commission solely or partly for the purposes of the 30existing road haulage undertaking and is then in the possession, as between the Road Haulage Executive; , and persons other, than the Commission, of thatExecutive; and.(b) property which after the passing of this Act is obtained 35or appropriated by the Commission solely or partly for or to the purposes of the said undertaking and thereby comes into the possession of the Road haulage executive as aforesaid or would thereby come intothe possession of that Executive if the undertaking 40were being carried on through that Executive,- other than property which is consumed or discarded in theordinary course of the carrying on of that undertaking:-Provided that the Minister may direct that any property heldby the Commission at the passing of this Act, or thereafter 45obtained or appropriated by them, partly for or to the purposes
of the existing road haulage undertaking and partly for or to   A.D. 1952other purposes shall be treated, or shall not be treated, as pro-perty held by the Commission for the purposes of that under-taking and this Act shall have effect accordingly.5    2. (1) There shall be a body, to be called the Road Haulage Road HaulageDisposal Board (hereafter in this Act referred to as &quot; the Board &quot;), Disposalwith the powers and duties conferred and imposed on them by  oar &quot;the subsequent provisions of this Act.(2) The Board shall consist of six members all of whom shall10 be appointed by the Minister.(3) Of the said members the Minister shall appoint one tobe chairman and one to be deputy chairman of the Board..(4) Of the remaining members of the Board (a) one member shall be appointed from among persons15 nominated by the Commission ;(b) one member shall be appointed after consultation withsuch bodies representative of trade and industry as theMinister thinks fit;(c) one member shall be appointed after consultation with20 such bodies representative of persons holding A or Blicences as the Minister thinks fit; and(d) one member shall be appointed after consultation withsuch bodies representative of persons holding C licencesas the Minister thinks fit.25    (5) Every member of the Board shall hold, and vacate his office in accordance with the terms of his appointment and shall, onceasing to be a member, be eligible for reappointment:Provided that any member may at any time by notice inwriting to the Minister resign his office.30 (6) A person shall be disqualified for being appointed or being a member of the Board so long as he is a member of the commons House of Parliament.(7) A member of the Board who is in any way directly or indirectly interested in any transaction entered into or proposed.35 to be entered into by the Commission under section three of thisAct shall disclose the nature of his interest at a meeting of theBoard ; and the disclosure shall be recorded in the minutes of the^ Board, and the member shall not take any part in anydeliberation or decision of the Board with respect to that trans-40 action:Provided that a member of the Board appointed under para-graph (a) of subsection (4) of this section shall not be.-deemed for the purposes of this subsection to be interested in any trans-action by reason only of the interest which the Commission has45 therein,
4 Transport 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952 (8) Any question arising at any meeting of the Board shallbe determined in accordance with the opinion of the majorityof the members of the Board present and voting at that meeting:Provided that if at any meeting of the Board there is a differ-ence of opinion between the members of the Board on any 5question, and the chairman or, in the absence of the chairman,the deputy chairman, considers that the matter is of sufficient importance to require to be referred to the Minister, he may refer the matter to the Minister, and where the matter is soreferred to the Minister the Minister may, if he thinks fit, give 10directions to the Board as to the course to be followed, andthe Board shall comply with any such directions.(9) The Board shall from time to time, and at least once inevery six months, make to the Minister a report in writing as tothe progress made in the disposal of the property held by the 15Commission for the purposes of the existing road haulage under-taking and the Minister shall lay a copy of each such report before each House of Parliament.(10) The Board may appoint a secretary and, with the approvalof the Minister, such other officers and such servants as they 20consider necessary for assisting them in the proper execution oftheir duties.(11) There shall be paid to the members of the Board and toany officer or servant of the Board such remuneration (whetherby way of salaries, fees or allowances) as may be determined by 25the Minister, with the approval, in the case of the members ofthe Board, of the Treasury; and any such remuneration asaforesaid and any other expenses of the Board shall be defrayedout of the Transport Fund established under the subsequentprovisions of this Act. 30(12) The Board may act notwithstanding a vacancy amongthe members thereof, and the quorum of the Board shall be three.(13) Subject to the preceding provisions of this section, theBoard may regulate their own procedure. 353. (1) For the purpose of disposing of the property held bythem for the purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking,the Commission shall from time to time, by public notice, invitetenders for the purchase, on specified conditions, of (a) one or more specified motor vehicles ; and 40(b) such other property, if any, as may be specified,and the specified conditions may include conditions whereby, asbetween the purchaser and the Commission, the purchaser takesover such rights and obligations of the Commission, whether under contract or otherwise, as may be specified, being rights and 45obligations connected with the subject matter of the purchase.Sales oftransportunits.
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6 Transport 5&amp; 1 Eliz. 2(2) In the case of each such invitation, the properties whichare to be the subject of the purchase, and the conditions of thepurchase, shall be such as, in the opinion of the Commission,are calculated to enable a purchaser to engage without delay in  the carriage of goods by road for hire or reward, and theaggregate of the property, rights and obligations which a pur-chaser obtains or will obtain under a purchase resulting from such an invitation is hereafter in this Act referred to as &quot; a transport unit&quot;.10 (3) In determining what are to he the transport units for which persons are invited to tender as aforesaid, the Commission shallhave regard to the desirability of securing that persons desirous of entering or re-entering the road haulage industry have areasonable opportunity of doing so notwithstanding that their15 resources permit them to do so only if their operations are on asmall scale, and, without prejudice to the generality of the fore-going provision but subject to the provisions of subsection (5)of this section, no transport unit shall, without the approvalof the Minister, include more than fifty motor vehicles or motor20 vehicles the aggregate weight of which unladen exceeds two hundred tons.Subject as aforesaid, the transport units shall be determined with a view to securing that the property held by the commission for the purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking fetches25 in the aggregate the best possible price.i(4) The provisions of Part I of the First Schedule to this Actshall, subject to the provisions of subsection (5) of this section,have effect for the purpose of giving to the purchaser of a transport unit and his successors in title the rights referred to30 in those provisions of obtaining free of charge, for the five year period therein referred to authorisations under A licences to use the vehicles comprised in the unit, or other vehicles substitutedtherefor in accordance with the said provisions, without being subject to the condition provided for in section fifty-two of the35 Transport Act, 1947 (namely that, except under or in accordancewith a permit granted by the Commission, goods shall not becarried for hire or reward in any authorised vehicle if at anytime while the goods are being so carried the vehicle is morethan twenty-five miles from its operating centre).40 (5) The vehicles included in a transport unit may includevehicles specified as additional vehicles, and the vehicles so specified shall la) be deemed for the purposes of Part I of the first schedule to this Act not to be included in that trans-45 port unit, but without prejudice to the substitutionthereof in accordance with the said Part I for othervehicles so included;
Transport15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2Transfer oftransportunits tocompaniesundercontrol of commission.(b) be disregarded for the purposes of the limitations im-posed by subsection (3) of this section on the size ofthe transport unit.(6) In performing their duties under this section the Com-mission shall consult the Board and act on lines settled from 5time to time with the approval of the Board, and no invitation to tender for a transport unit shall be issued by the Commissionwithout the approval of the Board and no tender for any trans-port unit shall be accepted by the Commission without theapproval of the Board; and the Board shall not give their 10approval to the acceptance of any such tender unless they aresatisfied that the price is a reasonable one having regard to thevalue to the purchaser of the property and rights which he will obtain by the purchase, including the rights provided for by part I of the First Schedule to this Act: 15Provided that if any difference arises between the Commissionand the Board as to the lines on which the Commission are toact in performing their duties under this section, either theCommission or the Board may refer the matter to the Ministerand the Minister shall give such directions therein as he thinks 20fit, and any directions so given by him shall be binding on theCommission and the Board.(7) In this section &quot; specified &quot; means specified in the publicnotice inviting the tenders or ascertainable in the manner speci-fied in that notice. 254. (1) The Commission may, within six months from thepassing of this Act or such longer period as the Minister mayallow, cause to be incorporated under the Companies Act, 1948,one or more companies which shall be under their control andthe powers of which shall include power to carry on business as 30carriers of goods by road in Great Britain.(2) Where either (a) an invitation to tender for the purchase of specified&quot;      property has been issued under the last preceding section ; or 35(b) the Board have approved the issue by the Commissionof such an invitation ; or(c) the Board haye informed the Commission that theywould be prepared to approve the issue of such an invitation, 40the Commission may, if the Minister gives his consent, makeover to any company incorporated under subsection (1) of thissection all the property and connected rights and obligations, ifany, which the purchaser would have obtained tinder a purchase
)15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6 Transport 7&amp; 1 Eliz. 2resulting from the invitation, and in that event subsections (4) a.d; 1952and (5) of the last preceding section, the next following section and the First Schedule to this Act shall have effect as if the transaction had been purchase in pursuance of the invitation5 and as if all such things had been done as would have fallen to be done if the transaction had been such a purchase, and,without prejudice to the generality of the preceding provisionsof this subsection, references in the said provisions of this Actto transport units, to purchasers of transport units and to addi-10 tional vehicles shall be construed accordingly:Provided that, without prejudice to the power of the Ministerto give or refuse his consent under this subsection in any case and on any ground, the Minister shall so exercise his powers under this subsection as to secure that 15 (a) the total weight unladen of the motor vehicles made over thereunder to companies incorporated in pursuanceof the said subsection (1) does not exceed the totaliweight unladen of the motor vehicles owned on thefirst day of January, nineteen hundred and forty-20 eight, by the bodies corporate which, on that day, came,by virtue of Part II of the Transport Act, 1947, underthe direct or indirect control of the Commission; and(b) as respects size, nature and quality, the vehicles so made over are comparable to, or, as the case may be, to part25 of, the motor vehicles so owned.(3) The annual statement to be prepared by the commission under section ninety-four of the Transport Act, 1947, shall, as respects any period during which any company incorporatedunder subsection (1) of this section remains under the direct or30 indirect control of the Commission, include information as to theprincipal activities of the company and be so framed as to show,,as far as may be, the financial and operating results of each suchactivity, and the Minister and the Treasury shall exercise their powers under the said section ninety-four accordingly.35    5.^-(l) If it appears to the Commission as respects any pro- Disposal ofperty held by them for the purposes of the. existing road haulage property- -      -     -  -   - -   - - - - otherwise thanundertaking that it is impracticable or inexpedient to dispose ofthat property as or as part of a transport unit, they may, with unHS.the consent of the Minister, dispose of that property otherwise40 than as or as part of a transport unit.Any consent of the Minister under this subsection may begiven so as to apply to a specified transaction or to a specifiedclass of transactions and may be given either absolutely or subject to conditions.45    (2) The Minister may give directions to the Commission, as respects any property held by them for the purposes of thein transport
OS Transport 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Buz. 2A.D, 1952 existing road haulage undertaking, requiring them to dispose of that property otherwise than as or as part of a transport unit,and the Commission shall comply with any such directions.(3) If it appears to the Commission as respects any property held by them for the purposes of the existing road haulage under- 5taking that the retention thereof by them for use for the pur-poses of some other part of their undertaking (being a part theoperations of which do not consist wholly or mainly in the carriage of goods by road for hire or reward) is necessary inorder to avoid prejudice to the efficient carrying on thereof, 10they may, with the consent of the Minister, retain that propertyfor such use as aforesaid instead of disposing of it.(4) Save as provided by the preceding provisions of this sec-tion, the Commission shall not dispose of any property held bythem for the purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking 15otherwise than as or as part of a transport unit:Provided that. nothing in this subsection shall prevent theCommission consuming or discarding any such property in theordinary course of the carrying on of the existing road haulageundertaking. 20Commission^ 6. 41) Section fifty-nine of the Transport Act, 1947 (whichvehicles to provides that no licence is required for goods vehicles usedoutTdbefree68 by the Commission), shall cease to have effect.twenty-five As respects goods vehicles which at the passing of this Actmile limits belonged to the Commission or were in the possession of the 25Commission under an agreement for hire or loan, the repeal ofthe said section shall not take effect until three months from thepassing of this Act and, if before the expiration of the said threemonths an application is made for a licence authorising theuse of any of those vehicles, that repeal shall not take effect 30as respects those vehicles until the application is determinedby the licensing authority.(3) If any vehicle as respects which the said section fifty-nineis still in force is destroyed or damaged beyond repair, the Com-mission may substitute for that vehicle  35: (a) if the vehicle is a motor vehicle, another motor vehicle,of the same or less weight unladen ;&apos;(6) if the vehicle is a trailer, another trailer,and thereafter the preceding provisions of this section shall haveeffect as if the substituted vehicle had, and the original vehicle 49had not, belonged to the Commission or, as the case may be,been in the possession of the Commission under an agreement for hire or loan at the passing of this Act.
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Buz. 2.(4) Section fifty-two of the Transport Act, 1947 (which pro-   A.D. 1952vides.for restricting the use of goods vehicles more than twenty-five miles from their operating centres), shall not apply to theuse of vehicles by the Commission.5 (5) The provisions of Part II of the First Schedule to this Actshall have effect for the purpose of giving to the Commission therights specified in those provisions of obtaining free of charge,for the five year period therein referred to, authorisations underA licences or C licences to use the goods vehicles specified in10 those provisions.(6) Vehicles specified, in licences which are being used by theCommission shall   . .-&quot;  -&apos;(a) for the purpose of any wages regulation order in force under the Wages Councils Act, 1945, at the passing of15 this Act; and (b)) for the purpose of determining the workers in rela-tion to whom the Road Haulage Wages Council re-ferred to in section one of the Wages Councils Act..     1948, operates ; and20       (c) for the purposes of Part II of the Road Haulage WagesAct, 1938, .be deemed to be vehicles not so specified. .,.7.-(1) As from the appointed day, section fifty-two of the Xs^mfromTransport Act, 1947 (which provides for restricting the use of of provfsions15&apos;&apos;&apos;25 goods vehicles more than twenty-five miles from their operating relating tocentres), any such condition in a licence as is provided for by twenty-fivethe said section fifty-two, and sections fifty-three and fifty-six, mile limit,subsection (2) of section fifty-seven, section fifty-eight, subsections, (1) and (3) to (6) of section sixty, and sections sixty-one and sixty-30 two of the said Act (which contain various provisions supple-mentary or incidental to the said section fifty-two) shall cease tohave effect.(2) The appointed day under subsection (1) of this section-(a) shall he a date not later than six months from the date35 of the making of the order of the Minister appointingit; and(b) shall be a date not earlier than that by which, in the.:       opinion of the Minister at the? date of the making of. the order; so much of the property held for the pur-40 poses of the existing road haulage undertaking as it is reasonably practicable to dispose of by the sale oftransport units will have been disposed, of.(3) Pending the coming into operation of subsection (1) of thisf.&quot;.i: section, subsections (5) and (6) of section fifty-three of the Trans-45 port Act, 1947 (which empower the Commission to revoke163 B2
10 Transport 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp;1ELIZ.2A.D. ,1952 original permits granted to existing undertakings for the use ofgoods vehicles more than twenty-five miles from their operatingcentres, and to substitute other permits therefor), shall not haveeffect, but without prejudice to the operation of subsections (3)and (4) of that section in relation to any substituted permits 5(within the meaning of that section) granted before the passingof this Act.Amendments g (1) In subsection (2) of section six of the Road andfOTgr^tingor ^ail Traffic Act&apos; 1933 (which specifies certain matters to whichrefusing licensing authorities are to have regard in exercising their dis- 10licences. cretion to grant or refuse applications for licences), for the words&quot;shall have regard primarily to the interests of the public generally, including those of persons requiring, as well as ofthose of persons providing, facilities for transport&quot; there shallbe substituted the words &quot; shall have regard to the interests of 15the public generally, including primarily those of persons re-quiring facilities for transport and secondarily those of personsproviding facilities for transport &quot;.(2) To the paragraphs of the said subsection (2) setting outthe particular matters to which the licensing authority is to have 20regard there shall be added the following paragraph-&quot; (/) to the extent to which the vehicles to be authorisedwill further the provision of services under whichgoods will be carried partly by road and partly by railwithout the need for unloading and reloading,&quot; 25and at the end of the said subsection (2) there shall be added the &quot;following paragraph--   &apos; &quot; Where goods are contained in a receptacle which is anadditional body for a goods vehicle constructed or adapted for the purpose of being lifted on or off the vehicle with 30goods contained therein, the lifting of the receptacle with. goods contained therein on to or off any goods vehicle oron to or off any railway wagon shall not be treated forthe purposes of paragraph (/) of this subsection as an un-loading or reloading of those goods.&quot; 35(3) Where, under subsection (2) of section eleven of the said act, the licensing authority takes into consideration any objectionto an application for the grant or variation of a licence ;(a) the onus of prdof that there are such grounds for the objection as are specified in that subsection shall lie 40, on the objector; and 1 v&quot; &apos; -(b) in considering whether existing transport facilities areto be treated, as suitable, the licensing authority shall- have regard to the relative efficiency, reliability andadequacy of the existing facilities and the facilities 45which the applicant will provide if his application is .
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6 Transport 11&amp; 1 Eliz. 2granted, and to all other relevant considerations, includ-   A.D. 1952ing the charges to be made in respect of those facilitiesrespectively.(4) There shall be included among the grounds on which an A Hcence or a B licence may be suspended or revoked under subsection (1) of section thirteen of the Road and Rail traffic act, 1933, or a direction may be given under subsection (3) ofthat section, the following additional ground, that is to say, thatthe holder of the licence made or procured to be made for the10 purposes of his application for the licence, or for the purposes ofan application for any such variation thereof as is mentioned in subsection (3) of section eleven of that Act, any statement of fact which (whether to his knowledge or not) was false or any state-ment of intention or expectation which has not been fulfilled.15 The proviso to subsection (1) of the said section thirteen(which imposes certain conditions on the powers of the licensing authority to revoke or suspend a licence) shall not apply to anyrevocation, suspension or direction made or given by virtue ofthis subsection, but, if the holder of the licence requests the20 licensing authority to hold a public enquiry, the licensing autho-rity shall not make or give any such revocation, suspension ordirection except after holding such an enquiry.9. (1) The power of the Minister under section twenty-five of Supplementalthe Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933, to make regulations for the provisions as25 purpose of, carrying Part I of that Act into effect shall extend sgCy0^dingto the making of regulations for the purpose of carrying intoeffect the preceding provisions of this Act, including the provi-sions of the First Schedule to this Act, and accordinglyreferences in that section to Part I of that Act shall be construed30 as including references to the said provisions.(2) Without prejudice to the generality of subsection (1) of this .section, such regulations as are therein referred to may make provision as to the means by which vehicles to which any of theprovisions of this Act referred to in the said subsection (1) apply35 are to be identified, whether by plates, marks or otherwise, andthe references in section thirty-four, of the Road and Rail traffic act, 1933, to documents, plates or marks by which a vehicleis to be identified as being an authorised vehicle shall be deemedto include references to documents, plates or marks by which a40 vehicle is to be identified as being one to which any of the saidprovisions apply.(3) The Commission shall furnish to the Board from timeto time such reports and information as may in the opinion ofthe Commission be of assistance to the Board in the discharge45 of their functions or as the Board may require them to furnish to the Board for that purpose.
12 Transport 15 &amp; 16 Gf.o. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952 . (4) If it appears to the Minister that, having regard to the stage reached in the disposal of the property held by the commission for the purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking, it is expedient so to do, he may by order provide for abolishing theBoard and winding up their affairs, and for transferring to the -5Minister any functions of the Board so far as they remain to beexercised or performed.. The power conferred by this subsection to make orders shallbe exercisable by statutory instrument and any such statutory instrument shall be subject to annulment in pursuance of a 10resolution of either House of Parliament.The Transport Levy and the Transport fund the transport     10. (1) In the case of the vehicles described in the firstIeyy- column of the Tables in Parts I and III of the Second Scheduleto this Act, being vehicles which are used on public roads in 15Great Britain on or after the appointed day, a. charge, in thisAct referred to as &quot;the transport levy &quot;, shall be made in accord-ance with the subsequent provisions of this section for the benefitof the Transport Fund established under the next following section. 20(2) The transport levy shall be charged for the periodscovered by the licences taken out in respect of the vehicle inI..-.:;; question under the Vehicles (Excise) Act, 1949, and the amountCharged by way of the levy for any such period shall be theamount by which the excise duty payable upon that licence 25&quot; &apos; would be increased if the annual amount of that duty were increased by the amount arrived at by multiplying the unitcharge, as defined in subsection (3) of-this section, by the appro-priate multiplier, as defined in subsection (4) thereof.(3) The amount referred to in this section as &quot; the unit charge &quot; 30shall , v (a) until the end of the year nineteen hundred and fifty-five,be thirteen shillings and sixpence;(b) for each period of three years following the end of thatyear, be such sum as may be fixed in relation to that 35period by an order of the Minister made before thebeginning of that period or, if no sum is so fixed, thesum which was the unit charge immediately before ther, -       beginning of that period,and the Minister shall exercise his&quot; powers under this subsection 40in respect of each period with a view to securing that, as nearly as conveniently may be, the said Transport Fund will, over thatperiod, be sufficient and not more than sufficient to meet thepayments falling to be made therefrom.The power conferred on the Minister by this subsection to 45make orders shall be exercisable by statutory instrument and no
order shall be made by the Minister under this subsection unless   aW. 1$52a draft thereof has been laid before Parliament and has beenapproved by resolution of each House of Parliament.(4) The number referred to in this section as &quot; the appropriate5 multiplier &quot; is the number arrived at under the second column of the Table in Part I, or, as the case may be, the fourth andfifth columns of the Table in Part III, of the Second Schedule to,.this Act by reference to the weight unladen of the vehicle, plus,in the case of a vehicle of the description specified in the first.10 column of the Table in Part I of that Schedule which is usedfor drawing a trailer, that one of the numbers in the thirdcolumn of the Table in Part II of that Schedule which is appro-priate; having regard to the weight unladen of that vehicle. - . ,(5) Sections eight, nine, eleven to fifteen and twenty-one to15 twenty-five of the Vehicles (Excise) Act, 1949 (which containprovisions as to the collection of the excise duties under thatAct and as to other connected matters), shall have effect as if&quot;the transport levy payable in the case of a vehicle for any periodwere part of the duty payable under that Act in respect of that20 vehicle for that period and as if, where a licence is in force ....ieon the appointed day with respect to a vehicle chargeable with nbifzneilthe levy, the use of the vehicle on a public road in Great Britain; .inon or after the appointed day and before the end of the period covered by the licence were, within the meaning of subsection;25 (1) of section thirteen of that Act, a use thereof for a purpose,bringing it within a class or description of vehicle to which ahigher rate of duty (that is to say, the rate arrived at by -increasing the annual amount of the duty by the product of the\unit charge and the appropriate multiplier) was applicable under j30 that Act:Provided that- . -(a) the transport levy paid to a council in respect of anyvehicle shall be paid by it to the Minister in accordancewith such directions as may be contained in any Order35 in Council made under the said section eight instead.&apos;,of being paid into the Exchequer; and&apos;    Cb) the power conferred by the said section twenty-five to;,make regulations for the purpose of carrying that Act -into effect shall include power to make regulations for,40      .      the purpose of carrying this section into effect.Any increase attributable to this subsection in the sums which,-!under section twenty-four of the Vehicles (Excise) Act, 1949, fall to be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament shall be paid;,out of moneys so provided.45    (6) In the case of each Government Department other thaiMthe Admiralty, the War Department and the Air Ministry, there;;shall be paid to the Minister for each year out of moneys pro-vided by Parliament such sum, if any, as the Minister may
A.D. 1952 estimate to be the total amount, or, as the case may be, thetotal additional amount, which would have been payable by wayof the transport levy in respect of vehicles used for the purposesof that Department in that year if the excise duties under the vehicles (Excise) Act, 1949, had been chargeable in respect of 5GroWn vehicles.In this subsection &quot; Government Department&quot; means a department or body the salaries or expenses of which are thesubject of a payment from moneys provided by Parliament, notbeing a payment by way of grant in aid. 10(7) In this section, &quot; public road &quot; has the same meaning asin the Vehicles (Excise) Act, 1949, and subsections (4) and (5)of section five of that Act (which relate to super-imposed vehicles and the meaning of the word &quot; trailer &quot;) and section twenty-six of that Act (which relates to the computation of the unladen 15weight of vehicles and other matters) shall apply for the deter-mination of the transport levy payable in respect of a vehicleas they apply for-the determination of the excise duty payable in respect thereof.Establishment     11. (1) There shall be established a fund under the control 20of Transport   and management of the Minister, to be known as &quot; the TransportFund. Fund,&quot; into which all sums paid to the Minister under the last preceding section either by councils or out of moneys providedby Parliament shall be paid, and out of which there shall be :made the payments provided for by the other provisions of this 25Act (and in particular by the two next following sections) and payments to the Commission equal to so much of the paymentsfalling to be made by the Commission under&apos; the provisions ofthis Act relating to compensation to officers and servants as isascribable to the duties imposed by this Act on the Commission 30as to the disposal of the property held by the Commission forthe purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking.(2) If it appears to the Minister that the Transport Fund willbe insufficient for the time being to meet the payments falling to be made therefrom, he may, within the period of twelve 35months following the passing of this Act, pay into the Fund, outof moneys provided by Parliament, sums not exceeding in allfifty thousand pounds, but sums equal to the sums so paid intothe&apos; Fund shall, as soon as the resources of the Fund are suffi-cient for the purpose, be paid out of the Fund into the 40Exchequer.(3) Any sums standing to the credit of the Transport fund which are not for the time being required for the purpose ofmaking payments out of the Fund may be invested by theMinister in such securities as may be approved by the Treasury, 45and any income arising therefrom shall be paid into the Fund.
(4) The Minister shall, as respects each.year, prepare, in such a.d. 1952form and manner as the Treasury may direct, an account of allsums paid into or out of the Transport Fund, and each suchaccount shall, on or before the first day of July next follow-5 ing the expiration of the year to which it relates, be transmitted to the Comptroller and Auditor General, who shall examine andcertify the account and lay copies thereof, together with his report thereon, before each House of Parliament.12. (1) An amount equal to- Payments to10       (a) the road haulage capital loss as defined in subsection (4) Commissionlot&quot; this section ; plus Transportib) such amount, if any, as in the opinion of the Minister Pund forrepresents any unavoidable loss of net revenue incurred J^i^i 0fby the Commission during the transitional period as a roa(i haulage15 result of disturbance of the existing road haulage undertaking,undertaking,shall be paid out of the Transport Fund to the Commission by such instalments as are hereinafter mentioned, that is to say (i) the first instalment shall be paid on the first day of20 January immediately following the end of the transi-tional period and the subsequent instalments shall bepaid on the first day of January in each subsequentyear until the whole amount is paid ; and(ii) subject as hereinafter provided, the instalments shall be25 equal instalments paid over such period as may bedetermined by the Minister:Provided that the Minister shall, not later than three months before the end of the transitional period, make a provisional estimate of the total amount falling to be paid as aforesaid30 and a provisional determination of the said period, and shallfrom time to time revise that estimate, and, if he thinks thatthe variations in his estimates warrant that course, also thatdetermination and -(a) the instalments from time to time payable shall be cal-35 culated and paid by reference to the latest estimate and determination for the time being; and(b) if, on a revision of the estimate or the determination, itappears that too little or too much has been paid, the subsequent instalments shall be adjusted as the Minister40 may direct in order to make good the excess ordeficiency.(2) The Minister-(a) in making or revising any such estimate as aforesaid,shall, as respects the road haulage capital loss, consult45 the auditor or auditors of the Commission who shall
16 Transport 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952 furnish him with such information and certificates ashe may require, and shall, as respects the amountreferred to in paragraph (b) of subsection (1) of thisseotion, consult the Commission and the Treasury;(b) in determining the period over which the instalments  5are to be paid and in revising any determination thereof,shall act with the approval of the Treasury.(3) If at any time the Transport Fund is for the time being more than sufficient to make all the payments which have become due to be paid therefrom, such sum, if any, as the 10Minister may direct shall be paid therefrom to the Commission,and where any payment is made under this subsection, the total amount falling to be paid under subsection (1) of this section shall be deemed to be reduced by the amount of the payment and the said total amount shall be estimated or re-estimated 15accordingly.A direction may be given under this subsection either before or after the end of the transitional period but not later than thepayment of the final instalment under subsection (1) of thissection, and, where the direction is given after any estimate has 20been made under the proviso to that subsection, the amountdirected to be paid shall not exceed the total amount of theinstalments remaining to be paid, calculated by reference to thelatest such estimate.(4) In this section &quot; the road haulage capital loss &quot; means the 25  ,amount by which the aggregate of the prices at which property is sold under section three or subsection (1) or subsection (2) ofsection five of this Act falls short of the sum of the followingamounts, that is to say-  -.(a) the aggregate net value of that property as at the times 30of the respective sales, as shown in the books of theCommission but adjusted so as to take into accountdepreciation up to the time of the sale so far as not already taken into account; and(b) the expenses incurred by the Commission in connection 35with those sales, so far as not included in the sumsshown in the books of the Commission as expenses. deductible in computing the sums shown therein asnet traffic receipts; and(c) such sums as may be just in respect of any sums paid 49or liabilities incurred by&apos; the Commission before the sales for rights or benefits which, as the result of the sales, are not, or are not wholly enjoyed by the Com-mission; and
W) so much of the sums shown in the balance sheets of the   A.D. 1952Commission as good will as is ascribable to the existingroad haulage undertaking and is not otherwise takeninto, account under this subsection ; and5 (e) any losses incurred by the Commission in respect of contracts entered into by them for the purposes of theexisting road haulage undertaking, being losses incurredas the result of the disposal of the property held bythe Commission for the purposes thereof and not being10 losses which could reasonably have been avoided by theCommission:Provided that, if any property held by the Commission forthe purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking is trans-ferred by them to a company under section four of this Act,15 or is retained by them under section five of this Act, the amountsarrived at under paragraphs (d) and (e) of this subsection shallbe reduced by so much thereof respectively as is properlyapportionable to the property so transferred or retained.In this subsection, &quot; price &quot;, in relation to property sold under20 section three of this Act, includes a reference to all sums forwhich the purchaser becomes liable as the result of his purchaseof the transport unit in question, irrespective of whether the sums are ascribable to property or to other rights which heobtains as the result of his purchase, &quot; net value &quot; means value25 after deducting depreciation, and the references to values andsums shown in the books or balance sheets of the commission are references to the values and&quot; sums so shown after makingall necessary adjustments of provisional items and, if the Coin-mission in keeping their books or making up their balance30 sheet for any year falling wholly or partly after the passing ofthis Act depart in any material respect from the principles and practice applied by them for the years falling before the passingof this Act, all adjustments which are necessary to produce theresult which would have been produced-but for the departure.35 (5) Interest shall be paid out of the Transport Fund to theCommission at such times as the Minister may direct on so muchof the amount required to be paid therefrom by subsection (1)of this section as is due and remains unpaid and, for the pur-poses of this subsection 40       (a) the whole of the said amount shall be deemed to have become due at the end.of the transitional period; and (b)) the proviso to the said subsection (1) shall, with any necessary adaptations, apply in relation to the payments of interest as it applies in relation to the instalments,
A.D. 1952      13. (1) As soon as may be after the end of each of thePayments to following periods, that is to say -ou^of1 Trans ^ ^e Per*oc* Q^ tw0 years beginning with the first dayport Fund   &quot; &apos; Q^ January, nineteen hundred and fifty-three ; andin respect of (b) &quot;each subsequent period of three years, 5revenue1 dueTo tne Minister shall obtain from the permanent members of transfer of the Transport Tribunal, acting as a consultative committee, antraffic from estimate of the average annual loss of net railway revenuerail to road.    for that period caused to the Commission by users of theservices provided by the Commission for the carriage of goods 10by rail having, since the first day of January, nineteen hundredand fifty-three, discontinued or ourtailed their use of those services and instead availed themselves of services for the carriage of goods by road.(2) In making any such estimate the permanent members 15of the Transport Tribunal shall (a) have regard to any evidence produced to them as to theextent to which persons have discontinued or curtailedtheir use of services provided by the Commission forthe carriage of goods by rail and instead availed them- 20selves of services for the carriage of goods by road, and,the extent to which that discontinuance or curtailmenthas led to a loss of net railway revenue and, in particu-lar, to any changes in the number of vehicles authorisedunder A, B and C licences, and in the volume of the 25traffic carried by rail, due allowance being made forvariations in the general level of production and tradein Great Britain ; and(b) disregard any loss of net railway revenue which theCommission could have avoided by economies which 30they could reasonably have effected in consequence ofthe discontinuance or curtailment:Provided that, in the case of any period other than the first period, the members of the Tribunal shall not enter again into any matters considered by them in making their estimate for any 35previous period and, save as provided by subsection (4) of thissection, shall proceed upon the basis that their conclusions asto those matters, in so far as they are still relevant and applic-able, were correct.(3) For the purpose of enabling the permanent members of 40the Transport Tribunal to make any such estimate as aforesaid,the president or acting president of the Tribunal shall have thesame powers as respects the attendance and examination of- witnesses and the production and inspection of documents asthe Tribunal have for the purposes of the exercise of their 45functions as such, and when the permanent members of the
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Elk. 2Tribunal have made their estimate for any period, they shall   A.D. 1952transmit that estimate to the Minister, together with such astatement of their reasons for arriving at that estimate as theythink fit, and the Minister shall lay a copy of their estimate and5 their statement before each House of Parliament.(4) Subject to the provisions of this subsection, on the first day of July in each of the three years next following the endof the period for which such an estimate as aforesaid has beentransmitted to the Minister, there shall become due to be paid10 to the Commission out of the Transport Fund an amount equalto the amount of the estimate:Provided that if the Minister, after consultation with thepermanent members of the Tribunal, is of opinion that, in makingthe estimate, any loss falling to be disregarded under paragraph15 (b) of subsection (2) of this section has not been disregarded,he shall lay a statement to that effect before each&apos; House ofParliament, setting out his conclusions and specifying the amount&apos; by which in his opinion the estimate is in consequence excessive,and the amount which becomes due as aforesaid to be paid to20 the Commission out of the Transport Fund on the first day ofJuly in each of the three years in the period next following theperiod for which the estimate was given shall be reduced bythe amount specified in the Ministers statement.Where the Minister lays before Parliament such a statement25 as aforesaid, the reference in the proviso to subsection (2) ofthis section to the conclusions of the permanent members of theTribunal shall, as respects the loss in question, be construed asa reference to their conclusions modified to such extent as maybe necessary to give effect to the conclusions of the Minister .30 set out in his statement.(5) In this section &quot; net railway revenue &quot; means, in relation toany period, the gross revenue arising to the Commission for thatperiod from the operation of their railways less sums properlychargeable to revenue account for that period as expenses of-35 the operation thereof, and the references to a loss of net railwayrevenue caused to the Commission shall be construed as refer-ences to the amount by which the net railway revenue of theCommission falls short of what would have been their netrailway revenue but for the operation of the cause in question:40 Provided that if the gross revenue arising to the commission for any period from the operation of their railways is less thanthe sums properly chargeable to revenue account for that period as expenses of the operation thereof, there shall be deemed tobe net railway revenue for that period of a negative amount45 equal to the difference, and the losses of net railway revenue. shall be calculated accordingly.
A.D. 1952 References in this subsection to the gross revenue arising tothe Commission from the operation of their railways shall bedeemed to include references to such sums, if any, as properlyrepresent the annual value obtained by the Commission from capital assets formerly used for the operation of their railways 5which have been diverted by the Commission to other uses orfrom the proceeds, or property representing the proceeds, ofcapital assets formerly so used which have been sold or otherwiserealised by the Commission.(6) Interest shall be paid out of the Transport Fund to the 10: Commission at such times as the Minister may direct on somuch of any amount payable under subsection (4) of this sectionas has become due and is unpaid.(7) Any reference in this section to the provision of services for the carriage of goods by road includes a reference  15(a) to the provision of such services by the Commission ; and(6) to the provision of facilities by the holder of a C licence for the carriage of goods for or in connection with any trade or business carried on by him.(8) The references in this section to the operation of the Com- 20mission&apos;s railways do not include references to the collection ordelivery of goods carried or to be carried thereon.Supplemental      14. (1) In this section and in the three last preceding provisions as to sections tlircc Isstpreceding &quot; the transitional period &quot; means the period beginning with 25sections. the first day of January, nineteen hundred, and fifty-three, and ending at the end of the year in which sectionfifty-two of the Transport Act, 1947, ceases to haveeffect;&quot; year &quot; means a period of twelve months beginning with 30the first day of January.(2) Any reference in this or the two last preceding sections to interest shall be construed as a reference to interest at suchrate as may from time to time be fixed by directions of theTreasury, and the rate fixed, by any such direction shall be such 35as would in the opinion of the Treasury be appropriate forsecurities the principal of which and the interest on which wascharged on the Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom orthe growing produce thereof, being securities issued at par atthe time when the direction was given and redeemable twenty 40years after their issue.(3) K at any time the Transport Fund is insufficient to make all the payments which have become due to be paid therefrom,&quot;   the payments shall be made as soon as the Fund becomes
/sufficient for the purpose, and, as between such payments, A.D. 1952priority shall be given, first, to the salaries, allowances and ex-penses of the Board, next, to the payments into the Exchequerrequired by subsection (2) of section eleven of this Act, next,5 to payments of interest, next, to payments to the Commissionin respect of compensation paid by them to officers and servants,and next to payments under the last preceding section otherthan payments of interest.Reorganisation of Railways10    15. (1) Within twelve months from the passing of this Act Re-or such longer period as the Minister may allow, the commissioners- organisationsion shall prepare and submit to the Minister a scheme for the of railways-reorganisation of that part of their undertaking which consists in the operation of the railways.15    (2) The said scheme shall provide (a) for the abolition (if it has not already been abolished)of the Railway Executive; and(b) for the setting up, for such areas as may be specified by or under the scheme, of such authorities as may20 be so specified; and(c) for the delegation to those authorities of such functionsof the Commission relating to that part of their under-taking as may be so specified in relation to those authorities respectively.25    (3) The said scheme may provide (a) for the setting up of other authorities and for the dele-gation to them of such functions of the Commissionrelating to that part of their undertaking as may be specified by or under the scheme, being functions which30 appear to the Commission or, as the case may be, to theMinister, to be unsuitable for delegation to ah authorityset up for a particular area ;(b) for the setting up for the purpose (i) of co-ordinating the exercise and performance35               of their functions by all or any of the authorities setup under the scheme, whether for areas of otherwise ;and(ii) of making provision for matters of common interest to all or any of those authorities,40 of co-ordinating authorities. .,(4) The said scheme may provide for regulating-(a) the relations of the authorities set up under the scheme with each other;
22 Transport 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952 (b) the relations of those authorities with the Commission;and(c) the relations of those authorities with persons other thanthe Commission,and for giving to the Commission such powers of control over  5those authorities as may be specified by or under the scheme.(5) The authorities to be set up under the scheme may beindividuals or bodies of persons, whether, corporate or un-incorporated, and the scheme may provide for the incorporation of any of those authorities. 10(6) The scheme may-(a) entrust to any authority set up under the scheme, orotherwise deal with, functions of the Commission not concerned or directly concerned with the operation ofthe railways if it appears to the Commission or, as 15the case may be, to the Minister, to be necessary or expedient that those matters should be entrusted tothose authorities or so dealt with by the scheme; .(b) authorise any such authority set up for an area to operate, as respects particular matters specified by or 20under the scheme, outside its own area either con-currently with, or to the exclusion of, the authority, ifany, within the area of which the operation takes place;(c) contain such incidental, consequential and transitional provisions as may appear as aforesaid to be necessary 25or expedient, including provisions amending or apply-ing, with or without modifications, any statutory provision.(7) Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shallbe taken to require that all functions of the Commission relating 30to the operation of the railways shall be entrusted to authoritiesset up under the scheme or as requiring that all functions ofthe Commission relating to the operation of the railways shallbe dealt with in the scheme, and, in particular, the scheme shallbe such as will, in the opinion of the Commission or, as the case 35may be, of the Minister, reserve to the Commission general financial control and general control of the charges to be madefor the services and facilities provided under the scheme.(8) In relation to Scotland, for the requirement in paragraph(b) of subsection (2) of this section there shall be substituted a 40requirement that the scheme shall provide for an authority forthe whole of Scotland (with or without authorities for areas inScotland) and, in relation to the authority for the whole of Scot-land, references to Scotland, shall, in the provisions of this sectionsubsequent to the said subsection (2), be substituted for the refer- 45ences to the areas of the authorities set up under the said sub-section (2).
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 eliz. 2(9) In the preceding provisions of this section, &quot; the railways &quot;   A,D. 1952does not include the railways the operation of which forms partof the passenger transport services provided at the passing ofthis Act fey the London Transport Executive.5    16. (1) On any scheme under the last preceding section being Approval and submitted to the Minister, the Minister shall consider the scheme amendment ofand may by order approve the scheme either without modifica- re-organisationtion or with such modifications as he may, after consultation with schemes-the Commission, think fit, andi the scheme, as so approved, shall10 come into effect as from such date as may be specified therein.(2) Any such scheme as aforesaid may be amended or revokedby a subsequent scheme prepared and submitted by the Com-mission or by an order of the Minister made after consultationwith the Commission, and the preceding provisions of this section15 shall have effect in relation to any such subsequent scheme.(3) The references in subsection (2) of this section to theamendment of a scheme include references to the revocationthereof and the substitution of a new scheme, and any schemeso substituted shall be deemed to be a scheme under the last20 preceding section.(4) The power conferred by this section on the Minister tomake orders shall be exercisable by statutory instrument, andany such statutory instrument shall be subject to annulment inpursuance of a resolution of either House of Parliament.25 (5) Before exercising his powers under this section in any caseaffecting Scotland, the Minister shall consult the Seoretary ofState for Scotland.Road passenger transport, trade harbours and port facilities17. (1) Sections sixty-three and sixty-four of the Transport Repeals and30 Act, 1947 (which relate to area schemes as to passenger road amendmentstransport services), are hereby repealed. relating to the^ Commission s(2) Subject to the provisions of subsection (4) of this section, functions withsections seventy-two to seventy-six of the Road Traffic Act, 1930 If^nUr r.....       J        ,        . - ,. ,   ,   ,,       , passengei(which relate to road service licences), shall apply to passenger transport.35 road transport services provided by the Commission as they apply to passenger road transport services provided by other persons, and subsections (1), (3) and (4) of section sixty-five ofthe Transport Act, 1947 (which exempt services of the Com-mission from the said sections seventy-two to seventy-six and40 impose and confer on the commission certain functions inrespect of road passenger transport services provided by them)shall cease to have effect:
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952Provided that (a) any passenger road transport service which is being pro-vided by the Commission at the passing of this Actshall, for one month from the passing thereof, and,if within that month an application for the necessary 5road service licence is duly made to the licensing authority for public service vehicles, until that appli-cation is determined by the licensing authority, be exempt from the operation of the preceding provisions(b) any enactment in force at the end of the year nineteenhundred and forty-seven which authorised any of the bodies mentioned in the Third Schedule to the Trans-port Act, 1947, to construct and maintain shelters,buildings or barriers shall have the same effect in 15relation to the Commission as it would have if sub-section (4) of the said section sixty-five had not been enacted.(3) Subject to the provisions of subsection (4) of this section,it shall not be lawful for the Commission to run any public 20service vehicle as a contract carriage.(4) The following provisions (being an adaptation of pro-visions contained in section fifteen of the London passenger transport Act, 1933, which, until the coming into force of theTransport Act, 1947, applied to the London Passenger Transport 25Board) shall apply to the Commission (a) it shall be lawful for the Commission to run any publicservice vehicle as a contract carriage on roads withinthe London Passenger Transport Area and roads out-side that area within a radius of ten miles, or, in the 30County of Kent, five miles, from any point on the boundary of that area ;(b) sections seventy-two to seventy-six of the Road traffic act, 1930, shall not apply to a road service providedby the Commission wholly within the London special 35area, and, in the case of a road service provided bythe Commission partly within and partly without theLondon special area, shall not apply to that service inso far as it is within the London special area ;(c) ,the licensing. authority for public service vehicles, in 40considering whether they will grant or back a roadservice licence to the Commission in respect of any .route or part of a route which is outside the Londonspecial area, shall, in addition to the matters to whichthey are required to have regard by virtue of section 45of this subsection ;10
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp;j. Eliz. 2seventy-two of the Road Traffic Act, 1930, have regard   a.d. 1952to the duty of the Commission to provide or securethe provision of an adequate and properly co-ordinatedsystem of passenger transport for the London passenger and for the avoidance of doubt it is hereby declared that sub-section (2) of section twenty-six of the London Passenger Trans-port Act, 1933 (which relates to charges and fares), has effect,in the case of a public service vehicle operating wholly or in10 part outside the London special area, subject, as respects anypart of the service outside that area, to the provisions of section-seventy-two of the Road Traffic Act, 1930.(5) Notwithstanding anything in subsection (2) of section twoof the Transport Act, 1947,-15 (a) the Commission shall not have power to acquire(whether absolutely or for any period) the whole orany part of any undertaking of any other person if theactivities of that undertaking, or that part thereof, asthe case may be, consist wholly or mainly in the pro-20 vision of passenger road transport services ;(b) the Commission shall not, without the consent of theMinister, acquire any securities the acquisition of whichwould bring under the direct or indirect control of theCommission a body corporate which is carrying on or25 is about to carry on an undertaking the activities ofwhich consist wholly or mainly in the provision of passenger road transport services.(6) Where-(a) the Commission directly or indirectly control a body30 corporate which is carrying on or is about to carry onan undertaking the activities whereof consist wholly or mainly in the provision of passenger road transport services; andis a result of disposing of any securities the Commis-sion would no longer have any control, whether director indirect over that body corporate.then, without prejudice to any other power of the Minister to: give directions to the Commission, the Minister may direct theCommission to dispose of those securities at such times and in40 such manner as may be specified in the direction, and it shallbe the duty of the Commission to comply with that direction.(7) The Commission shall not, without the permission of theMinister, cause or permit the voluntary liquidation of any body corporate directly or indirectly under their control which is45 carrying on an undertaking the activities whereof consist whollyor mainly in the provision of passenger road transport services.5Transport Area,
15 &amp; 16 Geo.&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952Tradeharboursand port facilities.(8) Passenger road&apos; transport services provided by any body corporate which is directly or indirectly controlled by the Com-mission shall be deemed for the purposes of section six of theTransport Act, 1947 (which relates to Consultative Committees),to be provided by the Commission. 518. (1) Sections sixtynsix to sixty-eight of the Transport Act,1947 (which relate to schemes as to trade harbours), are herebyrepealed.(2) The Commission shall not, after the passing of this Act,provide port facilities in any place in which they were not 10providing port facilities on the first day of July, nineteen hundredand fifty-two.amendments as to chargesschemes.Charges19. (1) The charges made by the Commission which areto be determined by or under charges schemes under Part V 15of the Transport Act. 1947. shall be the following and no other charges, that is to say (a) charges for the carriage of goods or passengers by rail-way or inland waterway ;(b) charges (including wharfage charges) for the use of 20inland waterways;(c) dock charges ;(d) charges for the carriage of passengers by road on routeswholly or partly within the London special area, notbeing carriage in contract carriages ; and 25(e) such other charges, if any, as, by reason of their con-nection with any of the charges aforesaid, should inthe opinion of the Commission be dealt with by acharges scheme,and, without prejudice to the generality of the preceding proyi- 30sions of this sub-section, the duty imposed by section seventy-six of that Act on the Commission to prepare and submit drafts of ;charges schemes shall be limited accordingly:Provided that no fares for any service or part of a service which is the subject of a road service licence shall be made the 35subject of any charges scheme after the passing of this Act andany fares which are the subject of a charges scheme in force at the passing of this Act shall cease to be subject thereto onthe service or part of a service to which they relate becoming thesubject of a road service licence. . 40(2) Any charges scheme submitted after the passing ofthis Act (including any such scheme revoking or amendinga previous scheme) shall, as respects the services and facilities
15&amp;16GEO. 6 Transport 27&amp; 1 Eliz. 2to which it relates, comply with the following requirements, that A.D. 1952is to say (a) it shall not provide  for fixed charges or standard; &apos; charges;&quot;5       (b) it shall fix maximum charges in all cases in which itappears practicable to fix maximum charges ;(c) in cases in which no maximum charge is fixed, it shallauthorise the Commission to make such charges asmay be reasonable and provide for any question as to10 the reasonableness of any such charge being determinedby the Transport Tribunal, to the exclusion of anyother court;(d) it shall, save as aforesaid, leave the charges to be madeto the Commission^ discretion without imposing con-    ;15 ditions or limitations thereon, other than conditionsas to the publication of charges ; and(e) the provision which it makes for through charges shallibe such as may be appropriate having regard to thepreceding paragraphs of this subsection,20 and section seventy-seven of the Transport Act, 1947, shall, as respects charges, be limited accordingly.(3) Rules made by the Transport Tribunal under section twenty-two of the Railways Act, 1921, may (a) authorise or provide for authorising the Commission, on25 such terms, if any, as may be specified by or underthe rules (i) to submit provisional proposals as respects anyof the matters which will fall to be dealt with underthe scheme, and, in particular, proposals as respects30 the classification of merchandise, or the terms andconditions applicable to the services and facilities which will fall to be dealt with under the scheme;i(ii) to submit to the Tribunal a request for guidance on such questions of principle affecting the scheme as35 may be specified in the request;(b) provide for the publication of any proposals or requestso submitted, for the making of objections and repre-sentations and the holding of inquiries with respectthereto, and for the provisional or. final decision by the40 Tribunal of all or any of the matters or questions:    referred to or specified therein ;;(c) prohibit, to such extent as may be specified by or underthe rules,, objections and other representations beingmade with respect to the scheme on grounds on which45 objections and other representations might have beenmade with respect to the proposals or request,
to which it relates, comply with the following requirements, that A.D. 1952is to say (a) it shall not provide  for fixed charges or standard... charges;&quot;5       (b) it shall fix maximum charges in all cases in which itappears practicable to fix maximum charges;(c) in cases in which no maximum charge is fixed, it shallauthorise the Commission to make such charges asmay be reasonable and provide for any question as to10 the reasonableness of any such charge being determinedby the Transport Tribunal, to the exclusion of anyother court;(d) it shall, save as aforesaid, leave the charges to be madeto the Commission^ discretion without imposing con-15 ditions or limitations thereon, other than conditionsas to the publication of charges; and(e) the provision which it makes for through charges shallfbe such as may be appropriate having regard to thepreceding paragraphs of this subsection,20 and section seventy-seven of the Transport Act, 1947, shall, as respects charges, be limited accordingly.(3) Rules made by the Transport Tribunal under section twenty-two of the Railways Act, 1921, may id) authorise or provide for authorising the Commission, on25 such terms, if any, as may be specified by or underthe rules (i) to submit provisional proposals as respects anyof the matters which will fall to be dealt with underthe scheme, and, in particular, proposals as respects30 the classification of merchandise, or the terms andconditions applicable to the services and facilities which will fall to be dealt with under the scheme;i(ii) to submit to the Tribunal a request for guidance on such questions of principle affecting the scheme as35 may be specified in the request&apos;;(b) provide for the publication of any proposals or requestso submitted, for the making of objections and repre-sentations and the holding of inquiries with respectthereto, and for the provisional or final decision by the40 Tribunal of all or any of the matters or questions referred to or specified therein ;ic) prohibit, to such extent as may be specified by or underthe rules, objections and other representations beingmade with respect to the scheme on grounds on which45 objections and other representations might have beenmade with respect to the proposals or request,
0)   150A.D. 1952Specialprovisions asto charges for carriage of goods.and the submission of any such proposal or request in accordancewith rules shall, unless the Tribunal or the Minister otherwisedirect, be deemed for the purposes of so much of section seventy-six of the Transport Act, 1947, as imposes on the Commission a limit of time to prepare and submit the draft of a scheme or 5schemes to be the submission of a draft of the scheme inquestion.i(4) References in this section to charges for the carriage ofgoods by railway or inland waterway do not include references to collection and delivery charges, but nothing in this subsection 10shall prevent collection and delivery charges being dealt with under paragraph (e) of subsection (1) of this section.20. (1) Notwithstanding anything in subsection (5) of section seventy-eight of the Transport Act, 1947 (which provides, among other things, that charges schemes are to have effect notwith-15standing anything in any statutory provisions relating to thesubject matter of the schemes), any charges scheme made afterthe passing of this Act shall, so far as it relates to the followingcharges (in this section referred to as &quot; charges to which thissection applies &quot;), that is to say  20(a)&apos; charges for the carriage of goods ; and!ib) such other charges, if any (including collection and delivery charges), as may be declared by the scheme tobe.charges which ought, by reason of their connectionwith such charges as aforesaid, to be treated as charges 25to which this section applies,have effect subject to the following provisions of this section.(2) Where, in the opinion of a person carrying on business as a carrier of goods for hire or reward or of a body representingany class of persons carrying on business as aforesaid, any 30charges to which this section applies made by the commission are being made at a rate (a) which is less than that of the maximum charge, if any,applicable under the scheme ; and (b)) which, if continued, must result in a loss to the Com- 35mission,and are being so made with a view to eliminating competition,he or they may complain to the Transport Tribunal, and theTransport Tribunal may make such order as to the charges whichare to be made by the (Commission as the Tribunal may think fit. 40(3) Subject to the provisions of the next following subsection,in the exercise of any discretion reserved to them by a charges scheme as respects charges to which this section applies, the Com-mission shall be subject to (a) the enactments relating to equality of charges referred 45to in subsection (1) of section seventy-four of the Trans-port Act, 1947; and
15115 &amp; 16 Geo. 6 Transport 29&amp; 1 Eliz. 2(b) so much of section two of the Railway and Canal Traffic   a.D. 1952Act, 1854, or any statutory provision passed or madewith respect to any particular undertaking, as prohibitsthe according of undue preference to persons, com-5 panies or descriptions of traffic ; and(c) section thirty-seven of the Railway and Canal traffic act, 1888 (which relates to complaints with respectto undue preference) in its application to inland, water- -ways as well as to railways.10 (4) Section thirty-seven of the Road and Rail Traffic Act*1933 (which relates to agreed charges fixed under that section on the application of traders) shall apply in relation to charges to which this section applies as if the references in subsection (1)of that section to the Railways Act, 1921, and to the grant- of15 exceptional rates included respectively references to any charges scheme and to the exercise of a discretion conferred on the Com-mission by any charges scheme to make charges less than themaximum charges.21. i(l) The charges to be made in default of agreement Amendments20 between the Commission or railway company concerned and of Cheapthe Secretary of State, Admiralty or police authority for any ^&apos;ns Arct-conveyance provided in pursuance of section six of the Cheap     &apos;s&apos;Trains Act, 1883, shall be charges at such rates as may from timeto time be determined by the Transport Tribunal on the applica-25 tion of the Commission or railway company concerned or of theSecretary of State, Admiralty or police authority, and paragraphs(ii) to (v) of subsection (1) of that section (except so much ofparagraph (iii) thereof as applies that section to wives, widows and children) shall cease to have effect.30 (2) Any increase in the sums payable out of moneys providedby Parliament which is attributable to the amendments of thesaid section six effected by this section shall be paid out of moneys so provided.(3) This section shall come into force on the appointed day.35    22. .(1) If it appears to the Commission that it is necessary Power ofto increase their charges in order to meet an increase in their Commissioncosts which in their opinion will, unless met quickly, seriously to m^eaffect their financial position, and that the necessary increase in fncrejfses oftheir revenue cannot reasonably be obtained without increasing charges in40 some or all of their charges above the maximum charges fixed advance of by a charges scheme as for the time being in force, they may alteration of increase-.     . . &quot;        gjjg^&apos; ia) all their charges for the time being in force for the carriage of goods by rail, being charges subject to a-45 charges scheme, for the time being in force ; or
)S10)30 Transport 15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Elk. 2A.D. 1.952 (6) all their charges for the time being in force for the carriage of passengers by rail or by road, being chargessubject to a charges scheme for the time being in force ;or(c) all their said charges for the carriage of goods and all 5their said charges for the carriage of passengers,,by a fixed percentage thereof respectively.The references in this subsection to charges for the carriage of goods by rail (i) include references to any charges which, in the opinion 10of the Commission, ought to be treated for the purposesof this section as part of their charges for the carriage of goods by rail, including such, but only such, col-lection and&apos; delivery charges as ought in the opinion ofthe Commission to be so treated ; but 15(ii) do not include references to agreed charges undersection thirty-seven of the Road and Rail Traffic Act,1933 or charges fixed under that section by theTransport Tribunal,but the exclusion by this provision of the said agreed charges 20and charges so fixed shall not affect any provision of the relevantagreement or determination of the Tribunal, being a provisionby virtue of which the charge is increased in the event of anincrease in other charges.The references in this subsection to charges for the carriage of 25passengers by rail do not include references to charges at ratesagreed under section six of the Cheap Trains Act, 1883, ordetermined by the Transport Tribunal under the last preceding section, but the exclusion by this provision of charges at ratesagreed or determined as aforesaid shall not affect any provision 30of the relevant agreement or determination of the Tribunal,being a provision by virtue of which the charge is increased inthe event of an increase in other charges.(2) Where the Commission make an increase under subsection(1) of this section, the percentage fixed in the case of that 35increase &apos;(a) shall not exceed ten per cent.; and(b) shall-(i) where the increase affects only the chargesmentioned in paragraph (a) of subsection (1) of this 40section or only the charges mentioned in paragraph(b) of that subsection, be the same for all the chargesaffected by the increase; &apos;      -(ii) where the increase affects both the chargesmentioned in the said paragraph (a) and the charges 45
I  315 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2Transport31mentioned in the said paragraph (b), be either the   A.D. 1952same for all the charges or the same for the chargesmentioned in the said paragraphs  (a) and (6)respectively,5 and those charges, as increased by the percentage so fixed, shallbe made accordingly:Provided that, where the increase, as arrived at by applying thepercentage, consists of or includes a fraction of a penny, then (a) in the case of a charge for the carriage of passengers by10 rail or by road wholly within the London passenger transport Area, the fraction of a penny shall, if it is less than a halfpenny, be left out of account and, if itis a halfpenny or more, be deemed to be a penny ; and(b) in any other case, the fraction of a penny shall, if it is15 less than a farthing, be left out of account, if it is notless than a farthing but less than three farthings, bedeemed, to be a halfpenny and, if it is not less than threefarthings, be deemed to be a penny.(3) Where the Commission have made an increase under sub-20 section (D&quot;of this section, they shall as soon as may be applyunder section seventy-nine of the Transport Act, 1947, for an alteration of the relevant charges scheme or schemes, and the proviso to subsection (1) of the said section seventy-nine (which prevents the Tribunal from entertaining applications under that25 section unless certain conditions are complied with) shall notapply to any application so made.For the avoidance of doubt it is hereby declared that an altera-tion applied for in pursuance of this subsection need not coverall or any of the increases made under subsection (1) of this30 section, may authorise greater increases than all or any of thoseincreases and may relate to charges not affected by thoseincreases.(4) When the Tribunal determine any application made inpursuance of subsection (3) of this section, they shall fix a date,35 which shall be the earliest date which in their opinion is prac-ticable, as from which no charge shall be made by virtue of theincrease which cannot be made under the relevant charges scheme as altered (if it is altered) in pursuance of the application.(5) Where the Commission have exercised their powers under40 subsection (1) of this section-to) they shall not again exercise their powers thereunderuntil the relevant application made in pursuance of subsection (3) of this section has been determined bythe Tribunal;45       (b) after that application has been so determined, they shallnot be entitled to exercise the s^id powers by reason
Amendments as to general duty and constitution of commission, etc. 10Amendments      23.-41) For subsections (1) to (3) of section three of theduty and      Transport Act, 1947 (which relates to the general duty of theconstitution of Commission), there shall be substituted the following subsection  . ,Commission, &quot; (j) it shall be the general duty of the Commission, in theetc&apos; exercise of their powers under this Act  15(a) to provide railway services for Great Britain ;(b) to provide or secure the provision of anadequate and properly co-ordinated system of passenger transport for the London Passenger Trans-port Area; 20(c) to provide, in such places and to such extent as may appear to the Commission to be expedient,other transport services and facilities for traffic oninland waterways; and(d) to provide, in such places (being places in which 25they were providing port facilities on the first day ofJuly, nineteen hundred and fifty-two) and to such extent as may appear to the Commission to be expedient, port facilities,due regard being had, as respects all the services and 30facilities mentioned in this subsection, to efficiency,economy and safety of operation and to the needs ofthe public, agriculture, commerce and industry.&quot;(2) The following provisions shall have effect as respects the membership of the Commission- 35(a) the maximum number of members of the Commissionother than the chairman shall, instead of being eight,be ten;ib) so much of subsection (2) of section one of the Trans-port Act, 1947, as requires not less than four members 40other than the chairman to render whole-time service to. the Commission is hereby repealed and accordinglyonly the chairman and such other members, if any, asA-.D;. 1952 of any increase in their costs occurring before the determination of that application or such earlier date,if any, as may be fixed by the Tribunal for the purposesof this paragraph when they make their determination.(6) Nothing in this section shall be construed as preventing &quot;5the Commission from making any increase in their charges whichthey would be entitled to make apart from the provisions ofthis section.
15 &amp; 16 Ceo. 6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2the Minister thinks fit, shall be required to render A.D. 1952whole-time service to the Commission;Ac) in exercising the powers exercisable by him under or by virtue of the said section one, the Minister shall have5 regard to the desirability of securing that the membersof the Commission include (i) persons who between them have had experi-ence in the management of railways and road transport; and10 (ii) a person who has had experience in theorganisation of workers ; and(iii) persons who, otherwise than by virtue of suchexperience as is mentioned in sub-paragraphs (i) and(ii) of this paragraph, may between them be expected15 to be conversant with the requirements, as respectstransport, of agriculture, commerce and industry.(3) It shall be part of the duties of the chairman of theCommission (or, in his absence, of the member of the Commis-sion acting as such), to keep the Minister at all times adequately20 informed as to all matters connected with the Commission or its undertaking which are material to be known to the Ministerfor the purpose of enabling him properly to discharge his duty asthe Minister, and, in particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision, all matters which the25 Minister might reasonably wish to consider for the purpose of determining whether to take any and if so what action in theexercise of his powers in relation to the Commission.(4) The power conferred on the Minister by subsection (3)of section five of the Transport Act, 1947, to make provision as30 to the number and names of the Executives shall include powerto provide that there shall be no Executives.24. 41) The following provisions shall have effect as respects Miscellaneousthe borrowing powers of. the Commission- amendmentsia) the provisos to subsections (1) and (2) of section eighty- commission.35 eight of the Transport Act, 1947 (which impose limits of twenty-five million pounds and two hundred and fifty million pounds on temporary borrowings andborrowings by the issue of stock otherwise than for thepurposes specified in paragraphs (b) and W) of the said40 subsection (2)), shall cease to have effect;(b) the aggregate of the amounts outstanding -.-. (i) in respect of the principal of any British trans-port stock issued otherwise than for the purposes specified in paragraphs (b) and (d) of the said sub-45 section (2); and
A.D. 1952 (ii) in respect of any temporary loans raised bythe Commission under the said subsection (1),shall not at any time exceed the sum of two hundredand seventy-five million pounds;: (c) any consent or authority for temporary borrowings given 5by the Minister under the said subsection (1) shall ,require the approval of the Treasury ;(d) nothing in the said section eighty-eight shall apply toany borrowings of the Commission from any body which, within the meaning of subsection (6) of section ifjone hundred and one of the Transport Act, 1947, is completely controlled by the Commission, but no suchborrowings shall be deemed to be temporary loans forthe purposes of subsection (1) of section ninety of thatAct (which empowers the Treasury to give guarantees 15.   in respect of borrowings by the Commission):Provided that nothing in paragraph (b) of this subsection shallprevent the Commission from borrowing in excess of the sumtherein referred to for the purpose of redeeming any british transport stock which they are required or entitled to redeem, 20or of repaying any money temporarily borrowed under sub-section (1) of the said section eighty-eight.Any additional sums which, by reason of the amendmentseffected by the preceding provisions of this subsection, arerequired by the Treasury for fulfilling any guarantee of British 25transport stock or of any temporary loan raised by the Commis-sion shall be charged on and issued out of the consolidate fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof.(2) The Commission shall have power to engage in any activi-ties which the Minister may from time to time think fit in the 30interests of national defence to authorise or direct them to engage in, and the limitations imposed by the provisos to subsections (2)-and (3) of section two of the Transport Act, 1947, and by sub-r ;     ;     section (4) of that section shall not apply to any such activities:Provided that the Minister shall not authorise or direct the 35Commission to engage in any form of activity falling withinthe scope of the said limitations unless he is satisfied that, unless he gives the direction or authority, work required in the interestsof national defence cannot be carried out or cannot be carriedout without serious risk of undue delay or of loss of efficiency.     49(3) For the purposes of section forty-two of the Finance Act,1930 (which gives relief from stamp duty in the case of a transferof property as between associated companies with limited liabi-lity), the Commission shall be deemed to be a company withlimited liability. 45
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; TEliz. 2(4) The obligation imposed on the Commission - A.D. 1952(a) by subsection (2) of section twenty-one of the railways act, 1921, to repay to the Minister the remunerationr  . of the members, officers and servants, and other ex-5 penses, of the Transport Tribunal, so far as they arenot met out of the amount recovered by way of fees;and.[ (b) by sub-paragraph (2) of paragraph 7 of the Tenth&apos;  ^Schedule to the Transport Act, 1947, to pay to the10 Minister the remuneration and expenses of persons appointed from any panel of the said Tribunal and ofcertain additional members of the said Tribunal, so faras they are not met out of the amount recovered byway of fees,15 shall not apply to so much of the said remuneration and expensesas may be apportioned by the Tribunal to the exercise after thepassing of this Act of the jurisdiction transferred to them bysection seventy-three of the Transport Act, 1947, in respect of appeals from licensing authorities under Part I of the Road and20 Rail Traffic Act, 1933.Pension rights and compensation to employees25.-0) The Minister may make regulations-  Provision as(a) for providing or securing the provision of pensions to or rights&quot;810&quot;in respect of persons who, having been in the employ-25 ment of the Commission and, in connection with that employment, having had pension rights under pension schemes (hereafter in this section referred to as &quot; existingpension schemes&quot;), lose that employment in conse-quence of the duties imposed on the Commission by30 this Act as to the disposal of the property held by themfor the purposes of the existing road haulage under-taking or of any modification of the functions of theCommission effected by or by virtue of this Act; and(b) for amending&apos;, for the purposes aforesaid, any existing35 pension scheme and any statutory provision relatingthereto; or any trust deed, rules or other instrumentmade for the purposes thereof.(2) Without prejudice to the generality of the preceding sub-section, regulations made under this section may provide, in a40 case where any such person obtains other employment and, inconnection with that employment, has pension rights underanother pension scheme, for the making of a payment, by way of
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 Buz. 2transfer value or otherwise, to the persons administering that scheme, being a payment by the Commission or out of any pension fund established under the existing pension scheme or a payment partly by the Commission and partly out of any suchpension fund, and for conferring on the said person, in accord- 5ance with arrangements made with the persons administering theother pension scheme, pension rights equal in value to thosewhich he had under the existing pension scheme ; and the regula-tions may empower any persons administering that other pension scheme to carry out any such arrangements, notwithstanding 10anything to the contrary contained in the scheme or in any statutory provision, trust deed, rules or other instrument madefor the purposes thereof.(3) Regulations made under this section may be made so asto have effect from a date prior to the making thereof, so, 15however, that so much of any regulations as provides that &apos;any provision thereof is to have effect as from a date earlier than the making thereof shall not place any person other thanthe Commission in a worse position than he would have beenin if the regulations had been made to have effect only as from 20the date of the making thereof.iA) Regulations made under this section may contain suchsupplementary and consequential provisions as the minister thinks necessary, including (a) provisions as to the procedure for determining questions 25arising under the regulations and the manner in whichiand the persons by whom such questions are to bedetermined ; and(6) in particular, provisions enabling appeals from anydetermination of any such question to be brought, in 30such cases and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the regulations, to a referee or board of. referees appointed by the Minister of Labour and national Service, after consultation with the LordChancellor, or where the proceedings are to be held in 35Scotland, after consultation with the Secretary of State.Where any such provision is made as is specified in paragraph(b) of this subsection, the decision of the referee or board of referees shall be final, and nothing in the Arbitration Act, 1950,shall be construed as applying to any proceedings before any 40such referee or board of referees.(5) The power to make regulations under this section shall be exercisable by statutory instrument and any such instrument shall .:;be subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution of either house of Parliament. 45
15&apos;&amp; 16 Geo. 6&amp; 1 eliz. 226. (1) The Minister shall by regulations provide for the   a,D, j952payment by the Commission, in such cases and to such extent compensation as may be specified in the regulations, of compensation to officers to officers andor servants of the Commission who suffer loss of employment servants,^5 or loss or diminution of emoluments or pension rights, or whoseposition is worsened, in consequence of the duties imposed onthe Commission by this Act as to the disposal of the property held by the Commission for the purposes of the existing road haulage undertaking or of any modification of the functions of10 the Commission effected by or by virtue of this Act.(2) Different regulations may be made under this section inrelation to different classes of persons and different classes ofcases, and any such regulations may be made so as to haveeffect as from a date prior to the making thereof, so, however,15. that so much of any regulations as provides that any provisionthereof is to have effect as from a date earlier than the makingthereof shall not place any officer or servant to whom the regu-lations relate in a worse position than he would have been in ifthe regulations had been made to have effect only as from the20 date of the making thereof.(3) Regulations made under this section (a) may prescribe the procedure to be followed in makingclaims for compensation, and the manner in which andthe persons by whom the question whether any or25; what compensation is payable is to be determined; -and&apos;, (b) may in particular contain provisions enabling appeals from any determination as to whether any or whatcompensation is payable to be brought, in such cases30 &apos; and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the regulations, to a referee or board of referees,appointed by the Minister of Labour and NationalService, after consultation with the Lord Chancellor,Or, where the proceedings are to be held in Scotland,35 after consultation with the Secretary of State;and, where any such provision is made as is specified in para-graph (b) of this subsection, the decision of the referee or boardof referees shall be final and nothing in the Arbitration Act,1950, shall be construed as applying to any proceedings before40 any such referee or board of referees.(4) The power to make regulations under this section shallbe exercisable by statutory instrument and any such instrumentshall be subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution of either House of Parliament.
15 &amp; 16GE0.6&amp; 1 Eliz. 2A.D. 1952Amendmentsas toConsultativeCommitteesfor ScotlandWales.Miscellaneous and General27.-(1) In proviso ib) to subsection (3) of section six of theTransport Act, 1947 (which provides, inter alia, that there shallbe a Transport Users Consultative Committee in respect of bothpassenger and goods traffic for Wales), after the word &quot; Wales &quot;,in both places where it occurs, there shall be inserted the words&quot;and Monmouthshire &quot;, and the Transport Users consultative committee in respect of passenger and goods traffic establised for Wales at the passing of this Act shall be deemed to have beenestablished for Wales and Monanouthshire.10(2) Copies of the minutes and of any recommendations or conclusions of the Transport Users Consultative Committee forScotland referred to in the said proviso (b) or of the TransportUsgrs Consultative Committee for Wales and Monmouthshirereferred to in subsection (1) of this section shall be sent to the 15Minister as well as to the Central Transport Consultative Com-mittee, and where a copy of such a recommendation is so sentto the Minister, the Minister may give such, directions to theCommission with respect to the matters dealt with by the recom-mendation as he thinks fit, and the Commission shall give effect 20to any such directions.(3) Copies of the minutes, and of the recommendations or conclusions of any Transport Users Consultative Committee thewhole or any part of the area of which consists of or includes a part of Scotland, a part of Wales or a part of Monmouthshire, 25shall be sent to the Committee for Scotland or, as the case maybe, for Wales and Monmouthshire, referred to in subsection (2)of this section as well as to the Central Transport consultative committee and the Commission, and the Committees referredto in the said subsection (2) shall each make an annual report 30to the Minister copies of which shall be laid before each Houseof Parliament.Amendments,as to CoastalShippingAdvisoryCommittee.28.-^(1) In subsection (1) of section seventy-one of the Trans-port Act, 1947 (which provides for the establishment of a coastal shipping Advisory Committee), after the words &quot; the interests 35of the Commission and those of persons engaged in coastal ship-ping &quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; or the interests ofcarriers of goods by road for hire or reward and those of thesaid persons, or the interests of the Commission and those ofthe said carriers and those of the said persons &quot;. 40- (2) At the. end of paragraph ib) of subsection (2) of the said section seventyHone there shall be added the words &quot; and&apos;i :.y (c) such number of persons representing the interests ofcarriers of goods by road for hire or reward as the
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6 Transport 39&amp; I Eliz. 2Minister thinks fit, to be appointed by him after con-  :A.D.. 1952sultation with such body or bodies as he thinks fit,being a body or bodies who appear to him to be representative of those carriers &quot; ;; 5 and in the said subsection (2), for the words &quot;the number ofrepresentatives of the Commission on the said Committee&quot;there shall be substituted the words &quot; the aggregate number ofthe other members of the said Committee.&quot;(3) The preceding provisions of this section shall come into10 force on the appointed day, and the persons who, immediately before that day, are members of the Committee shall cease tohold office as such on that day unless they have been re-appointed to be members of the Committee under the said section seventy-one as amended by this section.15    29.-(1) In subsection (4) of section one hundred and five of Amendmentsthe Transport Act, 1947 (which provides for the appointment of .s to Transporta person to discharge the duties of any member of the Transport Tribunal.011Arbitration Tribunal temporarily incapable of performing theduties of his office), for the words &quot; If any member of the arbi-20 tration tribunal becomes, by reason of illness or other infirmity,temporarily incapable of performing the duties of his office&quot;there shall be substituted the words &quot; If any member of thearbitrati n tribunal, by reason of illness or other infirmity orabsence, ;s temporarily unable to perform the duties of his25 office &quot;.Any increase attributable to this subsection in the sums which,under subsection (4) of section one hundred and seven of the said act, are payable out of moneys provided by Parliament shall bepaid out of moneys so provided, without prejudice, however, to30 the duty of the Commission under the said subsection (4) to repay the increase to the Minister. ,   .-(2) It is hereby declared, for the removal of doubt, that thepower of the Transport Arbitration Tribunal under subsection(5) of the said section one hundred and five to appoint a person35 or persons to hear and determine proceedings referred to himor them by the Tribunal may be exercised by the appointmentof a member or members of the Tribunal whether with or with-out other persons.30i Section seven of the Transport Act, 1947 (which enables Repeal of s. 740 persons carrying on undertakings to make and carry out agree- &apos;nd s- 114 ofments for the transfer of those undertakings to the Commission Actni947and contains other provisions for facilitating the carrying on of undertakings agreed to be transferred to the Commission), and section: one hundred and fourteen of that Act (which provides45 for the payment of additional compensation to local authorities
o-A;D. 1952   in respect of the. transfer of undertakings under Part II or part iv of that Act) are hereby repealed.Administrative;, 31.-(1) ThcMinister may hold inquiries for the purposes of provisions.      his powers and duties under this Act as if those purposes werepurposes of the Ministry of Transport Act, 1919, and section 5twenty of that Act shall apply accordingly.(2) Any administrative expenses incurred by the Minister inthe execution of this Act (including any charges and expenses of licensing authorities and other persons incurred in or by reasonof the execution thereof which are directed by the Minister under 10subsection (3) of section twenty-two of the Road and Rail traffic act, 1933, to be paid as expenses of the roads department ofthe Ministry of Transport) shall be paid out of moneys providedby Parliament.: (3) The Minister of Labour and National Service may, with 15the consent of the Treasury, pay, out of moneys provided byParliament (a) to any referee or to the members of any board of referees appointed by him under the provisions of thisAct relating to pension rights and compensation to 20officers and servants such fees and allowances as he-      - - may with the consent of the Treasury determine; andV (b) to a person giving evidence before any such referee or board such allowances as the Minister may with theconsent of the Treasury determine. 25(4) Any increases attributable to any of the provisions of thisAct in the sums payable into the Exchequer under subsection (2)of section one hundred and twenty-three of the Transport Act,1947, shall be paid into the Exchequer.Interpretation. 32.-(1) Section one hundred and twenty-five of the Transport 30Act, 1947, except subsections (2) and (3) thereof, shall apply for the interpretation of this Act as it applies for the interpreta-tion of that Act, as if any reference therein to that Act included a reference to this Act, and in this Act &quot; charges scheme &quot; means a charges scheme, as defined in section seventy-six of that Act 35(2) Except where the context otherwise requires, in the provi-sions of this Act relating to the carriage of goods by road expres-sions have the same meanings as in Part I of the Road and rail traffic Act, 1933, except that &quot; motor vehicle &quot; means a goodsvehicle within the meaning of the said Part I other than a trailer. 40(3) Except where the context otherwise requires, in the pro-visions of this Act relating to the carriage of passengers by roadexpressions have the same meanings as in the Road Traffic Act,1930..&quot; . ,&apos;
(4) In this Act &quot; the London Passenger Transport Area &quot;has   a.d. 1952the meaning assigned to it by section one. hundred and seven ofthe London Passenger Transport Act, 1933, and &quot;the Londonspecial area &quot; means the special area as defined in the said    -5 section one hundred and seven. - .. &apos;. - ;: ;i *(5) In this Act &quot;the appointed day &quot; means, such day as theMinister may by order (which shall be a statutory instrument)appoint, and different days may be appointed for different pur-poses and for different provisions of this Act.10 (6) Any reference in this Act to the Commission includes, &quot;as respects matters falling within the scope of any delegation to an executive, a reference to that Executive, and, as respects mattersfalling within the scope of any delegation to any authority or, other person which is effected by or under any scheme under this15 Act with respect to the re-organisation of the Commission^ rail-ways, includes save so far as the contrary is provided by thescheme, a reference to that authority or person.(7) It is hereby declared that any reference in the. transport act, 1947, to the functions of the Commission includes a20 reference to any powers and duties conferred or imposed on theCommission by this Act.33.-(1) This Act may be cited as the Transport Act, 1952.     Short title,extent and; (2) Sections fifteen, sixteen and twenty-three of this Act shall, repeals,so far as applicable to so much of the undertaking of the Com-25 mission as represents the undertaking of any of the bodies speci-fied in the Third Schedule to the Transport Act, 1947, extend to northern Ireland but, save as aforesaid, this Act shall not extend to Northern Ireland.(3) The provisions of the Transport Act, 1947, are hereby30 repealed to the extent specified in Part I of the Third Schedule-to this Act, subject to the savings contained in Part II of that schedule.
a.d. 1952 schedules first SCHEDULERights of obtaining Licences for Five Years for goods vehicles Free of Charge ;;Part I vehicles comprised in Transport UnitsRights on initial application1. If the purchaser of a transport unit, before the date on which heobtains delivery of any motor vehicles as or as part of that unit, makesan application with respect to any of those vehicles (except additional 10vehicles) and no other motor vehicles for an A licence authorising theuse of those vehicles, then, subject to the provisions of this Part ofthis Schedule, (a) the application shall not be refused; and(b) the condition specified in section fifty-two of the Transport 15Act, 1947 (namely that, except under or in accordance witha permit granted by the Commission, goods shall not becarried for hire or reward in any authorised vehicle if at anytime while the goods are being so carried the vehicle is morethan twenty-five miles from its operating centre), shall not 20apply to the licence; and(c) the licence shall be granted for so much of the five year period(as hereinafter defined) as remains unexpired on the date onwhich the licence is expressed to take effect, and subsections(1) to (4) of section three of the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 251933, shall not apply to the licence; and(d) no fee shall be charged in respect of the grant of the licence;and(e) until the application is determined, the applicant shall be inthe same position as respects the vehicles to which the 30application relates as he would have been in if the applicationhad been granted:Provided that the licensing authority may entertain any suchapplication as aforesaid which is through inadvertence or other causemade on or after the date aforesaid, and the preceding provisions of this 35paragraph shall thereupon apply to that application except sub-paragraph (e) thereof.A licence granted under this paragraph is hereafter in this Part ofthis Schedule referred to as &quot; a special A licence &quot;.2. Where a transport unit includes trailers, but not otherwise, an 40application made by the purchaser of the unit for a special A licencewith respect to any motor vehicles included therein may extend to a specified number of trailers:i     Provided that the number of trailers so specified, together with thenumber of trailers (if any) specified by him in other such applications 45relating to the same transport unit, shall not exceed the number oftrailers (other than additional vehicles) included in that transport unit.
15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6 Transport 43&amp; 1 eliz. 23. Where, before an application is made for a special A licencewith respect to any motor vehicle included in a transport unit, thatvehicle is destroyed or damaged beyond repair, another vehicle of thesame or less weight unladen may be included in the application instead5 of the destroyed or damaged vehicle and if, while any such application is pending with respect to such a motor vehicle, the motor vehicle isdestroyed or damaged beyond repair, the application shall, if theapplicant so requires, be treated as if it had been made with respect toanother vehicle of the same or less weight unladen instead of the10 destroyed or damaged vehicle; and paragraph 1 of this Part of this schedule shall apply in each case to that other vehicle as it would have applied to the destroyed or damaged vehicle.4. Notwithstanding anything in this Part of this Schedule, wherethe permanent base or centre specified in an application for a special15 A licence as that from which it is intended that the authorised vehicleswill normally be used for the purposes of carrying goods for hire orreward is not the permanent base or centre from which the vehicles in question or, as the case may be, the vehicles corresponding thereto,were last used by the Commission before the publication of the public20 notice inviting tenders for the purchase of the transport unit, the licensing authority may. refuse the application if it appears to him that the vehicles used from the first-mentioned base or centre could,not conveniently serve substantially the same areas as those whichmight conveniently be served by vehicles used from the second-25 mentioned base or centre.In relation to such a transfer as is provided for by section four of this Act, the reference in this paragraph to the publication of thepublic notice inviting tenders shall be deemed to be a reference tothe date of the transfer.30 5. Notwithstanding the last preceding paragraph, an applicationfor a special A licence shall be deemed, for the purposes of sectioneleven of the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933 (which relates to theprocedure on applications for licences), to be an application whichthe licensing authority is bound to grant.35 Variation, revocation and suspension of licences,assignment of vehicles, etc.6. No variation of a special A licence shall be made except a varia-tion consisting only of the removal of a specified vehicle from thelicence, or of the specification in the licence in substitution for a40 specified vehicle of a vehicle of the same or a less weight unladen,.orof a reduction in the number of trailers specified in the licence.7. Nothing in this Part of this Schedule shall be taken as preventing the licensing authority from exercising, in relation to special A licences,his power to revoke or suspend a licence or to give directions under45 subsection (3) of section thirteen of the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933.8. Where the holder of a special A licence-(a) agrees to assign any of the authorised vehicles to any other&quot; -     person (other than the Commission);. and     :
(b) gives particulars of the agreement to the licensing authorityby whom the licence was granted; and: (c) makes an application to the end that, as from the date ofthe delivery of the vehicles to the assignee, the licence shallbe revoked or so varied as not to authorise the use of the vehicles (or any vehicles substituted therefor in the licence),or, in so far as the vehicles are trailers, so as to reduce thenumber of trailers by the number of trailers agreed to be- assigned,the proposed assignee shall have the same rights under the preceding 10provisions of this Part of this Schedule, for the purpose of obtaininganew special.A licence with respect to the assigned vehicles or vehiclessubstituted therefor, as he would have if he were the purchaser of a transport unit consisting of the assigned vehicles and the date of delivery were the same date as the date of delivery under the assign- 15ment, so, however, that the five year period shall be calculated as fromthe date of the original delivery of the vehicles or, as the case may be,the vehicles corresponding thereto, as or as part of a transport unit.An application made under sub-paragraph (c) of this paragraph shall not be withdrawn unless the licensing authority, being satisfied 20that the assignment has not taken place, and will not take place,permits it to be withdrawn, and, where permission is given, thisparagraph shall not apply to that agreement.9. Any person who, by virtue of regulations made under section twenty-one of the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933, is deemed 25temporarily to be the holder of a special A licence shall have the same rights under the preceding provisions of this Part of this Schedule,for the purpose of obtaining a new special A licence with respect tothe authorised vehicles or vehicles substituted therefor, as he wouldhave if he were the purchaser of a transport unit consisting of the 30authorised vehicles and the date of delivery were the date on whichhe ceased to be deemed to be the holder of that licence, so, however,that the five year period shall be calculated from the date of the originaldelivery of the vehicles or, as the case may be, the vehicles corres-ponding thereto, as or as part of a transport unit. 35Interpretation10. Where the purchaser of a transport unit is, within the meaning of section twelve of the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933, a subsidiaryor holding company, the references in paragraphs 1 and 2 of thisPart of this Schedule to the making of applications by the purchaser 40of a transport unit shall include references to the making of applicationsby the holding company in accordance with the said section twelveand, in relation to a special A licence held by such a holding company,paragraph 8 of this Part of this Schedule shall have effect as if any agreement to assign, or assignment of, any of the authorised vehicles 45by the subsidiary company were an agreement or assignment by the ;holding company.11. The references in paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Part of this Scheduleto the purchaser of a transport unit shall include references to aperson who, on the death, incapacity, bankruptcy or liquidation of the 50
(015 &amp; 16 GeO. 6 Transport 45&amp; 1 Eliz. 2purchaser or the appointment of a receiver or manager in relation tohis business, becomes entitled to apply for an A licence in respect ofthe vehicles included in that unit.12. In this Part of this Schedule,&quot; additional vehicles &quot;means vehicles5 included in a transport unit and specified as additional vehicles under subsection.(5) of section three of this Act, &quot; assignment&quot;, in relationto any vehicles, includes the transfer of possession of the vehiclesunder a hire purchase agreement, and &quot; the five year period &quot;, inrelation to any vehicles, means the period beginning with the date on10 which those vehicles, or, as the case may be, vehicles correspondingthereto, were delivered as or as part of a transport unit sold by theCommission and ending with such date prescribed under subsection(2) of section three of the Road and Rail:Traffic.Act,. 193.3., as nextfalls before the expiration of the period of five-years beginning with the15 first-mentioned date. rPart IIGoods Vehicles of commission. If the Commission, before the expiration of three months fromthe passing of this Act, apply for the grant of an A licence or a C20 licence authorising the use of any motor vehicles which at the passingof this Act belonged to the Commission or were in the possession ofthe Commission under an agreement for hire or loan, and no othermotor vehicles,  . ..&apos; 1..(a) the application shall not be refused; and25 (b) the licence shall be granted for so much of the. five year period as remains unexpired on the date when the licence is expressed to take effect, and subsections (1) to (4) of section three ofthe Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933, shall not apply to thelicence; and30      (c) no fee shall be charged in respect of the grant of the-licence:Provided that no application for an A licence shall be made underthis paragraph in respect of any motor vehicles which at the passingof this Act were being used by the Hotels Executive, the Docks andInland Waterways Executive. or the London Transport Executive,35 exclusively for purposes other than hire or reward.2. An application under the preceding paragraph may extend to a specified number of trailers.3. If a vehicle with respect to which an application for the grant of an- A licence or a C licence may be made under paragraph 1 of this Part40 of this Schedule is destroyed or damaged beyond repair before suchan application is made withrespect thereto, another vehicle of the sameor less weight unladen may be included in. such an application insteadof the destroyed or damaged vehicle and if, while any shell application is pending with respect to such a vehicle, the vehicle is destroyed or45 damaged beyond repair, the application shall, if the Commission sorequire, be treated as if it had been made in respect of another vehicleof the same or less weight unladen instead of the destroyed orA.D. 1952-1st Sch. cont.
SECOND SCHEDULE 30Rates of Transport LevyPart IOrdinary Scale for Goods Vehicles1 Description of vehicle	2   -Number by which unit charge   35 is to be multipliedGoods, vehicles which are chargeable with excise duty in accordance with section five of, and paragraph 2 or paragraph 7 of Part I of the Fourth Schedule to, the Vehicles (Excise) Act, 1949, being vehicles the weight of which unladen exceeds one ton.	The number of quarters of a ton in the weight unladen of the vehicle, any odd part of a quarter of a ton being reckoned as a 40 quarter of a ton.A.D. 1952   damaged vehicle; and paragraph 1 of this Part of this Schedule shall1st sch     aPply in eacfl case to that other vehicle as it would have applied to-cant.     the destroyed or damaged vehicle.4. No variation shall be made of an A. licence granted under paragraph 1 of this Part of this Schedule except a variation consisting 5only of the removal of a specified vehicle from the licence, or of&quot; the specification in the licence in substitution for a specified vehicle of a vehicle of the same or less weight unladen, or of a reduction in thenumber of trailers specified in the licence.5. Nothing in this Part of this Schedule shall be taken as preventing 10the licensing authority from exercising, in relation to a licence granted under paragraph 1 of this Part of this Schedule, his power to revokeor suspend a licence or to give&quot; directions under subsection (3) ofsection thirteen of the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933.6. No vehicle shall be substituted in an A licence granted under 15paragraph 1 of this Part of this Schedule for any motor vehicle sold asor as part of a transport unit, and where a motor vehicle which has atany time been authorised to be used under such an A licence is sosold, any vehicle which has been substituted (directly or indirectly) inthat licence for that vehicle shall cease to be an authorised vehicle 20under that licence, and the Comniission shall give all such notices and make all such applications as are necessary to secure that any motor vehicle so sold or so substituted as aforesaid is removed from thelicence.7. In this Part of this Schedule, &quot; the five year period &quot; means the 25period beginning with the passing of this Act and ending with such date prescribed under subsection (2) of section three of the Road and rail Traffic Act, 1933, as next falls before the expiration of five years from the passing of this Act.
CO15 &amp; 16 Geo. 6&apos; &amp; 1 eliz. part IIAddition where Goods Vehicle mentioned in Part Iis used for Drawing Trailers10Weight unladen of vehicle		1		3Exceeding	Not exceeding	Number to be added to number		arrived at under Part I1 ton	2i tons	&apos;           42i tons	4 tons	64 tons		.               8A.D. 19522nd Sch.Part IIITractors1 Description of Vehicle	Weight unladen		Number by which unit charge is to be multiplied		2 Exceeding	3   . Not Exceeding	4 Initial	5 Addition to number in column 4 for each ton or part of a ton in excess of the weight in column 2Tractors which are charge-		2 tons	6	_able with excise duty in	2 tons	4 tons	12	 accordance with section	4 tons	6 tons	18	-four of,.and paragraph 6	6 tons	7  tons	.     22 ...	- fof the third Schedule to,	7 tons	8 tons	26	-&apos;the Vehicles (Excise) Act,	8 tons	&quot; -&apos;	26	&apos; ,   41949.				152530
QA.D. 1952THIRD SCHEDULEProvisions of the Transport Act, 1947, RepealedPart IExtent of repeal in subsection (2) of section one, from the words &quot; and of whom &quot; 5to the end of the subsection. ......&apos;&apos;,Section seven. ,,   .Sections thirty-nine to fifty-six.Subsection (2) of section fifty-seven.Sections fifty-eight to sixty-four. jqSubsections (1), (3) and (4) of section sixty-five.Sections sixty-six to sixty-eight.The provisos to subsections (1) and (2) of section eighty-eight.Section one hundred and fourteen.In section one hundred and twenty-five, the definitions of&quot; abnormal 15indivisible load &quot;, &quot; meat &quot;, &quot; operating centre &quot;, &quot; ordinary furnitureremoval &quot; and &quot; superimposed trailer &quot;.Subsections (9) and (10) of section one hundred and twenty-six.In Part I of the Eighth Schedule, in sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 1,the words from &quot; Provided that&quot; to the end of the sub-paragraph, 20and in sub-paragraph (2) of paragraph 3, the words from &quot;in the -case &quot; to &quot; any other case &quot;.Part II of the Eighth Schedule.The Ninth Schedule.1. The repeal of sections fifty-two and fifty-three, section fifty-six,subsection (2) of section fifty-seven, section fifty-eight, subsections (1)and (3) to (6) of section sixty, sections sixty-one and sixty-two of theTransport Act, 1947, and the said definitions in section one hundred 30and twenty-five of that Act except that of &quot; superimposed trailer &quot;,shall not have effect until the appointed day.2. The proviso to subsection (3) of section one of this Act shallapply in relation to the repeal of the provisions of the Transport Act,1947, which relate to the acquisition of certain road transport under- 35takings by the Commission as it applies in relation to the provisionsof that subsection.3. The repeal of section fifty-nine of the Transport Act, 1947, shallbe subject to the provisions of Subsections (2) and (3) of section six of this Act. . - 40Part II25Savings
CONFIDENTIALTransportDRAFTof aBILLTo require the British Transport Commissionto dispose of the property held by them forthe purposes of the part of their undertaking which is carried on through the road haulage Executive; to amend the law relating to the carriage of goods by road and to provide for a levy, for the benefitof the said Commission and for other purposes, on motor vehicles used on roads;to provide for the reorganisation of therailways operated by the said Commissionand to amend the law relating to thepowers and composition, duties of thesaid Commission; to repeal certain provisions of the Transport Act, 1947, andto amend other provisions thereof; toamend section six of the Cheap TrainsAct, 1883; and for purposes connectedwith the matters aforesaid.ccxvin-j (6)1st July, 1952163-6(77138)

</content>
</cab>
