<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/53/0 images: 232-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^30:&quot;::Y: 1 . I&apos;(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^- GOVERNMENT)CONFIDENTIAL ^   ^--- CABINET Oi-HGhC.(52) 238 RECORD COPY COPY NO._ //12TH JULY, 1952CABINETSCHUMAN PLAN:  APPOINTMENT OF UNITED KINGDOM DELEGATIONMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs in accordance with the Cabinet Conclusions of 22nd November, 1951(C. C, (51) 10th Conclusions, Minute 4) the Home Secretary announced at Strasbourgon 28th November, 1951, that if the Schuman Plan was ratified, Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment would set up a permanent delegation at the seat of the High Authorityto enter into relations and to transact business with it.2. The Plan has now been approved by the legislatures of the six member countries.   Ratifications are expected to be deposited, the treaty to enter intoforce, and the High Authority to be set up in the latter half of August,   The formalappointment of our delegation must await the conclusion of these processes, butif we are to be ready in time, preliminary decisions must be taken without delay.3. Commercial considerations also underline the need for quick action,I am informed that industrial interests on the Continent may already be concertingarrangements for the organisation of coal and steel markets after the treaty comes into force.   These preliminary exchanges may closely affect our own interests,but Her Majesty&apos;s Government and the industries concerned cannot at presenteffectively make their influence felt, for lack of recognised representation with authority to speak on their behalf.4, The High Authority will act for the six member states in their external relations within its field.   Moreover, though the matters with which it deals are in themselves commercial and industrial, the underlying purposes of the Communityare political and form part of the complex of federalist developments with whichI have to deal&apos;in the European Defence Community, in the Pflimlin Plan and inrecent proposals for a European Political Authority.   On these grounds I considerthat responsibility for our delegation, and for the conduct of our relations with the schuman Community, should rest with the Foreign Secretary.5, I should require continuous advice upon the varied departmental interests involved, and I propose that this should be provided by a small official committeeto be established under a Foreign Office Chairman with membership drawn,fromthe Ministries of Fuel and Power and Supply, the Treasury, the Board of Tradeand, as required, the Ministry of Labour.   Instructions to the delegation would beprepared by this committee and issued by me.6. In planning our delegation the first step must be the choice of a leader.Our relations with the Community will be under continuous discussion between now and the time when the High Authority is set up, and the leader of our delegation should be appointed without delay so that his advice may be available.For this post I consider that we should select a man if possible whose backgroundis commercial or industrial, though preferably not connected with either coal or steel.   The High Authority itself is likely to consist of a mixture of business men,politicians, officials and trade unionists, but our day to day dealings with it will be-1
on industrial and  commercial matters, and we should mark this fact in the selection of our representative.   But a business background is not in itselfenough.   If mistakes are to be avoided, it should be combined with some experienceof international negotiation.   Day-to-day political advice would be provided bythe appointment of a Foreign Service officer to the delegation;  but, in view of theimportance of the work for our future relations with Western Europe, politicalsense must rank with industrial experience as an indispensable qualification.I propose that I should be authorised, in consultation with the other ministers directly concerned, to select and appoint a candidate answering to thisspe cification.7. Initially at least, the permanent staff of the Delegation should be keptsmall.   Technical representatives from the Ministries of Supply and Fuel and power will be indispensable.   Other Departments have obvious interests:  these might, I suggest, be covered as far as possible by visits from officials based in this country.   Similarly, the need for advice from both management andlabour in the two industries could be met by the appointment of assessors whowould visit the delegation as required.8. I understand that consultations are proceeding, in accordance withE. A. (52) 36, with management and labour in the two industries, and with otherjoint advisory bodies.   I trust that these consultations will be pursued in such away as to permit the programme of action proposed above to proceed with dueexpedition.9. Summary of conclusions accordingly invite my colleagues to endorse the following conclusions:-(a) That Ministerial responsibility for the United Kingdom delegation should rest with the Foreign Secretary (paragraph 4).(b) That the Foreign Secretary should be advised by, and instruct the delegation through, an interdepartmental committee to be established under Foreign Office chairmanship  (paragraph 5).(c) That the qualities required in the leader of the delegation are industrialexperience combined with political sense, and that I should be authorised,in consultation with the Ministers principally concerned, to select thebest man available (paragraph 6).(d) That the permanent staff of the delegation should be selected from theDepartments directly concerned, and should be reinforced as necessary by representatives of other Departments and by assessors from bothsides of the two industries (paragraph 7).A.E.Foreign Office, S0 W. 1. ,12TH JULY, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
