<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/53/0 images: 251-254</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(52) 24516th JULY, 1952.CABINET office record copy copy no cabinet the EXPORT PROBLEMMemorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.We have before us memoranda about defence, about investment in industry and in social services and about the balance of payments.  Allthese are matters of great importance.   Our resources are insufficient for usto tackle all of them together.2. We all agree about the desirability for adequate defence measures, for social services and particularly for housing,,   I still considerthat the Chancellor of the Exchequer was right when he said in the House ofCommons on the 12th June that we must put the balance of payments first.   Ifwe fail to solve that problem we shall fail in all else too.3. We must therefore increase exports quickly.   The Chancellorasks for an increase of 20%.   I have set out my views on the export situationand outlook in C. (52) 175.   The latest results are certainly not more encouraging than I stated in that document.   So far from going up the dailyrate of exports has been going down, March  9.3 millions, April  9.1 millions,May  8.4 millions, June  8.1 millions.   Even in metals and engineering productsthere was a decline from about  119 millions in April/May to about  112 millions in June (both months being taken on a comparable 26 days basis).   Much ofthe decline in total exports is due to Sterling Area import cuts, but the downwardtrend in metal goods and engineering products is serious since exportsof these goods to all markets are either dollar earners or dollar savers.4. It will remain hard to sell consumer goods.   We could sell moreengineering goods if we could make them.   Some firms have heavy exportorder books but are unable to speed up deliveries.   Others are losing ordersnow because they cannot quote delivery dates comparable to those of their principal competitors abroad.5. No amount of exhortation will help our engineering export industries.   They are well aware of the need to increase exports, but they needour help.   Their principal difficulty is the overloading of capacity and shortageof steel with which to make the goods the world demands of them.   In my judgment we cannot help them adequately if we stand fast now upon a plan to limitdefence production by the metal-using industries to  500 millions in 1953/4.This would amount to little more than not increasing still further the claims ofdefence.   An agreement not to increase the burden is not enough.   It will not freenew resources for the export industries.   We know also that a high level ofdefence production almost inevitably requires a high level of defence investment.6, I attach a few examples of the difficulties which have arisen forexporters because of defence orders. The Minister of Supply has also referredto these clashes in his memorandum on exports from the metal-using industries-1-
(C. (52) 224 (Annex B)): these are of course only examples of a situationwhich is widespread throughout the engineering industries.7. We cannot in the nature of things automatically match thecontraction of defence claims with increased exports, firm by firm and workshop by workshop.   But, unless we take vigorous steps toincrease the resources available to exporters we shall find that we have lost a great deal of long-term business as well as vitally importantincreased earnings in the next year or so.   Therefore although limitationof defence production bythe metal-using industries to  400 millions in1953/4 may be too extreme we should, in my judgment, at least limit it to 450 millions if the export industries are to be given a fair chance,8. My conclusion is that we are still falling into the fatal errorof trying xo do too much.   I therefore ask my colleagues to thinkearnestly about the export problem before they confirm the adoption ofa level of defence production by the metal-using industries of 500 millions in 1953/4.P.T.Board of Trade, S, W. 1.,16TH JULY, 1952.
ANNEXTotal value1.   DominicanRepublicThis order for a complete raw sugarfactory was placed with the Mirrlees WatsonCo. Ltd. in March, 1951, for completion in22 to 24 months and to be ready forharvesting during the crop season 1952-53.Most of the work is sub-contracted and various delays arose owing to difficulties over steel supplies.   In particular theorder for turbines placed by english electric Company with Daniel Adamsonwas delayed because they had a very fullorder book which included defence orders.Further large contracts in this dollar area are expected but failure to keep todelivery promises, particularly formachinery required for growing crops,may affect tlie placing of orders with a united Kingdom firm. 1,250,0002.   Italy Davy &amp; United Engineering Co. Ltd.  125,000had an order for two rolling mills forPionbrine La Magora d&apos;Italia.   TheUnited Kingdom firm were given a statutory Direction ordering them togive absolute priority to two millsurgently needed for the defence programme.Delivery will now be delayed until april and July, 1953, and the United Kingdomfirm fear that this may damage theirreputation and goodwill in that commercial circle and may make theItalians decide to place other pendingorders with the firm&apos;s competitors inGermany.3.    Siam Delay in delivery of three generating Unknownsets ordered by the Loxley Rice Co.(Bangkok) Ltd. for the ThaiGovernment&apos;s new glass factory.   Thiswas due to shortages of materials and certain defence orders.4.   U. S.A. Simon-Carves have been asked to $9,000,000quote for coke oven plant with by-product plant, but they have to quote (and adhere to) a firmdelivery date, which will compare favourably with other tenders.They are accordingly seeking a firmassurance that they will be able toobtain delivery of the 4,000 tons ofsteel required between September, 1952,and June, 1953, before they can tender.
 200,000 450,000India Locomotive programme for 1953/4.  31,000,000United Kingdom manufacturers are proposing to tender but there is uncertainty in the minds ofthe Indian Railway authorities whether the UnitedKingdom can meet their needs due to difficulties and delays which have already arisen oversteel supplies for orders already placed with united Kingdom manufacturers under anagreement to supply 200 engines, and various parts for assembly at Chitteranjanworks, over a period of five years.Difficulties arise largely from the competing claims on limited rollingcapacity for steel for this and for otherproduction (including defence).Pakistan      Telephone equipment manufacturing Not statedproject.   General Electric Co. Ltd. but wouldnegotiated for three years but the contract be severalfell through because of the heavy penalties for   million,any delay in completing by the due date, whichG.E.C. did not feel able to accept in view of present material difficulties.   pakistan government have now signed an agreement withSiemens and Halske of Munich.   This closesthe Pakistan market to the United Kingdom asfar as telephone equipment is concerned,and it is expected that two furthertenders for exchanges of 5,000 lines inKarachi and 2,000 lines in Dacca will go toSiemens.Pakistan       Havelock Engineering Co. were interestedin erecting and equipping a factory for themanufacture of welding electrodes pro-posed by the Pakistan Welding Electrodes.No assurance could, however, be given thatthe electrode wire required could bemade available, owing to defence andother requirements in this country.The Swiss firm of Oerlitons competedand were able to promise assistance inobtaining raw materials (i. e. wire to beused in the factory - 900 tons per annum).The Swiss firm got the contract, though their price Was higher.

</content>
</cab>
