<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/24/44 images: 406-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(^4-^&amp;*v^*/*-V        5.-/ /f/tf I\ .. 19 7^CS^DCGjMgjT IS THE EROPBRTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERMJSKT.uar cabinet copy no      L j214.&quot;TjgjjS. HOSPITAL SHIPS IN THE KEDITERRAIJEANMemorandum by the First Lord of the. Admiralty.In April aftox- numerous attaoks upon British and Greekhospital ships during operations off Crete, His Ma;jesty*3 Government decidedas compensation for our losses to retain for our own use during a minimum period of six months, the Italian hospital ship RAIIB IV captured atllassawa.     A public announcement was made explaining the reasons for our action.For some time afterwards no further attacks on our hospital ships occurred.     Throe air attaoks made between August and December werenot thought to have been deliberate, but whilst we were considering theouostion of ^turning RA!\IB IV, four further air attacks occurred, one of which seemed to bo deliberate.     On April the ?th of this yoixr s, s.&quot;Somersetshire&quot;,whilst outward bound from Alexandria to Tobruk, was torpedoed by a U-boatbut, fortunately, was able to return to Alexandria..     On April 25th and 26thhospitals at Malta were rcpoatedly bombed and severely damaged.     Finally,the RAtIB IV herself, whilst returning from Tobruk to Alexandria, was bombed and sunk with heavy casualties amongst the Allied patients^It is still doubtful, however, whether the enemy do not any longerintend to respect the Red Gross Conventions,     Outside the Mediterranean areaour hospital ships are not attacked;   within the Mediterranean area the attacks have, for the most part, been made during military operations or oni ships either lying in port or proceeding along the Libyan supply routes.I The attacking forcos in the Mediterranean may expect heavy opposition from ourj air or anti-submarine defences, which makes it less easy for them to discriminate.The Middle East Authorities, moreover, carried out extensive testsI upon our own hospital ships and found that our aircraft could not distinguishf the markings from a height of over ten thousand feet.     Although the size ofour markings has been increased, it is clear that InLgh-flying aircraft havoj difficulty in distinguishing hospital ships.     The attaok on the RAMB IV isreported to have been made from a groat height and it is quite probable thatM *no ship was not seen to carry Red Cross markings.Several .........

Several of the enemy attacks have heen made in broad daylight.Our own aircraft have on a few occasions also attacked enemy hospital shipsinadvertently, but these attacks have mostly been made at night when the enemy ships were not illuminated.   On the other- hand, one of H.M. sulxuirinea recentlytorpedoed and sank in the Gulf of Taranto an Italian tanker taking part inthe arrangements for repatriating Italians from East Africa,     The attack wasmade in error and our admission to this effect was accepted by the Italians.Our own record is not, therefore, absolutely clear, but we are undoubtedly more successful than the enemy in avoiding attacks on hospital ships in daylight.     Although the enemy are probably much less scrupulousthan we are, it is known that at any rate until a few months ago, their instructions to their forces enjoined respeot of the Red Cross,     Consequently,I feel that in all the circumstances we should still reserve our. opinion onthe question whether the enemy have abandoned the intention to observe theConvention.Even if the enemy do mean, as a general practice, to observe theConvention, the numerous attacks to which I have already referred make itevident that in the present state of the war in the Mediterranean we have little hope of preventing attacks upon our hospital ships unless the detailsof each voyage are notified to the enemy beforehand.     It is clear that onroutes vfoere al.1 shipping serves military forces in the field, the enemy donot and will not go out of their way to examine each ship before deliveringtheir attacks.     The chance of a hospital ship escaping attack will not,therefore, be great unless its position can be plotted by the enemy withsome precision.I accordingly consider that we should try the effect of notifyingto the enemy full details of the voyages of all our hospital ships in theMediterranean.     I have consulted Commander-in-Chief Mediterranean, who- agrees that this experiment should be mado0     I therefore propose that afurther protest should be lodged against the numerous attacks on our hospital ships and a request made to the German and Italian Governments for the mostsolemn assurances that their forces will refrain from further attacks upon our -hospital ships,     \7e should at the same time inform them that, in future,

Admiralty, S.V/.1.May 20th, 1942.we intend to give prior notice of the time of sailing, the route, the speed of advance and expected time of arrival -of all our hospital ships in theMediterranean.     They would he told that these details will he corimiunicatedin plain language by Tf/T from Alexandria and Malta and that the ships will,in addition, report their position every six hours in plain language.     Yfehave in fact already addressed a note to the Italian Government in similarterms, when proposing to notify to them the special voyage of a hospital ship to Malta which the damage to Malta hospitals has made an urgentx*equiremcnt. &apos;   These representations would be renewed at the same time.If no assurances are forthcaoing or, if after they have beengiven, further attacks which in our opinion are deliberate, are then made upon hospital ships v/hose voyages have been notified in the manner described above, we shall be driven to conclude that the enemy does not intend any longer to observe the Convention.     In that event, I shall seek the sanction of the T/ar Cabinet to take appropriate counter measures.A.V.A.




</content>
</cab>
