<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/96/0 images: 86-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Note by Lt ,Col, Amery.*....The question raised in Sir M.Hankey!s note(-CP.393) on this subject is one of great importance.Presumably the Dominions and India, as full Members cfthe League of Nations, heave the right, if they insist upon it, of direct communication (in both directions)with the Secretary General en all matters connected withthe business of the League\    If this procedure is adopted, as it no doubt will be if no suitable alternative is devised in time, it is inevitable that on controversial and doubtful issues different views will be communicatedand sustained by different parts of the Empire, withthe consequence that when a crisis  arises they may welldiscover  that&apos;they have drifted into divergent or evenwholly antagonistic attitudes.    Such a result wouldnot only destroyin the,eyes of foreign nations, allidea of the British Empire being any longer a unit in international affairs, but would be bound to have amost unfortunate reaction  on the internal relations ofthe British Commonwealth.,   The only way to avoid thisis to provide some machinery for prior interchange of views and consultation.    It is clear from Sir MJiankey&apos;note that if anything of this kind is to be done itmust be done  promptly, before adverse precedents are established.Sir ivi, Hankey suggests that the Governmentsconcerned should be informed that a branch of theCabinet Secretariat is to be set up to act as a clear-ing house, and should be invited to forward theirreplies to the League through this channel,   In making this
this suggestion it will I think be necessary not onlyto lay oofora thorn the reasons which make it desirablethat comnunications should go through a cqmmon cjaanaal,but also to suggest measures which would secure to themdirest representation on the organ of corsiunication and consultation which is to be sot up0As far as the mere transmission and interchange of information is concerned the needs of the case mightbe met if tho Dominions each appoint^ an officer oftheir ewh to the new branch or secretariat to he set upfor this purpose, fallowing the precedent ftf the officersappointed by them on the Secretariat of the British&apos;Empire Delegation at the Peace Conference.Such a machinery w^uld, at any rate, insure thatone part of t]ae Smrire could not adopt a policy on anyparticular qu/ssstjUn without the rest of the Empire being,kept informed.     But it would still leave the reconcil-being of divergent views, and the agreeing on a common policy entirely to tho slow and far from satisfactory method of separate correspondence with half a dozendifferent Governments,    How unsatisfactory that methodis has been shown recently in connexion with the issuecf the British Dominion vc-tes raised by the Lenrootreservation,  &apos; The most satisfactory way of overcomingtho difficulty would be the effective establishment ofan Imperial Cabinet on which the Dominions would becontinuously represented.     But, short of that, itmigjit meet the present case if each Dominion were toappoint as its representative in London for League of ; -Rations purposes, in addition to a secretary, some person of sufficient standing to be able to form a judgment
&apos;)judgment on the points at issue and make rocoiimoridatioriswith a view tc securing a common course of action,,   Then arepresentatives need net bo iinisters but might be high commissioners or other responsible persons.    Tney couldmeet for purposes of consultation with each other andwith the appropriate British authorities, but would notbe members of the Imperial Cabinet or responsible for any questions except those arising in connexion with theLeague of Nations,-  OOLCrllAL OFFICE, th January, 1920;
judgment on the points at issue and make recommendations with a view to securing a common course of action.   Thenarepresentatives noed net bo iinisters bub might be high commissioners or other responsible persons.    They couldmeet for purposes of consultation with each other andwith the appropriate British authorities, but would notbe members of the Imperial Cabinet or responsible for any questions except those arising in connexion with the.League of Nations.L.-S. AtSEHYiCOLMIAL OFFICE,Sth January, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
