<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/96/0 images: 338-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. RET. 4JTHE CABINET.CAPACITY OF THE ARMY TO ASSIST THE CIVIL power in INDUSTRIAL DISTURBANCES.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.In connection with the memorandum on the Employment of Troops in IndustrialDisturbances, which I circulated on 12th November last, together with a report from field-Marshal Earl Haig and a note by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff(CP. 111), I now circulate below a further memorandum on the capacity of the Army toassist the civil power which has been prepared by the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff,The question is of great urgency, and I would request that it receive the very early consideration of the Cabinet.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.7 th January, 1920.MEMORANDUM BY THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF.1. On 6th November last, under instructions received from the Secretary of State, a paper (CP. Ill) was submitted for the consideration of the Cabinet in which was urged the necessity of taking certain measures with the least possible delay in order tomeet the new conditions arising from the rapid decrease in the Army, both as regardsstrength and efficiency, owing to demobilization. It must be remembered that this paper (CP. Ill), was written on the assumption that the Army would not be usedexcept as a last resource in any. future industrial disturbances, but should be allowedto prepare itself for its legitimate duties in the defence of the Empire.At a Conference held at 10, Downing Street, on 18th November, the cabinet approved of the proposed measures, although a reservation was made subsequently asregards responsibility for signal communications.2. The War Office proceeded to take action on the decisions of the Cabinet, butit has since become apparent to the Army Council that the Civil Departments concerned have not yet appreciated the extent of the responsibilities placed upon them, and continue to look, to the Army for assistance which it is quite beyond its power to afford.3. In view of the above, the whole question of the use to be made of the Array inany future internal trouble gives grave cause for anxiety. Not only will the Army be unable to find the guards for which it has up to now been responsible, but also it willbe far too weak to give the full measure of assistance to the police necessitated bydisturbances on a large scale. Apart from this, it is lacking in the necessary technicalservices for its own maintenance, and must rely on Civil Departments to assist it incarrying out even the limited duties of which it is capable. If it is called upon at anearly stage to assist the Civil Authorities, it will be dispersed, and thus the last reserve in the hands of the Government will be dissipated.4. The actual situation is explained in greater detail in Appendix A, and theArmy Council wish to point out in the plainest manner possible that (i.) The Government cannot rely on any technical assistance from the Army inits present state.(ii.) On the contrary, the Army is dependent for its communication, maintenance and mobility on the Civil Authorities,(iii.) Its weakness prohibits its employment except as a military force to be used only in the last extremity, and any premature dispersal would seriouslyweaken its capabilities in this respect.HENRY WILSON,C.I.G.S.3rd January, 1920.
APPENDIX A.Capacity op the Army to carry out General Protection Duties, and . AffordAid to the Civil Power.1. Great Britain. During January and early February, 1920, 28 Regularbattalions will be leaving for duty in various overseas garrisons. After their departurethere will remain in Great Britain (exclusive of Ireland) only 38 Regular battalions,including nine Guards battalions, and in addition 19 Conscript battalions. These Conscriptbattalions are due for demobilization at latest in March, 1920. On the assumption thatan adequate police force is in existence, it is considered essential to maintain the infantry garrisons in Great Britain at not less than i0,000 men in order to give aminimum strength of 30,000 effective bayonets for employment in an emergency, but during January and February next it is estimated that the total strength of infantry,including the 19 Conscript battalions, will not exceed 38,000 men, whilst in March,when the 1^ Conscript battalions will be demobilized, this number will fall to 25,000men, exclusive of untrained recruits at depots. The above will contain a largeproportion of young soldiers with little training, insufficient military discipline, very short of good and reliable senior non-commissioned officers, and consequently of little value if split up into small detachments. Further, an adequate police force does notapparently exist.2. Ireland. Tn Ireland there will be 28 Regular infantry battalions, including one Guards battalion, plus six Conscript battalions, till March, 1920, at latest. Tocarry out adequately the duties placed upon the Army in Ireland these battalionsshould be maintained at a total strength of 25,000 men, exclusive of untrained recruits.Up to March, however, the number estimated as available in Ireland is 24,400. during march when the six Conscript battalions are demobilized the strength will fall to 19,000men.3. Transport. The transport available in the Army is barely, sufficient for ordinary administrative and supply purposes; in fact, owing to the shortage of soldierdrivers and artificers it has been necessary to engage a considerable proportion of civilians, whose loyalty could not be relied upon if the transport workers were called out on strike. In the event of a railway strike of any magnitude, extra mechanical transport would certainly be required for general supply purposes to supplement therailways now being made use of. Consequently there would be no War Departmenttransport available for the movement of troops from their permanent stations to areasof disorder, and for this service the War Office must necessarily depend on the Ministryof Transport.4. Signal Communications. The personnel available for these duties at presentin the Army is insufficient to carry out the minimum requirements for the Army alone,as the few men available are young and untrained, whilst wireless personnel are practically non-existent. The Army can, therefore, at present, give no assistance tothe civil authorities in the maintenance of signal communications, but on the contrarymust rely on the General Post Office for the maintenance of Army communications in emergency. The Army Council have, however, been informed by the Postmaster-General that in the case of a strike extending to the Post Office staff or of sabotageand consequent breakdown of telegraph and telephone communications, he cannotguarantee the maintenance of signal communications.5. Intelligence. The Intelligence Section of the General Staff of General Head-quarters, Great Britain, together with its subordinate branches throughout thecountry will disappear when General Headquarters. Great Britain, ceases to exist on31st January, 1920. Apart from the undesirability of the Army maintaining anIntelligence Section for industrial purposes, there is no machinery available at the WarOffice to carry on this work, and the Army will have to rely for such information onthe Home Office and its Intelligence Branch at Scotland Yard.

</content>
</cab>
