<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/96/0 images: 397-398</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/^BJMpV       ^-^-^JPll^tv of/Jk, /&apos; &apos;i p i. OA    )Vlf   /i .....jyfaVTftwi v&apos;-YTO^Rirr mjtm^&apos; .^4^3^^^a^PPiHS Controller observes that following on the      fjp^frjolwyn Committee Report a Conference has been appointed by theAdmiralty to draw up a soheme for utilising the surplus facilities in the dockyards for. mercantile shipbuilding.The Shipping Controller feels bound to put on record hismisgivings with regard to the policy adopted in this matter.   HefeeJ.s certain that any attempt on the part of the Government tobuild merchant ships under present conditions in the dockyards is bound not only to involve an expensive subsidy, but also to have farreaching and serious effects on the ordinary shipbuilding in thiscountry.In November last year, at the request of the Admiralty,the Shipping Controller consulted all the principal merchant ship-builders in this country with regard to the possibility of absorbingin their works the surplus workmen from the Naval Dockyards.   As aresult it was found that these yards could absorb a very largenumber of men, and a considerable amount of house accommodation was available, and had it not been for the change in the policy of theGovernment in this matter, the Controller has no doubt that by this time a large number of workmen would have been enabled to leave the yards and find profitable employment in useful work in MercantileShipbuilding Yards.The Shipping Controller is informed by a firm of Shipbuildersthat at the present time, far from the ultimate position of thecountry being eased, men are returning from the North of England tothe Dockyard towns.   The difference in value to the country iswell exemplified by the experience of one Tyne firm who found thatsquads of riveters from the dockyards only did one third of the work done by the other men.   The Controller feels that if the policy which makes this re-transference of men possible is not modified theresults will be extremely serious.   On the one hand the pressure fromthe dockyard employers will force the Government further and further into the policy of subsidising building in the Naval Yards, and on theother hand the ordinary shipbuilding firms in this country will suffer
mere and more from the loss of their skilled men.   There can Inthe Controller^ opinion be no reason why the men wfto Joined the dockyards during the War should not be disoharged so that they may find their way back to their original homes.The Shipping controller submitted an offer for usingone of the dockyards or a great portion thereof for extensiveRepairing purposes, which could have been extended to other ports.22nd January, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
