<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/96/0 images: 406-406</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ary Secret.This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majsst/s C Dvernmeot.1261From Viceroy, Army Department, to SecretIWi January 1920.(Received 20th.)Secretary of State for India,720.  No. 147.Part I. (1) Mahnmd, chief Orakzais Mullah, reported to be actively opposingreturn of deserters&apos; rifles by Orakzais. He &quot;states his intention of taking representa-tives of all sections of Orakzais to Jalalabad to interview Nadir Khan.(2) Some unrest continues in Kabul Khel Waziri country, where lashkars ofnomad and some Tochi Waziris have collected on several occasions, but have subse-quently dispersed without taking serious action.(3) Later reports give conservative estimation ol Mahsuds and Waziris killed on14th January as 200.(4) At least 500 Wana Waziris have left Malisud country for their homes.(5) Some Kharati Ghilzais, with 60 camel loads of supplies, reported to havearrived at Wana,(6) On 17th January Largha Sherannis accepted all Government terms.(7) Reported from Meshed that Governor of Herat under orders from (corruptgroups).. (8) Three Bolsheviks arrived at Herat on 7th January, and more were reportedto be en route from Kushk.Part II. (9) On 16th, enemy, 200 strong, attacked troops covering picketconstruction party of Derajat column. Our casualties, two killed, three wounded.Fifteen enemy dead counted, exclusive of those killed by guns and aeroplanes.(10) Picketing operations continued on 17th January. Enemy collecting inNullah surprised and bombed by aeroplanes, when our infantry and guns obtainedgood targets. Our casualties, five killed, 12 wounded. Enemy casualties unknown,but aeroplanes reported many dead and wounded.(11) Derajat Column advanced to new camp at Sara Rogha, about 1 mile southof Murgai Kach, on 18th. As movement was opposed and sniping and attacks onpickets continue, Climo has sent notice that agreement referred to in para. 5 of seriesNo. 146 of 16th. January is cancelled, and that there will be no cessation of hostilitiesor any dealings with them until lines and security for rifles are paid in full. Ashead of (? someone) found in jar at Nai Kach, Climo has authorised Skeen tocompletely destroy village.(12) Aeroplane crashed in Shuza Tangi on 15th. Pilot and observer brought insafely by Bhitannis on 16th.(13) Following are extracts from appreciation by Climo dated 7th January: (a) Regarding medical arrangements: &quot;I would here add that medical andother arrangements for the comfort and care of troops on this line are working admirably. It is not always realised what an effect this hasthroughout a force, and the knowledge that wounded men receive allpossible care and comfort on their way down.&quot;(b) Regarding tactics: &quot;The tribesmen therefore have the weapons andammunition for covering fire. This they employ, and under its coverthev are able to concentrate for attack and to carry out much of their approach after concentration. This to some extent accounts for the factthat they are not hesitating to attack up hill, and though this, it is true,does not fully account for the up-hill attacks which have so seldombefore been met with in former campaigns, and it should be (? realised)that the tribesman is now a more scientific fighter than he has been inthe past.&quot;(c) Regarding situation generally. &quot; To summarise above I am of opinion thatdays of lightning frontier campaigns, except against insignificant tribes,are over. Such campaings must be more deliberative, will entail moretroops for the defence of communications, will require more transport,and will be more expensive in lines, but the results obtained willprobably be better and more lasting as we will take heavier toll of theenemy, and will undoubtedly reduce his stock of fighting men. he cannot afford losses of 1,000, and I believe his losses on this front onthe whole must considerably exceed this figure.Paras. (7), (8), and (13) not communicated to Press.

</content>
</cab>
