<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/96/0 images: 465-466</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
v tl e)(THIS DOCUMENT, . XS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIA MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT).CONFIDENTIAL.CABINET.Q.P.495. mr&apos; &apos;&quot;&apos;THE SITUATION IN HUNGARY.Copy of letter from Mr, A, Henderson. M*JV* ^0 tiiePrime Minister.The Labour Party,33 Ecoleston Square,London, S.W.I.January 17th 1920.The Rt. Hon. David Lloyd George, M.P.,10 Downing Street,Whitehall,London, S.W.1,Dear Prime Minister,If the House had been sitting 1 should have been obligedto call attention to the situation In Hungary and refer to the responsibilities of the Allied Governments in relation to theterrible events which are happening there*The moat reoent information in my possession comes fromthe Secretary of the International&apos;, M. Caraille Huysmans, v/hoencloses communications from Hungarian Social Democrats now inVienna and Switzerland.    It includes the opinion of Garami -the most prominent of the Social Democratic Leaders - whodemonstratively declined to take any part in the Bolshevistexperiments of Bela Kun and is now compelled to go abroad asecond time and refuse any responsibility whatever for theWhite Terror inaugurated end continued under the eyes of theEntente.I am informed that the present Coalition Government,which has been formally constituted and recognised by theEntente, seems bent on exterminating every trace -of a labour movement by iH&amp;dering everyone who might by ^possibilityhelp in leading or building it up.From five to six thousand is the lowest estimate given of the number of persons murdered under the present regime.According to my informants, there is scarcely a villagein Trans-Danuoia where men and women have not been murderedwholesale, and more persons have been killed in the very smallvillages alone by the officers of the present Government thanin Budapest under the Red Terror*The number of persons arrested is put at 20,000 and therecent decree authorising looal police to intern all &quot;politicalsuspects&quot; and the members of their households is given as proofabsolute of&apos;the government&apos;s intention &quot;to render innocuous all men who have had any share In the Labour Movement.    I am evenassured that undor the rules of internment and the conditions prevailing in the internment camps, internment amounts, notmerely to penal servitude, but to a sentence of death.
These men who appeal to the British Labour Movementcling to tho hope that comfort will come to them from theWestern democracies, vtfiom it will bo difficult to persuadethat the atrocities of internment under the Russian Bolshevistregime are not being surpassed by those of the White Terror ir.Hungary under the auspices of a Government recognised rby theEntente*It Is alleged, on tho other hand, that the BritishMissions in Hungary, carrying out instructions,.has made representations and protests on several occasions.    my information is that these protests nave been formal andperfunctory,,   It is mentioned, for example, that the demand of the Head of the British Military Mission in Budapest forthe suspension of the sentence of death passed on the nineCommunists (including Korvin and Dr1, Laszlo) did not preventthe condemned men from being *duly hanged1, as the ^imes1correspondent has put it*It may also bo remarked in extenuation of the Alliesfpolicy that the Social Democratic&apos;Party of Hungary is associated with the present Coalition Government.    But to manySocial Democrats this is the most revolting aspect of thepresent events.    The sole reason for their membership of the coalition is the compulsion applied to their Party by theEntente, through Sir George Clerk, who gave them the alternative of joining the Government or accenting responsibility for the impossibility of concluding peacej    Sir George Clerk, on theother hand, did not insist that the Government which was formed$would furnish guarantees of democratic liberties and free elections,&apos;    The one Social Democratic member Is powerless, ishimself virtually a prisoner,, is no more than a sacrifice toan illusion of unity and democracy created for the purposeof deluding the Labour Movement of our own and other countries.,I hope that the British Government will make every effort to bring about an immediate cessation of the ^hite Terror in hungary, and suggestalso be encouraged to have confidence in the variousAllied Missions in their Countryj   and therefore,that a representative of the British Labour Movementshould be appointed to the British Mission&quot;in Hungary,with full diplomatic rights and privileges.(2)   that any economic or financial assistance to the hungarian Government should be made conditional upon every form of terror ceasing, and that theGovernment should make it its business to see thatthis condition Is fulfilled,Yours faithfully,(Sd)   Arthur Henderson,

</content>
</cab>
