<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/214/0 images: 138-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPEltTY Off HIS           MAJESTY&apos;S COvTOUBflSgT)     I circulate for the information of my colleagues a-vreviseddraft of the Land Valuation.Bill.  Since the earlier draft was before the Cabinet I have had the opportunity of studying cer-tain suggestions made by the Lord President of the Council andof discussing the Bill with Colonel Wedgwood, M.P., and thedraft has been to some extent modified to meet their points ofview.  I cannot however pretend that the Bill is even now inall respects satisfactory either to Lord Parmoor or to ColonelWedgwood - though.both I understand approve the main structure- and I have obviously not had time, in view of the prolongedproceedings on the Finance Bill, to devote myself to reachingcomplete agreement with them before the end of the session.However I am very anxious to give an earnest of good faith inthis matter and I propose therefore to publish the Bill in itspresent form, prefacing the publication by an answer to theeffect that I am circulating the Bill for the information ofMembers and that I shall be ready to consider any suggestions which may reach me in regard to the Bill before the time comesfor its re-introduction nest session.CP.264(30) .CABINET.LAND VALUATION BILL.jjote^by Lthe Chancellor of the Exchequer.( Intd)I .S.Treesury Ch&amp;members ,July  2nd,  1930.
Land  Valuation  Bill.           FINANCIAL MEMORANDUM.    The first valuation under the Bill will be a work of magnitude the cost of which cannot be estimated withprecision, but the amount required, including temporary-additions to professional and clerical staff, office accom-modation and equipment, is likely to  reach  1,000,000,the expenditure of which would be spread over a periodof approximately two years.    The further valuations at intervals of seven and fiveyears will, it is estimated, cost  125,000 on each occasion.    In addition, the cost of receiving, checking and re-cording the particulars of sales  and leases to be furnishedunder clause 5 of the Bill will, it is estimated, be  55,000in each full year.134-13A
JLand  Valuation Bill.ARRANGEMENT OF CLAUSES.Clause. 1.  Ascertainment of values.. 2.  Objections to and appeals from valuations. 3.  Particulars  to  be  recorded  and  furnished  by       Commissioners. 4.  Power of Commissioners to obtain information. 5.  Production to Commissioners of instruments trans-       ferring land. 6.  Supplementary provisions. 7.  Interpretation. 8.  Application to Crown lands and Duchy of Cornwall. 9.  Application to Scotland.10.  Short title.     SCHEDULES :      First Schedule. Incumbrances from which Land        is not deemed to be free for purposes of Valua-.        tion.      Second Schedule. Particulars to be furnished on        Production of Instruments of Transfer.134-13
DRAFTOF ABILLTO   Provide for the valuation of land in Great Britain  A.D. 1930.      and  for  purposes  consequential thereon.   BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,         by and with the advice  and consent of the Lords   Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons,  in this  present   Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : -       1. (1) Subject to  the  exceptions hereafter in this Ascertain-   section mentioned, the Commissioners of Inland Revenue ment of   (hereinafter referred to as &quot; the Commissioners &quot;) shall, values-   as soon as  may be after every valuation date, cause a]0 valuation  to be made  of  all  land in  Great  Britain   showing, with respect to every piece of  land, the land   value thereof as at the valuation date, that is to say, the   amount which the fee simple  in possession might  have   been  expected  to realise upon a sale in the open market] 5 on that date upon the assumptions         (a)  that there had not been upon or in the piece  ofland (i) any buildings;20  (ii) any works  except any road and  any works executed for the purposes of any publicservice or for agricultural purposes;25  (iii) anything  growing on the land exceptgrass, and any heather, gorse, or other natural growth, and, in the case of agricultural land,except also  hedges and trees other than fruittrees:134-13
 AJ). 1930.      (6) that the  purchase  price  had  been  computed                  without taking into account                        (i) the value of any minerals as such;                       (ii) the cutting value of any trees;                       (hi) the value of any tillages or manure, or 5                     of any improvements specified in paragraphs                     (20)  to  (28)  of the  First  Schedule to  the13 &amp; 14               Agricultural Holdings Act, 1923, being tillages,Geo. 5. c. 9.            manure or improvements for which any sum                     would by law  or  custom be payable to an 10                     outgoing tenant:               (c) that the sale had, save as hereinbefore in this sec-                   tion expressly provided, included all  property                   and rights which, if the land had been conveyed                   at the  valuation date, would, by virtue of sub- 1515 &amp; 16             section (1) of section sixty-fcwo of the Law ofGeo. 5. c 20.          Property Act, 1925, have  been  deemed to be                   included in the conveyance, except any shooting-                   rights  over the  land which  were  in  different                   ownership from that of the land, any shooting 20                   rights over other land, and any fishing rights:               (d) that the piece  of land  had  been  subject to                   no lease or  other tenancy and free from  any                   incumbrance except  any  of  those mentioned                   in the First Schedule to this Act, and  that 25                   all rights  to tithe, tithe  rentcharge,  or  other                   payment in  lieu of  tithe, issuing out of or                   charged upon the  piece  of   land, had  been                   extinguished:               Provided that it shall be assumed  for the purposes 30          of the valuation that the piece of land was sold with the          benefit of no greater rights of support or rights to receive          compensation for damage to the surface than were vested          in the owner at the valuation date.               (2) Where at any valuation date any piece of  land 35          comprises  agricultural land,  the  Commissioners  shall,          in addition to ascertaining the land value of the piece of          land, cause to  be  ascertained the  cultivation value at          that date of the agricultural land comprised therein, that          is to say,  what would have been the land value of the 40          agricultural land as ascertained in  accordance with the
    provisions of the last foregoing  subsection if there  had    been a restriction imposed  by law on the user thereof    permanently prohibiting its use for any purposes other    than agricultural purposes. 5      (3) The valuation  of any piece of land under  this    section shall be made upon the basis that all the circumstances-    stances affecting all other land  and everything thereon    and therein were the actual circumstances at the valuation    date.10      (4) Subject as hereinafter provided, every parcel of    land in separate occupation at the valuation date shall    be deemed, for the purposes of this Act, to be a piece of    land, and every valuation made  under this Act shall    show separately  the land value of every piece of landJ5  and  the   cultivation  value  of any  agricultural  land    comprised therein :        Provided that           (a)  where  any building is   divided  horizontally              and. the  several  divisions  are  in  separate20            occupations,  none  of the  divisions shall be              deemed to be a piece  of land, but the  site              of  the building shall be deemed to be a piece              of   land, and this  Act shall apply  to every              owner or occupier of a  division as if he were05&apos;            an owner or occupier of that piece of land:          (b) the  Commissioners may  cause the  land value              of   any two  or more contiguous parcels of              land in separate occupation but OAvned by              the same owner, and the cultivation value of30            any agricultural  land comprised  therein, to              be shown as if  the parcels were in the same              occupation and were one piece of land.        (5) The Commissioners  shall  cause  all  shooting   rights which  are,  at the valuation  date, in  different35 ownership from that  of  the land over which  they exist,   and   all fishing  rights,  * to  be  valued and the  value   thereof as at that date to  be shown in every valuation   made  under   this Act, and  this Act   shall   apply   accordingly as if those rights were parcels of land.
A.D. 1930.      (6) No  valuation  shall  be  made  under  this  Act         of any land which, at the valuation date               (a) is the site of  any building  exclusively used for                  the purposes of religious worship ;              (b) is a churchyard  or a burial ground maintained 5                  by a burial authority;              (c) is a park, garden or recreation ground under the                  control or  management of  any government                  department  or  local  authority, being a park,                  garden or recreation ground to which the public 10                  are admitted without charge;              (d) is owned by a statutory company and used for                  the purposes of  their  statutory undertaking,                  being  land  which  cannot be alienated  by the                  company  or  appropriated  to purposes  un- 15                  connected with their  undertaking.Objections       2. (1) As soon as may be after a valuation show-to and     jj^g the land value of a piece of land as at any valuationvaluations111 ^a^e  kas ^een made under the foregoing provisions of          this Act, the Commissioners shall cause a copy thereof to 20          be served on every person who appears to the Commis-          sioners to be the owner of the piece of land or of  any          part thereof, and if, before the  expiration of  six months          after the valuation date, any person having any estate or          interest in the piece of land (otherwise than by way only 25          of mortgage, charge, or  power to create a charge)  has          applied  tor a copy  of the  valuation, the Commissioners          shall also serve such a copy upon him.               (2)  If any  person upon whom a copy of  a valuation          has been served under the last foregoing subsection gives 30          to the Commissioners,  within the  period of thirty days          after the service of  the  copy upon him or within such          extended time as the Commissioners may on  application          made within that period allow, notice in writing that he          objects to the land value or the cultivation value shown 35          in the valuation, or to  the  omission therefrom of  any           cultivation value, stating the grounds of his objection,           and his  estimate of  the  land value of  the piece of land          to which the valuation  relates, and of  the  cultivation           value of any  agricultural land comprised therein, the 40
    Commissioners  shall  either cause  the  valuation to be  A.D. 1930.    amended in agreement with the objector or give notice          to him of their refusal to do so.        (3) Within such time as may be prescribed by rules  5 made under this section after a notice of refusal has been    served upon any person under  the last foregoing sub-    section, that person may appeal from the refusal to one    of the panel of referees appointed  under Part I of the    Finance (1909-10) Act,  1910, and the decision of the lo.Ed.7&amp;l 10 referee shall, subject as hereinafter provided, be final :    Geo. 5. c. 8.        Provided that any party to such an appeal (including    the  Commissioners) may appeal  on any question of law    from the decision of the referee  to a single judge of the    High Court, or, where the land value of the piece of land 15 in respect of which the dispute arises does not, as alleged    by the Commissioners,  exceed five hundred pounds, to    the  county court  for the district in which  the  appellant    resides or the property is  situate.  Any party shall have    a right of appeal from a decision of  a countj^ court direct 20 to the Court of Appeal.        (4) If,  before the date on which any valuation of    a piece of land becomes final, any estate or interest in the    piece of land (other than an estate or interest by way    only of mortgage, charge, or  power to create a  charge) 25 is acquired from  a person having any rights under the    foregoing provisions of this section, the person acquiring    the estate or interest shall, subject as hereinafter provided,    have the like rights under the said provisions as were, at    the  time  of the acquisition, vested in the person from 30 whom the estate or interest was acquired:        Provided  that where  the person from whom the    estate or interest was acquired was a person who was at    the time of the acquisition entitled under  this section to    have a copy of  a valuation served on him,  but  upon 35 whom such a copy had not then been served, the Com-    missioners shall cause a copy to be served upon that person    and, unless  before the expiration of  thirty days from the    date on which they do so the Commissioners receive notice   in writing of  the acquisition,  the person by whom the40 estate or interest  was acquired shall not be entitled to   have a copy served upon him.        134                  B
A.O, 1930.      (5)  The  Reference Cummittees  for  England, and         Scotland  constituted &apos; by  section  thirty-three  of  the         &apos; Finance (1909-10) Act, 1910, shall  make  rules  subject          to  the approval of  the Treasury for giving effect to the          provisions of  this section relating to appeals to  a referee, 5          and such rules shall in particular make provision               (a)  as to the time within which, and the manner in                  which, any such appeal is to be made;              (b)  as to the manner  in which the  referee  to whom                  any  such  appeal  is  to  be  made  is to  be 10                  selected;              (c)  for enabling the Commissioners and the  appellant                  and  any other person upon whom a copy of the                  valuation  appealed  against has  been served                  under this section  or  any  person  nominated 15                  by them to appear and be heard ;              (d)  for limiting the number of expert witnesses who                  may be heard to  one on each side except where                  the referee otherwise determines ;              (e)  as to the form in which  any decision of the 20                  referee is to be given, and as to the amendment                  of any such decision in pursuance of any direc-                  tions which, on  appeal  to any court, may be                  given by that court.              (6)  A referee  shall treat any appeal  under  this 25          section as an appeal both against the land value shown          in  the valuation to which the appeal relates, and against.          the cultivation value (if any) shown therein, or against          the omission therefrom of any such value,  as the  case          may  be,  and may,  if  he thinks  fit, increase  any land 30          value or  decrease any cultivation value  shown in any          valuation to which an appeal relates, and  may order          that  the  costs of  any appeal to him incurred by the-          appellant  be  paid by the  Commissioners,  and that  any          such  costs incurred by the Commissioners be paid by the 35          appellant, and  any such order as  to  costs shall have          effect as if it were an order of the High Court,  save  that          it  shall not  be  enforced  as such  except by leave  of          that court or of a judge thereof.               (7) Every valuation of a piece of  land  made under 40          tins  Act  shall,  subject  to  the   determination  of  any
   appeal,  become  final at the first date on which, under A.D. 1930.   the provisions of this section and of any rules regulating        appeals thereunder, no further objection or appeal can be   made with respect  thereto,  and a  valuation  Avhich  has 5 become  final  shall  remain  hi force  until  the next   subsequent valuation date.       (8) The Commissioners  may cause any valuation of   a piece  of land to be amended at any time before it  has   become final, but, upon any valuation being so amended,10 the valuation as amended shall be deemed to be a new   valuation, and the foregoing provisions  of this section   as to the service of copies  and (except as respects  the   objector,  if any, in  agreement with  whom the amend-   ment was made) as to  objections  and  appeals, shall15 apply thereto accordingly as if the valuation which  was   amended had not been made.        3. (1) The Commissioners shall keep a record show- Particulars   ing, in  relation to . every   piece  of  land of which  a to be re-   valuation is in force under this Act                    ^ord?f a?d                                                          furnished20      (a) the description of the piece of land;             by Com-        (b) the amount  of the land value  thereof,  and the missioners.            amount of  the  cultivation  value of any agri-            cultural land  comprised  therein, according to            the valuation in force;25      (c) the names  and addresses of the owners upon            whom  copies of the valuation have been served.        (2) On  the application  of any person having an   estate or interest in any piece of land, and on payment   of such fee, not exceeding two shillings and sixpence, as30 the Commissioners, with  the approval of the Treasury,   may determine, the Commissioners shall furnish to  him   a copy of the valuation thereof (if any) in force under   this Act.        (3) As soon as practicable after such date as  His35 Majesty  may, in relation to every valuation date, by   Order in Council declare to be the date at which the valu-   ation of all land in Great Britain has been substantially   completed, the Commissioners shall furnish to every rating   authority a copy of so much of the record  kept under40 subsection (1) of this section as relates to any piece  of   land wholly  or partially comprised in the area  of  that   authority, and  the rating authority shall keep deposited        134                  B 2
Power ofOomrnis-sioners toobtain in-formation.A.D. 1930.  at their offices every copy so famished to them, so long         as the valuation to which it  relates is in force, and shall,          at all reasonable times, allow any person to inspect and          take copies thereof or extracts therefrom free of charge.              4. (1) The Commissioners may by notice in writing 5          require the occupier of any land, or any person paying or          receiving rent in respect  of  any land (either on his own          behalf or on  behalf of any other person), to furnish to          them, within thirty days  after  service  upon him. of any          such notice or within such extended time as the Commis- 10          sioners may  allow,  returns  showing  such particulars as          it may be within his power to furnish  as to               (a) the  ownership,  tenure,  area,  situation  and                  character  of the land;              (&amp;)  any rent  payable to or by  him and the lease 15                   under which it is payable;              (c) the name  and address  of  any  person to whom                  he pays, or on whose behalf he receives, rent;              (d)  the consideration paid by him for his estate or                  interest in the land;                           20              (e) any  other matters  properly  required for  the                  purposes  of the  identification  and valuation of                  the land.              (2)  If  the  owner of  any land  furnishes to  the          Commissioners his  estimate  of  the land value or of the 25          cultivation value of  the  land,  the Commissioners  shall          consider it hi making the  valuation thereof.              (3) Any person authorised in writing  by the Com-          missioners  for that purpose  shall  have  a  right,  ou          production of his  authority, to enter on and  inspect at 30          all reasonable times any land or premises for the purpose          of obtaining any  information  required by the Commis-          sioners for the discharge of their functions under this          Act.              (4) If  any person fails to make a return which he is 35          required under this section  to make,  or wilfully omits          to show in any such return any  particulars  within his          power to furnish  which  he  may under  this  section be          required to  show,  or  wilfully delays or obstructs any          person authorised by the  Commissioners in the exercise of 40           any power conferred on him by this  section, he shall be           liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding          fifty  pounds.
        5. (1) On the occasion of                         A.D. 1930.          (a) any transfer on sale of the fee simple of land;  pr0(i^j0]ll          (6) the making of any agreement for a transfer on to Com-              sale  of the fee simple of land;                missioners 5        (c) the grant  of any lease of land  for  a  term ^&quot;tstrans-              exceeding fifty years (including an agreement ferring ]ana.              for any such lease);          (d) any transfer on sale of any such lease;          (e) the making of any agreement for the transfer 10            on sale of any such lease;   it shall be the duty of the transferee, proposed transferee,   lessee,  or proposed lessee to produce  to the Commis-   sioners the  instrument by means  of  which the transfer   is effected, or agreed to be effected,  or the lease or the 15 agreement  for  the lease,  as the case may be, and to   furnish to the  Commissioners Avith respect thereto par-   ticulars in accordance with the requirements of the Second   Schedule to this Act, and if he fails to do so within thirty   days after the  execution  of the instrument, he  shall be 20 liable on summary conviction to a  fine not exceeding   ten pounds :        Provided that where any agreement for a  transfer   on sale of the fee simple  of land or for any lease of land   for a term exceeding fifty years or  for the transfer on 25 sale of any such lease, and particulars with respect thereto,   have been produced to the Commissioners in accordance   with  the requirements  of this  section,  it  shall not   be necessary   to  produce  to the  Commissioners the   instrument transferring the fee  simple or granting or  - 30 transferring the lease in  pursuance  of the agreement,   unless that instrument is inconsistent with the particulars   so furnished.        (2) This subsection shall  not apply with respect to   any instrument which relates solely to  incorporeal  here-.35 ditaments other than shooting rights and fishing rights,   or to a grave  or  right of burial, or  which is  a mining   lease  only  or  an instrument  by means of  which the   transfer of a mining lease only is effected or agreed to be   effected. 40      (3) Notwithstanding  anything in section twelve of   the Stamp Act,  1891, no instrument  required  by this  54&amp;55Viet*   section to be produced to  the  Commissioners  shall be  c. 39.   deemed,  for the  purposes of section  fourteen  of that
 A.D. 1930. Act, to be duly stamped unless it is stamped with a stamp        denoting that  the provisions of this section have been          complied with.Supple-         6. (1) Any document issued by or on behalf of thementary    Commissioners under this  Act may be served on any  5provisions.  person by delivering  it to him or sending it by post to          his usual or last known address, or, if his address is not          known and cannot reasonably be ascertained, by leaving          the  document  addressed to him with  the occupier of          any land to which the document relates or of any premises  10          on such land,  or, if no such  occupier can  be  found, by          causing it to be posted in some conspicuous place on the          land.               (2) Where  any such  document is required to  be          served on any owner whose identity cannot reasonably  15          be ascertained, the document shall be  deemed for the          purposes of the last foregoing subsection to be addressed          to the person&apos; who is  the owner if it is addressed &quot; the          owner&quot; without further name or description,               (3) Any copy of a valuation signed by a  secretary  20          or assistant secretary of the Commissioners and produced          by any officer  of the Commissioners shall be received in          evidence,  and any copy  of a valuation purporting to be          so  signed as aforesaid shall be  deemed  to be so signed          and to be a true copy unless the contrary is proved.       2553 &amp; 54 Viet      (4) The provisions of the Inland Revenue Regulationc. 21.      Act, 1890, as amended  by section  thirty-eight of the59 &amp; 60 Viet. Finance Act, 1896, shall apply as  if this Act were an Acte. 28.      relating to  inland revenue and  as if any matter or thing          to winch  this Act relates were a matter or thing relating  30          to inland revenue and as if any person  employed by the          Commissioners for  the  purposes of this  Act were a          person employed in relation to inland revenue.               (5) Any  expenses incurred  by the  Commissioners           under this Act shall  be defrayed out of  moneys provided 35           by Parliament. Interpreta-      7. In  this Act,  unless  the context  otherwise  re- tion.       quires, the following expressions  have the  meanings           hereby respectively assigned  to them, that is to say                &quot;Agricultural land&quot;  means agricultural  land and 40                    agricultural buildings with respect to which, by                    reason of subsection (2) of section sixty-seven of
           the Local Government Act, 1929, no particulars A.D. 1930.           are included in any valuation list, or which are    &quot;y-           deemed under that subsection to have no rateable i,9 &amp; ?0 , -           value for the purposes of the list;  and includes, 5         in  relation  to any land  occupied by  or on           behalf of the Crown, any premises which if in           rateable occupation would be agricultural here-           ditaments   as  defined  by the  Rating  and 18 &amp; 19           Valuation (Apportionment) Act, 1928 :          Ge0- 5;c-44-10     &quot; Agricultural  purposes &quot;  includes  all  purposes           directly connected  with the  use of land  as           arable, meadow or pasture  land, or orchard or           osier  or woodland,  or for  market  gardens,           nursery grounds or allotments,  bat  does  not15         include the use of land for shooting or fishing :       &quot; Buildings &quot; includes erections but does not include           fences :       &quot; Burial authority&quot;  means any burial  board,  or           any council, committee, or other local  authority20         having the  powers and  duties of a burial board           under the Burial Acts, 1852 to  1906,  or  any           local authority maintaining a cemetery under           the Public  Health (Interments) Act, 1879, or 42&amp;43Viet.           under any local Act :                          c- 31.25     &quot;Lease&quot;  includes an underlease and  an agreement           for a lease  or  underlease,  but does not  include           any mortgage; and &quot; lessee &quot; and &quot;grant&quot; have           corresponding meanings :       &quot; Minerals&quot;  includes all minerals  and substances30         in  or  under land, obtainable by  underground           or by surface working :       &quot; Mortgage &quot; and  &quot; possession &quot;  have  the same           meanings as in the Law of Property Act, 1925 :       &quot; Occupier &quot;, in relation to any land not in occupation,35         means  the  person entitled to  the occupation           thereof:       &quot; Owner &quot;, in relation  to  any land  subject  to  a           lease granted for a term exceeding fifty years           which   has  commenced,  means  the  person40         entitled to the  term, or,  if there are two or           more  such  leases,  the  person entitled  to  the           term which will first expire, and,  in relation to           any other land,  means the person entitled to
90.iO.          the fee simple in possession; and &quot;owned&quot; and            &quot; ownership &quot; have corresponding meanings :        &quot; Public  service&quot;  means the supply  by  a public            authority or statutory company of gas, electrical -            eity, water,  telegraphic  or  telephonic  com- 5            munication, sewerage, or other public services :        &quot; Rate&quot;  and (except in relation to London) &quot;rating            authority &quot; have the same meanings respectively            as in the Rating and Valuation Act, 1925 :        &quot; Road &quot; does not in relation to any piece of land 10            include any road  which the occupier alone is            entitled to use, but save as aforesaid, includes            any  carriageway or footway, whether  a street,            lane, mews,  square, court, alley,  passage,  or            of whatsoever other nature,  and whether a 15            thoroughfare or not:        &quot; Statutory company &quot;  means any persons author-            ised  by any special Act to construct, work,  or            carry on any railway, canal, inland navigation,            dock, harbour, tramway, gas, electricity, water, 20            or other public undertaking; &quot; statutory under-            taking&quot; means such an  uridertaldng as afore-            said; and &quot;special Act&quot; includes any order            having the force of  an Act:        &quot; Valuation  date&quot;  means, as  respects  the  first 25            valuation made under this Act  the date of the            commencement  of this  Act,   as  respects the            second valuation so made the seventh anniver-            sary  of  that  date, and   as  respects  every            subsequent valuation the fifth  anniversary  of  30            the last preceding valuation date :        &quot; Works &quot; includes neither buildings nor erections nor            works for the reclamation of land or for the pro-            tection thereof from flooding, but includes fences. on      8. This Act applies to land belonging to His Majesty  35    in right of the Crown or of the Duchy of Lancaster and    to land forming part of the possessions of the Duchy of    Cornwall,  and, in relation to any such land, the officer or    department having the control  or management of  the    land shall be deemed to be the owner thereof except  40    where the land is subject to a lease granted for a term    exceeding  fifty  years which has commenced  and  the    person entitled to the term is so entitled otherwise than    on behalf  of the Crown.
        9. In  the  application  of  this   Act  to  Scot-  AD. 1930.   land                                                    -         (a) the Agricultural Holdings (Scotland) Act, 1923, to^cotlMKh.            shall be substituted for the Agricultural Hold- 13 &amp; 14  5         ings Act, 1923 :                               Geo. 5.c. 10.        (b) &quot; agricultural land &quot; means land which is shown            in the valuation foil as agricultural lands and            heritages:        (0) &quot;burial  authority&quot;  means  a county or town10         council  vested with the  powers   and  duties            conferred  by the Burial Grounds  (Scotland) 18 &amp; 19 Viet.            Act,   1855, as amended  by  any  subsequent e. 68.            enactment:        (d) &quot;rating  authority&quot; means a  county or town15         council, and &quot;rate&quot;  means any rate, charge or            assessment the proceeds of which are applicable            to public local purposes and which  is leviable            on lands and  heritages, except any rate levied            as a  domestic water rate in pursuance of the20         Public Health (Scotland) Amendment Act, 1891, 54&amp; 55 Viet.            or of any similar provision in a local Act:       c. 52.        (e) &quot; easement &quot; means &quot; servitude &quot;; &apos;&quot; mortgage &quot;            means &quot; heritable security&quot;  and  &quot; mortgage            debt&quot;  shall  be construed  accordingly;  &quot;in-25         corporeal  hereditament &quot;  means &quot; incorporeal            heritable right,&quot; &quot;agreement&quot; includes &quot;grant&quot;            and  &quot;incumbrance&quot;  means  &quot;burden&quot;   and            includes a burden or charge  incident to  tenure:        (/) references to the High Court and to the county30         court shall be construed respectively as refer-            ences to the Court of Session and to the sheriff            court,  and an appeal shall lie to  the Court            of Session from  a  decision of the  sheriff court            under  subsection  (3)  of  section two  of  this35         Act,  and any reference in the said subsection            to appeals  to the Court of Appeal shall  not            apply :       (g) &quot; owner &quot;, in the case of land under  an entail            means the institute or heir of entail in possession,40          and in the case of land subject to a liferent            means  the  liferenter, and in any  other  case            has the like meaning as  in section - seven of            this Act:              134            C
 A.D. 1930.      (h) for any reference to property and rights which                 would by  virtue of subsection  (1)  of  section                   sixty-two  of the Law of Property Act, 1925,                   have  been  deemed  to  be  included in  a                   conveyance of  land, there shall  be  substituted 5                   a reference to such property and rights as would                   have been included in a disposition  of the land                   in common form :               (i) for the  purposes  of  sections  two and three                   of this Act, the superior  of, or the creditor in iq                   a contract of  ground annual  relating to,  any                   land shall not be deemed  to be a person having                   an estate  or interest therein :               (j) section five of  this  Act  shall  apply  on  the                   occasion of any grant of a feu or of the creation 15                   of a  ground annual in like manner as it applies                   on the occasion of  a transfer  on sale, and the                   expression  &quot;transferee&quot;&apos; shall  be  construed                   accordingly:               (h) regulations may be  made  by the  Commissioners 20                   for  dispensing  with  the production  of  any                   instrument and the furnishing  of particulars                   thereof under section  five of this Act in cases                   where arrangements are  made  for  obtaining                   such particulars through any register of  sasines, 25                   and  where provision  is  made  for  dispensing                   with such production or furnishing of particulars,                   it shall be the duty of the Keeper of the General                   Register of Sasines, and  of the  keeper of  any                   local  register of sasines to furnish to  the Com- 30                   missioners particulars  of  instruments  presented                   for registration or registered in their respective                   registers as may be prescribed  by regulations                   of the  Commissioners, and in  any such  case                   the  provisions of  subsection  (3)  of the  said 35                   section five shall not apply :               (I) the Court of Session shall  have  jjower  by Act of                   Sederunt  to make rules with regard to  appeals                   to that court or to the sheriff  court under this                   Act.                                          40Short title.      10. This  Act may be  cited as the Land  Valuation          Act, 1930.
SCHEDULES.                   A.D.  I080.FIRST  SCHEDULE.                   Section 1,   INCUMBRANCES PROM WHICH  LAND IS NOT  DEEMED TO            BE FREE  FOR PURPOSES OP VALUATION. 5     1. RIGHTS  OF  COMMON, DRAINAGE  RIGHTS, CUSTOMARY RIGHTS,   PUBLIC RIGHTS, RIGHTS OF SHEEPWALK, RIGHTS OF WAY, WATERCOURSES,   RIGHTS OF WATER AND OTHER EASEMENTS.       2. LIABILITY TO REPAIR HIGHWAYS BY REASON OF TENURE.       3. LIABILITY TO REPAIR THE CHANCEL OF ANY CHURCH.10     4. LIABILITY IN RESPECT OF EMBANKMENTS, AND SEA AND RIVER   WALLS,       5. RESTRICTIONS ON USER IMPOSED BY LAW OR  AGREEMENT AND   BINDING ON THE OWNER AND HIS SUCCESSORS IN TITLE.       6. RATES AND TAXES, INCLUDING LAND TAX.15                  SECOND  SCHEDULE.                  Sections.      PARTICULARS TO  BE FURNISHED ON PRODUCTION OP                  INSTRUMENTS  OP TRANSFER.        1. WITH ANY  INSTRUMENT PRODUCED  TO THE COMMISSIONERS   IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE PROVISIONS OF SECTION FIVE  OF THIS ACT,20 THERE SHALL  BE FURNISHED TO THEM A DOCUMENT  (SIGNED BY THE   TRANSFEREE OR LESSEE OR BY SOME PERSON ON HIS BEHALF AND SHOWING   HIS ADDRESS), GIVING PARTICULARS -        (A) OF THE DESCRIPTION OF THE  INSTRUMENT;        (b) OF THE DATE OF THE INSTRUMENT;25      (C) OF THE NAMES AND ADDRESSES OF THE TRANSFEROR AND TRANS-            FEREE OR LESSOR AND LESSEE;        (d) OF  THE SITUATION OF THE LAND  TO WHICH  THE TRANSACTION            RELATES, INCLUDING ANY DIMENSIONS STATED IN THE INSTRU-            MENT, AND, IF NECESSARY  FOR  THE  IDENTIFICATION OF THE30          LAND, A DESCRIPTION OF THE BOUNDARIES THEREOF, OR A PLAN;              134               0  2
A.D. 1930.      (e)  of  the estate  or interest transferred, including, where   -               the transaction is the assignment or grant of a lease 2ND SCH.            or    transfer of a fee simple subject to a lease, the term                    of the lease, the date of the commencement of the term,                    and the rent reserved;                                5              . (/)  of  the consideration, if any, other than  the rent shown                    under the last paragraph, showing separately any capital                    payment,  any mortgage debt released, any  mortgage                    debt covenanted  to  be paid,  any periodical  payment                    (including any charge) covenanted to be  paid, any terms 10                    surrendered, and any land exchanged;               ig)  of any minerals, mineral rights, sporting rights, timber or                    easements reserved, and  of any restrictions, covenant,                    or conditions affecting the value of the estate or interest                    transferred or granted :                               15               Provided that, if a copy of the instrument produced to the           Commissioners is supplied  for retention  by them,  it shall  not           be necessary for the document furnished under this Schedule to           show any of the particulars required by the foregoing sub-para-           graphs, except those mentioned in sub-paragraphs  (d) and (e) so far 20           as they are not set out in the copy.               2. In  this Schedule the expressions &quot; transferor,&quot;  &quot; trans-           feree,&quot; &quot; lessor &quot; and &quot; lessee &quot; include, in relation to any agree-           ment for a transfer or lease, a proposed transferor, transferee,           lessor and lessee respectively;  and the expressions &quot; transferred,&quot; 25           &quot;assignment,&quot;  &quot;grant,&quot;  &quot;transfer,&quot;  &quot;reserved&quot;  &quot;released,&quot;           &quot; covenanted,&quot;  &quot; surrendered,&quot; &quot; exchanged &quot;  and &quot; granted &quot;           shall be construed accordingly.


Land Valuation.DRAFT   OF A. ILLTo provide for the valuation of land  in  Great Britain and for  purposes  consequential thereon.LXXXII.  (13.)22nd July 1930.134-13

</content>
</cab>
