<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/214/0 images: 275-276</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
liI3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAMUIC  MAJESTY&apos;8  GOVERNMENT).EC RE T. 277  (?o)COPY NO               CABINET.Co-ordination of London Passenger Traffic, Memorandum by the Minister of Transport.         After consideration of my memorandum CP, 2lf7( 30)the Cabinet at their meeting on July 2Jrd decided:-    (a)  That when, in September, the Committee of Home             Affairs is considering the order of priority of             the various Bills, they should give careful             consideration to the Minister of Transport&apos;s case             in favour of the London Traffic Bills    (b)  That before the next Meeting of the Cabinet the             Minister of Transport should, examine the question             of whether there is any means by which he could             erter upon negotiations with the interests concerned             without the necessity of announcing that a London             Traffic Bill would be included in the i ing&apos;s Speech             next Session.         I have impressed upon my colleagues the very serious difficulties, both financial and political, which would follow from indecision or delay, having regard to developments in theLondon Traffic situation and the history of the matter, includingthe circumstances of the passage of the London Traffic Act, 1324.         The present position is that I am expecting at anytime the financial report of Sir William McLintock and thevarious private and municipal traffic undertakings are expectingnegotiations to be opened at an early date;  already I have hadto answer a number of Parliamentary Questions enquiring as tothe reasons for delay.         I suggest, therefore, that it is of the utmost importance that I should be authorised to commence negotiations with thevarious parties concerned.   Having regard to the Cabinet decision,I shall, of course, be  careful in the course of the negotiationsnot to commit the Government as to what may or may not appear inthe King&apos;s Speech.   It is clearly impossible not to enter into negotiations because that would involve us in the untenable
position that we were not now pursuing the course I was authorised to indicate in the House of Gomcions last december.         I therefore ask that I may be authorised, to enter upon negotiations as soon as I am ready,    I shall then reportprogress to the Cabinet and/or the House Affairs Gomnitteeas suggestea in the&apos; first decision (a) quoted above.   (Intd.)  H.M.28th July, 15350.

</content>
</cab>
