<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/156/2 images: 10-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYlS government cp(71) 27 COPY NO1 March 1971CAB METSOCIAL SECURITY REVIEW 1971Memorandum by the Secretary of State  or Social ServicesINTRODUCTIONI am about to discuss with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, andshall very shortly put to my colleaguesa proposals for the main benefit increases and the contribution changes which will be needed to finance the uprating,,    We decided last year that the increases in the main benefits should compensate only for the rise in prices since the last uprating in1969* the latest forecast of which is 17 per cent.    On contributions, I think we shall have to move towards the structure of the new scheme, which will mean raising the earnings level up to which graduated contributions are paid from  30 a week to about  42.2.        This paper outlines She main changes I have in mind, particularly my proposals for using the funds which have been allocated to me, over and above what is needed for the main &quot;prices only&quot; uprating, to introduce selectiveimprovements for relatively small groups in special need, rather thanspreading the money thinly over large groups,,SELECTIVE IMPROVEMENTS3.        The improvements I suggest are concentrated on the chronic sick and the very elderly thereby fulfilling one of our main pledges.    The social services Committee have already considered my proposals in some detail;they are summarised in the Annex,,    They will in total benefit nearly2 million people.    The main features are as follows;-4.       For the chronic sick I plan to introduce an invalidity pension.    the pension itself will be at the same rate as sickness benefit,, but it will carry with it invalidity allowances (initially small) at three rates depending uponage at onset of incapacity,    The highest rate will go to those who falsickyoung, because they are likely to be denied the chance of building up savingsor occupational pension rights.    The allowance will continue into retire-ment.    The invalidity pension will also carry with it substantial improvementsfor the children and the working wives of the pensioners.    these improvements and the invalidity allowance will also apply to unemployablepensioners under the industrial injuries and war pensions schemes.5. For the very elderly. I propose to extend the old persons1 retire-ment pensions under the 1970 Act to all non-pens^cccffs over 80, but as a personal benefit not carrying with it any benefit for less elderly dependants.6.        I propose an age addition of 25pfor all retirement pensioners of 80or over.    Households with a supplementary pensioner over 80 will have 25padded to their long-term addition.
7, In accordance with our election pledges I propose to ease the earnings rule and increase the increments for deferred retirement;,8,       My proposals include small special improvements in the warpensions field and in the provision for adolescents in supplementary benefithouseholds,,SUPPLEMENT FOR FIRST SIX MONTHS OF UNEMPLOYMENT,SICKNESS OR WIDOWHOOD9.       Earnings ^related supplement to benefits (ERS) is 33-j per cent of earnings between  9 and  30 in the tax year preceding the claim.   changing the contribution band to  9 -  42 would in my view necessitate acorresponding change for FRS.    Following discussion in the Social services committee I have in mind two stage si  9 -  35 for new beneficiaries from may 1972f  9 -  4?. from May 1973s limiting the increase in expenditure by reducing the percentage to 30 from May 1972,    I am discussing this with treasury Ministers,UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT FOR OCCUPATIONAL PENSIONERS10,       My colleagues h&amp;v$-z.gt&amp;&amp;&amp; to legislation to deal with misuse ofunemployment benefit by some occupational pensioners0    The social services Committee after two discussions agree that a test of further workand a sliding scale of benefit are both necessary, but that the levels of occupational pension above which these will apply should be substantially-higher than proposed by the Labour Government and that there should be a contribution concession,    I therefore propose that men over 60 with pensions of  30 a week or more should not qualify for unemployment benefit orcontribution credits unless they have satisfied a test of 6 months further worksince retirement and that the benefit payable to those over 60 with pensionsabove  18 a week should be reduced on a sliding scale.    To help those wholose credits, I propose to allow non-employed people over 60 to pay a class 3 contribution each week voluntarily instead of c ampuls or ily.    the saving will be   2 million a year g   3 million was allowed for in the public expenditure White Paper,COSTS11.       The cost of the selective improvements can be contained within mypublic expenditure programmes which allowed a sum of  45 million In a full year for this purpose f minor adjustments may be needed when we havedecided the main benefits etc.    There is also the extra cost, from 19^3-74,cf the changes in earnings-related supplement suggested in paragraph 9 above.This is the natural consequence of raising the level of earnings up tc whichcontributions are charged and will be a normal feature of our new earnings-related system of contributions,    I am discussing with the Chief Secretaryhow those costs should be dealt with in our public expenditure programme.EFFECT ON PUBLIC SERVICE MANPOWER12.       I estimate that these proposals will require 300-35 0 extra staff in myDepartment and the Department of Employment, at an approximate cost of 750, 000-  850, 000 a year.2
CONCLUSION13.       I invite my colleage\ies! agreement to my proposals9 and to theirpublication in a White Paper to follow shortly after the announcementplanned at the end of March, in advance of the introduction of the BilLK department of Health and Social Security, SE11 March 19713
ANNEXIMPORTANT BENEFIT IMPROVEMENTS ADDITIONAL TO THE INCREASES IN THE MAIN UPRATING-NATIONAL INSURANCE1.     Invalidity AllowancePayable to invalidity pensioners where incapacity began before the age of:-2.     Dependency increase for the children of invalidity and retirement pensionersThe higher rate of dependency increase at present payable to the children of widowsto be extended to these pensioners.   This will be worth about  1 extra per childafter the uprating.3o    Earnings rule for working wives of invalidity and retirement pensionersInstead of the present all or nothing rule, the more favourable one applicablehitherto only to retirement pensioners (improved as in 5 below) to be applied tothese wives.4,     Short term benefit for working wives of invalidity and retirement pensionersIf auoh wives fall sick or unemployed, they are to get standard short term benefit,instead of the married woman&apos;s rate.5.    Retirement pensions earnings ruleThe amount of earnings free of the rule to be increased from  7.50 to  9.50,6.     Increments for deferred retirementTo be increased by 20 per cent, from 5p to 6p for 9 contributions paid,and from 2-g-p to 3p for wives.7.     Pensions for the over-80sPersonal benefit for all non-pensioners over 80, at the same rates as the oldpersons&apos; pensions under the 1970 Act.8.    Age addition to retirement pension25p to be payable to all retirement pensioners over 80 as a personal benefit(compare 16 below).WAR PENSIONS9.     Preferential AllowancesThese small allowances peculiar to the war pensions schemes have not been upratedsince 1967, and in one oase since 1961, and with one exception they are to beincreased to make good their loss in value since they were last increased.3545 160 (men)/55 (women)60p30p1
10,   Exoo-jjtipnalXy, severe disablement allowanceNot increased since introduction in 1966 at  3.   To bo  it-.^1*   Cove r for war    dowsTo be extended to widows of men who received a high rate of constant attendance allowance, notwithstanding that death was unconnected with thsir pensioned disability^2.   War Jgidorrs^age allowan0eAn allowance of jj^P to be payable from age 65 to 70* after which the existing higherallowance becomes payable.13.   Unemployable pensionersTo be eligible for the chronic sick package (1-4 above).INDUSTRIAL INJURIES14o   Comparable improvements to those in 10, 11 and 13 above.SUPPLEMENTARY BENEFITS15.   Improvement in .3,calg rates for adolesoentsTo be increased over and above the uprating increase giving the largest increase,probably 35?, to children between 13 and 15.16.   Improvement in lon^-texTn addition for the oyer-SOsHouseholds containing a person over 80 to receive a long-term addition 25p higherthan that paid to other supplementary beneficiaries.   This provides a benefitsimilar to 8 above but adapted as appropriate to the principles of the supplementary benefits scheme.2


</content>
</cab>
