<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/147/0 images: 191-210</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION  OF  THE  ATTACHED  WESTERN  AND  GENERAL                           REPORT,  No.  35.                                     CANADA.   The session which has  just closed has been  remarkable, not only for  its length,but also for the importance of the issues discussed and  the measures passed into law,chief among which are the  Military Service Act, the War Time Elections Act, and thepurchase of the Canadian Northern Railway.   The Labour Congress  has wisely and patriotically accmieseed in  the  Military-Service Act, while putting in a strong caveat against any development of the measure which  might  make for  industrial conscription.  The  line taken is, in fact, identical with that taken by organised labour in  this country, after similar initial opposition.   The importance  of  the  War Time Elections  Act  is strikingly indicated by  anarticle in  &quot;The  Times&quot; of  26th  September,  which,  points  out  that  in.  1911  theEnglish-speaking  vote  polled  was 706,000,  or 51- per cent, of  the whole  electorate.To-day at  least  a third of  that vote is actually  in  the  trenches or in  hospital,  andprobably nearly half in uniform.  If the soldiers were not  enfranchised, the non-English speaking elements would  constitute a decisive majority  of the  electors.                                    AUSTRALIA.   According to this morning&apos;s press telegrams the attempt of  the Extremist sectionof Labour  to make Mr. Hughes&apos; Government impossible by  wholesale strikes  (seeReport No. 31) has ended in complete failure.                                      ITALY.   Italy is becoming increasingly more  difficult  to humour.   She is excessively soreat the idea that France  should secure more attention to her demands for coal and othernecessaries.   There may be some reason in her complaint.   Put she weakens her caseby her own reluctance to help herself or to face sacrifices in any degree comparable tothose made by France.   Unless England is prepared to buy her oranges at a loss shethreatens to send them  to Germany.  If she is  asked to help escorting the coal cargoesfor which  she has been incessantly clamouring she  at once discovers that she cannotspare  her destroyers.  Similarly  in the  military  sphere her  own  immediate  con-venience appears to count  for more than the  concerted strategy  of  the Alliance.   Shecannot have it both ways, and unless she plays up more whole-heartedly, she is not unlikely to find her claims treated with scant consideration in the final settlement.                                     GREECE.    The Arsenal incident shows the anxiety of  the  French to  secure  control over theGreek Navy as well as  over the Greek Army.
                                    HOLLAND.   Sir YT. Townley&apos;s prompt offer of British coal seems to  have been  just in time toprevent Holland putting her neck in the noose of a peculiarly objectionable economicagreement with Germany.   It remains to be seen if we  and the Americans  can nowkeep Holland running straight.                                    SWEDEN.   The iinal result of the elections, just to hand, places  the Liberal Socialist victorybeyond dispute, and makes the continuance of the present  regime  very difficult.  the conservatives.only hold 58 seats to  62  held by the Liberals, and 86 by the officialSocialists.                                    A Fit! KNTJNA.    Germany is evidently desperately anxious  to keep the peace with.  Argentina.Apart from  the  loss of the large stocks of supplies of various kinds which she hasbought up  and holds there with a  view to  the return of peace, she  dreads  a stillfurther loss of  territory on  that  economic war  map which has changed  so terribly toher disadvantage  in the last few months.  Since  the beginning  of the year nearly11,000,000  square miles of the worhPs  richest regions  have been transferred  byGermany&apos;s  blunders  from  the neutral to  the Allied zone;  the former, in.  fact, now only consist of the European neutrals and of such South and Central American  states as have not yet broken off relations with her.                                PEACE DISCUSSIONS. -  The  Imperial  replies  to the Papal  Note look as if the Central Powers meant toshow their determination to be as wholedieartcd in the domain of unctuous rectitude asin that of  frightfulness.  They are, apparently, by  way  of a pious preface  to theactual  terms  of  which the  first instalment is contained in Herr von Ivuhlmann&apos;s interview with the Papal Nuncio in Munich, outlining  German views as to Belgium.The  offer  to  restore and  partially compensate Belgium,  asking  only for a guarantee against  the &quot;menace&quot; of 1.91-1, arid for commercial facilities,  and disclaiming alldesire, to interfere with Belgian  domestic affairs beyond insisting on the maintenanceof the new  division between Plunders and Wallonia, is no doubt  meant to satisfy theReichstag  majority,  and, possibly,  to affect opinion in Belgium itself.  It is clearlyunacceptable  as it stands.27th September 1917.L. S. A.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic  Majesty&apos;s Government.Printed for the  War Cabinet.                  4 8SECRET.                                                         FOR  REFERENCE  ONLY.WESTERN    AND   GENERAL    REPORT.No. 35.   Week ending 26th September (night).CONTENTS.PART I. British Empire and Africa.        Canada.             Prorogation of Parliament.  War-time Elections  Bill.   Trades and Labour Congress               and conscription.   Enforcement of  Military  Service Act.   Arrangement  for               exemptions.   Forthcoming  Proclamation calling men up.   Lord Reading  to visit               Ottawa.  Financing-  of  wheat  crop.  United States troops to  train in Canada.               Passports for those leaving the Dominion.&apos;        Australian Commonwealth.             Mr.  Hughes and  German  possessions  in  the Pacific.   Surtax on  single men and               childless widowers.  Failure of the strikes.  Building of wooden ships.        New Zealand.             Leave arrangements for Expeditionary Force.        South Africa.             Libel action by General Botha ;  objects of German  South-West African campaign\               position of  Nakob on the  map.  Return  of  Governor-General from  Swaziland.               Supply of craft for Lake Nyasa.        Basutoland.             Contribution to War funds.        British East  Africa.             Distribution of forces.        German  East Africa.             Shortage of imported foodstuffs.  German local currency.        Liberia.             Departure.of ex-German Consul for Spain.         Straits Settlements.             Demand for subsidiary coinage.PART II. Foreign Affairs.        Allied Common Affairs.             The  Paris  Conference and the  representation of Poland.  Constitution of an  inter-               Allied Board of Blockade.   Inability of Siam to  co-operate in Allied embargo.        France.             New French War Committee.  Vote of confidence and co-operation of Socialists  in the               Chamber.  M. Caillaux and  the &quot; Bonnet Rouge.&quot;  Further arrests.   &apos;     I&quot;&apos;b&apos;- ;   &apos;                  . &apos;  &quot;.   .        ^ &apos;- .          .  \             The grain outlook.   The coal  shipments.  Failure to secure Italian, naval co-operation.        Albania.             Employment of Essad Pasha.         Greece.             The  British  Naval Mission.   French designs on  the  Salamis arsenal.   The  re-               occupation  of Janina.   Question of Italian.  Vice-Consulates  in  Epirus.   The               provisioning of Greece and the  proposed abolition of the navicert system.        Serbia.             Jugo-Slav volunteers in  the  United States.   Serbian  deserters in  Switzerland  and               Socialists in Sweden.        German  Affairs.             The  Seventh  War Loan.  Favourable economic  situation.  Dr. Michaelis&apos; tenure of               office.   Von Tirpitz&apos;s speech.  &quot; Germania&apos;s &quot; criticism of Pan-Germans.        Austrian Affairs.             Hungarian finance.        Holland;             British offer of coal accepted.  The German economic  pressure.   Question of embargo               on Holland and Belgian relief.  (33) 3897--4  Pk   80 9/17  E A S .                 A
9Switzerland.    Swiss partially  in  supply of  munitions.   Protest  against suspension  of  transit      facilities.   Offer of Egyptian oil cake.Sweden.    Detention of Swedish diplomatic hags at Halifax.  The export of h&apos;on ore to Germany.      Refusal  to release goods in transit through Sweden.  Importation  of oilcake from      Russia.   Mr. Trygger&apos;s speech.  Proposed Allied action in Sweden.Norway.     Large exports of United  States flour to Norway.  Position of British Government in.      consecmence of this.Denmark.    British apology for violation of  territorial  waters.  The  bacon, fish,  and  mineral oil      questions.  German manoeuvres in the Danish Press.Spain.     The  German submarine  at Cadiz.   The coal agreement.   Sterling exchange and the      prohibition of the export of gold from the United States.Portugal.     Visit of President of Portugal to the West  Front.Siam.     Deportation of enemy aliens.Argentina.     Relations with Germany.  Count Luxburg&apos;s safe conduct.  Bunkers for neutral ships      bound for the Plate.  Visit of H.M.S. &quot; Glasgow.&quot;Mexico.    Rebel Conference in opposition, to General Carranza.Peru.     Decline of interest in the  &quot; Lorton &quot; case.Cuba.    Recruiting for the British West India Regiment.Costa Rica.    Rupture of  diplomatic relations with Germany.Uruguay.    Pro-Ally demonstration and the Arbitration Treaty.United States.    Lord  Reading&apos;s reception  by the  President.    American  assistance   to  France.      Sir W. Wisemans  Report.   Proposed visit of the Secretary for War to Europe.      The Anglo-American Military Convention.The Shipping Situation.    Submarine  losses.    Japanese  shipbuilding.   Employment  of   ex-enemy  ships in      Portugal, China,  Siam.,  and Uruguay.  Use of the Kogrund Passage.Peace Discussions.    German and Austrian replies to the Papal Note.  Pan- German move, and the effects of      the Erzberger agitation.  Action  of  the  Majority Group.  Special Peace terms for      Belgium.  The  situation in  France.   French  desiderata.  Mission of  Kuhlmann&apos;s      brother-in-law to Holland.  International Peace Congress in Berne.General.                                                            ,    Arrangements for  prisoners  in  Holland.    Atrocious  ill-treatment  of  prisoners in       Germany.  Position of prisoners in Tui-key.   Case of Ayoub  Sabri.   Transfer of       officers to Holzminden.   Red Cross Conference, in Copenhagen.
PART  I.-BRITISH  EMPIRE  AND   AFRICA.                                    CANADA.    The  prorogation  of  the  Dominion Parliament on 21st September brought  toan end the longest session of  the longest Parliament in the history of the Dominion.In  the  course of the ceremony of prorogation, which  took place  in  the Senate, theGovernor-General reviewed the  measures  to which the Royal Assent had been given during  the past eight months, and stated that  the  people  of Canada had  neverfaltered in the supreme purpose of securing an abiding peace through victory.    The War-Time Elections Bill was passed by the Senate, with certain amendments,the day before the rising of Parliament.    Considerable discussion took place at  the annual Convention  of the Trades andLabour  Congress upon the subject of conscription.  A number of Resolutions were submitted and. a Special Committee was appointed to consider them.  This committee recommended the adoption of the following :     Under the present form of Government we  do not deem it right, patriotic, or  in      the interests  of the Labour movement of the Dominion to  say anything that      might prevent the Government from obtaining the  results anticipated  in      raising reinforcements for the Expeditionary  Force  by the  enforcement  of      the law.    The Congress  emphatically opposes any development in the enforcement of this      legislation which will  make for industrial  conscription  or  interfere with the      trade union movement in taking care of  the interests of  the organised workers      of the Dominion.    A message was read from Mr. Gompers, President of the American Federation ofLabour,  regretting that  he  could not  be present especiaRy at  a time when  theworkers of the two countries were drawn close together in  the  struggle for the greatcommon cause.   After  a long  debate  the Congress   decided to  adopt  the  aboveResolution by 113 to 106.    The Trades and Labour Congress re-elected Mr. J. C. -Waiters as President.    A Conference took place at Ottawa on 10th September between the Prime Minister,the Minister of Justice, and the Members of the Military Service Council to  considerthe course  of action  necessary to put the Military Service Act into  operation withoutdelay.    The Department  of Justice  has  issued a statement for the information of menliable to  military  service.   This indicates  that  exemption is determined by civiltribunals wdiose members are familiar  with local conditions.  Of  this tribunal, one member is  the local County Court Judge, or some person,  selected by  him, and theother is appointed  by the Board of  Selection.   The last-named body is composed ofmembers of whom the Government Leader nominates one-half  and the Leader of theOpposition the other half.  It is pointed out in  the statement  that those composingthe Local Tribunals will  generally have a  personal knowledge of  the economic and family reasons why those who come before them have not voluntarily enlisted and willbe able sympathetically to estimate the  weight  and importance of such reasons.There wdll be an appeal from the Local Tribunals to Provincial Appellate Tribunals ;while a  Central Appeal Tribunal will be constituted in  order to  ensure the applicationof  identical principles  throughout  the  Dominion.   Meantime,  those  liable  to conscription are being urged to go before the Medical Boards without delay, as acertificate of tin-fitness from the Board will  obviate the necessity of going before the exemption tribunals,  while  a certificate of fitness wdll not prevent  an  appeal for exemption being made on other grounds.    The Recruiting Authorities  claim that with the assistance of the civil and militarypolice it will be very difficult for men to ignore the forthcoming Proclamation callingthem up  for military service.   It is proposed  that badges shall  be worn  by men-affected by the Act for purposes of identification.   During the  first two weeks of thepresent month 6-10 men were attested in Toronto under the Act.    Lord Reading has telegraphed -that he and Lord  Northcliffe  have accepted,  an invitation to visit Ottawa from 4th to 6th of October.    As a result of a Conference between the Minister of Finance and  the Executive ofthe Canadian Bankers&apos; Association on the question of financing the exportable surplus-of the wheat crop (vide Reports No. 33 and  No. 34), arrangements have been concluded
for the Banks to supply a credit of $ SO,000,000.  The wheat will he held as securitytill it reaches the seaboard, when the Banks will be paid by the British Government.    Owing to the fact that the United States Government  have not sufficient training-camps in readiness for all the  men who have been already called to  the Colours, ithas been arranged that 10,000  United  States troops shall  cross to Canada at once inorder to undergo training at Niagara Camp.    An Order in Council has been passed  prohibiting any person embarking at  anyCanadian port for a destination outside the Dominion or the United  States without.a passport.   Infringement of the Order renders the person liable to a  fine of  f 1,000or imprisonment for two years, or both.   The  master or officer in charge of a vesselpermitting  a passenger  to  sail without  a passport is  made  liable to  the samepunishment.                       AUSTRALIAN  COMMON WEALTH.    The Prime  Minister (Mr. Hughes) has  announced that the  British Governmenthave expressed  their approval of the Commonwealth policy in relation to the  German possessions in the Pacific, but  that  they consider  the present time inopportune for making a public pronouncement on the subject.    Sir John Forrest introduced a  motion in the House of Representatives  last weekproviding  for  a special surtax on single  men and  childless  widowers between the ages of 21  and  45,  eligible for military service.  The money raised would be usedfor the purposes of repatriation.   In response  to  criticism made in  the House, theGovernment decided to redu.ce the tax to  51. or 5 per cent, and to widen the scopeof the Bill in order to include all single men  and  childless widowers over 21.   TheBill has now passed the House of  Representatives.  The  Senate have amended the-Bill, with the approval of the Government, exempting men over 60 whose gross income is under 100L and also incapacitated single men receiving under  150L    The strike of the employees of the railway workshops in Sydney last month whichwas followed later by other Railway and Tramway Unions, coal-miners, &amp;c, in NewSouth Wales and other States (vide Report No.  31), has resulted in  complete failure.Thousands of the strikers, for  the most part New South Wales  railwaymen, have had their places filled by voluntary workers employed by the Government.  It is estimated that there are some  50,000 unemployed in Sydney in consequence  of the strike, and thenumber is considerable in other States.   Several important Unions have been removed from the register by the Arbitration Courts.    Replying to a question in  the House of Representatives, Mr. Hughes stated that the Government did net intend to build wooden ships.                                NEW  ZEALAND.    With regard to the arrangements  approved,  by the  Dominion  Government  for granting leave to members of the Expeditionary Force who have completed three years&apos; service (vide Report No. 32), the Army Council have conveyed their grave apprehension as to the proposed conditions.   It is pointed out  that if  these  are to  apply to the- New  Zealand  Forces  they must equally apply to  all Imperial and Colonial  troops,, wdierever  situated,  irrespective  of  military  necessities,  and  this might  seriously compromise  the conduct-  of operations.   The   proposal   that  those   who  do- not  wish  to  proceed  to  New Zealand  should receive two months&apos;  leave  in the United Kingdom or  France is  regarded by the Army  Council as  open  to still greater objection from the standpoint of the impression created upon other troops.  The New  Zealand, troops have, it is stated, received the  same leave and facilities as other troops and preferential treatment could not be justified.  Further- more  the Admiralty  point  out that as the  proposed privileges would have to  be extended to all oversea troops if granted  to those from  New Zealand, it would  be- practically impossible to provide the  necessary shipping and escort, and that the employment of more ships as transports for this purpose would increase the difficulties connected with the shortage  of mercantile shipping.  In. the interests of&apos;the men themselves, it is added, the submarine menace  renders it advisable that there should be no more troops at sea  than  is absolutely necessary.  The British  Government. therefore  consider  that leave facilities  beyond those now  granted  wrould  be very undesirable and they express the hope  that the Dominion Government wdll not press their  proposals.
                                SOUTH AFRICA.   Tlie action in which General  Botha claimed  5,O00Z.  damages  against  SenatorWolmarans  for alleged libel, contained in statements connected with, the rebellionand the South-West African campaign, concluded on 20th September.   An important feature of the  case   was  the  question  whether  the German  attack  on  Nakobconstituted  an attack  on Union territory; the contention of Mr. Wolmarans  andthe Nationalists being that  Nakob was in German territory.  The evidence  showed that when the Railway Board was reporting on the railway from Prieska to Upingtonand Ealkfontein, an official map was secured showing Nakob as being on the Germanside of the border.  The Board learned that a police  post on the Union side was alsonamed Nakob, and authorised an alteration of the map accordingly.  In the coarse ofhis evidence, General Botha stated that the German South-West African campaign wasnot undertaken with a view to the  annexation or eventual possession of the country,which entirely depended on the terms of peace.   If  the Germans had immediatelysurrendered the Southern ports and the wireless statious, he did not think he wouldhave  moved any further, as  these objectives were all that the Imperial Governmentasked him to take.  The Presiding  Judge said that  he could not accept the statement that there had been any falsification of the map with regard to the  position of-Nakob,although perhaps the  alteration had occasioned  a  good  deal of  irritation.  the explanation  given, he  added,  wras quite an acceptable  one.  In  the  result,  the defendant unconditionally withdrew  all his  allegations against General  Botha, for whom, therefore, judgment was given with costs.   The Governor-General and Lady Buxton have returned to Pretoria from  a briefvisit  to Swaziland, where they met officials and European residents and a large and representative gathering of native chiefs.    The Union Government  have expressed their regret that they  cannot  supply anytugs or barges for use on Lake Nyasa.  They suggest that  powerful  motor or. steamlaunches, capable of carrying from four to six tons of  stores and  40 to 60 passengers,and of towing small boats, might be used, and  they express the belief that  14 to 25of these could be obtained at Durban.  In lieu of barges, the Ministers  suggest theemployment of small dhows, which could be purchased on the East African coast.                                BASUTOLAND.   A further sum of 10,026Z. has been forwarded by the Basuto nation to His majesty the Ring as a contribution to various war  funds.  This  brings their  total  gifts up to52,887Z.^                           BRITISH EAST AFRICA.   In reply to the suggestion of the Government of  the  East Africa Protectorate as tothe employment of part of the l/6th Battalion King&apos;s African Rifles on the JubaRiver(vide  Report No. 34), the Secretary  of  State  has  sanctioned  this and the proposeddistribution of the Forces.                           GERMAN EAST  AFRICA.    The Administrator  of German East  Africa reports that the supply of imported.foodstuffs for the civil population  is becoming a serious  matter.   Export has beenprohibited by the East Africa  Protectorate and Zanzibar on account of  shortage, andthere are no direct shipments to German East African ports from  overseas. further the British India  Steam Navigation  Company cannot  afford space, as that alreadyallotted to British ports in East Africa will, not meet the requirements.  It  is therefore suggested that the Government of India might arrange for accommodation for foodstuffsin transit to Tanga or Dar-es-Salaam via Zanzibar or Kilindini.    In view of the  demand for silver in India, the suggestion  has been put before the administrator of German East Africa, by His Majesty&apos;s  Government that  the surplusGerman local currenc.y might be sold to the  Indian Government at bullion value.   Atthe present price of silver (50 pence an ounce) it is pointed out  that this could  bedone with profit to the Administration.     3897- -1                            B
                                   LIBERIA.   The British Consul at Monrovia reports that  the Spanish steamer &quot; Cataluna &quot; left-Monrovia on 20th September  with the  ex-German Consul on board,  The intentionof the ex-Consul, it is stated,  is to travel to  Spain in order to evade the conditions  ofhis  safe-conduct, and it is reported that he is carrying with him to that country bothmails and money in gold.                          STRAITS  SETTLEMENTS.   The Governor states that,  on account of  the  rise in the price of silver and the high rate of exchange with Hong Kong, there is a  great  demand for  subsidiary coinage.A Commission of   Enquiry  appointed by  the  Governor  has   recommended thereduction in  the  fineness of  small  silver  coins to -100, and  the Governor hasenquired from the Indian Government whether  this can  be done, and to what extent the output  could  be  increased.   The Commission  also recommended that 10 and25  cent  notes should be printed  locally  at once.  The sanction of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment is therefore  sought for the debasement of the subsidiary coinage if Indiacan arrange it, and for the immediate preparation of the notes locally.PART  II.-FOREIGN  AFFAIRS.                         ALLIED COMMON AFFAIRS.   ddie Italian Minister for Foreign  Affairs is anxious that the proposed  allied conference should be held in Paris in October, even if the&apos; Russian Foreign Ministercannot attend, as he is anxious that  the policy to he pursued in the event of the totalcollapse of Russia should  be discussed, as well as the reply to  he given to the PapalPeace Note.   The Russian Minister  for Foreign Affairs  has informed Sir G. Buchanan that- hecould not consent to the proposed  representation of Poland, as a State, in the  allied conference.  He  had, however, offered to include a  Russian  Pole, who enjoyed theconfidence  of his  compatriots, in  the  Russian Delegation to the Conference, and considered that the Conference would  have  to discuss  the  measure  of financialassistance to  be given to Poland  by the Allies in order to launch her on her career  asan independent State, as well as the territorial limits of the future State.   On 22nd  September the Foreign Office informed the Danish Charge d&apos;Affairesthat  export licences to the Scandinavian  countries  and Holland were  now beingtemporarily suspended in conformity with the embargo placed upon  exports by theAllies of Great Britain.  As a result of the visit to London of M. met in,  the FrenchUnder Secretary for Blockade, the United States Government has been  informed  thatGreat Britain and France are anxious to co-operate as  closely as possible with theUnited States in  order  to obtain,  from neutral States  contiguous with Germany the cessation  of  essential  exports to the enemy.   Further, France  has agreed  to theestablishment of an inter-Allied Board for the joint  administration of the blockade,to have its seat in London, and both Great Britain and France have approached theUnited States Government suggesting that an American delegate should, be appointedto join the  Board  as  a  channel  for communications  with  the Exports Board  in washington.                                   .       -   Mr. Lyle, in reply to the proposal that Siam, by putting an embargo on the exportof rice, should co-operate in the application of economic  pressure to the ScandinavianStates and Holland, states  that  the Siamese Government cannot do this  withoutviolating Treaty rights and  thereby rendering the country liable for damages under adecision of the Court of Arbitration at The Hague.                                   FRANCE.   The new  French War  Committee has followed the British example, not  only inits general composition, but also  in the  creation of  a secretarial staff, charged withthe  summoning of its  meetings, the preparation of agenda  and  minutes, and the
                                         ttransmission of  its decisions  to  the  departments  affected.  The  new  &quot; chef desecretariat&quot;  is  M.  Helbronner.   The  War Committee,  however,  differs  from  theBritish War  Cabinet in this respect, that the final responsibility is  still vested inthe larger Cabinet.   The vote of confidence in the new Administration was actually unopposed  in theChamber, but there were some 170 abstentions which  may or may not be reckonedagainst the 368 Deputies who voted.  M. Renaudel, who  maintains  that the questionof desertion in the face of the enemy is a matter solely of individual opinion,-criticisedthe War Committee as being composed  of men who were too old, and gave reasons why the Socialists had for the most part abstained from joining the new Administration-Lord Bertie understands, however, that a large section of  the  Socialist  Party is likelyto vote for the Government in future, and that  one or more Socialists will shortly betaken into the Ministry.   Speaking on 23rd September before the Socialist Federation of the Seine, which ispreparatory for the National  Socialist Congress, to be held at  Bordeaux in  the  second week of October, M. Thomas expressed himself in favour  of participation  in  theMinistry,  subject to the conditions laid down  by the Socialist  Party during the recent-crisis,   and  M. Longuet  advocated  the  voting  of  Government  credits  until  theGovernment  should have refused  a possible peace, a question  which had not yetarisen.   Lord  Bertie  telegraphs  that.after  an attempt  to  rush  a  surprise  election ofM. Caillaux to the Budget Commission  had failed, M. Lebrun, a former Minister forthe  Colonies  and  of  War,  who belongs  to  the Democratic  Left, was elected in succession to M. Klotz, the Minister of Finance in  the new Cabinet.   M.  Caillaux in a letter  to a  provincial  newspaper  asserts  that  he  subsidised&quot; Le Bonnet Rouge &quot; between March and July 1914 solely in  order to have  a  vehiclefor his replies to the attacks of  the Paris evening Press,  which was at the time almostunited in vehemently assailing him.  Meanwhile two former  members  of the  staff of&quot; Le Bonnet Rouge &quot; have been  arrested on  the  charge of  having intercourse withthe enemy.                                    ITALY.   In  a letter to Lord Hardinge Sir R. Rodd relates  that  the Minister of Agriculture,in view of  the  unsatisfactory  grain outlook  and the complaints as to the neglect ofItaly by Great Britain in favour of France, has expressed the opinion  that the battlein Italy itself, with all the elements of opposition,  will be as severe during the winteras the battle wdth the enemy on the front.   The British Government have made arrangements whereby the average of coal sup-plied to Italy for August and September will amount to 600,000 tons apart from shipments from America.  - The Foreign Office points out that it is  only by putting traffic throughthe  Mediterranean that the requisite supply of tonnage for Italian  requirements canbe secured, and  to ensure the safety of this  route  the  Italians  must  furnish elevendestroyers to form part  of the anti-submarine patrol under  the Commander-in-Chiefof the Mediterranean.   Mr. Erskine, now acting as British Charge d&apos;Affaires in Romeduring the  AmbassadoFs absence  at home, understands, however, that this demand will  be opposed by  the Italian  naval authorities,  who  fear that the  detachment ofsuch craft,  which must come from the Northern Adriatic, would  unduly  exposeVenice.                                    ALBANIA.    The Italian Government lias  intimated to the Foreign Office that there was reasonto believe  that  the French and  Greeks were anxious to  instal Essad  Pasha asGovernor of Koritza, and  that  such an  appointment would be greatly resented by italy.                                    GREECE.    The executive control of the Hellenic  Fleet,  under  the  Minister  of Alarine, hasbeen secured to the Rear-Admiral in command of  the British Mission for the trainingof the  Greek Navy in.  virtue of understandings arrived at between M.  Venizelos,the  Minister of Marine and Captain Clifton Brown.     The French Vice-Admiral at  Salamis, who has expressed,  the opinion that the British Naval Mission should not be allowed  to oust the  French  from  the  control  of
sthe Greek Meet find from  the Arsenal at Salamis, which he  needed for  the french fleet, has asked the  Greek Minister  of Marine to sign a new agreement, with theFrench on the subject of this Arsenal.   According to this the Arsenal is  to be at thedisposal  of  the French and  to be  used for the repair  of French and Greek ships,while Greece is to control the police of the Arsenal and pay the  staff, all tugs andlighters,  and all repairs are to he under the  French who will decide what repairs areto be  done  to  Greek  ships.  A  mixed Franco-Greek Commission is  to  decide whatpurchases of material  are  necessary.  What  the  Greeks cannot buy locally must beprovided by the French who have the right to requisition local supplies.    The Hellenic Minister of  Marine has agreed not to sign, this agreement (which  isprejudicial  to  the position of  the British  Naval  Mission)  for  the moment,  andMr. Crackanthorpe hopes that the Foreign Office will notify the French Governmentof the fact that the British Naval Mission has been accepted by Greece and the termsof the  contract already settled.    The British Consul at Janina, telegraphing on 17th September, reported that some-200 persons declared for  local autonomy  in the Kutzovlach centre of Samarina,and that Greek gendarmes avIio were attacked  by the Ivutzovlachs of one  of the neighbouring villages,  had to be rescued by Italians.  Greek troops have been sent up, and  the agitation,  which was apparently short lived, is ascribed  to  the  effect  ofthe propaganda maintained by the Italian Consul-General in Janina.    The same Officer refers to the creation of Italian  Vice-Consulates in NorthernEpirus (vide Report No. 3d, page 7), as being, expressly destined to protect persons and communities wdio  sympathised  with  the  Italian occupation  and  are  nowexposed  to Greek  reprisals.  They  will be manned by agents of the Military PoliticalDepartment, wdiich aims at  fostering ignorance and weakness. in Greece with  a viewto Italian expansion.    The Greek Government, however, are not disposed to acquiesce in this manifesta-tion of Italian policy and before the evacuation of Janina  by the Italians, the  OfficerCommanding  the Greek troops  in Epirus intimated that he  would be unable  torecognise the new  Italian Consular officers in that district, in  that  as  they are reallymilitary  officers, their  presence is  for that reason  incompatible  with  the  existing arrangements for an evacuation by Italian troops.    Meanwhile, the Italians insist on maintaining their occupation of Konitaa and the villages  of Molitsa and  Kastanieh to the north of  it so long  as  there  are Frenchofficers in  the  Sarandaporos valley, as well as on the  retention of certain  militaryposts above the Santi Quaranta road.  Mr. Crackanthorpe has been informed  thatGreece is prepared to accept the latter contention, subject to the condition that it doesnot interfere with  the proper exercise of Greek civil authority.   The occupation of Janina by Greek troops took place on 22nd September, and thatof Philiates on  loth  September, when the Italian and Greek flags.were mutuallysalutaci and an appearance  of perfect goodwill maintained, both  at that ceremony a-ndat the subsequent reception  given by  the  outgoing Italian military authorities  whowithdrew next morning.    The British Government have  informed  Washington that, in view of  tonnagedifficulties and the unsafety of  the  Mediterranean route,- it is  preferable  that  Greeceshould be  provisioned from the East, and have  suggested  that  trade  between  theUnited States  might wdth  advantage be discouraged  by the withholding  of  export licences.  The  American Minister  in Athens  is, however, unlikely to support these representations, as Mr.  Crackanthorpe understands that it is  probably due  to  his-suggestion that the  Hellenic  Government  recently proposed  the abolition  of thenavicert  system.   Mr.  Crackanthorpe  urges the  importance of  the retention  of thissystem as without it, or some equivalent procedure  on the part  of  the United States,the whole control of Greek  imports  under the present rationing system will collapse.    ddie Foreign Office advises Mr.  Erskine  that  the Wheat Executive has agreed toassume the  responsibility  of  supplying Greece with  the  necessary grain, as it isconsidered  that  any   failure of  supplies might lead to an  irresistible  demand  fortonnage possibly at a more inconvenient moment.    Mr. Crackanthorpe announces  that a  daily import  of  1,025  tons of sugar intoGreece will be required for rationing purposes on the basis worked out by the AdliedHoard at the Piraeus,  but  this will only be  necessary  after December, - until when800 tons daily will supplement local resources.  The question of rationing food and fuel is-becoming so important that  M. Venizelos has temporarily left  the Ministry ofWar in order to supervise the Ministry of Supplies.
                                    SERBIA.   The British Government have  invited the  united  States to assume the expense-and responsibility o  sending Yugo-Slav volunteers for the Serbian Army to Salonika,while Great Britain and France will arrange for the transport of such volunteers fromthe rest  of. the  Avorlcl.   This  arrangement supersedes  the  proposals for sendingYugo-Slavs who volunteered in the United States to Canada in the first place, whichwere under consideration  while the United States were still neutral.   Sir C.  Spring Rice, however, points out that the United States are not at warwith  Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria, or Turkey,  and can  hardly  take active  steps tofacilitate the formation of an army destined to  fight against these countries.   Sir C. des Graz learns that certain Serbian deserters now under Austrian influencehave evolved the idea  of  a  Yugo-Slav Republican Federation.   They  are  said to bein contact with Bulgarian revolutionaries in Switzerland.   On the other hand, the Serbian Minister in London  has been informed  that the jugo - Slav  Socialist  delegates  sent to Stockholm by  permission  of the austrian government, have declined to return to Austria, and have asked for assistance to-enable them to come to England.                              GERMAN AFFAIRS.    The launching of the Seventh German War Loan has been heralded by patrioticannouncements signed by the Prussian and Bavarian  Crown Princes which appeared in &quot; Der Tag &quot; of 21st September.    The  Intelligence  Bureaids Weekly Report for  19th September states  that the economic situation in Germany, apart from the sufferings of the masses from scarcityand bad  quality of food and  from  clothing  difficulties, and apart from the terribly adverse foreign  exchange rates, appears  to be not unsatisfactory.   The subscriptionfor the  new  loan, which is the seventh,  was  opened on  Monday, 17th  September, and will close on or about .19th October.   There is plenty of money available for the subscription.  Enormous fortunes have been, made by Government contractors.  The commercial classes have not been able to  spend  in the lavish  way that was customary before the war.   Agriculture has been payiug well.  Capital  has been accumulating and is so plentiful that the banks are paying only some 2 per  cent, on deposits.  The new  5 per  cent, loan the seventh-is  being  issued  at  98.   The  Government  is making it more popular by an  express  declaration to the effect  that it will never reduce the interest without simultaneously offering to redeem the loan at par.  A new series of Exchequer 4-,- per cent,  bonds is being issued at the  same  time as the new loan, also at 9S.  These  bonds are redeemable after 60  years, but the chance of  a.good premium  is held out by drawings at stated intervals, the bonds so drawn being redeemed at  115.    At a. meeting in Berlin  of the German. Patriotic Party (vide Report No. 34, page 8) Grand Admiral von Tirpitz,  in  discussing the  Belgian question, stated that a really neutral Belgium had  never existed.   Belgium had always been  the bridgehead of England, and that Germans  must  therefore wish that  in  future  Germany  and not England  should be  the protecting power of  Belgium, as on that point turned the question of German economic and military existence.    Sir  W.  Townley  reports that the career  of  Dr. Michaelis as  Chancellor  is, according to opinions expressed to a neutral by members of  the  German Legation -at The Hague,  unlikely to be prolonged until Christmas.  Von Payer, the Radical Leader, is suggested as his successor.    The  &quot; Germania,&quot; which was  subsequently suppressed for another  indiscretion, -on  19th  September protested vigorously against  the  Pan-German agitation, saying that a  bottomless pit  which cannot be bridged separates the views of these people from. its own, as indeed from those of the Imperial Government as  well.                                    AUSTRIA.     According to a  Press report the  Hungarian Minister of Finance estimates the expenditure for this year at three milliards of kroner (approximately 126,000,000 .  at. normal rates of exchange) and hopes to meet the increase of 260,000,000 kroner  (10,900,000L) on last year by  new taxes on income,  oil,  petrol, war profits and -commercial combinations.      3897-4                            C
   The new session  of the  Hungarian  Parliament has opened, and it will now he-seen whether the new Prime  Minister, Dr.  Wekerle, was in  earnest  about hisdeclaration in favour of electoral reform.                               NETHERLANDS.   Sir W. Townley conveyed the  British offer of  100,000 tons of  coal to the  Dutch-Government just before  the meeting of the Conference which was  considering  theGerman  coal proposals.   As a result  the  pro-German elements in the Conferencesuffered  defeat  and  it  was  decided  that&apos; the  Netherlands Government  should immediately requisition tonnage  to bring the coal&apos;   It  is understood that the coalwill  be consigned directly to the Government Coal Distribution  Office  and will beinsured and transported by the Dutch Government.  Some  25,000  tons  of  shipping-have been commandeered for the  purpose, and the Foreign Office has agreed to allowBlack  List ships,  to  be used for these shipments  under  certain conditions.  The-prices  quoted for the coal to he supplied to  the Netherlands Government, f.o.b., vary from 23s. to 28s. Gd. per  ton according to quality.   This will do much to  counteract the German pressure which has been brought tobear upon the Netherlands.  Sir W. Townley considers that the question of the coalsupply is the chief form of this pressure, and is further of opinion that the pressure ismore a manifestation of economic necessity and commercial foresight rather than  dueto some new and obscure political scheme.  At present no German coal  is available,.and the Germans have fixed an absurd cash price  for purposes of negotiation only,.hoping thereby to frighten the Dutch to agree to pay a lower price partly in cash  andpartly  in credits.   The British Minister  has, however, reminded the Dutch unofficiallythat  they have themselves decided that to  grant credits to  one  belligerent  only isunneutral, and consequently that if credits be granted by Holland to Germany  similaraccommodation will be looked for  by Great Britain.   The Foreign Office is anxious to reduce Dutch exports  to Germany as  far aspossible, and  to that end  the German pressure which  is exerted in the opposite direction must be  combated,  but while the progress  of our negotiations has beenhelped by  the grant  of  coal to  the Dutch it is still hindered by  the  difficulty of inducing Holland to permit the transit of foodstuffs for Belgium relief while she is her-self prevented from importing similar supplies for her own population from overseas.                                SWITZERLAND.   Representations have had to be made again  to  the  swiss Government, protesting against the partiality  shown  by Switzerland  towards the  Central  Empires  in  thesupply of munitions, and the Foreign Office has directed  Sir  H. Rumbold to indicate-to the Swiss what wdll  be  the consequences unless evidence be forthcoming  that this attitude has been abandoned.   The ^Swiss Government  have protested  strongly against that suspension of  the transit  of  goods  for Switzerland from Netherlands  through Germany which was brought  about by the  seizure of cocoa en route through  Germany, referred to in report No. 33, page 12.   In  view of the  difficulty of securing an adequate supply of oil-cake for Swissrequirements in the United  States, Sir  H. Rumbold has been instructed to find  otitwhether the large quantities of cotton-seed cahe which are available in  Egypt,.possibly as much as  20,000  tons, would meet the needs of Switzerland.                                   SWEDEN.   Sir C. Spring Rice reports that the Swedish Charge d&apos;Affaires in Washington  hascomplained to the United States Government of the seizure by the British  authorities at Halifax of four diplomatic bags addressed to  the Swedish  Legation, and that  theSecretary of State hopes that the bags will not  be retained in view of the effect ofsuch action on the result of the elections in Sweden.  The Foreign Office, however,has been led to believe&apos; that one of the bags  has been  tampered with  en  route, andmaintains that diplomatic  immunities  cannot be considered to  cover such a case-Should delay be inconvenient, it  is proposed that the  bags should be forwarded to-
Washington under guard, and there opened in the presence of  a member  of  theSwedish Legation and of British and American officials.   The United States Government, which is anxious as to the attitude  of Sweden,and wishes to avoid any incident which might arouse Swedish national spirit  against.the Allies during the elections, have asked that the  bags should be allowed to proceedwith their bearers to New York,  and that they  shotdd  there  be lauded  withoutexamination,  provided that the bearers give  their  word of honour that  nothing is contained, in the  bags contrary to strict neutrality.   As, however, on  a previous.instance in which Diplomatic bags, when opened in the presence of an official  of  theSwedish Legation to which  they were consigned, were found  to contain u.uneutralmatter, the  &quot;Foreign. Office  insists  upon the necessity  for  opening the  bags  in  themanner previously suggested.   In  view of -the attitude of the  Swedish Government, which may either stop  theexport of iron ore to the Allies and divert  the  present Allied share  to Germany, orstop  the transit of Allied  goods to Russia, Sir E. Howard suggests that  it would  beimpolitic to press for the total prohibition of the export of  iron ore and other metalsto Germany.   He would prefer  to negotiate  with a view to  the reduction  of  the exports to Germany in order that the balance may  come to the Allies, on the  groundthat  a  total prohibition of export to Germany on the part of  Sweden would  beconstrued as an unrieutral act.   Sir E. Howard has been informed that the  Foreign  Office is unwilling to agree tothe release for  Sweden  of goods  stored  in  other parts  of  Scandinavia,  chieflybecause the United  States  are negotiating  for  full and free transit through sweden to Russia,  and the acceptance by  Great Britain  of such temporary  arrangements might  weaken their position.  At the same time, the Foreign Office  points out thatthe Russian Government object to the release of portions of transit goods for  sale in sweden, which, moreover, affords an opportunity for illegitimate profiteering.   Sir E. Howard understands that the Swiss Consul in Stockholm  has  obtained a russian licence to import into Sweden 30,000  tons of oil-cake  and 10,000 casks oflinseed oil from Russia, and that the First  Secretary of  the  Russian  Legation in stockholm is the prime mover in this matter.    Further, the Minister has information that  quantities of oil-cake are being smuggled into  Sweden  from Finland ports.   In an election speech  delivered on  18th September, Mr.  Trygger,  leader  of:  the conservatives in the Swedish Upper House, declared that the Swedish, love of  justice and honour, as well as  Swedish interests,  which demand neutrality,  would  preventSweden from associating herself with those  who sought to crush  the great culture-bearing German nation.   The final results  of the Swedish elections show  that the new Lower House, whichis to meet on 15th January 1918, is composed as follows :          Brantingite Socialists      -      -       -   86, a gain of 14 seats.         Socialists of the Left   -                     .12,  a loss of 2 seats.         Liberals    -      -      -      -       -   62, a gain of 5 seats.         Conservatives         -        -         -   58, a loss of 28 seats.         National Association       -      -           3         Peasants&apos; Association  -        -         -    9   The United States Minister in Stockholm learns that opinion is growing in favourof the formation  of  a  new Administration from among the Parties of the  Left inview of the results of the election.  Efforts are being made to persuade the King inthis  direction, in  opposition to the influence  of the Queen who  desires  the retentionof the  present Ministry.   The French  Minister, after a  conversation with the Ministerfor Foreign Affairs, is  inclined to  the opinion  that the  present Cabinet will hold office at least until the opening of Parliament.   Sir E. Howard deprecates the action  proposed to his Government by the italian minister in  Stockholm and  tentatively  approved  by the Russian Government inaccordance with which a joint Allied protest is to be delivered to Sweden  against  theunneutral acts of its officials, in order to prevent the King of Sweden from appointinganother  pro-German Ministry after the  elections.  The United  States Minister hasassociated  himself with his British colleague in this  objection, considering that  thecourse proposed would  excite resentment in Sweden.   The French Minister  has  advised  his Government in  a  similar  sense and  is ofopinion that the best way of bringing these matters to the knowledge of the Swedish
public is by means of a question and answer in one of the Allied Parliaments.  Onthis, Sir E. Howard&apos;s comment is that it would be better not to use  the  British.Parliament for this purpose.                                  NORWAY.   Sir C. Spring Rice states that owing to a shortage of flour in New York the United&quot;States authorities  have taken  over  S,000  tons of flour of  the  stock of  18,000 tonsbought there by Norway, and that  part of the price is the release for shipment of theremainder.  This action is understood to be exceptional.  It is, however, according toSir M.  Findlay,  being  trumpeted  in  Norway  as  a  diplomatic victory,  and &quot;has apparently prompted the G-overnment to take steps to increase  the native productionof copper a commodity at present imported from Great Britain in order,  as the british minister believes,  to  prepare for  as  long  a resistance as possible  to  any pressure which Great Britain  may  bring  to  stop   all   Norwegian   exports  to Germany(vide Report No. 33, page 13).   Sir M. Findlay again  emphasises the disastrous effect of a policy of  making smallconcessions upon our  prospects of striking a heavy economic blow at Germany, but inspite  of this it  appears that a  Norwegian  merchant,  having bought a   further18,000 tons of flour in New York has received an export licence for 9,000 tons fromthe United States Government in  return for the sale of the remainder to the BelgianRelief Organisation.  In view of  this  the Foreign Office  urges Sir C. Spring Riceto impress  upon the  authorities in Washington the exceedingly difficult  position inwhich the British  Government have now been  placed  owing to the  action of theUnited States in  allowing Norway to obtain a six months&apos; supply of grain  in  spiteof the embargo and the measures taken by  the Allies to conform with it.                                  DENMARK.   His Majesty&apos;s Government have  apologised  for the violation of Danish neutralityand offered reparation for any damage  Avhich may have been  caused  to Denmark byBritish naval forces off the coast of Jutland on 1st September.   Sir G. Spring Rice reports that the United  States  Export Board,  in the matter ofbacon, fish, and mineral oil (vide Report, No. 34,  page 11), considers that the best policyis to maintain the embargo and refuse petroleum.  The bacon question will settle itselfshortly, and  it is better  that Denmark  should confine  her energies to  being self-supporting rather than build up a food reserve  which might at any moment be seizedTry Germany.  The shortage of mineral oil for home consumption in the United states is a plausible excuse for refusing export permits, while  the control of  coal by theAllies will prevent the Danes  from drawing other  supplies  from the Argentine or elsewhere.   Mr. Gurney  notes the reduction of the Danish  stock  of  pigs and suggests thatthe bacou  if not wanted in the United Kingdom might be diverted to Norway in orderto decrease the amount available  for Germany.   Sir  M. Findlay, however, states thatthe Danes are asking for compensation, failing which they threaten to stop the exportof pork to Norway, although it is being sold freely to Sweden without compensation.Mr.  Gurney understands that the Danes  dare not entirely close down the  export ofbacon to Germany so long as any may be going to Great Britain.    In connection with the proposals now- under discussion that American oil shouldbe supplied in return for a limitation of fish export to 25,000 tons per annum, theForeign Office draws  the attention of Washington  to the apparent probability thatGermany  will be able to  supply mineral  oil  to the  Danish Fishing  Fleet whereby  a supply of  at least 100,000 tons of fish per annum would be secured for Germany.    Mr. Gurney  hopes that  the export of nitrates from Norway to Denmark may be stopped unless   the supply to Germany  be  reduced by a corresponding  amount or special concessions obtained from the Danes in return.    A Danish newspaper published a  tendencious  article  in connection with amespionage trial   in Germany in  which thinly  veiled accusations are made against certain  British   officials  in Denmark.  Mr. Gurney, considering the article  to beinspired by Germans as a set-off against the American disclosures,  has protested tothe  Minister  for Foreign Affairs against the  publication of  such articles, and  was assured that the Minister considered that  it was incorrect that attacks should be made
on members of foreign missions.  The Minister for Foreign  Affairs  also promised to approach the editor of the &quot; Politiken &quot; with a vdew to the prevention of the recurrence of such incidents.                                    SPAIN.   The Foreign Office has asked for assurances that the German submarine at Cadiz(vide Report No. 33, page 13) shall be kept interned, and has invited the co-operationof France in this matter.   The Spanish Government have intimated their readiness to accept unlimited supplyof British coal which  is to be fetched  in Spanish  bottoms  in return for unrestrictedfacilities for the export of iron ore, pyrites;  lead, and  other minerals from Spain to-Great Britain.   The British Government, while prepared to  give hunker facilities to spanish shipping outside Spain as  before, insist  upon the  export of coal from Spainbeing prohibited by the Spanish Government.  In view of the possibility of a changeof Cabinet in  Spain the Foreign Office  proposes  to conclude an agreement on theselines as soon as one or two minor points have been settled.   Sir C. Spring Rice considers that it  is  unlikely that the Spanish Government willbe able to obtain any coal from the United States  owing to the acute existing shortage in that country.   The British Consul in Bilbao reports that local bankers consider that if the exportof gold  from the United States to Spain be prohibited  the exchange will fall to10 pesetas.   According to Press reports the prohibition  came into force on  24thSeptember when the Spanish exchange against sterling was 20&apos;50 to 11.                                 PORTUGAL.   Field Marshal Sir D. Haig has intimated that the proposed visit of the President ofthe Portuguese Republic to the West Front would most  conveniently be timed  if itwere to take place on or about 8th  October or 15th October.                                     SIAM.   In view of the fact that  the British Charge d&apos;Affaires has applied to the indian government to secure accommodation for the 296  alien enemies at present internedin Siam and to the Admiral at Singapore for the  necessary-transport,  the SiameseGovernment have asked to be supplied with a precedent for such a transfer.                                 ARGENTINA.   On 19th September the Senate of the Argentine Republic passed  a Resolution  infavour of the suspension of diplomatic  relations wdth  Genuany by  23 votes to one,but Sir R. lower reports that the Chamber of Deputies adjourned on 22nd Septemberon learning of the official disavowal by Germany of Count Luxburg&apos;s acts.   Sir R. Tower, on 24th September, was told by two Argentine Ministers of Statethat the President of the Republic would be unable  to refuse to declare  war upon germany if the country were to insist on such a course, as he could not, steer a coursebetween neutrality and Avar.   Count Luxburg now wdshes to leave Buenos Aires  by a  Spanish  steamer leavingon 2nd October,  and has requested the Argentine  Minister  for Foreign  Affairs  toobtain a  safe  conduct  for  him.   The  Foreign Office,  however,  has  instructedSir R. lower to explain that  a  safe conduct will only be granted  for an unbrokenvoyage direct to a neutral country contiguous with Germany.   Pending more satisfactory arrangements which are  now  under&apos; discussion  with.various British authorities,  the United States Exports  Board is unlikely to grantlicences or bunkers to neutral ships bound for the  Plate, unless they undertake  toreturn thence in cargo for the United  States,  but  will permit the  export of bindertwine, which is needed for sacking the Argentine grain crop.    3897-4                              D
   H.M.S. &quot; Glasgow &quot; arrived off Buenos Aires on  20th September.  The Captainwas received by the President of the Argentine Republic, and  official  entertainmentswere given in honour of the visit, which was also well received by the public.  After a highly successful visit, P1.M. Ship left on 25th September.                                   MEXICO.   Mr. Cummins understands that General Carranza is now in communication withPelaez (vide Report No. 34, page 12).  A Rebel Conference has been  held where therepresentatives  of  several factions  are  believed,  to  have plotted concerted actionagainst General Carranza.                                    PERU.   Air. Rennie learns that the Peruvian Minister in Berlin has advised his Governmentthat the German Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs appears well disposed over the&quot; Lofton &quot; case, and  has promised preferential attention  to the Peruvian repre-sentatious..  The British  Minister has also noticed  that  public opinion is becomingless interested in the affair.                                    CUBA.   The Foreign  Office has informed Mr. Leech that for the present no more colouredBritish subjects will&apos; be required as recruits for service in the West India Regimentin France.                                COSTA  RICA.   Sir C. Mallet announces from Panama that the Republic of Costa Rica has broken off relations  with Germany, and that the German Charge dAffaires in San Jose,  whohad been suspected of plotting to foment internal trouble, has  now applied for hispassports and a safe conduct to Berlin for himself, his family and his staff.                                  URUGUAY.   Air. Mitchell Lines reports  that  a  popular demonstration of sympathy with theArgentine Republic and the Allies took place  on 19th  September,  and urges that asthe moment for a rupture between Uruguay and Germany is now favourable a decisionto accept the Arbitration Treaty should be no  longer postponed, the more so as  theMinister for Foreign Affairs has again pressed for a decision.                              UNITED  STATES.   Lord Reading, who was  received  by the  President  of the United States on21st September, has  arranged  to visit Canada on  the invitation of His Grace theGovernor-General with Lady Reading and Lord Northcliffe, and will  be at Ottawa onOctober 4th, 5th and 6th.   Lord Reading reports that President Wilson was inclined to agree to the proposals put forward by his Lordship on behalf of  the War Cabinet, that United States  troops should be sent to France as quickly as possible, and  should  take their -place on some part of  the line as and when ready without waiting for the completion of  the Army totake over a portion of the Front.  Lord Reading explained that  French moral neededencouragement and there would be disappointment  in France if no  active american co-operation were to  be looked for from American troops before next spring.   The President was eager for details about  the present developments of submarine warfare, and Lord Reading, who offered to supply any required  particulars, is  con-vineed that as everything depends upon  the  President, it is of the  first importance that he should be kept as fully informed as possible, and that he  should  be satisfiedthat nothing is being withheld from him by the British Government.
   Lord Reading assured the President that the War Cabinet  was anxious  to  co-operate closely and wholeheartedly with the United States and, with that end in view,to supply every information.   The President entertained fears that American  repre-sentatives on British or Allied Boards might  lose their independent judgment,  as hadalready happened in some cases.  The conversation is to be resumed later.   Sir W. Wiseman, telegraphing from. New York on  21st September, considers thatthe  situation had improved  during  the  last two  months.    Mr.  McAdoo is moreinclined to be helpful as he now realises his responsibility  were Allied finance tocollapse owing  to  niggardliness on his part.   The  action  of  Lord Reading,  whois a  persona  grata   with  all the   administration,  has   helped to  bring  this about.  There is as yet  little  public  enthusiasm for  the war, but the British  are becoming less unpopular while the Government is growing impatient with the French.The President has confidential information about the depression of French moral andis prepared to do anything in reason to remedy this, such as the sending up of  UnitedStates troops into the fighting line earlier than would otherwise have been done.   It  may be possible  to persuade  the President to  send either Colonel  House or mr.  Baker, the Secretary  for War, to  Europe to confer with the military authoritiesin London and Paris.   Sir C. Spring Rice reports that the American Press is not much interested  in the invitation sent to members of both Hoitses of Congress by the Lord High chancellor and  the Speaker of the Plouse of Commons to visit Great Britain and the British front(vide Report No. 33, page 21), and it appears that the invitation was issued prematurelyowing  to a  misunderstanding.  The  President, however,  seems to have formed theopinion that  the British  invitation to Members of both Houses of Congress, to  visitLondon and the British sectors of  the West Front was in some  way connected withthe proposals put forward by M. Franklin-Bouillon suggesting American co-operationwith the Inter-Allied  Parliament.  In any case,  according to the &quot;Times,&quot;  theForeign Relations  Committee, after consultation with the President, has decided to decline both invitations.    The proposed Convention  between  Great Britain and  the  United  States  on thesubject of compulsory  military service  for  British subjects  in  that country  enableseither party to call up  for service  its  nationals  resident within  the territory of theother.  Both parties will assist in  this  operation and give facilities for  transport.Those who do not return  to  theii&apos; respective countries, either freely or  under  arrest,will become liable for service  in the  country of their  residence, provided that they be not exempted upon the formal request of their  Diplomatic  Representative.   the oath to be taken by any person entering the  military service of a  foreign country willnot  be considered as an oath of allegiance involving his expatriation under the  laws ofhis own country.  Deserters will be  arrested and returned  to their own Armies.                            SHIPPING  SITUATION.   According to the War Trade Intelligence  Report, the total  tonnage of 500  tonsgross in the case of steamers and 100 tons gross in the case of sailing ships, reportediost owing to  the malice  of  the K ing&apos;s enemies during  the  period  14th September -20th  September  inclusive, is 81,914  tons, of  which 56,628 tons  were British, ascompared with  70,027 tons of which 37,128  tons were  British, reported  last week.The German wireless announces an  enemy claim to  have destroyed  808,000 tons ofmerchant shipping during  August.   This appears  to  be an exaggeration of some51 per  cent.,-the actual  figures, according to the War  Trade  Intelligence Reports,for the  first 30 days of August and  the last  five days of July  (five  weekly returns)being 542,140 tons.   Sir  C. Spring Rice  has been informed  by the Foreign Office  that  15 ships,averaging 9,000 tons gross, are being built in  Japan  for the British Government.   The Portuguese Government are willing to employ four of their  ex-German ships in trade between British, French and Portuguese ports, and Sir L. Carnegie has been instructed to press them  to do so without  delay.   In the matter of the ex-enemy ships in China the  British Government now proposethat if  Japan will agree to employ  her share of the nine ex-enemy ships in Siam,which have now been condemned by the Prize Court and are under repair, on warwork, they will  no longer press for such employment for  the Japanese share  of theships in China.     3897-4                            E
                            PEACE  DISCUSSIONS,   According to the German Press, the German  and Austrian  replies to  the  PapalPeace  Note were  handed to the Nuncios  at  Munich  and Vienna respectively,  on20th  September, but at noon  on 22nd September  the  Cardinal  Secretary of Stateinformed Count do Salis that he had received neither reply,  and on  23rd september the Vatican semi-official journal, while publishing texts of the replies furnished by anews agency, stated that no official communication had then been  received by the holy See.   ddie German reply refers to the prolonged efforts of the German Emperor towardsaverting the present war, and welcomes with  special  sympathy the suggestion  putforward by His Holiness that in future the material power of arms must be superseded the moral power of Right.  It accepts  in  consequence the theory  of regulatedsimultaneous  disarmament  by sea,  land and  air,  and  of  compulsory arbitration.The  Austrian reply supports  the Papal proposals  for a limitation  of  armamentsunder  appropriate guarantees,  for the liberation of the  high  seas from domination orparamountcy, and for compulsory arbitration in  international disputes.   Part of the German Press praises  the  replies as  contrasted with the violence of president Wilson&apos;s &quot; tirade,&quot; and finds that  they are in  harmony  with the wishes ofthe Pope and.  the  Reichstag peace resolution.   Other  sections, on the other  hand,deplore the wording of the later paragraphs which tend to convey an impression thatGermany finds herself in so unfavourable a  position  that she sees in peace the only possible solution of her difficulties.   The &quot;Vorwarts&quot; of  19th  September foresees an  officially engineered publicity campaign,  of  wdiich the Chancellor is supposed to  be  ignorant,  directed against a&quot;lukewarm  peace&quot; and  against the  attachment  of  importance  to  Parliamentaryresolutions ;  on the other hand,  the &quot; Tageszeitung&quot;  considers that the Erzbergeragitation which culminated in his  speech at Biberach. has borne fruit in the speech of dr. Pieper, who denies that  Germany has any  interest  in the  destruction of Britishtonnage, or in the national bankruptcy of Russia or France, and the Austrian Govern-ment is understood to have instructed their Minister in The Hague to emphasise their desire for peace in any conversations  he may have.   Sir W. Townley has private information to the effect that Herr Dernburgon behalfof the Majority group in  the  Reichstag  has asked Mr. Heemskerk, a former  DutchPrime Minister,  to address members of  that group  on the  subject  of  Belgium,as the German official reply to the Pope is considered non-committal and unsatisfactory,and  as a  final fight has now  become  necessary in the Reichstag.   According to alater telegram Mr. Heemskerk has already left for Berlin on this mission.  The british minister believes that he  will urge  the  unconditional  evacuation and restoration ofBelgium on the grounds  that  no  conditional German  offer  concerning that countrywdll be  entertained by the Allies, and that Belgium  cannot be made  an object o barter.                             .   *   The British proposals for the allocation of the ex-enemy ships in  China have nowbeen made in detail:       To the United States       -   2 ships of a total of 11,200  tons.      To Japan         -         -   0 ships of a total of 11,661  tons.      To Great Britain    -       -   6 ships of a total of 12,037  tons.      To China         -         -   2 ships suitable only for river work.   The British share would be handed over to the Inter-Allied Chartering executive to be chartered equally between Great Britain, France and Italy.   The Uruguayan Government, provided that they be relieved of any financial  obli-gation which might cause them to become liable for heavy compensation  in the eventof loss of the ex-enemy ships in  Montevideo,  are prepared  to use  them for trade to europe.  Otherwise they  will be  employed between American ports.   The question of obtaining leave from the Swedish Government for the free use ofthe Rogrund Channel for the passage of eight Russian ships of some  2,000 tons apieceand over, now in  Russian waters, depends  upon the result of the Swedish elections,and  His Majesty&apos;s Government are unwilling to  press  the  Russians to release themunless the Kogrund passage is free.
    The attention of Sir F. Villiers has been  drawn,  by the Belgian Under Secretaryof State for.Foreign Affairs to the communication forwarded  by the French Govern-ment with reference to the special  peace  terms which the  Germans propose  tooffer to Belgium through  the  Vatican as a sequel to their reply  to the Papal  Note.These  terms  have  been detailed  by Herr von Kuhlmann. in  conversation with  thePapal Nuncio in Munich and provide for the restoration and independence of Belgium.Germany would pay a share of the compensation due for war-damages, but  Belgiummust guarantee that  Germany be  never again menaced as in  1914.   Germany mustenjoy the right freely to develop her commercial  enterprises in. Belgium, particularly at Antwerp, and the administrative division of the country into Flanders and Walloniamust be maintained as Germany wishes it for reasons of racial sympathy.   The Japanese  Government, fully sharing the views of the British  Governmentwith regard to  the Papal Note of 1st August, have requested. Great Britain to acknow-ledge the receipt of that Note on their  behalf  to the Holy See, to which no Japaneserepresentative is accredited.   Lord Bertie in a despatch to the Foreign Office reports that French public opinionstill  hopes to  obtain the French desiderata in the question of peace, which areenumerated  below, but considers  that  so soon as the British offensive be brought toan end for the winter a  great deal of French front should be taken over by the Britishso as to let the  French troops rest, and thereby enable the French Army to hold onuntil the arrival of the Americans.  In spite of disappointment, France is staunch  in her belief in  ultimate  victory and, relying on the assistance of Great Britain  and theUnited States, is prepared  to  face another  winter of war, but if  there  are  signs  of weakening on  the  part of Great  Britain  we  must not be  surprised  if these are reproduced in France. .   The French desiderata  in the question of peace :--      (a) Evacuation  and rehabilitation  by Germany of  the occupied, parts of France             and Belgium,  with guarantees against further aggression.     (b) The recovery of Alsace-Lorraine.     (c) A slight rectification  in favour of France  of the frontier of Luxemburg, the             rest of which should be ceded to Belgium.     (cZ) The cession to France of the valley of the Saar, Le., the frontier of 1814.      le) The payment to France of a war indemnity.   The French Government realises that  no part of  the German  Colonies conqueredby troops of  the Dominions  can be retrocecled, and is prepared to come to an  agree-ment with Great Britain as to the disposal of the West African Colonies.  It is hoped.and  expected that  Great Britain will insist upon resuming possession of Heligoland.   Sir W. Townley understands that Herr von Kiihlmann has sent his brother-in-lawHerr Von Stumni to Holland in order to find out the intentions of the British Governmentwith regard to  peace, and Sir C. Spring Rice reports  that the Netherlands Minister is&quot;talking peace&quot; in conversations with  American journalists,&quot; but  will not permit  the associated. Press to quote him on the subject.   The German secretary of&apos; the  PapalDelegate in  the United States is also in communication  with  the Hearst Agency  onthe same topic, but is equally guarded.   The Netherlands Minister gives December asthe date when  peace may be looked for.   According  to Press reports Sir H. Rumbold understands  that  the Municipality ofBerne  proposes to entertain  the  delegates who will attend  the forthcoming  Inter-national Peace  Congress at Berne.  Sir W. Townley  believes  that the Congress willopen on 15th October, and hears  that  the Central Empires  will  be very fully repre-sented, some  dozen names of well-known  personages, including several notablepacifists, being already  mentioned in that connection.                                   GENERAL.    Considerable difficulties  are being experienced  by General Hanbury Williams in finding suitable accommodation for the British prisoners of war to be sent to Hollandfrom Germany in virtue of the recent Hague Agreement, and Sir  AV. Townley reportsthat the General has so far received little practical  assistance from the netherlands government and has been hampered by the dishonesty of house agents.    Escaped  officers have given detailed accounts of  the atrocious treatment to which british officers at Strohen  have been  sitbjected by German non-commissioned officersand sentries.  The British Government are  gravely concerned and  indignant at thisnews and have asked  for a report on the subject  from the Netherlands Minister inBerlin.
   The Spanish  Ambassador in Vienna  understands  that  the  suspension of theparcel post to prisoners in Turkey which has given rise to a protest from the BritishGovernment is due  to extensive troop movements.  The  suspension does not affectprisoners  in  the Vilayet of  Aidin.   The  seriousness  of this  hardship must beconsidered in the light of  Sir Id. Rumbold&apos;s telegram reporting the opinion expressedby a German doctor, who has returned from Turkey, that conditions are unbelievablybad  and  that hardly any prisoners of war would come out of  Turkey alive.   TheMinister, however, has been informed  by the International Red Gross at Geneva that49 gravely disabled  prisoners of  war, of whom the  majority  are  British, may beexpected to arrive shortly in Vienna from Constantinople.  Sir W. Townley is informedthat the  Sublime Port while declining to permit representatives of the netherlands government  to  inspect  prisoners&apos; camps has agreed  to allow an official to theLegation  in Constantinople  to visit the camps for the purpose  of investigating theneeds of the prisoners for the coming winter.   The Netherlands  Minister in  Constantinople was informed by Talaat Pasha thathe had irrevocably  decided to  deport all British  subjects other than  women andchildren from Constantinople and Smyrna if Ayoub Sabri be not released shortly,  ddieMinister has, however, succeeded in delaying the internment of British  subjects untilthe end of the month.   The Netherlands  Minister in Berlin has been informed by  the Ministry of war that officer-prisoners are to  be transferred to Hoi zm in den  camp  from Schwarmstadtwhich was reported by the visiting Commission of Dutch doctors to be overcrowdedand insanitary [vide Report No. 34, p. 15).   ddie Dauish Minister for Foreign Affairs has proposed the repatriation of ecpuivalentnumbers of British and German combatants of  corresponding ranks  now interned  in denmark.  The British Naval Attache favours  the suggestion, as  there are at present one  officer and 12 naval ratings  of the crewr of  the submarine  E  13 at presentinterned in Denmark.   Mr. Gurney learns that the Russian Government have directed  General Ivalishevskito&apos;proceed to  Copenhagen  with two  representatives  of the  Russian  Red  Cross  toattend a Conference  to be summoned  by the Danish Red  Gross  at which Allied and enemy delegates will be present to discuss the cpaestion of sending food supplies  tothe Russian prisoners held by the Central Empires.

</content>
</cab>
