<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/147/0 images: 231-252</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION  OP  THE ATTACH El)  WESTERN&apos;  AND GENERAL                           REPORT, No.  37.                                I.M PIOIMAI. A FJ)&apos;AIUS.   It. is satisfactory to note that  progress is  being made with the organisation of theImperial Mineral  Resources Bureau.   The more progress is made during the war withthis and kindred  organisations for effective common  action in  economic matters, both within the Empire ami among the Allies, tin; more-  rapid will be our  recovery afterthe war, and the greater will  bo the  anxiety of the Germans to  make  peace quicklybefore the world  outside is so  completely organised  as to allow them no  opportunityfor reorganising their system of  economic penetration and control of vital materials and   key  industries.   Mr.  Hughes  states the strength of-our position  bluntly  butcorrectly when he says that Australia can get on quite well without Geriuany&apos;s high-class goods, but that Germany cannot get on without wool and metals.                                 SOUTH AFRICA.   The settlement  of the  tiresome  controversy  over  the woo; clip  will  help thepolitical, sif.iiai.exploiting. by  depriving I he Nationalists of a grievance which Cliey have beenexploiting  as an  argument against  the  Imperial  connection.   It. docs not  seem tohave occurred to  them that  in these sort of bargains the position  of a neutral, subjectto the whole pressure of our highly organised  blockade system, is far Jess favourable than that of a British Dominion where the sense of  partnership and common interestpredominates over all other considerations.                                 German Affairs.   The Chancellors excommunication of the Minority Socialists as  enemies of thei1&apos;country may recall old memories to many of the Majority Socialists, and help  to shaketheir  allegiance to the Government, whose attitude seems to  lie swinging more towardsthe Right again.   The revelations about the mutiny  at Wilhelmshalen will accentuatethe reaction and  so intensify the  estrangement with  the Socialists.                                Austrian  Affairs.    The Emperor and the  ingenious Dr. Wekerle  seem to have hit on  a new solutionof the problem of  unifying the South  Slavs  within the A:;sLro-Hungarian  Empire,This  is to incorporate the whole of the South Slavs except the Slovenes  in. an enlargedCroatia.   Magyar pride  and constitutional prejudices would thus be reconciled  by thefact that the domain of the Hungarian  Crown was enlarged and not diminished, andthat the Dual  system was  maintained intact.  Austria, freed  from boles,  Dalmatians,and  the  Italians of  the  Treutino, might then reorganise itself  on Hungarian lines,putting Bohemia in.  the same position as the enlarged  Croatia.  The Dual system would thus  eventually, in fact if  not  in.  name,  be  converted  into  a Quadruplesystem.
                                       2                                 SOUTH AMERICA.   From  the point of view of I lie economic  future  the  rupture ol relations withGermany  by  Peru, Uruguay, ami apparently also  Ecuador, marks a further importantcontraction (not far off  a million  square  miles  in mere area) of the ever-narrowingneutral zone.                               PEACE DISCUSSIONS.   The fear of the economic future is bcco.nitug more and more the donrinahl note inthe discussion of peace by thinking Germans, and betrays itself at every turn in.  theutterances of Government spokesmen.   But.it is a mistake to imagine that it will makethe enemy pliable beyond a  certain point.  There are certain  irreducible minima which germany  will not yield except to the sword, even if she has to starve  for a generation.dderr you  Kiihlmann seems  to lay down Alsace-Lorraine as one  of  these.   But  onemay fairly suspect a mental reservation with regard to idetz and French Lorraine.11th October 1917L. S.  A.
[This Document is  the Property of His  Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War  Cabinet.SECRET.                    .                                     FOR  REFERENCE ONLY.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.No. 37.   Week ending 10th October (night).CONTENTS.PART  I. British, Empire and  Africa.         Imperial Affairs.             Imperial Mineral Resources Bureau.        &apos; Can ad a.             Sir Wilfrid Laurier and. Leadership of the Liberals.  Formation of Union Government.               Resignation  of Minister  of the Interior.  Number of bachelors  of  military  age.               Number medically examined.   Labour  and Conscription.   British War Mission at               Ottawa.  Supply of Munitions from the Dominion.   Transfer1 of steamers  on Great               Lakes.  Lord;Northcliffe on food question.         Austral i an C bm 111 on wealth.             Mr. Hughes  on economic boycott of  German)-.   End of  seamen and firemevrs strike.               Result of Western  Australian  Election.   Arrangements for  repatriation in New               South Wales  and South Australia.   Army  Council  and offer  of  flying officer-               pilots.   Leave  arrangements   for  Australian  Imperial Forces.   British  purchase               of butter.         New Zealand.             Numbers in training.  Purchase of butter and price of cheese&apos;.         South Africa.             General Botha on welcome to settlers and need for  Unity.  General  Smuts&apos; absence in               England.  Resolution of South African Party Congress regarding  wool clip.  Union               Ministers  and  arrangements   for  sale  of wool  clip.  Mohair clip  not  included.               General Hertzog and Dr.  Mal.au on Republicanism  and independence.  Transvaal               Provincial Council and independence of  small  nations.  Craft for  Lake Nyasa.         German East Africa.             Health of women and children-:  suggested repatriation.PART  II. Foreign Affairs.         Allied Affairs.             Russia and the Allied  Conference.         France.             Visit  of M. Klotsi to  London.   Military Service  Agreement.    Accusations against               M. Malvy.   Position of the Ministry.  Arrest of Tunnel and his wife.   The Socialist               Conference at Bordeaux.         Italy.             Statements of Italian  Minister in Athens.  Sicilian Deputies and  the orange  crop.                Alternative  scheme  for purchase.  Transit of Indian labour parties through Taranto.               Demonetization  of small silver. .         Belgium.             The future of the Flemish  movement.         Greece.                                  .             Italian occupation of Northern  Epirus.   Queen Sophie&apos;s  visit to  Germany.  Food.               situation in Greece.  Health  of M. Venizelos.  Maintenance  of  Navicert system.               Italian Ministers statements.   Censorship at Syra and the Passport Control.         Serbia.             Transfer- of Southern Slav troops to Macedonia.         Enemy Allied Affairs.             The meeting of the four Emperors.         German Affairs.             Naval Mutiny.   Responsibility of the Independent  Socialists.  Submarine difficulties.               Pan-German  propaganda  in.  the  Army.    Professor  Jaffe&apos;s  views   on   economic               warfare.   Attacks  on  the Reichstag and on  Herr von Helfferich.   The  German               Patriotic Party&apos;s programme.  German purchases  of laud in Holland.  Hen-  von               Kuhlinann&apos;s ambitions.   Demonetization of the 2-mark piece.  (33)4073-2  Pk    80  10/17  E &amp; S                 A
Austrian Affairs.    The Emperor Charles and the Southern Slavs.  Conflicting neutral reports on internal      conditions.   Popularity of the Emperor.  Austrian  pride  and  German assistance      against Italy.  Details of the drought.Bulgarian Affairs.    The Prime Ministers sophistry about territorial acquisitions.Netherlands.    Details  of  the British,  economic policy.   The  transit  trade  in  sand and gravel.       Suspension  of  Commercial  Cable  facilities.   Dr.  Kuyper&apos;s  fears about  Dutch       Flanders.Switzerland.    Drawbacks of the proposed Agreement with the United States.   Commercial  letters       in diplomatic bags.Sweden.    The Cabinet crisis.   Supposed failure of Coalition movement.  Details of the British       economic  policy.    German  offers of exports.  The  diplomatic  bags at Halifax.       Import of intoxicants from  Petrograd.   Disadvantages  of stopping-  coal licenses.       Seizure of Swedish colliers.Norway.    Details  of  the British economic  policy. United States Exports Board and Norwegian       grain rations.  Uses of the Navioert system.  German opinion on stoppage of exports.       Denunciation of Wholesale Grocers&apos; Agreement.Denmark.    Details of the  British economic  policy.  Proposals of the egg-exporters.Spain. .    Escape  of  interned German  submarine.  Allied  action&apos;.   Spanish  Note to  Berlin.       Dismissal of the Laraiche Germans.-Portugal.    Visit of President  Machado to  the West Front.   Meetings with Don Alfonso  and       President Poincarc.   Censorship  at Lisbon aud the  Azores, proposed  Allied co-       operation.China.    Relations between the President of the Republic and his Prime Minister.Japan.    Inability of Japan to sell Battle  Cruisers.   Results of  Viscount Ishi.i&apos;s mission to the       United States.Argentina.    Railway strike and Allied Army meat contracts.  German intrigues.   Proposed tax on       steamers.   Argentine grain purchase.  Count Luxburg&apos;s movements.Uruguay.    Rupture of relations with Germany.   Negotiations  for the Arbitration Treaty.Peru.    Rupture of relations with Germany.   Offer of hospitality to ships of the British  Navy.       Application for safe-conduct for former German Minister.Ecuador.    Sympathetic action  of Government with regard to German Minister.Chile.    Unwillingness of Government to allow7 Count Luxburg to enter the country.Mexico.    British subjects and military service at home.  The Tampico strike.  Mexican, schemes       for munition factories.Cuba,    The  sugar-mills strike and German agents.Costa Rica.     Proposed recognition of  President Tinoco&apos;s Government.United States.    Exports Board and  the bunker control over Neutral shipping.The Shipping Situation.     Submarine losses and new shipping.  Ex-enemy  ships in  Spain,  Portugal,  Chile,       American  West  Indies, Siam,  Uruguay.  Status fof  Norwegian, ships under bond       to Germany.  Commercial and Navigation Company in Brazil.Peace Discussions.    The Berne  Conference  and the  International Peace  Congress.  Hamburg mercantile       criticism  of  Erzberger proposals.  The Germany  peace  bluff.   A Dutch opinion :       &quot; Germans are hard hit.&quot;  Beichstag and Papal  Peace Note.General.     Neutral wireless stations.  Copenhagen Red  Cross  Conference.  The Porte  and its.       prisoners.  Reprisals on British prisoners.   British prisoners in  Prussia.
oOPART  I. BRITISH  EMPIRE AND  AFRICA.                              IMPERIAL AFFAIRS.   Following  upon the  Resolution  passed  at the  Imperial&apos; War  Conference on23rd  April in favour  of  establishing an  Imperial Mineral  Resources Bureau inLondon,  the War  Cabinet  have considered&quot; a  Memorandum  from the Ministry ofMunitions and  a  Report by the  Committee appointed  by Dr. Addison, upon  whichrepresentatives of the Dominions, Colonial Office, India Office and other  Departmentsserved.1  The Minister-  of Reconstruction has been authorised  by the War Cabinet toproceed  with  a scheme for  the  establishment of the  Bureau, subject to furtherconsideration.                                    CANADA.    With regard to Sir Wilfrid  LamieFs intimation of his  desire to relinquish the leadership  of  the  Liberal Party,  a final decision has not yet  been reached.   SirWilfrid has, however, been consulting with his supporters in Montreal and Toronto.Meantime  the  matter  of  a possible  successor is  being considered, and Liberalopinion appears generally to favour the choice of Mr. F. B. Carvell.    Sir  Robert Borden is - proceeding with the formation of a  Union Government.The first step was the appointment  of a Liberal, Mr. C. (1 Ballantyne, to the positionof Minister of  Public Works, while Mr. Hugh Guthrie, a prominent  Liberal memberof the House of Commons, who was one of the first  to support conscription from theLiberal Benches, has since been sworn in as  Solicitor-General.    Dr. W.  .J. Roche  has  resigned  the position  of  Minister  of  the  Interior in theDominion  Government,  and has  been appointed Chairman of  the Civil service commission.    It is estimated that there are  493,187 unmarried men in Canada between the ages of 20 and. 34, and if,  as is expected, the first  Proclamation, calling up 100,000 men formilitary service, is confined to men of that class, only one bachelor in five between the ages named will be affected.    Up to 29th  September last, 12,658 men in the Dominion submitted themselves for voluntary medical, examination  in  anticipation  of  the issue of the  Proclamationcalling up  the first class for military service.  Of  those examined, 7,491 were passedfit for general  oversea service.    Wdth reference to the Labour attitude towards conscription,  the Secretary-Tdeasurerof the Dominion Trades and Labour Congress (Mr. Draper) stated  officially in a speechlast month that though organised  labour had opposed the  passing of conscriptionwhile it was still in the stages cf agitation and discussion, their opposition ceased themoment the Bill became law.  The  opposition that organised  labour had offered to aConscription Act, Mr. Draper explained, was due to their knowledge that Labour hadalready given  a larger  proportion  of  men  to the Army than any other element  inCanada.   Out of the  160,000 members of the various Labour Unions in Canada,  he stated, there have been 22,500 enlistments.    Lord Reading, Lord Northcliffe, and members of the British War Mission to theUnited States held their first Conference at Ottawa  on 5th October, when the PrimeMinister, the Minister of Finance, and other  members of  the Cabinet were present.The subjects  of discussion included  the creation of further credits, the full use of canadian natural resources, and  increased shipbuilding.    Before  the  prorogation of Parliament, a discussion took  place in the  House ofCommons last month, upon a motion  to adjourn  the House,  when it was alleged  bythe mover  that the supply of munitions to  Great Britain was being decreased andthat stoppage was threatened.  In reply, the Minister of  Finance  (Sir Thomas White)pointed out that Great Britain was continuing to order in Canada the shells which she specially required.  lustead  of  the Dominion  Government decreasing the amount              1 Copies of this Report are being sent to the Dominion Governments.
y1 The elections in two constituencies have been deferred.supplied to the British Government for the production of shells in Canada, the amountduring  July  and August, Sir Thomas  stated, had  been greatly increased, and muchmore than $25,000,000 per month had been paid out.   (Vide Report No. 31.)   The  Keystone Transportation Company  have  declined  to  co-operate  with theDominion G-overnment for the purpose of transferring steamers on the Great Lakes tooversea service,  and the Canadian Ministers suggest that, as the vessels are registered in Great Britain, the British  Government should requisition them if they are urgently required.   Lord Northcliffe in a speech  to the  Canadian  Club of Montreal on 9th Octoberstated that unless the food question were taken  up  as  vigorously in Canada as it hadbeen in Great Britain, there  must be  a cutting down of the rations of the soldier atthe front.  There must be not only an elimination of all waste, but farmers must alsobe stimulated to increase the production  of  beef,  pork, cheese, butter, and condensed milk.                       AUSTRALIAN  COMMON WEALTH.    Referring to the economic boycott of Germany,  the Prime  Minister (Mr. Hughes)has  declared that  if the Allies stand  fast  by the  terms  of  the Paris EconomicConference,  Germany will find  that  the  means  of inflicting punishment are prac-ticable and  effective.   In. outlining the policy of  the Commonwealth, Air. Hughescontinued :     &quot;Idie  foolish assertion that after  the war Australia  is  not   going  to  give up       German  markets, nor those of  German,  goods that  had   once such a high       reputation,  may  be answered  in a few words.  Whatever other  nations or       parts  of the British Empire may do, Australia has neither  the desire  nor the       intention  of  resuming her relations  with  Germany.   Australia can  get on       quite  well without Germany&apos;s  goods  of  high reputation,  but Germany cannot       get on without  wool and metals.  Australia  can  sell  her  raw material,       wool,  metals, &amp;c, to Great Britain and her Allies, and she  will most certainly       do so.&quot;    Though,  the  New South Wales seamen and firemen declared  last week that theywere determined to remain out  on  strike  indefinitely, they have  now followed the example of the coal miners (vide Report No.  36) and returned to work.   The  results of the General  Election for the  Legislative Assembly  of  Western Australia  show a substantial majority  for  the Nationalists.  Mr. Lefroy thereforereturns  to power as Premier with 321 followers, as against a Labour  representationof lb.    The  New South Wales Government, while providing  for  the repatriation of australian soldiers, are also making provision for  at least 5,000 British ex-soldiers.   A Repatriation Bill providing for the settlement of  15,000  soldiers on the land isunder consideration, by the Parliament of South. Australia.    The Army Council  have  explained to the  Commonwealth Government that their non-acceptance of the offer of further flying officer  pilots was due to the fact that thetraining  at  the  Melbourne Central Flying School was Inadequate to provide pilotssuitable, for  conditions  of modern war, and that it was not intended to  discouragecandidates from  volunteering  for the Royal  Flying  Corps.   The Army   Council.strongly recommend that a training  organisation  should be established, in. Australia,similar to that in England, involving courses of training of Flying Corps Cadets anda School of  Military  Aeronautics with  training  squadrous  for  instruction.  It issuggested that a Royal Flying Corps  officer should proceed to Australia  to advise the  Government.    With regard to suggestions  put  forward by the Commonwealth Government for granting leave  to  members of the  Australian. Imperial Forces,  the Army  council have sent a reply in practically  the same terms as that sent in response to the similarrequest from New Zealand (vide Reports Nos. 32, 35 and 36).   The hope is expressed that the Commonwealth Government will not press their suggestions, and it is addedthat on the considerations outlined  being put,  before  the New Zealand Government, the  Ministers of  that Dominion  abandoned their proposals.    The Prime Minister has announced that arrangements have been made for the sale to the British Government of 30,000 tons of butter, representing 4,500,000i.
                               NEW  ZEALAND.   The Governor-General reports that the numbers in training in the Dominion on30th September amounted to 12,000, including 172 Maoris.   The Food Controller has stated  his preparedness to buy exportable New Zealandbutter for  the period  September 191 7 to  June 1918 inclusive, up to  the amount of15,000 tons.  In reply  the Prime Minister  has expressed  his intention of submittingthe offer to a Conference of  butter producers this week.   As,  however, cheese andbutter are intimately connected, the Prime Minister has pointed out the great importanceof knowing the price at which the British Government will  purchase the cheese output.The New Zealand producers, it is added, would be  content with a price equivalent tothat paid to the Canadian Government.                                SOUTH  AFRICA.    At the termination of the sittings of the South African Party Congress, the Prime Minister (General Botha) made a strong appeal for unity throughout the country.   He said that unfortunately their differences were  accentuated owing to the smallness of the population.   He added : &quot; Let them welcome every man making South Africa his home, and thus build up a great and noble nation.&apos;,&apos;  In conclusion General Botha  paid a warm tribute to General Smuts  and  asked  the Congress not to be impatient if  he remained away for some time longer.  &quot; General Smuts in England,&quot; he  stated, &quot; was ;&apos; working for the benefit of South  Africa because South Africa also desired to see a &quot; lasting peace.&quot;   A cable from General Smuts was read to the Congress in which he said : &quot; Only necessity and  the insistence of the Government keep me here, where the &quot;future  of  South Africa is being decided.  I shall return to my land and people as &quot; soon as circumstances permit.&quot;    The South African Party  Congress passed  a Resolution thanking the British Government for the manner in  which they had met South Africa regarding the  wool dip-,    The Union Ministers  have telegraphed to  the British Government  their warm appreciation of  the  offer  to purchase the whole of the  1917  wool clip  and wooled sheepskins at a rate  which the  Ministers considered to be fair.  In the same telegram the Ministers express their regret  that on account  of  the opposition  raised by certain farmers for  political reasons, and to the enhanced prices realised  and anticipated for purchases by Japanese merchants, it has been impossible to carry through the original scheme of  purchasing the whole  clip.    The  Ministers, however,  confirm  their acceptance  of the  terms  of  the British  Governments  latest  telegram,  and  are ascertaining the total quantity of wool  and wooled sheepskins, and the proportions of different qualities, available.  A Central Board will be appointed wdth whom the Army Contracts&apos; Department will arrange details  direct.   A Technical Committee, which was appointed, as the result of  a Conference at Pretoria  last July, recommended  that the Central  Board should consist of a Government official as Chairman, two producers, one  wool  buyer and one AVOOI  broker, and  that the  Board should  be assisted by a technical advisory Committee  and  appraising Boards.   The detailed  suggestions of the  Committee  were  made with  due regard  to the views of the  Army Contracts Department and to local conditions, but in submitting the recommendations the Union Ministers state that they are somewhat  hampered by absence of  knowledge concerning the amounts paid, by the British Government  for the Australian clip. They therefore wdsh that the proposals may  be  considered  as tentative  and  subject  to  possible modifications in  accordance with  the  information  which may reach them as to  the Australian practice.    The Minister  of Agriculture (Mr. Van Heerden) has announced that the offer of the British Government to purchase  the  South  African wool  clip does not include the mohair clip.    At the Bloemfontein Congress of Free  State Nationalists, General Hertzog referred to Republican propaganda  and  stated that  ultimate independence was  desirable and inevitable.  He observed that the policy of the Government, in  assisting Great Britain in the prosecution of  the  war, had resulted  in &quot; a spirit  of dissatisfaction  that was-almost revolutionary.&quot; Lie  expressed his disbelief  in the  possibility of  another     4073--2                            B
rebellion, the idea of whicb-he-ssrid originated with people not well-disposed  to  the nationalists.   They had a free constitution, he added, under which they  could  workout their destiny, but he complained that the Union Ministers had acted as agents ofthe Imperial Government instead of giving  effect  to the wishes of their  own people,and he therefore contended that self-government was only nominal.  General Hertzogwas supported in his views  generally by Dr. Malan,  editor of  &quot; De  Burger.&quot;  whostated that though the time was not ripe for carrying on Republican propaganda, thattime must inevitably come.   The wool and maize questions  were quoted by GeneralIiertzog and Dr. Malan as  examples  of what was termed by the Nationalist Leader&quot;the dire consequences of Imperialism.&quot;    The  Ihansvaai Provincial  Council,  has had  under discussion, the motion, of  aNationalist member which approved  the declaration of the Bidtish Government thatno peace is  possible before the independence  of small  nations  is recognised, and expressed  confidence  that  this principle would be- applied to South Africa.   an amendment was  carried by 17 votes to 12 substituting  for the latter part  of  theResolution  the words:  &quot; The  Council expresses  its confidence that  the  Union&quot;  Government will continue to support the Allies in the maintenance and carrying out&quot;  of the said, principle, and further expresses its sincere thanks and appreciation, to the&quot;  Prime Minister and the Government for the policy hitherto pursued.&quot;    With reference to the offer of the  Union Government  to  supply motor launches.instead of tugs or barges, for use on  Lake Nyasa (vide Report  No. 35),  the British.Government have expressed a  doubt as to whether such craft  would be suitable inview of the fact  that  they would have to be  transported  to Lake  Nyasa in sections.If, however, the launches are of steel and can be dismantled for transport overland,they could be used, and a naval officer  is : being sent from Lake Nyasa  to inspect thevessels at Durban.                           GERMAN EAST AFRICA.    The Administration reports  that a letter from the German doctor  of  the GermanHospital at Dar-es-Salaam to the German Governor  has been sent  to  him by themilitary authorities. This letter states that  considering tropical conditions the presenthealth of the community is passably good, and that food,  is  satisfactory.  He  draws attention, however, to the number of  cases  of organic ailment, most of which  beganbefore the British occupation, and which should be sent to  Europe.  Anticipating anincrease of sickness during  the approaching hot  season, he suggests  that,  failingremoval, to Europe, the women  and children on the coast should be sent to IJsumbura;The Administrator,  however, points out that the  available accommodation  does not make this possible,  and in  view of the responsibility incurred  if the  women  andchildren remain indefinite!)7 in an unhealthy climate, he urges  the  desirability  ofearl)&quot; repatriation.
PART  II. FOREIGN  AFFAIRS.                               ALLIED  AFFAIRS.   With reference to the proposed joint Allied economic action against the Scandinavian-scandinavian  states, in which Russia was invited to participate, the  Russian Minister forForeign Affairs points out that such action would  he disastrous to Russia.  He fearsthat Russia would find herself unable to obtain various necessaries, that her exchangewould fall, and that Sweden would put a stop to the transit  trade to  and from Russia.The Russian Minister hopes that action on this point may be deferred until the wholequestion can  be discussed by an Allied  Conference at which the United States wouldbe represented.  M.  Tereschenko  would prefer that such, a  Conference should beconvoked by  the  British Government,  and. that it  should sit in  London.  Sir G.Buchanan  reports that  the Russian Minister  for Foreign Affairs relies more  for support upon Great Britain than on any other nation.                                    FRANCE,    Lord  Bertie has been advised that the French Minister of Finance, M. Edotz, will shortly visit London in order to  discuss  questions in connection with the Swiss Loan, in France and Great Britain, and die granting of credits to  the Allies by the Northern Neutrals.    Mr. Cave,  in Algiers, has  been, informed by the Foreign Office that under the Military Service Agreement with France, British  subjects wdio  enlist in.  the French Army wdll not be compelled to join the Foreign Legion, and  -will not be  deprived of their right to  repudiate French  nationality,  as such repudiation, according to law, must be made within three months of reaching the age of 18 or before being called up for military service, or in the  case of men between the ages of 18  and 22, it should have been done before 3rd October just past.    M. Daudet,  Director of the &quot; Action Francaise,&quot; having formally accused M. Malvy, until recently Minister of the Interior, of treason, in a letter to the President of the Republic, the ex-Minis ter defended himself at some length in the Chamber.   In course of his speech, M. Malvy referred to the  fact that during  the  three years that he had been in office, he had defended not only France, but the Republic as well.  M. Painleve stated that justice would in all cases take its course, and would be no respecter of persons, but deplored the attitude of the  Press, which devoted so much space to scandals that there was but little left in which to record the  deeds of heroes and the progress of the war.    M. Daudet wras attacked, and  was informed by the Prime Minister that he must substantiate his accusations or take the consequences.  Legislation is  to be  introduced to render  irresponsible accusations impossible in future, and M. Caillaux came forward as a champion of such measures against calumny and slander.    Lord Bertie learns that the  position of the Government was not, improved by  the course of  the debate, and it is interesting to  note that M. Laval referred to the main- tenance of the regime,  that is the Republic itself:, as  being menaced in his speech.    The position may have been improved by the arrest  of the Deputy Turmel, which was effected on 6th October (vide Report No. 84, p. 7) as  the result  of the enquiry. According to Press reports Mme.  Tunnel has now also been arrested.    ddie Socialist Congress at Bordeaux defeated the  proposal  of the  Kienthal group that one of its members, M. Raffin Dugens,  should preside  over the Congress for a session by 1,493 votes to 1,369, this being the first  actual trial of strength between the  two  groups,  and  the Majority  Socialist, M.  Milhaud, attacked the  Minority extremists for  having misunderstood the national  sentiment of France,  M. Blazon having declared for immediate  peace  without  annexations  or  indemnities.  After:a number of sessions,  in which the  debates were  conducted amid scenes almost Russian  in their   disorderliness, the  Conference  declared,  for a  Conference  at Stockholm, for  participation in the present Administration,  for  support  of the war credits and for a  revision of the Allied  war aims.   This  resolution, wdiich  was supported by the  Majority Socialists  with 1,552 votes, Avas  opposed by the Minority
sSocialists who polled 831 votes, by the Kicnthal fraction with 385, and by an ultra-Kienthal sab-fraction which has  just  appeared under  the leadership  of  a  modernTricoteuse with .118 votes.  There were 85 abstentions.   Thus  the Majority of 1,552&apos;was either opposed or not supported by 1,419 votes.    M. Humbert continues to exculpate  himself and his  newspaper, the &quot;Journal,&quot;&apos;from the suspicion of having been suborned by Bolo.                                     ITALY.    In a conversation with, the Hellenic  Minister for Foreign Affairs (vide Greece), the Italian Minister in Athens alluded to the strength of the Socialist peace  movement in Italy as being so strong that his Government  might be unable to resist it.  He also asserted that Italy had been discouraged of late by a lack of sympathy on the j)art of her Allies.   Mr. Crackanthorpe  suggests  that  these statements may have been made in order to further the immediate interests of Italy in Greece,  and it is not  certain that they are a true  description of the existing situation.  Mr.   Erskine, our Charge. d&apos;Affaires in Rome, suggests that the conversation may have been purposely distorted by the Hellenic Minister  for Foreign Affairs in order  to embroil the Italian Minister with his chief and thus secure his  recall.    Owing to  the  inflammatory action  of the  Deputy Felice who has invited  all his Sicilian colleagues to meet at &quot;Palermo  (where Martial Law has not yet been declared) and protest against the failure of the Italian. Government to  secure the export of Sicilian citrus fruits, the Italian Government has become alarmed.  The Minister of Commerce  in consequence  begged  the British  Treasury to waive its condition of paying for the proposed purchase of oranges out of  sterling credits, but the Treasury has declined to submit to this further imposition.  The British Government, however, are prepared to grant sulphate of ammonia to Italy for her lemons  if the Italians willmake satisfactory arrangements for the  supply of tonnage for the export of the orangesto be taken over by Great Britain.    In view of this decision, Air. Erskine has suggested that Mr.  Dottridge, who wasin charge of the orange negotiations, be invited to assist  in the  private  financing ofthe purchase, a scheme for  which he  prepared  before  leaving Italy.   Mr.  Erskinepoints out that an abandonment of the project at this stage would produce very gravepolitical consequences.    Sir R. Rodd, in a telegram to Baron Sonnino, refers to the reported decision of theItalian  Government; to prohibit  the further  transit  of Indian or Egyptian labour companies  en route  for  France  through Taranto.  He  points out that no moreEgyptians will, be imported,  but  that some 3,000 Indians  per  month will be coiningfor the next four months, and  of  these 1,300  are actually upon, the sea bound for egypt.  The alternative port of Gallipoli  proposed  by the Italians is unsuited  for thedebarkation of the men as it is undefended against submarines, and has no  propercamps or water supply.   If  Taranto can still be used  every precaution will be takento prevent /Linger of infection from the Indians.    A decree has been issued  calling in all silver  two-lire and.  one-lira xyieces,  whichwdll be demonetised after a specified date.                                    BELGIUM.    Mr. Alaxse, in Rotterdam, has received information to the effect that the Flemish.movement, as  engineered by the Germans, is becoming an active danger in Belgiumwvhich is likely to cause trouble even after the Germans shall have left the country.                                    GREECE.    The Foreign  Office has asked whether the reported extension of the area of Italian occupation, over and above the Konitza district, has in fact taken place.   Mr. Erskine,. in reply,  reports that the Italians propose to retain Konitza until the French evacuate two of the four villages in the Sarandaporon valley which dominate the road  between Santi Quaranta and Macedonia.   The French decline to  evacuate unless the Italians agree not to occupy any of the four villages.  &apos; The Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs asserts that as the road in question forms the sole line of retreat for the Italian Armyin the event of a disaster in Macedonia,  it  is essential, that  it should be properlyguarded, and  that any difficulties which may have arisen with the Hellenic Governmenton this subject are clue to the action of  General Sarrail.
   Sir H. Rumbold learns that M. Streit, a former Germanophil Greek Minister for&apos;Foreign  Affairs, has  gone to Munich to arrange for a visit  of  Queeu  Sophie  toGermany.   Mr. Crackanthorpe draws attention to the gravity of the food  situation  in Greece,and suggests that if there is any farther reduction on the existing minimum estimate(allowing f- lb. per head daily), not only will Greek military  plans come to nothing,hut the very existence of the present Administration will be threatened.   As it is, thelabours of  the Food  Controllership,  which  was recently  taken  over by  the PrimeMinister, have graveR over-taxed his  strength to such an extent that  the state of his health gives cause for anxiety.    Lord  Bertie reports that France  concurs  with  the  British proposals for  themaintenance of the  Navioert system of Greece (vide Report -No.  34, p.  8),  and that theFrench Ambassador in Washington has been instructed to  support Sir C. Spring-Ricein his representations to the State Department on this subject.   Mr. Crackanthorpe reports  that the Italian  Minister  in  Athens  represented theinternal situation in Italy in such terms to the Greek Minister for Foreign Affairs  asto give  colour to  the  suggestion  that  Italy was  unwilling  that Greece should participate in  the war (vide under Italy).   The British Charge d&apos;Affaires, to whom this conversation was repeated by the Cabinet Minister, suggests that Italy is  anxious toprevent  a  successful  mobilisation  in  Greece, as  it is to her interest  to keep thatcountry in a  state of weakness and perpetual internal  agitation.  According to otherinformants, it is probable that France also is  pursuing a similar policy in Greece. .   Lord   Granvilie  reports  that  the Hellenic  authorities have re-established the censorship at Syra (vide  Report  No. 30,  p. 7) on its former footing, pending the definite settlement; of  the question, and has received  Notes from  the Hellenic Govern-ment accex^ting tire British  proposals for  the maintenance  and modification of the passport Control in Greece (vide  Report No.  33, p. 9).                                     SERBIA.   With reference to  the proposed transfer of Southern Slavs from Italy  and south russia to  Macedonia (vide  Reports No. 33, p.  8, No. 35, p.  9, and No.  36,  p.  8),Sir G. Barclay is  informed that definite  orders have now been  received  in  Jassyto send the Serbian troops serving on the Galatz front to Salonika,   He suggests that,if carried out, this movement may dangerously weaken that front, where the moral, ofthe Russian troops leaves very much to be desired.  So strongly is  this felt  that theKing of  Rumania has personally urged the British Minister  to endeavour  to  securethe retention of these troops in Rumania.  In this connection the Press report that anentire  Bosnian regiment, with its  officers and arms, deserted to the  Rumanian linesat Ocna is interesting.                          ENEMY  ALLIED  AFFAIRS.    Sir W. Townley has information tending  to confirm the report that the four enemyEmperors  are to meet, probably in Bulgaria,  at an early date.                              GERMAN   AFFAIRS.    Sir W.  Townley reports that there is reason to  believe that the incident which gave rise to heated debate  in the Reichstag to-day was  the following : The crews of four-vessels of  the line,  among which were the &quot; Kaiser &quot;  and the &quot; Westphalen,&quot; lying willhelmshaven, recently mutinied and left their ships. The crew of the &quot; Westphalen &quot;before forsaking the ship seized  the  Captain and threw him overboard, his body notbeing&apos;recovered for  eight days.   A  regiment of Marines was  ordered to &quot;quell  themutiny but refused to obey orders.   An Oldenburg  regiment  was then summonedwinch surrounded  the mutineers, who surrendered.  The &quot;  Nurnberg &quot; was cruisingat the time outside the port.   Her crew also mutinied, and having  arrested their officers,steered for the coast of  Norway with  the intention of getting the  vessel interned.  Shewas,  however,  met by a  flotilla of  torpedo-boats,  the  Commodore of  which  wassurprised  that  the &quot; Nurnberg &quot; did not reply  to his signals.  He  wirelessed toWilhemshaven to ask for instructions and  was  ordered to stop the &quot; Nurnberg &quot; or to sink her.  He surrounded the ship  with his flotilla, and the  crew surrendered whenthey saw that the vessel would be sunk if they  did not do so.  As soon as the mutinyhad been quelled the Kaiser went to Wilhemshaven with the  Chancellor and ordered     4073-2                        -   C
that one  in every seven  of  the  mutineers should  he shot.  Michaelis, however,protested, and in the end  only three  men were executed,  but severe punishments  ofpenal servitude were inflicted  upon the other offenders.   Bad food rations and disgustat the continual inactivity of the Fleet are given as reasons for the mutiny.    This mutiny was referred to in the Reichstag.   The Independent Socialist DeputyDittman accused the Government of considering his party to be traitors, and of beingthe slaves of the Militarists and. Pan-Germans.   Upon  this Admiral, von  Gapelle, theSecretary of Marine, asserted that the chief ringleader of the mutiny had laid his plansbefore the leader of the Independent Socialists  and had received his promise of full support.  The  Chancellor,  speaking later, said  that papers  had  been found,  on themutineers in which they agreed  to  recognise  the  principles of the  IndependentSocialists, and  proving that  the party had carried  on an extensive propaganda  inthe Fleet.    Sir  M. Findlay learns from the Scandinavian wife of a German  officer in theSubmarine Supply Department that several German seamen have  recently been  shotfor refusing to go to sea in  submarines.   This  news  was  communicated before  that about the German naval mutiny was known.    Sir W. Townley reports that an angry  debate  took place in the Reichstag on 6th.October when the Socialist Deputy Landsberg interpellated the Government on thesubject of Pan-German propaganda in the Army,   lie was supported in his attack on.the present  system  by the whole &quot; Majority &quot; Party, and it was apparent that members were much exercised by the increasing realisation  of  the economic dangers which lieahead if Germany continues to defy the world in obedience to  the Pan-German policy.Even the submarine campaign fails&apos;to inspire confidence and  the Deputy Gotheiu,  ina speech at a party  meeting, emphasised the ridiculous miscalculations of its advocateswho had.  predicted the collapse of  Great Britain if  5,000,000 tons of shipping were sunk, when  in point of fact the British Government had not found it necessary even to ration food when 7,000,000 tons had been  sunk.   In  view  of  this gathering dissatisfaction, it  is thought  possible that both theChancellor and Herr von Helfferich will havo to retire, and  considerable  interest lies in. the statements of  Professor  Jarre (vide  Report No.  36, p.  1.7), who  suggests  thatif  Germany could be made to believe that there is a serious intention on  the  part  ofthe Allies to put an embargo on German shipping in Allied ports for a term of years,or wage an  economic war against Germany in  the future, it  is possible that  publicopinion would realise the danger of such a situation.  In that case the schemes of the pan-Germans and the politicians would be upset and much, less  stringent terras  thanthose indicated last week would be offered by Germany in  order to secure economicas well as  political  peace.   That this view is  shared by others is shown by theuneasiness caused to the &quot; Kolnische Zeitung &apos;,&apos; by the formation of a British commercial intelligence Department, as it sees in this  step an indication of the determination  ofthe Allies to wage economic war after the  conclusion, of  peace, and. goes on to demand that Germany must  be  protected  from such aggression in the future by a clause  inthe Treaty of Peace.    According  to the  &quot; Frankfurter Zeitung &quot; a  bitter and apparently unjust attack was made upon the Reichstag, -with  Ilindenburg&apos;s  approval, at  his birthday party,and the Deputy  Waldstein has  drawn official attention to it as imperilling the Partytruce.   The &quot; Vossische Zeitung,&quot; on  the other  hand, publishes a considered attack upon Herr von Helfferich in which the Reichstag is urged  to refuse the credits askedfor the new post created for that official who is stigmatised as incompetent, misgnided,and ill-mannered.   In spite  of everything, however,  the Main  Committee of theReichstag,  as was  to be expected,  passed  the third reading of  the supplementaryBudget, w&quot;hich was opposed by the Social Democrats.    The German  Patriotic Party, however, has chosen  this moment  to come out with afull-blooded Pan-German programme of wholesale annexations both in  the West andin the  East, and  won support  in the Reichstag debate in. the natural revulsion amongmore moderate men caused by the exposure of the part  played in the naval mutiny bythe pacifist  intrigues of the Independent Socialists.    In  a letter to Mr. Campbell, at the Foreign Office, Mr. Maxse reports from Rotterdamthat the mediatized House of Hoheulohe and other leading German families haverecently been buying properties in Holland in order to  preserve some at least of theirfortunes in  the  event of  a  revolution in Germany.  Considerable sums  of Germanmoney have also been sent into the country for the same purpose.
   Tlie &quot; Neue  Freie  Presse&quot; is  reported  by Sir  W. Townley to be  reflecting  theviews of certain organs of the German Press when it suggests that perhaps Herr vonKuhlmann is now  trying to set himself up against the Chancellor.  Mr. Maxse learnsthat  the Foreign Secretary is, and has been, opposed to unlimited submarine warfare,.and is looked upon in many quarters as almost Anglophil.   In view of the rise in  the price of silver and with the intention of counteractingthe hoarding propensities  of the peasantry, steps have been  taken to call in all silvertwo-mark pieces which are to be demonetised as from 1st January .1918.                            AUSTRIAN AFFAIRS.   According to Press reports,  the  Emperor, in a recent interview with a Croatiandeputation which advocated the inclusion in Croatia not only of Dalmatia, but  also of Posnia-Herzegovina, and if the Austrians occupied part of Serbia, expressed himself in general terms favourable  to Croation aspirations for  expansion.   The inclusion  ofDalmatia was suggested by  Dr.  Wekerle, in the Hungarian Parliament last  month,and it looks as if a plan, were on foot for solving the Southern Slav  question on theselines, the only solution which the Magyars would look at, as it involves  an  extension,and not a  diminution, of the &quot;Lands of the Crown of Saint Stephen.&quot;   Writing on  18th  September to   Mr.  Balfour,  Sir   E.  Howard  states  that a neutral lately returned from travelling in the Central Empires asserts that the positionas regards food in Austria was  then not&apos; so bad  as  it had been.  Well-to-do people could get  all that was necessary in. Vienna where social life and racing went on muchas before.   In Berlin there was a greater shortage of food than in the southern  capital,but there  were many more well-dressed men to be seen in the streets.   The Emperor Charles has made himself exceedingly  popular among the Vienneseworking classes by his personal efforts to dielp the poor and his  unassuming abandon-ment of tire rigours of etiquette.  He  is personally far from being pro-German, but ismuch  under  the  influence of  his Foreign  Minister, Count Czerniu, who is  more german than the Germans,   ddie latter is, however, very unpopular, as, indeed, arethe Germans themselves, owing, in  both cases,  to overbearing and dictatorial habits.   ddie Austrians have hitherto consistently declined German offers to send troops tothe Carso front, as they have no wish to  be  beholden to  them for assistance againstthe Italians, but Sir  E. Howard&quot;s informant believes that  the Germans will insist oncoming to the help  of Austria  if Trieste  be  seriously endangered, as Austria wouldprobably make a  separate peace after  so heavy a loss, if reasonable terms were to be offered to her.   Sir  Id. Rumbold, on the other hand, telegraphing  on 3rd  October,  reports theopinion of a merchant just-returned  from Budapest.   This informant considers thatthe Dual Monarchy is completely exhausted and cannot hist over the  winter.   Her grainsupply  will fail  before  March.   Feeling in  Austria is bitter against Bavaria and hungary who decline to  export their foodstuffs to her.   lie hears that very little oil is coming from  Rumania,  and  understands  that  Hamburg merchants, from  fear of competition, are strongly opposed.to the annexation of Antwerp  by  Germany.    The Viennese  Press draAvs attention to the drought during the past summer, whichwas the driest for  72 years,  the rainfall having been only about one-third of thenormal.                            BULGARIAN AFFAIRS.    M. Radoslavoff, the Bulgarian Prime Minister, in  conversation with a journalist,laid down,  the  minimum Bulgarian  peace terms as  the recovery of all  territories&quot; annexed &quot; from Bulgaria, to which Bulgaria has the same rights as those of Germanyto Alsace-Lorraine.   These  territories  comprise the  Dobruja, both Bulgarian  andRumanian  as far as the  mouth  of  the Danube, Serbia up  to  the &quot; Bulgarian &quot;Moravia, and all Macedonia as far as  the district  south,  of Mouastir.  In view of this principle that the territories occupied. ,or  desired,  by Bulgaria  only involve legitimaterecovery of what  has  been lost, Bulgaria is  in no way opposed to a  peace  withoutannexations, and, in point  of  fact, does not desire  to  annex  anything.  &apos;The PrimeMinister also scouted the idea that there was any likelihood of a  change of Governmentin Bulgaria.
                                NETHERLANDS.   Sir C. Spring Rice has  been informed of the details of  the British policy towardsthe Netherlands.  According to this, the  Dutch are to agree to import nothing exceptwhat is controlled  by the  Netherlands Overseas Trust, to  grant a loan to the Alliesand  make a  satisfactory tonnage  arrangement.  All  transit of srmd, gravel, cement,minerals and metals  for Germany is to be stopped, and all  exports of food, fodders,fish, fish products, horses&apos; hides, dead or alive, and leather to the Central Empires areto be prohibited.  Exports to the  Allies and Belgian  Relief to continue as at  present.Further trustworthy statistics of all exports are to be  furnished  monthly.  In returnHolland will be granted wheat  and flour in proportion to the grants made for BelgianRelief,  rationed imports of   other  goods,  except  fodders  and fertilizers, bunkerfacilities  abroad, and coal to be put at the disposal  of the  Dutch, to be fetched  bythem, iii Great  Britain.  In view of the  continued leakage of sand  and  gravel into germany in spite of repeated protests to the Dutch Government, the Foreign office has suspended facilities for Dutch commercial cables, and has notified the NetherlandsMinister in London to that effect.   Idle importance of this traffic  to the enemy is shown by the fact that the BritishLegation  reports that nearly 4,000,000 tons of these materials (used by the Germansfor the * making of roads, gun-emplacements, and &quot;pill-boxes&quot; at the  front)  have passed through or out of Holland  this year.   Dr. Kuyper, a  former Dutch Cabinet Minister and well known for his pro-Germanviews,  has published an article in a Netherlands newspaper drawing attention to thedanger of an Entente victory to those  districts of the Province of Zeeland which lieon the south side of the Scheldt.                                 SWITZERLAND.   The Foreign Office has instructed Sir C. Spring Rice to suggest  to  the  state department  that it is of the highest importance that the  United States shoidd not commit  themselves to  the  proposed Swiss Agreement (vide Report  No. 36, p. 9)without previous consultation with the French Government.  It would be unfortunate if Great Britain and France,  having found it desirable to put further pressure  uponSwitzerland  with a view to the stoppage of  important exports to the enemy, were tofind  the United States unable to co-operate on account of the hampering provisions ofan ill-considered Agreement.   The British Minister is reminded that  the Swiss in theproposed  Agreement have  affected to  grant  concessions  to  the United States  by offering to forbid the export of  commodities which they have for  some time past beenunder  obligation to other Allies not to export, and  that the control, over transit ofgoods  to Switzerland is very complete both in France and Italy.   Sir C. Spring Rice learns that the United States Minister in Berne has discoveredthat &quot;very  important&quot;  commercial letters,  if presented  by reputable  native-bornSwitzers, are sometimes smuggled  through the Allied  censorship controls  by beingforwarded in Swiss diplomatic bags.                                    SWEDEN.    Sir E. Howard  learns that the  King  of Sweden on the 8th  October received therepresentatives of  the three parties in the new Chamber on his return from theAutumn Manoeuvres.  The Conservatives and  the Liberals favour a Coalition Ministrypledged  to   neutrality, but the demand  of  the Socialists,  who also  desire themaintenance  of a  strict neutrality,  for immediate  reform  of the Municipal Franchiseis not supported  by either of the  other  parties.  In consequence of this the Pressconsiders that the  attempt to form  a Coalition Ministry has failed and  the King hassent for the Speakers of the two blouses to confer with him.    The Foreign Office has  informed Sir  C. Spring Rice that the details of  its policytoward Sweden are that Sweden should agree very materially to reduce the export of iron ore  to  Germany, and should  totally prohibit the export of all food, fish, fish-products, metals, hides, leather, manufactured metal  and leather,  and ores other thaniron ore.  Further, Sweden should continue to export to Allied countries as at present,and furnish satisfactory monthly returns  of all exports ;  grant  a loan to the Allies ;facilitate the transit trade  to and   from Russia;  come to a satisfactory ShippingAgreement, and compel Swedish fishing vessels to  land their catch in  Swedish  portsonly.  In return, the British Government  will provide as much coal as may be called
                                   NORWAY.  .   The Foreign  Office has informed. Sir C. Spring  Rice that its policy towardsNorway is that Norway should agree  to suspend all exports to enemy countries, while continuing to export, as at present, to Allied countries, and to furnish a trustworthyreturn monthly of all  exports, both to Allies and neutrals.  In return for this, anadequate supply  of cereals for home  requirements will be granted.   To a certain    4073-2                               I)lor by Swedish ships, will permit a limited import of grain, and will  grant  the saleof 300,000 barrels of herrings to Sweden,  and  allow reasonable imports  of  other commodities.  The whole negotiation on this subject is to be one of bargaining;  thereis no question of attempting  to arrive at the desired  result by means of ultimatum.Sir E.  Howard  has had conversations with Messrs. Branting  and Lofgren, who&apos;may possibly  be members of the new Cabinet, and both agree that there are no objectionsin principle to the arrangement of a Shipping Agreement, or to a very large reductionin the export of   iron ore and  steel  to  Germany, as there  is considerable publicdissatisfaction with the terms of certain of the more important existing contracts withGermany.  Nor would there  be any great difficulty in giving guarantees  against there-export of imported goods or their products to Germany, or against the correspondingrelease of similar  commodities of home production for export.  But neither of the twoleaders thought that it would be possible for Sweden to agree to a total  prohibitionof iron ore or steel  exports to Germany, as  such a  proceeding would amount to a breach of neutrality.    Mr. Branting informed the British Minister that Germany was offering to supplySweden with lubricants, mineral oil, and  even grain, as well as coal and  other goods,and Sir lb  Howard suggests  that the best way to secure the reduction  of  the exportof iron ore  would  be to induce Sweden to put it on the export prohibition list, annulthe contracts made with Germany, raise the  price considerably, and in addition  exactlarge compensation in other goods, so that Germany could not afford to buy  as muchas she does at present.  This  procedure would  enable the Swedish Government tojustify their action to the public at large, and would  in any case win the  support ofthe dissatisfied shareholders in particular, as it would enable the iatter to benefit Bythe sale  of the iron,  ore  either to the Allies or to Germany at the current prices,instead of,  as at present, to Germany alone at pre-war contract prices.    In.  the  matter  of the Swedish  diplomatic  bags detained, at  Halifax (vide ReportsNo. 35, pp. 10-11, No. 30, p. 11), the State  Department has now  suggested  that thebags should be opened at the British Embassy in  the presence of the Swedish Ministerto Washington, and that no American representative should attend.    Sir G. Buchanan learns  that the Russian  authorities  in order to prevent a largestock  of wine, now stored in Petrograd, from falling  into the hands  of rioters, wishto export it to Sweden.  As there is an embargo laid upon the import of wine exceeding.14 per cent, alcoholic  strength  instructions are  asked for, in case the  wine, which.exceeds that  strength should be re-exported to Germany.    Sir  E.  Howard enumerates some of the disadvantages  which will have  to be weighed against the advantages to be gained from stopping the issue of  coal licences for Sweden.   Among  the more important  of  these   are the cessation of  shippingbetween Sweden and the United Kingdom owing to the lack of return freights whichwould entail a great  rise in freights and a possible prohibition  on the  part of theSwedish Government  to license exports or grant war insurance, the  refusal of therailways to carry  goods for shipment to the United Kingdom, as there is already greatdifficulty on this  score, or transit  goods for Russia,  and the  cessation of the nianu-facture of  goods for the Allies  in works making use of coal  for  this purpose,   lirerailways and works could of  course be rationed with licensed coal, but this would notbe  enough to  furnish return freights for the bottoms at  present employed on the voyage to and from Great Britain.    The Swedish  Minister for  Foreign Affairs (the  Conservative Ministers are stilltransacting the business of their respective departments pending the formation of  anew Cabinet) has protested  against  the seizure  of:  Swedish ships carrying coal ofGerman origin from Rotterdam to  Sweden.   Sir E.  Howard  reminded the  minister that this action, if looked at in the light of a reprisal, was mild when compared, withthe behaviour of the Germans who sank at sight  ships engaged on carrying goods ofBritish origin.
extent the value of this return has been depreciated by the  rashness of the ExportsBoard in granting cereals to Norway, which, as is pointed out, lias enabled  thatcountry to obtain promises of  70,000 tons of grain from the United States  in placeof the 28,000 tons allowed under  the  British rationing scheme,  and this in spite ofthe much vaunted intention of the United States to increase  the stringency of theblockade,  ddie Foreign Office, however, suggests  that much of the damage may be repaired if Navicerts be issued only for the original ration, and this weapon is  in thehands of the British Government, wdio propose to make use of it if the action of the exports Board  in licensing 70,000 tons be recognised as a mistake  and not as a deliberate policy.  Further, over  and above the  rationing of cereals, Norway can alsobe affected by rationing, or even stopping the supply of petroleum, meat, fat, oils  andseeds.  That this latter  weapon  is of  great value  is proved  by Sir  M.  Findlay&apos;despatch, in which he draws attention to the present serious  shortage of lubricantsin Norway, and asks  that arrangements may be made whereby an adequate supplymay.be secured for firms working  on Allied munition, contracts.  - The Minister pointsout that the Norwegian Government, in approaching him on this subject, referred toa possibility that the  shortage might  affect  Great Britain, and this  may mean  thatthe Government intend to requisition  lubricants in the  possession  of the firms inquestion.    Under  the  rationing  scheme which is still in  force  until the expiry of threemonths from 27th September, the  date of the denunciation by the British Governmentof the  Grain,  Flour  and Feeding Stuffs  Agreement, the  Norwegian  grain import requirements are estimated  at 800,000 tons  for the        17-18.  As stocks of185,000 tons were in hand in August last the importation necessary for the rest of theyear is  115,000  tons, consequently the 70,000 tons already granted to Norway is morethan  the allowance required for  the unexpired three months  under the  denouncedAgreement.  This will relieve the  British Government of any obligation, to allowfurther grain supplies into  Norway during the  remainder of the validity of  thatinstrument.  Sir M. Findlay, however, considers  that it would be better to act  uponthe contention  that as Norway is able to export  foodstuffs to Germany it  cannot benecessary for her to  import  so much as  she has hitherto clone.  In any case theproposed action will  inevitably compel the Norwegian  Government  to reduce thesupply  of milk to Great Britain owing to the decrease in production due to absence&apos;of imported fodders and the  increase  in home  consumption due  to the reduction in quantity of imported foodstuffs.    With respect  to the  possibility of  inducing  Norway to  suspend all  exports to enemy countries. Sir M. Findlay reports that a German Press correspondent confessedto a  Norwegian, editor that  the  Germans were  beginning to  realize that Norwaycould not  be expected to submit  to starvation  in order to maintain the privilege ofexporting goods to Germany.    The  British  Government  have  decided to  denounce the  wholesale  GroceFsAgreement and Sir  M.   Findlay has   been  instructed  to  advise  the  NorwegianAssociation accordingly.                                  DENMARK.   The Foreign Office  has informed  Sir  C.  Spring Rice  that  its  policy towardsDenmark is that the Danes should agree  not to  export more than 2,100 tons of fishper month to Crermany, Avhile  continuing to  export,  as  at present, agricultural produce, cryolite,  and  other articles  of importance to  the Allies; that a loan  begranted to  the Allies, and that the export of hides and leather, alive, or manufactured,into Germany be entirely prohibited.   No imports into Denmark of food, fodders, oils,oil seed, or artificial manure to  be permitted so long  as any food, cattle,  or  horsesare being exported into Germany.  In return for this enough petroleum for the fishing industry will be granted to Denmark, and the  import of a ration of other articles willbe permitted.   Air.  Gurney proposes  that  these  articles should comprise limited quantities of raw materials, in order to prevent general unemployment, which  wouldenable Germany to recruit skilled neutral labour, goods which the Central Empirescan still export in order to enable Denmark to evade German demands for compensation,.goods required by firms working for the  Allies, necessaries of life,  and materials-required by Danish public Departments.
   In  view of  tae heavy losses sustained  ivy the Danish egg exporters in  trading with Great Britain this  year, Mr. Gurney has  asked the  Foreign Office  whether their request for the fixture of a minimum price for future shipments of  pickled eggscan be entertained.                                     SPAIN.   Sir A. Hardinge reports that the  German  submarine which put into  Cadiz on 9th September, and was  subsequently interned, escaped to  sea on 6th  October.  Inthe opinion of the  British Consul at that  port, this  was only possible  with theconnivance of the local Spanish authorities, and both Sir A. Hardinge and. the italian ambassador think that the Madrid Government is in no way responsible.   The British and  Italian Ambassadors both sent identic notes asking what stepsthe Spanish  Government propose to  take to vindicate  its neutrality  and obtainsatisfaction for the violation of Spanish law by-the Captain of the interned submarine.   The Spanish Government  ordered a Court of Enquiry to be  held, in  consequence-of which  two Generals commanding  the Arsenal and Dockyard at Cadiz and. other high officials and Engineer officers have been  dismissed, and  orders  have been given that the German submarine interned at Ferrol should be partially dismantled.   Sir A.  Hardinge has been informed  that the Spanish  Government has addressed a vigorous Note to Berlin demanding that the submarine should be returned to Cadiz.   The state  of  siege which was in force  throughout Spain  since  the  August-disturbances was terminated, on 7th October.   Mr. Garnett reports from Tangier  that the Spanish authorities have removed theGerman  Customs employee at Laraiche, and also another German  employee in the harbour  service at  that  port  from  the  positions  they held under   the  SpanishGovernment.   [Vide Report No. 36, page 12.]                                 PORTUGAL.   Senhor  Machado,  the  President of  the Portuguese  Republic,  attended  by his prime Minister and his  Minister for Foreign Affairs left Lisbon on 8th October forhis visit to  the West front.   On  9th  October  the President  was entertained by theKing of Spain at San  Sebastian, and shortly after lunch  left for France by car.President Machado has been received by the President  of the  French Republic nearVerdun and arrangements have been made for  him to meet  the King of the Belgians.The  Portuguese  Government had hoped that it would be possible for His Majesty theKing to receive the President in some  part of the British front, but this could not bedone, consequently President Machado will pay a short visit incognito to  the Portuguesetroops training in  England and will then be received by His Majesty.   The Foreign Office has invited the co-operation of Portugal in the Allied embargoagainst the Netherlands and the Scandinavian States.   Sir L. Carnegie has  been, instructed to approach the Portuguese Government witha view  to increasing  the  efficiency of the censorship of the line  of  communication between Europe and South America by the employment of British and  French censorsin Lisbon and the Azores,  a step to which the Government is at present opposed.                                    CHINA.    Sir C. Greene has been informed in Tokyo that according to a report sent hy the-Japanese Minister in Peking of  a confidential  interview with the  Chinese PrimeMinister,  Tuan, the  situation in  China was favourable for the time  being.   ThePresident of  the Chinese Republic  and the Prime Minister are  working in harmony.as to the appointment of Governors in the south and other political appointments.                                     JAPAN.    The Japanese Government has notified  its inability to comply with the  request ofthe  British Government  for  the  sale of  two battle  cruisers  (vide  Report  No. 34,,page 12) to be added to the British Navy.
   The Japanese Minister for Foreign  Affairs  in  conversation  with Sir  C. Greenestated that he had every reason to hope that Viscount  Ishii had come to an under-standing with the United States on the  subject&apos;of securing American recognition ofthe special situation of Japan with  regard  to  China.  It  is hoped that the under-standing will be embodied, in Notes to be  exchanged between the two governments and subsequently communicated to Great Britain before being made public.   The Japanese Mission found a very different  atmosphere in the United States from what had been  expected, and  the  favourable reception is recognised as having been due partly to the entry of the United States iuto  the war.   The  Foreign Ministerbelieves that the rapprochement  between Japan and the United States will have asteadying effect on Chinese party politics, as the various  leaders will soon realise thatthere is nothing to be gained by further  attempts to play off one Power against theother.                                 ARGENTINA.   Sir R, Tower reports that the general.railway strike throughout  the  ArgentineRepublic has caused much  unrest, and the Foreign. Office has requested that adequate protection might be  assured  to the premises of the various meat  companies whichare engaged on British or Allied Army contract work.   This action had already  been anticipated by that of the American Minister in Buenos Aires.  . Sir R. Tower understands that the Germanophiles are  uniting with the politicalsupporters  of President  Irigoyeii to  convert  the .Columbus Day celebrations  on12th October into a great anti-Ally demonstration in favour of Spain.   In view of theexistence of a general railway strike and  of  the  disturbed condition  of the country the Ministers of  Finance, Marine,  and Agriculture are urging the President to forbidthe celebration,  and unless this be&apos; done  Sir  R. To\yer and   the other allied representatives  are of the opinion that trouble will ensue.   The Foreign Office, in addition to the  remarks  made last, week on the proposedexport duties (vide Report No. 36, page 13), has now directed Sir R. Tower to pointout to the Argentine Government that the proposed tax on  steamers will inequitablyaffect Great Britain.    With regard to the American  suggestion that the purchase of the Argentine wheatcrop should be  limited,  the Foreign Office, supported  by the Wheat  Commission, is anxious that the Allies should control  all  Argentine food  grains,  even if the wholecrop be not immediately required, and has instructed Sir C. Spring Rice to advise theUnited States Export Board accordingly.    According to a Press report  Count  Lux burg has left  the  Argentine on board aSpanish ship,  and  presumably  without  a safe conduct,  as  the grant  of  such  a document was made conditional upon the  ex-German Minister^ journey being direct to a neutral country contiguous with Germany (vide Report No. 35, page 13).                                  URUGUAY.   ddie Uruguayan Government, fortified, by  a favourable  vote  of the  general assembly of Parliament, broke off diplomatic and commercial relations with germany on 7th October.   No specific reason for this was given, but  the Minister for ForeignAffairs has intimated  that tire neutrality decrees in favour  of  Great Britain, france or Italy will not  be  repealed until  the  signature of the Arbitration Treaty.  Mr.Michel! Lines had pointed  out that the Minister had  agreed  to accept French  andBritish signatures alone to the Arbitration Treaty as sufficient  justification to inducehim to ask Parliament to vote a rupture,  but that the Minister  was embarrassed bothby the refusal of Italy to sign the Arbitration. Treaty and by the invitation sent by theArgentine  Government to  attend  a  conference  of  South  and  Central american republics for the purpose of exerting pressure on the belligerent Powers in favourof peace.   The present action in declaring a  rupture before the signature of the arbitration treaty is  undoubtedly a  friendly action on the part of the Uruguayan Government,and the British Minister  emphasises the intention of that Government  to help  the
Allies  if  we  avoid  as  far as  possible interference  with  Uruguay&apos;s  determination.to defend  its independence  of action, and make allowances for the  existence of anational pride similar to that which we  have already recognised as  influencing ourown Dominions.                                     PERU.    On the motion of  the Minister for Foreign A [fairs the Peruvian Congress in JointSession, on 5th October broke off diplomatic relations with Germany by 105 votes to 6.    Mr. Ronnie reports that the President of the Peruvian Republic informed him thatthe reasons for the diplomatic rupture with. Germany were two in number ; one wasthe procrastination of the German Foreign Office with regard to the Peruvian repre-sentations in the &quot;Lot-ton &quot; case.  The other was the  action of  the German minister in Lima in giving  secret orders for the disablement of  the German  ships lying  inPeruvian harbours (vide Report No. 36, p. 16) while engaged, in  negotiations for theirtransfer from the German to the Peruvian flag.    Idle President,  offered  the  hospitality of Peruvian  ports to His Majesty&apos;s ships ofwar, and stated that they might remain in harbour as long as they liked.  The BritishGovernment have expressed  their appreciation  of, and warm  thanks for,  this offer,which is interpreted as a token of  sympathy for the Allied, cause.   /The Peruvian Government have asked for a  safe conduct on behalf of the outgoingGerman Minister  who  was presented with  his  passports at noon, on  8th October.Mr. Rennie urges that he should not he allowed to go  by ship touching at Guayaquilas the Ecuadorean Minister has explained, unofficially, that  his Government would bemuch embarrassed if the German ex-Minister appeared, in Ecuador.                                   ECUADOR.   Mr. Jerome advises  the Foreign  Office that  the  Minister  for  Foreign Affairs has intimated to the former  German. Minister to Lima that,  owing  to  the  rupture  of diplomatic relations  between Peru  and.  Germany, he  cannot now be received if he come to Quito, although he be officially accredited as German Minister to Ecuador aswell as to Peru.                                     CHILE.   Sir F.  Stronge has been  informed, that while the  Chilean Government cannotlegally prohibit Count Luxburg from coming to Chile they are anxious to prevent it,and have caused a hint to that effect to be conveyed to him.                                    MEXICO.   The Foreign Office agrees that pressure must be applied to induce British subjects in Mexico  to  come forward for  military service.  Owing, however, to the nationalvalue of  the  employment of Messrs. PearsoiFs staff in the oil industry, none of  them will be accepted for service.   Mr. Cummins understands that the Tampion  strike is less formidable than was at.first feared, and that it is unlikely to last long.   Lord Bertie reports that the Mexican Minister in Paris  has got into touch with aBritish  subject  named William.  Fresco with a view to inducing the latter  to proceedto Mexico for the purpose of establishing munition works  and a machine-gun factory in Mexico.  Mr. Fresco would  have to become a naturalised Mexican and recruitskilled workmen in France  and Great Britain,  but  not the United States.   He has asked, the Ambassador what attitude lie should adopt;
                                     CUBA.    The President of the Cuban Republic has informed Mr. Leech that while no proofsPad as yet been forthcoming he had suspicions that the strike of sugar-mill operativesin the Santa Clara Province had been  caused by Germans.   A  number of agitatorswith Spanish passports have been arrested and will  be expelled from the Republic,and investigations are being carried out.  Tire  President  considers that he  now hascontrol of the situation.                                 COSTA RICA.   The Minister of Costa Rica -in Paris Iras  informed Lord  Bertie, there being noCosta Rican  representative  in London, that the French Government  have asked.whether  the  United States  have any  objection  to  the  recognition of  the  present government  in Costa  Rica,   If the . United States  are  willing to do so, France alsowill recognise President Tinoco, and the Minister has asked that Great  Britain willinstruct  Sir C. Spring Pice  in  a similar  sense.  It should  be remembered  that president Tinoco&apos;s Government  broke  off diplomatic relations with  Germany  inSeptember (vide Report No. 35, p. .14).                              UNITED STATES.   Sir C. Spring Rice reports that the new regulations enforced by the United StatesExports Board with regard to the granting of  bunkers to neutral vessels are actuatedsolely by the desire of the Board to prevent goods  from reaching Germany.   Thus, a neutral ship may carry a neutral cargo to a neutral state contiguous with Germany.Hitherto there has been no direct control  over this.  Now, however, that neutral, if ittouches at an United States port on  its  homeward voyage, will be refused bunkersunless it agree in future also to touch at an United States port on the outwardvoyage as well, when her cargo must be  approved by the Exports Board if destined for a &quot; Border Neutral&quot; before she is given bunkers to proceed.                            SHIPPING SITUATION.   According to  the  War Trade Intelligence Report, the total tonnage  of  500 tonsgross in the case of steamers and 100 tons gross in the case.of sailing ships, reported lost owing  to the malice of the King&apos;s enemies during the period 28th September to4th October inclusive is 66,474 tons, of wdiich 44,180 tons were British,  as comparedwdth 54,3.10 tons, of wdiich 2S,298 tons were British, reported  last week.   The  lossesshown in the five  weekly returns covering September amount to 396,009 tons, ofwdiich 249,139 were British, as  against 542,000 tons, of which 365,450 were British,fov the five weeks covering August.  Against these  figures may be reckoned the factthat, according to the  Returns of the Ministry of Shipping, newly-constructed steamers,built either at home or abroad, have been  brought into  the Merchant  Service  underthe British flag to the number of 22 of 106,300  tons for August, and 18 of 88,370 tons for September.   ddie British  Government have informed Sir C. Spring Rice that they have  noobjection to the purchase of Austrian ships in Spanish ports by an American syndicate,provided that the ships, when  bought, be controlled  and run  by the United  StatesShipping Board  and that the purchase money,  against which no third party claim isto be made, be impounded  and  retained by the United States authorities until afterthe war.   Sir L. Carnegie is informed that the British Government accepts the proposals made by the  Portuguese Government for the  employment  of  ex^enemy  ships  in portuguese ports [vide Report No. 36, p. 10), and trusts that  they will  be  put into service as soon as possible.
   The British Government has approved of the proposed purchase by the Committeefor the Belief of Belgium in the United States of three German ships in Chile and one in the American. Virgin Islands  (formerly Danish West Indies).  The  proposal  hasthe support of the United States Government.   The conditions of the British approvalare that the ships, if not required at any time for the service  of Belgian relief,  willengage in  Allied European  trade  from  the United States, and  that they  shall bebrought into account as regards distribution of  tonnage  if  at any  time enemy ships in South American ports be bought on behalf of the Allies jointly.    Great Britain has agreed to the proposed division of  the Siamese  ex-enemy shipsproposed  by the United States, in virtue of  which Japan gets one-quarter.   TheFrench and American Minister in Tokyo are supporting Sir 0.  Greene in his request that this share  will, be used in trade with the European  Allies.    Sir  C.  Spring Bice has  been advised that Great  Britain cannot agree  to  theproposed participation of Japan in any share of  ex-enemy ships in South Americanports, nor can any division into six  equal shares be accepted now  with regard  eitherto the  Chinese  or the Siamese ex-enemy ships.    Mr. Michel! Lines has been informed of the willingness  of the British Governmentto purchase the eight ex-enemy ships in Uruguay, the gross tonnage of which  amountsto 42.658 tons,  for  2,000,0001. payable  in London, but  the Uruguayan Governmentappear unwilling to part with what they consider  to be a valuable lever with which to  obtain  the  signature  of  the Arbitration Treaty  by Italy.  At  present  the  bestproposal which lias emanated from  Monte Video  as  to their disposal  is that  fourbottoms should be used in  the direct European trade, two in the direct American trade,and two  in  trade with Europe  by way of  New York.   A. Bill  has  been introducedempowering the Government to requisition the  ships and  form a native company to run them.  The Italian Government has  been  informed by Great Britain, that Italycannot expect to obtain any share in  these ex-enemy ships unless  she is prepared to sign the Arbitration Treaty.    Sir M. Findlay is advised that Norwegian ships built in Holland will  be treated asDutch ships while under bond to the Netherlands  Government.   Afterwards, if  they come under  bond  to  the  German  Government (not to  be used for  Allied purposesduring the war) they will be allowed to carry necessaries to Norway.    Sir A. Peel learns that the Commercial  and  Navigation Company, trading underthe Brazilian  flag (vide Report No. 33, p. 18), declines to sell its  ships,  and statesthat with  regard to its charter it is bound to do nothing  by agreement with  theUnited States Government until a counter proposal to its offer to  charter its ships atthe rate of 120,000L per month be made by that Government.                            PEACE  DISCUSSIONS.   Sir H, Rumbold on  finding  that the enemy  delegates to the Berne  Conference(vide  Reports  No.  35,  p.  17,  and.  No.  36,  p.  18) are mostly &quot; approved &quot; andpatriotic Trades Unionists, and  that even  among the neutral delegates there is onlyone Zimmerwaldian, inclines to the opinion that only Ihades  Union matters will after all be discussed.   The International Peace Congress which is to follow the Trades Union Conferencein Berne on 15th October  will  be attended,  according to  present arrangements,  byHerren Erzberger, Gothein, Dernburg, and Bernstein.   A certain number of Austrian.pacifist priests have also been furnished with passports.   Idie French and Italian Governments have been notified that Great Britain hasdecided to refuse passports to British subjects wishing to attend this Congress.   A Hamburg merchant  criticises the Erzberger peace proposals as a &quot; renunciation of victory,&quot; and considers that  such a peace would  involve the abandonment of theeconomic struggle with  Great  Britain.  He  emphasises the  comparison between themilitary position of Germany, however brilliant that may be, and the gloomy economicfuture of that Empire owing to the  destruction of German world commerce, shipping,and Colonies as part of  the British war aims.  He dreads a future economic war asbeing certain to stifle German overseas trade and her internal industries, and assertsthat the only hope for Germany  now lies  in the utter defeat of Great Britain, as thatalone will induce the British, to  abandon their schemes for the commercial exclusion of Germany.   He points out that  this last hope  will be thrown away if the Majority
Group are able to bring about a peace of renunciation, and calls for more furious and less  restricted  warfare.  A. mediatised  Prince also attacks  the  idea  of  a  peace by-renunciation, drawing a gloomy picture  of  the present  and future economic positionof Germany in comparison with her  neighbours, and pointing out that  the Empire-will  be unable to make both ends meet without a war indemnity.   On the other hand,the &quot; Vorwaerts,&quot; while asserting that German Social.Democrats desire to see Belgiumfree  in any circumstances, asks that they may be assured that the path to peace runsthrough  a free  Belgium, as German public  opinion at  large fears lest a Germandeclaration of willingness to  renounce Belgium would  be interpreted, solely as a  sign of military inability to hold it any longer.   Mr. Maxse, in a private  letter to Mr. Campbell from Rotterdam, reports that he hasinformation that the Germans are more war-weary than is generally thought and  thatthey are  putting up a great peace bluff  in  hopes of making pacifist trouble with the masses in one or more of  the Allied countries and, with a  view to sowing  troubleamong the Entente, are talking loudly of  British prowess and decrying  the acbieve-ments of the other Allies.  He suggests that the appointment of Herr von Kuhlmannto his present position is due to a desire  on the part of the Falser  to  reverse thepolicy of  unrestricted submarine warfare,  and  make use of him, as having been consistently opposed  to  that policy, in  that  direction.   Mr.  Cremer, a former  DutchCabinet Minister, informed Mr.  Maxse in conversation that German financial interests are relying upon the assistance of Germanophils in. (treat Britain to produce a strongpeace movement as the result of wdiich they -would, before the end of this  year, obtainfavourable terms  by negotiation, and thus retrieve  the  fortune of the Avar wdiich theyconsider to have been lost in  the field.  Mr. Cremer&apos;s own opinion, however,  is  thatthe Germans  arc hard hit and. are now merely trying to see who will hold out iongestand stand the financial strain best.   Lord Bertie lias been assured  that no proposals for a separate p)eace with Francehave been put forward, by any reputable agent of Germany.   Sir W. Townley understands that the German Reichstag will again  debate  on theGerman reply to the Papal  Note.                                   GENERAL.    The  Foreign.  Office  have  made enquiries as  to  the new wireless station  at Willemstadt on the island of Curacoa in the Dutch West Indies, which is reported to be in communication with  Nauen, near Berlin.   At the same time, Sir E. Howard draws attention to the completion of another new Avireless station of  great power at Karlsborg, in Sweden, which has a radius of over  3,000 miles.    The British Government has  declined to  send a representative to the Red Cross Conference at Copenhagen (vide Report No. 35,  page  18) where Allied and  enemy,delegates are  to meet.    Sir W. Townley has  been instructed to  find out through the Dutch Government whether the Porte wdll consent to  a Conference  on the subject of the  exchange of prisoners (vide Report No.  36, page  18).  The Porte has, indeed, suggested that its representatives at the proposed Conference should be Mahmud  Mukhtar Pasha and Senator Bosdani Effendi, but so  far  has gone no further,  ddie Ottoman, excuse for the delay is that their Government is engaged in studying the articles of the Hague Agreement concerning prisoners of war,  an agreement of   which the Porte  is  a signatory.    Sir W. Townley learns that the Porte, on the  pretext that a reprisal is necessary, has limited the amount of correspondence for prisoners  of Avar  to four lines of writing per letter or card.    The Prussian War Office has advised the Netherlands Minister in Berlin that  ail. British prisoners of Avar  have HOAV been transferred  from Ronnenburg to  another camp.

</content>
</cab>
