<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/22/0 images: 26-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINET 41  (20).CONCLUSIONS cf a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10, Downing Street 8.W.,. on Tuesday,July 20th 1920 at 11-50 a,m0-1PRESENTsTHE PRIME MINISTER    (in the Chair)be Lite Eon, JUBonar Law, M.Pord Privy Seal. ^he  -m -iiancelloyRon. A, Chamberlain, M*P.,he XV.;., Ron,  nhe Burl Curjson of sales ton, EG, ,G-C S-I- ,gas,I.3.,ecrct&amp;ry of State for Poro^gnffairs .he At. Hon. W. 8 * Ghurc hill s ii.P.,secretary of State for War &amp; Air.&apos;he Rt. Hoc C. Ad&amp;ison, map,minister  of Health.he it. Hon. E.A.L.Fisher, Hop.,resident, Board of Education..lhe Rt. Hon. Sir LiWorthingtonIvans, 3art.,K,P.The at. Hon. A. Balfour, O.M. ,H.P..,Lord President of the Council.The Rt. lion, E.Shortt, Z.C.,1Z..P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.The Rt. Hon. E ,3 . Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Rt. Hon. Wo Long. H.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.&apos;The Rt. Ron Sir E. Geddes, G.C.3.,G.B.E., M.P.,: Minister of Transport.The Rt. Hon. T. J. Macnamara, L1.D..,M.P., Minister of Labour.The Rt. Hon. the Lord Lee of fareham.G.3.E.jKiCiS., Minister of Agricultu&quot;and Fisheries.,The following were also present:-.e*-*field-Marshal Sir H;H.Wilson, Mr P0 herr.Bart.,G0c.BoSB.SBQ.; Chief offche Imperial General Staff6Lieutenant-Colonel $i r LLP -A JSanlcey. G-...C. B. .................. .Secretary-.Mr Thomas Jones. ....................... - -Principal. Assistant Secretary,
fglA AND With reference to Cabinet 35 (20), Appendix II, theLAND.Cabinet had before the:., the following documents(i) ^be telegram sent from Spa by the P&quot;imeMinister, with the consent of thf Alliesinviting the Russian Soviet Government tomake an a-mistice with Poland, and propos-ing a Peace Conference to be held in London[jc?. Aonendix I) :(ii) The Agreement signed by M. Grabskt, the acting President of the Council in Poland,tc this policy (See Appendix. 11) :(iii) The Reply of the Russian Soviet Government(Paper CP.-1645)  (See Appendix III) .Prom recent information from the British diplomatic androilitarv &quot;enresentatives in Poland, which was communicatedto the Cabinet/ it was clear that the Polish Army was over-weighted., to a considerable extent demoralised,  and, Inspite cf a rally in patriotic enthusiasm for the defence oftho country, the only real prospect of saving Poland lay inthe acceptance of an armistice by Poland.&quot;Vhile the Cabinet were endeavouring, to elucidate the precise purport of the Russian Soviet&apos;3 reply, it was dis-oovered that two versions of the document were before theCabinet, - -me received by the Foreign Office direct, fromReval, and the second communicated by M* Rlischko, amember of the Soviet&apos;s Trade Mission, who had been 1 eftbehind in London after tl. Krassin&apos;a departure for Russia.On a general review of the problem, it was pointed outthat while Poland had probably brought upon heraelf barpresent desperate situation by ill-advised attacks directlycontrary to the advice of the Allies, nevertheless this did not alter the fact that, if nothing were done, Polishindependence was threatened with extinction.    If she dis-appeared and were absorbed in Soviet Russia, this mightbe a prelude to the union of the latter with the Bolaheviselements in Germany and the postponement of,European peaceIt was generally agreed that in any measures taken inadvising or assisting the Poles, the main consideration
to be kept in mind must be the obtaining of a settled&apos;peace in Purope at the earliest possible moment.With a view to advancing this object, the cabinet agreed -(a) To take note of, and approve, the actionof the Prime Minister in sending a telegram tothe Polish-Government urging them to implement their undertaking to;ly direct to the russian soviet Government for an armistice:(b)general lines of theTo approve tneprepared by the Prime Minister, toto the invitation to make an armistice and General Vrangel, subject towhich were left to the Prime Minister,i dei.it of the Council and the Presidentof education:da-aftrejoxnaerRu3d\a:i replywit a Po&quot; andnsdraining a-to-asens -1.03of thejjoar a(c)(d)To approve the action of the prime Minister inrequesting the Admiralty to delay tho return to thiscountry of M.Krassin and M.liamenexf,  and to ask thePrime Minister to inform the Bussian Lelegation thattheir return was not desirable until H.M.Governmenthad learned the reply of the Russian Government tothe demand, of the Poles for an armistice:That the Prime Minister should send a telegram to M.Millerand, the French president of tho Council,proposing to him the immediate despatch of a jointBritish and Prench Mission to Warsaw to consult withthe polish and other Governments concerned upon theconclusion of the proposed armistice with SovietRussia,  to co-operate with them in the event of thenegotiations for this Armistice breaking down and generally to report upon the situation.     In this telegram the prime Minister should lay stress on thoimportanceMission:of General Peygand being attached to the( e) That the British envoy should be Lord B!Abernon, theBritish Ambassador in Berlin, who should be aceompan-&apos; ied by a military officer to be selectel by the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff, and. that they should leave that night for Paris to confer with MMMllerand.1*(f) That the Prime Minister should telegraph to Lord Derby,arranging with him for Lord LlAbernon to see M.Millerand early on Wednesday afternoon;(g) That,  in the event of a refusal on the part of theBolsheviks to accede to an armistice,  the GermanGovernment should bo pressed to consent to &quot;ike diversion to the Polos of war material duo to be handed over fordestruction under the Treaty of Versailles:(h) That,  In reply to a Question in the House of Commons, the leader of the House should state that the reply of theSoviet Government, received on the previous day, and the-   -It was subsequently decided to ask Sir Maurice Eankeyto accompany Lord I/Abernon.
a new er- of. H i s Ma jo sty&apos; &quot;a G oir e mme ntthereto, would be laid on the table of the Touse in due course,.Whitehall Gardens. S.W.I&apos;*July 20, 192.0.
c OiaiU lit cat 101&apos; british to  soviet g-ov^rkii^^Dated July 11,  19 20..(Approved at Inter-Allied Conference at  Spa on July 10th,  1920.)The British Government notes the acceptance by the russian soviet Government of the principles laid down in its Memorandumof July 1st,  as the basis of an agreement for the resumption oftrade relations and the cessation of mutual hostilities,  and it,therefore,  agrees to  continue the negotiations for a definitetrade agreement as soon as the Russian delegates return.The British Government has a further proposal to make  .The Soviet Government of Russia has repeatedly declared itsanxiety to make peace with all its neighbours.      The BritishGovernment which is no loss anxious to restore peace throughout europe, therefor&quot;-, proposes the following arrangement with thisobject in view.(a)        That an immediate armistice be signed between poland and Soviet Russia whereby hostilities are suspended.    The termsof this armistice should, provide, on the one hand, that thePolish army should immediately withdraw to the lino provisionallylaid. do,,Tn last year by the Peace Conference as the Eastern bound-ary within which Poland was entitled, to establish a Polish admin-istration.      This line runs approximateely as follows:-    Grodno,Valovka, Nemirov, Brest Lit ova&apos;.&apos;,  Borogusk., TTstllug, Bast ofGrubeshob, Erilov, and thence &apos;Test of Rawa Ruska, East of Pry eriys Lto the Carpathians.Lithuanians ^ill run along the- railway running from. Grodno to Vilnaand thence to Dvinsk.      On the other hand the arristic? should pro-vide that the armies of Soviet Russia should stand at  a distance of 50 kilometres to the East of this line.      In Eastern Gcliciaeach a my will stand on the line which they occupy at the date ofthe signature of the armistice.North of Grodne the line which Will be held by the
(b)        That as soon as possible thereafter, a Conferencesitting under the auspices of the Peace Conference shouldassemble in London to be attended by represent atiyes of SovietRussia, Poland, Lithuania, -Latvia,  Finland with the object .of negotiating a final peace between Russia and itsneighbouring states.      Representatives of Eastern Galicia wouldalso be invited to London to  state their  case.For the purpose of this Conference Great Britain nullplace no restriction on the represent at ives which Russiamay nominate, provided they undertake while in Great Britain,not to interfere in the politics or the internal affairs of theBritish Frrpire or to indulge in propaganda.Tho British Government as a separate proposal suggeststhat an armistice should similarly be signed between theforces of Soviet Russia and General Trangel,  on tho  condition that General Trangel&apos; s forces should immediately retire tothe Crimea and that during the armistice, the Isthmus be a neutral zone,  and that General *7r angel should bo  invitedto London to discuss the future of troops under his command and the refugees under his protection but not  as a meimberof the Conference.The British Government would be glad, of an immediatereply to this telegram for the Polish Government has askedfor the intervention of the Allies and if time is lost a situation may develop which will make the conclusion oflasting peace far more difficult  in &quot;astern Furcpe..     Furtherwhile tho British Government has bound itself to give noassistance to Poland for any purpose hostile to Russia and totake no action itself hostile to Russia,  it  is also boundun do r
under the Covenant of the   League of&apos;&quot; Hation-s--to- def ertd-the ..... .integrity and independence of Poland within its legitimateethnographic frontiers.      If,  therefore, Soviet Russiadespite its repeated declarations&apos; accepting the independence of Poland, will not &quot;be  content with the withdrawal of thePolish Armies from Russian soil on the  condition of amutual armistice but  intends to take action hostile to poland in its own territory, the British Government and itsAllies would feel bound, to assist the Polish nation todefend its existence with all the means at their disposal.The Polish Government has declared its willingness to makepeace with Soviet Russia and to initiate negotiations foran armistice on basis of conditions sot out above directlyit is informed that Soviet Russia also agrees.     The BritishGovernment, therefore, would be glad of a definite reply withina week as to whether Soviet Russia, is prepared to accept theaforesaid proposal for putting an end to further unnecessarybloodshed and giving peace to Europe.
AGREE? rEPT SIGFEL BTr H.  GRABSKC.)(approved at Inter-Allied Conference at Spa on July 10th., 1920)The Polish Government  agrees:-(a) To initiate and. sign an immediate armistice on thebasis that the Polish Army retires to and stands on the linefixed &quot;by &quot;the Peace Conference on..December 8,  1919, as the pro-visional boundary of Polish administration and that the Sovietarmies halt  $0 kilometres to the East of this line..    Vilna,however, to be handed over immediately to the Lithuanians,and to be excluded from, the zone to be occupied by the Bol-sheviks during the Armistice.      In the case of Eastern Galicia,the-armies to stand on the line which they have reached onthe date of the Armistice,  each army then to retire ten kilo-metres so as to have a neutral zone.(b) To send plenipotentiaries to a Conference to be held as soon as possible afterwards in London,  to be attended also by delegates from Poland,  Soviet Russia,  Finland, Lithuania,Latvia, and held under the auspices of the Peace Conference,which shall endeavour to make a lasting peace between Russiaand its European neighbours.Representatives of Eastern Galicia will also be sunnon-ed to London to state their case at the Conference.(c) To accept the decision of the Supreme Council as to the lithuanian boundaries, the future of Eastern Galicia,  theTeschon question, and the Treaty to be negotiated between Dan-zig  and Poland.In consideration of Poland agreeing to the above, theBritish Government will -In the event of the Russian armies refusing theArmistice,  and passing the line as above, theAllies wi31 give Poland all the assistance,especially.cia.(IV)  In -war material,  which is possiblecon si at a no with  -die I r own exhaustion and theheavy J Lab&quot;-Litiea they are  carrying elsewhere,to enable the Po.Li.eh people to defend their independence and national existence.Imm e d i at e 1 y mak eRuss ia:a similar proposal to soviet and(Signed)T7.  T.  GRA3SKI.
(Appendix 3)

RUSSIA AND POLAND.

Reply from Moscow.

(Subject to correction).

VERY URGENT. Klisrks?. Delsovpra. London.

Foreign Office, Earl Curzon of Kedleston July 17th.

 The Russian Soviet Government is the more pleased to acknowledge the declaration of the British Government on its desire to contribute to the establishment of general peace in Eastern Europe, as quite recently still at the time when the complications between Russia and Poland were developing which led to the Polish advance against Russia and the Ukraine, the British Government unfortunately did not manifest the same desire on contributing to the cause of Peace in Eastern Europe and as earlier likewise at the time when Soviet Russia was trying to obtain peace with the Border states the British Government did not support the attainment of this aim and when the Esthonian Government in December of last year it received a warning in the name of the Supreme Council. The present change in the attitude of Great Britain in the question of Peace between Soviet Russia and other States is in complete harmony with the wishes of Soviet Russia whose desire to live in peace with all other States to which reference is made in the last communication of the British Government remains firm and unalterable. Regarding Poland likewise in spite of the latters wanton aggression against the Soviet Republic,  Soviet Russia remains as faithful as before to the principles she has proclaimed so often and to her earnest desire of establishing peaceful relations with all peoples. The question,however, of cessation of the armed struggle between Russia and Poland will be unfavourably Influenced by the fact that on the part of the Polish Government there has been no direct declaration to the Soviet Government regarding its wish to conclude peace. Numerous utterances of the Polish People have come to the knowledge of the Soviet Government in which they express themselves in an extremely bitter sense as to the British Government&apos;s political action in this question and information has been likewise published in the Press as to the decision of the Polish Diet to reject the proposal of an
I 1v^pij^td^c^w^ The-Sovi^et^G-ov-erTm^^^ Iifconsider with some caution such proposals so far as they do not come directly from the Government  concerned and as long as thedanger subsists that the attitude of the-Polish Government will not correspond to the declarations of other Governments which speak inits name.      The necessity of a direct  communication from the PolishGovernment to the Soviet Government  in this case is the more urgentas the past attitude of the British Government in the conflict between Poland and Russia can hardly he considered as a reason forassuming the role of mediator between these two Governments.    if at the time when the Polish Republic was preparing its warttonaggression against Russia and the Ukraine the British government not only made no attempts of hindering this aggression but evenleft without any answer the communication of the Soviet Governmentto the Entente Governments in this question and if at the time whenthe Poliuh offensive has had as a result military disaster for Polandthe British Government on the contrary tries to assume the role of mediator in order to suspend the hostilities that have becomeso disastrous for Poland so the position which results for theBritish Government from this line of action is such that it deprivesit of the role of an impartial third party which would alone renderpossible its mediation between the belligerents.    It is necessaryto remind likewise the British Government that it has itself described the state dreated by the adoption by Russia of its Memorandum ofJuly first as a State of Armistice and that it has therefore describeditself in this way as is belligerent waging war against SovietRussia, a fact that   can in no way create a normal basis for the recognition of its role of mediator between Soviet Russia and anotherbelligerent.      Regarding the British Government, the Russian Governmethas in its answer to the Memorandum of July Eirst made an absolutelyconciliatory declaration including tho acceptation of all the denandsof the British Government.    It has thus shown its anxious desireto remove completely all fionolictp and to obtain definite peace withGreat Britain.      It  desires likewise to establish peace with poland and in the- attainment of this aim it  considers direct negotiations
,^th Poland ^rithouV^any-ukomix^^direct negotiations with Great Britain in &quot;its relations withlatter the proposed mediation for the negotiations with Be and asthe reconoiliation with Poland which it earnestly, d&amp;r/r?   can on&amp;be hampered in such a case in view of the subordinate ; vjitionwhich Poland1 s interests and fate in comparison with interestsforeign to Poland are occpytng in the &quot;domain of re&quot; ations betweenSoviet Russia and Third power.     Pith the frankness which canalone completely remove all misunderstandings between two Gdrern-ments the Soviet Government ventures to recall to the BritishGovernment that when one of its members defended in the House ofCommons the help given to denikin and Koltchak he justified this line of action of the Government by tho argument that the struggleof Denikin and Koltchak against the Soviet Government presumablyhelps towards the defence of India and of the British Intenes-tff-in,Asia in general against dangers which allegedly   threaten them*Hot long ago when the Head of the British Government was negotiating&quot;-with the Head of the Russian Trade Delegation regarding resxmrptdbon____of trade relations, he referred to the relations between Russia and-the numerous other States as to. such facts that can have some influ-&apos;ence upon the commercial relations between Russia and GreatBritain.    The Soviet Government is of the opinion that roconcili-ation with Poland can be successfully accomplished only in case thointerests of both parties are taken into consideration seeing &quot;thatthese interests can easily be reconciled and this aim will be ontho contrary extremely hard to attain If those interests are sub-ordinated to the interests, of. a third Power...      The labouring massesoi Russia, desire full and complete reconciliation with poland and in order to attain this aim the Soviet Government considers itnecessary to removo from the action of reconciliation all that doesnot belong to the interests and desires of the two peoples and governments.    In the cause of reconciliation with Poland theSoviet Government finds it necessary to consider besides the interests
and desixes ax^Jae^auasiozk^and desires of the Polish labouring masses and it finds it therefore possible to attain peace with Poland only throughdirect negotiations with Poland.      It must also point out thatit has already obtained without foreign inrri nation completereconciliation with three neighbouring states and that EsthoniabsuA concluded peace with Russia in spite of the warning of the Supreme Council that the Treaty between Russia and Georgiahas been at the moment of the negotiations ations between the head ofthe Russian Trade Delegation and the head of the BritishGovernment a complete surprise for the latter and that theBritish Government was deprived of any information regardingpeace between Russia and Lithuania when in its ultimatum ofJuly 12th it pointed to Lithuania as to one of the borderStates with which Russia has still t o obtain peace.     TheSoviet Government thinks that it can with the same successobtain peace with Poland through direct negotiations as it did with three other neighbouring States.The Soviet G-overnment still considers less admissablethe interference in the cause of peace between Russia and poland of the group of Governments called League of Nationswhose co-van ant/
The Russian Government has never received from ,the so calledLeague of Nations any communication as to its creation andexistence and it has never had the opportunity of adopting a  &apos;-decision about recognition or non-recognition of this Associationof States.     When acquainting itself from unofficial press-sources with the Covenant of the so-called League of nations the Soviet Government could not leave unnoticed the fact that according to Article seventeen the non-members in case of con-conflict with members of the  so-called League can be invited tosubmit to its decision as if they w ere members..    The SovietGovernment can in.no way agree that one group of Powers should assume the role of supreme body over all the States of the world and watching over the full invislability Of the sovereign rightsof the Russlan labouring people &apos;. the Soviet Government absolutelyrejects the pretentions of any foreign groups of Powers claimingto assume the role of supreme masters of the fate of other nationsIt absolutely rejects therefore every immixatis&amp;i of this associa-tion in the cause of- peace between Russia and Poland.Direct negotiation with Poland are in full harmony with thewishes of the Soviet Government and it declares therefore that ifthe Polish Government addresses to Russia the proposal of entering into peace negotiations the Soviet Government will not rejectits proposal and will also consider in the most friendly spiritany subsidiary proposal as to an armistice or to some other meansmeant to facilitate peace negotiations the Soviet Governmentexpresses also its willingness to agree to a territorial frontiermore favourable for the Polish people than the frontiers indicated by the Supreme Council in December last and proposed once more,by the British Government In its ultimatum of July 12th.    TheSoviet Government cannot leave without notice the fact that thisfrontier was elaborated by the Supreme Council In some parts underthe pressure of counter revolutionary Russian elements adherentsof the Russian capitalist and landed class and that for exampleas to the region of Kholm the decision Of the Supreme Councilclearly reflected the., influence of these counter revolutionaryelements and followed the races of anti-
&apos;&apos;l - 6 -Polish- T^od-Mcy-crf&quot;Tzrarist and of the Russian-. Imper^lisrt-- c-apdrtalist.class in this question.      .   Soviet Russia is willing in general asto the Peace conditions with Poland to meet.the interests andwishes of the Polish people the more fully the more the Polish-oeonle in its internal life will enter a path creating a solidbasis for real     fraternal relations between the labouring masses of Poland, Russia, Ukraine, Thite Russia, and Lithuania and will createguarantees that Poland ^ill cease to be an instrument of aggression and intrigues against the workers and peasants of Soviet Russia andof other countries.As a separate proposal the British Government has put forth the idea of an Armistice between Russia and the mutinous exgonera.1wrangcl.    The Soviet Government however oa:not. shut  its eyes uponthe indissoluble connection between the Military Operations of.Wrangel which, were supported by the Pntente Powers and the Polishcampaign against Russia and Ukraine.    This close connection found itsexpression in the negotiations and. the Military Agreement between-Trangel and the representatives of the Polish Government. Wrangelsoffensive which coincided with the advance of the Polish Array in theUkraine was only a subsidiary military manoeuvre aiming at. renderingmore difficult the struggle of the Russian and Ukrainian troopsagainst the Polish aggressor and at facilitating the latters task.,-The Army and Administration of -/range 1 being almost  completely deprivedbf sources of revenue of their own exist alnost entirely with thefinancial help received from some Entente Powers.    His Militaryoperations are carried out exclusively with the help of the &apos;7armaterial sent by these Bowers.      This &apos;7ar Material is brought tohim on British ships or from harbours under British occupation andthe proposal itself regarding Trangcl in the British Ultimatum ofJuly Twelfth in which the British Government decides for Wrangelthat he will come to London for tho discussion of the fate of his troops, shows with complete evidence that he is only a subordinateagent of. the British Government and partly of its Allies.  .  TheSoveit Government in its wish to obtain peace with the BritishGovernment and wishing to meet tho latters desires confirm once
more its will-ingne-ss to guaaantee..p-eri3oniil safety to the mu^ajafiaia.^--ex-General V.:rangel to all the persons belonging- toOixs-Axmy- and tothe refugees under his protection..on the condition of immediate and full capitulation and of surrender to the Soviet authoritiescf all the territory he occupies and of all the v.ar- material,stores buildings, means of Gommunications and so on in his powersn the same terms as it was proposed by the soviet Government withreference to the northern Government of the ex-General Miller.*ne do vi 31 Oov-trraaoht  cannot, ho&apos;7-vnr, &apos; remain indifferent to therepeated attempts of the British Government to transport the CrimeanPeninsula into an inviolable permanent asylum for the rmtiuousGeneral and for other mutineers *?ho in fact are the BritishGovernment&apos;s subordinate agents and thus really to render theCrimean Peninsula a British Dependence.      It  is impossible notto mention that at the time rrher. the Arohanrel and the I&apos;&quot;ourmanskregion &quot;/as in the ropo pnho^riinrt n nosit ion as to Britain, the^xxbian Authorities ruxed there unrestrained ana acted ae theSupreme lower devastating the whole region, wasting its natural resources and exporting to Britain as much as possible its riches*The bearer of the will and the representative of the interestsof the Russian Labouring People the Soviet Government cannot remainindifferent to any violation of its vital interests and of theinviolability of its territory and it protests most strongly against the attempt of Great Britain to annex in fact the CrimeanPeninsula.    It must also be pointed out that the present proposal of the British Government is a violation of its precedent proposalswhich became an obligation after having been adopted by the SovietGovernment regarding cessation of any help and support to the ex-General &quot; rangel.    The Soviet government is therefore of the opinionthat the greatest possible concession on its part a concession Vhic&quot;is the outcome of its anxious desire to come to terms with theBritish Government is its willingness to- agree to the capitulationef the ex-ireneral Ya-angel and cf his troops with the guarantee of their personal safety.The Soviet Government thija&amp;s that the proposal of convocationin London of a /
Conference of representatives of Russia Poland Lithuania Latvia and Finland is the outcome of insufficient information of the British Government as to the relations between the Russian Republic and her neighbours. The Peace Treaty between Russia and Lithuania was signed on July 12th and the negotiations between Russia and Latvia and Russia and Finland are being carried on independently without Foreign interference and their further continuance on the same lines is the best pledge of their successful result.

 Being animated with the most earnest desire of putting an end to all conflicts between Russia and Great Britain and to the struggle between them and to obtain definite peace with Great Britain the Soviet Government rests its hopes upon the Delegation which it sends to London with additional members with the purpose of carrying on negotiations with the British Government on the basis of the British memorandum of July 1st, and of the reply of the Soviet Government of July 7th in order to obtain a full agreement with Great Britain.      This aim will be attained the more successfully if all new and strange elements which can only do harm to the beginning improvement of the relations between Russia and Great Britain are kept aside.

No. 534 Peoples Commissary for Foreign Affairs.

TCHITCHERIN.



2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.

July 19th, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
