<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/99/0 images: 25-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET,COPY NO.CABINET    .25(39).MEETING of the Cabinet held in the PrimeMinister&apos;s Room, House of Commons,on TUESDAY, 25th APRIL, 1939 at 6.0 p.m.PRESENTThe Rto Hon. Neville Chamberlain, LLP.,Prime Minister.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.CS.I. ,G.C.V.O.,O.B.E.,K.C.,M*P., Chancellor ofthe ExchequeroThe Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt,, G.C.S.I.,G.B.li. ,C.M.G. ,M.P. ,Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.(In the Chair).The Right Hon.Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Viscount Halifax, K.G.,G.C.SvI.G.C.I.E., Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs. .The Right Hon.Sir John Anderson, G..C.B.., G.C.S.I.,    Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E. ,K.C.,G.C0I.E0, M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.The Marquis of Zetland,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Secretaryof State for India and Burma.M.P., Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.Admiral of the Fleet the right on. Lord Chatfield, G.C.B.,O.M., K.C.M.G. , CV.0. ,Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G.,D.S.O.,M.C., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C.,M.?.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C, M.P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.E.L. Burgin, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon.W.S. Morrison, M.C.,K.C.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon.L. Hore-Belisha, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.John Colville, M.P., Secretaryof State for Scotland.The Right Hon.The Earl De La Y/arr, presidentof the Board of Education.The Right Hon.Ernest 3rown, M.C, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right.Hon.Sir Reginald Dorman-Smith, M.P.Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.Captain the Right Hon. D.Euan Wallace,M.C., M.P., Minister of Transport.Sir Edward E. Bridges, K.C.B., M.C,Secretary.
a, r*CABINET      25 (39).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held on tuesday,  25th APRIL,  1939, at 6.0 p.m.CONTENTS.conclusion no.. Subject. Page.1. COMPULSORY MILITARY TRAINING. 1.2. CIVIL DEFENCE SERVICES: 18.Agriculture.STATEMENT TO BE MrJJE BY THE PRIMEMINISTER ON WEDNESDAY.  26th APRIL.19.
(TVCOMPULSORY 1. THE PRIME MINISTER referred to theMILITARYTRAINING. Conclusions of the Cabinet Committee which(Previous had been set up to give further considerationReference:Cabinet 22 to the proposals in CP. 91 (39). The Committee&apos;s(39), Con-clusion 3.) Conclusions, which had been circulated to the l  C3&apos;?)&apos;2&apos; 5 Cabinet in CP.94 (39), are appended to these minutes as Annex A.The Prime Minister explained that theCommittee&apos;s main conclusion had been that it v/asundesirable to introduce the Exceptional Powers(Defence) Bill at the present time, and that theproposed Military Training and Reserve and auxiliary forces Bill should be introduced as two separateBills, the first dealing with mobilisation of thereserve and auxiliary forces, and the second with military Training.     These Bills would be introducedtogether.     The former Bill would be proceeded with first and passed through quickly, so as to enablethe essential nudeus of the Air Defence of GreatBritain to be manned forthwith by territorialpersonnel who would be relieved later by reservepersonnel, pending the training of men to beenlisted under the Military Training Bill.     he hoped, however, that the Military Training bill would also be quickly passed into law.     Hesuggested that the Cabinet should deal first withthe main issues dealt with to the Committee1 s Conclusionsbefore considering other points on the draft bills which were dealt with in CP. 95 (39).THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR referred to thesuggestion which had been mooted at the previous meeting of the Cabinet by the Foreign Secretary,that arrangements might be made to call out theTerritorials forthwith ty a declaration of a State-1-
of Emergency,     He pointed out that the Territorialpersonnel of the Anti-aircraft units were men whohad incurred the greatest obligations, since theyhad undertaken to come up when called upon by theSecretary of State before an emergency had been declared.      The pre;..ent proposal, if proceeded with,was equivalent to putting these men into the same position as conscripts.     He was anxious that thepresent measure should pass with the maximum good will,but he was afraid that if the Territorial, personnel of these units were called out without the declarationof a State of Emergency this would give rise to badfeeling.He also explained that he had anotheralternative scheme under consideration, whereby the guns and searchlights would be placed on their war stations and kept there..      Consequently, if anemergency arose the personnel would he required toproceed direct from their homes or places ofbusiness to their war stations instead of having to proceed to drill halls and mobilisation stores.He was certain that this procedure would resultin greatly shortening the period before our groundair defences could be manned.     At the same time,while he was satisfied that the personnel of theTerritorial Anti-aircraft Divisions would come upif called upon, he was afraid that they would come up with ill will unless an emergency was declared.He was, therefore, in favour of adhering to theexisting procedure, and calling out a proportionof the personnel of the Territorial Anti-aircraft units and Reserves by the existing procedure, namely,the declaration of a State of Emergency.     He was sure that if this course were pursued he would securethe maximum of co-operation.
In reply to questions by the Prime Ministerand. the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Secretaryof State for  :ar said that, whatever the procedure adopted, he proposed to call up a proportion ofthe personnel of the Territorial Anti-aircraft units and of the ReservietsoTHE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER said that it seemed to him that in any event it would benecessary to impose this additional burden onthe personnel concerned,.     The point at issue was thus narrowed to one of procedureo     Further, evenif the procedure advocated by the Secretary ofState was adopted, it was fair to point out thatthe declaration of an emergency, in presentcircumstances would be something different from what had been contemplated when the personnel inquestion had undertaken their present obligations.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR thought thatthe fact that the new obligation to be imposedupon Reserve and Auxiliary personnel was for alimited period, would help matters.     He thoughtthat if the personnel in question were in any event to be called upon to come up, the preciseprocedure adopted was not perhaps very material.THE FIRST LORE OF THE ADMIRALTY suggestedthat the question was entirely one of presentation.Provided the right atmosphere was given, the men would come up with good willoTHE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE thoughtthat we were in danger of falling into someinconsistency^      On the one hand we were anxious
not to take steps which would cause alarm in theCity;    on the other hand, unless we   made it clearthat some real degree of danger was apprehendedthe men would not come up willingly.THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER said that he felt the force of the Secretary of State forWar1s contention that it was rather hard to pass legislation which would impose greater ohligationsoil persons who had volunteered to undertake a lesser obligation.      The fact that a MilitaryTraining Bill was to be introduced simultaneouslywould however help matters.      Further he doubted whether there was any special virtue in the use ofthe word &quot;emergency&quot;.     He thought that Clause 10of the Military Training and Mobilisation of theReserve and Auxiliary Forces Bill as at presentdrafted, whereby His Majesty could by Order inCouncil &quot;empower the Defence Ministers to callout the whole or any Class of the xteserves and auxiliary Forces at any time,&quot; should be amended.The power to call up should not be absolute, but might take the form of declaring that the servicesof the Reserve and Auxiliary Forces were urgently required for the service of the country.      Hethought that if the Clause were re-drafted on theselines it would remove a good many of the objections which might otherwise be felt.THE PRIME MINISTER said that his mind hadbeen moving on the same lines.      He suggested thefollowing words:--4-
30&quot;Upon a declaration by the Admiraltyor the Secretary of State respectivelythat a situation exists in which theservices of His Majesty&apos;s Reserve orAuxiliary Forces are urgently requiredby the country,. His Majesty may, byOrder in Council&quot;, etc.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF lancaster said that he had been in consultation with parliamentary Counsel on this point, and he understood that Counsel had it in mind to revise the draft on the lines indicated.     The realproblem before the draftsman was to find words which gave a proper description of the conditionof affairs in which we now lived.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER thought that itwould be necessary to consider whether the condi-tions should be fulfilled before His Majestyapproved the Order in Council or before the defence ministers gave their directions in pursuance thereof.THE LORD CHANCELLOR suggested that this might be done by way of provisoes to the Clause.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR then read aletter which he had received from the Earl ofDerby, to the effect that the calling up of theTerritorial personnel without the declaration ofa state of emergency would constitute a breach of faith which would be resented, and urging theadoption of conscription.     He (the Secretary ofState for War) agreed that the suggestions made forthe re-drafting of the Clause were on the rightlines.
THE SECRETARY.OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs referred to the suggestion which he had made theprevious evening that we should now declare a Stateof Emergency and call up forthwith a proportion of the personnel of the Territorial A.A. Divisions.      Inmaking this suggestion he had been impressed by thepossibility of any serious delay after our weaknessin this respect had been exposed;    and in so doing hehad been mainly concerned with obtaining quick results.Later his attention had &quot;been drawn to the consequences of declaring an emergency as, for example, the possible effect on the City and the inconvenience which wouldresult from our having to inform authorities all overthe world that, although we had declared an emergency,they were not to take the action which they had been instructed to take when that contingency occurredaHe thought that, provided the Reserve and auxiliary forces Bill could be passed in two or three days, thescheme now proposed was the better plan0     He also thought that if the Government were now to have recourse to the procedure of declaring     a state of emergency and were to call out the Territorials thereunder fora period of two or three months in all and if war didnot occur, the Government might then be criticised for having acted unnecessarily in advising the declarationof a state of emergency.     He therefore favoured i the coursenow proposed,THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF defence said that he thought that he and his colleagues were &apos;
a hiperhaps influenced by their share of responsibilityfor not having., up to the present, decided to take action to ensure the continuous manning of our air defences.,     The position was serious.     But werethe steps proposed the only course open to us?He asked hie colleagues to consider an alternative scheme, namely, that all the equipment of the air defence of Great Britain should be placed on the warsites by the Territorial personnel who should thenbe immediately relieved by Army Reservists, whom we had a much stronger moral right to call out.Our ground air defences could then be manned at muchshorter notice     It was true that the Army Reservists.]who would be manning them, would not be efficientanti-aircraft gunners.     He thought, however,that after a comparatively short time theReservists would be able to operate the search-lights successfully.     Further, as every daypassed, the Reservists would become more efficient.If this course was adopted, it would avoid allthe inconveniences of calling out Territorials,who would have to leave their civil occupations.The period of risk to which we would he exposedwould not exceed five or six hours.     He asked what would happen if units of the Territorial A.A.Divisions were now called out and after a monthit became necessary to decide whether further units should be called out to relieve them     would this not be a difficult, decision to take?
THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR explainedthat under this scheme the Territorial personnel would, he felt sure, willingly undertake thetask of placing the equipment on the war sites.They would also he willing to go to the warsites at weekends.     Thereby they would notbe deprived of their livelihoods.Considerable discussion ensued on thisproposal.THE-MXNISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OFDEFENCE explained tiiatTie, thought that the powers in the draft Bill to call out members of the auxiliary Force as well as the Regular Reservists,should be retained, as it might.be. necessary touse these powers during the next six months.The alteration which he proposed only affected the executive use which would be made of those powers in the near future.General agreement was expressed with theview-that it was desirable to include..dn theReserve and Auxiliary Eorce-s-3i.ll power to caUL-out members of the Auxiliary Force, as well as of the Reserve Forces, without the declarationof an emergency.       On the other hand, it was urged that if a proportion of the personnel ofthe Territorial A.A. units were not called out to man the guns., although we should diminish therisk, a substantial risk would still remain.Doubt was expressed whether any value would result
from having Reserve Regular Gunners for the guns.They had not had opportunity for practising firingfrom A.A. guns, since it was obviously impossiblefor them to do this on the war sites. Theview was also expressed that if we were now todecide that it was unnecessary to call out anypart of the Territorial A.A. units, we shouldthereby weaken the grounds of justification for the measure of Military Training.     Thesuggestion that guns should be put on the warsites by Territioials, who would go to the warsites at weekends and whose equipment in themeantime, would be looked after by Reservists,was questioned.      This arrangement would soon be known and the Government would be criticised for having adopted a makeshift and unsatisfactoryarrangement.       The view was also expressed thatour air defences constituted our &quot;Maginot Line&quot;and that all European countries had now mannedtheir &quot;Maginot Lines.&quot;     The need for doing thiswas, in a sense the main justification for thePowers to be proposed in Parliament.,       The view was also advanced that the real facts of theposition were very well appreciated by a largesection of public opinion; that the action proposed would be generally approved; and thatany reluctance on the part of the Territorialpersonnel would be overcome when they realised that the   in convent en ce to ^foich they were being subjected was part of an epoch making changein our military arrangements.
THE CHANCELLOR OP THE DUCHY OP LANCASTERreferred to the proposal in paragraph 10 of CP. 96 (39),that some provision should, if possible, be inserted Inthe Military Training Bill to put an employer under an obligation to reinstate Reservists or members of the auxiliary Forces on completion of their period of service,if called up under the Reserve and Auxiliary Forces Bill.He thought that this proposal would help to ease the....... ....... ,..    ...... , ....      ...        .. ^  ... ... . ...... ....   . ^   . ..... .      .........     ,.....position.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs thought that the two draft Bills taken togetherrepresented a coherent scheme, and that it was likely that a good deal of opposition to the scheme would disappear when its character was properly understood.The Cabinet agreed;(l)    To give general approval to theConclusions of the Cabinet Committee(CP. 94 (39) which are appended as annex A to these Conclusions:(S)    To adhere to the proposal that a proportion of the Territorial anti-aircraft units should be called up, assoon as the Reserve and auxiliary forces Bill had been passed into law.(3)   That the Chiefs of Staff, or theappropriate Sub-Committee of theCommittee of Imperial Defence, shouldbe instructed, as a matter of urgency,to advise as to the provisional schemefor&apos; the Air Defence of Great Britain,which should operate during the interim arrangement nowr proposed, i.e., from thetime when a proportion of the personnel of the Territorial anti-aircraft units are called out, until the date when men called up under the Military TrainingBill have been trained and are availablefor service in the Air Defence of GreatBritain.
THE PRIME MINISTER then invited theChancellor of the   Duchy of Lancaster to expoundto the Cabinet the Conclusions of a Meetingheld that morning (CP.  96 (39)), presided overby Mr.  Morrison, determine the year&apos;s age group to be included in the Military TrainingBill, and other outstanding points in that bill and in the Mobilisation of the Reserve and auxiliary Forces BilloThe Conclusions reached at thisMeeting are appended as Annex B*The following are the main pointsdealt with in discussion:-3(b). Exemptions - Medical Students.,THE MINISTER OP HEALTH said thatat the present time there were 1,800medical students in their last year of training,and he was anxious that their medical studiesshould not be interfered with, as this wouldprobably result in a shortage of doctors in anemergency*THE CHANCELLOR OP THE DUCHY OP lancaster said that he&apos; and his colleagues had realised thatthis point would he strongly emphasised by theMinister of Health.    Nevertheless, he hoped thatit might be possible to deal with the matter by the provisions for the postponement of calling up, rather than to make specificexemptions.    Emphasis was laid on the importanceof not granting exemptions which could be claimed by some classes of the community, butnot by others.
-THE MINISTER OF HEALTH suggestedthat it might he possible to arrange that, inthe case of medical students, training should be rendered in some other form, which would not inany way constitute a soft option.It was agreed that this point should befurther considered.    In this connection, thePrime Minister invited the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster  o take over responsibilityfor arranging the necessary consultations withthe Departments concerned, in connection with thepreparation of the Bills in their final form.-4. Faili-ire to answer the general calling upnotice.THE MINISTER OP LABOUR enquired whetherthe registration of the 20 to 21 year age groupcould be secured by concentrating the censusmachinery on this particular task.THE MINISTER OP HEALTH said that hehad discussed this matter with the Registrar-General, who took the view that to employ themachinery of national registration in order toobtain particulars of a class of some 300,000individuals would be using a steel headed hammerto crack a nut.    He thought that the matter could be dealt with by the machinery of the registers   of Births^    It was agreed thatthis point should be further looked into.
n oa 0THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OP LANCASTERalso explained that concerted efforts might he made in certain areas such as South Vales andGlasgow to organise wholesale evasion of recruitingunder the Act.5.    Machinery for calling up.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancasterexplained that under the War Book arrangementsthese duties would he performed by the Ministry ofNational Service into which the Ministry ofLabour would be merged.-    The Committee had reachedthe conclusion however that it was not necessaryto create a Ministry of National Service for the relatively limited task now in hand^.THE MINISTER OP LABOUR explained that itwas under contemplation that men called up shouldbe asked to attend the Labour Exchanges on aparticular Saturday, when the Exchanges would beemployed for this purpose only.      He welcomed asuggestion made by the Minister of Health thatin suitable cases men should be called&apos; upon toattend, not at the Employment Exchanges, but atthe Town Hall, the work being performed byExchange personnel.7.     The status of men called up under the MilitaryTraining Bill and allocated to the auxiliary forces of the Admiralty and Air Ministry*9.     Conditions of Service during six monthscontinuous training*THE CHANCELLOR OP THE DUCHY OP LANCASTERexplained that the War Office proposed to payment called up under the Military Training Act,a shilling a day as compared with the two shillingsa day paid to regulars and to Territorials when in camp or embodied.     A point which had to be
29settled   was whether persons called up underthe Military Training Bill and allocated to the auxiliary forces of the Admiralty and Air Ministrywere to he allowed to retain the status of volunteers and to he paid as volunteerso     The point was ofsome importance as the Air Ministry were most anxious to maintain the position that their force was primarily a volunteer force.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said thatthis was of great importance.     This was thepractice followed in Germany.THE PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OP TRADE askedwhether it was wise that persons called up -underthe Military Training Bill should he paid lessthan regular soldiers or than Territorials whenembodied.      The result might be to give theconscript army the stigma of an inferior body.In discussion the view was advanced that it was important to keep alive the idea that this was a citizen Army, that the men concerned would forthe most part have volunteered had the Act notbeen passed, but that it was necessary to have some more formal arrangement so as ^0 ensure that every fit man joined.It was agreed these pay questions should befurther discussed with the Treasury.As regards arrangements for dependants, THECHANCELLOR OP THE DUCHY OP LANCASTER explained that,while it was reasonable to take the view that if aman who had volunteered could only receive the pay of his rank under the conditions prescribed in the
regulations, if Parliament compelled the man to undergo six months training, it was necessary tomake arrangements to see that his dependants didnot starveoIt was agreed that this point should he further discussed with the Treasury.THE PRIMS MEOSOER said that he did not think itwould he necessary to make any announcement on this or similar points affecting pay or emoluments onWednesday.      These points could await the introductionof the Bill.8.     Men called up under the Compulsory MilitaryTraining Bill and allocated to the Army.THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR WAR explained thatthe arrangement now contemplated represented a change which had been made as a result of discussions atthe Meeting held the previous evening.     He was anxious to maintain the volunteer character of theTerritorial. Army, and he therefore proposed that,on the completion of their six months training,men should have an option to go into thespecial reserve or into the Territorial Army.Since the period of annual training of thespecial reserve was three weeks as comparedwith two weeks of the Territorial Army, the result would no doubt he. that mos-t-of.....them-would join theTerritorial Army.
The view was generally expressed that itwas desirable, if possible, to insert a provision on -these lines in the Bill, but that the matter presentedconsiderable difficulties.      For example, an employermight take a man back for a week and then give himnotice.      It was difficult to see what sanction couldbe enforced.THE MINISTER OF LABOUR said that his advisersattached considerable importance to this provision,notwithstanding these difficulties.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER    thoughtthat the practicability of this proposal could betterhe appreciated when a draft Clause had been prepared.The suggestion that a man who had an offer of a job shortly before the expiration of his sixmonths&apos;  training might be released earlier, did not meet with approval on the ground that a period of sixmonths&apos; training was too short to be further reduced.It was agreed that this proposal, i.e.reinstatement in civil occupations,should be further considered when adraft Clause had been prepared.(ll)    Application to Ireland.THE CHANCELLOR OF TEE DUCHY OF lancaster said that it had been agreed that the Bill should apply   to Northern Ireland.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR HOME AFFAIRSconcurred in this view.In regard to application to Eire, THESECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION AFFAIRS said that theClause, as at present drafted, provided that no person should be liable to service who was ordinarily resident in any part of His Majesty&apos;s Dominions outside theUnited Kingdom.     The difficulties inherent in
. determining when a person was &quot;ordinarily resident&quot; were well known.     A labourer who came over from Eire toEngland for the harvest was obviously not ordinarily resident in England;    but what was the position of alabourer who came over with a contractor for a job whichlasted two or three years?     He saw no objection,however, to a Clause on the lines proposed.It was agreed that all the Dominions mustbe treated alike in this matter.Requisitioning of Land.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR said that thissubject had not been referred to in the Report, but-he--.,assumed that provision should be made for the inclusionof these powers in the Military Training Bill.This was agreed to.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR undertook to consult with the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s Department in orderthat the powers of requisitioning now proposed should be linked up with the powers of requisitioning required for civil Defence.The Cabinet;(l) approved generally the Conclusions setout in CP. 96 (39) and appended as annex B,  subject to the comments madein discussion:(2) invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster to be responsible for arranging the necessary consultations with theDepartments concerned, in connection withthe preparation of the...Bills in their final form.
a 9CIVIL DEFENCE 2.      THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE and services.--- FISHERIES asked whether it would he possible to agriculture.      take certain steps which would facilitate services which related to Do-fence, hut which were carriedout by Civil Departments,     From this point ofview, he rather regretted the decision not toproceed with the introduction of the ExceptionalPowers (Defence) Bill..    If it was decided thatit would be a good thing that steps should nowbe taken in order to enable a larger area ofland to be ploughed up in the Autumn,  it wouldbe necessary to pass legislation in the nearfuture.    He understood that no parliamentary time was available, but he felt that this wasnot a very satisfactory answer to give for not taking action in this matter at the present time.He asked whether it would not be possible totake powers which would enable us to take such measures as might be necessary to tighten up thewhole range of our defensive preparations,  thosein the Civil as well as in the Military sphere.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he did not see how action on the lines proposed could betaken in connection with either of the twoBills now under discussion: nor,  indeed, didhe think that such action could have been taken under the Exceptional Powers (Defence) Bill.
STATEMENT TO-BE MADE BY THEPRIME minister on WEDNESDAY,26 th APRIL-.3.      THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR askedwhether the prime Minister proposed to include in his statement on the ensuing day any passage dealing withthe conscription of wealth.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he proposed tosay that it was intended to take steps to control theprofits of firms mainly engaged on the re-armamentprogramme.     As regards wealth during war, he proposed to say that war would not be allowed to beused as an occasion for unreasonable accretions tothe   fortunes of individuals, and thatat the outbreak of war, should war come, steps wouldbe taken to ensure that profiteering which could be identified would be the subject of special penalties.In reply to a question by the President ofthe Board of Education, THE CHANCELLOR OF THE duchy of LANCASTER explained that the draft Bill dealingwith the Ministry of Supply, which had been consideredthat afternoon, contained a Clause giving power to cost contracts.The Cabinet took note of this statement.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.25th April, 1939,
A3TOX, AaConclusions; ^of :a meeting of the Committee on CompulsoryMiljLvia^&quot;Traln3,nF&quot; held on&apos;Monday,&quot;&apos;20th April,  1939.(l) That it was undesirable&quot; to introduce the exceptional Powers (Defence) Bill at thepresent time:(2)    That any emergency powers for requisitioningbuildings, etc., or land, required inconnection with the partial deployment ofA.D0G.B. or the calling up of Reservists,should be included in the proposed MilitaryTraining Bill;(5)    That two separate Bills should be introduceddealing respectively with (a) Mobilisation of reserve and Auxiliary Forces, and (b.) MilitaryTraining, these Bills corresponding toParts II and I of the draft Military training and Reserve Forces Bill;(4)    That each of these Bills should contain a clause to the effect that the Act is tocontinue-in force for three years- providedthat -(a) at any time His Majesty may by Order inCouncil declare that the necessity forthis measure has ceased to exist, whenthe Act would expire except as regardsthings already done under it:(b) after the termination of three years, theAct may be continued from year to yearby means of an affirmative resolution ofboth Houses of parliament:(5)    That the announcement to be made by the PrimeMinister en Wednesday should refer to bothBills;    that both Bills should,  if possible,&apos;be introduced simultaneously, but that every endeavour should be made to secure the passage into law within a few days thereafter of the mobilisation of the Reserve and AuxiliaryForges Bill:(6)   That the Military Training Bill should contain aprovision enabling all British subjects withina single year&apos;s age group to be called up fordraining:    but that consideration should be given,to the inclusion of a provision allowingindividuals to apply to be called up eitherearlier or later than the normal age group:(7)    That the year&apos;s age group to be included in theBill should be determined at a meeting to beheld at Richmond Terrace on Tuesday, the25th April, at 10c45 a.m, of the following ministers j-The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(In the Chair)?The Lord Privy Seal., .The First Lord of the Admiralty,The Secretary of State for War,The Secretary of State for Air,The Minister of Labour,together -with their Advisers and ParliamentaryCounsels
4S(8)    That an endeavour should he made at theabove meeting to settle any other outstanding points on both Bills,particularly the provisions as toexemptions from and for postponements ofmilitary training, with a view to areport on any points of substance beingmade to the Cabinet at the meeting to be.held at 6 p.m.  on Tuesday,  the 25th April:(9)    That the. period of military training to beincluded in the Bill should be six months:(10)    That the Lord Chancellor should be authorisedto speak in confidence to Lord Buckmaster(who has given notice of a Motion on compulsory Military Service for Debate in.the House of Lords on Wednesday, the26th April) with a view to inducing him towithdraw his Motion.
ANNEX 3. zs snj% conclusions OF A MEETING OF MINISTERS HELDON TUESDAY,  25TK APRIL,  1939.MILITARY TRAINING BILL.1)    Age group to be included in the Bill.The best age group to be included in the Bill is20 to 21.      On the whole, this age group is likelyto cause least immediate disturbance, more parti-cularly in regard to the recruitment for the regular forces of the Crown,  the apprentices engaged in munitions production and also in regard to agricultural workers.2)    Inclusion of a Provision allowing individuals toapj^ly to be called up either earlier or later.thanthe normal age group.It would be desirable to include a provision to this effect.     The -provision should be drawn in general terms, so as to give the responsible Minister widediscretion to make regulations to meet difficultieslikely to arise in regard to those industrial under-takings employed on rearmament work which employ alarge number of engineering apprentices.3)   Exemptions.(a) A provision should be included for exemption ofconscientous objectors, subject to persons soexempted undertaking to carry out work of national importance.      The provision of exemption on theselines will necessitate the establishment of tribunals.(b) The question was considered whether it would benecessary to grant exemptions to, for example, medicalstudents.      The importance of not interfering withthe completion of training in these cases wasappreciated, but it was felt that the wisest plan would, be to rely on such cases being dealt with underthe provisions referred to in (2)  above in regard topostponement of calling up.
(4)    Failure to answer the general galling up notice.It should he appreciated&apos; that unless and until some system of National Registration has beenestablished, there will be no machinery to enabledefaulters to be identified and called up fortraining.     For the time being, at any rate, theonly course is to insert in the Bill a generalobligation on persons within the specified age group to come up when called upon, and to rely upon public opinion.     The establishment ofmachinery at a later date would enable defaultersto- be identified.      The point should also be borne in mind that in certain areas there might be anattempt to organise wholesale evasion of theobligations under the Act.(5)    Machinery for calling up.The question was considered whether it would nowbe necessary to establish a separate Ministry ofNational Service charged, with the -duties of calling up persons under the Bill, and of conductingthe Medical Boards and Tribunals.The general view of the Meeting was that itwas most desirable that existing machinery -shouldbe used for this purpose, and that the onlyXavailable machinery was that of the EmploymentExchanges.It was further agreed that the department responsible for the calling up procedure .mustcarry through the subsequent.stages of medical Boards and Tribunals, and that it would,lead to disorganistion if some Ministry, otherthan the Ministry of Labour, were to beauthorised to use the machinery of the Employ-men t Exchanges.o
(6)     Allocation between the three Defence Servicesof men called up under the scheme.The position of the Admiralty and the AiJPMinistry is that they would wish to take a limited number of men of this age group, who are willingto undertake not less than six months&apos;  continuoustraining in their auxiliary forces.The procedure would be that theDepartment responsible for calling up men wouldallocate volunteers for this service in so far asvacancies existed.-(7)     The status of men called up under the MilitaryTraining Bill and allocated to the auxiliary forcesof the Admiralty and Air Ministry.The War Office propose that personscalled up under the Military Training Bill should,during their period of continuous training, receive a lower rate of pay than Regular soldiers andTerritorials.Should the same procedure apply to persons called up under the Military Training bill and allocated to the auxiliary forces of theAdmiralty and Air Ministry?   The point is of some importance, since the Air Ministry, in particular,are anxious to preserve the principle that their forces are manned by volunteers only.It was provisionally agreed that, in orderto retain the status of volunteers (and to receive the sanepay as volunteers)persons called up under the MilitaryTraining Bill and allocated to the auxiliary forcesof the Navy and Royal Air Force must undertake a continuous period of training in excess of sixmonths.    It was agreed, however, that this point might require further investigation.
(8) Men called up under the Compulsory Military Training;Bill and allocated to the Army,The Secretary of State for War said that he proposed that, on completion of the six months&apos;  con-tinuous training, these men should he given an option of joining the Territorial Army or the SupplementaryReserve.    This plan would retain the principle thatthe Territorial Army was a voluntary Force,(9) Conditions of service during the six monthsrcontinuous training.It was suggested that the rate of pay shouldnot he less than l/- a day, and that special arrange-ments would have to he made for dependants and hardcases.    It was desirable that the outline of the, terms proposed should be settled before the announcement was made on Wednesday.    This involves consultation.with the Treasury.(10) Reinstatement in civil occupations *The view was held that it would be^desirable to insert a Clause in the Bill that any employer shouldbe under an obligation to reinstate -(a) a Reservist or member of the auxiliary forces on the completion of his periodof service if called up under the mobilisation of the Reserve and auxiliary Forces Bill;(b) a man on completion of his six months&apos;continuous military training under theMilitary Training Bill;and that if he failed to do so he should be calledupon to show reason.    This would involve the- e-stablishment of some form of Tribunal.(11) Application to Ireland..It was agreed that the Bill should apply to northern Ireland.    In regard to persons of Eire originliving for the time being in this country, it wasdecided to obtain the views of the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs.

</content>
</cab>
