<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/99/0 images: 185-229</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITaNNIC majesty&apos;s GOVERNMENT.)C RET.COPY NO.C A B IN E T    28 (39). JMeeting of the Cabinet to he held, at No.  10, downing street, S.W..-1..-, on WEDNESDAY,  17th MAY, 1939,at 10,30 a.rrioAGENDA,1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS.2.    PALESTINE.(Reference Cabinet 27 (39) Conclusion 7.)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonie&apos;covering final  text, of Command Paper. /CP.  114 (39) - circulated herewith.3-    UNION 0? SOUTH AFRICA:    UNITED KINGDOM TRADENEGOTIATIONSIJ/ITHT        &quot; &apos;    &quot;&quot;&quot;       &apos;    &apos;Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs and the President of the Board of Trade.CP.  113 (39) - circulated herewith.4.    RESERVE AND AUXILIARY FORCES BILL.Action to be taken by the Defence Ministers underthe powers to be conferred by the Rill*(Reference Cabinet 25 (39) Conclusion 2).Statement by the Minister for Co-ordinationof Defence.5.    DEFENCE REGULATIONS:    APPLICATION OF AT THE ONSETOF AN EMERGENCY.   &quot; &quot;      &quot;(Reference Cabinet 23 (39) Conclusion 1).Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence,covering extract from draft Minutes of the 356th Meetingof the Committee of Imperial Defence, together withSeventh Report of a Sub-Committee.CP.  112 (39) - circulated herewith.6.    FLAX.,Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence,covering extract from draft Minutes of the 35Gt.hMeeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence, togetherwith Memorandum by the Chairman of the Supply Board.CP. Ill (39) - circulated herewith.
7.    THE RAILWAYS:    &quot;SQUARE DEAL&quot; PROPOSALS.(Reference Cabinet 18 (39) Conclusion 15).Memorandum by the Minister of Transport.CP. 109 (39) - circulated herewith.8*    CORPORAL PUNISHMENT - (if required).(Reference Cabinet 26 (39) Conclusion 9).9&apos;    AGRICULTURAL POLICY:    BARLEY, OATS AND SHEEP.(Reference Cabinet 8 (39) Conclusion 8 and cabinet 24 (39) Conclusion 9).Joint Memorandum by the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries and the Secretary of State forScotland.CP. 110 (39) - to be circulated.10.      CONCLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.11th Conclusions (39) of Committee of HomeAffairs - to be circulated.(Reference Cabinet^&amp;4 (38) conclusion and cabinet^M(38) Conclusion 8).MemoranduiK^by the Secretary of Statefor Aj^fcovering draft Bill.(b)   Administration of Justice (emergency provisions) &quot;(&quot;Scotland) Bill&quot;(Reference Cabinet 24 (39) Conclusion 8).Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Scotland, Covering draft Bill.H.A.  22 (39) - circulated herewith.(Signed) E.E. BRIDGES.Secretary to the Cabinet.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,,May 12th, 1939.
COPY NO.CABINET 38 (39)..Conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10, Downing   Street, S.W.I., onWednesday, 17th May, 193 9, at 10.30 a.m.PRESENT;The Right Hon. Neville Gharaberlain, M.P.,Prime Minister.- (In the Chair.)The Right Hon..Sir John Simon,o.b.e., K.C., Mthe Exchequer.G.C.S.I., G.C.V.O.,P., Chancellor ofThe Right Hon..Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.,G.B.E., C. M.G., M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir John Anderson, G.C.B.,G.C.S.I.,  G.C.I.E., M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.The MarqUess of Zetland, G.C.SI.,O.C.I.E. , Secretary of Statefor India and Burma.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, G.C.B., O.M.,K.C.M.G., C.V.O., Minister forCo-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G., D.S.O.,M.C., First Lord of the Admiralty,The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Oliver   Stanley, M.C. , M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Health.Right Hon.S.L. Burgin, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon..Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor,The Right Hon.Viscount Halifax, K.G., GJCSXG.C.I.E.,  Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.,Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E., K .M.P., Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon..Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies..The Right Hon..W.S. Morrison, M.C., K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon..L. Hore-Belisha, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.John Colville, M.P., Secretaryof State for Scotland.The Right Hon.The Earl Be La Warr,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M..P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon,.Sir Reginald Dorman-Smith,M.Pa, Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.Captain the Right Hon0Euan Wallace, W.GPg MyP.,Riv, ^ Minister of Transport,,Edward e * Bridges, K.C.B., M.C.,Secretary.
CABINET      28 (59).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldon WEDNESDAY,  17th MAY, 1939, at 10.30 a.m.CONTENTS.conclusion no.._ Subject. Page.1. THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION:Russia. 1.2. THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION (Confd, ):Conversations with Turkey. 8.3- THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION (Confd.):Italian Relations with Prance. 9,4. THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION ( Confd.) :Vatican proposal for a Conference. 10.5. PALESTINE:Draft White Paper. 11.Position of the Mufti and of deportees.        14.6. UNION OP SOUTH AFRICA:United Kingdom Trade Negotiations with. 17.7&apos; RESERVE AND AUXILIARY FORCES BILL:Action to be taken by the defence ministers under the powers to be conferred by the Bill. 21.8. DEFENCE REGULATIONS:Application atvthe Onset of an Emergency.        23.&quot;&apos;9, FLAX. 28.10. MILITARY TRAINING BILL    AND RESERVE and auxiliary FORCES BILL;&quot; 30.Time-table.11- THE RAILWAYS:&quot;Square Deal&quot; Proposals, 31.12. AGRICULTURAL POLICY:Barley, Oats and Sheep. 36.13. ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE (emergency provisions )(SCOTLAND&quot;) BILL.       &apos;&quot; 39.
IE OTHER-SITUATION.RUSSIA.^PreviousinferencesCabinet 27.(59), Con-1 elusion 1),14   THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidthat the Cabinet would have seen telegram No. 95 from our ambassador at Moscow, reporting the Russian Governmentsreply to our proposals.   This reply raised very wideissues, which had been considered at a Meeting of theForeign Policy Committee the previous evening.    Apart fromthe objections which might be felt on general political grounds to a triple alliance between this country, Franceand Russia, there were two particular objections whichhad to be taken into account.    The first was that theRussian proposal ignored the attitude of the four 3alticStates, all of which showed a marked reluctance toreceiving a guarantee from Russia.   Finland, indeed, was unwilling to be guaranteed by any other country, Soo-ond3,y....if we went beyond the scope of our previous proposals,namely, Poland and Roumania, it would be necessary forus to consult the Governments of those countries, andthis would involve considerable delay.The Foreign Secretary said that it was clear thatan agreement should be reached with Russia at theearliest -opportunity.   He thought that the most helpfulline would be to point this out to the Russian Governmentand to press them to come to an agreement which would strengthen our Peace Front with Poland and Roumania withthe minimum of delay.   He thought that there was some prospect that they might be persuaded to agree to thiscourse if, at the same time, we were prepared to give greater precision to the form in which our assistance would be forthcoming.    This would involve staff conversations being held.
The Foreign Secretary reported that Sir robert vansittart had had a two-hours conversation withM. Maisky on the previous day, and that Sir Robertthought that he had persuaded m. Maisky that the fourBaltic States should be left out of the scope of theproposed agreement.   He thought, however, that in orderto secure agreement it would be necessary for us to consent to Staff Conversations taking place.Continuing, the Foreign,Secretary said that hethought the Foreign Policy Committee had been mainlyimpressed by the three following factors:   first, the undesirability of further delay;    secondly, that theywere unwilling to submit in writing a further plan to moscow if that plan was to be rejected;    thirdly, thatthey were unwilling to contemplate a breakdown in thenegotiations.    At the Meeting of the Foreign PolicyCommittee it had been decided to ask Sir robert vansittart to have a further meeting with M. Maisky inorder to see whether it was possible to reach an early agreement with the Russian Government on the basis indicated.    Sir Robert Vansittart would explain thatthe negotiation of any agreement on a wider basis thanthat which we had proposed would involve at least amonth&apos;s further delay.If it was possible to conclude an agreement onthe basis indicated, well and good.    If this proved impossible, we should have to consider whether we wereprepared to accept a wider arrangement with Russia.
The Foreign Secretary concluded by saying thatthe procedure adopted by the Soviet Government inthe last month did not fill him with any confidencesHe felt that they could easily have avoided thedifficulties which had arisen had they been sominded.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOE INDIA, while agreeing that we might have to go some way in order to x^reventa possible agreement between Russia and Germany, saidthat he was impressed with the difficulties whichwe should be laying up for ourselves if we made anagreement on the terms which the Russian government proposed.In reply to a question, THE SECRETARY OF STATEFOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS explained that the RussianGovernments latest proposal amounted to a triplepact between Great Britain, France and Russia, for mutual support if any of the three countries became involved in war with Germany.    It should be observedthat if we were at war with Germany, Russia could onlyafford us help through Poland and Roumania.    On theother hand, if Germany made a direct attack on Russiathrough the Baltic Sea, or through the Baltic States,under the Russian proposal we should be called&apos;uponto go to Russians help.    Generally, the Russianproposal represented a wide departure from our previous plan, which was to afford support for the weakplaces in the front rather than to establish a   system   of   close   alliances.
He also thought that the conclusion of an alliancereminded his colleagues^ in this connection, ofKm Gafencu&apos;s statement that while,, if war was certain,he would favour a close alliance with Russia, so longas there was a five per cent, chance of peace he would avoid such an alliance.In reply to a further quest! oil, the foreign secretary said that he had instructed Sir robert vansittart to sound M. Maisky on the possibility of negotiating an agreement on the lines proposed, inthe form of separate declarations to be signed by each of the Powers concerned.    If, however, this idea was not acceptable, he would propose that asingle document should be prepared to he signed byall three Powers,Asked as to the effect on Spain and Japan Q the signature of an agreement in the terms which we now proposed, the Foreign Secretary said that hethought the effect would be bad, but not catastrophic,Japan would, no doubt, be annoyed;   but he doubted whether Japan&apos;s actual course of action would be greatly affected provided that our agreement withRussia did not extend to the Far Hast,    When thetime came the Japanese Government would do whatsuited them, whatever their commitments.with
Reference was made to the Report prepared bythe Chiefs of Staff which had teen read at the meetingof the Foreign Policy Committee held on the previous evening.In the course of discussion, the MINISTERFOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCE explained that the Chiefs ofStaff had prepared three Reports: the first Report(Paper F.P.  (38)82) had dealt with the military valueof Russia as an ally, and made clear that this value wasnot nearly as great as was commonly supposed, moreespecially from the point of view of the possibility ofRussia undertaking offensive operations.    The second report (Paper CP.  108(39)) dealt with the balance of strategic value in war as between Russia as an ally and spain as an enemy.    The third Report had been prepared ingreat haste the previous day.    The Chiefs of Staff hadbeen shown.the two draft telegrams to our Ambassador at moscow setting out certain proposals.    These proposals were a middle course; they went further than our previoussuggestions, but did not go so far as a complete military alliance.    The Chiefs of Staff had been asked to express their views on the draft telegrams.    The main point oftheir Report was that if we decided to go as far as themiddle course proposed in the draft telegrams, they thought that on the whole it would be advantageous that weshould go somewhat further.    They came to this conclusion on the grounds that a military alliance would involvevery little more in the way of liability than was implied by the proposals in the draft telegram, but would give us a much better assurance of help from Russia than weshould obtain from those proposals.
The Chiefs of Staff were, of course, only       130concerned with the military aspect of this problem.    Ifthey had been present at the meeting ofthe Foreign PolicyCommittee and had heard the arguments there adduced, theymight perhaps, to some extent, have changed their views.Broadly, however, their argument was that, looking at thematter solely from the military point of view, they thought a full alliance with Russia was a better bargainfor us than the via media set out in the draft telegramprepared by the Foreign Office.In reply to further questions, the Ministerfor Co-ordination of Defence said that he thought thatit was true that the Chiefs of Staff thought that thetr&amp;Le,L  m^would. nj&amp;u&amp;L&quot;danger possible Russo-German combination outweighedthe disadvantages which might be expected to result fromthe hostile reactions of Spain, Portugal, Italy, japan and possibly other countries, to an agreement between thiscountry and Russia.In further discussion, the view was expressed that it would be desirable that the Cabinet should seethe Report of the Chiefs of Staff, together with theMinutes of the meeting of the Foreign Policy committee held on the previous evening and the text of the two draft telegrams to Russia.    The view was also expressed thatif negotiations reached a point where it was necessary tocome to a decision on the question whether negotiations should be allowed to break down, or a full military alliance with Russia accepted, the decision on this point should be reserved for the Cabinet.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed to the circulation of the papers in question, and said that it was certainlyhis intention that, if it became necessary to make a choice between these alternatives, a meeting of theCabinet should be held and that there should be full opportunity for discussion.
THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs explained that he was due to leave for Geneva on Saturdayand that time was therefore somewhat short.    It wouldcertainly he necessary to hold another meeting of theForeign Policy Committee before he left for Geneva, andhe asked that members of the Cabinet, after reading the papers to be circulated, should communicate &quot;their views tothe Foreign Secretary as soon as possible, before themeeting of the Foreign Policy Committee was held.This was agreed to.The Cabinet -(l) Took note of the statement made by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs.(S) Authorised the circulation to the cabinet of the draft Minutes of the meeting of theForeign Policy Committee held on Tuesday,16th May, together with the two draft telegrams to Russia and the Report of theChiefs of Staff prepared in connection therewith.(3) Took note that a further meeting of theForeign Policy Committee would he held to discuss the matter in the course of thenext few days, and that members of theCabinet were invited to communicate theirviews to the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs on points dealt with in the papersreferred to in (2) above.
THE INTER-national situation.(Confd)conversations with Turkey.(previous reference:Cabinet 27 (39)Conclusion 4*)2.      THE SECRETARY OF STATE POR FOREIGN affairs said that his colleagues would have seen the telegrams which had passed as to the bilateral agreement with Turkey leading up to the announcementof the declaration on Friday, the 12th May.      steps were now being taken to work out the further measures which should be taken in co-operation with turkey.     It seemed that somewhat desultorydiscussions were also taking place between France and turkey over Hatay.The Foreign Secretary said that he proposed to mention this matter to M. Daladier andM. Bonnet on Saturday next on his way to Geneva.The Cabinet took note of this statement.
THE INTER-national situation(Confd)ItalianRelationswith Prance.(previous references cabinet 27 (39)Conclusion 5*)ITR. 31^)1*-.3e      THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR FOREIGN affairs said that when he saw M. Daladier and M. Bonnet onhis way to Geneva on Saturday, he proposed to speak tothem about Franco-Italian relations.     The view whichhe proposed to put to them was that France was makinga mistake in not being willing to take some advantageof the feelers which were continuously being put out from Rome.     His general opinion was that we had done a great deal for France lately, indeed far more thanFrance had done for us.
THE INTER-national situation(Confd)Vaticanproposal fora Conference.(previous reference:Cabinet 27 (39)Conclusion 3*)U*      In reply to a question from the Presidentof the Board of Trade, THE SECRETARY OP STATE PORFOREIGN AFFAIRS said that this proposal was now in astate of suspended animation^     His attention had been called to a somewhat misleading account which had-appeared on the tape machine the previous day, andwhich put the chief responsibility for rejection ofthe proposal on this country.     Steps had been takento correct this mis-statement.The Cabinet took note of this statement.
PALESTINE. 5.    The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by thepraft White Secretary of State for the Colonies (CP. 114 (39)),Paper-circulating, for the information of his colleagues,(previous reference: the final text of the proposed White Paper on cabinet 27 (39)Conclusion 7.)   Policy in Palestine. R.2-^(3^)5*. THE SECRETARY GP STATE FOR THE COLONIES saidthat the White Paper would be published at 7.0 p.m.that evening, and the present indications were thatit would be criticised from all sides.    In particular,Opposition from the Jews would be very virulent.Dr. Weizmannhad seen the Prime Ministerand had urged   postponement of publication ofthe White Paper.    Later Dr. Weizmann had visited the Colonial Secretary and had urged postponementon him also.    According to Dr. Weizmann, the jews in Palestine would not take ehpmrfcpc action.    Hethought, however, that there would be strikes andpassive resistance, and that the Jews would continueto buy land in the areas where this was prohibited.If the authorities tried to turn them off the land,this would involve the use of force.A telegram had been received from the HighCommissioner in Palestine, which indicated that hethought that there might be acts of violence.    he anticipated however, that these would only besporadic and that the Jews would not organiseresistance on a widespread scale.    The HighCommissioner had also added that, if certain Jews wereuj-zaa Aj^p   L&amp; c*-   /S&quot;to repeat in public the statements which they, made inAt.private, it would be necessary to take drastic actionagainst them.    A telegram had been despatched toI. enquire further what this portended.    The colonial secretary&apos;.s view was that the Jewish leaders should be
allowed to blow off steam provided they did not actually incite others to violence or commit acts of violence themselves.Dr. Weizmann was busily occupied in going- roundand collecting support for the Jewish case.The Colonial Secretary said that two or three days&apos; ago he had seen Lord Samuel, who had taken theview that prohibition of further Jewish immigrationafter five years would be contrary to the balfour declaration.Discussion ensued whether the proposals in theWhite Paper were in accord with the Balfour declaration and the Mandate.THE LORD CHANCWLLOR said that he was clear thatthe proposals were consistent with the balfour declaration, but he felt that there were certain matters which would have to be dealt with at Geneva beforeeffect could be given to them.    He thought that it wasnecessary to distinguish between, (i) matters whichcould be dealt with by administrative action without reference to any other authority, and, (ii) theproposal to set up an independent Palestine State8 whichclearly involved the surrender by this country of theMandate, and which could only be done with the approvalof the Council of the League.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR THE COLONIES agreed thatthis was so, and pointed to the statement in the VifhitePaper which referred to the termination of the Mandate.The procedure which he contemplated was a follows:A statement had been drafted for submission to theCouncil of the League.    It was suggested in thestatement that the Council would not wish to dealwith the matter at once, and might prefer to remit it to
the meeting of tie Permanent Mandates&apos; Commission to beheld in the middle of June.     He thought that therewas a possibility that some of the proposals mightbe challenged on the grounds that they wereinconsistent with the Mandate, and that the Leagueauthorities might ask for the opinion of theHague Court.     He thought, however, that if itwas necessary to obtain such an opinion, a workingarrangement could be devised in the meantime.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he viewed an approach to the Hague Court,with its consequent delays, with some anxiety,and he would much -grefev it if the League ofNations could be induced, either to approve our policy as being consistent with the Mandate, orto say that the Mandate should he modified so asto make it consistent with our policy.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIESagreed with this view, but thought that thpCouncil of the League,/which was much under theinfluence of Zionist opinion, might not beprepared to act without obtaining the opinion ofthe Hague Court.THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER raiseda point on the wording of paragraph 15.     He was afraid that the y/ording which had now been adoptedmight be misinterpreted as meaning that theJewish National Home had not yet been established.
The present wording was:-&quot;... they will not he justified in facilitating, nor will they heunder any obligation to facilitate,the establishment of the JewishNational Home by further immigrationn.....After discussion it was agreedto alter the relevant words of this paragraph to read:-to facilitate the further GOiitensionof the Jewish National Home byimmigration ......&quot;THE SECRETARY OR STATE POR THE COLONIESgave some account of his contacts with the Press.He said that it was clear that the White paper would have a very mixed reception.     He agreed with the suggestion that steps should be takento get into touch with representatives of provincial newspapers.     He was clear that the Jewishside had spared no efforts in their endeavour to influence the Press against oUr proposals.As for the reception of the White paper on the Arab side, his colleagues would have seentelegrams from our representative at Baghdad (No.189)and our Ambassador at Cairo (No. 353), which took a serious view of the answer which it was proposedto give in Parliament as to the position of the mufti,     It was now clear thatj whatever view therepresentatives of the neighbouring Arab states might take about the White Paper, if we made astatement to the effect that the Mufti was to be
indefinitely excluded from Palestine, they wouldnot support the White Paper proposals publicly.On receipt of these telegrams he had telegraphed to the High Commissioner in Palestineexplaining the views held by the Egyptian PrimeMinister on the matter and enquiring whether the HighCommissioner had in any way modified his view that anannouncement in regard to the Mufti was essential.The High Commissioner had replied that he was stillof opinion that it was of the utmost importance thatthis announcement should be made:    if this were not done, it would be held that the Mufti&apos;s terroristicactivities had succeeded.      The Colonial secretary said that he had consulted the Prime Minister andForeign Secretary who had agreed with him thatwege-^a^o043*0.....tha^ axi announcement should be made about the Mufti.     It had been thought, however, thatthe answer agreed at the last Meeting of the cabinet should be strengthened by the inclusion of specificreasons to explain why the Mufti should be excluded.The Colonial Secretary read out the text ofthe draft reply proposed (a copy is attached to these conclusions as Appendix I), which was approved.The Colonial Secretary emphasised theimportance of making it clear that the Mufti was nota national leader, but merely the head of a factionwhose supporters had shot a very large number oftheir fellow Arabs (j3&apos;70 in the last few months) .In conclusion, the Colonial Secretary said it was clear that the policy in the White Paper wouldbe opposed by both sides.     That, however, was perhapssome Indication that it was a just settlement, andhe was satisfied that the policy was one which couldbe defended and to which the approval of parliament could be obtained.
THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR again referredto the Defence considerations involved,,      he asked whether it was intended that our strategic requirements should he expressed even more precisely in a Parliamentary Answer,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE colonies said that it was proposed to deal with thismatter in the course of debate.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that, inthe opinion of the General Staff, it was undesir-able that those who had participated in the rebellion, and had been deported, should beallowed to return before th^y had given an under-taking to co-operate with the Government.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES,referring to the draft reply agreed to at theprerious week&apos;s Meeting of the Cabinet, said thatas soon as peace and order had been sufficientlyrestored, consideration would be given to thepossibility of the early release of a number ofthose who had been interned.      He was unwilling to be more precise on this point.     This viowwas shared by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Cabinet took note of the statement by the Secretary of State for theColonies, and approved the issue ofthe White Paper, subject to the drafting amendment referred toabove.
UNION OF 6. The Cabinet had under consideration a south AFRICA,___ Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State for united Kingdom Dominion Affairs and the President of the Board ofTrade Negotia-tions with.       Trade (CP. 113 (39)) calling attention to a point which had arisen in connection with the negotiationsfor the revision of the Ottawa Agreement with theUnion of South Africa.    After outlining briefly the course of these negotiations since theirinception in 1937, the Memorandum went on to statethat a fortnight ago the Union High Commissionerhad intimated that he had received new instructionsto the effect that &quot;an effective preference&quot; by theUnited Kingdom on fruit must be a &quot;sine qua non&quot;to the renewal of the Ottawa Agreement or of any form of Imperial preference, and that the UnionGovernment must have an immediate assurance thatwe would give such a preference; otherwise, the ottawa Agreement would be denounced.    At a subsequent talk the High Commissioner had pointedout that his Government had in mind chiefly orangesand grapefruit.    By &quot;effective&quot; preference theSouth Africans no doubt meant such a preferenceas would enable them to sell in the UnitedKingdom market at a remunerative price all theoranges; they produced.    As the world productionof oranges was greater than could be soldprofitably, an &quot;effective preference&quot; in the SouthAfrican sense could only mean a prohibitive duty,or quota on foreign oranges,  and there was no possibility that we could agree to this.    TheMinisters felt, however, that it might now bepossible to contemplate some readjustment of theexisting duties on oranges in such a way as to give
the Union a wider margin of preference in the period whichwas of greatest importance to her trade, while compensatingthose foreign countries which would he affected by reducing the duties outside that period.    Such areadjustment of duties would not afford an &quot;effectivepreference&quot;  in the South African sense, and would conflict with our general policy with regard to any increase intariff   barriers.    Protests from the United States ofAmerica and Brazil would no doubt follow, and criticismmight also be caused in this country owing to the fear that prices might be raised and the consumption of citrusfruit restricted:,    Nevertheless,  the Ministers felt itso important not to risk a breakdown of negotiations withthe Union Government at this stage, that they consideredthe possibility of a readjustment of duties on orangesof the kind indicated in their Memorandum should not be ruled out,Affairs had outlined the main points in the Memorandum,the PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OP TRADE said that from theeconomic point of view the concessions were quiteunimportant.    They might, however, raise important political issues and therefore the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and he had thought it right to bringthe matter to the notice of the Cabinet.    The proposal toincrease the preference on South African citrus products .would be felt most by Brazil and the United States.    Theformer would be particular affected since the United Statesdid not normally export citrus products to this countryin considerable quantities, except in years when they hada bumper crop.    Nevertheless,  the proposal to raise therate of duty would certainly not be well received in theAfter the Secretary of State for Dominion
United States.    Further, criticism might he expected athome since the increase in duty could only he effected by special legislation; and an increase in duty would berepresented as undesirable in the case of a fruit whichwas regarded as of great importance from the healthpoint of view.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs asked the President of the Board of Trade to considerthe position of Spain.    He understood that before theSpanish Civil War a third of our oranges had come from spain, and the position of Spanish oranges in relationto the trade of this country might be a powerful factor in any commercial negotiations with that country.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE undertook to look into this point, although he was of the opinion thatthe main volume of our imports of Spanish oranges had ceased before the peak of the South African imports wasreached.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that hewould be glad if the Treasury could be consulted before any specific proposal was made to the South african representatives.The Cabinet agreed:-(l) To authorise the Secretary of State  &quot;--for Dominion Affairs and thePresident of the Board of Tradeto negotiate for the revisionof the Ottawa Agreement with theUnion of South Africa on thebasis that the possibility of are-adjustment of the duties onoranges on the lines indicated intheir Memorandum should not beregarded as excluded.
-(2) That the President of the Board of trade should take into consideration the views expressed by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs regarding imports intothis country of Spanish oranges.(3) That no specific proposals for variation of existing duties should be made to theSouth African representatives without prior consultation with the Treasury.
jytfns. AND-1YCBS BJXJjj, ;tion to been by thefence Ministersder the powersbe conferredthe Bill.eviousferences:binet 23 (39)inclusion 1 andbinet 25 (39)nclusi on 2.)7.      THE MINISTER POR CO-ORDINATION OP defence said that since the Bill had been discussed in its initial stages * the Cabinet as a whole had been given no information on the matter.At the meeting held on the 25th April(Cabinet 23 (39)), the Cabinet had remitted to theappropriate C.I.D. Committee, consideration of theprovisional scheme for the air defence of GreatBritain which should operate from the time when... the personnel of the Territorial. Anti-Aircraft Unitswere called but until the me;,, who were called up underthe-Military Training Bill had been trained?     Thismatter had been duly considered and it had beendecided that the scale of defence should be sufficientto act as a reasonable deterrent and to cover notmerely London but also the big industrial areas.It hadAheen arranged to man about 300 Anti-Aircraft^guns and     1,-000 searchlights together with a proportion of the balloon barrage and Light Anti-Aircraft Units.The total personnel required to man thesedefences was 22,000.     During the next four monthsthese defences would be manned by the TerritorialAnti-Aircraft personnel, units of which would have aimonth&apos;s consecutive training starting on the.11th June,     A quarter of the units would be called out each month.It was hoped that the Military Training and theReserve.,    &amp; &amp; d     . Auxiliary Forces Bills, would receivethe Royal Assent on Friday, 26th May..    It was, however,undesirable to delay giving warning notices as tothe personnel who would be called up until the Bill
had&apos; received the Royal Assent.      It had therefore&quot;been arranged at a Meeting of the Ministers concerned that information as to the dates of calling up shouldbe given in the reply to a Parliamentary Question onthe previous day (Tuesday, l6th May).Most of the Reservists required would becalled up on the 11th or 15th of June.     The first group of men, totalling some 50,000, to be called up under the Military Training Bill would be required toreport to their units about the middle of July.The Cabinet took note of this statement.
DEFENCE 80        The Cabinet, had before them aREGULATIONS.___ Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of application Defence (CP.  112 (59)) covering the Seventhat the Onsetof an Emergency. Report of the War Legislation Sub-Committee(Previous (C.I.D. Paper No.l551-B) concerning the method ofReference:Cabinet 25 application of Defence Regulations, together with .(59), Con-clusion 1.) the relevant extract from the draft Minutes ofEfr^Ctt^q)1 &apos;tiie Meeting of the Committee of ImperialDefence (Minute 4).    The recommendations of theCommittee of Imperial Defence,  to which theMinister invited the approval of his colleagues,were as follows:-&quot;(a) That the. procedure of issuing a short code of Defence Regulations to be followedafter a brief period by the issue of thefull code is impracticable.(b) To recommend to the Cabinet that,   inprinciple:-(i) It is essential that the defence regulations should be made at theonset of an emergency, instead of only on the outbreak of war, as contemplated hitherto,(ii) Subject to further consideration by defence Departments,  the moment atwhich it becomes necessary to orderevacuation should be taken as theonset of an emergency, i.e., thepoint at which Defence regulations would come into force,,(iii) If parliament is sitting,  the procedure to be adopted should be to introduceforthwith the Emergency Powers (Defence)Bill, and simultaneously to issue thefull code of Defence Regulations byOx^der in Council.    Departments would thus be able to operate the defence regulations immediately,  in anticipation of the passing of theEmergency Powers (Defence) Bill.,(iv) If an emergency develops when parliament is not sitting, the full code of defence regulations should bo issued immediately by Order in Council as in (iii) above,the Emergency Powers (Defence) bill being introduced afterwards as soon as parliament had  reassembled.
(v) The exercise of the powers containedin the Defence Regulations in anticipation of the passing of theEmergency Powers (Defence) Bill,as contemplated in (iii) and (iv),should he validated by antedating theBill to the date on which the Regulationsare aade9(vi) The arrangements for the issue of a defence Proclamation,  set out inrecommendations (d),  (e) and (f) ofthe Fourth Report of the War LegislationSub-Committee (C.I.D. Paper No.  1456-B)should apply if the procedure recommended in (iii) and (iv) above is carried out.(vii) The entries in the Government War Bookshould be amended accordingly.&quot;TILE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCE saidthat this matter had been under discussion over aperiod of two years, and that on more than one occasion a decision had been reached that it wasimpractical to introduce the Emergency Powers (Defence)Bill in time of peace.      This decision had been re-affirmed by the Cabinet on the 25th April (Cab, 23 (39),Conclusion l).The War Legislation Committee had endeavoured to solve the matter by the preparation of a short and longcode, but it had been found that the issue of a shortcode before the outbreak of war, followed by the issueof the full code shortly after the outbreak of War,would give rise to insuperable administrative difficulties.      It was also clear that some of thepowers to be granted by the Bill would be required inadvance of the actual.state of war.     In thesecircumstances, the proposal reconuended by the C.I.D.appeared to be the only practicable course.
THE LORD CHANCELLOR expressed great regret thatit should he necessary to authorise the issue of Order-in-Council which would have no legal justification andwould expose the Government of the day to severe criticism if no war should result.     He suggested thata one clause Bill should he passed, conferring on theKing the prerogative right by Order-in-Council totake such steps as might be necessary for the safety of the Realm if the risk of immediate hostilitieswas imminent.     The powers to be conferred by this order-in-Council would be of a temporary nature only,but they would serve to tide over the gap untilParliament could be summoned and the necessary legislation passed.     He was satisfied that such aBill could be passed through the House of Lords, atany rate, without any difficulty.In the course of discussion it was agreed thatthe Lord Chancellor&apos;s suggestion should be examined.At the same time it was felt that there would be difficulties in securing the passing of the Bill onthe lines proposed before the Summer Recess, and inthe meantime it was necessary that a decision should8be reached as to the basis on which action should,proceed, should this prove necessary.      In thisconnection, THE HOME SECRETARY and the LORD PRIVY SEALreferred to the necessity for having Regulationsprinted and stored in suitable locations up and down the country.      It was agreed, therefore, to acceptthe C.I.D.&apos;s recommendations as the basis for action,without prejudice to consideration of the LordChancellor&apos;s suggestion, which it was thought, should be remitted for consideration by the War legislation committee.
THE MINISTER OF HAALTH said that in connectionwith the Civil Defence Bill there was considerable pressure in the House of Commons (from both sides ofthe House) for the inclusion in the Bill of powers which would enable the process of evacuation to be started without waiting for any new powers to be conferred.     He thought that it would be verydifficult to refuse the inclusion of such powers in the Bill.General agreement was expressed with this view,but it was pointed out that there were a number ofother powers which Departments would require toexercise in the event of an emergency before theoutbreak of war, which were not affected by the powers in relation to evacuation, which might be conferred bythe Civil Defence Bill.Reference was made to the question whether thedecision to order evacuation should, be taken as thepoint at which Defence Regulations should come intoforce.     It was explained that the time when evacuationwas ordered had. been thought likely to he an occasionwhen matters would be so critical that it would benecessary to obtain emergency powers.      It had., however^been agreed that this matter should be further considered by the Departments concerned.      In thisconnection, TEE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE saidthat he might require powers in regard, to shipping,even if we were engaged, in war with some distant Power.,in which case evacuation of the Civil population wouldnot arise.
The Cabinet agreed -To approve the recommendations ofthe C.I.D. as set out above, withoutprejudice -(a) to consideration of thesuggestion made by the LordChancellor at &apos;A&apos; above; or(b) to any special legislativeprocedure to deal with evacuationwhich may be decided on during thepassage of the Civil Defence Bill.
9.The Cabinet had under consideration a-Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence(CP. Ill (39)) on the subject of flax, covering aMemorandum by the Chairman of the Supply Board(C.I.D, Paper No. D.P.R. 310) together with the relevantextract from the draft Minutes of the 356th Meeting ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence (Minute 1).     Theconclusions reached by the Committee of Imperial Defencewere as follows:--&quot;(a)   (i)   That the Service Departments should beinvited to consider and to report tothe Committee of Imperial Defence theextent of the reserves of finishedlinen products which they shouldaccumulate forthwith.(ii)   That no approach should be made to theRussian Government with a view to obtaining the reopenxng-of -the export of flax either in peace or war, until deemedopportune by the Board of Trade.(Aii)   That, as a practical step towardsencouragement of the development ofhome-grown flax and of the natural fibre.,process, the Norfolk ExperimentalStation should be taken over by theGovernment at the end of the currentseason.(iv)   That early steps should be taken toacquire all supplies available duringthe 1939 season of pedigree seed.(v)   That a single Controlling GovernmentDepartment is necessary for the developmentof flax production and of processing atthe Norfolk Station.(vi)   That the First Lord of the Admiralty andthe Minister of Supply-designate should discuss and report to the Committee ofImperial Defence whether the Admiraltyor the Ministry of Supply should be the controlling Department.(b)   That the Note by the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster, covering a Memorandum by theChairman of the Supply Board on the subject of flax (C.I.D. Paper No. D.P.R. 310), togetherwith the Minutes of the discussion in theCommittee of Imperial Defence and theconclusions thereon, should be forwarded tothe Cabinet.&quot;
THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCEexplained the main points in the Memorandum.    It was clear that the Service Departments&apos; requirements of flax in time of war could not he met unless special steps were taken to meet the position.    Among the steps to he taken for this purpose were included,first, the development of the natural fibre pro cess.As a. practical step to this end, it was proposed, thatthe Government should take over the Norfolk ^xperi-mental St a Lion.    Secondly, it was proposed that, theGovernment should acquire all available supplies ofpedigree seed during the 193 9 season.   Thirdly, thata, single department should be responsible for thedevelopment o^ flax production and processing at the norfolk Station.    These steps had been agreed withthe Departments  concerned, and the main reason forsubmitting the ratter to the Cabinet was that theproposals in question   although submitted on Defencegrounds   might. perhaps be regarded as somewhatoutside the normal a.ctivi4-ies of the Committee ofImperial defence *The Cabinet approve^ the proposalsof the Committee of Imperial defence as s et out above. -
MILITARYTRAININGBILL, and reserve ANDAUXILIARYFORCES BILL.Time-Table,(previous reference:Cabinet^, it10. THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was essential that both these Bills should receivethe Royal Assent before the Whitsuntide Adjournment.Any amendments to these Bills made in the House ofLords would not reach the House of Commons untilThursday, 25th May, i.e., the day before the Billswere due to receive the Royal Assent,      It wastherefore desirable that there should be as fewLord&apos;s amendments as possible.     He asked hiscolleagues in the Upper House to endeavour tosecure this0The Cabinet took note ofthis statement.I
THE RAILWAYS.&quot;Square Deal&quot;Proposals.(previous reference:Cabinet 18(39), Con-clusion 15)..   11.        In pursuance of the conclusion mentionedin the margin, the Cabinet had before them aMemorandum by the Minister of Transport (CP. 109(39)), to which was attached a proof copy of theReport by the Transport Advisory Council on theproposals of the Main Line Railway Companies forthe repeal of. the existing statutory control of charges for the conveyance of merchandise by rail.It was pointed out that although therecommendations in this Report, which were based ona series of agreements between the interested parties, had the appearance of unanimity, a close examination revealed reservations of considerable importance, but that, nevertheless, the large measure of agreement reached was a notableachievement and presumptive evidence of the soundness of the Report.The Council had re-affirmed their belief in the co-ordination of transport to avoid unnecessary overlapping of services and uneconomiccompetition, and emphasised that their proposals were of a temporary nature only and intended tocover a period of not more than five years,during which they hoped that a reasonable degreeof co-ordination might be attained through the setting up of a road rate structure.    The minister stated,that he would no doubt be pressed at anearly date to say what steps he intended to take to (ensure that a system of reasonable and ;correlated rates was applicable to all forms oftransport, and that he proposed to reply that,with the assistance of the Transport AdvisoryCouncil, he would watch developments which might
be expected as a result of the Council&apos;s two reports and the agreements now recorded, and take such action as those developments might show to be desirable.The Minister suggested that the proposals in the Council&apos;s Report should be accepted on the groundthat, together with the Road and Rail Agreement(Appendix VI to the Report), they seemed likely to clear the ground for the erection of a road ratestructure, correlated with rail, and to be of benefit inthe long run to all sections of the community.    Theproposals in the Report might be summarised as follows:-(i) that the present system of control of railway freight charges should be abandoned;(ii) that, subject to certain safeguards, the railway- companies should be entitled to make suchreasonable charges as they think fit;(iii) that the safeguards for trade and industry should be -(a) periodic Conferences on a voluntary basis;(b) no existing railway charges to be increasedsave by agreement (by the appropriateConference in the case of a general increase or by the traders concerned inthe case of an individual increase) orby the authority of the Railway rates tribunal;(c) a right of appeal to the Tribunal as to the reasonableness of any railway charge;(iv) that the safeguards for other forms of transport should be -(a) periodic Conferences on a voluntary basis;(b) agreement as to rates with the road haulageinterests, subject to the provisions of(iii)(b) above;(c) certain specific provisions to preventunfair competition.It was not suggested that the legislation tog ive effect to these proposals would be non-controversial,for, while the main principles might be accepted fairlyreadily, there was likely to be considerable difference
of opinion regarding the detailed provisions, andparticularly those matters on which the transport advisory Council had been unable to reach agreement.In view of the urgency and the complexity of thequestion, however, the Minister proposed:-(a) that the necessary authority anddirections should be given for thepreparation of a Bill to be introduced at the beginning of the next Session^(b) that he should be authorised to announceat once that the Government acceptedthe Report in broad principle, andthat while the specific proposals for changes in the law would require careful examination and consideration,it was intended to introduceappropriate legislation as soonas possible.On the question of the suggestions made to theCouncil for a relaxation of the licensing system forroad goods vehicles, the Minister proposed, as andwhen it became necessary, to indicate that theGovernment was not prepared in present circumstances to set aside the broad decision of policy embodied in the Road and Rail Traffic Act, 1933, but that hewould be ready to discuss proposals for the amendmentof that Act when the road haulage industry had achieved a greater measure of success in the task of putting its house in order.THE MINISTER OR TRANSPORT said that the Reportof the Committee went a good deal further than had
&quot;been originally contemplated.     The Railway companies had considerably modified their demands and had givenimportant safeguards.      It might be asked how therailways thought that they would benefit from theseproposals.He had seen the^ General Managers of therailways, and they had cxprooood themselves aooatiofiodu-5**e^set a^good deal of store on thefact that good feeling had now been, established betweenthe railways and their competitors on the roads, andteey hoped that this might prove the foundation fora better system of co-operation., t    He (the Minister)had explained to the Railway   aa^g^as that there was no chance of a Bill being passed into law before the endof July;    but he gathered that they acquiesced in thiscourse.The Report of the Transport Advisory council was unanimous.     He thought, therefore, that theGovernment were bound to adopt the Report and to base legislation upon it, failing some/good reasonto the contrary.      Close examination of the Reportshowed, however, that the degree of unanimity was not so great as appeared at first sights     There were anumber of reservations, and certain points werequietly ignored.     Broadly,  our main difficulties were involved.     First, that the traders weresuspicious of any real degree of co-operationbetween the railways and road transport.     Secondly,the attitude of the Mining Association, who hadnot reached agreement with the railway representatives.Thirdly,  that the Scottish users of mechanically-    *propelled vehicles had iwadu-tPiu1 Ouiu Twurvufliw^; /
Fourthly, there was the question of the publicationof rates.     The Minister said that his advisers were satisfied that it was essential to insist uponpublication of rates, notwithstanding the fact thatthis course would be opposed by the Railway Companies,It was proposed that the Bill should be for aperiod of five years, and it was hoped that road transport would, within that period, have developed a proper rate structure.The Minister said that if the Cabinet gave him the authority asked for in paragraph 38 of his memorandum, he would propose to consult with theinterests concerned and to arrange for the drafting of the Bill to proceed during the Recess.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO supported theMinister of Transport&apos;s proposals.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOaRD OF TRADE said thathe agreed with the Minister&apos;s proposals, althoughit was clear that the trading community wereintensely suspicious, and there might well be alively opposition.THE P RIME MINISTER thought that it would be undesirable to state definitely that the bill would be introduced at the commencement of next session.     It would be enough   to say that the bill would be introduced as soon as possible next Session.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the necessary authority anddirections should be given for thepreparation of a Bill to be introduced as soon as possible next Session:(b) That the Minister of Transport should beauthorised to announce at once that theGovernment accepted the Report in broadprinciple, and that, while the specific proposals for changes in the law wouldrequire careful examination and considerationit was intended to introduce appropriatelegislation as soon as possible next session.
Fourthly, there was the question of the publicationof rates.     The Minister said that his advisers were satisfied that it was essential to insist upon   -publication of rates, notwithstanding the fact thatthis course would be opposed by the Railway Companies,It was proposed that the Bill should be for aperiod of five years, and it was hoped that road transport would, within that period, have developed a proper rate structure.The Minister said that if the Cabinet gave him the authority asked for in paragraph 38 of his memorandum, he would propose to consult with theinterests concerned and to arrange for the drafting of the Bill to proceed during the Recess.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO supported theMinister of Transport&apos;s proposals.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOaRD OF TRADE said thathe agreed with the Minister&apos;s proposals, althoughit was clear that the trading community wereintensely suspicious, and there might well be alively opposition.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that it would be undesirable to state definitely that the bill would be introduced at the commencement of next session.     It would be enough   to say that the bill would be Introduced as soon as possible next Session,The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the necessary authority anddirections should be given for thepreparation of a Bill to be introduced as soon as possible next Session:(b) That the Minister of Transport should beauthorised to announce at once that theGovernment accepted the Report in broadprinciple, and that, while the specific proposals for changes in the law wouldrequire careful examination and oonsiderationit was intended to introduce appropriatelegislation as soon as possible next session.
agricultural policy.Barley, oats and Sheep.(previous references:Cabinet 8(39),conclusion, and Cabinet24(39),Conclusion 9).12. The Cabinet had before them a joint memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fish-eries and the Secretary of State for Scotland(CP. -110( 39)) , outlining the course of negotiationswith the National Farmers&apos; Unions and other interests concerned,  on the question of the practical application of price-insurance methods to Oats,Barley and Sheep, and describing in detail the ratesof assistance they proposed in each case.In vie?/ of the importance of an early announcement of the Government&apos;s intentions in regardto these commodities, the Ministers attached to their memorandum the draft of a statement for which theysought the approval of their colleagues.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIESexplained the main points in the Memorandum andthanked the Prime Minister and the Chancellorof the Exchequer for the assistance which they had given to him in settling the outstandingdifficulty in regard to the standard price for sheep.Discussion took place in regard to the concluding sentence of paragraph 2 of the draft announcement relating to sheep, which reads asfollows I -&quot;The adjusted scale would not however comeinto operation, even if the guaranteed price should remain above the market price for two successive years, if it could be shown that this price position were theresult of excessive imports of mutton and lamb&quot;.taHBBEkilj
Iu was pointed out that it was nowproposed to deal with imports of mutton and lambby a Commodity Council.    If the words proposedformed part of the public announcement, the Britishagricultural representative on the Council wouldbe in the position that, if he agreed voluntarilyto a certain scale of imports, he would be debarred from arguing at a later date that the rate ofimports had been excessive and had operated toreduce the price of sheep in this country.      Thiswould be putting the British agricultural represent-atives on the Commodity Council in a very awkwardposition,After some discussion, it was agreed thatthis sentence should be omitted from theannouncement and words to the following effectadded to the previous sentence:-&quot;........ subject to a review in which all relevant factors including imports would be taken into account&quot;.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE ANT), FISHERIESexplained that negotiations with the brewers inregard to        malting      doarley were still continuing.   While the brewers were willing tonegotiate, it was not yet certain what was the bestform of scheme which could be devised.Dealing with the proposals generally, theMinister said, that the more detailed figures whichhad now been obtained showed that the paymentsproposed were fully justified by the conditions whichhad prevailed in 1938.      That year had, in fact,
&quot;been by far the worst year since 1934 and nearly all the ground gained in the previousfour or five years had been lost.      The farmers were not, of course, altogether satisfied withthe proposals summarised in the Memorandum, but,on the whole, he thought the proposals wouldhave a fairly good reception and would be ofgreat value to the agricultural industry.     Itwas desirable that the Bill should he introduced as early as possible, and he asked for authorityto introduce the Bill as soon as it had beenapproved by the Home Affairs Committee and withoutfurther reference to the Cabinet.The Cabinet -(l) Approved generally the proposals set out in the Memorandum by theMinister of Agriculture and fisheries and the Secretary of State forScotland (CP. 110(39)):(2) Authorised an announcement of theGovernment&apos;s intentions on the linesof the draft appended to theMemorandum, subject to settlement with the Treasury of the point raised in regard to the adjustment of the standard price of sheep:(3) Authorised the Ministers to arrangefor the drafting of the Bill andfor its introduction after approval by the Home Affairs Committeewithout further reference to theCabinet, provided that no point ofprinciple, requiring decision bythe Cabinet, was raised at theMeeting of that Committee.
ADMINISTRATIONOP JUSTICE(emergency provisions)(SCOTLAND)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet ^4&quot;2 4(39), Con-clusion %l)13*     The Cabinet had under consideration aMemorandum by the Secretary of state for Scotland(H.A.-22 (39)), covering the draft Administrationof Justice (Emergency Provisions)  (Scotland) Bill,which, like the corresponding measure for Englandand Wales, was drafted to make the provision whichwould he necessary in order to enable the Courts ofJustice to function during a v/ar:    together v/with the following recommendation thereon by theCommittee of Home Affairs (H.A.C* 11th Conclusions(39), Minute 2) :-&quot;To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of Lords of the Administra-tion of Justice (Emergency Provisions)(Scotland) Bill in the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-22 (39), subject to any drafting or other minor alterations thatmay be found necessary or desirable.&quot;The Cabinet approved this recommednation.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.,17th May, 1939.
APPENDIX I.Question and, answer regarding the Mufti to be madein the House of Commons on 17th May.QUESTION.     To ask the Secretary of State for theColonies whether it is the intention of His Majesty^Government, in connexion with their forthcomingStatement of Policy, to allow the Mufti of Jerusalemto return to PalestinesANSWER.     No, Sir.     His Majesty&apos;s Government cannotlose sight of the facts, not only that the presentMufti of Jerusalem was the head of an organisation which they held responsible for the campaign of terrorism and violence against British forces and civil officials and against Jews, but also that heis the head of a faction which has for many monthspast pursued persistently a similar campaign againstArabs of other shades of political opinion.     Theyhave decided, therefore, to exclude him indefinitelyfrom Palestine.

</content>
</cab>
