<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/8 images: 82-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet,   July 1943.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 308.lUh July, 1943.WAR CABINET.THE NEED FOR DECISIONS.Note by the Prime Minister.I circulate for the information of my colleagues the attached-memorandum prepared by the Chancellor of the Exchequer at my requestregarding the memorandum circulated by the Deputy Prime Minister,the Minister of Labour and National Service and the Home Secretary(W.P. (43) 255).W. S. C.V10 Downing Street, S.W.1,Uth July, 1943.



THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET.Prime Minister.Paper on Need for. Decisions.1.   In your Broadcast to the Nation on the 22nd March you said : (a) &quot;First of all we must beware of attempts to over-persuade or even tocoerce His Majesty&apos;s Government to bind themselves or their unknownsuccessors, in conditions which no one can foresee and which may beyears ahead, to impose great new expenditure on the State without anyrelation to the circumstances which might prevail at that time, andto make them pledge themselves to particular schemes without relationto other extremely important aspects of our post-war needs.&quot;(b) Secondly,  you  said  &quot;the  business of proposing expenditure  restsultimately with the responsible Government of the day, and it is their duty and their duty alone to propose to Parliament any new changes and also to propose in the annual Budgets the means of raising thenecessary funds.&quot;(c) And &quot; nothing would be easier for me than to make any number of promisesand to get the immediate response of cheap cheers and glowing leading-articles. I am not in any need to go about making promises in orderto win political support or to be allowed to continue in office &quot; . . . .&quot; I am absolutely determined not to falsify or mock that confidence by making promises without regard to whether they can be performed ornot.&quot;id) Then there was your -pronouncement of a Four Years Plan and how weshould have to consider at the end of the war &apos;&apos; five or six largemeasures of a practical character which must all have been the subjectof prolonged careful energetic preparation beforehand and which fittogether. When this plan has been shaped it will have to be presented to the country. ....  A new House of Commons must be freely chosen by the whole electorate.....thus whoever is burdenedwith the responsibility of conducting affairs must have a clear policyand will be able to speak and act at least in the name of an effective and resolute majority.&quot;(e) So far as advance in the insurance system (Beveridge) is concerned, you said &apos;&apos; the time is now ripe for another great advance .... everypreparation, including if necessary preliminary legislative proposals,will be made with the utmost energy .... so that when the momentcomes everything will be ready.&quot;(/). You also enumerated a number of other matters, like Education, &amp;c, and you ended by saying &apos;&apos; for the present during the war our rule shouldbe no promises, but every preparation, including where requiredpreliminary legislation.&quot;2. The paper of the Deputy Prime Minister and his twro colleagues wouldappear to make proposals inconsistent with this declaration and to suggest thatthe Government now (or shortly) should enter into &quot; decisions involving financial commitments,&quot; and should also &quot; now take major decisions as to the items whichit is prepared to carry through into law before the end of the war.&quot;3. Ministers, with the approval of the Cabinet, stated in the course of the beveridge Debate certain aspects of the Government financial policy on this (and presumably similar matters), viz., that we should introduce legislation on such aproposal &quot; when we have considered the finances of this in itself and in relationto other claims and in relation to the general financial situation . ... we must consider the financial priorities .... and we must put defence first.&quot; (HomeSecretary, 18th February, 1943, Official Report, Col. 2048.)4. The Reconstruction Priorities Committee and Sir Willian Jowitfs Com-mittee are proceeding on these lines and have been commissioned to considervarious post-war schemes and the matter of priorities and report from time totime to the Cabinet.   So far as budgetary implications are concerned I have pre-[25741]
sented two papers, the last a few days ago, v\-hich gave an estimate of the national income after the war by the Economic Section of the War Cabinet secretariat and also a financial picture in the light of it of the budgetary post-war position(see P.R. (43) 35 and 36).In one of these papers, greatly daring, I have taken the responsibility ofsaying that I am, for my part, ready to let general financial discussions proceedupon the basis that in the third year after the war (assumed as 1948) the netnational income is likely to reach a definite figure which I have named, viz., 7,000 millions, which carries the corollary that the aggregate taxable national income, which is the foundation and basis of taxable capacity, would be 7,825 millions.5. This has yet to be considered by the Reconstruction Priorities Committee,who no doubt will report as soon as possible to the Cabinet. I should have thought that it was upon these papers and the Report from the ReconstructionPriorities Committee (of which Mr. Bevin and Mr. Morrison are members) thatthe matters raised by Mr. Attlee and his colleagues in the paper you have sent mewould in due course be best considered.6. The memorandum by the three Ministers might leave the reader with an impression that nothing is being done and everything is being held up for lackof certainty about a future question on which certainty is impossible, namely,the financial capacity of the Exchequer in the post-war years. I believe thatsuch an impression would be entirely incorrect. An immense amount of work is being done both on the official plane and upon the ministerial level in regardto a great number of issues of prime importance. One illustration would beCivil Aviation. Another would be Education Policy. I think also that whileit is wise and prudent for the moment not to hurry our deliberations on mostserious issues overmuch, yet the amount of material now accumulating is so large that if at any moment the guns cease shooting and urgent decisions are really requisite they could be urgently taken.7. There is one particular point which I think I must mention. At theend of paragraph 3 of W.P. (43) 255, the first matter mentioned as still requiringto come before the-Cabinet is &quot; Fiscal Policies designed to secure full Employ -ment.&quot; A memorandum bearing closely on this from the Economic Sectionof the War Cabinet Secretariat is now before-the Reconstruction priorities committee (PR. (43) 26) and I have it under very close personal considera-tion. I wish at this stage to make it clear that I do not believe thatfiscal or financial devices are by themselves the key to that immensely importantobjective, but that it requires a steady advance over a wide front of Govern-ment and industrial policy. In that advance the Treasury will, of course, playits full part.K. W.Treasury Chambers, 1st July, 1943.







</content>
</cab>
