<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/44/1 images: 4-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (44)130th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 130 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, 2nd October, 1944, at 5-30 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Simon, LordChancellor - (Items 6 and 7).The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Rt. Hon. A. V. Alexander, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The   Right   Hon.    Sir   archibald sinclair,  Bt.,  M.P.,  Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,  M.P.,  Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries(Items 6 and 7).The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Town and country planning (Items 6 and 7).   .The. Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-5).Marshal   of   the   Royal&quot;  Air   Force&apos;Sir Charles F. A. Portal, Chief ofthe Air Staff (Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary  of  State  for  dominion the Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary  of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon.  Sir  James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War. ^The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland(Items 6 and 7).The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,M.P.,  Minister  of  Health   (items  and 7).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somervell,K.C., M.P., Attorney-General (items  and 7).Admiral of th^ Fleet Sir andrew cunningham, rirst Sea Lord and chief of Naval Staff (Items 1-5).Field-Marshal Sir Alan Brooke, Chiefof the Imperial General Staff (items-5).[28376-3]Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.General Sir Hastings L. Ismay.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. L. F. Burgis.
WAR CABINET 130 (44).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations        ....      ....      ....      103Air Operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean.Naval Operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean.Military Operations:Northern France and Holland.Italy.China.Russia.2      Bombing Policy ........................ 1043      Russia and Poland     ....      ................      .... 1044      Attacks   by   Rockets,   Flying-bombs  and   Long-rangeArtillery    ....................      ........ 104Casualties and damage.5      Foreign Affairs........       .................... 104United States.6      Town and Country Planning Bill   ................ 1057      Civil Air Transport    ........................ 106
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (44) 127thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Home Theatre.Mediterranean.naval operations.Home TheatreMediterranean.MilitaryOperations.northern france and holland.Italy.China.Eussia.1. The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of theprevious week.Bomber Command, whose operations had been hampered by the weather, had flown 4,900 sorties and dropped 4,500 tons of bombs on targets in Germany and 7,800 tons on the Channel ports.Mosquitoes had flown 400 sorties and dropped 500 tons of bombs,all.,over Germany, losing only one aircraft.United States Heavy Bombers had flown 5,900 sorties, dropping12,100 tons of bombs on targets in Germany. 117 United Statesand 10 British bombers had been lost.The Allied Expeditionary Air Force, at the cost of 4 bombers and 105 fighters and fighter bombers, had flown over 15,000 sorties,mainly over the battle area. They claimed to have destroyed some200 motor transport vehicles, 5 tanks, 153 locomotives, 64 barges and55 oil tank cars.244 enemy aircraft had been destroyed.98,000 wounded had been evacuated by air from D-day up tothe previous night.5,000 sorties had been flown and 3,800 tons of bombs dropped.35 enemy aircraft had been destroyed as against 28 Allied. our aircraft had sunk one U-boat, one cruiser and 11 small vessels inthe Mediterranean area. 8 enemy air transports, evacuating troops from the ^aegean, had been destroyed.There had been no shipping losses from enemy action duringthe previous week. The total losses from this cause for Septemberhad been 28,973 tons. 8 U-boats had been sunk and one probably sunk during September.On the night of 30th September 5 M.T.B.S on patrol off theDutch&quot;Coast had, in a series of engagements, hit 2 enemy merchant ships and damaged 2 trawlers by gunfire. Two of our M.T.B.S hadbeen sunk.On the night of the 24th September 2 destroyers had sunk a convoy of 5 craft near Scarpanto. On the 28th September the cruiserH.M.S. Black Prince had bombarded Syra Island, sinking shipping and damaging harbour installations. On the 27th September Greektroops and stores.had been successfully landed on the Island ofPoros.The main feature during the previous week had been the battleat Arnhem and the withdrawal of the remainder of the First Air-borne Division, totalling some 2,200 men. Since then the enemy hadlaunched heavy attacks on both sides of the Nijmegen salient. these attacks had been held and broken, and the salient had now beenwidened. Canadians were now pushing on towards Tilburg. the taking of Cap Gris Nez and Calais had yielded some 8,300&apos; prisoners.Further south some progress had been made north of Aachen, andadvances made between Nancy and Belfort. The administrativesituation had improved.Our main gains had been north of Florence. A certain amountof progress had also been made north of Rimini after heavy fighting.The Japanese were now pushing down the railway line fromHankow towards Kweilin with a view to joining up with their forces advancing north-west from Canton. If this junction was achieved it would mean the loss of the United States aerodromes atKian, Kanchow and Sincheng.In the north the Russians were closing in on Riga. further south little information had been received about the Russian thruststowards Southern Hungary and into Yugoslavia.The War Cabinet-Took note of these statements.[28376-3]b 2
BombingPolicy.(previous reference erence:W.M.(44)69thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Prime Minister said that now that Havre, Boulogne andCalais had been captured, he hoped that Bomber Command woulddirect the greatest possible weight of attack against targets inGermany. The Chief of the Air Staff said that this was theintention.Reference was made to targets in Eastern Germany out of rangefrom the West. The Prime Minister suggested that the Chief ofthe Air Staff should supply him with a list of, say, 15 targets whichcould appropriately be bombed by the Russians. He would then consider forwarding this list to Marshal Stalin.Russia and poland.(previous reference erence:W.M. (44) 127thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The War Cabinet was given the latest information aboutthe position in Warsaw and the relations between Russia and poland.A record of the discussion and conclusions reached is containedin the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Attacks by rockets,Plying BombsandLong-RangeArtillery.casualties and Damage.(PreviousPuef erence:W.M. (44) 127thConclusions,Minute 3.)41 The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat during the week beginning the 25th September there had been,in all, 11 long-range rocket incidents. About 20 flying bombs had crossed the coast. Two had reached the London area and 10 hadbeen destroyed.  Casualties for the week were : -ShellingLong-range rocketFlying bomb ...TotalKilled.11&apos; 920The War Cabinet-Took note of this statement.Seriously   slightly injured.    Injured.20 451035 8955144Foreign Affairs.United States.5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed theWar Cabinet that the United States Government were anxious to publish at once their post-defeat directive to General Eisenhowerfor Germany. He saw great difficulty in agreeing to this. as drafted, it was calculated to harden opinion in Germany ratherthan to encourage an early surrender. Apart from that, we had consistently aimed at dealing with matters of this nature on a tripartite basis, and it would be essential to carry the Russians with us. Finally, while the directive contained much to which noexception could be taken, it would call for amendment in variousrespects.After discussion, the Prime Minister suggested that theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs should represent to the state department the difficulties which we saw in the American proposal.He would also send a reply to Mr. Hopkins, who had communicated with him on the matter, on the lines indicated in discussion.The War Cabinet-Approved the course of action suggested by the PrimeMinister at &quot; X.&quot;
Town and country planning Bill.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 128thConclusions,Minute 3.)6. The War Cabinet had. before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Town and Country Planning (W.P. (44) 547) dealingwith Clauses 45 and 46 of the Town and Country Planning Bill.The Minister of Town and Country Planning explained that since the Second Reading of the Bill he had received a large numberof representations against the restriction of the escalator clause toowner-occupiers of small houses and of agricultural properties, andhad come to the conclusion that, unless the Government, before theCommittee stage of the Bill, put down amendments making some concession, there was little hope of securing the passage of the Billthis Session. He accordingly proposed that a clause should beincluded in the Bill on the lines of Section 11 of the War DamageAct, 1943, under which a percentage increase might be made inrespect of, any class of property. He also proposed that all owners,and not only owner-occupiers, should be entitled to the percentage increase. There would be provision for a percentage deductionwhere this was appropriate, and payments in respect of war-damaged properties under the War Damage Act would have to bebrought into line with the amended proposals. .In favour of the amendments proposed by the Minister of town and Country Planning, it was urged that it was inequitableto give compensation beyond the 1939 standard to owner-occupiers of small houses while denying it to other claimants, such as smallshopkeepers and owner-occupiers of larger houses or of factories,all of whom would be hard put to it to reinstate themselves ifdispossessed. Again, the restriction of the concession to owner-occupiers would cause hardship in the case of Service men whoowned their houses but were not in possession of them owing to warcircumstances. Although the 1939 standard might fairly be appliedto undeveloped land, the rise in building costs was such that paymentof compensation on the 1939 standard was bound to be insufficientin the case of buildings. It was not proposed that all owners ofproperty should automatically get an addition to the 1939 standard,and the form of the amendment proposed would enable the treasury and Parliament to exercise full control over the extent to which the1939 standard was exceeded in any particular type of case.On the other hand, it was pointed out that Clauses 45 and 46 ofthe Bill, as they stood, represented a compromise agreed to by theReconstruction Committee and the War&apos; Cabinet. Instead ofproviding for a 1939 ceiling, which would have allowed localauthorities to purchase land in certain areas at prices below the 1939standard, the clauses provided that the 1939 standard should apply in all cases. Moreover, a special concession had been made in favourof owner-occupiers of small dwelling houses and agriculturalproperties. If this concession were now extended universally, theresult would be that the 1939 ceiling would be turned into a floor.While it might be possible to meet the special case of Service menwho had temporarily ceased to occupy their houses by some change inthe definition of owner-occupier, there was no ground for a universalextension of the concession to all owners of property.The amendments proposed by the Minister of Town and country Planning would place a considerable responsibility on theTreasury. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, having inview the variations between different types of property, he had greatdifficulty in seeing how the principles on which the Treasury were to operate could either be defined to the satisfaction of Parliament orworked in practice.The Minister of Aircraft Production supported the view thatin practice it would be impossible to devise a system which wouldprovide varying scales of increase, appropriate to different types ofproperty. In practice, it would be found necessary, if any further concession were to be made, to apply a single uniform percentage increase. *
Civil air transport.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 129thConclusions,Minute 7-)Reference was made to the risk that, unless this matter was very carefully handled, it might result in a division on party lines.In further discussion the Prime Minister suggested that thebest course might, be to arrange that, when Clause 45 was reached,there should be a general discussion on all the amendments. ThisAvould enable the Government to test the feeling of the House ofCommons. The Minister could explain that the Government had put forward Clauses 45 and 46 in their present form as, in all thecircumstances, the most workable solution of the problem and pointout the difficulties inherent in the various alternatives proposed. Ifafter hearing the views of all sides he came to, the conclusion thatthe House would not accept the Clauses in their present form, heshould not allow the issue to be pressed to a division, but shouldpromise to reconsider these two clauses. The War Cabinet wouldthen, in the light of the debate, be in a better position to decide what course should be taken. If necessary, additional time for theCommittee stage could be secured by arranging for the House to sit on a Monday.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the Minister of Town and Country Planning* should proceed on the lines indicated at &quot;X &quot; above.7. The War Cabinet was informed that Lord Londonderryhad put down a Motion in the House of Lords for Thursday, the5th October, in the following terms :-&quot; To ask His Majesty&apos;s Government, whether they have any information to give regarding any negotiations on post-warCivil Aviation in which the Lord Privy Seal may have been &apos;engaged during his recent visit to the United States; and what changes in the post-war Civil Air Transport policy ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government may be expected therefrom, inregard to the Ministerial direction of that policy, the &quot; ChosenInstrument,&quot; or the provision of Civil Air Transport machines;and to move for Papers.&quot;Lord Londonderry had now agreed to postpone his Motion for aweek, until the 12th October.The Prime Minister said that he was meeting a deputation of conservative Members in the near future, and he hoped that theWar Cabinet would be able to have a further discussion on Civil air transport later in the week.The War Oabinet--Took note of this statement.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,2nd October, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
