<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/18/6 images: 46-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1941.SECRET.W.M. (41)27th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 27 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at Paddock, onMonday, March 10, 1941, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The following were also present:The Right Hon. R. G. Menzies,K.C., M.P., Prime Minister of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister of.  Home Security.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary,Foreign Office.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The    Right    Hon.    Lord    Moyne,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. H. D. Margesson,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Lieut.-General Sir Robert Haining,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[22306]
WAR CABINET 27 (41).Contents.minute no. Subject...1      Naval, Military and Air Operations..Air operations.Naval operations:Shipping losses.2      The Balkans and the Middle East ..Future military policy.3      Air RaidsCasualties and damage.4      Civil DefenceFire-watching.Arrangements at Liverpool Docks.5      australia the Australian war effort.Statement by Mr. Menzies.6      Yugoslavia     ......      .....    ... ..
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 25thConclusions,Minute 8.)Air Operations.naval operations.Shipping Losses.1. The Chiefs of Staff made the following Eeports in amplification of Cabinet War Room Records 549-554: One hundred and sixty enemy aircraft had been over thiscountry on the night of the 8th March. Three interceptions hadbeen made without result. On the night of the 9th March about thesame number of enemy aircraft had been over, but our fighters hadbeen unable to operate owing to weather conditions. There were indications, however, that other methods of interception had met with some success.The Chief of the Air Staff said that the Commander-in-Chief,Fighter Command, was satisfied that definite, although slow,progress was being made with night interception aircraft. Improve-ment was also being shown in A.A. defence.A Sunderland flying boat had made a promising attack on aU-boat in the north-west approaches.As a result of two heavy attacks, one on a convoy in the north-west approaches and another on a convoy from Freetown, theshipping losses for the last four days had been heavy. 67,000 tonshad been sunk by mines, enemy aircraft, E-boats, and submarines,and 14,000 tons damaged.The Scharnhorst and the Gneisenau had been sighted by air-craft from the Malaya on the 8th March when she was escortingthe Freetown convoy, some 150 miles north of Cape Verde Islands,but the enemy ships had sheered off to westward.The War Cabinet were informed of the consequential disposi-tions that were being taken.Arbutus had sunk a U-boat north-west of the Butt of Lewison the 7th March, and taken 24 prisoners.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.The balkans and theMiddle East.Future military policy.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 26thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The War Cabinet had before them further telegrams onthis matter. A record of the discussion is contained in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Information to arrange for aconference in the course of the afternoon with representa-tives of the Foreign Office, Dominions Office and the three service Departments, to frame a draft Communique forissue to the Press as soon as it became known that British reinforcements were arriving in Greece, and to determine what guidance should be given to the Press.The draft Communique should be submitted to thePrime Minister before issue.Air Balds.Casualties and damage., (previous reference:W.M. (41) 18thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Home Secretary and Minister of Rome Security saidthat on the night 8th/9th March some 60-100 machines had made aconcentrated attack on London. Incidents had been reported from50 boroughs. Considerable damage had been done to property in westminster, Lambeth, Southwark and the Docks. Bombs had alsobeen -dropped at Portsmouth. The casualties in London hadamounted to 184 killed and 438 injured elsewhere, 4  injured.On the night of the 9th/10th March most of the enemy bombs had fallen in north-east London, but the casualties and damageappeared to have been less than on the previous night. casualties had been in London, 3 killed, 90 injured elsewhere, 16 killed,30 injured.  Later estimates, however, would probably be higher.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.-m.M: mam,
Civil Defence.Firewatehing.arrangements at&apos; LiverpoolDocks.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 5thConclusions,Minute 7.)4. The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat the North-western Regional Commissioner was anxious aboutthe fire watching arrangements for the warehouses adjoiningLiverpool Docks. If part-time voluntary or conscripted labour Wasto be used for this purpose, 15,000 persons would be required.Proper fire watching for this area was an urgent and vital need.The Regional Commissioner had asked whether some 2,000 militarycould, as an exceptional case, be provided for the purpose.The War Cabinet invited the Lord President of the Council (a) To hold a Meeting that afternoon with representativesof the War Office and other Departments concerned,to determine what immediate steps could be takento provide adequate fire watching arrangements forthe Liverpool warehouses.(6) Later, to submit proposals for long-term arrangementsfor dealing with this matter.Australia.The AustralianWar Effort.Statement byMr. Menzies.(previous reference: .W.M. (41) 20thConclusions,Minute 1.)Menzies made an oral statement on the Australian war(41)A record of this statement is being circulated as W.P5.   Mr.effort.55.In reply to a question by the Lord Privy Seal, Mr. Menziessaid that he would be very glad to make a similar statement at ameeting of Ministers not members of the War Cabinet.The War Cabinet-(i) Thanked Mr. Menzies warmly for his statement.(ii) Expressed their high appreciation of the war effort nowbeing put forth by the Commonwealth of Australia.Yugoslavia. 6.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous First Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (41) 54).Reference: A record of the discussion and of the conclusions reached revise.M. (41) 23rd contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions, Conclusions.-Minute: 3.), V, Great George Street, S.W. 1,-&quot;&quot; March 10, 1941.

Civil Defence.Fire watching.arrangements at&apos; LiverpoolDocks.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 5thConclusions,Minute 7.)4. The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat the North-western Regional Commissioner was anxious aboutthe fire watching arrangements for the warehouses adjoiningLiverpool Docks. If part-time voluntary or conscripted labour wasto be used for this purpose, 15,000 persons would be required.Proper fire watching for this area was an urgent and vital heed.The Regional Commissioner had asked whether some 2,000 militarycould, as an exceptional case, be provided for the purpose.The War Cabinet invited the Lord President of the Council-(a) To hold a Meeting that afternoon with representativesof the War Office and other Departments concerned,to determine what immediate steps could be takento provide adequate fire watching arrangements forthe Liverpool warehouses.(b) Later, to submit proposals for long-term arrangementsfor dealing with this matter.Australia.The AustralianWar Effort.Statement byMr. Menzies.(previous reference: .W.M. (41) 20thConclusions,Minute 1.)5. Mr. Menzies made an oral statement on the Australian war effort. A record of this statement is being circulated as W.P. (41)55.In reply to a question by the Lord Privy Seal, Mr. Menziessaid that he would be very glad to make a similar statement at ameeting of Ministers not members of the War Cabinet.The War Cabinet-(i) Thanked Mr. Menzies warmly for his statement.(ii) Expressed their high appreciation of the war effort nowbeing put forth by the Commonwealth of Australia.Yugoslavia. 6.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous First Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (41) 54).Reference: A record of the discussion and of the conclusions reached revise.M. (41) 23rd contained in the SecretaryJs Standard File of War cabinet conclusions,      Conclusions.Minute&apos; 3.),&apos; rGreat George Street, S.W. 1,March 10, 1941.



</content>
</cab>
