<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/23/0 images: 44-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS   THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS   BRITANNIC-jjiAIEOTYj;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  November 1951SECRETC.C. (51)8th conclusions copy No.37CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Monday, \9th November, 1951, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister and Minister ofDefence (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,NLP., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,K.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, K.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Ismay, Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The   Right  Hon.   lord paymaster-General.Cherwell,The following were also present:The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item I).Sir William Strang, Foreign(Item 2).OfficeSecretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. T. Padmore.contents minute no. Subject page 1     Coal      ...      ...     &quot;...      ... , ...38Miners&apos; Wages.2     Germany...      ... .......      ...      ...      ...     38Financial Contribution to Defence.41475
Coal. l.   The Secretary of State for Co-ordination of Transport, FuelMiners&apos; and Power explained the position reached in discussions between theWages. National Coal Board and the National Union of Mineworkers onthe claim for a wages increase of 18 per cent, which had been lodgedat the time of the General Election. It would be preferable to reach a negotiated settlement of this claim: an award at arbitration mightbe equally costly and would prejudice the subsequent discussions on methods of increasing output. The miners would not discuss those questions until the wage claim had been settled. The National coal board had indicated willingness to settle on an increase of 8 per cent.,but it was now clear that this would not be accepted. The Boardthought, however, that they might reach a settlement on an increasesomewhere between 95 and 11-8 per cent., possibly at about 10 percent. The Secretary of State recommended that the Board should beauthorised to negotiate on this basis. It would also be necessary to withhold in 1952 the second week of paid holiday promised by theBoard and to find some means of compensating the miners for this.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The present level of miners&apos; incomes was sufficiently highfor many of them to prefer leisure to higher earnings; and further increases, especially if they outstripped the rise in the cost of living,might have an adverse effect on attendance.(b) There would be insuperable difficulties, both administrativelyand in repercussions on other industries, in making a concessions which would exempt part of the miners&apos; earnings from income tax.(c) The railwaymen had recently accepted an increase of 8 percent, and the engineers an increase which on the average worked out at something under 10 per cent. A wage iticrease of 10 per cent, forthe miners, who were already the best-paid industrial workers in thecountry, might well start a further round of wage demands in these industries, which had received a lower percentage increase on a lowerbasic wage. It might therefore be preferable to allow the claim togo to arbitration. It was, however, the general view of the Cabinetthat an agreed settlement would be more conducive to successfuldiscussions on means of increasing coal output.The Cabinet Authorised the Secretary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power to inform the National coal board that the Government were willing that they should endeavour to reach a negotiated settlement of the miners&apos;wage claim on the basis of an increase of about 10 per cent.2. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the lord privy Seal (C. (51) 19) reporting the conclusions of the Committeewhich they had appointed on 15th November to review the proposals in C. (51) 15 regarding Germany&apos;s financial contribution to thedefence of Western Europe.In discussion the point was made that the figures of cost givenin C. (51) 15 were likely to prove, on examination, to be excessive.But, even when all practicable economies had been made, a gap would remain which could in fact be filled only by a contribution from theUnited States.The Cabinet Agreed that, negotiations should be opened at an early date with the German Federal Government regarding Germany&apos;financial contribution to the defence of Western Europe;and authorised the Foreign Secretary to seek agreement tothis course at his forthcoming meeting with the foreign ministers of the United States and France, making it clearthat the United Kingdom Government could only enter upon those negotiations on the understanding that they werenot prepared to accept any additional financial burden.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,19th November, 1951.Germany.financial contribution.to Defence.(previous reference:C.C. (51) 7thConclusions,Minute 4.)


</content>
</cab>
