<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/23/0 images: 47-52</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^29THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. November 1951SECRETC.C. (51)9th conclusions copy No.   37CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. lvon Tuesday, 20th November, 1951, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister and Minister ofDefence (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,K.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, K.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Ismay, Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(Items 1-3).The Right Hon. Gwilym LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Food(Items 1-3).The Right Hon. the Earl De La Warr,Postmaster-General (Item 4).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. T. Padmore.41492-1B
contents minute no. Subject page 1      Parliament       ...      ..................      41Secret Session.2     Parliament       ...............      ......      41Questions about Nationalised Industries.3      Colonial Food-stuffs and Raw Materials     .........      414     British Broadcasting Corporation     ...      ...      ......      42Renewal of the Charter.
1. The Prime Minister said that there seemed to be somedivision of opinion in Parliament about his offer of a secret session on Defence. He had thought that Parliament would welcome this opportunity for a private discussion on Defence; but he was not disposed to press his suggestion at the present time if it were foundthat there was a substantial body of Parliamentary opinion against it.The Cabinet endorsed the Prime Minister^ view, and invited him to express it in reply to a Question to be put to him that afternoonby ivlr. Ivl. Foot, !M^.P.2. The Cabinet agreed that the House of Commons should beinvited to approve the following terms of reference for the SelectCommittee which was to consider the problem of parliamentary questions about the nationalised industries:  &quot; To consider the present methods by which the House ofCommons is informed of the affairs of the nationalised industries and to report what changes, having regard to theprovisions laid down by Parliament in the relevant statutes,may be desirable in these methods.&quot;They further agreed that the Minister of Health, in announcing these terms of reference, should make it clear that the appointment of thisSelect Committee (which would be limited to considering theprocedure to be followed under the existing law) was not to beregarded as fulfilling the Governments pledge to undertake a com-prehensive review of the whole question of Parliamentary controlover the nationalised industries.The Cabinet also had some preliminary discussion about the composition of the Select Committee. It was argued that, if theCommittee was to be reasonably small and was to reflect the relativestrengths of the Parties in the House of Commons, the inclusion of arepresentative of the Liberal Party would not be justified. On theother hand it seemed unreasonable that the Liberals should be excluded on this account from all the smaller Committees appointedby the House. Some general understanding might perhaps be reached with the Leader of the Liberal Party about the representation of the liberals on such .Committees as these. The Cabinet invited theMinister of Health to give further consideration to this point and agreed to discuss it again at their meeting on 22nd November.3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum (C. (51) 14) by theSecretary of State for the Colonies outlining the possibilities ofincreasing the supply of Colonial food-stuffs and raw materials to theUnited Kingdom.The. Colonial Secretary said that development of the productivecapacity of the Colonies could in the long term transform theeconomic position of the United Kingdom; but at the present time he was primarily concerned with action which might increase supplies from the Colonies in the near future. He drew particular attentionto the conditions precedent to any early expansion of the supply ofgoods from the Colonies which were set out in paragraph 5 of his memorandum.In discussion the following points were raised:  (a) It was desirable to encourage investment in the colonial empire by citizens of this country and investment by United Statesnationals in the United Kingdom, rather than to encourage direct-1 B 2-
investment from the United States in the Colonial Empire. TheColonial Secretary said that he was already discussing with theChancellor of the Exchequer the operation of double-taxationarrangements and depreciation allowances, which were at presentmore favourable to American and Canadian enterprise in the Coloniesthan to our own investors.(b) The Colonial Secretary said that he was examining with theother Ministers concerned the supply of capital goods both to public authorities and to private enterprise in the Colonies and the supplyof consumer goods. He would present a separate paper on these subjects later,(c) Efforts should be made to increase the use of hard-woodsfrom the Colonies in replacement of soft-woods imported from outside the sterling area. Some useful research into this had alreadybeen carried out, and it should be possible to arrange that more ofthese hard-woods were used in the building of houses, especially those not built by or for local authorities.(d) Consideration should be given to the use of sterling balancesto provide funds for investment in the Colonial Empire and to reducethe calls on the London market.(e) Increased supplies of groundnuts from the Colonies might make it possible to dispense with the rationing of animal feeding-stuffs in this country, which was not working satisfactorily.The Cabinet Took note of the memorandum (C. (51) 14) by the Secretaryof State for the Colonies and of the points raised in discussion.British 4.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Postmaster-Broadcasting General (C. (51) 20) proposing that the Charter and Licence of theCorporation. British Broadcasting Corporation should be extended for a period ofRenewal of six months after the end of the present calendar year (when theythe Charter.      would otherwise expire) so that the Government might have more time to review their policy and make considered proposals toParliament.The Postmaster-General said that during this interval the maini questions to be examined were:  (i) Were the basic structure and powers of the B.B.C. to remain unchanged?(ii) What were to be the future financial arrangements?(iii) What was the Governments policy towards the creation ofa new regional organisation within the B.B.C. ?In discussion it was suggested that, if the existing Charter wasto be extended temporarily, it would be appropriate to maintain allthe existing conditions during this period and to refrain from reducingthe B.B.C. grant to 85 per cent, of the net licence revenue. On theother hand it was pointed out that this particular proposal was unlikely to be challenged by the Opposition, since they had announcedwhen in office their intention to make such a reduction. The cabinet agreed that, in view of the importance of underlining the need for economy, the reduction should be made as proposed in C. (51) 20.It was further agreed that the Postmaster-General should not atthis stage pronounce against breaking up the B.B.C. into a numberof independent organisations. He could formulate his proposals onthe basis that there should be no break-up of the B.B.C., but the cabinet&apos;s final decisions should not be pre-judged.
The Cabinet-(1) Authorised the grant of a temporary Charter and Licence tothe B.B.C. for six months from 1st January, 1952.(2) Decided that the grant to the B.B.C. should be reduced to85 per cent, of the net licence revenue from 1st January,1952.(3) Invited the Postmaster-General to arrange for these decisions to be announced to Parliament as soon as possible.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,20th November, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
