<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/55/36 images: 374-377</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
vf7THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT j00--,--\ouPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1944.Q pSECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 536.22nd September, 1944.WAR CABINET.PRODUCTION OF PREFABRICATED HOUSES.Memorandum by the Minister of Reconstruction.THE Prime Minister, on the 5th September last, set up a committee consisting of the Lord Privy Seal (Chairman), Minister of Works and Ministerof Information, with the following terms of reference : To make the best plan possible, with programme attached, for thelargest possible construction in the shortest time of prefabricated houses ofall types, without trenching notably on the normal building trade. In this inquiry the Committee should assume that the necessary impingement willbe made upon munitions production provided the scheme is approved bythe Cabinet.The Committee has now reported and I bring the report to the attentionof my colleagues.W.4 Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,22nd September, 1944.COMMITTEE ON PREFABRICATED HOUSES.Report.THE Prime Minister appointed Lord Privy Seal, Minister of Works and minister of Information to draw up a programme for the largest possibleconstruction of prefabricated houses without trenching on the normal building trade, but on the assumption that munitions production can be impinged uponto the extent required by a scheme approved by the Cabinet.2. It is the view of the Committee that about 50,000 steel (Portal) housescan be supplied by the industry within two years of the date when the programme is launched. Deliveries should begin twelve months hence and it is not to beexpected that they will exceed a maximum weekly rate of 1,000 houses.3. This rate of production will depend on the completion without delay of the drawings for dies, jigs, tools, fixtures and other production details.Additional plant is required, including presses, bonderising tanks, &amp;c, andthere must not be any delay in going forward with the whole programme.4.   There are three other types of temporary houses (i) Uniseco (asbestos cement on a timber frame);(ii) Arcon (asbestos cement on a light steel frame);(iii) Tarran (concrete panels in a timber frame).5.   The Committee recommends the production of two of these types.   TheTarran type is rejected.   It is only a paper project and the firm is in financial difficulties.   Their bankers have given us a warning.[28267]
6. Uniseco and Arcon say full production should be reached in the first half of next year. Deliveries are estimated by these two private contractingenterprises exceeding a total maximum rate of 1,500 houses a week, thus providingabout 100,000 houses within two years of the launching of the scheme. TheCommittee is satisfied of the good faith of the firms, but as there is not any past experience to guide us in actual production of these types of houses here, we areunable to give definite assurances of satisfactory results.7.   The successful accomplishment of these three projects depends on (a) adequate planning operations being undertaken without any delay; werefer, of course, to planning in the production sense and not toplanning within the usual political connotation;(b) an adequate flow of labour of a type suitable to the erection of houses onthe site;(c) above all, drive, energy, resource and capacity for improvisation will benecessary.8. The programme presented to us is not adequate for the needs of thepopulation. New projects for temporary accommodation should be launched atonce on lines more extensive and with prospects more abundant than the present plans.Note. Lord Portal points out that, if the programme is continued to the31st December, 1946, 65,000 steel houses and 125,000 in other materialswill have been produced, which is a total programme of slightly lessthan 200,000 temporary houses.B.lQth September, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
