<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/20 images: 366-369</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
UMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1940.-RET. Copy No-p (R.) (40) 20.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.PUBLICITY IN ENEMY COUNTRIES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues, for their information, a memorandum inhii-h Sir 0. Stuart reviews the past activities, surveys the present position andtempts to foresee the future work of the Department for Publicity in Enemyuntries.H.Foreign Office. January 12, 1940.PUBLICITY IN ENEMY COUNTRIES.Memorandum by Sir Campbell Stuart.I he coming of a new year has suggested a review of past efforts, a survey of present position and an attempt to see as far as may be into the future.op&apos;iwmda Policies.Since the outbreak of war British propaganda in Germany has passedugh two stages. In the first, which lasted only a couple of weeks, it followedlead of the Prime Minister with attacks upon the relations between theman Government and the German people. In the second, its ruling motive hast to lower the resistance of the enemy by undermining their morale. This has1&apos;ed eliorts to destroy confidence both in the Nazi regime and in Germany&apos;sacity to win. During the second stage it became necessary, owing to Nazi&apos;&apos;!&apos;al propaganda based on the Polish victory, further to argue that even^tn eess did not lessen the certainty of an ultimate defeat of Germany,ueh of the two main lines of propaganda pursued since mid-September hassupported by a number of auxiliary arguments. Undermining the Nazinie nas. for example, included efforts to sow mistrust in the Nazi leaders bydivergence between party and national interests, dissensions in the party-y^e iniquity in the party &quot;bosses,&quot; their responsibility for worsening1 &apos;?&quot;t m^ t^ie cnarge that it is they who stand in the way of peace. Attemptsal sense as remains in Germany.W823   [20630]0 been made to shake faith in German propaganda, and to appeal to such
The theme of destroying confidence in Germany5 s capacity to win has. on other hand, been developed by demonstrating Germany&apos;s inadequate military %economic strength, the growing power of the Allies, the hostility of subject pe0pjwithin the Reich, the absence of support from Germany&apos;s friends (including ^Soviets),,and the opposition of the civilised world.A more complex Situation.In the first four months of the war the situation, both military and politicalwith which we had to contend was comparatively simple.   By the New Year i:had become more complex.   There is now a real, though repressed, crisis jGermany.   It is chiefly the result of two factors :(a) The Russo-German Pact with its consequences, namely, the Finnish waithe abandonment of German interests in the Baltic, the physical anpolitical approach to Communism, the Nazi movement towardsLeft, and the threats to German interests in South-Eastern Furopeand to the supplies looked for from Russia.(b) The prolongation of the war beyond the expectation of the mass oGermans.In regard to (a) the German move towards Russia and its results have widen the breach between the older and conservative German nationalists and thyounger revolutionaries of the Nazi party. We, therefore, continue to harpthe injury wrought by the Russian entanglement to German interests. Propaganda along this line harmonizes the immediate aim of overthrowing the preset)German Government with the established British policy of protecting Euro,from Bolshevik penetration. The Nazi trend towards Communism offers, moreover, a powerful lever for detaching Germans from the existing regime. To man of them its anti-Communist crusade had been the great attraction of the Nazparty. Our earlier appeal against Nazism is, therefore, being developed into onagainst Nazi-Communism. This does not entail the suggestion that there artwo kinds of Nazism, a good one which is anti-Bolshevik, and a bad one whiclooks to Moscow, nor indeed that Stalin&apos;s dictatorship is essentially different frothat of Hitler. We propose rather- to exploit the volte-face towards Communistto illustrate the meaninglessness of Nazism, arguing that the Stalin-Hitler pacis the natural result of the assimilation of two systems of oppression. on appeal is, therefore, to human antipathy to a regime under which the lorsupporter suffers as well as the opponents. In making it, however, we must satguard ourselves against the retort that the British are socially reactionary. Thiin view of both our national record and Labour support of the war. should nprove difficult.Responsibility for Prolongation of the War.The prolongation of hostilities beyond German expectations has had a natural results of disappointment, uncertainty, and the creation of a mMof enquiry.   All of these, and particularly the last, yield opportunities british propaganda.   War guilt has, of course, been and remains an importsfeature of our case.   Indeed, such hopes as her enemies possess of revoluticin Germany are based on the evils of war being attributed by the German peopdirectly to the German regime.   Guilt for the prolongation of the war seerhowever, to us an even more effective form of indictment, since it assoeiathe Nazis with the abiding evils of privation rather than with the saerinclinked to triumphs of, for example, the Polish campaign.   It will be possirin propaganda on this note to play upon Hitler&apos;s implicit refusal to respoto the &quot;deeds, not words&quot; demanded last October by Mr. Chamberlain,is, in fact, difficult -to see a more effective way of outflanking the stistaiiand successful Nazi effort to persuade the Germans that the blame for alldistress they suffer lies on England.Undermining Hitler.Another development of propaganda which is now possible is systematicto undermine the position of Hitler himself.   We do not at this stage sag?
luinifinj 11. 1940.I at tacks on him, but that we should consistently treat him. as the pawnTits and personal influences, rather than the active master.of his country.&apos;s&apos; * 1 ji,js is a matter to which we are still giving careful thought. ,ad French Policies. ....There is yet another development which we have been considering with no,.AYQ   British propaganda has in its earlier stages been based on a distinc-between the German people and the Nazi regime.   A similar distinction is0, ltv,i nised by our French allies.   When we have spoken of Hitlerism they. ,Miitinued to speak of Germany.   The French attitude, if pushed to its&quot;irjcal conclusion, would render propaganda largely ineffective, since it would(l Germany to be beyond redemption.   The British view, on the other hand,uoi hitherto embraced the possibility of spurring the Germans to redeemhemselves. There has, moreover, been some danger in placing too much emphasisii our &quot;odd will towards the German people and on our readiness for a peacef reeoticiliatipn.  It might even have led some of them to feel that their country(mill wniTe a brutal war for as long as it was convenient, and then demand]1;it we should make good our words.   If we did not, our refusal might berented as a breach of undertaking, and used in propaganda against us.The Prime Ministers reminder at the Mansion House that the Germanleople must realise their own responsibility for prolonging the war has come,here fore, as a welcome lead. Not only will it sharpen the instruments ofnipaganda; but it will enable us to align our policy more closely with that ofin French colleagues. Once we have explicitly accepted the fact that the Germanviple are accomplices in Germany&apos;s crime, we are in a better position to winlie I reiu-h to the view that Germany should be offered the opportunity offileiuption. If agreement on this point were reached, it could be expressedn hotli British and French propaganda by the extension of our attack upon the&apos;;ir-mongering Nazi into one upon a war-mongering Germany.(&apos; a in m i in Formula.Such an attitude would compensate threats with offers, and fears with hopes,he earlier British formula that we had no quarrel with the German peopleiiiveyed to them only an indirect alarm. The French formula of quarrel withDth regime and people offered on tJhe other hand no hope to the latter. Ifie German people were now confronted with a clear alternative between warfareaged against themselves and ceasing to be the accomplices of crime, they might&quot;ell be stung to greater activity in the cause of peace. A formula which expressed his attitude might well, therefore, become the central theme of the Anglo-Frenchropaganda effort, each Government being free to enlarge upon it in accordance&apos;ith its own desires.I.vents must, before long, prove to what extent the German people are atue with their Government in waging war. If it were found that there is,uleed. a powerful element in Germany prepared, as far as possible, to resiste Nazi war policy, propaganda could be modified accordingly, and a waylould be kept open for this purpose. If, on the other hand, no such elementppears; the Prime Ministers insistence on the responsibility of the Germanople is susceptible of progressive development.


</content>
</cab>
