<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/69/0 images: 74-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret. (54) 2171st July, 1954CABINETCOUNCIL FOR THE CO-ORDINATION OF PUBLICLY-OWNEDTRANSPORT IN scotland memorandum by the Secretary of State for scotland on 29th June I was invited by the Cabinet to circulate a memorandumdescribing the organisation and functions of the Council which it is proposed toset up to co-ordinate publicly-owned transport in Scotland (C.C. (54) 44th Con-clusions, Minute 4).2. During the discussions in connection with the Transport Bill in 1952 and1953 great importance was attached in Scotland to the making of adequate arrange-ments for the proper integration of the transport services remaining in public ownership. It was suggested by the Scottish Council (Development and Industry)and others that a Scottish Transport Board should be formed which would be directly responsible for all forms of nationally-owned transport in Scotland. these suggestions were fully considered in consultation with the Minister of transport and the Secretary of State for the Co-ordination of Transport, Fuel and Power. Itwas felt, however, that to place the various forms of state-owned transport under one management would neither be possible within the framework of the transport bill nor desirable as a matter of government policy. It was, nevertheless, recognisedthat a need existed for the discussion within Scotland of problems common to thevarious state-owned transport agencies: and with this end in view the government undertook to appoint a Scottish Transport Council.3. The formation of the Council was discussed on different occasions duringthe Parliamentary proceedings on the Transport Bill, and full statements were madeby the Minister of Transport on the Third Reading of the Bill on 16th February,1953 and by the Minister of State in the House of Lords on 24th February, 1953.We then undertook that the Council (which would have no executive function)would be composed of representatives of the bodies responsible to the british transport Commission for goods and passenger services, both by rail and road, ofBritish European Airways, and of Messrs. David MacBrayne Ltd. The ScottishAdvisory Council for Civil Aviation would also be represented - and there wouldbe an independent chairman and independent members appointed by the Secretaryof State in consultation with the Minister of Transport.4. In his speech in the House of Lords the Minister of State said that it was too soon to define the duties of the Council in great detail but suggested that theyshould include the following:  (i) to review the work of the different transport authorities set up in Scotland;(ii) to consider matters of common interest;(hi) to formulate joint schemes for the future;(iv) to make proposals for the development of joint services in Scotland; and(v) to make proposals for improvements and economies in these services.46425Copy No.Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1954
The Minister added that the Council, in fulfilling its functions, would notweaken the executive-responsibilities of the different transport authorities norinterfere with the statutory responsibilities of the Scottish Advisory Council for civil Aviation.5., No action has been taken to appoint the Council pending the approval.ofthe railway reorganisation scheme. As soon, however, as the Scottfsftf^eji.Authority is appointed under that Scheme, I feel that it will be essentialTtp setup the Scottish Transport Council. i,lX -J. S. ,Scottish Office, S.W. 1,1st July, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
