<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/69/0 images: 103-107</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
4:(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)secret.(54) 230 COPY NO12th July, 1954CABINETEXPENSES OF MEMBERSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer attach the draft of a Supplementary Estimate to meet thecost of the Sessional Allowance scheme.    It will be noted that the draftmentions 24th May, 1954 as the operative date.    This, of course, has still to be settled.There are a number of points arising on the draft which Ishould like to discuss with my colleagues.R.A.B.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.12th July, 1954.
CONFTOEMITALr-PROOP1954-55SUPPLEMENTARY ESTIMATECIVIL ESTIMATESESTIMATE of further sums required to be voted forthe Service of the Year ending 31st March 1955One Hundred and Twenty-six Thousand PoundsPresented by Command of Her MajestyOrderedby The House of Commons to be PrintedJuly 1954   iLONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE /NBT
(ifiCLASS. IHOUSE OF COMMONSSUPPLEMENTARY ESTIMATE of the amount required in the year ending 31 March 1955 for the salaries and expenses of the House ofCommons, including a grant in aid to the Kitchen Committee.One hundred and twenty-six thousand pounds ,. j,( 126,000)II. Subhead under which this Vote will be accounted for by the House ofCommons Offices. 	T hr.i :        1954-55--			Original Estimate	Revised Estimate	Additional sum requiredMembers A.4. SESSIONAL ALLOWANCE     ...	 	  126,000	  126,000Total Original Net Estimate, 1954-55 .4-dd Sum now requiredTotal 948,466126,000 1,074,466m.Details of the foregoingMembersA.4.-SESSIONAL ALLOWANCE:Sessional Allowance in respect of expenses wholly, necessarily andexclusively incurred by Members in the performance of the dutiesof their office as such, payable as from 24 May 1954 at the rate of 2 for every day on which the House meets (other than a Friday ora day on which the House adjourns for a Recess) to Members of theHouse not in receipt of salaries or pensions under the Ministers ofthe Crown Act, 1937 (1 Edw. 8 &amp; 1 Geo. 6. c. 38), or otherwise as ministers, as Officers of the House or as Officers of Her Majesty&apos;sHousehold.........&quot; ...............126,000Treasury. Chambers^th July, 1954JOHN BOYD-CARPENTER
fobThe following Revised and Supplementary Estimates for 1954-55 havebeen presented to date: H.C. Paper		Service		Amount208 of 1953-	-54	Repayments to the Civil Contingencies Fund Colonial Services       ...... Broadcasting    ............... Public Education, Scotland........... National Museum of Antiquities, Scotland..... Ministry of Housing and Local Government Board of Trade................. Houses of Parliament Buildings      ........ Post Office      .................		  87,422 227,000 3,600,000 6,885 8,000 29,990 120,000 34,000 100,000		Add-Amount on this Paper      ...........		4,213,297 126,000135 of 1953-	-54	Less  Reduction effected by Revised Estimate for the Ministry of Food    .....................		4,339,297 27,300,000207 of 1953-	-54	Atomic Energy (Revised Estimate)*       ....      .,		:-		Net reduction on original Estimates, 1954-55	... 	22,960,703* This Revised Estimate shows no change from the total original provision.(30189)   (1)   12   7/54   D.L,
printed and published by her majesty&apos;s stationery officeTo be purchased from york House, Kirtgsway, London, w.c.2     423 Oxford Street, London, w.1P.O. Box 569, london, S.Ej113a Castle Street, Edinburgh, 2      1 St. Andraw&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff3i9 King Street, Manchester, 2     Tower Lane, Bristol, 12 Edmund Street, Birmingham, 3      80 Chiohester Street, belfast or from any Bookseller1954

</content>
</cab>
