<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/69/0 images: 194-198</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret.(54) 23819th July, 1954CABINETCRICHEL DOWNNote by the Secretary of the cabinet at their meeting on 1st July (C. C. (54) 45th Conclusions,Minute 6), the Cabinet approved the appointment of a small Committeeto advise Ministers on the question whether any of the officials criticised in the report of the Crichel Down Inquiry should be transferred to otherposts in the civil Service.COPY NO.2.        The report of this Committee has now been received and submitted to the Prime Minister.    He has agreed that the appointmentof the Committee and its recommendations should be announced by theMinister of Agriculture in his opening speech in the debate on Tuesday,20th July, and that the report should be made available to Members inthe Vote Office on that day.3.        The attached copy of the report, which is circulated to membersof the Cabinet only, is to be considered before the debate in conjunctionwith a note by the Minister of Agriculture (C.(54) 239) covering the text of that part of his speech in which he will deal with the report.(Signed) NORMAN brook cabinet Office, S.W.1.16th July, 1954.
Report of a Committeeappointed by the Prime Ministerto consider whethercertain Civil Servants should betransferred to other dutiesPresented to Parliament by Command of Her majesty july 1954HERCmd. 9220LONDONMAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERYthreepence netOFFICE
REPORT OF A COMMITTEE APPOINTED BY THE PRIME MINISTERTO CONSIDER WHETHER CERTAIN CIVIL SERVANTS SHOULDBE TRANSFERRED TO OTHER duties to The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, K.G., O.M., C.H., M.P.Sir,We were asked to consider whether, in order to maintain public confidence in the administration of Departments, any of the officers whose conduct was called in question in Sir Andrew Clark&apos;s Report on the disposal of land atCrichel Down (Cmd. 9176) should be transferred from their existing duties to other posts. In considering this matter we were asked to take into accountnot only the public interest and the efficiency of the public service, but alsofair treatment for the individuals concerned. Questions of disciplinary action,having been disposed of by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries in his statement in the House of Commons on 15th June, were excluded from our terms of reference.2. At the present date there are in the Civil Service five officers whose actionsare criticised in Sir Andrew Clark&apos;s Report with varying degrees of severity.Any individuals who were not Civil Servants at the date of the public inquiryor who have left the Service since were clearly outside the scope of our consideration. We have studied Sir Andrew Clark&apos;s Report; we have read the observations submitted to the Minister at his invitation by the five officersmentioned; and we have interviewed each of them separately. The observa-tions submitted did not accept some of the statements and conclusions in theReport; but it is, of course, outside our competence to seek to resolve theseconflicts. Our conclusions with regard to each of the officers are given in later paragraphs. In addition, Sir Alan Hitchman, Permanent Secretary to theMinistry of Agriculture and Fisheries, accepted our invitation to explain to uscertain matters on which we desired further information.3. There is no defined set of rules by which the confidence of the public in the administration of Government Departments can be secured and held.Incorruptibility and efficiency are two obvious requirements. In the present case corruption has not been in question; inefficiency has. Beyond that it isdifficult to particularise. But the present case seems to us to emphasise one further factor which may be less self-evident but which we regard as of thehighest importance. In present times the interests of the private citizen are affected to a great extent by the actions of Civil Servants. It is the more necessary that the Civil Servant should bear constantly in mind that the citizen has a right to expect, not only that his affairs will be dealt with effectivelyand expeditiously, but also that his personal feelings, no less than his rights as an individual, will be sympathetically and fairly considered. We think thatthe admitted shortcomings in this respect are the main cause of such loss ofpublic confidence as has resulted from the present case.4. Turning to the five individual officers already mentioned: Mr. C. G. Eastwood is Permanent Commissioner of Crown Lands, havingbeen appointed to that post in October, 1952.   His rank in the service
is that of Under Secretary. This post is an &apos; independent command&apos;and its holder is therefore required to exercise more independent judgmentthan is usual for Under Secretaries in Government Departments. Inthese circumstances and having regard to the terms of the letter that hewrote on 23rd March, 1953, we cannot escape the conclusion that hisusefulness as a public servant would be impaired if he were to remainin his present post. We are therefore of the opinion that it would bein the public interest that he should be transferred to other duties. Inmaking this recommendation we take into account the facts thatMr. Eastwood&apos;s considerable experience in other spheres of Governmentadministration should provide him with undoubted opportunities of usefulservice elsewhere, and that, in view of the short tenure of his presentoffice, the administration of Crown Lands would not suffer.5. Mr. C. H. M. Wilcox was at the period covered by the public inquiry the under Secretary in the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries responsiblefor the Land and Land Use Divisions and for the Education and AdvisoryServices Division. He was transferred on 1st May, 1954 to the post OfPrincipal Finance Officer to the Ministry, still in the rank of UnderSecretary. We were informed that his transfer to his present post wasmade in the normal course of events and had indeed been planned somemonths before the public inquiry was held. Had Mr. Wilcox remained in his previous post, it is obvious that, having regard to the letters thathe wrote on 25th March and 8th September, 1953, we should have hadto consider seriously whether his transfer to other work would not havebeen necessary in the public interest and in the interest of the efficient working of the Ministry. But in the circumstances outlined above theonly question before us is whether we should recommend his transfer from his present post. The duties which he is called upon to perform inthat capacity are essentially different from those which he previouslyperformed and call for fewer and different contacts with outside bodies and individuals. In these circumstances we do not recommend anyfurther action.6. Mr. L. J. Smith is a Principal in the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisherieswho at the material time in 1953 was serving as Secretary to theAgricultural Land Commission. In January, 1954 he was lent to theMinistry of Agriculture of a foreign Government under the auspices ofthe Mutual Security Administration, for a period of one year in the firstinstance. In the circumstances Mr. Smith was not available to give evidence at the public inquiry, a fact on which Sir Andrew Clark expressedregret. We share that regret and consider that his absence was detrimental to bis interests. As Mr. Smith was in London during our sittings wewere able to interview him. Having read his observations and heardwhat he had to say, we are satisfied that there is no occasion for any action with regard to him.7. Mr. D. A. Hole has served for some 24 years in the Agricultural LandService of the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries. He is, and was atthe time of the inquiry, the Provincial Land Commissioner for the South-Western Province of England. Although we do not think that Mr. Hole&apos;section can properly escape all criticism, they were not such as to impairhis usefulness as an officer of the Agricultural Land Service in his presentpost. We accordingly recommend that no action should be taken withregard to him.
- f8. Mr. R. G. A. Lofthouse was from November, 1950 until December, 1952ii! a Land Commissioner in the Agricultural Land Service, responsible forSomerset and Dorset. In the latter month he was promoted to ProvincialLand Commissioner and transferred to the headquarters of the ministry in London. In his present post he is brought little into contact withany of the bodies or individuals mentioned in the report and is engaged on an entirely different type of work. We conclude that the publicinterest would not be served by transferring Mr. Lofthouse from theposition that he now occupies.9. Apart altogether from the treatment of the claims of former owners orof other applicants for tenancies, Sir Andrew Clark&apos;s Report is critical of theadministrative handling of the disposal of Crichel Down in a number of respects for example, the assessment of the financial implications, the preparation of reports, and the briefing of the Minister. His criticisms are in the mainexpressed in terms of the actions of individual officers. Having had theopportunity of considering not only the report but also the observations ofthe men concerned and of questioning them on the sequence of events, we thinkit material to record our strong impression that some part of the deficienciesdisclosed in the handling of this case may have been due as much to the organisational relationship between the headquarters of the Ministry ofAgriculture and Fisheries, the Agricultural Land Commission and theAgricultural Land Service as to the faults of individuals.We are, Sir,Your obedient Servants,J. H. WoodsMaurice HolmesW. H. Pilkington.14/// July, 1954.printed and published by her majesty&apos;s stationery office To be purchased from york House, Kingsway, London, w.c.2     423 Oxford Street, London, w.1P.o- Box 569, london, s.e.113a Castle Street, Edinburgh, 2      1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff39 King Street, Manchester, 2      Tower iLane, Bristol, 12 Edmund Street, Birmingham, 3      80 Chichester Street, belfast or from any Bookseller1954Price Zd. net printed    IN    GREAT    BRITAIN(30205)   Wt. 820-1958   K40   7/54   D.L.

</content>
</cab>
