<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/69/0 images: 211-212</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.(54) 244 COPY NO.20th July, 1954CABINETTHE INDEPENDENT TELEVISION AUTHORITYMemorandum by the Postmaster-general as so many of my colleagues have expressed interest and indeedsome concern about the membership of the Independent Television Authority,I feel that the best way of getting their joint opinion is to put my proposals before them.2.        These are as follows:-Chairman The Rt. Hon. Lord Soulbury, Governor-General of Ceylon.Deputy-Chairman    Sir Henry Hinchliffe, Director of Barclay&apos;sBank and ex-President of the ManchesterChamber of Commerce and of the Associationof British Chambers of Commerce.Members Sir Kenneth Clark, Chairman of the Arts Council.Miss Margaret Popham, former Principal ofCheltenham College.Miss Dilys Powell (film critic)or, failing her acceptance,Mr. Ivor Brown (author and journalist).A practising Chartered Account (to be agreed with the Chancellor of the Exchequer).A Trade Union representative.    If the TradeUnion movement wishes to be represented onthe Authority, their nominee would probablybe Mr. Jack Tanner.     (If the Trade union movement does not wish to be represented,I suggest either Mr. Aidan Crawley or mr. D. R. Hardman, both of them ex-labour. Ps. and junior Ministers. )Mr. Tom Honeyman, representing Scotland.Lord Aberdare, representing Wales.Lt. -Colonel Arthur Chichester, representingNorthern Ireland.^THeTdOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET62-
3.    For the post of Chairman, I have considered a number of alterna-tives, but I prefer Lord Soulbury.    Although not a very dynamic personality,he has been Minister of Education (a good answer to the fears expressedby critics about how children would fare under our proposals).    He hasalso been Chairman of the National Assistance Board, even under aSocialist Government, and was actually appointed Governor-General of ceylon by them, which makes him a happy choice from the political pointof view.    On the proposed Authority as a whole, there are a number ofyounger and more dynamic personalities, but the position of its Chairmanreally calls for judgment and tact rather than any great drive.4.        The alternatives I have considered include Lord Hudson,Lord Coleraine and Air Chief Marshal Sir William Elliot.    BothLord Hudson and Lord Coleraine have only recently retired from activeParty politics in the House of Commons, and Lord Hudson in particularhas sometimes been a rather controversial figure.    Air Chief marshal sir William Elliot is, of course, a first-class person, but in this casepolitical experience in the widest sense is what is particularly needed.5.        The names I have proposed would produce a well-balanced team,at least comparable in standing to the Governors of the B. B. C.    Thereare many urgent decisions to be taken by the Authority if the new system is to be on the air before the end of 1955.    I have already warned some ofmy colleagues of the difficulties in any event of bringing this about.    Anyfurther delay might well prove fatal to our prospects of doing so.D.Post Office Headquarters, E. C.l.20th July, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
