<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/69/0 images: 213-219</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET Copy- No. - * *C. (54) 24521st July, 1954CABINETCYPRUSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the colonies and the Minister of StateIIn this paper we propose a statement of Her Majesty&apos;s Government^ policy for Cyprus, including reference to the introduction of a new Constitution, and we discuss the probable effects of this statement on Anglo-Greek and Anglo-Turkishrelations, and also the way in which the Cyprus question should be handled at theforthcoming meeting of the General Assembly of the United Nations.Policy of the Greek Government2. Although the Greek claim to Cyprus has existed for many years, GreekGovernments since the war, prior to the present Government, refrained fromsupporting agitation for Enosis. The Government of Field-Marshal Papagoshave, however, taken the question up with great energy and have asked her majesty&apos;s Government to engage in bilateral talks on the future of the island.They have let it be understood that, if these talks take place, they would putforward proposals for representative government in Cyprus for a few years, to befollowed by a plebiscite on the issue of union with Greece. Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment have refused to enter into negotiations with the Greek Government, andhave given the Greek Government no encouragement to believe that this attitudewill be changed in the future. The Greek Government have stated that, if we continue to refuse, they will put the question on the agenda of the United nations on 22nd August-presumably on the grounds of refusal of the &quot;right to self-determination.&quot; Meanwhile, they are canvassing support in every possible quarter,including the Council of Europe. They emphasise the reasonableness of theirattitude by saying that they will grant us bases in a Greek Cyprus and else wherein Greece.3. They have been warned by Her Majesty&apos;s Government that nothing butharm can result from the reference of the Cyprus question to the United Nations,and have been given no encouragement to believe that Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentwould yiekUn any way to Greek claims. We propose below that a new statementof policy should include a reaffirmation that we can contemplate no change in the sovereignty of Cyprus. This will be taken by the Greeks as a rebuff, particularly by Field-Marshal Papagos himself, and there will doubtless be anti-British out-bursts in Greece. In the opinion of Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Athens, theembitterment in our relations must be expected to continue. We must, therefore,act on the assumption that deterioration in our relations with Greece is the pricewe must pay if we are to keep Cyprus. A point may even come at which we shallhave to decide whether Cyprus is strategically more important to us than Greece.Anglo-Turkish Relations4.   On the other hand, announcement of our decision to allow no change inthe status of Cyprus will be welcome to the Turkish Government. Their attitude46537 b,Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1954
towards proposals for constitutional reform may be more reserved; but in generalthe more limited the changes contemplated, the better they will be received inTurkey.n5. To avoid occasion for international controversy we have done our best inrecent years to keep Cyprus out of the news. Any statements that we have had tomake about the movement for union with Greece have been confined to sayingshortly that Her Majesty&apos;s Government regarded the question of any change insovereignty as closed. On constitutional advance we have simply left it that theliberal type of Constitution offered in 1948, and not taken up by the Cypriots, was still available as soon as sufficient responsible elements asked for it.6. We are satisfied that this negative line is no longer adequate. TheGovernor reports growing bewilderment in Cyprus itself. The Greeks have goneso far that no reticence of ours will restrain them, and are piqued by our silence on constitutional reform. Finally, our attitude must be made clear for the sake ofan uncertain public opinion in this country, and also for the guidance of friendlynations in advance of the United Nations General Assembly.The Present Constitution in Cyprus7. The representative Legislative Council was abolished in 1931, after riots,and Cyprus is now governed by the Governor, advised by a nominated ExecutiveCouncil The continued absence of a representative element at the centre isdifficult to defend, and a new Constitution conferring virtually complete internal self-government was offered but refused in 1948. This is set out in more detail in annex 1.The Strategic Position8. In 1950 the Chiefs of Staff were emphatically of the opinion that our strategic needs in Cyprus could be met, both now and in the foreseeable future,only if full sovereignty were retained. A copy of the questions then put to theChiefs of Staff, and their answers, is given in Annex 2. It was recently announcedthat Headquarters, Middle East Land Forces, were to be transferred eventually to cyprus. We have assumed that the strategic argument for retention of full sovereignty over Cyprus is at least as strong to-day as in 1950.The &quot; Right to Self-Determination &quot;9. The Greek Governmenfs argument is that constitutional advance in cyprus should lead, in the near future, to the Cypriots being given the opportunityto choose their place within or without the Commonwealth. The Nationalists in cyprus have indeed hitherto stood for immediate union with Greece, and nothing else; but there are indications that they may acquiesce in the Greek Governmenfsline. The view we take is that, although it would make things easier for us in theinternational field if we could make some statement about ultimate self-determination, it would be a great mistake to do so. The Governor advises in the strongest terms that any statement that Her Majesty&apos;s Government contemplateaccording self-determination, at some time in the future, whether by means of a plebiscite or even as the result of a process of constitutional advance, will be interpreted as a weakening of our determination to maintain our position and soonly add to the present unsettlement in the island. Besides, once we promise self-determination, we shall be under strong pressure to name a date for its exercise,whereas we cannot at this stage see beyond a situation in which, on strategicgrounds, we could not risk conceding it. We therefore conclude that an announce-ment of immediate constitutional advance, as discussed below, must be coupled with the firm statement that this must be within the continued sovereignty of her majesty&apos;s Government over the island./TIT... fe^fe^ ,.;,,w&apos;&apos;..10. Before indicating the possibility of constitutional advance, we brieflysummarise the rather complicated internal political situation in Cyprus at present.
The Movement for Enosis in Cyprus11. The Nationalist movement is led by Archbishop Makarios and the&quot; Ethnarchy &quot; of the Orthodox Church. There are no middle-road political parties.The anti-clericals are Communist-dominated. They, too, stand for Enosis, as amatter of political tactics. The villagers tend to be dominated by the Church, andthe townspeople by one or other of the political parties, but the Enosis movement is kept active only by the extremists. In between, there is a considerable body of moderate opinion amongst the Greek-speaking population who realise that union with Greece would gravely jeopardise their present economic prosperity, not to mention the maintenance of law and order and the enjoyment of civil liberties.The Turkish-speaking minority are, of course, violently opposed to Enosis, and donot want a Constitution. Whilst, therefore, the sentimental attachment to Greeceamong the Greek-speaking inhabitants must not be underrated, the proportion ofthe people that actively wants immediate Enosis is easily exaggerated by currentpropaganda.12. The Governor believes that the lack of any recent full policy statement by her Majesty&apos;s Government has led many of the moderates, and indeed some of thecivil servants, to question whether Her Majesty&apos;s Government really intend to stayon in Cyprus. His view is that a containment of the Enosis movement is overdue,and that this calls for the dispelling of the notion that Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentmay allow self-determination for Cyprus. It also calls, he suggests, for the enforce-ment of the existing laws against sedition, particularly against the press and ifnecessary against clerical or other political leaders. The recent latitude which hasbeen allowed them has, in the Governors view, had a seriously unsettling effect.Constitutional Proposals&quot;hi13. Since he arrived in Cyprus in February, the new Governor (Sir RobertArmitage) has sounded opinion as far as he can on constitutional change. He has reached the view that the Constitution offered in 1948 is unworkable. The chiefreasons for this are that (a) the Nationalists and Communists fight shy of a Legis-lative Council elected on a general franchise, because each fears that the otherwould obtain power and attempt to proscribe its opponents, and (b) such an assembly would be used by Cypriot politicians mainly for discussing Enosis, andnot for tackling the day-to-day problems of government. We accept his advice on this point, and believe with him that the best hope of achieving orderly con-stitutional progress would be for Her Majesty&apos;s Government to impose a more restricted type of Constitution, as a first step. The aim would be to bring in asfar as possible all those elements that were willing to co-operate in self-government.14.   The outline of the Governor^ proposals is as follows:  A legislature will be brought into being, consisting of about 33 members,of whom 6 will be officials, and 12 nominated unofficial members. Therewould be a minority of about 15 members elected by constituencies. Of these,12 would be Greek-speaking, and 3 Turkish-speaking Cypriots. The governor has not yet furnished details of qualifications of electors, &amp;c, and urges thatno more information about the proposed constitution should be announced at present than is given in paragraph 4 of the draft statement in Annex 3.A number of nominated or elected members from the legislature would beadded to the present Executive Council; and the Governor proposes that afew of these should be entrusted with the supervision of departments. The.  :&quot;. Governor would have the usual reserved powers.IV15. We believe that the announcement of a policy along these lines offers the best course open to us, and that this announcement should be made beforethe subject comes up at the United Nations. In reaching this conclusion, wehave taken account of the repercussions of such an announcement on our relationswith Greece and Turkey, and of the problem of presenting our case at the united nations and elsewhere. 0Policy at the General Assembly16. In both the General Committee and the Plenary Assembly we proposeto oppose the inclusion of the Cyprus item in the. agenda. At each of these stages46537 b 2
our case will have to be based mainly on legal grounds, i.e., the absence of anyUnited Nations competence to intervene in the domestic affairs of Cyprus, as wemust for reasons of principle refuse to discuss the substance of the Cyprus issue.But points of substance which tell in our favour may be introduced parentheticallyand in consultations with friendly delegations, and the leader of the UnitedKingdom Delegation should have discretion to decide the emphasis which at eachstage, he places upon the legal issues and upon other considerations, bearing inmind that his objective throughout will be to employ the most effective meansof preventing the inclusion of the item on the Assembly&apos;s agenda. If, despiteour efforts, the item is inscribed on the agenda, or the substance of the Cyprusquestion is otherwise brought up for discussion in an Assembly committee, sothat it is the specific subject of debate, then the United Kingdom Delegation would proceed as laid down in CP. (52) 232, viz., the leader would have authority to threaten to withdraw our representative from the discussion. The threat wouldnot, however, be carried out without prior reference to London except as in resort.Within these broad limits the leader of the United Kingdom Delegation shouldhave discretion to exploit to the full the threat of withdrawal in whatever mannerseems the most likely to prevent a debate on Cyprus.17. There is no means by which our decision to retain Cyprus indefinitelycan be made palatable to the Greeks, and we must assume that they will go on with their efforts to secure discussion of this question in the United Nations. Wecan only combine our firmness with courtesy, and try to prevent the Cyprusquestion affecting our relations in other fields. We propose that the GreekGovernment (and also the Turkish Government) should, as a friendly gesture,be informed in advance of our intended statement. The United States Govern-ment tried, at our instance, to dissuade the Greek Government from proceeding with their appeal to the United Nations. The strategic arguments in favour ofour retention of Cyprus carry some weight in American military circles, and theannouncement of a programme for the progressive introduction of self-govern-ment will be of some help with American public opinion. But the absence of anypromise of ultimate self-determination for Cyprus may prove to be the decidingfactor, and we cannot count on strong American support in public. We shall,however, continue to try to induce the Americans to refrain from activelysupporting the Greek case.Conclusions18.   We seek the agreement of our colleagues to the following:  (i) That for strategic reasons, full sovereignty over Cyprus must be maintained in the foreseeable future;(ii) that no statement should be attempted that Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentmay at some date in the future be able to contemplate self-determinationfor Cyprus, but that on the contrary it should be reaffirmed that theycannot contemplate any change in sovereignty;(iii) that the 1948 offer of a Constitution should be withdrawn, and that amore limited type of self-governing institutions should instead be imposed at the earliest practicable date;(iv) that the new Constitution should be in the form outlined in paragraph 14of this memorandum;v.      (v) that an early statement should be made in Parliament along the lines of annex 3;(vi) that the Governor should be authorised to take such steps as are necessaryto ensure the enforcement of existing laws; and(vii) that the matter should be handled at the United Nations in the wayouh v;:^proposedin,SectionIV pf-this memorandum, ,;21st July, 1954.
ANNEX 1The Acquisition of Cyprus by Her Majesty&apos;s Government and the background to the Movement for Union with Greece (Enosis)Great Britain assumed responsibility for the adminstration of Cyprus in 1878with the agreement of the Ottoman Empire in order to provide a base to combatRussian expansionist aims. The island was annexed when war broke out with turkey in 1914, the annexure was confirmed by the Treaty of Lausanne in 1923,and Cyprus has remained a colony since then.  Our legal title is incontrovertible.2. In 1878 Greek-speaking Cypriots and Turks each comprised approximatelyhalf the population. Since that time Greek-speaking Cypriots have increased muchmore rapidly than the Turks and now constitute about four-fifths of the population,the Turks being about one-sixth.  The total population is about 500,000.3. Among the Greek-speaking Cypriots there has traditionally been a senti-mental and nationalistic movement for the union of Cyprus and Greece. TheAutocephalous Church of Cyprus, a branch of the Greek-Orthodox Church, hastraditionally led the movement and the chief exponent at the moment is Archbishop Makarios. He is supported by the Ethnarchy Council consisting of priests andlaymen. The Communist Party of Cyprus also agitates in favour of Enosis foropportunist reasons.4. The Enosis movement finds an echo in Greece and successive GreekGovernments have hoped that Her Majesty&apos;s Government would ultimately agreeto the cession of Cyprus to them. Till the present, however, their desire to preserveAnglo-Greek friendship has prevented them from taking any active steps to thisend. They still claim that they desire the cession of Cyprus to take place in an atmosphere of Anglo-Greek friendship.5. Successive Turkish Governments have made it clear that they  would not agree to the cession of Cyprus to Greece. They have sound historic, geographicand other reasons for this. Cyprus was Turkish for 300 years. It has never beenGreek. The island is 40 miles from Turkey; it is hundreds of miles from mainlandGreece. Geographically it is part of Asia Minor. There is a large minorityundoubtedly Turkish in origin. The Greek-speaking Cypriot population is of doubtful ethnic provenance.6. In 1950 the Archbishop, adopting an idea first put forward by the Com-munists, organised a so-called plebiscite in which Greek-speaking Cypriots were invited to annex their names to a statement in favour of the cession of the island to Greece. In a public letter issued before the &quot; plebiscite &quot; the Governor made it clear that the view of His Majesty&apos;s Government was that it constituted nothing more than an invitation to amass signatures in favour of a resolution on a questionwhich in practice did not arise; and that in these circumstances many people couldbe expected to sign without giving any real indication of their views.The Background to Constitutional Development7. In 1882 a Constitution was introduced in Cyprus in which there was an elected majority in the Legislature. This Constitution survived, subject to a numberof changes until 1931 when Enosis agitation, culminating in the burning down ofGovernment House by a mob, led to its suspension. Cyprus is now governed bya Governor advised by a wholly nominated Executive Council, including twoCypriot Greek-speaking unofficials and one Turk.8. In 1948 His Majesty&apos;s Government made the offer of a new constitution for Cyprus incorporating a Legislature with a large unofficial- majority and con-ferring virtually complete internal self-government. It appeared that the proposals were, unacceptable to public opinion in Cyprus. The Greek Nationalists (led bythe Archbishop) and the Communists both insisted that there was no substitute for union with Greece. In these circumstances it was agreed that it was of nouse to proceed. It was announced, however,- and this had been repeatedlyconfirmed, that the offer of a Constitution was not withdrawn, and that it would bere considered if &quot; responsible and fully representative political leaders in Cypruscome forward .... or there is any genuine manifestation of public opinion intheir favour.&quot;
ANNEX 2The Strategic Importance of Retaining Sovereignty over CyprusThe questions put to the Chiefs of Staff in 1950, and the answers made by them were as follows:  Question (1). &quot; Can an estimate be given of the minimum facilities which wemust have in Cyprus now and in the foreseeable future? &quot;Answer. The minimum facilities we require in Cyprus are:  (a) A free hand to station in Cyprus, in peace, that part of the British middle east forces which may be considered necessary, at any time, to meetthe strategic situation.(b) The right to develop the airfields necessary to support allied strategy.Question (2). &quot; If it is possible to make this estimate, are the facilities inquestion so extensive or of such a character that it is essential for the sovereigntyand ultimate civil authority to remain British? &quot;Answer. Yes. The retention in the long term of the military facilities whichwe require in Cyprus can only be assured if Cyprus remains under british sovereignty. Furthermore the effect on Turkey and other Middle East countries and indeed on the United States of any abrogation of British sovereignty is likelyto be so serious that it is strategically necessary for Cyprus to remain British.Question (3). &quot;If Cyprus must remain British territory, do strategic con-siderations require its indefinite retention or can an end be seen to the need? Inthe latter event would the Chiefs of Staff see objection to a public undertakingbeing given to review the status of the Island after a period of say 10 to 15 yearssupposing that other considerations made such an undertaking seem desirable? &quot;Answer, So long as the United Kingdom wishes to retain her position in theMiddle East, Cyprus must remain under British sovereignty. It is moreoveressential that Cyprus does not come under Communist control in peace.We see no reason therefore for any public undertaking to review the situationafter any future period; we consider such an announcement undesirable, as it would encourage the subversive elements in Cyprus and discourage our Middle EasternAllies.ANNEX 3Proposed Text of Public StatementHer Majesty&apos;s Government have decided that the time has come to take afresh initiative in the development of self-governing institutions in Cyprus. Theyare convinced that given goodwill, an early start can be made in associating thepeople of Cyprus in the fuller management of their own affairs.2. Her Majesty&apos;s Government wish to make it clear once again that theycannot contemplate a change in the sovereignty of Cyprus. [British administration in Cyprus, besides bringing much prosperity to the island and safeguarding therights of all sections of the population, has maintained and still maintains stableconditions in this vital strategic area. Nothing less than continued sovereignty over the island can enable this country to carry out its strategic obligations inEurope, the Mediterranean and the Middle East.]*3. Her Majesty&apos;s Government are also resolved to continue their vigorouspolicy of economic development in Cyprus. The efficient administration in the island, in which a large number of Cypriots play a most effective part, has broughtabout vast improvements in health, agriculture, communications and many other fields. Since the war great strides have been made, thanks to a stable currencylinked to sterling, and a sound budgetary policy. Cyprus has access to the Londonloan market on the favourable terms which are available to Colonial Governments.The Government^ plans for economic development are estimated to cost* We should be glad to have the advice of our colleagues on whether this passage should beincluded in the statement.
 15i millions over the ten-year period 1946-56. Substantial direct assistance hasbeen given from United Kingdom funds under the Colonial Development and welfare Acts and Cyprus will receive assistance from the additional funds which parliament will be asked to provide for Colonial Development and Welfare.Water supplies have been piped to hundreds of villages, denuded mountains havebeen reafforested, malaria has been expelled, the effects of soil erosion are beingvigorously combated and industry has been encouraged and developed. Thequestion of port development is at this moment being actively studied.4. The proposed constitutional arrangements have not yet been worked outin detail, but will be broadly as follows. In 1948 a Constitution was offered whichwould have given a high degree of internal self-government, but, although theoffer has remained open for six years, it has not been taken up by responsibleand representative political leaders. Her Majesty&apos;s Government have therefore decided to wait no longer but to introduce in the near future a modified Constitu-tion providing for a Legislature containing both official and nominated members(together forming a majority) and elected members and also the appointment ofsome unofficial members of the Legislature to take charge of Departments. Thiswill mark a first step along the road of constitutional advancement and will enableCypriots to take a part in operating self-governing institutions and exercisingresponsibility both in legislation and in the executive control of administration.The Governor has been instructed to take all action necessary in preparation forthe introduction of a new Constitution on these lines.5. Her Majesty&apos;s Government fully recognise that the Greek-speaking and turkish-speaking parts of the population have close cultural links with greece and Turkey. Without sacrifice of these traditions, Cypriots have before them the prospect of expanding opportunities in economic, social and constitutional development.

</content>
</cab>
