<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/16/11 images: 176-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet   April 1941.HOST SECRET.W.P. (41) 88.iprtf 20, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.NEW CONSTRUCTION PROGRAMME.  1941.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.I.-PROGRAMME AND POLICY.1.   The proposed New Construction Programme for 1941 is : 1 Monitor.!3 Medium Cruisers (6-inch).2 Fast Minelayers.40 Destroyers.14 Sloops.36 Submarines (including 3 already approved by Treasury).19 Fast Corvette-Minesweepers.15 Coastal Minesweepers.9 Trawlers.32 M.T.B.&apos;s32 110-ft. M.L.&quot;s, Type B97 72-ft. M.L.&apos;s.1 Boom Defence Vessel.3 Tank Assault Ships.t8 Tank Landing Craft.120 lengthened Tank Landing Craft.79 Assault Landing Craft.tf Already ordered, with Treasury approval.[22391] copy No.
14 Support Landing Craft.t10 Rescue Tugs (including 4 already approved by Treasury).4 Salvage Vessels (already approved by Treasury).1 Floating Dock.Miscellaneous craft as set out in para. 41 below.I expect that a supplementary estimate will be necessary later in the yearto cover further small craft, whose numbers and types will be dependent onexperience gained during the spring and summer of 1941 with the small craftalready completed.Additional requirements which may he met from the United States of America.The United States Government have agreed to release to the Royal Navv10 coastguard cutters and 28 M.T.B.&apos;s from the United States Navy. There arealso prospects of the release of further destroyers and/or coastguard cutters.The following additional requirements of ships for naval purposes have beennotified to the United States Administration for fulfilment, as far as possible,under the Lease-Lend scheme :  7 Tank Assault ships.12 Motor Vessels for conversion to Auxiliary Aircraft Carriers.60 Trawlers for A/S and M/S purposes.15 Yachts.2 Floating Docks.265 Motor Boats (for various services M.T.B.&apos;s, Motor Minesweepers.Rescue Craft, Raiding Craft, &amp;c).12 Salvage vessels.16 Steam (or Motor) Gun Boats (originally intended to form part of1940 Supplementary Programme).These requirements, except those covered by previous programmes, areadditional to the 1941 Programme. It is impossible at present to forecast theextent to which they will actually be obtainable from the U.S.A.2. The following ships outstanding from the supplementary programme for1940 or earlier programmes will now have to be laid down during the coming financial year or later : 1 Aircraft Carrier.4 Heavy Cruisers.4 Sloops.16 Fast Corvette-Minesweepers.21 Trawlers.2 Steam Gun Boats.40 110-ft.  M.L.&apos;s,  Type  D  (in  substitution  for  25   S.G.B.&apos;s and15 M.A/S.B.&apos;s):15 Boom Defence Vessels.Certain miscellaneous craft.f Already ordered, with Treasury approval.
3 &quot; r -General Policy.3. The Emergency War and 1940 Programmes were based on the immediateneeds of the Naval situation created by the War. It is now desirable to take steps towards resumption of a long-term policy, as recommended in the Chiefs ofStaff review of future strategy (CCS. (40) 683).4. Nevertheless, the special demands of the War still impose a severe limit on the long-term Naval construction which can be put in hand. The materialneeds of the tank programme and the man-power requirements for repairs,particularly to merchant vessels, make it impossible for the present to lay down orresume work upon several of the heavier ships which, on a long view, should betaken in hand now. I have referred to these in the detailed statement which follows, and I propose to review the situation in September, by which time I hopethe labour and material position may have improved sufficiently to permit more active measures towards the fulfilment of long-term needs. When these needs are considered, I trust it will be remembered that we cannot yet predict the lengthof the War, our future losses, or what other Powers will be drawn into thestraggle. There is, therefore, no justification for relaxing our ship-buildingefforts on the plea that such and such a ship is unlikely to complete in time to beof use in the present conflict.5. For the rest, in framing this 1941 Programme, the Admiralty have adopted the general policy of continuing to employ to the utmost the Naval ship-building capacity which will be freed during the year by the completion of earlier vessels. Due regard has been had to the importance of not trenching upon ,the output of merchant shipping, which has now been set at 1,100,000 tons a year. tWMCfti)It will be appreciated that the transfer of men to merchant repairs will meanslower progress on new ships. For this reason a considerable increase in thelabour forces of the industry is essential.II. ANALYSIS OF PROGRAMME BY CLASSES.A. Capital Ships.6. The way now seems clear to the completion of the King George V class and V anguard. For some time to come Merchant Shipping repairs, because ofthe higher priority accorded to them, must absorb labour which could otherwise be employed on the other outstanding capital ships. The better weather of the summer, and relief obtained from the use of repair facilities in the United Statesof America, may, however, lessen the demands of repairs in the United Kingdom ata later stage. I propose therefore to reconsider in September the resumption ofwork on Lion and Temeraire and the construction of Conqueror and Thunderer.7. Pending this later review, I include no capital ships in the 1941Programme, although the estimated strength of Germany, Italy and Japan inthe next six years considerably exceeds that which we shall attain.[22391] b 2
B. Monitors.8. In view of the recent loss of one of our two existing monitors, and ofthe Chiefs of Staff recommendation in CCS. (40) 683 that a second new monitorshould be built, one new monitor is included in this programme. The ship wouldbe a repetition of the Roberts, and carry the one remaining spare 15-inch turret.It would only occupy a slip for 9 months, and could be completed in 1942.C Aircraft Carriers.9. In W.M. (40) 277th conclusions, the War Cabinet gave approval for one further carrier, after Indefatigable, to be considered early in 1941. Our require-ment is, however, for no less than four more carriers in order to provide accom-modation for the 550 first line carrier-borne aircraft contemplated in the 1938naval air expansion programme. Two of these carriers would replace Courageousand Glorious.10. It is clearly not feasible, however, to lay down four new carriers withoutunbalancing the whole programme. At present only one could be undertaken.This would be the carrier outstanding from the 1940 supplementary programme and will be laid down at a date to be fixed after review in September.I have retained provision for this carrier in the financial statement (Table II)appended to this paper. I include no carriers in the present programme for 1941.though I desire to reserve the right to seek approval to lay down one more later in the year if the labour and material position improves sufficiently.D. Cruisers.Heavy Cruisers.11. In the 1940 Supplementary Programme, 4 cruisers were approved, of atype to be agreed later. I have reached the conclusion that, when built, these should be 8-inch cruisers, for two main reasons :  (i) The 8-inch gun is the smallest calibre capable of effective fire up to thelimits of accurate R.D.F. rangetaking.(ii) The United States Government have avowed their intention of con-tinuing 8-inch-cruiser construction.    While they continue in this intention, other Powers will not abandon the construction of 8-inch cruisers, nor can we afford to do so.The supply of armour plate will not, however, allow of these ships beingstarted at present. I accordingly ask for approval of the principle that our nextheavy cruisers should have Q-inch guns, and if this is given, I shall review thesituation in September and shall then make a fresh submission if material is available for any of these vessels. I consider it important to lay down not lessthan 4 such ships at the earliest possible moment. I have retained provision forthese ships in the financial statement (Table II).
Medium Cruisers.12. In view of our great need for cruisers, I consider that we ought not altogether to cease to lay down new vessels of this class as suitable slipsbecome vacant. I accordingly seek authority to include in this year&apos;s programme Q-inch cruisers of the Fiji Class, tvith improvements. These ships will be laiddown at an early date, and can be undertaken within the limits of the estimatedsupplies from existing armour plate capacity.13. Even if the four heavy cruisers were approved and laid down later&apos; inthe year, this programme would give us by the end of 1945, disregarding furtherlosses, only the following cruiser strength :  Under age.  Over age.      Total.Heavy cruisers with 8 or more8-inch guns.........       17 0 17Medium cruisers with 6 8-inchor 9 to 12 6-inch guns     ...      25 2 27Light  cruisers  with  8  or  less6-inch, 5-25-inch or 4-5-inch guns.........       ...       29 15 4471 1.7 8814.   Our total cruiser requirement is still considered to be Heavy cruisers    ...       ...       ...       ...      20Medium cruisers ...       ...       ...       ...      40Light cruisers     ...       ...       ...       ...      40100   of which 15 maybe over age.E. Fast Minelayers.15. From experience with Adventure and destroyer minelayers, we must expect casualties amongst the 4 fast minelayers which are due to complete betweenMarch and May 1941. \It is proposed to lay clown 2 more fast minelayers this year, for completionin 1943, and in the meantime to strengthen our surface minelaying forces byfitting out 4 of the destroyers now under construction as alternative mine-layers.F. Destroyers.16. During the last war we needed, and built, some 300 destroyers. Theonly reason why our present destroyer programme falls below this number is theincreased complexity of design and equipment. Forty ships are, in fact, allwecan lay down this year, and I include 40 in the programme.[22391] b 3
17. In 18 months of war we have lost no less than 38 destroyers and A.A.destroyers, in addition to two Allied vessels, which can only be made good fromBritish sources. The rate of loss has risen since Italy came into the war, andmust now be estimated at between 30 and 36 a year. Consequently, this year&apos;squota of 40 will in all probability give only a small net increase in strength.18. Construction of further A.A. destroyers has been suspended in view ofthe greater value for ocean convoy work of sloops carrying the same armament.G. Sloops.19. In the 1940 Supplementary programme the decision was taken to stopbuilding A.A. destroyers of the &quot;Hunt&quot; class, and to substitute sloops of the&quot; Black Swan &quot; class, with the same armament, two-thirds of the speed and approximately double the endurance.20. This policy is now carried a stage further with a quota of 14 moresloops, in addition to four outstanding from the Supplementary Programme of1940, to be laid down in 1941 for completion in the latter part of 1943.H. Submarines.21. Submarine losses during the 18 months of war amount to 26 British and3 Allied, but, as with destroyers, the rate of loss has risen since Italy came in. andmust now be estimated at from 30 to 36 a year.22. I include 36 new submarines in this programme. This number is themost we can undertake this year, and is not likely to do much more than replacecasualties. Our present strength is still below that with which we startedthe war.23. Of the new submarines, 2 will be minelayers, which, with the 3 mine-layers in the 1940 Supplementary programme, should make adequate provisionfor future casualties.  We have so far lost 3 of our 6 submarine minelayers.I. Corvettes and Minesweepers.Corvette Minesweepers.24. The pressure of war conditions has driven the corvette and fleet mine-sweeper types closer together. The new fast corvette will be fitted for bothescort and minesweeping duties. Allocation between the two duties will depend upon the needs of the moment. From the minesweeping point of view, their principal advantage will be their high speed (not less than 20 knots), which is now necessary for combating the submarine. This should enable them to accompany the Fleet when necessary without unduly limiting the Fleet&apos;s speed.25. There remain 16 fast corvette minesweepers to be laid down under the1940 Supplementary programme.  A further 19 only can be undertaken this year,
since the increase in speed has led to increase in size, and therefore reductionin the number of yards which can take the new design. I accordingly include19 fast corvette-minesweepers in the new programme.Coastal Minesweepers.26. In addition to the dual-purpose vessels, a number of coastal mine-sweepers are required. The call for these has been greatly increased by our new commitments in the Mediterranean. / include 15, which is the most that can betaken by the yards suitable for the purpose.j. Trawlers.27. Losses of trawlers up to date have been approximately 85. Require-ments abroad and the need for trawlers to operate in open waters make increasing demands for this type of vessel. It is only possible to build 9 in/W-jfi, in addition /,to the 21 in the Supplementary Programme for 1940 which have not yet been laiddown. It is hoped, however, to obtain 60 from the United States, which will gotowards meeting deficiencies.K. Coastal Craft.M.T.B.&apos;s.28. With the completion of existing programmes, our strength in M.T.B.&apos;swill have been built up to 12 flotillas. The 32 M.T.B.&apos;s included in the 1941programme are designed to provide replacements, on the basis of a life of threeyears for such vessels. Additions to our ultimate strength will depend on furtherdeliveries from the U.S.A.s.g.b:s.29. Of the 50 Steam Gun Boats authorised in the past financial year, only7 have been laid clown. The difficulty is that their construction clashes withdestroyer building. Two additional boats will be ordered in the United kingdom to complete a flotilla of 8 plus 1 spare. The question of constructing 16 furtherboats of this type in the United States is under investigation, since they are likelyto prove the most effective form of craft for waging war against the E-boat. Inview of the conflict with destroyer building, / do not include in the 1941programme any S.G.B.&apos;s to be built in this country.m.l:s.30. In order to keep the Fairmile building organisation in being, in case a sudden call should come for a large increase in the numbers of Fairmile boats,and to allow for possible casualties, a 10 per cent, replacement programme isproposed in 1941.  This amounts to 32 110-ft. M.L.&apos;s (Type B).The replacement programme for 72-ft. M..L.&apos;s of Harbour Defence type was intended to be 17.   Recent events such as the attack on Sucla Bay have, hi wever,
shown the need for additional harbour defence craft on a fairly large scale, and I now propose that a total of 97 7 -ft. M.L.&apos;s should be included in the current programme.31. I propose to make up for the deficiency in Steam Gun Boats by a modification of the 110 ft. M.L. Forty of these, covered by previous programmes,are being ordered as a first instalment. This figure is made up by the substitution of these boats for the 25 S.G.B.&apos;s outstanding from the 1940 SupplementaryProgramme and 15 of the M.A/S. Boats outstanding from the 1940 Programme.L. Boom Defence Vessels.32. There are 15 Boom Defence Vessels outstanding from previous programmes, which it is hoped to lay down this year. It will only be possibleto lay down one other vessel of this class during the year, and I accordinglyinclude only one Boom Defence Vessel in this programme.M. Tank Assault Ships.33. To effect a landing, headed by Armoured Fighting Vehicles, at the endof a long sea voyage, it has been found necessary to provide special vessels. Asan immediate step, and to provide some such vessels for service in 1941, threeMaracaibo oilers have been taken up for conversion.34. For the 1942 campaign the full requirement of the Chiefs of Staff isfor 10 tank assault ships specially designed for combined operations.Arrangements have been made to construct three such vessels in the UnitedKingdom, in place of 6 of the old pattern corvettes dropped from the 1940programme. We are examining the possibility of constructing the other7 T.A.S.&apos;s in the United States of America.In. Landing Craft.35. Since the 1940 Supplementary Programme was approved, the C.O.S.Committee have adopted the policy of providing two sets of landing craft, eachsufficient for an invasion corps of two divisions, one set to be held in the middle east and one in Home Waters. In addition, provision has to be made forcasualties, and for the complete replacement annually of all craft employed onintensive training.36.   This requires a further programme of 8T.L.C.&apos;s.79 A.L.C.&apos;s.14 S.L.C&apos;8.37. In addition to these commitments, landing craft on a large scale maybe required for Cross-Channel ferry operations in 1942 or later. Experimentsare in hand with a lengthened T.L.C., which, if successful, may lead to an order
for 200 such craft. Of these the number for which approval is sought in this programme is 120, the maximum for which orders can be placed with the structural engineers before the 1st April, 1942.38. When not actually in use for combined operations these craft may well prove of great value for emergency service in ports whose normal facilities havebeen damaged by air attack. Special trials with this object in view have beenarranged.39. I hope to find a further use for T.L.C.&apos;s when not required for combined operations, and trials are shortly to be carried out. Each T.L.C. would carry a/T net baffles, and would be able to proceed alongside ships in harbour to giveprotection against air torpedo attack. About 8 T.L.C.&apos;s would be needed toprotect each battleship.0. Rescue Tugs and Salvage Vessels.40.   10 Rescue Tugs and 4 Salvage vessels are proposed.p. Floating Dock.41. There is an urgent need for additional docking facilities for light craftoff our N.W. Approaches. This requirement cannot be met from the two floatingdocks it is hoped to obtain from the U.S.A.. which are needed for Freetown. Ipropose, therefore, that the construction of a floating dock suitable for light craftshould be undertaken immediately at Devonport.Q. Small Miscellaneous Craft.42.   I include the following in the new programme :  2 Impetus class tugs.5 Self-propelled mooring vessels.3 Dumb mooring vessels.1 Controlled minelaying lighter.1 Torpedo recovery vessel.3 Small motor lighters.43. Annexed hereto are financial statements showing the estimated cost ofthis programme, separately, and in conjunction with the outstanding liabilities of previous programmes.A. V. A.Admiralty, S.W. 1,April 20, 1941.
ANNEX.These estimates can only be regarded as approximations giving an indication on broad lines of the order of expenditure likely to be incurred.Table I.Proposed New Construction Programme, 1941.Estimate of Expenditure.--	1941.	1942.	1943.	1944.	Total Estimated Cost.1 Monitor 3 6-in. Cruisers (Fiji type) 2 Fast minelayers 5 Destroyer flotillas (7th-11th emergency) 14 Sloops (Black Sivan) 19 Corvettes 18 &quot;T&quot; submarines 16 &quot; S &quot; submarines 2 Cachalot submarines 15 Minesweepers... 9 Trawlers       ......... 32 M.T.B.&apos;s       ......... 32    Fairmile    110-ft.     motor launches 97 72-ft. Harbour defence craft 1 B.D.V.......      ... 3 Tank assault ships   ... 120 Lengthened T.L.C....... 101 Landing craft (other types)... 4 Salvage vessels 12 Tugs............ 1 Floating Dock 13 Lighters, mooring vessels,&amp;c. Totals       ...         	  600,000 650,000 500,000 2,000,000 150,000 675,000 1,350,000 750,000 150,000 260,000 30,000 790,000 289,000 850,000 45,000 1,000,000 1,500,000 334,000 360,000 475,000 180,000 487,000	  500,000 2,450,000 1,000,000 10,000,000 2,400,000 3,250,000 3,750,000 2,500,000 400,000 2,600,000 470,000 1,210,000 479,000 508,000 40,000 300,000 4,250,000 330,000 240,000 465,000 188,000	  3,000,000 500,000 10,130,000 3,250,000 2,265,000 3,450,000 2,650,000 400,000 890,000 85,000 240.000 250,000	  2,150,000 2,670,000 500,000 900,000 900,000 250,000	  1.100,000 8,250,000 2,000,000 24,800,000 6,300,000 6,190,000 9,450,000 6,800,000 1,200,000 3,750,000 585,000 2,240,000 768,000 1,358,000 85,000 1,300,000 6,000,000 664,000 600,000 940,000 180,000 675,000	13,425,000	37,330,000	27,110,000	7,370,000	85,235,000
These estimates can only be regarded as approximations giving an indication on broad lines of the order of expenditure likely to be incurred.Table II.Revised Estimates for the 1940 Supplementary Programme of New Construction. 	1940	1941.	1942.	1943.	1944.	1945.	1946.	Total Estimated Cost.1 Aircraft carrier 4 Cruisers (8-inch)    .. 2 Destroyer    flotillas (5th and 6th emer-gency) 14 Sloops (Black Swan) 30 Corvettes    ...... 20 Minesweepers 8 Trawlers      ...... 4 B.D.V&apos;s....... 5 &quot; T &quot; submarines 7 &quot; s &quot; submarines   ... 12 &quot; U &quot; submarines   ... 3 Cachalot submarines 4 &quot; T &quot; submarines 7 &quot; s &quot; submarines 65 Landing craft 9 Steam gun boats   ... 40 Fairmile motor gun boats 60 Small minesweepers 65 T.L.C&apos;s. (new design) 7M.G.B&apos;s. (Higgins)... Total......	  30,000 650,000 300,000 1,000,000 400,000 150,000 600,000 140,000	  500,000 3,000,000 1,800,000 4,210,000 3.550,000 280,000 40,000 1,750,000 1,700,000 2,360,000 750,000 930,000 1,220,000 130,000 550,000 1,000,000 1,430,000 2,000,000 140,000	  1,800,000 2,000,000 4,500,000 3,500,000 4,900,000 1,210,000 240,000 240,000 100,000 800,000 850,000 . 1,000,000 1,500,000 200,000 1,800,000 550,000	  1,800,000 4,000,000 1,800,000 1,000,000 60,000 120,000 70,000 80,000 ... ...	  :   900,000 3,500,000	  250,000 3,000,000 ...	  1,500,000	  5,250,000 14,000,000 9,300,000 6,300,000 9,140,000 4,760,000 520,000 340,000 2,500,000 2,800,000 3,380,000 1,720,000 2,000,000 2,800,000 530,000 900,000 2,800,000 1,980,000 2,600,000 280,000	3,270,000 1 27,340,000		25,190,000	8,930,000	4,400,000	3,250,000	1,500,000	73.880,000
Table III.Estimated Cost of New Construction by Financial Years.1941.1942.1943.1944.Programmes up to and in-cluding 1.939 Programme(including Lion, Teiiie-raire, Conqueror andThunderer)Additions to 1939 Pro-gramme up to 1940 Pro-gramme1940 Programme and ad-ditions1940 Supplementary Pro-gramme19-11 ProgrammeTotal            I        32,250,000     20,000.000    14,500,000     10,500,00024,035,000 .    7,690,000      2,870,000 ;      500,00022,400,000     15,850,000 I    6,000,000      3,250,00027,340.000    25,190,000 I    s,930,000      4,400,000..&apos;   13,425,000    37,330,000 j   27,110,000 ;    7,370,0001945.1946.1947 8,000,0001,250.0003,250,000&apos;    4,000,0001,500,000 1,500,000119,450,000   106,060,000 j   59,410,000 !   26,020,000 [   12,500,0005,500,0001,500,000
Table III.Estimated Cost of New Construction by Financial Years.1941.1942.1943.1944,1945.1946.1947.    Programmes up to and in- !   32,250,000     20,000.000 i   14,500,000     10,500,000eluding 1939 Programme(including Lion, Tone- jraire,   Conqueror    andThunderer)Additions to 1939 Pro-gramme up to 1940 Pro-gramme1940 Programme and ad-d it-ions1940 Supplementary Pro-gramme1941 ProgrammeTotal24,035,000 .    7,690,000 ,    2,870,000500,00022,400,000    15,850,000 i    6,000,000 i    3,250,00027,340,000    25,190,000 \    8,930,000      4,400,000..    13,425,000    37,330,000 \   27,110,000 j    7,370,000 8,000,0001,250.0003,250,000 4,000,0001,500,000 1,500,000119,450,000   106,060,000 J   59,410,000 !   26,020,000 [   12,500,0005,500,0001,500,000
Table III.Estimated Cost of New Construction by Financial Years.1941.		1942.	1943.	1944.	1945.     j    1946.		1947.Programmes up to and in-cluding 1939 Programme (including Lion, Tenie-raire,   Conqueror   and Thunderer) Additions   to   1939  Pro-gramme up to 1940 Pro-gramme 1940 Programme and ad-ditions 1940 Supplementary Pro-gramme 1941 Programme	  32,250,000 24,035,000 22,400,000 27,340.000 13,425,000	  20,000,000 7,690,000 15,850,000 25,190,000 37,330,000	  14,500,000 2,870,000 6,000,000 8,930,000 27,110,000	  10,500,000 500,000 3,250,000 4,400,000 7,370,000	  8,000,000 ... 1,250,000 3,250,000	  4,000,000 1,500,000 &quot;&apos;	  1,500,000Total	119,450,000	106,060,000	59,410,000	26,020,000	12,500,000	5,500,000	1,500,000



</content>
</cab>
