<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 7-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
: O(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C. (60) 52 COPY NO.    \V15th March, I960CABINETTHE CROWTHER report memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer am shocked by the proposal to announce now the provisionof 8,000 more places in teachers&apos; training colleges and other improvement2. I annex the covering note to the officials&apos; interim report onthe economic and financial implications of the Crowther Report.   This isan interim report, circulated only a few days ago, not yet fully digestedeven by the officials.3. However, there appears to be no doubt that even on existing policy, the educational bill will increase by over  650 millions(80 per cent) by 1974.   Clearly we cannot undertake more:   the questionis whether we can do as much.   There is not only a problem for theExchequer:  the part to be borne by local rates will, on the same estimate,more than double in the 15-year period.4. This educational expansion (from 3. 9 per cent of gross national product to 5 per cent) must be put in perspective with other claims :-(i) V/e have before us a paper (C. (60) 35) which suggests that weshould continue to devote the same proportion of an expanding national income to defence, economic aid, and other expenditure in support of external policy.   In the last seven years, this has fallen from 12^: per cent of the gross national product to about 8^ per cent - this is why we havebeen able to have tax reductions and increased social expenditure.(ii) The Minister of Transport is preparing a 10-year roads programme which would about treble our rate of spending in the next five years.(iii) My colleagues know my preoccupation with the rate of growth of the cost of the National Health Service.(iv) We shall soon be discussing pensions again.(v) I must mention space research, civil aviation, and Cunarders.(vi) There are also railways.(vii) The Chairman of the Party Housing Committee is calling for a50,000 a year housing programme - an extra  400 millions a year callon resources (private and public) and on savings.-1-CONFIDENTIAL
5. With all these claims from all our policies pressing upon one another, I must ask my colleagues to stop and consider.   At the bestwe are dissipating the prospects of continuing tax reductions overthe years.   We may be running the economy into inflation.6. Against this backgraound in my opinion we could notwith honesty justify announcing additional educational improvementsnext week.   The cost of building and running the extra colleges is asmall part of the cost - the real point is the costof extra teachersproduced year after year - over  30 millions a year as early as 1974-7 5,and of course rising every year.7. I would have hoped that the Education Ministers could presentan effective story of achievement.   We are already intending, it appears,to increase by 80 per cent in 15 years the cost of maintaining a childat school.   If this is not waste, it must be a revolution in education.For example :-(i) Improving secondary school staffing ratio by over one-quarter(21.9 to 16), and reducing average junior classes to 30.(ii) Increasing number of teachers&apos; training college places from23,000 to 39,000.   This will lead to an increase in the number of teachers from 264,000 to 332,000 by 1970.   Enough both to abolishoversize classes and to raise the leaving age by 1975-1976 - only three years after what would be possible with 8, 000 extra places.(iii) The school building programme - 50-60 per cent of thechildren to be in post-war schools by 1970.(iv) Doubling the number of further education teachers by 1970.8, This seems to me an impressive list, and I am sure wecannot and should not announce more.D. H. A.Treasury Chambers, 5. W. 1.15th March, I960CONFIDENTIAL
annex note by the Chairman of the Committee of officials the Committee1 s interim report shows that, under &quot;existing policy&quot;, educational expenditure (excluding universities) is expectedto increase as follows:-1959       1964       1969       1974Educational expenditure  millions 816 1,034      1,236      1,472(1959 = 100) (100)       (127)       (151)        (180)Educational expenditure as a percentage of gross national Product 3.9 4.3 4.7 5.02. If the Crowther recommendations (and certain other reforms,such as the forthcoming Anderson report on awards to university students)are implemented, these figures will be increased as follows:-1959       1964       1969       1974Educational expenditure millions 816 1,077      1,327      1, 590(1959 = 100) (100)       (132)       (163)       (195)Educational expenditure asa percentage of gross national Product 3.9 4.5       . 5.0 5.43. These tables show that &quot;existing policy&quot; alone will causeeducational expenditure to rise from  816 millions in 1959 to 1,472 millions in 1974 and that implementation of the Crowther report,etc. would raise the 1974 total by  118 millions to  1, 590 millions.4. It is not within my Committee&apos;s purview to assess theseprospective increases of expenditure in relation to the ether objectives of Government policy.5. At this stage Ministers are not being invited to approve the Crowther report as a whole.   It is understood that the Minister ofEducation is seeking agreement to three main prcposals:-(i) An extra 8,000 training college places.(ii) Agreement in principle to raising the school,-leaving age to 16, but no decision yet on the date for doing so.(ii) An indefinite postponement of compulsory part-time dayeducation for all up to 18, but the accelerated expansion of furtherediVation on a voluntary basis.-3-CONFIDENTIAL
6. Teachers&apos; training places.   The supply of teachers is the keyto the reforms and the chief item in the bill. Assuming no inflation,each 10,000 new teachers will by 1975 be costing  15 millions a year in pay and superannuation.7. Two major reforms are envisaged - the abolition of oversizeclasses (reducing the secondary school staffing ratio from 21.8 to 16)and the raising of the school-leaving age to 16.   On present (Englandand Wales) teacher training (with 16,000 new places   under construction)both of these reforms can be done by 1975-1976, in whichever order seemsbest.   With 8,000 more places, an additional   15,000 teachers could be trained in time to complete these reforms by 1972-1973.8. The date of complete of these reforms - 1972-1973 or1975-1976 - must be weighed against:-(i) The cost of the new colleges ( 12^ millions):  and the cost of pay and superannuation for the extra teachers ( 31 millions in1974-1975).(ii) The extent of the prospective need for a continuing rapid growth in the teaching force after the objectives have been reached in 1972-1973.9. Raising the leaving age.   The cost of educating those whowould otherwise have left at 15 would be about  42 millions a year.   Newschool buildings at  92 millions would be needed (loan chargesabout  7 millions). In the relatively short run, these costs might bemet by going more slowly in removing oversize classes and in replacingand improving sub-standard buildings.10. There would also be a reduction of gross national product,which we put at about  125 millions a year, as a result of the removalof the 15-year-olds from the labour force.11. We estimate the net effect on current outgoings from public funds (taxes, rates, national insurance funds) at about  72 millions ayear.12. Further education.   An llf per cent per year increase ofexpenditure is implied in the Minister&apos;s proposal, compared with10 per cent on &quot;existing policy&quot;.     The cost would rise from thepresent  68 millions to  209 millions in 1974-1975 on  &quot;existing policy&quot;and  235 millions as proposed.10th March, I960....... : &apos;CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
