<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 11-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1960C. (60) 53 Copy No.   5 116th March, 1960CABINETBRITISH TRANSPORT commission memorandum by the Prime minister the Cabinet will remember that on Tuesday, 15th March, we consideredthree possible courses of action in relation to the Guillebaud Report:(-a) A statement by the Government promising the implementation of the guillebaud Report, on the expectation that the Unions will co-operate,as from the date of the Report.&apos;ib) A statement in similar terms but making no specific reference to a date,(c) Letting the next round of negotiations proceed in the first instance betweenthe British Transport Commission (acting of course under Ministerialdirection) and the Railway Unions.2. Attached is an Annex containing a draft statement, with alternatives(a) and (b) above.H. M.10 Dowmmg Street, S.W. I,&apos; l&amp;th Mar-ch, 19M.
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1960C. (60) 53 Copy No.   5 116th March, 1960CABINETBRITISH TRANSPORT commission memorandum by the Prime minister the Cabinet will remember that on Tuesday, 15th March, we consideredthree possible courses of action in relation to the Guillebaud Report:(a) A statement by the Government promising the implementation of the guillebaud Report, on the expectation that the Unions will co-operate,as from the date of the Report.&apos;ib) A statement in similar terms but making no specific reference to a date,(c) Letting the next round of negotiations proceed in the first instance betweenthe British Transport Commission (acting of course under Ministerialdirection) and the Railway Unions.2. Attached is an Annex containing a draft statement, with alternatives(a) and (b) above.H. M.10 Dowmmg Street, S.W. I,&apos; l&amp;th Mar-ch, 19M.
ANNEXSTATEMENT TO BE MADE BY THE MINISTER OF TRANSPORT to representatives OF THE BRITISH TRANSPORT COMMISSION. 3 AND THE TRADE unions on 10th March in the House of Commons the Prime Minister stated thatthe Government accepted the objective underlying the Guillebaud report thatfair and reasonable wages should be paid to those working in the industry.2. He also made it clear that the problems of the British transport commission could not be settled without all the others concerned accepting certain obligations, as follows:&quot;First, the industry must be of a size and pattern suited to modern conditions and prospects. In particular, the railway system must be remodelledto meet current needs, and the modernisation plan must be adapted to this new shape. Those working in the industry must accept this. This is the only way of bringing about conditions in which a fair reward, not only in termsof money, but of satisfaction with their job, can be secured.Secondly, the public must accept the need for change in the size andpattern of the industry. This will involve certain sacrifices of convenience,for example, in the reduction of uneconomic services. Some increases willalso have to be made in fares and charges, and the Commission intend to take action in this respect as soon as possible. It will also be necessary to examineurgently the question of relieving the industry of restrictions and obligations which limit the Commission^ earnings and prevent them from making thebest use of their resources.Thirdly, the Commission must accept a radical alteration of its structure,so as to secure a more effective distribution of functions and a better use ofall its assets. Measures of reorganisation should include decentralisation of management so that individual undertakings, including regions of the british railways, should, as far as practicable, be made fully self-accounting and responsible for the management of their own affairs &quot;.3. The Government^ willingness to underwrite a settlement giving effect tothe Guillebaud report is based upon the acceptance both by the British transport commission and by the unions of their parallel obligations in this crisis of theindustry. The Transport Commission is expected to undertake to do everything possible to facilitate the work of the expert body which the Government areappointing and to co-operate with the Government in the implementation of their plans for reorganising the structure of the Commission. The unions are expected
to undertake to co-operate to the full in the reorganisation of the undertakings onthe lines indicated in the Prime Ministers statement. In particular they areexpected to facilitate those adjustments in the labour force that are required bythe management to secure the most efficient practicable operation of the reorganisedundertaking.(a)[ 4. On this understanding the Government now declare their willingness togive the necessary financial assistance to enable the Commission to give effect tothe Guillebaud report as from the date of that report. Thus the time inevitablytaken up in discussions between the Commission and the unions about the detailed application of the Guillebaud findings would not prejudice the railwaymen&apos;position. ](b)[ 4. On this understanding the Government now declare their willingness togive the necessary financial assistance to enable the Commission to negotiate anagreement on the basis of the Guillebaud report. ]March, I960.

</content>
</cab>
