<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 285-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   April I960C. (60) 69 Copy No.     5122nd April, 1960CABINETHOUSE OF COMMONS MEMBERS&apos; FUNDMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department the House of Commons Members&apos; Fund was established in 1939 to providegrants to Members and their dependants in financial need. At present the Fundamounts to about  100,000; its annual income is about  25,000, of which  10,000is a grant-in-aid,  11,000 is contributed by Members and  4,000 comes frominvestments.2. The Trustees are at present empowered by the House of CommonsMembers&apos; Fund Act, 1939, to invest the Fund in certain fixed interest stocksincluding &quot; securities in which a trustee may invest trust moneys under the powers conferred by Section 1 of the Trustee Act, 1925, as extended by a subsequentenactment&quot;. The Trustees of the Fund may therefore expect to secure in due course the benefit of the wider powers of investment proposed in the recent white paper, Powers of Investment of Trustees in Great Britain. (Briefly, these wouldenable trustees to invest not more than one half of their funds in the equity ofUnited Kingdom companies subject to safeguards. The Government have announced their intention to introduce legislation early next Session.)3. The Trustees are pressing for powers wider than those outlined in theWhite Paper; I annex a note which they have submitted setting out their grounds for wanting unlimited investment powers in advance of the general legislation.Briefly, they argue:(a) that they should not necessarily be restricted to the investment rulesproposed for trustees in general and that they need unlimited powersof investment such as were granted by Parliament recently in the caseof the Chequers Trust and the Funds of the Church of England;(b) that they should be given the wider powers forthwith, i.e., in anticipation of the general legislation.4. The Home Affairs Committee recently agreed that the Government neednot oppose in the current Session a few private Bills which would give to trustees of the funds of certain Church and University charities very wide or unlimitedpowers of investment. It was also decided that the Government should not opposeBills introduced by individual local authorities who were seeking wider powers of investment for their superannuation funds.5. In these circumstances we shall have some difficulty opposing the proposalsof the Trustees of the Members&apos; Fund, although these go somewhat wider than theproposals in the White Paper. I shall discuss the matter again with the Trusteesand tell them of the difficulties of legislation this Session.R. A. BbHome Office, S.W. 1,21st April, 1960.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
Printed for the Cabinet.   April I960C. (60) 69 Copy No.     5122nd April, 1960CABINETHOUSE OF COMMONS MEMBERS&apos; FUNDMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department the House of Commons Members&apos; Fund was established in 1939 to providegrants to Members and their dependants in financial need. At present the Fundamounts to about  100,000; its annual income is about  25,000, of which  10,000is a grant-in-aid,  11,000 is contributed by Members and  4,000 comes frominvestments.2. The Trustees are at present empowered by the House of CommonsMembers&apos; Fund Act, 1939, to invest the Fund in certain fixed interest stocksincluding &quot; securities in which a trustee may invest trust moneys under the powers conferred by Section 1 of the Trustee Act, 1925, as extended by a subsequentenactment&quot;. The Trustees of the Fund may therefore expect to secure in due course the benefit of the wider powers of investment proposed in the recent white paper, Powers of Investment of Trustees in Great Britain. (Briefly, these wouldenable trustees to invest not more than one half of their funds in the equity ofUnited Kingdom companies subject to safeguards. The Government have announced their intention to introduce legislation early next Session.)3. The Trustees are pressing for powers wider than those outlined in theWhite Paper; I annex a note which they have submitted setting out their grounds for wanting unlimited investment powers in advance of the general legislation.Briefly, they argue:(a) that they should not necessarily be restricted to the investment rulesproposed for trustees in general and that they need unlimited powersof investment such as were granted by Parliament recently in the caseof the Chequers Trust and the Funds of the Church of England;(b) that they should be given the wider powers forthwith, i.e., in anticipation of the general legislation.4. The Home Affairs Committee recently agreed that the Government neednot oppose in the current Session a few private Bills which would give to trustees of the funds of certain Church and University charities very wide or unlimitedpowers of investment. It was also decided that the Government should not opposeBills introduced by individual local authorities who were seeking wider powers of investment for their superannuation funds.5. In these circumstances we shall have some difficulty opposing the proposalsof the Trustees of the Members&apos; Fund, although these go somewhat wider than theproposals in the White Paper. I shall discuss the matter again with the Trusteesand tell them of the difficulties of legislation this Session.R. A. BbHome Office, S.W. 1,21st April, 1960.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
AnnexU  NOTE BY THE TREASURER OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONSMEMBERS&apos; FUNDWhile the proposals in the White Paper would apply to all Trusts there are,broadly speaking, two kinds of Trusts. For purposes of argument these could becalled the Private Trust and the Public Trust. By a Private Trust is meant the trust established by an individual for the benefit of another individual or individuals. Such a Trust cannot be of very long duration and is established fora particular purpose; in such a Trust the needs for stability of income and securityof capital are usually of equal importance. A Public Trust is that established by a company or under Government authority for a particular purpose and designedto continue so long as the purpose remains. In such Trusts capital growth is ofgreat importance. In many cases it is only by the continuous increase of capital andof income that the aim of the Trust can be secured. Certainly since the warTrustees of Trusts of this nature have thought fit to secure wider powers, namely,the investment of a large proportion of the Trust Funds in equities.2. The House of Commons Members&apos; Fund should be considered as a PublicTrust. By asking for full powers of investment it is not creating any precedent. Itis following an established practice. To-day the average Trust contains the widestpowers of investment and this practice is not confined to private individualTrusts. Industrial pension schemes and Government trust funds such as theChequers Trust, the London County Council, Essex County Council, manchester corporation, &amp;c, superannuation schemes equally give the widest of powers.3. In these circumstances we Trustees of the Members&apos; Fund desire no lessinvestment powers than the average Trust of this nature. We would not like to be bound by a regulation that investment in any Company with a paid-up capital of lessthan  1 million would be excluded. Very naturally, it is in the small energetic andthriving Company that an early investment may prove most lucrative for capitalincrement. The converse is equally true: the bigger and the more successful theCompany, the higher the price of its shares and the lower the yield. Further, therewould be restriction in taking up new issues (which in our case would not be morethan in  5,000 blocks) and loss of opportunity would certainly result.4. The commitments of the Fund reach their maximum at the beginning ofeach Parliament, and decrease slightly during the course of each Parliament. It istherefore very possible for investment plans to be considered at the beginning ofeach Parliament to cover the anticipated life of that Parliament. In turn this means that the liquidity ratio of the Fund can be accurately estimated. In turn, again,this means that policy designed to secure capital appreciation can be pursued withsafety.   &apos;5. The Trustees of the . Members&apos; Fund will have the advice of leadingStockbrokers and will retain the present services of the Public Trustee. In thisway they will obtain as good advice as it is possible to secure.6. At the moment the income of the Members&apos; Fund is  25,000, namely 10,000 Grand-in-Aid, Members&apos; contributions  11,300 and receipts frominvestments  3,700. The capital is  100,000 which under the White Paper proposals would free only  50,000 for investment in equities. -7. The importance of early legislation in this matter is paramount and couldbe done by a one-clause Bill. At the moment it is reasonable to assume that thepresent Parliament will last another four years which period should enable a faircapital appreciation to accrue. Delay will obviously mean loss of opportunity and less money available if and when the present rates of grants from the Fundare revised. The impression was formed that the main Government legislation would not be passed much before the end of this session.
8. The gratitude of the Trustees was expressed for the grant of  10,000 ayear made some few years ago: they hoped that the Government might soonconsider an increase.(Sgd.)     J. GRIFFITHS.18th February, 1960.(Note by the Treasury. The statement in paragraph 2 suggesting that localauthority superannuation schemes allow unlimited powers of investment is notcorrect. A number of local authorities have been granted by Parliament powersof investment outside trustee investments, but none have been allowed to exceed50 per cent, of the funds in company securities including equities.)

</content>
</cab>
