<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 297-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1960C. (60) 7225th April, 1960CABINETTOMATOES: APPLICATION FOR TARIFF increases memorandum by the Minister of Health sI have a substantial constituency interest in the matter discussed in theChancellor of the Exchequer^ memorandum C. (60) 68, as the greater part of theLea Valley lies within my constituency; and I believe that there is a strong case for granting a tariff increase on both economic and political grounds.Economic2. Dutch imports have materially increased their share of the market in theearly part of the season and it is on the early part of the season that the profitabilityand survival of the home industry may depend, it may be that this is partly dueto better organisation on the part of the Dutch; but it is also due to the disadvantage of higher labour costs. These labour costs are State regulated, and the home industry is also denied the greater flexibility in regard to hours of work which,I believe, helps the Dutch to keep down costs.3. In effect British horticulture faces the same economic difficulty as british agriculture high labour costs reflecting a predominantly industrial economy withan effective labour organisation. If it were feasible to apply the safeguards and guarantees of the Agriculture Acts nobody doubts that if would be appropriate. as these procedures are not feasible, we have ourselves pointed to the tariff as theappropriate and indeed the only mechanism.Political4. If this tariff application is rejected, it will be taken as a sign that no tariffapplication in respect of tomatoes will ever be granted. It will therefore, beconsidered as a violation of our Manifesto undertaking and a decision to sentenceto death the horticultural industry-or at any rate, a large part of it.5. If such a sentence is to be pronounced, it would have been more candid to pronounce it before the Election and to have used a different formula in the manifesto. But in any event, it would be wrong to pronounce sentence when thead valorem incidence of the tariff is lower than pre-war. It would be better andfairer to warn the industry that an increased tariff must be accompanied by improvedorganisation and competitive efficiency.6. The industry have established very good relations with interestedGovernment supporters in the House, and would not lack resolute and tenaciousadvocates. These specialists would be likely to be powerfully reinforced by others who would see in rejection a breach of Election faith, a departure from traditionalConservative principle, or a decision dictated less by tenderness for the consumerthan for the Dutch. It would be very difficult for this case to be effectively orconscientiously answered.Copy No.53
Printed for the Cabinet.   April I960C. (60) 7225th April, 1960Copy No.53CABINETTOMATOES: APPLICATION FOR TARIFF increases memorandum by the Minister of Health ^I have a substantial constituency interest in the matter discussed in theChancellor of the Exchequer^ memorandum C. (60) 68, as the greater part of theLea Valley lies within my constituency; and I believe that there is a strong case for granting a tariff increase on both economic and political grounds.Economic2. Dutch imports have materially increased their share of the market in theearly part of the season and it is on the early part of the season that the profitabilityand survival of the home industry may depend. It may be that this is partly dueto better organisation on the part of the Dutch; but it is also due to the disadvantage of higher labour costs. These labour costs are State regulated, and the home industry is also denied the greater flexibility in regard to hours of work which,I believe, helps the Dutch to keep down costs.3. In effect British horticulture faces the same economic difficulty as british agriculture high labour costs reflecting a predominantly industrial economy withan effective labour organisation. If it were feasible to apply the safeguards and guarantees of the Agriculture Acts nobody doubts that it would be appropriate. as these procedures are not feasible, we have ourselves pointed to the tariff as theappropriate and indeed the only mechanism.Political4. If this tariff application is rejected, it will be taken as a sign that no tariffapplication in respect of tomatoes will ever be granted. It will therefore beconsidered as a violation of our Manifesto undertaking and a decision to sentenceto death the horticultural industry or at any rate, a large part of it.5. If such a sentence is to be pronounced, it would have been more candid to pronounce it before the Election and to have used a different formula in the manifesto. But in any event, it would be wrong to pronounce sentence when thead valorem incidence of the tariff is lower than pre-war. It would be better andfairer to warn the industry that an increased tariff must be accompanied by improvedorganisation and competitive efficiency.6. The industry have established very good relations with interestedGovernment supporters in the House, and would not lack resolute and tenaciousadvocates. These specialists would be likely to be powerfully reinforced by others who would see in rejection a breach of Election faith, a departure from traditionalConservative principle, or a decision dictated less by tenderness for the consumerthan for the Dutch. It would be very difficult for this case to be effectively orconscientiously answered.
Green Belt7. If horticulture is to be sentenced to death in the Lea Valley, it is likely that the Green Belt, which the Minister of Housing is conscientiously seeking to preserve as a barrier against urban sprawl, would also be a victim. Preservationin the form of public open space, based on non-economic use, would of course be very costly.hGConclusion8. For all these reasons, I submit that the tariff should be increased asproposed by the Tariff Advisory Committee, with the amendment specified inparagraph 6 of C. (60) 68.D. W.-S.25th April, 1960.

</content>
</cab>
