<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 300-301</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1960Copy No.     yCABINET W-1-.INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY I memorandum by the Lord President of the Council and Secretary of, St atefor Commonwealth relations should like to consult my colleagues on the problem of the future of the india Office Library, which has for so long been unresolved, and while it remainsso, constitutes a troublesome irritant in our relations with India and Pakistan.2. On 11th September, 1959, an aide-memoire was presented to the Ministerof State for Commonwealth Relations on behalf of the Indian and PakistanGovernments.  This aide-memoire concludes as follows:&quot; What the Governments of India and Pakistan now want is that theBritish Government should recognise that the Governments of India and pakistan are the owners of the India Office Library. As regards the physicaltransfer of the Library to India and Pakistan, the two Governments agree that,for the time being, the Library should continue to remain in London.&quot;Although this document rehearses familiar arguments, it differs from previousrepresentations in that (a) It is explicitly a joint Indian-Pakistan approach, (b) Itdoes not press for the immediate physical transfer of the Library to the Sub-Continent.3. In my view it is desirable for us to make an attempt to reach an agreed solution for the future of the Library as the present situation is always a potentialsource of friction, especially between the United Kingdom and India. Therewould be certain advantages in a move by us now.(a) It would be a response to a joint approach by the President of Pakistan,General Ayub, and the Prime Minister of India, Mr. Nehru.(b) The rehousing of the Library is becoming urgent, and any proposals for moving it to new permanent quarters will inflame controversy if nosettlement is previously reached.(c) It is, in any case, important for us to find new permanent accommodationif we are to be in a position to redevelop the whole site lying betweenDowning Street and King Charles Street, as discussed in Cabineton 22nd March (C.C. (60) 19th Conclusions, Minute 3). Moreover, Ishould hope that if the question of the future of the India Office Libraryhas been settled in agreement with the Governments of India and pakistan, this would decrease the likelihood of any claim being pressedagainst us for compensation arising from our plans for the conversion ofthe India Office building.(d) It is possible that a good site may become available in the near future.4.   Our fundamental interests in the Library are that:  (a) It should remain undivided.(b) It should remain in the United Kingdom.(c) It should continue to be efficiently managed and developed and to providethe same type of service as it does to-day.(d) Private collections deposited or on loan to the Library should be allowed by their owners to remain with the Library.5. So far we have stood firmly on our legal rights of ownership, and the most that we have offered is that we would &quot; consider any suggestions that theGovernments of India and Pakistan may wish to make to us as regards the detailedadministration of or access to the Library &quot;. This suggestion has not been taken upby the Indian or Pakistan Government.C. (60) 7326th April, 196056939
6.   In looking for an agreed settlement the question of ownership is probably the crux.  On this point there is at present a head-on collision.   We maintain onthe advice of the Law Officers that the India Office Library, with the. other contents of the India Office building, passed into the ownership of the United Kingdomt, Government by the Government of India Act, 1935.   The Indian and Pakistan^Governments, on the other hand maintain that the Library was never intended tobe regarded as part of the contents of the building and that morally and in equitythe Library belongs to them jointly since (as is the case) all expenditure of the library prior to 1935 was solely defrayed by the revenues of undivided India. just as it is impossible for us to accept that the Library is. the property of the Indian and-Pakistan Governments, so it is politically impossible for them to acknowledge thatit is the sole property of the United Kingdom Government. Some compromise onthe question of ownership is therefore probably necessary.   This should not beimpossible; our interests as set out above could be safeguarded without maintaining the Library in United Kingdom Government ownership.7. A possible solution which I have in view is that by Act of Parliament a trust, independent of Government, should be set up to which we would transfer the ownership of the Library, subject to certain overriding conditions safeguardingour fundamental interests in the Library as set out above. There would be nomineesfrom all three countries on the Governing Body of the Trust. On their side theGovernments of India and Pakistan would take such steps as they might think necessary to acknowledge that the sole ownership of the Library would thenceforthbe vested in the Trust.8. The details of any arrangements on these lines would of course requirethe most careful examination. It would clearly have implications of particular importance for both the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister of Works,and we should need to ensure that the fullest safeguards of our own rights and interests were incorporated either in the Act or possibly in a Trust Deed. All thiswill require detailed working out, and will take time.9. However, if my colleagues are generally in agreement with the principle underlying the proposal which I have outlined, there would seem to me to be great advantage in my taking the opportunity of the forthcoming visit of Mr. Nehru and president Ayub to broach with them personally in very general terms our proposedplan. My idea would be that in speaking to them I would first reaffirm:(a) Our conviction, based on the best legal advice, that the legal ownership ofthe Library is vested in the United Kingdom.(b) Our view, based both on the legal position and on more general considerations, that the Library must remain intact in the UnitedKingdom.However, in recognition of the great significance which the Library has for theculture and history of India and Pakistan, and in a constructive endeavour to resolve the problem which has existed for too long between friends, I would thengo on to say that the United Kingdom, for its part, would be ready by Act ofParliament to set up a Trust, independent of Government, and to transfer to itthe ownership of the Library. There would be nominees from all three countries on the Governing Body of the Trust. The corollary of this arrangement wouldbe that, on their side, the two Governments, acting in a Similar spirit of goodwill,would take such steps as they might think necessary to accept the fact that the.Sole ownership of the Library would from that time be vested in the Trust. Finally,I would explain that if Mr. Nehru and President Ayub would confirm their readinessin principle to consider a proposal on these lines, I would arrange to have preparedfor their further consideration a detailed scheme to give effect to it.10. If I were tackled on the question of the accommodation Of the Library,I would merely say that I am conscious that the present premises are not entirelyadequate, and that the provision of alternative accommodation would be one of thematters to be given consideration in the working out of the detailed scheme.11. I should be grateful for the agreement of my colleagues to my speakingon the above lines to Mr. Nehru and President Ayub.H.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,26th April, I960.

</content>
</cab>
