<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 358-359</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
V1SOMALIANote by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs attach a minute which I sent to the Commonwealth Secretary on30th May about Somalia.   In it I suggest that it would be prudent to discourage any approach for membership of the Commonwealth whichmight be made to us by the new State, and recommend that Her Majesty&apos;sConsul-General at Mogadishu and the Governor at Hargeisa should be instructed how to react to any such approach.    I recommend also that the ethiopian, French, Italian and American Governments should be informedvery confidentially of the instructions sent to the Consul-General and theGovernor.2.        The Prime Minister has said that he would like the matter to bedecided at Cabinet.S. L.Foreign Office, 3. W. 1.31st May, I960.SECRETARY OF STATE FOR COMMONWEALTH RELATIONSSomali Membership of the CommonwealthI think we are generally agreed that we would not want to admitto the Commonwealth the new Somali Republic which will come into being on 1st July when Somaliland and Somalia unite.    The new State will bea pensioner for many years, depending upon financial and technical aid from the Americans and Italians as well as from ourselves.    The trend of discussion at the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; Conference was against the granting of membership to poor, sparsely populated andbackward territories such as the Somali Republic is bound to be.    More-over, in this case the granting of Commonwealth membership would do much harm to our relations with the Ethiopians, the French and theItalians;   and the Italians have made it clear that in these circumstancesItalian aid would cease altogether, thus leaving a very considerableburden to be picked up presumably by us.-1-(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(60) 91 COPY NO. ^ Q31st May, I960CABINET
2.        The question of Commonwealth membership was not raised by the protectorate Elected Ministers during the London Constitutional Talks.But I do not think we should assume that the Somalis have decided against it irrevocably.    It would obviously be embarrassing to receive, and haveto refuse, a formal request;  and it would seem better to put ourselves in the position to discourage one in advance.    I would not wish to takethe initiative in raising the matter with the Somalis;  but I should likeHer Majesty&apos;s Consul-General at Mogadishu and the Governor at Hargeisato be in a position to answer any tentative enquiries immediately, without having to refer to London.    I think they should say that very difficult problems would be raised by a request from a State two-thirds of whoseinhabitants have never been part of the British family of nations;  that commonwealth membership would not imply any increase in financial orother aid from the United Kingdom, while it might well jeopardise aid from non-Commonwealth sources;  that the Somali Republic does not need toenter the Commonwealth to ensure our friendship;   and that we should prefer not.to be faced with an application.    I do not think that a reply onthese lines would give serious offence to the Somalis.3.        The Ethiopians continue to show deep suspicion of our policy inthe Horn.    They have told the American and French Ambassadors in&apos;Addis Ababa that they believe we are trying to entice the Somali Republicinto the Commonwealth and that this would provide the Somalis withsupport for their Greater Somalia claims.    We have told them that if: isnot our policy to stimulate an application for Commonwealth membership.It is clear that we must go rather further than this if we are to dispeltheir suspicions, which are damaging to our own interests and to theprospects of satisfactory relations between the Ethiopians and the Somalis.If it is agreed, therefore, that we should instruct Mogadishu and Hargeisaon the lines of paragraph 2 above, I should like to inform the Ethiopians,the Italians, the French and the Americans very confidentially of thoseinstructions.4.        I should be grateful if you and the Colonial Secretary, to whom Iam sending a copy of this minute, would let me know what you think.I am also sending a copy of the minute to the Prime Minister.(Signed) SELWYN LLOYD30TH MAY, I960-2-

</content>
</cab>
