<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/101/0 images: 395-398</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of...........................TOP SECRET Copy No.C. (60) 9020th June, I960CABINETPOLARISMemorandum by the Minister of defence the Prime Minister, in his talks at Camp David with president Eisenhower, agreed in principle that the United States navy should station a tender and a dock for POLARIS submarines in Scottishwaters.   During my recent visit to Washington I carried this further withMr. Gates, the Secretary of Defence, and explained to him that we could hardly make the proposition acceptable to public opinion, in the changed circumstances of today, unless it were to be presented as a joint project;and this would mean that they would have to help us to get outrownPOLARIS  submarines, with missiles, which would be stationed with theAmerican submarines at the Scottish base and would share theirfacilities, within a reasonable period of time.2.        Mr. Gates is pressing us for an early answer.   We cannot make up our minds exactly what we ought to do, and what we can afford to do,without a technical study which will take some months.   Therefore, atthis stage, we can do no more than to ask for an option.   If we can reach agreement on two important issues to which I refer below, the place ofthe base and the relation of our POLARIS missiles to the Medium RangeBallistic Missile (M. R. B. M.) scheme of the North Atlantic Alliance, Ipropose that we should seek agreement with the Americans on thefollowing terms, to be announced if possible before Parliament rises.To the United States time is of great importance because they are most anxious to berth their tender and dry dock in Scotland by 1st December, 1960:.-(a) The base to be established at an agreed place in Scottish waters.(b) The base to be a joint enterprise.(c) The United States to give us the option of buying one or morePOLARIS submarines with its missiles at a reasonably early date (say the first for delivery by 1964/65) on the most favourable terms, and ofprocuring the necessary spares for their service life.(d) The United States to give us the drawings, know-how, etc. toenable us to build our own POLARIS submarines and missiles if we wishto do so.-1-
(e) The United States to enable us to buy POLARIS missiles for anysubmarine which we may build, if we decide not to manufacture them.(f) The United States to give us full access to training andmaintenance facilities on both sides of the Atlantic;  to assist us intraining our crews;  and to allow us to use their tender and dry dock inorder to support our POLARIS submarines when they are in operation.(g) The United States to give full facilities to a technical mission,to go over to America as soon as possible, in order to give us the dat^for determining the extent and nature of our participation.3. As in the case of SKYBOLT, a financial and technical agreement will have to be negotiated in due course.4.        Until we have studied the matter far more deeply, I cannot make any firm proposals for our participation, but the following detailsgive some idea of vhat is involved.   All figures of cost, at this stage,must be treated with the greatest reserve.5,;        The smallest British POLARIS fleet which would carry anyconviction would be three submarines.   If we had less we could not have -or even appear to have - one submarine on station all the time.   The only way of getting a submarine into service as soon as 1964/65 would beto buy one from the United States.   This, without missiles, would cost about  38 millions.   If we were to build ourselves, the quickest, butthe most expensive, method would be to make a Chinese copy of theUnited States design.     This would cost something like  34 millions(somewhere between the  38 millions for a United States-built ship and  30 millions for a United Kingdom designed and built ship).The first would come into service in mid-1967 and the second six months later.    Building in this country a Chinese copy of a United Statessubmarine would save a great deal of design   effort as well as time.   ABritish-designed version based on United States know-how would cost about  30 millions, the first one coming into service in late 1968 andthe second a year later.6.        The fcLiowing is a rough estimate of the other costs:-  millions(a) 16 missiles each for 3 submarines(excluding war heads) 26(b) Training equipment 10(c) Other works and plant 16(b) and (c) are contingent liabilities depending largely on the extentto which we can enjoy indefinitely access to United States facilities.There would also be costs, which cannot yet be estimated, for communications, accommodation, etc. , at the base.-2-
7.        The total capital cost of three submarines might therefore beof theaxd-a: of  150 millions.   Until our programme is more settled the spread of this expenditure over the period, up to about nine years, of theprogramme cannot be defined.8.        We have not yet settled where the base should be.   There are several places in Scotland which might meet the operational requirementsof the United States (of which the principal one is an inlet with smoothand deep water);  but they also want to be within easy reach of amenities and of an airport, preferably Prestwick.   The only place which has so, far been considered, as meeting those requirements exactly, is the holy Lock; but this is in a much visited part of the world near Glasgow,and the political and security disadvantages of placing the base thereare obvious.   I do not think that we can agree to this, and I propose insteadthat we should offer the United States the upper waters of Lock Linnhe,near Fort William.   This meets their main operational requirements;amenities (especially living facilities) are far less, but transport to Glasgow and Prestwick is manageable, and I do not think it is possibleto meet their desire to be within easy reach of large towns and airportswithout creating an impossible political problem for ourselves, and indeedfor them.   For William will not be more remote or difficult than manyof their naval and air bases,9.        The other difficulty, which will not be easy to surmount, lies inthe fact that Mr. Gates attaches the greatest important to his scheme forgiving land-based POLARIS missiles to the Supreme Allied Commander,Europe (SACEUR) - a scheme to which I have given general support in theNorth Atlantic Alliance, but which fills me with no enthusiasm.   He willnot be willing to give us the facilities for obtaining POLARIS missilesunless we make them available to SACEUR, so long as his scheme is alive -and even if it does not survive, it may be a long time dying.   It is clearthat we cannot afford to contribute to the M. R. B. M.  scheme as well asgetting our own POLARIS submarines;   and if we were to assign themwholly to SACEUR (quite apart from practical difficulties) they would nolong appear to be, or be, part of our independent contribution to theWestern deterrent.   I think that it may be possible to negotiate a compromise by which we should undertake to cover some of the targetswhich SACEUR wishes to cover;  there is an overlap between these targets and those of SACLANT, with whom we shall inevitably be working closely.10.       I should mention the question of control.   The United States willreadily agree, of course, that we should have a veto on the firing of anymissiles from submarines in our territorial waters.   But once submerged,they will range very far, and we cannot reasonably claim that we should share in the control of firing from submarines anywhere in the globe becausethey come up to breathe once every few months in our waters.   I do not recommend that we should raise the question of control outside territorial waters.11.       The general advantages of this scheme are very great;  itgets us into the seaborne POLARIS business;  it provides us with thebest possible reinsurance against the possible failure of SKYBOLT;  andit leaves us free to choose the direction of the next generation of the deterrent.-3-
12.       I therefore ask my colleagues to agree that we should informthe United States Government that we shall be willing, subject to theconditions set out in this paper and to a satisfactory solution being foundto the difficulty about the M. R. B. M. of the North Atlantic Allinace,to accept a joint POLARIS base in Loch Linnhe.H.W.Ministry of Defence, S.W.I.17th June, I960-4-

</content>
</cab>
