<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/47/0 images: 48-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS  document  is  the   property   of his  britannic  majestvs  governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1951CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.CP. (51) 23616th August, 1951CABINETCOUNCIL OF europe memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate herewith for the information of my colleagues the text of a statement which I made in a restricted session of the Committee of Ministers of the Councilof Europe in Strasbourg on 3rd August, in an endeavour to promote a more robustand energetic attitude on the part of certain of the Continental Governments.The statement was generally well received. M. Schuman thanked me for myanalysis of the successes achieved by the West in the last year and for the tone ofconfidence of my remarks, which he said he shared. Dr. Adenauer, the german federal Chancellor, said that this statement dispeiled any idea that Great Britainmight be adopting an attitude of reserve towards Europe.My remarks were followed by a statement by M. Stifcker on lines previouslyagreed upon between him, M. Schuman, M. Lange and myself, propounding theneed for a new initiative by the European Powers designed to secure increased production for defence. As a result of this statement it was agreed that theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.) should be invitedto prepare a draft Declaration which could be issued at a further ministerial meetingtowards the end of August. A draft already prepared by M. Marjolin, Secretary-General of the O.E.E.C., will form the basis for this text.My announcement to the Joint Committee that the Chancellor of the exchequer would be willing to introduce the O.E.E.C.&apos;s Annual Report to the consultative assembly in October next was very favourably received. There is no doubt thatthis is regarded as a step forward by His Majesty&apos;s Government in their relationswith the Council of Europe and as a mark of our desire to make full use of the consultative functions of the Assembly.We were concerned in the Joint Committee with a proposal by the bureau of the Assembly that among the subjects to be placed on the agenda for the forth-coming meeting of representatives of the Assembly with representatives of theUnited States Congress should appear an item headed &quot; Defence &quot; with a numberof controversial sub-headings on strictly defence matters, including german rearmament and the European Army. The Committee of Ministers were unanimous in considering that it would be improper, having regard to the Statute, for thesubject to appear on the agenda in this form, and the Assembly representativeseventually agreed that the items relating to defence and the economic state ofEurope should be merged in a new item headed: &quot; The Economic and PoliticalState of the Western World,&quot; from which the sub-heads on defence questions towhich the Ministers had objected would be dropped. The new item includes asa sub-head the economic, social and moral impact of the rearmament programme.The Ministers agreed that the O.E.E.C. Secretariat should be asked to providematerial for the use of the Assembly representatives in their discussion with theCongressmen on these points.41084-1
2Finally, I circulate for information a record of a statement made by theGerman Federal Chancellor at a small dinner party given by M. Stikker on 3rd August at which there were present the French, Netherlands and NorwegianMinisters for Foreign Affairs, the Belgian Minister of lrade and Commerce, theItalian Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Emigration) and myself. Thesecond part of the statement, dealing with German views on the Soviet threat andon the question of a German contribution to Western defence, will, I think, interestmy colleagues in the light of the Cabinet&apos;s recent discussions on this subject. Theremainder contains some interesting comment on the internal situation in Germany.H. M.-Foreign Office, SWA, -\6th August, 1951.
ANNEX statement BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGNAFFAIRS TO THE COMMITTEE OF MINISTERS IN STRASBOURGON 3rd AUGUST, 1951I entirely agree with the view expressed by a number of my colleagues that,when we have these meetings of Foreign Ministers, we should take the opportunityto exchange views on the general situation. It is not easy for us to fit in all theengagements which crowd upon us in these days and I do not think it is necessaryto arrange special meetings for this purpose. Far better make use of occasionssuch as this when we are assembled for other reasons. This has also the advantage that less attention is drawn to such discussions and we avoid arousing the expecta-tion that positive or striking decisions are to be taken. I think such exchanges canonly be really useful if they are strictly confidential and not intended to be thesubject of any communique, and I also think that they must be regarded as happen-jng outside the strict orbit of the Council of Europe, so that, if we wish to do so.we can exchange views on a wide variety of matters without prejudicing theprinciple, to which as you know the British Government and several otherGovernments attach importance, namely, that defence is outside the scope of theCouncil of Europe.On this basis I am glad to have the opportunity of giving my colleagues a brief outline of how I see our situation at the present time: the problems which concern us for the future and the measures which we must take individually andin common for the safety and welfare of our peoples.In the course of my remarks I shall try to convey to you the sense of balancedand assured confidence which animates the British people at the present time despiteall the clouds on the horizon, and which I am sure ought to be shared by the restof us in Europe. In any case, as confidence is said to be infectious, I make noapology for speaking of our confidence.I think on the whole we can say without any doubt that we have had a success-ful year, and I am speaking of Europe as a whole and of the West as a whole. our general calculations and the policies which we have based on them, have provedthemselves correct. We have all known for a long time that these were going tobe dangerous years and that between the moment when we first recognised the need to strengthen ourselves and the moment unfortunately still some way ahead when we can regard our defences as adequate, there would be severe tests on ournerve and courage. Each step we ourselves have taken to strengthen our cora-munity has been fraught with a certain amount of risk; and of course each time we have had to stand firm against moves by the other side, we have also taken a risk. But we have faced these risks, and we have proved justified. We find ourselves here, towards the end of 1951, with quite a series of successes behind us,with unimpaired unity and steadily growing strength. Western Europe has lostno ground since the fall of Czechoslovakia in 1948 and no one has dared to interruptus in our measures of defence and of resistance. On this, I certainly think we cancongratulate ourselves; and from this we can draw lessens as to how we shouldbehave in the future.To be more specific: our main successes in the past year apart from thesuccessful resistance to aggression in the Far East have been:  First: our refusal to be divided by the efforts of Soviet propaganda or deterred from what we know to be necessary for our independence and freedom.(And I must mention as a particular instance the success with which theWest avoided being divided over the negotiations for a Foreign MinistersConference.) It was not easy, as my French colleague knows and as myUnited States colleague knows;Second: the establishment of a joint Command in Europe under one of themost widely respected figures of our time, and the increase of Allied forces on the Continent; and thirdly: the substantial start which we have made with the financial andindustrial problems inseparable from any defence effort.In another realm of ideas, we must as Europeans congratulate ourselves onthe continuing and even increasing interest which the United States Government41084-2
2and people have shown in the security and welfare of Europe, and their continuedrecognition despite many temptations to the contrary that Europe is the key tothe defence of the free world and must have priority over other theatres. This isof vital importance to us all. It is not so long ago that we were wondering whether,as Marshall Aid tapered off, we should be able fully to retain the material and moral support of the United States.   We have done so in the fullest sense.And, finally, we have continued to be successful in building up understanding and co-operation amongst ourselves. We have done our international work inEurope with growing confidence; and little by little it has become less easy in a hundred ways for individual countries to adopt selfish or sectarian courses wherethe common interest is involved.We have welcomed the German Federal Republic into the Council of Europe;we have acted in many fields in concert with the O.E.E.C. which, among other activities, brought into successful operation the European Payments Union and thishas rendered possible a great increase of inter-European trade: we have seen anindependent &quot;Yugoslavia steadily affirm itself and its relations with the rest of usgradually improve; we have been conscious of a very definite European point ofview emerging in matters relating to peace and war in the Far East and elsewhere;we have seen the normalisation of diplomatic relations with Spain.To each of these things which I have mentioned, some of us or several of us may feel inclined to make reserves, I know. But the point is that if we look atthe situation as a whole, the current has been towards reconciliation in Europe, andthis current is still in full flow. In my opinion it does not matter if the forms and constitutional structure of union are not so far advanced as some might wish, solong as the reality of our relationship moves towards unity.In fact, if I may say so, I think that a lot of us, especially here in Strasbourg,pay far too much attention to the forms and too little to the reality.The main emphasis, then, in all the aspects of our present problem should beon unity. Subject to proper and necessary clashes as to political and economicideals, unity at home between the different groups and classes of our free society(subject to proper and necessary clashes as to political and economic ideals); unity of action and mutual comprehension amongst the diverse national and internationalgroups which make up the free world. I want to say something about both thesetwo forms of unity.First, as regards the sociological essentials of internal unity, the task is tocreate a balanced, just and contented society in which communism will find noappeal and whose natural vitality and cohesion will prevent its being infiltrated bydictatorial doctrines. To get this we must have social justice and fair sharing ofeconomic advantages, and we must have the internal discipline sufficient to ensurethese things. But at the same time we must have liberty also. I do not know how the requirement can be better expressed than in the words which inspired theFrench Revolution, &quot; Liberty, Equality and Fraternity,&quot; provided we give a newmeaning to the words &quot; Liberty &quot; and &quot; Equality &quot; and relate them to the conditionsof the twentieth century. Fraternity is a constant in human desire and perhapsneeds no redefinition.Now it is in the redefinition of equality that I venture to think Great britain to-day has something to offer. Frequently we are called upon by good friends togive Europe a lead and equally often we are told that we are not giving this lead.Well, perhaps it would be a good thing to have a careful look at this matter, inwhich, I maintain we are giving a very definite lead which we invite indeed arechallenging all to follow. I mean in the elimination of communism at homeby the creation of conditions where it does not flourish. There is no easy recipe forthis. It is not so easy, anything like, as setting up an international authority orcalling together a European parliament, even though these may be more highsounding. It is a question of social discipline, of having an adequately controlled and efficient fiscal and economic system, of sacrifice by the privileged and someausterity for all. It is a question of ensuring the right and the duty to work, thaiis to say, of maintaining a policy of full employment together with the principle of full social obligations; it requires a colossal effort on the part of a nation andat the same time great patience and care to combine control withliberty. Politically it demands stable parliamentary institutions and a general-respect for government. But the reward is worth working for a freecountry to which all classes are equally loyal. We cannot be satisfied with the stats of Europe, nor can our defence efforts give us any real assurance of
343security, until we have eliminated the material and emotional causes of communismin our midst. I would go further and say that you cannot expect to see consti-tutional union in Europe until all the countries have more or less equally succeeded in eliminating these internal weaknesses. Unity, in fact, like many other desirablequalities, begins at home.So that is the trumpet which I intend to blow next time I am asked that britain should give a lead.In international affairs there are other kinds of unity. I suppose we should all agree that the over-riding thing is to maintain unity between Europe and theNorth American continent and that one of the most dangerous things that couldhappen to us, apart from the spread of Communist doctrine itself, would be any- growth of anti-American feeling amongst our own people, or anti-European feelingsamong the Americans. We all have a responsibility for watching this at both endsIn the United States we ought to consider that the good reputation of any one of us enhances the good reputation of us all, and that we all suffer if there is criticism ofany one of our European nations. The true European spirit is to show a certainloyalty to one another when dealing with a wider audience, and I can assure you that you will not find British official spokesmen, if I can help it, criticising other european nations in the United States.As regards European opinion, there may be occasions when we can offer advice to the Americans themselves on how certain aspects of their policy and actions,might be better presented from the European point of view. In one matter, inparticular, publicity it will certainly be right for us as Europeans to be the judges of how best to present our common policies in our own countries, and this is a principle on which we have insisted in the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.Then again, in certain political matters we have been right to make our specificallyEuropean difficulties known, and I think we should continue to do so. We also have a common interest in ensuring that there shall be broad equality of sacrificeover the whole Atlantic community in meeting the dangers which threaten the West;in other words, that the contributions of all shall bear relation to their capacity.This does not mean that any one of us can go easy and rely on others to make upfor our slackness. This principle, too, has been accepted in the North atlantic treaty Organisation, but I mention it here because it seems to me to have a widerapplication. Generally speaking it is an essential interest of us all as Europeansthat the standards of sacrifice and effort which are applied to us should apply equallyover the whole of the Atlantic area and that we should not allow ourselves to get into a position where Europe, so to speak, sits on one side of the table and theNorth American continent on the other. We are aiming for a community of theWest; a joint enterprise in which the sacrifices and the benefits are equally shared.The second field in which unity must be preserved and in which the UnitedKingdom Government has a particular responsibility is the sterling area combina-tion, and, closely associated with it, the British Commonwealth of Nations. I donot think anyone will deny the importance of maintaining these combinations ordisagree that the United Kingdom Government and people must set aside a large part of their energies and resources to that end. It is not only a question of theeconomic and financial importance of the sterling area; there is also the fact thatthe Commonwealth represents one of the main ties linking free Asia with the west and may consequently play a vital part in preventing the spread of communismthroughout the whole of Asia. It would be a big mistake to ignore or underratethis part of what we are trying to do for the unity of the free world.Thirdly there is unity in Europe. I have already spoken about the strongcurrent of reconciliation and co-operation which is bringing us closer together everyday in all our affairs, but I want now to say a word about the more specific proposalsfor setting up institutions of a supranational character which are under discussion in Europe to-day. I mean, of course, primarily the Schuman Plan and the plan for a European Army, though there are other proposals of a similar nature whichhave not yet reached so advanced a stage. I want to make it clear that the UnitedKingdom Government have nothing but goodwill towards schemes of this kind,which are designed to bring together in specific fields certain European countries who feel disposed to unite in this way. The fact that, for various good reasons,we do not at present feel able to join such organisations should not be taken as implying any opposition to them or any reluctance to see them succeed. We wantthem to succeed, and as we have made clear in public statements, we shall always be ready to examine the possibility of being associated as closely as possible, andof co-operating in the most practical way with any authorities which emerge from
these schemes. It is to be anticipated that one such authority may emerge fromthe Schuman Plan Treaty as soon as this is ratified by the Parliaments concerned,as we hope it will be.As regards the European Army, I would like to say that we have been followingwith close interest the progress of the Conference in Paris and are now studying the interim report which has been produced. Clearly there are a large numberof important questions, especially on the military side, which have still to be cleared up, and it will be necessary to ensure that the whole plan fits in with the require-ments- of North Atlantic Defence and is acceptable to the Supreme Allied Com-mander in Europe. Subject to that, however, I can say that we wish the Conferencesuccess and shall look forward to hearing how its further studies progress.These then are the four main areas in which we must cultivate unity; unitybased on social justice at home; unity amongst the Europeans; unity of the wholeEuropean and North American community, and the ties of the Commonwealth,especially with Asia. They are four aspects of the struggle for the survival of what we loosely call &quot; the West &quot; or the &quot; free world,&quot; and so long as we cultivate themail and neglect none of them, we shall certainly win through. No single one isvalid without the others, but a!! are complementary to one another. If we keepthese realities before us, there ought to be no difficulty about surmounting theproblems of defence, the problems of inflation and raw materials shortages or anyof the physical or moral problems which may confront us. But we musrwork, wemust have more production and more equal sacrifice. A greater economic effort would itself improve morale by giving our peoples the feeling that things are on the move, and the more speedy and effective are our preparations of defence, the morecertain is the maintenance of peace. Therefore, while we keep our eyes open forany chance of a settlement with the Soviet Union, we must redouble our nationalefforts for defence. I am not one of those who despair of any settlement with soviet Russia; I think it may be possible when they realise that we are strong enough not to be pushed around. You will have seen recently various signs whichsuggest that there might be a new policy in Russia. There has been the move for acease-fire in Korea, and the publication of an English language paper in Moscow,which seems to speak of the possibility of understanding. It is tempting to be encouraged by these things. But if you look at the reply which Pravda has madeto my message, you will see that when it is a question of something which is goingto be read widely inside Russia, there is no real abandonment of hostility towards us. I think the Pravda reply, by Communist standards, was fairly mild; but it doesnot suggest any real attempt to open up, or to remove the misunderstandings whichhave been wilfully built up in the Russian peoples&apos; mind about the West.So I say we must wait for deeds as well as words, and we must not lower ourguard until we see the real evidence of conversion and of a will for friendship. Ifwe were to relax our efforts prematurely, we should be guilty of betraying the causeof peace. Each nation must concentrate on its own contribution and its internalmorale and self respect, and we must not be diverted from this.We must have confidence in ourselves and our peoples, we must ensure thateverybody&apos;s heart is in the job and that the civilisation which we are defending isa just and acceptable civilisation, worthy of being defended and genuinely basedon the eternal principles of liberty, equality and fraternity.
ANNEX IISTATEMENT BY THE GERMAN FEDERAL CHANCELLOR at mr. STIKKER&apos;S DINNER PARTY AT STRASBOURG on 3rd august the Ministers present were:  Mr. Stikker.Mr. Morrison.M. Schuman.M. Lange.Dr. Adenauer.M. Meurice (Belgian Minister of Trade and Commerce).M. Dominedo (Italian Under-Secretary).Mr. Morrison was accompanied by Sir E. Hall-Patch and Mr. Shuckburghand the other Ministers had one adviser each.Dr. Adenauer, whose remarks were translated into English by Dr. Hallsteinand into French by M. Schuman, spoke from a prepared text.He began by saying that the German people were not properly understoodabroad. There was mistrust in certain countries of democratic Germany and thismistrust was, of course, fed by the reports (which were often exaggerated in his view) of the activities of the Socialist Party of the Reich under Herr Remer and ofthe various ex-soldiers&apos; parties. People seemed to be afraid that if Germany weregiven arms she might use them to side with Soviet Russia against the West, ordemand the unification of Germany by force, or seek a position of hegemony overthe other European peoples. Dr. Adenauer said that he proposed to speak veryfrankly and openly, not as Chancellor but as a German who was deeply interestedin creating a new Europe into which the German people would be securelyintegrated.He said that to understand the present position in Germany one must knowsomething of the deep psychological and social upheavals which had occurred since1918. There had never been true democracy in Germany before 1918, since theGerman Empire had been dominated by Prussia and under the Prussian system the mass of the people had no political influence. The transition to a democraticconstitution in 1918 had been too sudden and there had been no chance for demo-cratic practice to grow before the inflation which &quot; proletarianised &quot; the middleclasses. Out of this had been built the evil system of nazism, and when thiscollapsed in the Second World War all authority except purely local authority was destroyed in Germany.- The victorious Allies unfortunately had not taken the necessary steps after thewar to win Germany for the West. It was not until 1947-48 that Germany hadbeen allowed to start out on the path of economic recovery. The result was a stateof acute insecurity and fear for the future. This was the atmosphere in which theRemer Party had been created. It must be carefully watched by the german federal Republic though he did not consider it a dangerous movement at present.It was natural that there should be some relics of nazism still lingering in theGerman mentality and the Russians were the first to avail themselves of this. TheSocialist Reichspartei was financed by the Soviets and its head was a Russian tool.The German Federal Government unfortunately could not give proofs of this to german public opinion without giving away their sources of information, but hecould assure the Foreign Ministers present that he had photographs of chequespaid to the party by the Russian Occupation Authorities.As regards the soldiers&apos; associations and the various meetings and speechesto which so much attention was given in the foreign press, it was necessary to take account of the following factors. The desire of former soldiers to club together insuch associations after a calamitous war was in itself quite natural and existed inother countries; but in Germany the Army had been defamed and its honourimpugned after the war. It had been blamed for all the crimes committed by the nazis and by a very small element in the Army. The higher officers, many ofwhom were decent people, had been treated with great lack of psychological under-standing and justice.   They had been put to manual work regardless of their rank.41084-3
sHe personally had known cases of senior officers who could hardly keep themselvesalive by manual labour and there had been numerous suicides. The war crimetrials, comprehensible in the heat of passion immediately after the war. had beenspun out and there were several hundreds of prisoners still in a certain Westerncountry for whom no trial had been arranged. Despite all this, there wouldprobably not be very strong feeling amongst former German soldiers, and in anycase it would have gradually disappeared, had it not been for the suggestion of aGerman contribution to Western European defence. The possibility of creatingGerman forces again had stirred up the ex-officers, and many of them thought--wrongly that they would have a better chance of participating in the new forcesif they took a lead in the military associations. That was why these associationshad sprung into prominence recently. Unfortunately, Germany had 2,000 former \generals. There was great rivalry between them and this led, he admitted, tounsuitable and improper expressions and actions. This would pass, but it was important not to let these elements become enemies of the State, which, he was glad to say, they were certainly not at present, except for the Bruderschaft. There were no disquieting National Socialist tendencies except in this one group which, as hehad said, was closely linked with the Soviet Occupation Authorities.Another great danger for Germany was the refugees, the &quot; expellees &quot; and thehomeless victims of bombing. Shortage of houses was a much greater danger todemocracy in Germany than the activities of former officers, and would remain for years one of the heaviest responsibilities of the Government.Dr. Adenauer then turned to the Soviet threat. He said that the Soviets hadtaken over the expanionist policy of the Tsars, but that since they were able by theCommunist system to co-ordinate all the forces of the nation they had a much better chance than the Tsars of overthrowing Europe. Their principal aim, in his opinion,was to absorb the German Federal Republic in the Soviet system. All other aimswere subordinate to this. If they could obtain the industrial and human potential of Western Germany, then all Europe would be at their mercy; the United states would cease to take the same interest in European defence and the fate of Westerncivilisation would be sealed. The Soviets desired to attain this end first by cold war methods and primarily through the activities of the Communist Party.Generally speaking, the Germans were immune to communism, knowing from theirprisoners of war and &quot; expellees &quot; what communism means, so the Soviets were trying to weaken German resistance by supporting right-wing radical groups andby creating fear. He did not think that the people in Western Europe had any idea how damaging to the psychological resistance of the German people was the fear created by the 25 to 30 heavily armoured Communist divisions in the SovietZone. When people were woken in the night by the passage of Allied transportthrough the streets their first thought was that the Soviet tanks had arrived, andeven the sound of friendly aircraft overhead reminded them of this ever-present -terror. The Soviet Union knew that so long as Western Germany was demilitarisedit would be only a question of time before it fell into the Soviet sphere. The allied occupation troops would not always be sufficiently strong. &quot; To neutralise ordemilitarise Western Germany by treaty, and prohibit her from protecting her neutrality with her own forces, would be absolutely fatal. This idea, which hasbeen advocated by Professor Noack and his friends, is directly attributable to theRussians with whom Professor Noack has direct contacts.&quot; The strong reaction of the Russians to the suggestion of a German defence contribution showed thatthey recognised that it would involve the integration of Western Germany withthe West and thus end the prospects of absorbing her into the East.Dr. Adenauer said he thought the present tensions with the Soviet Union wouldprobably subside without a shooting war, but that there would remain a constantthreat from Russia, who was now firmly established in the heart of Europe and whose pan-Slav and totalitarian traditions would compel her to expand wheneveropportunity arose. The United States would not for ever keep troops in Europe,and Europe itself must therefore take lasting and effective measures against Sovietexpansionism (with such assistance as the United States might offer). This wasonly possible if Europe was genuinely united. The Pleven Plan was, to his mind,the only possible method of protecting Europe permanently. The North Atlantic 1Treaty Organisation aimed rather at the present threat and at maintaining peace WAin the coming years; it would not meet the long-term need. HDr. Adenauer said that he did not regard the state of Germany as dangerous, mthough there were elements in it which might become dangerous if not watched. R,
2He personally had known cases of senior officers who could hardly keep themselvesalive by manual labour and there had been numerous suicides. The war crimetrials, comprehensible in the heat of passion immediately after the war, had beenspun out and there were several hundreds of prisoners still in a certain Westerncountry for whom no trial had been arranged. Despite all this, there wouldprobably not be very strong feeling amongst former German soldiers, and in anycase it would have gradually disappeared, had it not been for the suggestion of aGerman contribution to Western European defence. The possibility of creatingGerman forces again had stirred up the ex-officers, and many of them thought--wrongly that they would have a better chance of participating in the new forcesif they took a lead in the military associations. That was why these associationshad sprung into prominence recently. Unfortunately, Germany had 2,000 formergenerals. There was great rivalry between them and this led, he admitted, tounsuitable and improper expressions and actions. This would pass, but it was important not to let these elements become enemies of the State, which, he was glad to say, they were certainly not at present, except for the Briiderschaft. There were no disquieting National Socialist tendencies except in this one group which, as hehad said, was closely linked with the Soviet Occupation Authorities.Another great danger for Germany was the refugees, the &quot; expellees &quot; and thehomeless victims of bombing. Shortage of houses was a much greater danger todemocracy in Germany than the activities of former officers, and would remain for years one of the heaviest responsibilities of the Government.Dr. Adenauer then turned to the Soviet threat. He said that the Soviets hadtaken over the expanionist policy of the Tsars, but that since they were able by theCommunist system to co-ordinate all the forces of the nation they had a much better chance than the Tsars of overthrowing Europe. Their principal aim, in his opinion,was to absorb the German Federal Republic in the Soviet system. All other aimswere subordinate to this. If they could obtain the industrial and human potential of Western Germany, then all Europe would be at their mercy; the United states would cease to take the same interest in European defence and the fate of Westerncivilisation would be sealed. The Soviets desired to attain this end first by cold war methods and primarily through the activities of the Communist Party.Generally speaking, the Germans were immune to communism, knowing from theirprisoners of war and &quot; expellees &quot; what communism means, so the Soviets were trying to weaken German resistance by supporting right-wing radical groups andby creating fear. He did not think that the people in Western Europe had any idea how damaging to the psychological resistance 0* the German people was the fear created by the 25 to 30 heavily armoured Communist divisions in the SovietZone. When people were woken in the night by the passage of Allied transportthrough the streets their first thought was that the Soviet tanks had arrived, andeven the sound of friendly aircraft overhead reminded them of this ever-presentterror. The Soviet Union knew that so long as Western Germany was demilitarisedit would be only a question of time before it fell into the Soviet sphere. The allied occupation troops would not always be sufficiently strong. &quot; To neutralise ordemilitarise Western Germany by treaty, and prohibit her from protecting her neutrality with her own forces, would be absolutely fatal. This idea, which hasbeen advocated by Professor Noack and his friends, is directly attributable to theRussians with whom Professor Noack has direct contacts.&quot; The strong reaction of the Russians to the suggestion of a German defence contribution showed thatthey recognised that it would involve the integration of Western Germany withthe West and thus end the prospects of absorbing her into the East.Dr. Adenauer said he thought the present tensions with the Soviet Union wouldprobably subside without a shooting war, but that there would remain a constantthreat from Russia, who was now firmly established in the heart of Europe and whose pan-Slav and totalitarian traditions would compel her to expand wheneveropportunity arose.. The. United States would not for ever keep troops in Europe,and Europe itself must therefore take lasting and effective measures against Sovietexpansionism (with such assistance as the United States might offer). This wasonly possible if Europe was genuinely united. The Pleven Plan was, to his mind,the only possible method of protecting Europe permanently. The North atlantic treaty Organisation aimed rather at the present threat and at maintaining peacem the coming years; it would not meet the long-term need.Dr. Adenauer said that he did not regard the state of Germany as dangerous,though there were elements in it which might become dangerous if not watched.
345The Government would have to undertake tremendous work in the social field andto oppose nationalist and neo-Nazi trends. They must take especial care to attract the youth. Unfortunately the German State at present had no attraction for the youth, not being fully sovereign and having no glamour. It was necessary thatthe German Government should acquire sovereignty as quickly as possible, so thatthe inhabitants might learn to respect and love it. The Allies could assist in this and thus strengthen democratic ideas in Germany.If there were to be a German contribution to Western defence, the selection of higher officers must be done with the greatest care. He would appoint only those officers who were strictly reliable, faithful to the democratic constitution and notinvolved in politics. &quot; We are quite aware that we must select officers with thegreatest possible care. We do not in any circumstances want to encourage undesi-rable developments. Thus, in the discussions on the Pleven Plan and in supplyinginformation to the Allies at the Petersberg talks, I put in charge a man whom I regard as absolutely reliable Herr Blank who is one of our younger tradesunionists and who understands fully my own intentions. I should never givesupreme authority in this field to a soldier.&apos;1Nowhere was the European idea so popular as in Germany, Dr. Adenauerconcluded. The Germans always needed an ideal to follow. History had destroyed their dreams of a Greater Germany and the ideal of a united Europenow provided the only possible alternative. The European idea was particularlyattractive to the Germans because they knew of the Soviet threat and the Sovietterror, and the vast majority of them would be ready to contribute immediately and permanently to a European system of defence. This would involve no threat of a-revival of nationalism.But if Germany were not soon given sovereignty and integrated into the Westthrough a defence contribution it might well become a prey to Soviet expansionism.Mr. Stikker, speaking in German, thanked Dr. Adenauer for his remarks, which,he said, had given his colleagues plenty of food for thought. He did not consider,in view of the lateness of the hour, that there could be any discussion, but he hopedthat similar opportunities for informal exchanges of view would occur on futureoccasions.


</content>
</cab>
