<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/47/0 images: 86-98</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   A ugust 1951The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of ....................................TOP SECRET copy No.CP. (51) 24030//? A ugust. 1951CABINETGERMANYMemorandum by the Prime minister as my colleagues know, the question of a new relationship with the german federal Republic is the most important item on the agenda for the foreign secretary&quot;s meeting with Mr. Acheson and M. Schuman in Washington next month.Much has already been done since 1948 towards a more normal relationship and wehave now reached the stage of moving from an occupation regime to a contractualrelationship, while preserving supreme authority in certain essential spheres. Thisis tied up with the question of a German defence contribution. The report of theHigh Commission (a summary of which is attached at Annex I), on the proposed new contractual arrangements, has been received and one of the main purposes ofthe Washington talks is to send new instructions to the three High Commissionerswhich will enable them to resolve existing differences between the three nationalelements in the High Commission, and to complete their negotiations with theGermans before the Foreign Secretary, meets Mr. Acheson and M. Schuman againtowards the end of October. Ali this flows from the decisions taken by the foreign ministers of the three Occupying Powers in Brussels last December, which the lateForeign Secretary reported to the Cabinet in paragraph 6 of CP. (51) 74.2. The Western Government and public opinion are of course well aware ofthe proposed change in the international status of Germany and they conceive,unfortunately with some justification, that the proclaimed Allied desire for a german military contribution places Germany for the first time since the war in a strongbargaining position. These and other recent developments have affected the climate of opinion in Germany. The revision of the Occupation Statute, the Pro-hibited and Limited Industries Agreement, the signature of the Schuman Plan, andthe political and military discussions which have taken, place with, as well as with-out, German participation, about Germany&apos;s own future, have given the german public the impression that the Allies are moving, though, in their view, too slowlyand sometimes incoherently, towards the proclaimed goal of re-establishing Ger-many as a respectable and equal, or nearly equal, member of the Western family ofnations. Germany&apos;s relations with the Occupying Towers have recently been underconsiderable strain over such issues as the export of coal (and in our own casescrap) and, above all, the financial burden of increased occupation costs. Conjsiderable political capital has been made of this by opposition elements in Germany.There is an understandable impatience over any delay in the achievement of equalstatus, and unless this goal is achieved reasonably soon, there is a real danger that political extremists may undermine the moderate elements now dominating Germanpolitical life.3. Meanwhile, my colleagues will have seen Mr. Acheson&apos;s message and the replies sent by the Foreign Secretary and M. Schuman. The texts are attached asAnnexes II, III and IV. It is clear from this correspondence that the americans are set on a programme of study and discussion designed to lead up, before the endof this year, to fundamental decisions on the political relationship of the occupying powers in Germany. The first decisive stage in the programme Is to be the meeting between Mr. Morrison, Mr. Acheson and M. Schuman in Washington in September,when Mr. Acheson urges that we should be prepared to reach tripartite agree-41142a
ment on this matter. The views expressed by M. Schuman are generally in line with our own. He also hopes for early decisions and brings out the close associa-tion between a German political settlement and a German defence contribution.4. Thus the tempo of political evolution in Germany and the programmesuggested by Mr. Acheson (although it will be seen that the Foreign Secretary andM. Schuman have warned him that they consider his programme a pretty tightone), make early decisions unavoidable, both in regard to the political status ofGermany and to her participation in Western defence, which are of course closelyinter-connected. The Allies cannot with safety postpone for much longer a finaldecision on these issues. If, by the end of the year, it appears that they are unwillingor unable to reach such a decision, a damaging collapse of public confidence in theWest will take place in Germany. Either the three Occupying Powers must resolveto carry forward the policy of reconciliation and integration of Germany with theWest, on which we have acted since 1948 in accordance with our numerous publiccommitments in that sense, and to conclude a settlement acceptable not only tothe German Government (who will almost certainly need to make constitutionalamendments which would require a two-thirds majority in the German Parliament)but also to the general body of German public opinion, or we must be preparedto face the danger of the eventual collapse of our German policy and the gradualpassing of Germany out of the Western orbit and probably eventually into theSoviet camp. This view is strongly endorsed by the United Kingdom HighCommissioner in Germany. On the second hypothesis, security considerations would demand a tightening rather than a relaxation of the occupation regime,with all that this implies in increased financial and man-power demands upon us.in addition to the dangerous tensions thus revived in Western Europe. Such a reversal of our policy seems to me an alternative which we cannot possiblycontemplate.5. The question of Germany&quot;s future political status is bound up with thequestion of defence. The firm and lasting association of Germany with the Weston a basis acceptable to other Western European countries, including ourselves, canonly be made certain through defence arrangements. It would be unsafe to allowGermany that degree of political independence which would enable her to rearmexcept under arrangements effectively controlled by the West and linked with thedefence measures of the Allied Powers as a whole.6. Thus the question of Germany&apos;s political status and that of her contri-bution to Western defence are closely connected, and in accordance with thedecisions taken at the Brussels meeting of the North Atlantic Council they are tobe settled together. It was on this understanding and to this end that the high commission report has been prepared. The United States and French Govern -ments are quite definite that a German defence contribution is the price for political equality. It is dear, however, that, in view of the rapid political evolutionin Germany to which I have drawn attention above, we cannot escape from thenecessity of pressing on towards a political solution with its corollary of a defencesolution. The present intermediate position cannot be held much longer. Asettlement which, while giving Germany a new degree of political independence,would eliminate the threat of the recreation of German national armed forces under German control is a necessary prerequisite for any lasting solution of theold problem of Franco-German enmity in Europe. This has been, and remains,a major British interest. The atmosphere, both in France and Germany, is nowfavourable for such a solution. But if this opportunity is now missed, it is unlikely to recur.7. The High Commission^ report concerning a new relationship between theAllied Powers in Germany results from the Brussels Conference of the north atlantic Powers last December. At this meeting the three Foreign Ministersinstructed the High Commissioners to elaborate in broad terms, for considerationby their Governments, a general outline of arrangements to be made with theFederal Republic of Germany, which would reflect changes in the presentOccupation regime by reason of Germany&apos;s participation in Western european defence. The goal was to be the establishment of relations between the occupying powers in Germany on as broad a contractual basis as possible, excepting suchmatters as could be resolved only in a peace settlement. The problems involvedin working out such a relationship were to be explored with the Germans.8. The main questions covered by the Report are summarily outlined in annex I. What is involved amounts, in effect, to a peace treaty without territorialclauses, or a final settlement of claims against Germany.  The central issue is that
of the supreme or special authority of the Occupying Powers, deriving from the unconditional surrender of Germany. It is proposed in the Report to identify the fields in which the Occupying Powers will continue to exercise this authority.It is clear that in order to secure German agreement to the settlement we shall need to limit these fields to what is absolutely essential and that we must retain/- the exercise of our supreme authority only where it is vital to our interests as1 opposed merely to being desirable. It will also be seen from Mr. Acheson&apos;message (Annex II) that he proposes the following definition:  (a) The right to station troops in Germany and to protect their security:(b) Berlin (which is not part of the German Federal Republic and where,therefore, our position rests on the power derived froni the unconditional surrender);(c) The unification of Germany and a subsequent peace settlement;(d) Territorial questions.I am in general agreement with this proposal, but it requires furtherclarification. In particular, &quot; the right to station troops in Germany and to protect their security must specifically include the Allied right to resume supreme authority in an emergency. In fields in which contracts are concluded, the agree-ments will be binding upon both the Allies and the Germans and the exercise of supreme authority in those fields will thereby be renounced by the Allies.9. Upon the entry into effect of the agreements, the Occupation Statute willbe abolished and the Allied High Commission will be replaced by a Council of ambassadors. Before that stage the three Governments will need to agree upon a charter for this council. Normally our Ambassador would deal direct with theGerman Government and German Ambassadors would be appointed in London,Washington and Paris.10. The discussions in the High Commission and with the Germans have pro-ceeded without commitment, though on our side there has, of course, been inter-departmental consultation, both during the discussions and since the High Corn-missions report has been produced. The report shows that differences betweenthe United Kingdom and United States Elements in the High Commission are fewand that it should be possible to resolve them without great difficulty. On the otherhand, differences between the French Element and the other two Allied Elements are more numerous and more fundamental. The French have shown themselves anxiousto interfere as little as possible with Allied supreme authority and they contemplate the persistence of Allied reserved powers in a number of fields. It seems unlikelyat this stage that the French will be moved from these positions except in returnfor the satisfaction of French requirements connected with the European Army-proposals. Annex I to this paper shows the general line which it is proposed thatthe Foreign Secretary should take in Washington.11. The question of the European Army and of the German contribution towards Western defence will inevitably form an integral part of the discussions in washington of a new political relationship for Germany. Mr.. Acheson&apos;s andM. Schumans messages show that in their view the two matters are intimately con-nected and the programme of discussion and study, of which the tripartite talks in washington will form the first part, are designed to lead up to the North atlantic council meeting in Rome in the late autumn at which final decisions would bereached on both aspects of the German problem.12. The United States Government have moved even more definitely than wesupposed in the direction of supporting the European Army concept and although they appear to be taking a more optimistic view than either we or the French thinkjustified about the progress made in the Paris Conference they are clearly determined to do their utmost to bring the European Army idea to fruition, as the only means by which thev think the French will agree to a German contribution. We are accordingly attempting to arrange for discussions to take place on a military basisbetween the Americans, the French and ourselves in Washington before the meet-ings of Ministers, during which the somewhat vague and incomplete contents ofthe Paris interim report can be worked up into a more concrete plan, taking accountof the practical points set out in the Bonn Report on the recent exploratory discus-sions with the Germans. General Eisenhower has expressed his readiness to berepresented at these talks and has even offered himself to serve for an interim period as &quot; Commissioner &quot; of the European Army when formed. It is hoped that as aresult of these discussions the three Ministers may have before them in Washingtona set of proposals for the creation of a European Army, on which they might reach
agreement in principle. These agreed proposals would then be injected into the paris Conference so that some practical and effective plan would be ready forconsideration by the North Atlantic Council at its Rome meeting in October orNovember.13. As in the case of the contractual arrangements, this programme is a verytight one, but there is no doubt whatever that unless the Foreign Secretary is to-come out openly as opposed to further progress on the European Army (involving,as it does, a German contribution) he will be compelled to discuss the matter in some detail with Mr. Acheson and M. Schuman in the middle of September. When theCabinet considered this matter on 31st July (CM. (51) 56th Conclusions. Minute 6)they were concerned primarily with the forthcoming Ottawa meeting of the north atlantic Council, and with the Report on the Bonn discussions on the size, nature and organisation of German contingents. The emphasis now is on the european army and the tripartite talks in Washington, and it is for this reason that it isnecessary once again to consult the Cabinet on the general line to be followed.!4. In this connexion my colleagues should be aware of the far-reachingeconomic and financial problems which will arise from any German defence effort,on which a separate paper is being submitted to the Cabinet to-day. The foreign secretary will take full account of the considerations set out in that paper in any discussions which he may have on the German contribution to European Army.conclusions therefore hope that, before the proposed discussions with Mr. Acheson andM. Schuman begin, my colleagues will accept the following principles for theForeign Secretary&apos;s guidance:  (a) United Kingdom and European interests alike require a settlement whichwill retain the German Federal Republic in the Western camp and will ensure that the Western German defence potential is available to theWest and does not pass to the Soviet bloc. This is also a major factor in present United States policy, as Mr. Acheson has made clear.(b) This policy carries two implications :  (i) for this purpose and having regard to the political evolution already achieved in Germany, there is now no possible alternative toagreeing to a further advance by the German Federal Republictowards political independence on a contractual basis acceptablenot only to the German Government, but also to the main bodyof German public opinion;(ii) the question of Germany&quot;s part in Western defence must be head.We do not want an independent Germany whose security is the sole responsibility of the Allies without any economic or man-power contribution from the Germans themselves. As was explained in CP. (51) 233, the defence of Western Europe cannotbe assured except by the defence of Western Germany and thisrequires German participation. Moreover, it is only by associa-ting her in defence with the rest of Europe that Germany canbe firmly tied to the Western camp.(c) The European Army concept, as advocated by the French and now strongly supported by the Americans, is primarily &quot;a method of ensuring that any german defence contribution shall be inextricably bound up with western European defence as a whole and prevented from leading tothe creation of German national armed forces.(d) Provided therefore that the European Army plan can be made militarilyeffective and acceptable to the&quot;Supreme Allied Commander in Europe,the Foreign Secretary should give every encouragement to it and ifpossible reach agreement with Mr. Acheson and M. Schuman on the broad principles which should govern it. These would then be further examined amongst the participants in Paris, with a view to the sub-mission of a concrete plan to the North Atlantic Council later in the Iautumn.(e) All possible steps should be taken to ensure that the economic burdenborne by His Majesty&apos;s Government for Western Defence is not increased on account of a German defence contribution.C. R. A.10 Downing Street, S.W.I,30th August, 1951.
ANNEX report of the Allied High Commission concerning a New ContractualRelationship to be established between the Allied Powers andGermanyGeneral Principles Underlying the Allied High Commissions RecommendationsSupreme Authority1. It is agreed that the Allies must retain the supreme or special authorityderived from the unconditional surrender of Germany in 1945, but that they willidentify the fields in which they will exercise it. There is agreement that Alliedresponsibilities relating to the ultimate Peace Treaty and the reunification ofGermany, the right to maintain forces in Germany and, in emergencies, to take steps to protect their security, and the occupation of Berlin are not proper subjectsfor contractual arrangements. Mr. Achesoifs formulation of these basic require-ments is set forth in Annex II. The French wish to see Allied supreme authority-maintained in a number of other fields, namely, in respect of reparations, occupation costs, security controls, offences against Allied security and expulsions. They arealso reluctant to see the limitation of the supreme authority expressed in anycontractual document. They would prefer a notification to the German federal government.2. In the fields in which contracts are concluded, the agreements will be binding upon both Allies and Germans, and the exercise of supreme authority inthose fields will thereby be renounced by the Allies.Disputes3. In the event of disputes arising out of the contracts, it is proposed thatresort should first be had to discussion between the parties. If redress could notbe secured, either party could refer to an Arbitral Tribunal. The Tribunal, whichwould be composed of an equal number of Allied and German members and a chairman of another nationality, would have power to take any action necessaryto correct a violation, and to authorise the complainant to take specific direct actionto redress the wrong in the event of the defaulting party&apos;s failure to comply.Principles Underlying the German Attitude4. The German Delegation has declared that if the eventual arrangementscontain provisions which would not be appropriate in a Treaty between equaland sovereign States, they will be unacceptable to the Bundestag and to german public opinion. They have, however, admitted the, existence of certain special problems and in these cases their position does not appear completely inflexible;they have, for example, envisaged proposals which would give Allied Forces some-what greater rights than have normally been accorded to forces stationed by agree-ment in the territory of a friendly nation. They have also expressed themselveswilling to consider the possibility of a contract regarding security controls, provided the conditions of the contract were such as to be politically and constitutionallyfeasible. Similarly, while they have demanded complete freedom from externalintervention in the German governmental process and the relinquishment of presentAllied legislative powers, they are willing to contemplate Allied emergency powers which would include certain legislative functions. The Germans also recognise thespecial character of the Allied position in Berlin. It must be borne in mind, how-ever, that, whatever position the German Delegation adopts when the arrangementscome before the Bundestag, the influence of German political parties is certain tobe exercised in the direction of greater, rather than lesser, demands.Areas of Disagreement and Line to be Adopted in dealing with them5. The differences between the United Kingdom and United States positionsare few and it should be possible to resolve them without great difficulty. Differ-ences between the French position and the positions of the other two Allies are bothmore numerous and of a more fundamental character. The immediate object ofthe Washington meeting must be to surmount these inter-Allied differences so thatthe Allied representatives may present a common front to the Germans in a secondround of exchanges of view which will have to be held before the Rome meeting.41142 &apos; . &apos;    b
While, therefore, the following paragraphs deal principally with inter-Allied differ-ences and the line which it is proposed to adopt in dealing with them, reference is made in certain instances to the difficulties with which the German attitude on particular problems is likely at a later stage to confront us.Security Controls6. The United Kingdom and United States High Commissioners have recom-mended that the contractual arrangements should provide for such minimumcontrols as security may require in the fields of disarmament and de-militarisation,scientific research, industry and civil aviation. The French High Commissionerbelieves that such controls should continue to be based on Allied reserved powers,exercised in the same manner and through the same channels as at present. TheFrench position seems inconsistent with our political objectives.7. It is therefore proposed to support the American proposal that the mini-mum safeguards required should be:(a) those proposed last December by the N.A.T.O. Military Committee:viz. that Germany shall agree not to produce or manufacture (except as may be authorised by N.A.T.O. or other approved Western defence organisation) heavy weapons, military aircraft, naval vessels other thanminor defensive craft, atomic, biological and chemical weapons or long-range missiles; or any specific productive, testing or training equipment or components associated with the development, production or use ofsuch material;(b) that, in addition, restrictions shall be maintained over atomic energymaterials and facilities, and prohibitions be maintained over the produc-tion of civil aircraft and some electronic tubes. This proposal would entail further modification of existing industrial controls (see C. P.(51) 89).Preservation of Democracy8. The French High Commissioner recommends that the Germans should berequired to undertake to maintain a basically democratic and federal form ofgovernment, in which civil liberties are protected and the decentralised structure ofthe police preserved. The United States and United Kingdom High Commissioners,while favouring some such declaration of intention in the preamble of the contractor agreement, would not be in favour of providing for an Allied intervention in theGerman constitutional system except in an emergency in which security was affected.French motives in this matter are suspect; the French would certainly wish to use a general undertaking of the kind envisaged by the French High Commissioner asa means of perpetuating the present constitutional weakness of the Federal Govern-ment, which is already an embarrassment to us. While it is recognised that afundamentally undemocratic development in Germany would imperil Alliedsecurity, it seems politically wise not to attempt to extract particular undertakingsfrom the Germans in this field. We should rather rely on the provisions of theGerman Basic Law and the Constitutional Court which we hope shortly to seeestablished, and upon the concept of Allied security as our proper recourse if anything goes fundamentally wrong.Logistical and Financial Support of the Allied Forces9. The United States and United Kingdom High Commissioners consider thatthese questions should be regulated by a contractual arrangement, while the french high Commissioner considers that occupation costs should continue to be leviedby Allied authority. The French position here is unrealistic. In the absence otinter-Allied agreement of this subject and of a decision regarding a German denfence contribution, it has not been possible to have detailed discussion with the germans in this field. We have however a clear idea of our own requirements regardinglogistical support when the time comes for such a discussion. A separate cabinet paper (CP. (51) ) has been prepared on the economic and financial implications of a German hiilitary contribution to Western defence.Security of the Allied Forces10. There is inter-Allied disagreement regarding the extent to which theAllies should in future rely upon the Germans to deal with offences by Germans
against Allied security and to carry out the expulsion of undesirables from theFederal territory. The French High Commissioner believes that certain excep-tionally serious offences should in normal circumstances only be triable beforeAllied Courts; the United States High Commissioner believes that, although suchoffences should normally be tried by German Courts, the Allies should retain theright to withdraw cases from the German Courts for trial by Allied tribunals. The^ United Kingdom High Commissioner considers that a stage will have been reached at which the Allies should retain no jurisdiction to try Germans. This seems to bethe only position which we can expect the Germans to accept. As a corollary,we shall have to rely upon the German authorities to arrest, detain, interrogateand expel German and other non-Allied security suspects, as soon as efficientGerman services can be provided for that purpose.Legal Status of Allied Personnel11. There is inter-Allied disagreement regarding the status of Allied nationalsserving with the Council of Ambassadors, and their dependants. The UnitedStates and French High Commissioners would wish to ensure for such persons the privileges and immunities provided for Allied military personnel, whereas the UnitedKingdom High Commissioner believes that these persons should enjoy only suchimmunities and privileges as are normally accorded by diplomatic usage. TheUnited Kingdom High Commissioner also considers that the Allies should not attempt to retain any Allied tribunals in Germany except courts martial; it wouldbe difficult to expect the Germans to accept any other arrangement. The AirMinistry agree and although the War Office would prefer to see the present control commission Courts retained, they recognise that this may be politically impossible.Reparations12. The French High Commissioner alone considers that Allied reserved powers should be retained in this field. Apart from this question of principle,the Allies are agreed on the scope of the undertakings which we should wish theGermans to assume in this field. The treatment of German external assets is,however, a field in which we must expect major German resistance.Foreign Interests13. The Allied High Commission has not yet been able to inform the Germansof Allied requirements regarding foreign interests and establishment rights inGermany. It is hoped, however, that Governments will shortly be able to approvea detailed report on this subject so that discussions with the Germans can take place.Form of Arrangements14. The High Commissioners recommend that the subjects which Governmentsagree to place on a contractual basis should be grouped into a small number of agree-ments. They recommend that there should be a General Convention containingprovisions of general applicability. This Convention should be given a form whichsummarises the salient points of the new relationship and can be readily understood by the general public; it will be seen from Annexes II and III that we are in agree-ment with the United States Government on this point. It is of interest thatthe United States High Commissioner has already produced a draft of such anagreement: the general lines of this seem satisfactory. It is not clear whether the document carries State Department approval, but we shall certainly hear more ofthis. To this General Convention should be attached, either as annexes or as relatedconventions forming a single whole with the General Convention, a series of arrange-ments covering the arbitral tribunal, security controls, status and protection ofmembers of the Allied Forces, logistical and financial assistance to the Allied Forces,the foreign relations of the Federal Republic, its relations with other parts ofGermany, certain Allied programmes in Germany and the protection of certaininterests (e.g., decartelisation, restitution, reparations, foreign interests in Germanyand Displaced Persons and refugees).41142
ANNEX IIText of the Letter of 9th August from the United States Secretary ofState, Mr. Acheson, to the Foreign Secretary, Mr. MorrisonDear Mr. Morrison: I have been thinking a good deal about the range of problems we face jointly in integrating a German contribution into the defense ofEurope and in establishing a new contractual relationship with the German federal republic. We clearly ought to reach a common understanding as to how satis-factory solutions to these problems can be reached as quickly as possible.Accordingly, I am writing to you personally with a view to agreement upon a working program which will enable us to reach decisions on the various questions involved. In view of this purpose, I shall not attempt here to discuss detailedsolutions to these problems since I believe this can be handled more satisfactorilythrough appropriate channels after we have agreed upon the general approach.The urgency of these matters arises from their inseparable connexion withbuilding the defense of Western Europe. We all agree that our common plans for western European defense will not be complete without a German contribution.We also agree, and recognised at Brussels, that a German contribution depends upon simultaneous progress in adjusting relations between the Western occupying powers and the German Federal Republic. Nor is the immediate problem ofdefense the only reason for urgency. Both of the above matters bear directly uponthe development of further consolidation of continental Europe, which depends to agreat extent upon decisions soon to be made the ratification of the Schuman plan and the success of the efforts now being made in Paris by European nations toestablish a common defense community.Our approach to these problems has not been a static one. We have thought and still think that rapid progress toward continental European association withina developing Atlantic Community is essential to our common peace and prosperity,and to that of the whole free world. We have also thought and still think thaturgent progress in realising our common hopes for a concrete German contributionto Western defence is also essential. During the past year we have given full support to the development of a European defense force under the Atlanticumbrella as a long-range concept to which all of our efforts should be devoted.At the same time we have thought that the urgency of securing a German contribu-tion to defence required an interim solution which would allow Germanpreparations to get under way in such a way as to be compatible with the longerrange goal of establishing a truly European defence force.We now see a real hope that these two objectives can be combined. The recentand striking progress made in the Paris Conference on the establishment of a european defense community makes it possible that a German contribution canbe obtained quickly through the establishment of a European defense force.General Eisenhower believes this can be done. We are prepared to act on thebasis of this hope and possibility. We will give the fullest support to a programme which would combine the short-range necessity of obtaining the German contribu-tion quickly and the fulfilment of the long-range concept of the establishment of acommon defense force in Europe. We will do this vigorously if the continentalEuropean nations themselves approve this course, if they will promptly work outthe military aspects satisfactorily to the N.A.T.O. Military Committee and toS.A.C.E.U.R., and if they will complete the process in time to allow Germany&apos;contribution to become effective within the time schedule we have all agreed mustbe urgently met for the defence of Europe. For this reason we believe it essentialthat the full elaboration and final implementation of all the necessary administrativestructures and political arrangements in connexion with the European defenseforce would not be a condition precedent to the actual beginning of Germandefense preparations. We would hope that agreement in the Paris Conference,acceptable to N.A.T.O. as a whole, could be reached this fall among the european nations participating at Paris which would allow initial preparations in Germany toproceed pending the final and formal act of establishment of the European force.We believe such steps can be taken without prejudice to the security considerations,relative to German rearmament, which we all have in mind.With these considerations in mind I turn to a plan for moving to rapid agree-ment on the new political relationship to be established between the Westernoccupying Powers and the German Federal Republic. We agree, I think, that the
progress made in this field must be equal to that made in the defense field. Fora variety of reasons the three Governments have been slow in this field and my present concern is that the completion of an agreement recording a basic changein our relations with the Federal Republic might in itself be a delaying factor inits entry into defense. The cumulative effect of recent world events and the presenttemper of German opinion make it not only necessary, but in our own interest, toj put forward, simultaneously with the military solution, a political formula of afar-reaching nature. I also believe that we cannot ignore the effect in Germany ofthe forthcoming peace treaty with Japan.I suggest that in general the Germans should be given full power to conduct their own affairs and that the powers we retain should be determined solely bythe fact that Germany is a divided nation confronted with a menace to its securitybeyond its own control. Our mission there should be changed from one of&quot; occupation &quot; of the territory of a defeated enemy to one of assistance to a partnerwho is freely contributing to our mutual defense. This will involve, as we havealready agreed, abolishing the OCC Statute and the High Commission. supreme authority would be retained in four fields only: (a) the right to station troops inGermany and to protect their security; (b) Berlin; (c) unification of Germany anda subsequent peace settlement: and id) territorial questions. I believe we shouldalso begin to give thought now to the admission of Germany to N.A.T.O. as a full member after she has obtained this new political status and final decisions havebeen taken on Germany&apos;s defense contribution. By proceeding along these linesI believe there is a good chance of building a solid foundation for future Germanco-operation with Western Europe and the whole Atlantic Community.The High Commissioners are now working on a report to Governments onresults of their political conversations with the Germans. We should receive thisreport within a few days. The High Commission has done a great deal of essential work in exploring the numerous complex problems to be dealt with. But I am told that they will be unable to reach agreement on a substantial number of fundamentalquestions regarding Germany&apos;s new status. Governmental agreement on thesematters will clearly be necessary prior to final negotiations with the federal republic. So it seems to me that we should make this one of the primary subjects to be dealt with by the three Foreign Ministers when we meet here in September.I would urge that we be prepared to reach tripartite agreement on these matters atthat time. In view of the work schedule we all face this fall, the High Commission,after submitting their report, should continue to work together and with theGermans on certain matters which do not have to be reserved for our personalconsideration in the conference in Washington.In the light of what I have said, I suggest the following working program:  (1) We should each give urgent attention to the forthcoming High commission report on their discussions with the Germans on contractual relations.We should exchange views as soon as possible after study of their report,and do such other preparatory work as will enable us to reach tripartite agreement on all matters presented in their report when we meet inSeptember.(2) Agreement, reached in our tripartite discussions in Washington on Ger-many&apos;s new status should be sufficiently complete so that the high commissioners could subsequently conduct and conclude final negotia-tions with representatives of the German Federal Republic. We should do our best to give them a text of a basic agreement with the federal republic along broad lines susceptible of public understanding. Wewould also, of course, discuss progress on defense arrangements withspecial emphasis on the accomplishments at that time of the paris conference.(3) The three Foreign Ministers should meet in Europe in late October beforethe meeting of the North Atlantic Council to reach final agreement oncontractual relations. Sufficient progress should have been attainedin Germany so that the German Foreign Minister could join our meeting. We should aim for final Four-Power agreement then. By- - that date, also, I hope that a completed treaty on the establishment ofthe European defense community would have been signed by Govern-ments and be ready for submission to Parliaments. . This would allow the simultaneous submission in the German Bundestag of the final arrangements on both the political and military aspects of Germany&apos;s
association with the West.   I am sure we all agree that this is essential.Both from our point of view and from the German point of view ques-tions of political equality and military contribution must be finallyconsidered and decided together.(4) At the meeting of the North Atlantic Council in late October, we should endeavour to obtain final agreement on those aspects of the abovearrangements which are within the competence of that body.   At this p.meeting we would make the appropriate formal disposition of the^N.A.T.O. act-ion regarding a German contribution assigned to the three powers at Brussels and of the separate mission undertaken by european nations to plan for the formation of a European defense force.   Inother words, we should aim for final agreement, acceptable to N.A.T.O.as a whole, on the problem of the German defense contribution at thattime.If some schedule along these lines seems possible to you, I suggest that weshould, for the present, postpone any formal action on the report recently receivedfrom the High Commission of their discussions with German representatives atBonn on a German military contribution.Such a schedule of work and accomplishment would put us well on the road to a stabilisation of the German problem and a major strengthening of our owndefenses. In confining this letter to the subjects which I have discussed, I do not intend to limit the scope of our talks in September about which our representatives will continue to consult.1 would greatly appreciate receiving your views.I am sending a similar letter to M. Schuman.ANNEX IIIText of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s Reply of 16th August to Mr. Acheson&apos;sLetter of 9th AugustMy dear Acheson,I was very glad to have your personal message communicated by the UnitedStates Embassy about the problems which we face jointly in integrating a german contribution into the defence of Western Europe and in establishing a new con-contractual relationship with the German Federal Republic. I have been giving muchthought to these questions and I am happy to see that we are thinking on similar lines.As regards the contractual arrangements I have only just received the report which the High Commission has prepared and have not yet had time to study it.My first impression is, however, that the United States and British Elements are inagreement on most essential points. Our first objective must be to reach tripartite agreement and I hope this will be possible when we meet in Washington inSeptember. You will already be aware that I have suggested to this end that our meeting in Washington should be preceded by tripartite official talks. Like you i hope that agreement in our tripartite discussions will enable the High commissioners to conduct and conclude final negotiations with representatives of the german federal Republic. I would attach importance to the production of a basic agree-ment with the Federal Republic along broad lines which will be readily understood by the general public.The central problem in the contractual negotiations is that of the retention of supreme authority by the three allies. I agree that the fields in which supreme authority would be retained should be defined. While, however, I am in broadagreement with the four points mentioned in your message, the precise definition of these fields clearly requires further consideration prior to our meeting next month.I agree with you on the urgency of pressing on towards a decision on thesequestions. The working programme which you suggest is a very tight one. we will do our best to adhere to it, but it is clear that the contractual relationship is nota question that can be considered by itself. As you say, both from our point ofview and from the German noint of view questions of political equality and military contribution should be finally considered and decided together.As regards a German defence contribution, I agree that the establishment of a european defence force may well offer an acceptable solution. Before we give our
full support to this project, however, 1 think we must first be sure that it is a practicable proposition and can be satisfactorily organised for the efficient defenceof Europe. I note your view that the recent striking progress made in the paris conference makes it possible that a German contribution can be obtained quicklyin this way. We have no information on this beyond the interim report of the Con-ference, which is, as you know, vague and incomplete on many points of militarydetail. We are now looking at it and I am sure it would be valuable to discuss it with M. Schuman in Washington. In the meantime, since the time factor isimportant, I think it would be useful if our national representatives on the StandingGroup could study it from a practical military point of view. At the same time, Ithink they should make use of the report from the High Commission on their dis-cussions with the German representatives at Bonn, since it contains much usefulpractical material on the possibilities of a German defence contribution.We shall, of course, have to consider the big issue of Germany&apos;s admission tothe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation at a later stage in the light of the progressachieved in regard to her new political status and her defence contribution.I am bound to say that the final phases of your proposed time-table strike measures a bit ambitious, given the complexity of the subject. But you may be sure that my colleagues and I, for our part, will do our best.ANNEX IVText of the French Foreign Minister&apos;s Reply to Mr. Acheson&quot;s Letterof 9th AugustDear Mr. Acheson,Thank you for having been kind enough to inform me, in your letter of 9thAugust, of your personal views on the fundamental problems which are to bediscussed in our conversations in Washington in September.My reply, which is also made in a personal capacity, has been delayed by theneed to consult the new Government on the multiple and serious problems whichwill be examined in the course of the coming Conferences and which cover the responsibilities of several ministerial departments.Let me first tell you how happy I am to note the interest you take in the efforts which France is at present making to create a European Community, and the sup-port which your Government is giving to our plans.This policy is being manifested by the ratification and rapid execution ofthe Plan for a Coal and Steel Pool, now laid before the six Parliaments concerned,and the elaboration of the Treaty concerned with the organisation of a european defence Community which we intend to complete as shortly as possible. We will thus be brought to the preparation of a real political community between the freeStates of Western Europe, including Federal Germany.These initiatives have been inspired by the governing idea, to which my Govern-ment rests firmly attached, of integrating Western Germany, on a basis of equality,in a European community, itself included, in your own words, &quot; in an Atlantic com-munity continually developing.&quot; It would thus be possible to renounce a system ofcontrol whose guarantee is force and which would not be as the experience of theperiod following the First World War proved a satisfactory and lasting solution.At the same time the risk must be avoided, so serious to peace and for the germans themselves, of rebuilding a nationalist Germany which might be tempted to play offEast against West.It is then from this point of view that we should, I think, tackle withMr. Morrison the examination of the German problem.I need not underline the fact that France wishes ardently that Great britain should be able to participate in these arrangements, or be associated with themin a manner corresponding with her interests. If, for her own reasons, and of theseshe must be the only judge, Great Britain were unable to take an integral part inthe European Community, we would regret it, being assured however that, inconformity with the general aim of our common policy, Great Britain would make every effort to facilitate our action and would co-operate closely with the UnitedStates and the European Community in the Atlantic framework, which would thus be reinforced.The policy of European union implies for all those who participate in it. andfor France in particular, important sacrifices, a fundamental modification of tradi-
tional systems which have been established for centuries, and sacrifices of sovereigntyto supranational authorities. But we feel that we make this contribution not onlvin our own interest but in that of the whole of the Atlantic Community. If thisFrench initiative makes the integration of Germany into Western Europe possible,it will be to the advantage of all democratic and peaceful countries.The only too recent past has unfortunately taught us that Germany was subjectto rapid and unpredictable evolution. We must, in our own interest and in thatof the Germans themselves, forearm the Atlantic Community against such possibleevolution. If we wish the integration of Germany in a strongly organised europe to be, and to remain, an efficacious guarantee, we must in our forthcoming meetingsforesee the necessary precautions. Moreover, the Europe in which we wish toinclude Germany will not be set up overnight. Its constitution will necessitatedelays of which we must take account.I am happy to note our agreement on the fundamental principles on whichthe new situation of Germany should be based. I think that, after a preliminary meeting of experts at governmental level, we could reach a rapid conclusion on allthe essential points, taking as a basis the Report of the High Commission and therecommendations of the London Working Party. I believe, as you do yourself,that we will not have enough time to study the details of these documents, andthe most important thing for us to do is to reach agreement on general directiveswhich will enable our representatives to continue and finish their work. But itshould be clear that the new contractual statute should not be put into force beforethe Treaty for the organisation of the European Defence Community is signed andratified by the Parliaments concerned, amongst them the German Parliament.Similarly, I would like to remind you that we had concluded that the international authority of the Ruhr could not be abolished before the entry into force of theCoal and Steel Plan.As regards the contribution of Germany to common defence, I entirely under-stand your wish to proceed rapidly to concrete action. You therefore quitelegitimately wish not to await the final conclusion of all the administrative andpolitical arrangements regarding the European Army before taking a certain numberof preparatory measures for the organisation of defence in Germany. I would agree with you if this is not to be the beginning of the execution of plans and iithe measures undertaken do not include the recruiting of soldiers in Germany. Itis indispensable to my mind that the first man recruited in Germany should be ableto wear the European uniform, just as, from the time the Community is set up,the forces provided by all the participants should become European. Should thereexist at any time the embryo of a German army, the whole basic idea of theEuropean Defence Community risks a definite check. We should therefore examinewith great care the nature of preparatory measures which would be at once bothnecessary and compatible with the success of our plan. Moreover, I can assureyou that, with the help of S.H.A.P.E., we will do all in our power to ensure thatthe drawing up and putting into effect of the Treaty should be achieved with theminimum of delay. Our objective is to establish a text by the end of October. Iwould also like to remind you that as soon as the Treaty is ratified, the machineryforeseen therein will be set up. Recruiting could then begin in Germany, even ifthe European organisation only began to function progressively.I believe that it is most inopportune to bring up the question of the entry ofthe German Federal Republic into N.A.T.O. in the present circumstances. our whole European policy, and in particular the integration of German forces, wouldbe compromised by the possibility of the direct access of Germany into the atlantic community. I feel it my duty to point this out to you forthwith. We could laterexamine the way in which the European Community could be harmonised withother international organisations once it had been established economically, mili-voluntarily and politically.These are, dear Mr. Acheson, the principal problems which are so important for the future of our countries and which I have taken up in this letter. We shall certainly have occasion to discuss them at length in Washington and then in Ottawaand in Rome. I wonder, however, if it will be possible to adhere to the time-tablefixed, given the importance of these questions added to others. We can discuss this again in the course of our coming meeting.Believe me, &amp;c.(Sgd.)        ROBERT SCHUMAN.


</content>
</cab>
