<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/47/0 images: 234-242</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCl MINT IS THE PROPLR TY OF HI&quot; BRI l AN NIC MAJESTY &quot;S GOVERNMENT183Printed for the Cabinet.   October. 1951TOP secret copy No. 31CP. (51) 263ctober. 1951CABINETTREATY  OF ALLIANCE  WITH LIBYAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs should like my colleagues to be aware of the most recent developmentsregarding the negotiation of a Treaty with Libya. It will be recalled that on1st August the Cabinet approved the text of a 25-year Treaty of Alliance withLibya which was to be negotiated in the near future and signed when Libya becameindependent *C.M. 151) 57th Conclusions, Minute 6). Financial and military agree-rhents. to rait concurrently with the Treaty, were to be settled between departments and possibly negotiated in the near future but were not to be signed until theUnited Nations General Assembly had completed their coming debate on Libya.Meanwhile in Libya the United Nations Commissioner^ Co-ordinating Com-mittee. comprising British. French and Libyan members, were considering themanner in which power should be transferred progressively no the ProvisionalLibyan Government in accordance with the United Nations Resolution of 1950.2. The first new development was the Co-ordinating Committee&quot;s conclusionthat, in order to comply with the Resolution, the United Kingdom and France wouldhave to transfer financial responsibility to the Libyans before the declaration of independence: in fact, there should be three transfers, first of comparativelyunimportant functions involving no financial expenditures: secondly, of a largegroup of Powers involving financial responsibility: and thirdly, of defence andforeign affairs on the declaration of independence. The consequence of this decision was that His Maiestyh Government would have to conclude an interim financial agreement with the Provisional Libyan Government before transferring the secondgroup of powers. in the immediate future; and a tentative draft agreement wastherefore prepared by the Foreign Office and the Treasury. It is proposed toinform Parliament after signature of this Interim Agreement.3. The second new development was the preoccupation of the Secretary ofState for War concerning our security of tenure of military facilities in Libya duringthe interval which was bound to occur between the signature of a Treaty of Alliance,on Libyan independence, and the ratification of such a Treaty by a Libyan Parlia-ment. In order to cover this interval it was considered desirable to prepare an interim Military Agreement which could be negotiated at the same time as the interim Financial Agreement and (while containing nothing likely to excite violentcriticism in the United Nations Assembly) would guarantee the stunts quo untilthe conclusion of a new arrangement (i.e.. a long-term Military Agreement nextyear.4. This was the state of affairs when the Libyan Prime Minister. MahmudBey Muntasser. visited London on 10th September, and it was agreed that hisunofficial comments should be sought on all five documents, viz.:  (i) Treaty of Alliance.(ii) Interim Financial Agreement.41304b
(iii) Interim Military Agreement.(iv) Long-term Financial Agreement (very similar to the Interim Agreement).(v) Long-term Military Agreement (a highly complex document of which a tentative draft had been prepared by the interested Departments).Mahmud Bey&apos;s suggestions have been extremely useful as a means of shorteningand facilitating future negotiation and many have already been incorporated, withthe agreement of the Treasury, into the latest draft of the Interim Financial Agree-ment, which is attached to this Memorandum as Annex I. This document was sentto the British Resident at Tripoli on 22nd September with instructions to negotiateit formally with the Provisional Libyan Government.5. On the other document which it was proposed to negotiate immediately,the Interim Military Agreement, the Libyan Prime Minister made comments whichhave not proved entirely acceptable to the Service Departments and a re-draft(Annex II to this Memorandum).was sent to the British Resident in Tripoli, also on22nd September. Unfortunately our intention to conclude this agreement simul-taneously with arrangements for the transfer of intermediate powers to the Libyanshas come under heavy criticism from the United Nations Commissioner and it now appears that it would be dangerous to insist on concluding an interim military agreement with the present semi-autonomous Government. The wiser course seemsto be to negotiate and initial, the agreement with the present Government now, butto defer signature until the day of independence, when the present Cabinet will, weanticipate, be appointed the &quot; duly constituted Government of Libya &quot; by theKing of Libya. After current discussion of this question with the Service Depart-ments and the Treasury it is proposed to send telegraphic instructions to the british resident concerning negotiation of the Interim Military Agreement.6. The Treaty of Alliance and the Long-term Financial and Military Agree-ments, on all of which the Libyan Prime Minister had comments to offer, must nowbe reconsidered by Departments and a meeting of the Former Italian ColoniesCommittee will shortly be called for this purpose.7. Meanwhile arrangements are being made for the Commonwealth Govern-ments to be suitably informed of the position. The United States and french governments, being immediately concerned, have already been informed.H. M.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,3rd October, 1951.
ANNEX IAgreement between the Government of the United Kingdom of GreatBritain and Northern Ireland and the Provisional Government of libya regarding Financial Assistance to Libya to be provided by theGovernment of the United Kingdom of Great Brtain and NorthernIrelandArticle 1Interpretation(1) In this Agreement &quot; the British Government&quot; means the Government of the UnitedKingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland;&quot; the Provisional Government &quot; means the Provisional Government of libya;&quot; the Libyan Government &quot; means the Federal Government of Libyawhich is to succeed the Provisional Government;&quot; the Provincial Administrations&quot; means the local Governments orAdministrations of Cyrenaica, Tripolitania and the Fezzan;&quot; the Currency Commission&quot; means the Currency Commission theconstitution, powers and duties which are provided for in the Currency Lawenacted bv the Provisional Government of Libya on theday of   &quot; , 1951;&quot; the initial issue of Libyan currency &quot; means all Libyan currency notesand coins issued by the Currency Commission against Military Administrationlire notes, Egyptian currency notes and Algerian franc notes which are tenderedin Libya within such period or periods from the date on which the Libyanpound becomes the standard of currency in Libya as the Currency commission may in its discretion determine.(2) As from the date on which the Libyan Government succeeds the Provi-sional Government, this Agreement shall have effect as though references to theProvisional Government were references to the Libyan Government.Article 2Coming into force and duration of AgreementThis Agreement shall come into force upon signature and shall continue inforce until 31st March, 1953, unless previously replaced by an Agreement betweenthe British and Libyan Governments.Article 3Purpose of AgreementThis Agreement is made to ensure that Libya shall enjoy conditions of financial stability and orderly economic development.Article 4Obligations of the British GovernmentIn order to carry out the purpose set out in Article 3 of this Agreement, theBritish Government will, provided Libyan fmajicial affairs are being conducted in a manner appropriate for the achievement of that purpose and provided that theBritish Government is informed fully of Libya&apos;s needs, give financial assistance toLibya as follows:  (a). The British Government will contribute during the financial year begin-ning on 1st April, 1952, to the Development and Stabilisation Agencywhich is to be established under Libyan Law, and may contribute duringthe financial year beginning on 1st April, 1952, to the Finance Agencywhich is to be so established, sums not exceeding  500,000 sterling inthe aggregate for the purposes for which those Agencies are to beestablished.41304 b 2
(b) The British Government will provide one hundred per centum sterlingbacking for the initial issue of Libyan currency in accordance with arrangements acceptable to the British and Provisional Governments.(c) Until 31st March, 1952, the British Government will continue to give finan-cial assistance to the Governments or Administrations of Cyrenaica andTripolitania, it being the intention that the Provincial Administrationswill, out of their general revenues, finance the Provisional Governmentin order to enable the Provisional Government to exercise the powersprogressively transferred to it.(d) As regards the financial year beginning on 1st April, 1952, if, without&apos; prejudice to the undoubted right of Libya to determine its own Budgets,there is agreement between the British and Provisional governments that the Budgets of the Provisional Government and the ProvincialAdministrations for that year have been framed prudently, economically and with regard to the purpose set out in Article 3 of this Agreement,the British Government will make a contribution to the ProvisionalGovernment of a sum equal to any deficiency in the combined Budgets.In the event that agreement is not reached, the British Governmentwill nevertheless make a contribution to the Provisional Government ofany sum essential to support the Libyan economy.Article 5Obligations of the Provisional GovernmentIn order further to carry out the purpose set out in Article 3 of this Agreement,the Provisional Government agrees that there shall be a Chief Financial andEconomic Officer and an Auditor General, who shall be officers of the ProvisionalGovernment and subject to the Civil Service Laws of Libya. All matters relatingto their appointments shall be the subject of consultation between the British and provisional Governments.Article 6Duties of the Chief Financial and Economic Officer and Auditor-General(a) The Chief Financial and Economic Officer shall have access to the PrimeMinister and the Minister of Finance of the Provisional Government. He shall bethe principal financial and economic officer of that Government.(b) The Auditor-Genera! shall be the principal auditor of the ProvisionalGovernment.(Secret)Draft Letter from the British Resident, Tripolitania. to the Prime Ministerof the Provisional Libyan GovernmentTo be handed to the latter when the Financial Agreement is signedYour Excellency,I have the honour to transmit to Your Excellency a Minute of the negotiations with preceded the Financial Agreement, signed to-day between our two Govern-ments, and to enquire whether you agree that the Minute correctly records theproceedings.I avail myself, &amp;c.(Secret)DrXft Reply from the Prime Minister of the Provisional Libyan GovernmentYour Excellency,I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of to-day, which reads as follows:  (set out the letter and enclosed Minute)I confirm that the Minute correctly records the proceedings.I avail myself, &amp;c.
MinuteNegotiations between the British Government and the Provisional Govern-ment of Libya regarding the Financial Agreement of 1951In the course of discussions the British Delegation drew attention to tne openingwords of Article 4 of the Agreement which require that Libyan financial affairs shallbe conducted in a manner appropriate for the achievement of tne purpose set outin Article 3 of the Agreement and that the British Government shall be fully informed of Libya&quot;s needs and explained the reason for this provision. the delegation said that the forms of financial assistance which the British government proposed to give to Libya, while agreed by the two Governments to be those most likely to bring the greatest benefit to Libya, made it essential that the financial arrangements in Libya should be such as to ensure the effectiveness of theassistance. The Delegation regarded it as implicit in the opening words of Article 4that the British Government should be satisfied regarding these arrangements andfelt that it would be of assistance to Libya if they indicated the arrangements which,in the view of the British Government, were necessary for this purpose. the delegation said these arrangements were that Libya should ensure that  The Development and Stabilisation Agency and the Finance Agency(a) no variation of the constitution, powers and duties of the Development andStabilisation Agency and the Finance Agency is made without prior consulation with the British Government;Currency(h) the Libyan currency is always maintained with one hundred per cent,backing in foreign currencies, of which at least seventy-five per cent, shallbe sterling;Currency Commission(c) no variation of the constitution, powers and duties of the CurrencyCommission is made without prior consultation with the British Govern-ment:(d) the holders of the offices of Chief Financial and Economic Officer and auditor General are persons acceptable both to the British Governmentand to the Provisional Government;(e) all questions for the decision of the Provisional Government which havefinancial or economic implications and all draft laws and subsidiarylegislation of the Provisional Government, which have financial or economic implications are considered by the Chief Financial andEconomic Officer and that he is given full opportunity of advisingthereon before the decision is made or the legislation is enacted;(/) the Chief Financial and Economic Officer is permitted to make to theProvisional Government recommendations relating to financial andeconomic matters, including recommendations for the enactment of any law or subsidiary legislation having financial or economic implications;Auditors of the Provincial Administrations(g) the Heads of the Audit Departments of the Provincial Administrations are under the direction of the Auditor General of the Provisional Govern-ment;Budgets(/?) (i) the Budgets of the Provisional Government and Provincial Admini-strations for the financial year commencing on 1st April, 1952, arereviewed by a Budget Committee composed of the Finance Minister ofthe Provisional Government and the principal financial representativesof the Provincial Administrations which should examine the Budgets indraft in the light of the purpose set out in Article 3 of the agreement and prepare a consolidated statement of the Budgets and of the Budgetsof the Development and Stabilisation Agency and the Finance Agency;
(ii) the consolidated statement above referred to is made available to theBritish Government before 31st October. 1951. There should be consul-tation between the British and Provisional Governments, as required,including consultation, prior to the determination of the amount to becontributed by the British Government under paragraph id) of article of the Agreement, regarding the incurring of any major expenditureor obligations in connection with projects not provided for in theprevious Budgets;Languages(i) all accounts and documents relevant to the implementation of the Agree-ment shall be in English and Arabic, each version being equally authoritative;Sterling Area(j) Libya becomes a member of the Sterling Area in accordance with theterms of letters to be exchanged between representatives of the Britishand Provisional Governments, drafts of which have been initialled bythe principal British and Libyan delegates in the course of the negotia-tions.2. As regards the Development and Stabilisation Agency and the FinanceAgency, the British Delegation explained that the constitution, powers and dutiesof the Agencies had been carefully considered at the meeting of Experts on LibyanFinancial, Economic and Development Problems and had been accepted by theProvisional Government. The Delegation said that the British Government feltthat it could not be satisfied that Libya was conducting its financial affairs in an appropriate manner unless the constitutions, powers and duties of the Agencieswere retained substantially as the Provisional Government had approved them.3. As regards the question of Libyan currency, the British Delegation saidthat, for reasons which had been explained fully at the meeting of Experts onLibyan Financial, Economic and Development Problems, the Currency Corn-mission system was the only currency system appropriate for ensuring that Libyawould enjoy conditions of financial stability and orderly economic development,since in no other way could a stable currency be provided so simply, inexpensivelyand quickly. The Delegation said that the Currency Commission system pos-tulated that Libya should be a member of the Sterling Area. The Delegationadded that, in these circumstances, the British Government felt that it could notbe satisfied that Libya was conducting its financial affairs in an appropriatemanner if she did not comply with paragraph ib) above, retain the Currency Lawsubstantially on the lines along which the Provisional Government had approved itand remain a member of the Sterling Area.4. The British Delegation also referred to the concluding sentence of article id) of the Agreement and explained that, in the event that the Libyan Budgetswere not agreed, the British Government would still wish to make a contribution of any sum essential to support the Libyan economy but wouid be compelleditself to assess that sum.5. The principal delegate of the Libyan Provisional Government stated that theProvisional Government proposed the enactment of laws which would include pro-visions for ensuring that:  ia) Consolidated Fund-Credits. All income (including the proceeds of taxes,duties and other imposts and all grants or loans received) of the Pro-visional Government and of the Provincial Administrations is paid into. the Consolidated Fund concerned;ib) Consolidated Fund-Debits. Only expenditure sanctioned by legislation is paid out of the Consolidated Fund concerned;ic) Consolidated Fund-Withdrawals. No sum is withdrawn from the saidConsolidated Fund except under the authority of a warrant counter-signed by the Auditor General in the case of the Provisional Govern-ment or the Head of the Audit Department in the case of the Pro-vincial Administrations, every warrant to be so countersigned if theofficer concerned is satisfied that it has been issued and is in accordancewith constitutional requirements and the provisions of paragraph ib)above, but not otherwise;
(d) Audit. The accounts of all Departments of the Provisional Governmentand of the Provincial Administrations are audited by the AuditorGeneral in the case of the Provisional Government and the Head of theAudit Department in the case of the Provincial Administrations andare rendered as required by those officers; and that those officers andtheir deputies at all times have access to all books, records, returns andother documents relevant to such accounts and report to the Govern-ment or Administration concerned on the exercise of their functions.The British Delegation took note of the statement that the ProvisionalGovernment proposed the enactment of such laws, which they regardedas essential to the orderly conduct of Libyan financial affairs.(Secret)Draft Letter from the Britisfi Resident, Tripolitania to the Prime Ministerof the Provisional Libyan GovernmentI have the honour to refer to the request that Libya should become a memberof the Sterling Area, which was made by the Minister of Finance in the ProvisionalLibyan Government at the Fourth Session of the Meeting of Experts on LibyanFinancial. Economic and Development Problems, and have pleasure in informingYour Excellency that arrangements are being made so that Libya will become amember of the Sterling Area with effect from 1951, the date on whichthe control of Libya&apos;s finances is handed over to the Provisional Libyan Govern-ment. These arrangements will hold good when the Libyan Government takesover from the Provisional Libyan Government.2. So long as Libya remains a member of the Sterling Area, she will be ableto trade automatically in sterling throughout the Sterling Area. She will also beable to trade freely with other countries and to draw automatically upon theCentral Reserves of the Sterling Area to meet such commitments as she may have incurrencies other than sterling, including commitments in United States and canadian dollars. The extent to which Libya can make drawings in United Statesand Canadian dollars will not be limited to her net earnings of these currencies.3. For her part, Libya will, so long as she remains a member of the sterling area, be expected, in common with all other Sterling Area members, (a) to maintain an exchange control system on normal Sterling Area lines;(b) to pay into the Central Reserves of the Sterling Area all United States and canadian dollars that she may earn beyond necessary working balances of banks;(c) to confine her drawings of currencies, other than sterling, to what sheconsiders to be reasonable to meet her requirements and. wheneverstringency exists in United States and Canadian dollars, to limit herdrawings in these currencies to what is required in order to meet heressential needs.4.   I avail myself, &amp;c.(Secret)Draft Reply from the Libyan Prime minister have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Excellency&apos;s letter ofto-day, in which you informed me as follows:  ANNEX note from the Libyan Prime Minister to the British Resident, Tripoli(Draft of 22nd September)Your Excellency,In view of the delay which must necessarily occur before it will be possible to conclude the Treaty of &quot;Friendship and Alliance into which our two Governmentsearnestly wish to enter, and in view of my Government^ desire that interim pro-vision should be made for our mutual defence, 1 have the honour to propose that
the facilities which your Government at present in fact enjoy for stationing Britisharmed forces in Libya, including privileges and immunities in that connection, shall continue pending agreement between our two Governments on any new or differentarrangements.The facilities in question shall include an option on the sites which theCyrenaican Government have been asked by the British Government to make available, and the right if the option is exercised, to use the sites in question formilitary purposes.It is understood that the British Government will carry into effect its plan for accommodating British forces outside the cities, except in a limited number ofcases where the nature of the duties of the British armed forces renders this courseimpracticable. The British Government will use its best endeavours to complete the execution of the plan as quickly as the physical difficulties can be overcome.If the British Government accept this proposal, it is suggested that this note and your Excellency&apos;s reply to it in that sense should be regarded as constituting anAgreement between our two Governments.(Draft)Reply from the British Resident, Tripoli, to the Libyan Prime minister have the honour to acknowledge Your Excellency^ letter of the        day1951, as follows:-(Quote text of letter)I am to inform Your Excellency that His Majesty&apos;s Government welcome theproposal contained in Your Excellency&quot;s letter and agree that this exchange of letters between us shall be regarded as constituting an Agreement between our two Governments.


</content>
</cab>
