<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/47/0 images: 250-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  document  is   the   property  of  his   britannic   ma.iestvs   government confidential Copy No. 3 1CP. (51) 26512th October, 1951CABINETCLOSER ASSOCIATION IN CENTRAL africa memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies and theSecretary of State for Commonwealth relations we circulate herewith for the information of our colleagues the finalcommunique issued on 21st September by the Conference on the Closer Associationof the Central African Territories which we attended at the Victoria Falls withrepresentatives of the three territories. No immediate decisions are required onthe conclusions of this conference; but early decisions will be needed after theGeneral Election and we wish to place our views on record. Our main recom-mendations are that (1) as soon as possible after the General Election His Majesty&apos;s Governmentshould publicly endorse the conclusions of the Victoria Falls Confer-ence, including the proposal to resume the conference in London aboutthe middle of 1-952;(2) at the same time His Majesty&apos;s Government should state publicly that itwould favour in principle a scheme of federation between the three territories on the general lines recommended by the London Conferenceof officials, and considers that such a scheme is in the best interests ofthe Africans as well as of the other inhabitants of the territories; that it recognises that African opinion in the two northern territories has declared itself as opposed to these proposals; but that, in the light ofthe assurances agreed upon at the Victoria Falls Conference and of theeconomic and other advantages of closer association, it trusts thatAfricans will be prepared to give further and favourable considerationto the proposals; His Majesty&apos;s Government should also endorse thestatement in paragraph 11 (i) of the Victoria Falls Conference com-munique that any consideration now or in the future of amalgamation of the three territories is excluded unless the majority of the inhabitants of all three territories desire it, and should make it clear that a similarprinciple would apply equally to amalgamation of two of the territoriesor any part thereof;(3) we should regard the federation of the three Central African territories asan essential measure for preventing non-British influences from theUnion of South Africa from encroaching on and eventually engulfingBritish Central Africa. In our public statement we should endorse the agreed declarations of the Victoria Falls Conference that the british connection and British traditions and principles in the Central african territories should be so strengthened as to ensure that they continue toprevail.Background of our visit to Central Africa2. In our memorandum of 3rd May we submitted to our colleagues the reportof the London Conference of officials, which recommended that closer association between the three territories ought to be brought about urgently and that this shouldbe done not by amalgamation of the territories but on a federal basis. On 31st Mayour colleagues approved our proposals that the report should be published and thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government, without being committed to acceptance of the proposals,41328      . bPrinted for the Cabinet. October 1951
should commend them in general terms for the careful consideration of all the peoples concerned as embodying a constructive approach. The report was dulypublished and a statement to this effect made on 13th June when our intention to visit the Central African territories during the summer recess was also announced.Since then public discussion of the proposals has been proceeding in the three territories.Our visit to Central africa. We duly visited Central Africa during August and September. The Secre-tary of State for the Colonies left London on 24th August and spent eight days in nyasaland and twelve days in Northern Rhodesia before proceeding to the victoria falls. In Nyasaland he held discussions with the Acting Governor and his ExecutiveCouncil; with members of the Legislative Council, European, African and Indian;with representative European bodies, both commercial and agricultural; with certainmissionaries; with representatives of the Indian and Coloured communities; withthe three African Provincial Councils and the African Protectorate Council, whichare the recognised bodies for the expression of African opinion; and with the nyasaland African Congress, which corresponds to a political party. In northern rhodesia the Secretary of State for the Colonies held discussions with the governor and his Executive Council; with the members of the Legislative Council, european and African; with representative European bodies, commercial, agricultural, muni-cipal and trade union; with representatives of the Indian and Coloured communities;with the Barotse National Council, the African Provincial Councils in the five other provinces or representative members of them, and the African RepresentativeCouncil; with the Northern Rhodesia African Congress (a body similar to the nyasaland Congress); and with representatives of African urban councils, welfaresocieties and trade unions. The Secretary of State attended over eighty meetingsduring his tour and thus obtained a complete picture of public opinion on theproposals in Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland.4. The opinions which were expressed to him may be summarised asfollows:  (a) European, Indian and Coloured OpinionEuropean opinion in Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland is generallyfavourable to the proposals, subject to some minor reservations on points of detail. Europeans recognise the economic advantages of federation and theneed to create a strong British bloc to resist pressure from the Union of SouthAfrica and they believe that the proposals would safeguard their own future.The European leaders in Nyasaland, in view of African opposition to theproposals, expressed the hope that if the proposals were put into effect this might be done in such a way as to carry African opinion with them, indeed theywould regard a measure of African support for the proposals as a necessarybasis for their own agreement that the proposals should be carried into effect.Indian and Coloured opinion is at present generally suspending judgment on the proposals. Indian and Coloured people recognise the economic advantages of the proposals but, before they make up their minds finally, wishto see how any detailed scheme would affect their own interests and future in central Africa.(b) African OpinionAfrican opinion in Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland, as expressed tothe Secretary of State for the Colonies during his visit, was almost unanimouslyopposed to the proposals. This opposition has been organised by the twoAfrican Congresses, bodies which are mainly although not entirely composedof the comparatively small educated elements in the two territories. InNorthern Rhodesia the Congress has been influenced and assisted by a localEuropean resident known to be a Communist. In Nyasaland in particular the campaign has been much influenced and indeed largely directed from outside by Dr. Hastings Banda, a Nyasaland doctor in London, who is rigidlyopposed to federation and issued a pamphlet against it directed not againstthe report of the London Conference of officials but against the earlier pro-posals&quot; for federation produced in 1949 by the unofficial conference at the victoria Falls; this pamphlet, although published after the London Conference,was written before it. The administrative staff in Northern Rhodesia and nyasaland, although they have very fully explained the proposals to the african population over a period of weeks, have been bound, because His
Majesty&apos;s Government is not yet committed to them, to refrain from anyattempts at persuasion.   This position has been scrupulously observed, withthe result that the two Congresses have had the field open to them for threemonths.   Although the organised campaign by the Congresses has powerfullyinfluenced the course of events, it would be a grave mistake to regard theopposition as representing nothing more than the views of the educatedminority.   The chiefs and other Africans who have considered the matteralso expressed themselves as opposed to the federal scheme, partly as a resultof the organised campaign against it and of their dislike of change, but largelyalso because of their fear of Southern Rhodesia and in Northern Rhodesia ofdomination by the local Europeans.   It must be admitted that at the timeof our visit African opposition to the scheme was both general and deeply felt.This opposition ignores the advantages of federation, both economic andpolitical, and, as some of the more intelligent Africans admitted, is based noton the proposals in the officials&apos; report itself, but on their fear of what might follow if federation came into being.   Africans are afraid that in that eventtheir land would be taken away, that their political advancement would been dangered, that the Protectorate status of Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland would be abolished and that federation would before long be changed intoamalgamation; many of them also confuse the two terms since the same wordcovers both in a number of native languages. These fears are not justified by theterms of the officials&apos; report, which contains full safeguards for african interests, specifically reserves land and political advancement, and indeed all. other services closely affecting the lives of Africans, to the Northern rhodesia and Nyasaland (and not the federal) Governments under the general super-vision of His Majesty&apos;s Government as at present, and clearly lays down thatthe Protectorate status of the two northern territories would be preservedunder the scheme; while no change in the federal scheme could be madeexcept by His Majesty&apos;s Government with the consent of Parliament.Reassurances to this effect were given by the Secretary of State to the Protec-torate Council in Nyasaland in a formal statement which was repeated at other meetings.   But by the time of the visit African opinion had hardenedand the African representatives at the Victoria Falls Conference were given a definite mandate to oppose federation.   Indeed, it was only with greatdifficulty that the Africans in Nyasaland were persuaded to be represented at the Victoria Falls at all.  In Northern Rhodesia there was a favourabledevelopment just before the conference; as a result of the patient arguments of Mr. John Moffatt, unofficial representative of African interests on theExecutive and Legislative Councils, the African leaders authorised their repre-sentatives to inform the conference that, while the Northern Rhodesia Africansopposed federation, they would be willing to consider the question of federa-tion again on the basis of the officials&apos; report after the policy of partnership between Europeans and Africans in Northern Rhodesia itself had been defined and, as so defined, put into progressive operation.   This very importantstatement means that Africans in Northern Rhodesia are likely to be willingto consider the federation proposals more favourably if as a result of dis-cussions to be held between their representatives and Europeans during thenext few months they are satisfied that their own political future in northern rhodesia is secured.   In Nyasaland also there are now signs of a morefavourable development of opinion which is referred to in paragraph .14 below.5. The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations arrived in Salisburyon 10th September. During the next few days he had talks with the Cabinet, with opposition Leaders, and with a number of representative people. The SouthernRhodesia Government had arranged for him to have meetings at Salisbury andat Bulawayo with representative Africans, urban and rural. Some of the Africanswere in favour of federation, but the preponderant opinion was against it for a variety of reasons, of which some were mutually inconsistent. The SouthernRhodesia Government appeared to be prepared to come out in favour of federation,though there were certain specific points (see paragraph 16 below) on which they expressed themselves as dissatisfied. European opinion generally seemed to bein favour of closer association, with a tendency in some cases to prefer the completeamalgamation of the Territories rather than federation. As the result of the dis-cussions with the Commonwealth Secretary, it was hoped that the southern rhodesian representatives at the Conference would observe care in putting forwardtheir suggestions for varying the London proposals and would do their best to avoid a breakdown of the Conference.41328
The Victoria Falls Conference6. It was made clear in the statement to Parliament on 13th June that the victoria Falls Conference was not expected to reach decisions binding on government-ments, but was regarded as a further stage in our consultation with local opinion.As a result of the differing views expressed to us in the three territories, it became evident before the Conference that we could not hope to reach agreed conclusions on the substance of the officials&apos; report. We therefore decided to aim at preventinga breakdown of the consideration of the proposals and at securing that there shouldbe an adjourned conference next year in London where Africans had made it plain that they would always be glad to attend discussions. We also decided to aim at sercuring general agreement as to the economic advantages of closer association between the three territories and at persuading the Southern Rhodesia delegation to join with us in assurances which would make it easier to carry the discussionsfurther with Africans after the conference. All these objectives were achieved.7. The conference was not easy to handle. The Southern Rhodesia dele-gation consisted not. only of Sir Godfrey Huggins and three of his Ministers, butalso of the leaders of the Opposition parties; they were therefore a somewhat rigidbody. They were anxious to secure some tangible results at the conference whichthey could present to their public opinion, hesitant as much of it is, about theadvantages of federation. They were irritated that African opposition to the prin-ciple of federation, based on grounds which they did not regard as reasonable,prevented the discussion at the conference of the specific recommendations in the officials&apos; report. It was only with some difficulty and with the support of the governors of Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland, of Mr. Welensky and Mr. Moffatt,that we were able to keep the conference on an even keel and to bring it safely intoport with satisfactory conclusions. The communique which was eventually agreedto was based on our own draft with minor amendments by the Central Africandelegations.8.   The main points in the communique are:  (a) There was unanimous agreement that the conference should be adjourned until next year when it would meet in London; it was also agreed thatin the interval there should be discussions within each territory andexchanges of views between the four Governments.(b) Certain assurances to African opinion were unanimously accepted and itwas agreed that, if any form of closer association is eventually decided upon, all these should be enshrined as an integral part of the constitu-tion. The most important of these assurances is that the Protectoratestatus of Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland should be preserved under any federal scheme and that any consideration now or in the future of amalgamation of the three territories is excluded unless a majority ofthe inhabitants of all three territories desired it. This represents a very substantial concession by Sir Godfrey Huggins and his colleagues and means that federation cannot lead on to amalgamation unless a majorityof the Africans accept amalgamation at some stage in the future. an absolutely watertight answer to what is undoubtedly the main objectionof the Africans to the scheme is thus provided. An assurance was also agreed to that the political advancement of the peoples of northern rhodesia and Nyasaland must remain the responsibility of the northern rhodesia and Nyasaland Governments (subject to the ultimate authorityof His Majesty&apos;s Government) and not of any federal authority; thisprovides the answer to the African fear of interference by a federalauthority in their own internal political advancement. Finally it wasagreed that land and land settlement questions in Northern rhodesia and Nyasaland should remain the responsibility of the Northern-Rhodesia and Nyasaland Governments and not of any federal authority.(c) There was unanimous agreement that the policy of economic and politicalpartnership between Europeans and Africans was the only policy underwhich federation could be brought about; on the need for counteringthe dangers which would flow from any weakening of the British con-nection in the three territories; and on the advantages of closer association for the common handling of problems transcending terri-torial problems such as communications, research, defence, &quot;higher education and the planning of economic development.
(d) We joined with the conference in declaring ourselves favourable to theprinciple of federation; the African representatives naturally abstained from this declaration. The conference as a whole recognised thatAfrican apprehensions are one of the main obstacles to the general acceptance of federation. The Northern Rhodesia Africans, in accord-ance with the decision referred to in paragraph 4 above, recorded their agreement to consider the question of federation again on the basis ofthe report of the London Conference after the policy of partnership inNorthern Rhodesia had been defined and, as so defined, put intoprogressive operation.9. The concrete conclusions of the conference were themselves of considerable importance and will in our view materially contribute to the solution of the problem.The conference had an equally important intangible value as the first occasion onwhich Europeans of ail three Central African territories have sat down with african representatives to discuss the relations between the three territories. The african members of the conference, particularly those from Nyasaland, were generally recog-nised to have made an important contribution to it. All the Africansexpressed theirdeep gratitude for the arrangements made for them at the conference and the nyasaland Africans, who had with so much difficulty been persuaded to come,volunteered at the end to other members of their delegations that it had been wellworth while. The African representatives were certainly impressed by the attentionpaid to their views and they cannot have failed to be impressed also by the extentto which the African attitude to the scheme dominated the discussions and the differ-ing views expressed on this subject by the various European representatives. It is significant that Sir Godfrey Huggins had already informed us before the conference,and repeated at it, that if Africans from the two northern territories were to sit on a federal Legislature Africans from Southern Rhodesia would have to sit there also.We can regard the conference as an important precedent for the inter-racial discus-sion of major problems in Central Africa.Our Conclusions and Recommendations10. So far His Majesty&apos;s Government has not declared its attitude towardsthe proposals in the officials&apos; report, but if the discussion in Central Africa ofthose proposals is to go forward it will be necessary for an early statement ofthe views of His Majesty&apos;s Government to be made. We believe, for reasons givenin the following paragraphs, that this statement should be favourable to federation.11. From the economic point of view we believe that there is an unanswerablecase for federation. The economies of the Central African territories are linkedby a common port at Beira for all three of them, a common railway system forthe two Rhodesias, the dependence on coal from Southern Rhodesia of the coppermining industry which is the life-blood of Northern Rhodesia, the prosperity whichcopper mining in Northern Rhodesia brings to a number of industries in SouthernRhodesia, the dependence of the two Rhodesias on manpower from Nyasaland,the many commercial connections between the three territories and, last but not least, the Zambesi and Shire River basin with its great potentialities for the develop-ment of hydro-electric power and irrigation facilities if handled on a central african basis. The population of the three territories will double itself within twenty-five years so that a vast effort in economic development will be needed iffood supplies are to be adequate and living standards are to be progressivelyimproved. For this purpose economic planning on a Central African basis is needed so that the resources of the whole region may best be devoted to economicadvancement. There must be effective machinery for settling priorities in transport, supplies of coal, &amp;c, between the competing claims of the three territories. Industrial development must proceed on a Central African basis ifadequate markets are to be available as a basis for new industries and the morebackward areas are to secure the advantages of this form of development. Thepresent units of government are too small to sustain the vast expenditure needed for hydro-electric development and large-scale water control schemes and difficulties are already appearing between the two Rhodesias in connection withthe plans for the harnessing of the Zambesi and its tributaries. With its enormouspotentialities the Zambesi should be the centre of economic activity rather thana frontier. It may be argued that theoretically all these matters could be handled by co-operation between the three existing Governments. Experience over thepast few years has shown that this not so and the only effective method of handling41328 B 3
them is by a single federal authority answerable to a single Central AfricanLegislature. There can be no doubt, moreover, that in external economic relationsCentral Africa operating as a single economic unit would be more effective thanthe three territories operating separately, while from the long-term point of view a Central African federal state with a more broadly based economy would be in a stronger position to face a world recession than the three territories individually.12. Important as the economic arguments in favour of federation are, weare convinced on the basis of our recent experience in Central Africa that thepolitical arguments are still stronger. We referred in our memorandum of3rd May to the urgent need to counter South African pressure on Central Africa.Immigration from the Union into the two Rhodesias is almost double that fromthe United Kingdom. Not all of this is Afrikaner immigration, but we havedefinite evidence that Afrikaner immigration is being officially inspired, while,as a sign of the political interest being taken by the Nationalist Party in central africa, a census of all South Africans in the Rhodesias and their political sympathiesis now being conducted through the Dutch Reformed Church. In SouthernRhodesia a new party has just been formed under the title of the DemocraticParty; it is directed by a Mr. Cloete, who receives his salary from South africa and described himself to The Times correspondent as an Afrikaner extremist.In Northern Rhodesia the position is still more serious in view of the comparativesmallness of the European community and the dependence of the mining industry on white South African labour and owing to the difficulty of getting suitablepeople from this country. It is thought probable that at the next General election in 1953 the Afrikaners will obtain five of the ten European seats on the Northern Rhodesian Legislative Council if the present electoral arrangements remain unchanged. There is a general fear among Europeans of British stock that theAfrikaners will gradually prevail, but the British element among the unofficialEuropean community has so far shown little willingness to take active steps against this menace. The leading Southern Rhodesian Ministers are gravely apprehensive that the Afrikaners wilt succeed in dominating Northern Rhodesia and will thenturn back on them. In Nyasaland there are so far few Afrikaners and the danger is less immediate; but if the two Rhodesias were absorbed or dominated by theUnion Nyasaland could hardly stand out against such encroachment.13. Southern Rhodesia has tightened up its immigration control law and made two years&apos; residence and Southern Rhodesia citizenship a necessary qualifi-cation for the vote. The Northern Rhodesia Government is hoping to introducesimilar legislation before the end of this year and the Colonial Secretary took theopportunity of emphasising the urgency of this to the Governor and leadingunofficials. But the geographical and economic circumstances of the two Rhodesiasmake ft impossible to keep out Afrikaners entirely and in any case immigration control and tighter conditions for the franchise, important though they are, are not sufficient by themselves to resist encroachment by the Union. We are faced in central Africa with pressure by a country far stronger economically andindustrially than any of the Central African territories, led by a militant nationalist party with expansionist aims, anxious to strengthen its influence in the north.This pressure can be countered only by an equally firm policy of resistance to it bothin the political and economic spheres a policy which must have the support bothof the European and African populations of the Central African territories, andwhich in our view has little chance of succeeding unless we can establish a Britishbloc of territories in Central Africa knit together by constitutional ties. To secureour objective we must establish conditions in Central Africa under which the british element in the European population will remain not only substantially greater in numbers than the Afrikaners but able and willing to assert their loyalty to theBritish connection, and at the same time conditions in which the relations betweenEuropeans and Africans will be progressively improved and the share of the africans in the political and economic life of the territories will be progressively increasedunder the policy of partnership. In our view the proposals for federation are welldesigned to achieve these conditions. Political development for Africans in the twonorthern territories is secured under the scheme to their territorial Governments andHis Majesty&apos;s Government. The Victoria Falls Conference has accepted theprinciple of partnership as an essential condition for federation; the federal legislature would contain African representatives from all three territories, and thefederal constitution would have full safeguards for African interests. The pre-vention of excessive Afrikaner immigration could be far more effectively secured
on a Central African basis than by the three territories acting separately. Thecreation of a Central African federal state would greatly strengthen the confidence in themselves of the British elements in all three territories and their willingness to resist Afrikaner encroachment and by increasing the political and economic strengthof Central Africa as a whole and reducing friction between its component partswould provide a much firmer foundation on which that resistance could be based.On the other hand, if owing to African opposition federation had to be abandoned,relations between Europeans and Africans in the two Rhodesias would be. seriously damaged and particularly in Northern Rhodesia a political vacuum would be created which would open the way for Afrikaner infiltration on a still more powerfulscale. Signs are not lacking that the South African Government, although openlyits attitude is correct, is anxiously hoping that the federation proposal will come to nothing.14. We cannot too strongly emphasise the danger to British and african interests at present assailing the Central African territories. In our view we cannot continue to adopt a negative attitude towards this danger. It is incumbent on usto take positive steps to resist it. The establishment of a federal state in central africa is by far the most effective step that could be taken and this, combined withthe economic advantages, convinces us that positive support for federation shouldbe given by His Majesty&apos;s Government. The Afrikaner pressure, moreover, makesearly action urgent; but we should be strongly opposed to any attempt to force thefederation proposals through in the face of the present solid African opposition.Fortunately the Victoria Falls Conference conclusions, with the adjournment ofthe conference until the middle of next year, give time for further discussions withAfricans in Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland. The African leaders in northern rhodesia have already indicated that they will be prepared to consider the proposalsagain provided that their own political future inside Northern Rhodesia is securedand discussions to this end between Europeans and Africans are shortly to begin.The African members of the Nyasaland delegation at the Conference revised theirviews materially after hearing the discussions although their mandate preventedthem from saying so publicly and since the Conference, they have already succeeded in persuading one of the three Provincial Councils in Nyasaland to give furtherconsideration to the scheme. The Governor of Nyasaland considers that, providedthat His Majesty&apos;s Government will publicly state its general support of the federal scheme, there is a distinct chance, given a period of from six to nine months, of persuading Africans to take a less negative line. Both he and the Governor ofNorthern Rhodesia are convinced that if further progress is to made a favourablestatement by His Majesty&apos;s Government is an essential prerequisite to it. If there-fore our opinion of the advantages of federation is accepted it is clearly important that an early opportunity of announcing this should be taken by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.15. We accordingly recommend that, at as early a date as possible after theGeneral Election, the following action should be taken:  (1) His Majesty&apos;s Government should publicly endorse the conclusions of the victoria Falls Conference, including the proposal to hold a furtherrepresentative conference in London about the middle of next year.(2) His Majesty&apos;s Government should at the same, time state publicly that itwould favour in principle a scheme of federation between the three terri-tories on the general lines recommended by the London Conference of officials and considers that such a scheme would be in the best interestsof the Africans as well as of the other inhabitants of the territories;that it recognises that African opinion in the two northern territories has declared itself as opposed to these proposals; but that, in the light of the assurances agreed upon at the Victoria Falls Conference and of theeconomic and other advantages of closer association, it trusts thatAfricans will be prepared to give further and favourable considerationto the proposals. His Majesty&apos;s Government should also endorse thestatement in paragraph 11 (i) of the Victoria Falls Conference com-munique that any consideration now or in the future of amalgamation of the three territories is excluded unless the majority of the inhabitants of all three territories desire it, and should make it clear that a similarprinciple would apply equally to amalgamation of two of the territoriesor any part thereof.
(3) The Governors of Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland should be authorisedto arrange further discussions on the proposals with Africans in the two territories on the basis of His Majesty&apos;s Governments statement thatthey favour the scheme in principle and in the light of the assurancesagreed to at the Victoria Falls Conference.(4) The discussions envisaged in paragraph 5 of the final communique of the victoria Falls Conference between His Majesty&apos;s Government and thethree Central African Governments, or between the three central african Governments themselves, should be undertaken in due coursewith the object of elucidating points of detail in the officials&apos; report in preparation for the London Conference.. (5) We should regard the federation of the three Central African territories as an essential measure for preventing non-British influences from theUnion of South Africa from encroaching on and eventually engulfingBritish Central Africa. In the public statement referred to above weshould endorse the agreed statement of the Victoria Falls conference that the British connection and British traditions and principles in theCentral African territories should be so strengthened as to ensure thatthey continue to prevail.16. No detailed examination of the proposals in the officials&apos; report is neededat this stage, but there are certain important points on which we wish to recordour views. The final communique of the Victoria Falls Conference records thatthere are certain proposals in the officials&apos; report relating to the federal Legislaturewith which the Southern Rhodesian Government do not agree; these are known to concern the number of nominated members proposed for that Legislature, the african Affairs Board and the Minister for African Interests. Our views on these points are as follows:  (a) The Southern Rhodesia difficulties about the nominated members in theLegislature can to some extent at any rate be met. The officials&apos; report(paragraph 90 and Annex VII) proposes that the federal Legislatureshould consist of seventeen members from Southern Rhodesia, elevenfrom Northern Rhodesia and seven from Nyasaland, three of whomfrom each territory would represent African interests. Of the twenty-six general members the fourteen from Southern Rhodesia and the eight from Northern Rhodesia would be elected, while the four fromNyasaland would be nominated by the Governor from a panel selected by the Convention of Associations (the body officially representingEuropeans in the territory). The Southern Rhodesia Government takethe view that on the basis of twenty-two elected members it would bedifficult to operate a party system effectively. In our view we can meet them over this by arranging for the four Nyasaland representatives tobe elected, either directly or indirectly. Of the African representativesthose who are actually Africans could also be elected indirectly, leavingonly three European representatives of African interests to be nominated.(b) It is possible that Southern Rhodesia will suggest a bicameral legislaturewith a Senate consisting partly of members representing African interests as a substitute for the African Affairs Board proposed by the officials.Our view (which was made clear to the Southern Rhodesian Cabinetby the Commonwealth Secretary) is that any such suggestion should be opposed, first because a second chamber would make the constitutioncumbersome, and secondly because we do not believe that a second chamber, however composed, could be as effective as a safeguard for african interests as the African Affairs Board proposed in the report.Powers of delaying legislation would not be sufficient, while it wouldbe hard to secure a second chamber with an absolute veto.(c) The Southern Rhodesia Government is likely to suggest that the Ministerfor African Interests should be appointed in the ordinary way on therecommendation of the Prime Minister rather than by the Governor-General subject to the approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government. Wethink that such a proposal should be rejected, since a Minister respon-sible to the Prime Minister rather than to the Governor-General andHis Majesty&apos;s Government could not effectively exercise the safeguard-ing powers proposed for the Minister for African Interests in the report,which are the lynch-pin of the proposed federal safeguards. Such achange would moreover be strongly objected to by African opinion and
would make it more difficult to convince Africans in the northern terri-tories that the scheme does not prejudice their interests. The Common-wealth Secretary sought to persuade the Southern Rhodesian Govern-ment that, with good will on both sides, the appointment of the Ministerof African interests need cause no constitutional difficulties. Theycould be assured that His Majesty&apos;s Government would for its partwork the system reasonably.17. It will also be open to His Majesty&apos;s Government at the conference inLondon next year, and indeed to the African representatives at that Conference,to put forward any amendment of detail to the proposals which may appearnecessary from the African point of view since, owing to African opposition to theprinciple of federation there was no opportunity at the Victoria Falls Conferenceof obtaining the views of Africans on the details of the scheme. The way for thisis kept open by the statement in paragraph 14 of the Victoria Falls Conferencecommunique.J. G.P. C. G. W.Final Communique of the Conference on the Closer Association of central african Territories: 21st September, 19511. The present Conference was convened by the Governments of the UnitedKingdom, Southern Rhodesia, Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland for the purposeof discussing the question of closer association of the British territories in central africa.2. The Conference opened at Victoria Falls on Tuesday, 18th September,and was of a representative character. In the case of Southern Rhodesia the repre-sentatiyes included the Prime Minister and other Ministers, and leaders of theOpposition parties in Parliament. In the case of Northern Rhodesia the delegationconsisted of the Governor and official and unofficial members of the LegislativeCouncil including Africans. Nyasaland was represented by the Governor, senior officials and leading unofficial persons, European and African. The UnitedKingdom delegation consisted of the Secretaries of State for the Colonies and forSesSH^eratai-Relations, accompanied by some of their chief advisers.3. The Conference had before it the Report prepared last March by a numberof senior official advisers of the four Governments concerned. The authors ofthat Report had been requested &quot; to examine the problem in all its aspects and consider whether it is possible in the light of this examination for them to formulateproposals for a further advance to be made in the closer association of the threeCentral African territories which they could recommend to the Governments ofthese Territories and to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom.&quot; their work was purely exploratory and did not commit any of the participating Govern-ments to the adoption of any proposals that they might formulate.4. The Report of the London Conference of officials was unanimous on all points. Its main recommendation was that closer association between the three territories ought to be brought about and that the need for this is urgent. Itrecommended further that this should be done not by amalgamation of the terri-tories, but on a federal basis; and put forward in some detail a scheme framed totake particular account of the special features of the Central African situation,including the self-governing status of Southern Rhodesia, and designed .o providesubstantial safeguards for the interests of Africans. Moreover, those matters most closely affecting the life of Africans would, under the proposals in the Report,come within the territorial and not within the federal sphere; and within theterritorial sphere the Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland Governments would remain responsible, as at present, to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom.5. In announcing the present Conference it has from the outset been made clear that there was no intention of reaching decisions at it binding on any Govern-ment. It was realised that such a Conference might disclose points of differencewith regard to the principle of federation as well as to the proposals made in Report


</content>
</cab>
