<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/32/0 images: 424-431</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Cuw* *&amp;*    87*.this DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1949CONFIDENTIALCP. (49) 247th February, 1949CABINETUNITED NATIONS: NON-SELF-GOVERNING TERRITORIES ANDTRUSTEESHIPMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the colonies annex, for the information of my colleagues, a report on the work ofthe first part of the United Nations Third General Assembly in respect of: (a) Information on Non-Self-Governing Territories (Chapter XI of the charter).(6) Trusteeship (Chapters XII and XIII of the Charter).2. Regarding (a), the United Nations has now realised that the UnitedKingdom is not to be shaken from its refusal to agree to a widening of the charter so as to permit that body either to exercise supervision over&apos; the adminis-tration of the Colonial territories or to discuss the political and constitutionalaffairs of the Colonies. There was considerably less pressure in this directionthan at either of the two previous sessions of the General Assembly.3. As regards trusteeship the situation is less satisfactory. As the reportshows, there was a serious deterioration in the atmosphere of the trusteeship council at its Third Session following on the decision of the U.S.S.R. to take up their seat on the Council. Thus, in the Report of the Trusteeship Council tothe General Assembly, prejudice and ignorance of conditions in trust territoriescombined to produce a series of superficial, largely platitudinous and for the mostpart impracticable recommendations. The conduct of the Council&apos;s discussionswas such as to damage its reputation as a serious organ of the United Nations,and to transform it into a forum for largely ignorant and often malicious criticism of the Administering Authorities, serving ends of political propaganda ratherthan the interests of the inhabitants of trust territories. The bitterness of the debates in the Trusteeship Council was also reflected in the discussions on trustee-ship matters in the Fourth Committee of the United Nations, where the atmosphereduring the debates on information on Non-Self-Governing Territories had been,on the whole, friendly and composed.4. The Trusteeship Council has wider powers than those possessed by thePermanent Mandates Commission of the League of Nations, and if it continuesto act as it did at its Third Session it can hardly fail, through the effect of itsdebates and recommendations on sections of the local populations, to become a source of embarrassment to the Administering Authorities in their task ofgoverning and developing their trust territories. I am much concerned therefore that our policy towards the Trusteeship Council and the United Nations ontrusteeship matters should be such as to minimise these injurious effects.5. We must obviously continue to carry out to the best of our ability our obligations towards the Trusteeship Council under the Charter and the Trustee-ship Agreements, and to co-operate with the Trusteeship Council to the full inthe discharge of its legitimate functions. But this will not prevent some ofthe non-Administering Members from regarding the United Kingdom as an obstacle to Colonial progress.   As the principal Administering Authority of36537 copy No. ^
trust territories, we have consistently refused to agree to any extension of thepowers of the Trusteeship Council inconsistent with the terms of the charter and the Trusteeship Agreements and our own duties and responsibilities as anAdministering Authority. We cannot, for instance, agree to the principle ofprior consultation with the Trusteeship Council without making the task ofadministration an impossible one, and prejudicing our plans for the futured development of our trust territories, and particularly for the future organisationof East Africa. .6. It seems necessary to isolate the Soviet representative in the trusteeship council and to expose the real motives behind the Soviet Government, theabsurdities and inaccuracies of their attacks, and the conditions in the soviet union and satellite countries. The Americans should also assist in this. Thereare other non-Administering Members whose doctrinaire and ill-informedcriticism is sometimes as harmful as the malicious Soviet propaganda. We should maintain as patient and conciliatory an attitude towards them as possible, butat the same time refuse to accept compromises that are unreal or result indangerous conclusions. So far as possible our spokesmen should move forward from the defensive and seize the opportunity to proclaim and stress before world opinion those positive achievements in the advancement of dependent peoples,particularly in recent years, of which we have good reason to be proud.7. As regards the Administering Authorities, there is nearly always identity of views between the United Kingdom, France, Belgium and Australia. Ourcollaboration with the French and Belgians has been useful and a number ofexchanges of views have taken place with fruitful results.. The attitude ofNew Zealand is less helpful and I have recently discussed our policy withMr. Fraser, who now understands our position. So far as other members ofthe Commonwealth are concerned, we are also often at variance with India and,to a lesser degree, Pakistan in the Fourth Committee and General Assembly.8. The attitude of the United States is of importance, as experience inthe Trusteeship Council and the Fourth Committee has shown that, when theUnited Kingdom and the United States are agreed on a line of action and are determined to see it through, their combined influence can usually prevent anyother solution from obtaining a two-thirds majority. The United States do not always see eye to eye with us, though recently there has been a steady adjustment of their views to ours. We must continue our efforts to secure United Statescollaboration or at least to prevent them from seeking compromise solutions on questions of principle which could prejudice our position in our trust territories.9. The United Kingdom has been well served by Sir Alan Burns on the trusteeship Council and the appointment of Mr. Grantley Adams of Barbadosto the United Nations Delegation was a successful experiment. The FourthSession of the Trusteeship Council opened on 24th January and promises to bea stormy session. I am convinced that the principal Administering Authoritiesshould continue to maintain a firm line, for only in this way will they be ableto make the Trusteeship Council a more workable body, or at least prevent it from prejudicing the administration and development of the trust territories.A. C. J.Colonial Office, S.W. 1,7th February, 1949.
UNITED NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLYThird SessionREPORT ON PROCEEDINGS IN REGARD TO TRUSTEESHIP and information  ON  NON-SELF-GOVERNING   TERRITORIESA. Non-Self-GovernIng TerritoriesIntroductionChapter XI of the Charter contains a general declaration of colonial policy and, in Article 73 (e), an obligation on the Colonial Powers to transmitregularly to the Secretary-General tor information purposes, subject to suchlimitation as security and constitutional considerations may require, certain technical information on economic, educational and social conditions in the non-self-governing territories for which they are responsible (other than trustterritories which are covered by Chapters XII and XIII).2. In spite of the strictly limited character of this obligation, during thefirst and second sessions of the General Assembly attempts were made :-&apos; (a) To include political and constitutional questions amongst the subjects on which the Colonial Powers have to send information; and(b) to establish the principle that the Colonial Powers are accountable tothe United Nations for the administration of their Colonial territories.These attempts, which are made largely under Slav and Indian leadership, were strongly resisted by the United Kingdom and were defeated (although a Resolu-tion was passed encouraging the voluntary transmission of political information).3. The procedure adopted for handling the information sent in to theSecretary-General has been that the Secretariat have prepared summaries andanalyses for examination by a Committee consisting of the eight Colonial Powerstransmitting information and an equal number of other countries. So far theCommittee has been established on an ad hoc basis for one year only at a time.The first Committee, termed the A d Hoc Committee, met before the 1947 Assembly.The second Committee, known as the Special Committee on Information from non-Self-Governing Territories, was set up at the 1947 Assembly and met in geneva in September of this year.Special Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories.4. The terms of reference of the Committee were to examine the informationtransmitted and submit reports thereon to the General Assembly with suchprocedural recommendations as it might deem fit, and such substantive recom-mendations as it might deem desirable relating to functional fields generallybut not with respect to individual territories.5. The instructions to the United Kingdom representative were to be asco-operative as possible, but to oppose firmly any attempt to widen the obligationembodied in Article 73 (e). He was in particular to be guided by the followingpoints :      0        . .   &apos;(a) The Charter gives no warrant for any United Nations supervision overcolonial administration;(b) His Majesty&apos;s Government is not prepared to transmit political orconstitutional information under Article 73 (e) (although, as stated inparagraph 8 below, the Library of the United Nations is supplied with the fullest information oh ail aspects of colonial affairs, includingpolitical developments);(c) Any attempt to make the Committee a permanency should be resisted,since its procedural functions cannot be permanent, and the examina-36537 b 2
tion of social or economic conditions in colonies is more properly a function of the Specialised Agencies, as part of their study of such questions on a world-wide or regional basis.6. As had been expected, the non-Administering members attempted toextend both the life and scope of the Special Committee, but the pressure wasnoticeably less than in previous years. The other non-Administering membersalso tended to dissociate themselves from the irresponsible attacks of the soviet representative. Eventually the Special Committee submitted to the general assembly four draft Resolutions, all confined to procedural matters, which theUnited Kingdom was able to support.Fourth Committee and General Assembly7. The discussion of the Special Committee&apos;s Report in the Fourth Gom-mittee was marked by a general improvement in the atmosphere as comparedwith previous years, and again by a definite tendency on the part of most ofthe non-colonial Powers to dissociate themselves from the Slav bloc. The Slavsand a few others continued to argue that Chapter XI entitles the United nations to exercise the same supervision over colonial administration as its does overtrust territories. Most of the non-colonial members, however, accepted the factthat the only obligation on the Colonial Powers is the limited one in Article 73 (e)and tended rather to appeal to the Colonial Powers for co-operation in exceedingtheir obligations under the letter of the Charter than to argue that such proposals were, in fact, compatible with the wording of the Charter. The Slav repre-sentatives introduced a number of amendments to the Special Committee&apos;s reso-resolutions which, had they been accepted, would have given the United nations the right to send missions of investigation to and to receive petitions from colonial territories, would have authorised the Secretary-General to draw on unofficialas well as official sources of information in compiling his summaries and analyses;and would have recommended the obligatory submission of political information.All these amendments were easily defeated. The Slav representatives also pro-posed that the Special Committee should become a permanent body. When thisproposal was rejected, the Slav bloc voted against a Brazilian proposal to consti-&apos; tute the Special Committee for a further three years instead of only one year, ashad been proposed by the Special Committee, and were thus instrumental indefeating that proposal. The Special Committee&apos;s resolutions were then for-warded to the General Assembly with only insignificant textual amendments.8. In the Fourth Committee, however, the Indian representative introduced a fifth resolution inviting the Colonial Powers, when they considered it no longer necessary to transmit information about any of their colonial territories underArticle 73 (e), to submit to the United Nations full details of the constitutionalinstruments by virtue of which they deemed the territory concerned to have become self-governing. After considerable debate this resolution was carried inthe Fourth Committee by twenty-nine votes in favour, none against, and seventeenabstentions. The United Kingdom abstained, explaining that, while HisMajesty&apos;s Government would, as a matter of courtesy, inform the Secretary-General whenever any change occurred in the constitutional status of any of its&apos;territories as a result of which it deemed it inappropriate to transmit informa-tion in respect of that territory under Article 73 (e), and while His Majesty&apos;sGovernment had always published, and would continue to do so, full details ofany changes that occur in the status of the territories under its control, it couldnot agree to bring the details of these changes officially to the notice of the Secre-tary-General in such a way that this information could become a matter fordiscussion and debate in the United Nations. It would, however&quot; continue tosupply full details to the Library of the United Nations, which is regularly supplied with the fullest information on all aspects of the Colonial Empire, includingpolitical developments. The United Kingdom representative repeated this state-ment before the General Assembly.9. All five resolutions were then adopted by the General Assembly withouta vote. All except the Indian Resolution are in accord with the policy of HisMajesty&apos;s Government towards Chapter XI of the Charter; and, in particular, theSpecial Committee has again been established for 1949 only. The result was thus satisfactory. - r        .-h
B. Trusteeship Questions10.   The Trusteeship Council is composed of-(a) Six administering Authorities (Australia, Belgium, France, New Zealand,the United Kingdom, the United, States).(b) China and the U.S.S.R. as permanent members.(c) A sufficient number of other non-Administering Members, elected for athree-year term of office, to ensure parity between Administering and non-Administering Members. At present there are four elected members: Costa Rica, Iraq, Mexico and the Philippines.11. A brief note on the third session of the Trusteeship Council (June-August 1948) is necessary as a background to the discussions at the general assembly.Third Session of the Trusteeship Council12. Although there has always been a latent division in the trusteeship council between Administering and non-Administering members, during the first two sessions this cleavage did not come to the surface and the Council showed some signs of developing a sense of responsibility. This was largely due to the fact thatthe Soviet Government had decided to boycott the Trusteeship Council, allegingthat the Trusteeship Agreements were illegal. At the very end of the Councilssecond session, however, in connection with the discussions on Palestine, the SovietGovernment reversed its attitude and took up its seat on the Council, since whenits participation in the Council&apos;s work has been purposely vexatious. At thethird session the Soviet representative indulged in violent propaganda attacks against the Administering Authorities, and in long procedural wrangles. As aresult he succeeded first in splitting the Council and then in exasperating it. it became apparent towards the end of the Session that he had overplayed his hand,but he had, in the meantime, crystallised the latent antagonism in the CounciLAlthough most other non-Administering members were generally reluctant to associate themselves with the Soviet representative^ more violent and abusiveattacks this did not lead them to adopt a more understanding attitude towards the administering Authorities. On the contrary, the resultant worsening in thegeneral atmosphere of the discussions seems to have been an added encouragement to them to indulge in doctrinaire and ignorant criticism without regard to conditions in the trust territories concerned.13. The Annual Report on the Administration of Tanganyika for 1947 was examined in this hostile atmosphere. The Council paid particular attentionto political and educational conditions in Tanganyika and also devoted much timeto discussing the East African Inter-Territorial Organisation. The latent dis-agreement on the respective rights and powers of the Council on the one hand andthe Administering Authorities on the other came to the fore over the questionwhether the Council was entitled to be consulted before an administering authority set up an &quot;administrative union.&quot; All the non-Administeringmembers claimed that such prior consultation should take place. The UnitedKingdom, supported by France, Belgium and Australia, maintained that, if the trusteeship Agreement specifically authorises the Administering Authority toestablish common services or constitute a trust territory into an &quot; administrativeunion &quot; with adjacent colonies (as is the case with many of the trusteeship agreements, including that for Tanganyika), prior consultation with the Trustee-ship Council is unnecessary and would be administratively impracticable. TheUnited States and New Zealand took the line that, whilst there is no legal obliga-tion for the Administering Authority to consult the Trusteeship Council inadvance, in practice it is desirable that it should do so. The Council&apos;s conclusions and recommendations on the Tanganyika Report as a whole were either unreal,such as their conclusion (based upon a superficial debate) that the existing tribalstructure in Tanganyika is a hindrance to its political development, or platinum-tudinous, such as their recommendation that ways and means be found to makeincreased appropriations for education with no word on (nor indeed any interestin) the practical question of where the money might be found.14. The Annual Reports on Ruanda-Urundi and New Guinea were no moresympathetically treated. It was also noticeable, during the examination ofpetitions from Tanganyika, that some members of the Council were inclined to
attach more weight to the allegations of petitioners than to the statements andevidence submitted by the Administering Authorities.The Fourth Committee and the General Assembly15. The atmosphere in the Fourth Committee was distinctly more unfriendlywhen the Trusteeship Council&apos;s report was discussed. Again India stood out as a leader of non-administering members. For the most part the Slav blocremained isolated, although there were times when they and the other non-administering members made common cause, particularly on the question of administrative unions.16. As had been expected, the Fourth Comnimittee focussed its attentionmainly on administrative unions and educational advancement in trust territories.Eventually the Committee forwarded four resolutions to the General Assembly,but only two need be mentioned here.Resolution on Administrative Unions17. This resolution, which calls on the Trusteeship Council to investigate the question of administrative unions in all their aspects, originally containedseveral objectionable features, notably that of consultation with the trusteeship council prior to the establishment oi an administrative union, or any extensionof an existing union. The United States, whose attitude towards prior consulta-tion appeared to have been radically modified since the third session of the trusteeship Council (see paragraph 13 above) took the lead in opposing theseobjectionable paragraphs, and the combined efforts of the United States, theUnited Kingdom, France, Belgium and Australia succeeded in securing theirdeletion by the General Assembly. The final form of the Resolution is unexoep-tionable : all the Administering Authorities were able to vote for it and theResolution was adopted unanimously. This was a considerable victory for the administering Authorities, particularly for the United States and the United* Kingdom. The protagonists of the objectionable features were principally India,Iraq (though not the other Arab States), a number of Latin American countries,the Philippines and, of course, the Slav bloc.Resolution on Education in Trust Territories18. This resolution recommends inter alia that the Administering Authori-ties should intensify their efforts to increase educational facilities; and that the trusteeship Council should study the financial and technical implications of theestablishment and maintenance of a university for Trust Territories in Africaby 1952. The Administering Authorities pointed out the impracticability at thepresent time of realising some of the recommendations, but no heed was paidto them. In particular the existing facilities for higher education in our african territories were ignored.  The Resolution was eventually adopted by the Assembly.



</content>
</cab>
