<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/32/0 images: 518-629</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CONFIDENTIAL ^   ,CP. (49) 29 COPY NO.   W 5 -16TH FEBRUARY,  1949CABINETECONOMIC SURVEY FOR 1949Memorandum by the Chancellor of the- exchequer circulate herewith, for the consideration of mycolleagues, the first proofs of the Economic Survey for1949.      I propose that publication should take place on 15thMarch, so that, as last year, the Survey can be debated atthe same time as the Budget.The main text has been prepared in the light of dis-cussions of an earlier draft (P. C. (49) 8) at the production committee on 26th January (P. C. (1+9) 2nd Meeting), and at theOfficial Committee on dcononvc Development and the economic planning Board.The appendix on Investment Programmes in 1949 seeks to cover the same ground as was covered last year in aseparate White Paper (Cmd.  7268).It will be noticed that no figures for 1949 areyet shown in the tables relating to the national income.My colleagues may remember that in the last Economic Surveyv/e published figures different from those in the White paper on National Income and Expenditure and this caused some criticism, which I am anxious to avoid this year,     Calcula-tions for this year&apos;s White Paper are not yet complete, butI shall be able to describe their general tenor to theCabinet.The Survey will contain some illustrative charts,but these are not yet ready for circulation.This draft will be discussed by the official committee on Economic Development and the Economic PlanningBoard on 21st Februars&apos;-,  and by the Production Committee on22nd February.      I will circulate a note setting out theirrecommendat ions.R. S. C.easury Chambers, S. W. 1.16TH FEBRUARY,  1949.

CONFIDENTIAL-FIRST PROOFEconomic survey for 1949Presented by the Chancellor of the Exchequer to parliament by Command of His majesty march 1949Cmd.LONDON *HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICEnetCONTENTSPart I. Progress in 1948Part II. Prospects for 1949A. Introductory ...B. Production in 1949CoalElectricity  ...SteelOther Raw MaterialsTextilesAgriculture ...C. Investment in 1949D-The Balance of Payments in 1949E. Man-powerF. National Income and ExpenditurePart III.-The Tasks for 1949A. Targets for Production and Export;B. The Need for Greater ProductivityC-The Need for StabilityD. The Need for International Co-operationAppendix. The Capital Investment Programme inParagraphs  page 1-14.    15-11615-16. 17-41. 18-20. 21-26. 27-30. 31. 32-36. 37-41. 42-49. 50-87. 88-9495-116. 117-142. 118-119. 120-127. 128-136. 137-142

ECONOMIC SURVEY FOR 1949PART I. PROGRESS IN 19481. Introductory. The purpose of the opening Part of this economic survey, the third of the series to be published by the Government, is to summarise briefly the events of 1948 and to compare them with the record of the year of crisis, 1947. Detailed figures will be found in the statisticaltables in Part II and these will enable the reader also to make comparisons with the targets and forecasts contained in the Economic Survey for 1948.Here it is necessary only to draw attention in general terms to the salient features of the year.2. In 1946 the country was still in the process of rapid reconversionfrom war to peace. In 1947, though great advances were made, the fuelcrisis at the end of the winter and the balance of payments crisis in the summer showed forcibly how fundamentally precarious was the UnitedKingdom&apos;s economic situation in the post-war world, and when the yearended the chance of continued recovery was seen to be dependent uponforeign assistance.3. 1948 was a year of great and steady progress. We received generousand timely assistance from the United States, under the great european recovery Programme, our essential imports from dollar sources were assuredand we escaped the grave crisis which threatened not only ourselves but so many other of the countries of Western Europe. With this help, andas a result of the successful completion of the post-war reconversion ofindustry and of a steady, united national effort, there was a striking increaseof output in nearly every sector of industry. Though the industrial popu-lation only increased by 2 per cent., industrial production as a wholeincreased by 10 to 12 per cent, over the 1947 level. It is impossible totell how much of the improvement was due to gains in productivity following the building up of working stocks and the wearing off of the effects o the 1947 fuel crisis, and how much was the result of new. investment and improved techniques. but whatever its exact causes, this improvementwas the main reason for the increase in output, and higher output on productivity was the basic factor in all the progress made during 1948. ,Itpermitted exports to rise far faster than imports without total national resources being reduced, it allowed investment to increase and it allowed a small rise in consumption.4. Production. Output rose in all the critical sectors of home industry.There were substantial increases of production in coal and in textiles eventhough the target figures were not quite reached. The improvement inthe coal situation allowed a resumption of exports on a significant scale.Agricultural output was higher in every branch, and there was a con-siderable growth in the numbers of all kinds of livestock. The consumptionof electricity rose. and, though load shedding continued to be necessary,serious dislocation due to excessive peak loads was avoided. Most important of all, the great increase of steel output which exceeded even the raisedtarget, enabled production to expand in a wide variety of investment and export industries.5. Investment. An extensive review of investment plans for 1948 was published in December, 1947 (Cmd. 7268). The policies there set out were designed in the first place to reduce investment below the rate at whichit was running in the middle of 1947, and to an even greater extent below what would otherwise have been attempted. This was undertaken because it was then estimated that the continued need to expand exports and limitimports would reduce resources for investment in 1948 even below thelevel of 1947. In the event the receipt of E.R.P. aid and the increase in steel output made it possible for a less restrictive policy to be followed,and investment in 1948 proved to be substantially greater than in 1947.** The measurement of fixed investment involves the utmost statistical difficulties. Further .experience in this new field of Government statistics has made it possible to bring in categories of expenditure not covered by the original estimates published in the lastEconomic Survey. These revisions suggest that the original estimate for 1948 involved areduction (in the categories now covered) from about  1,800 million in 1947 to about  1,625million in 1948 (at 1947 prices). Instead investment in 1948 is now estimated to be about 1,925 million at these prices, or  2,050 million at 1948 prices. The figures for 1948 are setout in Table VIII below and brief summaries of progress in each sector during 1948 will befound in the Appendix on the 1949 investment programme. Despite an improvement in productivity increased expenditure on construction was accompanied by an expansion of thebuilding and civil engineering industry in place of the contraction allowed for in the lastSurvey.6. At the same time a second objective of the investment review hasbeen attained. The volume of work in progress on new buildings of all types was brought into a proper relation to the rate at which work couldbe completed. The number of houses under construction in England andWales was reduced to a level commensurate with the rate of which new houses could be finished. Considerable progress in this direction was also made in Scotland. A similar improvement in the rate of completion andequipping of factories in the Development Areas was particularly welcomeand during 1948 an additional 25,000 workers found jobs in newly completedfactories and extensions in these areas. A proper balance in all kinds ofbuilding work together with an easement in the supply of building materials

helped both to shorten the periods of construction and to raise productivity in the building industry generally. Thus, while the increase in fixed invest-ment achieved in 1948 contributed towards maintaining an inflationary pressure in the economy, it also meant a welcome improvement on therate of reconstruction that was earlier thought possible.7. The Balance of Payments. Nearly every aspect of the overseas tradeproblem changed for the better in 1948. The volume of imports roseby about 5 per cent, above 1947 to more than four-fifths of the level ofthe years immediately preceding the war. By comparison with 1947 therewere particularly large increases in* feeding-stuffs, wheat and flour, iron-ore and scrap, rubber, petroleum and machinery, but there were some reductions,notably in imports of meat, hides and leather. There was also a verystriking change in the sources of these imports; the proportion coming from the Western Hemisphere, nearly a half in 1947, was only a thirdin 1948. Our exceptional dependence on imports from the Americas dueto the effects of war on the output of many of our traditional supplierswhich so greatly contributed to the dollar deficit in 1947 was thus greatlydiminished, and a more normal pattern of trade began to show itself.8. While the volume of imports increased by about one-twentieth, exportsincreased by as much as a quarter over 1947 and were in volume thelargest since 1929. There were increases in every class of exports and to every type of market, and though all objectives were not reached (forexample, in textiles) performance in some cases, and especially in the metalgroup, outstripped all expectations. In contrast to imports, there was little change in the proportions of exports going to the different areas.9. The full gain to the balance of payments that might have been expected from the fact that exports expanded so much faster than imports, did notaccrue since, especially in the first part of the year, the terms of trade con-tinued to deteriorate. Nevertheless, in the latter half of the year exports and re-exports paid for over 90 per cent, of imports compared with a littleover two-thirds in 1947 and a little less in 1938.10. When account is taken also of an immense improvement in the balanceof invisible payments, the overseas deficit in 1948 is provisionally estimatedat only  145 million an improvement of nearly  500 million in the courseof a single year. The preliminary figures for the last half of the year evenshow that this country probably then had a small surplus on current account.11. This was a great step forward, but the overall figures conceal the continuing gravity of the Western Hemisphere deficit. Though this was practically halved in 1948, it was still nearly  350 million. The gold and dollar deficit which was (as shown in Table XVII) over  1,000 million in 1947,fell by no less than  600 million in 1948, the progress of the other countries of the sterling area greatly contributing towards this reduction. This deficit,which is now the worst danger spot in the economy, was met in the first halfof the year largely by drawings on the United States credit and later byreceipts of  170 million under. E.R.P. As a result of these transactions, therewas only a comparatively small fall in gold and dollar holdings during theyear.12. National Income and Expenditure. Between 1947 and 1948 there was probably an increase in the national income in money terms of the orderof 5 per cent. This was more than enough to counter-balance the reductionin the overseas deficit, so that, despite the success of the export drive, totalreal resources available for use at home were more in&quot; 1948 than in 1947.Personal consumption increased very little. Thus the expansion in total output combined with the measures, taken in concert by Government and people to make the best use of these resources, did much in 1948 to restoreour balance of payments, and to improve our capital equipment withoutsacrifice to the standard of living.13. All this was achieved without aggravating the inflationary problem.There was a continued pressure of demand for labour, but civilian employ -ment was rather more than expected, and unemployment remained at a low level. Wage rates continued to rise, but greater understanding of theneed for stability, moderated the increase. Retail and wholesale prices,which were rising fairly fast in the last half of 1947, have remained approxi-mately stable since the Spring of 1948. To this stability the co-operationof labour and industry made a great contribution. Much can also be fairlyascribed to the deliberate policy of disinflation followed by the Government.The large Budget surplus which was created offset the inflationaryeffects of the reduced overseas deficit, and of the increase in &quot;home investment,and enabled these changes to be made without the dislocation that mighthave been feared. It restrained consumption in the interests of reconstruc-tion and solvency, and enabled the nation to take a very large stop towardsthe goal of economic independence. An analysis of the experience of dis-inflation in 1948 is given in Part II.14. To sum up, 1948 was a year of substantial progress in nearly every part of the economic life of the United Kingdom. This progress, combined with assistance received from the United States averted the breakdown thatthreatened at the end of 1947. But great as it was, this economic advancepointed to no early and complete solution of the country&apos;s problems. Theposition is still dangerous in a number of critical sectors: above all, we were still, at the end of the year, far from paying from our current earnings for our dollar imports. We are still not paying our way. Sustained efforts to solve the hard core of our economic difficulties are still required. The main plans and forecasts are described in detail in Part II and summarised in simplegeneral terms in Part III.

PART II. PROSPECTS FOR 1949(a) Introductory15. It is impossible to count upon 1949 improving on 1948 to anything likethe extent that the results of 1948 improved on those of 1947. Plans for1949 will be misconceived and the problems facing the country misunder-stood if it is thought that output and exports can continue to expand as fast as in the last two years. Output during much of 1947 was disorganised anddelayed by the fuel crisis. 1948 was the first post-war year in which, the longand difficult process of reconversion from war having been completed (withall the reorganisation, rebuilding of working stocks and breaking down ofshortages of particular commodities that it involved), physical output began to match the productive capacity of the country. If the detailed figures lyingbehind the broad comparisons of the last two years given in Part I are ex-amined, it will in fact be seen that the rising curve of industrial productiontended after the autumn of 1947 to flatten out. The period of rapid ex-expansion in many parts of the economy is drawing to a close. The processof growth has changed. Future progress will result from new capital equip-ment, improved organisation, steadier and more productive work and not from an increased labour force and the gathering of the fruits of reconversionin earlier years.. This fundamental change in the forward prospect must beborne in mind in considering every part of the plans programmes and fore-casts for 1949.16. It is not yet possible to state all the programmes with precision. Thereis one uncertainty of exceptional importance. Decisions about assistance under-the European Recovery Programme are made by the United StatesCongress and the Economic Co-operation Administrator by reference to dieUnited States fiscal year which starts on 1st July. Decisions for the year1949-50 have not yet been made. The United Kingdom&apos;s Programme for thisyear, based upon a provisional assumption of assistance of $940 million, hasbeen submitted to the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation andto E.C.A. and figures from this programme have been used where necessaryin this Survey. But the aid the United Kingdom may receive is still unknownand many plans may yet need to be revised. A further caveat is necessary.Ail statements in this Survey about 1949 assume the continuance of present policies relating to defence as described in Cond ... If there- are any majorfresh developments many of these calculations will of necessity go awry.(b) Production in 194917. So long as the working population is fully employed, its size and theaverage amount each worker produces will determine total production. In1949 the civilian labour force will change very little: this is discussed belowin paragraphs .   The need for greater productivity is examined ingeneral terms in paragraphs . But beyond these broad factors, and moreimportant in the short period, are the problems of particular industries and particular supplies. The output of coal and of steel, the supplies of someraw materials, which are mainly imported, and the output of textiles and agriculture have a close and direct connection with investment, exports and consumption in 1949.18. Coal. The need for a further increase in coal output in 1949 is. urgentfor two reasons. First, provision must be made for some increase in home consumption, especially by the public utilities. Secondly, coal exports, par-ticularly to European countries, must be increased as part of the programmesubmitted to O.E.E.C.19. Measures necessary to secure an increase in production have been dis-cussed at a joint committee on production appointed by the National coal board and the National Union of Mineworkers. The keys to success are moreregular attendance, a greater output per man-shift and an increase in thenumber of face workers. During 1948 the number of face workers rose from291,000 to 296,000. Special efforts are being made to accelerate this increase by up-grading and other methods. It is hoped that by the end of 1949 thenumber will have increased to 310,000, so that the average over the year would be 303,000-3^ per cent, more than in 1948. This increase in thenumber of face workers will only be possible if replacements are found formany of the men up-graded and if there is a rapid development of additionalface room. It is difficult to be precise about the degree of success which willattend the efforts of the National Coal Board and the National Union of mineworkers to carry out the recommendations of the joint committee on production; but it is estimated that total output in 1949 should be between215 and 220 million tons, of which about 13 million tons will be opencastcoal. This represents an increase of from 7 to 12 million tons above the 1948output. The higher of these two figures will be a task difficult of achievement,in fact a greater improvement from one year to the next than has yet beenmade.

		1947	1948		1949	1946					Actual	Actual	Economic Survey for 1948	Actual (52 weeks)	EstimatedProduction:					202-207Deep mined   .........	181-2	187-2	200 0	196-7	Opencast	8-8	10-2	110	11-7	13Total     ...      ......	190-0	197-4	211-0	208-4	215-220Imports.........		0-7	  &apos;.	01	 Total Supply    ......	1900	198-1	2110	208-5	215-220Home Consumption:				24-5	Gas    .........	22-7	* 22-7			Electricity     .........	26-2	27-1		28-7	Railways      .........	15-1	14-6		14-5	Coke Ovens   .........	20-1	19-8	a *	22-2	Irons and Steel       ......	9-6	8-7		8-6	Other Industry        ......	32-7	31 0	&apos;.&apos;	33-6	Domestic and Miscellaneous...	52-6	61 0		60-6	Total     .........	1860	184-9	195-0	192-7	198-200Exports and Foreign Bunkers ...	9-2	5-5	160	16-3	Change in total stocks......	-5-2	47-7		-0-5	* *Stocks at end of year:					Distributed	8-3	16-3	&apos; &apos;&apos;.v.&apos; v-a	14-4	Undistributed.........	1-7	1-4		2-6	20. Home consumption needs vary considerably with the temperature andthe difference between coal consumption in a warm year and a cold year isseveral million tons. But it is clear that, in any case, more coal will berequired in 1949 than in 1948 to provide the coke needed by the iron and steelindustry, to meet the needs of engineering and other industry and to satisfy the rising trend of gas and electricity consumption. Taking all these factorsinto&apos; account, it is estimated that, given average weather, home consumption in 1949 will be between 198 and 200 million tons. Based on the figures ofproduction and home consumption given above, it is estimated that there willbe available for export and bunkers in 1949 between 18 and 20 million tons.21. Electricity. The problem in electricity remains the gap between peakdemand and available generating capacity. This has arisen because of the enormous growth in demand during and since the war, which could not be matched by the construction of sufficient new power stations. Thus, peakdemand in the winter of 1948-49 was 4,000 megawatts, or 50 per cent, above that in the winter of 1938-39, while the available generating capacity had increased in those ten years by less than 1,000 megawatts, or only 18 per cent.Moreover, the strain on the power stations today is greater not only becauseof the growth in peak demand, but because total consumption has increasedeven more rapidly, having in fact doubled since 1938, as the chart onpage shows. The plant must therefore be kept more constantly in use and, of course, its age is all the time increasing.22. Although the amount of new plant commissioned in 1948 was dis-appointing 566 MW. compared with the forecast of 1,100 MW. therewas one outstanding achievement. The British Electricity Authoritysucceeded in reducing the amount of plant out of service for repair andother reasons from 15 per cent, in the winter of 1947-48 to 11 per cent, this winter the lowest figure since 1939-40 and this contributed about 400 MW.to the available generating capacity, largely making up for the shortfall in new generating capacity.23. The growth in demand last year was also rather less than expected,being only about 500 MW. It is impossible to be precise about the reasonsfor this. No doubt the mild weather helped, but a considerable contributionalso came from the load spreading schemes operated by industrial and commercial consumers, while domestic consumers have been made moreconscious of the need to keep down peak demand by the introduction of a differential tariff. Whatever the reasons, load shedding in November,December, and January of 1948-49 occurred on 26 days compared with29 days the previous winter, while the. average of the maximum load shedwas only about 181 MW. compared with 272 MW. a year earlier.Table Coal Output, Consumption and Exports(Million tons) - -

24. The position next winter will probably be very similar to this winter.A realistic estimate of the amount of new plant likely to be commissionedin 1949 is about 1,000 MW. (and this will only be achieved by a sustainedeffort on the part of everyone in the industry, on the manufacturing, civil engineering and generating side alike), but when allowance is made for theproportion of this which, through various teething troubles, will not be in service, and for the amount of old plant that will have to be scrapped, thenet increase in available capacity is unlikely to be very much in excess ofthe growth in demand. It seems certain, therefore, that load spreading by industry and commerce will be necessary next winter. The extent to whichlpad shedding can be avoided will depend on the effectiveness of the loadspreading schemes, the severity of the weather and the success of the british electricity Authority&apos;s efforts to keep down the amount of plant out ofservice for repairs, etc.25. Detailed figures for the winter of 1949-50 and subsequent years aregiven in the Appendix. The factors affecting both demand and capacityare, however, so uncertain that these figures must be regarded as extremelytentative. The figures of demand assume no load spreading and severe winterweather; as for capacity, it is too early yet to be certain that the british electricity Authority will be able to keep the amount of plant out of servicenext year to this winter&apos;s level, in view of the increase in the amount ofover age plant, and an upper and lower limit for plant out of service has there fore been given.26. Thus while we should, during 1949, prevent any further increase in the gap, it is doubtful whether we shall be able to reduce it much, if at all. Thiswill not be possible, so long as demand continues to increase so rapidly, untilthe B.E.A. can put into commission well over 1,000 MW. of new plant eachyear. The situation therefore still calls for the greatest endeavour from allengaged in the electricity industry to increase capacity and from all con-sumers, industrial, commercial, and domestic, to reduce electricity consumption at times of peak demand.27; Steel. Despite the remarkable progress made in increasing steelsupplies-reflected in an increase in home output of from 12.7 million ingottons of steel in 1946 to the record of 14.9 million ingot tons in 1948 continued expansion of output during the next three or four years is essentialto the success of our economic and industrial policy. Long-term plans forthe steel industry aim at an output of about 17* million ingot tons in 1953-54which, with imports, would, it is hoped, yield a total supply of at least18 million ingot tons. Further progress towards this objective must be looked for in 1949. In the shorter term, the indications are that the demand for steel both for export and for home investment will remain intense in 1949and that the pressures of demand in relation to supply will continue to imposelimitations on various parts of our industrial effort. The largest possiblehome output and the greatest practicable imports will therefore again be needed in 1949.28. Because of the new blast and steel furnaces that will be coming intooperation this year, it might be thought that a further large increase in steeloutput in 1949 presents little difficulty. This, however, is not the case. other factors may limit output, the main ones being raw materials, hard coke ofadequately high quality, rich imported iron ore and scrap. Steps havealready been taken and will, it is hoped, secure adequate supplies of cokebut the margin is narrow. Expansion of supplies of hard coke remain amost important task. Imported ore supplies are not yet fully assured and only a part of a deficiency can be made good by the greater use of the lowerquality home ore. As to scrap, much of the increase in steel output in 1948was due to the additional scrap obtained from the special industrial scrapdrive in this country, from larger releases of Government surplus stores andfrom heavy deliveries from overseas. We must be prepared for some falling off in the first two sources in 1949. Our dependence on German scrap is tothat extent increased. Every effort will continue to be made to securemaximum imports from Germany, but it must be remembered that we are by no means the only purchasers in that market. It is true that there shouldbe increasing quantities of process scrap available from the steel using industries and from &quot; circulating &quot; scrap within the steel industry itself, but such increases can only be regarded as marginal.29. With all these considerations to be taken into account, it is possibleto arrive at a variety of views on the probable steel output from the possibility-mistic which would assess the figure at less than the 1948 output to the highly optimistic based on the full capacity of the furnaces. The objective is the maximum output the industry can achieve with the materials it can obtain. In the most favourable circumstances this should be between 15  and15* million tons of ingot steel. It must, however, be recognised that whatever may be the total output, there will not be a corresponding improvement in supplies of some products, especially sheet, strip, tinplate and wire rod, outputof which will continue to be limited by finishing capacity.

30. It is hoped that imports of steel in 1949 will be substantially larger than in 1948, rising from a total of 400,000 tons to about 1,000,000 tons(including semis and finished). On this basis the total supply of finished steel from all sources should in favourable circumstances be 12-12J million tons as compared with 11.2 million tons in 1948. Exports, substantialy all of finished steel, are likely to rise a little from 1.5 to 1.6 million tons, so thatthe aggregate supply to home consumers including manufacture for exportsshould be between 10.5 and 10.7 million tons compared with 9 7 million tons in 1948.  The principal figures are set out in Table II.Table IISteel Output and Materials Consumed(Thousand tons)	1946	1947	1948					Economic Survey	Actual	1949 ForecastPig-iron Production-Total   ............ For steel making     ......		7,784 5,819	9,200 7,000	9,276 7,034	Scrap for steel making  Home-bought......... Imported      .........		3,505 449	3,700 850	4,300 1,050	1 ;; *Steel ingots and castings pro-duction        .........		12,724	14,000(*)	14,877	15,250-15,500 &apos;Steel imports (crude semi&apos;s and finished)       ......		410	700	620	Total supply of finished steel ...		10,328	10,800	11,200	12,000-12,250Exports of steel ...      ......		1,278		1,500	1,600Supply of finished steel to home market.........     ...		q nsn 1 &quot;&quot;&quot;		9,700	10,500-10,700 ]i(*) Target subsequently raised to 14,500.31. Other Raw Materials. Table III summarises present estimates ofthe probable consumption of other important raw materials in 1949. these estimates for 1949 are very provisional. They are based partly on the import programme for 1949-50 which is, as already said, founded upon an assump-tion about E.R.P. assistance in that year. A different allocation of aid,changes in prices or in overseas supplies, greater or less progress with ex-ports, may all involve alterations in this programme. Moreover, changesin plans regarding stocks, for whatever reason they may become desirable,would also affect consumption. It is very difficult as a result to give anygeneral answer to the question whether the supply of raw materials is likelyto be a limiting factor in 1949. All the non-ferrous metals are scarce in varying degree. It is not likely that supplies will increase substantially in1949 with the possible exception of aluminium which is being increasinglysubstituted for other metals, but even in this case any additional suppliesdepend upon our dollar resources as well as upon world supplies.Table IIIConsumption of Selected Raw Materials(Thousand tons)	1947	1948	1949	Actual	Actual	EstimatedAluminium ...     ...............	156	175	209Copper      ..................	350	360	375Tin.........    ..........	27	27	28Lead............      ......	174	180	194Zinc.............   .........	222	223	240Sawn Softwood (Thousand cubic metres)	4,710	4,670	4,760Hardwood (Thousand cubic metres) (&apos;) ...	1,608	1,700	1,870Paper and Paper Board   ............	2,115	2,230	2,585Cotton       ..................	365	433	472Wool.....................	188	220	226Leather      ..................	120	121	120Sulphuric Acid      ...............	1,357	1,563	1,622(&apos;) General purpose hardwoods only excluding certain specialities.

Increases in timber and paper consumption are limited by currency eon-siderations and the general world shortage. The shortage of softwood inparticular is very persistent: consumption has increased since 1946 less than for any other important raw material and. there is no prospect of improve-ment in 1949 or indeed in 1950. In the cotton and wool industries laboursupplies and, in some lines, demand for the finished product rather than rawmaterials probably limit output. The chemical industry made good progressin 1948 and production in each of the main divisions is expected to continueto increase through 1949, although it will be some considerable time beforefull benefit is obtained from the many expansion and development schemes in hand, e.g. for alkalis, dyestuffs and chemicals from oil-cracking. Depen-dence upon imports for certain types of plastic materials is being steadilyreduced by the measures taken to increase or initiate output in the UnitedKingdom. Increases in the labour forces of 23,000 cotton, 9,000 in wool and,000 in other textiles made an important contribution to the growth of out-put during 1948. While further increases are still necessary in 1949 in thenumbers employed, greater emphasis is now laid upon the part which increasing productivity can play. In general the relation between raw material consump-tion and output is not exact or fixed since changes in design and the use of substitutes are taking place continually under the stimulus of price move-ments and normal industrial developments. Nevertheless these estimates asthey stand throw some light upon the likely trend of production.32. Textiles. Large increases in textile output were needed in 1948 ifthe targets set were to be reached, and the increases that took place werein fact very substantial. Further expansion is needed in 1949 if the export programme is to be achieved and home supplies increased. Table IVsummarises the principal output and export figures.Table IVTextile Output, Exports and Targets	j. yiu		1948		10/l nj		I9t7	Economic Survey for 1948	Actual	Targets1,358	741	740 48	900	890 60	11,04033 19	71 40	119 84	150 105	148 86	/ 3003,640	1,626	1,620	&amp; . .-   :	1,900	2,050484	348	390	., Ill &apos; i	500	570224	146	154	190	182	194317	223	232	290	267	2811,448(2)	529	541		766	1,000(3)64(2)	52	54		76	87(3)					Cotton and Rayon Output:Cotton yarns (includingcotton waste yarn) (mn.lbs.)  .......:.Spun rayon and mixtureyarns (including waste)(mn. lbs.)     ......Rayon (mn. lbs.):Continuous FilamentStaple Fibre ...Cotton cloth (mn. linearyds.)......Rayon cloth and mixtures(mn. linear yds.)Wool Output:Worsted yarn (mn. lbs.moist content)Woven wool cloth (mn.linear yds. excludingblankets)      ......Exports:Woven cotton piece goods(mn. linear yds.)Woven wool piece goods,excluding blankets andcarpets (mn. linearyds.)(*)        ......(&apos;) Not in all respects comparable with post-war figures.(2) 1938.(3) Forecasts.(4) Exports are shown in the Trade and Navigation Accounts in terms of square yards. Theyare here converted to linear yards using the approximate conversion factor of 3 squarefor 2 linear yards.The production targets for 1949 shown in it are high. Nevertheless theydo not represent the full increase that is desirable.

33. The 1948 export targets for cotton were attained but the lesser increasein output implied that the home market had to be correspondingly deprived of supplies. This has caused a relative shortage of cotton garments and household textiles which will inevitably continue for some time. Its effectsare most noticeable on shirts, linings, -overalls and sheets, though as muchcotton cloth as possible is being put into the production of these articlesas there are no suitable alternative materials. Cotton export targets havebeen raised for 1949. In the wool textile industry also a further rise in out-put is needed. Exports in 1948 fell far short of target and the 1949 targethas been lowered, though to a figure still above current exports. There is,in particular, still an unsatisfied demand in hard currency markets for the better quality worsteds. In the home market in 1948 there were few shortages of wool cloth, except worsted and gaberdine cloths. How long these short-ages will persist depends on the one hand, upon this industry&apos;s success withexports and, on the other, on the. increase in production. Output of spunrayon yarn and continuous filament yarns should continue to expand, largelyas the result of new capacity, and this will include an increase in industrialyarn supplies, especially tyre yarns. In the woollen and worsted industry themost urgent task is to increase the output of the sections producing the hard currency exports.34. A major limitation upon increasing output in 1949 will be, as in 1948,the supply of labour. Productivity rose during 1948 and, with improvementsthat are believed to be well within the limits of practicable technical pro-gress, the output targets for 1949 should be possible of achievement.35. Though these targets can be reached, it will be no easy task. no improvement in the supply of cotton cloth for the home market can beexpected, since, in addition to the requirement for exports (which can andmust be increased above 1948 levels) there is a considerable demand forcotton cloth for industrial purposes and this must be met in preference toneeds of the ordinary consumer. Exports of wool manufactures were already in the third quarter of 1948 one-third more in volume than 1938, and it isdoubtful whether (except for some of the finer products) they can increasemuch further because of market saturation and import restrictions. If so,increased output will be available mainly to the home market.36. The level of home demand in 1948 was still limited by rationing. Therewas, however, a bonus issue of coupons and a good deal of downpointing,and footwear was taken off the ration. On the other hand prices have movedupwards as a result of the removal of subsidies, the trend of raw material prices and increased purchase fax on non-utility garments. In the result,-consumer expenditure rose sharply. During the first three quarters of 1948expenditure on men&apos;s and boys&apos; wear was about 45 per cent, above the corre-sponding figure for 1947, and on women&apos;s, girls&apos; and infants&apos; wear 20 per cent,above, possibly corresponding to changes in the volume of cloths sold inthe two classes of 20 to 25 per cent, and 10 to 15 per cent. Comparisonsof the third quarters of the two years taken separately show, even greaterincreases. With the further relaxation in the rationing system made at theend of January, 1949, consumer demand is not limited by rationing overabout half the field formerly covered and the issue of new coupons hasbeen on a more generous scale. The level of demand in 1949 is difficultto forecast but the greater opportunity for consumers&apos; preference to expressitself freely may lead to some further increase in expenditure beyond the1948 level.37. Agriculture. The second year of the Agricultural Expansion Pro-gramme provides for further increases both in total acreage under crops andin the output of livestock products. Home-produced wheat direcfly savesdollar expenditure and it is therefore important that the maximum acreageshould be sown to bread grains. Last year&apos;s wheat target was not attainedand although the weather in the autumn of 1948 was rather more favourable,the exceptionally heavy potato and beet crops, and the late corn harvest,made it impossible for many farmers to carry out their programme of autumnwheat sowing. Consequently the prospect of achieving an increase of 250,000acres has diminished. Coarse grains can be grown successfully in parts ofthe country where wheat-growing is very much of a gamble, and the pro-gramme should be realised. The target acreage for linseed, while morethan double the acreage harvested in 1948, is still only half the ultimate

target. Linseed is an unfamiliar and in some ways Unattractive crop; con-ditions in 1948 were not favourable, and a quicker expansion of the acreageis not likely to be possible. Table V gives details of the targets for the maincrops and estimates of output of livestock products.Table VAgricultural Production in the United Kingdom (*)	Average 1936-37-38-39	1947-48	1948 Economic Survey 1948	-49 Preliminary Estimate	1949-50 Programme		(a) Acrea	3E		(Thousands)Bread Grains Other Grains Potatoes    ...... Sugar Beet ... Linseed     ......	1,872 3,429 723 335 2	2,199 5,866 1,330 395 38	2,595 6,050 1,423 400 150	2,340 6,016 1,548 413 86	2,600 6,200 1,400 400 200(b) Production                       (Thousand tons)					Bread Grains Other Grains Potatoes    ...... Sugar Beet ... Linseed     ......	1,661 2,781 4.873 2,741 1	1,689 4,513 7,760 2,959 15	2,484 5,190 9,961 3,600	2,324 5,463 12,278 4,234 42	2,500 5,330 9,800 3,600 100(c) Livestock Productionpercentage of pre-war production)Milk         ...     ...	100	109		119	121Eggs...      ......	100	83		98	108Beef and Veal	100	83		83	92Mutton and Lamb...	100	55		70	72Pig Meat   ...	100	. 29		43	50(&apos;) The agricultural crop year runs from June to May. Acreages represent areas under crop. at the annual census on 4th June. Crop production represents the yield of these areasduring the following months. The acreages for 1949-50 are targets. The correspondingproduction figures assume normal yields from the acreages sown. The figures for livestock products are the best forecasts which can be made at present. They make no allowance for any improvement in ration scales of dairy cows, pigs and poultry.38. The further progress of the livestock expansion programme depends onadequate supplies of feeding-stuffs. There have been no increases in ration scales since September, 1947, but rations have been provided for new entrantsinto pig and poultry keeping, and from January, 1949, bonus issues have beenmade against deliveries of pigmeat and eggs. Farmers have also been allowedto keep 20 per cent, of their wheat and barley crops in 1948 for feeding then-own stock. Since further supplies of imported feeding-stuffs depend on bothsupply and currency considerations and cannot be predicted with certainty, itis more than ever necessary to increase production of home-grown feeding-stuffs. The progress of the grassland improvement campaign should afford sub-stantial further help in this direction in 1949-50. When the agricultural expan-sion programme was first announced it was estimated that the grasslandimprovement campaign would contribute the equivalent of 1.3 million tonsof coarse grains annually by 1951-52. Later study shows that, given sufficientfertilisers, this figure can be surpassed. After many years of research into thetechnical problems of improved grassland, management it is believed that theknowledge now acquired will enable us to make a great additional contri-bution to the net agricultural output of the country since grass representsapproximately 57 per cent, of the total cultivated area in the TJ.K. A nation-wide campaign to this end has been undertaken. The campaign has had good results in 1948, and it is hoped that by 1952 it will result in a saving equivalentto a very substantial quantity of imported coarse grains and other feeding-stuffs.

target. Linseed is an unfamiliar and in some ways Unattractive crop ; con-ditions in 1948 were not favourable, and a quicker expansion of the acreageis not likely to be possible. Table V gives details of the targets for the maincrops and estimates of output of livestock products.Table VAgricultural Production in the United Kingdom C1)	Average		1948-49							1949-50 Programme	1936-37-38-39	1947-48	Economic Survey 1948	Preliminuy Estimate			(a) ACREAl	3e		(Thousands)Bread Grains Other Grains Potatoes Sugar Beet...... Linseed     ......	1,872 3,429 723 335 2	2,199 5,866 1,330 395 38	2,595 6,050 1,423 400 150	2,340 6,016 1,548 413 86	2,600 6,200 1,400 400 200		(6) Production		(Thousand tons)	Bread Grains      ____ Other Grains Potatoes    ...... Sugar Beet ... Linseed	1,661 2,781 4.873 2,741 1	1,689 4,513 7,760 2,959 15	2,484 5,190 9,961 3,600	2,324 5,463 12,278 4,234 42	2,500 5,330 9,800 3,600 100(c) Livestock Production percentage of pre-war production)					Milk Eggs...     ...... Beef and Veal Mutton and Lamb... Pig Meat   ...	100 100 100 100 100	109 83 S3 55 . 29		119 98 83 70 43	121 108 92 72 50(&apos;) The agricultural crop year runs from June to May. Acreages represent areas under crop. at the annual census on 4th June. Crop production represents the yield of these areasduring the following months. The acreages for 1949-50 are targets. The correspondingproduction figures assume normal yields from the acreages sown. The figures for livestock products are the best forecasts which can be made at present. They make no allowance for any improvement in ration scales of dairy cows, pigs and poultry.38. The further progress of the livestock expansion programme depends onadequate supplies of feeding-stuffs. There have been no increases in ration scales since September, 1947, but rations have been provided for new entrantsinto pig and poultry keeping, and from January, 1949, bonus issues have beenmade against deliveries of pigmeat and eggs. Farmers have also been allowedto keep 20 per cent, of their wheat and barley crops in 1948 for feeding theirown stock. Since further supplies of imported feeding-stuffs depend on bothsupply and currency considerations and cannot be predicted with certainty, itis more than ever necessary to increase production of home-grown feeding-stuffs. The progress of the grassland improvement campaign should afford sub-stantial further help in this direction in 1949-50. When the agricultural expan-sion programme was first announced it was estimated that the grasslandimprovement campaign would contribute the equivalent of 1.3 million tonsof coarse grains annually by 1951-52. Later study shows that, given sufficientfertilisers, this figure can be surpassed. After many years of research into thetechnical problems of improved grassland, management it is believed that theknowledge now acquired will enable us to make a great additional contri-bution to the net agricultural output of the country since grass representsapproximately 57 per cent, of the total cultivated area in the LJ.K. A nation-wide campaign to this end has been undertaken. The campaign has had good results in 1948, and it is hoped that by 1952 it will result in a saving equivalentto a very substantial quantity of imported coarse grains and other feeding-stuffs.

39. Fertiliser consumption is now twice to three times pre-war. further increases are necessary, particularly for grassland. Shortage of fertilisersshould not seriously hamper the programme in 1949-50, but an expansion ofthe fertiliser industry is likely to be needed to meet requirements, particu-larly of nitrogenous fertilisers, in the later years of the expansion programme.Figures for supplies of feeding-stuffs and fertilisers are shown in Table VI.Table VISupplies of Feeding-stuffs and Fertilisers(Thousand tons)	1947-48	.    1948-49 Forecast	1949-50 programme a. Feeding-stuffs^)  Coupon Issues(2) 					3,315	Cereal     .........	2,711		3,750Protein    ..........	-    653	765	800Farm Retentions 		wl	Cereal     ...     ......	2,905	3,800	3,8503. Fertilisers 			Nitrogen (as N)       ......	186	190	233Phosphates (as P2O5)......	390	420	452Potash (as K2Q)      ......	180	190	195(&apos;) The &quot; feeding-stuff year &quot; runs from May to April.(2) No allowance has been made in these estimates for any improvement in ration scaleswhich might result from an improvement in feedingstuffs supplies.As regards machinery, it is hoped that the full current demand can be met,except possibly for some types of specialised machinery such as crawlertractors and combine harvesters. The number of workers in agriculturerose by nearly 50,000 in the first half of 1948, and was within 1 per cent,of the forecast of the industry&apos;s needs given in the Economic Survey for1948. Some increase may be expected, and will be needed, in 1949. Themost acute need, as in 1948, will be for temporary assistance at harvest timeespecially for the lifting of potatoes and sugar-beet in the autumn,40. In the fishing industries, the demand for white fish still exceeds supply,and efforts to increase home production will continue. The construction ofnew vessels has not yet made good war-time losses, but British landings nowexceed pre-war figures and imports are very much higher. Total supplies in 1949 are expected to reach over 1 million tons as compared with 950,000in 1948. Supplies of herrings have kept pace with increased demand andare expected to do so in future. In both sections of the industry quickfreezing is being developed in order to space the distribution of glut landings.41. Table VII attempts to show the extent to which the increasing outputof home agriculture is enabling a larger proportion of home food consump-tion to be met from home output, In considering the figures given it mustbe remembered that a good deal of home output is dependent upon imported feeding-stuffs and fertilisers. No attempt has been made to allow for this factor. Nevertheless these figures bring out clearly the notable contributionagricultural expansion is making to bur food supplies and to righting thebalance of payments.Tablf VIIContribution of Home Production to Food Supplies(Nutrient equivalent of food consumption per head per day)	Pre-war		1947-48		1948-49		Home Pro-duction	Per cent, of Total Con-sumption	Home Pro-duction	Per cent, of Total Con-sumption	Home Pro-duction	Per cent, of Total Con-sumptionCalories    ......	916	31	985	35	1,091	37Animal protein (gm)	26-7	63	260	63	26-7	66Vegetable    protein						(gm)     ......	9-3	25	13-6	32	16-6	38Total protein (gm)...	36 0	45	39-6	48	43-3	52

. (c) Investment in 194942. A review of the claims upon investment in 1949 similar to, but more complete than, that made for 1948 has been made in recent months. Theproposals for particular programmes in 1949 are set out in detail inAppendix I.f Here the general scale of the investment effort proposed, andthe principles underlying its distribution are set out.43. The size of the total investment programme depends on the ability ofthe nation to match its investment needs in money and physical resourceswith its monetary savings and the supplies of material and labour. It isthe Governments intention to maintain a large investment programme. Thispolicy depends for its success upon the continued self-restraint of the com-munity as a whole in limiting present consumption in order to release theresources necessary to carry out such an investment programme, which isrequired to ensure the nation&apos;s future well-being, stability and independence.44. The problem of financing investment is discussed later in this Survey.The physical limitations on investment are imposed by the labour and materials which can be devoted to this purpose. It is wasteful to put inhand more work, however urgent or important it may be, than can be com-pleted in a reasonable time with the available resources. Of materials, timber .and steel are likely to prove the most critical in 1949 as in 1948. While an increasing proportion of our timber supplies are coming from Europeansources, we shall continue to be dependent for a substantial portion of our imports of softwood on North American sources. The scale of these importsdepends on our ability to pay for them by our export earnings and by theE.R.P. Aid which we are granted. As shown in Table III only a small increase in timber consumption is expected in 1949. The supply of steelfor investment is fixed by the level of total supplies and by the proportionof these supplies needed for export either as steel or as manufactured goods.Provision has of course also to be made for consumption goods for the home market and for defence. After weighing these claims, the diversion of totalsteel supplies in 1949 is planned to be about 60 per cent, for home investment,30 per cent, for exports and the remainder for defence and consumer needs.45. It is still necessary to increase our earnings from engineering exports,for which there is a strong and continuing demand in nearly all overseas markets. Moreover, part of these exports is for investment overseas to in-crease supplies of materials and foodstuffs for which we are at presentdependent on dollar sources. Nevertheless, home investment should receivein 1949 twice as much steel as overseas markets, and, what is perhaps as important, it is in many fields enjoying preference in the matter, of deliveries of plant and machinery second only to exports to hard currency markets.There is no simple and final answer to the problem of the right balance between the claims of home investment and those of exports. The position has to be kept under review product by product. The division now planned for 1949 is. believed to be such as to allow all the most essential and urgenthome investment to proceed, having regard to the Size of the total investment which we can afford;46. This does not mean that a start can be made in 1949 on all the projects for new investment that we would wish in other circumstances tohave a place in the investment programme. A large part of gross invest-ment must go to maintenance and replacement, particularly at present when there are war-time arrears to make up which can no longer be deferred. Thetotal stock of fixed capital, whether in the form of buildings or plaut, is so large in any highly developed community like ours that total expenditureon maintenance is inevitably very large. . Consequently, the resources whichcan be devoted to new investment are strictly limited and it is within thesenarrow limits that the apportionment has to be made among the urgentclaims of transport, of fuel and power, of housing, education and the other social services, and of agriculture and industry. In accordance with the objectives set out in the Long Term Programme (Cmd. 7572) it is the Govern-menfs intention, while maintaining at the 1948 level investment in the social services, to increase to the maximum extent that resources permit the levelof investment in those industries and basic services where increased output will, directly or indirectly, assist substantially towards the balance of pay-ments, and more particularly serve to increase dollar earnings or reduce dollarexpenditures.47. At.the same time the Government will continue its policy of steeringwherever possible new industrial expansions to areas of unemployment ratherthan to those where congestion of industry and public services is alreadycausing economic waste and labour shortage. This is desirable both to achieve the maximum use of our labour resources and to prevent the &apos;economic losses due to congestion in such areas as London. It is hoped thatthe improved rate of completion of factories in the Development Areas willin 1949 ensure that an even greater number of men and women now unem-ployed will find useful jobs in this way than in 1948.

48. Table Vffl sets out estimates for the principal sectors of gross fixed investment in 1947 and 1948, and the distribution in 1949 which is expectedon the basis of recent trends, decisions already taken regarding the con-trolled sectors and probable supplies of investment materials. The sum ofthese estimates suggests an increase of some  100 million in 1949, but past experience has shown that however carefully the estimates for work to beundertaken may be drawn up, the investment actually achieved will, insome cases, be less than the programme as a result of unforeseen difficulties,and delays. But it is impossible to say in advance which programmes willbe affected, and therefore the full figures are set out in the table. Over and above those items for which it is possible to make fairly detailed estimates,there is a volume of miscellaneous investment estimated in 1948 to amountto about  400 million. Of this rather less than half consisted of machinery and equipment and the remainder of constructional work. Included in this-category are such items as the building, repair and maintenance of churches,,offices, shops and other commercial premises, office machinery- and equip-ment and passenger cars for business use.As these totals are not expected to change much in 1949, the total.of gross fixed investment is unlikely to rise much above the level of 1948.Table VIIIEstimated Gross Fixed Investment in the United Kingdom,1947-1949(Principal Sectors)(  million) (&quot;)	1947			1948			1949			Con-structure-tion	Plant	Total	Con-structure-tion	Plant	Total	Con-structure-tion	Plant	TotalFuel and Power ...	35	90	125	60	105	165	80	135	215.Transport and Communi-									cations ...	125	155	280	125	170	295	140	150	290&apos;Shipping......	v- )	70	70	-	75	75	-	60	60Agriculture, Forestry and									Fisheries	25	45	70	30	60	90	35	60	95Other Industries......	95	280	375	110	310	420	135	340	475Housing (including repairs									and maintenance)	455	 	455	480	 	480	435	 	435Other Social Services . ...	45	-	45	65	-	65	105	5	110Defence and Government	40	10	50	50	10	60	60	10	70Total (&apos;)......	820	650	1,470	920	730	1,650	990	760	1,750(&apos;) At current prices in 1947 and 1948, and&apos;for 1949 at 1948 prices.49. A comparison of the changes between 1948 and 1949 in the estimates for the main groups shown in Table VIII brings out the effects of thegeneral investment policy described above. Expenditure on housing andother social services shows a slight decline. The fall in housing is princi-pally due to the virtual completion in 1948 of the temporary house pro-gramme, the cost of which is included in the figures for construction, andalso to some extent to a reduction in expenditure on conversions and the rebuilding of houses destroyed in the war. Education accounts for most ofthe large rise in other social services. The decline in investment in trans-port and communications is mainly due to the somewhat delayed carryingout of the &quot; make do and mend &quot; policy on the railways and in road passenger and goods transport, described in Cmd. 7268. Over 60 per cent, of theincrease in investment in the Fuel and Power group is accounted for byelectricity and by developments in the petroleum industry in this country..A small increase is expected in &quot; other industries &quot; which broadly speakingcovers manufacturing industry.

(d) The Balance of Payments50. For the second half of 1948 the United Kingdom^ overseas accountshows a small surplus, i.e., an approximate balance between total payments and total receipts on current account. This development was contrary to-expectation, and it is still too early to be certain that it has come to stay.In this particular period, there were certain special factors such as non-recurring receipts under various governmental settlements, particularly thatwith India. More important was the fact that expenditure on importsremained virtually unchanged compared with the first half of the year, whilereceipts from exports rose by about  100 million. As a result, it isprovisionally estimated that there was a surplus of  5 million in the second half year, whereas in the first half of the year there was, according to the revised estimate, a deficit of  150 million.51. It is not expected that the first half of 1949 will show any very matenal-change from the second half of 1948. The import programme is substantially higher than the rate of actual imports in 1948. This assumes that the difficultieswhich were encountered towards the end of 1948 in procuring supplies willbe overcome. Various elements in the invisible account, such as shippingincome and net receipts from travel, will probably continue to improve.Receipts from exports should rise still further though at a slower rate thanin 1948.The broad prospect, therefore, is that Our total overseas account in thisJhalf year will again be roughly in balance increasing expenditure,particularly on imports, being met by an approximately equal rise in our overseas income though on the whole a small deficit is more probable thana surplus. The prospects for the balance of payments in the latter half ofthe year are particularly uncertain because, as explained below, the amountof E.R.P. assistance we may receive is still unsettled. For this reason noestimates for the last six months of 1949 are shown in Tables XI to XIX.52. The virtual disappearance of our overall balance of payments deficit in recent months is a most notable achievement. When it is recalled&apos;that in 1947 we were in deficit with the outside world to the extent of 630 million its magnitude becomes evident. It means that we are now ineffect consuming no more goods and services from overseas than we ourselvesare sending in return. But great though the achievement is, it represents only.a stage in the progress towards our final goal of full economic independence.With the Western Hemisphere, particularly the dollar area, we are, and arelikely to remain, substantially in deficit, even though this deficit is steadilydiminishing. For the present, E.R.P. aid enables us to meet this deficit andto cover the other calls on our gold and dollar holdings, such as the require-ments of countries in the rest of the sterling area and the payments which wehave to make to certain countries in Europe and elsewhere.53. The dollar deficit remains the crucial problem. It is a many-sidedproblem that needs to be attacked from a number of angles. Some of themain issues involved and the obstacles which remain to be overcome beforedecisive progress can be made are discussed later in this section. the paragraphs that follow immediately are devoted to an examination of themain elements in the balance of payments and the detailed evidence on whichIhe forecasts for 1949 are based.

54. Exports. The provisional export targets for end-1949, already announced, are summarised in Table IX below and compared with those for end-1948. Details of the volume of exports achieved in the fourthquarter of 1948 are also given for purposes of comparison. The sum ofthe individual industry targets for 1949 is arithmetically equivalent to avolume of about 160 per cent, of 1938, but, because of the possibility of individual shortfalls, the general * export target has been put at 155 percent. Table X shows the forecast levels of exports for each main classof goods. These are the levels of exports on which reliance is placed forthe purpose of programming imports.Table IXExport Targets, 1948 and 1949(Monthly rates at end-1948 and end-1949)	Exports, 4th Quarter, 1948,	Target, end-1948	Target, end-1949   -				  million at forecast prices (i)	Per cent, of 1938 volume	Per cent, of	1938 volume		Machinery ...      .........	204	206	25	225Vehicles	282	255	23	285Electrical Goods and Apparatus ...	231	252	8	271Iron and Steel      ...     ......	134	111	,      9 lr	119-Other Metal Goods	260	210	8	^226Textiles and Clothing      ......	100	134	36	125Chemicals  ......	157	184	9	198Pottery, Glass, Abrasives, etc.   ...	210	223	5	254Coal......      .........	36	39	6	57All other Exports.........	113	123	30	122				Total	147	150	159	155				(0 Assumed to be as at end-1948.Table XExports of United Kingdom Produce, 1947 to 1949,by Commodity Groups(Volume indices, 1938 = 100).&apos;                             ....	1947	1948		1949 Jan.-June		Jan-June	July-Dec.	ForecastMachinery ...	158	186	200	210Vehicles     ...........-.	185	254	278	282Electrical Goods and Apparatus ...	164	&apos; 209	225	235Iron and Steel      ......	107	112	124	120-Other Metal Goods       ...     ...	181	- 206	242	235Textiles and Clothing     ......	72	86	100	104Chemicals   ...      ......     ....	140	152	160	165Pottery, Glass, Abrasives, etc.	154	200	206	215Coal...............	3	21	36	45All other Exports......	91	102	106	108Total      ......	109	130	143	147

27055. In both halves of 1948 the volume of exports exceeded the forecasts,contained in the Economic Survey for 1948, by 4 per cent, in the first, andby 5 per cent, in the second, half-year. Most categories of exports contributed to this surplus, notably vehicles and machinery, but textiles fell short by approximately 5 per cent. In the aggregate there was an increase of 25per cent, over the volume of exports in 1947 a remarkable achievementfor which great credit is due to British industry. A more modest riseis expected in 1949. The limitations on exports in 1949 fall into three categories. First, there are difficulties of supply on our own part whichprevent in particular, any great expansion in the export of cotton goods,,pottery, coal and metal goods. These difficulties derive generally either from manpower difficulties (as in the case of cottons and pottery) or fromthe rival claims of the home market. Secondly, there are the restrictions which other countries in balance of payments difficulties continue to placeon the entry of a wide range of consumers&apos; goods which form an important element in United Kingdom exports. Finally, there are the difficulties of finding buyers at our present selling prices. Demand is falling off insome markets where restocking is now completed. At the same timeincreasing competition from other exporters has to be faced in the mainhard currency markets. It was in the light of these considerations that the forecast of probable exports in 1949-50 contained in our programme for1949-50 submitted to O.E.E.C. in October last year (Cmd. 7572) was put at 145 per cent, by volume of 1938 exports. In view of subsequent develop-ments this particular figure is probably to be regarded as too low.56. Table XI shows the volume of United Kingdom exports to differentdestinations expressed as a percentage of the volume exported in 1938 to thesame areas. Exports to the Western Hemisphere are forecast as rising to 145in the first half of 1949 compared with a figure of 138 achieved in the last half of 1948. Small changes are expected in the volume of exports to other areas. The proportion of our total exports going to the Western Hemisphereis expected to remain at about 17 per cent. This suggests that in the first part of the year, at least, the broad geographical pattern of British exportsis not likely to change in a very significant manner.Table XIVolume of Exports of United Kingdom Produce by Destinations(Volume indices, 1938 = 100)	1947	1948		1949 Jan.-June		Jan-June	July-Dec.	ForecastWestern Hemisphere      ......	94	125	138	145Sterling Area       .........	117	141	157	163O.E.E.C. Countries.....,	99	122	136	133Other Countries (&apos;)        ......	107	113	110	117				Total      .........	109	130	143	147(0 Includes Egypt, Sudan, Palestine and Transjordan throughout.57. A special factor in export policy which became more apparent during1948 and to which increased attention will be paid during 1949, is the require-ments of the Colonial Empire. In considering these, account must be taken not only of the contribution which the Colonial Empire can make and is making to the economy of the United Kingdom, but of the responsibilities which the United Kingdom Government owes to the Colonies. If the forward policy of Colonial development to which the Government is committed is to be carried out with the speed and efficiency that are requiredin the interests of the Colonies and the United Kingdom alike, the supplyof both capital goods and consumers&apos; goods to the Colonies must beincreased. This obligation is particularly important when the Colonialareas are restricting their dollar expenditure so drastically in the interestsof the sterling area as a whole.

58. Imports. The volume of imports in the second half of 1948 was no-greater than in the first. This is largely due to a shortfall in our pro-grammes of purchases for a number of commodities, e.g. Argentine meat and-Australian wool. Table XII gives details of our imports under the main categories and a forecast of the probable level of imports in the first-half of 1949. Some increase over the low level of the second half of 1948,.particularly in imports of raw materials is expected.Table XIIVolume of Retained Imports in Main Groups of Commodities (*)(Volume indices, 1938 - 100)	1947	&apos; 1948		1949		Jan.-June	July-Dec. Provisional	Jan.-June ForecastFood and Feedingstuffs   ......	75	78	76	78Raw Materials     ...     &apos;......	81	81	83	89Petroleum   ............	98	115	126	Other Imports      ...      ...     ...	60	61	76	68Total	77	81	81	84(i) The 1947 figures are based on a revaluation of retained imports at the average values ofretained imports in 1938: figures for later periods are based upon revaluations ofactual or programme figures at 1947 average values.59. Table XIII gives the percentage distribution of total imports bysources. These figures bring out the substantial increase in the proportionof our 1948 imports which came from the non-dollar areas. The pre-warproportion of imports from the Western Hemisphere was restored. Anyfurther reduction will prove more difficult, but it is hoped to reduce it to&apos;27 per cent, in the first half of 1949. Thereafter the reduction can only be gradual, as non-Western Hemisphere supplies and home production increase.The practical problems of the policy of dollar saving, to which we havebeen reluctantly driven by the necessity to reduce our dollar deficit to manage-able dimensions are discussed below.Table XIIIDistribution of Total Payments for Imports by Sources (*)(Percentages)			1948		1949	1938	1947	Jan.-June	July-Dec. Provisional	Jan.-June ForecastWestern Hemisphere	&quot; 32	46	33	31	27Sterling Area	31	33	38	38	38O.E.E.C. Countries	23	15	17	19	21Other Countries (2)	14	6	12	12	14Total	100	100	100	100	1000) The percentages for 1947, 1948 and first half of 1949 relate to f.o.b. payments. The1938 percentages relate to c.i.f. values of imports from the Trade and NavigationAccounts.(2) Includes Egypt, Sudan, Palestine and Transjordan throughout.

60. Terms of Trade. Although during the first half of 1948 the terms of-trade continued to move against us, in the second half of the year there was little change, but the end-year position was substantially worse than a year before. In estimating the balance of payments for the first half of 1949,no increases in prices of exports or imports have been assumed. A similarassumption was made in the 1949-50 and 1952-53 programmes submitted toO.E.E.C. These price assumptions are one of the most unpredictable elements in forecasting the balance of payments. On the one hand the recent pausein the adverse movement of the terms of trade suggests that a turning pointmay have been reached; on the other hand growing competition in export markets and the high level of demand for primary products give no grounds for optimism. A movement of only 5 per cent, in the terms of trade canchange the balance of payments on current account by some  100 million in.a year.61. Invisible Payments and Receipts. The invisible balance has usuallyproved much less stable and predictable than the visible balance since itis the net result of a very large variety of independent transactions. TableXIV shows the movements of the main items in recent periods and alsoa forecast for the first half of 1949. During 1948 the invisibles showed anoteworthy improvement, giving a surplus over the year of  98 million asCompared with a deficit of  184 million in 1947. Receipts from inter-Government settlements and disposals of war stores were again heavy, though a little less than in 1947. A big reduction in such receipts is expected inthe first half of 1949 (apart from the special Indian transaction). Neverthe-less, the surplus on invisible account is very little below the figure in theprevious half-year, since a continued improvement in the other items isexpected to make good the natural decline in these post-war governmentaltransactions. Travel expenditure abroad will show some seasonal decline,but net shipping income is expected to rise further, and higher income from,miscellaneous sources, including the earnings of oil companies, can be looked for.Table XTVInvisible Payments and Receipts(  millions)	1938	1947	1948		1949 Jan.-June			Jan.-June	July-Dec. Provisional	Payments: Government Overseas Expen-diture: (a) Military        ...... (b) Relief and Rehabilitation (c) Germany Administrative,   Diplo-matic, etc.         ...... ie) War disposals and Settle-ments     ......... &apos;(/) Other Government (net) Total (net)   ... &quot;Shipping Interest, Profits and Dividends Films (net)    ......... Travel ... Total Payments Receipts: Shipping       ......... Interest, Profits and Dividends Travel......     ...... Other (net)    ......... Total Receipts Surplus (-(-) or Deficit (-) on t Current Account     ......		197 58 80 37 -121 - 44	64 9 12 22 - 43 - 1	52 5 11 19 - 67 - 1	113(i) 7 21 - 79(2) - 1	16	207	63	19	61	80 30 7 40	181 106 14 80	94 56 7 27	96 56 3 43	98 56 2 30	173	588	247	217	247	100 205 28 72 .	205 153 21 25	122 78 15 58	126 84 20 59	133 81 17 78	405	404	273	289	309	-1-232	-184	4- 26	&apos;4- 72	4- 62(0 Includes  55 million paid under Indian settlement.*(2) Includes  55 million received under Indian settlement.

62. The Balance of Payments on Current Account. If the various esti-xnates of exports, imports and invisibles are put together we arrive at astatement of the balance of payments on current account. This is shown inTable XV. Compared with a surplus provisionally estimated at  5 million in the second half of 1948. the balance in the first half of 1949 is forecast asa deficit of  10 million. It is necessary to emphasise that in a geld sofraught with uncertainties little significance can be attached to such smallvariations. The main point to be made is that despite the assumption of aconsiderable increase in imports our payments - are expected to remainapproximately in balance&apos;.* This latest apDreciation of our position [for 1948-49 is much more favourable thanthe estimate of a deficit of  362 millions published in Cmd. 7572 in December. The latterestimate was prepared in June 1948, and, as well as being put forward before information on the significant changes in invisible items was available, assumed that we would be ableto obtain much greater supplies from the non-dollar world than we did and that we shouldhave paid somewhat higher prices than those which in the event ruled in the second half of1948.Table XVBalance of Payments on Current Account with All Areas(  million).			1948		1949	1938	1947	Jan.-June	July-Dec. Provisional	Jan-June ForecastPayments: Imports (f.o.b.):   . (a) Food and FeedingstufFs (h) Animals, seeds, etc.   ... (c) Raw Materials... (d) Tobacco (e) Petroleum      .... (f) Manufactures and other imports  ...      ......	...	719 25 517 30 78 172	421 11 303 18 62 81	400 14 311 21 61 75	425 10 382    -2 54 .74Total.........	835	1,541	896	882	947Receipts: Exports and Re-Exports (f.c.b.) Invisibles (net)        ......	533 -1-232	1,095 -184	720 -1- 26	815 -1- 72	875 4- 62Surplus (-f) or Deficit ( ) on Current Account     ......	- 70	-630	- 150	+ &apos; 5	- 1063. How far this tendency towards general balance will persist after themiddle of this year cannot yet be firmly established. The provisional esti-mate for 1949-50 published in December but prepared in September envis-aged a deficit in 1949-50 of  200 million ; the actual development will depend largely upon the availability of essential supplies from non-dollar sources,and upon the continued success of the export drive. For the reasons des-cribed in the following paragraphs, the Government does not attach majorsignificance to the achievement or maintenance of a general balance as such ;much more important is the progress made towards a solution of the criticalparts of the balance of payments problem and in particular the dollar deficit. For purposes of the national income calculations in this Survey,it is assumed that in the year 1949 as a whole, the state of general balancecontinues, but this clearly carries no implication about the course of the dollar deficit.64. The general balance conceals a varied and complex&quot; pattern offinancial relationships. With some countries, particularly the Western Hemis-frhere but also in the Middle East, we continue to be heavily in deficit.With others, including some of our partners in O.E.E.C. and a number of countries in the rest of the sterling area, we continue to be in large surplus.For as long as the non-dollar world remains critically short of dollars, it isnot possible for us in general to earn from the countries with which wehave surpluses the dollars which we need to finance our dollar deficit.The general balance, taker/ by itself, shows that we are sending as muchin goods and services out of the country as we are bringing in, but itdoes not in present circumstances represent a financial equilibrium.65. It is, however, very necessary at present to have these surpluses.Part of them represent the assistance which we are giving to France andother European countries under the Intra-European Payments Scheme;part of them represent the investment which we are making in the colonies and other parts of the Commonwealth an indispensable part of theprogramme for developing new sources of supply upon which our ultimatehope of solving the dollar problem so largely rests; part of them servedirectly to strengthen our financial position with countries which holdbalances of sterling, making it less likely that in future they will be ableto draw gold or dollars from us. In all these directions it is well worthour while to export more than we import; indeed, the improvement whichhas taken place in the last year in the position of sterling in the world&apos;financial centres is ample proof of it.

66. Table XVI sets out the course of our balance of payments with themain areas of the world during the past two years and a forecast forthe first half of 1949. It is necessary to emphasise that such forecasts are inevitably more liable to error than the estimates of the balance ofpayments as a whole.Table XVIBalance of Payments on Current Account by Areas. (  million)	1947	1948		1949 Jan.-June Forecast		Jan-June	July-Dec. Provisional	Western Hemisphere:. Imports (f.o.b.)......... Exports and Re-exports (f.o.b.) Invisibles (net)   ...     ...... Surplus or Deficit       ...... Sterling Area: Imports (f.o.b.)......... Exports and Re-exports (f.o.b.) Invisibles (net)......... Surplus or Deficit       ...... O.E.E.C. Countries: Imports (f.o.b.) ...     ...... Exports and Re-exports (f.o.b.) Invisibles (net)   ......... Surplus or Deficit       ...... Other Countries: Imports (f.o.b.) ... Exports and Re-exports (f.o.b.) Invisibles (net)   ......... Surplus or Deficit       ......	717 172 -110	293 119 _Of.	276 145 .-4	255 150 .   -5		 zo			-655	-200	-135	-110	504 561 -2	337 344 4-48	333 390 4-73	363 425 4-53	4-55	4-55	4-130	4-115	233 267 -59	156 178 4-23	167 197 4-15	201 210				,    +31	-25	4-45	4-45	4-40	87 95 -13	110 79 -19	106 83 -12	128 90 -17	-5	-50	-35	-5567. The deficit with the Western Hemisphere which is not the same thing .as the dollar deficit was reduced during 1948 from  200 million in the first half to  135 million in the second. The forecast deficit for thefirst half of 1949 is  110 million. There is thus a steady improvement inthis all important part of the balance of payments, both as regards thedecline in imports and as regards the rise in receipts from exports.68. The surplus with the Sterling Area rose considerably during 1948,but much of the total of  130 million in the second half of the year wasaccounted for by an exceptional receipt of  45 million under the terms ofthe Indian settlement. Some fall is expected during the first half of1949. With the O.E.E.C. countries the balance was favourable duringthe whole of 1948. In 1949 our import programme allows for an increasein the level of imports from Western Europe greater than the prospective increase in exports. But bigger receipts from invisibles are expected andthe surplus may not be much lower.69. The remaining areas of the world are grouped together in the lastsection of Table XVI. The most important regions concerned are theMiddle East and Eastern Europe. The United Kingdom had a deficit on current account with these areas during 1948 and this may increase during 1949. A difficult payments problem is involved here, but the deficitshould largely be met through a complex pattern of multilateral payments with the sterling area and other countries.

70. The division of the balance into separate balances with four mainareas of the world gives only a rough indication of our payments problems.The actual situation is more complex. The countries of the western hemisphere are not all equally hard (nor are countries in Europe and elsewhere equally soft). A hard currency country, in this sense, is one whichtends to accumulate too much sterling, so that either our trade or financial relations become strained or we have to repurchase some of it against gold ordollars a not unimportant charge on our reserves (see Table XVII). Itis above all the object of our bilateral negotiations to avoid such gold and dollar payments. This is not simply a question of influencing the course oftrade with the United Kingdom: a country&apos;s sterling position is largelyaffected by its balance of payments with the rest of the sterling area and bythe transfers of sterling between it and other non-sterling countries. the multilateral use of sterling is most important in this context.Table XVIIUnited Kingdom Balance of Payments Capital Account(  million)	1947	1948		1949 Jan.-June Forecast		Jan-June	July-Dec. Provisional	/. Net Gold and Dollar Deficit: 1. United Kingdom 2. Rest of the Stering Area 3. Whole Sterling Area: Net gold and dollar pay-ments   to  non-dollar countries Total net gold and dollar deficit	657 204 163	186 17	125 9 35	112 29 55	1,025	254	169	196				//. Net reduction in United Kingdom external capital assets: Non-sterling area Sterling area     ...... 111. Net increase in sterling liabilities-ties:     : Non-sterling area Sterling area Net overseas disinvestment	-73 -179	58 -143	42 -24	- -186	-252	-85	18		3 -145	-138 119	-108 -84		-142	-19	-192		630	150	-5	1071. The overseas Capital Account and Gold and Dollar Deficit. TableXVII sets out the main elements in the capital account of the United King-dom. First in importance is the analysis of the size and composition of thenet gold and dollar deficit. In the second half of 1948 the total sterling area deficit, which falls as a charge on the central reserves, was reduced to 169 million from a figure of  254 million in the first half-year. Mostnotable was the reduction in the United Kingdom&apos;s own deficit with the dollar area, which fell from  186 million to  125 million. A further smallreduction is expected in the first half of 1949. After the immense improve-ment recorded by the Rest of the Sterling Area since 1947, an improvement towhich the increasing dollar surplus of the colonial territories contributed verymaterially, no further reduction in the net drawings on the central reservesis to be expected in the first half of this year. Large payments to non-dollar countries are also likely to continue. This underlines the difficultyof achieving a reasonable balance in the sterling area&apos;s relations with certainnon-dollar countries, such as Belgium, Switzerland and Persia, which was referred to above.72. Despite the probable increase in the total gold and dollar deficit whichhas been forecast for the first half of 1949, it remains true that our dollarrequirements are likely to be fully met by the amount of aid under E.R.P.which has been allocated to us for the year 1948-49 (provisionally,  313million) together with similar allocations to Eire (whose net dollarrequirements are of course met from the central reserves) and by drawings onthe Canadian credit which we have now been permitted to resume by theigenerous action of the Canadian Government.

73. Because of uncertainty about the rate at which reimbursements can beexpected from the European Co-operation Administration of the UnitedStates of expenditure already incurred by us, it is impossible to forecast the precise change in the level of our actual holdings of gold and dollars in thefirst half of this year. A statement showing how the gold and dollar deficithas been met since 1947 is given in Table XVIII.Table XVIIIThe Settlement of the Gold and Dollar Deficit(  million)	1947 Actual	1948		1949			Jan.-June Actual	July-Dee. Provisional	Jan.-June Forecast	Drawings on: U.S. Credit    ......... Canadian Credit      ......	707. 105	74 13			Drawings on International Monetary Fund: By U.K.       ......... By India       ......	60	15 11	6		&quot;    196South African Gold loan ...	-	80			Receipts under E.R.P.......	-	22	147		Decrease in gold and dollar hold-kinds (0......     .......	152	39	16	-	Total net gold and dollar deficit ...	1,024	254	169	196	(0 At the end of 1948 holdings of gold and U.S. and Canadian dollars amounted to 457 million.74. The Level of E.R.P. Aid in future.-For the year 1949-50, estimates were tabled at the O.E.E.C. (Cmd. 7572) which indicated that on certain assumptions we should be able to carry out our programmes with E.R.P.aid of $940 million compared with $1,263 million in 1948-49. At the presenttime the United States Congress is considering the size of the appropriationto the O.E.E.C. countries as a whole for 1949-50, and when the legislation hasbeen enacted it will be necessary for O.E.E.C. to present recommendations toEC.A. for its division between the various countries. It is perfectly clearthat we cannot yet rely upon receiving the $940 million indicated in theestimates presented to O.E.E.C., and it is therefore impossible to state withprecision how serious the immediate dollar problem will be after the middleof this year. It must be emphasised that the maintenance of the present levels of consumption and employment depends upon the fact of American aid and upon the scale upon which this aid is available to us.75. It is not possible to make precise forecasts of the other transactionson capital account shown in Table XVII. The movement of our sterlingliabilities to non-sterling area countries, for example, depends on a complex of circumstances in which not only is the balance of payments of theUnited Kingdom with hem involved, but also the balance of other membersof the sterling area, and the extent to which non-sterling area countries arelikely to continue to repatriate their overseas debt or to purchase otherU.K.-owned overseas assets.76. A further point is the extent to which O.E.E.C. countries will drawon the sterling grants which we have made available to them under theIntra-European Payments Agreement. During the period July, 1948, toJune, 1949, we have agreed to an amount of  70 million and in additionwill allow certain countries to draw on their existing sterling balances tothe extent of  52 million. On the other side, we ourselves have beengranted  7* million by Belgium, of which  5* million was used during thelast quarter of 1948. It is impossible at present to say whether all the drawing rights will be exercised under the scheme or whether use will bemade of aU the sterling releases. Nevertheless the existence and the extentof these facilities represent a very substantial contribution on our part to the cause of European recovery.77. If our balance of payments on current account turns out in accord-ance with the forecast previously given, the net capital export, defined inthe broadest sense to include the assistance offered by us under the Intra-European Payments Agreement as well as capital investment in the sterling area and elsewhere, may be of the order of  180 million during the first half of 1949: that is, at about the same rate as in the second half of1948.

78. The Long-Term Dollar Problem. It is clear from this description ofour balance of payments position that the outstanding problem with whichwe are now faced is the large and continuing deficit with the western hemisphere, and in particular with the dollar area. Our total overseasaccount shows an approximate balance. This represents the completion ofa vital stage in our progress towards full recovery. But the present levelof food consumption and our ability to purchase the necessary rawmaterials to maintain industrial production, are dependent entirely upon the willingness of the United States and Canada to finance our dollar deficitby grants and loans. The purpose of our long-term programme is to, eliminate this deficit, and this need must determine our overseas economic policy in 1949.79. With the prospect that the worst of the gold and dollar deficit maybe covered for us in the short run by American help, the main efforts ofeconomic policy can be devoted to promoting longer term developments-that can assist its eventual solution. These were discussed in a generalway in the Economic Survey for 1948 (paragraphs 67 to 81) and in more detail in the Long Term Programme submitted to O.E.week. (Cmd. 7572)..Five types of specific policy are involved. We must promote home product-tion in appropriate fields to save imports from hard currency areas: thedevelopment of home agricultural and chemicals output is especially important in this connection, but these are only two of many programmes to which attention is being paid. We must expand exports, including oilsales, to areas where they can earn gold or dollars, and in particular to north America. We must make further diversions of imports away from,areas where gold, or dollar payments are necessary to areas where paymentcan be made in currencies of which we have a more plentiful supply.We must, by promoting colonial development, maintain and if possibleincrease the now substantial dollar surplus earned by the Colonies. Wemust, lastly, assist the countries of the sterling area to effect continued,economies in their dollar imports and further expansion in their dollarexports. Some of the practical issues raised by the policies of increasing,dollar exports, and of diverting imports, deserve further description inthis Survey.80. Exports to North America-In spite of the efforts of the past threeyears the proportion of total United Kingdom exports at present going to north America is still slightly lower than pre-war. While we have established a firm foundation for a further intensification of our export drive in thesemarkets we must in the next two or three years greatly increase exports to canada and the United States if we are to become independent of E.R.P.Aid without a reduction in the standard of living. It is, of course, the case that in the last two years the contribution of exports to alleviating the dollarshortage is not accurately measured by statistics of direct exports to theUnited States or Canada. Much, for instance, of the textiles sold to Common-wealth countries achieved dollar savings by the sterling area quite as effec-tively as the textiles exported to North America achieved dollar earnings,since the alternative to imports from this country for the commonwealth countries was to make their essential purchases of textiles from the UnitedStates. From the standpoint of our gold reserves the two transactions were equally helpful. Nevertheless, an intensive drive to increase our direct dollar earnings is becoming vital.81. A notable advance in exports to North America has already occurredand we have also built up promising markets for some manufactures whichwere not exported to the United States or Canada before the war. The time has now arrived however when we can and must- intensify our attack on theNorth American market. National incomes in North America are at unprecedented-cedented levels and the prospects for increased sales of manufactures arevery promising. Our problem is to produce goods which, through quality and price, will command buyers in a free market and we certainly cannotrely on securing more favourable conditions for the entry of our goods thanexist to-day.82. The Government has endeavoured to give practical assistance to manu-facturers and exporters anxious to increase their sales to North America.There is now a much keener and more widespread understanding of the paramount importance of the dollar market problem. But these are difficultmarkets and the competition of domestic manufactures is often fierce. Thereis inevitably some reluctance to enter the American market particularlybecause of the risk of rapid changes of demand and the smaller manu-facturers and exporters lack the resources with which to undertake newventures in North America.83. The Government is resolved to play a full part in the North Americanexport drive and is developing plans for the reinforcement of existing measures.of practical assistance for exporters.

84. Import Diversion. The third of the ways of solving the dollar problemdistinguished in paragraph 79 the reduction of imports from dollar sources demands the encouragement of production in the non-dollar world in orderthat increasing supplies may be available for export to us. The post-warrecovery of primary production in other parts of the world, together withprojects for new development in the Colonies and elsewhere, have madeprogress in 1948 but must be pressed further in 1949. A considerable time is needed to bring such projects to fruition, and great efforts will have to bemade now in order to secure results in three or four years&apos; time.85. In this connection the Government has welcomed the declaration ofthe President of the United States that the United States intends to embark on a bold new programme for making the benefits of scientific and industrialprogress available for the improvement and growth of under-developed areas.Important developments of this kind are already taking place within thecolonial territories of the Commonwealth which, besides contributing to the welfare of the Colonial peoples and to the saving of dollars in U.K. imports,also lead to an expansion in the Colonies&apos; dollar income and to the avail-ability of non-dollar supplies for other countries, particularly those of western Europe. These developments include both the expansion of existingColonial production and also the initiation of completely new sources ofproduction.86. Besides Colonial development, projects are under discussion for expan-sion of primary production in the rest of the Commonwealth, and it is hopedthat as part of the programme for European recovery there will be substan-tial expansion of production of basic products for the U.K. market in western european countries.87. This is indeed part of the task of expanding primary production in theEastern Hemisphere generally which is a necessary condition for worldrecovery. The Government are using a number of means of stimulatingproduction to this end. These range from the direct development work under government auspices, e.g. the Overseas Food Corporation and the colonial development Corporation, to the support and initiation of measures in inter-national organisations which are designed to lead to this result. They includethe conclusion of long-term contracts which guarantee a market to primaryproducers (e.g. Western European and Commonwealth livestock and dairy products), the conclusion of long-term bilateral agreements which have thesame effect (e.g. the agreement with Poland), the provision of capital goods and inducement goods^to provide for the expansion of production and to stimulate producers. These measures cannot yield results at all quickly butthey are an essential part of the long-term strategy.(e) Manpower88. During 1948 the total working population declined by. 100,000, rather less than a third of the fall anticipated in the last Survey. Releases from the armed Forces was however more than sufficient to counteract the potentialeffect of this reduction on the total industrial population and this rose bysome 300,000 during the year. During 1949 the total working population is expected to be practically constant, and the stabilisation of the size ofthe Forces, means that the nation now has a practically constant industrial population. The long term tendency for the number of women in employ-ment to decline is likely to begin to show itself though for the present it is offset by an increase in the number of men. This is due to a declinein the total number of women in the age groups from which the employedare principally drawn. In the five years from 1948 to 1952 this may cost the country some 300,000 workers (unless the proportion at work increases)and raise some difficult problems in industries such as textiles which employ a high proportion of women.89. The distribution of manpower in Great Britain in recent periods isshown in Tables XIX and XX. Two tables are needed because the cominginto operation of the new National Insurance Scheme in 1948 brought intothe count of employed persons many who were previously excluded. At thesame time the classification of jobs was changed to conform to one whichis being adopted for all Government Statistics. Consequently exact com-comparisons between figures on the old and the new bases cannot be made.A full account of the changes is contained in the issue of the Ministry ofLabour Gazette for February, 1949. Table XIX shows the trends up tothe end of 1948 on the old basis and compares them with forecasts in thelast Economic Survey. Table XX gives forecasts for 1949 on the new basis,and these are the figures that are used in the following paragraphs and willbe used in any future Surveys.

(Thousands)Total working population	Mid-1939 Actual	End-1946 Actual	End-1947 Actual	End 1948					Economic Survey	ActualC)	19,750	20,435	20,429	20,100	20,328Strength of Armed Forces	480	1,461	1,119	730	809Ex-Service men and women on					release leave ...		300	123	50	.18Total industrial population	19,270	18,674.	19,187	19,320	19,501Of whom Men        ......	14,176	12,983	13,475	13,720	13,772,,     Women    ......	5,094	5,691	5,712	5,600	. 5,729Coal (total man-power)......	773	730	758	790	766Other Mining and Quarrying ...	100	71	73	75	74-Public Utilities ...      ......	242	264	270	280	279Transport and Shipping	1,233	1,384	1,438	1,460	1,461Agriculture Fishing............	910	1,046	1,055	1,110	1,091	40	35	35	37	35Building and Civil Engineering	1,310	1,289	1,364	1,200	1,357Manufactures 					Building Materials   ......	567	574	590	575	585Metals and Engineering	2,267	2,822	2,876	2,900	2,908Cotton............	344	255	267	325	287Wool............	210	167	178	200	186Other Textiles         ......	244	193	207	235	217Clothing       ......	1,005	807	831	800	839Food, Drink and Tobacco ...	654	599	623	600	642Chemicals     .........	266	321	336	335	343Other manufactures......	1,258	1,268	1,343	1,355	1,337Distribution     .........	2,887	2,309	2,351	2,320	2,406Consumer Services      ......	2,225	1,984	2,120	2,123	2,110Public Service 					Civil Service ...	408	722	692	715	Li f\QAOther National Government	211	384	375	360	Local Government   ...	.   846	1,052	1,105 -	1,075	1,146Total Employed...      ...... Unemployed     ......	18,000 1,270	18,276 398	18,887 300	18,870 450	19.153 348(0 Final figures are not yet available.Table XXDistribution of Manpower in Great Britain, 1939-48(New Series)(Thousands)Total working population         ......... Strength of Armed Forces         ......... Ex-Service men and women on release leave	Mid-1948 Actual	End-1948 Actual(0	End-1949 Forecast	23,147	23,239	23,200	847 92	810 -     17	y    775Total industrial population        .........	22,208	22,412	22,425Of whom Men   ..................	15,160	15,280	15,335,,     Women.............	7,048	7,132	7,090Coalmining...      ......      ............	787	786	788Other Mining and Quarrying.........      ...	82	82	.   82;Gas, Electricity and Water...............	296	301	305-Transport and Communication............	1,814	1,808	1,790-Agriculture......      ...............	1,227	1,236	1,240-Fishing      ......      ............	41	41	40&apos;Manufactures 			Chemicals and Allied Trades   ............	426	436	440&apos;Metals, Engineering and Vehicles     .........	3,903	3,931	3,920Cotton    ...     ..................	310	320	331Wool      ...............      ......	209	214	220-Other Textiles    ..................	430	438	444Clothing...............      ......	700	718	715Food, Drink and Tobacco     ...     .........	725	743	740-Other Manufactures     ...............	1,411	1,431	1,430Building and Contracting...............	1,498	1,485	1,490Distributive Trades         ...     ......	2,689	2,755	2,755Professional, financial and miscellaneous services	3,925	3,884	3,890*Public Administration 			National Government Service............	687	691	675Local Government Service     ............	766	784	780Total in civil employment  *     ............ Unemployed...................	21,926 282	22,084 328	22,075 350(0 Figures for end-December are not yet available. These are end-November figures.Table XIXDistribution of Manpower in Great Britain, 1939-1948, (Old Series)

90. Earlier plans for the size of the peacetime forces had assumed a gradual.and uninterrupted return to peacetime conditions. During 1948, however,it was found necessary to strengthen the Armed Forces by increasing militaryproduction and by checking the fall in uniformed strengths. This meant that the numbers employed on Defence at the end of the year were greater-than the numbers forecast in the Economic Survey for 1948. In 1949 onlya small decrease in the size of the Armed Forces is expected. The totalcall on man-power at the end of this year is estimated to be about 1,410,000,of whom 760,000 will be in the Forces, 240,000 will be non-industrial Civil-Servants in the Defence Departments or industrial staffs not directly engaged on production and research and some 410,000 will be in industry, either directly employed by the Defence Departments or on contract work. the civilian man-power is included under the appropriate headings in Table XX.91. The policy of the Government during 1948 has been to increase thelabour force of certain industries regarded as essential to our economic-recovery. It must be recognised that full employment creates a rigidity inthe distribution of the labour force which makes large scale movements of labour difficult to achieve. The Control of Engagement Order wasreintroduced in the Autumn of 1947 and experience during 1948 showedit to be effective in enabling large numbers of workers to be guided intoessential work, without the interference with individual freedom which thewidespread use of powers of direction would entail. Only 300 directionshave had to be issued during the year which 576,000 placings were effected in.the essential industries granted priority in the supply of labour. At thesame time a large scale publicity campaign was carried on to stimulaterecruitment in the essential industries. These policies resulted in increasesduring 1948 in the labour forces in textiles, agriculture and coalmining, aswell as in the maintenance of the necessary supply of labour to many other important branches of industry. The increase of 6 per cent, in textilesis the largest percentage increase of any industry group during 1948. Inagriculture, the increase was 4 per cent, and in general all the effectivedemand for labour in this industry was met. In coalmining British recruit-ment was practically sufficient to offset wastage amounting to 70,000 in theyear. The net increase of 8,000 in the number employed in the industry would have been larger if difficulties had not arisen over the recruitment and absorption of all the foreign workers whom it was hoped to place inthe industry.&quot;92. Foreign labour provided in 1948 a valuable addition to the total man-power in civil employment. Altogether about 95,000 foreign workersrecruited under official schemes have been placed in employment in 1948,for the most part in the undermanned or other important industries or in hospital and domestic work. In addition, there has been a substantial influx of labour oh permits, mainly for domestic work. Over half of the foreign workers went into mining, agriculture and textiles making a -considerablecontribution to the net increase during the year in their total manpower.Some further addition of foreign workers will be necessary, particularly men for coalmining and women for textiles, though the total is likely to be lessthan in 1948.93. During 1949 there will be no more large net accessions of manpowerfrom the Services or from armaments work upon the labour market, andno large scale redistribution of labour between industries is required. but more labour continues to be needed in certain industries and it will alsobe important to keep other industries up to strength and to ensure that theydo not go short of the labour they require. The Government thereforeintends to maintain&apos; unchanged their existing labour policy. In the textile industries substantial increases are likely to be required. The forecast showsincreases of 10,000 in cotton and 5,000 in wool but an improvement on thesefigures would be desirable. Jn the coalmining industry the main objectivewill be to increase by 14,000 the number of workers employed at the coalface. To the extent that it is necessary to replace men upgraded to work at the face, a further increase in the total number of wage earners oncolliery books will be required. Not all the men upgraded to the coal facewill need to be replaced. The estimate made toy the industry is that thenumber of replacements required will be some 10,000. If this proves tobe correct the calculated figures of labour requirements (which depends ofcourse upon a number of very uncertain and detailed estimates) would befor about 735,000 men on colliery books at the end of 1949. The attain-ment of this total will need intensive efforts to increase recruitment andthe entry in particular of further foreign workers. In agriculture some increase will be needed but the most acute need will be for temporary labour at harvest time.94. The forecast for National Government Service for 1949 shows an overall decrease. During 1948, When there was a slight increase, two factorswere at work. There was a decrease in the staff engaged in a number of departments, particularly those concerned with the administration of controlsand in the Defence Departments.   On the other hand, the extension of the

Social Services, in particular the National Insurance Acts, has meant a net increase in the Social Service Departments of 22,000. Some part of this increase was accounted for by the transfer of staff doing such work from local Authorities and from Approved Societies and did not. constitute anadditional call on the nation&apos;s manpower. The estimate level of unemploy-ment shows little change. This does not mean any slackening in the effort to improve the position in the Development Areas and other places where unemployment is serious, or in the Governmenfs measures to encourage the employment of disabled persons. Further progress with these policieswill be sought in 1949. It is intended only to make allowance for someslackening of the intensity of demand for labour and of the rate of turn-over in the labour market. Apart from the special problems referred to unemployment at the extremely low level of the present time is little morethan a reflection of the numbers of workers changing from one job toanother.(f) National Income and Expenditure95. The following section sets out in round figures a forecast of the national income and expenditure accounts, the country&apos;s total balance sheet, for 1949,so far as it can now be constructed on the basis of the particular programmes and estimates described in the preceding sections. These calculations cannotclaim to give more than a broad illustration of the tendencies at work. Thefigures for 1948 are also provisional, since they are based on data that arestill incomplete. They are however consistent with the detailed figures conrtained in this year&apos;s White Paper on National Income and Expenditure.96. National Income.-Table XXI presents a general summary of the prin- ipal totals. For past years/the various items of income and expenditure arevalued at the prices actually ruling during those years. For 1949 the figures are expressed in terms of the wage and price levels ruling at the beginningof the year. It will be seen from the income side of the account that between1947 and 1948, there was an increase in the national income in money termsof about  900 million, or 10 per cent. About half of this increase was dueto the rise in prices between the two years. The rest was due to an increasein industrial production and an increased return from those services forwhich we receive invisible earnings from abroad. Of the aggregate increase,about  450 million accrued to wage and salary earners (including the armed forces),, and about  450 million represents the increase in rent profits and interest. Of the latter  265 million was set aside by companies as extrareserves and thus became available to finance re-equipment. The Govern-ment&apos;s appeal not to increase dividends met with a very good response, andthe profits actually distributed consequently increased very little. The national income forecast for 1949 is based upon the distribution of the working population, shown in Table XX and upon the general assumption that output per man year in industry will increase by about 3 per cent, abovethe 1948 level.** It is important to avoid confusion between the different definitions and uses of the term productivity. In national income calculations it is used in the sense of the output perman-year of the whole working population. As many classes of worker e.g. the armed forces,civil servants do not produce a measurable &quot; commodity,&quot; the change in productivity forthe whole community is less than can be hoped for in individual manufacturing industries, itis usually found convenient to measure output per man-year of operatives ignoring the con-tribution of managerial and clerical labour. But output per man-how of all workers taken together, with allowance for the change in the quality of output is what we mean when we discuss the need for greater productivity. Output per man-year confuses the idea of output per man-hour, or productivity in its most desirable sense, with the number of hours or weeksworked in the year. Output per man-year could be increased by a wholesale lengthening of hours and reduction of holidays ; but no one would suggest that this would be desirable.Lastly a more complex definition in terms of resources rather than man-hours is used in-discussions of economic theory.

(  million)RESOURCES	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949 at end	EXPENDITURE	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949 at end			- &apos;48 prices				- &apos;48 pricesNational Income of the United Kingdom Provision for Depreciation and Mainten-ance Net Loans and Gifts from Abroad and Sales of Foreign Assets	8,770 775 630	9,685 825 145		Domestic Expendi-ture on Goods and Services at Market Prices: Personal Government... Gross Capital Formation Total   ... Subsidies less Indirect Taxes	7,425. 2,140 2,000	8,000 1,960 2,300						i 1,565 440 -1,830	12,260 490 -2,095	Total Resources available for use at Home	10,175	10,655		Total   Resources available for.use at Home	10,175	10,655	(&apos;) The various items in the following Tables are denned in the same way as in the white paper on National Income and Expenditure. In reading Table XXI it should forinstance be noted that the estimate for subsidies has a slightly different coverage tothat given in the debate on the Budget in April, 1948.97. In 1947 we supplemented our national income by borrowing abroad to the extent of  630 million. In 1948 our net assistance from abroad was reduced to  145 million. The gross resources available for use at hometherefore increased between the two years from  10,175 million to  10,655million, an increase in real terms of perhaps per cent: although weexported more of our own production, total real resources for use athome were more in 1948 than in 1947. The increase in resources between1948 and 1949 is fairly certain to be smaller: that shown in Table XXIrepresents an increase, after allowing for the probable conversion of theforeign deficit into a surplus, of the order of        per cent.98. National Expenditure (i) Consumption. The expenditure figures inTable XXI show the way in which the national resources were used in1948, and the way in which it is estimated they will be divided betweenpersonal consumption, government expenditure and investment in 1949.The proportionate division is shown in Table XXII.Table XXIIUse of the National Resources-	1938	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949Current Expenditure: Personal Consumption    ...     ... Government  Current  Expenditure   on Goods and Services     ...     ......	Per cent. 72 15	Per cent. 65 22	Per cent. 62 18	Per cent.Total Investment: Gross Capital Formation at Home External Investment       ......	14 -1	20 -7	21 -1	Gross National Resources.........	100	100	100	100In money terms, personal expenditure on consumption increased con-siderably between 1947 and 1948. But it rose by less than the 10 percent, increase in national income and thus absorbed a smaller proportionof the national income in 1948 than in 1947. When corrected for price changes, the increase in consumers&apos; expenditure was about one per cent.This figure of aggregate consumption is not necessarily a good measure ofthe change in consumers&apos; satisfaction that took place. The composition of consumption changed: for example, less tobacco was available, but theincrease in clothing consumption was an important move towards givingconsumers what they wanted.Table XXINational Resources and Expenditure (*)

The detailed figures given in Table XXIII should be read with this,proviso in mind. The figures for 1949 attempt rather to illustrate thepossibilities than to forecast the exact pattern of consumption in 1949-Table. XXIIIPersonal Consumption Expenditure, .1947-1949			Forecast		KltSil! ell Jl	1947	1948	for 1949  m. at	1948 and 1949 as per cent, of 1947 at		 m.	 m.	end-1948	constant prices				prices		Food     ............	1,995	2,185		Mi	Alcoholic Drinks        ......	678	760		96	Tobacco............	690	760		95	Rent, Rates and Water Charges	564	585		103	Fuel and Light ...	310	360		108	Durable Household Goods	393	430		101	Other Household Goods	72	75		106	Clothing ...      .........	704	865		113	Books, Newspapers and Maga-					zines   ......     ...     ...	119	125		101	Private Motoring       ...... Travel	134	70		S3		296	320		103	Post Office (Communication Ser-					vices).........&apos;	56	60		102	Entertainments......     ...	174	180		102	Other Services   ...	866	820		98	Other Goods	373	405		105	Total    .........	7,424	8,000		101	.99. Estimates for food consumption in real terms in the United kingdom for the periods 1947-48 and 1948-49, with comparable figures for pre-war are shown in Table XXIV. In the Economic Survey for 1948 a similartable gave a preliminary forecast for the first half of 1948 which proved to be unduly pessimistic, partly because it was drawn up before E.R.P.assistance had been introduced and reflected cuts in imported food,particularly from dollar sources, which were at that time projected, and&apos;partly because an exceptionally good early potato crop was harvested..Table XXIVFood Consumption in the United Kingdom Q)	Pre-war Actual	1947-48 Actual	1948-49 Partly Forecast(a) Average Daily Intake			Protein 			Animal (gms.)    ...............	42-7	41-0	41-0Vegetable (gms.) ... -    ............	37-2	42-1	43-8Total (gms.)      .........     ......	79-9	83-1	84-8Fat (from all sources) (gms.)      .........	130-2	104-8	109-2Visible fat (butter, margarine, lard, etc. fat			content) (gms.)   .........     ......	56-2	44-4	48-8Total energy value (calories)      .........	3,000	2,850	2,960(b) Annual Consumption in lbs. per head (2)			Dairy products (milk solids)      ...     ......	38-3	48-0	50 1Meat (edible weight)       ............	109-6	74-8	70-1Fish, Game, Poultry, etc. (edible weight)	32-8	37-7	380Eggs and egg products (shell egg equivalent)   ...	24-5	21-3	22-3Oils and fats (fat content)............	45-3	35-6	39-2Sugar and syrups (sugar content)..........	109-9	880	88-7     jPotatoes     ..................	1760	257-8	280-1Pulses and nuts     ...............	9-6	60	6-3Tomatoes and fruit (fresh equivalent)   ......	141-5	138-4	143-3Vegetables...............	107-4	111-8	1150Grain products     ...............	209-8	242-7	252-8Beverages    ..................	14-7	14-5	14-6(&apos;) The corresponding Table in the Economic Survey for 1948 was erroneously stated to-refer to Great Britain only.(2) The method used for arriving at consumption per head makes allowance for exports and changes of stocks and includes estimates for home produced food consumed on farms.and obtained from gardens and allotments, but no allowance is made for wastage inthe home and consumption by domestic animals.

100. During 1948-49 the average level of food consumption per headis above the pre-war level in the case of milk, fish, potatoes, vegetablesand grain products, but below for the other main food groups. the biggest decrease is in meat, of which before the war we consumed on theaverage more per head than was consumed in the United States or Canada.Owing to the effects of the war, world supplies are much reduced, and though an improvement in total fats supplies can be expected, it will belong before meat consumption can be fully restored. Measured innutrients the chief difference between the current and pre-war diet is anincrease of 13 per cent, in vegetable protein and a decrease of 24 per cent,in fat from all sources: The higher income groups have suffered a sub-&quot;stantial fall from their pre-war consumption level, but, in the case of-certain important foodstuffs, particularly liquid milk, the consumption ofthe lowest income groups has risen appreciably.101. It will be seen that between 1947-48 and 1948-49 there was anincrease in consumption per head of all classes of food other than meat.In particular liquid milk production has been largely increased, and average-consumption in 1948-49 was about 5 pints per head per week comparedwith 3.2 pints before the war. The operation of the National Milk scheme has enabled much of this increased supply to be made available for mothersand children, whose health, according to scientific opinion, is likely to benefit more from this than from any other single measure. There hasbeen a marked improvement in the supply of shell eggs, though consump-tion is still below pre-war. In 1948 the average consumption was 78per head compared with 58 in 1947 and 53 in 1946. In 1949 this figure-should rise to between 100 and 105.102. (it) Government Consumption. Government expenditure on goods and services includes purchases by the central government, the national insurance funds and the local authorities, of such things as military stores,medicines, or school equipment, and the pay of the armed forces, civilservants, teachers and doctors in the health service, etc.: these representthe direct employment of resources by the public authorities on the provi-;sion of services to the community. The public authorities also incur largeexpenditure in subsidies and in making transfer payments, e.g. pensions and insurance benefits; an account of such expenditure is given in Table XXV.Table XXVRevenue Account of Public Authorities, 1947-1949(  million)REVENUE	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949 at 1948-49 tax rates	EXPENDITURE	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949 at 1948-49 tax ratesTaxes on Income: Direct Taxes Indirect Taxes	1,620 1,830	1,770 2,105		Current Expenditure on Goods and Ser-vices       ...... Subsidies   ...... Transfer Payments: Social Security Pay-ments  ...... War Pensions, etc.	2,140 440 455 255	1,960 490 500 160	Total    ... Income from Property: Income from Pro-perty and Trading, etc.       ...... Less National Debt Interest ......	3,450 85 -545	3,875 145 -540									Total Transfers io Private Capital Account: War Damage Pay-ments and E.P.T. Refunds .......	3,290	3,110	Total Direct    Taxes   on Capital......	-460 165	-395 215			305	190					Total Current Expen-diture     ...... Surplus on Current Account......	3,595 -440	3,300 395	-Current Revenue ...	3,155	3,695		Current Expenditure plus Surplus	3,155	3,695	Capital expenditure by the Government is included along with private investment in Table XXVI. Government current expenditure on goods and services fell from  2,140 million in 1947 to  1,960 million in 1948.In 1949 such expenditure is likely to increase by about   million, chieflyon account of increased expenditure by the central government on the health-service.

103. (iii) Capital Formation. The figures of gross capital formation shownin Table XXI include several items which are not included in the figuresof fixed investment shown in Table VHF .   It is estimated that gross* There are several differences between the figures here given for capital formation andthose for fixed investment given in Table VIII. In particular the present figures include an allowance for the increase in the value of inventories and work in progress. This allowanceif however particularly vulnerable. They also include the net increase in the value of exportsalready shipped but not yet paid for, and the net additions to the overseas capital equipment of British oil companies.capital formation increased from  2,000 miUion in 1947 to  2,300 million in 1948: about half of this increase was due to higher prices. In 1949it is expected that capital formation will in real terms not be much abovethe level of 1948. The general principles underlying the investment pro-gramme for 1949 have already been discussed in paragraphs 42-49 above and a detailed account of the main individual programmes will be foundin the Appendix.104. The Problem of Inflation. The Economic Survey for 1948 gave an analysis of the problem of inflation as it then presented itself. Beforeexamining the prospect today, it will be useful to summarize the con-sequences in 1948 of the policy of disinflation which the Government haspursued. The Budget aimed at a large surplus; and in the event the totalsurplus of all public authorities reached  395 million in 1948. this represented a change of no less than  835 millions since 1947, when therewas a deficit of  440 millions.105. The Government surplus represents saving by the Government, butGovernment activities also affect the amount of private saving. Thus war damage payments and refunds of Excess Profits Tax must by and largebe treated by their recipients as sums available for capital development;such state expenditure therefore increases private saving. Some Govern-ment transactions have the opposite effect. The net effect of these various factors on the nation&apos;s saving is shown in round figures in Table XXVI.Table XXVICombined Capital Account, 1947-1949(  million)SUMS SET ASIDE	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949 at 1948-49 tax rates	CAPITAL FORMATION	1947	1948	Forecast for 1949 at 1948-49 tax ratesGovernment Saving: Current Surplus of -   Central Govern-ment ... Plus Additions to Company   Tax Reserves Plus Transfers to Private Capital Account Less Direct Taxes on Capital Current Surplus of Local Authori-ties    ...... Surplus of National Insurance Funds	-540 - 40 305 -165 15 85	295 40 190 -215 20 80		Gross Capital Form-ation at Home   ... Plus External Invest-ment foreign Bal-ance)     ......	2,000 -630	2,300 -145	Total Saving from Government Activity Depreciation Allow-ances    ....., Undistributed Profits Personal Savings ...	-340 775 370 565	410 825 500 420	c)				Total Sums Set Aside	1,370	2,155		Total Capital Form- iion         ...        ... \	1,370	2,155	(i) The figure of personal savings for 1949 is not a forecast but a balancing item.It is estimated that Government activity in 1947 resulted in a dissaving of 340 million, and in savings of  410 million in 1948. In addition to this large change of  750 millions, there have been very useful additions tosavings on the part of companies, in response to the Governmenfs appealnot to increase dividends.

106. The growth in the Government surplus had to counterbalance twochanges that tended to increase inflationary pressure during the year. Thefirst of these was the reduction in the deficit in the balance of payments.This amounted to  485 millions and was even more than had been expected.The second was the increase of  300 millions in gross investment at home.The effectiveness of the disinflationary policy can be measured by the factthat these changes took place without aggravation of the inflationary ten-tendencies which were noticeable in 1947. Indeed the increases in exports and investment would not have been possible without this policy. By itsmeans, consumption in real terms was maintained almost unchanged, whilepractically the entire expansion in national output went to increase exports and investment.107. The restraint imposed upon consumption has shown itself iu a numberof ways. There has been a check to hasty and extravagant expenditure;there is a wider variety of goods on sale; stocks have improved and thereare fewer shortages; it has been possible to relax the rationing of someconsumer goods without fear Of an uncontrollable increase in demand ; andthere has in general been an increasingly competitive temper both amongstbuyers and sellers.108. But disinflation has not gone very far. There have been some impor-tant price reductions: but at the present stage, the abandonment of pricecontrols would almost certainly lead to higher prices for essential goods.There are signs of a lessening in the pressure of demand for labour; butthis has not been such as to lead to the greater mobility of labour betweenindustries that was hoped for. The Economic Survey for 1948 allowed for450,000 unemployed at the end of the year. In the event unemployment inGreat Britain did not rise above 330,000; though now slightly higher thanin the latter part of 1947, it amounts to little more than one and a half percent, of the total industrial population, and the bulk of the unemployed are either elderly or infirm persons, or persons transferring to new jobs. Increasedconsumer resistance in certain fields was responsible for small local redundancies-dancies, chiefly during the first half of the year. In most of the areas affectedthese were quickly re-absorbed into employment. Unemployment at theend of 1948 was still far below what in the past was considered the prac-ticable minimum. The Development Areas and some other districts are ofcourse exceptions, and the problem of securing more work for them continuesto be tackled by the special methods which have proved their value in thelast three years.109. During 1948 the index of weekly wage rates (based on June 1947 as100) increased by four points, two of them in the first three months. Thecorresponding increase for the whole of 1947 was about four points, ofwhich three represented the rise in the last half of the year. These increases in 1948 do not compare unfavourably with the increase in productivity thattook place. When wage movements are under some voluntary restraint they provide somewhat uncertain evidence about the inflationary situation. Theslower rate of increase in the months from April, 1948, compared with theearly part of the year, must be attributed in large part to the favourable response to the Government^ appeal for restraint in wage negotiations, andto the relative stability of retail prices and the success of the measure to restrict the increase in distributed profits.110. In. 1949 we have to deal with a further stage in the problem of inflation. It is still necessary to restrain home demand so that more goodswill be available for export. We expect this year to be able to reduce oue independence on assistance from abroad and to eliminate the balance of pay-ments deficit of 1948. This change, welcome as it will be, will have inflationaryeffects which will have to be offset. In addition, we must try to secure some further moderate easing of the pressure of demand.111. The national income, from which must be found the resources forthe increase in exports, for Government expenditure, for investment andfor home consumption, is not likely to increase so much this year as last.In considering whether the inflationary pressure is likely to increase or decrease, it is convenient to ask whether enough purchasing power will beheld back by the savings of the Goveriunent and the public to pay for the investment programme, or whether an attempt to buy more than is availablewill maintain the pressure on prices.112. The programme for home investment in fixed capital is not, muchgreater than what was achieved last year, but continued restraint in the pro-vision of credit is desirable if this programme is not to be exceeded. Butthe figures are uncertain, and allowance must be made for the fact that prices at the beginning of 1949 are higher than the average of 1948, and for someincreases in stocks (including goods exported but not yet paid for). A small increase in total investment in 1949 over 1948 is therefore to be expected.

113. It will continue to be difficult to save enough to offset this total. Thechange in the foreign balance as shown in Table XXVI, will increase theneed for savings at home. On the other hand, there will be an automaticincrease in the depreciation allowed to industry as old plant is replaced athigher prices. And the continuance of voluntary restraint on dividends-should lead to some increase in undistributed profits. Thus on balance,the total of personal savings and Government surplus needed to prevent any increase in inflationary pressure may not be greater than it was last year.114. It is not, of course, possible to anticipate the Budget in any way.But the figures in Table XXV are intended to illustrate in very rough formthe problem of inflation in 1949 as it appears from the forecasts and pro-grammes of this Survey. In order to draw up the Table, it has been assumed that present policies of expenditure and taxation remain unchanged.As pointed out in paragraph 102, expenditure would be  [ ] m. higherthan in 1948 ; but the large increase in national income would also mean that present tax rates would produce a higher revenue.115. The surplus on current account shown in Table XXV is brought intothe national capital account in Table XXVI and thus we reach the figureof personal savings which would be required, on the assumptions made, ifthe planned level of investment is to be financed without inflation. any changes in expenditure or taxation would, of course, involve an adjustment in this figure. How far this or, indeed, any particular figure would inpractice be realised is a matter of judgment and comparisons with past yearsmay be misleading. In 1948 the total demand on the national resources was greater than could be met and some part of the saving was the result of aninflationary process still at work. But personal savings in 1948 were only about 5% per cent, of personal incomes after paying taxes, and this proportionwas saved in 1938, which was not an inflationary year.116. The figures given in the Tables XXV and XXVI refer to calendaryears, while the fiscal year runs from April to March. To assist study of the budgetary problem, Table XXVII shows approximate figures for thecurrent account of the central government for the corresponding fiscal years.Table XXVIIRevenue Account of the Central Government for fiscal years1948-49 and 1949-50(  million)REVENUE	1948-49	Forecast for 1949-50 at 1948-49 tax rates	EXPENDITURE	1948-49	Forecast for 1949-50 at 1948-49-tax-ratesDirect Taxes on Income Direct Taxes on Capital Indirect Taxes   ...... Income   from   Property less National Debt In-terest   .........	1,630 235 1,660 -430		Current Expenditure on Goods and Services ... Subsidies......... Social Security and other Personal Transfers ... Transfers to Other Pub-lic Authorities Transfers to Private Capital Account (War Damage Payments and E.P.T. Refunds)	1,380 500 330 430 145	- -			Total Current Expends ture   ..... Surplus.........	2,785 310	Current Revenue	3,095		Current Expenditure plus Surplus       ......	3,095	117. This discussion makes it clear that the evils of inflation can be avoidedonly through the cO-operation of the Government and the nation as a whole.The Government is trying to keep down prices by subsidies on essential goods and by direct control. It is also saving through a Budget surplus.Similarly, employers and employees must exercise restraint on prices, divi-dends and wages; and everyone must save through the National SavingsMovement or in other ways. These are the necessary conditions for economic and social stability.

PART iii the Tasks for 1949118. In Part II have been set out, with as much precision as is possible ina few pages, the Governmenfs economic programmes and estimates for1949. As this detailed account has shown, the year should be one of steady progress in 6very field, consolidating the great advances of 1948, and takingus a further stage towards the economic independence and settled prosperitywe seek. Despite the distance we have travelled we are still to-day dependentfor many vital supplies on the generous gifts and loans we have receivedfrom the United States and Canada. Above all else in 1949 therefore wemust so conduct our affairs that we can do without such help as soon aspossible. To do this the full co-operation and the steady effort of every one-of us, in one sphere of action or in another, will be needed. In this final Partare described in general terms the endeavours each must make if the nationis to continue in 1949 its steady progress towards its goal of economicindependence and when this has been attained a better standard of living.(a) Targets for Production and Exports119. First we must see that we reach the production arid export targets forthe year. These have already been set out in Part II, but they are worthrepeating:(i) Coal. We must continue to expand the output and export of coal.We must strive to win 220 million tons from the mines and the open-cast workings.(ii) Steel. We must endeavour to secure all the materials needed to employ our steel making capacity to its fullest extent and to make afurther advance on the achievements of the past year to a total outputof 15 -15  million ingot tons.(iii) Textiles. Output of all classes of textiles must continue to rise andwe must try to attain the production targets set out in Part II.(iv) Agriculture. The farming community must make every endeavourto bring to a successful issue the next stage of the agricultural expansion programme and to achieve the output and acreages which have been set as the objectives for the year.fy) Exports. We must continue to maintain the volume of our exportsat a high level and ensure that we do not fall short of the end yeartargets set out in Table IX. Above all it is imperative that we should increase as rapidly as we can our exports to Canada and to the UnitedStates.120. The call for special effort is not confined to those directly concerned&quot;with these targets-to workers and management in the mines, steel works,textile factories, and export industries, and to the farming community. These,and those who can join them, and those who can help by producing themachinery and the materials they require have a special responsibility. Butthere are also obligations of a more general kind on all of us, whether or not we are directly concerned with these vital parts of the economic machine:to increase productivity and to assist the maintenance of financial stability.These are discussed in the two following sections.(b) The Need for Greater Productivity121. There are good reasons why productivity should now come to the forefront of economic problems. The post-war reconstruction of Britishproduction has involved two processes: an effort to increase peace-timeoutput as a whole and a change in the pattern of that output. The secondprocess has meant increasing or restoring the output of coal, steel, textiles,agriculture and export manufacture to meet the profound change in thecountry&apos;s post-war position. It is essentially a job of shifting resources fromone use to another. The greater part of this, if not the harder part, has been achieved except for the dollar problem. The first process, that of increasingoutput generally, has also passed its first stage, that of absorbing and organis-ing for peace-time production the masses of men and resources released from war-time uses. The labour has been recruited, working stocks have been built up, crippling shortages of particular materials and components havebeen largely overcome. Sometime during the last twelve or eighteen monthswe passed from the stage of reconstruction with its spectacular increases of output into the period of normal progress. This progress, with a stablelabour force and with capital fully employed and new investment necessarilylimited, can only come from increased productivity.

122. Productivity is a very general term which it is difficult to define in anexact and convenient sense. Essentially what we mean by it for practical purposes is output per man-hour. * By output we mean not only the produc-* When we try to measure productivity in industry, and when the term is used in calcu-lations of the national income, rather different definitions have to be used as explained in thefootnote to paragraph 96.tion of material things in the factory and the mine but the provision of services of all kinds as well (such as transport or attention in shops), andnot only the amount of output but also its quality. When we say, forexample, that productivity in a factory has increased between one year andanother, we mean that more or better goods were produced in it for eachman-hour worked in the second year than in the first. Productivity in this sense can be increased either as a result of more and better capital equipment or as a result of improvements in efficiency unaccompanied by big changesin the plant used.  Both ways should contribute in 1949 and in later years.123. During the period ahead investment in the manufacturing industries will be limited by the need to export much of the plant and machinery weproduce, by the claims of basic services and by the danger of inflation. Wecannot hope to obtain large annual increases in productivity by increasedcapital per head in manufactures.. But new investment should contributeat least as much as pre-war; the suitability of capital equipment to modernproductive methods should improve in the normal process of replacement;and there should be ho real difficulty in carrying out the small-scale invest-ment often required by improvements in factory organisation which leadto important increases in productivity. Moreover, a good deal of post-warinvestment has yet to bear fruit in greater current output.124. The main source of greater productivity, to which we must now look,must be the development of efficiency by greater skill, energy and adaptability.Careful technical studies in individual factories have demonstrated that output per man-hour can be greatly increased by the rearrangement of plant,by the better sub-division of jobs, both of labour and management, bythe proper organisation of the flow of materials and similar managerialaction, as well, of course, as by improvement in design and the fuller applica-tion of our scientific knowledge. If we could bring the less efficient uptowards the level of the best, notable increases in productivity could besecured.125. In seeking these ends all have their parts to play. government can do much to help. It directly finances a great deal of research andassists many bodies which promote the use in industry of scientifictechniques and discoveries; It assists the training of management through such bodies as the British Institute of Management, and it provides directhelp to those who seek it in a number of ways. It has a measure ofresponsibility for the supply of imported raw materials. It seeks to administer the economic controls that are necessary in the ways that are least costly,that least distract the energies of management and least hamper the progressof efficient firms. Much has been done in the past year and every further opportunity will be taken to modify or remove controls whenever this canbe done without too great a risk of deflecting our productive resources from the most essential purposes.126. What Government can do is mostly indirect. The problem is primarily one for industry and within industry for management. The bestpractice in this country is as good as that of any other, but prewar diffi-culties developed in some sections of British industry the habit of seeking:stability and security rather than progress. This has retarded the study and &quot;adoption of the best methods. In our present economic position this attitude is a real danger to the national welfare. Our recovery will never be complete unless we can develop a keen and adventurous spirit in management.127. Responsibility for improving production technique does not restsolely on management. Willingness on the part of the workers to co-operate in introducing improvements is essential, and there is no reason, particularlyin conditions of full employment, why workers should view such changeswith suspicion. Collaboration by the workers is most likely to be forth-coming where the human relationships in the industry are good and wherethere are arrangements for joint consultation through which proposed changes can be explained and discussed beforehand so that the need forthem is fully accepted by all concerned. A forward-looking partnershipof this kind will do more to achieve the increase in production necessaryfor our economic progress than increases in physical effort or in hoursvof work.

128. There are encouraging signs that progressive views on these matters are spreading. The leaders of both sides in industry are already activelysupporting the drive for higher productivity, as instanced by their support for the Anglo-American Council on, Productivity and by the campaignundertaken by the Trades Union Congress. But this good work is not amatter for the leaders only: it is work in which all can join. The fruitsof its success will be found not only in the simple form of more and cheaperfood, and clothes and coal, more houses and schools, and so on, but in the fulfilment of our great general objective, the early restoration of our country&apos;s economic independence and prosperity.(c) The Need for Stability129. The need to increase productivity is clear and fundamental. Butthere is also another general need which all can help to meet: financial stability, the avoidance of inflation. We must in 1949 increase our exports and maintain a large investment programme, and devote more sourcesto our defence and our social services. This means that there is likely tobe, throughout the year, a strong demand for labour which gives rise tothe danger of inflation and instability.130. When there is a strong pressure of demand, there is pressure also for money wages and salaries and profits to rise. This in turns tends toraise prices, and the rise in prices stimulates demands for further increases in incomes. For the community as a whole increases in money incomesdo not mean an increase in the amounts of goods and services we can getfor an increase in the amounts of goods and services we can get for ourmoney. We cannot invest or consume more than we produce (or are given or borrow as a result of overseas transactions). Increases in the amount ofmoney that changes hands will not increase this total. If any one person or class gets more, it must be at the expense of others and if an inflationaryspiral develops, it is those who receive fixed incomes (pensioners, personsliving on their savings and the like) who suffer. While others gain at theirexpense, all would agree that such a gain is certainly unjust.131. Moreover an inflation of money incomes actually endangers pro-duction and trade. By raising costs it hinders exports, and especially exportsto the strongly competitive hard-currency markets where increased salesare, for reasons already explained, vital. At home it strains the controlsdesigned to secure &quot;fair shares&quot; of scarce essential goods, and gives the black market operator the chance he seeks. Above all a situation in whichthere is &quot;a lot of money about&quot; and profits are easy to come by, lessensinitiative and slackens the incentive to increase productivity.132. These are familiar arguments. They have been set out in two white papers issued by the Government, the &quot;Statement of the Economic Con-sideration affecting Relations between Employer and Worker&quot; published in January 1947 (Cmd. 7018) and in the Prime Minister^ &quot;Statement on personal Incomes Costs and Prices&quot; made in February 1948 (Cmd. 7321)reprinted in the last Economic Survey. The appeal for restraint made onthese occasions has met with a good response. The arguments on whichit was based still hold, and the Government now asks for this restraint tobe continued. For its part the Government will continue to take all themeasures within its power to prevent inflation: but success depends moston the restraint and understanding of us all in our daily life as citizens.133. Inflation can be caused if we selfishly or short-sightedly, pursuesectional interests in matters connected with prices, profits or wages. Itcan also be caused if too little is saved and too much is spent on current consumption. A large investment programme is vital if we are to have theindustrial equipment we need to regain a stable, independent and prosperousposition in the post-war world, and if we are to have the houses, schools,roads and so on essential to back up the industrial effort. This invest-iment must be financed and this can only be done without inflation ifthe community sets aside adequate sums from its current income. If wedo not do so, if we attempt to spend too much of our income on con-sumption goods and services, their prices will be forced up and inflationmay follow. It could be avoided only by releasing men and materials forthe production of these goods and services. This could be done in two ways only. We could cut down on investment. This, besides being diffi-cult or organise in the short run, would set back our long term recoveryprogrammes. We could reduce exports. But this would mean the abandon-ment of our hopes of paying our own way when the temporary help weare now receiving comes to an end. In the long run it could lead only toreduced imports, unemployment and a lowered standard of living.

134. A high level of savings is therefore imperative if we are to reconcile-recovery and stability. To get these savings the thrift and understanding ofthe general public and of the business community are quite as important as.the decisions of the Government. By creating a Budget surplus the Govern-ment can provide part of the sums required to finance investment withoutinflation. But this entails high taxation and is very much a second best to the savings voluntarily made by the private citizen or by companies.135. For these reasons the Government last year appealed to industry forrestraint in the distribution of dividends and asked firms to keep back, as-reserves to finance re-equipment, funds which might otherwise have gone toincrease consumption. This restraint was asked for because the Government:felt that the national interest outweighed the natural desire of industry to dis-tribute increasing profits to its shareholders. These concerned have respondedwell- to the appeal as the figures in Part II show, but the position is not yetsecure and the same appeal is now repeated for the present year.136. The personal savings of the private citizen, whatever the form they take, are another vital element in the total provision for investment. In totalthey fell in 1948 well below the figure for 1947. But the higher figures of thelatter years were largely due perhaps to the fact that the consumer couldnot then find the goods he wished to buy. In 1948 he could get more of what he wanted in the shops. The reduction in the amount he saved was thuspartly due to a decline of involuntary rather than voluntary savings. now that most of the war-time shortages of household goods have been worked,off, the Government appeals to all to increase their savings in 1949, and to.join whole-heartedly in the efforts of the National Savings Movement.137. If, in these ways, incomes can be kept at a steady level and savings can-be matched with investment, financial stability can be maintained, prices can.remain reasonably level, and the underlying conditions for steady economic progress can be assured.(d) The Need for International Co-operation138. If in 1949 we can reach our production and export targets, improve^productivity and maintain financial stability, we shall have met the mostvital needs of our own immediate economic problem. But the Britishproblem is part only of a problem that affects the economic life of large areas of the world, and our tasks must be seen in the framework of the-many kinds of international effort that are being made to solve this world-wide crisis.139. The most striking evidence of our dependence upon internationalsolutions lies in our receipt of Aid from the United States under the Euro-pean Recovery Programme and of credits from Canada. As has alreadybeen pointed out, all the forecasts and the programmes for 1949 described in this Survey are based upon the assumption that Aid on a sufficient scaleis accorded to us. Without the ample and generous assistance we are being given by the American people our condition to-day would be very grave. Itis because this assistance is temporary, and because we are determined to beable quickly to do without it that our forward plans are directed primarily to&apos;solving the problem of the dollar deficit, and that other aims take second place. The broad strategy of these plans has been described at length in theLong Term Programme submitted to the Organisation for european economic Co-operation (Cmd. 7572) and the whole of this Survey can beconsidered as a detailed account of one stage of that programme.140. The British people are not alone in receiving gifts and loans from theNew World. The eighteen other countries of O.E.E.C. are being assisted,and the whole aid programme is based upon the conception of a commonEuropean effort to solve a common European problem by the pursuit ofco-operative economic policies. In this endeavour this country is joiningwhole-heartedly: The prosperity of Europe is a vital interest to us, andthe creation of O.E.E.C. to foster joint action has enabled us to continue with renewed energy the economic co-operation which has continued ever since the end of the war. In 1949 the United Kingdom will go on with this work. In particular we shall be taking our full share in the work of reconcil-ing and improving the Long Term Programmes which the member nations of O.E.E.C. will be continuing in Paris. Our own programme is open to change in the.light of this work as is the programme of every other member.This is the first time that anything of this kind has been attempted in timeof peace between independent nations.   It must not fail.

141. Not only must we work with the other nations of Europe (both in-O.E.E.C. and through the United Nations), but we must, of course, furtherdevelop our co-operation with the countries of the Commonwealth. Wehave special responsibilities towards the Colonies. His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment is responsible for the welfare of their peoples, and increased exportsof food and raw materials produced in the Colonies have a great part toplay in world recovery. The development of these territories requires thesupply of large quantities of capital goods and of consumer goods. Colonialagriculture must be developed both to provide more food for the Colonialpeoples themselves, and to provide more crops for the world market. Allthese needs compete with other claims on our resources. To ensure thatthe right balance is kept the Government is seeking to establish a closerrelationship between economic planning in the Colonies and the UnitedKingdom.142. The closest co-operation in economic matters is also needed with theindependent nations of the Commonwealth. This goes beyond the great tradeconnections which together account for a high proportion of our export and import trade, to the many joint discussions on the future economic develop-ments needed for the stability and prosperity of the whole Commonwealth.The balance of payments between Canada and the rest of the Commonwealth,including ourselves, presents a particularly difficult problem. These frankand intimate contacts between the independent partners of the Commonwealthare being constantly developed and will play an increasing part in the evolution of our own recovery plans in 1949.143. This Survey has sought to set out plainly the prospects, good and bad,and the tasks, difficult as they are, which face the British people and their government in 1949. If this account is correct, and we can achieve the tasks described, we should in the present year consolidate the gains of1948, and take a firm step forward towards the paramount objective ofeconomic independence. There is likely to be no rapid change of the kindwe saw in 1947 and 1948. The policies we must follow are no longer the transition policies of re-adjustment from time of war or the improvisationsof crisis: they are becoming rather the steady policies of long term progress.With the continued understanding and co-operation of the whole community:Xhe Government are confident that these policies can succeed.

CAPITAL INVESTMENT IN 1949CONTENTSParagraphs PageIntroductory......     ...     ............     1-summary of Estimated Investment in Principal Sectors      2A. Fuel and PowerCoal     ..................... 3-5Hard Coke     .................. 6-7Electricity...............      ... 8-9Gas      ......      ............... 10-13Petroleum       ......      ...      ...      ...... 14-16B. Transport and CommunicationsRailways..................      ... 17-18Roads   ..................... 19-21Road Vehicles............      ...      ... 22-24Shipbuilding    ............      ...      ... 25-27Ports and Inland Waterways ...      ...      ...      ... 28-31Civil Aviation......      ............ 32-34Post Office      .........      ......... 35-36C. Agriculture, Fisheries and ForestryAgriculture and Fisheries     ...      ...      ......    37-42Forestry...............      ......    43-44D. Industry-Iron and Steel..................    45-46Other Industry..................    47-52E. Social ServicesHousing..................... 53-59Education       ...............      ... 60-65Health Services.................. 66-70Water and Sewerage............... 71-72Services administered by Home Departments      ... 73-74British Broadcasting Corporation    ......      ... 75-77F. Defence and Public AdministrationService Departments...............    78-80Ministry of Supply    ...............      81Government Building......      .........    82-85G. Investment in Northern Ireland    .........      861. IntroductoryThe&quot; main factors governing the size and distribution of investment in 1949have been discussed in paragraphs 42 to 49 of the Survey. The followingnotes give a brief account of the progress achieved in 1948 and the pro-grammes and prospects for 1949 in the principal sectors of gross fixed invest-ment. This review is not intended to be exhaustive. In general it relatesonly to those categories of investment which can be clearly distinguished andfor which it has been possible to make fairly detailed estimates. As was explained in paragraph 48 of the Survey there lies outside this field a wide range of miscellaneous investment both in building and equipment for whichdetailed estimates cannot at present be usefully attempted. This includeswork required for such varied purposes as hotels, warehouses, shops, offices and commercial buildings and for equipment used in them as well asinnumerable minor works of adaptation, and extensions which proceed con-tinuously. In 1949 the scale of investment in this field is not expected to change appreciably from the global estimate for 1948 which is given in the survey.2. The following table summarises the estimates of gross fixed investment for 1949 which is envisaged for the principal categories dealt with in this appendix. The comparable figures for the two preceding years are given for purpose of comparison.APPENDIX

Transport and Communications6. Railways............7. Roads   ...............8.*Road vehicles (other than private cars)9. Shipbuilding   -......10. Ports and Inland Waterways......11. Civil Aviation............12. Post Office      ............Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry13.*Agriculture and Fisheries (including arterialwatercourses)...............14.tForestry...............D. IndustryIS. Iron and Steel16.*Other IndustrySocial Services. 17. New housing and maintenance18. Education       .........19. Health............20. Water and Sewerage  ......21. Home Departments   ......22. B.B.C.   ...     .........Defence and Public Administration23.*Service Departments  ...24. Ministry of Supply25. Government building ...* Includes expenditure in Northern Ireland,t See footnote to para. 14.% Includes expenditure in Northern Ireland amounting to:( Million)1947 194S9 101947	1948	1949&apos;16	25	283	5	675	97	12728	32	377	9	24129	168	222133	161	[    ]46	43	5275	83	r 64]70	77	6210	11	1620	18	[ 25]32	37	42386	430	[    168	85	921	1	169	86	9325	32	49345	380	425370	412	474446	468	42114	28	4713	17	[ 19]12	18	292	2	[ 4]-	A	2487J	5341	[522]J18	16	[ 22]12	15	2017	23	2347	54	651949131947	1948	19498-1*	13-5	14 05-5	60	7-0 	0-8	2-80-3	0-7	1-813-9	21 0	25-62-5	4-3	2-01. Coal(  Million)Deep-mined coalrviiuorj-c /Development and reconstructioncollieries \Repiacenient of plant    ......New coal preparation plant    ......     ...Pithead baths and canteens     .........Total.........Opencast coal...............* Includes (1947) new coal preparation plant.3. Most of the 1948 development and reconstruction expenditure ( 13 million) was on short term schemes designed to maintain production or to yield immediate increases in output. Some  9 million out of the  14 million to be invested under this head in 1949 will likewise be on small schemessuch as mechanization at the coal face, reorganization of haulage, or thedevelopment of drift mining. A further t\\ million will be on larger schemes,coming to fruition before 1952, e.g. a concentration scheme at Williamsthorpe,a new shaft at Calverton and underground locomotive haulage at YorkshireMain. The balance ( 3  million) covers expenditure on major reconstruc-tion, e.g. a new sinking at Rothes, a new shaft for skip winding and a newsurface lay-out at the Bradford pit (Lancashire) and a new colliery atNantgarw (South Wales). Projects of this kind, which in themselves will increase output and productivity, will eventually lead to reduced costs bypermitting the abandonment of high-cost collieries or seams.Summary(  Million)A. Fuel and power. Coal     ................2. Hard Coke      .............3. Electricity       .........4. Gas      ................5. Petroleum       .............

4. The expenditure on coal preparation plant will benefit consumers athome and will facilitate sales abroad. The investment in pithead baths andcanteens is essential to improve working conditions and make the industrymore attractive.5. The need for capital investment in opencast coal mining is now declining,although this does not imply a falling output in the next two years.2. Hard Coke( Million)1947 1948 19493-5 4 1 6-56. The growing scale of activity in heavy industry, particularly iron and:steel and heavy chemicals, is making increasing demands on the availablecoke oven capacity: On the other hand the total capacity of the coke ovenshas changed very little during the past two years since much of the new plant,which has been installed, has merely replaced obsolete plant that was in-capable of continued operation. As a result supplies of hard coke are insufficient to satisfy the demands of all consumers.. 7. In view of the projected increases in the output of the steel and chemical industries over the next four years, additional coke oven capacity is urgently needed. The problem of extending capacity to meet the full requirements is at present under review.3. ElectricityBritish Electricity AuthorityValue   Million	1947	1948	1949Generation        .........	......     21-5	32-5	58-0Main Transmission      ......	2-8	3-3	3-5Distribution      .........	210	230	24-2Maintenance and Repair	......     250	27-0	290	70-3	85-8	114&apos;78. The total cost of the new power stations which are under construction-or have already reached the stage of detailed planning is estimated to beabout  550 million at present prices. This vast programme will involve a greatexpansion in the capacity of the industries which manufacture electricity generating plant. The rate of investment set out in the White Paper on capital investment in 1948 (Cmd. 7268) was based on too optimistic an assessment of the speed with which this could be done and did not take fully into account the need to relate deliveries of plant to the completion of build-ing and civil engineering work to receive it. The figures have been revised and the maximum capacity which it is now hoped to make available and theestimated peak demand are given in the table below. Even these figuresmust be treated with considerable reserve, since they represent an effort bythe industries concerned far above anything ever achieved previously. Forexample, the new commissioning planned for 1951 amounts to 1,500 MW,which is twice the highest level ever achieved before the war and nearly three times the level reached last year.Megawatts	Capacity available at peak		Peak demand in severe winter weather*	Gap	Assuming 15% out of service	Assuming 10% out of service		1949-50... 1950-51...... 1951-52... 1952-53......	10,400 11,400 12,800 13,900	11,000 12,000 13,400 14,600	12,500 13,300 14,100 14,900	1,500-2,100 1,200-1,900 700-1,300 300-1,000* It may be estimated that the difference between severe and normal winter weather is approximately 1,000 MW and the difference made by load spreading a reduction of demand-of about 750 MW.

North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board(  Million)1947 1948 19495 &quot;11 129. This programme provides for the installation of 455 megawatts of generating capacity between 1948 and 1953, most of the work in 1948 beingpreparatory. During 1949 it is expected that 51 megawatts of capacity willbe installed. The expenditure involved in 1949 is  12 nnllion, of which  9million is for hydro-electric schemes,  2 million for main transmission lines and  1 million for distribution.The programme is part only of a longer term scheme for hydro-electricdevelopment but the later stages are unlikely to make any significant call on resources before 1952.4. Gas(  Million)1947        1948        1949Extensions and Renewals       ............     22 26 31Repairs and Maintenance       ......      ......       6 6 628 32 3710. During 1948 the gas industry has been mainly occupied in overtakingthe arrears of maintenance, repairs and renewals which had accumulatedduring the war. The increase in manufacturing capacity has been of theorder of only 3 per cent, to 4 per cent.11. Approximately one quarter of the investment for 1949 will be on distri-bution; some extension of distribution systems by mterlinking mains willtake place in 1949 and this will further develop in succeeding years, since itis often less economical to increase the capacity of small undertakings than to supply them with gas from larger plants.12. In view of the heavy demands on plant manufacturing capacity, the gas industry cannot undertake all the work it is desirable to do. For thenext few years, therefore, much plant will have to be used which would normally be scrapped or reconstructed, and in some areas where demand hasincreased substantially, shortages are inevitable.13. In general the industry has no reserve capacity and the growth of demand will make it necessary to increase the scale of investment as soon asmanufacturing capacity is available.5. Petroleum(  Million)	1947	1948	1949In U.K.............	.........       7	9	24Overseas............	..........     66	83	91	73	92	11514. The 1949 Investment Programme for the petroleum industry is part ofthe large-scale plan to increase the production of crude oil by British con-trolled companies from 53 million tons in 1947 to approximately double that amount in 1953 and to increase the throughput of U.K. refineries to nearly20 million tons by the latter part of 1952. Capacity of refineries overseaswill be increased by over 40 per cent.15. The additional refined products will reduce very greatly the drain ondollar resources made by current petroleum demands and will enable therequirements of home industry, and ultimately of the domestic consumer, tobe more freely met. The expansion within the United Kingdom of therefining industry, on which work has already started on four major schemes,will also permit the development of an important petroleum-chemical industry.16. About half the total investment will be on the expansion of production,pipeline and refinery capacity, including the building of refineries in theUnited Kingdom. The remainder covers the maintenance of existingproduction and installations.

	1947	1948	1949-Permanent way, works and structures ...	44	52	I ]Rolling stock     ............	75	90	[  1New civil engineering works    ......	-.*&apos;-&apos; 7	10	[  other repairs and renewals (including			war damage repairs).........	7	9	i  1Total......	133	161	[ !Locomotives		Number		409	420	500Carriages.........     ......	1,198	1,328	2,100Wagons   ...     ...     ...     ......	31,275	41,025	27,00017. The capital invested in the railway system is so large that considerable^investment is necessary each year simply to make good normal depreciation.-Hence the greater part of the expenditure is on repairs and renewals, and only a small proportion is on additions or improvements. In i948 restric-tions on capital investment limited both the construction of railway rolling stock and replacement of tracks. Efforts had, therefore, to be concentrated on making the best use of existing equipment by additional repair work.Arrears of track renewal were overtaken only to the extent necessary forsafety. Nevertheless some improvements were made in running bothpassenger and goods trains, though the shortage of passenger carriages was-acute.18. In order to make resources, notably steel, available for other expandinginvestment programmes which contribute more directly to the balance ofpayments, it has been decided that as a temporary measure the railways&apos;replacement programme should be kept at a restricted level. Track renewalwill continue in 1949 at approximately the level of 1948 ; existing restrictionson general building and maintenance work will have to continue for a further year, particularly where steel and timber in large quantities are called for.7. Roads(  Million)1947 194% 1949Improvement of trunk roads   ......... 1-0 1*4 2*3Improvement of classified roads       ...      ... 1-9 3-2 4-5Maintenance of all roads       ......... 43-5 38-0 44-9Total ...     ...     ....... 46-4 42-6 51-719. Road maintenance in 1948 was restricted in order to release labour for agriculture, rural housing and other essential work, the volume of maintenancebeing only about 60 per cent, of the 1936-39 average. If this level of main-tenance were continued, road surfaces might deteriorate to such an extent that the ultimate cost of essential repairs would be disproportionately high.The volume of maintenance work in 1949 will, therefore, be increased to between 70 per cent, and 75 per cent, of the 1936-39 average, and will be concentrated on the most important roads. In agricultural areas, the pro-gramme will be arranged in such a manner as not to interfere with the supplyof labour for agriculture.20. Last year work on road improvements was either reduced or postponedto save labour and materials. In 1949 there will be only a modest increase and schemes which would require substantial amounts of steel will continueto be postponed as long as possible. The works to be carried out will fall into the following categories : (1) urgent structural repairs e.g. bridge reconstruction,(2) works which must precede the rebuilding of blitzed areas,(3) improvements in industrial areas, which are likely to make a markedcontribution to production,(4) comparatively small works which will add greatly to road safety,(5) improvements which can be economically combined with essentialmaintenance work.21. In areas of serious unemployment, however, including most of theCrofter Counties of Scotland, a number of schemes will be carried out which,though very desirable on traffic grounds, could otherwise have been post-poned for a year or two; they will not involve any significant demand omsteel, timber or cement.6. Railways(  Million)

8. Road Vehicles(excluding private cars)Public Service Passenger VehiclesValue   Millions1947 1948 194919 33 2922. The number of road passengers has increased since 1938, at a greaterrate than the number of pubhc service vehicles. In Cmd. 7268 it was contem-plated that the number of pubhc service vehicles of all kinds delivered to thehome market should be reduced during 1948 to 6,000. Difficulties in adjust-ing production, which must be a gradual process and, initially, in findingexport markets have meant, however, that the intake was over 8,000, anumber of these being light single deckers.23. Production for home use will have to be restricted in 1949 in theinterests of other more important investment programmes and of exports.The minimum demands for trolley-buses and double-decker buses will, how-ever, be met in order to remedy existing shortages of these vehicles in several large cities, especially London, where services are seriously handicapped bythe shortage of heavy vehicles. It is proposed, therefore, that home invest-ment in 1949 should be approximately as follows:  Trolley buses       ..&apos;.............        450Double-decker buses       .........      ...      4,250Single-decker buses        ............      3,0007,700Goods Vehicles for Road HaulageValue   Millions1947 1948 194956 50 3524. As with public service vehicles, and for the same reasons, the numberof goods vehicles supplied to the home market in 1948 (8,500) exceeded thenumber proposed in Cmd. 7268 (50,000) although it represents a substantial reduction on the figure for 1947 (nearly 100,000). Annual requirementssimply to refresh the pre-war fleet amount to 70,000 and it is estimated that120,000 vehicles per year would be required to restore the fleet to its pre-warstandard. Although the present fleet of about 700,000 is about 180,000greater than before the war and 250,000 greater than in 1945, a considerable part of the increase consists of ex-service vehicles which are well-worn, costlyto run and wasteful of petrol, and over the whole fleet the average age of the vehicles is considerably above pre-war. Nevertheless, since curtailment here will have less serious consequences than in some other sectors of investment, itis necessary that a further reduction in the number of vehicles taken into thehome market during 1949 towards the figure of 50,000 should be effected.9. Shipbuilding(Vessels of 100 gross tons and over)Dry Cargo and Passenger VesselsTankers............Others............	1947	1948	1949		&apos;000 gross tons			Completions	/Home	604	635	509V Overseas   ...	187	335	220/Home	103	144	17210verseas   ...	17	59	149/Home	9	25	27\ Overseas   ...	29	23	23	949	1,221	1,100Value   MillionHomeNew Construction. *See Note 1Repairs.   *See Note 2......OverseasNew Construction and Repairs1947	1948	194954	61	5171	71	6827	43	35* Note 1: The value of vessels of less than 100 gross tons built each year is about  1 million.*Note 2: The values given above for repairs include all repairs, not only those chargeable to capital account. The amounts chargeable to capital account as home investment are estimated as follows:1947     .........      15 million1948     .........      15    ,,1949     .........      10    .

25. The volume and value of total deliveries in 1948 were well up toexpectations and exceeded the 1947 figure owing to the number of vessels which were delayed in the fitting-out stage during 1947 and completed in1948 when the supply of component parts became easier. One-third of thetoanage completed in 1948 was sold abroad and two-thirds was for Britishowners.26. In 1949 production will continue to be limited by the amount of steelavailable. The gross tonnage of ships to be completed in the year, excludingthose of less than 100 tons, is estimated to be 1,100,000 tons, valued at  81million. As in 1948, two-thirds of the tonnage, 700,000 tons valued at 51 million,&apos; is expected to be for British owners. Of this, it is estimatedthat 500,000 tons will be dry cargo and passenger vessels and 170,000 tonstankers, with the balance made up principally of trawlers and whaling ships.Of the dry cargo and passenger vessels to be completed in 1949 for Britishowners some 25,000 tons will be of vessels under 1,600 tons or not oceangoing, whilst 250,000 tons will replace tonnage going out of commissionthrough loss or obsolescence. The net addition to the dry cargo fleet by theend of the year will thus be about 235,000 tons.27. The British tanker fleet at 3,500,000 gross tons is larger than it was in1939 but even so American tankers equivalent to 300,000 gross tons have tobe chartered at a cost of $36 million per annum. The increase in the oiltrade is expected to exceed the prospective increase in the capacity of the tanker fleet on the present programme of building and it may be difficultto fill the gap by chartering. For this reason, special attention will continueto be given to the tanker construction programme and an increasing proportionof tonnage building in British yards will be devoted to tankers.10. Ports and Inland Waterways&apos; (  Million)	1947	1948	1949Ports:-			Building and civil engineering......	... &apos;    7-8	8-9	12-plant and Machinery	0-5	0-6	11Total    ...	3-3	9-5	13-5Inland Waterways............	14	1-5	20Total    ......	9-7	110	15-5Ports28. In 1948 the most important work was on transit sheds at Liverpool and southampton, deep-water quays at Leith, dock junction improvement and land reclamation work at Sunderland, and oil berths at Lackenby (River Tees).Elsewhere only small works, urgent repairs and ordinary maintenance were undertaken.29. Much war damage, both to buildings and to plant, remains to be made good; the damage at London amounted to  13^ million and at Liverpool to 11 million, and Hull and Southampton lost nearly two-thirds of their shedsand warehouses. Ships are now on the average larger than pre-war andto accommodate them new dock entrances,- deeper berths and even newdocks are required.  Handling facilities also require improvement.30. Since delays at the ports mean higher costs and fewer cargoes, andmay mean a loss of foreign earnings, more work will be undertaken in 1949than in 1948, and special attention will be given to schemes which promisequick improvement in turn round.Inland Waterways31. No major improvements or developments are contemplated. Workwill consist mainly of deferred maintenance and a few small schemes whichwill allow better use to be made of existing waterways.

11. Civil Aviation(  Million)	1947	1948	1949Aircraft and ground equipment...... Building and civil engineering ...	16 0 40	14-5 3-7	[19-6] [ 5-6]Total   ......	20 0	18-2	[25-2]32. In i947 and 1948 the aircraft programme provided for the re-equip-ment of the Corporations with such types as Plymouth and Solent flying-boats) Tudors and Vikings. In 1949 Canadairs and Hermes will come into service, and in. 1950 Stratocruisers and Marathons. Production is proceed-ing on the Ambassador and the S.R.45 flying-boat. The first trial flightsof the Brabazon I and the D.H. Comet are expected to take place in 1949.33. Additions to the Corporations&apos; fleets will enable them to make a bidfor a greater share of the increased traffic which is expected, particularly on theNorth Atlantic route. There B.O.A.C.&apos;s share in 1948 was limited,chiefly by its carrying capacity, to about 20 per cent. The heavy capitaloutlay involved is attributable mainly to the need for re-equipping the Cor-porations with new types of aircraft of improved performance.34. The aerodrome construction programme in 1948 was restricted by thelimits which it was necessary to impose on the general building and civil engineering programme. In 1949 the level of investment will be raisedslightly, but the programme, both within and outside London, will be concentrated on work which is essential for maintaining international air services. The work to be done at London Airport (which was the projectmost affected by the 1948 restrictions, and where the volume of traffic atpeak hours is steadily increasing) will include runways and improved ter-minal buildings. More hangars and technical accommodation will also be built which will eventually allow maintenance work to be concentrated andso permit economies in operating costs.12. Post Office(  Million)1947        1948        1949Engineering       ..................     30 34 38Building  ......      ...............       2 3 4Total    ............     32 37 4235. The bulk of this investment is in respect of the telephone service.During the war long-term projects for dealing with the normal growth of thesystem had to be sacrificed. Although over two million telephones havebeen installed since the war representing an annual rate far above thatof any pre-war year the waiting-list of applicants has grown steadily to nearly 520,000. In 1949 the aim will be to meet the present rate of demand and so prevent an increase in the waiting list, but the rate of installationcannot be increased further without cutting down valuable exports of tele-phone exchange and other equipment. As the needs of industry, commerce and other essential users must continue to receive priority, only a small proportion of residential applicants will be able to obtain telephones.36. Building work will mainly be concerned with the rebuilding and exten-sion of those telephone exchanges in large cities which are overloaded and cause delays.   Work on postal buildings will be kept to a minimum.13. Agriculture and Fisheries (including arterial watercourses)United Kingdom(  Million)Agriculture:  Building     ...      .......... Machinery (including replacements)	1947 21 44	1948 25 57	1949 31 57Total......	65	82	88Arterial watercourses    ..........	2-6	2-4	2-9Fisheries................	0-3	0-8	0-9Note.  These figures exclude livestock, crops, vehicles and fishing vessels.37. Agriculture. In 1948 considerable progress was made in farm build-ing. Gross investment in all kinds of farm machinery rose by nearly a quarter, and the greater part of the total net increase which was planned for 1948 to support the agricultural expansion programme was achieved.

38. In 1949 most of the building work will consist of new farm buildings and repair works essential to the expansion programme. In the public sector  1  million will be spent on Farm Institutes, Research Institutes,Agricultural and Veterinary Colleges, workers&apos; accommodation, experimentalfarms and miscellaneous buildings.39. In recent years rapid progress had been made in the mechanizationof agriculture. The number of all kinds of tractors in use has risen from some 50,000 in 1939 to more than 250,000 today and big developments havetaken place in the employment of other implements such as combines andgrass driers. This movement is vital to the success of the expansion pro-gramme since the increase in output of 2\ per cent, per worker per annum,which is its aim, must be obtained largely by more mechanization.40. In 1949 gross investment in machinery will remain at much the same level as in 1948 but replacements will comprise 60 per cent, of the totalas compared with 52 per cent, in 1948. Within the gross total the intake of new medium-powered wheeled tractors and ordinary cultivating machinerywill decline, but there will be an increase in the number of new heavytractors, both crawler and wheeled types, and newly developed machines,particularly labour saving machinery for harvesting.41. Arterial Watercourses. In addition to ordinary maintenance ( 1.8million) there are certain major schemes to be carried out most of whichare of direct and primary importance to agriculture. Those for the Wellandand Severn rivers are already under way and a start will be made on those for the Great Ouse and the Yorkshire Ouse before the end of the year.42. Fisheries. Investment in the fishing industry is small but important.In 1949 building work will be carried out on research projects, development schemes by the Herring Industry Board and on improvements at small fishingharbours.14. Forestry(  Million)1947 1948 1949Forestry Commission        ...      ..........     2-6 4-5 4-7Private woodlands.............      ...      1-5 2-3 2-5Total*       ...      ...      ...     4-1 6-8 7-2* Not all this expenditure can be classified on the same basis as other investment programmes; planting and upkeep are, for statistical purposes, treated as work in progress,and only about  1 million in each year is treated as capital investment.43. At present the country&apos;s resources of growing timber are negligible.Most of the convertible timber has gone and much that is immature is still being cut. It is important that the reserves of home-grown timber should beincreased.44. The long-term forestry programme set out in the Report on Post-WarForestry Policy (Cmd. 6447) and subsequently approved by Parliament,extends over 50 years, the object being to have 5 million acres under effectivemanagement at the end of that time. Of this 3 million acres will representafforestation mainly by the Forestry Commission, and 2 million acres therestocking of private woodlands dedicated to the purpose by their owners.It should then be possible to supply two-fifths of the country&apos;s present con-sumption of softwood from home resources. In the years preceding 1939home production covered only one twenty-fifth of the nation&apos;s consumption of timber and wood products. The programme for 1949 is in accord with the objective for the first decade of the scheme during which it is hoped toreafforest 500,000 acres and replant a further 600,000 acres.15. Iron and Steel(  Million)1947 1948 194925 32 49 .45. The investment programmes of the iron and steel industry for 1948and 1949 represent stages in the previously announced development and reconstruction plan, by which steel-making capacity will be increased to givea projected output of 17.5 million ingot tons in 1953-54. The expenditurein 1948 also included work on foundries and arrears of maintenance outsidethe development scheme.46. In 1949 the capacity of the basic and hematite, pig blast furnaces willbe increased from 8.0 million tons to 8.44 million tons, and that of the steelfurnaces from 15.25 million tons to 15.8 million tons. Among the schemescoming to fruition during the year will be:  the construction of open hearthsteelmaking capacity, reconstruction of strip mills, a new melting shop and replacement of a cogging mill and small mills at Brierley Hill (Staffs.); a newblast furnace at Consett to replace an obsolescent unit and increase the outputof pig iron; an additional open hearth steel furnace in Ebbw Vale. Workwill go forward on many other schemes, including the new steel works andstrip mill at Margam, which will not be completed until 1950 or succeedingyears. Special attention will be given to the expansion and reconstruction of coke oven capacity to meet the steel industry&apos;s expanding requirements ofmetallurgical coke.

16. Manufacturing Industry (excluding Iron and Steel)Capital Expenditure (  Million)Construction ...Plant  ......1947 194885 90260 29034538042547. In 1948 more investment was achieved in manufacturing industry than was considered feasible when the White Paper on Capital Investment in 1948(Cmd. 7268) was issued. The restrictions then imposed on starting new works were intended partly to divert resources to exports and partly tobring the volume of work in progress into balance with the available man-power and materials. In the event more steel became available and with thereceipt of E.R.P. aid it was possible to adopt a less restrictive policy inthe latter half of the year. Thus the monthly average value of licences issued for new industrial building work fell from  11.3 million in the second quarter of 1947 to about  3.2 million in the first quarter of 1948 when thefull effect of the restrictions on new investment were being felt; subsequentlyit increased to an average of  8.6 million in the second and third quartersand   [     ] million in the fourth quarter*.   Meanwhile the reduction in* Footnote. The figures include small amounts of work on warehouses, commercialbuildings, etc.the rate at which new building work was allowed to start enabled moreeffort to be concentrated on work already under construction and broughtabout a marked acceleration in the rate at which projects were completed.Thus in the Development Areas the amount of factory building completedrose from 1.1 million square feet in the third quarter of 1947 to an averageof over 2 million square feet in each of the second and third quarters of1948. A similar improvement was also experienced in other parts of thecountry.48. New work authorised during the past year included a substantial number of projects designed to increase our exporting power or reduce oue independence on supplies from difficult currency areas. Apart from minorworks and factory maintenance, building licences granted in the first three quarters of 1948 included important projects in the chemicals and alliedtrades ( 6.7 million), mechanical engineering ( 3 million), electrical engineer-ing ( 1.9 million), vehicle industry ( 2.3 million), refractory bricks, cement,earthenware, and glass industries ( 2.4 million), non-ferrous metals( 1.4 million), textiles ( 2.7 million), in addition to schemes in the rubber,paper and printing, food, drink and tobacco and other groups.49. During 1948 it is estimated that gross fixed investment carried outby the manufacturing industries as a whole, excluding the iron and steelindustry, amounted to some  90 million in constructional work and 290 million in plant and machinery.50. The claims of investment in manufacturing industry will continue tobe accorded a high place in the allocation of resources during 1949. Moresteel is being made available for industrial building and a larger labour force is now engaged on this type of work. For the reasons given inparagraphs to of the Survey this does not mean that all the needs for investment in manufacturing industry can be satisfied, but the resourceslikely to be available should permit those projects which will make animportant contribution to the solution of our economic difficulties to go forward and enable a better balance to be achieved between the supply of plant and the provision of improved and increased factory space.51. Discrimination will-continue to be necessary in the authorisation ofnew projects in favour of schemes which will make a substantial contribution towards the balance of payments and especially serve to increase dollar earnings or reduce dollar expenditure. The available resources must not bespread too widely, if schemes are to be brought to early fruition. special consideration will be given to (i) investment to increase capacity needed to overcome shortages of basic materials and components in common use (such as alkalis, cement,refractories, ball bearings, precision chain, dyestuffs intermediatesand sulphuric acid);(ii) projects likely to increase substantially exports to hard currencymarkets;(iii) projects making marked and direct savings in imports from hard currency sources, either by providing a direct replacement for imported articles or effective substitutes ;(iv) projects to develop technical advances and new practices of genuineimportance (e.g. tunnel kilns, some synthetic fibres, plastics, gasturbines) and research and development projects contributingsubstantially to industrial progress ; and(v) a limited number of projects which will yield marked and immediatereductions in costs.115310

52. It is difficult to forecast the volume of investment likely to be realised-during 1949 in this sector which is not susceptible to detailed programming^Any estimate must of necessity be imprecise. It is believed, however, thatthe resources likely to be available in 1949 should permit an increase inthe level of investment in manufacturing industry in respect both of buildings-and plant and that the aggregate investment may be of the order of 425 million of which a quarter will be on buildings and the remainder onplant.17. Housing(  Million)1947 1948 1949&apos;England and Wales...............     420 430 375Scotland      ............     ...     ...       26 38 46Total        .........     446 468 421England and Wales53. New Housing. During 1948, in accordance with the Government^decision, the Housing Programme was brought into balance in relation to theresources of labour and material available for housing. At the 31st Decem-ber, 1947, 225,000 men were engaged on construction of 215,000 houses inEngland and Wales. At the 31st December, 1948, 190,000 men were engaged on the construction of 150,000 houses. With the more effective deployment of men and materials the rate of completion of houses was much improvedduring 1948. With the gradual running down of the temporary house pro-gramme it has been possible to concentrate on the erection of permanent houses, the supply of which has also been increased by the special provi-sion made for permanent alununium houses. During the twelve months ended 31st December, 1948, 206,000 permanent houses were completed as-compared with 127,000 in the previous twelve months.54. Since the programme was brought into balance early in 1948, LocalAuthorities have been authorised to put out further schemes to tender inorder to secure a continuing adequate intake of new contracts. At the same:time a strict control over tender prices has been maintained.55. Capital investment in new housing for 1949 will be less than that in1948, largely because there will be no further capital expenditure on tem-porary houses and the bulk of the expenditure on permanent aluminiumhouses to meet special industrial needs was incurred in 1948. In 1949 theprogramme will consist entirely of permanent houses, almost all of tradi-tional type, on which the standard rate of subsidy is payable.Repair and maintenance, conversion and improvement56. A very large proportion of this expenditure falls below the licensing;limits of  100, and an accurate estimate of its total is not possible. Althoughlarge arrears have accumulated since 1939, present costs are likely to operate as a deterrent, and it has, therefore, been thought reasonable to assume that this expenditure will show only a slight increase.57. It is estimated that in 1949 the total capital expenditure on housing(including repairs and maintenance, etc.) will amount to approximately  375million.Scotland58. Although at the end of the year there were still too many houses under construction in relation to the available resources of labour and materials,,substantial progress was made in 1948 towards the balancing of the Scottishhousing programme. This was achieved partly by a severe restriction onthe starting of new houses and partly by an acceleration in the rate of completing houses under construction.At 31st December, 1948, 38,500 permanent houses were under construc-tion, and a further 11,000 were covered by existing contracts but had notbeen started. Broadly speaking, new contracts were approved only for houses urgently needed for agricultural workers, miners and key workers in industry. The total number of new houses approved during 1948 was6,000 as compared with 19,000 in 1947; the number of permanent housescompleted rose from 12,000 in 1947 to 21,000 houses in 1948. The aimwill be to continue this process in 1949 and, if possible, to bring the pro-gramme into balance by the end of the year.59. It is estimated that in 1949 total capital expenditure on housing inScotland (including repairs and maintenance) will amount to approximately, 46 million.

	1947	1948	1949-England and Wales			New places in primary and secondary schools   ...	5-5	12	21School meals..................	2	3	3-5Technical Education...............	0-2	0-7	3-other new work (including plant and machinery)	1	3-7	7Maintenance ...     &quot;...     ............	3	3	3	11-7	22-4	38Scotland			New School places  ,..     ............	0-95	2-45	2-6School meals ...	0-4	0-2	0-8Technical education......     ......     ...	0-05	005	0-other work (including approved schools) ... ,	0-6	0-6	0-7	2	3-3	4-5^Universities...............     ......	 	2-5	4-5England and Wales60. In 1948 educational building did not progress as rapidly as was hopedlargely because of shortage of steel; there was however some improvementin the second half of the year.61. The main task during the next few years is to provide new school places in primary schools. The number of children aged 5 to 14 (inclusive)in maintained and assisted schools was about 4.7 million in January, 1947;by 1948 it had risen, mainly through the raising of the school leaving age to 15, to about 5.2 million and, owing to the increase in the birth rate, itwill reach 6.0 million by the end of 1953. In addition there have been shiftsof population to areas where there are not enough schools or even noschools at all. A million new school places are needed to meet the rise inthe birth rate alone. In 1949 work on-projects, which will ultimately cost 40 million, must be started if substantial increase in the existing sizes ofclasses and in overcrowding is to be avoided.62. It is also proposed in 1949 to carry out the first instalment of a pro-gramme designed to meet the most pressing needs of technical education,the expansion of which is essential to improve the efficiency of the nation&apos;sindustry and commerce.63. Building for school meals will be kept to a level sufficient to maintain a reasonable standard and to meet the most urgent unsatisfied demands.The volume of other work e.g. for teachers&apos; training colleges, special schools for handicapped children, independent schools-will be small.Scotland64. In Scotland work will be on similar lines, allowing for the fact thatrather less progress has been possible because the Education Act for Scot-land was passed a year later than the Act for England and Wales.Universities65. There is a serious shortage of all types of buildings which seriouslyhinders the work of all universities. The number of full-time students has risen from 50,000 in 1938-39 to 83,000 in 1948. Provision has been made for-a substantial increase in university building, work in 1949.18. Educates(  Million)

-England and Wales Hospital and Welfare Services......... Miscellaneous Local Government Services   ... Maintenance     ...     ............	1947 3-7 3-0 5-0	1948 4-5 4-5 6-5	1949 I 7-8] [ 4-0] [ 50]Total............	11-7	15-5	[16-8]Scotland All services (including maintenance)   ...	1-7	1-8	[ 21]Grand Total.........	13-4	17-3	[18-9]* These figures relate only to building work, no account being taken here of equipment.66. Since the end of the war it has been possible to carry out only a verylittle building work for the Health Services the bare minimum of improve-ments, additions and renewals which could not be postponed. There wasa small expansion in 1948 which will be continued in 1949.England and Wales67. In 1949 investment valued at about  5J million is planned for hospital and specialist services. Though this is an increase of  2^ million over 1948it represents a level of building still considerably below the pre-war average.Work will be concentrated on making good war damage, overtaking arrears of maintenance and bringing existing accommodation up to standard; par-ticular attention will be paid to accommodation for nurses, since the quickestway of expanding the hospital services is to bring back into use the 60,000beds which are at present empty for lack of staff. A start will also be madeon a programme of work which will progressively ehminate the presentovercrowding in mental hospitals and mental deficiency institutions.68. In the field of public health and social welfare services, investment willbe confined to such work as the provision of additional day nurseries in the textile areas and the replacement of day nurseries now in requisitionedpremises. The building of experimental Health Centres will be begun insome of the larger towns.69. The miscellaneous services carried out by Local Authorities cover a wide range of works most of them on a small scale but of considerable localImportance.   The largest single item is sea defence.Scotland70. In Scotland broadly the same problems exist and will be tackled on similar lines.20. Water Supply and Sewerage&apos; (  Million)1947 1948 1949England and Wales      ............      10-8 15-0 25-scotland..................       2 0 2-5 3-5Total    .........      12-1 17-5 29-171. Between 1945 and 1947 the only schemes allowed to proceed were those designed to meet the essential needs of public health, housing and factories. In 1948 the level of work was allowed to rise somewhat sothat progress could be made with some large scale water projects whichcould no longer be postponed without danger to public health, and withschemes associated with the expansion of agricultural output.72. In 1949 there Will be a further increase to enable a start to be madeon a few more of the many schemes which were held over during the war,as well as on fresh schemes made necessary by the increase in the population and by industrial development. The resources available will, however,permit only the most urgent schemes to be approved.19. Health Services(  Million)*

73. This category of investment, most of which is in building, covers the:needs of the Police, Prisons and Borstal Institutions, Children&apos;s Homes,Approved Schools (in England and Wales), Probation hostels and homes, and fire Services, with the exception of houses for staff which are included in thenational housing programme.74. In 1948 investment was at a low level; in 1949 there will be a signifi-cant increase. The main emphasis will still be on maintenance and adapta-tions but some new building is essential; requisitioned premises have to bereplaced, many buildings are inadequate for present needs, and more police and prison accommodation is required.22. B.B.C. ,(  Million)	1947	1948	1949Building and civil engineering	.....     0-2	0-3	0-8Plant and machinery..........	.....     01	0-3	Q-8Total	.....     0-3	0-6	1-675. In 1949 investment on the technical side will be concerned mostlywith the development of ultra high frequency sound broadcasting and withtelevision. The purpose of the former is to exploit the use of short wave-lengths ; one station will be completed and another started.76. Work on the Television Relay Station at Sutton Coldfield will continue..This will extend the general coverage of the service to the Midlands andalso give experience of the technical problems of relaying. There will be nocommitments in 1949 for any further extension.77. In other branches, work will continue on a new Research headquarters and a start will be made on the conversion of premises for a new publicationsoffice in order to release requisitioned property. The replacement of regional offices will, however, be deferred.23. Service Departments(  Million)1947 1948        1949Service DepartmentsBuilding       ............-   ...     ...      15 14 [20]Machinery and Plant...............       2-5 2 2Total        .........      17-5 16 [22]Note. These figures exclude expenditure by the Service Departments on armaments, war-like stores and housing.78. In 1948 the Admiralty&apos;s major building projects did not proceed asswiftly as had been hoped due largely to shortage of staff. Much maintenance and repair work was undertaken mainly on rehabilitation of dockyards andair stations. The War Office and Air Ministry, which have large amounts of temporary wartime accommodation to maintain or replace, did not achieve their full programmes.79. In 1949 the expenditure on building shown above will be dividedlargely between major works ( 5  million) and maintenance ( 13^ million)..For all three Services maintenance is a heavy item because of the large war-time arrears and the amount of temporary hutting which must continue to&apos;be occupied.80. The major works, which will be carried out by the Admiralty, in addi-tion to the construction of married quarters and the improvement of barracksrelate mainly to airfields, research and development establishments, harbourworks and dredging. The War Office&apos;s chief task will be to meet the needsof the Territorial Army, by buying or leasing properties and supplementingthem with huts. In addition there is some vitally important work to be doneon providing storage accommodation and at training, technical and educa-tional establishments. The Air Ministry will carry out a programme of air-field reconstruction which had to be temporarily postponed in 1948 but must now be put in hand in the interests of operational efficiency.21. Services Administered by Home Departments(  Million)1947 1948 1949-England and Wales...............     1-5 1-9 [3-9]Scotland (excluding N.S. Hydro-Electric Board 5and Fisheries)     ...............     0-3 0-4 [0-5]Total        .........     1-8 2-3 [4-4]

Ministry of SupplyBuilding  ......Machinery and PlantTotal1947	1948	19498	10	12-53-5	5	711-5	1*	19-581. The Ministry of Supply is responsible for providing and maintainingbuildings for various branches of research including aeronautics, weapons,signals and atomic energy and for other establishments including the royal ordnance Factories.   Practically all their work is for defence purposes.25. Government Building(  Million)		1947	1948	1949New Works		8-3	12-3	11-4Maintenance		90	110	11-4	Total    ...	17-3	23-3	22-882. In 1948 it was not possible to realise all the economies laid down in cmd. 7268 because of the need to adapt premises for the Ministry of national insurance and to provide more hostels and camps for foreign workers.83. In 1949 no new employment exchanges will be built except where no alternative exists, but work must proceed on other office accommodation which is chiefly needed to replace requisitioned premises. Single storey semi-permanent construction will continue, where possible, since it is quickly builtand saves steel, but some permanent building in inevitable for sites in central london and similar areas. Work will, therefore, continue on the new Govern-ment offices in Whitehall Gardens and a start will, it is hoped, be made onthe new Colonial Office. The balance of the accommodation required forGovernment departments will be provided by office premises erected by private - owners for letting to the Ministry of Works. These will cost 5 million in 1949 and are excluded from the table above.84. The programme of camps and hostels for workers has now passed itspeak and the estimate of what is still required will be revised periodically inthe light of progress in recruiting and absorbing labour. For the rest thereis a wide field of work which includes the Houses of Parliament, RoyalPalaces, Museums, Art Galleries, Department of Scientific and industrial research laboratories and Ministry of Pensions hospitals.85. Maintenance covers the needs of about 25,000 public buildings allover the country. In 1949 it is hoped to make some small improvement onthe standards which had to be accepted during the war and which are nowbelow those of many non-Government buildings.26. Northern Ireland86. Capital investment in Northern Ireland is not set out in detail herebecause much of it, with certain important exceptions such as shipbuilding and defence, is subject to the control of the Government of Northern Ireland.There has, however, been consultation between the two Governments so asto ensure that plans are related to the resources available and that they arein harmony with the general principles governing the corresponding pro-grammes for Great Britain. The information supplied by the Government ofNorthern Ireland shows that in 1949 the total value of building work willbe about  30 million, of which two-thirds will be for social services (housing,health, education, water supply). Industrial building will amount to about 6 million.24. Ministry of Supply(  Million)




</content>
</cab>
