<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/26/38 images: 254-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;s GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet,  June 1942.SECRET.W.M. (42)77th Conclusions.Copy, No. ^zj.TO BE KEPT UNDERTOOK AND key it is requested that special care may ba taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 77 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Thursday, June 18, 1942, at 5-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Secretary of State for Dominion affairs and Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for &quot;War.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Lieutenant-General A. E. Nye, Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Brigadier L. C. Hollis.Contents.minute no. - Subject. page 1      United States Forces....................      ....      84Announcement of arrival in this country.2      United States Forces................      ....      ....      84Carrying capacity of giant liners.3      Parliament      ............      ........      ....      ....      85[23986-2]
1. The War Cabinet had before them a Report by the Chiefsof Staff as to the announcement of the arrival of American forcesin this country (W.P. (42) 257).It was explained in the Memorandum that the news wasleaking out and could not be withheld from the public much longer.The Chiefs of Staff recommended that the Security ban onPress references to the impending arrival of United States forcesin this country should be removed, subject to there being norelaxation of the rule that the details of the administrative plan should only be disclosed to those to whom the knowledge was essential for efficiency, and that, in particular, the dates of arrival,the locations and strengths of United States formations must bekept strictly secret.The War Cabinet approved this recommendation.2. The War Cabinet had under consideration a Memorandumon this subject by the Minister of War Transport (W.P. (42) 256).The Chief of the American Army Transportation Services had suggested that, for the purpose of bringing American troops to thiscountry in voyages due to start in August next, the carrying capacity of the Queen Mary and Queen Elizabeth should beincreased from 10,500 to about 14,000 or 15,000. It would probablybe practicable for these ships to carry this number of troops. Butthe equivalent of a whole Division would be at risk in one ship, andthere would bound to be very heavy loss of life if the ship were sunk.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that ships of this speed,travelling alone, ran a smaller risk of attack by submarine, but this risk could not be ignored, and, in addition, there was the danger ofair attack in the Western Approaches. In these circumstances, theAdmiralty could not support the suggestion of increasing thenumber of troops carried in these ships.The Secretary of State for War said that it was the policy ofthe United States authorities to get these troops over to this country as rapidly as possible; and on political grounds it was desirable toavoid giving any impression of obstructing this policy. So far as british troops were concerned, the War Office would not be preparedto risk such large numbers in -a single ship except for reasons of extreme operational urgency.In discussion, it was pointed out that, for these voyages, theships would be put at the disposal of the American Army, whowould be responsible for the use made of them. If they were willingto take the responsibility of increasing the number of troops carried,it would be difficult for us to press objections to this course merelyon the ground of increased risk to the British crews.The War Cabinet&apos;s conclusions were as follows : (1) The Minister of War Transport should make it clear to theUnited States authorities that we should not ourselvesbe prepared to risk so large a number of British troopsin a single ship except for reasons of extreme operationalurgency. If, however, the competent United . states authorities were prepared to take the responsibility sofar as concerned the troops, we for our part would not raise objection to these two ships carrying the larger numbers proposed by reason only of the increased risk to which the British crews would be exposed.(2) If he were assured that the competent authorities in the .United States were prepared to assume the responsi-bility on this basis , the Minister of War transport should make such arrangements as were necessary toenable these two ships to carry the increased numbersproposed.United states forces.Announcementof arrival in thiscountry.United states forces.carrying capacity ofgiant liners.
3. The War Cabinet were informed that there was likely tobe a demand for a statement to be made in the House on Tuesday,the 23rd June, as to the position in Libya, and possibly as to the malta convoys.The War Cabinet-Decided that this matter should be further considered attheir Meeting on Monday, the 22nd June.In the meantime, the Secretary of State for War was invited to ask General Auchinleck to send an appreciation of the position which could be used in Parliament.The First Lord of the Admiralty was invited to prepare a draft of a statement covering the question of the convoys, in case something on this matter had to beincluded in the statement to be made on Tuesday, the23rd June.Great George Street, S. W. 1,June 18, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
