<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/43/8 images: 80-83</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 508.8th November, 1943.WAR CABINET.SUPPLEMENTARY PENSIONS AND unemployment assistance.* Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.ON the 29th July last, the War Cabinet were informed that the assistance board had under consideration the codification of all Regulations relating to;supplementary pensions and unemployment assistance; and that these would be;considered, in the first instance, by the Lord Presidents Committee (W.M. (43)107th Conclusions, Minute 2).The Committee have now considered a Memorandum from the Board(L.P. (43) 231), setting out their proposals for the simplification and revision ofsthese Regulations.2. The constitutional position is that the initiative for proposing amend-ments to the Regulations rests with the Assistance Board. They submit draft regulations to the Minister or Ministers responsible, who must either make theRegulations in that form or, if they decide to change them, must disclose toParliament the changes made and the reasons therefor. In order to avoid publicdisclosure of differences between the Board and the Minister, it is the normal practice of the Board to hold informal consultations with the Minister before the stage of submitting formal Regulations is reached, so that when that stage isreached, they are in a position to know whether the Minister will concur in the!Regulations&apos; submitted. It is at this stage of informal consultation that thematter has been brought before the Lord Presidents Committee.3. A substantial measure of simplification is achieved by the draft Regula-1tions. In particular, women are now to be given, the same rates as men, and thelower rate for the wife of a pensioner (who is not herself a pensioner) is abolished; thepayment of winter allowances during the six winter months is to be discontinued,this discontinuance having been taken into account in deciding the new rates; thetreatment of rent is greatly simplified, and the differentiation against rural areas,is abolished. Partly as a result of ,this simplification, the general level of assist-&quot;ance is raised. The general effect will be an improvement of the allowances paidin the great majority of cases. In a small minority of cases the new proposals would result in some small reduction. But the Board intend to make special pro-vision so as to avoid making reductions in the payments current when the new regulations are brought into force.4. The Lord Presidents Committee have considered the new rates recom-mended in their relationship to the rates payable by the Ministry of Pensions.An exact comparison between the two sets of rates is complicated by two funda-mental differences in the principles on which the rates are determined. In thefirst place, the rates paid by the Ministry of Pensions are inclusive of rent up to8s. a week, whereas the Assistance Board rates are exclusive of rent, the actualamount (if reasonable) being paid in addition to the scale rate. In the second place, the Ministry of Pensions pay 9s. Qd. for the first child, 8s. 6*1 for the secondchild, and 7s. Qd. for the third and subsequent children, for all children under 16.The Assistance Board propose to pay at the rate of 6s. for children under 8,7s. Qd. for children between 8 and 11, and 9s. for children between 11 and 18irrespective of the number of children in the family. It follows thatthe relationship between the two sets of rates varies according to the[26382]Copy No,     3 4- : ;&apos;:3fj
2circumstances of the family. An examination of the rates payable in a largenumber of typical cases shows, however, that the Ministry of Pensions rates,taken as a whole, will be more favourable than the rates now recommended bythe Assistance Board, although the gap between the two sets of rates will bereduced.Cases will arise, however, in which the Assistance Board rates will be some-wiat more favourable than the Ministry of Pensions rates. These would have tobe considered, on the basis of discretion, by the Assistance Board and the Ministryof Pensions jointly.5. We have reached the conclusion that the adoption of the rates now recommended by the Assistance Board will not result in any demand, which wouldhave to be conceded, for a re-opening of the recent settlement of the rates of WarPensions.6. The Lord Presidents Committee also considered the relationship betweenthe Assistance Board&apos;s rates now recommended and the rates contemplated by ministers as a result of their consideration of the Beveridge Report. Here againa direct comparison is not easy. It is the policy of the Assistance Board to give more generous terms to old age pensioners than to persons out of employment.The reasons for this policy are set out in paragraph 31 of their Report. On theother hand, it is contemplated that under the Social Security Scheme the amountspayable by way of old age pension will certainly be lower than the amountspayable by way of unemployment benefit, although the difference will be less thanat the present time.7. Looking at the &quot;matter very broadly, it does not appear to us that therates recommended by the Assistance Board are likely to have any repercussionon the. rates of unemployment benefit proposed under the Social Security Scheme.It must be recognised, however, that the rates proposed by the Assistance Boardfpr pensioners will be distinctly more favourable than the rates of contributorypension contemplated under the Social Security Scheme, and it will, of course,be open to any contributory pensioner to apply to the Assistance Board for asupplementation of his contributory pension on grounds of need.:. 8. Payments by the Assistance Board are, of course, all subject to test of need, whereas contributory pensions are payable as a right and irrespective ofthe other resources of the pensioner. Nevertheless, we should not ignore thefact that the attractions of the contributory pensions under the Social SecurityScheme, must, to some extent, be diminished by knowledge that more favourablerates will be payable by the Assistance Board on proof of need.9. The financial implications of the Board&apos;s recommendations are set outin a separate note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.10. The final recommendations of the Assistance Board, on whom reststhe constitutional responsibility for submitting proposals to Ministers, will bereceived in due course. We have thought it important, however, that, in themeantime, the War Cabinet should be informed of the main considerations involved.C. R. A.Privy Council OfficexGreat George Street, S.W. 1,8th November, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
