<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 46-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED EASTERN  REPORT,  No. XVIII    THIS week&apos;s report is exceedingly brief.   There is nothing which justifies specialcomment exceptino- the Turkish advance in Persia which is to be noted.                                                                     M. S.    May 16, 1918.[898-95J
[This Document is the Property-of His Britannic MajeWs Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRET.FOR REFERENCE ONEY.      EASTERN&quot;  REPORT.       No. LXVIIT.  May 16, 1918.(Incorporating ARABIAN REPORT N.S. XCV.)CONTENTS.&quot;Russia.    Germany, Kussia, and Ukraina.    German Atrocities.    Conditions in Petrog-vad.    Ukraina.      The coup (VEtat.      Proclamation by the new Hetraan.    The Caucasus.      Aims of Parties.  &quot;Serbia.Turkey.    Relations with Bulgaria.    The Crimea.    Syria and Palestine.    Ayoub Sabri.Persia.    Attitude in regard to British policy.    Advance of Turkish Troops.    The Ex-Shah.    Farinan Farma.See Latest Intelligence.                                    RUSSIA.     Germany,  Russia, and Ukraina. In a telegram dated the  9th May [No.  169]Mr. Lockhart said that the Germans  bad declared an  armistice between Russia andUkraina.   They had informed the Russian Government that the Ukrainan delegationwould have to be altered, in view of the change of Government; and they now suggestedKieff in place of Kursk for the negotiations.     The Germans, he said, had taken  Taganrog  and Rostoff on the 6th  May, but aPetrograd  agency telegram of the  8th May stated that  the latter place  had  beenretaken by the Soviet troops.  On the 7th Ma3&apos; M. Trotsky had issued orders  that thetroops in the South should resist any German attempt to cross the line  of demarcationbetween Russia and Ukraina.   The Don and  Kuban districts had been declared  to  bein a state of war.     Telegraphing again on the  same  day [No. 171] he said that the action of theGermans in setting up  a bourgeois Government  in Ukraina  would  win them  the sympathy  of  the vast majority  of the  Russian bourgeoisie  and aristocrats.   Manyinfluential  Russians  would doubtless find their  way to Kieff and,  with German  help,would  become a serious menace to the  Bolsheviks, whom by themselves they  werepowerless to overthrow.   It seemed quite clear that the new Government would serve&apos;as a rallying  point for a counterrevolution in Russia rather than as an  independentGovernment of Ukraina.   The situation  was extremely serious ; and  in view of themilitary weakness of Russia the Germans were doing exactly as they  liked.     German Atrocities. According to a Russian wireless message received in london on the  13th May the Government at Moscow has  addressed to the German government lengthy protest against the atrocities  committed in Russia by German troops.  Fromthis document  the following passages are taken :      Many trustworthy eye-witnesses inform us of the terrible position of the populationof  the  occupied  regions of White Russia along  the line of demarcation, of violence, ofpogroms, of tortures, of executions, and of savage methods of dealing with the workingclasses, as  well as of the plundering and burning  of Russian  villages by German detach-ments.  Special mention in this respect is necessary with respect to the Polish Legions.     From the first days of occupation in the Bobruisk district, the Polish authorities
   undertook the settlement of difficulties of every kind.   Political activities in the town   were put a stop to.  The early days of occupation were characterised by general raids,   the smashing up of property,  and the requisitioning of all products.   The employees   of State institutions are not receiving their salaries, and suffer in a deplorable manner.   All money has been taken from the banks.  Entry  into and departure from Brobruisk   are prohibited.  The position of the working classes is desperate.        All this,  however, is nothing in comparison with  the situation in  the  villages.   Whole villages and small towns have been set fire to and plundered.             ******        The German authorities in the town and the Province of Minsk have caused whole   quarters to be surrounded and  raided.  All those who have served in the army  were   arrested, as well as many other persons who have never been soldiers.  Many thousands   of persons have been  arrested.  They- are kept  in  dirty and specially constructed&quot;  barracks, which have guns aud  machine-guns trained on them.  Arrested men are being   sent in their thousands to the West.  Thousands of  families  have been robbed  of  their   supporters, and are without any means of subsistence.             *           *      &apos;     *           *           *           *        The People&apos;s  Commissariat for Foreign Affairs, believing that all these acts have   taken  place  without  the  knowledge  and  against the instructions  of the  German   Government, suggests the formation of mixed commissions for the purpose of visiting   the  occupied  regions  of White  Russia,  in  which the representatives of the  local   population should also take part, especially representatives of the Jewish populations.        Conditions in Petrograd.. Mr. Woodhouse, telegraphing from Petrograd on the 30th   April [No. 159, received on the 13th May], said that  then, generally speaking, the town   was  quiet, though violence  and burglary continued  as well as  daylight  robberies.  It   was dangerous to be out after dark.   The workmen were getting dissatisfied ; they and   the sailors openly abused the Bolsheviks. So. far as possible the British colony had  been   evacuated, but some 500, chiefly women, were left; they would  be  unable to gain their   living in any other country,  but could eke out an existence in Russia.   Ninety per cent.   of them did not require supplies gratis; they were willing to pay for food even at the   current high prices, but  before long none would be available, except at a fabulous  rate.   Attempts had been made to obtain stores from villages, but, as  a rule, they were either   stolen en route or requisitioned by  the Red Guards on arrival in Petrograd.  There was   only one law, that of the strong ; therefore they would all soon be in a critical position,   unless there should be some  extraordinary change, and of that there was no hope.   UKRAINA.       The Coup d&apos;Etat. On  the  9th May  Mr.. Lockhart  telegraphed [No,  169]  the   following press, resume of the  recent coup d&apos;etat in, Edeff:-On  the 29th  April the   Germans closed,  down the  Rada by force.  On the same day  the congress of grain-   growers was  opened at Kieff,,  and a resolution  passed declaring the dissolving of the   land committees and the cessation  of all attempts to socialise the land to, be necessary.   At the same meeting it  was decided to offer General Skoropadsky the  hetmanship of   Ukraina, with unlimited  powers, and on the following day the new hetman entrusted   the formation of a cabinet  to Ustimovitch, who formed one  as  follows: temporary   Prime Minister and temporary Minister for Foreign Affairs, and Education, Wassilienko,   Cadet  and formerly  assistant  Minister  of Education  in  Kerensky&apos;s  Government;   Minister  of  Interior,  Lisogub, OctohrisV former  president  of  Poltava.  Zemstvo;   Minister of Finance, Rjepetsky, Cadet \ Minister of Commerce, Gutkin, Cadet; Minister   of Agriculture, Kijanitsin,  former  president  Poltava   Zemstvo ;  Minister of Food   Control, Sokolovsky, Economist; Minister of Labour, Wagner,  former, member of  War   Industries  Committee;  Minister  of  Health,  Dr.  Linbinsky;  Minister of  Justice-,   Professor  Affanassieff, Octobrist,  former  director  of Kieff branch of State  Bank \   temporary War Minister, Colonel Shivinsky.  Later news stated that Count Bobrinsky,   a  well-known sugar refiner, had also  entered the  cabinet.       The new hetman. General Skoropadsky,  who  is 44  years of age,  finished  his   education, in the  Corps des Pages.    He joined the  Chevalier Garde, and  at one  time   commanded the first Guards division.       There are three Cadets in the new Government.  The  Cadet  Party has issued a   notice declaring  that, though in- principle- the party recognises the necessity of taking-   part  in the Government for the present, it considers that the three Cadets entering it   enter on a purely personal basis.
    Proclamation by the new Hetman. -On the same  day Mr. Lockhart telegraphed   o. 170] the new hetman&apos;s proclamation :     Ukrainan  citizens,  you will all  remember that  recently&apos; when  the  best ofIIkraina&apos;s sons were shedding their blood and her newly formed power was on the vergeof destruction, it  had to thank  the  Central Powers not only for their efficacious aid.,but also for continuing  to  strive for her  peace  and integrity.  From the  aid  thusreceived, a new  hope  for the restoration  of order  and the return  of economical lifeinto normal courses was born in all.  But this hope was vain, for the former UkrainanGovernment proved incompetent.  Disorder and anarchy continued, economical ruinand unemployment increased, and now fruitful Ukraina is threatened with famine.Ukraina being menaced by this fresh catastrophe, the working classes have risen  andcategorically  demanded  the  immediate formation of a Government  which should be capable of ensuring to  the people, peace, order,  and the  possibility of productive labour.As a true son of Ukraina I have answered this  call and  taken upon myself full power :and in this manifesto I  proclaim- myself the  hetman  of Ukraina.   The  country willbe governed by a Cabinet of Ministers appointed by  myself in accordance  with the strict  basis of the laws, hereinunder  stated, of  the Provisional Ukrainan Government.The Central Bada, the lesser Radas,  and the land Committees, henceforward  chargedwith the maintenance of law and order in the country, will  insist on the fulfilment ofall  orders issued by  the Government, and will assist the authorised powers,  nothesitating when  necessary  to  take  the  severest measures.   The  right  to private property,  as  the  foundation  of culture and civilisation,  is reinstated;  and all  lawsissued by the  Ukrainan or  Provisional Russian  Governments altering or restrictingthat right are abolished.   Steps  will  be taken on  these  lines to requisition land fromlarge  landowners for divisions among the poorer agriculturists.   The  rights  of workerswill be guaranteed and&apos; special  attention will  be paid to the improvement of labour conditions for railway  workers,  who  have uninterruptedly continued the discharge oftheir   duties  under  exceptional  circumstances.  Freedom   of commerce  will  beestablished, financially and  economically;  and a wide  field of action will  be given to private enterprise and initiative.   Foreseeing  difficulties in my task, I  pray God togive  me strength  honourably to fulfil what  I consider my  duty  to my country in her present critical condition.  I am far removed from  jaersonal ambition ; my sole aimis the welfare of  my people  and my country.   Having this in view I call upon the citizens of Ukraina,  whatever their nationality or  religion, to co-operate with me inthis difficult and responsible task.                                        .  .THE CAUCASUS.    Aims of Parties. On  the  13th May, Sir C. Marling  telegraphed saying that areliable agent, who was  in Baku  at the beginning  of  the month, had given GeneralDunsterville the following report of the state of the various parties in the Caucasus.The Mohammedans in  the north, he said, were  monarchists ;  the Daghestans sided withthe social revolutionaries,  who  were conducting  propaganda in  favour  of  British.assistance their programme was the resurrection of Russia and a constituent assembly ;the Musafat party, opposed by the social revolutionaries and by all  Christians, was in.Turkish hands.                                    TURKEY.    Relations with Bulgaria. Sir H. Rumbold telegraphed  on the 2nd/May [No.  6So]that the military attached department had learnt on good authority that the TurkishGovernment  had recently  made representations to  Berlin  on the Turco-Bulgarianquestion.    There had  been  a  meeting at the  German general headquarters, at which the bulgarian delegates in Germany were present.   The Turks were given assurances ;  but,being extremely suspicious of Germany&apos;s intentions,  they believed that  Germany, owingto secret Austrian  support  of  Bulgaria,  found it very hard  to put pressure on the bulgarians.    The Germans were trying to postpone a settlement of the question  till the peace^conference.  Helfferich had already put off his  proposed visit to Sofia.     Unless the Turkish Government  obtained satisfaction the Cabinet  would resign.Talaat had already expressed his readiness to  do  so if the  Committee of Union and progress desired  it.  Jemal was intriguing strongly to  become Grand Vizier, but theGerman Government had let it be known that  they  strongly disapproved of any changeof government at present.        [898-95]                                                    &apos;   B 2
     The Qrimea. In  the  same telegram  Sir II. Rumbold  said  that the  Turks were anxious to send a few regiments from the Dobrudja division to the Crimea,   Germany had, however, objected  that there were one hundred thousand persons of  German origiiP already established in the Crimea, and that they must be protected by German troops. The Turks were convinced that Germany meant to establish a German colony there.     Syria and Palestine, Sir H. Rumbold further said that another cause for Turkish discontent was that, up to a short time ago, Germany had told Turkey that the fate of Syria  and Palestine  would be  determined on  the  western front. .  Now there was  a strong feeling in Germany in favour of making a determined attempt to wrest Palestine from the British, and  to establish an  independent state, under Turkish  suzerainty, managed by the German Jews.   This scheme had the support of many leading Jewish financiers in Germany.     Ayouh  Sabri  [E.R. XXI, p. 2;  XXII,  p.  5; XXVII, p. 3; XXVIII, p. 4; XXX, p. 4 ; XXXII, p. 3].-Mr. Balfour telegraphed  to Sir W. Townley on the 13tli May [No. 1064] that the date of the repatriation of  Ayoub  Sabri depended solely on the Turkish  Government.   Instructions had already been  given for bis  transfer to Egypt with a view to repatriation as provided for by the Berne Agreement.                                     PERSIA.    . Attitude in regard to British Policy. On the 10th  May  Mr. Balfour telegraphed [No.  250J to Sir C.  Marling asking for a general  appreciation of the attitude of the Persian Government towards British policy.  Sir C. Marling replied on the  14th May [No. 411] saying that  the Prime  Minister, in spite of his  own  friendly feelings, was unable to redeem his promises, as his rather passive supporters were unwilling to oppose the elements in the Cabinet hostile to us.  Failing  fiuancial  support  from England his resignation  could hardly be  long  deferred;  and  Sir C.  Marling had  given  him to understand  that no such support would be given to the Persian  Government until he had sent a circular to the local authorities prescribing a friendly  attitude in regard to British interests.     The  early  accession to  power  of Vossugh Dowleh was   generally   considered inevitable :  he certainly appeared to be the only possible successor of the present Prime Minister.     As regarded the people, whilst the great mass of the nation remained indifferent, the commercial  classes,  recognising  that  our influence made for order and peace,  were friendly.  At the same  time it could not  be denied  that the active anti-British propaganda had  had an  effect  on  certain  tribal chiefs  and  the  comparatively small portion of the people which  took  any interest in politics.     Sir C. Marling said that&apos;the real Germanophil  or Turcophil party was very small indeed :  he  did  not  think that the German  propaganda  was  making  any  great headway.     Advance of  &quot;Turkish  Troops. On the  9th  May Sir  C.  Marling telegraphed [No. 394] that in Teheran there was considerable apprehension as to the possible  loss of the province of Azerbaijan on account of the advance of Turkish troops  and the threatened   occupation  of  Tabriz.  It was  possible  that   the   Government would secretly encourage opposition to the Turks whilst endeavouring officially to maintain its neutrality.     On the same day Sir C. Marling transmitted [No. 396] a telegram from the consul at  Tabriz  announcing  the arrival  at  that place   of Nouri Pasha, accompanied by officers and  men to the  number of  thirty.   They gave themselves out to be part of the general  staff  of  the Turkish army,  which,  they  said,  had  three  objectives Kars, Einan, and  the annexation of Astara and Baku to the Turkish Moslem regions of the Caucasus.   Azerbaijan they claimed as belonging to Turkey;  though, in the opinion of the Russian consul-general, this must mean the old frontier, which ran to  the west of Lake Urumia.  They also said that they had no hostile intentions with anyone who did not interfere, and that only the general staff would come to Tabriz with its requisite personnel.     Telegraphing again on  the  following day [No.  400] Sir C. Marling  said that the arrival of at least forty Turkish  officers  at Resht had been reported by the  vice-consul at that place.  These officers, who were in uniform,  had travelled  via  Bijar and Zenjan,and had reached Resht  between the 6th and 8th May.
    The Ex-Shah. Sir  C.  Marling telegraphed on  the 13th May  [No. 406]  thatagents were travelling in Khorassan trying to induce various chiefs to rise  in favour ofthe Ex-Shah.  This had been reported by the consul-general at Meshed.  Sir C. Marlingadded that these agents  must be in German pay, as the Ex-Shah had  no money, and instructions for their arrest had been given to the consul-general.    Farman Farina [E.B. LXVII, p. 6]. Mr. Balfour telegraphed  to  Sir C. Marlingon the 13th May [No.  259] that  having regard to the situation in Fars he hoped thequestion of allowances  might be  left in abeyance  for  the  present.   It appearedunnecessary to come to an immediate decision ; but it was improbable that  the amountssuggested would  be approved.  To this  Sir  C. Marling replied  on the 14th  May[No. 413] saying that, whatever else were done; he should like to make  the gift  toFiruz, who had been of  the  greatest service, since Farman Farma went  to Fars.   In.regard to the allowances he had suggested, they were modest in comparison with thosepaid by the  Germans to  their friends; but perhaps the question  would not  arise.LATEST INTELLIGENCE.                                    RUSSIA.SIBERIA.     Prisoners of War. On  the  10th May Sir C. Greene transmitted  [No.  491]  atelegram from the consular officer at Vladivostock in regard to the German and Austrianprisoners of war in Eastern Siberia.   Referring  to the three centres, Nicolsk, Spasskoe,and  Habarovsk, he said that the prisoners in  the first named, who were inclined tosympathise with the  Bolsheviks,  were practically free ;  those in the other two centreswere kept under good discipline..  The prisoners were not armed.   The Germans werebeing transferred to Irkutsk.                                    SERBIA.     The Parliamentary Crisis. Sir  C.  des Graz  telegraphed  from Corfu [No. 59] on&quot;the 14th May that the  parliamentary crisis remained unchanged; a coalition  Govern-ment had not been formed.

</content>
</cab>
