<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 117-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
APPRECIATION  OF THE  ATTACHED  EASTERN  REPORT,  No. LXXVIII.                                     RUSSIA.     THE murder of the ex-Emperor Nicholas  marks another period in the Russian revolution.  The crime will no doubt  have its influence on the minds of the people as time passes ; whether it  will tend to a revival of the popularity of the dynasty or no is a matter of  doubt, the probability being that it will not.   However, the fact remains that once a man  has  been unjustly killed, the errors attributed to him diminish in popular estimation, while the acts of  his murderers are more and more open to popular condemnation.     The  attitude  of the  Bolsheviks  toward the Allies  and  the  Germans  continues unchanged.  When the Germans do  anything contrary to Bolshevik principles, words take the place of deeds, while as regards the  Allies, the Bolsheviks  always take as much action as their resources will allow.                                    PALESTINE.     The  Governor of Jerusalem&apos;s account of the celebration of the King&apos;s birthday atJerusalem is interesting and satisfactory.                                                                          M. S.     July 25, 1918.[898-105]
is tlie Property ,of His Britannic Majesty s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRETFOR REFERENCE  ONLY.      EASTERN   REPORT.      No. LXXVIII.  July 25, 1918.(Incorporating  ARABIAN REPORT N.S.  CV.)Q9CONTENTS.Eussia.    The ex-Emperor Murdered.    The Allies on the Murman Coast.    The Allied Consuls at Odessa. .    Archangel.    The Soviet Congress and the Constitution     of  the soviet Eepublic.    Eefusal  to  allow  German  Troops  in     Moscow.    Siberia.     The Ozecks Occupy Irkutsk.     General Horvat.Palestine.    The King&apos;s Birthday in Jerusalem.    Deportation of Germans and others.    German Prisoners of War.Persia.    The Kashgais.    The Bakhtiari.    Abadeh.                                     RUSSIA.     The Ex-Emperor Murdered. The following wireless message was sent out by theRussian Government on the (?) 19th July :-     At the first session of the central executive committee elected by the fifth congress of the councils a message was  made public, received by  direct  wire  from the Uralregional council, concerning the shooting of the Ex-Tsar, Nicholas Romanoff.     Recently Ekaterinburg, the capital of the Red Ural, was seriously  threatened bythe approach of the Czecho-Slovak bands.  At the same time a , counter-revolutionaryconspiracy  was discovered, having  for its object the wresting  of  the tyrant from thehands of the councils authorhy by armed force.     In view of this  fact the presidium of the Ural regional council  decided to shoot theEx-Tsar, Nicholas R,ornanoff.  This decision was carried out on the 16th July.     The wife  and son of Romanoff have been sent to a place of security.   Documentsconcerning the conspiracy which  was discovered  have been forwarded to Moscow by aspecial messenger.     It had been recently decided to bring the Ex-Tsar before a tribunal, to be tried forhis crimes against the people, and only later occurrences led  to delay  in adopting thiscourse.   The  presidency of. the  central  executive committee,  after having  discussed the  circumstances which  compelled the Ural regional council to take the decision toshoot Nicholas. Romanoff, decided as follows :  &quot; The Russian central executive committee,in the persons of the presidium, accept the decision of the Ural regional council as beingregular.&quot;     The central executive committee has now at  its  disposal extremely  importantmaterial and documents concerning  the  Nicholas Romanoff affair;  his  own diaries,which he  kept almost to the last days;  the diaries  of  his wife and children;  hiscorrespondence, amongst which  are  letters  by Gregory  Rasputin to Romanoff and his family.   All these materials will  be examined and published in the near future.     The Allies on the Murman Coast. The following wireless message was sent out bythe Russian Government :      The following order has been given by L. Trotsky :  In connection with the landing of English  and French detachments on the Murman coast, and the open participation of      [898-105]
French officers with the  counter-revolutionary mutineers the paid Czecho-Slovaks Iorder all military institutions and soldiers not to  support the French and English navaland military  officers ; not to permit them to go from one town to another ;  to watchcarefully all their acts as the acts of persons who, it has been proved, are capable withinthe territories of the Russian Republic of  conspiring against the sovereignty of theRussian people.  The causes which have  compelled me to issue  this  order&apos; will be explained later.     The allied consuls at Odessa. On  the 20th July  Mr.  Grahame transmitted from paris (No. 886] a telegram,  despatched on the 17th by the Allied Ministers at Jassy,saying that the allied consuls who had  stayed on at Odessa (those, that is, of  France,Italy, and Greece) had been  sent to Moscow, as Ukraina had been declared to be in thewar zone.     Archangel. Mr. Young telegraphed on  the 15th July [received the 20th July]that  Kederoff had  been given full powers  to  stamp out  the counter-revolution inArchangel,  and  the  allied  agents;   he was expected  to  arrive  within the nextfew days.     The  Soviet Congress  and the Constitution  of the Soviet  Republic. A  belatedRussian message says that at the last meeting of the  Soviet Congress the constitutionof the Russian Federal Soviet Republic was accepted : &apos;     Hitherto  there has been considerable doubt  as  to  who had the right to vote at elections for the Soviets.   Under  the constitution now accepted it is provided that thefollowing classes possess  this right: members  of  organisations who earn their living bymanual or brain  work,  peasants and  Cossack  agriculturists  who do  not use hiredlabour, intellectual and  technical  employees in state departments  and  institutions,soldiers and sailors of the revolutionary army and navy.   To prevent the  bourgeoisieattaining power it is provided that  persons who have incomes, derived entirely or partly from private trade or from, invested capital, and persons who employ hired labour, havenot the right to vote.  The right to enter the army  or navy belongs exclusively to thosewho possess the right to vote at the soviet elections.   Thus peasants and workmen areliable to  compulsory military service.   The sons of persons who  have been bourgeoisor capitalists are only permitted to  enter the  army or navy if they are willing to workon  the land  or in  factories.  The constitution  provides  for  the nationalisation of railways,  waterways,  banks and mines, which are to be considered the property ofthe state.    Refusal to allow German Troops in Moscow. The following wireless message  was sent out by the Russian Government on the 17th July :     At a meeting  of the central  executive  committee at Moscow  the  president ofthe council of the  People&apos;s  Commissioners, M. Lenin,  made the  following  announce-ment:      Yesterday, the 14th July,  at  11  P.M.,  the People&apos;s  Commissioner  for  ForeignAffairs  received  a  visit from^Dr......,  the Charge d&apos;Affaires  of the Germanembassy,  who  communicated the  contents of  a message just receiyed%by him from berlin, in which the German Government instructed him to  request the consent of theRussian Government to the sending of  a German battalion, in  military equipment, to moscow to guard the  German embassy,  and to  support the  rapid  sending  of these troops to Moscow.   He added that the  German Government had  no intentions in thedirection of the occupation of Moscow.     The Peopkfs Commissioner for Foreign Affairs replied that Russia  desired peace,and that  the Russian  Government  was  prepared  to  give   the German  embassy,consulate, and commissions, from its own troops, a perfectly trustworthy and  sufficientguard, but that in no case  could  the Russian Government permit the  presence  of aforeign military detachment  in Moscow.  The commissioner expressed  the hope thatthe  German  Government was inspired  by  the same desire  for  peace  as  was  theRussian Government,  and that the German Government would  not  insist  upon itsrequest.     In reporting this to  the executive committee M. Lenin expressed the hope that asatisfactory solution of the incident  might be  reached,  adding  that  &quot; on everyoccasion when complications in our international relations arise  we consider it necessaryto make the facts known publicly, and to face all such questions squarely.&quot;
  4p- j                                              -SIBERIA.     27ie Czechs occupy Irkutsk. On the 17th July Sir J. Jordan telegraphed [No 605]that a message, dated the  14th July, had  been received  from the Russian diplomaticofficer at Urga saying that on the previous day Irkutsk had  been completely Occupiedby the Czechs.     General Horvat. On  the  17th July Sir J. Jordan  telegraphed [No. 602] that theRussian  minister had admitted that General Horvat only controlled two small railwaystations  close to  the frontier.  The  French minister had intimated in regard to thesuggestion that the general should establish  himself at Vladivostock that  there wouldbe strong objections  to its adoption.                                  PALESTINE.     The Kings Birthday  in  Jerusalem. -Lieutenant-Colonel Ronald  Storrs,  C.M.G.,military  governor of Jerusalem, writes as follows :      I received and  entertained the notables  and inhabitants of  Jerusalem on  the3rd June in the morning, afternoon,  and evening.   At 9-30 I  paraded twenty speciallychosen prisoners and announced to them that, in honour of His Majesty&apos;s birthday, theywere liberated, and might at once leave the prison.  From 10 to 12-30 I held a reception:i,t the governorate of the notables  and various communities in the following order:-Egyptian officers ; police and gendarmerie officers ; grand mufti and kadi of Jerusalem ;officials of the Sharia court ;  ulama ;  grand rabbi and other rabbis ; ecclesiastical headsof various Christian  communities ; mayor with members and officials of the municipality ;judges and law court officials; director-general of wakfs and wakf officials ; director ofpublic education  and officials; notables of  Jerusalem  and  Beduin shaykhs,  in two groups;  notables  of  villages and Beduin shaykhs  in two groups ; notables of Salt andKerak ;  young Moslems ; and  officials of administrative office, finance, and public debt.     Distributions of money on a fairly  liberal  scale  were made  to the  heads  ofcommunities, out of  funds  placed at my disposal by their co-religionists in Egypt and elsewhere.  &apos; The  moment seemed favourable for enlarging upon  the benefits alreadyaccruing through  British  rule, as well as for  bespeaking the goodwill of the leadingpersonages ; for appreciating,   and at the  same time claiming, their loyalty ;  and fordemanding their  active  co-operation  to increase the supply of labour, combat prostitu-tion,  check useless  expenditure, increase  municipal  receipts, consider themselves  ascitizens of Jerusalem first, and Moslems, Christians, or Jews second, remembering thatGreat Britain was fighting for Arab freedom from Aden to Akaba, and from Tripoli tothe Persian Gulf; and,  finally, to assist the  army in all its branches by every means intheir power.  Throughout this somewhat exacting ceremony I received the spontaneousand. invaluable assistance of Musa Pasha  Kazim al Husseini, the mayor of Jerusalem,who was good enough to constitute himself master of ceremonies for the occasion.     In the afternoon I entertained  the inhabitants  and their families to tea  in the municipal  gardens,   enlivened by  the band of  the 1st Egyptian  regiment.  Themunicipality had  festooned the gardens and erected outside them  a decorated (if hardlydecorative) triumphal  arch.   A very large concourse  of people formed round  therailings,  and it was not without difficulty  that the roads in  two directions were kept open for  the  necessary  military  traffic.  Loyal  and  congratulatory  poems  weredeclaimed  by local poets and there was a general atmosphere of evident satisfaction andpleasure.  The Jewish  and Moslem  elements were largely represented, and I publiclysummoned  beside me the mufti, the mayor, and the two  most prominent grand rabbis.At 8 P.M. a dinner was served in the governorate, to which  the following persons were invited : the  grand  mufti, the mayor of Jerusalem, Ismail Bey-al-Husseini, Arif PashaDaudi, the president of the Franciscans, the Armenian bishop in Cairo, the ArchimandriteNicoclemos of the Holy Sepulchre,  Judge Homsy,  M. Sylvain  Levi, M. Meyuhas,Dr.  Eder,  and Mr.  Cleland, besides  certain members  of my staff.  Music was againprovided by the Egyptian  band.  His Majesty&apos;s health  was drunk with enthusiasm.     Deportation  of  Germans  and Others. German  interests in Jaffa being in  chargeof  the Spanish vice-consul,  this gentleman wrote to the military  governor,  on theoccasion of the deportation of Germans, informing him that the deportees had expressed their satisfaction at  the humane arrangements made on their behalf and the generoustreatment accorded  to them.   For the chivalrous manner in which they had dischargeda difficult duty, the  vice-consul thanked the  officer in charge of the deportation.
    General Clayton telegraphed on the 21st July [No. 10] that notices of deportationhad been served on German, Austrian^ and Bulgarian subjects other than Jews.    German Prisoners  of War. In the above-mentioned  telegram General Clayton.said that a large body of German  prisoners of war, recently  captured, had marchedthrough Jerusalem, by which the inhabitants were greatly impressed.                                     PERSIA.    The Kashgais [see E.R. LXXVII, p. 5, under Shiraz]. Telegraphing on the  17th:July,  Sir C. Marling [No. 631] transmitted a message,  dated the 3rd July, giving detailsof the arrangements which had been made with  the Kashgais, the  greatest credit forwhich, he said, was due to the Governor-General, who  kept  Kawam straight, and  then to the latter, who very successfully carried through the negotiations.  The preliminarynegotiations between Kawam, Ali Khan Kashguli, and  the  Governor-General led  to  ameeting between the  first  two  of these and the  Sirdars Ali Khan and  Ehteshan,resulting in an  agreement,  the  principal points of which  were as follows : (a.) TheBritish should not interfere in Kashgai tribal politics.   If they  should have reason tocomplain in regard  to disturbances or robberies they should refer the complaint  to theGovernor-General, who, in the first place,  would try to settle the matter through theIlkhani, but in  case of failure would  deal  with  it  himself;  (6.) It was settled  thatSirdar Ehteshan should be Ilkhani, and  Ali Khan, Salar-i-Hasmat,  Ilbegi; both ofthem  have accepted the responsibility of securing the safety of the roads and maintainingorder, Kawam agreeing to act  as their adviser.  Sir Percy Sykes  had approved theagreement.   The consul added that incidentally Kawam had enormously strengthenedhis position to our advantage.     The Bakhtiari On the  18th July the political officer at Baghdad reported to theIndian Government a message sent to  Sir Charles Marling by the vice-consul at Ahwaz.The vice-consul  said that  undisputed authority over the Bakhtiari tribes was at presentenjoyed,by  the Ilkhani, the Iloegi, and Sirdar Fahteh; he thought that  intrigues inthe north should make but little  headway during the continuance of this combination.The khans in the district felt that though Sirdar  Jang and  Sirdar Assad might take  adifferent line in Tehran, still they  were  on  their side and would support them inBakhtiariland.   So far as a judgment could be formed  in Ahwaz, there was no cause for anxiety as to the situation; our loan of a mountain-gun section had had an excellenteffect on our relations with the khans.    Abadeh. On the&apos; 21st July  the Viceroy  transmitted  a message  from Sir PercySykes informing him that early on the 17th Abadeh  had been reached by the  reliefcolumn, which consisted of Indian troops and 150 South Persian Rifles.  The besiegingparty had retired during the previous night.

</content>
</cab>
