<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 180-188</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.107APPRECIATION-  OF THE  ATTACHED  EASTERN   REPORT,  No. LXXXVI.                                      RUSSIA.     THE  reign - of- terror in Russia is. now  at  its height.   There are no signs of its being of short duration, or that  the  Bolsheviks  are other than competent to continueto carry on their Government for some time to come.     The anti-Bolshevik forces lack unity of purpose and organisation.   The Bolsheviksseem when the - occasion requires to  he able to produce forces  sufficiently effective fortheir own purposes.-.  The situation at Archangel is  not encouraging..                                     TURKEY.     Not too much reliance ueed be placed on Dr.  Parodi&apos;s report.  The C.U.P. is theonly vital force-in Turkey, and whether it acts openly or occultly it is equally powerful.                                      ARABIA.     The situation; seems  to remain  stationary at Khurma,  but still  gives  cause for anxiety.     The importance  of Idrisi&apos;s  reported  successes cannot  be  estimated  until  moredetails have been received.                                      PERSIA.     The Turks and their agents are evidently extending the policy of extermination ofChristians- to Tabriz.                                                                           M. S.     September 19,. 1918.[8-98   113]&apos;
Printed for the War Cabinet.108SECRET.FOR REFERENCE  ONLY.       EASTERN  REPORT.    No. LXXXVI.  September 18, 1918.(Incorporating ARABIAN REPORT N.S. CXIII.)CONTENTS.*Russia.  Moscow.    His  Majesty&apos;s Government and the Con-      stituent Assembly.  &apos;  The  Soviet Government on Itself.  Northern Territory.      Resume of Events.      The Coup d&apos;$tat.      Conscription.  Siberia.    The  Commander of the Czechs.    Czech Operations.    Martial Law.Turkey.    The C.U.P.Arabia.  Hejaz.    Khurma.  Asir.    Successes of Idrisi&apos;s troops.Persia.    Murder of French Missionaries.    Persian Bolsheviks in Moscow.* See Latest Intelligence.                                      RUSSIA.     Moscow--Sir  M. Findlay telegraphed on  the 14th September [No.  3246] that  hehad received authoritative information that the American consulate had been besiegedby Red Guards,  who had threatened  that,  if  the  English  and  French  were notsurrendered, they would force their way  in.  The date of the information was the 11thSeptember, and the siege had then been going on for five days.     His Majesty&apos; Government and the Constituent Assembly. Mr.  Balfour  telegraphedto  Mr. Lindiey on the  13th September [No. 117], instructing him to do everything possible to destroy any erroneous idea in regard to the attitude of the British Govern-menfc towards a constituent assembly, any idea, to wit, that it  would not be ready  tofacilitate the formation of such a body, or that it would oppose it when formed.     The Soviet Government on Itself. The Bolshevik Government sent out the followingwireless message on the 15th  September :--     The representatives of the neutral bourgeois countries at Petrograd have instructed the Swiss Ambassador, the doyen of the diplomatic corps, to hand a note to theCommissaryfor Foreign Affairs communicating the collective protest  made on the 3rd September  toCommissary Zinovieff against  the regime of terror, and declaring that their Governmentsreserved to themselves the  right  to demand a complete  satisfaction  and  personal responsibility before the law of the authors of these acts  of violence.  The Commissaryfor Foreign Affairs,  M.  Chicherin replied by a note, of  which  what follows is  aresume&apos;:      The note handed to us on the 5th September by the representatives of the neutral countries constitutes  an impertinent act of intervention in the internal affairs of Russia.The Soviet Government could  have left it  without reply, but it prefers to take advantageof this opportunity to explain to the masses in every country the essence  of its politics,as it represents not only the working classes of Russia, but also all the exploited masses of humanity.   It  is  futde  to contradict the facts, which  are advanced  without proof.  ...  as the representatives do not protest against these facts,  but against the regimeef the workers&apos;  and peasants&apos; Government in its struggle against the exploiting classes.
     The above-mentioned representatives are aware that the international war, provokedby small groups of bankers, generals, and bureaucrats, is already in its fifth year, and ischaracterised by.the. extermination  of millions of men, by the bombardment of opentowns by the two belligerent groups, and by  the  condemning  to death by famine ofmillions of human beings,  owing  to the  fact  that each belligerent group hopes,  bypreventing the  ^victualling of the other  group, and  by reducing  its children  to star-vation,  to  compel  surrender to  the mercy  of  the victor.   Moreover,  in   all   the belligerent countries  reigns the white terror  of  the bourgeois, characterised  by  the arrest of workers and the  suppression of all  liberty.   The neutral countries  do  notprotest against this terror of capitalism because the bourgeoisie of all neutral countriesassist the capitalists of the  belligerent countries to continue the war, as they thus gainmilliards in profits on the supplies for military needs.   The Governments of the neutral countries do not protest against the repression  of the  Sinn Feiners dn  Dublin, againstthe white terror in Finland, against the massacres of workers and peasants in Ukraina,and  against the terror of the Czecho-Slovak bandits, the mercenaries  of Anglo-Frenchcapital;  and in their  own countries Denmark, Norway, Holland, Switzerland   theyrepress  by armed force all  manifestations of the  workers.  The representatives of theneutral  countries are sent here not for the defence of humanitarian principles, but for  thedefence of  the interests of capitalist countries.   Let them beware of the revenge of the masses of the whole world,  which  will rise against the  capitalist civilisation, which  has brought  humanity to a regime of massacre.     The working classes in Russia have destroyed the imperial power and the domination of the bourgeoisie, against the crimes of which  the neutrals never protested.  After  the immense majority of the Russian  people, through  the second congress  of the  Soviets,had  handed over power to  the  workers&apos; and  peasants&apos; Government, a small  group ofcapicalists, landowners, and generals  cut off communications leading to the fertile cornregions, organised counter-revolutionary mutinies,  and delivered northern and southernRussia over to foreign imperialists, and.....     We declare in the face of the  proletariat of the whole  world, that  hypocriticalprotests  will not deter us from punishing  those who take up arms against the workers and  poor peasants of Russia, and who strive to reduce them to starvation  and  to drawthem into fresh wars in the interests of capitalism.     Let us bring peace, equal rights and freedom to those who loyally  carry out their obligations.NORTHERN TERRITORY.     Resume of Events. On the  13th  September Mr.  Lindley telegraphed [No. 164]that in  order to make the situation clear he was  sending the following resume ofevents      &quot; As soon as it became known in Moscow that the allies intended to intervene in thenorth, the central organisation for the regeneration of Russia, whose headquarters were at Samara, and which  was  directed  by General Alexieff and MM.  Stepanov  andAvksentiev, delegated those who  afterwards formed  the government of the  northern region, six of whom were  also members of  the  Constituent  Assembly,   to  come to archangel to work among the people and eventually to  form a  local government  underM. Chaikowsky.     &quot; The work was carried on in concert with Captain Chaplin, and the Government  was declared as soon as ihe rising took place and our ships were in  the river.  The first act of the Government was to invite the allies to land.     &quot; As soon  as  General Poole had landed he declared martial law, which presumablymeant the Prussian state of siege under which  all authority of every kind passes into thehands of the military.   A week later he appointed a French officer  military governor ofthe town.     &quot; The Government never recognised the validity of these acts, and when we arrived on the 9th August there was already a great  deal of friction between the Governmenton  the  one side and the  commander-in-chief and Captain Chaplin, commanding  theRussian forces, on the other.  The latter officer bad been appointed by the Governmentand was only under the orders of the commander-in-chief in so far as military operations were concerned.     &apos;.&apos; M. Chaikowsky naturally turned to the  allied representatives in his troubles,  andwe made every possible effort by the creation  of an inter-allied chancery, and in otherways, to diminish the  friction.   In this we  were unsuccessful,, and  there followed aseries of disputes regarding the release of persons  believed by  the  military authorities
to be dangerous and by the Government to be innocent, the&apos; permissibility of certainmeetings, and other matters.  In short the Government never acquiesced or attempted to  accommodate  themselves  to  what the military authorities considered to be the necessities of the situation, and the military authorities complain that certain membersof the Government, especially  MM. Maclov and Likhach, were creating an atmosphereso hostile to the allies as to constitute a  military danger.  Friction  was  particularlysevere between the Government and Captain Chaplin, who, as you are aware, meditateda coup d&apos;etat as long ago as the 11th August.  This was averted,  but  actually took placeon  the 6th September after General Poole had, at my  instigation, sent  a  note toCaptain Chaplin expressing disapprobation  of his intentions, which  he said he  couldscarcely  credit.     &quot; The coup d&apos;etat, as  you are  aware, caused a general   outburst of resentmentmanifested by a general political strike and the  arrival of armed bands of peasants inthe town.  I do not agree with those who consider these, manifestations factious.   Thegeneral opinion was that the allied military authorities, if not the allied representatives,were behind the coup d&apos;etat, the success of which the man in the street could explain on no other hypothesis.     &quot; The allied representatives at once  ordered  the  return  of  the members of theGovernment, but nothing has been clone to punish offenders except that the resignation of Captain  Chaplin has been accepted, and he has gone to the  front in his former rankinstead of as commander of the forces.     &quot; During  the  absence of most of the members  of the Government, two others who  had not  been arrested  issued  a proclamation  calling   on their supporters todefend  the  rights  of  the  Government,  and  ascribing  to the plot  the object of putting a grand duke  on  the throne.   This proclamation was  certainly objectionableand untrue, but I cannot agree with military authorities  in  considering it  as grave an offence as the coup  d&apos;etat.     &quot; Nor can I agree  with  them   in  regarding the  coup  d&apos;etat  as  an  internalaffair in which they were not called on to interfere either in their military capacity or as those  responsible  for  order in the town.    To me it seems a gross  breach of discipline and as disorderly an act  as could well be imagined, even though  the  RussianGovernment had neither authorised martial law  nor recognised the appointment of a.military governor.     &quot; Since the Government came back a  preliminary censorship has been establishedwithout   consultation  with  me or  anyone else,  and  papers,  including  the officialGazette,  appear with  those immense blank spaces to which the old  regime  and theBolsheviks have accustomed Russia.   The Government have declared that they cannot continue to work under those conditions, and are  preparing to leaye at once.&quot;     The Coup d&apos;Etat  [E.R.  LXXXV,  p.  3].-Mr.  Lindiey telegraphed on the  11thSeptember [No. 153] that on the previous day the allied representatives had had anotherlong  conversation with M. Chaikowsky, and had agreed with  him  that punishments,fixed by the. competent Russian authorities, in  consultation with the allied commander-in-ehief, should be meted out to those who had been implicated in the recent coup d&apos;etat ;and further  (it being considered advisable that the effects of a long drawn-out  public enquiry should be avoided), that the investigations should be  carried out, not by the-ordinary procedure&apos;of law,  but by  the Government secretly.     Conscription.-MT.  Balfour telegraphed on the   13th September [No.  115] toMr. Linclley that General Poole had been instructed to make it  clearly understood thatthe British  Government  was  not only in no way responsible for the  measures tointroduce conscription which had  been taken by the local  Government,  but,  more,regretted them.SIBERIA .     The  Commander  of  the   Czechs. Sir  Charles  Eliot   telegraphed  on  the13th   September [Nos. 46, 47, 48] that the supreme command of the Czech  troops had been assumed by General Gaida, in place of General Dietrichs.   This seemed toindicate that the Czechs preferred not to be commanded by a Russian;  but Sir CharlesEliot understood  that  there was no quarrel, and that General Dietrichs had undertaken to organise the Russian  troops in  co-operation  with General  Knox.   General Gaida,however,  described himself as commanding the  Russian as well as  the Czech troops,and the French representative seemed  disposed to support his claim.
     Czech Operations. On the 12th September, Sir Charles Eliot transmitted [No. 41]&apos;a telegram [No. 5]&apos; from the consul at Irkutsk  saying that a message had been receivedfrom the French vice-consul at Ekaterinburg to the effect that that place was surroundedby  30,000-40,000  Bolsheviks under  an Austrian general.   The situation  was very grave.  In the  same telegram  it was stated that there were some 40,000 Bed Guardsat Kasan under a  German  commander.   On  the following day, Sir Charles Eliottransmitted  [No. 42] another telegram  from the consul at Irkutsk informing him thatKasan had been retaken by Bolsheviks and Germans;  this had been officially reported.     On the  15th September Mr.  Alston transmitted [No.  55] a telegram [No. 10] fromthe consul at Irkutsk announcing the evacuation  of Simbirsk on the 12th September(the Czechs and  Russians  doing  this  on account  of  the superior numbers  of theenemy) and  the retaking of Volsk by the Bolsheviks.  The consul added that german troops were  helping, and that  Germans were directing everywhere.     Martial Law. Sir Charles Eliot telegraphed on the 13th September [Nos. 47  and48] that  an  order had been published at Harbin by General Gaida, the  practical effectof which  was to establish martial law along  the line of railway from Olovyannaya[south-east  of  Chita in  Trans-Baikalia] to  Vladivostock :  and  that it  had beenunanimously decided by the  allied military  council (the American general agreeing atthe end of three hours&apos; discussion) that the commander of the  Russian troops  in the maritime province should declare martial law throughout that province.                                   TURKEY.  *     The C.U.P. Sir Horace Rumbold telegraphed on the 12th September [No. 1565]that Dr.  Parodi had been  informed that the recent news  from Constantinople pointed to the end  of the C.U.P., as represented by Enver  Pasha, Jemal Pasha, and  Javid.He had been informed too that, in view of the situation, the Germans  were  calling inthe outlying troops in  the  neighbourhood  of  Constantinople for  the  purpose of concentrating them in the city itself.   Turkey desired the war to  end,  and emissariesof persons in the confidence of Javid Bey agreed in thinking that Germany had lost the game.                                     ARABIA.HEJAZ.     Khurma. Sir Reginald Wingate telegraphed on  the  15th  September [No. 1362]that  according  to  their  latest  information Shakir  was encamped to the west ofKhurma  with a force of about 2,000 men; the local  opinion was that he would nottry to penetrate to Khurma, but would continue to act on the defensive.   The  peopleof Taif, being nervous,  showed an inclination to move to Mecca.Asm.     Successes of Idrisi&apos;s  Troops. Sir Reginald  Wingate  telegraphed on  the 14thSeptember  [No.  1357]  that  Ganda,  Atu,  and  Loheiya  were occupied by  Idrisfstroops.                                     PERSIA.     Murder of French  Missionaries. Sir Charles Marling telegraphed  on  the 11thSeptember [No. 808] saying that  it was reported from Tabriz that, the  German  consulhad brought the  news  that all the members  of  the  Lazarist mission  had beenmassacred in Urumia on account  of &quot; war necessity.&quot;  The report added that most  ofthem Were native Syrians.     Persian Bolshevikt  in  Moscow. According to a Russian  wireless message (sent out on the 15th September) the  Persian  colony  in Moscow has decided to  organise  asociety for self-education and propaganda of which many Persian men of letters wdlbecome members.   The object of the society  is to  translate the Soviet constitution and other Soviet literature into the Persian language and  to distribute it in the East.
LATEST INTELLIGENCE.                                    RUSSIA.     Report on the Situation by the Netherlands Minister in Pelrograd. Sir MansfeldtFindlay, on the  17th September, telegraphed [No. 3281] the following  report by theNetherlands Minister  at Petrograd, dated the 6th September, on the situation in Russia,particularly as it affected  British subjects  and British  interests  under  the Ministersprotection :      On the 30tb August  I left for Moscow largely in connection  with the negotiationsfor the evacuation of British subjects from Prussia.   The same day Uritsky, Commissaryat Petrograd for  combating counter-revolution,  was assassinated by a Jewish studentKanegiesser, whose father is a  wealthy (?  engineer) and holds  a  very  good position at Petrograd.   This murder was at  once attributed by the  Bolshevik authorities andBolshevik press (the only existing press  in Russia) to the French and the  English.     That  same night  Consul Woodhouse and Engineer-Commander Le Page were arrested at 1 A.M. in the street.   Every effort was made the next day (the 31st August)by my secretary, Mr. Van  Niftrik, to obtain their release, and that of Consul Woodhousewas  promised for the afternoon.     At 5 P.M. on the 31st August,  when  Consul Bosanquet and Acting Vice-ConsulKimens, who had been busy the whole day with Mr. Van Niftrik in  connection with hisattempt  to obtain  the release  of the  arrested, and  were heading to the  embassyand  were near the embassy building, they were warned  not to approach the embassy,and  told that it had been  occupied by the Red Guards and that two persons  had been killed.   They  at once decided to head back to find Mr. Van  Niftrik and ask  him,to endevour to secure an entry  into the embassy.  While driving slowly away fromthe embassy their car was stopped by Red Guards  in another car, one of whom levelleda revolver at them and told them to hold up their hands.  They were  searched  andhad  to give their - names and rank, but to their great surprise were  allowed to proceed.Mr.  Van Niftrik drove with them to  Gorokhovaya  2, headquarters of the commission for combating the counter-revolution, to which persons  arrested are usually taken, and where Mr. Woodhouse was confined.  He had a long interview with  the commandantof Petrograd,  Shatov,  and  strongly protested  against  the  unheard-of breach ofinternational law which  had  taken place, and demanded  to  be  allowed  to driveimmediately to the embassy to be present at the search  there.  Permission was refusedby Shatov, who said that  the embassy was being searched  because the authorities haddocuments proving  conclusively  that   the  British  Government  was  implicated inUritsky&apos;s murder.  When they had left Furm  .... and their car was  passiag theWinter Palace, the  staff of the  British  consulate  and of  the  missions and somecivilians who were at  the embassy when it was invaded were seen walking under guardto No. 2, Gorokhovaya.     A meeting of the neutral diplomatic corps was held that night upon the initiative ofMr.  Van Niftrik, at which the following points were submitted :       (i.) That the immediate release of those arrested should be demanded.      (ii.) That it should be insisted upon that Mr. Van Niftrik  should  be present at           the examination of those arrested.     (iii.) That attention should  be drawn to  the gross breach of  international law           committed  by the armed occupation of the embassy,  which bore on the           door  a signed and sealed notice to the effect that it was under the protection           of the Netherlands Legation, and by the refusal to allow Mr. Van  Niftrik to          . be present at the search.     The  meeting  drew  up a  protest to  be presented to  the  soviet  authorities at moscow.     On the 1st September particulars were learnt as to the violation of the embassy,and  details will be found in a statement, herewith enclosed, made by Mrs.  Bucknall, wifeof Lieutenant Bucknall, now under arrest.   Mrs. Bucknall  was at  the embassy at thetime of its invasion.  The Red Guards, under  the direction of several commissaries,,had  made their way into the embassy at 5  P.M. and behaved with the  greatest brutality.Captain Cromie, who had tried to bar their entrance and had  been  threatened that hewould be killed &quot; like a dog,&quot; had  fired,  killing two men.  He had then been  shothimself and died nearly instantaneously.  The whole staff of the consulate and missions,and  some civilians accidentally present at the  embassy,  had  then been marched under       [898 113]                                                         C
escort to Gorokhovaya No. 2, where they remained until Tuesday, the 3rd  September,when (at 4 P.M) they were conveyed to the fortress of Peter and Paul.     During.the next few days repeated efforts were made by Mr. VanNiftrik, Mr. Vander  Pals, and  by the  neutral legations to obtain  the release  of those  arrested, but without  success.   Mr. Van Niftrik  endeavoured successfully  to obtain  an interview with Zinoviev, president of the northern commune, on the  1st  September,  and M.  deScavenius, Danish Minister, who expressed profound indignation at what had occurred,saw  Zinoviev at 9 P.M. on that day, and expressed himself in the strongest terms.   Hewas  promised  that the body of  Captain Cromie should  be  delivered up  to him andMr.  Van Niftrik,  and on the  2nd September they together removed the body to theEnglish church.  The funeral took place in the presence of the whole of the corpsdiplomatique and the greater part of the British and French communities.  The coffinwas  covered with the Union Jack and was completely wreathed with flowers.  After  ithad  been lowered into  the grave I pronounced the following short address in French and english:          &quot;In the name of the British  Government and in the  name  of the&apos;family  of     Captain Cromie I  thank you  all, especially the  representatives of  the allied and     neutral countries, for the honour you have shown Captain Cromie.         &quot; Friends, we have all known  Captain Cromie as a real friend, as a  British     gentleman, as a British officer in the highest sense of the word.         &quot; Happy is the country that produces sons  like Captain Cromie.         &quot; Let his splendid and beautiful example lead us  and  inspire  us all until the     end of  our days.   Amen.&quot;     The doyen of the  corps diplomatique, M. Odier,  the Swiss Minister, gave expression to his deep  sympathy and  admiration for the late  Captain Cromie, who had  died forhis country.     In the  evening of the 3rd September,  no  impression having yet been made on the communal  authorities, another meeting of the corps diplomatique  was  held.  Thismeeting was  attended  by the  neutral diplomatic  reprsentatives, Mr.  Van  der Palsrepresenting the Netherlands Legation.  An unexpected feature of the meeting was theappearance,-at the suggestion of M. Scavenius, of  the German and Austrian  consuls-general.   The whole of the body met  together at 9 P.M.,  and  proceeded to Zinoviev&apos;sresidence, where they  with difficulty succeeded in   obtaining an  interview with  him.M. Odier strongly protested in the name of the neutral legations at the action takenby the communal authorities against foreign subjects.  He emphasised  the fact  thatfor  acts of violence committed against foreign subjects in Russia  the soviet  officialswould be held personally responsible.   He demanded that permission should be granted for a neutral representative to be present at the examination of the accused.  Zinovievsaid that he must consult his colleagues  on  the matter.  Mr. Van der Pals afterwardsagain laid stress on this  point.   M. Odier was followed by the  German consul-general,who made  a  forcible  protest in the  name of  humanity against  the terrorism nowentered upon by Bolsheviks.  He referred  in strong terms to the &quot;sanguinary&quot; speechmade  the other  day by M. Zinoviev, and said that even  though the French and theEnglish arrested  belonged to nations at war with Germany yet it was  impossible not to unite  with  the neutral representatives in a  strong  protest against the  course nowadopted by the Bolsheviks.  He appears to have spoken with great force, though one lineof (words or perhaps pages missing).     I returned to Petrograd yesterday, as I had received a telegram from my secretaryurging my return, and could not therefore  take the responsibility of  remaining longerabsent from Petrograd, where the position I gathered must be very bad.  Up to to-day the situation here has in no way improved.  Besides the British arrests numerous others of French  citizens have taken  place, including that of the commercial  attache to the. French  embassy, though  the French consular officers have not so far  been  touched. Thousands  of Russians belonging to officer and wealthy classes, not excluding merchants and shopkeepers, are being arrested daily,  and, according to an official  communication, five hundred of them have already been shot; among the arrested there are a large numberof women.  For the last four days no further British arrests have been made.  . I enclose herewith a full list of British officials and civilians now under arrest at Petrograd.     The position of British subjects in prison is most precarious, and during the last few days constant reports have reached  the legation that the  question whether to shoot orrelease them has not yet been decided. &quot; There seems also to be a strong  tendency to regard those arrested as hostages.   Those belonging to the military and  naval missions are probably in most danger, and in the present rabid temper of the Bolsheviks anything
 is possible, but there is some hope that the consular staff and civilians  may be released before matters become still  more serious.  With regard  to  members  of the  missions hope of release seems very small.   &apos;  The conditions under which Englishmen at Peter and Paul fortress arekejot are most miserable.  I was informed yesterday&apos;by M. d&apos;Arcy, commercial  attache to the French embassy, just released, that they are crowded  together  with other prisoners,  some twenty in a cell, 20 feet by 10 feet.  In each cell there is only one bed&quot;; the rest must sleep on a stone floor.  No food whatever is  supplied by  the prison authorities, and they depend entirely on arrangements which this legation has made,  and food  furnished by friends and relatives.   Rugs, pillows, medicines, warm clothing, and other comforts are being  sent from time  to time, but great difficulties are experienced in getting these articles delivered.  From the 31st August to  the morning of the 2nd September no food at all was  accepted for the prisoners.  Since then they  have received some supplied from outside, but it still remains to be seen whether it will reach them regularly  at the fortress, though I shall leave no stone  unturned  to  secure its  proper  distribution. Russian prisoners in the  fortress appear to  be absolutely starving, and this will make the question of supply of British subjects even more difficult than it would otherwise be, owing to the presence in their cells of famished Russians.  I  enclose herewith copy of a letter just received from British prisoners which speaks for itself.     Yesterday evening I endeavoured to  see  Zinoviev in order to inform him of the appalling conditions at the fortress, but he absolutely refused  to see me.   I was equally unable  to see  Uritskys  successor,  and  could  only gain access to a subordinate of latter, who behaved with the lack of courtesy which may now be expected.   I informed him  of the conditions obtaining in the fortress, and he eventually promised  to speak to the commandant of the fortress, whom he bad occasion to see that  night.  He refused to give me the number of Zinoviev&apos;s telephone or the name of the  commandant of the fortress.     As regards the situation in Moscow,  I can only say  that  in  my  opinion it is most grave.  Nineteen Englishmen and thirty  Frenchmen have been  arrested and  are kept under the worst conditions.   Mr. Lockhart,  who was  released  and subsequently rearrested, was only saved from being shot on the 4th  September by my most strenuous exertions.  Before I left Moscow a solemn promise was given  to  me that he should be released,  but  his  position is  precarious in  the extreme, while all those now  under arrest there are in great danger.   Mr. Lockhart is accused by  the soviet  Government of organising a plot to overthrow it, and the Bolshevik official and  unofficial papers are full of details  of an  alleged  conspiracy,  while it  is asserted that  British officials  at Petrograd were concerned in the plot.  The attempt on  the life  of Lenin,  is of course attributed by Bolsheviks to the British and  French, and if he should die it  is  quite possible that all now under arrest at Moscow  and Petrograd will be  shot.     At Moscow I had  repeated  interviews with  Chicherin and Karahan.   I  consider Chicherin beneath contempt, and can only apply to him the term &quot; reptile.&quot;  I was able to show pretty clearhy what opinion I held of  him.   The whole  soviet Government has sunk to the level of a criminal organisation.   The Bolsheviks  realise that their game is up, and have entered on a career  of criminal madness.   I repeatedly told Chicherin, with all the energy of  Avhich I am capable,  that  he  must realise full well  that  the Bolshevik  Government was not  a match  for  England.   England  had  a  longer wind than   the  Soviets.  She  would not   be  intimidated ;   even, if hundreds  of British subjects should  be executed by order of the Bolsheviks, England would not turn one  hair&apos;s breadth  from  her purpose.   The moment  would  come when the soviet authorities, man by man, would have to pay  for  all the  acts of terrorism which they committed.   But in spite  of the  persistence with which I drove these  facts  home, I could not obtain  any definite promises  from  Chicherin, but only a  few  evasive replies and  some lies.  The  Bolsheviks  have burnt  their boats and are now  ready  for anywickedness.     As regards  the  original objects of my  journey to Moscow, the evacuation of theBritish from Russia, I found  it necessary to promise that Litvinov should be allowed toleave England at once, provided that in exchange for this concession all British subjects in Russia, including the consular staffs and missions, were allowed to leave the country.This was agreed to so far as the consulates and civilians were concerned, including those now  under   arrest at  Petrograd; but an exception was made  with regard to themembers of military and naval missions, who would  be released only on  the arrival  ofthe Russian Red Cross  delegates in France for the purpose of repatriation of Russiansoldiers.   The result of negotiations was reported by telegraph to His Majesty&apos;s Ministerat Stockholm through thev intermediary oCtlre Swedish  consul-general at  Moscow for communication to the British Government.
o     As  regards  the  invasion  of the  British embassy at Petrograd I had occasion to-present to Chicherin and Karahan, in addition to my protest and demands for repatria-tion, embodied in my note to Chicherin of the 2nd September, a joint protest drawn upby the neutral diplomatic representatives  at Petrograd  (see above) which I also signed,demanding  the release of all those arrested  at  the embassy, and that the  embassyshould be handed over to me, and stating that the  soviet Government would be  held responsible  in  every  respect for the consequences of this breach  of international  law -;which was quite unique in history.  This  I reported to my Government at The Hague,.through the intermediary  of Chicherin for transmission to the  British legation there,,though  I cannot affirm that  the telegram was  sent.   Chicherin wished to evade  thequestion of the release of persons arrested at the embassy and only agreed to the demand that the embassy should  be&apos; handed over to me,  but I told him plainly that it must beall or nothing, and that  I  would  not consent  to  half measures of this kind.  I have further  demanded  that all  documents seized at  the  embassy shall  be delivered tome.....     The following copy of a letter received from British prisoners in the  fortress ofPeter  and  Paul at  Petrograd,  dated  the  5th September, 1918, accompanied  thereport:      Your Excellency,         We  are not allowed  to write letters.   We will write to you daily, as  the     chance  of  our letters  getting through is very remote.  Our life here is even worse   .  than in Gorokhovaya 2, and in a sense we are being  treated exactly like the Russian  &apos;   officers  and bourgeois, who are being  slowly  starved to death here.  Our only hope     lies in  parcels, but delivery of parcels has been stopped for the moment.   Those     due on  Monday last have not yet been delivered.   It all  depends on the caprice of     some one in authority, and  he seems  very capricious.  Surely we are entitled to be     treated like  prisoners of war and to be inspected by neutrals, to have the right of     buying food, of getting news, of sending letters, of exercise,  of  getting clean linen,     &amp;c.   Apart from the  question of food, that  of  clothing and medical attention are     most important.   All the prisoners here have a chronic diarrhoea, most of us have     now got it.  Requests for a doctor or medicine,  complaints to the commandant, all     receive  no attention.   In short, our treatment is absolutely inhuman.         What follows is a short account of  our treatment since  Saturday last.   We    were never told why we  were arrested, and  from  the first aU  requests,  &amp;c, to see    you have been contemptuously and  rudely refused.   We  reached. Gorokhovaya at     (j P.M. on Saturday, and after questioning of  an aimless sort we were put, at 8 P.M.,    in a room about 25 feet by  15 feet, where there were already about fifty  arrested    Russians, murderers,  speculants (sic), &amp;c.  All beds were already occupied, and we    spent the night between the  three odd chairs,  the  floor, and walking  about.   By    morning we  were  all in  the first stages of verminosity, very dirty,  tired,  and    hungry.  The first food came at 1 T?.M., small bowls of bad fish, soup, and one-eighth    of a lb. of bread.  At 6 P.M. we got  another one-eighth lb. of bread.  We received    the same food ou Monday also.  On Sunday night the room was less full and we    got some  sleep.  By that time we were  also  getting used to  the journey (sic).    Parcels arrived on Monday and eased the  food situation.   On Tuesday at 4 P.M. we    were marched through the streets under escort  here.  The consubs  request for a    vehicle  for our kit was most rudely refused.  Here we were distributed in different    cells, size about 20 feet by 10 feet, in order to make up the number twenty ; in our    cell are thirteen Russians, four of whom are slowly starving to death.   They have    had no  food for three days.   After we had been here thirty-three hours soup came    in at 3  A.M. and one-eighth lb. of bread.  We  could not eat the soup wood, leather,    stones,  mixed with cabbage and paper were its main ingredients.  So we, too, shall    sooner  or later be starved  to death. Our  immediate need  is  parcels,  but it is    essential for  you  to  send  someone  here  on Saturday to see  if they  have  been    delivered and to obtain our receipts.   Otherwise they will not be delivered.         Next is  medical comforts (1)  for  diarrhoea, (2)  aspirin.   We can get none.    Third, is some money.         We will write again to-morrow.   We are not allowed to leave our cells.   The    door is  never opened.   The  w.c. periodically refuses to  work, and the atmosphere    is appalling.         Need  I  say  more, save that  I hope you will lay the substance of  this report    before His Majesty&apos;s Government.

</content>
</cab>
