<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 198-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
APPRECIATION OF  THE ATTACHED EASTERN REPORT  No. LXXXVIII.    NO1 appreciation will be-given  this week, as no subject  has matured sufficientlysince- last week&apos;s report was issued to justify comment..                                                                    M. S.    October, 3, 1918.[898-115]
ETjris  Document is the Property -of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s^jvernment JPrinted for the War Cabinet.SECRET.FOR REFERENCE  ONLY.      EASTERN   REPORT.     No. LXXXVIII.   October 3, 1918.(Incorporating ARABIAN REPORT  N.S. CXV.)CONTENTS.Russia.    Exchange of Officials.    Situation in Pot rograd.    Note from M. chicherin on the Alleged     Arrests iu  Samara.    Allied Subjects at Saratow.    Allied Subjects in Moscow.  Northern Region.    The New Government.  Siberia.    The Oufa Conference,    A Loan wanted.Bulgaria.    Armistice.Tunis and Tripoli.    Projected Rising.Palestine.    After the Victory.Syria..    Capture of Damascus.Arabia1.  Hejaz.    Kecognition of the Belligerent Status of     the Arab Forces.    King Hussein&apos;s Thanks.    The Inhabitants of the Hauran and the     King of Hejaz.  Yemen.    Loheiya.Persia.    The Assyrian Refugees.                                     RUSSIA.     Exchange of  Officials. On the 29th September Sir Mansfeldt Pindlay telegraphed[No. 3472] that the arrival of M. Litvinoff and his party at Bergen  had been reported by the consul at that  place.  On the  following day he telegraphed again [No, 3486]saying that  the departure  of the party  by train had been reported by  the consul,who added that M. Litvinoff had stated that  lie  had  informed his Government of his,arrival in  Norway.  Sir M.  Fiudlay  had  suggested  to  the  Ministry for  ForeignAffairs that  the  party should be detained  at  Honefoss pending satisfactory news of Mr. Lockhart  and  his  party,  and he  thought that the suggestion  would  be,acted on.     Telegraphing  again on the 1st October [No. 3487]  Sir Mansfeldt Findlay said thatM. Litvinoff and  his party  had refused to leave the train at Honefoss and had. arrivedat Christiania where they were being put up by their socialist friends.     M. Litvinoff wished  his  party   to  continue  their journey,  saying  that  theundertaking he had given  to remain  at Christiania till the arrival of Mr.  Loekhartin Finland referred to himself only, and further that it  had no reference to the french officials.   Sir M. Findlay however quoted Mr.  Balfour s telegram  in regard to the first point and pointed  out that it could only  admit of one  interpretation,  whilst as. to  thesecond M.  Chicherin  had   himself agreed  to  the departure  of the French  withMr..Lockhart. Sir M. Findlay added that  if the Russian Government kept its promisehe would do his best to facilitate the journey of M. LitvinofFs party ;  if it did not heand  his party would be bound in honour to return  to England.     The Swedish  charge&quot; d&apos;affaires was, Sir M. Findlay said, telegraphing for instructions as to giving a visa.  He also said that  so far there was  no news of Mr. Lockhart.     Telegraphing again on  the same day [No. 3494] he said that he had been informed by the Ministry for Foreign Affairs that they had telegraphed the information regardingthe departure of M. Litvinoff&apos;s party  from England to their Petrograd legation on the28th September, and had since instructed  the Norwegian  representative  to informM. Chicherin of the arrival  of that party in  Bergen.  Sir M. Findlay had asked thatthese telegrams might  be  repeated and  the Norwegian  representative  instructed to forward them to Moscow.     In his telegram of the 29th September  Sir Mansfeldt Findlay asked  for  definite instructions in regard to the conditions for  the passing of M. Litvinoff and  his partjr       [898-115]                            &quot;      &quot;                       B
 over the Swedish frontier : was this to depend on  Mr. Lockhart being accompanied by the French military attache and consular agents?   Mr. Balfour replied that the under- taking given by M. Litvinoff certainly included those officials.     On the 1st October Mr. Robertson telegraphed [No. 3405] from The Hague -that the following message had been received from the Netherlands Minister at Petrograd :- M. Chicherin has now added to the list  of Russians to be  repatriated  that of Rappo Ginsburg, who appears to have been interned with Baitler.   It  is  evident  that he is augmenting his demands considerably according as the delay becomes greater.     On the same  day Mr. Balfour telegraphed &apos;[No. 2846] to Sir Mansfeldt Findlay informing him that he had received a wireless message from M. Chicherin saying that, though he had received a telegram -from M. Litvinoff fdeclaring his impending departure, he had not yet  received a telegram from  the Norwegian consul,  as asked for.   He added that he was preparing the immediate departure of  Mr. Lockhart  and the other British officials in order that they should cross the Finnish  frontier when M. Litvinoff reached  Norway.   Mr.  Balfour   went  on  to  say that  the  telegram announcing M. Litvinoff&apos;s departure was sent on  the evening of the  27th  September by  the secretary  of the Norwegian legation (who accompanied M.  Litvinoff to Aberdeen) to the  Norwegian  Minister in  London, &quot;who  telegraphed  it  to  Cbristiania -that same evening :  he then instructed  Sir M. Findlay to ascertain whether  full  information of M. Litvinoffs departure from England and  arrival  in Norway was being telegraphed to Moscow.     Situation in Petrograd;-Mr.  Robertson telegraphed  from  The  Hague on  the 28th  September  [No.  33&apos;9&apos;.2] &quot;that information had been received from Petrograd to the effect that everything was being nationalised ;  merchandise was stolen, as well as the clothes of people who were being &quot;turned out of their houses.  Nothing  was respected, the suffering was prodigious,  and the price of food incredible.  The situation was getting worse  daily and &quot;al! &quot;were -leaving who  could do so.  He was evacuating -the British colony.  It was clear that life would be impossible there  during the winter.    Note from M. Ghicherin on the alleged  -Arrests in Samara,  On the 2nd October Sir, Mansfeldt  Findlay telegraphed [No.  3497]  the following translation  of a note addressed by -M.Ghicherin to the neutral legations in Petrograd-oh f he 2-3rd September : Friends who have &quot;escaped from Samara  relate that -12/000 persons  have been arrested., and that all &quot;the &quot;adherents of the Soviets have been  shot; among  those arrested were thirty-five women,-of whom  sixteen, being  wives  of  Bolsheviks,  were shot,  whilst therest  -were  condemned  to be  hanged.  As Samara  is occupied -by  Czecho-Slovaks,  for whom  the Entente Powers are formally responsible, it amounts to occupation by them. We expect you will protest a.s;your share in action :to obtain the liberation-of Entente Subjects &apos;(sic).   We have always  maintained that such political reprisals in  Ententedistricts render necessary measures  of reciprocity, especially in view of such atrocities.  &apos;    Allied Subjects  at :Sara.tow.--Sir Ralph Paget telegraphed-on the*28th September [No. 2848] that information had been -received from the Danish Minister&apos;at Petrograd tothe effect  that  the  British  and French subjects  who had  been arrested at  Saratow [E.R. LXXXVII, p.  3] bad been &quot;released.   He added that  confirmation of the-snooting of several British and  French subjects ;at Vologda had -been Teceived.     Allied  -Subjects  in   Moscow. -Sir  Mansfeldt Findlay   telegraphed  on  the 28th  September   No.  34&apos;54] the following  &quot;summary of information just received from the Norwegian legation at-Petrograd :    The Norwegian attache, Mr. Christensen, Who was in charge of  American interests in  Moscow reported  on &quot;the Tlth &quot;September that the French consul-general, a French general, a French colonel, three British members of the diplomatic mission  and &quot;two  British  consular  officers  had taken  refuge in the American consulate-general which was &quot;under the protection of the Norwegian legation. The  Soviet  had demanded  their surrender  and  Mr.  Christensen  had  protested. M. Chicherin and   M. Zynz-?Bruevitcn, the secretary  of the  Council of  Peoples Commissars, Lad promised not to use force  but had repeated &quot;the demand for surrender. Mr. &quot;Christensen Tj believed) feat M. Chicherin  would endeavour &quot;to avoid violation of Norwegian extra-territorial rights,  but was.afraid that Peters and the extremists might get their way and break into fee consulate  which  was  being watched by Red Guards. Mr. Christensen had been.sent back to Moscow  on the 11th  September with  orders not to surrender the  French and  British &quot;refugees and to urge M. Chicherin to prevent the Red &quot;Guards from violating the American consulate-general.   The  Norwegian, legation
 had reported (no date) that the besieged refugees had so far not been attacked and that the situation seemed somewhat improved. NORTHERN  REGION.     The Neiv Government. Mr. Lindiey telegraphed on the 27th and 28th September [Nos. 208 and 2111 that on the 26th September he had been informed by M. Chaikowsky that all the Ministers would resign and that then he  would form a new Government. In  this  he would be president  and  would  have charge  of foreign  affairs ; Colonel Dourov, the governor-general, would have full control of all matters dealt with by the Ministers of the Interior and  War ; M. Grudistov would,  with  the  aid of a  council, have charge of financial and economic  matters ;  and M.  Gubovski would stay on as Minister of Justice.  That is, the  executive power  would be  in the  hands of four persons.     Later  on  the  same  day   M. Chaikowsky had explained  the  object of  the reconstruction to the allied representatives.   This he said was to retain some form of Government (whilst reducing  civil interference in the administration) as it would have made a bad impression to have left the governor-general alone in power and so to have virtually  set up a military dictatorship.  M. Grudistov, he said, had  consented  to perform all the functions of a leader  and to  preside  over the financial and economic council ; but, as he refused to accept  the responsibility of leadership, M. Mofoclieffi a Cadet member of the fourth Duma would be asked to take his place as minister.   It had also been decided to grant an amnesty to  all concerned in the coup oVetat.     This arrangement, Mr.  Lindiey said, seemed  to offer  good hope for the future, as the most unpractical members of the Government had been removed and the troublesome question of the coup 3&apos;etat cleared away.  But M. Chaikowsky had sprung a new difficulty on  them :  he had made it known that, at the same time  that he announced the new executive, he intended to publish a statement that  all the members  of the  original Government remained as the supreme legislative body to  which  the new executive was responsible.  Mr. Lindiey wrote protesting:  M.  Chaikowsky answered expressing his surprise at the objection of the allied  representatives  at his doing what  he proposed. The matter would, he said, be further discussed, but an  executive body  not responsible to  an  organ of sovereign power was, he thought, inadmissible.   Mr. Lindiey  foresaw that the upshot would be a long fruitless discussion in three languages.     This conversation took place, and in a further telegram [No.  213] Mr. Lindiey said that it had been agreed that a Government of four persons should be  formed and  that this Government should have legislative as well as executive functions.   The four would be  MM.  Chaikowsky and  Gucinski,  Colonel Dourov, and another not yet named. M.  Chaikowsky would be President of the Council and Minister for  Foreign Affairs ; M.  Gucinski, Minister of Justice;  Colonel Dourov, Governor-Genera! ; and the fourth would  have charge of economic  and financial matters, having the assistance  of  the council presided over by M. Grudistov.   The first  two being members of the constituent assembly would, Mr. Lindiey added, be  regarded  as  the only true repositories of  the sovereign power,  but   the  four  together would  form  the  ministerial  council: M.  Chaikowsky&apos;s scruples bad compelled the allied representatives to cease from forcing the idea that the unelected members  should be on exactly the same footing as  the others. SIBERIA.     The Oufa Conference. Mr. Alston telegraphed  on the 24th September [No.  82] that, according to the information he had received, the object of the Oufa conference was to form a central Government which should be responsible to the various provincial Governments and institutions representing Russia and Siberia, and to decide upon the temporary residence and programme of  that central Government.  There were present at it representatives of the Siberian Government  at Omsk,  the  Volga Government at Samara, that of the Urals at Ekaterinburg, as well as representatives of Turkestan, the Volga Tartars, and the Society of the Regeneration of Russia  The provincial Governs ments would be autonomous in regard  to commerce, education, and local matters, but. the central Government would deal with finance, foreign  policy, railways, posts, and telegraphs.  An executive council of five members had been elected, one of them being.M.  Vologotski.                                                               6m-iH     Telegraphing again on the 27th September Mr. Alston said  [No. 90] that informantion had been received from Oufa to the  effect that a very  lukewarm recognitionf,had.
been accorded to the Omsk  Government, whose members  were looked upon as beingnot only of very uncertain principles but also  as  men  of but little note.   Apparentlythere were two political schools in  western  Siberia; one, represented by the  Govern-ments of Ekaterinburg (legally in European Russia) and Samara, wanted an  All-RussianGovernment, whilst the other wanted a Siberian Government distinct from that of Russia ;and it was believed that the latter policy was really that of the Omsk Government,which, Mr. Alston said in a  later telegram [No. 95] had, according to  a  report of the ^vice-consul at Irkutsk, lost prestige on account of the assassinations, which had renderedthe Social Revolutionaries disaffected, so that its position was Tins table.     The result of the conference appeared to be  a compromise, providing provisionallyfor a directorate till the Constituent Assembly could meet in January.     A. Loan  Wanted. Mr. Alston telegraphed  on the 25th September [No. 83] thathe had received a  report from the consular  officer at  Nikolaevsk (in the north of the maritime Province) to  the  effect that the local  authorities  wanted to raise a loan of50,000,000 roubles from the  allies,  pledging as security the  resources of the island  ofSaghalin.  A separate offer, however, was being  made  by the Japanese to provide the required amount on condition that they should  have the right of navigation on theAmur and exclusive mining rights.                                   BULGARIA.     Armistice. On the 27th September General  Franchet  d&apos;expansion^rey was approached by a  Bulgarian officer of high rank, with a flag of truce, asking for an armistice of forty-eight  hours  to permit  the  arrival of two delegates  of  the Bulgarian Government,M. Liupketeff (Minister of  Finance)  and General Loukoff (commander of the secondarmy), who were coining to negotiate the conditions of  an armistice and eventually ofpeace.   The  commander of the allied forces  replied that he  would receive, with allcourtesy, the  representatives of the Bulgarian Government, but he could not consent tothe cessation  of hostilities pending  their arrival.     The delegates arrived in due course, and at noon on Monday an  armistice was signed with, the intention that it should last till  the  final peace settlement.  The mainterms are as follows : That  the Bulgarian army  be immediately demobilized, its arms,munitions, and equipment being stored  at given  centres and placed in allied custody;that  all Greek  and Serbian Territory still occupied  by Bulgarian  forces  be at onceevacuated ;  that  all  Bulgarian means  of transport,  including  the  railways  andBulgarian ships and other craft on the Danube, be placed at the disposal of the allies ;that the allies shall have control of the ports and  navigation  of the Danube  ; that thereshall  be free communication  with Roumania ; that Bulgarian territory be  available for allied operations against the enemy, and that in  particular, strategic points he occupiedby the allied armies, such  occupation  to be  reserved  to British, French, or italian troops ;  and  that Bulgaria  shall cease  henceforth to be  a  belligerent, save  with the-complete consent of the allies.                             TUNIS  AND  TRIPOLI.     Projected Rising. Mr.  Balfour telegraphed to Sir Reginald Wingate on the 26thSeptember [No.  1180]  saying that  the Italian embassy had  stated  that, according  tocredible  reports, a mission of Arab  officers had proceeded from  Turkey to  Austria, andwould sail thence in a submarine to promote a rising in Tunis and Tripolitania.                                   PALESTINE.     After the Victory. General Clayton telegraphed on the 26th and 27th September[Nos. 70, 72  74, 75, 76,  77] that Colonel Storr,  the  military governor  of Jerusalem,had received the congratulations  of a large deputation of notables  representing all the communities in the city;  and that  throughout the provinces  which had been Occupiedprevious to the  recent advance widespread enthusiasm had been excited  by general allenby&apos;s complete defeat of the Turkish army.  The  Bedouins were especially pleasedat Arab forces occupying  Maan.     The conditions  in the  newly occupied territory were satisfactory : no appreciabledamage had  been  done, as the  retirement of the enemy  had been  too hurried.   Thearea cultivated had been less than usual, but  there had been a good harvest, and theinhabitants had enough for their present  needs.   Though somewhat  stunned by the rapid march of events the inhabitants were everywhere very friendly.
      At  Nablus business was being transacted as -usual, and  the  administration was &quot;normal, the local Arab officials having-immediately resumed their duties.  The town itsdlf had  been practically undamaged.   The inhabitants appeared prosperous, -with the -exception, of  course, of the usual poorer-classes.; -all the shops were open,.-and there was -no scarcity of supplies.  The -new conditions appeared to give satisfaction. atr-   At Haifa a large majority -of-the inhabitants, irrespective -of--race or  creed, was^genuinely pleased at the British-occupation.  &quot;The-Ottoman public  debt officials-and the entire staff of the municipality had stayed on, &quot;and the Imperial&apos;Ottoinan Rarik was carrying-on business.  There was  no:serious food shortage, and the sanitary conditions &quot;were good.   The Latin patriarch  was reported to  be in the town-; jhe proposed to return to Jerusalem as  soon as he  was well enough to travel,  being then  somewhat indisjmsed. There were, too, a large number of Jewish  refugees from various colenies, who, as soon as possible, would be repatriated.      In Nazareth the situation was very satisfactory, there was a sufficiency of food, and the municipal administrative council was  working.                                       SYRIA.      Capture  of  Damascus. The  War  Office has  announced  that  troops  of the Australian mounted division entered Damascus during the night of the 30th September. At 6 A.M. on the  1st October the city was occupied by a British force and by a portion -of  the Arab  army of King Hussein.  Over 7,000 prisoners  were taken.   After the surrender, with the exception of necessary guards,  all the allied troops were withdrawn from the  city, and  for  the time being the local authorities remain  responsible for its administration.                                      ARABIA. HEJAZ.      Reeognition of the Belligerent Status  of the Arab Forces. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir Reginald Wingate on the 1st October [No. 1200]  instructing him  to telegraph to King Hussein and  Sherif  Feisal  informing them that the allied Governments  had decided to recognise the belligerent status of the Arab forces, fighting as auxiliaries of the allies  against the common enemy in Palestine and Syria.      On  the  same   day Mr. Balfour  telegraphed to Sir  Rennell Rodd [No. 1485] iuforming him that this had been done with the concurrence of the French Government and expressing the  hope that the Italian Government would concur in the recognition.      King Hussein&apos;s Thanks. Sir  Reginald Wingate telegraphed on the 26th September [No.  1429] that King Hussein had acknowledged  the receipt of the messages recently sent  him  [E.R. LXXXVII, p. 6] and  begged that  the Foreign Office would convey to the officers in  camp at Grantham and to the  Manchester Syrian Association his sense of the honour they had done  him and his great  pleasure at  receiving the expression of their good feeling,  which reflected the honour and dignity of their fathers and their grandfathers.   At  the  same time he  expressed his boundless thanks  to the British Government  for its solicitude for, and care of,  the Arabs and their  affairs, and to the Foreign Office for forwarding the messages to him.      The  Inhabitants of  the Hauran and the King of Hejaz. On the 25th September a telegram  was  sent  from the G. II.Q., Egypt, notifying that all the inhabitants of the Hauran had come over  to the King of Hejaz.   The authority for this statement was a report which  had been received from the  intelligence  officer attached to Sherif Feisafs forces. YEMEN.      Loheiya. Sir  Reginald  Wingate telegraphed on the  25th September [No. 1415] that it was reported that Idrisi&apos;s troops had evacuated Loheiya on account of the water difficulty  ; but the situation was not very clear.  Ganda and Atn Gomrie were still in the possession of Idrisi&apos;s troops.                                       PERSIA.      The  Assyrian  Refugees. Mr. Barclay telegraphed  from Washington on  the 16th September [No. 4151] saying that  the Assyrian National  Council  would  be most
grateful for any information in regard to  a rumour that  45,000 of their compatriots-had fled from Urumia to Hamadan in the hope of reaching the British lines and that15*000 of them had been massaged on the way.    This telegram was repeated to Teheran and in reply  thereto  -Sir  P. Cox, on the25th  September,,  transmitted [No. 840] a telegram from Hamadan to the following effect: About 59,000 refugees had reached Hamadan, and if  another 8,000  wej-eadded for those &quot;missing&quot; between Urumia and Hamadan, it would, it was considered!be a liberal estimate.   It was impossible to form any  accurate  idea of the number ofAssyrians among them.  The native Christian population  of  Urumia  had been  aboxf$-75,000, but some 20,000 of them were Armenians.   The fate  of those who had  stayed.on in  Urumia was  unknown.o

</content>
</cab>
