<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 311-316</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government;]Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRET.FOR REFERENCE ONLY.        EASTERN  REPORT.        No. CIV.  Januamj 23, 1919.(Incorporating ARABIAN REPORT N.S. CXXXI.)CONTENTS.Russia.    -Bolshevik Atrocities.    The Hungarian Prisoners.  Northern Territory.    The Government.  Siberia.    General Semenoff.    M. Sazonoff.    Supreme Military Command.  Southern Russia.    General Denikin in Supreme Command.Poland.    M. Paderewskfs Cabinet.    Poles and Ukruinans.    irilesia and  Poland.    Bolshevik Chinese Troops.    Imprisoned Zionist Leaders.    Attempted  Coup d&apos;l tat.Lithuania.    The Bolshevik Invasion.Rumania.    M. Bratiano.    Relief.Turkey.    Cabinet Reconstructed.    Anatolia.    Economic Conditions.Morocco.    Position of Rsiisuli.Syria and Palestine.    The Lebanese Deputation.Arabia.    King Hussein to be represented at the     Peace Conference.    King Hussein and Ibn Saud.    The tlejaz  Subsidies.Persia,    The Shah and the Cabinet.    The Cossack Division.                                     RUSSIA.     Bolshevik Atrocities. On the 18th January Mr. Alston reported that he had beengiven information in regard to what was giiing on in Russia, which  showed that theferocity  of the Turks in Armenia  was as  nothing in comparison with  that of theBolsheviks.  His informant was the chief of the American Red Cross mission who had just returned from the neighbourhood of Perm.  This  gentleman  said  that for rankbarbarous  brutality the mutilations and  tortures of the  wounded and  others baffleddescription.   He had also shown him a proclamation containing the regulations for the(?)  &quot; matiimonialisation &quot; of women  between the  ages  of 17  and  32, which had beenposted in  Saratov ;  regulations, enforced under severe penalties, which, he  said, could hardly have been surpassed in bestial ingenuity by the denizens of hell.     The Hungarian Prisoners. In a  wireless message  of the  Russian Government,.printed in  last weeks. Report [p. 2], it was stated that the  Hungarian prisoneis hadeither gone home or were on  their way there.  Three  days later, Kith January, Countde  Salis sent the following telegram from Home : The primate of Hungary has addressedan  urgent  appeal  to  the Pope asking if  news can be obtained respecting  the fate  ofHungarian prisoneis in Russia, begging  that something may be done to secure eithertheir return to Hungary or at least their internment in conditions of  safety where theycan be fed.     It appears that there are some hundred  thousand  Hungarians, originally prisoners in Siberia, who for want of transport and  owing to disorders in Russia could not return home after the peace of Brest-Litovsk.NORTHERN TERRITORY.     The Government. On the 17th January Mr.  Lindley reported  f&quot;No.  41] that  hehad been infoimed by the minister for foreign affairs that he  had decided to  leave forParis, via  London.  He would leave M. Zubov as acting president of the Government       [756]-74                                     &quot;                       B
and minister of agriculture.   General Miller would  be  governor-general and ministerfor foreign affairs;  General  Marashevski assistant-governor-general ;  and M.  Ignatieffminister of tbe interior.     M.  Zubov  was  formerly assistant  mayor of  Vologda,  and  at  present  wasminister of education and secretary of the Government.   He was a man of little energyor capacity, and had been chosen because he was the only member left of the Govern-ment who had been elected to any office by  universal suffrage.  He belonged to theextreme left wing of the cadets.     Mi1.  Lindiey had heard that the changes had caused some  excitement amongst theparties  of the  right,  amonj  whom  M.   Ignatieff was  suspected  owing  to hisf? close] relations with the social revolutionaries.   Personally he regarded his appoint-ment with favour as he had influence with the people, and, although he was lacking in[? administrative] experience and impulsive, he had. both energy and capacity.SIBERIA.     General  Semenoff. On the  20th January Mr.  Alston  transmitted [No. 80] a message  TNo.  63]  dated the 17th  January,  from Sir  Charles Eliot.   The highcommissioner  said  that  he  had been  officially  informed that a telegram  had beenreceived  from  Semenoff requesting  that a commission  should be  sent to  Chita to enquire  into  his  conduct  and  clear  him  of the  charges of treason :  his failure torecognise Koltchak bad, he  said,  been  due to a misunderstanding.   Sir Charles Eliotadded that the  commission  asked for had  been promised ; and on tbe 20th January,Mr. Alston reported [No. 84] that  die officer  in command of  the 3rd division at Chitahad been instructed by General Otani to guarantee the safety  of the commissioner andwitnesses sent there.     In his telegram of the 17th January Sir Charles Eliot also reported that GeneralSemenoff had intimated that he wished  to  be sent  to the front, and tha,t he bad been invited to  go to Omsk to consult as  to  his future post an invitation  which he,Sir Charles Eliot, thought would not be accepted by General Semenoff till he had beenexculpated.     M. Sazonoff.-The Foreign Office informed Mr. Alston on the 21st January [No. 60]that it had-been informed by the Russian representative in London that he had receiveda telegram from M.  Sazonoff intimating  that he  had accepted the appointment offoreign minister in the Omsk Government.     The Supreme Military Command. Telegraphing to Paris  on the 20th January theForeign Office said  that General Knox  had reported from Omsk on the 14th Januarythat  General  Janiu had been accepted  as commander-in-chief of  tbe allied forces(excluding the Russian) [?]  west of Lake  Baikal, and that,  in order to secure unity of action, the  Russian command would conform, to the general  conduct of operations.SOUTHERN RUSSIA.     General Denikin in Supreme Command. On the 21st January the Foreign Officeinformed  Mr.  Alston  [No.  60]  that M.  Neratoff had  reported to  the Russianrepresentative in London that in agreement with  General  Krasnoff,  ataman  of the don, and of General Filimonoff, ataman of the Kouban, the commander-in-chief of theRussian  volunteer army  had  taken  the  supreme command of all  the naval andmilitary  forces operating in  the south of Russia ; and that an order of the day to that effect was  signed  by  General Denikin, in  the  presence  of General Krasnoff, on the.26th December.                                    POLAND.     M.  Paderewsk^s  Cabinet. RetifeFs   agent  telegraphed  from   Paris  on the 19th January  that  M. Paderewski had formed  a cabinet  in which,  in addition  to being prime minister, he was minister for foreign affairs.  The other ministers, he said, were as follows:  M.  Wojoiechowski, interior ; M.  Honcia,  commerce and  industry; M. Englich, finance ;  M. Jauiszewski, public health; M. Eberhardt, communications; M.  Kinde, post-office;  M.  Janicki,  agriculture ;  M. Przesmycki,  arts and culture; M. Iwanowski, labour and public  welfare ; Colonel Wroczynski, war ; M.  Mihkiewicz, food supply;  M. Supinski, justice  ; M.  Pruchnik (? Prochink),  public works.  The last five were members of M. Moraczewskis cabinet.               ......            .
     Poles  and Ukrainians. -On  the  loth  January,  Colonel  Wade reported  that information had  been received to the  effect that an armistice was wished for by theUkrainans.  The Poles were apparently in the same frame of mind ;  but neither side-would take the first step.  With the approval of the chief of the general staff, he had sentCaptain  Johnson  to  Lemberg to call on both sides to stop fighting and  negotiate an armistice, believing as  he did that it was essential for the Poles to be freed from  theLemburg campaign and to concentrate on the eastern front.     Telegraphing again on  the 17th January Colonel Wade said that he had  sent aletter to the  Ukrainan  commander asking  him to  send delegates for  the  purpose of discussing  the possibility  of an armistice  being arranged.  He had done this after consulting  the Polish generals.     Silesia and Poland. Sir Horace Rumbold reported on the 17th January [No. IS4]that he had received a telegram from Mr. Kenney from Vienna (who was there en route for Warsaw!,  asking him to obtain permission  from the Swiss  Government  for a delegation  from the national Radah of upper Silesia, to travel through  Switzerland inorder to proceed to  Paris to state their case for the incorporation of upper Silesia in poland.  It was, however, not possible for him to apply, on  behalf of persons who werenot British subjects, for permission to enter  Switzerland, as the Swiss Government wasvery strict in these matters.     Bolshevik Chinese  Troops.-On the 16th January, Sir Horace Rumbold  reported[No. 123] that be had  received an official  note from M. Zaleski informing  him, under instructions from the  Polish Government, that the latter had received (? representations)to the effect  that (? Bolsheviks) had introduced Chinese guards, who were known fortheir ferocity and  cruelty  into (? villages).  The  presence  of  these Chinese  in  the villages was a direct menace to  the lives  and property of all the inhabitants without distinction of nationality.     Imprisoned  Zionist Leaders. On   the 28th  December Lord Kilmarnock  tele-graphing [No. 3953J from Copenhagen  reported  that  his attention had again been called to the imprisonment of our Zionist  leaders ;  which  the Zionist bureau said was regarded as an affront to us, as they had been throughout the war .active  sympathizerswith Great Britain.     In reply to an enquiry made on this subject, Sir Horace Rumbold  reported, on the16th January [No. 121], that the Polish Government deeply regretted the necessity fordetaining these men as.hostages: the  necessity having arisen from the Zionists in theeastern part of Galicia having openly ranged themselves on  the side of Ukraina.   Theywould be released as soon as the military situation in Lemberg permitted.     Attempted Coup d&apos;Etat. The following message was sent out from the wireless-stations of the Russian  Government on  the 13th  January:  The  Warsaw  newspaper&quot; Peranna  &quot; reports that on the night of the 5th  January the National Democrats of&quot;Warsaw  made an attempt to oust M. Pilsudski.   M. Paderewski requested M. Pilsudskito  call  a  national  government  of all three  parts of  Poland,  and  M.  Pilsudskirefused.    The premier, the minister of foreign  affairs, the  director of militia, andother officials  were arrested ; and the abolition of the old government was announced by proclamation.     In regard to this a telegram was received on the 18th January  from Colonel Wadereporting that the attempt had failed, and  that the projected revolution had  been acomplete failure.                                  LITHUANIA.     The Bolshevik Invasion. On the 1 9th January Sir Horace Rumbold transmitted[No. 148 1 a telegram he had received from the representative,  in  Switzerland, of the lithuanian provisional  Government, M.  Daumatas, who,  after saying that the  RussianBolshevik invasion threatened to make Lithuania a country of ruins, asked for help fromthe allies.   In the course of his telegtam he stated that the Bolsheviks had imprisonedfour Lithuanian ministers and other official  persons at Vilna.                                   RUMANIA.     M. Bratiano. On the 19th January Mr. Wratislaw transmitted [No. 32] a messageJNo. 23] dated&apos;the 11th January from Sir George Barclay, reporting  that M. Bratiano-       [756]-74&apos;                              .                         B 2
had suddenly decided to go to Paris for the purpose of making an attempt to obtain a proper hearing at the Congress.     Relief. On the 22nd  January, the Foreign Office informed [No. 4(5] Sir GeorgeBarclay that cargoes of flour were being sent for Rumanian relief                                    TURKEY.     Cabinet Reconstructed. On the 19th January Admiral Calthorpe reported [No. 141]that Tewfik Pasha  had  reconstructed  his  cabinet.   The  principal  change was theremoval  of Mustafa  Arif, who  was  said to be a  Crypto-Jew  in sympathy  with theC.U.P.  The new cabinet was slightly more homogeneous than the old one, but almost as weak.ANATOLIA.     Economic Conditions. The War Office &quot;Summary of Information &quot; for the 20thJanuary gives the following report of a  British officer, repatriated from  imprisonmentin Turkey, of the state of supply, transport, &amp;c, in Anatolia:      There is plenty of food in  Anatolia, much actual destitution, and a vast inflationof prices.     Tbe Smyrna fig-harvest has been bad for the last two years.   The grape harvest inAnatolia is well below the average owing (i)  to the ravages of phylloxera, (2) to thescarcity of labour.   Figs, raisins, and sultanas  are of course a staple article of diet, and stocks, in spite of bad years, exceed the normal local demand, as there is now no export.Grain  harvests are from fair to gco 1 ; more land is under cultivation than in 19 16 or 1917and in most places there is a good return.     In spite of all this, prices have risen from 3,000 to 4,000 per cent.  Thus grain (orbread  in Yuzgat was 40  piastres per oke, in  Kedos  20-30, in Smyrna 25-30 (peaceprice about lj piastres) ; meat has risen from 2 piastres to&apos;60 per  oke, egos from being12-18  for a piastre now cost each from 2 piastres (Ouchak)  to 3^ (Kara Hissar) and-10  (Smyrna);  native  butter has risen  from  16  piastres per oke  to 180  or 200(Kedos) and 300 and upwards in Smyrna.   Of course with imported articles a greatrise  is natural,  paraffin having gone up from 18  piastres per tin  to   T. 19, sugarfrom 2  piastres per oke to 280  [for  a short time at Kedos) and 450 at Smyrna, tea to  T. 20 per oke ; but in the  case of local products  the rise is  due  wholly to threefacts, viz. :                (1.) The original  distrust of the: paper currency.              (2.) Speculation,              (3.) Cost of transport,     For cash most local products could be bought in the country at  little more thanpeace prices.     The gold   T.  was  quoted in  Smyrna in, January 1918 at 747  piastres; theaverage rate of exchange is 600 piastres (November  1918).  But in  practice no coinis used  in  trade ; the exchange rate is merely a  concern for  speculators, and the purchasing power of gold is far greater than the exchange rate would show.     The bulk of the  Anatolian Turks are agriculturists  working  on a small scale.The peasant goes on the  principle of  barter;  the  nominal value  of the  exchangemedium does not  affect him; he reckons corresponding  values, and if  calico goes up 100  per cent., he simply doubles the price of  his eggs; in fact, in some districts, plainbarf r has to some extent replaced ordinary  purchase.  The peasant, therefore, has notsuffered  at all  by the depreciation of the currency, and  would not  sutler if thatdepreciation were  definitely  fixed.    The  non-producing town element, the middle-men,  Ac,   have suffered  very greatly.  Very  many,  both  Greeks and Turks, butparticularly  the former, have died  and are  dying of hunger.  In August 1916 women were  dying  in  the streets  of  Adana,  in the  richest food-producing distiict ofAnatolia;  during the winter months of 1916-1917 the  average  death  rate amongstthe Greek  element  alone at  Kastamuni was  about  10 per diem; in  Yuzgat in theisummer  of  1918 the  greater part of the population was virtually  destitute, and deathswere reckoned at several hundreds a week.     The bigger landowners are  holding up. stocks and gambling on the  ultimate  valueof the paper-money ; should this be fixed at the  present value they will hisve  madeprofits;  they are expecting the Entente Powers to guarantee Turkish paper at face value, in which  case they would make their fortunes.                           &apos; &quot; 1
     Owing to WAR EXIGENCIES THE DIFFICULTIES  of TRANSPORT ARE GREAT,  BUT THESE HAVEbeen ENORMOUSLY INCREASED BY CORRUPT PRACTICE.  The MONOPOLY OF RAILWAY WAGGONS&apos; HAS-been GRANTED TO INFLUENTIAL TURKS OR HAS BEEN  PURCHASED BY SPECULATORS, AND THE RATESCHARGED BY THESE MEN ARE FABULOUS, AND  FULLY  ACCOUNT FOR  THE  HIGH   PRICES OF  LOCAPRODUCTS IN TOWN  AREAS, THE CONDITIONS OF  WHICH HAVE OF COURSE  REACTED ON country districts.   THUS THE SON OF  A FORMER AMBASSADOR TO ENGLAND &quot; POSSESSES &quot; ONE WAGGONon THE Smyrna-Kara HISSAR line,  WHICH  FOR  THE LAST  TWO YEARS HAS BROUGHT  HIM  in  T. 700 WEEKLY.  A CONTRACTOR IN  SMYRNA RECENTLY OBTAINED   T. 2,500 FOR A SINGLE run of BIS  TWO WAGGONS.  THIS  SYSTEM OF EXPLOITATION HAS  EXTENDED TO OTHER MEANS OFTRANSPORT,  THE BULK OF THE CARTS BEING CONTROLLED BY GOVERNMENT, e.g., THE PRESENT HIREof A TWO HORSE  CART FROM KECLOS TO OUCHAK (66  KILOMETRES)  IS   T. 20.                                   MOROCCO.     The Position  of Raisuli. THE &quot; TIMES &quot; OF THE 21ST JANUARY PUBLISHED A TELEGRAMFROM ITS TANGIER CORRESPONDENT IN REGARD TO  THE COST  OF  MAINTENANCE  OF THE SPANISHZONE.  To  THIS AN EDITORIAL NOTE WAS  APPENDED CONTAINING THE  FOLLOWING STATEMENT:&quot; THE SEAPORTS APART, THE VIRTUAL RULER OF THE  MAJOR PART  OF THE ZONE IS THE CHIEFTAINBaisuli.&quot;     &quot; THE SPANISH AMBASSADOR DEALT WITH THIS IN A  LETTER, PUBLISHED IN THE &apos; TIMES &apos; OFTHE 23RD  JANUARY, IN WHICH  HE WROTE AS  FOLLOWS : CONTRARY TO  THE ASSERTION THEREINMADE, ALLEGIANCE IS PAID TO THE LOCAL CHIEFTAIN  RAISULI ONLY  BY A CERTAIN NUMBER OF TRIBESINHABITING THE HILL DISTRICT TO THE SOUTH OF THE  TOWN OF TETUAN, AS  ALSO THE MOUNTAINRANGE OF THE DJEBALA.  A STUDY OF ANY LARGE-SCALE MAP OF THE  SPANISH PROTECTORATE inMOROCCO WILL SOON  SHOW THAT THIS TERRITORY IS BUT A FRACTION OF THE ZONE PLACED BY TREATYUNDER SPANISH SWAY.     &quot; This IS ENOUGH IN ITSELF TO DISPOSE OF THE IMPLICATION THAT THE RECOGNITION of SPANISHAUTHORITY  IN MOROCCO is CONFINED TO THE SEAPORTS.  THE  SPANISH ZONE IN THAT COUNTRY HASOFTEN BEEN APTLY COMPARED TO AFGHANISTAN ON ACCOUNT OF ITS TOPOGRAPHY  AND THE.WARLIKECHARACTER  OF ITS PEOPLES.   ALTHOUGH THE PROCESS  OF PENETRATION IN  SUCH A  LAND MUSTNECESSARILY BE  DIFFICULT, COSTLY, AND GRADUAL, J^PAIN HAS  LAID DOWN TWO RAILWAYS,  ONE OFTHEM BUILT DURING THE WAR, BUILT ROADS, SCHOOLS, BOTH EUROPEAN AND NATIVE, LIGHTHOUSES,AND  TWO LARGE  PORTS, BESIDES OTHERS OF  MINOR IMPORTANCE, OPENED DISPENSARIES, HOSPITALS,AND VETERINARY STATIONS FOR THE NATIVES, AND CARRIED OUT OTHER PUBLIC WORKS.&quot;                            SYRIA AND  PALESTINE.     The   Lebanese   Deputation. GENERAL  CLAYTON REPORTED  ON THE   18TH- JANUARY[No. 8] that THE BRITISH REPUTATION FOR FAIR  PLAY WAS BEING GRAVELY PREJUDICED BY  WHATWAS LOOKED UPON AS ACTIVE DISREGARD FOR THE WISHES OF [? THE MAJORITY] FOLLOWING CLOSELYUPON THE PRONOUNCEMENT OF SELF-DETERMINATION.  THE CAUSE OF THIS was THE DEPARTURE OFA LEBANESE DEPUTATION FOR FRANCE, GREAT  BITTERNESS  HAVING BEEN  PROVOKED  BY THEINJUSTICE, AS it IS REGARDED, OF ALLOWING A PACKED DEPUTATION TO PROCEED to EUROPE WHILSTOTHER  AND MURE REPRESENTATIVE GROUPS HAVE  BEEN STOPPED.   THERE  APPEARED TO BE no immediate RISK OF A  SERIOUS OUTBURST, BUT THERE COULD BE  NO DOUBT THAT IT WOULD BENECESSARY  TO RETAIN AN EFFECTIVE ARMY OF OCCUPATION FOR MANY YEARS TO COME, IF, IN ADDITIONto THE ZIONIST  PROGRAMME, THE AGREEMENT OF 1916 in REGARD TO SYRIA  AND PALESTINE WERERATIFIED AND AN ATTEMPT MADE TO EXECUTE IT.     TELEGRAPHING AGAIN ON  THE  20TH JANUARY [NO.  10] GENERAL  CLAYTON SAID  THATPROTESTS FROM  VARIOUS  PARTS  OF SYRIA  AND PALESTINE,  INCLUDING THE  LEBANON ITSELF, had reached GENERAL ALLENBY ; AND DEMANDS HAD BEEN MADE FOR THE IMMEDIATE RECALL OF THEDEPUTATION IN QUESTION,  or, IF  THAT COULD NOT BE EFFECTED,  AUTHORITY   TO  SEND  OTHERDEPUTATIONS TO REPRESENT THE OPINIONS OF THOSE WHO CLAIMED TO BE IN THE MAJORITY.  InONE  PETITION WHICH  HAD BEEN RECEIVED IT  WAS  PLAINLY STATED THAT THE SIGNATURES TO THEOBJECTIONABLE PETITION HAD BEEN IMPROPERLY OBTAINED.                                     ARABIA.     King  Hussein to  be represented at the Peace Conference.  On THE  21ST JANUARY [No. 102]  THE  FOLLOWING MESSAGE WAS SENT TO Sir REGINALD  WINGATE :      FEISAL HAS SECURED THE ADMISSION TO THE PEACE  CONFERENCE OF TWO HEJAZ DELEGATES.THESE CAN BE DRAWN AT WILL FROM A PANEL, BUT EACH DELEGATE MUST HAVE  CREDENTIALS FROMTHE ARAB GOVERNMENT.  PLEASE OBTAIN FROM KING HUSSEIN SIX FORMS OF &quot; PLENIPOTENTIAIRE &quot;IN ARABIC, EMPOWERING THE HOLDERS TO REPRESENT HIS MAJESTY AND SIGN TREATIES, ON his behalf.
     King Hussein and Ibji Saud. The Foreign Office informed Sir Reginald Wingateon the 17th January [No. 75] thata telegram was being sent to Baghdad notifying thatthe instructions in regard to an ultimatum to Ibn Saud were  cancelled.   The wholequestion had  been carefully considered in  the  light of recent developments, and moreespecially of the surrender of  Medina;  and  the conclusion  was  that nothing wasto be gained for the present by further intervention  in the dispute between the ruler ofNejd and the King of liejaz.     The Hejaz Subsidies. In  reply to a telegram from the Foreign Office  in regard tothe  reduction  of  the  Hejaz  subsidies Sir  Reginald Wingate  telegraphed on  the16th January [No. 93] that he  recommended  that the 8O,0O0L a month,  which wasformerly allotted  to Prince Feisal at Akaba and had since been used for the maintenanceof the Arab administration, should be continued for  the latter object and be paid throughthe commander-in-chief.   As to the 120,OO0Z.  a month paid directly to King Husseinthrough himself, Sir Reginald advised its continuance for the present.  It could not, hesaid, be safely reduced till the Turkish garrisons had  been completely evacuated;  the thought that the  time of plenty was nearing its end  made the tribesmen  restive, anda  sudden cutting  off - of doles would  lead to disorders  which  might have seriousconseqrzences in view of the Khurma situation.                                     PERSIA.     The Shah and the Cabinet. Sir Percy Cox reported on the 15th January [No. 32]that the Shah appeared  to have come to bis senses now that he had been warned that financial and  moral support would be withdrawn if he did not put an end to his intrigues.He had  already  warned the  princes  and democrats that their activities must cease,activities which he had previously encouraged : and he had  openly announced that  hehad decided that  hearty  support of the present cabinet was  best for his own interestsand those of the country.     The Cossack Division. In his  telegram of  the 15th  January, Sir  Percy Coxpointed  out  that the importance  of  the officer in command of this division had been greatly reduced by the intimation, which had  been made through the Russian legation,that the monthly  subvention  would for  the  present  be paid through  the Persiancabinet.o

</content>
</cab>
