<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 323-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for&apos;the War  CabinetSECRET.FOR REFERENCE  ONM,Y.            EASTERN   REPORT.             No, CVI.   February 6,  1919.(Incorporating ARABIAN REPORT  N.S. No.  CXXXIII.)CONTENTS.Russia.    A Message for M. Trotsky.    The Soviet Government and jittie sug-      gested Conference.    Bolshevik Atrocities.    An  Englishman^  Experiences  of  the      Bolsheviks.  Ukraina.    Soviet Proclamation.  Siberia,    Proclamation to the Army.    Feeling  at Irkutsk iu regard to the pro-      posed Conference.    The Japanese  and Admiral Koltchak.    Attitude towards the Allies.  Turkestan,    Arrest of Allied Subjects.Poland.    Internal Conditions.    The Czech Attack.    Settlement of the differences between      Poles  and Czechs.    Elections for the Diet.    Poles and Germans.Rumania.    The Dobrudja.Greece.    Claims at the Peace Conference.Turkey,    Escape of Reshid Bey.    The Arrests.    Demand for the  Surrender of certain      Officers and Officials.Syria.    The Reported Agreement between Prince      B&apos;feisal and M. Clemenceau.    The Syrian Union Party.Arabia.    Ibn Saud and Fakhri Pasha.Mesopotamia.    Native opinion in regard to the future      Government,Kurdistan.    RowanduzAfghanistan.    Monthly Report.                                        RUSSIA.     A Message for M. Trotsky. On the  1st February  the Foreign  Office sent  thefollowing message to Lord Derby for transmission by wireless from Paris : &quot; To the People&apos;s Commissary, Trotsky.  Copies to Lenine, Chicherine, and Altvater.     &quot; Am taken prisoner by British.  Am being kept, together with Niniuk,* as  hostagefor all British civilian,  naval,  and military prisoners in your  hands, as well as CaptainSchoonjans.f  Am at present receiving good treatment, but am informed that my fate andfuture depends solely  on treatment given by you to  British.   British authorities are willing to release men in return for all British civilian, naval,  and military who  areprisoners in  Russia or  are prevented from leaving Russia, as well as Captain Scboonjans,.Beg you to take all necessary steps.                                                        (Signed)      RASKOLNIKOFE. J     The  Soviet  Government  and   the  suggested  Conference. The  following  wireless message was sent from Moscow on the 3rd February :      On the receipt of the radio-telegram  from Paris announcing the decision to invitethe existing Russian Government to Prince&apos;s Island, the peophfs commissary for foreignaffairs  sent  a  radio-telegram to Vorovsky,  in Stockholm,  and  to the  editor of the    * A member of the Petrograd Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Council.    f A Belgian mercantile marine captain.    j The Russian Soviet  Governments chief naval commissary, taken at the time of  the capture of  theBolshevik destroyers iu the Baltic.     F756 1271                                                                B
&quot; Populaire,&apos;jS requesting them, in view  of wide  enquires,  to  reply  to the questionsinspired  by the report.  The people&apos;s commissary pointed out  that  no invitation hadbeen  received  by the Soviet  Government, adding that the convocation of a  special conference on a distant  island must be  surrounded by impenetrable  mystery.   WhyPrince&apos;s Island ?   Surely there is a more suitable  place.   The very problems  of thespecial conference mentioned in the Paris radio-telegram appear unclear.  Where theSoviet power has been established, there counter-revolution  has been conquered and complete calm reigns.   Where, thanks to the support  of foreign bayonets, reactionarygroups reign, there civil war continues and is unavoidable.  The sole means to put an end to this is to discontinue  the support of counter-revolution from without.  Mediation initself is impossible, as the proposal comes from Governments actually participating  inthe struggle against us,  and occupying a part of our  territory with  their armies.  Aproposal to cease military activities was not made at the time when the Soviet republicexperienced difficulties in the military sphere, but is made now when counter-revolutionis on  the eve of its final crash.     In view of  the  possibilities  at Vorovsky&apos;s  command  to  procure  informationinaccessible to us, the people&apos;s commissary especially requested him to say whether anyannexationist aims were actually being  entertained with regard to Archangel, Siberia,Baku, Ashabad, and Rostov-on-the-Don.   Whether that radio reached its addressee isunknown to us,  but  Maklakov, who is in Paris now, in his  interview for the Americanpress, according to a  transmitted  radio-telegram, says: &quot; Chicherin, in answer  to the invitation to the peace conference, has demanded  guarantees and more exact explana-tions.&quot;  As no other document with tbe signature of the commissary for foreign affairs had been transmitted, it is  clear that  that radio had reached the notice of Maklakov inParis, and, therefore, of the French Government.  In view of this, the  commissary forforeign affairs on the 31st January sent for transmission to  M. Pichon a radio-telegrampointing out that, except for the enquiry addressed to Vorovsky  and the &quot; Populaire,&quot;no other announcements on  this question, were made  by  him ; that tbe  demand forguarantees and elucidations  could have been addressed only to the French Governmentand not to the editor of a French newspaper, and only in the event of the actual  receiptof a diplomatic document, whereas no document on the matter had been received ; andthat  the  people&apos;s commissary could not have made any demands; and could not havegiven any answer whatsoever in connexion with an invitation to  all the  Governmentsof Bussia which has not been received.    The following wireless message  signed  by  M. Chicherin  was  sent out on the4th February :     As to the complaints often made m  the  press of the Entente countries concerninginternational&quot; revolutionary  propaganda, the Russian Soviet Government [?  whileunwilling] to limit the liberty of the revolutionary  press, declares that it is ready, ifthere be occasion, to enter  into a general  agreement with the Entente  Powers on their undertaking  not to interfere in Russian internal affairs.    On the  basis indicated, the  Russian Soviet  Government is disposed to enter intoimmediate  [? conference] on  Prince&apos;s Island  or some other place, be it with all theEntente Powers or with some of  them separately,  or even  with some Russian politicalgroups at the request  of the Entente Powers.  The . Russian Soviet  Government  begsthe Powers of the Entente to inform it without delay to what place its representativesare to go, and also the date  of the meeting and the route which, is  to  be followed.    Bolshevik Atrocities [E.R. No.  CIV, p.  I].-On  the   29th January  Mr.  Alstontransmitted.  [No.  122], a message from  Sir  Charles  Eliot [No. 91] in regard to the proclamation referred to Mr. Alston in a previous  telegram.    The high commissioner said that a similar proclamation had been shown him by the vice--cOnsui at  Omsk and strongly  suspected that  the one seen by Mr. Alston wasidentical with  it : if  so, it  should be made use  of with great caution.  Most peoplethought it a  hoax: it was  not dated, the original was not forthcoming, and only an english translation was known.  Further, on  the copy  seen by him there was a note  tothe effect that it was  an anarchist production.  As  to the nationalisation of women, hehad never been able to verify the reports though they were  current in various towns ofEuropean Russia.     Mr. Alston  added  that he  had  consulted  the chief of the  American Red Crossmission (who, it will be remembered, was  his informant) and had ascertained that on hiscopy  also there was a note declaring it to be an anarchist proclamation.   His informantdid not regard  the proclamation as a hoax, and was  telegraphing for further information
from the source near Perm whence he obtained the document.   He said tha,t the decreehad been posted in Saratoff and  thereabouts,  and some families had been  so  terrifiedthat they had fled from the place with&apos;their daughters.     An Englishman&apos;s Experiences of the Bolsheviks. On the 2nd February Mr. Alstontransmitted [No. 136] a message from  Sir Charles Eliot (dated  the 31st  January) inwhich  lie reported a conversation he had had with a Mr. Thornasson, a British subjectwho had lived  at  Lisva, between  Perm and Ekaterinburg, until the  17th December,when it was taken.     Mr. Thomasson&apos;s picture of the Bolsheviks was less lurid than the usual one ; though he said that he believed conditions in Moscow and Petrograd were-terrible,  much worse than in eastern Russia.   He said, too, that they should n&apos;ot be treated with as if they were a political party- though he had already said that, considered as a machine for executingits own purposes, he thought their administration more energetic and efficient than anyRussian  Government be had known.  The peasants were opposed to  them for various reasons,  one  being that they  were subjected  to  unnecessary  requisitions  ; whilst the workmen did much less  work than formerly and had a much higher wage.     He  said that life at Lisva was tolerable till the attempt was  made on Lenin&apos;s life.After  that  attempt terrorism  began,  and many  Were shot there and elsewhere for noapparent reason : he thought that wholesale murder or bodily torture was the exception,but he confirmed the reports of people having been led out to be shot several times beforethe sentence was executed, and said that many became insane under the strain.  orders were received for the arrest  of all French and  British  : he himself  had been  able to hide,and  bad only been under arrest for a short time.     There were  in  the town  something  over a thousand officials of one kind  andanother, who between them drew some six million  roubles  salary.  They also  occupiedthe houses of the upper and middle  classes and had plenty of provisions.   The soldierstoo were- well supplied  with  food, whilst a quarter of a pound of bread a day was the portion of a Non-Bolshevik.     He  had heard  nothing of the nationalization of women.  Only  civil marriageswere allowed though the churches were not closed ; their bells, however, were not rung,and  soldiers were forbidden  to attend them.     As  to the  army,  Mr.  Thomasson said  that it  was well disciplined,  though  thesoldiers  were allowed to loot  freely,  and he believed it to be still formidable.   Theofficers who were forced to  serve apparently did not mind their position as  much as one might have expected.UKRAINA.     fiowet-Proclamation. The following proclamation to  all governments and peopleshas been sent out  through  the  wireless stations of the Russian Government.   It isdated  from  Kharkoff,  the  28th January,   and signed by  M.  Rakovski, Chairmanof  the Ukrainan provisional  workers&apos;  and  peasants  Government and  people&apos;s  com-missary for foreign affairs :       The struggle for the re-establishment of the authority of  the Soviet in Ukraina isnearing the end.   The  working population have not for a  single moment  relaxed thestruggle  which manifested itself during  the  reign of the  hetman government, instrikes and public risings, while later on a general mutiny has  overtaken  the  whole ofUkraina.  This struggle arose from an elementary  movement  to  an organised  and definite  storm against  the  reign   of  the bourgeoisie.  By  far   the  greater part ofUkrainan territory  is  already liberated.   The  red flag of the  Soviet power of theworkers  and  soldiers  is   already  waving over   Chernizoff,   Kharkort,  Poltava,Ekaterinoslav, and a part of the Donetz  Basin.   The  columns  of the Red UkrainanSoviet troops extend   from  the  east, north   and  west,  and  are  swelling like  anavalanche from the workers and peasants and deserters from the army  mobilised by theso-called Directorium, who  are joining the  Red  army, which is at present only  afew dozen verst  distant from Kieff,  where the last authority of the bourgeoisie aud the capitalists is still in  existence.   The Directorium is  seized with  -panic  and is making-preparations for flight.     The provisional Ukrainan soldiers&apos; and workers&apos; Government declares in the  nameof.the whole  of the working  population of Ukraina. that the  workers and peasants ofUkraina are bound together with the  workers and  peasants of all countries  by  indis-soluble ties, and firmly intend  to live  in peace and friendship with all peoples.    The Government therefore invites the peoples and Governments of all countries to establish
regular diplomatic relations with the Ukrainan socialist Soviet republic, and especiallyinvites the socialist Soviet governments of Russia, Lithuanian White Russia, Esthonia,and Lettonia to conclude a close defensive alliance in order to protect against all attacksthe. authority of the workers and peasants which has been established by such heavysacrifices.  Long live the  solidarity of the working peoples.                    (Signed)    RAKOVSKI, Chairman of the Ukrainan Provisional                                             Workers&apos; and  Peasants&apos; Government,                                             and, People&apos;s Commissary for Foreign    Kharkoff, January 28,  1919.             Affairs.SIBERIA.    Proclamation  to  the  Army. On the  30th  January   Mr.  Alston  transmitted[No. 125] a message [No.  107]  sent on the previous day by Sir Charles Eliot, reporting that Admiral Koltchak had published an order, couched in very strong  language, whichhe had  issued  to  the  army.  In this he said  that  neither  agreement nor armisticewas  possible  with  the   Bolsheviks,  whose  only  object was  the  annihilation  ofRussia, though traitors were spreading reports that both armistice and  agreement werein contemplation.   There  should be no question  of entering  on any negotiations withthe dishonourable and criminal Bolsheviks whose leaders were rascals and assassins.    The announcement that the allies had invited the Omsk  Government to meet  theBolsheviks at a conference had probably made Admiral Koltchak feel that he was in  acritical position.  M.  Sazonow had,  Sir  Charles Eliot said, sent a second telegramsaying that there were  great differences of  opinion among the  Allies,  and urgingAdmiral Koltchak not to be  in a hurry.  But the latter,  apparently thought that  thesituation was too serious for delay.    Feeling at Irkutsk in regard to  the proposed Conference. On the 1st FebruaryMr. Alston  transmitted [No. 132] a  telegram, dated  31st January, from the consul atIrkutsk,  who reported that General Volkow had given an official dinner to the foreign representatives, military  and  civilian,  at  which  there  had been some conversation on mr. Wilsons suggested conference at  Prinkipo.   Doubt was raised as to  whether thePowers really understood  the meaning of Bolshevism  ; and it- was  asked  if the alliescould not see the great risks they were running by giving countenance to the conference,and the bad effect any truce with the Bolsheviks would have on the troops at the front.It was also said that Bolshevism was.not a labour movement but an  effort to exterminatethe educated classes and must  be stamped out ;  and that in extending an invitation toits adherents the president  had made  it impossible for  any  self-respecting Russian toattend the conference.  Generally speaking the very  idea of  the conference  met withbitter opposition.    The Japanese and Admiral Koltchak. On the 3rd February Mr. Alston transmitted[No. 137] a message, dated  the  31st January [No. 107],  from Sir Charles Eliot, who reported that he bad  been shown a telegram from the Russian ambassador (? in Tokio)in which he said that the  Japanese Government  regretted that there had been mis-understandings  with: the Omsk Government and  desired more friendly relations.  TwoJapanese generals were, they said, being sent to Omsk on  a special mission.    Attitude towards the Allies. In  his telegram of the 31st  January Sir Charles Eliotsaid that tire allies were very unpopular.TURKESTAN.    Arrest of  Allied Subjects. On the 29th January Mr. Alston transmitted [No. 117]a message from Sir Charles Eliot [No. 98] reporting that an interrupted wireless message to the commissioner of foreign affairs in Moscow from the Bolsheviks in  Tashkent, whichhad been published in the Russian press,  stated that British and French  subjects,.together with the United States consul, had been arrested in  that place.                                     POLAND.    Internal Conditions. On the 1st February  Colonel Wade reported [No. 43) that,except for labour troubles, the internal conditions of the country were,  as a rule, orderly and  normal.  The labour troubles were, he  said, due to  lack of  food and stagnationof industry in the mining and  factory districts.
     Colonel Wade said that a French courier who had just arrived from  Prague hadbeen told that Poland was seething with Bolshevism ; arid that the Czechs had used the argument of Bolshevism to justify their aggression in. Silesia.   Whereas, as was provedby the elections, the general feeling of the nation was entirely opposed to the Bolsheviks ;though it was true Bolshevik agitators were at work  and  would make trouble in theevent of economic catastrophe.     The Czech Attack......On the 31st January Colonel Wade reported  [No. 46] that agreat display of patriotic feeling had been produced by  the Czech attack in&apos;the Teschendistrict,  and had  been shown by all classes and all  parties.  The occasion is being exploited by the Socialists and (? the Jews) to  show  tbe desirability  of  coming to an understanding with the Russians and the Germans; and at the same time to  point out.the error of the  pro-ally  policy.   Intense indignation  had, he said, been shown in. regardto the Czechs, and not them only but the allies as well, on account of the action takenby their officers  in this treacherous attack.  The attack was regarded as a flat negationof the  principles  which  the peace  conference   was  trying  to  establish;   and thedeclaration on those principles made by the allied  statesmen would  lose all appearance of sincerity  in Polish , eyes unless the Czechs received orders for an immediate and unconditional withdrawal.     In a telegram [No. 34A] sent from Warsaw on the  30th January by Mr. Kimens,the antagonism of the Socialists had already been reported,  the  subject of his messagebeing what he described  as a very dangerous article on  the allies which  had appeared in the  &quot; Robothuok,&quot; a Socialist organ.   In this article  the Entente  Powers wereaccused of supporting the Ukrainans and Czechs to the detriment of Poland.     The Socialists, he added, were making  use of events in Teschen, in Posen, and inUkraina for the purpose  of discrediting the Paderewski Government, and their action might have  serious consequences.     Settlement of  the Differences between the  Poles  and the Czechs. On the 1stFebruary Mr. Balfour reported [No. 203] from Paris that an agreement comprising the differences between the Poles and the  Czechs on the Teschen question pending thedecision  by  the peace conference, had been signed by the representatives of the great powers.   It was agreed that a report on the situation should be prepared by delegates of the great  Powers, each of whom should send one for the purpose.   To days  later thefollowing official communique was issued,  the communique being  signed by Messrs.Woodrow Wilson, Lloyd George, Orlando, clemenceau, Dinowski, and Benes :     The  representatives of the  great Powers haying  been  informed of the conflictwhich  has arisen  between the Czechs and the  Poles  in the  principality  of  Teschen,in consequence  of which  the mining  district  of Ostrawa-Karwin and the railway from 0.derberg to  Teschen and  Jablungkau have  been occupied  by the Czechs, have declared as follows :      In the first  instance they think it necessary to remind the nationalities  who haveengaged to submit the territorial questions which concern them  to the peaue conference that they are, pending its decision, to refrain from taking as a pawn, or from occupying the territories to which they lay claim.     The representatives take note of the engagement  by which  the Czech  delegateshave declared that they were definitely stopping their troops in the line of the railwaywhich  runs from  Oderberg  to  Teschen-Jablungkau.   Pending  the  decision of tbepeace congress as to the definite assignment of the territories, that  part of  the railway line to the north  of Teschen and the mining regions will remain in the occupationof Czec,h  troops, while the southern section  of the  line, starting from and including the.town of Teschen down to Jablungkau, will be entrusted to  the military  supervision ofthe Poles.&quot;     The undersigned  consider it indispensable that a commission of control  should be immediately sent to the  spot  to  avoid any conflict between the Czechs and Poles inthe region of Teschen.   This commission, apart from  the measures that it  will have to prescribe, wdll proceed to an inquiry on the basis  of which  the peace  conference  mayform its decision in fixing definitively the respective frontiers of the Czechs and  Polesin the  contested  zone.  The seat of this  commission   will be situated in  the  town of Tescben.     In order to ,se.al  the entente between two friendly nations which  should follow apolicy in  full  accord  with that of the allied and associated Powers, the representativesof the  great  Powers register  the  promise  of  the  Czech  representative   that  his country will put  at  the  disposition  of the Poles all its  available resources in war
 material, and will grant  to  them  every facility for the  transport of  arms  and ammunition.   The exploitation of the  mines of the  Karwin-Ostrawa  district will he carried out in such a way as to avoid  all infraction of private property, while reserving any police measures which the situation may  require.   The  commission of control will be empowered to supervise this, and, if necessary, to secure to the Poles that  part of the  output which may be equitably claimed by them to meet their wants.     It  is understood  that  the local  administration  will  continue  to function  in accordance with  the conditions of the pact of the 5th November, .1918, and that the rights of minorities will be strictly respected.     Pending  the decision  of the  peace congress, political   elections and  military conscription will be suspended in the principality of Teschen.     No measure implying annexation of all or of a part of the  said principality either to the territory of Poland or of Czecho-Slovakia taken by interested parties shall have binding  force.     The delegates of the Czech nation engage to release immediately,  with  their arms and  baggage, the Polish prisoners taken during the recent conflict.     [The duchy  of Teschen  (here  called  a  principality)  is  the  easternmost part  of Austrian Silesia.   The  Polish  population is about 235,OuO.   The  duchy has  extensive coal and iron fields.]     The Elections for the Diet. On the :-S0th  January Colonel Wade reported [No. 45] that it could already be said that in the former Russian Poland the national parties had won, and that in  Galicia  the Socialists had been victorious.   At Warsaw 10 National Democrats,  3  members of  the Polish Socialist party,  and 3 members of the  Jewish parties had been  elected.   The provincial results would be  completed  in a few.days, but  it  was  already obvious that in the former Russian Poland a great many peasants had  been elected.     Poles and Germans. On  the 1st February Mr.  Balfour reported [No. 203 j that at a  meeting  of ministers held  that day, Marshal Foch&apos;s instructions to the  German military authorities in regard to  missions about to leave for  Poland  were approved. Those missions,  Mr.  Balfour  said, would insist that the Poles should refrain from the use  of force  against the Germans, and  Marshal Foch was instructed to demand that they, on their  part, should act in like  manner pending the conclusion of the conference.                                                                               v.                                    RUMANIA.     The Dobrudja. On the  1st  February the  Foreign Office telegraphed to  Sir G. Barclav [No. 781 in regard to the representations made by the Rumanian  Governmenton the subject  of our opposition to its troops entering the Dobrurija, giving  the  gist  ofa  note  received  from the  French Government and informing him that the  BritishGovernment shared its views.     The occupation of  the  province  by the allied troops was  a natural result  of thearmistice with Bulgaria which  was signed when Rumania was still a neutral;  but  itwas  in no wise inspired by any desire to favour the former country.   The future  status of the Dobrudja would not be influenced by the exclusion of Rumanian  troops ; thoughthe restitution of  the province must  depend on a decision  of the peace conference itwas  to be implied, from the annulment of the treaty of Bucharest, that it would  returnto Rumania.   The military  authorities of the allies must be the judges of what shouldbe done for the maintenance of order, and up to the  present  they had been  successful.It was most important to avoid any possibility of contact  between the  Rumanian andthe Bulgarian troops.                                     GREECE.     Claims at the Peace Conference. On the  4th February Mr. Balfour reported from paris ;No. 216] that M. Venezelos had put in a statement of the Greek  claims.   these included Thrace,  both eastern and western ; Northern Epirus, the islands in the eastern mediterranean, including  Cyprus, and,  in Asia  Minor, the vilayet of Aidin except thesandjak  of  Denizli (where the population  is  chiefly Moslem),  part of  the  vilayet  ofBroussa, and all  the islands  not  already Greek.   In  regard,  to  western Thrace  hesuggested that the Moslem deputies in the Bulgarian Sobranje should be consulted as towhether the  Turks in that district would prefer Bulgarian or Greek rule.
TURKEY.     Escape  of  Resliid  Bey. On the   28th  January,  Admiral Calthorpe  reported-[No.  203] the  escape  of Reshid Bey who had  been very  deeply  implicated in the armenian massacres.   Mr. Ryan had, on  his behalf, spoken very seriously to the grandvizier and the minister of the interior  informing them that he, Admiral Calthorpe, took a very grave view of. the  incident.  Mr.  Ryan  pointed out that British statesmen had promised the civilised world that those responsible tor the massacres should he heldpersonally responsible and that it was the  firm intention  of his  Government to fulfilthat promise.   It was useless to attribute the escape to  the slackness of subordinateofficials : members of the Government would be  held  responsible for not having seenthat the prisoner was properly  guarded.   If the  Turkish Government could give nobetter earnest of a serious intention to punish the guilty, other means would have to befound for the attainment of that object.     The two ministers appeared to realise the gravity of the  affair and were apparentlydoing their best to  recapture  Reshid.   But unless they screwed themselves  up toarresting numerous other criminals, the effect of Reshid&apos;s escape, even if  be should berecaptured, would be deplorable :  the  grand  vizier had, however, said definitely thatthese arrests were to  he made.   But he, Admiral Calthorpe,  bad heard that the Sultanwas growing even more timorous.     The Arrests. Telegraphing  on the 30th  January, Admiral Calthorpe  reported[No. 230] that he  understood  that some forty  persons,  all of  real  importance hadbeen  arrested.   Among them  were Jahid,  Midhat, Shukri,  Rahmi, Carasso and others of great local importance  though but little known  in Europe.   Others such as JahidHalii, and Said Halim were being kept under surveillance.     Admiral Calthorpe thought that the  Sultan and the minister of the interior were mainly responsible for the arrests ; the minister  for foreign  affairs had  been in favourof waiting to make them till a formal demand had been made.     Demand for the surrender of certain officers and officials. On  the 5th  february the Foreign Office instructed Admiral  Calthorpe  to demand  the  immediate  surrender to  himself  or  the nearest  allied commander  of such Turkish  officers  and officialsas  he  or   the  commanders  concerned  should  require  for  any  of the  following-reasons  : -Outrages  to Armenians or  other subject races  in Turkey or Transca-ucasia ;ill-treatment of  prisoners ;  failure  to comply  with  or  impeding  execution  of thearmistice terms; participation  in looting,  destruction  of property,  &amp;c,  or  any otherbreaches of the  laws and customs  of war;  or  finally,  insolence  to British officers.Military courts were being formed for the trial of such persons.                                     SYRIA.     The Reported Agreement between  Prince Feisal and M.  clemenceau [E.R. No. CV,p. 5].   On the  1st February Mr. Balfour  telegraphing from Paris [No.  4, repeated to F.O.  No.  195] to Sir Reginald Wingate informed him  that no agreement  had been arrived  at between Prince Feisal and M. Clemenceau, and at the same time transmittedthe following message from the former to the Hejaz [group uudecypherable] agency :      Please publish  that  I am asking  the peace conference  for an  independent  Syriaunder the League of Nations.     The Syrian  Union  Party. Sir Milne  Cheetham  reported on the  1st February[No. 173] that  a telegram was being  despatched  to Mr.  Balfour  by the  Syrian UnionParty, whose claim  to represent the great  majority of Syrians in Syria as well  as inEgypt  was believed to  be  well  founded.   The  Union  had already sent  a similartelegram to M. Clemenceau, as president of the peace conference.   In  its. message theUnion asked for an invitation from the conference for  a  delegate  to  proceed to Paristo explain the details of its programme ; and further that there  should be a plebisciteof the Syrian people  under the supervision of an inter-allied  commission.                                     ARABIA.     Ibn Saud and Fakhri Pasha  [E.R., No. CY., p. 5.] Sir Milne  Cheetham reported[No. 177] on the 2nd February, that information had been received from Yembo to theeffect that  Turkish  officers, and among them  Fakhri&apos;s adjutant, asserted that nocaravan had ever come  through from  South Nejd ; they denied, too, any knowledge of communications with ibn  Saud.
MESOPOTAMIA.    Native  Opinion in regard to the future  Government. Baghdad was  dealt with  inthe last report [pp.  5 and 6], and  it was there stated  that the Moslem  delegates whohad been chosen to consider  the question  had. in their reply made no reference  toforeign protection, but after their reply had become known there  had been a revulsionof feeling, which led to a request for  British  protection without the appointment of anyArab  ruler.  Telegraphing  on the  2nd  February the political officer  in  Baghdadreported that this revulsion was increasing and that be had received three declarationsasking for British protection without an  emir ;  these declarations having been  signed by leading Moslems.    Kadhimain. -In his telegram of the 29th January the political  officer at Baghdadsaid that a document demanding the continuance of British rule had been prepared bythe head  of the  municipality  and the only other big merchant  in  the town, and wasbeing extensively signed by the  tribal shaykhs  and others;  and that tins had beendone in spite of the ulemas having threatened to excommunicate  anyone  who voted forBritish control, in which they were  backed  by  agents  from Constantinople.  On the2nd February the political agent reported that he had received the  document referredto above, and that  it had been  signed  by  the  tribal  shaykhs in that area withoutany exception.    The political officer in  Baghdad reported, on the 26th January, as follows in  regardto other districts :    Nasiriyah Division. The political officer -of this division  reported  that an Arabruler was favoured,  but  there was an overwhelming opinion against the appointment ofa son of King Hussein, and in favour of no such appointment  being  made for at leastfive years.   Public opinion  was unanimous in wishing the union  of  Mosul with Basraand Baghdad.    Kerbela. The  tribes of the district have definitely  demanded a continuance of thepresent regime without alteration.    Basra. All  desire the fullest measure of British protection.   Christians and Jewsare emphatically opposed to having an  Arab ruler ;  so are the Moslem mercantile andlandowning classes,  but  the eventual establishment of an Arab Government  under anemir is favoured by a  section of educated  Moslems,  who, however, hold this viewwithout enthusiasm, being clearly apprehensive of the  probable  results on the rapid development of the  town and on their flourishing trade.    Kut Division. Practically  the same as Nasiriyah,  a considerable number of itsleadino&apos; men would dislike an emir in any circumstances.    Khanikin. Every  tribal chief, and every merchant or landowner of note, Christian,Jew, or Moslem&apos;is in favour of the present regime.  This place is predominantly Sunni.    Mandali. The people here want a British high-commissioner and no emir.   they also want the inclusion of Mosul.   Mandali is mainly Turkish Sunni.    Kirkuk. This place  is  largely Turkish  with an admixture  of  Kurds,  Arabs,Christians, and Jews, the majority are of the same way of thinking as the inhabitants of Mandali.    Kifri. Here too opinion is in favour of a state  including Mosul and being under british production.  They, however,  favour  the idea of an emir; but as  they areunable  to agree on  any  particular  person,  they  ask for  delay in ^ making  an appointment.    Mosul. Extensively   signed  documents have been  received  from the differentcommunities asking for  union  with Baghdad under British as opposed to  Arab rule. *    Baqubah  Division. The  townspeople of Baqubah  ask somewhat diffidently for a titular  Arab head  to rule from  Mosul to Basra, and the  majority seem to favour a son of the  King of Hejaz.   The  inhabitants  of all  other centres,  and tbe  tribes wholargely predominate in the district wish  for a continuance of the present regime andno emir.
                                 KURDISTAN.    Rowanduz. On  the  31st  January the political officer at Baghdad  telegraphedextracts from reports in regard  to the districts about Rowanduz which had  been sent by Captain Noel.   The latter said that there was a  feeling of profound relief that wehad assumed,. responsibility for  the country&apos;s future.   The town itself was  a heap ofruins :  out of 2,000 houses only  sixty were standing.  The country between Rowanduzand Diaz was  practically  deserted :   [? Rayat] formerly  a flourish  g villageaonly three houses left and Neri had ceased  to  exist.   The people in the district werelifeless and apathetic, the result of the desolation which  had been wrought by successivewaves of advancing and retiring Turks and Russians.                                AFGHANISTAN.    Monthly  Report. The viceroy  reported on the 1st February  that  the state of afghanistan was peaceful.v

</content>
</cab>
