<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 347-352</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This  Document is.the  Property  of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s G-overnrfient,]^SECRET.FOR REFERENCE ONLY.            EASTERN   REPORT.               No, CX.  March 6, 1919.(Incorporating  ARABIAN  REPORT N.S. No.  CXXXVIL)CONTENTS.Russia.    Soviet Warning to the Mensheviks.    The  Orthodox Church and the Peace     Conference.  Lithuania and White Russia.    Soviet  Request for Recognition of the     Republic  Ukraina.    Soviet Threat to the Allies. - .  Don Country.                    ;    Activities of the French Military Mission.  The Caucasus.    Attitude of Great Britain towards the     Trans- Caucasiim Republicanism 1 ics.Poland.    Announcement of Recognition.  .  The Diet and M. Paderewski.    The Armistice Commission at Lemberg.    Representation at Berne.Turkey.    Reconstruction of the Cabinet.Syria and Palestine.    Fear of Zionists.    British and French Co-operation.    The Armenian Claim to Cilieia.Afghanistan.    Amir Habibulla&apos;s Successor.                                      RUSSIA.     Soviet Warning to the Mensheviks. On the 26th  February the  central executivecommittee of the Soviets of all Russia adopted a resolution in regard to the Mensheviks;of which the gist was sent out through the wireless stations of the Russian governmenton the 3rd March.   This resolution stated that the central executive committee had cometo the conclusion that to make the demand, for the cessation of civil war  in  the formexpressed  in the &quot; Period,&quot; the official organ of the party, would be equivalent to thedesertion of the working classes and peasants in the presence of bandits and hangmen,and  that the Menshevik  propaganda  had the sole  aim  of  weakening the  power of resistance by the state, which, under the circumstances, was transformed  into a campattacked from all sides by the enemies of the workmen&apos;s  and  peasants&apos; revolution, andhad therefore decided  not to allow propaganda of this kind, which was conducted in the rear of the  Red  army, and which was utilising the difficulties of the food  situationagainst that  army.  It had  also decided to  suspend  the journal  &quot; Period &quot; until  &quot;theMensheviks  could  show by their actions [that  they could be trusted].  The resolutionreminded the opposition that the&apos; soviet  republics were a military camp consisting ofmen, in whose veins flowed the blood of the best of the worker and  peasant class, whodefended the great conquests of the revolution.,  The Mensheviks  were warned  that ifthey  continued their  counter-revolutionary  activities they would, be expelled  to  the&quot; democratic &quot; territory of Admiral Koltchak.     The Orthodox Church and, the Peace Conference. In reply to a request  that theRussian Orthodox Church  might  be  represented at the peace conference, which  hadbeen sent through the British, consulate-general at Odessa, the Foreign  Office telegraphedto Mr. Bagge on the 26th  February [No. 100] saying that this would be impossible, asthe Vatican was not represented.LITHUANIA AND WHITE russia.     Soviet Request for Recognition of Republic.  The  following message from  thecentral executive committee  of the Soviets,  &amp;c., of the soviet  republics of Lithuania  and white  Russia was  sent  out on  the 3rd March through the wireless stations  of  theRussian government.[756]-301B
    &apos;&quot;The central-executive committee of the Soviets of workers, soldiers, and&apos;&quot;&quot;Red&quot;guards of the socialist republic of Lettonia and White Russia addresses a proposal to all peoples and their governments that they should recognise the socialist soviet republic of Lettonia and White Russia, and enter into negotiations with it.     The central  executive  committee again  emphasizes  its willingness  to settle all questions in dispute in a peaceful manner;     It learns with great indignation that the Polish government has not replied to  the proposal for the formation of a mixed commission for the purpose of dealing with questions regarding territorial disputes between  the republic of Lithuania and White Russia, on the one side, and Poland on the other, and that it continues to conduct  an offensive.     The central  executive  committee appeals  to the working  masses of  Poland, over the head of their reactionary government, which attempts to play the rble of hangman to the  socialist revolution  of Lithuania, and  again categorically declares that  the working classes of Lithuania  and White Russia have no annexatiouist designs what- ever, and that their only desire is to live in friendly relations with the working masses of the whole world, especially with their neighbours.      ,              V :     Being  however attacked by Lithuanian, White Russian, German and Polish White guards,&apos;the workers and peasants of Lithuania and White  Russia are prepared to  die rather than give up the conquests of their revolution.     The central executive committee again affirms its readiness  to solve  peacefully all questions in dispute, but at  the same time demands from all those to whom freedom and socialism are dear to take arms and fight against the  capitalists  and exploiters who attempt to  strangle the revolution and to crush the power of the peasants and workmen of Lithuania, and White Russia.                            &apos;   ,;     The central executive committee requests the workers&apos; and peasants&apos; government elected by it to enter into relations  immediately with the governments of the Entente powers in order&apos; to determine the question of the proposed  peace negotiations on Prince&apos;s Island, but at  the same time demands  that  the most energetic  measures be taken  for the protection of the socialist soviet republic of Lithuania and White Russia from any offensive of the military forces of the united imperialists. Ukraina.    Soviet Threat to the Allies. The following announcement which was issued through the wireless stations of the  Russian government  on- the  28th  February, was&apos;signed by M.  Radowsky, president  of the provisional soviet  government  of Ukraina and commissary for foreign affairs :-    According to  official reports, our  communist  comrades are  languishing  in prison in  all   the towns  on  the  Black Sea   occupied  by   the  allies,  in  particular  in Sebastopol  and Odessa.  Amongst  those  detained in Odessa is the  Rumanian social, democrat, Bouglor, who was  arrested for having been associated  with  the soviet power at Odessa last year.  ....   The socialist  soviet government of Ukraina,  considers it necessary to carry [out reprisals ?] on all subjects of  the  Entente powers whom it finds on the territory of the Ukrainan soviet.  Among these there are at Kharkoff ninety-one French subjects, eighty-two  Belgian subjects,  sixty-one  Italians, twenty-five British, four Africans.  Apart from these  there are Greeks, Rumanians, and Serbians who up till now have lived in complete freedom on Ukrainan territory.   Besides residing here without being  [molested] they have been allowed the [services  of the] Belgian and Italian consuls.  At Krement the Rumanian vice-consul remains. -    Desiring to give proof of its pacific policy the Ukrainan soviet government has hitherto taken no measures for reprisal against the subjects of the Entente states who are at war with it.  It declares itself ready to enter into negotiations with the French government&apos; and with the other allied governments, to make a treaty for the freeing of their subjects whovare found here in exchange for  the citizens  of the  Ukrainan soviet republic who were arrested with the  concurrence of the French government, or  were  found  in the various countries of the allies, and who  now wish to return to Ukraina.   The agreement should equally provide for the return of Ukrainan prisoners of war.    If  the  French government, and the French  command at  Odessa on whom above all depends the cessation of measures of violence against citizens  of the Ukrainan soviet, do not deem it necessary, to  enter  into negotiations with us  on the subject of the exchange as indicated,  the  socialist soviet government of Ukraina declares  that, in order to defend the interests of the  Ukrainan  revolution,  it will  find itself obliged totake more severe measures against the subjects of the allied governments.
s     Holding that the preservation of the liberty  and the life of the subjects of these powers comes within the province of the French  government  and of the governmentsof the allies, it urgently awaits a precise answer.DON  COUNTRY.     Activities of the French Military Mission. On the  27th February the ForeignOffice telegraphed [No. 547] to Lord Derby instructing him to call the attention of theFrench government to a report which had been made by the British military representative at Ekaterinodar  in regard to the activities of  Captain Fouquet, the head of the french military mission, pointing out that the French zone of influence in South Russia was,by the convention of the  23rd December, 1917, confined  to Bessarabia, Ukraina, andthe Crimea, and  that the activities of the French  military authorities appeared to be directly at variance  with the terms of that convention.  Lord Derby was  furtherinstructed  to ask  that the  French government should immediately  disavow CaptainFouquefs activities and statements.     The British representative had reported  that Captain Fouquet had recently tried to make a treaty with the ataman of the Cossacks, General  Krasnov, by  which thelatter was to  assume  responsibility for the losses suffered  by French citizens in the don country  and in  Ukraina, and at the same time  to acknowledge the  supreme authority of  General Franchet d&apos;Esperey in  both military and  economic matters inreturn for allied  troops being sent to his  aid.  General Krasnov referred the matter toGeneral Denikin who advised him to sign the treaty; at the same time  the  latter sent a strong protest  to General Franchet  d&apos;Esperey.  Nine days  before the date of theForeign Office telegram, an announcement was made in the press  by Captain Fouquetto the effect that troops which had been detailed for the northern  Don and the Donetzbasin were being delayed on account of a shortage of transport ; that General Briggs,the  British  military  representative,  had been  despatched, by order of the Frenchsuperior command, with a party of military  officers to organise  the  technical sectionof the Russian troops, and that General Briggs would be  superseded  by a new Frenchmission.     In regard to these promises and assertions, the  Foreign  Office pointed  out  in itstelegram to Lord Derby that Captain Fouquets promise of allied troops may well havebeen the foundation upon which General Krasnov based his promise to  his troops thatsuch  aid would  be forthcoming, and so may have been one of the  factors  which ledto the recent debacle  on the Don  front, whilst  the statement in regard to  GeneralBriggs  could only be looked upon as  insulting  to  the British  mission, and  ascalculated, by undermining  its prestige, to  destroy the  value  of its   work at  the headquarters  of General Denikin.THE CAUCASUS.     Attitude  of Great Britain towards the  Trans-Caucasian   Republics. On the27th February the Foreign Office telegraphed [No. 128] to Sir  Percy  Cox  in regardto a proposed mission to Teheran from Azerbaijan, and incidentally defined our attitudevis-a-vis the  Trans-Caucasian republics.   It was explained that we  regarded  theiraspirations with some sympathy,  and had given a warning to  General Denikin to abstain from  interference with them ;  but their  future status was  a matter for thepeace conference, and  pending its decision we could not recognise  them.                                    POLAND.     Announcement of Recognition. On the 25th February Sir Esme  Howard reported[No. 23]  that the official  announcement of the recognition of  the Polish government by  the allied governments, which  had been  made in the  papers of that day, had beenreceived  with lively satisfaction.     The Diet and  M. Paderewski.- Telegraphing  from Warsaw on the 28th February,.Sir Esme Howard reported  [No.  33] that M.  Paderewski  had  received  a vote ofconfidence  from  the diet.   The Thugut socialists and the members of the Left Populistparty had, he said, abstained from  voting, but the vote had  been passed by a  large majority.     The Armistice Commission at Lemberg. On  the 28th February  Sir Esme Howardreported [No. 37] that a report  had been received  from  the  commission at Lembergto the effect that it had hopes that  an armistice would be  concluded.
     Representation  at  Berne. On  the  25th February Sir Horace Rumbold  reported[No. 347] that M. Zaleski, the  Polish representative&apos; in  Berne, was- expecting to betransferred to another post very shortly.  It had always been  understood, Sir Horace.went on  to  saj, that  he would be succeeded by M. Modzelewski;  he, however, hadreceived a communication from  M. Dmowski informing him  that  it  was proposed to abolish the Polish mission in  Berne, and  that even  if this should not be  done,  itwould be run on different lines.   M. Dmowski, in fact, proposed that M.  Modzelewskishould  stay on, after the departure  of M. Zaleski, as the representative of the na/tionaicommittee, not of the government in Warsaw- a change of status which M. Modzelewskithinks, undesirable.     M. Zaleski is of the same  opinion  as M.  Modzelewski  in regard  to  the  Parisproposal,  which he thinks is explained by rumours that the resignation of the  Warsaw.government may be brought about in the near future, and that, should this be  the case,its probable successor would be a peasant government  under  M. Witos.   The  views ofsuch  a government  would probably not harmonise with  those of the committee, and itwould probably wish to  communicate  with the allies through some other medium ;consequently the national committee wishes to establish its agent in  Berng in place of-a regular diplomatic representative,  as such an agent would  continue  in office in spite.of changes in Warsaw and. would make it very difficult for the expected government to treat with the allies.     Two days later  Sir Horace Rumbold  telegraphed again [No.  364] reporting  that count Szembek, the diplomatic  secretary of the Polish mission in Berne, was to proceedto.Paris, for the purpose of setting before M. Dmowski the views of M. Zaleski and his proposed successor.                                                             -  -;.                                    TURKEY.    Reconstruction of  the Cabinet. On the  26th February Admiral Webb reported[No. 417] the  reconstruction of the cabinet for reasons which are not clear, though themain feature had been the exercise of pressure by the &quot; Entente Liberale&quot;  and  &quot; peace and Security  &quot;  parties, both of which were hostile to the C.U.P.   The  principal changes were as follows : Reshid Bey-had  been  chosen for the vacant ministry  of the interiorwhich he had held in Kiamifs  last cabinet.  Till  his  return from abroad  Izzet Beywould  continue to act.   Jemil Molla had. been  appointed minister of justice; he was.a somewhat remarkable member of the ulema class, very intelligent,, and well-read, in.,history, who  had taken  no public part in politics  since  1908,  though  he had played acertain role under Abdul Hamid.  The  ministry for foreign  affairs had been  given toYussuf  Pasha, a Syrian catholic who- was  formerly governor of the Lebanon ; he was said to be very Francophil.   He was the only Christian in the government ; the Greeks&apos;and Armenians would no longer accept office.   Ata  Bey, formerly  a member  of thefinancial reform commission, had the ministry of finance; and the  little-known general,Ferid Pasha, was minister of war.    The result of the reconstruction, Admiral Webb said, was an unstable and  probablyshort-lived government, if anything, rather more likely than  its predecessor  to give ustrouble.,                          SYRIA  AND  PALESTINE.    Fear  of  Zionists. Telegraphing on the  28th February [No.  162/426]  General&apos;Clayton reported the existence of a widespread fear of Zionism among all  classes,&quot;;!Christian  and  Moslem alike, a fear  which had  been  intensified by  the utterances of leading Zionists and the  publication in Zionist journals of a programme considerably inadvance of that laid down by Dr. Weizmann  in his  interviews with the Christian and moslem communities.   The fear  and dislike of Zionism is general, and may be attributedalmost entirely to the rapid advance in Zionist  demands  during the  last few months.Provided Great Britain  guaranteed the maintenance of the rights of the majority, the moderate proposals made by Dr. Weizmann when in  Palestine, though  not welcomed,.would have been accepted: but the present programme is by  far more drastic, and hasseriously alarmed all sections of the population, other than,  the Zionists, not only in.Palestine  but also in Syria.   It is convenient, General Clayton said, in certain  circles to,attribute the feeling against the Zionists  to the influence of the effendis,  tyrannicallandlords, who must  be  considered : this was not a fair statement, for not only were they.worthy representatives of their class, but the dislike  and fear of Zionism was generalthroughout all classes.    It was being realized that Great Britain had one hand  tied  by her declaration tothe Zionists  and  the other by her agreement  with  France, and the outcome was a
lack of confidence in the power  to  whom the majority had looked for help, feeling thattinder its guidance the prosperity of Syria and Palestine would be best assured.     This had led  to a strong combination of Christians and enlightened Moslems in syria, Palestine, and Egypt, whose programme  was  independence  as soon as thecountry could stand alone, and meanwhile local autonomy under the guidance of one ofthe great powers.   This party,  despairing of Great Britain,  was turning to America,and had already submitted a memorandum to the  American consul-general for trans-mission to Mr. Wilson.     They claimed an undivided Syria including in that term Palestine-and thsy held that, both Great Britain and France being unsuitable, America was the only power leftto them ; America being free from pledges and agreements and having no interests which would clash with those of Great Britain, to  whom Syria must always  look  for much of her economic progress and by whose influence she must alwaj^s be surrounded.     The  reasons for the  rejection of both Great  Britain and France  by this party were  that  those  powers  were  bound by agreements  which  must  result  in  a-divided  Syria and  in  a clashing  of interests which  would menace  the  peace notonly  of Syria herself but of the  civilized world.   Great Britain, too, by her agreements with France and the Zionists, would be debarred from  the only policy which  could produce a stable and prosperous Syria : whilst France was unsuitable as a mandatory,since the economic and commercial interests of Syria were bound up  wdth regions underthe control of Great Britain.     The  fear of Zionism had also brought into being a young Arab  party, whi;h wasgaining some support among the more fanatical Moslems its programme  was complete independence and freedom from  all foreign control.     British and French Co-operation. On the 25th February Lord Derby telegraphed[No.  414] the summary of an article which  had  appeared in  that evening&apos;s &quot; Temps,&apos;.&apos;the writer of which, he said, was probably M. Philippe Millet.   Lord  Derby  thought the article inspired.   He said:      The  &quot; Temps&quot; this evening has an article in favour of Franco-British co-operation in the Levant, but pointing out  the danger  of friction owing to the misplaced, zeal of.local  agents unless the spheres of influence are clearly defined.     According to the &quot;Temps&quot; it is  clear that no single people or  group of  the lateTurkish empire in Asia Minor  is  capable of managing its  affairs  without Europeanassistance, and  must therefore be provided with mandatories.  It is  indispensable,however,  that the latter should not come into conflict  with one  another, since  rivalryamong European powers is the most  dangerous scourge that a small nation during  itsminority  has to dread.  Everyone in England  and France fully recognises that thepreservation of the present friendship between the two countries is a primary considera-tion.   Once that axiom is borne in mind the problem  of  the Levant is, the &quot;Temps&quot;observes, a simple  one.   Nowhere is co-operation more necessary or more easy.  France,if she be entrusted with the administration  of  Syria,  must build a railway  fromAlexaudretta coastwards&apos; to enable the wealth of Mesopotamia to flow through Syrianports ; Great Britain, if  she wishes to  develop . Mesopotamia, needs that railway  for asimilar purpose.    Therein lies the basis  of future agreements respecting the  utilizationin common of railways and^oorts.   England has abandoned her policy of isolation, andeverywhere, in West Africa, Oceania, the Far East,  or the Levant, Englishmen recognisethat France and Great Britain must work in ever closer harmony, since they are  fatedto &quot; stand or fall together.&quot;  Hence, according to the &quot; Temps,&quot; the references made  by those in touch with Lord Milner during  the war to the  future Anglo-French railway from  Alexandretta to Baghdad imply that a Syria under French eegis is not a rival buta partner for the Anglo-Arabian world.     But, the &quot; Temps &quot; continues, there is one essential condition  of such co-operation.The British and French spheres of influence must be clearly enough  defined to  prevent any confusion  of a political nature.   In  such  matters  the goodwill  of  the  respective governments is not  sufficient.   Local agents, generally zealous, soon find opportunities of quarrelling among themselves,  and such  opportunities are undoubtedly offered ifcertain Arab states,  as in the  1916 agreement, are placed  half in the British and halfin the French sphere.  The &quot;Temps&quot; quotes Damascus as  an  instance  ; there not the closest economic agreement would prevent French agents in the North from quarrellingwith  British agents in the  South, to the  prejudice  of the  unfortunate  native  govern-ment of Damascus itself, and  productive  of nothing but  an  exchange  of acrimoniousnotes between Paris  and London.     The  almost  inevitable  intrigues in  eastern  countries  would, however,  pursues
the &quot;Temps,&quot; be rendered inoffensive if each were  master in his own bouse, if thelimits assigned to the British  and French zones coincided with the boundaries of thenative states, and if it were laid down that no native state under  the aegis of france should have the least political link with the native states dependent on  Great Britain.On such conditions alone can  the great work of co-operation in  common run smoothly,and the  joint foundations be laid  of  a  vast  programme of beneficent regeneration  ofthat portion of the  world.    To  work  together,  however,  concludes  the  &quot;Temps,&quot; every  smallest  germ  ofsuspicion must be suppressed,  and past experience  has proved the  inconvenience  ofany form of condominium,  and at the same time  the advantage in  the interest  of humanity of economic co-operation.   Two  things  are  therefore  necessary :  union  of effort,  and, to attain that, clearly  defined spheres.   Once  this double formula  is applied  to Syria it will, says the &quot; Temps,&quot; be extended to the remainder of Franco-British world.                      a    The Armenian Claim to Cilicia. On  the  27th February Lord Derby  reported[No. 424] that  whilst the leading organs  of the French press expressed  sympathy  ingeneral with Armenia, they  regarded statement made by Boghos Nubar Pasha andM. ill cman respecting the aspirations of that country as a maximum programme, anddomed her right to  Cihcia to which Syria had a prior and better claim.    The &quot; Temps &quot;  of that evening observed that, whereas the. Armenian delegation,before making its statement,  came to an agreement with the Greek government on thesubject  of the Greek claim to Trebizond, it failed to do  so with the French governmentrespecting Cilicia  and Alexandretta, where France had historical  and other rights.   this fact did not, however, continued the &quot; Temps,&quot; prevent France  from considering the armenian claims in a friendly manner; but the Armenian programme had, it pointed out,a weak  point.   Except in the province of Van, the Armenian population was nowhere&apos;in a majority.   In the whole of Cilicia the total Armenian population was only 407,000,whereas the vilayet of Adana had alone 420,000 inhabitants.    According to the &quot; Temps &quot; there were  two solutions  of the  Armenian question :one to create an  Armenian spreading over  a large  extent of  territory in which the armenian population was everywhere in a minority, the other to attempt to collect the armenian  population  within  more  restricted  but   compact  limits.  The  Armeniandelegation had opted  for the  former solution ;  the  &quot; Temps &quot;  professed its preference for the latter.                                 AFGHANISTAN.    Amir Habibulla&apos;s Successor. On the 3rd March the viceroy  of  India transmitteda telegram from Sir George Roos-Keppel, who had himself transmitted to the viceroytwo firmans which had been sent to the Afghan agents in.Peshawar.   In one  of  theseNasrulla announced that he had decided that Arnanulla, son of the late Amir, should.be &quot; King and Amir of Afghanistan,&quot; and that  he had sworn allegiance to him  ; andthis was confirmed in the other by Amanulla himself.  Sir George  Roos-Keppel saidthat the firmans,  which were undoubtedly genuine, had been read to  all the Afghanofficials  in Peshawar.   &quot; Sir George also sent an account of what had happened  in Jalalabad and Kabul,,as given in letters received from  relatives in those places by the Afghan postmaster  in.Peshawar.   . -. According to the postmaster&apos;s correspondents,  on receipt of the news in Kabul,.Amanulla, after  consultation  with  certain  notables, summoned  all the military and.civil officials,  and informed  them that Nasrulla  had  proclaimed himself Amir after having murdered  ITabibulia,   He declared  his intention of avenging his  father, and.those  present swore to support him.   Amanulla  then promised  the troops a higher rateof pay together with immediate  payment  of arrears.   He  next sent a, message  toJalalabad informing  the  authorities that  unless they arrested Nasrulla their families in Kabul would  be  executed.  They in turn threatened  General Nadir  Khan, whowas credited  with  having  actually arranged  the  murder ;  and he is said to havestated that he acted under Nasrulla&apos;s orders.   Surrender of the murderer was demanded by the troops, and it appeared that Nadir Khan and Nasrulla himself were under some sort of arrest, or at  any rate of surveillance.  The people had turned towards Amanullaand so had the  army ; but Nasrulla still had the keen support of the mullahs.

</content>
</cab>
