<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/145/0 images: 481-487</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This  Document is the Property  of His Britannic Majestys CtovgrranantJPrinted for the War Cabinet.SECRET          EASTERN  REPORT.        No. CXXXIV.  August 21, 1919.(Incorporating  ARABIAN REPORT N.S. No.  CLXI.)CONTENTS.Russia.  North-West Russia.   New Provisional Government.   Declaration made by the New Govern-     ment.   Message from General Rodzianko.   General Yudenich.  Northern Territory.   Petitions in regard to Evacuation.   The Future Defence of Archangel.  Omsk Government.   Appointment of New  Committees.Turkey.    Resignations of two Cabinet Ministers.    Escapes from Prison.Persia.    The New Agreement.    A greement for a Loan.    The 1911 Loan.    Letters to Vossugh-ed-Dowleh.    French Criticism of the Agreement.    The Shah.                                     RUSSIA.NORTH-WEST RUSSIA.     New Provisional Government for North-West Russia. The three Russian govern-ments of Petrograd, Novgorod, and Pskoff,  having been formed into the provisionalgovernment of North-West Russia, Reuter reports that the following coalition ministryhas been formed :      Mr. Lianozoff, prime minister and foreign affairs and finance.     General Yudenich, war, and commander-in-chief of the north-western army.     Mr.  Alexandroff (member of the  Constitutional Democratic Cadet party), homeaffairs.     Mr. Margulios (Radical Democrat), commerce, industry, and munitions.     Mr.  Ivanoff (former president of  the  Petrograd municipal council),  controller-general.     Mr. Ivanoff (Moderate  Revolutionary Socialist), minister without portfolio.     Mr. Bodganoff (Moderate Revolutionary Socialist), agriculture.     Mr. Ern (Cadet party), education.     Mr. Korn (Moderate Social Democrat), minister without portfolio.     Mr. Eishinsky (non-party Socialist), minister without portfolio.     Mr. Philippoff (Cadet party), posts and telegraphs.     Admiral Pilkin, navy,     Mr. Butleroff, economic reconstruction.     Telegraphing on the 14th August [No. D.C. 11] the deputy commissioner at Revalstated that Mr. Eishinsky, said in  the above list to be minister without portfolio, wasminister of supplies, and added Mr. Konderev  as  minister of public affairs.  Telegraphingagain  on the  16th August  [No.  D.C. 27]  he mentioned   that  one  of the  twoMessrs. Ivanoff was minister of justice.     On the 14th August the deputy commissioner at Reval reported [No. D.C. 14] thatthe newly constituted North-West Russian  government  had decided to make its head-quarters for the present at Beval.   He  had,  he  said, been assured that the majority ofthe  members feared to establish themselves -in Pskoff,  as  they were convinced thatBalachovich  would  in  that  case  attempt  a  coup d&apos;etat  from which  their lives would
 certainly be in grave danger.   In view of the presence of the new Russian government in Reval, General Gough had  invited  him,  the deputy commisssionei&apos;, to take over all political negotiations  with it.   He therefore requested that the chief British commis- sioner for the Baltic provinces  might be accredited with the new government as soon as his majesty&apos;s government had recognized it.     Declaration made by the new Government. On  15th August  the deputy commis- sioner at Reval telegraphed [No. D.C. 15] the following  text  of a declaration  made by the North-West  Russian goverziment  to the Esthonian government  and to the, representatives at Reval of Great Britain, France, and United States :      In confirmation of our preliminary declaration  regarding  the recognition of the independence of  Esthonia as  a group undertaking  the function of  indemnity for government authority in the north-west province  as a  part.of United Russia, we make the following supplementary declaration :      With a view to active military assistance to the  Russian army of the north-west front in the field on the part of the Esthonian government, and in  view of the declaration made by the Esthonian government in  regard to its agreement to sign a treaty on this subject only with a democratic  government of the north-western province, a government which it was essential to form  for this purpose, we, the undersigned, appreciating the circumstances involved by the problem of saving our country and freeing it from the tyranny of the  Bolsheviks, and the  circumstances which pointed to  the complete impossibility of further assistance from our allies under  existing conditions, hereby declare :     Firstly, that we have formed a government of the north-west province of Russia, comprising the former governments of Petrograd, Pskoff, and Novgorod,  and also those which shall be freed in that area from the tyranny of the Bolsheviks.     Secondly,  that we  have  undertaken  full  responsibility  for  the  decision of all provincial questions.     Thirdly, that we  rely on the Esthonian government to give immediate  aid  to the government of North-West Russia with an armed force for the deliverance of Petrograd and of the  Petrograd, Pskoff, and Novgorod governments from Bolshevik tyranny so that the government may establish in  Petrograd firm  democratic  order,  and initiate a democratic policy founded on respect  for the rights and liberties of man.     Fourthly, that we believe  that the allied  military mission which is  supplying the Russian  army with warlike stores will  continue  that  supply and also  that  of  foods, munitions of war, and other equipment  through the minister of war, and will also give us financial assistance.     Fifthly, that independently of this it is unavoidable to commence negotiations with-the Esthonian government in regard to the obtaining for the  new  province an outlet to the sea in the ports of Esthonia, with a view to mutual commercial relations.     Sixthly, in full  confidence that  the All-Russian government  of Admiral  Kolchak will appreciate, as we do, the  situation which  has been  created, we, while informing the supreme government of Admiral Kolchak of what has occurred and of  the  decision made by us, pray the  representatives of the United  States, France, and  Great Britain to  obtain from  their governments  a  recognition of  the absolute  independence  of Esthonia.     Message from General Rodzianko. On 1 6th August  the  deputy commissioner at Reval reported  that General  Rodzianko had sent  the  following  telegram to the government of North-West Russia :      To  the president  of the  North-Western government.    The north-west  army welcomes  in your person the  government  of  North-West Russia and hopes to find therein full support  in  the  task already begun  of freeing Russia from  the Bolshevik yoke,  introducing law and  order, and eventually leading Russia to the  constituent assembly as well as establishing good relations with the neighbouring states.     General Yudenich. In his telegram of 16th August the deputy commissioner at Reval also reported that he  had been informed by  the  premier, Mr.  Lianosov, that General Yudenich had telegraphed to Admiral Kolchak to the effect that he had placed himself unreservedly under the orders  of the  North-W^est Russian government, thus recognising the essential supremacy of the civil  power in a truly  democratic state.
NORTHERN TERRITORY.     Petitions  in regard  to  the  evacuation.   On  13th  August,  telegraphing  fromArchangel, Mr. Hoare transmitted [Nos.  527 and 528] a long message from the Unionof the Intelligentsia, and  another, equally long,  from  the  regional organizations of thecity of Archangel, both one and the other asking that the evacuation of the allied forces should not be proceeded with.  Mr. Hoare said that he did not feel justified in refusing to send these messages, which were intended for  the prime minister,  but he had told thedeputations which  had  brought  them  that the  decision  to  evacuate  was  quitedefinite.     The future defence of Archangel. In his  telegram of  13th  August Mr. Hoarereported that on the previous day the government had fully explained the  situation  tothe zemstvos and municipalities, who were told that the government could not delay for more than 3 or 4 days  its decision  in regard to the possibility of defending Archangel.At an  adjourned meeting  it was  decided that  in any case the  struggle  against theBolsheviks must continue.THE OMSK GOVERNMENT.     Appointment of  neio committees. On  16th August  Mr..  OReilly  transmitted[No.  725] a message sent from Omsk on the  12th by  the high  commissioner.   sir charles  Eliot said  that the  government wished to appear more  democratic for manyreasons:  amongst  others the growing  power of the Social Revolutionaries, and tbefear of civilian members of the government that the  present  crisis  would, result in tbewhole power of the  government being thrown  into the hands  of a few generals.   two new committees had therefore been formed with a view to  limiting military authority.First, a defence committee, composed of the  prime minister,  the ministers of theinterior, finance, foreign affairs, and war,  and  a second general;  and then a  committeeof law and order, consisting of the ministers  of justice,  war, and  the  interior,  whowere empowered to enquire into  all cases of  arbitrary  action, and could overridemilitary orders any citizen being at liberty to appeal to them.                                    TURKEY.     Resignations of  two  Cabinet Ministers. Telegraphing from Constantinople  on17th August [No. 1668] Admiral Webb reported the resignations of Tewfik Pasha andthe minister for war.  A certain Suleiman  Shefik  Pasha  had been  appointed [? to theministry of war] and apparently  had satis!ied  the grand vizier and  the  minister ofthe  interior that he would co-operate with them, but his antecedents  did not inspire confidence.  Admiral Webb added that the desertion of Tewtik  Pasha was significant;he, the admiral, doubted  whether, even with the support of the sultan  (which he stillenjoyed), Ferid would be able to carry on, though hewart   had expressed his determination to do so.     Escapes from Prison. On 18th August Admiral Webb  reported [No. 1670] thatHalil Pasha (EnveFs uncle) and Kutchuktala Bey, a prominent member of the C. U.P.,had escaped from the military prison in Constantinople, and that  Nouri Pasha (Enver&apos;sbrother), who had been confined at Batum, had  aiso escaped.                                     PERSIA.    . Agreement between the governments of Great Britain and Persia.-The following is the text of  an agreement which was signed at Teheran  on 9th August:      Preamble : In virtue  of the  close  ties of  friendship which have  existed  betweenthe two governments in  the past, and in the conviction that it is in the essential and mutual interests of both  in  future that  these ties  sheukl  be cemented, and that theprogress and prosperity  of Persia should be promoted  to the  utmost, it is herebyagreed between the Persian government on the one  hand, and his Britannic majesty&apos;minister, acting on  behalf of bis government,  on the other, as follows :-     1.  The British government reiterates, in the most  categorical  manner, the under-takings  which  they  have repeatedly given  in the past  to respect absolutely theindependence and integrity of Persia.
     2.  The British government will supply, at the cost of the Persian government, theservices of whatever expert advisers may, after consultation between the two govern-ments,  be considered necessary for  the several  departments of the Persian adminis-tration.  These advisers shall be engaged  on contracts and endowed with adequatepowers, the nature of which shall be the matter  of agreement between the Persiangovernment and the advisers.     3.  The British government will  supply, at the cost of the Persian  government,such officers  and such munitions and equipment  of modern type as  may be adjudgednecessary by a joint commission  of military experts, British and Persian, which shallassemble forthwith for the purpose of estimating the needs of Persia in respect of theformation of a uniform force which the Persian government proposes to create for theestablishment and preservation of order in the country  and on its frontiers.     4.  For the  purpose of financing the reforms indicated in clauses 2 and 3  of thisagreement, the British government offers to provide or arrange  a substantial loan forthe Persian  government,  for  which adequate  security  shall  be sought  by the twogovernments in  consultation in the revenues  of the customs or other sources of incomeat the disposal of the Persian government.   Pending  the  completion of negotiationsfor such a loan the British  government will supply on account of it such  funds as maybe necessary for initiating the said reforms.    5.  The British government, fully recognizing the urgent need which exists for theimprovement of communications in Persia,, with a view both to the extension of tradeand the prevention of famine, are prepared  to co-operate with the Persian governmentfor the  encouragement of Anglo-Persian enterprise  in this direction, both by means ofrailway construction and other forms of transport; subject always to the examinationof the problems by experts and to agreement between the two governments as to theparticular projects which may be most necessary, practicable, and profitable.    6.  The two governments agree  to the appointment forthwith of a joint committeeof experts  for the examination and  i-evision of the existing customs  tariff with a viewto its reconstruction on a basis calculated to accord  with the legitimate interests of thecountry and to promote its prosperity.    Agreement Relating to a Loan. The following agreement was also signed at Teheranon the 9th August:     Preamble :  Contract between the British government and the Persian governmentwith reference to an  agreement concluded this day between  the  said  governments.  Ttis agreed as follows :     Article .1. The British government grants a  loan  of  2,000,000Z.  sterling to thePersian government, to be  paid to the Persian government as required in such instal-ments and at such dates  as may be  indicated by  the  Persian  government after theBritish financial adviser shall have  taken up  the duties of his  office at  Teheran,  as provided for in the aforesaid agreement.    Art. 2.- -The Persian government undertakes to pay interest monthly at the rateof 7 per cent,  per annum upon sums advanced in accordance with Article 1 up to the20th March, 1921, and thereafter to pay monthly such amount as will suffice to liquidatethe principal sum and interest thereon at 7 per cent, per annum in twenty years.    Art. 3. All the revenues and customs receipts assigned in virtue of the contract of the 8th May,  1911, for the repayment of the loan of 1,250,000L are assigned for the repayment of the present loan with continuity of all  conditions  stipulated in the saidcontract, and with priority over all  debts  other  than the  1911  loan and  subsequentadvances made  by  the British  government.  In case  of insufficiency  of the  receiptsindicated above, the Persian government undertakes to make good the necessary sumsfrom other sources, and for this purpose the Persian government hereby assigns to theservice of the present loan  and of the other advances above mentioned, in priority andwith continuity  of conditions stipulated in the aforesaid contract, the customs receipts of all  other regions, in so far as these receipts are or shall be at its disposal.    Art. 4. The Persian government will have the right of repayment of the presentloan at  any date out of the proceeds of any British loan  which it may contract for.    Article 5  of Contract for  1911 Loan. The following, being  Article a of the contract between the Persian government and the Imperial Bank of Persia relating tothe Persian government 5 per cent, loan of 1,250,000Z. of the 8th May, 1911, has been published in  connexion with  the above treaty : The  imperial government of  Persiaspecially assigns to the service of the loan, and as  a  first charge thereon, subject only
 to prior  charges amounting  to  15,714Z. Is. lOd.  per  annum for three  years,  and 30,2781.  12s. 7d. per  annum from  the year 1913 to the  year  1928.  The  full net customs receipts of every  description which  the government now is,  or at any time hereafter may be, entitled to collect and receive  at  all ports or places in the Persian Gulf, including Bushire, Bunder Abbas,  Lingah, Mohammerah,  and Ahwaz,  which receipts are hereby made payable to  the bank, and the imperial government of Persia hereby engages forthwith after receipt thereof to pay  to the bank all  such customs receipts as aforesaid without deduction  other than for actual expenses of administration of the customs of the said ports disbursed prior to the date of such payment.    .  (a.)  The imperial government of Persia undertakes that throughout the continuance of the loan ad sums collected by the  customs  administration shall be paid to the bank at the  ports  the collection  or at  its nearest branch,  week by week  for meeting the prior charges referred to above and for the service of the loan, and  an  account of such receipts shall be submitted to the Persian government by the bank  at the end of each month.      (b.)  The bank shall,  out of the moneys  so collected, pay the prior charges  above mentioned, and the interest  and sinking fund of the loan, and shall  hold the surplus at the disposal of the imperial government of Persia.      (c.) The bank undertakes, out of the moneys so received, to pay  on behalf of the imperial government of Persia the  half-yearly  coupon in London, and supervise the working of the sinking fund and service of  the  loan  free of charges  connected  with the same.      (d.)  In the  event of the customs  receipts  of  the above-mentioned ports for  any three months falling short of the amount required for the prior  charges  and the service of the loan, either for interest or amortisation, the imperial government  of Persia binds itself to make good such  deficiency from  other sources of government revenue ;  and further, should receipts from these sources fall below the  amount required as above, the Persian government hereby assigns for this purpose the revenue derived from the receipts of the telegraphs this assignment to constitute a second charge on the said telegraph. receipts up to the year 1928, after which the  telegraph receipts will be free.     Letters to Vossugh-ed-Dowleh. On the 9th  August, the day  on  which the two agreements were signed,  the following letters were addressed by Sir Percy&apos; Cox to Vossugh-ed-Dowleh  -   -   (1.) Your highness, I  trust your highness has been able, during  your  successful direction of  affairs of the  Persian state, to convince yourself  that his  Britannic majesty s government  have  always endeavoured to support to the utmost the efforts of your highness&apos;s cabinet on the one hand to  restore  order and security in the interior of the country, and on the other to maintain a policy of close co-operation between the Persian and British governments.     As further  evidence  of the  goodwill  by which the cabinet of London  is inspired, I  am now authorised to inform  your highness that, in the event of  the  agreement regarding projects  of reforms  which  your  government contemplates introducing in Persia  being  concluded,  his Britannic  majesty&apos;s government  will be prepared in  due- course to co-operate with the Persian government with a view to the realization of the following desiderata :      1.  The revision of the treaties actually in force between the two powers.     2.  The claim of Persia to compensation for material damage suffered at the hands of other belligerents.     3.  The rectification of the frontier  of  Persia at the points where it is agreed upon by the  parties to be justifiable.     The precise manner, time, and means to be chosen  for pursuing these  aims shall be discussed, as soon as practicable, by the  two governments.     (2.) Your highness, With reference to the second desideratum  indicated in my previous  letter  of to-day&apos;s  date,  it  is  understood  and  agreed between the two governments  reciprocally  that,  on the  one hand,  his majesty&apos;s government will  not claim from the government of his majesty  the  Shah the cost of the maintenance of British troops which  his  majesty&apos;s government  was obliged to send to Persia owing to Persia:s want of power  to defend her neutrality, and that  on the other hand  the Persian government will not claim from the  British government an indemnity for any damage which may have  been caused  by  the said troops  during their  presence in Persian territory.       [647]   &quot;                                                          0
G     It is to be understood, however, that this agreement of the two parties does not inany way affect the  claims of individuals and private  institutions, which will be dealtwith independently.     A note from your highness informing me that you  accept this position on behalf ofthe Persian government will  suffice to record the agreement of the two governments onthis subject.     French  Criticism of the Agreement. On the 17th August Sir  George Grahametransmitted [No. 960] the following summary of a leading article in the &quot;Temps &quot; ofthat date,  which referred  to the explanation published in the &quot; Daily Mail &quot; to  theeffect that  the new agreement could not be  harmful to  France&apos;s commercial interestsand declared that French preoccupations were not of a commercial character :      In  this  article  the  writer, who  is  probably Monsieur Jean BZerbette, the foreigneditor, describes the wonderful geographical position of  Persia, which he says lies at the cross-roads of the three influences, English, Russian, and  German, which have opposedone another in the East: and points out  that it is impossible to calculate the advantages which Persia in twenty or thirty years may bring to a power which  employs modernmethods of exploitation there.     He says that the new Anglo-Persian agreement explicitly maintains the integrity and independence of Persia, but that the same expression was used in  the preamble tothe Anglo-Russian agreement of the 31st August,  1907, the  object  of which  was to divide Persian territory into  a British  and a Russian  zone.   The same words integrity and independence now reappear, and it  is difficult  to  give them in  1919 a differentmeaning to that attached to  them in 1907, namely, a purely oratorical precaution.     The writer affirms that it is easy to  see that the new treaty is  prejudicial  [porteatteinte) to the  independence of  Persia ; and the  fact that  the Persian governmentpromises to trust her army to British officers and her finances to  British  experts showsthat it has no independent force or resources wherewith to exercise her sovereignty andto  carry out  the policy which suits  her.   He  insists on  the fact that the political independence of Persia will no longer be after the treaty what it was before; article 10of the pact of the league of nations is quoted as laying  down that the  members  of theleague guarantee to respect and maintain against all foreign aggression  the territorial integrity and the present political independence of all its members.  Persia is mentionedin the annexe as being among the states invited to accede to  the  pact : therefore in virtue of the treaty of Versailles which contains the pact the present political indepen-dence of  Persia  ought to be but has not been respected.  It would be a very pharisaicargument to say that the treaty of Versailles has not yet  been put into force, or that Persiais not  yet a member of the league of nations, and the  British value  too highly theirreputation for rectitude to invoke such, arguments.     The writer draws attention to the fact that the new Anglo-Persian agreement doesnot exist until it has been duly voted  and passed by the Persian national assembly inaccordance with  article  24  of the Persian constitution of the  30th  December, 1906.The regular elections to the assembly,  which have only taken place in certain divisions,cannot be  completod while  the  present state of affairs  continues, and the country isunder a regime of British military occupation.   If  there  exists any doubt on this scoreir, is only necessary  to send  an  international commission of enquiry to make investiga-tions on the spot.     Still  pursuing the same line of  argument, the writer puts the  supposition  thatBritish  troops leave  Persia  in  a  few months, that the elections for the assembly aresuccessfully concluded, that  the assembly (which seems  unlikely to the writer) ratifiesthe  treaty, and  then asks   what would be the result.  By that time the  treaty ofVersailles would be  in force, and Persia would be a member of the league of nations.Article 10  of the pact would then apply, the dismemberment of Persia&apos;s independence would  be illicit,  and the Anglo-Persian  agreement would be annulled by article 20 ofthe pact, which  states that if a  member  before joining the league has entered into anyengagements incompatible with its terms, it must take immediate steps to rid itself ofthese obligations.     The writer  denies that he has  any arriere-pensee in thus drawing attention tothe legal aspect of the case, or any idea of  saying  to  the British &quot; Give us compensa-tion elsewhere and  our  scruples will vanish.&quot;  &quot; We remain,&quot; he declares, &quot; faithful tothe principle which President  Wilson proclaimed  on the  11th  February,  1918.&quot;&quot; Peoples and provinces should no longer be  bartered for  among  governments likecattle, or like the pawns on a chess-board.&quot;   &quot; The  maintenance of right in the East asin the West is the only saleguard of peace,  and that is why,&quot;  he adds, &quot;the  case of persia appears to be  disquieting.&quot;
    The writer concludes by  pointing to  the  indefensible  contradiction  that  exists between the policy which Great  Britain has pursued in  Persia in carrying on longnegotiations at Teheran, while a Persian delegation  was waiting in vain to obtain ahearing from  the peace  conference in Paris, and the engagements into which  GreatBritain has entered in Paris ;  and he speaks  of the security of France in the Europe ofto-morrow depending  in part on Great Britahfs engagement in  connection  with the pact of the league of nations.   &quot; We cannot tolerate  the thought that British promisescan be the subject of discussion, even when they apply to Asia.&quot;    The Shah. Telegraphing from  Constantinople  on the 19th  August  [No.  1680]Admiral Webb reported that the  Shah  had  arrived that morning after&apos; a highly successful journey from Teheran.  His further  movements were  uncertain ;  but hisobjective was Switzerland.o

</content>
</cab>
