<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/23 images: 222-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1945.if Copy No.W.P. (45) ,273. %f28^ ipn7, 1945.WAR CABINET.RECRUITMENT  FOR  THE  INDIAN  CIVIL  SERVICE ANDTHE INDIAN POLICE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.AT their meeting on the 9th June, 1944,* the War Cabinet agreed that itwas essential to maintain European recruitment for the Indian Civil Serviceand the Indian Police at its present strength and quality and invited me to give further consideration, in consultation with the Treasury and the Civil service commission, to the basis and terms of recruitment to secure this end.As regards the basis of recruitment, the question of inte-rchangeability withthe Administrative Class of the Home Civil Service, which was felt by some ofmy colleagues to merit examination, has been discussed by officials of my Depart-ment with representatives of the Treasury and of the Civil Service Commissionand has been found not to be a practicable proposition. (This does not exclude the possibility of secondment of selected officers for limited periods either fortraining purposes or to undertake specific tasks. Such interchange of personnelis of value and will continue to be encouraged in suitable cases.) Nor is inter-changeability with other overseas Services any less impracticable.It is agreed to be essential that candidates for the Indian Civil Service andthe Indian Police should be clearly warned that, if they are appointed, theirappointments under the Secretary of State will be liable to be terminated at anytime on account of constitutional changes, subject to their being given 12 months&apos;notice. As regards the terms to be offered in these conditions to post-war recruits,some of my colleagues felt that the terms outlined in my previous memorandum twere likely to prove insufficiently attractive. This matter has been the subjectof prolonged discussions by officials of my Department, in consultation with theTreasury, the Civil Service Commission and the Department concerned in theGovernment of India, and also at a later stage by the Governor-General of indian Council and by my Advisers, whose concurrence in the decision reached upon it is required by Section 261 of the Government of India Act, 1935. As a resultof these discussions it has been decided to substitute for the existing pensionarysystem, not the combination of a contributory Provident Fund and a graduatedscale of gratuities originally contemplated, but a scheme of lump sum grantsranging from  1,500 after 5 years&apos; service to  15,000 after 25 or more years&apos;service in the case of officers who retire voluntarily, and from  4,000 after 5 years&apos;service to  15,000 after 16 or more years&apos; service in the case of officers whoseappointments under the Secretary of State are terminated on account of constitu-tional changes. It is not considered necessary to provide for the payment of aretirement grant to officers who retire voluntarily within 5 years. Officers whoseappointments under the Secretary of State are terminated within that periodon account of constitutional changes will receive such proportionate grant asthe Secretary of State may decide. The proposed grants have been referred by my Department to the Treasury. The latter, after close examination and consultation with the Government Actuary, have expressed concurrence in theproposals as likely to satisfy the requirement of being sufficiently generous to attract recruits of the right type without being unduly extravagant.CONFIDENTIAL.* W.M. (44) 74th Conclusions, Minute 3[29789]f W.P. (44) 287.
It is hoped that, if and when appointments under the Secretary of Stateare terminated on account of constitutional changes, many of the officers affectedwill be invited and will be willing to continue to serve under Government inIndia. In such cases the grants appropriate to their length of service under theSecretary of State would be placed to their credit with an independent authority and would be paid to them on their leaving the service of Government in India,or to their heirs if they die while still serving.The necessary measures have been taken to issue full information aboutrecruitment to and service in the Indian Civil Service and Indian Police, togetherwith the requisite application forms, &amp;c, simultaneously with comparable matter in respect of the other civil Services in which a career is now being offered, bymeans of Admiralty Fleet Orders, Army Council Instructions and Air MinistryOrders to all potential candidates now serving in the Forces in all theatres, aswell as by Press announcements to those qualified by other types of &quot; war service.&quot; The date fixed by agreement between the Service authorities and theDepartments concerned for this general publication is the 1st June.L. S. A.India Office,26th April, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
