<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 30-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Majesty1 s 24Government.It is roguested that this doeument be &apos;       treated&quot;as^hTfl^Xy bonfllen^TaT7 &quot;SECRET Special Branch,Report Ho. 193; flew Scotland Yard,February 15th, 1923.0&apos;  .   &apos;05     (23) )*)WoRT OB REVOLUTIONARY ORGANISATIONS__----i^ / IK THE UNITE]) KINGDOM.WMALl GAR^pT -..............O00r-----&apos;.............THE COMMUNISTS.............................. Page 1THE COMMUNIST PARTY PROGRAMME............... &quot;   5THE RSD INTERNATIONAL OF LABOUR UNIONS...... &quot;   6THE YOUHG OOSMOHIST LEAGUE.................. &quot;   8OPEN LETTER TO THE BRITISH LABOUR PARTYFROM MANaBEKIRa EaTH ROY.............. &quot;11THE UN EMPLOYED.............................. &quot; 12IRISH REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES IBGRSi. T BRITAIN...................... &quot; 14SUMMARYOn February 5th the wholly unemployed on the live registers totalled approximately 1,386,300, a decrease of 23,690 on the preceding week:   on the same date the number working short time and drawing benefit for intervals of unemployment was 52,800 as compared with 54,674 on January 29th.The recruiting march orrsmised by the Council of Action of the unemployed has proved a iiasco:   the number of marchers who returned to London on February 13th was smaller then the number who set out on January 24th:   the leaders are disappointed and doubtful about their next move.There are indications of growing restlessness among the unemployed in seme centres:   this is at present taking the form of demonstrations to the Guardians for increased, relief.Details are given of a meeting of the Communist Party Council held in London last week-end, also of the communist programme published in the first issue of the new paper.The British Bureau, of the Red International of labour&apos; Unions is demanding that a &quot;national assembly of working-class representatives&apos;1 should be convened in order to secure the unification of Labour forces against the &quot;capitalist attack&quot; on., wages and hours, :The Young Communist League is making plans for an &quot;anti-militarist&quot; campaign.
TSB COMMUNISTSOn February 10th and 11th, the Party Council of the Communist Party met at the Shaftesbury Hotel, london, sitting from 3-7 p.m. on Saturday and from &apos; 10 a.m. -10 p.rn. on Sunday:   each delegate produoed, presumably in lieu of giving a password, a slip bearing the words &quot;in pursuit of these alms we are prepared to approach any other.&quot;    Some thirty delegates were present including Mrs. Crawfurd, Albert Inkpin, H. Inkpin, rJ?om Bell, V/. Gallacher, G. Peet, B. Joy, &apos;W. Brain, 0. Ford, IL. Davies, E.H. Brown, &apos;J?om Clart, J?. luvin, R. Foulis, J. Dowell, J. Braddook, F, Duggan, E.W. Cant, Hat Watkirrs, J. Wilson, H. Webb, S. lismer ana Palme Dutt.After discussion regarding the Party Programme, which is to be drawn up and submitted to Mosoow, all agreed; that it should indicate a fighting policy and not contain rules but aims and objects with a definite objective and a statement that oivil war would be inevitable before the dictatorship of the proletariat could be established.Certain delegates offered the customary opposition to the United Front polioy but it was eventually decided to work &quot;hand in glove&quot; with the labour Party for the following concrete demands:1.    Wage8:    Ho reduction in wages.2*    Spurs:    Ho extension of hours.3.    Unemployment:    Work at Trade Union Rates or full maintenance and no gaps.4*    Workshop Control.5.     Housing:(a) Ho increase of rents.(b) Ho compromise on back rents.(c) Ho evictions.(a)   Clearing of slums and temporary accommodation for those dishousea.&apos; Civil 6./&apos;;.&apos;
6.     Post of Living:(a) Removal of all taxation on food.No reduction of taxation for the rich.(b) formation of Housewives1 Committees to struggle against high cost of living.(o)   Full maintenance for expectant mothers, eight weeks before end eight weeks&apos; after confinement.(a)   Feeding of infants.&quot;The Executive Committee was blamed for not exploiting the unemployed movement but Tom Bell denied inactivity in this direction ana said that the credit for organising the unemployed march to London was due to the Communist Party who praotically controlled the National Administrative Council of the organised unemployed:   as however men of all shades of political opinion belonged to the unemployed movement it was considered unwise for the Communist Party to show   its hand too much.Some of the discussions were distinctly acrimonious and at one time during the S,unday session the speakers beoame so heated that their remarks were overheard by the hotel residents who were alarmed to hear such phrases as &quot;Work within the Labour Party and blow them to bits&quot; - &quot;Civil War&quot; -&quot;Revolution&quot;.     The Executive Committee was severely taken to task for autocratic action, discourtesy, inactivity and failure to leaa or even to answer simple questions:     Tom Bell adroitly countered with details of &quot;insurmountable difficulties&quot; and managed to smooth matters down.     The Scottish delegates who were reproved for Quoting&apos; nationalities&quot; instead of talking about &quot;oommunists In Scotland&quot; protested violently against the new name of &quot;The Communist&quot; which they said damaged the sale of the Glasgow &quot;Worker&quot;:   it seems likely however, that the new name will be retained.It is reported that 10,000 more copies of &quot;The Workers1 Weekly&quot; had to be printed on Thursday night, making the totalissue/
issue of the first number 25,000i   Froude, the printer, is pressing for payment of his account, which totals nearly  400,   The main feature of the first issue, was the Party Programme which is dealt with in another part of this report:     there was also a &quot;Woikers&apos; Sports section&quot; in the course of which it was stated that a red football team was recently formed in south Shields which a hundred young workers had joined and that the Young Communist League was organising sports sections throughout the country.     The author of the serial &quot;The Pt-.th of the Workers&quot; is Ruth Morgan.The Communist Party is holding a &quot;propaganda Week&quot; from February 17th - 25th in connection with which Tom Bell will speak at a meeting of the Ilford Labour Party on February 25th.A Women&apos;s National Committee has been formed and consists of:-Mary Moorhouse, Minnie Biroh, Ellen Wilkinson, Nellie Lansbury, Esther Enever, Helen Crawfurd, William Gallacher, -   Marx (Minute secretary)Three departments have been set up:(a)   Press. Mary Moorhouse with small committee., (b)   Propaganda.   Minnie Birch.(c)   Finance.        He Hie Lansbury and small committee.Another packet of verbose instructions regarding&quot;the international women&apos;s Kay&quot; on March 8th has been sentto this country from Moscow and Helen Crawfurd is thinkingout sohemee for a celebration in this country.The Executive of the Communist Party has selected theI following list of parliamentary candidates for theAmalgamated/
Amalgamated Engineering Union and has instructed groups towork for one or the other according to the locality:Gallacher, Hannington, Dickson, Lawrence, Hinshelwood, Murphy.The Communist groups at Coatbridge and Mrdrie, which have a total membership of 35, have formed a Local Party Committee:   the Wiahaw, Motherwell and Bellshill branches are also combining to set up a Local Party Committee.The Executive of the Communist i?arty of Great Britain end the Communist Party of Ireland intend to hold a joint meeting in the near future:   A.B.F. White, the political secretary of the latter suggests that the meeting should be held in London as &quot;three out of our five executive members are employed by capitalist firms which give no week-end holiday.     It is reported on the authority of a single informant that Connolly and MoLay are discredited in Russia and with the Communist Party of Great Britain who told them last week to leave 16 King Street and find fresh offices.Jackson has been appointed to the Information Department of the Communist P^rty in place of J.T. Wtlton Newbold, M.P.Percy Howard, who was for .erly distribution and business manager at 16, King Street, has been replaced by ex* councillor Hawkins:   Howard has gone to arcos.Robert Stewart has resigned from the Russian Famine Department, and intends to go home this week.A. purcell is organising the Eastern Counties for the Building Trades&apos; Federation:   he is a member of the Communist party and a keen advocate of the Red International of Labour Unions.V THE/
. 5 - 6 yTHE COMMUNIST PARTY PRO GRAINSThe first issue of &quot;The Workers&apos; Weekly&quot; contained a programme from \which the following extracts are taken:it is hoped to ascertain the nature of the passages&quot;Censored by Printer&quot;.&quot;Our aims are the aims of the Communist International, the International of the &quot;Workers.   The following summary has been drawn up to assist new readers to understand our position, and to show why every Worker should look to the Communist Piirty as his Party...&quot;The workers must change the present conditions. They must drive the capitalists from possession and set up instead a workers&apos; system of society, where all in common own and work and share the results of work. Capitalist society, which has broken down, must give way to Conim-unist society, or mankind perishes.   Only the workers can accomplish this change.&quot;To do this the workers must got power.   The capitalists will resist any change by all means at their disposal.   The power of the capitalists must be wrested from them.   The workers must set up their own Uiate.Censored by printer.&quot;A real workers1 government must be based on the workers&apos; mass organisations and bo responsible to them. The workers&apos; State is a class states   openly and unashamedly   - The Dictatorship of the Proletariat: just as the capitalist State is a concealed class state, in which the pretence of democracy and liberty and eeuality is used to conceal the dictatorship of the capitalists.    The Dictatorship of the Proletariat is the necessary means of the change from capitalism to Cornnunism.Censored by Printer.&quot;How will the workers make the change once they have established their State?the big&quot;The workers must first of all expropriate capitalists, the big financiers, landowners and industrialists-    The small property owners they can leave alone until their forces are stronger.   Rut all largo property must be confiscated at once without compensation:   since to buy out the capitalists, whose power is money, is only to leave them in power.&quot;The Workers&apos; Government must nationalise the banks.It/
&quot;It must take over all largo industrial undertakings, mines and shipping.&quot;It must declare all land and houses public property.&quot;It must establish a State monopoly of foreign trade.&quot;It must annul all debts, public and private.THE RED IHSERHATIOHil, OP LABOUR 1MI0HSOn Jftnuary 29th, 1923, Reinhardt and Xrebs, on behalfof the Central European Bureau sent the followingcommunication to the British Bureau of the RedInternational of Labour Unions:&quot;The Congress in Moscow stated, that there   is quite necessary to organise in all countries a strong work in the different Propeganda Committees.   Therefore we beg. you to indicate us the comrades who are intrusted with the work in the following professions:-1.	Msttallistg	7.	Typographers2.	Miners	8.	Agricultural workers.	Building workers	9.	Teachers, etc.4.	Textile	10.	Woodworkers5.	Transport	11.	Cor-jmunworkers.6.	Chemists.	12.	Leather.Then there is necessary that the comrades be trusted with the leading of these groups send regularly monthly reports to the General Secretary of the Propaganda Committee of the profession in question.You h^ve probably heard that many good champions in Prunce have &quot;been errested by the government of &quot;Poincare-la Guy r re&quot;.     You must prepare a great movement of protestation against this emprisonnement of Trade Union fighters.   Will you please send the results of this nation to Coiart-do Rosmer in the CG.T.U- raid to the french trade press for publication.We send you to-day the appeal of the Textile I CP to all Textile-Workers requesting you to publish it in your press.&quot;The appeal mentioned above urges the textile workers to protest against the arrest of the secretary of the Textile Wovkers Union and of other workers in prance.The Contra! European Bureau of the Red International of labour Unions has sent the British Bureau othe official report of the Fourth International Conference of RevolutionsMineworkers/ernational Committee of Propaganda.
Mineworkere which took place in Moscow on December 4th and 5th, 1922.   S.O. Davies, of the south Wales Miners&apos;Federation, was electee&apos; a member of the Exeoutive of theInternational Propaganda Committee with N* Watkins as Mssubstitute.    A lengthy programme for the InternationalPropaganda Committee was drawn up which covered inter alia&quot;Nationalisation with the gradual socialisation of the mines without compensation to the owners and the right of the workers to manage the industry.&quot;&quot;6 hour day for plain labour and 4 hours for dangerous or especially hard work.&quot;&quot;4 weeks&apos; leave yearly with full pay.&quot;&quot;Full Recognition of soviet Russia&quot;.&quot;Abolition of Versailles Treaty.&quot;It is of interest to note that among the measures to be employed in attaining the desired objective it is laid down that &quot;before each strike of the mine workers the Presidium of the International Propaganda Committee is to be informed about it in the right time in order to enable it to call conferences and to make the necessary preparations.&apos;&apos;The Central European Bureau has advised the British Bureau that it is better for propaganda for &quot;all English speaking countries such as South Africa, Australia, India, China and Japan&quot; to be sent from Berlin than from London and has requested that a supply of the English &quot;Miners&apos; Bulletin&quot; be sent to Germany for distribution in the above mentioned countries.The British Bureau has decided:&quot;To proceed with the Recall conferences at onoe in London, Glasgow and Cardiff, not only to hear the delegates report from the International Congress, but to incorporate in our programme, resolutions dealing with the present phase of the working class struggle, such as full support for the Building Workers in their struggle to resist the 47 hour week.   Also in view of the close proximity of the output of the British mines to the figures quoted in the Sankey Commission Report the miners should fight for a six hour dey, instead of an eight hour day as suggested by the employers.&quot;The/
Hie British Bureau of the Bed International of labourUnions has issued a manifesto in leaflet form in the courseof which it declares that:-&quot;To-day the organised working-class movement is faced with the most- critical situation of its history. Having succeeded in brestteirtg down the wages standards of the workers, the employers massed behind the Federation of British Industries and the Government, are now embarking upon a general attack on the hours of labourt beginning with the Building Trude Workers and the Miners.,.&quot;We must reply to the coming attacks by taking the offensive.   Wo must concentrate all the available strength of our movement in order to win.WORK or FULL MAniTENANCE FOR THE ITNEMPLOYEDTHE FORTY-FOUR HOUR WORiCIilG week the SIX-HOUR DAY FOR MINERS.THE CONSCRIPTION OF WEALTHAIL POWER TO THE workers should now be our fighting slogans.&quot;In order to ensure the unification of the forces of our class we must urge the General council of the Trades Union Congrays to immediately convene a national assembly of working-class representatives. The times demand something larger and more decisive than a Trades Union Congress, consisting mainly of Trade Union officials.   We suggest that a national gathering of delegates from trades councils, trade union branches and district committees, working-class local and national political organisations, unemployed organisations, co-operative societies and guilds - a really All-in-Conference - should be called.   Such a conference to meet to elaborate plans of campaign, and form Councils of Action to ensure the carrying into effect of the workers&apos; demands.&quot;THE YOUNG COMMUNIST LEAGUE&quot;Acting on instructions issued by the Fourth Congress of the Young Communist International&quot;, the Young Communist League intends to conduct an &quot;anti-militarist&quot; campaign from Mr..rob llth-18th, with demonstrations in Trafalgar Squure, if possible on both these dates and an indoor meeting in the Memorial Hull,The Young Communist League has recommended theissue/
- 9 -33issue of a &quot;Headquarters Bulletin&quot; - &quot;for the informationof members only&quot;:   in No.l of the new Series, it isstated, in reference to the anti-militarist campaign that:&quot;The Third World Congress of the young Communist International decided to instruct the international Executive Ccmlttee to organise this campaign.   This means that in practically every corner of the Globe, young workers, in large or sPall numbers, according to the influence wielded by the Young Communist International, are leading a campaign for a decisive struggle against militarism.&quot;Great Britain plays a most important part in this campaign, despite the comparative smallness of our numbers..&quot;The reasons for the instruction to institute this campaign are now obvious to all, at the time of the Third Congress, it was apparent to all students of the World Situation, as Young Communists are, that now wars were not far distant.&quot;Since the time of that Congress Decision events have happened with bewildering rapidity.&quot;The Ruhr, Mosul, Memel, events which are demonstrating the Determination of the Imperialists to carry their offensive a stage further by forcing the workers down at the point of the bayonet, and that their need for Oil and spheres of influence will hurl the workers into another world-wide catastrophe.&quot;These things we Young Comnrunists know, and the significance of our campaign lies in the fact that we are that section, that conscious minority of the working class youth (which is mainly depended upon for the cannon-fodder for the coming war), which is equally determined that the working class youth shall not., be used by the British bourgeoisie to further TFs dreams of empire...&quot;We demand a United Front with the pacifist proselytes of the   and  ^ Internationals because it applies the test of action to those who will do anything to prevent the workers from taking action.&quot;Yfhen we confront the leaders of the Young Labour league with an appeal for a United Front, we virtually say to them &quot;Here are the youyg workers in this terrible situation, here are our definite demands, will you stand together with us for the aafe-guarding of the lives of the young workers.     If you refuse, then you expose, to your own followers, your betrayal of the elementary interests of the yousg workers.   If, in fear of exposing yourselves to your misguided followers, you agree, then you will be forced into the struggle, with the masses hehind you, and the struggle itself will eventually drive you out and put the real loaders of the workers, the Communists at theit head.The/
- 10 -34&quot;Trie United Front tactic has been characterised at the Fourth Congress of the Comintern as the key to the situation, it must be the key-note of our anti-militarist campaign, always and everywhere throughout the campaign we must harp on this note, and force the pacifists and Labourites either to betray themselves to their followers or drive them into a joint struggle...&quot;Points for Speakers Luring the Campaign&quot;General lines pamphlet, &quot;Ho More War&quot;.10,000,000 dead, 80,000,000 wounded.   Result of War.Unemployed walk streets in &quot;country fit for heroes&apos;.Promises of Government, Land, Homes, etc.Statements of politicians.   (War to end War).To-day they say &apos;Ite rubbish to say that the last mv wae a war to end war, we shall have a war, and a big war, within the lifetime of many of you sitting in this room&apos;. Speech of Major-General Egerton at the annual dinner of officers of the H.L.I. in Glasgow.The great wax (to end war) cost this country approximately 12,000,000,000 pounds.Colonel W. Guinness says that &quot;That it cost this country 54,658,000 pounds from the armistice to July 31st, 1922.They spend 1-^d per head on slum clearing.In 1915 the whole of Europe was spending  426,000,000 on armaments, to-day Great Britain alone spends  159,000.000 more than one fourth of the total Exiropean expenditure in 1915.Total number of troops under arms in 1913,3,780,950. According to Major-general   Maurice.After the Washington Disarmament (?) Conference,-according to the League of Hetions Bureau 4,458.,179 actually under arms.Great Britain:   the tax-payers of Groat Britain are faced with an annual bill of 60-70 million pounds.This sum is roughly equivalent to the total expenditure of this country on poor law relief and unemployment benefits during 1921-1922*&quot;The Supplement to the &quot;Young Communist&quot; for February, reproduces in fi.ll the &quot;Ho More War&quot; manifesto of the Young Communist International from which extracts were given in Report Ho. 191.Open/
OPBH LETTER TO jjgg BRITISH LABOUR PARTY FROM laAflABEBDRA NATH ROYThe issue of &quot;The International Press Correspondence&quot;dated February 6th contained the following:-&quot;Open LetterTo the Executive Committee ofThe British Labour Party,London.Gentlemen,Out of the 228 men sent up for trial in connection with the riots in the village of Chauri chuura in the United provinoes, 172 have been aentenoed to death by . imperialist justice.   The history of the oase may not be unknown to you.   In the winter of 1920-21 the discontent among the poor peasantry of the United Provinoes, where Feudalism reigns supreme under the protection of the British government, was very acute. . In many a place this discontent broke out into open revolt against the oppression of landlordism.   The British government, which always poses as the protector of the tenant and has given some legal shape to this pretension in order to secure the Royalty&apos; of the peasant masses, however, did not hesitate a moment to send armed forceb as soon as the &quot;life and property1 of the loyal landowners were menaced by poor cultivators driven to revolt by hunger.   Thus the traditional illusion of the Indian peasantr;, about the &quot;benevolence&apos; of the airkar was shaken and they found themselves face to  ace with the forces of Slate coeroion allied with tyrannical landlordism.   This combination of forces led up to the   incident at Chauri Chaura, which was brought about by Police provocation.&quot;The men arrested after the Cbxuri Chaura riots and after the outbreaks that subsequently spread in the surrounding districts had been suppressed by unrestrainec use of bayonets and other forms of terrorism, were charge with the &quot;murder1 of a number of policemen at Chauri    \ Chaura.     22 policemen were killed in the affray;   but&apos;&apos; the dispensers of imperialist justice conveniently overlooked the facts&quot;that the affray was begun by the policemen firing on peaceful demonstrators, and that the number of men killed and wounded in consequence of firing volleys on a crowd of several thousand must have exoeedet the casualties on the government side.One hundred and seventy-two men, many of whom were hungry peasant a&quot; and who were soTiungry because they had been forced to contribute too heavily to the fund for helping the &apos;vi&amp;r for democracy&quot;, stand sentenced to be *hangod by the neck until dead&quot;.   This legal murder is being perpetrated in the name of &quot;law and&quot;order&apos; and &quot;good government&apos;.   The real crime committed by these to rebel against unbearable economic exploitation and to demonstrate the desire to fight for their rights.     In doing so, they had to challenge the feudal absolutism whioh flourishes in India under the benign protection of British Democracy.     These men will legally be murderedfor/
for having spontaneously expressed the noble principles;, that inspired the glorious pousant Revolts of Great Britain and other European countries.   In order to defend the rights of landlordism, which constitutes its most loyal-support, British Iuperialism is committing a barbarous : deed which will even surpass its own none too admirable records in India.   Mils prostitution of justice will be unparalleled in its majestic vindictiveness and brutalltyi,On behalf of the toiling millions of India, and in the name of &quot;justice and fair play&apos;, in which you believe so implicitly, we call xipon you to lead the British working -class to intervene and demand the reprieve of the condemned champions of the Indian peasantry.   Wo oall upon the British labour Party to exert pressure upon the government by means of Parliamentary action, as well as by strikes and demonstrations in case parliamentary action fails to bring about the desired effect.   You must take these steps if you want to prove that you are not a party&apos; to the imperialism of the Briuish bourgeoisie.   If you fail to act in this tragic moment, you will go down in history with the blood of the Indian peasantry on your head, and you \vill stand charged with the betrayal of those principles of &apos;freedom and democracy&apos; that you claim to advocate.   A% the same time we appeal directly to the British proletariat to repudiate your leadership in case you fail to act and thus condone this legal murder by infuriated Imperialism,Zurich, February 2, 1923.II.K. Roy,For 3Sia Communist Party of India,&quot;m UHSMPLOYEDThe rooruiting march of the unemployed has proved a fiasco,for when the &quot;northern and southern armies&quot; arrived at hyde park on Tuesday,, their number was smaller than when they set out from Tower Hill on January 24xh.     By 3 p.m. on February 13thmarchers and London unemployed in Hyde Park totalled about 700and were addressee by Hannington, Gibson, Stangroom, Cook,Homer and the Rov. T.E. Pickering.   The speeches containedcomparatively little new matter.    H*nnington said that the fineof  5 imposed on him at Rugby had been paid by one of theGuardians.     Gibeon of Sheffield said:&quot;I call the red card system all right, I claim here and now that every unemployed man should make it a point of duty to see that every week he has got a red stamp on his card...   You can have your card paid up to date, you can/
can show it to the policeman and say look here, I am fully paid up, you can ask Wal Hannington and Percy Haye if you iike, and say to the police will you get out of the way and let us capture the national gas-house. Iu io silly, my friends.   You will have to altar the whole business of the whole national system on the character similar to the Irish rebels.   I don&apos;t care what the consequences are that will have to be done. The best of the unemployed will have to get together, and damn your meetings of protest they get nowhere my friends.   The Irishmen, when they want to shift the police, he does not get a red card out of his pocket and show It to the policeman, he goe3 through the same motions but it is not a red card.&quot;The marchers were told to disperse as follows:-Oarringtqn House, Peptford:   Sheffield, Coventry, Salford, Rotherham, Newcastle and Gateshead.Poplar:   Edinburgh (1st and 2nd.), Glasgow, Dundee,Sewton Heath, Gt. Yarmouth, Paisley and Birmingham.South West Ham:   Manchester and the Manchester district contingent whioh joined the marchers at Coventry.The Chief Constable informs me that when the two contingents passed through Windsor on February 11th the majority were carrying stout sticks about 32 inches in length, on some of which were pasted slips of paper with the words &quot;For you Bonar Law&quot;.-Priox to the opening of Parliament a few unemployed with sandwich boards and red rosettes paraded Whitehall hut left the line of route before the Royal Procession.The Chief Constable of Brighton informs me that ageneral meeting of the Brighton Unemployed Organisation onFebruary 9th passed the following resolution:&quot;That owing to the Communistic attitude of the leaders of the Notional Unemployed Committee Movement, the Brighton Unemployed Organisation feel that the Communists are using the unemployed as an exploiting ground for.&quot;Red7 propaganda. &apos; The Brighton Unemployed Organisation, therefore cancel their affiliation with the National Administrative Council; and henceforth link up with all the unemployed throughout Sussex.&quot;2he Chief Constable of Barrow informs me thi-t onFebruary 6th several thousand unemployed formed a torchlightprocesBion and marched to the offices of the Board of guardians where a de-nutation introduced by the oommunistH.E. Itowbold&apos;
- 14 -tH.E. Newbold put forward the national demandb of the iorganised unemployed movement:   it was announced that the Board would give a decision at their meeting on jrebruary 13th when another torchlight procession was to have been held.The organised unemployed appear to he losing ground in Barrow:   one newsagent stated last week that he was only selling 300 instead of 900 copies of &quot;Out of Work&quot; in a fortnight:   it was also reported that the weekly financial contributions have failed from  5 to 30/-.IRISH REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITEBB IB GREAT BRITAINThe announcement of Liam Deasy^ volte face caused considerable consternation among the Republican leaders here,, although, after having had time to recover themselves, they now profess to regard it as being of no importance.   Their; first move was to circulate a story that the man under arrest was not the real Liam Leasy, but a man of no importance/who happened to bear a similar name;   this they have now dropped.That they do attach considerable importance to it is shown by the issue of a &quot;fight to a finish&quot; leaflet headed &quot;Fraud when Force has failed&quot; and containing the followingipassages:-&quot;The Colonials, having failed to break the forces of tT*eRepublic by terrorism are again resorting to intrigue.   By false words they are trying to fool bravo men for whom the firing Bquad and the torture chamber held no terrors...&quot;There may be a few amongst us who,,under the influence of terror or falsehood, will fall from the ranks. The only result of their defection will be to harden the determination of those who are left that the cause we stand for will be brought to triumph.&quot;Art 0&apos;Brien has been quiet since his rebuff over theChelsea Town.Hall meeting but a meeting of the London DistrictCommittee of the Irish balfour-Determination League has beenarranged for       February 15th when the following matters are to be cGmjiilereds-W
1.    Reports from distributors of Handbills re interference with them by the clergy.2.    co-operation between branches for entertainments and meetings.S.    Ways and means of pushing the sale of the new Republican paper.4.    Special public meetings - Possible visit of an important speaker.5.    Suggested meeting for members of all Republican Organisations in London.The speaker referred to is the Countess MarkievicziAn important meeting took place on a&amp;feruary 8th at84, Blaokfriars Road, and was attended by Art 0&apos;Brien,Dr. 0&apos;Connor, P.]). 0&apos;Harte, C.B. Dutton, Father MdXenna,Bintan Murphy, Ssklatvala, two members of the organising committee of the Communist Party of Ireland and J. J.0&apos;Leary the Organising Secretary.      The political situation was fully discussed and it was agreed that the future policy of both organisations would be better served by amuch closed relationship between them.   With this object inview it was decided to hold fraternal meetings at whichcomrades of both parties would attend and get more into touch with eaoh other.The Countess Markievicz, whose departure from Glasgowhad been arranged for the 12th, is stated to have changed hermind and she is now expected to remain for another week.In her many addresses she made no secret of her sympathy withCommunism, although some of her speeches did not give entiresatisfaction to that body.   She has infused now life into the republican movement and is reported to have had an interview with Joe Robinson on February 7th with a view to uniting the communists ana Irish Republicans in Scotland.   Charles Diamond,Robinson&apos;s Brigade Adjutant, is said to be in favour of suchan alliance.At/
At St. MungCa Hall on February 6th the Countess M&amp;rkievicz advocated the shooting of spies ana tho destruction of capitalist property in Ireland but was opposed to the shooting of prisoners of war.   The burning of houses belonging to those high in authority against the Republic was, she said, a means of making them feel a sense of their responsibilities.At many of her meetings she pleaded for more financial support so that whon she returned to Ireland she could say:   &quot;Tho Irish exiles of Sootland are with us.&quot; Her criticism of the Free State was very bitter.   She asserted that the Irish people knew nothing about the Treaty and if they could only read the   Froe State Constitution for themselves they would not be duped.   &quot;Bad as the British wero the present pro-British crowd are worse.&quot;Joseph Brown, the Republican Organiser, is in communication with Art 0&apos;Brien on the question of common propaganda policy for Scotland and England.On February 9th the Cum6nn-na-m3an and &quot;the Irish Republican Army gave a reception to the Countess Markievicz in the Brugha Hall, Govan;   Miss Molly Duffy read the address. A dance followed y&apos;kioh lasted till 5 a.m.     During the progress of the dance an Irish Republican Army Battalion Council meeting was held in a roon off the Hall.

</content>
</cab>
