<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 221-236</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Tills document is the property of His Majesty&apos;a Government.It is requested that this document be  Creeled&quot; a a highly oonfiaTrHiaTT^SgOKBTgen or t No. 194.Special Branoh,Now Scotland yard, S.W.I.February 22nd, 1923.THE COMMUNISTS............... page 1REVOLUTIONARY PROPAGANDA IN THE TRADEUNION MOVEMENT....................... &quot; 5THE YOUNG COMMUNIST LEAGUE................ &quot; 9THE UKEMPIOYSD............................ &quot; 11IRISH EBTOIUTIONARY ACTIVITIES INGEEaT BEITAIN........................ &quot; 13SUMMARYOn February 12th the wholly unemployed on the live registers totalise approximately 1,363,800, ft decrease of 22,531 on the previous week:   on the seme date the number working short time and drawing benefit for intervals of unemployment was 53,000 ue compiled with 52,741 on February 5th.The Unemployed Council of Action decided that the marchers should return to their homes on S&apos;etru-..ry 20th but tfiany of them are still in London st; they hope to have their railway fares paid by the Guurdians:   sh- leaders are disconsolate but Ht-nnington has attempted to save the situation by talking of another march after the national conference in April.Botuils are given of sPrae of the attempts mads by the CoEiiauniot Party to permeate the trade unions:   extremists are active in connection with the schemes for trade union amalgamation on the b&amp;sis of one union for one industry.The sales of extremist literature are increasing.The Young Cbfunuiiiss League is drawing up a series of Iscfieta for its &quot;imti-militarist&quot; ompstign.
THE C0HMUHIS3SThe National Organising Bureau has sent amemorandum on procedure to District Party Committees fromwhich the following extracts are takeni-&quot;Structure of a District Party Committee is as follows:&quot;Distriot Party Committee,&quot;Organising Bureau Political BureauFinancial Dept. Temporary: OrganisingIndustrial Dept^Distribution DepartmentCommittee:Prop. Dept.Registration Department:Electoral Dept:   Training Dept.Each of the above departments, and such others as it may be necessary to establish, is in charge of a member of the District party Committee.&quot;Each Department works through a committee of members drawn from the District whose work it is to apply Party Policy in the special sphere of activities coming within its scope.&quot;For instance:   The Industrial Department knows the party policy.   This is conveyed hy the Executive to the District Party Committee which discusses its particular Distriot application, and then it is conveyed to the Industrial Department through the Distriot Party Committee member who is its head. The Industrial Department then, having its policy in front of it, has to apply it through the trade union nuclei, trades council fractions etc., in such a way as to make the policy effective in the District.&quot;Each Departmental Committee meets as often as its work makes it necessary to meet.   This should seldom be leas than once each woek...&quot;Each Bureau meets separately at least once each week and receives reports from the Heads of the Departments under its control.   Those reports should be detailed reports so that matters arising therefrom, both political end organisational, can receive full consideration.   The Bureau considers the reports of its various Departments, sanctions proposals which do not involve matters of principle, and presents its own report,, covering the essential points of the work of its Departments, to the full District Party Committee asking for sanction of any matters of principle...&quot;A/
A second memorandum deals with the registration ofmembers and safe keeping of records and contains thefollowing passages:&quot;In fairness to the members who have supplied the information the District Party Committee has a very strict obligation to take every precaution against tlie particulars getting into wrong hands... The place of storing should only he known to those immediately connected with the work...   The General membership must on no account have access to the Register, not even the Local party Committees:   this information is for the uss of the Distriot Party Committee only...&quot;The cards that are most urgently required for use are those for Trades Union Branch Nuclei, Trades Councils, and Local labour Parties.   In eaoh case.the particulars must be copied from the membership cards (which we now send you)...&quot;Party Register.   A-s soon as conveniently possible the particulars contained on the oards we are sending you should be copied on to the larger blank cards, of which we also enclose a supply...&quot;When completed this will form a duplicate set of cards:   each set must be kept in an entirely different place, but both sets regularly brought up to date. The usefulness of this measure is worth the trouble involved.&quot;The Party Training Committee has issued lessons 4 and 5 of the elementary syllabus:   the whole document is misleading and mischievous&apos;, two passages in Section &quot;A&quot; of the 4th lesson bear quotation:&quot;Communist Administration.&quot;Communist administrators will not be judges, Jurors, policemen, Lawyers, hangmen, etc     The state (as an organ of class rule - see lesson 3) will cease to exist.   Communist Administrators will include the oivil engineer, the electrical engineer, the statistician, the costing clerk, tho book-keeper, etc. These, as comrades and equals of all other workers, will administer the policies determined by the community.&quot;Dictatorship of the Proletariat.&quot;The transition from capitalism to communism will not, as the Russian Revolution has proved, be accomplished in a day, or without a struggle.&quot;During the difficult transition period, a Dictatorship will be needed as in previous revolutionarycrises/
crises, e.g. the protectorate of Oliver Cromwell.   The absense of any such dictatorship prevented the Paris Commune from destroying the old state Power or fostering the psychology necessary for its own triumph.1The new dictatorship must he a class dictatorship and can only he realised through the workers1 own &apos; organisations, the Workers&apos; Councils or Soviets.&quot;The task of the Party Is to prepare for the coming struggle and for the problems of the Dictatorship.The question of comnunists who are members of the british legion was raised at the recent London meeting of the PartyCouncil and it was laid down that:&quot;The Communist Party works for the penetration of all organisations affecting the Labour movement, for the advancement of Communist principles and the Communist Party.&quot;The importance of this is, that when, as in the caso of at. Helens, a number of Party members belong to a tody like the British Legion, they should act as a fraction in tha closest consultation with the District &apos; Party Committee.&quot;&quot;The International Press Correspondence&quot; is to he enlarged as from March 1st, 1923, to a sixteen page weekly edition which will be sent to subscribers in addition to the usual communist recipients.Specimens of a new publication in Frenoh entitled &quot;La Russia des Soviets illustrqe&quot; have just been sent into this country from Berlin.   This paper is propaganda calculated to assist the International Workers&apos; Belief Committee.As this is &quot;Propaganda week&quot; &quot;Che Workers&apos; Weekly&quot; hasan extra page:    the note of agitation against almost everyaspect of the existing order is maintained.    According to additional reports received the paper sold well lastweek: thefollowing was the return of the Glasgow District Committee:Ferguson              70 quires McGill                 66 Airdrie                 4 Coatbridge           10 Zilmarnock             7 Motherwell           20 Paisley                12^-Renfrew                 1-1 Vale of leven       &amp;f Wishaw                  1 Greenock (Phoenixl7 Pub,)       -217-i- quiresThe/
lit aThe following is an illustration of the efforts madeto push the paper in a small Scottish group:-&quot;On receipt of information that the &quot;Communist&quot; was changing to &quot;Workers1 Weekly&quot; and was to he one penny, we immediately decided to order 200 copies. Previously we had only been selling 50 copies of the &quot;Communist&quot;.     A comrade and myself sold 45 copies at unemployed concert, of the first issue in order to give the neff&apos;paper a boost.   All comrades are on the job and are selling from 1 to 6 copies each.   We have ordered 30 quire (720) for propaganda week.   we believe however, our average will soon reach 500 and then we will strive to reach 1,000.   All group leaders are compiling lists of names and addresses of permanent readers., These will he entered in a hook and the whole district will be divided into Wards and streets.   Next week is -going to be a big push week with Banners and posters and lorry parade.     le intend creating a sensation and give the paper a great advert.&quot;The Chief Constable of Manchester informs me that literature sold during the month in his area amounted to 42 dozen &quot;Communists&quot;, 23 dozen &quot;Workers&quot;, 12 dozen &quot;All Powers&quot;, 1 dozen &quot;Communist Internationals&quot;, 1 dozen &quot;Communist Reviews&quot; und 1 dozen &quot;Labour Monthly&quot;.During the week the All Russian Co-operative Society has had on sale at soviet House programmes for a carnival on behalf of the London District party Committee of the Co-smunist Party:   a correspondent purchasing one of these programmes was informed that he could have an unlimited number but that the sale must be regarded as unauthorised:   it was also stated that many members of the All Russian Co-operative Society Suaff proposed to attend the carnival.,J. T. Walton Nowbold, 1,1..P., since his return from Russiahas addressed at least three meetings in the Metropolitan area:speaking at Poplar Town Hull on february 18th he said:-that the message he brought from the Red Army to the British Workers was T&apos;v*e are ready to help you when you want us&apos;*     He had been privileged to visit the training centres of the Red Army, and he was glad to eay they were as well equipped as any other Army in the world.   They had their tanks, artillery, aircraft, armoured cars, and poison-gas laboratories, as well as the most perfect anti-gas apparatus.   They had notbeen/
5 -17been prepared for his visit, as he accompanied, the Government *s Inspectors.   The troops were well disciplined and their accoutrement ready for use. Their bayonets wore long and shiny, long enough to go right through our friend Winston Churchill - if hs got in the way;   but he did noli think he would, as it was more likely he would follow up his old tradition and get someone else to do that work for him...&quot;REVOLUTIONARY PROPAGANDA IN THE? TRADE UNION MOVEMENT.The Communist Party has begun the issue of a fortnightly bulletin to District Party Committees &quot;on matters of importance in connection with the party&apos;s work in the trade unions:   it will be the work of the industrial organisers to see that the recommendations made in the bulletin are pushed by communist nuclei at trade union branch meetings.The first number of this bulletin covers:Resolutions for the Trade union Congress. Trade Union Elections. Boilermakers&apos; Revision of Rules.Under the second heading a list of communists nominated ascandidatesparliamentary/and delegates to national congresses ie given:&quot;Amalgamated Engineering UnionParliamentary candidates - Comrades Gallaoher,Hannington, Dickson, Lawrence, Hinchelwood, Murphy.Union of Post Office WorkersExecutive Council 19 members )   G-.E* Albon, B..R. Don*ll Trades Union Congress 6   &quot;     )   U.0- Osborna Labour party Conference 6&quot;     )   W* Greenhaugh)   J.M. Johnstone.Party Members already nominatedWoodworkers societyTrades Union Congress (District Ballot)London District     -     Comrade E. BlackwellGlasgow     &quot; - &quot;      J. Strain.Parliiaentary Candidates National Ballot - 6 vacancies. J. Strain, Colin Wright,W. King, E. Blackwell,J. Poster.Boilermakers/
Boilermakers SocietyTrades Union. Congress and Labour Party Conference -Comrade Pollitt &quot;      Henry-Parliamentary Candidate - Comrade Cusker.Amalgamated Engineering UnionFinal Appeal Court (District Ballot)London Southern Division - Comrade P. Gl&amp;dlng. London Northern Division - Comrade      Redman,British Iron, Steel and Kindred Trades AssociationEreoutive Committee - Comrade R. Puree 11,Altogether Society (Builders&apos; Labourers^Assistant General Secretary - Comrade Keeley.&quot;One of the proposed amendments to the rules of theTrade Union Congress would, if adopted, enable the general council of that body to call a national general strike if thecircumstances of a dispute involving any particular union&quot;warrant such action&quot;.   In this connection interest attaches to a paragraph in the pamphlet &quot;How a Trade Una. on BranchNucleus Works&quot; issued by the Communist party of Great Britain&quot;The extension of strikes is a most important task of all Nuclei in Trade Unions.   In the case of a seotional dispute involving a single Union, the branch Nuclei inside other Unions concerned must work to secure sympathetic action.   Their policy must always be to make every struggle a genejral straggle and if possible a national one, and to push the Union officials as much towards a revolutionary situation as possible.   The Union Nuclei must fully utilise other Party machinery during every attempt to extend a local or sectional struggle...   They must work through the Trades Council or local labour ptrty fraction to secure publicity for the cause of the strikers, and representations in favour of United Working Class Action to other Unions concerned.   The workshop Nuclei in those plants which are affected must be called upon to work for solidarity, and to take as full a share as possible in picketing, workgate meetings, etc.&quot;There is increasing evidence that communists areconcentrating upon propaganda inside the trade union movement, particularly in regard to the conferences being held/
held to forward the project of one union for one industry.The Chief Constable informs me that at Manchester onFebruary 6th delegates from 29 different unions,representing over 500,000 workers in the engineering industry, adopted the following resolutions:&quot;(1)   That in the opinion of the delegates, efforts should be made to arrange terms of amalgamation of workers in the Metal Trades Industry.(2)   That a Committee be appointed to investigate the possibilities of amalgamation and report to a further Conference.(3)   That each Executive Committee appoint one representative to the Committee of Investigation(*)   Thai: the Genoral Council be empowered toappoint to the Committee any representatives of any union representing the Metal Workers&apos; Industry desiring to take part in the work.&quot;At Bradford on February 7th a similar meeting of delegates from Textile Trade Unions, other than cotton in Yorkshire, was attended by 32 delegates representing 17 unions and approximately 400,000 members.     Eesolution3 identical with those adopted at Manchester apart from the name of the industry concerned were passed:      the Chairman at each conference was J.B. Williams and the speakers at Manchester included Robert Smillie, A.B. Scales, Julia varley and George Hicks.S.0. Davies&apos; report le this conference was as follows:-&quot;The British Communist B^rty and the R.I.I.U. Minority Movement are exerting themselves to the utmost, both among the leaders and the &apos;Rank and File1 to welcome this move towards amalgamation.   It can be safely asserted that this first step on the part of the Metal Trades is due more to the activities of the revolutionary minority than to any other body. The same activities are in progress in the other industries.&quot;There is a recrudescence of activity among Trades and labour Ccuncils which may be due in part also to communist propaganda/
propaganda:   for instance, the Chief conaiable of WestRiding informs me that on February 7th the S; en ValleyCouncil passed the following resolution:-&quot;That this meeting of the Spen V&apos;.lley Trades and Labour Council calls upon the General council of the Trades Union Congress, to take the necessary steps,, immediately to enable the whole Trade Union Movement to offer united resistance to any worsening of the conditions of labour either through extension of hours, or further reduction in wages.   We demand that the General Council bring the whole movement in behind the building workers.   Remember the mouldersi   Remember the minersi     Remember the engineers.     and let our policy be all in behind the building workers.&quot;Alexander Gossip, the general secretary of the nationalAmalgamated 2*uraishing Traces&apos; Association has sent to the berlin Bureau of the Red International of Lebour unions &quot;as requested&quot; s copy of the monthly report of his union andhas promised to send it regularly.   Ho lu-s also addressed a long letter to the officials and members of the RussianWood Workers in which he states that he had &quot;Ho sympathy with those so-called Internationalists who talk aboutthe necessity of defending their own country but are againstgoing to War with other countries for the purpose of somesupposed gain.&quot;    Gossip-concludes his letter:&quot;We ought to train our young people and children in such a way that when they grow up, they will no more think of doing the dirty work of the Capitalists, no matter in what flowery language they may put their case, than they would think of cutting off their own nose.&quot;Per over 26 years I have used some of my spare time ever:/ week in trying to instil those ideas into the minds of the young people, with the result that most of them who attended, my classes from their boyhood days, absolutely refused to go as Soldiers against the Germans and went to prison instead, during the great onslaught from 1914 to 1918.&quot;I believe in preaching the same doctrine In the Tr*..de Unions, and am hopeful that in time the working class will reocgnise who is the real enemy.   Hurrah for the overthrow of the Capitalist System and with Best of Witness and Fraternal Greetings.&quot;THE/
gjg YOUM CQMUHIST LEAGUEThe Young Communist League is having various leaflets printed in oonnectlon with its anti-militarist campaign:   the drafts for three of these have come into my possession and contain the following passages:-(1) &quot;Anti-Militarist Campaign (Feb. - May)&quot;Mr. Bon-vr Law says:&quot;We do not want war (?)- not one of us;   hut if war is inevitable, it will have to take place.What does this mean?&quot;That we are on the eve of another outbreak of war that will make the last look like a skirmish.Why?&quot;Because Lord Curzon1a Masters want the oil at Mosul and monsieur poincare&apos; s Bosses want the coking-coal of the Ruhr.Young.Uaemp1oyed workers:&quot;&quot;They will want you to fight their dirty battles.&quot;They want to fling you into another bloody slaughter a thousand tiraes worse than the last.Young Employed Workers:&quot;They will want you too to leave your jobs and go to the Hear East and. the ittiiaelaad to slaughter the young workers of other lands.Soldiers, Sailors and Airmen:&quot;You will be the first to be sacrificed to the gold lust of the imperialists!.Young Workers, Soldiers and Sailors on whose side will you be?The Workers orThe BosBes.Will you fight for them   or    With us.&quot;Think of the results of the last war.&quot;We are fighting for. the Communist International. The International working Class, and no More Capitalist Wars.E.C. of the Y.C.L. of G,B.&quot;&quot;The/
- 10 -175The Young Ooifsaunlst League appeals to you on behalf of ell young workers toSupport the demands of the Communist partyfor aUNTIED FRONTforunited working class action against War. PEEP ARB PGR A GENERAL STRIKE &quot;AGAINST A HEY/ WAR. Demand&quot;That the General Council takes action&quot;-for j The scrapping of the Versailles Treaty.   The withdrawal of-all armies of occupation.   The convening of a World Congress-of all states to include fiovxet Russia and the peoples of the East to lay the foundations for World peace and Disarmament.   The immediate .summoning of a Congress of all working class organisations, which shall organise the action to be taken to meet the threat of a new imperialist war. &quot;v     ;-.THE YOUNG WORKERS DO HOT WISH TO BE FLUNG&apos; INTO ANOTHER HOLOCAUST.     WILL YOU ALLOW THEM TO BE?S.C of Y.C.L. Of G.B.&quot;&quot;To All Unalloyed Young Workers...Thoy tell you&quot;On Great Big Potters, to:&quot;Join the Royal Air Force and processes the World for Nothing.&quot;Good Food&quot;.&quot;Good Clothes, etc., etc.^If you want&quot;To know how good life in the Army and Navy is,, read the 1Young Communist&apos; which publishes Soldier&apos;e and Sailor&apos;8 letters,    (Hot Officers) exposing the bullying and misery of life, in the Capitalists Aray, Navy and Royal Air Force.&quot;To shoot down your own class comrades and brothers.&apos; of other lanis, then join us, and be drowned in your own blood.&quot;To take a stand for all the workers, join the Natl-nal Unemployed Workers&apos; Committee Movement and fight for:;&amp;iW;6rk; or Pull Maintenance* &quot;If/
*Make them provide you with it outaide.&quot;Arrangements have been completed for holding a London District Congress of tho Young Communist League at 36, Lamfs Conduit Street on February 25th for tho purpose of inaugurating the new scheme of organisation and of forming a London District League Committee:   delegates are not to be bound by a system of mandates which the Executive considers obsolete but are to be given full power and freedom to vote as they think best.m unemployed on February 17th some 600 unemployed marched toTrafalgar Square in two batches:   others arrived subsequentlyand, at one period, the audience, including casual people,numbered 2,000.   W. Strakor took the chair;   the otherspeakers were Cook, Hannington, Murphy (Dundee) and theBc:v. T.E. Piokering.     The following resolution was passed:&quot;That this demonstration of employed and unemployed workers assembled in Trafalgar Syoare on February 17th pledges itself to assist in every way possible the continuation of the great national Unemployed march after the national conference has been held until the marchers have succeeded in compelling the Prime Minister to hear the case presented on behalf of the Unamployed Of Great Britain by their duly elected representatives.&quot;A second resolution demanding the release of William Hunter, concerning whose trial several misstatements were made, was also adopted.     About  2 was thrown on the plinth.Hanuington said:-&quot;Uo hiiVe agreed that the marchers shall drop out of this line, the fighting line of London, shall be taken back to the localities from which they come, shall prepare to send their delegates to the National Conference to be held in Coventry the first week in April...   After the national Conference we are going to prepare for the greatest advance of all.   That advance wili begin with the good weather, and there are quite a good deal of things that grow in? the fields thatse rve/&quot;If they can provide you with full maintenance inside the loyal Air ForcefflEH
serve a&apos;useful purpose, for feeding not only horses hut men as well, and the weather will he better, the men will be able to take to the roads much easier and if necessary when they got into loudon, if the local authorjties will not put them up, then at any rate it will be summer time -.nd they can stop on the streets.   But they will not let them step on the streets, there is a great danger of private property being damaged if they do, end when private property is in danger, then by God, you can move heaven and earth rather than have that property damaged by these low common hunger marchers or anybody else.   I say to you be prepared for the greatest of activities that has ever been organised, we are going to be determined to break down the callousness, the brutality of this individual known as Bonar Law.   We shall stop at nothing, and we shell employ every possible method that we can in order to drive home our cause and to force an interview with Bonar Law,.   We are ready and capable of carrying on tho fight, it has been a long drawn out fight, but it is likely to bo a longer drav/n out fight before we have finished.&apos;.&apos;&apos;The Council of Action decided that the marchers should leave London on February 20th but only Stangroom and seven others actually left, for Yarmouth, on that date.     112 men from the north, who aro in the poplar Workhouse, are demanding their fares home as are the rnon at Carrington House Loptford Broadway:   uo far, however, the Guardians show no disposition to pey the fares.One of the marchers has given the following accountof his experiences on arrival in London last week:-&quot;We arrived in London on Tuesday, had a meeting in Hyde Par.,, and then went to our living places.   On the way we were told that wc were to have a good dinner. When we arrived wo found HO food NO beds and we rare in a COHDEMHEiL house.   Wo sent a deputation to 3, Quean&apos;s Square, l\\t all they found us was- a place till Monday, NO beds and only one blanket between two chaps. We got tickets from the Guardians at lo/- a man, but we have nowhere to cook any food.   We cannot get cigarettes or tobacco and the boys wish me to ask you to send us some monoy for Cigss and to .   One or two have spoken about going home but I don&apos;t think they will.&quot;On February 16th hunnington, Straker, McGlnley, stangroomencs Pickering visited the House of Commons where they spoke to/
to lansbury and Saklatvala:   Pickering was heard to ask lansbury if he would help the unemployed to oome to the House in a body but the latter replied that he could not do this as it would injure his position and as he would be held responsible if any disturbance took place,The Chief Constable of Coventry informs me that the officials of the National Unemployed Workers&apos; Coraaittee Movement have issued a circular, in which it is suggested that the week of agitation arranged by the Scottish Division to be held from Fabruary 26th to March 3rd inclusive be extended throughout the country^   It its proposed that the following resolution shall be put to as many meetings as possible and forwarded to the prime Hinisxux, the Minister of labour, the Executive of the Labour Party, the General Coui.cil of the Tr-v.ee Union Congress and the ,fDcily Herald&quot;:&quot;That this..............Branch of the.............in meeting assembled, demands that immediate steps be taken by the Government to entirely aboilok the vGep! periods which are at present operating under the Unemployment Insurance Acts.   Further, it v:;ews with disgust the fact, that whilst responsible Ministers of the Crown are stating that everything that is possible is being done for the unemployed, they -. the unemployed -are being subjected to one of the most vicious regulations that hare yet been devised. tx5sgi.Bg with it as it does, untold and unnecessary suffering to the tens of thousands that are affected by it.   We demand that this matter shell receive immediate attention.&quot;The Chief Constable of Liverpool informs me that therehas been a good deal of dissension among the localunemployed since the return of the marchers:   variousmeetings have been held at which the language was remarkablyvituperative and on January 26th a motion expelling allcommunists from the unemployed organisation was accepted.REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES 111 GREAT BRITAIN.Hopes of an early Irish peace arising out of theDeasey/
Doasep incident and the consequent offer of an -amnesty hy the Free ytate Government slumped very badly during the week-end and great disappointment is expressed in Irifih circles.There is little or no sign of a revival of Irish life in Lovioon such as might lead to a uniting of the moderate sections for the purpose of combatting the persistent propaganda of the Extremists.    Petty squabbles among the loaders and lack of interest on the part   of the rank and file continue.Tho Extremists are growing bolder and claim to have greatly increased their following, particularly in theNorth:   nevertheless they are not without their troubles:Art 0&apos;Brien has found it neoossary t$ send a. confidentialcircular to all Brunoh secretaries appealing for their help to &quot;combat the campaign of calumny&quot; being launches againstScan McGrath, the General secretary, who has been accused of disloyalty.     0&apos;Brien talks of &quot;peoret propaganda andvicious innuendo&quot; b;; malicious persons, and adds that&quot;many of our present troubles are duo to their evil work&quot;:he ssks for      lp to give the work of tho League the impetus which it sorely needs at the moment.&quot;    Fin;.ncialmatters also aro troubling him for, in the same confidentialcircular, he says:&quot;It is essential, at the present critical moment in tho history of oxir country, that we of the race abroad should help the cause unstintedly in the most effective manner at our disposal-that is, financially. Communications from home are constantly reaching me, enquiring why our people in England and w*-les are not doing more ink this respect.&quot;&quot;It if-: obvious to all that no cause can prosper without adequate finanoial support.   Yfit, the contributions, etc. coming in from the various branches are not even sufficient to keep the machinery of our organisations going, and, of course, leaves no margin whatever for any financial assistance to begiven/
- 15 - .given to the cause at home.&quot;Further trouble has arisen over the action of the Irish national Assurance Company (Head Office, Dublin) in sending out a warning to its officials in this country that they must not, on any account, identify themselves with any of the Irish political organisations under pain of dismissal.   Art 0TBrlen has found it necessary to send an official protest on behalf of the Irish Self-Determination League.    Many of the Irish Republican Army officials are prominent Republicans, one of them, Zing (of Newcastle) is a commandant of the local Irish Republican Arr,y.Art 0&apos;Brion has been telling his friends that President Cosgrave was over here to make arrangements for his (0&apos;BrienTs) deportation.   Ho also fears that some action with regard to Irish Republican Funds in /msrican is contemplated.On the night.of February I6th-17th the rifle store of the Basex Territorial Association at Stratford was broken into and six short Unfiold Rifles, with spare parts,, were stolen:   this would seem to be the work of Irish Republican Agents, although no trace of the thieves has been as yet obtained.The Countess Markievicz left Glasgow on February 14th and is now in London:   she addressed a meeting of the Central Brecon of the Irish so if-Determination League, at the Minerva Cafe, Holborn, on the 20th:   Art 0&apos;Brien is endeavouring  to arrange a series of public meetings at which she is to be the principal speaker.

</content>
</cab>
