<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 299-300</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Ibis document is the property of His Britannic Majeaty^a (kreernnant).C B E I. .W0.X29(2g)0 A BSaf egvu^rdlng of Industriea Aot. Application to Franca^ Belgium and. Italy.Hote by the First Lord ofi tba Adalrslty^The proposal of the President of the. Board of Trade (C.P.126(23))     not to apply Part II of the safeguarding of Industries Act to France, Belgium or Italy/ .....,1raises issues of great importance.   It is just if had^by:, (a) the fear of French retaliation, (b) the necessity of denouncing the Italian and Belgian commercial treaties if the Act is to be applied to these countries, and (c) the fact that Part II of the Act ceases to be operative in August 1924,The last named is the dominant consideration, and our whole policy must depend upon what decision we come to now on this point.   If part II is really to be allowed to expire next year and ia not to be succeeded by provisions at least equally effective, then there might be a good deal to be said for avoiding trouble in connexion with a moribund policy.   But I do not believe it is possible to let that happen, as we have precluded ourselves from the only effective alternative, viz: an avowedly protective tariff.   The exchange situation is not going to be normal by next year and the industries now helped by the Act cannot be simply thrown over.   We shall have to renew, and reinforce the Act.If so, then the sooner we denounce the Belgian and Italian treaties in order to free our hands for the general application of the Act the better,   I cannot
conceive either these countries or France &quot;retaliating&quot; against as, for, after all, they already treat our trade as drastically as it suits them.   As a matter of fact the fall of the franc already, in itself, constitutes a more drastic &quot;retaliation&quot; in advance than any other measure they are likely to take.   Two years ago parliament might still have been affected hy a certain amount of misguided sentiment about special consideration for our Allies, hut I trust we are sufficiently cared of that.I see no reason why the Nottingham Lacs Trade should he killed hy the unfair competition of the depreciated franc, itself a result of a policy on the part of Franco which is diminishing our chances of reparations, and injuring our European trade,, and I would strongly urge that the president of the Board of Trade should hold the inquiry demanded hy Nottingham and should,, at the same time, denounce any treaties which may inter-fere with the effective carrying out of an Act which is more essential than ever in view ox the present state of employment 0(intd.)   I.S.A.Admiralty, S.W.I.S7th February 1323.

</content>
</cab>
