<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 407-416</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, jPrinted for the Cabinet.  March 1923.-----------------------------secret.CP. 137 (23). CABINET.SPECIAL REPORT ON   UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 86.     Period ended February 23, 1923.SUMMARY OF UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION.The number of persons registered at the Employment Exchanges as wholly unemployed at the 19th February was 1,340,260, a decrease of 23,511 on the previous, week.POSITION IN CHIEF INDUSTRIES.COAL-MINING.The improvement in the Forest of Dean continues, but depression still exists in the Somerset coalfields. Increased activity is reported from South Yorkshire and Durham. In the Lancashire centres the industry continues to maintain good employment. The situation in Scotland is satisfactory, and prospects are reported to be good. The satisfactory position in the Midlands has been maintained, and in. Wales, apart from some local stoppages, employment has remained steady.IRON AND STEEL.An improvement has been recorded in the Midlands. In Yorkshire, Lancashire and the North of England activity has been maintained, but the output has been hampered at some centres by the shortage and increased cost of coke. Employment has improved in Scotland. In North Wales there has been a considerable improve-ment, but the situation in South Wales is unsatisfactory.SHIPBUILDING AND SHIP-REPAIRING.Some activity has occurred at Avonmouth among ship-repairers, but the outlook at Portsmouth and Southampton is not promising. On the Tyne and Tees the improvement in constructional work has been maintained, but employment among ship-repairers is intermittent. The situation on the Mersey continues to show a very slight improvement. In spite of occasional reconditioning and repair work on the Clyde, the industry as a whole in that sector remains unsettled, with no indication of any immediate improvement. There is little activity at Holyhead, but. in South Wales some improvement is evident.ENGINEERING.While employment in this industry generally remains below normal, there is evidence of gradual progress at most centres.TEXTILES.Cotton. The slow improvement in Lancashire has continued, but trade is very small and employment remains below normal. There has been little change in Yorkshire and the outlook is not encouraging.Hosiery, Woollen and Worsted. The hosiery trade in the Midlands is active and prospects are promising. In Yorkshire, however, trade has not improved. The position in Scotland is only fair.
Silk. Trade is quiet in the Midlands, and the anticipated improvement has not materialised.Lace. The industry in the Midlands is still very depressed. Trade is also bad in Somerset.Jute. The improvement previously reported continues, and prospects are good. BUILDING.There are indications in most quarters of a slight improvement, but further improvement depends very largely upon a satisfactory settlement of the negotiations between employers and operatives on the question of wages and hours.BOOT AND SHOE.The depression in the South-Western Counties continues. In the Midlands, as a whole, employment is below the normal level, although at Leicester and Stafford unemployment is not so heavy. Unemployment and short-time working, however, are prevalent at Kettering and Wellingborough. At Northampton, a further slight improvement is reported. In Scotland trade is slack and prospects are uncertain. The improvement at Norwich continues.CLOTHING.At most centres in the London and Home Counties orders have been received for women workers in the wholesale tailoring trade. Some improvement has also been reported at certain centres in the South-Western Counties.POTTERY AND GLASS.The pottery trade, as previously reported, is not likely to become very active until the spring. In the glass and glass-bottle industries trade generally is bad, and the improvement anticipated some time ago has not yet been realised.TINPLATE.The position has remained unchanged since the last report. TRANSPORT.There has been a little more employment at the docks on the north-east coast. The situation at Liverpool is fairly satisfactory, and a continued improvement is anticipated. At Avonmouth and Bridgwater employment has improved. Trade at Southampton is slack owing to seasonal depression. At the London Docks work is quiet, but in Wales the general cargo trade is brisk.c. a. Montague jbaelow,Ministry of Labour.
3313I.-DETAILED UNEMPLOYMENT FIGURES.1. General Percentage of Unemployment.[Note. Down to November 1920 tho only percentages of unemployment available are those derived from Trade Union returns covering- roughly 1.000,000 workers. From November 1920 percentagesjderived from the Unemployment Insurance Scheme, covering 11,000,000 to 12,000,000 workers, are also available.] .At the end ef-		Trade Union	Unemployment!		Percentage.	Insurance Percentage.January	1921	6-9	8-0February	11 :	8-5	95March	n         -          *	100	111April	&apos;&quot;                    - &apos;&quot;	176	.   14-7May	-   &quot;	22-2	17-4June		23 1	17-9July-		16-7	14-8August		16-3	130September	- &apos;**                              *	14-8	12-2October	11.                  *	15-6	12-8November	1)                          *	159	15-5December		16-5	15-9January	1922	16-8	15-9February		16-3	151March		16-3	143April		170	14-2May	ii. -             -:&quot;&apos;*	;.           164	13-3June	a.;     .        .. -*	15-7	12-5July	&apos;&apos;-	14-6	121August	.&apos; 11                          &apos;	14-4	11-9September	J)	14-6	120October	li                      .vi*	14-1	120November	-   &apos;1                      -    &apos;	14-2	12-4December	ii       . /&apos;/!    - *	14-0	12-2January	1923	13-7	127The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent. The average for the ten years prior to the war, according to Trade Union figures, was 4-7 per cent. It was as high as 78 per cent in 1908 and 77 per cent in 1909.[9597]
2. Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain.-	1920.	1921.		1922.				Dec. 3.	July 1. 1	Oct. 7.	Jan. 10.	April 3.	July 3.	Sept. 4.Men ..&apos;: Boys Women Girls ..     .   .. Totals  ..	371,617 20,627 117,012 23,212	1,469,170 77,884 429,846 63,378	1,003,688 51,702 207,726 37.269	1,404,175 63,667 311,397 44,504	1,292,914 53,064 256,090 38,726	1,161,069 41,809 157,286 29,799	1,089,419 47,663 164,579 36,351	532,468	2,040,278	1,299,985	1,823,733	1,640,794	1,389,963	1,328,012-	1922.			1923. HhhRBHHKBhrI				/ Oct. 2.	Nov. 6.	Deo. 4.	Jan. 1.,	Feb. 5.	Feb. 12.	Feb. 19.Men Boys Women Girls Totals ..	1,092,670 46,540 154,434 36,139	1,116,546 45,731 170,402 34,095	1,121,353 44,405 189,935 34,201	. . .           &apos; - j &apos;:-r&apos;f; 1,165,057 1   1,085,669 47,584 &apos;      50,758 234,955 i    207,720 38.282 i      42,184		1,070,184 49,104 203,612 40,871	1,051,569 47,242 202,213 39,236	1,328,783	1,366,774	1,389,894	1,485,878 ;   1,386,331		1,363,771	1,340,260a. Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges in Greater London Area.1923.	Jan. 29.	Feb. 5.	Feb. 12.	Feb. 19..Men    .. Boys   .. Women . Girls   .. Totals	174.670 11,469 38,434 9,342	173,679 11,311 38,746 8,805	171,819 10,802 38,358 8,306	170,376 10,103 38,130 7,664	233,915	232,641	229,285	. 226,273II.-SUMMARY OF ACTION TAKEN.[From Autumn 1920 onwards.] Cabinet Unemployment Committee.The prospect of a severe trade depression first became evident in the early autumn of 1920. On the 13th August, 1920, the then Cabinet appointed a Cabinet Unemployment Committee to consider the whole question and devise means foi relieving unemployment. This Committee continued to function till October 1922. The present Government appointed a 1 Cabinet Unemployment Committee on the 1st November, 1922.(A.) Unemployment Insurance.An Unemployment Insurance Act of general scope came into operation on the 8th November, 1920. The Act applied compulsory insurance against unemployment to 12,000,000 persons as compared with 4,000,000 previously. Subsequent amending Acts modified the conditions as regards rates of benefit, extended the periods of benefit and increased the contributions. As from November 1921 the Unemployed Workers&apos; Dependants&apos; (Temporary Provision) Act, 1921, made temporary provision for grants in respect of wives, dependent husbands and children, and imposed a special levy to provide for these grants. The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1922, which operates as from the 6th April, 1922, amalgamates the dependants&apos; grants with Unemployment Benefit, and the special levy with the Unemployment Insurance
contributions, and extends until June 1923 the special periods during which &quot; uncovenanted &quot; benefit may be drawn. The authority to borrow money from the Treasury is increased to  30,000,000.Table showing amount paid out in Unemployment Benefit (including Benefit in respect of Dependants), and the Contributions during the period from the 8th ,  November, 1920, to the 17th February, 1923.1. Benefit paid       ... ... ....       ...      114,342,0002. Appropriation for administration (2 years) ...        ...        8,636,000*3. Miscellaneous payments, refunds, &amp;c. ...        1,037,000124,015,000(Up to April 1922, this is on the basis of 10 per cent, chargeable on the annual revenue under Section 12 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920; from April 1922, the maximum charge was increased to 12-^- per cent, by the Act of April 1922, and the actual charge representing the total cost of administration has -s been 11 per cent.).4. Contributions  EmployersEmployed ... &apos;StateState (for ex-Service men)5. Old fund at November 1920   . 6. Loans from Treasury 7. Interest (net) +S. Deposits, &amp;c. balance 32,297,000 29,345,000 20,335,000 2,436,000 -       84,413,00022,210,000 16,670,000279,000443,000 ---       39,602,000124,015,000* Mainly refunds to contributors reaching the age of 60, and refunds of contributions paid by persons - subsequently excluded from insurance or otherwise found not to be insnrable.t Mainly sums deposited by employers to cover arrangements for stamping unemployment books quarterly (or at other extended intervals) instead of weekly.(B.) Emergency Works and other Measures.A full statement of the measures taken in the autumn of 19&apos;20 and of the later measures from, autumn 1921 onwards has been set out in previous issues of this Report. At least 300,000 men have had employment on these schemes at various times, and at the present time over 140,000 men are employed, exclusive of the work provided for men in ancillary occupations and the effect of the Export Credits Scheme.(C.) Recent Extensions of Remedial Measures.Some of the measures comprised in (B) above are still, in operation, e.g., past  0 sanctions of grants by the Unemployed Grants Committee and the Ministry of Transport. The Export Credits Scheme continues, and schemes approved under the Trade Facilities Act are in progress.In June 1922. the Unemployment Grants Committee and the Ministry of Transport issued circular letters to Local Authorities inviting them to submit schemes for works of public utility, which, with assistance from State funds, might be undertaken for the relief of unemployment in their respective areas. Approved schemes are assisted by grants made on the same bases as heretofore. In the case of schemes assisted by the Unemployment Grants Committee, particulars of grants already sanctioned are set out below. . .   ,-In September 1922, the. Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries issued circular letters to County Councils (except the London County Council) and Drainage Authorities, inviting them to submit schemes of land drainage which, if approved, might be assisted on fundamentally the same conditions as those applicable in the [9597] b 3-mm
case of schemes assisted last year. All applications were to be received in the case of Drainage Authorities on or before December 1, 1922, and in the case of County Councils (Agricultural Committees) on or before December 16, 1922. County Councils were also circulated with regard to schemes for the supply of water to farms, the conditions of assistance from the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries remaining substantially the same as last winter, &apos;with the exception that the Ministry, instead of advancing the whole cost ot any scheme and recovering a proportion from the owners concerned, will make grants to cover part only of the total cost of each scheme. Further circulars, issued to County Councils and Drainage Authorities on the 5th and 6th December respectively, notified the extension of the date up to which applications might be received to the 13th January, 1923, and invited the submission of additional schemes. The time for receiving-applications was further extended provisionally to the 10th February, 1923. Particulars of grants sanctioned and of the number of men employed to date are shown below (see table 6).On the 30th November, 1922, the Minister of Labour, in the House of Commons, outlined the manner in which measures taken by the late Government would be continued and extended. The additional sums promised in extension of existing funds are set out below :  Unemployment Grants Committee (for grants on the basis of60 per cent, of Wages Bill) ... ... ... ...       600,000Land Drainage ... ...        ... ... ...        170,000     -*Afforestation....................        100,000Acceleration of Government contracts Office of Works    ... ...... 375,000General Post Office ...... 946,000-     1,321,000It was also then announced that guarantees under the Trade Facilities Act Scheme- would be made available up to  50,000,000 ( 25,000,000 extra); that the Export Credits Scheme would be extended if necessary; and that the Local Authorities concerned would be asked to co-operate in putting in hand the Manchester-Liverpool Road, which would involve an expenditure of about  3,000,000, half of it from the Road Fund.In December 1922, the Unemployment Grants Committee issued a further circular letter to Local Authorities inviting them to submit schemes suitable for assistance on the basis of 60 per cent, of the Wages Bill, i.e., works the cost of which is normally defrayed out of revenue and not by loan. The conditions under which grants may be sanctioned are substantially the same as those previously in force, except that in the. case of Rural Districts the Committee have discretion to allow, where clearly necessary, a modification of the conditions regarding the giving of preference to 75 per cent, ex-service men and the engagement of labour through the Employment Exchanges.On the 12th December, 1922, the Minister of Labour, in the House of Commons, further announced that, in addition to the acceleration of contracts by the Post Office and Office of Works, previously described, the Admiralty would accelerate miscellaneous works to a total of about  365,000; whilst the Home Office would put in hand certain accelerated building work, together with repairs to buildings, including Police Stations.On the 13th December, 1922, the Forestry Commission issued a press notice to the effect that. forestry grants were available for the relief of unemployment on the same general conditions as those applicable to grants made last winter. The sum of  100,000 referred to above is to be used partly for this purpose and partly for the purpose of. relief schemes in Crown Forests and for additional work in the Commission^ forests by the Trade Facilities and Loans Guarantee Act, 1922 (Session 2), enacted on the 15th December, 1922, formal sanction was given for the increase of the aggregate capital amount of loans the principal or interest of which may be guaranteed under the Trade Facilities Act, 1921, from  25,000,000 to  50,000,000.
SUMMARY SHOWING THE LABOUR EMPLOYED IN GREAT BRITAIN AT FEBRUARY 17, 1923, ON CERTAIN OF THE SCHEMES REFERRED TO ABOVE.Scheme.Number Employed in Greater London.Number Employed in Provinces.Total.1. Arterial roads2, Road maintenance   ..3. Housing (acceleration of lay-outs, &amp;c.)..4. Unemployment Grants Committee5. Local Authorities (without grants)6. Land drainage7. Water supply8. Forestry   ..9. Light railways10. Acceleration of Government contracts (G.P.O., Admiralty and H.M.O.W.) .. 11. Trade Facilities Act SchemesTotals      ......5,472*&quot;oo 4,685 1,451 Nil Nil Nil Nilll,703t22,147*460 38,745 9,469 6,706245 2,55364080,965t27,619 20,000 555 43,430 10,920 6,706 245 2,553 6466,000 21,971 (Deal)140,839* No separate figure for London and Provinces available.t Plus number (unknown) employed on Road maintenance, Acceleration of Government Contracts and Trade Facilities Act Schemes.[As reports for week ended the 17th February, 1923, have been received from only 476 Local Authorities out of 661 who were asked to supply information (in respect of items 3,4 and 5 above) it is probable that the relief schemes inaugurated by the Government and Local Authorities are finding employment for a number of men in excess of the figures given.]III.-PROGRESS REPORTS. 1. Loans and Overdrafts to Boards of Guardians.(England and Wales.) Totals to February 24, 1923.Nature of Assistance.	Number of Unions concerned.	Amount.Loans granted Overdrafts, current Sanctions under Section 3 of Local Authorities (Financial Provisions) Act 1921 Application for sanction to borrow under Section 3 Application for extension of loan period	1      100 2 Nil	  7,997,376 55,000 nil totals   ..	102	8,052,3762. Unemployment Grants Committee.- (A.)- -Grants Made on the Basis of 60 per cent, of the Wages Bill.(a.) Amount Originally Authorised Winter 1920-21.In the autumn of 1920, the Unemployment Grants Committee were -authorised to make grants on the basis of 60 per cent, of the Wages Bill of approved schemes, up to a total of  2,630,000 to Local or other Public Authorities in Great Britain and Ireland. Up to the 22nd February, 1923, grants had been sanctioned to a total of  2,807,532, but the full amount of the grant indicated will not be earned in every case. Work is still in progress on a few schemes originally approved for assistance on this basis.
Totals to February 22, 1923.Number of Local Authorities.		Number of Schemes.		Total (lost of Schemes.		Labour Cost of Schemes.		Total Amount of Grants Sanctioned.	Number of Men expected to be Em-ployed (for average of 7 months).	Making-Application.	Promised Grants.	Submitted.	Approved.	Submitted.	S	Submitted.	o1 s		(Jndei-Schemes Submitted.	Under Schemes Approved.298	198	840	507	1,993,635	  1,401,963	  1,129,477	  777,417	  36S.395	15,985	9.447(B.) Grants towards Loan Charges. (a.) Winter Programme 1921-22.Under Ministry of Health Circulars 245 and 251, of the 22nd September&apos;, 1921. and the 12th October, 1921, respectively, the Unemployment Grants Committee were authorised to make grants in approved cases to Local Authorities in Great Britain of 65 per cent, of the interest and sinking fund charges on Loans raised to meet expenditure on non-revenue producing schemes for half the term of the loan, subject to a maximum of 15 years and of 50 per cent, of the interest on Loans raised to meet expenditure on revenue-producing schemes for a period of 5 years.Up to the 22nd February, 1923, the number of Local Authorities assisted on these bases was 565. Approval was given to 1,728 schemes submitted by these Authorities indicating a total cost of  18,969.999, and the total-amount of loans sanctioned was  17,765,044.(b.) Winter Programme, 1922-23. Totals to February 22, 1923.Number of Local Authorities.		Number of Schemes.		Cost of Schemes.		Number of Men expected to be Employed (for average of 7. mouths).	Making-Application.	Promised Grants.	Submitted.	Approved.	Submitted.	Amount of Loan Approved for Grant.	Under Schemes Submitted.	Under Schemes Approved.540	392	2,280	1,471	  15,354,810 -	  8,452,344	85,700	43,7163. Ministry of Transport.The Ministry of Transport make grants up to 50 per cent, of the cost in the case of approved arterial road schemes undertaken by Local Authorities.The amount available for this year is about  5,300,000, and applications for schemes costing  12,000,000 have been received. The total grants indicated to Local Authorities up to date in respect of approved schemes amount approximately to  2,380,000.(b.) Extension Recently Authorised Winter 1922-23.
(a.) Export Credits.Date.	Credits given.							Advances.		Specific Guarantees.		General Credits.		Total Sanc-tioned	Sanctioned.	Taken up.	Sanctioned.	Taken up.	Sanctioned.	Taken up.	October 27,1921(j.e., beforenewscheiiie operated) February 19, 1923.. Increase	  &apos; -. 2,916,780 3,164,237	1,309,119 1.752,150	  730,465 16,361,708	  jj&quot;; 62,037 1,954,944	  5,704,613	  573,333	3,647,245 25,230,578	247,477	443,031 15,631,243		1,892,907	5,704,613	573,333	21,583,333(&amp;.) Guarantee up to 50 Millions for Capital Works. Totals to Date.Total guarantees given or sanctioned, November 20,1922  22,243,645 Number of men employed at December 1, 1922 ... 21,9715. Overseas Settlement.\a.) Free Passages for Ex-Service Men and Dependants.Up to the 3lst January, 1923, free passages, costing  2,354,016, had been granted in respect of 88,558 persons.(b.) Empire Settlement Act, 1922.Pursuant to this Act, a scheme was agreed with the Government of Australia on the 19th July, 1922, under which assisted passages may be granted to applicants selected by representatives of the Government of Australia. The number of cases assisted under this scheme up to the 3rd February, 1923, was 6,521.6. Miscellaneous Schemes.(A.) Agricultural and Kindred Schemes.(a.) Land Drainage.Schemes of this nature were operative during the winter, 1921-22.  650,000 were set aside for assisting drainage authorities with approved schemes&quot;, and at the termination of the programme 624. schemes had been approved, costing  383,533.Under the programme for the winter, 1922-23,1,131 schemes have been approved, costing  473,550, and the number of men at work during the week ended the 17th February, 1923, was 6,706.(b.) Water Supply.-.Last winter forty-five schemes, costing  28,228, were approved.Under the 1922-23 programme 110 schemes, costing  40,316, have so far been approved, and the number of men at work during the week ended the 17th February, 1923, was 245. &apos;4. Trade Improvement Schemes.
(c.) Forestry.Last winter a sum of  250,000 was allocated for the assistance of schemes of the above nature. 573 schemes were approved, involving a total cost of  166,000.Under the 1922-23 programme 317 schemes have so far been approved for grants amounting to  56,679, and the number of men at work on these schemes during the week ended the 17th February, 1923, was 1,823. In addition the Forestry Commission were also employing, at that date, 730 men in excess of their normal staff employed on forestry operations.(B.) Light Railways.Two schemes approved under last winter&apos;s programme are still in operation and at the 17th February, 640 men were employed thereon.

</content>
</cab>
