<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 458-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is ths property of His Majesty1b government.IropuqjstQd that this document bj^hlfeaTed asHiIaliTy confidential&quot;, .   1 Q, Spooial Branch,I- New Scotland Yard,h IfO&apos;. 196,f^sir^^^ Maroh 8th, 1923.(25) )  ,B^ALlT^^^HEPORtP OH REVOLUTIONARY 0RGA1II3ATIONS  ^ III &apos;JH3 UNITED KINGDOM-,-,,-o0o-----------------IKE COIMWISS INIILKHATIOHAX AND GREAT BRITAIN..Page 1TEE CGuMMXISTS                     .................... &quot; 3THE COMliWflSTS AWL TEE UNEMPLOYED.............. &quot; 6THB RFJ) INTERNATIONAL OP LAB CUE UNIONS.......... n 11THE YCUKG CCiiKUKIbT IBAGUE..................... &quot; 13THE UlffiHPlOYED................................. &quot; 15IRISH REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES IN GREAT BRITAIN &quot; 16S U M II A R YOn February 26th the wholly unemployed on tho live registers iallod approximately 1,328,000j, a deoreaso of 12,260 on the iTious weok:   on tho same date the number working short time and twing benefit for intervals of unemployment was 54,500 as compared th 55,524 on February 19th...41 unemployed marchers are still in London..Tho Communist Party is making oareful arrangements in connection ft the national conference of the organised unemployed next ith:   definite instructions regarding policy and resolutions re been sent to the District Party Committees.The Presidium of tho Communist International in Russia has Jssed an important resolution on the &quot;Piitiiianentary activity of tho Imunist Party of Great Britain&quot;, which is quoted In this report.She Communist P.-.&apos;.rty has rcnowed its application to the labour fty for affiliation.The Communist Party and the Red International of Labour Unions Jthis country have been instructed to sand delegates to the llerenoo which is to be held in Germany on March 17th in JfflGction with the occupation of the Ruhr.The anti-militarist campaign of the Young Communist League I led to tho issue of literature which is intended to undermine discipllno of Ris Majesty1,,-. Forces.
TEEB COMMUfllSx ISWBSAIlOSASt  &amp; GKEUT BRITAIH&apos;JBie Presidium of the Communist International in Russia recently passed an important resolution on the Parliamentary activity of the Coromunist party of Great Britain:   this document is given below and, since the Communist International has been proved to be a department of the Soviet Government,affords a decisive answer to the Ruasian olaims in regard to abstention from propaganda in this country:   the resolution,. according to the written statement of a leading official of the party, &quot;is regarded as purely an executive document and not to be published&quot;.     Kuusinen is a member of the Executive Committee of the Comintern end led the communist revolt in Finland In 1918.&quot;The parliamentary activity of the Communist Party of Great Britain,1.   &quot;The tactics of the united pront must under no circumstances be interpreted to mean that our Party must lose its identity, cease to criticise or even to lessen its criticism of the labour Party, etc.&quot;On the oontrary, those tactics have meaning only in so far as they enable us to expose to the masses the bourgeois character of the leaders of the Labour Party who have been corrupted by Imperialism.2.     &quot;The instruction to affiliate to the Labour party does not imply unconditional affiliation, but affiliation on such oenditions as would secure for communists        -. -! absolute freedom of criticism and complete independence ;.i of their own militant revolutionary organisation. Without this condition, the affiliation to the Labour Party for the purpose of conducting revolutionary work within it loses all meaning.   Generally the instruction to affiliate to the Labour Party is rendered possible in England owing to the special character of the Labour Party and the specific form of its organisation.   Such an instruction would have been totally impossible in any other country.   Consequently this wa3 the only exception made throughout the whole of the Communist International, and was called forth by the peculiarities of the Labour Party, whioh is not a party in the strict sense of the word.3.     &quot;In Parliament, in whioh the class struggle in the country is focussed, our chief task should be to develop   our own revolutionary position whioh should be the very opposite to that of all other parties,including/
including the labour party.    Joint-Action, with the^ ;Lab^rytr     344 party is by no means obligatory.   On the contrary,&quot;what aa, obligatory, is to keep up the sharpest criticism of that party, which at the present moment is one of the greatest props of British Imperialism.4.    &quot;Joint action with the Labour party in Parliament is possible only on the oondition that the labour Party will agree to joint mass action Outside of Parliament.   Even on this condition, however, the partly must, in addition to supporting joint demands, make clear its own position.5.     &quot;Thus the main task of our comrades who have bean the firBt to penetrate into the citadel of British Imperialism, ie to introduce an absolutely new revolutionary spirit in parliamentary action, hostile in principle to the basis of British Constitution, to the policy of the British Government and to all the parties that support it.6.     &quot;Parliamentary action must be olosely connected with the aotion outside of Parliament, as is explained in detail in the Theses of the Second Congress of the Communist International.7.     &quot;In Great Britain, more than in any other country, work should be concentrated, not on &quot;taking part in legislation&apos;- . but in campaigns of exposure and on opposition to the views, the measures and the laws of the bourgeoisie, the point of view of revolutionary communism.8.     &quot;The important questions that should be subjected to the sharpest criticism in Great Britain are as follows:-(a) &quot;Unemployment, and the attitude of the Government towards the economic position of the Working Class.(b) &quot;The Colonies &amp; Ireland.(o)   &quot;The Foreign policy of the Government, particularly in connection with the question of the Ruhr, reparations, etc.(d) &quot;The policy towards soviet Russia,(s) &quot;Militarism,(f) &quot;The Budget,(g) &quot;The Bourgeois policy of the labour Party.9.     &quot;It is necessary to give battle all along the line on all these questions, giving prominence to those facts that will be best ur^errtcod by the masses and bringing tc the front and making popular the general aims and watchwords of the Communist International,    (per. ex. question of the Ruhr, Essen conference, etc.)10.   &quot;Under no ciroumstances must parliamentary action be regarded as an end in itself nor must the interests let alone the prejudices, of a given group of electors be plaoed higher than the interests of a revolutionary proletarian movement as a whole.11.   &quot;The more revolutionary consistent our criticism will be, the more quickly shall ws widen the horizon of the working class &quot;which to-day is so limited by prejudices, and the greater will be the Service that Comrflunisui will render to the cause of the Social Revolution. .12./
COMMUNISTSThe Communist Party has renewed its application foraffiliation to the Labour Party in the following letter toMr. Arthur Henderson, M.P., dated B&apos;ebruary 26th:-&quot;In pursuance of the decision taken at our Party Congress at the Battersea Town Hall, on 7-9th Ootober, 1922, and subsequently ratified by our party council meeting on  February 10th and 11th, to seek affiliation to the Labour Party, I am directed by our Central Committee to apply formally to your Executive Committee to accept the Communist Party of Great Britain as an affiliated body to the Labour Party..&quot;Our Central Committee is not unmindful of the decision taken last year at Edinburgh by your Annual Conference, but we consider the experiences since then of common working together in the localities, both in connection with the municipal and parliamentary elections, as well as in the common action against the industrial offensive of the employers, have demonstrated the desire of the vast majority of the working olass for united action.&quot;It is stated in the issue of &quot;The workers&apos; Weekly&quot; dated March 3rd that:-&quot;The Communist Party has renewed its application to the Labour Party for affiliation.   The leaders of the Labour Party are trying to maintain their power by excluding all those who are prepared to fight their treacherous policy of alliance with capitalism.   The Communist party applies for affiliation in order to take Its part in the united struggle of the workers against capitalism.   The policy of exclusion adopted- by the &apos; official amendments to the Constitution at the Edinburgh Conference last year has failed.   The Edinburgh amendments are inoperative. Reports from all over the country show that the workers and the Communist party are too olosely bound up to be separated.   Everywhere the masses are for unity, whatever their leaders may say,&quot;The/12.     &quot;The first step that Comrade Hewbold should take should he to raise the Buhr question, the conduct of the Government and of the Labour Party and also of the whole of the Amsterdam International, which latter has not even replied to the proposal for a United Front on1 this decisive question.&quot;A corresponding oampaign must also be commenced in the Press.The Presidium of the E.C. of the C.I.(Signed)   O.W. Kuusinen.&quot;
The communist! Psrty has issued handbills and an Open letter to the Rank and File of the labour Party in connection with the Party&apos;s exclusion from that &quot;body in consequence of the Edinburgh amendments,   The arguments advanced in the Open letter raise no new points hut local labour Parties are esked to pass and forward to Ecolaston Square the following re solution&quot;This....,.....Branch of the............approvesof the acceptance of the application of the Communist Party for affiliation to the Labour party and instructs its delegates to all Local and Hctional Conferences to support this attitude.&quot;Pages of instructions amplifying the Commission Report on the working of Local Party Committees and Area Groups have been sent to tho District Party Committees:   these are not reproduced in this report as, apart from affording additional proof of the minute attention to detail which is part of the communist re-organisation, they are of merely departmental interest.In April the Presidium of the Communist Internationalwill consider &quot;the whole English question..,and there is likelj,to be a Must up*.   All Executive Committee members are togo on the carpet.    Agenda:-United Front.Labour party, affiliation.Parliamentary Policy.Colonial questions.Ireland.Organisation of Party.&quot; Speaking at a communist meeting in the west Islington Library on March 4th, Tom Bell, the political secretary of the CoiBmunist Party said that the only remedy for capitalism from the workers&apos; point of view was to end it, and in order to do that a social revolution was neoessary, and there must be a dictatorship of the proletariat.   This had been brought about in Russia with beneficent results to the workers there.   The Communist Party in this country was atpresent/
present very weak b?ii the Coitmunist International, whosecongress he had recently attended in Moscow, was verymorepowerful and was becoming /so every day.   The Ked Army ofRussia was behind the Communist International and gave it an armed strength of something like five million men.   It wasimpossible for the Communist Party in this country to organisean armed force - the capitalists saw to it that they did not get that chance - but by sowing the seeds of discontent inthe rank and file of the naval and military forces, who were all sprung from the ranks of the workers, they hoped at theopportune moment to win over sufficient of these to form the nucleus of the armed forces of the Communist stato.It is stated in the issue of &quot;The Workers&apos; Weekly&quot; dated march 3rd that:&quot;The london District Party Committee of the Communist Party has instructed all its local organisations falling within the Mitcham constituency to take active part in working for the return of the labour candidate against Bosoawen and the other capitalist candidates.&quot;The business side of &quot;The Communist Review&quot; has been plaoed in the hands of the management committee of &quot;The Workers&apos; Weekly&quot;:   after the Maroh number the sise of &quot;The Communist Review&quot; will be reduced from 64 to 40 pages &quot;in order to partially make up the loss.&quot;It is reported that the Communist Party and the Red International of Labour Union   are sending men to Wales and other mining areas with the idea of forcing the position in the coal-fields.Philips Price returned to Gloucester on February 24th &quot;for propaganda work in the constituency&quot;:   he met W.H. Ewer, of&quot;she Herald&quot;, on his way through London and left with him instructions for the Communist Party and the british bureau/
-i 5 -347present very weak bint the Communist International, whosecongress he had recently attended in Moscow, was verymorepowerful and was becoming /so every day.   The Red Army ofRussia was behind the Communist International and gave it an armed strength of something like five million men.   It wasimpossible for the Communist Party in this oountry to organisean armed foroe - the capitalists saw to it that they did not get that chance - but by sowing the seeds of discontent in.the rank and file of the naval and military forces, who were all sprung from the ranks of the workers, they hoped at theopportune moment to win over sufficient of these to form the nucleus of the armed forces of the Communist State. &quot;It is stated in the issue of &quot;The Workers&apos; Weekly&quot; dated march 3rd that:&quot;The London District party Committee of the Communist Party has instructed all its local organisations falling within the Mitcham constituency to take active part in working for the return of the Labour candidate against Bosoawen and the other capitalist candidates.&quot;The business side of &quot;The Communist Review&quot; has been placed in the hands of the management committee of &quot;The Workers&apos; Weekly&quot;:   after the Maroh number the aizQ of &quot;The Communist Review&quot; will be reduced from 64 to 40 pages &quot;in order to partially make up the loss.&quot;It Is reported that the Communist Party and the Red International of Labour Union   are sending men to Wales and other mining areas with the idea of forcing the position in the ooal-fields.Philips Price returned to Gloucester on February 24th &quot;for propaganda work in the constituency&quot;:   he met W.H. Ewer, of&quot;The Herald&quot; on his way through London and left with him instructions for the Coranunlst Party and the british bureau/
i 6 *Bureau of the Red International of labour unions to make preparations ana select delegates for tho Conference of &quot;red&quot; trade unions which is to &quot;be held in Germany        month &quot;to discuss methods of dealing with the Ruhr situation.&quot;  Price spoke on Germany at two meetings in Gloucester on February  7th and expects to be in London this wee3c, when he will visit the communist headquarters.W.P. Earsman, the Australian communist who recently came to this country from Australia 13 now in Berlin working for the Russian Trading Delegation who &quot;are going to open connection with Australia and are sending a man out&quot;, Earsman has &quot;to supply information and advise how it would be advisable to work and with whom&quot;.   He is shortly going to Moscow &quot;to take up an appointment in the university&quot;. Barsman states that during his stay in the East of Scotland ho took oharge of the Communist Party training group and election departments and reports that although he was at first opposed to door to door canvassing, tho results of this method &quot;are very good and far more effective than street corner meetings&quot;,   EarBman subsequently spent a weok in Glasgow doing &quot;work for Russian Trading Delegation, arranging business connections on the Clyde&quot;.Helen Crawfurd has applied to the Exeoutive of the Communist Party for permission to return to Sootland:   like Robert Stewart she is dissatisfied with tho &quot;limpets&quot; in London.COMMUNISTS AMD THE. UHEMPLQ1ED *She editorial notes in the Maroh issue of &quot;The Communist Review&quot; are devoted in the main to unemployment and certain passages are worthy of quotation as they are an accurate reflection of the communist attitude towards unemployment:-There/
&quot;Thero is one point upon which the communist Party has scored a most emphatic success, and that has been in its handling of the unemployed,   with unerring revolutionary Instinct the Party saw in unemployment the greatest danger to capitalism;   and it concentrated upon it in order to make it the rallying centre of the discontented masses and of the whole labour movement... As the Communists, in consequence of their activity on behalf of the workers, are the first to be victimised during strikes, lock-outs, or unemployment, it was only natural that they should have been the active ones in urging upon their workless mates the need for building up a National council of the Unemployed.     Thus the young Communist Party was tho only influential body in the labour movement that shouldered the enormous task of organising the unemployed, and of making it a disciplined foroe instead of permitting it to degenerate into a noisy rabble.&quot;The creation of this Council by local groups, without money, and without the assistance of any of the great official sections of the labour movement, was a herculean task... When the struggle of the unemployed In the streets, to force an interview with the head of the British State, was taken up by the new labour Members, the class war, between labour and Capital, made its first appearance In Parliament.   The Hunger Marchers&apos; sweep upon London scored a greater triumph than would have been possible by any interview forced upon the Premier;   they compelled the General Council of the Trades Union seriously to take up the question of unemployment nationally;   they make the Trades Councils and the Labour Parties throughout tho country take action   locally...&quot;But the new agitational campaign on behalf of the unemployed, launched by the joint Labour forces, cannot be so easily swept aside.   Firstly, because the demands of the National Council of the Unemployed cannot be accepted by the Bonar law Government;   secondly, because the capitalist system, in its present critical condition, is unable to carry out any far reaching schemes that would satisfy the unemployed masses.   Thus we have in the present unemployed movement splendid revolutionary potentialities, and the possibility of driving the whole of the labour forces to the Left and away from the influence of the timid leaders of the Right wing...&quot;It goes without saying that unemployment cannot be solved within the framework of capitalist society.   The Prime Minister has admitted as much...   Our task is to make the question of unemployment one that must be taken up by the whole working class movement;   and to be taken up in such a way that the Government and its sooial system shall be forced either to furnish adequate maintenance or make room for a Workers&apos; Government and a system that can provide such maintenance.   In this way a revolutionary situation is forced upon the ruling olass through demanding something which every worker looks upon as an elementary end urgent need.   Hot only is unemployment a menace which the masses dread;   it is one which they are prepared to struggle to overcome even if it means marching over a government or sweeping away a social system...&quot;!The/
&quot;The Labour movement always makes the greatest headway whero it is audacious and uncompromising;   the Municipal and Parliamentary elections of last year proved this up to the hilt.   Let Labour prepare a housing programme running into three or four hundred million pounds;   let Labour architects produce plans showing how the houses would be built;   lot Labour town-planners show how the new towns would be laid out;   let it be shown how these schemes would cut into the unemployed problem.   In the industrial spheie it could be shown that a fight for higher wages and a shorter working day is a part of the struggle against unemployment. In such a policy as this whioh directly appeals to every working man and woman who have suffered through unemployment, bad houses, low wages, etc., there is nothing that Bavours of Utopia.   It makes its appeal because it is linked up with tho every day problems of their lives...&quot;Those who are looking for an international policy that will assist tho unemployed may ,have forgotten the memorandum prepared by the Russian Delegation for the Hague Conference last July.   This was a detailed statement showing how the Soviet Government intended to spend the foreign credits whioh sho was asking for, and whioh were absolutely necessary for her programme of economic reconstruction.   Comrade Na.wfco.ia did splendid work in tho large industrial centres by showing how the granting of a big credit to Russia would mean an immediate resumption of work in tho heavy industries.   It should be an important point of the workers&apos; agitation on behalf of the unemployed to demand that a credit of three hundred million pounds be immediately granted to Russia.   Such a demand, if properly handled would demonstrate the industrial solidarity of Labour.   It would mean that just as the large financiers are able to utilise political pressure in order to enforce ruinous loans upon woak governments, so the Workers&apos; movement would exert all its agitational power to compel the Government to negotiate a big loan with Russia upon the most favourable terms.   This would moan that Russia would be able to restore her agriculture and industrios;   and it would place her squarely on the path of social advancement.*Pago Arnot discusses &quot;tho Labour Movement and theUnemployed* in the Maroh issue of &quot;The Labour Monthly&quot; anddeclares that:&quot;Pull maintenance must oease to be an orator&apos;s catchword.     The worker must be the first charge on the Budget - the vote must be for maintenance and against the Army and Navy.     Demands once formulated must be enforced by every means in the power of the workers, leading up to the General strike.     The general  Strike is reached, not by a bombastic summons from these chiefs without an  army, but by every party and union presenting a unitod front and carrying on a continuous campaign in Parliament, in tho municipalities, in tho workshops, at tho Labour Bxohangos, on the streets/
streets, and from door to door, inoroasing steadily in intensity and fill concentrated on one iBBue.   When that stage has been reached it does not much matter whether the General Strike is   victorious or defeated.   For, if defeated, it is the defeat of a class and the dofoat or a class is hut a phase of victory-..&quot;The Political Bureau of the Communist Party has issued,on &quot;Unemployed Bulletin&quot; to District Party Committees on thesubject of the agenda of tho national Unemployed Workers&apos;Committee Movement conference in Coventry on April 9th, lothand 11th.   In this document the items on tho agenda are takonin detail and definite instructions as to resolutions arelaid down.   The communist position is defined in the resolutionsand amendments given bolow:(1)   Unemployed Belief.&quot;This conference demands that Unemployed Relief be a national charge on the National Exchequer and to be administered through the Trade Unions.Note.   This resolution is important.   It will provide a sound line of appeal to the Unions as a means of proventing loss of membership and recruiting new membership.   It will provide an alternative to going cap in hand to the Guardians ivhich are dominated by middle class elements., ana strengthen, the claims of the organised working class to. administer their own affairs.&quot;f2)   Trading Agreement with Russia.(a) Resolution reoommended by National AdministrativeCouncil of Unemployed:-&quot;That as a means of finding employment for the unemployed in the trades with which they are associated, the British Government shall immediately grant complete recognition to Soviet Russia, with a view to the improvement of trading relationships.&quot;(b) Additional resolution to be put forward bycommunists:-&quot;This conference recognises the limitations of its demands as a means of solving the unemployed problem and looks in the direction indicated by the Communist Party as the only way to a final solution.   Wo therefore welcome the lead gi/en by tho Communist party to the working class and are prepared to form a United Front with it and all other organisations which will fight for our immediate demands and the overthrow of capitalism.&quot;
(3)   National Hunger Marchers.Hosolutions to be put forward by communists:&quot;This conference is of the opinion that the National Hunger March to see Bonar Law has served its exceedingly useful purpose and that we are now faced with the necessity of rousing the employed workers for a United effort to enforce our demands which are as vital to the employed workers as to ourselves.   We therefore resolve to organise mass agitation by means of mass marches to the factories, pits, railway centres, trade union branches and committees in the localities to prepare the way for a General strike to force our demands.   Wo further resolve to let no district slacken its efforts and that each strongly organised committee shall organise marches from district to district for the same purpose, to organise new committees end ensure national action on the broadest possible lines.&quot;&quot;This conference resolves that unemployed workers shall not pay rent or rates until the demands of the unemployed havo boon conceded and further, this conference resolves to resist evictions by every available means and warns the authorities that we regard ag a policy of terrorism against the people who can by no means be regarded ae responsible for their poverty.&quot;(4)   Payment for Belief Work.Resolution to bo put forward by communists:-&quot;This conference demands full trade union rates for all work undertaken as relief work and insists that all workers so employed shall become members of the trade union catering for the cltss of work upon which they may be engaged,&quot;Although the fact that the Communist party controls the organised unemployed movement has long been established, a specific instance of the manner in which control is exercisedmay not be without   interest:   on March 1st, the secretary ofthe Vale of Leven Local Party Committee reported to Scottishheadquarters ae follows:-&quot;As group leader of the Unemployed Committee group I have to make the following report in answer to your questionnaire of February gist, and I will endeavour to htivo weekly reports sent in future.(1)   Out of a Committee of 35 in Alexandria we have 19 members of the Communist phrty and we have two womon members of the party in the women&apos;e Sub-Committee, and four members of the party in the Renton Unemployed Committee.(2)   We have party members in the following positions inthese/
these Committees:   Vale Committee, Chairman, Minutes Secretary, Organiser, lit. Sec, Parish Financial dec., and convenor of complaints Committee, Women vs Sub.- commit tee our two women comrades, are President and secretary lenton Committee;   Chairman ia member of Communist Party and other three Cummvnist party members have strong influence on Committee,(3)   We sell papers to all members of the Vale Committee, and in Renton sell about a dozen to members of the Committee.(4)   During the past month we have gained 8 recruits for the Party from the Unemployed Committee.(5)   We have two party members (Comrade 0&apos;Hare and myself) selected as delegates to attend, the National Unemployed Workers&apos; Committee Movement Conference in Coventry on 9, 10, 11 April.&quot;No other Political Party has any influence in the Unemployed Movement locally, our members completely dominate the situation, and I might point cat that we have taken the initiative this last week in the Rent Campaign.   We hare formed a tenants guard to operate in casss of eviction, and we intend taking the initiative inside the Unemployed movement, and calling a conference of all working class bodies in our locality to place before them our proposals re the 1&apos;enants Guard and by this means endeavour to secure a Working Class United Front in this distriot.&quot;I RED INTBRNAT IONAL OF, LABOUR UNIONSThe British Bureau of the Rod International of LabourUnions appears to he in (possibly temporarily) financial difficulties:   on February 22nd Roinhardt of the central european Bureau informed Watkins that:&quot;We informed our financial department to send you immediately the requested amount of 10 Pounds stlg.&quot;About the whole finanoial question we are writing with the next mail to Moscow to regiilate this point without any discussion.&quot;The Central European Bureau appears to be making thearrangements for the conference of &quot;red&quot; trade unions inGermany next month and has sent the following circular tothis country:&quot;The Committee of 23 of the Rhenish-Westphalian Shop Councils issues invitations for a Conference to take place on March 11th in order to discuss and adoptpractical/
-12 -practical measures forjroalising tho revendioatione       9 proclaimed hy the Shop councils of tho Mining Industry   &quot; in Essen on January 24th*   The Conference shall further discuss measures against the military despotism and the misery under which the workers of the Rhine-province and Wnetphalia are suffering.   Its object will be to organise the common resistance of the German ana French proletariat from which depends the future of the whole Middlo European   working &quot;class.&quot;This oommon resistance must immediately begin. All ready the workers on the Ruhr, on the Mosolle on the Bear and tho miners of France are fighting!     If we fail to aot, it is on ua that the responsibility will fall for the economic destruction of Europe and of the whole World.&quot;We therefore invite you to   cond your delegates to our addross.&quot;It is of greatest importance to delegate as far as possible comrades who are really representatives of the movement and are invested with full power to speak in the name of their respective organisations.&quot;In our opinion it would be best to delegate representatives of the miners&apos; and transport workers&apos; organisations, on account of the fundamental importance of those latter ones in the economic sphere...&quot;date of this oonferenoe has now been altered to iiarch 17th, The International piMpaganda Committee of miitary&amp;re in Moscow has informed the British Bureau that;&quot;It may be supposed that the-French capitalists will attempt to get coal from England,   you are requested to make clear to tho English miners tho meaning of the strike in France whioh, though mainly of an economic character, is assuming political significance in oonnootion with the occupation of the Rvlir district, you must So everything within your power to prevent the possibility of strike-breaking.   You are also requested te send greetings on behalf of the revolutionary British miners to the French unitary Federation of Miners and give whatever possible material assistance to the striking French comrades through the collection of contributions among tho miners.&quot;The Central European Bureau is trying to  make arrangements for the exchange of publications with all the more important British trade unions and has also made a similar application to the Labour ReHearoh DeT)**rtnent.The &quot;International propaganda Cocn.iltt*e of Office and   Comaercial Enployeaa&quot; is greatly annoyed hy the fact that it has no connection with the &quot;movemont of office employeeb in England&quot; a.i6 Wt; lnstruoted the British Buwauto/
THE YOUNG CQIMJBISQ? ISASUEThe March issue of &quot;The Youny Cotaonnist&quot; is a double number and is devoted almost exclusively to the anti-militarist campaign:   the whole issue is highly undesirable and undoubtedly intended to undermine the discipline of His Majesty1s Forces.    Tuo manifestoes are worthy of special mention;   the first &quot;India for the Indians&quot;, is headed &quot;Don&apos;t shoot your fathers&quot; and contains the following passages:-&quot;The Young Communist league of Great Britain addresses Itself to you on behalf of the Young Coraraunlst International.   It stretches forth the hand of comradeship and calls for united action against British Imperialism, which is crushing both of us, Briton and Hindoo...&quot;You are to be the cheap slaves of British Imperialism.&quot;Finding itself unable to comfortably compete with the other imperialist powers, it turns to you, - Indian comrades, and hopes to grind from your sweat and misery fabulous profits with which to restore its equilibrium which was shattered by the world-war.&quot;Indian comrades, what does this mean to you?&quot;Slavery?     Misery.   Never-ending toil and hardship.&apos;&quot;...They (the imperialists) are determined to force you down, as they are determined to force the German workers down, at the point of the bayonet.   As a consequence of your Turkish comrades&apos; courage and determination, the Treaty of Sevres, the offspring of Versailles, has gone into liraba, and the yoke of British Imperialism flung off the necks of the Turkish peasants.&quot;They are now attempting to introduce conscription in India.   This means that they want to dress you, young comrades, in the uniform of the British Imperialist Army and issue you rifles to shoot down your fathers and brothers when they rebel against the intolerable conditions which ere intended to be forced upon them.&quot;Indian comrades, you also must line up alongside the youth of Great Britain and the revolutionary youth of the whole world for a common struggle against our one enemy, imperialism.&quot;United, we British and Indian young workers can throw off the yoke of British Imperialism..&quot;India/to ascertain why Elian Wilkinson is not sending in reports.
&quot;India for the Indians.1&quot;Down with the imperialist robber banal&quot;Down with the Treaty of Versailles!&quot;Jhe second which is addressed to British soldiers inIndia reads as follows:-&quot;lay Down Your Guns IFraternise with your Indian BrothersJAn Appeal to the British Soldiers in India.English Comrades,&quot;The Young Communist League of Great Britain addresses itself te you on behalf of the young working olass of Greet Britain and the Young Coiamunist International.&quot;We know that most of you are young workers, like ourselves, that you are with the colours in India because you could not find a job in the old country.&quot;Wo know, furthermore, that you are sent to India by the British Imperialists, to crush, by military force, if need be, the Indian workers and peasants.&quot;This is the.reason why you are in India, in order to safeguard, not your interests, nor those of the British workers, or any other workers, but the interests of British Imperialism, which is determined to wring big profits out of the Indian workers ana peasants.&quot;Young English comrades, you knwo that they are now setting up in India tejctile factories, steel mills, and all kinds of big plant - they are industrialising India.&quot;Why?   Because they want cheap slaves.&quot;British white labour is too dear for them,&quot;They want the Indian worker to be driven into the mines, mills and steel works, and they want you to do it for them.&quot;What does this mean for those at home?   It means unemployment, starvation and misery.     It means that your -   sister, your brother^ o&quot;F your father, in the cotton mills of Lancashire, the steel works of the Clyde, or the factories in Birmingham or Coventry, will be thrown out of a job.&quot;If you drive the Indian workers to work long hours for the crust of a slave, you drive your family at home into starvation.   Because the Indian workers will work cheaper titan the English workers at home.&quot;What should you do?&quot;Refuse to be t^e tools of British Imperialism.&quot;Join/
&quot;Join hands with tho young adult workers in India who are standing solid with us.&quot;Recognise the right of the Indians to decide theii,: own Indian affairs without outside Interference.&quot;Don&apos;t drivo your own people at home to starvation and despair.   Insist on your right to decide your own action yourselves.&quot;long live the solidarity of the workers of India ana Great Britain.   Long live the fraternity of the workers, soldiers and peasants of the whole world other parts of the paper deal with alleged flogging in the Ifcvy and the &quot;veritable hell&quot; of the sailors1 sad soldiers&apos; life.Ihe paper has boon submitted to the Director of Public Prosecutions for consideration.THE UNEMPLOYEDTho officials of the organised uneaployed are devoting most of their attention to the forthcoming national conference.Butohos of unemployed marchers continue to leave London at Intervals:   on Muroh 17th 41 still remained.Aw from next week the size of &quot;Out of Work&quot; is to be doubled and the wholesale price reduced to 2/4d. for 24 copies though the retail price will remain one penny.S.E. Dallas whs released from Brixton on March 3rd: there was no demonstration outside the prison:   about 500 unentployed assembled in Trafalgar Square to welcome him on March 4th:   speeches were made by H&apos;-nnington, Dallas, Holmes, M&amp;xtin, Soderberg, J. Quinton and John Staele. Holmes said:-&quot;They can fling every man, woman and child into prison, and by suffering and by tribulation we shall come to tho top, and when the day oomos workers, when you have got&apos;intelligence enough, we shall be behind the guns, and tho guns will be in front of us and theY.CL. of G.B.&quot;capitalist/
capitalist classes will be in front of the guns, and we will say to them &apos;Pey up you rogues or we will fire.   Blima me, won&apos; - we firo..&apos;T They say we ere out for bloodshed.   But. what about Waterloo;   the Crimea; what about the bloodshed from 1S14 to 1918.   20 million killed.   Ho, 12 million killed, 20 million wounded. Armless, legless, men are walking about.   Thoy told you they would look after you when you came back from the war.   They promised to do such a lot for you. They treat you as muck.   You have boen robbed all your lives, robbod of the wealth you produced, robbed of enjoyment and in the place of beautiful scenes they give you picture shows.   They tell you that the Union J.-;ck is the flag of freedom, but under the Union Jack the workers have boon massacred...&quot;It is reported that u meeting of unemployedorganisations was recently held in Glasgow for the purposeof forming a Central Ctommittoo:   among those present wereH..-McShane, W. Clark (Scots t oun), J* Me Tc r:g art (par tick),C. E;.. ad arson (Polldkshaws), J. Mellon, (Howood), C Clancy(Howbod), ;S. Brown (Clydebank), P. Hart (Glydebank),0&apos;Haro (Vvla of levon). Ciimpball (Vale of Leven) and C.Gallacher (Paisley).   It -was agreed to form Councils ofAction in all districts of Glasgow to fight evictionsfollowing on the Rent Acs decisions but the main idea isfor tho Councils of Action to &quot;discipline&quot; the unemployed.The Scotstoun and Whiteinch Labour Housing Association isreported to be controlled by oommunists:   Robertson ispresident and there are about 1,000 paying members.The Association has broken away from the Glasgow and scottish labour Housing Association and Robertson is saidto be gaining support by his eirposures of Zirkwood, Wheatleyand others.IRISH REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES IN GRgAT BRITAIN.The Irish situation in this country remains much the same.   The trouble at homejnaturally re-acts on tho position here and the various political clubs and leagues are Buffering accordingly.Art/
- 17 -Art 0&apos;Br.!.on&apos;s ^ttom-t to boom Countess Ifc.rkievicz is falling flat;   her presence arouses no enthusiasm in the London Irifch, who mostly regard her   as mad:   only the faithful   few turn up at her meetings which are a distinct fallure.for this Art 0&apos;Brion i;.nd his lieutenant Sean McGrath blame the police whom thoy accuso of interfering with tho rights of free speoch by inducing tho local authorities to refuse them tho use of the larger public halls.Another sore point is thyt, while hitherto they havo had it all thoir own way at these meetings, now they are encountering a certain amount of opposition of an organised character, presumably by prcu St:.tors.   To counteract this at a recent mooting a &quot;ciiucker out&quot; section was in evidence -. half a dozen stalwart young men in shirt eloeves standing by a tablo, placod just inside the door, upon which a number of heavy blackthorn sticks were displayed.Miiuama Markievioz is expected to return to Scotland about Miirch 20th.In the current issue of &quot;Eire&quot; Art 0&apos;Brien publishes a copy of his memorial no the International Committee of the Red Cross in which he states the Republican case and charges the Free State Government with breaches of the laws of war. He sli^ns it &quot;Ambassador of the Government of the Irish Republic.&quot;The Irish Republican Army leaders in this country are still activa in spite of the disconcerting fact that so many of their agents and so much of their material have fallen into tho hands of the police in Liverpool and in Ireland.A Glasgow correspondent whoso information can usuallybe relied upon, says that a big deal in ammunition is beingmade in Hamburg (presumably through Cooke, the Irish Republican;Army purchasing agent there) running into something like amillion/
million rounds.   Sailors aro to bo engaged to bring it across to Glasgow in small quantities and It will then be sent to Ireland via Liverpool.Ji&apos;.i Lar;-:in has sent privately to his sister in Dublin saying that he expects to reaoh that oity with his &quot;food ship&quot; at Saster:   a correspondent in close touch, thinks he will probably also try to do a little gun running.

</content>
</cab>
