<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 564-568</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS IX)OuWT. IS. THE PROPERTY OP HI 3 BRITAE1IC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYSBSKmi.; - . Copy Ho. _ &apos;;EffiCBET.C.P. 154125) . CABINET,Home, Affairs Cqmittee. Agiy CULTTl-B.^. BETOPff 3 $ILL;,Memorandum by the Minister of^Agriculture,and.Fisheries.I desire to introduce the Agricultural Returns Bill, copies of which are circulated herewith.The Bill reproduces .in effect the provisions of section fifteen of the&apos; Corn Production Act, 1917, which wa3 repealed with the rest of that Act as the.powers were expressly stated to be given &quot;in order to obtain such information as is necessary for the purpose of the proper exercise by the Board of their powers under this Act&quot;.The desired returns have for many years been obtained without compulsion, but there are in each year a few persons who decline to make returns.     To secure complete statistics a power to deal with such persons is desired and this proposal is approved by the principal -bodies representing agricultural opinion.     Following the precedent of the Corn Production Act the Bill provides for the form of return being settled by regulations laid before Parliament.Unless the Committee considers that adherence to this precedent is desirable I should prefer to omit sub-section (7) dealing with this point.It is proposed to introduce the Bill in the Houseof Lords.R.A.S.Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries. 19th March, 1923.
[13 Geo. 5.]       Agricultural Returns.D.EAPTop a .....BILLtoFacilitate the preparation of Agricultural Statistics.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty,  A.D. 1923. by.and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows: 1. (1) The Minister of Agriculture and fisheries Power to may, by notice served on the occupier of any agricultural reclmi&apos;e land in England or Wales or the person haying the retiuiis-management of any such land, require him to make within10 such time as is specified in the notice, and in such formand to such person as the Minister may prescribe by &apos;-regulations made under this Act, a return in writing for the current year with respect to the cultivation of the land, or the crops or live stock thereon, or the persons15 employed on the land, and, if the occupier is also the owner of the land, that fact shall be stated in the return.(2) No individual return or part of a return made under this Act shall be used, published or disclosed, except for the purposes of the preparation and publication by the 20 Minister of agricultural statistics or of a prosecution under this Act.(3) (a) Any person who refuses, or without lawful excuse, neglects to make a return required under this Act to be made by him shall be liable on summary con-25 viction to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds. 31-&amp;
2Agricultural Returns.       [18 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1923. ^ jj a return made under this Act is untrue in any material particular, the person by whom the return was made shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, unless he proves that be made the return innocently and without negligence.     5(4) Any person who uses, publishes, or discloses contrary to the provisions of this Act any individual return or part of a return shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds.(5) Any notice under this Act may he served on the 10 person to whom it is addressed either personally or by post, and, in the case of a notice to an occupier, may be addressed to &quot; the occupier &quot; without naming him.(fi) The expression &quot; agricultural land&quot; includes land used as grazing, meadow, or pasture land, or orchard, 15 or osier land, or woodland, or for a market garden or nursery ground.(7) Any regulation made under this Act shall be laid before each House of Parliament forthwith, and if an address is presented to His Majesty by either House of 20 Parliament within the next subsequent twenty-eight days on which that House has sat praying that the regulation may he annulled His Majesty in Council may annul the regulation, and it shall thenceforth he void, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 25 thereunder.Application 2. (1) This Act in its application to Scotland shall to Scotland jjaye effect with the substitution of references to the and extent.  jjoar(j Q  Agriculture for Scotland for references to theMinister,and,of a reference to Scotland for the reference 30 j      to England or Wales. .(2) This Act shall not extend to Northern Ireland.Short title 3. This Act may be cited as the Agricultural ReturnsAct, 1923.

Agricultural Returns.DRAFT or aBILLTo facilitate tlie preparation of Agricultural Statistics.XXII.   (4.)16th March 1923.31-4

</content>
</cab>
