<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 569-573</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This pocunent is the Property of His.Britannic Majesty&apos;3 Government]43?/?. Copy Bo._/ ,secret. CABINET.5&quot;xt55 (23)Railway, Fires (1905) Amendment Bill. Agricultural Holdings Acts (Amendment)   Bill, Memorandum.by&apos;the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.On Friday next two private members&apos; bills dealing with agricultural subjects will come before the House of Commons, for second reading;   copies appended herewith.The Railway Fires Bill purports to enable an owner whose land is injured by sparks from a railway engine to recover compensation without proof of negligence up to  200 instead of  100 as allowed by the K?.il&apos;.&apos;-ay Fires Act. 1905.   The Bill passed second reading In the House of Commons last session by 134 to 27 and went through Committee -ithout amendment.The Agricultural Holdings Act (Amendment) Bill enables p. tenant to trer,t as his landlord, for the purpose of serving any notice, the person to whom he has been paying his rent until he has received written notice that some other person has become his landlord.   The bill is promoted by the Agricultural Committee of the House of Commons and seems a harmless measure.With the consent of my colleagues I should like to say that the Government regards both bills with   favour *R. A. S.iistry of Agriculture and Fisheries. I 19th March, 1923.
[13 Geo. 5.]Railway Fires Act (1905) Amendment.ABILLtoAmend the Railway Fires Act, 1905. A.n. 1923.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this, present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows :-1. Subsection (3) of section one of the  Railway Amendment Eires Act, 1905 (hereinafter called the principal Act), of 5 Edw. 7. shall be amended by the substitution of the words &quot; two s&apos; 1 (3)-hundred pounds &quot; for the words &quot; one hundred pounds &quot; 10 in the said subsection.2. The principal Act shall not apply in the case of Conditions any action for damage by fire brought against any railway precedent to company unless (1) notice in writing of the fire having jJPpl1!fna*-)0&quot;1 occurred and of intention to claim in respect thereof shall Act.UnC&apos;P&apos;1 15 have been sent to the said railway company within fourteen days of the occurrence of the damage; and (2) particulars in writing of the damage showing the amount of the claim in money not exceeding the said sum of two hundred pounds shall have been sent to the said railway company 20 within twenty-one days of the occurrence of the damage.3. Section three of the principal Act is hereby Repeal of s. 3 repealed. of principalAct4. This Act may be cited as the Railway Eires Act short title. (1905) Amendment Act, 1923.[Bill-10]
BA.ILLTo amend the Railway Fires Act, 1905.Presented by Mr. Sparkes, supported by Mr. Pretyman, Mr. Shepperson, Mi: Thomas Davies, Mr. Lambert, and Sir Robert Newman.Ordered, by The House of Commons, to be Printed, 16 February 1923.LONDON:PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE.To be purchased through any Bookseller or directly from H M Stationery Office at the following addresses:. Imperial House. KrnKsvroy, London, W.O. 2, and 2S Abingdon Street, London, S.W. 1: 37. Peter Street, Manchester;1, St. Andrew&apos;8 Crescent. Cardifl; or 23, Forth Street, Edinburgh.Printed by Eyes and Spottiswoode, .LTD.,East Harding Street, E.C. 4 Printers to the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty.[Bill 10][Price 2d. Net.&apos;]
bill to amend the Agricultural Holdings Acts, 1908 to a.d. 1923.1921.E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows: 1. Unless or until a tenant of a holding shall have Provisions received notice in writing from the person to whom he is ils \0 serving under or in pursuance of the terms of the contract of notl0e-tenancy required for the time being to pay his -rent, or10 from the agent of such person, informing the tenant that some other person is or will from a date named therein become entitled to receive the rents and profits of the holding and giving the name and address of such other person, any notice, request, demand or other instrument15 which the tenant shall serve or shall have served upon or deliver or shall have delivered to the person to whom the tenant is under or in pursuance of the terms of the contract of tenancy required for the time being to pay his rent or upon or to the agents of such person, shalljbe20 deemed to have been served upon or delivered to the landlord of such holding for the time being as defined by section forty-eight, subsection (l) of the Agricultural Holdings Act, 1908.2. This Act shall not apply to Ireland. Applicationof Act.2fi3.-(1) This Act may be cited as the Agriculture Short title (Amendment) Act, 1923. and con-[Bill 16] Structiou-[13 Geo. 5.]    Agricultural Holdings Acts 1(Amendment).
11 -&apos;. -:]:&apos;1.1 Wa111    Z&apos;&apos;&quot;i&quot;i &amp; B   ILLT&quot;) amend the Agricultural Holdings Acts,-1908 to 1921.Presented by Brigadier-General Clifton Brown,supported byMr. Pretyman, Mr. Lamb, Mr. Murrough Wilson,Mr. SAepperson, Mr. Lambert, Sir Arthur Jiolbrook, and Sir Robert NewmarisOrdered, by The House of Commons, to be Printed, 16 February 1923.LONDON:PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE.To be purchased through any Bookseller or directly from h.m. Stationery OtfFiaffl at the following addresses i lmperialcSouse, kingsway , London, W.C. 2, and 28, Abingdon Street, London, S.W. 1; 37, Peter Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andre w&apos;s Orescent, Cardiff; or 120, George Street, Edinburgh.Printed by Eybb and spottiswoode, Ltd.,East Harding Street, E.C. 4, Printers to the King*s most Excellent Majesty.\_Price 2d. Net.&apos;][Bill 16]2 Agricultural Holdings Acts   [13 Geo. 5.1(Amendment)...D. 1923. (2) This Act shall, so far as it relates to England and Wales, he construed as one with the Agricultural Holdings Acts, 1908 to 1921, and, so far as it relates to Scotland, heconstrued as one. with the Agricultural Holdings (Scot-land) Acts, 1908 to 1921, and this Act and those. Acts 5 respectively may he cited together as the Agricultural Holdings Acts, 1908 to 1923, or the Agricultural Holdings (Scotland) Acts, 1908 to 1923, as the case may be.

</content>
</cab>
