<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/159/0 images: 683-685</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governs n5)2 9s e c r iin.p.m(2g)CABINET.SUBSIDIES to arab chiefs.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.By direction of the Prime Minister the Cabinet Committee on Iraq, took into consideration on the 26th March the question of the payment of subsidies to Arab Chiefs. They had before them a paper prepared by the Colonial Office, in consultation with the India Offioe, Foreign Office and Treasury, sketching the past history of the question and making recommendations for the future.Stated briefly, the only Arabian Chief at present drawing a subsidy from British revenues Is Ibn Saud, the Sultan of Nejd, whs is paid in Indian oirrenoy at the rate of  5,000 a month, or  60,000 a year.     The King of the Hejaz received a subsidy during the war and for some time afterwards, but payment has long been discontinued.     It has always been contemplated, however, that the subsidy should be renewed if and when the King concluded a satisfactory treaty of friendship with His Majesty&apos;s Government. Negotiations for such a treaty ?Jore in progress in tho latter part of 1921.     In the event they oame to nothing.     They have, however, recently been resumed and there is now good prospect of a treaty being concluded.     King Hussein will oertainly expect some financial assistance when the treaty has been signed.The only other Chiefs concerned are&apos; the Imam of the Yemen and the Idrisi of Asir.    ; These rulers, who v/ere under the Turks before the war, live in South West Arabia, in the/.&apos;.eighbov.ir-hood of &quot;the Aden Protectorate.   Relations -with- them are conducted through/   wl-
the Resident at Aden.     Like King- Hussein and Lbn Baud, they are keen rivals *     In the interests of Aden it is most desirable that they should be required to keep the peace towards one another and towards ourselves.     The Imaiaj who is the more powerful of the two, was for .some time after the war In &apos; occupation of a part of the Aden Protectorate.     Unless we can come to terms with him he vis likely to be a constant thorn in our side.     VTe have already entered into preliminary negotiations with him, but it is unlikely that, a satisfactory agreement can be reached unless we can&quot;induce the Idrisi to evacuate the port of Hodeidah in his favour.     Hodeidah, vzhich is on the Red Sea, ia the natural port of Saana, the Imam&apos;8 capital, and for geographical and other reasons belongs &quot;properly&quot; to the Yemen rather then to A sir.     Ve occupied the port for strategical purposes during the war.   When our troops sere withdrawn in 1920 we allowed the Idrisi to take possession of the place.     The difficulty now 1b to get him out of it.    ; :  &apos;&apos;The policy framed in 1930 contemplated the payment of subsidies to both these chiefs&apos;, conditionally upon their coming to satisfactory arrangements with the British Government. Modified proposals were put forward in 1932, which contemplated the payment of a subsidy to the Idrisi only, it being considered that the Imam ought to be content with the recovery of Hodeidah..The Committee were clearly of opinion that the whole system of subsidies should be brought to an end as soon as possible. The objections to asking Parliament for money for such a purpose year after year &amp;re obvious.     The Committee favoured the proposal of the Colonial Office that an attempt should be made to liquidate once and for all by lump sum payments ail our liabilities under this head.     It is believed that Ibn Baud, ..*ho is in special need of funds ,at the.present moment, would probably be willing to accept a reasonably &apos;l.arge amount in lieu of all recurrent subsidy. It is further believed that King Hussein, v?ho has always taken
Colonial Office. . March S7th 1935;great-esoeption to oui1 oubaitUaing IbJj; Baud, would te content to put hia own deBianM..re&amp;9on&amp;biy low if lie a ere assured thatno further payments v:ere to he made to his rival.     With regardto the Idrisi, There sterns no reason why the desired object.Viz&apos;: - his evacuation of Hodeidah, should not be achieved by a lump sum payment just as  veil as by a monthly subsidy.The Committee agreed to recommend to the Cabinet thefollowing propositionsi-(1)     That Ibn Saud. should be informed that a single payment of  50,000 will be made to him for the . year 19.33-24, but that after the 31st March 1925 his subsidy ..111 be discontinued.(.3.)     That King Hussein should, be informed that, if and when he signs a satisfactory Treaty with us, - he will be given a lump sum of  50,000, but no recurrent subsidy,(5)     That the Resident at Aden should be authorised to negotiate with the Idrisi on the basis of his evacuating Hodeidah in return for the payment to, him of a single sum of  20,000.&apos;..1.     1 . .Unde&apos;x* these&apos; proposals payment to Ibn Saud (though not to thev ,.....-;-&apos;P.eothb, j).would fall due at the beginning of the new financial year.v    The Committee considered that it might be preferable to pay thd&apos;,sum in two instalments of  85,000 at a time instead of making a ,.s ingle payment at onoe ,  thereby extending the period during which we should retain a lever for exercising our Influence lover Ibn Baud,     They recommended that this point should be put to Sir P,Co% through ;vhom the negotiations with Ibn Saud will&apos; be conducted,,It should &quot;ce made clear to all three chiefs that &quot;the offer holds, good only for the financial year 1935-34.     If they do not come to terms within that period they will get nothing at all. The sum of  120,000 which has been provided in the Middle Eastern Services -estimates? for 1925-E4 will cover the payments proposed,(Signed)     DEVONSHIRE.

</content>
</cab>
