<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/230/0 images: 50-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.!SECRET.CP. 160 (32).CABINET.Reports by  Local Governments on the  Political Situation in India.   I circulate for the information of my colleagues the latest weekly reports from the-Local Governments in India.                                                                        S.  H.      INDIA OFFICE,      18th May 1932.Government of India.   Weekly provincial reports show that nothing of importance has occurred duringthe week.Delhi.   There has been another quiet week.  A Sikh demonstration planned  for 6th Mayrthe Sisganj anniversary, did not materialise.  Section 3, arrests one :  total detained, 10.Section 4, fresh orders, nil.  Total to date in respect of whom orders are in force, 16-Convictions to date for contravening orders, 3.Bombay.   There have been no important occurrences in Bombay city or in the Mofussil districts -An attempt at Sholapur to observe Sholapur Martial Law Day, on Friday, caused no localexcitement.  There was a partial hartal  in the town and several arrests were made.Damage to letter-boxes is  reported from  three districts.   In Bombay city picketingis being  continued  on a decreased  scale, a new development being its extension tocloth shops in  the Colaba area on Monday.  This, however, was discontinued after thepicketers had  been arrested.   The Bullion Exchange  continues to remain open.  Ageneral  meeting of the Stock Exchange on Monday expressed confidence  in the Board,and the resignation of the directors will now be withdrawn.  Several raids have beencarried out and a  considerable amount  of Congress  literature and  one cyclostylemachine  has  been seized.    Ordinance  II,  section  3:  arrests,  6;  total  under detention, 52.   Section 4: orders, 38 ;  total in force, 882.  Section 21 : convictionsduring the  week, 17.  Congress funds to  the amount of Rs. 940 have been forfeitedunder Ordinance IV during the week.Bengal.   The situation remains unchanged.   There are, however, signs of a no-tax campaign in the Tamluk subdivision in Midnapore and in the Vishnupur subdivision in Bankuradistrict.   Section 3 : arrests 1.  Section 4  : orders issued, 31 approximately ; number in force, 373 approximately.  Figures not  complete.   Convictions, 120.Madras.   The situation remains much the same, though there has been a temporary increaseof civil disobedience activity in two west coast districts.United Provinces.   Except for  letter-box incendiarism and the cutting of telegraph wire, the lull incivil disobedience activity continues.   No  order under  section  3, Emergency PowersOrdinance; 52 orders  under section  4, and two convictions for defiance  of orders under section 4.   Convictions during the week under Ordinances, 23 ; under ordinary law, 112.   Total to  date, 9,048 ; releases, 2,161.     928    60  5.32
Central Provinces.   There has been a slight recrudescence of  Congress activity in Jubbulpore and&apos;Bilaspur.  Elsewhere there is nothing to report.   Prosecutions, 75 ; convictions, 94.Punjab.   The Province remains undisturbed.  Congress persists in efforts to enlist AmritsarSikhs, but without appreciable  success.  In Ludhiana District  telegraph wires were cut in three places on the same night by revolutionaries, who left a bomb on one site.A linesman was seriously  injured.  Political arrests under ordinary law, 10; underOrdinances, 27; total to date,  595 and  901  respectively.  One fresh order undersection 3 ; total such detenus, 4.   No fresh orders, section 4.   Total  persons  servedunder section 4, 103.   Of this  number, total  under restraint for infraction of such order, 23.North-West Frontier Province.   Section 3 : arrests, nil; total detained, 3.  Section 4 : orders during the week, IS ;.total orders in force, 1,465.   The situation is normal throughout the Province.Assam.   There has been no change in the situation  during the past week, except that thefirst attempt in  this Province to burn the  contents of a letter-box was  made  in  thedistrict of Sylhet.Bihar and Orissa.   The  Province  is  quiet.   One  new  order has  been  passed  under  section  4,Emergency Powers Ordinance, making a total of 12 in force.   No prosecutions have-been made for disobedience of such orders.   Total convictions up to 7th May, 6,303.Ajmer Merwara.   Political activity during the week has been insignificant.  Five arrests have beenmade under the ordinary law.From the Resident, Mysore.   The  situation  in Coorg is unchanged.  There have been no arrests in Bangalorethis week and the  general situation is very quiet.

</content>
</cab>
