<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/230/0 images: 102-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 0? HI3 BRITANNIC 1/AJESTY1 3 GOVERNMENT) .         COMMITTEE ON TRADE WITH RUSSIA.                  THIRD REPORT.                  Iatr o duet c ry.1.     On the 27th April 1952 (Cabinet 25(32&apos;  Conclusion 7);.the Cabinet had before their, our Second Report  (CP.  141(52))and adopted our view tbst the policy in regard to furthercredits for Russia ?an net so inseparably interlocked -with thequestion of the Commercial Agreement as to render necessary the postponement of a decision on the question of creditsuntil one could be taken on the Commercial Agreement.2,     On that occasion after a full discussion cf the questionof further credits, the Cabinet approved the suggestion  &quot;thatthe previous proposals for obtaining security  for bills  of over12 months should not be pressed., and that the  credits which falldue during the next 6 months, amounting to about  1,600,000should be replaced by fresh bills up to 10 months, on the under-standing that the duration of the bills should be shortened, nofar as possible&quot;.   (CP. 141 (52) paragraph 10).This decision was subject to the approval of the Chancellorof the Exchequer, which was subsequently given,  and to  the  rightof the President of the Board of Trade to re-opon at the  Cabinet0 H E 1.( 53).CAP I.N E Tothe larger proposals sex, out in hlie  Memorandum  (CP, 154(32));and was also without prejudice to the/
decision to be taken by the Cabinet on the question of thefuture of the Russian Trade Agreement,3,             On the 11th May, 1932 ( Cabinet 27(32)  Conclus-ion 2) the Cabinet had under consideration a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign affairs ( CP. 154(32)) relatingto the question of     Russian Propagandao   On this occasion the Cabinet agreed inter, alia that the Committee on Trade withRussia  -should be asked to report as soon as possible, and thequestion of propaganda should then be further considered.4.              In our Second Report we informed the Cabinet thathe denunciation of the Commercial Agreement and the restriction of imports from Russia gave rise to a number of questions, e.g.the legal position of the Soviet Trade Delegation in London;the probable financial and commercial effects of restrictingimports from Russia into the United Kingdom; and the valueof the Fisheries Agreements which were then under urgent examination by the Departments concerned.   We have no?/considered the results of this Departmental examination, and submit this further Report to the Cabinet.   For convenience of reference a copy of the Commercial Agreement of the 16thApril, 1930 is attached ( Appendix I).           DENUNCIATION OF THE COMMERCIAL AGREEMENT.5.         The Foreign Office have advised us that thisAgreement is perhaps more important from a political  than from a commercial standpoint; that its existence has had some  .effect as a stabilizing influence in Anglo-Russian relations,and that its cancellation would undoubtedly be represented bythe Soviet Government as a first step in some active anti-Soviet policy.   At the same time the Foreign Office agreethat these considerations are not of sufficient weight to
constitute the deciding factor, if the. cancellation, ofthe Agreement is required in the interests of the government&apos;s general commercial oolicy,6,          In our view the question whether theAgreement should be denounced or&apos; not is intimately con-neeted with the further question of the oolicy to be pursued and the objects to be attained by its denunciation-tion.   WE dc not agree with the view that the agreement should be terminated for purely political reasons, and weare satisfied that freedom of action as regardsnegotiation for commercial advantages, present and prospective, must be the governing considerations inany decision to be taken.    In this connection thequestion of future oolicy in regard to the applicationto Russia of import restrictions, is of first-class importance.7.          After summarising in the following paragraphs(i)  the advantages and disadvantages of denunciation ofthe Commercial Agreement;   (ii)  the probable effects of a restriction of imports from Russia, we  set cutfor the consideration cf the Cabinet our conclusions and recommendations.
        THE ADVrtITTAG53 and DlXvABTOTAGES OF . DEliUisCIATIQi-I OF THE                          COiflMERCIAL AGRKKJENT.vantages,   8.     The main objection to the Commercial Agreement from           the  point  of  view of  the United  Kingdom is that the  &apos;most           favoured nation&apos;  provisions contained in Article I lose           practically all effect  owing to  the Soviet monopoly  of           foreign  trade.    Thus Russia can exclude British goods from           the  Soviet Union  (by  the simple  process of not buying in           cur  market) whilst  we are bound  to admit Russian gcods into           the  United Kingdom  on exactly  the same terms  as goods from           any  other  country.           9.      If  the Agreement were cancelled the Government wouldbe free to apply to Russian imports any restrictions orquota schemes which may be part cf their policy, while theSoviet Government, who have already complete power todecide whether to buy in this market or not, would netderive - csryrfurther1    advantage from the cancellation ofthe most  favoured nation previsions.10.   It  fellows that if the policy of the Government should require the exclusion or restriction of any class ofRussian imports the denunciation of the agreement would benecessary.  This requires six months&apos;  notice,,11.   Similarly, if any attempt is to be made to secure,by agreement with the Soviet, that they should take more ofour goods and thus attain a more equal balance of Anglo-Russian trade, the Government would obviously be in a stronger position if they had their hands free to impose orto threaten restriction of Russian imports.  For negotiations on these lines the denunciation of the agreement would berequired.    The effects of a possible restriction ofRussian imports on the commercial interests of this country are dealt with in oaragraohs 20 to 22 below.
12-      In short the  advantages of denouncing theAgreement  are  (l)  that its  disappearance would, freeus from  the one  sided obligation of giving Russiamost  favoured  nation  terms  while we get  no commer-cial  advantages  in  return as  the Soviet  government can buy  in  any market at  their  discretion,  and ear-thus  discriminate against us, if they  so desire:(2)   that  we should secure  freedom to  negotiate at and. after  the  Ottawa  Conference,  e. g.  to takeArgentine in place  of Russian wheato        In  this connection we are informed  that at  a recent meeting the Ottawa Committee  of  the  Cabinetexamined the question of an Empire Vheat Quota and agreed inter alias-       &quot;that the question of quantitative restriction        or  complete prohibition, of  the importation        of Russian wheat into the United Kingdom must        depend on the decisions  to be reached by the        Cabinet on the general question of  trade with        Russia; that a jflecision^ n^thi^^question        before the Ottawa Conference was very ^im-        p o r tazrTT^p^.,,. ^j^osS^S^JL^TBST^^^^^^^        negotiations^there; and  that, in the event        of  -ffie&quot;&quot;&quot;C bTne-C^Se&quot;rlding  in favour of the        policy of prohibition or restriction of        the import of Russian wheat  into the        United Kingdom, no announcement of  that        policy should he made prior  to  the  Ottawa        Conference&quot;o        The import of Russian wheat  into the UnitedKingdom could only be prohibited or  restricted afterthe Commercial Agreement had ceased  to  operate^ &apos;,?esee no objection to the Ottawa Committee&apos;s  sugges-tion that if the Cabinet decide  to prohibit orrestrict the import of Russian wheat into thiscountry, that decision sho\ild be taken, but shouldon no account be published before the Ottav/aConference  opens.
 13.       The possible disadvantages of denouncing the agreement depend largely on the attitude which may be adopted by the Soviet Government and an accurate estimate is thus difficult., 14. (a) Shipping.   Article 3 of the Agreement provides for national treatment (with certain exceptions) in respect of shipping. The disappearance of this fir tide would leave the Soviet Government free to discriminate against British shipping. Whether they would do so or not would no doubt depend on whether they wished to continue to employ British tonnage, and on the extent to which they oould replace it from elsewhere.   It is also to be observed that avon whilst the agreement is in force there is no adequate uecurity against a decision of the Soviet Govern- mert to employ less British shipping should they wish to do so- 15. (b) Flshing Agr agreement^   If the Commer-1 cial Agreement is denounced;, we must assume as probable that the Soviet Government will, on their side, denounce the  temporary- Fisheries Agreement, which is also  termin- able at six months 1 notice.   The  object of thi
Agreement  was  to  secure  for  the British  fishing industry the right  to fish in  the  White  Sea  area up  tothe  three  mile limit.  The Russians  claim e  twelve mile limit., and. before the Agreement was  signed british vessels had only been able to  fish between the twelveand  three mile limits under  the protection of Britishcruisers-  The Agreement was well  received by theindustry,  and has worked well.   The value of the fisheries Agreement to British trawlers  is estimated atroughly , 100 s COO a ye arc   If it were denounced by theSoviet Government it might still be possible eitherto continue the fishing under  the protection of cruisers,as v/as done before the agreement was made, or to con-elude a new agreement on similar lines as part of afurther negotiation with the Soviet Government,.15..-  (c)  Legal positj on of  the Soviet Trade Delegation.We attach a Note by the Board  of Trade and the ForeignOffice (Appendix II) on  the  legal  position of the soviet trade Delegation in the event  of the denunciation ofthe Agreement.   It will be  seen that the effect ofcertain provisions of the Agreement  is &quot;tshat thereis someone available, against  whom proceedings can ifnecessary be instituted...  and in respect  of whom theRussian Government has agreed  to waive its immunity from proceedings-  Further,  there  is an  agreement thatcertain property of the Russian State shall be availableto answer  any  judgment obtained against  it.&quot;  It must,however., be noted that this  agreement to submit to thejurisdiction of the British  Court  is somewhat illusory,and  that in  the opinion  of the Attorney  General theSoviet could successfully  decline  to submit  to  the  jiiris-diction  of the Courts in relation/
t.-) execution on its property within the jurisdiction evenif it had submitted to the jurisdiction in an action andhad judgment given against ic.   The position as regardsthe effect of denunciation on existing obligations under-taken by the trade representative in accordance with thetrade agreement is discussed in the concluding paragraphof Appendix II,   A-s a matter of &quot;ingiish law, these obligations would not bt affected by the termination ofthe agreement, but in view of the fact that the guaranteesgiven by the trade representative would not be enforceablein British courts of law, if the Soviet Government, not-withstanding the terms of the agreement, claimed immunityin any proceedings, the change in the position from thestrictly legal point of view might not be very substan-          The  present Agreement includes provision forsecuring the Covenant of the  Soviet Government to meetthe obligations undertaken in this  country by Soviettrading organisations, such as Areas.   The export credits Guarantee Department&apos;s Advisory Committeeattach great importance to obtaining  the  securitythereby given.   The denunciation  of  the  present agreement  would, in  the absence  of  a  fresh  agreement,           .......                     . ....... :. .  ......                .covering  this  point,  remove machinery by  which,  inthe  case  of  future as distinct from existing obliga-tions,the  credit of  the Soviet Government  is pledged.
   17.    (d) British Claimants.   The British claimants against   Russia may he expected, to renew their proposal for a special   tax  on Russian goods for the benefit of the claimants.   18.    (e) Mqral and political pressure to prohibit imports.         The pressure to prohibit imports from Russia on moral   and  political grounds, e.g0, that they are the product of slave   labour will be renewed.   19.    (f) The Export Trade.   The effect of the denunciation   of the Commercial Agreement peruse on British exports is a   matter on which it is difficult to formulate a definite   opinion.   The Agreement as  such  is  of no practical value to*   British traders.  On the other hand  it may be noted that  the   declared policy of the Soviet Government is to place  their   orders, so far  as possible and other things being  equal,   with those countries which afford them what they consider   proper conditions for  their  trade organisation.    The main   requirement  of  the Soviet Government is, however,  credit, and   in the long  run it  is  probable  that  this factor will  be   the  determining one.-8-
PROBABLE EFFECTS OF A RESTRICTION OF Tr?OR?S FROI-.I RUSSIA.20.   We attach (Appendix III)  a Memorandum by the Beardof Trade on the probable effects of restriction of importsfrom Russia.   It is estimated that the true excess of purchases from Russia over sales to Russia, (after setting offinvisible exports of say,  5. ms.)amounts to about  15 ms.or  16 ms.  in each of the last two years.    The restriction ofimports from Russia by causing us to pay more in othermarkets for the seme goods, would have the effect ofincreasing the aggregate amount of our adverse trade balance;and this adverse reaction would be accentuated if as a resultof restriction the Soviet Government reduced the considerableorders which she now places with British industry.  Importsfrom Russia consist mainly of goods of kinds either notproduced at all, or not produced in sufficient quantitiesin this country.   The effect on the British industries concerned of restricting the import from Russia of certaincheap raw materials may be serious;  examples are givenin paragraphs 11-17 of the Memorandum of raw materials(timber, furskins, bristles, cotton, refined petroleum) theimport of which from Russia  is  of value to the Britishindustries concerned.   Cn the  other hand, the exclusion  ofRussian oil would be welcomed by the large British oil companies partly because it  would assist a rise of prices.The views in the Board of Trade Memorandum are summarisedas follows:-     &quot;It has been argued:-       (a)   That although cur trade with Russia shews a           substantial balance  &quot;adverse&quot; to the United
            Kingdom this does not  to an equivalent -ex-tent            affect our total  trade balance because Russian            funds accumulating in  this  country  are remitted            abroad to pay for Russian purchases elsewhere/here            and through their influence on the  rates of            exchange discourage imports into  this country            and stimulate exports.        (b)  That Russian produce imported into  this country            is in a large proportion of cases required to            supplement deficient or non-existent home            supplies, and if  it could not be  obtained  it            would be necessary to  increase our  imports from            other sources.        (c)  That the goods imported in  substitution for the            Russian supplies  would probably be  more expen-            sive, and that the cost not merely  of the            additional supplies but conceivably also of the            whole of our supplies  of particular kinds  of            goods might be increased with a consequent            additional strain upon the  sterling exchange.        (d)  That in some cases particular kinds or  qualities            of goods (e.g. bristles and fur  skins)  might  be            unobtainable.        (e)  That the rise of  prices of  certain  materials            and the inavailability of  supplies  would  injure            our export and re-export  trade.        (f)  That to this extent, and to the  extent  to  which            Russia  responded to the  restriction of our  im-            ports from her by reducing  the  considerable            orders which she  places with British industry            our trade balance would be  &quot;unfavourably&quot;            affected&quot;.These views, whilst constituting a useful note  of  warningas to the possible effects of restriction of  Soviet imports,do not, on balance, affect the conclusion which we havereached, namely, that denunciation will, by freeing our hands for negotiation with a monopolist purchaser, enable us to secure an adjustment of the trade balance, and this inthe direction of increased exports from  this country.                         -10- &apos;
 21.     The probable effect of restricting the sale of Russian commodities in the United Kingdom on the Soviet Governments ability and readiness to meet its outstanding obligations in this country and in Germany is examined in  the attached Memorandum by the Export Credits Guarantee Department (Appendix IV).   The Department estimate that these obligations may amount in the aggregate to about  120 as, of which in 1932, 1933 and 1934  14 ms. is due to Great Britain and no less than  67 ms. to Germany.   The decline in the value of her exports has made it  increasingly difficult for Russia to meet her bills for past purchases, and her payments in cash and on shore credit as she has no other means of  payment than the proceeds of what she sells abroad.   The situation is  very obscure, but on the whole the Department feel that while Russia is likely to continue to meet her obligations, the margin between solvency and default for  some time to come will probably be very narrow, even if  no new difficulties arise.   During the last three years Great Britain has taken about 30ii of Russian exports, and as Russia would probably experience great difficulty in finding alterna- tive markets it seems clear that  substantial restric- tion of her sales by Great Britain would place the Russian Government in serious financial difficulties, the extent of which would probably depend on the nature and extent of the restrictions.    Thile special action by the British  Government in the  direction of a partial exclusion of Russian products would probably leave-&quot;illrr
S5Russia in a position to meet some of hercommitments, it must he borne in mind thatsuch action if carried very far, wouldprovide the Russian Governiaent with a goodexcuse for not meeting bills due in theUnited Kingdom,   In the penultimate paragraphof the Memorandum attention is drawn to thevery serious injury which would be sustained by British financial interests if, as aresult of far reaching exclusion of Russianproducts from the United Kingdom, the Sovietbecame unable to meet their German obligations,,22c   In conclusion, the Department advise that the present moment is not unfavourablefor exacting concessions from Russia withincertain limits, those limits being set by russia&apos;s financial position,.,   In the Depart-ment view it is Impossible for Russia to start buying in the United Kingdom for cashon any considerable scale;  having regard toher existing commitmentc there seems to theDepartment  t-o be no escape from the conclusionthat exports to Russia on any large scale forsome cime to come can only be conducted onthe basis of some credit-   If Russia is toobtain such credits she may reasonably beasked to make certain concessions,
          CONCLUSIONS AND RSCO-^NPATIONS.iation    23.      After  carefully  reviewing the considerations  &apos;cial      summarised in  the  foregoing paragraphs, we have reached  theento          conclusion that  the Temporary Commercial Agreement of 16th          April.  1930  should he  denounced forthwith, and we accordingly          recommend that nntiee  should he given under Article 7 to          terminate that Agreement on the expiration of six months          from the date  of  the notice.  In our view it  is Imperative,          for the reasons  given  in paragraphs 8 to 12 yf this Report .          that the Government  should regain full  liberty ofaction- to          exclude&quot; or restrict  any kind of Russian imports and/to          negotiate on an even footing with the Soviet  Government      j                          -          with a view,  If possible, to securing a more  equal balance          of Anglo-Russian Trade.   The first and.  essential  step          towards the attainment of these objects is  the denunciation          of the Agreements          240      We have not  overlooked the fact that  the Agreement          has had a stabilising influence on Anglo-Russian political          relations, and that  it contains some provisions  of value to          this countryi   we have had regard to the disadvantages which          cancellation of the  Agreement must necessarily entail, and          we have given full consideration to the representations          contained, in the memoranda by the Beard of Trade and the          Export Credits Guarantee Department as  to  probable  effects          of a restriction of imports from Russia consequent  on the          denunciation ef the Agreement.,  On balance,  however,  we are          satisfied that taking a long viewy the  commercial and          economic interests of the country will  best be served by          the disappearance of the present agreement                                   13.
tations of   25.      We must,  however,  warn, the  Cabinet  that resultsnunciation   denunciation of the Agreement will  probably give  rise  inbepointed.     many quarters to  expectations for which,  in our view,            there is no justification and which  cannot possibly be             realised.             Neither the Board of Trade nor the Export  Credits  Guarantee             Department dissent from the  view that the Agreement should             be denounced.   But &quot;both  these Departments have warned us             of the difficulties and risks which will  be involved if             a policy of sevore restriction of imports from Russia is             adopted.6 Q         26.     If  the Cabinet adopt  our recommendation that thee ofnation      Agreement should forthwith be denounced, the questionre ernent,            arises as to the precise nature of the notice which should            be given to the Soviet Authorities.    It has been  suggested            to us that  as it is clearly desirable that some kind of            treaty obligation should govern Anglo-Soviet trade relations            it would be well to endeavour to arrange  that the  Agreement            should, when denounced, run on from  month  to month subject            to one month&apos;s notice.   It is represented that this would            be all the  more desirable in view ef the  fact that            negotiations for  a fresh agreement could not in any case            be instituted until after the conclusion of  the Ottawa            Conferonoe, and that, if the  notice  terminating the            Agreement is given at once, there would clearly not be
        sufficient time between the end of the Conference and (say)        1st December next  within which to  negotiate  a new  arrangement.        It has also been urged that -until  the  new trade  policy vis a        vis Russia has  been definitely  formulated,  it would be best        to allow the existing Agreement to  run on.        27.      We realise the force of these considerations, but we        think  that the  Soviet Authorities  are  much more  likely to come        speedily to terms if a plain six months notice  is given  to        terminate the Agreement,  with no indication that any extension        of time will be conceded.   We  fear that the  proposal to accom-        pany denunciation with an arrangement  which allowed the  Agreement        to run on.month after month would be open to  damaging criticism        and would give  the Soviet authorities  endless opportunities  for        displaying their mastery of the arts of procrastination  and        evasion.        28.      We recommend, therefore,  that the notice should be  one        to terminate the Agreement at  the  end.  of six  months without  any        addition or qualification.   In order, however,  to  provide against        the contingency that it may be  in  our  interests to  extend  the        Agreement temporarily after the date of its expiration,  we re-        commend that the representatives of His Majesty&apos;s Government        who will be concerned with any  negotiations for a fresh  agree-        ment,  should have discretion to concede, if they think necessary,        a temporary extension of the Agreement.jresh    29.      We are satisfied that  the negotiation  of a new  Anglo- iement aid be  Russian Trade Agreement is in the  best interests of the  country, otiated.        and we recommend that the undertaking  of such negotiations        should be authorised if and when opportunity  offers. Ottawa 30.      We draw the attention of  the  Cabinet to the conclusion committee&apos; s elusion of the Ottawa Committee  auoted in paragraph  12 of this  Report. the sub- t of    If the Cabinet  accept our recommendation regarding the si an at Imports the ted                                 15. ECdom.
denunciation of the Agreement,  it will then, he open to theCabinet to determine their policy in regard to the prohibitionof rentriction of the import 3f Russian wheat into the UnitedKingdom.,  We cote that if the Cabinet decide In favour of apolicy of prohibition er restriction, the Ottawa committee recommend that no announcement of that policy should be madeprior to the Ottawa Conference, axid we concur in thisrocommendati ohoct onaganda,er.un-ion cfemento310     TFe have endeavoured to form some estimate of whateffect denunciation cf the Commercial Agreement will be likelyto have cn other aspects of -Anglo-Soviet relations such, forexample, as the problem of Russian propaganda..   It is doubtfulwhether it would have any substantial effect, though with a free hand in trade matters we might be able by threats ofeconomic pressure to induce the Soviet Government to exercisemore effective control over organisations, such as the Third.International.  In any case, we arc agreed that denunciation of the Agreement cannot worsen the position as regards the propaganda issue,.32.     Our recommendations may be summarised as follows z-        (l) The Temporary Commercial Agreement of 16th            April, 1930* should be denounced forthwith            by moans of a notice to be given under            Article 7 to terminate that Agreement            on tho expiration of six months from the date            of the notice*(2)  The notice should be one to terminate the  Agreement at the end of six months,  without    any addition or qualifieatlon.    The    representatives of His Majesty1a Government    concerned with any negotiations for a fresh    agreement should have discretion to concede    a temporary extension of the Agreement if this    is in our interests.  The fact  that this    discretion has been given should, however,    &quot;be kept secret.
       (3) The negotiation of a fresh Anglo-Russian           Trade Agreement is in the best  interests           of the country, and the undertaking of           negotiations should be authorised if arad           when opportunity offers.       (4) If the Cabinet accept our recommendation           regarding the denunciation of the Agreement,           it will then be open to the  Cabinet to           determine their policy in regard  to the           prohibition cr restriction of the import           of Russian wheat into the United  Kingdom.           We note that if the Cabinet  decide in favour           of a policy of prohibition or restriction,  the           Ottawa Committee recommend that no announce-           ment of that policy should be made prior  to           the Ottawa Conference, and we concur in this           recommendation.                ^      J.H  onxo       (5) It is doubtful whether denunciation of the           Commercial Agreement will have  any substantial           effect as regards such aspects  of Anglo-           Soviet obligation as propaganda, though with           a free hand in trade matters, we  might be           able by threats of economic  pressure, to           induce the Soviet Government to exercise           more effective control over  organisations           such as the Third International.   In any           case we are agreed that denunciation of the           Agreement cannot worsen the  position as           regards the propaganda issue.33.     The Chancellor of the Exchequer was  unable to  be present at the Meeting at which the recommendations  embodied in this Report were adopted.  It has not been possible since that Meeting to ascertain Mr. Chamberlain&apos;s  views in regardto these recommendations, and we suggest that before action is taken on any decisions which may be  reached by  the  Cabineton this Report, the assent of the Chancellor of the  exchequer to those decisions should be obtained.                            Signed on behalf of the  Committee                                     JOHN  SIMON                              ACTING  CHAIRMAN.Whitehall Gardens, S.V.1,30th  May, 1933.
APPENDIX  I.         Treaty Series No. 19 (1930)  Temporary  Commercial               Agreement                     between HIS  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT   IN        THE  UNITED  KINGDOM                     and theGOVERNMENT  OF  THE   UNION  OF    SOVIET  SOCIALIST  REPUBLICS               London, April 16, 1930       Presented by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs          to Parliament by Command of His Majesty                     LONDON: PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICETo be purchased directly from II.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses    Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120, George Street, Edinburgh;        York Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;               15, Donegall Square West, Belfast;                 or through any Bookseller.                    .,  x93oCmd. 3552            Pr&apos;ce 2d&apos; Net
Temporary   Commercial   Agreement   between   His    Majesty&apos;s Government  in the  United Kingdom  and    the  Government  of the Union  of Soviet  Socialist    Republics.                    London, April  16,  1980.   His  Majesty&apos;s  Government in the United  Kingdom of GreatBritain  and Northern  Ireland and  the  Government of the Union.of Soviet Socialist Republics, being mutually desirous to conclude assoon as  possible a  formal  Treaty of Commerce  and  Navigationbetween the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Irelandand the  Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, have meanwhile agreedupon the following temporary Agreement to serve as a modus vivendipending the conclusion of such a Treaty.                          ARTICLE I.   For the purpose of  developing and strengthening the trade rela-lions between  the  United Kingdom of Great Britain and NorthernIreland and the Union  of Soviet Socialist Republics, the ContractingParties agree that, without prejudice to any more favourable provi-sions contained below, all facilities,  rights  and privileges which inthe United Kingdom and the Union of  Soviet Socialist Republicsrespectively are or  may be  accorded with  respect to trade to  the subjects or citizens of any other foreign State or to  juridical personsincluding companies constituted under the laws of  such State or tothe property of such subjects,  citizens or juridical persons includingcompanies shall be  extended reciprocally  to citizens or juridical persons  including  companies of  the Union of Soviet Socialist  Re-publics and to British subjects, British protected persons or juridical persons  including companies of the United Kingdom respectively andto their  property.   The natural produce and manufactures of  theUnited Kingdom shall  enjoy in  the Union of Soviet Socialist  Re-publics and the natural produce  and manufactures of the Union ofSe-viet Socialist Republics shall enjoy in the  United Kingdom, all thefacilities, rights and  privileges which are at  present or may be here-after accorded to the natural produce and manufactures of any other foreign country, in all  that relates to the prohibition and the restric-tion of imports and exports, customs duties and charges, transport,warehousing, drawbacks and excise.    Nothing in the  present Agreement shall  apply to     (a)  the special  provisions relating to trade contained in treaties          which the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics has con-          cluded, or ma3^ conclude, hereafter with  those States, the          entire territory of which on the 1st August, 1914, formed          in all respects an  integral part  of the  former  Russian          Empire  or with the continental border States in Asia;
8102   (b) the  rights which have been accorded or may be accorded to         any third country forming part of a customs union with         the Union of Soviet Socialist Eepublies;   (c) the  privileges which the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics         has accorded, or  may accord,   to  border States with         respect  to  local trade between  the  inhabitants of the         frontier zones.   NOTE. The  expression  &quot;British protected persons&quot;  in thisAgreement  is  understood  to  mean  persons  belonging  to any territory under His Majesty&apos;s protection or suzerainty or in respectof which a Mandate has  been  accepted by His  Majesty.   It  isunderstood, however, that the stipulations of Article 1 do not applyto persons  belonging to any such territory to which the present agreement  is not extended in  accordance  with the  provisions  ofArticle 5.                           ARTICLE 2.   1. In view of the fact that,  by virtue of the laws of the  Unionof Soviet  Socialist Republics, the foreign  trade of the  Union is  aState  monopoly,  His  Majesty&apos;s  Government   in   the   UnitedKingdom  agree  to accord  to  the Government of  the  Union  of soviet Socialist Republics the right to establish in  London a  TradoDelegation, consisting of the Trade Representative of the  Unionof Soviet  Socialist Republics and his  two deputies,  forming partof the Embassy  of the Union of Soviet Socialist  Republics.   2.  The  head  of  the  Trade  Delegation shall be  the  TradeRepresentative of the Union of Soviet Socialist  Republics in theUnited Kingdom.  He and his two  deputies  shall, by  virtue ofparagraph   1  of  the  present  Article,  be  accorded  all diplomaticprivileges and immunities, and immunity shall attach to the officesoccupied by the Trade  Delegation  (5th Floor, East Wing, BushHouse, Aldwych, London) and  used exclusively  for the purposedefined in  paragraph 3 of the present Article.  No member  of thestaff of the Trade Delegation, other than the Trade representative and his two  deputies, shall enjoy  any privileges  or  immunitiesother  than those which  are, or may be, enjoyed  in  the  UnitedKingdom by officials of the State-controlled trading organisations of other countries.    3. The  functions of the Trade Delegation shall be     (a)  to &quot;facilitate  and encourage  the development of trade and           commerce  between the United Kingdom and  the  Union           of Soviet Socialist Republics;    (b)  to  represent the interests of the Union of Soviet Socialist           Republics  in  all that  pertains  to  the  foreign trade  of           the Union, and to control, regulate, and carry on such           trade  with, the United Kingdom  for and on  behalf  of           the  Union of  Soviet  Socialist Republics.    4. The Trade  Delegation  acting  in respect  to trade for and on behalf  of the Union of Soviet Socialist  Republics, the Govern-    3362 Wt.- 3M 4/30 F.O.P. 20955
 merit of  the  latter will assume responsibility  for  all transactions lawfully concluded in the United Kingdom by the Trade Represen- tative  or by  persons duly  authorised  by him.   The Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics will not,  however, accept any responsibility for the  acts of  State  economic  organisations which,  under the laws of the  Union of Soviet Socialist  Republics, are  exclusively responsible for their  own acts,  except in  cases where responsibility  for such acts has been clearly  accepted by the Trade Representative, acting  for  and  on behalf  of  the  Govern- ment of the Union of Soviet  Socialist Republics.    5.   The names of the Trade Representative and of the persons empowered to represent him shall  be periodically published in the &apos;&apos; Board of Trade Journal&apos;&apos; and in addition shall in other ways be clearly made known  to the  public.   The  authority of these persons to represent the Trade Delegation shall continue until such time as notice to the contrary has been similarly published.    6.   Any questions which may arise  in  respect of commercial transactions entered into in  the United Kingdom by  the Trade Dele- gation shall be  determined by the Courts of the United kingdom in&apos; accordance with  the laws thereof.    7.  The property of  the  Union of Soviet Socialist  Republics in the United Kingdom shall  be subject to such  measures  as maylawfully  be taken to give effect to  the  Orders of the Courts of theUnited  Kingdom, in so far as these Orders have been issued inconnexion with transactions  referred to in paragraph 6, unless it isproperty which,  according to international law, is immune from such measures as being necessary for the exercise of the rights of  Statesovereignty or for the official functions of the diplomatic or consular representatives of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.                           ARTICLE 8.    British vessels and their cargoes and passengers and vessels of theUnion of Soviet Socialist Republics and their cargoes and passengersshall enjoy in the  ports and territorial waters of the  Union of soviet socialist. Republics  and of  the United Kingdom respectively, thesame rights, privileges and  facilities as are enjoyed, or may be en-joyed hereafter, by national vessels, their cargoes  and passengers,or the vessels of the most favoured foreign country and their  cargoesand passengers.    The provisions of this Article do not extend to the coasting trade.The Contracting Parties reserve the right to limit to national  ships the coasting trade between  ports on the same coast.   In regard totrade between ports not on the same coast they undertake to accord to the ships of each  other treatment not less favourable than thataccorded to the ships of any other foreign country.    The provisions of the present Article  shall not extend to     (a) The application of special laws for the safeguarding, renewal          and development  of  the national merchant fleet.    (b) Privileges granted to marine sports societies.
    (c) Port services, including pilotage; towage and life-saving and          maritime assistance.    (d) Navigation on  inland waters closed to foreign  vessels  in          general, even though  such navigation  may be open  to          the vessels of limitrophe States.    NOTE 1. Nothing  in this Article shall be deemed to confer onthe vessels of either Party the right to carry on fishing operations in the territorial waters of the other,  or  to land  their catches  inthe ports of the other, nor shall it  entitle British  vessels to claimany privileges  which  are,  or may  be, accorded by the Union  of soviet Socialist Republics to the fishing fleets of countries situatedon  the Arctic Ocean.    NOTE 2. Nothing  in this Article shall affect the right of either party to apply regulations in accordance with its  national legisla-tion for the transportation of immigrants, emigrants and pilgrims.    NOTE 3. The provisions  of  the present Article do not applyto ships registered at the  ports of His Majesty&apos;s self-governingDominions and  to their cargoes and passengers  unless  and untilthe present Agreement is extended to them in the manner provided in Article 4.                           ARTICLE 4.   The provisions of the present Agreement may by mutual agrce-ment be extended with any modifications agreed  upon to  any  ofHis Majesty&apos;s self-governing  Dominions  (including any  mandated territories administered by  the Governments  of such Dominions)or to India, by means of  an  Exchange  of  Notes  between theGovernment  of  the  Union  of Soviet Socialist  Republics and theGovernment of any such Dominion  or of India.                           ARTICLE 5.   The provisions of the present Agreement may also be extendedon  condition  of  reciprocity  to  any of  His  Majesty&apos;s colonies,possessions   or   protectorates  or  to   any  mandated   territoryadministered by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdomif a  notification to that effect is  given to the Government  of theUnion of Soviet Socialist  Republics by His Majesty&apos;s ambassador at Moscow  or, in his absence, by His Majesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires.   The Contracting Parties agree that in case a notification is madeby His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Moscow (or,  in  his absence, byHis  Majesty&apos;s  Charge d&apos;Affaires)  extending,  in  accordance withthe  provisions of the  foregoing  paragraph,  the  present  agreement to any of His Majesty&apos;s colonies, possessions,  or  protectorates  orto any mandated territory  administered by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in the United  Kingdom,  the trading  organisations  of theUnion of Soviet Socialist Republics  shall be accorded the right  tosend to the respective  colony, possession, protectorate  or mandated territory,  agents, who shall  be acceptable to the  government concerned,  for the purpose of carrying out the commercial transaction-
tions  of  the  Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in such colony,possession, protectorate or mandated territory.   It is understood that any such agent will in all cases be subjectto the ordinary law relating to  aliens in the colony,  possession,protectorate or mandated territory in  which he  resides and  willnot be entitled to enjoy any diplomatic  or consular privileges orimmunities.                           ARTICLE 6.   So long as in  any territory referred to in Articles 4 or 5  whichis not bound by  the present Agreement  the  natural produce  and manufactures  of  the  Union of  Soviet   Socialist  Republics  are accorded treatment as favourable as  that accorded  to  the naturalproduce  and  manufactures  of  any  other foreign  country,  thenatural produce and manufactures of such territory shall enjoy inthe Union  oE Soviet Socialist Republics complete  and unconditionalmost-favoured-nation  treatment.   At  the  same time, however, theGovernment  of  the  Union  of Soviet  Socialist Republics  reserves to itself  tho right to  denounce this Article at any time in respectof any particular Dominion  or of India.                           ARTICLE 7.   The present Agreement  comes into force on this day and shall remain in  force until the coining into  force of a  commercial  treaty between  the United Kingdom and the Union of Soviet Socialist Re-publics, subject, however, to the right of either Party at any time togive notice to the other to terminate the Agreement, which shall thenremain in force until the expiration of six months from  the date onwhich such notice is given.   So far as  concerns   any  of His  Majesty&apos;s  self-governingDominions, India or  any colony,  possession, protectorate  or man-dated territory in respect of which notes  have been exchanged in virtue of Article 4 above or in respect  of which notice of the appli-cation of this Agreement has been given in virtue of Article 5  above,the Agreement may be terminated separately by either Party at theend of the sixth month or at any time subsequently  on  six months&apos;notice to that effect being  given  either  by  or  to His  Majesty&apos;ambassador at Moscow or,  in his absence, by or to His Majesty&apos;charge d&apos;Affaires.   In witness  whereof the undersigned,  duly authorised for  thatpurpose, have signed the  present Agreement,  and  have  affixedthereto their seals.   Done in duplicate  at London in the English language the six-teenth day of April, 1930.   A translation shall be made  into the Russian language as  soonas possible and agreed upon between the Contracting Parties.   Both texts shall then be considered authentic for all purposes.                           CL.S.)   ARTHUR  HENDERSON.                           (L.S.)   G.  SOKOLNLKOFF.
                          Protocol.   In concluding the present  Agreement the Contracting  parties are animated by the intention to eliminate from their economic relations all forms of discrimination.   They accordingly agree that,so far as relates to  the treatment accorded by each Party  to thetrade with the other, they will be. guided in regard to the purchase and sale of goods, in regard to the employment of shipping and inregard to all similar matters by commercial and financial considera-tions  only  and,  subject  to  such considerations,  will adopt  nolegislative or administrative action of such a nature as to place thegoods, shipping, trading organisations and trade  in general of theother Party in any respect, in a position  of inferiority  as comparedwith the goods, shipping  and trading organisations of any  other foreign  country.   In accordance with the  above principle, trade between theUnited Kingdom  and the  Union  of Soviet Socialist Kepublics shallbe eligible for consideration on the same basis as trade between theUnited Kingdom and other foreign countries in connexion with anylegislative or administrative measures which are  or may be  takenby  His   Majesty&apos;s Government  in  the   United  Kingdom  for the granting of credits to facilitate such trade.  That  is to say, that in considering any given transaction, regard shall be had to financialand commercial considerations only.   Done at  London  the 16th April, 1930.                                    ARTHUR  HENDERSON.                                    G.  SOKOLNIKOEF.                    Additional Protocol.   With reference to paragraph 6 of Article 2, it is understood thatthe privileges and immunities conferred on the head  of the trade delegation and his two deputies by paragraph 2 of Article 2 of thepresent  Agreement shall  not be claimed in  connexion  with any proceedings before the Courts of the United Kingdom arising out ofcommercial transactions  entered  into in the  United  Kingdom bythe. Trade Delegation of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.   Done at London the 16th April, .1930.                                   ARTHUR  HENDERSON.                                   G.  SOKOLNIKOEF.
Declarations  by  His  Majesty&apos;s Principal  Secretary of                State  for Foreign  Affairs.   At the instance of and on behalf of  His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the Union of South Africa, I hereby declare that the Union ofSouth Africa is  excluded in  all respects  from the  operation ofArticles  4 and 6 of the Temporary Commercial Agreement signed this day between His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdomand the  Government of the  Union of Soviet Socialist republics.                                  ARTHUR HENDERSON.   London,  April 16, 1980.   At the instance of and  on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the Irish Free  State, I hereby declare that the Irish Free state is excluded in all respects from the operation  of Articles 4 and 6 ofthe Temporary Commercial Agreement signed this day between HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom and the Governmentof the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.                                  ARTHUR  HENDERSON.   London, April 16, 1980.    Declaration  by the  Ambassador of the  Union of                Soviet Socialist Republics.   At the moment of signing the Commercial Agreement betweenthe Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist  Republics on theone hand, and His Majesty&apos;s Government in the  United kingdom on the other, I am instructed by the Government of the Union of soviet Socialist Republics to make the following declaration :       &apos;&apos; The Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics   declares that it reserves to itself the right of the Union of Soviet   Socialist  Republics to all vessels of the former Russian fleet,   both military and merchant, which were either the property of   the Russian Government or were subject to nationalisation  by   Soviet law and which were seized abroad without the knowledge   and consent of the Soviet Government or in any  other way   escaped  actual  transference to  Soviet Government  organisa-   tions.&quot;                                        G. SOKOLNIKOFF.   London,  April 16, 1930.
BRET,(32)  10.APPENDIX II.              CABINET,    COMMITTEE 03&apos;-! TRADE WITH RUSSIA..          The legal position                 of    THE SOVIET TRADE delegation in the event of the denunciation of the  TEMPORARY -COMMERCIAL AGREEMENT .      Note fry the Board of Trade and the Foreign Office.     1.  By Article 7 either Party nay at any time give notice to the other to terminate the Agreement, hut, it is providedthat it shall then remain in force until the expiration of six months from the date on which such notice is given.     2D   So soon as a denunciation takes effect the reciprocalmost-favoured-nation provisions of Articles 1 and 3 relating tothe international trade of the Parties and to the persons and property of their respective subjects, citizens  or juridical persons including companies and to their vessels., cargoes and passengers, cease, and it would then be open to either Partyto impose trade restrictions with regard to the other, or to discriminate against the persons or property of each othersnationals.     3.   All the diplomatic privileges and immunities accorded to the Trade Representative, or his two deputies, and to the offices occupied fry the Trade Delegation (5th Floor, East Wing,Bush House5 Aldwych, London), and used exclusively for thepurposes mentioned in paragraph 3 of Article 2 (whereby thefunctions of the Trade Delegation are defined) would also ceaseexcept in so far as the persons to whom privilege and immunitiesare afforded under the Trade agreement, may, notwithstanding thatthat Agreement has terminated, be entitled to immunity under theordinary principles of international law as applied fry English Courts
     4.   The remaining provisions of Article  2  must  be  con-sidered in connection with the later paragraph of the Protocol,which provides that, as regards those Export  Credit  facilities,trade between the United Kingdom and the U.3.S.R.  shall  be  eligiblefor consideration on the same basis as trade  between the UnitedKingdom and other foreign countries.   If the  Agreement  wereterminated this obligation would no longer exist.          Paragraphs 3, 4 and 5 of Article Z  relate  to tradetransactions between the two countries, and,  while there is aprovision that the U.S.S.R. will assume responsibility for  alltransactions lawfully concluded in the United Kingdom by theTrade Representative, paragraph 4 goes on to  state definitely that the U.S.S.R. will not be responsible for the acts of Stateeconomic organisations (e.g. Arcos Selosojus), which, under the laws of the U.S.S.R. are exclusively responsible for their  ownacts, except in cases where responsibility for such  acts hasbeen clearly accepted by the Trade Representative acting forand on behalf of the Government of the U.S.S.R.          In consequence of that declaration  on the  part of soviet Government, letters of guarantee signed by the TradeRepresentative on its behalf have been required by the export credits Guarantee Department in all export transactions, whereit has given any guarantee to the Exporter,  except in some  fewspecial cases where the undertaking by the Trade Representativehas been endorsed on a Bill of Exchange itself.          If the Agreement were terminated,  the covenant ofthe U.S.S.R. to honour obligations undertaken on its behalfby the Trade Representative would not be available in respect  ofany transaction entered into after the denunciation  of theAgreement became operative.
     5.  In addition to that covenant provision is made inparagraphs 6 and 7 pi] Article 2 that any question arising in respect of a commercial transaction entered, into in theUnited Kingdom by the Trade Representative shall &quot;be deter-mined by the Courts of the United Kingdom in accordancewith the laws thereof? and that the property of the U0S,S^E,in the United Kingdom shall be subject to &quot;such measures asmay lawfully be taken to give effect to the Orders of theCourts of the United Kingdom, in so far as these orders have been (sic) issued in connection with&quot; the before men-tioned commercial transactions, unless according to -inter-national law that property i!Is immune from such measures as being necessary for the exercise of the rights of State-sovereignty or for the functions of the diplomatic or consulrepresentatives of the U030S0R.&quot;     The effect of these pro vie ions is that the &quot;re is some-one available, against- whom proceedings can if necessary be instituted, and in respect of whom the  -Russian Govern-ment has agreed to waive its immunity from proceedings.Further, there is an agreement that certain property of theRussian State shall be available to answer any judgmentobtained against it.     This agreement to submit to the jurisdiction of BritishCourt is however somewhat illusory.  In October 1930 the attorney-General advised that, as  an agreement to submit isnot equivalent to an actual submission^ it would still &quot;beopen to the U.S0S^R. to refuse to  subiait  to the juried!c-tion, notwithstanding their general undertaking in Article 2to the  contrary.   He also advised that as the lav/ stands atpresent, and  subject to what the House of Lords might decideif the  case were taken so far, the UoS0S0H0 could-o-
     successfully decline to submit to the jurisdiction of the     Courts in relation to execution on the property of the     UoSoSoEo within the  jurisdiction even if it had submitted     to the jurisdiction  in an action and had judgment given     against it.          Vhile, therefore , according to English municipal law,     it is still open to  the Russian Government to claim immun-     ity from proceedings here, such action on their part would     clearly5. so long as  the Commercial Agreement is in force.     be in broach of their international obligation to His     Majesty&apos;s Government, who could take the apjjropriate dip-     lomatic action in respect of such breach.          6.  There remains the question of how the denunciation     of the agreement wo\ild affect existing obligations under-     taken by the trade representative in accordance with the     trade agreemen to  As a matter of English law, these obliga-     tions would not be affected by the termination of the     agreement, but in view of the fact that the guarantees given     by the trade representative would not be enforceable in     British courts of lav, if the U0S0ScRo, notwithstanding the     terms of the agreement, claimed immunity in any proceedings,     the change in the position from the strictly legal point of     view might not be very substantial3  On the other hand it must     be remembered that hitherto the Russian authorities have not     defaulted in their obligations and it may be that so long-     as the. agreement exists they will implement the guarantees     which ,i,have been given; if, on the other hand, we terminate     the agreement, it may -well.be that they would refuse to     submit to the jurisdiction of British courts in airy action     on those guarantees.PORE I GIT OFFICE.     9th Hay, 1952.       i :                         -4-
                                                                 In r\                                    .....                          V  DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY  OB&apos; HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.                                                    COPY NO.   8 9                        COMMITTEE ON TRADE  wITH RUSSIA.11.                       Memorandum &quot;by the Board of Trade.           Probable Effects of  a Restriction  of Imports  from Russia.   1. The purpose of this memorandum is to consider theprobable effects on industry and trade in this country of restrictions on imports from Russia.   2. It will be convenient to begin with a short summaryof the value of imports from Russia and exports to russian each of the last three years, distinguishing the principalolasses of goods.   A more detailed statement relating to our trade with Russia.is annexed to this memorandum (Appendix A).1		1929.	1 1 1930. ;	1931.i		 &apos; 000	1  f000 i	 &apos;000Imports from Russia into	United		!	&apos; Kingdom:			I &apos; 1	food, Drink and Tobacco	n		i 1			7,340	. 13,235 J			6,894	12,815 j	, Raw Materials, etc. -			i j			12,253	i 13,244 1 J	Not		10,023	! 11,053 i	yet			* !	availableManufactured goods, etc.	-		I i T			6,895	j 7,706			6,190	I 7,0191: i	, All Articles -			! i			126,487	&apos; 34,235 i	,32,179		!23,106	; 30,887 -	(not		I--	T	availableExports (United Kingdom	gopdsl	I V; 1	i :	i to Russia.		1	! !	! J&apos;ood, Drink and Tobacco		25	1,729 ;	421		622	i 408	349i Manufactured goods, etc		&apos; 3,046	! 4,602 J	6,443		- 3,743	; 6,772 , &apos;. !&apos; - &apos;	7,291! Exports (imported Goods) to				1 Russia:			I :	I I!,ood, Drink and Tobacco		! 822	428 :	1 Not		542	851 I	1 yet! Manufactured goods, etc		i 1,435	1,240 i	) available		; 2,799	; 2,519	1,923i : ! 1 i				
   3. These figures relate to goods consigned to this country from Russia and goods exported from the United Kingdom toRussia;  and they thus take no account of any indirect tradewith Russia through third countries, as to which no information is available.   4c Retained imports from Russia showed an excess in valueover exports of United Kingdom and imported goods to Russiaamounting to  516,564,000 in 1929 and  221,596,000 in 1930.Information as to the value in 1931 of retained ii.ports as distinct from total imports is not yet available but it seems likely that the corresponding figure for 1931 will be approximately .320,000,000.   5. In considering the true excess of purchases from Russiaover sales to Russia a deduction must he made from thesefigures on account of &quot;invisible&quot; exports represented byfreight earnings of British shipping in the Russian trade, by insurance and other items.   The amount of these items hasbeen put at roughly  5,000,000.   There remains an excess of purchases over sales amounting to say  15,000,000 or  16,000,00fin each of the last two years.   6. This &quot;adverse&quot; balance of trade with Russia consequent on the fact that our sales to that country fell short of our purchases from her, is not to be regarded as independent ofthe balance of our trade with the rest of the world and merelyadding to an adverse balance with them which might in anycase exist.   Although Russia accumulates balancer, in london on her trade with this country, these balances are not investedhere but are remitted to other countries to pay for Russianpurchases in those countries.   The process of remitting the balances tends to depreciate the sterling exchanges,  and this in turn tends to check imports into the United Kingdom and to stimulate exports.   7. Moreover, if imports from Russia were restricted to
Hithe amount of our exports  to  Russia  (at whatever l&apos;..vel these mightbe) the imports thus excluded would  have  to be  obcained in aiarge proportion of cases  from other external  sources of supply.Tnis would Involve purchase as a  rule at  a higher cost, so that alarger aggregate sum would be expended on obtaining the samequantity of goods or the same aggregate sum would purchase onlya reduced quantity.   It should be noted  also  that higher pricesmight be charged not merely for the  supplies wnich we shouldotherwise have Imported from Russia  but to a certain  extent inrespect of the whole of our supplies of goods  of the  classesaffected, as foreign suppliers would no longer  have to meet thecompetition of cheap Russian goods in the United Kingdom market.So. far as we had to pay more for goods hitherto imported fromRussia, the strain upon the sterling exchange would be increased.It is of course assumed that by a system  of  certificates of origin, indirect Imports of Russian goods through other countries would be prevented,     8. The effects upon our industry and trade of excludingRussian goods might clearly be considerable.    They would be serious in so far as particular kinds or  qualities of goods re-quired by British industries and hitherto imported from Russia,might cease to be obtainable.   Our&apos; export  trade  in  certain branches might be impeded, and to that extent  our trade balance would be affected in an &quot;unfavourable&quot; sense.   And were russia to respond to the restriction of our imports  from her by reducingthe considerable orders wuich she places  with British industrythis adverse reaction would be accentuated.     9. Turning to consider in some  detail  the  nature of our trade with Russia, it may be observed that  imports from Russiaconsist predominantly of goods (mainly food,  raw  materials andrefined petroleum) of kinds which are either not  produced at all  cnot produced  in  sufficient quantities in  this  country.
    10. With, regard to imports of food,  little  detailedcomment appears to be necessary.   The main items are various kinds of grain, ( 7,687,000 in 1930 and   8,538,000  in 1931);canned salmon, ( 2,652,000 in 1930 and  1,717,000 in 1931);butter, ( 1,005,000 in 1930 and  1,969,000 in 1931);  poultryand game, ( 620,000 in 1930  and   667,000 in 1931).   Importsof foodstuffs represented in 1930 about  40 per  cent, of  our total imports from Russia *    11o Among imports of raw materials,  wood and timber  are by far the most important items.   They  represented a value of 10,428,000 in 1930 and  7,467,000 in 1931.  Other rawmaterials of considerable importance include undressed skins andfurskins ( 1,236,000 in 1930 and  506,000 in 1931); vegetableoils, fats and greases ( 300,000 in 1930 and  103,000 in 1931);raw cotton and cotton waste ( 298,000 in 1930 and  2,058,000in 1931);  bristles ( 283,000 in 1930 and  126,000  in 1931);and flax and flax tow ( 114,000 in 1930  and  186,000 in  1931).Most of these raw materials could be obtained from other sources,though in many cases doubtless at a higher price.   For  example,though there are numerous varieties of timber growing in Russiawhich grow nowhere else, the principal timbers  of  commerce whichare shipped to this country are in close competition withSwedish and Canadian timbers, and have made headway in the british market by being sold at considerably lower prices.   It  is said,however,  that Russian pitprops receive a certain preference  onthe score of quality4   Some of the Russian furskins  (e.g.Kolinsky) are derived from varieties of animals which arepeculiar to Russia.   Russian bristles too are  generally superiorin quality to others.   Being, moreover, white  in colour (theChinese bristles being black and the Indian bristles  yellow)they are essential for good quality hair brushes and  toothbrushes.
   12.  The particular quality of Russian materials in somecases, and the comparatively l^w price at which many of the materials are sold., would malts it very disadvantageous toBritish industry to do without them.  There is, as has alreadybeen indicated, a valuable re-export trade in certain articles;and the cessation of Russian imports would affect not only this trade but possibly also, as regards furs, the position of thiscountry as the leading world market for the whole class ofgoods in question.  London is the centre of the world&apos;s furtrade, and if Russian furs no longer came here it is possiblethat London&apos;s position in the fur trade generally would be undermined.   13.  The cessation of imports -Jf Russian furs would affectnot merely the re-export trade proper, but also the export tradein dressed furskins and articles manufactured from fur.  uuraggregate exports of dressed skins and furs other than sealskins amounted in 1930 to  459,QuO;  while exports of manufactures of skins and fur amounted to  167,UOO.These exports consist of course of goods made no doubt in most cases from furs other than Russian.   14.  Similarly the British brush-making industry, whichmanufactures largely high grad.? brushes and carries on aconsiderable export trade, would be seriously injured if Russianbristles were not obtainable.   15.  An illustration of the immediate advantage which aBritish industry can derive from Russian supplies by reason oftheir cheapness is afforded by thd purchase of Russian cotton ata  ^rice said to be fully ^d per lb, below that of American cottorfor which it is substituted0  In view of the fierce competition which exists in tlra world&apos;s markets for c-tton goods at thepresent time the importance of such purchases scarcely requires to be emphasised.
     16. Of the value of manufactured goods imported from russia the greater part is represented &quot;by refined petroleum ( ?,5,492, COCin 1930 and  4,100,000 in 1931).  A statement relating to Russianoil, which has been furnished by the Mines Department, is annexed(Appendix B).  It indicates broadly that Russian oil could bereplaced, though at some inconvenience or loss, from other sources of supply;  and that the exclusion of Russian oil wouldprobably be welcomed by the large British oil companies partly because it would facilitate a rise of prices.     17. Among other manufactured imports are dressed skins andfurs (3568, $00 in 19u1 and 21,792, COO in 1931); wood and timbermanufactures,  including mainly plywood but,also no doubt consider-able quantities of cheap doors which are in competition with american doers and presumably also with British made doorsS417,Q^C in 1930 and 5318,000 in 1931);  manufactured orprepared drugs (.34 55,000 in 193C and 3105,000 in 1931);  andcarpets and rugs (5237,000 in 1930 and 5110,000 in 1931).     18. To sum up.  It has been srgued:-         (a) That although our trade 7/ith Russia shows a               substantial balance &quot;adverse&quot; to the United Kingdom               this does not to an equivalent extent affect our               total trade balance because Russian funds               accumulating in this country are remittee, abroad               to pay for Russian purchases elsewhere  and  through               their influence on  the rates of exchange discourage               imports into this country and stimulate exports.         (t) That Russian produce imported into this country is               in a large proportion of cases required to  supple-               ment deficient or non existent home supolies, and               if it could not be  obtained it would be necessary to               increase our imports from other sources.
(c) That the goods imported in substitution for the     Russian supplies would probably be  more expensive,     and that the cost not merely of the additional     supplies but conceivably also of the whole of our     surnlies of particular kinds of goods might be     increased &quot;with a consequent additional strain uoon     the sterling exchange.(d) That in some cases particular kinds  or qualities of     goods (e.g. bristles and fur skins; might be     unobtainable.(e) That the rise of prices of certain materials and the     insvailability of supplies would injure our export     and re-export trade.(f) That to this extent,  and to the extent to which     Russia responded to the restriction of our imports     from her by reducing the considerable orders which     she places with British industry, our trade balance     would be &quot;unfavourably&quot; affected.Board of Trade,    Fay 13th, 1932.
   Appendix A - British Trade with Russia.I. IMPORTS PROM RUSSIA INTO THE UNITED KINGDOM.Drink and Tobacco.Quantities,uding:-ber (Theowt.)  .......s (Th. gt.hundreds)  .mon,  canned (Th.cwt.)at             &quot;ley            &quot;Izeon[lltry and game iteriala, eto.fu3ing: -  Ootton  (Th.  Centals)  .... ns and Purskina undressedthousands)  .......0.......   fats  and greases, refined  vegetable,  other an essential.  (Tons)  ..... d and Timber:- m,  soft (Th.  loads)          (Th.          (Th.Values.nnoubio feet)loads) ....11wn m, hard vm, softItpropstavesleeperslax  (including  tow  or odilla) (Tons)  ..... sties (Tons)  ....... r  (excluding  mohair) Th. cwt.)  ..........ufaotured GoodsasTuding: -rags,  etc.  - manufaccuredor prepared...............troleum,  refined mill,  galls.)...........(od and  Timber manufacture aipets and Rug-3 of wool Th.,  sq.  yards) ..........pna and furs (other thanIrabbit  and seal) (dressed) \rti.clea................f which retained.........1929	1930	1931	1929	1930	1931.			&quot;- r000&quot;	 ^OO	 &apos;000-	-	-	7A340	13,285	(a)290	165	404	2,999	1,005	1,969608	85	262	323	31	84367	536	367	2,186	2,652	1,717- 118,717		28,934	-	5,752	6,594- i	5,892	5,638	- j	1,298	1,18123	2,757	2,784	7 i	600	629-	124	660	-	37	134209	50	29	952	205	67-	-	-	613 j	620	667	1		12^253	13,244	(a)4	1 85 ! . 1	886	20	298	2,0585,982	(b)	(b)	1,162	1,236	50814,606	9,510	4,590	-468	300	103153	272	222	288	453	330173	161	153	54	46	341,673	1,751	1,700	7,721	7,423	5,690415	731	543	988	1,726	1,0649	9	4	95	105	5972	169	114	313	675	2902,913	1 2,149	6,073	218	114	186561	! 519	329	372	283	12613	30	47	73	124	68	1 &apos; . -j 1 I		6^895	7*706	(a)	-	-	512	455	105202	264	271	4,573	5,492	1 4,100-	1 .  	-	395	417	518254	209	104	336	237	1103,368	5,303	10,754	546	538	1,792Thous.	Owts.	Gwts .						26^487	34^235	32,179-	-	-	23,106	30,887	(a)(a) Not yet available. (b)  Number  not  available,-8-
II.  EXPORTS OP BRITISH GOODS TO RUSSIA.Quanti ty.Value.T1929.!1930.1931.1929.   1930.  Drink and Tobaccolluding: -irrings (Th.  cwt. ) ..........igar,  refined (Th. cwt.) ....Materials, etc.:luding : -ieepf s and Lambs&apos; wool(Th. centals)................I;ol waste and noils (Th.centals)lollen rags (Th. cwt.)  ..... afactured GoodsIcluding: -Isnionium Compounds (Tons) ....achinery  and  parts (Tons) ...pen  and Steel Manufactures(Tons)......................ickel in  pellets, cubes, etc.(Tons).................... . . .sol  tops  (Th.  centals).......^Articles *..................3337 4 6 7,21715,03614,690   204    11  1822,59712213763,19727,779 5,972   640    2638 21  2121 &apos;000   &apos;00021,26340,38651,5921   8931   0.4252262*  518   43   285.046   671,737  403   35  1673.7431,729  1221,409  408  107  146  1194,6021931.  5012,693  375 &apos; 109  3306,772 &apos;CC0   421    20   349  109    4  1736,443  1494,418  807  152    57,291
III.  EXPORTS OP 12 PORTED VFEOHANDISE TO RUSSIA.	Quantity		%	Value.			1929.	1950.	1971.	1929.	1970 .	1931.				fi&apos;000	 &apos;000.	 &apos;000.	-	-	-	822	428	(a)including: -							11,878	7,525	5,09?	726	407	175		m,,		542	851	(a)inoluding:-						Ootton, raw (Th. centals) ..	16	72	-	82	134	-Rubber, raw ( &quot; &quot; ) ..	84	171	367	762	62?	767	mm	..		1,475	1,240	(a)including:-						Pig and Sheet Lead. (Tons) ..	13,558	29,988	12,605	316	558	169Tin blocks, ingots, eto . (Tcrs)	4,792	2,677	1,660	942	490	194Zinc and Zinc manufacture							3,026	2,980	3,383	84	55	48	mm	mm		2.799	2^519	1,923						(a)  Not  yet  available.
         APPENDIX B  -  RUSSIAN OIL.(Memorandum furnished  hy Mines Department).     During the last three years,  1929  to  1931,  the imports of oil from Russia have averaged 247  million  gallons annually, or11$ of the total.     The undermentioned table shov/3 the imports  during these three years divided under the principal products:-                  1929       1930                 1931                                  Million  gallons                       % of                             % of                       Total           fb of             Total                      Imports          Total            Imports.                                     Imports.	86	33.6	75	30.6	79	29.2Motor Spirit.. .	78	9.6	116	12.3	127	13.9Lubricating Oil	11	11.2	13	12.8	15	15.3	8	7.0	16	12.2	8	9.3	21	5.3	44	8.9	44	9.1     The following are some of the considerations  which might beborne in mind in considering the jpossibility of excluding  these supplies.  (a) Motor Spirit.           On the whole the large oil importing and distributing      companies would probably welcome such a measure.      The importation of such enormous quantities  of      cheap motor spirit hac had an influence in forcing      prices down to an uneconomic level.    Since  March,  1929,      Russian Oil Products Limited has been allowed within      the outer ring of Combine Companies on condition      that they did not quote public prices which  were more      than Id. less than the combine prices.   This agreement
applied however only to sales to the public and the company were free to quote any price they chose for contract business.In this direction it is Known that they have fixed  up contracts with large consumers at extraordinarily low prices  - a price aslow as 9-Q-d. per gallon has been mentioned,  which, when the tax of -3d. has been deducted, would only leave them l^d.  a gallon delivered in this country.   With at least ^d. a  gallonfor ocean freight this reduces the amount to l^d. to cover thecost of the oil at the port of shipment, together with porthandling and storage charges and the cost of distribution inthis country.     The agreement between Russian Oil Products and theCombine Companies came to an end at the end of March lastand nothing has yet taken its place.   The removal  of R.O.P.from the market might very well result in easing the difficultyof the Combine Companies in coming to terms with the Cleveland,the largest of the &quot;pirate&quot; companies and thus pave the  way fora fairly  substantial increase in the price of motor spirit.Ouch a result could not be entirely attributed to the elimination of R.O.P. as it is believed that in any eventsome increase in the price of motor spirit cannot be much longer avoided.  (b) Lamp Oil.     Large quantities of lamp oil or kerosene are imported into this country for cracking into motor spirit,  the greater proportion of lamp oil so treated coming from Russia, although some quantities are received from Roumanian   This  cracicingof kerosene is mainly done by the Medway Oil and storageCompany at Isle of Grain, Kent, (and subsequently  sold as&quot;Power&quot; petrol) and by Cory Brothers at Coryton.   In 1930,
the last year for which figures are available, nearly70 million gallons of kerosene were so treated in this country.The stoppage of the Russian part of these supplies might havethe effect of putting the Isle of Grain refinery out ofbusiness, as they rely very largely on Russian supplies.   Theymight possibly get the supplies they need from Roumania and theUnited States, or perhaps from Aruba where large quantities ofVenezuelan crude oil are refined, but they would not have theassured supplies at cheap rates on which their &quot;business hasbeen built up during the past 10 years.   It is generally believed, however, that the Medway Company has been bought bythe Vacuum Oil Company, a wealthy American controlledCorporation,     Another effect of stopping supplies of Russian motor spiritaud kerosene might be a serious loss of business to Cory Brothersand Company at Coryton where, besides cracking some quantitiesof Russian and other kerosene, they act as general storagecontractors and warehousemen for Russian Oil Products Limited.   (c) Lubricating Oil.     About 15% of our lubricating oil supplies were obtainedfrom Russian in 1931.   This oil is of good quality and is usedin the manufacture of some of the best lubricating oils.   Nodoubt It could be replaced by imports from the United States,Mexico and elsewhere, but the sudden cutting off of supplies would probably lead to a dislocation of business on the partof such people as Silvertown Lubricants Limited and Lubrioatingand Fuel Oils Limited and might cause some difficulty in meetingthe existing- specifications of large consumers of luricating oil until such time as the trade could readjust itself.   (d) Gas Oil and Fuel Oil.     It is not considered that the loss of these supplies wouldbe a matter of serious concern.   Owing to the world
over-production of crude oil and the consequent flood ofresidual oils suitable for use as fuel, it is probable thatthe large British oil companies would rather welcome the stoppage of Russian supplies to this country,     In considering the effects of the shutting out of thiscountry of about a million tons of cil per annum it should notbe overlooked that the Russians may export thi3 oil to othercountries.   The attached statement shows the destinations ofthe Russian oil exports for the last two years, and it will beseen that the three next best customers to Great Britain areItaly, France and Germany.   The diversion of the greater partof a million tons of oil to those countries might tend towardsthe exclusion from those countries of oil marketed by the shell and Anglo-Persian Oil Companies which have speciallydeveloped their oilfields in Persia, Venezuela, Mexico and theDutch 3ast Indies at great expense, in order that the product of these oilfields may be marketed all over the world.   Ifrelieved in this country of the competition of Russian OilBritish Oil Companies may be faced with fiercer competitionabroad,  not only in the countries named but in the variousbunker nil ports of the world, especially in the mediterranean and the near East,   On balance however the Oil Companies wouldprobably welcome the psychological effect of attempting to stop the large Ivports of very cheap oil to this country which tends to depress the whole of the industry..
EXPORTS OF  OIL PRODUCTS FROM RUSSIA.----	1931 tons.	1930 tons	Increase or decrease, per cent.Great Britain ..0	1,001,700	973,100	-4- 2.9	971, 200	326,200	4- 17.5	- 866,900	556,800	+ 55.6	499,300	504,700	- 1.1	187,400	95,300	4- 96,6	157,100	105,500	* 48,9	154,900	204,800	- 24.4	151,SOO	189,600	- 20.3	147,300	-361,300	- 59.3	141,900	103,600	4-38.9	117,000	41,400	4- 182.6Czechoslovakia ..	113,300	83, 500	4- 35.other countries..	544,500	577,800	- 5.8	223,700	180,000	4- 24.2	5,277,400	4,803,000	4- 9.9
fSEORET. &apos;.R. (58)12.                                        OOPY NO.                      CABINET .           Committee on Trede with Russia.Probable effect of restriction of the sale of Russian   oopgioditles in tne OniTeS^Klngdom on tne&quot;l$6vietr   Governments ability and reaoTiness to meet T a oursTanding&apos; obiigatTons iri this oountry &quot;and&quot; Germany.Memorandum by the Export Credits Guarantee Department.84     In its memorandum on the question of Russian solvency(See T.R.  (3?)3) the Export Credits Guarantee Departmentexpressed the view that the one thing most likely to bringabout Russian default was severe restriction of imports fromRussia, especially by England.   (2) While opinions may differ about the prospects of a russian default in the absence of such restrictions, there willbe no disagreement that the loss of the British market wouldhave the most serious effects on Russia&apos;s ability to meet her obligations.   (3) Exact figures of Russia&apos;s obligations to foreigncountries are difficult to obtain.   Details are given in theAppendix but so far as the more important countries areconcerned, the amounts falling due seem to be roughly asfollows.-------	Remainder of 1932. &quot;	1933.	19*4.	  4,000,000 5,000,000	  6,000,000 37,000,000 4,000,000	  4,000,000 10,000,000	29,000,000	47,000,000	14,000,000In addition there are fairly	considerable sums due to Italy,		czecho-Slovakia, Austria, Poland, etc                             APPENDIX  IV.CHIS  DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY  OF HIS  BRITANNIC MA JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.
These are stillmore difficult to estimate but may perhaps be guessed at10,000,00039,000,00015,000^000   5,000, OOP62,000,000  19,000,000Total (say)= in all  12,0,000,000.     The figures are in   sterling at 4 dollars to the  .   (4) Practically the sole source from vrhich Russia can meet these obligations ic her export of commodities.  These exports have declined from.  103,000,000 (gold) in 1930 to  81,000,000 in19?]..  From these resources? Russia has to meet  not only herbills for past purchases but all her payments in cash and on very short credit.   These latter payments cover purchaseo ofraw materials as veil as freights and other invisible items.The invisible exports from Great Britain alone have been estimated at  5,000,000 per annum and by the Russians at 7,000,000 to  8,000,000 per annum.   (5) The fall in the value of Russian exports is verysignificant.    it is due partly to the continued fall in prices,partly to the increasing difficulty in marketing her good3 andpartly to internal difficulties in Russia which have resulted,e.g., in Russia exporting practically no wheat during this last winter.   It is reasonable therefore to expect that irrespective of action by foreign governments the value of Russian exportsmay oontinue to decline.   (6) Even, therefore, if no new obstacles are placed in theway of Russia marketing her products it seems clear that russia is conducting her foreign trade on comparatively narrow marginsat the present time.  Further evidence of this is forthcomingin the fact that Russia has for some time past diminished herpurchases in foreign oountries.  Thus exports from the U.S.A.for the first three months of 1972 are  3,600,000 as against^44,000,000 for the corresponding period of 1971.  On the otherhand  it may be that Russia has oertain hidden resources which
oould be available at a moment of crisis and all the evidenceshows that the Russian Government seem to entertain no doubt  asto their ability to continue to meet their existing commitments.The explanation may be found partly in the size of th^ RussianGovernment&apos;n cash disbursements for raw materials and freightwhioh in a time of crisis oould no doubt be reduced to much smaller dimensions.     To summarise a very obsoure situation, the Export credits guarantee Department feel that whilst Russia is likely to continueto meet her obligations, the margin between solvency and default13 likely for some time to come to be very narrow, even if no new difficulties arise.   (7) The difficulties that would be created for Russia by aserious restriction of her sales in Great Britain would be considerable.   During the last three years Great Britain hastaken about 30^? of Russian exports.   In 1931 the proportion wasabout 33^.     If Russia were deprived of this outlet the natural coursewould be for her to seek alternative markets, but, as H.M.Ambassador at  Mosoow has recently stated, it is difficult toindicate alternative markets whioh could readily be found for most of the Russian commodities whioh the United Kingdom takes.     The question becomes of greatest importance in relation toRussia&apos;s commitments in Germany, and German officials haverecently informed the Export Credits Guarantee Department thatthis question is causing them great anxiety.   They haveenvisaged the possibility of the imposition of restrictions by great Britain on the inflow of Russian goods and are considering whether Germany could take a larger share of Russian productsthan at present,should suoh restrictions be imposed^  Judging,however, by the difficulties which have already been encountered in attempting to encourage larger sales of Russian oil and grain,
the prospect of Germany absorbing any large proportion of the 30,000,000 of goods whioh this oountry at present takes fromRussia is remote.     Russia might then seek to find larger outlets in othercountries but, apart from any special considerations that might arise between such countries and Russia, the fact that most countries are now seeking to restrict imports of all kindsholds out little prospect of success for Russia in such attempts.     Moreover insofar as Russia should be able to sell e,g,more wheat to Germany or other countries, this would probablytake, the place of Canadian wheat.  German officials have hintedthat this result might be expected*   (8) It seems clear that serious restriction of sales by russia to Great Britain would place the Russian Government in serious financial difficultiea*     The extent of the difficulties would probably depend onthe extent of the restrictions.    Partial exclusion of Russianproducts would probably still leave Russia in a position tomeet some of her commitments.   This would leave Russia free to choose which of her creditors it would pay her best to  satisfy.While speoial action by the British Government directed towardsincreasing Russia&apos;s purchases in this oountry might be effective.,it might also if carried very far provide the Russian Governmentwith good  exouses for not meeting bills due in the UnitedKingdom.     Whether in this eventuality, Russia were to meet all herBritish commitments or not, it seems likely that Germany mightsuffer.   Germany is due to receive 1,000 million R.Mk3. fromRussia and against these bills the Reichsbank and itssubsidiaries have advanced very large sums  (possibly up to 700million R.Mks.) on the guarantee of the German Government and the Federal States.  Either these credits would be frozen or theGerman Government and the States Governments would have to find
large suns for whioh. their Budgets make no provision.   Thefinancial position of Germany is already sufficiently precarious,and Russian default on  German bills a,t the present time would undoubtedly add seriously to the difficulty of obtainingrepayment of the large amount of British money at present lockedup in Germany and would thus be definitely injurious to Britishinterests.   (9) The practical conclusion seems to be that the presentmoment is not unfavourable for exacting concessions from Russiawithin certain limits.   Those limits are set by Russia&apos;financial position.   It would appear to be impossible for russia to start buying here for cash on any considerable scale.  Inview of Russia&apos;s existing commitments there seems to be noescape from the conclusion that exports to Russia on any large scale for some time to come can only be conducted on the basis ofsome credit.  If Russia is to obtain such credits she may reasonably be asked to make certain concessions.
                           APPENDIX.       Estimate of Runnla&apos;3 out standing obligations to the             United Kingdom, Germany and the U.S.A.   (1) So far an this country is ooncerned the total amountcovered by the Export Oredits Guarantee Department at the endof April was some  10 million.   Of this amount it is estimatedthat  2-1 million will mature in 19*2,  4^ million during 193?and  3 million during 19*4.   Export Credit Guarantees haverecently covered  about 30% of the total domestic exports fromthe United Kingdom to Russia, but during 1930 the proportion waslower, and some of the unguaranteed credits then given may bematuring in 1932.   On the whole it seems probable that theSoviet&apos;s obligations will not exceed -                4 million from 1/5/32 to 31/12/32                6     &quot;   during 1933                4     B      &quot;   1934.   (2) Prom figures recently supplied confidentially by Germaa.officials it is known that Russian obligations maturing inGermany amount to -    R..mks. ?50 million or say  20 million from 1/4/?2 to 31/12/32      n    600    &quot;    n   &quot;   37     &quot;   during 1933      ft    150    w    n       10     n     r,    19?4   v(3) Information about outstanding debts to the U.S.A. is naturally difficult to obtain, but it in learned in the^ strictestconfidence that the American Department of Commerce estimated the amount falling due during 1932 at ^25 million, of which it inunderntood that a substantial part has  already run off.  Anothersource, an American bank, staten that the total outstanding isbelieved to be .^40 million.   In any case it is certain, in viewof the very large decrease in exports from the U,S,A. to Russia,that the total is diminishing, and the  probability in that thefigure is not more thar. -     ^20 million or say  5 million from 1/4/32 to 31/12/32     $15    &quot;    &quot;   &quot;   4    &quot;    during 1933.
   (4) According to Soviet official statistics about  60% ofRussia1s imports in 1930 and 1931 came from Germany,  the U.S.Aand the united Kingdom.   Of the balance a substantial  partcame from Afghanistan, Egypt, India, China, Mongolia  and PersiIt seems reasonable to assume that this part consisted  verylargely of raw materials and that it was paid for in  oash.The amount of credits obtained by Russia from countries otherthan her three principal suppliers is not therefore likely tobe on an important scale.   In any case so little is  known ofthe figures that anything more than a guess is impossible.24th May, 1932.

</content>
</cab>
