<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/230/0 images: 212-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cVERY URGENT,G.Po&apos;179 (32) o               Circulated to Cabinet0   Indications of j?rench &quot;policy after recent elections      Lord Tyrrell has been, at my suggestion, takingsoundings with a view to ascertaining how far, if atall, the policy of the new French Government on externalquestions may be likely to differ from that of its pre-decessor3   The annexed Notes have been prepared in theForeign Office end His Majesty&apos;s Embassy at Paris to summarise the impressions gleaned there by Lord Tyrrelle(Intld.)  J.B,FOREIGN OFFICE,S o W. 1.30th May,  1932.
     The recent general election in France resulted in asweeping victory for the Radicals.  The Tardieu cabinet will resign when the Chambers meet and will, in LordTyrrell&apos;s view, be replaced by a purely Radical Cabinetunder M. Herriot which will receive the support of the minor Left groups.  Such a Ministry will, (in M,Painleve&apos; &apos;view) also enjoy at least for the time being the benevolentneutrality, and. on some occasions the actual support, ofthe Socialists under M. Blum,     During the last ten days His Majesty&apos;s ambassador at paris has, at the suggestion of the Secretary of State,been sounding those leaders of the majority parties inFrance of whom the new Herriot Cabinet is likely to be composed, as to their views on reparations and war debts,as well as on disarmament and Central European questionfe.The BP leaders include M. Herri ot himself, M. Painleve&apos;,M. albert Sarraut, Mo Bonnet (a leading Radical), M.Germain-Martin &apos;(a right wing Radical), M. Pierre Cot(a Left Wing Radical), and M, Chautemps, Mayor of Tours,a very influential Radical.  Lord Tyrrell has also seenMM.Caillaux and Blum  (the last named being of course, the leader of the Socialist party) and is to see M, Palmade                                           (probably,.,.,Summary of Conversations between His Majesty&apos;s ambassador at Paris, and leading French politicians on Reparationsand war Debts,  Disarmament and the affairs of central europe, prepared in Foreign Office.
(probably the future Minister of the Budget) very shortly.He has asked that we should await the result of all hisinterviews before any definite decisions are taken atthis end.(1) General,     It appears from a memorandum dated May 13th supplied to Lord Tyrrell by a &quot;reliable French source in &quot;touch withthe Left&quot; that the new French Government will, cn takingoffice, seek a close collaboration with His Majesty&apos;sGovernment for internal as well as external reasons.  this document observes that many people in France believe that,with a view to establishing a sound basis for the reconstruc-tion of Europe, a new Entente is required, based, not on new agreements regarding security, but on the 1904 princi-ple; but before this can be achieved there are certainproblems to be settled of which the chief are: reparationsand war debts; disarmament; the reconstruction of central europe; and future policy as retgards Germany.  Franceis anxious to know whether she and Great Britain canafter a study of these questions enter upon this summer&apos;s negotiations with &quot;des vues a peu pres communes&quot;.  The newFrench Government will no doubt be ready for conciliatorysolutions where reparations and Disarmament are concerned:but fears that once these solutions have been reachedGermany will immediately bring up Treaty revision or thePolish Corridor,  In these circurnstancess what is required is to establish the precise scope and limits, of the concessions which both Governments are prepared to make in                                              Europe.,o o
&quot;europe with a view to the recreation of a new spiritof collaboration, but beyond which the French Govern-ment can be certain that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentdefinitely will not go, in any circumstances.   In trans-mitting the document from which the preceding views havebeen summarized Lord Tyrrell points out that this is thecrux of the matter so far as the foreign policy of any French Government is concerned.(2)  Franco-German. Helat.lo.ns.     M, Herriot and other leaders interviewed by LordTyrrell spoke strongly in favour of Franco-Britishcollaboration (MM, Herriot and Cot preconising exchanges of points of view and &quot;work on parallel lines&quot;) andthere was general agreement among them that France&apos;policy must be more generous as regards Germany than ithas been in the past. .  But two of them (MM.Pain].eve&apos;and Bonnet) made the point that this was made difficultat the moment by the Hitler successes, the Chancellor&apos;recent statement in the ^eichstag about reparations, andthe publication  of the Stresemann Papers (this last isa collection of the speeches,  newspaper articles, privateletters, etc,, of the late Dr. Stresemann, which was recently published in Berlin  and has been translated into French.   The general trend of the speeches andarticles, etc., is to show France as endeavouring toprevent Germany from reaching that position of &quot;freedom&quot;and &quot;power&quot; to which she is properly entitled).  M. blumtold Lord Tyrrell that he was disappointed and disturbed by the attitude of Germany and M, Sarraut, while emphasis--ing that the projected collaboration between France and                                                 Great....
Great Britain would not be practised to  the  exclusion ofGermany  (a principle also endorsed by Mi.  Germain Martinand Bonnet) declared that the new majority in the Chamber&quot;rouId ask that Germany should cease to try and play off&quot;France against Great Britain and vice versa.(3)  reparations and Debts,     AS regards reparations and war debts, the chief points made in these conversations were as follows:   /Jlote:  to test their views the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s Houseof Commons statement of February 2:id - copy  attached -annex A. was shewn to MM. Herriot, Chautemps and Caillaux?.     M. Herriot himself declared that he  could subscribe to.the statement made on February 2nd by  the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer in the House of Commons (M.  Caillaux said&quot;There v/as no difficulty about any of that &quot;) and v/as incomplete agreement with it and would make a  similar declara-tion himself at the first opportunity..   This presumablymeans that M. Harriot (1) recognizes the  necessity for a comprehensive and permanent settlement,    (2) agrees that.the best means of securing this would be  by  means of ageneral cancellation of reparations and war  debts  and (3)holds that as Germany&apos;s legal obligations were laid down at The Hague they cannot be altered unilaterally,,but(4) that Germany is not in a position at  the moment to re-Bume the discharge of those obligations,  a fact which willhave to be taken into account at Lausanne.     Both l&apos;\. Germain-Martin and M, Cot believe in completecancellation to cover - and this is important T the war debt                                                to....
to the united States, which is, it appears, the greatstumbling block.  M. Chautemps also believes in thepossibility of Prance agreeing to complete and generalcancellation, subject to the waiver of the united Statesdebt, but he ( toad Mvi. Sarraut and Caillaux) are insistentthat no unilaterul action on the part of Germany can be tolerated.  Legality must be observed.  MM, Chautemps andCaillaux both feel that I/I. Harriot must bring back withhim from Lausanne the consent of Germany to some small lumppayment as an earnest of Prance&apos;s legal right to reparationsif the Chambers are to endorse the according of relief to&apos;Germany in respect of her reparation obligations.  /TheGerman Embassy in Paris is said to have admitted that theGerman Government will be ready to acknowledge Germany&apos;legal obligation to pay/.     M.  Blum while personally in favour of complete cancel-lation of reparations and debts and believing that the Chamberwould share this view with &quot;quasi unaniraite&quot;, wondered, if in order to keep the principle of reparations alive there could not be some continued obligation on Germany by.meansof a contribution to a large and international scheme of &apos;public works,     AS regards the conditions upon which Prance would agreethat Germany might be let off either the whole or part ofher reparation obligations /i.e, complete cancellation orcancellation of the part representing PranceVs soldo/,there were mentioned by one or more of Lord Tyrrell&apos;sinterlocutions: some protection against an eventual german economic recovery; a settled Europe witn Germany agreeing
to co-operate in its peaceful  organization;  Germany  toagree to a  political truce  to  cover  the  Corridor  question,and to give guarantees  that she  will not spend  on arma-ments the sums which she  is to be  excused paying  onreparation  account.     Li.Sarraut drew attention  to the exceedingly  seriousnature of the French financial situation which  was in itselfan obstacle to a generous reparations policy.     as regards the &quot; :.olde&quot;, the admission was  generallymade that France&apos;s net  reparation  surplus might be abandonedbut not unconditionally.  In addition to the  conditionsreferred to in the preceding paragraph,  the following maybe mentioned;  MM. Painleve, Bonnet  and  Cot were  in  agree-rnent that in return for   the abandonment of the &quot;solde&quot;,the least that France would expect would be that  GreatBritain would abandon her claims on  France: in respect ofthe war debt.  MM. Sarraut  and Chautemps pointed  out thatthe &quot;solde&quot; was the only  compensation France would receivefor the devastation of her  Northern  provinces during thewar:  and that it would be difficult  to sacrifice  the &quot;solde&quot;if the Americans were to  make  no sacrifice at all  over theBe at s0     all the leaders, with  the important exception of M.Herri ot, were insistent that France  would  not a,o:ree to pay any of her debt to the  united  States  exceut out of Germanmoney.   M.  Herriot, on the  other hand, observed that he                                              &quot;strongly....
&quot;strongly objected&quot; to M. Laval&apos;s statement that france would, not pay the United States except with Germanmoney as this placed France on the level of a contract-breaking Power.   M. Painleve mentioned, hut without committing himself, the possibility that France wouldadmit the sharing with Germany, in accordance with therespective capacity of each country to pay and to transfer,of the burden of any war debt payments ultimately claimed by the United States, which might in future be termed&quot;war charges&quot;.     It may be ^added that ivi. Herri ot said, in reply to aquestion by Lord Tyrrell, that it would be useful for sir Fv Leith hoes to come to Paris for a private andunofficial discussion with M. Germain Martin:  Lord Tyrrellthinks this would be a wise plan, but &quot;not before themiddle of next week&quot; (i.e. June 1st),
      (4)   Disarmament.      1.   M0 Herriot, the future Prime Minister, express-ed himself strongly  in favour of Franco-British co-operation,,   He also said that he entirely shared theviews expressed recently by M. Paul-Boncour at Dijon(it was conjectured by the Department at the time thatMo Paul-Boncour would be unlikely to have expressed him-self  so strongly without being sure that the views were those of M. Herriot,   It will be remembered that amongthe considerations urged by M. Paul-Boneour was thepossibility of a continental association for mutual assistance.)..      2t    Mo Pierre Cot,  who is unlikely to be M.Herriot&apos;&apos;s Parliamentary Under-Secretary,  thought that france would be able to agree to the practical abolitionof military atrc-raft,provided some, small international force of smaller machines was constituted for policepurposes;  he also spoke in favour of the international-:isation and elimination of competition of civil airlines.   He further thought th rfc France would be willingto make concessions over &quot;offensive weapons&quot;;   if wewould limit the size of big cruisers they would followwith, heavy artillery, large tanks and large sub-marines.   As regards the naval question,,would we enterinto a limited sort of Mediterranean Locarno,  so thatif Germany and. Italy together attacked France,  we  should support France in the Mediterranean?   M. Cot  asked that the British and French Governments should informone another of their respective positions during thenext two weeks, so that they could work on parallellines at Lausanne and Geneva.
13G     3.   M. Georges Bonnet (Radical, friend ofM. Painleve&apos;) spoke of a 25 per cent reduction of militarycredits.   He mentioned also the difficulty constitutedby the British attitude on security.     4.   M. Germain-Martin (Gauche Radicale, the groupjust to the right of the Socialist Radicals) declaredhimself in favour of Franco-British co-operation,drawing in Germany and, if Italy wished it, Italy too.     5.   M. Painleve&apos; (Socialist Republican, that isM. Briand&apos;s old party  half-way between the SocialistRadicals  and Socialists) also expressed himself strongly in favour of Franco-British co-operation, but saidnothing about disarmament.     6.   M. Sarraut (Senator of the Democratic Left)declared that the new Government would desire confidentco-operation with Great Britain and  immediate, intimateand unofficial contact, but they would not  desire to practise  that co-operation to the  exclusion of Germany.Germany,  however, must cease to try  to play off GreatBritain against France and vice versa.   M. Sarrautmentioned the possibility of an agreement  limiting theFrench naval forces  in the mediterranean to the  size  ofthe  Italian fleet, whilst  allowing France  additional  *naval  forces in  othdr  seas which  could not be broughtinto the  Mediterranean in normal  circumstances.M.  Sarraut  mentioned M,  Paul-Boneour&apos;s recent  speochat  Dijon,  and  said that  it was  necessary to realise that concessions in  disarmament would have to be made without the complete fulfilment of the  security conditions laid down in M.  lardi.eu&apos;s memoranda.
                                                     4 on                                                     I o i                                                       i     (5)  Austrj.an situation.     M. Painleve&quot; recognises the need for immediate help for Austria and is prepared strongly to urge the advanceof the French credit, his only condition bein; that theBank of England credit should not be withdrawn.   horeadily admit8 the need of helping Austria before theother Central European foyers,     M. Chaut mps (Layor of lours:  prominent member ofthe Radical Party:  probable Minister of the Interior)&quot;thinks we shall find a caenge in Preach policy in central Europe,  and that the assistance required un austria win be liven&quot;.     ivi. Pierre Cot (Radical) fully realises the import -ance which His Majesty&apos; s Government attach to preliminaryand immediate aid for Austria:  and why His Majesty.&apos;sGovernment consider that France should supplement the aid.given by tne Bank of England.   He is particularlyimpressed by the fact that Austria is already underhe ague of Nations supervision, and by any renewal ofthe &quot;Anschluss&quot; danger.   His view is that the new government ought to be able to live His Majesty IsGovernment satisfaction as regards Austria,     to. Germain-Martin (member of the Gcucha Radicals,f:nd to the Right of the no&apos;&quot; m. jority) advocates close and friendly co-o Deration with Groat Britin in central europe, but in no way to the exclusion of Germany.     M. Caillaux said that a feature of the electoralcampaign had been the strong feeling in the country against further indiscriminate foreign loans, but he did not deny that the position mi ;;ht be different un austria.   xie wag against further idyllscrimiuatc loansend had a  general plan on the matter.
A O O       (6)  General Currency and Economic Questions,     Only one of the French politicians  interviewed &quot;by LordTyrrell referred in any detail to  general  currency andeconomic questions.   This was Monsieur  Germain-Martin (for whose  position in the Chamber see  under  paragraph 4 of thesection dealing with disarmament),.  He  said that his viewscoincided with the resolutions passed at the Inter-Parlia-mentary Conference on Cemnerce which was held at Prague inMay 1951c   He v/as the rapporteur  at that  Conference, andthe resolutions then adopted were  as follows:-1&apos; With re.f*er;ence to the Constitution of the Metallic Reserves,     that the States, whose economic and monetary systems are threatened by general and continuous displacements ofprecious metalsa proceed to a complete and impartial study ofthe causes of these displacements, in order to realisepossible improvements in their legislation or their activitywith a view to avoiding in future  the serious consequences of a distribution of precious metals;     that the States holding the most important gold reservesadopt  an extension of a policy similar to  that of the Bank ofFrance in order to avoid, or at least to lessen,, generalmovement of precious metal subsequent to the international settlements, this result depending above all on the politicaland economic attitude of the States whose metallic reserves are threatened with withdrawals;     that to this end the functions, of the Bank of Inter-national Settlements be intensified in order that theessential powers of the Bank., stipulated in article 24 of thestatute, be exercised in an efficient manner.2. Re-solutions relating to the Circulation  of Floating^.Capl/hal.     The Conference declares that:          (i)  Economic reorganisation is not to be visualised     as long as excessive floating credits are abruptly dis-     -olaced from market to market  and provoke economic and
     stock exchange activities of an artificial and temporary     character.          (ii)  That it is desirable that the excessively     great facilities for the affording of credits be res-     trained in case there are causes of excessive specula-     tion or of an artificial development of industrial and     commercial activity.          (iii) That the creation of credit secured on gold     reserves or.on guarantee papers or on bank securities     or on security bills be in suitable proportion in view     of the probable development of economic activities.          (iv)  That there can be no hope for the economic     reorganisation of Europe by the means of credit and the     transformation of short-term credits into long-term     credits except by a policy of rapprochement and pacifi-     cation between the States interested;  that this policy     alone can restore confidence in the place of uncer-     tainty which is the determining cause of the hesitation     shown by capitalists to engage in monetary operations     of long date.3.Resolutions relating to the Methods of Long-Term Investments     The Conference, anxious to hasten the realization of long-term loans which are indispensable to the economic structure of the world, declares          (a) that Agreements be arrived at between the     markets which have capital available for employment;          (b) that loans be granted after a close study of     the uses to be made of the capital lent;          (G) that the securities be defined and chosen,if     possible, by the Financial Committee of the League of     Nations; that the latter envisages the safeguarding   i     measures to be taken in case of default;          (d) that the securities be specified in different     currencies in order to guarantee a very wide market to     the negotiation of the securities.          It does not appear that any action has so far beentaken on the above-mentioned resolutions.
     stock exchange activities of an artificial and temporary     character.          (ii)  That it is desirable that the excessively     great facilities for the affording of credits be res-     trained in case there are causes of excessive specula-     tion or of an artificial development of industrial and     commercial activity.          (iii) That the creation of credit secured on gold     reserves or.on guarantee papers or on bank securities     or on security bills be in suitable proportion in view     of the probable development of economic activities.          (iv)  That there can be no hope for the economic     reorganisation of Europe by the means of credit and the     transformation of short-term credits into long-term     credits except by a policy of rapprochement and pacifi-     cation between the States interested;  that this policy     alone can restore confidence in the place of uncer-     tainty which is the determining cause of the hesitation     shown by capitalists to engage In monetary operations     of long date.3.Resolutions relating to the Methods of Long-Term Investments     The Conference, anxious to hasten the realization of long-term loans which are indispensable to the economic structure of the world, declares          (a) that Agreements be arrived at between the     markets which have capital available for employment;          (b) that loans be granted after a close study of     the uses to be made of the capital lent;          (c) that the securities be defined and chosen,if     possible, by the Financial Committee of the League of     Nations; that the latter envisages the safeguarding   )     measures to be taken in case of default;          (d) that the securities be specified in different     currencies in order to guarantee a very wide market to     the negotiation of the securities.          It does not appear that any action has so far beer-taken on the above-mentioned resolutions.
                       h  h N &apos;1 X   A.           HAMSAHP.. - February 2nd. 1932.               R&quot;1:! ORATIONS AMD WAR DWS.   30o   MR. MANDUR asked the Prime Minister the presentposition with regard to holding an international conference  fordealing with matters of currency, finance, reparations,  inter-allied debts, and other matters of mutual concern?   34.   MR. COOKS asked the Chancellor of the Exchequerwhether he can make a statement as to the results of the meetingat Basle of the advisory committeo under the Young Plan and  uponthe present position of the question of reparations and  war  debts   TH7&apos; CHANCELLOR OF TIP&apos; SXCHUQUIB (MR, CHAMB3RL/IM):  I havebeen asked to reply.  The policy of His Majestyl-s Government isthat a comprehensive and  permanent settlement of the reparationquestion must be reached as soon as possible.  We believe, assuccessive Governments of this country have believed in the  past,that this aim could best be realised by means of a general oan-oellation of reparations and war debts.     As soon as the report of the Basle experts was received at christmas, we urged the necessity for the Governments to cometogther immediately to conclude a pormarient settlement of thereparation question on the basis of a frank recognition of thefacts established in the unanimous report of the experts. Butit became apparent that the present juncture) was not favourable for a settlement on such a basis0     We accordingly expressed our willingness to agree to the postponement of the Inter-Governmental Conference till Lay or Jun.when we hoped that conditions might be more favourable for apermanent settlement9  We also suggested that some provisional                                                   arrangement /
arrangement should he made cohering the vaar^ttO^ABilc&amp;sg the1st July next in case the Conference could not he oon.could^dbefore the 30th June, when the Hoover moratorium will expire^.An interchange of views on the subject has taken place with&apos; theFrench Government, hut as it has not hitherto  been found possibleto secure full agreement in advance among the  Governments chiefly concerned on the various arrangements which would be  involved,It rnaj- prove to be the best course to reserve  the whole question for settlement by the Conference when it meets0     In the meantime I would prefer to make no statement whichmight in any way render the task of the Conference-more difficult.a     There is, however, one further observation which I desire tornake^  The legal obligations of Germany are laid down, by TheHague-Agreement and cannot be altered or annulled by the uni-lateral action of Germany,,  That is clear:  indeed, so far as Iam aware, it has never been contested in any quarter-  But itis equally clear, from the report of the Basle Committee thatGermany is not in a position to resume the fulfilment of these obligations and that consequently-when the Creditor Governmentscome to consider future arrangements, that fact will assuredlyhave to be taken into account.     COLONEL WEDGTOOD:  Can the right hon Gentleman say when     -our next payment to America becomes due?     IRo CHAMBERLAIN:  Not until December next,     MR. HALSS:  May we have an assurance that no further pay-merit will be made to America unless we receive a correspondingamount from Germany or France or other debtors?
VERY CONFIDENTIAL.  II.  THE SITUATION IN THE CHAMBER AND THE PPOBABLE          FOREIGN POLICY OF THE NEW FRENCH CABINET              (PREPARED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos; S EMBASSY                            PASIS.)     A.  SITUATION IN THE CHAIV1BER OF DEPUTIES.     The situation is complicated.  Though the Radicals,Socialists and minor Left Centre paid Left groups muster some370 out of the 600 deputies in the Chamber,(see annex), theresult will not necessarily he a strong and  stablegovernment,     2,  The deputies of the majority will be sharplydivided in domestic politics and to a lesser extent inforeign politics.  The Socialists, fearing an increase inCommunist strength in the country, will advocate a forwarddomestic programme including advanced financial measures andthe nationalisation of certain public services.  The leftwing of the Radicals and Socialist Republicans, anxiousrespecting their own position in the constituencies, will be considerably influenced by this programme.  These facts andthe conservatism of the Senate will always work against thelong maintenance in office of a government based on the Leftgroups, whether or not Socialists are members of it.Past experience shows that the result of Socialist pressureis usually to detach from a Left government a considerablesection of the Left Centre groups and the right wing of theRadicals and Socialist Republicans.  Even in the newChamber with its large Left majority this result would                                                 probably
probably bring a Left government down.     3o  Alternatively a &quot;concentration&quot; government based ona section of the Tarodeu group  (&quot;Republicains de Gauche&quot;)Left Centre and a section of the Radicals and&apos; SocialistRepublicans could,  in any immediate future,  at best musteronly a little over 300 votes.  It Would be faced on criticaloccasions by a junction of the Right, Socialists andCommunists and would always be exposed to the loss of the radical left wing which would imply its destruction.-.,     4.  To a lesser extent the same considerations will apply-in questions of foreign policy, though there the cleavagebetween the Socialists and the Radical right wing is slightly less pronounced than in domestic matters.     5.  It is important to realise that whatever may bethe case in theory and appearance, in practice the line ofcleavage in the new Chamber will run across and through the radical and Socialist Republican groups.  It is this lineof cleavage of which we shall have to take account in estimating the possibility of securing French acceptance ofour requirements-in foreign policy.  We should remember thatthe difficulty of li. Herriot or any President of the council will be to reconcile on the one side the views of people likeMM Caillaux, Albert Sarraut and Chautemps, who,  whatever theymay say in private,  are steeped in the tradition (though itmay be the best tradition) of French policy,  and, on theother side,  of men such as h%U Pierre Cot, Ualadier and LdonBlum who are internationalists of varying degree.  We should try to make use of the views of the latter;   but we shallfail to obtain agreement if we ignore what will undoubtedly be, by &apos; ar,  the dominant opinion.
B.   Preliminarjr forecast of attitude of Herriot          Government on foreign policy.     6,   The following forecast is based on the soundingstaken as to the attitude of the new leaders during the lastweek.   It must be remembered that they have not yet been inofficial touch with the departments.7enorations and Debts.     7,   It does not seem impossible to secure agreement onthe lines of the Chancellor of Exchequer&apos;s declaration ofFebruary 2nd 1932.   Such an agreement would probably requireto be prefaced by a reference to the treaty position and therights of the Creditor Powers.   French, consent to a longmoratorium seems more probable than to a final agreementlimited to Europe and excluding- the American debt and theGerman payments designed to cover it.   It is not clear thatthe &quot;solde&quot; will be abandoned if the claim to the ^nericandebt is maintained.   There may be an attempt to ask forcertain political guarantees from Germany in return for an *abandonment of the &quot;solde&quot;. (e. g.,  that money otherwise paidin reparation will not be used for rearmament,  that treatieswill be respected unless revised by mutual consent).    Onthe other hand such, a demand might be forestalled&apos; or renderedinnocuous by an agreement covering Central durope and dis-armanent as well as reparations.   It seems useless to askfor the abandonment of that part of the repartition paymentsdestined to cover the war debt payments unless  the latter are abandoned,   There is. ground for the view that a French                                               demand
demand for the maintenance of some payment as security againsta German economic revival could be successfully resisted.,Central Europe,     8.   The policy of foreign loans is in disrepute,   It ispossible that some special financial treatment could beobtained for Austria on the ground that her collapse as a&quot;protege&quot; of the League would react on the latter and becauseof fear of the &quot;Anschluss&quot;.   Provided Germany respects thetreaty scruples of the French in the natter of reparationsand gives evidence of a general desire for peaceful co-operation in future, the new government could probably be relied upon to show more regard for German susceptibilitiesin Central Europe.General currency and economic questions..    9.   Attention is drawn to    Germain-liar tin&apos;s view sentto Sir H, Vansittart on Lay 24th (see Part I of Section 6)aThere is certainly a feeling that an examination of thesequestions by the Lausanne Conference might help towards asettlement of the question of the American debt and possiblyof that which is constituted by the fear of eventual german economic expansion,   If it is desired to modify the Frenchquota policy., it seems necessary to know what policy is to besubstituted for it.   There is a wide tendency here to regardthat policy as part of the movement towards a better inter-national economic organisation,,^Disarmament.     10.   There will be strong pressure from the Socialistgroup for reduction of armaments expenditure;   and financialexigencies make some reduction imperative,    A 25 per cent reduction is mentioned by the more advanced elements.   Again
 by the  advanced  elements,  the possibility  of  some  concession on &quot;offensive weapons&quot; is  not denied;   and big guns, tanks and large submarines have been mentioned.   It is not  clear that some small  concession to Germany in the matter of  &quot;prohibited weapons&quot; would present insuperable difficulty.   The elements of  a solution of the Franco-Italian naval  question could pos- sibly be found in some special Mediterranean  agreement.   In any case the question can  be reopened with advantage.   It is possible that the Tardieu  security proposals will  be less seriously pushed..   There  is a strong desire in certain quarters for control of the manufacture of armaments British policy.     11.   It seems very desirable to give .   Kerriot private-r ly and unofficially some forecast of the attitude  of His :&apos;.ajesty&apos;s Government on all these questions..   The new leaders are not too clear as to what our policy and wishes are;  and there is a certain justification for the view that a more definite indication now of what we will and will not accept might make it easier for 1... Ferriot to define a moderate policy &quot;hen he meets the Chamber possibly on June  7th..    There isj ^ little doubt that,, if tactfully  explained within the next fewdays, a better knowledge of what our policy is would enable the advanced Left elements&apos; to bring pressure to bear on U. .Ferriot0British Embassy,      P ar i s 0                         May 2 8 th, 1932f
AHNEX,           Probable strength of groups in Chamber.RightPopular Democrats      ...   .,.....r.......    (very moderate views on foreign questions).Right Centre     (Tar(lieu group)Left Centre       ......     (Gauche Radicals, etc.)-Ll C-i- *tj   m m 9  c m m   4*4  * * *     (Socialist Radicals  and     Socialist Republicans)Extreme Left    Socialists    Communists   604approximate.106 16 90 45195140 12

</content>
</cab>
