<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/230/0 images: 352-483</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  June 1932.Copy No,   9CABINET.REPORT  ON FINANCIAL  QUESTIONS  IN  KENYA  BY                       LORD MOYNE.       MEMORANDUM BY THE  SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE  COLONIES.    I  CIRCULATE,  for  the information of my colleagues,  advance  copiesof the Report on Financial Questions in Kenya by Lord Moyne.  Publication hasbeen deferred  until^lfth June, in order  that it may  take place simultaneously in London and Kenya.   Copies are also being sent in advance to the Governmentof India.    It will be remembered  that Lord Moyne&apos;s mission was undertaken to carryout a recommendation made by  the Joint  Committee of Parliament on  close reunion in East Africa  (paragraph 105  (i) of  their Report), which is  in thefollowing terms :           &quot;105 (i).   The Committee have  had much  contradictory evidence as  to    the incidence of taxation, and as to the respective shares of that taxation    borne by the African, the Indian and the European communities.  They are    unable to express any clear  view as to how, in  fact, taxation is divided    between the various  races, and they consider that an  enquiry  into the    incidence of taxation under existing circumstances should be held at an early    date.  Such an  enquiry,  clearly, cannot be conducted by themselves.  The    Committee consider that there is sufficient evidence of its need to justify    them in recommending that one should be held by an independent authority    and  without delay.  It should include a careful  and detailed examination    of the financial situation with respect to          (a) the contribution made  to taxation, both direct and indirect,  by the              different racial communities;         (b) railway freights and import duties, with a view to discovering the              extent to which each community benefits or suffers by them;         (c)  the amount of  money expended in the interests of each community,              in particular on natives and non-natives; and        (d)  the degree and manner in which financial responsibility should be              conferred on the native councils.&quot;    The  main recommendations of the Report that the native contribution  to revenue cannot reasonably be increased at the present  time; that 50 per cent, of native direct taxation should be paid into a Native Betterment Fund; andthe Budget must be balanced by non-native  direct  taxation, i.e . into^ tax, wu.all be highly contentious.    I should not feel justified in  taking a decision on  the report  until I havereceived  the Governor&apos;s comments.  If the Governor agrees that  the facts asfound are substantially correct and that  the conclusions founded on  those facts are sound,  I think  the Government here  will have  to give him full  support incarrying  out  the  necessary  reforms.   But I   have  no illusions  as  to the unfavourable reception  which  the Report will receive from settlers in Kenyat.I think, therefore, I should bring the Report to the notice of my colleagues.                                                                 P. C.-L.    Colonial Office, June 9, 1932.SECRET.O.P. 196  (32).[7141]
Report by the Financial Commissioner           (LORD MOYNE)               on certain  QUESTIONS   IN           KENYA            -M^J 1932
Report by the Financial Commissioner           (LORD MOYNE)                on certain  QUESTIONS  IN           KENYA.             May, 1932
  All expenditure in connexion with the Commission, other thanthe cost  of printing the Report, was borne by the Governmentof Kenya.  The  cost of  printing and  publishing this Report isestimated by H.M. Stationery Office at  96.
V  XCONTENTS.                                                          Para.  Page  I. INTRODUCTION..........     ..     ..            1 XI -ADJUSTMENT OF RELATIONS BETWEEN COMMUNITIES.       Obligation to Native Races Security to Europeans..     2       2       Interpretation of Trusteeship   ..      ..     ..     ..     3       3       Afro-Asian  Relations   ..     ..      ..     ..     ..     4       3       Relations between Settlers and Natives..     ..     ..     5       4rn. CONTRIBUTIONS  TO TAXATION.       Racial Classification of Revenue       ..     ..     ..     6       4       Tourists..............     7       5       Comparison with previous years       ..     ....     8       5IV.-NATIVE TAXATION.       Hut and Poll Taxes     ..........     9       5       Widows......&apos;........10       5       Variation of Practice    ..     ..      ..     ..     . .    II       7       Duration of Exemption Certificates    ..     ..          12       7       Age of liability to Poll Tax     ........13       7       Objections to present Hut and Poll Taxes    ..     ..    14       8       Low standard of Native  Life   ..      ..     ..     ..    15       9       Necessitous Areas       ..     ..      ..     ..     ..    16       9       Native Resources ..     ..     ..      ..     ..     ..    17     11       Improvement in Native Standard of Life     ..     ..    18     12       Contrast between Native and European Production ..    19     13       Comparative Rigidity of Native Taxation in Kenya..    20     13       Proposed Transformation of Native Taxation     ..    21     13         Hut Tax      ..........     ..    21     14         Poll Tax       ............22     14         Livestock Tax Meat Factories      ..     ..          23     14       -  Cultivation Tax       ..........2&apos;4     16         Effect of proposed Changes   ...      ..     ..          25     16         No case for increase in Native Taxation    ..     ..    26     16 V. RAILWAY RATES.       Scope of Enquiry . .     ..     ..      ..     . .          27     17       Principle of Rating Policy     ..      ..     ..     . .    28     -17       Construction of  Branch Lines   ..      ..     ..     ..    29     17       Passenger-Train Fares   ..     ..      ..     ..     . .    30     IS       Parcel-Goods Rates     ..     . .      ..     ..     ..    31     18       Freight-Rates Policy    ..     .;      ......32     18       Export Rates    ..&quot;     ..........33     18       Unremunerative Rates   ..     ..      ..     ..     ..    34     19       Cotton Cloth and Blankets     ........35     19VI. IMPORT DUTIES.       Customs Union Protective Duties     ..     ..     ..    36     20       Unbleached Cotton Goods      ........37    .21       Balance of advantage between Communities  ..     ..    38     21       Free List..............    39     22       Fairness of Present Tariff      ......     ..    40     22VII. EXPENDITURE ON COMMUNITIES.       Racial Classification of Expenditure   ..     ..     ..    41     23       Basis of Classification Military and  Police   ..     ..    42     23       Indivisible Services     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    43     24111310)  Wt. 4122/2844 2000 6/32  Hw.  G.3                                 A 2
                         CONTENTS continued.VUL-Balance of Contributions and Services.                   Para.         Adequacy of Contributions     ..     ..     ..     ..    44         Necessity for different Standards of Service  ..     ..    45         Standards of Life compared    ..     ....     ..    46         Native Contributions   ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    47         Benefits from Colonial Services ..     ..     ..     ..    48         Natives bearing relatively greater burden    ..     ..    49         Exact balance unobtainable    ..     ..     ..     ..    50         Agricultural Subsidies   ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    51         Agricultural Credits     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    52         Communal Education Charges  ..     ..     ..     ..    53         Cost of European Education   ..-    ..     ..     ..    54         Goan Education ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    55         Ishaak Shariff and Darot Ismailia Communities     ..    56         Native Education       ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    57         Local Government Services    ..     ..     ..     ..    58         Road Finance    ..     ...   ..     ..     ..     . .    59         Basic Road-Grants      ..     ..     ..    ..     . .   60         Medical Services ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     . .    61         Importance of Native Agricultural Development   ..    62         Veterinary Research     ,.     ..     ..     ..     ..    63         Coffee Services   ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     . .    64         Applied Agricultural Research for Native Reserves and           Coast Province       ..     ..     ..     ..     . .    65         Agricultural Training Schools  ..     ..     &apos;. .     . .    66         Improvement of Sheep and Goats     ..     ..     ..    67  IX. Native Betterment.         Native taxable capacity ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    68         Need for ensuring minimum Native Services ..     ..   69         Proposal for Native Betterment Fund ..     ..     ..   70         Native Betterment Committee ..     ..     ..   &quot;  ..   71         Powers and responsibility of Committee     ..     ..   72         Necessity for  co-ordination illustrated  by needs of           Tanaland      ............73         Relations between Native Betterment Fund and Local           Native Councils  .    ..     ..     ..    ..     ..   74         Advantages of Grants-in-aid system   ..    ..     ..   75         Revenue of Native Betterment Fund ..    ..     ..   76         Insufficient provision in 1931 for backward areas   ..   77         Inequalities of treatment between Native and Settled           Areas   ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    ..     ..   7S         A fair settlement ..     ..     ..     ..    ..     ..   89         Loan Money for Native Betterment   ..    ..     ..   80         Administrative separation  of Communities not recom-           mended  ..     ..     ..    .-.     ..    ..     ..   81         Native Marketing Advisory Council   ..    ..     ..   82   X: Financial  Responsibility of Local Native Councils.         Organization     ..     ..    ..    ..    ..     ..   83         Comparison with Tanganyika and Uganda   ..     ..   84         No need for Provincial Councils in  Kenya  ..     ..   85         Constitution of Local Native Councils . .    ..     ..   86         Standard of Education and financial aptitude..     ..   87         Financial Resources     ..    ..    . .    .....   SS         Basis for Financial Assistance ..    ..    ..     ..   99         Communal Labour on Roads   ..    . .    ..     ..   90         Transfer of  responsibility for certain services..     ..   91
O &apos;-J J                        CONTENTS continued. XI. General Budgetary Position.        Supplementary Terms of Reference        Unbalanced Budgets          1929    ....          1930    ......          1931        Recoverable Expenditure from Surplus Balances        Causes of Financial Difficulty        Efforts for Economy        Savings partly non-recurrent        Need for further Retrenchment        Economy Committee        Divided Financial Responsibility        Control of Establishments        Colonial Regulations        Prospects for Out-turn of 1932        Prospective Deficit        Cash Position     . .        Prospects of Recovery        Yield of Direct Taxation        Yield of Indirect Taxation        Other Revenue        Debt Charges     ..    ..        Prospects summarized  . .;        Need for Fresh Taxation        Taxes on Land and Buildings        Problem of Income-Tax in Kenya        Light Non-Native Direct Taxation        Necessity for Balanced BudgetXII. Conclusions  and Recommendations.        Summary  . .     ..        Ac knowledgments. .Para.	Page92	4893	48&quot; 94	4995	4996	4997	4998	5099	50100	- 50101	51102	51103	52104	53105	53106	54107	54108	55109	55110	55111	55112	57113	57114	57115	58116	58117	; 59118	59119	60120	60121	62                           APPENDICES.1. Revenue and Expenditure in 1931.       Schedule 1. Summary  of  Revenue  collected  in  1931,           distinguishing Taxation Revenue from Other Revenue,           and  classifying contributions  of the  various  com-           munitiesSchedule 2. Detail of Schedule 1Schedule 3. Itemized  Table of  Receipts  from    Revenue,  1931    ..     ......Customs1931-Schedule 4. Classification  of   Expenditure  in    SummarySchedule 5. Expenditure  on Indivisible Services    Statement A Miscellaneous Services Expenditure    Statement B Contributions  to  Local  Government        Authorities    . .     ....Page63646881818283(11310)
* HX. 184, 1931 (Report).  H.L.  29, 1931 (Appendices).                      APPENDICES continued.                    Page 1. REVENUE AND EXPENDITURE IN 1931 continued.        Schedule 6. Expenditure on European Services   ..     ..      84        Schedule 7. Expenditure on Asiatic Services     ..     ..      84        Schedule 8. Expenditure   on   Non-Native  Indivisible            Services    ..     ..    ..    ..     ..     ..     ..      84        Schedttle 9. Expenditure on Native Services     ..     ..      So            Schedules 5-9.                Note No. 1. Public Debt........      85               , Note No. 2. Forestry     ........      87                Note No. 3. Administration      . .     ..     ..      88                Note No. 4. Agriculture  ..     ..     ..     ..      89                Note No. 5. Education   ..     ..     ..     ..      89                Note No. 6. Medical      ........      91                Note No. 7. Public Works........      95        Schedule  10. Racial  Balance  Sheet  of  Revenue  and            Expenditure in 1931    ..    ..     ..     ..     ..      97        Schedule  11. Statement  of  Re-imbursements  and  Cross-            entries appearing on both sides of 1931 Accounts     . .      93 2. NOTE ON CONTRIBUTIONS TO REVENUE IN KENYA BY THE NON-NATIVE      AND NATIVE COMMUNITIES IN 1931..........      99        (Comparable with Appendix No. 26 to the Report of the            Joint Select Committee on Closer Union in East Africa.*) 3. NATIVE CASH RESOURCES      ..    ..    ..     ..     ..     ..     107        (Nandi, Elgeyo, Mwimbi-Chuka, Masai, and Coast Province.) 4. OUTLINE OF UNIFORM MALE NATIVE POLL TAX ..     ..     ..     ..     Ill 5. OUTLINE OF NATIVE LIVESTOCK TAX    ........     ..     Ill 6. OUTLINE OF NATIVE CULTIVATION TAX..........     112 7. FINANCE OF NATIVE BETTERMENT FUND..........     113 8. TABLE OF REVENUE AND EXPENDITURE OF LOCAL NATIVE COUNCILS IN 1931     114 9. COMMUNAL LABOUR   ..     ..    ..    ..     ..     ..     ..     116        (Resolution of Kiambu Local Native  Council.)10. GENERAL BUDGETARY POSITION         TABLE-1.   REVENUE FIGURES  1926-1931  ..    ..     ..     117        TABLE 2.   COMPARATIVE EXPENDITURE FIGURES 1925-1931     1 IS        TABLE 3.   ALLOCATION OF  TOTAL  PUBLIC  DEBT  AND                    ANNUAL  CHARGES     ..     ..    ..     ..     120        TABLE 4.   PROBABLE  SHORT-FALL ON  1932 REVENUE ESTI-                    MATES    ..    ..           ..    -..     ..     121        TABLE 5.   ESTIMATE OF CASH POSITION AT 31ST DECEMBER,                     1932      ............     122
To  THE  RIGHT  HONOURABLE  SIR   PHILIP  CUNLIFFE-LISTER,  G.B.E., M.C., M.P., SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES.                     I.-INTRODUCTION.SIR,  YOU APPOINTED ME ON 28TH JANUARY,  1932, TO PROCEED AS FINANCIALCOMMISSIONER TO KENYA WITH THE FOLLOWING TERMS OF REFERENCE:       (1) TO ENQUIRE INTO THE MATTERS SPECIFIED IN PARAGRAPH 105 (I)    OF THE REPORT OF THE JOINT SELECT COMMITTEE ON CLOSER UNION    IN EAST AFRICA, VIZ.:         (a) THE CONTRIBUTION  MADE TO TAXATION,  BOTH DIRECT  AND      INDIRECT, BY THE DIFFERENT RACIAL COMMUNITIES ;        [b) RAILWAY  FREIGHTS AND IMPORT DUTIES,  WITH A VIEW TO      DISCOVERING THE  EXTENT TO WHICH EACH COMMUNITY BENEFITS      OR SUFFERS BY THEM ;        (C) THE  AMOUNT OF MONEY EXPENDED IN  THE INTERESTS OF      EACH COMMUNITY, IN PARTICULAR ON NATIVES AND NON-NATIVES;      AND        (d) THE DEGREE AND MANNER IN WHICH FINANCIAL RESPONSIBILITY      SHOULD BE CONFERRED ON THE NATIVE COUNCILS.      (2) SO FAR AS MAY BE NECESSARY FOR THE PURPOSES OF THE ABOVE    ENQUIRY TO CONSIDER THE GENERAL  FINANCIAL AND ECONOMIC SITUATION    OF THE COLONY AND PROTECTORATE OF KENYA ; AND      (3) TO MAKE A REPORT.  ON  7TH  APRIL, 1932,  YOU  ISSUED  A SUPPLEMENTARY INSTRUCTION INTHE  FOLLOWING TERMS :       &quot;  IN ORDER TO MAKE IT CLEAR THAT YOU ARE AUTHORIZED TO REVIEW    THE  GENERAL BUDGETARY POSITION  OF THE COLONY, I HAVE ADDED THE    FOLLOWING  TO  THE TERMS  OF  REFERENCE OF YOUR ENQUIRY &apos; TO    MAKE RECOMMENDATIONS  AS TO  THE RE-ADJUSTMENT OF TAXATION    AND EXPENDITURE IF EXAMINATION OF THE PRESENT POSITION UNDER    THE  ORIGINAL TERMS OF REFERENCE DISCLOSES A CASE FOR CHANGE &apos;.&quot;  I  ARRIVED AT NAIROBI, TRAVELLING BY IMPERIAL AIRWAYS, ON 2ND MARCH,1932.  I RETURNED TO ENGLAND BY AIR, LEAVING KENYA ON 8TH MAY.  DURING MY STAY IN KENYA I RECEIVED VERBAL  AND WRITTEN evidence from ALL AVAILABLE SOURCES OF INFORMATION,  OFFICIAL  AND UNOFFICIAL,INCLUDING THE REPRESENTATIVES OF THE DIFFERENT NATIVE AND NON-NATIVECOMMUNITIES.  I DISCUSSED MATTERS  WITH THOSE WHO EITHER IN THEIROWN OPINION OR IN MINE APPEARED LIKELY TO ASSIST THE ENQUIRY.  I am glad TO RECORD MY APPRECIATION OF  THE ASSISTANCE WHICH WAS FREELYOFFERED BY ALL.(11310)A 4
(   I visited by road the Local Native Councils of South Nyeri, Meru, Kajiado,  Nandi, North  Kavirondo, Marakwet, Elgeyo, Digo,  and Machakos.   From  Mombasa I  was able to see something of the less accessible  coastal  districts by flying  northwards  to  Kilifi, Malindi, and Lamu, thence up the estuary of the Tana River as far as Ngao, and  southwards  to Vanga and the  Tanganyika border. I also visited Uganda, Tanganyika, and Zanzibar, in which territoriesJ. was  enabled  by the  courtesy of the respective Governors  and British Resident to obtain much useful information from the  Heads of the  Administration which provided  valuable materials for corn- paring the methods of Native Administration in the four territories. At Zanzibar I had a useful discussion with Mr. G. V. Maxwell, late Chief Native Commissioner of Kenya. On the way out from England the Civil Secretary  at  Khartoum  was good  enough  to give me information as to systems of native government and taxation in the Sudan.   The  Colonial  Office  obtained  at  my request valuable memoranda by officers  of  the Administrative  Service  in Southern Nigeria as  to  the assessment and  collection  of the General  Tax (&quot; Haraji&quot;). II. ADJUSTMENT  OF RELATIONS BETWEEN COMMUNITIES.    1. I have not ventured on  the vexed ground of definition of the Dual  Policy in East Africa*, or &quot; the complementary development of native and non-native communities,&quot; and  to attempt to do so would be outside my authority.  I have been content to take the various declarations  as they stand  and to assume that the Imperial Parliament agrees that there is room for all races now established in Kenya to  achieve full  development within the  Colony and  Pro- tectorate.   I have understood it  to be the main purpose  of my enquiry to satisfy the anxiety of Parliament that a fair balance of taxation and  benefits  be achieved between the  various  racial communities.                    Obligation to native races.    2. The Joint Select Committee  on Closer Union in East Africa  defined the primary obligation to the native races as followsf :-         &quot; The principle of trusteeship implies not only the avoidance     of direct  injustice  to  the natives as individuals,  but also the     more positive obligation to afford to the natives,  as a race, both     time and  opportunity to  develop their latent  capacities and     play such part as they may eventually prove capable of playing     in the ultimate  destiny of  the country.  Every opportunity for     advancement should moreover be afforded to such natives as     may reach a higher level than is common to their race.&quot;    * Cmd. 2904 (1927).    t Report of Joint Select Committee on Closer Union, Vol. I, paragraph 5S.
                     Security to Europeans.  The Joint Select Committee further observed^ that :      &quot; While any discrimination, by means of subsidies or other    privileges, customs duties, railway rates, or otherwise, designed    to  favour unduly any one community is of necessity open to    serious criticism, at the same time it is most important  to give    adequate security to those  Europeans  and other non-natives    who have settled in the country, and who have made a  perma-    nent home there, often  under very difficult and trying condi-    tions.&quot;Interpretation  of principle  of trusteeship  in  terms  of concrete                            services.  3.  In approaching  this  enquiry an  attempt must necessarily be made to interpret the principle of trusteeship for the natives asenunciated above in  terms of concrete services.  In  the first place,it would seem that the objective to which policy for native affairs should  be directed is  a general  improvement of  the standard of native  life.  In a material sense this may be translated to  mean aco-ordinated effort to improve the economic conditions of the native,the general level of his intellectual attainments and domestic life,and the physical health of himself, his wives, and children.   On theeconomic side there  can be  little doubt that amongst the greatestneeds of the majority of native producers in Kenya to-day is trainingin agriculture (including animal husbandry) and increased  accessi-bility of markets, with  adequate  means of comm.unication  andtransport by road and rail.   On the social side, education, which iseagerly demanded on  behalf of their people by many Chiefs andLocal Native Councils, is desirable, not only as in civilized com-munities as an end in itself, but also as a powerful auxiliary for themedical and sanitary services in combating that ignorance of healthlaws which levies such a heavy toll of suffering and of life, and alsoin spreading knowledge  as   to improved methods  of agricultural production and skill  in craftsmanship.                      Afro-Asian relations.  4. Before proceeding to discuss the main problem of the compara-tive financial treatment of the native and non-native communities,it is convenient here to draw attention to the changing relations ofthe African and  Asiatic communities under the stress of growingsocial and economic competition.  The gradual attainment of a higher level of education and civilization by the African is being accompaniedby a claim to equal treatment with the Asian in the matter of employ-* lb., paragraph 74.
ment, pay, and conditions in the public services.  The time will surelycome in Kenya, as it has already come in Uganda, when considerable numbers of Africans will be available who will be just as well qualifiedas Asians to man the lower ranks of the Government service.  Amatter concerning the opportunities for employment in the colonial administration was brought to my notice at Nairobi and Mombasaby two independent groups of East African natives, one from withinthe Government service and one from outside.  It was represented that there is a racial discrimination between the African and Asianclerical classes in the  Government servjce.  It is a reasonable claim that entrance into the clerical class should depend on efficiency  astested by examination, and by promotion for merit from within theservice in suitable cases, and not by race.              Relations between settlers and natives.  5. It is hardly necessary to state that orderly improvement in thestandard of native life need in no way impair the excellent relations which now exist between the British  and African communities.After a stay of about ten weeks in East Africa I am much impressed by the amount of good feeling evident between the natives and settlers,and my observations  fully accord with  the statement of the ChiefNative Commissioner given at the end of his  Annual Report for1930 :-      &quot; Members of the general public have shown a consistent and    increasing interest in all that concerns native welfare.  Probably    nowhere  in the  world are relations between  employers and    employed better than in Kenya.  But quite apart from that the    concern  of  the unofficial population for  the development  of    native communities has manifested itself  in many and diverse    ways and is a particularly noteworthy factor in the social and    political life of the Colony, and one which I am glad to be able    unreservedly to acknowledge.&quot;           HI. CONTRIBUTIONS  TO  TAXATIONS               Racial classification of revenue.  6. Examination of the racial contributions to revenue has beenmade easier by the attention given to this subject in recent years.Administrative Officers have lately followed the routine of indicatingracial classification on taxation receipt counterfoils.  The StatisticalDepartment has thus been enabled to prepare Schedules 1 and 2 of appendix 1 (pp. 63 to 67) to show in summary and  in detail  thecontributions of the various racial communities under the separateheads of Taxation and other Revenue for the year 1931.* Terms of Reference, 1 (a).
  Schedule 3 of Appendix 1 (pp. 68 to 80) gives an itemized table of receipts from Customs Revenue.  The allocation as between racialcommunities is an estimate by the Commissioner of Customs basedon long experience of the  habits of consumption throughout  theColony.  It has been submitted to  detailed independent criticism and I am satisfied that it  gives a  result which though obviouslysubject to considerable error in  detail may be  accepted as a  fairapproximation in its total figures.                    Revenue from tourists.  7. No attempt  has  been made to  distinguish under EuropeanRevenue  between that paid by  residents in the Colony and thatderived from tourists.  Although it might be possible to arrive at an allocation for items such as  game  and gun licences, there is no satisfactory basis for estimating the tourist share of import duties,  etc.                Comparison with previous years.  8. The Statistical Officer has prepared a memorandum which is printed as Appendix 2 (page 99)  in which he discusses the changes which are shown in the above-mentioned tables as compared withthe position as laid before the Joint Select Committee and published as Appendix 26 to their Report.  Before  discussing whether the distribution of taxation is fair asbetween communities it will be convenient to examine the system of direct native taxation and to consider whether the present methods and incidence can be justified.                  IV. NATIVE TAXATION.                      Hut and poll taxes.  9. Direct native taxation still remains in the primitive form ofhut and poll taxes and every adult male native has to pay one orthe other, but not both.  Three matters incidental to the administration of these taxes were brought to my notice.                     Liability of widows.  10. The suggestion was made  that no tax should be  levied  onhuts occupied by widows.  Under the Native Hut and Poll Tax Ordinance of 1910 the hut taxis payable by the owner of every hut.  Though women are notexempted as such, I am advised that under the laws of Kenya theyare not in practice liable because native women can only themselveshold property as trustees for their families.
  The hut tax, unlike the poll tax, is a form of property tax,  and,being levied according to the number of huts owned by the taxpayer,varies to some extent with the ability to  pay.   Wives are still avery popular form of capital investment, especially as their valuehas lately appreciated owing to the relative increase in the numbersof cattle which still remain the  usual form of native  currency.Women also yield a valuable income  by working with their children in the fields, and  they can therefore fairly be taken as  a  simplemeasure of the taxable capacity of the  hut owners.  The incidence of the tax was discussed with the nine Local  NativeCouncils which I visited, and also with many officers responsiblefor native  administration.   The  objection to the  tax  as regardsits incidence measured by  the number of women for whom a tax-payer is responsible  was by no means chiefly on  the ground of its application to widows.   The older and richer natives object to the tax because they feel that it is, in effect, one on wives, and  they desire  to see the tax abolished and a universal poll tax substituted.I found, however, much  opposition amongst the younger  mento this suggestion when it was realized that the  poll  tax would necessarily have to be increased to make up for the revenue to be sacrificed by the proposed abolition or modification of the hut tax.To accept even the smaller suggestion of exempting all huts occupiedby widows would mean a loss of revenue difficult to measure.  While the hut tax is in force I can see no case for exempting allwidows as such.  To do so would indeed do much to  destroy the limited discrimination  between rich  and poor which the  tax  noweffects, and would go far to make it indistinguishable in its incidencefrom a poll  tax.  The justification for taxing according to  the number of  hutsowned is that a man with many huts will, generally speaking, havea proportionate number of people to work for him and contribute towards his  taxable resources.  There is no more  reason to exempt from  taxation the wealth produced  by the agricultural work of a young and able-bodied widow than there  is to exempt the samewoman&apos;s produce before the death of her  husband. The customswith  regard to re-marriage vary very considerably between the tribes, but it  is the general rule  for every woman to have somemale  guardian, and  even in tribes such as the Marakwet, Elgeyo,Lumbwa and  Nandi,  where  widows  do  not generally re-marry,they  are often well  off relatively to the rest of  the population ifthey have several sons and daughters and enjoy an interest  in aconsiderable number of livestock.   The inheritance of old widowswithout resources and  past the time  of work is, on  the other hand,an undoubted liability and cannot fairly be  justified as a ground for additional taxation.  It is, however, very difficult to find anymethod of discrimination suitable for securing uniform treatmentof such cases.
           Variation of practice in grant of exemption.  11.  I found some variation in the principles followed by DistrictOfficers in granting exemption from the tax.  The Native Hut andPoll Tax Ordinance gives general power to remit taxes leviable inthe case of any person who is without sufficient means to pay thewhole amount of such tax and is unable to obtain employment byreason of age or infirmity.   Sympathetic use is generally made ofthis power of exemption in favour of old persons of both  sexesincapacitated from production by age or other causes.  I can findno completely satisfactory formula for defining what should begrounds for exempting old women in particular, but, to preventall possibility of any harsh exaction of tax on  account of widowswho are not a source of revenue but merely a liability, I recommendan amendment of the law to incorporate the following grounds of exemption  which were recommended  by  a meeting  of  DistrictCommissioners in Kavirondo in 1930 :       &quot; If a widow is inherited by a man after she has passed child-   bearing age he should not be called upon to pay.      If  a widow is young and  capable  of  bearing children her   inheritor should pay.  If a widow, now old, was inherited when   of child-bearing age, the inheritor should pay.&quot;              Duration of  exemption certificates.  12.  Another grievance has been brought to my notice in connexionwith tax remissions on the ground that District Commissioners oftengive exemption  for only a year at a time, and  that it is a  greathardship  for old and  infirm  people  to  have  to  make  repeatedapplications at the time of yearly tax-collection.  It appears from the ordinance that there is no limitation to the time for which exemptionmay be given, but as there seems to be some variation of practice inthe matter I recommend that instructions be given to administrative officers that they should not hesitate in suitable cases  to grantexemption for life to old, infirm, and indigent persons.                  Age of liability to  poll tax.  13.  Representations were made to me that the age  at which polltax becomes payable should be raised from 16 to 18.  This suggestion seems  to  have  originated  in the  Kikuyu area where natives  are in  close  contact  with Europeans and  haverealized that liability to the poll tax begins only at 18 among thenon-African population.  The systems of native and non-nativetaxation are, however, necessarily different throughout,  and thisparticular discrimination may also be justified by a definite racialdistinction.  Natives mature at an earlier age than Europeans and
are capable of doing a man&apos;s work at 16, at which age non-nativesare still immature. Although the Ordinance provides for collectionfrom the &quot; apparent age of 16 &quot; the tax is in practice collected fromthe time when the native is looked upon as mature  according totribal  custom.  No registration of births is in force  and nativesrarely have exact knowledge of their age.  The rite of circumcisionhowever takes place at about the age of 16 and is considered as the mark  of having  attained man&apos;s estate.  The  physical appearance of natives varies little  between the  ages  of  16 and  18.   To fixliability to tax  at the  later age, besides involving great practical difficulty, would lead to a loss of revenue of about   40,000 perannum.  Such remission would become very unpopular as soon asit was realized that it would have to be made up  partly  by othertaxpayers  less able to  earn the  money  than  able-bodied youngmen between the ages of 16 and 18.       Objections to existing system of hut aud poll taxes.  14.  Even if the provisions for collecting hut tax are amended as suggested,  I am of opinion that this system of taxation is no longersatisfactory and should be transformed or replaced as soon as possible.Owing to  the increase  of monogamy the  graduation of  the tax-according to means is becoming less and less effective, and as the natives advance in civilization its defects are becoming more obvious.If a whole  family and  their visitors sleep in one house, one tax onlyis payable, but if separate huts are provided for children and gueststhree taxes become due. The tax therefore discourages the improve-ment of housing conditions and is an incitement to overcrowding.If the hut tax is to be modified  and finally  replaced by a morescientific tax according to ability to pay, it is advisable at the sametime to separate it from the poll tax which  was grafted upon itshortly after its introduction.  Hut and poll tax has been collected since 1922 at the uniform rateof Shs.12 throughout the Colony, except in the Masai Province wherethe tax is Shs.20  for the Masai and-Shs.10 for the Wanderobo tribes,and the Northern Frontier and Turkana Provinces where it is leviedat Shs.10 and Shs. 6 respectively.  Kenya is inhabited by a large number of tribes of different racialorigin, with varying customs and unequal in their intelligence and capacity, for improvement.  Some  have been  brought into muchcloser contact with civilization than  others and marked contrastsbetween the economic conditions of various areas are already evident.With the development of communications and of markets, differences between the taxable capacity of districts is increasing.  Whereas itis easy for natives living near towns&apos;or railways to turn their crops and livestock into money  for the payment of taxes, there is muchgreater difficulty in the areas which are less favourably placed.
                  Low standard of native life.  15.  An examination of native  life close  to  Nairobi and other european markets gives no indication of the primitive conditions andextreme poverty found in areas which have so far been little affectedby civilization.  It is difficult to decide whether ignorance or povertyis the greater obstacle  to improvement  in  native conditions  and health.  Even when natives have been taught by European employers or in the schools the use of soap and the elements of sanitation theyare often  content  to leave  their  families in  dirt and ignorance,and are apt themselves to revert  to their original state and spendtheir earnings not on improving their surroundings but in adding tothe number of their wives and livestock.  Progress must thereforeinevitably be slow and can only  be a matter of the cumulativereinforcement of civilizing influences and  the  gradual  defeat  of deep-rooted prejudices and superstitions.  In this advance education is an invaluable auxiliary provided that  it does not take the easyline of too much literary training  and avoids the danger of makingthe native discontented with the conditions of an agricultural life onwhich his general advancement must continue to depend.  education is however now provided by the Government on wise lines. Besidesbeing an invaluable civilizing influence it lays special stress on trainingin agriculture and handicrafts.  The wisdom of this policy is obviouswhen it is considered how primitive and insanitary are the domesticarrangements in the Native Reserves and how devoid is the averagenative of the knowledge and means with which to improve them.  The native hut  is  an ideal habitation for  carriers  of infectivedisease such as rats and insects  and other vermin.  Even whereeducation is bringing knowledge of a better type of housing, fewnatives possess the means to get proper roofing material or to buildwell-lit,  rectangular houses which would enable them to discouragethe attentions of insect pests by the use of beds, tables, and chairs.The lack of domestic utensils such as plates and  spoons facilitatesthe communication of internal parasites.  Mosquito nets, essential in many areas to the prevention of malaria, are beyond the means ofthe great majority  of natives.  Civilization  is,  however,  slowlyadvancing among natives, and they will gradually learn to profit bythe benefits which it  can bring to mental and physical well-being.                       Necessitous areas.  16. Meru may be taken as an example of a back area where thenative is now meeting with great  difficulty in finding  money withwhich to pay taxes.  The administrative centre, close to the boundary of the Native Reserve, is nearly sixty miles from rail-head at Nanyuki.Although produce is exchanged within the  area  partly by barter,taxes are only  accepted in money, and the  necessary currency can
hardly be obtained  except either by selling to the local Indiantraders for export from the area, or by the earnings of those who goto work in  the settled districts.  In 1928 and  1929 the Districtsuffered famine owing to locusts and drought, and the difficulties ofthe population have been increased by the heavy falls in demand and prices for native produce.  This has either rendered the cropsunsaleable or made it necessary for natives to dispose of from  two Ito four times the quantity which was sufficient in 1928 to raise the necessary money for taxation.  The following figures which were given me independently by twoof the largest Indian traders, and have since been confirmed fromtheir books, show how greatly the real burden of taxation has been increased although its nominal money-value has remained  the same.They apply to the only  four  local products  which are of sufficientvalue to bear the cost of transport which is  Shs. 1 - 50 per ton-mileto  Nanyuki and thence by  rail.  As the cost of transport  and merchants&apos; profit remain constant, the whole drop in price is passed on to the native producers :                      Price paid to                      native in                    Meru per load                      of  60 lb.                        Shs.Nkinna (green gram)        192S              10        1932                2-50Price  realized in Nairobi.    Shs.       15        4-50Njahe  (beans)        1928        193252-504 to 4-50Ghee (native butter)   Per frasila (36 lb.)                         Shs.1928193257 to 58   19  Shs.61 to 6322 to 25Cattle hides        1928        193236 to 37    4Price realized in Mombasa.    Shs.  40  to 43   6  to 6-50  Goat skins which were bought at the price of Shs. 22 for 20 skinsin 1928 are now unsaleable in Mombasa.  During tax collection 1year the price of bullocks fell to from Shs. 15 to 30 each as comparedwith from Shs. 30 to 50 each in 192S.
  The fall in prices and the increased burden of real taxation hasdestroyed  the natives&apos; purchasing-power for the blankets,  cotton piece-goods,  and &quot; jembes,&quot; or hoes, for which there was a demanduntil 1928.  On my visit  it was noticeable that far fewer nativeswere wearing blankets and strips of calico than I had seen in other districts.   Much propaganda  had recently been directed to  theobject of increasing the production of the native by substituting the&quot; jembe &quot; for the wooden digging-stick.   Although these implementscost only Shs. 2 and natives are now aware of the advantage theyafford as compared with the older methods, their purchase is impededby lack of cash.  Ploughs, cultivators, and harrows, costing  about 3 apiece,  and carts costing about  8 are now far beyond the meansof the natives, yet their use would be of great benefit.   opportunities for earning money by working outside the Reserves are now greatlydecreased  owing to the fall in the demand for  labour among thesettlers.  Reports by the District Commissioners  of Nandi, Elgeyo, Embu(Mwimbi and Chuka) and by  the  Provincial Commissioners of theMasai and Coast Provinces, printed as Appendix No. 3 (page 107),show that the case of Meru does not stand alone.  In contrast tothe position of such Districts, where distance from markets is causingdifficulty in  turning crops and livestock into the currency needed for paying taxes, I found other areas where, in spite of the fall inprices,  there were clear evidences of prosperity.  All things con-sidered I am of opinion that  the  present amount of direct nativetaxation could be collected without hardship  if the  incidence oftaxation were transformed so as to  vary according to taxable ability.                       Native resources.  17. No  reliable  figures  exist on the subject of native resources,and estimates which are often quoted as to average income shouldbe accepted with the greatest reserve.   Although rough estimates of agricultural production in the Native Reserves have been published,no firm foundation yet exists on which to base reliable opinions.  In this  connexion I explored the basis of the figures alleged inthe Report of the Kenya Labour Commission of 1927 to give a fan-average for  the cash value of native production in the Reserves.An examination  of  the  departmental  files and the  criticisms of administrative Officers in touch with the  Reserves have disclosedhow misleading it would be to accept any such estimate as  a truepicture of present conditions.  The Labour Commission  consisting of experienced agriculturistsand  business men was set up to examine the needs of the  Colony&apos;for labour outside the Reserves. For comparison with the conditionsof native  life in  European areas  they gave an estimate of average
cash-returns received by an assumed family or producing-unit of fourand one-third persons inside the  Reserves.  The validity of theestimate depends on the accuracy of the agricultural and statisticalassumptions  on which they were based, and  these assumptionshave been strongly contested by the Native Administration, whohave  independent and  certainly not  less reliable  sources  ofinformation.  The  Director  of Agriculture  has prepared for the  purpose  ofthis enquiry  entirely different  figures  founded not  merely  on estimates as in 1927, but on the result of recent definite computationsof crop  yield obtained  by inter-planting and other methods  of cultivation from  the  more productive  soils of the Nyanza andKikuyu Provinces. These new figures show a much lower estimateof the average proportion of produce  sold off the shamba than thaton which the calculations of the Labour Commission were based.He adds the reservation that in other  areas with less productive soilthe &quot; figures of production furnished would not be  attained.   Thereare certain areas  with small populations in which  production isbarely sufficient for the maintenance of the population and wherefood shortages  periodically  occur.  There  are  also large areasinhabited by purely pastoral tribes to which these  figures  of pro-duction do not apply.&quot;  Bearing these limitations in mind and also the consideration thata large and varying proportion of production is not turned into cashat all, but if sold off the shamba is the subject of a barter transaction,and in  view also of the great  variations in wealth as between individuals, the  danger  of  relying  on  average  figures becomesapparent.  After careful  enquiry and examination  of information available since 1927, I therefore endorse the view expressed by the kenya Government, at the time, that the validity of the average figure for native  production in  the  Reserves as  published in theReport of the Labour Commission is open to so much criticism thatit cannot possibly be made the basis of any conclusive argument.  Accurate information on this subject is of great importance, notonly for the purpose of ascertaining taxable capacity, but also as afoundation for wise policies of  development.  The Chief  NativeCommissioner in  August,  1931,  issued  instructions  to  ProvincialCommissioners to prepare reports  in the nature of economic surveys.              Improvement in native standard of life.  IS. I  was  assured  by  many  impartial observers with long experience in the country, including several missionaries, that in the districts  in closest contact with European civilization and marketsthe native standard of living has very markedly improved during
recent years. Even, however, if such increase of wealth were easilymeasured, accepted European tests Of taxable capacity would  bemisleading if applied to native conditions in Kenya.        Contrast between Native and European production.  19. Modern industrial  organization has not yet begun to affectproduction in the native areas.  Native  craftsmanship  and villageindustries highly developed in other parts of  Africa hardly exist in Kenya.  Native capacity to pay taxes therefore remains  far lessfixed and measurable than in  the  case of non-native communities.European production is generally based on the maximum economiclevel of output and the wage-earner strives to secure  the greatestreward obtainable in return for his  regular effort.  The Africannative, however, does not produce at the same full pressure. Thevolume of output is far below the maximum and is regulated mainly by the need to provide the bare necessities of life.   Natives living in their Reserves do not need to work for a living wage.  Wantsare still few and primitive livestock and wives remain practically theonly form of investment  and accumulation of wealth.  Under theseconditions, natives pay their taxes not out of  a fixed income butby means of additional production in the Reserves or, alternatively,they may choose to earn the money by a few weeks&apos; work in settledareas.        Comparative rigidity of native taxation in Kenya.  20. Whereas hut and poll tax has  been collected since  1912 atfour different rates in Kenya, there has been a much greater variation in the neighbouring territories. In Tanganyika, for instance, eightdifferent  rates are in force varying from  Shs. 4 to  Shs.  15, andfrequent  changes are made according to the  relative plenty  orscarcity of crops.  I am advised that no serious difficulty or dis-content would  be caused  in&apos;  Kenya if  the same  elastic methodswere to be applied and if not only varying rates but also, as suggestedbelow,  different  systems  of taxation were  to be  in force in neigh-bouring areas.  At the same time, under existing conditions in Kenya, it cannotbe expected  that the change-over to a  fairer system  of taxationwill be altogether popular. Natives are  accustomed to the  present arrangements and, while those whose  burdens are reduced willremain inarticulate,  those who have to pay more will naturallycomplain.  This however is no  sufficient ground for perpetuatingthe present  ill-adjusted  system.          Proposed transformation of native taxation.  21.  Increased flexibility and closer adaptation to taxable capacitymight  be achieved by  the  following  changes which  are hereindicated only in outline.
                            Hut Tax.  Hut and poll  tax should be  varied according to the  taxable capacity of each District, the rate varying between, say, Shs. 6 perhut in the remote and poorer Districts and  Shs. 20 in the richerDistricts where the present tax is borne without difficulty.  Whenthe new  uniform  poll tax (see below) is brought into force, the huttax should be reduced to a rate varying between Shs. 2 and Shs. 14according to  District (cp. para. 25).                            Poll tax.  22. Poll tax as now collected should be replaced as soon as possible by a uniform adult  male poll tax at Shs.  6, collected by means ofstamps to be affixed to the registration  certificate (Appendix 4,page 111).  This change would solve many difficulties now occasioned by collecting poll tax in the locations.  Men who are absent workingfar away from their villages are believed now  sometimes to  paytwice over, the father in the Reserve and the son at his work, eachwithout  the  other&apos;s knowledge.   In spite  of all the efforts madeto trace  men, and of much correspondence between administrative officers,  many  also avoid  payment  altogether,  because  of thedifficulty of verifying, in a centre such as Mombasa, how many ofthe 10,000 up-country natives working  there  have already paid the tax  in their villages.  The separation of hut and poll tax  would also greatly simplifychecking the hut tax as receipts could then be left in the hut as evidence of payment instead of being carried away to other Districts.It often  happens at present that men working outside, the Reservetake hut-tax receipts away as  evidence  that  they have already paid tax and are not again liable.  I am  assured that this changeof method when fully applied will immediately save a great amountof labour to  District Officers,  and  when  the cultivation tax (seeparagraph 24) is also in force it will do away with the necessity of taxcollection in villages by European officers.   It is estimated by theChief Registrar of Natives that the additional work in his office couldbe carried out by six to eight African clerks, and that the expenses ofthe additional staff and other necessary incidentals would certainly be more than covered by the closer collection of tax.  Owing to thenumber  of temporary registration certificates now in circulation thechange-over to the new method here suggested could necessarily beachieved neither immediately nor simultaneously throughout allDistricts.                          Livestock tax.   23. Native livestock tax as outlined in Appendix 5 (page 111) shouldbe instituted as  a  tax on  wealth only, applicable over and above a certain free allowance of livestock  sufficient to provide the necessi-ties of life.  It should enable a greater differentiation of  taxation
 according to means and should allow of relative lightening of burdens upon the poorer Districts.  While the hut tax differentiates  against the  native who  invests in many wives, it is unjust that he who receives the price in livestock of many daughters should escape an equivalent burden.  This tax would have an additional advantage in discouraging the over-stocking  of native  pastures,  which  in  certain  Districts  is becoming an acute problem since  British rule has prevented the raiding  of cattle, and  the natural check by animal  disease has to some extent been brought under control.   No census of livestock has been attempted in the Native Reserves, but the Administration estimates  that cattle have increased from 4  million in 1924 to at least 5 million in 1931, while sheep and goats increased from 6 to 7 million.    Livestock owned by  native squatters on European farms now amount to 223,584 cattle, 191,671 sheep,  and 285,000 goats.  It has been suggested that the collection of such a tax would be hampered owing to the difficulty of finding markets and that its imposition must  wait  for the establishment of meat factories to deal with native cattle.                        Meat factories.  The experience of Tanganyika in this matter is not encouraging.A factory has been established at Mwanza in which it is hoped that 10,000 cattle will be dealt with every year.  Their quality, however,is such that the price paid to native stock owners has now fallen to Shs.6-50 per head.  As  the  Government have  to subsidize  the factory to the extent of  3,000 a year, practically the whole amount which is paid at present prices to the native seller comes indirectlyfrom Government funds.   It is probable that the Masai would notsell their stock for so low a  price as Shs.6-50 and would prefer toslaughter them so as to  dispose of the hides after consuming the meat. Conditions would have to improve very materially to justifythe establishment of meat factories in Kenya.  Although the problemof marketing of native cattle will need to be watched, I am informedthat practically all animals which are offered for sale, now findpurchasers.  The researches of Dr.  Orr and Dr. Gilks suggest that many tribes suffer from a deficiency of animal protein.  Propagandaamong native consumers in favour  of a mixed diet may thereforebe justified for the improvement of their health and would help toensure a sufficient market for cattle sold for tax payment.   The  Ormsby Gore  Commission  reported*  to the effect that  itwould be unjust to impose  an additional tax on  the chief form of native wealth unless a corresponding tax is imposed  on non-natives. If  another recommendation!  of that  Commission  in favour  of a* Cmd.23S7, page 32.t lb., page 175.
non-native income-tax be also adopted there will  no  longer beany just ground for grievance on the part of natives, as the nativeand non-native systems of taxation are entirely  different and theonly common principle that need be considered is that both shouldbe based on reasonably equivalent sacrifice.                         Cultivation tax.  24. Native cultivation  tax (Appendix 6, page 112) should besubstituted  for the hut  tax, at  first  experimentally in the more advanced and  most suitable Districts, but eventually throughoutthe Native Reserves.   If this policy be adopted it might be well foran official familiar with the system of cultivation and cattle taxesin force in Nigeria to be lent to Kenya to advise how they could best be adapted  to local conditions.                   Effect of proposed changes.                  j  25. Of the above changes those outlined in paragraphs 21 and23 are the most urgent and could be applied without delay;  thosedescribed in paragraphs 22  and 24 though  equally desirable wouldinvolve longer  preparation.   The  actual   regrading  of  taxationbetween the various areas would be a matter of careful and gradualadjustment.  The halving of the poll tax from its present general level  of  Shs.12, owing to the relatively small proportion of thesetaxes  collected,  would not in  itself  have much  effect  on the totals  to be  made up  from  the two  other forms of taxation.In certain of the Districts which were visited  and where the taxesare  recorded separately the figures indicate that a  probable ratiomay be about four hut taxes to one poll tax, and, if this experiencebe found to  be a fair sample for the whole Colony, the loss caused byhalving the poll tax could be made up by substituting for the presenthut and poll tax of Shs.12 a  total payment of Shs. 13-50 for the owner of a single  hut, made up of Shs.6 uniform poll tax and Shs.7-50payable on the hut.  It must not be understood, however, that thisaverage would  actually be applied because  the total native burdenof direct taxation should be spread, according to the local resourcesof Districts, between  the hut or  cultivation  tax and the nativelivestock tax.             No  case  for increase in native taxation.  26. I wish to emphasize that these changes are recommended not for the purpose of any  immediate increase in the total yield of nativetaxation but  so as to  secure  adequate   differentiation betweenDistricts according to their taxable capacity  and between individualsaccording to their relative wealth.
                   V.-RAILWAY  RATES.*                       Scope of enquiry.  27. I have thought it well to interpret the Terms  of Referencerather narrowly  in  view of the appointment of  a Railway Com-missioner to consider the larger questions of inter-colonial railway rates and railway finance raised in paragraph 46  of the Report ofthe Joint Select  Committee.  My enquiry into the fairness of thepresent railway rates as between the different racial  communitieshas therefore been limited to an examination as to whether services which are used mainly  or entirely for any one race are charged inaccordance  with the accepted rating principles,  or whether these principles have been neglected so as to confer an  unfair advantageor, alternatively, to impose unduly heavy charges upon any racialcommunity.                 Principles of rating policy.  28. These principles have been enunciated as follows :       (a) Get traffic.  The more traffic carried the less it costs to    carry.      (b) Charge no rate so high as to stop the traffic from passing.      (c) No rate  to be so low as  not to  cover the additional    cost incurred by the railway in dealing with the traffic to which    the rate applies.  The principle (b)  may be taken as the maximum rate based oncapacity to pay, and (c) the minimum fixed by the price at whichthe railway can afford to take business.  There is no evidence to show that the existing rates have been fixedother than in accordance with the above principles of sound railwayadministration.                 Construction of branch lines.  29.  So far as railway construction is concerned the advantageshave been fairly divided between all communities.  In the case ofthe branch fines, the Thika-Nanyuki branch was built to provide for50 per cent. European and 50 per cent, native areas.  Thomson&apos;sFalls and Kitale branches are almost exclusively in European areas,and the Kisumu-Yala-Butere branch exclusively  in native areas,as is also the Soroti line.  The Solai branch is mainly European, butalso serves a proportion of native interests. Regarding the main line,almost the whole of the Uganda extension was built to serve nativeareas.* Terms of Reference, 1 (6).
                      Passenger-train fares.  30. It does not appear from an examination of the scale charges of passenger-train  fares that undue preference is given to any one class  of the community.  The services  rendered in the way ofcomfort and facilities are in accordance with the fares charged.                       Parcel-goods rates.  31. All traffic conveyed by passenger train is charged at the samerates, irrespective of its source, and all these rates are remunerative.  Receipts  from this traffic  are derived  almost entirely from  thenonrnative communities.  In addition to these services by passenger or mixed trains, there isalso a  reduced scale  of  charges on  a very  low basis  for  loadsof native produce carried by third class African passengers.                      Freight-rates policy.  32. In regard to freight rates, in addition to the general principlesof railway rating, the Railway Ordinance lays down (Clause 13) thatthe service shall be administered on business principles, due regard being paid to agricultural and industrial development in Kenya and uganda by means of cheap transport.  Generally speaking, no verygreat progress has been made in industrial  development, and both countries are, to a very considerable degree, dependent upon agricul-tural development, both native and European.  The Asian remainsas the small shopkeeper, middleman, or skilled labourer.  The policy adopted to accord with Clause  13 of the Ordinance hasbeen to  provide  cheap  transport for the export and. marketing ofagricultural crops and for necessities of agriculture, such as manuresand implements for cultivation, etc.  This policy, of course, necessi-tates that  higher rates  must be charged on traffic other  than thatconnected with agriculture or industry in order to secure the financialposition  of the railway.  Broadly, the policy has been for low exportrates and high import rates, except on those articles used principallyin agricultural development.                          Export rates.  33. The classification of the export rates is, roughly, as follows :      Coffee. A European crop in Kenya, but a native crop in parts of       Uganda and Tanganyika.     Cotton. An entirely native crop, but confined to Uganda and       Tanganyika.
    Grains, including barley, beans, oats, peas, rye, sharps, wheat.       European and native crops.    Rice,  tapioca,  matama,  millet,  wimbi. Almost  exclusively      native crops.    Fibre, sisal, flax. Entirely European crops.    Maize. European and native crop, but mainly European.    Soda and soda ash. The only large industrial development in      the country giving employment to Africans under European      supervision.  There is no  important crop, either native or European, which isnot provided for in the way of cheap export rates, most of which donot cover full charges including interest and depreciation.  The rates per  ton-mile  compare favourably  with the relativevalues of the commodities.  For instance, the receipt per ton-milefor coffee, which is a commodity of high value, is 13 -184 cents, butin the case of beans and peas, which are of low value, the receiptsare as low as 3 cents per ton-mile.                     Unremunerative rates.  34. In recent  years some  of the export and  exceptional ratesbecame  unremunerative owing to the complete reversal of theconditions under  which it  was financially  sound for the RailwayAdministration  to encourage  the export  of produce by quotingspecially low rates so as to obtain a return load for trucks carrying thehigh-rated import traffic.  Export tonnages of  certain low-ratedcommodities, notably maize,  increased as was  intended.   Whenimports fell relatively  to  exports, the traffic  conditions becamereversed, and trucks had to be hauled empty from the coast up-country to bring  down export traffic.   As from 1st January, 1932,however, these losing rates have been revised and are now fixed on abasis which, I am informed, will  not  only  cover  the cost of directhaulage, but also make  a small contribution to overhead expenses.I have  reason to believe that with the following exceptions the incidence of rates is on the whole fair as between racial communities.                   Cotton cloth  and blankets.  35.  It has been represented to fne that unfair rating discriminationoperates in the case of cotton cloth and blankets which are classifiedat the highest rate in Class  1.  The definition of Classes  1 to 5  is as follows :     Classes  1, 2, and 3 : Articles of high value, fragility, or expen-      sive to deal with.    Classes  4 and 5 : Articles of  every-day use, the value of which      will permit a fair transport charge.
  These commodities are mainly but not exclusively purchased bythe native.  The Railway Administration has, from time to time,had under consideration the reduction of the rate to Class 3, but ithas been represented to them, and confirmed by enquiries, that suchchange would amount to an  average reduction in  selling  cost  of2-4 cents per yard only, in the case of cotton cloth, and of  27-3cents in the case of common blankets.  It has been stated, however,by certain trade organizations that  the  minimum  reduction that could be passed on is 5 cents in the case of cotton cloth and 50 centsin the case of blankets.  On the other hand, I was informed by theIndian Merchants&apos; Chamber at Mombasa that a reduction of 10 centswould certainly be passed on in the case of blankets.  On looking, however, at the definition of Classes  1 to 5 mentionedabove, I am not satisfied that even Class 3 would be a suitably low-classification  for cotton cloth and blankets, for this class appears toinclude articles of higher value or of greater fragility such as china-ware, crockery, cinematograph films, electrical and power accessories.  I therefore recommend that cotton cloth and blankets of the cheapqualities used by natives  should in future  be included  either in class 4 together with such articles as condensed milk, dog biscuits,and books, or in Class 5 which covers other commodities of every-dayuse such as orange-squash, salt, soap, beer, and onions.                    VI. IMPORT DUTTES.*                        Customs Union.  36. A Customs Union is now in force between Kenya, Uganda, and tanganyka, and the tariff applied since April, 1930, was based on therecommendations of an Inter-Colonial Customs Committee which reported in March of that year.   Representations were made to me by the Indian Merchants&apos; Chamber at Mombasa and by the indian national Congress against the protective duties now levied on certainproduce which competes with local agricultural production.                       Protective  duties.  These  protective duties (applied through &quot; suspended duties&quot;as distinct from basic duties) have been introduced with the objectof assisting the establishment of local industries for the supply of flour, sugar, timber, rice,  and dairy products including ghee, and,as mentioned in paragraph 111  of  this Report, they appear to befulfilling their purpose if judged by the evidence of  decreases in* Terms of Reference, 1 (6).
9 -i no I 0imports.  The &quot; suspended duties &quot; differ from basic duties in that,although they are included in the schedules of the common tariff,they are imposed not by the Tariff Ordinance itself, but by Proclama-tion issued by &quot;the  Governor with the approval  of his LegislativeCouncil  in any of the  three territories.  This allows for a  definedmargin of elasticity in the matter of imposition on specified articlesof &quot; suspended duties &quot; as  distinct from basic duties without inter-ference with the main principles of the common tariff.  The protec-tive effect of suspended duties is by no means exclusively designed for the benefit of non-native agriculture.  They also afford protec-tion for native production in the cases of rice and ghee and bothnative and non-native  production in the case of sugar.  There isno evidence that the application of these duties has unfairly affected the incidence of taxation on the various communities.            Specific duty on unbleached cotton goods.  37. The Indian communities also drew my  attention  to the specific rate of 30 cents  per lb. on unbleached cotton piece-goods which at current  prices was equivalent to 42 per cent, as  againstthe standard ad valorem rate of 20 per  cent.  Owing to the heavyfall in the price of Japanese piece-goods to which this rate mainlyapplies the specific rate is now much higher in comparison with thead valorem rate than when it was last adjusted in the tariff revisionof 1930.  It was then reduced from 40 cents to 30 cents and in viewof the fluctuations in prices it is inevitable that at certain times suchspecific rates should vary considerably in their ad valorem equivalent.It would not  be  practicable continually to be  changing  specificrates, but I recommend  that  the  prices  ruling for  these cotton goods, which are almost entirely purchased by the native population,should be carefully watched  and that the specific rate should again,if necessary, be adjusted  when the next periodic revision of ratestakes place.           Balance of advantage between communities.  38. Upon the adoption of the new tariff in 1930 the Inter-ColonialCustoms Committee reported as follows :       &quot; So far as possible alteration in the incidence of taxation    among the various sections of the community is  concerned,    adjustment of the specific  rates of  duty will benefit primarily    the non-European races, the loss following reduction of taxation    of necessities  being to some extent  redressed by an increase in    the rate of duty on tobacco, a semi-luxury article.      Modifications  of the  duties  on cement, passenger-carrying    vehicles, parts and accessories, proprietary medicines, mechanics&apos;    tools,,etc., will be of undoubted benefit to all communities  as    the Committee has every reason to believe that the reductions
    proposed are such as will in fact be passed on to the consumer,    and is fully satisfied that the incidence of taxation will not be    appreciably disturbed by the adoption of its recommendations.&quot;  Although in recent years Customs duties have been increased and excise duties imposed mainly for the purpose of raising revenue, an effort has been  made to  differentiate between the  rates of duties imposed on necessities and luxuries respectively, and attention hasbeen paid to the fact that there is always a point in Customs taxationat which consumption drops and receipts diminish.                            Free List.  39. The  tariff is designed to  allow free importation of articlesnecessary for the agricultural,  industrial, and educational develop-ment of the territories.  It was  suggested that it would be of interestif I  could  obtain  an itemized  list  of annual imports showing thevalue of those  free from duty  and allocated, as in the case of thedutiable imports shown in Appendix 1, Schedule 3 (page 69), betweencommunities in  accordance with  the  considered opinion  of theCustoms authorities  concerning the uses to  which the variouscommodities are put.  The Commissioner of Customs for Kenya and uganda, however, informs me that he does not consider that such alist could be accurate enough to be of any value.  Whereas he is ableto judge  with  some confidence which community purchases thearticles of common consumption included in  the  tariff, he wouldhave no experience to guide him in  the very different case of articlesimported for constructional purposes and agricultural  development.After examining the tariff and considering the recent drop in revenue from import duties I am satisfied  that the point of a diminishingreturn has in some cases already  been passed and that  it wouldcertainly not be to the interest of the Colony in its present stage ofdevelopment to extend  the range  of import  duties  by including those articles which are now on the free list.                    Fairness of present tariff.  40. In my considered opinion  the tariff as at present framed is just in  its incidence upon racial communities so far as the mainstructure is concerned.  Each territory has a margin of elasticity inthe matter of imposition of protective  as  distinct  from revenueduties, the needs of the Colony are already being met to an increasedextent by  local production of many of the  articles involved, and,although the  maintenance of an  absolute balance as between thevarious communities is a practical impossibility, the effects of theprotective duties taken as a whole cannot  be said to bear harshly onany particular section.
          VTL EXPENDITURE ON COMMUNITIES^               Racial classification of expenditure.  41.  On  examining  the  existing materials for  estimating  the&quot; amount of money expended in the interests of each community, inparticular on  natives and non-natives,&quot;  it appeared that, althoughconsiderable attention had been  directed to defining the positionas regards native services, no comprehensive classification to cover the other races had yet been attempted.  It seemed best, therefore,to abandon the basis of classification  of  expenditure  which wasadopted for the years 1929 and  1930 and submitted to the joint select Committee, as  that dealt only with  native  services andwas framed to  show  that  the native community received a fairreturn in Government  expenditure for the  revenue contributed.                     Basis of classification.  42.  In order to do this, the earlier classification took into account the estimated cost of housing Government  officials employed  onnative services,  an addition to their  emoluments  representing the pension  liability  which ultimately  would  fall upon Governmentrevenue,  and also the estimated cost  of  reliefs,  leave pay, andpassages.  A classification of that nature, whilst it may give a fairpicture of the real cost to Government of native services, cannot beadopted as a basis for allocating the actual expenditure of any oneyear to  the various  racial  communities which  contribute  to  theColony&apos;s revenue.  It has accordingly been necessary to separatedirect racial benefits from the Colony&apos;s indirect expenditure.  Owingto the impossibility in the case of many services of arriving at any-thing  beyond  a  rough  estimate in  apportioning HeadquartersAdministration  charges between  the  various  community services,these costs, as also those of pensions  and housing, are in all casesshown in the schedule of indivisible  general  services.                   Military and Police.  The cost of the Military and Police  which in the previous classifi-cation was allocated partly to natives  has now been  shown as ageneral service  since  it  is  thought that the  cost of defence and protection benefits all communities alike  regardless of the disposition of the forces.  The cost  of administrative  personnel has also been shown as general service  as it is not possible on any accurate basisto allocate the services of  District  Officers to  any  particular com-munity.  Notes 1 to  7  which follow Schedule 9 of Appendix 1  on page 85show  generally  the basis on which the more important heads ofexpenditure have been apportioned by the departments responsible.* Terms of Reference, 1 (c).
  The division of services according to the benefits derived by variouscommunities must be largely a matter of opinion and, in many cases,although the direct advantage of a service may appear  to go toone community, indirect benefit may also be derived by another.I have discussed many of the detailed items with those responsiblefor the services, and Appendix  1, Schedules 4 to 9,  pages  81 to 96,give, in my opinion, as fair a picture as is possible of the incidence of benefits between communities.                      Indivisible services.  43.  By far the largest amount of expenditure, however, is shownin Appendix 1, Schedules 4, 5 and 10, on pages 81 and 97, underindivisible services.  The  impossibility  of finding any arithmeticalequivalent for the benefits derived from these services is made clearby an examination of the  items.  Although I have been unable tofind any acceptable basis of  division for these services, it is evidentthat they are by no means of equal benefit as between  communities.  VIII. BALANCE  OF  CONTRIBUTIONS  AND  SERVICES.  44. Having apportioned revenue and expenditure for 1931 as faras practicable on a community basis, it is now possible to consider theresult in the form of a balance sheet.  As information does not existto enable the costs of services to be divided between  the Asiaticraces, Schedule 10 of Appendix 1, page 97, shows contributions of indians, Goans, and Arabs grouped  under the same head.  It is thus seen that after paying in each case for the services by which theydirectly benefit, the following surpluses are left over by the variousracial groups as contributions towards the costs of the indivisibleservices.                      Contributions.   Services.      Surplus.                                                           European..     ..  665,781       171,247       494,534    Asiatic    ..     ..  385,658        46,080       339,578    Native    ..     ..  791,100       331,956       459,144                   Adequacy of  contributions.  The problem as to whether the contributions are adequate cannotbe decided by any accepted test, and judgment must depend on a balance of considerations.   The  latest population figures are asfollows :         European    ........       17,285        Asian        ..     ......      56,903        Native      ..     ......    2,950,000Europeans,  by far  the smallest community,  are thus  paying  thelargest contribution of any of the three groups towards the cost ofcommon services.
  The matter, however, cannot be judged merely on a communitybasis. Although owing to differences between the levels of European,Asiatic,  and Native civilizations the various  communities must betaxed by  different methods, expenditure should be based on thegeneral  interest.   The  European community have  pointed  outthe limitations which apply to any arbitrary division of revenue andexpenditure,  and  their  representatives before the  Joint SelectCommittee* deprecated &quot; any  economic measure which  tends topromote the  disintegration  of the community, believing that thematerial interests of the constituent elements are complementaryand that every attempt to separate them into watertight compart-ments would be against the best interest of all of them.&quot;           Necessity for different standards of service.  45. Contrasts between racial  standards  of life have  made themeasure of equality of sacrifice in taxation even more difficult of practical application than in Europe.  It is impossible satisfactorilyto compare the burdens of taxation where the native pays out ofadditional production and  the  European out of fixed and limited resources  (see paragraph 19).   An opinion as to whether existingsocial services accord with the needs of the population is also greatlycomplicated by the contrasts in conditions of life between nativesand non-natives.  The smaller  European and Asiatic communitieswhich provide so large a proportion of the total revenue are entitled,for instance, to special  standards ot education and other services which it would be quite impracticable to provide for the large native population who are  only  able  to  make such a  small per cafiutcontribution to the  cost of their  services.   Though educationalfacilities are gradually being extended for the African population,to provide these on non-native standards would cost immeasurablybeyond what could possibly be paid at present by the natives them-selves or what it would be fair to ask from the non-native community.                  Standards of life compared.  46. The European community as a whole  appears to  be livingat no higher standard of life than would  reasonably be expected in Great Britain.  On the other hand I am assured by those who are familiar with Indian lif e, including Indians themselves, that membersof that community in East Africa very generally show evidence ota greater level of prosperity and a higher standard of life than theywould be  enjoying in India. Natives, poor and backward as theyare when judged by European standards, are certainly far better offthan before  the  British  Government,  by building the  UgandaRailway, opened up the country and began the process of civilization.* Report of Joint Select Committee on Closer Union, Appendix 25, page 176.
Having seen something of African life under African administration in an African Native State, and something also of the life of thesavage where left without  any European guidance in the greaterislands of the Pacific, I am  convinced that the great work of nativebetterment which has been achieved during the present century in east  Africa cannot  be measured  merely  in terms of  money.Instead of living for the most part in a state of preventable disease and  in  constant fear  of famine, slavery,  and violent death, the kenya native now enjoys liberty and security and in varying degreeaccording to the district where he lives, is  being gradually taughtto improve his health and his standard of life.                       Native contributions.  47. The hut tax was instituted in  1901 and the poll tax in  1903,but the latter was only applied generally in 1910.   By 1911, apartfrom contributions to Customs duties, the  native  population wascontributing no  less than  37  per  cent,  of the total revenue ofthe  Protectorate (excluding railway revenue) by  these  forms of direct  taxation.  Considering  the  services  provided  in returnit is evident that the natives have long paid an ample contribution towards the general  revenues of the country.  The relative con-tributions to the cost  of Government  services are  shown by theStatistician   to   the  Governors&apos;  Conference  to  have   changedconsiderably in the last few years owing to the impoverishment ofthe European population and the relative growth in Native Reserves(Appendix 2, page 99).  Judgment as to whether Europeans havebeen contributing a fair proportion of the cost  of the indivisible orColonial services must largely  depend on  opinion as to  how farthese services are of equal benefit to all races, and how far they havebeen developed primarily for non-native  benefit.   In this matterthere is no need to consider the case of Asians apart from Europeans,Their contributions are based on scales not greatly different and, as their civilization and needs are  largely similar, they benefit equally with  Europeans from amenities  of little present value to the native,                 Benefits from Colonial services.  48. On examining the general structure of these Colonial sen-icesand the proportion of cost due to the provision of such conveniencesas motor roads,  municipal water-supply and the general scale ofGovernment and municipal services, comparing also the services in settled areas with those provided in neighbouring areas  whereEuropean interests are less dominant, I have formed the opinion thatin the development of the undivided or  Colonial services in Kenyathe prevailing bias has been toward the convenience of a civilizationin which the native so far shares little of the direct advantages.   The
word bias is here used in an entirely impersonal sense.  It is not suggested that Europeans have taken any unfair advantage of theiropportunity to mould Kenya services to suit an advanced civilization,but in examining the figures showing the value of services indivisibleas between races  and in weighing the  adequacy of proportionalcontributions, account must in justice be taken of this consideration.  Comparing the burden of  taxation  throughout the world withthat borne by the European population of Kenya, it is evident thatthe latter enjoys the amenities of civilization in return for a relativelylight  scale  of contribution.  No formula attempting to lay downexactly what would be a fair  contribution from each community togeneral  services could however be other than entirely arbitrary.The  matter is altogether so involved and so unsuitable for exactjudgment that I  certainly do not consider that any sudden  ordrastic re-adjustment  of taxation or of the  general  balance  ofexpenditure would be called for in this connexion.            Natives bearing relatively greater burden.  49. Reasons have already been given for the view that the nativecannot in his present circumstances fairly be expected  to  makeheavier contributions, and if further revenue has  to be  raised it ought to be from  the non-native.  Fortunately, however, there isno reason for any such readjustment of burden or benefit on this account as need interfere with non-native standards of life.                   Exact balance unobtainable.  50. An exact balance of contributions and benefits on a communitybasis acceptable from all points of view is unobtainable.  Profounddifferences in social  and economic organization and needs mustbe reflected by arrangements for the special but quite legitimatebenefit  of particular interests.    Well-considered measures,  forinstance,  to  save  agriculture  from  disaster, even  though theymay be directly for the benefit of a section  of producers,  may be fully justified in the general interest.  Bearing this&apos; consideration in mind, some of the complaints whichhave been directed against Europeans on the  ground that their services are relatively costly when compared with  those providedfor natives are found  to be  without  substance.  As, however,criticism has been advanced in certain quarters on the subject ofthe special measures taken to assist European agriculture and of thehigh cost of non-native education as compared with that of native,it is  well to examine briefly how far these complaints are justified. (U3I0)                                                       B
                     Agricultural subsidies.  51. It has been suggested that unfair discrimination against non-European interests has been exercised by the Government in theprovision  of various forms of agricultural subsidies for  Europeanfarmers.   I can see, however, no possible method of government ina mixed  community under which expenditure of an  emergencynature for the  benefit of one  section could be balanced by an equivalent expenditure for the benefit of the others.  The so-calledsubsidies  consisted in  providing  financial assistance  to farmers,chiefly grain growers, who were faced during the year 1930 with theworld  depression  of prices and  unfavourable crop conditions  in kenya.  The  services for grading,  inspection,  conditioning, and port storage, had accumulated profits which were the main source ofthe remissions of four-fifths of the charges which should have been collected on the 1929-30 crops of maize and wheat.  Further relief to grain growers was given in 1930, in conjunctionwith the Railways and Harbours Administration, by refunding thewhole  or  part of the railway rates and port charges in respect  ofthe maize, wheat, and barley exported since 1st January, 1930.General, not individual, assistance was also given to the producers of the 1930 maize crop  by means of a  loan subsidy on exports.In all these cases,  however, it was stipulated that the Governmenthad the right to demand  repayment of the refunds  made by it inform or manner to be decided later.                      Agricultural credits.  52.  As  a  result of the  bad season and depressed conditions infarming in 1930, credit facilities were becoming  very scarce.  TheAgricultural Advances Ordinance, 1930, was passed, making available a sum not exceeding  100,000 for advances to farmers who were in financial difficulties. This provision was made in order to enable thenormal rate of agricultural development to be maintained, and tokeep on the land  efficient farmers whose prospects were normallygood but whose financial position was, owing to these conditions,becoming precarious.  .It is stated in the Department of Agriculture^Annual  Report for 1930 that  &quot; the  timely  introduction  of thisscheme had a steadying  effect on a very panicky situation whichmight easily and very quickly have led to something in  the natureof a disaster.&quot;   Such disaster would have had a serious effect upon other  communities besides the European.   The Land Bank was  established  under Ordinance  in 1931  to supplement this emergency arrangement.  Its main function is to finance long-term  loans to farmers on a first mortgage of their land.The operations of  the Land Bank extend to native as well as to non-native farms, but loans to the  former will not be possible until adifferent  system of land tenure  for natives is instituted.
                 Communal education charges.  53. It was agreed in 1927 with the Elected Members of the Legisla-tive Council that the cost of European and Indian education, withthe exception of administration charges and loan charges for theprovision of schools,  should be paid for out of special revenue.  Thenecessary revenue was provided by the imposition of education polltaxes and the wines  and spirits  consumption tax.  As will be seen from Appendix 1, Note No. 5, page 89, the account for 1931 shows asmall credit balance  in the case of European education but a deficit of  7,605 in the case of that provided for Indians.  The distinctionbetween the expenditure to be covered by these special contributions and that left  on Colonial charge (namely, loan expenditure, centraladministrative charges, and cost of housing and pensions) seems tobe drawn on no clear principle. I see no useful purpose in continuingthis arbitrary arrangement and retaining a separate racial account which does not in practice balance.  The present taxation on whichthe arrangement was founded should remain in force, but the non-native poll tax and education taxes might now with advantage  be merged, the European  continuing to pay a total of Shs.60 and theIndian Shs.50.                  Cost of European education.  54. I am not in a position to judge whether the present per caputcost of European education is justified even by the special circum-stances of a scattered community.  It is of course vital to the futureinterests of Kenya that nothing  should interfere with the provisionof European  education  on a scale as far as possible equal to thatenjoyed by the British race and civilization elsewhere throughoutthe Empire.   It  is indeed in the interests of the  Colony that thechildren of the settlers  who must inevitably in future play an in-dispensable part in its development shall be adequately fitted for their task. It is disturbing to find that a very high proportion of the feeschargeable  are not recovered from parents, and I consider that a standard of educational provision measured by boarding fees  of 45 and tuition fees up to  6 10s. 0^. for a nine months&apos; periodrepresents an unduly high scale  of advantage to be enjoyed at thepublic expense.  This matter should receive careful examination inconnexion with measures for economy (see paragraph 102).             Lack of education facilities for Groans.  55.  The arrangement  that special contributions should be leviedto cover European and Indian education has made no provision forthe Goan community. Indian schools are unsuitable for them as theyare of the Roman Catholic faith.-  No explanation of this anomalyhas  been given beyond the argument that Goans are not Britishsubjects.   This is an inconclusive  reason especially as non-British (11310)                                                      B2
European residents are granted full privileges in European schools.Moreover, many Goans like other natives of India have grown upin the country, and considering that their community contributed in1931 no less than  58,406 to the revenue of Kenya (see Appendix 1,Schedule 1, page 63) I consider that they have an unanswerable claimto adequate educational facilities.  Being provided with no servicethey do not at present pay the education tax.  It is a matter for examination by the Government whether they are in a position nowto be put on the same level as Indians in the matter of taxation, but whatever may be decided on this point their contribution to revenuealready entitles them to reasonable educational facilities.         Ishaak Shariff and Darot Ismailia  Communities.  56. The Ishaak Shariff and Darot Ismailia Communities, nomadpeoples of Arab extraction from  British  Somaliland, have formany years been paying non-native poll tax at their own requestin order to be distinguished from  African natives.  They  havereceived nothing in return for their extra contribution and, although,owing  to their occupation as cattle  dealers which  compels  themto pursue a wandering life, they cannot all be provided with educa-tional facilities, they would be satisfied if arrangements were madeto assist the education of such children as are left in Nairobi.  Thefact that their racial distinction has been recognized by the acceptanceof extra taxation establishes a claim to some educational assistance.                       Native education.  57. A scheme for native education was approved by the Kenya government  in 1930  to provide  eventually  for  a rninimum of requirements.  While  still in  its  infancy  this scheme has  been subjected  to a decrease in this  year&apos;s  education  vote of  9,250as compared with 1931.  At the  Local Native Council meetings which I attended I enquired what were the chief wants felt by thenative.  &quot;More education&quot; was invariably the first answer. That theLocal Native Councils really do feel keenly as to the need of education is shown by the  provision of  17,000 (see  Appendix 8, page 114)which they voted in 1931 for these services from their own resources.I therefore endorse the view expressed by the Director of education in connexion with his estimates this year:       &quot; The African position is  worst  of  all.  The demands for     education are insistent.  The need for  meeting these demands     was never more urgent.  This  service should not be allowed to     suffer especially when the shortage of revenue is likely, in the     main, to be a shortage of revenue derived from Europeans and     not from Africans.&quot;
  A further serious anomaly has  developed in  connexion with capital expenditure for education.   Local  Native Councils have since 1926 voted  33,381 for the provision  of school buildings to make  up  for  the  insufficiency  of  Government grants, although accommodation on a very generous scale has quite properly been found  entirely from central  funds for the school buildings  of the European and Indian communities.  I have examined the items  of reduction in the education estimates for 1932 and am satisfied that they have involved decreases both in the number of natives who can be taught and the efficiency of their instruction beyond what is fair in consideration of  native contributions  to taxation.  There is therefore a strong  claim for provision to be made to enable the programme of native education to be developed according to the scale of progress in force in 1931.                    Local Government services.  58. Contributions  to  Local Government Authorities and servicesof the  Public Works Department in settled areas which are  shownin detail in Appendix  1,  Schedule 5 (Statement  B) on  page 83,and Note No. 7 on page 95,  are doubtless of greater direct benefitto non-natives who five under civilized conditions  than to nativeswhose  present mode of life precludes any but indirect advantagesfrom many of the principal services provided.                         Road finance.  59. Examination  of  the system  of  road  finance  discloses ananomaly which calls for remedy.  In 1931, Local Native Councilscontributed  9,509 to  supplement Government  grants.  By thismeans  they actually paid the capital cost of bridges which  would otherwise have had  to  be borne by Colonial funds.  In European(District Council) rural areas  no such contributions  are made either from local rating or otherwise.  District Councils have now enteredtheir fifth year of life and there is no evidence that they intend to raise any local contribution by means of levying rates, as was expected when they were founded, while the present system relievesthem from  such necessity.  Although, owing  to the different classof traffic carried, it is  not necessary for  roads primarily servingnative  areas  to  be of  such  expensive  construction as  in settledareas, they fulfil just as necessary a function in the life of the native reserves in giving access to markets and  offering facilities for communication,  and should in equity be afforded a larger share ofassistance from central funds.                       Basic road-grants.  60. Under  an Ordinance passed in  1928  each  District Councilreceives automatically from  central funds each  year a statutorybasic road-grant equal to the  sum spent by the Government on the (11310)                                                      B 3
maintenance and  improvement of the  District roads within  itsarea in 1927, plus 25 per cent, for indirect charges  and  overheadcharges connected therewith, or such larger amount as the Governor-in-Council  shall deem necessary for  the purpose of enabling theCouncil to employ the necessary staff to maintain the necessaryplant and  equipment and generally  to carry out its duties  and obligations as a local governing body in respect of  roads.  Underthe heading of &quot; overhead charges &quot; come  such  different itemsas the salary of the engineer and the cost of his travelling; election expenses and  travelling  expenses  of councillors, depreciation of plant, rent of office, office furniture and equipment, and emolumentsof an accountant and clerk.  The Councils also deal  in an advisory capacity with a wide range of subjects unconnected with roads.  The basic road-grant  has been increased in recent  years  for various reasons by way of &quot; additional grants &quot;, for which, however,no provision has been made in the  estimates for  1932  owing to thefinancial situation.  For similar reasons of economy, expenditure on roads of all classes has had to be reduced this year  to the level of1927, but the basic road-grants to District Councils, plus 25 per cent.for indirect charges and overhead charges cannot be altered withoutamending legislation.  Negotiations are now  taking place  on thissubject with District Councils with a view to an agreed  reductionof 7 per cent, in these payments for the current year.  Local Government finance is not working in accordance with theprinciples  upon which  the enabling  legislation  was founded.  Itappears from the Feetham Report* and from Section 104 of the LocalGovernment (District Councils)  Ordinance of 1928,  that it  was originally intended that basic  road-grants with their percentagesurcharge should be devoted  entirely to expenditure  in respect of road work. Owing, however, to the  failure of District Councils torate their Districts for  general purposes, as provided in Part VI ofthe Ordinance,  these grants are now subject to miscellaneous charges,including those mentioned above not directly connected with roadupkeep.  The Economy Committee (see paragraph 102) should examine thepresent system of financing Local Government in Kenya, bearing inmind the fact, now generally admitted elsewhere, that local authori-ties are apt to  be inefficient and wasteful administrators of funds towhich they  do not  themselves  directly contribute.  Comparisonshould also be made between the cost of administration throughDistrict Councils  and  through the  District  Road  Boards  and committees  which they replaced, in  order  to  consider how farreversion to the former system might  be justified  on grounds of efficiency and economy.Report of Local Government Commission, Vol. II, page 96, paragraph 2.
                                                               t) f) f)                               33                         Medical Services.   61. The expenditure  on  Medical Services was reduced  from 236,934 in 1930 to  222,897 in 1931, and a further cut has beenmade in the expenditure for 1932.  The savings have been effected by a reduction of the establishment of Medical Officers from 75 to58 and the following retrenchment of services :        (a) Total abolition  of .the School Inspection Service, with     disbandment of one  Medical Officer, two Health Sisters,  and     clerical staff.       (b)  Abolition of the special Railway Medical Service, involving     one Medical Officer and three Sub-Assistant Surgeons.       (c)  Closure of medical service in respect of farm labourers in     the Trans-Nzoia District, involving one Medical  Officer  and     native staff.       (d)  Medical services in the Native Reserves :           (i)  Masai Reserve, population 50,402, withdrawal of the       only Medical  Officer.         (ii)  Central Kavirondo, reduction of Medical Officers by       one, leaving one Medical  Officer for a population of 343,205.        (iii)  Lamu District, withdrawal of Medical Officer, leaving       a  Sub-Assistant  Surgeon in charge of  a District with  a       population of 29,8S2.        (iv)  Postponement of special Officer for malarial research.       (e)  Reduction  of  Medical  Officers  at  Native  Hospital,     Mombasa, by one.       (/)  Reduction of  Medical Officers in Nairobi by two, duties     partially taken over by the appointment of a part-time private     practitioner.       (g)  Withdrawal of Medical Officer of Health at Nakuru.The provision for health propaganda, of primary importance in theprevention of  diseases  among  natives, has been  progressively reduced from  3,150 in 1929 to  60 in 1932.  It will be noticed that with the exception of  [fj and (g) above, the list is almost  entirely at the expense of native services.  The classi-fication included  in Note  6  to  Appendix I (page 91)  shows howinsufficient was the establishment provided to cope with the medicalneeds of the Reserves even before these cuts took effect.  I considerthat expenditure for direct native medical services has been undulyreduced and that there is a strong case  for securing more adequate provision.         Importance of native agricultural development.  62. The Agricultural Department is by far the most importantservice for improving native prosperity and social conditions as these,in view of the non-existence of any other native industry producing(11310)
exportable commodities, must directly depend on the wealth thenative can win from the soil.  Indirectly, the Agricultural Officerscan achieve much by their teaching to improve the health  and efficiency  of the population.  The economic future of the  Colonymust  increasingly depend on the efficiency of native agriculturalproducers, whether in  the Reserves  or  employed by Europeans.Immediate return for the effort devoted to improvement of nativeefficiency  will  be reaped by the collector of revenue, by employers of labour and, so far as it depends on the spending-power of thenative, by the general trade of the Colony.  A marked increase in native production,  and&apos; consequently innative exchange resources or cash, has been made necessary by therecent improvement of the standard of native life, by the develop-ment of new wants in diet and in the amenities of life, and not leastby the demands of the tax collector. Intensified production  and thenecessity  to &quot; sell off the farm &quot; are creating a new and urgentproblem in the depletion of soil fertility.  When his needs werefewer the  native could supply them by a smaller agricultural return.He therefore cultivated  a smaller amount of land which allowed thereplenishment of soil fertility  and compensation for erosion byfrequent fallowing and change of ground under cultivation.  Inmany areas, with increasing needs of production, the native has nolonger enough land to follow the old method of cultivating  for fouryears and fallowing for a corresponding period.  European methods and crops if unwisely applied may intensify the mischief.  Special problems have therefore arisen in the Reserves.  The nativeneeds to be shown how to get a fair balance between the crops whichhe turns into cash, either by export from the Reserves or from theColony, and the  new crops  which he  should grow for his  ownconsumption in the interests of his health.  I am convinced that not enough attention is being paid at present to native development.   The benefit derived from the AgriculturalDepartment by the native community cannot be measured merely by comparing the figure of  39,018, which is shown as having been spent last year on non-native direct services, with that of  38,389,spent for the direct benefit of the natives. The expenditure of theremaining  88,482 shown as indivisible as between communities,has largely been devoted to work of  greater interest to the Euro-pean settler than to the native, although the native, doubtless, getsan indirect benefit by the prosperity  of non-native agriculture andthe additional employment  which  is  thus  afforded.  A furtherinequality is shown in the fact that Local Native Councils provided 8,497 in 1931 for agricultural and veterinary services, although thewhole expenditure  on  the corresponding non-native services wasmade from central funds.
                 Veterinary research at Kabete.  63. Invaluable research work in the  general  interests  of  theColony has been carried out at the Veterinary Research Institute atKabete.   Probably more than half the effort ot this Institute haslately  been  devoted  to the  three  cattle  diseases,  rinderpest,pleuro-pneumonia, and East Coast fever.  In the case of rinderpest,a  new   treatment  has  recently  been   discovered  at  Kabetedepending on  a vaccine  produced from the spleens  of  animalswhich have had the disease.  The Masai are now providing, forevery hundred of their  cattle  to be immunized, seven cattle tobe  sacrificed  to the disease so  that  vaccine can be producedfrom their spleens.   This new method  is now being provided forthem as a free service, apart from the cost of the cattle which theysupply for vaccine production.   In the case of pleuro-pneumoniaand East Coast fever, there is less prospect of successful control,but  the  department has  recently worked  out  a  scheme whichpermits the free movement of cattle from an infected area if theybear suitable brands denoting  that they  have been inoculated orvaccinated against rinderpest and pleuro-pneumonia or that theyhave been through a six weeks&apos; test for immunity to East Coast fever.Even with this provision  for moving immunized cattle,  the  losssuffered in Native  Reserves from  quarantine regulations is veryserious, and the possibility of relaxation should be carefully watchedby  the Native  Betterment  Committee in  consultation with  theAgricultural Department.                        Coffee services.  64. Other agricultural research has been  devoted to Europeanrather than to native problems.  In addition to  5,000 a year spent in assisting the  coffee industry to control disease, about  8,000 ayear is being spent on coffee research.  This figure is large in pro-portion to the total  vote for the Scott Agricultural Laboratories of 11,354.      Agricultural research  for Native Reserves  and Coast                           Province.  65. A  due share  of applied research should be afforded to  the peculiar&quot; problems of native agriculture.   I recommend that threeresearch  stations should be established,  two in suitable  native reserves and one on the coast, to deal with the problems  of those areas. Work should be directed to the maintenance and improvementof soil fertility, to  the trials of  varieties of crops, the testing oftraditional native methods of crop culture as compared with modernpractice,  and  the introduction of improved crop rotations, plantbreeding, and selection for native crops.  I recommend that applica-tion be made to the Colonial Development Fund for capital grants to cover the cost of these stations which would amount in all toabout  10,000.  The recurrent expenditure of about  1,200 per annum
on  each station  should be found  from the central funds of theDepartment of Agriculture as a set-off for the applied research whichis now being devoted to problems affecting the European coffeeindustry.                  Agricultural training schools.  66. Great advantage would be gained by attaching to each of theproposed research centres a training school for courses of instruction in agriculture. If such schools be  attached to research stations asproposed for the Native Reserves, their cost and upkeep might fairly be charged to the Native Betterment Fund (see paragraph 70).  Itis doubtful whether the Native Betterment Fund could in the nearfuture also bear  the  cost of such a  school in the  Coast  Province.In view of the fact that the Coast Research Station would be dealingwith  problems affecting  Arabs,  Europeans,  and  Indians  equally with natives, the establishment of the school could be left over foifuture consideration.                Improvement o  sheep and goats.  67.  In addition to the research for the benefit of native agriculturealready outlined, further attention should be given to the questionof introducing rams of good wool-bearing breeds in order to grade upthe present native sheep which are useless for anything but mutton.Efforts should also be devoted to  improving the milking capacityof goats so that the native population may have the necessary milk-supply in the villages.  This is becoming the more necessary sincenative cattle have so  often to be driven to distant pastures owing tothe larger area being  brought under cultivation.  To enable the Native  Betterment Fund to be in a position to finance an increasing programme it will be necessary that resources should be provided at least sufficient to reinstate the agricultural andveterinary services up to the level for which provision was made inthe estimates for 1931.                   LX. NATIVE BETTERMENT.                     Native taxable capacity.   68.  Even if direct native taxation be transformed in the way thatI have suggested with the  object  of making it  more adaptable totaxable capacity, it will, if maintained at its present level, representa heavier individual sacrifice than that at present imposed upon thenon-native population.   For reasons which have already been given (paragraph 17) it isdifficult to get an exact measure of native resources and I haverefrained from accepting any of the average figures of native pro-duction and cash earnings which have from time to time been put
w a: forward because since no statistical information is in existence they depend upon  guesswork.   Even,  however, if they were arith- metically correct, they  would  be uncertain ground upon which to  base conclusions as  to  individual taxable  capacity  under  a system which so largely depends  upon a flat rate.  There is great variation in individual wealth measured in terms of livestock even among primitive native communities.   Native  taxable capacity must  therefore  be largely a matter of opinion, but, taking into account the  conditions under which  the native lives and the fact  that taxes absorb  so large a proportion of his available cash resources, I have no doubt that, however the bur- den may be redistributed between one District and another, it would not, under present conditions, be fair to budget deliberately for any increase in the total. As development takes place, however,  the yield of native taxation will show a natural increase, and  it is just that a certain fixed  proportion of the present yield of tax together with a share  of any future increments should be devoted to services for native  betterment.           Need  or ensuring minimum native services.  69. The  main justification for asking the native to submit to  a heavier sacrifice in taxation than  the non-native may be found in the difference between their respective levels of civilization and  the varying needs  of  the two  communities for State expenditure on social services and development. Whereas the non-native is capable of paying for a large part of the cost of his children&apos;s education, this service must be available for the  native  entirely from public pro- vision.  In the  same way the European  population arrange and pay for their own medical treatment,  but  the  native  is quite unableto provide this service for himself and depends entirely upon  the public medical arrangements.  Attention has already been  drawn to the large decreases in the education and medical votes for directnative services (see paragraphs 57 and  61).   If,  because  of  hishelplessness, the native is to be taxed to provide exclusive services for  the improvement of his condition, it is necessary to secure thatthe extra burden that he bears for this purpose be not deflected.The problem is to find some form of guarantee that the vital servicesof native  development which  are the  main  justification for theheavy contribution  made by the  native to  public taxation fromhis slender means shall not be subject to recurrent cuts.  70.  I have given  much thought to the recommendation of theJoint  Select  Committee* that &quot; the Chief  Native commissioner should be  charged with the preparation of an Annual Estimate ofthe Financial requirements of his  Administration and should haveallocated to it  such funds  as the Governor thinks desirable and* Report of Joint Select Committee on Closer Union, paragraph 87.
necessary.&quot;  I assume that the Select Committee intended that thisoutline of policy should be interpreted into a workable and effectiveguarantee for  assuring to African natives a fair share  of Colonialexpenditure.              Proposal for Native Betterment Fund.  Bearing in  mind the  exceptional constitutional arrangements which have grown up in  Kenya  I do not consider it practicable forthe Governor year by  year to abstract  from the Colonial revenue and from the control of the Select Committee on Estimates a varyingsum for the Chief Native Commissioners  administration, and  i therefore recommend the alternative method of making  a statutorybody responsible, under the Governor as Chairman, for one half ofthe proceeds of direct native taxation.  I therefore propose that aNative Betterment Fund be created out of which the direct servicesof native development should be financed.                 Native Betterment  Committee.  71. This Fund should be controlled by the Governor, as Chairman,advised by a Committee  to include the Chief Native commissioner and  representatives of native interests  on the Legislative Council.The  Governor should have power to nominate other officials.  an unofficial elected member should also  be added  in view  of theadvantage of associating  settler interests with the special respon-sibility of the Governor as trustee for the Crown in the developmentof native races.  As the justification for such a fund is to be found inthe high level of native taxation in proportion to native wealth andtheir claim to special direct services, its administration should not come under review by the  Select Committee  on Estimates.   that body is  predominantly representative of the non-native interestsand  is not therefore in a position to deal with the special needs ofthe native areas.            Powers and responsibility  of Committee.  72. The Committee  should be empowered to build up balancesfrom year to year  in order to provide against fluctuations in the yield of native taxation and to be in a position to pursue  a consistentpolicy.   By this means it should be possible to finance a wideningprogramme of native development  as resources  increase  in thefuture.   It would be the  duty of the Native Betterment Committeeto co-ordinate the efforts which are being made by  the  various departments to  assist  in  native betterment.  The problem of theimprovement  of native  conditions  is  beset  with many complexdifficulties.  The objective may often have to be approached not by a frontal attack on the part of the department directly concerned,but  by a combination of  effort on the part of several departments
O fj (Jtogether.   Although the provision in the estimates of  1931 hasbeen taken as a convenient  measure for the minimum needs of theservices of direct native benefit these services should in future beconsidered as  a whole and there should be full discretion to allotresources available from the Betterment Fund by whatever system and in whatever proportions are found to be of the greatest benefit for natives.     Necessity for co-ordination illustrated by needs of Tanaland.  73. An illustration may here be  given of the necessity for  co-ordinated effort such as might with advantage be arranged by  theCommittee.  There is  urgent  need in the  Tana  River area  for improvement of the health of natives who are now almost universallysuffering from preventable  diseases.  It may possibly be best thatthe doctor himself  should  not lead  the way alone.   To get rid ofbilharzia and malaria the land should perhaps first be drained and improved in condition by the advice  of agricultural officers, who can also build up resistance to disease by teaching the native to growcrops which will afford him  a balanced diet.   The school-teacher andthe sanitary officer should reinforce the effort by teaching the people the simple rules of health  which, though accepted as a matter ofcourse  in a civilized community,  are  still  entirely  unknown toprimitive people.  Before the hookworm can be eliminated nativesuperstitions must  be broken  down to  enable the  introductionof elementary rules of sanitation in the locations and  to securethe protection of the water-supply  from infective  pollution.  Theactual  healer  should probably come last  as it is of little use tocure  diseases if ignorance  and lack of sanitation  are continuallycausing re-infection.  The Native Betterment Committee would  actas general staff in the war against native disease and ignorance, andit would be their duty to secure a wise allotment of tasks betweenthe various forces engaged.   Relation between Betterment Fund and Local Native Councils.  74.  Having been instructed* to examine &quot; the degree and mannerin which financial responsibility should be conferred on Local NativeCouncils &quot;  I have considered  various different methods of giving them control over the spending of a definite proportion of the yield of native direct taxation, whether derived from the present  systemof hut and poll tax, or from any such amended system as  I have recommended in paragraphs 21 to 24.  My discussions with LocalNative Councils have convinced  me  that there is  a very generaldemand that some considerable proportion of the heavy direct taxation now paid by the native should come back in the form of
direct and tangible services.   To satisfy this wish there is no needfor these services to be strictly limited to those spent in the Reserves,provided that they are devoted to direct native benefit throughoutthe Colony  under the control of an impartial body such as that suggested in paragraph 71.               Advantages of grant-in-aid system.  75. For reasons  with  which  I  shall deal  when  discussing thefuture development of Local Native Councils, I am convinced thatit  would not be desirable merely to give back to each area  a pro-portion of the taxes there raised.   Provision should be made by asystem of grants-in-aid  for  the pooling  of resources and for thebenefits to be allotted according to needs.  By this expedient theNative Betterment Fund should serve to some extent as a  devicefor equalization of expenditure between the richer and the  poorernative districts.   The  proposed grant  could not  at present  beaciministered  entirely through the  Local Native Councils, but theNative Betterment Committee should aim at the gradual develop-ment of a system of grants-in-aid, and seek to associate Local NativeCouncils in  increasing  measure with  the administration  of the betterment services.               Revenue  of Native Betterment Fond.   76.  I recommend that  statutory provision should be made for thepayment into the Native  Betterment Fund of half the average annual yield  of  native  direct taxation for the  previous six years for which  final figures  are available,  this  fund to  be  expendedprimarily upon the development of  the four major services of directbenefit to the natives, namely, education, medical, agriculture, andNative Reserve roads and bridges.  It  is necessary to  base this50 per cent, grant on a six years&apos; average because revenue from thehut and poll tax varies considerably from year to year according tothe yield of native  crops.   In  establishing this Fund provision would have to be made for safeguarding  the  claims of holders of  Kenya Government stocksecured on the general revenue of the Colony in the event of other resources proving at any time insufficient to meet the service of thisdebt.   A comparison between the yield of direct native taxation in 1931,and the average for the six years 1926 to 1931 will show the necessityfor taking an average of years as the financial basis for the  NativeBetterment  Fund.   In  1931,  native direct  taxation yielded  the exceptionally low figure of  530,877, whereas the average for  the six years mentioned is  559,196.  If a percentage were to be taken of the year 1931 alone, it would of course have to be fixed  higherthan  50 per cent, to cover the actual cost of  270,954 for the major
direct native services in that year ;  but it is evident that a consistentgrant-in-aid system could not be founded on a fund subject to suchheavy fluctuations as occur from year to year in the yield of nativedirect taxation.  Fifty  per cent, of the above-mentioned average figure is  279,598, and I would justify this percentage as a fair basis for the proposed Fund on the following grounds.         Insufficient provision in 1931 for backward areas.  77. The expenditure on the four major direct native services in1931 was in my opinion insufficient for providing reasonably ade-quate services.  Great reductions had  already  been made  in themedical service as compared with 1930. Many areas were seriouslyneglected.  There was, for instance, no provision whatever for anymedical,  educational, or other services for the Pokomo Tribe, wholive along the Tana River, in return for  their contribution to theColonial  revenue.   The  Commissioner  for Turkana, a  very poorProvince, inhabited by  nomad tribes  except for the single  andequally poor cultivated  area of Suk, sent me figures showing that whereas  7,578 is raised in direct native taxation only  710  comesback in services of direct native benefit. Although the figures maynot be prepared on exactly  the  method  adopted throughout thisReport, I am satisfied that it is not fair to give back to such poordistricts  so  small a proportion of  the  taxation which they raise.Under the appropriate headings I have already discussed the veryserious effects of the heavy cuts included in the estimates for 1932from the provisions made in 1930 and 1931 for the more importantservices of  direct native benefit.   I consider,  however, that it is areasonable compromise to take the expenditure of the year 1931 asbeing  the   standard of  a fair  minimum  contribution  for the major services to be  provided  out of the  proposed  Native Better-ment Fund.    Inequalities  of treatment between native and settled areas.  78. To re-instate the provision for the major services merely atthe level of 1931 would however afford no set-off for the practice which has recently developed whereby  Local  Native Councils have begun to make large contributions for services owing to insufficiencyof Government grants, although such grants are given to defray thewhole cost of analogous services in  settled areas (see paragraphs 57,59 and 62).  It is difficult to assess a fair set-off for these anomalies, especially as the basic road-grants may in future be reduced by amending legis-lation and District Councils may also decide to levy rates (see para-graphs 59 and 60).   The inequality of treatment between  nativesand non-natives with regard to  agricultural services is also not altogether suitable for redress by means of an extra grant to native
areas.  It should preferably  be dealt with by requiring the Agri-cultural Department to give to native problems a larger share of their attention, particularly in the  matter of research as recommended inparagraphs 62  and 65.                       A fair settlement.  79. The 50 per cent,  average figure of  279,598 for  next year would give a margin of  8,644 over the annual 1931 expenditure.Having regard to the present  serious  financial difficulties of theColony, this  may be accepted  as  a reasonable settlement  under existing conditions, and such arrangement will.give some scope for expansion of services under  the control of the Native BettermentFund.  I suggest that the allocation of the amount to be found out of theFund for expenditure on these four direct native services shall be arrived at in the same manner as has been adopted for the classifica-tion of expenditure  on  the  same  services shown in Appendix  1,Schedule 9, page 85.  Appendix 7, page 113, gives  a fuller definition of services to be borne by the Fund.               Loan money for native betterment.  80. Although the grant of 50 per cent, of the yield of direct nativetaxation  should cover ordinary expenditure on the betterment ser-vices, cases may  arise in future  where provision of loan money fromthe  Colonial Development Fund or other sources  may be justified.The establishment of the Native Betterment Fund should not debarthe services covered from such further assistance on suitable objects.   Administrative separation of communities  not  recommended.   81. I  would emphasize that the proposal for a Native Better-ment Fund is not one for the administrative separation  of the non- native and native communities as to  the advisability of which at some future date the Joint  Select Committee kept an open mind*, although they &quot; felt unable to recommend   the  adoption at  the present  time of any  scheme in  preference to the existing system of government, on unitary lines, for the Colony as a whole.&quot; Adminis- trative separation of the communities would,in existingcircumstances, be open  to great objections  on financial and political grounds.  An apportionment of revenue and expenditure as  between the communi- ties is impossible to obtain arithmetically with any  degree of accuracy under the existing fiscal and administrative systems, and the cost of duplicating  headquarters staffs and  overhead charges could  not be justified.  More serious even than  the financial difficulty is the* Report of Joint Select Committee on Closer Union, paragraph S6.
political one.  The effect of setting up a separate and independentadministration for native areas would be to promote that disintegrate-tion of the co-operative state that it is a main purpose of the &quot; DualPolicy &quot; to prevent.  The expedient of a Native Betterment Fund is admittedly in-consisterit in theory with the unitary system of Colonial government,but I am convinced of the urgent need of a temporary guarantee that the more  backward community shall get a fair share from central funds during the present period of unequal racial needs andpolitical  representation.  If, in future,  the civilization  of the native and non-native com-munities becomes more closely assimilated, or if, before  that time,native wealth and the yield of their taxation so increase as to make this  admittedly arbitrary  apportionment no  longer appropriate,the matter should  be reconsidered.                Native Marketing Advisory Council.  82. The  increase and  improvement of marketing facilities fornative produce  and the introduction and co-ordination of improvedcommercial methods in the native areas will be suitable objects forassistance by the Native Betterment Fund.  With the object of assuring to growers a more ready sale and alarger share of  the proceeds, a Native Marketing Advisory council should be set up by the Governor consisting  of the Chief NativeCommissioner, two or three members of the Native Administration,and two or three experienced members of the business community.Some questions that  might usefully be considered by this advisory body would  be co-operative production  and marketing, bulkingand grading, establishment of marketing centres where  large-scalebuyers might be induced  to handle  native produce, licensing oftraders, and the prohibition or restriction of the system of barterwhich as practised in some of the small Asiatic stores is alleged to operate generally to the disadvantage of the native producer.  X-FINANCIAL  RESPONSIBILITY   OF   LOCAL  NATIVE                          COUNCTLS.*             Organization of Local Native Councils.  83. The  Local Native Councils in Kenya are a deliberate creationunder an  Ordinance passed  in  1924, whereas in  Uganda and insome parts of Tanganyika they have been built up on a previouslyexisting  system of tribal administration.  It has sometimes been suggested that  Kenya has  been at a dis-advantage  in this matter as compared with neighbouring territoriesowing to the fact  that there  were no paramount native chiefs and
that the traditional system of tribal government was very rudi-mentary and variable.  As a  result, however, of the necessity forimprovising these local government bodies from the start, the Kenyasystem has been framed to suit the functions to be performed andit has generally been found convenient to take the tribe, or part ofa tribe, as the unit of administration.  It has not been found possible to include in this system the nomadand  scattered tribes which  inhabit  the  Northern Frontier andTurkana Provinces outside the Suk area.  The Lamu and KipiniDistricts of the  Coast Province are also  excluded.  Altogether in kenya there  are now twenty-three Local Native Councils and they represent convenient units for local administration  and rating,as they each cover a definite local community with common interestin the tasks of local government and sharing equally in any communalbenefits which may be provided out of funds raised locally.           Comparison with Tanganyika and Uganda.  84. In the neighbouring territories the systems are much more complicated.   In Tanganyika, for instance, there are 143 Councils,and  the  fact that these bodies are being gradually combined in larger units appears  to show that their  original distribution wasnot found to  be ideal and is being gradually modified in accordancewith the needs of administration.  In those districts of Uganda where the highest native civilizationhad  been attained the traditional system  was  continued in  theform  of  two  or three different grades of  councils according to the size  of the tribal unit.  Several villages are grouped together inthe lowest grade and send representatives to the county organization(&quot; Saza &quot;).  In the case of the largest tribes these county units mayagain be combined in the tribal assembly.  There is no  reason forsuch an  elaborate system in Kenya, and the existing organizationis well adapted to the needs of the Colony.  The Provinces  of Kenya were established as convenient areas for administration but do  not  generally represent  any tribal unit ordeliberate tribal grouping.           No need in Kenya for Provincial Councils.  85. As communications improve it is uncertain whether  thepresent grouping  will necessarily remain permanent.    Occasionalmeetings of tribal representatives at provincial headquarters maybe  of value for  discussing   application of  native  policy  butthere are no administrative functions which could with advantage be  taken away from  the  smaller tribal units  and be entrusted to  a larger  group.  The  only suggestion for  a wider groupingwhich was brought to my notice  was in  Kavirondo and that was based not on any desire to break down barriers between  different
9 Q oO y&apos;-J Qtribes but,  on the contrary,  on an aspiration  for tribal re-unionof the Bantu and Nilotic (Luo) tribes who are now split into fourdifferent Local Native Council areas by the Kavirondo Gulf whichcuts right across the tribal boundaries.  This difficulty could notbe met by  setting up a Provincial Assembly as the whole  area of ,122 square miles with a population  of about  a million would be too unwieldy  for purposes  of unified local administration.   Ifcommunications so improve  in future  as to overcome the  present difficulty it would seem better to combine  existing Local NativeCouncils so as to keep Bantu and Luo together rather than to unitethem in a Provincial Assembly.             Constitution of Local Native Councils.  86. The  constitution  of the  nine Local Native Councils whichI visited showed considerable variation both in size and in the methodof election  of  members.  In  Northern Kavirondo,  the  Councilconsisted of 64 members of  whom 38 were elected  and  26  werenominated.  Some Councils, on the other hand, had  a nominatedmajority.   The Local Native Council of South  Nyeri, for instance,consisted of 23 members, 12 of whom were nominated and 11  elected.  After it had been explained to the Councils that I had been sent out as a result of last year&apos;s  Parliamentary enquiry,  discussionstook place  as to the conditions under which these Councils  workand various suggestions for lightening the system of  taxation were brought forward.  In some cases, where my  visits coincided with aroutine meeting, I also saw the Councils at work on their ordinary business.           Standard of education and financial aptitude.  87. In spite of the fact that in most cases only a minority couldread and write, members seemed  to follow the  proceedings very closely and to take an  intelligent  interest in the business.  Therewere, however, great contrasts between the various Districts inthis respect.  Whereas the educated minority in the more advancedDistricts could appreciate simple accounts, there was only onecouncillor at another  meeting who could read, and I was assured that few members could distinguish between any numbers over 80.  These conditions were in marked contrast to the Kingdom ofBuganda where I saw the Lukiko at work and was much impressed by the efficient accounting system which I was shown  in the NativeTreasury.   It will be very long before such a level of education canbe reached  by any District in Kenya.  It seemed quite obvious that without a District Commissioner to guide each  Council as President, none of the bodies that I visitedwas capable of exercising any effective financial control.  Currency,other than  livestock, has  only recently come into the lives of the natives, and financial calculations are for the most part meaningless.
   On the other hand, many of the native members are very business-like in the sense that they know what they want and will take muchtrouble to see they get value for money, and undoubtedly they arealready very useful as advisory bodies to the District commissioners in the allocation of available funds in accordance with the wishes of the tribe.                      Financial resources.  88. The revenue and  expenditure of the various Native Councilsduring 1931 are shown in Appendix 8 (page 114), which also shows the credit balances carried forward  to 1932.   It will be noticed thatrevenues are derived from various sources.  At the present time therates voluntarily imposed vary from Sh.l to Shs.3 per head.  Thetotal revenue amounted to   62,691 of which  39,952 was derivedfrom rates,   14,070 from land revenues  and  8,669  from other sources.  I do not recommend any immediate change in the constitutionor responsibilities of Local Native Councils.  They should be allowedto develop on their present  lines and be brought into closer touchwith  the  work  of  the  District Commissioners as their capacitiesincrease.  Local finance should be supplemented by grants-in-aid.                  Basis for financial assistance.  89. Such financial assistance should take the form  of grants forspecial capital purposes and annual grants in aid of recurrent expendi-ture and should be payable either out of loan funds, general revenue,or, in suitable cases, from the Native Betterment Fund proposed inparagraph 70.  The alternative system of a definite rebate to LocalNative Councils of some fixed  proportion of  the taxes collected intheir Districts would be too rigid for the present conditions in Kenyain view of the  great contrast in the stage of development reached between areas, such as Kikuyu, which are generously provided withservices,  and Tanaland, where hardly any services have yet  been created.  The following passage from Lord  Lugard&apos;s Memorandum onTaxation  issued to political  officers in Nigeria in 1917 is equallyapplicable to conditions in Kenya : &quot; Distant Provinces .  .  . mustnot feel aggrieved if the annual direct expenditure upon them  ... isnot the equivalent of the tax they  pay to Government.  The stemand main branches of a tree must receive the bulk of the sap and be developed before  its outlying limbs. .  . . Later the  bulk  of theexpenditure may in return  be devoted to the development of theoutlying Provinces.&quot;  Thus  the  Native  Betterment  Committeeshould give special consideration to those areas which have beenhitherto the most neglected, and they should design their grants tobring all areas up to a general level of development.
                  Communal labour on roads.  90. In connexion with road upkeep it was brought to my notice that the Local Native Councils of Kyambu and Meru had recentlypassed resolutions expressing their wish  to be allowed to repair their local roads by the traditional method of communal labour in preference to paying a gang of workers for this purpose (see Appendix 9, page116).  Criticisms of the old-established system seem often to be made without due consideration of the conditions in the Native Reserves,where road repairs often involve merely filling up a gap which hasbeen made by storm water and can be carried out very quickly whenthe  inhabitants of a whole village turn  out and work together.  Cash for payment of wages is moreover  often very short and therate payers may naturally prefer to do the work themselves insteadof having to pay others to carry it out.  There is nothing in theInternational Convention concerning Forced and Compulsory labour to interfere  with such communal work provided that the services are  of a  kind which can &quot; be considered as normal civic obligationsincumbent upon the members of the community provided that themembers of the community or their direct representatives shall havethe  right to be consulted in regard to the need for such services.&quot;*  It is difficult to justify the uprooting of harmless Native customsmerely to satisfy European theories and I  recommend that in  caseswhere Local Native Councils express a wish to make use of communallabour for communal service under proper safeguards their right ofself-determination in this matter should not be taken away.         Transfer of responsibility for certain services.  91. Responsibility for local education should gradually be trans-ferred to Local Native Councils, powers of inspection and ultimatecontrol with the right to withhold grants  in case of unsatisfactoryservices  being reserved to the Director of Education.  The teachingstaff should remain officers of the Department of Education. Grants-in-aid for elementary education might be made to Missions in areas where they can offer efficient service.  Educational institutions of colonial importance would continue to be  financed from central funds, whether out of loan money or from the Native  BettermentFund.  The same principle might also be  progressively  applied first tosanitary and then to medical services but doctors and nurses should always remain members of the Colonial Service.  The cost of head-quarters staff and such central institutions as the Medical research laboratory would naturaUy remain as  charges on central funds.  In the same way the responsibility for local agricultural services should eventually devolve upon local government bodies but here again the control  of policy must remain vested in the  Director ofAgriculture and officers should continue to be members  of his staff.
    XI. REVIEW OF GENERAL BUDGETARY POSITION.               Supplementary Terms of Reference.  92. Supplementary instructions issued on 7th April, 1932, directme to review the general budgetary position of the Colony, and itis  indeed necessary that I should discuss this subject in view ofthe considerable re-adjustment of expenditure which I have recom-mended in connexion with direct native services.  These re-adjust-ments amount to about  30,000, mainly in connexion with re-estab-lishing the major native services to  1930-31  levels.  additional provision for the education of Goans and the Ishaak Shariff  andDarot Ismailia communities, and for applied research on agriculturalproblems in Native  Reserves and the Coast Province is also recom-mended.  To  appreciate the present budgetary situation  it  isnecessary to make a brief examination of the financial policy whichhas been pursued in recent years.                      Unbalanced Budgets.  93. The Colony of Kenya has from 1929 onwards failed to balanceits budgets out of current revenue and successive deficits have been met out of accumulated savings.  Details of the changes in revenue and expenditure since  1926  will be found in Appendix  10, Tables1 and 2, pages 117  and 118.  The  following  table  summarizes the  gross  figures  of revenue and  expenditure  and  also  surplus balances  for  the  vears  1926to 1931 :-                                      &quot;Year.	Gross Revenue.	Gross Expenditure.	Surplus or Deficit on year.	Surplus at end of year.	 	:  	 	 1925			 	149,7231926	2,627,223	2,414,681	-f 212,542	362,2651927	2,S46,110	2,515,115	-h 330,995	693,260192S	3,020,694	2,S34,647	-I- 186,047	879,3071929	3,333,742	3,505,072	- 171,330	707,9771930	3,241,600	3,438,S75	- 197,275	510,7021931	3,066,930	3,216,0S9	- 149,159	361,543  It will be seen from this table that the Colony&apos;s financial position atthe close of the year 1928 was a strong one.  There had been a surplus on each year&apos;s accounts from 1924 to 192S when the surplusbalances reached the highest figure.   It may be of interest to give a brief outline of the way in  which these accumulations  have beenexpended since 1928 to balance the deficits  of successive years.
  94.  The 1929 budget provided for a surplus of  77,009.  It did not,however, include provision for the amount voted in December, 1928,against surplus balances,  a large part of which formed  a charge against the 1929 accounts.  Abnormal expenditure during 1929 was incurred as follows :     Expenditure  specially  voted  against   Surplus      Balances............ 72,914    Locust Campaign   ..    ..    ..     ..     ..   55,272    Famine Relief (net)..........   59,238                                                   187,424At the same time revenue collections were affected by the invasion of locusts ; native hut and poll tax figures were  35,589 short ofthe estimate, and other revenue suffered.  The actual accounts forthe year  1929 showed a deficit of  171,330 and the Colony&apos;s surplusbalances  were reduced to  707,977.                            1930.  95.  A deficit of  93,923 was budgeted  for in 1930 after aUowingfor expenditure of  90,537 against surplus balances and  15,000 forfamine relief.  The actual amount spent during the year as a specialcharge against the surplus  was  107,121 and the deficit of the year&apos;saccounts amounted to  197,275.                            1931.  96.  The  1931  estimates, as  passed by  Legislative Council  inNovember, 1930,  provided for a surplus  of  73,051.   expenditure was  226,843  less than the  original estimate but  revenue fell  by 449,053 as compared with the budget estimates.  As from 1st July,1931,  postal letter-rates were increased to the level from which theyhad been reduced on 1st  April,  1930.  Additional Customs dutieswere  imposed  on motor tyres and accessories.    12,622 wastemporarily provided from surplus balances for famine relief, some part of  which, however, will be charged to  expenditure in 1932.Expenditure  on  the locust  campaign during 1931  amounted to 18,776.  The deficit on the 1931 accounts  was  149,159,  and the surplusbalances were reduced to  361,543.          Recoverable expenditure  rom surplus  balance.  97.  In  the  figures given  above  for  expenditure  from surplusbalances no account is taken of the following items which, beingrecoverable, are shown as assets in the balance sheet:      100,000 appropriated for the purpose of  making advances and         meeting expenses under the Agricultural  Advances Ordi-         nance, 1930.     116,000 appropriated during 1931 for the assistance of maize         and wheat farmers.
  Concurrently with  the dissipation of balances the Colony  hasincurred a large increase in its Funded Debt. Appendix 10, Tables 2and 3, pages 118 and 120, shows how this increase has been reflected in annual payments on account&apos;of debt charges.                  Causes of financial difficulty.  98. The weakening of Kenya&apos;s financial position has, of  course,been due largely to the trend of world prices. In a community whereexternal payments must depend almost entirely on primary produc-tion, the catastrophic falls in prices for maize, sisal, and other localproducts have necessarily caused a great restriction of purchasing-power which has been reflected in a heavy decrease in the revenuederived from Customs duties.  A serious local misfortune leading to heavy losses in the maize crop has added to the financial difficulty.The recent crop destruction by locusts began in 1928 and by the endof 1930 was estimated to have caused a loss to growers of  200,000.In 1931 an even worse visitation destroyed 40 per cent, of the maizecrop.  This reduced the  export of maize  by  1,000,000 bags and,taking into account the destruction of other crops including wheat,is estimated to represent a money loss of  400,000 up to the end of1931.  The trouble still continues, and it is impossible at this stage to assess what damage will be suffered by  the  crop which has now-been planted.  This misfortune has not only caused disastrous losses to cultivators, but it has also had serious indirect results, firstly on expenditure in connexion with  special defensive measures,  and secondly,  by reducing purchasing-power and  thus  contributing tothe fall in indirect revenue.                     Efforts for economy.  99. In the early months of 1930 the  necessity for  economy in expenditure was realized and  efforts were made to  curtail expendi-ture without involving a reduction of services.  At the beginning of1931, however, the need for economy became urgent and as a  first step towards retrieving the position a schedule of authorized reduc-tions on the original estimates for the year amounting to  157,543was  issued in May, 1931.  Strenuous efforts to retrench have again been made this year and a cut of  103,754  on the current estimatesas approved for 1932 has already been secured, mainly on recurrent expenditure.                  Savings partly non-recurrent.  100. These  savings, however, are to  some extent non-recurrent.For instance, an important decrease of about  20,000 is to be broughtabout  by lengthening the period of the  &quot; tour &quot;  of government officials and postponement of  leave.   The actual saving on accountof passages must be far greater at the beginning of the period thanwhen the working of the new system is fully established.  The effectof this economy will  therefore quickly  cease to show itself in  theexpenditure of departments becaxise being temporary only it cannot
be followed up by any corresponding decrease in establishments to compensate for the extra number of officials who will be available for duty at any one time in the Colony while the scheme is in operation.It is evident, therefore, that if this saving of  103,754 is to be repeatedin 1933 continued efforts must be made to keep down the cost of services which will otherwise tend to work up towards their formerlevel.                Need for further retrenchment.  101. There are other reasons to justify renewed efforts to retrenchat the present time.  If it be decided that the financial situation and prospects make further taxation unavoidable, those who will haveto bear new burdens may fairly ask that  these be lightened to theutmost by a further examination and application of the  maximummeasures of economy consistent with administrative efficiency.  An  additional ground for re-examining the cost of government establishments is to be found in a comparison between revenue andexpenditure in 1926 and revenue and expenditure in 1932.  Generalrevenue (excluding land sales)  amounted to  2,051,994 in  1926,rising in the intermediate years to its peak in 1929.  It had fallen by1931 to  2,085,450, and the indications are that on the present basisof taxation it will fall considerably below the 1926 figure. The expen-diture on recurrent votes, excluding public debt and  interest,  has risen during the same period from   1,803,194 in 1926  to   2,104,769as the final figure for 1932 after readjustment of estimates in accord-ance with the economies in sight.  During the same period  the serviceof public debt and interest has gone up from  484,981 to  1,010,500,although much of this increase is on account of loan charges on the transportation debt which are set off by  reimbursements5&quot;.  Thesefigures point  to the conclusion that the scale of public  services  is greater than the Colony can  now afford and suggest the urgent needfor  its reconsideration.                     Economy Committee.  102. It would have been outside the  scope of my enquiry and  itwould indeed be  an unsuitable  task for a single Commissioner toexamine the possibility of detailed  retrenchment in all the activitiesof the Administration.  At  the time of writing, the  Governor has stated his  intention of setting  up  a  small local Committee forthis purpose.   No Terms of Reference have as  yet been announcedbut as it will be necessary to  search for economies by an examinationof the responsibilities, organization, and activities of the departments of Government, and also the policies upon which they are based,  itis necessary to ensure  that while business and political elementsare included there should also be  strong  representation  of  officials who know  the Government machine from inside and  can direct  * The Colony, however, guarantees losses on  certain branch lines.  Theamount actually paid to the Railway Administration in 1931 was ^19,871.
attention to possible economies in organization.   In view of thepersistent efforts which have been made in recent years to achieveeconomies which,  although not  necessarily all recurrent  in theliteral sense, have totalled since 1930  195,462 on ordinary recurrent expenditure, excluding public debt charges and interest, and  280,738on extraordinary votes, I do not anticipate that it will be possibleto find  any very large new economies, especially as about half thefield  of public  expenditure  is  covered by  irreducible services including public debt,  pensions,  and provision   for  the  NativeBetterment Fund, and scope for retrenchment is therefore definitelylimited.   For this reason,  while  seeking to ensure  that expendi-ture  is  so  conditioned as to give  the best  possible return,  itmust be a  main part of the Committee&apos;s task to consolidate theretrenchments  already  in force and to counteract any automaticincreases.                 Divided financial responsibility.   103. Efforts to economize are likely to prove temporary in theirresults unless spending continues to be curbed by effective methodsof financial  control.  In Kenya there is in force a system of dividedfinancial administration under which  the Treasurer is responsiblefor  the collection of revenue  while the allocation of resources  toprovide  for the various services  is controlled by  the  Secretariat.The preparation of the main estimates of the year is thus in the handsof the Colonial Secretary whose duty it is as chief adviser to theGovernor to take  a large  share  of  responsibility for  their finaladoption.  The Colonial Secretary is in effect also Financial secretary as he is not only responsible for expenditure but also introduces thebudget  and conducts  the  Appropriation  Bill  in  the LegislativeCouncil.  Actually the  chief fimctions of the Treasurer  of Kenyaare those of an Accounting  Officer.  This arrangement is in marked contiast to the system of Treasurycontrol in force in Great Britain.  British Government departmentsdo not even  begin to consider  proposals  for fresh expenditure, Ior to frame the policy upon which the normal estimates of the year Idepend, except in the closest touch with the Treasury throughout. IThe  tendency to increase  expenditure is therefore checked and Icontrolled from the earliest stages by officials with special financial Iexperience.  The British system is not entirely  appropriate to  Crown Colony Iconditions but there is a strong  case  for the application of closerfinancial control, with whatever modifications may be necessary  to suit the constitution of Kenya.  I consider that the Treasurer shouldbe regarded as the Financial Adviser to the Government, and that his advice should be sought not only on all proposals for raising revenue,but  also on all matters involving expenditure from public funds  orotherwise affected by financial considerations, before decisions are
                                                                    9 0 9                              53                                    0 *j^taken on such, questions.  He should have free access to all Secretariatfiles in order that he may be fully cognisant of all the considerations affecting the financial policy of the Government and be in a positionto offer advice when that policy is in process of formation.  Thetendency to increase expenditure would thus be checked and con-trolled from the earliest stages by an official with special financialexperience.                   Control  of  Establishments.  104. Another marked contrast  with the British system  is to  befound  in  the Establishments  Branch  being under the  colonial secretary and not under the Treasurer.  The effect of departmentalestabhshments on Government expenditure can hardly  be exaggerated-gerated.  The very high proportion of total expenditure represented by the pay list of Government departments under modern conditionsexplains and justifies the British system  under which the controlof establishments is  one  of the five main heads under which the responsibilities of the  Treasury are divided.  If extravagance  in personnel and services is to be avoided in Kenya I am convincedthat  control of the establishments in Government departments should be placed under an official responsible for the whole systemof finance.                      Colonial Regulations.  105. Whatever may have been  the  intentions of the  ColonialOffice as to the control of expenditure in the past, the  ColonialRegulations issued in 1928 no longer impose any necessity for thissystem  of  divided responsibility.   In the  Regulations for  HisMajesty&apos;s Colonial Service published in 1923 it was laid down (para-graph 223)  :-      &quot; Annual Estimates of the Revenue and Expenditure of a    Colony will be prepared by the Colonial Secretary and submitted    to the Governor at such a  date  as  will admit  of  their con-    sideration by  the Legislature.&quot;Colonial  Regulations in force since  1928,  however, provide asfollows (paragraph 210) :       &quot; Annual Estimates  of the  Revenue and Expenditure of    a Colony  will be submitted  by the Colonial  Secretary to the    Governor, etc.&quot;  It is  therefore no  longer necessary for the  Colonial Secretaryhimself to be responsible for the preparation of estimates.  The present  arrangement  under which financial  responsibilityis divided between the Treasurer and the Secretariat seems likely
to lead to  lack of control, duplication, waste of energy, and  un-necessary expense.  In the present difficulties of the  Colony itappears  to be more  than ever necessary that there  should be one  official primarily  responsible for finance in  all its aspectsand  for advising  both the Executive  and Legislative Councils onall financial matters.                   Prospects for out-turn of 1932.  106. It is now  necessary to consider the prospects of the budgetout-turn for the year  1932, and the information which is at present available definitely points to a worsening of the position.   although a deficit on January accounts is unusual, there was a  heavy fallin Customs revenue  this year.   The  Colony&apos;s  loan  charges  were increased in January  by  50,263, being the first payment of a half-year^ interest on the loan contracted in 1930, in which  by far thelargest  item was a  provision  of  973,367 for  public  buildings.Eliminating, for  the purpose  of  revenue  comparison,  colonial development Fund receipts in 1931 and 1932 and the  additionalreimbursements  amounting to   51,273 from  the Railways  and harbours Administration, the revenue for January shows a short-fall of  48,410 as compared with revenue for January, 1931.   Thepreliminary figures for  February  and March  indicate  a furtherdecrease of  28,449 making a total decline of  76,859 on the first three months of the year as compared  with the  correspondingperiod of 1931.  In respect of Customs duties an increase of  62,595on last year&apos;s revenue was shown in  the 1932 budget  estimates.There is already, however, a short-fall  of approximately  59,000in Customs receipts on the first three months of the year as comparednot  with the budget estimates but with the  lower level of  lastyear&apos;s monthly receipts.   The short-fall is the more discouragingsince the basic figure of Customs duties in force last year includednothing for the wines and spirits  duties which had not at  thattime  been  incorporated  in the general Customs revenue.  Against these decreases may be set the arrears of 1931 in nativehut and poll tax  amounting to approximately   30,000 which  havebeen collected  during the first  three  months  of 1932.   It is too early to judge how far the collecting of these arrears will be offset by a possible short-fall in the hut tax  estimate for 1932.                       Prospective deficit.  107. It is impossible at this stage to estimate with any confidencethe deficiencies which are likely to develop as compared with therevenue estimates for the current year.  I have, however, examined the latest available  returns  as to  the  yield of revenue under itsvarious heads since the beginning of the year and compared it withthe original  estimates and  the corresponding  figures of  1931.
Appendix 10, Table 4, page 121, showing a total estimated short-fall of  281,700 is  based on  this information.   There might well  beincreases of revenue  under other subheads  which cannot  yet  before seen, but on  present  information  it would appear reasonable to expect a net short-fall in  total revenue  of about  250,000 ascompared with the budget  figures.   Assuming  the expenditure to be at the level  to which it has been reduced by the recent reduc-tions already referred to, this may lead  to  a  deficit on  the  1932accounts of  144,682.                         Cash position.  108.  In Appendix 10, Table 5, page 122, a statement is given of the cash position which may be expected to develop by the end of 1932 inthe  event of a  deficiency of  250,000 as forecast in the footnote toTable 4.  It will be seen that  a cash deficiency of  181,639 wouldresult after making provision for the  100,000 required for day-to-day needs of the Government.                     Prospects o  recovery.  109.  It is now possible to discuss the trend of various factors inthe budget position and to try to assess the likelihood of recovery.  Expenditure may still further be reduced as  the result of an examination by  an  Economy Committee.   No great alleviation,however, can be hoped for in this  direction because, as  already pointed out, the economies achieved by that Committee will be partially offset by the decreasing advantage of certain economies ofa temporary nature effected by the postponement of expenditure.                   Yield of direct taxation.  110. There is little prospect of expansion in the yield of direct taxation owing to the fact that it does not at present vary accordingto capacity, but depends to a great extent on the inelastic system of native and non-native poll taxes.                   Yield of indirect taxation.  111. Indirect taxation shows no present sign of recovery andthere is strong evidence that the recent increases in the tariff and the encouragement which they have given to the development of Kenyaindustries must lead to diminishing returns.  The protective effectthat is already shown by some of the duties imposed can be gauged
from the following examples comparing the revenue derived fromduties, the quantities and the values of selected imports in 1928 and1931 :-	1928.			1931.			Customs Revenue.	Quantity.	Value.	Customs Revenue.	Quantity.	Value.Bacon and Ham . . Ghee . . Sugar . . Tea Wood and Timber Aluminium Hollow-ware . . Butter . . Cheese . .	  268 3,092 49,880 20,972 7,618 5,634 243 629	93 cwt. 8,986 ,, 78,353 ,, 8,897 ,, 116,809 tons 166 ,, 147 cwt. 262	  848 36,372 66,406 81,913 17,380 31,302 1,624 2,968	  74 1,341 2,377 2,799 3,174 333 110 332	35 cwt. 5,813 ,, 5,377 ,, 1,341 ,, 71,792 tons 13 ,, *110 cwt. 122 ,,	  313 14,891 4,893 11,621 9,386 2,255 803 1,228* Includes 87 cwt. (value ^580) of Kenya butter re-imported.  It will be seen from the above that Kenya producers and manu-facturers are making good use of their opportunities and although this  development is of excellent promise from the point of view ofinternal production  it cannot fail to have an increasing adverse effect upon the yield of the tariff.  A consideration of the revenuederived from certain luxury duties also suggests that they are now so high as to check consumption and that more revenue might besecured by a lower rate of duty.  Owing  to the Customs Union thisis a matter which cannot in any case be considered by Kenya alone,but  when the periodic reconsideration of tariff rates takes place itwill  be necessary to ensure that any decreases in the rates on theluxuries  consumed by non-natives are  set off  by  correspondingconcessions to the native population who, especially in the matterof dirty on unbleached cotton goods, are paying a specific rate farabove the ad valorem standard originally  fixed, and who have there-fore a strong claim to a lightening of the burden of taxation whichthey are paying on  this  article, the purchase  of which absorbs aconsiderable part of their cash resources (cp. paragraph 37).  Although there is some ground for re-examining the case forlightening certain  rates of import duty, it is out of the question to embark on any course which might involve loss of existing revenueuntil the budget has been balanced and until the yield of new taxationwhich may be imposed is established not merely on estimates, butupon firm experience.
                        Other revenues.   112. The items of revenue which have not been shown in Appendix 10, Table 4, are not likely to make any appreciable difference in the balance.                         Debt charges.   113. The increased burden of public debt involves a very heavy charge on the taxpayer.  The whole burden of sinking-fund payments will not be felt until 1935 when the full sinking-fund charges on the 1930 loan become  payable.  Taxpayers who examine these figures may not unreasonably enquire whether there is no hope of relieving their prospective load by means of conversion.  Such a course might lighten the responsibilities of the present taxpayers by throwing the burden forward on to the shoulders of a future generation, who may be in a better position to pay for their advantages when the  fruits of present expenditure on development are being gathered.  The  possibility  of  debt  conversion will no  doubt be  carefully watched, but it is  well to point out  that  the problem in Kenya is very  different from that  in Great  Britain.   Whereas British Conversion Loans  have been issued to deal with  debt close to the date of maturity,  the borrowings  of Kenya are not repayable for many years to come and stand to-day at a price well  above par. Under  such conditions,  debt  could only be  converted with  the consent of the bondholders, and it  is evident that terms would naturally  be required  for a  successful  conversion which would prevent any spectacular advantage to the borrower.                     Prospects summarized.  114.  To summarize the prospects,  there is no present indication that the financial difficulties of Kenya will solve themselves.  Nextyear appears likely to open with an adverse balance against cashreserves and with the expectation of a large deficit on the revenue and expenditure accounts even on present lines without  taking into consideration  the  re-adjustments summarized in  paragraph  92. The yield of taxation is dropping steadily below last year&apos;s estimates.Those subheads such as stamp duties and licences  (see Appendix 10, Table 4, page 121) which give an indication of the state of commerce and industry point to stagnant or shrinking conditions of business. On the other hand, although import duties are at present falling far short of the budget estimate  it  must be  remembered that if this year&apos;s coffee crop fulfils its present promise of yield and  quality, an increase of  purchasing-power will result for coffee growers and native  pickers, and this may be expected to bring about  some increase in the revenue from import duties as compared  with the short-fall  indicated  by  the  present receipts and estimates  in Appendix 10,  Table  4.  This possibility cannot be  assessed  in figures and in any  case would only be of uncertain duration.
  It would surely be unwise to build hopes of permanent financialrecovery on so narrow a foundation.  Crops vary from year to yearand it would appear that in the absence of a world-wide recovery ofprices budget stability can only be ensured by broadening the bases of tax revenue.                    Need for fresh taxation.  115. During the present stringency there is a natural fear of thedepressing effect of new  taxation, in spite of  the world-wide ex-perience of the danger of  unbalanced budgets.  Taxation, however,can be devised on such principles as would protect capital resources from any interference.  Attention has been drawn to the inelasticityand one-sided foundation  of Kenya finances. Even in a storm it is sometimes necessary to re-stow the cargo, and in the  heaviest ofweather it is imperative at least to stop the leak of an  unbalancedfinancial system.   Kenya can  only ensure escape  from present difficulties by following the example of the rest of the world and by taking  action without delay to restore her position, not only  bybalancing the budget  out  of revenue but also by  replacing theexhausted cash reserves so as to avoid the need of meeting current expenditure out of borrowings.  I am forced to the conclusion thatfresh taxation is called for.   It can be imposed in a well-tried form which need involve no serious hardship.  Increased burdens cannotwith any justice be borne by the native population and, if imposed,they should be graduated according to the ability to pay.   Various alternative methods of direct taxation  which have been applied in other parts of the Empire, with or without income-tax inaddition, have consequently been considered.                   Taxes on land and buildings.   116.  A land tax, whether applied generally or to undevelopedland only, would be inapplicable to Kenya in  view of the extreme difficulty of arriving at a fair valuation.  There  is very little demandfor agricultural land in the settled areas under present conditions,and valuations based upon erratic market prices would be unjust.The  possibility of a tax on buddings, or alternatively a tax ofnarrower application  on inhabited houses only, has also been examined.  The former tax would operate ve^ unequally as betweenindustries and persons, having regard to the great variations in needs for building accommodation. An inhabited-house duty based on avaluation  of the dwelling occupied, although it  might bear somerelation to the apparent standard of life, would be extremely unequalin its incidence upon income. An overwhelming objection, however,to taxes of this type in  a community  where agriculture is of suchgreat importance as in Kenya is that they would fall with heavyincidence  upon  that  industry  and  upon many individuals whoare making no income and from whom no  tax could justly beraised.a
                Problem of income-tax in Kenya.   117. Income-tax in Kenya is apt  to  be judged  on the  very exceptional experience of 1921.  When it was imposed in that year alarge proportion of taxpayers failed to pay, and, instead of enforcing the law, the  Government decided to repeal the tax on the recom-mendation of a local Economic and Finance Committee in 1922.The distortion which the half-hearted enforcement of the tax broughtabout in the receipts can be judged from the fact that, although theestimated yield for the nine months of 1921 was  328,413,  only 95,073 was  eventually  collected, and doubtless  owing largely tothe passive resistance of a section of the population, the proportionreceived from employed persons worked out at 63 per cent, of thetotal receipts as against 1 per cent, in England.  The  mixed  population of Asiatics offers  no special problem in kenya.  It would, seem reasonable that accounts should be kept in english, or at the  most in one other language, and in a particular form, and there is  already  an arsenal of fiscal weapons which  maybe borrowed, to deal with administrative details, from many CrownDependencies where the same  and other initial  difficulties havebeen successfully overcome.                Light non-native direct taxation.  118.  The argument  is sometimes used that the imposition of an income-tax would  deter prospective settlers from choosing  thisColony.  In view, however, of the almost universal application ofthis system and the high rates in force elsewhere, Kenya would stilloffer great advantages to intending settlers under the comparativelylight scale of  taxation which would be  necessary if remedial actionbe taken in advance of a serious crisis.  The comparison  of the burden of non-native taxation in Kenyawith that borne by taxpayers in other  countries is indeed striking.Whereas elsewhere  civilized communities have had  to maintain their solvency  by  adding  still  further to burdens of direct  and indirect taxation which had already seemed  almost intolerable, thenon-native population of Kenya are in the probably unparalleledposition among civilized nations of bearing no direct taxation at allbeyond a male poll tax of Shs. 30, a male  education tax of Shs. 20or Shs. 30, and a comparatively light  scale of death-duties.   Theresource of direct  taxation in some degree proportionate to themeans of the taxpayer is  therefore at present practically untapped,and the budgetary balance could be restored by  a relatively lowtax on incomes.  The growing industries of Kenya  are naturally anxious not to discourage fresh capital,  but the British  investor is much more likely to feel  alarm at the present precarious budgetary situation11310)c
with undefined possibilities of future taxation than by a reasonablerate of income-tax.   Under the usual arrangement for double-income-tax  relief  within the  Empire  such tax would  make no difference to the  total tax payable on an income  and  would ineffect  merely be deducted by the taxpayer from the higher rateotherwise due to  the British Inland Revenue.                 Necessity for balanced budget.  119. The opposition to income-tax now evident in  Kenya  may perhaps be based very largely on imperfect knowledge of the realfinancial position and prospects of  the Colony.   When the facts and  alternatives are realized, the  non-native  population  whoseenterprise and belief in the  future of their new country havehitherto contributed so much to its progress will  doubtless not fail to respond to the need of enabling the  Colony again to balance itsbudget, by  accepting an  equitable system of   taxation in  pro-portion to capacity.   Neither her youth among peoples nor her fairinheritance among nations can save Kenya from facing hard facts and from the need  to adjust her circumstances  to new and harsheconomic  conditions.XII. CONCLUSIONS  AND RECOMMENDATIONS.                           Summary.  120. Recommendations  are made for exemption from native hutand poll tax of widows inherited when past child-bearing age andfor the granting of certificates of exemption from taxes for life for old and  infirm persons in suitable  cases  (paragraphs 11 and 12,page 7).  Owing to the inelasticity of the present system of native hut andpoll tax  and differences in wealth both as  between Districts and individuals, the  following changes are recommended for  gradualintroduction :       Native hut and poll tax to be charged at varying rates according    to the  taxable capacity  of Districts  (paragraph 21, page 13),    pending gradual replacement and reorganisation under paragraphs    24 and 22, respectively;      Uniform male native poll tax at the rate of Shs. 6 to be collected    by tax stamps on registration  certificates (paragraph 22, page    14) ;
       Tax  on  native  livestock over  and  above certain minima     necessary  or mamtaining  life  to be  introduced  in suitable     Districts  (paragraph 23, page 14) ;       Native  cultivation tax to be substituted  or hut tax (paragraph     24, page 16).   Reduction o  railway rates on unbleached cotton cloth aud blankets o  cheap qualities is recommended (paragraph 35, page 19).   Figures are  given to show racial contributions to indivisible services (paragraph 44, page 34).  It is shown that natives cannot in present circumstances  airly be expected  to make a  heavier contribution to revenue  and that  any present increase in the total taxation paid by communities that may be found necessary should be borne by non- natives (paragraph 49, page 27).   The cost of non-native education is discussed  and it is  suggested that non-native poll and education  taxes  should be  consolidated (paragraph 53, page 29).   The cost of European education should be examined  by the pro- posed  Economy  Committee  (paragraph 54).  Education facilities should be provided  for Goans  (paragraph  55, page 29),  and also for the Ishaak Shariff and  Darot Ismailia Communities (paragraph 56, page 30).   The Economy Committee should examine the finance  of  local government with  special  reference to the basic  road-grants (para- graph 60, page 31).   As a set-off to  the large proportion  of expenditure now devoted to research on non-native agricultural problems, applied  research on Questions affecting native  agriculture  should be initiated in the Reserves aud in the Coast Province. Application should be made to Colonial  Development  Fund  for  the  necessary building  grants (paragraph 65, page 35).   Agricultural teaming schools should be attached to these  Research centres in Native Reserves (paragraph 66, page 36).   It is proposed to set up  a Native Betterment Committee to finance and co-ordinate the  direct native services of  education, health, agriculture, and roads, etc. (paragraph 70, page 38).   The  Native  Betterment  Fund should be financed by the grant of 50 per cent, of six  years&apos; average yield of native hut and poll tax or any future substitutes (paragraph 76, page 40).   To improve  defective marketing  arrangements  in native areas a Native Marketing Advisory  Council should be set  up (paragraph 82, page 43).  Local Native Councils  should  be brought gradually  into closertouch with  District  Administration which  should be increasinglyfinanced by grants-in-aid  from Native Betterment Fund  (paragraph 89, page 46).(11310)C 2
  Employment of communal labour should be allowed under proper safeguards  at  the  option  of Local Native  Councils (paragraph 90,page 47).  Attention is drawn to the failure to balance budgets from revenueevery year  from 1929 onwards (paragraph 93, page 48).  The division of financial responsibility under the existing system in Kenya and  the consequent lack of proper financial control arecriticized (paragraphs 103-105, pages 52 and 53).  On present indications it is shown that this year&apos;s deficit on revenue account may amount to about  250,000, which  would involve thecomplete exhaustion of accumulated surpluses and a cash deficiency of about  180,000 (paragraphs  107 and 108, pages 54 and 55).  No prospect  is discovered that present financial difficulties  willsolve themselves, and a recommendation is made that budget stabilityshould be ensured by broadening the bases of tax revenue (paragraph114, page 57).  Alternative forms of  direct  taxation are discussed in paragraphs116 to 118  (pages 60 and 61).                       Acknowledgments.  121. I wish  to express my appreciation of the great help afforded by Mr. H.  H.  Rushton, Treasurer of  Kenya, and I am particularlyindebted to Mr. K. S.  J. Chamberlain,  Assistant Treasurer, whocarried out with great efficiency much detailed work in preparationof the schedules, etc.  Mr. H.  E. Bader, of the Secretariat, organizedthe collection  of evidence  in advance  of my arrival, and during my visit contributed much  to the smoothness  of local arrangements.  Major A.. W.. Fosbroke-Hobbes accompanied me  from Englandas Secretary for the enquiry.   He showed the greatest ability and efficiency and his  assistance was invaluable  to me throughout myinvestigations  and in the preparation of the Report.                    I have the honour to  be,                    .          Sir,.                                Your obedient Servant,                                                    MOYNE.nth May, 1932.
APPENDIX  1.                                                 SCHEDULE 1.Summary of Revenue collected, in 1931, Distinguishing Taxation Revenue from Other Revenue and Classifying Contributions of                                             the various  Communities.	Europeans.	Indians.	Goans.	Arabs.	Natives.	Indivisible.	Total.								  :	  &apos;	  ,	  -	 	  :	 DIRECT TAXATION ......	42,596	39,170	3,251	18,114	530,877	- &apos;	634,008INDIRECT TAXATION	334,477	145,213	47,346	16,992	. 199,181	2,345	745,554OTHER TAXATION REVENUE	109,113	45,406	4,057	6,241	11,446	1,936	178,199OTHER REVENUE (NOT TAXATION) ..	179,595	49,213	3,752	6,903	49,596	1,220,110*	1,509,169TOTAL .. .. 	665,781	279,002	58,406	48,250	791,100	1,224,391	3,066,930   * IncludesPost Office........    ..      168,132Reimbursements    ..    ..    ..    ..      883,716
APPENDIX  1 (Continued).      SCHEDULE  2.  (Details of Schedule 1.)         DIRECT TAXATION.Native Hut and Poll TaxNon-Native Poll Tax  ..European Education TaxAsiatic Education TaxEstate Duty.....                 Total         INDIRECT TAXATION.Customs DutiesPetrol Tax     ........Wines  and Spirits Consumption TaxBeer Excise Duty                 Total      ..     ..t     OTHER TAXATION REVENUE.Native RegistrationGame LicencesExplosives,  Gun  and  Ammunition  LicencesEuropeans.12,41111,39918,78642,596298,582 22,296 11,808  1,791334,47711,166 2,114Indians.21,90014,481 2,78939,170137,480  4,047  3,200   486145,213228327Goans.Arabs. 3,005  2463,25144,739   182 2,106   31947,3466671   5,25512,85918,11416,625  36716,992 66165Natives.Indivisible.   530,877530,877198,813   368199,1811,460  79  1822,3452,345Total.530,877 42,571 11,399 14,481 34,680634,008698,584 27,260 17,114  2,596745,554 1,46011,605 2,85905
Liquor Licences	4,684	2,147	2,070	18	2,322	_	11,241Traffic Licences	42,615	7,735	349	701	705	 	52,105Miscellaneous Licences	1,788	1,102	66	493	518	_	3,967Licences under Carriage of Goods 							Motor Control Ordinance	_	1,290	 	 		_	1,290Coffee Licences	1,254	44	 	2	2	_	1,302Registration of Documents and Titles	1,596	1,068	117	187	195	_	3,163Stamp Duties, various Revenue pur-							poses	33,265	13,693	598	&apos; 432	264	1,652	49,904Cattle Traders&apos; Licences	55	360	6	1,354	1,863	 	3,638Traders&apos; Licences	5,276	14,312	601	959	423	_	21,571Registrar-general&apos;s, Official Receivers,							and Public Trusteed Fees	1,624	1,739	48	279	157	_	3,847Registration of Companies and Business							Names ........	965	287	17	 	 	 	1,269Registration of Inventions, Designs, and							Trade Marks, and Bills of Sale Fees	483	43	4	 	  -	 	530Conveyancing Fees on Crown Titles ..	742	569	15	23	30	22	1,401Market and Cattle Pound Fees	236	58	, .	1,216	1,841	_	3,351Miscellaneous Fees (Cemetery, Marriage							and Divorce ; Translation and Copy-							ing; Testing Liquor; Weights and							Measures; Legal Library; Fees							under Ordinances for Doctors, Den-							tists and Druggists, Pawnbrokers,							etc.)..........	1,216	327	29	346	1,405	9	3,332Fees for Licences to Exhibit Films ..	34	77	-		-	253	364Total .. .. 								109,113	45,406	4,057	6,241	11,446	1,936	178,199
Europeans.Indians.Goans.Arabs.Natives.Indivisible.Total.  OTHER REVENUE (NOT  TAXATION).Fines and ForfeituresFees of CourtSurvey FeesVeterinary Inoculation Fees, etc.Hospital FeesBills of Health........Infectious  Diseases  Hospital  Fees,  Nairobi MunicipalityInfectious  Diseases  Hospital  Fees,  Mombasa MunicipalityMarine Protest Fees......Passport Fees........Tuition Fees, European Schools    ,,      ,, Indian      ,,Boarding Fees, European Schools    ,,      ,,   Indian     ,,Special Police  GuardsConservancy, Water Rates, etc., general medical Research LaboratoryAgricultural Produce, Grading, Condi-  tioning and Cold Storage Fees, etc. ..Registration of Domestic Servants  6603,1623,4493,4429,635  374 4,11212,436  163 1,915  623 6,665  3161,0309,120  348  170  412   42  8865,1941,0002,010   72  470  104 24343 32 24188172  443 3101,817  331,352  22  21232620,60710,226    74 6,92985534690108594292121 1714402813522,63124,668 4,04411,89310,093   657   292   121    17 1,479 4,112 5,19412,436 1,000   177 4,248   727 7,669 1,289SCHEDULE 2-(Continued).
Widows&apos; and Orphans&apos; Pensions Con-							tributions	25.268	 	 	 	_	_	25,268Aviation Housing and Landing Fees ..	518	 	 	 	 	_	518Fees from Agricultural Chemical Labor-							explanatory	108	 	 		 	 	108Fees from Government Analyst	156	 	 	 	 	53	209Boarding Fees, Arab and African		 	 	 	69	 	69Reimbursements .. ;.	588	 	 	 	2,688	887,864	891,140Posts and Telegraphs	 	 	 	 	 	168,132	168,132Earnings of Government Departments	24,001	12,468	2,223	2,390	2,333	44,206	87,621Revenue from Government Property							and Royalties	51,363	8,603	650	728	725	9,278	71,347Sale of Government Property	2,052	557	9	88	2,588	9,283	14,577Miscellaneous Receipts	756	512	40	23	1,713	13,148	16,192Interest	7,433	_	_	_	_	22,061	29,494Forest Department Revenue	1	8	 	20	309	30,563	30,901Land Sales ........	20,399	6,207	 	49	18	3,250	29,923Colonial Development Fund	-.	&apos;		-		30,923	30,923Total Other Revenue (Not Taxation)  	179,595	49,213	3,752	6,903	49,596	1,220,110	1,509,169
                             APPENDIX  1.                            SCHEDULE 3.                   Incidence of Customs Duties, 1931.                 NOTE  BY COMMISSIONER OF CUSTOMS.  Figures in the last column are exact.  The remainder are purely estimatesliable to a wide margin of error so far as individual items are concerned, but probably not grossly inaccurate in regard to aggregate totals.  The difficulty of assessing the amount of duty paid by various sections of thecommunity on such articles as motor spirit, cinema films, building materials,etc., is obvious, and the statement is submitted with considerable diffidence,seeing that it is based so largely on guess-work.                                                  G. WALSH,                                            Commissioner of Customs,                                                Kenya and Uganda.
APPENDIX  1 Continued.SCHEDULE  3-Conlinued.An Estimate of the Incidence of Taxation through the Customs Tariff based on the Net Customs Duty collected on Goods retained for                                      Consumption in Kenya during the year 1931.Articles.		Indians.	Goans.	Arabs, Somalis	Natives.	Total net	Europeans.					duty.				and others.		CLASS I 	 	 	 	 	 	 Wheat..............		350	5	30	 	385Barley ..	5	8	 	 	 	13Rice ..............	617	6,000	1,000	1,000	8,500	17,117Millet .. .. .. .. ......	_	100	50	34	100	284Other Grain	_	30	 	 	2	32Beans	 	_	 	 	20	20Pulse		200	22	 	100	322Dhall ..............	_	1,000	140	 	 	1,140Wheat, Meal, and Flour	3,500	9,000	500	500	240	13,740Pulse Meal and Flour..........	_	200	33	 	 	233Other Meal and Flour	14	 	 	 	50	64Feeding Stuffs, other sorts	11	20	10	10	60	111Bacon and Ham	60	 	4	 	 	64Meat, Tinned, Canned or otherwise preserved	300	10	15	- ;		325Poultry and Game, Dead Aerated Waters	5	 	 	 	 	5	70	5	6	 	 	81Ale, Beer, Stout, etc...........	10,000	842	1,500	 		12,342Betel Nuts ............		400	  i*	16	 	416Baking Powder...... ,, ,. ,. Beverages and Syrups	250 332	20 300	47	.		317			100	50	50	832Biscuits	1,400	358	200	 	 	1,958Butter	40	3	3	 	 	46
SCHEDULE ^-(Continued).				Arabs,		Total net duty.Articles.	Europeans.	Indians.	Goans.	Somalis	Natives.					and others.		CLASS I continued.	 	 	&apos;  . .	 	 	 Cakes, Pudding, and Pastry	9		 			cheese	300	10	22	 	 	332Coffee, Parchment	6	 	 	 	 	6Unhulled .. ..........	10			 		10,, Prepared	1	 	-	&apos; --. ,	, 	1Chocolates and manufactures thereof	900	283	200	 	 	1,383Other Sweets and Confectionery	800	404	400	100	&apos; 300	2,004Dates	20	50	20	300	100	490Extracts and Essences, Food	50	20	7	 	 	77Extracts and Essences, Flavouring	50	54	50	50	50	254Fish, Salted, Pickled, or Dried .. .....	36	20	20	100	200	376Fish, Canned or otherwise preserved ..	750	250	300	100	127	1,527Fish, Fresh or Frozen	.100	 	8	 	 	108Fruit, Bottled, Canned or otherwise preserved	800	19	100	 	 	919Fruit, Dried .. .. .. .. i.	300	757	100	100	100	1,357Garlic and Onions, not preserved ......	68	2,000	100	300	 	2,468Ghee	 	1,100	 	24	 	1,124Hops.............	100	9	10	 	 	119Lard and its Compounds ..	60	5	8	--		73						Macaroni, Vermicelli and Spaghetti	200	 	52	 	 	252Malt and Wort, Condensed ...	250	10	12	 	 	272Margarine, Marrowfat, Butter-substitutes and similar						164substances for use as food or in cooking	150		14	 	 	Marmalades, Jams and Jellies	500	100	188	50	50	888
Molasses	to	 	 	 	 	milk, Condensed or otherwise preserved	2,000	1,500	500	500	864	5,364Patent Foods	350	50	48	 	-	448Pickles, Sauces, Chutneys and Condiments	400	200	100	26	 	726Provisions, Other	600	1,219	500	500 .	1,000	3,819Table Salt	180	20	10	 	 	210Salt for Curing, Dairy and Agricultural purposes	59	 &apos;	 	 	 	59Salt, Other .. .. ......	500	. 740	200	500	2,000	3,940Spices	200	1,500	100	59	 	1,859Brandy	5,000	4,337	9,000	 	 	18,337Gin and Geneva ..	18,000	 	644	 	 	18,644Liqueurs	2,000	25	500	 	-	2,525Rum .. .. .. .. .....	250	 	18	 	 	268Whisky .. ,. .. ..	75,000	5,121	8,000	 	 	88,121Spirits, Unenumerated	50	 	14	 	 	64Jaggery ........	 	9	 	5	15	29Sugar, Refined, in bulk	500	566	200	200	500	1,966Refined, in packages or tins	300	25	38	 	 	363,, Saccharine and derivatives thereof	25	 	  -	 	 	25Tea - :. .. .; &apos; :.. ..	1,000	850	113	150	500	2,613Vermouth	4,000	-	296	 	 	4,296Wine, Still, in bottles	3,000	 	279	 	 	3,279,, Still, in casks	500	 	135		 	635Sparkling Wine (Champagne) ..	1,500	50	46	 	 	1,596,, ,, (Other than Champagne) ..	200	 	26	 	 	226Other Foods .. .. .. .. ....	175	50	50	25	75	375Yeast ..............	3	 	 	 	 	3Cigarettes	6,254	5,000	2,000	1,000	40,000	54,254Cigars and Cigarillos	1,000	100	90	 	 	1,190Tobacco, Manufactured .. .. .. ,, Unmanufactured Snuff .............. Total .......... 	2,000	1,000	409	500 40	15,000 10 100	18,909 10 140							147,112	46,299	28,562	6,269	70,113	298,355Cv3
SCHEDULE 3-iContinued).Articles.	Europeans.	Indians.	Goans.	Arabs, Somalis and others.	Natives.	Total net duty.CLASS 11 	i	 	 	&apos;  	 	  ,Teak ..............	300	300	. 77	-		677Timber, Hewn or Sawn .. ........	1,000	700	200	100	306	2,306,, Planed or Dressed	70	9	_	_	_	79,, Other Sorts ..........	20	10	_	_	7	37Coir, Fibre	10	10	5		3	28Gum Arabic	7	_				7Beeswax	1	_			_	1Oil, Groundnut ..		5		3	5	13,, Sesame .. .. .. .. -	_	6	_		5	11Skins, Other Animal	50	16	r.			66Shells, Marine	9	_		_	_	9Goods, Unmanufactured .. .. ,.	100	40	2	-	-	142Total .. .. .. .. .. 	1,567	1,096	284	103	326	3,376CLASS III 						Chinaware, Porcelainware ........	250	250	50	25	82	657Bricks .. .. .. ..	25	25	3	_.	_	53Tiles .. .. ........	200	200	25	_	_	425Sanitary-ware	350	100	10	_	_	460Earthenware, Other	300	200	100	100	207	907Chimneys, Globes and Shades	30	SO	20	50	262	412
Glass Bottles and Jars, Common	6	6	_	_		12Glassware, Domestic and Fancy	231	100	50	20	50	451Mirrors and Looking-glasses ..	75	75	19	20	80	269Plate and Sheet Glass..........	300	200	86	_	_	586Glass and Glassware, Unspecified	350	132	100	50	200	832Asbestos, Manufactured.........	250	200	45	&apos;_. -	_	495Cement, Building ..........	6,000	2,000	300	57	500	8,857Chalk, Prepared :.......	20	 	2	- ...	 	22Fireclay	20	8	 	 	 	28Grindstones	 	6	 	_		6Slates, Roofing	5	5	 	 	 	10Miningand Quarry Products, Manufactured,Unspecified	300	39	 	 	 	339Anchors, Chains and Grapnels	8	 	 	 	_	8Bars, Rods, Angles, Shapes and Sections	500	200	88	 	 	788Bedsteads and Finished Parts thereof	150	50	28	_	_	228Buildings, Sections and Parts	1,500	800	271	150	 	2,721Galvanised Sheets, Corrugated	1,500	1,200	300	200	681	3,881,, ,, Flat ........	250	100	21	 	_	371Girders, Beams, Joists, Pillars, etc.	50	40	18	 	_	108Hollow-ware, Enamelled	210	500	100	100	500	1,410,, Not Enamelled Nails, Screws, Rivets, Bolts, Hinges, etc.....	81	50	10	10	50	201	600	300	75	25	187	1,187Plates and Sheets, Not Galvanised	100	87	 	 	_	187Stoves, Grates, and Ranges (domestic)	250	75	31	 	 	356Safes .. .. .. .. ......	125	100	25	 	 	250Tubes, Pipes, and their Fittings	5	 	 	 		5Wire Cable and Rope (Not Electrical)	2	 	 	 	 	2Wire, Iron, Other Sorts	 	 	 	 	30	30Wire Steel, Other Sorts ,........	 	- 	 	 	13	13Wire Mattresses	30	19	 	_	_	49Iron and Steel Manufacturers n/e	1,000	500	100	89	200	1,889Aluminium Hollow-ware, Domestic	50	50	13	_	20	133Aluminium Wire .. .. J.	 	 	 	 	35	35Aluminium Sheets	300	400	70	100	500	1,370
 APPENDIX 1- (Continued).SCHEDULE 3-(Continued).Articles.	Europeans.	Indians.	Goans.	Arabs, Somalis	Natives.	Total net duty.				and others.			 	  .	  ..	  .	 	 CLASS III. continued.						Brass Sheets, Plain or Perforated ......	15	6	  -	 	 	21Brass Wire	30	12	 	 	350	392Brass Manufactures, Unenumerated	150	150	6	 	50	356Copper Sheets, Plain or Perforated	6	3		 	 	9Copper Wire ....	13	  &apos;	 	 	300	313Copper Manufactures, Unenumerated	6	16	4	 	 	26Lead, Bar and Sheet .......	30	5	 	 	 	35Lead Manufactures, Unenumerated .. ..	30	20	8	 		58Tin, Bar, Plate or Sheet	2	2	-.		 	4Tin Manufactures, Unenumerated ...	50	50	16	10	50	176Zinc, Bar, Plate or Sheet	10	2	 	-		12Zinc Manufactures	2	-	 	-	 	2Metal, Bar, Block, Ingots, or Pigs	: 40	8	 	 	-	48Metal Manufactures, not elsewhere specified	500	150	50	20	46	766Agricultural and Horticultural Tools Artisans&apos; Tools .. .. .. .. ....	50	 	 	 	7	57	298	500	50	 	50	898Bioscopes, Magic Lanterns, Cinematographs, and					16	186Parts thereof	125	25	15	5		Clocks, Complete .. .. .....	100	90	25	10	50	275Cutlers&apos; Wares not elsewhere specified	185	150	25	50	350	760Hardware, other than hollow-ware	100	100	25	10	145	380Locks and Fastenings for Doors and Windows	400	360	30	22	250	1,062Implements and Tools and Parts thereof	400	100	25	10	164	699
Knives, other Machine Knives .. ..	SO	35	5	10	188	288Optical Instruments ..........	3	  -	 		 	3Photographic Cameras, Parts and Accessories	300	51	50	&apos; 	 -	401Binders, Reapers, and Mowers	13	-  		 	 	13Razors	20	20	30	4	25	79Shovels, Spades, Axes and Hatchets	40	20	5	5	50	120Scientific Instruments and Appliances..	7	.  -	 	 	-  	7Stoves, Primus and other Oil .. .....	60	40	15	5	17	137Watches, complete ..........	40	30	10		23	103Electrical Goods and Apparatus	900	500	SO	-	 	1,450Electric Light Bulbs ........	150	50	18	&apos; - .	 	218Pumps and Pumping Machinery-	800	500	68	  -	100	1,468Machinery and Parts not elsewhere specified	250	50	-	 	16	316Machines, Adding and Calculating ......	100	10	 	 	 	110Machines, Addressing, Duplicating, Numbering, and						8Perforating	8	 &apos;	 	 	 	Cash Registers	25	5	3	 	 	33Knitting Machines (Domestic)	2	 		 	 	2Sewing Machines (Domestic) .. .. ..	250	330	50&apos;	 	250	880Typewriters and Accessories .. .. ..	300	125	&apos; 12	 	  -	437Weighing Machines (Scales, Balances, etc.)	50	50	20	10	13	143Furniture and Cabinet-Ware	460	300	20	20	156	956Builders&apos; Woodwork (Window-frames, Domestic)	125	65	 	 	13	203Wooden Manufactures not elsewhere specified	300	200	50	20	95	665Cotton Piece-goods, grey, unbleached	500	3,000	22	100	36,400	40,022,, ,, bleached ..	592	1,500	200	200	2,100	4,592,, ,, printed khangas	 	 	 	-  	2,763	2,763printed, other sorts .. ..	1,000	1,800	200	734	3,000	6,734,, &apos; ,, dyed in the piece.. .. ..	1,250	3,250	500	617	10,000	15,617,, coloured (manufactured wholly or						15,274in part of dyed yarn)	1,500	3,274	500	1,000	9,000	Cotton Blankets .. .. .. .. ... ..	200	500	100	1,671	12,200	14,671,, Threads............	300	320	30	30	500	1,180,, Yarns .. .... ..	150	100	30	20	104	404
SCHEDULE 3-[Continued).Articles.	Europeans.	Indians.	Goans.	Arabs, Somalis and others.	Natives.	Total net duty.CLASS III. continued.	 	c. -	 	 	 	 Cotton Manufactures, not elsewhere specified	2,500	500	50	35	250	3,335Woollen Blankets ..........	700	500	184	200	1,800	3,384,, Carpets and Rugs	450	250	50	50	39	839,, Tissues............	. 750	100	25	25	53	953,, Yarns	27	 	 &apos;	 	 	27Manufactures, not elsewhere specified	300	40	15	8		363Silk Tissues	1,500	2,100	250	150	350	4,350,, Yarns	20	8	T-	 	 	28,, Manufactures, not elsewhere specified	100	50	11	 	 	161Awning, Tarpaulins, Tents, etc.	125	34	; 	 	16	159Coir Mats and Matting	30	40	10	5		101Cordage, Ropes, and Twine, Other	400	150	 	25	42	617Jute Carpets and Rugs	25	5	4	 	 	34Linen Piece-goods ..........	&apos;50	15	3	 	  -	68Linen Thread .. .. .. .. .&apos;.	30	2	.  	 	 	32Linen Manufactures, not elsewhere specified	350	60	21	-	-	431Sail Cloth and Canvas	500	300		 	15	815Textile Manufactures, not elsewhere specified	250	50	6	 	 	306Artificial Silk Piece-goods	1,000	1.800	250	100	750	3,900Artificial Silk Manufacturers ..	61	20	10	 	 	91Boots and Shoes ..........	1,000	600	200	100	555	2,455
HaberdasheryHats, Caps, etc...........Stockings and Hose    ..     ....Hosiery,  Other   ..     ..     ..     .. &apos;Wearing  Apparel, second-hand, imported for saleWearing  Apparel, not elsewhere specifiedCarbonic Acid Gas      ........Carbide of CalciumChemical Manufactures  and  Products,  Unenum-  eratedDyestuffs and Extracts for Dyeing and TanningPainters  Colours and VarnishesProducts and Materials, not elsewhere specifiedSodium Carbonate     ,, Caustic  ..     ,, Sulphocyanide  ..CandlesLubricating Oils ..Lubricating GreasesMotor SpiritMineral Oil, Illuminating or Burning (KeroseneSoap, Common   ..  ,,   Toilet  ,,   OtherTurpentineOils, Essential and PerfumedOil Manufactures n/e &apos;Leather,  DressedSaddlery and Harness  ..Leather Manufactures  ..Paper, Cigarette ..   ,, Packing 1,000  300  500 2,000 2,000    30    10 1,000    60 1,000    23  300  100     2    75 1,250  20030,000 3,000  750 1,000  100    50  150  350  500  287  700  500  500  300  100  200 1,000     7  300    20  750    19    25    25  750  10020,000 2,027  500    84    46    20    50    42  400  100  100100	24	10075	39	50025	10	3050	,  	15. 	73	1,400500 4	200	1,073 		17610	10	7250	-	15910	-	37100	50	205 	 	432,000	334	6,000500	1,000	14,000100	150	951150	z	-4 20	5	32100	9	16025	50	25 o50	50	0 134 1,724 1,214  665 2,265 1,473 4,773   41    10. 1,476   107 2,159    23  319   125     2   147 2,355  34358,33420,527 2,451 1,234   146    74  257  392 1,169  287  900     8  834
APPENDIX l-(Continued).SCHEDULE ^-(Continued).Articles.EuropeansIndians.Goans.  Arabs, Somalisand others.Natives.Total net  duty.CLASS III contd.    Paper, Printing  ..        ,,  Other    Playing Cards    Stationery    Paper Manufactures, Unspecified    Cycles (not Motor)    Motor Cars    Motor Car Parts and Accessories    Motor Lorries    Motor Lorry Parts and Accessories    Motor Cycles    Motor Cycle, Sidecar and Tricar Parts and AccessoriesOther Vehicles, not mechanically propelledOther Vehicles, Parts of and AccessoriesMotor Car  Covers   ,,     ,,  TubesMotor Cycle Covers         ,,   TubesBicycle Covers        Tubes  :	 	 		 	 500	342	_	_	_	842100	40	9	 	 	14970	60	20	30	50	2304,000	1,500	250	50	264	6,0641,400	300	29	 	 	1,72950	50	50	 	399	5496,000	3,000	362	 	 	9,3622,250	1,250	82		 	3,582500	432	 	 	 	932100	99	 		  . .	19975	75	25	 	53	228: 70	70	20	 	24	18450	50	20	_	36	156100	100	20	 	55	2753,500	1,750	250	 	479	5,979500	250	35	 	102	88720	20	5	 	4	4910	10	2	 	4	264	- -	_	 	20	248	 		 	. 30	3S
Power Lorry Covers .. .. .. &apos; ..	1,500	750	200	50	253	2,753Tubes Rubber Manufactures, unspecified	170	80	20	7	33	310	300	110	23	20	50	503Air Guns and Air Rifles	6	 	  ...	 	 	6Ammunition (Sporting)	750	 	6	 	 	756Basketware	20	7	 	 	 	27Beads .. ..	90	 	 	 	2,000	2,090Blacking ..............	100	20	5		 	125Polishes	1,250	100	28	 	 	1,378Brooms and Brushes	400	150	50	20	179	799Electro-plated ware ..........	100	30	8	 	 	138Felt, Ruberoid, Uralite, and similar substances for						building purposes ........	200	38	 	 	 	238Films for Bioscopes and Cinematographs	290	75	25	10	20	420Films and Plates for Photographic Cameras	475	74	25	 	 	574Guns, Rifles, Revolvers, and Pistols	623	 	 	 	 	623Gold, and Silver-plated ware	90	4 &apos;	 	 	 	94Jewellery and Imitation Jewellery	120	50	20	10	60	260Lamps and Lanterns	200	227	50	50	750	1,277Matches, Wooden	851	1,000	300	200	6,000	8,351other sorts	16	 	 	 	 	16Methylated Spirits .. ..	70	5	 	 	 	75Musical Instruments .... .. ..	750	500	250	 	782	2,282Perfumery, Cosmetics, and Toilet Preparations	1,000	800	96	 	 	1,896Perfumed Spirits	750	200	59	 	 	1,009Pictures and Engravings ..	40	7	  1	 	 	47Rockets and Fireworks	 	2	 	 	 	2Starch	100	25	7	 	 	132Blue ..............	100	100	25	25	231	481Toys, Games, and Sports Goods (not including Billiards						and Bagatelle Requisites)........	500	100	100		5	705						Umbrellas	50	200	32		100	382do(LJc
SCHEDULE 3-(Continued).Articles.	Europeans.	Indians.	Goans.	Arabs, Somalis and others.	Natives.	Total net duty.CLASS III. contd. Personal and Household Effects, Unenumerated as Passengers&apos; Baggage.......... Miscellaneous Goods, Manufactured, not elsewhere specified .. .. .. ......	  70 12,000	  3 6,000	  . 2,016	 	1	  73 20,016Total ..  	127,403	80,085 .	13,893	8,753	123,346	353,480CLASS V. Parcel Post .............	22,500	10,000	2,000	1,500	5,028	41,028CLASS I ...... II ......&apos; ,, III ........ V .. .. .. y.	147,112 1,567 127,403 22,500	46,299 1,096 80,085 10,000	28,562 284 13,893 2,000	6,269 103 8,753 1,500	70,113 326 123,346 5,028	298,355 3,376 353,480 41,028GRAND TOTAL . . 	298,582	137,480	44,739	16,625	198,813	696,239	Per cent. 42-88	Per cent. 19-75	Per cent. 6-43	Per cent. 2-39	Per cent. 28-55	: -
                                           Indivisible Services     ..     ..     ..    1,771,180European Services     ..     ..     ..      171,247European  and   Native  (Indivisible)    Services    ..     ......       2,962Asiatic Services......     ..       46,080Non-Native (Indivisible) Services    ..       8,948Native Services........     331,956Reimbursements and Cross Entries  ..     883,716                        Total  &apos;    ..    3,216,089 Vide Schedule 5. ,n     a    6.P.W.D. Water-boring. Vide Schedule 7.              8.  it     it    9.        SCHEDULE 5.Expenditure on Indivisible  Services.Government House Votes    ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      15,992Audit Department Votes (net, after deducting reimbursements)..      14,214Coast Agency (net, after deducting reimbursements)    ..     ..       3,956Conference of East African Governors     ..     ..     ..     ..       1,228Customs Department (net, after deducting reimbursements)    ..      31,354Game Department    ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      10,355Judicial Department  ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      33,087Legal Department -    ..     ..     . .     ..     ..     ..     ..       9,420Military Votes  (including Defence Force)  (net,  after deducting    reimbursements)  ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      93,158Pensions   and  Gratuities  (excluding  European Widows&apos;  and    Orphans&apos; Pensions)     ........     . .     ..     130,390Police Votes (net, after deducting reimbursements)      ..     ..     141,028Printing and Stationery     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      32,475Prisons        ................      46,714Public Debt (vide Note No. 1, page  85) (net, after deducting    reimbursements)  ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      87,214Registrar-General     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..       5,842Rent and  Interest paid to Sultan of Zanzibar     ..     ..     ..      16,000Secretariat and Legislative Council ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      19,024Survey and Registration Department     ..     ..     ..     ..      36,232Trade and Information Office. .     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..       4,837Treasury (net, after deducting reimbursements)   ..     . .     ..     25,336Statistical and Meteorological Services    ..     ..     ..     ..       4,031Native Registration Department   ..    ..     ..     ..     ..       8,961Domestic  Servants&apos;  Registration   . .    ..     ..     . .     ..      1,648Finger Print Bureau  . .     . .     . .     ..     . .     . .     . .       7,535Miscellaneous Services -(pide Statement A attached) net,  after    deducting reimbursements)    ..    ..     ..     . .     ..     74,887Forest Department  (vide Note No. 2, page 87)    ..     . .     ..     34,902Contributions  to Local  Government Authorities  (vide  State-    in ent B attached) ..     ..     ..     ......     -..    101,751         SCHEDULE 4.Classification of Expenditure in 1931.            SUMMARY.
                                                             1,620,064Add-Post Office  and  Telegraphs  (less reimbursements  from      Uganda)       ..............    151,116Total Indivisible Services (less reimbursements)    ..     ..     ..  1,771,180                             Statement A.Miscellaneous Services Expenditure.                                     Maintenance of Landing Grounds ..     ..    ..     ..     ..        726  Subsidy to Imperial Airways     ..     ..    ..     ..     ..      7,500  Commission and Fees to Bombay Agents..    ..     ..     ..      1,381  Commissions of Enquiry and Committees      ..     ..     ..        53S  Contingencies       ..     ..     ..     . .    ..     ..     ..        402  Contribution to African Affairs Report . .    ..     ..     ..         20  Contribution to Naval Entertainment Fund   ..     ..     . .        150  Purchase of Cycle Discs   ..     ..     ..    .....     . .         90  Expenses of Distinguished Visitors      ..    ..     ..     ..        237  Repairs to Duplicating Machines ..     ..    ..     ..     . .          5  Expenses of Film Censorship Board     . .    ..     ..     . .        228  Grant to East Africa and Uganda Natural History Society   ..        700  Grant to Imperial Institute      ..     ..    ..     ..     . .        300  Guarantee in respect of Nanyuki Branch Railway     ..     . .      2,306  Guarantee in respect of Thomson&apos;s Fall Branch Railway -    . .      7,856  Guarantee in respect of Kisumu-Yala Branch Railway..     ..      9,709  Insurance of Specie ..     ..     ..     ..    ..     ..     ..         35  Language Examination Expenses ..     ..    ..     ..     . .        224  Contribution to International Institute of African Languages, etc.       100  Contribution to Inter-Territorial Languages Committee      ..      1,006  Management Expenses of Loans (less reimbursements)..     . .        370  Contribution to Mechanical Transport Committee     ..     . .        500  Burials of Destitute Persons     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..        105  Postages     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..        306  Preservation of Ancient Monuments    ..     ..     ..     . .         48  Refunds of Revenue..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      9,S55  Commission, etc., on Remittances..     ..     ..     ..     ..        581  Rent of Land:  Mbaraki.........     ..     . .        140  Rent of Land:  Mweza Creek    ..     . .     ..     ..     . .        125  Expenses of Salved Goods and Ambergris      ..     ..     . .         64  Payment to Railway in respect of Stand Premia and Rents . .      8,792  Telegrams   ..     ..     ..     ..     . .     ..     ..     - -      1,084  Purchase and Repairs of Typewriters   . .     ..     ..     . .        755  Expenses of Beer Ordinance     .....     ..     ..     ..         31  Expenses  of Traffic Ordinance   ..     ..     ..     ..     ..          3  Expenses of Census ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      2,323  Contribution to Publication of &quot; Birds of Kenya and  Uganda &quot;       375                      SCHEDULE  5-(Conlinued).Administration (vide Note No. 3, page 88) .                        tog  oeAgriculture (vide Note No. 4, page 89)    ..    .&quot;           &quot;     ^education (vide Note No. 5, page 89)                         . -     00,48.Medical (wVfe Note No. 6, page 91)  ..    .&apos;&quot;           &quot;     &quot;     l%-frtPublic Works Department (vide Note No. 7,  page 95)    \\          253^594
                                                   31?Development of Civil Aviation   ..     ..     . .     ..     - -      1,877Redemption of Old Currency     ..     ..     ..     . -     - -          8Safes and Cash Boxes     ............       265Contribution to Rowett Institute ..     ..     . .     ..     - -       762Removal of Nairobi Race Course ..     ..     ..     ..     - -        60Damage to Private Cars............        50Compensation in Bagishu Murder Trial  ..     ..     . -     - -       450Trade Exhibition Antwerp      ..     ..     ..     . -     - -        92Payment to  Coode, Wilson and Vaughan, Engineers  ..     ..       479Depreciation of Post Office Savings Bank Investments             11,874Total Miscellaneous Services (General)      ..    ^74,887                             Statement B.          CONTRIBUTIONS TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES.Nairobi Municipality.                                                  Contributions in lieu of Rates    ..     ..     ..    ..    ..      11,174  Contributions in respect of       Main Roads    ..............       2,980      Public Health Staff............       1,883      Public Health Services      ..     ..     ......       1,215      Traffic Revenue       ......     ......       8,426      Municipal Staff       ............       1,165      Diminishing Grant in respect of Public Health   ..    ..      1,163Mombasa Municipality. -Contributions in lieu of Rates    ..     ..     .  .    ..    ..       9,415  Contributions in respect of :       Main Roads    ....     ..     ..     ..    ..    ..        556      Public Health Staff......     ......       2,279      Public Health Services      ..     ......    ..       1,625      Traffic Revenue       ............       3,520      Municipal Staff       ............        694      Diminishing Grant in respect of Public Health   ..    ..       1,623Consolidated Grant to Nakuru Municipality     &apos;.....    ..       3,000Consolidated Grant to Eldoret Municipality      .  .    ..    ..       3,000District Councils.  Basic Road Grants......     ..     ..    ..    ..      36,412  Township Roads    ..     ..     ..     ..     ..    ..    ..       543  Vehicle Licence Fees       ..     ..     ..     ..    ..    ..       1,230Extraordinary Expenditure.  Hospital Grant to Eldoret Municipality  ..     ..    ..    ..      1,608  Special Grant for Roads to Eldoret Municipality      ..    ..       250  Grant to Nairobi Municipality on account of Road Construction       984  Grants to District Councils under Section 105  (1)  (6)  of Ord.    No. XXI of 1928        ............       7,006Total Expenditure^101,751APPENDIX l-(Continued).SCHEDULE 5-(Continued).
       19,869   7,434   2,442   1,124    500  49,600  39,018  24,527  24,485  *1,590    658 171,247  * The European Widows&apos; and Orphans&apos;  Pensions have been classified as a european service because the revenue  derived from European  officials&apos;contributions to  the Widows&apos;  and Orphans&apos;  Pension Scheme,  credited togeneral revenue, has also been classified in that category.        SCHEDULE 7.Expenditure on Asiatic Services.Rebate on Paraffin used for Agricultural Purposes       . .     ..         34Repatriation   ..     ..     ..     ..     ..                 - -        222Public Debt Charges (vide Note No. 1, page 85)......      4,104Education (vide Note No. 5, page 89)      ..    ......     41,185Medical* (vide Note No. 6, page 91)......     .....        460Public Works Department (vide Note No. 7,  page 95)    ..     ..         75Total Asiatic Services  ..    ..     46,080  * The medical  expenditure  on Asiatics  cannot be shown separately, asAsiatics share native hospitals and dispensaries  and no record exists thatwould render a division of expenditure possible.                            SCHEDULE 8.  .             Expenditure on Non-Native Indivisible Services.Maintenance of Destitute Persons   ..     .,     ..     ..     ..         21Local Government, Lands and Settlement Department  ..     ..      8,927                   Total Non-Native Indivisible Services ..     ..      8,948                            SCHEDULE 6.                   Expenditure on European Services.Public Debt Charges (vide Note No. 1, page 85)Rebate on Paraffin used for Agricultural Purposes.RepatriationMaintenance of Destitute PersonsContributions to Rural LibrariesEducation (vide Note No. 5, page 89)Agricultural (vide Note No. 4, page 89)Medical (vide Note No. 6, page 91)Public Works Department (vide Note No. 7, page 95)European Widows&apos; and Orphans&apos; Pensions  ..Expenses of Widows&apos; and Orphans&apos; Pensions Scheme                           Total European Services
O $ o   6,756     292      41     159   1,957   5,445   3,506  42,846  38,389  77,722 124,642  30,201 331,956             SCHEDULES 5 to 9.           Note No. 1.-Public Debt.(i) LOAN CAPITAL  EXPENDITURE CLASSIFICATION.                               Summary.1. General Indivisible Expenditure2. European services . Asiatic Services4. Arab services. Native Services         Total Public Debt        16,253,371&quot;    470,613     56,795      9,718    109,503. 16,900,000vide details  below.(ii) LOAN ANNUAL CHARGES CLASSIFICATION OF EXPENDITURE.                                         1. General Indivisible Charges2. European Services (a)3. Asiatic Services (6)4. Arab Services (c)  ..5. Native Services (d)  Reimbursed chargesTotal Expenditure, 1931 87,214 (excluding reimbursed          items amounting to           773,552.) 19,869  3,504    600  6,756773,552 891,495  (a) The  European Services are composed of the  items  detailed  below.Interest and sinking fund charges are calculated as follows :       On  Public  Buildings  expenditure totalling  230,613, interest at the    rate of 5* 17 per cent, and sinking fund at 1 per cent, per annum.  The    interest rate is the  average  rate payable on  the 1927, 1928, and 1930    loans, plus charges covering  expenses of issue and discount.      On  Land Bank funds totalling  240,000,  interest at 4-7 per cent, for    six months  of 1931, the interest in this case being  the actual  interest    payable on the 1930 loan, plus expenses of issue and discount.t                            SCHEDULE 9.                    Expenditure on Native Services.Public Debt Charges (vide Note No. 1, below)RepatriationHut and Poll Tax ExemptionsWages of Bankrupt Contractors&apos; LabourForest Department (vide Note No. 2, page 87)Native Affairs DepartmentLabour DepartmentProvincial Administration (vide Note No. 3, page 88)Agriculture (vide Note No. 4, page 89)Education (vide Note No. 5, page 89)Medical (vide Note No. 6, page 91)  . .Public Works Department (vide Note No. 7, page 95)                   Total Native Services
DETAILS OF LOAN CAPITAL EXPENDITURE.                    1. General Indivisible Expenditure.                                                                     1.  Kilindini Harbour Works     ..     ......     ..   1,094,594 2.  General Port Development, Mombasa       ....     .-.   1,200,000 3.  Port Improvements    ....     ..     ..     ..     ..      99,542 4.  Construction of Quays and Jetty     ..     ..     ..     ..     695,339 5.  Interest on Railway and Harbour Works during construction      51,857 6.  Interest on Kilindini Harbour Works and Uasin Gishu Railway    377,955 7.  Construction of Uasin Gishu Railway........   2,000,000 8.  Purchase and reconditioning of Voi-Kahe Branch Railway ..     100,000 9.  Nyeri, Kitale, and Solai Branch Railways   ..     ..     ..   -  801,97110.  Railway Branch Lines  ..    ..     ........     313,00011.  Locomotives and Rolling Stock       ........   1,056,00012.  Railway Main Line Improvements and Equipment ..     ..     346,17313.  Site for New Railway Station, Mombasa    ..     ..     ..      54,99914.  Repayment to H.M. Treasury of Loans for Development   ..   1,103,91215.      ,,      to Revenue of Advances for Loan Expenditure..     600,00016.      ,,      of 1924 Loan raised  for Railway Development ..   3,280,46717.  Expenses of Issue and Discount of Loans raised   ..     ..     942,75318.  Roads, Bridges, and Communications       ..     ..     ..     328,27519.  Water-supplies..............     225,80020.  Loans to Local Authorities    ..     ..     ..     ..     ..     490,84721.  Housing for Government Services  &apos;   ..     ..  -   ..     ..     653,17522.  Maize-drying Installation     ..     ..     ..     ..     . .      10,74323.  Cold Storage............     ..      11,30024.  Customs House, Mombasa    ..     ..     ..     ..     ..      23,627                   SCHEDULES 5 to $-(Continued).  In connection with the Land Bank funds it should be noted that, althoughthe Land Bank Ordinance permits the granting of loans to persons of anyrace, the  240,000 actually raised has been granted to  Europeans (less ad-ministrative expenses) and for the purposes of this classification the whole ofthe charges on the full sum of  240,000 has been shown as a European Service.Natives and others benefit indirectly from  these loan monies by increasedemployment, wages, etc.  The European  recipients of the loans reimburse the  Land Bank  for theinterest and the Government receives from  the Land Bank the full interest charges incurred,  but not the sinking fund charges (which will not be incurred by Government until 1934).  (6) The expenditure on.Asiatic  Services, amounting to  56,795, represents the cost  of schools and a special  extension to  the Mathari  Mental Hospital.The annual interest and  sinking fund charges  have been calculated at 5-17per cent, and 1 per cent., respectively, as in the case of European expenditureon public buildings.  It should be noted that no part of the expenditure on native hospitals hasbeen placed to the Asiatic account, although Asiatics are actually accomodated in the native hospitals.  (c) The Arab expenditure of  9,718 on a school at Mombasa involves annualcharges, as above, of 5-17 per cent, interest and 1 per cent, sinking fund.  (d) The Native expenditure of  109,503 involves similar annual charges of5-17 per cent, and 1 per cent, for  interest and sinking fund,  respectively.
          APPENDIX  l-(Continued)..       SCHEDULES 5 to $-(Continued).1. General Indivisible Expenditure (Continued).25  Offices  at Kwale,  Ngong,  Rumuruti,  Machakos,  Eldoret,      j       Nanyuki, Maseno, Narok, Kisumu.......  -;      io onnoe  Nairobi Central Offices ( 154,882 less  61,682 not yet raised)     ,?3.20027.  Nairobi Law Courts    ............        7i,28.  K.A.R. (Military) Lines............      To-fw29.  MedicalStore    ......     .......if&apos;n*o30.  P.W.D. Buildings at Nakuru and Eldoret......      I AH31.  Medical Research Laboratory.........-32.  Unallocated Funds     ..            ......              3MTotal    ..     &quot;..     .   16,253,371                        2. European Services.                -       1.  Land Bank      ..............     240,0002.  European Hospital, Kisumu   . .     ..     ..     ..      ..       6,6123.  Nairobi Schools..............      38,2414.  Kabete School..............      66,4335.  Nakuru School.......     ..     ..     ..      ..      44,7036.  Eldoret School   ....    ..     ......      ..      45,1347.  Kitale School    ..............      29,490                                   Total     ......     470,613                          3. Asiatic Services.                       1. Mathari Mental Hospital     ...     ..     ....     ...       3,3502. Nairobi School   ..     ..    ..     ..     ......      53,445                                   Total.......      56,795                           4. Arab Services.1.  Arab School, Mombasa............      ^9&apos;718                          5.  Native Services.                        1.  Native Hospitals       ............      9fi&apos;4nn2.  African Schools, Kabete       ..     -.......      ^o,wuTotal    ....... 109,503  * Asiatics are also accommodated in native hospitals but it is not possibleto divide the expenditure on any equitable basis.                         Note No. 2. Forestry.  1. Under Native Services the actual expenditure in the Native Reservesis included.  2. The rest of the departments expenditure is in the Crown forests outsidethe Native Reserves.  The maintenance of the forests. benefits all com-munities by the amelioration of the climate, the conservation and regularizationof water-supplies, the prevention of erosion, and the guarantee of a sustainedsupply of all kinds of forest produce.
                      Note No. 3. Administration.  The classification  of Administrative Expenditure has been made on thefollowing basis :  General Staff. This sub-head includes the salaries, travelling expenses,and  passages  of  all Administrative Officers,  whether stationed within theNative Reserves  or in other parts.  It also includes the salaries of  Cashiersand  Clerks in District Offices,  the salaries, allowances, and expenses of theFrontier Agent, Maji, H.M. Consul for  Southern Abyssinia, the Liwali for theCoast, and miscellaneous items of expenditure that cannot be divided on anyaccurate basis.  The whole of this  expenditure  (with the. exception of the salaries of three Labour Officers) has been classified as &quot; Indivisible GeneralExpenditure.&quot;  Native  Affairs Department  Headquarters. This section of  the NativeAffairs Department has been classified as a &quot; Native Service.&quot;  It is concernedwholly with native affairs and interests.  Labour Section. The cost of this  section, together with the Salaries of thethree Labour Officers, is shown as a  &quot;  Native Service.&quot;  The Labour Officerscome into direct contact with native labourers and their whole time is devotedto the improvement of labour conditions and the protection of the interests oflabourers.  Local Government,  Lands and Settlement. The whole of this section hasbeen classified as a &quot; Non-Native Service.&quot;  Provincial  Administration. The  salaries of  Chiefs and Headmen andTribal Police have been classified as a &quot;  Native  Service.&quot;   The  expenditure under &quot; Rewards and Rations to Natives  &quot; and &quot; Expenses of Tribal Police &quot;has also been  shown as a &quot; Native Service.&quot;  All other items, which cannotbe classified accurately, have followed the classification of &quot; General Staff&quot;expenditure under &quot; Indivisible General Services.&quot;  The item &quot; Masai Agents &quot; under  the Masai Province has also been shownas a &quot; Native  Service.&quot;  The expenditure on reconditioning  of  the  Kamasia Reserve  in  the RiftValley Province has been classified as  a &quot; Native Service.&quot;  The salaries of Liwalis, Kathirs, Mudirs, and Tembo Supervisors, as wellas allowances  to ex-slaves in the Coast Province, are included as a &quot; NativeService.&quot;                   SCHEDULES  5 to 9-(Continued).  3. About 50 per cent, of the Crown forests actually border Native Reservesbut a far larger number of rivers flow from these forests than from the Crownforests bordering  non-native  lands.   It  might be said therefore  that thepreservation  of the forests benefits the natives to an even greater extent than other communities.  There are, of course,.other forms of benefit such asthe continuity of the supply of forest produce (which perhaps is more important to the European than to the native) and  the permanence of a large field forremunerative employment,  but it is not considered practicable to apportionthe benefits of forest conservation between the different communities, andthe main expenditure of the department is therefore shown under &quot; IndivisibleGeneral Services.&quot;
                        Note No. 4. Agriculture.  The expenditure upon native services is based upon the actual known costof the staff working in the native areas, plus the actual expenditure upon other services solely devoted to natives.        -  In  regard to &quot; Indivisible &quot; expenditure in which differentiation  cannotbe made, the position is as follows :  Headquarters Administrative  Expenditure. This expenditure cannot  be divided  on any accurate basis.  Locust Destruction ( 18,776). The expenditure involved was in the general interests of the community as a whole and was incurred in the Native Reservesas well as in the settled areas and other districts.  Scott  Agricultural Laboratories  ( 11,354)  and  Plant  Breeding  Services( 3,107). These services are chiefly and directly related to crop improvement and protection, also soil conditions throughout the Colony.   Veterinary Research ( 28,500). This service has general application.  Board of Agriculture  ( 970).- The  constitution and organization of theBoard now being appointed embraces both native and non-native agriculture.  Grading and Inspection, Grain  Conditioning and Cool Stores  [includingExtension to Plant) ( 8,786). These services, which are revenue-earning andfor which the  grower indirectly pays,  apply to both native and non-nativegrown products.  European Services. In view  of the  impossibility of allocating this itembetween European and Asiatic Services, the Director of Agriculture includedit in  Non-Native  Indivisible Services, but owing to  the small number ofAsiatic  cultivators and the small benefit that could therefore be derived  by-Asiatics, the Commissioner considers it would, on the whole, be fairest totransfer the Non-Native Agricultural Service into the schedule of expenditureon European Services.                        Note No. 5. Education.                                  . I.  1. The figures submitted are the tables of expenditure  on the particular services.  Expenditure  is accounted for separately under each division ofthe estimates.  These divisions are :             i. Administration.           ii. European Tuition.          iii. European Boarding.          iv. Indian and Goan.           v. Arab and African.          vi. Extraordinary.  2. All expenditure is  posted in  the departmental ledger first to the voteas a whole, and secondly to the individual service.   The totals of the items of expenditure as posted to the individual services are the figures submitted in the return.                   SCHEDULES 5 to $-[Continued).  Kabete  Reformatory. The whole  of  the expenditure  on  the KabeteReformatory has been shown as a &quot; Native Service.&quot;  It is considered thatthe Reformatory should properly be regarded as a school of instruction, not as a prison.
                                   II.REVENUE AND EXPENDITURE  ON  EUROPEAN  AND  INDIAN  EDUCATIONAL                            SERVICES, 1931.                                Revenue.	European.	Indian.	 	 Education Tax	11,399	14,481Wines and Spirits Consumption Tax*	21,396	5,961Tuition fees .. .. ..	4,112	5,199Boarding fees	12,436	1,000Total ..	 49,343	26,641Expenditure.(a) chargeable to Education vote.	 	 Recurrent	49,191	34,100Extraordinary	411	246Total ..	 49,602	34,346(b) not chargeable to Education vote.	 	 Housing	2,961	2,957Pensions!	4,041	2,166Loan charges	10,421	2,481Total ..	 17,423	7,604  *Consumption tax was merged in general import duty on 16th June, 1931.The figure given is the sum of the following amounts :       (a) Consumption tax collected up to  16th June, 1931.      (b) Amount of  import duty collected after 16th June,  1931, which    would have been  collected in consumption tax if that  tax had remained    in force.  f Estimated at 15 per cent, in case of Europeans and at 10 per cent, incase of Indians.                   SCHEDULES 5 to 9-(Continued).  3. Non-recurrent expenditure is voted in the estimates for Extraordinaryexpenditure as European, Indian, or African,  as the case may be, and thefigures submitted show the expenditure charged to the services.  4. Indivisible expenditure is expenditure on Administration and nothing else.  5. The total expenditure  ( 6,595) recorded  against the following schoolshas been classified as an Asiatic service, viz. :               Arab School, Mombasa.              Coast Secondary School, Shimo-la-tewa.              Ali bin Salim School, Malindi.  It is understood  that the estimate of the cost of Arab education is onthe generous side as it is not possible  accurately to divide the cost betweenArabs and Africans attending these schools.
91351Note  No. 6. Medical.  1.  Under the heading  &quot; Nature of the  Service &quot; certain abbreviationshave been  used to indicate services rendered, namely :   2.  Under the heading &quot; Native Services &quot;  are included :       (a) The actual costings of all native hospitals  with their European,    Asiatic, and Native staffs.      (6) Grants to Missions for maintenance of hospital beds for Africans.      (c) Grants-in-Aid to native maternity centres.      (d) Costings of that proportion  of work performed at District Health    Offices on account of native services.      (e) All expenditure on African child-welfare work.      (f) Capital grants to Missions for the erection of buildings in connexion    with the Health Scheme for the hospitalization of the native services.      (g) Cost of medical stores for native services.      (h) Expenditure on training  of  Africans.  3.  It has been found impossible, in the absence of exact data, to give anyfigure for expenditure on &quot; Asiatic Services &quot; apart from definite expenditureconnected  with dental services and grants to private hospitals  in respectof Indian maternity and child-welfare.  Other Asiatic expenditure is included under &quot; Native Services &quot;  as Asiatics are treated at  native hospitals both as in- and  out-patients ;  separate costings do not exist.   It is understood,however, that  Asiatic services represent a small proportion of the  total amount included in &quot; Native Services &quot;.  4.  Under the heading &quot; Indivisible General Services &quot; have been included :       (a) Head Office (including Administration charges).      (b) Laboratory.      (c) School Medical Service.      (d) Charges in  connexion with passages, leave salaries,  etc., and    fees and expenses of Medical Officers attending courses of instruction    in England.      (e) Mathari Mental Hospital.      (f) Contributions to  the  Uganda Government in  connexion  with    trypanosomiasis  research, and contributions to the  Sanitary Station,    Zanzibar.      (g) Miscellaneous telegrams, telephones,  etc.  5.  The cost of  medical treatment and nursing expenses of  government officials treated in private hospitals or by private practitioners is included under the  heading  &quot; European Services.&quot;  This  heading also includes  a contribution  to the Seamen&apos;s Hospital and capital contributions  to certainhospitals in respect of maternity and child-welfare.  (11310)                                                               DN.H.E.H.M.O.N.S.S.I.S.A.S.Native Hospital.European Hospital.Medical Officer.European Nursing Sister.Sanitary Inspector.Sub-Assistant Surgeon.SCHEDULES 5 to 9 (Continued.)
Classification of 1931 Expenditure, Medical Department.Nature of the Service.			Native Services.	European Services.	Asiatic Services.	Indivisible General.Ukamba Province 	Pop.		 	 	 	 Teita and Voi Kitui..... Machakos ..	44,100 140,807 222,285	N.H., M.O., N.S. N.H., M.O., S.A.S. .. N.H., M.O., N.S., S.A.S.	3,506 2,351 5,853	 	 	-		Total	11,710	 	 	 Coast Province 	Pop.											Lamu Tana River .. Digo Malindi Kilifi. Mombasa	16,462 \ 13,420/ 50,881 28,146\ 69,298/ 34,591	N.H., S.A.S..... M.O., S.I..... N.H., M.O., S.A.S. .. E.H., N.H., M.O., N.S., Port Health Officer..	1,144 3,850 2,863 14,605	5,092	-	-		Total	22,462	5,092	 	 Nzoia Province 	Pop.											Nandi Elgeyo-Marakwet . Uasin-Gishu Trans-Nzoia	41,491 34,768 20,661 24,140	N.H. Compounder N.H. Compounder N.H., N.S., S.A.S., S.I. N.H., M.O., S.I.	518 381 4,058 2,099	1,220 715	- -			Total	7,056	1,935	 	-SCHEDULES 5 to $-(Continued).
Nyanza Province  C.K. and Kisumu .. S. Kavi rondo N. Kavirondo S. Lumbwa	Pop. 343,205 312,226 341,232 92,525	.N.H., E.H., M.O., N.S., S.I., S.A.S..... N.H., M.O., N.S., S.I., S A S N.H., M.O., N.s!, S.I... N.H., M.O., N.S.	14,909 6,578\ 7,002/ 2,347	2,767 258 19	-	-Kikuyu Province &apos; North Nyeri South Nyeri.. ;. Meru ..... Fort Hall..... Kiambu Nairobi and Thika		Total	30,836	3,044		-	Pop. 7,775 202,893 160,721 187,278 93,060 67,710	N.H., SAiS., S.I. N.H., M.O., N.S. N.H., M.O., S.A.S. .. N.H., M.O., S.A.S. .. N.H., M.O., N.S. N.H., E.H., M.O., N.S., S.A.S., Asylum	3,540 3,121 2,675 3,259 6,137 22,351	288 23 54 13 10,291	-	-Rift Valley Province 		Total	41,083	10,669		-	Pop.					Baringo Nakuru .....	43,567 23,346	N.H., M.O..... N.H., D.S., M.O., N.S.	1,374 3,651	1,377	 			Total	5,025	1,377		-Turkana Province  West Suk..... North and South Turkana	Pop. 24,805 \ 53,511/	N.H., M.O., S.A.S. ..	2,696	 		-	Total carried forward		120,868	22,117		
                    APPENDIX l-(Continued).                SCHEDULES 5 to $-(Continued).Classification of  1931  Expenditure, Medical  Department (Continued).Nature of the Service.	Native Services.	European Services.	Asiatic Services.	Indivisible General.Total brought forward...... Masai Province  Pop. Narok0 &quot; J&quot; 50,402 N&apos;H&quot; M 0&quot; ComPoun(ler	  120,808 1,299	  22,117	 	 Naivasha Province  Pop. Naivasha .. .. ..\ nq aon Native dresser and Laikipia ......J &apos; dispensary-	40	-		- -.Pop. Northern Frontier Province .. 80,000 , 2 N.H., M.O., S.A.S. ..	2,435		_	Expenditure Miscellaneous items and General	/---- , -	2,410	460	73,268Grand Total - .. .. .. ..  	124,642	24,527	460	73,268^CD4-  TotalExpenditure 222,897
                       APPENDIX 1 (Continued).                  SCHEDULES 5  to $-(Continued).                      Note No.  7.-Public Works. In view of the difficulty of classification, the following procedure has been.adopted :      (a) All trunk roads have been treated as &quot; Indivisible General Services.&quot;      (b) Roads primarily serving  European areas have been  treated as   &quot; European Services.&quot;      (c) Roads primarily serving Native areas have been treated as &quot; Native   Services.&quot;      (d) Maintenance of all Government  buildings and water-supplies have   been classified as &quot; Indivisible General Services.&quot;      (e) All expenditure  on  work  in townships,  including water-supplies.   drains, roads, etc., are included in the &quot; Indivisible  General Services &quot;   column.(11310)U 3
   APPENDIX l-(ConHnued).SCHEDULES 5 to $-(Continued).Service.	Native Services.	European Services.	Asiatic Services.	Indivisible European and Native Services.	Indivisible Services.Roads, Extraordinary	  496	  253	 	 	  1,200Recurrent	25,547	10,908	 		79;009Buildings, Recurrent	 	 	 	_	26,484,, Extraordinary	458	2,766	75	__&apos;	17,491Miscellaneous Town Plot Roads and Drains	_	_	_	;_	1,605Furniture, Recurrent ......	 	. _	_	__	1,850,, Extraordinary	623	485	 	_	2,849Workshops	 	 	: 		235Preliminary Invoice N.W.	-	 	 	- -	184Loss and Depreciation	 	 	 	--	588Rents and House Allowances		 	 		65,826Tools and Plant	783	877	_	._	3,283Water-supplies and Drainage	 	 	 	._	5,786Purchase of Mechanical Plant	 	 	_		295Water-supplies		 	 	_	28,616Transport	 	 	 	-	4,589Hydrographic Survey ......	 	-	 	-	5,302Water-boring..	1,555	9,196	 	2,962	2,468Technical Trainings, Africans	&apos; 739	 	 	,_	133Timber Seasoning	 	 	 	._	1,867Asian and African Housing	 	 		_ -	352Overheads on services for other departments	 	 	 	; 	3,582Totals .. .. ..  	30,201	24,485	75	2,962	253,594Total Expenditure,    311,317.
APPENDIX 1 (Continued).SCHEDULE  10.Racial Balance Sheet of Revenue and Expenditure  in 1931.Direct Taxation.    Europeans    Asiatics    Natives     .....Indirect Taxation.    Europeans    Asiatics     ..    Natives    IndivisibleOther Taxation.    Europeans    Asiatics    Natives     .....    IndivisibleOther Revenue.    Europeans    Asiatics    Natives     ..     ..    Indivisible:         Posts and Telegraphs        Other Heads  ..REVENUE.      42,596 60,535530,877334,477209,551199,181  2,345109,113 55,704 11,446  1,936179,595 59,868 49,596168,132168,262634,008745,554178,199625,453Total Revenue     ..     ..       2,183,214Reimbursements and Cross-entries   883,716Deficit 3,066,930   149,159 3,216,089                     EXPENDITURE.                                            European Services      ..      .....European and Native Services (Indivisible)Asiatic ServicesNon-Native Services (Indivisible)Native ServicesIndivisible Services:     Posts and Telegraphs       ..     ..   151,116    Other Votes........ 1,620,064    171,247  2,962 46,080  8,948331,9561,771,180CDTotal Expenditure..     ..        2,332,373Reimbursements and Cross-entries   883,716 3,216,089
Service.Roads, Extraordinary   ,,   Recurrent......Buildings, Recurrent    ,,     ExtraordinaryMiscellaneous Town Plot Roads and DrainsFurniture, Recurrent    ,,     ExtraordinaryWorkshopsPreliminary Invoice N.W.Loss and DepreciationRents and House AllowancesTools and PlantWater-supplies and DrainagePurchase of Mechanical PlantWater-suppliesTransportHydrographic SurveyWater-boring..Technical Trainings, AfricansTimber Seasoning   ..Asian and African HousingOverheads on services for other departmentsTotals NativeServices.      49625,547   458   6237831,555 739European Services.30,201 AsiaticServices.Indivisible european and Native Services.    25310,908 2,7664858779,19624,48575752,9622,962Indivisible Services.    1,20079;00926,48417,491 1,605 1,850 2,849   235   184   58865,826 3,283 5,786   29528,616 4,589 5,302 2,468   133 1,867   352 3,582253,594Total Expenditure,     311,317.SCHEDULES 5 to 9-(Continued).
APPENDIX 1 (Continued).                    SCHEDULE  10.Racial Balance Sheet of Revenue and Expenditure  in 1931.REVENUE.Direct  Taxation.    Europeans    Asiatics    Natives Indirect Taxation.    Europeans    Asiatics     .....    Natives    Indivisible Other Taxation.    Europeans    Asiatics    Natives    Indivisible Other Revenue.    Europeans.....    Asiatics    Natives     ..      ..    Indivisible:          Posts and Telegraphs         Other Heads   ..    I 42,596 60,535530,877334,477209,551199,181  2,345109,113 55,704 11,446  1,936179,595 59,868 49,596168,132168,262Total RevenueReimbursements and Cross-entriesDeficit634,008745,554178,199   625,453 2,183,214   883,716 3,066,930   149,159 3,216,089                     EXPENDITURE.                                            European ServicesEuropean and Native Services (Indivisible)Asiatic ServicesNon-Native Services (Indivisible)Native ServicesIndivisible Services     Posts and Telegraphs      ..     ..   151,116    Other  Votes........  1,620,064    171,247  2,962 46,080  8,948331,9561,771,180CDTotal Expenditure..Reimbursements and Cross-entries2,332,373  883,716 3,216,089
Total Reimbursements and Cross-entries 883,716                          SCHEDULE  11.    Statement oi Reimbursements and Cross-entries appearing on both                        sides oi 1931 Acconnts.                                                                  Share  of  Customs Department  expenditure  recovered from   Uganda Government    ..    ..     . .    ..     ..     ..     16,084Share  of  Coast  Agency  expenditure recovered   from Uganda   and Tanganyika Governments        ..    ..     ..     ..      2,078Share of Treasury and Audit services recovered  from  Uganda   Government and Currency Board, London         ..     ..      6,255Share of Military expenditure recovered  from Sudan Govern-   ment      ..    ..    ..    ..     ..    ..     ..     ..      6,130Police expenditure recovered from Railway and  Port  Adminis-   tration     ................      8,950Share of  Postal and  Telegraph expenditure recovered from   Uganda Government    ..    ..     ..    ..     ..     ..     38,166Public Debt charges recovered  from Railways  and Harbours   Administration and from Local  Government  Authorities   773,552Share of Loan Management  expenses recovered  from  Railway   and Harbour Administration   ..     ..    ..     ..     ..      1,578Colonial Development Fund receipts and expenditure  ..     .. -    30,923
                            APPENDIX 2.    Note by Mr. A. Walter on Contributions to Revenue in Kenya by            the Non-Native and Native Communities  in 1931.     (Comparable with Appendix No. 26 to the Report of the Joint            Select Committee on Closer Union in East Africa.)  1. The Commissioner of Customs  has submitted a statement showingthe estimated proportionate contribution of the  European,  Asiatic,  andNative Communities to the Customs Revenue for 1931.  The resulting  values  are : 	 	shs.	cents.	17	15	0Asiatics	......3	10	0Natives ..		1	35  2. In considering these figures it must be understood that there are no direct means by which the contributions can be measured. The proportioningsare,  however,  effected on a large number of articles by officers possessinga wide knowledge of local conditions.   It is very improbable that errorswill all tend in the same direction, and it may be expected, with a certaindegree of confidence, that errors in excess or defect will compensate in thefinal average.  3. The results secured for the year 1926 have already been incorporated in Memoir No. 2 issued in Nairobi by this department.  The text of thisMemoir was published in Appendix 26 to the Report of the Joint SelectCommittee on Closer Union in East Africa, with the exception of the  con-cluding paragraphs.   These conclusions are now appended to this Note forthe purposes of reference.  The  values of Customs dues derived for that year per head of each com-munity, were:                                                         shs.  cents.       Europeans     ..........     30   12    0       Asiatics  ..     ..     . .     ..     ..     . .      4   15    0       Natives............           1   26  The  figures of total taxation given in the Memoir under reference were :-                                                          shs. cents.       Europeans     ..     . .     ..     ..     . .     41     6    0       Asiatics  :.     ..     . .     ......     10    3    0       Natives  ..     ..     . .     ..     ..     . .           6   04  4. The methods adopted in each year in deriving both Direct and indirect taxation Revenue are entirely similar, and the proportions are, in conse-quence,  comparable.  In the conclusion to Memoir No.  2, which, as stated in the previous para-graph, was  not included in the statements forwarded to the Joint SelectCommittee,  the consistency of the  Customs  figures for  Europeans  andAsiatics was examined and a value of total per capita expenditure on importedarticles derived, based on the per capita contribution to Customs Revenue.The value deduced was  136 per head.
               CONTRIBUTIONS TO CUSTOMS REVENUE.                                Kenya.      Uganda.   Tanganyika.                                     s.  c.        s.  c.        s.  c.      Non-Natives   ..     ..   10   5  0    10  0  0   .  16  1   0      Natives......       1 20        2 30         1  10  8. The reason for a high per capita contribution to Customs  Revenue inthe East  African territories must be sought  in the peculiar composition of the population in these undeveloped  native countries,  especially thosecountries unsuited to extensive European settlement.  The lower and middlestrata of European society are almost entirely missing in such communities,and the age frequency  of the population becomes bunched up about themiddle ages between 25 and 50 years.  In other words, the frequency curveof ages bears all the characteristic features belonging  to an  immigrantpopulation.  9. The more undeveloped the country and the more unsuited to Europeansettlement,  the greater the preponderance of highly-remunerated officials and managers, and the smaller the number of persons in the lower Europeanranks and lower  ages.  As the country develops, especially if  its climate conditions are suitable for European  settlement, families  are created, theage frequency curve is modified by the inclusion of young people, a demandarises for the employment of less-highly-paid employees  of  the  artisan andclerical classes, the per capita standard of living is lowered, and the demandfor  imported articles decreases. Local industries develop, wherever possible,in order to supply the demands of the increased numbers  in the lower strataof society, and this still further reduces the demand for imported goods.  10.  In Kenya,  a country in which European settlement  has  become es-tablished and in which European families have always been able to accompanyboth settlers and officials, the age distribution has not been markedly affectedsince 1911, the proportion in each ten-year group having remained practicallyconstant.  The ratio between the numbers working as employer, employee.  The percentage change of contribution  to Customs Revenue between1926  and 1931 is as follows:        European      ..      . .     ....    42 per cent, decrease.       Asiatic  ..     ..     ..     . .     ..    27 per cent, decrease       Native  ..     ..     . .     ..     ..    7 per cent, increase.  5. In  the  Memoir No. 2 under reference, it  was  pointed  out  that theproportion derived for the Europeans in 1926 was undoubtedly high, butthat the special conditions obtaining in the East African territories madea high standard of living a characteristic feature  of  the  conditions underwhich colonization had taken place up to that time.  6. Comparisons  with  similar results secured quite independently  fromTanganyika,  as well as an analysis of Uganda conditions, conducted on thesame lines as that for Kenya, all pointed to the same conclusion a highconsumption of imported goods.  7. For purposes of reference, the results for 1926 derived from the three territories,  are shown below.  Separate values for  Europeans and Asiaticsare not available for Tanganyika.
NATURE  OF EMPLOYMENT OF THE EUROPEAN  POPULATION.				Own Account.Census year.	Dependants.	Employers.	Employees.	1926	6,123	1,036	4,091	1,2791931	8,288	768	6,267	1,489Percentage increase or decrease in 1931 on 1926.					-4-35	-26	-t-53	4-16  12. The  &quot; dependants &quot; and  &quot; employees &quot;  jointly have increased 43 percent., and the &quot; employers &quot; and &quot; own account &quot; have decreased 3 per cent.This alteration in  the  occupational  composition  of the population must inevitably lower the per capita income and, in consequence, the per capitademand for imported goods a change which is a natural consequence of thepermanent colonization of the country.  13. Other changes in the composition of the population have also to betaken into consideration. From the 1926 and 1931 Census returns it appearsthat the male age-group 20 to 55 has only increased 29 per cent., whereas, theother ages have increased 36 per cent.   The total female population increased40 per cent, and the total male population 30 per cent.  A further change which may have modified the demand for imported goods is to be found inthe increase among persons born in Kenya in relation to those born out of kenya.  The former increased by 41 per cent.,  while the latter only shows anincrease of 33 percent.  Tables illustrating these changes will be published inthe report on the 1931 census.  14. Super-imposed on these perfectly normal changes in the composition of the population, the  period 1928 to 1931 has had to suffer a very seriousdecrease in the purchasing power of all non-native communities as a result ofthe world economic depression.   A reference to the measures of the changesin economic,factors, which are revealed by the Bank statistics, as well as theown account,  and no occupation have, however, been seriously modified,especially since 1926, and it appears evident that the rapid increase in  thepopulation by migration during this period affected principally the  lower-salaried class who entered the Colony in search of employment as the demandfor this class increased very rapidly.  So much so, in fact, that it is now possibleto staff  practically all the lower ranks from locally-recruited young men  andwomen.   11. The decrease in the contribution to Customs Revenue since 1926, whichthe 1931 values reveal, is partly explained by this change in the composition of the population, the extent of which change is indicated in the accompanyingtable : 
INDEX NUMBERS  OF THE PRICE OF KENYA PRODUCE,                   1926 TO 1931.Year.	On local market.		On export market.*			Grocery Group.	Coffee.	Sisal.		Maize.			1st Grade.	2nd Grade.	1926 1927 1928 1929 1930 1931	1,049 1,024 1,043 986 899 785	1,052 1,000 973 970 703 642	1,000 1,089 758 428	1,000 1,081 752 415	1,000 1,015 696 500* On 1928 as base.  15. As the Customs duties are in part ad valorem duties, the marked fallin the price level of imported  goods  is naturally reflected in the customs revenue.  The extent of the fall in price level of imported articles for Customspurposes should be measured by the fall in price in the exporting country,rather than the fall in price as shown in  the Nairobi returns. The wholesale-price levels, according to the Bulletin of the League of Nations, decreased inthe United Kingdom 31 per cent, between 1924 and 1931.  16. Although the 1931 conditions are decidedly abnormal, in so far as theyare the result of the world economic depression, it is unlikely that the per capita contribution  will ever return to the 1926 value, as the change in the composition of the population is a permanent one.  Moreover, as any popula-tion increases from very small numbers, the per capita results may be expectedto decrease, although the global values of each community may, and probablywill, increase.  17. The global contributions to  Taxation Revenue in Kenya are shown below for 1926 and 1931, distinguishing Customs from all other  Taxation,and showing the total Taxation Revenue as adopted in 1926 : CUSTOMS REVENUE (to  nearest  100).Year.	Europeans.	Asiatics.	Natives.	Total.1926 ...... 1931......	  383,400 298,600	  195,400 198,800	  158,500 198,800	  737,300 696,200Increase or decrease in 1931 over 1926 ..	-84,800	+3.400	-1-40,300	-41,100	OTHER	TAXATION.		1926 ...... 1931......	172,700 187,600	95,000 126,900	611,300 542,700	879,000 857,200Increase or decrease in 1931 over 1926	-f 14,900	-f-31,900	-68,600	-21,800COMBINED CUSTOMS		AND OTHER	TAXATION.	1926 ...... 1931......	556,100 486,200	290,400 325,700	769,800 741,500	1,616,300 1,553,400Increase or decrease in 1931 over 1926 . .	-69,900	+35.300	-28,300	-62,900price-level values of local produce in Kenya, will indicate how serious thisdecrease has been.  The price-level index numbers are summarised in thefollowing table : 
  IS. The 1926 global figures of Customs taxation, for all communities,  arethose derived by multiplying the adopted per capita values for 1926 by  thepopulation of the Census year 1926, to which the figures refer.  This shouldbe read in conjunction with paragraphs  20-27, page 186, of Appendix 26,and  Schedule VI (5), page 211, of Appendix 26, of the Report of the JointCommittee,  and the figures contained in Schedule II, page 191, of the sameAppendix.  19. In regard to the total annual expenditure per European, which the per capita contribution implies, the conclusions of Memoir No. 2 appended to this note, should be considered. There is further reason to believe that the amountsspent in Kenya by wealthy visitors are larger than was anticipated in thatMemoir, and that this fact will explain in part, the conclusion that &quot; even after taking these factors into consideration the value of the European con-tribution still appears high.&quot;  20. In the Treasury Statement of Revenue and Expenditure the followingclassification has been adopted for Direct and Indirect Taxation Revenue :   For^the purpose of establishing comparison with the 1926 figures supplied to the Joint Select Committee, the following items of Revenue have been included in Taxation Revenue : Motor traffic licences.Road transport licences.Game licences.Native registration.Explosives and gun licences.Liquor licences.Miscellaneous licences.Coffee licences.Registration of documents.Stamp duties.Cattle traders&apos; licences.Traders&apos; licences.Registrar-General&apos;s office fees.Registration of companies.Registration of inventions.Conveyancing fees.Market and cattle pound fees.Miscellaneous.Fees for licences to exhibit films.  21. In view of.the classification adopted in the Treasury Statement, thetotal contributions are here shown under four heads for 1931 :       Direct Taxation as adopted by the Treasury.      Indirect Taxation distinguishing Customs.      Other Taxation.      Other Revenue.Direct.Indirect.Native hut and poll tax.Non-native poll tax.European education tax.Estate duty.Customs duties.Petrol consumption tax.Wines and spirits consumption tax.Beer excise.
	European.	A sialic.	Native.	Total.	 	 	 	 1.	Direct Taxation . . 42,596	60,535	530,877	634,0082.	Total Indirect Taxation&quot;1 334,477	209,551	199,181	743,2093.	Other Taxation .. 109,113	55,704	11,446	176,2634.	Other Revenue .. 179,595	59,868	49,596	289,059	 665,781	 385,658	 791,100	 1,842,539	Unallocated Posts and Telegraphs			168,132	Unallocated Miscellaneous			172,543	Reimbursements			883,716	Total Revenue			 3,066,930  22. The total Taxation Revenue, as distinguished from other MiscellaneousRevenue for 1931, is :      Europeans.       Asiatics.        Natives.          Total.       4S6.186         325,790         741,504         1,553,480or under the two main racial classifications :                         Non-Native    ............811,976      Native         ............    741,504  The population totals on which the 1931 yields depend are:       European    ..    ..      ........       16,812      Asiatic       ..    ..      ..     ..     ..     ..      58,133      Native       ............    2,950,000Total Population ..     . .     ..     3,024,945  23. The per capita contribution  to  Taxation Revenue, as given in the returns for 1926, and incorporated  in Memoir No. 2  (a copy of which was submitted to the Joint Select Committee), is compared with the 1931 figures as follows:                               1926.      1931.      1926.     1931.                               Shs.       Shs.           s-        s-       European  ..     ..     823.60     578.38    4 1  4    2S  IS       Asiatic     ..     ..     188.98     112.08     9  9     5  12                                                   Shs.      Shs.       Native     ..     ..       5.75       5.03     5.75      5.03  The decrease of  13 is  entirely in the Customs Revenue.  The  causes ofthe diminished  yield from this source have been explained in  previousparagraphs.                                        A. WALTER.                                              Statistician,                                  Conference of East African Governors.                           European.   Asiatic.     Native.      Total.                                                                   *Customs Taxation     ..     298,582     19S.844     198,813     696,239 Other Indirect Taxation      35,895      10,707        368      46,970 334,477    209,551     199,181    743,209  The final values of Revenue under these heads from all sources for the year1931 are as follows :-
 CONCLUSION  TO MEMOIR No. 2,  THE TEXT OF WHICH  WAS PUBLISHED  AS APPENDIX 26 TO THE REPORT OF THE JOINT SELECT COMMITTEE ON CLOSER                        UNION IN EAST AFRICA.   An examination of the foregoing analysis, leading up  to the final adopted values of Taxation Revenue per head for the three main community classifi- cations, suggests the questions : (1) Are these results consistent ?  (2) Do they represent a correct perspective of the relative communal contributions to Revenue ?   The further  questions  as to &quot; whether the distribution of the burden of taxation on each community is a just one &quot;  and &quot; whether the incidence  on the individuals forming  the different  social strata of  each community is equitable,&quot; although they are certainly problems of grave importance to the economic life of the Colony, are not strictly relevant to the subject matter ofthis Memoir.  The direct  taxation values  cannot  be doubted.   It  remains in  con-sequence to test the  Customs figures for consistency and it is proposed  toexamine them for the European  community.   If  they  can be justified  inthis case,  the remaining two values cannot  be seriously  modified.  Theonly element of doubt  which  can  exist  is  that  the  European  figure is too high in relation to the  other two.  The mean of  the three years  for theEuropean is :-  This value represents an expenditure of  153 per head on dutiable articlesor services exclusive of Customs Dues or Transport Charges.  The Customsdues amount to 20 per cent, on the average and transport to about 10 per cent.This increases the expenditure in round figures to  200 per head.  From the tables  of proportions it can be estimated that  about 15 per cent,  of  theRevenue goes to make  up the industrial dutiable articles and others which do not enterinto the direct personal expenditure of the community, thus leavingabout  170 per head on the average to be spent in this manner.  At first sight,this certainly appears to be a high figure.  Examining the items which composeit, however, reveals the fact that they comprise charges which, although they appear as -per capita charges, are in reality community  charges.  Some ofthese may be enumerated as follows :       (a) Visitors spend considerable sums on dutiable articles and on services    which require dutiable articles.      (6) They do not appear in the population returns.      (c) Clubs and hotels are large consumers of dutiable articles.  Twenty per  cent,  may safely  be deducted  from  the above value forsuch expenditure, leaving about  136 as personal expenditure on dutiablearticles and services&apos;per head.  In addition to these  community charges, there are  very considerablecharges for motor transport, and the number of cars for individual use isunusually high.  Costs for petrol, car purchase, parts, etc., constitute one ofthe heaviest charges on the personal budget.or Shs. 612.
  Several typical family groups have been asked to split up their expenditure between local services and dutiable services.  The imported items which goto make up the latter are more considerable than would be supposed at first sight.           Transport (car purchase or depreciation, spares, petrol, oil, etc.).           Clothing.           Household linen.           Household utensils.           Imported groceries.           Drugs.           Sports material.           Tobacco.           Alcoholic liquors.&apos;  Taking all these items into consideration  on  a very conservative scalefor a family group of  seven adults and one child, the annual expenditureper head on imported articles worked out at  156 a year. Most of the ex-penditure items included  had been  calculated inclusive  of  local services for distribution, etc.  Allowing 20  per cent, for those items for which this allowance had not been made reduces this value to  125  a year per head,as compared with the  136 per head deduced from the Customs figures.  In considering this value, two characteristics of the population of Kenyashould be kept in mind : (1) the standard of living in Kenya is high and the stage of the poor white settler has  not yet been reached to any considerable extent;  (2)  the age-frequency curve shows all the  characteristics of animmigrant population with predominance of numbers in adult ages ;  (3) theproportion of persons in comfortable circumstances is much greater than in long-established communities with wide differences between the social strata ;(4)  the  average monthly salary of Government European  officials worksout at  43-6.                                                -  The differentiation between the various units composing  the non-european community is not insisted  upon and was abandoned in 1926 and 1927.   Nocomparison should in consequence be made between Indians, Goans, Somalis,Arabs, etc.  Even after taking these factors into consideration, the value of the Europeancontribution still appears high in comparison with the Asiatic contribution,but there is little evidence to show  that the contribution to indirect taxation on  the part of the native is much in error.  Some further measure of non-native (European  and Asiatic) expenditure will be found in the Bank statistics which will shortly be  published. Theseindicate that the per  capita expenditure is certainly  higher than  that of most European communities and it seems probable that the reasons adducedabove are not without some foundation in fact.  There is at  present  no direct means  of ascertaining whether the  totalexpenditure for the European population to which this figure leads is con-sistent or not.  Measured by standards of European countries it is undoubtedlyhigh, but the  circumstances are  quite  as  undoubtedly different.  the europeans in Kenya are, on the whole, a selected community.  Collateral statistics  may,  however, be helpful as a guide, and referenceto the Bank returns shows that for  the whole population drawings by chequeon  Kenya Banks (Total Debit Transactions) amount to nearly  200,000a day over  70,000,000 a year while deposits on current  account exceed 3,000,000.  These  figures  refer   to  the non-native  communities  almost exclusively.                                               A. WALTER,                                                     Statistician,                                    Conference of East African Governors.
APPENDIX 3.Native Cash Resources.                             No. 1. NANDI.  1. The  Nandi  appear to derive their  taxes  mainly from the followingsources :          (a) Wages.         (6) Sale of cattle, sheep, and goats.         (c) Sale of honey.  2. Wages for unskilled labour have dropped during the  last four yearsapproximately  from Shs. 14 per month to  Shs. 8 per month and, employmentobtainable being considerably less, more tax is now derived from (6).  3. Enquiries  made from traders and  natives, together, result  in  thefollowing prices being agreed upon :-	192S.		1932.			Shs		Shs.		Large oxen .. .....	45 to	65	20	to	30Cows and large heifers	75 to	SO	25	to	45Cows with calves	90 to 120		40	to	65Heifers, small	40 to	60	25	to	30Young bulls	20 to	25	10	to	15Goats and sheep, large	S to	14	4	to	6Goats and sheep, small	6 to	10	2	to	4Fowls75 cents, to Sh.l  25  to  50 cents.    Hides, sun-dried, are selling at approx. Shs.4 per frasila, shade-dried,      at from Shs. 11 to Shs.12.  Prices in 1928 were approximately double.  The prices  quoted for stock are for rinderpest-immune animals, andmay be reduced by approximately  10  per cent, for non-immune.  Cost ofimmunization is Shs. 2-50, plus  the risk of loss during immunization.  4. Honey is  sold  in relatively large  quantities, and the relative  pricesquoted  to me are :                 1928.                             1932.      Shs. 18 to Shs. 20 for 50 lb.       . Shs. 6 to Shs. 7 for 50 lb.  5. Practically no  grain  is sold,  except between-members of the  tribe.It is the Nandi custom after a good harvest to fill their stores, and &quot; lay off &quot;cultivation for one season or more.      K.  L.  HUNTER,District Commissioner, Nandi.
(d) Cattle (male stock A.M. branded)   Sheep and Goats(6) Wimbi (per bag)   Maize (per debbi)  Elgeyo ..          (per bag)  Marakwet(c) Hides (each)   Goat skins (each)   Leopard skins (average)   Honey (per pot)   Beeswax  (per lb.)   Tobacco (per 6 lb.)   Blacksmithery (sundry articles for local     consumption)(d) Work (on farms)         (on Railway) Shs.to 75to 10   12    3    to  6  1932.  Shs.15 to 35 1 to  4       6       1       3 No sale30 6 1161 to 275 2 per mensem S to  16               16half-price 5  to  6       10  2. This District, too, suffered from food shortage in 1928-29, owing to thedepredations of locusts,  and again  during 1931.  District  Headquarters(Tambach) are 29 miles from railhead (Eldoret).  3. There is a strong demand for hand-mills for grinding maize but althoughthe prices quoted lately are extremely reasonable they remain beyond thefinancial capacity of the would-be purchasers. The few which were purchasedand distributed to the maize-growing centres by the Local Native council a year or two ago are now almost worn out, owing to incessant usage.  4. There is to-day a constant cry on the  part of natives that-Governmentshould help to find them work.  Last year, too, natives who went out seeking work were compelled  to return  home empty-handed even after three orfour excursions. During the course of my present safari in Southern Elgeyowhen discussing tax prospects, etc., I have been repeatedly asked to help byfinding work, especially for those who have no stock to sell and therefore no other means of raising the cash with which to pay their hut tax for 1932.                                               J.  G.  HAMILTON-ROSS,                                                  District Commissioner.                     No. 3. MWIMBI  AND CHUKA.  1. Money for hut tax is normally obtained  by the Mwimbi  and Chukafrom the following sources. They are given in the order of their importance from the point of view of their money-producing capacities :          (a) Labour for non-natives outside the  Reserve.         (6) Sale of goats,         (c) Sale of pigeon pea,         (d) Sale of tobacco,         (e) Sale of njahi,         (/) Sale of maize,         (g) Sale of ghee.                            No. 2. ELGEYO.  1. Although the export of food-stuffs  has been prohibited for years past,a certain amount is exchanged between Elgeyo tribes and their neighboursacross the Kerio River, e.g., mtama exported and meat and milk imported.Furthermore the Somali traders at Marakwet buy maize, grind it, and resellit later in the form of posho.                COMPARISON OF PRICES IN 1929 AND 1932.                                                 1929.
   1. With regard to (a) this is the most important tax-producing means in a normal year, since not only does it account for the direct tax paid by the labourer for himself and his dependants, but indirectly also, by bringing a surplus of money into the Reserve, it allows those who do not seek labour outside it to obtain money to pay their taxes by the sale of the normal increase of stock and the products of their work in the Reserve.   This year, owing to  the  financial depression, the demand by settlers for African labour is very much decreased.  Large numbers of men have left this district in search of work and at  least 75 per  cent, of them have returned without finding it.   Rates of wages have dropped by as much as Shs.4 to Shs.6 for  a .30-day- month&apos;s work for an unskilled labourer.   It is probable that the amount  of money entering the Reserve at present from this source is not more than  one-eighth of the normal.   3. With regard to (6), the price obtainable for a goat is now Shs.6 to Shs.S as against Shs. 15 to Shs.20 in a good year.  Many Mwimbi and Chuka will certainly  have to dispose of more than  the normal increase to obtain their tax this year.  In fact, their taxes will be paid from capital.   The  price of goats will certainly decrease still further when the Kikuyu market is glutted by goats brought by the Akamba in search of tax-money.   4. Pigeon pea is the most paying of the Mwimbi crops and in  a normal vear Shs.7 is obtainable for a load of it.  Now possibly Shs.3 could be obtained. In any case this source of tax-money is  practically valueless this year since most of the pigeon pea was destroyed by locusts.   5. To a man skilled in the preparation of good snuff, tobacco is a lucrative crop in a normal year.  Now, however, the mass of the population  is so poor that the demand has fallen away to such an extent that a drum of snuff which normally would fetch  Shs.30  in one day will now fetch only Shs. 15, sold in small quantities over a period of three months. Leaf tobacco has depreciated in. value about 75 per cent.   6. Njahi is of little money-producing value this year;  the crop obtained was very  small,  the plants failing to seed as a result of  some undiagnosed condition, and the  price of  a load in Mwimbi and Chuka is about Shs.2 as against Shs.7 in normal times.   7. Maize is very little grown in  Chuka and Mwimbi for export, since there is no market for it, the cost of transport from Chuka to the railway being prohibitive.   S. Some of the Lower Chuka depend on the sale of ghee for their tax-money. There is now no demand for it.   9.  It will be seen from the foregoing that all the usual means at the disposal of the Chuka and Mwimbi of obtaining money for tax have become  so meagre that the chance of their paying in full within the year is slight. It is noteworthy that, even in a normal year, the distance from a market for their crops makes the natives of these areas practically dependent for their tax on the  labour of the young men outside the  Reserve ;   the crops produced are redistributed in the areas themselves, most of the sale being to natives of the areas who have returned from work writh a  surplus amount of  cash.  Apart from this, most of the money obtained is from the sale of native luxuries, such as tobacco, and a few foodstuffs, such as pigeon pea, either directly by safari to Masai, Ukamba
                            No. 4.   MASAI.  The commodities upon which the Masai mainly depend for the payment oftheir taxes are the following :                                       Price per frasila   Price per frasila                               Year.      at Narok.        at Kajiado.                                            Shs.             Shs.    I.   Hides......   1928         30               32                                1932          6                7           ...... ; &quot;  :    .&apos;      ;            .&apos;              &apos;          ..&apos;.  The total export of hides from the Province in  1928 was approximately550 tons.                                        Price per head    Price per head                               Year.      at Narok.        at Kajiado.                                            Shs.             Shs.   II.   Slaughter cattle     ..   192S         35               55                                1932         20               30  III.   Sheep......   1928          6                7                                1932          3                4                                                 Per frasila.  IV.   Ghee......   1928         55               60&apos;                                1932         25               25   The Masai have large reserves of livestock and the drop in prices has been of indirect benefit by causing increased sales of surplus cattle and thus reducingoverstocking.                                               G. E. DECK,                                        Provincial Commissioner. No. 5.   COAST PROVINCE.Prices of Native Commodities.(Forwarded by Provincial Commissioner.)		1928.		1929.		1930.		1931.		April 1932.		H.	L.	H.	L.	H.	L.	H.	L.			Shs.	Shs.	Shs.	Shs.	Shs.	Shs.	Shs.	Shs.	Shs.Simsim,	gisila	74	50	57	35	37	29	37	26	36Pojo,		SO	35	80	40	41	28	40	20	30Kundi,	-- -:	65	40	65	24	45	29	40	16	27Mtama,		40	28	55	24	30	20	30	14	25Maize,	V ,,&quot;v i *	32	12	40	16	20	14	24	10-50	20Hides,	frasila	42-50	24-50	28	12	14-50	8-50	11-50	4	4Copra,		7-25	5-90	6-20	4-50	5-65	3	3-60	2-25	2-75Ghee,		&quot;	-	-		40	26	30	22	29Note. H. represents Highest; L. represents Lowest.and the Northern Frontier, or indirectly, through Kikuyu middlemen, whoagain sell to Indian middlemen,  the actual producer getting very little forhis trouble.                                            H. E. LAMBERT,                                      District Commissioner, Embu.
Ill-                             APPENDIX  4.             Outline of Uniform Adult Male Native  Poll-Tax.  1.  The tax shall be payable at the rate of Shs.6 per year by all male natives of the apparent age of  16 years and upwards, except those exempted by a district Officer on the grounds of poverty and inability to pay.  2.  The tax shall be collected by means of stamps to be affixed to the backof the registration certificate.  In cases of exemption the certificate shall besuitably endorsed by the District  Officer, who will  also inform  the ChiefRegistrar of Natives.&apos;  3.  Tax stamps shall be on sale at any Office of a District Administration.They will also be issued on payment of tax by the officer engaged in collectinghut tax.  A list of those to whom stamps have been issued with the numbersof their registration certificates shall be kept in duplicate  by each issuingofficer, and one copy shall in due course be sent to  the Chief Registrar  ofNatives.  Stamps shall be affixed in the presence of the issuing officer or his deputy in  any district where the taxpayer can most conveniently pay histax,  and shall be cancelled at the time of issue by an indelible mark to shewyear of payment. It is a matter for consideration whether post offices shouldalso  be charged with the duty of issuing and cancelling tax stamps.  4.  A statutory obligation shall be imposed on employers on the paymentof wages to see that stamps are affixed in each case, under regulations to beissued.  5.  The Chief Registrar of Natives will enter payment  of taxes in his cardrecords, and will from time to time inform District Commissioners as to thosetaxpayers in default.                             APPENDIX  5.                    Outline of Native Livestock Tax.  Livestock tax shall be imposed per head of cattle, sheep, and goats, at amoney-rate  per  head to be fixed  by the Govemor-in-Council,  and to  bevariable  as  between districts and  from year to year.  In fixing the rate,account shall be taken of current prices.  Owners of less than a statutory number of cattle, sheep, and goats, shallbe exempt from payment of tax.  The statutory number of tax-free livestockshall be higher in  the pastoral districts than in the agricultural areas, andshall in both cases be fixed with the object of exempting from taxation that amount of stock which is needed to provide food for an average family.  Taxshall be levied only on  that number of stock which is above the exemptionlimit.  Young and immature animals shall also be exempt.  For the purposeof deciding as to liability to tax, five sheep or five goats shall be consideredequal to one head of cattle.r
                             APPENDIX 6.                    Outline of Native Cultivation Tax.   1. The tax shall be based on the value of the crops estimated to be producedfrom  the land  in an average year.  The rate of tax shall be levied  as a percentage of the valuation and  shall be variable as between  Local NativeCouncil Districts and from year to year.   The rates shall be fixed annually by the Governor-in-Council.  2. The estimated yield of each taxation unit shall be assessed by the DistrictOfficer advised  by an Assessment Board consisting of the Headman with the help of native  assessors.  For the  assessment  of yield one  or both of twomethods shall be applied first, a general survey of the taxation  unit, theprobable yield of each crop then being computed according to soil and averageexperience second, computation of yield of various crops on sample holdings,the resulting figures  being taken to represent the average  and multipliedaccording to the number of cultivators in the taxation unit.   Having arrivedat the estimated yield of each crop, valuation shall be made on the basis of market prices ruling in each District.  3. When the computation of yield on sample holdings has been made anda per capita average has been established, it is most important to withholdfrom the native Headmen any information as to  the per capita average thusestablished, as  otherwise on Nigerian experience it is  found that Headmenand taxpayers are apt to take this average as a flat rate thereby destroying the distinction  between a cultivation tax graded according to ability to pay and  a flat  poll-tax.  On  the  subject of  differentiation between individualtaxpayers, the Lieutenant-Governor of Southern Nigeria has stated :       &quot; It should be  borne in mind that among the most primitive com-    munities it is customary for  contributions to be made by members of a    family for some general family purpose, festivals, the building of a familr    house, and the like, and such contributions are by native custom graded    in accordance with ability to contribute, and the same applies to larger    social units. Grading of  ability to pay is no new thing to the African    native.&quot;  4. Variations in percentage rate of tax to be levied shall be based inter aliaon variations of price from the price levels on which valuations were originallymade.  5. The tax payable to the Government shall be fixed as a percentage ofthe total valuation.   In the Sudan it is collected at the rate of 10  per cent.and in Nigeria at 2j per cent.  In the Sudan, however,  the valuation is madeyearly for each  cultivation unit on the basis of local prices, whereas in Nigeriarevaluation takes place at rare intervals, and the tax is adapted to capacityby varying the annual percentage of tax.  6. Assessment Boards shall  be responsible for detailed  allocation of the tax within  each unit among cultivators in proportion to their estimatedoutput, but an appeal to the Local Native Tribunal and finally to the DistrictOfficer shall be  provided in cases of dispute.  7. Native Council rates might be collected on the same valuation and at thesame time  as the Government tax.  They might be levied as a percentagesurcharge to be paid over to the Local Native Council.
                             APPENDIX 7.                  Finance  of Native Betterment Fund.  In order to make a clear  distinction between expenditure^to be borne onthe general budget and that to be financed by the Native Betterment Fund,the following procedure is suggested :       (a)  That no part of Head Office Administration charges be paid from    the Native Betterment Fund.      (6)  That cash emoluments and expenses of agricultural officers working  - wholly in  Native Reserves be included in the Native  Betterment Fund    and excluded from the general budget.      (c) That the cash emoluments and expenses of Education Officers  and    Inspectors attached to native schools  be included in the Native  Better-    ment  Fund and excluded from the general budget.      (d)  That the cash emoluments and expenses of Medical Officers in charge    of native hospitals and those stationed in Native Reserves be included in    the Native Betterment Fund and excluded from the general budget.      (ey That expenditure on roads and bridges within the Native Reserves,    which may be regarded as  primarily  of native benefit, be included in    the Native Betterment Fund and excluded from the general budget.      (f) That the cost of all reliefs,  pensions, leave pay,  and passages be    borne on the general  budget.      (g) That the cost of medical and other stores issued to hospitals, schools,    etc., from  Government main stores be recovered from the Native  Better-    ment  Fund and brought to account as revenue in the general budget.      (h)  Generally,  that expenditure from the Native  Betterment Fund    should be  confined to direct services and  that all  indirect expenditure    should be met from general revenue towards which the native community    contributes.  8. It shall be  the  duty of employers  to send valuations  of squatters&apos;holdings and livestock to the District Officer, who shall satisfy himself thatthey are reasonable.  Employers shall be under statutory obligation to paythe cultivation and livestock  taxes and  to recover from the squatter bydeduction from wages.  9. The tax shall be collected by the  Native Assessment Boards, and, toprevent over-charging and peculation, District Officers shall  issue to suchBoards sheets of one shilling tax-receipts to the total value of the tax andlocal rates to be collected.  Such tax receipts shall be issued to the cultivatorsby the Assessment Boards in varying numbers against the payment of tax.They shall be cancelled at the time of issue by a rubber year-stamp.  A per-centage of the tax collected might be allowed as remuneration to each Assess-ment Board.  10. Livestock tax may be merged in the cultivation tax as in Nigeria.
                        APPENDIX  8.Table of Revenue and Expenditure of Local Native Councils in 1931.		Revenue.			Expenditure (including expenditure on building).						Surplus																						balance in hand at end ofProvince and Council.	Rates.	Land, (Rents, fees, etc.)	Other.	Education.	Medical.	Agricultural, Veterinary,	Roads and	Water supplies.	Famine relief.	Other.							Forestry.	bridges.				1931.											Coast.	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 Digo	620	282	631	304	190	310	313	216	100	216	2,208Giriama	719	753	781	-	213	241	182	881	 	298	3,641Teita	1..042	142	1,440	- 	164	99	132	5	 	151	4,441Nyanza. North Kavirondo .. Central Kavirondo.. S. Kavirondo (K-B) S. Kavirondo (L-A) South Lumbwa	9,528 4,245 2,656 2,090	929 415 448 949 420	1,006 739 240 224 101 .	6,608 1,605 211 500 440	1,084 999 .. 115 &apos; 357	1,149 487 475 209 56	2,500 1,331 623 524 347	10	1,818 214	2,032 1,281 803 1,061 116	18,386 13,023 7,087 7,298 2,306Nzoia.																						Nandi Elgeyo .. &apos; .. Marakwet	594	704 900 283	312 283 70	484 779 190	284 175 S	709 254 78	428	2	62 39	1,370* 374 33	3,819 4,329 983	 						3 28				
Rift Valley.											Baringo I. ..	507	249	58&apos;	 	2	86	17	_	337	324	1,713Baringo II.	108	70	16		2		-	 		386	229Kikuyu.											Kyambu	2,563	374	290	200	339	422	767	211	_	1,110	7,758Fort Hall	2,524	903	219	10	1,657	548	917			746	7,939South Nyeri	2,946	600	215	2,857	224	1,457	79		_	1,384	5,662Embu	1,142	328	207	 	358	100	 	17	_	211	2,216Meru	1,676	994	60		4	398	89	 	 	121	5,006Ukamba.											Machakos	4,771	1,013	369	910	343	1,272	799	819	_	655	9,527Kitui	1,632	666	904	202	390	144	431	208	 	948	6,788Masai.											Narok	 	1,060	92	169	3	2	. 	_	 	55	2,591Kajiado	589	1,151	360	1,082	4	 	 	520	 	345	1,694Turkana.											West Suk	 	309	52	449	 	 	_		- _.	96	. 732South Turkana	 	128	 	 	 	 	..  	 	. -\,	 	128Total .. . . 	39,952	14,070	8,669	17,000	6,915	8,496	9,510	2,889	2,570	14,116	119,504Oi* Includes  1,144, being refund to Government of rents and stand premia overpaid.CO
                             APPENDIX 9.                           Communal Labour.(Extract from Minutes of Kyambu Local Native Council Meeting held on                     27th and 28th January, 1931.)                          MINUTE NO.  66/31.           Allocation of money for Bridges to be erected in 1931.   Agreed that the following should be built if funds allowed in 1931:              (1) Rui Rwaka (Headman Koinange),             (2) Kamiti (Headman Mimi),             (3) Ndarugu (Headman Kiranga),             (4) Ruiru (Headmen Rimungi and Gathingo),and that if any money remained over that a  bridge be built over the Karurariver in Headman Philip&apos;s location. The Council also gave their opinion thatthe provisions of the Native Authority Ordinance should be followed in regardto communal work on roads.  That such labour should be unpaid and thatHeadmen should call out labour in their locations for maintenance and repairsof existing roads under this law.  Too much money had been wasted un-necessarily last year in paying gangs of labour for upkeep of roads and the resulting shortage of funds had seriously deflected money from being expendedin the building of bridges and the opening of new roads which were of great value to the trade of the Reserve.  It was agreed, however, that labour shouldbe paid for when assisting &quot; fund is &quot; to build bridges.
APPENDIX  10.  TABLE  1.Revenue Figures, 1926-1931.	1926.	1927.	1928.	1929.	1930.	1931.Customs Licences, etc. Fees, etc. Posts and/Telegraphs Earnings of Government Departments Revenue from Government Property Sale of Government Property Miscellaneous Receipts Forest Revenue	  741,374 842,587 125,734 148,258 48,713 106,908 26,774 11,646	  830,550 898,166 129,670 165,100 54,022 90,044 35,075 12,278 39,199	  915,282 907,639 128,356 171,646 79,586 79,081 , 22,763 &apos; 10,244 37,329	  949,725 902,566 123,843 182,158 96,988 74,657 60,046 11,767 39,461	  815,286 948,774 140,886 173,525 98,750 72,241 33,959 17,042 38,705	  698,584 867,714 130,382 168,132 87,621 71,347 14,577 16,192 30,901Total General Revenue ..	 2,051,994	2,254,104	2,351,926	2,441,211	2,339,168	2,085,450Port, Harbour, and Light Dues Land Sales Reimbursements Interest .......... Colonial Development Fund	21,357 39,362 385,558 128,952	598 48,387 397,390 145,631	57,955 570,616 40,197	55,288 770,843 66,400	42,587 788,435 55,323 16,087	29,923 891,140* 29,494* 30,923Total Gross Revenue	 2,627,223	2,846,110	3,020,694	3,333,742	3,241,600	3,066,930  * The items &quot; Reimbursements &quot; and &quot; Interest &quot; include recoveries from the Railways and Harbours Administration in respectof annual loan charges.  In 1931 the loan charges recovered from the Railways and Harbours amounted to  753,167, and this amount is included in the &quot; Reimbursements &quot; total of  891,140.
APPENDIX 10-(Continued.)       TABLE 2.Comparative Expenditure Figures  (Recurrent Votes).							Budget	Revised	Department.	1926.	1927.	1928.	1929.	1930.	1931.	1932	Bridget	Remarks.							(original).	1932.		 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	H.E. The Governor ..	18.432	18,213	18,363	17,465	16,874	15,780	16,565	15,950	Administration	249,297	254,791	257,770	259,777	259,037	256,401	266,818	255,456	Native Registration									Dept. included up to 1927.Agriculture	106,899	113,354	128,021	147,257	160,804	144,310	143,385	136,036	Audit	15,446	16,771	18,803	18,836	19,158	19,398	20,792	19,812	Coast Agency	. -  	 	7,679	5,585	5,976	6,034	5,826	5,676	Conference of East									African Governors..	2,576	1,391	&apos; 1,636	1,193	1,409	1,228	1,250	1,250	Customs	39,449	41,948	44,032	45,328	48,123	47,438	49,747	48,637	Education	108,074	121,139	152,030	165,088	180,734	182,224	188,632	178,465	Forest	29,855	32,750	36,813	38,914	38,729	36,859	37,150	35,637	Game	8,627	11,207	11,041	12,557	11,382	10,355	10,939	10,439	Judicial	22,752	26,308	26,119	30,286	33,759	33,087	34,136	33,426	Legal	9,621	10,627	9,813	9,924	9,566	8,809	8,755	8,755	Local Government									Contributions	 ,	_	&apos;  .. i	85,087	103,008	91,903	90,931	87,652	Medical	161,043	180,206	194,814	222,185	236,934	221,201	219,357	207,498	Military	125,304	114,579	114,448	123,896	97,447	89,015	97,258	90,288	Miscellaneous Services	107,301	132,141	97,680	50,659	64,371	69,459	87,7S3	87,633	Pensions and Gratuities	86,804	89,133	109,001	117,285	113,669	132,637	130,700	130,700	Police	134,274	137,946	144,429	160,872	172,017	149,232	147.99S	141,894	Post Office	136,421	144,515	149,625	159,054	172,255	172,5H6	li!9,oy5	157,045	
Printing and Stationery	21,442	34,406	36,114	37,418	38,025	32,475	36,534	32,534	Amalgamation of Government and Railway Press in									Prisons									1927.	43,640	43,194	45,114	50,369	50,392	46,714	49,000	47,995	Public Works Depart-									ment	71,826	83,058	122,728	141,297	149,354	133,088	112,925	107,898	Public Works Recur-									reht	196,638	178,994	190,730	173,617	182,459	154,658	145,500	137,600	Registrar-General	3,330	4,428	5,300	5,113	5,530	5,842	6,007	5,635	Rents and Interest,									Zanzibar	16,000	16,000	16,000	16,000	16,000	16,000	16,000	16,000	Secretariat and Leg.									Council	19,637	20,205	18,079	19,752	21,101	19,024	20,946	19,146	Statistical Departments			21,121	20,176	22,808	22,175	21,260	20,959	Survey and Registra-	41,061	43,450	35,516	39,516	37,927	36,233	36,500	34,520	Land Department in-tion (including Land									cluded in Admini-Department to 1927).									stration from 1928.Trade and Information									Office.....	5,000	5,000	6,013	4,955	4,895	4,837	4,800	4,800	Treasury	22,445	25,129	24,887	26,726	26,487	26,407	25,879	25,433	Public Debt and In-									terest*	484,981	503,538	591,876	781,590	814,683	891,495	1,011,500	1,010,500	Extraordinary Expen-									diture	109,181	110,634	199,051	517,295	307,874	108,282	32,250	27,135	Port and Marine	17,325	60	&apos; - -	 	_		_		Colonial Development									Fund					16,087	30,923	319	319	Total Gross									Expenditure  	2,414,681	2,515,115	2,834,646	3,505,072	3,438,874	3,216,089	3,246,477	3,142,723	    * The item &quot; Public Debt and Interest &quot; includes provision for the annual loan charges of both Colony and the Railways and HarboursAdministration. The amount recoverable from the Railways and Harbours, which in 1931 amounted to  753,167, appears under &quot; Reimburse-ments &quot; on the revenue side of the Colony&apos;s budget.
           APPENDIX  lQ-(Conlimted .                   TABLE 3.Allocation of Total Public Debt and Annual Charges.	Capital Debt.			Annual Charges.						Total Annual Charges.Loan.	Colony.	Railways and Harbours.	Total Public Debt.	Colony.			Railways and Harbours.							Interest.	Sinking Fund.	Total.	Interest.	Sinking Fund.	Total.		 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	sell	 1921	754,614	4,245,386	5,000,000	45,277	9,810	55,087	254,723	55,190	309,913	365,0001927	- &quot;	5,000,000	5,000,000	-			250,000	50,000	300,000	300,0001928 ..	659,669	2,840,331	3,500,000	29,685	6,596	36,281	127,815	28,404	156,219	192,5001930	2,233,909	1,166,091	3,400,000	100,526	22,339*	122,865	52,474	11,661*	64,135	1S7.000Total  	3,648,192	13,251,808	16,900,000	175,488	38,745	214,233	685,012	145,255	830,267	1,044,500* Contributions to the sinking fund in respect of the 1930 loan commence in July, 1934.
OOPdubLicenses, Duties, Taxes, etc. :     Native Registration    Stamp Duties, Various Revenue purpose    Liquor Licences  ..    Cattle Traders&apos; Licences    Non-Native Poll Tax    Fines and Forfeitures    Traders&apos; Licences    Petrol Tax    Cotton Tax    European Education Tax    Asiatic Education Tax    Motor Drivers&apos; Licences    Entertainment Tax    Other Licences RevenueFees and Payments for Specific ServicesPosts and Telegraphs Revenue -Earnings of Government DepartmentsRevenue from Government PropertyForest RevenueReimbursements                                  Total   200,000     700 9,500  500 1,700 4,50010,000  500 5,500 1,200  600 2,500  500 1,500 3,900-   43,100    2,600    S,000   10,000    6,500    7,000    4,500  281,700  The total short-fall of  281,700 may be off-set to some extent by excesseson other sub-heads, e.g., Miscellaneous Receipts, which it is impossible toestimate accurately, and by the receipt of arrears of 1931 hut-tax revenue.It is considered that a reasonable estimate of the  probable total short-fallat this early stage would be  250,000 if account is taken of revenue increasesthat may accrue.If  HA                             TABLE 4.             Probable Short-fall on 1932 Revenue Estimates.Customs Revenue
                                         Original Expenditure Estimate    ..   3,246,477Add Special Warrants to date    ..     27,373Add  Reserve  for further  Special      Warrants     ......     20,0003,045,414                                    3,293,850Less Economies      ..     ..     ..    103,7543,190,096      Deficit ..     .........    ....     ..     144,682      Surplus Account at 31st December, 1932 ......     216,861B.  Commitments against Surplus at 3lst December, 1932.                      Agricultural Advances      ..    ..    ..     ..     ..      100,000      Grain Subsidies     ............      116,000      Loans to Local Authorities  ..    ..     ..     ..     ..        2,500      Unallocated Stores  ..     ..    ..     ....             80,000                                                                298,500      Estimated Surplus at 31st December, 1932 (as above)  ..     216,861      Cash Shortage       ............      81,639       Add Cash required for current Treasury needs  ..     ..     100,000      Cash Deficiency      ............ 181,639                              TABLE  5.           Estimate of Cash Position at 31st December, 1932.A. Surplus  Account.                                                     Balance on 1st January,  1932      ..     ..     ..     ..    361,543      Less Deficit on 1932 Accounts :                               Original Revenue Estimate      ..     ..      3,295,414         Less Short-fall    ..     ..     ..     ..        250,000

</content>
</cab>
