<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/27 images: 294-303</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  July 1943. i QQ.       ^ /        -    - -SECRET. V Copy No.  3W.P. (43) 327.2lst July, 1943.WAR CABINET.MORALE AND THE WAR AGAINST JAPANANDTHE TWO-STAGE ENDING AND DEMOBILISATION.Memorandum by the Prime Minister.EIGHT Memoranda^ have been circulated on these subjects, and it may help to focus discussion if I set forth some of the main issues involved and myprovisional views thereon.2. Although we cannot tell how things will work out, we are bound toprepare for a two-stage ending of the war. The paramount object will be the speedy destruction of Japan. For this purpose the necessary forces, which will inmany ways differ from those at present in our hands, will have to be foreseen and later on possibly prepared in skeleton while Hitler, is still resisting. The actualscale and character of these forces can only be shaped in concert with the UnitedStates, and it would be a help if both countries took similar measures on thishypothesis. Evidently the largest proportion of skilled and experienced veteranunits will have to be used at the end of these long communications; yet these arethe ones most entitled to release on grounds of equity. We cannot fight Japanwith raw, lightly-trained youths. The war against Japan may well take several years and will require a large proportion of our best troops. The heart-burningswhich will arise about all this will be fierce. However, if it is all laid downbeforehand and made public beforehand, and if it conforms to the soldiers&apos; broadsense of justice, the difficulties will be mitigated.* W.P. (43) 232, by the Secretary of State for India.W.P. (43) 238, by the Minister of Information.W.P. (43) 239, by the Secretary of State for War.W.P. (43) 241, by the Minister without Portfolio.W.P. (43) 252, by the Secretary or State for Air.W.P. (43) 284, bv the Minister of Labour.W.P. (43) 294, by the First Lord of the Admiralty.W.P. (43) 315, by the Minister without Portfolio.[25777] b
Partial Demobilisation.3. The main issue, and the one which links the two questions dealt with inthese Memoranda, is this : How are we to frame our man-power measures in theperiod after Germany and Italy have been beaten so as to bring the maximumeffort against Japan in accordance with our solemn duty and yet to return the elements not needed for this effort to civil life in a manner which will be accepted as fair by members of the Services \4. Far more is involved here than priorities in demobilisation. Thus, wehave to consider : (a) The method of recruitment for the Forces.    Obviously, liability to compulsory military and national service must continue on a universalbasis at least until Japan has been defeated, and all plans should bemade accordingly.(b) Measures to relieve and bring home to this country as large a number aspossible of the troops who have served for many years overseas. Thisshould be done, even if the men concerned have to be retained withthe colours at home or on garrison duty in Europe.(c) There will be certain sections of the Forces and Civil Defence Services(e.g., A.D.G.B., Coast Defence troops and National Fire Services) who,on military grounds, could in large part be demobilised. How canthese be dealt with, so as not to engender a sense of grievance among those retained on active service ?(d) It will be most important that the younger men who have been retained in this country on civil jobs during the war should be compulsorilyenlisted and used to facilitate the relief of older men who have seenlong service overseas.I had to send all the &apos;&apos; Eighteens &apos;&apos; over to Germany by a newConscription Act after the last war was over to relieve their fathersand elder brothers who had done the fighting. This same need willrecur in an even more acute form this time.5. In brief, we have planned hitherto for a complete demobilisation, andhave sought to secure an orderly and equitable order of discharge, on the basisof age and length of service. The two-stage ending of the war calls for a newalternative plan for the comprehensive re-shaping and re-arrangement of our military man-power in such a way that all will recognise that it is as fair asmay be between man and man, military needs being prime and predominant.6. The need is clearly established for an inquiry into these matters by theDepartments concerned. It remains to settle how this inquiry should becarried out.On the whole, I favour the establishment of a Standing Committee on demobilisation Problems, with representatives of the Service Ministries, theMinistry of Labour and National Service and the Reconstruction Secretariat.
It is for consideration whether it would be convenient that a MinisterialChairman should be appointed to this body.7. This Committee&apos;s first task would be to re-examine the broad lines ofour scheme of demobilisation, on the basis of a two-stage ending of the war.The Committee should also examine the question referred to in paragraph 4of the second Memorandum by the Minister without Portfolio (W.P. (43) 315),namely, what modifications in the National Service Acts would be requiredbetween the cessation of hostilities and the signature of peace. The necessaryBills should be drafted as soon as the policy is settled.8. The question is also raised, whether this Committee, or some other body,should be charged with deciding the criteria to be adopted in granting priorrelease where this is essential to a rapid revival of peace-time production, and generally with the question of demobilisation priorities. My own inclinationwould be to wait until a Report has been received on the enquiry suggested inthe first sentence of paragraph 7, and until replies have been received to thequestions as to war production referred to in paragraph 12.This information will enable the question of demobilisation priorities to bedealt with on a more practical basis.9. The question of publicity for our demobilisation scheme has also been raised. On this my view is that it is only by full publicity for the Demobilisation-Rules beforehand, and rigid adherence to them, that widespread dissatisfactioncan be avoided.  But we must be sure of our ground before anything is published.Reinstatement.10. It is also suggested in these Papers that an assurance should be given that every effort will be made to absorb into employment those who are demobilised,late. This is clearly desirable in principle, but with a two-stage ending of thewar it will be very difficult to keep available a proportion of good jobs for thosewho are retained for service against Japan. Yet this will be above all thingsdemanded. This point should be borne in mind by the Committee suggested inparagraph 6.Service Pay.11. Connected with the above is the suggestion in the Memoranda by the secretaries of State for India and Air, and by the First Lord of the Admiralty,that the pay and conditions of service of those who will have to continue in theServices and endure the dangers and. hardships of the war in the East shouldbe increased. It will certainly prove necessary to offer some further benefits to offset the hardship of a new campaign at the other end of the world and ofindefinitely postponed demobilisation. Volunteering for the Far East from anyof the veteran classes to be demobilised or brought home must play an important part. But this can be looked at when the principles of the scheme are ready for examination.[25777] b 2
Production.12. So much for the Services. The two-stage ending of the war will,however, also involve the release, for civilian purposes, of some proportion of theresources now engaged in war production. Since the amount so released will belimited, it will, as pointed out by the Minister without Portfolio, give rise todifficult questions of discrimination between firm and firm. All this is of thegreatest importance and will require attentive study, I doubt if this problem can well be tackled until an estimate has been obtained of the extentof the resources which would be released from Service purposes at the endof hostilities in Europe. The Minister of Production has already arranged thata number of questions on this matter should be put to the Chiefs of Staff. A listof these questions, which are now under examination, is set out in the Annextq this Memorandum.Public Opinion and the War against Japan.13- Several of my colleagues draw attention to the importance of stimu-lating the national morale towards waging war against Japan until that countryis completely defeated. There will be no disagreement on this object. For my own part, however, I doubt the utility of setting up a Ministerial Committee todeal with this issue.I suggest that the presentation of these issues to the civilian population should be recognised as being the responsibility of the Minister of Information.If some inter-Service machinery is required to co-ordinate the steps necessary to stimulate the morale of the men in the three Fighting Services, this can, i suggest, be settled by the three Service Ministers.(Initialled) W. S. C.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,21st July, 1943.
ANNEX.Some of the Questions to be put to the Chiefs of Staff.(i) What will be the approximate size of the sea, land and air forces required (a) against Japan, (b) to police Europe, and (c) in other theatres of war, e.g., Persia? Even a rough indication in terms of proportion of those at present in various theatres would be helpful.(ii) Will the whole of the United Kingdom Civil Defence be available for demobilisation ?(iii) To what extent will the various parts of the present A.D.G.B. beavailable for demobilisation?(iv) What will be the scale of demand for Escort and other small naval vessels ?(v) What will be the scale of total requirements of landing craft, tanks,guns, ammunition, &amp;c. ? What, if any, substantial changes in typecan be foreseen now?(vi) How substantial will be demands for engineer, transportation, accom-modation and similar stores, oil-pipe lines, boring machines, &amp;c. ?(vii) What will be the scale and tendency in aircraft, e.g., will land-basedfighters give way to FA.A., and some heavy bombers to transports?(viii) Will Airborne Forces be required to greater or less extent, and canany indication be given of what will be required ?(ix) Are there any other important new types of equipment likely to berequired, not covered above ?(x) Can any guide be given of probable timing or priority ?(xi) Can an approximation be given of the amount of cargo shipping whichwill have to be employed continuously on military voyages ?Note by the Prime Minister.The Chiefs of Staff must delegate this work to organisations under their control, and must not allow it to cumber current business. Their general guidance will, however, be required at an early stage.w. s. c.21.7.43.






</content>
</cab>
