<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/101/0 images: 148-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/i 122j ****** &apos;&quot;&quot;1THIS DOCUMENT IS THE ffiOPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT,Proposed Ministry of Minesa Memorandum&apos; by the Minister of Health,Miners1 Housing,The scheme outlined in Cabinet Paper C.P.604 for the setting up of a Ministry of Mines suggests that the powers or duties of the Minister of Health relating to the bousing of miners might be transferred to the proposed new Minister, or exercised by him concurrently or in consultation with the Minister of Health,    It will be observed that in this respect the scheme goes considerably beyond the proposal contained in the Memorandum circulated by the president  of the Board of Trade on 17th December last (G,PM)The practical difficulties connected with any such transfer of powers would, in my opinion, render the proposal wholly impracticable *At the present time it is the duty of every local authority to see that the needs of their district as regards the provision of new houses are met, and to prepare schemes for the necessary number having regard to any proposals of other persons or bodies to build within their district.    Any such schemes must comply with the standards and meet with the approval of the Ministry of Health,    The proposal&apos;to place miners1 houses and miners1 houses alone under the Ministry of Mines would mear   that two Government Departments would be dealing with the same problem of housing standards in the same district, and all the difficulties of dual control would arise.The difficulties in the way of tho proposal become much. /more
1, Z 3more acute when bousing problems other than the provision of new houses are considered.In the first place, housing problems, especially when they Involve the provision of thousands of new houses, cannot be separated from town-planning problems, and in town-planning problems large areas have to be considered with regard to their needs as a whole, from the point of view of linking up with the development of adjacent areas, the provision of new main roads, railways, etc.     It is quite clear that to secure effective results, the approval of town-planning schemes must be in the hands of one authority0Again, the Housing Acts and other Acts have given to local authorities various powers and duties in regard to housing in their area other than those relating to the provision of new houses.    Examples of such powers and duties are the power to order repairs to be carried out, to order the closing of premises unfit for human habitation, to order the demolition of unfit houses, to make slum clearance and re-housing schemes, and to make bye-laws relating to houses and buildings generally. These powers and duties arc subject to the general jurisdiction of tho Minister of Health, whose approval, or decision on appeal is necessary.    Obviously there is every reason against a proposal to split up such jurisdiction between two Government Departments on the sole ground of the occupation of the tenants concerned.There is also the question of finance,    tinder the Housing, Town Planning, etc. Act 1919, the annual   loss on housing schemes (including schemes for slum clearances and re-housing) undertaken by a local authority are borne, as to the extent of the produce of a penny rate by the local authority, and as to the remainder, by the State,    It is difficult to see how a second Government Department, dealing only with houses   of tenants of a/particular
particular occupation could &quot;be fitted Into this scheme without overlapping and friction.II.VMinersT Diseases,The suggested provision for the transfer of Miners Diseases from the Ministry of Health also calls for comment.In the first place Mirers Diseases, strictly so called, such as, Miners Phthises and Miners Nystagmus, are at present under the Home Office.    The general care of the health of-the miner, as of the rest of the population, namely,&apos; sanitation, housing, infectious diseases, tuberculosis, V.D.&apos;, insurance and medical practice are under the jurisdiction of the Ministry of Healths    The question might arise whether the functions of the Home Office In regard to industrial diseases might not ultimately be properly transferable to the Ministry of Health, because the Cabinet will remember that it has been the settled policy of the Government to concentrate in the Ministry of Health all health functions,,    But I cannot conceive on what principle it&apos; should be pc-o posed that any health functions should be alloted to a new Ministry of Mines, thereby creating yet another Medical Department, which is contrary to the whole principle of the Government1s policy underlying the creation of the Ministry of Health.MINISTRY CP HEALTH.C.ADDIS0H,19.3.1920.

</content>
</cab>
