<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/101/0 images: 207-212</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fjlgg^ MINISTRY OF HEALTH,Whitehall, S.W.I. 23rd March, 1920,oOf ALL 01-^&apos;Sir, ,I am directed to forward herewith the following report on the work of the Ministry of Health during the. month of February,Yours faithfully,ihASecond    Secretary.je Secretary,The Cabinet.1,   HOUSING.1. The Model Form of Agreement for the purchase of houses to be erected by builders and conveyed with their sites.to local authorities, under Section 12 (.3) of the Housing, Town Planning, etc., Act,: 1919, was published during the month. 2*&apos;   ?I0J^i?l&amp;.. 9^41*.     ^m Regulations with regard, to the borrowing of money by local authorities by the issue of local Bonds were circulated during the month.   A memorandum was at the same time addressed to local authorities drawing their attention to the necessary procedure and advising them with regard to the most suitable machinery.,3*   Grants to Private Builders.     The procedure to be adopted in. regard to the making of grants to private builders towards the erection of houses requires that a certificate shall be issued by the local authority conveying their approval of a proposal to erect the house in respect of which a grant will be claimed. Up
mto the 28th February, returns had only boon received from196 local authorities.   These had issued certificatesrelating to 1722 houses.   The total amount of the grant -for whichthese houses will be eligible is  267,457.   A very large volumeof correspondence on the subject from private individuals hasbeen dealt with.4.   Housing Survey.   Up to the present, 1,790 authorities have submitted housing, schemes as required by Section 1 of the Housing, Town Planning, etc., Act, 1919.   Of these schemes 915 have been approved, as satisfactory and 765 as satisfactory instalments. &quot;Local authorities, whose schemes are on the face of it unsat-satisfactory, are being pressed to amend their schemes.   The parti&quot;-circulars given in the Surveys relating to insanitary areas and unfit houses are now being examined.5.   Housing Schemes.     During the four weeks ending the 28th February, 556 sites were submitted by local authorities and Public Utility Societies, making a total of 8,970 (exclusive ;f a number of sites which had been withdrawn or had to , c. be rejected as unsuitable or for other reasons).   The total area comprised in these sites was over 62,000 acres, which would provide approximately for 620,000 houses.   The sites approved numbered 4,855 covering over 40,000 acres.   The total number of applications up to the 28th February for approval of lay-outs was 2,876 of which the Ministry had approved 2,293. Up to the same date,   house plans for 135,703 had been submitted, and of these the Ministry had given approval for 122,020,   Tenders had been submitted for 65,820 and of this number the Ministry had approved 59,704.6*   ,conyorsion of Houses into Flats,   Proceedings arc being taken for the acquisition and conversion of 227 houses which have been found suitable said in which no steps for the conversion
ware being taken by the owners.    Work on the conversion of 94 houses is in.hand or has been completed, and approximately 342 flats are now ready.3.
11,___PUBLIC HEALTH.1. Plague&apos;.   A fatal case of plague occurred In the person of a native steward from the s.s. &quot;Alpa Mam&quot;.   This vessel arrived in the Port of London on the 14th February, 1920,   The patient fell sick on the 15th February and died on the 19th February, Diagnosis was confirmed by the Bacteriologist of the Ministry. 2. Tuberculosis.   A Medical Officer of the Ministry, with repre-sentatives of the Office of Works, has been occupied in visiting sanatoria, in connection with the provision of training centres for tuberculous ex-service men,3. Smallpox.     Twenty-eight cases occurred during February.   Of these, eighteen were notified from East London.   One case was notified at each of the following ports       London, Manchester, Plymouth and River Tees.   The circumstances associated with these cases have been the subject of investigation by Medical Officers of the Ministry,4. Foods.   The Ministry received an application for financial assistance from the National Clean Milk Society, which aims at raising the hygienic standard of milk and milk products and at educating the public asi to the importance of a clean&quot;and whole-some milk supply.     The &quot;Ministry have obtained Treasury sanction to their making a grant of  500 in respect of the work to be done by the Societ;f during the first half of the ensuing financial year, at the end of which period the question will be further considered in the light of the work accomplished.The Treasury have also sanctioned the making of a grant of  800 by the Ministry to the Research Institute in Dairying at the University College, Reading, in respect of the salary of a research worker to be engaged on the public health aspect of problems connected with milk production. 5*   Lpaguej^of Nations.   The Ministry have received a request
from the Council of the League of Nations to call together a conference of international health experts to advise the Council on the establishment of an international health office of the League, and steps are being taken to comply with this request.111.   GENERAL. 1*   National Health Insurance. Terms of service for insurance practitioners.Remuneration.    The Minister offered to calculate the remunera-tion of insurance doctors on the basis of an 11s. Od. capitation fee;    this offer was rejected and a request made that the matter should be referred to arbitration.   The Minister assented to this after consultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.   The Board of Arbitrators has been appointed and their decision, to operate from the 1st April, 1920, will shortly be given.    In the meantime the fee of lls. Od. has been accepted as from 1st January last.    (Subsequent to the period, viz.   the month of February,   to which this Report refers,   i.e. on the 5th March,   the Arbitrators issued their Award.   The amount awarded was lls. oi&apos;&apos; - the amount offered by the Government.)General Co; litions of Service      The conditions of service embodied in the new Medical Benefit regulations which have now been formally made, have been notified to insurance doctors throughout the country and generally accepted.   The number of resignations from the panel from various causes is well under one per cent.2.   Rentfiction^Aots,    A Committee, with the Marquess of Salisbury as Chairman,&apos; has been appointed to consider the operation of these Acts and to advise what steps should be
taken to extend,   continue or amend them.3*   Representation of the People Act. - Expenses of Registration. The Committee appointed last December to enquire into the scales of payment for the registration of electors and to advise as to possible economies,   have reported to the Treasury.4.   Poor Law, . The quarterly return of cases of persons suffering from clinically well-defined delirium tremens admitted to poor law institutions shows a further increase in the number of males but a decrease in the number of females.   This return is obtained at the request of the central Control Board.    The returns are summarised in the following table *-Males. Females. Quarter ended 31.3.19.                    &quot;&quot; IT&quot;&quot; IT30,6,19. 45 1030,9.19. 82 2431.12.19. 95 155*   National Relief Fund., The process of winding up the local machinery created to administer the National Relief Fund during the War is being delayed, particularly, by staff difficulties in the local offices.   Nevertheless, in all but 55 cases,   the Local Representative Committees have been definitely wound up, have closed their accounts, and have submitted audited statements which have been found satisfao-tory.

</content>
</cab>
