<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/101/0 images: 213-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MINISTRY  OF   FOOD.SECRET. 8P.   940     )Report for Month ending 15th March 1920.Total imports of the principal foods and feeding stuffs in February did not maintain the high level reached in the first month of the year. The decrease is accounted for by the fall in arrivals of cereals, especially wheat and flour. Stocks of the latter now represent about 10 weeks&apos; supply. Stocks of rice remain notably low. Imports of fresh meat were again very heavy and the quantity in store created a new record of 147,000 tons. At the present rate of total consumption arid with prospective home supplies, this represents about 10 to 11 weeks&apos; supply of imported meat. In spite of a fall of over one-third in the net imports of bacon and hams as compared with the preceding month, these were still sufficient to allow of the addition of over -11,000 tons to stocks in store during February. Movements in the stocks of butter, cheese and sugar were small, but they were all in an upward direction. Stocks of tea, coffee and cocoa remain large in spite of decreases in the two first named.There are no marked movements in consumption to record. That of flour remains approximately at the level of a year ago. The estimated weekly consumption of butcher&apos;s meat by civilians in Great Britain during February was 28,400 tons, or 16,000 tons of home-grown and 12,400 tons of imported meat. The latter has increased with the seasonal decline in home supplies, but the upward movement of the total, though steady, shows a relatively small response to reductions in the price of imported supplies.The statistics collected by the Ministry of Labour as on March 1st again show a slight decrease in the average retail food prices. The percentage increase on July lV)14 fell from 134*9 on February 1st to 133*2 on March 1st. -The principal decreases were in fish 7*1 per cent., milk 1&apos;6 per cent., and eggs 23 per cent.; the principal increases were in potatoes 8*3 per cent., margarine 4 per cent., and butter, both fresh and salt, 11*5 per cent. Although the decreases outbalance the increases, prices have fallen only in those commodities which are affected seasonally. The principal increases nave been enumerated above, but several other foods have risen to a very small extent, insignificant in detail, but indicating in total a general trend.Regarding wholesale prices in February, cereals remained steady. There was no movement in bacon, cheese, or sugar, but imported (controlled) butter rose from 270s. 8d. to 287s. per cwt., and tea, both Indian and Ceylon, rose Id. per lb. Oilseed prices again rose, and the downward trend of oilseed cake prices continued. Scotch oatmeal remained at 35L per ton.a (33)10443 Pkl7 145 3/20 BAS
Table A.-Summary for February.				Stock, March 1st.			Stock, February 1st.		Home Production.			Commodity.		Net Imports.		Quantity.	.N umber of Weeks&apos; Supply.		Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Wks.	Days.Wheat (including flour) (a) -	1,596,000	358,000	 -	1,428,000	10	barley (a) -	654,000	34,000	 	543,000	15	 Oats (a).....	1,328,000	16,000	 	975,000	9	3Maize.....	48,000	112,000	 	60,000	2	1Rice -     -      -	32,000	2,000	 	34,000	8	3Butchers&apos; meat ....	142,000 65,700	71,800	72,600	147,000	5	2Bacon and hams		32,500	8,000	77,100	7	5Lard -	18,800	5,000	700	14,800	5	butter     -     -	12,000	9,000	3,000	12,400	8	margarine -     -     -     -	3,300	4,100	23,200	3,600	 	cheese     -      -	11,400	10,500	1,000	12,300	4	4Sugar      -	286,000	122,000	 	290,000	12	 Tea -     -      -     -	106,400	9,600		99,600	30	1Coffee      -.....	35,000	500	 	34,200	68	 Cocoa	42,900	9,200	 	47,700	41	 Oilseeds, &amp;c.     -	376,000	108,000	 	348,400	11	2Oilcake and meal      ...	225,400	20,000	90,000	225,900	9	-(a) Including stocks on farms.Table B. Weekly Consumption of Flour and Butchers&apos; Meat in theUnited Kingdom.[The figures are based upon quantities of imported food-stuffs released for consumption, plus estimated home production.]Flour.Butchers&apos; Meat.Army demands from U.K. Stocks and SupplyFebruary 1920     -     -     -     .-For Civilian Consumption : a verage for 4 weeks ended : March 29th - -      -April 26th  -May 24th - ; ., -June 21st -     -     -July 19th.....August 16th -     -     -September 13th   -October 11th       -     -November 8th     -     -      -     -December 6th January 3rd -      -31stFebruary 7th        -      - :14th      .-     -     -21st      &apos; -  - -        ......-28th -    - ... -Tons. 1,00099,900	24,90085,100	25,800102,700	27,400	25,90097,800	26,60099,000	27,000103,600	25,300103,700	28,500101,800	&apos;    28,600100,400	28,60090,900	28,000100,400	29,00097,100	29,10095,300	29,400i 96,900	30,200101,400	.29,900Tons. 1,000
Approximate Date.Commodity.								Nov. 1st,	May 1st,	Aug. 1st.	Nov. 1st,	Jan. 1st,	Feb. 1st.	March 1st,	1918.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1920.	1920	1920.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.Wheat (including flour)	979,000	494,000	605,000	348,000	293,000	312,000	310,000Oats.....	57,000	133,000	99,000	62,000	44,000	16,000	6,000Maize ------	12,000	29,000	8,000	9,000	3,000	 	2,000Rice.....	155,000	130,000	70,000	19,000	11,000	9,000	6,000Sugar -	414,000	317,000	285,000	131,000	144,000	126,000	152,000Butter       ....	6,600	19,500	16,900	12,900	7,900	9,700	14,800Lard.....	23,600	10,700	3,400	28,000	16,700	14,000	10,000Cheese      -	25,200	7,600	6,600	20,600	19,500	15,300	13,000Frozen meat      ...	33,300	21,400	26,700	44,900	62,200	47,000	34,500Bacon and hams -	40,000	23,700	1,300	52,000	45,000	80,000	56,000Tea.....	34,000	39,000	12,200	1,900	300	100	.   200* Inclusive in certain cases of quantities on boats arrived, but not yet discharged.jTable D. Percentage Increase in Retail Food Prices in the United Kingdom, at each of the Undermentioned Dates, as compared with&quot;Normal Prices in July 1914.&quot;[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]	Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.										Article.												1st Jan.	1st July	1st Jan.	1st July	1st Nov.	1st Jan.	1st July	1st Nov.	1st Jan.	1st Feb.	1st Men.	1917.	1917.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1920.	1920.	1920.Beef :-											British Ribs	64-2	96-1	80&apos;-5	84-8	102-7	102-4	84-4	110-0	110-1	110-2	110-5Thin flank -	83-5	132-2	100-9	98-2	126-2	125-9	98-7	126-9	127-1	127-3	127-5Chilled or frozen 											Ribs -    -	85-4	119-6	116-4	147-9	175-4	175-4	120-3	143-8	143-8	116-2	116-2Thin flank    -	101-2	156-5	137-3	164-7	206-5	206-5	122-9	143-8	&apos;143-8	102-0	102-0Mutton : 											British Legs   -	58-7	100-0	76-8	85-5	102-3	102-3	84-9	103-8	103-9	104-1	104-breast	84-2	142-2	92-5	80-8	106 5	106-2	78-8	107-6	107-8	107-9	108-1Frozen Legs   -	86-4	134-4	134-0	176-5	205-6	205-6	147-4	161-9	132-8	132-8	132-8Breast	122-0	190-8	161-8	168-5	217-4	217-4	119-7	144-1	95-3	95-3	95-3Bacon. streaky*	56-3	76-4	138-7	138-3	141-7	141-1	142-8	154-4	155-6	155-9	155-9Fish    -	131-1	127-1	195-9	189-7	167-4	166-3	132-8	139-9	128-4	130-0	113-2Flour   -	88-5	109-3	51-8	52-1	52-2	52-3	51-7	52-0	52-1	52-2	52-4Bread   -	73-3	100-3	54-4	54-5	54-8	54-9	55-2	61-8	62-3	62-5	62-6Tea     -     -	50-9	73-7	98-2	73-3	73-3	73-3	65-1	78-3	86-6	87-3	89-sugar, granulated -	170-0	187-7	189-3	240-3	241-3	241-3	242-1	242-5	289-7	290-2	290-4Milk    -	56-6	59-7	99-5	77-3	141-0	153-9	111-1	lyn-o	212-2	201-8	197-0Potatoes	121-7	144-3	37-1	57-1	59-3	57-3	83-8	112-8	125-8	141-9	162-margarine	25-0	73-5	65-9	68-8	97-0	68-8	82-4	85-0	85-0	85-4	92-8Butter, fresh -*	72-9	64-7	103-4	97-3	106-8	107-4	106-5	108-8	109-7	123-4	149-2Butter, salt   -	70-6	65-3	105-4	102-4	112-3	112-6	111-6	114-2	115-2	129-1	155-cheese, Canadian or											U.S.*	74-8	108-0	91-2	93-6	130-2	130-3	106-5	108-1	122-0	129-7	129-6Eggs, fresh   -	175-0	95-3	242-1	248-3	412-1	347-2	231-1	332-1	341-4	328-9	230-1* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative.Table C. Ministerial Stocks in the United Kingdom/&apos;

</content>
</cab>
