<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/101/0 images: 277-283</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DftOlMflT IS THE PROPERTY Qg HIS BRITAMIO MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.) SECRET.O.P,948i0 A B I g IS T.TREATY   OF   PS APE   WITH   TURKEY. Artloles relative to Egypt, Sudan and Cyprus .*   copy of letter f rom Sir M. hankey to the Chairman, drafting committee.(Circulated for information.)2, Whitehall Gardens,London,    S.W.1.25th Maroh, 1920.Sir,I am direoted by Mr. Lloyd George to forward, foT the Information of the Drafting Committee, Artioles relating to Egypt, the Sudan and Cyprus, which were approved hy the Confer-enoe of Ambassadors and Foroign Ministers now meeting at the Foreign Offioe in London on March 23rd.    These Clauses were accepted hy the French Delegation ad referendum to Paris.I am direoted to draw the attention of the Drafting Committee to article 4 which is somewhat similar to Article 49 of the Economic Clauses.    The Conference of Ambassadors and Foreign Ministers desire that the Drafting Committee should ensure that the two chapters of the Treaty are harmonised in this respeot.As regards Article 5, $he suggestion was made thatthis provision might better be included in the NationalityClauses.   In support of this it was urged that a principleonoe laid down in the Treaty was not usually repeated in orderto make a particular section of it self sufficing;   for.in-stanoe it was not considered neoessary to re-state this prin-ciple in the case of Syria or Armenia.     On the other hand,the/
the desirability was urged of making the Clauses regarding Egypt.as complete as possible and in this oonneotion it was pointed out that the Eoonomio Chapter recognised that the oase of Egypt was a speoial oase.The conclusion of the Council of Ambassadors and Foreign Ministers was to leave the matter to the Drafting Committee.Articles 11 and 13 were reserved by the French Delegation pending, immediate reference to Paris and the Prenflh Delegation hoped that if no  .alteratl on was necessary a reply would jfeje given within twenty-four hours.    flo such reply has been received and consequently these Articles may be considered to stand, subject to the general acceptance by the French Delegation ad referendum to Paris.Finally, I am further directed to request that the Drafting Committee will add to the Clauses relating to Cyprus a sentence to the effect that &quot;Ottoman subjects habitually ^resident in Cyprus &amp;ould ipso facto lose Ottoman and acquire British nationality&quot;.I have the honour to be, Sir, Yours obedient Servant,(Sgd) M. P. A. HAMEY.     &apos;British Secretary.
2L.J..111.MEMORANDUM BY BRITISH DELEGATION, PROPOSING ARTICLES TO BE INSERTED IN THE TURKISH TREATY&quot;&apos; RELATIVE TO EGYPT,, SUDAN AND CYPRUS *CHAPTER .....W      EgyptMarginal Motes.C&amp;jriain corrections otfi* made by London Conference, df .23.3.20,. (I.CP.83).Article A* to be harmonised with Article 49 of the Economic Clauses.Turkey renounces all rights and title in or over Egypt.     This renunciation shall take effect as from November 5th, 1914. Turkey declares that in conformity with the action taken by the Allied-Powers she recog-recognises the Protectorate proclaimed over Egypt by Great Britain on December 18, 1914,,2.   Ottoman subjects habitually resident in Egypt on December 18, 1914, will aquire Egyptian nationality ipso facto and will lose their Ottoman nationality, except that if at that date such persons were temporarily absent from,, and have not since that date returned to,,Egypt they will not acquire Egyptian nationality without a speoial authorisation from the Egyptian Government.3.   Ottoman subjects who became resident in Egypt after December.18, 1914, and are habitually resident there at the date of the ooming into force of the present Treaty may claim Egyptian nationality, but such olaim may in individual cases be refused by the com-petent Egyptian authority.4.   For all purposes connected with the present Treaty, Egyptian nationals will rankas/
as Allied ^nationals, ana Egypt will be    248regarded as allied territory.5.   Within a period of one year afterthe coming into force of the presentAttention of Drafting    Treaty persons over 18 years of age ac-Oommittee to questionwhether this provision   quiring or entitled to claim Egyptian&apos; should not oome in the nationality Glauses.      nationality under the provisions of On the other hand,caseof Egypt is a special    Artloles 2 and 3, will he entitled to opt one and Glauses regard-ing Egypt should be as   for Turkish nationality, or in case they complete as possible.differ in race from the majority of the population of Egypt they will within the same period be entitled to opt for the nationality of any State to which Turkish territory is transferred, if the majority of the population of that State is of the same race as the person exercising the right to opt.Option by a husband covers a wife and option by parents covers their children under 18 years of age.Persons vho have exercised the above right to opt must, except where authorised to continue to reside in Egypt, transfer their place of residence to the State for which they have opted.    They will be en-titled to rretain their immovable property in Egypt and may carry with them their . movable property of every description. Ho export or import duties or charges may be imposed upon them in connection with the removal of such property.6.   The Egyptian Government shall have complete liberty of aotion in regulate-ing the status of Ottoman subjects in Egypt and the conditions under whioh they may4 - establish/
establish themselves in the territory.7.   Egyptian nationals shall be -entitled-wh^zT abroad to the diplomatio protection of Great Britain.8.   Egyptian goods entering Turkey shall en-joy the treatment accorded to British goods.9.   The Powers conferred upon His Imperial Majesty the Sultan by the Convention signed at Constantinople on October 89th, 1888, relating to the free navigation of the Suez Canal, are trans-ferred to the Government of His Britannic Majesty.10.   All property and possessions in Egypt belonging to the Turkish Government pass to the Egyptian Government without payment.All movable and immovable property in Egypt belonging to Turkish nationals (who do not acquire Egyptian nationality) shall bo dealt with in . accordance with Part 49 (Economic Clauses) of the present Treaty.11. Turkey renounces all claim to the tribute formerly paid by Egypt.Great Britain undertakes to relieve Turkey ofall liability in respect of the Turkish loans securedon the Egyptian tribute.    These loans are:-The guaranteed loan of 1855The loan of 1894 representing the convertedloans of 1854 and 1871. The loan of 1391 representing the convertedloan of 1877.served by The sums which the Khedives of Egypt have from men Delegatesiding referenoe    time to time undertaken to pay over to the houses Paris.by whom these loans were issued will be applied as heretofore to the interest and the sinking funds of the loans of 1894 and 1891 until the final extino-tion of those loans.    The Govermisnt of Egypt willalso/
1 1also continue to apply the sura hlttonrto^poJLfr^tho interest on the guaranteed loan of 1855.    Upontho extinction of these loans of 1894, 1891 and 1855,      jall liability on the part of the Egyptian Governmentarising out of the tribute formerly paid by egypt to Turkey will&apos;cease.The payment of the interest upon tho loan of 1868 having been guaranteed by the Governments of Great Britain and France, the High Contracting Parties take note that the Government of His Britannic Majesty agrees to indemnify the Government of the French Republic against the payment of any sums in respect of such interest, and thereby relieves that Government of ali liability under its guarantee.12.   To safeguard the position of the holders of loans issued by the Egyptian Government, Great Britain declares that, in the event of any default by the Government of Egypt in tho payment of the annuity of the Guaranteed Debt, or of the interest on tho Privi-leged or Unified Debts, she will take the measures necessary to restore financial equilibrium in Egypt, and to protect the interests of the bondholders of the Egyptian Public Debt.13.   The Commission of the Egyptian Public Debt being no longer required for the protection of the--holders of Egyptian&apos;Debt in view of the declaration made by His Britannic Majesty&quot;&apos;s Government in the pfecoding article, the Eigh Contracting Parties agree to the repeal, or to tho modification of such extent as the Egyptian Governs nt may think desirable, of the decree issued by His Highness the Khedive on the 28th November 1904.14.   The Government of His Britannic Majestyagreo in view of the altered political status of egypt to relieve the Governments of Germany, Austria,France,Italy, KusBia anfl Tur&apos; oy of any liability under theoh! ig at ions/
Whitehall Gardens, S*W*1.26th March, 1920.obli trbiona&apos;lYk^ of those coiiirtrtl.ee- -contracted in respoct of the interest- ar.d...si.nJr.lrg fund on the loan of 9, COO,-COO lo raised by the Egyptian Government in 1885 in accordance with the terms of the Convention signed at London on the 18th March, 1885, .as modified by the Convention of the  5th July of that year.    The Governrrant of His Britannic Majesty for their part reaffirm their obligations to guarantee the regular payment of the annuity of 315,000 1. assigned to tho service of the above loan.(b) Soudan.1.   The High Contracting Parties declare that they have taken note of the Convention between the Government of His Britannic Majesty and the Egyptian Government defining the status and regulating the administration of the Soudan signed on January 19th, 1899, as amended by the supplementary convention relating to :the town of Soualln signed on July 10th, 1899.2.   Soudanese shall be entitled when in foreign oountri&amp;3 to the diplomatic protection of   Eis Britannic Majesty,(o) Cypruso: 1.   Tho High Contracting Parties recognise theentence to be annexation of Cyprus proclaimed by the Government ed to the effeott Ottoman sub- of His Britannia Majesty on the 5th November, 1914. ... ts habituallyident in Cyprus Turkey renounces all rights and title over or relat-uld ipso-Eaoto i8 Ottoman and ing to-&apos;Cyprus,-including the right to tho tribute ui*e Britishionality. &quot; formerly paid by that island to the Sultan,

</content>
</cab>
