<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/101/0 images: 507-508</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THB PROPERTY OP, HIS. BRIT AMI 0 MAJESTY&apos;secret, C.P.992.CABINET.TREATY OP PEACE WITH TUP KEY.JUDICIAL RgPQRM IN ifitiliix.6opy of letter from Sir Maurice Henkey to the Chairman, Drafting Committee.kmwhw tttmwLrimm*\-*m- *anjpoa(Circulated for information ).LONDON, 29th March, 1920.Sir,I am directed to enclose for the information of the drafting Committee two draft articles on the subjeot of judicialreform in Turkey which wer^e considered by the Conference of ambassadors and Foreign Ministers now meeting at the Foreign office in London on Saturday, March 27th, together with a oopy of theot     minutes of the Conference on this subject (l.C.P.87, Minute 3)*. pro-oed. I am directed to request that the Drafting Committee v/illasuse these articles as amended by the minutes,(i.s./corrected in the attached copy) as the basis of appropriate articles for inclusion in the Treaty of Peace with Turkey.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Sgd.) H.P.A.hankey,British Secretary.The Chairman,Drafting Committee of the Peace Conference
SECRET. A.J j.29,Memorandum by the British Belogntion for oubmiaoion to Council of Foreign Ministers and Ambassadors,6The British Delegation have the honour to recommend tho following draft articles for insertion in the Turkish treaty at tho place considered appropriate by the Drafting Committee j&quot;1, Une Commission de quatre membree, nommes par la jftrande Brotagne, la Franco, Ultslie eVJLe .J  on. sera otablie dans lesft ? *six mois apros la mice en vigueur du present traitef pourprepsrer un projet de reforms judiciare de nature a rem:olaoer*leL present regime des capitulations en motiere judiciairec      La Commission aura toute competence pour recommander, g&apos;11 &apos; y. a lieuet apres consultation avec le gouvernement ottoman, 1? adoption d&apos;unIregime judioia&amp;e soit mixte, soit unifiedCe projet sera soumis oux gouvernements de dites Puissances et entrero on vigueur des qu?il a ete approuve par euxc        LaTurquie s? engage a 1*avarice a accepter le projet oinsi approuve0,;,2.   La Turquie s! engage a accepter tcute deoision prise par un juge ou (tribunal Allie Biegeant en Turquie depuis le 31 Octobre, 1918, jusqu&apos;a la mise en vigueur du nouvcav Gy&amp;temo judiciare&quot;.(Note:-   Alterations are underlined).

</content>
</cab>
