<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/51/0 images: 133-146</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJ5STY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)COPY NO.cabinet meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10 Downing Street,S.E.I., Thursday, December 3rd,  1925, at 11.30 A.M.1. IRISH &quot;SITUATION. (IF REQUIRED)2. IRAQ.(Reference Cabinet 54(25) Conclusion l) .Report of Cabinet Committee,(CP. 502(25)      -     circulated herewi3, AIR FORCE EXPANSION FOR HOME DEFENCE.(Reference Cabinet 52(25) Conclusion 17).Report of Cabinet Committee,4&apos; REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.Note by the Secretary covering Proceedings of.   the CojTtmittee of Imperial Defence,(CP. 504(25)      -     circulated herewith).5. TITHE BILL.Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor,(CP. 505(25)      -     circulated herewith).Note by the Secretary covering Proceedings ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence,(CP. 455(25)      -      already circulated).V. AIR RAIDS PRECAUTIONS.   &apos;Note by the Secretary covering Proceedings ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence,(CP. 456(25)      -     already circulated).AGENDA,(C498(25)circulated herewith).6. FOOD SUPPLY IN TIME OF WAR.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.30th November, 1925.(Signed)  M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.
mOlMBHT IS the PROPERTY OF HIS BHITANHIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) ./COPY NO.CABINET   57(25)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of tho Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on THURSDAY,&apos;DECEMBER 3rd, 1925, at Ho30 A.M.    .PRESENT: -Tho Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.The Bight Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain,K.G.,M.P,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.!Fhe Earl of Balfour, K.G.,0.M.,lord President of the Council.jibe Eight Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.H..M.P.,Chancellor of the Exohequor.[The Right Hon.L.8. Amery, M.P., secretary of State for Dominion affairs and Seoretary of State fortbo Colonies..3 Right Hon.Kie Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for India.I&amp;e Right Hon.W.C. Bridgemaa, M.P.,First lord of the Admiralty.(The Right Hon. .Nevillo Chamhorlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.h Rigbt Hon.Sir Arthur St oel-Ma it land, Bart.,, Minister of Labour.(In tho Chair).The Right Hon.Yisoount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,KoG.,G.C.V.0* tC.B.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hloks,Bart.,M.P., Seoretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Bight Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bart. .G.B.E. ,M.P., Sooretaryof State for War.Tho Hight Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart.,C.M.G.,M.P., Seoretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.B. ,M..C ,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.W0 Guinness, D.S.0..M.P.,Minister of Agrioulture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E., first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon. Sir Douglas Hogg,K.C.,M.P., Attorney-General.M.J?.A. Hankoy, G.C.BSocretary.
19 9i d JPRESS OOM- 1.    The attention of the Cabinet was drawn towrWIQ.UT?S .the issue of an official Press Communique in regard(Previous       to the conversations between the representa-Heference:Cabinet 59   fives of the British Cabinet and Irish representa-(24) , Con-elusion 1     tives on the previous day.    It was pointed out that(c).)it was not customary to issue the names of ministers who were members of Cabinet Committees, and that inthe present instance some personal embarrassmenthad been occasioned by the issue of the names.The Prime Minister said that when he himself had seen representatives of the Irish Governmenthe had usually caused a communique to be Issued inorder to forestall speculation in the Press as towhat had occurred, and no doubt this precedent hadbeen followed on the pres.ent occasion.    He thought itwould be better in future if the Ministers presentwere consulted before a communique was issued.
tlSH 20    The attention o^ the Cabinet was drawn to^IONVan article in &quot;The Daily Mail&quot; which gave theimpression of having been based on informationnee:t 56 obtained of the results of the Cabinet Meeting onthe previous evening, which had terminated at about 7-45.rE OP In this connection the Prims Minister1ATI0N 0reported that information had come to him to theusnee: effect that on the previovrs- evening &quot;The Morningt 50Con- Post&quot; had obtained information as to what had beenn 5.)decided at the Cabinet, and his Private Secretary(Sir Ronald Wsterhouse) had conveyed a warning tothe effect that if the newspaper believed itselfto be in possession of information, it was highly understandable that it should be published.JERS The Home Secretary drew attention to item 3TEDTHFRN of the Agreement reached with Sir James Oraig andro.the representatives of the Irish Free State, vis.:-That the cases of prisoners convictedin Northern Ireland in respect of offences during the period of distufc-ance shall be reviewed by the BritishGovernment, whose decision in eachcase shall be accepted by theGovernment of Northern Ireland.He hoped that if this was to be embodied in any agreement it would be worded differently,,so asto make clear that the question would be referredto the&apos; Ho^e Secretary to consider whether theexercise of the Royal Prerogative was desirable inany partic\ilar cases.    It was also for considera-tion whether,  in the discharge of this duty, theHome Secretary should not be assisted by two ofhis colleagues.-&apos;  The Chancellor of the Exchequer explainedthat this matter would not be dealt with in any agreement;    it would probably be announced a little
id dlater than the Agrean-ent, by Sir James Craig inhis own Parliament.The Prime Minister added that if any announce-ment was to be made here on this matter the HomeSecretary ought to be consulted.The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed hiscolleagues that the representatives of the IrishFree State, whom he had informed on the previous evening, had warmly welcomed the decision of theCabinet.   Sir James Craig, whom, he had informed thesame morning, had also welcomed it with enthusiasmand had stated that it would enable him greatly toreduce the requests for financial relief which hewould have had to make if the Commission^ Award hadbeen adopted.    Sir James intended to pay a publictribute to the statesmanlike attitude of the BritishGovernment.Progress was now being made with the details ofthe Agreement and of the financial arrangements, ofwhich Mr Churchill gave some particulars.    The IrishFree State Ministers considered that legislationmust be introduced at once in the Bail, and Sir james craig intended to pass the necessary resolutionsthrough his Parliament.    If the Parliamentary time-table permitted, it would be desirable immediately to introduce legislation here also.    The irish minister of Finance was expected on the following day. &quot;At the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s request,the Cabinet agreed - That the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries should, assist the Chancellorof the Exchequer in the financialnegot negotiations .
The Prime Minister said that he had arranged to see the Irish Boundary Commission the same afternoon at 4-15.The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that sir James Craig hoped it might be found possiblenever to publish the projected Award of the IrishBoundary Commission.
3 .    The Secretary -of - State-for&apos; Foreign.-affairs read to his colleagues a letter--from Sir-CharlesVahe^ield offering to defray the coat.of a picture of the signing of the Treaty.of Locarno, and suggesting that Sir William Orpen should be invitedto undertake the task, although Sir CharlesWake fie Id was willing to leave this point toSir Austen Chamberlain&apos;s discretion.The Cabinet authorised the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs toaccept Sir Charles&quot;Wakefield&apos;s offer.
4,   The Cabinet had before them a Report by theCabinet Committee appointed at a previous Meeting,containing the terms of a statement to be made inParliament, which should also be used by theSecretary of State for the Colonies as instructions for his guidance when representing the government at the  Council of the League of nations.    TheReport was not unanimous on the question whetherthe statement should be made to Parliament beforethe Meeting of the Council of the League or at some later date (Paper C.P.-502 (,2b)) s   In additionthey had before them, a Memorandum, by the Secretaryof State for War, covering a Note by the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff on the subject of themilitary oltuation in Iraq (Paper CP.-513 (25)),and a statement circulated by the Secretary ofState for the Colonies on the subject of Britishcommitments in regard to  Iraq (Paper 0.F.-499 (25)).The Secretary of State for-Foreign affairs read to the Cabinet telegram No.134 of December 1st.from Sir R, Lindsay, the British Ambassador atConstantinople, containing the gist of a Reportfrom Mr Deeper, who had Just returned from Angora,regarding the critical state of this question, atthat Capital.    Allusion was also made to a secondtelegram, from Sir R. Lindsay, No,133,  suggestingcertain possible concessions in regard to theKurdish parts of Iraq. &apos;  -The suggestion was made that the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs should instruct hiaOffice to examine &apos;the possibility of any concessions which might be made to the Turks in the event of an award in our favour by the Council of the Leagueof Nations .
Tho Cabinet wore informed that 11. Briand had alreadyspoken seriously ts tho Turkish Ambassador in Paris as tothe oonaequenoos of any Turkish aggression.Comment was made on the discrepancies between the newMemorandum of the Chief of tho Imperial General Staff andthe Report of the Chiefs of Staff 3ub-Ccmm.ittee, which lord cavan had signed two months ago (C.I.D. Paper No.632-B).The suggestion was made that if tho Chiefs of Staff Committeewore going to oensider this question they should be askodt*     jjoiT iu miag tho effect on the garrisens ofEgypt and Palestine if we were to withdraw rapidly from Iraq,Tho Cabinet agreed -fa) That the Committee of Chiefs of staff should be assemblod at onoo to considorthe Memorandum by the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff ciroulated with CP,-499(25),: and that- they should be instructod te statowhether they wish to modify tho advice givonin their previous Report (G.I.D. Paper n0.632-B),and, in this event, to give their reasons infull;   that they should also consult Sir HenryDobbs, the High Commissioner of Iraq, who Isat present in London;    and that a Report shouldbe transmitted te the Committee of ImperialDefence, whoso Conclusions thereon shouldthon be considered by the Cabinet:(Arrangement3 were made for aMeeting of tho Chiefs of staff committee on the same day,during the Cabinet Meeting.)(b) That tho Seoretary of State for Foreign affairs should have authority to send for the turkish ambassador and to point out to hin that if theTurks, in consequence of a possible adverseAward by tho Council of tho League of Nations,should advance on Mosul, they would find them-.selves in conflict not enly with Great Britainbut with the League of Nations alBO.    If theTurkish Ambassador repliod by asking whetherthe two Governments oould not roaoh an agree-neat he should, if he thought fit, be at liberty to intimate that ho had it in mind,in the event of a decision in our favour,to discuss with tho Turkish government whether anything oould be done to easetho situation for then;
(c) That the following alteration,propos ed by. Lord Cecil,  should bemade in the &quot;Terms of the statement to the House of Commons&quot; submitted bythe Cabinet Committee in CP.-502 (.25),viz:-^e last sentence to read asfollows:-&quot;They must be determined bythe Government of the dayif ever the case arises, inthe light of the then existingcircumstances, the general interests of world peace andof the Empire.&quot;(.N.B.    The words underlinedare new.)(d) That the Prime Minister should use theformula contained in CP.-502 (.25)(as amended) for a statement to bemade by him before the end of theParliamentary Session, but preferablynot much in advance of any opportunity which the House might be given fordebating the subject:(e) That the Secretary of State for theColonies, in repeating before theLeague of Nations the assurances givenby him to the Council of the Leaguewith regard to the renewal of thetreaty relationship with Iraq assatisfying the mandatory relationshipreoommended by the Commission of theLeague, should take for his guidancethe formula contained in the Reportof the Cabinet Committee (Paper C.F.-502 (25)) and incorporate it in hiestatement to the Council, insofar asthe points referred to in it might beraised.
5. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe&apos;Lord Chancellor pointing out that in his view the educational and other charities have a substantialgrievance under the Tithe Bill as at present drafted,and suggesting, if an amendment is moved.in the Houseof Lords in favour of the Colleges and Public schools and other charitable foundations, the Minister incharge of the Bill should be authorised to state thatthe point will-be further considered before theCommittee Stage (Paper C.P.-505 (35).)-, as well as aMemorandum, by the Secretary of State for War drawing attention to some of the difficulties involved inthis proposal (Paper 0,P.-509 (25)).The Cabinet agreed --(a) That any amendment In favour of.Colleges and Public Schools andother charitable foundations whichmight be put forward in the Houseof Lords should be dealt with ingeneral language by the government spokesman, who should be authorisedto state that the representations made would be carefully considered:(b) That a Cabinet Committee, composed as follows -The Lord Privy Seal,The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries(who would also represent theChancellor of the Exchequer),The Minister.of Health -should consider whether any plan couldbe devised to overcome the difficultywithout destroying the basis of TitheRant Charges.
6.   The Cabinet, bad before them the Report of aSub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial. X-efeno-e^--&quot;together with an extract from the draft Minutes ofthe 206th Meeting of the Committee of ImperialDefence containing the Committee&apos;s Conclusions(Paper CP-.-504 (.25)).Affairs,The Secretary of State for Foreign     / y whohad taken the Chair at the Meeting of the Committeeof Imperial Defence, stated that the Chief of theNaval Staff had objected to the proposal in Conclusion(ii; of the draft Minutes to the effect &quot;that GreatBritain would be ready at the proper moment tomake a proposal in regard to cruisers, etc&quot;After some discussion the Cabinet agreed -To approve the Conclusions of theCommittee of Imperial Defence (amended to meet the objections of the first sea Lord to draft Conclusion&apos; ii))whichare as follows!-(i) That the Report of the Sub-Committeeon Reduction and Limitation of Arrca-ments (O.T.R. Paper No.649-3) shouldbo forwarded to the Cabinet with ageneral expression of the Committee&apos;approval, and that, pending confirma-tion by the  Cabinet, the Chane ellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster should beauthorised to base his attitude atthe meeting of the Committee of theleague of Nations at Geneva thereon.(11) That the Chancellor of the Duchy of&apos; $Lancaster should, during the proceed-).ngs of the above Committee, keepQarefully In mind the suggestion ofthe Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs that the most hopeful methodh? bringing about limitation and reduction of armaments would be tofollow the Washington precedent:    that lord Cecil should have authority,  ifhe thought de sir able, &quot;&quot;to suggest thatdome great land Power might take theinitiative In regard to land and airarmament fi .(The words objected to by theChief of the&apos;Naval Staff havebeen omitted .)(iii)  That it woiald be undesirable for theLeague of Nations to approach the UnitedStates of America directly vith a viewto their participation in the League&apos;a
1 A 3enquiry Into red\iction and liroita-tion of armaments without firstascertaining informally whether a formal invitation.would be welcomed.That this informal sounding had best be done by the League itself through its own channels.   That the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster shcrald keepthe Foreign Office informed .of whatwas being done by the League with aview to appropriate action by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs:(iv) That the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should be authorisedto communicate the Report of the Sub-Committee on Reduction and Limitationof Armaments (C.I.D0 Paper No.649-B)to the Dominion Governments, and thatthe Secretary of State for india should be authorised to take similar action with regard to the Governmentof India If he so desired.
7.    The Cabinet had before them the Report ofa Committee appointed by the Cabinet to considerthe rate of Expansion of the Air Force for HomeDeferoe (Paper CoPo-4S8(25))*The Cabinet approved the aboveReport.2 Whitohall Gardens, S.V/.T.,lecembcs 3, 1925.-12-m

</content>
</cab>
