<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/49/3 images: 26-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT&quot;Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1945.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (45)3rd Conclusions.WAR CABINET 3 -(45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet war room on Tuesday, 9th January, 1945, at 5-30 p-m-Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, .M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of - State for DominionAffairs.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War;The Right Hon. Sir Stafforo Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The   Right Hon.Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade(Items 4-6).The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Town and country planning (Items 4-6).Lord   Cherwell,Secretariat:Sir Edward Brioges.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. W. S. Murrie,[29062-3]
WAR CABINET 3 (45).Contents. -Minute .No. Subject, \ page 1      Italian Claims against Germany........      ....      ....      172      Constitutional Policy in Malaya    ....      ............      188      Resettlement of Men released from the Armed Forces ....      19Gratuities, Prize Money and Prize Bounty.4      Distribution of Industry     ....      ....      ....      .....      ....      215      Press    ....      ....      ....      ........      ....      ....      ....      21Daily Worker&apos;s Request for Accrediting of a Correspondent toBritish Forces.Suggested T U.G. Deputation;6      Relaxation of Lighting Restrictions in the London Area       22
Italian Claims 1. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theagainst . Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (45) 3) on ItalianGermany,       claims against Germany.- In September, 1944s the Italian Government had asked whetherthey would be permitted to participate in the armistice with- Germany, We had consulted the United States and had said thatwe were not prepared to concern ourselves in any way with anyclaims that Italy might make against Germany. The United StatesGovernment, who felt that the subsequent Anglo-Americandeplafation about Italy made it more difficult to adopt an entirelynegative attitude in this matter, had how suggested that the ItalianGovernment should be invited to submit informally their views onthe surrender arrangements for Germany to the United States,United Kingdom and Soviet Governments. Subsequently the UnitedStates Government would submit the Italian claims to the european advisory Commission for scrutiny. It would, however, be made clear that we undertook no obligation^ towards the Italians by accepting their claims for examination.The treatment proposed &quot;for Italy, though more favourable thanthat proposed for non-European United Nations Governments, wasa good deal less favourable than that being accorded to our european Allies. The fact that Italy had been ravaged by Germanyand had lost great numbers of prisoners to Germany was an argument for the American proposal. In these circumstances, andsubject to the understanding that the Soviet Government and theFrench Provisional Government should be informed of this exchangewith the Italian Government and that the French ProvisionalGovernment should be among those to whom the Italian Governmentshould communicate their views concerning the surrender arrange-ments for Germany, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairsadvised that no harm would be done by accepting the United states proposals. .The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theinitiative in regard to these proposals had come from &quot;the UnitedStates. He was/not greatly attracted by them, but he did not think.. (   that any harm would result from allowing the Italians to state their views. ^ .In the ensuing discussion the following points were made : -(a) There was general agreement that Italy should be entitled tothe return of any works of art that had been removed from Italian* territory.(b) Doubt was, however, expressed as to the wisdom of accepting the United States proposal. On her record in this war,Italy had no claim to special consideration. 1 While it was onlysuggested that Italy should be given an opportunity to formulateclaims, she might, nevertheless, be encouraged to think that thoseclaims would,be accepted. If accepted, they would, of course, haveto rank against whatever reparations we could hope to secure fromGermany, and to that.extent might reduce the amount for divisionamong the United Nations.(c) Moreover, the object of this move might well be to lead upto the recognition of Italy as an ally.(d) On the other hand, it was urged that the War Cabinet -should only reject the American proposal on grounds on which wewere determined to stand.   In the view of the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs it would be very undesirable to oppose theproposal now, and later to concede it under pressure.(e) The initiative in this matter might well come from president Roosevelt. No commitment was involved, and any Italianclaim that might be put in should unquestionably rank after any claim put in by a member of the United Nations.(/) Italy would be a claimant for relief for a very long timeahead.   We hoped that the United States would bear as high as&quot;-- possible a proportion of the cost of such relief, thereby reducingthe charge on this country.  This might be more difficult to secureif we opposed the United States on proposals of minor importance[29062-3] B 2
After further discussion the Prime Minister said that therewas general agreement, first, that Italy was entitled to the return of any works of art that had been removed from her territory;secondly, that any claims that she might put in must rank at the bottom of the list below any claims by any member of the united nations, On the main issue there was, however, clearly somedifference of view, and he suggested that the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should consider the matter further and again bring it before the War Cabinet if, on further consideration, he concluded that in the interests of general relations with the United States,their proposal should be accepted.The War Cabinet-Accepted the Prime Minister &apos;s proposal at. &quot; X.&quot;Constitutional 2. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thePolicy In Lord President of the Council (W.P. (44) 762) on ConstitutionalMalaya. Policy in Malaya.(Previous At their meeting on the 31st May, 1944, the War Cabinet had reference: approved a directive on policy in Malaya to the authoritiesW.M.(44)70th responsible for planning for the civil administration of Malaya on conclusions, liberation, on the understanding that no publicity should be givenMinute 3.)      to the policies contained therein.The disadvantages of complete secrecy in this matter were becoming more marked as time went on. The Supreme allied commander, South-East Asia, had represented to the Secretary ofState for the Colonies the importance of making our future plansknown to the people whom they would affect, and thought the timefor this was now ripe. Representations had &quot;also been receivedfrom the authorities engaged in political warfare.The Secretary of State for the Colonies, while not convincedthat the time had come for our plans to be divulged in full, sawadvantage in the distribution        N(i) to selected circles, of a brOad statement of the fundamentalproblems in Malaya which bore directly on the political,administrative and economic future of the country;(ii) to restricted circles which could guide and influencethought and discussion on the subject; of a brief state-ment, not for publication, and purely for backgrounduse, setting out the main features of our proposed p&quot;policy.The Committee on Malaya and Borneo supported the proposalsof the Secretary of State for the Colonies and recommended the, statements proposed by him (drafts of which were attached toW.P. (44) 762) for the approval of the War Cabinet. These state-ments, as explained by the Lord President of the Council, involvedno departure from the policy already approved by the War Cabinet,which, moreover, contemplated an increase in British control.In discussion, it was urged that the distribution proposed forthe proposed statements gave the worst of both worlds. On the onehand we had not the advantage which would result from,fullpublicity for a settled policy on which we were prepared to stand.On the other hand, with so large a distribution, leakage might well, result.   It I would then be asked why we&apos; had issued this statementonly as a confidential document. (This applied in particular to annex II.) It was also urged that the statements, as at presentdrafted, would not be satisfactory as a basis for a declaration ofpolicy if destined to become public since they would inevitably giverise to certain questions to which no answers&apos; were afforded.The War Cabinet-Postponed a decision on the proposals in W.P. (44) 762until after the return of the Secretary of State for theColonies.
resettlement of men released fromthe armed forces.Gratuities,Prize money and PrizeBounty.(previous reference :W.M. (44) 128thConclusions,Minute 4.)3.   The War Cabinet had before them %(i) a memorandum by the Minister of Labour and NationalService (W.P. (44) 602) setting out comprehensively thevarious schemes for the resettlement of men released from the Forces;        &apos; / ..(ii) a memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer(W.P. (44) 700) on the question of the amount of wargratuity for the Armed Forces; and(iii) a memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty(W.P. (44) 711) on the subject of prize money and prizebounty. &apos;The War Cabinet considered first the amount of the wargratuity for the armed Forces.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that he had agreed with the Service. Ministers and the Secretary of State for India onthe general principles to be followed in calculating the gratuitybut, as shown in the Appendix to W.P. (44) 700, it had not beenpossible to reach agreement on the scales. The scale proposed bythe Service Ministers involved an expenditure of the order of 300 millions, whereas his own proposal was estimated to cost about 200 millions. The Service Ministers recognised that the totalprovision made for ex-Servicemen would be generous, but they believed that there would be a tendency, both in Parliament and elsewhere, to consider the amount of the war gratuity in isolation,and to criticise it on the grounds that it was inadequate. a subsidiary point of difference was that, in his view, the differentialof 20s. a month for the rate of highest other rank and the lowestcommissioned rank in the scale proposed by the Service Ministersappeared to be excessive. &quot; &quot;In discussion it was pointed out in favour of the scale proposedby the Service Ministers that the minimum under the Treasuryscale was equivalent to a payment of 4d. per day to a private foreach day tof war service. There was likely to be strong criticism of this amount both in Parliament and through the British Legion,and there was a serious risk that the Government would, in theend, have to yield to pressure. If the Service Departments&apos; proposal,which was equivalent to payment of 6d. per day, were&quot; adopted,it would be easier to stand firm. Officers&apos; gratuities at the end ofthe last war had been substantially higher than those proposed andthe gratuities payable to other ranks had been roughly on theTreasury scale. Regard should be had to the expenses which members, of the Forces would have to incur on release in settingup; homes, and to the fact that it was not proposed, as after the last war, to make any provision for assisting them to meet their civil liabilities. The war gratuities would be expended in this countryand would serve to stimulate trade.Against the scale proposed by the Service Departments, itwas urged that it would involve an additional expenditure of 100 millions. It was misleading to consider the amount of thegratuity as so many pence per day, and members of the Forcesthemselves would not regard it in this way. Even on the proposalsof the Chancellor of the Exchequer there was a serious risk of inflation at the time when the gratuities would be paid, and theaddition of  100 millions would accentuate the difficulties. If theGovernments proposal were presented to the House of commons as one for the distribution of  200 millions in the form of gratuitiesand if examples were given-of the lump sums which would be payable to typical members of the Forces, it seemed unlikely that-there would be serious criticism in Parliament. The global sumof  200 millions would, of course, have to be increased to take account of any prolongation of the war or any increase in thenumbers of the Armed Forces.Further points in discussion were-^(a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out that it wouldbe necessary to provide in the Finance Bill for the exemption of wargratuities from tax.      .    -
(b) The Minister of Labour arid National Service said that he hoped that it would be possible to announce a decision with regardto the amount of war gratuities at an early date, since he was.anxious to circulate to the Armed Forces a comprehensive pamphletdescribing the various schemes for resettlement. &quot; --(c) The Prime Minister emphasised the importance of planning,in advance for the production of furniture and internal fitments fordwelling houses, so that members of the Forces would be able to setup house on release without paying exorbitant prices.The War Cabinet then discussed the question of prize money and prize bounty.The First Lord of the Admiralty pointed out that in March,1940 (W.M. (40), 80th Conclusions, Minute 8), the War cabinet had agreed to defer a decision in regard to prize money and prizebounty until the end of the war. Prize money was recognised by statute, and the Navy expected this payment where the appropriateservice had been given. Accordingly, any decision that there was tobe no prize money in the present war would be regarded as breach of faith by the Government. So far as could be estimated, theamount of prize money likely to be available would be about 9 millions and, after deduction of the necessary costs, the averageamount payable to each man would be about  5. If it were agreedthat prize money could he paid, he would not press the case forthe payment of prize bounty. It was proposed that prize money should be payable to crews of aircraft who took part in operations for which prize money was payable and the Secretary of State forAir saw no difficulty in working out a scheme for this.The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out that if it were decided to grant prize money, it would be necessary to legislatespecifically for this purpose; and if prize money were paid therewould be inequalities between man and man of the sort which theGovernment had striven,to avoid in framing the schemes for the resettlement of men released from the Armed Forces. Moreover, he felt that it would be extremely difficult to devise any satisfactory scheme for the payment of prize money to air crews.-The War Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the information given in w.P. (44) 602 regarding the provision which was beingmade for resettlement, and agreed that a pamphletgiving a comprehensive picture of what was being doneshould be prepared for circulation to members of the armed Forces. &quot;(2) Approved the scale of war gratuity for men released fromthe Armed Forces proposed by the Chancellor of theExchequer in W.P. (44) 700.(8) Agreed that the Chancellor of the Exchequer should announce the Government^ proposals to Parliament and.that in their presentation stress should be laid on thetotal charge which they laid on the Exchequer.  At thej same time examples of the lump sums which would be payable in particular cases might be given.(4) Agreed that provision should be made for the payment ofprize money, to the crews of ships and of aircraft inappropriate cases, and invited the First Lord of theAdmiralty and the Secretary of State for Air to devise a scheme for the equitable allocation of prize money tocrews of aircraft.(5) Agreed that prize bounty-should be declared obsolete).
Press. - 5.   The War Cabinet were reminded that nearly a yearDaily Workers previously they had decided that the Daily Worker should not be permitted to have accredited correspondents with His Majesty&apos;forces. This decision had been conveyed to the Daily Worker onthe 18th January, 1944, and had been incorporated in an Answergiven by the Secretary of State for War to Mr. Pritt, M.P., on thesame day.Since that date there had been continued protests, against thedecision, coupled with requests for a deputation from theAmalgamated Engineering Union and the National Union of journalists.   These requests had been refused.The Secretary of State for War informed the War Cabinetthat the T.U.C. had now asked that a deputation should be received.After a short discussion the War Cabinet-(1) Reaffirmed their -previous decision in this matter.(2) Took note that the deputation would be received by thePrime Minister, accompanied by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs and the Secretary of State for War.Request forAccreditingof a Oorres-correspondent toBritish Forces.Suggested -T.U.C.Deputation.(previous reference:W.M.(44) -7thConclusions,Minute 7.)* The directive as subsequently approved by the Prime Minister, i8appended to these Conclusions. . &apos;Distrjbution pf 4. The War Cabinet had before them a report by theIndustry. Distribution of Industry Committee (WP. (45) 2) dealing with the(Previous       strategic aspects of industrial location.Reference: After consultation with the Chiefs of Staff, the Joint war.M. (44) 168th Production Staff had put forward for the guidance of the Distribu-Conclusions,    tion of Industry Committee four broad propositions, which were minute 2.)      set out in paragraph 2 of W.P. (45) 2.   The Committee recom-mended that Departments should be directed to pay due regard tothese propositions, as well as to industrial and social considerations,in connection with the location of new factory development.In  the  immediate  future  the  main  application  of   thepropositions would be in connection with the decisions which wouldhave &quot;to be taken with regard to the disposal of factories built in the. early years of the war as part of the Governments dispersal policy,and the Committee recommended that every effort should be madeto ensure that, in the event of another war-, these factories wouldbe available for use again at relatively short notice. In paragraph 5of W.P. (45) 2 suggestions were made as to the methods by whichthis policy could be carried out, A further point was that sincemany of the factories in question were located in development areas,their retention would, fit in well with the Government&apos;s employ-ment policy, provided that wherever possible the factories located in development areas were kept in production and not reduced toa care and maintenance basis.In discussion some doubts were expressed as to the wisdom of retaining factories on a care and maintenance basis, since, owingto the rapid development of war weapons, it might be found thatfactories built during the present war would be of little or nouse for future war production. On the other hand, it was urgedthat if the policy now proposed had been applied after the end ofthe last war, many of our difficulties in the early years of the present, war would have been avoided. The risk of the retention of factories which would not be of any real use as part of the war potential,might be avoided by periodic reviews.The War Cabinet-,   . (1) Endorsed the policy outlined in paragraphs 4 to 6 of w.P. (45) 2, on the understanding that there should beannual review of the position, particularly in regardto any factories kept in being on a care and maintenance-     :        basis. : -(2) Agreed that a directive* to this effect should be issued toall Departments concerned with the disposal ofGovernment factories.
Relaxation of 6.   At their meeting on the 30th November the War CabinetLighting had taken note of the progress made with the improvement of streetRestrictions lighting in London, and had invited the Home Secretary andin the Minister of Home Security to consider, in consultation with the AirLondon Area. Staff, whether full lighting by gas-lit street lamps could be allowed(Previous       in suitable cases.wM^nCe: The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security noww.M.(44)l60th reported that the Air Staff strongly opposed the use of peace-timeConclusions, street lighting in London on account of the assistance which the minute 7.)      glow would give to the aircraft which launched flying bombs.Moreover, most of the gas-lit boroughs had installed or wereinstalling intermediate lighting, some of it at considerable cost.To reward less active boroughs for their inaction by giving thempermission for full lighting would arouse strong resentment fromthe more active boroughs.At the suggestion of the Prime Minister the War Cabinet Agreed that the question whether, and if so, to what extent,the institution of full lighting by gas-lit street lamps inLondon would assist the enemy aircraft which launchedflying bombs should be remitted for consideration by theChiefs of Staffs Committee.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,9th January, 1945. ,APPENDIX.Strategic Aspects of Industrial Location.Directive by the Prime Minister.1. The following four propositions may for the time being be accepted asdenning the bearing of strategic considerations upon problems of industriallocation: -(a) Although the development of modern weapons is likely to increase thedanger of attack in the North and West of the British Isles, it will&apos; be desirable for vital installations to be located in that region ratherthan in the East and South.(6) The highest degree of security lies in dispersal in smaller units andduplication, and large and concentrated plants should, if possible, be avoided.(c) (&amp;) overrides (a) i.e., dispersal in smaller units over the country wouldbe preferable to concentration in the West and the North.(d) In locating vital installations security would be increased if large centres of population which themselves present profitable targets for attackcould be avoided. London is the supreme example.These propositions will be reviewed from time to time and any changesnotified.2. Departments charged with the implementation of the government&apos;s policy on the distribution of industry as set out in Chapter III of the white paper on Employment Policy (Cmd.6527) should pay due regard to strategic considerations, as well as to industrial and social considerations, in exercising their functions in regard both to the location of new factory development andto the disposal of Government factories. In particular every effort should bemade to ensure that the large number of factories which have been built, as partof the Governments dispersal policy, in relatively safe areas and areas away from the larger centres of population should not be dismantled or dismemberedin such a Way as to make it impossible for them to be used again at relatively short notice for the purposes for which they were constructed.3. Cases in which this policy can only be carried out by keeping a factory in being on a care and maintenance basis should be reported to the Distributionof Industry Committee; and that Committee should carry out an annual reviewof the position, particularly in regard to any factories kept in being on, a care and maintenance basis.4. Wherever possible, factories located in development areas should be kept in production and should not be reduced to a care and maintenance basis.



</content>
</cab>
