<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/43/0 images: 48-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel Jorte* g gvviiR CABINET .F O U D.         I hope that the Food question will bedrastically dealt with without any  further delay.    I  am -confident that if the present state  of affairs  isallowed to continue much longer, we  shall have  veryserious trouble with the people of  the country, and  theywill be exposed to grave privations  which can,  I a/:convinced,  be avoided.    I don&apos;t think the responsibilityfor the present position rests with  one Department -alone.   There seems to be a want of co-operationbetween the various Departments and all my informationwhich comes from practical farmers  in all parts of thecountry, and wnich is drawn also from my own personalexperience as a land-owner and farmer in the west ofEngland, goes to prove that existing rules and  -regulations have tendea to paralyse  production.   Thefirst object of the Government surely ought.to be toincrease the supply of home grown food by every meansin its po^er.   I agree with Sir Charles Bathurst,  thanwhom there is not a t^reater authority on thesequestions in tne country,  when he points out that thedesire to increase.the corn supplies has been carriedto a dangerous point, and is already resulting in aserious diminution of other food supplies.   It iseasy to fine illustrations.   I give one widen I thinkmay be instructive.         The producers in a parish of a very typicalkind meet and decide that while continuing all theirexports to London and elsewhere,  they vail by special                                          effort
effort increase theix&apos; production  for local consumption.A working system is devised, and  all the arrangementsmade, but it is found to be impossible to givepractical effect to the plan because of various Actsor Regulations of Government Departments.   Farmer A.has decided to increase his meat,  supplies.   Immediatelyhe is told that although he has already ploughed asmuch of Jus land as is fit for the plough, he is toplough more, and the particular land selected is knownto him, and indeed to everybody in the neighbourhood,to be wholly unsuitable.   He naturally says &quot;what isthe use of my trying to add to the supplies ifGovernment Itepartments treat me in this way?&quot;Farmer B. undertakes to increase  the pig supply -perhaps the most important thing  of all.   He is atonce brought up by Regulations affecting, feeding.The same applies to poultry, and  it would be possibleto  0 on ad infinitum with illustrations of the wayin which present regulations interfere with andrestrict production.         I venture to ^ake a series of suggestionswnich I nave discussed with a Representative of theFood Department, whom Lord Hhondda was good enough tosend to see me, but I find no reason to change my views,and I an confident that uniess the present system ofdealing with prices, especially of meat and corn, andthe general Regulations and rules which are issued bythe various Departments undergo a radical alteration,we shall have still greater shortage,  and the peoplewill be rightly indignant with us because they knowquite well that much of&apos; tne trouble is due not tounavoidable causes, but to the direct action of theGovernment.
      I would divide the food stuffs under two heads -those which cone from oversea, and those which are pro-duced here.   In regard to the former, i;.e. importedmeat, bacon, cereals, tea, sugar, and cheese;  I suggestthat the Food Control Department should concentrate alltheir energies upon their purchase and transport to andwithin Great Britain.   To effect this latter reformimmediate stens should be taken to improve the internaltransport of the United Kingdom.  This can only be done,in my belief, by somebody who really understands thisquestion - it must cover both rail and road transport0Possibly some use might be made of rivers and canals.This reform is essential if supplies are to be distri-buted throughout the country with anything &quot;dike equality.      1 suggest that the country should be divided intodistricts; that the imported meat, cheese, bacon etc,should be sent in the main to the great populous cen-tres, where the lar^e numbers of wage-earning classescreate a special demand, which makes it very difficult,if not impossible, for local authorities to cope withthe task of supply.   With regard to the rest of thecountry, I suggest that towns should be selected as thecentres, and with the surrounding country covering apopulation of from 25,000 to 35,000  should be createdspecial areas, and that they should  be called upon tocohtrol the distribution and the feeding of the peopleas they deem best.  It might be desirable to  give theLocal Government Board  power to decide where  any                                             difficulty
difficulty arises inXfie composition of an area.  I donot myself, however, anticipate that there would hemany cases of this kind.   The local markets to a verylarge extent govern these questions, and it would not, -I believe, often happen that there would be any seriousdispute.  It is not possible to make .the County Committeesact in these cases-, or to give the County Councils thepower of setting up the areas, for in many cases theseareas will cut into Counties.  I may perhaps be allowedto give my own County as an illustration of the way inwhich the scheme I suggest would work,.     fe have a population of about 290,000, of whom from60,000 to 70,000 would probably be found, in and aroundthe town of Swindon, combined with the adjoiningvillages, some of which are really now part- of the town.This would leave the balance to be divided into areascontaining the population which I have already indicated,I am satisfied that if a scheme somewhat on these linesbe adopted, these are&amp;e would be able very largely toincrease the local supplies.   It would of course bemade clear that there must be no diminution in thesupplies from these areas to external markets..  Tostarve A in order to feed B would of course not inany way help the situation.  But when local people arecharged not only with duties, but actual authority,and when it is.known that every additional effort willresult in feeding the locality itself,  it is wonderfulwhat efforts people will make,  I srn speaking fromsome local experience,  and I could,  if necessary,give an exa.mple of work of this kind already well done.     But if this policy is to be adopted, it is,  inmy judgment, essential that there should be                                               some
 some relaxation of the present regulations with regard the fixing of prices.  The prices of meat were fixed some months ago. and the warnings which were addressed by many of us to the Food Department have been un- happily proved to be well founded, and in the opinion of   .3most of the practical men with whom I come in con tact, or whose remarks I read in articles or letters in the newspapers, the shortage has been mainly due to this method of dealing with prices.  I am informed that only the other day rabbits were plentiful in the market.  They were making as much as 3/- not at all an excessive price in war times for these most useful articles of food.  The price was altered and I am told that immediately the supplies fell off.      There is one other suggestion which I wcdd desire to make.  I am told by those who are well acquaintedwith the present condition of Ireland that a great dealmore food could be spared from that country than isallowed to come at present,  and when I have asked why it is that such severe limitations are imposed upon export of food from Ireland,  I  am told that it is tomeet the views of the Sinn Feiners,  who threaten to interfere with all transport  if more than what theythink to be right is sent to  Great Britain&apos;.  Now surely there can be no justification for such a stateof things as this?   It.is a  matter of common know- ledge that the food conditions  in Ireland are muchbetter than they are in Great Britain.   The people ofIreland are not doing their  share in the war;   thereare probably between two  and  three hundred  thousandmen who would be of the greatest  value  to us  now,who ought to be in the Army and are  not;  and  if. thisstate of things is to be  allowed  for high reasons  of                                             State,
State, and if it is oelieved that the country would notsupport the measures necessary to get these men, therecan, I think, be no question that when it ccrnes tomailing a. fair contribution to tno general food supply,if anv   ,sistance were offered in Ireland, the wholecountry would support the Irish Government in puttingit down with a firm hand.  Large supplies of both meatand butter were coming to this country from Ireland upto quite recently.   They have been stopped for thereasons which I have given;  they should be at once eon--tinued, because every one of the customers hitherto fed byby Ireland, if those supplies fail, creates a fresh de -mand upon our resources in Great Britain, and simul-taneously the large supplies of Irish mea/b which areeasily controlled should be directed to the big populouscentres, as it is easy to collect and transport them fromIreland to nsndon, where the size of the population maitesit impossible for local effort to compete with the &quot;task,-and the same applies to those pa,rts of Great ^rita-mwhere the largest numbers of cattle can easily be coi-lected together.        Again, supplies of fish food could be largely in-creased, e.g. eels, an excellent and nutritious articleof food, could be caught in cur rivers in much largerquantities.   I only throw this out as an illustration,but I am convinced that, if proper steps were taken,there are sources of supply not yet sufficiently tapped                                              from
        from which a considerable addition to our fish supplies        could be made.   Moreover,  if increased ice storage was        provided, considerable quantities of fish caught on the        Irish Coasts would be available, for distribution by the        Food Controller.               I believe  that if the Food Controller would set        up a panel of practical land agents from all over the        country, and avail himself  of their advice at head-        quarters, and ompioy them in their own localities fcr        local advice,  he  would be greatly fortified in tho        discharge of his  duties,  and would find not. a few        of his difficulties materially decreased..  If this        delegation of power and responsibility were made the        work of the Food  Controller would be. still-more than        sufficient to tax the energies and abilities of any        Minister.               Lastly,  I  should like to see a determined        attempt made to made everybody leave London who is not        engaged upon real work and  who can find a home for        himself or herself in the Country.   This would mean        that a fairly large number  of people would go,  but        the real advantage would be found not so much in the        mere numbers as in the stopping of the extra consump-        ticM cf food,  fuel,  light,  petrol,  which at present        cau,30d much resentment among the people who can. only        got their supplies by waiting in queues or going from        shop to shop.                               W.H.L.                                      22nd February,  1918.Colonial Office,         Dowining Street.

</content>
</cab>
