<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/43/0 images: 161-164</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
: This Document Is the PjgPggyjpj.His Britannic itfajesty&apos;s Government)     confidential.Colonel Jds&amp;   126War Cabinet.      JX^ \\  Exchange of interned civilians.T  iVl )-)--!--. 1 s  &apos;  Me-ffl^p^ndum by. the Secretary of State for War,_______^&quot;&quot;kV&apos;&apos;            i circulate a record of the proceedings of a Committee  assembled at the War Office on 12th February, 1918, for ths  information of the War Cabinet.                        Present:-       The Rt.Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.. G.C.V.O., C.B.,               Secretary of State for War  (in the Chair)Captain H.K.Kitson,  R.H.     AdmiraltyMr. W.J. Evans, C.B.??.,     AdmiraltyLt.General.Sir H.-E. Belfield K.C.B., K.C.H.G\, D.S.O.,  Director of Prisoners of War,         War Office.Colonel V.G.,r-\ Kell, C..B,         ViTar Office,Mr. M.L.Waller, C.B.,         Home Office.          Lord Newton, who attended  the meeting, made  an  explanatory statement regarding  a memorandum he  had drawn  up for  submission to the V/ar  Cabinet urging a  reconsideration  of  the decision  of  the Cabinet  of  28th March, 1917, War Cabinet  107 (10  (a))  that  &quot;a&quot;general  exchange  of  interned civilians was impracticable  and not&quot;in the&apos;interests  of  the State&quot;,      2.   The proposal as put  forward by  Lord  Newton  is br(e^ijfly follows;-as          That all civilians interned in the United Kingdom andGermany shall be at liberty to return to their own country, butthat, as the number of Germans who would probably avail themselvesof the permission *- estimated at 15,.000, is much in excess of the3,000 (which number includes men of the Mercantile Marine, referredto below) whom we may hope to receive, a condition should be madethat 5,000 British private soldiers should be transferred toHolland from Germany and that all Mercantile Marine officers andcrews now in Germany should be included among the civilians, theirservices being much required in this  country.     3.   The arguments in favour of  this proposal are          (a) Humanitarian(b)  The  removal  from this  country  of  a  number  of  Germans    whom it would be difficult  to  repatriate after  the    conclusion of peace.!.(c)  It would  be  a popular  movement,(d)  The  expense  of maintenance  and difficulties of  food    supply of.prisoners would be materially reduced.                                                  (e)
    (e)   The small amount  of work which can be extracted from          these interned aliens,    (f)   The change in the military situation owing to the          collapse of Russia, thereby releasing a very large body          of German troops  for employment on other fronts, among          whom the number repatriated from this country would be          negligible,     4,.   Having considered the various points raised, theCommittee decided as follows:-     (a)  They adhere to the conclusion reached by a Committee          assembled at the  War Office last March, and submitted to          the War Cabinet that wthe best and really most humane          course to follow  is to place and keep out of action as          many  of the Enemy as possible&quot;,     (b)  The surrender to  Germany of 15,000 men of military age,          in sound health,  of whom the great majority are believed          to be reservists, in exchange for 3,000 British subjects          on whose services we have no claim would be condemned by          public opinion and is not justified by the defection of          Russia.     (c)  The advantage of  repatriating every interned German          civilian and thereby incidentally reducing the cost and          difficulties of maintenance is recognised, but this is          not contemplated  and is, probably, impracticable.  Only          those would avail themselves of permission to return to          their country who are desirous of taking up arms against          us, and those are the very men whose repatriation on the          conclusion of peace will present least difficulty.  It          will still be necessary to maintain internment camps          for such as do not elect repatriation.     (d)  Although it cannot be anticipated that enough work will          be obtained froia  the interned aliens to repay for their          maintenance, it is to be observed that some 3,000 of          them, or upwards  of 14 per cent, are employed in various          ways to the National advantage and it is expected that          this number will  be increased.     (e)  It is very doubtful if Germany would consent to the          transfer of 5,000 private soldiers to Holland or whether          that country would or could accommodate them..                It is also  practically certain that Germany will          not abandon her determination to treat officers and men          of the Mercantile Marine as combatants, and as the          Admiralty attach  great importance to maintaining the          contention of His Majesty*s Government as to the Non-          Combatant status  of Defensively Armed Merchant Ships and          their crews the distinction  between Merchant Seamen and          other Civilians involved in this proposal is in their          opinion open to grave objection.  It would involve the          abandonment of the right of the Mercantile Marine          prisoners in Germany to be considered as Civilians and        *  to benefit by the existing agreements for the exchange          of Civilians: it  amounts to a tacit admission that the          action of the German Government in treating them          differently from  other civilians has been correct:  and          it implies that a special arrangement distinct from                                                           these
     those already  in force  as regards  clvlllan-^prtsoners,  is     necessary to effect  their repatriation.   Any prnpcraaX whJjcif     differentiates the position of Merchant  Seamen from that of     other Civilians or suggests that the;/ should not  receive     identical treatment  must inevitably weaken the view hitherto     maintained as  to the status of Defensively Armed  Merchant     Ships,          A short summary of the circumstances in which this     question has arisen  is  attached,  (f)0n many occasions since the decision of  the War Cabinet of     tho 28th March, 1917, that  &quot;A general exchange of &quot;interned     &quot;civilians was impracticable and not in  the interests of the     STtate&quot;, His Majestyfs Government has urged all Allies to resist     suggestions for the  exchange of valid prisoners-of-war and in     October last asked them to  give a  formal assurance that they     adopted our views.   It  will be impossible to justify the change     of policy which the  adoption of Lord Hewton&apos;s proposal would     entail,   5,     The Committee recommend that  the proposal for an exchangeOf civilian pri3oner&quot;*^of-war should not be entertained.                                               DERBY,25th February,  1918.          The Admiralty have consistently urged the importance ofmaintaining their contention as to the Civilian status of MerchantSeamen, which is the logical outcome of the view expressed by thisCountry that Merchant Ships are ^entitled to be armed and to usetheir armament for self-defence without losing their non-combatantcharacter.  The point is, therefore, of real and permanentimportance to us and our Allies,          The attitude which the German Government decided toadopt was first definitely indicated when oh the 8th November 1916they transferred 96 Merchant Officers and Seamen captured fromDefensively Armpd Merchant Ships from the.Civilian Camp atRuhleben to the Combatant Camp at Brandenburg,  Since then, theAdmiralty have repeatedly urged that their contention as to thestatus of these prisoners should be brought to the notice of theGerman Government, and a definite assurance demanded that theywould be treated as Civilians, both while in internment and for thepurpose of repatriation^  It may be observed that, apart from theirinherent right in this latter respect, the agreement for theexchange of civilians over forty-five specifically provided that itshould apply to Merchant Officers and Seamen.           (No communication of our views has, however, been made tothej German Government, and the process of interning MercantileMarine prisoners in Combatant Camps has continued ever since).          Those who have so far been released under the presentexchange are believed to be either prisoners from Ruhleben, i,e.Seamen captured in the very early days of the War (August 1914);Seamen from Unarmed Merchant Ships and Fishermen,  whom the Germansregard as Civilians, or men from Combatant Camps who have beenrepatriated as coming within the schedule of disabilities applicable                                                            to
to Combatants.  There is no clear indication that the GermanGovernment intend to fulfil their obligations by releasing allMerchant Officers and Seamen who are over forty-five or whocome under the other arrangements relating to Civilians.          German Merchant Seamen captured by this Country havebeen placed in Civilian Internment Camps, though, havingregard to the compulsory system of Service in force in Germany,there would seem to be quite sufficient reason for enteringthem in Combatant Camps as potential branches of the Bnemy&apos;sArmed Forces.          Negotiations for any new arrangement for the releaseof Merchant Seamen would be not only unwise,  but positivelyharmful, until a clear understanding has been reached on thepoints at issue between us and the German Government.Admiralty,          19.2.18*

</content>
</cab>
