<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/43/0 images: 186-190</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 i ifi &quot;) COL          , TWs  Document is the PropertyJ  I     /Mm          &apos;-------------------......&quot;y&amp;jj         TTT^-H-mi&apos;- N*aiestv&apos;s  Government.)   Confidential.LABOUR  POSITION  IN  MUNITION  INDUSTRIES.                     (23rd February  1918.)     I circulate the following notes which have been prepared in the Intelligence andStatistics Section of the Ministry of Munitions on  the labour position in munitionsindustries.                                                  WINSTON S.  CHURCHILL.                                     SUMMARY:.                                          I.    The reduction of some elements iu the munitions programme for 1918 may cause a certain amount ofdislocation of industry even before the end of the war, and consideration is beiug given to the best methodsof avoiding unemployment and the waste of labour.                                         II.    No strike involving more than about 300 munition workers was reported by chief investigation officersas in progress on the 18th February.  During the last complete week for which figures are available theweek ending the 13th February there were in addition to minor stoppages four strikes which involved aloss of about 1,000 working days.  None OF the stoppages lasted more  than a few  days, and the aggregateloss of time during the week was under 30,000 days or less than one-fifth of 1 per  cent. (0-19) of the totalpossible working  days  of all  munition workers.   Almost two-thirds  of the time lost resulted from thestoppage at Messrs. Beardmore&apos;s Parkhead Works, Glasgow.                                         III.    The causes of the stoppages which have occurred during  the present week illustrate  the growingtendency of trade unions TO INSIST on their PRE-WAR  RESTRICTIVE PRACTICES.  THE ALLEGATION that  the Grovern-ment pledges may not be  redeemed is having its effect, and the worker s in several industries are againresisting dilution and the introduction of non-union  labour.                                         IV.    Closely associated with the question of dilution is that of recruiting.  In this connection the word&quot; dilutee&quot; is interpreted  variously.   The matter is complicated by the. bearing of dilution upon  therestoration of trade union conditions after the war.                                         V.    Developments of more or less importance  affecting women workers are  recorded  in connection withwages, hours, training, and welfare.                I-LABOUR  AND  THE  NEW PROGRAMME.     The revision of programme  consequent  upon  reduction of tonnage and  cancel-lation of Russian orders may have a material bearing upon labour problems in munitionfactories.   Any full statement is impossible until programmes for reduction of outputhave been worked out in detail, but some of the points  involved may  already beindicated:      (1) There will be no appreciable decrease  in  the demand  for skilled labour for           munitions work.   A large number of skilled men will continue to be           essential for work in the toolroom, and  for supervising  the work of other           less skilled workers.     (2) No considerable number of able-bodied men will be made directly available           for military service.   The workers likely to be discharged are engaged on           work which has already been highly diluted and fairly well &quot; combed out.&quot;           There may, however,  be an  opportunity  of  recruiting  boys  of &quot; A&quot;           category, as they  attain  military age.     (3) The workers principally affected  will be women.  Of  the 36,000 people in           shell and filling factories likely to be involved by reductions  decided on           in December, 26,000 are women.     (4)  Alternative methods are  possible &quot;closing down&quot; and the  discharge of           workers, or &quot;scaling down,&quot; and  the  retention of workers on  short time.           In  the former case  it  will not necessarily  follow   that  the  discharged           workers will be  wholly deprived of employment. There  may be  oppor-           tunities to transfer many of them  to other work (e.g., aeroplane manufac-           ture) for which labour  is in demand  and raw material can  be supplied.    A  (33)5219  Pk 20 125 2/18 E&amp;S                                                A
         -  On &quot;the other hand,  &quot;scaling  down&quot;  may provide  an  opportunity to           diminish overtime  and overcrowding, though  reduced  opportunities for           earning&apos; high wages are likely to be unpopular    There is here  only a first adumbration of a situation which is in process ofdefining itself, and which may involve practical questions of  reconstruction beforethe war has come to an end.    The whole condition is  being considered broadly by the Supply Departments, inconjunction with the Labour Department,&apos; as a matter of great urgency.                                  II. -STRIKES.    Week ending .13th February  1918. The  number of  workpeople reported  bychief  investigation officers to have been involved in strikes during the week ending theloth February was 11.512 as against 8,275* in the preceding week.   The number ofpeople  still  on strike  at the  end of  the  week was 552,  as  against 2,325  on the6th February.   The number of working days lost during the week  was 29,034 asagainst 28,169* in the preceding week.    By far the  greatest loss of time was  occasioned by the stoppage at the Parkhead&apos;Works  of Messrs.  W. Beardmore &amp;  Co.,  Ltd.  (Glasgow),&quot;]&quot;  where 6,000  men lost18,000  days.  At the  Waddon  National Aircraft Factory 2,000 workers lost  4,000days  in enforcing their demand for the 12h per cent, bonus ;  1,500 women employedby a  Bermondsey firm were on strike for one day in protest against the failure of thefirm to pay the  3s. 6(1  advance granted  hy an Order of the 14th  January;  and 500bricklayers and navvies at Glasgow lost two days each in support of their claim torecent engineering trade advances.    Since the 13th Febritary.-Du.rhig  the  current week very few  stoppages havebeen  reported.  The most important case is that of  electricians employed on privatework on the Clyde.   Two  hundred  of  these men are demanding  payment .of the121 per cent, bonus.                III.-OPPOSITION  TO  NON-UNION  LABOUR.     In three of the minor strikes of - the  week ending the 13th February, the cause oftrouble  was the  objection of  trade  unionists to work with non-unionists J or  withmembers of  other unions.  The cases occurred in different parts of  the country andaffected widely  different classes of workers aircraft wood-workers at Leeds, who weresuccessful in compelling at least five out  of six non-unionists to join unions ;  mouldersat Lincoln, who claimed that four members of  general  labour unions should join theFriendly Society of Ironfounders;  and girls  employed  as winders^ at Denton inLancashire, who stopped work from the 6th to the 10th February as a protest againstthe employment of two non-unionists.     During the war the strike to eliminate non-unionism has been most  common inthe mining industry.   In the skilled engineering and shipbuilding trades such strikeshave generally taken the form of opposition to dilution, whether dilutees were or werenot willing to become trade unionists.  It is reported by the chief investigation officerat Manchester that Lancashire firms have recently been meeting with serious oppositionto dilution from many of the most powerful trade unions including engineers, boiler-makers, electricians, carpenters and joiners, and sheet metal workers.      An Apprenticeship Question.-An illustration of the tendency to revert to restrictive practices occurred at Liverpool on the 13&apos;th February.  A firm of electrical engineers, Messrs. Scott &amp; Co., Ltd., engaged as an apprentice a  discharged,  soldier, 23 years of age.   The rules of the Electrical Trades Union prohibit the starting of an apprentice- ship  after the age of 19.  In spite of  the  fact that the man was  entitled to special consideration as  a discharged soldier,  the skilled  electricians  maintained  that his    &quot; These figures for last week, it may be observed, do not agree with those given in this Report for the13th February.  The chief investigation^officer iu Scotland has revised his estimate of the namber of peopleinvolved in the strike at the works of Messrs.  IBarr &amp; -Stroud, reducing it from 3,000 to 2,000.  Thisinvolves &quot;a reduction of 5,000 in the number of days lost during the week ending the 6th February i.e.,  areduction from 33,169 to 28,169.    i See this Report for last week, p. 3.    % In view of this tendency, it is interesting to recall a passage fr&amp;m the recent speech of the Ministerof Reconstruction at Manchester -(4th December) :-&quot; I believe that; it is in the best interests of the country&quot; that every workman should be in a trade union and -every -employer in a trade association with a joint&quot; council for considering common questions.&quot; (Manchester Guardian, 5.12.17).    5 Making covering for field telegraph cable.
introduction was  a case of dilution on which, they should have  been consulted, andthey were supported not only by their own union, which threatened  to  bring out allthe electricians in Liverpoof iinless the man was discharged, but also by the Liverpoolboilermakers,  who  threatened  a sympathetic  strike.  The Mersey  Ship Repairers&apos;Association, of which Messrs. Scott &amp; Co. are members, reluctantly advised that  theman should be discharged; the firm agreed that this  should be done  and the menreturned to work.  .  .     Position and Polictj of Electrical Trades Union. The strike just mentioned issymptomatic of  what. appears  to be  a  distinctive  policy  adopted by the  ElectricalTrades Union.  The skilled members of this union, if they act in concert, are pecu-liariy well placed for exacting higher wages and better conditions of labour in relationto their  skill than any other group, of skilled workers.   The number of men engagedin the industry is  comparatively  few,  and their conditions  of  work can easily besupervised by  trade union officials.    Their work is essential  to  many industries,although, on the other hand, even if  they secured exorbitant wages this  would affectthe cost  of production in such industries very  little, because  their numbers are smallin comparison with the numbers of the  other  workpeople.  In London, for example,the bulk  of  manufacturing establishments are dependent  upon the public supply ofelectricity for power and light.  In large works and collieries where electricians  areemployed, other than works for the production of electrical apparatus,  they form buta small section of the maintenance staffs, and yet they are essential to the running ofthe businesses.     There is every indication that the Electrical Trades Union means  to take fulladvantage  of  these  special circumstances in its favour.   In London, at  least, it hasbeen far-sighted  enough to remove all fear of competition with the general labourunions in the industry by forming a  joint committee with these  unions&apos;5&apos; for  thepurpose of organising, in the first place, all skilled, semi-skilled, and unskilled menat the electric supply stations.  If  the union is able to enforce a strict limitation ofthe number of apprentices entering the trade, which the Liverpool  strike  seems toindicate is its policy, it will, have in its  hands  a powerful lever for forcing up wagesrates and imposing conditions of employment.   In this  connection the expansion ofelectrical engineering after the war will be an important factor.     The policy of  limitation of apprentices, if applied successfully by one or twoskilled unions, is bound to be attempted  more or less successfully by others, and thismay  materially  affect the problem  of  the  employment  of  discharged  soldiers  inindustry after the war.  Many of  the men now in the  army are precluded by theirperiod of service from apprenticeship  to a trade, and if the policy referred to issuccessful to any extent, a number of  avenues to skilled occupations will be closed.        IV.-RECRUITING AND  THE QUESTION  OP DILUTEES.     Recruiting under the revised schedule of  protected occupations is proceeding inaccordance with the instruction of the 31st January to Munitions Area Dilution Officers.Clause 5 of this instruction is as follows :             &quot; In selecting men for release from the classes  now rendered available       under M  M. 130 (Revised),  Munitions Area Dilution Officers should  be guided       by the consideration of the  effect upon output.   They  should at the  same time       bear in mind that especially in occupations requiring a considerable degree of       skill, the man who has entered the occupation since August 15th, 1915, can, as       a general rule, be more easily spared than men of longer service.&quot;     The uncertain temper of the trade unions in regard  to the revised schedule tendsto make the work of dilution  officers difficult.  To facilitate immediate recruiting andallow time for a definite understanding to be  arrived at between  the Government andthe unions, the following &quot; strictly  confidential &quot; instruction has been issued to chiefdilution officers :            &quot;In  view of the  recruiting for the Army that is now about to take place,       and also in view of the new programme  for certain munition products, dilution       will not be enforced in cases where  it is resisted  by unions.  &apos; This policy will       be reviewed when the  recruiting has  been completed.  Chief  dilution officers       should, therefore, for the present refrain from arranging inspections of works in   * The Workers&apos; Union; the National Union of General Workers ; and the Enginemen, Firemen, andElectrical Workers&apos; Union.                             &apos;                 - .
      which, union opposition is1 usually encountered, while if such an inspection is called      for by a minute from headquarters they should make sure that^the question of      opposition, if any, from the union concerned is dealt with fully in the report.&quot;    By clause 5 of the  instruction to Munitions Area Dilation Officers (quoted above)it will be seen that the official view taken by the Ministry of Munitions of the meaningof &quot; dilutee,&quot; for  recruiting  purposes, is that, the  term  applies to men who haveentered scheduled occupations  since the 15th August, 1915, the date  of nationalregistration.   The nature  of a man&apos;s  employment before that date  could not bedetermined with ease or certainty.    This view of the connotation of the word &quot;dilutee&quot; is  not universally accepted.The  general labour  unions contend that, for  recruiting  purposes,  the  term shouldapply to  men who  have entered the industry not the  specific occupation sincethe beginning of the war.  For example, they contend that a man of 36, who has beenfor many years in the industry and has been up-graded  from semi-skilled to skilledwork during  the war, should  not be called to the colours in preference to youngskilled men of 23.  It is to  be  observed  that  this view is necessarily limited to therecruiting question.   For purposes of the  restoration of pre-war practice in the work-shops, there can be no doubt that the &quot; semi-skilled man on skilled men&apos;s work &quot; is adilutee.  Fear lest the case for restoration should be  prejudiced is an important factorin the apparently selfish  attitude of  skilled workers who  demand the protection oftheir members at the expense of up-graded &quot; dilutees &quot;  as well as of newcomers in theindustry.   A  high official  of the Amalgamated Society  of Engineers  in a  recentconversation said  that  this view  of  the case  had  not been adopted officially by thesociety, but he agreed that a section of the members  might  attempt  in  futurenegotiations to have  the up-graded machinist classed as a dilutee.    Another matter of reproach to. the A.S.E. is their choice, at the time of  the TradeCard Agreement, of  the date  of  national  registration (15th August, 1915), as thequalifying date for the protection of members.   During the first year of the war, themembership of the A.S.E. increased by 25,000 ;  many of the newcomers, it is suggested,were actuated even then by the  desire to  find  an  alternative to military service, andsome of them transferred from other unions to the A.S.E. as the most powerful unionin the munitions trades.  By other  skilled unions, therefore, the view is held that, inspite of its  obvious  convenience, the date of  registration, as chosen by the A.S.E.,should not be the starting-point for classifying  &quot; dilutees,&quot; but that all those who haveentered skilled  trades since the beginning  of the war should be excluded from thepreferential treatment claimed by the unions for their members.    In spite of minor differences and of the vagueness of the official attitude of someof the unions, the general feeling of the members of skilled unions  is that protectionshould be dependent on membership of a union, and should be granted in increasingmeasure in accordance with the duration of such membership.   The dilutee is notwanted  after the war ; his competition in the labour market is feared; and for theseindustrial reasons skilled trade  unionists are very willing to hand him over  to themilitary authorities.                          V.-WOMEN  WORKERS.    Saturday Afternoons at Woolwich Arsenal. On the recommendation of the Hoursof Labour Committee, it has  been decided to close  on Saturday afternoons  all thedepartments of the Arsenal in which women are employed.  The change  will affect26,000 women, and will reduce hours on the day shift to 57f and on the night  shift to591 Per week.&apos;:i:&quot;  The hours worked by women on  both shifts averaged  67-^th weeklyup to November 1916 and thereafter 62.    The 121 per  cent.  Bonus. Applications  are  being made on  behalf  of  womenworkers for the 12% per  cent, bonus.   While women on skilled men&apos;s work are entitledto the skilled man&apos;s rate, they are not entitled to  the  war Wage advances grantedto men.   In  the munitions industries these advances amount generally to  20s. for.men and to 10s. for women.  Railway workers have obtained 21s. for men and 8s. 6d.&apos;for women ; the National Union of Railwaymen are now applying for the extension towomen of the full war advance of 21s. .    * In connection with the  reduction of hours of  labour generally, it may be noted that the W:Priorities Committee have given directions that no Sunday labour is to be employed on constructional woiafter &quot; summer time &quot; has been introduced.
     Training for Munition Work-The training centres established by the Ministryof Munitions are transferring about  a thousand  women every month  to  munitionfactories.   The only men accepted at the training centres are discharged soldiers andmen with some previous mechanical experience who are capable  of  being up-graded.Attention is being  concentrated  on  aeroplane construction, and in this  directionthere should be  openings for large  numbers of  women discharged  from factoriesengaged on other classes of munition work.    Inquiry as to  Creches. The Welfare  and Health  Section  is making a  carefulinvestigation throughout the country  into the need  of creches for the children ofwomen munition workers.   Information is also being obtained  as to the grounds forany objections or prejudices against creches.

</content>
</cab>
