<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/43/0 images: 206-216</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Britannic jv?a]e3ty[3(Thssr:overncnenx.jJones   163Intelligence BureauDepartment of Information  A.G.W./040             WEEKLY  REPORT  OH  GERMANY   XL                 ( Feb. 26 1918)   Whatever may have been. Kuhlmann1    personal misgivings as tothe peace&quot; with the Ukraine, as to the provisional incorporationof Cholm with the new Ukrainian Republic, the &quot;breach with theBolshevists and the consequent German advance towards Kieff andPetrograd, he has had to conform to the views of the GeneralStaff now backed by the whole Reichstag except the twenty to                                               4thirty Independent Socialists and the Polish Party.   The Reichstaghas ratified the treaty of Peace with the Ukrainej  adequatedetachments from the German Armies of the East,are advancingrapidly icwards Reval and towards- Kieff and are sweeping up                                       ...... X &apos;&quot;&apos; &quot;  *- .the disorganized remnants of the Russian forces.  T,fce Ger;riaiitroops enter Russia proper as the powerful instrument of law andorder, and it 1b probable that they are welcomed as the lesser oftwo evils by thousands of respectable Russian feunilies who haveheen at the mercy of the Bolshevist terror.   The Bolshevists, afterattempts to negotiate by wireless, whioh the Germans brushed aside,have accepted the German terms of peace as drawn up in elevenA: Nicies above the signature of Kuhlmann and the &quot;Commander-inChief of the Eastern German Army.1,  Bolshevist envoys are againon their way to Brest-Litovsk.   For the moment Kuhlmann is atBuftea Castle, near Bukarest, negotiating together with Czeminand. Radoslavoff for a peace with Rumania.X   Tho German advanced troops are said to be specially purgedof possibly-Bolshevist-inclined men.
 2.   The terms of peace with Bolshevist Russia, which theBolshevists will doubtless have to accept in their entirety, willcut off Couriand, Lithuania, Congress Poland and the Ukraine fromall connection with tho Russian State.   As for Livonia andEsthonia., they must be immediately olearod of Russian troops andBolshevist bands (Red Guards),, and will be occupied by &quot;GormanPolice&quot; (i,c. military forces) unti the date when tho constitutionof the so territories can provide them with social security andpolitical order.   &quot;./ith these exceptions, Germany is prepared toevacuate the territory east of the line proposed by her for thenew Vestern frontier of Russia at the Brest-Litovsk negotiations.,but only after complete Russian demobilisation - a condition whichthe Bolshevists may find it difficult to carry out..   The blockadeof the Arctic Ocean Is to continue till the conclusion of a ce^eralpeace, so that Russia will, so far as the G-ermnn submarino &quot;blockade&apos;can complete her isolation, &quot;bo out off from all commorce with her .late Allies until they make peace with the Central Powers.   V/ithC-ormany on the other hand commercial relations are to be at onceresumed on the basis of the Russo-German Troaty of 1904, with aguaranteo for the free, untariffed export of ores, the immediatecommencement of negotiations for a new commercial treaty aricVtheguarantee of the most-i?.voured-nation treatment at least until 1925.The kind Ox most- .avourecl-nation treatment which Germany is toextend to Russia is the same as that which she covenanted to ^iveto the Uliraine.   It reserves ** and this is very important - thosemutual advantages which are contemplated as between Germany andJ:.                                            :    The reference in Art.VII of the German peace terras to Art.XIsections 5,4a end 15 of the Peace Treaty with tho Ukra ne Isprobably really to Art,VII - II sections 3,4,. etc about favoured^nation-treatment and special agreements about customs Unions.
Austria-Hungary in the arrangements now being negotiated.   Theannouncement has just been mado by the Hungarian Minister of Commercetha^ an Article similar to that in the Treaty with the Ukraine willbe embodied in every other peace-treaty.   This means that everyPower concluding peace with Germany will be expected to recognize thecommercial solidarity of Mittol-Europa.   It is likewise understood by the German pross that all Germanyfsfuture treaties of peace are to contain this provision for exceptingspecial customs conventions between Germany and her Allies from theoperation of the most-favoured-nation clause.   The other contractingparty may make the same reservation, so that, e.g., a BritishEmpire Customs Union would not be expeoted to grant Germany the most-favourod-nation treatment as against its own members.   Nay more;the Allied Western Powers might retaliate in their Poaoe Treatyby reserving complete liberty to contract with ono another forspecial commercial treatment;  and the Contral Powers, even if theyobtained in the Peace Treaty the most-favoured-natlon treatment,would not be able to claim it as against the Western Powors in theirdealings with one another.   The Hamburg Chamber of Commerce, perhaps in all Germany the bodythat is most keenly interested in international trade, has beenquick to seize this point.   It has hastened to memorialize theGerman Government on the perilous consequences of this innovation,and it urges that a &quot;iVittel-Uuropa&quot; Customs Union ought only to beresorted to if the Allied Powers now opposed to Germany take theinitiative by concluding exolusive or preferential Convontionsamong themselves.   Germany and Austria-Hungary,  they maintain,ought not to give Great Britain^ prance, Italy and America apretext for concluding conventions prejudicial to German foreigntrado.
                              - 4- -   Experienced observers,  it should be added, are of opinion thatthe German Government itself is not favourably disposed towards the&quot;iiittel-Europai: idea, which, they think,  has only been allowed tointrude itself into the Ukraine Treaty in order to satisfy anAustro-Hungarian demand, without really committing Germany to anentirely novel commercial policy by which her foreign trade v/ouldstand to lose incomparably more than it could possibly r.;ain.   A statement made in this connection by the same HungarianMinister, M, Szterenyi, is of great significance.   He said on the23rd at the conclusion of the debate on the Estimates:  &quot;&quot;Even before the war an economic union (with Germany) was thought   of, which could not be realized, because a preliminary condition   would have been that the. SteUft composing it should renounce their   sovoroicnty and recognize one centralised sovereignty&quot;.   If M, Szterenyi is accurately reported, what he says fully confirmsMr Gerard1s account of Gorman Imperial schemes which would havereduced the Austrian Emperor to the position of a mere Federal Prince,3,   The task which Germany is undertaking amounts at the very leastto an attempt to break up the t;estern frontier nationalities ofRussia into separate States with separate interests, but all in oneway or another under the influence of Germany,   The magnitude of thisenterprise, combined with the economic prospects thus opened up and theglamour of tho word &quot;peace&quot;, seems to have disarmed serious oppositionin Germany and  to have caused the Reichstag demand of last July xora settlement without annexations to fall into temporary oblivion.It is true that a storm of indignant Polish protest was let loosein  arsaw, Cracow and Posen.   In Cracow black flags were nuns outjin Posen demonstrations took&apos; place before the statue of the Polishpoet Miokiewioz, while in Warsaw the public protests were regarded asso serious from the German point of view that a heavy pecuniary finehas been imposed upon the city. .  In the severed Cholm country
                         - 5 -&apos;funeral services were held. *  As a Polish Deputy pointed out in theGerman Reichstag, Polish disappointment and indignation were allthe greater5 that arrangements had been made for the institutionof Polish schools in Cholm and for elections to the Polish NationalCouncil.   The Polish Government was not even consulted before thisregion was severed from Poland and added to the Ukraine.   This isthe kind of national independence which the Germans have bestowedupon Poland.   The result will be to draw Prussian, Austrian andRussian Poles closer together and to make the suppression of Polishaspirations a permanent problem for Germany on her Eastern frontier -a problem more formidable than that of Alsace-Lorraine on the West.For is any consideration shown for the internal difficulties ofAustria, whose Poles have now beon driven into opposition and intounion, for the time being, with the rest of the Austrian Slavs.   The policy of tho Austro-Hungarian iionarohy is by no means clear.It endeavours to allay the excitement among the Galician Poles bytho announcement that the Ukrainian peace-treaty is subject as regards                                                              V                                                              -v.the Cholm territory to revision by a mixed boundary Commissionand that a separate Treaty has been signed by representatives ofthe Ukrainian Rada and the Austro-Hungarian Government acoordingto which the Cholm territory does not fall within the UkrainianRepublic.    But there Is as yet no evidence that resentment at the vw&amp;y in which Germany has played fast-and-loose with Austro-Hungarianinterests in this matter Is leading to any real disintegrationof the Central European Alliance.   Count Czernin may play the flutein the Concert, but Count Hertling wields the conductor^ baton.     Lr von Seidleris speech in the Reichsrat on rob.19.   Asimilar provision appears in the Supplementary Treaty just ratifiedby the German Reichstag,
It wag a remarkable confession of ICuhlmann!s to the Reichstagthat without Gholm Ukrainia would not have made peace.   Havinggot peace, ho apparently now proposes to partition Cholm, givingone i&amp;i, to Ukrainia and leaving the other part to Poland.4.   The effect of theso momentous events upon the domesticsituation in Germany cannot fail to be considerable..   It is alreadymanifested in  he more aggressive tone of the Pan-Germans and In theaction of the Junkers and great industrialists in the Committeo ofthe Prussian Chamber, where they have* just rejected the principleof equal suffrage in the Franchise Bill.   A few days ago thePrussian Agrarian League(Bund der Landwirthe), the associationwhich in 1S94 intimidated the Aaiser into dismissing Count Capriviand initiating the reactionary policy whioh has since prevailed,celebrated the twenty-fifth anniversary of its foundation.The typical Junker Deputy, Herr von Oldenburg-Janausohau, a friendof the Crown Prince and the man who once said in the Reichstagthat the Kaiser could ata any time send a lieutenant with ten mento clear the place out, addressed the meeting.   He declared:-   &quot;The war is one for world-supremacy.   It must be carried to    victory, and that victory must be taken advantage of.   The great    Hohenzoxlerns compelled the Junkers to take service in the    Army, and the Kohenaollerns and the Fatherland thereby did a good    stroke of business.   In return for their services the Junkers    demand indemnities, annexations, and power.&quot;   Herr von Oldenburg in the course of his speech denounced Bethmann^Hollweg and lamented that &quot;all the rains of heaven could not washaway the blunder Bethmann had made in speaking abou^the 1 wrong&apos;done to Belgium&quot;,&apos;   Their armies would put things ri ,ht boyondthe frontiers, but how were they ever to emerge from the ness .;.thome ?   (Herr von Oldenburg was evidently referring to the promiseof political reforms and the Government co-operation with the mMajority Socialists.   A future Chancellor who should try to putthings right again would certainly be shot at;  the important
thing wo*s that he should be able to Bhoot back.   He ended bysneering at Eertling as a Bavarian who did not understand thePrussian spirit.   This speech is a true reflection ofAthe Prussian ruling-classes. It coincides with the action of the majority (electedon the three class indireot suffrage) in the Prussian Chamber,who, through the Special Committee of the House, have justrejected the clause bf tho Franchise Bill establishing equalsuffrage and have substituted a scheme of plural voting accordingto property and other qualifications.   It is not clear what attitude the Prussian Government, whichin this question is represented by the Vice-President of theMinistry, Pr Friedberg, and the Minister of the Interior, HerrDrews, is going to adopt towards this rejection of a vital reform 1solemnly promised by the Emperor last spring and summer in twopublic edicts.   Both Ministers had declared that the Governmentwould use every constitutional means to carry the Bill through,but Dr Friedberg the other day lot fall some hint of a compromiseon the question of equal suffrage, although he seemed to contradictthis in a communication to the press on the following day.The Liberal and Socialist newspapers are making a great noiseabout the action of the Combined Junkers and National Liberalsin the Committee.   (The National Liberals by the way prudentlysplit their votes, four of them voting with tho reactionarymajority and two for equal suffrage.)   But the Radical andSocialist protesta will probably be drowned in the generalcs &amp;acclamation of the peace with Russia.   That peace, the UkrainianTreaty and the terms which are about to be imposed upon theBolshevists - is regarded as the first stage in a general&quot;Germanpeace.&quot;
                                         J                           - 8 -The more ignorant amon  the lower middle classOs (Mlttelstand)possibly now hope that the Western:  Powers and America will nolonger have any heart to continue the war.   The military and annex-ationist parties will expeot that the Government Will stiffen its termsfor tho West.  Demands for control over Belgium, for the Briey-Longwydistrict, for a great Central African Empire  and oven for thereturn of the German Colonies in the South Seas are again insistent.The ory for&quot;a free hand in the Wsst&quot; appears for a moment to havetriumphed over RuhlmannU attempt to reduce the whole Westernconflict to the question of Alsace-Lorraine.   Even that attemptwill probably be abandoned in view of the deolarations ot thesubject which have just been made by the meetings of allied andneutral Socialists in Paris and London.   It will be interestingto see what reply the German Majority Socialists will make tothese declarations.   Thoy will probably have recourse to elaborateexplanations of Germany^ position as regards the new Easternfrontier States and will attempt to reconcile it with the Reichstagresolution of last July.   As to Alsace-Lorraine they will beadamant.   In present conditions it is vain for the WesternSocialists to expeot that the German Majority Socialists couldexorcise any serious influence upon the Western policy of theirGovernment.   If the German Government were in a position toeffect annexations on the West and at the same time to end the war,the Majority Socialists would accept the situation with a fewexpressions of warning or regret, but they would soon bury theirmisgivings just as they have consigned to oblivion Beb6lfs and theeldc?r Liebknecht&apos;s protest of 1871 against the annexation ofAlsace-Lorraine.     cf. Dr Solf *s fresh pronouncement at Karlsruhe.
                           m 9 -i5.   The position of the German Government at home will greatlydepend upon the success of its Eastern policy.   If it can bythe contemplated Organization of direot commercial barter obtain foodsupplies from the Ulcraine by next autumn, If it oan reconcile theLetts who hate Germany as much as they hate Russia, if it canmanage to repress the manifestations of Polish disillusionment,it may, for the present, stave off tho perils of discontent at home.It is already being warned regarding the dangers of a system ofbuffer States under German proteotion on the East, a system whichthe Berliner Ta^eblatt compares - not very appositely - to Napoleon&apos;sRheinbund. If Napoleon had contented himself with the Rheinbundhe might oonoelvably have permanently established his Empire andhis dynasty.  &apos; But Letts, Lithuanians and Poles will hardly hail Germantutelage as a safe stop towards tho realisation of their desirefor freedom and independence.   It Is also on the cards that theKaiser, like a certain school of Pan-German writers, will suoourAbto the lure of vast Eastern ambitions, that he will hope todominate continental Asia by means of the economic and militarysupremacy which he could establish over a Russia divided intocomparatively impotent and loosely-connected Russian republicsor monarchies.   He may hope one day to see Odessa incorporatedin a Central European ^ollverein, as Hamburg was ultimatelyincorporated in the Zollverein of the German Empire.   He may dreamof commanding the Black Sea as he now commands the Baltic.   Through Persia and Afghanistan he may hope that he or hissuccessors will menace India,and, as the virtual protector of allthe Rusr^ias, he iiiay aim at restoring tho German oconomic andpolitical position in China.   Tho unwisdom which unchained thiswar may well bo capable of still wilder folliesj  and it is a
characteristic of the politically unripe Gorman nation that theyeasily fall a prey to the wilder suggestive power of inordinateambitions,G.   Meanwhile, as it is universally admitted, the bitternessleft by the politically ineffective strike remains,  -The militaristtreatment of tho strikes and of tha press which tried to interprettheir views combines to rankle in tho mind of the masses,Soheidemann and the Majority Socialists are bound to take account ofthis diBaffeotion on pain of losing to the Minority Socialiststhe bulk of their following in the country,   For the present theMajority leaders are clinging to co-operation wifith the Centre and theRadio als.. It is hoped that a more democratic stand will be madeby these parties, and a by-election on the Rhinejwhere theunofficial, non-annexationist Centre Candidate won the day againstan opponent who was backed by the Catholio annexation!st press,seems to indicate that the Catholic electors refuse to beshepherded into the reactionary and air-.exationist camp,   l?otoworthy,too, is the success of the new &quot;League for Freedomand Fatherland:&apos; started to combat TirpitzU Fatherland Party,The League has already recruited no less than 4,OC0,O0O membersthroughout Germany, and the recruits belong to all the*e partiesof the bloc the Catholic Centre, the Radicals and the SocialDemocracy,   There are even some National Liberals.  A greatpublic meeting held under the auspices of the League In Berlin theother day was addressed by a Catholio, a Socialist, and a rationalLiberal, Deputy.   It appears that the left section of tho NationalLiboi als are beginning to protest against the action of the rightseotion who have gone over bag and ba-\- age to the^reactionariesand  annexation!sts,   As the Frankfurter Zeitung  insists, the
P.S.   The first reports of Count Hertling1s Reichstag Speech ofi-ebruary 25 arrived while this report was being ooncluded.   The speeei:speech will be discussed in a future report.democratic elements in Germany will have to wake up and wagea far more vigorous campaign than they have hitherto contemplatedif militarism and economic and politioal reaction are not tohold the field after the conclusion of peace.

</content>
</cab>
