<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/43/0 images: 331-337</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic (VSajesty&apos;8 Government.)jLLiGizi-CE he .  .u-..y.T--Ts  of  the MINIST1.Y of  iv?orrmon.     I enclose for. the consideration of my Colleaguesa Memorandun upon eertain proposals recently madeby the Minister of propaganda in connection with the     The scheme of the Minister of propaganda Involveson the face of it, the reversal of a decision, recentlyccrae to by the Cabinet, and the dislocation of ailthe arrangements made in this Office, with Cabinetauthority, for organising the intelligence Branchas a part of the Foreign Office work,     I am convinced from what I hear that it willalso involve the dislocation of the IntelligenceBranches of the,Admiralty and War.Office, which areat present co-operating, with perfect harmony &quot;1thmy Department,     I douot, therefore, whether the new scheme willwork satisfactorily in practice, Surely there is alsomuch to he said.against it on grounds of principle,     It is quite true  that propaganda must be basedupon knowledge; but the knowledge required -covers  onlyfraction of that involved in the day to day work ofthe Foreign Office; the Admiralty, and the War Office;and the creation  of a new Department, vhich regardsit us  one  of its functions to co-ordinate all themost confidential  informatien which three otherfEMOHAMDLM  BYTHE SEChaTA^Y OF STATE FOP FOREIGH A?&quot;&quot;AIKS.intelligence Branch of this. Department.-  (f,T,Departments
                    (2).Departments have collected im their own purposes,is not only indefensible irqm the point oi&quot; view oforgan!sation,  but would render secrecy even more&apos;difficult to maintain than it is at present,  .     I need hardly say that the Foreign Office  wouldbe&quot; delighted to give -the Minister of Propagandathe information ho may require for his special  work,and the establishment of a &quot;liaison&quot; officer  tofacilitate intercommunication between the Departmentswould oe welcomed by us,                         A.J.B.FOREIGN OFFICE,  -     28th February,, 1918.
     The question of the transfer to the  foreignOil.ice of the &quot;intelligence Branch&quot;  of the Departmentof information was first raised in November last bythe Director of Information himself, who  requestedthe Foreign Office to take it over on the groundthat it performed a function vhich really belongedto and could be better exercised by  the ForeignOffice, and that such a transfer would secure forit more, cordial co-operation, than .i-t had hithertoreceived, from other intelligence Departments.The Director of Information was- Informed that theForeign Office, had always felt that the&apos; work ofthe intelligence Bureau- was .such as ought to beperformed by them, and that they would long agohave created a special Department for tho purposehad they not been handicapped by shortage of staffand, above all., lack of  soace..  The latter difficultycould  be overcome now that Sir Edward Carson- intendedto concentrate the whole  of the Propaganda Organisationunder  one roof - and the roans in the Foreign Officehitherto occupied by the  Department of informationcould  be utilised to house the &quot;Intelligence Branch&quot;,which  would  be foamed into a Department of the ForeignOffice,  In  these arrangements Sir  E.Carson and theDirector of  Information entirely concurred, and thetransfer would have taken place many weeks ago, hadit not been  for the delays in getting ready theHoward Hotel, destined  for the new  quarters of theDepartment  of Information,                                         So
     So much for the actual negotiations culminatingin the mutual arrangement,  recently sanctioned bythe War Cabinet, which was. the outcome of a loiin-felt want by the Foreign Office and of a year * sexperience gained by the Director of Information.This alone would seem to justify the War&apos; Cabinet&apos;sdecision, but there are other considerations offar-reaching importance,     Lord Beavcrbroo:cls Memorandum, inasmuch asit recommends the amalgamation of Propaganda andIntelligence, is based on a- fundamental fallacy.propaganda and intelligence are two totally differentfunctions; tho former dopends on the latter forinspiration, but in their inherent nature and methodof operation they have nothing in commc.no  Diplomacyand Intelligence have; the one is tho essence of theother-,   It follows that intelligence., whioh is theart of  sifting, appraising and co-ordinating inform a-tion  derived from many different sources, is bestcontrolled; where concerned with foreign countries,by those whom training and experience have madeconversant with the customs, psychology and policiesof other nations, and whose daily task is to supplythe material on which our  own foreign policy isbased,      It is not  the  business of the Foreign Officeto  enter into the questions raised by Lord BeaV^rbrookconcerning  the  Intelligence Branches of the. War  Officeand Admiralty;  the  latter  will no doubt speak for                                        themselves.
 themselves.  But  it may he mentioned  that  the Foreign Office intelligence Service whkh  it was decided to  expand and  develop  BO as to meet the altered conditions Drought ah out &quot;by the new phase into  vhich  the war is-  passing, has been assured the unstinted co-operation of both those  Branches,  In agreement, moreover, with the Director of Informationdt  Was&apos;arranged that the greater part of the staff of  the  &quot;Intelligence Bureau&quot;, to their entire satisfaction, should be merged into the Foreign Office system,  &apos; Trie results-of  their labours, checked and controlled  by the Foreign Office4 and improved by the addition of Information not hitherto at their disposal, will be communicated to the B..artraent responsible-for propaganda,.and-will  thus  furnish &apos;the&quot;nocescary knowledge and &quot;inspiration.   This is the only practical scheme and  in order to  facilitate close co-operation between the Foreign Office and Lord Beaverbrook&apos;s Ministry the appointment of a liaison officer&quot;-between the two Departments would be  of great advantage-.  This -system has been already accepted by Lord  -Northcliffe who is charged with propaganda in  enemy countries; a liaison officer has been appointed:, and the Foreign Office are anxious to do  all in their power to co-operate closely and cordially  with  this new Dep.... tment, There is every reason to believe that the  system will work well and prove a  complete success.      As regards the Secret  Service, the  less said the better,  It must,  however,  be  pointed  out that it is not the fact that the  control  exercised by  the                                         Foreign
Foreign Office is purely nominal, though in navaland military matters a free hand of course is givento tho experts.  Lord Beaverbrook1 s statement thatthe political side of the Secret Service is itsWeakest-may. be a matter of opinion but is nitadmitted,., As a matter of fact.the political sideof^the Secret Service has been developed to such --an extent during the,war that, judging by results,no other foreign service is comparable with it.It is however, only-natural that Lord Beavcrbrookshould .not .be in a position&quot; to give. a balancedopinion, upon a service of V1iich.:the activities,to ensure, success, must necessarily,be-shrouded insecrecy.,  There is also a cardinal axirm of SecretService, of which Lord Beaverbrook may not be aware,namely that two independent organisations existingside by side re-act prejudicially on one another..If Lord Beaverbrook is to run his own intelligence &apos;Service he must employ his o,rn agents, and I thinkthe naval and military experts&apos;will probably confirmmy belief that this would lead to a falling-off inthe flow of information on which.tho army and navydepondo  It is not clear, moreover, why he should  &apos;wish to do so when, under the arrangement made, hecan enjoy the benefits of the existing organisation,     There is much political information  thatreaches the Foreign Office of  such a very secretand delicate&apos;nature  that it would be impossible tocirculate it  for use  in&apos; propaganda Departments&apos;.                                        outside^,
:^uiside, but this information is  essential  foruse in the preparation and control  of reports onpolitical questions  emanating from  the Foreign Officefor the use of. the Cabinet...&apos; it Department of politicalIntelligence outside the.Foreign-  Office- and withoutsue.;: 1: owl edge must necessarily be  severely handlecapped in the: preparation of such reportsv. -     It seems so obviously to .everyohe1 s..advantagethat the process of digesting the material  forpropaganda should, be done in the  Foreign Officethat it is-difficult to see how there can be twoquestions about it.  &quot;The. Foreign  Office ^quXfi^pffibecause they would know that propaganda was.-notbeing, launched, based possibly, on false pronisos^.^&apos;The propaganda Department would gain because agreat deaf of drudgery, would be done for them and;.they would enjoy the benefit bf more complete.,information.  Under  any other arraxigement; a .good-deal, of material would not reach  them in any form,-     In a word Lord Beayerbrook&apos;fe; scheme seemsinferior in. all, respects: to  &quot;that  recently: sanctionedby the War Qa-binete:            t    ,

</content>
</cab>
