<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/125/0 images: 90-174</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential.  .. .,    J* 74i his Document 13 the Property 01 His Britannic EVlaJesty&apos;s GovernmentTKE APPOINTED EX THE CALIHBT TO CONSIDER THE PKOPOSAl/o OF TH3S BF.ITISH TilOPIIiS STATISTICAL COHERENCE,/fcilT,By Cabinet minute 20/2, Conolueion 5 (2) of the 15th April, 1920, a Committee waB appointed under ray chairmanship to examine the proposals of the British ,^empire Statistical Conference, to ascertain the views of the Departments affected, and to report to the Cabinet, In submitting, in accordance with this instruction the two appended reports, 1 have to express my regret that my Committee have been unable to agree on a unanimous recommendation.The proposals of the British empire Statistical Conference are embodied in the &quot;Report and Resolutions&quot; of that Conference (Cmd.648 of 1920).        The most important of these is that in favour of the establishment of an Imperial Statistical Bureau.        The Conference recommended that the Bureau should be established in London, that the different Governments of the itopire should be financially responsible for it, and that its operations should be controlled by a Council, incorporated by Royal Charter, consisting of nominees of those Governments with the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom as Chairman,       The functions of the 1&apos;ureau would be to obtain, co-ordinate, analyse and publish statistical information relating to the empire.      In particular, the Bureau would publish an annual statistical review of the l^empire containing interpretations based upon, or illustrated by the statistical data, and would publish periodical monographs embodying statistics on any matters which might be found desirable for the purpose of assisting the study of sooial and economic conditions anr- progress in the Jmpire.        The
The important character of the functions proposed for the Bureau would bo reflected in the status and emoluments of ito directing staff. It is proposed that in the caeoof the Director these Bhould be those of tho permanent secretary in a Department untfer a Secretary of State end corresponding provisions are proposed for his principalsubordinate0, The initial cost of the Bureau is placed by the Conference at  30,000 per annum and it is proposed that rather more than one-half of the annual charge should be borne by the United Kingdom.The need for the improvement of the present organisation cf imperial Statistics was recognised in general terms both by the Dominions Hoyal Commission and by the Imperial War Cabinet of 1918, but the specific proposals outlined in the preceding paragraph represent the first concrete scheme &quot;which has been formally proposed to the Governments concerned. It was this concrete scheme upen which we were- instructed to obtain the views of the Home Departments, and which in the light of their observations we were called on to examine,We accordingly addressed t i the Home Departments a number of specific questions chiefly directed to ascertaining whether:(l)   they could supply material to the Bureau to enable it to v/ork in the manner contemplated;(2).   they would wish to impose any conditions on the use made by the Bureau of the- materials so supplied; and(3)   they expect to&apos;derive material assistance from tublications of the Bureau,In my opinion, which is shared by those of my colleagues who have signed the Majority-Report, it is clear from the replies . received that, while a considerable measure of assistance mi  lit
bo expected from the Home Departments, thero would, be substantial objections on the part of Beveral of them to the exerciBo by the Buroau of the full powers proposed for it. Such Departments as the Ministry of Health, the Board, of uJduoation, and the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries either deprecate the extent of the powers proposed to be given, or claim that statistics relating to subjects with which they are concerned should be excluded from the purview of the Bureau. Various departments malco reservations asto confidential statistics and practically all of them claim consultation and their concurrence in regard to interpretations and comments by the Bureau upon statistics for which they are responsible, There are few indications of any definiteadvantage expected to be derived by the Departments from the establishment of the Bureau.We concur in the soundness of the reservations and stipulations of the Departments having in view the responsi-bility of Ministers for the work of their Offices.    , V/e believe that if the Bureau is established with the constitution and functions proposed, its powers of independent comment, ostensibly on statistics, but in effect on the policies of which statistics are merely the outcome, may be seriously embarrassing, and this not only to the Home Government in relation to its domestic responsibilities, but to the various Governments concerned in their relations with each other.       The high status suggested for the directing personnel must be taken to indicate the authority proposed to bo conferred upon the publications of the Bureau, and therefore to emphasise the gravity of this issue.?o have considered whether, within such a constitu-tion as is proposed, the powers of the Bureau can be limited
in regard to its functions of interpretation and comment, ;.7e believe that this would he impossible and that if it bo given such functions at all it must have them without restraint,      jgither therefore, the J3uroau mu3t have the right of free comment on all questions or, alternatively, it must refrain from any comment,        The one course appears to us to involve the embarrassing risks above indicated;   the ether course seems to us to limit the Bureau to functions which, in themselves desirable, could be achieved toy other and simpler means,vve have not overlooked such apparent precedents for a Bureau with the constitution proposed as those of the Imperial Mineral Resources Bureau and the Bureau of Mycology. v7a find, however, no real analogy between these organisations and the pro posed imperial Statistical Bureau,      The presentation of statistics by a representative Imperial body, and in particular cf interpretative comments on statistics expressive cf policy, involves, in our view, a rmch greater possibility of controversy end of t-moerrassment to the Governments concerned, than is the case where the functions assigned to the organisation are directed to purely scientific ends,We understand that the Government of Australia declines, in effectt to co-operate in the establishment of the Bureau unless the Home Government sets up a Central statistical Office for the United Kingdom. In a previous Report, our Committee hasadvlsed unanimously against such a project, and. the Government has accepted our report.        It would appear, therefore, that unless and until one of the two Governments ooncerned revokes its oocision it would be useless to hope that even if the scheme proposed were acceptable it could be brought into operation for the whole of the empire.
IFor those and&apos; other reasons, which we have discussed in our report, the majority of my Committee recommendthat the Government should not accede to the establishment,at the present time, of such an organisation as that proposed, but that in lieu thereof, consideration should begiven to the improvement of existing publications ofImperial Statistics, Per this purpose, we think thatvarious Departments could render assistance in regard tothe statistics in which they are especially interested andwo recommend that the subject should be referred to thenew Permanent Consultative Committee Of Official, Statisticians,it being understood (1) that the co-operation of theDominions would be sought, and (il) that the volumes to bepublished would contain no comments or interpretations.fThe Minority He port is signed by fou^jmembers of the Committee, who have supplied, me with the following summary of their arguments and conclusions:-(a) The idea of an Empire Statistics Bureau was generally approved by the Dominions Royal Commission (1914) and. by the Imperial War Conference (1916),(b) The scheme for the Bureau was adopted by a large majority including the representatives of all the Dominions, at the Imperial Statistical Conference of 1920.(c) The Dominion Governments have agreed to support the scheme prepared by the Conference, subject to some qualification in the case of Australia.(d) The general attitude of the Home Departments towards the scheme is favourable, provided that they are consulted as to any interpretations by the bureau of statistics for which they ere responsible.(o)   There is no adequate warrant for the fears expressed in the majority report that interpretations must involve criticisms of policy and therefore create friction both with the Home Departments and with the Dominion Governments,      Safeguards aro provided by the proposed Council of the-Bureau, the Advisory Committee and the qualifications of the Director,
(f) The question of eueh intorpretation a being published was ^ fully considered by the Imperial Statistical Conference,   fjj which held that they were necessary, in order to render statistics intelligible arid useful, .(g) This necessity is admitted by the proposed, in the majority report, to include &quot;explanatory noto-e&quot; in a new Abstractof empire Gtatistica.(h) This new Statistical Abstract would require a considerable staff of experts, and if prepared by United Kingdom officials only, would not command the confidence of the Dominions,(i) Precedents exist for Imperial organisations,dealing with matters neither political nor administrative.       Such organisations need not be responsible to any individual Minister.(j)   while the .Bureau would naturally be attached to any more comprehensive Imperial organisation, ita establishment need not wait for the creation of euoh a body,,Ff*r the we and other reasons, those of my colleagues whohave signed the minority report therefore recommend that if theproposed scheme is supported by a substantial majority of theMinisters from tbe dominion8 attending the forthcoming ImperialConference, His Majesty1s Government should concur in theappointment of a Cenrolttoe to settle the necessary details.1 Sri j B i r fYour obedient Servant,The Secretary,Cabinet Offices,
EMITTED TO COIISIDSH THE PROPOSALS OP TH2 tfTISH EWCPIB3 STATISTICAL COIFEKI^&quot;CScMAJORITY REPORT.-,
COiVuilTTSTS TO CONSIDER TH3 PROPOSALS Oij&apos; THE BRITISH BiaPIxtE STATISTICAL CONtfEilSNCE.MAJOiUTY aiSPOiiT.1.    By Cabinet&apos; Minute 20/ii conclusion 5(2) of the 15th April, 1920, a Committee was appointed to examine the proposals of the British Empire Statistical Conference, to ascertain the views of the Departments affected, and to report to the Cabinet.     As the majority of the Committee we have the honour to submit the following report,2-    The report and resolutions of the British Empire Statistical Conference were laid before the Cabinet by the President of the Board of Trade and the minister of Health under cover of their memoranda oi the 30th inarch, 1920, and were presented to Parliament as Cmd. 648 of 1920,3.     The Conference passed 90 resolutions relating to the organisation of statistics, and to the statistics of trade, production, population, prices and index numbers, and finance.     The resolutions&apos;may be divided conveniently into two groups(a) resolutions 1 to 1? relate to the establishment of a British Empire Statistical Bureau, and to the organisation and functions of statistical offices in general;&quot;(b) re&amp;ulutions 18 to 90, relating to technical matters are directed towards the improvement of the statistics compiled in the different parts of the Empire, and to securing a greater degree of uniformity in those statistics than at present exists.4.     vve have thought it unnecessary to examine in detail the second group of resolutions.     The nome Departmentsaffected have not desired to comment at length upon themand, moreover, effect can be given to these resolutions under present arrangements independently of the establishment ofa British Empire Statistical Bureau.5.     This report is thus concerned entirely with such of the resolutions of the Conference as relate to the
establishment oi n British Empire Statistical Bureau.PROPOSED SCHEME). 6.     Tho ochomc for the establishment rf an Empiro Statistical Bureau contained in Resolution?! Hoe. 1 to 10 oftho Imperial Statistical Conference may be summarised as follows(a) The Bureau is to be established in London andjis tc be maintained by joint contributions from the various countries of the Empire concerned in its establishment(b) The governing body is to be a council, Incorporated by rioyal Charter, consisting of the Prime Minister of tho United Kingdom, as President (in his capacity as ox-ofi icio President of the Imperial Conference) and 22 members nominated by the Governments assenting to the scheme in the following proportions viz:* United Kingdom, 10 members;   India and the self-governing Dominions 2 members each;   Colonies,and Protectorates, 2 members.(c) Tho Council would be responsible for the general administratirn and for the financial control of the Bureau, and in the latter respect would be&apos; responsible to each of the contributing Governments.(d) The Council should appoint a permanent Advisory. Committee consisting of not less than-12 members of tho Council and other members (including for example representatives of economic, commercial * industrial and financial interests in important parts of the Empire) to be co-opted.     The duty of the Advisory Committee would be to assist the Director of the Bureau who would act as its Chairman, (o)     The Staff would consist of a. Director appointed by tho Council after consultation with the governments concerned, who would be an expert statistician
Of approved administrative andjpff ioial experience and ability, assisted &quot;by an adequate number of Chief Professional Assistants and other technical and clerical staff, (f)      The emoluments of the Director would be at least equivalent to those of a  ornancnt Secretary of a Department under a Secretary of State, and the emoluments of the chief professional assistants would be at least equivalent to those of officers of the grade of assistant secretary in such a department. A proportion of these assistants would be provided by loan for determinate periods from the statistical staffs of Indian and -Dominion Statistical Offices and, reciprocally, oiiicers of the Buraau might be seconded for v/ork in the Indian or in a Dominion Statistical Office under suitable arrangements as to salary and additional allowances.(g) The functions of the Bureau would be to obtain, co-ordinate, analyse and publish statistical informa-tion relating to the whole of the British Empire. From time to tiraq, the Bureau would communicate suggestions for variations in the form of, or for add!&quot; tione to, existing statistics, for the consideration of the statistical authorities concerned v/ithin the limits imposed by statutory or other local conditions.     The Bureau would provide the &quot;co-ordinating link&quot; between the various statistical organisations throughout the Empire.(h) The bureau would publish an annual statistical review of the Empire, bringing together the statistics supplied by the various countries in a &quot;correlated and aggregated form&quot;, and containing interpretations based upon or illustrated by the statistical data, and surveying the resources of development and activities
of the Empire.    The Bureau would also publish periodical monographs embodying statistics of trade, production, transport, communication, population, lab our and industries, finance or any other matter whioh might be found desirable for tho purpose of assisting tho study or social and economic conditions and progress  n the Empire.Without attempting a close estimate the Conference was of opinion that the coot of the Bureau in the first complete year of its existence would be about . 30,000, of which it was proposed, &quot;on enabasis of apportionment beforeAthe Conference&quot; that the United Kingdom should bear  16,000 .7.    In order to appreciate the bearing of these recommendations, it is necessary to refer briefly to the circumstances in which the Imperial Statistical Conference was called on to consider the establishment of an Imperial Statistical Bureau.8. The Dominions -loyal Commission which was sot up in 1913 to enquire and report upon the natural resources of the Dominions and their development, the trade of those parts of the Empire with the United Kingdom, each other and the restof the world, and their requirements, and those of the United Kingdom in the matter of food and raw materials, pointed out in their final report dated 21st February, 1917, (Cd.8462 of lulV) that their attention had been called to the need for improvement in the Imperial Statistics bearing upon the subjects upon v/nich they had been asked to report.      After a reference (in paragraph 672 of their report) to certain specific defects for which thoy suggestedX This estimate was presumably framed with reference to the conditions as to salary and bonus which prevailed at the end of 1919, subsequent to which date the emoluments of officers of the status contemplated for the Director of tho Bureau have been substantially increased in accordance with the recommendations of tho Committee appointed to advise as to the Salaries of the Principal Posts in the Civil Service (Cmd. 1188).m    4    *
suggested specific remedies they went on to mention (para.676) the absence cf any institution specially charged with the work of collecting, collating and preparing -Statistic! for the Empire as a whole, and to state that the establishment of such an institution had been advocated by several statisticians who had given evidence before them.    The report continues - &quot;we gather that the Board of Trade is disposed to favour the establishment of such a Bureau, which might take ever the compilation of some of the Statistics now prepared by that Department.     We are of opinion that the creation cf some Office of the kind is eminently desirable&quot;.9.    The kind of Bureau contemplated by the Board of Trade to which the report refers and the establishment of which the Commission considered desirable, is indicated in a memorandum submitted in evidence before the Commission by Sir Herbert Llewellyn Smith. -  This memorandum after throwing a certain amount q* doubt on the proposals put before the Commission at an earlier date by Dr. Bpv/ioy, states that &quot;there is, however, a good deal to be said for the establishment of an Imperial Bureau for the compilation, in a convenient form, of annual or other periodcal digests and summaries of Imperial Statistics if located in London, 1 do not think therc^would be any insuperable difficulty in putting it, if desired, under the immediate management of the Board of Trade, while the general scope of its operations might bo regulated and supervised by an Inter-Imperial Committee&quot;.  ,.10.    It is important to note that the scheme reaemmen-ded by the doyal Commission thus differs materially from that put forward by two other Schemes submitted to them, nnc by kr* G.H. Knibba, C.^.G.t Commonwealth Statistician, Australia, and the other by Dr. A.L. Bowley, University of London.   That of Mr. Knibbs extended over an area of statistical activity far wider tnan that which fell within the purview of tile xioyal Commission, as indicated in its terms of reference.
Moreover it assumed the office which he desired to see established to be vested with wide powers of analysis and interpretative comment.     Dr. Bowley on the other hand appears to have regarded the compilation on a continuous plan of current trade statistics, and their issue at monthly intervals for the information of traders and others, as the essential feature of an Imperial Statistical Office; and lavs no stress on the functions of analysis and inter-pretation of statistics in general which is so prominent a feature of the alternative plan.11.   The *toyal Commission warmly commended Dr. Bowley&apos;s scheme for the speeding up of monthly&apos; trade statistics, but did not apparently regard the scheme as in any strict sense dependent on the institution of a central Statistical Office,12.   The wider scheme urged upon them by       Knibbs was not recommended by the Commission.13.     J? oil owing the report of the .ioyal Commissionimmediate steps were taken by the Government of the day toiascertain theviews of the Dominions not only on the proposal to hold an Imperial btatistical Conference but on the specific proposal for an Imperial Bureau, as outlined in the memorandum on Imperial Statistics submitted to them by the Board of Trade.14.   In their replies to this specific enquiry, the Governments of Newfoundland, Australia and South-Africa suggested that the question of an Imperial Statistical Bureau snould be held over for consideration at the Imperial Statis-tical Conference,     The Government of Canada insisted&quot; however that the question should be discussed at the imperial Conference itself;   and at the Imperial war Conferjenco of 1916 ivir. i*eighen moved the following resolution :-&quot;Tire Imperial war Conference having considered the correspondence as to the improvement of Imperial statistics
arising out oi the recommendations 01 the i,* opinions doyal Commission, is in favour oi the proposal to hold a conference of statisticians after the war, and also agrees in principle to tho establishment of an Imperial Statistical Bureau under the supervision of an Inter-lmporial Committee&quot;.15.     Prom the discussion which took place &quot;Extracts from minutes of the Proceedings and Papers laid before the Conference Cd. 9177 of 1918 pp 80-87) it is clear that the Dominion repreeentativce had trade considerations almost Wholly in view and that some of them were doubtful of the utility of tho proposed organisation pending the definition of some Imperial policy, particularly in relation to trade. At the same time there was practical unanimity as to the necessity lor collecting facts and for making them available. ab a result of the discussion the resolution ao originally proposed was amended,- the words &quot;and also agrees in principle to&quot; being deleted fr,om the resolution and the words &quot;and that such Conference consider&apos;1 being substituted.16,&apos;    we thus see that oi tho three schemes, for the improved organisation oi Imperial -Statistics put before the Dominions aoya 1 Commission, (one by Dr. Bow ley for a s.:sall central organisation for speeding&quot; up&quot;certain trade statistics, ofte by a\ Iinibbs for a Central statistical office with extremely wide field and functions, and v/itn, preferably, an independent status, and one by the Board of Trade amounting to little more than a proposal to expand the present statis-tical organisation of that Department in so far as it deals with Imperial statistics it was the Board of Trade scheme that the Dominions wore asked to consider and that the Dominions were unable to agree to any express recommendation even of this proposal.     At the same time, they were sufficiently1 impressed with the- heed for greater co-ordination of Imperial Statistics to recommend that the proposal should be further considered bv an Imperial
Statistical C o nler er.ce.17.   It will be apparent however from the summary which we have given above of the Statistical Conferences proposals that the scheme on which we are asked to report, is based not upon that suggested by the Board of Trade and considered by the Imperial Conference, but on that put forward in evi-dence before the Dominions -ioyal Commission by io\ Knibbs and subsequently elaborated in a document circulated by him to the Statistical Conference.     The absence from the report of this Conference of any reference to the alternative schemes favoured by eminent official and statistical authorities suggests the existence bf a greater approach to unanimity among statistical experts on the question of the most practical organisation of Imperial Statistics, than we think actually exists.18,     In one respect the Conference^ recommendation goes beyond the original proposal of Mr. Knibbs, who, in a memorandum prepared by him for the Dominions 4oyal Commission and submitted to them at Melbourne on the 5th my, 1913, (Cmd. 7172 of 1913) made the following remarks ;-&quot;Whether the Central Bureau should be an independent body or should be attached to the proposed imperial Seeretarr iat requires careful consideration, and much will depend on the constitution of the Secretariat.     In any case there would be no need to await the development of the Imperial Secre-tariat before instituting the Central Statistical Bureau., and, if necessary, it Could in the meantime be attached to the Board of Trade or the Colonial Office or could be constituted an independent organisation&quot;.     lor, Knibbs1 memorandum continues with a strong recommendation in favour of an independent organisation but it will be clear that he was not, at that date, prepared to rule out as useless the alternative organisation which would place the
Bureau, for the time being, under one 01 the home depart-merits.     On the other hand the Imperial Statistical Conference make no suggestion of any alternative organisation.19.   we approached the consideration of the Conference^ proposals with a full sense of the responsibility which had been placed upon us, appreciating not only the ideals which animated the Conference but confirmed in our general recogni-tion of the need for the bettor co-ordination of Imperial Statistics by the unanimity of opinion expressed on this point at the Imperial War Conference of 1918.     At the same time, the fact that the functions to be discharged by the Bureau under the scheme before us were far wider than those contemplated for any Imperial Statistical organisation recommended by the Dominions rioyal Commission and subsequently considered by the Imperial Conference, coupled with the fact that these functions were to be discharged by an independent organisation having no woll-dofined place in the constitu-tional hierarchy made it necessary for us to consider not only what reaction its establishment might have on the policy of the Home Government as expressed through the different Departments, but also whether the range of functions suggested for the Bureau was such as to ensure that it would be advis-able for us to recommend the Government to support, at tho present stage of Imperial development, the creation of an independent Imperial organisation possessing these functions.20.     moreover it seemed to us apparent that for financial no less than constitutional reasonst only the most urgent public need, and a reasonable assurance that this need would be met by the Conference^ proposals, could justify us in recommending any scheme of the novel, ambitious and expensive character now proposed.21,     In order best to ascertain the views of the Home Departments on the proposals of the Conference we circulated
to all Departments affected, a questionnaire, the ter^is of which were directed by the considerations above indicated,   a copy, oi this questionnaire is appended, with the replies of the chief Departments to those questions which raised the more important points.     We also found it desirable to talcs certain oral evidence on the wider statistical and constitu-tional questions involved, and this also is appended.22.     It will be seen from our questionnaire that in order to ascertain the views of the Home Departments with reference to the proposal, we asked each Department for somewhat detailed information as to(l)   Its published statistice and unpublished statistics or statistical material.(2)   The extent to wnich and the conditions on which it could supply such statistics or statistical material to the Bureau.(3)   The extent to which it would think it necessary to regulate the use made by the Bureau of Departmental Statistics in order to avoid embarrassing conflict of view.(4)   Whether in the discharge of its own administrative duties it would be likely to find the. Bureau of assistance.(5)   whether it wished to be represented on the Council of the Bureau.23.   It is clear that the Bureau would have access to all the published statistics of the Home Departments.   From the replies to our enquiries it would appear that in addition most of the principal departments possess, in varying degress, other statistics and statistical material, which is not published. In many cases, these statistics are compiled for internal and administrative purposes, or for special ad hoc purposes, in circumstances vvhich make them oi a confidential nature.     The willingness oi departments to furnish such statistics and material to the Bureau depends upon the circumstances of each particular case.     Some information could be furnished to the
Bureau for confidential information, some for its general use, and some (particular information on confidential enquiries.) must be withheld.   In tills connection, a limitation upon the assistance given to the Bureau is made dependent upon the amount of work and expense which would be laid upon the particular department. Where the department concerned felt that the value of the information sought did not justify the expense, or that its value to the department of origin was negligible, no assistance would be given.   In themajority of cases, the departments would be willing to furnish to the Bureau copies of the forms used with explanatory memoranda except where they were of e  confidential natures24,   jitost of the departments&apos;would be willing to furnish to the Bureau any necessary explanations-as to the nature of the material dealt with, the sources whence it is derived, and the methods of compilation adopted by the department.   The Ministry of health, while it would be willing to reply to specific enquiries, could not undertake to give sufficiently exhaustive explanations to enable the Bureau to assess the validity of the material and to allow for its biases and qualifications,, for this would involve the attempt to put the Bureau into possession of the highly specialised technical knowledge which in some cases (particularly as respects medical statistics) would be essential to a full appreciation of the subject matter.25.   a wide devergence of view exists among the departments with regard to the proposed inclusion in annual or other statistical reviews published by the Bureau, of interpretations based upon or illustrated-by the statistical data, and the proposed publication of monographs embodying statistics of trade, production, transport, communication, population, labour and industries, finance or any other matter which may be found
doeiratio for the purpose of assisting the study of social and economic conditions and progress in the Empire.   The ministry of Agriculture deprecates the issue of any publication containing comments or interpretations oi statistics compiled by the   - department.     The ministry of Health could not be indifferent to the possibility of monographs and statistical treatises being issued by the Bureau containing constructive interpretations and comment upon matters falling within the province for which the Department is responsible to the Parliament of the United Kingdom.     It points out that it is clearly conceivable that an independent authority such as the Bureau might quite honestly draw from statistical material conclusions as to policy which conflicted v/itu those drawn with equal honesty by the Department concerned from the s^mo data,   and it states that in view of the authoritative official status of the Bureau such conflict would undoubtedly embarrass the Department in the discharge of its responsibilities.     This ministry indeed doubts whether any such Bureau would be competent to produce sound and reliable work of the kind contemplated, so far as healtn statistics aro concerned, and is therefore apprehensive that there may be embarrassing devergenciec of view.   The ministry of Health thus desires to adopt an attitude of caution to these particular proposals.     It would nevertneless be prepared to contribute to the Bureau its considered views upon any particular matters within its province which might be the subject oi study by the Bureau as regards the Empire as a whole.     The Home Office, Board of Trade and -the Ministry of Labour, view the proposal favourably, under the safeguards provided in the scheme, and other offices such as the Board of Inland Revenue and the ministry of Transport have no objection to offer.     All statistically important departments, however, desired to be consulted in reference to the interpretation of their statistics, and in most cases stipulate that their concurrence must be obtained. They are in all cases willing to undertake the examination, before publication, of proposed statistical reviews and monographs.
26.   Except in the cane of the Home Office, which scorns to have anticipated that the scope of the Bureau would be ouch as to enable it to advise in regard to administrative questions and proposals for legislation already dealt with by overseas coiiimunitiea and further states that, as a centre of statistical information the Bureau would save much time, trouble and expense, the replies received to our enquiries regarding the probable utility of the Bureau to Home Depart-ments werenot very definite.   Some Departments anticipate generally that, under the proposed Bureau, Imperial Statis-tics would be(l)   more readily available(2)   co-ordinated to a greater degree, and(3)   compiled in greater detail;but, apparently, it is rather from the incidental developmentof existing Imperial Statistics along these lines, to whichthey consider that the establishment of the Bureau would give an impetus, than to a definite expansion in the scope ofImperial Statistics, that they look for advantage.   In regardto other Departments it is not clear whether they consider thata wider range of statistics would be made available to them or merely that it would be more convenient to obtain statisticsfrom an office in London than through correspondence with india   and the Dominions.   On the whole we are left with theimpression that these Departments are supporting the scheme as an abstract proposition rather than expecting individuallyto derive definite benefit from the existence of the Bureau.27.    The following views, expressed by Departments  &apos;in the course of their replies to our questionnaire, seem tous to call for particular mention(a)   The Board of Education who are in doubt as towhether the Bureau would deal with educationalstatistics, point out that the satisfactory colla-tion of the statistical returns of educational- 13 -
systems throughout the Empire could only be under-taken with a considerable expenditure of time and thought.   Official statistics of education at present published throughout the Empire are not identical in the range of facts which they portray nor are they constructed in such a way as to facilitate-comparison even where the material with which they doal is similar in character.   The terms employed in various ports of the Umpire do not always bear the same significance.   Until these difficulties are in a ,\fair way to be overcome (which it is hoped to accomplish through the Imperial Education Conference), it is felt that no useful purpose would bo served by the inclusion of educational statistics within the purview of the proposed Empire Bureau.The Ministry of Health advert to the omission from the general scheme of the Bureau of any provision defining its position in relation to the organisa-tion of the League of Nations, and moved by the special nature of its own responsibilities in regard to health, considers that an Empire Bureau if established, will need to be brought into definite relation to the projected League of Nations Statis-tical organisation.The Colonial Office, while not anticipating that the bureau will be of any great assistance in the normaladministration of the Colonies and Protectoratesadministered by the Department, has no doubt thatsuch a Bureau would be useful in supplying material for consideration of questions of policy affectingthe Empire as a whole, and in affording authoritativeguidance in statistical questions.    It is thereforewilling to co-operate in the direction of obtaining- 14 -
the fullest possible information from the Colonies and Protectorates for the Use of the Bureau, (d)   The Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries expresses the opinion that statistics of agricultural production cannot be properly considered with reference to the British empire alone, points out that the compilation of annual and other abstracts is already being done very efficiently by the International Agricultural Institute at Rome, and accordingly suggests that it would be a matter for consideration how far such -statistics could, in order to avoid duplication, be excluded from the purview of the Bureau,28,   The following Departments think it necessary to be represented on the Council of the Bureau should it be established.   The Board of Trade, War Office, Board of Inland Revenue, Ministry of Health, General Register Office, Colonial Office, Registrar of Friendly Societies, Admiralty, Ministry of Labour, Ministry of Agriculture and fisheries Ministry of Pensions, Ministry of Transport, Board of Control, Scottish Office, Registrar General1s Department, (Scotland),Fishery Board for Scotland, -Scottish Board of Health, Depart-f itment of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland, General Register Office, Ireland.   The Board of Customs and Excise reserves this question.     The Board of Education, having regard to its view that educational statistics should be excluded, states that at the present stage it does not desire to be directly represented on the Council.29, &apos; Generally it will be observed from the replies that in the view of the Hoirj Departments, the Imperial Statistical Bureau must either refrain from the analysis or interpretation of Official Statistics published by those Departmental? its relationship with them must be such as to ensure that the analysis and interpretations put forward are, in fact, those of the Departments and not those of an inde-pendent statistical body.      , -
30,   The unanimity with which the Homo Departments nave put forward these views confirms uo in our interpreta-tion of the nature and scope of the Conference^ proposals. It seems to us clear that tho object which the Conference had in view was to create an organisation which in its detached position would be enabled to exercise the functions of an independent critical organisation,    Such a pov/er would of course involve a constitutional innovation of some magnitude-tude,a point which, if our interpretation of its intention bccorrect, the Conference did not perhaps sufficiently appreciate.31*   The ConferencReport emphasises in a moat ,.marked fashion the important position to be occupied by. the Bureau,   The Chariman of the Council is to be, not a Depart-mental Minister, but the Prime Minister of the United &quot;Kingdom, and his colleagues are specifically referred to as vrepresentatives of the Governments concerned,   We can only assume that bo far as the Dominions are concerned officials of at least the status of the High Commissioners are here in -view.   Such a Council, if placed in control of a scientific Bureau, might be content to exercise a nominal suzerainty but to adopt the-phrase employed by Mr, Hughes when speaking&quot;&quot;&apos; on the question at the Imperial War Conference Hhis is a different matter&quot;,   The nature and scope of the subject--matter and functions of a Bureau of Entomology or Mycology, -or even of an Imperial Mineral Resources Bureau,  seem to us to differ,so far from those of the Bureau which we are con-sidering as to afford.little,if any( ground for an argumentby       -      from them.   Accordingly we are convinced that such*  analogyCouncil as that proposed would be regarded as responsible in a very real sense to the different Parliaments of the Empire for the publications of the Bureau,   This is of chief Importance because on all matters of policy which had-a -statistical aspect and in regard to which the trend of
particular policies could be statistically illustrated, or could be thought capable of such illustration, the Bureau would be the centre of enquiry to which every advocate or opponent of every policy would naturally turn, and its answers would inevitably be regarded as autnoritative.32.   Finally the express view of the Conference on the functions of a Statistical Office appears to us to negative any but the widest interpretation of the functions which they propose to allot to the Bureau.   In this conneo-tion Resolution 11 of the Report is of importance,   This resolution records&quot; the opinion that the functions of no statistical office can be exereisedproperly when limited to the initial work of collecting and compiling figures and indicates, inter alia, that these functions should include &quot;the utilisation of the special &quot;knowledge and experience &quot;gained in the course of the work of tabulating the statistics, &quot;and the critical analysis of the results&quot; in nuch a way as to &quot;indicate most clearly their value and significance&quot;.   We must assume that no loss important functions arepronosed to beT   &quot;assigned to the central Bureau than it would be desired to give to the statistical office of a particular State or of a particular Department, and that the extent and responsibility of these functions is reflected in the status proposed to * be conferred upon the directing personnel of the Bureau.33.   Such being our interpretation of the proposals made in the report, it appeared to us to be necessary to explore the possible consequences of their adoption.34.   To establish a statistical Bureau with an official status, and to endow it with the wide functions to which we have referred in paragraph 32 above, i3 in our opinio to vest it, as a matter of course, with critical powers in regard to any policies of which the tendencies may be statis-tically illustrated,   tthen this is understood, the relations of such a Bureau to those who are responsible for the policies-liable to be brought under review is conceivably a matter of
the first importance.35,   On the one hand the Prime Minister, as the Chairman of the Council of the Bureau, would presumably have to accept responsibility for the decisions of a majority of the Council.   On the other hand, tho Prime Minister would be responsible to the Imperial Parliament- * for bringing to the notice of the Council the views of the Home Government in regard to any proposed publicati one. In a dispute between the Home Government and the Bureau the Prime Minister would apparently be committed to representing the views of both the contending parties.4.36.   The difficulty on this point appears to have been appreciated by the Home Departments,   At any rate from their replies to our questionnaire it is clear that, so far from regarding the proposed Bureau as an indepen-dent organisation which, without constitutional impropriety or political disadvantage, could comment freely on statistical data freely supplied to it, they regarded it as a proposal for an Imperial organisation speaking authoritative^/&quot; on behalf of the government contributing, to its maintenance.37.    It has been suggested that, however difficultmay be the theory of the constitutional relationship of theproposed Bureau to the Home and Dominion Governments, no practical difficulties are likely to arise.   In pursuanceof this line of argument, it is said that the high personalcharacter and qualifications cf  the Director no less thanthe understanding with Home Departments as to prior con-sultation before any use is made of their statistics wouldprovide sufficient safeguards against divergence of view between the policy which might appear to be advocated bythe publications of the Bureau and that which was being pursued at the time by the respective Departments,   further,- 18 -
it has been suggested that it might be worth While to obtain even greater security against these riska by includ- . ing a provision in the Charter which should operate to restrict the discretion of the BUroau (i,o, the Director, the Council, and, we presume,&quot;the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom collectively) in tho exercise of tho powers of interpretation conferred upon it,i5S,    It is no doubt the case that therewill be noInecessary conflict between the policy of the Home Govern-mcnt and that of the proposed Bureau.   We are, however,quite unable to&apos;agree that the likelihood of such a conflictcan be ignored,   We have referred above to the instance ofsuch possible conflict which had been adduced by the Ministryof Health.   It will be apparent that in the matter of Tradestatistics (a point to which Lord Southborou&amp;h alluded inhis evidence appended to this Keport) there is no less apossibility that, should questions of fiscal policy againbecome a prominent issue in domestic politics, the viewsof the different Governments of the Empire might.not be identical.    In connection with such questions the proposedBureau might well bo called upon to produce monographs orreturns which would be seized upon as illustrating theadvantages or disadvantages of a policy which might be in dispute in different parts of tho Empire.39.    V.re do not doubt that the Director would bemindful of his responsibilities to the Council and of theextent to which the destinies of tho Bureau wore dependenton the manner in which those responsibilities were fulfilled.But obviously he would be liable to be placed from time totime in a position of peculiar difficulty and it appears tous unreasonable to assume, where so much is involved, that inthe c-refulness of his selection, adequate security againstconstitutional difficulties would,  in fact, be attained.If we arc right in our interpretation of the scope of the- 19 - &apos;
problem we cannot advise the government to ^e a party to proceeding with the scheme ass presented on the supposition that even if it be unsound in principle the chief official of the Bureau will make it acceptable in practice^40.   We cannot believe that any attempt to  \ limit the powers of the Bureau by an indefinite formula in restraint of its functions is likely to prove successful.   The Conference&apos;s Report contemplates no such restriction.   The weight which it attacheat0 the qualifications of the Director of the Bureau seems, indeed, to be inconsistent with such a suggestion,   fa have not had the advantage of hearing the precise terms of the provision to this end which it would be proposed to insert in the Bureau1a Charter.   Their formulation may bo expected to give difficulty to the draftsman. But the importance of the suggestion is in our view that it leads to the conclusion that a definite and unqualified decision must be taken on the question of giving inter-pretative functions to the Bureau,   If they are given, they must in our   opinion be given without reservation, a course which, for the reasons stated in this Report, we cannot recommend.   If&apos; they are withhold, it is obvious that such developments of work in relation to Imperialstatistics as would remain to be put in hand might be...efficiently undertaken without the ee t abllsTWRt.- of an organisation involving the creation of a new and highly paid staff of statistical officers,41,   Having realised in the course of our deliberations that issues of some nagnitude would arise. ;, ^ &apos;    :    .    ...    .   I -on the specific proposal made by the Conferencowe decided that it was desirable to take evidence on the proposal before us from persons, who, while competent to express an authoritative view upon it, either from the statisticalor the administrative point of view, were not limited in* 20 -_____     ......-_______________  ........     .
their expression of opinion by official responsibilities.We therefore asked Sir Joslah Stamp and lord Southborough,as former Civil Servants of wide experience gained indifferent spheres of official life, to give evidence beforethe Committee and in order to get the full benefit of their advice submitted for their inspection the replies of the moreimportant Departments toWr questionnaire.i i42.   The evidencc&amp;iven beforeus by Sir Josiah Stamp, was directed to an examination of the specific services which an Imperial Bureau might render tcjthe Home Departments without tho risk of divergences of view arising.   Ho considered that the Departments, in their replies toour questionnaire, had failed to appreciate the wide field over which the activities of the Bureau could -range without raising any controversial question, and in consequence had.greatly exaggerated the difficulties which would arise from vesting it with the functions proposed.   He felt certain that the Bureau, if estab lished, would devote itself to these non-controversial questions in the early years of its existence, and that only later, when, the Bureau had acquired a working experience and could obtain the willing co-operation of the Departments, would it venture on fields which might otherwise be. contro-versial.   At the same time he felt that the Bureau could never occupy its intended position in the official hierarchy if, falling agreement, it were compelled ultimately to take upon its official publications the impress of the policies of the Governments concerned in every case.   To prevent this he suggested -that the Bureau should have certain independent powers of appeal and in the case of dispute between Itself and a Department of the Home Government he suggested an Appeal Tribunal composed of a Cabinet Minister, a Judge of the High Court, and an eminent Statistician.   He took the view that the existence of such a Tribunal would serve as a salutary check on any tendency which the Government might have towards the suprossion of statistical information which, though of public
value, night appear to challenge its political policy.In the case of&quot; a dispute &quot;between the Bureau and aDominioniGovernment ho would provide for appropriate variation of the constitution of thin appellate Tribunal.43.  tfhXortuhabcIy    as it appears to us, tho settlement of differences of opinion by methods such as this would givo rise to difficulties as great as those they were intended to solve.   A dispute with a Government Department presided over by a Minister of the Crown would, in fact, be a disxjute with the Government, which in view of its responsibility to Parliament could not consent to be over-ruled by an independent Tribunal, especially where the question at issue involved, as generally would be the case, considerations either of Governmental policy or public expenditure.   It is necessary to add that in the event of any such dispute arising the position would be further complicated by th* fact, to which we have already called attention, that (assuming the full scheme as proposed by the Conference to have been adopted) the Prime Minister would in his dual capacity be responsible for the policy of each party concerned in the dispute.44.   lord SouthbOiough1s- evidence was dovotod to the examination of the proposals from the Imperial point of view.   In his opinion the real responsibility for the activities of the Bureau would rest upon its Council and ho suggested to us that the Imperial Statis-tical Conference, in taking for granted the assent of the self-governing Dominions to tho creation under Royal Charter of an Imperial organisation on the governing body of which they would be represented officially hut whose pronouncements would not necessarily reflect the policy of their own Governments, had been unduly optimistic.   He would not admit that tho establishment of the Bureau
under Hoy hi Charter, with the Prime Minister as ex-officio President of its Council&apos;,- could affeot in any way the responsibility of the Dominion representatives to their Parliaments, or of the Prime Minister to the Imperial Parliament, for the publications of the Bureau.   Nor was he prepared to suggest *W limitation in the functions outlined for the Bureau which would in his view, ensure that questions which might be controversial in one or other part of the Empire should invariably be excluded from review by the Bureau,   In short, he considered that it was useless to explore further the possibilities of an Imperial-Statistical Bureau until the Dominion Prime ministers, by a Resolution at a future Imperial Conference, had agreed not only in principle,to its establishment but to the precise nature of its functions and of its constitutional relation-ship to their respective Parliaments,45*   Lord Southborough&apos;s view was confirmed by the fact which came to our notioo in the course of our delibera-tions that the Government of Australia had unexpectedly withheld its support from the proposals of tho Imperial Statistical Conference,   While expressing a general approval ef the objects to bo served by the proposed Bureau that Government declined to co-operate in its establishment in view of tho absence of a central statistical Bureau for the United Kingdom.   His Majesty1a Government have already approved our Committee&apos;s Interim Report, which contains a unanimous expression of opinion that a Central StatisticalOffice shouldnot be established for the United Kingdom, andithere is therefore no reason to anticipate that, in so far as its establishment is to bo regarded as a condition precedent to support by the Government of Australia of the larger pro-ject, that condition will bo fulfilled.46,   Briefly to sum up on tho constitutional question we consider that the scheme outlined by the Conferoneo fails to meet the needs of tho oaso for throe reasons:
(a) It is not practicable to oot up an organisation, whether by incorporation under Royal Charter or by any other moans, consisting of nominees of the difforont Parliaments and Governments of tho Empiro, which willnot be held strictly responsible by thoso Parliaments or Governments for the actions of the exouutivo staff placed under their control.(b) Publications of the Bureau containing common-taries On and interpretations of statistics relating to any matters which are or can bo tho subject of political controversy will thus inevitably be regarded as an authori-tative exposition of Imperial policy in regard to those matters, and in so far as Imperial policy as discerned through those publications, appears to be at variance -with the policies of any of tho Governments responsible for the Bureau a situation presenting acute difficulties will at once arise.(c) To attempt to restrict the activities ofjtho Bureau to publications which do not bear upon any policy at the time a matter of controversy in any part of^tho Empire would, in our opinion, prove impracticable.47.   Unless, therefore, the Bureau is tobe limited in its functions to the more aggregation of statistics, in which case the somewhat elaborate organisa-tion suggested by tho Conference is clearly unnecessary, the fadt must be faced that an Imperial Statistical Bureau must have a definite basis in and derive its powers from an Imperial organisation constitutionally qualified to speak for the Empire as a whole. -48.   However desirable in itself may appear to be some Imperial Statistical organisation we consider there-fore that the question of establishing such an organisation as that proposed by the Statistical conference must wait upon and follow the issue of such discussions as may take placeupon the relations between the constituent parts of the- 24 -
Empire.49.   We now proceed to examine the proposal fromthe point of view of ito practical utility to the (Jovern-ments responsible for the maintenance of the Bureau.   Wo.have already indicated our appreciation of the advantages ofbetter co-ordination in Empire Statistics.   We do not,however, share the view, which appears to underlie the Report,that a system producing this result, to be practicallyvaluable to the  peoples responsible foy its cost, must be such as to involve or provide scope for a large amount oforiginal or advanced statistical work.   The material supplied to an Empire Statistical Office must, in the nature ofthe case, be brought together in the Government departments of the several communities from which it emanates.   Much ofit would be of a technical character relating to specialisedsubjects and deriving.its value   to a large extent from the expert knowledge of the branch of administration to which itrelated possessed by those who had compiled and issued it.A central statistical organisation could doubtless exercise a valuable function by summarising any comparable statisticsso compiled, but if it is proposed, as in the Report of theConference, to give to the organisation wider powers thanthese, the proposal1 should be supported by some indication ofthe practical value of the powers in exorcise arid of the disadvantages that would result from their absence,   Y/e havebeen unable tdour regret to derive any help from the Reportin this respect.   The omission of any references by theConference to the purposes to bo served by the wide range of duties with whioh it is proposed to invest the Bureau is amatter of some consequence since, without a clear   perceptionupon this point, it appears to us difficult to justify the elaborate organisation proposed to be set up, with itsDirector and an &quot;adequare number&quot; of Chief ProfessionalAssistants and with its provisions for interchange of staffsbetween statistical offices in the various parts of theEmpire.   In this connection we would refer to tho estimates of- 25 -
initial outlay mentioned in paragraph 6 above.   It is clear to ud on perusal of the Memorandum submitted to the Imperial Statistical Conference by Mr. Knibbs that the expenditure will rapidly increase if the Bureau io to be given the functions and equipped&apos;with the staff which that Memorandum contemplates.50.   As indicating the difficulties attendant upon the determination of the proper functions of such an organisation we refer to the evidence tendered to the Dominions Royal Commission,   Dr, Bowley advised, as indicated in paragraph 10 above, a certain type of statis-tical office.   Mr0 Q.H, Knibbs advocated the establishment of a different kind of office and strongly criticised Dr, Bowleyts proposal, indicating that in his view it would not serve the practical purposes for which Dr.Bowley had proposed it.   It appears to us that if immediate utility in the practical affairs of life is-to be ono of the criteria for the justification of a Statistical Bureau, and to the extent towhich this criterion is valid, the scheme advocated by Mr. Knibbs and adopted by the Imperial Statistical Conference is open to precisely the kind of criticism which he&quot;applied to Dr, Bowley1s project.   It does not appear that the latter gentleman had in mind such an elaborate establishment as the Conference considered requisite for the scheme which they endorsed, and w^think it important to indicate that so far as vre can judge such an establishment is not an essential part of a useful statistical service for the Empire. ,51.   Moreover it is essential to remember that tothe United Kingdom tho value of the proposed Bureau would be&apos;somewhat restricted by the consideration that its area of.operation would be that of the British Empire only.   TheMinistry of Agriculture, in reply to our enquiries, draws attention to the fact that so far as the subject of theactivities of that Department are concerned it is not- 26 -
sufficient to have regard to the 33r tieh jmpire only.      It is indeed obvious that for the purposes of the United Kingdom it is of equally groat importance to obtain statistics relative to agricultural produce in the United States, South America and certain other parts of tho world outside the British empire.      We are also given to understand that in the consideration of transportation problems the Railway Statistics cf the United States, South America and certain European countries are at least of equal importance, to the Home Government, with those of the Dominions,   &apos; Similarly as regards trade and manufactures, our relations with the various nations of Europe, with their teeming populations and important markets, are of vital concern to this country and statistical information bearing upon our commercial in tar-course with them is of no lass weight to us than the like Information regarding our relations with the Dominions,      In another sphere, the Ministry of Health is concerned with figures showing the incidence of disease;   problems as to the improvement of health must be pursued irrespective of geographical frontiers.      It it is accepted that for the development of tho national progress and wellbaing an enlarged statistical conception is essential, that&quot;-conception must embrace a wider field of activity than the British jimpire, and while this affords no argument against the development of Empire Statistics, it enforces the fact that the share of the cost of such a developrtent falling up*n the United Kingdom is not the whole cost of new statistical services to which this country will be subject.52.    We have no-v   described the proposal made by the Imperial Statistical Conference (paragraph 6), have recounted its history (paragraph 7 to 16), have indicated, in accordance with our terms of reference, the views of the departments affected (paragraphs 21 to 29), have discussed its constitutional position and relations to the Governments concern-ed (paragraphs 30to 48) and have submitted our views with regard to
practical utility of an organisation such as the Reportproposes to set up in due relation to tho cost whioh itwould involve (paragraphs 49 - 51).   We have found thaton the constitutional issues involved the eohemo presentsserious difficulties, and that so far as Departments ofthe Home Government are ooncerned there would be consider-able opposition, founded on a realisation of thoso diffi-difficulties, to the exercise ofvthejfull powers proposed.Further, we have indicated that the Report remitted to us for examination includes no convincing argument in supportof the utility of such an elaborate organisation as isproposed, and that there i3 evidence that eminent 3tatis-ticians are not unanimous as to the functions which an imperial Statistical Office should exercise.   Finally wehavo pointed out that the Government of the United Kingdomcannot in its consideration^ statistical developments andtheir cost have regard to the British Empire alone but must give due weight to the varied interests of the oountryin world-statistics.   We have thus been brought, by stages,to the conclusion that His Majesty1 s Government cannot be advised to endorse the proposal- in its present form.53.   We have indicated (paragraph 48) thatjinrespect of the constitutional issues the scheme proposedcannot properly be considered apart from the larger questionwhich, indirectly, it raises and we recommend accordinglythat the Government submit to the forthcoming ImperialConferenoe that the present scheme must beregarde^as partof this larger question, and that its acceptance at presentwoul^ .?e premature,5&amp;.   If it should appear that a decision on thelarger question is unlikely to be reached at an early date,He &apos;rSf iM20!4 Vb&amp;t consideration be given to the developmentcf the arrangements under which, prior to the war, a statistical Abstract for the British Empire was periodicallycompiled by the Bo*rd of Trade and presented to Parliament.Siioh a publication appears to us to be indispensable, and- 28 -
we have no doubt that it oould be made of a von greater value to otatdemon, publicists and the Empire generally than have bean the abstracts for which, hitherto, tho Board of Trade has been responsible   It should b$planned to give greater prominence to demographic and social and financial statistics than has been attempted in the past, while continuing the customary Tablee relative to Trade and Shipping,   It should contain no comments or interpretations, but should include any explanatory notes that may be necessary as to the contents of tho Tables to secure that any important differ-onoeo between statistics drawn from different sources and superficially corresponding should not be overlooked.   A publication of this kind was evidently in the mind of the frsmers of the Report of the Imperial Statistical Conference, although their proposals(in resolution 3 (a)) went further than we should be prepared to recommend, in its inclusion of interpretations and statistical surveys.55.   If the props sal which we have here made should be approved by His Majesty&apos;s Government the (juestion arises for consideration &amp;&amp; to which Department should be responsible for the work Involved.   In view if the range of the Statistics which the suggested publication would include it seems probable that a broad division according to subject matter might afford some convenience, especially as permitting of the distribution of responsibility between a small number of departments having special interests in particular classes of statistics and facilities for dealing with work of the kind contemplated,   tfe think that this question night vith advantage be referred to the Permanent Consultative C*KS.itte* *f Official Statisticians which, we understand, is to be set up in accordance with the recommendation in our,Woyioui Report and that that COiamlttee should advise the Government as to the best way in which, in their opinion, the proposal
could be carried into effect, regard being had to securing the co-operation of the Dominions. We consider that any volume or volumes of statistics produced under this recommendation should be issued as a Stationery Office publication and not as a Parliamentary Paper.

56. We desire to place on record our sense of obligation to the two gentlemen. Mr. W.T. Matthews. M.B.E.. and Mr. D.F. Jerrold, both of the Treasury, who have successively acted Secretary to the Comittees,

Mr. Matthews was ? for service in Ireland as an early stage of our proceedings and the greater   part of the secretarial work which our prolonged deliberations have involved has fallen upon Mr. Jerrold and has been most ably discharged.

        ALFRED W. WATSON

          (Chairman)

       J. GEORGE BEHARREL

      (SD) M. HESELTINE

           JAMES RAE

           P.J. ROSE

           S. VIVIAN

      (Sd) D.F. JERROLD

           (Secretary).

19th May, 1921.

 

THE PROPOSALS OF THE CONFERENCE OF EMPIRE STATISTICIANSFORAN EMPIRE BUREAU OF STATISTICS.Constitution of Committee.Sir Alfred \7. Watson, K.O.B. (Chairman) Government Actuary.Sir J. George Beharrell..      Ministry of TransportMr. W.H. Ooates..........      Board of Inland RevenueMr. A.W. Flux, 0.3.......      Board of TradeLir. M. Heseltine, C.B....      Ministry of HealthMr. John Hilton..........      Ministry of labour mr. J. Rae...............      treasury mr. H.V. Reade, C.B......      Board of Customs &amp; ExciseMr. P.J. Rose............      Scottish office mr. S.P. Vivian..........      Registrar General.Mr. D.F. Jerrold. (Secretary)MINORITY REPORT SIGNED BYMr. W.H. OoatosMr. A.W. Flux, C*B.Mr. John Hilton.Mr. H.V. Reade, O.B.
MINORITY REPORT. &apos; Table of Contents.Section. paragraph .      Introduction............................. 1-3II,      History of the proposal for an EmpireBureau of Statistics.................... 4-11III.      The scheme of the Empire Conference...... 12-15IV.      The views of the Home Departments........ 16-20V.      The evidence of Sir Josiah Stamp andLord Southborough........................ 21-30VI.      The functions of an Empire Bureau........ 31-34VII.      Political and constitutional aspects..... 35-43VIII.      The practical utility of an Empire Bureau    44-48r \IX.      Conclusions and recommendations.......... 49-57Appendix    extract from Report of Proceedings of the british Empire Statistical Conference.
MINORITY REPORT ON THiL PROPOSALS OP THE BRITISH EMPIRE STATISTICAL CONFERENCE.I._INTRODUCTION.1. By Cabinet kinute 20(20). conclusion 5(2) of the 15thApril, 1920, we were appointed members of a Committee under the Chairmanship of Sir Alfred Watson, K.O.B., to examine the proposals of the British Empire Statistical Conference, to ascertain the views of the Departments affected, and to report to the Cabinet.     We regret that we have found it Impossible, after prolonged discussions with our colleague.?, to arrive at a sufficient measure of agreement to justify us in signing one report.    We beg, therefore, to submit the following minority report.2. Our Report, like the ChairmanTs Report, is ooncernedwith the resolutions passed by the British Empire StatisticalConference which relate to the establishment of a BritishEmpire Statistical Bureau.     The point of fundamental import-ance on whioh our views are opposed to those of our colleaguesis whether the functions of an Empire Bureau, if established,are to be limited to the mere tabulation of records compiledin different parts of the Enpire - a routine process requir-ihg little slcill or intelligence - or to include(a) action directed towards the improvement of theserecords and especially towards securing statistics which are properly comparableand   (b) the analysis and interpretation of the statistics * so assembled, by the application of the methods developed by statistical science.Z* In ordor to facilitate a clear statement of our views and of the comments which we desire to make on the views expressed in the Chairman*s Report, we shall follow the arrangement of that Report a3 closely as possible.
II. HISTORY OF THE PROF OS AL.The Dominions Royal Commission, in their final report (Cd.8462 of 1917), signed by:-United Kingdom.Lord D&apos;Abernon, K.C.M.G. (Chairman)Sir H.Rider Haggard (Norfolk)Mr. T.Garnett (Lancashire)Sir W. Lorimer (Scotland)Mr. J. Tatlow (Ireland)Sir A.E. Bateman, K.C.M.G. (London)- Canada.      The Rt.Hon.Sir G.E.Foster, K.C.M.G.NOw Zealand. Mr. J. R* Sinclair.Unionof South Sir J.E.S.Langerman Africa.stated that in the course of their enquiries, both in the United Kingdom and the overseas Dominions, they had frequently found difficulties owing: to the absence of adequate statistical information.     In some cases, no official figures were available; in other cafeea, where official data were collected, they were either admittedly defective, or were compiled upon bases which made effective comparison with similar figures for other parts of the Empire, either difficult or impossible.    After indicating briefly several directions in which the statistical work then performed by various Government authorities both in the kother Country and the Dominions appeared to be Capable of improvement, co-ordination and expansion,   the Royal Commissioners recommended that a conference representing the Government Departments in the different parts of the Empire, which were enraged upon statistical work, should be convened immediately circumstances permitted, in order to consider the steps to,be taken towards the improvement of Empire statistics.New-foundland.The Hon. Sir E.N.Bowring.
5. The Commission also referred to the advocacy by severalwitnesses of the establishment of a oentral statisticaloffice for the Empire.     They pointed out that none of theadministrations in the Empire was specially charged with thebusiness of collecting, collating and preparing, statisticsfor the Empire as a whole, and after mentioning the work ofthe Board of Trade in this connection, said:-We are of the opinion that the creation of some office of the kind is eminently desirable (para.676).6. These proposals for a conference of Empire statisticiansand for an Empire Statietioal Bureau subsequently formed thesubject of correspondence with the overseas Dominions, andtheir replies came before the Imperial War Conference, heldin 1918.    The proposals were discussed at a meeting on the10th July, 1918, when there were present Ministers of theUnited Kingdom, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, South Africa,Newfoundland and India, and the following resolution waBpassed unanimously by the Conference, viz:-The Imperial War Conference having considered the correspondence as to the improvement of Imperial Statistics arising out of the recommendations of the Dominions Royal Commission, is in favour of the proposal to hold a Conference of Statisticians after the War, and that such Conference consider the estab-lishment of an Imperial Statistical Bureau under the supervision of an Inter-Imperial Committee.7. We consider that the Chairman^ Report fails to appreciate the importance which was attached by the Dominions Royal Commission (see especially para.674 of their Final Report) to the improvement, oo-ordination and expansion of Empire, statistics, and to the necessity for adequate investigation of existing divergencies of trade statistics.    Paragraph 9 of the Chairman&apos;s Report states that the Dominions Royal Commission specifically approved of the kind of bureau referred to in the quotation given from the evidence of Sir Hubert Llewellyn Smith, which would be a mere extension of the existing work of the Board
v99of Trade on Empire statistics, as contrasted with the wider soheme put forward by Mr. Knibbs, and paragraph 12 states that the latter soheme was not recommended by the Commission.8. It appears to us that these statements do not correctlyrepresent the attitude of the Royal Commission.     The Commis-sion carefully refrained from either approving or condemningany specific scheme for an Empire Bureau of Statistics.   their conclusions and recommendations on the subject are as follows(paragraph 735)(48)   It is urgent that steps should be taken to improve statistical methods, and compilations now existing in the various parts of the Empire, particularly as regards movement of population, imports and exports, prices, wages and cost of living, and movement of capital (paragraph 672).(49)   The best method of bringing about such improvement is to call a conference of the statisticians of the Empire.     We suggest agenda for such a conference, and outlino the preliminary wort needed if it is to have the best effect,  (paragraphs 673-5).(50)   In future the colleotion, collation, and publication of Imperial Statistics should be entrusted to a central statistical office, working under the new Imperial Development Board recommended below, (paragraphs 676-7)Again, in their recommendations as respects the proposedImperial Development Board, the Commissioners say:-(56)   Existing organisations are inadequate to deal with the scientific development of the resources of the Empire, with tho deepening of its harbours on a co-ordinated plan, with the improvement of its mail and cable services, the* preparation and publication of its statistics, and other matters of joint interest to the Empire as a whole (paragraphs 715-9).It is perfectly clear, therefore, that the Royal Commission,far from approving a mere extension of the work already per-formed by the Board of Trade, definitely recognised the needfor a new and wider organisation.ftflote.- The emphasis on these words is ours, and not that, of the Royal Commission&apos;.
I 1 j ...5.9. The account given in the Chairman1a Report of the stepstalcen to ascertain the views of tho Dominions on these recommendations of tho Royal Commission *t.ka Hh^ rminnfit tupitrtappears to us to need amplification.     It is material to note that the Secretary of State for the Colonies, in his letter to the Dominions welcoming the idea of a conference of Empire statisticians, suggested that the establishment of an Imperial Statistical Office might be included in the subjects for dis-discussion, and did not merely invite attention to the Board of Trade memorandum on the subject.     Australia stated that the Commonwealth Government would send a representative to tho proposed Statistical Conference, and would forward an. exhaustive memorandum on the subject) South Africa and New-foundland expressed general approval of the proposal for an Empire Bureau of statistics;   while Canada recommended that this proposal should be discussed at the Imperial Conference.10. We also feel obliged to dissont from the account of theImperial War Conference of 1918 (Cd.8177 of 1918) given in paragraphs 15 and 16 of the chairman Report.     It startB from the view that it was only the expanded funotions of the Board of Trade that the Dominions were invited to consider, and goes on to state that &quot;the Dominions were unable to agree &quot;to any express recommendation, ovon of this proposal&quot;.   The report of the disoussion shows on the contrary that the Dominions were unanimously in favour of the principle of an Empire Bureau of Statistics.     Only Mr. Hughes (Australia) was doubtful of the utility of a Bureau pending tho definition of some Imperial policy, and even he said that he would support the proposal.     The original resolution before the Imperial War conference was amended by the substitution of the words &quot;and that suoh Conference consider&quot; for the words &quot;agrees in principle&quot; but the steps by which the substitution was effected
1016.elaarly indtoates that it was due to the desire of the Con-ference to see a detailed soheme developed by the proposed Conference of Empire Statisticians, and not, as might be gathered from the Chairman&apos;3 Report, to any dissension on the main issue,11. We are of opinion, therefore, that the history of theproposal for the creation of an Empire Bureau of Statistics as presented in the Chairman&apos;s Report cannot be reconciled with the aetual correspondence, events and discussions that took place.III.   THE SCHEME OF THE EMPIRE CONFERENCE FOR AN EMPIRE BUREAU OF STATISTICS.12. We do not need to repeat the summary of the scheme foran Empire Bureau of Statistics which is contained in paragraph5 of the Chairman^ Report, but proceed to oonsider theoritieisms made.    Paragraph 17 after repeating the statement that the Imperial War Conference only considered the suggestion for the expansion of the Board of Trade functions, alludes tothe absenoe from the report of the Conference of Statisticiansof any reference to &quot;alternative schemes favoured by r eminentoffioial and statistical authorities&quot;.     The alternative schemes indicated are, we presume, the expansion of the Boardof Trade functions referred to above, and Dr.Bowley&apos;s schemefor routine tabulation of various Empire statistics.     This,. criticism seems to overlook the facts that an assistant secretary of tho Board of Trade acted a3 Chairman of theConference, and that Dr. Bowley accepted the invitation ofthe Conference to place his views before them.   As the confer-ence decided after full discussion to put forward a much moreoomprohensive scheme than either of those mentioned, theabsence from their Report of any reference to those schemesdoes not appear unnatural.
Nor do we think it fair to assert that this omission bythe Conference suggests a greater approach to unanimity amongstatistioal experts pn the question of the most practioalorganisation of imperial statistics than aotually exists.Official statisticians from all parts of the Empire werepresent at the Conference and the resolutions relating tothe establishment of a British Empire Statistical Bureau were adopted without dissent, as to all material points, with the single exception of the question whioh is the main reasonfor the existence of this minority report, namely that ofthe interpretative functions of the Bureau.     This issue wasdireotly raised at the Conference by the Chairman of ourCommittee, who moved to omit from a preliminary draft inconnection with the Bureau the1 words&quot;Such a bureau would not merely assemble the &quot;records;   but would apply the analytical methods &quot;which have been developed by the advance of &quot;statistical science to the examination of the &quot;material and the presentation of the results.&quot;In the full discussion which followed,, the statisticians from australia, Canada, South Africa and India as well as speakersfrom various Home Departments all dissented from the viewsadvanoed in favour of the motion, which on being put to the vote was lost by a large majority.     A copy of the verbatimnotes of the speeches made on this occasion i3 appended tothis Report.If the general referenoe to &quot;statistical experts&quot; is intended to include opinion other than that represented at the Conference, we would refer to the views expressed in the dis-cussion which followed the paper on the Organisation of Imperial Statistics read by Mr. Knibbs to the Royal Statistical Society on the 20th January, 1920.    (Journal of the Royal Statistical Society March, 1920).     We would also refer to the resolution adopted by the Ninth Congress of Chambers of
Commerce of the British Empire, held at Toronto, in September, 1920, viz-&quot;That this Congress records with satisfaction the action of His Majesty&apos;S Government in convening the Imperial Statistical Conferenoe, and desires to express &apos;   its endorsement of the proposal for the establishment in London of a Central Eureau of Statistics, adequately equipped and staffed, for the purpose of obtaining, collating, examining and publishing statistics which bear upon the conditions and resources of the Empire and.the relations of its members with one another and the rest of the world.&quot;In forwarding a copy of this Resolution to the Parliamentary Seoretary of the Department of Overseas Trade, the British Imperial Council of Commerce stated that they would gladly co-operate in any manner which may be necessary to bring about the object desired, the importance of which was fully appreciated.15. Paragraph 18 attempts to show that the recommendationsof the Conference as to an Imperial Eureau are not in accord-anoe with the views which Mr. Knibbs put before the Dominions Royal Commission in 1913.   This appears irrelevant, in view of the fact that Mr. Knibbs was the representative of Australia at the Conference, and took an active part in preparing the soheme for the Bureau which the Conference embodied in its report.&apos; - : XV.&apos; THE VIEWS OF THE HOME DEPARTMENTS.16. We are generally in agreement with the summary of the viewsof the Home Departments, as presented in paragraphs 21 to 25 of the Chairman&apos;s Report.    Paragraph 26, however, seems to be based on an erroneous view of the objects to be served by the Bureau.     Stress is laid upon the fact that the.replies of the Home Departments do not indicate that they expect &quot;t* derive definite benefit from the existence of the Bureau&quot;. But it was never supposed that the coordination.and development of statistics relating to the Empire generally would be of. direct benefit to particular Departments of the Home Government.
1049.    ;Some suoh benefit may incidentally result, but the object of the Bureau is, as stated in Section VIII. of the present report, to enlarge and improve the statistical materials from all parts of the Empire which form an important part of the data on which policies are based.Paragraph 27 of the Chairman&apos;s Report calls special attention to the views expressed by certain Departments.   As regards those of the Board cf Education, it may be pointed out that the defects in the educational statistics of the Empire which the Department mentions are precisely the defects whioh exist in many other branches of Imperial statistics, and that to remedy suuh defects is one of the objects which tho Bureau is intended to accomplish.     If, however, the co-ordination of educational statistics is to be effected by an Imperial Eduoaticnal Conference, the Bureau while avoiding any independent action, might be able, through its permanent maohinery, to assist the objects of such a conference.    As regards the points raised by the Ministry of Agriculture and the Ministry of Health, it is obvious that in setting up an Empire Bureau careful consideration would have to be given to the work already being done by the International Agricultural Institute and by the International Labour Office, as well as to the projected League of Nations statistical organisation. But it does not follow that these subjects should be altogether excluded from the activities of an Empire Bureau.     On the other hand there is much to be said for the view expressed by Dr. Bowley to the Dominions Royal Commission that the existence of*an International Statistical Bureau issuing certain publications would make it necessary that there should be an Imperial Bureau in order that the Empire statistics should be sent to this international body in a properly prepared form (Q.2180, Cd.7351. 1914).
Subject to the qualifications set out in the chairman Report (paragraphs 23, 24 and 25) the general attitude of the Home Departments towards the proposal to establish an Empire Bureau of Statistics upon the lines set out in the Resolutions of the Conference of Empire Statisticians is favourable, and the undermentioned Departments anticipate that the Bureau may-be of service, to them, vizs-admirality ministry of AgricultureAir Ministry (as regards civil aviation)Colonial office board of Customs and ExciseDevelopment CommissionMinistry of PoodForeign office government Chemists&apos; Department Home office board of Inland Revenue Ministry of Labour National Debt Office Department of Overseas Trade General Post OfficeScientific &amp; Industrial Research Department Board of Trade War OfficeOffice of Woods and Forests Board of Agriculture (Scotland) Fishery Board (Scotland) General Register Office (Scotland) Department of Agriculture&apos;and Technical Instruction (Ireland)The strongest adverse oritioism of the scheme of the Bureauis expressed by the Ministry of Health, to whose views theChairman&apos;s Report (paragraph 25) attaches, in our opinion,somewhat disproportionate importance.The majority of the Departments desire that interpretationsby the Bureau based upon or illustrated by the statistical datapublished in annual reviews and periodical monographs shouldreceive the prior concurrence of the various Departments con-cerned.     This desire may arise from an apprehension that theseinterpretations may:-(a)   involve pronouncements by the Bureau on policies which have formed or may form the subject of acute political controversy, in the United Kingdom or the Overseas Dominions, or
106 ii.(b) express opinions whioh diverge from the publicly expressed views of the Departments themselves, or(c) be based upon Imperfect comprehension of the statistics under examination.20. Paragraph 29 of the Chairmanfs Report bases on these views the statement that the Departments hold it necessary to ensure that any interpretations put forward by the Bureau shall in fact be those of the Departments themselves and not of an independent body.     We do not think that thio inference can legitimately be drawn from the replies.     The Departments desire to prevent the publication of comments on their statistics which differ from their own published views, or are mistaken, or are undesirable for reasons of policy, but it is clear that muoh interpretation of official statistics is possible which is not open to any of these objections.   We discuss in Paragraphs 34 and 37 below the nature of the inter-interpretations and oomments which the Bureau would be likely to produce.V. THE EVIDENCE OF SIR JOSIAH STAMP AND LORD SOUTHBOROUGH. 21. The summary of the evidence given to the Committee by SirJoslah Stamp and Lord Southborough, set out in the Chairman!s Report, does not in our opinion give equal weight to the two sides of the questions discussed, and we are, therefore, under the necessity of amplifying it,22.. On the general question of the desirability of theestablishment of an Empire Bureau of Statistics      Sir Josiah Stamp agreed that for the due consideration of the many problems that touch the welfare and progress of the Empire as a whole, adequate statistics were a prime necessity.    He further agreed that it was essential to try to obtain uniformity of praotioe in the compilation of like statistics produced in various parts of the Empire, particularly in view of the present
tendency to interpret statistics narrowly.    He thus approved the primary function of the proposed Empire Bureau, namely the examination of Empire statistics as at present produced, with a view to making suggestions for variations in form, or for additions thereto, in order to render them more comparable, and agreed that the setting up of a permanent machine of this kind would be likely to achieve results of greater value than could be obtained by the only alternative method, already tried with but imperfect success, namely that of detailed correspondence between the respective statistical Departments at home and in the overseas Dominions.25. As regards interpretations by the Bureau of statisticsfurnished by the Home Departments, Sir Josiah Stamp appreciated the desire of Departments to protect themselves against the publication of Departmental statistics which had not been made public because of their confidential character, and against interpretations, whether of published or unpublished statistics, whioh drew inferences of a weight whioh the Department knew the statistics in question oould not adequately support, or whioh threw full weight in one direotion without realising that other inferences might be legitimately drawn in the opposite direction.     Nevertheless, Sir Josiah thought that an Empire Bureau whioh was &quot;absolutely at the mercy of the veto of Departments&quot; in these matters, would be a mere shadow, and he therefore considered that ultimately an Empire Bureau should have some independent powers of appeal in case of divergence of view.     For this purpose, he had contemplated an independent tribunal, which he suggested might consist of one Cabinet Minister, one Judge of the High Court and one eminent Statist-ioian.     In the case of a difference between the Bureau and a Dominion, he would provide for appropriate variation of the constitution of this appellate tribunal.
13.On the other hand, Sir Joaiah Stamp was of the opinion that the &quot;questions of over-riding the veto of Departments in &quot;tho wider statistical interests were questions that would solve &quot;themselves in the course of time,&quot; and he pointed out that an Empire Bureau would be largely &quot;occupied during the first few &quot;years of its existence with branches that do not raise these &quot;questions&quot; and that, under competent management and direction, it should normally gain the confidence and assistance of Departments,   In this connection, Sir Josiah also thought that this early period of study of the existing Empire Statist-ios would enable the Bureau to absorb a considerable knowledge of the precise conditions under which the material for statist-ics is oolleoted by the Home Departments, and of the limitations that must be placed upon their interpretation.     Where the statistics handled were highly technical, Sir Josiah considered that &quot;it would be an extraordinary thing if even an able &quot;statistician published a monograph without sending a copy&quot; to eaoh of the departments concerned for examination, and he imagined that careful attention would be given to all comments and observations upon the monograph, with a view to the neoess-ary modifications being made.     Sir Josiah Stamp did not deny the possibility of acute personal differences arising between the authorities of the Empire Bureau and tho heads of depart-ments, but he considered that such a deplorable stato of affairs could only be envisaged, if there were &quot;postulated a certain &quot;set of people with extraordinarily fixed interests and extraord-&quot;inarily touchy dispositions.&quot;     In short, he thought that this danger might be likened to putting &quot;a 5 per cent, point against &quot;95 per cent, of clear efficiency and ease of working.&quot;We do not view favourably Sir Josiah Stamp&apos;s proposed appellate tribunal, and we are of opinion that under the safe-guards proposed later in this report, this machinery is
unnecessary. In all other respects, we find ourselves entirely in agreement with Sir Josiah1s views as summarised above.Lord Scuthborough&apos;s evidence was devoted to an examination of the question rather from the point of view that might be expected to be taken by the overseas Dominions.    He was doubt-ful, until the views of the Dominions on the whole proposals of the Dominions Royal Commission were known, whether it was an appropriate time &quot;to deal with one of the recommendations&quot; namely that for the establishment of an Empire Bureau of Statistics.    Apart from this general criticism, he emphasised the obstacle in the way of the establishment of any Empire bodies, whioh arises from the (fundamental &quot;difficulty of who was to appoint the persons who were really to take control of the management of this body incorporated by oharter.&quot;    As an illustration, he noted the failure up to the present to overcome this dlffioulty as respects an Imperial Secretariat.On the question of interpretation by an Empire Bureau of published statistics, Lord Southborough was of the firm opinion that it was impossible to interpret statistics without ooming into oollision with the publicly expressed policies of Ministers in various parts of the Empire.    He did not regard the presence of Dominion representatives upon the Council of the Bureau, or of Dominion statisticians upon its staff, as constituting any safeguard against this danger, for he had found in his exper-ienoe that Dominion prime Ministers had &quot;resisted every attempt &quot;to delegate affairs, small or great, for whioh they were &quot;responsible, by sending men to London or elsewhere, or by &quot;establishing committees or other bodies who might out across &quot;the line of policy of his cabinet, and play into the hands of &quot;the opposition.&quot;     He considered that this &quot;dislike to delegate &quot;policy and administration really extended to the High Commis-&quot;sioners themselves.&quot;     Lord Southborough was of opinion that
no15.when Dominion cabinets wore &quot;faced with the details of the &quot;Bureau, with the duty of nominating two men for a period of &quot;years,&quot; (to ait upon the Council of the Bureau and to serve upon Its staff), and &quot;with the finding their salaries and &quot;keeping them here, they would become uneasy and refuse to &quot;ratify the scheme.&quot;    Lord Southhorough, therefore, considered that it was useless to explore further the possibilities of an Empire Statistical Bureau until the Dominion Prime Ministers, by a resolution at the next Imperial Conference, had agreed to its establishment and the nature of the powers to be given to it.Wo have found it impossible to reoonoile Lord Southborou^hfe definite views with the aotual history of the movement for the establishment of an Empire Bureau of Statistics, as already set forth In Section II of this report.    These views appear to overlook In particular the resolution, passed by the Imperial War Oonferenoe, which sat so recently as July, 1918, in favour of convening an Empire Conference of Statisticians, with the proposal of the establishment of an Empire Bureau as one of Its chief subjects of consideration.    That resolution reo*lved the unanimous approval of Ministers from Canada, Australia, New Zealand, South Afrioa, Newfoundland and India. Some oxtraots from the proceedings of the Imperial War Con-ferenoe on the 10th July, 1918, are of great relevanoe in this connection, vizs-Mr. Melghen - Canada.- We are anxious for the ostablish-ment of an Imperial Statistical Bureau - we are very anxious for it - and we have not the slightest hesitation In supporting the resolution which is before the conference.It should be noted at this point that the original draft ofthe resolution &quot;agreed in principle&quot; with the establishmentof the Bureau.
Ill16.Mr. Cook - Australia.- And this Bureau, If rightly set up, oould tali9 those statistics, analyse them, and see what they mean to our Umpire roaouroos, as to the Empirefs requirements, and as to the possibilities for tho em-employment of our labour and capital up and down the Empire.   In that direction alone, I think it would be fulfilling a very useful function.Mr. Burton - South Africa.- But I regard this proposal as really an attempt to start some sort of definite ground for the promotion of trade relations within the Empire. One of our greatest obstaoles, aa far as I know, in the past In competition  with other people, has been our ignoranoe in one part of the Empire of what oan be done, and of what is produced, and of what is to be found in other parts of the Empire.I am afraid that there is no doubt about it that the lack of co-ordination of our information, tho laok of exact, scientific and full knowledge of the facts, has been largely responsible for suoh successful compe-tltion against us aa there has been in the past; and to my mind the very first requisite, if you want to make a success of your promotion of trade relations within the British Empire, and to oompete successfully against the powerful competitors you have had, and whioh you will have again, is that you should endeavour as far as possible, to get available from all parts of the Empire an accurate statement of what your actual capacities of production, of manufacture, and so forth, are.   So that I welcome this proposal of Canada&apos;s and to my mind If we we pass it, it will be one of the best things we have done at this Conference.Mr. Lloyd - Newfoundland.- First of all, I agree heartily with the resolution.     I think in any case the e3tab-llshment of an Imperial Statistical Bureau would be the foundation of better trading within the Empire. Whether that trade is to be on   the free trade principle or on preference makes no difference.   It would be a distinct advantage to all concerned, and I consider that it is a K       foundation whioh will make more effeotive our trade within the Empire.Mr. Montagu - for India.- I should like to say that the policy which I consider it my duty to advocate is the development of the resources of India, not only for her own sake? but for the sake of the Empire.     I think if we are to have suoh a polioy, statistics of this kind must be collected, and I, therefore, heartily support the resolution.The contrast presented between these views expressed by the Dominion Ministers named and the view of Lord Southborough, as evldenoed by the following extract from his evidence, needs no emphasis.If you like to seek a charter, the primary object of which would be to bring together a number of gentlemen, learned in these subjects, with the object of co-ordin-ating tho statistics of the Empire, amending them and
Illbettering them in many ways, that is a thing whioh could be done, but when you introduoe the representa-tlve element not evon representativea of one Govern-ment, but of so many Governments, then I think you will get into trouble in the later stages, whether the Bureau is intended to be political or not. I also think you will never launch your ship.Lord Southboroughts views are further negatived by thegeneral approval of the proposal to establish an Empire Bureau,with the functions and under the organisation recommended bythe Conference of Empire Statisticians, which, it is understood,has been expressed by all the Dominions overseas, in theirreplies to the despatch, (Dominion, No.173 of  6th April,1920),of the Seoretary of State for the Colonies, forwarding a copyof the Report of the Conference for their observations.Only one of these replies oalla for further oomment,   Tho Commonwealth of Australia believes that it would be desirable -at the appropriate time - that a conspectus of the statistics and organisation of the Empire should be readily available for the use of the Governments and publicists of all parts of the Empire, and that, as recommended by the Conference, a Bureau of Statistics for the British Empire should be created.   This definite general approval is, however, qualified by the suggestion that the creation of a central Bureau of Statistics for the United Kingdom appears to be a desirable, if not
ICS18.indeed a neoossary, preliminary to the establishment of an tCmpiro Bureau.     The Commonwealth considers that unless suoh an organisation were first created, a large part of the work of the proposed Empire Bureau of Statistics would neoessarily consist of formulating tho statistical conspectus of the United Kingdom itself, a labour with whioh the Empire Bureau ought not to be charged.     In this connection, we can only rooall the fact that our Committee has Just had tccasion to consider, in its deliberations upon the reoent petition to H.M.Government upon Home Official Statistics, the establishment of a central Bureau of Statistics for the United Kingdom.     In its report to the Cabinet the Committee was unable to reoommend the establishment of such a Bureau. It recommended, however, that the Government should establish a permanent Consultative Committee of Government Statisticians, and we may be permitted to hope that consideration by the Commonwealth Government of the arguments contained in that report, and of the decision whioh may be taken by H.M. Government thereon, may load to a withdrawal of the qualiflw cation stated, and to the participation of tho Commonwealth of Australia in a scheme for an Empiro Bureau of Statistics.
VI. THE FUNCTIONS OF AN EMPIRE BUREAU OF STATISTICS.31. The functions of an Empire Bureau of Statistics as con-ceived by the Conference of Empire Statisticians fall under four main heads, viz:-(a) receiving all Empire statistics:(b) examining these statistics, and making suggestions for variations in form or additions, in order to render them comparable;(o) publishing the co-ordinated Empire Statistics.(d) Interpreting the statistics published either in annual reviews or poriodical monographs.The desirability of the first three functions is not onlyunquestioned but is accepted by the great majority of theHome Departments.    The notable exception is the Ministry ofHealth.   Except perhaps in the reply of that Department wehave been unable to find in the replies from the Home Depart-ments any expressions indicating that they &quot;regarded it as&quot;a proposal for an Imperial organisation speaking authoritative-&quot;tivoly on behalf of the Governments contributing to its&quot;maintenance&quot;,   (para. 36 Chairman&apos;s Report).32. The real issue arises on tho function of interpretation.We fully concur with the view expressed in paragraph 40 of the Chairman^ Report that a mere aggregation by arithmetical processes of existing Empire statistics as published in their present variety of forms and significance,;unillumined by any explanations, interpretation or analysis, would not justify the existence of an independent Empire Bureau of Statistics.33. But what is this function of interpretation?   What doesit moan and how is it to be exercised?   &quot;Statistics&quot; may lie called the science which measures the social organism, regarded as a whole; or the science of averages.   The primary business of the statistician is to furnish facts, to collect, arrange and describe, to present and weigh evidence.   The
11520.word &quot;interpretation&quot; signifies the explanation of what the figures mean, and of the statistical inferences which can properly be drawn from them.   We are wholly unable to accept the view expressed in paragraph 34 of the Chairman&apos;a report, that interpretation involves, as a matter of course, the exercise of &quot;critical powers in regard to any policies of ^which the tendencies may be statistically illustrated&quot;. Similarly, paragraph 31 of that report states that an Empire Bureau&quot; would be the centre of enquiry to whioh every advocate &quot;or opponent of every policy would naturally turn and its -&quot;answers would inevitably be regarded as authoritative&quot;. If this were an objection to the creation of an Empire Statistical Bureau, it would equally be an objection to statistics being supplied by any Government Department. Advocates of policies who require statistics must frequently obtain them from official sources, but the Department which supplies them is not held responsible for the political inferences whioh may be drawn from them or the uses to which they may be put, and the Bureau would be in the same position. It would obviously be improper for the Bureau to prepare statistics with the object of supporting a particular policy and it is only reasonable to assume that the Bureau, acting under the general direotion of a Council representing all parts of the Empire, would be especially careful in this respect.34. As regards interpretations by the Bureau of the publish-ed statistics of Home Departments we recommend that no publica tion should be issued by the Bureau until it has been circulated to each member of the Council and of the Advisory Committee of the Bureau, at a suitable interval before meetings of those bodies.     Home Departments can be trusted to make their cum terms with the Bureau as respects any un-published statistics, memoranda, explanation, etc., which
SI.they supply&quot;&quot;.    These safeguards should neither detract from the independence of the Empire Bureau, nor interfere with its efficient working.VII. POLITICAL AND CONSTITUTIONAL ASPECTS.35. As the differences between our colleagues and our-selves turn mainly on this interpretative function we propose to examine it more fully, in its political and constitutional aspects.36. On the political aspect the views of our colleaguessigning the chairman report may be summarised as follows.As published statistics record most of the salient facts which have either emerged from, or will form the subject of, political controversy in different parts of the Empire, it is inevitable that interpretation of these statistics must support or discredit the policy of one party or another.    Moreover, it is suggested, a policy may be in favour or in progress in one part of the Empire at the same time that a directly opposite policy may have been adopted in some other part of tho Empire.   On this view, it is urged that the interpretations of statistics published by an Empire Bureau must of necessity give offonce or lead to friction in one part or another, and that it Is imperative to avoid any step whioh might lead to such regrettable effects upon inter-Empire relations.37. Our.view on the contrary is that while statisticsrecord these salient facts, the results of past action,which may and probably will form the basis for decisions affecting the policies of the future, it is not a neoossary consequence that their publication oven when accompanied by analyses, explanations and interpretations, will lead to conflict of views between the Bureau and respective Governments in different parts of the Empire.     Statistical data will be
treated statistically, and the interpretations furnished will be directed towards explanations of their character-istics, their limitations, and their comparability.   The work contemplated is in fact a sifting of the information presented.    A scientific examination of the data published will content itself with an impartial statement of all the points emerging, and will not attempt to arrive at any conclusions, much less to issue authoritative and didactic pronouncements, on thorny and controversial issues of a political character.   It appears to us that this conception of the interpretative function will be ensured by the proposed constitution of the Empire Bureau,    The Council is to consist of representatives of the Dominion Governments and of the Home Departments.   The Advisory Committee has . power to co-opt to its membership representatives of economic, commercial, industrial and financial interests in important parts of the Empire.   The Director is to be,not only an expert statistician, but also a man of approved administrative and official experience and ability.   We hold therefore that it is highly improbable, if not inconceivable, that under such a constitution the disasters anticipated in the Chairman^ Report will ever occur.38. The lack of foundation for the apprehensions in theChairman1s Report is, we think, shown by the fact that in the discussion of the project by United Kingdom and Dominion Ministers at the Imperial War Conference of 1918 not a hint of these dangers found expression in any quarter.   Nor was this because they did not consider the question of the interpretative function, as the two following extracts from their discussions show:-
- (1)&apos;Mr, Cook,-Australia. 83&apos;I cannot oonoeive what would be a better thing for the Empire in the future than to colloot all the facts, and collate and analyse them, and make suggestions for the use of these faots in the development of our Empire resources generally.   The mere collection of dry figures means nothing.   As Mr. Hughes (Australia) haB just said, unless you are going to turn these statistics to practical use, there is no use In collecting thorn, but there is a very useful function, I think, for a Committee of this sort if you get the right men on it.(ii) Mr. Cook - Australia.As I understand, the point is not so much the collection of new statistics, but collating them, and trying to find their meaning - making them more useful. Mr. Lloyd - NewfoundlandPutting them on definite lines, Mr. Burton - South AfrioaCo-ordinating them. The Chairman - Mr. Walter Long.TTthTnk&apos;1 that is very Important.We now turn to an examination of the constitutional aspect of an Empire Bureau of Statistics, still with especial referenoe to the interpretative function.    Parliamentary Government both In the United Kingdom and in the self-govern-ing Dominions is based upon the responsibility of Ministers to Parliament.      Ministers are responsible for the action of all Government Departments and of the Civil Servants employed therein - with the one exception of the Comptroller and Auditor General.   Criticism of departmental action is therefore effected by oritioism of the Minister responsible.   Thep. &quot;difficulty is how to reconcile this fundamental concept of ministerial responsibility with the creation of an officialbody upon an Imperial baBiB and accordingly not responsible to any single Minister or Parliament.The chairman Report takes the view that an Empire organisation of this kind must essentially have &quot;a definite &quot;basis in and derive its powers from an Imperial organisation &quot;constitutionally qualified to speak for the Empire as a whole&quot; (paragraph 48) and again that &quot;it is not practicable to set up
&quot;an organisation, whether by incorporation under Royal &quot;Charter or by any other means, consisting of nominees of &quot;the differont Parliaments and Governments of the Empire, &quot;which will not be held strictly responsible by those &quot;Parliaments or Governments for the actions of the executive staff placed under their control&quot;. (Para. 46 (a)).41. We, on the other hand, recognising that the developmentof organisations and machinery representing the Empire as a whole is in its infancy, and that the process of development must necessarily raise doubts and difficulties, believe that no hard and fast rules can be laid down beforehand for regulating the relations of but bodies to the various parts of the Empire.   We hold that the experience of the past4Justifies the belief that, given patience and goodwill, difficulties will gradually be solved.   The constitutional history of the United Kingdom and the British Empire is a continuous record of experiment and compromise, in which the dangers that inevitably attend every step of progress have been avoided largely by unwritten rules and oustoms, while the supremacy of Parliament has always been preserved.   But given a number of Parliaments within an Empire, each supreme within its own territory,owning allegiance to one monarchy, we consider that the conception of Empire unison can only be attained through the machinery of a body of represent-atives whioh, discussing all aspects df any question, agrees at the greatest oommon measure of unity.    A process of conference and counsel may be trusted to load (in words recently used by a well known publicist) to a &quot;steadily inoreasing identity of purpose which, in course of time, will discover its own sufficient instruments of policy. The principM of consultation adequately applied should do its most valuable work not in the solution of orystallised
difficulties, but in the prevention of difficulties arising&quot;. Nations &quot;whioh keep in touoh with eaoh other&apos;s standpoints from the beginning of things cannot well fall out unless their purposes are separated by a radical discrepancy&quot;.42, The working out of the problem of Empire organisationsin some spheres, such as those touching diplomacy, defence and all matters requiring, legislation for the purpose of future action, must necessarily be slow, tentative and cautious.    But the organisation of Empire statistics stands on a different footing.   For an Imperial body, dealing with matters whioh are neither political nor administrative, there are already in exlstenoe the precedents of the three Imperial Bureaux of Entomology,Mycology, and Mineral Resources, guided by bodies representing the various Governments of the Empire, and supported by contributions from those Governments.   A grant in aid by any Government towards the maintenance of an Empire Bureau of Statistics could be borne upon the same vote as that whioh sustains the present grants to the bureaux named.   Criticism of the aotion of the executive officials employed in the Bureau, direoted to the issue of adherence to or withdrawal from participation in the Bureau, could always take place upon that vote.   Responsibility for the action of the Bureau would not attach to any Minister, either In the United Kingdom or in the overseas Dominions *   The conception of an Empire organisation necessarily involves departure from that-principle.43. In this connection we may quote the following passagesfrom the Report of the Conference of Empire Statisticians viz:The Dominions Royal Commission suggested that an Empire statistical Bureau might conveniently be placed under the authority of the Imperial Development Board whioh the Commission desired to see established.   That Imperial authority has however not as yet been created, nor does there yet exist any Imperial Secretariat,
responsibility to whioh might have socured the primary objects aimed at by the Conference.   The Conference has. accordingly, proposed that the Bureau should be controlled by a special Council, established by Royal Charter, and has suggested that, in order to emphasise the Imperial /-charaoter of this Council, the President should be the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, in his capacity as President of the periodical Imperial Conferences.The Conference while desiring to emphasise the objects in view, does not desire to press for the exact procedure outlined in the resolutions, if it should be found that these objects can,better be obtained by other methods.This quotation also shows that the suggestion that thePrime Minister of the United Kingdom should be Presidentof the Counoll of the Bureau only proceedod from the desireto emphasise the Imperial character of the Bureau.    the criticism which the Chairman&apos;s Report (para. 35) bases uponthe contradictory duties which it is suggested the PrimeMinister might thus be called upon to perform does not at allimpress us.   It appears to us that hie position as ex-offioioPresident of the Council need not involve him in any adrainio-tratlve or executive functions whatsoever.VIII.THE PRACTICAL UTILITY OF AN EMPIRE BUREAU OF STATISTICS.44. Paragraphs 49 to 51 of the Chairman&apos;s report are largelydevoted to discussing whether the proposed Bureau would be of any practical use,   and the view which seems to underlie these paragraphs, and indeed the report generally, is that the production of statistics at the publio expense cannot be justified unless suoh statistics can be shown to serve some immediate and tangible purpose.    Wo do not feel called upon to discuss that general question, and content ourselves with pointing out that, if the view indicated were to prevail, a large part of the statistics already publish-ed by the Governments of the United Kingdom and other parts
mof the Empire would be supjsroesed..   But It appears necessary even at the risk of repetition, to set out some of the reasons why further developments in statistics of the British Empire are desirable.45. The main purpose of the establishment of an EmpireBureau of Statistics is the circulation throughout the Empire of full, accurate and comparable information as to its population, its natural resources, its capacity for production and manufacture, its communications, labour, finance, etc.   The collection of information, sifted, analysed and co-ordinated, is designed to solve one of the great difficulties of the past, namely, the absence of that knowledge of facts brought into their proper shape, which is the essential preliminary to action.   The objects sought are the promotion of trade, the closer unity of the Empire, a clearer comprehension of mutual difficulties, a knowledge of the problems that present themselves in various parts of the Empire, their magnitude, their peculiarities and the methods being adopted for their solution.46. We are well aware that it will not be possible topoint to this and to that specific resultant gain from the establishment of such a bureau.   As we have already observed in paragraph 17, we do not expect that measurable advantage will accrue to any of the Home Departments, in the exercise of their administrative functions in the United Kingdom.   We look rather to the broader advantages which are likely to follow on the development of Empire resources, advantages which will be shared between the particular Dominion concerned and the Mother Country. Our views are well expressed by rir. Cook, Minister of the Navy, Australia, in the following extract from the proceed-ings of the Imperial War Conference, 1918, viz:-
47. The Chairman&apos;s Report (para. 20) describes the project&apos;s oharaoter as &quot;novel, ambitious and expensive&quot;. We agree that it is novel, we Bee no reason to condemn it because it is ambitious, but we think it an exaggeration to describe as expensive an organisation which would achieve the ends desoribed above at an initial annual cost of approximately  30,000 - shared among the United Kingdom and the , Dominions overseas.48. While Paragraphs 49 and 50, as well as many otherparts of the Chairman^ report, oondemn the project of an Imperial Bureau as too ambitious, paragraphs 51, on the other hand, argues that the value of such a Bureau would be restricted by the limitation of its field to the British Empire, and the exclusion of international statistics. It is of course true that many branches of statistics must be treated on an international basis, and that conclusions oannot safely be drawn from examination of material relating solely to the British Empire.    But that con-sideration does not at all,weaken the foroe of the arguments for the Improvement of Imperial Statiatios v/hich have been developed above,&quot;I can m*a the function which this Imperial Bureau will fulfil and it is a very useful one. That is in the direction suggested by my colleague, the Prime Minister, just now.   It is in the direction of forecasting the Empire&apos;s requirements a thing which none of the statisticians yet seem to me to have attempted in any of the States.   That is to say, not only ascertaining the faots from time to time, but so shaping those faoto as to be of use to the traders, the produoers of the Empire, and even to suggest suitable employment for the capital of the Empire. At present we are at haphazard in those higher spheres of State action.   It seems to me that a little socialism would not be a bad thing at all as it applies to this question of ascertaining the Empire&apos;s requirements, the Empire&apos;s resources, and the possibility of fulfilling those requirements.   That is a function that we have never yet attempted. After all, the Dominions Royal Commission that has just concluded its labours and made its final report, might very woll have been oalled an Imperial Statistical Bureau.   That is really all they have been doing for five years - collecting Empire Statistics&quot;.
IX. CONCLUSION AMD REOQi^lENDATION.4-9. Me have now dealt with the history of the proposal toestablish an-Empire&quot;Bureau of Statistics, we have proved how the idea has received practically unanimous support from the Dominions overseas and from the Home Departments, we have explained the true meaning of the functions propos-ed to be entrusted to such a Bureau, we have reviewed its political and constitutional aspects and we have shown that the Bureau, if established, would be,of practical utility both to the Dominions and the kother Country.   In our opinion the arguments in favour of the establishment of an Empire Bureau of Statistics far outweigh the arguments against it which are sot out in the Chairman1e Report.   The question remains whether its establishment should be proceeded with independently of the creation of &quot;an Imporial organisation constitutionally qualified to %peak for the Empire as a whole&quot; (paragraph 47 Chairman&apos;s Report).50. If such an Imporial body be established, it would, we assume, have attached to.it an Imperial statistical Office, and the powers of aotion of that office with reference to the Governments concerned, and its machinery for securing the expression of co-ordinated opinion on statistical matters would be thoso of the Imperial body itself.   But it does not at all follow, as stated in the Chairman&apos;s Report (paragraph 48) that consideration of an Empire Bureau &quot;must wait upon and follow the Issue of such dis-&quot;cussions as may take place upon the relations betweon the &quot;constituent parts of tho Empire&quot;.   The problems attending this larger question are obviously greater in degree than those attaching to the establishment of an Empire Bureau
12530.of Statistics.   Inasmuch as the collection, co-ordination and sifting of statistical data is intended to provide the material for the wise decision and balanced judgment of problems re-quiring futuro legislative or oxeoutive action, we are of opinion that the establishment of an Empire Bureau of Statistics might well precede, and in any event, need not wait upon, the establishment of an Imperial organisation represent-ing tho Empire as a whole.51. The Chairman^ Report to some extent supports this oon-clusion, for it recommends (Para. 54) that if it should appear that a decision on the larger question of the readjustment of Imperial relations is unlikely to be reached at an early date, other steps should immediately be taken towards the improve-ment of Empire Statistics, namely, that the existing Statis-tical Abstract for the British Empire (at preaont prepared by the Board of Trade, lust issue 0d.. 7327 of 1915) &quot; should be &quot;planned to give greater prominence to demographic and social &quot;and financial statistics than has been attempted in the past, &quot;while continuing the customary tables relative to trade and &quot;shipping&quot;.   This proposal would appear to extend the Empire field of statistical activity until it covered the majority of statistical investigations directly Interesting-to tliose concerned in Empire progress.    koreover, still further functions are to be undertaken...  The tables of statistics given over this wide field are to be accompanied by &quot;any &quot;explanatory notes that may be necessary to secure that any &quot;important differences between statistics drawn from different &quot;sources and superficially corresponding should not be over-&quot;looked&quot;.58. But if, as tho Chairman13 Report anticipates, difficulties and dangers are certain to result from tho inclusion of
&quot;interpretations&quot; in any publications issued by the Bureau is it not oqually oertain that they v/ould result from the inclusion of &quot;explanatory notes&quot; in the new Empire Abstract? As wo have said, wo do not think those anticipations well grounded, but we are of the opinion that any such dangers aro much moro likely to arise if &quot;oxplanatory notes&quot; aro published in a United Kingdom volurao in which the Dominions only indirectly co-operate and for whioh they take no responsibility, then if published by an Empire Bureau of Statistics, which is supported, controlled and manned by the United Kingdom and the Dominions Jointly.53. Moreover, explanations of the. different basesemployed in the compilation of various Empire statistics can only be given after close study of the particular facts, laws, etc., governing their meaning, a point on whioh the chairman Report lays special emphasis.   The work in-volvod by such an extended Statistical Abstract for the British Empire would be of a difficult and responsible character, and would thus necessitate now staff, controlled by statistical officers with the expert qualifications necessary for such studies.    The expense which would fall upon the United Kingdom alone under the recommendation of the Chairman^ Report might well provo to be not much less than that involved by participation in an Empire Bureau of Statistics.54. The proposal in para. 55 of the Chairman^ Report thattho work of preparing the new and oxtonded Statistical Abstract for the Empire should be distributed befyveen several of the Home Departments seems to us to introduce a further souroe of weakness.    kuch would be lost and little gained, financially or otherwise, by such a division
of responsibility.   It is in our opinion essential that Empire Statistical Publications, in order to command con-fidence throughout the Empire and to yield the maximum of utility, should be prepared under the control and direction of a body representative of tho various parts of the Empire.55. Tho resolutions of the Conference of Empire Statisticiansrecommending the establishment of an Empire Bureau of Statistics will no doubt form one subject of the deliberations of United Kingdom&apos;and Dominion ministers at their mooting during tho present year.   After careful consideration of all the fore-going arguments and issues, we recommend that, in the event of ministers from the Dominions supporting by a substantial majority the resolutions of the Conference of Statisticians in favour of the institution of an Empire Bureau, His -majesty^ Government should express their concurrence with the broad outlines of the scheme, and agree to the proposed reference of the scheme to a Committee of representatives of the Governments concerned, with a view to settling all the necessary details.5&apos;v. Although we are officers responsible for the work of statistics and intelligence branches in the Departments of the Sbard of Inland Revenue, the Board of Trade, the ministry of Labour, and the Board of Customs and Excise, we understand that we wero made members of this Committee in our individual rather than in our official capacities.   The views expressed in this-Report are, therefore, put forward as our personal views and not as those of our Departments.
19th may, 192157. We desire in conclusion to associate ourselves with our colleagues who have signed, the Chairman^ Report in their appreciation of the able manner in which the secretarial work of the Committee, has been discharged, partly by Mr. T.W. Matthews, M..$ ,E., and mainly by Mr.. D.F. Jerrold.W. H. COATES A. W. FLUX . JOHN HILTOri R, V. READE..
APPENDIX.BRITISH EMPIRE STATISTICAL OONFERENOE.Extract from Report of Proceedings of Meeting held on 13th February, 1920.SIR ALFRED WATSONj May I move a resolution.   I am afraid I may be raising rather a large question and perhaps I move my resolution more for the purpose of getting information as to the meaning and intention of the Committee1s scheme than necessarily in order to obtain a modification of that scheme. The proposal that I have to make is to strike out from the report the last sentence on the first page in Mr. Reads&apos;s draft, the words &quot;Such a Bureau would not merely assemble the records, but would apply the analytical methods which have been developed&quot; and so on.   I have read the report with extreme care several times, and I am not quite clear as to the extent to which the framerB of it contemplated that the Director of the Bureau will investigate and criticise the enormous number of social phenomena whioh will come before him in all parts of the British Empire.    With the main object of the Bureau, which I think is to oo-ordinato statistics and to publish a yoar book to which wo can all resort (and I may say at once that had there been suoh a year book in the past I should have found it of enormous advantage for my own professional work and public work)., I am in very strong sympathy but I am not at all certain that in the sentence, the elimination of which I move, we are not contemplating something in the nature of the disestablishment of the private investigator, and the substitution for him of a publio official.   If that should be the case I think it would be a misfortune not only because many private investi-gators can speak with authority quite as great as that whioh any public official can possess, but also because -I am perfectly certain that you never will eliminate the private investigator, and that the only result of the promulgation of analytical results obtained by modern statistical methods In an official publication will mean a great deal of violent diBsont outside and a good deal of friction in whioh the new authority may become involved.   It is not as though these analytical methods which have been developed by the advances of statistical science in reoent years are all absolutely agreed.    There are different schools of statisticians.  All of thorn jjroduoe extremely Interesting work, and somo of it of great value, but they do not all follow the same methods and unfortunately they do not all agree with one another, and they very often do not hesitate to express their dissent from one another in quite unBoientlfio language.   1 must confess that, as one who would seek to benefit very greatly by the work of the new Bureau, I dQ not want to Bee it involved in that sort of thing.To pass to another point, I have of course assumed in reading the report that the Bureau would got, let us say, from England and Wales returns and statistics in respect of all the large Departments of State, and would do the same with each of the Dominions, would examine them oritioally,
and would report its views upon thorn not merely as statistical mattors, but in the words of the report itself in a paragraph whioh I think comes a little later, but which I hope I am not out of order in quoting: &quot;To utilise its staff in the skilled work of surveying and presenting information collected by existing statistical and other authorities, in reference&apos; to social and economic conditions throughout the Empire&quot;.   I venture to say upon that that no statistician, be he ever so much the super-statistician of whom our Chairman spoke- and such a one would certainly be required - could ever hope to go through his official career without oxciting the keenest resentment on the part of many people, not only Departments of State, but Ministers of State and the Press in various parts of the Empire in reference to his comments upon the particular social and economio conditions prevailing in the Communities with which he was dealing.   He would begin to rub up sores.   It would be said at once that he could not know the local conditions, he was a theorist sitting in London thousands of miles away from where these things were going on, and it would utterly out of place for him with his limited range of comprehension of local difficulties to attempt to draw conclusions, from mere figures, as to the particular social and economic conditions of the people whose ire he had excited.   They would say of course that figures can prove anything, the usual tag, and they would say it certainly in the more distant parts of the Empire, with the comment that figures done by some fellow in London were not worthy for a moment of local consideration.   This is, unhappily for me. my first appearance at this Conference and some of you may think I am uttering a certain amount of nonsense, but as a practical illustration of that sort of thing I might tell you what happened once in my own case.   I have representatives of my staff working in Edinburgh, Dublin, and Cardiff, on what is in the main national statistics.   My Dublin rep-resentative was very much interested in the social conditions of Ireland, and particularly of Dublin, and he wrote a valuable paper or made some observations, I forget which, on infantile mortality prevalent in the City of Dublin. It did not please the political people.   They did not attempt to challenge the findings of this young Actuary, which by the way were perfectly sound: they knew he was a Scotsman and a representative of a Government Department centred in London, so they said &quot;This fellow&apos;s conclusions are not worth con-sideration for he is out of sympathy with the aspirations of the Irish people&quot;.   That I am afraid is the kind of thing which the Director will he up against if he publishes what I think this report contemplates, a learned disquisition upon social conditions in various parts of the Empire.   Then, as regards the Statesmen who might have to consider his report, and his conclusions, let us take the Home Statesmen.   He may come to certain conclusions which aro of an unfavourable character as regards certain things going on in Great Britain. It is highly probable that the Department which is concerned in those matters will come to an entirely contrary opinion. It is almost human nature that it should be so, and I am very much afraid the Bureau would come to one set of conclusions, the department concerned would come to another; questions would be asked in Parliament; and the Minister would support his own department, and the Bureau would at once be in trouble. My own opinion is that the Bureau would be unwise to touch matters which are the subject of investigation by the departr ments concerned.    Finally, suppose Ministers wanted to be advised by the Bureau and were prepared to lean upon the Bureau for advice, and to sit at the feet of the Director; before any statistician can submit his conclusions in a way to carry conviction to tho mind of a Minister and the mind of Parliament, esneoia]?y   if they are conclusions which are
3&apos; 131not obvious from general oonsiderations or are novel oonolu-sions which have not previously been in the public mind, he has got to discover some new way of expressing himself.    We oan understand and follow the very valuable mathematical demonstrations whioh are produced from time to time on statis-tical subjects but when we talk to the general public or to members of Parliament or oven to Cabinet Ministers, about skew curves and variants and correlation, and matters of that kind, we are simply talking to the air,   they will listen to what you say but it will make no impression on their minds because they do not understand it.     I am bound to say that from my reading of statistics, I have never yet found any oase In which a statistician, after producing very valuable results, has been able to express them, and the reasons which have brought him to his conclusions, in language which can be under-stood of the people, and until we can do that I am very much afraid that the use or the practical application of modern statistical methods will lag behind.I am afraid I may have Bald a good deal which is contro-versial,   but I say it with an earnest desire that the new Bureau should have a fair start and set out on its career with good prospects.    While believing that what I have said is germane to the present position, I Indulge the hope that after a time, in the course of the natural development which is Inevitable in an organisation of this kind, it will be possible to do all that the Committee have contemplated, in their report, but my present view is that at this stage it is not wise to promise to undertake the advanced scientific analysis of figures that are obtained, but that the primary purpose of the Bureau should be to co-ordinate the form in which statistics are collected, to obtain the statistics from the various parts of the Empire, and to present them in the form of the Year Book whioh the report proposes.     I move, Sir, in order to test the feeling of the Conference on this very important matter, the elimination of the last paragraph ch page 1 of Mr. Readers draft.CHAIRMAN:   Is that amendment seconded?MR. VIVIAN:   I should like to second that amendment.   In the terms in which Sir Alfred Watson proposes it, It is a method of raising a question which I had myself Intended to raise upon a paragraph which seemed to me to raise the point in an even more aggressive form, that Is 2 (d).   May I say here that part of my difficulty in approaching this dooument arises in connexion with general principles such as Sir Alfred Watson has raised, and which would, if adopted by the Conference; involve shall we say, revising the tone not only of speoific paragraphs, but generally of the whole draft.   If I may refer by anticipation - we are discussing general principles and therefore it may perhaps be permitted - to 2 (d) that con-templates that the Bureau, in addition to other things which It is proposed it should do, should act as an advisory authority towards the statistical officers of the several Governments of the Empire.     The conception whioh I have formed of the Bureau&apos;s function is the creation of a body of statistics which are in a sense an innovation, and in which there is at present no existing activity, that is the creation of a body of Imperial Statistics.     The Imperial field is, I think I am right in saying, vacant at the present time, and if we con-ceive of the Bureau as one whose sole object and function is Imperial, that is to say, the synthesis of the statistics of the several countries from the Imperial standpoint, we are creating a function, a province, which does not overlap, and which does not oome into conflict with that of any existing authority.   It appears to me that m that ground the Bureau
is safe, and that its aotivitlee aro hound to bo oxtra-ordinarily usoful and wholly unaseailablo; but directly the quostion arises of its advising, of its being ready to advise, the statistical authorities of oach separate country, not on tho framing of their statistics from the point of view of thoir utility for Imperial purpoBes, but from the point of view of their utility for thoir sovoral national purposes, an entirely difforent set of circumstances comes into opera-tion.     Thero aro men responsible for the national statistics of each country, who aro capable and experienced men, and well acquainted with their own local conditions and circum-stanoev .    Tho momont that any question arises of advice being tendered by the Bureau for national purposes there is serious danger of the Bureau coming into conflict with existing authorities in the field of those existing author-ities,     I have a certain amount of experience of Advisory Committees, and thero is an inovitable tendency which may give occasion for conflicts.    A body which, in the first place is under tho liability to give advice when approached, tends to become a body which has a right to advise on some&apos; occasions or on all occasions, and such a body imperceptibly develops into one whioh entertains the expectation that its advice will bo taken.    That course of evolution is at any rate one whioh has, in the case of Advisory Committees, been made the subject of apprehension.    For that reason it appears to mo that tho moment tho functions of tho Bureau go beyond the Imperial functions, that is to say, the act of oo-ordina-tion and of the assembling of information from the Imperial standpoint, it steps out of a province in which it is un-atisailable and runs a considerable risk of creating con-troverey by overlapping authorities which are established for the express purpose of statistics within each country.   It is for that reason that I should in any event have asked the Conference to re-consider paragraph 2 (d) and Sir Alfred Watson has now raised the point upon an earlier paragraph.In tho opening speech of the Chairman, indications were givon that the intontion of tho Buroau wa3 not to deal with statistics, or with tho statistical authorities, of any country except from the exprossly Imperial point of view, and I noted thoso observations bocauso they appeared to mo to conflict with paragraph 2 (d) at any rato and it was in order to olear up what tho precise intontion was that I   intended to raiso tho point.     If the views of the Chairman as express-ed in his opening comments correctly ropresent those of the Conference, then I think it follows that tho document will have to bo revised in rospect certainly of 2 (d) and possibly in vrespoct of the paragraph to which Sir Alfred Watson has adverted, with a view of clearing up any ambiguity which it may contain.    With thoso views I desire to be rogardod as seconding Sir Alfred Watson in favour of whatever revision of the&apos;document is necessary to exclude the possibility of tho Bureau creating or provoking controversy by invading fields which are already covered, and in favour also of its functions boing dofined so as to restrict it to whs-t after all is the important aspect of ito work, the synthesis of statistics from tho Imporial point of view.CHAIRMAN:    There are two questions, it appears to me, that are raised hero which it may be expedient, with a view to pro-ceeding with tho bUGinoso in regular order, to separate. One is the point of tho relations between the Central Bureau and tho individual countries of the Empiro to which Mr.Vivian
has just alluded.     The other is tho point of eliminating tho paragraph to which Sir Alfred Watson has directed our attention.    The two things aro brought together., but the specific point to which this paragraph is immediately directed, I think, is what I referrod to in my opening remarks&apos;as the &apos; functions of the Bureau as a place of statistical research. I would suggest that it is.convenient to take that aspect of tho mattor here, not losing sight of tho other of oourse, but remembering that statistical research may be confined to the statistics of a locality or may only bccomo possiblo in oon- &apos; nexion with bringing together of tho statistics of many local!-ties.     It io in tho latter aspoct of tho matter that I think tho Oommittoo intonded to express its opinion as to the desira-bility of tho Bureau fcoing a place of statistical research. Perhaps Mr. Knibbs may like to oxpross his views on those topics.MR. KNIBBS:   Mr. Chairman, I think we are greatly indebtod to Sir Alfred Watson for bringing tho mattor undor prominent notice, and also to Mr * Vivian for oxprossing his view of the functions of the Bureau, becaueo it brings into relief the essential nature of the statistical function.    It is obvious from Mr. Vivian1s romarks (and one would almost have inferred it from Sir Alfrod Watson1 s romarks, if ono did not know the learned actuary) that the mattor of mero assembling is  -always a simple mattor.    Those of us who aro actually engaged in statistical work know that when ono variable has a complex law of relation with tho othor variable, procise knowledge may bo necessary for the proper assembling of the facts.    Particularly is this tho case when tho rangos of the variable aro different. I would liko to express it as my conviction, after considerable oxperienco in the statistical field, and some study of the science   underlying statistics, that it is quite Impossible to have efficient direction of a statistical Bureau by ono who is not expert in statistical method.   I submit that wo should make it quito clear that we aro not proparod to rocommend a Bureau, the hoad of which shall be a moro administrative officer. Ho must bo a professional statistician   with a commanding knowledge of statistical method, who has in addition common-sense and administrative ability.     It is not by any means a supor-man, as has boon suggested, to have that combination of qualifications.     No other person would bo regarded as satis-factory by myself, and as far as I know the opinions of the statisticians of the so if-governing Dominions tho same may be said   by eaoh of them.     In ordor that ho may properly exercise his functions and be able to suggost or advise persons in all parts of tho world in regard to supplying information in an appropriate form to be properly assembled; the Director must bo a man who commands respoct in regard to his technical know-, ledge of statistics,&quot; that is essential.     I am perfectly certain that Sir Alfred Watson would not in his own field accept sugges-tions from a mero administrator who did not understand the subject of assembling information,     He would be unprepared to accept mero administrative directions as to what ho was to collect. It requires&apos;knowledge to direct .     The characteristic of progress in control is that we aro roalising the necessity of tho moro difficult and higher function being associated with the easier one.     You can see it for example of the Navy.     To be a Cora-mander of a ship one must now have the&apos; engineering qualification. Ono is not in a position to direct  a ship:s movements unless one has that knowledge.     There is also a movement&quot;in insurance circles which shows that it has come to be rocognisod that ho who directs the business is a hotter man if he have actuarial knowledge.     While wo must avoid putting in command some more academic statistician ono who has that class of knowledge ard has
1*1346.aleo administrative ability and common-sense is alone qualified to direct operations.     Therefore we shall do well to put the words in question in the list of requirements.     Throughout the drafting of the report we intend to make it quite clear that wo will not recommend nor shall we bo satisfied with a director who is not technically a statistician, who has not the command of that mathematical knowledge which is appropriate thereto, namely, that which also lies   behind actuarial science, and that if we keep that in mind right through this we shall secure the right type of man for the Directorship.     Without that I do not think any of us will be satisfied with the re-commendation.MR. READE:   Mr. Chairman, I rise to oppose this amendment.   I think the Conference will realise at once that the amendment if carried would entirely transform what has been intended by this report.     It would very seriously limit the functions of the Central Bureau to be established;   I may say it would almost limit it to the&apos; collection of material, and would pro-hibit it from expressing any opinion upon the material.   That I am sure is the last thing the Conference desires, and it does seem to me that the reasons given by Sir Alfred Watson are not very strong, certainly not conclusive.     His first point was that there are numbers of private investigators largely engaged in examining statistics, and writing monographs-and expressing opinions on various points, and that therefore that should be left to then,     I cannot see that is any reason why the Central Bureau should not also investigate, why it 3hould leave the field entirely to private persons.     It is quite true that if the Bureau does what is outlined in this report it will embark upon controversial matters, but surely in statistics, ae in everything else, controversy is very healthy: it is a necessary condition of advance, and I do not see why that should in any way interfere with the utility of the Bureau, the fact that it does express views which will not be generally accepted, and which will conflict with views already published or give rise to fresh controversy.     I do not think that it is necessarily inconsistent with what may be called a Government Department.   I am sure for instance that the representatives of the Local Government Board, reports by Sir George Kewman, for instance, deal with a great many oontro-versial matters; reports by the Home Offico on the causes and treatment of crime - one could think of a dozen cases where official reports issued by leading Government Departments have entered on very controversial matters, and where that has been generally welcomed by the Press and everybody else.Then another thing, which Sir Alfred Watson feared was that the result would be serious differences with the Dominions and Colonies; reports would be issued, as they would say by an officer in London who knows nothing about it dealing with their local affairs.     In the first place it is contemplated 1by the constitution of the Bureau as outlined in this report.that the Dominions shall be actually represented on its staff.     Then the whole origin of it as represented by this Conference ought I think to ensure that there shall be cordial co-operation, and that before the Bureau undertook to issue a report let us say on labour conditions in Australia or South Africa it would&apos;consult the representatives of those places , and at any rate ensure that there should be no unpleasantness even if the views held here and the views held in those Dominions were not in agreement.
With regard to what Mr. Vivian said, he was objecting to the clause which stated that the control Bureau would act as : an advisory authority on the ground that advisory authorities, although they might begin by merely giving information when they v/ere asked for it, inevitably encroached on that, and took to offoring opinions whether they were asked or not, and expecting that those opinions would be acted upon.   Well, that again would dopond I think on the discretion, tact, common-sense of the director of the Bureau, and the remainder of the staff.     Of course it would bo an unfortunate thing if the Bureau took to offering gratuitous advice to tho various Dominions on tho way in which they conducted their statistics in a manner whioh was offensive to thorn, but I do not think roally ono noed anticipate that.    It is practically con-do Jiming in advance tho manner in which the Bureau will be conducted.    What the report says is that there should bo a central authority which Dominions, Colonies, or any part of the Empire engaged in statistics could consult if thoy liked, and that it should be in a position to offer advice owing to its oxpert knowledge     I do not see how you can possibly cut that out of tho functions of any Bureau of the kind.    No doubt other people wish to express thoir opinions, so I say no moro, although I feel I could cay a good deal.     I wish to oppose this amendment very strongly.wB. KNIBBS: Might I say I also endorse tho views of Mr. Reade.MR. SHIRRAS:   I wish to endorse what Mr. Knibbs and Mr. Reade have said,   It is obsolutoly essential that we keep here the phrasing as the Oommittoo originally drafted it, because so much is being done from day to day in etatisties.     If the Bureau cannot apply modern methods it will be a great loss to the Imperial Bureau.    There is no danger such as that antici^ pated by Sir Alfred Watson.   For oxample the director (and ho is going to be I am   sure a man with large oxperience, wide common-sense) would refer to the Government of India for any-thing on the duration of lifo as deducod from tho Indian life tablos published in tho Census before ho gave his conclusions to the world.    On the other point which Mr. Vivian referred to, the question of making the Bureau an advisory authority, surely that is what wo statisticians want.    From day to day we aro having real live &quot;problems before us, for examplo the construction of a Cost-of-living index-number.   We   want to be. able to go to the Imperial Bureau and say: &quot;This is our pro-blem; do you think this is or this is not tho beet way of . tackling the question.&quot;     It io important therefore that we should; although I quite see Sir Alfred Watson&apos;s and Mr. Vivian&apos;s point, that thero might be a danger if you got the wrong man, that he might nettle up Governments in a way that would be, to put it mildly, dangerous; but I am quite certain that if ho is the man that we hope him to be with a real live practical experionoo of statistics, and at the same time a man of large administrative experience, there will be no danger whatsoever.    I therefore have very much pleasure indeed in ondorsing what iar. Knibbs and Mr. Roade have said.MR. COUSINS:    I should like to add a word if I may.   I think wo owo Sir Alfred Watson a dobt of gratitude for probing really to what is the root of the whole matter.     He has detected the essential character which it was designed to give to this Bureau, and ho has detected it correctly.    As Mr. Vivian
a.point out, that principle which is enunciated there ia carried throughout a series of propositions which follow it; in other words&apos;the Committee has suggested a Bureau which is certainly not to be limited to tho mere mechan-ical process of collecting Empire statistics and present-ing them in tho form whioh has passed muster previously, but whioh I trust will pass muster no longer.   It seems to me that by giving this character to the Bureau we are not going to promote friction; we are going to remove the possibilities of friction, because we shall realise at once the   moral, authority not only the moral authority but the practical technical and professional superiority of the staff of this Bureau in comparison with that which is possible of accomplishment in our own individual departments.     I am speaking now as a representative of a self-governing Dominion in which statistics are in their oarly days of development, and I speak quite seriously when I say that a Bureau fashioned as this is to be fashioned will secure our cordial co-operation and will be regarded by us as a valuable source of help in all timeB of need, in other words that we shall feel that here is an authority which we can respect, and which we can trust, and which will give us at critical points in our career, and also on a great many technical questions, and in the case of technical difficulties which arise from time to time, that assistance which we so sorely need.     I am perfectly certain myself that assuming we have the right man at the head (and if we do not have the right man at the head the whole thing will collapse;   I admit that so much depends on the personality of the Director) in this form the Bureau will carry weight and move towards suooess.    Deprive it of this essential characteristic,&apos; and I believe the whole soheme is fore-doomed to failure.MR. R.H* COATS: Mr Chairman, it seems to mo that anyone in charge in a large way of statistical work must have three oualifications: he must in the first place be a good organiser with all the tact and common-sense that organisation work requires, but in the second place he must be a mathematician to the extent of being able to answer a mathematical oritic out of his own mouth, and to devise fundamental principles of procedure.   These principles strotch, as Mr. KnibbB remarked, into the realm of collection no le;ts than of analysis.    Unless you know what your objects are you cannot collect your data correctly.   In the third place I think tho head of a statistical Bureau 3hould be a good working economist, appreciating the broad economic and social drift of his time.     I therefore associate myself cordially with Mr. Reade!e remarkB, and I would like to soe this re-main very much in the form in which it is at present.
MR. HAWTREY: I do not want to express any view on this controversy which I have listenod to with the greatest interest, but it struck me in the course of it that there was a certain amount of   misunderstanding arising.    As I understand, Sir Alfred Watson&apos;s objection was to analysis being one of the functions of the Bureau, analysis in the sense of discovering and demon-strating tendencies, whereas several of the speakers have apparently assumed him to mean that almost any intelligent consideration of statistics should be excluded.    For example, Mr. Findlay Shirras said that it would be within the functions of the Bureau to advise as to suitable constitution of an indexr number for cost of living.     It is a very good example, but that has nothing to do with what is technically called analysis; that is entirely a question of co-ordinating, unifying and similar functions at a stage before analysis begins.     I cannot see that functions of that kind would be in any way affected by the exclusion of the sentence to which Sir Alfred Watson referred.MR. SHIRRAS: &quot;But would apply the analytical methods which havo beon developed by the advance of statistical science to the examination of the material&quot;   I understand Sir Alfred Watson would like that omitted.MR. HAV/TREY: Yes.     I understood that he meant the elucidating and discovering of tendencies from recorded statistics.     I cannot seo that is in any way implied in the other functions of the Bureau.     Then there was another thing on whioh it seemed to me there was a danger of misunderstanding, and that is that the exolusion of analysis from the functions of the Bureau does not mean that the direotor need not know anything about mathematical analysis of statistics.     It is clear that the head of the Bureau ought to be not merely a Secretary; he ought to be a statistician, and that is equally so whether ho actually is responsible in his official capacity for analysis or whether he merely advises on the co-ordinating and unifying the statistical information referring to all parts of the Empire.     As I say I do not wish to express a view on one side or the other in the controversy, but it struck me those two points were becoming grounds of misunderstanding, and that it would not be out of placo to call attention to that.DR. DUHLOP: I would really like to understand Sir Alfred Wataon&apos;s ^ point.   He says these four lines should be omitted.   Does he imply that the head of this very important 3ureau is not to    &apos;   . use statistical method, but that we are to have a statistician and limit him to acting *-.s an arithmetician and not to use ordinary statistical methods?    If it were a legal appointment surely the lawyer would not be excluded from using all his legal knowledge,     I do not really understand Sir Alfred Watson&apos;a position.SIR WILLIAM THOMPSON: Mr. Chairman, may I say that I feel very greatly indebtod, and I am sure the other members do too, to the observations of Sir Alfred Watson.     His vast experience in dealing with figures carry a great deal of weight.     But in this case his reference to Dublin makes me disagree with him altogether.     I claim to know something of Dublin, living there for 50 years, and having been in practice for a number of years, and being registrar-general for over 10 years, long before his representative came from London, whom I have had the privilege of knowing, and who has helped me
idL38considerably in social affairs.     papers have been prepared and meetings have been held in connection with this subject whioh his report, dealt with.     It is one of the characteristics of Dublin, and of Ireland, no matter what their political feelings are, or their religious persuasions are, on social reforms we are all on the same platform.   All social people welcomed Mr. Kydfs admirable analysis of infant mortality which he dealt with, and I for one have not heard or do not know of any political bias taken up in this paper;   I am not convinced from the statements he brought forward, and I fully endorse Mr. Reade&apos;s improvement.CHAIRMAN: Perhaps Sir Alfred Watson would like to make this point clearer.SIR ALFRED WATSON: After listening to various speeches I feel that I must be getting very incompetent to express myself, for which I apologise very humbly to the Conference.    May I just recapitulate?    The resolution was moved to raise what seems to me an important issue, and the words the deletion of which I havo moved seemed the most appropriate peg on which to raise that issue.     I do not say that that is the best place on which to raise it, but it Is extremely difficult in going through the detail paragraphs which follow to find a point at which the question could best be raised, and I thought it was best raised on this purely general paragraph.     With reference first of all to Mr.Knibb!s remark on the personnel, and particularly with reference to the head of the new establishment, I can only endorse every word he said.     It was never for one moment in my mind to suggest that the head of a department such as this, dealing entirely with statistics, should be anything other than an eminent statistician.     It seems an elementary point in one&apos;s mind that he must be of eminence and a very competent statistic-ian if only from the sole point of view of the discretion he has got to exercise in the collection of the material.&apos;    In all statistical work that is a good deal more than half the battle, and I can only say that I quite agree on that point with Mr. Knibbs.Mr. Reade frankly is against me on the general question, quite apart from the matter of personnel, and I am sure we respect each otherfs views.    But I should like to say, with respect to him, that his argument that Government Departments issue controversial reports which are welcomed by the public in this country does not appear to me to really touch the point. The. danger that I see is that a body which is not a publio department in this country, or not a public department of this country, will issue reports inevitably dealing with the work of departments here, and those departments will assuredly have to defend themselves; their Minister will have to defend them and the controversy will be between the new body and the publio departments.     Similarly in the case of the distant parts of the Dominions I feel quite sure that no critical remarks from a central Bureau stationed in London or some other comparatively remote centre will be. welcomed by the people of the Dominion concerned, and would escape criticism among those to whom the observations of the Bureau have been primarily addressed.MR. KNIBBS: They would pump plenty of metaphorical lead into him if he is wrong.SIR ALFRED WATSON: Mr. Reade made another point, that the Dominionsf position will be safeguarded, because each Dominion will be represented on its staff.     That may be perfectly true, but, as I have read the report, the representatives of the Dominions of the staff will be junior officers who have come over here not
to adviae the director of the Bureau aa to the problems in their own country, but in a quite minor capacity to acquire experience, and to go back to their own Dominion and apply it.     Knowing aomething of the way in whioh departments and bodies of this kind work, I cannot imagine that the director of the Bureau, having come to certain conclusions, will be prepared to refer them to junior members of his staff, and temporary members at that, and to modify his views on any expression of opinion which they might think fit to put before him.Then Mr. Cousins said that the Dominions statistical departments want an authority that they can respect, and to which they can go for assistance, and he laid stress on the personnel of the proposed Bureau and the head of it.   There again I have never contemplated that a Bureau of this kind would be other than a body which would assist people in their problems when they went to it and asked for assistance, but that is a very widely different thing from the department setting out on its own to review the social and economic conditions of the various parts of the Empire, and to publish its conclusions in a sense with the heads of the various local bodies concerned.     That I think is the point of difference between us.     I have never for one moment thought that the department would not be adequately staffed in order to give its assistance, and would not give the fullest assistance to those who desire it.     That I think also answers the point raised by Mr. Coats.   He laid stress, aa Mr,Cousins did, on the personal qualities of the head of the department and with his observationa I have nothing but concurrence to offer.Aa to Sir William Thompson&apos;s remark, I know aa well aa he doea that the thoughtful social workers in Ireland and people of his class, and people with whom he is associated, welcomed the observationa of Mr, Kyd, the gentleman of whom I spoke on the matter of controveray, but.my observation waa perfectly true; it was a quotation.    What I was referring to was the view that politicians took of the functions of my man stationed in Dublin, and I venture to aay that where any central Bureau tabulates view a baaed on its investigations as to the social conditions prevailing or any other conditions prevailing in any particular part of the Empire which views are inconvenient to the politicians concerned, or obnoxious to them, they will not fail to be challenged quite as promptly and quite as incisively as the conclusions of my representative were challenged on the occasion to which I have referred.THE CHAIRMAN: I think possibly this matter has been talked about sufficiently to enable us to vote on the subject.   I merely remark that a part of what has been raised ia dealt with in detail in what ought to be the following resolution, the adoption of paragraph 2.   In that connection it may not. be improper to remark that Mr. Readers re-draft evades one of the difficultiea in the report of the Committee.   It may be desired to amend it.     That we shall take up on the next resolution.   I suggested (and I think what has passed
justifies that suggestion) whether we aro to conceive of tho Bureau as of the nature of a statistical rosearch institution or not. That appears to me to bo tho fundamental point raised by tho question of omitting or including these four lines.MR. KNIBBS: Is it not that in addition to assembling ho must bocompetent to do othor things?   Assembling is its ordinary routine function, but in addition to that it must be competent to analyse, etc.CHAIRMAN:   That is so.UK, VIVIAN:     I think that after what has fallen it is desirable that I should mako clear the attitude in which I seconded Sir Alfred Watson&apos;o resolution.     I do not desire to opposo the suggestion that this Buroau should bo able to undertake statistical research, I understood Sir Alfred Watson1s objection to that was tho nature of tho resoaroh as overlapping the functions of statistical re-search by the statistical authorities of tho several countries, and it was on tho subject of intervention in the several national spheres that I desired to second  his proposal.   But on the question of research or no research I am not opposing.     I think that if there is a provinoe of an Imperial rosearch it ought to go to this Bureau, and I think that there is such a provinco.     My real objects would porhaps be bettor secured on a subsequent paragraph,CHAIRMAN:   As a matter of form we will take a vote on tho question of the inclusion or omission of these four linos.(Amendment put to tho Conference and lost).(Retention of the linos proposod to bo deleted agreed to).

</content>
</cab>
