<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/125/0 images: 205-208</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document ib ine Ifropefig of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, ]Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1921.163SECRET.CP. 3020. 1CABINET.SPECIAL WEEKLY REPORT ONUNEMPLOYMENT.lso. HI.WEEK ENDED JUNE 3, 1921.T. J. MACNAMARA,Ministry of Labour.
I. NOTE ON UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION IN UNITED KINGDOM on june 3, 1921.1. The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent. The average for the ten years prior to the war, according to Trade Onion unem-ployment figures, was 4-7 per cent.  It was as high as 7-8 per cent, m 1908 and 7-7 per cent, in 1909.Throughout 1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent, in September and 3-2 per cent, in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.The figures for 1920 are :- ret cent-To the end of  January-February ... March April May June July August September OctoberXT_____1__December ...The figures for 1921 are To the end of-January   ... February ... , March April1-6 11 09 111-2 1:4 1-6 2-9 5-3 8-7 606-9 8-5 100 1762. Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges.	1920.			1921.					Aug. 27.	Nov. 12.   Dec. 3. 1		Jan. 7.	Feb. 4.	Mar. 4.	April 1.	April 8.Men  Civilians Ex-service   . -Boys Women Girls Totals  ...	86,476 142,600 17,608 58,982 17,480	134,868 239,816 21,872 97,964 22,237	137,222 263,553 . 21,379 119,886 23,663 565,703	250,365 312,147 35,704 215,869 41,441	357.701 362,866 48,507 286,821 55,419	450,651 379,184 51,571 319,394 53,877	625,663 377,250 62,655 382,573 57,939	694,379 397,979 C7,893 394,388 . 60,968	818,096	516,757		855,526	1,111,314	1,254,677	1,506,080	1,615,607-	1.921.								April 15.	April 22.	April 29.	May 6.	May 13.	May 20.	May 27.	June 3.fMen  Civilians Ex-service   .. Boys Women Girls , Totals &quot;..	732,788 412,654 71,285 412,784 63,727	.787,097 419,038 74,332 429,281 &apos;    66,713	833,320 427,269 77,033 448,324 68,113,	880,687 437,021 79,230 461,395 68,729	922,619 444,145 81,486 471,790 60,078	986,728 454,267 84,725 481,735 70,267	11,472,012* 85,383 497,845 71,538	1,489,600 84,100 502,700 71,000	1,693,238	1,776,461	1,854,059   1,927,062		1,989,118	2,077,722	2,126,778	2,147,400* KSeparate figures not yet available.f Estimated figures.In addition to the above figures, which represent persons wholly unemployed, 1,077,660 adults are in receipt of uneployment benefit or out-of-work donation under systematic short-time schemes.
II. EMERGENCY WORK.As announced by the Prime Minister on the 19th October, certain schemes have been put in hand by the Local Authorities in conjunction with the Ministry of Transport and the Ministry of Health, and by the Local Authorities themselves, designed to secure work for unemployed men, preferentially ex-Service men. The following is the result at this date: (a.) New Arterial Roads.21,393 men employed up to date (in and around London, 2,784; Provinces, 18,609).(b.) Road Maintenance.It is estimated that employment has been provided for approximately 20,000 men over and above those ordinarily so employed.(c.) Housing (Acceleration of the Lay-Out of Roads and Sewers and Approved Housing Schemes).Men employed up to the 27th May, 3,976 (in and around London, 304; Provinces, 3,672).(d.) Lord St. Davids&apos; Committee.Men employed on work other than the above up to the 27th May, 32,961 (in and around London, 5,702; Provinces, 27,259).(e.) Alternative Work in Government Establishments.War Office establishments: men employed up to the 28th May, 2,787 (in and around London, 2,069; Provinces, 718).Alternative work provided in Admiralty establishments: men employed up to the 28th May, 6,456 (in and around London, nil; Provinces, 6,456).(f.) Short-time in Government Establishments.Number of men who have found employment up to date as a result of the intro-duction of short-time system. Men employed-up to the 28th May: War Office estab-lishments, 2,029 (in and around London, 1,902; Provinces, 127) ; Admiralty estab-lishments, 3,667 (in and around London, 194; Provinces, 3.473).(g.) Office of Works Emergency Programme.The special Emergency Programme of decorating and repair work in GoVern-ment Departments by the Office of Works is now completed.(h.) Emergency Work found by Local Authorities. iTotal number of men employed up to the 27th May, 12,606 (in and around London, 2,857; Provinces, 9,749).Total labour employed on above schemes = 105,875.[6381]   -&quot;     -\GENERAL.No improvement in the general industrial position is reported, and, in the absence of any settlement of the coal dispute, unemployment continues to increase. All the larger firms in the iron and steel trades have either closed down or are working short-time. A slight improvement, due to fresh repair contracts coming to hand, is reported in shipbuilding. The position in the textile trades remains unchanged, and, although a few firms are making use of oil fuel, the experiment has apparently not proved very successful. The lace and hosiery trades are almost at a standstill, but in the boot and shoe industry employment remains comparatively good, although short-time working has been generally adopted. In the pottery trade work is also practically suspended, and the fishing industry continues to be seriously affected by the lack of fuel.
As reports for the week ended the 27th May have been received from only 374 Local Authorities out of 409 who were asked to furnish information, it is probable that the Relief Schemes which have been inaugurated by the Government and Local Authorities are finding employment for a number of men in excess of the figures given.III. 50,000 EX-SERYICE MEN TO BE TRAINED IN THE BUILDINGINDUSTRY.The industrial stagnation caused by the coal stoppage, and the consequent uncertainty of the outlook, have seriously interfered with the progress of this scheme. The employers, however, have set up District Committees in many of the more important industrial centres, and it is understood that they will shortly be posting notices on all jobs advising their workpeople that the job is only open to men willing to work with and assist in the training of ex-Service men taken on under the scheme. This action has already been taken in London by the Master Builders and also by the Office of Works.In addition steps are being taken to make it clear that contracts for building and constructional work in which the Government is financially interested will in general be confined to contractors who are employing men under the conditions of the scheme.In the meantime the total applications are 16,914. In the London and South-Eastern Division 7,276 men have applied, and the following are figures for other Divisions: South Midlands and Eastern Counties, 1,114; South-Western Counties, 1,419; West Midlands, 1,715; Yorkshire and East Midlands, 1,556 ; North&apos;-Western Counties, 2,230; Northern Division, 438; Scotland, 972; Wales, 194.About 60 men have been taken on under the scheme, chiefly by the Office of Works in the London area; in addition the London employers Committee have allocated a further 130 men among employers in the area, and these men should be starting work immediately.IY.   PAYMENT OF UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT AND OUT-OF-WORKDONATION.1., The following statement represents the position as shown by the Exchange-registers on the 27th May: 	Men.     1	Women.	Total.Numbers wholly unemployed Numbers on short time*	1.472,012 566,337	497,845 511,323	1,969,857 1,077,660Total	2,038,349 i	1,009,168	3,047,5172. As a result of the operation of the Act of the 3rd March, 1921 (and of the-grant of Out-of-Work Donation to ex-Service men and women), the following work-people are in receipt of Unemployment Benefit or Out-of-Work Donation: 				Men.	Women.	Total.Wholly unemployed (estimated) On short time*	1,435,688 566,8.87	464,369 511,323	1,900,057 1,077.660Total   ..	2,002,025	975,692	2,977,717* There is no record of the number of workpeople on short time, who are not eligible to receive-Unemployment Insurance or Out-of-work Donation, i&apos;.e., those who are employed in such a way that they xre unable to comply with the rules aS to continuity of unemployment.

</content>
</cab>
