<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/125/0 images: 261-262</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.)ONFIDEWEIAL,CABINET!U?j522fi* LEAGUE    OB1    NATIONS.&quot;A&quot; &amp; &quot;B&quot; MandatesNotes of a Conference, held in Lord Curzon&apos;s ivoom at the Foreign Office, S.W.I., on Wednesday, Juno 1st, 1921, at 6.3.0 p.m.ProsontRt,Eon,Earl Curzon of Ke dies ton, K.G. fG.CiS.I., G.CI.B.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in; the Chair.lit. Hon. A.J. Balfour, O.M., M.P., Lord President of the Council.Rt. Hon. W.S. churchill, M.P., Secretary of State for the colonies.Rt. Hon. K.A*L. fisher, M.P., president, Board of Education.The following also were present :--Sir C. Hurst, K.CB., K.C, foreign Office Major II, W. Young, D.S.O., Foreign Office Sir,&apos;3ric Brumraoiid, K.(S.J .0., C.B., Secretary-General of\ tho Leagie of Nations.G.S. Spicor, C.B.,,.......SecretaryaThe Conference had before them certain papers, eoimunicated by the Secretariat of tho League of Nations in which it was pointed out that some of the Members of the Council were anxious, owing to the attitude of tho United States towards the subject of Mandatesj not to proceed with the question of passing tie Mandates at the forthcoming meeting of the Council, unless an agreement on this point, had first been reached between the United Stales and the Allies. , The Secretariat wished to know whether H.M. Govern-mont agreed to this course.It was pointed out that both -the French and the Spaniards were very averse to take any aotion opposed to the wishes of the
United States and would probably bo supported by tho Belgians and the Chinese, and that tho Italians would adopt a similar attitude, though for different reasons, due to their apprehen-sions as regards the fato of tho Tripartite Agreement.It was agreed that it was important to do everything possible to get the mandates passocl without delay.     It was urged on the one hand that failure to accomplish this would seriously prejudice and endanger our whole position in Palestine and Mesopotamia:   that it might bo emphasized that so far from receiving any benefit whatever from these Mandates Great Britain would reap nothing &quot;but trouble and expense for a generation or more, and that if we could not secure the Mandates at once we had bettor make it clear that wo must decline any further responsibility and withdraw altogether from those territories.On the other hand it was pointed out that it would, be exceedingly difficult in practice, however desirable in theory to withdraw from Palestine and Uosopotamia and hand thoso countries over to anarchy, and it was questioned whether there was any serious disadvantage in continuing, for a while to administer thoso regions without the formal passing of the Mandate by the Council.The Conference felt generally that it was highly dosir-able to make every effort to secure a majority at the next meeting of the Council in favour of proceeding with the Mandates, but decided in the first instance to refer tho question to the Cabinet, and roquested the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies to propare a memorandum for that purpose.2nd June,. 1981..SOO t- The papers referred to in paragraph 1 which wore under consideration by tho Conforenco aro not attached hereto. . Copies will bo furnished, howovcr, on application to tho Cabinet Secretariat,

</content>
</cab>
