<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/125/0 images: 272-273</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JThis Document is the PYooerty of &apos;Hla Britannic-MeJesVa Government 6 * 3I submit the following for the consideration of the Cabinet..       IAN MACPHERSON.       &apos; q10th June, 1921. IREDUCTION OP PUBLIC EXPENDITURE.^pnnrT Memorandum by the Minister of Pensions,)t\irhi ^- -&quot; &quot;--r-rI have had under consideration for some time the Question of the reduction of the expenditure of this Department, both immediately and prospectively for next yea.r!s estimates.   An elaborate and searching investigation into the expenditure of each Eranch of the Ministry is In progress, the results of which will in due course be reported to the Treasury,In the meantime, there are certain aspects of the&apos; problem of reduction of the cost of Pensions Administration to which I wish to call the immediate attention of the Cabinet,The Pensions Estimates for 1919-1920 were  123,000,000; for the present year they are  111,000,000, and in reply to a recent Treasury Inquiry my officers gave  105,000,000 as the probable estimate for 1922-1923, on the present administrative basis.   This progressive reduction Is due partly to the natural decline of pensionary charges owing to deaths, remarriages, etc., but partly also to the increasing efficiency of the financial and administrative control and of the curative services of the Ministry, a continuing.process, which will effect further and greater savings in the near future.In order to secure the rapid reduction required by the present emergency, it will be necessary to expedite this process. This could of course be done by curtailing pensions, or by adopting some other expedient of the same kind, such as the anticipation of the reduction of pensions under the sliding scale, but no such plan could be carried out without a violation of explicit undertakings by the Government, which would be very difficult to defend, and which indeed the Country would not tolerate.There is however one direction in which a considerable reduction of expenditure oould be at once effected in the pensionary charges without any breach of faith and that is by officially bringing the war to a termination at the earliest possible date.All the conditions of the War Warrants apply to disabilities attributable to or aggravated by service during the War,   Until, therefore, the date of the termination of the war Is determined, the benefits of the War Warrants are granted In all cases of disability now arising,   Active operations in the field may be said to have ceased shortly after the Armistice In November, 1918.   But for the fact that the war has not yet. officially terminated, many disability cases nov arising would be entitled only to the post-war rates.   Many of these cases are really peace disabilities.The official termination of the War would restrict future disablements to post-war rates, though it might be necessary to continue the Great War rights in certain areas, e.g., Mesopotamia or Ireland,   This could be effected by the exclusion
exclusion from the operation of the Order of such areas where the Service Departments, with the agreement of the Treasury, decide that &quot;active service&quot; operations still continue.   Prom an examination of a number of these cases now being dealt with under the Great War Warrants and Orders it would appear that the saving would be at least  300,000 a year,A further consequence would be that the liability in respect of pensions, gratuities, or treatment, in non-attributable cases would automatically cease 12 months after the date of termination.   The saving effected would be  280,000 a year, some of which would become immediately effective.This economy is both substantial and reasonable end I urge tnat immediate consideration may be given to It by the Cabinet * /      .        &apos; ,     - UM&apos;-I expect to secure considerably greater reductions of expenditure, commencing in the current financial year and largely influencing nextyearfs estimates, as the result of certain extensive administrative reforms which have now become possible and will be carried out without delay.  As some of them require statutory authority^ I propose to address a further memorandum to the Cabinet on the subject at an early date*Ministry of Pensions. 10th June, 1921*

</content>
</cab>
