<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/125/0 images: 345-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^This Document is tne Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the Cabinet,  June 1921.SECRET.CP. 3044.CABINET.SPECIAL WEEKLY REPORT ONUNEMPLOYMENT.No. 32.WEEK ENDED JUNE 10, 1921.T. J. MACNAMAKA,Ministry of Labour.
I. NOTE ON UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION IN UNITED KINGDOM on june 10, 1921.1. The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent. The average for the ten years prior to the war, according to Trade Union unem-ployment figures, was 4-7 per cent.  It was as high as 7-8 per cent, in 1908 and 7-7 per cent, in 1909.^ Throughout 1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent, in September and 3-2 per cent.in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.The figures for 1920 are :- rer cem&quot;To the end of- 2-9 January   ...        ...February ...        ... ...March     ...        ... &apos;&quot;               0,gApril      ...        ... ---        &quot;:&apos;                j.may        ............... v2June       ...        ..- ---        -                           j.4August    ...        ... -        -                2.9September           ... ---                           ^October    ...        ..- ---                           ^November            ... &quot;&apos; December ...        ...The figures for 1921 are :-To the end of  g.gJanuary   ...        ... ---                           g.gFebruary ...        ... -                                    1Q.0March     ...        ... -^.gApril2. Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges.1		1920.		1921.					Aug. 27.	Nov. 12.	Dec. 3.	Jan. 7.	Feb. 4.	Mar. 4.	April 1.	May 6.Men  Civilians Ex-service   . -Boys Women Girls	86476 142,600 17,608 58,982 17,480	134,868 239,816 21,872 97,964 22,237	137,222 263,553 21,379 119,886 23,663	250,365 312,147 35,704 215,869 41,441	357.701 362,866 48,507 286,821 55,419	450,651 379,184 51,571 319,394 53,877	625,663 377,250 62,655 382,573 57,939	880,687 437,021 79,230 461,395 68,729Totals  ..	818,096	516,757	565,703	855,526	1,111,314	1,254,677	1,506,080	1,927,062	1921.						May 13.	May 20.	May 27.	June 3.	June 10.f	Men-Civilians Ex-service  .. Boys Women Girls	922,619 444,145 81,486 471,790 69,078	986,728 454,267 84,725 481,735 70,267	1,010,702 461,310 85,383 497,845 71,538	11,493,158* 84,424 501,335 70,481	] ,523,098 84,266 506,153 72,201	Totals ..	1,989,118	2,077,722	2,126,778	2,149,398	2,185,718	* Separate figures not yet available. f Estimated.In addition to the above figures, which represent persons wholly unemployed, 1,069,187 adults are in receipt of unemployment benefit or out-of-work donation under systematic short-time schemes.
GENERAL.The industrial position is now further complicated by the dispute in the cotton industry. Unemployment is still increasing in the metal trades, but certain firms have been able to obtain small supplies of coal, and have re-engaged some of their workpeople. A number of engineering firms have adapted their plant to the use of oil fuel. No change is reported in the shipbuilding industry, and employment in the woollen factories is now seriously affected by the fuel shortage. Production in the hosiery trade remains fairly good, and it is anticipated that there will be a marked improvement when the coal dispute is settled. At Northampton, work in the boot and shoe factories has been somewhat dislocated owing to the restrictions in the supply of gas. The arrival of large cargoes of coal, timber, &amp;c, at various ports has slightly improved the prospects of employment among dock-workers.II. EMERGENCY WORK.As announced by the Prime Minister on the 19th October, certain schemes have been put in hand by the Local Authorities in conjunction with the Ministry of Transport and the Ministry of Health, and by the Local Authorities themselves, designed to secure work for unemployed men, preferentially ex-Service men. The following is the result at this date: (a.) New Arterial Roads.20,895 men employed up to date (in and around London, 2,937; Provinces, 17,958).i.(b.) Road Maintenance.It is estimated that employment has been provided for approximately 20,000 men over and above those ordinarily so employed.(c.) Housing (Acceleration of the Lay-Out of Roads and Sewers and Approved Housing Schemes).Men employed up to the 3rd June, 3,456 (in and around London, 353; Provinces, 3,103).(d.) Lord St. Davids&apos; Committee.Men employed on work other than the above up to the 3rd June, 34,220 (in and around London, 5,509; Provinces, 28,711).(e.) Alternative Work in Government Establishments.War Office establishments: men employed up to the 4th June, 2,718 (in and around London, 2,004; Provinces, 714).Alternative work provided in Admiralty establishments: men employed up to the 4th June, 6,468 (in and around London, nil; Provinces, 6,468).(f.) Short-time in Government Establishments.Number of men who have found employment up to date as a result of the intro-duction of short-time system. Men employed up to the 4th June: War Office estab-lishments, 2,024 (in and around London, 1,888; Provinces, 136) ; Admiralty estab-lishments, 3,432 (in and around London, 193; Provinces, 3,239)./g.) Emergency Work found by Local Authorities. -Total number of men employed up to the 3rd June, 12,739 (in and around London, 2,844; Provinces, 9,895).Total labour employed on above schemes = 105,952.:6429] &quot;
As reports for the week ended the 3rd June have been received from only 379 Local Authorities out of 409 who were asked to furnish information, it is probable that the Relief Schemes which have been inaugurated by the Government and Local Authorities are finding employment for a number of men in excess of the figures given.III. 50,000 EX-SERYICE MEN TO BE TRAINED IN THE BUILDINGINDUSTRY.The industrial stagnation caused by the coal stoppage, and the consequent uncertainty of the outlook, have seriously interfered with the progress of this scheme. * The employers, however, have set up District Committees in. many of the more . important industrial centres, and it is understood that they will shortly be posting notices on all jobs advising their workpeople that the job is only open to men willing to work with and assist in the training of ex-Service men taken on under the scheme. This action has already been taken in London by the Master Builders and also by the Office of Works.In addition steps are being taken to make it clear that contracts for building and constructional work in which the Government is financially interested will in general be confined to contractors who are employing men under the conditions of the scheme.In the meantime the total applications are 17,728. In the London and South-Eastern Division 7,601 men have applied, and the following are figures for other Divisions: South Midlands and Eastern Counties, 1,177: South-Western Counties, 1.522 : West Midlands. 1,809 :&apos;Yorkshire and East Midlands. 1,623: North-Western Counties, 2,309: Northern Division, 474; Scotland, 1,010: Wales, 203.IV.  PAYMENT OF UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT AND OUT-OF-WORKDONATION.1. The following statement represents the position as shown by the Exchangeregisters on the 3rd June: --	Men.	Women.	Total.Numbers wholly unemployed Numbers on short time*	1.493.158 567,779	501,335 501,408	1,994,493 1.069,187Total	2,060,937	1,002,743	3,063,6802. As a result of the operation of the Act of the 3rd March, 1921 (and of the grant of Out-of-Work Donation to ex-Service men and women), the following work-people are in receipt of Unemployment Benefit or Out-of-Work Donation: 	Men., i	Women.	Total.Wholly unemployed (estimated) On short time*	1,465.306 567,779&apos;	473,313 501,408	1,938,619 1,069.187Total.....	2,033,085	974,721	3,007,806* There is no record of the number of workpeople on short time, who are not eligible to receive Unemployment Insurance or Out-of-Work Donation, i.e., those who are employed in such a way that they are unable to comply witli the rules as to continuity of unemployment.

</content>
</cab>
