<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/125/0 images: 950-963</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.SECRET.CP. 3096.THE CABINET.ALTERATION OP THE TITLES OP THE TERRITORIAL FORCE AND SPECIAL RESERVE.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.I circulate a draft Bill which has been prepared in order to give effect to decisions of my predecessor that the titles of the Territorial Force and Special Reserve should he changed to &quot; Territorial Army &quot; and &quot; Militia &quot; respectively. Wide publicity has been given to these intended changes of title, which are believed to be generally popular and likely to further recruiting for th% forces in question.The revival of the name &quot; Militia&quot; in a new sense involves as a necessary consequence the repeal of Acts relating to the old Militia force, and the elimination of references to it in a large number of statutes. These Acts and references have long been obsolete, and the question of their repeal has previously been raised from time to time, but it has been decided on each occasion to let them remain on the Statute Book for the time being, in case it should ever become necessary to make use of the machinery of the Militia ballot. The experience of the war has, however, shown conclusively that for present-day purposes this machinery is of no value whatever, and there is, therefore no reason why the Acts should remain any longer on the Statute Book. The Yeomanry Acts, and references to the Yeomanry, which are similarly obsolete, are being repealed at the same time.No difficulty is anticipated in passing the present Bill, which is not likely to be controversial. The Bill has been drawn in such a way as to leave unaffected (i) the position of Deputy Lieutenants and Deputy Wardens of the Stannaries; (ii) the provision for the levying of a trophy tax in the City of London, authorized by the Militia Act of 1662, and the Militia (City of London) Act, 1820, and applied to Special Reserve and Territorial Force purposes in the City of London by Section 39 (.5) of the Territorial and Reserve Forces Act, 1907 ; and (iii) certain buildings, originally store-houses for the old Militia, which under various Acts have to be maintained by the Counties concerned until they are either purchased by the War Department or released to the County authorities. A number of the buildings are still maintained by the Counties, from whom the War Department ^olds them on lease, and in these circumstances the saving provision with regard to them is necessary.I ask for authority to introduce the Bill at an early date. It is necessary to pass it into law during the present session, as it has been decided to open recruiting for the new Militia in the autumn.The Wae Office, June, 1921.680
Territorial Army and Militia Bill.ARRANGEMENT OF CLAUSES.Clause.1.   New designation for the territorial force. 2.   New designation for the special reserve. 3.   Amendments of the Army Act. 4,   Abolition of existing militia and yeomanry. 5.   Short title and commencement. Schedules.87- 3A
DRAFTOF ABILL. toProvide for the application of new designations ajxhtci. to the territorial force and the special reserve, and to repeal enactments relating to the militia and yeomanry; and for purposes in connection therewith.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : 1. The territorial force which His Majesty is em- New designated-powered to raise and maintain under Part II. of the nation for Territorial and Reserve Forces Act, 1907, shall be called f1^6^&quot; the territorial army, and accordingly that Act and any 7E(iw7 c9 10 other enactment, Royal warrant, proclamation, order, regulation, or document applying to the Territorial Force shall have effect as though references therein to the territorial army were substituted for references to the territorial force.15       2. That portion of the army reserve which has New designated-hitherto been known as &quot; the special reserve&quot; shall nation f(?r be called &quot; the militia,&quot; and accordingly sections thirty the special to thirty-three of the Territorial and Reserve Forces ^ Edw&apos; Act, 1907, and any other enactment, Royal warrant,20 proclamation, order, regulation, or document applying to the special reserve shall have effect as though references therein to the militia were substituted for references therein to the special reserve, and as though references therein to a militiaman and to militiamen were substituted87-3 A 2
A.D. 1921. for references therein to a special reservist and to special reservists.Amendments        3. The sections of the Army Act specified in the Act?0 Amy   First Schedule to this Act shall be amended in the manner shown in the second column of that Schedule. 5Abolition of existing militia and yeomanry.Short title and com-mencement,4.-(1) The power to raise and maintain a militia force or a yeomanry force under the enactments set out in the Second Schedule to this Act shall cease, and those enactments shall he repealed to the extent specified in the third column of that Schedule: 10Provided that, notwithstanding anything in this sec-tion, any enactment repealed by this Act which relates to militia storehouses shall continue to apply in relation to militia storehouses provided before the commencement of this Act, as though this Act had not been passed.        15(2) In this section the expression &quot;militia store-houses&quot; means any buildings or premises provided for the purpose of keeping therein the arms, accoutrements, clothing, and other stores belonging to any regiment, battalion or corps of militia, when not embodied. 205. (1) This Act may be cited as the Territorial Army and Militia Act, 1921.(2) This Act shall come into operation on the day of nineteen hundred and twenty-one.
SCHEDULES.EIRST SCHEDULE.A.D. 1921.Amendments op the Army. Act.Section.How to be amended.5   13(1) (a)(ft)     -10   92 (3) -108a (1) -15 115 (7) and (8)175(3) -.    -(3a) -     -20       (5) -     -(6) -     -(10) -     .25 176 (5)(6) -(6a) -     -30     (7) -    -(8) -     .181 (4)3540For &quot; the militia or territorial force when embodied&quot; or the yeomanry when called out for actual&quot; military service &quot; there shall be substituted &quot; the&quot; territorial army when embodied.&quot; For &quot; the militia or territorial force &quot; there shall besubstituted &quot; the territorial army.&quot; For &quot; special reservist&quot; there shall be substituted&quot;militiaman.&quot; For &quot;territorial force&quot; there shall be substituted&quot; territorial army.&quot; The words &quot;or an order for the embodiment of themilitia &quot; shall be omitted from both subsections. The subsection shall be omitted. For   territorial force&quot; wherever those words occur,there shall be substituted &quot; territorial army &quot;. The words &quot; officers of the yeomanry and &quot; shall be omitted.The words &quot;yeomanry or &quot; shall be omitted. For &quot; special reserve &quot; there shall be substituted &quot;militia &quot;.The words *&apos; or the militia reserve force &quot; shall be omitted.The subsection shall be omitted.For &quot; territorial force&quot; there shall be substituted&quot; territorial army &quot;. The subsection shall be omitted.The words &quot; or with any portion of the militia when subject to military law &quot; shall be omitted.The following subsection shall be substituted for subsection (4) : &quot; (4) An order issued and signed as a route &quot; or an order signed by the officer commanding &quot; the unit of the territorial army, or the battalion &quot; or corps of volunteers, shall be substituted for &quot; a route &quot; (a) In the case of any man of the &quot; territorial army attending for his pre-&quot; liminary training ; and
a.D. 1921.Section.(6) -190(9) -02)-(13)-How to be amended.&quot; (b) In the case of any officer, non-&quot; commissioned officer, or man of the &quot; territorial army, assembled for training &quot; and exercise at the place in the United &quot; Kingdom appointed by His Majesty in &quot; that behalf ; and&quot; (c) In the case of any officer, non-&quot; commissioned officer, or man of the &quot; territorial army, embodied under an order &quot; of His Majesty, who has joined his corps &quot; at the place appointed for his assembling ; &quot; and&quot; (d) In the case of any officer, non-&quot; commissioned officer,  or  man  of  the &quot; volunteers  attending at  the  place  at V which his corps is required to assemble ; and an order to billet such officer, non-commis-sioned officer, or man purporting to be signed in manner required by this Act in the ease of a route, or by the officer commanding an unit of the territorial army, or a battalion or corps of&apos; volunteers, as the case may be, shall be evidence until the contrary is proved of the order being issued in accordance with this Act, and when delivered to an officer, non-commissioned officer, or man of the territorial army or volunteers shall be a sufficient authority to such officer, non-commissioned officer, or man to demand billets ; and when produced by an officer, non commis-sioned officer, or man to a constable shall be conclusive evidence to such constable of the authority of the officer, non-commissioned officer, or man producing the same to demand billets in-accordance with the order.&quot; &quot; territorial force&quot; there shall be substituted &quot; territorial army &quot;. For &quot;and the militia reserve force&quot; there shall besubstituted &quot;including the militia&quot;. For &quot; territorial force &quot; there shall &quot;territorial army&quot;, and the words the yeomanry &quot; shall be omitted. The subsection shall be omitted.Forbe substituted &quot;the militia,10152025303540
SECOND SCHEDULE.a.D. 1921.Enactments Repealed.Reign and Chapter.Title.Extent of Repeal.5 14   Car.  2.,   c. 3.1015   Car.   2. c. 4.19 Geo. 3. 15    c. 44.37 Geo. 3. 20    c-25-42  Geo. 3. c. 68.42 Geo.  3. c. 72.25 42  Geo. 3. c. 90.3042   Geo. 3. c. 91.3543  Geo. 3. c. 10.The Militia Act, 1662The Militia Act, 1663The Nonconformist Relief Act, 1779.The Militia (Tower Hamlets) Act, 1796.The Teomanry (Ireland) Act, 1802.The Militia   (Cornwall and Devon Miners) Act, 1802.The Militia Act (England), 1802.The Militia (Scotland) Act, 1802.The Militia (Exemption from Ballot) Act, 1802.The whole Act, except so much of section twenty-six as pro-vides for the imposition-tion and levying of a rate in the City of London.The whole Act.In section one the words &quot; from serving in the &quot; Militia of this &quot; Kingdom, and shall &quot; also be exempted.&quot;The whole Act.Tho whole Act.The whole Act.The whole Act except so much of section eighteen as prescribes the appointment of clerks to general meetings.The whole Act except so much of section thirteen as prescribes the appointment of clerks to general meetings.The whole Act.
A.D. 1921.Reign and Chapter.Title.Extent of Repeal.43  Geo. 3. c. 50.43   Geo. 3. c. 89.43  Geo. 3. c. 100.44 Geo.  3. c. 54.44 Geo.  3. c. 94.49   Geo. 3. c. 120.152  Geo. 3. c. 38.52 Geo. 3. c. 68.52 Geo. 3. c. 105. -52   Geo.  3 c. 116.52 Geo.  3. c. 155.53   Geo.  3 c. 28.53   Geo.  3 c. 29.53   Geo. 3. c. 48.55 Geo. 3. c. 65.56 Geo.  3. c. 39.The Militia Act, 1803The Militia (Scotland) Ballot Act,. 1803.The Militia (Scotland, No. 2) Act, 1803.The Yeomanry Act, 1804The Yeomanry (Amendment) Act, 1804.The Militia (Ireland) Act, 1809The Local Militia (England) Act, 1812.The Local Militia (Scotland) Act, 1812.The Militia (Returns) Act, 1812.The Local Militia (England) (Amendment) Act, 1812.The Places of Religious Wor-ship Act, 1812.The Local Militia (England) (Amendment) Act, 1813.The Local Militia (Scotland) (Amendment) Act, 1813.The Militia (Ireland) Act, 1813The Militia (Medical Examina-tion) Act, 1815.The Yeomanry Muster or Exer-cise Act, 1816.The whole Act.Section twenty-one.      5The whole Act. The whole Act. The whole Act.10The whole Act except so much of section seventy-four as pre- 15 scribes the appoint-ment of clerks to general meetings.The whole Act. The whole Act. The whole Act. The whole Act. Section nine. The whole Act. The whole Act. Section two. Section eight. The whole Act.i&apos;   &apos;20253035
Reign and Chapter.57&apos; Geo.  3. c. 44.5 1   Geo.   4. c. 100.7 Geo. 4. 10    c. 58.2 &amp; 3 Viet, c. 93.3 &amp; 4 Viet, c. 84.15 5 &amp; 6 Viet.7 &amp; 8 Viet, c. 85.Title.Extent of Repeal.A.D. 1921.2015 &amp; 16 Viet, c. 50.16 &amp; 17 Viet, c. 73.2517 &amp; 18 Viet, c. 105.17 &amp; 18 Viet, c. 106.QQ 17 &amp; 18 Viet, c. 107.18 &amp; 19 Viet, c. 57.20 &amp;,21 Viet.35   c. li.21 &amp; 22 Viet, c. 90.87The Yeomanry Act, 1817The Militia (City of London) Act, 1820.The Yeomanry Act, 1826The County Police Act, 1839The Police Courts (Metropolis) Act, 1840.The Regulation of Railways Act, 1842.The Railway Regulation Act, 1844.The Militia Act, 1852The Naval Volunteer Act, . 1853.The Militia Law Amendment Act, 1854.The Militia (Scotland) Act, 1854.The   Militia   (Ireland) Act, 1854.The Militia Act, 1855  -The   Militia  (Ireland) Act, 1857.The Medical Practitioners Act, 1858.BThe whole Act.The whole Act except sections thirty-four to forty, and section forty five.The whole Act.In section ten, the words &quot; or in the militia &quot;.Section ten.In section twenty, the word &quot;militia.&quot;In section twelve, the . words &quot; militia or &quot; iu both places where those words occur.The whole Act.In section eight, the words &quot; from service in the militia and &quot;The whole Act. The whole Act. The whole Act. The whole Act. The whole Act.In section thirty-five, the words &quot; and from &quot; serving in the &quot; militia &quot;.
A.D.1921.      Refgaancl -&apos; Chapter.Title.Extent of Repeal.22 &amp; 23 Viet, c. 40.23 &amp; 24 Viet, c. 94.23&amp;24 Viet, c. 120.25 &amp; 26 Viet, c. 4.26 &amp; 27 Viet, c. 65.The   Royal   Naval Reserve j In section seven, the(Volunteer) Act, 1859.words &quot;from service in the militia and &quot;.    528 &amp; 29Vict. c. 46.32 &amp; 33 Viet, c. 80.33 &amp; 34 Viet, c. 67.33 &amp; 34 Viet, c. 77.33 &amp; 34 Viet, c. 96.The Militia (Storehouses) Act, j The whole Act. 1860.The Militia Ballot Act, 1860 -The Officers Commissions Act, 1862.The Volunteer Act, 1863The Militia (Ballots suspension-sion) Act, 1865.The   Militia   (Ireland) Act, 1869.The Army Enlistment Act, 1870.The Juries Act, 1870   -The Appropriation Act, 1870 -The whole Act.in   section   one,   the 10 words &quot; Militia and &quot;.In section five, the words &quot;and Militia&quot; and &quot; and shall rank &quot; with officers of the [rt &quot; Yeomanry Force &quot; according to the &quot; rank and date of &quot; their respective &quot; commissions in the &quot; respective forces &quot; ; in section eight, the words &quot; enrols him-&quot; self as a volunteer &quot; or substitute in 25 &quot; the Militia, or is &quot; attested to serve &quot; on the permanent &quot; staff thereof or &quot; ; section forty-one ; 30 and part (iv) of the Schedule.The whole Act.20The whole Act.Section twenty.35In the Schedule, the words &quot; militia and 40 yeomanry.&quot;In section six, the words &quot; militia, yeomanry.&quot;
Reign and Chapter.Title.Extent of Repeal.A.D. 1921.34 &amp; 35 Viet, c. 86.1015 38 &amp; 39 Viet, c. 25.The Regulation of the Forces Act, 1871.The public c Stores Act, 187520 39 &amp; 40 Viet. I The  Customs   Consolidation c. 36.41 &amp; 42 Viet, c. 33.2545 &amp; 46 Viet, c. 48.30354045 &amp; 46 Viet. 45    c 49.50Act, 1876. The Dentists Act, 1878The Reserve Forces! Act, 1882The Militia Act, 1882  -In section six, the words &quot; militia, yeomanry, and &quot; wherever those words occur, and the words &quot; militia, yeo-manry, or&quot;; in section nineteen, the words &quot; the Constable of the Tower,&quot; and the words &quot;in re-lation to the General or Local Militia &quot;.In section eight, the words &quot; militia or &quot;, and in section thirteen, the word &quot;militiaman.&quot;In section nine, the words &quot;in the militia or&quot;.In section thirty, the words &quot; and from serving in the militia,&quot; and &quot; in the militia or &quot;.Sections eight to ten ;: sections eleven to twenty, twenty-three, twenty-four, twenty-seven, and twenty-nine so far as they relate to the militia reserve; in section eighteen, the * words &quot; or by a militia officer &quot; ; and iu sec-tion twenty-eight, the words &quot; and militia reserve force,&quot; &quot; re-respecively,&quot; and &quot;and militia reserve&quot;.Sections three to twenty-eight; thirty-seven to forty-seven ; subsections (1) to (4) of section forty-nine ; so much of subsec-tion (5) of section forty-nine as relates to the raising of a corps of miners ; section fifty-one, and the Third Schedule,87c
a.D.1921.Eeign and Chapter.		Title.	Extent of Repeal.47 &amp; 48 Viet, c. 55.		The Pensions and Yeomanry Pay Act, 1884.	The whole Act, so far as it applies to the yeomanry.               551 &amp; 52 Viet, e. 31.		The National Defence Act, 1888.	Section two.51&amp;52 Viet, c. 41. 53 &amp; 54 Viet, c. 21. 59 &amp; 60 Viet, c. 25.		The Local Government Act, 1888. The Inland Reyenue Act, 1890 The Friendly Societies Act, 1896.	Section fifty-nine so far as it relates to the militia.                   10 In  section  eight the words &quot; or   in   the militia &quot;. Section forty-three so far as it relates to the 15 militia or yeomanry.61 &amp; 62 Viet, c. 9.		The Reserve Forces and Militia Act, 1898.	Section two.1   Edw. c. 14. 2  Edw. c. 39.	7. 7.	The Militia and Yeomanry Act, 1901. The Militia and Yeomanry Act, 1902.	The whole Act. 20 The whole Act.7  Edw. c. 9.	7.	The Territorial and Reserve Forces Act, 1907.	Section thirty-four.8  Edw. c. 48.	7.	The Post Office Act, 1908    -	In section forty-three 25 the words &quot; or in the militia &quot;.

Territorial Army and Militia.DRAFTOP   AB   I   L   LiTo provide for the application of new designations to the territorial force and the special reserve, and to repeal enactments relating to the militia and yeomanry; and for pur-poses in connection therewith.LXX.  (3.)27th June 192187-3

</content>
</cab>
