<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/44B/0 images: 90-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MOTES of a CONVERSATION held atthe Hotel Britunnique, Spa, onWednesday, July 14th 1920.? r e s e n t.The Right Hon. D. LloydGeorge, 0.^.,:.. PrimeMinister.Dr. von Simons,German Seoretary forForeign Affairs.Mr. Philip Kerr, Secretary.THE PRIME MINI ST :K said that he was very sorry for thesituation which had arisen.      He did not want the war to&quot;be renewed and greatly regretted the breakdown of the Spanegotiations.     He had proposed the Spa Conference because he was.-.anxious to improve the relations between Germanyand the Allies.      There was no doubt that after a certainpreliminary stiffness the atmosphere had begun to improve.The intervention of Herr Stinnes, however, had made a greatimpression.     -ue had been appalled at the introduction ofthis spirit into the negotiations and the Allies could not help feeling that it was Herr Stinnes,   and those whom herepresented, who were really putting the veto on the GermanGovernment agreeing to the Allied proposals.     He feltthat it was right that he should inform Dr. von Simons atonce that the Allies intended to occupy the Ruhr if theGerman Government did not accept their proposals.      Theyhad already sent for Marshal Poch and Field Marshal Wilsonto concert the details.      He himself had done his best to prevent the occupation of the Ruhr,     He had always beenagainst it as he had been against the advance into Frankfurt,but he had, however, been reluctantly driven to the oonclu-
sion that there was no other course open to the allies in view of the situation   by which they were confronted.DR. VON SIMONS said that he also greatly regretted the breakdown, though he had realised that it was likely inview of $he reply which the German Government had given.He said that the Conference had not had a very good start.It had really assembled too soon before the new Governmentwas in the saddle, and had asserted its authority.     As to herr Stinnes&apos; intervention he had no idea that Herr Stinneswas going to take the line he had.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Allies had beenexpecting the new German Government to propose the postponement of the Spa Conference, but they had not done so,   doubtlessbecause they came into office too late.     He said that hethought Herr Stinnes was thinking too exclusively of theGerman coal situation and especially of his own interests.Great Britain was short of coal as compared with her pre-war position.     Prance was very short of coal.      Italy&apos;s interests *were almost closed down for want of coal.     The needs ofall the Allies were,  therefore,  extremely aoute.      It wasno use for the German industrial magnates to consider onlytheir own position.DR. VON SIMONS said that as for Herr Stinnes i*t wasnecessary ttwwork through him.THE PRIME MINISTER said that in that event, within a fortnight there would either be fighting in the Ruhr distriotor the Ruhr would be isolated from Germany.     What gainwould there be to Germany from this result?     The allies would occupy the Ruhs- with the sole object of obtainingtheir due rights in the delivery of ooal.     What would Germanygain by forcing them to occupy the Ruhr to get the coal?DR. VON SIMONS said that he did not think the occupation..... would
would be of much advantage to France either.     She would not get the coal for the miners would strike also.     The Ruhrpopulation was not like the Saar Valley population.     Itwas an obstinatepopulation;    the same kind of. people as were referred to by     la.*-Mr**-**    and Caesar.     Besides theoccupation of the Ruhr would mean that while France mightbe able to get some coal it would get nothing for reparation.He thought that if an expert commission were sent to sit in Essen itself it might be possible to induce the workmento produce enough coal.     The principal difficulty did not come so much from Herr Stinnes and his friends as from theminers.      Stinnes,  for instance, was able to make a profiton the export coal.     The mining population, on the otherhand, were concerned by the fact that a reduction of thecoal available for German consumption meant unemploymentfor their brethren in other industries.     All the workers&apos;unions were united in resisting tne Allied demands.DR. VON&quot; SIMONS then described a great union of proprietors-tors and workers with an equal number of representatives from each which had been formed during 1918 for. producingbetter relations throughtout German industry.     Me hadbeen a representative of the employers in this body and yet he enjoyed in a peculiar degree the confidence of theworkers,  especially, Ebert, Haase, and Dittmann.      In facthe ha d only taken office ax Foreign Secretary at Eberfsspecial request and with the right to resign as soon as Ebertreleased him.     Inasmuch, therefore, as he possessed theconfidents of both employers and employed he could speak with some authority.     Me was absolutely certain that both employers and employed would resist any efforts on the partof the Gotsarrnment to make them work under conditions of...... which
whioh they themselves did not approve.     It was for thisreason that he proposed the meeting of a special JointCommission in Essen.     He believed that by this means itmight be possible to get the Trade Unions to agree to thisproposal, and if they agreed Herr Stinnes could not stopJthe arrangements.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he understood the difii-culties of the German Government.     Just as other Governments,the German Government was doubtless being aocused of givingway.     He thought,  therefore,  that the position of theGerman Government in securing jihe execution of the Treatymight really be easier after the Allies had occupied thePuhr Valley.DR. VON SIMONS said that he was afraid that theoccupation would cause too much havoc and that the mineswould be destroyed,THE PRIME MINISTER replied that the destruction of the mines would mean the destruction of Germany.     As theexperience of Prance had shown it would take ten years to restore the mines to working conditions.     ...DR. VON SIMONS said that this would be a very bad revengefor the destruction of the French mines.     He himself hadbeen against the signature of the Treaty, andi at that time he hsL thought out the consequences of a refusal to sign to theend.     He had faoed those consequences and yet he had beenagainst signature.     He could not now give undertakings tothe Allies contrary to the resolutions of the miners and employers.      It was better that the German Government shouldbe coerced by revolution or invasion than that they shouldmake promises which they could not fulfil anddefault month by month.      hat would&apos;be the worst result of all because it..... would
would destroy the reputation and credit of germany the PRIME MINISTER said that he could see that perhaps the &quot;best solution was the coercion of Germany.     rorhr.pswhen Stinnes and others saw that the occupation of the Ruhrentailed they would see the necessity for executing their obligations under the Treaty.     He wished to say that he himself had always been against any proposal involving theadestruction of Germany, for he believed than/prosperousGermany was essential to Europe.      There was a military party, however, in France and some extreme newspapersin England which did believe in tfawjGerman military menaceand thought that the best course was to destroy Germany&apos;schance of recovery.     M.Clemenceau had never held thisview,  still less did M. Millerand who was a iaoderate man,and there was no -British statesman who did not wish to seeGerman prosperity restored.     But it -.?a3 impossible for him to go back to Parliament having accepted Dr. von Simmonsoffer of yesterday.     It was even less possible for M.iiillerand to return to Prance.      If he did so he would fall at once, and yet M. Millerand was both a reasonablestrongand a xkrxxxicfc man, xxax who in the past had takendecisions violently opposed by public opinion and was prepared to face any opposition for what he thought right.It had been an act of great courage on his part to agreeto the Spa Conference.     Even the British Government whichwas in a far stronger parliamentary position would meet with grave difficulties.     He had,  therefore,  felt boundto agree to the occupation of the Ruhr Valley in the lightof Dr. von Simons&apos; reply of yesterday, because the allies had felt that the German Government was not in a positionto overcome the internal resistance to the Treaty,  and that.. c... they
they must take their own 3tapa to overcome it.     He greatlyregretted the decision.      It was thorouhgly &quot;bad foreverybody.     -&quot;ut he had come to the conclusion that it wasinevita- le because apparently no German Government under existing circumstances could undertake to make any arrangement which the Allies could accept.DR. vOJN 3IM0MS repeated that Spahad come too early,hie believed it was possible to make a good Government inGermany at the present time - a Government which would beable to take the Treaty of Peace as the basis of Germanyfsexternal relationa.     But the present Government was notstrong enough to overcome internal difficulties unless theAllies would make one more offer to bring over the miners.THE PRIME iilNJST^ said that he thought that it was too late to adopt this course.     As he had already explained,M. Millerand would fall if he went back to Prance havingaccepted any dilatory arrangement of this kind.     He wouldhave thought that from the point of view of Germany,  thewise course would have been to have taken risks and to have undertaken to deliver the 2,000,000 tons of coil per month,provided they got credits for the purpose of food for themineru abroad.     Por instance,  suppoaing the differencebetween the internal German price for coal and the exportprice was utilised for thia purpose.      They might alaoask for as3i8tance in the matter of loana and fertilisers.Could not the Geraian Government make some proposal of thiskind?DR. VON SIMONS said that Germany wanted the coalitself in order to stop 8tarvation in Germany.The prime Minister said that foreign credits wouldenable Germany to get food, but that the addition of aa..... further
a/further liability for an increased army of occupation wouldnot posaibily help Germany.     The miners might refuse to workhut they could not refuse for long.      Germany&apos;s output was something like 9,000,000 tons per month, and under tk*?arrangement proposed 7,000,000  xuLd go to Germany.      Itwas impossible for a strike to continue long on the basis that while it might prevent the Allies getting 2,000,000tons per month,  it prevented Germany getting 7,000,000 tons per ..,months.     They would certainly not continue,  if as theAllies extended,  they would assure Gemian workmen food in*return for work.      If the mifl*s were destroyed throughfighting the position of German^ would be even worse.      Itwas surely better for Germany; to take the risk of undertaking the delivery of the coal.      Dr. von Simons had displayedgreat skill in his conduct of the negotiations and hadmastered the facts w&amp;th which he had to deal with wonderfulrapidity considering thesaort time he had been in office.He did not wish him, however,  to be under, any illusions andhe urged him to attempt no kind of bluff.      The Allies hadalready taken the decision to occupy the Ruhr with a largeinter-allied force,  and they were meeting at six that day to consider the declaration they were going to make toGermant in this sense on the following day,     Unless Germanyconsented in the meanwhile.      The occupation, however, wouldnot be made with blaok troops.     He had made that a conditionof Britain&apos;s consent.      It was not that he wished to castany reflections on France^ blaok troops, but he knew the prejudice the use of blaok troops always created among a white population.     Unless,  therefore,  the German Governmentgave its consent the whole Ruhr Basin would be occupiedwithin a few days.     He greatly regretted the decision andhad long resisted i t, but he felt that the Gorman Government......had
$ IVhad &quot;been overriden by Stinnea and the temper he represented.D3. VON SIMONS aaid that he knew Stinnea very well,and that the German Government had not been overriden byhim.     He would, however, give careful conaideration, withhis colleagues, to the suggestions which had emerged inregard to the aupply of food, and would communicate a clear answer in the courae of the afternoon.     He was greatlydistreased at the present po8ition.      The Government,  of whichhe was a member, had not had time to con80lidate ita position.outMoat of hia colleaguea were men with^/experience,  and who didnot de3ire to lead a political life and were not well qualified to deal with the present aituation.      They had,  further,  todeal with public opinion which would neither fight nor work.

</content>
</cab>
