<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/44B/0 images: 147-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETARY&apos; &apos;i NOTES of a Cabinet Committee Meetingheld in the Secretary of State&apos;a Room., ForeignOffice, on MONDAY, 22nd SEPTEMBER 1919 at 11.3C a,m.appointed to consider the question of the temporary and provisional lino in Palostino and Mosopetomiabehind whioh tho Bi-itish Troops arc to ho withdrawn.PFF3ENT:Lord Curzon (in tho Ghuir).Lord -Minor. Mr.       0. Garbott,Indi : Office.Field-Marshal Lord Ailenby.Coi. K. Cornwallid,Lt.-General Sir H.V,Cox. Egyptian D.t;.oditionaryForco.Lt.-Ool. *7.H. Gribbon,&apos;:.&apos;er Office.Major E.I7, Young,Foreign Office.Lt.-Col. L. Stcrr, Secretary.me Ch irmon aaid that the terms of reference to the Committeewere contained in the following decision o; the War Cabinet st aMeeting hold at 10 Downing, otreet, on the 1-th September 1919at 4 p.n.  (W,C, 6*s2, Minute 3.)The &quot;Tar Cabinet clocidod:-(a) Befoie the doapatoh of the Draft telu^ram to E^ypt,a Cabinet Committee composed as follows:The Secretary of State for ..orei0n   -fairs.The Secretary of 3t-..te for tna Colonies. iel&amp;-Marshal Lord alien by, with colonel Gribbon . no. other exports ss necessary,should consider tho question o if the temporary yndprovisional line in Palestine .nd Mesopotamia b:hindv.&apos;hioh the British Troops   rj to bo withdrawn(b) The tale&amp;r mi jhould not be uj.. vtched until v-fterthe   &quot;orthcomlng no^oti- tions v*ith the Emir Faisal.S B 0 R B T.4&quot; WAR     C A B I 1! E T.
Colonel Gribbon said that at a Conference held early in the month at Deauville, which had been attended by Lord Allenby and himself, the Prime Minister had provisionally approved a line behind which our troops should withdraw, which was described in Paragraph 5 of the draft telegram (G.T.8176)(Appendix A) referred to in the decision road out by the Chairman. He reminded the Committee that subject to such arrangements as might be eventually approved by the League of Nations, the Arabs were to be allowed possession of Damascus, Home, Hamah, and Aleppo. He also invited the attention of the Committee to paragraph 10 of an Aide-Memoire dated Paris, 13th September, 1919, in regard to the occupation of Syria, Palestine and Mesopotamia pending the decision in respect to mandates, which was handed the same day by the Prime Minister to M. Clemenceau, (18/Q/252 Appendix 3) which was worded as follows:-

"Until the boundaries of Palestine and Mesopotamia are determined, the British Commander-in-Chief shall have the right to occupy outposts in accordance with the boundary claimed by the British Government."

In reply to a question, Colonel Gribbon said that the French had complete liberty of action in the blue area shown on the map illustrating the Sykes-Picot agreement of 1916, but not in area "A".

Lord Milner pointed out that as our troops were in possession of the field, we were masters of the situation, and consequently able to decide how far we should retire. If the French objected to our decision, we could refer them to President Wilson and to the League of Nations.
Lord Allenby agreed, and said that he thought M. Clemenceau fully understood the situation. Lord Allenby then explained, and described with the aid of a map, the line which had been provisionally drawn by the Prime Minister in France. He said that he attached importance to the line including the river Litani and Benias as well as the mountains of Galileo and Bosra. He did not think it necessary to include the whole of the Druz mountains, but the line should give to the British, control of the water supply obtained from the various streams in the hills.

Colonel Gribbon said than the possession of Bosra was necessary for the purposes of the railway to be constructed, and the reasons for our requiring it should be made clear to the French.

Colonel Cornwallis said that he thought the Emir Feisal should have no objection to our having a post at Bosra  when the proposal arrangement had become an actual fact since he had already had considerable trouble with the natives in that district. Lord Allenby said in reply to a question that military headquarters would be established at Dera Kunetra and Safed.

Lord Milner thought it would be better if the line ran South of the Druz range.

The Chairman pointed out that it was desirable that we should possess Wadi-ol-Araji and not relinquish it to the French. In his opinion our best policy would be to be quite frank with the French and say that our line must swing North at this point, as the possession of this area was vital to the railway we proposed to construct. It was important that we should now put in a claim for it, to be adjusted in the future when the time came for a permanent settlement. The line therefore might run South of Druz, round Wadi-ol-Araji, thence to Deir-er-Zor, (roughly the old Sykes-Picot line) where we had a/
Political Officer.

Colonel Cornwallis said that the boundary of the district of Deir-er-Zor ran some miles north of the town of that name and suggested that the Mesopotamian authorities should be consulted before it was decided to draw the line through the town itself.

Lord Milner thought it was desirable, in order to obviate any unnecessary friction with the French, to keep our boundary as far back as was consistent with the maintenance of our position and our interests.

General Cox, in reply to a question by the Chairman, said that the interests of India were affected directly the line passed East of Palestine. He asked for time to consider the question before giving any definite opinion on the proposals before the Committee.

The Chairman said that he understood that the Committee were in favour of accepting the line provisionally approved by the Prime Minister, from Euphrates Eastwards, subject to such modifications as the India Office might suggest to the Committee for their approval.

(This was agreed by the Committee.)

Colonel  Cornwallis, reverting to the Western portion of the line, informed the Committee that El-Bukka was a most fertile area and stated that Emir Feisal would certainly fight if this were taken from the Arabs to whom it had been granted by
SECRETARY1 S ROTES of a Cabinet Meetingheld in the Secretary of State*s Room,foreign OfficOj on Hondo7, J?Wnd Seotemb1919, at 11*30* a.m.. appointed to con-aider the oueation of the temporary and provisional line in.Palestine andrtesopotonin behind which the Pritichtroops are to be withdrawn..PAGE 4.      last lino.Please insert &quot;provisionally&quot; after the word&quot;granted&quot;.CORRIGENDUM,(Sl/med)L* STORE n2, Whitehall Gardens, Sf&quot;*13th October, 1919.Assistant Secretary3Var Cabinet,
Lord ftlionhy.   He further thought it desirable thatthe line should include Hasbnia and riasboya, and otherplace.&apos;:, no--; administered by the Arabs.Lord . ilnfsr thought that any arrangementsnhich had been made by Lord Alionby, and had beenfound to work satisfacvorily, should be preserved.He the:: quoted paragraph 4 of the &quot;.ide-Menoire&quot;In pursuance of this policy, the garrisons in syria &quot;.est of the Sykos-PIcot lino and the garrisons in Cilicia will be replaced by a French force, andthe garrisons at Damascus, Horns, Hamah and Alssppowill be replaced by an Arab force&quot;.     He feared that this night crer-te an awkward situation.    Inhis view, the Arabs mi;ht be left where they were,but no new territory should be handed over to them.Fie wondered whether It would be worth while, In any communication we might make to the French, to avoidintroducing any reference to the so-called Sykes-Ficot line.     he further thought it  vas unfortunate that the contemplated arrangement involved the railwaypassing partly through French and partly through;-rab spheres.The Chairman, in regard tc the point raisedby Lord Milner, explained that the 11 garrisons&quot; referredto by him must surely mean British garrisons and notArab.    In respect of the western portion of the pro-visional boundary of Area A to be fixed, ho suggested thatthe Committee should recommend that the existing lineof the Occupied Enemy Territory Administration from Baniasnorthwards should be followed, and that in the amendeddraft telegram no reference should be made to eitherbank of the river Litani.     It *ras for the/
-Committee to see that our agreement with theFrench as set forth in the Aide-Memo iro was carriedout.    If the French chos&apos;.   to cone to blows withthe Arabs wc could not prevent then.   He doubted whether we could fix a provisional line without consulting the French Government.Colonel Gribbon thought that paragraph 16 ofthe Aide-Memo ire rendered this unnecessary.The Chairman read out the following extractfrom a Eote by the Secretary to the War CabinetGlS/Q/252)- (1) &quot;ii. Clemcnceav. on behalf of theFrench Government accepted Mr, Lloyc. Georgefs pro-posal for the evacuation by the Eritish Array of Syria and Cilicia and their replacement by Frenchtrcops in Cilicia and Syria west of the SykesrPicotline, on the distinct understanding that, in accept-ing this proposal the French Government was not com-mitted to acceptance of any other part of thearrangements proposed in Mr. Lloyd George1 s Aide-Memoir dated September 15th, 1919 &apos; in regard-to theoccupation of Syria, Palestine and Mesopotamiapending the decision in regard to mandates&apos;, (2) TheConference took note of tho above agreement as a purely temporary provisional arrangement for military occupation without prejudice to the final settlementof mandates or boundaries, which v/ould have to beconsidered as part of the general question of Peacewith Turkey&quot;. All the Committee could do v;as to draft an amended telegram, embodying the result oftheir deliberations that morning, which, should not however be despatched until tho 7.rar Cabinet had againseen Emir Feioal,   Ho further thought it was important that a line should be fixed between the French and
General Milne*s sphere in the north; this., however,was not included in the Committee&apos;s terms of reference,Lord i.lIonby referred to paragraph 7 of the&quot;draft telegram &quot;with reforcr.ee to telegram IP.81147dated 12th September,, regarding exchange of Turkishfor British rifles for Feisal&apos;s troops, it is intendedto consult the French Government, with a view toproceeding with the exchange as promised, and by whichcontrol of Faisal1e ammunition supplies will beestablished.       Further instructions   will follow in dueco\u?se on this r-oirit.&quot;     Lord Allcnby said that he hadpermitted Feisal to raise a brigade of 6,000 Arabs andhe made an agreement with him about their equipment to theeffect that no were to supply them with British rifles. in exchange for the good Turkish rifles.     He had,however, delayed carrying out this   agreement for fear that the French might thin!: that we wore providing theArabs with rifles to be used against them.Colonel Gribbon referred to paragraph 2 of thedraft telegram &quot;steps will be ta&quot;.:c5n immediately to prepare for the evacuation by the   ritish Army of Syria andCillcia including the Taurus Tunnel.&quot;     He said that theV/ar Office were anxious that early notice might be givento the British Headquarters in Palestine of the impendingevacuation and hoped that, pending the Government1sapproval of the draft telegram, a brief premonitorytelegram in thin sense might be sent.The Committee reached the following conelvisions :-(la)     They recommended tho &quot;war Cabinet that theprovisional and temporary.line* inPalestine and Mesopotamia behind which theBritish troops are to be withdrawn should run as follows:-x this lino has since been approved by the India Office.
kNahr Kasimiya,  (Litani river),Bania3 inclu-oive, Wadi-Mughani, Western and Southernbordr ox&quot; 1-ejja, Western foothills of JebelDruze,exclusive, so as to include as far aspracticable Upper waters of Wadis flowinginto Yermuk, and 3osra, thence Salkhad, Araan,Ghadi-ez-Zarura,21-C-harz,Kalat-el-3eida,El-3resiya,pt.615 Tel-Ghurab, thence Sykes-Picot line from longitude 38 to jtmction withroute marked Mu3il 1908, thence North to Tell-Zubar inclusivo, thence right bank of Khaburand ?/adi-er-Rudd to bend of Tigris East ofHidiat, thence by right banlc of Tigris to Til.All places named inclusive except Jebel DruzeandThat in para., 2 Sub-Para. A. after tho words&quot;purposes of relief&quot; the following words shouldbe Inserted &quot;but the French Government will be advised by H.II. Government to adhore to presentadministrative boxindary of 0.E.TYA. ,i&apos;est.(lb)        They approved the despatch of the draft telegram,as amended (Appendix B) subject to the approvalof the War Cabinet; the telegram not to be sentuntil the Cabinet had seen Emir Feisal again.(2) As regards the question of exchanging Britishrifles for Turkish with the Arabs, the V,c.r office should oreoare a case and submit it to the ForeignOffice.&quot;(3) That the War Office should be authorised to sendat once to the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-&apos;.1&apos; LEgypt, a telegram warning him that steps would betaken immediately to prepare for the evacuation by the British Army of Syria and Cilicia, includingthe Taurus Tunnel.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,22nd September, 1919.-S-
AFP ill! PI X A.3ECKLT. tfAfi     CABINET.O.T.  8176.p.iii:aky cccu-^tioi: op syria ..;id cilicia.Draft Telegram from War Office to Field MarshalCommander-in-chief, Egypt. September 1919.1. As a result of last week1s negotiations with the Frenchregarding the Egyptian situation k the following agreement hasbeen come to :-2.       Steps will be taken immediately to prepare for the evacuation by the British Army of Syria and Cillcia, including the TaurusTunnel.     The British garrisons will be relieved as follows :-(a) in Cilicia and in Syria west of the Sykes-Picot line,by a French force.     The expression &quot;west of theSykes-Eieot line&quot; is taken to mean the Blue Area forthe purposes of relief,(b) The garrisons at Damascus, Horns, Hama and Aleppo wil]be replaced by an Arab force,3. The relief will commence on November 1st., 1919, under theorders of Field-Marshal Lord Allenby, who will retain command ofthe v.&apos;hole area until the relief is completed.     After the Britishbeentroops have, withdrawn rnd the relief completed, neither theBritish Cov.rnment nor the British Commsnder-ln-Chief shall have any responsibility within the zones fxom which the Army has retired
4. Subsequent to the above relief, the territory occupied by British troops will be Palestine (provisionally defined in accordance with its ancient boundaries of Dan to Beersheba), and Mesopotamia, including Mosul. This arrangement will be purely temporal and provisional without prejudice to the final settlement of mandates or boundaries, which will be considered as part of the general question of peace with Turkey.

5. Pending the delimitation of the boundaries of Palestine and Mesopotamia, the British Commander-in-Chief shall have the right to occupy outposts as may be necessitated by the military situation. The following approximate line should be occupied accordingly - Ref. 1/1,000,000 :

Litani river (right bank). Banias, Wadi-Mughani, Western and Southern border of Lejja, Western foothills of Jebel Druze, so as to include Upper waters of Wadis flowing into Yermuk, and Bosra, thence Deir-ez-Zor (exclusive of Tadmur), right bank of khabur and Wadi-er-Rudd to bend of Tigris East of Midiat, thence by right bank of Tigris to Til. All places named (other than Tadmur) inclusive.

6. The French are very desirous that their detachments should be allowed to remain in Al?ppo and Damascus, but this can only be done with consent of Feisul with whom question will be raised after arrival in London where he is due 18th September.

7. With reference to telegram No. 81147 dated l2th September, regarding exchange of Turkish for British rifles for Feisul&apos;s troops it is intended to consult the French Government with a view to proceeding with the exchange as promised and by which control of Feisul&apos;s ammunition supply will be established. Further instructions will follow in due course on this point.
SECRET.

G.T. 8176.

APPENDIX B.

WAR CABINET.

MILITARY OCCUPATION OR OF SYRIA AND CILICIA.

Draft Telegram from War Office to Field Marshal Commander-in-Chief, Egypt. September 1919.

1. As a result of last week&apos;s negotiations with the French regarding the Egyptian situation, the following agreement has been come to..:-

2. Steps will be taken immediately to prepare for the evacuation by the British Army of Syria and Cilicia, including the Tunnel. The British garrisons will be relieved as follows :-

(a) In Cilicia and in Syria west of the Sykes-Picot Line, by a French force. The expression "west of the Sykes Picot Line" is taken to mean the Blue Area for the purposes of relief; but the French Government will be advised by His Majesty&apos;s Government to ? to present administrative boundary of O.E.T.A. West.

The garrisons at Damascus, Homs, Hama and Aleppo will be replaced by an Arab force.

3. The relief will commence on November 1st, 1919, under the orders of Field-Marshal Lord Allenby, who will retain command of the whole area until the relief is completed. After the British troops have been withdrawn and the relief completed, neither the British Government nor the British Commander-in-Chief shall have any responsibility within the zones from which the Army has retired.

4. Subsequent to the above relief, the territory occupied by British troops will be Palestine (provisionally defined in accordance with it ancient boundaries of Dan to Beersheba).

? As amended by the War Cabinet Committee (W.C. 622 Minute 3) held at the Foreign Office on Monday 22nd September 1919 at 11.30 a.m.
and Mesopotamia, including Mosul. This arrangement will be purely temporary and provisional without prejudice to the final settlement of mandates or boundaries, which will be considered as part of the general question of peace with Turkey.

5. Pending the delimitation of the boundaries of Palestine and Mesopotamia, the British Commander-in-Chief shall have the right to occupy outposts as may be necessitated by the military situation. The following approximate line should be occupied accordingly - Ref. 1/1,000,000 :- Nahr Kasimiya (Litani) river, Banias, inclusive, Wadi-Mugheni, Western and Southern border of Lejja, Western foothills of Jebel Druse exclusive, so as to include as far as practicable Upper waters of Wadis flowing into Yermuk, and Bosra, thence Salkhad, Arman, Ghadi-ez-Zarura, El-Gharz, Kalat-el-Beida, El-Bresiya, pt. 6l5 Tel-Ghurab, thence Sykes-Picot line from longitude 38 to junction with route marked Musil 1908, thence North of Tell-Zubar inclusive, thence right bank of Khabur and Wadi-er-Rudd to bend of Tigris East of Midiat, thence by right bank of Tigris  to Til. All places named inclusive except Jebel Druze.

6. The French are very desirous that their detachments should be allowed to remain in Aleppo and Damascus, but this can only be done with consent of Fiesal with whom question will be raised after arrival in London where he is due 18th September.

7. With reference to telegram  No. 81147 dated l2th September, regarding Exchange of Turkish for British rifles for Feisal&apos;s troops it is intended to consult the French Government with a view to proceeding with the exchange as promised and by which control of Feisal&apos;s ammuntion supply will be established.

Further instructions will follow in due course on this point.

</content>
</cab>
