<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/44B/0 images: 204-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>

Per3 onalOth February, 1923Pear lord Ctamfordham,Many thanks for yours of the Oth February.Tho Conclusions of Cabinet 16 of March 6th, 1922giving instructions to the Secretary to continue to send a complete copy of Cabinet Conclusions to His majesty the Ming have boon complied with without any exceptionwhatsoever.     Pis Majesty has always received a copyat the earliest possible moment.As regard the instructions you quote of the 1stNovember, 1922, I v/ould point out that you have onlyquoted them partially.      i have acted on paragraphs 2and 3, which are as follows :-&quot;2.     The Secretary will attend meetings of theCabinet, unless instructed to the contrary, forthe purpose of recording the conclusions.3*     In the absence of instructions to thecontrary the record is to be as short as possible and, apart from the oonclusi on &quot;itself, should normally be limited to such exp la nation as is indispensable to render the conclusion itself the St.lion.lord Stamfordhara, C.C.B., G.C.I.E.,&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;o.
intelligible.     As a general rule It should suffice to refer to any documents circulatedto the Cabinet before the meeting, and to anysupplementary data produced at the meeting.In particular ca3es a statoment by n Minister may,by decision of the Cabinet, be reproducod andannexed to the Minutes after approval by thePrime Minister and correction by the minister concerned.&quot;I believe I have acted in the strictest conformitywith these instructions on every occasion.     Up to thepresent time, however, there has only been one Instancewhere the statement of a Minister has been reproduced andannexed to the Minutes.     As a matter of fact, tho question was discussed the other day as to whether I should repro-duce and attach a copy of lord Cursors statement on his return from Lausanne.     As, however. Lord Curzon hadalready prepared a draft of his statement for circulation to the Cabinet in the form of a telegram, it was decidedthat this would suffice without annexing anything to theMinutes.The Proceedings of the Cabinet have been a gooddeal shorter since this Government came into office.This is partly due to the fact that a very large numberprevi ouslyof the subjects have/been fully examined by cabinet committees whose Reports had already been circulated.The Ming receives copies of all documents circulated from
this office and referred to in the Minutes.The Prime Minister tells me, however, that he has undertaken to supplement when necessary, the Conclusionsof the Cabinet and I shall of course do my utmost toassist the i-rime Minister in this matter and am glad you have mentioned tho ratter to me privately.Yours sincerely,(Signed) M.P.A.Hankey
1BUCKINGHAM  PALACE3th. February, 1923.Dear Hankey,I find on reference to the Conclusionsof Cabinet 16, 8th. March, 1922, when new instructions were given as to the distribution of documents fromthe Cabinet Office, a note was made that: -&quot;The Prime Minister has given verbalinstructions to the Secretary to continueto send a complete copy of the cabinet conclusions to H.M. the King&quot;.Again, instructions to the Secretary of theCabinet, given on the 1st. November, 1922, lay down:-&quot;One copy of the draft Minutes will besent to the King as heretofore ?with HumbleDuty&apos; from the Prime Minister&quot;.There is no doubt that, up to the resignation of Mr. Lloyd George, the records of the
Cabinet v/ere more copious than those subsequently-sent to His Majesty.Yours very truly,Lieutenant-colonel sir M.P.A. Hankey, C.C.B.,Secretary to the Cabinet,2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1

</content>
</cab>
