<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/44B/0 images: 260-260</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
M in continuation of War Cabinet 40C, Llinuto 2, the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs read tc the Cabinet a telegram reooivedfrom Sir H. Rumbold, i!o, 1745(e) datod October lot 1910, indicating-thr probability of early ovcrturo3 for Peace from Turkey.Tho TJar Onbinot had some disc-JSoicn in regard to the plaoo whichwould be most suitable, in the -vent of an offer being made, forsuch negctiationc, mhether in Switzerland, or Smyicna or PalestineTho majority of opinion appeared to bo in favour of Palestine, inas nuoh as it mac considered dosirablo to follow the proocdent ofthe Bulgarian Armotioe and to exclude all political questions. Ifthe negotiations took place iu Paloctino they would be conductedby the Brr&apos;.tr.ah General, and would merely be ooncernod v/ith theUaval and Military situation in Turkoy v/ithcut any roferenoo topolitical natters, ouch as the Armenian question,,    The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that ho wouldlike time to think tho matter over, but for the moment he gatheredthat the Cabinet wcro of opinion that, in the &quot;eventuality oonton-plabod, we should make a truce, in tho sonso of suspension of hos-tllicies, but not a treaty, v/ith Turkey as soon as possible; thatour General in Syria should carry nut the negotiations whioh. shoulddeal rath the control of the Kaval and Military situation in Turkey.The Chancellor of the Exchoquor then reported the views of\tho PrimemMinlstor in regard to holding a Supremo War Oounoil asproposed in War Cabinet 400, Minute  .The Prime Minister was of opinion that a War Oounoil was tooctmbrous for dealing v/ith tho present situation.As the result ofhis intorriov/ v/ith tho Prime minister on the provione evening, &apos;theChief of the Imperial General Staff had alroady loft for Paris tooonfesr with li, Olemonocau, and tho Prime Minister was himself readyto leave for Paris, at an early dato.    Whothor the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs should accompany tho Prime Minister to Pariswould dopond upon the rostil&quot;5 ox tho preliminary; conversations botwecithe Chief of tho Xmporial General Staff and M, Olomonooau, whiohwould show whether diplomatic as woIIIas ndlitary^opnsidoratlonswere inwolvod.

</content>
</cab>
