<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/193/3 images: 20-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS government cp(76) 113 COPY NO    g J26 November 1976CABINETEXPORT CREDIT policy note by the Secretary of the CabinetI attach a joint memorandum by the Secretary of State for Trade and theSecretary of State for Industry.    This has not been considered by the ministerial Committee on Economic Strategy and is now for discussion at cabinet.Signed   JOHN hunt cabinet Office26 November 1976
confidential this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER BRITANIC MAJESTY&apos;SGOVERNMENTEY(76)6315 November 1976CABINETMINISTERIAL COMMITTEE ON ECONOMIC STRATEGYEXPORT CREDIT POLICYJoint Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Trade andthe Secretary of State for IndustryINTRODUCTION1 The Chancellor of the Exchequer is rightly concerned about the financial and economic burden arising from thepresent arrangements for subsidising and financing medium and long term export credit.   Whilst sharing his anxietieshowever, we have serious misgivings about the nature and timing of the proposed remedy of   raising   the   fixedinterest rate for sterling credit by 2 percentage points.These misgivings focus primarily on the total incompatibilityof such a step with the main thrust of the Governmentspublicly stated economic and industrial policies.   linked with these doubts are the uncertainties surrounding the viability of the cheaper interest rate option for businesstransacted and financed in hard currencies.   Some of ourmisgivings are referred to in the Chancellor^ paper, butthey are sufficiently important to justify further elaborationECONOMIC AND INDUSTRIAL STRATEGY2 Apart from the control of inflation, the oft-repeatedobjectives of current Government strategy are to securestable export-led growth, through a switch of resources intoexports and investment.    Closely associated with this is theindustrial strategy, designed to raise industrial efficiency and competitive power, with   priority being given to there-generation of manufacturing industry.confidential.
3 It has long been established UK policy to give ourexporters broadly similar export   credit facilities to thoseenjoyed by their major competitors.   Although, overall, the fixed rate export finance scheme covers only about Bfo of exports, the amount is high in absolute terms (up to  2,000mthis year) and it is particularly important to the heavierend of inftuatry and to a number of key industries which areheavily dependent on overseas orders to maintain output andemployment - shipbuilding, process plant, electricity generating machinery, and aerospace.These industries face depressed demand at home, surplusworld capacity and fierce competition for overseas sales -some of it from countries who also have weak domesticcurrencies and yet who still offer internationally competitivefixed export rates of interest (eg Prance and Italy).TIMING4 Against this background, a sharp and unilateralincrease in UK interest rates for sterling export credit must inevitably damage the export prospects of those industriesdirectly affected.    It will also be interpreted more widelyas a further blow to manufacturing industry at a time whenconfidence in the Governments industrial strategy hasalready been shaken, notably by the National InsuranceSurcharge and the increase in Minimum Lending Hate.    In this context a recurring theme in the Sectoral Studies in thefirst phase of the industrial strategy work was a plea for various improvements in aid   to exports, and one of the mostimportant themes in the last NEDC meeting was the need for a positive manifestation of the Government&apos;s declared intention
CONFIDENTIALto give priority to manufacturing industry.   Thus, unilateraltightening of UK export credit terms would, to say theleast, appear inconsistent with our economic and industrialstrategy, especially at a time when we are experiencing apause in the growth of exports and the prospects are uncer-tain.PUBLIC SECTOR BORROWING REQUIREMENTS5       We accept that present arrangements for the provisionof finance for sterling export credits of two years ormore do involve, via ECGD&apos;s refinancing arrangements with the Clearing Banks, a substantial burden on PSBR.But the Chancellor has recently secured the banks1 agree-ment to carrying themselves approximately an extra  200mof this burden in 1977/78.   This will provide a once forall, though substantial and valuable, reduction inthe PSBR; moreover the refinancing arrangements come upfor fundamental review prior to next October, and thereis no reason why the Government should not take that oppor-tunity to press the banks to hear from 1978/9 onwards an even larger share of the burden of financing export credits,at least for medium-term maturities.FOREIGN CURRENCY OPTION6      Against this background we accept that a switch tocontracting and financing of exports in foreign currencieswould be a desirable step, but the prospects of achievingsuch an early switch on any substantial scale should not be exaggerated.    It is estimated that about 20$ of UK exports are at present invoiced in currencies other than sterling but
7 Thus, an immediate 2% differential between sterling and foreign currency interest rates could be excessivelydamaging for our most vulnerable industries.   On balance,therefore, we should recommend a trial period during whichsterling interest rates should be left unchanged, but more would be done to assist and stimulate exporters to move intodollar or deutschmark financing.   Action on this frontis already   in hand in that a special unit is being set up inECGD to act as a &quot;marriage bureau&quot; between exporters who maybe interested in exploring such possibilities, and thosebanks who are interested in promoting such business.   Inthis connection, some of the UK subsidiaries of foreign,(particularly American banks), have shown interest inmobilising external finance for UK exports under the ECGD*piarantee and interest support mechanism.    This potentialencroachment by the foreign banks into a profitable and4.confidential this practice is almost entirely confined to short termbusiness.    In the fixed rate finance field (ie credit of2 years or more), which is the field affected by theChancellor^ proposals, contracting and financing in foreign currency represents a step into the unknown.   Therewill inevitably be resistance amongst overseas buyers mostof whom will &quot;prefer to incur long term liabilities in sterling.    The extent of the resistance cannot be assessedat this stage.   Time will be needed for our exporters andfinancial institutions to cope with the new and sometimesdifficult techniques which are involved,
risk free area of business hitherto dominated by the UKbanking system could in itself act as a stimulus to our ownclearing banks to take a more active role in organisingforeign currency financing.    It would therefore be a mistake to run the danger of an increase in the sterling ratecertainly before seeing what the effect of pressures on the banks could achieve in the next 6-12 months.    In addition,ECGD could avoid levying an extra premium specifically uponexporters in foreign currency (to pay for the extra cover now given against exchange fluctuations) by spreading this cost over all exporters in the same general classes of business.Again, in respect of all markets where prudential limitshave to be set to the total amount of medium and long termexport credit which we can extend (some 60 or so countriesat present), it would be possible to announce a policy,which would convey a very clear message to many classes ofexporters, of setting lower limits for sterling businessthan for exports in foreign currency.8 It it were thought that even further stimulus were needed, the future of the cost escalation insurance schemefor export contracts of  2m and more, (fchich runs until next?%rch in its present form and can only be extended thereafterby Affirmative Resolution), could be reviewed in the presentcontext.   We would be agreeable to the case being urgentlystudied without commitment for its extension to be on thebasis of significantly less favourable terms for sterlingexports than for foreign currency exports.   Against presentfears in industry of a resurgency of cost inflation, such achange,whilst undoubtedly provoking an outcry from those whowould not believe thej^^ouldL^ind^j^^&quot;tlieir overseas customers
CONFIDENTIALto accept invoicing in foreign currency, should be * powerfulinducement to swtich to foreign currency exporting whereverthis seemed feasible.conclusions  To sum up, we consider that the Chancellorsproposal is ill-timed against the background of the present-pause in expert growth, while confidence on &quot;both sides of industryis in a very delicate state, and when doubts are being express-ed about the Government *s real commitment to the IndustrialStrategy.   Recent Government measures - especially theNational Insurance Surcharge and the MLR increase - haveadded to these doubts.   A tightening of export credit facilities would be difficult   to justify, and the rationaleof the move would be incomprehensible to many, both at homeand abroad.    Even if the underlying motive were appreciated,there is a danger that cuts in this of all areas would be interpreted as a measure of desperation.10 In addition, any adverse effect on externalconfidence would be added to an appreciation thatlherewould be new and additional public expenditure costs arisingfrom the unemployment which an increase in the sterlingexport ratfi would create through loss of orders.    Thisfollows from the inescapable logic that a rise in interest rates would lead to a loss of exports by firms who are notfaced with long order books   and whose resources simplycannot be switched easily or quickly to other uses.11 We therefore see very substantial objections to anincrease of 2?S in the sterling interest rate at the presenttime.   These would extend from serious damage in basic industries, many in areas of high unemployment, toCONFIDENTIAL
wider damage to confidence at home and abroad.That is why we favour continued urgent concentration on assisting and encouraging exporters to contract inforeign currency linked with the stimulation of competition between financing institutions to mobiliseforeign currency financing,without making the immediate leapin the dark which an increase in the sterling interest rate would represent.Department of Trade E.D.Department of Industry E.G.V.15 November. 19767

</content>
</cab>
