<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/19/0 images: 98-108</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1951SECRET Copy No.      4 fCM. (51)12th conclusions cabinet 12 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 8th February, 1951, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. T. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State  for the  home department.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister  of Labour and  NationalService.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Hall, FirstLord of the Admiralty (Item 3).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 6).The Right Hon. Ness Edwards, M.P.,Postmaster-General (Item 7).The Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,K.C., M.P., Solicitor-General (Item 3).The Right Hon. Lord Henderson,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (Items 4-5).Sir William Strang,(Items 4-5).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Item 3).The Right Hon. Maurice Webb, M.P.,Minister of Food (Items 1-2).The  Hon.  K.  G.   Younger,   M.P.,Minister of State.The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-2).Mr. A. M. Crawley, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State forAir (Item 3).Foreign OfficeSecretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.Mr. O. C. Morland.THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE   PROPERTY   OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENT
CABINET 12 (51)contents minute no. subject     Parliament        ..............Business in the House of Commons.2     Food..................Meat Supplies.3     Defence   .................Call-up of Reservists.4     Germany ...      ..............Rearmament.5     War Crimes      ..............6     Sulphur   .................7     Recognition of Staff Associations in Post Office
Parliament.Business in theHouse ofCommons.1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.They agreed that in the Defence debate on 14th and 15th february the Government spokesmen should be, in order of speaking, theMinister of Defence, the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Ministerof Labour. They further agreed that the annual Statement on defence should not be presented in advance of this debate; and they invited the Minister of Defence to consider, after the debate, whether a white paper was required on this occasion and, if so, what form it shouldtake.2. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in pursuance ofthe Cabinefs decision of 23rd January, he had considered, with theMinister of Food and the Minister of State, how negotiations could best be reopened with the Argentine Government for a long-term meatagreement, and he had also discussed the problem with Sir JohnBalfour. His colleagues and he had agreed that we should be readyto pay a price of  120 a ton, if satisfactory arrangements could bemade about the terms of the agreement and the proportion of chilledmeat to be bought under it. Before the discussions had been broken off, we had suggested an agreement ending in June 1952, and a pro-portion of 50 per cent, of chilled meat, and it was proposed that weshould continue to negotiate on that basis. It was difficult to indicate to the Argentine Government our willingness to resume the negotia-tions without giving them reason to think that they could successfullyraise their terms, but it had been decided that the best course was tosend a short note saying in general terms that we were prepared toconsider an agreement to terminate in June 1952, and to resume the expert discussions on chilled meat. A note to this effect had been handed to the Argentine Charge d&apos;Affaires in London on the previous day. The Minister of Food would mention this in the debate that day in the House of Commons, but nothing should then be said whichwould appear to commit the Government to reaching an agreementwith the Argentine.The Minister of Food gave the Cabinet a general outline of the speech which he was proposing to make in the debate. If an early agreement was reached with the Argentine and shipments began atonce, the meat ration could be increased without delay by drawingon the remaining reserves of canned corned meat; but it would clearlyprejudice the success of the negotiations to mention this possibility inthe debate, or to refer in any other way to a prospective increase inthe ration.In discussion several Ministers referred to the public discontentwith the high prices of fish and rabbits, and it was suggested that some reference should be made in the debate to the possible reimpositionof price control for these foods. The Cabinet were informed that theProduction Committee had recently agreed that a decision on thisquestion should be deferred for a few weeks, since increased catchesmight lead to a reduction in fish prices; and it was agreed that in the debate the Minister of Food should go no further than to say that theGovernment would not hesitate to reimpose control when they thoughtthat the public interest required it.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of the further approach which had been made tothe Argentine Government.(2) Invited the Minister of Food to speak in the debate that day in the House of Commons on the lines approved in their discussion.Food.Meat Supplies.(previous reference:CM. (51) 6thConclusions,Minute 1.)
Defence. 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofCall-up of       Defence (CP. (51) 42) on the form of the legislation required to giveReservists.       effect to the call-up of reservists which had been outlined in the Primeprevious        Ministers statement on 29th January (Cmd. 8146).Reference:CM. (5.1) 8th The Minister of Defence said that the main point for cabinet conclusions, decision was whether, as he and the Service Ministers desired, powerMinute 2.) &apos; should be taken to call up Class Z and Class G reservists for fifteendays&apos; training in 1952, 1953 and 1954, as well as 1951. There was noquestion of a second period of service by the reservists who were tobe called up for longer periods. The men called up for fifteen days&apos;training in 1951 would provide the necessary man-power to completefour Territorial Divisions, but in later years it would be necessaryto complete further Divisions. Moreover, the Class Z reservists called up for A.A. Command in 1951 would go only a small way to complete the twelve A.A. Divisions that were contemplated, and men would therefore have to be called up for A.A. Command in the three subse-quent years. Wastage among the men called up in 1951 would also have to be made good. For the most part different men would be selected for call-up in subsequent years; but some of the men called upin 1951 should have refresher courses in the later years and somehighly experienced men might have to be called upon again in later years because they alone could carry out certain skilled tasks. It was difficult at this stage to be specific about the exact requirements ofthe Services in future years, and he therefore proposed that all thenecessary powers should be taken in the Bill, subject to annual affirmations-tive resolution in both Houses.The Parliamentary Vnder-Secretary of State for Air said that itwould have to be made clear, not necessarily in the Bill but in a state-ment made when the Bill was debated, that men who in futurevolunteered for the Royal Auxiliary Air Force would not be liableto be called up for the three months&apos; training. Unless this assurance was given, recruitment for the Royal Auxiliary Air Force would be gravely prejudiced.In discussion, the general view of the Cabinet was that the Class Zand Class G reservists who were being called up for fifteen days&apos;training in 1951 should not be called up for similar periods of trainingin later years. The suggestion that all these men would be liable for training in subsequent years would cause resentment out of all proportion to the value to the Services of the relatively small numberof them who would in fact be called back for training. The services should endeavour to rely on volunteers for any men, trained in 1951,who were required to come back in a later year. While the powers in the Bill might be expressed in general terms, the government spokesmen should indicate specifically and in detail how the powers were to be exercised.On the other questions raised in CP. (51) 42, the following points were made:  (a) Although it was a heavy burden on their resources, theMinistry of Labour would arrange for the reservists to be medically examined before they joined their units.(b) Doubt was expressed whether one month&apos;s imprisonment wasa sufficient penalty for disregarding a training notice. This question should be considered by the Legislation Committee.(c) The Legislation Committee should also scrutinise the proposedprovisions penalising incitement to disobey training notices. It was doubtful, for example, whether incitement against voluntary enrol-ment in the Armed Forces should be treated, in time of peace, asa criminal offence. If a right of search for literature inciting to dis-obedience was granted, the Law Officers were anxious that theprovision of the Incitement to Disaffection Act, 1934, should bereproduced, under which a search warrant could be issued only bya High Court judge.
Germany. 4.   In their discussion on 1st February of the Soviet proposalRearmament,    for a meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers, the Cabinet had(Previous        agreed that, while they were committed to the principle of a GermanReferences:     contribution to the defence of Western Europe, they would need toCM. (50) 86th   give very careful consideration to all the issues involved beforeConclusions,     reaching a final decision on the manner and timing of Germany&apos;sMinute 4 and    rearmament. The Cabinet now had before them a memorandum byCM. (51) 11th   the Minister of State (CP. (51) 43), to which was annexed a statementConclusions,     summarising the successive steps leading up to the current discussionsMinute 6.)       with the German Federal Government.   This showed that each ofthese steps had been fully endorsed by the Cabinet; that the timing of further moves towards the rearmament of Germany could still be regulated at the will of the North Atlantic Treaty Powers; that theneed for caution in the timing of these further moves had been recognised by those Powers and by General Eisenhower; and thatthe discussions now proceeding in Bonn could not result in any newcommitment by the United Kingdom Government or in any final decisions.The Minister of State said that the discussions with the german federal Government fell under two heads-first, the details of themilitary contribution which Germany might make; and, secondly, thepolitical conditions on which the Germans might be prepared to make that military contribution. There was no likelihood that the dis-cussions would reach an early conclusion; for the Americans were now relaxing some of their earlier pressure for speed in the militarytalks, and the Germans had made it clear that they would insist ona satisfactory political settlement as a condition precedent to theconclusion of any military agreement. General Eisenhower, in his public reports in Washington on his recent visit to Europe, had giventhe impression that he was not in favour of pressing forward toorapidly with German rearmament until the North Atlantic Powers had(d) The Minister of Labour was doubtful whether statutoryprotection against loss of employment or holidays should be extendedto volunteer members of the Auxiliary Forces. Employers had beenhelpful in giving facilities to employees belonging to the TerritorialArmy; and it might do more harm than good to place them under a statutory obligation of this kind. The Secretary of State for Warsaid that his Territorial Army advisers were of this opinion. It was,however, agreed that there might be need to give reinstatement rights to officers from the Emergency List of the Royal Navy who volun-teered for eighteen months&apos; service.The Lord President said that he was anxious that the Bills should,if possible, come before the Legislation Committee on Tuesday,13th February, with a view to its introduction in the course of theDefence debate or shortly afterwards.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that definite assurances should be given in parliament that no Class Z or Class G reservist called up for fifteendays&apos; training in 1951 would be called up for similartraining in a subsequent year; and that men who volun-teered in future for the Royal Auxiliary Air Force wouldnot be liable to be called up for the three months&apos; training.(2) Invited the Minister of Labour and the Minister of defence to give further consideration to the proposal that statutoryprotection should be given to members of the auxiliary forces in respect of their annual period in camp and, ifnecessary, to consult informally with the two sides ofindustry on this proposal.(3) Invited the Legislation Committee to consider the remainingquestions raised in CP. (51) 42.
themselves built up more substantial forces in Europe. The UnitedKingdom High Commissioner in Germany had reported that this hadbeen eagerly welcomed by Germans of many different shades ofpolitical opinion, and that in Germany the sense of urgency aboutthe problem of German rearmament had largely disappeared. three separate sets of discussions would have to be completed before theNorth Atlantic Treaty Powers were confronted with the need to takefinal decisions (i) the discussions on the scale and method by whicha German military contribution might be made; (ii) the discussions regarding the replacement of the Occupation Statute by contractual obligations; and (in) the forthcoming conference in Paris to discussthe French plan for a European army. The High Commissioners hadbeen instructed to proceed urgently with the first group of discussions;but the second and third were bound, by their nature, to be prolonged.And there were two further factors which would make for delay.First, the impression created by General Eisenhower&apos;s reports, towhich he had already referred. Secondly, the attitude of the german federal Government, who were claiming that, before any scheme ofrearmament could proceed, it would be necessary, not only to secure a political settlement which would give the German forces genuineequality of status with other national contingents, but also to convince the German people that the Allied forces in Germany had been substantially strengthened. Thus, there was no practical prospect thatthe North Atlantic Treaty Powers would be invited to approve, atany early date, proposals for implementing their decision of principle in favour of Germany&apos;s rearmament. But, if the Cabinet were notcontent to rely on the delays which seemed bound to arise from thevery nature of the current discussions with the Germans, they might consider, in consultation with the United States Government and thereafter the French Government, whether any positive steps shouldbe taken to slow down the course of those discussions.The Minister said that another risk might arise if there were a breakdown in the negotiations for a meeting of the Council of foreign ministers or if such a meeting were held and proved inconclusive.The Soviet Government had already described as &quot; intolerable &quot; thepreliminary steps which the North Atlantic Treaty Powers were takingtowards the rearmament of Western Germany; and they might regardsuch a breakdown as a decisive moment.The Prime Minister said that it had always been his view that theAllied forces in Europe should be substantially strengthened before any German units were added to them; and that on this account thenegotiations with the German Federal Government about a german contribution towards the defence of Western Europe should be spunout. There was now an additional reason for delay, since we were anxious to use German rearmament as a bargaining counter in thediscussions at the proposed meeting of the Council of foreign ministers. If it were true that the Soviet Government were genuinelyapprehensive about the rearmament of Western Germany, we might now be in a position to extract some real concession from them. Hewas, therefore, in favour of consulting with the United States Govern-ment on the basis suggested in paragraph 9 of CP. (51) 43.In discussion there was general agreement with the view expressedby the Prime Minister. The following particular points were made:  (a) The Minister of Defence recalled the circumstances in whichthe North Atlantic Council had been asked to accept the principle of aGerman military contribution towards the defence of Western Europe.The original strategic plan had been to defend the line of the Rhine;but it had become clear that it would be difficult to secure theco-operation of the Dutch and the Danes on that basis. A newconcept had then been formulated for the defence of a line furthereast, in Germany. rAs soon as it was contemplated that the battlewould be fought on German soil, it became evident that the Gerrnansmust take some part in it; and it followed that, in principle, Western
Germany should make some military contribution towards the defenceof Europe. Provided, however, that this decision of principle was maintained, there was at the moment obvious political advantage indelaying its practical application.(b) There was widespread anxiety among Government supporters^about the risk of proceeding at this stage to put into practice a plan for the rearming of Western Germany. General eisenhower&apos;s report was therefore to be welcomed. Public anxiety would be allayed by theknowledge that he saw no early prospect of absorbing German unitsinto an integrated Atlantic force in Europe. In these circumstances it was clearly reasonable to prolong the current conversations withthe German Federal Government.(c) The Cabinet were reminded that there were large sections of responsible public opinion in this country which had never favoured the rearmament of Germany. The view was therefore expressed that,although the Government had accepted the principle of rearmingWestern Germany, in the face of very strong pressure from the UnitedStates Government, there would be great political advantage indelaying the application of this principle for as long as possible. any military forces raised in Western Germany were bound to includemany former Nazis and other dangerous elements; and, once theGermans were allowed to raise any military forces, it would be difficultto prevent the recreation of a German General Staff. It would alsobe a mistake at this stage to provide military equipment for Germanunits: such equipment as was available should be reserved for theforces of the Atlantic Treaty Powers. Grave risks would be involvedin proceeding now with the rearmament of Western Germany, in face of the declaration of the Soviet Government. It was illogical to saythat a German contribution was essential to the defence of western europe, and at the same time to pursue a policy which might provokean attack on Western Europe long before any German military unitscould be raised.(d) As against this, attention was drawn to the action already taken by the Soviet Government in raising and equipping a para-military force in Eastern Germany. Was nothing to be done in western Germany to counter-balance this? If Western germany were left wholly unarmed, would the Atlantic Powers be prepared tooffer armed resistance to any attack by the Bereitschaften?Moreover, were the Atlantic Powers to leave unnoticed theimpudence of the Communist claim that the peace of the world wasthreatened by the rearmament of Western Germany, while the SovietGovernment proceeded steadily with their rearmament of eastern germany? The anxieties which Government supporters felt aboutGerman rearmament would certainly be fostered assiduously byCommunists in this country, and Ministers should not hesitate to expose this manoeuvre.(e) The view was expressed that the eventual rearmament ofGermany was inevitable. Ministers should not hesitate to support inprinciple the rearmament of Western Germany as a contribution towards the defence of Europe. That need not mean that hasty orprecipitate action should be taken to put that principle into operation at the wrong moment. There was bound in any event to be a consider-able delay before a practical start could be made with the raising of military units in Western Germany.(/) The point was made that, while there would be obvious advan-tages in reaching some general settlement which would relieve thepresent state of international tension, there was as yet no evidencethat the Soviet Government had any sincere desire to reach such asettlement. Moreover, while we might be prepared to use german rearmament as a bargaining counter in negotiations with them, wehad no very clear idea about the specific concessions which they mightbe asked to make in return. Nor could we be sure that the UnitedStates Government would agree that any Soviet concession would justify the abandonment of German rearmament unless it weresufficient to warrant the abandonment of the whole scheme for
building up the defensive strength of the West under the north atlantic Treaty.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of State to arrange for His Majesty&apos;sAnibasador in Washington to make known to the UnitedStates Government their anxiety regarding the timing ofthe next positive move towards the rearmament of western germany, as proposed in paragraph 9 of CP. (51) 43.(2) Invited the Minister of State to inform the United kingdom high Commissioner in Germany that he should now seek to prolong the current discussions with the german federal Government.War Crimes. 5.   In the course of the discussion recorded in the preceding(Previous        Minute it was pointed out that the current anxiety among government reference:      supporters about German rearmament had been enhanced by the cm. (51)11th   recent announcements regarding the exercise of clemency towardsConclusions,     Germans convicted of war crimes. The suggestion that military unitsMinute 5.)       were to be raised in Western Germany was being connected in people&apos;sminds with the release of German generals and other former Nazis;and as a result the impression was growing that the Western powers were ready to acquiesce in a resurgence of German militarism. Therewas special misgiving about the action of the United States HighCommissioner in Germany in releasing Alfried Krupp von Bohlenund Halbach and in cancelling the order for the confiscation of his property.   It would be useful if the Prime Minister could make areassuring statement on this point in the course of the debate onforeign affairs in the House of Commons on 12th February.The Cabinet-(1) Took note that they would have before them at their meetingon 12th February memoranda (CP. (51) 38 and 45) on theexercise of clemency towards Germans convicted of war crimes.(2) Invited the Minister of State to provide the Prime minister with material for a statement to be made on this subject in the foreign affairs debate in the House of Commons on12th February.Sulphur. 6.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Presidentof the Board of Trade (CP. (5.1) 39) drawing attention to the graveshortage in this country of supplies of sulphur and sulphuric acid.The President of the Board of Trade said that the annex to his paper explained the causes and the extent of the shortage, and in thepaper he had outlined some of the effects which it would have on our economy. This was the most serious of the threats to our productionin 1951 which had so far arisen from shortages of raw materials;and in this case, unlike some others, our deficiency could easily bemet if the United States Government took appropriate action. Therewere large stocks of sulphur, amounting to 2-8 million tons, lyingidle in the United States, and it seemed clear that their export wasbeing prevented by the United States Government, probably onaccount of their stockpiling programme. Our additional need in 1951was for not more than 135,000 tons, and he recommended that theUnited States Government should be strongly pressed to meet it.Lord Knollys, our representative on the Raw Materials Group Or-ganisation, had recently arrived in Washington and had already hadpreliminary discussions with United States officials, but responsibilitywithin the United States administration seemed to be divided and he
felt that the gravity of the situation demanded an approach on a higher level. A communication by the Prime Minister to President Trumanmight be desirable, but he felt that this should be held in reserve until we had received the advice of His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washing-ton, and possibly until he had himself visited Washington.The Prime Minister said that it was clear that urgent action mustbe taken. Subject to the advice received from His Majesty&apos;ambassador he felt that a visit to Washington by the President of theBoard of Trade might be the most effective step.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Unless prompt action was taken to secure further supplies ofsulphur, large-scale unemployment would develop in this country. Itwas therefore essential that the Government should be able to demon-strate that they had taken every possible measure to increase supplies.(b) Some sulphur was already being bought through privatechannels from Italy, but total production there was relatively smalland under the present arrangements with the United States theamount of supplies obtainable from elsewhere would be deducted from our United States allocation.(c) Some Ministers were doubtful whether Lord Knollys hadthe right qualifications for the exacting task of negotiating with theUnited States Government on supplies of raw materials. It waspointed out that he had assumed his duties only a few days previouslyand that much of the present difficulty appeared to be due to a lackof co-ordination within the United States administration.id) Research in the United Kingdom into the provision of substitutes for sulphur should be expedited. It was suggested that industry should be urged to make more use of iron pyrites for themanufacture of sulphuric acid. It was pointed out, however, thatpyrites had to be imported and that supplies were limited. Anhydrite,which was available in the United Kingdom, and the conversion ofspent sulphur, might be more reliable sources of additional supplies.(e) In our representations to the United States Government weshould emphasise our efforts to avoid waste in the use of sulphur andto employ substitutes. We should also explain the urgent steps thatwe were taking to reduce our dependence on imported sulphur.(/) The Minister of Labour said that the serious situation whichhad resulted from our deficiency in sulphur emphasised the urgent need for a survey of the mineral resources of the United Kingdom.Such a survey might reveal both further deficiencies and unexpectedassets.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a high-level approach should be made to theUnited States Government without delay on the supplyof sulphur; and invited the Prime Minister to determine the method of this approach in the light of the advice nowawaited from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington.(2) Invited the Minister of Labour to submit a memorandum tothe Cabinet on the need for a survey of the mineral resources of the United Kingdom.7. The Postmaster-General said that he had received a demandfor recognition from the National Guild of Motor Engineers, which represented 1,700 postal workers in a grade of 3,000 men. Since thenumber of men in the union was higher than the percentage normallyrequired for recognition, he would in the ordinary way have recognised the Guild. This would, however, increase his difficulties in regard toother break-away unions notably the Engineering Officers (Tele-communications) Association-which had much larger memberships,though the percentages in relation to the grades concerned were not
so high. Moreover, recognition of the Guild would almost certainlyencourage the creation of break-away unions in other grades. he therefore proposed to appoint a committee, composed of personsexperienced in industrial relations, to report on the general problemof the recognition of staff associations in the Post Office and on the specific claims for recognition that were now outstanding. The three main unions in the Post Office were agreeable to this course.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would like anopportunity to consider the terms of reference of the proposed committee and also to sound informally the National Staff Side. Hewould also like to consult with the Postmaster-General on the composition of the committee so as to ensure that the Civil Service,as distinct from the industrial, aspects of the problem were kept inmind.The Minister of Labour said that, while he was in agreement withthe procedure proposed by the Postmaster-General, he also would wish to be consulted on the points mentioned by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer.The Cabinet Agreed in principle that the Postmaster-General should setup a committee to investigate the question of the recognitionof staff associations in the Post Office; and invited him to consult with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theMinister of Labour on its composition and terms ofreference.Cabinet Office, SWA,Sth February, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
