<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/19/0 images: 233-241</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    133THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE   PROPERTY   OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTYS   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1951 .SECRETCM. (51)27th conclusions copy No.CABINET 27 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 12th April, 1951, at 11-00 am.Present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(in the Chair).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right  Hon.  Viscount  Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Edith Summerskill,M.P., Minister of National Insurance.(Item 2.)The Right Hon. John Wheatley, K.C.,M.P., Lord Advocate. (Item 3.)The Right Hon. H. A. Marquand, M.P.,Minister of Health. (Item 2.)The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury. (Item 2.)
CABINET 27 (51)contents minute No. Subject page 1     . K.01 c 3.       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...   2132     Parliament.........      ......      ......  213Business in the House of Commons.North Atlantic Treaty: Command Organisation.Budget Legislation.3     United Nations: Covenant on Human Rights ...      ...      ...  2154     Bechuanaland Protectorate       ............      ... 216Tshekedi Khama.5     Film of Berlin Youth Rally      ............... 2176     Stone of Scone    ..................... 218
134CM. 27 (51)Korea. 1.   The Foreign Secretary said that in the light of the Cabinets(Previous        discussion on 22nd March he had suggested to the United states reference:      Government that a fresh initiative might now be taken in the searchCM. (51) 23rd for a political settlement in Korea.   He had proposed that theConclusions,    Governments whose forces were fighting under United NationsMinute 1.)       command in Korea should issue a fresh declaration of policy,combined with specific proposals for a settlement; and that thereafterthere should be an approach to the Peking Government and possibly to the Soviet Government also. The United States Government hadbeen inclined to favour a more limited programme; and this inclina-tion might be reinforced by the political difficulties which were likelyto follow the Presidents dismissal of General MacArthur.  He had,however, asked His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington to press the State Department to give further thought to his proposals, for he considered that world opinion would regard this as a favourablemoment for some fresh initiative.   He had also asked the FrenchGovernment to support his views in Washington. If it proved impos-sible to secure a multilateral declaration on the lines which he had originally envisaged, it might be necessary to consider whether theOther interested Governments would be willing to make separatedeclarations. :-In discussion it was suggested that the United States government might have been influenced by the reports that the Chinese weremounting a new offensive: they might have thought it wiser to post-pone any fresh attempt to secure a political settlement until after any new military offensive by the Chinese had been countered. From thelatest intelligence reports, however, it now seemed less likely that aChinese offensive was imminent. Even so, some Ministers feltdoubtful whether it would be wise for the Foreign Secretary to presshis suggestion too strongly upon the United States Government at atime when they would be obsessed by the political difficulties resultingfrom the dismissal of General MacArthur. It was also important thatno fresh initiative should be taken which might appear to relieve theUnited Nations of their responsibility for handling the Korean situa-tion. The Governments contributing contingents to the united nations forces in Korea should stand united in this matter: ifseparate declarations were made by some, but not all, of these governments, the Chinese would not fail to exploit the apparentdivision of opinion between them.In further discussion the question was raised whether the newUnited Nations Commander would go forward with the naval opera-tion off the Chinese coast which had recently been proposed byGeneral MacArthur. The Cabinet agreed that it would be inexpedient to put this question formally to the United States Government. HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington might, however, be warned tokeep the point in mind in case he had an opportunity of mentioning itin informal conversation with United States officials.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary, in his further approaches tothe United States Government regarding the Korean situa-tion, to take account of the points made in the cabinets discussion.Parliament. 2.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in business in the  the House of Commons in the following week.House ofCommons.
North Atlantic The debate on the North Atlantic command organisation wouldTreaty: be held on 19th April; and the Opposition had now asked that anCommand       interim White Paper should be presented for the purposes of this organisation,    debate even though all the appointments to be made under this(Previous        command structure could not by then be announced.  A draft had reference:      therefore been prepared, which contained a description of the militaryCM. (51) 24th   organisation created under the North Atlantic Treaty, a statement of conclusions,     the arguments in favour of the appointment of an American AdmiralMinute 1.)       as Supreme Commander, Atlantic, and some account of the problems which arose in connection with the appointment of a supreme commander, Mediterranean. This draft would be submitted to theDefence Committee at their meeting on 16th April and, subject totheir approval, could be presented to Parliament on the late afternoon of 17th April. The White Paper would contain a full statement ofthe Governments case on the main issues which were to be discussed in the debate. In these circumstances the Cabinet agreed that it wouldbe convenient if the debate were opened by an Opposition spokesman.The Minister of Defence outlined to the Cabinet the difficultieswhich had arisen over the Mediterranean command. The UnitedStates military authorities had now realised that they had gained littleadvantage by the appointment of an American Admiral as supreme commander, Atlantic. This Supreme Commander, who would havehis headquarters at Norfolk, Virginia, would be concerned largelywith matters of administration and planning; and the bulk of thenaval operations in this theatre would come under the control of theBritish naval commander in the Eastern Atlantic. They were thereforeanxious to secure that in the Mediterranean the naval commandershould be an American; and, on that basis, they might have beenprepared to agree that the Supreme Commander, Mediterranean,should be British. This arrangement would, however, have the resultthat an American Admiral would command all the British naval forces in the Western Mediterranean and would also control theBritish naval bases in the area. Such an arrangement could not beaccepted: it would plainly be most unwelcome to public opinion inthis country. An attempt was therefore being made to secure agree-ment with the Americans on the basis that the Supreme Commander,Mediterranean, should be a British Admiral who would himself be indirect command of all the British naval forces and bases in theWestern Mediterranean; but that he should be assisted by a DeputySupreme Commander, who should be a United States officer. Thefurther course of these discussions with the United States militaryauthorities would be reported to the Defence Committee.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Chief Whip to try to arrange that the debate onthe North Atlantic command organisation on 19th Aprilshould be opened by an Opposition spokesman.(2) Took note that the Minister of Defence would submit to theDefence Committee a draft of the White Paper which hewas proposing to present to Parliament for the purposes ofthis debate.Budget The Cabinet discussed the timetable for the legislation requiredLegislation.      to give effect to the proposals announced by the Chancellor of the(Previous        Exchequer in his Budget statement.  In addition to the Finance BillReference:      there would be a National Health Service Bill authorising charges forCM. (51) 26th   dentures and spectacles supplied under the Health Service, and a conclusions.)    National Insurance Bill making provision for the new rates of pay-ment to old age pensioners. There would be advantages in making progress with these two Bills before the introduction of the finance bill. The Home Secretary proposed that they should be introduced on 17th April and that Second Reading debates should take place inthe week beginning 23rd April.
United Nations: 3. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the ForeignCovenant on Secretary (CP. (51) 82) and the Attorney-General (CP. (51) 91) on human Rights, the question whether the United Kingdom Government should con-tinue their efforts in the United Nations to secure the adoption of aCovenant on Human Rights.The Lord Chancellor said that he viewed with grave misgivingsthe consequences, in our domestic law, of ratifying these international conventions on Human Rights. He had drawn the Cabinefs atten-tion, on 18th January (CM. (51) 4th Conclusions, Minute 3) and earlier occasions, to the legal difficulties which might arise from theadoption of the Convention on Human Rights which had been underdiscussion in the Council of Europe. The draft Covenant now underdiscussion by the United Nations might be even more objectionable;for it was suggested that this should confer on some international bodya judicial power to pronounce whether the domestic legislation ofsignatory countries was in conformity with the terms of the Covenant.By way of illustration he offered the opinion that, if the UnitedKingdom Government ratified this Covenant in its present form, theywould be unable to introduce legislation providing for the deportation of stowaways; they would deprive themselves of the power to excludeTshekedi Khama from the Bamangwato Reserve (see Minute 4below); and, by reason of Article 3 of the draft Covenant, they would throw doubt on the right of a military sentry to fire on a suspect. it seemed to him to be a very serious matter to limit in this way the sovereignty of Parliament and the powers of the Executive. In hisopinion, definitions of human rights were more suitable for a politicalmanifesto than for an instrument having the force of law.  Framed,The Minister of Labour said that, if there were a division on theNational Health Service Bill, he would not feel able to vote in favourof it.The President of the Board of Trade suggested that, in view ofthe division of opinion within the Cabinet on this question, it wouldbe preferable that further Cabinet discussion of it should be post-poned until the Prime Minister (who was still in hospital) was ableto preside. Meanwhile, he suggested that the introduction of the Billshould be delayed.The Foreign Secretary said that the Cabinet had decided toimpose charges for dentures and spectacles supplied under theNational Health Service, and had authorised the Chancellor of theExchequer to announce that decision in his Budget statement. Thedecision had proved acceptable to a substantial majority of thoseattending the meeting of the Parliamentary Labour Party at whichthe Budget statement had been discussed. From the point of viewof Parliamentary tactics the wisest course was to proceed at once with the legislation authorising the imposition of these charges. Ifthe introduction of the legislation were delayed, the Governmentwould be thought to be wavering; and, once this impression wasgiven, the Parliamentary difficulties of passing this legislation wouldbe greatly increased.After discussion, the Cabinet-(3) Decided that the National Health Service Bill and the. National Insurance Bill should be introduced on 17thApril.(4) Agreed that the Second Reading of the National health service Bill and the National Insurance Bill should betaken in the week beginning 23rd April.(5) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the drafts of thesetwo Bills to be examined by the Legislation Committee ata special meeting on 16th April. ,
as they were,, by processes of compromise in international discussion,these documents were necessarily cast in imprecise or ambiguouslanguage inappropriate for a code of law. If, however, it was thought necessary on political grounds to go forward with this Covenant, hewould not press his legal objections; but in that event he suggestedthat every Article of the draft Covenant should be subjected to the closest scrutiny, and he asked that he and the Law Officers shouldbe brought into consultation at all stages.The Foreign Secretary said that he had always been scepticalabout the value of these conventions on human rights. But, as theUnited Kingdom Government had played a leading part in promotingthem, it would be difficult to draw back at this stage. In these circum-stances the prudent course might be to prolong the international dis-cussions, to raise legal and practical difficulties, and to delay theconclusion of the Covenant for as long as possible.The Cabinet favoured the course suggested by the foreign secretary. Additional delay might be secured by proposing that particular parts of the draft Covenant should be referred, for examination and report, to the Social and Economic Council, theInternational Labour Organisation or other specialised agencies.They might with advantage be asked to comment on aspects of theCovenant on which they were specially qualified to pronounce.In further discussion the point was made that the Colonial appli-cation.clause had now been deleted from the draft Covenant. Thiswas perhaps an argument in favour of continuing to participate in international discussion of the draft, in order to seek modification of provisions which we should find it impracticable or undesirable toapply in Colonial territories. Despite these efforts, however, it seemed unlikely that the convention would emerge in a form which wouldmake it possible for us to ratify it if it was expressed as applicable toall Colonial territories.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the United Kingdom Government should con-tinue to participate in the discussions in the united nations of the draft Covenant on Human Rights; butinvited the Foreign Secretary to instruct his representative in those discussions to exploit to the full any opportunityfor delaying the conclusion of the Covenant and, inparticular, to suggest that appropriate parts of it should bereferred to the various specialised agencies of the united nations for examination and report.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for the LordChancellor and the English and Scottish Law Officers tobe consulted at all stages in the further discussion of this draft Covenant.(3) Invited the Foreign Secretary to submit to the Cabinet areport on the proposed Protocol to the Convention on human Rights which had been adopted by the Councilof Europe.bechuanaland protectorate.tshekedi khama.(previous reference:CM. (50) 40thConclusions,Minute 6.)4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations (CP. (51) 103) proposing thatTshekedi Khama should continue to be excluded from the Bamang-wato Reserve but should be helped in preserving his private propertythere.The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations said thathe had hoped at one time that it might have been possible to allowTshekedi to return to the Bamangwato Reserve, and to take a partin the administration of the tribe.   It had now become clear, however,
Film of Berlin 5.   The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the ForeignYouth Ra%     Secretary (CP. (51) 86) and the Home Secretary (CP. (51) 102) on theattitude which the Government should adopt towards proposals thata film of the Berlin Youth Rally should be brought into this country, for private or public exhibition.The Foreign Secretary said that he had seen the film and hethought that, while older people with recollections of the Nazi regimemight see in it a strong resemblance between the East GermanAdministration and the Nazis, it might give younger people a favour-able impression of conditions in Eastern Germany. He thought,therefore, that, if the film were to be shown in this country, it shouldbe severely edited and material introduced to point to the resemblancebetween the Communist and Nazi regimes.that Tshekedi was feared and hated by the Bamangwato and, in theinterests of law and order in the Reserve, would have to be excludedfrom it. If he accepted this situation, it would be reasonable to help him by protecting his extensive property in the Reserve and by improving the pasture in the south of the Reserve where his cattlecould be concentrated. He was an able man, and useful work mightbe found for him in connection with the activities of the colonial development Corporation.In discussion the following points were made: - -la) It was not necessary at this stage to suggest to Tshekedi thathe would be permanently excluded from the Reserve. All that was proposed was adherence to the policy outlined in the White Paper(Cmd. 7913), by which Tshekedi was to be excluded from the Reserveduring the five years for which the chieftainship of the tribe was toremain in suspense.(b) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he must not betaken as assenting to the proposal that the United Kingdom exchequer should contribute towards the improvement of the pastures in thesouth of the Reserve. The Commonwealth Relations Office and theColonial Office should discuss with the Treasury whether this improve-ment should not be financed from Bechuanaland funds, which receivedColonial welfare grants.(c) The improvement of these pastures would not be undertakensolely in Tshekedi&apos;s private interests. A public interest would be served by improving the agricultural condition of the Reserve witha view on a better distribution of cattle throughout the Reserve.(d) It was not certain that Tshekedi would be prepared to accept this exclusion from the Reserve and to co-operate in the other measures proposed. It was understood, however, that his lawyer was likely to advise him to accept the proposals outlined in CP. (51) 103.(e) It would be unnecessary to issue any detailed statement tothe Press, on this subject, unless Tshekedi proved unwilling to acceptthe proposals and was likely to give the Press an elaborate statementof his own case.(/) The development of a system of native administration in the bamangwato Reserve on more representative lines would necessarily be a slow process because the people were accustomed to a dynasticsystem of government and Seretse Khama had a considerable follow-ing. Experience in Basutoland, as indicated in CP. (51) 92, had shown the danger of pressing too fast constitutional developments which cut across tribal organisation.The Cabinet Approved the proposals in paragraph 11 of CP. (51) 103,subject to further consideration of the need for any detailedpublic announcement of Government policy on the matter.
The Home Secretary said that, because of its technical qualitiesand the favourable light which it cast on the East German regime andits methods, the film was a very dangerous one. At the same time there could be no question of using the Prerogative power to preventits being imported into this country.The President of the Board of Trade said that he would not bein favour of using import licensing or film registration to prevent thisfilm from being shown in this country. It might be possible to getone of the film companies to buy from the East German Governmentexclusive rights in the film in this country; and, if these rights werepurchased without difficult conditions being attached to them, the film company might edit the film in such a way as to point theresemblances between the present regime in East Germany and thepre-war Nazi regime.The Cabinet agreed that it was difficult for Ministers to take afinal decision on this matter without seeing the film.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for the film of the berlin Youth Rally to be shown in the House of Commonscinema at a time convenient to those Ministers who wishedto see it.Stone of 6.   The Home Secretary said that the stone deposited in the ruinsScone. of Arbroath Abbey had now been identified as the Stone of Sconewhich had been removed from Westminster Abbey on the night of24th-25th December last. Arrangements were being made for thestone to be brought back to London, in circumstances which shouldobviate the danger of any demonstrations.The Cabinet Took note of the Home Secretary&apos;s statement.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,12th April, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
