<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/19/0 images: 251-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY   OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENT&apos;Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1951.SECRETCM, (51)29th conclusions copy No.     ^CABINET 29 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 19th April, 1951, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(in the Chair)The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P..Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State  for the home department.The Pvight Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister  of Labour  and  NationalService.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also present:The Right. Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 5).The Right Hon. John Wheatley, K.C,.M.P., Lord Advocate (Item 4).The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General(Items 1-4).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P.,     Parliamentary     Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-3).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.Mr. O. C. Morland.
CABINET 29 (51)contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1      Parliament ...      ....      ...      ......      ...      ...      ...     227Business in the House of Commons.North Atlantic Treaty: Command Organisation.Durham County Council: Conditions of Employment.2     National Health Service Bill    ...............     2273      Council of Europe...............      ...     2284     The Stone of Scone      ...............      ...     2295     National Coal Board     ......      ............     230Borrowing Powers.6     Japanese Peace Treaty    ......      ............     231General Scope of Treaty.Individual Claims.7     United Nations Armed Forces...............     2328     Food..........      ......      ..r      ......     232Meat Supplies.9      Germany   ...      ......      ......      .........     232Soviet Proposal for a Meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers.
Parliament.Business in theHouse ofCommons.North atlantic treaty:command organisation.(previous reference:CM. (51) 28thConclusions,Minute 6.)DurhamCountyCouncil:Conditions ofEmployment.(previous reference:CM. (51) 19thConclusions,Minute 1.)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.^ On 23rd April, the House was likely to dispose quickly of theFirst Order, and would have ample time to debate the Prayers againstthe Railway Freight Charges Order. The Cabinet agreed that, as thiswas a matter of considerable importance and public interest, it was reasonable that the House should have a substantial opportunity to debate it, even though it were raised on a Prayer by the Opposition.The Cabinet were informed that the leaders of the conservative opposition had been unwilling to accept further postponement of theproposed debate on the North Atlantic Treaty command structure.The White Paper had therefore been presented and the debate was totake place that day. There was now little prospect that the UnitedStates Government would release, before the debate, the official announcement of Admiral Fechteler&apos;s appointment as Supreme Com-mander, Atlantic. In view of this, and of the difficulty of discussingat the present stage the arrangements for the Mediterranean com-mand, the debate was not likely to give any satisfaction to publicopinion in this country.The Minister of Education said that the Durham County council had shown signs of unwillingness to comply with the direction whichhe had issued to them regarding their action in requiring applicants for teaching appointments under their control to state whether theybelonged to a trade union or a professional association. He had nowwritten a further letter offering to meet representatives of the Councilto discuss their difficulties if they, for their part, showed willingness to comply with his direction. Squadron Leader M. C. Hollis, M.P.,had put down a Question, for answer that afternoon, asking whetherthe Council had now given him the assurances for which he had asked;and, as that Question was not likely to be reached, he proposed to circulate a written answer containing the text of his latest letter tothe Council. He did not, however, wish to provoke further discussion in the House of Commons by giving this answer orally. The cabinet agreed that, if the Question was not reached in the ordinary course,the Minister was under no obligation to accede to a request that heshould give the answer orally at the end of Questions.National health service Bill.(previous reference:CM. (51) 27thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Cabinet were informed that the Second Reading of theNational Health Service Bill would be taken&apos; on 24th April.The Minister of Labour said that, if the Second Reading debateled to a division, he would be unable to vote in favour of the Bill; and,if the Bill were carried on Third Reading, he would resign from theGovernment. He was proposing to inform the Prime Minister accord-ingly, by letter; but he thought that he should also make it plain tohis colleagues that these were his intentions, and he wished to havethem placed on record.In discussion, it was recognised that during the Second reading debate some Government supporters must be expected to offercriticisms of the proposed charges for dentures and spectacles.Apprehensions would also be voiced about the effects of limitingannual expenditure on this Service to  400 million: the Governmentwould be asked, in particular, whether this might not mean that infuture years charges would have to be introduced for other facilities provided under the Service. It was suggested that these anxietiesmight be met if the Government spokesmen could be authorised tostate that neither the upper limit of  400 million nor the particularcharges proposed in this Bill were necessarily permanent features ofthe Health Service. It was, however, important that any such state-ment should be framed in terms which were consistent with what hadbeen said on this subject by the Chancellor of the Exchequer in his budget statement.40611-2 B 2
J    The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary to discuss with the Chancellorof the Exchequer, the Minister of Labour and the health ministers whether a suitable form of words could be devised, for use by the Government spokesmen in theSecbnd Reading debate on the National Health service bill, to allay the fears of some Government supportersthat the limit upon expenditure on the National health service and the charges imposed by this Bill would become a permanent feature of the Health Service and would leadto the imposition of charges for other facilities provided under it.(2) Asked the Home Secretary to report the result of these dis-cussions to the Cabinet at their meeting on 23rd April.Council of 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ForeignEurope. Secretary (CP. (51) 105) recommending that, at the forthcoming(Previous meeting of the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe, the reference: United Kingdom representative should be authorised to put forwardCM. (51) 19th an amendment of the Statute which would permit the ConsultativeConclusions, Assembly to discuss the political aspects of defence, while ensuringMinute 5.) that the Committee of Ministers were precluded from taking decisions on defence questions.The Foreign Secretary said that the United Kingdom Govern-ment would find themselves in great difficulty if, at the meeting ofthe Committee of Ministers in Strasbourg in May, they maintained their opposition to all the amendments designed to enlarge thefunctions of the Consultative Assembly. He had reached the con-clusion that.the least objectionable proposal was that the consultative assembly should be empowered to discuss the political aspects ofdefence. The existing provisions of the Statute had not prevented the Consultative Assembly from discussing defence matters. Hesuggested that the Cabinet might make a virtue of necessity by givingstatutory recognition to the existing state of affairs, which had beentolerated by the Committee of Ministers, while at the same timeinsisting that decisions on defence matters were not within the compe-tence either of the Committee of Ministers or of the Assembly.In discussion, attention was drawn to the extent to which debates in the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe tended to cutacross the work of the United Nations, the specialised agencies andthe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation. It had always been con-sidered that discussion of defence questions was particularly inappropriate-priate to a body which had no responsibilities and could take no executive decisions, and for that reason defence had been specificallyexcluded from the scope of the Council when the Statute was framed.As the Assembly had debated defence questions when it was specifically -cally precluded from doing so, was there not a risk that it would go far beyond the limits now proposed if its intrusion into the field ofdefence were recognised and legalised? Might not the debates rangeover technical military matters and the strengths of forces, in additionto the political considerations which the Foreign Secretary had inmind?In support of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposal, it was pointedout that the Government had accepted the principle of a Council ofEurope, in which representatives of the democracies of western europe would meet to discuss means by which their common heritagecould be safeguarded. The delegations included many prominentstatesmen from Western Europe, who were profoundly concerned about the Soviet menace; and there was some danger that the workof the Council would become unreal if such people were denied any opportunity to discuss the threat that hung over Western Europe.
Stone of 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theScone. Attorney-General (CP. (51) 111) stating that he had decided not to(Previous institute criminal proceedings in respect of the removal of the StoneReference: of Scone from Westminster Abbey and indicating the terms in whichCM. (51) 28th he proposed to announce that decision in reply to a ParliamentaryConclusions,    Question later that day.Minute 5.) In discussion of the terms of the proposed announcement, it wassuggested that nothing should be said to imply that this incident had brought discredit on those who supported the claim for a greater measure of Scottish self-government, but condemned sensational orextreme measures in pursuit of it. While the removal of the Stonecould properly be described as a vulgar act of vandalism, it wouldbe inexpedient to use stronger language, which might invite therejoinder that it ought to be possible to take some proceedings against those responsible for it. Nor should anything be said which mightimply that further evidence was still being sought on which pro-ceedings might be based. -Although the Attorney-General did not propose to draw atten-tion to the fact, this incident might have the effect of making it more widely known that, in order to establish a charge of larceny, the prosecution must prove that the accused intended permanently to deprive the owner of his property. If so, other incidents of a similarkind might follow. Supporters of other nationalist movements might attempt to remove the Lane Pictures from the Tate Gallery or theElgin Marbles from the British Museum. Were public librariesadequately protected against the removal of books by persons who could claim that they were merely borrowing them and had no inten-tion of retaining them permanently? The Cabinet considered thatthis question should be further examined.In further public controversy about the Stone of Scone, it wouldbe asked whether anything was to be done to meet the view strongly expressed in some Scottish circles that the Stone should be returnedpermanently to Scotland. The Stone was not the property of theGovernment, and the Dean and Chapter of Westminster Abbey wouldhave to be consulted. The question should, however, be examined,since The King would probably wish to have advice on it from his ministers.Admittedly it would be difficult to define closely what was meant bythe political aspects of defence, but some general discussions on defence questions might serve a useful purpose in enabling distin-distinguished European statesmen to give public expression to their viewson a matter on which they felt so strongly. General debates on defence should not have any serious adverse effects, provided thatit was made clear that decisions on defence were not within thecompetence of the Council of Europe, and that no action had to betaken on the views on this subject expressed in debates in the Con-consultative Assembly.There was general agreement that, so long as due emphasis was laid on- the consultative character of the Council of Europe, theForeign Secretary need not regard himself as bound by any particularformula for achieving what he had in mind in regard to the discussionof defence matters in the Consultative Assembly. Thus, a suggestion had been made in preliminary discussions in Paris on 16th April that,instead of an amendment to the Statute, the Committee of ministers might adopt a resolution to the effect that the provisions of Article 1 (d)of the Statute did not preclude the Assembly from discussing thegeneral aspects of peace and security.The Cabinet Authorised the Foreign Secretary to go so far as to concede,if he thought it advisable to do so, that the Council of Europemight discuss (but not make recommendations upon) thepolitical aspects of defence.
The Cabinet -(1) Took note of the Attorney-General&apos;s decision not to institutecriminal proceedings in respect of the removal of the Stoneof Scone from Westminster Abbey.(2) Invited the Attorney-General to take account of the views expressed in the Cabinefs discussion regarding the terms in which this decision should be announced to the Houseof Commons in reply to a Parliamentary Question later that day.(3) Invited the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State forScotland to consider whether the English and Scottish lawadequately protected museums, art galleries and churchesagainst the removal of possessions in circumstances inwhich it might be difficult to frame a charge of theft, andto submit a memorandum on this matter to the lord presidents Committee.(4) Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland, after consultationwith other Ministers concerned, to submit a memorandum to the Cabinet on the issues arising in connection with thefuture location of the Stone of Scone.5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of fuel and Power (CP. (51) 112) recommending that his present powersto lend  150 million to the National Coal Board, which expired inJuly 1951, should be replaced by a power to lend up to  300 millionwithout time-limit. The Socialisation of Industries Committee had approved this proposal; but the Legislation Committee, when con-sidering the draft of the Bill, had expressed doubt whether in thepresent Parliamentary situation powers should be sought to lend thislarger amount, particularly since (if the time-limit on the present powers was removed) the existing lending powers would meet theneeds of the situation for some years to come.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that socialisation measurespassed after the Coal Industry Nationalisation Act; 1946, had givenborrowing powers for larger amounts and without a time-limit. Hethought that the power to lend up to  300 million could be justified by reference to the &quot; National Plan for Coal,&quot; recently published bythe National Coal Board, and would be an earnest of the Govern-ment&apos;s intention to support the execution of that Plan. The NationalUnion of Mineworkers had expressed dissatisfaction about the extentto which capital development in the coal industry was being financed from allowances for depreciation taken out of current revenue, andthey would suspect that a refusal to give the National Coal Boardwider borrowing power showed a disposition by the Governmentto force the Board to finance development from current revenues and thereby reduce the prospect of further concessions in respect of wagesand conditions of service.In support of legislation which would remove the time-limit on existing lending powers but would not increase the amount whichthe Board might borrow, it was pointed out that the Board had so farreceived only  41 million out of the  150 million which they mighthave borrowed. It was unlikely that the total borrowings would exceed  150 million within the next four or five years. If powers were taken to lend larger amounts, it would be said that parliament was being asked to authorise borrowings some years ahead undercircumstances which would not at present be envisaged, and that itwas right that Parliament should consider borrowings for furtheramounts nearer the time when they would be required. Alternatively,it would be argued in Parliament that the Board were being encouraged in financial extravagance. Although the later nationalisa-tion statutes had not placed a time-limit on borrowing powers, thesetime-limits had been common in the past in legislation affecting publicNational coal board.borrowing powers.
japanese peace Treaty.General Scopeof Treaty.(previous reference:CM. (51) 23rdConclusions,Minute 7.)IndividualClaims.(previous reference:CM. (51) 1stConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (51) 104) seting out the issues for decision in con-nection with the forthcoming discussions with the United StatesGovernment on a Peace Treaty with Japan. Two provisional drafts of a treaty, prepared as unofficial working documents by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment and the United States Government respectively, wereannexed to the memorandum.The Foreign Secretary recalled that the Cabinet had agreed thatit would be inexpedient to delay discussion by the interested Govern-ments of the terms of the treaty, and it was proposed to begindiscussions with the United States&apos; authorities on 23rd April. Thepoints on which he invited his colleagues&apos; agreement were enumerated in paragraphs 5 to 8 of his paper. In general his recommendations were based on a policy of conciliation and were designed, within thenecessary limits, to promote co-operation with Japan when she againenjoyed freedom in her international relations.Several Ministers said that they would like to have more time forstudy of the issues raised in the paper, which had been circulated only two days previously, and it was. agreed to defer its consideration untilthe next meeting of the Cabinet.Reference was again made to the question of compensatingindividuals who had suffered at the hands of the Japanese duringthe war. The Cabinet had previously agreed that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should neither press for payment by Japan nor make further payment themselves, and the United Kingdom draft annexed to CP. (51) 104 included no provision for the payment of compensa-tion by Japan. A large number of Members of Parliament had,however, tabled a Motion calling upon His Majesty&apos;s Government togive early consideration to the payment of compensation by Japan,and careful consideration would have to be given to the line to betaken by the Government if that Motion were debated.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was at presentdiscussing with his colleagues the disposal of the Japanese assets,amounting to about  1  million, in the possession of His Majesty&quot;sGovernment.  The United States Government had used their muchutilities and local authorities, and the Coal Board differed from othersocialised industries in that it did not raise its own stock butborrowed from the Consolidated Fund.The general view of the Cabinet was that a power to borrow upto  300 million without time-limit could be defended. It would showthat the Government intended to assist the National Coal Board tocarry through the National Plan for Coal, and the debates on theBill would afford an opportunity to give wide publicity to the long-term plans of the Board, with their far-reaching effects on the geographical distribution of the industry and the improved conditions under which work would be carried on in the mines. Any imputationthat the Government were encouraging extravagance could be refutedby indicating the extent to which development in the coal indusrty was controlled by the capital investment programme. The progressof the long-term plan for the coal industry would be determined bygeneral investment policy and not by statutory controls over borrow-ing powers. The argument that the Board had not made much use oftheir existing borrowing powers and did not require wider powers for larger amounts could be met by showing the extent to which capital development would have to increase in the next few years.The Cabinet-Agreed that, in the forthcoming Coal Industry Bill, theMinister of Fuel and Power should have power to make advances to the National Coal Board up to  300 millionwithout time-limit.
larger Japanese assets for distribution among former prisoners-of-war,and the suggestion had been made that the  li million might be handed over to charitable organisations concerned with the welfare of ex-prisoners of war. It was pointed out that, if this was done,it would be undesirable to differentiate between prisoners who hadbeen held by the Germans and by the Japanese. There was also astrong interest in this matter in the Colonies, where very large claims against Japan had been put forward.The Foreign Secretary said that he would arrange, whendiscussion of the paper was resumed, to put his views on this question before his colleagues.The Cabinet-Agreed to defer consideration of CP. (51) 104 until their next meeting.United Nations t 7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the ForeignArmed Forces. Secretary (CP. (51) 106) on the United States proposal for the forma-(Previous tion of a United Nations Legion. In September 1950, when this reference: proposal had originally been made, we had been able to persuadeCM. (50) 57th the United States Government to drop it, and they had nowConclusions, suggested that it should be discussed, without committing Govern-Minute 1.) ments or reaching final decisions, by the Collective MeasuresCommittee of the United Nations.The Foreign Secretary said that he recommended that we should agree to such a discussion by the Collective Measures Committee.Our opposition to the formation of a United Nations Legion couldbe maintained, and expressed in discussion; but it wrould be undesir-able for us to refuse to discuss the suggestion, since the &quot; Unitingfor Peace &quot; Resolution, which we had supported, contemplated theconsideration of action of this kind.The Cabinet Approved the recommendation made in CP. (51) 106.Food.Meat Supplies.(previous reference:CM. (51) 25thConclusions,Minute 1.)8. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Mission underthe leadership of the Economic Secretary, Treasury, were now on thepoint of concluded an agreement with the Argentine Government,and an announcement was likely to be made on the evening of20th April. The agreement provided for the. supply of 200,000 tons of meat., at an average price of about  128 a ton. The lowest price forfrozen meat under the agreement would be below  120 a ton.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer.Germany.:Soviet Proposalfor a Meetingof the Councilof foreign ministers.(previous reference:CM. (51) 19thConclusions,Minute 3.)9. The Minister of Labour suggested that it might be helpful to the Cabinet if they could have an interim report on the progressof the discussions now proceeding in Paris with a view to framing an agenda for a meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers.The Foreign Secretary said that the situation was changing from day to day and he feared that any such report was likely to be out of date before it was discussed by the Cabinet. He would, however,consider whether he could provide the Cabinet with a general appre-ciation of the course which these discussions had so far taken.


</content>
</cab>
