<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/19/0 images: 260-268</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE  PROPERTY   OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  April 1951SECRETCM. (51)30th conclusions copy No.45CABINET 30 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, SWA,on Monday, 23rd April, 1951, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(in the Chair).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gmtskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.  Viscount  Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also present:The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 3).The Right Hon. H. A. Marquand, M.P.,Minister of Health (Item 1).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.Mr. O. C. Morland.40659-1B
CABINET 30 (51)contents minute no. subject      National Health Service Bill     .........2   , Houses of Historic or Architectural Interest   ...3     Persia       .....,      ...... ......4     Japanese Peace Treaty   ...     ...     ...     ...Individual Claims.General Scope of the Treaty.5   . Organisation for European Economic Co-operationProposed Merger with Council of Europe.6     Film of Berlin Youth Rally      .........
1. The Cabinet were informed that, in pursuance of their decision of 19th April, the Ministers directly concerned had met toconsider what could be said, by the Government spokesmen in theSecond Reading debate on the National Health Service Bill, to allay the fears of some Government supporters that the limit upon expendi-ture on the National Health Service and the charges imposed by this bill would become a permanent feature of the Service and would leadin due course to the imposition of charges for other facilities provided under it. It had not been found possible to find a form of words whichwould satisfy the Minister of Labour, and he had now resigned fromthe Government. The other Ministers concerned were agreed inmaking the following recommendations to the Cabinet:  ;(i) In moving the Second Reading of the Bill, the Minister ofHealth&apos; should say that the proposed imposition of a charge fordentures and spectacles need not necessarily be regarded as a per-manent feature of the Health Service: it could be revoked or modified by Order-in-Council on an affirmative resolution.(ii) In replying to the debate, the Secretary of State for scotland should amplify the statement made by the Chancellor of theExchequer in his Budget speech about the upper limit of expenditureon the Health Service. After recalling the Chancellor^ statement thatthis limit would be maintained only &quot; for the time being,&quot; he should say that expenditure on the Health Service, as on the food subsidies,would be looked at afresh each year in the light of the general financial situation and all the many claims made upon the Exchequer,including those for defence and other social services as well as forthe Health Service itself. He should add that it would be obvious tothe House that very heavy burdens would have to be carried by theExchequer in the next year or two.The Cabinet-Approved these recommendations; and invited the Ministerof Health and the Secretary of State for Scotland to includestatements in the terms set out above in their speeches inthe debate on the Second Reading of the National health service Bill.2. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (51) 110) on the report of theCommittee, under the Chairmanship of Sir Ernest Gowers, which had considered what arrangements the Government might make for thepreservation, maintenance and use of houses of outstanding historicor architectural interest.The Lord President said that there had been a preliminary dis-cussion of this memorandum by the Lord President&apos;s Committee, whowere agreed in supporting the proposals outlined by the Chancellorof the Exchequer as the right way to begin to handle this subject.These proposals, in their view, were more consistent with LabourParty principles than the scheme put forward in the Gowers Report.They therefore invited the Cabinet to approve the Chancellorsproposals.In a short discussion the following points were made:  (a) The Minister of Agriculture suggested that any agricultural land which might be acquired by the State under these proposals should be administered by the Agricultural Land Commission. TheCabinet agreed that this suggestion should be considered in thecourse of the preparation of the necessary legislation.-1 b 2
(b) The Secretary of State for Scotland drew attention to thefact that special arrangements would have to be made for handlingthis problem in Scotland.The Cabinet Approved the proposals set out in CP. (51) 110.Persia. 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Foreign(Previous Secretary (CP. (51) 114) regarding the basis on which negotiations for reference: a new oil agreement might be opened with the Persian Government.CM. (51) 28th This proposed that, if the Persian Government agreed, a missionConclusions,&apos; headed by a junior Minister should visit Tehran, as soon as order had minute 3.) been restored in the oilfields, to negotiate a fresh agreement.The Foreign Secretary said that it would be necessary to go someway to meet Persian national aspirations regarding the nationalisation of their oil resources, while at the same time taking all practicable steps to ensure that the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company continued towork the oil and that adequate supplies of oil were available for thiscountry. The United Kingdom Government should take the initiative in suggesting a settlement before the Majlis Oil Commission had com-pleted their investigation and the Persian Government were com-mitted to some extreme course. He hoped that it would prove prac-ticable to find a solution along the lines indicated in paragraph 4(i) of cp. (51) 114, which would admit some Persian directors to the Com-pany and share the profits^ between Persia and the Company,while retaining full company shareholding in a United Kingdomcompany. The United States Government had, however, indicated that they could not give active support to such a proposal, though theywould maintain an attitude of benevolent neutrality towards it: they themselves believed that it would be necessary to agree to a solution which might involve the vesting of the Company&apos;s assets in Persia inthe Persian Government. The objection to that solution, which wasoutlined in paragraph 4(iv) of his memorandum, was that it would almost certainly involve the abrogation of the existing concession, and thereby subject the Company to the jurisdiction of the Persian courts.The United States Government had suggested that it would be prefer-able to leave the conduct of the negotiations to His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Tehran. The Prime Minister had taken the view thata junior Minister should not be sent to head a mission to Tehran, since it was by no means clear that a suitable agreement could be negotiatedat this stage. The choice therefore lay between leaving the negotia-tions to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, or finding some suitable person other than a Minister to head a mission from this country.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that the Company shouldbe enabled to retain control of the oilfields, the refinery and their other assets in Persia. At the same time it would be a mistake to under-estimate. the pressure in Persia for the transfer of theCompany&apos;s properties to the Persian Government. Oil supplies were a wasting asset; and, if the Persian Government considered that theyhad failed hitherto to secure a sufficient share of the profits of theAnglo-Iranian Oil Company, they would be all the more inclined topress for substantial control during the remaining life of the oil wells.It might therefore become necessary to envisage a settlement on thelines indicated in paragraph 4 (iv) of CP. (51) 114. The company had shown little appreciation in recent years of the political forces atwork in Persia, and he supported the proposal that the negotiations should be undertaken by the United Kingdom Government ratherthan by the Company. &amp;In subsequent discussion there was general agreement that theUnited Kingdom Government should take the initiative in openingearly negotiations with the Persian Government for a fresh agreement.At the outset there would have to be some informal soundings by His
japanese peace Treaty.(previous reference:CM. (51) 29thConclusions,Minute 6.)IndividualClaims.4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (51) 97) seeking authority to make an early public announcement of the Cabinefs decision of 2nd January (CM. (51) 1stConclusions, Minute 4) not to press for the inclusion in the japanese peace Treaty of an obligation on Japan to pay individual claims for compensation.The Foreign Secretary said that in his view (which was shared by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the President of the Boardof Trade) the balance of advantage lay on the side of making the cabinet&apos;s decision public as soon as consultations with the other commonwealth Governments and Colonial Governments had beencompleted. He also proposed that, in order to make clear the Gov-governments intentions in respect of the  1  millions of Japanese assets in their possession, the statement annexed to CP. (51) 63 should be expanded to indicate that this sum would be used for the benefit of organisations assisting former prisoners-of-war and internees whohad suffered at the hands of the Japanese.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that this was a matterof keen interest to Colonial Governments, who held Japanese assetstotalling about  5^- million. If we decided to use the Japanese assets in the United Kingdom as proposed by the Foreign Secretary theColonial Governments might wish to take similar action. He under-stood, however, that this  5^ million might already have been com-,mitted for payment into the United Kingdom Exchequer inconnection with the payments already made to the Colonies underthe war damage schemes, and he would wish to discuss the position with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Some Ministers thought it would be unwise, in advance ofthe discussions on the Peace Treaty, to make an explicit statementvirtually abandoning the hope of obtaining any compensation from japan. A shorter statement, making it clear that we were continuing to press our claims on Japan, and that we were consulting other commonwealth Governments, should suffice for the purpose of the debate on the Motion calling upon His Majesty&apos;s Government to giveearly consideration to obtaining payment of compensation from japan.Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Tehran. While later developments would to some extent be determined by the result of these preliminaries,Ministers favoured the despatch of a mission from this countryheaded by some suitable person who was not a member of the Gov-ernment and accompanied by a director of the Anglo-Iranian oil company. His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Tehran had been heavilyinvolved in the recent developments and it would be easier for a mission from this country to make a fresh start in negotiations withthe Persian Government. Every endeavour should be made to reach an agreement with the Persian Government along the lines indicatedin paragraph 4 (i) of CP. (51) 114.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Tehran to take informal soundings aboutthe opening of early negotiations for a fresh oil agreement,and to arrange, if it were found to be appropriate, for a mission headed by a suitable person who was not amember of the Government to visit Tehran as soon asorder had been restored in the oilfields.(2) Agreed that the proposal in paragraph 4 (i) of CP. (51) 114should be treated as the basis on which negotiations withthe Persian Government might be opened.
(b) It would be politically inexpedient to differentiate betweenprisoners-of-war who had suffered at Japanese hands and thosewho had suffered at the hands of the Germans. It was a duty of HisMajesty?s Government to furnish assistance to former prisoners-of-war, Whatever monies could be extracted from ex-enemy countries for this purpose.&apos; (c) When the decision was announced, it would be undesirable to leave in doubt the negligible prospect of obtaining substantialcompensation from Japan. The United States Government wouldbe able to advance a much more powerful claim than ours in theunlikely event of any compensation being forthcoming.It was the general view of the Cabinet that it would not bedesirable at present to make a full statement on the lines of the draft annexed to CP. (51) 97. The Government might accept the motion when it came before the House and a shorter statement might then be made, bringing out the principal points in the draft statement and explaining in addition the position of the Japanese assets in theColonies, which required further elucidation.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with the other ministers directly concerned, to reconsider the form and timing of a statement in the light of the views expressedin the Cabinets discussion.General Scope The Cabinet then resumed their consideration of the Foreignof the Treaty. Secretary&apos;s memorandum (CP. (51) 104) on the issues for decision inconnection with the discussions with the United States Governmenton a Peace Treaty with Japan. :The Foreign Secretary said that it was important that we should enter into these discussions without delay. There might be a numberof points on which the Cabinet would wish to defer a final decision,but he proposed that in the preliminary discussions our representa-tives in Washington should follow the line indicated in his paper.The accession of Japan to the cause of democracy would be of very-great value, and he felt that this could best be secured by theconclusion.of a Peace Treaty on relatively liberal lines. An unfriendlyJapan, allied to the Soviet Union, would constitute a grave peril toour interests in the Far East and to the peace of the world.In discussion the following points were made:  id) The paper did not deal clearly with the question of Chineseparticipation in the negotiations for a Treaty. It was the Cabinetsview that the Peking Government should participate; but the UnitedStates Government appeared to contemplate the participation of theNationalist Government. The Foreign Secretary said that this wasa matter which could best be considered further after some preliminary discussions had been held with the United StatesGovernment.(e) The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations said thathe could not support the proposal in paragraph 5 (e) of-CP. (51) 104that Japan should not be required to renounce her claims inAntarctica. There was strong feeling about this in Australia andNew Zealand.(/) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was not infavour of abandoning at the outset our claim to a share in the stocksof Japanese gold (paragraph 5 (i) of CP. (51) 104). We might haveto agree to this in the end, but our representatives should not concedeit without argument.(g) The, Secretary of State for the Colonies said that it was important that the Treaty should include a Colonial applicationclause.
(h) Some Ministers doubted whether it was desirable to omitfrom the Treaty, as proposed in paragraph 5(c) and (d) of CP. (51)104, clauses referring to , Japan&apos;s moral guilt and unconditional surrender. The balance of opinion in the Cabinet was, however, infavour of omitting these clauses. This would assist friendly relationswith Japan in the future and would not involve the sacrifice of anybenefit which could be obtained by the other parties to the Treaty.The Cabinet-(2) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to arrange for preliminary discussions to be held with the United States government regarding the content of a Japanese Peace Treaty.(3) Agreed that, subject to modification on the points noted inparagraph (e) to (g) above, the proposals in C.P. (51) 104could be adopted as guidance for our representatives inthese preliminary discussions with the United StatesGovernment.Organisation 5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Foreignfor European Secretary (CP. (51) 101) regarding a proposal by the SwedishEconomic Government that a committee should be appointed to study meansCo-operation, of promoting the creation of a new organisation into which theProposed Organisation for European Economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.) andMerger with the Council of Europe would be assimiliated. It was proposed in theCouncil of memorandum that the United Kingdom Government should opposeEurope. this proposal and should seek to prevent, or delay, the appointmentof such a Committee; but that, if the proposal were strongly pressed,they should finally aquiesce in it, provided that the terms of reference of the Committee did not pre-judge the issue which it would berequired to consider.In a short discussion it was suggested that it would be impoliticfor the United Kingdom Government to appear obdurate in their opposition to the appointment of the proposed Committee. On theother hand, strong opposition was expressed to the project of mergingO.E.E.C. in the Council of Europe.The Cabinet Approved the proposals in paragraph 10 of CP. (51) 101.Film of BerlinYouth Rally.(previous reference:CM. (51) 27thConclusions,Minute 5.)6. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the action to betaken in respect of a film of the Berlin Youth Rally.The Foreign Secretary said that he was sorry that so few of his cabinet colleagues had attended the showing of the film which hadbeen arranged in the House of Commons, in accordance with the cabinet&apos;s decision of 12th April. He himself still feared that the filmmight give young people in this country an unduly favourableimpression of conditions in Eastern Germany.Other Ministers who had seen the film thought it more likely that the average audience in this country would not be favourablyimpressed, since they would find in it too many reminders of the nazi regime in pre-war Germany.The Cabinet were informed that the President of the Board ofTrade had come to the conclusion that cinematograph exhibitors inthis country would not be interested in the film, and that it would not therefore be practicable to get one of the film companies to acquireexclusive rights for its public exhibition in this country.It was the general view of the Cabinet that there were no grounds on which the Board of Trade could properly take action, whether by-withholding an import licence or otherwise, to prevent the NationalUnion of Students from showing this film to private audiences in thiscountry.
The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the President of the Board of Trade could notwithhold the grant of an import licence in respect of thisfilm, or take any other action to prevent its being shown to private audiences in this country.(2) Agreed that the Government should not themselves take any action with a view to promoting the exhibition of anedited version of this film to a wider range of audiencesin this country.Cabinet Office, S.W.I,23rdApril, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
