<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/19/0 images: 331-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  document  is  the   property   of  his   britannic  majesty&apos;s   government&apos;Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1951SECRET Copy No.CM. (51)39th conclusions cabinet 39 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, list May, 1951, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.p., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C., M.P., President of theBoard of Trade.The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.(Items 1-4).The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Alfred Robens, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Richard Stokes, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,K.C., M.P., Attorney-General (items-6).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 1).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.Mr. O. C. Morland.
CABINET 39 (51)contents minute no. Subject page 1      Parliament .........      .........      ...      49Business in the House of Commons.2     United Nations......................      49Representation of China.3     Central Africa.....................      50Closer Association of Southern Rhodesia, Northern Rhodesia and nyasaland.4     Egypt      ...      .....................      51Anglo-Egyptian Treaty.5     War Crimes      ......... .........      526     International Labour Conference, 1949       .......1.      53
Parliament. 1.   The Cabinet &quot;were informed of the business to be taken in theBusiness in the House of Commons in the following week.House ofCommons.United Nations.Representationof China.(previous reference:CM. (50) 55thConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Foreign Secretary said that he wished to consult hiscolleagues on the situation which would arise in the Security Councilif the Soviet representative, when he assumed the Presidency of theCouncil on 1st June, sought to secure the exclusion of the ChineseNationalist representative and, perhaps, the substitution of a repre-sentative of the Peking Government.Our existing policy was to vote for the seating of a Peking repre-sentative, a policy in direct conflict with that of the United StatesGovernment. The United States Secretary of State had recentlyproposed a &quot; moratorium&quot; on this question, and he had now suggested that our delegations should consult together in order toagree on a procedure to avoid a direct vote on it. Mr. Acheson had suggested a motion proposing that consideration of Chinese repre-sentation in the Security Council should be postponed as long as the aggression in Korea continued, and our representative on the council had recommended that we should support a motion on these lines.As a procedural motion it would have priority over any motionsubmitted by M. Malik, and its adoption would leave us free tomaintain our existing policy in the future. In supporting the motion,Sir Gladwyn Jebb could make it clear that our policy remained unchanged, though we were willing to refrain from pressing for its adoption while Chinese aggression continued in Korea.Alternatively, we could vote once more for the seating of a Pekingrepresentative, but explain that in the face of Chinese aggression wecould not continue indefinitely to support the admission of a Pekingrepresentative to the Security Council.The Cabinet discussed the further possibilities of proposing thatfor the time being neither Chinese Government should be repre-sented on the Council, or of abstaining on a vote for the admissionof a Peking representative. They considered, however, that the first of these courses would be constitutionally impracticable, and that thesecond, in addition to exposing the conflict of policy with the UnitedStates, would be unpopular with certain sections of public opinion in this country.The Cabinet-Authorised the Foreign Secretary to instruct the UnitedKingdom representative in the Security Council that heshould support a procedural motion proposing that con-sideration of the question of Chinese representation in theCouncil should be postponed for the time being, but thathe should make it clear that this did not mean that theUnited Kingdom Government had modified their view thatthe Peking Government were entitled to represent China inthe Security Council.Central Africa.CloserAssociationof SouthernRhodesia,northern rhodesia and nyasaland.(previous reference:CM. (51) 34thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the memorandumby the Secretary of State for the Colonies and the Secretary of Statefor Commonwealth Relations (CP. (51) 122) on the closer associationof Southern Rhodesia, Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland. Theyhad also before them a further memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Commonwealth Relations (CP. (51) 144) regarding the desire of the Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia that the United KingdomGovernment should commend the proposals in the report of theconference of officials as a suitable basis for the closer association ofthese territories.
The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that there wouldbe many economic and political advantages in the closer associationof these territories. Immigration into the Rhodesias from SouthAfrica was increasing, probably with unofficial encouragement fromthe Union Government, and some counter-action should be taken to check this northward expansion of the Union. It was, however,essential that any form of closer association should provide adequate safeguards for the African population of Northern Rhodesia and nyasaland. He believed that the proposals made in the report, ifthey were workable, would afford such safeguards. In the first place,African affairs would remain the responsibility of the individualGovernments and so subject to his control. Secondly, the plan pro-vided for a Minister for African Interests who, though a member ofthe Federal Cabinet, would be ultimately responsible to the UnitedKingdom Government. Thirdly, the plan provided for the creationof an African Affairs Board, with three Africans among its members.No plan on these lines could succeed unless the Africans could be convinced that it would offer them effective protection. The draft statement in Annex III of CP. (51) 122, which was to be made whenthe report was published, while it made it clear that the UnitedKingdom Government were not committed to the plan, would com-mend it as a constructive approach to the problem which deservedcareful consideration by all concerned. We should go no further than this until we could gauge the effect of the proposals on African publicopinion.The Secretary of State said that he favoured the proposal thathe and the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations should visit the territories in the autumn and hold a conference there; buthe was not sure that it would be possible to reach final conclusionsat that conference, and he would prefer that in the final sentence ofparagraph 4 of the draft statement the conference should be described as one at which the proposals would be further considered.The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations endorsed the views expressed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Therewas a real danger that Southern Rhodesia might be absorbed by theUnion of South Africa, especially if her economic position becamedifficult, and in his view closer association with the northern terri-tories provided the only effective safeguard against this. The estab-lishment of a Central African bloc opposed to the native policy andrepublicanism of the present South African Government would beof great value in encouraging the proper development of our african territories. There was great danger that public opinion in SouthernRhodesia might reject the proposals, which involved a diminution ofher present autonomy, in favour of an attempt to attain full dominion status; but he hoped that this danger could be averted if we were able to give to the present Prime Minister some measure of the support for which he had asked.If it was agreed that the report should be published, and thestatement made as proposed, every effort must be made to ensurethat the proposals were not condemned without proper consideration,either here or in Central Africa; and he proposed, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for the Colonies, to discuss them onpublication with representatives of all political Parties and with thepress.The Minister of Defence said that the Chiefs of Staff consideredthat from the point of view of defence there would be advantage in promoting a closer association between these three territories.In further discussion some Ministers expressed doubts lest theprovisions for the proposed federal association might prove too com-plicated to work smoothly in practice. It was, however, the general view of the Cabinet that the plan was worthy of careful consideration and that a public statement should be made in the terms proposed,
Egypt. 4.   The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the ForeignAnglo-Egyptian Secretary (CP. (51) 131 and 140) on the progress of the discussions inTreaty. Cairo regarding the revision of the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty of 1936.(Previous The Foreign Secretary said that he had hoped that His Majesty&apos;reference: Ambassador in Cairo would have been able to keep these discussionsCM. (51) 24th going for some time on the basis of the proposals approved by theConclusions, Cabinet on 5th April. The Egyptian Foreign Minister had, however,Minute 3.) been unwilling to give serious consideration to those proposals andhad now brought forward the counter-proposals set out in Annex ii of CP. (51) 140. These contemplated the complete withdrawal of all british troops from Egypt within one year and offered no constructivebasis for negotiation. The Foreign Secretary therefore proposed that,in order to keep the discussions going, His Majes.ty&apos;s ambassador should now be instructed to open conversations about the future ofthe Sudan on the basis of the principles set out in CP. (51) 131, adding that in the meantime we should be making a careful study of theEgyptian proposals for the revision of the Treaty. It was understoodthat the Egyptian Foreign Minister was anxious to come to london to pursue discussions about the Treaty; but the Foreign Secretary,while not excluding such a visit, felt that it would be preferable thatthe discussions should be continued for a time in Cairo.The Lord Privy Seal said that, from his personal knowledge of conditions in Egypt, he was satisfied that no agreement could bereached with the Egyptian Government unless we were prepared togive an assurance that all combatant British troops would be removed from the Canal Zone within a reasonable period. He believed that,if the Egyptians could be given satisfaction on this point, they wouldbe ready to agree that substantial British forces might be stationed in Egypt for the purpose of training the Egyptian army, and also thatwe should maintain a military base in Egypt manned by civilians.The proposals which His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador had put forward,in pursuance of the Cabinefs decision of 5th April, had been regarded by the Egyptians as an ultimatum rather than a basis for negotiation;and he feared that no progress could be made unless we could satisfy the Egyptians that we were prepared to make some concessiontowards their point of view regarding the evacuation of combatanttroops from the Canal Zone. In these circumstances he saw no advantage in putting forward at this stage proposals regarding thefuture of the Sudan which would be equally unacceptable to the egyptians. This was likely to exacerbate feelings still further andthus increase the difficulties of reaching any agreement on the Treaty.On the other side it was argued that, if we had to break with egypt, it was preferable that we should do so on the question of theSudan, where our legal and moral case was so much stronger. More-over, our main objective was to prolong the discussions in order to gain time; and from that point of view also there was advantage in introducing a new subject for discussion. There was in fact little prospect of our securing a satisfactory bilateral defence agreementwith Egypt. Our best hope of finding a solution to this problem layin developing some wider arrangements for the defence of the Middlesubject to the amendment suggested by the Secretary of State for theColonies in the reference to the purpose of the proposed conference.The Cabinet (1) Approved the publication of the report annexed to CP. (51)122.(2) Approved the terms of the draft statement annexed to CP.(51) 122, subject to an amendment making it clear thatthe purpose of the conference mentioned in paragraph 4would be to give further consideration to the proposals in the report.
East, from which Egypt would be unable to stand aside. We might beable to guide in that direction the increased interest which the UnitedStates Government were now showing in the defence of the middle east. These developments would, however, take some little time tomature; and in the. meantime our wisest course would be to avoidreaching any definite conclusion of the discussions with the Egyptians.In further discussion the following points were also made:  (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had nowlearned that the proposals put to the Egyptian Government inpursuance of the Cabinets decision of 5th April would have involved a net additional capital expenditure of  59 million and an additionalannual expenditure of  9 million. The Minister of Defence said thatthe gross cost of the plan for redeploying our troops in the middle east was estimated at  97 million.(b) Had the Chiefs of Staff considered the possibility of securingmilitary bases in Israel? The Cabinet were informed that, since his appointment as Commander-in-Chief, Middle East Land Forces,General Robertson had undertaken a special mission to Israel andthe conversations which he had held there had been encouraging.There was some possibility that we might be able to secure military facilities in Israel, but we were not yet in a position to put forwarddefinite proposals.(c) The United States Government, who were anxious that weshould avoid any breakdown in the negotiations on the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty, had suggested that the Egyptians might be mollifiedby the supply of arms. The Cabinet expressed doubts about the expediency of considering any increase in the supply of arms to Egypt;this would certainly arouse suspicion and criticism in the House ofCommons.The Cabinet-Authorised the Foreign Secretary to instruct His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Cairo to open discussions with the egyptian government on the future of the Sudan, on the basis indicated in CP. (51) 131.War Crimes.(previous reference:CM. (51) 13thConclusions,Minute 5.)5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (51) 135) proposing that the power of clemency inrespect of war criminals in Germany should be withdrawn from theUnited Kingdom High Commissioner, and that in future the king should be advised by the Foreign Secretary on these questions. Itwas also proposed that similar arrangements should be adopted un austria, and that the United States and French Governments shouldbe asked to agree to some co-ordination of policy regarding theexercise of clemency towards war criminals.The Foreign Secretary said that the proposal that he should advise on the exercise of the prerogative of mercy towards war criminals in Germany and Austria was in accord with the general view taken by the Cabinet when they discussed this matter on12th February. He would try to follow the practice of the HomeSecretary, though political considerations would clearly play a largerpart. When informing the United States and French Governmentsof the change in procedure he would suggest that an Occupying Power&apos;vhich proposed to revise or remit a sentence in an important case should give the other Occupying Powers an opportunity to express their views on the timing and announcement of any decision.In discussion the following points were made: -(a) The power of clemency at present exercised by the UnitedKingdom High Commissioner was derived from a Royal Warrantunder which the power to review the sentences of war criminals had
been delegated to the Secretaries of State for Foreign Affairs and Warand subsequently by the former to the High Commissioner. TheWar Office were doubtful whether His Majesty should be directly involved in these cases. Ministers considered, however, that thereshould be no difficulty in withdrawing the power of clemency and arranging for it to be exercised by the King on the advice of theForeign Secretary.(b) It would not be practicable or desirable for the foreign secretary to lay down any rigid set of principles by which he wouldbe guided in advising on the exercise of the prerogative of mercy inthese cases. He might be under pressure from German opinion toreduce these sentences, but it would be wrong for him to be guided by German opinion, and it was indeed the fear that the High Com-missioner might be unduly influenced by it that had led to the proposalto transfer the power to the Foreign Secretary. The principal war criminals were held by the four Powers jointly, and their sentenceswould not come under review by the Foreign Secretary. The greatmajority of the war criminals held in British hands had hot been guilty of political offences but of ordinary war crimes.(c) Three reviews of the sentences imposed on war criminals hadalready been held, with a view to ensuring that there were no unduediscrepancies between the sentences imposed for similar offences at different places and by different courts. It seemed unlikely that therewas any scope for any further general reviews of these sentences.(d) The Foreign Secretary, in any public statement, should avoidimplying that the sentences imposed on war criminals would bebrought under review periodically and that this review would entail a great deal of work. It should be indicated that the prerogative ofmercy would be exercised only in a few exceptional cases, and thatin the ordinary way the sentences imposed on war criminals wouldbe allowed to run their course.(e) It had been reported that 200 Japanese held in British handsfor war crimes, but not yet tried, were to be handed over to theJapanese Government for trial in Japan. In view of past experienceof the trial of war criminals by defeated nations, any proposal of thiskind required careful examination.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in CP. (51) 135, subject to further examination, in the light of the Cabinefs discussion, ofthe draft answer in paragraph 14 and of draft communica-tions annexed to the memorandum.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to investigate the report that200 Japanese held for war crimes were to be handed overto the Japanese Government for trial.international labour conference,1949.(previous reference: -CM. (50) 51stConclusions,Minute 7.)6. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Minister ofLabour (CP. (51) 134 and 146) regarding the action to be taken by theUnited Kingdom Government in respect of two Conventions and oneRecommendation adopted by the International Labour Conferenceat its meeting in Geneva in 1949.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the United Kingdom Government should ratifyConvention No. 95 on the Protection of Wages, subject tothe exclusion of non-manual and domestic workers fromthe operation of Article 3-11 and 13 (2) of the Convention.(2) Agreed that the United Kingdom Government should ratifyRecommendation No. 85 on the Protection of Wages,subject to the reservations set out in paragraph 8 of CP.(51) 134.
(3) Approved the proposals in CP. (51) 146 for the preparationof legislation which would enable the United KingdomGovernment to ratify Convention No. 96 on Fee-ChargingEmployment Agencies.(4) Authorised the Minister of Labour to notify these conclusions to Parliament in a White Paper in the terms of the draft annexed to CP. (51) 134.Cabinet Office, S.WA,list May, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
