<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/19/0 images: 340-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY  OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1951SECRETCM. (51)40th conclusions copy No. 4 cabinet 40 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 5th June, 1951, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The Right Hon. Alfred Robens, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 1-3).The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C., M.P., President of theBoard of Trade.The Right Hon. Richard Stokes, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The following were also present:The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 2).The Right Hon. Maurice Webb, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 5).The Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,K.C., M.P., Attorney-General (items-5).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 1).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 2).The Right Hon. H. A. Marquand, M.P.,Minister of Health (Items 5-6).The Right Hon. John Wheatley, K.C.,M.P., Lord Advocate (Items 4-5).Mr. E. A. J. Davies, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (Item 3).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.40768-13
CABINET 40 (51)contents minute no. Subject page 1     Parliament   ... ..................      57Business in the House of Commons.2      Integration of French and German Coal and Steel Industries      573     Germany......................    ...      58Soviet Proposal for a Meeting of Foreign Ministers.4     North Atlantic Treaty   ...............      ...      60Immunities of the Organisation.5     Resale Price Maintenance       ...      .........      ...      606     Equal Pay:..............      .........      62Discussion at International Labour Conference, 1951.
Parliament.Business in theHouse ofCommons.Integration ofFrench andGerman coal and steel industries.(previous reference :CM. (51) 28thConclusions,Minute 2.)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.2. The Cabinet had before them two memoranda (CP. (51) 147and 152) regarding the Schuman Treaty. In the first of these theForeign Secretary renewed the proposal, which he had put to theCabinet on 16th April, that Allied controls over the German coal and steel industries should be abandoned as soon as practicable afterthe Schuman Treaty came into operation. The second was a note bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer covering a report by the EconomicSteering Committee on the reply to be given to the suggestion of theFrench Prime Minister that the United Kingdom Government should discuss the Schuman Treaty before it was ratified by the Parliamentsof the six signatory Powers.The Cabinet first considered the question raised in CP. (51) 152.They were informed that a report would shortly be submitted by the officials who had been studying the implications of the schuman treaty on the coal and steel industries of the United Kingdom. Itwould be preferable that discussions with the French should be post-poned until Ministers had been able to consider this report. Therewas no reason why those discussions should be held before the treaty was ratified. The Cabinet agreed that in the meantime the Frenchmight be informed that the United Kingdom Government welcomed the fact that agreement had now been reached on the form of theTreaty, that they were studying its text and were most anxious toconsider how far and by what means they could be associated withthe organisation to be established under the Treaty, and that theywould be glad to discuss these questions in due course.The Cabinet then turned to discussion of the proposal in CP.(51) 147. The Foreign Secretary said that, since the Cabinefs dis-cussion on 16th April, the Schuman Treaty had been signed by the six participating Governments. It had also been ascertained, ininformal discussions between officials, that the United States Govern-ment would support the French proposal that the existing Alliedcontrols over the German coal and steel industries should be abolishedas soon as the Schuman Treaty came into operation. It it were known that the three Occupying Powers were all agreed on this point, theGerman Parliament would be more likely to ratify the Treaty.Politically, there were strong arguments against offering oppositionto the French wishes in this matter, particularly as such opposition was likely to be ineffective. Economically, we had little to gain byretaining the existing controls; in the long term the Schuman treaty was likely to be our most effective safeguard against any undueexpansion of German steel production.The Minister of Supply said that he was gravely concerned aboutthe probable effects of this proposal upon the progress of rearmamentin the United Kingdom. He had hoped that, in return for a promise to support the relaxation of Allied controls, we should be able toobtain satisfactory assurances that the Germans would supply us withthe steel scrap or semi-finished steel which we needed for the purposesof our defence programme. We had not succeeded in securingGerman scrap on this basis. But he thought that a further attempt should now be made to reach a satisfactory agreement about thesupply of semi-finished steel from Germany. When German steel production had been allowed to rise above the earlier limit of11 million tons a year, it had been understood that production above that limit would be utilised in improving the defences of western europe. According to his information, however, the Germans were using this additional production to develop their commercial markets and were exporting steel to Latin America, Finland and even Czecho-slovakia.   The French had been able to obtain assurances that)768-1b 2
Germany would supply them with all the coal and coke they needed.Could we not make a similar bargain with the Germans which wouldassure us the supplies of semi-finished steel which were urgently needed for our rearmament programme?The Minister of Fuel and Power said that, so far as concerned the German coal industry, it would probably be more difficult tosecure supplies of German coal for European countries which werenot signatories of the Schuman Treaty if the existing Allied controls over the industry were abandoned. On the other hand, he believedthat in the long run the interests of the British coal industry wouldbe best served by some form of association with the international organisation to be established under the Schuman Treaty.In discussion there was general support for the view that, before we expressed our willingness to abandon the existing Allied controls,we should make a further attempt to secure satisfactory assurances of adequate supplies of semi-finished steel from Germany. TheCabinet recognised that the control exercised through the Inter-national Authority for the Ruhr was no longer very effective, and alsothat, if the two other Occupying Powers were anxious to terminatethat control, our bargaining position with the Germans was not very strong. It might, however, be even weaker if we indicated our inten-tion to abandon all existing controls as soon as the Schuman treaty had come into operation.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the French proposal that they might discuss the schuman Treaty with the United Kingdom government before it was ratified should be answered on the lines pro-posed in paragraph 28 of the report annexed to CP.(51) 152.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to discuss with the Minister ofSupply whether a further attempt could not be made to assure ourselves of adequate supplies of semi-finished steel from Germany before we agreed in principle that theexisting Allied controls over the German coal and steel industries should be abandoned as soon as the schuman treaty came into effective operation.     &apos;Germany.Soviet Proposalfor a Meetingof foreign ministers.(previous reference :CM. (51) 37thConclusions,Minute 5.)3. The Foreign Secretary said that the Western Powers had followed the course approved by the Cabinet on 28th May and had sent to the Soviet Government identical notes proposing that the fourForeign Ministers should meet in Washington in July on the basisof any of the three agendas which had been drawn up by theirDeputies in Paris, expressing the view that it would be unprofitableto continue the Deputies&apos; discussions, and explaining why they were unable to accept the Russian proposal that the North Atlantic treaty should be included in the agenda. The Soviet Government had nowdelivered and published their reply to these notes. In this theyreaffirmed their desire for an early meeting of the four foreign ministers, urged that the Deputies should continue their attempts tosecure agreement on an agenda for the meeting, and suggested thatthe North Atlantic Treaty and the military bases of the United states should be included in that agenda as an unagreed item. They addedthat discussion of those two questions, &quot; which constituted the chiefcause of the worsening of relations between the/Soviet Union and theWestern Powers,&quot; would relieve the tension in Europe and facilitate the work of the meeting of the four Ministers.The Foreign Secretary said that it seemed to him to be impossibleto accept this Soviet proposal. The Russians were clearly trying toconstruct an agenda which would portray the Western Powers asthe aggressors. The North Atlantic Treaty was the consequence, notthe cause, of the international tension in Europe. If the four Ministers
were to discuss this Treaty, they must also discuss the earlier Sovietmoves (e.g., the activities of the Cdminform and the rearming of theSoviet satellites in Eastern Europe) which had made it necessary. TheNorth Atlantic Treaty included, however, a number of Powers whichwould not be represented at a meeting of the Council of foreign ministers, and it could not therefore be made the subject of decisions by that Council.The Foreign Secretary said that he concluded from their reply that the Soviet Government were not genuinely anxious that thefour Foreign Ministers should meet. He was inclined to think thatthe best course would be to return a reasoned answer to the Sovietnote, so as to avoid allowing it to appear that the project for a Four-Power meeting had broken down by reason only of the unwillingnessof the Western Powers to discuss the North Atlantic Treaty.The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said that the Soviet purpose in pressing for a discussion of the north atlantic Treaty was to undermine public support in the countries of western Europe for the policy of building up their defences. It was clear to him that this Soviet proposal must be rejected. In his view,the only question was whether it should be rejected in a direct replyto Moscow, or in a written reply handed to M. Gromyko in Paris,or by an oral statement at a further meeting of the Deputies in Paris.He himself favoured making an oral reply and suspending thereafter the meeting of the Deputies in Paris. The French Government, onthe other hand, would probably wish to keep the meeting of Deputiesgoing, and to defer a final reply until after the French elections.In discussion it was suggested that there would be grave disad-vantage in breaking off the Deputies&apos; discussions in Paris. If this were done, there would be great difficulty in avoiding the impression thatthe breakdown was due solely to the refusal of the Western Powersto allow the North Atlantic Treaty to be discussed by the Council ofForeign Ministers. Indeed, if we declined to allow this to be listedeven as an &quot; unagreed &quot; item on the agenda, it would be said thatwe were unwilling to allow the four Foreign Ministers even to con-sider whether they should discuss it. The Soviet Government wouldthen exploit to the full the propaganda openings for putting theWestern Powers on the defensive in respect of the North atlantic treaty. In those circumstances it would be difficult to convince publicopinion, both in this country and in Western Europe generally, thatit was the Soviet Government who were responsible for the break-down in the negotiations. The international tension, which had been relieved by the Soviet proposal for a meeting, was likely to increase.There were special reasons for prolonging the Deputies&apos; discussionsuntil after the French elections. But there were more general reasonsfor continuing those discussions; for, so long as there was some prospect of a Four-Power meeting, public anxieties would be allayed.The rejection of this Soviet note, and the adjournment of the Deputies&apos;meeting, would be taken to mean that all hope of a Ministerial meeting had been abandoned. Would it not, therefore, be better to put for-ward counter-proposals? Might we not suggest that, if the north atlantic Treaty was to be added to the agenda as an &quot; unagreed &quot;item, we must ask that the rearmament of Russia&apos;s satellites or thesituation in Yugoslavia should be similarly added? Alternatively, itmight be suggested that the North Atlantic Treaty might be placedon the agenda under the general heading of &quot; Consequences of RussianRearmament.&quot;On the other side it was argued that any concession to this latestSoviet proposal would be interpreted as a sign of weakness on thepart of the Western Powers. The Soviet note would have a damagingeffect on public opinion unless its insinuations were promptly and effectively countered in a published reply. The suggestion that theNorth Atlantic Treaty was itself the cause of the current international tension should be publicly repudiated, and disproved, without delay.From this point of view there was much to be said for sending a formal reply in writing.   If that course were followed, it would be
easier to ensure that full publicity was given to all the counter-arguments which could be deployed. This would also provide anopportunity for making clear to public opinion in this country, inpursuance of the Cabinet&apos;s decision of 28th May, the reasons whythe Western Powers were unwilling to agree that the North atlantic treaty should be discussed by the Council of Foreign Ministers. Themain purpose of the note would, however, be to repudiate the sugges-tion that the responsibility for the state of international tension rested with the Western Powers and to make it clear that if it proved impos-sible to hold a meeting of the four Foreign Ministers, the responsibilityfor the failure would rest with the Soviet Government.Later in the meeting the Cabinet were informed that the FrenchGovernment were likely to propose that the Deputies&apos; discussions inParis should be resumed and prolonged until after the French elections.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to prepare, in the light oftheir discussion, a draft of a reasoned reply to the Sovietnote, and asked the Prime Minister to consider whether this draft should be brought forward for further discussion bythe Cabinet.North Atlantic 4.   The Cabinet had before them a note by the Prime Ministertreaty. (C.P. (51) 153) reporting the results of discussions in the Lord Presi-Immunities president&apos;s Committee on the extent of the immunities to be granted to of the the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation and to persons associatedOrganisation. with it.(Previous . It was the general view of Ministers that it would be necessaryReference: to grant the wider immunities on which the Foreign Secretary believedCM. (51) 23rd that agreement could be reached with the other member States. this conclusions, should, however, be regarded as an exceptional measure, concededMinute 5.) because of the importance&quot; of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he could not acceptthe proposal, made in paragraph 10 of the memorandum annexed to CP. (51) 153, that the Government should in certain circumstancespay compensation to wronged individuals. The emphasis should beplaced on inducing the member State concerned to waive immunityor to pay compensation.The Cabinet Agreed that the wider immunities indicated in paragraph of the memorandum annexed to CP. (5.1) 153 should be conceded in respect of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisa-tion, subject to the administrative safeguards outlined in(i) to (iv) of paragraph 10 of that paper and to the reserva-tion made by the Chancellor of the Exchequer regarding thepayment of compensation.Resale price maintenance.(previous reference:CM. (51) 14thConclusions,Minute 6.)5. On 15th February the Cabinet had invited the President ofthe Board of Trade to prepare a White Paper explaining the Govern-menfs proposals for restricting resale price maintenance. They now had before them a memorandum by the President of the Board ofTrade (CP. (51) 149) covering the draft of such a White Paper.The President of the Board of Trade said that he did not believethat legislation directed against individual and collective measures ofresale price maintenance would in present circumstances secure any appreciable reduction in the cost of living. Under certain conditions the prohibition of resale price maintenance would have enabled thelarge chain stores to undercut the small shopkeepers and eventually to put them out of business, but many consumer goods were at presentscarce and were allocated among retailers in a way which prevented
full competition from operating. Had he been approaching thesubject afresh, without regard to decisions already taken by theCabinet, he would have preferred to rely on an overhaul of the monopolies Commission, a prohibition of collective (but not indi-vidual) resale price maintenance, and severe measures against devicessuch as stock-lists and boycotts. Anti-boycott legislation could havebeen directed, not only at measures taken against price cutters, butalso against the restriction of supplies and the difficulties placed inthe way of entry into trades. Anti-boycott legislation would be more easily justified and more easily enforced than the rather complicatedmeasure which would be required to deal with individual and collec-tive resale price maintenance.The Minister of Local Government said that the draft white paper developed in a convincing fashion the case for prohibiting resale price maintenance. Legislation on the lines which the Cabinet hadalready approved would be of great value, although admittedly theimmediate effects of a prohibition of individual and collective price maintenance should not be overstressed. At a time of rising prices,a measure designed to reduce the costs of distribution would be popular. It might be useful, as an additional measure, to introduceanti-boycott legislation on the lines- suggested by the President ofthe Board of Trade.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) While the projected legislation could not be expected, inpresent circumstances, to bring about a reduction in prices, the com-petitive conditions which it would introduce would have a salutary effect on the distributive trades. In commending the government&apos;s policy emphasis should be placed on its bracing effect on the distribu-tive trades rather than on expectations of any spectacular reductionin prices.(b\ There would be strong opposition to the Governments pro-posals from manufacturers, shopkeepers and certain sections of thetrade unions; and it would be argued that the problem could be handled more effectively by reducing distributors&apos; margins. in existing conditions of full employment, the Governments proposals would be supported by the trade union movement. They would also have the support of the co-operative societies. And in a time of mounting prices the public at large would welcome measures whichpromised some alleviation of the rising cost of living.(c) There was general agreement that the White Paper shouldbe drafted in terms of &quot; resale price maintenance &quot; and should notemploy terms designed to cast opprobrium on the practice, thoughsuch terms might be useful on political platforms. There was alsogeneral agreement that the White Paper should be in the conventionalform and should not endeavour to deal with the subject in a popularway. The balance in the draft White Paper between economic argu-ments and objections to a private system of law was accepted.(d) The Attorney-General drew attention to the fact that, underparagraphs 34 and 40 of the draft White Paper, practices designedto enforce resale price maintenance would become criminal offences.Since failure to comply with an Order under the Monopolies and restrictive Practices (Enquiry and Control) Act, 1948, led to civil proceedings, the Government would be asked why criminal pro-ceedings were now proposed. It would be more difficult to collect the necessary evidence for criminal, as distinct from civil, proceedings.He suggested that, pending further consideration of the enforcementprovisions, the draft White Paper should not say more than that theGovernment proposed to make these various practices illegal. TheLord Advocate agreed that further consideration should be given tothe question of enforcement. He realised, however, that criminal proceedings were a greater deterrent than civil action. If it wasdecided to invoke the criminal law, he thought it should not beimpossible to collect the necessary evidence in appropriate cases.
(e) There was general agreement that it was not necessary tobe more explicit in the White Paper about the Governmenfs attitudetowards price fixing among retailers and discrimination. When legis-lation was being drafted, however, means of penalising discriminationshould be examined, and the question of taking wider anti-boycottmeasures on the lines outlined by the President of the Board of trade should be explored.(/) Doubt was expressed whether the White Paper should stress the Governmenfs willingness to consider special claims for exemp-tion. In particular, some Ministers considered that the public shouldbe expected to deal with price cutting, which led to a lowering of thestandard of services promised after the sale of certain goods, forinstance, in the maintenance of motor cars or wireless sets.(g) The possibility that the Government might consider means ofrestraining extremes of price cutting should not be emphasised.Ministers had hitherto taken the view that the economic disadvantages of the &quot; loss leader &quot; had been over-stressed in the report of the LloydJacob Committee, and the whole matter would require to be examined further when legislation came to be drafted.(h) A Private Membefs Motion about monopoly practices wasto be discussed in the House of Commons on 15th June. The Presi-dent of the Board of Trade, in the course of the debate, would givethe broad outlines of the Governmenfs policy regarding resale price maintenance as it would be set out in the White Paper, would refer to the intention to strengthen the Monopolies Commission and would indicate the possible value of anti-boycott legislation. While reaffirm-ing the Governmenfs intention to introduce legislation to deal withresale price maintenance, he would not commit the Government tointroduce this legislation in the following session. It would not be practicable to publish the White Paper in advance of the debate.The Cabinet (1) Subject to amendments designed to meet the points agreed in discussion, approved the draft White Paper on resale price maintenance annexed to CP. (5.1) 149, and authorised thePresident of the Board of Trade to arrange for its publication.(2) Agreed that, on the occasion of a Private Member &apos;s motion on 15th June, the President of the Board of Trade should indicate the Governmenfs policy on the lines indicated inparagraph (h) above.(3) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Law Officers, to consider whether infringementsof the proposed law about resale price maintenance shouldbe the subject of criminal or civil proceedings, the mannerin which discrimination should be handled, and the scopeof any general anti-boycott measures which might be proposed.Equal Pay.Discussion atInternationalLabour Con-ference, 1951.(previous reference :CM. (50) 35thConclusions,Minute 1.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Labour (CP. (51) 150) on the policy which the United kingdom delegation should adopt regarding equal pay proposals which wereto be discussed at the International Labour Conference later in themonth.The Minister of Labour said that, if the Cabinet approved theproposals summarised in paragraph 15 of his memorandum, it wouldnot prejudice the question when equal pay should be introduced intothe Civil Service, which was raised in the memorandum circulated bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (51) 151).-The Cabinet Approved the proposals in CP. (51) 150.Cabinet Office, S.WA,5 th June, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
