<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/8/33 images: 340-345</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i b DTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   August 1940.SECRET. Copy No.   4 2W.M. (40)221st Conclusions.BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.&apos;It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 221 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, August 7, 1940, at 12 noon.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Item 1).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma(Item 1).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Contents.minute no. Subject. &apos; page 1      The Fighting Services................    206Pay and Dependants&apos; Allowances.2      Naval, Military and Air Operations...      ...       ...       ...    207Air.Military: British Somaliland.Navy.3      Foreign Affairs ...      ...............     208German intentions.Belgium.J apan.The United States:   supply of Destroyers.[21624] &quot; b
The FightingServices.Pay and dependants&apos;Allowances.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 56thConclusions,Minute 7.)1. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (G.) (40) 209) on the recentrepresentations for relieving members of the Forces from the effects of the additional taxation on tobacco and beer, and from the higherpostal and railway charges.The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that he could not afford a series of concessions on the items in regard to which there hadbeen pressure for improvement, including family and dependants&apos;allowances. He therefore recommended the grant of an increase in pay of Qd. a day, applicable to all non-commissioned ranks in thethree Services. In announcing the concession, he would emphasise that an increase of pay was the fairest way of meeting all the claimsput forward on behalf of the Forces, since it left the soldier free to determine where the shoe pinched him most, i.e., whether on theprice of his tobacco or on the impact of the higher cost of livingon his family or dependants.The Secretary of State for War then took two distinct points :First the question of beer and tobacco which arose largely from thereturn of the B.E.F. from France, where they had enjoyed valuableconcessions. They were now mixing with the civil population, manyof whom were drawing very high wages. A new scale of wages for agricultural labourers had been introduced by government action. In some cases, soldiers and civilians were working side by side in constructing defences. Since the war substantial increaseshad also been made in Unemployment Benefit and Workmen&apos;compensation.The cost of living had risen since 1st September, 1939, by some20 per cent.The soldier&apos;s family allowance of 17s. remained unchanged.Children&apos;s allowances had been twice increased, but some of thepre-war rates had been indefensible.Taking family allowance, plus children&apos;s allowance, plus allot-ment the comparison was : September,   August,    Increase.1939. 1940.Wife and 1 childWife and 2 childrenWife and 3 childrenWife and 4 childrens.29323435s.30343639per cent.3i6under 6HiThe Secretary of State thought it would be unwise to say thatthe increase of Qd. a day covered family and dependants&apos; allowances.It would spoil the whole effect of the Chancellor&apos;s announcement.Sooner or later these allowances would have to be raised, but thatwas a matter which ought to be dealt with separately and afterdue enquiry.In discussion the following points were made :-(i) The First Lord of the Admiralty and the Secretary ofState for Air were in general agreement with theSecretary of State for War. In the case of the navy and Air Force, however, there had been little or nopressure for an increase in pay.The First Lord of the Admiralty thought it important to make it clear that the Qd. a day would bea temporary war provision, and not a permanent increasein basic rates.(ii) The Secretary of State for India thought that the Govern-ment of India would have wished to be consulted about these proposals before they were put into effect. Theywould add  350,000 or  400,000 a year to the Indianbudget, in respect of the British Army in India. If acorresponding increase had to be made in the pay of thesepoy this would cost another  800,000.
4     l      I&quot;lot)Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 219thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air.Military:british somali land.2. The Secretary of State for Air said that weather hadrestricted operations.Amongst the targets attacked on the night of the5th-6th August had been oil targets and shipyards - at Plamburgand Kiel.A Dornier 17 had been shot down over Lowestoft theprevious day.Air reconnaissance showed that Schellingwoude seaplane base,near Amsterdam, was occupied for the first time.The Secretary of State for War said that the chief militaryevent was that a strong Italian attack in three columns had developed against British Somaliland. One column was directed onZeila; a second column was directed on Berbera and had reachedHargeisa; and the third column, also directed on Berbera, had reached Oadweina.It would be politically impossible, the Secretary ofState thought, to confine the concession to troops in theUnited Kingdom. It would have to cover British sailors,soldiers and airmen wherever they were stationed. Inany case he thought the House of Commons would regard a flat increase of pay, regardless of the soldier&apos;s domesticcircumstances, as the least fair way of dealing with theproblem, unless it were made clear that the increase wasnot intended as in any sense a reply to the claim forincreased family allowances.(iii) Further discussion showed that the general view of theWar Cabinet was that the claim for an increase in family and Dependants&apos; Allowances should be dealtwith separately from the claim for a concession to meetthe effects of additional taxation on tobacco, beer, &amp;c.But it would probably be better that any increase inthese Allowances should not take place until, say, the1st October, having regard to the likelihood that thecost of living would rise over the next two months.(iv) It was suggested that on merits it might be better to grantincreased Family and Dependants&apos; Allowances and to withhold the proposed grant of 6d. a day, and to saythat members of the Fighting Services ought to makesacrifices in the same way as the civil population. Butit was felt that the disparity in pay between the Servicesand the civil population made this impracticable.The War Cabinet agreed as follows : (1) That an increase of Qd. a day should be made, as atemporary concession due to war-time conditions, in the pay of all non-commissioned ranks of the three defence services.(2) That the Chancellor of the Exchequer should announce thatthis increase would be put into effect as soon as possible.(3) That in this announcement the claim for increased Familyor Dependants&apos; Allowances should not be included among the points which this concession was intendedto meet.(4) That, if the question of Family and Dependants&apos;Allowances was raised, it should be stated that thematter was under consideration, but that its examinationwould necessarily take some time.
The Secretary of State gave particulars of our forces anddispositions.Navy. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the submarinePandora had reached Malta with base personnel and stores.The British S.S. Cape St. George had collided with the wreckof the Rad and had sunk.A U-boat had been attacked 10 miles north of Anglesey.Details were given of a number of important convoys.The War Cabinet took note of this information.Foreign Affairs.german intentions.Belgium.Japan.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 219thConclusions,Minute 4.)(previous reference:W.M. (40) 220thConclusions,Minute 6.)The UnitedStates: supplyof Destroyers.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 220thConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs gave thefollowing information : The German Military Attache at Angora had reported thatthe attack on England was due to start on the 11th August(telegram No. 918 from Angora).The Belgian Ministers of Finance and of the Colonies hoped tocome to this country immediately (telegram No. 54 from Lisbon).The latest telegram from Sir R. Craigie (No. 1488) referred toa report (not yet received) of an interview with the JapaneseMinister for Foreign Affairs. This telegram suggested, however,that the situation was easing.The Foreign Secretary added that the Japanese ambassador in London thought that he should have been told before Japanesesubjects were arrested. This was clearly impossible. The foreign secretary proposed to see the Ambassador on the following day. Hewould tell him of our intention to withdraw our garrisons from north China, and would take the line that we were not allowingourselves to be deflected from our long-term policy by recentincidents.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to a further telegram which had been received from Lord Lothian (No. 1629).An interim reply would be sent, pending further discussion withthe Prime Minister and the First Lord of the Admiralty.The War Cabinet took note of the Statement by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs.Richmond Terrace, S.W.August 7, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
