<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/81/29 images: 340-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

*(85)

rncl  ion^^

CABINET

/^CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet ./&gt; held at 10 Downing Street on

TUESDAY 15 OCTOBER 1985

at 10.30 an

PRESENT

Th^^t^on Margaret Thatcher MP &apos;O/&apos;^Exime Minister

l0rdRPresIdIntCtTt Whitelaw

The	01 the Council

coCretaryn0f1st-eoffrey Howe QC ^

^onwealth	^or Foreign and

T^RtH     rairS	^

^celior nfgel Laws  n MP .	  f ^e Exchequer

S Rt Hon q-

6cretary of1gtKeith Joseph MP ^	ate f  r Education and Science

Secretary 0f1C^ael Heseltine MP ate ^or Defence

ecretary 4iCchoUs Edwards MP The	State	for	Wales

^^tary^0^11 Fowler MP

Th~    	tate	for	Social Services

SeCr^ H  n Tom Ki

etary of * Kln8 MP

ThB    	3te	^or	Northern Ireland

SeCte^ H  n Lord y0

ary of St unS   f Oraffhan The &gt;.	ate	^or	Employment

p. Rt Hon v

faster	     *   QC MP

The Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St Marylebone Lord Chancellor

&gt; The Rt Hon Leon Brittan QC MP

^ecretary of State for Trade and Industry I

WrSt/^t Hon Douglas Hurd MP

y of State for the Home Department I

The R^wh Peter Walker MP Secre  pj^of State for Energy

The Rt Ho&amp;^p^  &gt;rge Younger MP Secretary/^! State for Scotland

The Rt Hon John Biffen MP Lord Privy Seal

The Rt Hon Norma^Te^hjJ: MP Chancellor of theT^idfiV^of Lancaster

The Rt Hon Nicholas R^f^A^MP Secretary of State for hn&amp;fevoTt

The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker

Secretary of State for the^fw^npnment

The Rt Hon John MacGregor MP Chief Secretary, Treasury


   ALSO PRESENT

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury

SECRETARIAT

Sir Robert Armstrong Mr	C L	G Mallaby	(Items	2	and	3)

Mr	A J	Langdon	(Items	1	and	4)

Mr	J H	Holroyd	(Items	2	and	3)

Mr	M J	Eland	(Items	1	and	4)

	CONTENT	S	

1.	Subject		Page

	PARLIAMENTARY affairs		1

	Statement on the (^^m^wealth Heads	of Government Meeting	1

2.	Statement on the Tea{^  r^XDispute		1

	f  Reign affairs ^tsit of Indian Prime Ministg^-v Middle East		

			2

		s.	2

	^jacking of the Italian Cruise&apos;ww	^&quot;Achille Lauro&quot;	3

3.	Nigeria ^ Belgium international Monetary Matters Immunity affairs -	\&gt; \	4 5 5

4.	Atr Service Agreement with Belgium Home affairs tsturbances at Tottenham t	%&gt;	5 6


   I AFpAlR?^%

The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House   f Commons in the period up to the prorogation of Parliament which was ^planned to take place on Wednesday 30 October.

^o   :n

   eth He*js

^^^l&amp;ME MINISTER said that she would make one statement on Monday ^	t0 cover the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting, her

the United Nations anniversary celebrations and her meeting w^th TjStTSSr^ent Reagan of the United States.

Statemenc the t f 0n Dis-Teachers&apos; lsPute

THE SECRETARY OE^SSATE FOR SCOTLAND said that it might be advantageous or him to mak&lt;/Va statement on the teachers&apos; dispute in Scotland, in the course of whicnMQi/fSHld once again set out the terms of the offer made t   the teachers tln   p^pvious August.

THE SECRETARY OF	EDUCATION AND SCIENCE said that it would not

e aPpropriate at tha^^^we for him to make a statement on the progress   f the dispute in Englimc^ura Wales. The employers, at the instigation   f the Labour, Liberal aiuK^Caal Democratic Parties&apos; majority on the Panel, had increased thei^cTtfar. The unions had rejected it. It was Possible that the forthcomi^Ej^^^Xonstruction of the membership of the anion panel - which would medn^^uced representation for the National nion of Teachers (NUT) to re&apos;^lajz&apos;Oa fall in their membership - would reak the deadlock, as the NUTwyMUose their majority on the panel. e separate settlement of the	supervision of midday meals

&quot;^ght also contribute to a soluticufj^^w: was, however, now unlikely to e Possible to introduce the planned/  erorms in teachers&apos; conditions of service that year.

the prime minister, summing up a brief ^vdcussion, said that a statement y the Secretary of State for Scotland w^ld lead to demands for a ^-roilar statement from the Secretary of State for Education and Science llch would not be appropriate at that time. The timing of statements needed further consideration.	//^\\

The Cabinet -

Invited the Secretary of State for Education&apos;^attj^w Science and the Secretary of State for Scotlan^r^jp^O^ discuss with the Lord Privy Seal and the Chief Wt^p/^ve oeed for and timing of further Ministerial statenrenM/^ on the teachers&apos; disputes in England and Wales and

Scotland.


   *FfAI ^]U&gt; !isit

Hflan

Hmister ^

2* THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Prime Minister of India, Mr Rajiv Gandhi, was making an official visit to London. Indians were prone to regard the British as still harbouring colonial attitudes and as being -^interested in India only as an export market. It was therefore ^important that Mr Gandhi should receive the best possible treatment ojjHing his visit. The Prime Minister herself had welcomed him on the    vW^ious day at London Airport, where some of the arrangements had been X^STji^Vhan adequate. She hoped that members of the Cabinet would take with him when he arrived at 10 Downing Street after the meeting &gt;bin6t that morning.

*n a bj^Ediscussion, it was noted that the arrival lounge for importajjS^Tfsitors at London Airport South Side was inadequate and ought to be re^l/ap^. When this had been considered in the past, it had not been found^ossible within the constraints upon public expenditure to meet the v  &amp;y high cost of replacing the arrival lounge.

The Cabinet -

1. Invited^h|  -&amp;ficretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Awau\s and the Secretary of State for Transport to cKgfWdV the question of replacing the arrival lounge f^^towjrtant visitors at London Airport South Side.	4%^

Middie p

East

lrfVi0us

Cc(85)nC2e:

&lt;  ncls    h MinuteS;  ns&gt;

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH S^^MiRY said that, as announced by the Prime Minister in Jordan on 20&apos;Se^iemiber, he had planned to meet a joint Jordanian/Palestinian delegation ofl^^^\October. The delegation was to have consisted of the Deputy PrimJ-&apos;Mijp^er and Foreign Minister of Jordan and Bishop Khouri and Mr Moh  *lecM  L lhem of the Palestinian Liberation Organisation (PLO). The B&lt;    Lejh Government had received from the Jordanian Prime Minister plain, ex^rt5  &amp;^*and textual assurances that the delegation would publicly accept Univ^^^Nations Security Council Resolutions Numbers 242 and 338, renounchWiolence and terrorism and accept Israel&apos;s right to exist. This had been a vital component in the arrangements for the visit. When the Palestinian members of the delegation had arrived in London, they had tried .-t2Namend the proposed text to omit any explicit reference to Israel1 s	to exist. The

British side had replied that reference to the r&apos;vgk^SS. Palestinians to self-determination must be balanced by reference tw^Jt^A/ael1 s rights.

The Palestinian members of the delegation had been rf^^^och with the top lavel of the PLO, apparently iticluding its leader, Yiry.MttX Arafat, himself. They had remained adamant in their refusal	to

mentioning Israel&apos;s right to exist in the proposed text. JJ^bBritish side had taken the view that the basis for the meeting wi&lt;&amp;%RV\ Jordanian/Palestinian delegation had ceased to exist and tn^^A    eeting therefore could not take place. The Foreign and Conuntfrf^Jth Secretary had issued a statement which made clear that the Pal&gt;ASjrurftan members of the delegation had after all been unwilling to assoc&lt;  tt//&gt; themselves with a statement, which had been agreed with the Jorda^^n^v


   members of the delegation and which contained explicit references to Israel&apos;s right to exist. This account of events had been confirmed in a Y&apos;X statement by the Jordanian Government on 14 October. The fact that even moderate members of the PLO were unwilling to acknowledge Israel&apos;s right exist showed the inherent difficulty of the quest for peace.

&apos;s&apos;   ^^\Palestinian members of the delegation had given no reason for their position. They were of course in personal danger and it might their courage had failed them at the eleventh hour. The Foreign snd/^^wonwealth Secretary had seen the two Jordanian members of the =	They had been disappointed at the frankness of his

Their concern now was to limit the damage caused by this incidetS^^tjOfting Hussein of Jordan&apos;s initiative for peace in the Middle

East- ip&gt;

THE FOREIGt^ND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that comment in the British Press of 15 October included hostile criticism, on the one hand from British supporters of Israel and on the other from those who accused the Government of givi&lt;jgN.in to United States pressure. In fact, the United States had we lcoTWdiyie British decision to receive the joint delegation at the time, and MSti/&apos;JJeX expressed other views since then. Moderate comment in the Briti^Vidress was taking the line that the Government had Been right to try to&quot;-aj}$ance matters in the Middle East.

a brief discussion,	lowing points were made -

a. The cancellation	meeting was a serious setback for

King Hussein and for	initiative. It would also cause

problems for the United	since supporters of Israel in this

country would believe mise&amp;Jcw&gt;*\ that their pressure had caused the cancellation of the mee t ingc/^taw would be encouraged to seek to apply pressure even more read^Py^a the future.

B. One historical factor relevan^co this episode was that Palestinians still blamed the Unf^^^ingdom for leaving Palestine in 1948 and considered this countryyYa/pe among those responsible for the Palestinians&apos; problems since^nen.

Ct-, . aUan &quot;a,l Ship ,AchUle P caur0&quot;

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thah^^j^ix British members   f the crew of the &quot;Achille Lauro&quot;, which had beeiY7a^jyfcked by Palestinian terrorists on 7 October, had returned A^edyVo the United lngdom. Egypt seemed to have/handled the incident	the early

stages but the decision to let the terrorists leave Eg/j^f&amp;d given rise to difficulties with the United states. The Egyptian G&lt;y^ri  ent bad Probably feared the reaction in Egypt if the hijackers had^^rtv Prosecuted there. The President of Egypt, Mr Husni MubarAt^fidd Probably known, when he ordered the deportation of the Palej^^^k errorists, that a United States citizen had been murdered on&lt;^t&gt;^f  the

Mk


   &quot;Achille Lauro&quot; during the hijacking; he had probably not known in advance of the United States plan to intercept the aircraft bearing the &gt; terrorists.

/^The British Government had welcomed the United States interception of aircraft, as a positive move in the struggle against international X^f\Torism. All the countries concerned in the incident would probably \fV*ry to reduce the damage to their mutual relations. There was an &apos;v^/W^ed risk of terrorist attacks against United States interests the incident, and possibly also against British interests.

in a	discussion, it was argued that the United States had been

iegall^iE^r^tled to apprehend the terrorists; piracy was a crime in internat&apos;p!Vm  &gt; law and states had a right to apprehend pirates wherever this was&apos;visible. The knowledge that terrorists might be brought to justice shahid act as a useful deterrent against hijacking in the future. it was a positive feature that Tunisia and Algeria had both refused to accept the Egyptian aircraft bearing the terrorists.

Ni8eria

Si  u8

gtSrs&apos;h

lnute 2	5

THE FOREIGN AND COMMS^^LTH SECRETARY said that the two engineers from Bristow Helicopters Lxm^^Nhad been sentenced by the High Court in Nigeria on 7 October to^aAaWum sentences of seven years for stealing an aircraft and seven years fo^^arispiracy, to run consecutively. An appeal had been filed. HeM  Id)i\ssued a statement expressing shock and concern and calling for expd$i*ttert^s handling of the appeal. The statement had pointed out theXm^^cations of the excessive sentences for United Kingdom/Nigerian reV^t^^s. The Minister of State, Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Mr Rifl  M|XKad repeated this point to the Nigerian Acting High CommissionerC^^AN.

The sentences of the two engineers % ilar to the sentence facing Hajor Mohammed Yusufu who had stood	Britain for the kidnap of

the Nigerian former Minister for Transp^^/The Foreign and Commonwealth Office was considering whetfvkr Nigeria was trying to Prepare for an exchange involving the two^ngineers on the one side and Major Yusufu on the other. There was conflicting evidence on this question. There had earlier been an indication t&gt;at the Nigerian leadership understood that the United Kingdom witafTcmiot entertain the rdea of a bargain and that the two engineers mus^be^airly dealt with. Subsequently, however, the Nigerian High Court hadAjneddd out the Excessive sentences on the two engineers. Most rei^wro there had been indications that the President, General Babangida, i^tWd^d to act e  iently towards the two enginners, but there had als^j^^s^l indications Pointing in other directions. The truth might be that Mo^r^ in Nigeria Was in a position to take a definite decision. It would ^r^^Skessary to consider whether there were other measures open to the Uni^^AAngdom 0r persuading the Nigerian Government to take a sensible dVe^Grah.


   ,8% 585&gt; 25tl^

cirri

THE FOREIGN and COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that, in the general Section on 13 October in Belgium, the Flemish speaking Christian ^Democratic Party of the Prime Minister, Mr Wilfried Martens, had been ^fhe victors. This was welcome news for the United Kingdom.

lnternational

0n*tary 031 Hatters

THE CH^^^xor OF THE EXCHEQUER reported on the International Monetary Fund/Wotjt^prank meetings held in Seoul on 6-9 October. These had been attended	Economic Secretary, Treasury, and the Governor of the

Bank of EnVund. The meetings had considered proposals by the United States TreaMiry Secretary for ameliorating the financial problems of least developed countries and the international debt problems of the countries of LatiivJUnerica. The proposals on the former had not made   uch progress. KwHybe latter, the United States Treasury Secretary had Proposed greater V^^&apos;oiv^ment of the World Bank, which seemed sensible, and of commercial binksYj an option which needed to be treated with more caution. Further ta^3d^5^ these ideas would be held before the international MonetaryC^ljopdyWorld Bank meetings in spring 1986.

The Cabinet -	ik

2. Took note.

^mhunIty

*FpAlRS Air q

Agr ervice &gt;6nt

h Belgium

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR	reported the successful

conclusion of a bilateral air servicMjjg^ement with the Belgian Government on terms at least as good	previously concluded with

the Government of the Netherlands. Thi3^6^,the fourth agreement concluded with a member state of the Eurto^fn Community, and he believed that agreement would be possible with furt^vpr Community countries.

The Cabinet -

Took note.


   DistUrbCj^\

n Tottenh^/

i

&apos;&lt;  ) 28a

Scions       inute 3

4.	THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE HOME DEPARTMENT reported that police inquiries into the disturbances in the Tottenham area of London the previous week were proceeding satisfactorily. Over 750 arrests had been &apos;&apos;Pade following the disturbances in Handsworth, Brixton, Liverpool and *W&gt;ttenham. The police were currently reviewing tactics and equipment

in the light of the recent experiences with such disturbances. He expected to receive a number of requests for increases in police While he believed such requests should be viewed yfe^tically, they also needed to be tested against real need. He WaV^n^ous not to lose, through an over-generous provision in response to iig^^cT^ate events, the gains in efficiency that had been made over the Past

In discu^larfpthe following points were made -

a.	rv was important that the police were provided with the resources they needed, particularly to tackle the drugs tratfic that was a cort  ributory factor in the disturbances.

b.	There V&amp;a. Jt-certain element in the disturbances which could be

dealt with onLw^tMough firm police action. It was important, however, to stsfc^Wjd^ element from growing. This was not simply a matter of increa&lt;*m^ftxpenditure in inner city areas. It was notable that Hands^S^ok Brixton and the Broadwater Farm Estate in Tottenham had all bttD^tt.ed from significant sums of public money. The problems needed to^ro^considered in a wider setting. It was, however necessary to	sober look at how that money was being

c.	There was now a very^&gt;i4jnficant problem caused by those who, from positions of secure empLQi^kt in the private sector, usually sinecures with local authoriMes^kevoted their time and energies to fermenting opposition to Go^rnm^nt policies. It was interesting in that connection t&lt;Wu&gt;fca the success of the Docklands renovation project, which was a cwjs&amp;epative project with the private sector bypassing local autnj&amp;e&apos;fcxes. It was very possible that this was a better mechanism for^hannelling public funds to areas than through local authorities that were inherently vulnerable to manipulation by extreme left wing groups.

d.	It was also important to consider edu^ti^i as an influence in the disturbances. There was growing eviden    y&lt;f  ^s&gt;olitical indoctrination in schools. Parents were ofteff^tyoafraid to complain. The Prime Minister had already askMMZUV Secretary of State for Education and Science to investigate

THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that^Wxabinet Were agreed upon the need fully to support the police in	with

these disturbances, and to be ready to meet bids for extra\^ojAc   manpower directed at real needs. The Horae Secretary was alr^VS^i touch with colleagues concerned to find ways to steer depr ive*^&apos;v/D communities away from such disturbances. The other issues ment%  tf^in fscussion should be further explored.


   The Cabinet -

Invited the Home Secretary, the Secretary of State for Education and Science, the Secretary of State for the Environment and the Secretary of State for Scotland to explore further and follow up as appropriate ^the issues raised in the course of the discussion, as ^indicated in the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up.

Cabinet Office 15 October 1985



</content>
</cab>
