<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/44/26 images: 216-221</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCDMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted, for the War Cabinet.   November 1944.SECRET.W.M. (44)155th Conclusions.Copy No.WAR CABINET 155 (44),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, 24:th November, 1944, at 11 a.m, &apos;Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.  Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,&quot;M.P.,  Secretary of  State  for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Lord   Woolton,The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Colonel   the   Right   Hon.    oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The   Right   Hon.    Sir   archibald sinclair,  Bt.,  M.P.,  Secretary ofState for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Item 4).Sir  Edward  Grigg, M.P.,  minister resident in the Middle East.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War(Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C:, M.P., Minister of Aircraft-Production.Colonel the Right Hon. J. J.Llewellin, M.P., Minister of Food(Item 4).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. W. S. Murrie.minute no.&apos; .  1 -2Contents.Subject.PalestineAustralia and New ZealandConference at Wellington.3       Conditions of Surrender4      Argentine Meat Contract[28743]Page.262262264264
Palestine. 1.   The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the(Previous Secretary of State for the Colonies (W.P. (44) 678) on the situationEeference:      in Palestine.W.M. (44) 153rd       A discussion took place, a record of which is contained in theConclusions,     Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Minute l.) The War Cabinet reached the following conclusions : (1) The fullest support must be given to the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies and to the High Commissioner forPalestine in their efforts to break up the terroristorganisations and hunt down the members of the murdergangs.(2) The balance of advantage was against any public warningat this stage that immigration would be discontinued ifoutrages did not cease.(3) The High Commissioner in Palestine should, however, beauthorised to speak to Dr. Weizmann privately on thefollowing lines : A continuance of terrorist activities would clearly lead to a position in which immigrationwould have to be suspended; he knew that thisma,tter had been under consideration by HisMajesty&apos;s Government and such a course might well have to be adopted if the outrages continued.(4) All possible steps should be taken to bring the PalestinePolice up to their authorised strength, and consideration should be given to the question whether their authorisedstrength was sufficient.(5) Special attention should be given to the question whetherthe intelligence side of the Palestine Police organisationrequired strengthening by the addition of carefullypicked expert personnel.(6) Consideration should be given to the practicability ofmaking some addition to the military forces in Palestinebecause of the effect that this would have on public confidence and because also of &apos; the importance of strengthening the High Commissioner^ hand as much aspossible in the event of further disturbances.(7) The organisation of the troops stationed from time to timein Palestine and, immediately, the Fifth Division, shouldbe so arranged as to provide mobile columns of, say,200 men, who would be available to conduct searches for arms or deal with outrages, &amp;c, as might be necessary, at short notice.(8) No systematic searches for arms should, however, at thisstage be undertaken.(9) A system of compulsory national registration should beintroduced in Palestine if that step was definitelyrecommended by the High Commissioner.AustraliaandNew Zealand.Conference atWellington.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 149thConclusions, &apos;Minute 10.)2. The War Cabinet had before them the following threememoranda dealing with questions arising out of the recent NewZealand-Australia Conference.(i) A joint memorandum by the Minister of Labour and national Service and the Secretary of State for Dominion. Affairs (W.P. (44) 676) about the suggested international conference on employment.(ii) A memorandum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (W.P. (44) 677) about the declaration published on behalf of the Australian and New Zealand Govern-ments regarding colonial administration!(iii) A joint memorandum by the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and the Secretary of State for theColonies (W.P. (44) 681) about the proposed South SeasRegional Commission.
With regard to the proposed international conference on employment, it was pointed out that the Australian Government fely strongly that more consideration should be given to the problem of. assuring full employment and of maintaining and improvingstandards of living, and that if we were to reject outright thesuggestion of a conference, the Dominion Governments might be driven into the arms of the United States. By supporting thesuggestion we should gain an opportunity for an exchange of ideason various aspects of domestic employment policies in the post-war period, and would be able to impress on the Dominion governments that, if they wanted us to help them by taking their exports, theymust be prepared to take ours..It was proposed that a telegram should be sent to the australian and New Zealand Governments in the terms set out in Annex III toW.P. (44) 676. The telegram would stress the fact that the proposed conference should be regarded as forming &quot;part of the Article VIIdiscussions, that the Governing Body of the International LabourOffice should be associated with it, that the United States Govern-ment should be sounded informally before any official approach wasmade to them, and, in particular, that there should be, in the firstplace, further discussions between ourselves and the Dominions atthe official level on the precise scope, objective and agenda of theconference.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed that a telegram in the terms set out in Annex III of w.P. (44) 676 should be sent to the Australian and New- Zealand Governments.On the question of the declaration made by the Australian andNew Zealand Governments regarding colonial administration, theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs pointed out that the telegrams from the two Governments given in Annex I of w.P. (44) 677 ignored almost entirely the point that there ought tohave been prior consultation with us before the declaration was published. The suggestion that the United Kingdom HighCommissioner at Wellington had been consulted before the statement to the Press was released and that the statement had thereafter been modified was disingenuous.In discussion, attention was drawn to the fact that conferencesat which only some of the Empire Governments were representedwere apt to be a source of embarrassment. It was also pointed outthat, if, as suggested in paragraph 5 of the telegram from theGovernment of Australia, views expressed at a Prime Ministers&apos;Conference could only be regarded as the personal opinions of thePrime Ministers concerned, this would detract greatly from thevalue of Prime Ministers&apos; Conferences.The War Cabinet-(2) Authorised the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs tosend a telegram to the Australian and New zealand governments in the terms set out in x\annex II toW.P. (44) 677.With regard to the suggested establishment of a South SeasRegional Commission, it was suggested in W.P. (44) 681 that weshould avoid committing ourselves to the scheme until the widerquestion of the international supervision and inspection of colonies had been satisfactorily settled and until the Australian and NewZealand Governments had had an opportunity of considering amemorandum which the * Secretary of State for the Colonies was preparing on the international aspects of colonial policy generally.The War Cabinet were asked to approve the despatch of a telegram(Annex III to W.P. (44) 681) to the Australian and New zealand governments informing them that, while we agreed in principle,it would be necessary to consider their proposal in its relation to
the wider question .of international co-operation in colonial policy,and, in the first instance, to approach the United StatesGovernment.The War Cabinet-(3) Agreed that a telegram should be sent to the australian and New Zealand Governments in the terms set out in annex III to W.P. (44) 681.Conditions of 3.   The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet that heSurrender. iiacj received a telegram from the President of&quot; the United States(Previous proposing that, in order to help in breaking down German morale^Reference: the Prime Minister and the President should issue a joint statementW.M. (44) 34th making it clear that we did not seek to devastate Germany or conclusions, destroy the German people but only to eliminate Nazi control.Minute 5.) The Prime Minister said that he was opposed to the issue ofsuch a declaration. Ordinary propaganda designed to undermineGerman morale should, of course, continue; but a declaration bythe heads of the two Governments was a different jnatter and would,in his view, be more likely to encourage the Germans to believethat, if they resisted stoutly enough, they would obtain a corn-promise peace. In any event, no declaration could be made withoutthe assent of Marshal Stalin. He read to the War Cabinet a draft reply to the Presidents telegram which he had prepared, giving his reasons against a declaration of the kind suggested at thepresent stage. If the War Cabinet approved, he would consult theChiefs of Staff with regard to the references in the telegram to military operations; and he might make some adjustments in the wording in consultation with the Secretary of State for&apos; ForeignAffairs.The War Cabinet-Approved the despatch to the President of the UnitedStates of the telegram prepared by the Prime Minister,subject to any amendments which he might decide to makein consultation with the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs and the Chiefs of Staff.ArgentineMeatContract.(previous reference erence:W.M. (44) 149thConclusions,Minute 11.)4.   The War Cabinet had before them (a) A Memorandum by the Paymaster-General (W.P. (44) 674).\b) A Memorandum by the Minister of Food (W.P. (44) 682).(c) Copies of telegrams exchanged between the Prime Minister,President Roosevelt and Mr. Hull on this matter.   (Notcirculated  IS cl W.P. paper.)Discussion took place on the proposal put forward by thePresident in his telegram of the 19th November that we should carry on for the present on a month-to-month basis, and should notconclude any long-term contract for the supply of Argentine meatat the present time.The War Cabinet decided the lines on which the PrimeMinister should reply to the Presidents telegram. A record ofthe discussion and conclusions reached is contained in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,24th November, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
