<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/28/41 images: 392-403</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.  December 1942.SECRET.W.M. (42)171st Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AMD key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 171(42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S,W. 1, on Monday, December 21, 1942, at 5 - 30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P.Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService,The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The following were also present:The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce, Repre-sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M:P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Items 3-7).The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.H.H. the Maharaja Jam Saheb of nawanagar, Representative of India.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Lieutenant-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. Norman Brook.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[24805]
WAR CABINET 171(42).Contents.minute no. Subject.1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....Air Operations :Home Theatre.North Africa.Malta.Cyrenaica.Naval Operations :Malta.Mediterranean.Pacific.Military Operations :French North Africa.Cyrenaica.Burma.Pacific.Russia.2      Air Policy       ....      ....Bombing of Rome.3      Jibuti    ........4      North Africa    ................5      Sr. Rodriguez VegaFacilities to visit United Kingdom.6      Prisoners of War7      China    ....................Extra-territoriality.8      Honours and Awards ....Posthumous Honours and Awards.9      Requisitioning of Accommodation ....
237W;M. 171 (42).Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (42). 168thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Home Theatre.North Africa.Malta.Cyrenaica.naval operations.Malta.Mediterranean.Paeific.MilitaryOperations.French north africa.Cyrenaica.Burma.Pacific.Russia.1. The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of thepast week.It had only been possible to bomb Germany on two nightsduring the previous week. On the night of the 17th / 18th December49 bombers had attacked targets in North-West Germany. Theintention had been that our aircraft should fly below the clouds. Itwould appear that many aircraft had not done this, and 17 had been lost. The matter was being investigated. On the previous nighta successful attack had been made by 230 bombers on Duisburg.Fighter Command on the previous day had supported a heavy attack by United States Fortresses and Liberators on Romilly. Inday attacks on the South Coast during the week the enemy had lost11 machines destroyed, 2 probably destroyed and 11 damaged. total enemy losses in the Home Theatre had been 15 aircraft destroyed,3 probably destroyed and 13 damaged. Our losses had been2 fighters, 33 bombers and 8 Coastal Command aircraft destroyed.In the attack on Romilly the United States air force had lost,6 Fortresses. The fighting had been heavy and the United Statesbombers had inflicted severe losses. The assessment Was not yetcomplete. The first claims were 45 aircraft destroyed and26 probably destroyed.Our air effort in North Africa had more than doubled duringthe previous week, whilst that of the enemy had fallen off. enemy losses had been 43 aircraft destroyed, and ours 20 destroyed and4 damaged.During a heavy night attack on Malta .7 of our aircraft hadbeen destroyed on the ground. Enemy losses for the week had been17 aircraft destroyed, 8 probably destroyed and 10 damaged. our losses had been 6 aircraft, excluding those destroyed on the ground.In Cyrenaica there had been little air opposition.Including belated reports, shipping losses for the previous week amounted to 82,000 tons.Further stores had been landed at Malta, which was nowprovisioned until the end of April.Our submarines in the Mediterranean had sunk 1 U-boat, a destroyer and 7 merchant ships. In addition, possibly 3 otherU-boats had been sunk.Enemy attempts to land reinforcements in Southern new guinea had failed.There had been little change in the positions held by our forcesin Tunisia during the previous week.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook tofurnish the Prime Minister with a detailed analysis of the tanks which were to accompany the 11th armoured division if it were sent overseas.The Prime Minister read out a telegram from general eisenhower which referred to the effect of dive-bombing attacks on some of the troops in this area.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff was requested toobtain further information from General Anderson on thismatter.The chief event of the week had been the successful turningmovement by which the New Zealand Division had got across theline of retreat of Rommel&apos;s rearguard from Agheila. In confusedfighting we had taken 500 prisoners and 30 guns and destroyed20 tanks.   Our advance forces had now reached Es Sultan.Our forces were advancing on Akyab. The operations in this area were not oh such a large scale as had been represented in thePress. ,In the Pacific theatre during the past week the Japanese had.been on the defensive.The Russian offensive in the Middle Don area reported in the newspapers that morning had great possibilities. The main attack had been on a 50-mile front with a-subsidiary attack on a 13-mile[24805]B 2
front. The enemy troops engaged consisted mainly of Italians. TheRussians had also had successes at Tuapse and in the Caucasus. Theposition on the whole Russian front appeared to be most satisfactory.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Air Policy. 2.   The War Cabinet had a discussion on certain approachesBombing of which had been made as to the conditions on which the UnitedBome. - Nations might undertake to refrain from bombing Rome.(Previous ^ record of the discussion,  and conclusions reached,  isBeference: contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet.M. (41) 98th Conclusions.Conclusions,Minute 8.) &apos;&apos;Jibuti- 3.   The War Cabinet were informed that the negotiations with(Previous the Governor of Jibuti to rally the colony to the Allied cause had reference: not been successful. General Fowkes and Mr. Hopkinson, who had.M. (42) 162nd visited the Governor, thought that the time had come when a demon-Conclusions, stration in force was necessary to bring matters to a head, since the minute 3.)        Governor and his advisers were probably awaiting an excuse toplead force majeure before giving way.   This course was also recommended by General Platt.The War Cabinet-Agreed to the course proposed, and invited the Secretaryof State for War, after consultation with the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, to arrange for the necessary instructions to be sent to General Platt.North Africa. 4.   The War Cabinet had a general discussion as to the(Previous position in French North Africa.Reference: Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theW.M. (42) 169th United States authorities were anxious to see the French Adminis-Conclusions,      tration in North Africa strengthened by an infusion of new blood.minute 1.)        There were not, however, very many strong candidates.   several members of the Fighting French movement were suitable, but had made it clear that they would not serve under Admiral Darlan.The Prime Minister doubted whether General de Gaullerealised that the French Administration in North Africa underAdmiral Darlan might develop in such a way that it would over-shadow the Fighting French movement. He thought that it was neither in the public interest nor wise on General de Gaulle&apos;s part to maintain his present aloof attitude.Reference was also made to the telegrams which had been exchanged in regard to the appointment of American and british political representatives in North Africa.The Prime Minister explained that it had been proposed that both we and the United States should send senior political repre-sentatives to North Africa who would relieve General Eisenhowerof political work. He had had in mind the appointment of a junior. Minister, who would have the title of Agent-General. president roosevelt, however, had now appointed Mr. Murphy as his personal representative; Mr. Murphy would, however, be a member, of. ; .. General Eisenhower&apos;s staff.   It was clearly difficult to appoint a.    member of His Majesty&apos;s Government to such a position, and thismatter would therefore require further consideration.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.
Sr. RodriguezYega.Facilities to visit UnitedKingdom.5. The War.Cabinet were informed that representations hadbeen made by Sir Walter Citrine on behalf of Senor RodriguezVega, formerly Secretary-General of the Spanish Workers&apos; Union,who had been persuaded to leave Spain and was now at Lisbon.Senor Vega desired to proceed eventually to Mexico, but it wassuggested that he should be allowed to come to this country in thefirst instance. He was an associate of Dr. Negrin, who was anxiousto meet him in this country. If he were allowed to come here, this fact would undoubtedly be used to our disadvantage in enemy propaganda. It was probably true that his life would be in dangerif he remained in Lisbon; but it would be preferable that we&apos;should do what we could to facilitate his journey from Lisbon to Mexicorather than enable him to travel to this country.The War Cabinet-Invited the Foreign Secretary (1) To take such steps as he could to ensure that SefiorVega was given facilities to proceed from Lisbonto Mexico at the earliest possible date.(2) To inform Sir Walter Citrine that, while HisMajesty&apos;s Government thought it undesirable inpresent circumstances that Senor Vega should visitthis country, they were using their good offices tosecure for him an early passage from Lisbon toMexico.Prisoners of(previous reference erence:W.M. (42) 168thConclusions,Minute 7.)6. The War Cabinet again discussed this matter, and decidedthat we should see what action the Germans took at Christmasbefore reaching any decision as to what further reply should be sentto the Swiss Government.Cnina&apos; 7.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the extra- Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (42) 600) about theTerritoriality. Kowloon Leased Territory. The Chinese Government were pressing(Previous that, as part of the proposed Treaty on Extra-territoriaiity, weReference:        should agree to abandon our position there.   We had maintainedW.M. (42) 162nd t-na^ tne Leased Territory was outside the scope of the Treaty, which conclusions      concerned only extra-territorial privileges in Chinese territoryMinute 7.) &apos;      proper.   The Chinese Government might find it impossible towithdraw from the position which they had taken up.   In orderthat the signature of the Treaty might not be delayed, the foreign secretary recommended, in his Memorandum, that we should statethat we were prepared to discuss the future of the Leased Territorywhen victory had been won. His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador understoodthat this solution would be acceptable to the Chinese.Points made in discussion : :(1) We might argue that, on the analogy of the bases which wehad leased to the Americans, the Chinese should not object to leasing Kowloon to us, since.it was essential for the defence of Hong Kong.(2) It was pointed out, however, that the value of Kowloon tous was. not limited to defence. Hong Kong&apos;s watersupply and airfields were op the Leased Territory, andthe town anddockyards had both spread from the island to the mainland.(3) The Prime Minister thought that in this matter we shouldV        not go beyond the line to which we had firmly adheredon other occasions, namely, that questions of territorial
Honours and 8.   On the 16th October the War Cabinet had invited the awards. Committee on the. Grant of Honours, Decorations and Medals inPosthumous Time of War to give further consideration to the possibility ofHonours and devising a scheme for extending the classes of gallantry decorationAwards. which might be awarded posthumously./T,   . The War Cabinet how had before them a Note by the SecretaryReference- (W.P. (42) 577) covering a further Report by the Committee on thisWM&amp;1?42) 145th *luestion-   The Committee recommended that, in view of the many&apos; i -... difficulties involved; there should be no extension of the presentConclusions, rMinute 5 V       practice.1 mu 6    - The Service Ministers indicated that they were in agreementwith the conclusion reached by the Committee.The War Cabinet-Took note of the Committee&apos;*s Report and decided to make no change in the existing rules regarding the posthumousaward of decorations for gallantry.Requisitioning 9.   The War Cabinet took note, with approval, of a Note by theof Lord President of the Council (W.P. (42) 589) setting out the accommodation, procedure to be followed by Departments having occasion &quot; to(Previous requisition buildings.Eeferenee:W.M. (42) 54th. . ...Conclusions.), Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,December 21, 1942.adjustment could not be considered now and must be lef!to be raised at the Peace Conference.   If necessary, I might be added that we felt this principle should hiapplied in the case Of KoWloon, even though it wals nora territorial question in the strict sense.(4) The. Minister of Aircraft Production suggested that the!reply might be on the lines that, if the Chinese Govern-ment desired that the terms of the lease of these jterritories should be reconsidered, that, was a matterf;   which should be discussed at the Peace Conference.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the Foreign Secretary should have discretion!to send a reply to the Chinese Government on the lines offthe suggestions made at either (3) or (4) above.
MOST SECRETINCOMING MESSAGEHEADQUARTERS ETOUSA.ROUTINEReference No.2487Dated: Dec 191658ZReed. Dec 202145ZNAF 47From:ALGIERSTo:AGWAR WASHINGTONUSFOR LONDON.NAF 47Dated 1658Z,1658Z/19th December, 1942..EDITED LITERAL TEXT.Interior Addresses:   To:   AGWAR for COMBINED CHIEFS OF staff to:   us for for BRITISH CHIEFS OF STAFFSigned: EISENHOWER1.    To date one of the seemingly obvious lessons of thiscampaign is that, in general practice,we are far behind theenemy in the amounts of light flak made available to groundtroops and forward aerodromes.   This relative deficiencyshows up with particular effect because of the comparativegreenness of our troops.   Our experience to date shows thatthe dive bomber, unless through our own carlessness ithappens to encounter a most vulnerable target, has much,greater moral than material effect.   Actual personnel lossesresulting from this form of attack are quite moderate; butas a preliminary to tank and infantry advances&apos; againstcomparatively raw troops, it is quite devastating.   Our ownairplanes, attempting to operate at low altitude over enemyground forces and aerodromes, invariably encounter severeflak and a high rate of casualty.   On the other hand we havebeen far less successful in this regard   and this factcreates among ground forces an insistent demand for aso-called air umbrella.   Normally the Air Force cannotprovide this and. still execute essential tasks in defeatingthe enemy fighters and long range bombers and in escortingour own bombers.2.     I recommend that these matters be given the mostearnest attention, not only in all training programs but inthe matter of devising appropriate equipment and includingit in strong percentage in all combat formations.   For staticdefense, of aerodromes and other fixed.installations the effort should be to provide a maximum of weapons with a,minimum of personnel and with mounts so designed that some protection to operating personnel can be quickly providedthrough digging of pits or throwing up of revetments.   In thisconnection the anti aircraft weapon on fixed mount in halftrack is so exposed, particularly in barren, country, thatoperating personnel apparently has to become seasoned before   &apos;it will/

asoned before/it will stick by the weapon, and operate it effectively.All personnel must be indoctrinated with the conviction that the best defense against a low.flying plane is awell directed and intense volume of fire from everyavailable weapon.     It appears that when the enemy&apos;slosses- begin to mount he will be reluctant to undertake this particular&apos; type of attack according to experiencedairmen.RELAYED TO AGWAR BYSIG CEN.CirculationBrigadier JacobForg i gn S secretary.irst Sea Lord.6.&apos; Tels W/Ov0 1,1 o C o S o   ( C )o C c 0 o




</content>
</cab>
