<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/67 images: 668-681</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  June 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)172nd Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER  LOCK  ANI   IO v.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 172 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Wednesday, June 19, 1940, at 12-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.Secretary   ofAffairs.Viscount Halifax,State   for   foreign the Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff.Vice-Admiral T. SThe Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 4 to 13).General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff. .V. Phillips. Vice-Chief of Naval Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. E. P. Donaldson.Major C. R. Price, R.E.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[21433]
WAR CABINET 172 (40).minute no.13467S910111213Contents.Subject.The Air Situation     ............Air raid on Great Britain.Fighter Command.Withdrawal of fighter squadrons from France-Bomber Command.Coastal Command.Operations against Italy.The Military SituationEvacuation of B.E.F. from France.Middle East.Evacuation of stores from Brest and NarvikFrance   ...Position at Bordeaux.The French fleet.Visit of Lord Lloyd.Position of Polish troops.Czech troops.France   ...Position in the French colonies.Proposed seizure of Swedish destroyersSpainQuestion of Gibraltar.JapanAir defence of Great Britain ...Defence against invasionUnited States of AmericaShipment of arms.Channel IslandsMan-Power in the armyPage515515516516518518518519519519520520521
bill the air situation.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 171st(Conclusions,Minute 1.)Air raid on great Britain.fighter command.Withdrawal offightersquadrons from france.bomber command.coastal command.operations against Italy.1. The Chief of the Air Staff said that an air raid had beencarried out during the previous night by about 120 aircraft. bombs had been dropped near Chatham and Sheerness and Canvey Island;at Cambridge, near a number of aerodromes in East Anglia, King&apos;sLynn, and Lincolnshire, and elsewhere. Very little damage hadbeen caused. An oil fire, lasting two hours, had been started atCanvey Island. Eight houses in a row had been destroyed atCambridge. Casualties so far reported were 9 killed in Cambridge,and a few persons wounded elsewhere. Enemy losses were 5 aircraftconfirmed, and 7 unconfirmed. These included one, or possibly two,aircraft shot down by anti-aircraft guns. The rest had been broughtMown by our fighter aircraft. We had lost 3 fighters, but one ofthe pilots had escaped by parachute.There was some speculation as to the object of this raid, which seemed to have been carried out in a rather purposeless and half-hearted way, having regard to the size of the force engaged.Th Prime Minister hoped that a careful watch would be kept onthe expenditure of A.A. ammunition.The Chief of the Air Staff undertook to impress this point onthe Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief, Fighter Command.Continuing, the Chief of the Air Staff said that two of our fighters escorting a bomber operation over France had been shot down.   One or more enemy aircraft had been shot down.Three of the five fighter squadrons in France had returned tothis country from France; the other two had been withdrawn to theChannel Islands.A number of bomber operations had been carried out on theprevious night. Hits had been obtained on enemy columns con-verging on Cherbourg; oil refineries, electric power stations andmarshalling yards in the Ruhr had been successfully attacked.Preliminary reports indicated considerable success in these attacks.Four of our bombers had failed to return.The Secretary of State for Air informed the War Cabinet thatour bomber losses since the outbreak of war amounted to 1 for every60 sorties. The pre-war estimate of probable losses had been1 in 21.Anti-invasion, anti-submarine and convoy escort patrols hadbeen flown in areas ranging from Western France to Norway. ports on the French, Belgian, Dutch and Norwegian coasts had also beenreconnoitred, and bombing attacks made on nor deney aerodrome.No aircraft had been lost during these operations, but no detailedreports had yet been received.Raids had been made against targets in Eritrea, where fueldumps and aerodromes had been hit. It was believed that about aircraft had been destroyed on the ground, and direct hits were also claimed on targets, hangars and wireless stations. Enemy raids had taken place at Malta, in the Sudan, and at Aden, but little or no damage had resulted from these actions. The South AfricanAir Force, operating from Kenya, had done some good work, andhad destroyed petrol dumps and some mechanical transport.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 171stConclusions,Minute 2.)Evacuation of.E.F. from france.2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff gave the followingdetails of the total numbers evacuated and landed in the UnitedKingdom up to midnight the 18th-19th June : Personnel, fit    ............      80,452Personnel, casualtiesGunsVehiclesAmmunition (tons)1,562176960150It was not certain that all evacuation from Cherbourg had beencompleted.   Further, it was known that there were many more[21433] b 2
men in the ships which had left France and were now en route forthis country.Middle East. Further details had now been received of the engagement on the(Previous Libyan frontier on the 16th June.  Of 12 enemy tanks, 11 had beenEef erence:        destroyed and one captured; 2 guns had been destroyed and 2,W.M. (40) 171st captured.  Of the 300 embussed infantry encountered, 20 to 30 had conclusions,      been killed, 20 to 30 wounded, and the remainder captured.   It had minute l.)        been reported that among the captured was an Italian General,believed to be the chief engineer of the Tenth Army.    these operations had been carried out by our armoured division, who had probably sustained only light casualties.A mechanised unit of the Sudan Defence Force&apos; had, on the17th June, carried out a series of successful raids across the frontier in the Kassala area. A native battalion had been routed, with no casualties to our troops, whose morale was very high.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Evacuation of 3.   In connection with the preceding Minute, the Chief of the stores from Imperial General Staff said that it appeared that a quantity ofBrest and valuable stores had been needlessly lost off Brest, owing to an orderNarvik. having been given that only personnel should be evacuated.   Thismatter would be made the subject of an inquiry.The Prime Minister said that the proportion of anti-aircraft guns brought off from Narvik appeared very unsatisfactory. he hoped that the War Office and the Admiralty would arrange for an informal inquiry to be carried out in both these cases, and thatdisciplinary action should be taken if any officers were found tohave failed in their duty.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.France.Position atBordeaux.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 171stConclusions,Minutes and 10.)The french fleet.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 171stConclusions,Minute 3.)Visit ofLord Lloyd.Position of polish troops.4. The Prime Minister said that he had received a telegramfrom the First Lord of the Admiralty who was at Bordeaux withthe Chief of Naval Staff, which gave a more encouraging picture of the general situation than we had been led to believe possible.Apparently, the fighting was continuing and the French Navywas in good heart. They had bombarded the Italian coast and had sunk two Italian submarines. The First Lord had been favourablyimpressed with Admiral Darlan, who was confident that the french fleet would obey him. He seemed determined to ensure that theFrench ships did not fall into the hands of the Germans. the battleship Richelieu was already on her way to Dakar and theJean Bart would be sunk if she could not be towed to England.Demolitions of oil stocks and harbour facilities would be carriedout and ships unable to put to sea would be destroyed (telegramNo. 459 from- Bordeaux).The First Lord proposed to remain at Bordeaux for the timebeing.   The Chief of Naval Staff was on his way back.The Prime Minister said that he had been approached on theprevious day by M. Monnet who had urged that another member ofthe Government should fly out to Bordeaux.The Prime Minister had agreed that Lord Lloyd should go,and the latter was on his way accompanied by M. Monnet, and amember of the French Embassy Staff. M. Corbin had strongly pressed this suggestion.The Prime Minister said that he had that morning seenGeneral Sikorski who had just returned from France. The general had told him of his experiences during his 8-10 days on the FrenchFront. The French troops had seemed paralysed in the face of theGerman onslaught, and had disappeared into houses before the advance of the German tanks. The German troops were notparticularly formidable, but the French morale seemed to be low.ft)  Coj)\j commOn^^ion    hancW fh*   FrenchCTOvcrnmcnf-     b*j    Lord    Uayd    15  -Aftactad.
Czech troops.A&quot;On the other hand the Polish troops had fought very well and hadbeen highly complimented by General Weygand, who had said thatwith a few more Polish divisions he could have stemmed the tide.Polish troops were now marching on Bordeaux and wished to.be evacuated in order to continue fighting. If in any way possiblearrangements must be made to embark them. Polish pilots had been instructed to fly any machines they could get hold of to England,and they seemed to be experiencing no difficulty in flying off with french aircraft. There was a Brigade of Poles at Brest, but hewas afraid that it was too late to get them away.The Secretary of State for War said that arrangements hadbeen put in hand at Bordeaux and Marseilles to take off any czech troops who wished to leave, but he would much prefer to embarkPolish troops. In view of the congestion at Bordeaux, however,,embarkation might prove very difficult.The Prime Minister suggested that the Foreign Office should send a telegram at once, drawing the attention of the FrenchGovernment to their responsibility for the security of Allied troopswho had been fighting on their soil. The honour of France washere at stake.Steps must also be taken to ensure the safe return to thiscountry of the Duke of Windsor.At this stage the First Sea Lord who had just returned fromBordeaux entered the Meeting, and informed the Cabinet of thelatest position. As he was about to leave he had heard reports thatthe Germans were only some 120 km. away, and as far as he could see no attempts were being made to defend it. The Governmenthad arranged a system of warning and intended to slip out on the approach of the Germans. They might wish to embark on HALS.Arethusa. The First Lord had remained, according to instructionsreceived from the British Government the previous day, and wason board H.M.S. Berkeley. Some minelaying had been reported offBordeaux, but there should be no difficulty in getting these shipsaway.Admiral Darlan had seemed very calm and determined, and during the conversations between them, he steadfastly maintained that in no circumstances would the French Fleet be surrendered.He had stated that the presence of the First Lord and First sea lord had made no difference to his resolve. It would not be possible at present, however, to send the Fleet to British ports. french troops were still fighting and, in the circumstances, the Fleet couldnot desert the country, but must remain in French waters untilFrance surrendered. Resistance had not yet ceased and marshal petain had at no time issued an order to the troops to lay down their arms (&quot; cesser le combat &quot;). Statements to this effect wereuntrue. The Richelieu had sailed for Dakar where she would be&quot; worked up,&quot; a process that could not be satisfactorily carried out at British bases. If it were found impossible to tow out theJean Bart, she would be blown up.Admiral Darlan had gone on to explain. that the FrenchGovernment had asked for an armistice because they felt that theycould not ask the French people to continue to endure the horrorsof invasion unless the terms on which peace was obtainable hadbeen found to be unacceptable. There would be time to get theFleet away, if necessary, while negotiations were being conducted.Some doubt existed at Bordeaux as to the whereabouts of theBelgian gold.The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to telegraph to the French Government as at &quot; A.&quot;(2) Invited the Admiralty to make such arrangements as were practicable to embark Polish and Czech troops at French,ports, and to bring them to this country.[21433]b 3
ProposedSeizure ofSwedishDestroyers.(previous reference:     &apos;  ,W.M. (40) 171stConclusions,&apos;Minute 4.)6. The Lord President of the Council referred to thesuggestion which had been made to the War Cabinet on the previous day, that steps should be taken to seize the four Swedish destroyersacquired from Italy which were on their way from Eire to the faroe islands. They could not reach Sweden, and it was thought thattheir intention was to proceed to Petsamo.- The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs suggested thatthis was a case in which we could very well claim to exercise theright of angary.   .The Foreign Secretory suggested that we might say that we had information that the Germans were intending to seize them if theyproceeded further.The Prime Minister said that it was of the highest importanceto us to secure possession of these destroyers. Immediate steps should be taken to see that they did not slip through our fingers,and we could consider later what explanations we should offer.The War Cabinet-Authorised   the   Admiralty   to   issue   the   necessary instructions without delay for the seizure of these Swedishdestroyers.Spain.Question of gibraltar.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 171stConclusions,Minute 5.)7. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff informed the WarCabinet that reports from Gibraltar referred to an increase in spanish movements but gave no more precise indication as to what this indicated.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew the attentionof the War Cabinet to telegram No. 365 dated the 18th June, fromSir Samuel Hoare at Madrid reporting a satisfactory conversationwith the Spanish Minister for Foreign Affairs. He had givenrepeated assurances that Franco was determined to keep out of thewar and had made no demand as to Gibraltar, though he continuedto complain of shipping delays.The Secretary of State also mentioned that he had been givingsome consideration on the previous day to the question of thePosition in theFrenchColonies.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 170thConclusions,Minute 10.)5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed theWar Cabinet that a number of telegrams had been receivedindicating that the position in the French and Belgian overseas possesions was on the whole satisfactory. It seemed likely thatthe local authorities would be willing in most cases to co-operate with us, whatever decision might be reached by the Government inFrance. He drew their attention, however, to two telegrams which showed that we needed to be careful in our actions at the presenttime so as not to offend the better French elements. TelegramNo. 461 from Sir Ronald Campbell at Bordeaux reported thatM. Charles Roux had discussed with him the communication madeto the Governor-General of Algeria by Hiss Majesty&apos;s Consul-General on instructions from London, and deplored the effect whichthese instructions had produced at a time when the FVench forcesstill held the field and it had been decided that the war should becontinued if the German terms were excessive.Telegram No. 462 DIPP reported that the French Governmentwere very indignant at the message communicated by the UnitedStates Ambassador to the effect that they would forfeit the friend-ship and goodwill of the United States if they didn&apos;t put theFrench Fleet in a place of safety before the armistice.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.
detention of a Spanish ship bound for South America, but thatthis had now been released by the decision of the Governor of gibraltar, in his opinion quite rightly., The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Japan. 8.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed theWar Cabinet that telegram No. 1032 had just been received fromHis Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Tokyo to the effect that the british military Attache had been sent for by a Japanese Military Repre-sentative and had been informed that unless we took immediate action to comply with certain Japanese demands, e.g., the closing of the Hong Kong and Burma-Chinese frontiers, and the withdrawalof British troops from Shanghai, the Japanese Military woulddeclare war. He wished to defer his comments on this telegramuntil he had had time to consider it.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Air Defence ofGreat Britain.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 131stConclusions,Minute 10.)9. The Lord Privy Seal said that he had received twocomplaints as to the state of London&apos;s anti-aircraft defences. Thefirst was that the system of detecting aircraft was not complete,as the necessary priority had not been given for the provision ofmaterial. The second was that the control of the defences was in several hands.The Secretary of State for the Home Department said that thismatter had also been raised that morning by the Minister of Labourand National Service at a Meeting of the Civil Defence Committee.The Minister had referred particularly to the Thames defences. as many of the guns were not visible, the public were not always aware of the density of the defences.The Secretary of State for Air said that the control of the anti-aircraft defences was centralised in the hands of theCommander-in-Chief, Fighter Command. It was not the case thatthe system for detecting aircraft in the Thames Estuary wasincomplete. He would arrange for a statement to be prepareddealing with the points raised.(Previous The Minister without Portfolio said that material for the reference: R.D.F. system had already been given a high priority, but he wouldW.M. (40) 110th look into the point raised by the Lord Privy Seal.Conclusions, The War Cabinet took note 0f theSe statements.Minute 9.)Defence againstInvasion.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 170thConclusions,Minute 9.)10. The Prime Minister said that he had had a long talk that morning with the Commander-in-Chief, Home Forces. It was clearthat our defences were getting stronger every day, and that theposition was, on the whole, satisfactory.Discussion ensued as to the difficulty of obtaining accurate information as to subversive activities in this country. reference was made to a case in which members of a Swedish colony hadconstructed landmarks which would be helpful to aircraft inattacking an important objective; and to a case in which twoOfficers were said to have been in correspondence with the enemy.The War Cabinet Invited the Minister of Home Security and the Secretaryof State for War to make reports on these two cases on thefollowing day.
United States ofAmerica.Shipment ofarms.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 167thConclusions,Minute 1.)11. The Prime Minister referred to the shipment of arms fromthe United States of America. It appeared that these&apos; arms hadbeen unduly concentrated in a few ships.It was explained that the loading had been carried out inaccordance with instructions given in the United States, in some instances by the French. The attention of the Admiralty had been drawn to these cases, and arrangements were in hand to providethe necessary escort.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.channel islands.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 163rdConclusions,Minute 4.)12. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChiefs of Staff recommending the adoption of a policy ofdemilitarisation of the Channel Islands as soon as the aerodromeson them are no longer required (W.P. (40) 208).The Prime Minister said that it ought to be possible, by theuse of our sea power, to prevent the invasion of the Islands by theenemy and that, if there was a chance of offering a successfulresistance, we ought not to avoid giving him battle there. It wasrepugnant now to abandon British territory which had been in the possession of the Crown since the Norman Conquest.The Vice-Chief of Naval Staff pointed out that the materialnecessary for the defence of the Islands was not available. It wasimpossible to provide the anti-aircraft guns and fighter aircraft which would be required for this purpose, without denuding theessential defences of the United Kingdom. The Islands were too far away from our shores and too near the enemy-occupied bases at brest and Cherbourg for an effective use of naval forces to preventinvasion by sea.In reply to a question, the Chief of the Air Staff explainedthat the &quot; destruction of the facilities,&quot; referred to in paragraph(iii) of the Chiefs of Staff recommendations, included the miningof the aerodromes, which would render them unusable for a period,though not permanently. It was doubtful, however, whether theselanding grounds would be of value to the enemy for an attack onthis country.The Secretary of State for the Home Department and Ministerof Home Security said that the attitude of the Island Governmentswas that they felt bound to acquiesce in the policy of abandoningactive defence, but were most anxious to organise the evacuation oftheir women and children. This was not recommended by the Chiefsof Staff, but it was doubtful whether it would be possible to continueto feed and supply the whole population. In his view, if it were decided that the Islands could not be defended, the least that wecould do would be to give the inhabitants an opportunity of leaving.All arrangements would be undertaken by the Island Governments,who would bear the cost entailed in the evacuation measures.General agreement was expressed with the view that thiscountry could not refuse to receive British subjects evacuated fromthe Islands in these circumstances.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, distastefulas the decision would be, especially as it gave the enemy an oppor-tunity of claiming that he had occupied British soil, he (the foreign secretary) could not see that the Cabinet could well reach anyconclusion other than that proposed by the Chiefs of Staff.The War Cabinet-(a) Approved recommendations (i) to (iii) and (v) set out inparagraph 3 of the Chiefs of Staff Memorandum(W.P. (40) 208).
9. V H3 t/ JMan Power ini;he Army.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 110thConclusions,Minute 7.)13. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for War on Man Power in the Army (W.P.(40) 210).The War Cabinet deferred detailed consideration of this paperuntil the following day, but invited the Secretary of State for war to proceed with the action proposed to be taken, on the assumptionthat his proposals would then be approved by the War Cabinet.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,June 19, 1940.(b) Did not approve the suggestion in recommendation (iv)that it would be unnecessary to evacuate women andchildren from the Islands.(c) Invited the Home Secretary to inform the Island Govern-ments that we would be ready to receive in the UnitedKingdom such of the inhabitants of the Channel Islandsas the Island Authorities wished to evacuate to thiscountry, under arrangements to be made and financed by them.

GOPY.Communication handed to the French Government by Lord Lloyd.Le 18 Juin 1940.1.     Le Gouvernement britarmiojue est pret a mettre ala disposition du Gouvernement francais les raoyens detransport necessaires pour evacuer vers l&apos;Afrigue duKord le maximum d&apos;hommes et de materiel.Afin d&apos;eviter tout delai nous dirigerons desmaintenant vers les ports de Bretagne et de 1&apos;Atlantiquedes navires qui pourront embarquer aussitot les troupeset le materiel.Des bateaux seront egalement a Bordeaux et aBayonne pour embarquer les personnes que le Bouvei-nementfrancais designera.2. La flotte anglaise et les forces aeriennes enMediterranee collaboreront avec la flotte et les forcesaeriennes francaises poufi la defense de l&apos;Afrique du Nord.3.     L1aviation francaise actuellement dans laMetropole ralliera les aerodromes africains, et evacuerale plus grand mombre possible de pilotes.Les avions necessaires seront mis a la dispositionde ces pilotes,  soit en provenance des Stats-Unis, soiten provenance de la Grande Bretagne.4.     L&apos;offre faite au Gouvernement precedent detransformer l&apos;alliance en une union totale est confirmee.




</content>
</cab>
