<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/2/0 images: 24-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed, for the War Cabinet.   March 1917.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 87.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, on Monday.,March 5, 1917, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG, G.C.S.I., G.O.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.The following were also present:The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (for Minutes 1 to 7).The Right Hon. the Lord Hardinge of penshurst, KG, G.C.B., G.C.S.I.,G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O.,Permanent Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 7).The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, KG.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes 1 to 8).Major-General   F.   B.Director  of  MilitaryMinutes 1 to 8).Maurice, C.B.,Operations  (for major Sir Gdthrie Smith, K.C.M.G.,Director of Artillery (for Minute 13).Lieutenant-General Sir D. Henderson,K.C.B., D.SO., Director - General ofMilitary Aeronautics (for Minute 8).Major J. L. Baird, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P.,Chairman of the Air Board (for Minute 8).Admiral Sir Cecil Btjrney, G.C.M.G.,K.C.B., Second Sea Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 1 to 7).Commodore  G. M. Paine, C.B., M.V 0.,Fifth Sea Lord (for Minute 8).The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D., M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 8to 14).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minutes 9 to 14).The Right Hon. Sir A. M. Mond, Bart.,M.P., First Commissioner of Works andPublic Buildings (for Minute 15).Mr. N. Chamberlain, Director-Generalof National Service (for Minutes9 to 12).Lieutenant - General Sir F. Ponsonby,K.C.V.O., C.B., Keeper of the PrivyPurse (for Minute 14).Mr. H. Fountain, C.M.G., Board of Trade(for Minutes 9 to 12).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Haxkey, K.C.B., Secretary.Colonel .E. D. Swinton, C.B., D.S.O., Assistant Secretary.Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.
Western Front. 1. THE Director of Military Operations reported indications(as mentioned in the latest weekly appreciation by the General Staff)that the enemy might presently continue his retirement. The objectof these retirements would appear to be to gain time, as his pre-reparations had been somewhat delayed by the recent frost.Mesopotamia. 2. The Director of Military Operations reported that GeneralMaude expected to have concentrated forces at Azazieh, and to beready for an immediate advance towards Bagdad on the 5th or6th March.It was calculated that the enemy might concentrate a maximum of 10,000 men for the immediate defence of Bagdad. The maximumforce which the enemy could concentrate in that region for sometime to come was 24,000 men, and of these a part would be taken from the forces which had been confronting the Russians.General Maude was satisfied that he could, with his existingmeans of communication, maintain 4 infantry divisions and 1 cavalrydivision at Bagdad.In reply to Lord Curzon, the Director of Military Operationsstated that the General Staff and General Maude realised thatBagdad itself was not a defensible position, and that the line to beheld eventually by the Russo-British force was north of Bagdad ;they also realised that it was politically impossible to withdraw fromBagdad.The Russian forces were already in movement, and GeneralBaratoff had by this time occupied Hamadan.The War Cabinet wished to place on record their opinionthat The recent successes in Mesopotamia reflected most favourablyon the General Staff and the Quartermaster-General&apos;department of the War Office, as well as on the localCommand.The Arab Revolt. 3. The Director of Military Operations stated that there werefurther indications of a Turkish withdrawal from, the Hedjaz.Portugal and 4. The Director of Military Operations explained that, if andGerman East when the German forces in East Africa split up into small columns,Africa the Portuguese Government might attempt to put pressure on theWar Office to deal first of all with those German columns whichshould cross the frontier into Portuguese territory. He stated thatto do this would not be sound for military reasons, and that, onaccount of the nature of the communications respectively available,we should deal with the Germans who cross into Portugueseterritory after we had dealt with those that went North. The WarCabinet decided that The Foreign Office should, in conference with the War Office,make any communication that was thought necessary ohthis subject to the Portuguese Government.The War Cabinet, on the advice of the Director of MilitaryOperations, speaking on behalf of the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff, decided that The Chief of the Imperial General Staff should authorise theGeneral Officer Commanding in German East Africa to pursue the enemy, in case of necessity,, into PortugueseEast Africa.
Prussic Acid Shells-(Cyanide ofPotassium).5. The Secretary of State for War undertook, in conjunctionwith the Minister of Munitions, to supply the War Cabinet with amemorandum explaining the present position as regards prussicacid (hydro-cyanic acid filled) shells (War Cabinet,. 48, Minute 6).German Prisonersof War Employedin the WesternZone of Operations.6. In view of telegram No. 474, dated the 2nd March, 1917,from the British Minister at The Hague (Appendix I) the WarCabinet asked The Secretary of State for War to enquire from the FrenchGovernment what information they had, and what action,if any, they were taking in regard to the statement that french prisoners of; war were employed by the enemyimmediately behind the line in France (War Cabinet, 51,Minute 13, and Appendix IV).Mercantile Losses:British, Allied, and neutral.7. The Second Sea Lord reported that the total mercantile losses of British, Allied, and neutral ships from enemy attack during themonth of February were very nearly 500,000 tons.The Air Services ofthe british expeditionary force.8. The War Cabinet took note that all necessary action on thesubject of the letter dated the 15th February, 1917, from the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief, British Expeditionary Force, to theChief of the Imperial General Staff (Appendix II) had already beentaken as the result of an enquiry by the Air Board, to whom it hadbeen referred in the first instance by the Secretary.Home Productionof Ores and RawMaterial otherthan Iron Ore.9. In reference to a memorandum by the Minister of Munitionsdated the 26th February, 1917 (Paper G.T.-89), (Appendix III), theWar Cabinet approved the following recommendations : (a.) That a branch associated with the Materials Departmentof the Ministry of Munitions be instructed to make acritical examination of the mineral and refractoryresources of the United Kingdom, and to classify andreport upon them.(&amp;.) That the Ministry be authorised to secure for this purpose the co-operation, so far as need be, of officersattached to the Geographical Survey, as well as those under the Department of the Chief Inspector of Mines.(c.) That the question of the establishment of an ImperialBureau of Mines in London, with the object of making-available all properly digested and verified information with regard to the mineral and raw material resources ofthe Empire, should be discussed with the representativesof the Dominions and India.Home Productionof Iron Ore.Foreign Labour.10. The War Cabinet took note of the action of the Minister ofMunitions for the development of home supplies of iron ore (WarCabinet, 40, Minute 17 [d) ), as set forth in a memorandum byDr. Addison, and a note by Sir Stephenson Kent, dated the22nd February, 1917 (Appendix IV). These memoranda weresupplemented by information given by Dr. Addison to the effectthat the Ministry of Munitions were trying to obtain the services,for ironmining, of some of the Welsh coalminers who were onlyworking three or four days a week ; that he had despatched aspecial mission to Italy for the purpose of securing Italian labour ;that later he might be. forced to ask the Army for the releaseof from 1,000 to 2,000 skilled ironminers ; and that he had set up an
informal Committee for the consideration of the question of iron-mining in Cumberland and Yorkshire. In regard to two districts in the Midlands, he had made arrangements for the necessary surveywork and uncovering operations.Steel. 11. In reference to the decision reached by the War Cabinet atthe Meeting held on the 30th January, 1917 (War Cabinet, 49,Minute 2), the Minister of Munitions reported that the question of reducing the approved shell programme had been discussed betweenthe Ministry of Munitions and the War Office. Whilst the supplyof the larger size of shells had been admittedly on the generousside, the expenditure of gun ammunition had been less than thatanticipated. The result was that a reserve stock of 15,000,000heavy shell, which it was expected would be accumulated bythe 1st March, had, in fact, been accumulated half-way throughFebruary. From this it was obvious that there could be someslowing down in the output of heavier shell. A scheme had therefore been worked out to limit the production for four months,giving the French at the same time a proportion of the output ofsteel as heretofore. The proposal was to restrict the allotment ofsteel for shell manufacture to 40,000 tons (30,000 tons to the Britishand 10.000 tons to the French), and to allow the whole of theremainder of the output of the shell metal to the shipbuilding-industry for the construction of mercantile marine so far as- American shipments made this possible. At the moment this contribution amounted to 2,000 tons of shell steel (equivalent toabout 3,500 tons of shipbuilding steel), which, he understood, would satisfy the present requirements of the Shipping Controller.Scrap Metal. 12. In reference to the decision reached by- the War Cabinet,at the Meeting held on the 22nd January, 1917 (War Cabinet, 40,Minute 17 (d)), the Minister of Munitions reported as follows : Thatin regard to lead and copper scrap, the Ministry of Munitions had issued orders limiting the facilities for purchase. (This did not include the issue of licences for small amounts for light work.)The Ministry had also called for a return of stocks ; had made arrangements for the collection of scrap from munition works ; had set up an organisation for the purpose of collecting and briquettingsteel scrap ; had set up an oig-organisation for dealing with brass scrapor &quot; swarf &quot;; and had installed collecting centres at Birmingham,Glasgow, and London. A Collector of Scrap Metal (Mr. A. Walker)had also been appointed to deal with other scrap than that being produced by the munition works. This official was working throughthe agency of voluntary organisations and could possibly use localauthorities.13. The War Cabinet had under consideration a memorandumby the Minister of Munitions on the purchase of arms in Brazil,dated the 27th February, 1917 (Appendix V), and came to theconclusion that it was not worth while to enter into negotiations forthe purchase of the rifles and other war material reported to be forsale.The War Cabinet therefore authorised The Minister of Munitions to make a communication in this sense to the French Minister of Munitions, adding that, inthe circumstances, His Majesty&apos;s Government did not propose to send any official to accompany M. Thomas&apos;agent to Brazil, should M. Thomas decide to send one out;. *Pbut would be glad to join in the consideration of his report&quot; when it was received.The Director of Artillery undertook, on behalf of the Master-Purchase of WarMaterial in Brazil.
General of the Ordnance, to furnish M. Thomas&apos; repre-sentative with all the information in the possession of his department, both as to the negotiations on the subjectinitiated earlier in the war, and as to the quality of thewar material.The Order of theBritish Empire.Proposed national war Museum.Motor Cars for cabinet Ministers.14. The War Cabinet had under consideration a memorandum,drawn up by the Committee appointed by His Majesty the King to frame the Statutes for the proposed Order of the British Empire(War Cabinet, 60, Minute 3, and War Cabinet, 80, Minute 9).The War Cabinet decided that -Lord Curzon and Sir George Cave should confer with thisCommittee as representatives of the War Cabinet, towhich body they should report.15. The War Cabinet approved the proposal made by the first commissioner of Works to form a National War Museum, as setforth in his memorandum dated the 27th February, 1917 (paper g.T.-83), (Appendix VI), and authorised The First Commissioner of Works, subject to the concurrence of the Admiralty, War Office, and Ministry of Munitions,to proceed with the formation of the following committee proposed by him : First Commissioner of Works (Chairman, ex officio).A Director-General.A representative of the Admiralty.,, ,,     War Office.,,     Minister of Munitions.,, ,,     Literary and Art side of the question.An Honorary Secret ary.The Secretary of the War Cabinet to put himself in com-munication with the Admiralty, War Office, and Ministry ofMunitions in reference to this subject.16. The War Cabinet, with the concurrence of the Secretary ofState for War, decided that -Members of the War Cabinet should, for the discharge of jtheirofficial duties, have the privilege of obtaining the use of motor-cars furnished from the War Office pool of cars.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.March 5, 1917.(Initialled)A. B. L.
APPENDIX I.Telegram from Sir W. Townley (The Hague), dated March 2, 1917.(No. 474.)DURING first reading of budget in Reichstag yesterday, Minister of War statedthat, as the French employed German prisoners of war immediately behind firing line,Germans were going to do same Avith French prisoners. English soldiers bulliedprisoners, and officers did not stop them, but the English generally denied this. Thetreatment in England was, however, better now, but English nevertheless madeGerman prisoners work under German fire, and reprisals of similar nature were beingtaken by Germany. It was well known that German prisoners in French ports were forced to work by the English under unfavourable conditions, therefore british prisoners would be placed in similar situations behind German front. At time of announcement of submarine warfare, British Government were informed that ifsubmarine crews taken prisoner were subjected to different treatment of otherprisoners, reprisals would be taken. Contents of your telegram No. 319 were dulycommunicated to Netherlands Government on 7th February.APPENDIX II.State oe the Air Service with the British Expeditionary Force.Letter from the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief to the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff, dated the 15th February, 1917.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff!IT appears to me necessary to bring to the notice of the War Cabinet the state ofthe Air Service in France. On the 15th January I informed the War Cabinet, at theConference in London, that this service would probably not be fully ready for an offensive by the 1st April. To-day the situation appears to be worse than I had hoped.On the 30th September, 1916, I called the attention of the Army Council tothe urgent necessity of an early increase in the number and efficiency of fightingaeroplanes, and, after some correspondence on the subject of our estimated require-ments, I was informed officially by the War Office on the 15th November, 1916, thatthe establishment of 56 squadrons was approved in principle, and 1 was furnished with a forecast of the estimated rate of supply.Since that date continual short postponements of the arrival of new squadrons,and machines for replacement, have been notified to the G.O.C., R.F.C., in France bythe Director of Air  Organisation, and I am informed that the situation is now asfollows : Promised by the 7th March. I    Probable Arrivals by the 7th March.5 New type corps squadrons.5 Replacements.11 New type fighting squadrons.2 Replacements (new type fighting    j (2 of these doubtful)squadrons). i       No replacements.3 New type corps squadrons.2 Replacements (1 doubtful).7 New type fighting squadronsThe result may be summarised as under: (1.) There will be no reserve of corps squadrons, and five squadrons which shouldhave been new type will be old type.(2.) There will be a shortage of from four to seven fighting squadrons below whatwas promised, and of seven to ten below what I asked for, and in additiontwo squadrons which should have been new type will not have been.converted from old type.
The position as regards fighting squadrons in particular is most serious. Ourfighting machines will almost certainly be inferior in number, and quite certainly inperformance, to those of the enemy. In view, therefore, of the marked increase in thenumber and efficiency of the German aeroplanes, it appears that we cannot expect to.gain supremacy in the air in April, and it is even possible that it may pass to theenemy.The seriousness of this situation cannot be over rated, and its possible effect onthe results of our operations will no doubt be fully realised by the War Cabinet.(Signed) D. HAIG, Field-Marshal,Commander-in-Ghief, British Armies in France.APPENDIX III.Development of Home Production op Various Opes and Raw Materialsother than iron ore.(Memorandum by the Minister of Munitions.)The Prime Minister,STEPS are being taken in the Ministry of Munitions to focus and give more effective shape to the efforts which have already been made in different directions todevelop, for war purposes, certain of the mineral resources of this country and ofdifferent parts of the Empire. The acuteness of the shipping position rendersadditional efforts in this direction more urgent than ever.I have dealt in a separate note with the iron-ore deposits which exist in different parts of the country, and which are immediately capable of development, with a viewnot only to avoiding a great deal of the shipment of foreign ores, but with a view torendering our large steel and iron extensions more self-supporting.In addition, we are already taking steps to promote an increased output ofzinc ore in this country and to develop the output of wolfram in Cornwall, and weare endeavouring to promote the working of some very valuable ganister deposits in durham.I may also say, with regard to other metals, such as lead, tin, copper, manganese,and the utilisation of silica rock and sand, that the Materials Department have obtainedvery valuable information and some promising offers.&apos; Whilst in many of these directions we may obtain assistance during the war for war purposes, and the projectstherefore come properly within the scope of the Ministry of Munitions, it is impossible in the majority of instances to lose sight of post-war considerations.With a view to rendering our information as complete and accurate as possible,-and for testing in a sensible and efficient manner the information which is obtained,I suggest that the Ministry of Munitions should set up a Branch associated with the materials Department, which will be instructed to make a critical examination ofthe mineral and refractory resources of the United Kingdom, and to classify them andreport upon them. There are in the service of the Ministry many men thoroughlycompetent to assist in this work, but I think it will be advisable that the Ministry ofMunitions should be authorised to secure the co-operation, so far as need be, of officersattached to the Geographical Survey as well as under the Department of the ChiefInspector of Mines.When immediate action appears to be indicated, schemes would be submitted tothe War Cabinet in cases where after-the-war considerations are particularly involved,but I think it would be a serious omission if we were to fail to make use of the presentfacilities of the Ministry of Munitions and of the experience of the staff it has gatheredtogether in^encouraging and promoting action in connection with promising schemesfor developing our Home resources.It may be reported that, with the concurrence of the Admiralty and the Board ofTrade, I have recently established a section charged with the duty of promoting thedevelopment of the shale-oil deposits in this country, and I am glad to say that in theScottish shale oil district a most valuable result has already followed from their efforts.The operations of the Ministry of Munitions have also involved the development of
different ores in various parts of the Empire, and I think it should be a subject fordiscussion at the forthcoming conference with representatives of the Dominionswhether an Imperial Bureau of Mines should not be set up in London, with a view to making available all properly digested and verified information with regard to the mineral and raw material resources of the Empire, especially as regards those minerals and raw materials which we have found to be essential for the prosecution of the War.(Signed) 0. ADDISON.February 26, 1917.APPENDIX IV.Increased Home Production oe Iron Ore.(Memorandum by the Minister of Munitions and a note by Sir&apos;Stephenson Kent, of theLabour Supply Department, Ministry of Munitions.)The Prime Minister,I HAVE further discussed the iron-ore proposals in great detail, and have anumber of tables which can be furnished, if you wish.It is estimated that we can produce in Cumberland and Lancashire an additional400,000 tons of high-grade ore per annum by obtaining the service of 2,000 skilledminers. In the Cleveland district we can produce an additional 2,000,000 tons a year of low-grade ore.   This will require the labour of about a further 4,000 skilled miners.In addition, there are a large number of districts which have been carefullysurveyed in Yorkshire, North Lincolnshire, and thereabouts which, with the provisionof additional machinery, plant, &amp;c, and say 500 men, can produce an additional 20,000tons of low-grade ore per week.There are also a number of districts similarly requiring more machinery, plant, &amp;c.,.in the Midlands, Northamptonshire, Rutland, Stafford, and neighbouring counties,,which can give an additional 30,000 tons of low-grade ore by the provision of an extra2,500 men.Knowing that we must allow a liberal discount for inexpert labour, difficulties ofmachinery, difficulties in obtaining labour, &amp;c, difficulties in transport (which are verygreat, and which will require the most determined efforts to overcome), I estimate thatwe may look to these various schemes, by the provision of from 10,000 to 12,000 men(of whom 5,000 must be expert miners and the remainder able-bodied labourers), toproduce in, say, six months from now, at the rate of an additional 400,000 tons of high-grade ore and an additional 4,000,000 tons of low-grade ore per annum. We should,of course, before that time be gradually coming up to this rate of production-You must, however, bear in mind that the low-grade ore will not release an equivalent tonnage of foreign high-grade ore nor make the same quality of iron. W&quot;ecan put it approximately at 2 to 1, so that the whole effect would be equivalent toabout 2,400,000 tons of high-grade ore, which represents approximately 200,000 tons amonth, or equivalent to a third of our last year&apos;s imports of ore.I shoiikl also tell you that the greatly increased use of low-grade ores, of which isclassed as the basic type, will mean a profound alteration in the methods of manufactureon an extensive scale. It will mean the provision of additional blast-furnaces andConverters. Further, the output from the furnaces with low-grade ore is materiallyless than that of furnaces using higher-grade ore ; but we have to face up to these difficulties. We propose to begin with the Cumberland and Cleveland districts,representing an increased output of over 2,000,000 tons of ore. The whole thingrepresents a very big proposition, but I think that, by the end of six months, the promise herein made can be realised, provided the labour is forthcoming.I should also add that the estimates which Watson provided covered the estimatedore reqxiirements for the present year, and that the reduction of imports of foreign oreat which I am aiming is a reduction on the estimates which have formed the basis of&apos;Watson&apos;s calculation.(Signed) C. ADDISONFebruary 22, 1917.
Note by Sir Stephenson Kent of the Labour Supply Department.,The Minister,With reference to the Memorandum you read to us this morning, which youpropose to address to the Prime Minister, I venture to submit that the labour demandyou set out will prove insufficient for the following reasons. This very largely increased production of iron ore will, I assume, necessitate either an increase in steelworks or in any case the proper manning of the steel extensions that are alreadycontemplated. In the latter case this labour is not provided nor in sight.. There willbe required a further considerable number of men for ganister and limestone quarrying,silica and firebricks, the erection of blast furnaces, etc., and for the steel works when in operation.To work out the number of men required for a programme of this description,must take some very considerable time. I would suggest that in your Memorandum tothe Prime Minister you make it a condition that the men of the types suitable for theoccupations I have mentioned above be released from the Colours, in the first place from the Home forces, and should that prove insufficient, in some short period, from overseas. I am convinced that if you wish production of iron ore and manufacturedsteel in some reasonable period, it is essential that we get workmen who are accustomed to such employment. At the present moment the only reinforcement of labour that wecan look forward to is useless for any such work ; it will consist of B 3 and C 3men, who will be quite incapable of undertaking work of any arduous or hot nature.(Signed) STEPHENSON KENT.February 22, 1917.APPENDIX V.Purchase op Arms in Brazil.(Note by the Minister of Munitions.)M. THOMAS has sent over an officer, Captain Ganne, with a letter to the PrimeMinister to ask whether His Majesty&apos;s Government is interested in the purchase ofcertain Brazilian armaments. On the French side the position appears to be thatM. Lafont, a Director of the Credit foncier de Bresil, has ascertained apparently fromthe release of a Brazilian Government official that certain Brazilian armaments are forsale by the Brazilian Government, although no negotiations have been carried on direct with the Minister of War.The brother of this M. Lafont is a French deputy and a member of the ArmyCommission, and through him the matter has been brought to M. Thomas&apos;s notice.M. Thomas proposes to send Captain Ganne to Brazil, but before the journey is under-taken M. Thomas wishes to know : 1. Have we sent any agent to Brazil ?2. Have we any reliable information ? .3. Are any negotiations in progress ?4. If the British Government is interested, to whom should the armaments go ifacquired ?   Should they go to Russia ?5. If to Russia, who is to negotiate ?   Will His Majesty&apos;s Government or France,or both?6. Who will pay ?7. French bankers say they have an option.   M. Thomas asks shall the Frenchnegotiate with them &apos;?8. If His Majesty&apos;s  Government is interested, will they send an officer withCaptain Ganne to Rio.The armaments consist of 400,000 new Mausers, 1908 pattern, with bayonets, and50,000,000 rounds of ammunition and components ; 180 Krupp guns, 75 slow-fire;150 ditto, quick-fire; 80 Krupp howitzers 105, and a large quantity of shells, H.E. andshrapnel. In addition, there are between 300,000-400,000 Mauser rifles which are notnew, and which are said to be in good condition.
The Position in Brazil.The Secret Intelligence report stated that one Theodore Mayer has made an offer topurchase these armaments with a deposit of 5,000L On being challenged, he produced a power of attorney signed Adolpho Pauli, German Minister, accredited to the brazilian Government, authorising Mayer to purchase on behalf of the GermanGovernment. M. Lafont, the Director of the Credit foncier, says that he has seenphotographs of the original documents. He also stated that he has obtained a writtenundertaking from a member of the Minister of War&apos;s personal staff that no steps should be taken to complete the sale to the Germans before the 15th March next, after which date the Brazilian Government are to have a free hand.The secret report states that, at a Brazilian Cabinet meeting held in August 1916,it was resolved to sell surplus war material if a suitable offer could be obtained, that aprovision was inserted in the Budget Law 1916, giving authority to the Government to dispose of unserviceable war material, and that it is supposed that under this power the Brazilian Government may act. It is thought that their financial position makes the desire for sale not improbable.Captain Ganne is waiting in London for a reply to M. Thomas&apos; letter.(Signed) C. ADDISON.February 27, 1917. There is no record of any negotiations, either by theMinistry of Munitions or by the War Office, with the Brazilian Government withregard to the purchase of arms, and we have sent no agents to Brazil.II.Letter from M. Thomas to the Prime Minister-.(No. 10865 1/M.)Dear Mr. Lloyd George, Paris February 17, 1917.I take the liberty of sending to you on my behalf Captain Ganne, in order todiscuss with you a business of which you have no doubt already some knowledge thepurchase of rifles and guns from the Brazilian Government. The business was broughtto my notice some months ago. We have in Brazil certain financiers and manufacturerswho have interested themselves in the matter. We have also here in France somedeputies and members of commissions who have often pressed on me the argument that if the arms exist in Brazil we should procure them, if not for ourselves, at least for our Allies. I wish to have my conscience clear in the matter. I propose, there-fore, to send to Brazil Captain Ganne, but before he undertakes this journey I-should like to know from you 1. Whether you have sent any agent to Brazil ?2. Whether you have obtained any precise information on this business ?3. Whether any negotiations  have   already been undertaken by the BritishGovernment ?In my opinion we should undertake the business in common, especially as any stepswe may take will probably be on behalf of our Russian or Roumanian Allies.Captain Ganne will return to France after having seen you, and we will then cometo a definite decision.I wish to thank you in advance,for the information which you may be able tosupply, and beg you to believe me,(Signed)      &apos;  ALBERT THOMAS.
APPENDIX VI.National War Museum.-Memorandum by Sir Alfred Mond% First Commissioner of Works.Prime Minister,IT has been suggested to me that it would be of great value for the future to begin collecting material for a National War Museum, which is now being done inFrance ; such material would include : 1. Naval and military trophies and specimens.2. Books, pamphlets, maps, posters, pictures dealing with the war.The collection would be formed partly by purchases from funds placed by theTreasury at the disposal of the Committee in charge of this object, and secondly bygifts from private persons.I understand that there are a number of people who are collecting various objectsrelating to the war, which fchey will probably be pleased to hand over to some permanentnational collection.I propose that a small honorary Committee should be formed, of which the first commissioner of Works should be ex officio Chairman, and which should consist also of a Director-General of the Collection, a representative of the Admiralty, a repre-sentative of the War Office, representatives of the literary and art sides, and anhonorary Secretary. I believe there would be no difficulty in obtaining gentlemen ofposition who would gladly undertake this work.The question of where the Collection can be finally housed need not be dealt with at the present time. The immediate necessity and the important matter is thecollection of the material, which can be stored, if necessary, until the end of the war.If the scheme is approved, I would siiggest that a small grant of, say, 3,O00Z. bemade by the Treasury to cover the purchases, where gifts are not available, and anyrunning expenses for secretarial and record work.(Initialled) A. M.February 27, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
