<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/2/0 images: 114-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His - Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   March 1917.SECRET. &apos;       31WAR CABINET, 101.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onThursday, March 22, 1917, at 1\15 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.! TThe Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.The Right Hon. a. Bonar Law, M.P.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, CM.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby,KG., G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Major L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Ireland. 1. THE War Cabinet, at the conclusion of the Second Meetingof the Imperial War Cabinet held at an earlier hour the same morning, had a brief discussion on Irish Policy, arising out of thefollowing amendment to be moved in the afternoon by Sir HenryDalziel, M.P., on the Second Reading of the Consolidated FundBill :-&quot; That, having regard to the state of affairs in Ireland, andthe supreme importance to the cause of the Allies of a satis-factory settlement being effected without further delay, it is, inthe opinion of this House, imperative to take such steps as maybe necessary to achieve this end.&quot;The War Cabinet, after giving careful consideration to the increasingly serious nature of the Sinn Fein movement, to the.   . political situation, the general trend of public opinion, as recentlyevidenced in the London and Provincial Press of various shades ofpolitical thought, and to the great desire of all parties andconspicuously the Labour Party to find a solution, inclined to theview that the craestioii should bo referred to a Commission.a365 -101.]
In view .of the fact that certain private negotiations for theestablishment of a Commission of a special character are in progress,it was agreed that The Leader of the House should avoid making any prematurestatement which  might stultify such negotiations, andshould postpone any announcement in Parliament in the &apos;afternoon until the last possible moment.If no issue to the above negotiations was in sight, the Leader ofthe House was authorised to confine his statement to adeclaration that the Government did not intend to leavethe question as it stood at present, but would develop thepolicy already announced by the Prime Minister, on thelines indicated by the latter, at an early date.2. The following draft Terms of Reference for the proposed commission were put forward as a basis for discussion :-&quot; To enquire and report in what respect the Home RuleAct of 1914 should be altered and modified to admit of its application to Ireland at the earliest possible date, and alsowhat form of Amending Bill should be introduced in order tocarry out the pledges that had been given both by the late andby the present Government.&quot;The precise Terms of Reference and the composition of theCommission were postponed for further consideration. In regardto the latter, the War Cabinet took cognizance of a proposal thatthe Representatives of the Dominions now in the United kingdom might be invited to participate in the work of the Commission ; theywere, however, of opinion that no decision on this point could, inview of various important considerations of Dominion politics, bereached without the full and free consent and authority of the saidRepresentatives, and they authorized the Secretary of State for theColonies to sound the Dominions&apos; Representatives on the subject.(Initialled)      D. LI. G.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,March 22, 1917.o

</content>
</cab>
