<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/2/0 images: 326-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.Of61WAR CABINET, 135.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Wednesday, May 9, 1917, at 11 *30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right  Hon. the Earl Ccrzon of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.A. Bonar Law, M.P.,the    Exchequer   (forThe Right Hon.Chancellor of minutes 1 to 8)The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.The following were also present: The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, KG.,M.P., Acting Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 8).The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby,KG., G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of Statefor War (for Minutes 1 to 8).General Sir W. JR. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (for Minutes 1 to 8).Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, KG, Minister for Defence,Union of South Africa (for minutes to 8).Major-General Sir F. C. Shaw, K.C.B.,Chief of General Staff, Home Forces.55Lieutenant-General Str C. F. N. Macready,K.C.B., KC.M.G., Adjutant-General tothe Forces.*Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B., O.M..,&apos;G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 1 to 8).The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D., M.P.,Minister Of Munitions (for Minutes -and 10).Major the Hon. Waldorf Astor, M.P.(for Minute 8).Professor Adams. *The Right Hon. R. E. Prothero, M.V.O.,M.P., President of the Board of Agri-culture and Fisheries. &quot;*The Right Hon. R. Munro, KG, M.P.,Secretary for Scotland.*Mr. R, B. Greig, Commissioner of theScottish Board of Agriculture.*&quot;The Right Hon. H. E. Duke, KG, M.P.,Chief Secretary for Ireland. *Mr.   J.  R.   Campbell,   Department  ef*Agriculture and Technical Instruction,Ireland. *The Right Hon. Sir j. Maclay, Bt.,Shipping Controller. *Sir Arthur Lee, KC.B., M.P., Director-General, Food Production Department^The. Hon. E. G. Strutt, Food production department^Mr. Neville chamberlain, Director-General of National Service.*Mr. J. Harling Turner, Director ofAgriculture Section, National service department^Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, KGB., Secretary.Fleet Paymaster P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas-Jones, Assistant Secretary.Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1917.
The Western 1. THE Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that theFront: number of prisoners taken by the British Army now exceeded 20,000,       -Prisoners. 1,500 having been taken during the last few days. 1There was some discussion on the subject of the loss of Fresnoyand Bullecourt, which, however, were described by the Chief of theImperial General Staff as minor incidents compared with thesuccesses of the last few weeks.Russia. 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that he hadreceived a telegram to the effect that peace propaganda was nowbecoming active in Moscow, and the French Socialist Deputiesconcurred that the situation there was not at all satisfactory.The Baltic Fleet. 3. The Chief of the   Imperial General Staff reported thatLieutenant-General Hanbury-Williams had telegraphed that, thoughthe state of the Russian Baltic Fleet was bad, it was thought thatthey were in a fit state to engage the enemy.The First Sea Lord stated that the Russians had begun to re-laytheir minefield in the Gulf of Riga.Reconstruction ofthe War TradeAdvisory Com-mittee.4. with  reference to War Cabinet 131, Minute 9, the WarCabinet approved the appointment of Commander Leyerton Harris,M.P., as Vice-Chairman of the War Trade Advisory Committee.Naval Losses. 5. The First Sea Lord stated that an armed yacht had been mined and sunk near Kirkwall and that that port had, in consequence,been temporarily closed.a Enemy SubmarineSunk.6. The First Sea Lord reported that the destroyer &quot;Milne&quot;had rammed and sunk the German submarine U.C. 26 about  miles from Calais, and has rescued two of the crew.Enemy Sub-marines :Publication of losses.7. The War Cabinet discussed the question of the publicationof sinkings of enemy submarines.The First Sea Lord stated that he had no objection, providedthat some time, viz., a period exceeding four weeks, was allowed toelapse between the loss and the publication of the facts.The War Cabinet decided that The facts as to the known losses should be communicated to theMembers of the House of Commons at the forthcomingSecret Session, after which the War Cabinet would consider their further publication or otherwise.Liquor Restriction 8. The  War   Cabinet   resumed   the   discussion   of   Liquorand Control. . Restriction and Control, adjourned from yesterday&apos;s Meeting (WarCabinet 134, Minute 11).The Prime Minister stated that he had met, as arranged, hisLiberal and Labour colleagues and also a representative brewer.When the policy of the Cabinet was outlined to them he foundthey were quite prepared to accept State Purchase. The fact that local Option was to accompany State Purchase weighed stronglywith them. The general opinion was against proceeding in two stages.   What was preferred was immediate action involving State
Control, the announcement of State Purchase, and the appointmentof a Finance Committee to arrange details.The Prime Minister announced that he hoped to see a numberof leading brewers.on Friday next, and to receive the last of a seriesof deputations.The War Cabinet decided that Subject to the interview with the brewers on Friday beingsatisfactory, the Government should announce next weektheir policy of State Control, State Purchase, and theappointment of a Finance Committee, the necessary administrative action being taken under the Defence of the realm Acts, and legislation postponed for the present.Engineering TradeStrikes.9. The Minister of Munitions brought to the notice of the WarCabinet the. widespread unrest in the engineering trades and the stoppage of work in certain places. He stated that the trouble wasbeing caused by quite a small section of the engineering trade, andwas said to be a protest against the new schedule of protectedoccupations, which is designed to replace the original trade cardarrangement, and that this alteration had now been accepted by allthe Trade Unions concerned.The War Cabinet decided that The whole of the facts of the case should be stated in theHouse of Commons at an early date, and that, to assist inthis being done, the Minister of Munitions should arrangefor a Private Notice Question to be put to the Chancellorof the Exchequer.agricultural programme for1918.10. The War Cabinet had a preliminary discussion on theagricultural programme for an increased production of cereals in theUnited Kingdom for the harvest of 1918, as proposed by the English,Scottish, and Irish Boards of Agriculture (G.T.-650), (Appendix),and requested Lord Milner to enquire into the question of the provision of (a.) The requisite labour;(&amp;.) The shipping requirements for the phosphate rockasked for;(c.) The horses stated to be necessary ;and inform the War Cabinet as soon as practicable as tothe result of his investigations.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,May 9, 1917.[1365-135]B 2
APPENDIX.G.T.-650. -Increased Production of Cereals, Sc., in the United Kingdom.PURSUANT to the request of the Prime Minister, a Conference of theAgricultural Departments of England and Wales, Scotland and Ireland assembled toconsider, with a view to harmonious action, the programmes which had been putforward by the Departments respectively for the year 1917-1918 (G.T.-536, 570, and 619).The Conference came to the conclusion that, at present, the data which will benecessary for determining the relation to be maintained between the provision for crops and the provision for livestock are not sufficiently - complete to warrant definiteestimates on the subject of reduction of livestock and increase of tillage. Inquiriesare being urgently prosecuted which will result in the supply of the requisite informationas to livestock, in the course of two or three weeks, and as to estimated new tillagefor next season in the course of six or eight weeks.The Conference will keep in touch with the Committees who are to provide this information and immediately the means are available will submit a further report.The estimates of 1918 tillage at present relied upon, provide for an increase inEngland and Wales of 3,000,000 acres, in Scotland of 350,000 acres, in Ireland of1,500,000 acres. These figures are the figures of increase beyond the tillage of 1916.The Conference is satisfied that it is necessary and practicable now to forecast thenecessary provision of implements, fertilisers, and labour which will be required to cope with this vast increase in our national means of food supply.1. As to implements, not less than 6,000 tractors, 6,000 tractor-ploughs, and60 complete steam ploughs ought to be provided for at once. Requisitions for smallerimplements will be presented as soon as requirements are definitely ascertained. Thenecessary census is now proceeding.The key of the situation as to implements for ploughing is found in the generousconduct of Mr. Henry Ford in placing at the disposal of the Government his designs and business machinery for the manufacture of the Ford tractor. A practical trial of theFord tractor has been carried out by the Royal Agricultural Society of England withexceedingly good results, and the Society&apos;s judges conclude their report with a recom-mendation that &quot;steps be taken to construct immediately as many of these tractors aspossible.&quot;The Conference became aware of risks which threaten this undertaking arising outof not unnatural trade anxieties of a certain section of British motor manufacturers.Any miscarriage in the provision of these implements would have disastrous consequences;It ought to be possible, and if full advantage is taken of Mr. Ford&apos;s generous proposalsit will be possible, that the delivery of these tractors at the rate of 1,000 a month shouldbe in process by the end of the summer. This can only be done, however, if theGovernment takes direct charge of the manufacture as though the objects to be providedwere vitally necessary munitions, e.g., tanks or high-explosive shells. Mr. Ford hasplaced his representative, Mr. Perry, at the disposal of the Government, and hasdespatched from the United States of America a body of experts, who are now on their way. The Conference urgently recommends that the manufacture of the Ford tractorand tractor-ploughs should be carried out under the direct control of the Ministry ofMunitions on the terms of Mr. Ford&apos;s offer, and with the assistance of his representative,Mr. Perry, as business manager. In this way, the 12,000 large implements which arestipulated for can probably be secured. It is too late for consideration of possible alternatives, none of which are at present in view.2. For the necessary supply of fertilisers, 800,000 tons of rock phosphate, 480,000tons of pyrites, 500,000 tons of basic slag, and about 250,000 tons of sulphate of ammonia appear to be necessary. The provision of these raw materials for artificialmanure will no doubt impose a very heavy strain upon the available tonnage at thedisposal of the Controller of Shipping. If the increased tillage which has been resolvedupon is to proceed, these supplies of fertilisers are indispensable. It may well be that a cargo of phosphates will be of more importance for food supply during the next ten weeks than a much higher tonnage of cereal food. Besides fertilisers, sulphate of copperfor spraying potatoes, to the amount of 14,000 tons, and of soda crystals to the amount^,,of 13,500 tons, will have to be provided.3. The labour involved in the great English programme of additional tillage raisesquestions of most serious difficulty.   The Board of Agriculture (England and Wales),
estimate that 80,000 men must be provided on the land, in addition to 40,000 already-employed. The Scottish Board estimate their additional i-equirements at 10,000.There will be work in England and Wales for 25,000 women upon the land beyond thenumber now engaged. The Conference is not able, with the. means presently at its disposal, to suggest methods of procuring this large amount of additional labour.The English Board called the attention of the Conference to difficulties which will arise if certain skilled ploughmen who have been lent for the immediate emergency bythe Army are withdrawn before the urgent work for which they were provided is reasonably complete. The Conference was satisfied that the premature withdrawalof these men would cause serious difficulty to the English farmer, and requestedMr. Prothero to communicate this view to the Secretary of State for War.The supply of horses for farm work in England and Wales, and to a smaller extent in Scotland, and perhaps Ireland, will need to be supplemented. The English Boardestimate their requirements in this respect at 60,000 additional horses, the scottish board estimate theirs at 6,000; while 2,000 may be needed in Ireland. WhetherArmy horses can to an appreciable extent supply these needs appears very doubtful.The use of the horses in question will, the Conference are satisfied, be required for thegreater part of the year.The Conference present this Interim Beport in order that the Prime Minister maybe aware of the present necessities of the tillage schemes taken as a whole. Theyhave secured the continuous joint action of a Committee of experts from the threeAgricultural Departments, who will ascertain and recommend, from time to time, thenecessary steps for the provision and distribution, according to the several requirementsof the three countries, of the supplies upon which the progress of the agricultural development now in hand will depend, and the Conference will re-assemble, from timeto time, and inform the Prime Minister of the progress of the general undertaking andof any action thought necessary for its promotion.(Signed) H. E. DUKE.Maxj 7, 1917.


</content>
</cab>
