<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/2/0 images: 342-345</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.-- ..   31WAR CABINET, 138.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, 8.W.,on tuesday, May 15, 1917, at 11.30 a.m.The Right Hon. the Earl curzon orKedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.Present:The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The Right Hon. A. Henderson, M.P.The following were also present: The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil,K.C., M.P., Acting Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Derby, K.G.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretary of State forWar.General Sir W. R. Robertson, G.C.B.,K.C.V.O., D.S.O., Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.The Right Hon. Sir E. Carson, K.C.,M.Pf, First Lord of the Admiralty (for minute 10).Admiral Sir J. R. Jellicoe, G.C.B.,O.M., G.C.V.O., First Sea Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, LL.D.,M.P., President of the Board of Educa-tion (for Minute 10).The Right Hon. H. E. Duke, K.C.,M.P., Chief Secretary for Ireland (for minute 10).Colonel W. Dally Jones, Acting Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.[1365-1381Printed for the War Cabinet   May 1917.  &apos;
The Western Front:Shortening ofBritish Line.1. THE Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that hehad heard from Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig that the French hadtaken over a small part of the British Front.&amp;The Italian Front. 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that theItalians had begun their attack well on the afternoon of the14th May, and had succeeded in taking the first system of theenemy&apos;s defences on a front of from 14,000 to 15,000 yards.Submarines. 3. The First Sea Lord made his usual report on merchantshipping losses.Destruction of 4. With reference to War Cabinet   137, Minute 8, attention was called to the fact that certain newspapers bad published theinformation that Zeppelin L. 22 had been brought down by a battle-plane, whereas other newspapers had refrained from giving any information on the means of destruction.5. The Prime Minister drew attention to the publication in the&quot;Daily Express&quot; of the 15th May, of a substantially accurateaccount of the private interview which Ministers had had withcertain brewers on Friday, the 11th May, headed by Sir GeorgeYounger.The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that notice had reached him of a question on the subject by Sir Henry Dalziel in the Houseof Commons, and asked for some indication of the terms of his reply.The War Cabinet decided that (a.) Sir George Younger should be asked who had supplied the&quot; Daily Express&quot; with this confidential information.(b.) The Prime Minister should write a letter of censure to theperson responsible for this breach of confidence.(e.) The Chancellor of the Exchequer should reply to theParliamentary question to the effect that there had been several inaccurate reports published in the newspapersof what the Government proposed to do, and that reportsof this kind, which were neither accurate nor authorised,could not be dealt with by way of question and answer.(d.) Lord Milner should see Sir George Younger and ascertain the views of the brewers as to the Government proposals at an early date.Coal for Italy. 6. With reference to War Cabinet 137, Minute 9, the PrimeMinister stated that he had arranged that the Shipping Controllershould send a telegram to Washington withdrawing the veto onthe transport of coal from the United States to Italy in UnitedStates ships.Liquor restriction and Control:Newspaper Report.PortugueseContingent for france.7. With reference to the proposed discontinuance of transport offurther Portuguese troops to France, as set forth by the First sea lord (Paper G.T.-713), the War Cabinet agreed that The matter should be referred for decision to Lord Robert Cecil,the First Sea Lord, and the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.
Man-Power:dumber of Recruitsy July 1.8. The Secretary of State for War called attention to a question by the Earl of Meath, down for answer in the House of Lords on theKith May, relating to the supply of 500,000 men to the Army by the1st July, and asked whether in making his reply he could use thefigures given in the Secret Session.It was pointed out that, owing to the opposition to thewithdrawal of the Trade Card Scheme and to labour troubles, therehad been delay in combing out, and though the numbers required would be forthcoming they would not be available by the 1st July.The  Secretary of State for War undertook to submit to thePrime Minister a draft reply on these lines.SocialistDelegations toRussia.Ireland.9. The War Cabinet bad before them a telegram, dated the10th May, from M. Miliukoff to the Russian Charge&quot; d&apos;Affaires, trans-mitting a message from the Council of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos;Deputies, in which the Governments of Great Britain. France, andItaly were asked not to withhold facilities for the visit to Russia ofrepresentatives of certain Socialist organisations (Appendix I).The Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs submitted adraft reply, which, after some amendment, was agreed to as printedin Appendix II.10. The War Cabinet proceeded to consider the question ofIreland.The discussion of the question was adjourned to a further meeting at (5 p.m.2, Whitehall Gardens, 8.W.,May 15, 1917.
APPENDIX I. .___ 6)Socialist Delegations to Russia.Telegram from M. Miliukoff to M. Nabokoff, Petrograd, May 10, 1917.THE Executive Committee of the Council of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Deputieshave asked me to forward to the Governments of Great Britain, France, and Italy thefollowing telegram : &quot;The Executive Committee express the hope that the Governments of GreatBritain, France, and Italy will not refuse to grant facilities for the journey toRussia to the delegations of the Italian Social-Democratic Party, the BritishIndependent Labour and Social-Democratic Parties, and of the Opposition group of the French Socialist Labour Party who have been invited to Petrograd. TheExecutive Committee would be grateful for a favourable reply.&quot;Please convey this message to His Majesty&apos;s Government.APPENDIX II.Proposed Telegram to Paris and Rome approved by the War Cabinet.HIS Majesty&apos;s Government have received through the Russian Embassy here a formal invitation from the Executive Committee of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos;Deputies to grant facilities for the journey to Russia of representatives of theIndependent Labour and Social Democratic parties. These parties form a smallfraction of the Socialist movement in Great Britain, and their opinions are of apacificist complexion. His Majesty&apos;s Government understand that a similar invitationhas been issued to the French/Italian Government. To reply by a direct refusal wouldirritate the Russian extremists and perhaps discourage their moderate colleagues.On the other hand, in view of the resignation of M. GutchkofF, and the reports of the growing disorders in Russia, it seems impossible to accept the invitation withoutreserve. His Majesty&apos;s Government therefore propose to reply stating that, owing tothe submarine warfare, the means of communication between Western Europe and russia are very much restricted, and only those persons can be allowed to travel inthat direction who wish to do so for business of National importance. No intimationhas yet reached His Majesty&apos;s Government from any section of the Socialist partyexpressing their desire to go to Russia. But it is impossible for His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to give a definite reply on the subject until they know what persons wishto go to Russia and what is the object of the proposed journey.His Majesty&apos;s Government would be glad to know if the French/Italian Govern-ment concur in the action proposed.

</content>
</cab>
