<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/6/20 images: 192-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majestvs government^-.-,-:-,----;--V-H-TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.0JLJL2&apos;&apos;40) 90.rTL0..S,(40)368(S)MARCH 9  1940.COPY NO. &quot;2/WAR CABINET.SCANDINAVIA: OPERATIONS IN THE face of SCANDINAVIAN NON-CO-OPERATION.Report by Chiefs of Staff Commi11ee.1. We have been considering the.....-possibility of implementing our plan to assist the Finns and secure theG-alivare ore fields,  in circumstances in which the norwegians and Swedes submit to force majeure,  and while not actively opposing us, present us with a form ofnon-co-operation.2. Before considering these implications in detail,we wish to emphasise two points:-(a) The Galivare project alone involves the useof both Narvik and Trondheim.      The port of Narvik and the railway inland are suitable for personnel and light storesbut not&apos; for the bulk of the mechanical transport, which the troops will need whenthe snow melts, and which must be passed through Trondheim.(b) The Galivare project cannot be divorced fromthat for seizing Stavanger and Bergen, where we cannot afford to see the Germans installed.In short the project involves landings not only at narvik but also at Trondheim, Bergen and Stavanger.     Aslong as we are not actively opposed, there is no doubt thatwe could land at all these places,.

3, We do not consider that the small forces atStavanger and Bergen having landed could fulfill theirroles, in the absence of Norwegian co-operation.4. A fore     landed    at Narvik, must have Scandinavianco-o-operation at least to the extent of providing rolling stock and permitting the use of the railway.     Unlessrolling stock were available and the Scandinavianswereprepared to work the railway, a force could not progressbeyond the port of Narvik, since  there i3 ,no road.Although perhaps it is unlikely that the Norwegians would oppose the landing, there are already grounds for belief that the Swedes would remove the rolling stock.59 Similarly, a force landed at Trondheim would depend on Scandinavian co-operation for the use of therailway.     There is a road, of limited capacity, fromTrondheim to the north.     But in the absence of allScandinavian co-operation the 500 miles march by roadsto Galivare could oniLy be very slow and the force could notbe expected -to reach Galivare in sufficient strength beforethe Germans.6. In the unlikely event of a small force reachingGalivare from Trondheim within a reasonable time, itcould probably go on into Finland, though it would beimmobilised until after the thaw.There are, however, two Army Corps (70,000 men)of the Swedish Army now in the Galivare - Boden area, and though they might allow us to pass through into Finlandit is inconceivable that they would allow our small force to prepare for demolition the        ore fields and.transportation facilities upon which Sweden so largelydepends for her economic existence.

7. We are still of the opinion that Swedish and norwegian co-operation is essential if we are to have any chance of forestallingthe-Germans in the Galivare-Lulea area.(Signed)    G.L.N.newall..DUDLEY POUND.EDMUND IRONSIDE.a Dine t War Room,




</content>
</cab>
