<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/14 images: 132-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1942.SECRET.W.M. (42)14th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 14 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, February 2, 1942, at 5 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary   of   State   for affairs.foreign the Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Supply.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Earle Page,Special Envoy from the Governmentof the Commonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.[23425]The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secre-tary of State for the Colonies.Captain the Right Hon. H. D. Mar-gesson, M.P., Secretary of State forWar.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade (Item 8).
The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.WAR CABINET 14 (42).Contents.M minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....      ........       ...      71Air Operations.Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations:Far East Malaya.Burma.Netherlands East Indies.Pacific Islands.Libya.Russia.2      Par East ....      ........................      72Allied Co-ordination.China.3      China    .................................      73Loans from United States and Great Britain.4      Egypt    ................................      735      Air Policy ........................      74Occupied France.6      Man-Power      ............................      74Beveridge Committee on Skilled Men in the Services.   Publica-tion of Second Report (Part IV7      Evacuation of Civil Officials from Territory in danger of enemy Occupation       ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      758      Consideration under Lease-Lend   ....      ....      ....      ....      75
1. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following information in amplification of Cabinet War Room Records Nos. 877-883.Summary of Aircraft Losses since the 26th January : In the Home Theatre we had lost 13 bombers in over500 sorties.In the Middle East we had lost 15 aircraft to 8 of theenemy. Most of our losses had occurred as a result of low-flyingattacks on ground troops.Malta had been subject to constant attacks, but they hadnot been pressed home so strongly recently.In the Far East we had lost 35 aircraft to 31 of the enemydestroyed.In Burma 26 enemy aircraft had been destroyed to 5 ofour own.The attack on the Japanese convoy in the Malacca Straits by united States and Dutch air forces had resulted in 5 transportsbeing sunk, 2 probably sunk and 10 damaged. In addition,4 Japanese cruisers and 2 destroyers had been damaged by air attack.The Prime Minister said that he had telegraphed to general wavell asking the reasons for the decision to remove a large propor-tion of our aircraft from Singapore Island to Sumatra. He would inform Sir Earle Page of the answer received.The Chief of the Air Staff undertook to inform the HomeSecretary arid the Minister of Home Security, so that he could warn the Northern Ireland Government, should the Air Staff anticipateair attacks in strength in Northern Ireland.The Chief of the Air Staff said that he was proposing to circulate a Memorandum for the consideration of the DefenceCommittee as to the policy to be pursued in regard to air attacks onthe German warships at Brest.During the previous week 36,000 tons of shipping had been lost by enemy action, and 12,000 by marine casualties.   Belated reportsLosses, might account for another 51,000 tons.December shipping losses, after including all doubtful cases,amounted to 442,000 tons: 352,000 tons by enemy action and90,000 tons by marine casualties.A U-boat ha,d been sunk off the Azores and 39 prisoners taken.The Prime Minister said that, if the Admiralty could not obtain a satisfactory answer from the United States naval authorities with regard to the scheme for convoys in the Atlantic,the matter should be reported to him.During the night the 30th-31st January our forces on the mainland of Johore, with certain exceptions which had been cutoff. had withdrawn to Singapore Island. During the previous five nights the Navy had evacuated some 2,000 men from the west coast of Johore.The garrison of Singapore amounted to the equivalent of about four divisions. Food supplies, the water supply and ammunitionstocks were considered sufficient.In answer to a question by Sir Earle Page, the Prime ministers aid that it would be for General Wavell to decide the destination of further reinforcements now on their way to Singapore.Our troops had evacuated Moulmein and were now in positionwest of the River Salween. Further reinforcements had arrived in burma during the previous week and negotiations were in progress with the Chinese with a view to their taking over certain areas.The Japanese were expanding their hold in north-west borneo and at Balikpapan.  Landings had occurred on Ambon.[23425] B 2Militarys.(42) 11thasions,considerations.
Pacific Islands.Libya.Russia.Raboul had been occupied by the Japanese. There was no news of our garrison, which consisted of one Australian battalion and afew other troops.The enemy advance from Agedabia had been in two columns,one towards Msus and the other towards Benghazi. During a heavytank engagement between the Germans and ourselves, our 2ndArmoured Brigade had suffered considerable losses. The IndianBrigade at Benghazi had successfully fought its way back throughthe German lines, with the exception of the sappers engaged on demolitions.The War Cabinet had some discussion on the arrangements forrepairing and refitting our tanks, which appeared to compare unfavourably with the enemy&apos;s organisation in this respect.The news from Russia continued to be satisfactory. In theLake Ilmen-Lake Seliger sector they had made considerable advance, and in the central sector their forces were now near toVelizh, some 50 miles north-east of Vitebsk. West of Vyasma theRussians had succeeded in pushing detachments astride the mainGerman line of withdrawal to Smolensk. South-west of Moscow theRussians had advanced to within 20 miles of Vyasma.On the Donetz front the Russians continued to make excellentprogress and had probably reached the neighbourhood of Pavlograd.This advance was most significant.In the Crimea the German claim to have recaptured Feodosiahad been confirmed.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff was invited to circulate to the War Cabinet the recent reports from Russia which had beenreceived from General Mason Macfarlane.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Far East.allied co-ordination.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 13thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Prime Minister said that he had now received a reply from the President as to the arrangements for Allied Co-ordination in the Far East. The President proposed that all political andgovernmental matters concerning New Zealand, Australia and theNetherlands East Indies should continue to be handled in London;and that military matters should be resolved in Washington. If,however, all these countries were each to be represented by three menon the joint staff considering the A.B.D.A. problems, the result would be an unwieldy body. He therefore proposed that the present organisation for the collaboration of British and United Statesstaffs should continue as at present, but that, where the Dutch,Australians and New Zealanders were concerned, the CombinedStaffs should invite their participation in the discussion of matters which involved their national interest and collaboration.The Prime Minister said that he had forwarded this communi-cation to the Prime Minister of Australia and had asked whetherthe arrangement proposed by the President was satisfactory to him.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs read a telegramfrom the Netherlands Government to the United States Governmentsetting out the reasons which, in their view, made the establishmentof a Far Eastern Council in London, rather than in Washington, amatter of vital importance to them.In discussion, the view was generally expressed that the estab-lishment of a Far Eastern Council, in London would be far more advantageous to the Netherlands, Australian and New zealand governments. The suggestion was made that, if a Far EasternCouncil were set up in London, these three Governments might also have military attaches or representatives in Washington, who mightbe consulted when Far Eastern matters were under discussion there.It would, however, be of vital importance that these military repre-sentatives should speak with the same voice as the representatives oftheir Governments in London. Otherwise confusion would ensue.
The question was raised whether the Chinese Governmentwould be invited to take part in the deliberations of the Far EasternCouncil in London, or, alternatively, of the Pacific Council in washington.The Prime Minister said that the United States Governmentwould almost certainly wish to see the Chinese aspect of Far Easternco-ordination handled in Washington.The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs to arrange forthe text of the telegram from the Netherlands Govern-ment to the United States Government to be communi-cated to the Governments of Australia and New Zealand.(2) Took note that Sir Earle Page would communicate to hisGovernment the suggestion outlined at &quot;X.&quot;China.Loans from united StatesandGreat Britain.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 13thConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the UnitedStates Government had informed us on the previous day that theywere approaching Congress for approval for a loan up to 500 million dollars to China, to be advanced at such time or times and upon such terms as were deemed to be in the interests of the U.S.A.; the news had now come in that it had been decided in Washington topresent this Resolution to Congress at once and to make a public announcement on the proposal. The Resolution was being published that day, at about 7 p.m. British time.It was uncertain to what extent the new American loan would,in fact, be drawn upon. The United States Government wereproducing the psychological effect which General Chiang Kai-shekdesired without committing themselves to any specific advances.It seemed desirable that His Majesty&apos;s Government should takeparallel action. Our contribution, while large enough to achieve the desired political effect, ought not to be equal to the United Statescontribution, in view of their much greater financial resources.This indicated a loan of say,  50,000,000. Within this limit we might advance sterling as and when required for war purposes. Itshould not constitute an unconditional cash loan.The Chancellor suggested that we should issue a communiquethat night (i.e., simultaneously with the American announcement)saying, first, that we were offering to make available to China undera lend-lease arrangement all the munitions and military equipment which it was in our power to supply, and, secondly, that we were offering to lend to China an amount up to  50 millions at such times and for such war purposes as may be agreed upon between HisMajesty&apos;s Government and the Chinese Government.The War Cabinet-Approved the issue that evening of a communique on thelines proposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer. TheForeign Secretary was invited to telegraph at the sametime to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Chungking,instructing him to convey this offer to General chiang kai-shek -shek. ;Egypt. 4   The Foreign Secretary said that the War Cabinet would(Previous have seen Cairo telegrams Nos. 441, 442 and 443, which reported a reference: political crisis in Egypt.  The Prime Minister, Hussein Sirry, wasWiM. (42) 10th obviously tired of a situation in which he was exposed to continualConclusions, pin-pricks from King Farouk.   He was about to resign, and had minute 6.) advised King FaroUk to send for Nahas.[23425]b 3
The Foreign Secretary said that he had telegraphed to Sir miles lampson (Foreign Office telegram No. 572 to Cairo) recommendinghim to establish direct communication with Nahas, if possible beforeHussein Sirry&apos;s resignation was announced, and to make it clearthat we should expect him, if he took office, to adopt an attitudefavourable to the prosecution of the war effort. While we had no intention of departing from the Treaty, every point which arosewould not be capable of being measured by the yard-stick of theTreaty signed six years previously. We should also expect Nahasto eliminate certain undesirable elements in King Farouk&apos;s *household.The Prime Minister enquired whether the advent of Nahas to power would mean a general election.The Foreign Secretary thought that Nahas might not insist upon an election if, as we anticipated, he were forming a purelyWafdist Government.The War Cabinet-Approved the Foreign Secretary&apos;s instructions to Sir miles lampson (Foreign Office telegram to Cairo, No. 572).Air Policy.OccupiedFrance.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 3rdConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The War Cabinet again had under consideration a Memo-randum by the Secretary of State for Air (W.P. (41) 260) in regardto the bombing of certain factories in occupied France which were making munitions for the enemy.The War Cabinet-Confirmed the decision that steps should now be taken to bomb these factories.Man Power.BeveridgeCommittee onSkilled Men inthe Services.Publication of second Eeport(Part I).6.   The War Cabinet had before them -A Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and NationalService (W.P. (42) 45) circulating Part I of the second reportof the Beveridge Committee on Skilled Men in the Services.A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Warreplying to certain criticisms of the Army&apos;s use of its skilled men, contained in the second report (W.P. (42) 44).A Note by the Minister of Labour and National Servicecirculating a further Memorandum by Sir William Beveridge(W.P. (42) 56).The Secretary of State for War said that he had satisfiedhimself that the two documents attached to his Memorandum weresuitable for publication, and contained the appropriate reply to the criticisms in the report of the Beveridge Committee.He did not consider himself as precluded from coming forwardlater on, if circumstances should make it necessary, with proposals that the Army should recruit the ranks of its skilled personnel from industry to a much greater extent than the Beveridge committee recommended.The Secretary of State hoped that it would be unnecessary tohave two Army debates in the House of Commons in close succession,one on the Beveridge report and the second on Army Estimates. Ifthe publication of the report could be held up until, say, the.12th February, it would be possible to deal with it when army estimates were taken on the 19th February.
Evacuation of 7.   The War Cabinet had before them a Joint MemorandumCivilian Officials by the Secretary of State for Burma and the Secretary of State for from Territory the Colonies (W.P. (42) 52). Attached to the Memorandum was ain Danger of draft telegram to the Governor of Burma. The draft proposed that,Enemy while, in general, European officials should be withdrawn when theOccupation. occupation of territory by the enemy was imminent, a limited number of officers on the administrative staff should stand fast.This course was proposed on the ground that, if all the Europeanofficers were withdrawn, we should suffer a great loss of prestige.In discussion, it was urged that, while the withdrawal of these officers would lead to some loss of prestige, this would necessarily follow our withdrawal in the face of superior enemy forces.Further, the officers left behind would almost certainly be taken prisoner and might well be subjected to humiliating treatment. No. useful purpose would, therefore, be served by their remainingbehind.It was pointed out that the withdrawal of all white officersmight lead to some difficulties with the Native staff. This, however,might be overcome if the instructions were so drafted as to ensurethat all officers in particular grades, whether European or Native,were instructed to withdraw and no discrimination was made on grounds of colour.The main purport of the telegram to the Governor of Burmashould, however, be that all European staff should be withdrawn,when they had carried out all the duties required of them, beforeenemy occupation.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Burma to modify thedraft telegram in the above sense.Consideration 8.   The   War   Cabinet   had   before   them   the   followingunder documents : Lease-Lend. ^ Memoranda bv the Minister without Portfolio, the Secre-(lrevious tary of State for India, the Chancellor of the ExchequerReference: and  fa  Secretary of  State  for  Dominion  AffairsW.M. (42) 2nd (W.P. (42) 21, 23, 25 and 32).Conclusions, (&amp;) Messages from the United States Department of State,minute li.) circulated   by   direction   of   the   Foreign   Secretary(W.P. (42) 58).(c) Telegram No. 542 from our Ambassador at Washington.(d) Telegram No. 89 from the High Commissioner in Australia,to the effect that the Commonwealth Government were likely to press for acquiescence in Article VII.Discussion turned, not on the merits of the economic policyembodied in Article VII, but on the more limited issue whether weshould sign an Agreement embodying Article VII at this juncture.The following were the main points in favour of this course : (1) The Foreign Secretary said that the Constitutional position was that the President could put his own interpretationon the Lease-Lend Act.   If, however, we did not reach the War Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Labour and National Service andthe Secretary of State for War to arrange for the publica-tion as one document, about the 12th February, of thesecond report of the Beveridge Committee together withthe War Office reply.
agreement with the President, we might have to havenegotiations with Congress.(2) He wished it to be on record that he thought that, if we didnot accept the terms now offered, we might have to agreeto much less favourable terms later on.(3) If we did not agree to the revised draft of Article VII now put forward, he feared a worsening of our relations withthe State Department.(4) Emphasis was laid on the fact that the american ambassador and Lord Halifax had consistently repre-sented to us the importance of reaching agreement onthis topic.(5) The Secretary of State for Air expressed agreement withthese views. Having regard to the reduction in our foreign investments and other adverse factors, and to the probability that our balance of payment after the war would be seriously adverse, he thought it would benecessary to ensure, by negotiation with the UnitedStates, that they would ease our difficulties by a reallysubstantial lowering of their tariffs and by other measures if we agreed to abolish Imperial Preference.At the same time, it would be well worth while to acceptthe latest draft of Article VII, if possible, with suitableinterpretations, in order to solve this difficult question and to improve the prospects of post-war economic co-operation between Great Britain and the UnitedStates.(6) The Dominions Secretary said that it should be on record that the present Governments in the Dominions wereprepared to accept the revised draft of Article VII.The Secretary of State for Air attached great importanceto the Dominions being consulted forthwith.The main arguments against the signature at this juncture ofan Agreement embodying Article VII were as follows : (i) There was no evidence that opinion in the United states was interested in the subject, or that Congress wouldnot acquiesce in whatever line the President might take on this subject.(ii) The whole position had been altered by the fact that america was now in the war. The draft had, indeed,been prepared before America had come into the war,and before the two countries had agreed to pool their resources.(iii) While there was much to be said in favour of the line ofpolicy outlined in Article VII, there was no inherentconnection between this policy and the benefits received under the Lease-Lend Act.(iv) In any case, before we entered into a commitment that wewould work towards &quot; the elimination of all forms of discriminatory treatment in international commerce andthe reduction of tariffs and other trade barriers,&quot; we ought to know what we should receive in return.(v) Objection was seen, from the Constitutional point of view,to signing an Agreement which would tie our hands on matters which members of the British commonwealth should settle among themselves. Further, signature atthis moment would be regarded by certain sections ofpublic opinion as an attempt to break up the BritishEmpire.
It seemed that the proper course would be to draft a reply onthe lines that we were ready that conversations should be started,between the two Governments at an early date on the issues ofeconomic relations between our two countries, and that we did not exclude from discussion any of the matters falling within the scopeof Article VII. At the same time, we felt that it would be inappropriate-priate that we should sign an Agreement embodying an Articledealing with these matters until such discussions had taken place.The War Cabinet Postponed decision on the main issue, and meanwhileinvited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theChancellor of the Exchequer to prepare a draft reply onthese lines, which should be submitted to the War cabinet for alternative consideration at an early Meeting.Great George Street, S.W. 1,February 2, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
