<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/27/0 images: 125-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information.CRW/023.WEEKLY REPORT ON RUSSIA. XXIII.(24 September, 1917).The situation in Russia is again full of uncertainty.     A fortnight has now passed since Kornilov launched his ultimatum, but, though the Government defeated Kornilov in a few days, it has not been able to strengthen its own position.   Kerenski1s success was more apparent than real.   He has not yet succeeded in forming a Coalition Government that could command any wide-spread support, and ho has not succeeded in retaining the services of Alexeyev.     Since he became Prime Minister two months ago Kerenski has been consistently pursuing his policy of gathering together in his Government all the moderate elements in the country.     Under slightly more normal conditions his policy of a National Government might have been successful, but conditions have been growing less and less normal. Class feeling has become more acute and the military failures have continued without any appreciable improvement.   An agreement between Kerenski and Kornilov might have saved the situation, and it was apparently for this that -Savinkov, then Minister of War, was working. It was Kornilov&apos;s premature action that destroyed the whole basis of the Coalition that Kereneki was attempting to build up.     There was still a ray of hope when Alexeyev intervened and assumed the post of Chief of Staff, but with his resignation Kerenski&apos;s plans seem doomed to failure.From what evidence we have it would appear that the disagreement between Kerenski and Alexeyev was due to the impossibility of harmonising Kdrenskifs political views with Alexeyev&apos;s military requirements.   Kornilov1s revolt has made the political situation far more difficult to handle than it was before, and Kerenski1s
Illattempts at a reconciliation between opposing extremes are becoming more and more of a forlorn hope.     Nevertheless, having committed himself to this policy, he cannot withdraw, and he seems determined to continue fighting opposition both on the Right and on the Left. His opponents, however, declare that he shows more activity in acting against the Right than against the Left, and maintain that his severity towards Kornilov&apos;s supporters is far stronger than it is towards the Maximalists.Whatever Kerenakl&apos;s intentions may be there seems to be little doubt that the Maximalists are getting more and more out of hand. They have secured Chernov as their leader and, with Chernov, a large number of the Social Revolutionaries have gone over to their side.     This is quite a new feature of the situation.     In the early days of the Revolution the Social Revolutionaries, though divided into various groups, had come together far more effectively than had the Social Democrats, who adhered to their old division into Maximalists and Minimalists.     Now the Social Revolutionaries have followed suit, and the split beWeen Kerenski and Chernov is just as marked as between Tsereteli and Trotski.     It   is this which explains the rapid increase in the numbers of the Maximalists.   They have now secured a majority in the Sovyet and are making frantic efforts to carry through their policy at the meeting of Democratic Organisations, which meets on September 25.   They are making a definite bid for power, and their candidate for the post of Prime Minister is Chernov.Against the Maximalists are arrayed all the Moderate Socialists, whether Social Democrats or Social Revolutionaries, but counsels of moderation are not having much success in the present excited atmosphere.     Kerenski&apos;s position appears to depend upon the success of the Moderate Socialists.     Should they come out on top at the forthcoming conference he will, no doubt, continue his attempt to
form a Coalition;   should Chernov secure a majority it is probable that Kerenski will resign.     A majority for Chernov would mean the uprooting of the very foundation of Kerenski&apos;s policy, as it   would mean the definite refusal of the Sovyet to join any Government where the bourgeois parties were represented.   In this case Kerenski would have one of two alternatives, either to go definitely to the Right or else to retire altogether.   He could not, with any show of consistency, join the extreme Left, and his recent open attack in the press on Chernov seems to remove all possibility of such a step on his part.The next week, therefore, may see a recrudescence of trouble in Russia with the two extremes pitted against one another in a final bid for power.   The spectre of civil war is again looming large as it was a fortnight ago.     It was then averted by mediation,, but, if Chernov controls the Sovyet, it will be far more difficult to mediate between him and the Cadets than it was in the case of Kerenski.     It will be the greatest calamity should the final struggle come between the two extremes, as Germany can hardly fail to gain whichever side proves victorious.   Prom the victory of Chernov, should it prove permanent, she would probably gain peace before the winter, and a peace which would mean the disruption of Russia, as Chernov and his followers care far  more about class war than the maintenance of Russia as a great power.   Should the Right win and democracy in Russia be defeated, the German militarist party will lose no opportunity of instilling in the minds of the German people new fears of the Russian danger and the necessity of German militarism in the future.   The worst enemy of the German militarist party are the ideaB of Kerenski, who has tried to establish Russian democracy on a broad national basis.   As usual, German propaganda has aimed at destroying what was the steadying
influence by working in the two extreme camps and arraying them one against the other.German Peace Offers and Russia.The Pope&apos;s Note was the first sign of the new German move in favour of peace at Russia1s expense.    In the first days of the Russian Revolution, when it was still uncertain how formidable the Russian armies might be, the German Government left no stone unturned to secure a separate peace with Russia,   Now, however, with the Russian armies disorganised and no longer a danger, Germany may think it will pay better to offer favourable terms . to her Western instead of her Eastern enemies.   What she cedes on the West she will more than recover on tho Bast.Germany will probably count largely upon the unpopularityof Russia in England and France owing to her military failures.While exploiting the unpopularity of Russia in the West, she at thesame   time loses no opportunity of letting Russia know anythingunfavourable to Russian democracy that appears here.   For example,her wireless messages emphasise the way the British and French pressosupported Kornilov.   By sowing syspicions against us in Russia she makes the Russians more ready to believe that they will be let down by their Allies in the terms of peace.     In these circumstances the statement made by Kerenski to General Barter (Sir G. Buchanan&apos;s telegram, September 16) may be said to voice a widespread fear in Russia,&quot;Kerenski remarked that many people thought England and France wore disposed to make peace with Germany and to leave Russia in the lurch.   He stated that German peace propaganda was now being directed more to making peace with the Western Powers than with Russia and that Germany intended to offer favourable terms to France and England at the expense of Russia&quot;.
24.9.17.RALThere are at least 3 reasons against Russia making a separate peace:-(1) Kerenski and his supporters are sincerely anxious to fight in the interests of democracy.(2) To conclude peace when she is weak and disorganised would place Russia entirely at Germany1s mercy after the war, however good the outward terms might appear.(3) It is impossible for Russia to demobilise her armyIn its present condition.   If the present undisciplined hordes were set free they would rob and plunder unrestrained,JThe Maximalists are the only party v:rho would consent to peace at any price, but should they succeed In forming a Government under Chernov they could hardly fail to provoke a civil war and their peace policy would be immediately reversedJThe danger of Germany1s peace terms at Russia&apos;s expense is obvious.   Not only would Germany get complete commercial control over Russia after the war, but she would have her roftte to the East secured, and would draw within her orbit a future Polish or a future Lithuanian Kingdom, while keeping under her control,   &apos; in complicity with Finland, the whole of the Baltic Provinces.

</content>
</cab>
