<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/27/0 images: 148-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
LT.FJS DQcm^T Ig THJg P^g^TY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S GOVEMMSSe,G.T.-2130 W A Hi, CABIN B,Tl3UPBQUfflY jgjjj HOUSING ACCOMMOJDATION AT BAHHOW.Memorandum by. the flight Batu George N* Barnea. MfP. Previous gaper G.T., 1758.(Circulated with reference to War Cabinet 232, Minute. 16).1. ;    In accordance with the decision given&apos;in War Cabinet 232 (16) I have consulted with the Ministry of Munitions and the Local Government Board on this subject.   I found, however, that the Local Government Board are not ouncemed, as Barrow is a. purely munitions centre, and the Local Government Board have no*b intervened and do not propose to intervene between the Ministry of Munitions and the local authority in the matter of housing accommodation,2.      The Ministry of Munitions have made&apos; the following arrange-raerits to cope with the problem:-Erection of additional houses.Schemes are in hand for tho provision of 500 semi-perma-nent and 500 permanent houses.   The two schemes are to be started simultaneously and.it is anticipated that the semi-permanent houses will begin to be ready by Christmas and will, probably be finished by the, end of March next., and the permanent houses will begin to be available by the latter date.   Once these houses have been erected the housing question at Barrow will not be completely solved, but its immediate urgency-will bo relieved,, The semi-permanont houses are to be built of concrete and con-sis t of four *nd five rooms.     The permanent houses will be of the same size and will be planned and laid out with a view to aesthetic as well as sanitary considerations,   The rente will vary from 6/6d, to 8/6dv per week according to the class of house.The Ministry of Munitions/have arranged with,the Corpora-tion that 250 of the 500 permanent houses should bo taken over by them&apos;five years after the war and it is hoped that the second 250 will also be taken over by the Corporation,3,      Whilst the work: of oonstruotion is going on, something must be done to mitigate the unsatisfactory housing conditions that, prevail;   and to meet them the Ministry of Munitions have reported the matter to the Central Billeting Board who prepose to billet munition workers, both by voluntary and (if necessary) -by compulsory methods.   The iiilleting Aet however, has the grave defect that it contains no power to billet the families of munition workers and this to a certain oxtont ,is interfering with the work of the Billeting Board.4.      Billeting.  .The Billeting Board is now making&apos;up a register of all available lodgings and whorevsr possible vacant houses are being requisitioned.   Up t:/ the present time, 413 hr-uess have been inspected and it has been found that accommodation for
about 139 persons is available.   Assuming that this proportion is maintained throughout the enquiry, it would appear possible, for six or soven hundred additional persons to be billeted in Barrow &amp;nd the surrounding area..o.      Accommodation outside Barrow,..The Billeting Board also .propose to investigate areas . outside Barrow such as DaIton and Ulverstdn.   A certain amount of accommodetion is known to be available thero, but the work-men naturally do not like living at such a distance especially In view of the deficiency of Railway, accommodation.   It may further be possible&apos;, if arrangements with the Railway Executive. Committee can .-.e&amp; gale , to arrange for a certain number to live at Coniston, bufc as at best the railway journey would take an hour and twenty minutes this is not likely to afford much relief.     Altogether it is hoped that additional accommodation from all sources may be available for 2,000 persons.   Steps are being taken to billet munition workers without waiting for the completion of tho register of lodgings.6,.      Evictions.All arrangements have now been mede for the making of an Order in Council to prevent eviotions in Barrow.   The people evicted since the attention of the Ministry of Munitions has been drawn to the matter have now been rehoused in unoccupied houses requisitioned by the Ministry under the Defence of the Healm Act.7.      Publicity.I think that everything possible has now been done to mitigate the immediate need of houses in Barrow and to provide sufficient additional bouses,.. If my colleagues agree. I propose to oommunicats to the Press the particulars given above in paragraphs.2 ^ 6 inclusive.(Initialled)     &amp;.i,.B.26th September, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
