<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/27/0 images: 308-336</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL.MINISTRY OF PENSIONS. Report for period from 22nd September to 28th September 1917*Pensions*Number of Pensions.    The number of pensions granted during the week to officers and men, and to widows, children and dependants (Appendix I) was 13,982 against 12,858 last week and 13,638 the week before.   Tils is once more a record. Since the beginning of the war 849,778 pensions, including children&apos;s allowances, have been awarded.Appendix II shows that last week 39 grants cf supplementary pensions and special allowances were made by the Special Grants Committee against 36 in the previous wesk.   The total number to date is 4,514. 2.    Pensions to Soldiers.   The number of fresh claims to pension of disabled soldiers dealt with by the Awards to Soldiers Branch during the week ending 26th September was 7,000 as compared with 6,COO during the previous week, and 5,300 during the week before.Of the 7,000 cases 4,015 were disposed of by the award of pension, permanent or temporary, and 2,967 by the grant of gratuities, and in 18 cases the claims were rejected.   Claims which had previously been rejected under former Warrants were admitted in 913 cases, 894 of themen being granted gratuities and 19 pensions.   The total number of claims previously rejected which have bee&apos; dealt with up to date is 8,992 of whifth 1,128 have been met by the award of pension and 7,864 by gratuities.$* Pensions to widows and dependants. The work of awarding and authorising payment of Widows- and Dependants pensions in current cases is completely, up to date.2,548
2,548 re -a s sea smeorts-of--depeiidairts- - pensions were made during the week against 2,545 last week and 2,031 the week before.   There remain 10,261 cases to be dealt with (Appendix III).   The 2,548 cases this week include 250 dependants pensioned under the old Warrant who have benefitted by the re-assessment to the average extent of 5/ld. a week, and 1,512 dependant parents whose cases had been settled by a gratuity under the Old Warrant but have new been placed on pension at an average rate of 8/4ci. a week.   The rest of the 2,548 receive no benefit, their pensions already being equal to pre-war dependence&apos;As a result cf the week:a re-examinations as to entitlement under the new Warrant 15 widows not previously helped have been admitted to full pension, 5 to temporary pension, and 5 dependants have been admitted to pension or gratuity.   34 (widows and. dependants) remain to be dealt with out of the original total of 4,722. (Appendix IV) . 4*   Pensions to Parents - Hew Scheme. Over 2,000 claims to the benefit of this Scheme have now &quot;been received and steps are being taken to deal with them.    The work of investigating facts as to incomes etc, of claimants will devolve upon the Local War Pensions Committees and it has been thought advisable to issue a Circiilar of Instructions to those bodies calling attention to the necessity for prompti-tude in rendering their reports.   It is hoped that this will have good results.155 Parents Pensions of less than 3/G a week have been increased to that amount with effect from 1st September 1917.   The average rate of increase is l/ld a week.   More rapid progress is now being made with this part of the work. 5&apos;   Gratuities to Widows.   Several complaints having been received that there was delay in the issue of the gratuity to the widows of soldiers after tl-e notification to them Iof
of their husbands&apos;deaths the far Office, at the request of the Ministry, issued Army Council Instruction No.1480 containing directions on the subject to Officers i/c of records and officers paying separation allowances. (Appendix V),6*   Retired Pay to Officers etc.     The following is a summary of the progress made in the review of case;.; under the Officers Warrant of the 1st August 1917.Officers.   Retired pay re-examined in 505 cases, of which 401 have received increased rates, the average increase being  30 a year.   About 845 remain to be re-examined.   19 officers &quot;slightly impaired&quot; have been placed on retired pay in lieu of gratuities previously granted and 3 have had their gratuities increased by an average amount of  37.   33 gratuities in non-attributable cases have been increased the average increase being  48. 4 gratuities of an average amount of  31 have been awarded where no previous grant was admissible.Nurses.   34 have had their pensions increased, the average increase being  53.   4 have received increased gratuities the average increase being  33.Widows and Children.   22 Widows have had their pensions increased from the intermediate rate to the highest, and 3 from the ordinary rate to intermediate, the average increase being  48.   32 Childrenrs allowances have been increased the average increase being  5.2 Widows who had previously been granted gratuities where no pension was previously admissible have been granted pension at the intermediate rate.Other Relatives.    No progress can be made until rules have been agreed to by the Treasury.    These rules were submitted to them on the 26th August.
^*    Pensions Appeal Tribunal.   816 Appeal forms had been received by the 26th September, an increase of 185 since 15th September.   They have been o: alt with as shown in Appendix VI.   40 more cases are ready for the Tribunal than on the earlier date and while the number disposed of has substantially increased the number under investi-gation remains practically the same.     Since the 26th , 3 cases have been determined by the Tribu. al favourably and one unfavourably to the men.8&apos;   Delays in Pensioning.   A Conference took place at Lord Derby!s suggestion between a representative of the &quot;ar Office and representatives of the Ministry of Pensions on the 24th instant., on the subject of delays in the issue of pensions to men discharged from Class W.^.   and to other men whose documents fail to reach the Ministry in a sufficiently complete state to enable the pension to be7granted until sometime after the men are discharged   The result of this Conference and other matters connected with delay i;i the issue of pensions are dealt with in the Memorandum prepared for the Conrntsatoa of Enquiry into Industrial Unrest whiah is attached as Appendix VII hereto.Treatment.9,   General Schemes of Treatment.   The Local Committees of Kent, Birmingham, and Burton-on-Trent have submitted schemes for particular forms of treatment in particular institutions. These are ,dealt with in Appendix VIII.The preparation of schemes for Institutional treatment is now generally passing to the Joint (Disablement) Committees and several such schemes dealing with the wider areas in tliese Committees1 charge are understood to be approaching completion.10.   Individual Cases of Treatment.   The great bulk of cases of treatment are under general schemes which have receivedapproval
approval, but a small number- of cases requiring special treatment or treatment in institutions for which approval has not previously been given are submitted each week. During the week ended 26th instant 158 such cases were so sanctioned,11-   Numbers under Treatment.   Appendix IX shows the number of men for whom treatment has been provided under arrangements made or approved by the Ministry and to whom allowances under Article 6 of the Royal Warrant are payable.    It will be seen that 201 cases were admitted for treatment during the week ended 26th September andtha* 904 men wore under treatment on t/iat elate, as compared with 804 men at the end of the previous week.The Table shows also the nature of the disablements for which treatment was required, and it will be seen that more than half the cases are of wounds or injuries, 12 per cent being cases of paraplegia.   102 cases of neurasthenia ard under treatment at Colders Green and 27 of advanced tuberculosis in the hospitals of the Metropolitan Asylums Bfcard in London.     The number of discharged men in lunatic asylums who have been admitted to the benefit of the special arrangements for &quot;Servioe Patients&quot; referred to in previous reports was, on the 26th instant, 432.   Of these 89 had been re-adjnfctted during the week.Training.12.   Arrangements with Board of Education-    In order to make the most effective use of the technical institutions and schools provided by the Local $ducatleraal Authorities Find to provide for the supervision of training for disabled men, it has been felt desirable to associate the Board of Education with the work of the Ministry more fully thanhas
9 Q 9has hitherto been the case.   Arrangements have accordingly been made that where a scheme of training is proposed by the Local Committee in concert with the Local Education Authorities the scheme should be submitted concurrently to the Board of Education and to the Ministry, The Board cf Education will be concerned to criticise and supervise the technical and administrative aspects of the scheme from the Educational point of view.   Instructions with this object have been issued by the Board of Efucation of which a copy is given in Appendix X.13.   Training in Motor Tractor work.   Arrangements have been made for the training of suitable men in motor-tractor work under the general supervision of the Board of Agriculture. As the work is heavy and of an exciting nature the men will have to be carefully selected, and a circular has been issued to Local Committees warning them as tto this.   It has been arranged that the men shall be seen and selected in all cases by the local Tractor Representatives of the Board of Agriculture whose names and addresses have been communicated to the Local Committees.14.   Training in Diamond Cutting.   The work of training disabled men in diamond cutting is progressing successfully, 17 men are now under training and the founder of the scheme, Mr. Oppenheimer, is so far satisfied with the work that he propose^ to construct two more workshops which will acco27t&apos;nodate another 30 men.   In addition fully equipped workshops where the men after training will .be employed at a good wage are being provided by Mr. Oppenheimer.Visits to training cenfrfrtts in t&amp;e provinces. Visits have been paid by the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary, accompanied by Major Mitchell, the Technical Adviser to the Department, tp various centres of training,including
(including the Cowen House, Newcastle, the workshops at &apos;&apos;;,ueen Lary&apos;s Auxiliary Hospital for Limbless men at.Brighton, the workshops for training in Diamond Gutting at Brighton and the workshops at Roehamptqn.The Cowen House,founded by Miss Cowan has been doing useful work in training in various trades, including electrical maintenance work, carpentry and tailoring, and is now proposed to bo extended.Arrangements are in progress for &quot;systematis^-ag&quot; the training given at Brighton and Roohampton Hospitals so as to encourage serious vocrtional instruction for those men who are under the necessity of adopting a now occupation. A detailed report will be made on these arrangements when completed,-s* General Schemes of Training.   Appendix XI contains a review of tho proposals for training submitted by Local Committees during the week ended the 26th in.&quot;.tant.     They include an important scheme of boot and shoe repairing which has beon sanctioned for operation in London. 17. Individual cases of Training.    Owing to the comparative ease with which employment is obtained now, the number of men offering themselves for training Is, In the area of any single Local Committee, usually limited and are frequently not enough to call for general schemes of training.     In consequence a large proportion of the men who rre admitted to training are the subject of individual application and sanction by the hinistry.     During the week ended 26th instant, 43 cases of training were thus sanctioned,     Of those 11 were to be trained in boot and shoe repairing, six in tho trader connected with engineering, and six in motor mechanics,18. Number of Lien under Training.   Appendix 711 shows that
50 men were admitted to training by Local Committees during the week and that the total number reported as under training at the end of the week was 287.   Rather less than two-thirds of the number were under training in Technical Institutes.Organisation.19.   Reports of Inspectors.   Extracts from the reports of the Inspectors of Accounts for the week ending the 25th Septomber are contained In Appendix XIII.The administration of the Northumberland Committee requires overhauling and is receiving it.   The York Local Committee is working on approved lines.   The East Riding Committee is reported to be particularly good all reund; they are carefully going into questions of treatment and training and alternative pensions.   In Surrey all cases are now being reviewed and brought under the Regulations,   kiddlesex Sub-Committees adhere to reflations but in some cases insufficient ly look after case papers.As a result of an important meoting at which there was much criticism of general and local liar Pensions Administration the Rhondda Committee is to be organised.   The adjoining Pontypridd Committee, thanks largely tc a retiring Secretary, is working smoothly.   The Llanelly District Committee promises a higher level of work when free of the Carmarthenshire Committee.    In Glamorganshire District Committees are rising to a higher standard of organisation. The Swansea Committee is keen and sympathetic but not wholly regular.in its awards.   The Secretary of one of the Monmouthshire Sub-Committees which is to be granted autonomy was ignorant of the existence of Treatment and Training Instructions.In Scotland the Inspector doubts the capacity of tho present Clerk and Treasurer of the Midlothian Committee.At,
9 Q c:At Portadown in Co. Armagh the work is well and carefully done.Staff etc.20.   Appendix XIV shows an addition of 71 to the staff of the Ministry during the week, 23 having been added to the Awards to widows Branch and 46 to the Pensions Issue Office where there are now 6 holiday workers to replace girls on their annual leave.   The other branches remain much as they were.   The staff on the books of the Ministry now comprises 278 men and 4,148 women, or 4,426 in all.The daily percentage of absences during the week was 4 among the male and 4*9 among the female staff.M.N.29th September 1917.
Summary of tensions and allowances granted to Soldiers and sailors disabled and to the Widows,Childrenand other dependants of soldiers and sailors  ^ceased.ireriod.ijtal from lo/2/17 toiA /it..i-&apos;^r week ond-i tg 8/8/1715/8/17  /b/1729/8/17 5/9/1712/9/1719/9/1726/9/17Officers. en and iursos.! 61,7751ij 2,701 3,1973*365ij 3,089 3,857 4,4^4 3,762 4,21527,2^655545u706 847 665 977 668Children.114,1483,462 3,9264,548 4, c!2 5,364 5,965 5,976 6,041ependants39.: , 0oC* 2,4572,551 2,857 2,567 2,404 2,1433,058votal242,73Q8,768lv-&apos; , v. 3\.;11,282 10,864 12,635 13,638 12,858 13,982&quot;T&quot;jl eriodiTirom&quot;beginning of war.I Officers ren and purses-itup to C/b/17 &quot;15/:/17&quot;22/8/17203,753 2j6,95,j 210 315I&quot; 9/8/171 213,404TT&quot; 5/9/17 &quot;12/9/17 &quot;19/9/17 &quot;26/9/17217,261 221,665 223,427 229,642.idows.91,055 91,505 92,323 93,029 93,876 94,741 95,718 96,384children399,342403,268S 407,616 jI 412,028 &apos; 417,-392 423,357 429,333435,374dependants.70,339	764,489.72,796	774,51975,347	785,60178., 204	796,6658u,771	809,30083,175	822,93885,318   .	.835,79688,376	649,776Total.to 6b era
AffEMOOC II^ablkjx?SUMMARY   OF   AtikKDS OFSUPPLEMENTARY ALLOWANCES AND SPECIAL ALLOWANCES, BY THE SPECIAL GRANTS COMMITTEE.For the week ending September 26th, 1917.During week     Total to ended 26th      Wth Sept, Sept. 1917      litDisabled Officers	0	39Officers1 Widows.	0	66Officers1 Dependants.	1	140Education Grants (Officers)	I	134Education Grants (Men)	2	1P3Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.	0	9e2Sailors1 and Soldiers&apos; Widows.	87	2,380SailorsT and Soldiers1 Dependants.	go	S70TOTAL        39 4,514
iU^uui&apos; A3   TO itis-a^s j sStit uit    &quot;nypgnp a ftps iriijnsxgiis jos.kliitd  September   2 6 tlx,   1917Gratuities eon-vorted into pensions.uratuities allow-l od to stand temporarily pre-war dependence being under 3/6.Pensions incr:tensions greeted (no previous grant)ronsions unchan-ged (already equal to pre-war dependence.Parents dependent&apos; on one son. !xarents depdt on more than one son.Grandparents and Poster Paronts.iio. ixv1 ge .*tate.a.v 1 ge Inor.i-;ate ilncr.&apos;972 10713/7  \    8/7    &apos;    537;  7/11j  7/llj    1902q2ajuIL343i10/81    5/3 3:1708/934710779/107/11i22.jv&apos;ge lv&apos;geAato   ilncr.I4-5/-   j 5/-4/11;4 -2512/65/-7/6Parents drawing o.A.as wife or pension a^s widowClass B. widow 10/* a week..oI-v1ge; AvT ge ^ate.i Incr.o.-,v&apos; ge iner.7/38/67/38/6Illeg. children 5/- a week.1o. PiVge Incr.2/61011] ; is-cellanooua-8383(Total i(o. (corrected) to bo re-assessed as i-.c-assossod as per previous reports ...abovo   ... BalanceSummary for weekat *pril 4th 1917.72,SQQipensions increased 2oG.avTtnor.5/1 per week.it50^691. pensions granted, previously settled ...    &apos;    0*46 j by gratuity f 1512.i i-st)^VGraSe rate of pension 8/4 per week.re-GO OO
Report for week ended 26th September, 1917 as to new entitlement to &quot;widows and Dependants pensions.The following shews the approximate number of cases to be reconsidered at date 4-th April, 1917.Widows Widows Dependants11 Aggravation&quot; gratuity admitted.............503.Ho claim under Old I&apos;arrant.................1522.Do. 2697.TOTAL.4722.Total re-examined to date.7ID07SDEPEISDA1ITS.ylggrav casesOther cases $admittedfinally refused!TotalPens,aliod iiig -Q.17,9.17teranted.It-i-^ull pension!Pull pensions Short&apos;. pension-1-----------------64650350362110229631651or Grats admitted?inaiiyrefus1999151169229 (2014   1174i1500Total1500   126692674number still to be disposed of 34.
No. 1480 of 1917.War Office,21th September, 1917.1480. Gratuity to Widows of Soldiers killed in Action or dying of Wounds, &amp;c.1. With reference to Article 14 (1) of the Royal Warrant of the 29th March last, promulgated by A.0.178 of 1917, the Minister of Pensions has called attention to the necessity for the greatest oromptitude in rendering the information necessary to enable the Ministry to authorize payment of this gratuity which is intended to meet expenses immediately arising and consequent on or caused by the soldier&apos;s death.2. Officers i/c Records are, therefore, requested to take steps, in conjunction with officers paying separation allowance, to ensure that A.F. B. 104-88 duly completed is forwarded to the Ministry of Pensions (Widows and Dependants Branch), 45, Grosvenor Road, London, S.W.1, within four days, if possible, of the date on which, the widow is informed of the soldier&apos;s death.7/Gen. No./8275 (F. 3).By Command of the Army Council, m    9[Copies for G.Os.G.-in-C. and G.Os.C.; Officers i/c Records; Pay-masters; T.F. Associations; Ministry of Pensions.](b, 13258-1562)  6m  9/17   H &amp; 8  A 17/1562ARMY COUNCIL  INSTRUCTION.
APPENDIX   VI.ANALYSIS of TRIBUNAL CASES DLALT WITH UP TO WEDNESDAY the 26th SEPTEMBER.Number of Appeal Forma received. 816Number sent to Tribunal as not being on points within their reference.Notified on Daily List ) 16)Not Notified       ) 79Number of Cases given &quot;due to1&apos; or &quot;aggravated by&quot; on further enquiry.       135Cases considered by Tribunal.Given attributable &amp;c. 10Given not attributable.        8Adjourned 422Cases ready for Tribunal but notheard. 61Cases under investigation, 503
APPENDIX VII.MEMORANDUM of the Ministry of Pensions fcr the Commission of Enquiry Into Industrial Unrest.The Commission of Enquiry into Industrial Unrest reported that one of its causes was the delay in granting pensions to soldiers, especially these in Class W Reserve. This latter Reserve was formed In June 1916 for soldiers whose services were deemed to he of more value to the country In civil than in Military employment.     A further Class of the Reserve called P. Class was formed later In the year of men similarly situated, but who as a result of having served In the Army had contracted disabilities which wnuld have entitled them, had they been discharged, tc disability pension. Difficulties arose through the discharge of men tc Class W. who claimed that they should have been placed in Class P. Steps have been taken to rectify the matter.     Class F, has been abolished, and men in Class V/. who claimed tc be dis-abled have been re-examined medically.     Other men in Class W. who are unable to obtain employment are being recalled to the Colours, re-examined, and if unfit or likely tc be unfit for the higher categories will be discharged to pension.   Those who are ill and need treatment are being placed cn Army pay from the time when they report their cases, and sent to military hospitals, and while the men&apos;s cases are being ex-amined Local Committees make special temporary grants to their families.     These steps are having a satisfactory result, and Local Committees v/ho sent in many complaint8 up tc the end cf August of the destitution of the men and their families have now almost ceased to do so.2. There have also been complaints as to the delays ingranting pensions to other men than thpse in Class W.    There has certainly been such delay in some cases due to late or Incomplete submission of papers from Record Offices, tc the incompleteness of the evidence they contain whereon to decide the claim and to the consequent necessity fcr further en-quiries.     To obviate these difficulties Mr. Hedge proposed in a letter of the 13th instant addressed to the Secretary of State for War that discharged Invalided spldiers should be retained cn pay (with Separation Allowance) until a decision on their claim to pension was reached.     The War Office believing however, that the delays occur nearly entirely with the Class W. men are averse to this0arrangement which would not assist that Class, and   steps are new being taken both by the War Office and the Pensions Ministry to tighten up the arrangements by which t$ avoid delays in ether cases which may be caused at the Record&apos;Offices.     If such delays cannot be obviated the Minister will press his proposal for continuance of pay and Separation Allowances until the claim to pension has been settled.3. The introduction of the Royal Warrant of 29th March,1917 with its attendant advantages and with perhaps a more generous Interpretation in administration than had hitherto been taken, has resulted in a large increase in the number of cases where compensation of some sort is given.     Prior tc April 1917, there had been 65,673 rejections cf claims or an average of 2084 a month.     Since then there have only been 484 or an average of 97 a month..The
u o 0-The-establishment of an Appeals&apos; Tribunal .whioh commenced its work in August is resulting in this compensation taking more often the form of pensions than it did, that is to say, in fewer gratuities being granted instead of pensions. The refusal of any compensation and later the grant of gratuities whan men considered they had suffered in health owing to their services were undoubtedly as groat grievances as delay in the issue of grants and the cause of these grievances is being removed.4. Apart from the question of delay in the grant ofpensions to disabled men, there has been much complaint pf the delay in the assessment of Dependant&apos;s Pensions, and, though this further matter only touches this Department through   &apos; the local War Pensions Committees of the delay in granting Dependants&apos; Separation Allowances on men joining the Army. This has been due to the attenuation of the staff under the Board of Custom and Excise, who undertake the necessary investigations,     This has been the subject of correspondence with that Department, which is making every effort to cope with the difficulty.5. Among the recommendations of the Commission, wasone that Pensions Committees should have a larger discretion in dealing with men discharged from the Army.     Local Committees have been enabled, pending decisions as to pensions to make immediate advances.     This power has been largely used but in certsin directions it may require extension.     The Special Grants Committee set up by the Minister are considering how far any modifications of the Regulations are required in order to give a wider discretion to the Local Committees, and they are anxious to give effect to this policy.     They have before them the views of the Local Committees and will lose no time In dealing with any suggestions that are made.     They have however, to bear in mind that all Committees are net equally well staffed and that voluntary workers cannot be given unlimited control over the expenditure of public funds.6. As regards the Treatment and Training of disabled menunder the Royal Warrant, some alterations in the Regulations in the direction of wider discretion to Local Committees havo already been approved.     Until Local Committees had surveyed the provision available within their areas, both as regards hospitals and technical schools, and until the Ministry had been able through their Joint Committees to tabulate the accommod-ation   which they   would approve, and to decide In what employ-&quot;ments there were likely to be openings for which men could be trained, it was not possible to allow Local Committees an entirely free hand.     The Ministry have, however, greatly advanced their arrangements, and have now been able to give power to the Local Committees to send men immediately on thoir application to the Military and larger Civil Hospitals without having to obtain special sanction from the Central Office. The Ministry have also given advice to the Local Committees as to courses of Training, and in addition, to a large number of technical institutions which have been approved and in which Local Committees can Immediately arrange for courses of training, the Ministry have given them authority to provide Training in workshops for individual men up to a limited number, without reference to-the Central Office,     These Instructions which havo been issued subsequently to the Report of the Commission, have gone a considerable way in giving the larger discretion to the Local Pensions Committees, which was recommended by the Commission,26/9/17.M.N.
TREATMENT.Report of Schemes etc. submitted during the week ending 26th September 1917.1.       The Kent Local Committee submitted a proposal to use the Hospitals at Bath, Buxton, and Droitwich for the treatment of discharged disabled men in their area.     The proposal has been sanctioned provisionally pending the submission of a comprehensive scheme.2.       The Birmingham Local Committee are proposing to start a Home for disabled men who are in need of prolonged institutional treatment.     The capital expenditure, including the purchase of the hous9, and the necessary alterations and equipment will be met out of a special fund for which the Lord Mayor has consented to appeal, but before taking definite action the Committee wished to know whether the institution would be approved.    The necessary sanction has been given but it was pointed out that if the main-tenance charges are to be in excess of the rates laid down in Schedule I of the Instructions on Treatment and Training, a further report should be submitted.3.       The Local Government Board have forwarded a proposal to set aside accommodation at the Tuberculosis Hospital, Ualkergate, r!ewcastle-upon-Tyne, for the use of discharged men suffering from Tuberculosis in an advanced stage.     The Town Council, to whom the Institution belongs, are prepared to receive such cases provided that the Ministry agree to pay the actual maintenance charges as agreed by the Local Government Board.   This proposal has been accented and the scheme sanctioned.4.        The Burton on Trent Local Committee have submitted a general scheme for the treatment of discharged men in their area, comprising arrangements with the Burton Infirmary, the local Red Cross Hospital, and the Southport Hydropathic Hospital and other institutions with all of which terms have been arranged in accord-ance with Schedule I of the Instructions.
C-ases in receipNature of Disabilitypt of Allovrr.noes ciurir:Treatnenten.dc.....ibor  1917V&quot;:ounds &amp; fe&apos; Iniur ies Veurasthenioi Paraplegiad co -Pco tor5 d o o or-J 03Co CDO COO CuoNumber under treat-ment on 26.9.17.i-r-54226dumber reported during -week as admitted, for . Treatment.do ocoCD to d or-i COcu *DO COO d1-3 OrHd 01&amp; CD-p til  do o oEpilepsy tuberculosis fOthoriH 02dO d 5   h3 Or-4d to3 erf CD O O61101153   !JT1erf CDlo coiO dt-3 or-4d 03U Qa dCD O O13r-t COd CDo coo di-3 oDiseases ----- -d co iU CD i r-i CD-P co i d CDj3 d i o co) CD o ; o dTotal4254      219;  804InInstitutionsHot; treated.rr-ld toCD-1&quot; \-P3COdCD OorH COd CDO Kl.&apos; O d294416Other?;! sed w-PCD COdCD Oo8TII   22    I   63;   101611t4 1 11t 35i   50&apos; 201    1Lumber reported duringj jweek as discharged.       j !from. Treatment. !    -   I911 I   -&quot; i    1Total under Treatment on 26.9.1776280!  71Total who have been/ orj &apos; are under&quot; treatment      1 under arrangements  maa.o ,r sanctioned by the.    H68 Linistry up to 26.9.17J.15114r22i 304i 258 !17 j   128 ;53-4I71 i1231!-4-3211586262;   984I361 !524-4-iI38 ii 53764  I  318: 3055      I     2348    604 i Ir-l COd CDO coO d868918to95  clo GJ2
Circular to Local Education Authorities and Governing Bodies of Technical Schools.Circular 1014. 24th September 1917.All communications should be addressed to &apos;:The Secretary &quot;BOAED OP EDUCATION,at The Victoria and Albert Museum, South Kensington, London, S.W. 7.Training of Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.(1) It is the desire of the Ministry of Pensions that vocational training for disabled sailors and soldiers should as far as possible be provided in proximity to the men&apos;s homes and through institutions conducted by Local Education Authorities or Governing Bodies of Technical Schools which are aided by the Board of Education. The Board are confident that Local Education Authorities and Governing Bodies will co-operate in the matter to the utmost extent of their power with the Ministry of Pensions and the Local Committees under the Ministry.(2) It is recognised that disabled men will, as a rule, require training in themanual processes of industry, and that as courses of this type do not ordinarily form alarge part of the normal work of Technical Schools, new and perhaps considerable expendi-ture may be involved.   It is not intended, however, that the provision and maintenance ofany courses of training which may be specially required for disabled sailors and soldiersshould impose a new burden on existing educational funds, whether central or local, andthe arrangements set out below are designed to carry this principle into effect.*(3) (a) If the training is such as can be given to disabled men in common with ordinary students of the School, it will be treated as part of the ordinary work of the School, and will be recognised by the Board and aided with grant in the way ordinarily provided by their Regulations for Technical Schools, &amp;c. In these cases the Ministry of Pensions will pay, in respect of each disabled man enrolled, the ordinary fee charged to other students in the same classes.(b) If it becomes necessary to establish special classes for disabled men, either as part of the organisation of an existing Technical School or otherwise under the direction of the Local Education Authority, the Board will assess special fees, for payment by the Ministry of Pensions, of an amount calculated to cover the actual additional cost to the Authority or Governing Body of giving the instruction. This fee, however, will not cover any part of the ordinary cost of management or of such establishment charges as lighting and heating, if the class is held in the premises of a School already receiving grant from the Board of Education, under any of their Regulations. Where a &quot;special fee&quot; is paid by the Ministry, no grant in respect of the instruction will be paid by the Board. Each proposal for a class or classes will be sent by the Local Education Authority, or the Governors of the Technical School, to the Board, together with an estimate of the additional cost entailed. The Board will require to be satisfied that teachers on the ordinary staff of the Authority or Governors are not available for the classes, and that in other respects the additional cost is justifiable, and will also consider whether the scheme of work is likely to be effective for its purpose. The proposal will be submitted concurrently by the Local Pensions Committee to the Ministry of Pensions, Avho will consider the suitability of the instruction for disabled men, the probability of a rea.sona,ble number of men desiring to receive it, and the prospects of x   (36)3082   Wt 23389 A 733$  2500   9/17   E &amp; S
it Ksubsequent employment which it will give them. The two Departments will then confer as to whether the course should be approved, and if it is approved, the Board will assess a fee adequate to cover the cost. Unless the case is exceptional, or experience suggests some other basis, the assessment will proceed upon the assumption that classes averaging 12 students will be formed for instruction of a scientific or manual kind, and classes of 18 for subjects of a literary or commercial kind. These numbers are based on the principle that instruction cannot reasonably be provided for smaller classes than 10 or 15, according to the nature of the subject, and that, if the number of students reaches 15 or 20, as the case may be, additional teachers will be required. The fees, when assessed by the Board and approved by the Ministry of Pensions, will be payable through the Local Pensions Committee under the Naval and Military War Pensions Act, 1915, to the Authority or Governors providing the instruction. The Board will test the efficiency of the instruction by inspection and, if it proves inefficient, will communicate the fact to the Ministry of Pensions, with a view to the improvement or termination of the classes.(c) The Ministry of Pensions, acting through the Local Committees, will make arrangements for payment of maintenance allowances to the students, and for passing them into employment when their training is completed.(4) The Board will provide forms on which particulars of special classes can be sub-mitted, with a view to the assessing of the fee; but it is important that the earliest possible notice of any contemplated proposal should be given to the Board in order that the assistance of their Officers may be available in the planning of the arrangements.
APPENDIX XX TRAINING.Report of Schemes submitted during week ended 26th September 1917.The London Local Committee have submitted a scheme for training disabled men in the Leather Gocds Trade, instruction to be given either in Technical Institutes or Workshops on the following lines :-A,-, Training given in a Technical Institute &apos;The Period of Training to be six months at the Cordwainers Technical College and any other Institutions recognised by the Local Education Authority at which it may subsequently be found convenient to set up classes.     The fees not to exceed 10s. a ^eek per men to include all materials.   Men ordinarily resident in London to be selected by the Trade Panel appointed by the London Local Committeo, who will advise the Committee as to the number of men whom it Is desirable to train.     In the case of men not ordinarily resident In London, the provincial Local Committee to state thut they consider that the men whom they send are suitable for training and that they will be able tc obtain employment in their own districts on the completion of tneir course of instruction,or    B. Training given in factories or workshops.The Period of Training tc be six months, subject tc every man being on probation for a period not exceeding one month and the training to be given in Workshops o** members of the National Leather Goods Manufacturera Association,    Wages to be paid by firms,during training at the following rates :-First two months 7/6 per weekSecond &quot;      &quot;     11/3   &quot;     &quot;TMrd   &quot;      &quot;     15/-   &quot;     &quot;At the conclusion of training the employer to giveeach man a complete set of tools to the value of  5,* . The Glasgow Local Committee have submitted a schemefor training disabled men in hand tailoring at the Royal Technical College, Glasgow, the length of period of training to be 12 months and the fees 7/6 per man per week.     The Scottish Federation of ftierchant Tailors have undertaken tc find employment for all men whom the Committee think it advisable to train, and the attitude of the Local Employers and Trades Unions in the industry towards the scheme is entirely favourable.     In view of the fact that this scheme conforms In all particulars with the Minister&apos;s requirements the Local Committee have been Informed that s anction is given to their proposal to provide this training as part of their general scheme.
3, The Oxford Local Committee have submitted ascheme for training disabled men at the works of the Burford&amp;c. Electric Light and Power Co.,Ltd.   Further information from the Local Committee has been required on various points.4. A scheme submitted by the Denbighshire LocalCommittee for establishing a horticultural training centre for disabled men at the Wrexham Garden Village.     A request has been made by the Welsh Town Planning and Housing Trust that payment of the total sum expended by them fcr providing this training, should be guaranteed by the Minister. The estimated expenditure is  271 per annum and as there may not be a sufficient number of men continuously under training, to provide this amount on the basis of the fee already sanctioned.     sanction has been given for- the payment of such fees as will not exceed the sum of  175 for the 6 months commencing 1st October.These fees are to be paid subject to the followingconditions(a) That not less than 8 men are prepared to accept training under the scheme irom the outset.(b) That suitable arrangements can be made for billeting thte men at reasonable rates, the cost of their board and lodging being defrayed by  he men cut of the allowances made them by the Local Committee.(c) That every effort Is made to Increase the number of cases under training.The Local Committee have been asked to furnish a full statement of the work done,  and the expenses incurred at the end of the fifth month.     It is hoped that the work will be so successful that the fee of 7/6 per man per week will cover all the out-of-pocket expenses.
tra i am.Cases in receipt of oi lowances during training in Technical .itutes and in Factories or Vorkshops in week ended 26/9/17.	In Tech,Instit.	In Factories or Workshops.	Total[reported under lining on 26/9/17.	146	92	238I reported during 1; ;.r: admitted for lining.	42	8	50[ reported during \\: &apos;xb air;charged x- Tr .ining.	1	4*	1ial under Training 26/9/17.	187	1 i i 100	267-   Occupations of men reported as having hegun Training during week Ided 26/9/17.Branch of TradeWo. of den.Agriculture		3Arts and Crafts		3Building		4MCinematograph V.&apos;ork		*.Commercial Work		2Engineering *		0furniture Trude		MLe ather ;.-Ianuf ac toure		4Printing		Professional T-ork		2Tailoring		Textile Industries		Toy Making		MlMiscellaneous		28	Total	50*Engineering includes allied trades such as motor repairing Jotylene welding, electrical work, &amp;c.
ORGANIZATION BRANCH.Extracts from Reports of Inspectors for week ended 25th September 1917.RHONDDA LOCAL COMMITTEE.Visited by the Inspector on Septemoer 6th in order to obtain further information relative to conditions generally. A specially convened meeting was held at Porth to consider the adverse report on the work of this Committee.   There were about 30 members present.   The Chairman, Mr.Nicholas, covered the ground at considerable length on the circumstances which had led to the meeting.   He did not admit that matters were as bad as they had been represented and said that it was for the Inspector to prove his case.   No one knows the Rhondda temperament better than Mr.Nicholas.   It was finally admitted that the office organization had broken down and the only excuse that was offered was their desire to keep down expenses.   Decisions were arrived at to remove the headquarters of the Local Committee to Porth, to take new and suitable offices, to appoint a first class man as whole time Secretary and to re-organize the present staff. For nearly two hours afterwards the Inspector was a target for some of the hottest criticism connected with War Pensions.   With a population of 170,000 people it naturally follows that difficult cases arise and on this occasion they were in strong evidence.The Chairman in conclusion remarked that he felt that . they were started on a new ora and he hoped that the future with their new efforts would bring about the desired reformation. Altogether the meeting was a success, there was plenty of straight talk but no sign of hostility, and the Chairman is to be con-gratulated on the maftfrer in which he conducted a difficult meeting.   The delay of the Authorities in dealing with widows1 cases in the past has bean a factor in the spirit of unrest.PONTYPRIDD LOCAL COMMITTEE.Visited by the Inspector on Scptemoer 7th.   This Committee adjoins Rhondda and it is - remarkable considering all the circumstances how well the Committee has done.    The credit must be given to the out-going Secretary, who has resigned in consequence of increasing duties, and who has been very firm since the start with this Committee.    The out-going Secretary remarked that of all the public work with ?;hioh he was connected the War Pensions work was by far the most difficult.    The same story is told everywhere.   Generally this is a good Committee, kept well in hand and is working smoothly.CARMARTHENSHIRE LOCAL COMMITTEE.Llanelly District Committee.Visited by the Inspector on-September 10th,    The Secretary has promised to place the office organization on a high
level as soon as he is free of the County.   Considerable irritation prevails in Llanelly over delays of the payment of the  3 or  5 to the widow after the notification of the death of a soldier.   Another contentious matter is that of the man being sent home three weeks before discharge with no allowance for hia keep.   This quickly gives rise to dissatisfaotion in an industrial district like Llanelly.As regards disablement.   This Dietriot Committee realisas tho need of attention to this branch of the work and good results may be expeoted.SLAMOHGAN LOCAL COMMITTEE.Visited by the Inspector on 5th September, who had a prolonged interview with the Secretary.   Ths District Committees are rising to a higher standard generally cf organization, Maesteg in partioular.Pontyclyn Dietriot Committee.Previous reports on this Sub-Committee were bad.   Tho Inspector reports that his visit on 4th September shows there had been great improvement.   Many old oases had disappeared in oonBequenoo of the review.   Emergency Grants formerly made for indefinite periods now come under the proper ruling.   Grants for euoh articles as spectacles have ceased.   The measures adopted in oonnection with this Sub-Committee were neoecsarily drastlo but tho objeot to a great extent was aohievedaSWANSEA. Z.OOAS COMMITTEE.The Secretary of the Local Committee is inclined to be a bit lenient.   Ee admitted there had been some irregularities. Rent Allowances had been granted to wives who had marriod their husbands since enlistment.   This.was a oommbn practioe and the Inspector requested that it should be stopped.   Complaints wore made regarding delays in replies from tho Admiralty.   The Committee appears to be keon and sympathetic generally.The lack of aooommodation for tuberculous oases oauses a oertain amount of amriety.MOMOUTH LOOAL COMMITTEE.ibertillery Sub-Committee.The Inspector reports that in spite of the lack of reoords it appears that the Regulations have been on the whole faithfully carried out.   The Secretary of the Sub-Committee appeared not to know of the existence of the Instructions on training and treatment.   This is distressing in an area with a mining population of 35,000 in the heart of Wales.The Inspeotor romarfced that it is most desirable that Abertillery and the four other districts in Monmouthshire who are to be granted autonomy should be notified as soon as possible.
PORTADOWN LOCAL COMMITTEE.Visited on 11th September.   Twenty-five applications have been oonsidored sinoe work started on 1st April; advances made in nine of these.    The work is well and carefully done and the proper interest is bein?.&apos; taken, only a few minor suggestions were made by the Inspector.MIDLOTHIAN LOOAL COMMITTEE, ,Vi3ited on 21st September by the Inspector.   This Committee is in course of re-organization but the Inspector is not too sure that the improvement will be permanent so long as the present Clerk and Treasurer remain in office.EAST RIDING- LOCAL COMMITTEE -No Honorary Auditor can be found for this Local Committee^ accounts.Regarding Enquiry Officers. ,   Some claims are heing held up waiting the appointment of these Officers.   The -Chairman suggested that the East Riding Pension Offioer should be appoint-ed.   This.recommendation Is supported by the Inspector.    It is anticipated that there will be few claims for Alternative Pensions from the East Biding.Training and treatment are being very oarefully gone Into.   This is reported to be a particularly good Committee all round.Holderness Sub-Committee... The Regulations are carefully observed..   A good and careful. Sub-Committee..YORK LOCAfr COMMITTEE.Advances during the last four or five months have been well recovered.   The Committee is working on approved lines and suggestions previously made have been adopted.   Cases are weli and regularly reported on.   The Committee much regrets having no power to help pension oases beyond the small provision in Regulation l3fo) for widows and dependants.N0RTH17MBEBLABD LOCAL COMMITTEE,The administration is hardly satisfactory.   A large number of forms have been printed with many headings that are not really required and the printing account is consequently very heavy.The Inspector proposes to spend a week with the Acting Secretary and Treasurer, paying visits to Sub-Committees wlth&apos;a view to simplifying the work.   The total expenditure of the Central Office during the half year ending 30th June was  13,270,
3 0 dSURREY LOCAL COMMITTEE.The revision of the whole of the oases is being prooee&amp;ed with and the Chairman considers that in a very-short time every case will have been reviewed and brought under the Regulations.   The Inspector went through a large number of cases vhich the Committee had revised and found these in accordance with the Instructions.MIDDLESEX. LOCAL COMMITTEEEnfield Sub-Committee.Case-papers do not contain complete records.Wealdstone Sub-Committee.No infringements of the Regulations.   Accounts are well kept.   Work for disabled soldiers is easily found.   A few oases of training are in course.   The work done by this Sub-Committee 1b good.Sunbury Sub-Committee.The accounts are well kept; those for the Quarter ended 30th June have been audited.   Case-papers are not very well kept.   The work of this Sub-Committee is practically all done by the Secretary and is on the whole Satisfactory, but the Regulations are not thoroughly understood.Staines Sub-Committee.No infringements of the Regulations found.   The Sub-Committee meets irregularly every two or three weeks and in urgent cases the Secretary/ Treasurer and Almoners of the district are authorised to make giants, subject to confirmation. This Sub-CommitteeTs work is well and carefully carried out.
September 26th   1917., ......       - &quot; &quot;-1 Branch	Men. r                        i  i   i	Women *	Total.v ......   ..... i Admini strati on.	4.0	164	204Treatment &amp; Training.	10	25	35Guards to Officers.	12	31	43Guards to Seaman.	16:	31	47Av/ards &quot;to Soldiers	94	1500	1603Alternative Pensions.	6	20	26-/wards to Widows ^ and Dependants. J	27	711	738Pension Issue.	23	1596*	1619*Special Grants Committee.	50	61	111	278	4148*	4426**   Includes   6   Holiday Workers,-STAFF   OF   MINISTRY - OF    PENSIONS,

</content>
</cab>
