<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/27/0 images: 337-338</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^cuiiieirt&quot;^^ Britannic LIajestyrs Government).W A R    .C.1BIOI.ECONOMIC   OFFENSIVE.Memorandum by the, Mini a tor of Ro construe tion* (See also G.T. 2113 and G. 156)In connection with the important questions raised in Sir Edward Oarson!s Memorandum on Economic Offensive (G. 156), it may perhaps be useful to furnish the v/ar Cabinet with certain supplementary informa-tion.The auestion of our requirements and possible supplies of materials for industry after the vJar was the first question to which I devoted attention on undertaking my present duties.The Interim Report r\f Lord Bulfour of 3urleighrs Committee drew attention to certain commodities of which there.might be shortages or or which we and our Allies might possibly be able to secure a substantial measure of control, and a great mass of valuable information has been accumulated by different Departments.   Frits information, however, had not been got together in a collected form and clearly required supplementing in certain directions,   nfter consultation therefore ?/ith Sir Albert Stanley, Lord Robert Cecil and other colleagues, I have arranged to appoint a Materials Supply Committee, with the following Terms of Refer-enceTo consider and report upon -1. The extent of the supplies of raw materials which in their opinioi Jill be required by British manufacturers for the purpose of restoring and developing trade during the period which will elapse between the termination of the War and the restoration of a normal condition of trade2. The extent to which such supplies of materials night be obtained from the United Kingdom or within the Eiapire; or from Allied or Neutral lountries, and to make recommendations for the purpose of securing and  locating any such supplies which might not be available in sufficient lu&amp;ntities and at reasonable prices through the ordinary commercial ihannels.For this wgrk, I have secured the services of t-Sir Charles Fielding Sir Clarendon HydeMr. Cecil Budd (with the concurrence of the Minister of Munitions) Sir Henry BirchenoughSir Henry Babington Smith (with the concurrence of the President Mr. Wallace Thorneycroft    of the Board of Trade) Mr. Andrew Weir (with the concurrence of the Secretary of Statefor War)This Committee will colloct togethereither through individuals or trough sub-committees and consulting with the different trades concern-information on different branches of subjects; such as non-ferrous petals, textile materials, building materials, etc., and arrangements re already well advanced in some directions for these purposes.   The ^formation can then be brought together in a collected form and the uated questions of finance and tonnage presented therewith.   We should hereby obtain very shortly a presentation of our own requirements with aat of the available possible supplies outside enemy countries.I would
28th oeptember 1917(Intdo) C. A.I would suggest as a step preliminary to the conference suggested by oir Edward Carson in his Memorandum at the foot of page 3 that our Ulies should be asked to take similar steps, if they have not already done so.   When we know our own requirements, we shall then be in a position to discuss questions of allocation and tonnage between our-selves and our Allies.In examining this subject, it also became apparent that, in a large number of different Departments, valuable information had been accumulated as to the economic requirements and efforts of the enemy, tut no agency was provided for the information being brought together in a collected form available for those charged with the responsibility of dealing with these matters.    It is also obvious that in this matter it is impossible to separate questions of a possible economic offen-size with those of industrial^requirements.    I therefore ealled a con-ference of the different Departments which possessed or had collected this information, and I found them to consist of the following :-The War Cabinet Secretariat, The Treasury The Colonial Office The Admiralty The War Office The Board of TradeTho War Trade Intelligence Department, and The Department of Information.After conference with my colleagues, with a view (bo bringing all this information into a compact form, I have appointed a Committee under Sir Arthur Steel Maitland as Chairman, consisting of representa-tives ofThe AdmiraltyThe Board of TradeThe Foreign Office (War Trade Intelligence Department) The Ministry of Reconstruction.with the following terms of referenceTo bring together and classify the available information bearing on economic conditions in Enemy, allied and Neutral countries, with special reference (a) to commercial and financial questions likely to arise in connection with peace negotiations, and (b) to the furnishing of such information as may be required by the Minister of Reconstruction for the assistance of the Raw Material or other Committees set up by him.This will, in some measure, help to meet the need suggested in paragraph (2)-at the top of page 3 of Sir Edward Carson&apos;s Memorandum.Our final requirements of materials necessarily:involve an examina- ! tion of the demands upon our industries already formulated or likely to be forthcoming for different classes of work, and this again must affect, in some measure, the order of demobilisation of the Forces. I am not altogether therefore cuite satisfied that the proposal in the final para-graph of the Memorandum on the top of page.4 can fully meet the require-ments of the case, but it will be doubtless considered when tho Cabinet aiscusses tho cuestion as a whole. 1

</content>
</cab>
