<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/206/27 images: 338-341</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(79) 27 80COPY NO6 July 1979CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE:  THE ECONOMIC BACKGROUNDMemorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer1. This paper sets out the economic background against which we mustconsider our future public expenditure plans.2. It is now clear that the early 1970s saw a major turning point in thedevelopment of the world economy, with a dramatic fall in the ability ofeconomies to grow at a satisfactory rate without excessive inflation. Theheightened risk of inflation and the problems of energy supply impose severe]constraints on growth over the next five years.    For most of this period, itis true, this country should be self-sufficient in energy.    We cannot,however, escape the deflationary effects of the energy shortage on the world]economy.    And we will have to contend with the deep-seated domesticproblems of low productivity growth, poor trading performance and strongpressures for higher real wages.3. The economy is currently in a weak condition.    Inflation hasacquired a considerable momentum and (quite apart from the once-for-alleffects of indirect tax increases) is accelerating.    Our externalcompetitiveness has worsened seriously in the past three years. Thecurrent account is weak, despite North Sea oil.    Industrial output andprofitability are low.    Money supply has been growing at, or above, thetop of the old target range of 8-12 per cent, necessitating increased interejrates.    The full effects of many of these developments have yet to be felt.If the next five years are to improve on the poor performance of the lastfive, there is an urgent need to bring about major improvements in inflation]productivity and competitiveness.    This has to be done in a world environ-ment that, to say the least, is unlikely to be favourable.4. Governments themselves cannot regenerate industry.    But they cancreate the conditions in which the market economy can function moreeffectively.    The Budget was the first step in this process.    The majorobjective in this year&apos;s public expenditure decisions must be to ensure thatthis strategy can be continued by leaving sufficient room both forprogressively reducing the growth of money supply and for making furtherreal tax cuts.    This means that we will need to be very tough in ourexpenditure decisions.1SECRET
SECRETINFLATION AND GROWTH5. Our first priority must be to bring down the rate of inflation.Without this, all our other objectives for the economy will remain unfulfilled.To this end it is essential to hold to the guidelines we have set for moneysupply, and, over time, progressively to reduce them.    And we must dothis without driving interest rates higher or severely restricting credit tothe private sector.    This means that we must reduce the public sector&apos;sdeficit, at the very least as a proportion of Gross Domestic Product (GDP).6. These policies will entail accepting a loss of output and employmentin the short-term.    How severe these losses will be, and how long they willlast, will depend partly on how quickly our policies change the climate ofexpectations in which price and pay decisions are made.    Thece is no pastevidence here on which we can draw.    Obviously, the more resolute weshow ourselves in pursuing our policies, the more quickly will the publicbuild these policies into their expectations.    But it would be unrealisticto expect very quick responses.    Though there is good reason for hopingthat GDP and employment will be rising towards the end of the Survey period,we cannot look for much growth over the period as a whole.7. The Treasury&apos;s latest projections, which are broadly in line with theunderlying assessmaats made by many outside forecasters, indicate a fallin output and a steep rise in unemployment in the early part of the period,with a recovery in the later part as inflation moderates.    These projectionsassume a growth in world trade at about half the pace recorded in the decadeto 1973.    This itself could be optimistic, particularly for the yearsimmediately ahead.    The projections also assume that public expenditure iscut on the scale envisaged in the Chief Secretary&apos;s earlier paper (C(79) 11),with an adjustment to social security spending to allow for higher levels ofunemployment than the working assumptions used for the Survey and shownin Annex D of C(79) 25;  and that tax allowances, bands and specific dutiesare fully indexed.    The growth of money supply is assumed to beprogressively reduced, to 7 per cent in 1983.    On these assumptions theprojection&quot; show the economy eventually moving on to what should be a soundand sustainable growth path.    The speed at which this takes place will depenon how quickly our policies lead to a change climate of expectations. Butthe intervening period is bound to be a very difficult one, in which we willhave little room for manoeuvre,8. The poor prospects for growth over the next three years or soreflect the combination of a number of adverse developments:a. World trade is depressed, and is likely to remain so forsome considerable time. The latest oil price increases seemcertain further to curtail world growth.2SECRET
SECRETb. Productivity in United Kingdom industry is extremely low.On the latest evidence it looks as though the estimates ofproductivity growth included in the last Governments publicexpenditure White Paper, though substantially lower than earlierestimates, were not low enough.    Our tax reductions, and othermeasures to restore incentives, should in time help to improveproductivity.    But in the next few years these beneficial effectsare likely to be more than offset by the impact of falling outputand investment.    Excluding North Sea oil, we cannot count enoutput per head rising at more than half the 2f per cent averagedin the years 1964-74.c. The trading performance of our manufacturing sector is poor,and its cost competitiveness has been seriously weakened byincreases in pay far in excess of productivity.    In the short runthis loss of competitiveness has been increased by the appreciationof the exchange rate.d. The need to reduce inflation will entail tight fiscal andmonetary policies that will reduce the pressure of demand.In time, the adverse factors should be overcome; but it seems clear thatthe next three years are going to be a very difficult time.PROSPECTS FOR THE PUBLIC SECTOR BORROWING REQUIREMENTAND TAXES9. These poor prospects for growth together with the likelihood ofdifferentially high pay increases in the public services in the next twoyears as a result of comparability awards mean that substantial reductionsin the volume of public expenditure will be necessary if the Public SectorBorrowing Requirement (PSBR) is to be contained.    Increased pay is aparticularly important element in 1980-81:  it is assumed in the projections,on the basis of existing commitments and a judgment on the likely outcomeof the Clegg reviews, that earnings in the pnblic services will be 18-^ per centhigher in that year than in 1979-80 (implying an increase of S.4j billion inthe public service pay bill).    Earnings in the private sector are assumed tobe about 14 per cent higher and retail prices about 13^ per cent higher.These assumptions for earnings are of course highly uncertain, but giventhe commitment to honour comparability awards it would be imprudent tocount upon a significantly more favourable outcome for the public services.Increases in pay and prices thus add enormously to the projected total ofexpenditure at current prices in that year.10. The table below summarises the Treasury&apos;s projections of thePSBR (on tiie fiscal assumptions noted above of full indexation of taxes andpublic expenditure cuts on the scale envisaged in C(79) 11.3SECRET
SECRETPublic Sector Accounts(  billion at current prices)1979-80 1980-81General Government receipts 76.2 87.7General Government expenditure 85. 1 97. 0Public Sector Borrowing Requirement               8.3 9.2PSBR as % of GDP at market prices                  4. 4% 4. 2%11.       For later years, the margins of uncertainty are of course enormous,but the projections suggest that the PSBR would remain around its 1980-81proportion of GDP in the following year (implying a rise to about  10 billionin current prices) and would decline quite sharply in the final year of theSurvey.12. The implication of these projections is that the levels of publicexpenditure implied in C(79) 11, which would involve cuts from theinherited plans of about  6^ billion in 1980-81 (at 1979 Survey prices),would leave no room for real tax cuts in the 1980 and 1981 Budgets.13. Progress towards our objective of reducing the basic income tax rateto 25p would require further cuts in public expenditure (or a further switchto indirect taxes, which would put up prices).    The size of the additionalcut would depend partly on its composition, but if the cut were wholly ongoods and services, as a rough rule of thumb every lp off the standard ratein 1980-81 would entail a cut of  0. 7 billion in expenditure at 1979 Surveyprices.CONCLUSION14.       We face a very difficult economic prospect over the next few years.There is little hope of any significant growth of the economy until inflationhas been substantially brought down.    To this end, it is vital to hold to ourpolicies of containing the PSBR and reducing the growth of money supply andto establish a firm conviction that we intend to do so.G HTreasury Chambers6 July 19794SECRET

</content>
</cab>
