<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/64/0 images: 78-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
French Embassy, - 11th Sept. 1918-.TRANSLATION.&quot;In face of the acts of devastation committed by the German troops during their present withdrawal on French territory, the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs have instructed the French Ambassador to sub-mit the following observations to His Majesty&apos;s Government.In the course of their hurried retreat the Germans are again resorting to systematic destruction. The method and extent of these devastations as well as thecold-blooded fury and ferocity shown by the presence-v  ofSlSUi   CIRCULATED TO THE KrrO AND ?IAR CABINET&apos;   EELM1SE&apos;This Note raises questions which are quite outside purely Foreign Office activities and can only he settled by the Cabinet,&quot;(Initialled)   A.J.B. ......oOo------Foreign Office,September 18th, 1918.
A     Kho&quot;   2  rof jUrfermljnaohljiefirand time-fuse bombs, which are hidden in the villages and the few buildings which - -remain undestroyed, have made a profound impression on French opinion.The French Government consider that they cannot remain indifferent to such procedure, or accept in * silence the patience and courage of our soldiers and civil population in the face of these barbarous methods of destruction and massacre, which are contrary, not only to the law of nations, but to the dictates of humanity.The French Government have decided, therefore, to institute a searching enquiry into the matter and to collect forthwith evidence from soldiers and prison-era who have witnessed the atrocities committed by the enemy in.the invaded districts on his withdrawal in face of the Allied armies. The Commission which hap- been entrusted with investigating the crimes committed, by the enemy in violation of international law, &quot;riii undertake the task of collecting the exactevidence indispensable to such an enquiry.It will not, however, suffice to lay this collection of evidence before the public opinion of the world, K, Pichon is considering whether it would not be well to secure a solemn declaration on the part of the Allies, having as its object the punishment of, and reparation for, these crimes.This declaration could be drafted in very general terms, since any Indication of definite reprisals would give rise to certain disadvantages,M. Paul Cambon would, be glad to receive the views of His Majesty1 s Government in regard to this pro-no sal, and. he would take this occasion to renew to . Mr. Balfour the-assurances of his high consideration,Albert Gate House, 11th September 1918,

</content>
</cab>
