<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/64/0 images: 142-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/if. p-pwAf......CABfifeM B M 0 S A I D U M/a0OHI3W.....A G E.......-:S:.U A T I;Q M,BY THE MINISTRY 01? LABOUR ON MEMORANDUM G.7,5706,In the absence of the Minister of Labour I submit certain comments on the memorandum G.T. 5706 Submitted by the Committee on Production.Generally the Ministry of Labour endorses the arguments of the Committee on Production, with special reference to the difficulties consequent upon the settlement of wage advances by negotiation between the State and powerful labour organisations, In so far as the wage situation can be met by the addition to the pre-war wage of a bonus calculated in relation to the increased cost of living, I am in entire agreement with the Committee on Production that it is essential for all the chief organised industries of the country to have their wage advances settled by reference to one- central arbitration authority, independent of any Government Department,   To permit such organisations as the Bailwaymen, the Miners or even the Police to use their power in war time to bargain with a State department, is direotly to encourage similar action throughout the whole of the overstrained munitions industry.     The difficulties of bringing such bodies within the Munitions of War Act are obvious and serious.     It may not,,however, be necessary to do more than announce as an administrative decision that the,chief industries which are not compelled by Part I.j of the 1915 Act or have not agreed to refer their claim for wage advances to an Arbitration Tribunal, should have in future to make their case for a rise to such a Tribunal,     If this decision is taken, it must be enforced absolutely in the case . of labour organisations, which like the railwaymen and the metiers receive their wages directly from the State under present conditions.It is also highly desirable that as maxy industries as possible should agree to a periodic review of their wages before one central Tribunal, and that so far as is practicable, this review should take place at the same time for all industries,I think it necessary, however, to call the attention of the War Cabinet to one consequence that will follow such a course. The standard of wages during&apos; the war is determined generally by the munitions standard, and the standard paid direct by the State to Miners, Railwaymen, etc.    Private industry and publio utility companies either trading as private concerns or as municipal bodies, follow these standards, although their financial position is not comparable to that of the State.     It is clear that the wage advances in certain industries whoso productivity is handioapped by the war situation, or whose prices are regulated by State decree as in the case of the bread, or who depend upon public rates for financial assistance, are now perilously near the line at which either they will be unable to follow the State standards and thus tend to discredit the authority of the Arbitration Tribunal, or will demand from the State some sub-&quot;sentlon in order to meet the demands of the State that in national interests they shall keep running.     This might involve the subsidy of Private Industries./ As
As a matter of faot the Ministry of Labour are not clear that the proposals of the Committee on Production, even if fully adopted, will meet the wage situation in industries outside the shipbuilding, engineering and allied trades, i.e., the important industries which are not strictly munitions, and from their knowledge of the situation they are satisfied that these proposals will not in any way restore the stability within the munitions industry which is essential to a proper solution of the industrial situation, especially if the war lasts much longer.    I understand that the Ministry of Munitions are submitting a memorandum drawing particular attention to this po^nt, and in the circumstances the Ministry of Labour content themselvefe with putting forward to the War Cabinet certain general features of the wages situation, which they consider of the highest importance:1,   With the shortage of labour, and the necessity in the national interests of preventing any prolonged stopppfgge.   Labour has the State and Industry in its power undess the State faoes the position properly.   If organised labour chose seriously to exploit this position, no admistrative solution would be effective, and peace would only be bought toy a series of financial concessions. Happily there is not the slightest evidence that organised labour is in a temper to exploit their power without regard to the we&amp;l-being of the community as a whole.   It is true that certain sections . not confined to labour, intelligent, well-organised, and extremely vocal, are prepared to do so, but it must be stated that in doing so they believe that they are fighting not the State, but private capital.   It &amp;s true also that without bad intent, sections in the munitions industry have utilised and continue to use the war position to, get sectional wage advances.   It is these advances whioh have disturbed the whole level of the wage situation and having regard to tho general attitude of organised labour as exemplified in Mr. Thomas&apos; acceptance of the Governments terms once he v/as con-vinoed of their justice, it is important to realise the chief oauses of this desire for sectional bargaining.2. When the first Munitions of War Act was passed, lafeoui surrendered its power of bargaining, and on the significance of that surrender it is unnecessary to dwell.   It was, however, understood at the time that capital with equal generosity would surrender its power of obtaining lucrative oontraots at the expense of the State, and that the State would take from capital profits which could be reasonably attributed to the war situation. The Government has been on the whole more rigorous in compelling Labourtto abftde by this bargain than Capital, and the Ministry of Labour is convinced that the deliberate use of its bargaining power by skilled labour in the munitions industry is mainly, if not entirely, due to the fact that they see the firms for whom they are working paying enormous dividends taken ultimately from the States and that in their demand for higher wages, they are not anxious that the State should continue to compensate the employer, but that tho employer should, in fulfilment of the bargain in 1915, cut down his dividends to meet their demands.   I venture to emphasize that no solution of jrhe wages position during the war can hope^o &quot;stand lor a moment unless &quot;the TypvernmerrFIs prepared&quot; seriously Tq face&quot; &apos; TKe^fosItion of &quot;Government contracts as alBclbsed py the Excess I Profits returns. * j      ^&apos;      3, Arising out of this paragraph, the Ministry of Labou^ once again ask the War Cabinet to consider seriou&amp;Ly. a definite  ^ announcement on behalf of the whole Government that a Bill toraptors/Z.
restore trade union conditions, as honestly as is possible under the change situation of the war, has been drafted, and will be submitted to Parliament a&apos;:; the earliest possible moment.   The effect of such a prcjso-.ro^ntric might go far to clear up the whole industrial si tea Mon. the trouble of which has been caused as much by distrust oi the Gojernmenfs intentions, as perhaps anything else,   That thai distruct may be unfounded unfortunately will not-dispose of its existence.4. The Ministry of.labour submit that it is academic for the Committee on Production to bolieve that tho wage   position can be met by an addition to the pre-war wage of a bonus nicely calculated on a statistical cost of livu^   Organised labour has awakened to a consciousness of its power, not only in the economic world, but as a constituent element of the political State,   I believe that it will not be content ever to accj^t wages whioh maintain a pre-war standard.   The claim of labour now,is for a greater share in the control of the conditions under which it works, and  fir a more equitable ratio between profits and wages.   Wo hope tfcat the Whitley Councils will go far to meet both those claims without damaging industry, but they cannot be successful in the difficult years of reconstruction if they inherit from State administration, a wago situation founded on opportunism and inequality.I venture to emphasize to the War Cabinet tho gravity of tfc&amp;s aspect of the position.   In my opinion the solution of the present wages situation is as vitally important, for the reconstruction of industry, as was the negotiation in 1915, which led up to setting industry on a war basic   EqualXfciryof rationing, the levelling of the cost of living between rural and urban districts, the change of the position of the agricultural labour under the Corn Production Act, oven the application of a flat wat bonus &quot;. irrespective of skill or craft or pre-war earnings arc factors which have disturbed the whole indtfcBtrial position.   There are forces in labour which would only be too glad to use this disturbance for their own ends, and I believe that not only to ensure the smooth running of the war machine, but to obtain a stable foundation for the reconstruction of Industry,   it is necessary that a thorough and urgent examination of the wages situation should take place immediately, and I venture to express the hope that the War Cabinet wi&amp;L appreciate the seriousness of the whole position, both in the present for the Adminstetive Departments, and for the future, and will allow time for suggestions,to be put forward without committing themselves to an immediate acceptance of the proposals fif the Committee on     ,;. Production,(SIGNED)   D.J .Shackleton20/9/18.

</content>
</cab>
