<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 51-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C A 31 N E T .J3705.GGSFESWSCB at (nwxaWith reference to 0 .P. 3698 the attached further statements regarding the forthcoming Conference at Genoa, which have been sent to aie cemi-officially by the Italian Embassy, are circulated to the Cabinet for information.(Sgd:.) M,?JU HABE&amp;secretary.Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 8th February, 1922..
Immediately the decision wan taken to hole, the Conference . of Genoa, the Italian Ministry of Posts and Telegraphs con-corned tliemsclv.es with the extraordinary requirements of the postal * wireless, telegraphic and telephonic communications, with a view to placing these services in a position to fully meet the needs.A sum of 12 millions lire was placed at the disposal of the Ministry, a -programme of work was .quickly arranged - and experts and officials were urgently sent to&apos;.Genoa to direct end supervise the work.The principal steps taken, in addition to -all the improve-ments already planned, are as follows-:-(l) Hew telegraphic and telephonic wires are being placed on the lines Genoa/Milan, Genoa/Turin, and Genoa/Vcntindg 1 ia and Milan/Trieste for the&apos; connection with the international linos.(a) A complete telegraphic and telephonic office is being installed at the Royal palace, where-the Conference will take&apos; place and a similar office, with even larger means, will be installed, in the Palace specially destined for the Press. Such Palace is in the centre of&apos; the City and near the Royal palace(3) A special telephonic exchange will be set up and special wires laid down to connect, the apparatus placed in the   E.cya-1 palace,&apos; in the palace&quot; of the- Press and at the residences of the various Delegations,- of the Authorities of the City,, and all the other Offices, directly or indirectly concerned with the Conference.   -   .&apos;-. &apos;    . (4)/- 1 -
(4) So far as the service with&apos;England and America is con-cernecl, arrangements are being made with the French adroinistra-tion to secure telegraphic communication with printing apparatus Baudot, each sector of which can transmit about 1C00 words hourly, with fourteen sectors on.the Genoa/Paris line, 10 sectors on Genoa/London, two sectors for Genoa/Brussels.   All this in.    &apos;     &apos; ....... *. .....addition to the oreinary communication which Pome, Turin and Milan already have with France and Great Britain..(5) Special consideration has also been given to- the wireless service.    There are three existing stations of Oolta.no, Can Paolo and Gentocelle through which the Genoa office can comma-... communicate direct with France, -.Great Britain, Germany, Russia, Hungary and Spain.   A new 15 kilowatt station is being erected at Spczia for the service of the Conference.    This station, in direct communication with Genoa, will be in a position to communicate with Carnarvon and Hauen for Great Britain and America.    If conditions arc favourable it is also possible to transmit direct to America from the station of San Paolo.(3) Negotiations are pending with the neighbouring, States to obtain telephonic communication with the principal centres abroad.   Pew wires are laid on. the Italian territory and amplifiers are being fixed in Turin and Milan&apos;,  so that telephonic communication between Genoa/ Paris, Genoa/London and Genoa/ Brussels will be guaranteed, provided the French Administration give the necessary-assistance, on their part.The steps already taken are official; however any suggestions or proposals wcuid be. immediately considered by the Italian Minister of Posts and Telegraphs..th February, 1922.
THE GENOA, CONFERENCE. &apos;COUNTRIES,, WHICH HAVP &apos;ACCEPTED INVITATION. m&apos; The invitation to the Conference has &quot;been accepted up -to now by.:.the &quot;Governments which are members of. the Supreme Council-, except the United States; and also by the following countries:-Albania, Austria, BulgariaCzech,o-Slovakia, Denmark, Esthonia, Finland,. Germany, Greece / Holland, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Poland, Portugal, Russia,- Romania, Spain Sweden.All these countries have accepted the invitation, but some of them-have asked,, in order to better compose their. -Delegations, to have.-some-&apos;.more -particulars regarding the programme &quot;Of the Genoa Conference.Prance, on -the 2nd instant, communicated, through the &apos;Havas Agency,-that a3 the invitation to the Conference and its programme had been fixed at Cannes with the co-operation Of the French Government, it would not be necessary to signify her acceptance.Never, up to now., as far as the Italian Government is. concerned, has. there been an idea of a postponement of- the Conference.-&apos;.&quot; &apos;6th February, 19.22.

</content>
</cab>
