<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 101-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C^F.3715. C A B I 13 S. T.REPORT BY THE G3H3RAL OFFICER COMMATilDIBC-IN-CHIEF OS THE SITUATION 101 IRSLAO FOR WS3K--3J!I)IKG 4th FS3RUARY.,  1.922.Since iny last report the following units hare left Ireland for Croat Britain.:-31st Jan nary,1st. Sherwood Foresters 1st. Middlesex Regt.-Bde- HvQ. &amp; 2 Batteries 7thr Brigade- R.G.A.from Slribberee:1st February,2nd:. luCclwI,2 Batteries 7th. Brigade RCA. 1st Bn, M.G-, Corps,2nd February.1st Gloucestershire Regt.1st Bedfordshire &amp; Hertfordshire Regt, . .Bdo-HD^Qrs, &amp; 2 Batteries End Bde .R,F.A.3rd February,1st. E.R.R.C.1st. Manchester Regt.2 Batteries 2nd, Brigade, R,.F*A.6 th February,.3rd. Rifle Brigade2nd Cameron HighlandersBde .H2\Okrs. &amp; 2 Batteries 1st Bde.R0F.*A,Tho following Units are due to sail tc-day1st. Northumberland Fusiliers. 1st. Devonshire Regt. KcLQrs. 6th Bivsickal Artillery. 98th. Battery R,F*A. 13 6th.     &quot; &quot;Depot Royal Dublin Fusiliers De ta iIs of Dep ot R * Muns ter Fns ,VTtrTr trTTtrn0 J 0 GC ill .L .Moere Park.Dublin Moore Park. Ballyvonare,Kanturfc-Sligo. For racy.RillyKlstlaFBallincolligFermoy.&quot;   Dublin&quot;   Queenstown,&apos;r Kilkenny.&apos;&quot;-   Car low. &quot;   Waterford. Cork. Fethard. KilkennyHaasTralee.The&apos; following Units have change o their stations inIreland; -3rd February.1st R. Warwick Regt. 2nd, Green Howards.6th February2nd, II. Staff.Regt,Kewoastle West to Ballylclnlar. Tipperary to Ballincollig.Henagh to Queenstown,
and to-day 2 companies of the 1st Northamptonshire HeBt.ir.ove from Birr to the Curragh;.On account of the Railway strike many of the lines In Southern Ireland have been elossd, with the result a that moves of troops, which oho aid have bo en carried out by rail, have had to .be carried out by Motor Transport.The evacuation of Stores has consequently been c!alayad:. and&apos; the move of the 1st. Kingf3 Regiment, vshlch shoulfi haya takon place on 1st, February, has been postpones.The only outrage of importance reported daring the -week: was the holding up of a Ford Van with its escort at Boyle Station on the 27th January,       The Ford Van and two rifles were stolen;.It is reported from Cork this morning that the Motor Oar conveying Colonel-Commandant Elgginson and two officers from Quo ens town to Cork yesterday was fire? 3 on by armed men.. The driver of the Car was slightly wounded but no pas nail-ties, occurred amongst the officers who returned the fire-,      One civilian was severely wounded, but he is believed not to have been implicated In the: outrage .(Signed). J. BRIdl),Colonel,for -Ooinmanding-in-Ghisf, I33I.:AE!Dtar;H0Q.., Ireland,7 th- February.,. 19 20.

</content>
</cab>
