<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 112-114</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TiilS DCCbMNUT. 13 Trt,. PROPERTY OF MIS BRITAhlilD      JKC/IY&apos; S C-0&apos;7KRT-l      1S ill C R i.j T .C-p.   3717-BhlTISii TROOPS JQMjlOBUL. Memo; by the S, of 8.  for WarThe Colonial Secretary desires, that wLien our military    , forces evacuate mosuI a company of Armoured Cars should be left behind there, together with a squadron R.A.F.    I&apos;-append a memorandum on this question by the General Staff.    - -( Intd.) LVW.E,The War Office,9th February&quot; 1922, - :&apos;1013/2 580.       The General Staff have&quot; taken note of the letter from theColonial Office dated 3rd February, 19.22, in which the Colonial Secretary strongly supports the Air Ministry and the High Commissioner:of:;.Iraq in their view that the squadron R.A.F. and the company of Armoured Cars should be left at Mosul,&apos; after the withdrawal of the British troops, but they are unable to alter their original views on this matter,When the existing garrison in Iraq was accepted at the Cairo Conference, one of the basic conditions was the creation of a friendly Turkey,    Far from this condition having been realised the recent telegrams of Sir Percy Cox show that the probability of Turkish aggression is becoming daily more Imminentjftieh the present garrison in ifostil is withdrawn the Air Squadron and Armoured Car Company will be completely Isolated and there can be no question of sending any column to extricate them, -&apos; V,:. It
.   2. &quot; 102- It is a mistake to think that either the Squadron or the Armoured Car Company inspire the Turks or the turbulent inhabitants with any degree of awe,  and. directly the rest of the Mosul garrison has departed the situation of these 2 units will be precarious..    At the instigation of the Turks and. inoividual extremists amongst the population, there will probabl-- be frequent attempts to loot and damage the stores and equipment which will have to be left in charge of these units, and the guard and sentry duties will prove ah increasing strain upon them.v/hen they are directly threatened with an attack either by the lurks or by rebel tribes, their only hope will be to extricate themselves before the attack materialises, for obviously they cannot hope to crush their enemies unaided, and it will be impossible to reinforce them.   As far as the Armoured Car Company is concerned It is extremely doubtful whether it can possibly succeed in such an attempt.The establishment of this unit is 14 officers, 202 Other Ranks, 16 Armoured Cars, 11 Motor Gars and. 5 kotor cycles.Out of the total strength of over 200 personnel only 48 are normally carried in the Armoured Cars,   The number might be increased to a maximum of 5 per car making 80, but freedom of free action would be greatly cramped.In any case over 100 personnel must be carried in open vehicles and also tho petrol, water, and rations for the whole party for a journey of some 300 miles.The local tribes are now by experience well acquanted with the limitations of these units, and their usual way of ,dealing with.them is to creep in under cover of darkness and cut the tyres, thus immobilising the vehicles,    Apart from this danger, when leaving aosul the. cars must keep to the road, for some 15 miles or so out of the town and. the road, winds up several steep hills with hairpin bends,.    It may be  confidently predictedthat
that this road will be rendered impassable at such places and that ambushes will be laid for the&apos;men., when they get out to try and clear -a wa? for the cars,        .... . &quot;There are also several wooden&apos;bridges which can be easily destroyed, , ; -In view,of these considerations&apos; the General Staff-are obliged to contemplate the likelihood of this- small detachment being over-whelmed, possibly within a.few.weeks of the withdrawal of the rest of tho Mosul garrison,, for the assistance which could be given by,the Levies or by the Arab .Army at - this early stage of its development may be ignored.The General Staff realise, that military objections must at times be over-ruled.-for-reasons of policy., but in this case the-alternatives se-em to. be .to withdraw the whole garrison now, as a logical outcome of the reduction of the forces in Iraq,, or to leave a detachment which may be forced to try to withdraw at any moment but -may fail disastrously .In- the attempt..It is hardly necessary, to add that in any.case the course,advocated by the Air Ministry,, and supported by the Colonial Ofr\ip.e,  is in complete variance, with the doctrines of war and is strongly opposed by the General Officer Commanding In Iraq.If the political reasons for retaining this detachment in Mosul are overwhelming perhaps all military objections may have to be discounted, but the; General-Staff feel-bound to add that they can see no - political gain which will in any way compensate for the consequences, political   as well as.military of the defeat and. capture, of theso british units .. : .   -    .General Staff*tfar Office, 9th February,  1922 *

</content>
</cab>
