<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 312-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
v La. \.   . &quot;oC &amp; i v.. tfl-i-L-1    KsvA [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government.jPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1922.SECRET.CP. 3746.CABINET.SPECIAL WEEKLY REPORT ON UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 57.WEEK ENDED EEBBTJARY 10, 1922.THE  SITUATION.The position in industry generally remains the same. Employment in coal-mining shows little change. The improvement recorded in the iron and steel industry is very slight, and the position is very unstable. In shipping and marine engineering there is little new work being carried out, but a certain amount of activity in repairing is reported on the Thames and in the South Wales ports. The improvement in the woollen trade is maintained, but there is no change in the situation in the cotton industry. The hosiery trade, however, continues to be brisk. General engineering is still very depressed. The improvement recorded in the motor and cycle section is very slight. Employment in the tinplate trade remains the same. There are no signs of improved employment in the building industry. The improve-ment in the tanning and linoleum industries in Lancashire is continued.T. J. MACNAMARA,,Ministry of Labour
note on unemployment situation in united kingdom onfebruary 10, 1922.1. The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent.The average for the ten years prior to the war, according to Trade Union unemployment figures, was 4-7 per cent. It was as high as 7-8 per cent, in 1908 and 7-7 per cent, in 1909.During 1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent, in September and 3-2 per cent, in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.During 1920 it ranged between 0-9 per cent, in April and 6-0 per cent, in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.The figures for 1921 were : To the end of  Per centJanuary    ...        ... 6-9February ... 8-5March      ...        ... 100   .April       ...        ... 17-6May        ...... 22-2June        ...        ... 23 1The figures for 1922 are : January    ...        ... 168JulyAugustSeptemberOctoberNovemberDecemberPer cent. 16-7 16-3 14-8 15-6 15-9 16-52. Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges.1920.				1921.				Ang. 27.		Nov. 12.	Dec. 3.	July 1.	July 22.	 	Oct. 7.	Oct. 14.Men  Civilians Ex-service Boys             . .-Women Girls	86,1/76 142,600 17,608 58,982 17,430	134,868 239,816 21,872 97,964 22,237	137,222 263,553 21,379 119,886 23,663	1,068,288 488,722 80,539 466,965 65,883	934,528 471,233 67,085 345,112 49,528	 	11,060,812* 53,133 224,487 38,336	1,072,867* 52,354 221,279 37,740Totals   ..	818,096	516,757	565,703	2,170.397	1,867,486	-	1,376,768	1,384,2401921.	Oct. 21.	Oct. 28.	Nov. 4.	Nov. 11.	Nov. 18.	Nov. 25.	Dec. 2.	DealMen  Civilians Ex-service Boys Women Girls Totals ..	j. 1,106,531* 51,465 228,111 37,685	1,252,117* 56,560 263,281 39,518	1,332,461* 61,117 294,105 41,156	1,377,949* 62,342 307,346 41,795	1,399,065* 62,174 313,797 41,700	1,411,254* 61,370 318,880 41,681	1,414,632* 60,684 318,032 40,661	1,412,3! 59,9 321.j 40,11	1,423,792	1,611,476	1,728,839	1,789,432	1,816,736	1,833,185	1,834,009	1,833,6:1921.Dec. 16.Dec. 23.Men Civilians Ex-serviceBoysWomenGirlsTotals.1,406,309*58,734 319,156 38,6381,822,8371,402,315*58,100 314,556 38,7291,S13,700Dec. 30.1,451,434*60,103 333,671 40,5351,885,7431922.Jan. 10.1,481,713*65,690 340,967 46,4191,934,789Jan. 17.      Jan. 24,1,475,256*66,790 336,708 47,1821,925,9361,466,823*66,890 333,696 47,7731,915,182Jan. 31.1,458;443*66,740 332,923 47,8271,905,933Feb. 111,446,65,1 332,2 47,*1,892,1* Separate figures for ex-service men no longer available.
	Wholly Unemployed.		Short Time.		Numbers Unemployed.	Number on Benefit.	Number Working Short Time.*	Number paid Benefit during Week.Men Boys Women Girls	193,077 9,093 49.038 6,819	190,644 4,888 46,558 3,423	11,384 250 2,763 457	2,579 87 1,160 257total	258,027	245,513	14,854	4,083* the number given represents workpeople who are engaged on short time in a manner which enables them to comply with the rules as to continuity of benefit. Workpeople who are unable so to comply are excluded.&apos;ec.41232 if 40j.833.i. summary of action taken by the government. [from autumn 1920 to autumn 1921.]cabinet unemployment committee,The prospect of a severe trade depression first became evident in the early autumn of 1920. On the 13th August, 1920, there was a special discussion at a meeting of the Cabinet, when the Cabinet Unemployment Committee was appointed to consider the whole question and devise means for relieving unemployment.[This Committee has since been in constant session and has, up to the 10th February, 1922, held 42 meetings.The problem of unemployment in one form or another has also been before the Cabinet on 56 occasions between the 13th August, 1920, and the 10th February, 1922.] b &apos;(a.) unemployment insurance.An Unemployment Insurance Bill of general scope was passed into law on the 9th August, 1920, and came into operation on the 8th November following. The Act applied compulsory insurance against unemployment to 12,000,000 persons as compared with 4,000,000 previously. Subsequent amending Acts modified the conditions as regards rates of benefit and the amount thereof which could be drawn. Contributions were also increased and authority given to borrow money from the Treasury up to  20,000,000.table showing amount paid out in unemployment benefit during the period november 8, 1920, to february 4, 1922,eb.446651 332471 892Source of Contribution.	Amount.Employers Employed persons State State (in respect of benefit for ex-regular sailors, soldiers and airmen) Advances by Treasury Provision from accumulated reserve fund	13,291,100 12,124,400 6,502,360 1,610,000 10,140,000 20,708,303Total..	64,376,163[7887]	B 23. Numbers receiving Unemployment Benefit and Numbers on Short Time inUnited Kingdom.The number of persons in receipt of benefit on the 7th February was &quot;1,794,000 wholly unemployed and 285,000 on part-time.4. Unemployment in the Greater London Area, February 7.
(B.) Emergency Works and other Measures.A full statement of the measures taken in the autumn of 1020 and of the later measures from autumn 1021 onwards has been set out in previous issues of this Report. At least 250,000 men have had employment on these schemes at various times, and at the present time over 124,000 men are employed, exclusive of the work provided for men in ancillary occupations and the effect of the Export Credits and Trade Facilities Act schemes (see table below).SUMMARY SHOWING THE LABOUR EMPLOYED AT FEBRUARY 3, 1922, ON CERTAIN OF THE ABOVE SCHEMES DESCRIBED IN SECTIONS I AND II ABOVE.Scheme	Number Employed in Greater London.	Number Employed in Provinces.	Total.1. Arterial roads 2. Road maintenance 3. Housing (acceleration of lay-outs, &amp;c.) .. 4. Unemployment Grants Committee 5. Alternative work  War Office.. Admiralty 6. Local Authorities (without grants) 7. Land drainage 8. Forestry 9. Light railways 10. Office of Works 11. Acceleration of Government  contracts (G.P.O.)........	7,696 * &apos;593 4,942 1,170 Nil 2,243 Nil Nil No information 347 100 (about)	25,357 * 2,597 40,506 Nil 1,864 8,407 3,602 4,137 No information 500 (about)	33,053 20,000 3,190 45,448 1,170 1,864 10,650 3,602 4,137 347 600 (about)Totals	17,091t	86,970t	124,061* No separate figure for London and Provinces available.t Plus number (unknown) employed on road maintenance. [As reports for week ended the 3rd February, 1922, have been received from only 485 Local Authorities out of 502 who were asked to supply information (in respect of items 3,4 and 6 above) it is probable that the relief schemes inaugurated by the Government and Local Authorities are finding employment for a number of men in excess of the figures given.]PROGRESS ON  LATER MEASURES. 1. Loans and Overdrafts to Boards of Guardians.Nature of Assistance.	Number of Unions concerned.	Amount.		 Loans granted Overdrafts, current Sanctions under Section 3 of Local Authorities (Financial Provisions) Act Application for  sanction  to  borrow  under Section 3 Application  for  sanction  to  borrow under Section 3 over two years Application for extension of loan period	12 34 54 10 6 5	500,000 1,322,500 2,970,526 291,100 397,810 171,676Totals	121	5,653,6122. Unemployment Grants Committee.Grants made on Basis of 60 per cent, of Wages Bill since September 10, 1921.Number of Schemes Sanctioned.	Number of Local Authorities Assisted.	Total Cost of Schemes.	Total Cost of Labour.	Maximum Grant Sanctioned.	Additional Men expected to be Employed.854*	514*	  2,271,767*	  1,560,717*	  845,992*	37,030* Decrease due to the fact that only 2 schemes were sanctioned during the week, and that 4 schemes were abandoned or withdrawn.
3. Grants towards Loan Charges.(a.) Applications.Date.	Number of Local Authorities making Application.	Number of Schemes Submitted.	Total Estimated Cost of Schemes.	Number of Men expected to be Employed.February 9,1922	720	2,410	  23,395,292	120,000				(for average of				7 months.)(b.) Grants Sanctioned.Date.	Number of Local Authorities Assisted.	Number of Schemes Approved.	Total Estimated Cost of Schemes.	Loans Sanctioned.	Number of Men expected to be Employed.February 9, 1922	831*	1,323	  13,917,478	  13,153,207	73,257 (for average of 7 mouths)4. Trade Improvement Schemes.(a.) Export Credits.Date.	Credits given.								Advances 		Guarantees 		Floating Credits.		Guaran-tees to Banks under Part 2 of Export Credits Extended Facilities.	Total Sanc-tioned.	Sanctioned.	Taken up.	Sanctioned.	Taken up.	Sanctioned.	Taken up.		October 27,1921(i.*., before new scheme operated) February 9, 1922 .. Increase	  2,916,780 3,083,211	  1,309,119 1,448,647	  730,465 2,410,240	  62,037 413,005	  1,685,850	  35,998	  10,700	  3,647,245 7,190,001	166,431	139,528 1 1,679,775		350,968	1,685,850	35,998	10,700	3,542,756(&amp;.) Guarantee up to 25 Millions for Capital Works. Totals to Date.Week ending-Guarantees Given or Sanctioned.Interest or Principal on-Total to Date.5. Overseas Settlement.Month ended 	Free Passages to ex-Service Men and their Dependants Granted to Date.   Number of Persons 	Expenditure to Date.		 January 31, 1921	69,869	1,586,877* The actual number of authorities receiving assistance is 462 ; the figure given represents the number of separate authorities shown week by week in the Schedules. [7887]
6. Land Drainage, Forestry, Light Railways.Form of Work.	Week ended 	Number of Schemes Approved.	Amount Involved.	Estimated Number of Men to be Employed.	Number of Men actually at Work.Land drainage	Feb. 11, 11)22	240	  268,898	8,003	3,602					(February 4)Forestry	Feb.   4, 1922	489*	191,419	4,826	4,137Light railways      .. ..   No information at present available.* This figure includes 65 schemes which are being undertaken by the Forestry Commission direct, and 16 in Crown Woods, 3 of the latter being&apos; road making.7. Unemployment Workers&apos; Dependants&apos; Fund.The estimated income of this Fund for the period the 7th November, 1921, to the 4th February, 1922, is  2,870,000. The estimated amount paid out as grants for the period the 10th November, 1921, to the 4th February, 1922, was  2,060,000. (In both figures the amounts for Northern Ireland are excluded as from the 31st December, 1921.)The number of claims made in Great Britain and Southern Ireland up to the 7th February was 1,064,373. Of these, 939,810 were authorised, of which number 259,200 were in respect of dependent wife, housekeeper or invalid husband only; 88,330 were in respect of children only; and 592,280 were in respect of both classes of dependants.The number of claims current at the above date was 678,338.o

</content>
</cab>
