<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 373-378</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THISJDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.agreed that I should be authorised to inform the Railway Companies that the increased charging powers of railway owned docks and harbours will be extended until the 15th February, 1924, subject to a power of revision vested in the Minister of Transport acting on the advice of an Advisory Committee, and further that a Bill should be prepared for the- consideration of the Committee, continuing until February 15th, 1925, and making applicable to railway-owned undertakings, the Harbours, Docks and Piers (Temporary Increase of Charges) Act, 1920.     In accordance with this decision I submit a draft Bill.Charges Act, 1920, and continuing it until the 15th February, 1925, is to avoid the necessity for the introduction by the Railway Companies owning docks or harbours of separate private Bills before tho amalgamations under the Railways Act, 1921, are complete.     It would be far more convenient to allow each of the four new amalgamated Companies to introduce Bills dealing with all the docks belonging to the Group.     As the amalgamations will normally take place on the 1st July, 1923, an extension beyond the 15th February, 1924, is necessary and the extension of a year seems convenient.S3CRV2T.CP.3755.HARBOURS, DOCKS AND PIERS (TEMPORARY INCREASE OF CHARGES) BILL.Memorandum for the Cabinet by the Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Transport.On October 27th the Home Affairs CommitteeThe object of amending the Temporary Increase of
The Bill is quite simple.     Possible opposition might come from shipowners who apprehend that dock and harbour charges will be maintained at an unduly high level. But so far as I can ascertain it is unlikely that the shipping interests will raise this point, as it is open to them at any time to ask the Minister to refer the existing charges to the Advisory Committee before whom they can state their case, a procedure which is preferable to opposition before, a Parliamentary Committee.     Other dock and harbour authorities might seek to inelxide in the Bill powers to prevent railway-owned docks and harbours charging lower rates than competing ports, but I do not anticipate they will press this point on a temporary measure.(Signed)    ARTHUR NSAL.Ministry of Transport. 18th February, 1922.
[12 Geo. 5.)    Harbours, Docks, and Piers(Temporary Increase of Charges).DRAFTof aBILLtoAmend and extend the duration of the Harbours, a.d. 1922. Docks,   and   Piers   (Temporary  Increase  of Charges) Act, 1920.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows: 1. The Harbours, Docks,  and Piers  (Temporary Application Increase, of Charges) Act, 1920 (hereinafter referred to of the as the principal Act), shall, in its application to any principal port, harbour, dock, or pier undertaking forming part act ^ cks&quot; 10 of a railway or other undertaking, have effect as if for ^ fe u proviso (b) of subsection (1) of section one of that Act q ^ 5 c 2\ the following proviso were substituted : &quot; (6) No such modification shall be authorised which is more than sufficient to provide, with clue 15 care and management, for a reasonable return onthe capital expenditure on the port, harbour, dock, or pier undertaking, regard being had to its prospective development.&quot;2. (l) This Act may be cited as the Harbours, Short title, 20 Docks, and Piers (Temporary Increase of Charges) Act, and duration. 1922, and the principal Act and this Act may be cited together as the Harbours, Docks, and Piers (Temporary Increase of Charges) Acts, 1920 to 1922.18-1 &apos;
Harbours, DocJcs, and Tiers [12 Geo. 5.] (Temporary Increase of Charges).A.D. 1922, (2) The principal Act, as amended by this Act, shall have effect until the fifteenth day of February, nineteen hundred and twenty-five, and subsection (4) of section ll &amp; 12 eighty of the Flail ways Act, 1921 (which continues the Geo. 5. c. 55. rates advisory committee in existence so long as it may 5 he necessary for the purposes of references under the principal Act), shall have effect accordingly.

Harbours, Docks, andPiers (Temporary Increase of Charges).JJ R A E TOF ABILLTo amend and extend the duration of the Harbours, Docks, and Piers (Temporary Increase of Charges) Act, 1920.xxx :i.)lith January 1922.18-1

</content>
</cab>
