<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 696-698</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document Is the Property of His Britannlo Majesty1a Government.SECRET. Copy NO:   jF CABINET,fr.P ,3779 *r rOOT-AND-MOUTH DISEASE.Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Minister of Health has circulated a Memorandum (CP,3757) with reference to the method of meeting the cost of dealing with the present outbreak of Foot-and-Mouth Disease and It will probably be for the oonvenienoe of my colleagues if I state the views of the Ministry of Agriculture on the subject.The matter is governed by the Diseases of Animals Act, 1894, which provides in Section 15 (5) that the compensation for slaughtered animals should be paid out of the Cattle Pleura-pneumonia Account for Great Britain.    Section 18 of the Act provides for the payment into the Account of such moneys (not exceeding  140,000 in any one year) as may be provided by Parliament and that if in any financial year the money standing to the Account la Insufficient to meet the liabilities the difference shall be made up out of the Looal Taxation Account and the Looal Taxation (Scotland) Account in the proportion of 88 and 12 per cent, respectively.    Included in the maximum grants of  140.000 for Great Britain, and, under Section  73,  20,000 for Ireland are Bums up to  50,000 for Swine Fever. Great Britain^ share of the Swine fever Grant amounts approxi-mately to  40,600 so that the amount available for Foot-and-Mouth Disease ill Great Britain is limited to  100,000 a year.On the occasion of the present outbreak of dleease the balance on the Cattle Pleuro-pneumonia Account available for Foot-and-Mouth Disease was approximately  75,000 and consequently it1I
will be necessary to draw from the Local Taxation Accounts the whole cost less this amount of dealing with the outbreak, whioh may amount to as much as  1,000,000, though the whole of this sum will not be expended in the present financial year.Up to the present it has been the practice of the Ministry to provide In its Estimates each year whatever sum has been necessary (not exceeding the maximum amount of  100,000 a year) to recoup the Local Taxation Accounts the whole amount which may have been advanced on account of Foot-and-Mouth Disease expenditure; and during the last 33 years the whole expenditure, though met in the first instance from the local Taxation Accounts, has been recouped by Parliamentary Grants in the following or subsequent years.   The total amount so voted for the 32 years from 1890-91 to 1921-22 inclusive has, however, only amounted to  315,750 or an average of  9,867 a year, whereas the maximum amount that would have been voted if it had been necessary would have been  3,200,000 on the basis of  100,000 a year.Uo to the present, therefore, there has been no final charge on the Local Taxation Accounts in respect of the opera-tions against Foot-and-Mouth Disease and it has been assumed by the Ministry that it was the intention of Parliament that the whole cost of such operations should be met In due course from the Exchequer.In view,   however, of1 the magnitude of the present outbreak it is obvious that it would take several years before the drafts on the Local Taxation Accounts could be repaid by means of Parliamentary Grants at the rate of  100,000 a year, and it may be added that even before the present outbreak there was
a sum of  69,400 (part of the balance of  75-000 in hand mentioned above) due to the Local Taxation Accounts in respect of Foot-and-Mouth Disease expenditure in 1920 and 1921.In these circumstances tho Minister of Health proposes that the whole of the burden fallinc: on the Local Taxation accounts, i.;hich may amount to as much as  1,000,000 should be recouped forthwith by the Exchequer.In this connection I ?/ould point out that both the Royal Commission on Local Taxation of 1901 (Cd, 636) and the Kempe Departmental Committee of 1914 (Cd. 7315) recommended that the whole oost of operations against Foot-and-Mouth Disease should be providod entirely from national funds.   Legislation to carry out these recommendations was included in Part IV of the Finance Bill, 1914, which provided that any sums payable out of the Local Taxation Accounts in respect of animal diseases should be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament instead of out of the Local Taxation accounts.   This part of the Bill, however, was not proceeded with owing to the outbreak of war.There is, therefore, a considerable weight of authority in favour of the proposal of the Minister of Health that the cost of extirpating Foot and Mouth Disease should * not be borne by the local ratepayers.*A.G. BOSCAWEN.f25th February, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
