<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/133/0 images: 831-851</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SB C EJJ, fZCP, 3800.0 a B I II E dSUPPLY AID) TRaHSPORT S,Ltd-A30;&amp;riTTE3.REPORT OH THE&apos; REOOHSTTTUTIQH OF JDEE SUPPLY^ AKP &apos; TRANSPORT ORC4AifT.3AT.tO!?.The following Report, showing in outline a schema to be carried out in the event cf industrial disturbance and the nucleus organisation to he -retained in order that the scheme may be -kept up-to-date and ready to function, has been drawn up in accordance with Conclusion 10.1 f.5)    of the Committee of Home Affairs (-89 th Hovember., 1921)..I. OBHERATi POLICY.&apos;,I-t is considered essential that there should be some scheme ready to be put into operation by means of which the Government would bo able to ensure that vital services will bo maintained in the event of an -emergency,..On the other hand from the point of view of general desirability and In view of the urgent need for economy it is thought that the main burden of responsibility should be moved from the Government to the -trade and/or local authorities and that the financial liability of the Govern-ment should be brought to,a minimum,.(THIS &quot;DOCUMSKT IS TEE PROPERTY- OiT EIS ERITAHNIC MAJESTY *   GO^ERITIvEKT) .
SEigv JOE^ 11^ mpH. OOVK?.aMFiJIT assistance -STAROS .IB E SElj&apos;JT.ATi,It is therefore suggested that the trade and local authorities should he responsible for the maintenance of all looal services and that the action to he taken by the Government should ho confined to the following, and that, where assistance is indicated, such assistance should only bo given where the trade, and/or tho looal authorities are unable to deal with the situation:- &apos;ii)     assisting in the maintenance of law and order;(ii)     the maintenance of an Organisation for the reoruiting of volunteer workersj(ill)      the continuance of postal, telegraph, and telephone facilities;(iv)     assisting in the supply and distribution of .- pood;(v)     -the operation of a scheme for the supply of Yeast; &apos;(vi)     -assisting in the provision of emergency transport . :- services;.:(viz)      the -requisitioning of read vehicles for essential services;f viii)     the control of fuel,-if necessary;fi;i)     assisting in. supply and distribution of liquid fuel;(x)     the use of propaganda and the supply of .- information to the Press;(xi)    *aps-.i.sting in maintaining the supply of electricity ia London;Ixii)   &apos; the-- execution- of such work and the provision of--such e^iu^ment o;il accommodation as --may. fbe- -.&apos;- r^quirsd- by &apos;the Government;fzili)     such other duties as may from time to time be &apos;:-- considered ;ne.Qoasary*- .     .  - - ;--]&amp;B0P0SPil)-0RGMISA!ri6H,-&apos; -For the above purposes it is considered that an organisation would be required on the lines set out-below.This/............................
This organisation would only ho brought into being on the outbreak of an emergency and then only to tho extent necessitated by the nature of the emergency, but it will be necessary for a certain amount of work to be done and lor a nucleus to be maintained during times of industrial peace to keen the full scheme up-to-date and ready to be put into operation.It is proposed that the Supply and Transport Sub-Committee chould continue in existence, that the Chairman should   he nominated from time to time by the Cabinet Minister in charge of the Emergency Organisation, and that it should meet at least every six. months during times of industrial peace to review that organisation; this would not Involve any expenditure as all the members perform their duties in connection with the Committee as an addition to their normal duties.The general lines of the organisation should folio that v&amp;ich- has existed, up to the present, namely, a series of Sub-Comittees which, together with the Departments oon-corned,  are responsible for Uie various sections of tine whole scheme.     To this end it is essential that any        -&apos;.&quot;: necessary work on emergency questions should be recognised as part of the ordinary duties of a Government -Department and. that notice should be taken of such work when consider-ing the staff necessary in any Department;    this should &apos; not however necessitate any increase - in the normal staff-Tho re would then bo one officer in each Department to whom reference could be made on any questions concerning the emergency scheme.
-OHOAfllS&amp;TOflS .FQR WHICH. TEE VARIOUS DEPARTMENTS AND SUBCOMMITTEES TOlTlJE RES OJBTp T7&quot;&quot;Tho. following gives an .outline of the proposed organisation for -each Department and Sub-Committee concerned with&apos; the Supply and. Transport Organisation, together with an estimate of the annual oost of any nucleus to he retained in times of industrial-poace..For various reasons,.such as the importance of the organisations oonoerned or. the fact that considerable modifications ih the&apos; iresont- organisation are suggested, it has teen decided--to set out rather fully the proposed organisations.&apos;under the following Departments and Sub-Committees.-    It&apos;will, therefore, be more convenient for Statements In resoeot of theso to he attached to this report as Appendices.-Food Department and Food organisation for Scotland. .&apos; Appendix A.Road Transport Sub-Committee&apos;-. &quot; B.Supply Department. &apos;T C.Mines Department. &quot; B.Communications Sub-Committee, &quot; E.It is proposed that the organisations for whioh the following Departments and Sub-Coiunittees are responsible should remain substantially the same as at present,     The&quot;&quot;^&quot; estimated yearly cost during peaoe time Is stated in eaoh oaeo.        This expenditure will;be mainly in the. nature of travelling expenses.Department/
Pepartnent or Sub-pomaittee and schemes in which they are Interested&quot;.Admiralty. &quot; 1. Assistance -in protection, and provision **&apos;&apos;-:::,  o..f .ip&apos;e;so.nne&apos;l-and ships for various schemes (e&apos;g.,., Yoast&apos;schemo, London&apos;&apos;&quot;   ,; Electric Power. Scheme, Thames Petzol Scheme, Operation of Pood Locks,&quot; etc) .Water TransportJSubrCdmmitteo.Coastwise conveyance of foodstuffs; berthing, and-unloading of food ships*elect.tr.1 oal ,,Servieos Sub-Coimax11eo *Maintenance of essential&apos; electrical services within the Greater LondonHome Office and :?rqtection Sub-Cotnaittee,Assisting in tho maintenance of law and order-   preparation of Regulations under the.-Boiergeney Powers Act..-Motor Spirit Sub-Commi11ec.Supply and distribution of motor spirit:-, more especially with regard to the omeiigenoy Road Transport Schemes.Office of Works and Stores Allocation Sul&quot;-&quot;-CljIpTtt SWl &apos;    &apos;   &quot; ;Provision of accommodation, stores and equipment as,may be necessary.public 1 city Qonmjfc t to eKeeping-tho-position of tho Government before the public;    advertising special services-;    publication of Government news-sheet should the ordinary distribution of news fail.Scottish Office    &apos;Assisting tho Emergency&apos; Organisations to carry out their schemes in Scotland;   maintenance..of law and/ order in Scotland;   direotion of Volunteer Service. Committees in Scotland. &apos;(ffote;-      See remarks.in last paragraph of report and in&apos;Appendix A.).
War Office.Provision of troops fcr protection and other purposes;     constitution of any special Emezgenpy Force (a,g, Defonoe Foroe) as may ho required.oHil,The following DopartmenlB and Sub-Committees are not responsible for any definite schemes but are called in to help and advise the Committee when an emergenoy ocours or appears to be; imminentg     Ho nucleus organisation is required in these cases.2-ip-posal and liquidation&apos;; Commission.Supply of stores for emergency purposes from Government Surplus Stores.Exempt ions Subcommittee *5?o advise as to the exemption of certain grades of workors on the mobilisation of the Army, lavy, or Air Foroe Reserves *FlnPuieo Sub-Oqmpltteo,To consider expenditure proposer during an emergency ar:d, under powers delegated to it by the Treasury, accord or withhold sanction to such expenditureIntelligence and Statistics Sub-Oornmittee.To colleot and dissominato in the form of a Bulletin, information concerning the progress of the emergency. This has never been constituted as a Committee and the duties have in the past been carried out by the Ministry.of Transport;    it is now proposed that the Board of Trade should undertake this &amp;uty*Leg el Sab-Comml 11 e e *- To advise as to the legality of any proposed action.Ministry of. HealthsTo assist local authorities in carrying out their &quot;iuijiCD,  and. provision of staff for Civil GOiJisiis stone rs;Ministry of jLgbour,Information as to industrial situation.
Supply Priority Sub*;Comi111ee.To wc-with stocks of oeeentiS! 0.001010dities ana advise as,to conservation and distribution.Tr-transport Co-:ordl nation Sub-OofoDittep to.advise as to tho co-oxdination of the various forms o;f transport available during an eraergenoy.cost op peopope/j ..aisi^is.cTipj.It will thus be boon that the total estimated, annual- cost of the proposed nucleus organisation is as follows:-&apos; - ,Pood Department 1,050Pood Organisation for Scotland .200Supply Pop ailment 200Mines Bep/ar^snt 200Water Transport Sub-Co.1 jmittee 50 (*2.00i. 1st Yr.)S0 c-tti air 0f f i 00 50Remainder&apos; Nil. 1,750/( I,-900 1st Yr)The Treasury dps ire that the Special Services..Vote should.be disponr :nue-d and it Is recommended that each Department should bear any. expenditure- Incurred on account of their nucleus organisation oh their own. Votes, and that any; expenses/,., such as the Supply Dep-artnent, which would&apos; hot naturally fall on the vqt-q of any other Department should be oh -rgod to the IP; me- Office Vote *Ir is imporjsrble to hidce any forecast as to the . cost of tho v/.;..-;-. ou3 schemes when put Into operation as this would depend on the nature of tho emergency and the decision of the Government as to the extent to which the schemes are to be put Into operationr    Por instance in
the last ooal strike conedde;able-bxperditure- was involved, in the Ct over linen t importation&apos; cf ooal from abroad to supplement that imported by the trade,- quite apart from the cost of tho organisation set up for that purpose *If tho foregoing arrangements are - approved in principle it is proposed to won: out for Scotland a unified organisation based uuon the principle of bringing all tho emergency arrangements in Scotland undor&apos; the control of one Minister or other representative of the Government during an emergency.     The details of this organisation will be worked cut by the Secretary for  -Scotland and the Board of Trade in consultation with any o th e r D e p ar tmen t s c on c e r n e 3 *fSgd) ARTHUR HEAL.- : Chairman, &quot;.-..&apos;.*: .Supply and Transit oft Sub-Committee.2, Whitehall Gardens*    S.&apos;7. 3rd March,  1922...Appendix A,/
APPENDIX   A.POOD DEPARTMENT AND FOOjD ORGANISATION POR SOOTEAND,.1 *-   GENERAL CONSIDERATIONS..It Is desirable now that the Government has ceased to exercise control over food supply and distribution in4normal times that the emergency organisation of the Food Department and that of the other departments Which actively participate in the direction of emergency operations should be brought into closer Co-operationsThis might be attained ir. the provinces by co-ordin-ating the duties of the several departments under the Chief Assistant-, of each Civil Commissioner who would-be primarily responsible for. the administration of all. essential&apos;, emergency services and under whom the other necessary technical officers should act,,    The retention of the Civil Commissioners1 organisation, Which is considered essential,. is assiimed, -Whilst it- cannot be expected that a Voluntary Scheme will be as easily controlled, or as fully efficient in action as the schemes which have in the past been directed by a staff of highly trained technical officers in continuous Government&apos; employment,,, it would probably serve as a basis., on. Which efficiency could be obtained. In a reasonable period.The application to the peculiar requirements of London, of the Principles here set out is at present under consideration and it IS possible that some modification may &apos; be requisite.     Should it be deemed necessary for the Govern-&apos; ment to make more detailed provision and to assume more definite responsibility in the Metropolitan Area the matter will be made the subject of further recommendations.-.,./IT
II.,    POOD SUPPLY &amp; DISTRIBUTION.The first essentials as regards the supply and distribution of food are :-SUPPLY.DISTRIBUTION,(a) the provision of an adequate number of road transport- vehicles with the requisite personnel(b) the -provision of a guaranteed supply of petrol;adequate protection where necessary.(c)(a) the provision of adequate information, With;,regard .to. -stocks , -.. and short a aes; .(b) the equalisation .of ....supplies-;in the hands -of. traders where, necessary;     .(c) . the conservation ofsupplies, by rationing if the crisis is prolonged;Provided these requirements can be met,  it is thought that the trade generally would be able to deal adequately with the. replenishment of bulk supolies and serious diffi-difficulties- could only arise in providing an adequate, transport service to the retailer and the consumer..     They would not,-however,  be likely to reach serious proportions unless a strike of road transport workers synchronised with a strike of railway workers *So far as food is concerned, the Government will only assume responsibility for the following:-.(a )     the distribution of yeast;(b) -   the requisitioning of road vehicles for foodservices - if necessary;(c) the provision of a small nucleus advisory and requisitioning staff throup.ho.ut the country;
the equalisation of food supplies in thehands of traders, by agreement with the traders 1associations concerned or by theexercise of requisitioninr powers where necessary,(a)The Yeast Schome .The Yeast Scheme should betreated as a national and not a local problem owing to the exceptional nature of the trade, the perishable character of the commodity^ and the distance&apos;which separates the centres of production from the mai,n centres of consumption. It would still be necessary for the Admiralty to transport yeast to various English Ports- but the Trade have now undertaken to distribute it from those ports.     The increased cost of carriage should not be sufficient to lead to an increase in the price of bread.(b)     The Requisitioning; of Vehicles,       If the trade&apos; are to deal with their own transport problems three preliminary steps appear to be necessary,First, the issue of an Order on the occurrence of a strike making it an offence for any transport contractor to charge more for transport services than the rate which ruled for similar work in the some locality immediately prior to the strike;, or such higher rate as may be approved by the Government,Secondly, that in all important localities., some officer should be available to hold, the authority of the. Government to requisition transport!     This power need only be used in the event of an owner being unwilling to make his transport available for use upon essential services *
Thirdly j the continuance by the Government of the arrangement whioh has existed &apos;.in the past whereby Insurance Companies have held&apos; the boners of vehicles covered in respect of damage occurring during a strike, although the protection afforded by insurance&quot;has been invalidated as a result of the4owner complying with the &apos; instructions of the Government.The question of the requisitioning of road vehicles, is dealt with&apos;more fully in&apos; Appendix Bo.&apos;,- -   -   ,(c)     Emergency staff&apos; :(i.) Emergency Food Officers,    Seme officers with&apos;&apos; experience in food organisation should on the occurrence of an emergency be attached to the staff of each Civil Commissioner as a technical adviser.     In the majority of , ^     cases it is thought that the Divisional Officers who have formerly acted under the Board of Trade (Food Dept.?) would be willing to undertake this duty, and it is antici-pated that where they are not available some other-officer of experience can be found.     There may, of course, be some difficulty m securing any promise of co-operation In the absence of an offer of something in the nature of . a . retaining f ee,-.(ii) Emergency (Food) Supply Officers.     Under these Technical Officers it would he advisable to appoint Emergency (Pood) Supply Officers in charge of groups of /&apos;,,..,    Local Authority Areas to keep in touch with the Food Trades Advisory Committees;    to act as Intelligence . Officesj and m an advisory capacity, &apos;   Upon such officers might be placed the duty, in consultation with the Local Authorities concerned,, of taking such &quot;steps/as
as Tiny be necessary to secure th?: equalisation of supplies in the bands of retailers-.(ill) nond transport Requisitioning Officers*     Up to the present road transport for &quot;&apos;ood purposes has been separated/from other emergency road transport, but it is no?; considered desirable that there should bo only one requisitioning authority for all road transport puropses in each area except London, where 4 it is necessary that nriergency passenger traffic should bo dealt with separately.    (See Appendix B), (iv) Finance Officers -.    A small financial staff would be required to deal with requisitioned vehicles and other minor matters.     The necessary arrangements for this staff will be settled in conjunction with the Finance sub-Committee * - -(d) Equalisation of Food Supplies^       Experience hasshown that the eduallsa-tion of supplies in the hands of retailers by agreement with the Traders&apos; Associations concerned can only be secured if the power of requisition can be used as a last resort,     This power should be conferred upon the Food Adviser to the Civil Commissioner and upon such Emergency (Food) Supply Officers as he may select.III. M1RILISATICF 0&apos;R; TEAD v^RgSOURC ES,,In order to carry out the mobilisation of voluntary effort, it is suggested tot in each Civil Commissioner f,s area a local Fnvergency Supply and Transport Committee should be formed to consist of a representative from each of the various food traders &apos; advisory committees, and committees of haulage contractors which have been set. up by Divisional (Food) Officers *     The functions of these committees would be to co-ordinate trade effort and arrange for the pooling of resources.   The requisitioning officers in the various/localities
localities and the Food Adviser to tho Civil Commissioner&quot; ... should be ex-officio members of such-commit beas.IVo     DERELICT FOODSTUFFS UPOF RAIL-AYS tIt is not considered that under the neve conditions the Government should, assume responsibility for the clearance of foodstuffs left derelict upon railways durin- an emergency.V. SCOTLAND.The arrangements proposed above.are intended to apply primarily to England and     las       The mo.in report pro-poses a unified emergency organisation for Scotland and so far as food is concerned, the details of this organisation-,- as well-as those for other services, will be worked out hy the Secretary for Scotland and the Board of Trade In consultation with any other Departments concernedtVI. COST OF NUCLEUS OROAPTSATION.It Is estimated that the annual cost of the nucleus organisation required to keep the above scheme, including the road transport schemes proposed, to be transferred from the -Road Transport Sub-Committee, rip-to-date and. ready to function in England and Wales would be  1 0 50aThe annual expenditure on the nucleus organisation for Scotland cannot be estimated at all closely until the details have been worked out$ but in any ca.se -it should not exceed  200 * ...   - - ..... - - - ;
APPENDIX B,ROAD TRANSPORT SIlB-COLailT TEE *It is suggested that in future the organisation ofemergency road transport services should be upon the followinglinos which aro in accord with the proposed Food DepartmentOrganisation : -(i)       Tn any future emergency the power to requisition,   , outside the metropolitan area, road vehicles for any essential service (including the supply and transport of food), should be vested in&quot; one. and only one, set of officers,.(ti)iStops .should be taken to approach suitable men who have held positions of responsibility in the emergency organisation, in the/ past, to act as chief Requisitioning Officers. a&apos;;t the Headquarters of each of the thirteen &apos; Divisions into which Fngland and Scotland hove been divided for emergency purposes-(ill)   &quot;   The&apos; late Road Commissioners of the Road Transport Sub-Committee or the&apos; late Divisional Road &quot;Transport- Officers, of the Food Deportment should be asked whether they pre willing to assume the position of Chief Requisitioning. Officer for . ..... their respective areas, and they should be asked to select such suitable persons, from among their late volunteer staff or from other sources, as they may require to represent them throughout their Divisions/    These officers should not normally be charged with the duty of formulating road transport schemes j but they should, mainly be concerned with securing emergency transport by requisition when it cannot otherwise be obtained for essential services,-     It is not necessary that these officers, apart from the Chief Requisition-ing Officer of each area, should be informed in advance of the duties which may devolve dh - them. &apos;5!h.ere any of the Area Road Transport Officers of the T^ood Department are available they should assist the Chief Requisitioning Officer of. the divisions w  &apos; &apos;.(iV)       The Chief Requisitioning Officers should also be -asked to prepare schemes for any necessary machinery for the inspection of vehicles when requisitioned, and the assessment of any damage or loss occasioned by their use for emergency purposes... r(y)       The only, duty of these officers would be to act as requisitioning agents for the Government., It would.be their business to moot demands for road vehicles from :-(a)    local authorities or recognised r,,mc r g.)noy C omrn 11 te e a-V&apos; -15- &apos; &apos; / (b)
(b)   Tho accredited representatives of Government Departments.(vi)     So far as possible tho persons employing thelabour or the vehicles would be expected to . ,       make direct payments, in respect of wagesand hire charges..  &apos;  It might be necessary, however, for the requisitioning officers to cssdme some financial responsibilities In the case of services rendered to representatives of Government Departments.(vii)      Tnf.smuofr.ps the most ^important. duty of the requisitioning offleers In an emergency . would be to provide transport for&quot; food, the responsibility&apos;for maintaining the skeleton of the requisitioning organisation and for the&apos;preparation of the necessary instructions and forms, should rest with the permanent nucleus emergency staff of the Pood Department.(viii)     The main Emergency Road Transport Sub-Committee should cease to function.(ix)     In order to meet the special case of themetropolitan area, &quot;the London Road Traffic Emergency Sub-Committee should be maintained, and should be attached to the Roads Department Und-sr the Chairmanship of the Director General of Roads.     Its duties would be limited to the organisation of emergency road passenger services in*&quot;the metropolitan police sreaT   For^tEis purpose, in the metropolitan police area,- and , in that area^alone, the power to requisition&quot;&quot; passenger&apos;carrying vehicles would, on an-emergeno arising&quot;,&quot;be vested in a set of officers differ-ing :from;those empowered to requisition goods carrying vehicles. .       7-: jThe cost of the nucleus organisation required for(i) - (vli) above has been included under Food Department.   - .,No expenditure would be incurred on (ix) during times ;ofk ..industrial peace.&apos;   &apos; If Industrial trouble wore anticipated,the&apos; Roads Department of the Ministry of Transport could.immediately be mobilised to render all possible assistancein matters connected With road transport.   In particular,theprovincial offices and staff of that Department would beavr liable for service . - &apos; - -      .
APPENDIX C,SUPPLY DEPARTMENT.Conclusion 101 -(4). of the Committee of Home Affairs &apos; states::-   &quot;That the organisation of the Civil Commissioners and the Supply Department and the] corresponding organisations for Scotland should be retained.;&quot;   &apos;    &apos;Tho - following, recomrrferidatlons arc made with regard to the future worfe: of thevSupply&apos; Department: -(I)       That the Local Authorities should be informed that the &quot;Memorandum forthe. Guidance of Local Authorities&quot; (the so-called &quot;Strike Book&quot;) issued in April 1921, should be regarded as no longer--holding: good, and should be destroyed;-and that the Ministry-of Health should issue this communication &apos; to..the Local Authorities(ii)     That it is not necessary that any subsequent Memorandum to take the ple-ce-of that now cancelled,, should be issued to the Local Authorities, but that the General.Inspectors of the Ministry, of health:;(-who will continue to act as Chiefs -of Staff in their respective divisions) should,.,.in the ordinary course of their -duties -:.&apos;iv-(a) keep;- in- touch&quot; with existing Chairmen-of VolunteerService. Committees, with a view to these Chairmen bo.ing.-ava liable&apos; for- co-operation with the Local Authorities -should, any future emergency! occur,, and(b) keep In.-touch-with, the Local Authorities,.. giving them to -^understand, that Chairmen of Volunteer Service-/Committees ,wlll. be available to co-operate with them in the event of it being .necessary in....      .....ianemergency.to call for volunteers fOr National&apos; and Local services  . . -..; . .f(Til)     That&quot; the existing &quot;&quot;Instructions to Chairmen of Volunteerv.Service. Committees&quot;-.&apos; should, be&quot; cancelled and&quot; other instructions be prepared by the- Supply Department,. in; con-;: sulta tipn. with, the Treasury &apos;as.-&apos;r.egardo all the points&apos; in which questions of &quot;finance arc involved 7. t      .-. -, (iv)     That as and when existing Chairmen of Volunteer Service .Committees./resign, &apos;now Chairmen should&apos;be appointed and that in making such&quot;appointed&apos;allotments it should be regarded * as more .importsntTto -secure the best -possible Chairmen &quot;than to fill vacancies immediately they occur.,(V)-    . That in the event of an omerconey arising,, the Ministry. of Health-should,, as it has done In the past&apos;, provide Finance Officers for- the Civil Commissioners, and volunteer Service Committees..        , &apos;
It is impossible to make arty forecast of the probable annual cost of this nucleus organisation, until the new Instructions to Chairmen of Volunteer Service Committees have been drawn up, but it will, in any caco be small (say -F200). -     -/Appendix. U.
APPENDIX D. ]JM^^L, DEPARTMENT.DUTIES OF THE MINES DEPARTMENT.The Mines Department is responsible for providing an organisation to deal with all matters relative to the con-servation, distribution and if necessary, importation of fuel during an emergency.     So far as the foregoing involves transport, use of volunteers, or protect!on* the Mines Department^ function Is to satisfy itself that adequate provision exists for meeting these requirements, but it has no direct responsibility for them.EMERGENCY ORGANISATION.The organisation whioh it is proposed should be brought into operation In . any future emergency is In the main the same as that employed during the late Coal Strike.     It may be roughly divided into two parts, viz:-(a) That dealing with export and bunkering.(b) That regulating Inland distribution andenforcing restrictions in consumption.The efficiency of* the Mines Department Emergency scheme depends mainly on close co-operation with the Coal Trade Federations, and it Is essential that the preparation of the arrangements and the conduct of operations be centred in the Mines Department which is in constant touch with the Federations referred to.COST.The Mines Department does net maintain any paid organlsa-tion for emergency purposes in peace time and apart from two classes of individuals, (Reproscntatives at Coal Loading Ports and Divisional Coal Officers) the work during an emergency will be done by volunteers and Civil Servants,The five Ports representatives and twelve Divisional Officers referred to will bo the direct representatives of the Mines Department and it is necessary that they should be thoroughly conversant with the arrangements made and the conditions prevailing,     The men who will be used for that work were employed in the Coal Mines Department during the period of Control but have now returned to their normal work-at Railway Companies Offices, etc - and in order to keep them in touch with the progress of events it is proposed to mobilise them 2 or 3 times a year for instruction,It will also be necessary to confer with various re-presentatives of the Coal Trade Federations and payment of    &apos; expenses will have to be made to them.It is estimated that the annual cost during times of industrial peace will be  200,
APPENDIX - E.COMMUNICATIONS SUB-COMITTEE.In view of the decision to disband the War Office nucleus wireless organisation it is considered impossible to prepare any comprehensive wireless scheme in advance of an emergency.The existing Committee has been disbanded and it is recommended that tho Committee should remain in abeyance until such time as it may be thought necessary to reconstitute it in view of any threatened industrial unrest*&apos; . The new Committee should consist of representatives ofthe following and should be called together by the Home Office:-:;- Admiralty,Board of Trade, Air Ministry, Home Office, Post Office, Railway Companies, Scottish Office, :   Supply Department, War Office,,These Departments should be requested to notify to the Home Office the name of their contemplated representative and any changes that may occur from time to time*&quot;Each Department concerned w ill be responsible for keeping up to date&apos;any information available as to material and personnel which can be called upon in the event of an emergency.:Each Department concerned will also keep on hand such paper schemes as have been prepared for operation by that Department,     Under this arrangement the larger schemes/will
will be kept in readiness as follows:-(a) Aerial Mall Service.Air Ministry In conduction with the Home Of floe-,(b) Wire1ess Telegraphlo ServiceiAdmiralty, War Office and Air Ministry.(c) p? zpatch Rider Seryl ce.General lost Office.(d) Railway Concnunj cations,The Superintendent of Signals, London and North Western Railway,(e) Emergency Postal, Telegraphie and Telephonicit rran goment s.General Popt Office.The emergency telephone, telegraph and wireless arrangements have hitherto been co-ordinated by a small sub-committee comprising representatives of the three Fighting Services, the General Poet Office, and the Railway Companies.     This sub-committee would be reconstituted at the same time as the Communications Sub-Committee.Under this scheme no expenditure would be involved ^during times of industrial peace.

</content>
</cab>
