<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/43/0 images: 206-219</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1968Copy No.   3 3CC (68)12th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 6th February, 1968,at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Lord G-\rdiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Richard Grossman,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. George Thomson, m p.Secretary of State for commonwealth affairs the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the  Right  Hon.  Fred  Peart,  m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, m p,Minister of power the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Patrick gordon walker, m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Peter Shore, mp,Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, m p,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,   The Right Hon. Frederick Mulley,m p, Minister of Health [Item 2) u p, Minister of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon Sir Elwyn Jones, qc.   The  Right  Hon.  John  Silkin,  mp,m p, Attorney-General [Item 1) Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. E. M. rose mr. L. errington mr. H. L. Lawrence-wilson mr. P. E. Thornton
contents subject parliament      .........Defence: Draft White PaperSpecialist and Select CommitteesGaming BillCensus of Population 1971 ...First pre-test 1968
Defence: draft white Paper(previous reference:CC(68) 11thConclusions,Minute 5)SECRET(ii) The Defence Secretary said that, when the Cabinet at their previous meeting considered the draft Statement on the defence estimates, 1968, the only point left to be settled was the precise termsof the reference to be made in it to the Territorial and ArmyVolunteer Reserve Category III (T &amp; have III). This Volunteer force had been formed a year ago with a planned strength of 23,000 andwith the role of supporting the civil power in general war. Its annual cost at full strength would be  3 million of which  300,000 would beborne on the Defence Budget and the balance on Home Office votes.Recruiting had been good and, by April this year, it had been expected that the strength of the force would be about 14,500. Whenthe force had been formed it had been announced that its continuingexistence would be reviewed after three years; the expectation hadbeen that it would then be disbanded on the grounds that it servedno useful purpose. In the recent review of Home defence expenditure, the decision had been taken that this force, togetherwith the Civil Defence Corps and the Auxiliary Fire Service, shouldbe disbanded and this had been announced in the White Paper on public Expenditure 1968-69 and 1969-70 (Cmd. 3515). As expected,the decision to disband the force had provoked objections, and ministerial assurances had subsequently been given in parliament that no steps would be taken to disband the force until there had beenconsultations with the Council of Territorial and Auxiliary ForcesAssociations.The defence interests in T &amp; have III were that it was a usefulsource of recruits for the regular forces, particularly when regularrecruiting was as poor as at present, and that we wished to keep in being the remaining elements of the army volunteer reserves, andso had a strong interest in maintaining good relations with theCouncil. He therefore proposed that, in the Statement on theDefence Estimates, 1968, a form of words should be used about theT &amp; have III which would leave some room for manoeuvre in discussions with the Council about its future. It might be that a worthwhile scheme could be worked out which would enable theforce to be retained in some form for a period though at a reducedcost to be borne wholly on defence votes; the objective would in any event remain complete disbandment later. If, on furtherconsideration, he wished to adopt this course he would put forwardspecific proposals for decision. To deal with the matter in thisfashion did not seem inconsistent with the decision to place HomeDefence preparations as a whole on a care and maintenance basis,particularly as it had been decided to make only a small reductionin the Royal Observer Corps and Monitoring organisation.8775CC 12 (68)confidential parliament 1 (j) fhe Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
Although there was some support for the Defence Secretary&apos;proposal, the general view of the Cabinet was that the decision to disband T &amp; have III should be maintained. Although the force had some merit, it was of very low priority from the defence viewpointand, in terms of Home Defence and peacetime emergencies, was much less valuable than the Auxiliary Fire Service which was also to be disbanded. If we were to give way to a small pressure group on this element of the expenditure cuts, it would not merely be necessaryto review the package of reductions that had been agreed on HomeDefence generally; the determination of the Government to standby the expenditure cuts as a whole would be put in doubt. Thestatement on Defence Estimates, 1968, should therefore state clearly that T &amp; have III was to be disbanded.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the statement on the Defence Estimates, 1968,should state that we were discussing with the Council ofthe Territorial and Auxiliary Forces Association the disbandment of the T &amp; have Category III.Specialist andSelectCommittees(previous reference:CC (67) 30thConclusions,Minute 1)(iii) The Cabinet considered a memorandum (C (68) 33) by theLord President on the evidence to be given to Select Committees.Select   Committee   on   the   Parliamentary   Commissioner   forAdministrationThe Lord President said that the Select Committee on theParliamentary Commissioner had intended themselves to conduct a detailed investigation, including the re-examination of Foreign Officeofficials, into the matters already covered by the recent report ofthe Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration on the refusal to pay compensation to certain survivors of Sachsenhausenconcentration camp. Although such an inquiry was strictly withinthe Committee&apos;s terms of reference, it had not been envisaged whenthe Committee was appointed that it would in effect retry individual cases already considered by the Commissioner, and the ministerial committee on Parliamentary Procedure were agreed that it wouldbe open to the strongest objection as undermining the doctrine of ministerial responsibility and the position of the parliamentary commissioner himself. They had accordingly agreed that if theSelect Committee embarked on such an inquiry the confidential information and the attendance of departmental witnesses essential toit should be refused.The Select Committee had now however been informed by theParliamentary Commissioner that it would not be possible for himto give them access to the confidential departmental papers on whichhe had based his report, and in these circumstances it was unlikelythat the Select Committee would pursue a detailed re-examination ofthe cases concerned. However, the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement in the House of Commons on the previous day had shown that hediffered from the Parliamentary Commissioner on questions of judgment, and it was likely that the Select Committee would now
wish to pursue this issue. Government spokesmen had made it clearwhen the establishment of the Committee was under discussion inthe House of Commons that it should keep under review the scope ofthe Parliamentary Commissioner^ functions and concern itself withthe implementation of his reports and with the correction ofmaladministration. It would be difficult to contend that an examination of the points on which there was disagreement betweenthe Government and the Parliamentary Commissioner was outside its proper function so long as such examination fell short of areinvestigation of the cases and examination of the officials concerned.In discussion there was general agreement that, if the SelectCommittee sought to conduct its own detailed investigation of thecases covered by the Parliamentary Commissioners report, the confidential information and the attendance of witnesses necessary tosuch an investigation should be refused. However, even if theCommittee confined its inquiry to investigating the points on whichthe Foreign Secretary had expressed disagreement with theParliamentary Commissioner, which involved matters of judgment,it would be desirable to establish clearly that, as in the case of thePublic Accounts Committee, official evidence on behalf of the ForeignOffice would be given only by the Permanent Under-Secretary ofState, as the officer responsible for the conduct of the Department,or by other senior officials nominated by him. The same rule should apply where other specialist Select Committees v/ished to examinedepartmental witnesses. Where the permanent head of a department nominated some other senior officer to give evidence, itwould be desirable that he should himself accompany the witness.In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) It would be important to maintain the Governments rightto disagree with reports of the Parliamentary Commissioner,particularly on issues of judgment where expenditure was involved.The proper function of the Select Committee in relation to individualreports was limited to the question of their implementation, on whichthe Committee could call Ministers to account, and it was forconsideration whether, on reappointment in the following Session, theCommittee&apos;s terms of reference should be redrafted so as to prevent it from conducting a further inquiry on issues of fact.(b) The analogy with the Public Accounts Committee in relationto witnesses was not exact, since the Select Committee might need totake evidence from Ministers to ascertain the basis on which they hadtaken decisions.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion, saidthat the Cabinet were agreed that, if the Select Committee on theParliamentary Commissioner asked for confidential information andthe attendance of departmental witnesses for the purpose of conducting a detailed reinvestigation of the cases covered by theParliamentary    Commissioner^    Sachsenhausen    report,    such
information and attendance should be refused. Subject to this, itshould be a clearly established rule that official evidence on behalfof Departments before this, and any other, specialist SelectCommittee should be given only by the permanent head of theDepartment or by other senior officials nominated by him for thepurpose.The Cabinet (2) Agreed that any request by the Select Committee on theParliamentary Commissioner for confidential information and the attendance of departmental witnesses for thepurpose of a reinvestigation of the cases covered by theParliamentary Commissioner^ Sachsenhausen report should be refused.(3) Agreed that official evidence before the specialist select committees should be given only by permanent headsof Departments or other senior officials nominated bythem for the purpose.Select Committee on agriculture the Lord President said that the Select Committee on agriculture proposed to enquire into the Ministry&apos;s departmentalassessment of food requirements over the next few years, the extentto which it would be practicable and in the national interest toincrease home production, and the methods of ascertaining costs ofproduction, returns to producers and all associated matters. Theyhad asked for extensive information covering the very wide issues ofpolicy which arose in this field. The Ministerial Committee on parliamentary Procedure were agreed that considerable restraintwould be necessary in providing the Select Committee with theinformation which they wanted. In addition to the objections ofprinciple to giving information of this sort, its provision would place a substantial burden on the Departments concerned. The ministerial committee were agreed that Ministers should exercise their owndiscretion in giving Select Committees confidential material, bearing that mind the risk that the new Committees might not observe the conventions which had been established by the older Committees,and might insist on the publication of material contrary todepartmental requests. Ministers should therefore have regard tothe degree of damage which might result from publication of confidential material in any particular case, and exercise specialcaution in relation to confidential material of a commercial nature.In view of the number of Departments concerned with theinformation requested by the Select Committee on Agriculture, the ministerial Committee considered that the Economic Ministers should consider collectively the extent to which this information should begiven. In the meantime, the Minister of Agriculture should write tothe Chairman of the Select Committee explaining that theGovernment required more time to consider the provision of theinformation for which the Committee had asked, in view of its very wide scope.
The Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food said that theGovernment was in effect being asked to disclose the assumptionsand forecasts on which the whole future economic policy of thecountry, and not merely future policy for agriculture, would bedecided, including the allocation and use of resources, taxation and investment policy and availability of land. There were risks of embarrassment if the forecasts were falsified by events, and there wasa particular risk to our international commercial negotiations and trading relations if the information for which the Committee askedwere published. In writing to the Chairman of the Committee hewould make clear the Governmenfs desire to help, but that theycould not be committed to giving the Committee all the informationrequested.In discussion it was pointed out that there were strong objectionsin principle to giving to the Committee the forecasts of future economic trends and the other assumptions on which the government&apos;s economic policy was based. There was a special difficulty of timing, since the Government were currently consideringthe annual farm price review and were reviewing their future policy for agriculture as a whole: it would be wrong to give the SelectCommittee information bearing on the formulation of these policiesuntil they had been settled and announced to Parliament. Moreover,requests for information by Select Committees on this scale couldnot be met without increasing departmental staffs or sacrificing workof greater priority. It would be preferable to make clear to the SelectCommittee at the outset the limitations which the Government mustimpose for these reasons on the information which could be given tothe Committee. The Committee could be told however that it wouldbe open to it, once Government policy had been announced, to askfor the information on which the policy had been based.In further discussion the following main points were made:(c) The Select Committee was likely to obtain, and seek theMinistry&apos;s views on, statistical information from the national farmers&apos; Union and other bodies, but it would be necessary to refrain from commenting on such information to the extent of providing theCommittee with the Governmenfs own statistics and forecasts.(d) There was a risk of embarrassment if the Select Committeewere to take evidence from foreign agricultural attaches or to travelabroad to take evidence from foreign agricultural Ministers.Arrangements had, however, been made for closer liaison between theForeign Office and the Committee Clerks, which would help to avoid the difficulties which had arisen in the previous Session over theCommittee&apos;s foreign travel; in addition, it would now be for theCommittee Chairmen themselves to decide how the limited sum whichhad been made available for the purpose of foreign travel should be apportioned between the various Select Committees.
(e) Consideration should be given to some limitation of the cost which Departments might agree to incur in providing information forthe specialist Select Committees.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion, saidthat the Cabinet were agreed on grounds of principle, timing, andthe burden which such work would throw on Departments, that information bearing on the current farm price review and the government&apos;s review of their policy for agriculture, should not begiven to the Select Committee until policy on these questions hadbeen decided and announced. The Minister of Agriculture, inconsultation with the Lord President, the Foreign Secretary, theCommonwealth Secretary and the other Economic Ministers, should write to the Chairman of the Select Committee accordingly. TheLord President should attend any meeting of the Select committee at which the matter was discussed in order to convey the government&apos;s view.The Cabinet (4) Agreed that information bearing on the current farm price review and the Governmenfs review of their policy for agriculture should not be given to the Select Committeeon Agriculture until policy on these questions had beendecided and announced.(5) Invited the Minister of Agriculture, in consultation with theLord President, the Foreign Secretary, the commonwealth secretary and the other Economic Ministers, to inform theChairman of the Select Committee of the Governmenfsview in accordance with the summing up by the PrimeMinister of their discussion.(6) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Lord President, to consider whether any limitationshould be imposed on the cost which might be incurred by Departments in furnishing information to the specialistSelect Committees.Gaming Bill (jv) The Home Secretary said that, in the light of the recent decision of the Court of Appeal in the case of R. v. Commissioner ofPolice ex parte Blackburn, he had considered whether it would be right to proceed with the Gaming Bill introduced in the House ofCommons before Christmas. He had reached the conclusion that thepolicy embodied in the Bill was sound, but that some usefulamendments could be made in Committee. The Betting and gaming Act, 1960 had been intended to permit the milder forms ofgaming while excluding commercial exploitation of gaming for highstakes, but it had had the unforeseen consequence that because ofthe uncertainty of the law a large number of commercial gamingestablishments had sprung up and flourished. The Court of Appealhad now insisted that the Act should be strictly enforced, but their belief that this would effectively prevent the commercial exploitation of gaming underestimated the ingenuity of the proprietors of gamingestablishments in inventing means of taking money from their patrons
which could be shown to be illegal only after lengthy proceedings before the courts. The police were about to prosecute a number ofclubs using such devices, but, even if convictions were obtained, itwould not be difficult for the proprietors to introduce others andconstantly keep one move ahead of the law. Stronger measures were therefore necessary, and he considered that the licensing system tobe introduced under the Gaming Bill was essential. He proposed,indeed, that the system should be used to make a substantial reductionin the number of gaming establishments, of which it was estimatedthat there were over 600 in this country, compared with 150 inFrance. He proposed also that power should be taken to preventgaming from being offered in conjunction with other forms ofentertainment. He would make clear in the debate on the SecondReading of the Bill the opportunities which the growth of gamingwas giving to criminal elements in this country, as it had in the UnitedStates, not only to make high profits but to acquire the means ofexerting political pressure.He proposed at the same time to relax the restrictions on bingoclubs by enabling membership of one club to admit to othersthroughout the country and by increasing the value of the prizewhich a registered members&apos; club could give so as to enable workingmen&apos;s clubs, for example, to withstand the competition of thecommercial organisations. At the same time he proposed to prohibit&quot; linked &quot; games, which enabled audiences in different parts of thecountry to participate in a single game. This increase in scale altered the character of the entertainment by making much higher prizesavailable and by eliminating the safeguard against dishonestpromotion provided by local knowledge of the winners. He wouldalso take power to prohibit the provision of other forms of gamingon the same premises as bingo. If bingo was to be regarded as an acceptable form of family entertainment its patrons should not be encouraged to participate in other forms of gaming offering higherinducements, and hence the risk of greater losses. Finally, he was concerned about the growth of the use of gaming machines, thecapital for which was provided entirely from American sources, oftenof a dubious character. He proposed to discuss with the treasury the possibility of requiring a minimum participation of British capital in the undertakings providing the machines.In discussion there was general agreement with the proposal toproceed with the Gaming Bill. In view of the expansion ofcommercial gaming since 1960 it would be impossible to revert toreliance on the Betting, Gaming and Lotteries Act without exposingthe country to increased danger from the association between gamingand crime, which experience elsewhere had shown to be unavoidable.Moreover, it was socially undesirable to allow the demand for commercial gaming to grow unchecked, and in particular to give any encouragement to people who were at present content with the moderate stakes and moderate prizes of bingo to experiment withother forms of gaming in which the risks were greater. There might
be practical difficulties, however, in determining how and on whatcriteria the number of clubs were to be reduced, whether the licenceswere granted by local justices of the peace, or, as might be preferable,by the Gaming Board itself. If discretion lay with the justices ofthe peace it was arguable that, as an additional safeguard againstthe penetration of gaming clubs by criminals operating throughpersons of good character, the police should be given a right to appeal against the grant of the licence. Consideration should also be givento the possibility of insisting on some British participation in the undertakings providing gaming machines.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion said that theCabinet agreed that the Gaming Bill should proceed, with amendments on the lines proposed by the Home Secretary. Thequestion whether the police should be given the right to appeal againstthe grant of a licence, and any other details that required resolution by Ministers collectively, should be considered by the Home AffairsCommittee.The Cabinet (7) Agreed that it would be right to proceed with the &quot;GamingBill, subject to amendments on the lines proposed by theHome Secretary.(8) Invited the First Secretary of State to arrange for outstanding questions on the Bill to be considered by the Home AffairsCommittee.1968CONFIDENTIALCensus of 2.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum (C (68) 31) by theI97&quot;,at&apos;0n First Secretary of State about the inclusion of two new questions in first pre-test    tne ^68 pre-test of the 1971 census of population.The First Secretary of State said that a small majority of theHome Affairs Committee had been in favour of including questions about income and about parents&apos; country of origin in the scheduleto be used in the pre-test in April for the 1971 census of population;but apart from the division of opinion in the Committee he thoughtit right to bring the issue to the Cabinefs attention because of theimportant presentational issues involved. Participation in the pre-test, which would cover a sample of 40,000 households in Englandand Wales and 3,600 in Scotland, would be voluntary and there wouldbe no statutory compulsion to complete the forms. The inclusionof the two additional questions for this pre-test would enablereactions to them to be assessed, without pre-judging their inclusion in 1971 census schedule, to which answers were statutorily required;but if the questions were excluded from the pre-test they would also have to be excluded from the census itself. The inclusion of thequestion about income had been advocated by a number of departments particularly the economic Departments as a meansof obtaining valuable information about individual and householdincomes and correlating it with other census data such as particulars of education and employment.   It had to be accepted that all the
replies would not be accurate but experience of previousgovernmental surveys suggested that they would probably be reasonably so. It had been suggested that the response would bemore accurate and the published census totals less likely to be misunderstood or misrepresented if the recipient indicated hisincome bracket from a series on the form. The proposed question about parents&apos; country of origin would also provide information required by the Government about the extent of social and economic integration of the children of coloured immigrants. The 1961 censusform had asked for the place of birth of the respondent. Withoutthe new information the Government would not be able to measure the progress, or lack of it, towards successful integration of the immigrant population and, particularly important, their children in a wide variety of fields. The main objections which had been raised in the Home Affairs Committee to the inclusion of thesequestions were that they would be resented as &quot; snooping &quot; by theGovernment, that the reasons for asking them would be misunderstood, and that these objections outweighed the possible advantages of collecting information to some degree inaccurate about incomes and ethnic origin.He recommended that the two questions should be included inthe pre-test schedules and that considerable care should be takenin publicly presenting the reasons for their inclusion. The publicmust be persuaded to recognise that in modern society Governmentsrequired more and better information on which to base a whole range of social and economic programmes.The Minister of Health said that he was satisfied that the two questions would provide useful information which could not otherwise be obtained. He recognised that a number of ministers had strong misgivings about asking one or both of them; but thesemisgivings could be put to a practical test only by including thequestions in the voluntary pre-test schedules. The questions wouldbe asked of only half the sample of households, themselves a verysmall proportion of the population. He agreed that proper public presentation was important.In discussion it was suggested that census information aboutincome was long overdue and essential for the formulation of policyin many fields. Experience of other surveys in this country and ofthe United States census indicated that the response would be likelyto be reasonably accurate. The information need not be disclosedeither to the head of the household or to the enumerator but couldbe sent direct to the census officer. The collection of censusinformation about incomes should not however delay considerationof the extent to which the Inland Revenue could make available toother Departments and publish much more information aboutincomes. While public objection might be reduced by asking only for the income bracket this would also reduce the usefulness of theinformation obtained. On the other hand, it was argued that therewould be widespread opposition to compulsory collection of details
of incomes and that a voluntary pre-test would not be a reliableguide to public reaction to a statutory requirement. The publicwere already required to give details of their incomes for tax purposes,rates relief, educational grants and other forms of social assistance and would resent further intrusion into their private affairs. Theinformation would not only be inaccurate but out of date long before it was published.As to parents&apos; origin, it was pointed out that until information about ethnic origin was available and correlated with other censusdata the problems involved would be approached on a basis ofprejudice and ignorance. Although the parents&apos; country of originwould not in every case be a guide to their ethnic origin, the twowould generally be the same and the question would provide usefulinformation. It was important, for example, to ascertain the extentto which the second generation of coloured immigrants, who hadbeen educated in this country, had been able to find satisfactoryemployment. If the Government were too sensitive about possible reactions to ask this question they would deny themselves theopportunity of obtaining information required to help colouredimmigrants and their children. On the other hand, it was argued thatit was a serious and repugnant step to make a distinction betweencoloured and other citizens in official statistics. Whatever resultantbenefits might be gained for the coloured population would be offset by the psychological impetus against integration which would stemfrom making the distinction. It had already been pointed out thatthe question would not in fact provide accurate information aboutethnic origin.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that asubstantial majority were in favour of including both questions inthe voluntary pre-test schedule. The Minister of Health should examine in consultation with the Secretary of State for Scotlandwhether the census results could not be published much more rapidly than in the past; if for example the results of the 1971 census weremade available in 1972 this would significantly reduce public criticism and opposition. And the Lord President should consider with the Home Publicity Committee the public presentation of the april pre-test in general and of the two new questions in particular.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland and the Ministerof Health to arrange for the inclusion of the questions, onthe lines indicated in the annex to C (68) 31, about income and parents&apos; country of origin in the schedules to be usedin the census pre-test in April.(2) Invited the Lord President to consider and advise theSecretary of State for Scotland and the Minister of health on the public presentation of the census pre-test in april and of the two new questions which would be included init.Cabinet Office, S.W.J,6th February, 1968.



</content>
</cab>
