<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/43/0 images: 220-234</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1968CC (68) Copy No.   -j 313tn conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 15th February, 1968,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, m p,Secretary of Slate for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Secretary of State for the FlomeDepartmentThe Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right hon. Patrick gordon walker, m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. George Thomson, m p.Secretary of State for commonwealth affairs the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p. Minister of Housing and local government the  Right  Hon.  Fred  Peart,  m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Peter Shore, mp,Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, m p,Minister of power the following were also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson, j The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, Q c,m p, Minister of Health (Item 4)      \    m p, Attorney-General (Item 4)The Right Hon. John Silkin, m p.Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. E. M. rose mr. H. L. Lawrence-Wilson
contents subject parliamentary Business     .........Home Information Services        ......Committee on Home PublicityOversea Affairs      ............Prime Ministers Visit to the United StatesMiddle Er.itPeopled Republic of Southern YemenLegislation     ...............Commonwealth Immigration
contents subject parliamentary Business     .........Home Information Services......Committee on Home PublicityOversea Affairs      ............Prime Minister^ Visit to the United StatesMiddle East:, People&apos;s Republic of Southern YemenLegislation     ...............Commonwealth ImmigrationSECRET
ParliamentHomeInformationServicesCommittee on home Publicity(previous reference:CC (67) 60thConclusions,Minute 3)confidential. The Prime Minister said that he had considered, inconsultation with the Lord President, means of co-ordinating the timing and presentation of White Papers and statements ofGovernment policy. He asked Ministers to inform the Lord Presidentof their intention to publish a White Paper before they were publiclycommitted to doing so. The Lord President would then arrange forthe Home Publicity Committee to consider with the Minister the timing of the publication and any questions of presentation which ought to be taken into account when the relevant ministerial committee, and subsequently the Cabinet, were considering thesubstance of the White Paper. It would not be necessary for theHome Publicity Committee to go through the text in detail sincedetailed examination would be undertaken elsewhere, but before theWhite Paper reached its final form the Committee should have anopportunity to take any points of presentation which might arise on the text, as well as to offer final advice on the arrangements for publication. Similar procedure should apply so far as possible tostatements of Government policy: some would of necessity be madeat short notice, but major statements would normally be foreseenlong enough in advance to permit consultation with the Committee.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the statement by the PrimeMinister.OverseaAffairsPrimeMinistersvisit to theUnited StatesSECRET*3. The Prime Minister said that his recent visit to Washingtonhad been unexpectedly successful. The arrangements made by the americans had been deliberately designed to create a friendlyatmosphere. He had the impression that the United States neededour friendship and support at least as much as we needed theirs.His meeting with President Johnson on 8th February had lasted four hours instead of one and a half hours as planned; and they had had further talks the following day. In spite of the recent attacks by theVietcong on South Vietnamese cities he had found the Presidentrelaxed and confident but also anxious to start peace talks with theNorth Vietnamese. The President had not even raised the questionof our planned military withdrawal from the Far East and thePersian Gulf. There had been some discussion of the North atlantic treaty Organisation and relations with France.   The Prime Minister* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.8796a 2CC 13 (68)confidential. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
had made clear to the President that we expected the United Statesnot to pre-empt all Germany&apos;s available resources of foreign exchangeso that there would be none left to offset the cost of maintainingBritish forces in,Germany. The President had expressed his concern about the world economic situation; and they had discussed themeasures which the United States proposed to take to restore theirbalance of payments.The Prime Minister said that there had been certain confidentialcontacts between the United States and North Vietnam even beforePresident Johnson, in his speech at San Antonio on 29th September,had offered to stop bombing North Vietnam provided that it would lead promptly to productive discussions and that North Vietnamwould not take military advantage of the bombing halt. Subsequentelucidation had made clear that by &quot; promptly &quot; the President meant a period of days, not months; that &quot; productive &quot; was intended notto prescribe results but merely to refer to a genuine determination tonegotiate; that the talks would be called off only if the north vietnamese were obviously exploiting the bombing halt for a majoratttack; and that North Vietnam could, if it wished, write the agenda for the talks. It was now evident, as had been stated publicly by theUnited States Secretary of State, Mr. Dean Rusk, on 14th February,that these peace efforts had so far failed to produce any positivereaction from North Vietnam. It was difficult to say whether thiswas because the North Vietnamese did not wish to open talks orwhether they merely wished to avoid giving the impression duringthe present crisis that they were being driven to the conference tableby lack of military success. It was encouraging that, in spite of the apparent failure of their peace efforts and the recent attacks on south vietnamese cities, the United States were not adopting a moreintransigent line. On the contrary, their attitude had become moreconciliatory in the course of the last year, especially in regard to theconditions on which the bombing of North Vietnam might be halted.It was now hard to claim that they were standing in the way of a peace settlement. The United States had shown equally remarkablerestraint as, indeed, had the Russians in their handling of the incident resulting from the seizure by North Korean naval forces ofthe United States ship Pueblo. The United States attached greatimportance to the part which the Soviet Union and the UnitedKingdom might in due course play as Co-Chairmen of the geneva conference. The first stage of negotiations for a settlement wouldhave to be direct talks between the United States and North Vietnam;but it might well be desirable to reconvene the Geneva Conference inthe second stage which would follow.The Prime Minister recalled that he had already reported to theCabinet on the long-drawn-out discussions on North Vietnam whichhe had had during this visit to Moscow from 22nd to 24th January.The Soviet leaders had taken the familiar line that the bombing of north Vietnam should stop unconditionally because the United
SECRETCC 13 (68)States were attacking North Vietnam while North Vietnam was notattacking the United States. They had expressed doubt about thegenuineness of the contacts between the United States and north vietnam and had described them as a &quot; charade &quot;. Nevertheless, hehad the impression that the Soviet Government had been doing whatthey could to bring pressure to bear on North Vietnam. It was doubtful, however, whether they still had much influence there; andthe Soviet leaders had certainly been less confident than a yearearlier.It was an open question how events would now develop andwhether the North Vietnamese really wanted peace talks. If theydid, the gap between their position and that of the United States was now narrow and the only difficulty lay in initially bridging it. It waspossible, however, that they merely wished to drag things out inorder to gain the maximum propaganda advantage. North Vietnamhad its pro-Russian and its pro-Chinese factions. The power of theSoviet Union to use its influence in favour of a peace settlement wasinhibited by the pressure of the Chinese Government in the opposite direction. There was little doubt that the Chinese would interveneactively if there was any risk of North Vietnam being defeated; andthey might even do so if the North Vietnamese tried to make asettlement with the United States. It was doubtful if there would beany significant progress towards a settlement in the immediate future.Meanwhile it seemed very unlikely that the attempts of theSecretary General of the United Nations, U Thant, to get talks goingwould make any headway. U Thant had compromised his status asa possible mediator by his biassed and anti-American attitude. Onhis way back from a visit to India he had passed through London on13th and 14th February, coming from Moscow where he had clearlybeen subjected to heavy pressure by the Soviet leaders. He had puta number of questions to the North Vietnamese Consul General in new Delhi and, while in London, had received, through a channelwhich was clearly meant to come to our notice, a message to the effectthat the answers were waiting for him in Paris. The questions were such as might have been asked by any journalist and the answersfollowed the standard Communist line.The Prime Minister said that on the whole he did not think theUnited States were being over optimistic about the situation in vietnam. The Vietcong had suffered enormous losses during therecent attacks on South Vietnamese cities: there had been no risingof the civil population of South Vietnam against the Government:and none of their forces had deserted. He did not have theimpression that the United States Government believed they could in the foreseeable future impose a military solution on Vietnam: but,equally, they were determined that a military solution should not be imposed by the other side. As a result of the recent attacks on south vietnamese cities public opinion in the United States was running in
Middle East(previous reference:CC (68) 11thConclusions,Minute 2)the Presidents favour. The Russians, and probably the Vietnamese,seriously underestimated the strength of American public opinion insupport of the war. The &quot; hawks &quot; who wished to escalate the war were in the ascendant; but the President was strongly resisting them.A lot would depend on what happened if there were a second round of Vietcong attacks in South Vietnam; whether many Americans were killed; and whether there was a successful rising in South Vietnamitself. It was not out of the question that the President himselfmight, before the Presidential election in November, make a dramaticbid for peace, just as President Eisenhower had done in Korea beforethe Presidential election of 1952. In the speech which he had made after dinner at the White House on 8th February, the Prime ministers aid he had sounded a warning note against the dangers of escalation.The speech had been well received by his audience and by thePresident, who had evidently been glad to have things said which hecould not say himself. There was little more we could now do except to keep in close touch with the United States Government with a viewto preventing any change in their present mood.The Foreign Secretary said that it was difficult to make anyreliable assessment of the military situation in Vietnam until it was clear whether there was going to be a second round of attacks on south Vietnamese cities and what the results would be. There wasno doubt that the Vietcong had suffered considerable losses; but theywere still in control of parts of Saigon, Cholon and Hue. If therewere a second wave of attacks, the United States forces might be in serious danger; and the United States Marines&apos; position at Khe Sanhmight be overrun. From a military point of view the Vietcong wereplaying from a strong hand. The authority and morale of the south vietnamese Government were low and their pacification programme had been disrupted. On the other hand the Americans now had theadvantage of knowing what they were up against. The enemy had come out into the open and the United States forces had got to gripswith them. It there were a second round of attacks on south vietnamese cities, the Americans would be prepared and would notbe taken relatively by surprise as they had been in the first round.The situation in Laos and Cambodia was also giving grounds for concern. There was a serious risk that the United States forces would pursue North Vietnamese and Vietcong guerillas into Laos orCambodia and thus provoke another international crisis. The SovietGovernment had refused to agree to the reinforcement of theInternational Control Commission either by the provision ofhelicopters or by an increase in the number of observers; and therewas reason to believe that they might welcome the prospect of theUnited States becoming embroiled in this way with Laos andCambodia.The Foreign Secretary said that he was doing everything possibleto get work started on clearing the Suez Canal. But it was necessaryto recognise that the re-opening of the Canal now appeared to be along way off.
SECRETLegislation 4.   The  Cabinet   considered   memoranda   on   immigrationlegislation by the Home Secretary (C (68) 34), the commonwealth secretary (C (68) 35) and the Attorney-General (C (68) 36).Commonwealth The Home Secretary said that he was seeking the approval of immigration uie Cabinet to introduce legislation on four aspects of Commonwealth(Previous immigration. Three of his proposals had been endorsed by theCC (65) 42nd appropriate Ministerial Committee. The first of these was designedConclusions)    to deal with the clandestine entry of immigrants, mainly Pakistanis.who, as the law stood at present, were able to avoid immigration control altogether if they succeeded in doing so for 24 hours.Secondly, he proposed that power should be taken to prevent the entry of children under the age of 16 who came to join a singleimmigrant parent in this country; this was intended primarily to dealwith the problem of boys, particularly from Pakistan, near to workingage, who came to join all-male households, thus evading the vouchersystem and creating social problems. The powers would bediscretionary and would be used to keep family units together ratherthan to keep them apart. Thirdly, he proposed that, in order tomeet the strongly expressed wishes of the health authorities, thewives and children of immigrants should have to undergo a medical examination on entry. It was not intended to put them on the same basis as voucher holders, who could be refused entry on healthgrounds, but to compel them to go for treatment after entry should this be necessary.His fourth proposal, which was both urgent and controversial,was that immigration control should be extended to citizens of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies who did not belong to this country inthe sense of having any direct family connection with it or havingbeen naturalised or adopted here. There were about 400,000 such people who at present had the right to come permanently to thiscountry if they wished; about 200,000 lived in East Africa, mainly in kenya. In addition, there were about one million persons of dualnationality with similar rights who would be affected by the proposed legislation, but these did not pose as serious a practical or moralproblem. Until 1966 immigrants from East Africa had been enteringthis country at the rate of about 6,000 annually, but there had been aPeople&apos;republic ofSouthernYemen(previous reference:CC (67) 37thConclusions,Minute 3) -The Foreign Secretary said that we were entering a difficult period in our relations with the Government of the People&apos;s republic of Southern Yemen. The Government had sentenced the AmirHood to death, but as a result of his own intervention, the sentencehad been commuted to 15 years&apos; imprisonment. Three other Sultanswere in the Governments hands; and the charges against themspecifically referred to their association with us.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Prime Minister and theForeign Secretary.
sharp increase in the summer of 1967. Although Ministers had thenconsidered whether action should be taken to deal with the problem,a decision had been deferred. It was now clear that the increasedflow was continuing and might become a flood. It was due to theAfricanisation policy of the Kenya Government who, although theywere not actually expelling Asians, were making it increasingly difficult for them to obtain employment in certain trades andprofessions.   The influx was being stimulated by publicity.The problem was extremely difficult. On the one hand therewere the obligations which we had undertaken when Kenya and other colonial territories had achieved independence that their citizens who did not opt for local nationality would retain the rights of citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonies. There were also the various international conventions which we had signed or ratified which made it difficult for us to deny entry to these people, although suchconventions had not in his view been intended to deal with the kindof problem which we now faced. On the other hand, there was thefact that, unless we took action now, we might this year have toaccept a total of 150,000 immigrants from this source and under theCommonwealth Immigration Act; this would be more even than in1961 when immigrants had Hooded in before that Act came intoforce. So large an influx was more than we could absorb, especially since Asian immigrants tended to concentrate in particular localities in this country; and, unless the influx could be greatly reduced, therewas a very real risk that our efforts to create a multi-racial society inthis country would fail. Some of the provisions of the forthcomingRace Relations Bill, which was aimed at creating such a society,would in any event encounter serious opposition; the passage of theBill would be jeopardised if nothing were done to reduce the presentflow of Asian immigrants from Kenya. In these circumstances theonly practical and fair course was to legislate in the way that he proposed, and in doing so to eliminate the contingent liability thatproblems similar to that which had arisen in Kenya might createin other countries having large numbers of citizens of the UnitedKingdom and Colonies or dual citizens. We should at thesame time allot a generous quota of vouchers to this new class of controlled immigrants which would be in addition to those alreadygranted under the Commonwealth Immigration Act. Although weshould do what we could to persuade the Government of Kenya to moderate its actions against Asians in that country and also seek theagreement of the Governments of India and Pakistan to accept someof them should they wish to go to those countries, we could not afford to delay legislation which to be effective must be passed very quickly.The Commonwealth Secretary said that he accepted the needfor legislation to deal with the clandestine entry of immigrants, withthe entry of dependent children of immigrants and with the medical examination of wives and families. He was, however, strongly opposed to depriving citizens of the United Kingdom and Coloniesof the right to enter this country freely. Although he recognised the difficult problems that would be created by a continued influx of alarge number of Asians from Kenya, to pass such legislation would
be wrong in principle, clearly discriminatory on grounds of colour,and contrary to everything that we stood for. We should be going back on legal and contractual obligations which we had undertakenas recently as 1963 and which had been an essential element in theprocess by which we had been able to hand over our responsibilities in Kenya and the other colonies concerned. We should effectivelydeprive large numbers of people of any citizenship at all or, at best,turn them into second-class citizens. Although these people werenot yet being expelled from Kenya, under Kenyan laws they werenot allowed to remain in the country unless they had work permitsand these were not being granted. If we were to pass the proposed legislation we should face strong criticism both at home and abroad,particularly when, as was inevitable, large numbers of people arrivedat our ports with British passports but were refused entry.We should therefore seek other ways of reducing the flow of immigrants to manageable&quot; proportions so that our policy of integration could succeed. The Home Secretary&apos;s proposals ondependents&apos; clandestine entry would go some way to reducing the flow but, in addition, he would support a policy.under which the flow of immigrants from other sources, and particularly India and pakistan, which were not facing their responsibilities in this matter,was reduced, and priority for immigration was given to those entitledto British passports. At the same time we should bring pressure tobear on Kenya to control the number of emigrants. Although therewas no prospect that President Kenyatta could be persuaded to drophis policy of Africanisation, there were growing indications that some members of the Government of Kenya were becoming alarmed atthe effects on the economy of the large exodus of relativelywell-educated, highly qualified and prosperous Asians. We should therefore decide against legislation in this matter and Mr. Malcolm Macdonald, our Special Representative in East and Central Africa,should visit President Kenyatta urgently and attempt to persuade him to control the emigration of Asians from East Africa.The Attorney-General said that, if we were to pass legislationdepriving citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonies of the rightto enter this country, our position in relation to the relevantinternational agreements and declarations would be difficult but not impossible. In the case of the Universal Declaration of human rights, the United Nations Convention on Racial discrimination and the International Convention on Civil and Political Rights, we might justify our action on the grounds, among others, that thepeople concerned did not in any real sense belong to this country.The European Convention on Human Rights presented greater difficulties. Article 3 of the Fourth Protocol of this Conventionprovided that no-one should be deprived of the right to enter theterritory of the State of which he was a national, and it would bedifficult to argue that refusal of entry to an Asian immigrant from east Africa would not be in breach of this provision.   But although
we had signed this Protocol we had not yet ratified it. A problemalso arose in relation to the proposed restriction on the right of entry of dependent children, since Article 8 of the same Convention,provided that everyone had the right to respect for his family life;it could be contended that refusal of entry to the dependent child ofone parent already in this country was contrary to this provision.There were already two cases before the European Commission inwhich it was being alleged that we were in breach of the EuropeanConvention, and we had accepted the right of individuals to petitionthe Commission and the compulsory jurisdiction of the EuropeanCourt of Human Rights. It would be a serious matter to refuse toobey the decision of the Court or of the Committee of Ministers sinceparties to the Convention had undertaken to accept their decisions as binding.In discussion there was general agreement that legislation shouldbe introduced to deal with the clandestine entry of immigrants, to restrict the right of entry of dependent children of immigrants andto make the medical examination of their wives and childrencompulsory. On the proposal to deprive citizens of the UnitedKingdom and Colonies of the right to enter this country freely,opinion was divided. On the one hand it was argued that for reasons of moral principle, because of the effect that such action would have on our international standing and because of the practical difficulties that we should face, we should not legislate in this matter. although we should not be depriving these people of citizenship we should betaking away its most essential feature and creating a new class of refugees. At the very least a decision should be delayed until thepractical and legal problems had been further examined and anattempt made to reach a solution in consultation with theGovernments of Kenya, India and Pakistan. We had given solemnpledges to these people in 1963 and, very recently, compounded thesituation by giving assurances to people similarly placed in Aden. Ifholders of United Kingdom passports presented themselves here andwere turned away, having nowhere else to go, the Government mightbe faced with a public outcry in this country and serious criticismabroad.On the other hand it was argued that in our present economicsituation and with the great pressure on the social services,particularly on education, we could not afford to allow theunrestricted entry of the Asians from East Africa. The situation inthe schools in some localities was already very grave and becomingworse, with increasingly high proportions of immigrant children in individual schools some schools might soon be used wholly byimmigrant children. There was opposition in the trade union movement to some of the measures which it was proposed to include in the Race Relations Bill and this would become more serious if thenumbers of coloured immigrants entering the country were allowedto rise. The proposed legislation would undoubtedly represent a major change in policy, but we had already made a similar break with tradition when the Commonwealth Immigration Act was passed.
Although we had given assurances to these people when Kenyabecame independent, we could not now afford to honour them, andin these circumstances the right course was to give them a share ofvouchers within whatever total we could afford to allocate toimmigrants as a whole. This would mean that they would know thatthey could, if they wished, join a queue and in due course enter thiscountry. Urgent examination was necessary of the total numbersof immigrants we could afford to accept and what the share forAsians from East Africa should be. It was urged, however, thatdelay would be dangerous because we might be faced with anuncontrollable flow of immigrants. We should either legislatequickly and arrangements could be made to pass the Bill through parliament in a day and a half or we should announce that wewere not going to legislate to exclude holders of United Kingdompassports and thus reduce the incentive to come here in the immediatefuture.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were agreed that legislation should be introduced to dealwith clandestine immigration, to restrict the right of entry of dependent children of immigrants, and to make compulsory themedical examination of immigrants&apos; wives and children. TheCabinet were not at present prepared to take a decision either tointroduce legislation to deprive citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies of the right of free entry into this country or to announce that no such legislation would be introduced. It was, however,essential that an early decision should be taken and they should therefore consider the matter again at their meeting on22nd February, when a final decision must be taken. In themeantime the Commonwealth Secretary should arrange urgently for mr. Malcolm MacDonald to visit President Kenyatta in an effort to persuade him to control the rate of Asian emigration from Kenya;before this visit Mr. MacDonald should be briefed on all aspects ofthe problem. An approach should also be made to the Governmentsof India and Pakistan. The Home Secretary should arrange for officials to examine and report on what reduction in the total numberof Commonwealth immigrants was likely to result from the restrictive measures which the Cabinet had approved; the appropriateallocation of vouchers to citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies on the assumption that these were deprived of the right of normal entry to this country; the extent to which the present allocation of vouchers to Commonwealth countries might be reduced toallow for this; and what criteria should be adopted for the allocation of the new class of vouchers. Mr. Duncan Sandys intended to seekleave to introduce a Bill on Asian immigration from East Africaunder the 10-minute rule on 28th February or earlier but arrangements should if possible be made for the time to be taken by another Member. The Home Secretary would, however, have toindicate, in reply to Questions later in the day, that the problem ofAsian immigrants was being considered.
The Cabinet (1) Agreed that legislation should be introduced to deal withclandestine immigration, with restrictions on the rightof entry of dependent children of immigrants and withthe compulsory medical examination of their wives andchildren.(2) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary, in consultation with theHome Secretary, to arrange for Mr. Malcolm MacDonaldto visit President Kenyatta on the basis indicated in thePrime Ministers summing up and to report the results ofthis visit before their meeting on 22nd February.(3) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to arrange for consultations with the Governments of India and Pakistanon the problem of Asian immigration from Kenya and toreport their outcome on 22nd February.(4) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for officials to carryout the examination indicated by the Prime Minister inhis summing up of their discussion and report by 22ndFebruary.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,15th February, 1968.



</content>
</cab>
