<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/43/0 images: 414-425</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cc (68)27th ConclusionPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1968Copy No.9 cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room, House of Commons, S.W.1,on Thursday, 11th April, 1968, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. HaroldThe Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (In  the Chair for part ofItem 2)The Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Peter Shore,SecretaryAffairsm p,of   State   for   economic the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Secretary of State for Education and science the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Paymaster general wilson, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Lord President of the Council(Items 1 and 3)The Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p, lord privy Seal (Item 1)The Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. George Thomson,mp, Secretary of State for Common-wealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of Transport (Item 1)The Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas,m p, Secretary of State for WalesAlso present:The Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury(Items 1 and 3)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. R. R. D. mcintosh mr. K. barnes mr. P. E. Thornton
contents item Subject page 1     Approach to Europe ...............&apos;   european Space policy      Housing Policy       ...     ...      ...      ..........       5The Older Houses: Draft White Papers3     Unilateralist Demonstration     ......      ......       9Aldermaston March
confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary on European space policy (C (68) 69).The Prime Minister said that he had considered with the foreign secretary the outcome of the last meeting of the ministerial committee on the Approach to Europe when this subject had beendiscussed and when the Foreign Secretary had found no support forhis views. The issues at stake were important. He thought therefore that the Cabinet should consider whether it might not be possible,and desirable, to postpone the announcement of our decisions onspace, which no one wished to reopen, so that we could announcepositive proposals for European technological collaboration inparticular, by speeding the establishment of the proposed EuropeanTechnological Centre at the same time as we made known ourlargely negative decisions on European space projects. A smallMinisterial group might then be set up and charged with the task of formulating a programme of practical proposals for earlyimplementation.The Foreign Secretary said that although he had set out in his memorandum the general opinion of the Ministerial Committee,he still adhered to the view that we should aim to postponeannouncement of our decisions on space until a general technologicalconference had been convened at which we could put these decisions in the context of our aims and proposals for European technologicalcollaboration as a whole. Our decisions on space which would bea profound disappointment to other European Governments, hadimportant implications not only for our European policy but for our foreign policy generally. While we could and should explain thatwe believed that the right approach to collaboration lay not throughuneconomic intergovernmental projects but through fosteringcollaboration and integration between European industries, the fact remained that we had at present no satisfactory programme of actionto offer in place of the space projects. We should therefore postpone the announcement of our decisions until a general technologicalconference had been convened, by which time we must be in aposition to offer a practical programme of our own. However, ifit were nevertheless decided that our decisions should be revealednow, preparations had been completed for the despatch of thenecessary messages to Dr. Stoltenberg, the German Minister of science and chairman of the Bonn Space Conference, and to theEuropean Foreign Ministers concerned. The Lord President had also made the necessary arrangements for domestic presentation ofthese decisions.In discussion it was the general view that nothing would be gained by postponing the announcement of our decisions and that much might be lost. In the first place, it was a mistake to suppose that the Government could, or indeed should, work out a series ofcollaborative projects for early presentation to our Europeanpartners.   There was a remote possibility of agreement by the
summer on a European advanced combat aircraft, but in general we did not wish to promote further Government-to-Government projectsbut to stimulate industries to restructure on a European scale (withthe minimum of finance provided by Governments). Our approach to technological collaboration was based on the establishment ofthe European Technological Centre, whose purpose would be to discover in which fields European industry had most to gain fromcollaboration and reorganisation on a European scale and torecommend the methods by which this might best be achieved. a successful Centre could be operated only with the general supportof European industry as well as of European Governments. the confederation of British Industries and the Government were carrying on discussions with their European colleagues in order topromote the Centre but its establishment would inevitably take aconsiderable time. We should in any event seriously prejudice the chances of the Centre if we sought to link it, at a generaltechnological conference, with our decisions on space: the Centrewould then be regarded by the Europeans as a presentational devicerather than a serious proposal. The date of any generaltechnological conference should be related to our preparedness for it and not to the presentational needs of our space policy: if ageneral technological conference were called as soon as June weshould almost certainly not be properly prepared. For two or threeyears we had been postponing announcement of our decisions onspace because of their possible effect on our European policy, butit was doubtful whether they would have a decisive effect on thefuture of our approach to Europe and further delay in announcingthem would be unlikely to provide us with a better occasion. Itshould not be overlooked that when we had raised objections tocostly European projects as for example with Dr. Stoltenberg inrespect of the 300 percent accelerator we had found a considerable measure of support from other European Governments. Finally, ameeting of the Committee of Alternates had been called for23rd April and a Ministerial meeting for 29th April to take stock of Government positions. If we delayed telling our Europeanpartners of our decisions beyond the meeting on 29th April weshould be charged with wrecking the Bonn conference. In thesecircumstances our best course was to make our decisions knownfully and forthrightly and as soon as possible.If it was agreed that our decisions should now be made knownto our European partners, it was important that these decisions,and the reasons for them, should be presented at home at the sametime as they were made known abroad; and arrangements forPress briefing to this end were in hand. It was reasonable to expecta favourable domestic reception for a clear-cut decision to stopfurther wasteful Government expenditure on these projects providedthat our general approach to technological collaboration with europe was also clearly explained. It was proposed that messages should go to Dr. Stoltenberg and the Foreign Ministers concerned on16th April; and that the British Press should be fully briefed on thesame day but with an embargo until 17th April.  Parliament would
secret. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of housing and Local Government and the Secretary of State for Wales(C (68) 66) and a note by the Secretary of State for Scotland(C (68) 67) to which were attached draft White Papers on the olderhouses in England and Wales and in Scotland respectively.The Minister of Housing said that the draft White Papers hadbeen approved by the Housing Committee. Agreement had beenreached with the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the figures forhave to be informed at the first opportunity after the Easter recess,on 23rd April.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet endorsed the decision of the Ministerial Committee on the approach to Europe that we should communicate our decisions onspace policy to the European Governments concerned immediatelyafter the Easter holiday. Arrangements should be made to ensurethat the Press received briefing so that there was full and informeddomestic presentation at the same time as our decisions became known abroad. Parliament should be informed at the earliest opportunity. Meanwhile swift progress was required towards theestablishment of the European Technological Centre; and theMinister of Technology should also give urgent consideration to theorganisation of a pilot study of the advantages which might accrue from and the problems which might be involved in theorganisation on a European scale of, for example, a sector of theelectronics industry.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the summing up by the PrimeMinister.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with the lord president and the Minister of Technology, to arrange formessages to be delivered to Dr. Stoltenberg and to theEuropean Foreign Ministers concerned, immediately afterthe Easter holiday, conveying the Governments decisions on space policy.(3) Invited the Lord President, in consultation with the foreign secretary, the Lord Privy Seal and the Minister of technology, to arrange for the domestic presentation ofour space policy to Parliament and the Press.(4) Invited the Minister of Technology (i) to take the action necessary to speed the establish-ment of the European Techological Centre;(ii) to consider the organisation of a pilot study onthe lines indicated in the Prime Ministetssumming up.
expenditure on old and new housing in England and Wales forthe forthcoming Public Expenditure Survey, though without commitment on the programme to be finally settled; the white paper would not prejudice that settlement. The intention behind the policy embodied in the White Paper was to bring about aredeployment of resources from new housing to improvement of theexisting housing stock. Total expenditure in housing would be moreor less stablished, with increased expenditure on old houses offset byreduced expenditure on new construction. This switch of emphasiswould prevent deterioration in a national asset and the break upof existing communities; and the new proposals would have considerable administrative advantages. The proposals had beendiscussed with the local authority associations who were likely to welcome them warmly.As regards improvement and repair, a new duty would be laid on local authorities to secure improvement of whole areas of housing and they would be given extended powers for this purpose. Therewould be increases in the limits on grants for improvement andconversion, and more liberal rules for eligibility. Powers of compulsory purchase would be strengthened, though they wouldbe used only as a last resort. There would be wider powers tocontrol multiple occupation.The proposals were also designed to speed up slum clearance.On present rates of clearance, we should not be rid of slums forsome 25 years. A major obstacle to progress was the present basisof compensation to owner-occupiers for property acquired forclearance. With limited exceptions, this was based on the site valueof the property, together with supplements for good maintenance.Since site values for owner-occupied property were normallysubstantially less than market values, the present arrangements wereunfair and local authorities were therefore reluctant to press ahead with clearance. It was proposed that owner-occupiers in futurewould be compensated on the basis of market value. The difficulties were less acute with tenanted property, and here compensation would continue to be based on site value, but supplements for goodmaintenance would be increased. These proposals, together with more vigorous action to improve the existing housing stock andthe reform of housing subsidies which was now under consideration,offered the prospect of completing slum clearance within a decade.Entitlement to compensation on the new basis would date from thepublication of the White Paper; this was necessary to avoid delay in clearance programmes which would otherwise be likely in the interval between the appearance of the White Paper and the enactment of legislation.The law on rents would also be changed. Houses at presentsubject to rent control would pass to rent regulation (i.e., the &quot;fair rent&quot; system) once they were brought up to the required standardof repair, whether or not this was done with the assistance of agrant. This was essential if landlords were to be given an adequateincentive to effect repairs. Rent increases resulting from these provisions would be subject to phasing; they would take effect only
after the passage of the legislation and would probably affect notmore than one-third of controlled tenancies.If the Cabinet agreed, he proposed that the White Paper, subjectto any necessary drafting amendments, should be published aboutthe 23rd April.The Secretary of State for Wales said he fully supported theproposals outlined by the Minister of Housing. One-third of thehouses in Wales were over 80 years old, and the proportion of owner-occupied property was much higher than in England. Thenew policy would therefore be specially relevant to Welsh housingproblems. It would be important in the conditions obtaining in wales to use the extended powers of compulsory purchase only as a last resort. The proposal that houses in a satisfactory state of repairshould pass from rent control to rent regulation was likely eventually to mean the virtual elimination of rent control.The Secretary of State for Scotland said the proposals in theWhite Paper annexed to his note were broadly on the same lines as in the White Paper for England and Wales, except that inScotland there would be a new standard of &quot; tolerability&quot; forpurposes of defining the areas of older houses needing treatment bylocal authorities. However, Scottish housing problems were different from those of England and Wales. There were in Scotland some300,000 old houses which needed to be replaced urgently; a further200,000 needed rehabilitation; these categories together accountedfor 30 per cent of the total housing stock. 40 per cent of homeswere in tenements or flats; improvement of these was difficult and expensive, and normally resulted in a reduction in the number of families which could be accommodated. In these conditions,attempts to improve the housing stock under existing powers hadlargely failed, and only modest results could be expected from thepresent proposals. There was no room for a switch of resources from new building to improvement and repair since it was seldompossible to effect improvements without providing new housing forsome of the people displaced. While he had accepted that totalexpenditure on Scottish housing should not be increased by reasonof the new policy in 1968-69 or 1969-70, he could not agree thatthe existing programme for new housing in subsequent years shouldbe reduced to accommodate additional expenditure under theprovisions of the White Paper.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it was essential thatapproval of the policies for older houses should be on the basis thatimplementation of these policies would not lead to an increase inthe future total expenditure on housing, but that increased spendingon older houses should be balanced by reduced expenditure on new construction. Unless we proceeded on this basis, the result wouldbe to approve an increase in the housing programme in isolation, atthe expense of other programmes. He could accept the publicationof the White Paper for England and Wales on the basis of theagreement reached with the Minister of Housing and the Secretary
of State for Wales as regards the implications for public expenditure.But he had not been able to reach similar agreement with theSecretary of State for Scotland; until this had been done, on thebasis he had indicated, he could not agree to publication of theWhite Paper for Scotland.He wished to make two detailed points. First, it should bemade clearer in paragraphs 1 and 2 of the White Paper on Englandand Wales and in paragraph 9 of the White Paper on Scotlandthat what was involved was a shift of resources within the totalhousing programme with no overall increase in expenditure. Second,while the White Paper on England and Wales proposed that houses in a satisfactory state of repair should pass from rent control torent regulation whether or not the owner had been assisted by grant,the corresponding proposal in the White Paper for Scotland relatedonly to property where repairs had been effected with the assistanceof a grant. The Scottish White Paper should be brought into line in this respect.In discussion there was general approval of the contents ofthe White Paper for England and Wales subject to amendments to meet the points made by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.There was general support for the view that implementation ofthe new policies should not lead to an increase in total housing expenditure for Scotland in 1970-71 and subsequent years. It mightbe that because of the different conditions in Scotland, it would be wrong at the present time to increase expenditure on improvement and repair at the expense of new building; it might be preferable tocontinue to concentrate for the time being on the provision of new housing and to review the case for a switch of emphasise towardsolder houses at a later stage. This would mean that there should beno White Paper for Scotland at the present time. If, however, itwas regarded as essential that there should be a White Paper forScotland, it would be necessary for the Secretary of State to reach agreement with the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the implications for total housing expenditure before the White Paper was published.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet approved the draft White Paper for England and Wales,subject to amendments to meet the points made in discussion andto any further drafting amendments which were thought desirable.The Minister of Housing and the Secretary of State for Wales should arrange for the White Paper to be published as soon as possible after the Easter recess. The Secretary of State for Scotland should consider further in the light of the discussion whether he wished toabandon the proposals for new arrangements for improving oldhouses and the publication of the White Paper for Scotland at thisstage. If he concluded that the proposals should not be abandoned and that there should be a White Paper, he should seek to reach agreement with the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the implications for total housing expenditure in Scotland in 1970-71 and subsequent years, on the basis that additional expenditure in pursuance of thenew policies should not lead to an increase in overall housing expenditure.  If agreement could not be reached, the issues should
UnilateralistDemonstrationAldermastonMarch(previous reference:CC (68) 26thConclusions,Minute 5)confidential. The Prime Minister said that, in view of the risk of disorder arising as a result of attempts by persons taking part inthe march from Aldermaston to London to break into the atomic weapons Research Establishment (AWRE) and the Royal OrdnanceFactory, Burghfield, it was important that it should be made clearwhere responsibility for controlling any disorder lay. He had accordingly asked the Home Secretary, as the Minister responsiblefor the maintenance of public order, to ensure, in consultation withthe Secretary of State for Defence and the Minister of Technology,that a clear command structure was established, that adequatenumbers of service and departmental police were available at thetwo establishments and, if necessary, that helicopters were provided to move police reinforcements to the scene of any disorders.be brought back to the Cabinet. If agreement were reached, theWhite Paper for Scotland, amended to meet the points made in discussion and to incorporate any further drafting changes whichthe Secretary of State thought desirable, could then be published.While it was desirable, assuming there was to be a White Paper forScotland, for the two White Papers to be published simultaneously,publication of the White Paper for England and Wales should notbe delayed on this account and if necessary the White Paper forScotland would have to be published later.The Cabinet (1) Approved the text of the draft White Paper for Englandand Wales annexed to C (68) 66, subject to the amendments proposed in discussion and any furtherdrafting amendments which the responsible Ministersdeemed desirable.:(2) Invited the Minister of Housing and the Secretary of Statefor Wales, in consultation with the Lord President, toarrange for publication of the White Paper for Englandand Wales as soon as possible after the Easter Recess.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland (i) to consult the Chancellor of the Exchequer onthe basis indicated in the Prime Minister^summing up;(ii) if agreement could be reached on the financial implications, to arrange, in consultation with theLord President, for the publication of the white paper (subject to the amendments proposed in discussion and any further drafting amendmentshe thought desirable);(iii) if agreement could not be reached, to bring the issueagain before the Cabinet.
The Home Secretary said that the march was expected to attract to this country foreign students, including a number ofGerman students of a type which had introduced new and moreviolent tactics on the occasion of the demonstration in GrosvenorSquare on 17th March. The police were anxious that foreignstudents should be refused entry, but only one of those expectedhad been charged as a result of the disorders in Grosvenor Squareand it was not clear on what grounds the exclusion of others couldbe justified.In discussion it was pointed out that this type of demonstrationwas increasingly being organised on an international scale byanarchist and Communist elements, who, unlike the Campaign for nuclear Disarmament, were interested in provoking violence. TheGovernment would be open to criticism if so soon after theGrosvenor Square demonstration they permitted foreign students tocome in and violence of a similar kind occurred. On the otherhand, it was wrong to exclude all foreign students, irrespective ofany known record of previous violence. Moreover, it was important that both the civil and service police should keep the use of forcein restraining the demonstrators to a minimum, and that the Directorof the Royal Ordnance Factory, who intended to have army department constabulary, with dogs and fire hoses, ready to repelthe expected attempts to penetrate to the vital areas of the factory,should act in close accord with the civil police.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that, while there should be no general exclusion offoreign students, any individual known to the police of his own country to have been concerned in violence should be refused entry,and the Home Secretary should seek relevant information from thepolice forces concerned. The arrangements to be concerted by theHome Secretary with the Secretary of State for Defence and theMinister of Technology should, in particular, establish clearly whereresponsibility for action within the perimeter of the Atomic WeaponsResearch Establishment and the Royal Ordnance Factory rested.The Cabinet Invited the Home Secretary (i) to deal with foreign students seeking entry to thiscountry in connection with the Aldermaston Marchon the lines indicated in the Prime Minister^summing up;(ii) in consultation with the Secretary of State for defence and the Minister of Technology, to ensure that thearrangements for dealing with the march included a clear understanding as to the command structure,the responsibility for action inside the perimeter oftwo establishments concerned, and the arrangementsfor the use of service and departmental police.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,11th April, 1968.



</content>
</cab>
