<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/43/0 images: 442-455</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. August 1968CC (68) Copy No.    3329th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W. 1, on Thursday, 16th May, 1968at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Right Hon. Peter Shore, m p,Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas, mp,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Richard Grossman,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p, lord privy seal the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon.  Lord Shackleton,Paymaster GeneralThe following were also present:The Right Hon. Judith Hart, mp,Minister of Social Security (Item 6)Sir Arthur Irvine, qc, mp, Solicitor-General (Item 5)The Right Hon. John Diamond, mp,Chief Secretary, Treasury (Items 4-6)The Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. E. M. rose mr. R. R. D. mcintosh mr. L. errington mr. K. barnes mr. P. E. Thornton
contents item Subject page 1     Parliamentary Affairs      ...............       3Report of the Parliamentary Committee on ElectoralReformNext Week&apos;s business     Oversea Affairs   .........        .........       5RhodesiaPeople&apos;s Republic of the Southern YemenMiddle EastForeign Secretary&apos;s Visit to Moscow3     Industrial Affairs   ......     ............      7Pay  Claims  in the  Shipbuilding  and  EngineeringIndustries4     Public Expenditure  ...     ............      ...       85     Prices and Incomes   ..................       9Prices and Incomes bill     Social Services        ..................     11Responsibility for the Early Days of Sickness
ParliamentaryAiffairsCC 29 (68)secret. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that theParliamentary Committee had considered at a recent meeting therecommendations of the Sub-Committee on Electoral Reform, whichhad carried out a comprehensive examination of the recent Reportof the Speakers Conference on Electoral Law. On the main issues involved the Parliamentary Committee had reached the followingprovisional conclusions:(a) The minimum age for voting, which the speakers conference recommended should be 20, should be reduced to 18.(b) In conformity with the majority recommendation of the speakers Conference, the proposal that there should be a secondannual register should be rejected, primarily on grounds of economy.(c) The hours of polling, on which the Speakers Conference had recommended no change, should be extended to 10 p.m.(d) It would be preferable to reject the recommendation of the speakers Conference that publication of the results of public opinionpolls and betting odds should be prohibited within 72 hours of the poll.(e) The prohibition on the use of Party labels on nominationand ballot papers should be removed, despite the recommendationof the Speakers Conference to the contrary effect. The difficultieswhich might result in local government elections should be thesubject of further examination.(/) Further consideration should be given to the questionwhether, if Party labels were permitted, it should continue to benecessary for a candidate to state his occupation.These conclusions were, of course, subject to approval by theCabinet; but it might be preferable for the Cabinet to defer detailed discussion until they had before them the draft of a White paper which was now being prepared. It would then be possible for ministers to raise any other point which they thought requiredexamination, e.g., the desirability of declaring polling day a public holiday.In discussion some concern was expressed about the wisdom ofa decision to reduce the voting age to 18. There was no evidence ofa substantial public demand for this change; nor should it beregarded as following necessarily from the Governmenfs recent decision to accept the recommendation of the Committee on theAge of Majority that the age of majority should be reduced to 18 forother purposes. Moreover, it could not be assumed that the change would operate to the electoral advantage of the Government. Manyof the Governmenfs supporters would not give to this latest instanceof progressive social reform any warmer welcome than they had given to such earlier examples as the Governments proposals to reform the law on divorce and abortion. And the young themselveswere more likely to give their support to the more extreme formsof political opinion, particularly the nationalist movements inScotland and Wales, than to the established political Parties.   The9112
extent to which, they could be influenced by their teachers in thisrespect should not be under-rated; and considerable problems could arise in connection with the teaching of political subjects and currentaffairs in the schools. The situation would be aggravated if areduction in the voting age to 18 led to a demand that young peopleof that age should also be entitled to stand as candidates for parliament; and such a reduction in the age of candidacy might haveconsequences for the House of Lords which ought to be considered in conjunction with the proposed reform of that House.On the other hand there was considerable support for the viewthat, quite apart from the extent to which the issue had in effect been determined already by the Governments decision to reduce the ageof majority for other purposes to 18, the change v/ould be right on merits. All earlier measures of electoral reform for example, the granting of votes to women had in fact merely recognised a stateof affairs which public opinion had already accepted; and this wouldbe found to be equally true in the present instance. It was now generally accepted that young people matured at an earlier age thanin the past; and, if they were to be accepted as fully responsible inthe social and commercial contexts with which the Committee onthe Age of Majority had been concerned, there was no-valid reasonfor refusing to grant them a corresponding degree of politicalenfranchisement. Indeed, to accept that they were capable of responsible political behaviour should do much to correct the growingsense of social alienation which undoubtedly lay at the root of someof the more extreme manifestations of youthful insubordinationwhich had recently attracted public attention.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet clearly needed to give more detailed consideration to the issues involved before reaching a final decision; and arrangements would be made for this purpose. The Cabinet should seek to reach an early conclusion on the matter, since it was desirable that, if thechange was to be made, it should take effect in time to be operativebefore the next General Election; and adequate provision wouldhave to be made for the necessary legislation in future legislativeprogrammes.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Lord President to circulate, for consideration atan early meeting, the report of the Sub-Committee on electoral Reform which had examined the conclusions ofthe Speakers Conference on Electoral Law, together withsuch further comments as the Sub-Committee might wishto offer on the points which had been raised in thediscussion.The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it had become clearthat it would be necessary to move a Timetable Motion relating tothe Finance Bill unless the Opposition were prepared to agree to aNextWeek&apos;business
OverseaAffairsRhodesia(previous reference:CC (68) 28thConclusions,Minute 6)confidential. The Foreign Secretary said that it had so far been impossibleto reconcile the views of the Afro-Asian Group and our own on a security Council resolution on Rhodesia. The Afro-Asians couldalready count on seven votes in the Security Council out of the ninenecessary to secure the passage of their draft resolution; and theyhad now obtained the support of Brazil, and probably of Paraguayas well, by omitting any reference to Portugal. He had given theUnited Kingdom Representative at the United Nations, LordCaradon, discretion to inform the members of the Afro-Asian GroupCC 29 (68)voluntary timetable. This, however, seemed unlikely, since theircriticism of the proposal to consider the Finance Bill in Committeeupstairs was based in part on the belief that this would inevitably involve the imposition of a timetable.The Minister of Transport drew attention to the difficulties involved in the proposal to take the Report and Third Reading ofthe Transport Bill on three consecutive days, 27th, 28th and29th May. He understood that it was intended to suspend the sittingat 11.30 each evening and to sit from 10.30 the following morninguntil 2.30 p.m. This would mean that the division on the third reading would come at 2 p.m. on the day preceding the adjournment of the House for the Whitsun Recess, when many Members wouldalready have left; and the almost continuous sittings would makeit very difficult for Ministers to consider amendments put downduring the course of the proceedings. It was pointed out, however,that it would be impossible to begin the Report Stage of the Bill inthe previous week, because the printing of the Bill as amended in committee could not be completed until Saturday, 25th May; andequally impossible to spread consideration of the remaining stagesover a longer period because it was essential that the Bill should leave the House of Commons before the Recess. Moreover, it wouldbe necessary to leave time in the previous week for the discussionof a Timetable Motion on the Prices and Incomes Bill.The Lord Privy Seal said that he would be pressed on theBusiness Statement that afternoon to find time for the discussion ofa Motion in the names of a number of Government supporters calling for the dismissal of Mr. Cecil King from his part-time membership of the National Coal Board. He proposed.to make a non-committalreply.The Prime Minister said that since Mr. King had not renderedit impossible for himself to discharge his statutory duties as amember of the National Coal Board, no question of dismissing himcould arise. While, therefore, the signatories of the Motion shouldnot be unduly discouraged, it was important not to enable Mr. king to assume the guise of a martyr, and the demand for his dismissalshould not be given undue prominence.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to deal with the matter on thelines indicated by the Prime Minister.
People&apos;republic ofthe southern yemen(previous reference:CC (68) 28thConclusions,Minute 6)Middle East(previous reference:CC (68) 28thConclusions,Minute 6)that if they continued to insist on the inclusion in their draft resolution of provisions which we could not accept, we might have toveto it. This was not, however, a final decision to veto the resolution;and if it became necessary to take this step before the next meetingof the Cabinet, he would of course consult his colleagues before thedecision was taken.The Foreign Secretary said that the Government of southern yemen had rejected our offer of further aid; the negotiations had broken down; and our delegation had returned. We should,however, continue to make available until the end of this month the interim aid promised under the Geneva Agreement, provided theSouthern Yemen Government continued to observe the Agreement.Our Ambassador had urged that we should be scrupulously fair incarrying out our part of the Agreement, particular with regard tocertain sums charged against the Southern Yemen Governmentwhich were open to question; and he would be raising this point withthose of his colleagues directly concerned. The Southern YemenGovernment had said that normal relations would continuebetween the two Governments; and there had been no threat to theBritish community or to the British Petroleum refinery. Theauthority of the Southern Yemen Government was, however,precarious, and disturbances had recently broken out in a remotepart of the country. The British community had been warned ofthe dangers of the situation; and the time was approaching when we could no longer afford to keep a large naval task force availablefor their protection. He would be in touch with the defence secretary about this.The Foreign Secretary said that the conciliation mission of theSpecial Representative of the Secretary-General of the united nations, Mr. Gunnar Jarring, had taken a new lease of life. Israel,the United Arab Republic (UAR) and Jordan had agreedto consultations in New York; and Mr. Jarring would be havingdiscussions with their permanent representatives there. The mainobstacles to agreement were the Arab suspicion that Israel intendedto retain the Arab territory she had occupied and the Israelisuspicion that the UAR was not prepared to reach a lastingagreement. During his recent visit to Copenhagen he had agreed with the Danish Government that they would urge the Israel ForeignMinister, Mr. Eban, who was shortly expected there, to refrain fromany action which might give the impression that Israel was proposing to annex the occupied territories. Meanwhile, the United kingdom representative at the United Nations, Lord Caradon, was using his influence to keep down the temperature at the United Nations. Thesituation was complicated by the fact that the United States wishedto omit from any resolution all reference to Jerusalem; and thiswould be difficult for the Arabs to accept.In discussion it was agreed that the decision to hold talks in new york was a considerable step forward and that the influence whichwe had been able to exert in the UAR since the resumption of diplomatic relations had played its part in achieving this result.
Pay claims in theShipbuildingand EngineerinjIndustriesSECRET3. The First Secretary of State said that the EngineeringEmployers&apos; Federation (EEF) had arranged further informal discussions with representatives of the Confederation of shipbuilding and Engineering Unions (CSEU) on 22nd May about the pay claim;in the engineering industry. In these discussions the employers would take soundings in general terms about possible improvementson their present offer to the CSEU. They had not at this stagedisclosed what they had in mind, but would be in touch with herDepartment immediately after the meeting on 22nd May. following the one-day strike on the previous day in support of the CSEU claim,there should be no further industrial action without a reconvening ofthe Executive of the Confederation, and the employers hoped thatthe discussions on 22nd May would be followed quickly by a resumption of formal negotiations.The National Union of Seamen had made a claim for a 5 percent increase in basic rates of pay and improvements in overtime pay.The Shipping Federation had offered improvements amounting toan increase of 3-J per cent on the wages bill; the Union had rejectedthis, but a further joint meeting was to be held on 31st May. she had earlier considered referring the claim to the National Board for prices and Incomes, but had so far refrained from this since therewas still a possibility that the negotiations would lead to a settlement in conformity with incomes policy. She would continue to watch the situation closely.The Cabinet Took note of the statement by the First Secretary of State.SECRETCC 29 (68)The Foreign Secretary recalled that immediately following theinitiative of 1st April by the President of the United States to end thewar in Vietnam he had suggested to the Soviet Government that itmight be useful to exchange views. The Soviet Government had proposed that he should visit Moscow and the visit had now been fixed for 22nd-23rd May. He would return from Moscow by wayof Bonn, where he would see the Federal German Foreign Minister,Herr Brandt. The Soviet Government had asked that no publicmention should be made of the subjects to be discussed. He had therefore taken the line with the Press that it would be unreasonable to suppose that Vietnam would not be among the subjects raised;and these might also include the Middle East. It was difficult to foresee how his discussions would go. The Soviet Governmentwould probably make another attempt to divide us from the UnitedStates. We should have to be particularly careful to avoid makingpublic pronouncements on the various points at issue between theUnited States and North Vietnam as they came up in the course ofthe current peace talks between the two sides in Paris. We hadresisted a request to support the United States line on the place ofthe meeting; and our attitude had been justified by events.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Foreign Secretary andof the points made in discussion.
4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum (C (68) 72) by theChancellor of the Exchequer to which was attached a paper aboutpublic expenditure which he had previously circulated to the ministerial Steering Committee on Economic Policy.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that his paper had beenconsidered at a recent meeting of the Steering Committeeon Economic Policy (SEP) which had endorsed the proposals set outin paragraph 10. He now invited the Cabinet to endorse theseproposals and drew attention particularly to that in paragraph 10 (c),viz. that decisions on new proposals which would add to public expenditure should be postponed until completion of the forthcomingpublic expenditure survey. The projected overspending in both1968-69 and 1969-70 was serious and would have to be resolutelytackled. Representatives of the International Monetary Fund, nowin London to discuss with the Treasury the progress of the UnitedKingdom economy, had naturally attached great importance to thisunfavourable development.The Prime Minister said that the proposals were essentiallyinterim ones pending consideration by SEP during June of the public expenditure survey; of the new savings required to be made in1968-69 and 1969-70; of the investment programmes of the nationalised industries; and of the possibility of adopting a system ofblock control of expenditure. As to block control, the general rulehad been established after the January cuts that any proposals by a department for new expenditure could only be considered ifoffsetting savings could be found within that Departments Vote. Asa long-term policy this seemed an unduly rigid and inflexible rule and SEP were therefore considering the possibility of establishingseparate &quot; budgets &quot;, on the analogy of the defence budget, for blocks of expenditure such as the social services as a whole, overseas expenditure and aid to industry. There would be greater scope foroffsetting increases by corresponding reductions in expenditure within blocks of this kind than within the smaller, DepartmentalVotes. SEP would report their conclusions on all these matters tothe Cabinet about the end of June.In discussion it was pointed out that an urgent decision was required on the level of subsidy to be provided to the fishing industry.The industry a substantial import saver was already in serious financial difficulties yet, under the provisions of the Sea Fish industry act 1962, the present subsidy of  1 -5 million a year would be reducedautomatically by about 20 per cent on 1st August next. a substantially larger subsidy than  1 - 5 million would be required tomaintain the industry and its substantial contribution to the balanceof payments by import saving. Legislation must therefore be enactedbefore 1st August amending the Sea Fish Industry Act 1962 so as topermit the higher rate of subsidy required and a decision could notbe deferred until the public expenditure review had been completed at the end of June. In any event a delay even of a few weeks in informing the fishing industry of an improved subsidy wouldsignificantly increase the risk of a rapid reduction of the fishing fleet.
CC 29 (68)On the other hand it was pointed out that no notice had hitherto been given that a Bill might be required this Session to increase the fishing subsidies and it would almost certainly prove impossible tofind the time for it at this late date. In any event there were not sufficient grounds for exempting the proposals for a larger subsidyfrom the ambit of paragraph 10 (c) of the paper by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer. His proposals would enable the fishing industry tobe offered a continuing subsidy of  1 -5 million a year provided thatthe automatic reduction in subsidy effected by the Sea Fish industry act in August could in some way be avoided and it should bepossible to take a decision by about the end of June when the public expenditure survey had been completed, on whether a larger subsidythan  1 - 5 million a year should be offered. Meanwhile, the ministerial Committee on Agricultural Policy would be able tocomplete its current review of the fishing subsidies and make detailed recommendations about the scale and nature of the future assistanceto be offered to the industry.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet endorsed the proposals in the paper attached to C (68) 72.As to the fishing subsidies, the Lord President, in consultation withthe Lord Privy Seal, the Secretary of State for Scotland, the Ministerof Agriculture and the Chief Secretary, Treasury, should examine whether in fact legislation was required during the currentParliamentary Session to maintain the subsidies at their current levelor to increase them. No decision to increase the subsidies above 1-5 million a year could be taken before completion of theforthcoming public expenditure review.The Cabinet (1) Took note with approval of the summing up by the PrimeMinister.(2) Approved the proposals in paragraph 10 of the memoran-dum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer annexed toC (68) 72.(3) Invited the Lord President in consultation with the lord privy Seal, the Secretary of State for Scotland, theMinister of Agriculture and the Chief Secretary,Treasury, to consider whether legislation was required during the current Session in order to maintain the subsidies to the fishing industry at their current level, orto increase them, after 1st August, 1968.secret. The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet had previouslyagreed that provision should be made for the statutory powers in thePrices and Incomes Bill to continue for a period of 18 months andthat they should be renewable thereafter by the Expiring laws continuance Act (CC (68) 20th Conclusions, Minute 4 and cc (68) 22nd Conclusions, Minute 4). However, when this question was reviewed by the Parliamentary Committee at their meeting on 9th May, it had been the unanimous view that in the light of the
opposition which would otherwise be aroused among theGovernments supporters in Parliament and among the trade unions,there was a strong case for renouncing any intention to use the expiring Laws Continuance Act and for making it clear that if itwere thought necessary to renew the powers after the initial periodof 18 months, this would be done by the introduction of fresh legislation. He had subsequently consulted individually those members of the Cabinet who had not been present at theParliamentary Committee and there had been general agreementwith this course. The Governments position on this matter had accordingly been made clear to their supporters in Parliament.The Cabinet (1) Endorsed the decision that the powers in the Prices and incomes Bill should not on their expiry be renewed bythe Expiring Laws Continuance Act.The First Secretary of State said that the effect of sub-section (4)of clause 3 of the Prices and Incomes Bill was to confer power toextend standstill orders on prices and wages made under existing legislation up to a total duration of 12 months. Thisprovision had particular application to the orders at present in forcein respect of wage increases for municipal busmen and certain groups of draughtsmen. This would be fully appreciated by the employersand unions concerned and the provision would no doubt arousecriticism. It was, however, essential to retain it. It was known thatcertain municipalities would be ready to pay the increase to busmenretrospectively to the date of the settlement as soon as the existingorder expired on 26th July, thus nullifying completely the effect ofthe standstill. If the provision in clause 3 (4) were dropped, therewould be no means of preventing this. She proposed, however, tomake it clear that the Government were in no way committed toextending the duration of existing standstill orders; while therewould be power to do this, she intended to use the interval beforethe expiry of existing orders to encourage the parties tothe settlements in question to negotiate revised agreements inconformity with incomes policy.In discussion it was pointed out that the Government had announced in the Budget debate that the new phase of incomes policy would take effect from 19th March, 1968. While there couldbe no objection in principle to using the new powers to extendstandstill orders made before that date, it could be regarded as unfairthat orders, including that covering busmen, made before the inception of the new phase should be amended under the newpowers. The general view, however, was that in the case of busmenparticularly, the consequences of allowing retrospective payments oftheir wage increase following the expiry of the existing order wouldbe unacceptable in view of the repercussions which this would have on the negotiations in respect of London busmen and on the incomes policy generally; the Government should therefore reserve the rightto extend existing standstill orders, even where these were made before 19th March.
-    229SECRET &quot; 11CC 29 (68)The Cabinet-(2) Agreed that sub-section (4) of clause 3 of the Prices and incomes Bill, providing for the extension of existingstandstill orders, should be retained.The First Secretary of State said that it would be important inthe debate on the Second Reading of the Bill to give the fullest possible evidence of the efficacy of the Governments policy on prices by referring to action already taken or to be taken. She proposedto refer to action on the price of hearing aids following the recent report by the National Board for Prices and Incomes, and ondistributors&apos; margins on the sale of paint which had now been referred to the Board. She was discussing with the President of theBoard of Trade the possibility of announcing that other price increases were being referred to the Board, and was considering withthe Minister of Agriculture whether she could announce voluntary arrangements with the industries concerned to avoid increases in theprices of tea and beer; even though these arrangements would be ona voluntary basis, it would be useful to publicise them. It would alsobe most valuable if an announcement could be made about theMiddle East surcharge on oil prices and she would discuss this withthe Minister of Power.The Cabinet -(3) Invited the Ministers with responsibilities for prices to offer the maximum co-operation to the First Secretary of state in preparing announcements of action on prices to bemade at the Second Reading of the Prices and incomes bill.SocialServicesResponsibilityfor the early days of sickness(previous reference:CC (68) 25thConclusions,Minute 2)confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum (C (68) 73) by theChancellor of the Exchequer on responsibility for the early days of sickness.The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that the Cabinet hadearlier accepted a proposal by the Minister of Social Security for anincrease in family allowances by 3s. Od. a week on a &quot; give and take &quot;basis, the net additional cost being offset by limitation of the rightof occupational pensioners to receive unemployement benefit andby abolition of the present provision for retrospective payment ofbenefit for the first three days of sickness or unemployment lastingfor 12 days or more. The saving from abolishing the payment forwaiting days, which had been incorporated in clause 2 was estimated to be  15 million a year initially, rising to  19 million a year later.The abolition of payment for waiting days was to be effected by clause 2 of the Family Allowances and National Insurance Bill. Inview of the opposition to clause 2 which had developed among theGovernments supporters in the House of Commons, the cabinet had asked the Minister to open consultations with the Trades UnionCongress (TUC) and the Confederation of British Industry (CBI)on  the  possibility  of  substituting  a  more  general  provision
transferring responsibility for the early weeks of sickness to employers; the possibility of retaining clause 2 was, however, to beleft open in case the discussions proved abortive.These consultations had now shown that there was no prospectof reaching early agreement on such a transfer to employers and thatthere was no chance of achieving any saving at all from it in 1969-70,let alone in the current financial year. He accepted that, in presentcircumstances, there was an overwhelming political case againstretaining clause 2 in the Bill and that it should therefore be withdrawn. However, it would be essential that correspondingsavings should be found elsewhere, since they had already been written into the forward estimates of public expenditure and theneed to secure them had become even greater in the light of thelatest forecasts. He had been unable to find any alternative saving in the social security field, and he therefore invited the Cabinet toagree that, if clause 2 were withdrawn, they should makecompensating savings elsewhere in the course of their forthcominggeneral review of public expenditure. In the meantime, thediscussions should continue with both sides of industry on thepossibility of achieving an eventual transfer of responsibility for sickness benefit. The episode had illustrated the dangers ofincurring firm commitments to expenditure in return for hypotheticalsavings before it was clear that the latter could be achieved, and itwould be necessary to look with special caution at any similarproposals in future.In discussion it was suggested that the strength of the oppositionto clause 2 of the Bill could not have been foreseen; and there was general agreement that the clause should now be withdrawn.Corresponding savings should, however, be found elsewhere in thefield of public expenditure, and if possible in expenditure on thesocial services which was currently under examination by the social services Committee.The Cabinet (1) Approved C(68)73.(2) Invited the Lord President to arrange for the Social services committee to consider the possibility of achievingsavings in expenditure on the social services to compensate for the withdrawal of clause 2 of the family allowances and National Insurance Bill.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,16th May, 1968.



</content>
</cab>
