<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/36/0 images: 370-391</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1949The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of        ........(4R*Vrr*-.v......SV.TOP SECRET Copy No,CP. (49) 17523rd August, 1949CABINETTHE ECONOMIC SITUATION-WASHINGTON TALKSNote by the Minister of Fuel and power circulate, for discussion by my colleagues at the meeting arranged for29th August, a draft brief for the forthcoming Ministerial talks in Washington.2. This has been prepared, in the absence of the Chancellor of the Exchequer,by a group of officials of the Departments primarily concerned under the general direction of myself and the Economic Secretary.H. G.23rd August, 1949.37472B
DRAFT BRIEF FOR MINISTERIAL TALKS IN WASHINGTONObjective of the Talks1. The general objective of the three Governments in the Washington talksshould be (a) to secure that all three Governments will work together on a basis of close co-operation in order to establish equilibrium in the balance of pay-ments between the dollar and the sterling and non-dollar areas on apermanent basis, at a high level of trade and without the recurrence of crises.The specific objective of the United Kingdom Government should be^-(b) to secure (a) with the highest standard of living for ourselves and withoutthreatening the maintenance of full employment here.The immediate objective of the United Kingdom Government should be (c) to secure that the United States and Canadian Governments take certain specific steps which, together with the steps taken by the UnitedKingdom Government, will ensure that the immediate dollar crisis willbe overcome.Attitude of the United States and Canada to the Talks2. We start by setting out the views of United States and Canadian ministers as we believe, on the best advice we can get, United Kingdom ministers will find them when they get to Washington. These are set out in the following paragraphs.8.&quot; Briefly summarised, the views of United States and Canadian ministers will, we believe, be as follows : (a) That the United Kingdom since the war has been faced with recurrentcrises, and cular now appears to be needing more rather thanless dollar assistance;(b) that, despite the recovery which the United Kingdom undoubtedly hasmade, we have made little progress during the whole post-war periodtowards the state of international economic relations which we have,equally with them, repeatedly asserted as desirable and pledged our-selves to try to reach;(c) that, despite our repeated assurances, our actions, particularly throughbilateral agreements, are building a structure of world trade whichis further and further from that which we say we want, and thusthat we are deceiving either them or ourselves;(d) that we are trying to insulate ourselves in a high-cost world, and thatsome of the causes of this situation lie in our internal economy; andthat our failure to deal effectively with our internal inflationaryforces and high costs has driven us increasingly to bilateral practiceswith all the evil effects that that has in their eyes;(e) that in particular we have taken no effective action to deal with theproblem of the sterling balances, despite the quite clear undertaking which we gave on this matter in the Anglo-United States financial agreement^ 1945 (Cmd. 6708), and that we are, in effect, usingMarshall Aid to repay the sterling balances, and also using sterling balances in order to promote British trade at the expense of the trade of the United States;(/) that on the basis of present United Kingdom policies they cannot, there-fore, have1 confidence in the basic United Kingdom capacity to recover from its present troubles and to continue subsequently in a healthyeconomic situation;(g) that no purpose will be served by making any proposals designed tocontribute towards our joint long-term objectives, or by having anyserious discussion of major issues unless their doubts can be removed and their confidence in the United Kingdom as a healthy and stableeconomy can be restored.
4. These arguments can be refuted, in general and in detail. The necessary material will be available to Ministers on these points, and to save time we donot set forth all the arguments here. We should admit, of course, that thereis a clear obligation upon us to attain viability and freedom from dollar aidat the earliest possible moment; that our campaign for greater productivity and efficiency must be relentlessly pushed forward; that inflationary pressures stillexist in the United Kingdom and have to be countered; and that we have so farfailed in the effort to steer an adequate proportion of our exports to north america. We should, however, repudiate the fallacious idea that the sterlingdollar problem is entirely a matter of United Kingdom effort or United Kingdompolicies. This is patently false, since something like half the deterioration in sterling area dollar earnings this year relates to goods originating from outsidethe United Kingdom.Ministers will also no doubt wish to deal with any confused idea put forward by the other side on such matters as that British Government social expenditure is a major element in United Kingdom direct costs of production. ministers will wish to point out; if necessary, that money raised in private taxation and paid out in certain services such as food subsidies and family allowances tendsnot to raise costs and export prices, but to lower them.5. The United States and Canadian outlook on these matters cannot,however, be properly understood without reference to the discussions which tookplace during the latter stages of the war and immediately after the war toestablish a general code of economic behaviour. This code and the general rules of international financial and economic conduct were worked out in Anglo-American talks during the war. They were discussed in International Conferencesbetween 1944 and 1946, and culminated in agreement on the International trade organisation (I.T.O.) Charter, which is at present before Governments for theirratification. During these discussions it was. recognised that we should be facedwith transitional difficulties. There is no doubt that the United States and canada consider that, since our figures of production and exports show that wehave recovered from the damage caused by the war, we ought to be making greaterprogress towards the agreed objectives. On this we shall probably have to makeit clear that convertibility and greater multilateral trade must be the resultsof equilibrium in the balance of payments, and not steps towards it. If attemptsare made to introduce them first, equilibrium will be itself retarded, and theattempted convertibility and multilateralism will collapse, as 1947 plainly showed.We must defend the successful bilateral agreements made since 1947 as vital, tothe rebuilding of our economy after the misguided attempt at premature converti-bility in 1947, and as having certainly increased rather than diminished the totalworld trade. It should be made clear that these agreements are flexible and various, and do not by any means always or usually imply an exact two-waybalancing of visible trade. Our recent proposals for freeing intra-European trade,for example, show that we are ready to move away from bilateralism in certain conditions. The main condition is that we can see our way to meet any newobligations in goods (which we can supply), and that we are not called upon tomeet them in gold or dollars (which we cannot spare). If we are forced into thelatter course, this can only delay progress towards equilibrium, which is the foundation of any progress towards convertibility and multilateralism. Finally,we should perhaps again point out that we maintain in the sterling area thelargest multilateral system, with widespread convertibility, in the world.6. There is evidence in the press of North America of campaigns castingdoubfe on the ability of this country to extricate itself from the present difficult situation. We only mention this because the attitude of the general public inthe United States might well have an effect upon the present Administration&apos;swillingness to give a lead to public opinion, and its ability to put its policies intoeffect, more especially because of its lack of control of Congress. With publicopinion on its side, the United States Administration might be ready to try to force through the policies which it thought right, even against Congressionalopinion. Without the backing of public opinion, the Administration will hardlyventure to take a lead.7.   We would also remind Ministers of the considered advice of His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Washington, and that of the United Kingdom High Commissioner?n Ottawa, that it is very likely that the attitude of the United States Ministersm the forthcoming discussions will be to sit back and not make any suggestions37472 B 2
themselves, unless and until they are satisfied that this country is determined todo everything in its own power to extricate itself from the present difficult situation. We believe this consideration is also of great importance in regardto the degree of support we can look for from Canada. Canada&apos;s undoubted wishis to remain a full and active partner in the Commonwealth. Provided that theCanadian Government are satisfied as to our determination to do all we can tohelp ourselves, we shall find strong support from them in Washington, particu-larly in stressing the duties of creditor countries. This became quite clear in thediscussions which Mr. Norman Robertson had with the United States officialsabout drawing up the agenda.United Kingdom Attitude at the Outset of the Talks8. Putting all these considerations together, we make the following suggestions: If the United States and Canadian Governments advance the argumentssummarised in paragraph 3, these arguments will have to be rebutted. Butdiscussion on these points is not likely to lead to any constructive basis forthe talks, the time available for which is already short enough. The right line, inour view, is therefore to consider whether we cannot, by actions decided on beforethe Conference, create the conditions which would enable United kingdom ministers to discuss immediate and long-term problems with the United Statesand Canada as matters of common concern between partners.9. Such action as we ourselves decide upon should not, of course, beregarded as concessions to the United States and Canada. They should not bespoken of as such, and they are not matters for negotiation or bargaining. Theyshould be steps which we take of our own accord, in our own interest and inthe common interest.^Proposals for Action by the United Kingdom10.   The Cabinet have agreed that the following steps should be taken : (i) A review of Government expenditure has been put in hand, with a viewto securing such economies as can be obtained without prejudice to major Government policy. The Prime Minister has issued to all ministers in charge of Departments a directive (CP. (49) 170) calling upon Ministers (a) to curtail services not essential to major Government policy;\b) to effect more economical administration of policies which must beretained;(c) if the economies under (a) and (b) do not amount to five per cent.,to submit a statement showing what further action would haveto be taken to achieve a reduction of this amount. The proposals under (c) will be considered by the Economic Policy Committeein the latter half of September.(ii) The Economic Policy Committee are to consider what measures couldbe taken to counter any inflationary pressures which may develop.Ministers have, in particular, asked for a study of the reductions which might be made in the Investment Programme; and a paper on this subject will shortly be submitted by the investment programmes Committee.11. On the basis of existing policy, a public announcement at this stage would cover the ground of (i) (a) and (6) in the succeeding paragraph. As regards(ii) (the Investment Programme) a decision on what can be said should awaitconsideration by Ministers of the report of the Investment Programmes Com-mittee.   Nothing can yet be said about (i) (c).12. We doubt whether a statement on these lines would have sufficientimpact either on conditions here or on the talks in Washington, and we think thatno public announcement about Government expenditure would be worth whileunless it was made in the context of a fixed determination on the part of HisMajesty&apos;s Government to halt the automatic growth of Government expenditure.
*13. For our part, we doubt whether action on these lines would be sufficient,and we would like to recommend that His Majesty&apos;s Government should declare^as a positive decision of policy, that: (i) As a short-term measure Government expenditure is to be decreasedforthwith (vide the Prime Ministers recent circular); the more preciseand definite this can be, the better. ,(ii) As a long-term policy the growth in Government expenditure is to be stopped and its level further decreased (defence expenditure must bean exception to this). ,, ,-We recognise, however, that there would be difficulty in getting the new decision which would be required to this effect, in the time available.14. As regards monetary policy, no announcement is needed, nbr is anysubstantial action called for, but the situation would need to be carefully watched.Short-Term Measures by the United States and Canada to help the UnitedKingdom to tide over while Long-Term Issues are Settled15. Ministers should be able, at the opening of the talks, to show that wehave decided to apply the internal remedies which are within our own power.They would then be able to seek the assistance of the United States and canadian  supporting these remedies and in taking others in the external field which arenot wholly within our own power. For example, it would clearly be of thegreatest value if the United States and Canada took the steps within their powerto reduce the prices of essential dollar products sold to the non-dollar world, e.g.,by modifying restrictive measures. We should thus hope to have created a basisof mutual confidence and to be able to argue our case, not on narrow detailed issues,but in the broadest political context.16. At this stage the United States and Canada may themselves have somemeasures to suggest, e.g., we understand that the United States are looking intothe possibility of further action by way of tariff reductions. The Canadianscould act reasonably quickly in this direction under their existing powers, but although the United States will no doubt secure very shortly the renewal of the reciprocal Trade Agreements Act, this machinery is very cumbersome, and it isdoubtful whether actual reductions of the United States tariff could be effective in much less than eighteen months. The possibility of United States action inthis field is discussed in paragraph 28 below; and for the reasons there givencannot be regarded as a substitute for the much more important objective of unilateral action by the United States themselves in reducing their tariffs.17. We on our side would jpress the various short-term points which havebeen raised with Mr. Snyder and Mr. Abbott and are set out in CP. (49) 165 (alist is attached as Appendix A). It should be recognised that these measuresfall, in the case of the United States, into two classes; those which require new legislation and those which can be put into effect by administrative action. Thisis an important distinction, as some of the most important matters, such as actionon non-discrimination (Section 9 of the United States-United Kingdom financial agreement, 1945 : Cmd. 6708), require new legislative action. We cannot rely,in the conditions prevailing, on new legislative action becoming effective until themiddle of 1950. The problem of ensuring that E.R.P. dollars can be used forCanadian wheat would also involve legislative action if wheat should be declaredsurplus, This again is a matter of great importance. It will be mentioned toMr. Hoffman and has been put to the Canadian Prime Minister, whose reactionhas been helpful (see CP. (49) 172, CM. (49) 52nd Conclusions, Minute 2, andOttawa telegram No. 943 of 16th August). The remaining matters specified in cp. (49) 165 do not require any legislation. These are, as far as the UnitedStates are concerned :- More favourable administration of E.R.P.Resumption of stockpiling.Loans from Export-Import Bank.Drawings from International Monetary Fund.Reciprocal tariff reductions.* This paragraph represents the views of the officials by whom this draft brief has been prepared.It is not endorsed by the Ministers who submit the draft brief for the Cabinet&apos;s consideration.
But even in these cases it must be remembered that the latitude which theAdministration will allow itself will be tempered by Congressional views andpublic opinion.18. The same consideration, i.e., the need for new legislation, applies onlyin a minor degree to the short-term measures which Canada can take and whichare listed in CP. (49) 165; and in all cases they could take action more quicklythan the Americans.There are, however, two other matters which have both short- and long-termimplications, which were not dealt with in CP. (49) 165. These are non-discrimination and oil.Non-Discrimination19.   In the short-term this raises two problems : (a) The effect of Section 9 on the plan we have sponsored in O.E.E.C forrelaxing import restrictions.(b) The discrimination we must commit in order to obtain the imports wereally need ourselves.No new decisions of policy are required on either of these points, but ministers will be required to take decisions on the former point during September. Thesematters are dealt with in a fuller note at Appendix B.20. The issue of non-discrimination enters into the long-term in thefollowing way. Section 9 of the Financial Agreement itself ceases to be effectiveat the end of 1951. We obtained an informal assurance earlier this year fromthe Americans that if and when the Havana Charter came into force and anInternational Trade Organisation was thereby established, of which both theUnited States and the United Kingdom were members, they would regardSection 9 as automatically superseded by the modified non-discrimination rules of the Charter. Unless there is some radical change in United States opinion there is now no chance of the United States ratifying the Charter before next spring. If the Washington talks fail, the resulting situation will be such thatthe Charter is unlikely to survive, and there will be no International trade organisation and no rules about non-discrimination after 1951. It is true thatwe are parties to the Geneva General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.)which embodies modified non-discrimination rules identical with those of the charter, and that if the G.A.T.T. survives these would hold the field for us when Section 9 expires. But if there is to be no Charter it is doubtful whetherthe G.A.T.T. will survive. The G.A.T.T. or Charter rules on this subject could,however, be very onerous; they are necessarily somewhat vague and everythingdepends on how they are interpreted. We made it clear in signing the Final Actat Havana that we should not be able to accept the Charter unless the ruleswere administered very broadly. Since then we have had experience at the Annecymeeting of an attempt by the United States representatives to apply the rulesin a strict and narrow way. A further test will come when we put to the UnitedStates the arrangements we have just made with South Africa to ensure us aminimum amount of gold. If, as is probable, their reaction to the arrangements which may be regarded as a test case is very hostile, this would show thedifficulties the United Kingdom would have in accepting the Charter withoutthe assurance that the United States would support us in securing temporarycomplete suspension of the non-discrimination rules. It cannot be determined in advance whether some such indication of our thinking should be given in thecourse of the talks. It would probably be best not to attempt a detailed discussionof this complex subject, but, since in any event the question of United Statesacceptance of the Charter is by no means immediate, to suggest that the matter might be studied through such means of continuous consultation as may emerge from the talks. The balance of advantage is clearly against forcing this issueduring the forthcoming talks.Oil21. The non-discrimination provisions of the Loan Agreement strictly apply only to oil produced in the United States (but this strict interpretation mightbe questioned by the United States Government and we have never formallyraised the matter with them).  We have, however, in fact treated all imports of
oil by United States companies into the United Kingdom as if they came withinthe scope of Section 9. Any discrimination against American oil anywhere inthe sterling area would undoubtedly be held by the Americans to involve important questions of principle. So long as this position continues, we cannot cut importsof dollar oil into the United Kingdom without at the same time cutting consump-tion of &quot;sterling&quot; oil proportionately so that, to save 1 ton of dollar oil,consumption in the United Kingdom has to be reduced by 3^ tons or in the restof the sterling area by 21 tons. Moreover, the British oil companies will have,even in 1949-50, oil which is surplus to their present commitments. While non-discrimination is in force we cannot consume this oil in the sterling area withoutbuying additional dollar oil which we cannot afford; far less can we use the british companies&apos; surplus to displace dollar oil and so reduce our dollar deficit. More-over, if American and British-controlled oil companies are allowed to maintain their relative market positions in the sterling area as a whole, the dollar cost ofthe American-controlled companies&apos; share of trade within the sterling area mayon present estimates rise over the period up to 1953 to a point which wouldneutralise a large part of the expected reductions in the dollar cost of British-controlled companies&apos; operations over the same period. The oil which we supply for sterling to Western Europe at considerable dollar cost to ourselves is so vitalfor European recovery that we can take very great credit for it. We can, there-fore, make good use of this point in argument. The talks on oil in washington should not be pressed too far; we should present the problem as we see it and try to get agreement to our negotiating a solution with the American oil companies which, while securing for us the dollar savings that we must have, will damagethem as little as possible. But it will be highly desirable, as a preliminary to such discussions, that the United States Government should agree in principle that non-discrimination should not apply strictly to American oil imports into the sterling area. We must therefore press for the agreement of the United StatesGovernment to this.Value of short-term measures22. The object of these short-term measures, coupled with the action whichwe are ourselves taking, is to help us to stabilise and then reinforce our reservesquickly, and maintain them above the indispensable minimum, until longer-term measures can take effect. It is difficult to estimate the value of the various measures in terms of dollars, since the range of possibilities is large in each case;but an attempt at such an estimate will be made before Ministers go to Wash-ington. The major factor will be a restoration of confidence, the effect of whichit is impossible to quantify.Long-Term Policies23. These short-term measures, even if implemented in full and in the mostgenerous fashion, provide no permanent solution. The essential purpose of theconference will be to set the stage for the consideration of long-term policieson the basis of mutual confidence and of agreed long-term objectives.24. It will not be impossible during the few days of the Ministerial confer-ence to reach final conclusions on these long-term matters. The most we can hope for is for the problems to be set out, for the establishment of the greatest identity of views possible between the three Governments, and for agreement on thenecessity for more frequent talks at Ministerial level backed up by a continuanceof meetings at official level.25. The ultimate objective of all three countries is the attainment ofequilibrium in world trade at a high stable level. It is essential, however, thatwe should not accept obligations which may be beyond our powers to implement,and in particular that we should not be committed to any specific time-table insuch matters as convertibility or multilateralism. We must indeed emphasise that experience since the war has made it quite certain that the attainment of suchconditions will only be possible if all countries concerned strive towards them,and that it is quite beyond our powers to make much contribution in the absenceof effective action by countries such as the United States and Canada. In a word,the object of United Kingdom Ministers should be to place the long-term policiesvery definitely in the context of the responsibilities of creditor and debtor nations which were given such great emphasis during the recent discussions with the
Commonwealth Finance Ministers. (Annex to CP. (49) 160, Section I.) If wecan succeed in this, then the discussions can proceed on the right basis--namely,that of the mutual responsibilities, according to their strength and ability tocontribute, of debtor and creditor nations. It can then be shown, on a basis not of controversy but of economic fact, that a satisfactory solution of the UnitedStates surplus in world trade cannot be provided by efforts of the debtors alone;and that unless both sides make great efforts, involving radical re-examination ofexisting policies and patterns, of production, then the level of trade with the dollar area must decrease rapidly, thus postponing indefinitely any hope of convertibilityor multilateral trade.26.   There are six main long-term issues which we should seek to discuss inmore detail during the Ministerial talks.   These are :-(a) Full employment.(&amp;) Restrictive measures taken by the United States to support domestic pro-ducers and to prevent earning of dollars by other countries.(c) Foreign investment by the United States and Canada.(d) Sterling balances.(e) Commodity Agreement for Tin (and points on other commodities).(/) Dollar price of Gold.Full Employment Policy27. The first point is that of the maintenance in the United States of a high level of employment, income and demand. The United States are deeply com-mitted to a full employment policy, and the President, in his message to Congress,shows full American realisation of their commitments and responsibilities. Itwould be easy to get embroiled in discussions on the proper interpretation of full employment, on whether the Americans are prepared to tolerate a larger measureof unemployment than is desirable, or on whether our own policy leads to unduerigidity. There is room for dispute on the extent and nature of the presentrecession in America and there has been at least a temporary improvement. Itwould, therefore, be unwise to make too much of this, though we could certainlyt take the Presidents message as our text. It would seem best to treat this as a&apos; matter on which there is no basic difference of view between the Americans and ourselves and one in which they will themselves be prepared to take the necessary steps. We should argue strongly that one of the most helpful steps which theUnited States could take in the long-term and when certain present shortageshave been overcome would be to consume&apos; at home more of her own production,and thus decrease the pressure of her exports and surpluses on world markets.Full employment is the major factor in ensuring high internal consumption, andis essential to a stable and healthy position both internally and externally. Thus,unless the United States is prepared to consume or to lend abroad as much as sheproduces she will inevitably exert a deflationary pressure on the countries withwhich she trades^ We cannot hope for immediate practical advantages out of this discussion, but it should form one of the bases of long-term action.United States Restrictive Measures28. The next set of points are in the field of restrictive measures by the americans in the interest of their own domestic producers which block ways inwhich we could earn dollars. Both the level of their tariff and the methods bywhich it is administered place considerable obstacles in the way of imports. TheUnited States Government support their own agricultural prices at levels whichcould easily become much higher than those in the outside world and whichpractically prohibit imports if there is any danger of foreign competition. Itwill, of course, be realised that any action which the United States Administrationcould take in respect of tariffs under existing powers would be subject toreciprocity on our part. They might be persuaded that some easement for us would be provided in this way without very hard bargaining and with a resultwhich did not in effect mean a tooth for a tooth. It is, however, probable thatthey would regard this as another good opportunity to whittle away substantially(and for as long as the G.A.T.T. or the Charter is in force) the preferences weenjoy in other Comonwealth markets. What we really need is a measure of unilateral tariff concessions on their part. Since this would involve legislation it is necessarily a long-term rather than a short-term matter and, as is pointed
out in paragraph 16 above, action by the United States even under the ReciprocalTrade Agreements Act would not become effective in much less than eighteen months from now.29. There is also a major point as regards shipping. The United StatesGovernment argue very strongly in favour of the competitive basis of trade, yet in the field of shipping they adopt a highly discriminatory policy in order toprotect their own shipping, which is far from competitive. We think that thisis a point which should be strongly pressed on the Americans. They may arguein reply that it is essential for them to maintain a large merchant fleet on strategicgrounds. We do not think that we should ourselves raise this aspect of the matter,because of effects which it might have in other fields mainly military. But ifthe Americans raise the point, we should argue that the coming into force of the atlantic Pact reduces greatly the strength of this argument -at any rate so faras cargo vessels are concerned.Foreign Investment30. The next question is that of United States and Canadian foreign invest-ment. It is vitally important that both should encourage international investment by their nationals and through national and international institutions. For the investment to be really effective it is essential that it should be made undercircumstances which do not impose limitations on the area within which fundscan be spent. This has not presented great difficulty in the past, when investmenthas been mainly private investment, but it is probable that investment in thefuture will tend more and more to take the form of Government lending and. inthese circumstances to be &quot; tied &quot; to a much greater extent than in the past.This is a matter which will have to be pressed very strongly and it is one to whichthe countries of the Commonwealth attach great importance. The resumption ofsuch lending on a considerable scale is essential both to bring the United Statesinto balance and to develop under-developed areas. At the moment United Statesprivate lending is on a very small scale for a number of reasons, including politicaluncertainties. The only Government agencies are the Export-Import Bank andthe Economic Co-operation Administration, whose funds are limited. We mustshow ourselves fully willing to take any steps in our power to make investmentoverseas by American private lenders more attractive. When we have showed our willingness to do this, we can then press the United States and Canada (a) to reconsider such legal and technical obstacles to private lending as mayexist, e.g., through the regulations of the Securities Exchange Corn-mission in the United States and any similar requirements which mayexist in Canada;(b) to adopt a steady policy of encouragement to the banking communitiesto explore all likely possibilities of foreign investment;(c) to couple this with a policy of further education of Congress so that public agencies may be kept amply supplied with funds for lending(which is clearly recognisecf by the Governments concerned as essential)without hampering the beneficial employment of these funds throughundue restrictions and precautions. We can emphasise that a restric-tive policy, however much it may appear justified to Congress, willdefeat its own end, and that the surest way of losing money is to make an adequate investment on impossible terms.All this is a matter for mutual and continuous study by the parties concerned,but it would be wrong to think that the creditor countries may not raise important issues affecting internal policies.Sterling Balances31. This matter will certainly by raised with us by the Americans and weshall have to explain our policy in recent years, especially in the light of specificundertakings given by us in the Anglo-American Financial Agreement of 1945.Our explanations should be so made as to enlist the effective co-operation of theUnited States Government in achieving a solution of this problem. In fact, weroust be ready to take a positive line of inviting the Americans to assist us in thismatter and be ready to put forward proposals. This is a strategic and politicalquestion as well as a financial and economic one, both for the United Kingdomand the holders of sterling themselves.  In particular, holders of sterling are in
the main countries in whose political stability the Americans are concerned and Jwho occupy positions of great strategic importance.   We are examining further and will report on the positive proposals which we consider we can best make tothe Americans. -Commodity Questions32. Ministers have already decided that a Commodity Agreement is neces-sary in the case of tin. It will be necessary to persuade the Americans to with-draw their opposition to the proposal for a Tin Agreement and also to co-operate in short-term measures to deal with the present precarious situation in the interval before a Commodity Agreement can come into effect. As regards rubber, wool,cotton, sugar, cocoa and sisal, it is considered that Commodity Agreements wouldnot increase the Sterling Area&apos;s dollar earnings and would also be open to other objections at the present time. In the case of rubber, the chief source of thepresent difficulties is the regulations governing the use of synthetic rubber, andit is proposed that we should press the Americans to modify these regulations inorder to allow the maximum competition between natural and synthetic rubber.It is recommended that we should not seek any change in the Rubber Act itself,which will in any case have to be reviewed by Congress before June 1950, whenthe Act expires. These conclusions and the arguments which lead to them are set out in Appendix C.The dollar price of gold33. Since 1939 the costs of gold production, like all other costs, haveincreased but the dollar price of gold has remained unchanged. There has there-fore been a steady fall in gold production and an increase in the price of goldwould reverse that tendency. It would also have more general advantages: itwould immediately increase the dollar value of the monetary gold reserves of allcountries and thus increase their purchasing power in the United States and canada; an immediate dollar profit would accrue to the United States Govern-ment on its own large gold reserves and that profit would make it easier for itto assist other countries; and there would probably be a public expectation of higher commodity prices which would give general encouragement to business and international trade. Such advantages make it desirable to press the UnitedStates Government to increase the gold price. At the same time present indica-tions are that the United States Government are unlikely to be sympathetictowards the proposal possibly because they fear that its effects in the UnitedStates, direct and indirect, might be too inflationary. Any change would requirethe consent of Congress. As &quot;stated, we should expect great benefits from sucha step and United Kingdom Ministers should seek to raise this matter in washington if the progress of the talks affords any opportunity to do so.It should be added that it is almost certain that Dr. Havenga will press the proposal on the United States Government in South Af rica&apos;s interest.Need for Continuing Consultation34. During the war there was very close and continuous consultation andco-operation with the Americans and Canadians at all levels in the fields whichwere of mutual concern. Since then this has ceased to be the case and it is onlynow that we are beginning to build up again this close working together in themilitary and political fields. But we have not made any real progress in theeconomic field. We therefore recommend that we should seek, agreement withthe American and Canadians that there is a need for more frequent meetingsof Ministers and for continuous discussions of economic problems by an informalgroup of officials of the three countries concerned.35.   If this can be generally agreed, we consider that the constitution of the informal group of officials should be governed by the following considerations.(a) The officials should be of high rank and this work should have first callon their time.(&amp;) Their role should be advisory, with power to consider fully and franklyall subjects bearing on the economies of the three countries.(c) They should deal not only with current matters but also with trends anddevelopments in the future.(d) Their work and their reports to their Governments must, therefore, betreated in the strictest confidence.
(e) We should not add representatives of other countries as the success ofthis group will depend upon its being small. (From our point of view,this means that we must find other methods of keeping the othermembers of the Commonwealth informed and of ensuring that this method of work does, not cause difficulties with the Organisation for european Economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.).)Position of O.E.E.C.36. The Marshall Plan, and the need for its success, are very deep rooted inUnited States policy, and it would be contrary to our interest and to the interestof European recovery if we were to give the impression in any way that we did not regard the Marshall Plan as of major importance. It would be equally wrong, as this paper shows, to give the impression that we regard it as providing a solution for the difficulties which now face us. It is clear that many of the questions whichwill arise during the Washington discussions are of concern to the members ofO.E.E.C. and that they will expect to play their part in their solution. Indeed,O.E.E.C. will soon be examining long-term problems and the report which is due in October will deal with many of the issues which we shall be discussing in washington. We must play our full part in this O.E.E.C. operation. It shouldbe emphasised that under the Convention of O.E.E.C., this body is not limitedto any fixed period, and that the United Kingdom Government hassubscribed to a recent resolution of the Council of the organisation that O.E.E.C. should continue beyond the end of Marshall Aid. Thereis no doubt that there is suspicion in O.E.E.C. about the Septembertalks. This suspicion will naturally be increased if the tripartite consul-tation is continued as we suggest above. It is for this reason that themachinery must be kept as informal as possible. But provided that we do not inany way diminish the role we play in O.E.E.C. or in any way give an indication that we regard it as of lesser importance, we should take the line that this tri-partite consultation is designed to enable us to play a more effective roie inO.E.E.C. But it is essential that we should ensure that we have the full supportof the United States Administration in this.-37. We therefore recommend that, in seeking the continuation of the tri-partite discussions, we should make it clear that this will in no way diminish the role we play in O.E.E.C. and that we shall expect United States support inthe line that it will help rather than hinder our contribution to european recovery.Position of the Commonwealth38. For the reasons which are set out above we do not think that it wouldbe right to have Commonwealth participation, apart from Canada, in the con-tinuing tripartite discussions. But the extent to which we shall succeed in this objective, while retaining the full confidence of the Commonwealth, depends onkeeping the other members of the Commonwealth fully informed both of our policy and of our discussions in September and in the future, as they unfold.The Commonwealth Finance Ministers noted with satisfaction that the Septembertalks were to take place, and we must not do anything to diminish this satisfaction.We have already been asked at the official level at the Commonwealth liason committee what is the line we are proposing to take in September. We therefore seek ministerial authority to inform the Commonwealth Governments of the broad lines which we propose to take, to keep them informed of the discussionswhile these are in progress, and to use existing channels of information, includingthe Commonwealth Liaison Committee, to the fullest possible extent for thispurpose.SUMMARY OF recommendations i. Objective of Talks (paragraph 1)Our general objective should be (a) To secure that all three Governments will work together on a basis of close co-operation in order to establish equilibrium in the balance of paymentsbetween the dollar and the sterling and non-dollar areas on a permanent basis, ata high level of trade and without the recurrence of crises.37472 c 2
The specific objective of the United Kingdom Government should be (b) To secure (a) with the highest standard of living for ourselves andwithout threatening the maintenance of full employment here.The immediate objective of the United Kingdom&apos; Government should be (c) To secure that the United States and Canadian Governments take certain specific steps which, together with the steps taken by the United KingdomGovernment, will ensure that the immediate dollar crisis will be overcome.II. Proposals for Action by the United Kingdom (paragraphs 10-14)(a) Before Ministers leave for Washington a decision should be taken onthe form and timing of any announcement about reductions in government expenditure. Any announcement should be so timed as to avoid any suggestion of United States or Canadian pressure. An announcement on the basis of existing policies, which must necessarily exclude any reference to a five per cent, cut,would be not worth while unless it were made in the context of a fixed determina-tion on the part of His Majesty&apos;s Government to halt the automatic growth ofGovernment expenditure.(b) The officials responsible for the preparation of this draft brief doubt the adequacy of an announcement on the lines of (a) above and recommend thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government should declare, as a positive decision of policy that (i) as a short-term measure Government expenditure is to be decreased f orth-with (vide the Prime Ministers recent circular); the more preciseand definite this can be, the better;(ii) as a long-term policy the growth in Government expenditure is to be stopped and its level further decreased (though defence expendituremust be an exception, to this.The officials recognise, however, that there will be difficulty in getting, in the time available, the new decision which would be required for this purpose.(c) A decision on what can be said about the Investment Programme shouldawait consideration by Ministers of the report of the Investment programmes committee. *III. Short-Term Measures by the United States and Canada (paragraphs 15-21)We should press the United States and Canada on all the short-term measures in CP. (49) 165 (a list is at Appendix A and an appreciation of their effect isbeing drawn up see paragraph 22) and in addition on Non-discrimination (paragraphs 19 and 20).Oil (paragraph 21).IY. Long-Term Policies (paragraphs 23-25)(a) We should recognise that it will not be possible to reach conclusions on long-term issues in the time available. Our objective should be to open them up,get the maximum identity of view possible, and then lead on to the proposal forcontinuous discussion at official level with more frequent Ministerial meetings on the lines of recommendation (V) below (paragraphs 23 and 24).(b) We should seek to place the long-term policies in the background of the responsibilities of creditor and debtor countries (paragraph 30).(c) The six main issues are : Full Employment (paragraph 27).Restrictive measures taken by the United States (paragraphs 28-29) tosupport domestic producers and block our means of earning dollars,especiallytariffs,agricultural support prices,snipping.United States arid Canadian Foreign Investment (paragraph 30).Sterling Balances (paragraph 31).Commodity Questions (paragraph 32).Dollar Price of Gold (paragraph 33).
Y. Machinery for Continuing Consultation (paragraphs 34 and 35)We should seek agreement on the need for more frequent tripartite meetingsof Ministers, with the corollary of the need for continuous discussion of thesematters by an informal group of officials of the three countries, to be established on the basis proposed in paragraph 35.VI.-Position of O.E.E.C. (paragraphs 36 and 37)We should not seek to minimise the importance of the Marshall Plan orO.E.E.C., though we must make it clear that the Plan of itself cannot solve theproblems which face us, We should stress that we will continue to play our full part in O.E.E.C. and seek to secure United States support for the view that thesetripartite talks will enable us to play a more effective role in O.E.E.C. We should,on these grounds, resist any proposal for enlarging the tripartite talks by inclusionof O.E.E.C. countries.VII. Position of the Commonwealth (paragraph 38)Further Commonwealth participation in the new proposed special machinery would equally impair its effectiveness. It is essential, therefore, to keep the othermembers of the Commonwealth fully informed of policy and of the discussions inSeptember and in future as they unfold. We should use existing channels ofcommunication, including the Commonwealth Liaison Committee, to the maximum extent for this purpose, In particular, we ask for specific authority to give theother Commonwealth Governments, and the Commonwealth Liaison Committee,on which Canada is represented, the general outline of the policy which we pro-pose to follow in the Washington talks when it has been approved by Ministers.APPENDIX AShort-Term Measures by the United States and Canada(paragraphs 15-18)United States(a) Administration of E.R.P. in a flexible manner which will ease the strain on United Kingdom reserves: in particular E.R.P. financing of canadian wheat.(6) Resumption and intensification of stockpiling purchases.(c) Revision of United States policy on drawings from the international monetary Fund.(d) More liberal use of the resources of the International Bank.(e) More liberal administration of United States tariff.(/) Reduction of proportion of synthetic to natural rubber to statutoryminimum.(g) Loans from Export-Import Bank.Canada(a) Active encouragement by Canada of United Kingdom and sterling areaimports, particularly as regards United Kingdom capital goods.(6) Freer use of the Canadian credit.(c) Canadian stockpiling of certain strategic raw materials.(a) Co-operation in avoiding any liability on the United Kingdom to repayNewfoundland^ interest-free loan,(e) Easement of the arrangements for repayment of the 1942 interest-freeloan.(/) Co-operation in evolving a scheme designed to relieve the United Kingdomof the heavy drain of emigrant remittances to Canada.
APPENDIX BNon-discrimination in the short-term, this raises two problems.First, Section 9 of the United Kingdom-United States Financial agreement is blocking the carrying out of the plan we have sponsored in O.E.E.C. for relaxingimport restrictions by means of Open General Licences, for the import of specifiedcommodities from specified countries. We have taken the line with the Americans,as well as with the European countries, that we must be able to relax our restric-tions in favour not only of O.E.E.C. countries but of the rest of the sterling area Commonwealth as well. This we cannot do under our existing understanding with the United States, which allows us to discriminate to obtain imports wegenuinely need provided that the discrimination is concealed as far as possible,since it is here a question of open discrimination in respect of a wide range ofgoods, many of which we have no real need to import freely. We have had noresponse so far from the Americans to our approaches on this point, and we havetold the sterling area Commonwealth countries that we are considering how farwe could meet the need to go ahead with the plan in the immediate future if theUnited States remained adamant. This means in effect modifying our list ofrelaxations so as to avoid in practice seriously damaging the interests of sterling area Commonwealth countries, but still making good our proposals to do our partin a substantial relaxation scheme, with all the benefits we see in its train byway of greater efficiency and scope for competition. We should, however, only with the greatest reluctance accept a situation whereby this contribution on our part to the effective working of the European trade exchanges was made at thecost of our relations with the rest of the sterling area Commonwealth; and inthe first place, no sort of inkling should be given to the Americans that we haveeven considered the possibility of not extending the relaxation to our partners in the sterling Commonwealth.No immediate new decision on policy is required on this point, but we havefb table our list of relaxations in Paris by 1st October. If, as this date approaches,the United States authorities have still not come forward with some means of removing the Section 9 obstacle, we shall have to make up our minds whether toadopt one or other of the extreme courses of (a) dropping the scheme entirely(which would have the most serious repercussions on O.E.E.C. and E.R.P. aid),or (&amp;) going ahead with the scheme on a basis of general discrimination againstthe sterling Commonwealth (possibly omitting a number of classes of goods soas to reduce the practical damage to Commonwealth trade to very small propor-tions) or whether to adopt some middle course.Secondly, there is the discrimination we must commit in order to obtainimports we really need ourselves. As indicated above, the United States have accepted that this must be allowed on condition that we keep up a facade ofcompliance with Section 9. So far, owing to high United States prices andrelative lack of interest on the part of United States producers in the UnitedKingdom market, we have managed to keep up this facade without serious trouble;and we can still hope to be able to do so so long as the present interim stand-still on dollar imports lasts. Once, however, we carry out our re-programming,we shall in all probability be compelled to make specific cuts on dollar imports which will knock down this facade completely, or at least make obvious that itis an entire sham.This second difficulty would be eased, though not necessarily removed, bydevaluation, and this only provided that most other countries follow the leadof the sterling. Commonwealth. It is clear, however, that in the earlier stagesat Washington we must continue in any case to maintain that we are looking for a favourable reply both on our own account and to enable us to go ahead with relaxations of import restrictions by way of helping European trade.The Canadians are formally in the same position on this problem as are theUnited States, but we can be fairly confident that if the United States give way,and to the extent that they give way, the Canadians will follow suit.
APPENDIX CCommodity Agreements as a Means of Increasing the Dollar Earnings ofthe Sterling Area(Summary of the Findings of the Working Party on Raw Material Prices)Summary of conclusions. This report discusses the individual primary commodities for which, onthe face of it, commodity agreements might be useful as a means of increasing the sterling area dollar earnings, i.e., tin, rubber, wool, cotton, sugar, cOcoa and sisal.In the case of tin, Ministers decided on 22nd July (E.P.C. (49) 29th Meeting,Minute 3), that a commodity agreement was necessary. . It is proposed below thatthe Americans should be urged to abandon their opposition to a tin agreement and also to takes certain other remedial action of a more immediate character. Asregards the other commodities, the general conclusion reached is that agreements would not have the effect of increasing dollar earnings and, in most cases, wouldhave positive disadvantages from the point of view of the United Kingdom. Evenif a rubber agreement could be negotiated, a proposal for one would probablywreck our chances of securing better arrangements about the consumption ofsynthetics (on which specific proposals for discussion with the Americans are proposed). In the case of cotton and sugar, the dollar area itself is a largeproducer; commodity agreements would not increase our sales to that area andwould have other disadvantages. The price of wool will probably have to fall to ensure continued large sales to the dollar area, and there is no reason to suppose that a commodity agreement would assist this process. In the case of cocoa andsisal, it seems probable that prices and quantities can be maintained at theirpresent relatively high levels without any international arrangement.The International background. Possible commodity agreements need to be examined against the back-ground of international discussion of commodity problems and, in particular,against the general rules governing commodity agreements which are embodied in the Havana Charter for an International Trade Organisation. These rulesprescribe, among other things, that there shall be adequate international study of each commodity before an agreement is considered, that an agreement shallbe negotiated at a conference at which all countries may be represented, thatthere shall be equal representation of producers and consumers on any bodyadministering a commodity agreement, that agreements regulating prices orlimiting production shall be concluded only when a burdensome surplus of the commodity or widespread unemployment exists or is expected, and that such anagreement should provide scope for a shift from high- to low-cost producers. TheUnited Kingdom has an interest in the trade of primary commodities both as aconsumer (of food-stuffs and raw materials for manufacture) and as a producerby virtue of a common interest with the rest of the sterling area in earning dollars for primary commodities and because of our direct responsibility for the economicwelfare of the Colonies, and it is therefore in our interest to observe these general rules which are designed to hold the balance fairly between producers and consumers. &apos;Tin3. Estimates of production, consumption and stocks made at the meetingof the International Tin Study Group in June, 1949, show that there is likelyto be a growing surplus of world production over commercial consumption in thenext five years, and that the position is rapidly developing in which a commoditycontrol agreement is required. The United States, however, does not yetadmit that a burdensome surplus is in sight. The Study Group has set inhand the preparation of a statement of the case for a commodity conferencetogether with a draft agreement and will consider them towards the end of thisyear. However we cannot count On such an agreement being effective in under two years from now, even if the negotiations are successful.4?., In 1948 our dollar earnings from tin were about  15 million (29,000 tons),and about  13 million (23,000 tons) in the first half of 1949.
5. The Americans recently stopped buying, and the arrangement by whichthe Ministry of Supply takes all Malayan production resulted in their accumu-lating tin at the rate of 1,200 tons a week. The United States hasnow resumed buying, but it is clear that the commitment by the Ministry of supply to purchase the whole Malayan output cannot continue much longer.6. The United Kingdom has in effect been supporting the world price often for some time by buying up all Malayan production. In this process theMinistry of Supply has accumulated about 15,000 tons (say about  8 million atpresent prices) more tin than is considered commercially desirable. The MalayanGovernment have suggested that in order to support prices at or about theirpresent level the United Kingdom should continue to buy all surplus Malayantin, for stockpiling purposes. This cannot be recommended, for financial reasons and because the effect would be that the Dutch and Belgians would undercutUnited Kingdom resale prices and secure most of the dollar markets for them-selves. The deliberate creation of a United Kingdom strategic stockpile cannotbe entirely ruled out, but there are financial objections to and no strategicjustification for the stockpiling of any further significant quantities. Pre-liminary consideration has been given to two possible courses of action to dealwith Chinese unemployment which would follow a falling off in demand, and arenow being further discussed. These are (a) a Malayan Government scheme eitherto divert the discharged labour to public works or to provide unemploymentbenefits; (6) a form of subsidy to marginal tin producers, possibly by some alteration in the system of taxation, to keep them in production.7.   The following points should be put to the Americans : (a) It should be stressed that Malaya is in the front line of the cold warand that its stability is essential for all of us, including the UnitedStates. A stable and adequate price for tin is of the first,importance to Malaya. A drastic fall in the price would mainlyaffect the Chinese producers whose costs are higher because they workground which cannot be worked by dredgers, and might throw out ofemployment as many as 10,000 Chinese who might well find their way into the Communist forces. Moreover, it would involve a lossof revenue, since 16 per cent, of the revenues of the Federation arederived from ad valorem duties on tin and there is no other way of getting this revenue.(b) Sales of tin are of great importance to the sterling area.  The Americansthemselves cannot escape some responsibility for the present precariousposition, since until recently they have been pressing for increase in production and maintaining that their stockpile would take care ofany surplus over the next four years. Now they have announced thattheir stockpiling requirement for four years is 104,000 tons (which is considerably less than the anticipated surplus).(c) The Americans should be urged (i) to lift all their internal controls on the end use of tin immediately(they are believed to intend this and may have done so by september);(ii) to conclude the bilateral agreements for stockpiling without delay(if they have not already been concluded). Negotiations areat present suspended owing to difficulties in Congress aboutappropriations.(iii) to consider urgently the possibility of increasing stockpiling pur-chases of tin metal, under these bilateral agreementssubstantially above the figure of 104,000 tons at present contemplated.(iv) To enter into discussion with ourselves, the Dutch and the belgians, without further delay, about the date on which inter-national tin allocation is to cease, the length of warning to begiven and the methods by which tin will be dealt with there-after. ...(v) To change their attitude towards the need for a CommodityAgreement, and support any reasonable proposals which mayemerge.
(d) The Americans are suggesting that when allocation ceases, supplies often should still be denied to the Russians. The line should be takenvery strongly that if the Americans are not prepared to absorb thesurplus, ail producers must be free to sell where they like.(e) We have been and are at the present time taking action to support pricesthrough Ministry of Supply purchases (see beginning of paragraph above), (When decisions have been taken on the proposals mentioned at the end of paragraph 6 above the Americans should be told what wehave in mind.)Rubber8. Rubber is one of the most important dollar earners. Unlike almost every other commodity, natural rubber is now very nearly back to a pre-war price level(having fallen in the last year from 22-80 cents a pound to 16-50 cents as corn-pared with pre-war 15-50 cents), in spite of increased costs of production? Thishas a serious effect in Malaya which is even more dependent on rubber than tin.The Commonwealth produces 57 per cent, of world supplies (mostly in Malaya),the United States takes 45 per cent, of world supplies. Last year rubber earned$200 million; this year earnings are running at about two-thirds of that. Thereasons for this fall are (a) A drop in the price of rubber (30 per cent, of the loss).(b) A fall in United States imports (15 per cent, of the loss).(c) Relative decline in United States imports from the sterling area in com-parison with Indonesia and Siam (accounting for 55 per cent, of theloss).As regards the last cause action must be taken elsewhere than in Washington,since the Americans buy in a free market, but the United States Governmentcould take action in regard to the synthetic rubber industry which would help to counteract the first two causes.9, The origin of the synthetic industry was strategic, and it is still regardedas having strategic importance. The United States Rubber Act requires thePresident to ensure a minimum annual consumption of 225,000 tons. But lastyear the United States consumed 442,000 tons of synthetic in addition to 627,000tons of natural rubber. The Act expires next June. It is not recommended thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government should seek to influence future action as regards theAct itself, but it is proposed that they should attempt to persuade the Administra-tion to alter the regulations under the Act. The present regulations (known asOrder R. 1) make the use of specified proportions of synthetic rubber mandatoryin the manufacture of tyres and tubes, but not for any other purpose. Even inthis limited section of the industry the regulation is unnecessarily drastic, sincemandatory consumption on tyres and tubes in 1948 was more than 50,000 tonsin excess of the 225,000 tons required by the Act. In addition, there was a voluntary usage of 166,000 tons for other purposes. Logically, therefore, itwould seem that the Americans could reduce the amount required to be used intyres and tubes to the difference between the 225,000 tons specified in the Act andthe actual voluntary usage. This would widen very considerably the field fornatural rubber and thus strengthen the price. Only a moderate increase in pricecan be hoped for, since synthetic is selling for 18 - 5 cents a pOund and it is doubt-ful whether natural rubber will obtain a higher price, though we might hope thatit will obtain as much. The Americans should be urged to go as far in thisdirection as they can. Reference might be made to the view recently expressedby Mr. Shafer (a Republican who is considered the outstanding Congressionalauthority on rubber) in the House of Representatives that either Order R. 1 should immediately be suspended entirely, or that the amount required for mandatoryconsumption should be substantially reduced. Our object should be to persuade the Administration to permit the maximum competition between natural andsynthetic rubber that their legislation permits. Effective action on this might make a material difference to our dollar earnings &quot;over the next few months.10. It would also be of assistance if the Americans could maintain their purchases of natural rubber for their stockpile at a steady and high rate duringthis period, particularly if some assurance could be given that stocks would notbe reduced without consultation with the producers of natural rubber.37472 B
11. A commodity agreement for rubber as not recommended.. The chiefarguments against it are (a) The profound American dislike of rubber regulation. It must beremembered that in the case of rubber (unlike most primary com-modities) the manufacturers have the power to counter any measuresthey dislike because of the existence of an efficient and competitivesynthetic industry; this opposition would take the form of pressure in Congress to prevent the Administration from entering an agreement and to renew the Rubber Act next year in an even more restrictiveform.(&amp;) The impossibility of enforcing, except in Malaya and Ceylon, a schemerestricting production.(e) The practical difficulties, in the case of rubber, of enforcing a price controlscheme without Government buying.12. The primary object must be an increase in the area of competition between natural and synthetic rubber. An attempt to secure a commodity agree-ment (even if - otherwise desirable) would almost certainly, fail and would destroysuch chance as we have of succeeding in this primary objective.Wool13. The price of wool is still three or four times the pre-war level, andwhen, by the summer of 1950, the war-time stocks held by United Kingdom/Dominion Wool Disposals Ltd. are virtually exhausted, the tendency will be for prices to rise. On the other hand competition from synthetic textiles is encouraged by the disparity in price, and it is likely that sales of large quantities of wool tothe United States during the next few years can only be maintained by a fall in price.14. There is no reason to suppose that a commodity agreement would hastena fall in price. Moreover the conditions of surplus Which, in accordance withthe provisions of the Havana Charter, justify a price fixing agreement are not present. Finally, it is unlikely that the Commonwealth producers would favouran agreement which would include the United States; indeed they are thought tobe contemplating some form of arrangement exclusively between certain producers.Cotton15. Of the quantities of cotton which enter into international trade, theUnited States exports 40 per cent., Egypt 17 per cent., &quot; other Africa &quot; 11 percent., Brazil 11 per cent., Pakistan 7 per cent. Shortage of dollars has led toconcentration of buying from non-dollar sources, which (except injthe Colonies)has forced up the price of non-dollar American type cotton, as compared with united States cotton, and created differentials ranging up to 15 per cent. Thisis in spite of United States price support measures at about three times thepre-war level.16. Any cotton agreement which might be negotiated at the present time would almost certainly have two results which would be unfavourable to theUnited Kingdom, since non-dollar and non-sterling producers, such as Egypt,would exploit their present strong position to fix prices at a high level, while theUnited States would try to ensure for dollar cotton the largest possibleshare of markets. As a result of pressure by Egypt for a commodityagreement, the International Cotton Advisory Committee is now engaged in study-ing methods of increasing consumption and methods of balancing productionand consumption, but we hope that this study will be prolonged and not lead todefinite proposals in the near future.Sugar17. It is important that Commonwealth production be increased, both fromthe point of view of those Colonies economically dependent on sugar and also forcurrency reasons, since Canada buys a large part of her requirements from theCommonwealth, and this at present necessitates an import of sugar from hard currency sources into the United Kingdom. His Majesty&apos;s Government havealready undertaken to find a market for total exportable Commonwealthproduction until the end of 1952 and have just announced their intention to
undertake discussions this autumn about longer-term arrangements with commonwealth producers.18. For currency reasons, however, there is already an impending surplusof dollar sugar. The Cubans, in particular, who during the war increased their production to twice its pre-war size, are anxious about the future and have been pressing for a commodity agreement. Our primary objective is to preserve sufficientfreedom for Commonwealth countries to expand their production and for theUnited&apos; Kingdom and Canada to absorb it, and we should, therefore, neithertake the initiative in raising the question of an agreement, nor, if it is raised,even admit that conditions yet exist for considering an agreement.Cocoa19. West African cocoa is sold through two producers&apos; marketing boards,which, until 1948, paid prices below the world prices and accumulated reserves to cushion prices and for development work. In spite of American suspicions,these boards are not Government monopolies, although informal consultations (towhich no public reference should be made) take place between the boards, theColonial Office and the Treasury, to ensure that they do in fact adjust quantitiesand prices in a way which ensures maximum dollar earnings and reasonablestability of prices. As regards the level of prices, the excess of demand oversupply, which is expected to continue, should maintain a high price. For these reasons a commodity agreement seems unnecessary and, indeed, against our interest.Sisal20. Sisal is essentially in a similar position to cocoa, in that demand tends to exceed supply, prices are high (five times pre-war) and the growers are well organised. The chief danger to the price and volume of sales in the case of sisalis increased competition from other materials, but although this may become more serious later it is not a significant factor at the moment. The negotiation ofan agreement on sisal now would tend to decrease our dollar earnings in the shortterm without necessarily increasing them in the long term.Additional Notes21. It is possible that a proposal for a tin agreement might lead to UnitedStates proposals for agreements on cotton or sugar. We should have to pointout that the difficulties in the case of cotton and sugar are primarily currencydifficulties limiting consumption. In any case, however, we should take our standon the principle embodied in Chapter VI of the Havana Charter, that the only possible way to consider commodity agreements is singly, on the merits of eachcommodity.22. It is recommended that the subject of barter agreements should be avoided if possible. Barter agreements on raw materials would tend towards anet loss of dollars in the long run since they would tend to provide for acquisition by the United States of strategic materials such as rubber and tin, without dollarpayment; in return for purchases by us of cotton and maize for dollars. while these purchases would accelerate the rate at which the stockpile was accumulated,they would not ultimately increase its size. On the other hand we should beexpected to take raw materials such as cotton and maize in excess of our minimum requirements.23. A proposal was recently put forward by the United Kingdom Delega-tion to the Interim Commission of the I.T.O. in Annecy for the provisional appli-cation of the commodity chapter of the Havana Charter in advance of the Charteras a whole. The proposal was rejected, principally because the United Statesfeared the effect on Congress. It has been suggested in the press and elsewherethat this proposal was due to a desire on the part of the United Kingdom forcertain particular commodity agreements. This was not so, and, if the point is raised, we should emphasise that our object was to have machinery ready in casethe need arose (and to secure that commodity agreements were dealt with by theI.T.O. or its forerunner, and not the Food and Agriculture Organisation).




</content>
</cab>
