<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/36/0 images: 488-493</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT-    233Printed for the Cabinet.  August 1949SECRET Copy No.CP. (49) 18123rd August, 1949CABINETINDIAConsequential Legislation to Deal with the Position which will arise when India becomes a republic memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal and the Lord chancellor the Government of India have informed us that the new indian constitution, under which India will become a Republic, will have effect from26th January, 1950. On that date India, though remaining a member of theCommonwealth, will cease to owe allegiance to the Crown or to be part of HisMajesty&apos;s dominions.2. The Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers in April recorded inan unpublished Minute agreement that all the countries of the commonwealth should regard themselves as not foreign in relation one to another, and that each should maintain the right to accord to the citizens and trade of the otherspreferential treatment, though each remained free to determine the method and extent of the preferential treatment to be accorded.3. Officials of the Departments directly concerned have considered whatadjustments are required in the law of this country to enable us to accord thispreferential treatment to India after she has become a Republic, for so long as&apos;she remains a member of the Commonwealth. They have concluded that legis-lation should be passed, before 26th January, 1950, for the following purposes : (i) To make general provision that the existing law of the United Kingdomand the Colonies shall, unless and until it is altered by the competent authority, continue to apply to India and Indian citizens in the same way as it would have done if India had not ceased to be part of HisMajesty&apos;s dominions.(ii) To take power to make by Order in Council detailed amendment of statutory provisions which need adaptation to meet the new circum-stances. (An example of this is the Fugitive Offenders Act, which atpresent operates only between different parts of His Majesty&apos;sdominions. It will be necessary to discuss with the Indian Govern-ment how far existing practice under this Act needs to be modified in the new circumstances.)(iii) To deal with the nationality position : (a) Under the British Nationality Act, 1948, citizens of India havethe status of British subjects; but we cannot claim that thiswill suffice to secure that status for them after 26th January,1950, unless we maintain as we did not maintain in relationto the Irish Republic that the Act of 1948 is not affected byan important change in India&apos;s constitutional relationship tothe Crown which was not in contemplation when that Act waspassed. Even if we could make that claim, India would notbe content that her citizens should continue after 26th January,
1950, to enjoy a special position in the United Kingdom by virtue of being classed as &quot; British subjects,&quot; i.e., as subjects of His Majesty. It will therefore be necessary to provide thatwhile Indian citizens will not be British subjects by virtueonly of their Indian citizenship, nevertheless the law in thiscountry will apply to them as if they were British subjects.(6) It will also be necessary to make appropriate provision for persons of United Kingdom descent and connection resident in India.The Indian Constitution, which will probably be finally passedby the end of October, includes an Article, already approved,which defines what persons are to be Indian citizens as from26th January, subject to any later provision which the IndianParliament may make. Under this Article persons resident in India will become Indian citizens only if they are domiciledin India and possess certain other qualifications. The effect will be to exclude the bulk of the United Kingdom community in India. At the same time the Article provides that a person who was born in India, or possesses an Indian-born parent orgrandparent, and is resident outside India, may become an indian citizen by registration. This provision will cover alarge number of Indians in the Colonies who are citizens ofthe United Kingdom and Colonies by birth. It will also covermany Indians in other Commonwealth countries who arecitizens of those countries. There is, however, a considerablenumber of persons born and resident in India wholly or pre-dominantly of United Kingdom descent and connection, whowill be able to establish Indian domicile. Some of these areat present British subjects but not United Kingdom citizens.Some of them will wish to acquire Indian citizenship but willbe reluctant to do so if they cease thereby to be British subjectsby reason of the provision proposed in (a) above. These people will wish to be clear what their position is on and after26th January, and we must be prepared to give definite answers.It may be necessary to make special provision to enable these persons, in suitable cases, to remain, if they so desire, Britishsubjects notwithstanding that they become Indian citizens.The Indian Government could hardly raise objection to this,since they have made a similar provision with regard to Indiansresident outside India.4. The Lord Chancellor has considered whether the decision that Indiashall remain a member of the Commonwealth after she has become a Republiccalls for amendment of the Statute of Westminster. He has reached the con-clusion that such amendment is neither necessary nor expedient.5. We are, however, satisfied that some consequential legislation on thelines indicated in paragraph 3 above is necessary and should be passed by26th January, 1950. We should have preferred that, if possible, this should not include provisions dealing with nationality and citizenship, for we are appre-hensive that any such provisions will give rise to difficulties in Parliament as theydid on the Ireland Bill. If Parliamentary discussion of the nationality problem could have been avoided by omitting such provisions from the Bill, we should certainly have recommended this course. But we are satisfied that, when any legislation on this subject comes to be discussed in Parliament, nationalityquestions are bound to be raised. The general issue will be raised by Lo^d Simon;and particular questions will be brought forward on behalf of those who, as noted in paragraph 3 (iii) above, are anxious to know how their personal status willbe affected. Such questions will be raised in Parliament as soon as the indian constitution, including the nationality provisions described above, comes intoforce on 26th January. If we had not taken these matters up with the indian government and framed a policy in consultation with them, we should find ourselves in the position of being unable to answer the questions addressed to us.We have concluded, therefore, that from the Parliamentary point of view theless embarrassing course is to face these difficulties now and to include in theBill provisions dealing with the nationality points noted in paragraph 3 (iii)above.
6. Before it can be decided precisely what provision is necessary to dealwith the position under paragraph 3 (iii) (b) above, we need to be clearer than we are at present about the attitude of the Government of India. We therefore propose that discussions should be opened as soon as possible with the Govern-nient of India to elucidate their intentions. We ask that our representatives should be authorised to say at the outset that, subject to the outcome of thediscussions, it is our present intention to provide in our law that Indian citizenswill cease to be British subjects but will continue to be recognised as Common-wealth citizens and to enjoy in the United Kingdom and Colonies the same rightsand obligations as are enjoyed by British subjects. We hope that, if an approach is made to the Government of India on this basis, it may win a generous responsewhich will enable us to secure agreement that persons of United Kingdom descentand connection who are qualified and desire to become Indian citizens can doso without relinquishing their status as British subjects. We should hope thatwe could also secure, in accordance with the agreed Minute of the Prime Ministers&apos;Meeting referred to in paragraph 2 above, a measure of preferential treatment in the Indian nationality law for citizens of Commonwealth countries. It mustbe recognised, however, that we shall not be able to press this latter point very far against Indian reluctance; for the recent South African citizenship legis-lation has reduced to very narrow limits the preferential treatment in the matterof acquisition of citizenship which is to be accorded in South Africa to citizens of other Commonwealth countries.Summary7.  We ask our colleagues to agree : (1) That in principle legislation of the kind outlined in paragraph 2 above is necessary and should be passed before the new Indian Constitutioncomes into operation.(2) That the Commonwealth Relations Office should be authorised to informthe Government of India of the general lines of the legislation whichwe have in view; to seek to elucidate their attitude on the nationalityquestion; and to secure their agreement that persons of UnitedKingdom descent and connection who are qualified and desire tobecome Indian citizens can do so and retain their status as Britishsubjects or United Kingdom citizens.(3) That a final decision about the content of the Bill on the nationality -question should be taken in the light of the outcome of these discussions.A.J.23rd August, 1949.




</content>
</cab>
