<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/36/0 images: 590-605</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1949THE WASHINGTON DISCUSSIONS, 7th-12th SEPTEMBER, 1949Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer. Before landing from the Mauretania the Foreign Secretary made a longstatement to the Press setting out the problem and the objectives concerning ourvisit, and this had the effect of rendering the Press most helpful during the restof our visit. On arrival in Washington we held a meeting of the seven* Ministers,together with the British and the Canadian Ambassadors, and constitutedourselves a Steering Committee. No officials were present and no notes were taken of any of the meetings. This arrangement enabled us to have not only veryconfidential, but very frank discussions. We called in to our discussions any additional persons who were required on particular topics. Mr. Douglas andMr. Harriman were, in fact, present most of the time, except when we werediscussing exchange rate problems, and Mr. Willard Thorpe and Mr. Martin agood part of the time.2. At the first meeting (7th September) I made a prepared statement as tothe foreign exchange rates of sterling, a copy of which is attached as Appendix A.This was very well received by both the United States and Canadian representa-tives and undoubtedly had the effect of creating a good atmosphere. We thenproceeded to discuss an agenda and decided to set up a number of working groups to deal chiefly with shorter-term problems, leaving the more difficult and important matters to be discussed by Ministers. The matters dealt with by the working parties were (1) Commodities and stockpiling.(2) Economic Co-operation Administration (E.C.A.) eligibility.(3) Overseas investment.(4) Customs procedures.These working groups all reported on the Saturday morning (10th September)and the substance of their reports was included in the Joint Communique. Copiesof these reports will be circulated to the Departments primarily concerned.3. On the Wednesday afternoon (7th September) a plenary session was heldat which a large number of officials were present from all the countries, makingabout 50 in all, at which introductory statements of welcome were made by theUnited States Ministers and responded to by myself and the Foreign secretary and the Canadians. The first real discussions started on Thursday morning(8th September) and lasted throughout the afternoon and Friday afternoon(9th September), and were resumed on Saturday morning (10th September), andthe Joint Communique was finalised on Monday (12th September). The ten mainsubject matters discussed are set out in paragraph 7 of the Communique, which* Mr. Acheson, Mr. Snyder, Mr. Hoffman, Mr. Lester Pearson, Mr. Abbott, Mr. Bevinand myself.37596 bThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of .....%^.f......^i^.V?r-ft*!i!&apos;.....l&amp;ASra&amp;r...............TOP SECRET Copy No.     28CP. (4,9) 19120th September, 1949CABINET
is attached as Appendix B. Of this, as already stated, items 1 to 4 were dealt withby working parties. I can, I think, best deal with the Ministerial discussions by reference to various paragraphs in the Communique.4. The first two paragraphs demonstrate the agreement that was arrived at as to the common objectives, and also that any solution of the problems mustentail action by all three countries. There was no question of that solution beingthe responsibility of ourselves alone.5. Paragraph 3 shows the agreement upon the problem and upon thenecessity for continuing efforts by all three countries if there was to be a solution.6. Paragraph 4, which was put in at the request of the United states secretary of State, and was not greatly welcomed by the Canadian finance minister, is an acknowledgment that the action we have taken in cutting downdollar imports is essential and is recognised as such by the three governments the reason for this insertion was that the United States Secretary of Statewished it to be made quite clear that we were going to adhere in the full to the economies which we had already put forward to the House of Commons.7. Paragraph 6, which deals with the longer-term solution, has an importantfinal sentence to the first section, and was written in the light of the knowledge that we were going to change the dollar exchange rate of sterling. It was insertedat our request and in order to make clear that no steps must be taken to counteractour efforts to enter and remain in the United States&apos; and Canadian markets. Thesecond section of the paragraph deals with the positive steps to be taken by theUnited States and Canada to assist our import of commodities into those markets and provides the argument that the Canadians and Americans will use in theirown countries for freer markets.8. The summary of the reports of the working groups is in paragraphs 8-10.So far as foreign investment is concerned, it will be seen from paragraph 8 thatthe Presidents Committee for Financing Foreign Trade (which is under the&apos; chairmanship of Mr. Winthrop Aldricn) is to explore the possible lines ofco-operation for external private finance from the United States. I had a talkon this matter with Mr. Aldrich after he had been asked to act, and he-will shortly be in this country with a view to discussing exactly how the investigations of his committee should proceed. We stressed the necessity for United States privateenterprise to act in an enterprising manner and not to require absolute guarantees of every kind before making investments abroad. The group on commodityarrangements and stockpiling were successful in arranging for the United states to modify the Executive Order relating to the consumption of synthetic rubber,thereby opening a wider market to natural rubber. The United States represen-tatives said that they were prepared to review their stockpiling programme and hoped to be able to expand it in tin and other materials besides rubber, but for themoment this is held up as Congress has not yet passed the appropriation for stock-piling and the Defence Ministry have not yet decided upon their programme of purchases. I mentioned this to Mr. Louis Johnston when I saw him and expressedthe hope that the Defence Ministry would not hold matters up unduly. He wasvery friendly and co-operative. The United States Ministers expressed themselves as being ready to proceed with the preparation of a tin commodity agreement,though they did not wish this expressly mentioned in the Communique&apos;.9. In paragraph 10 the eligibility of articles for E.C.A. aid is dealt with,and in this a very considerable improvement has been brought about. The actualextra list that was drawn up amounts to nearly 300 million dollars includingparticularly 175 million dollars for Canadian wheat. In order to assist theDepartment of Agriculture in giving their approval to E.C.A. purchasingCanadian wheat with off-shore dollars we agreed--(a) to purchase up to 10 million dollars&apos; worth of agricultural surpluses ofvarious kinds, and(b) to purchase 30 million dollars&apos; worth of United States wheat at the world price some time during the course of the next twelve months.It was on this understanding that Mr. Hoffman took the chance, against the advice of his legal advisers and against the advice of the legal advisers to the Departmentof Agriculture, of promising to include in the E.C.A. list the purchase of canadian wheat to the extent of 175 million dollars. He also secured for his policy the support of the three leaders of the Farm Lobbies, to whom I subsequentlywrote letters of gratitude for their help.
10. Paragraph 11 deals with the question of Customs Procedures. Theseare being satisfactorily dealt with by the United States Government and thoughlegislation will be required in some cases, good progress is being made in theadministrative sphere. They have promised to proceed with this as rapidly aspossible and to promote the legislation as soon as it is practicable. The. state-ment in this paragraph as to tariff rates&apos; is, of course, immensely important.Though the United States Ministers recognise that it would be desirable tohave a unilateral lowering of United States tariffs;, they stated that this wasimpossible and that if they were to make any such proposals to Congress it would undoubtedly result in the raising and not the lowering of tariffs. The best thatthey could do was to seek to get the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act passedand to operate under that. They did not despair that, if the campaign whichthey proposed to carry out publicising the necessity for the United States adopting a true creditor attitude succeeded, they might be able, possibly some time nextyear, to act unilaterally.11. Paragraph deals with the question of the liberalisation of inter-European trade, which really, of course, turns upon the non-discriminationclauses of the Anglo-American and Anglo-Canadian Financial Agreements. Theview set out in the last sentence but one of the paragraph is intended to prepare the way for pressure upon Senate and Congress Leaders to agree, without legisla-tion, to the practical abandonment of Section 9 so far as European trade isconcerned. Nothing further was stated in the Communique as it was thoughtthat, after we had changed our exchange rates, it would be much easier to convince the Senate and Congress Leaders that the abandonment of Section 9would have no effect on United States economy and could therefore quite easily be done. The last sentence of the paragraph was intended to assist the americans and Canadians in their arguments to their own people, emphasising that if thecircumstances changed so as to make discrimination unnecessary, there couldbe a review in which they could urge the abandonment of any discriminatorypractices by us.12.. Paragraph 13 deals with sterling balances. We had a full discussion ofthis and I made a statement as to the reasons for the action we had taken inreleasing sterling balances. I think I convinced both the Americans andCanadians that this matter could not be dealt with apart from the question ofcapital investment and capital development in such countries as India and pakistan. This is made clear in sub-paragraph (c) and it was agreed that thisrather complicated subject matter should be discussed fully, the countries concernedbeing called in as necessary to join in those discussions. These discussions are,I hope, proceeding now in Washington.13. Paragraph 14 deals with petroleum and shipping. So far as shipping is concerned all the American Ministers who were present were fully in agreement that the present practices as regards the shipping subsidies by the United States,which are now said to amount to $350 million annually, were quite indefensibleand most undesirable. On the other hand, they made it clear that the shippingLobby was so powerful that it would be quite idle to make any direct attack upon it. They are, however, hopeful that if their general line of propaganda asregards America behaving as a creditor country is successful, they may be ableto make some improvement upon this shipping position. For the present,however, nothing can be done.14. So far as petroleum is concerned, we had a discussion on this at whichI outlined the problems with which we were confronted and the Americans pointed to the complaints of the American companies that we were keeping them out ofcertain markets. We agreed to appoint a working party to go into the whole ofthe petroleum matter to try and clarify the issue on both sides, which should then be presented to the Ministerial group for some directive as to possible linesof solution. The matter could then be pursued by a joint official working partysitting in Washington: It may be that such a working party would be able toreport to the Minister, including the Foreign Secretary, before he returns.15.   Paragraph lS deals with the Continuing Organisation.   This is madeas innocuous as possible as there is a great fear in the United States of unlimitedproliferation of organisations of this type.   The idea is that there should be acommittee, consisting of the three United States Ministers, the two Canadian37596 b 2
Ministers, our Ambassador and any Minister who happens to be in the UnitedStates or goes there specifically for the meetings, which can meet when matters are ready for Ministerial decision, but as a normal matter the board will meet atthe official level with alternates who will be persons of first-class standing. we propose to send such a person to Washington in order to devote his whole timeto this matter under the control of the Ambassador. The latter part of the paragraph was intended to remove any fears that the other European countries might have that we had been coming to arrangements which would be antagonisticto their interests.16. Paragraph 16 was inserted in order to show that we anticipated that ifthe same spirit of co-operation could be continued in the future, we should be ableto find the way out of the sterling-dollar difficulties.17. The major gain of these meetings is not, I think, to be found in the precise and detailed matters agreed upon, though these are in themselves mattersof great value and importance, but rather in the acknowledgement by the UnitedStates and Canada (a) that the steps we have already taken were necessary, e.g., the cuts indollar imports;(b) that the dollar-sterling problem was their problem as well as ours;(c) that they must henceforward behave as creditor nations if the problem is to be solved, that is (i) they must invest abroad;(ii) they must reduce tariffs and remove other impediments to imports;(iii) they must get rid of all devices to protect and subsidise their owntrade or services in competition;(d) that they must do their utmost to help us and all non-dollar countries to earn dollars for the sake of their own exporters.It is this new friendly and co-operative atmosphere that augurs well for thefuture.18. The reaction of our Canadian and American colleagues to our announce-ment of the change in the dollar rate of sterling was excellent, and as will be seen from Appendix A we made it clear that we wanted a promise from them not to counteract the hoped-for advantages of our action by the raising of tariffs or thereduction of the value of the dollar.19. Though they could not of course bind themselves not to take any suchaction they made it clear that it would certainly be no part of their policy orintention so to do, and the words inserted in the Communique (particularly inparagraph 6) make this clear and were put in for that purpose. Similarly, the reception of our action by the Monetary Fund and by the United States Govern-ment preclude the United States Administration substantially from taking anyretaliatory action.20. We were satisfied that we had got as much as was possible by way ofpromise not to act so as to cut down or cancel out the effectiveness of our changein the rate.21. I attach as Appendix C a telegram just received from our ambassador in Washington giving his view on the talks, and as Appendix D a telegram fromSir H. Wilson Smith.E. S. C.Treasury Chambers, London, S.W.1,20th September, 1949
APPENDIX AStatement made by the Chancellor of the Exchequer to a Meeting ofUnited States and Canadian Ministers on Wednesday, 7th September,1949What I would like to do at this first informal meeting is to give my colleagues in a very few words an account of the problem and of its magnitude as we see it and a short description of the steps that we in Great Britain intend to take to try and go as far as ever we can towards its solution.We are all familiar enough perhaps too familiar with the events of thelast ten years in the fluctuating economic relationships of the sterling and the dollar areas and the rest of the world. We have heard the criticisms, well- andill-informed, of a host of persons on both sides of the Atlantic, and we certainlydon&apos;t want to emulate them either in the multitude of their words or in theacerbity of their criticism.Indeed, I think we can best leave the dead past to bury its dead. No doubtwe have all been dealing with great economic forces engendered by the world war and by the historical development of the world economy over a much longer period which are immensely difficult to master or to bring into order and none of us would claim unlimited success or unrelieved failure. We&apos;ve all done our best with some measure of success, but we have now reached a period when itis really better to restate the problem in quite simple terms and then see what we can each and all do to contribute to its solution.We all know how the sterling area earned its dollars before the war and how greatly the position has changed in the post-war period.In the United Kingdom we have increased our visible earnings, but have lost most of the income formerly derived from dollar investments. At the sametime, as a result of the war and the political difficulties standing in the way ofa restoration of the former level of trade with Eastern Europe, the european countries are more than ever dependent on supplies from the Western Hemisphere.Thus, reduced to its simplest terms, the problem before us is to find a new wayof balancing, at the highest possible level, trade between the Western Hemisphereand the rest of the world, of which the sterling area forms so large a part. Inthe early part of this year we estimated that the United Kingdom would beable to finance imports from the dollar area in 1949-50 to the annual value ofabout $ 1,600 million. This calculation depended, of course, upon variousassumptions, especially as regards the levels of E.R.P. assistance and of dollar earnings. As you know, we found last June that a large and increasing gapwas appearing and was causing a dangerous drain on our reserves; we had tofind some way of stopping this and took the only course immediately open tous, of arranging to reduce our purchases. The reductions we have planned wouldhave the effect of reducing the total value of our import programme to somef 1,200 million. But even the figure of $1,600 million was on an austerity basis and represented the minimum volume of imports from the dollar area if we werenot seriously to retard our recovery. None the less, we were faced with the harshnecessity of making cuts of this order if we were to have any hope of arrestingthe drain on the reserves. We have faced that necessity and we shall see thatour intentions are carried out. Likewise the rest of the sterling area,&apos; since theLondon Conference in July, are taking steps to diminish their call on the centraldollar pool by amounts equivalent to 25 per cent, of their dollar imports.I now want to tell you what it is we in Great Britain have decided to do to try and make a new contribution to the solution of this world problem fora world problem it is. This is, of course, in addition to the many steps we havealready taken to stimulate our dollar earnings-steps which I do not now proposeto recapitulate.We have re-examined the whole situation as to the exchange rates of sterlingagainst the dollar in the light not only of the factual situation but what is perhaps of equal, if not greater, importance the psychological situation. Itis quite possible, in anything so arithmetically uncertain and incapable of proofas a fixed exchange rate, for world opinion generally or in specific countries totake an attitude as to its rightness or wrongness which can either give support to or undermine the stability of a currency.
So far as sterling is concerned, there are some factual indications that, inregard to particular sections of trade, sterling prices when translated into dollarsat the existing rate of exchange are too high to be competitive. This is not,in fact, so great an element in the situation as many people have suggested, andthere are a great many other important factors, such as salesmanship, whichare equally or even more influential in retarding dollar sales of sterling goods.So far as the United Kingdom is concerned, a change in the sterling-dollarrate of exchange would make little, if any, difference to the volume of dollargoods imported into the United Kingdom, though it would, of course, increasethe cost of living quite materially in terms of sterling.We have to remember, of course, that the exchange rate of sterling affects allthe rest of the sterling area and no doubt other countries too, who are liable tokeep their existing parity with sterling whatever may be done to the sterling-dollarrate of exchange.On the psychological side there is no doubt whatever that since last springa very wide expectation has grown up that sterling would be devalued and thishas militated against the stability of sterling and has caused a certain degree ofstrain upon our reserves. That strain has now diminished, we believe, as theamount of our drain of gold and dollars since 30ch June has been rather less than we then estimated. Nevertheless there is, no doubt, still withholding of purchasesas well as a considerable volume of black-market activities, especially in certainsterling raw materials, which is losing us dollars.We have as I have said reviewed all these and other considerations andwe have concluded that the best policy for us to pursue in the interest of thesolution of our common problem is to embark forthwith on a sterling devaluation.You will appreciate that this is a most highly confidential announcement thatI am making and if it were to become known outside this room it might lead tothe loss of many scores of millions of dollars of our reserves. In addition, it is highly probable that at least for a short period there would be a more or less com-plete interruption in international trade. I must therefore beg all of you not to mention this decision to anyone whatsoever at this stage.We hope to carry through the arrangement on 18th September, and I shall- fly back to make the announcement in London on that day. We must keep thematter absolutely secret till a day or two before the 18th, when we shall officiallycommunicate the fact to you, still in the greatest confidence, but also in more detail.We do not naturally ask you for your views on what we are doing. That is,of course, for us to decide, but there is one matter on which Ij would wish to give you an opportunity of commenting, if you wish to do so, at the time when we makethe official, but still very confidential, communication to you. That is the questionof the new rate. We must take the decision, but if we are to try and solve this problem together I would like you to have the opportunity to give us the benefitof your views before we finally decide. It obviously must be a sufficiently largedevaluation to satisfy people that it is final and conclusive, but it must not be so large as to increase unduly the cost of living for our people or to make othersfeel that we are getting an undue advantage of them by the device of over-devaluation.You will, I know, all realise that when one is dealing with a currency likesterling, which has a very wide international circulation both throughout the sterling area and the so-called transferable areas, it is absolutely essential that once devaluation takes place it should be regarded as final and that no countersteps should be taken to make negative the effect of the devaluation. The objectof the devaluation is two-fold. It gives greater stability to sterling and it should enable sterling countries to earn more dollars.The first objective would be wholly defeated if it were to be suggested thatwe should embark upon a further devaluation at some fairly near date-or indeed at any date after this devaluation.The central issue is one of confidence. In this respect, it is perfectly clearthat a great deal will depend upon the attitude taken by informed opinion in theUnited States and Canada. If we are to get the maximum benefit from thechange and to use this particular decision by the British Government as a constructive contribution, then it is most essential that the British Governmentshould have the full and wholehearted support of your two Governments and ofinformed opinion in your two countries. Nothing could be calculated to have amore beneficial influence on world opinion and thus in confidence in sterling.  We
should hope, therefore, that once devaluation takes place we could all join in achorus of support and of assertion that the degree is adequate and satisfactory and ought to settle once and for all the whole question of sterling devaluation.That we regard as very important indeed. &apos; &apos;Second, it would obviously be of no avail to us in earning more dollars ifany steps were taken to reduce that advantage by a devaluation of the dollar as occurred in 1933, or if steps were taken by other means to keep out sterlingimports which had won their way into the dollar markets by devaluation.Our people will be paying quite a high price for devaluation in an increased cost of living, which we do not intend to cancel out by increasing subsidies, andthey would feel greatly disappointed if they were by other means to be deprived of the benefits of devaluation in extra dollar earnings.On both these aspects the degree of devaluation is, of course, important andthat is why we should like your observations on it before we come to our finaldecision.We would also like to be assured that when we take this step we can be accorded your unqualified support and made secure against any loss in its effective-ness as a result of any of the extraneous measures that I have mentioned.There is one matter in reference to I.M.F. procedure which I think I mustmention. You will be aware that for any sizeable devaluation 72 hours or longernotice is required for consultation with T.M.F. This might be possible under some circumstances and with some currencies, but in the case of a world-widecurrency like sterling we could not risk the losses that might be incurred ifthere were premature publicity and we cannot therefore comply with this periodof notice, though it is our intention to inform M. Gutt personally and confidentiallybefore 18th September.We can see no way of getting round this difficulty and we hope you will allagree with us upon the procedure which we propose.The circumstances also make it impossible for us on this occasion to take partin discussions at Fund meetings on Exchange and Monetary policies. I am sureyou will appreciate this, and I hope that we may have your support in avoiding any such discussions by suitable adjustment of the Agenda in the Committee on procedure.It is important, I think, to make it clear that we do not regard devaluationas a miracle-working device which can put matters right by a wave of the wand.We hope and believe it will help and may be one factor in the solution of this verydifficult and stubborn problem.I am quite sure that the gravity of the problem has been very generally under-estimated. If it cannot be solved then it does mean a division of the western world into two economic groups and the very likely collapse of the economy ofEurope, which is balanced on a knife edge to-day.It is a very grave matter for anyone who has charge of the sterling area&apos;resources and currency to suggest what I am suggesting to-day, and it will have very difficult and strong political reactions in our own country, but I am so con-vinced of the greatness of the risks that we are running in a collapse of the equilibrium of our economies that I feel this is a step we in Great Britain must take.So much then for our first decision on devaluation.I now pass to another aspect of the problem which arises out of our internalfinancial position and as to which I would like to tell you of our decisions and intentions. Again, I would make it quite clear that I am not attempting to put upon you the onus of any decision. This is a matter that concerns my Governmentand we have taken the necessary decisions, but I feel that if we are to co-operate in the solution of this problem you must be the first to be informed of what we are doing in the direction which we believe necessary.You will be aware of the steps that we have taken in the last two years toavoid inflation and to bring about some measure of disinflation.In so far as devaluation encourages exports it will of course have an inflation-tionary effect. Moreover, the increase in the cost of living, though in itselfdeflationary, will reinforce the demand for higher incomes generally. Apartfrom that there are signs to-day that our disinflationary policy is no longerpowerful enough to disinflate against the pressures that are growing in the opposite direction. This has not yet become serious, but with devaluation it might become so, and we have therefore decided that we must reinforce our existingdisinflationary policies by a concerted attempt to bring down Government expendi-
ture. Steps have been put in operation to this end. We are determined to dowhatever is necessary, as we have done over the last two years, to avoid any increasein inflationary pressure.This will, we hope, reduce the pull of the home market on resources requiredfor exports and accompanied by the increased attractiveness of the dollar marketdue to devaluation it will, we believe, result in considerable increase in our dollar earnings.You would not I know wish to go into these domestic matters, but I thoughtit right that you should know the general line that we have decided to take.No one can of course evaluate the effect of these steps that we intend to take we hope that they may have a marked effect on the volume of our dollar earnings;provided as I have said that nothing eventuates which will counteract their good effect.These steps are sufficiently far reaching and serious for our people and for all those of the sterling area for you to realise, I am sure, how seriously we regard the problem and that we do not regard its solution as a question of &quot; more aiti, for britain.&quot;I am quite sure that the aid period must be regarded as drawing to a closewith the Marshall Plan and that it must be followed by some readjustments of oureconomies which can prevent recurrent crises and which can be regarded for thepresent as steps towards a permanent solution rather than temporary expedients.I don&apos;t suppose that any of us imagine we can here and now finalise theeconomic pattern of world trade for that is what we are in reality discussing for all the future. We can, I believe, agree upon the utility of certain short-term measures and of a number of steps which each of us can contribute towards themore permanent adjustment of our economies to the achievement of a dollar-sterling equilibrium.APPENDIX BJoint Communique Issued at the End of the Tripartite Discussions in washington on 12th September, 19491. Eepresentatives of the United States, the United Kingdom and Canadahave met during the past week to examine the trade and financial relationships between the sterling area and the dollar area. The pound and the dollar are thetwo principal world trading currencies. While the development of a satisfactorybalance of payments between the two areas is a matter of fundamental concern to the democratic world, it involves many problems which concern in the firstinstance the Governments which are the centers of these two currency systems.The present discussions were held to examine these problems. It was recognisedthat the task of working out conditions under which world trade can developsteadily and in increasing freedom will require a strenuous and sustained effort,not only on the part of the United States, the United Kingdom and Canada, butalso by all other countries desiring the same objectives.2. It was agreed that the common aim is to work toward an ultimate solution which will maintain employment and establish equilibrium of inter-national trade on a mutually profitable basis at high levels. These objectives and general course of action have already been set forth in the United nations charter, the Bretton Woods Agreement, and the Havana Charter for an Inter-national Trade Organisation. It was the broad purpose of the present meetingsto explore, within this general framework, various specific measures which thethree Governments might take to prevent a serious breakdown in the dollar-sterling relationships which would have led to a crippling limitation of dollar imports into the sterling area and to hasten the achievement of those objectives.3. These conversations have carried forward the consultations initiatedin London during 8th-10th July. They have resulted in a clear unstanding of the character of the difficulties to be faced and an increasing realisation thata fully satisfactory solution will necessitate continuing efforts in many directions.In the course of these conversations it has become possible to discuss with com-plete frankness specific problems and the types of measures which will have tobe taken if the three countries are to achieve their common purpose.
4. In the early stages of the discussion, attention was.given to the immediate problem confronting the United Kingdom and the rest of the sterling area as aresult of the rapid decline of gold and dollar reserves. Note was taken by thethree Governments of the emergency action which sterling area countries havedecided to take to meet this situation. These measures are not pleasant ones;they will cause difficulties and sacrifices for everyone concerned. Nevertheless,they are a temporary necessity, and are recognised as such by all three Govern-ments. \5. The Ministers were in complete agreement that no permanent solution to the problem could be found in the emergency steps contemplated. A more fundamental attempt would have to be made by all concerned to expand the dollar earnings of the sterling area and to increase the flow of investment from theNorth American Continent to the rest of the world, including the sterling area.6. This more fundamental attempt would involve both separate actions bythe three countries operating individually, and joint action by the three acting in co-operation with each other. In approaching these possibilities of individual and joint action on the sterling-dollar problem, there was common agreement that this action should be based on the assumption that extraordinary aid fromthe North American Continent would have to come to an end by the middle of1952. TJus would require that the sterling area increase its dollar earnings soas to pay its way by 1952. This would, require in the sterling area the creationof appropriate incentives to exporters to the dollar area and a vigorous attack upon costs of production to enhance the competitive position of sterling areaproducts. Maximum efforts would be made to direct exports to the dollar area and build up earnings from tourism and other services. As a part of this exportcampaign by the sterling area countries, it was recognised that an essential element was the creation of a feeling of confidence on the part of sterling areaexporters. They must feel that they will be afforded the opportunity to remainin the markets of the 1/nrte&apos;d&apos; States aTTat&quot;t!Ta1Taain^a place^hd that^elnlSumumjoT^ffi^rSes wiUbe pl^e^m^eir way iri enteringthpse&quot;markets. &quot;&quot; &quot;&quot;T   **&quot; -- *&quot;^&quot;On tKeiFpart the creditor countries undertook to facilitate, to the greatestextent feasible,, an expansion of dollar earnings by debtor, countries, includingthe sterling area. It was agreed that the United States and Canada should reduce obstacles to the entry of goods and services from debtor countries, in orderto provide as wide an opportunity as possible for those countries to earn dollarsthrough the export of goods and the provision of services, including tourism.It was recognised that such a policy would be in the interest of producers in theUnited States and Canada, for only in this way can the future level of tradeprovide adequately for those sectors of the American and Canadian economicswhich depend in considerable part upon foreign markets.7. The discussion of possible individual and joint actions, both long-runand short-run, ranged over a wide field. In addition to the question of dollar earnings of the United Kingdom and the rest of the sterling area, mentioned above,the Ministers gave special attention to the following subjects: (1) Overseas investment.(2) Commodity arrangements and stockpiling.(3) Limitations on items which may be financed under present E.C.A.procedures.(4) Customs procedures.(5) Tariff policy.(6) Liberalisation of intra-European trade and payments.(7) Sterling balances.(8) Petroleum.(9) Shipping. ^(10) Provisions for continuing consultation.8. A working group on overseas investment reviewed both recent experience and future prospects for the flow of productive investment, both private andpublic, from North America to overseas areas, especially underdeveloped countries.It was agreed that a&apos; high level of such investment could make an important contri-bution toward reducing the sterling-dollar disequilibrium and that every aspect of this problem should be explored on a continuing basis.   In order to initiate37596 c
this work, the Presidents Committee ior Financing Fgr^ign Trade;twill be askedimmediately to explore possible lines of action in cQ-operaiicnwith, correspondinggroups of British and Canadian financial and business representatives.; ^Kiledealing with all aspects of private and public investment, the -Commit^e will fjeexpected to address itself especially to the problem of incentives and of providing a suitable environment for a high level of private investment.9. A working group on commodity arrangements and stockpiling gavespecial attention to rubber and tin. The Canadian representatives stated thatthe Canadian Government was prepared to take steps to increase reserve stocksof tin and rubber in Canada. The United States representatives reported thatthe United States Government was prepared to open to natural rubber a subrstantial additional area of competition, including a modification of the Govern-ment order relating to the consumption of synthetic rubber. The United states would reyiew its stockpiling program, with particular reference to rubber and tin.10. Special attention was given by another group to the practical difficultybeing experienced by the United Kingdom in making fully effective use of itsE.C.A. aid to cover its dollar deficit. This difficulty arises out of the fact that,although the United Kingdom needs dollars to pay for goods in the UnitedStates, to make settlements with other countries, to paly for services, and for other purposes, the types of transactions which may be financed by E.C-A. dollars havebeen definitely limited. It has been agreed that, in order to Garry out the, basicpurposes of the Economic Co-operation Act, it will be necessary for the UnitedKingdom to finance with its share of E.C.A. funds a wider range of dollarexpenditures than has hitherto been eligible, both within and outside of theUnited States. After careful examination of the dollar expenditures proposedto be made or authorised by the United Kingdom, it appears that eligibilityrequirements can be broadened to the extent required within the limits set bythe Economic Co-operation Act. This would broaden the use but not increase theamount of E.C.A. funds allocated to the United Kingdom.11. In the consideration of measures which creditor countries might take to reduce barriers to trade, it was recognised that customs procedures may create* obstacles, psychological as well as actual. Technical discussions of this subjectdisclosed that the United States, through administrative action and proposed legislation, was already contemplating constructive steps in this field. Canadianrepresentatives stated that the Canadian Government would undertake a further review of the administrative operation of its Customs Act in the light of.these discussions. As to tariff rates, it was noted that high tariffs were clearly incon-sistent with the position of creditor countries. There had already been significantand substantial reductions in United States tariffs during the last fifteen years,.The policy of the United States Government was to seek further negotiation of trade agreements through which additional reductions might be made, withinthe framework of the Reciprocal Trade Ageements Act.12. There was agreement that one of the ways in which the competitive position of United Kingdom products might be improved was by a widening of thearea in which such products competed freely with those of other countries. Inthis connection as an initial step towards a more general liberalisation the UnitedKingdom delegation outlined its proposals for liberalising trade with countries with which it did not have balance of payments difficulties, and raised the questionwhether the provisions of Section 9 of the Anglo-American Financial Agreement,and Article 5 of the Anglo-Canadian Financial Agreement presented an obstacle to such a plan. It was the view of the United States and Canadian delegationsthat such liberalisation of United Kingdom import regulations should be con-sidered since the United Kingdom shortage, of dollars should not in itself force the United Kingdom to reduce its purchases from areas with which it does nothave a shortage of means of payment. It was agreed that any United kingdom import regulations as they affept United States and Canadian products would bethe subject of continuing review by representatives of the three Governmentsthrough continuing facilities for consultation.13. (a) A further subject which was discussed was the United Kingdomliability represented by the sterling balances of other countries^ A large numberof countries has been accustomed to hold either all or a part of their foreign
exchange reserves in the form of sterling. The existence and availability of suchholdings is an integral feature of the widespread multilateral use of sterlingfor the purpose of financing international trade. One of the problems of thepostwar period has been the existence of exceptionally large accumulations dfsterling which were built up, mainly during the War, as the result of payments by the United Kingdom for goods and services purchased overseas in furtherance of the common war effort. In June 1945 these balances amounted to $13-^ billion.Since then there have been considerable fluctuations both in the total and in theholdings of individual countries, though the amount outstanding at the end of1948 was approximately the same as at June 1945.(6) In principle the whole of these balances represents a charge on UnitedKingdom production of goods and services. In practice, however, a substantial proportion will continue to be held as. reserves by the countries concerned. Tothe extent that the balances are liquidated, some proportion of United kingdom production of goods and services is used to discharge this liability instead of topay for current imports of goods and services.(c) This whole problem in its various aspects, including the necessity to pro-vide capital goods for development, was discussed in a preliminary way on thebasis of prior technical examination by the experts of the three Governments. Itwas agreed that this was one of the subjects which concerned other countries andwould require further study.14. Investigation of the ways in which the sterling area could move towarda position in which it could earn its own way lead to the discussion of other special problems, including petroleum and shipping two important elements inthe sterling area balance of payments picture. The United Kingdom representa-tives set forth the facts of the very large dollar deficit which the sterling areapresently incurs because of oil transactions, and their desire to reduce this deficitto the minimum possible level. It was mutually recognised that the question of oil production and. refining, and geographical distribution raised problems of extreme complexity involving the protection of legitimate interests of the majorproducing countries and companies. The Ministers recognised that these two questions of petroleum and shipping could not be resolved in the short time available to them, and that further study would be required. In the case ofpetroleum they agreed to appoint representatives to analyse the facts and toprovide the basis for subsequent discussions.15. There has been agreement on the objective towards which policies shouldbe directed and agreement on certain immediate steps which will be taken to bringthat objective nearer. There are, however, as has been emphasised, a numberof questions requiring closer examination than this short conference has allowed.It is proposed, therefore, to continue the examinations, initiated during theconference, of questions on which it is hoped that useful understanding can bereached under the direction of the present Ministerial group. These arrangementsfor continuing consultation supplementing the usual channels of communication between Governments wTll be used to keep under review the effectiveness of actions already agreed upon and to prepare, for governmental consideration,measures which could carry further those adjustments which are considered to be necessary. In establishing these arrangements for continuing consultation,the three Governments wish to emphasise that these arrangements underlinerather than diminish their interest in the development of economic co-operationwithin the entire community of western nations. The tripartite arrangements will not in any wray encroach upon, or detract from, the area of competence of theO.E.E.C. and other existing organs of international economic collaboration.On the contrary, these arrangements for continuing consultation, by contributingmaterially to the solution of problems which to-day adversely affect the workingof the entire O.E.E.C. group and yet are not susceptible of solution within that group, will facilitate the progress of economic collaboration in the wider field.16. In summary the Ministers of the three countries concerned are satisfiedthat a real contribution to the solution of the sterling-dollar difficulties has beenmade by the conclusions recorded above. They are confident that, with sustainedefforts on all sides apd with the seizure of every opportunity by sterling area-exporters to enter into and remain in dollar markets which are open to them thereis the prospect of reaching a satisfactory equilibrium between the sterling and dollar areas by the time exceptional dollar aid comes to an end.37596 d
APPENDIX CTelegram No. 4555 from Hig Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Washington, dated19th Steptember, 19491. Wilson Smith will send you his impressions to-morrow morning. I send you mine now to give you something to go on. I was present at all meetings ofMinisters during the tripartite talks.2. The week of official talks made a good impression despite great difficultiesencountered the British could not deal with policy issues and the Americans hadinstructions to avoid all policy issues unless the British had already indicatedtheir policy. As a result discussion was purely factual, but it accomplishedgood work in familiarising all three teams with the essential facts and figures,and deepened understanding of them. Wilson Smith earned admiration of bothAmericans and Canadians for the way in which he handled a difficult situation.3. On Saturday, 3rd September, I had a long conversation with Acheson afterdinner. He told me that there was real anxiety on the American side whetherthe British wished to work towards a free world in which exchanges betweendollar and sterling areas were at a high level, or whether they wished to buildup a soft currency world centred round the sterling area and cut themselves off from North America. He said our attitude would be judged by what we could say of our resolution to go through with the cuts we had decided Upon, whether we were prepared effectively to devalue the pduhd, an operation which in ail thecircumstances seemed sensible, and whether we were prepared to stop playingwith the export drive to North America and deal with it as a matter of serious and urgent business. In the long term he indicated two other topics as of importanceto the Americans, what we were going to do in the general field of productivity,and what we were going to do to minimise the dollar drain of the sterling areaupon the central reserves. The attitude of the Americans would be sympatheticand helpful, but the extent of the help they could give would turn on what we had to say.4. In the light of these American preoccupations the Chancellor&apos;s utteranceat the first ministerial meeting made a profound impression both in content andmanner. It went right home and was responsible for the evident goodwill andhelpfulness of the attitude of both Americans and Canadians throughout the talks. In the light of the Chancellor&apos;s remarks it forthwith became possible to treat the whole problem of trade between the sterling and dollar areas withinthe group as &quot; our &quot; problem, and this attitude was manifested in all subsequentministerial meetings dealing with the particular problems listed in the com-munique as contained within the general problem. FoUr subjects were remitted to working parties of officials which reported on Saturday, 10th September; theyare the first four items of the communique. The remaining items mentioned were discussed in the ministerial meetings; none of them was taken very far, but all were admitted to be problems of concern to all three parties, and it was agreedthat their solution was essential for the general problem in all cases. It was agreedthat discussions on these problems should be carried further in the continuinggroup.5. At another ministerial meeting On 10th September the Chancellormentioned to the Americans and Canadians certain limits within which he felt the exact figure to which the pound would be devalued would fall. NeitherAmericans nor Canadians expressed opinions or a figure, but Snyder expressedthe view that the rate should be low enough to ensure that the operation was once for all, and it was significant that at the close of the conversation on this subject the Americans clearly indicated that when the operation was announced theywould give it all the support and backing they could.6. AIT three countries emphasised in private and played down in public theimportance of the continuing group. It was felt that the discussions Of the weekhad decisively put the three countries on the right read, but there was a long. distance to travel, and that therefore the work of the continuing group was essential if progress was to be maintained. The greatest importance was attachedby all to the continuous character of this work and the quality of the deputiesto Acheson, Snyder, Hume Wrong and myself, who would be engaged whole-timeupon it.
7. John Snyder made a goad sympathetic- and friendly, chairman. He wasadmirably backed up hy Dean Acheson. The Chancellor and Foreign Secretarywere a very strong and mutually complementary team for us. My impression, isthat all Ministers concerned reached a mew degree of frankness and friendliness intheir ability to discuss difficult questions with each other.8. In my view the great gains resulting from the week&apos;s tripartite talkswere (1) The creation of an entirely new spring of goodwill and confidence towards. . us on the. American and Canadian sides and a corresponding enhanceddegree of readiness to help.    The previous crisis of confidence wasresolved.   The precise value of this in dollars is incalculable but ispossibly very great.(2) A real conviction that the three countries represented at the talks have itin their power to remake the economic and trade pattern of the western world if they can agree together, and a conviction that as a result ofthe week&apos;s work such agreement will be progressively possible. It was clear that the Americans decided to regard us once more as their principal partner in world affairs, and not just as a member of theEuropean queue.(3)&quot; The creation of a continuing organisation which can take up the workand thresh out in a good atmosphere for subsequent meetings ofMinisters the longer-term problems required for the full post-waradjustment of the economic and trading world.9. I add two points. In my opinion the calibre of the man we send out aswhole-time deputy for the work of the continuing group will set the standard forthe American and Canadian appointments. It will also be used as a criterion ofthe extent to which we are prepared to press on with the job. I think it is of vitalimportance that the candidate the Chancellor has in mind should be named andappointed very soon.Secondly there were no understandings or tentative agreements reached onsubjects under discussion in the tripartite talks which could influence or prejudice the future work of the continuing group. We have the great advantage of being able to raise the problems which relate to the big one of the relationship of the sterling&apos;to the dollar area with friends under a general agreement to agree and an admission that the solution of these difficulties is a matter of common interest andconcern to which all three parties can and should contribute.10. I have not included in this review the short-term results in terms of dollars. Though limited in amount, they are of real importance in our effort to reverse the dollar drain.[Copies sent to Sir W. Strang and Treasury for Sir E. Bridges.]APPENDIX DTelegram No. 140 Remac from Sir Henry Wilson Smith in Washington,dated 19th September, 1949Your Camer 146.1. Owing to our other preoccupations, Ambassador and I have not been ableto discuss reply to your telegram. He is sending his own reply and I am sendingmine. If there is any marked discrepancy I will endeavour to send explanationin a late telegram.2. My general impressions are of course secondhand because I was not present at most important talks. Subject to that proviso I consider that generalatmosphere and approach by United States Administration was immenselybetter than we had any reason to expect.  Main reasons were (a) Truman&apos;s speech; and(6) our tactics on devaluation.On latter point we should have lost ground if we had either acted unilaterallybefore talks or failed to take decision before talks.
3. The willingness of United States Administration to co-operate was mostmarked. The chief limitation in effective action was as usual Congressional andLobby Opinion. Even so I consider that on fundamental issues we made a goodbeginning. From conversation which I have had to-day with Martin I am sure that they mean business now that we have devalued.  For example-(a) Snyder is consulting Congressional leaders on Tuesday and Wednesdayin endeavour to clear our proposals on liberation of trade.(b) Administration are seeking support for stockpiling programme and action contemplated on rubber, &amp;c.(c) On overseas investment they have appointed strong interdepartmental committee under Webb of State Department. Winthrop Aldrich,Chairman of Presidents Committee on Foreign Investment, is leavingat once for Europe and will come to London.(d) The Treasury have appointed Working Group on Customs Administra-tion and want help from Canada and ourselves. State department are to consider ways and means of tackling problem of tariff rates.(e) Hoffman has been asked to assume personal responsibility for campaignon shipping protectionism.4. Big gain in all this is the common problem approach founded once more on belief that we are determined to play our part and that we can and&apos;must bedifferentiated from rest of Europe.5. Immediate cash dividends are disappointing. . On eligibility they found it necessary to drive a bargain which detracts somewhat from otherwise solidadvantages. On commodities and stockpiling they are still vague because Congressis liable to cramp their style. On Monetary Fund Snyder showed little willingness to meet us on drawings for India and Australia. I have persuaded Martin this afternoon to have another look at that problem and have undertaken that Boltonand I will discuss with him on Wednesday whole structure and function of theFund.6. If we can keep the momentum going the possibilities are better than Iever imagined but we have a long way to go and much responsibility still rests on us.



</content>
</cab>
