<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/41 images: 306-311</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT- 156Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.SECRET Copy No. 3 oW.P. (43) 441.5th October, 1943.WAR CABINET.INDIAN POLICY.Memorandum by Secretary of State for India.MY colleagues may be interested to see the following summary of a recentpress article by Mr. Rajagppalachariar which is relevant to matters which havebeen under discussion in the India Committee and which will come before theCabinet this week.L S. A.5th October, 1943.Mr. Rajagopalachariar and the &quot; Cripps Offer.&quot;Mr. Rajagopalachariar, in a contribution to the Annual Number of theAmrita Bazar Patrika, recently appealed &quot;for the organising of a Nationalacceptance of Sir Stafford Cripps&apos; scheme of April 1942 &quot; containing the british governments immediate and post-war constitutional proposals for India.Mr. Rajagopalachariar attacks &quot; the soul-killing negative attitude &quot; of the peopleof India and their leaders, and their refusal to consider any scheme &quot; to correctpast mistakes.&quot; He is of the opinion that the withdrawal of the congress ministries from eight Provinces was wrong, and deeply regrets that &quot;throughmismanagement we lost the magnificent opportunities which, in the counter-balancing of good and evil in this world, the Avar presented us. It will be a double tragedy if Ave do not save at least the years immediately following theend of the war for vital constructive effort.&quot; &quot; The sending of the Cripps mission to India,&quot; Mr, Rajagopalachariar adds. &quot; Avas an act of political insight Avhichgave the advantage to British Imperialism, while our rejection of the offerbetrayed a lamentable lack of foresight. It was a great mistake to have broken off negotiations when, for whatever reason, the British Government was in its most yielding mood. With the Avhole country deeply anxious over the problems offood and clothing, many people should now be feeling in their heart of heartsthat the poAver to deal with these problems at the Centre, and with great authority in the Provincial field, is worth taking up on any terms.&quot;Mr. Rajagopalachariar draAvs a picture of the present Indian situation, andpoints out the fallacy of regarding the Indo-British conflict as &quot;a strugglebetween arrogant Imperialism and uncompromising Nationalism.&quot; &quot; The truthis,&quot; he says, &quot; that the forces concerned are many, and the conflict many-sided.British Imperial politics always have been a mixture of national self-interest andcertain truly noble ideals, whereas Indian Nationalism is not the irresistiblelonging of a homogeneous and united people ready to sacrifice their all in theirthirst for freedom. The politically conscious section of the Muslims set up arival feeling to Nationalism, based on a religion which has the Avidest appealamong the Muslim masses. Indian industrialists are making their pile by quietand uninterrupted services at the call of a bureaucratic Government Avhileshedding copious tears for Nationalism. The poverty and illiteracy of the massesare heavy drags, even Avhile these facts may serve as convincing arguments forcondemnatory propaganda against the existing order. The States and Zemindars,and innumerable caste and sectarian jealousies, pull in favour of the status quo.In this entanglement of forces, the possession of an unbroken tradition of loyalservice is not a negligible factor.&quot;[26190]
Mr. Rajagopalachariar proceeds: &quot;Unfortunately, however, IndianNationalism has so long been in opposition that it seems incapable of realisingthat it can make honourable use of power and responsibility. Through the wiseand effective exercise of political power, Indian Nationalism can make greatheadway removing fissiparous tendencies and strengthening the economic staminaof the people. Non-violent resistance has been a powerful method of agitationand regeneration of the spirit. But as a positive means to bring about the transferof political power to representatives of people composed as we are it has provedinadequate. At the critical point where resistance should end, and persuasionand formative compromise be requisitioned so as to save and fix the moral gains,there is a gap, and all that has been achieved melts into mere history. Ours is nota condition in which anarchy could automatically crystallise into ordered self-government. This is forgotten by those who have nobly suffered. If people whohave perceived the truth in their minds can openly confess this distasteful fact,and act according to their conviction, it would bring a remarkable change in thepolitical situation. We have achieved great things through the sanction of Non-co-operation, but we must now follow other plans in order to consolidate ourachievements. It is not weakness that we realise that Britain, with its dependence on the other democracies of the world, cannot deny the fundamental right ofIndia to rule herself, and we should act on this realisation. We have reachedthe stage when we should &apos; stoop.to conquer,&apos; and should redouble our persuasivetactics. We cannot succeed by drifting from non-Co-operation with Britain to non-Co-operation with the whole world.&quot;Mr. Rajagopalachariar then discusses the details of the Cripps proposals,and. observes : &quot; The negotiations over the Cripps proposals broke down overinterim arrangements for the war period. It is not possible to improve upon theprecision and completeness of the declaration contained in the proposals, that thoobject of the plan is &apos; the creation of a new Indian union, which shall constitute a Dominion associated with the United Kingdom and other Dominions by acommon allegiance to the Crown, but equal to them in every respect, in no waysubordinate in any aspect of its domestic or external affairs.&apos; The wordingand minor particulars of the Cripps proposals might, perhaps, be improved, butthe British Government could not offer a more radical scheme than that embodied in the Cripps plans. Nor is it possible to see what further we could have askedof the British Constitutional lawyers to which they could agree.&quot;Replying to criticisms in Hindu circles of the right of non-accession concededto the Provinces and Indian States, Mr. Rajagopalachariar says : &quot;In the face of the demand made on behalf of the Muslim areas, it is difficult to see how thistreatment of the issue could have been avoided on the occasion of a plan for thefinal settlement. Ruling out coercion, as wre must, we cannot object to the Crippsplan for the initial coming together of representatives with the fullest freedomof decision. The re-demarcation of British Provinces is not ruled out if objection is taken to the present delimitations. If in the Constituent Assembly we could notpersuade one another, and decide on a united Central Government, it is surelybetter for the growth of freedom and democracy in this vast country that thosewho insist on a separate existence should be allowed to try it. Why, even if five or six Provinces, like Madras, Bombay Bihar, United Provinces, Central provinces and Orissa, decide to unite and start a Union, it would be second to none in thewhole world, and the law of political gravity would inevitably bring others intoits fold, provided the Union had patience and good-will.&quot;Discussing the Cripps proposals for the future status of India,Mr. Rajagopalachariar says : &quot; Time and circumstances have contributed to therecedence of the interim proposals into unimportance. There should, however,be no hesitation in accepting the Cripps plan for making the future constitution as being the only practical plan for the reconciliation of all the forces in play inIndia. If, even now, public opinion in the country makes it clear that this solutionoffered by Britain is acceptable, that the restoration of the existing constitution in the Provinces, where it is now suspended, would be welcome, and that it willnot mean any obstruction to the Allied war effort, but, on the contrary, a strengthening thereof, it may be possible to resume popular control in the Govern-ments of the Provinces, and effect the release of all leaders now under detentionwithout charge or trial.&quot;Proceeding, Mr. Rajagopalachariar observes: &quot; It should not be forgotten that, though Mr. Churchill may hold the whip hand to-day, he is not just aDictator. When it is clear that the Indian people are agreeable to.a reasonable, it will reduce the risk- which Britain would have to take, and which those in power paint in a deep colour for the people of Britain, and it will attract
the effective support of the better-class politicians in Britain and America. Therecent successes achieved by the Allies make such trust easier. Apart from all this, the Indian people should not hesitate to do what.is right and reasonable atthe present moment for fear that such action may not be attended by success. Itcannot be misunderstood as surrender, and it does not matter if it is so calledprovided it is really good for India. With the end of the war in sight, the indian people will save themselves many precious post-war years if they declare their whole-hearted acceptance of the Cripps plan for a Constituent Assembly on thebasis of complete self-government for India.&quot;Concluding, Mr. Rajagopalachariar says: &quot;The long range, no less thanthe immediate issues like food and clothing, demand a National stock-taking.It is certain that a new order will be forced upon the world, perhaps not so rosyas Allied propagandists may paint, but not so dark as we may imagine in ourgloom. India, too, must share in that new order. But this share will be brighterand more glorious to the extent that the best and noblest Indians take a willingshare in making the destiny of their country. In 1919, and again in 1930. were fused our co-operation in making a Constitution, and, though this refusal mighthave helped to vindicate Nationalist self-respect, it did not help in a positiveway, and left the constructive work to the reactionary elements. It would be sadif the mistake should be repeated for the third time.&quot;




</content>
</cab>
