<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/54/0 images: 24-28</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(TH LJHliS^T I&amp; THE property 0F HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT )s e cJL Ll&quot;G opyNo.CABIN E T    3  (27)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.VV.1., on FRIDAY,January 21st,  1927, at 3.0 p.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain,  K.G.-,M.p., Secretary of State forI Foreign Affairs.The Kight Hon.L.S. Amery,  M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,I Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.I Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The   Mo&amp;iv Hon.The . - r-quess of Salisbury,K.C. G.C.V.0.,C.B.,  lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir Laming-Worthington-Evans,Bt.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.W.E. Guinness, D. S. 0. , M.P..,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.The Right Hon.Viscount Cecil of Chelwood,K.C., Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster...The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.P.,Attorney-General.Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.secretary.
The Cabinet had before them a Report by theChiefs of Staff Sub-Committee of the Committee ofImperial Defence, on the Defence o^ Shameen, datedJanuary 1*, 1937 (Paper CP.-IS (27)), with a Noteby the Secretary explaining that, in view of the urgency of the question, instructions to the ActingConsul-General at Canton and to the Naval, Militaryand Civil authorities at Hong-Kong, had been tele-graphed on the authority of the Prime Minister andthe Ministers concerned.For the benefit of Ministers who had not been present at the previous meetings of the Cabinet onthis subject, the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs gave a full summary of the recent deci sionsand the circumstances in which they had been made.Sir Austen Chamberlain informed his colleagues thaton Wednesday, January 19th,.after consultation withthe Prime Minister,  the Secretary of State for Warand the Secretary of State for. the Colonies, he had sent a telegram to Tokyo (No.13)  instructing the ambassador to explain to the Japanese Governmentthe considerations of time and space which (moreespecially in the absence of knowledge as to the intentions of the Japanese Government) compel the British Government to take decisions beforematters might appear urgent to the Japanese Govern-ment, who are so much closer to the danger zone.He had pressed for a reply regarding Japaneseintentions within 48 hours, which would expire at-15 the same evening.   At the same time, in viewof information as to the hesitating attitude of theJapanese Government, the Secretary of State for war had been asked to withhold for a further period of
48 hours the issue of final orders to units in-this^country for embarkation, and of notices to Glass Areservists, and the Government of India had been invited to order the units of their mixed Brigadeto prepare to sail in seven days and had been notifiedthat a further telegram would be sent later in theweek.    There was as yet no reply from Japan, but the telegrams from Peking showed that Sir &quot;Miles Lampsonhad made an impression on the Japanese Minister thereIn support of our policy.A discussion then took place as to whether thereshould be a further delay &quot;in the issue of orders forthe movement of troops.    from the diplomatic point ofview it was realised that It would be undesirable togive the Japanese Government an excuse for not co-operating on the ground that we, by our military dispositions,were precipitating trouble, contrary to their advice.On the military side it was recognised that any further delay in sending troops might be critical.The Cabinet were informed that Lord Inchcape had placed the whole o^ the British India Fleet in india at the disposal of the Indian Government for transportpurposes:    also that the British Military Attaches in peking and Tokyo had been instructed to forward allpossible information as to the movements of theCantonese troops, and that the Japanese General staff had been asked for a military appreciation.The Cabinet were informed that if notices to the2,000 Class A. Beserv? sts were not issued the same evening they could not be called out before Monday.It was recognise:!, however, that any calling out of reservists would be regarded by the public as veryserious.    The possibility was discuss 3d of giving
After full consideration, the Cabinet agreed -(a) That if the telegram from Tokyo should show unmistakably that the Japanese .have no serious intention of co-operating with military forces in thedefence of Shanghai,, the whole of the dispositions decided on by the Cabineton January 17th (Cabinet 2 (27),Conclusion 2), should be carried out:(b) That if by 8 p.m, the same evening no reply had been received from Tokyo,the whole of the above dispositionsshould be carried out with the excep-tion of the ii^sue of final notices toClass A. Reservists, which should be suspended until a further decision was taken:(c) That if the telegram from Tokyo should show that the Japanese are prepared toco-operate,  or should be indefinite,authority should be given to  the foreign secretary and such Ministers as might be within reach of London during the nextfew days to take a decision on behalfof the Cabinet as to what modifications(if any) should be made in the previousmilitary dispositions-(d) To take note of the instructions sentto Canton on the recommendation of theCommittee of Chiefs of Staff (No .49 toPeking,  repeated to Canton):(e) To take note that the Secretary of State. for War was sending a Gas Unit to fflhinafor defensive purposes&quot;,    that he waspurchasing gas to send with the unit;but that the gas was not to be employedwithout express authority from home.NOTE. Shortly after the Meeting the at?ss-hed- telegram wasreceived from Tokyo indicating that the contingencyprovided for in Conclusion (a) had. arisen.    immediate steps were taken accordingly.*      *      *, &quot;l^i i t ehal 1 Gardens,  S &apos;&quot;.1,January 21,  1927.orders for the British troop3 to proceed, in thefirst instance,  to India,  or Singapore, or Hong-Konghut this course did not commend itself to the Cabinet.
APPENDIX.TELEGRAM PROM SIR J. TILLEY (Tokyo),  datedJanuary 21, 1927.No. 31.My telegram No.28.Japanese government are not able to give the required assistance.They maintain that proposed international forceof 4,000 can keep order- and prevent any excuse for irrup-tion by Cantonese troops into settlement.    Cantonese wouldbe afraid to make deliberate attack on international con-session.    Decision to send Japanese expeditionary force would require preliminary measures which must become known.    Knowledge would inflame Chinese and make mattersworse.    At present Japanese are not being molested.Cantonese are well aware that if really provoked Japancould send any number of troops at short notice with or without British co-operation.    He did not quite excludehowever possibility of Japanese evacuating Shanghai.I made clear that on receipt of this telegramyou would have at once to decide your policy (Gr.undec.)Japan, namely whether you must evacuate (Gr.undec.) orsend a large force on your own account, but that yo^lrdisappointment would be great, not only on this accountbut at missing an opportunity of co-operating with Japanwhere we have such close allied interests.This argument lasted nearly two hours.

</content>
</cab>
