<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/54/0 images: 288-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
RpOirr^^^iS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT) eE To Copy No.cabinet    22 (27).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.I., onFRIDAY, April 1st,  1927, at. 0 p*iruPRESENT:-....The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.F.,Prime Minister.      (In the Chair).mt Hon.iir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,l,p., Secretary of State forforeign Affairs.,ght Honei,S. Churchill, C.H.,M.P,,lancellor of the Exchequer.Right Hon.,:,S. Amery, M.Po, secretary State for Dominion Affairsd Secretary of State forie Colonies.Ight Hon.e Earl of Birkenhead,ecretary of State forght Hon.lr John Gilmour, Bt* ,D .S. Oo ,.P., Secretary of State fortotland.Sight Hon.lr Philip cunlif fe-Lister,iB.E.,M.C. ,M.P., Presidentf the Board of Trade.Sight Hon.ir Arthur Steel-Maitland,:,&quot;)M,pSf Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon..Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary  ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bt.,G.B.E.,M.Po, Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B*E.,First Commissions.&quot;   of Works,The Right Hon.-Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C,M.P.,Attorney-General.r M.PB; , Hankey, G .C.B.Secretary.
The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer (Paper CP.-Ill(37))  and a preliminary Report by the Committeeof Chiefs of Staff (Paper CP.-113 (27))(Appendix) on Admiral Sir Reginald Tyrwhitfscomments on the proposals in the previous report of the Chiefs of Staff (Paper CP.-110(.27)).    On the major question, however,  of reprisals  for the Nanking outrages, the Chiefsof Staff had reserved their opinion pending thereceipt of further information from the naval commander-in-Chief&apos;.&quot;The Chief of the Naval Staff and the Directorof Military Operations and Intelligence(representing the Chief of the Imperial   GeneralStaff, who was absent on duty) made certainstatements in amplification of the Report of theCommittee of Chiefs of Staff.    Among other points. Lord Beatty informed the Cabinet thatthe Admiralty had sent a telegram to the naval commander-in-Chief enquiring as to the valueof the Chinese arsenals at Shanghai and Hankowto the Cantonese forces.    He gave some particu-lars as regards  the position and vulnerabilityof these arsenals.    Lord Beatty also informed&apos;the Cabinet that at Nanking, where there are some guns mounted to command the river,  theNaval Commander-in-Chief might be unable to interrupt the passage of troops, but that at hankow, where the defences are negligible, andat other points on the river,  it should bepossible to interrupt troop movements. but everyday&quot;&quot;s delay increased the difficulties.General Charles explained in detail    the diffi-culties and dangers involved in the proposal
to demand the withdrawal of the Chinese froman area within 12 miles of Soocbow Creek.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs gave the Cabinet a review of the attitude ofthe Governments of Japan and the United Statesof America so far a3 could at, present be judged,and at the end of the meeting he read to theCabinet draft telegrams which he proposed tosend to Washington and Tokyo.The Cabinet agreed  (a) In regard to the forts at Wusung(dealt with in the first of therecommendations of the Committeeof&quot;Chiefs of Staff)    that theAdmiralty should send thefollowing telegram, to the o mma nd e r-i n-Chi e f: -&quot;We cannot approve thedestruction of the Wusungforts as a measxare ofreprisal for Nanking, for it would exerciae no effective coercion on theSouthern Government orforces.    But you suggestthat these forts endangeryour communications withShanghai.    If now or-  atany time this danger is serious and it is necessaryfor the protection ofShanghai to destroy theforts you are &quot;authorisedto take action for theirdestruction   without further reference home&quot;.(b) As regards the proposed with-drawal of Chinese troops froman area around Soaohow Creek:that  the Secretary of State forWar should send a telegram tothe General Officer commanding the Shanghai Defence Forceputting the objections con-tained&apos; in the Report of the Com-roittee of Chiefs&apos; of Staff:    askingwhat action he proposed to take ifthe Chinese Commander-in-Chiefrefused to comply with therequest&quot;,    and enquiring whether(since the use of internationalforces was apparently contem-plated) he expected to obtainthe assent of the OfficersCommanding the American and japanese forces.
(c) As regard3 the proposed rein-forcements to China, to approve the proposal of theSecretary of State for war to send an additional infantry brigade and more artillery from england.(d) As regards a .telegram from SirMiles hampson (Peking telegramNo. 575, dated March 50th)drawing attention to the import--ance of the Cable Stations atSharp Peak, near Foocho\7. andat Amoy, the following action should be  taken:(i)  The Admiralty shPaid draw the attention of theCommander-in-Chief to theimportance of securing the safety of Sharp Peak:(ii)  The Foreign Secretary shouldtake such action, at such time as he might deem desirable,to draw the attention of theFrench Government  to theimportance of the Amoy GableStation:(e) To approve the telegrams which theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs proposed to send to washington and Tokyo on the subjeebof the proposals of the ministers at Peking in regard to the Nankingoutrages (Appendices II &amp; ITJT ) .-s    To be circulated later,2, Whitehall Gardens,  S..W.1,April 1,  1D37.
A P P E IT D I g.13 (27). &apos;.CGLIITTEE OP IMBEiUAI. DEFENCE.CHIEFS OP STAFF SUB-COMMITTEE.THE SITUATION IN CHINA.  APRIL 1st. 1927.Draft Be port Toy the Chief 8 of Staff.We met this afternoon, Friday, April 1st, at 3 p.m.,to consider the reply by Admiral Sir Reginald Tyrwhitt(Appendix) to Admiralty telegrams No. 655, dated March30th, and BO. 658-9, dated March 31st, asking for his views on the proposals contained in our Report of March29th (CCS.-69).Vie submit the following recommendations:-(1) If the forts at Wusung are a danger to thedefence at Shanghai they should he dealt with at onoe and destroyed.     This question is quiteindependent of the Nanking ultimatum and itssanctions.(2) The proposal to include in an ultimatum thewithdrawal of all Chinese armed forces otherthan police from an area within 12 Englishmiles measured from the mouth of Soochow Creekis not recommended for adoption as we have notthe force required for the defence of so largean area.     The conditions, owing to the intensive propaganda behind the lines and thedifficulties of dealing with a large hostilepopulation, are far less favourable than theywere at the time of the Taiping rebellion, when we understand this step was taken.(3) V7e support the proposals of the Chief of theImperial General Staff in favour of sendingfurther reinforcements to China.Pending the reply by the Naval Commander-in-Chiefto telegrams sent by the Admiralty asking some furtherQuestions for purposes of elucidation, we are unable todiscuss the wider question as to how pressure is to he put upon the Cantonese If they should deoline to oomplywith an ultimatum.BEATTY.(Signed)       G. P. MILNE.H. THENCHARD.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,April 1,  1927.
APPENDIX.Copy of cypher  telegram from Commander-in-Chief, China,to Admiralty.D.    11.10 a. .m. 51st March, 1927.R.    4.31 o.m.. 31st March,  1927.Ho. 923.r a mr?ib iij *Addressed to Admiralty, repeated to British Minister,Peking.Your 655, your 658, your 659.While I agree that forcible measures must be taken ifnecessary to enforce ultimatum this is tantamount to war andI cannot concur as  to feasibility of your proposals.      Referenceto your 655 (a)  interruption of  troop movements and stoppage of chinese traffic on Yangtse amounts  to internal blockade and cannot be effected without engaging forts.      Any co-operation by other Powers iH improbable until their nationals have been evacuated from the Yangtse.     Any (? direct) interference withoperations by Southern forces against North will not be  to our advantage.      I strongly advise that if forcible action is takenit should be in the form of a definite Operation againstdefinite points.    It should bring us some concrete advantage^Its successful achievement must be quick rathe;   than protractedpr?. when completed such that it cannot.be denied or mis-eoresented to the world by propagandists..      I.suggest:(A) The seizure of V/usung forts including Shihtzulin.(B) The seizure or neutralization of Chinese naval forces.
This will entail employment of several of his&apos;.;piesty&apos;s shies.      Both these are advantageous toforeign Powers.      Ports can be destroyed before theyere evacuated.      In the case of  &quot;usung it will addgreatly to security of shipoing entering lYueungwhich ma?/ become a vital point as regards food supply.     After consultation with General Duncan werecommend ultimatum should include at Shanghai thewithdrawal of all Chinese armed forces other thanpolice from the area within a radius of twelveEnglish miles measured from the mouth of SoochowCreek and the subseouent military occupation by foreignarmed forces of such points within this area    as may bedeemed necessary to ensure the security of Shanghai.The number of Police mentioned above shall not exceed thoseempl07/ed in said area on 1st January, 1927.     Theadvantage of this is  that it would safeguard presentposition at Shanghai which other Powers particularlyJapanese and French will probably insist upon as a condrtiobefore agreeinr to any action elsewhere.      The seizingBoca Tigris and Dane Island, forts has not beensuggested on account of paragraph 2 of 7/our 659.2128/31.
A g P E B D I X      II.Code telegram to Sir E. Howard.      (Washington).Foreign Office.     April 1st., 1927.      6.25 p.m.Ho.- 154.      (3) .My immediately preceding telegram (repetition of telegram to Tokyo).Unless you think it politically inexpedient pleasemake a communication - to the United States government onthe following lines.His Majesty&apos;s Government have as yet received nointimation from the United States government of theaction which they are prepared to take in regard to theBanking incident.      They assume that the United Statesgovernment do not contemplate allowing this outrageousaffair to pass without insisting on proper apology andreparation, and that they will be ready to co-operate with the other Powers concerned in opposing and doing what they can to prevent for the future so flagrant amanifestation of the present wave of violence and disorder which prevails throughout South China, accompaniedas it has been by deliberate outrages upon and insults topeaceful and law-abiding Amerioan and other foreign;citizens.His Ifoj6Sty&apos;s Government are themselves seriouslyconsidering what measures can usefully be taken to meet this situation;,   and they will be glad to communioatemost frankly to the United. States government the resultof their deliberations in the hope that the latter willbe willing to co-operate whole-heartedly with them in defending their common interests in China against any
repetition of this outrageous attack upon them.      In the meanwhile, His Majesty&apos;s Government would be glad to learn whether at this stage the United States governmenthave any observations or suggestions to offer as tothe nature and scope of the measure which might betaken for this end..Repeated to Tokyo No. 69 for Peking.
APPENDIX      III.Code telegram to Sir Jf. Tilley.  (Tokyo).Foreign Office&apos;.   April 1st,  1927.      Q.35 p,m.No..68.    (R). . -Your telegram No.138 and Peking telegrams Nos. 577r.nd 578.Unless&quot; you think&apos; it inexpedient in which case pleasereport your reasons at once you should make a communication to the Japanese government In the following sense:His Majesty&apos;s Government fully appreciate thedifficulty in which the Japanese government are placedowing to the necessity of completing the evacuation oftheir nationals from Southern China before any sanctions areapplied for the purpose of enforcing the proposed demands in connection with the Nanking affair.If, as His Majesty1s Government trust, this Is theironly objection to the application of such sanctions,  some arrangement can doubtless be arrived at with regard to thequestion of imposing a time limit for their application.His Majesty&apos;s Government feel most strongly that theHanking incident is of so outrageous and inexcusable a nature that they cannot allow it to be passed over&apos; without taking serious steps to prevent the recurrence else wherein China of a similar incident.-&apos;      The whole of their future policy and position in China depends upon their ability assoon as possible to take such steps- as will be adequate forthis purpose.     They are therefore compelled, before actuallyPresenting their demands for reparation and apology for this incident, to consider most carefully at once what  action may
be required in order to enforce these demands or meet a refusal on the part of the Canton government to makethe reparation demanded.Recent events on the Yangtse have convinced HisMajesty&apos;s Government that what is now happening thereamounts in fact to the triumph of the communisticsystem of subversive and- anti-foreign propaganda andagitation which has developed for the last few years inChina.     This movement relies largely for strength onthe demoralisation of the mob and unruly elements inChina while disregarding those more stable and orderlysections of the population who,  though they are desirous of peace and quiet, and form, as we believe, the greatmajority are totally Incapable of making their wisheseffectively heard.Unless this wave of mob-rule is speedily checkedHis Majesty&apos;s Government fear that it will soon burst allbounds and extend so as to dominate the whole of China..Hitherto it has directed its energy mainly against british interests which have accordingly sufferedmore than those of other foreign nations.     But 1-t isquite obvious that this is only the first stage of thoseCommunist activities which so soon as they have underminedthe British position in China will turn their energiesagainst all other foreigners.     The turn of the Japanese,will most certainly follow-.      In that event it appears toHis Majesty&apos;s Government that not only will Japaneseinterests be made.to-suffer in like manner but that theconsummation of Communist alms in China will affect Japaneven more vitally than it does as owing to her geographicalProximity and greater economic dependence on that country.
In these circumstances His Majesty1s Governmentare of opinion that it is a matter of common interest for the two governments to act in the closest co-operation in devising means of stemming this most dangerous tide.     There should be no occasion for rivalryor serious competition between their respective interestsin so vast a country as China, where, on the contrary,the aims and objects of the two governments are.sosimilar.      It can therefore only be to their mutual advantage to act in the closest co-operation in meeting this seriousmenance to their mutual interests.His Majesty&apos;s Government are at present seriouslyconsidering what measures can usefully be taken forthis purpose;    the:/ will be glad to communicate mostfrankly to the Japanese government the result of theirdeliberations.     In the meanwhile we sho\ild be glad to knowwhether the Japanese government on their side are ready todiscuss this question with them with a view to concertingcommon action and if so whether they would wish at thisstage to offer any suggestions or observations on the nature and scope of the measures which might be taken.Repeated to Washington No.  153.&apos;   Repeat to Peking.\

</content>
</cab>
