<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/54/0 images: 355-374</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IIS DOC Ui-liSHT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BR IT ANN I0 MAJESTY rS GOVERNMENT )E 0 HE T. Copy No.__C A B I NET    28  (27).E V I S E.Meeting of the Cabinet to be hold at No.  10,Downing Street,  S.vV.1., on WEDNESDAY,27th April,  1927, at 11.30 a.m.*  o   o oAGENDA.1*      THE SITUATION  IN CHINA.(Reference Cabinet 27 (27) Conclusion l).Interim and Second Reports of Chiefs ofStaff Committee.(CP. 127 (27) and CP.  128 (27)    -already circulated).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.(CP. 130 (27)    -   already circulated).Third Report of Chiefs of Staff Committee.(CP. 131 (27)    -    circulated herewith).Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(CP. 133 (27)    -   already circulated).2.      PROPOSED ESTABLISHMENT OF A  CONVALESCENT HOSPITALAT WEI-HAI-WEI FOR THE SHANGHAI DEFENCE FORCE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War,(CP. 134 (27)    -    circulated herewith).3.      THE SITUATION IN EGYPT.Note by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs covering telegraphic correspondence with Lord Lloyd.(CP. 132 (27) - -   already circulated).4* SUPPLY OF INFORMATION WITH REGARD TO SOUTH IRISECOAST DEFENCES TO REPRESENTATIVES OF IRISH FREE:STATE GOVERHIIEHT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for &apos;Dominion Affairs.(CP. 135 (27)    -    to be circulated).. !
5c      PRIVATE members BILLS.For- Friday,, April 29th,  1927.1.    The Married Women (Employment) Bill.Sir Robert Newman2.    The Tithe Redemption (Charges) Bill,Major Carver (U).3.    The Protection of Dogs BilloSir Robert Gower (U).For Friday. May 6thj 1927.Is    The Prevention of unemployment..Mr. G* Hall (La.)2.    The Local Authorities (Enabling) Bill.Mr-o Co Edwards (La.)(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1.26th April, 1927o
nOCuVLfNl IS THE PROPERTY  OF HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTY !S GOVERNMENT) .CABINET    28  (27).Copy No,CONCLUSIONS       a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.I.,  on WEDNESDAY,27th April,  1927, at 11.30 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon.  Stanley Baldwin,  M.P.,Prime Minister.      (In the Chair).iii ght Hon.ir Austen Chamberlain,  K.G. ,,?,, Secretary of State forjreign Affairs.jight Hen.,3^ Churchill, C.H.,M.P.,:ancellor of the Exchequer.Right Hon.,S. amery, M.P., secretary i State for Dominion Affairsmd Secretary of State forthe Colonies.ht Hon.Earl of Birkehhead,Secretary of State forIndia.Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour,  Bt.,D.S.0.,K.P,., Secretary of Statefor Scotland,The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury, .K.G. ,G .C .V. 0. ,C .B. ,  lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,MoPo, Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.&apos;Sir Laming Worthingto n-evans bt. ,G .B.E. ,M.P., secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C.M.G.M.P., Secretary of Statefor Air.The Right Hon.-WoC. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.ight Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,LB.E, ,M.C- ,M.P., Presidentn the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.Right Hon.&apos;&apos;.E. Guinness, D...S. 0. ,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.-3 Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P., Minister of Labour*The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Beard ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,First Commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.M.P.,Attorney-General.THE F0LL0V.:ING WERE ALSO PRESENT:-siiral of the fleet general Beatty,  O.M. ,G,C.B. ,8.C.V.O. .D.S. 0. , first sea Lord.(For Item 1).^shal of the Royal Air force sir Hugh Trenchard, Bt.,G.C.B.,D.S.O.; Chief of the Air Staff.(For Item 1).General Sir G.F. Milne,G.O.B. ,G.CoM.G.,D.S*0. ,A.D.C., Chief of theImperial General Staff.(For Item 1).The Right Hon.R. McNeill,  MoFo, FinancialSecretary1- to the Treasury.(For Item 5).Sir M.P.A. Hankfey, G.C.B.*&quot;&quot;*v\^...... Secretary.
1. The Cabinet had before them trie following documents in regard to the situation in Gbina:-The Interim. Second and ThirdReports of the Committee of chiefs of Staff on the questionof Sanctions (Papers C.P*-I27 (27),CQP,-128 (27)  and C.P.-131 (27)):A Note by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs on the second report of the Chiefs of.staff committee on Sanctions (PaoerCP.-130 (27)) :A Memorandum by the Chancellor of- the Exchequer on the question of sanctions (Paper CP.-133 (27)).The Chief of the Naval Staff read a telegramhe had addressed to the Naval Commander-in-Chiefas the result of the last meeting of the Committeeof Chiefs of Staff, making enquiries as to theforce required for the re-occupation of theBritish Concession at Hankow and the maintenanceof the communications on the river (Appendix I),together with Sir Reginald Tyrwhitfs replyrecommending the re-occupation of the BritishConcession with the aid of two Battalionsembarked from the Shanghai Defence Force, - an operation which Sir Reginald Tyrwhitt reportedto be concurred in by the General Officer Command-ing and the Consul-General at Shanghai (Appendix II).Lord Beatty said that while the Cabinet wasassembling he had taken the opportunity for ashort consultation with his colleagues on theCommittee.of Chiefs of Staff,  and that they had unanimously agreed to recommend the proposals ofthe Naval Commander-in-Chief,  on the understandingthat the two  Battalions embarked from the ShanghaiDefence Force should be regarded as landing-partiesused in the same manner as Marines.    In reply to
various questions.  Lord beatty  confirmed, on his present information, the vie&quot; of the Naval Com-roander-in-Ghi &quot; f regarding the practicability of keeping open communication between Hankow and thesea.    The more important forts were at or belowNanking, to which point Cruisers could ascendeven during the season of low water.    during that period Destroyers, or at any rate Gunboats(some of which mounted 6-inch guns) would beavailable to deal with field guns.    He was notprepared to state definitely that Hankow couldbe held durina the period of low water, but,  atthe request of the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, he undertook that the subject should be examined further by the Committee of chiefs of Staff.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that he had received information from Sir Miles Lampson to the effectthat copies  o^ two of  the Minister&apos;s despatchesto the Foreign Office, as well as of his  telegrams to British Consuls, had been discovered among theSoviet archives at Peking recently seized byChang Tso-lin.    The leakage was being investigated.On the subject of sanctions he read to the cabinet a telegram he had sent on the previous day toSir Miles Lampson favouring the re-occupation ofthe Hankow Concession and its return to british administration,  and asking for his opinion on various aspacts of this proposal  (ft appendix III) .This telegram had been sent before Sir austen chamberlain had seen the Third Report of theChiefs of Staff on Sanctions or the telesxair ofthe Naval Commander-in-Chief in Appendix H.
While his telegram indicated, the trend of hisown views,  the Secretary of State felt bound toinform the Cabinet that Sir Charles Addis,  theformer Chairman of the Hong-Kong Shanghai bank and a great authority on China,, was a strongpartisan of the policy of patience hithertopursued by His Majesty&apos;s Government, and, althoughunaware that the project was seriously underconsideration, had expressed disapproval of theproposal to re-occupy the Hankow Concession.Sir Austen Chamberlain wished to reserve his ownfinal opinion until he had heard from. Sir miles lampson and had a little more information as tothe practicability of holding the Concessionduring the period of low river.    -The preciseposition In regard to the Nanking demands at thepresent moment was that the Ministers at Pekingwere considering the despatch of a further note to Eugene Chen.    It was certain that the UnitedStates would not oo-operate in sanctions,  and theattitude of Japan (where there had been a changeof Government) was uncertain.    Italy alone waswhole-heartedly in favour of strong measures.If purely British action was to be undertaken,the precise moment would depend on whether afurther communication was sent by the Powers tothe Nationalist Government.The Cabinet were reminded that the greatobjection to holding the Concession in Januaryhad been that British women and children wereliving outside the Concession and their liveswould have been in jeopardy if we had fired onthe mob.    This limitation no longer applied,  andthe Japanese had successfully resisted Chineseattacks on their Concession.-3-
Subject to a favourable reply from Sir MileLampson to the Secretary of State&apos;a telegram(Appendix III),  the Cabinet were in principle in favour of the re-occupation of the BritishConcession at Hankow,  as proposed in the telegrafrom the Naval Commander-in-Chief (Appendix II)and supported by the General Officer CommandingShanghai Defence Force, the Consul-General at shangai, and now by the Chiefs of Staff, and agreed  -(a) That,  on the receipt of a reply from Sir Miles Lampson to theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs&apos;  telegram (Appendix III),the Secretary of State,  in con-sultation with the Prime Ministerand after consideration o^ anyfurther information which theCommittee of Chiefs of Staffmight be able to furnish regard-ing the holding of the Concessionduring the period of low river,should have authority to authorisethe re-occupation of the Concessionand its return to British adminis-tration, unless, having regard toall the circumstances, the PrimeMinister thought it necessary to summon a Cabinet, for furtherconsideration of the question:(b) That the Committee of Chiefs ofStaff 3hould consid-r further thequestion of the practicability of holding the British Concession at hankow during the period of lowriver:(c) That the Admiralty should instruct the Naval Commander-in-Chief to repeat the telegrams in appendices and II to these Minutes  to theBritish Minister at Peking:(d) Not to adopt,  in present circum-stances, the proposal in the second report of the Chiefs of Staff(Paper CP.-138 (27))  in favour of greater powers being given to theNaval force-s not merely to fire onbut to counter-attack with all their power those who fir-d on shipsflying the British Flag on the Yangtse.    The question whetherthis proposal should be adopted onits merits,  not as a sanction butas a measure of security, was res ;.-rved.
iKTftA 2 o The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State.for War on the subjectproposedEstablishment of the proposed establishment of a ConvalescentIf a Convales- .cent Hospitsi Hospital at Wei-Hal-Wei for the Shanghai Defencejt Woi-Hai-Weifor the Shanghai     Force (Paper CP.-134 (27)).sfsnce Force.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said he would like to consult Sir Miles Lampsonin regard to this proposal before giving hisopinion 0The Cabinet agreed  .   That, subject to the approvalof the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, the proposal of the Secretary of State forWar to despatch a Battalion of infantry to Wei-Hai-Wei from shanghai, to return the Platoonnow there to its Battalion at tientsin, and to take this opportunity for organising aConvalescent Depot,  should be approved.
3. The Cabinet had before their a Note by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs coveringtelegraphic correspondence with Lord Lloyd inregard to the change of Government in Egypt(Paper C.P.-133 (27)) .The Cabinet took note of the correspondencein Paper CP.-132 (27)  and approved the actionof the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs in authorising Lord Lloyd to let it be known,if and when he should deem necessary,  that his majesty&apos;s Government would not permit Zagloul totake office.
4. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Dominion Affairsreporting that, at an informal meeting between representatives of the Servioe Departments and experts of the Irish Free State held as a preliminary to the resumption of the conference with the Free State Government contemplated by article 6 of the Articles of Agreement of 1931,the Free State representative had asked forinformation to enable his Government to considerthe question of taking over and maintaining theforts at the three defended ports in the IrishFree State (Paper O.P.-135 (27)),The Cabinet were reminded that questions relating to Articles 6 and 7 of the IrishArticles of Agreement of 1921 were under consid-eration by a Sub-Committee of the Committee ofImperial Defence, and that when the InterimReport of that Sub-Committee had been brought before the Committee of Imperial Defence theMinutes showed that there was no intention of withdrawing the British garrisons from defended ports in Southern Ireland (Minutes, of 220thMeeting of 0.I.bo (7)).The Cabinet agreed  That it should be made clear tothe representatives of the IrishFree State that the Cabinet wasnot prepared to discuss the handing over of the defences &amp;f the ports in Southern Ireland,      and thatconsequently there was no object in furnishing the informationasked for.
5,, The Cabinet considered the attitude to beadopted by the Government towards the MarriedWomen (Employment) Bill, to be introduced by aPrivate Member sir Robert Newman) on Friday,April 29theThe Financial Secretary to the Treasuryinformed the Cabinet that the Treasury were strongly opposed to this Bill, which,  if passed into law, would deprive the Government of theright to dismiss women Civil Servants on theirmarriage.    The Bill was one which could not be passed unless the King&apos;s Assent were signified,and,  if the Cabinet so desired,  the Bill couldbe blocked by an intimation that the Governmentwould not advise His Majesty to signify his assent.After some consideration,  the  cabinet agreed  (a) That if enquiry were to be made orthe question of the King&apos;s Assent,the Government Spokesman should intimate that His Majesty wouldbe advised to give his assent-in order that Parliament mighthave an opportunity to discussthe Bill:(b) That the Bill should be opposedon its merits, and that theGovernment -&quot;hips should be so informed.
THE TITHE 6.    The Cabinet were informed that the TitheREDEMPTION&apos;(CHARGES) Redemption ^ Charges) Bill, which was down &quot;secondBILX.on the list of Private Members&apos; Bills for Friday,April 29th, would not be introduced.
THB PROTECTION 7.    The Cabinet agreed  OF DOC-3 BILL.That the Protection of Dogs Bill,whioh was down third on the listof Private Members&apos;  Bills for april 29th. 1927, should be opposed and the GovernmentWhips should be so informed.
THE PREVENTIONOP UNEMPLOYMENT8. The Cabinet agreedBILL.&apos; previous reference :Cabinet %J(2&quot;$,  Con-elusion 11.)That the Minister of Labour&quot;sEou 1 &amp;7j&amp;ew-e- a reasoned araend-Tfieiat^to the Prevention ofUnernployjnanJL. gill 9Tto be intro-duced by a Private Member(Mr G. Hall)  on Friday, May 6th;that the Whips should be askedto ensure a Government majority;and that the Minister of labour should consult the other Depart-ments concerned in regard to theamendment.-11-
THE ARGENTINE 9. The Cabinet were informed that an importantREPUBLIC.newspaper in the Argentine Republic,  &quot;La Nacion&quot;,had decided to publish a pro-British number andhad asked that British Cabinet Ministers mightcontribute messages to be published in thisedition.    The proposal was strongly supportedby the British Minister at Buenos Ayres.The Cabinet approved the proposal in principle and invited theSecretary o^ State for ForeignAffairs and the President ofthe Board of Trade to make arrangements with a certainnumber 0** Ministers for giving effect to the proposal.2, Whitehall Gardens,  SX1,April 27,   1927.
APPENDIX      I.Copy of a telegram from the Admiralty to the Commander-in-Chief, China, Ho.  756, &quot;dated 2S&quot;th April,T9ST.EMERGENCY STATE.With reference to your repeated reoammendations to take immediate action against Hankow what have you in mindbesides bombardment of arsenal.Do you still contemplate reoocupation of Concession videyour No. 980.      If so, after consulting General OfficerCommanding report what foroe you propose to use.Having in mind however, If the situation is not completely-cleared up by October, the garrison would have to be evacuated when Cruisers are withdrawn, and that It wouldbe deplorable to evacuate a second tine, the Chief of staff Committee is definitely opposed to a military occupation with considerable garrison.Perhaps, however, occupation&quot;by Naval Hatings andMarines or troops acting as Marines and based onwarships, would not involve the same loss of face.With reference to your No. 999 and Bear-AdmiralYangtse&apos;s 1946/23 and 1946/24 arG you satisfied thatlines of communications between Hankow and the sea canbe maintained, whether Chiang-Kai-Shek remains friendlyor otherwiseD. 0. Do
41 PS I BII     IICopy of Telegram from Commander-ln-Ohief, China totho AlBiralfry   dated,&apos;26th April, 1927VEMERGENCY STATE-      10.      Your 756.      I hsve never (groupcorrupt repetition asked for) policy present or future hutI am still of the opinion which is shared &quot;by G.O.O. andConsul General Shanghai that time has come when an all british effort should he made as follows;-   Embark forceof two battalions which the GoOaC is prepared to supply.Proceed to Hankow with strong Naval force (I propose to gomyself).      Inform. Authorities at Hankow that we intend toreoccupy our Concession we hope peacefully but are fully,prepared to use force if necessary.      If any opposition Ismade we shall first destroy Hanyang Arsenal and if we are obliged to take this drastic step we cannot he responsiblefor lives of inhabitants of Hankow and that other drasticsteps will be taken at same time.      The points of thisproposal are as follows  (1) Hankow Concession willprobably be reoccupied without firing a shot   (ii) it is anall British operation and does not affect any Nationalityexcept our own (iii) it will pave the way for raoccupationof all other Concessions and if Chiang Kai Shek is stillin power it will place him in very strong position.With regard to situation next October I could nothazard reply except that I an prepared to keep open allcommunication between Hankow and tho sea but it willprobably be necessary for a cruiser to winter at Hankowand a permanent guard number to be decided later onprobably two companies.
APPENDIX      III.Qvpher telegram to Sir k. Lampson (Peking) No. 326,dated 26th April, 192V.1. It Is now clear that we cannot count on the active collaboration or support of the United Statesgovernment in prosecuting our demands for satisfaction forthe Nanking outrages.      The United States government arenot prepared to agree to or oven to discuss any form ofsanction and deoline to sond any reply to Mr. Chenrsnotos of April 14th.2. The attitude of Japan is still uncertain as aresult no doubt of the change of government and of thepreoccupation of the new government with the financialcrisis hut It seems unlikely that It will differ much fromthat of the last government.3. Chiang-Kai-shek&apos;s position is more difficult todetermine.     Ho has acted with vigour against theextromists and so has somewhat relieved the tension at shangai and Canton and even somewhat improved&apos; thesituation at Hanking.      It would appear therefore unwise to do anything to antagonise or weaken him but it is too early yet to found a policy upon his final success oreven upon his goodwill if successful.4, The various sanctions whioh have been suggested would appear to ne either impraotioable or ineffective orlikely to injure Innocent parties or the less hostilesections of Nationalist China rather than those directly or indirectly responsible for the outrages.5. There remains, howsvor, one possible course which seems to me worthy of serious consideration, namelytho rooccupation of the Hankow concession and its return
to British administration, whether exercised by themilitary or by a reinstated British Municipal Council.6. One advantage of this course is that theaction to be taken concerns British interests alone and could therefore be appropriately taken by His majesty&apos;s government acting alone.     A further advantage is that itstrikes directly at the prestige and interests of thefaction responsible for the Nanking outrages.     Further,the Japanese have already landed detachments in theirconcession and are holding it In force;    by acting now weshould be aligning ourselves with them.7. The reocoupation of the concession would not imply the abandonment of the policy outlined in myDeoember memorandum or in the treaty revision offer ofJanuary.     Eis Majestyds Government would be stillprepared to negotiate the return of the concession so soonas there appears a government able and willing to carryout its undertakings.      Those given by Mr. Chen at thetime of the signature of the Hankow agreement have,however, been flagrantly broken by the forcible occupationof the Chinkiang concession by Nationalist troops, by thefailure to give effective protection at Hankow, Kiukiangand other places and lastly by the Nanking outrages.      i feel therefore that the cancellation of tho agreement madewith Chen and the reoccupation of the concession ar6 amplyjustified if deemed expedient.8o Our appropriate advisers are being consulted onthe military aspects of the question.      I should at thesame time be glad of your views on all the political issues involved such as the possible reaction of suchreoccupation fa) upon Chang Iso-lin and the North,  fb)upon Chiang Kai-shek and the more moderate Nationalist
elements,   (o) its effect on the struggle &quot;between theModerates and tho Extremists?9. V/ould you consider it a fatal objeotion toreoccupation were it to ho necessary, for military reasons, to withdraw the garrison again at low watereven though no arrangement had been made in themeantime with any Chinese authority for the future adminis-tration of the concession, or would you advise reoccupationnotwithstanding the possibility of this contingency?Also bear in iaind that so long as the garrison is at hankow it may bo difficult to withdraw the defenco force from tho International Settlement at Shanghai.10. Sooner or later we hope to get on to termsof amity with a genuine Nationalist government orgovernments of China.     We do not want to take actionwhich, however justifiable now, might place yet anotherformidable obstacle in the way of good relations.      the precedent of JapanTs Hankow garrison 1911-22 is notencouraging.     You will remember the strong anti-Japanese feeling which it arousod.Repeat to Shanghai for commander-in-Chief.

</content>
</cab>
