<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/54/0 images: 375-383</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
qjS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HI S BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .sEC RET. Copy No.CABINET    29  (27).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10,Downing Street, S.W.1*, on MONDAY,2nd May,  1927, at 12 noon.AGENDUM.THE SITUATION IN CHINA.(Reference Cabinet 28 (27) Conclusion l).Fourth Report by the Chiefs of Staff.(CP.  138 (27)    -   to be circulated).(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S-W.1.29th April, 1927.
CAB I NET    29  (27).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on MONDAY, 2ndMay,  1927,  at 12.0 noon.PRESENT:-The Right Hon.  Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (In the Chair).! Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G. ,;:.P.,  Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.Be Right Hon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.f:e Right Hon.?/.S.&apos; Churchill, C.H.,M.?.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Earl of Balfour, K.G.,0.11., Lord President of theCouncil.The Most   Hon.Tnc iiarquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C *B.,  lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P.,Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.fe Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-evans bt. ,.G .B.E., M. P.,  Secretaryof State for War.(he Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forInli a.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C. :.G.M.P., Secretary of Statefor Air.fhe Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour,  Bt.,D.S.O.,M.P.,  Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman,  M. P.,First Lord of *he Admiralty.[he Right Hon.    .Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E., M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.Right Hon.W.E.  Guinness, D.S.0.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-iLaitland,Bt.,M.P.,  Minister of Labour;ne Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,First Commissioner of work  the Ri ght Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.P.,A11 or ney-G enera1.THE FOLLOWING  -.-.-aRE ALSO PRESENT:-*ural of the fleet general Beatty,  0.M, 3.C.B.,CC.V.0. ,D.S.O. , first sea Lord.(For  part of the meeting).General Sir G.F. F,ilne,G.O.B. ,G.C.;.;.G. ,D. .0.,A... .C, Chief of the,Imperial General Staff.(For  part of the meeting)./Iarshal of the Royal Air force sir Hugh Trenchard, Bt.,G.C.B.,D.S.O., Chief of the Air Staff.(For  p^rt of the meeting).
-   The Cabinet had before them a fouth report by the Committee of Chiefs of Staff inregard to Sanctions, relating exclusively tothe sanctions possible at Hankow, namely, there-occupation of the British Conoesaion there and the destruction of the Hanyang Arsenal(Paper C.P.-138 (27)).The new factors sinoe the last Meeting,when the Cabinet had been favourable in principle to the re-occupation of the British Concessionat Hankow, may be summed up as follows:-(i) Sir Miles Lampson, though prepared toagree to the re-occupation of the Concessionrather than to do nothing at Hankow (TelegramgivenNo, 791 of April 27th), had/powerful reasonsagainst the proposal (Telegram No. 792 of April28th, repeating his telegram No. 288 to the naval commander-in-Chief).    But Sir Miles Lampson&apos;salternative, viz., the destruction of HanyangArsenal, had been shown by the Chiefs of StaffSub-Committee, in the Report referred to above,to be open to strong objections on military grounds.(ii) The Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee,after a eareful examination, have r-ported (in paper C.P.-138 (27))  that they cannot guarantee that communication with Hankow can be kept openduring the period of low water on the river(December to March 26th).(iii) The Naval Commander-in-chief has reported (Telegram No. 1015) in favour of pro-tec ting the bulk of British property outside the concession, whioh is more than ten times aavaluable as that within the Concession. This
involves a much larger force and a greaterCommitment,  and is opposed by the Chiefs ofStaff Sub-Committee on military grounds.    TheCommander-in-Chief&apos; s telegram No. 1019, of April28th, though sent to the British Minister&apos;at peking to advocate the re-occupation of the concession, was quoted as setting forth someof the risks of the operation:-&quot;Every day we wait defences ofYangtse are being improved and added to.    It is&quot;clearly anothercase of the Dardanelles, and ifwe do not strike at once our difficulties are going to be intensified.I know it is a gamble, but nogamble has ever been won by shilly-shallying&quot;, etc.(iv)  The United States Government isdefinitely unwilling to participate in a second &apos;&apos;Note to the Nationalist Government or insanctions.   A second Note, signed by only four powers, would accentuate the abstention of theUnited States of America, who had participatediIn the original Note in regard to the Nankingoutrages.    Further, the United States Ministerat Peking, who has throughout favoured (joint action, has warned Sir Miles Lampson irj the strongest terms against a re-occupation of the concession as an Independent British action ascalculated to have a sensational and adverse effect in America, where our motives would bemisconstrued &quot;and render hopeless any furtheridea of future Anglo-American co-operation inChina&quot; sir Miles Lampson, Peking, No.80$, ofApril 30th).    The only nation whose co-operation in sanctions at Hankow can be counted on i^Italy .
(v) There is evidence that in Shanghaithe ^ankow Agreement is regarded as a &quot;low river&quot;policy, to be thrown over when the rise in theriver enables the Concession to be re-occupied.This accentuates th^ difficulty of convincingworld opinion of the real justification which exists for tearing up an agreement which has beenflagrantly violated by the Nationalist Government.(vi) Some evidence was produced that the justification for a re-occupation of the Conces-sion is not well understood in the Dominions atpresent.(vii) There are many indications that theNationalist Government at Hankow is weaker, both from a political and economic point of view.The Chief of the Naval Staff read telegramshe had exchanged with the Naval Commander-in-Chief regarding the difficulties of maintainingcommunications during the period of low river(Appendix).    He recalled to the Cabinet theadvice given by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committeein their Second Report on Sanctions (Paper C.P.-128 (27))  in favour of greater authority being given to the naval forces, not merely to replyto fire from the banks, but to counter-attackwith all their power anyone firing on ships flyingthe british  Flag on the Yangtse.    This plan,Lord Beauty pointed out, might be extended to appropriate action at ports where &quot;British livesor property were assailed by the nationalist forces.    In this connection he quoted thefollowing passage from Sir Miles Lampson&apos;telegram No.805, of April 30th:-
&quot;Of course if His Majesty&apos;sGovernment, deliberately decide to adopt a new policy and arehenceforth prepared in seriousearnest wherever practicallypossible in future to defendby force and at once any attackon British lives and. property,matters at once assume a newaspect.   But in that case itshould be dealt with on that basis and not as a reprisal forNanking.    I should welcome sucha modification of policy which(two groups undecipherable) isoverdue and should see with asigh of relief such encroachmentsas are taking place almost dailyat practically every Yangtse portforcibly resisted.    If we didthat   as we are not onlyjustified but now in a positronto do   such encroachments wouldquickly cease and our whole posi-tion In China would be immediatelyimproved.    Our prestige would atonce rise one hundred per cent&quot;.The Cabinet felt that, on political grounds,the case for re-occupying the Concession at hankow had proved on investigation to be weakerthan they had expected.    They were impressed by the fact that the operation was not only not-likely to be welcomed by the Powers who hadparticipated in the Nanking Note, but that- it did not receive whole-hearted support, from all british official representatives in China.While accepting the view of the Committee of chiefs of Staff that the original and more limited plan is a feasible military operation,it was commented that proposals had already beenmade to extend its scope and that the extent ofthe ultimate military liability could not begauged.    In these circumstanoes the cabinet agreed -(a) That neither the re-occupationof the British Concession at hankow nor the destruction ofthe Hanyang Arsenal should beundertaken at present:
(b) That, in the absence of anyacceptable sanctions, it wouldbe undesirable to co-operate in any further Note by four powers only to the nationalist government at Hankow:(c) That further enquiry should bemade into the proposals submittedby the Committee of Chiefs ofStaff (Paper CP.-128 (.27)) andin Sir Miles Lampson&apos;s telegramNo. 805 ^quoted above) in favourof greater authority being givento the naval forces on the Yangtseto counter-attack with all their power those who fire on shipsflying the British Flag and generally to defend by forceand at once attacks on Britishlives and property.2, Whitehall Gardens. S.W.1,May 2, 1927.
APPENDIX.363COPY OF TELEGRAM.(1)From Admiralty.No. 771.ToO-ln-C.China.Date 29.4.27.Cypher G.E.(P.O.).Emergency State.Your 10 and 15. We accept your view that concession can bere-occupied and held until low river.    In light ofinformation at our disposal however, we are not preparedto endorse your undertaking to maintain communication between Hankow and Sea during winter months.   Apparentobjections are (a) uncertain attitude of Chiang Kai Shik.(b) Field guns possibly are greater menace than Forts.(c) owing to fall of river which amounts to a maximum of45 feet ships guns may not be able to hear on field guns.(d) Difficulty of ships locating and engaging field guns in concealed positions unless prepared to land parties.(e) Difficulty of landing parties on muddy foreshore.(f) Readiness with which field guns can be removed fromdanger zone and replaced.    Request your views on these points.    We are fully alive to the necessity of action atearliest date possible but must be able to measure asaccurately as possible the risks involved. D.O.D.NOTE.    No distribution outside Admiralty.
COPY OF TELEGRAM,fii).From C. in C. China- No. 32.To   Admiralty. Date 20.4.27.Cypher G.E. f F.O.)EMERGENCY STATE.Your 771 Ta) please see Minister Peking1 s 7823:to Foreign Office with reference to ?(political situation at)Eanfcow (b) this may be so but I do not consider thatfield guns will ever &quot;definitely block river.    If so theymust be dealt with by aircraft. (Field guns) are illadapted to rapidly moving targets.    It would be possibleto convert a river steamer into an aircraft carrier (c)in this case ships may require howitzers but I do notconsider this a serious (danger) (d) this is inevitablebut I do not think this is a difficulty which cannot becontended with (c) and (f) accepted as obstacles.Apart from this (it is) quite impossible to say what willbe the state of Yangtse or China in 6 months (time)(but It is) general opinion that when we have establishedourselves in Hankow rest will be easy.    (I have) interviewedseveral people lately from Hankow who all state thatretaking British Concession will be welcomed.    Pood and silver are getting scarce and unemployed are only tooanxious to get back to work.    I again urge haste in finaldecision as hot weather is approaching and Hankow isconsidered the hottest place in Yangtse.2257/30 .NOTE.    Eot circulated outside Admiralty.^ Probably No. 792 or No. 805 is Intended.

</content>
</cab>
