<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/54/0 images: 384-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:TS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S GOVERNMENT) *S C R E T.COPY NO:CABIN E T    50    (27).MEETING OF THE CABINET to be held at 10, Downing Street,S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, MAY 4TH, 1927, at 11.30 a.m.AGENDA   .1.      SITUATION IN CHINA.    (IF REQUIRED).2 .      EXPORT OF AERONAUTICAL MATERIAL TO RUSSIA.Memorandum by the Secretary (S  Ste te for Air,CP. 139 (27) - Circulated herewith.THE 7/ASHING TON HOURS CONVENTION.Reference Cabinet 15 (27), Conclusion 4,Memorandum by the Minister of Labour,CP. 137 (27) - Already circulated.4.   &apos;  PRIVATE MEMBERS1  BILLS FOR FRIDAY, 15TH MAY,  1927.(1)    Ootical Practitioners (Registration) Bill:Mr . West Russell&quot; ( C).(2)    Protection of Animals (Amendment) Mill;Ka ior McLean ( C) ,(3)    Government of Scotland Bill:Mr. Barr (La0)TO TAKE NOTE OF:-5&quot;      CONCLUSIONS OF COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRS.The Audit (Local Authorities) Bill, 1927.Reference Cabinet 27 (27),  Conclusion 5.Committee of Home A fairs 8th Conclusion,  (27) 1,(Signed)     M..P .A. HANKEY,Secretary.f, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1May 2nd,  1927. -
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .SECRET.Copy No.CABINET    30 (27).CONCLUSIONS of a meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,4th May, 1927, at 11.30 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.Prime Minister.    (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P., Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.H.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.The Earl of Balfour, K.G.,O.M., Lord President of theCouncil.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C.B., lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.V; Sir Laming Worthing ton-evans bt.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C.M.G.M.P., Secretary of Statefor Air.  -The Right Hon.Sir&quot;John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O.,M.P., Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.W.E. Guinness, D.S.0.,M.P. ,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt,,M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Peroy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G B.E.,First Commissic .3.r  :f Works.The Right Hon,Sir Douglas Hogg,Attorney-General.Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.secretary
CHINA. 1. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs drew attention to a telegram from the British(previous reference: Ambassador In Tokio (No. 216 of May 3rd) reportingCabinet 29(27).) an interview with the new Japanese Minister ofForeign Affairs, in which the latter, in replyto Sir J. Tilley&apos;s statement of our desire toco-operate with Japan, had replied that &quot;althoughour Alliance no longer existed the spirit of it did, and he hoped by frank conversations&quot; to keep it in force.    Sir Austen Chamberlain intended tosend a telegram to Tokio reciprocating the views expressed by the Foreign Minister.In regard to the decision at the previous meeting of the Cabinet (Cabinet 29 (27), Conclusion(c)),&quot;That further enquiry should be made into the proposals of the Committeeof Chiefs of Staff (CP.-128 (27))and in Sir Miles Lampson&apos;s telegramNo. 805 in favour of greater authoritybeing given to the naval forces onthe Yangtse to counter-attack withall their power those who fire on ships flying the British Flag, and generally to defend by force and atonce attacks on British lives and property&quot;,the Cabinet were informed that the Foreign office had prepared a Memorandum which had been circulatedto th-^ Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee, who hadbeen asked to prepare for consideration draft instructions to the Naval Commander-in-Chiefgiving effect to these proposals.After some discussion the Cabinet agreed  (a)  To take note with approval of theproposal o^ the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to reciprocatethe views of the new JapaneseMinister of Foreign Affairs as reported in Sir J. Tilley&apos;sjtelegram No. 216, that, although&apos;our Alliance no longer existed,  thespirit of it did:-1-
(b) That, when considering the points referred to them at the previous meeting of the Cabinet,  theattention of the Chiefs of StaffSub-Committee should be invitedto the following points:-(i) The importance of keepingdistinct the two issuesreferred to them, viz.:-their own proposal thatHis Majesty&apos;s Ships should at once take action against those who fired on vesselsflying the British Flag;and Sir Miles Lampson&apos;proposal for early reprisalson the spot for hostile action against Britishinterests anywhere in China:(ii) Mr Newton&apos;s telegram fromHankow, No. 138 ^r May 1st,suggesting that british property at Chinkiang shouldbe protected by direct orretaliatory action there,to which the Sub-Committeeshould give separateattention.
EXPORT OP 2. The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumAERONAUTICALMATERIAL TO by the Secretary of State for Air (Paper C.P.-RUSSIA.139 (27))  regarding four applications which had(Previous recently been reoeived in the Air Ministry from reference:Cabinet 18 aircraft manufacturing firms for the export of(27)    Con-clusion 3.) aeronautical material to Russia,  together with recommendations thereon.The Cabinet agreed  To authorise the Secretary ofState for Air to act as proposedin his Memorandum (Paper C.P.-139 (27)), viz., to reject the applications for (i) a number(unspecified) of &quot;Horsley&quot;machines, complete with engines and instruments (this machinebeing a modern type of bomberwith which several BombingUnits o^ the Royal Air Poreshave recently been equipped),as well as (id) the order fora large quantity of &quot;Napier&quot;engines:    but to approvepermission being given for one&quot;Yeovil&quot; Bomber and a number ofcrank-shafts for &quot;Liberty&quot;engines.
INTERNATIONAL 3. The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumREGULATION OPHOURS OP WORK.. by the Minister of Labour (Paper CP.-137 (27))reporting that, after consultation with the Law(previous reference: Officers of the Crown on the possibility ofCabinet 15(27), Con- reconciling the provisions of the Coal Mines Act,elusion 4.)he proposes to proceed with the action contem-plated in the First Interim Report of the CabinetCommittee on the Washington ^ours Conventionapproved by the Cabinet on March 9th, namely:-&quot;To consult the employers&apos; representa-tivss privately, using as a basis ofdiscussion the main points containedin the draft Bill as approved by theCabinet, with the inclusion of a clause on the lines of the LawOfficers&apos; opinion, after whichhe would report their views to theCabinetIn connection with this question the cabinet were informed that the same afternoon LordParmoor was calling attention in the House ofLords to recent discussions at Geneva on thesubject of an International Convention for an eight-hours&apos; Lay, and it was pointed out thatthe Government spokesman must be in a positionto make some statement of policy on the subject.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the proposals of theMinister of Labour as set forth in cp.-137 (27) and summarised above:(b) That the Lord President of theCouncil should reply to LordParmoor in the House of lords to the effect that His Majesty&apos; sGovernment were anxious to ratify the Washington Convention, butwished to be assured on two points,namely:-(i) That the principal indus-trial competitors of thiscountry should ratify atthe same time?    and(ii) That all the Powers con-cerned interpreted theConvention in the same manner.
On this latter point he should explain that a large measure ofagreement in regard to interpre-tation had been reached at theLondon Conference, but that oneor two points of difficulty of interpretation had since arisenand were being considered.   he might draw attention to thedifficulties which had arisenon the matter in connection with german industrial legislation.The Lord President should alsoindicate that the Eritish Govern-ment were seeking to secure somejoint&apos; international action witha view to the enforcement of theprovisions of the Convention whenratified.(c) That the Minister of Labour should prepare a Memorandum on the linesof, and amplifying, Conclusion (b)above, for the use of the lord president in the House of Lords.-5-
THE OPTICAL 4. The Cabinet were informed that the OpticalPRACTITIONERS(REGISTRATION)     Practitioners (Registration) Bill, to be intro-BILL.duced by a Private Member (Mr West Russell) onFriday, May 13th, involved controversial ques-tions, and that the Minister of Health had appointed a Committee to examine into the wholequestion.    The Promoters of the Bill had beenasked to withdraw it.    They had declined to doso, but had intimated that they would not pressit to a Second Reading Division.The Cabinet agreed -That if, notwithstanding theirpresent intention, the promoters of the Eill should express a desire to press it to a SecondReading, the Minister of Health(or the Parliamentary Secretary)should inform the House that itwas undesirable to give the bill Second Reading pending the investigations referred to above.-6-
THE PROTECTION 5.OP ANIMALS(AMENDMENT)BILL.The Cabinet agreed  That the Protection of Animals(Amendment) Bill, to be intro-duced by a Private Member(Major McLean) on Friday, May13th, should be supported.
6.    The Cabinet took note of and approved the following decision, taken with their authority by the Committee of Home Affairs(H.A.C. 10th Conclusions (27), Para. 1)&quot;To approve the Audit (LocalAuthorities) Bill,1927, inthe form of the draft annexed to CP.-93 (27) subject to clause 4 (2) being modified asindicated in the Minutes ofthe ,Committee of Home Affairsif the Minister of health should think fit&quot; (CA.C.    10thConclusions (27), Para. 1).2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,May 4, 1927.THE AUDIT(LOCALAUTHORITIES)BILL,  1927.(previous reference:Cabinet 27(27), Con-clusion 5.)

</content>
</cab>
