<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/38/48 images: 474-481</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1943.SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (43) 298.7 th July, 1943.WAR CABINET.WAR PENSIONS PENSIONS APPEAL TRIBUNALS BILL.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.IN a separate memorandum circulated to-day, I have submitted to mycolleagues certain proposals for changes in the War Pensions code and havesuggested that, if the War Cabinet approves these proposals, they should be incorporated in a White Paper to be presented to Parliament in the near future.The two questions to which I wish to draw the attention of my colleagues inthis memorandum are connected not ,so much with the War Pensions code itself as with the scope of the appeal to be allowed under the Pensions Appeal TribunalsBill which is now before the House of Commons.2. The first question concerns the discretionary powers of the Minister ofPensions.Most of the important issues which the Minister of Pensions has to determineare laid down in Regulations. In regard to these matters, he has no discretionand, on such issues e.g., entitlement, award of a permanent pension, amount ofthat permanent pension, provision of that permanent pension provision is madefor an appeal to the independent Tribunal.There are, however, certain matters in regard to which the Minister has aconsiderable measure of discretion. Thus, while in the 1919 Warrant, if seriousnegligence or misconduct was proved, no pension could be awarded, under thepresent war Warrant, the Minister is not bound to refuse pension, but has powerto make an abated award and this is the normal practice. v3. The Pensions Appeal Tribunals Bill provides for an appeal on thequestion whether, or not, there was serious negligence or misconduct, but not onthe question of the quantum of any abatement, if serious negligence or misconductis proved. In this respect, the present Bill follows the lines of the 1919 and 1921Acts, to the provisions of which no objection has, in the past, been taken.The view, has, however, been pressed in the &quot;House of Commons that any matter which&quot; falls to be determined by the Minister of Pensions, whether by regulation or in the exercise of his discretion, should be subject to appeal; andit will be urged that it is unreasonable in any way to limit the rights of. theclaimant.. 4. Although no formal indication of their views has been expressed, thereis reason to believe that bodies such as the British Legion are not particularlyattracted by this idea. Their view, no doubt, is that any Regulation would haveto provide for the normal case; that this would preclude special treatment whichcan at present be given to the abnormal case; and that the result of substitutingRegulations for discretion would be a levelling out of benefits, with less regardto the merits of individual cases.5. The Lord Presidents Committee have considered this point and have asked me to inform the War Cabinet that, in their view, decisions taken by theMinister of Pensions in the exercise of his discretion should not be made thesubject of appeal. If Parliament desired that the Minister&apos;s decisions on matters in regard to which he can at present exercise a discretion should be subject toappeah to the Tribunals, then it would be necessary to deprive the Minister of his existing discretion -and to have these matters determined by precise rules whichwould be binding on the Tribunals. The Ministers decisions would have to be -judicial rather than administrative in character.[25701]
A list of the matters in regard to which the Minister of Pensions has ameasure of discretion is attached as Appendix A to this memorandum incase the War Cabinet should wish to consider how far, in their view, it wouldbe advisable or practicable for these matters to be dealt with by means of preciserules on the lines outlined in the preceding paragraph.6. Since the Lord. Presidents Committee considered this question myattention has been drawn to a second point of a similar nature on which a decision is required before the Committee stage on the Pensions Appeal Tribunals Billis resumed in the House of Commons.For the proper understanding of the point at issue, it is necessary to explain that, in the immediate post-discharge period, the Minister of Pensions makes atemporary award which is reviewable upwards and downwards in the light of changes in the discharged man&apos;s condition. When the degree of war disablementhas stabilised and can&quot; be permanently assessed, the Minister of Pensions makes afinal award which cannot be reduced. It can exceptionally be reviewed in an upward direction if there is an unanticipated deterioration in the man&apos;scondition.7. Under the procedure adopted after the last war the man had the. rightof appeal, first against &quot;the decision that his condition was stabilised and that apermanent award should be made, and secondly on the quantum of the permanentaward granted. The Bill now before the House of Commons makes similar provision; and hitherto there has never been any suggestion from any of the interested parties that, in the field of assessment, there should be an appeal to thetribunal otherwise than on these two points.In the course of the recent debate in the House of Commons it was, however,suggested that all temporary awards should be subject to appeal as to quantum;and this is the-question on which a decision is now required.In considering this point my colleagues will no doubt bear in mind that,although there has not been much complaint on assessment when entitlement hasbeen conceded, the creation of a right of appeal against temporary awards would add considerably to the work of the Ministry of Pensions. Tribunals would always be loath to reduce an award, and pensioners might well think that they had nothing to lose and possibly something to gain by taking their case to theindependent Tribunal.J. A.Privy Council Office,Great George Street, S.W. 1.7th July, 1943.
Summary of Types of Case in which Minister&apos;s Decision is Discretionary.I. Grant of wife&apos;s and children&apos;s allowances where pensioner is living apartfrom his family.2. Grant of pension to a separated wife (widow) (dependent on amount of support given by deceased husband).3. Grant of allowance or pension to an immarried dependant who claims to have lived as the wife of the member and been wholly or mainly supported byhim for the prescribed period.4. Extension of pension beyond 12 months to a childless unmarried wife(dependent on need and incapacity for self-support).5. Award of pension at the higher rate to an under-40 childless widow(dependent on incapacity for self-support).6. Termination or suspension of an award on ground that recipient isunworthy of a grant from public funds.7. Extension of children&apos;s allowances on the ground of education orapprenticeship (dependent on financial test).8. Extension of children&apos;s allowances on the ground of infirmity which had arisen before the child attained the normal age limit (dependent on financial test).9. Education allowances for children (dependent on child&apos;s ability, financialtest and deceased parent&apos;s ability to provide education had he not been disabledor killed).10, Family allowances or pension for the husband and children of a womanmember (dependent on incapacity of husband and his dependence on wife and onpecuniary need).II. Restoration&quot; of pension of ofncer&apos;s widow on second widowhood(dependent on financial circumstances).12. Award of pension to the illegitimate child of an unmarried mother(dependent on amount of support by deceased father)..13. Award of pension to illegitimate child of. deceased woman member(refused or reduced if surviving father liable to contribute to its support).14.   Administration of pension, e.g., to secure proper care of child.15. Parents&apos; pensions where entitlement admitted (dependent on need and where deceased member was a married man, on need and support).16. Pensions to &quot;other dependants&quot; (dependent on need, incapacity for self-support and dependence on deceased member).17. Constant attendance allowance (dependent on membefs need for anattendant on account of his 100 per cent, disability).. 18.   Assessment of degree of disablement.19. Abatement of pension on ground that disablement or death due to serious negligence or misconduct of member.20. Adjustment of pension in respect of other compensation for the samedisablement or death, or where the pensioner unreasonably refuses or neglects to recover compensation from a third party.






</content>
</cab>
