<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/51/14 images: 192-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   June 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 314.Sth^June, 1944. / &apos;&apos;WAR CABINET.-VCHILDREN&apos;S ALLOWANCES TO V/IDOWS OF OFFICERS killed in ACTION.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs and leader of the House of Lords.1. During the past eleven months there have been four Debates in theHouse of Lords on the insufficiency of the allowances to ,the widows of officers who have been killed on active service.2. On the first occasion (30th June, 1943), the Earl of Cork and Orrerydid not press his Motion on this subject, as the Government spokesman represented that rates of pay and other kindred matters affecting war pensions and allow-ances were then under active consideration.3. On the second occasion (8th December last), following the White Papers&apos; on War Pensions (Cmd. 6459 and 6473) of July and October 1943, Lord Corktabled a Resolution &apos;&apos; that the rate of allowances for children of officers killed on service is too low and should be raised.&quot; That Resolution was adopted withouta division in a House so hostile that Lord Snell, the Deputy Leader, who was incharge at the time, considered this course preferable to allowing the matter togo to a division where the Government would undoubtedly have been heavilydefeated.4. On the third occasion (14th March last), Lord Cork refrained from pressing his Motion to a division, as the conversations between government representatives and Members of Parliament drawn from all sides of the house on rates of Service pay, which followed the Debate in the Commons on the army estimates, were immediately pending.5. At the end of April, the White Paper on Service Pay and Allowanceswas produced and made available to both Houses of Parliament, and on the24th May, Lord Cork returned to the charge. On this occasion I myself, as leader of the House, replied on the agreed lines, but I found no support in the house for the case advanced on behalf of the Government, and finally, in order to avoid a division with an inevitable Government defeat on so invidious a subject, the debate was adjqurned, upon my giving an undertaking that I would bring thematter before my colleagues in the Cabinet and report back in due course on the resumption of the Debate.6S Meanwhile, the Committee of Ministers, who have- been holding conversa-tions with Members of all Parties in the House of Commons on the.subject of pay and Allowances of the Services generally, have circulated a Memorandum(W.P. (44) 306), the recommendations of which regarding pensions and allowances for the widows and children of deceased officers I do not dispute in view of the wider issues involved. But, at the same time, I feel bound to record my dissent from some of the arguments advanced in the report of the Committee to theCabinet.7. I cannot feel that the position of officers is so nearly akin io that of other ranks as is indicated by the Committee. No one would seek to suggest that officersdeserve special treatment because they are drawn from a particular stratum of society, and, indeed, as the report itself indicates, there is, in any case, to-day noofficer class in the old sense of the term. But undoubtedly officers do undertakespecial responsibilities and run special risks.   *
8. Moreover, those officers, in particular, who have risen by their own meritsfrom the ranks and they are now a very considerable proportion of the totalnumber surely deserve of their country rather more favourable treatment than would have been theirs if their courage and ability had not raised them topositions of responsibility. Already there are many men who will not take corn-missions because the advantages do not compensate them for the additionalburdens and risks involved. This is not a tendency to be encouraged. I cannotfeel that equalitarianism should be carried to the point where it ignores thereward which is due to merit. While I would not press for an increase in thepensions for the widows of officers, I feel strongly that the education allowance for children should not be limited to.  50, but that there should in suitable cases bemore generous grants. Each case would, of course, have to be examined on its merits by an appropriate body, and those who did not need a grant would not receive one. No doubt such a solution would be likely to stimulate a demand for similar increases of rates for other ranks. But I believe that this could be resisted, on the grounds I have stated above, and I would urge this course on theCabinet, as an equitable way out of the present difficulties.9. If, however, my colleagues do not accept this proposal, I have no option but to accept, though reluctantly, the conclusions of the Committee. But I shouldbe most grateful if the Cabinet Committee could, as is suggested in their paper,interview Lord Cork and other Peers who have taken a special interest in thisquestion, as they have already interviewed Members of the House of Commons.These will then, at any rate, feel that the fullest consideration has been given tothe views that have been expressed in the House of Lords.&quot; ..: 8 r   V\;V/&apos; - &apos;:.       c. .&apos;Dominions Office, 8th June, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
