<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/282/0 images: 260-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
f) (% s(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S: GOVggNMgWT) SJS C R E T.                                        OOP:&quot; NO. CP. 84 (391.                           C A BIN E T.        FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO CZECHOSLOVAKIA.     Memorandum by the Chancellor&apos; of the Exchequer.     1.   The negotiations which have been proceeding withthe Czechoslovak Financial Delegation have now been concluded, and the Agreements resulting from them weresigned to-day.   It was early agreed that both.the UnitedKingdom and the French Government should make free giftsto the Czechoslovak Government of an approximately equalamount.   The United Kingdom gift would take the form of releasing the Czechoslovak Government from its liability to repay a corresponding part of the advance of  10 millions which was made by the Bank of England in october , 1938.It was also agreed that the two Governments should guaranteea loan to be raised by the Czechoslovak Government, out ofthe proceeds of which the balance of the Bank of England&apos;sadvance would be repaidc   The main questions at issue havebeen the amount of the free gifts to be made by the twoGovernments, and the question whether the loan should be larger than the amount due to be repaid so that the Czecho-slovak Government would receive some fresh money from this source.     2.   On the 7th December last the Cabinet authorised meto make a free gift of  4 millions, on the understanding thata similar gift would be made by the French Government, and to guarantee with them a loan of  6 millions, the whole of whichwould  go towards repaying the Bank&apos;s advance.   Thecorresponding gift which the French would make was to meet                           - 1 -
                                                       ? n 3                                                       W Uthe service of the 5% Czechoslovak Loan, 1937/42,  which isguaranteed &quot;by them,.  The nominal value of the bonds out-standing of this loan is about 700,000,000 francs (equivalentto about  4 millions).  However, as the negotiationsproceeded we found great difficulty in achieving our main purpose of securing that the Czechoslovak Government should set aside amounts equivalent to our free gift for thepurpose of providing free exchange for refugees who might wish to emigrate; the advance had already been made to them,the money was in their hands, and we could only persuade them to use part of it for this purpose by allowing them tohave some fresh money.  On the 21st December, therefore,the Cabinet, at my request, authorised me to increase -thetotal assistance which we would give to  12 millions by wayof loan and gift, of which  5 millions, if necessary,might be by way of gift.  With the French gift of  4 millions this would make a total assistance of  16 millions.     3.   We found that the Czechoslovak Delegation didnot press us to increase the free gift but were most anxious that the amount of the loan should be increased to 10 millions.  After long negotiations we have been able toreach agreement on a free gift from the United Kingdom of 4 millions, the corresponding gift of the service of the czechoslovak Loan from the French Government, and a loan of  8 millions to be guaranteed jointly and severally by theUnited Kingdom and French Governments.   6 millions of thisloan will be used to repay the balance of the advance madeby the Bank of England, and  2 millions will be fresh money available for the Czechoslovak Government,     4.   An essential part of this Agreement is that theamount of the free gift of the United Kingdom government shall be paid into a Special Account and used to provideforeign exchange for refugees emigrating from Czechoslovakia
9^! C\W  Uin accordance with an agreed scale.   The czechoslovak government will also pay into a Special Account the amounts which they would have had to pay for interest on the FrenchGuaranteed Loan, and these amounts will be used for the samepurposes;  so will the amount corresponding to the capital of the loan in 1942, so far as it is required for these purposes.  The expenditure of these sums will be administered by the Czechoslovak Refugee Institute in Prague, and willbe controlled by the British Liaison Officer and FrenchLegation in Prague respectively.  Detailed arrangements forthe use of the money so provided are contained in a letterfrom the Head of the Czechoslovak Delegation which will bepublished, with the Agreements-, in the White Paper.  this letter also contains an assurance that there will be no discrimination in the treatment of refugees on religious,political or racial grounds.     5.   The conclusions reached as a result of thenegotiations are contained in four Agreements, whoseprovisions are shortly as follows:-     (l)   An Agreement between the United Kingdom,         France and Czechoslovakia, providing for the issue         by the Czechoslovak Government of a loan sufficient         to raise  8 millions (together with the expenses         of issue), to he guaranteed jointly and severally         by the United Kingdom and the French Governments.     (2)   An Agreement between the United Kingdom and         Czechoslovakia providing that the United Kingdom         Government shall release the Czechoslovak Government         from liability in respect of  4 millions of the         advance already made, and that the Czechoslovak         Government shall pay the same sum into the Special         Account to be disbursed in accordance with the         arrangements agreed;  also that when they have         received the proceeds of the Guaranteed Loan they         shall repay to the United Kingdom Government the         balance outstanding (viz.   6 millions) of the          10 millions advance, with interest at 1.%.     (3)   An Agreement between France and Czechoslovakia         embodying the arrangement described above for         the French free gift.
     (4)    An Agreement &quot;between the United Kingdom and         Prance providing that each Government shall         provide half of any sums required under the         guarantee.     6.    Parliamentary authority is needed to empower the Treasury to repay the amount of the advance made to theBank, and in order to carry out the provisions of the first two Agreements mentioned above.  A Bill has been drafted andwill be submitted to the Home Affairs Committee on the 30thJanuary (H.A. 6 (39)),   It is important to obtain parliamentary sanction as soon as possible for the repayment of the advance to the Bank of England  and also for the release ofthe  4 millions in order that the same amount may be madeavailable for the relief of refugees at the earliest possible date.  In view of these circumstances and the fact that theCabinet has already approved the principles of the Agreements,the Prime Minister has agreed that I should give notice of presentation of the Bill on Tuesday next, 31st January,before its terms have been approved by the Cabinet.  It will,however, have been before the Home Affairs Committee.                         (Intld.)   J.S.Treasury, S.W.1.,   27th January,  1939.

</content>
</cab>
