<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/42/0 images: 135-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*? ( This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.IBPI-DENT IAL.. i^THLY IMPORT OP *TK3 70RK OF TH3 BOARD OP TRAJE.^?V*     circulate a brief account of the work of the Board of Trade for the^Smth of January. /JM/re-organisation of the Board of Trade described in the ^,^aper Cd. 8912, presented last month, is now in full opera-^.,n\    The new Department of Overseas Trade under the joint control of the Foreign Office and the Board of Trade, is also at work.The following is a summary of the most important work dono by the various sections of the&apos; Department during the last month.A.H. STANLEY15th February, 1918.I. DJjPARTlCiNT OF 001^1303 AIT) INDUSTRY.A.foreign ProblemsChinese Tariff   The suggested revision of the Chinese tariff is under discussion.   It is proposed that the gew specific rates of duty should be established a&apos;t the rate of 5% on the average values&apos; of imports during the three vears 1911-13.    4s however this system will admittedly not yield an effective 5/o a surtax on the new specific rates will be imposed.     In this connection it has been suggested to the Foreign Office that 15^ is a maximum surtax to which the British Delegates should agree without irefer-ence home.     The new tariff is to bo revised 2 years after tho end of the war.    The revision of the present duties leviable on imports over the Chinese land frontier is also suggested, (duties made under various old treaties between China on the one handj and Great Britain, Francej Russia and Japan on the other), but it is understood that Russia is opposed to&quot; this..;Anglo-Portuguese Qommercial-Treaty.   His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Lisbon has been instructed to notify tho Portu ues$ Government of the withdrawal of the adhesion of all the British Dominions and Colonies, except Newfoundland, to the ^nglo-Portuguese commercial treaty owing to the View taken by the Portuguese Government that adhesion imposes on the Colonies the same obliga-tions as it im oses on the United Kingdom regarding the importa-tion and sale of certain winesiMiscellaneous.It has been arranged that British goods on onemy shins in Portugal shall be delivered, and the Dcnartmcnt is trying&apos;to effec a similar arrangement with Brazil and Uruguay.New licences have been granted to firms in this country to trade with ap:-roved firms at&apos; Bagdad.An arrangement is pending by which it will be possible to import wood pulp from iweden on deferred payment should there be sufficient tonnage available.Arrangements have been made to supply sufficient Alizarine to India to alleviate the shortage in that country.Uganda Cotton Oron - . arrangements have been made by which it is hoped the British Cot ion Growing Association will be&apos; able tomake
, M rmake tho necessary financial provisions for continuing their operations in Uganda.The   otton Control Board are taking stoT)S to /rive effect to tho Tro. siirv Regulations concerning the purchase of cotton in the United States by framing a new form of licence.Candidates have been selected for the posts of Trade Commis-sioners, and arrangements aro being made for them to leave for their posts as quickly&apos; as oossiblo.   The Trade Commissioner in Zealand is visiting Samoa and other islands in the Pacific.Satisfactory progress has been made with the scheme for in-creasing British&apos; trade in Colombia, and for instituting a big commercial and financial organisation in Mexico City      deal with trade between the ;nited ,,ingdom and ilexico. ^Arrangements have also been made to obtain from Commissions abroad information regarding temporarily abandoned public works and schemes contemplated by foreign Governments, Municipalities and Corporations^ with a view to the consideration of their suitability for British enterprise.    J^uiries are also being mak with regard to the schemes for the reclamation of the Zuyder ^ee and as to the possibility of starting British Trade in ;:esopotamia.Delegates representinn Serbian commerce arc at present being conducted on a tour throw $out this country by an Officer of the Department.( Another Officer of the Department will shortly be proceeding to oouth America on a mission of investigation into the*prospects of the Jewellery and allied trades.( The organisation of the British industries Fair is proceeding satisfactorily, and by arrangements a small number of foreign buyors are being invited to visit the Fair.B.Home Industries.Tho i,on-Fcrrous I-iotals Bill has received Hoyal assent.Arrangements have been completed for the visit to France of v preliminary commission representative of the -Toun of British ironmasters who have taken ud the scheme for Permanent exchanpe of coking coal from this country for iron ore from North-westernJ France Algeria and Tunis.-collecting information for the purposes.of;a rationing scheme.underta expo DrocFurther licences have been ^raritpri to Critic.!-. riw*w i ,work enemy patents rclatin..; to dye stuffs. ^jes- . imted toP. Industrial i^nejrtv
II.   DEPARTMElNT Off PUBLIO ghjTIggg MdlNIsfelTIOH.Mercantile Marine,   , , i ,.A new scheme of gxaiination of candidates for certi-ficates of competency in the Mercantile Marine as Master or ?;ate came into force on the 1st January 1913; and a new scheme for the examination of the sight of Lascars and Chinamen for &quot;look-out&quot; duty has also been arranged.   The object of the changes is to&apos;bring the syllabus into bettor accord with modern requirements.The ferro-concrete ship l,as now advanced so far a printed notice to shipbuilders and an instruction to Board of Trade Surveyors have been ii^ued by the Department.The Committee appointed by the Board of Trade to advise as to the Standard uniform for the Mercantile-Marine has . presented its report.Marine Insurance- ,; The Treasury- have now agreed to the proposal made by the Department that where the Marine Insurance on a high valued&quot; cargo cannot all be placed at a fair terket rate., -the Government should take &quot;the balance at a rate slightly exceeding that rate, on the understanding that no more business is to be taken than is absolutely necessary to prevent excessivo rates being Th&amp;rged on essential commod-ities.    An illustration of the conditions prevailing is the rate which was. charged for cotton from Egypt.   A fair market rato would have been 1 per cont.   Owing to the mar-ket having absorbed all the risks of this character that were desired, speculators were charging 11 to 12 -oer cent, for this cottoniWar Bisks Insurance.Approximate Promiums and Losses on Hulls and Cargo from the beginning of the War to January 31st, 1918,Debit &apos;Premiums Losses. Balance.Hulls.......43,983,000 47,104,000 3,121,000Cargo......47,700,000 57,796,000 10^088,000Total ......91,691,000        104,900,000 13,209,000The excess of losses over Premiums roacheo a maximum last August when tho debit balance was  37.182,000. There has&quot;been a steady diminution in the figure since that time.*ULmJt^ )claim to&quot;this Policy/for any. lose of market or of adventure or for any costs, charges or damages incidental to the operations of discharge, re-shipping or forwarding conse-quent on compliance with any regulations made or orders given by or under the authority of,His Majesty^Govern-iiient or of the. Officers of any Allied Government,
tion msConsiderable ,dA^c6ntent fas express^ by the men in several of the Railway 0k?^paJxti^4^H^ativ and Waggon Shoos through their noa being&quot; p bonus given to&quot;Munition workers.   The ques to the Special Arbitration Tribunal,.and it has now been agreed that the bonus shall be paid to all time workers    &amp; in the Railway shops.Man Power.The question of Manpower has been discussed and it&apos; has been arranged for a total of 6,000 Railwayman to be re-leased for Service with the Colours during the present year. All these are to be Grade I men.MiscellaneouSj.The question of cabmen refusing to ply 4for hire at Railway Stations in London while the Id. toll was continued has been settled, and it has also been arranged that cabs may enter London Railway Stations in order to ply for hire for the period of the war without &quot;paying toll, the Companies being compensated for this loss of revenue,The basis of compensation for the English Canal Com-panies and by-traders&quot;has been agreed upon and the work of the Tramways Committee is proceeding rapidly.The standardisation of railway plant is being consider-ed by the Department.Gas Undertakings.fhe Department have suggested to the authorities of both Bouses of Parliament that a joint Select Committee should be appointed next session to consider the financial hardships of Gas undertakings arising out of the war in con-nection with various Provisional Bills that have been de-posited and this suggestion has been accepted.They are also working in close touch with the Ministry of National Service on the question of the recruitment of dock labour.A Bill has been drafted to amend the Trading with the Enemy (Amendment) Act, 1916, for the purpose of facilitating the winding up of companies; and a committee on&quot;Company Law Amendment is being set: up3Important enemy-owned oil shares have been sold with the consent of the Department -e^the Anglo-Persian Oil CompaiProm investigations made by the Registrar he has come&apos; to the conclusion that registration of ousiness names has been effected in approximately 15% of the cases in which re-gistration is required.Ill *  ^TEMPORARY WAR DEPARTMENTS. Coal Mines, jThe Mobility Bureaux scheme by which it is hoped to re-   1 move mining labour fre^i ri::f:rict;3&apos;&apos;where short time is being worked to pert j or&quot; i    *. /^iiiy rners the labour supply is----- * deficient I
deficient is held up for the moment owing to difficulties in getting the Miners&apos;federation to worn with the Ministry of National Service.The Department has under consideration the fr en oh and Italian objection to the.recent general increase of Z/oa per ton m coal orices (introduced to meet the cost of the war wage granted&quot; to the miners) being aoplied to shipments of coal to France and Italy- it is reported that the sunoiy of coal within the Metropolitan area 13 satisfactory. Tns most serious problem is still one of cartage facilities4Arrangements made for the supply of fuel to the poorer classes throughout the provinces and for the establishment ot emergency stocks for this ouroose have so far enabled all requirements to be reasonably me^iThe Goal Mines Control Agreement (Confirmation) Bill was passed by the House of Lords on the 16th January.B.    Timber.It has been airranged that the v/ork connected with thG survey and preparation of statistical reports with regard to re-afforestation shall be undertaken by the Department, and that all purchases of hard wood, soft wood or aerohauti-cal wood in the United States or Canada is to be made by this Department.   It has also been agreed that the Timber Controller shall be responsible for1 the supply of all timber required by Government departments.   The supply of timber for building scheises and reconstruction in Dublin has been arranged, and it has also been arranged that s representative of the Timber. Controller will shortly proceed to the United States to represent him on the British Purchasing Commissioru The total labour emplbyed by the Timber Controller is January 1917  was 4,500.   At January 1918 the number was 15,000 inciud-ing 3,000 Portuguesej 2,000 German Prisoners and 4,500 of the Canadian Forestry Corps.   The Department is also training Women for timber cutting.0.    pans la...It has been decided that Canal employees shall be granted the same war wage arrangements as those adopted by Railway Companies.   The terms on which canals shall be controlled h&amp;ve /been agreed upon, and a draft agreement with th6 Canal Carriers, whose undertakings have come under Government Control is being prepared and Several of the carriers have signified their in-teniion to sign the agreement.Over 600 men of the Transport Workers&apos; Battalion are now working on the canals.D*    -Horse-Transport.- j    \ -  .... ..,v fhe Department has concluded an arrangement with the Board of - Agriculture by which horses released from agriculture are passed on to appropriate commercial use.   The registration of Various breeds of horses continues, and many licences under the Eorse Rationing Order have been granted.    Towns are still suffering owing to shortage of Hay.the Board of Trade Journal appeared ill its new form on the 3rd January.

</content>
</cab>
