<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/42/0 images: 193-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1918.SEC HUT.NAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION-No. 38. Week ended 9th February, 1918.NAVAL OPERATIONS.North Sea.^^^ifineg^liave been laid in the Heligoland Bight.On February 3rd R.N.A.S. machines from Dunkirk carried out a raid on Houttave Flanders aerodrome and over 900 lbs. of bombs were dropped among the principal sheds and area-huts.Our machines also carried out several patrols and reconnaissances, in the course of which one enemy machine was destroyed and three were driven down out of control. Two of our machines are missing.On February 5th, at 7 p.m., the transport &quot; Tuscania &quot; was torpedoed off the north- Casualties, east coast of Ireland, while carrying United States troops.   Of about 2,400 troops and crew on board, 166 are missing.On February 8th the destroyer &quot; Boxer &quot; sank after collision with s.s. &quot; St. Patrick,&quot; 14 miles south of Portsmouth.   One boy was lost.One of our seaplanes fell into the sea two miles south of Polperro (Cornwall) and was lost.   The pilot and observer were saved.ATTACK UPON ENEMY SUBMARINES. During the week about 16 large enemy submarines have been located, including Submarinesnn^hil6 TT/w   ?eQutscMrd &quot; *pe-   TWe tas bee* considerable activity in thf operXg northern part of the Irish Sea and to the north of Ireland, and also in the Mediterranean as many as six submarines having been reported in the western basin between Genoa andThe following Table shows the number of actions with enemy submarines in Home Actions Waters during- recent weeks, and the nature of the craft which have been engaged, and ^th enemy also the number of submarines destroyed :  submarines.	Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended	-	January 19th.		January 26th.		February 2nd.		February 9th.	Nature of Craft.									Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.T.B.D. and T.B.........&apos;.	_,		3	1	1		5	1A.P. Vessels     .........	1	-	, 1	 1	3	1	1	-: Aircraft   ...	-\ -	 	1	 	2	  -	2	Sloops and &quot; P &quot; Class Vessels ...	- &quot;: \		1	1	 		1	 Merchant Vessels...	1		* 1	 	6	 .	1	 Destroyed by Mine     ......	 	1	-  &apos;	 	  -		 	1Submarines		__		 	 	&apos; -	2	Total	2	1	7	2	12	1	12	2&quot; Results&quot; indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.(C958)   Wt.       55  2/18  H&amp;S
2One of the submarines sunk during the week was destroyed by mine in the Straits of Dover, having been foreed by a drifter to dive in the minefield.An instructive hunt by means of hydrophone also took place during the week in the eastern part of the English Channel, the submarine being sighted at long range after having been picked up by the hydrophone. The hunt was subsequently misled by the sounds from a &quot; P &quot; boat in another hunting unit, which were picked up as a faint sound and followed, although these vessels must have been from 10 to 12 miles distant.number and toh-nage of all vessels lost.losses of british steamships in trades.MEKCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all Merchant Vessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action&apos;:-	British Vessels.&apos;				Allied and Neutral Vessels.				Total.	Week Ended	1,600 tons gross		Under 1,600 tons		1,600 tons gross		Under 1,600 tons		All sizes.		and over.		8	ross.	and over.			gross.			No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.&quot;	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1917.										December 29th	17	67,172	4	3,969	8	-   25,372	8	7,177	37	103,6901918.										January 5th	18	75,281*	2	1,391	9	30,056	 	- -	29	106,728*January 12th	4	14,489	1	.1,049	11	32,566	4*	5,165*	20*	53,269*January 19th	5	15,878	2	1,227	2	7,031	4	3,274	13	27,410January 26th	9	37,248	6	3,510	10	26,792	10*	7,137*	35*	74,687*February 2nd	12*	61,652*	5	2,097	5*	19,715*	21*	6,169*	43*	89,633*February 9th	11	53,521	6	2,200	6	27,785	7	4,697	30	88,203* adjusted.The losses for the week are again heavy, and the enemy appears to have been more than usually successful in his attacks on ships of large tonnage. The figures for the week ending February 2nd have been increased by the addition of 3. large and 12 small vessels, which are now reported to have been lost in the Mediterranean.The table in Appendix I shows in detail the numbers and tonnage of sailings and of losses by enemy action, and the percentage of losses to sailings of British merchant steamships of over 500 tons gross register ; and the table in Appendix II shows by trades as regards such ships the percentage of tonnage sunk by enemy action to tonnage sailing to and from United Kingdom ports during the last four weeks.The percentage of losses to sailings this week, as regards British tonnage employed in overseas trades, is 2.69 as against 1.92 last week, the increase being largely accounted for by the loss of the &quot; Tuscania.&quot; On the other hand, as regards Coastal and Cross-Channel traffic, the percentage is .18 as against .53 last week ; while the total percentage of losses to sailings, as regards all United Kingdom traffic, is 1.13 as against 1.03 the previous week.Areas in Th-e table in Appendix III is a comparative statement of all British merchant vesselswhich sunk, damaged or molested, and of all Allied and Neutral merchant vessels sunk m the vessels lost, last two weeks by enemy craft and by mine, classified according to areas.The feature of this week&apos;s statement is the great reduction in attacks in the English Channel after many weeks of exceptional activity in that area. Most of the losses this week, have taken place in the Irish Sea and the Mediterranean.\
The following statement shows the number and tonnage of British and Foreign Compara-Merchant Vessels sunk by. enemy action in each month since the commencement of j^8^&quot; unrestricted Submarine Warfare : 	British Merchant		British Fishing		Merchant Vessels		Merchant Vessels		Total		Vessels.		Vessels.		of other Allies..		of Neutrals.		of all Vessels.	Month.	No.	Tonnage	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1917.						It				February  ...	105	313,486	30	3,478	60	84,280	69	135,090	264	536,334March	127	356,230	43	3,586	62	.81,151	92	165.225	324	606,192April	168	541,887	41	5,920	82	134,448	122	189,373	413	871,628May...	121	349,419	19	1,448	70	102,960	96	139,605	306	593,432June	122	416,448	21	1,342	79	126,097	89	139,229	311	683,116July......	98	364,430	18	2,736	70	110,990	56	70,370	242	548,526August	90	328,688	5	242	61	125,482	34	53,018	190	507,430September ...	77	191,512	7	245	63	112,451	18	29,941	165	334,149October	85	274,973	5	227	53	127,932	30	54,432	173	457,564November ...	64	173,560	3	.  87   ,	39	80,699	21	29,647	127	283,993December ...	81	250,356	5	413	45	86,710	36	.. 51,997	167	389,4761918.						&quot;V -r -				January	52	173,462	10	375	39	86,810	20	33,783	121	294,430monthly losses.The total number of vessels sunk in January is the lowest for any month since unrestricted Submarine warfare commenced. Although the total tonnage sunk in January is slightly in excess of the figure for November, which was the best month of 1917, the daily average of tonnage sunk in January is less than in November,The following Table shows the average daily tonnage of British Merchant Vessels Daily which was sunk or damaged by Enemy Action, or which escaped from attack for each average of month since the unrestricted Submarine Warfare commenced, standardized by taking British 100 as the daily average for February in each case : tonnage attacked.Month.Sunk.Damaged.Escaped.Total Attacks.1917. February .. March April May JuneJuly August September October  .. November December..1918. January ..100 102.6 161.3 100.7 124.0 105.0 94.7 57.0 79.2 51.7 72.150.0100 72.4 79.0 46.4111.0 53.6 31.0 79.0 45.2 69.6 62.849.8100 91.1 140.2 117.9 165.6 118.1 80.7 50.7 34.5 40.5 60.039.8100 93.5140.3 98.7137.8101.9 79.3 58.1 56.8 50.2 66.046.1It will be seen that the average tonnage attacked daily in January, 1918, is less than half the corresponding figure for February, 1917, while the daily average of tonnage ZoeSS^ the month is just one-half the February figure, both asregards vessels sunk and vLels damaged. The daily average of escapeshom attack however, is less than 40 per cent, of the February figure, so that the tendency for less tonnage to be attacked but for the attacks to be more successful is maintained.ENEMY MINES.Enemy minelaying activity has this week been experienced in the Lowestoft and Minelaying. Harwich areas.   The resumption of minelaying in these areas synchronized with the movement of the Dutch trade, but the field of 18 mines was swept up without casualty. (C 958) A 2
Casualties.        The following table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed and British vessels sunk by mine in Home Waters in recent weeks : Week Ended.	Numberoof Enemy -Mines Destroyed.	Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.January 12th ...	22	Nil	Nil,,    19th.......	36.	2	Nil26th......	62	Nil	NilFebruary 2nd  ...	26	2	Nil   -9th  ...   1 ...	30	Nil	NilTwo fishing trawlers are reported to have been mined during the week, one of which was sunk.DEFENCE AGAINST SUBMARINE AND MINE.The number of vessels convoyed and the losses in convoy in the last two weeks are as follows: 	Week	j ended	Week	ended	February 2nd.		February 9th.	Convoys.				,   .                 .         ....	No. of		No. of		Ships	No. Lost.	Ships	No. Lost.	Convoyed.		Convoyed.	Atlantic Trades: 				Homeward..................	114		134	wOutward    ...............*	94	 	107	1Scandinavia Lerwick Humber   ,......	117	&apos; 	86	 French Coal Trades     ......      ...      ......	. 322	1	324	1Mediterranean Local   ...............	100	1	178	3Total.......	747	2	829	00The loss in the Outward Atlantic Convoy was the result of a collision. The vessels lost in the Mediterranean were two in the Alexandria Bizerta Convoy, and one in the Gibraltar Bizerta Convoy.Defensive The additional merchant vessels fitted to take defensive armament during the weekarmament,  are 34 for primary armament and 32 for supplementary armament.The number of howitzers and bomb throwers delivered to date is 688.Mine pro- 1,266 merchant vessels have been fitted with Otter equipment,tectiongear.MOVEMENTS OF ENEMY SHIPS.Merchant- Seven enemy merchant ships have this week arrived at, and five have sailed from,men/       Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat.  None have entered or left Rotterdam.Nine enemy vessels are reported as having left Delfzyl with coal, two for Denmark and seven for Sweden.
FOREIGN NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. Fkance.Six merchant ships have been sunk in the Gulf of Lyons during the past week, four &apos; of them being in one convoy.   The other two were sunk in the vicinity of Toulon.This area lies in a French zone, and there are 18 T.B.D&apos;s. and a division of four sloops based on Toulon, besides a large number of trawlers and other patrol craft working from Toulon, Marseilles and Port Vendres.pokttjgal.Three Portuguese submarines, completed and commissioned four months ago in Italy, axe reported as having sailed from Gibraltar for Lisbon. Presumably the interval has been employed in exercising and training the crews.These submarines, which are of a type designed for coastal defence and are of small displacement, correspond in radius of action, speed, armament, &amp;c, to our &quot; C &quot; class.Spain.Four ships have been sunk in the neighbourhood of Alicante during the past week. At least one of these, the Italian s.s. &quot; Duca di Genoa,&quot; was undoubtedly attacked inside territorial waters.The reply of the German Government to&quot; the Spanish Note on the sinking of the &quot; Giralda &quot; has not yet been published, but it is very unlikely that any satisfactory answer or compensation will be given to Spain, as the German Government are probably in possession of information proving that the ultimate destination of the cargo carried was an Allied country.Russia.The Special Commission for reorganising the Fleet has dismissed the &quot; Committee of Twenty,&quot; which consisted of 20 sailors whose duties were of an administrative nature, and also the &quot; Naval College,&quot; which dealt entirely with the political situation, and kept in touch with the Government and with the Baltic and Black Sea Fleet Committees. Duibenko, a torpedo gunner and Secretary to the Ministry of Marine, who was one of the three members of the &quot; Naval College,&quot; has in turn dismissed the Special Corn-mission.The Baltic Fleet at Helsingfors has apparently sided openly with the Finnish Red Guards.Sweden.The Swedish Government is much concerned at the situation in Finland and would like to assist the White Guards, but are afraid to do so for fear of agitation among the Socialists in Sweden. No&apos; embargo has been placed upon properly licensed exports of arms to Finland.At the request of H.M. Minister, the Swedish Government have promised to allow British refugees to make use of Swedish refugee ships leaving Finnish ports provided there is room, but it is doubtful whether more steamers can leave in the immediate future on account of the ice conditions.Naval Staff,lUh February, 1918.Appendices.
APPENDIX I.Statement of Numbers and Tonnage of SAILINGS and LOSSES of British Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross register forthe Week ended 9th February, 1918.TradeUnited Kingdom, to and from-North America Coast ...Gulf and West Indies ...      ......Gibraltar......      ...      .........Dakar, St. Vincent, W. Africa and S. America Bay, Portugal and Spain, West of GibraltarScandinavia     ...      ...      .........Holland ...Russia   .........      .........Total Overseas Traffic to and from United KingdomCoasting......      ............Cross-Channel  ...Total of Coasting and Cross-ChannelGrand Total of traffic to and from -United KingdomSailings.Losses.Percentage of Losses to Sailings.In.Out.No.Tons.51 12 29 11 15 18 6142 119*259313,769 61,368112,218 59,644 35,085 31,024 7,251620,359 553,536*472,456No.31 12 31 14 22 11 4 1126 129*227Tons.Total.No.219,262 71,781 119,108 80,099 41,826 17,034 4,718 2,489556,317 535,839*406,31382 24 60 25 27 29 10 1268 248*5884861,0741,009*1,342 1,257*Tons.In.No.Tons.Out.Total.No.533,031 133,149 231,326 139,743 76,911 48,058 11,969 2,4891,176,676 1,089,375*11,052,982 878,7691,931,751 1,933,493*3,108,427 3,022,868*1Losses on other Trades Total Losses for Week .. * Figures for previous week.3 2*14,348 . 4,160 2,87621,384 5,385*32*Tons.7,907 2,37210,279 15,491*3,501No.Tons.In.Out.Total.No.Tons.No.Tons.64*24*88*45f12 13f14,348 12,067 5,24831,663 20,876 *j3,5013,501 10,172*35,164 31,048*19,299 31,987f54,463 63,035-fj1.96 3.45 6.672.11 1.68*4.57 3.71 8.203.45 .97*6.45 4.54.&quot;2.38 1.55*6.64 5.671.852.89*.86No.Tons.1.22 5.0 7.412.69 5.22 6.822.24 j 2.69 1.61*, 1.92*.41.19.40*.40.59 .64*.18 .53*1.131.03*&quot;j&quot; Figures for previous week amended, to include late notificationsOS
APPENDIX II.Statement showing by Trades as regards British Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross the percentage of tonnage sunk by Enemy Action to tonnage sailing to and from United Kingdom Ports in recent weeks.       _tradeunited kingdom, to and from week ended 19th jan.week ended 26th jan.week ended 2nd feb.week ended 9th feb.north america coast      ......gulf and west indies     .........gibraltar    ...............dakar, west africa and south america bay, portugal and spain, west of gibraltarscandinavia...............hollandrussiaa * * ** *fin   ... -I out ... t total fin   ...-! out...L total fin   ...-I out ... [ total fin   ....1 out ... [ total fin   ...-I out ... t total fin   ...1 out... L total fin   ...\ out... I. total fin  ...J out ...-1 totaltotal of above trades       .....coasting    .........      .....cross-channel      ...........total of all united kingdom trades4.873.24 5.802.191.03.39.35 .18.193.86 1.898.46 4.704.30 7.21 5.20.50 2.60 1.51.12 .25 .49 .38.729.29 2.7911.306.17 13.775.99.97 2.89 1.92.38 1.50.721.034.57 2.693.71 6.64 5.228.20 5.67 6.823.45 1.85 2.69.86 .401.13APPENDIX III.Statement of the number of British Merchant Vessels sunk, damaged or molested, and Allied and Neutral vessels sunk, during weeks ended 2nd and 9th February, 1918, according to areas._area.arctic and white sea atlantic (north)   ... atlantic (south) bay of biscay gibraltar azores... below mogadornorth sea......english channel irish sea and bristol *   channel ... -mediterraneantotalsbritish.sunk.1,600 tons and over.week endedunder 1,600 tons.week endedcd PRrQcoPRCMrQcdPRcd PR45126 4114 13 1damaged or molested but not sunk.1,600 tons and over.under 1,600 tons.week endedrQcd PRrQCOPRweek endedCD PRrQCD PR131 2allied and neutral.sunk.1,600 tons and over.under 1,600 tons.week endedweek endedCMcd PRrQcd PRCMrQCDPROSrQ&apos;CD-PR5 613i    413115 212 2

</content>
</cab>
