<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/42/0 images: 296-298</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
, IQCUMKKT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRTTAIifllC MAJESTY TS GOVERN&apos;] KT). .W AH   0 A B I K E T,STATE Of THE LAIC). - IRISH POLIOY.Memorandum ley tho Chief Secretary for Ireland.Th* o rganis at ion. &amp;Uk hju JIASfij^in movamwrto in Ireland is bsing std at present ohiefl^ in fomenting&quot;; agrarian trouble in the rest nd S**th.   For this purpds^^orts j-are systematically spread that here is danger of famine such as &quot;lihat of 1847 and that the G^rernmcitt re exporting the food which should bo the safeguard against it; Ofal authorities are induced and independent local committees are ormed t* devise measures of food supply and control intended to istire and thwart those of the Government; cattin drives are organ-.oed in some of tho grazing districts under protonce of clearance if land for tillage j and in other cases large hodiep c^ men mlawfully entered upon grazing farms and marked out areas for iillage, and even made a pretsnce of tillage work.   In some instances and I think the majority) owners whose land wag demanded for tillage iy organised parties of the neighboiu-ing peasantry have come to. terms dth thorn, no doubt unwillingly.   In others the police have under-taken prosecutions of ringleaders.   Prosecution, however, is not an. sffective deterrent when the offenders are ready to go to prison and starve themselves into a.condition in which the executive has the alternative of letting them die in prison or making a temporary release and a subsequent re-arrest.   I have not been informed in the course of this predatory campaign of any occasion when the Interference with tha rights of property was attended by conduct amounting to riot which would havt? warranted repression by armod force.   The problem becomes increasingly difficult and is intimately sonnocted with the avowai determination ef ths Sinn Fein loaders to make administration impossible.   The offences to which I have referred ara, hewever, not very widespread at present..Interference with the export ef food has been attempted In small ways by the Extremists but not with any appreciable success. If real danger of famine were in viow.there is a possibility that they, eould combine the Transport workers of the ports to resist shipments.   At Cork a committee has been formed with that among ether objects.   The leaders of the Transport Union whfl -are in close touch with the leaders of the Sinn Fein may be relied on to cause trouble if it suits the purposes of both organisations.   As yet, Hwever, the attempts which are being made command no serious support. - The interests of the farmers,, and the dependence of Ireland upon Great Britain for supplies ;Of wheat and wheaten flour as well as for some other food supplies may J hope be relied upon as material influences which will contribute to prerent any grave trouble as to the continuance of exports of Irish produce to&apos;the extent to whioh this country is dependent on th^m.R E T,I: gtjftRaids
Raids for arms and seizures-tf arms are not so frequent at present as they were recently under the pressure tf public opinitn they are even being to stme extent discouraged &quot;by Sinn Fein.The pastoral addresses which the Irish Roman Catholic Bishops issue every year at the beginning tf Lent have this year laid great stress ;tn questions of public order in Ireland and also in a majority of cases on the demand for self-govertuuc:.!4&apos;-.   Exceedingly   urgent injunctions against rebellion and crimes connected with rebellion are expressed by sonvg of the Bishops.   Dr. Eoley, R.C., Bishop of Kildare lays emphasis on the necessity tf resisting all inducements to disorder upon a possible failure tf the Convention.   So far as I know trily one member of the Roman   hierarchy in Ireland shows distinct ttlerance to the tendencies tf Sinn Fein. He is Dr. Eogarty, Bishop tf Killaloe, whose ditcese comprising the county   tf Clare is the cantre of the western area where there is evidence tf latent rebellion. On the whole the influence of the Bishops is cast definitely, and as I think worthily and powerfully ,  on the side of order.   But they all call for Irish self-government tn national lines.
AFTER THE CONVENTION.In view of the possible inability of the Convention to cone to general agreement I venture to add some brief obscr-vations to those I have made in previous memoranda.I. As to the time for actienIt is commonly objected that Parliament and the nation cannot-reasonably be a eked to deal with Home Rule-.during the wor...     Except on grounds of utter necessity such a demand of course ought not to be made.     It is, however, strenuously made in Ireland by a great majority of the population.-     It is ?.lso notoriously involved in tho definition of our War Aims and those of the;limited States.     What in my judgment is even more important is that if a conservative parliament be not secured for Ireland before the next General Election the members returned by very many and perhaps a majority of the Ir-irii constituencies will be avowed advocatesIrish Independence,, and as a&apos; parliamentary assembly they will command attention on quasi constitutional grounds in. a way which has not been possible for any Irish revolutionary party in modern times.   This is in my opinion a grave peril which ought to be averted.II. All the delegates in the Convention except those representing the Ulster minority are ready to recommend a parliamentary constitution for Ireland which 7/ould seem sure to secure conserva-tive administration and,policy there for a life time.     The Ulster minority have also I believe - given a&apos;provisional assent to the establishment of such a Parliament.III. The division which threatens to wreck the chances of settlement arises upon the question of Finance.     The Nationalist majority demand fiscal autonomy but would no doubt take something less, and as I understand would be ready to post-pone the operation of tho financial settlement until after the end of the war.,     I cannot doubt that if they were offered such a conservative parliamentary constitution as they are ready to accept it is a natural sequel that the Irish administration of the future should have its own sources&apos; of revenue, and that as from the appointed day after the termination of the War they should be under its enture control.     Irish control over Irish administration,, taxation, and expenditure, and Imperial control over Imperial administration, taxation, and expenditure - with proper Irish representation and a proper Irish BCjfJtributlGmis I believe a solution which all the Nationalists and even great part of the supporters of Sinn Fxin would be ready to accept.As to the grave alternatives to s settlement I retain the opinions I have repeatedly stoted in previous memoranda.(Signed) . H.F.DUKE.-19/2/1918.

</content>
</cab>
