<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/42/0 images: 319-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel JonesSapient is the Property of His Britannic Majastys Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  February 1918.SECRET.G.T.-3677.THE LABOUR SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending the 20th February, 1918.Summary.Part I: General Remarks.The labour situation is described.Part II: Press Comments.The opinions of the Labour press on the A.S.E. and Man-Power, on War and Peace, on the Labour Party, and on the International Conference are summarised.Part III: District Reports.The man-power question is discussed in all districts, and, on the whole, the opposition to the proposals of the Government appears less keen. The food position is still serious in many areas, and appears to be worst of all in the northern district.Part IV: Disputes.(a.) Invoking a Stoppage of Work. The week has been almost free of strikes, and such as have occurred have not been serious.(b.) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work. The only disputes which might develop into widespread trouble are the demand among the textile operatives in the woollen trade for increased wages and a similar demand on the part of the National Trans-port Workers&apos; Federation on behalf of &apos;bus and tramway men.17I.-General Remarks.Labour Situation.During the past week the unrest in the industrial world has perceptibly continued to abate. There have been no strikes or labour troubles of any importance. Conditions have, in fact, been quieter than during any week since this Report was first instituted. It is unquestionable that this state of affairs is largely due to the firmness of the Government in the matter of its man-power proposals. As was reported last week, the loyal section of the working classes has been encouraged and the disloyal section proportionately disheartened; the latter section, indeed, realises quite definitely that for the time being its power has gone, and at the last meeting of the Clyde Workers&apos; Committee, held on the 16th February, so few members were present that it was impossible to form a quorum. Among the absentees was McManus.The success of the War Aims Committee&apos;s campaign upon the Clyde has been remarkable, and as the Clyde Workers&apos; Committee is regarded by all other shop stewards&apos; committees as the leading institution of the kind in the country the diminu-tion of its influence, due very largely to that campaign, has had an effect out of all proportion to the area in which it was conducted.There are, however, other causes which have assisted in the improvement in the situation. The action taken by the Minister of Food to introduce compulsory rationing in London and in the Home Counties, and the anticipation that this[1100-17] &quot; B
measure will subsequently be extended to the rest of the country, have convinced the working classes that the food problem is at last being tackled upon the right lines. The provision by which the allotted amounts are reckoned, not in weight but in value, has insured against any advantage to the possessor of the longer purse, and the poorer class has not been slow to perceive the equity of the arrangement. Mr. dynes&apos; state-ment in the House of Commons and the proposed sale of tea for 2s, 8d. per lb. have also contributed to create a better feeling on the food question.It cannot be doubted that the increase in wages so widely secured in consequence of the 12^ Per cent- advance has also tended to allay discontent. This fact may. perhaps, be placed to the credit of an arrangement which in general has caused so much trouble and ill-feeling.Finally, the main cause of the existing peaceful situation is perhaps to be found in the course of the Brest-Litovsk peace negotiations, in their result, and in the present chaotic position of the Russian Republic. It has been impressed upon the minds of all thinking men, first, that the German Government is just as much imbued with militarist imperialism as it was before the passing of the famous Reichstag-resolution, and the Russian method of negotiating after disarmament has simply enabled them to carry out their annexationist programme to the letter. It is also beginning to be realised that the principles of the Bolshevist regime have only suc-ceeded in producing a state of disorder in Russia unprecedented in the annals of history, and that the promise of general freedom and equal justice remains unful-filled, oppression being rampant and self-determination of peoples&quot; forcibly prevented by the Bolsheviks themselves.It would be a mistake, however, to conclude that the immediate future is free from difficult problems. The ballot taken by the A.S.E. upon the man-power pro-posals of the Government has resulted in a 9 to 2 majority against those proposals. The reference on which the vote was taken could not have resulted in any accurate indication of how those proposals are, in fact, regarded by the members of the society, nor can the vote which has been cast be considered a vote against the acceptance of the principle that more men must be taken from industry to supply the needs of the Army. The question asked was : &quot; Are you in favour of accepting the Governments new proposals? Are you against acceptance?&quot; In view of the fact that the new-proposals of the Government have been very seriously obscured in the case of the A.S.E., owing to the unfortunate misunderstanding in regard to negotiations, it may probably be concluded that very many of those who voted against acceptance actually considered that vote, not as representing their opinion with regard to the man-power proposals, but as indicating their feelings with regard to the refusal of the Govern-raent to conduct separate negotiations.It is also reported this morning that the negotiations between the Executive of the A.S.E. and the Committee appointed by the other trade unions on the question of a full joint meeting for the consideration of the Government scheme in the absence of Government representatives have fallen through. As far as the A.S.E. is con-cerned, therefore, arrangements on the subject of the man-power appear to be at an absolute deadlock. There can be little doubt that the result of the ballot will be a recrudescence of activity on the part of the revolutionary element on the Clyde and elsewhere. It is also to be anticipated that when a commencement is made to enlist members of the society for the Army local trouble may occur. The whole situation is, however, modified by the fact that men are being discharged owing to the reduction of the munitions programme, and this is having a very sobering effect on those who have thought themselves absolutely indispensable. The Government is in a very strong strategical position, as it will be supported, in the first place, by public-opinion ; in the second, by those unions in protected trades whose hostility to the pretensions of the A.S.E. is marked; and in the third place, by a large number of the members of the society itself who disagree with the attitude adopted by its Executive. There can be little doubt that reflection will convince the Executive of the society of the truth of this statement.II-Press Comments.The A .S...E. and Man-Power.Although there is some falling-off in the amount of criticism devoted to the question of the A.S.E. and man-power, it remains the chief topic of interest,
The &quot; New Statesman &quot; probably represents the view most widely held when it says that, though &quot; the peril of industrial unrest is still grave, there are signs that a serious breach may be avoided.&quot; The great thing is that the matter has been permitted to go to discussion, and time has been given to responsible officials to explain the situation. The &quot; Herald &quot; agrees that the situation still &quot; hangs in the balance &quot;; while the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; is afraid that &quot; the Government may succeed in averting the present strike by some temporary concession.&quot; It holds, however, that the question has passed beyond the original cause of dispute, and now involves the whole issue of peace and war. The &quot; Call &quot; is also very doubtful of the issue, and says it quite appreciates how difficult the Clyde engineers may find it to hold to their original resolution.The papers of the opposite.camp, such as &quot; Justice &quot; and the &quot; British Citizen,&quot; are also very moderate in their comment. The former is sorry that the obscurit)^ into which the question had fallen &quot; owing to the friction between the A.S.E. and kindred trades &quot; is increasing, while the latter admits the Army&apos;s debts to the A.S.E., but holds that the A.S.E. does not realise its own debt to the Army.War and Peace.Less interest is displayed on the score of war aims in last week&apos;s Labour and Socialist press.Mr. Noel Buxton, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; attacks the Labour Party&apos;s memo-randum on war aims, and states that &quot; it-is welcomed by the extremists of the enemy countries and our own country as an expression of imperialist policy.&quot; The &quot; British Citizen &quot; claims, however, that the world of Labour regards the manifesto as largely pacifist, and gives support to Mr. Havelock Wilson&apos;s proposal to debate its terms with Mr. Henderson.&quot; Forward &quot; has a somewhat non-committal article emphasising how important it is to be clear on the subject of war aims, and suggesting that people are &quot; asking whether it is possible to realise those aims by any other means than by the prosecu-tion of the war.&quot; The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; returns to the topic of the Versailles Conference, which is affirmed to have caused as much &quot; indignation and regret &quot; in France and elsewhere as in this country.The Labour Party.The provincial press, both Labour and bourgeois, reports great political activity on the part of local Labour parties.&quot; Forward &quot; comes into line with the &quot; Herald &quot; and those papers which have long been supporting a definite split with the Government. The writer thinks that Labour&apos;s expectations have been falsified, and that it ought &quot; to retrace its steps and start afresh at a point from which it can begin a policy of its own.&quot; Later, however, he declares that he would be content with a Lansdowne Government, though he recognises that Labour should not join it.The &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times &quot; deals with the subject in two places, first from the point of view of the new Act, and later in approval of Mr. Henderson&apos;s speech on the necessity of &quot;a live, national democratic party.&quot; The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; is anxious to secure the Radical pacifist group, and refers with approval to a letter on Radicals and Socialism which Mr. Trevelyan recently contributed to the &quot; Nation.&quot; It thinks that &quot; by wise statesmanship the adherence and support of this invaluable element &quot; may be secured by the Labour Party. In this connection an article on a proposed, restatement of the basis of the I.L.P. which is to be brought forward is significant.The &quot; New Age &quot; admits that the Labour Party is increasing in popularity, but doubts whether it is increasing in power. It has two ineradicable defects: firstly, that it has &quot; neglected to consolidate its basis in the organised industrial movement,&quot; and, secondly, &quot; its hostility to ideas is becoming more and more fixed &quot; the latter criticism, however, appears to refer only to the ideas supported by the &quot; New Age.&quot;The International Conference.This proposal continues to attract attention, though criticism will no doubt remain indefinite until the proposals of the Allied Socialists assume a more concrete character.
The &quot; Cotton Factory Times &quot; devotes its attention to the attitude of Mr. Samuel Gompers and the American Federation of Labour. It thinks that Mr. Gompers must understand that the position of Mr. Appleton and those he represents is by no means that of the British worker in general. The &quot; Call&quot; has a mischievous article entitled &quot; The Capitalist International,&quot; in which it suggests that Russia having become democratic, the Allied Powers determined at all costs to drive her to a separate peace, and states that the Government have an agreement to maintain the capitalist order by its diplomacy &quot; both in Allied and enemy countries.&quot;Food.This subject comes in for the usual amount of comment, though its character is even more marked by moderation.The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; rather unexpectedly admits that the Consumers&apos; Council are making things move, and thinks that they should receive every encouragement and consideration; while Mr. Hyndman in &quot; Justice &quot; continues his weekly descrip-tions of the Councils meetings. He is much more optimistic about the influence which the Council is going to have, though still &quot; convinced that it has been sum-moned because it is too late for us to get anything really effective done.&quot;The section which has burned its boats maintains its violent, if unconvincing, attitude. The &quot; Call,&quot; for example, thinks that Germany is &quot; just as likely to succeed in starving us out&quot; as we to succeed in starving out Germany.There is a good deal of complaint about the complexity of the meat rationing scheme, though other papers use it merely as a peg on which to hang plans of their own. The &quot; Herald &quot; repeats that nothing short of the pooling of all stocks of food can succeed, while the &quot; British Citizen &quot; demands the stoppage of horse-racing and the putting down of dogs.Visits to the Front.This subject attracts the attention of several papers. The &quot; Herald &quot; is content to point out that there is a good deal of opposition to these visits, but the &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times &quot; supports them on the ground that they are likely to prove most effective methods of peace propaganda.III. District Reports.London and South-Eastern.The situation in this district seems at present to be moderately quiet, but there are again signs of considerable agitation among the shop stewards. Resolutions passed by them are no longer .directly unfavourable to the Man-Power Bill, but rather lay emphasis upon the need for negotiations for peace. A feeling is also evident that as the Government are prepared to break their agreements, the engin-eers are entitled to pursue the same course. At one meeting a resolution was passed in favour of a national stoppage of work in order to force the Government to enter upon negotiations, and a further resolution to work no overtime was also carried.The general feeling seems still, however, to be opposed to a strike upon the man-power question, and opinions to this effect are reported both from Woolwich and the E.T.U. -The actual situation as regards food has by no means improved, and the queues last week-end were longer than ever. There is, however, much less active discontent, owing to the general confidence that the rationing scheme will relieve the situation.At Islington the local Food Committee are doing excellent propaganda work by means of leaflets and posters. In these the people are reminded how much better is their position than that in Germany, and are exhorted not to give way to violence, but to set an example to the rest of the nation.South- Western.Some unrest has been reported from this area with regard to the man-power question. The employees of the Whitehead Torpedo Works, WeymoutH, passed a resolution declaring that the objects for which the war was started are now complete, and hence demanding negotiations before a further claim upon the man-power of the country is made.
\West Midlands.Considerable unrest is reported from this area, for the most part due to wages questions.There continues to be much discussion in the Midlands with regard to the recognition of shop stewards. The main reasons which are thought to have actuated the A.S.E. executive in their refusal to accept the agreement entered into by the other unions are-fear of their own rank and file, who were thought to be opposed to accepting those terms/and also anger against Mr. Alan Smith of the Employers&apos; Federation, who is thought to have adopted a high-handed attitude, and to have attempted to force his own plans on the conference without regard to the wishes of the A.S.E.Serious complaints as to the effects of the food shortage are reported. At the Triumph Works, Coventry, the milk shortage is the cause of much distress, and the curtailment of the usual supplies is likely to affect seriously the output of the men employed upon sand blasting, for whom milk appears to be a medical necessity.There is also unrest among men employed on the canals, and there is some fear that a stoppage of work will result, while strikes have actually occurred among tram conductors.The difficulty appears to be chiefly due to the shortage of butchers&apos; meat.Some unrest is reported upon the man-power question, and the Wednesbury branch of the toolmakers have passed a resolution to protest by all means possible against the Man-Power Bill until all dilutees of military age and fitness have been called to the colours. *Yorkshire and East Midlands.The situation in this area seems to be somewhat unsettled, but as regards the man-power question there are signs both that the attitude of the A.S.E. is resented by other unions, and also that they themselves are now regretting the position they have adopted; at a meeting of the A.S.E. in Leeds emphasis was laid upon the fact that the Executive Council only demand that all dilutees shall be combed out before the A.S.E. members themselves, but it is thought exceedingly improbable that any serious strike will take place in this area.At York the Federation of Engineering Trades, at a meeting held on the 18th, made a strong protest against the irresponsible way in which attempts have been made to foment unrest. A delegate from the Clyde was present, and said that the temper of the men was decidedly against any attempt to carry out their notorious resolution.   This resolution was eventually unanimously repudiated.The Sheffield meeting was held on the 10th, at which the workers were encouraged to refuse submission to the Bill. One speaker addressed the meeting in a revolutionary manner, asserting the need of revolt against the capitalists, and urging the workers to follow the example of Russia.The general position in Sheffield is, however, calm, and though it is said that agitation for a General Election exists in some quarters, the attitude of the shop stewards is quiet.There is widespread unrest among the textile workers in the West Riding over a dispute which has arisen out of an application for an advance in wages (see Section IV),In the Nottingham district the system of rationing has relieved the unrest which was prevalent.Considerable discontent has been created by the action of the local police at Richmond in requesting the names of subscribers to the &quot;Herald.&quot; Several branches of the Workers&apos; Union in Yorkshire have in consequence passed resolu-tions protesting against this &quot;police intimidation,&quot; and stigmatising such action as &quot; worse than Prussianism, and savouring of Russia under the Czar.&quot;North-Western.In this area unrest is chiefly due to the man-power proposals, the food situation having apparently improved.At Barrow it is said that the present Bill is rendered necessary solely by the blunders of the War Office in the early part of the war.   Resolutions have also been* The local representative of the Ministry of Munitions is of opinion that the A.S.E. are sirnply &quot; marking- time.&quot;[1100-17] C
passed by the Mersey Federation of Engineering Trades and by the Liverpool boilermakers to resist any further calls for man-power unless the Government adopts the war aims of the Labour Party. In the case of the latter the question of an international conference seems to be uppermost. They have, however, threatened to down tools if further dilution is introduced into their trade.Hostility to dilution is also making itself felt in the Manchester district, where it was responsible for the strikes of last May. The men are nevertheless very strongly of opinion that all dilutees must be taken before skilled men, and the chief investigation officer of the Ministry of Munitions is of the opinion that they will strike immediately the skilled men are called up.The unions affiliated to the Mersey Federation held a conference on the 12th to discuss the housing question, and the revision of the Wages Award; at this conference it was decided to demand the building of 1,000 houses in the district, while upon the wages question a general advance of 10s. is to be asked for.A mass meeting of the Liverpool Vigilance Committed of the N.U.R. an extremist body was held on Sunday, and violent resolutions on the subjects of food and man-power were carried.Northern.Some improvement is reported in this area, and it is said that the only oppo-sition to the Man-Power Bill comes from the younger members of the A.S.E. At Sunderland, on the 17th. an enthusiastic meeting took place, under the auspices of the British Workers&apos; League and the Sailors and Soldiers Fellowship, in favour of carrying on the war to a successful conclusion.Pacifist activities seem, however, to be somewhat prominent, and a meeting of the U.D.C. was held on the 15th protesting against the Defence of the Realm Regulations and urging Democracy to assert itself for peace.The food situation is regarded as worse than ever before, more particularly in regard to meat supplies. Officers of the Ministry of Munitions state that conditions are &quot;appalling,&quot; and refer to cases of families subsisting on dry bread for three weeks.South Wales.The Labour situation in this district appears to be satisfactory at present. It is feared, however, that most members of the A.S.E. have voted against the Govern-ment upon the question of man-power, and from Cardiff it is stated that the question is raising opposition among employers as well as workmen.The food situation, however, appears to have improved considerably, and the Chief Investigation Officer of the Ministry of Munitions thinks that &quot; complaints are dying out.&quot;Scotland.Reports from this area show an improvement in the situation. As far as the man-power question is concerned matters appear to be quiet, and it is thought that the leaders of the pacifist section are not prepared to carry out their former threats. This, perhaps, is due to a decline in the strength of their following, both Clyde Workers&apos; Committee and Industrial Workers of Great Britain, the latter more particularly, having recently lost many members. War aims speakers have been active, and have on the whole been well received in the various important works.At a meeting on the 16th, however, the C.W.C. still expressed a determination to stir up a strike on the Clyde unless the demand for peace and negotiation were conceded. It was stated that Messrs. Beardmore&apos;s, Dalmuir, were taking on only women in the gun shop to replace &quot; the rebels of the Clyde district,&quot; and that &quot; unless action was taken soon the men who had kept the flag flying would all be in the army.&quot; McManus, however, is reported to have said that there must be no strike for the present, and the general view is that the A.S.E. will continue to mark time in the hope that the Government will &quot; comb out &quot; the dilutees before touching skilled men.
IV. Disputes.(a.) Involving a stoppage of work.The general situation is still satisfactory, and the marked improvement which was reported last week has been maintained.The Shipyard Labour Department reports 24 cases of stoppages, 10 of which, involving about 1,000 men, have occurred during the week, and in 22 of these cases work has already been resumed.In the Glasgow area the strike of riveters has extended to two more firms, but the workmen of one of the firms formerly on strike have now resumed work. Another somewhat curious stoppage has occurred at the Ardrossan Dry Dock Co., where 47 shipwrights ceased work on the 12th over a question of overtime. The Shipwrights&apos; Society is making extreme demands, and threaten a general stoppage of other trades than their own under an alleged agreement.The 12  per cent, bonus has again caused two short strikes in the London area, in one case of 240 carpenters and in the other of 70 shipwrights, plasterers, and labourers. In both cases work has been resumed pending an investigation.Eleven of the strikes whioh are in progress are reported from the Newcastle area, Eiveters and drillers have been involved, but for the most part the stoppages have been of short duration, and with one exception work has now been resumed.The Ministry of Munitions reports the settlement of six strikes during the week.Of these the most serious was one at Messrs. Scott and Co., Electrical Engineers, Liverpool. The firm had engaged a discharged soldier, aged 23, as apprentice; the skilled men objected to this on the ground that the man was too old to begin as an apprentice, and that therefore this was really dilution. The General Secretary of the Electrical Trades Union threatened to bring out all men in London, Hull, and Glasgow, and some possibility existed that the boilermakers in Liverpool might come out in sympathy on the question of dilution.   The men, however, resumed work upon the dismissal of the soldier.The strike of glassworkers at Gateshead with regard to piece-work prices still continues, and there is as yet no sign of a settlement.The total number of men involved in strikes which commenced during the past week was almost as many as 5,000; as, however, the average number of days lost was only 1.5 per man, it does not appear that the majority of the strikes were of a very serious nature.The Coal Controller reports eight new stoppages, six of which have already been settled.One of these has occurred at Barnsley, and seems to be in some degree similar to the case of the Yorkshire surfacemen; it is feared that considerable difficulty may arise in this case.The dispute over the wages of coke-oven men at the New Monkton Colliery in Yorkshire, described last week, has since resulted in a stoppage of work. Several small stoppages, which have already ended, occurred in South Wales, and in West Lanarkshire a number of collieries stopped work for one day in connection with the Man-Power Bill.The number of men affected is somewhat considerable, being as many as 11,000; fortu-nately in at least half the cases the duration of stoppages has been short:The War Office Contracts Department has no fresh cases involving stoppages of work to report.It does not appear that any one of the three cases which are mentioned as previously reported has yet been settled. The most serious of these involves some 1,500 women workers at Messrs. Hepburn, Gale, and Ross, Bermondsey, and arises out of a disputed claim to participation in a bonus award.(b.) Not involving a stoppage of work.The Shipyard I^abour Department reports this week 46 fresh cases of dispute, and 159 to which reference has previously been made. A total of 31 cases has been -settled during the week.The number of controversial cases reported from Liverpool, which has this week a total of 42, is somewhat large. The Barrow area seems, however, to be quiet, and there are no cases to report.An arrangement has now been reached with regard to the dispute at Armstrong&apos;s Naval Yard, Newcastle, by which it is agreed that no stoppage of work shall take place; the firm, however, have agreed to file a record of departure from previous practice on the question of dilution of the shipwrights&apos; drillers with fitters&apos; drillers. The dispute at Messrs. Short Bros, is also settled, and it is agreed that the platers&apos; helpers shall receive an advance of 15 per cent.
The Ministry of Munitions reports the settlement of eight disputes with regard to the 12^ per cent, bonus. Several others arising out of the same question are still pending.At Barrow the men employed by the Creighton Construction Co. threatened to strike on the 1st February unless they were guaranteed Sunday labour. The firm is now negotiating on the subject with the Building Labour Committee.The War Office Contracts has five new controversial cases to report.Of these the most important is caused by a movement among the textile operatives to obtain an increase in wages for all engaged in the woollen trade; about 240,000 operatives in Yorkshire, Lancashire, Cheshire, Derbyshire, Leicester, and Nottingham are affected. The application involves an increase of about 24s. per week on pre-war rates, previous advances averaging about 18s. The employers have formally declined to grant an advance, and a twenty-one days&apos; notice has been handejd in by the General Union of Textile Workers. The women workers especially are in a particularly determined state of mind, and it is thought locally that they will not hesitate to stop work if their demands are refused.The Coal Controller reports the possibility of a serious situation with regard to an arbitration on surfacemen&apos;s wages in Yorkshire.At the Wombwell Main Colliery again the surfacemen are, contrary to agreement, refusing to work overtime unless paid a proportionate) part of the war wage for doing so.The possibility of trouble between the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation and the employers, on account of the alleged refusal of the latter to negotiate with regard to an advance of 11. a week to &apos;bus and tramway men, is reported. Strikes are threatened horn all districts, involving in all about 60,000 workpeople. The employers, however, express their willingness to negotiate, and a conference has been held between the Federation and the Ministry of Labour.The Chief Industrial Commissioner reports 220 cases of difference, 77 of which are, however, claims arising out of the 12-1 per cent, bonus.An agreement has been reached with regard to a claim by the boilermakers upon the Shipbuilding Employers&apos; Federation, which extends to workers in various districts; this agreement has been referred to the Ministry of Munitions for sanction.A conference was also held to consider the question of &quot; wet-time &quot; allowances in the building trade, with regard &quot;to which some discontent has recently been expressed.The Committee on Production and the Special Arbitration Tribunal, appointed to consider cases arising out of the 12^ per cent, bonus, heard during the past week 38 cases, 25 in London and 13 in Scotland.IVo important claims under the 12J per cent, bonus were made, the one by a number of unions on behalf of their members in the employ of the London County Council, and the other by building trade operatives employed on the construction of buildings erected under the authority of the Ministry of Munitions, the Air Ministry, War Office, Admiralty, and Office of Works.D. J. SHACKLETON.

</content>
</cab>
