<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/35/1 images: 10-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENT iPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1943.W.P. (43) 101.March 9, 1943.TO BE KEPT  UNDER LOCK AMMD key it is requested that special cars may be taken toensure the secrecy of this documentSECRET. Copy fta.30WAR CABINET.SHIPMENTS TO THE MIDDLE EAST.BY direction of the Prime Minister, the attached telegram from the Ministerof State is circulated to the War Cabinet.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES,Secretary of the War Cabinet.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,March 9, 1943.(No. 513.) ^ March 6, 1943.Following for the Prime Minister from the Minister of State : I am disturbed about allocation of shipping from North America for civilsupplies for the Middle East.2. Civil supplies for this area have already been cut to the bone, as I havealready emphasised in telegrams to London (see my telegram No. 2 Mast to LordLeathers). Civil programme of loadings from North America for Red Sea. area is now 23,400 tons per mensem. 20,000 tons is cereals, of which 8,000 tons are for fighting services.3. The remaining 3,400 tons per mensem of civil supplies (with about1,500 tons per mensem from United Kingdom and 5,750 from India) must cover the irreducible requirements of the entire Middle East for other basic foodstuffs(including Navy, Army and Air Force institutes); chemicals, raw materials and replacement machinery for industries working for the services and essential civilneeds; civil medical supplies; stores to maintain the transport system of theMiddle East, which is now strained very closely to breaking-point; newsprint;clothing; and agricultural machinery. These quantities are the absolute minimafor security in Middle East. Purely civil imports are using only 17 per cent, ofthe tonnage used at this time last year.4. I am assured by all my experts and advisers that, owing to the steadyreduction in the civil import programme during the past year, stocks of the above-mentioned essential civil supplies have already been eaten into to such an extent that this process cannot be continued for more than another month or two withoutgrave danger.5. Egypt is the principal granary of the Middle East (Iraq supplies only some barley). Egypt, more than any other country in the Middle East, can makethe whole area self-supporting. For three months Sir M. Lampson. with suchhelp as I have been able to give him, has been struggling with the egyptian government for the release of Egypt&apos;s surplus rice and cereals. Up to a point wehave succeeded.[25144]
6. The Egyptian Government have already undertaken to release150,000 tons of rice and cereals for export as soon as we can move them; but the fulfilment of this undertaking and our hopes of getting a further 100,000 tons in1943, including a further substantial quantity of rice, are entirely dependent onour being able to assure the Egyptian Government that we shall supply them withnitrates. This means loading 10,000 tons per mensem for six months from Aprilonwards. Such loadings are essential not only as a means of persuading the egyptians to part with the maximum of their rice and cereals surpluses that we need so badly in 1943; they are essential if there are to be any surpluses in 1944and if we are to get them.   Thus the key to the situation is nitrates.7. Realising this, the Middle East Supply Centre, in a series of telegrams to the Ministry of War Transport, pressed hard for shipment of minimumsupplies of nitrates required in 1943. I should mention here that last year, owingto shipping difficulties, we were able to supply Egypt with only about three-quarters of the nitrates which we had undertaken to do our best to supply to them.In December last the Ministry of War Transport undertook to load 10,000 tons monthly throughout 1943. But the special shipping cuts imposed in Januarytorpedoed the programme. Loadings of nitrates ceased. Middle East SupplyCentre then pressed for resumption of loadings from April and, from ForeignOffice telegram No. 358 to Sir M. Lampson, Ministry of War Transport appearto have agreed to this for the month of April, but only at&apos; the expense of an equivalent quantity of cereals and other civil supplies mentioned in paragraphs 2and 3. I regret that I cannot accept this without warning you of the dangerinvolved.8.   There are thus three courses open to us : (a) To accept the cut of 10,000 tons in cereal shipments in April in favourof nitrates. This would get us over the immediate hurdle with theEgyptian Government, but would mean that we should have 10,000 tonsless cereals in the Middle East at the most critical period of all (i.e.late June/(group undecypherable : early July)). The risk of starvation-tion in all countries of the Middle East other than Egypt and Iraqwould then be so great as to be unacceptable.(b) To load in April present cereal programme of 20,000 tons and provideextra shipping for 10,000 tons of nitrates. This course would get usover the immediate hurdle and also cover the critical period from june/July. However at the best this is only a partial solution, andwe shall be faced with a fresh crisis each month as we want to exportcereals and the Egyptians will want an assurance about nitrates before they let us.export them.  I therefore do not recommend this course.(c) To lift nitrates as a definite programme for six months from Aprilonwards.9. The first course being unacceptable and the second&apos; course only atemporary expedient, we are left with the third. This can only be achieved by providing extra shipping or by cutting our existing civil programme still further in order to lift nitrates. A further monthly cut of 10,000 tons in our presentloadings of cereals and other civil supplies for countries served by the Red sea route could, however, have disastrous results. In accepting shipping cuts from november onwards we were already counting on getting out of Egypt the150,000 tons of rice and cereals mentioned in paragraph 6. I have recently hadno alternative but to draw on our slender working stocks here and send two fullcargoes of flour to the Persian Gulf to prevent starvation in Tehran. The cerealposition in Palestine is bad. Now I am receiving pressure to find grain for turkey as well, without any assurance of replacement. The small programmeof civil supplies other than cereals cannot be further reduced as you will have-seen from paragraphs 2 and 3. We arc, in fact, between the devil and the deepsea; we cannot yield a ton out of our already heavily-cut civil programme and.yet must have nitrates to get the cereals we require from Egypt to meet part ofour cereal commitments for the Army (which have hitherto been imported) andour unavoidable grain commitments for civil populations.10. I have suggested to my advisers an alternative, namely, that in theexisting anc. prospective tight shipping position we might well gamble on theMediterranean being opened by, say, July, and postpone the nitrates programme.Their reply to this is that we are already gambling appreciably in respect of ourcereal commitments in May, and that postponement of nitrates shipments from america until, say, June (apart from the fact that they would arrive too late forcertain crops) would inevitably lead to the Egyptian Government shutting down
on cereal exports from Egypt in the very near future, as we eould not hide from them the fact that nitrates shipments had not been made. From paragraph 9you will see that we are already banking on these exports, and we could not takethe grain by force, as stocks are so widely scattered in the hands of cultivatorsand small merchants.11. You know that I appreciate the present necessities of the militarysituation and the United Kingdom import programme, but I believe the onlysolution is to allocate additional shipping for the nitrates programme. If thisis not done we shall be landed with a much greater shipping commitment from may onwards to bring in cereals for the deficit countries in the Middle Eastand for some of the services requirements which would otherwise be met from egypt.12. When I first met Sir M. Lampson in April 1942 I gave him my personalassurance that all figures reflecting the shipping requirements of the middle east would be strictly and absolutely honest figures. I have impressed this on mystaff throughout, and I believe that we have lived up to our word. The representa-tions in this telegram are a reflection of what I believe to be the absolute truth.13. Sir M. Lampson is unfortunately ill, but his Minister and expertadvisers assure me that he would endorse this telegram entirely. He is beingcontinually pressed by the Egyptians to arrange for substantial nitrates deliveries,and is convinced that these are not only economically vital, but are also a primarypolitical issue over which it would be disastrous to let Nahas down.14.   Can you help me ?




</content>
</cab>
