<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/6/14 images: 144-147</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty*s governmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1940.MOST SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (40) 84.TO BE KEPT  UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.ROYAL MARINE  OPERATION.Note by the First Lord of the Admiralty.1. IT will be possible to begin the naval operation at any time at 24 hours&apos;&quot;notice after March 12. At that time there will, as planned, be available 2,000fluvial mines of the naval type, comprising three variants. Thereafter a regularminimum supply of 1,000 per week has been arranged. The detachment of Britishsailors is on the spot, and the material is ready. All local arrangements have beenmade with the French through General Gamelin and Admiral Darlan. Thesemines will, it is believed, affect the river for the first hundred miles belowKarlsruhe. There is always risk in keeping men and peculiar material teed-upso close (4-6 miles) from the enemy&apos;s front, although within the Maginot Line.The river is reported to be in perfect order this month. It will probably bedeepened by the melting of the snows in April, involving some lengthening ofthe mine-tails; also the flow from the tributaries may be temporarily stopped oreven reversed.2. The Air Force will not be ready till the moon is again goodin mid-April. Therefore, unless our hand is forced by events, it would seembetter to wait till then, so as to infest the whole river simultaneously, and thusalso confuse the points of naval departure. By mid-April the Air Force shouldhave a good supply of mines which could be laid every night during the moonin the reaches between Bingen and Coblentz.   All mines of both classes will[20937]
become harmless before reaching the Dutch frontier. Before the end of April it ishoped that a supply of the W. 2 mines for the still-water canals may be ready,and by the May moon the M. mines for the mouths of the rivers flowing intothe Heligoland Bight should be at hand.3. Thus this whole considerable mining campaign could be brought intGbeing on the following timetable:  Day 1. Issue of proclamation reciting the character of the German attacks on the British coasts, shipping, and river mouths, and declaring that hence-forth, (while this continues), the Rhine is a mined and forbidden area, and givingneutrals and civilians twenty-four hours&apos; notice: to desist ;from using it orcrossing it.Day 2. After nightfall, deposit as many mines as possible by both methods,and keep this up night after night. The supply by that time should be such asto keep all methods of discharge fully employed.Day 28. Begin the laying of the W. 2 mines in the still-water canals andriver mouths, thereafter keeping the whole process working, as opportunityserves, until the kind of attacks to which we are being subjected are brought toan end by the enemy, or other results obtained.4.   The decisions in principle required are : (A) Is this method of warfare justified and expedient in presentcircumstances ?(B) Must warning be given beforehand, observing that the first shock of surprise will be lost? However this is not considered decisive, as theobject is to prevent the use of the river and inland waterways ratherthan mere destruction.(C) Should we wait till the Air Force are ready, or begin the naval action as soon as possible after March 12 ?(D) What reprisals, if any, may be expected, observing that there is nonatural or economic feature in France or Great Britain in any waycomparable with the Rhine, except our coastal approaches, which arealready beset.5. It is desirable that the Fifth Sea Lord, who has the operation in charge,should go to Paris on Thursday, concert the details finally, and ascertain there actions of the French Government. From the attitude of M. Daladier, general gamelin and Admiral Darlan it is thought these will be highly favourable.6. If the Cabinet approve provisionally the general policy of this operation,it is suggested that it should be remitted to the Chiefs of Staff for review and advice, all preparations proceeding meanwhile.W. S. C.March 4, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
