<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/22/50 images: 468-500</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. Copy No.     I \)W.P. (42) 120(Also C.O.S (42) 171)March 12, 1942TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 132)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 March 5th, to0700 March 12th,1942[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]cabinet War Room
General.1. The German battleship Tirpitz lias been attacked by naval aircraft tothe west of the Lofoten Islands.H.M.S. Naiad has been torpedoed and sunk in the Eastern Mediterranean.Heavy naval losses have been reported from Java.Shipping losses, which include Dutch ships scuttled at. Java, have been heavy.Home, Northern Waters and North Atlantic.2. On the 4th, the Home Fleet sailed to the northward from Scapa and onthe 5th the Commander-in-Chief reported that an outward-bound convoy to russia had been shadowed by Focke-Wulf aircraft when about 300 miles north-east of iceland (C). In the evening of the 6th H.M. Submarine Seawolf reported anenemy battleship or 8-inch cruiser about 55 miles north-east of Trondheim steeringN.E. Subsequently this ship was identified as the Tirpitz, which was located and attacked with torpedoes by aircraft of the Home Fleet at 0930 on the 9th, about80 miles west of the Lofoten Islands. No hits were claimed and Tirpitz was last seen steering towards Vestf jord.  The Home Fleet has returned to Scapa.On the 5th, H.M. Trawler Cornelian shot down an enemy aircraft offEddystone.During the night 10th/11th H.M. Destroyer Vesper had her engine-roomflooded as the result of a collision with H.M. Destroyer Campbell off Dungeness.Mediterranean.3. On the 16th February H.M. Submarine Thrasher torpedoed a supplyship which was entering Suda Bay and on the 27th H.M. Submarine Upholdersank a 3,000-ton merchant ship to the west of Tripoli (L). She also sank a ship which was probably a French collier. On the 1st March H.M. SubmarineUnbeaten attacked a northbound convoy off Mahedia (Eastern Tunisia) andprobably sank a tanker which may have been the Vichy French P.L.M. 20 (5,417tons).The submarine trot at Malta was twice attacked by enemy aircraft on the 6th.In the second attack H.M. Submarines P. 39 and P. 36 were damaged by near misses and a fuel lighter was sunk.A reinforcement of aircraft for Malta consisting of 15 Spitfires was success-fully flown off from H.M. Aircraft Carriers in the afternoon of the 7th.H.M.S. Naiad was torpedoed and sunk on the evening of the 11th off mersa matruh. Survivors, Avho were picked up by destroyers, are reported to includeRear-Admiral Vian, 33 officers and 548 ratings.An Italian convoy of four ships has arrived in Libya.During the week about 29,000 tons of French shipping has passed throughthe Strait of Gibraltar eastbound and 27,000 tons westbound, under escort.East Indies and Far East.4. Naval losses in the Dutch East Indies include the American 8-inch cruiser Houston and H.M.S. Exeter (reported as having been damaged in theResume of last week), now presumed to have been sunk. In addition H.M.A.S.Perth, H.M.A. Sloop Yarra, H.M. Destroyers Encounter and Stronghold and theAmerican Destroyer Pope, H.M. Gunboat Scorpion, the Boom Defence VesselKoala and the R.F.A. Tanker War Sirdar (5,647 tons) were also sunk, as were a number of auxiliary naval craft, details of which are given in Appendix V.Ucout^o H.M. Ships Erft^pfmrse-, Dance, Dragon,[IL.M.A.S. Hobart and the Dutch cruiserv^w^o Heemskerk have arrived at Colombo. The Dutch cruiser Tromp has arrived atSydney.The Dutch submarine K. 15 sank a Japanese tanker in Bantam Bay (Celebes),and the American Naval Authorities report the sinking of a Japanese destroyerand a large naval tanker and damage to an aircraft carrier and three cruisersduring the week ending the 6th March.
Anti-Submarine Operations.5. Surface craft have attacked U-boats off the Murmansk coast, in theNorth-Western Approaches, off the Liberian coast and north-west of Freemahtle(Australia).Of the seven attacks carried out by aircraft, four were in the West Atlantic.In none of these attacks was there evidence of destruction.Enemy Intelligence.6. The Tirpitz has not yet been located but may be at Narvik. There isno change in the position of other main units.U-Boats.An average of about 40 [J-boats have been operating during the week,including those on outward and homeward passage. The main concentration hascontinued to be in the Western Atlantic and Caribbean Sea. Others have been operating off Freetown, and there appears to be a renewal of activity in thelie bri des-Tlockall-I eel and area.Protection of Seaborne Trade.7. During the week ending the 11th March 887 ships, including 238 allied and 18 neutral, were convoyed. Two cruisers, five anti-aircraft ships, four oceanboarding vessels, 69 destroyers (including 12 American destroyers) and 95 sloopsand corvettes were employed on escort duties.Imports into Great Britain by ships in convoy during the week ending the 7th March totalled 627,000 tons, compared with 420,000 tons during theprevious seven days, and an average of 647,700 tons for the past ten weeks. Ofthe week&apos;s total, 137,000 tons were oils of various grades.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.8. During the week 20 ships have been attacked by U-boats, 16 in theWest Atlantic and West Indies, three in the Freetown area and one in the NorthWestern Approaches; of these, 12 are known or presumed to have been sunk.Seven ships were scuttled to avoid capture in Java, and one ship was mined and sunk off the Norfolk coast.Shipping losses in February, so far reported, of which details are given inAppendix I, were 83 ships and three small craft, totalling 472,228 tons. this includes the loss of 28 tankers, 11 of which were British. The cause and localityof these losses is summarised in the following two tables : Summarised according to locality (tonnage in 1.000 gross tons).Flag.	Atlantic.		Far East and Pacific.		Mediter-ranean.		U.K. Coastal.		Elsewhere.		Total.		No.	Tons.	1 No.  ! Tons.		! No.  &apos; Tons.		No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.British Allied Neutral	20 31 1	120 185 15	17 11	96        4 28		19	1 1	3 5	... ...		42 43 1	238 218 15	52	320	28	124	4	19	2	8			86     471	[23573]
Summarised according to cause (tonnage in 1,000 gross tons).Flag.	By Sub-marine.		By Mine.		By Surface Craft.	By Aircraft.	Other Causes and Cause Unknown.		Total.		No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	1 NTo. i Tons. 1	1 No.  Tons.	No. 3 6	Tons. 11 14	No. 42 43 &apos; 1	Tons. 238 218 15British Allied      ......... Neutral	24 30 1	137 173 15		; it	ll     9 1 2      3	............71 14 I   81 11					55	325	2	17	3 I   12 i	17 I   92	9	25	86	471It will be seen that the bulk of the losses were from U-boat attacks in the atlantic. About 90 per cent, of the total losses from U-boats occurred on the atlantic seaboard of North America and in the Caribbean Sea and its approaches,where 45 ships totalling 291,000 tons (of which 23 were tankers) were sunk. Oneoutward-bound convoy was heavily attacked by U-boats south-east of Newfound-land, but only one ship in homeward-bound convoys ha;? been sunk by U-boatsduring the month.Losses in the Far East and Pacific have mainly been caused by enemy aircraft and surface craft during the final attacks on Singapore. Four ships(17,000 tons) were sunk by Japanese U-boats operating in the Indian Ocean.In addition, the loss of 158,018 tons of shipping was reported in February,although occurring in previous months.British Minelaying.9. On the 9th and 10th March motor launches laid mines off the Flemishcoast. There has been minelaying by aircraft both in the Bay of Biscay area andoff the German North Sea coast, and in the Mediterranean oft&apos; Benghazi andTripoli (L).Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.10. Minelaying by enemy aircraft took place on two nights of the week&quot;offthe East Coast between the Thames Estuary and Flamborough Head, and E-boats were operating on one night off the Norfolk Coast.Thirty-one magnetic, seven acoustic and four moored mines have been destroyed during the week, and the mine totals now are 1,891 magnetic,1,243 acoustic and 1.101 contact.Enemy Merchant Shipping.11. The German tanker Germania (9,851 tons), which had been in theCanaries since November 1940. sailed from Teneriffe on the 5th March.American Intelligence.12. Six battleships are still on the western coast of the United States. Theaircraft carrier Enterprise, with two 8-inch cruisers, has returned to PearlHarbour from the Wake Island area. The Yorktown, with two 8-inch cruisers,is in the vicinity of Canton, Phoenix Island, and the Lexington, with four 8-inch cruisers, is in the Suva area. , One 8-inch cruiser is in Australian waters.Four battleships, two aircraft carriers, five light cruisers, 74 destroyers and 25 submarines will be completed for the Navy by December 1942.
Russo-German Campaign.(An outline map showing operations in Russia is included in this resume as an inset.)Leningrad Sector.13. South-east of Leningrad the Russians claim to have broken through ona wide front on the 3rd March and to have cut the Leningrad-Novgorod railwayas well as that from Chudovo to Novgorod. Any further success here will seriously affect the German positions in the Leningrad area.Lake Ihneu-Ljake Seliger Sector.14. South of Staraya Russa it appears certain that a considerable part of theGerman 16th Army has been surrounded. Despite fierce resistance, the ringround the encircled German divisions is being steadily closed. The Russians havenow established and hold a continuous line west of the encircled area.Central Sector..15. West and south-west, of Rzhev the situation is very confused and hasfluctuated considerably during the past month. It appears, however, that theGerman position may now become serious as a result of a successful russian advance north-east of Gshatsk. After capturing Yukhnov the Russians havemade considerable progress south of Vyasma, and should be in a position to threaten German communications running westwards from that town, especially if the Russians are still holding Dorogobuzb (which was recently captured byparachute troops and partisans).Ukraine.16. The Russians have made local advances north-east of Kursk and east of Kharkov. In the Donets area, Russian attacks have again made some progress towards Dnepropetrovsk and near Bakhmut.Crimea.17. After heavy fighting, the Russians have made local advances in theKerch Peninsula and from Sevastopol.Summary.18. The Russian position has improved during the week. Apart from theencirclement of considerable German forces in the Staraya Russa sector, a promising situation appears to be developing west of Moscow in the area Rzhev-Gshatsk-Vyasma. Farther south, Kursk, Kharkov and Dnepropetrovsk are allthreatened in varying degrees. It is very satisfactory that the Russians shouldcontinue successfully to exert severe pressure on so many sectors, despite difficultweather conditions, at a time when the Germans urgently wish to withdraw forces for rest, refitting and regrouping for the spring.Libya.19. Land activity during the week has been limited to offensive patrollingon both sides, mainly in the Tmimi area. There are indications that the enemyintends to organise a defensive position based on a line running from Wadi Dernato Mekili.Far East.Java.20. Communications with Java were interrupted on the 7th March. Thelast message received from Air Vice-Marshal Malt by stated that he anticipatedthe early capitulation of the Dutch Army, but that orders had been given verballyby the Dutch Commander-in-Chief that any order of capitulation was to be disregarded by local Commanders, who must go on fighting.[23573] &apos; B 2
The Japanese claimed that the Dutch capitulated on the 9th: Smalldetachments may still be continuing local resistance.Nevj Guinea.21. Japanese landings took place during the night. 7th/8th, at Salamoaand Lae. A further landing was reported to have taken place at Finsch Harbouron the 10th.Burma.22. Lt-Gen. The Hon. Sir H. R. L. G. Alexander. K.C.B.. C.S.I.. D.S.O.,M.C., assumed the appointment of G.O.C.. Burma, on 5th March.23. A late report has been received of a successful attack on Dacoits in thearea of Mingaladon on 3rd/4th. The ringleaders were shot and a quantity ofservice arms recovered.Fighting continued in the Pegu area, and our troops inflicted severe casulties on the enemy. During 6th/7th the enemy continued to infiltrate round the left flank of our defences in the Pegu area, and a small Jap-Burman sea-borneexpedition landed at Dedaye in the Rangoon Delta.As a result of increased enemy pressure, and the possibility of our forces in southern Burma being cut off, G.O.C.. Burma, issued orders for the evacuation of Rangoon on the 7th, and for the blowing of all demolitions to begin at1400 hours that day. The demolitions were reported as being successful and extensive.When our troops in the Pegu area began their withdrawal it was foundthat they were surrounded, and it was only after repeated attempts to break outthat they succeeded.At the same time our forces withdrawing up the Rangoon-Prome road foundthat the enemy had succeeded in cutting the road 26 miles north of Rangoon.An attempt to break through on 7th failed, but a second attempt on the morning of 8th by our armoured forces, supported by infantry and field artillery, was successful.   Both sides suffered severe casualties.Advanced Army Headquarters is now at Tharrawaddy. and our withdrawalcontinues, in face of constant enemy air attack.24. During the week one division of the Chinese 5th Army arrived in thePynmana-Yedashe area and is about to move to the Toungoo-Pyu area, with aview to relieving our troops there for action elsewhere.One division of the Chinese 6th Army has almost completed its concentration in the northern area.The bearing of the Chinese troops of the 5th Army has created an excellentimpression.Intelligence.France and the Low Countries.25. Movement out of France to Russia continues. This is presumablycounterbalanced by some westward movement of divisions to rest and refit, but little evidence of this has come to hand. The total number of divisions is now estimated at three in the Low Countries and 27 in France.Norway and Denmark.26. There is a possibility that the German garrisons in both Norway and denmark are being reinforced. Many reports speak of German apprehensions of further British raids; any such reinforcements will doubtless be for defensive purposes. The number of German divisions is still estimated to be eight in norway and two in &quot;Denmark.Balkans.27. There are indications that Turkey is being subjected to Germandiplomatic pressure and to a revival of the war of nerves. There are, however,no signs that Germany intends to take military action against Turkey in the nearfuture.  The strength of her forces in the Balkans remains unchanged.
Far East.28. It is estimated that there are still 29 divisions employed in the area of operations in the South-West Pacific. The principal change has been in the grouping of the Japanese forces operating against Java where there are now estimated to be six divisions and in the New Guinea area.AIR SITUATION.General Review.29. Large forces of night bombers were despatched against Essen. By day,targets in occupied France were attacked by bombers heavily escorted by fighters.Attacks on Malta, aerodromes resulted in damage to a number of our aircraft.United Kingdom.30.   Fighter Command flew 1.850 sorties by day and 264 by night.31. Enemy activity against this country was on a small scale, although on one night 20 aircraft flew overland and carried out a widespread raid. Twobombers were destroyed by our night fighters.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.32. A total of 620 sorties were despatched by Fighter Command on offensive operations, and 34 sorties were flown by Bomber Command.33. Two offensive fighter sweeps over Northern France involved a total of nine squadrons, and a total of 35 squadrons were employed in providing escortand cover for four operations by Bomber Command against targets in occupiedFrance. In combat, Spitfires (six of which are missing) destroyed eight enemy aircraft, probably destroyed one and damaged ten.34. Eight Boston light bombers attacked the ford (Matford) works atPoissy, 10 miles from Paris, which has been manufacturing lorries for the enemy;hits were reported on the lorry park and factory, the roof of which was seen tobe blown off. During this operation bombers (one of which is missing) destroyedan enemy aircraft.35. Further raids were carried out by Bostons against the railway centre at Abbeville, which was crowded with traffic and where bursts were seen in the target area, and on power stations at Comines and Gosnay.Night.36. Bomber Command despatched 637 sorties, compared with 393 last week.The weather on three nights was unfavourable, but, when conditions permitted,heavy attacks were directed against factories in the Ruhr. A total of 653 tonsof bombs and 82,650 incendiaries were released.37. The principal target on three nights was Krupps&apos; Works at Essen, atotal of 336 aircraft dropping 397 tons of 1T.E. bombs (including 37 of 4,000 lbs.)and nearly 78,000 incendiaries. Our bombers included Lancasters, which were taking part for the first time in offensive operations. Fifteen of our aircraft are missing.38. The second of these three attacks on Essen is considered to have beenvery successful. Fires were started in Krupps&apos; Works and oil storage cisternsare believed to have been destroyed. Individual crews reported fires in the target area which looked like whole streets ablaze and a fire of great size near a railway-junction. On the preceding and subsequent night indifferent visibility precludedaccurate identification of the primary targets, and numerous aircraft droppedtheir bombs on alternative objectives.39. Attacks on a smaller scale were made against St. Nazaire, where fires were started in the dock area and on Havre, Ostend and Boulogne.
40. Fighter Command despatched a total of 13 Havocs. Bostons andHurricanes against aerodromes in Holland and Northern France; three enemy aircraft were claimed as damaged in the air.Coastal Operations.41. Coastal Command despatched 331 sorties, of which 00 sorties were onconvoy escorts. Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Command involved 886sorties.42. Bomber Command despatched a total of 34 aircraft to lay sea-mines offLorient and the Frisian Islands.43. Enemy activity by day consisted principally of weather and shippingreconnaissances, the latter being more marked than usual in the Shetland. Orkneyand Faroes areas. Night activity was on a small scale except on the night 8th/9th,when the long-range bomber effort was the greatest recorded in 1942. the activity consisted mainly of anti-shipping operations over the North Sea and east Coast and probably including minelaying. Minelaying was carried out also on the 9th/10th in the Thames Estuary.Mediterranean.Libya and Egypt.44. Our fighters maintained their offensive patrols over the forward areas and also provided protection for shipping. Their activity was. however, curtailedduring the earlier part of the week by bad weather and the waterlogged conditionof the forward landing grounds. A patrol of Kittyhawks made a very successfulinterception over Tobruk of a formation of Ju. 87s, escorted by Macchi fighters,nine of which were destroyed and others damaged without loss to ourselves.Another formation of fighters on shipping protection patrol near Sicli Barrani,destroyed one enemy aircraft, probably destroyed a second and damagedtwo more.45. Small scale night attacks were made on the harbours of Benghazi andTripoli (L) where sea-mines were also dropped. One ship at Benghazi was destroyed and a near miss was obtained on another. A large concentration of enemy aircraft on Martuba landing ground was attacked on two nights by hurricanes and Blenheims and transport, vehicles on the Derna road were bombed.46. Enemy operations were mainly directed against&apos;aerodromes at Fuka;Mersa Matruh and Gambut, for which attacks single-engined fighter-bombers were largely employed. During one raid one of our aircraft was shot down, and seven others were damaged on the ground; otherwise the damage caused wasnot considerable.   Railways and troops in the forward area were also attacked.Malta.47. The aerodromes of Luqa, Hal Far and Takali were repeatedly bombedduring the week, the heaviest attack taking place on the 8th and was carriedout by approximately 115 aircraft, of which it is estimated some 35 were Ju. 88s.The submarine base at Luqa and the harbour at Valetta were attacked on several occasions. Continuous intruder operations were carried out on every night ofthe week, the maximum number of aircraft employed on any one night being25 Ju. 88s.48. Considerable damage was caused to the Tigne Barracks (Valetta) andto R.A.F. buildings, while the aerodromes were extensively cratered. Nine of our aircraft were destroyed on the ground and 21 others were damaged.49. Hurricanes, fighting against heavy odds, continued to inflict casulties on the attackers. On the 10th, Spitfires, which had recently arrived as reinforce-ments, successfully co-operated for the first time. The following day 20 Ju. 88sand Me. 109s were intercepted approaching the Island, and the Ju. 88s turnedback.
Greece and Dodecanese.50. Piraeus Harbour and naval workshops on Leros Island were bombed by Wellingtons.Sea Communications.51. Beau forts from Libya made a torpedo attack on an enemy convoy of four merchant vessels with naval escort N.E. of Misurata, One large ship was set on fire and hits were also obtained on ci cru lsgi&apos; &amp; nd a destroyer. a striking force of Wellingtons was despatched, but only three of them located the convoy, and a possible hit was made on one ship.52. Albacores from Malta made a probable hit on a south-bound merchant vessel of 8,000 tons oft&apos; Pantellaria.Russia.53. There has been no marked change in the air situation ou the russian front.Burma.54. Our lighters provided continuous protection to troops and shippingduring the withdrawal from Rangoon and carried out sweeps in support of our ground forces in the forward area.55. Japanese aircraft destroyed two of our aircraft on the ground at atemporary aerodrome and are reported to have heavily attacked an ArmyDivisional H.Q. in the Hlegu area (20 miles X.X.E. of Rangoon).Netherlands East Indies.56. Enemy attacks, which were directed principally against aerodromes,were maintained on a heavy scale, at least 150 aircraft operating on the 3rd.On the 5th, the last Allied fighters were destroyed iii repulsing an attack north of Bandoeng.Australia.57. Darwin aerodrome was machine-gunned by eight Japanese fighters :one Hudson was destroyed on the ground.Pacific Zone.58. Hudsons bombed Gasmata and Koepang (jews Britain): at the formerbuildings and the runway were hit and a flying-boat on the water was set on fire.59. Hudsons hit an 8.000-ton transport at Salamoa (jews Guinea) and claimed near misses on others. Eight Fortresses dropped bombs on enemy shipping in the harbour; preliminary reports claim four transports were set on fire, another beached and that a sixth was sinking.60. Four attacks were made by Japanese bombers on Port Moresbyaerodrome; the resultant damage was slight. Bulolo (100 miles north of port Moresby) was also raided, but results are not known.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.61.   Bombing has again been on a very small scale.During daylight on 5th March three people were killed at Freshwater, isle of Wight, and a house wrecked.On the night of 8th/9th there was scattered bombing along the North-Eastand East coasts. A few houses were damaged and one person was killed atLowestof t.Casualties.62. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 on llth Marchare four killed and two seriously injured.
APPENDIX J.Date,Feb. 1Feb. 2Feb. 3Feb. 4Feb. 4Feb. 4Feb. 4Feb. 6Feb. 6Feb. 6Feb. 7Feb. 8Feb. 9SECTION A. Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages lost by enemy action,during the month of February 1942.(Note. Tonnages are gross and vessels are of S.S, Cargo type unless otherwise stated.)By Submarine.Name and Tonnage.Tacoma Star       ...   7,924S/S TankerW. L. Steed 6,182M/Y CargoAmerikaland 15,355M/Y Cargo Silvcray    4,535M/Y TankerMonisolite 11,309S/S TankerIndia Arrow 8,327San Gil      ......3.598M/Y Cargo Opawa ... 10,354S/S TankerChina Arrow 8,403Halcyon     ...      ... 3,531Empire Sun .Ocean Venture... 6,9526,500Empire Fusilier     ... 5,408Nationality.BritishAmerican ...SwedishBritishBritishAmerican ...PanamanianBritishAmerican ...PanamanianBritishBritishBritishCargo.From Refrigerated I Buenosand general ] AiresI PortEverglades; Baltimore ...General    ... Liverpool ...Crude oil       GuiriaII CorpusClsrisii; Sanla MartaRefrigerated Lyttleton ...and general 1Beaumont ..Halifax    ...Portland(Me.)VancouverBallast TynoTo-Liverpool ..New York&apos; ..Halifax ..New York ..PhiladelphiaHalifax andU.K. viaPanamaNew York- ..Denlerara ..11 a m p to nRoads andILK.TampaI low sunk.I I n Convoy!    or not.Torpedo... not torpedo...j not torpedo...; not torpedo...! NotITorpedo..., No!Torpedo ... not torpedo...1 not torpedo...! not torpedo... NotGunned ...! not torpedo..,] not torpedo... not torpedo... YesPosition.300 miles E. of New-port News100 miles E.S.E. ofDataware Bay105 miles E.S.E. ofHampton RoadsE.N.E. of Cape Sable360 miles E. of CapeIiatteras130 miles E.N.E. ofNorfolk, Virginia55 miles S. of Dela-ware Bay400 miles&quot; S.S.E. ofHalifaxU.S. Atlantic Coast300 miles E.N.E. ofBermuda55   miles   S.W.   ofHalifax70 miles E. bv N. ofNorfolk (Yii\)260 miles S.E. of cape RaceFate of Crew and Remarks.Crew presumed lost.Crew 38. 3 survivors. 2 deadpicked up.Crew 29.   11 landed U.S.A.,some others landed Aruba.41 snved, 2 killed.22 saved.12 saved, 26 missing.Crew 41.    2 lost. 4 wounded.2 known to he lost.Crew 37.   No casualties.37 saved, 3 lost, 2 wounded.54 saved, 4 killed, 7 missing,including some service per-sonnel.14 saved, 30 missing, 1 dead.38 saved, 8 lost, 1 died.
Date.OSm Fob. 10-Ico- Feb. 10Feb. 11Feb. 13Feb. 14Feb. 15Feb. 15Feb. 15&apos; Feb. 16Feb. 16Feb. 16Feb. 16Feb. 16Feb. 18Feb. 19Feb. 19Feb. 20Feb. 20Feb. 20Name and tonnage.Nationality.Cargo.From How-Sunk.I M.Y. TankerVictoiite 11,410j M/V Cargo Heina ... 4,028Blink2,701M.Y. CargoDerrymore 4,799Kamaning   ...      ... 2,076Johannc Jusiescn ... 4,681Meropi        ...      ... 4,181Buarque      ...       ... 5,152S/S TankerOrangestad 2,396S/S TankerSan Nicolas 2,391S/S Tanker Tia Juana 2,395S/S Tanker Bolivar ... 2,651S/S Tanker Monagus   2,650Olinda        ...      ... 4,053M/V CargoEmpire Seal 7,965S/S TankerPan Massachusetts 8,201Nordvangen......2,400BritishNorwegian..Norwegian..BritishBritishBritishGreekBrazilian ..BritishBritishBritishBallast     ... Halifax    ..General    ... New York ..Phosphates   CharlestonSingapore ..Rangoon  ..Akyab(Burma)LondonLas PiedrasLiverpool ...Halifax andU.K.GeneralFeeder Ser-Singaporevia ColomboCochin(India)Halifax    ...Torpedo...Torpedo...Torpedo...-.Torpedo...TorpedoandgunnedTorpedo...vicej Feeder Ser- j Maraeaibj   viceI Feeder Ser- , MaracaibviceVenezuelan   Coasting  ...Venezuelan j Feeder Ser- I Maraeaibo..;   viceBrazilian ...        ... Pcrriarhbucitorpedo.;Rio Janeiro   New York ... Torpedo..Torpedo..Aruba ... Torpedo..Aruba       ... Torpedo..Torpedo .j Torpedo..British     ... Special Ser-  New York .viceAmerican ... ... Texas CityArubaNew York ...GlusgowNorwegianParamaribo   Trinidad   ...Scottish StarDel Plata    ..7,224 I British     ...1 Mixed gen-   Londoneral5,127American ..BuenosBuenosA iresNew OrleansAiresTorpedoeiandgunnedTorpedo..Torpedo:.TorpediTorpcdiIn convoy or not.Not:YesNotNotNotNotNotNotNotNotNotNutNotNotNotNotNotPosition.Fate of Crew and Remarks.410 miles E. by N. of cape llatteras4-15   miles   W.   of bloody Foreland150 miles E. of CapeHatteras70   miles   N.W.   ofBatavia30   miles   N.E.   ofTriucomali100  miles   N.W. of cape Coinorin50   miles   S.E.   ofHalifaxOff Hampton Roads,VirginiaAt anchor off  SanNicolas, ArubaGulf of Venezuela ...Gulf of Venezuela ...Gulf of Venezuela ...Gull&apos; of Venezuela ...135 miles N. by E. of cape 1 latteras35 miles   E.S.E. of cape Sable130   miles   N.    ofMiami, FloridaCaribbean SeaG50  miles   N.E.  of \Georgetown, British(1 uiana60   miles   N.W.  ofMartiniqueNo information.Crew saved.Crew 30.   6 saved, 20 lost,4 missing,Crew saved.3 killed, 4 wounded.1 lost,14 saved.Crew   and   passengers   85.1 killed, 1 missing.No casualties reported.1- 22 saved, 26 missing.jNo information.No information.Crew saved.Crew saved.18 saved.   2 lost.   20 believedlost.No information.Crew about 73.    09 saved.4 missing.52 saved.TO
1 Date,    i      Name and Tonnage. I		Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	How sunk.	In Convoy or not.	Position.	Fate of Crew and Remarks.Feb. 20 ... Feb. 21 ... Feb. 21 ... Feb. 21 ... Feb. 22 ... Feb. 22 ... Feb. 22 ... Feb. 22 ... Feb. 22 ... Feb. 23 ... Feb. 23 ... Feb. 23 ... Feb..23 ... Feb. 23 ... Feb. 23 ... Feb. 25 ... Feb. 25 ... Feb. 26 ... Feb. 27 ...	Bhhna        ......5,280 S/S Tanker J, N. Pew 9,033 M/V Tanker Circe Shell 8,207 M/V Tanker Kongsgaarcl 9,407 George L. Torian   ... 1,754 M/V Tanker Adellen 7,984 S/S Tanker Cities Service Empire 8,103 M/V Cargo Sama  ... 1,799 S/S Tanker W. D. Anderson 10,227 Lennox       ...       ... 1,904 West Zeda   ......5,658 M/V Tanker Thalia... 8,329 Lithue        ......7,001 S/S Tanker Inverarder 5,578 M/V Tanker Eidanger 9,432 S/S Tanker La Carriers 5,685 M/V Tanker Esso Copenhagen 9,245 Mafore       ...      ... 8,215 MacQregor......2,498 a.	British American ... British Norwegian... British British American ... Norwegian... American ... British American ... Panamanian American ... Britisli Norwegian... British Panamanian American ... British	Gunnies and general Ballast    ... Presumed ballast Ballast    ... Ballast    ... Ballast    ... Ballast    ... Coal	Rangoon  ... A rub a Glasgow   ... Puerto la Cruz Paramaribo Newport   ... Port Arthur Cardiff Corpus Christi Paramaribo Mombasa ... New York ... New York ... London-derrv Belfast     ... New York ... Aruba Cruz Grande Loch Ewe...	Durban and W. Indies Cliristobal... Curacao (diverted Trinidad) Aruba Trinidad   ... Trinidad   ... Philadelphia St. Johns, N.B. Philadelphia Trinidad   ... Trinidad   ... Aruba Middle Fast Trinidad   ... Mobile Trinidad   ... Buenos Aires Baltimore ... Tampa	Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo and gunned Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo and gunned Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Gunned...	Not Not Not Not Not Yes Not Yes Not Not Not Not Not Not      ... Not Not Not Not Not	250 miles \V. of (&apos;, Comorin 225 miles W. of Aruba 40   miles   N.W.   of Trinidad Off    West    Point, Curacao 130  miles   S.E.  of Trinidad 500 miles E. of New-foundland, approx. Off   U.S.    Atlantic Coast 500 miles E. of New-foiindland, approx. Off Florida...... 160 miles S.S.E. of Trinidad 150 miles N. by W. of Georgetown, British Guiana 100 miles from Aruba 240 miles S.S.W. of Ponce, Puerto Rico 420 miles S.S.E. of St. John&apos;s (N.F.) 420 miles S.S.E. of St. John&apos;s (N.F.) Off   Ponce.   Puerto Rico G50 miles N.E. of Georgetown, British Guiana 30 miles S.E. of Cape Hatteras Off Santo Domingo...	70 saved. No information. Crew 57, 1 missing. Crew 4G, 8 saved. 4 saved. 12 saved. 29 saved, 7 killed, 4 missing. 14 crew, 5 passengers, saved. Crew 35, 1 saved. 18 saved, 6 wounded, 2 miss-ing. No information. 1 killed, rest saved. No information. Crew saved. Crew saved. 26 saved, 1 lost, 13 missing. Crew saved. Crew saved. 30 saved, 5 wounded, 1 miss-
By Submarine.S     Bate.                *ame and m               i             ionnage. CO		! Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	How sunk.	In Convoy or not.	Position.           Fate of Crew and Remarks.	Feb. 27 ... Feb. 27 ... Feb. 28 ... Feb. 28 ...	Bayou        ......2,605 S/S Tanker R. P. Resor 7,451 Everasma   ...      ... 3,644 M/V Cargo Leif     ... 1,582	Panamanian American ... Lat. Norwegian...	Manganese Ore	Bio Janeiro Houston   ... Hampton Roads New York ...	Canada Fall River... Rio Janeiro Ciudad Trujillo	Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo... Torpedo...	Not Not Not Not	__________ Near Paramaribo   ... Off New Jersey coast 765 miles E. by N. of Martinique Off Atlantic coast ...	1 survivor. Crew 43; 2 saved. 15 saved. 10 saved, 15 missing, 1 be-relieved drowned.By Mine.									Feb. 16 ... Feb. 21 ...	S/S Tanker E. H. Blum 11,615 Atlanticos......    5,446	American ... Greek	Grain	Philadelphia St. John&apos;s (N.B.)	London	M. Prob.	Not Yes	Off Cape Hatteras ... Barrow Deep	Crew saved. Crew 41.   1 missing.By Surface Craft.AboutFeb. 26AboutFeb. 26o AboutFeb. 26City of Manchester    8,917Prominent ...      ...    2,232M/V Cargo Tomohon    983BritishNorwegian.DutchProbablyBallastRaider orWarshipRaider orWarshipRaider orWarshipSouth of Tjilstjap,Dutch E. IndiesSouth of Tjilstjap,Dutch E. IndiesSouth of Tjilstjap,Dutch E. Indies2 killed, 8 wounded, 127 saved.No information.No information.
by aircraft.Date.Name and Tonnage.M/V Cargo 4,433Norah MatterKatong       ...      ... 1,461S/S Tanker Pinna ... 6,121Loch Banna.....4,958Corland      ......3,431S/S Passenger 10,909Empress of AsiaSubadar     ...      ...  5,424Clan Chattan.262M/V Cargo 7,798Bowallan CastleM/V TankerBrtfis/i Motorist 6,891Zealandia    ...      ... 6,683Neptuna      ...      ... 5,952Manna Loa ...      ... 5,436Florence D.......2,638M/V CargoDon Isidooro 3,261Hawne        ......1,360M/V Cargo Bintang... 2,825Nationality.BritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishAmericanAmericanAmericanBritishBritishCargo.CoalErom-BlvthePalembamSourabaya.AlexandriaAlexandriaTo-LondonBataviaTobrukTobrnkHow sunk.Tn convoy or not.YesYesYesPosition.Off Sumatra...Off Sumatra...Singapore StraitOff Sumatra...Off llumber ...SingaporeApproachesDutch East IndiesWaters168 miles North ofBenghazi240  miles   Hast  ofMaltaPort Darwin...Port Darwin...Port Dai win...Port D&amp;s-win......Dutch  East  IndiesWatersNear Darwin...25   miles   N.E.   ofBardia50 miles E. of BardiaFate of Crew and Remarks.No information.No information.16 killed, 7 wounded.No information.No casualties.iSomo casualties.No information.Crew saved.Crew saved.2 killed.No casualties reported.10 killed, 5 missing,so casualties reported.3 killed.73 saved.20 saved.27 saved.
By other Causes or Cause unknown.Date.Name and tonnage.Hua TongM/Y Cargo Hhu295254S/S TankerSemiramis 5,792S/S Tanker Iris     ...  3,887Lighter KilatTaUhybins ...NationalityBritishBritishDutehDutch221 I Dutch. 10,254 ! BritishSanta Fc1,543M/V CargoDon Estaban  1,610S/S PassengerSurigao    790PanamanianAmerican ...American ...Cargo.From To-How sunk.In convoy or not.Position.i Fate of Crew and Remarks.ISingaporeSingaporePalembang RiverPalembang RiverPladjoeSingaporeSaigonE. IndiesE. IndiesPresumed captured.Presumed captured.! Scuttled to avoid capture.; Possibly scuttled   to avoidcapture.Sunk to avoid capture.Vessel unable to leave owingto desertion of Chinese crew.Presumed captured..1 Captured by Japanese.No information.No information.
Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages lost by enemy action reported during February 1942,but relating to January 1942, or previous.(Note.-Tonnages are gross and vessels are of s.s. Cargo type unless otherwise stated.)By Submarine.Date.	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From-	To-	How Sunk.	In Convoy or not.	Position.	Fate of Crew and Remarks.1940 Sept. 30 ... 1941 Mar. 17 ... Mar. 24 ... June 9   ... 1642 Jan. 12 ... Jan 22  ... Jan. 26  ... Jan. 31   ...	Samala      ......5,390 Medjcrda    ......4,380 Koranton     ...      ... 6,695 M/V Cargo Silver[laljn 6,373 M/V Cargo Yngaren   5,246 Gandia       ......9,626 Traveller     ......3,963 M/V Tanker San Arcadia 7,419	British British     ... British British Swedish Belgian British     . . British	... Copra   and Manganese Ore General General Gas    and lubricating cat-ing Oils	Kingston (Ja.) Pepel Halifax   ... Freetown ... Bombay   ... Mersey Norfolk (Va.) Houston   ...	Liverpool ... Tees Loch Ewe... Clyde 1-1 nil (via Halifax) St. John&apos;s (N.B.) Halifax    ... Mersev (via Halifax)	Presumed Torpedoed Presumed Torpedoed Presumed Torpedoed Presumed Torpedoed Torpedoed Torpedoed Presumed Torpedoed Torpedoed	Not Not Not Not Not  .   ... Not Not Not	North Atlantic North Atlantic North Atlantic North Atlantic 460 miles S.S.W. of Iceland 420 miles S. of Cape Race North Atlantic 400 miles S. of Hnli-fax	Arbitration award. J.A.C. award. Arbitration award. Arbitration award. 2 survivors picked up after 30 days on a raft. Crew 79.   14 saved, 65 lost. Presumed lost.  No survivors. 9 saved.LOSSES IN THE PACIFIC.British.Indian Ocean 1 ship      ...............      2,498British Diala (8,106 gross tons) previously shown as sunk is now known to be afloat, but damaged.
Date.Name and Tonnage.      \ Nationality, i     Cargo. From- To-1941.Mar. 13 ... M/V CargoBuenos Aires 5,646May 3-4... Steam Barge Walton      82Aug.  8 ... Steam TrawlerOcean Victor    202How sunk.In convoy or not.SwedishBritishBritishWishing PresumedGrounds     bombedPosition.LiverpoolLiverpoolIceland FishingGroundsFate of Crew and Remarks.Now declared  constructive;total loss.Now declared constructive;total loss.Crew of about 10 lost. J.A.C.award.LOSSES IN PACIFIC.Allied.Manila 1 ship...............      5.33-1Two British ships of 2,053 gross tons, previously shown as sunk in the Pacific as &quot; no exact position,&quot; must lie deleted, as these ships are now known to have been small commissioned ships.By other Causes or Cause Unknown.1939.Nov. 17  ... ParkLill1940.Oct. 24   ..Dec. 14 ..MaiinaKyleglen...    500... 5,389... 3,670BritishBritishBritishCoalBlvthKirkwallJamaica ... Liverpool ... C.lOban Baltimore ... C.U...J North Sea... North Atlantic...: North AtlanticArbitration award.Arbitration award.J.A.C. award.LOSSKS IN PACIFIC.British.Ships under charter to Japanese since May  or.I line 1911 now presumed lout by confiscation:  7 ships       ............      37.196Ships under embargo by Japanese in Chinese portsnow presumed lost b\ confiscation: 8 ships       ............      23,397In addition to the above, 7 Russian ships of 25,012 gross terns were seized in German Baltic ports following the German declaration of war on Russia.ZJ1
SECTION B. Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of 500 gross tons and over damaged by enemy action during the month of February 1942.   Vessels suffering superficial or minor damage are excluded, and vessels are ofS/S Cargo type unless otherwise stated.Date.	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	Cause.	In 011          Position. voy or not.		Extent of Damage.	Casualties lo Crew. Remarks.Feb. 2 Feb. 6 Feb. 9 Feb. 10 Feb. 13 Feb. 16 Feb. 16 Feb. 18 Feb. 18 Feb. 22	M/V Tanker Corilla 8,096 Blush Rose      ...   645 M/V Tanker Anna Knudson  9,057 Lieutenant Robert Mory 3,176 Clan Campbell ...   7,255 S/S Tanker Pedemales 4,317 S/S Tanker Arkansas 6,452 Mokihana         ... 7,460 S/S Tanker British Consul 6,940 S/S Tanker -  Republic 5,287	Dutch British Norwegian... British British American ... American ... British American ...	Spirit Ballast ... Ballast ... Ballast ... Feeder Service Govt. stores and coin Loading...	Curacao Dublin     ... Seydisfjord Southamp-ton Baltimore... Freetown ... Philadelphia	UK. Swansea   ... Loch Ewe Barry Table Bay and Suez Trinidad   ... Houston   ...	S/M A/C      ... S/M     ... A/C A/C S/M S/M     ... S/M     ... S/M S/M	_______ Not... Not... Not... Yes... Yes... Not...	80   miles   S.E. of Halifax 3 miles S. of St. Amie&apos;s Head 130milesW.N.W. Butt of Lewis 5   miles W.  of Trevose Head E. Mediterranean At anchor off San Nicolas, Aruba Alongside wharf, Oranjest a d, Aruba Trinidad anchor-age Trinidad anchor-age Off Miami Beach	Returned Halifax damaged; 3,000 tons spirit lost Making water in engine-room and beached. Later refloated and arrived Car-diff. Arrived Kames Bay in tow with engine-room damage Badly damaged amidships and beached. Later ar-rived Penzance Damage not stated. Vessel arrived Alexandria. Re-pairs to be completed 12th March Damage not stated but vessel beached Damage not stated. Vessel still afloat and moved to anchorage Damage not stated, but in no danger of sinking Damage to starboard side of Nos. 5 and 6 tanks and pump room Torpedoed. Damage not stated	No casualties re-ported. No disunities. No casualties. 34 crew; 2 killed, 5 wounded. No casualties re-ported. No casualties re-ported. No casualties re-ported. No casualties re-porfced. No casualties. 28 saved, 5 rniss-ing.
Name and tonnage.Nationality.Feb. 22 I Enseigne    MarieSt. Germain 3,139M/V Tanker liars 8,888S/S TankerEmpire Celt 8,032Harboe Jensen ... 1,862Thyra     ......1,796BritishBritishBritishNorwegianSwedish   .BallastBallastTimberFrom To-London    ... BlytheTrinidad   ... HalifaxGreenock ...1 New YorkMiddles-b roughLondonj   Cause.A/CS/MS/MA/CM.I   InCon-yoy ornot.I Yes.... Not...: Yes...Position.Extent of damage.Off Yarmouth ...25 miles Southof Halifax420 miles S.S.E.of   St,   John&apos;s(N.F.)Tobruk ...YesOff YarmouthArrived Yarmouth with 8 ft.hole in starboard sideAfloat and  burning afterhalf towed into HalifaxProceeded under own powerto 35 miles off St. Jolm&apos;sand  broke in two, bothparts afloat and salvableEngine-room holed.    ShipbeachedBeached.   After hold belowwater line.   Survey pro-ceedingCasualties to crew and otherRemarks.No casualties.2    survivors.since died.47 saved, 0 missing.No casualties24 saved.This report does not include details of damage inflicted on shipping in the Far East, reports of which are incomplete.
APPENDIX II.Total Losses by Enemy Action and Marine Causes of Merchant Ships, including Tankers, other than Merchant Ships Commissioned tor naval service.   (Including vessels of all tonnages for losses by enemy action and vessels of 100 gross tons and over for losses by Marine Causes.)A. British, A Wed and Neutral Losses.Months.	Total.		British.		Allied.		Neutral.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons. i______	No.	Gross Tons.	No.           Gross Tons.	1939 September-December (4 months) ... 1940-January-March (3 months)        ...... April-June (3 months)     ......... July-September (3 months)       ...... October-December (3 months)   ...... 1941-January February March         ............... April.........      ...      ...... May.................. June          ... -    ........s.-July.................. August       ......      ......... September   ... October November December 1942-Januar3T February	317 297 313 348 365 92 138 154 167 138 122 58 64 109 67 01 152 121 107	929,000 800,000 1,038,000 1,332,000 1,337,000 38S.000 464,000 508,000 662,000 530,000 451,000 144,000 153,000 338,000 233,000 175,000 432,000 477,000 550,000	158 111 153 211 255 54 98 101 84 90 G5 43 42 75 41 38 90 58 47	498,000 352,000 109,000 925,000 981,000 222,000 359,000 374,000 304,000 392,000 280,000 108,000 105,000 254,000 100,000 117,000 234,000 200,000 203,000	17 13 GO 50 00 29 21 37 G9 21 35 0 10 11 17 10 50 55 59	90,000 30,000 326,000 211,000 234,000 153,000 75,000 147,000 248,001) 100,000 143,000 24,000 3-1,000 46,000 58,000 32,000 107,000 259,000 272,000	______ 142 173 94 81 50 9 10 10 14 18 22 9 12 20 9 13 12 8 1	341,000 412,000 243,000 190,000 122,000 13,000 30,000 47,000 50,000 38,000 28,000 12,000 14,000 38,000 15,000 20,000 31,000 18,000 15,000	3,190           11,007,000		1,820	6,657,000	651	2,061,000	719	1,689,000
B. Losses analysed by Cause.hoOSOiOSMonths.1939-September-December(4 months)1940-January-March ...(3 months)April-June(3 months)July-September...(3 months)October-December(3 months)1941-JanuaryFebruaryMarchA prilMayJuneJulyAugustSeptemberOctober  ..NovemberDecember1942-t)    JanuarytoFebruaryEnemy Action.Total.Total.Tons.929.000800,0001,038,0001,332,0001,337,000388,000464,000568,000062,000536,000451,000144,000153,00033S,000233,000175,000432,000477,000550,000Tons.743,000524,000935,0001,241,0001,145,000313,000300,000535,000624,000501,000412,000119,000125,000278,000205,000104,000300,000356,000172.000Submarine.11,007,0009,301,000Tons.421,000291,000346,000770,000689,000125,000172.000234,000240,000331,000287,00092,00080,000205,000152,00002,000102,000288,000325.0005,212,000Mine.Tons.258.000109,000151,0005-1,000133,00017,00010,00023,00025,00023,00014,0009,0001,00015,00014,0002,00058,00010,00017,(100,012,000SurfaceCraft.Tons.57,00074,000220,000219,00094,00082,000103,00018,00015,00018,0006,00025.001115.0003,000J 7,0006.00012.0001,083,0Aircraft.Tons.3,00033,000250,000179,00080,00077.00090,000113,000291,000132,00066,0009,00019,00041.00035,00023.00023,00043,00003.000OtherCauses orCauseun known.Total.Marine Fiisk.Overdue,presumed lost.41,012.0UI)Tons.4,00031,000111.00012,00015.0002,00017,00027,0003,0002,0001,000180,00012,00025,000442,000Tons.180,000276,000103,000&quot; 91,000192,00075,000104,00033,00038,00035,00039,00025,00028,00000,00028,00071.00003,000.21,00078,0001,646,000Tons.12,00044,0008,00025,00025,0008,00040,00010,00010,00024,0002,0001,0001,000S,00024,00018,00024,00044,000OtherCausesf33 1000Tons.174,000232,00095,00006,000167,00007,00058,00023.0002S.00035,00015,00023,00027,00059,00020,00047,00045,00097,00034,0001,312,000toSome of these losses may eventually bo held to be due to enemy action.f Including losses due to vessels running on BritishIS5
Appendix III (1) will be inserted in a subsequent Resume.(2) Merchant Ships (100 gross tons and over) under construction in the UnitedKingdom as at 28th February, 4942.Tankers.			Others.		Xo.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.Coasting ships and colliers ... Other ships Total    .........	S 31	5,000          14 314,000         172*		22,000 910,000	45	319,000        1S6		932,000* Including 9 vessels (5,000 gross tons) of Merchant type intended for Naval use. In addition the following merchant ships are on order in the United Kingdom and abroad : 					Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.United Kingdom Canada and United States   ... Total    .........	17	109,000	80f 72i	305,000 518,000	17	109,000	152	823,000j Including 9 vessels (5,000 gross tons) building for the Navy.i Some of these vessels are already under construction but details are not available.APPENDIX IY.Enemy Merchant Ship Losses as assessed to 15th February, 1942.Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously7 Damaged.		Damaged.		Total.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German Italian Other enemy ships  and ships useful to enemy-Total     ......	897 412 113	1,721,294 1,760,273 202,689	113 76 16	309,603 354,868 43,706	181 84 12	598,889 420,984 48,824	691 572 141	2,030,086 2,530,125 295,219	922	3,684,256	205	708,477	277	1,068,697	1,404	5,461,430This table does not include losses inflicted on the enemy by our russian allies, which are estimated at about 556,000 gross tons sunk : nor does it include losses inflicted on Japanese shipping in the Far East and Pacific estimated veryapproximately at about 360,000 gross tons.In addition, there is about 336,000 gross tons of Axis shipping in south american ports which is no longer available to the enemy.
APPENDIX V.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.March 3. M.T.B. 31 damaged by gunfire.March 5. M/S Trawler Cedar slightly damaged in an air attack south-west of the Needles.   Four casualties.March 6. M/S Trawler Staunch damaged by mine off Harwich.March 7. Trawler Sheldon beached near Buckie (Inverness) after springinga leak.March 8. A/S Trawler Notts County was sunk by mine or torpedo southof Seidisf jord (Iceland).March, 9. Whaler Shera capsized and sank in pack ice north of Murmansk.Three survivors.March 11. M/S Trawler Craftsman slightly damaged by aircraft offAberdeen.February 27/March 5. -Presumed sunk by enemy action in the Java area :Auxiliary M/S Gemas, Rahman, Anking, Scott-Hurley, Wo-Kivang, Jarantut.Elias, Tapak, Malacca, Una Tone/: Armed Trawler Vyner Brooke, MotorM/S 31, and M.L.&apos;s 1096 and 1097.&apos;The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported :  Officers : 7 killed, 3 wounded. 100 missing.Ratings : 28 killed. 11 wounded, 115 missing.Note. Eighty-six of the officers missing were at Hong Kong.2*,-$ Q
(2) Merchant Ships (100 gross tons and over) under construction in the UnitedKingdom as at 28th February, 1942.	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.Coasting ships and colliers  ... Other ships Total    .........	8 37	5,000 314,000	14 172*	22,000 910,000	45	319,000	186	932,000* Including 9 vessels (5,000 gross tons) of Merchant type intended for Naval use.In addition the following merchant ships are on order in the UnitedKingdom and abroad : 	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.United Kingdom Canada and United States   ... Total    .........	17	109,000	80f 72$	305,000 518,000	17	109,000	152	823,000f Including 9 vessels (5,000 gross tons) building for the Navy.% Some of these vessels are already under construction but details are not available.APPENDIX IY.Enemy Merchant Ship Losses as assessed to 15th February, 1942.Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		seriously                         , Damaged.     j     Damag^-				Total.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross    i ,T Tons.    j No-1		Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German Italian Other enemy ships and ships useful to enemy-Total     ......	397 412 113	1,721,294 1,760,273 202,689	113 76 16	309,603 354,888 43,706	181 84 12	598,889 420,984 48,824	691 572 141	2,630,086 2,536,125 295,219	922	3,684,256	205	708,477	277 .	1,068,697	1,404	5,461,430This table does not include losses inflicted on the enemy by our KussianAllies, which are estimated at about 556,000 gross tons sunk : nor does it include losses inflicted on Japanese shipping in the Far East and Pacific estimated veryapproximately at about 360,000 gross tons.- In addition, there is about 336,000 gross tons of Axis shipping in south american ports which is no longer available to the enemy.Appendix III (1) will be inserted in a subsequent Resume.
Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.March 3. M.T.B. 31 damaged by gunfire.March 5. M/S Trawler Cedar slightly damaged in an air attack south-west of the Needles.   Four casualties.March 6. M/S Trawler Staunch damaged by mine off Harwich.March 7. Trawler Sheldon beached near Buckie (Inverness) after springinga leak.March 8. A/S Trawler Notts County was sunk by mine or torpedo southof Seidisfjord (Iceland).March 9. Whaler Shera capsized and sank in pack ice north of Murmansk.Three survivors.March 11. M/S Trawler Craftsman slightly damaged by aircraft offAberdeen.February 27/March 5. ^Presumed sunk by enemy action in the Java area :Auxiliary M/S Gemas, Rahman, Anking, Scott-Harley, Wo-Kwang, Jarantut,Elias, Tapak, Malacca, Hua Tong, Armed Trawler Vyner Brooke, MotorM/S 31, and M.L.&apos;s 1096 and 1097.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 7 killed, 3 wounded, 100 missing.Ratings : 28 killed, 11 wounded, 115 missing.Note. Eighty-six of the officers missing were at Hong Kong.
Provisional operational aircraft battle casualties compiled from reports received during the period:0700 hours, Thursday, 5th March, 1952, to 0700 hours, Thursday,12th March, 1942.British.Bombers ....Fighters ...CoastalArmy Co-operation total enemy.BombersFighters     ...MiscellaneousMetropolitan Area.In the Air....... 18...... 6.:.     ... no pilots are safe.Destroyed.39.probably destroyed.On the Ground.Damaged.3121Total12Of the above totals none were destroyed by A.A. fire.16British.Bombers.Fighters .OthersMiddle East (including Malta).In the Air.851On the Ground.92Total14Enemy.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousNo pilots are safe.Destroyed.10121ProbablyDestroyed.2511Damaged.2183Total2332Of the above totals, four were destroyed, fivo (damaged by A.A. fire and three damaged by Naval A.A.Week ending 5th March 1942. Delete &quot; One Fighter probably destroyed &quot; and substitute&quot; One Fighter destroyed.&quot;British and Allied.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousFar East (A.B.D.A. area).In the Air.2...       ... 8*On the Ground.413Total108Two pilots are safe.* On 4th March, 1942, six Hurricanes were reported serviceable. On 7th March, 1942, amilitary source states &quot; Last Allied Fighters destroyed.&quot;Enemy.Bombers ...fighter miscellaneous destroyed.541Probably\Destroyed51Damaged.41Total    ......     10 6 5Of the above totals, five were destroyed and five probably destroyed by A.A.Notes. (a) No account is taken of enemy aircraft destroyed on the ground in any theatre,(b) No account is taken of British Naval aircraft casualties.
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week from Air Reconnaissance and Intelligence sources :-Occupied France.Paris.-Persons present during the attack on the night of the 3rd / 4th Marchon the Renault Works describe this attack as the most important occurrence inFrance since the Armistice, and as a tremendous success for Great Britain. HighNazi authorities are stated to have been enraged because the German high command, in direct violation of their advice, had denuded Paris and the greaterpart of the occupied zone of defensive equipment. In the attack the SalmsonWorks were destroyed, and the Renault Works, with the exception of one department, were razed to the ground. The public in Paris are said to have beenoverjoyed at the attack, particularly because the Renault factory had become thesymbol of collaboration with Germany.Germany.Kiel. Photographs taken on the 2nd March, 1942, show considerable repair work to the Gneisenau in progress. About 30 feet of the deck plating in the bowshas been removed, exposing the deck below. There is a deep hole abreast&quot; B &quot; turret on the port side and some deck plating has been removed. Thereis also what appears to be damage on the port side abaft &quot; Y &quot; turret.dusseldorf. At the end of October and beginning of November, tihe effects of numerous bombardments were still very noticeable, although most of the ruinsnear the new station had been hastily cleared away. What must have been theresult of heavy bombs on houses and the General Post Office could be observed in streets near the main station. Damage was particularly noticeable in theneighbourhood of the Zoo, where two streets and railway lines in the dusseldorf-Derendorf station were destroyed.Mannheim. During the raid, either on the 11th/12th or 14th/16th February,a loaded petrol tanker barge was hit and sank after a violent explosion. Otherbarges were also hit and several cranes were badly damaged in the dock area.Bombs fell on wharves and one close to the Friedrich station.Hamburg. In the raid on the 30th November/1st December, a 4,000-lb.bomb fell near the Rabenstrasse main station. A row of houses was reduced torubble and windows over a mile away were broken by the force of the explosion.Ostend. Photographs taken during the daylight attack on 28th Februaryshow two bombs bursting on the railway lines and platforms of the passenger station between the outer harbour and Bassin No. 1.Sea Mining.In July 1941 the Sassnitz-Trelleborg ferry Deutschland, of 2,459 tons, was mined and sank off Oland Island.On 12th December, 1941, the German steamer Delphin, of 400 tons, was sunk by a mine off Kiel.   She was carrying cattle from Heligoland.On 9th February, a German ship was damaged by a mine off the North Seacoast.On 26th/27th February, the Swedish ferry icebreaker Starke was sunk bya mine. The exact position is not known, but it is thought to have been betweenSassnitz and Trelleborg.







</content>
</cab>
