<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/195/3 images: 29-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 28 COPY NO c 911 March 1977CABINETSALE OF BP SHARESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Energy1. Cabinet decided (CM(76) 39th Conclusions) that British Petroleum(BP) shares in excess of those required to keep the combined Governmentand Bank of England holdings at no less than 51 per cent should be sold.2. This decision was announced on 15th December along with other measures we were taking to reduce the Public Sector borrowing requirement (PSBR)o    As I expected it is provoking a strong adversereaction not only from all sections of the Party, but also from a wide variety of opinion in the couotry as a whole, which sees it as unpatriotic.3. There is concern in particular that the Government holding may bereduced to 31 per cent without any certainty that we shall be able to holdon successfully to the Bank&apos;s former Burmah BP shares.    If this happenedthere would be a reversal of the policy set out in the Social Contract - asthe Trades Union Congress (TUC) has reminded us - and an abandonment of our traditional stance on the level of our holdings in BP.    I share thisconcern and believe that the risk is one that we should not take.    many people believe, and I agree with them, that BP shares are still undervaluedbecause the benefits of its North Sea and Alaska investments have yet to be fully realised.    A year ago these assets alone were estimated to be woi&amp;t 8 a share to*BP which places virtually no value on the rest of the Group&apos;sassets at today&apos;s prices, and recently there have been reports that the shares were worth at least  12.    We are rightly being criticised for considering selling them before they realise their full potential.4^ If indeed the shares were to be valued at  12, then we should have failed to hold for the Government an increase in asset  values of over 200 million.    It could be argued that a sale, rather than helping theinternational&apos;financial position of the United Kingdom, had damaged that position by reducing the growth of assets which could serve as a securityQf collateral for existing or new loans which may have to be serviced orsecured.5.sI should also point out to my colleagues that the BP interest inettling the issue of the Burmah shares is to clear the way for a rightsssue.    If Her Majesty&apos;s Government, as in the past, is unable to take up* s share of such an issue, its percentage share holding will fall again,Just as it fell from 51 per cent to 48 per cent following the previous rights
issue.    And ifs unexpectedly, we lost the action with Burmah, and ourholdings drops to 31 per cent it will only take a one for four rights issue(to which we did not subscribe) for our stake to drop to 25 per cent whichis the level below which we cannot be certain of preventing the Company1 sArticles being altered, thus putting at risk Her Majesty&apos;s Government1 srights which are part of the Articles,6. The current situation in the oil market re-emphasises the need tobe able to assert control over BP0    It is essential that any decisions which BP take3 about its oil interests in Iran should take clear accountof the national interest and not be determined only by commercial motives.Theoretically we should be able to use the powers available to us in BP&apos;sArticle ox Association to ensure that the company acts in the national interest, but we have not, so far, been prepared to make any effective useof these powers.    I feel therefore that to reduce our shareholding wouldmake it even less likely that we shall be able to use these powers, eventhough the trend of events is towards situations where the national interestmay require their use.7. Nor do I think that it would be difficult to retain the entire holding ina manner which is consistent with the objectives of our previous decision.For example, the British National Oil Corporation (BNOC) could not doubt be persuaded to offer to buy BP shares as a commercial investment,financed without recourse to the Treasury by commercial borrowing.    Wecould reasonably argue that such a sale achieves precisely what we intendedthe raising of additional finance for the Government to help cover the excessof its expenditure over revenue.8. This approach to disposal of BP shares would answer our critics byretaining them still as a national asset.    It would also forge a link betweenBNOC and BP to the advantage of both in their oil production and tradingactivities.9. Thus the case for retaining these shares may be summarised asfollows:-a. They are a good commercial investment.b. The shares enable the Government to ensure that BPdoes not come under the influence or control of other oil interests.c. They give the Government an opportunity to encourage BPto play a role in support of our oil policies (and foreign exchangetransactions).d. Our holding strengthens the Government politically since there would be very strong opposition from right,   left andcentre, to selling BP to foreigners.
The case for disposing of them is solely based on the PSBR and theInternational Monetary Fund (IMF) commitment for 1977-78,,10.       But counting sales of BP shares against taxation or expenditure on public services within a fisted total PSBR is contrary to the Treasury&apos;s ownmethodology and model of the economy.    The issue only arises becauseof the mistaken use of a general overall target - the PSBR - which is intendedto reflect our broad objective, rather than provide precise financial options.Moreover the forecasts of the PSBR for 1977-78 or any other year have alarge margin of error - possibly  if -  2 billion either way, judging by theforecasting error this year and in the. previous two or three years.11.       We are therefore in the situation of facing a requirement to do something which is generally thought to be wrong in itself and of having tojustify it by an arithmetic which is not intellectually supportable.    The issue which the Cabinet should discuss is not whether to sell the shares, but how toavoid selling them without damaging our real interests,1?&apos;.       The following solutions should be examined in detail before thedecision to sell is confirmed:-a. A request to the IMF to agree to a technical adjustment ofthe PSBR in the light of the Government&apos;s view that the sale ofBP shares does not now make sense.b. A public statement that foreign borrowing by BNOC willvery much strengthen public sector financing in terms of assettransactions, and that the BP stake itself is a highly profitablepublic sector investment.c. An oiiiicial indication that owing to the regrettable Burmahsuit it will not now be possible to come to an early conclusion onthe sale.d. A clarification of the improving public sector balance sheet(with assets and investments which maintain their value duringinflation set against nominal debts whose value has been erodedby inflation) which will improve all the more in future years withNorth Sea revenues coming in and the worst of recession putbehind us.e. A further exploration of the possibility bf a BNOC purchaseof the shares financed by additional BNOC borrowing in foreign currency.1 &quot;KJ&apos;       The Treasury can help the Cabinet here.    The announcement of^finite plans for a sale in the Budget would needlessly offend a very widePolitical spectrum, and would confuse the public about our oil policy.
l4.       I invite my colleagues to consider the proposal for a freshapproach to the question of BP shareholdings, and to defer any action ondisposal until a further examination of all options has been concluded.A W BDepartment of Energy11 March 19774


</content>
</cab>
