<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/4/27 images: 350-355</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HrS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK  AND  KEY.It is requested that special care may he taken toensure the secrecy of this document.A8&amp;9C R E T..(39)177TTn 0.0TS. (39)179)COPY NO.    /Lit.V/AP. CABINETPOSSIBILITY OF INCREASING THE NUMBER OF A.A.  G-UNSTO BE SUPPLIED TO THE BRITISH ARMY IN france at THE EXPENSE OF AIR DEFENCE OF GREAT BRITAIN.REPORT BY THE CHIEFS OF STAFF COMMITTEE.The &apos;7ar Cabinet at their meeting56 held on1st December, 1939 -&quot;Invited the Chiefs of Staff to examine and report upon the possibility ofincreasing the number of heavy and light anti-aircraft guns to be supplied to the British Array in Prance at theexpense&quot;of the air defence of GreatBritain.&quot;2.        In the course of the discussion at the V/nr cabinet it vms suggested thnt our Report should be based on a re-view by. the Air Ministry of the gfficGcy.of fighters andother means of defence, in the light of the experience-which  hasbeen gained since the outbreak of war.    It has been pointed out by the Air Stafft however, that there has notbeen sufficient war experience on which to base the suggested review.    In the circumstances, therefore, theAir Staff are not prepared to say that the efficacyof the fighter defences permits any reduction in thenumber of A.A. guns.3.       We wish to emphasise that the ^.ir defence of GreatBritain is still far short of requirements in A.A. and,particularly- light A.A. weapons.    Only about one-third ofthe requirements in A.A. guns   and one-twentieth in light A.A. guns have so far been deployed.   Moreover,it has already been decided to despatch 48 guns to theBritish Expeditionary Force by the end of February, 1940,OSld investigations are being made as to the possibilityof taking measures to enable a further 48 guns to be despatched at short notice should an emergency arise.*fc\M. (39)  100th Mtg. . Conclusion 13 (iii).

In view of these facts v/e do not feel justified in     1  &apos;8recoiamendinc; that any further heavy or light anti-        00aircraft guns should &quot;be sup. lied to the British Armyin Prance at the e:;pense of the Air Dofence of GreatBritain.(Signed^   C;L;N.NEv/ALL.DUDLEY POUNDEDMUND IRONSIDE&quot;Central War Room.29th December, 1939




</content>
</cab>
