<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/32 images: 526-553</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. 255It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.MOST    SECRET.COPY NO.W.M.(40) 45TH CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 1.Confidential Annex.(18th February, 1940).ASSISTANCE to finland.(previous reference:W.M.(40) 43rdConclusions,Minute 1).The time factor.The War Cabinet had before thorn a JointReport by the Foreign Office and the Chiefs of Staffon the Time Factor (W.P,(40) 59).THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF explained thatif our hand was forced, it would not be possible to accelerate the departure of the main expedition toNarvik and Southern Sweden.      In the case of thenorthern force, the special equipments required werethe limiting factor.      The expedition to southern sweden had, of course, always been looked upon as theprice we should have to pay for Swedish co-operation,and the two forces were therefore timed to movesimultaneously.     There was, however, a possibilityof accelerating the sailing of the small forces to occupy the southern Norwegian ports.     This question was being examined by the Chiefs of Staff.     Asregards general Gamelin&apos;s proposals for the immediate despatch of a token force by air to assist the Finns,(referred to in the Telegram attached as Annex I toW.P.(40) 59), we had no details yet of what the french high Command had in mind.      It was possible that theproposal was being put forward mainly on political grounds.     Further details were being ascertained fromthe French High Command.

THE SEC23TARY OF STATE FOR AIR enquire whether the Chiefs of Staff were satisfied that thepossible scale of German air attack on Trondheimwould not endanger the security of the forces whichit was contemplated would go to the assistance ofthe Swedes&apos; in Southern Sweden.,     He was informedthat Trondheim was within range of 1,400 german aircraft which might drop up to 100 tons of bombsa day on the porto     This weight of attack might beincreased if the Germans seized additional aerodromes in Southern Sweden?THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF agreed that aconsiderable risk was involved0     The Chiefs ofStaff, however? felt that the risk was worth acceptingfor the sake of the great advantage which we should obtain if we secured, possession of the Swedish orefieldso     The danger of air attack on Trondheim wouldcertainly be increased if the Germans anticipated us and secured the aerodrome at Stavanger0     For thisreason, it was most important to forestall the Germansat Stavanger with a small force0     If this small force were heavily attacked9 it could destroy the aerodromeand be withdrawn by sea,The view was e;cpresscd that it wouldprobably be found possible to make arrangements whereby the small infantry forces for the occupationof the three southern Norwegian ports, could, be madeready to sail at a very early date, and that the shipping-problem ought not to present special difficulties0It was agreed, however, that the point shouldbe investigated as a matter of urgency0M g -

Some discussion ensued on the possibilityof the Germans making a sudden move to obtainpossession Of ports and aerodromes in Southern Norway- and Sweden.     It was thought that they might well bestung into making such a move in the near future andit was therefore clearly desirable that we should bein a position to take counter-action at short notice.The most important place from our point of view wasthe Stavanger aerodrome which the Germans might possibly seize by parachute troops.     The possessionof aerodromes in Southern Scandinavia would admittedlyfacilitate German air action against our shipping inthe North Sea.     So far as their U-boats were concerned,however, it would give them comparatively littleadvantage.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY thought thatif the Germans violated Scandinavian territory, itwould on balance be to our advantage.     Our main object was the ore fields in Northern Sweden, and we had tofind some pretext for getting a footing in Scandinaviain order to secure these fields.       If the Germansviolated Scandinavian territory, we should at oncehave full justification for going in and, indeed, the swedes and Norwegians would be likely to invite us tocome to their assistance.     He entirely agreed withthe Secretary of State for Air that the risk of german air attack on Trondheim was serious if we had toundertake operations in Southern Sweden.     Nevertheless,,it seemed essential that we should at least make the swedes a fair offer to make common cause with them ift-._-.-j  3os&quot;

they were attacked by Germany.      If the Swedes did notresist German aggression, and refused to invite us into their assistance, it might still be possible tocarry out the limited operation of seizing theNorthern ore field.     The line of communication from narvik to Gaiivare was not liable to heavy air attack as were the communications from the Norwegian ports to Southern Sweden.He was not convinced that we could not reach Gaiivare from narvik, even in the teeth of Scandinavian opposition.The railway from Narvik might be sabotaged, but a small force under a determined leader might overcome these difficulties.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF pointed out thatif we had not. the use of the Narvik railway in workingQg&amp;&amp;ws it was very doubtful whether our forces could reach Gaiivare in time to instal themselves therebefore the ice broke in the Baltic and the germans could send an expedition to the ore field via Lulea.Moreover, there was the possibility that, in thecircumstances envisaged, we should have to meetopposition from Swedish forces.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR agreed thatthe main objective was to secure the orefields atGaiivare.     He doubted, however, whether the War Cabinetrealised all the implications of the proposedexpedition..-     It was now contemplated that we should send a force amounting to about 4-g- Divisions to scandinavia.     One of these was to be a regularDivision but the remainder were not at present in avery advanced state of training.     The 48th Division,

which had recently arrived in Prance and was in thesame category, was not thought &quot;by the Commander-in-Chief of the British Expeditionary Force to he yet in a condition to undertake mobile operations.     Thedanger of air attack to which the Secretary of Statefor Air had referred was a serious limiting factorjand when we made our offer of assistance to Sweden,the Swedish General Staff would no    doubt realise the grave difficulties of the operation which we proposedoThey might well doubt whether we could make good our offer.       The original conception had been to sendtwo divisions only to Southern Sweden, but now thatthe force was to be increased to 3^ Divisions, thewhole affair was in danger of becoming an unmanageablecommitment.      If we undertook   a   new commitment on this scale, we should not be able to send any moretroops to France until well on into the summer.THE PRIME MINISTER observed that these doubts as to the quality of the troops which it was proposed to send to Scandinavia were a new and some-what disturbing feature, which had not before beenbrought to the notice of the War Cabinet.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO thought thatit would be very difficult to persuade the Swedes to throw in their lot with the Allies and to invite us tocome in, when we could only offer them such a limited amount of support.

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs thought that our only chance was to work uponScandinavian public opinion and to make all thecapital we could out of assistance to the Finns inorder to support our proposed demand for entrythrough Narvik^     We should, of course, have to say at the same time that we were very ready to discuss with Sweden what should be d.one to support her incase of German aggression against her6THE FIRST LORD OF TEE ADMIRALTY emphasised the importance of our having some troops in Finland: as early as possiblee     Even if the Finns were driven back and our troops with them? there would be areasonable chance that, in the course of theirretirement, they might after all secure possession ofthe Galivare ore fields and thus deny them toGermany.The discussion then turned on the desirability /of making an immediate communication of our proposals to the Finnsji as was recommended in the Joint report under consideration (w.p . (40) 59, paragraph 5)oThe text of the instructions given to Brigadier Ling,a copy of which is attached to these Minutes, was readouto     It was generally agreed that, in the firstinstance, it would be better for the proposedcommunication to be made by Brigadier Ling direct toField Marshal Mannerheim, and that the finnish government should not be informed officially.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER questioned whether it. would be wise for cur intentions to be disclosed toField Marshal Mannerheim at the present stage, He might take the view that the assistance which we could send,was of little valueP and that on balance he would bebetter off without it, owing to the danger of its

THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs thought that our only chance was to work uponScandinavian public opinion and to make all thecapital we could out of assistance to the Finns inorder to support our proposed demand for entrythrough Narvik.     We should, of course, have to say at the same time that we were very ready to discuss with Sweden what should be done to support her incase of German aggression against her0THE FIRST LORD OF TEE ADMIRALTY emphasised the importance of our having some troops in Finlandas early as possible.,     Even if the Finns were driven back and our troops with them, there would be areasonable chance that, in the course of theirretirement, they might after all secure possession ofthe Galivare ore fields and thus deny them toGermany,The discussion then turned on the desirabilityof making an immediate communication of our proposals to the Finns, as was recommended in the Joint report under consideration (w.p . (40) 59, paragraph 5).The text of the instructions given to Brigadier Ling,a copy of which is attached to these Minutes, was readout.     It was generally agreed that, in the firstinstance, it would be better for the proposedcommunication to be made by Brigadier Ling direct toField Marshal Mannerheim, and that the finnish government should not be informed officially,THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER questioned whether it would be wise for cur intentions to be disclosed toField Marshal Mannerheim at the present stage, He might take the view that the assistance which we could sendwas of little value, and that on balance he would bebetter off without it, owing to the danger of its

acceptance involving Finland in hostilities withGermany as well as Russia0THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs pointed out, however, that this difficulty would arise even if the communication was delayed.     If itwas made at once, we should at least know where westood with regard to the Films.It was thought that the instructions toBrigadier Ling, as drafted^laid undue emphasis on thepossibility of operations at Petsamo.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR undertook to arrange that Brigadier Ling, who had memorisedthese instructions and not taken a copy with him,should be informed that the possibility of operations in the Petsamo area was considered remote0Some discussion followed on the probablereactions of the Finns and the Swedes to the variousdiplomatic moves which were proposed.     The following were the principal points which emerged:-(i)   The Allied force sent to Finland would b-.about 2 brigades initially, rising later to 3 brigades^     This force, owing tomaintenance difficulties^ would not beable to operate South of the &quot;waist-line&quot;;but it was on the Mannerheim Line thatthe Finns were most in need of assistanceat the present time (ii) The Swedes might well take the view thatwe could give them no adequate support,and might therefore press the Finns not toaccept our offer of assistance but to cometo terms with Russia. Reference was madein this connection to telegram Ho. 61 from Stockholm,(iii)   Field Marshal Mannerheim might think thatthe acceptance of the forces referred toin (i) would prejudice his chance ofobtaining any direct assistance from the swedes - assistance which would be farless likely to involve him in difficulties with Germany.

(iv) Oil the other hand he might be ableto use our offer of assistance as alever to extract more assistance outof the Swedes than they would other-wise provide-      It was quite possiblethat the Germans would raise no serious objections to the Swedessending assistance to Finland,provided that they did not interferewith Germany&apos;s supply of iron ore.They might give Sweden some form of assurance that, on these terms, theywould undertake to see that Swedendid not suffer at the hands of Russia.(v) It might well be, however, that field marshal Mannerheim might see more inour offer of assistance, limitedthough it might be, than appeared atfirst sight.    He might realise that itmeant that the whole strength of the Allieswas to be   engaged on his side.    the moral effect of our interventionmight, therefore, be very great.     Weshould have to point out to him thatthe extent of our assistance was inany event limited by the inadequacy of the communications to Finland.He knew perfectly well that therailways in the North of Swedenwere already choked.The War Cabinets-(a) Took note of the joint report of theForeign Office and the Chiefs ofStaff Committee (W.P.(40) 59).(b) Agreed that on his arrival in finland on Monday, 19th February,Brigadier Ling should be directed to speak to Field-Marshal Mannerheim,in accordance with his instructions,but that in making reference to thePetsamo project, he should emphasise that the possibility of our undertakingthis enterprise was remote.(c) Agreed that for the time being noparallel communication in the same sense as (b) should be made throughForeign Office channels to theFinnish Government,

(d) Agreed that the French Governmentshould he informed of the action taken under (b) above.(e) Invited the Chiefs of Staff toreport to the War Cabinet as a matterof urgency, the earliest date bywhich force &quot;Stratford&quot; (i.e. theforce for Bergen, Trondheim andStavenger) could be made ready tosail.(f) Took note that the Chiefs of staff would ascertain from the French high command further details of general gamelin&apos;s proposal to send immediatelya small detachment to Finland by air and to accelerate the despatchof a larger force (Annex I toW.P.(40) 59).Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,

Instructions to Brigadier Ling.I.     The War Cabinet at their 39th Meeting on12th February, 1940 -&quot;Agreed that Brigadier Ling should be sent ona mission to Finland with the object of affording moral support to Field-marshal mannerheim, and of providing us with accurate information of the situation.     Brigadier Lingshould be in possession of full information about the projected Allied moves in finland and Scandinavia, but should, not disclose themto anyone until he received orders to do so.&quot;02.     You will carry no communication in writing, but will be prepared to deliver a verbal message personally to Field-Marshal Mannerheim on the lines indicated below.Mr. Vereker, the newly appointed British Minister, isbeing fully informed by the Foreign Office before hedeparts for Finland in the course of the next few days.3.     When authorised., you are to inform Field-marshal mannerheim that the British and French Governments are preparing a military force which we will be ready to despatch to Finland after the midd.le of March, provided the Norwegian and Swedish Governments would allow this force to cross their territory.     We should hope to obtainthis permission as a result of an appeal by the finnish government to the world for assistance against Russia,This appeal would be addressed particularly to norway and Sweden who are Finland&apos;s nearest neighbours and whowould be the next to be over-run by Russia,In making this communication to Field-marshal mannerheim you are to impress on him the importance to finland that this project should not be prejudiced by either acceptance of invitations from any neutral powersto accept mediation for an early peace or by a prematureappeal to the world.     The timing of the appeal must be closely co-ordinated with the date on which the Allies

2S5will be. ready to intervene,,     The Allied intervention would give the Finns a chance of beating the Russiansrather than having to accept unfavourable terms ofpeace,40     The forces which the Allies would be in aposition to move into Finland arriving in April wouldbe in the order of two infantry brigades.     This forcemight subsequently be increased to a divisioncThese forces would not be prepared to operate on any point,South of an East and West line drawnthrough hemisphere, operations in the more southern areabeing precluded both by aclininistrative difficulties and strategical considerations.5o      Secrecy is all important and you will notcommunicate the information contained, in theseinstructrons to anyone until you are authorised to doso,     You will inform Mr. Vereker as soon as you haveimparted the Allied, plans to Field-Marshal Mannerheimo6.     You should know that the Allied governments are examining the possibilities of -(a) a landing in the      samo area,   or(b) despatching tlirough Norway and Swedenthe force (in paragraph 4) disguisedas &quot;volunteers&quot;.Preliminary investigations on these lines hr.so far*s not proved favourablee     We do not propose toattempt to put these alternative plans into operationunless Norway and Sweden refuse to permit the passage ofAllied troops through their countries after the Finnishappeal has been made0When you communicate the Allied plan toField-Marshal Mannerheim he may well raise this aspect of Allied intervention.     You may use your discretion

2sein informing him that the Allied Governments havethe above possibilities in mind, but you shouldimpress on him that such intervention is, in theopinion of the Allied Governments, a very indifferentalternative to the despatch of recognised militaryformations through Norway and Sweden..The War Office,18th February, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
