<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/67/3 images: 20-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PHOPPrinted for the Cabinet.  June 1945The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of.....Sr^... .Af^xJ:t?^rrri..-...............................uTOP SECRETCP. (45) 53.2%th June, 1945.CABINET.MAN-POWER IN THE SECOND HALF OF 1945.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I.THE Prime Ministers Directive on Man-Power in 1945 (W.P. (45) 250 ofthe 14th April, 1945) asked that the Ministerial Man-Power Committee should draw up a balance-sheet for the second half of 1945 in the light of a newassessment of our military effort in Stage II. The Chiefs of Staff have prepared a new appreciation of military needs in Stage II (C.O.S. (45) 310 (O)), and theestimates put forward by the Service Ministers (in W.P. (45) 297, 307 and 321)of the man-power required for the Armed Forces in the second half of 1945 are based on that appreciation.2. Annexed to this Memorandum is a general survey of the man-power position in the second half of 1945 prepared by the Minister of Labour and national Service. This disclosses a prospective shortage of man-power whichis as serious as any we have had to face throughout the war. The demands for additional man-power in the second half of 1945 amount to 1,245,000, asfollows : 1Intakes into the Armed Forces   ...       ...       ... 326,000Net increase in building and civil engineering ... 200,000Net increases in all other industries and services 719,015*Total............      ...      1,245,015Against these demands there will be a supply of only 688,000 men and women.To meet demands for civilian industries and services totalling 920,000, it will notbe possible, on present plans, to provide more than 522,000, of whom 200,000 are needed for building and civil engineering.3. In Part II of this Memorandum certain proposals are put forward for increasing the numbers available for civilian industry by an additional releaseof women from the Auxiliary Services (paragraph 12 below). But even if these additional releases are approved, they will make only a small contribution toclosing the gap.The Man-Power Committee have also considered the possibility of additionalcuts in the munitions industries; but they are satisfied that any releases from munitions beyond those already planned must depend upon a reduction of thedemands to be made by the Services upon their Supply Departments.* This includes the latest demands for the building materials industries, which are putforward by the Minister of Works in CP. (45) 9. Of the total of 10,375 claimed in that paper,only 5,000 were allowed for in the survey by the Minister of Labour and National Servicereproduced in the Appendix.[30146] b
4. The Man-Power Committee therefore consider that, if civil industries and services are to receive the additional man-power they require in order toenable them to make a reasonable start in 1945 with the most urgent tasks of civilreconstruction, the scale of our military effort in this period must be reduced tosome extent below the level at present planned. The Committee do not think they can usefully put forward proposals for detailed allocations of man-powerover the whole field until the Cabinet have considered this major issue of policyand decided whether we can continue to sustain a military effort on the scalenow contemplated.II.5. Meanwhile, it is necessary that the Cabinet should settle, at least on a provisional basis, the scale of intakes into, and releases from, the Armed forces during the remainder of 1945.Intakes of Men.6.   The Service Ministers have asked for the following intakes of men :  Royal Navy    ......       .........&apos;    56,000     -Army    ..................   199,000R.A.F...................     65,000Total......   320,000(Note. The requirements for the Army and the R.A.F. take into account the cessation of transfers from the Royal Navy and the R.A.F. to the Army).These demands arise for the following reasons :  (a) New intakes are needed to facilitate the reorganisation of the Servicesinvolved in the operation of the release scheme. Each Service has a formidable problem in rearranging its available man-power to releasemen in the appropriate age and length of service groups while, at thesame time, providing balanced Forces for deployment against Japan.(b) It is agreed policy that men released in Class B shall be replaced, so as toavoid reducing releases in Class A.(c) The Secretary of State for War asks for an intake of 50,000 men toreplace 50,000 Pioneers who are not due for release in the normal waybut who cannot be reabsorbed into the Army, and will therefore haveto be discharged in the early months of 1946.7. The Committee consider that these claims can be reduced on thefollowing grounds : -(a) The intakes claimed for replacement of men to be released in Class Bare calculated so as to cover Class B releases equal to 10 per cent, of class A releases over the whole of the first year of the reallocationscheme, i.e., up to 30th June, 1946. As Class B releases were introduced in order to meet the urgent needs of certain industries[e.g., building and coal mining) which would not be met by releases in Class A, they ought to tail off as Class A releases gather speed, andin 1946 should be appreciably less than the maximum figure of 10 percent, of Class A releases. The Committee recommend that intakesin 1945 in compensation for Class B releases should not exceed thenumbers to be released in Class B in 1945. The Service ministers would adquiesce in this recommendation if they could be assured thatClass B releases in 1946 will not in fact be substantial. While theCommittee do not feel that it is possible to guarantee that there willbe no further block releases in 1946 (as distinct from the releases of individual specialists, under present arrangements limited to 10 percent, of Class B releases), they consider that the Service Ministers can,and should, be given an assurance that releases in Class B in 1946will not involve an addition to the total releases at present planned for that period.(b) The Committee do not consider that any intake should be given to theArmy to replace the 50,000 surplus&apos; Pioneers; the need to replacemen who will be redundant in 1946 cannot be considered a legitimateclaim on the very limited call-up which will be possible in the second half of 1945. The Secretary of State for War has pointed out thatthis will mean stopping the release of an equivalent number of menfrom the Army in the early months of 1946.
(c) The claim for the Royal Navy relates to the period from 1st June to31st December, 1945, and should therefore have deducted from it the outstanding balance of intakes for the first half of the year whichwill be received in June, amounted to 2,000 men.8. In the light of these recommendations, the claims of the Armed Forcescan be restated as follows :  Royal Navy.........      ......      47,000Army..................       75,000R.A.F. ...............      47,500Total     ...............     169,5009. Under the arrangements proposed in the White Paper on Reallocationof Man-power (Cmd. 6568) for the call-up of men between the ages of 18 and 27together with a continuation of the existing policy with regard to the cancellation of deferments of men in the same age groups, the number available for call-upin the second half of 1945 would be about 120,000. This figure could, however,be raised to 160,000 by adopting the following two measures : - (a) Refraining from reducing to 27 the maximum age of call-up. It hasalready been announced, that the present maximum age of 30 years will be retained for the time being.(b) Adopting a much more stringent policy for the cancellation of defermentsof fit men aged 18 to 30 at present retained in industry. The extentto which these men, many of whom are highly skilled, can be withdrawnwithout serious damage to industry is severely limited, and the mainsource must be the release of men from the munitions industries asmunitions programmes are cut.The Committee recommend that these two measures should be adopted inorder to achieve a total call-up of 160,000. This will not be easy to accomplish,and the Minister of Labour and National Service will need the full co-operationof other Ministers, particularly the Supply Ministers, in securing the necessaryreleases of skilled men. On the other hand, the Service Ministers regard it asthe minimum compatible with the Government pledge that young men, particularlyin the munitions industries, whose call-up has hitherto been deferred, will nowbe taken into the Forces. Indeed, they would have liked to see a much more extensive call-up.10. We recommend that the call-up of 160,000 men should be allocated asfollows : Royal Navy...............      47,000Army ...       ...............      68,000R.A.F...................      45,000Total     ...............     160,000When account is taken of the recommendation in paragraph 11 below thatthe W.A.A.F. should be allowed to recruit 2,500 women, these allocations meet in full the reduced requirements of the Royal Navy and the Royal Air Force, as stated in paragraph 8 above, and go most of the way towards meeting the reducedrequirements of the Army.Intakes of Women.11. The Royal Navy ask for an intake of 3,000 women for the W.R.N.S. andthe Army for 13,000 women for the A.T.S. The Secretary of State for Air makes no specific demand for an intake of women, but states that if women can beprovided a limited number could be accepted in place of men. It has already been announced (Cmd. 6568) that women will not be called up but will be permitted to volunteer, and the only source of recruitment for the Women&apos;s Auxiliary services will be a continuation of volunteering. The Committee recommend intakes basedon estimates of the numbers of volunteers likely to be forthcoming, as follows :  W.R.N.S.............      ...        3,000A.T.S...................      10,000W.A.A.F................        2,500Total      .........       ......       15,500[30146] - B 2
It is possible that the W.R.N.S. can obtain more volunteers than are needed to meet the proposed allocation of 3,000. The Committee therefore recommendthat volunteering above the allocation should be allowed, provided that releases from the W.R.N.S. are increased above the figure of 15,000, proposed in para-graph 12, to the extent of any additional recruitment.Releases.12. The Prime Minister&apos;s Directive requires the Man-Power Committee toconsider releases as well as intakes. The Service.Ministers proposed the followingreleases (including Class B releases of men at 10 per cent, of Class A) for thesecond half of 1945 : -Men. Women.Royal navy         ......        99,000 10,000Army      *.........      515,000 47,000R.A.F..........       139,000 12,250Total.........       753.000 69,250The Committee considered that a substantial increase in the release of women would be one of the most effective means of helping to meet the severe shortage ofman-power available for civilian industry. The Committee therefore asked theService Ministers to examine the effects of releases of women on the followingscale : . W.R.N.S................      15,000A.T.S. ...............      75,000W.A.A.F................      45,000Total      ............       ...     135,000The First Lord of the Admiralty has accepted the release of women of 15,000.The Secretary of State for War considers that an increase in the release ofwomen must involve an equivalent reduction in the release of men.The Secretary of State for Air does not consider that the proposed increasedscale of release could be achieved without radical reorganisation of the R.A.F.,and a reduction in its effective strength. The difficulties of reorganisation inthe R.A.F. have already been accentuated by the standstill order in respect ofthe Metropolitan Air Force,. which involves a delay of at least two months inthe various programmes of reorganising and retraining. If the Secretary ofState could be given a firm assumption, for planning purposes, that the standstillwill not be maintained beyond a given date, say, 31st -July, 1945, it would ease the present difficulties and enable the Secretary of State to make a precise assess-ment of the situation which will result from our proposals.Conclusions.13.   Our conclusions may be summarised as follows :  (i) The man-power situation generally is more serious than it has been atany time during the war. It will be impossible both to maintain thescale of effort in the Far East as at present planned and to meetminimum civilian needs, at home. The Cabinet should therefore consider whether there should be some reduction in the scale of themilitary effort planned for Stage II.(ii) The call-up of men for the Armed Forces in the second half of 1945should be 160,000, allocated among the three Services as follows :  Royal Navy     ...............      47.000Army     ...&quot;      ...............      68,000R.A.F...................      45,000Total    ...............160,000This recommendation is made on the assumption that releases in class B in 1946 will not be allowed to increase the total of releasesof men above those already planned for Class A.
(iii) Volunteering for the Women&apos;s Auxiliary Services should continue, andthe following allocations should be made : W.B.N.S.......      .........       3,000A.T.S...................      10,000W.A.A.F................        2,500Total.......      ......      15,500Recruitment for the W.R.N.S. should be allowed beyond the alloca-tion of 3,000, on condition that the number of women released fromthe W.R.N.S. will be increased beyond 15,000 to the extent of any additional recruitment above the allocation of 3,000,(iv) Releases of men from the Armed Forces in the second half of 1945should be as follows :  Royal Navy    ...............        99,000Army..........      .........       515,000R.A.F...................      139,000Total..........      ...      753,000These releases include Class B releases at the rate of 10 per cent, of class A.(v) The Service Ministers should be asked to do their utmost to reach thefollowing target figures for releases of women in the second half of1945 :-W.R.N.S................        15,000A.T.S...................        75,000W.A.A.F...........      ......        45,000Total.............      135,000The target figure for the w .A.A.F. cannot be reached if the stand-still order in respect of the Metropolitan Air Force is maintained.If this cannot yet be withdrawn, we suggest that the Secretary ofState for Air might be authorised to proceed, for purposes of planning,on the assumption that the standstill order wall not be maintainedbeyond the 31st July, 1945.J. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,29^ June, 1945.[30146]
ANNEX.[M.P. (45) 12.]31st May, 1945.CABINET.Ministerial Committee on Man-Power.MAN-POWER REVIEW, 1st JUNE TO 31st DECEMBER, 1945.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service.1. The total working population of Great Britain at the 31st May, 1945,is estimated at 21,710,000 (including 90,000 unemployed). This total includes all prisoners of war in Europe (hitherto excluded from statistics of the working population) who are assumed to have returned to the strength of the Forces bythe end of May.It is estimated that by the end of the year the total of 21,710,000 will havefallen by 1,130,000 to 20,580,000 (including possibly 150,000 unemployed). The,decrease is accounted for as follows :  Wastage by death, by reaching age 65 (men), age 60 (women), and excess of wastage to non-industrial section over intake therefrom : From Forces      ...       ...       ...          ... 71,000From Civil Defence      ......          ... 17,000From Industry : Normal  &quot;    ......       ...      342,000Abnormal    .........      700,000-- 1,042,000Total    ......... 1,130,0002. Large numbers of women with household responsibilities will retire from industrial employment during the next seven months. The estimated loss to industry from this cause by the end of the year, out of the 2 million womenspecially mobilised for war-time employment is put at 700,000 (two part-timewomen being counted as a unit). This figure is shown in paragraph 1 above asabnormal wastage.3. If there were no intake into the Forces from industry(&apos;) in the second half of the year the changes in the strength .of the Forces; Police, National fire service, and Civil Defence (General) Services; industry and the unemployed inJune and in each of the last two quarters of the year would be approximatelyas follows i -Estimated Strengths.(Thousands.)--	31st May.	30th June.     30th September. i	31st December.Forces ...       ...    Hllll Police, National Fire Service, Civil    Defence    (General) Services      ...    &quot;1 j!-&apos;^^!-?&apos;^-;--&apos; Industry Unemployed Total working population ...	5,130 158 16,332 90	5,080                  4,800 140                     107 16,045                 15,973 100                     120	4,210(J) 100 .16,120(s) 150	21,710	21,365                21,000	20,580(1) The&apos; figures in the Table for the Forces and for the total working population allow forintake into the Forces in the second half of the year of 10,000 students from the non-industrialsection.(2) It is assumed that releases under the Realloeation Scheme will number 822,000,including about 68,500 Class B releases, of which 40,000 will go to the building industry.(*) This figure assumes that all those released from the Forces up to 31st December whodecide to go into industry will have taken up work by that date. In fact, a large number will still be on leave and these may amount to as many as 150,000.
The table shows that the numbers in industry as a whole would fall by 287,000in June, by a further 72,000 in the third quarter, and that there would be arise of about 147,000 in the last quarter of the year. The net change in industry as a whole during the period the 1st June to the 31st December would thus show adecrease of about 212,000.4. Industry Groups(4) II and III have borne the brunt of mobilisation forwar purposes. Group III in particular has suffered a heavy net reduction inthe numbers employed. Neither of these groups can bear further cuts, on thecontrary, they are urgently in need of substantial expansion. The man-power required for the Forces and for the expansion of civilian industry must be foundin the last resort from the Group I munitions industries (metal and chemical industries).5. Within the Group I industries substantial cuts are to be made in thenumbers working for the Supply Departments. Existing plans provide that thesecuts will amount during the last seven months of this year to approximately900,000. I understand that this is the maximum number on present plans thatwill be available (a) to offset the net decrease in industry; (b) to provide intakeinto the Forces; and (c) to expand civilian industry. As shown in paragraph above, the net decrease in industry is estimated at 212,000, and this leaves atotal of 688,000 available for providing intake into the forces and the expansionof civilian industry.6. The expansion of the labour force of the building and civil engineering-industries is of the highest priority. The total of 822,000 releases from theForces already planned will include about 753,000 men. It is estimated thatthis will provide 110,000 men for building and civil engineering and that a further90,000 can be transferred from other industries by the special registration of ex-builders already approved by the War Cabinet. Other ordinary intake willoffset normal wastage and the releases from the Forces and transfers from otherindustries will yield an estimated net increase in building and civil engineeringby the end of the year of 200,000.7. This would leave 488,000 as the maximum supply available to provideintake into the Forces and an expansion of the rest of civilian industry. Thedemands of Departments for civilian industries and services other than building and civil engineering amount to a total net increase of 713,640. A summaryof these demands is given in the Appendix. The demands of Service Depart-ments for intake into the Forces during the second half of the year amount toa total of 326,000. An intake into the Forces is required in order to allow forthe release of older men in Class A and to replace releases in Class B. The total demand thus amounts to 1,039,640 against which the available supply is 488,000.Sup-ply fGr the Forces.8. The field from which intake of men into the Forces can be obtained is limited to fit men under 30&apos; years of age. The supply divides itself into two parts (a) those who will reach 18 by the end of the year, and (b) those aged 18and under 30 at mid-1945.9. (1) From among students reaching 18 years of age, 10,000 can be recruited to the Forces by the end of the year.(2) The number who will reach 18 by the end of the year in industry is about130,000, and it is estimated that under present arrangements 100,000 of these can be made available for the Forces. (The remaining 30,000 will be given defer-ment in industries such as metal manufacture, shipbuilding, agriculture,coalmining and building, or on grounds of hardship.)10.   The total number of fit men aged 18 and under 30 in industry is 627,000Of this total 371,000 are in Groups II and III distributed as follows :  Group II Agriculture     ......        .....       112,000Mining......       .........       145,000Shipping        ............        50,000 j-      350,000Other transport        ...       ...       ...        31,000Other Group II industries   ...       ...        12,000(*) Those Groups comprise the basic industries, agriculture; National and Local Government;Utilities; Transport; Food, drink and tobacco manufacture; and the industries mainly servingcivilian needs-building and civil engineering; distributive trades; textiles; clothing:&apos; leather^wood;   paper;   bricks, pottery   and glass;   and   other   manufactures and  services such  acommerce and finance; professions; entertainment; hotels: laundries and cleaning.
sGroup III Building and civil engineering      ... 7,000Other industries       ...       ...       ...        14,00021,000Total............      371,000It will in practice be found impossible to withdraw any appreciable numbersfrom these industries.11. Group I now includes 256,000 fit men aged 18 and under 30 distributedindustrially as follows : Metal manufacture          ...       ...       ... 27,000Shipbuilding         ......&quot;      ...... 23,000Engineering          ...       ...       ...       ... 121,000Motors aircraft, &amp;c.        ......... 53,000Metal goods          .....,      ...... 28,000Chemicals, explosives, paint, oils, &amp;c.   ... 4,000Total   ...............      256,000This total includes 30,000 apprentices. Almost the whole of the remainder areskilled men and the withdrawal of substantial numbers for the Forces would giverise to difficult problems of readjustment. They include certain highly-skilledoccupations such as draughtsmen, platers, rivetters, tool-makers, precision fitters,&amp;c, who will be essential to industry in the period of reconversion In metalmanufacture much of the work is particularly arduous and can only be performed by fit young men accustomed to that type of work. To achieve the withdrawal ofsay 50,000 men from Group I it will be necessary to apply more rigid tests in granting deferment and it will be necessary to have the full support of the supply departments and the Board of Trade when individual cases are dealt with by theDistrict Man-Power Boards. A proportion of such men could, in normal cireum-stances,. only have been posted to the Forces in a Service Trade capacity, but will now have to be recruited for general service.12. On the above basis the maximum number of men that can be madeavailable for the Armed Forces up to the end of the year will be : From non-industrial classes Students      ............... 10,000From Industry Those reaching age 18      ...       ...       ... 100,000Those  aged- 18  and under  30  (almostentirely from Group I industries)     ... 50,000Total ....      ......       160,000If in addition the demands of the Service Departments for an intake of16,000 women are accepted, the total intake for the Forces will thus amount to176,000, of whom 10,000 will come from the non-industrial classes and 166,000from industry. Of the balance of 488,000 available for the Forces and civilianindustry (para. 7) there will, therefore, be only 322,000 available for civilianindustry (other than building and civil engineering).13.   The foregoing may be summarised as follows : Total supply derived from munitions cuts 900,000Deduct net decline in industry  ... ...      212,000Balance available for Forces and expansionof civilian industry     ...       ...       ... 688,000Required for building and civil engineering 200,000Balance   ......... 488,000Maximum   number   that   can   be   madeavailable for the Forces from industry 166,000Balance available for civilian industry otherthan building and civil engineering )(net increase)    ...       ...       ...       ... 322,000Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,31st May, 1945.R. A. B.
Appendix.MAN-POWER REVIEW--1st JUNE TO 31st DECEMBER, 1945.Civilian Demands (net increases).Group I-Aluminium houses, civilian aircrBoard of Trade ...Ministry of Fuel and PowerMinistry of War transport ministry of Food ...Total Group Iaft, &amp;cFisheries Group II Ministry of Agriculture andAgricultureFishingMinistry of Fuel and Power-CoalminingMinistry of War Transport Stone quarrying   ...National Government service non-industrialIndustrial ...Scottish Office Education ... %...Local Government ...Ministry of Fuel and Power UtilitiesMinistry of War Transport Inland Transport ...Shipping   ...Ministry of Civil AviationMinistry of FoodTotal Group group III Distributive Trades Ministry of Food ...Fuel and PowerBoard of Trade ...Ministry of Food CateringMinistry of Labour Hospitals   ...Total Group III     .........Total. Civilian   industries  and   services   otherbuilding and civil engineering ...Building and civil engineering   ...50,0002,200than60,000181,0009,70028,8003,0004-282,50045,00010003,6003,0005,0006,240 (including19,700 forN.A.A.F.I.)503,30013,00040,0007,0003,45030,300---4- 165,94052,000173,00025,00015,0004- 265,2004- 713,6404- 200,000Grand Total ...4-913,640




</content>
</cab>
