<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/50/45 images: 436-447</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1974CM (72)44th conclusions copy No. (J %cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Friday, 6 October, 1972,at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham ofThe Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber,mp, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mp, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustrySt. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Secretary of State for northern ireland the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord President ofthe council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,q c, m p, Chancellor of the duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for employment the following were also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-General (Items 1and 2)
Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. J. B. hunt mr. H. F. T. smith mr. K. T. barnett mr. I. T. lawman mr. H. F. Eixis-ReesContentsSubjectOversea Affairs............     ......UgandaIcelandVisit of the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to theUnited StatesEgyptPrime Ministers Visit to Italy     ............Industrial Affairs     ...............Meetings with the Confederation of British Industry andthe Trades Union CongressTelevision of the Proceedings of the House of Commons1973 Revaluation for Rates...............
OverseaAffairsUgandaPreviousReference:CM (72) 43rdConclusions,Minute 11. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that it hadbeen clear during his visit to the United Nations General assembly in the previous week that many of the African Governments wereembarrassed by the behaviour of the President of Uganda, GeneralAmin. The announcement of our intention to seek inscription of an item on Uganda had prompted them to take a more active role in seeking to moderate Ugandan policy; and in the light of the offer of president Mobutu of Zaire to intervene it had seemed right to delayour action in the General Assembly to promote inscription. after his visit to Kampala President Mobutu claimed to have receivedassurances from General Amin that he would extend the time limit for the expulsion of the Asian holders of United Kingdom passports(UKPH); would relax the prohibition on the transfer of their assets;and would withdraw the threat to imprison any who remained afterthe time limit had expired. It seemed likely that General Aminwould in fact extend the time limit, although in view of Uganda&apos;scritical financial position it was unlikely that he would allow UKPHto remove their assets. Nevertheless, he had disputed PresidentMobutu&apos;s understanding of their agreement. We had therefore asked the Secretary-General of the United Nations, Dr. Waldheim,to try to resolve the uncertainty. If he was not able to do so to oursatisfaction we would probably table a resolution in the ThirdCommittee of the United Nations. In presenting it we would bearin mind the legal as well as the humanitarian arguments. It now seemed that we might be successful in evacuating all the AsianUKPH by the original time limit.The future of stateless persons, however, continued to givegrounds for anxiety. We have made little headway with the united nations High Commissioner for Refugees, who had so far done little to establish camps in other countries to receive these individuals.We might have to decide to refer to this in any resolution which wetable in the Third Committee. On this issue African opinion in theUnited Nations might be more helpful than on the other aspects ofour complaint.The Home Secretary and Lord President of the Council saidthat the latest estimates suggested that not more than 25,000 AsianUKPH would be coming to the United Kingdom. This was lower than earlier estimates. Even so, the administration of our resettle-ment centres needed to be reinforced, particularly by senioradministrative personnel; and, together with the Lord Privy Seal,he would be approaching Departments on this account in the very near future. As regards stateless persons, it had been agreed thatwe could not technically admit them into this country but that, since we could not reject them immediately, we would place them in aresettlement centre on an interim basis, making it clear to themthat, if they left the centre, they would be liable to arrest and deportation.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary and the Home Secretary and lord president of the Council.
IcelandPreviousReference:CM (72) 42ndConclusions,Minute 2Visit ofthe ForeignandCommon-wealthSecretary toThe UnitedStatesEgyptPreviousReference:CM (72) 42ndConclusions,Minute 2The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that as a resultof the agreement which he had reached in New York with the icelandic Foreign Minister resumed negotiations were now takingplace in Reykjavik. There were indications that the icelandic government might offer to allow us to take up 150,000 tons of fisha year, as against the figure of 170,000 tons awarded by the Inter-national Court. Iceland had stopped harassment of our trawlerswhile the negotiations were on; but, if harassment were resumed,urgent decisions might need to be taken about the provision of naval protection for our trawlers.The Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food said that theindustry would probably be content with a catch limited to 150,000tons a year. It would be preferable, however, to avoid mentioninga specific quantity and to rely on the boundaries of the permittedareas being so drawn as to ensure that this level of catch would infact be achieved. The fishing industry were well satisfied with theway in which the Government had been dealing with the matter.The Cabinet (2) Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary and the Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that he had been particularly impressed by two things during his recent meeting withthe President of the United States, Mr. Nixon, and the United states secretary of State, Mr. Rogers: first, the importance which theUnited States Government attached to promoting discussions on commercial policy between Japan, Europe and the United States;and, second, the emphasis which the President had placed on hisrefusal to contemplate the withdrawal of United States troops inEurope without some corresponding reduction in the Soviet militarypresence.The Cabinet-(3) Took note of the statement by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that he did not expect the most recent exchanges between President Sadat of egypt and the Soviet Government to lead to the resumption of soviet military support for Egypt. It was more likely that any assistance would be in the economic field. The Soviet Services were still usingEgyptian ports to some extent; but they might be thinking of movingelsewhere, e.g. to Syria. There had been discussion about arms supplies when the Egyptian Foreign Minister, Dr. Zayyat, had visitedLondon. He had been told that we would like to help the egyptian government but that we could do so only in terms of defensiveweapons. He had appeared to understand our position.The Secretary of State for Defence said that the ForeignMinister of Saudi Arabia, Mr. Saqqaf, had told him that the SaudiGovernment would like to buy Jaguar aircraft but that they would
not accept conditions which would prevent these from being trans-ferred to other countries. There seemed little doubt that SaudiArabia had it in mind to ensure that the aircraft eventually reachedEgypt.The Cabinet-(4) Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary and the Secretary of State for Defence.CONFIDENTIALPrime 2.   The Prime Minister said that the Italian Government hadMinisters taken great pains to make his visit to Rome from 2 to 5 OctoberVisit to enjoyable and successful. He had reviewed a wide range of questionsItaly with the Italian Prime Minister; and there were no bilateral problemsat issue. So far as the forthcoming European Summit Meeting was concerned, he had stressed the importance which we attached to thedevelopment of a regional policy which would take account of our needs and would be financed by the Community&apos;s own resources;and we were assured of the support of Italy on this question. TheItalian Government also fully accepted that progress on economic union must proceed in step with progress towards monetary union.They had shown signs, however, of thinking that the french president, President Pompidou, had created domestic political embarrassment for himself because he had purported to prescribeconditions for a Summit Meeting which he had been unable toobtain; and they had felt that it might now be necessary to help himto reinsure his position with French public opinion. It had therefore been necessary to emphasise to the Italian Government that thisshould not result in our making concessions at the Summit whichwe were unwilling to make in order to ensure that the Meeting tookplace.He had also been very impressed by the trouble taken by the vatican authorities to secure the success of his visit and by thewarmth and friendliness of his discussions there. In addition to along private Audience with the Pope he had met the CardinalSecretary of State and the two Archbishops with most influence onVatican policy. Normally, the Pope did not make a public statementafter private Audiences; but on this occasion he had wished to do so and had also departed from precedent in discussing the draft withthe British Minister in advance. The statement had been satisfactory,particularly in relation to the problem of Northern Ireland in so faras it had condemned violence without the usual qualifications. Hehad emphasised to the Pope that the most helpful action which hecould now take would be to persuade the representatives of the roman Catholic community to take part in the discussions aboutconstitutional reform.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ statement.
IndustrialAffairsMeetingswith theConfederationof BritishIndustry andthe TradesUnionCongressPreviousReference:CM (72) 43rdConclusions,Minute 4CONFIDENTIAL3.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, although no firminformation was available, it seemed likely that the Press reports ofthe counter-proposals which the Economic Committee of the TradeUnion Congress (TUC) would be recommending the TUC to putforward in reply to the Governments proposals as outlined in the annex to CP (72) 99 were broadly correct. If so, the figure of  3 - 50which they were reported as advocating as the level of flat rate wage increase should be compared not with the Governments proposed 2 but with the rate of average earnings of  2 - 60 with which the  2flat rate would be compatible. The counter-proposals were likely tocomprise concessions by the Government on rents, Value added tax, dividends and pensions; and the TUC would also be concerned about the efficacy of the machinery for monitoring both retail prices and the incomes of individuals who were self-employed.   further work on all these matters was in hand.   It would be desirable toavoid public comment on reports about the tuc&apos;s proposals inadvance of the tripartite meeting on 16 October, although further efforts should be made to impress on public opinion the substanceand the fairness of the Governments proposals and to emphasise, inparticular, the basic fact that the higher the increase in pay the largerthe increase in prices and the less the chance of curbing inflationwould be. The Ministerial Steering Committee on Pay negotiations had agreed guidelines for dealing with pay negotiations during october against the background of the proposals put to the Con-federation of British Industry (CBI) and the TUC.  The Committeehad also agreed that officials should review all outstanding pay claims and should refer those which did not conform to the guidelinesfor a decision by Ministers.   They had agreed that it would be helpful to try to ensure that, in those cases where an offer had beenoutstanding when the Governments proposals were published, asettlement would be reached before the next tripartite discussions,provided that the unions themselves sought a settlement on the basisof the existing offer and that the latter was not increased. It wouldbe made clear at any meetings with the unions on such cases thatthe offer would lapse if it had not been accepted by the time when a tripartite agreement had been reached; and the announcementrelating to any such settlements would make it clear that theGovernment had acquiesced in the settlement only because a firmoffer was outstanding.   The Secretary of State for employment would co-ordinate the publicity in all such cases in consultation withthe Home Secretary and Lord President of the Council and thePrime Ministers Press Office.In discussion the following were the main points made:(a) It would be necessary to be prepared to answer the claim ofthe TUC that a 6 per cent rate of growth in the economy should be practicable rather than the 5 per cent rate on which the Govern-menfs proposals were based.(b) It was important that, if employers in the private sectorsought advice on the procedure to be adopted in relation to currentpay negotiations, they should be firmly advised not to make any offer
at the present time. If, as had happened in the case of the staff ofthe British Petroleum refinery at Llandarcy, an offer of an increaseof even  2 was made, this would merely serve as the basis for further negotiations which would increase the present difficulties.(c) The Chairman of the Electricity Council appeared confidentof his ability to defer the negotiations on the electricity manual workers&apos; claim without precipitating industrial action.id) There was a particular problem in the case of agricultural workers in Scotland, where the Scottish Agricultural Wages board was expected to announce a substantial increase well in excess of 2 on 24 October. Although the Government had no formal powers in the matter, the position had been discussed informally with theChairman of the Board, who had agreed to defer the Boards decision and the consequent announcement from 2 October to 24 October.But the timing might still give rise to embarrassment in the context of the further tripartite discussions. There was a case for seeking afurther postponement of the announcement.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that, whileit would be important to make progress at the tripartite meeting on16 October, not least because of the expiry on 31 October of theCBFs extended period of price restraint, it would not be possible to formulate the Governmenfs response to the tuc&apos;s counter-proposals until it was known more clearly which of them the TUCregarded as most important. The discussions must reflect a rationalapproach to the problems of inflation; and it would in any event benecessary to press the TUC about their ability to enforce any agreed proposals which depended upon the co-operation of their members.Further publicity for the Governmenfs proposals should be arranged,in order to emphasise that they were based on substantial prelimi-nary discussion between the three parties and that any modificationmust be acceptable on a tripartite basis as contributing to the controlof inflation. Further consideration should be given to the most appropriate means of dealing with the pay increase for Scottishagricultural workers.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland, in consultationwith the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food,and the Secretary of State for Employment, to consider further, in the light of the discussion, the means ofdealing with the pay increase for Scottish agricultural workers.CONFIDENTIALTelevision of 4.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the secretary the Proceedings of State for the Home Department and Lord President of the Councilof the House (CP (72) 100) on television of the proceedings of the House ofof Commons    Commons.
The Home Secretary and Lord President of the Council said that before the Summer Adjournment he had announced that there wouldbe a debate on 19 October on the question of an experiment in the broadcasting of the proceedings of the House of Commons. Theissue should be regarded as very much a matter for decision by theHouse. The debate should therefore take place on a Motion putdown in the names of Private Members who were prominentadvocates of the broadcasting of proceedings; and there should bea free vote. He himself would speak in the debate; but, so far asthe Government were concerned, he would simply say that theywould abide by the decision of the House. Fie would, however,state his personal belief that the broadcasting of proceedings wouldbe in the interests of Parliament; and he would also provide infor-mation about the form which the proposed experiment might take.It was envisaged that it should last three weeks and that it shouldcomprise the television and sound broadcasting proceedings of theHouse of Commons and the sound broadcasting only of the pro-ceedings in the House of Lords. It was essential that the experimentshould be public; the broadcasting authorities were strongly of thesame view and had little or no interest in a closed-circuit experiment.Although a public experiment would be contrary to the proposal ofthe Select Committee in 1966 and there might therefore be rather less chance that it would enlist a favourable vote, it would have theadvantage of securing that Members would have the opportunity to assess not only the way in which proceedings were broadcast butalso the public&apos;s reaction and the effect of public broadcasting on theconduct of proceedings. The broadcasting authorities&apos; proposalsfor possible experimental programmes as indicated in Annex A to cp (72) 100, were acceptable as a basis for discussion. But assur-ances would be needed that the coverage would be fair and balancednot only in Party political terms but also in relation to the standing andreputation of the House. While it v/ould not be practicable or desir-able to seek to exercise censorship over the content of broadcastsand, indeed, the broadcasting authorities would not proceed on any basis other than their ultimate editorial independence, both authori-ties had general obligations to maintain due balance and impartialityand had indicated that they would be willing to consider givingundertakings relating those obligations to the specific circumstancesof the experiment. It would probably be undesirable that any formalrestrictions should be imposed on the broadcasting authorities in thisrespect, except that their broadcasts should be confined to proceed-ings in the Chamber; but the assurances to be required of them would need careful thought and should be embodied in a formal exchangeof correspondence. Certain installations and enchanced lightingwould be required in the House for the experiment; and the effects of these, which would be varied as far as possible in order to demon-strate alternative options, would have to be judged by the House.While the lighting requirement for colour television was high the broadcasting authorities were confident that the effects of glare andheat could be kept to tolerable limits. The arrangements for the experiment should be examined by a special Sub-Committee of theHouse of Commons Services Committee in consultation with theHouse authorities, the broadcasting authorities and the Department
of the Environment. If the experiment was public, the maximumcost to public funds would be  2,000, to be borne on the vote of theDepartment of the Environment; but, if the experiment were bymeans of a closed-circuit, the broadcasting authorities would requirethe reimbursement of their expenses. If the House decided in favourof the public experiment, it might conveniently take place in theearly summer of 1973.In discussion some concern was expressed that the broadcastingof proceedings might have an adverse effect on the character ofParliament. Moreover, it must be open to question whether the broadcasting authorities would succeed in providing balancedcoverage and impartiality; and there was some risk that they wouldattach more importance to entertainment content than to theprovision of informative programmes which would enhance the reputation of Parliament. On the other hand there was support forthe view that the broadcasting of proceedings would prove to be inthe general interests of Parliament; and it was right that a decision whether to hold the proposed experiment should be left to the Houseof Commons. The provision of a separate television channel allottedwholly to broadcasting the proceedings of the House in full or,alternatively, the institution of programmes prepared under thecontrol of the House itself, might be preferable; but these courseswould involve practical difficulties. An experiment in the early summer might involve inconvenience to Members as a result of the extra heat generated by the additional lighting; but the broadcasting authorities were confident that new techniques would reduce heatand glare. At present there was no demand for proceedings in theHouse of Lords to be televised; but, if the House of Commonsintroduced permanent arrangements for televising their proceedings,there would undoubtedly be pressure for similar arrangements in theUpper House.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet approved in principle the proposals in CP (72) 100. Membersof Parliament, including Ministers, would have a free vote on the motion. The Leader of the House, in speaking in the debate, wouldbe entitled to indicate his personal views; but he should also makeit clear that the Government regarded the matter as one for decision by the House and did not seek to influence that decision one way orthe other. He should speak frankly about the problems of ensuringbalanced coverage and impartiality in the broadcasts; the need toprovide a means for considering complaints in this context; andthe prospects of avoiding inconvenience to Members from heatand glare. /The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Home Secretary and Lord President of theCouncil to make arrangements for the debate on broad-casting of the proceedings of the House of Commons onthe basis indicated in CP (72) 100, taking account of thepoints made in the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.
confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for the Environment (CP (72) 101) about the implications ofthe rating revaluation which was due to come into force on 1 April,1973.The Secretary of State for the Environment said that theGeneral Rate Act, 1967, required new valuation lists to come intoforce on 1 April, 1973. The Valuation Office had been at work onthe lists for nearly three years; and they were now virtually complete.Because the previous Government had cancelled the quinquennialrevaluation due in 1968, rateable values were now 10 years old; andthe new lists would show large increases. For the domestic sector,which accounted for about half the total rateable value, the increase would be about 2% times present values, the value of modern housesbeing expected to rise more than old and the value of flats andmaisonettes to approach more closely that of houses. Values forshops and offices, particularly in London, would rise rather more,values for industry rather less; and geographical variations would bereduced. The average increases for all property would be about\ times present values. The extent of this increase would be disclosed when regulations about the rating of the electricity industry, which must take effect before 15 November and wouldrequire approval by Affirmative Resolution in both Houses ofParliament, were laid immediately after the Recess. Althoughhigher rateable values should lead to a corresponding reduction ofrates in the pound, it would be several months before the public would know the new level of rates; and, unless measures were takento anticipate misunderstanding, some public alarm and criticismmust be expected. The revaluation could be postponed by legislation,as in 1968; but, apart from the criticism which such a step would attract, postponement by one or even two years would create greatproblems for the new local authorities, particularly in relation to the uncertainty about rate revenue which would arise from appealsimmediately following the revaluation; and the longer the postpone-ment, the more the rating system, for which there was no alternativeas the principal source of local revenue, would risk falling into disrepute. Special measures might be taken to allay public disquiet,including the distribution, when the valuation lists were published at the end of the year, of a leaflet (a draft of which had been circulated to members of the Cabinet) explaining the reasons forrevaluation and its implications for ratepayers.In discussion it was suggested that the temporary advantage tobe gained from deferring revaluation would lead to added difficultieslater and that there would, in general, be public understanding ofthe need to maintain a realistic balance between the rateable values of different types of property. In Scotland revaluation had takenplace in the previous year; and the measures then taken to allaypublic disquiet, which had included the distribution of a leafletsimilar to that proposed by the Secretary of State for the Environ-ment, had had considerable success. On the other hand revaluationat the present time would be liable to cause concern among the1973Revaluationfor Rates
CONFIDENTIAL 11Governmenfs supporters and might lead to the whole basis of the rating system being called in question. This in turn might raisefundamental issues about the impact on the rates of expenditure on education and the financial and administrative structure of theeducation services.In further discussion it was emphasised that it would be important to ensure that changes in the level of rates should conform with the Governmenfs criteria for the restraint of price increases.This might in part be achieved by means of the level of rate support grant; but the Exchequer should not be expected to bear the whole burden and savings in local authorities expenditure should also besecured.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet would wish to give further consideration to this problembefore the regulations relating to the electricity industry were laid inParliament. They would wish to consider, in particular, the extentto which local authorities could be induced, through the machineryof the rate support grant or by other means, to conform with themeasures of price restraint which should emerge from the Govern-ment s discussions with the Confederation of British Industry and theTrades Union Congress; and they would also wish to consider thepublic presentation of the Secretary of State&apos;s proposals and theextent to which it was practicable, in view of the likely increase in local authority costs and changes in the relative values of different types of property, to give ratepayers the simple reassurance whichthey would expect.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.Cabinet Office,6 October, 1972.


</content>
</cab>
