<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/50/53 images: 516-532</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. January 1975CM (72)52nd conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in thePrime Ministers Room, House of Commons,on Wednesday, 15 November, 1972,at 4 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. edward the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber,mp, Chancellor of the Exchequer(Items 5 and 6)The Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mp; Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry .The Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for EmploymentHeath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for Defence (items-6)The Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Sir Geoffrey Howe,qc, mp, Minister for Trade and consumer Affairs (Items 1-4)
CM (72)52nd conclusions this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. January 1975Copy No.   01CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in thePrime Ministers Room, House of Commons,on Wednesday, 15 November, 1972,at 4 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber,mp, Chancellor of the Exchequer(Items 5 and 6)The Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mpj Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for Trade and industry the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for Defence (items-6)The Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,q c, m p, Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Sir Geoffrey Howe,qc, mp, Minister for Trade and consumer Affairs (Items 1-4)
The following were also present:The Right Hon. The Viscount Eccles,Paymaster-General (Item 6)Mr.   Patrick   Jenkin,   mp,   chief secretary, treasury mr. Paul Channon, mp, Minister for housing and Construction (Item 5)The Right Hon. Sir John Eden, mp,Minister of Posts and telecommunications-cations (Item 6)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury(Items 1-5)The Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-General (Item 4)The Right Hon. Norman Wylie, qc,m p, Lord Advocate (Item 4)Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. J. B. hunt mr. H. F. T. smith mr. K. T. barnett mr. J. anson mr. I. T. lawman mr. H. F. Ellis-ReesContentsItem Subject page 1     Parliamentary Affairs       ...............      3Motions Relating to the Immigration Rules for Controlof Entry and Control after EntryLocal Government Boundary OrderLegislative Programme 1972-732     Oversea Affairs ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...      5Icelandic Fisheries Dispute3     Industrial Affairs     ...     .........     ...     ...      5Measures to Restrain InflationHousing Finance Act4    Civil Liability for Personal Injury      .........      65     Whitehall Redevelopment   ...     ...     ...     ......      86    Public Expenditure to 1976-77     ...     .........     10
ParliamentaryAffairsMotionsRelating to theImmigrationRules for control of entry andControl afterEntryLocalGovernmentBoundaryOrderThe Secretary of State for the Environment said that he proposed to publish on 21 or 22 November the Report of the LocalGovernment Boundary Commission defining the new districts in theEnglish non-metropolitan counties and to announce at the sametime that the Government accepted its recommendations withoutamendment. The Order which would be necessary to give effectto the adjustments would be laid in draft immediately thereafter.Since it was essential that it should be made before the end of theyear, it would be necessary for the requisite Affirmative resolution to be passed by each House before the Christmas Recess.The Cabinet 1.   Took note, with approval, of the statement by the Secretaryof State for the Environment.LegislativeProgramme1972-73PreviousReference:CM (72) 51stConclusions,Minute 1The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the legislative programme for the 1972-73 Session.The Lord President of the Council said that, in consultationwith the Chief Whip, he had now completed his review of thelegislative programme. In order to provide the legislative time forthe additional Bills required to give effect to the Governmenfscounter-inflationary policies, together with the further legislation which would be needed on Northern Ireland, it would be necessaryto defer a number of measures. These might include either theBill on Water Reorganisation or the Bill on the Third london airport; the Bill on Insurance; the measure on Employment ofChildren I Work Experience for School Pupils; and the Bill on training and Employment. It had been agreed that the public trustee Bill should be deferred; and the Unoccupied Office PropertiesBill clearly could not be accommodated. The Spot-the-Ball Billshould also be considered for deferment; but it might proveunavoidably necessary to introduce it. The/ provisions required onthe assessment of graduated national insurance contributions shouldnot be the subject of a separate Bill but should be incorporated in aprogrammed Bill; and any measures providing for compensation to nationalised undertakings for price restraint should be includedin the Bill dealing with the sound stage of the counter-inflationarypolicies.Unless the legislative programme were lightened on the lines which he had indicated, the Bills to which the Government must give1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.In the debate which would take place on the Motions relatingto the Immigration Rules for Control of Entry and Control afterEntry it would be necessary to be ready to rebut criticisms of the government&apos;s immigration policy and to demonstrate, in particular,that the procedures which it entailed were both adequate for their purpose and fair as between one category of immigrant and another.
priority would be jeopardised and the Government would be subjectto severe criticism for inflicting on Parliament a wholly unreasonableburden of legislation. Deferred Bills might still be included in theReserve List; and their drafting should proceed as resourcespermitted, in order that they might be introduced without delay if inthe event it proved possible to find time for them.In discussion there was general agreement that it would be preferable not to make any announcement at this stage that someBills would have to be deferred. The Bill on Water Reorganisationwas an essential part of the reorganisation of local government whichwas due to take effect in the near future; and it would therefore bemore difficult to enact in the following Session. It might prove possible, however, to make it less controversial and to reach under-standings with the local authority associations who were at presentopposed to it. The Bill on the Third London Airport was requiredin the current Session if the opening of the airport was not to be deferred beyond the planned date of 1980; and it would be necessaryto decide by 20 November whether to deposit plans of the work, as required under the relevant Standing Orders. The Bill on training and Employment constituted an element in the Governmenfseconomic strategy which had hitherto been regarded as essential;and its deferment would be liable, by prejudicing the Governmenfsrelationships with the trade unions, to hamper the development ofthe second stage of the counter-inflationary policies. It might provesuitable for introduction in the House of Lords if one of themeasures which it had been planned to introduce into that Housewere deferred. The Bill on Insurance was needed because theGovernment would incur severe criticism if another insurance scandaloccurred before the deficiencies of the existing law had been rectified;but it should be possible to effect a substantial reduction in its scale.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet accepted in principle that some reduction in the legislative programme must be secured. No announcement of any defermentof Bills, however, should be made at the present stage; and theCabinet would need to give further consideration to the matter earlyin December. Meanwhile, the Lord President of the Council should consider, in consultation with the Secretary of State for the environment, whether the preliminary steps relating to the third london Airport Bill might be authorised in advance of the legislation committee&apos;s examination of the draft Bill.The Cabinet 2. Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion and agreed to resume considerationof the legislative programme early in December.3. Invited the Lord President of the Council, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for the Environment, toconsider whether the preliminary steps relating to theThird London Airport Bill might be authorised.
OverseaAffairsIcelandicFisheriesDisputePreviousReference:CM (72) 48thConclusions,Minute 2SECRET2. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that theposition which the Government of Iceland were likely to adopt inthe resumed negotiations about fisheries limits afforded little prospectof agreement. But it would be unwise to reject the offer of further discussions since the Icelandic authorities could then be expected to resume harassment of our trawlers, which would be forced to confine their fishing to very limited areas under naval protection. the icelandic Foreign Minister, Mr. Augustsson, was therefore beinginformed that the Minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs, Lady Tweedsmuir, and the Minister of State, Ministerof Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, would visit Reykjavik on26 November for a further discussion of the issues involved.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said that,if the Government of Iceland were allowed to suppose that we wereprepared to negotiate indefinitely, they would simply harden their position still further. Despite the obvious difficulties, therefore, weshould consider whether we might do better to show greaterdetermination to protect our fishermen by deploying rather largernaval forces for this purpose than we had hitherto been willing to contemplate.  This possibility would require further discussion.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.IndustrialAffairsMeasuresto RestrainInflationPreviousReference:CM (72) 51stConclusions,Minute 3CONFIDENTIAL3. The Secretary of State for Employment said that there was evidence that, under pressure from the unions, some employersregarded themselves as free to negotiate, during the standstill period,pay settlements which would take effect when that period had ended.Such settlements, however, could well conflict with the policy to beadopted after the end of the standstill and would then have to berenegotiated. It was therefore desirable to make it clear publicly thatthe Government did not wish employers to enter into negotiations on pay increases before the guidelines for the period after the end ofthe standstill had been announced. The most suitable way of achieving this would be for a Minister, speaking in the debate on the counter-Inflation (Temporary Provisions) Bill in the House ofCommons, to indicate that the Government did not intendnegotiations in the public sector to take place in advance of publicationof the guidelines and would expect private sector employers to adoptthe same policy. This would make it clear that it was not intended that there should be any discrimination between the two sectors. he proposed to discuss with the Chancellor of the Exchequer the termsof a statement on these lines.The Cabinet 1.  Took note, with approval, of the statement by the Secretaryof State for Employment.
require them to remedy the default within two weeks. It was proposed, on the following day, to institute the first extraordinaryaudit in the case of Clay Cross, the authority who were adopting themost intransigent attitude. Most of the other authorities could probably be persuaded to comply with the requirements of thelegislation.The Secretary of State for Wales said that at the beginning ofthat week default orders had been made against the only twoauthorities in Wales who remained in default. These would give them 23 days in which to send out the notices of increase in rents,which would then take effect after Christmas.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that he had deferredthe interim payment of the residual element in the housing subsidy in the case of the 21 authorities who remained in default in Scotland.Four public inquiries, as a necessary preliminary to the making ofdefault orders, were to be held during the following week. He had made it clear that there could be no question of amending thelegislation; and he might find it necessary to seek the Cabinefsagreement to further public inquiries at the end of November.The Cabinet 2.  Took note of the statements by the Secretaries of State forthe Environment, for Wales and for Scotland.3.  Agreed to review the position again during the week beginning 27 November.SECRETCivil Liability 4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Lordfor Personal Chancellor and the Secretary of State for Social Services (CP (72) 123)Injury about civil liability for personal injury.The Lord Chancellor said that liability for personal injury was at present based on the concept of &quot; fault&quot;; but an alternative systemof &quot; no fault liability &quot;, which had been adopted by a number of othercountries, had been canvassed for several years. The RobensCommittee on Safety and Health at Work (Cmnd. 5034) had recentlyrecommended an inquiry into the question of employers&apos; liability.It had originally been envisaged that such an inquiry should belimited to accidents at work, although it might extend to include,in addition, accidents on the road. An inquiry so restricted mightanticipate the risk of an unacceptable recommendation in favour ofa State insurance scheme. After discussion with the Secretary of StateHousing The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the steps whichFinance might be taken to deal with local authorities who maintained theirAct refusal to give effect to the provisions of the housing financePrevious legislation.Reference:CM (72) 46th The Secretary of State for the Environment said that defaultConclusions, orders had that week been made against three of the eight localMinute 6 authorities in England who remained in default. These orders would
for Social Services, however, he had concluded that, in view of thepublic and Parliamentary concern about the adequacy of the prospective compensation for the children who had suffered injurybefore birth as a result of the administration of the drug thalidomide,a more wide-ranging inquiry could not now be avoided. It should bepossible to satisfy an appropriate Royal Commission that any schemeproviding for compensation without the need to prove negligenceshould be supported by private insurance and not by the State andthat a State scheme, in addition to being very expensive, could not provide benefits on an adequate scale in all cases. The Home and social Affairs Committee had accordingly endorsed his proposal that a Royal Commission should be appointed on this basis.In discussion some doubt was expressed whether the need for socomprehensive an inquiry had been fully established. The widerits scope the more probably it would recommend in favour of a state scheme of compensation; and the Government could not subsequentlyreject such a recommendation without provoking acute controversy.Nor could such an inquiry provide any relief for the thalidomidevictims beyond the remedies under the existing law which they were already pursuing in the courts, since any changes in the law could notbe given retrospective effect. On the other hand there was nowconsiderable public dissatisfaction both about the apparentlyinconsistent and arbitrary manner in which the present system of liability operated and about the delays which occurred in theconsideration of claims for compensation. A wide-ranging inquiry would probably become inevitable sooner or later; and theGovernment should therefore take the initiative by conceding it inprinciple forthwith, while ensuring that the evidence to be submittedto it would be balanced and objective, particularly as regards theobjections to a State scheme of compensation.In further discussion the Cabinet were informed that judgmentsin the actions for contempt of court in relation to the thalidomidecases were expected to be given within the next few days. It was to be hoped that a dispassionate account by the court of the facts of thesecases would serve to present them in their correct perspective andto rectify the distortions which public opinion had imported intodiscussion of the issues involved, to the damage of the victimsthemselves. The administration of justice in this country was beingprogressively impeded by irresponsible and unscrupulous pressuresof the kind which had characterised the thalidomide cases.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that, on balance, a Royal Commission should beappointed to consider the basis of liability for personal injury.Before this decision could be announced, however, it would benecessary to give urgent consideration to a number of detailedquestions1, including the membership and terms of reference ofthe Commission; the provision of supporting staff; the form inwhich the Governmenfs decision should be presented; and thearrangements for any subsequent debate. It would also be necessaryto consider urgently the arrangements for preparing the evidence tobe submitted to the Commission by the Government. The Lord
Chancellor, in consultation with the Ministers principally concerned,should consider these questions urgently and should endeavour toreport the conclusions as early as possible in the following week.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Home Department (CP (12) 120) about proposals toredevelop sites in Whitehall for Government accommodation.The Home Secretary said that the Ministerial Committee on regional Policy and the Environment had recently examined theproblem of Government accommodation in Whitehall. Soon afterthe Government came into office, they had received the report of apublic inquiry under Mr. Harold Willis, qc which had reviewedcertain proposals to build Government offices on the area nowoccupied in part by Richmond Terrace and the Norman Shaw Northbuilding, which had formerly been used by the Metropolitan Police.The report, on which no decision had yet been taken, had recommen-ded the preservation of both the Norman Shaw North building andthe facade of Richmond Terrace. This, however, would entail a largereduction in the 4,000 places to be provided by the new government offices which it had originally been intended to erect on those sites;and it would involve considerable additional expenditure. The futureof the Old Public Offices was also a matter of concern. Much of the accommodation which they provided was in poor condition; but therewas a strong body of public opinion in favour of preserving thisbuilding also.The cost of building new offices to house 8,000 staff on these siteshad been estimated at  21 million. If the three buildings in question were now to be preserved, the extra cost arising from the reducedcapacity of the sites had been estimated at  8 million if the staffaffected were accommodated on the London periphery, at  23 millionif they were moved to a South Bank site and at  38 millionif they were retained in Whitehall but on another site. In addition, 2 million would be required to develop the Norman Shaw Northbuilding as a police station to replace Cannon Row.The Committee had concluded that in thCse circumstances adecision on the future of the buildings involved, which was nowseriously overdue, must be distinguished from decisions about the accommodation of Government Departments. They had agreed inprinciple that Richmond Terrace, the Norman Shaw North building and the facades of the Old Public Offices should be preserved. Theyhad recognised that this decision would entail a complete reassessmentof existing plans for the rehousing of Government staffs in Whitehall;and they had put this review in hand as a matter of urgency. But itwould inevitably take time; and, in view of the importance of theWhitehallRedevelopment
area, the public interest in proposals for its redevelopment and thedelay which had already occurred, they had considered that, if theCabinet endorsed their proposals, it would be right to announce the decision to preserve the three buildings as soon as possible.In discussion it was suggested that, although the demolition ofthese buildings might have been tolerated at an earlier stage, the tideof public opinion was now running more strongly in favour ofconservation. The Norman Shaw North building and the OldPublic Offices were listed as Grade 1 and Richmond Terrace asGrade 2*. No Grade 1 building which was capable of preservationhad ever been demolished; and, if the Government were to departfrom this precedent in the interests of providing better accommo-dation for their own staffs, their efforts to preserve such buildingselsewhere would cease to carry conviction. There was also a wide-spread feeling that the character of London had been greatlydamaged by hasty and ill-considered development; and there was little public confidence that if the buildings involved in the present case were demolished, they would be worthily replaced. Theirpreservation would not preclude some improvement in the accommodation now available; and the extra costs could be significantly reduced if alternative accommodation for the staffsconcerned were found elsewhere than in the Whitehall area.This need not be a disadvantage, since the dispersal of a Departmentamong a large number of buildings in Central London was arguablymore of a handicap to efficient administration than its concentration in a single building on the periphery.On the other hand the Government could not afford to accept that buildings should be preserved regardless of cost, which in this case must be measured not merely in relation to the expenditure involved but also in terms of the efficiency of the Government service.The Departments whose accommodation would be reduced by theproposal to preserve the buildings in question were among those whose business particularly required them to be located near thecentre of Government. Moreover, the merits of the buildings them-selves were not beyond dispute; and the current enthusiasm forindiscriminate conservation reflected a reluctance to face changes,many of which were highly desirable. The Government shouldbeware of allowing themselves to be driven by the outcry ofpreservationist cliques into costly and unjustified decisions whichmust ultimately be paid for by the general body of taxpayers.In further discussion it was suggested that this question must also be considered in relation to the proposed redevelopment ofCovent Garden, on which a decision would soon be needed. Even ifthe current controversy about the proposals in this context resultedin their being resubmitted in a more modest form, the size of any contribution to their irriplementation which the Government mightbe prepared to offer to the Greater London Council could be affectedby the cost of the proposals for Whitehall.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet accepted on balance that the three buildings in question should be preserved. Nevertheless, they were concerned about the
implications of this decision in terms both of the expenditure entailedand of the efficiency of the public service; and the further studieswhich had been commissioned must take particular account of these aspects. The Cabinet also agreed that the announcement of the government&apos;s decision to preserve the buildings need not await the outcome of these studies. The Secretary of State for the Environmentshould accordingly consult the Home Secretary and the lord president about the timing and content of a public statement tothis effect. The statement should avoid reference to the question of costs; and its bearing on the proposals for a new Parliamentarybuilding in Bridge Street should also be taken into account. these decisions, however, had been partly forced on the Government by thecircumstances of the case; and they did not imply any new decisionof principle. Indeed, in the light of the Cabinet&apos;s discussion it wouldbe necessary to review the Governmenfs attitude both to theproposed redevelopment of Covent Garden and to any other caseswhere a contribution to the costs of conservation might be soughtfrom public funds.The Cabinet-1. Agreed that plans for the future development of Whitehallshould be based on the preservation of RichmondTerrace, the Norman Shaw North building and the external facades of the Old Public Offices.2. Took note that the Ministerial Committee on regional policy and the Environment had commissioned an examination of the implications of this decision for thefuture accommodation of Government Departments.3.   Invited the Secretary of State for the Environment (a) To consider, in consultation with the Home secretary and the Lord President of the Council, the timing and content of a public announcement of the government&apos;s decision to preserve the buildings in question and to arrange for it to be prepared in consultation with the Prime Ministers PressSecretary.(b) To circulate to the Ministerial Committee on regional policy and the Environment a memorandumreviewing, in the light of this decision, the government&apos;s attitude to the redevelopment ofCovent Garden.PublicExpenditureto 1976-77PreviousReference:CM (72) 36thConclusions,Minute 5SECRET6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (CP (72) 121) reporting the outcome of had discussions with Ministers about the proposals for additional expenditure noted in the 1972 report of the Public Expenditure survey committee (PESC). They also had before them a memorandum(CP (72) 122) by the Central Policy Review Staff (CPRS), examining the implications of public expenditure in general.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that at their meetingon 13 July the Cabinet had agreed that the growth of public expenditure between 1971-72 and 1976-77 should not exceed anaverage annual rate of 3 - 8 per cent in terms of use of resources andthat the total for public expenditure in 1976-77 should not exceed 30,300 million. The Prime Minister had subsequently circulated a minute to the Cabinet on 15 September stressing the importanceof keeping within this limit. He and the Chief Secretary, Treasury,had now discussed with the Ministers concerned the problems of priorities entailed in various proposals for additional expenditure which had been noted in the 1972 PESC report. He was grateful forthe efforts which these Ministers had made either to reduce or rephaseexpenditure or to offset extra spending. As a result, the original proposals for additional expenditure totalling  843 million in the annex to CP (72) 121 had been reduced; but proposals amounting tosome  200 million net were still outstanding. If these were to beaccepted without being offset by savings elsewhere, they would raisethe annual rate of growth of public expenditure from 3 - 8 per cent to4 per cent; and they would pre-empt part of the contingency reserve.Probable claims on that reserve already amounted to  650 millionout of the  750 million which had been allotted for 1976-77; and to add the outstanding proposals would leave no room either for new policy developments or for any additional commitments flowing fromthe counter-inflationary measures which the Government were nowintroducing.The decision by the Cabinet in July had been taken for both political and economic reasons. The Government had gained greatcredit for their initial decision in 1970 to reduce the annual rate of growth of public expenditure; and in the last public expenditure white Paper this had stood at no more than 3-2 per cent. If this figure were increased beyond 3 - 8 per cent, which was approximately the rate of growth in the expenditure programmes which the Govern-ment had inherited from the previous Administration, this would belikely to evoke considerable criticism from the Govermenfssupporters, who were already concerned about the rapid growth in public expenditure and the money supply. Indeed, even an increaseof this order would be difficult to defend when retail sales wereincreasing at an unprecedented rate. From the economic standpoint,one of the main pillars of the Governmenfs policy had been the achievement of faster economic growth. While the present growth rate was high, the slack would eventually be taken up and the public and private sectors would then be competing for resources. Thememorandum by the Central Policy Review Staff was right toemphasise that there would inevitably be growing pressures forincreased expenditure and that there would also be unforeseen events which might require further increases. It also suggested that theGovernment were over-committed on public expenditure and thatthere were serious risks that either hasty and damaging economiesmight be necessary in the lifetime of the present Parliament or thatthe Government would fail to achieve their objectives as regards thereduction of taxation. It should be possible to avoid this situationif the annual rate of increase of public expenditure was limited to3-8 per cent; but any increase above this level would be damaging to international confidence in the economy.
On the other hand a further detailed examination of spendingprogrammes to yield sufficient savings to provide the necessaryuncommitted margin while maintaining the 3 - 8 per cent limit wouldtake still more time; the publication of the White Paper would be delayed; and this would threaten the confidence which was nowbeing re-established as a result of the Governmenfs action to stabilisepay and prices. The White Paper should accordingly be published as early as possible in December. But it would remain important toensure that the continuing examination of the programmes, togetherwith any necessary re-assessment of policies, was fully effective in keeping total expenditure under control and preserving a correctbalance of priorities. It was also necessary to reach a clear under-standing now that, as plans for the programmes were rolled forward for 1977-78, the Government should not again run the risks whichthey would be taking this year in relation to 1976-77 and that the rateof increase of each programme should therefore be submitted tocritical scrutiny with no presumption that the rates in thisyear&apos;s White Paper could be continued. Subject to these provisos,and provided that a satisfactory solution was found to the outstanding points on certain programmes noted in the Annex to CP (72) 121, hewas prepared to recommend the Cabinet to accept the position now reached as a basis for drafting the White Paper.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that, since CP (72) 121 hadbeen circulated, further progress had been made in resolving some ofthe issues noted in its Annex. In the trade and industry programme,the Secretary of State had been prepared to reduce the additional demand for steel investment from  100 million to  50 million; and hehad also suggested that a provision of  100 million for assistance tothe coal industry in 1976-77 might be omitted from the programme on the grounds that the relevant legislation would only be effective for three years. While the latter provision would remain a potentialclaim on the contingency reserve, the net effect of these changes was toreduce the programme by  50 million. The Secretary of State for social Services had agreed to hold the programme for health and personal social services to its existing level and to withdraw proposalsfor specific improvements in social security benefits (other than forincrements for deferred retirement). As regards pension upratings,the Secretary of State had proposed that provision should bemade for a real increase of 80 per cent of the differencebetween prices and earnings and that there should be a lower rate ofuprating for supplementary and short-term benefits. This proposal,however, had been made before the recent tripartite discussions aboutpay and prices between the Government and botrj, sides of industry;and there must be some doubt whether, in the light of the expectationsgenerated during those discussions, it would in practice be possibleto increase benefits at a slower rate than earnings. Here, therefore,was another potential claim on the contingency reserve. Theeducation programme at present showed a net increase of  22 million,representing an increase of  40^ million in local authority current expenditure, offset by reductions of  18^ million achieved else wherein the programme. The Secretaries of State for Education and science and for Scotland had agreed to find further savings of 8 million; but a reduction of  14 million was still needed to bring the
education programme as a whole back to the level of the PESC report.The programme of the Department of Employment showed an excessof  47^ million. But most of this was attributable to a proposal for additional housing to assist the mobility of labour; and he hoped thatthe Secretary of State would be prepared to abandon the bulk of theproposed increase. If all the savings which he was now seeking weremade, the excess of about  200 million Would be reduced to about 75 million. This would mean that, in the terms of paragraphs 3 and4 of CP (72) 121, the contingency reserve for 1976-77 would becomemarginally under-committed; but, taking into account the furtherpotential claims which he had mentioned, the real position was stillone of heavy over-commitment.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The increase noted in the education programme was theresult of higher expenditure by local authorities. This was not subjectto direct control by the Government; and it would tend to be encouraged still further by the decision to increase the limit ofexpenditure which could be incurred by local authorities under their general power. Substantial reductions had already been made in anumber of educational programmes, including teacher training andthe proposals for nursery education; and any further reductions would present serious political difficulty. On the other hand thepresent system of public expenditure control was based onfunctional programmes which included local authority as well ascentral government expenditure. The difficulty of reducing localauthority expenditure had already been recognised when it had beenagreed not to seek savings in order to offset the increases in 1971-72which provided the starting point for the present PESC forecasts.The suggestion had been made that the nursery education programmemight be brought forward in order to reduce the excess in 1976-77;but the Secretary of State had felt that this would make the annuallevel of expenditure unacceptably low. There would be both social and political disadvantages in further reducing the proposed level ofexpenditure on nursery education, which had also been cited as the justification for the reduction which had been made in the urban aid programme.ib) In considering the PESC programmes, the proper distinction should be made between different types of expenditure. For example,subsidies to offset price increases might be regarded as having someaffinity with reductions in taxation; and a distinction could also bedrawn between social expenditure and expenditure which was directly related to improving the prospects of economic growth. The increasein present expenditure on steel investment in 1976-77, for instance,represented the peak of important projects for modernising theindustry. Although the method of PESC accounting could not readily be changed, points of this kind should be taken into account when decisions were made.(c) The proposal to remove from the trade and industryprogramme the provision of  100 million for assistance to the coalindustry in 1976-77 might be criticised as unrealistic. It was intended, however, to limit the legislation to a 3-year period on the
basis that, if adequate co-operation within the industry had not been achieved within that period, consideration could be given to a more drastic policy of closing uneconomic pits.(d) The proposal that pension upratings should be limited to80 per cent of the difference between prices and earnings meant thatthe increase in benefit would be of the order of 2 per cent a year in real terms. This was doubtfully realistic in present circumstances.(e) The proposed expenditure on housing to assist labourmobility would have relatively low priority within the programme ofthe Department of Employment. Nevertheless, the proposal was stillworthy of examination; and ways might be sought of achieving the objective by some means which would not involve a charge on public funds.(/) Some reductions had proved possible in forecast expenditureon agricultural support because of the present high level of world prices; but it should not be assumed that such reductions could beachieved in every year. In considering the forecast cost of such support, due weight should be given to the receipts which would beobtained from the European Agricultural Guidance and guarantee fund. These had been taken into account in the PESC report.(g) A saving of  10 million could be achieved by abandoning theproposal for a mid-term census; and the merits of this proposal should therefore be re-examined.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet recognised the considerable efforts which had been made byspending Ministers to implement the decision taken by the Cabineton 13 July. The Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Chief Secretary,Treasury, should now pursue further with the Ministers concerned theremaining outstanding points, with the aim of achieving the objectivesset out in his minute of 15 September and publishing the White paper as early as possible in December. The proposal for a mid-term censusshould also be urgently re-examined. Provided that a satisfactory solution could be found on the various outstanding points, a further discussion in Cabinet at this stage should not be necessary. But theCabinet endorsed the recommendations in paragraph 9b and c of cp (72) 121 for a continuing examination of the programmes withinthe PESC period; and it would be necessary to review progress inthis respect in the New Year.The Cabinet 1.  Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.2.   Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the chief secretary, Treasury (i) to discuss further the remaining outstanding issues withthe Ministers concerned and to report the outcometo the Prime Minister;(ii) to circulate to the Cabinet for consideration a draft ofthe 1972 Public Expenditure White Paper;
(iii) to circulate to the Cabinet for consideration in theNew Year a further report on the progress madein re-examining public expenditure programmes asproposed in paragraph 9b and c of CP (72) 121.3.   Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the proposal fora mid-term census to be urgently re-examined.Cabinet Office,16 November, 1972.


</content>
</cab>
