<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/29/0 images: 112-122</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document Is the Probes-c j*--o^ .8-3.....HiS E-jD r e t.irx NAL COPY 130.CAB I N E T 9CtfNCWTTONS of a Meeting of tbe cabinet held pci 10, nowning Street, S.W., on Wednesday,15th February, 1922, at 12 NooiUP R E S E N Tr-THE PRIME MINISTER (IN THE CHAIR).iThe Right Hon. A.&apos; Chamberlain, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Vi-soount- Birkenhead,Lord Chancellor-.The Right   Hon. E. &apos;Shortt, K.C,M.P.,Secretary of State for HomeAffairs.The Right Hon. W.S. Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of. State for the Colonlers^-.The Right Hon. Sir L. worthington evans, Bart,,M, P., Secretary ofState for War.The Right Hon. S. Baldwin, M. T)1,President of the Board of.Trade.The Right Hon, H.A.L. Fisher, M. P.,President of the Board of Education.The Right Hon. T.J. Macnamara, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon. A*J. Balf$fixr,0,H,,M,P,, Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. jBir Robert Horne,O.B.E. ,K. C.,iirP. , Chancellor ofthe Exchequer.The Most Hon. The Marquess curzon of Kedleston, K. 0. ,0* C, S. I.,G. C. L.E.Secr-etary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. E.S. Montagu, . M.P.\^Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Lord Lee of Fareham,0. B.E. ,K. C.B., First Lord of theAdmiralty,The Right Hon. Sir Alfred mond,Bart*,M.P., Minister of Health,The Right Hon, Sir A. Griff1th-Boscawen, M.P., Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. R, Munro, K.C.,M.P., Secretary for scotland the Right Hon. Sir hamar greenwood, Bart,,K,C,M.P.,Chief Secretary for Ireland,THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTCaptain The Rt. Hon. F.E. Guest, Mr. L.S. Amery, M.P., ParliamentaryC.B.F,,D,S.0*,M.P., Secretary of and Financial Secretary, Admiralty.State for Air,Sir Edward Grigg, K.C.V.0.,C.M.G.Lt.Col. Sir M. P. A. Hankey, G.C.B..........................., Secretary.Lt,Col. Sir J, Chancellor, k.C.W.G.,D.S.O., Principal Assistant Seer tory,C.T.D.
UNEMPLOYMENT AND UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE.

(1) With reference to Cabinet CB (21), Conclusion 6, the Cabinet had before them the following documents on the subject of Unemployment and Unemployment Insurance:-

 Memoranda by the Minister of Labour, (Papers C.P. 3689 and C.P. 3724),

 A Memorandum by the Minister of Health,(Paper C.P.3721).

 After the Minister of Labour had given the Cabinet a short summary of his proposals, and the Chancellor of the Exchequer had expressed his willingness to sanction the expenditure involved by a six weeks&apos; extension of benefit, the Cabinet agreed ---

 That the benefits under the Unemployment Insurance Acts should be continued for another six weeks, subject to conditions generally on the following lines:--

(a) Workers under 18 years of age whom when employed are not dependent on their earnings for their livelihood, should be excluded from the extended rights. This was done in the case of the first extension.

(b) In the case of single men and women and of widowers and widows without children under 14, the extension shall not be granted except on the specific recommendation of the Local Employment Committee, who would be asked to exercise special care in considering such cases, and to ascertain the true facts in each case. The Committees should be told that the extension should not be granted to individuals in this class unless it could be shown that they have relatives wholly or mainly dependant on them and that there was in fact no suitable work available for them.

(c) Local Employment Committees should be directed to have regard to the earnings of short-time workers.

(d) Committees should also be specially directed to examine carefully all cases of persons who have previously drawn Unemployment Benefit for long periods. In the case of women there are manifestly vacancies to which their attention should be directed.
NATIONAL EX-        (S) With reference to Cabinet 8 (22), Conclusion (1)PENDITURF. &apos;   ;*^&apos; the Cabinet had before their the followinp documents or. thenai-&apos;ffentB.     sublet       the Interim Reoort of the Committee on national expenditure (Paper C.P.-3570)Report of Mr Churchill&apos;s Committee onPart I (Paper CP.-3692),Appendices to the above (Paper CP.-3692 A),A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor War (Paper C ,P.-3682),A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor War as an alternative to a Ministryof Defence (Paper C.P.-3681),A Memorandum, by the Admiralty on Relationsbetween the Navy and the Air Force (paper c.P.-3700).The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that hehad circulated to the Cabinet his Report, together with avolume of Appendices showing the observations of theAdmiralty, War Office and Air Force, on the Report of theCommittee, and also the action taken by the Committee inregard to each recommendation of the Geddes Committee.He explained that the Naval Estimates for 1921-22 amountedto  83,000,000,with Supplementary Estimates.   The Chancellorof the Exchequer had earlier in the year asked for&apos;a reducticof those Estimates.   The Admiralty also had before them thoReport of the Cabinet Committee on Capital Ships, and a deci-sion that four capital ships should be built during ,the ensuing year.   The Admiralty had made an effort to reduce their Estimates for 1922-23 so that the cost of the capitalsMpg, which involved an increase of about  12,000,000 inthe Building Vote, should be met from economies made else-where.   The Admiralty had thus effected a reduction of 10,000,000 on the previous year&apos;s Estimates before theysubmitted sketch Estimates to the G^ddes Committee.   thus the sketch Estimates, although they apparently showed areduction of only  2,000,000 as compared with 1921-22, Jiowed an actual reduction of about  12,000,000.   The G*dd-*Committee had stated that in making their recommendations
they did not tak* the Washington Conference Into considers-tion.    &quot;&quot;hey specifW economies of  1^,500,000 exclusive of Washington.   They then added a lump sum of about 7,000,000, raking a total savins of  21,000,000 apartfrom Washington.   Assuming that the savings effectedthrough Washington were from  iO,000,000 to  12,000,000,and that a saving bf  2,000,000 was made on oil reserves,that made a total saving of  35,000,000, which would resultin Naval Estimates of  46,000,000.    The purchasing power of 46,000,000 today was equivalent to  22,000,000 before theWar.   He was certain that such a reduction of the NavalEstimates was impossible.     If there were such a reductionthe one-Power standard could not be maintained and our navy would, sink below the level of that of Japan.   He statedthat his Committee had gone through the Geddes Report indetail and had carefully studied each of their recommenda-tions.   Their action in regard to each recommendation was shown in Appendix IV to his Report3    It was also the dutyof his Corn?ittee to consider the maintenance Of the one-Powfir standard,    ^h^y considered that 15 Battleships infull commission was the minimum number required for thetraining of a sea-going fleet in being.   As regards manning,the numbers before the War wore 159,000,     In the sketchEstimates laid before the Geddes Committee the admiralty had proposed a figure of 121,000.   The Geddes Committee had recommended a reduction to 80,000..     His Committee, in collaboration with the Admiralty, had succeeded in reducingthe number on Vote &quot;A&quot; to 98,000..   He did not consider itwas possible to maintain the Navy as an effective force with fewer men.   If the United States made great reductions in their personnel during the year, the question might ber*-0pened and reviewed in the light of the one-Power standard.   At present the American Navy had an establishment of139,000 men.   Comparing our proposed strength of 98,000
with that Retire, wo were apparently not. maintaining a one-Powpr standard;    *but taking into consideration ourreserve of seafaring population and men trained in theWar, he considered that the figure of 98,000 could be jus-justified.    He felt, however, that the Admiralty should notbe pressed to consent to a lower figure.    In the courseo^ h-ie Commit *-ee&apos;-b examination of the Naval Estimates,pressure had been put upon the Adriralty by a close exam-ination of the complements of ships, the numbers maintained in depots and schools and on shore establishments, and theAdmiralty had reduced the number from 121,000 to 107,000.He then specified an establishment of 95,000, and ashed theAdmiralty to endeavour to put forward a scheme on that basis .He had discussed the question with lord B--atty personally.He alone was sufficiently familiar with the Service to beable to say how that further reduction could be made, andhe appealed to him to do his best to attain that figure.Lord Beatty had applied the whole prestige of his great navalposition to that task, and had managed to bring down thefigure to 98,000, and he hoped the Cabinet &quot;-ould accept that figure.   With regard to the Vote for new construction,his Committee had cut it down as low as possible, and bydelaying the commencement of ships and extending the periodof armour-piercing shell and reducing the Vote for oilroser*res, by which the mobility of the Fleet was compromised,bis Committee was enabled to bring the Estirat^s down to 61,750,000, a saving of  20,750,000 compared with theEstimates of 1921-22.    He was of opinion that there was still roorr. for further Departmental refinements.   His Com-mittee had little time at their disposal, and their decisionswer,a necessarily of a rough and ready character, but he believed that if the Board of Admiralty, in collaboration with the Treasury, were to examine the Estimates in detail,further reductions could be made.   He believed that if theAdmiralty were pressed to make further reductions the NavalMembers of the Board would carry out the instructions of
the Government, hiit th-y would b* compelled to say that th-ywere inconsistent with th/: maintenance       the one-Powerstandard.    If it became widely known that we had abandoned  Ithe one-Po^er standard, our diplomatic position throughout   1the world would he weakened, and it would indicate to theDominions that a new centre had been created &apos;or the Anglo- \Saxon world.   In conclusion, he pointed out &apos;that the ecoh-    Iomies so4- forth in his Coirmi&apos; tee&apos; s Report would produceincreased savings next year, which would, however, be off-set by the increased charges that would fall due for theconstruction of the new capital ships.The Chancellor of the Exchequer expressed the opinionthat Mr Churchill&apos;s Cormittee had done admirable work in the short, time at their disposal.    T-e reminded the Cabinet thatthe people were overburdened with taxation.   Leading membersof the commercial cot&quot;, unity had recently - been impressing upon him that the weight of the present taxation was not onlybtnd^rlnt? the development of new business but was seriouslyha^perinc th*. carrying on of tho present industries.   Theybad informed him that in many cases Income Tax was being paid out of capital, and that if the burden of taxation wasnot relieved in the forthcoming Budget further discharges of workmen would be necessary.   They had impressed upon him that, the only method by &quot;hich taxation could really be re-duced was by a large reduction of expenditure.    The Reportof the fleddes Committee had exercised a great influence onthe minds of the commercial ^community.   Their jriew was that heavy cuts must be made upon the Estimates of the defence departments and on Fducation.   Unfortunately, owing ^o the contracts maa** &quot;lib the teachers as regards, tivdr salaries,the great swing which had been hoped &apos;ror on Education couldnot be effected.   Even If the whole of the economies reopm-mend**d by the G^ddes Committee were effected, there would bea deficit on the Budget for the coming year. . The Chancellor
of the Exchequer then handed round a statement showinga sketch of the Budget, for next year, which had been pre-pared before the appointment of the Geddes Committee.   he asked that these papers should he returned to him, as itwas important that the figures should not be published.He pointed out that it was only by carrying out the re cor.-mendations of the Geddes Committee in full that the Budgetcould be balanced.    If the Pudget were not balanced theGovernment would be exposed to a most formidable attach bythe business community^ and he was doubtful if the Govern-Tnert wpuld survive it.    Fe explained that the recommends-tions of the Geddes Committee at the present time resultedin a saving of  75,000*000 only.    To enable their; to reach 100,000,000.it was necessary for a further saving of 15,000,000 to be rrr.de by taking into account the cutting down of the warship construction programme and the provi-slon ^or oil reserves.   In the above remarks he had not taken into consideration the question of spreading the terminal charges and the pension charges over a period ofyears.   He considered that these steps could only be taken with the object of reducing taxation and that the Budgetmust be balanced irrespective of that measure.    He pointedout *-.hat -*r Churchill&apos;s Committee took into account the saving o-f  1.2,000,000 by the cessatioh of th&quot; constructionof capital ships and the reduction of expenditure on oilreserves.    This l*ft a reduction of only  7,000,000 asagainst the  20,000,000 saving proposed by the Geddes Com-rittee.   He also pointed out that although the personnel0f fhp American Navy stood at 139,000 men, the &quot;Times&quot; ofthat morning had stated that the Secretary of the Navy had proposed to reduce the number to 06,000.The First Lord explained that what was pT &apos;0--was a reduction of the enlisted men by 10,000, to 96,000.That number did not include Marines ^nd officers.    If they
were included,  the total reduced establishment of theAmerican Wavy would be 129,000 to 130,000.The Chancellor of the Exchequer then referred to several ite? s in Appendix VII to Mr ChurchillTs Committee&apos;sF*nort.   *e MHttPd that only  14,500,000 of the geddes committee&apos;s economies were actually specified, and thatthey gave no guidance as to how the balance was to be made up.    The question of personnel was, however, of vitalimportance.    The propposed Committee had recommended an estab-lishment of 88,000 men as against 98,000 proposed by theCabinet Committee.   He urged that the numbers on Vote MA&quot;should be further reduced.The Secretary of State for the Colonies pointed outthat the figures of personnel given In the Geddes Committee&apos;Report contained errors and miscalculations due in soroemeasure to their dealing with the proposed allocations oft^e rven on mobilisation and not with the. peace establishmentThe Chancellor of the Exchequer saSd that Sir eric geddes had written to him and had stated that his Committeehad taken exception to the recently published admiralty memorandum, which used contemptuous language towards them.The Geddes Committee claimed that they had re-exawined theirfigures and were prepared to substantiate them.   They had written to him a letter in this sense for publication.    Hehad felt he could do no less than publish it, and had agreed to do so.The Secretary of State for India suggested that itwas almost impossible for the Government to decide as tot)ia value o^ the recommendations of the Geddes Committeeso long as the facts as regards&apos; the figures remained in dispute.   He had studied the Geddes Committee1s calcula-tions very carefully, as a member of Mr Churchill\sCommittee,  and h* believed that th-ir calculations wsj &quot;wrong not only as regards the Navy but as regards the Arcyand Mr Force as well.   If the propposed Committee could show
that their figures were right and that -further reductionin personnel of the Navy could be made without unduly weak-eninp th* -Javy, such reduction should be made:    but if their figures wer* wrong, the Cabinet could not assent tomake such reductions as might render it impossible for theFleet to put to sea.The Parliamentary and Financial Secretary to theAdmiralty referred to the Admiralty Memorandum and statedthat fepart. from questions of policy the Geddes Committeehad claijr^d to put -forward recommendations which wouldresult in a saving of  20,000,000.    Of these  20,000,000, 7,000,000 were not specified, and  7,000,000 were basedupon a statement of the position as regards the vanningpower of the Navy which was altogether fallacious.- Thatrue savins *-he Committee recommended was thus only  7,000000The Geddes Report had been published,  and if the mistakesin it were not pointed out it would be accepted as a factby the public.   He regretted if the tone of the admiralty memorandum was too controversial, but he pointed out thatthe whole tone of the G^ddes Committee&apos;s Report impliedineo^T-xM-pnc5 and extravagant administration on the part ofthe Mmi^al+y. Committee had ignored the. facts that hadb*en given to them, by the Admiralty correcting their figures.He had felt that, 1+ was his duty to defend the Admiraltyagainst a grave injustice.The Fxrst lord of the Admiralty stated that,although he had been absent -from the country when the Geddes Consr-it-tee&apos;s Report was being discussed, he had received a copywhen he was in Washington.   The impression it had made on him was that the Report was an unfair condemnation of theadministration of the Admiralty for its extravagance, andthat the Admiralty were charged with maintaining largerumors, of unnecessary men.   He f-^-lt that it was necessaryfor a r^plv tp he mad&apos;-1 in     for.cc of ti: e Admiralty.
The Prime Minister dspr^ented the adoption of a hostileattitude of mind towards the Geddes Committee.     The ..Committee should not be treated as making a wanton attack .;upon the Government Departments.     Such an attitude towards them would be unwarranted and ungenerous.;     The Committeehad acted on the invitation of thO Government.     Per monthsthose great business mon had gratuitously given their services to the country.     To treat them as a hostile body would be altogether wrongd     The Cabinet should treat themgenerously and should recognise the great services theyhad rendered^     As a result of their labours they suggestedmeans by which a saving wf  70, COOt 000 could be effected,-.It would have been impossible f&apos;-r the Heads of the various departments to-effect such savings without the pressureoreated by that instrument,      It was unfortunate that theAdmiralty document had infused in it an element of bitternesstowards the Committee *     The result of that would be that opinion m?uld tend to range itself behind the Committee,to the detriment of - the Government.&apos;.       He trusted that theether Departments would not defend themselves in that spirii.It would&apos;be necessary that the wh/ie Report should be carefullystudied dri its merits, in order that its recommendations should, so fur as possible, be adapted,,The Secretary of State for War pointed cut that he had^endeavoured, without success, to obtain, from the Geddesor from the Treasury Officials who had assisted that CommitteeCommittee,,/an   explanation cf the figures contained Intheir Report, which in certain cases were irreconcilable*The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that his officialsbelieved in the figures of the Geddes Committee.It was agreed  That, before further progress could be made,it was essential to endeavour t-c arrive atan agreement as regards the facts...The First Lcrd;  the Secretary of Statefor War and the Secretary of State for Air,were requested to appoint officials who
should get into Immediate communicationwith the Treasury Officials with a viewto arriving at the facts in regard to thefigures in dispute between the departments and the Geddes Committee,mo POSED HALFHOLIDAY ON THEOCCASION OPfHE MARRIAGE&apos;0P PRINCESSMARY.(3)   The Secretary of State for Home affairs said that a suggestions had been made that a portionof the day of Princess Maryfs marriage should be madea general holidaya     The suggestion was that allshops should be&apos;closed until 1 o&apos;clook, in Londonalsne0     The question was how such a suggestion couldbe given effect to, and whether It might be done by apublic announcement     that shops would be closed bythe desire of His Majesty The KingcThe Minister of Labour expressed doubt as to the expediency of taking any action In the directionsuggested.     It must be remembered that employeeswould be effected by a declaration of a general half-holiday, as it would Involve them in the loss of half a day?s pay.     He did not think that sueh aresult would be popular at the present time*     Therewas no doubt there would be plenty of people in the streets to witness the wedding without any aotionon the part of the Government.It was agreedThat no action should be taken inthe matter*2, Whitehall Gardens,&apos;S*W,February 15th, 1922,

</content>
</cab>
