<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/204/7 images: 52-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
dqcument is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s government cp(78)107copy no23 October 1978cabinetPUBLIC EXPENDITURE, 1979-60 TO 1982-83:OUTSTANDING ISSUESMemorandum by the Chief Secretary, treasury as requested at Cabinet on 17 October (CM(78) 35th Conclusions,Minute 4), I have met the Secretaries of State for Education and Science and paymaster General, Social Services and Scotland and the Minister for social Security to discuss the division of the remaining  57 million from the extra  100 million which the Cabinet allocated from the Contingency reserve to programmes in 1979-80.1979-802. The Ministers pressed me at length to recommend a larger additionto programmes amounting to  107 million which they regard as anirreducible minimum for their extra requirements in 1979-80. (details are in their joint paper, CP(78) 108, and at Annex A below.) Theirsuggestion was to reduce the planned Contingency Reserve by a further 50 million.3. The Cabinet decided last week to reduce the Contingency Reserve in1979-80 by  100 million.    I am opposed to going further than this. the contingency Reserve is already lower than I thought necessary in relationto potential requirements already foreseen.    Estimating changes couldwell reduce it further even before the White Paper is published.4. I was unable to persuade the Ministers to accept the figure of 57 million as a basis for a settlement, but ultimately they indicated that*H their view an appropriate split, albeit of a higher total, could be in theproportion 2:1 between health and social security and education respectively.5* My personal preference would be to allocate the whole of the 57 million to the Health Service but I recognise the strong wish of theSecretary of State for Education and Science and Paymaster General to have something from what remains.    My proposal is therefore to divide the 57 million in the suggested proportions of 2:1.     This could given an extra 38 million for the Health Service and  19 million for education bothfigures for the United Kingdom.1
1980-816. For 1980-81, my earlier memorandum indicated an excess of 24 million over the planning total.    This excess was increased to 38 million by the Cabinet&apos;s decisions on the Home Office (including itsconsequences for Scotland and Northern Ireland) and the scottish development Agency.    There is no room for further additions to programmes in 1980-81, when the Contingency Reserve is already lower than thecorresponding figure in the plans we published in the last White Paper.7. With regret, therefore, I must recommend against using part of the extra provision for health and social security in 1979-80 to extendeligibility for long term supplementary benefit, as the Minister for social security has proposed.    There is no room for the growing cost of this measure in 1980-81, and it pre-empts our studies of the best way ofproviding for the long term unemployed.8. Nor at this stage can I recommend further additions to the health oreducation programmes in 1980-81.    I recgonise that there may be someknock-on effects from the increases suggested for 1979-80, but there shouldbe room to accommodate these within programmes of this size for the later years, especially when both programmes will still be higher in 1980-81 thanin 1979-80.EDUCATION MAINTENANCE ALLOWANCES (EMA)9. The estimates that are now put forward in CP(78) 108 showexpenditure of  17 million in 1979-80 rising to  27 million in 1980-81 and 54 million in 1982-83 (when it is assumed that about half the localauthorities will have joined the scheme).    In my view the rate at which localauthorities will join must be highly uncertain and the expenditure might wellbuild up faster than those figures assume.    Additional amounts would berequired for Scotland and Northern Ireland (Annex A).    Moreover the EMAscheme would be much less cost-effective than any specific employmentmeasure, and the Secretary of State for Employment is not prepared to finance it from the employment programme.    My reasons for opposing thescheme are set out in more detail in Annex B.CONCLUSIONS10. I invite the Cabinet to agree that:-i.        the decision should stand to reduce by  100 million (butnot more) the Contingency Reserve planned for 1979-80;ii.       the  57 million available for allocation following lastweek&apos;s Cabinet discussion should be divided in the proportion2:1 between the Health Service and education, both on a UnitedKingdom basis;2
iii.       no provision should be made for the scheme for educational maintenance allownaces.H. I attach a revised version of Table 1 from my earlier memorandumincorporating these proposals.J treasury Chambers23 October 19783
confidential annex ACHANGES IN PROGRAMMES PROPOSED BY SECRETARIES OD STATEFOR EDUCATION,  SCOTLAND AND SOCIAL SERVICES (CP(78)l08)  million at  1978 survey prices1979/801980/811.       Health end Social Security(UK) 572.       Education,   Science and Arts(UK)(other than maintenanceallowances in 3 below)501503.       Educational Maintenance AllowancesDES  (England and Wales)ScotlandD/Employment171.9- 18.9273-30TotaKl + 2 + 3)107150
EDUCATIONAL MAINTENANCE ALLOWANCESe limited scheme for educational maintenance allowances (EMAs)ln England and Wales is described in the Annex to CP(78)108. Itdiffers from the mandatory version that we have considered earlier111 that for the present local authorities are to have discretionWhether to enter the scheme,  which will only cover 16 year olds inth* first year.is does not change the essential character of the scheme, but only***e Pattern of expenditure build-up.    Objections to the proposalslnclude the following points:-(i)      The estimates show a rapid growth in spending from thefirst year&apos;s  17 million,  to  27 million in I98O-81,  41million in 1981-82 and  5^ million in 1982-83 withcontinuing growth thereafter.(ii)      The pace of this build-up is completely uncertain asexemplified by the fact that several different sets of figures have been quoted in the past week.    The aboveestimates assume that  12 authorities covering 25 per cent of the age-group would join at the outset,  and that thenumber would rise gradually so  that,  in 1982-83,   55 per cent of the age-group would be covered.    If however there werefull coverage in    1982-83 - which seems equally plausible -the cost would be twice as high, ie  112 million.*ii)      It is     also        uncertain whether we would be able to sustain the proposed discrimination between 16 year olds and therest for the first two years.(iv)      it is    likely    that 80per cent of the awards would go to young people who would stay on in education anyway, becauselocal authorities joining the scheme would be obliged toapply it  to all.(v)This scheme is no more cost-effective than the mandatoryscheme,  as a means of reducing unemployment,  and indications are that the net cost of reducing unemployment would be atleast twice that of any specific employment measures.There can be no question of making room for the scheme fromthe employment programme after 1979/80,  as the legislativeshort-term working scheme must then be assumed to take up the planned provision in full.
TABLE 1^LIC EXPENDITURE PLANS, 1979-80 TO 1982-83  million at 1978 survey prices.a.3.4Initial &apos; headroom1 (-) wjth^\. .Planning totals agreed by Cabinetdevaluation revisions and mainestimating changes on demand-responsive services&quot;Headroom1 (-) after changes at  net changes&apos; recommended in thispaperM/DefencePCOODMmaff/dafs/woad/ibapForestry CommissionD/TradeDPCP (inc OFT)D/IndustryD/finploymentVEnergy /Transport     , ,^/Environment (excl psa;Home OfficeLCDDESDHSSDHSSPSA SD (computers)Jey Sol, Ord Survey &amp; OPCSScotland (excl daf6) ***X^es (excl v0ad)&quot;*Northern Ireland **Health and PSSsocial security3.ChiTOTAL&apos;J^g68 to set contingency reserve**Pe )&apos; 15U0* 2100* 2500 (SeC malJ!?^oom*    (-) or Excess&apos; (*)^ep changes at 2, 4 and 51979-80- 36522.6-3^2.4- 8.7- 4.16.21- 4.26.220022- 2012.5- 1.916.771.724.5- 0-59.03.68.71980-81- 424-38.2-462.2- 20.5- 121.41.775.942510240.566.418.5618*13.915.21981-82-1023-100.7-1123.71982-83 :-1845342.7600.1-1000.3* 37.98.71.85.41.522460850415.567.122410- 1.619.06.818.7290.4-1554.6* *51.23-02.4- 1.71.9- 16.246071007511.9212.325.5710&quot; 46.&quot; f18.426.2749.9200-173.81037.9300-216.7* *ePopt*lan6es are measured against the baseline figures in the surveyK 5llPe-r* 5Ure incorporates an estimating change of 4-22.4 on civilv    ^uation which was omitted from cp(78)99.^aSjp^?8 for these programmes have been adjusted to reflect the^se8 in the corresponding English programmes.

</content>
</cab>
