<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/267/0 images: 27-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S iii C R xij T.CP. 4A (57) .                                          COPY NO.                             CABINET.THE IRISH FREE STATE CONSTITUTIONAL LEGISLATIONNote &quot;by the Secretary  of  State for         Dominion Affairs.     With reference to ray Memorandum (CP. 4 (37)), Icirculate herewith the attached copy of extracts from theOfficial Report of the Irish Free State Dail for the 11thand 12th December,                      (Intld.)  M.M.Dominions Office.     January 11th, 1937.
11111A/287            EXTRACTS  FROM DAIL EIREANN DEBATES OF                     11TH AND 12TH  DECEMBER,  1936                ******    THE PRESIDENT : Very well.  My reply to these questions, is, first, that thereis not in this Bill any proposition to sever our connection with the States of theBritish Commonwealth.  Article 1 of the Constitution remains untouched.  Thenext is that what we propose to do in this is to bring the law and the Constitution intoaccord with the actual facts of  the situation.  The actual facts will be reflected in the Constitution as it will be when these amendments have been effected.  Next :Have we consulted the other members of the  Commonwealth on this particularmatter ?  I say that this is a matter  that affects ourselves alone.   It is a purelyinternal matter and it has no connection whatever and no other State is interestedin, or has a right to be  interested in, what mechanism  we have here for giving effect to the will of our own people and the will of our Parliament.   I can say, ingeneral, however, that as far as Great  Britain is concerned, a  considerable time ago I indicated quite clearly that the new Constitution would be one in whichthere  would be no reference whatever to the King the King would not appear in  our new Constitution and that any relations that would  exist between ourState and Great  Britain, so long as  the  people willed to  have that connection,would be maintained by  the fact of co-operation, and would be  regularised, so faras  that was concerned, by law.    Now, that general indication, that the  King was to  be removed from theConstitution was given a considerable time ago.  Of course, it was only indicatedinformally, and as  a matter of courtesy because,  again, they  have no right  tointerfere in any way with what  we may do in this particular matter.  However,as  a matter of courtesy  it was  indicated, but there was no opportunity, in thepresent circumstances, to give any specific communication.  With regard  to these bills, there was a general desire expressed by the States of the British Commonwealththat there should be concerted action as quickly as possible.  Canada, Australia,New Zealand, South Africa  are arranging for simultaneous action  by means  ofassent to British legislation.  We, on  our part,  are  not  prepared to give anycountenance to the idea  that the British Parliament can in any way legislate forus.  If this thing has to  be  done, it  has to be done by our Parliament  and ourParliament alone.  At the same time, so long as there is  any association at  all,so long as we continue in association at all, it is obvious  that we ought to do our part to facilitate other countries in dealing with this  situation. If not, clearly,the right thing for us to do is to go out;  but so long as  we do remain,  it is clearthat you would have either by goodwill to meet situations of this sort, or therewould, have to be some convention in advance with regard to the  meeting of  it.In fact, there has been already not in our time, but in the time of our predecessors -a sort of general convention, not that they would take simultaneous action of that kind,  but it was implied  that the question of  succession was a matter in whichnothing definite should be done unless  all the States who were associated would co-operate  in the doing of it.  That is why, in answer to the third question as towhether we have given any information of this, we  have  not had the opportunityof giving it formally, (and we would not do it informally) to the British and wehave  not communicated  the terms of this to any of the other  States.  Time didnot permit.  I say, however, that it is  a matter concerning ourselves alone andtherefore is a matter which is quite proper for us to determine here, and my reasonfor the summoning of the Dail at this short notice was that this situation should bedealt with as quickly as possible.               ******    I move :  &quot; That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;  When I introducedthis question this afternoon I indicated, I think quite clearly,  the reason for the urgency.  I pointed  out that there would be an anomalous situation existing herelegally or rather that it might give rise to anomalous interpretations  if whenCanada,  Australia,  New  Zealand, Great  Britain and  South Africa, when thesemembers of the British Commonwealth of Nations, had ratified the abdication of king Edward VIII and provided for  a successor we, while still belonging to that group of nations, that community of nations, continue to  have a different King,particularly in view of the fact  that there was a convention or an understandingthat questions of succession were matters which required  consultation and consent in regard to all the members.  I  think that the continuance of that situation wouldbe in every way harmful and I  felt that it was my duty to advise  the ExecutiveCouncil and to summon  Parliament to deal with it with  all possible speed. Constitutional Relations (C.23931 /664. 125.
    Undoubtedly a very abnormal situation has arisen.  No special provision hasbeen made for it in advance.  It had to be dealt with.  We naturally had to consider how we should deal with it, being careful to maintain the status which we at presenthave, and in the general interests of our own nation.   Some people, I take DeputyNorton as one, undoubtedly think that we should remedy this situation by declaringa Republic for the Twenty-Six Counties.  I wonder whether that is precisely what he wanted to say or that we should just leave the position as it is and do nothing.Whatever might be said for the solution of declaring a Republic for the Twenty-six counties,  I certainly see no argument whatever in favour of leaving the situationin the form in which it would be if we did nothing. The effect would not be in our favour  I  feel certain,  but altogether against it.   We would have theorists  andpublicists  trying to explain the situation in which we would be  placed  by some sort of pretence that  the King who was appointed in  Great  Britain, or whosesuccession is provided for in Great Britain and in the other States, could somehowbe  regarded as King  here.  Australia, Canada and  New Zealand had to face a situation somewhat similar to ours.  They  recognised, too, that legislation wouldbe necessary  in order  to maintain their  status.   They did what they wanted tohave  done to regularise the situation by requesting and assenting to legislation tothat effect in the British  Parliament.    As I said at the start, that is the one thing that we certainly could not consent to and which I  do not  think any Government here would be willing to consent to.We had,  therefore, to regularise the  situation-.  I  did  not propose to  use this situation to declare a  republic  for the Twenty-Six Counties.   Our people at anytime will  have  their opportunity for doing that.  We are putting no barrier ofany sort in the  way.  They can do it, if they want to do it, at  any time.   I have indicated  already that  that is not our policy, that what we want ultimately is tosee a republic for the  whole  32 counties of Ireland.  I want to say also that, ifI were  proposing  that we should declare  either a  Twenty-Six County republicor a 32 county  republic an occasion like the present  would not  be the occasion todo  it.  Neither is the present occasion one  on  which we  should introduce apermanent Constitution here.  That is not proposed either.   We had intendedat one time to  continue constitutional amendments, just like those we have putthrough in the  old Constitution, to bring the law in the Constitution into accord with  the  practice and the real position.   But when we had  reached a certainposition after some time I satisfied myself that this  instrument, or whatever youlike to  call it,  this fundamental law, which is scored through in several places,was no longer a fit instrument or a fit document to be regarded as the fundamentallaw, and I said  the time has come when we ought now, with full freedom of actionin regard  to it, to consider what should be, in our  own circumstances,  our ownConstitution.    This  Constitution  came  into being under  very  abnormal  circumstances.Nobody denies  that the Treaty was accepted here only under threat of force and,consequently, if there is any truth in the statements that are made so often fromthe opposite benches, if there is any truth in the liberty of action and freedom whichnations enjoy  whilst  retaining membership of  the British  Commonwealth ofNations, we should be at liberty at least to make a Constitution that would accord with  our  own aspirations and  our own  desires and use the symbols which our people desire to see of  their power, of their authority, in their own Constitution.    I had to consider  what advice I would give to my colleagues when dealingwith this  situation.  It was clearly necessary to  bring in some Bill by which itwould be regularised, or rather by which I do not like to use the word regularise,because it would be regular, on our theory at any rate -but by which any ambiguitythat it  might be  possible  to  import  into the situation would be completely andthoroughly cleared up.  I asked myself :  &quot; How can I do this ? &quot;  I would not ask the members, of our Party, nor would I myself take the responsibility for theintroduction of a measure such as the second one here unless it was made clear,side by side with it, what the true situation was.  I think that, instead  of beingregarded as some trick, or something  of that sort, by some side-wind to secure some  advantages,  everybody who is sincerely  and genuinely  anxious about theconstitutional situation here should welcome our bringing in the first measure andputting it side by side with the other so as to show clearly what the true position is.    I  have heard  speeches  this . afternoon from the opposite benches and, asI listened  to them, I said  to myself :  &quot; Surely these men, when talking about thefreedom that was possessed,  never believed that we had that freedom,  or theycould not talk  like that.&quot;  If any excuse was  required for putting through  this
measure quickly it could be found from listening to some  of the speeches that were made from the opposite benches.  If it were possible to stir up irritation andto cause trouble it would be caused by these speeches.  It is not by the action ofthe Government that irritation between the people of this country  and the peopleacross  the  water would be caused, but by the false  interpretation and misinter-pretation of our attitude expressed in the speeches I listened to to-day.  In thesetwo Bills we are giving expression to the position as it is to-day,  in reality and inpractice, and, if we are to take responsibility for Bill No. 2, we are not prepared todo so unless we have Bill No. 1,  which makes quite clear what the functions ofthe King are for whom succession is provided. We think this is the proper time.In the time of  King Edward VIII I had indicated quite clearly that we proposedin the new Constitution to make the position of the King roughly as it was in theold Constitution, with these deletions.  I said that informally, because I had hopedthat these were matters of our own domestic concern, and that we are not obligedto get the consent of any of the other States in the British Commonwealth in orderto do what we proposed to do.  Informally, and as a matter of courtesy, the BritishGovernment was informed, and as it was  purely informal, naturally I did notkeep records in the way Deputy 0&apos;Higgins tried to make it appear.  I was asked aquestion if that was done, and I gave my recollection  of what was done.  I  wasthen asked where were the documents, and so on.  The fact that informal noticeor information  was given was quite sufficient. I  hold that  it was not necessaryto give formal  or informal notice of what we  proposed to do.    What  we  are doing  is nothing but what the people of Ireland  anticipatedwe would do, and what we said we would do ultimately with regard to this matter.We are making clear what is the fundamental position in practice. It should bewell known now, at any  rate,  that those who take responsibility  for any action and decide the  policy in regard to it, even where the King is the final instrumentby which effect is given to it, are the Executive Council.  They have in fact theauthority, and as they have authority, it is right that it should be fully and formallyexpressed here on the face of the document, so  that  there may  be  no possiblemisrepresentation  or misunderstanding.  We propose  to continue the King  forthe functions which he in  fact directly exercises and for these only.  The functionsprovided for here are the only  functions which in fact the King  exercises.   Weare providing for the continuance of these functions on the advice and authority as in the past  and in the future of the Executive Council.  We are  clearing upthe political constitutional situation. We are making clear to everyone what thesituation is, and we are removing fiction.  Whatever justification there might bein British  history or British constitutional theory for such fiction, there is no justification in  our case.   It is very much better that  our people should see clearlywith no fog and no mist of constitutional theory  about it, what the situation is.That is what is being proposed in this Bill.    What  is happening, then is that from the King are being taken away  anyfunctions internal, either direct or indirect, in the Administration of the Governmentand in the internal Executive ofvthe country, and we are  retaining the King for those purposes  for  which he was  used hitherto.   He is being retained for these purposes because he is recognised as the symbol of  this  particular co-operation in the States of the Commonwealth.  If the Irish  people do not wish to continuehim for these purposes they can end that by legislation. They can end the whole situation by law or limit  the exercise of these powers by law.  What is given inthe Bill is permission to continue to use the same instrument.  Somebody objected to the word &quot; organ.&quot; I  think it is as  good a word as organisation, for instance.In the Constitution it is stated already that Executive authority will be given effectto by certain organisations,  one being  the King.   If the King can be called an organisation I think he can be  called much more properly a  constitutional organ.With regard to any impropriety in the expression, I think it is only people whoare looking for difficulties will find them.  All this  talk is  in keeping with theattitude of people who talked about &quot; slaps in the face &quot; and that sort of thing.We are administering no slap in the face to anybody, but we are asserting our right and so we are doing this positive act of our own, and doing it under certain con-ditions, clearly  setting down what  those conditions are, so that there can be  nomisrepresentation.  That  is the  purpose of the two Bills.  That is why they arelinked together. I certainly and this Government would not take responsibilityfor one without the other.  There has been too much misrepresentation  of  thesituation, and too much of an  attempt by foreign jurists and theorists to try togive the situation here an interpretation  for which we do not stand,  and whichwe think in law is not warranted.(C 23931)B2
     I do not think it is necessary to go through the Bill in detail.  The effect simply is to eliminate the King from all those Articles of the Constitution which seem to give him functions here in our internal affairs.  We are taking these out. The whole purpose is to do that.  In the case of the Governor-General, the appoint-i ment and executive powers provisions are being deleted.   Whether the Governor-&apos; General is immediately ended by that is another question.   The amendment does not expressly state what functions in connection with legislation disappear.  There are certain statutory functions which would require a consequential Act to clear up.  We do not propose to  do that  now.  We can let the situation  rest  at the moment.  If it should be necessary to bring in a consequential Act to deal with it, we are prepared to do so.  We have not the list made out of the places where the Governor-General has some functions.  There does not appear to be  any  urgent need.   I feel confident, notwithstanding speeches  that  were made, whether by Deputy Norton,  Deputy Thrift or Deputy 0&apos;Sullivan, that these  speeches were clearly made by  people who understand the situation, even though they tried to over-emphasise a particular aspect of it.   I shall leave it at that.  They thoroughly understand the situation.  Those who say  we are  doing something desperate at the moment, that we are taking a mean advantage of the Irish people,  know that, in fact, we are making clear the position as it is.  I am  quite confident also that if Deputy Norton reflects a little, on his suggestion with regard to leaving matters alone,  he  will be satisfied that they  could  not remain in  that condition for any length  of time.   Finally you would have to clear them up, and you would clear them up under much worse conditions than  you can clear them up  now.  You would  have considerable  irritation created by the  misrepresentations  that are bound  to be made on matters of this sort.by people who do not thoroughly under- stand them, who do not  understand the need we  have  for them or the purpose behind  them.   I am satisfied that  to leave the  situation to continue  for  a considerable time would be to do harm rather  than  to  do good.  I move  the Second Reading of the Bill.     With regard to the Six Counties, we were prepared in 1921 to make  certain concessions to the minority if they were prepared  to  come into a  united Ireland at that time.  There is a limit, obviously, to the concessions that the  majority of the people down here ought to be asked to make in  order to bring in the people from the North.  We are laying the frame-work into  which they can come if they want to.  It shows  the utmost limit  of our concessions.   If, after a certain time, they do not come,  the Irish people will  constitutionally be at liberty to take any other line of action they please.               sjc                  $Jg                           tft     As regards my attitude towards the Treaty, it has been expressed thousands of times in this House as well as out of it, and in despatches to the British Govern- ment which have been published. That Treaty, as far as I am concerned, was imposed by force,  and it imposes no moral obligation on the Irish people.   But leaving that to one side, the question is whether the actions which we are taking can be construed as breaches of  that Treaty in itself.  I  say they cannot.  We have heard here to-day two or three different interpretations of the Treaty.   One set of  Deputies want to say that the Treaty is to  be interpreted practically as it was when it was signed, and under the conditions under which it was signed.  Then we hear of constitutional advances in 1926 and in 1931.  I want to say with regard to these that they were hardly made when I was one of the first to admit that these did constitute a tremendous advance in regard to the position in the Free State. I was  one of the first to admit it.   The moment the Governor-General ceased to be the instrument  of what,  in fact,  was the  Crown,  of the  British Cabinet as was shown up to that time the moment that he ceased to be the instrument of the British Cabinet  and became subject  to the advice and authority of the Executive  Council here, his position was completely changed.  That is true.  I admitted it  at the time and spoke of it here in the Dail.  Similarly there was an advance from  one point of view at a later stage, not because the Statute of Westminster ran here,  but because fundamentally it showed and  was  a declaratory recognition as far as  they were concerned that they had no right to interfere and legislate anywhere.      I would not be here bringing in these Bills at all if it was not that  I felt it  to be my duty to see that whatever was in the situation, as long as we were here  anyhow, would be maintained.   From the day on which I came into the  Depart-  ment of  External Affairs, although we  came into a situation with the creation of
which we had nothing to do, one of the things that I set out for myself was thatif we were not able to make a definite advance I was, at least, going to leave thesituation in such a position that,  if my predecessors came back into office, theywould not find, from their point of view, at any rate, a worse position to deal with.That has been my attitude. There is no one here who has had anything whateverto do with the Department of External Affairs who will not admit that it is very important from our point of view that this situation should be clarified. They askwhat advances we have made.  I say that by the choosing of our symbols and theexercise of our rights, by our standing on the theories that we hold and standingon them against the theories that are held by people elsewhere, we are assertingour liberty and making advances.  The  symbols will be here after this.     I am not saying that this is going to be our permanent Constitution.  I have proceeded in this way because I would not take responsibility for bringing in thisAct No. 2 unless I put it in conjunction  with Act No. 1,  which was going to clarifya situation and clearly define the extent to which the King was going to be usedin our regard.     Another question that  was  raised was what our attitude was with regard tothe Act of Succession.   The advice given to me on the matter was that  the act of Succession, in so far as it would be held not to be in conflict with the Constitution,was  taken over by Article 73 of the Constitution, as it was adopted in December,1922.  Accordingly, it  makes provisions with regard to succession  which are  thelaw of Saorstat Eireann.     MR. NORTON : We have here, at all events, a situation where we are being askedfor the first  time voluntarily to appoint as King of Saorstat  Eireann the sameperson who has been appointed as King of England and King of the other countriesin the Commonwealth.   No previous  Government in this country has ever volun-voluntarily  appointed  a King.   No  previous Government  in this  country has evervoluntarily appointed King of Saorstat Eireann one and the same person who wasKing of  England.  Here,  by rushed legislation, panicky legislation, the Housebeing asked to meet on Saturday, in a few short hours we are to provide not merely for the abdication of one King but for the appointment of a successor.  I should like to know  whether the President really thinks that that speed is of advantage toour people, or whether the British people have asked that  not only should abdicationbe provided for speedily but that a successor should be provided for with equal speed.Is the explanation  of all this speed  a request from the British Government for legislation providing for legal recognition of the abdication of the King  and  theappointment  of a successor ?  Is the  explanation of that speedy legislation to  befound in any request by the British Government that it is desirable to have that legislation enacted ?  If  it is not, if this legislation  is not being introduced at the specific request of the British Government, will the President tell the House why he considers it necessary, in the interests of the Irish people,  that  a successor tothe abdicated King should be appointed in a few hours  on Saturday.               ******    THE PRESIDENT :  There has  been  so  much talk all around this in  variousdirections that anything  I  would  have to say would be simply a repetition  ofwhat I said before.  There is one  thing, however, which it might be valuable  to try and make clear.  Deputy Norton and others seem to think that I thought,or that anybody who examined the situation thoroughly thought, that there wasa  heaven-sent opportunity  for  doing something nationally, and that somehowthat heaven-sent opportunity has not been availed of.  I say that there was nothing of the sort.  We have now at this instant, before this Bill passes, exactly the sameopportunity as we will  have when it is passed to do anything that we want to doin regard to this part of  Ireland.  If we want, the day after this Bill is passed,  to repeal this  Bill or to declare a republic,  whatever line of conduct we may care  toadopt in order to make  it effective, we can  do precisely what it is suggested byDeputy Norton and others we can. only do now.   In fact, Deputy Norton tookvery good care not to say or suggest what was to be done in the present situation just wait.
    There are people who imagine that some legal technicalities are things that can persist for a length of time and cause difficulty for a length of time.  We area Parliament here.  If there was some legal difficulty interfering with the interestsof this State what would we do ?  We would summon Parliament to clear up thedifficulty ;  we would end the legal difficulty by making a law to solve it.  AnyStates that  might be inconvenienced if that  was the point he had in  mind by our refusal  to pass this Bill, could, similarly, in so far  as they were concerned,rectify the situation,  as Deputy MacDermot has pointed out, by making a law.What I was interested in was that it would not be rectified by making a  law whichwould be injurious to us.  I wanted to make quite sure that any regularisation ofthis position, as far as we were concerned, would be done by us, and this Bill is introduced in our interests and not in the interests of any  other country.  It is brought in absolutely in the interests of our people here because we want to seethat there will be no ambiguous position legally here.    I think  I need say no more about it.  As I have said already, one of  the thingswe can do is to declare a  Republic for the Twenty-Six  Counties.  Does DeputyNorton propose that  we should do it ?  No,  he  does not.  Do nothing.  To do nothing legally  and technically, in my opinion, would mean that we are continuing the monarchy with King Edward as monarch.  Is that what Deputy Norton wantsus to do ?  &quot;What would be the position of our  representatives abroad ?  Thereare a  number of other things that would cause difficulty if we wanted to continue in that position.    Quite clearly, what we have got to do now is either to regularise the positionor declare a  republic.  We came into office with a certain policy.  We have pursuedthat policy  honestly the whole time we have been here.  I am anxious to see  acondition established here in which the people of this country can be on friendlyterms  with  the people across the water.  But I know it cannot be  done withoutsatisfying the aspirations of our people.  I believe that the existing situation doesnot satisfy their aspirations and what I am trying.to do in this, and will proposeto do in the coming Constitution, is to  get nearer to a position which will satisfytheir  aspirations.  I have  said many a time that the foundation on which friendly relations between the two countries can really be established will not be reacheduntil  it is reached on the basis  of  a  united Ireland.  Deputy  MacDermot says i must have lost  sight of that view when 1 introduced this.  I did not lose sight of it for one instant.  But  I have to balance two  things the sentiments of a  certainminority in the North which have caused them to adopt a certain position, andthe sentiments of the majority of the people  here who want  a different position.How  am I  to do. it ?  How is anybody, anxious about the unity of this countryand its future,  to do it ?   Clearly you have to ask yourself is there any point atwhich you will reach something with which the majority of the people are likelyto be satisfied and which will, at the same time, possibly satisfy the other section ?The two are going in opposite directions.  The majority can claim that  their viewought to prevail.  They have the right to claim that it should prevail. But we havea practical situation, not one which can be solved or settled by legal  technicalities,unfortunately.   It has to be solved by facing hard facts.  In  doing what we are doing we are working along to a position where we hope ultimately we will be ableto satisfy the interests and the aspirations of the majority  of the  people to thepoint, at any rate, that they will say, &quot; We are prepared to sacrifice some of therest in order to get a united Ireland.&quot;  That has been the basis all the time.    This is no  new problem.  We had precisely the  same problem in 1921  andthe general line of solution was the same as that towards which we are workingnow.   If we do reach that, having a united Ireland, then ultimately the  view ofthe majority of the people will prevail.  Obviously, when you get a situation like that the ultimate future of the country will be determined by what the majorityregard as their general interests.  Deputy MacDermot has some idea that you can bring in the North by a fuller acceptance of the British Empire than is acceptedby the majority at the moment.  I do not believe that at all.  There was no questionof that sort before 1921.   It was a question there of whether the laws governing the people  of this country were to be made in  Westminster, where there was acertain majority, or  to be made here.   They refused to enter  a Parliament here and the real reason for that refusal, obviously, is that they think their particularviewpoint in an assembly of that sort could only be expressed as a minority view.     When  all is said and done that  is the situation.  We have got to solve thatpractical fact.   Notwithstanding what  Deputy MacDermot or anybody may say, I cannot conceive anybody being more anxious for  the re-establishment of the
                                     7unity of this country than I am. There is neither apparent to Deputy MacDermotnor to anybody else at this moment any clear line  by which that unity can bere-established.  One thing is  certain, that you must, to a certain extent, at anyrate satisfy the aspirations of the majority  until they say  : &quot; Well, having got tothis particular point, we are now prepared  to make concessions to the minority.&quot;I do not know  at what point that  will be reached.  I have no idea when it will bereached.   What I am doing, and what was our policy in 1921,&apos; was to advance onthat road so that we would reach such a point.  We do not do it in a doctrinairefashion notwithstanding what has  been said.    This  Bill was not introduced to deceive anybody.  Clearly the main purposeof this Bill was to settle this situation.  It  was mainly for the purpose of settlingthis situation.  That was. the  only  excuse and the only reason for summoningParliament quickly.  I said I would not introduce a Bill  as long as there is mis-conception about what has been done.  I am going to put in black and white what are the functions that are going to be exercised,  making it quite clear that thereis no  reserve of right or authority  other than what is indicated on the face of theBill.  It has been suggested  overnight by  Deputies  that  it was due  somehow toa suggestion that this was a plan and a plot to  deceive them.  Nothing of the kind.    Certain doubts  were raised last night.  One of these was that somehow, if we.did pass the Bill, it would give  certain external functions to the successor of KingEdward VIII ;  that King Edward VIII himself  seemed to hover around looking for some corner in which he would have authority to act in virtue of the fact thathe was previously King. It is to cover that situation that these words &quot; all other(if any) purposes &quot;  are inserted.  It is not an uncommon phrase  in  law.   Veryoften you cannot get a complete list of things that may possibly occur into legis-lation of this sort and, therefore, the only safe thing is to put in an omnibus clauselike this, so that  if  there was any  oversight or if something was left out it wouldbe covered in the Act.  That is the whole explanation of this change.    MR. DILLON :  And carried on to the next King.    THE PRESIDENT :  Yes. There was a question about Article 51.  A number ofthings would be involved in that,  and I  would have liked to give an answer thatwould be  regarded  as authoritative by the  Deputy.  As far as this Article is con-cerned I would be inclined to say, yes.  If there is any hole or corner in which thedisembodied spirit  was hovering or trying  to get into, then,  if that does exist, itwill be filled already by this country.  We do not see any at the moment.   I donot know of any functions internally that are  left for the  King, whether it be theKing we were supposed last night to be completely removed from or his successor.I see no internal  functions left  for him.  Some sort of vague title or something ofthat sort is probably there, but  there are no internal functions left as far as I know.The purpose of this Bill was to remove the King from the exercise of any functionswhatever internally.    As to external functions, we  are concerned  to make it as clear  as we could make it, what  the external position  was going to be, and on what conditions theKing who was being substituted for King Edward VIII would exercise his functions.You can approach these things from different points of view. I resent the suggestionthat there has been an intention on my part to deceive Deputies.  Nothing of thekind.  It is a common trick  on the  opposite benches.  If Deputies hold that theBill passed yesterday did not do a certain thing, certainly those who were responsiblefinally for it, believed it did.  It could be  argued even now, if I wished to wastethe time of the House doing so, that it did, and  by  a number of Deputies that it did not.   We will leave it at that.  The change was made to make it quite definite.I think it is right when there is a question  of law that we should be as definite aswe can, and that we should  make quite definite the things we said yesterday we intended doing.  These things will, in fact,  be  done by this Bill.               ******     MR. MACDERMOT :  I do not know whether or not  the President has deliberatelyrefrained  from answering the question put to him by Deputy O&apos;Sullivan  at thebeginning of this debate.  It is a crucial question and I do not think that thePresident ought  to leave  it alone simply by forgetfulness.  Under this Bill, dothe Government tell us that there will be a king  of Ireland or that there will notbe a king of Ireland ?
    THE PRESIDENT : So far as I can see on the face of this Bill, there is no changein regard to the Title or anything of that sort.  What I said  I tried to make asexplicit as I could.  I said that we have taken all the internal functions away fromthe King.  Is that clear ?              *        *         *      *  *        *        *    MR. DILLON :  What is the meaning of the words &quot; all other (if any) purposes &quot; ?    THE PRESIDENT : While Deputy Dillon was absent I spoke on  that matter.I indicated that there were certain words raised last night in which there mightbe some nook or corner which Edward VIII or his disembodied  spirit might behovering around to get possession of. It was to make quite certain that, if therewas any such nook or corner, it would  be  taken possession of, if I might  put it that way, not by Edward VIII, but  by his successor.    MR. MCGILLIGAN :  Does it include such a thing  as  a declaration of war?Is it intended to include such a thing as a declaration of war ?    THE PRESIDENT :  It is  intended, as many phrases of that  sort  are, when you have not been able  to  get a complete examination in detail of each separateitem that if there was any such you can deal with it.  It is intended as an omnibusclause.    MR. MCGILLIGAN :  Is it intended to exclude the declaration of war ?    THE PRESIDENT : It is intended as  an  omnibus clause.              ******

</content>
</cab>
