<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/146/0 images: 140-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(jg DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJ&apos;ESTY*S GOVERNMENT)C(69)1562 4th, November   1969.CABINETTHE POLICE BILLg  MUTUAL, AID AND THE SPECIAL,&quot;* POWERS ACTSMemorandum by the Secretary of State fox- the Home Department.The Police BilL, which received a Second Reading on Tuesday,18th Novembers makes provision for a Great Britain police force toprovide constables or other assistance to the Royal Ulster Constabulary(RUC) when that force needs to meet a special demand on its resources,The Bill provides that this provision comes into force on an appointed da.y.Mutual aid is ah element in the police reform programme, but not a majorelement,,20       I had intimation that anxiety would be expressed about thepossibility of police from Great Britain being required to operate under the Special Powers Acts,,    I. said in my Second Reading speech(Official Report 18th November, cols, 1001-2) that I would not bring the mutual aid provisions into force until conditions of police operations and service in Northern Ireland approximate more closely than, they havedone in the past with those in Great Britain?  and that it was not theintention for policemen sent from Great Britain to help the RUC toexercise powers under the Special Powers Acts,,30      During the course of the debate there was considerable interestin the Special Powers Acts - and also in the Northern Ireland legislation on flags and emblems - and the possibility of an amendment wherebyBritish police would not operate the Special Powers Acts wasforeshadowed.    In winding upf. the Minister of State waid thatthe question of powers under the Special Powers Acts would bedetermined when a situation giving rise to giving mutual aid arose,,She a,added that the question could be explored at greater length in committee,,    Major Chichester-Clark told me on Tuesday that therewas no intention of using British police under the Special Powers Acts,,40       The powers given by the Special Powers Acts and regulations made under it may be summarised as follows&apos;&quot;(a)    Powers to detain and intorn0COPY NO.
(b) Powers to proscribe associations and publicad.ow.Bo(c) Powers of regulations  e0 gD curfew, blocking of roads, manufacturand control of explosives,,(d) Special offences, such as possessing offensive weapons,interfering with wireless apparatus, collecting information about police dispositions.-.(e) Police powers (which are available also to members of HerMajesty5s Forces) of search of houses and vehicles, search for firearms, arrest without warrant for any criminal offence,arrest and detention for 48 hours of persons acting or suspected of acting in a manner prejudicial to the peace, power to stoppersons and require answers to questions, to require persons from outside Northern Ireland *.o satisfy the police that their presence is not detrimental to the peace, power to require theproduction of articles and documents and power to stop a personleaving a designated ship in a designated portDThe powers in issue are those described in (e) above.50      At the beginning of the year the Northern Ireland Government had it in mind to revoke all the Regulations currently in force except for eight(including the power to proscribe associations) and to consider the incorporation of some of them in other permanent legislation.    Butthe sabotage incidents in March put an end to this plan0    Their presentpublic position is that they intend to look afresh at the Special PowersActs when a period of calm could be assured,6,       The issue is likely to be strongly pressed in Committee by bothsides of the House, and the Police Federation who accept the Bill only with reluctance, have a strong interest in not having to enforce lawsregarded as odious.    The balance of advantage undoubtedly lies infavour of an amendment and the draft amendment which has beenprepared is annexed to this paper g    I informed the Northern ireland government of my intention and they had no comment to offer on itiregarding the question as one for us entirely.    They certainly did not object.70       I can see no point in refusing to write into the Bill a provision which would give effect to the intention J. stated at Second Readingparticularly when this is also the intention of the Northern ireland government,,    An amendment would clear the air and assist in gainingconfidence for the measures we are trying to &amp;adopt, particularly withthe bodies representing police interests here - those representing bothpolicemen and police authorities,,    It would also help in repelling morefar ^reaching amendments already on the Order Paper 0uo2 ***
0o       The Secretary of State for Defence, however s thinks that theamendment to the Police Bill will lead to strong pressure for similaramendment of the Ulster Defence Regiment (UDR) Bill to precludemembers of the UDR from exercising the special powers *. and indeedto demands that the regular army should cease to use fchem0    TheSecretary of State for Defence could not agree to male a concession on either point.    My view is that the use of the special powers by theArmy in present circumstances caa be shown in the House to be different from their use by British policemen assisting the RUC0    The fact thatthe Army has been called in indicates that a serious situation exists thatjustifies for the Army the kind of powers it is exercising.    In the longer term this kind of power is apt for defence against infiltration and sabotage, but it is not apt in normal circumstances for the police,and certainly not for policemen visiting temporarily to give assistanceto the RUG,    The Northern Ireland Government do not suggest that the visiting policemen should exercise these powers; and I have already said at Second Reading that there is no intention that they should do so,,9U       I have reluctantly withheld the amendment to enable the issue tobe discussed in Gabinet0    I ask my colleagues to agree that an amendment should be put down, either as a manuscript amendment on Report or inthe Lords^ to ensure that British police do not exercise police powers under the Special Powers Actsalio Jo CoHome Office, S0YJ*lo?-lst November, 1969.,3.
ANNEXClause 1, page 2, line 16, at end insert:-( )    No enactment of the Parliament of Northern Ireland shall operate to confer on a constable provided under this flection for the assistance ofthe Royal Ulster Constabulary a power exercisable under the civil authorities (Special Powers) Act (Northern Ireland) 1922 by a memberof that Constabulary;  and the power conferred by section 1(3) of thatAct on the Minister of Home Affairs for Northern Ireland to make regulations shall not include power to confer any powers or duties on a constable so provided or to enable any powers or duties to beso conferred,)


</content>
</cab>
