<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/146/0 images: 517-525</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
bus9th December a 1969COPY NO.3CABINETCOMMISSION FOR INDUSTRY AND MANPOWER;DRAFT CONSULTATIVE DOCUMENTMemorandum by the First Secretary of State and secretary of State for Employment and productivity the Cabinet agreed in October (CC(69) 47th Conclusions, Minute 4)and it was announced in The Queen&apos;s Speech that legislation would beintroduced to rationalise the v/ork of the Monopolies Commission and theNational Board for Prices and Incomes and to merge the two bodies.    the ministerial Committee on Industrial Policy was established to supervise the preparation of this legislation,2.      The Committee has reached agreement on the main elements of thelegislation,    The attached draft document for consultation with outside interests incorporates changes put forward in discussion and subsequentlyby interested Departments, but the draft will &amp;sirJ  be further discussed ata Committee meeting on 10th December on which I 6hall be reportingorally.3.      The main points on which discussions have taken place in theCommittee have been the definition of the range of private sector firms which might be referred to the new Commission! the precise scope of references to the Commission; and the Commission^ role in relation tothe nationalised indiistries and to pay in the public sector.    TheCommittee&apos;s views on these matters are reflected in the consultative document.    The Commission^ special functions in connection with top salaries in the public sector are still under discussion in the Committeeand will be brought before the Cabinet in due course.4.     Outside consultation ought to begin as soon as possible.    TheCommittee agreed that the consultative document should first be discussed in the strictest confidence with the Confederation of British Industry(CBI),     I propose to make the consultative document public early inJanuary for formal consultation with the Trades Union Congresse iheCBI and other interested parties,, and to work on the preparation of a bill which ws can be ready to introduce to the House in February.5.     I invite my colleagues? approval to the opening of consultations as described above on the basis of the consultative document.B . A0 CaDepartment of Employment and Productivity, S,W01.9th December, 1969.DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRJ.TAJNNIC MAJESTYXS GOVERNMENT)
COMMISSION FOR INDUSTRY AND MANPOWERDRAFT DOCUMENT FOR CONSULTATION VTTH OUTSIDE INTERESTS1,      The Commission for Industry and Manpower is being established to take  over and develop the work at present  carriedout by the Monopolies Commission and the National Board for prices and Incomes.    The Monopolies Commission has been concerned with industrial structure and with the activities of privately-ownedfirms which may prevent,  restrict or distort  competition.    the nbpi has been concerned with matters affecting prices  and charges and income from dividends,  rents and employment  not only in theprivate sector but also in nationalised industries and the public services.2.      The work of the NBPI has been,   and continues  to be,   of vitalimportance in helping the community to combat inflation withoutrestricting growth.     It has done so by highlighting the ways inwhich costs could be contained,  and prices kept more stable,  bythe more efficient use of manpower and other resources and byrelating pay to performance wherever possible.    The monopolies commission,   too,  has been concerned to  ensure that  the conductof any firm which exercises a substantial degree of market power is not  contrary to  the public interest.     Both bodies have  alsodealt with matters of general interest to the efficient conductof an industry or service and increasingly their work has  tended to overlap.    The work of the NBPI has emphasised that  firms are able to exercise substantial market power without necessarilyhaving  control of one-third of a particular market.     But  thework cf both the Commission and the Board has also  shown clearly that it is necessary to  consider particular aspects of a  firm&apos;activities against  the background of its business  as a whole.It is not helpful to the  community or fair to the  firm to   con-si der prices, profits,  pay settlements or market domination in isolation,3.      For these reasons the Government believes  that the work ofthe two bodies  should new bo merged.    The essential role  of the nbpi in scrutinising the  factors which make  for  inflationaryprice and pay increases is of continuing importance.    The needfor this arises particularly in circumstances where the operationof competitive  forces is restricted;   the existence of a monopolyis one case in point,  and so is the increasing and often dominantinfluence which may be exercised within the  economy or animportant sector of it by very large  enterprises.    In the
Government1s view major industrial,  commercial and financialundertakings have a special responsibility to the  community at large which make their structure and their decisions andactions a matter for reasonable public concern.ko      The Government therefore proposes that the new legislation should establish a single body to be known as the Commission for industry and Manpower to which references could be made on matters which have in the past been dealt with by the two bodies.The new Bill would supersede all the  existing legislation onmonopolies and mergers and on prices and incomes but with anumber of modifications.     It would not simply establish a body which vrculd  in future  carry out  the functions of the Commissionand the Board in their respective legislation.    The main provisions which it is proposed to include in the new legiala-tion are outlined below.A.  PRIVATELY OWNED ENTERPRISES5o      The legislation will provide for a reference of matters arising from or relating to  the  conduct of an individual enter-prise for the purpose of reporting on whether any aspects of the issues raised in the reference operate against the public interestincluding the provisions of the prices and incomes policy.    Theindividual firms whose activities could be so referred would be those : -a.    which have capital employed of more than  10m.,  orbo    which supply or purchase at  least one-third of specified goods or services in the UK or a substantial part of it.The inclusion of large firms within the field of possible enquirydoes not of  course imply any presumption that the conduct of alarge firm is against the public interest;  any more than in thepresent monopolies legislation the control of one-third of themarket is presumed to be against the public interest.    In both cases the purpose of an enquiry is to  establish whether thepublic interest is affected,&apos; and if so what  should be done about it.2
6.     The possibility of references of firns with capital employed of more than I0n would apply to about 400 major industrial firns and to the major financial institutions.     It would include most major firms in important industrieswhether or not they controlled one-third of the market in particular products,and would therefore cover the important cases arising at present under theprices and incomes policy while excluding many snail firns7.    References to the new Commission would be possible on any aspect of theconduct of the business where it was considered that the question of publicinterest arose.     The legislation would make it clear that it was intended tocover enquiries into specific questions concerning prices and profits, conductlikely to restrict or distort competition and payments to enployees and share-holders.     References would not be made of matters olearly regulated by the restrictive Practices or other legislation.8.    In considering any reference the Commission would be required to have regardto the public interest (which would be defined in the legislation in terns similarto Section 14 of the 1948 Monopolies Act) as well as to the prices and incomes policy or other general considerations (which would be set out fron tine to time inStatutory Orders made under the Act).9.     Normally the Commission would be asked to consider and report on specificaspects of the conduct of Its business by a particular firm.     Some of the references might be related to such specific matters as a particular price rise ora pay settlement.     A reference night be related to specific issues of discrimin-ation against suppliers or distributors.     Such references would be dealt withexpeditiously by the Commission as have such enquiries by the NBPI.10,   Other references would be concerned with wider questions affecting individual firms and would naturally take a longer period to complete.     These will include the studies of major monopolies of the kind carried out by the Monopolies Commission inthe past.     However, even in these cases, it is desirable to shorten the periodtaken for carrying out the enquiry and the legislation will provide for fixing by ministers of a date by which the new Commission shall report.11.  The legislation will also provide for references of agreements and commonpractices among these concerned with providing or purchasing services where theseappear likely to prevent, restrict, or distort conpetition (most such agreements inrespect of the supply of goods will of course remain a matter for the restrictive trade Practices Court and not the Commission).&quot;1.2.   It is also intended to continue the provision for a reference to theCommission where two or more firns conduct their business (though without anyregistrable agreement or arrangement between then) in such a way as to prevent,/restrict
CONFIDEMTIALrestrict or distort competition.   In most cases, the conduct of the firms concerned would he referable in any case since they would fall within the definition in paragraph 4.     However, some of the firms concerned might not fall within this definition;    and in this sort of case it would be desirable for allthe firms concerned to be referred.B.    MERGERS1,3.     The new legislation will incorporate the provisions on mergers (includingnewspaper mergers) contained in the Monopolies and Mergers Act.     It isnot intended to make significant amendments in these provisions.14.   Experience has however shown the desirability of enquiring at a later dateinto the consequences for the public interest of mergers to which no objection is raised.     At the time of a merger it may be expected that the advantages v/hichwill flow from the merger are likely to offset any disadvantages to the publicinterest flowing from increased concentration of market power. .   The government considers it desirable in certain cases to enquire later whether the advantagesexpected from the merger have actually resulted and whether the disadvantageshave been no greater than was thought.     It is therefore intended to provide for references of this character.     The firms concerned would of course in nearly allcases fall within the definition in paragraph 5 above.NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES15.   Nationalised industries are of course normally established by statutes which require them to conduct their affairs with proper regard for the public interest.Nevertheless&apos;, there may be matters arising where an investigation by the Commissionnay be desirable, and the legislation will provide for references on nationalised industries with capital employed of more than  10m.     These will include incertain cases proposals to raise prices or charges;    and proposed pay settlements.1&apos;6.    However, in addition, Ministers may wish to ask the Commission to undertakegeneral enquiries into efficiency in individual nationalised industries.     these enquiries will be of the sane kind as those now carried out by the NBPI.     Thelegislation will be in sufficiently wide terms to enable this to be done.; NBPI in relation to pay in the public services, and suitable provisions&quot;willnade for this in the legislation. /. fl
CONF8DENTIM.13.   References to the Commission on these matters will in no way affect thearrangements for pay negotiations in the public services any more than in private industry or the nationalised industries.   References may be concerned with individual claims or settlements for a particular group of workers and the purposeof the reference would be to investigate whether it conformed with incomes policy.19*   The legislation will also provide for wider ranging enquiries into paystructures and their relation to efficiency in the public services.   There will beocoasions on which Ministers may wish to ask the Commission to undertake such general studies of particular services in the public sector.20.   The Commission will also be given the responsibility of advising theGovernment on the remuneration of a number of persons for whom no negotiating machinery exists.   One example of this is the pay of the Armed Forces where theCommission will take over the present responsibility of the NBPI for advising theGovernment on the remuneration.2i\,  k paragraph to be inserted here, describing the Commission^ functionswith respect to politically sensitive top salaries, is under discussion by theIndustrial Policy Committee and when agreed will be inserted before publication^PRICES AND INCOMES POLICY22.   References will be made to the Commission in appropriate cases where it isthought that proposed price rises or pay settlements are contrary to the prices and incomes policy or raise general problems of importance in relation to that policy.   References of proposed price increases and pay settlements by individualenterprises will be able to be referred under the provisions of the earlierSections.   It is not intended to take power to make references concerning charges or pay settlements by enterprises or organisations not covered by the preceding paragraphs.2-3,   In order to provide a means of receiving national pay agreements, it willalso be necessary, to provide for the reference to the Commission of payagreements concluded by two or more employers, and the legislation will so provide./GENERAL REFERENCES5
GENERAL REFERENCES24o   The legislation would provide for reference to the   Commission of generalmatters affecting an industry as a whole or a practice in the economy as a whole.It would therefore be possible for the Commission to carry out studies such asthose of the Monopolies Commission on recommended resale prices or the NBPI&apos;sreports on toiletries or Job Evaluation.POWERS OF THE GOVERNMENT2&apos;5,   The legislation will provide for notification of price increases, pay settlements and declared dividends along the lines of Part II of the 1966 prices and Incomes Act.   These powers will be on a permanent basis.   The government believes, however, that these matters are best handled by voluntary arrangements and hopes jit will not be necessary to make use of the powers which will be-thereonly in reserve.2&quot;fS,   The legislation will provide for standstill arrangements in respect ofmergers along the lines of those in the 1965 Act.    It is not intended to include in the new legislation provisions for stand stills on other matters while theCommission is investigating them.27.   In cases where the Commission reports that the conduct of an enterprise isin specified respects contrary to the public interest, Ministers will have thepowers set out in Section 3 of the 1965 Monopolies Act.   These powers will be exercisable only insofar as they are relevant for the purpose of remedying the specific mischiefs which the Commission has reported to exist.   The power toregulate prices in particular will be exeroisable only where the   Commissionfinds that the prices charged (or to be charged) would be against the publicinterest because of the unreasonable exercise of the power of the enterprise todetermine prices for goods or services which it is supplying.28.   The legislation will also give Ministers a new power to forbid therecommendation of resale prices for its goods by any enterprise where theCommission has reported that the practice would in the particular case operate against the public interest./&apos;29o
29.   It is proposed that the Coraadssion should consist of a full-timeChairman, and up say to 20 other full-time Members and part-time Members.The Chairman would have a power in particular cases after consultation withthe Minister to appoint some members of the Commission as a Panel to dealwith a particular reference and report to Ministers on behalf of the commission as a whole.     The Commission would conduct inquiries only on references to it by ministers and time limits would be set for the making of reports.     TheCommission would be encouraged to establish a strong Secretariat and would begiven the responsibility of keeping under review important matters concerningits general field of activity.     The Commission would operate in an independentmanner and would have the necessary powers to obtain information relevant to the references made to it, and a duty to avoid the unnecessary disclosure of such information.


</content>
</cab>
