<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/43 images: 431-442</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1973CM (71) Copy No. 1143rd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 3 August, 1971,at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the following were also present:The Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,   The Right Hon. Frederick Corfield,Minister for Trade (Items 6 and 7) u p, Minister for Aerospace (Item 5)Mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, Chief   The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Secretary, Treasury Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. E. Thornton: i    . Mr. J. crocker mr. P. J. hudson mr. B. G. tucker mr. J. Anson
ContentsItemSubjectPage1     Parliamentary Affairs     ...............      32     Oversea Affairs     ..................      3ChinaPakistanRolls-Royce RB211 Engine3     Northern Ireland   ..................      44     Rhodesia       .....................      45     Aircraft Industry   ..................      47     Employment of Aliens in Great Britain       ......      88     Student Union Finance     ...............     10Rolls-Royce M45H Engine6Malta69British Petroleum Limited11
secret. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary informed theCabinet that it now seemed probable that at the forthcoming meetingof the General Assembly of the United Nations the United StatesGovernment would support the admission of the People&apos;s republic of China to the Organisation but would also oppose the inevitableattempt to expel the Taiwan Government. If they maintained this&quot; two-Chinas &quot; policy without compromise, they might make it moredifficult to pursue President Nixon&apos;s recent overtures to the People&apos;republic. But in the last resort they would probably acquiesce in a vote in favour of the expulsion of the Taiwan Government.Meanwhile, our negotations for the appointment of an ambassador in Peking were making reasonably satisfactory progress. But theywere complicated by the insistence of the Government of the People&apos;republic that Taiwan should be described in the relevantcommunique as a province of China.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary informed the Cabinetthat the Government of India had now rejected the proposal by theSecretary-General of the United Nations that special arrangements should be made on the frontier between India and East Pakistan toenable the United Nations to try to persuade the refugees that theycould safely return to East Bengal. The Indian Government had also required our voluntary organisations engaged in the relief of distress in East Pakistan to withdraw within 10 days on the groundthat Indian resources were adequate to deal with the situation. these. The Cabinet were informed of the arrangements for theremainder of the current week before the summer Recess, including a proposed debate on Northern Ireland on the Motion for the adjournment, and for the period after the Recess before Prorogationon 28 October. The decisive debate on our accession to theEuropean Economic Communities would take place from 21 to 28October; and, despite the demand for additional time which would undoubtedly be made, it would be necessary to arrange for the finalvote to be taken at 10 p.m. on the last day.The House of Lords might need to reassemble slightly earlier than the House of Commons in order to complete other outstandingbusiness. As regards the debate in the Upper House on our accession to the Communities, it would be for subsequent consideration whether the final vote, which was likely to show alarge majority in favour of the Governments policy, should takeplace on 28 October or on the previous day.i The arrangements for these debates after the Recess would need to take account of the fact that important issues in our negotiationsfor accession to the Communities, including the Fisheries regulation and the arrangements for the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man,would probably not have been concluded before the final vote wastaken.
developments offered little prospect of Indian co-operation inresolving the problem of East Pakistan.The Cabinet were informed that the United States Senate had now voted by a majority of one in favour of the United states government providing the necessary financial guarantee to enablethe Lockheed Corporation to proceed with the TriStar aircraft.Provided that we were also satisfied that the requisite orders wouldbe placed by the airlines, the future of the Rolls-Royce RB 211engine seemed assured.It was agreed that in these circumstances the GovernmentsWhite Paper on the episode should be published in the fairly nearfuture. The Cabinet should consider the precise timing of publication in September.Rolls-RoyceRB211 EnginePreviousReference:CM (71) 42ndConclusions,Minute 7NorthernIrelandPrevious ,; -\.Reference:CM (71) 40thConclusions,Minute 2 vSECRET3. In the course of a short discussion about Northern Irelandthe Cabinet agreed that the Prime Minister, the Home Secretary,the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and the Secretary of Statefor Defence should be authorised to take whatever action might berequired at short notice to deal with developments during the Recess.The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that during his absencein the following week the Home Secretary would be in charge of theGovernment.SECRETRhodesia 4.   The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary informed thePrevious Cabinet that, provided that the regime in Salisbury responded to his reference: latest message to their leader, Mr. Ian Smith, it should be possibleCM (71) 42nd to arrange the next stages in the negotiations in such a way that theConclusions, issue would not come to a head in Parliament until the followingMinute 4 Session.AircraftIndustryRolls-RoyceM45H EngineSECRET5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Trade and Industry (CP (71) 97) about the Rolls-RoyceM45H engine.The Minister for Aerospace said that Rolls-Royce Ltd. had beenpartners with a French engine company, SNECMA, in developing the M45H engine for a small German passenger aircraft, theVFW 614. The original estimated development cost of  20 millionhad been financed in agreed proportions by the German Government,Rolls-Royce and SNECMA; and the British Government had notbeen directly involved. The estimated cost had now increased to 37 million and might reach  45 million. Rolls-Royce (1971) Ltd.
!had not yet assumed contractual responsibility for the project. until recently they had been prepared to take it over, provided that theGerman Government and SNECMA contributed their share of theincreased development cost and that a higher selling price for the engine was negotiated. They had now concluded, however, that the project was unlikely to be profitable; and, while they would have preferred a Government indemnity against any loss on development or production, their latest suggestion was that the Government should provide launching aid up to a maximum of  9 million, leaving themto finance production and to bear the remaining risks of the project.On commercial grounds there was no case for continuing theventure; and it was for consideration whether the Government should become involved at all. Termination of the project, however, wouldinvolve substantial claims for damages against the Rolls-RoyceReceiver; it would constitute a setback to the hopes of increasedEuropean collaboration on aero-engine projects in future; and itmight affect the German attitude towards continued collaboration with us on the Multi-Role Combat Aircraft (MRCA). If these considerations were regarded as overriding, the best course would beto offer launching aid within a maximum of  5 million, on condition that Rolls-Royce negotiated satisfactory terms with the Germaninterests and with SNECMA and obtained the agreement of theformer to a substantial increase in the engine selling price, to a reviewOf delivery dates and to German financing of any &quot; stretched &quot; version of the engine which German requirements might entail. Since these negotiations would have to take place during the Recess, the cabinet might wish to give some preliminary consideration to their attitudeif Rolls-Royce were unable to achieve a settlement on this basis.In discussion it was argued that, while the termination of theM45H project was not likely to lead the German authorities to cancel the MRCA undertaking outright, it could affect our chances ofsecuring an increased share of avionics orders under the MRCAdevelopment programme. At a time when the future of the Britishaerospace industry was still under examination following the failureof Rolls-Royce Ltd. it would be inappropriate to take action whichwould prejudice future European collaborative projects, on whichthe industry was likely to depend. The effect on employment in theUnited Kingdom also ought to be carefully considered before any decision to terminate the M45H project was taken. On the otherhand it was argued that, if this venture was allowed to continue,Rolls-Royce (1971) Ltd. would be participating in a furtheruneconomic project in addition to the RB211 engine and the concorde aircraft. Any risk of damage to our interest in the MRCAproject might be reduced by delaying a final reply until the end ofAugust. The effect on employment would be felt mainly in bristol and Coventry; and a contribution of  5 million to the project could hardly be justified on employment grounds. It was probablyunrealistic to suppose that, once launching aid was given, it couldbe limited to a single payment. It would be an addition to public expenditure which had not been provided for in the latest public expenditure survey; and it would therefore require further offsetting savings in other programmes to be found.
i In further discussion it was suggested that, if launching aid wasto be given, strenuous efforts should be made to arrest furtherescalation in cost, not least by strengthening the management of rolls-Royce (1971) Ltd. The launching aid should in any case not cover the total development cost. Negotiations should be based onthe assumption that the development cost might eventually rise as high as  45 million. The German interests should be asked tocontribute 50 per cent of the increased development cost; and, inaddition to the other conditions proposed in CP (71)97, they shouldbe asked to give a guarantee that the VFW 614 aircraft project wouldnot be abandoned.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet accepted that the British interest in future collaboration onthe MRCA and other European projects justified the provision of launching aid for the M45H engine project. Rolls-Royce (1971) Ltd.should now be asked to negotiate with the German Government andSNECMA on the basis proposed in paragraph 8 of CP (71) 97. TheGerman Government should be asked to meet 50 per cent of any increased development cost and to give a guarantee that the VFW 614aircraft project would not be abandoned. If the negotiations couldnOt be settled on this basis, the Cabinet should consider the matter again.;i   The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister and invited the Ministerfor Aerospace to proceed accordingly.CONFIDENTIALMalta 6.  The   Cabinet  considered  recent  developments  in thePrevious        negotiations for a new agreement on defence and financial relationsReference:       with Malta.CM (71) 42ndConclusions, . The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that at the minute 3 previous meeting he had been invited to put forward, in association with the Secretary of State for Defence, proposals for a new offer tothe Malta Government on the assumption that our original proposalto the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) that we should contribute about  1  million a year towards a NATO cash offer of 6-1 million a year over a period of four to six years failed to attract the necessary support from our allies. Proposals had been draftedaccordingly; but changes in the past 24 hours had made itinappropriate for the Cabinet to consider them substantively. Duringthe week-end the United States Government had conditionally agreedto offer up to  2 million a year towards our proposed  6% millionoffer; and, in view of this encouraging response, he had obtainedI the; agreement of the Prime Minister and of the other ministers principally concerned to the proposal that, at the North Atlantic: CounciTs further meeting on 2 August, we should offer alternativecontributions of  5 million a year in economic aid, or  1^ million
i   !ia year in cash together with  3^ million in economic aid. The ItalianGovernment were also likely to make a contribution of up to 1 million; and the Federal German Government might well do thesame. On this basis the total should not be far short of the figure of 10 million a year which, in the view of the Secretary of State for defence and himself, might represent a settlement which mr. Mintoff would be unable to reject without alienating his own public opinion. But it might be desirable to increase the aid content of our own offer to  5 million, if this was necessary in order to raisethe total of NATO contributions to  10 million.In discussion it was pointed out that an offer of  10 million a year to Mr. Mintoff would represent a very considerable improvement over the terms which his Nationalist Party predecessor,Dr. Borg Olivier, had accepted, since under existing agreementsMalta would receive no more than  4 million in 1972-73 and 3 million or less in subsequent years. Mr. Mintoffs standing in malta would therefore be greatly strengthened by an offer of the kindnow envisaged, which might be interpreted as a virtual capitulationby the United Kingdom to the intransigence with which he hadconducted the negotiations. On the other hand the strong NATOinterest both in enjoying the island&apos;s facilities and in denying themto the Soviet Union made it essential to demonstrate to the Maltese people that we were doing all that we reasonably could to seek an agreement. Mr. Mintoffs reactions were irrational andunpredictable; and we could not ignore the possibility that, if he felthimself rebuffed by the West he would turn to the Soviet Union,despite the political embarrassment which he might incur in doing so., In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) So far the only positive indications of willingness to subscribe to a new financial agreement had come from the UnitedStates, Italy and the Federal Republic of Germany. An effort shouldbe made to ensure that other Western Powers, especially France, alsocontributed.(b) Information from Belgian sources suggested that Mr. Mintoffhad already modified his aims and would now be content to reach agreement on the basis of an annual payment of  18 million. This,though still far from reasonable, represented a considerable reduction from his original demand for  30 million a year; and itsuggested that he might yet be persuaded to reduce his price stillfurther. There were also some indications that, contrary to hisearlier assertions, he would be prepared to receive part of thesubvention in the form of economic aid.(c) It would be desirable to send an interim reply to Mr. Mintoffduring the current week, indicating that we were still in discussionwith our NATO partners. The tactics of our substantive reply,however, might subsequently prove to be a matter of some difficulty.If we offered at the outset the full amount which we had in mind,Mr. Mintbff would be liable to regard this as merely an opening bid;and he would then proceed to seek to compel us to increase it. If,however, we initially offered a smaller sum, say  7 million, ourattempt to show ourselves to the Maltese public as reasonable and
fair negotiators might not be realised. Moreover, Mr. Mintoff wouldprobably be aware, through various unauthorised disclosures, of the exact content of the agreed NATO offer.(d) We must make it clear that in return for an offer of 10 million a year we should expect the exclusive NATO use of malta&apos;s defence facilities, together with their denial even to countries,like Libya, who were not members of the Warsaw Pact.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that an interim reply to Mr. Mintoff, indicating that discussions within NATO were still continung, should be sent at anearly date. Meanwhile, efforts should be made to obtain adequatecontributions to a NATO offer, together with a parallel offer in thecase of France, from those countries which had so far failed to come forward. The maximum offer to Mr. Mintoff should be based on ourown offer of a  \\ million cash contribution plus  3^ million aid,together with whatever sums our allies might be induced to volunteer.In the light of the final outcome of our approach to NATO, furtherconsideration should be given to the negotiating tactics by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and the Secretary of State for Defence.They should have discretion to determine the terms of our openingoffer; but it seemed desirable to keep some margin in reserve forpurposes of negotiation.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and theSecretary of State for Defence to proceed accordingly.Employment of aliens inGreat BritainPreviousReference:CM (71) 25thConclusions,Minute 4CONFIDENTIAL7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Employment making proposals to restrict further theemployment of foreign workers in Great Britain (CP (71) 92).The Secretary of State for Employment said that, when theCabinet had considered in May proposals for further restrictions onthe employment of foreign workers in Britain, they had reachedgeneral agreement in principle but had decided that a change ofpolicy should not be announced until our negotiations for accession to the European Economic Communities (e.c.) had made further progress. The position in this respect was now clear; and he accordingly proposed that no further permits to work in industryand commerce (apart from hotels and catering) should be issued for unskilled and semi-skilled men from foreign countries other thanthose which were members, or candidates for membership, of the eec. This proposal had been generally accepted by the other ministers concerned. As regards foreign workers in the hotel and catering industry, there should be further restrictions on the issue ofpermits for semi-skilled workers and seasonally employed unskilled workers. This would be achieved by establishing a quota of 3,500
for such workers for 1972 from all foreign countries other thanmembers, and candidates for membership, of the e.c.. Asignifipantly larger quota would not constitute an adequateinducement to our hotel and catering industry to recruit, train and provide suitable working conditions for British nationals. At a timeof, substantial unemployment it seemed clearly desirable to exert themaximum possible pressure on the industry in this direction. Inview of the proposed discrimination in favour of nationals of EECmember countries and of countries applying for membership of the communities, the Cabinet might think it desirable that theannouncement of the proposals as a whole should be deferred until after the Parliamentary debate at the end of October on UnitedKingdom accession to the e.c..The Minister for Trade said that a very large expansion of theBritish hotel industry was now in train; some 41,000 new hotel roomswould be available in England by 1972. There was no prospect ofobtaining additional labour on the scale required if the quota were as low as that proposed by the Secretary of State for Employment.If, however, the number of foreign workers allowed to enter in 1972were reduced by 1,000 or 2,000 rather than by the 4,000 implied bythe Secretary of State&apos;s proposal, this would impose the necessarypressures on the industry without making it impossible for them to recruit sufficient staff.In discussion it was pointed out that many workers regardedhotel and catering employment as essentially menial and accordinglypreferred, even at considerable financial penalty, to remainunemployed rather than to take such work. In the last 10 yearsBritish nationals had absorbed most of the additional skilled jobsavailable in the industry; and foreign workers had in the mainprovided the unskilled labour, which tended to be poorly paid andto provide less attractive working conditions than other employment.Moreover, in the absence of any restrictions on nationals of member states of the e.c., the only effect of the proposals before theCabinet would be a larger influx of Italian workers to replace the lossof Spanish and Portuguese. On the other hand the hotel and cateringindustry was a major growth industry in this country; and, ifemployment was to be provided for those who could no longer find employment in declining industries, a real effort must be made toensure that the hotel and catering industry provided unskilled and semi-skilled, as well as skilled, work for British nationals.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theSecretary of State for Employment, the Secretary of State for social services and the Minister for Trade should discuss the matter withthe hotel and catering industry. It should be made plain that theGovernment were determined to reduce the number of foreign nationals employed on unskilled and semi-skilled work in the industryin order that more jobs might be available for British nationals; andit should be emphasised that suitable arrangements for obtaining andtraining the latter must be put in hand. The Ministers concerned should also consider with the hotel and catering interests how anyprejudices on the part of British workers against taking employment
in the industry might best be overcome. They should report the outcome of these discussions to the Cabinet in order that a decisionon the level of the quota to be applied might be taken in time forannouncement by the end of October.The Cabinet-Invited  the Secretary of State for Employment, theSecretary of State for Social Services and the Minister for trade to proceed on the lines indicated by the PrimeMinister in his summing up of the discussion.CONFIDENTIALStudent Union 8. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofFinance State for Education and Science (CP (71) 98) on the financing of student unions.The Secretary of State for Education and Science said that membership of student unions was normally compulsory. Theunions&apos; main source of income was the students&apos; subscriptions, thelevel of which was fixed by agreement between each union and theacademic institution concerned; in the case of students withmandatory awards, who constituted the majority, the subscriptionwas paid direct by the local education authority to the union as partof the award. The funds were intended to provide recreational facilities for students and to support student activites such as clubs.But the unions tended to be controlled by politically consciouscliques; and money was being diverted from its proper purposes tothe support of political demonstrations and extreme Left-wing. i activities. This stage of affairs was already in danger of becoming a public scandal and would deteriorate still further if no remedial action was taken. She therefore proposed to consult the Vice-&apos; 1 . v .! : Chancellors and representatives of local education authorities and students about the desirability of an alternative arrangement whereby the provision of student facilities would become the responsibilityof academic institutions and student maintenance grants would be somewhat increased in order to give the individual student the means to support the activities of his choice. The Home and Social AffairsCommittee, however, while accepting that there were serious abusesin the present system, had doubted whether the benefits which wouldresult from her proposals would outweigh the hostility which theywould be likely to excite among student organisations.In discussion there was general agreement on the need to curb themisuse of union funds; but opinions differed on the wisdom of taking action at the present time. The reaction of the student unions would undoubtedly be hostile; and, although the response of the Vice-Chancellors was less certain, it was unlikely that all who approvedof the Governmenfs proposals would be prepared to say so in public.It would also be a mistake to place too much reliance on popularsupport. The great bulk of public opinion might sympathise withthe proposals; but it would be less vocal than the critical minority.
It might therefore be preferable to defer any initiative for somemonths and to use the interval to educate public opinion on thesubject.On the other hand it was suggested that the misuse of fundsresulting from domination of the unions by a minority was resentedby the majority of students and was in itself a source of studentunrest. The Government should not necessarily assume that theproposals would inevitably provoke a major controversy; instead,they should proceed with caution, sounding the ground as they went.The first step should be to consult the Vice-Chancellors, and,thereafter, the local education authorities on a confidential basis. Inthe light of those discussions it would be possible to decide whether to approach the students&apos; unions. Meanwhile an attempt should bemade to educate public opinion about the matter.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed in principle that the misuse of student union fundsought to be checked. There was some difference of opinion aboutthe wisdom of initiating any action for this purpose at the presenttime; but on balance the Cabinet favoured an approach in confidence to the Vice-Chancellors and the local education authorities,suggesting changes on the lines advocated by the Secretary of State.A decision whether to approach the student unions and whether totake steps to prepare public opinion for changes in the present arrangements should be taken in the light of the outcome of these consultations. The Secretary of State should proceed accordingly,reporting to her colleagues as appropriate.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion and invited the Secretary of State for education and Science to act accordingly.SECRET*9. The Chief Secretary said that the Chairman of british petroleum Ltd. (BP) had approached the Chancellor of the Exchequerearlier in the year inviting the Government to subscribe  70 million in 1971-72 to take up their share of a rights issue of Ordinary Shareswhich would be announced on 23 September and would be intendedto raise  140 million in total. BP&apos;s requirements had now beenreduced to  120 million; and the Government had been asked tocontribute  60 million, to be subscribed in two equal instalments in1971-72 and 1972-73. The Chancellor of the Exchequer hoped thatthe Cabinet would agree that we should accede to this suggestion.It would have little impact on demand, since it would represent afunding of existing BP loans and no offsetting savings in public expenditure would be required in order to provide for thesubscription. If the Government refused to take up their rights,however, this might be interpreted as indicating that they had some doubts about the company&apos;s prospects; and general confidence inBP might be adversely affected.
In discussion it was suggested that in present market conditions it should be possible for BP to obtain a larger proportion of its financial requirements from private investors and that theGovernment should therefore not take up their rights in full,especially since the cost to the Exchequer of borrowing the money would be substantially more than the dividends which we could expect to receive from the investment. On the other hand it waspointed out that since the British Governments first participation inBP early in the century the investment had proved extremelyprofitable and it was reasonable to expect that this furthersubscription would prove no less advantageous over a period.The Cabinet-Agreed that the Government should take up their share ofthe forthcoming rights issue by BP at a cost of  60 millionpayable in 1971-72 and 1972-73.Cabinet Office,3 August, 1971.

</content>
</cab>
