<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/52/12 images: 140-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm(73) 34th COPY no conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 28 JUNE 1973at 11. 30 am.-.PRESENTThe Rt Hon Edward Heath mp prime minister the Rt Hon Sir Alec Douglas-Home mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon William Whitelaw mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Robert Carr mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon Maurice Macmillan mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC mp minister for Trade and ConsumerThe Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St marylebone lord chancellor the Rt Hon Lord carrington secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Prior mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Geoffrey Rippon QC mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Gordon Campbell mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Peter Thomas QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Joseph Godber mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Rt Hon Lord windlesham lord Privy seal the Rt Hon Peter Walker mp secretary of State for Trade and Industry
THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MP The Rt Hon Francis Pym mp chief Secretary, Treasury (Item l) Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Rt Hon The Earl St AldwynCaptain, Gentlemen-at-Arms (Item 1)secretarial the Rt Hon Sir Burke trend sir John hunt mr H F T smith mr P benner mr I T lawman mr D evans contents item                                                            Subject page 1.                   PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS national Health Service Reorganisation Bill 1Publication of Parliamentary Papers 1Legislative Programme 1973-74 22, OVERSEA AFFAIRSFrench Nuclear Tests 3Rhodesia 33. EUROPEAN COMMUNITY AFFAIRSRegional Aids 4Council of Ministers 4Sugar Refining Margin 5New Zealand 54.                  NORTHERN IRELAND 7ii
SubjectINDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSFrench Nuclear TestsIndustrial Relations ActCounter-Inflation policy the Motor IndustryCammell Laird
4PARLIAMENTARY  1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the affairs House of Commons during the following week.NationalHealthServiceReorganisationBillPreviousReference:CM(73) 15thConclusions,Minute 3The Cabinet considered the tactics to be adopted in seeking to reverse the amendment removing the power to make any charge for family planning services, which had been adopted by the Houseof Lords on consideration of the Commons amendments to theNational Health Service Reorganisation Bill.    Opinion in the Houseof Commons about the merits of this issue was divided, not whollyon Party lines.    Theise appeared to be general agreement, however,that the primacy of the House of Commons in relation to financial matters must be maintained; and this attitude was likely to be relevant to the consideration not merely of the present amendmentbut also of an alternative amendment which it appeared might subsequently be moved in the House of Lords, providing for thecontinuance of a free family planning service in any local authorityarea in which it was provided without charge at the time when theBill came into effect at the cost of additional public expenditure ofthe order of  500,000 a year.    In the House of Lords the majorityview held that, on merits^ family planning services provided by theNational Health Service should be entirely free; but on theconstitutional issue there was general acceptance of the improprietyof seeking in the last resort to challenge the primacy of the House ofCommons in financial matters.    In these circumstances it wastactically desirable that the forthcoming debate in the House ofCommons, together with any subsequent debate in the House ofLords, should be directed primarily not to the relative merits of the arguments for and against charging for family planning butto the constitutional issues which had been raised.    In the light ofthis conclusion the Secretary of State for Social Services and theChief Whip should consider how the debate in the House of Commonscould best be managed.PublicationofParliamentaryPapersPreviousReference:CM(73) 33rdConclusions,Minute 1The Cabinet were informed that difficulties continued to be encountered in connection with the printing and publicationof Parliamentary papers.    The employees concerned, whoseweekly earnings were already in the range  75- 90 when parliament was sitting, were claiming increases of pay well above the amountspermissible under the Pay Code.    The Pay Board might consider,during the following week, making an Order requiring them to desistfrom industrial action; but 14 days1 notice of such an Order wouldhave to be given and it could not therefore come into operation beforemid-July.    Legal action might subsequently be considered under the counter-Inflation Act; but it could scarcely be effective before the
tmiddle of August,    There was likely to be little public sympathy forthe printing workers, particularly in view of their already highaverage earnings.    But legal action under the Counter-InflationAct seemed likely to be counter-productive, while any attempt tomake arrangements on a permanent basis for Parliamentary documents to be printed elsewhere - perhaps outside the United Kingdom - was likely to have unfavourable repercussions on industrial relationsgenerally.    The position would be kept under careful review; butit seemed besta at least for the time being, to rely on the existingemergency arrangements, which had so far proved adequate toprevent any unacceptable interruption of Parliamentary business.LegislativeProgramme1973-74PreviousReference:CM(73) 22ndConclusions,Minute 9THE PRIME MINISTER referred to a report on the preparation oflegislation for the next Session of Parliament, which the lord president of the Council had recently addressed to all membersof the Cabinet.    Progress so far had been disquietingly slow;  andthere was now a danger that the number of Bills ready for introduction into both Houses of Parliament early in the next Session would be insufficient to secure the orderly management of the Governmentslegislative programme.    At the present stage of the year the demands on the Parliamentary draftsmen were relatively light; and it was important that Ministers contemplating legislation should takeadvantage of this opportunity by ensuring that agreement wasreached on any outstanding policy issues, and that the preparationof drafting instructions was completed, at the earliest possible moment.Ministers should also arrange that all questions requiring collectiveconsideration by the Cabinet or one of its Committees should now besubmitted as rapidly as possible in order to anticipate an excessiveconcentration of business on the eve of the Parliamentary Recess,2
t2, THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat the French Government had refused to comply with an interiminjunction by the International Court of Justice restraining them fromconducting a series of nuclear tests in the Pacific Ocean in the nearfuture.    As a result we were coming under renewed pressure tomake a formal protest to them on this issue.    It should suffice,however, to maintain our public contention that they were alreadywell aware of our views.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that thePermanent Under Secretary of State, Sir Denis Greenhill, had metboth Mr Ian Smith, the leader of the Rhodesian regime, andBishop Muzorewa of the African National Council in the courseof his recent visit to Rhodesia.    There were some signs that both parties might be beginning to realise that they must make a fresheffort to reach an accommodation.    Sanctions were having someeffect on the Rhode sian economy; and the recent outbreak of Africanterrorism was making an even greater impact on local opinion,Mr Smith had agreed to discuss the situation with Bishop Muzorewain the near future.    The modifications to the 1971 proposals whichthe Bishop had in mind appeared to be fairly modest; but sir Denis Greenhill had advised him to concentrate initiallyon trying to establish a satisfactory personal relationship withMr Smith and not to press his proposals at the outset.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the statements by theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary.OVERSEAAFFAIRSFrenchNuclearTestsRhode siaPreviousReference:CM(73) 32ndConclusions,Minute 2
3. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat the Commission of the European Communities had now agreed on the application to the United Kingdom of the Community system of&quot;central&quot; and &quot;peripheral&quot; areas for the limitation of State aids to industry.    The Commission decision was satisfactory.    Our non-Assisted Areas and Intermediate Areas would be designated as&quot;central&quot; and the rest of the United Kingdom would be unclassified,Asa result we should be able to continue our present levels of aid.The Commission had also given an assurance that they would givesympathetic consideration to derogations to meet the special problemsof steel closures in the Intermediate Areas,    It had been agreed thatthere should be no public reference to this decision until it had been formally addressed to the Council of Ministers;  and we must therefore defer any comment until this step had been taken,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, saidthat the Cabinet agreed that the solution proposed by the commission was satisfactory.    Once the proposal had been formally addressed tothe Council it would be necessary for a statement to be made 5aParliament,    Further consideration should be given to its most appropriate timing.The Cabinet -L Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinisters summing up of their discussion.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatthe Council of Ministers, at their meeting on 25-26 June, had approved a document defining the approach of the community to the forthcoming multilateral trade negotiations.    This wasa significant achievement;  and the document should provide asatisfactory basis for the further preparatory work which wouldbe required.    The Council had also discussed Community relationships with those developing countries which would be parties to negotiations on a new Association Agreement,    There were some signs that theCouncil were beginning to appreciate that it would be preferable to refrain from pressing the developing countries to provide reciprocaltrade advantages to the Community unless they were willing to do so.The Cabinet -2, Took note, with approval, of the statement by the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary.
THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said thathe had just learned that the Commission proposed to rule that thesubsidy paid to our refiners of cane sugar was incompatible withthe Treaty of Rome.    We had introduced this subsidy following thefailure of the Agricultural Council in January to agree ontransitional arrangements for sugar which would allow anadequate margin for our cane sugar refiners.    The arrangement was politically important since, without an adequate margin, therefiners would be unable to fulfil the commitments into which theGovernment had entered with the developing countries of theCommonwealth Sugar Agreement.    We had repeatedly canvassedour views on this subject with the Commission; but they appearedto have decided to bring the matter to a conclusion without more ado.Urgent messages had accordingly been sent to the two BritishCommissioners, reiterating our case, emphasising the political importance of the subject and suggesting that it would be better toavoid precipitate action.    In addition, the United Kingdom permanent representative had been instructed to give the same message to theCommissioner responsible for agriculture.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatit would be necessary to give further thought to our policy.    Wecould raise the subject in the Council;  or we could allow eventsto take their course, continue to pay the subsidy and then defendour position as necessary before the European Court.    The variousoptions open to us should be urgently examined.The Cabinet -3. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister^ summing up of their discussion,4. Invited the Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and Food to submit to the Ministerial Committee onEurope, as rapidly as possible, proposals for dealingwith the alleged incompatibility between the Treaty of rome and our cane sugar refining subsidy.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD recalled that under the special arrangements set out in Protocol 18 to the Treatyof Accession the price guaranteed for New Zealand sales of butter and cheese to the United Kingdom was fixed in   sterling.    The NewZealand Government had continually pressed for allowance to bemade for changes in the value of the  ; but we had resisted all theseapproaches.    The situation had now been complicated, however, bythe fact that the New Zealand authorities had learned that the
Commission were crediting to the United Kingdom monetary-compensatory amounts in respect of our imports of New Zealandbutter and cheese relating to the change in parity between the   and community currencies since the introduction of the transitional arrangements on 1 February.    The New Zealand authorities had pressed for these compensatory amounts to be transferred to themselves.    In Discussion ssion with the New Zealand High Commissionerhe had rejected the claim that the full value of the sums involved was due to New Zealand; but he had agreed to consider the possibility ofa much smaller recoupment related to the change in parities betweenthe   sterling and the   New Zealand,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe possibility of compensating New Zealand for any changes in theparity of the   sterling involved major issues of principle.    Thesubject should therefore be urgently considered in the ministerial committee on Europe before it was taken any further either with theNew Zealand authorities or with the Commission.The Cabinet -5. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up of their discussion,6.        Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster to arrange for the Ministerial Committeeon Europe to consider urgently the problems arisingfrom the claim of the New Zealand Government to benefit from the compensatory sums allotted to theUnited Kingdom by the European Commission in respectof our imports of New Zealand dairy produce.6
northern ireland previous reference:CM(73) 33rdConclusions,Minute 44. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN ireland said that intensive security measures had been taken in the periodleading up to the elections to the new Assembly, which were takingplace that day;  and there had been less violence than had been feared.It remained impossible, however, to predict the probable outcome ofthe elections with any confidence.The Cabinet -Took note of the statement by the Secretary of Statefor Northern Ireland,
INDUSTRIAL-AFFAIRSFrench.NuclearTests5.        f HE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said thatthe General Council of the Trades Union Congress (TUC) had on theprevious day requested unions to boycott French goods, transport and communications during the first week in July as a protest against the proposed French nuclear tests in the Pacific Ocean.This seemed likely to lead to a refusal by postal workers to handlemail to and from France, and by dock workers to load and unloadFrench ships, during that week.IndustrialRelationsActThe General Council had also endorsed a recommendation that the27 unions which had defied the TUC policy of non-registration underthe Industrial Relations Act should be expelled if they had notderegistered when the TUC Annual Congress opened on 3 September.The Electrical Power Engineers Association had already decided toderegister;  and Equity might also do so.Counter-InflationPolicyThe Annual Conference of the Confederation of Shipbuilding and engineering Unions (CSEU) had on the previous day adopted aresolution put forward by the Amalgamated Union of EngineeringWorkers (AUEW) instructing the Executive Council of the CSEU topress the TUC not to participate in any discussion with theGovernment on any form of wage freeze and declaring that the confederation would not be bound by any decision arising fromthe discussions between the Government and the TUC which placedeither voluntary or imposed restraint on free collective bargainingin relation to wages and conditions of work.    While this decision was unlikely to prevent Mr Basnett, the representative of theGeneral and Municipal Workers Union (GMWU), from attending the Stage 3 discussions, since the union had already approved hisparticipation, it now seemed increasingly likely that Mr Jones, the spokesman of the Transport and General Workers Union, which hadabstained from voting on the AUEW resolution, would be obliged toput before the Annual Congress resolutions calling for the ending of restraint on collective bargaining.    The CSEU Conference had alsoadopted a claim for substantial improvements in the pay andconditions of skilled workers in general engineering, which wouldbe discussed with the Engineering Employers Federation on thefollowing day.
The strike by Chrysler workers at Ryton had now ended; but the shop stewards at Perkins Engines of Coventry were still seeking to insist,as a condition for the resumption of work, on a commitment by themanagement to parity of pay between the workers at Peterboroughand those at the parent Massey-Ferguson Company at Coventry.He had resisted a proposal by the employers that he should convene a court of inquiry; but he proposed to discuss the situation with the managing Director of Perkins on the following day,    A furtherdispute affecting the motor industry had arisen at the WellworthyCompany, one of the industry^ major suppliers of piston rings,where 600 workers at the foundry were now on strike.    Here,again, there was to be a meeting with the management on thefollowing day.A long-standing inter-union dispute between the GMWU and theBoilermakers Union about the recruitment of stagers at the CammellLaird works at Birkenhead had now led to picketing at the gates.    Ameeting was to be held that day in an endeavour to resolve the dispute.The Cabinet -Took note of the statements by the Secretary of Stateior Employment,Cabinet Office28 June 1973

</content>
</cab>
