<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/41/22 images: 168-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1944.SECRET.W.M. (44)22nd Conclusions.Copy No.WAR CABINET 22CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Thursday, 11th February, 1944, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, HP., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest . Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Lord   Woolton,The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir James Gricg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State forScotland.The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Sir William Jowitt,K.C., M.P., Minister without Port-folio.Major the Right Hon. G. LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Fuel andPower.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir ArchibaldSinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Lord Portal,Minister of. Works.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster- General.The    Right    Hon.womersley,     M.P.Pensions.Sir    WalterMinister   ofSecretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.MinuteN o.Contents.Subject.1      Indian Pood Grain Requirements2      Demobilisation ....[26966]Page102102
IndianFood GrainRequirements.(PreviousReference:W.M.(44)19tliConclusions.)1. At their meeting on the 7th February the War Cabinet hadconsidered the reply to be sent to the Viceroy about the Governmentof India&apos;s request for the continued importation of food grains. Areply on the lines approved bv the War Cabinet had been despatchedon the 15th February (No. 3891).The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet that a furthertelegram had now been received from the Viceroy (No. 332-S of the16th February) strongly urging the reconsideration of the WarCabinet&apos;s decision.The Prime Minister said that he thought the most convenientcourse would be for this telegram to be considered by the Committeeconsisting of the President of the Board of Education (in theabsence of the Secretary of State for India), the Minister of Food,the Minister of War Transport and the Paymaster-General whichhad previously examined this question.The War Cabinet-Approved this suggestion, and asked that the Committeeshould consider this further telegram from the Viceroy,and submit a report for consideration on Monday, the21st February.2.   The War Cabinet had before them (i) A Note by the Minister of Labour and National Service(W.P. (44) 71) with an Annex setting out proposals forthe reallocation of man-power during the transitionperiod between the end of the war in Europe and theend of the war in Japan;(ii) A Memorandum by the Home Secretary and Minister ofHome Security (W.P. (44) 94) dealing with the applica-tion of the proposals in W.P. (44) 71 to the Civil DefenceServices;(iii) A Joint Memorandum by the Home Secretary andMinister of Home Security and the Secretary of Statefor Scotland (W.P. (44) 97) on the question of the releaseof Regular Police serving with the Forces; and(iv) A Note by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs(W.P. (44) 106) covering a Colonial Office Memorandumon the question of the release from the Forces of recruitsfor the Colonial Service.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that hisproposals were confined to the demobilisation of the Armed Forcesand dealt only with the position in the transition period betweenthe end of the war in Europe and the end of the war in Japan.During this period the Navy and the Royal Air Force would haveto retain a larger proportion of their personnel than the Army, andhe had come to the conclusion that there should be no generaldemobilisation until the end of the war with Japan, and that duringthe transition period compulsory recruitment of men for the Forcesshould be continued, while releases of men should be regarded notas demobilisation but as a reallocation of man-power between theForces and Industry. The proposals must, on the one hand, satisfythe Forces that as many men as possible were being released, and,on the other hand, should release the necessary labour for essentialreconstruction work. Accordingly, in addition to the men, referredto as Class &quot; A,&quot; who would be released from the Forces on an ageand length of service basis, there should be an additional class,known as Class &quot; B,&quot; who would be transferred out of turn fromthe Forces to Industry for certain specified reconstruction employ-ments on the application of the Ministry of Labour. There wouldbe a marked distinction in treatment between the two classes.In addition to the men released in Classes &quot; A &quot; and &quot; B,&quot; itwould be necessary to provide for the release of a limited numberof specialists on an individual basis on the lines of existing practice.Demobilisation.(PreviousReference:W.M. (43) 170thConclusions,Minute 2.)
The Prime Minister complimented the Minister of Labour andNational Service and the Minister without Portfolio on theproposals. He stressed the importance of devising a straight-forward scheme which would be accepted as fair by the Forces, andsaid that the experience at the end of the last war showed that thefundamental principle must be release on the basis of age and lengthof service. He recognised that the release of a certain number ofmen in Class &quot;B&quot; was essential, but he felt that it would beimportant to keep down the number of men in this class, andsuggested that the proportion of Class &quot; B &quot; to Class &quot; A &quot; shouldnot exceed one to ten. He also emphasised the need for dis-tinguishing the treatment given to men in. Class &quot;A&quot; from that,given to men in Class &quot; B.&quot;The following points were raised in discussion :-- (a) Finance.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was lessconcerned with the total cost of the proposals than with thedesirability of making payments to men released from the Forces,in such a way as to avoid inflation and fit in with general economicpolicy. He suggested that it would be sufficient to give men inClass. &quot; A &quot; a period of six weeks, instead of eight weeks, onfurlough with full pay and allowances, and that the &quot; transfergrant &quot; proposed for men in Class &quot; B &quot; should be restricted totwo weeks instead of four. These periods did not include additionalperiods of paid furlough in respect of foreign service. This pointwas reserved. There were also certain other financial points (withwhich he need not trouble the War Cabinet) on which he was incorrespondence with the Minister of Labour.(b) Position of Civil Defence Workers.The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security claimedthat, although Civil Defence workers might not be entitled totreatment absolutely identical with that given to men in the Forces,they should receive similar consideration. Many Civil Defenceworkers had undertaken dangerous duties, and in pay andconditions of service they were in a similar position to men in theForces. &apos; He suggested that Civil Defence workers might at leastget the same treatment as men in Class &quot; B.&quot;The Prime Minister expressed doubt whether the claim couldbe justified.The Minister of Labour and National Service thought thatthere would be some advantage in having a separate schemeapplicable to Civil Defence Workers.The War Cabinet were informed that, in a note addressed tothe Prime Minister, the First Lord of the Admiralty had pointedout that any proposal to treat Civil Defence workers on lines similarto those proposed for the Forces might react on the Admiralty&apos;sDepartmental Constabularies^(c) Release of Regular Police.The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security and theSecretary of State for Scotland stressed the importance of releasingregular policemen as early as men in Class &quot; B.&quot; We must have anefficient police force to deal with any possible unrest in the yearsimmediately after the war, and the return of the regular police totheir duties could be regarded merely as a transfer from onedisciplined service to another.(d) Principle of Release on Basis of Age and Length of Service.It was pointed out that the principle of release on age andlength of service basis was not identical with the principle of &apos;&apos; firstin first out,&quot; since a weighting was given for age, and it was agreedthat the balance between the respective, weightings given for ageand length of service would require examination. It was alsoexplained that consideration had been given to the possibility ofgiving a weighting for foreign service, but after very full enquirythe conclusion had been reached that no practicable scheme couldbe devised.
(e) Public Announcement of the Proposals.In the Note which the First Lord of the Admiralty had sent tothe Prime Minister attention was drawn to the importance ofarranging the public announcement of the Governments proposalsin such a way as to avoid any danger that men in the Forces mightget a garbled version. It was agreed that the arrangements forannouncing the proposals would require very careful consideration.(f) Compensation to Men retained in the Forces.In his Note to the Prime Minister the First Lord of theAdmiralty suggested that men who would otherwise be entitled todemobilisation, but had to be retained because of overriding militaryneeds, should be given compensation by improved pay or specialgratuities. It was suggested that, so far as the Royal Air Forcewas concerned, an alternative might be to offer men retained forservice in the Japanese war permanent service in the peace-timeRoyal Air Force, which would, in any event, have to be kept at ahigh level. It was pointed out that issues of great difficulty werehere involved, which would have to be examined.(g) A gricultural Workers.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries said that he hopedthat it would be possible for some of the younger agriculturalworkers who had been reserved during the war to be called up forservice in the Forces and to be replaced by men released inClass &quot; B.&quot;(h) Release of Specialists.It was pointed out that it should be possible to meet theessential requirements of the Foreign Service and the ColonialService under the arrangements for the release of specialists set outin paragraphs 10 arid 11 of the Annex to W.P. (44) 71.(i) Pension Rights.The Minister of Pensions urged that any public announcementshould clearly explain the pension rights of the men released ineach class, and it was agreed that this would be necessary.The Prime Minister said that, while he felt sure that the WarCabinet would approve the general lines of the scheme, the variouspoints raised could properly be referred for examination by anInter-Departmental Committee. Detailed proposals should beworked out in the next few months and &quot;full preparations made soas to enable a complete scheme to be presented to Parliament and tothe Forces at the appropriate moment. He thought, however, thatit would be premature to reach a decision at this stage oh theproposals (set out in paragraph 3 of the Annex to W.P. (44) 71) forpresenting the scheme to the public.The War Cabinet-) (1) Approved generally the proposals for reallocation of man-power set out in paragraphs 4 to 12 of the Annex toW.P. (44) 71, subject to (a) above.(2) Agreed that the Committee, under the Joint ParliamentarySecretary to the Minister of Labour, referred to inparagraph 13 of the Annex, should be set up forthwith,and that, in addition to discharging the functions setout in paragraph 13, the Committee should examineoutstanding points, including a number of those raisedin discussion.j(3) Agreed that the Departments concerned, acting in con-sultation through the Committee referred to in (2),should forthwith prepare a detailed scheme on the basisoutlined in W.P. (44) 71.(4) Deferred a decision on the date and method of presentingthe scheme to the public.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,17th February, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
