<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/106/0 images: 49-50</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property of.m mjiimmiTfflffli ****______mhhi.. iwh mm........&apos; .......... &quot;&apos;......m i&apos;m-Hihiwwj-iim^iHis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. QABIHBg. nncTjLUritl.With reference to CP. 1315 (Memorandum by the Minister of labour on the Training of Fit Ex-Service Men) the attached copy of an official letter of June 1st. from the Ministry of Labour to the Treasury gives an estimate of the cost of the proposals contained in the Memorandum. .6.20.
T.D.S. 582/24Finance,1st June, 1920.air,I am directed by the Minister of Labour to state for the information of the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty1a Treasury that, whilst it is very difficult to put forward any but very speculative figures of the number of men likely to require training if the minister  Proposals respecting fit men are approved, it is, nevertheless, considered reasonable . at this stage to assume that the number may be something like 40,000.Bo far as possible it is the Minister1s view that the training of fit men should be given in employers&apos; works and that the period during which the trainees should be in receiptof full maintenance allowance should not exceed an average period of nine months.In addition to the maintenance allowances, expenditure would, of course, be incurred in connection with fees and administration expenses.  Whilst it is exceedingly difficult at this stage to give figures which are really valuable the Minister feels that the following represents a reasonable approximation of the cost which might be expected to be in-curred based on the assumption that the number of men requiring training did not exceed 40,000 -(a) Maintenance Allowance of say  3.5s perShould, it become necessary to train any of the men in Government Inatmc Li anal Factories the cost would, of course, be increased correspondingly.   Dr. Macnamara does not anticipate that there will be any considerable number of such cases.week for nine months 4,800,000(b) Fees, Administration etc 1,200,000 6,000,000The Secretary,His Majesty18 Treasury,LONDON. S0W. 1.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant, E.G,MA?JjOW,

</content>
</cab>
