<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/106/0 images: 284-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this Document (&apos;3 tne Property of His Britannia (Vfejes*y&apos;o Governmegi. Iwr&apos; n^HutA-a-fr&apos;* SE0R1T.   For the information of Members of the Board.IB^Y^lffiOUTIOH 0? MATTERS OF NAVAL HITEKBST.For the week ended 22nd May, 1920cNo.75.G.P. 1 360BALE Id&apos;.S.s; &quot;0LGA*,The French Government have now requested that the dangerous ammunition be dumped in such quantity ae will enable the s.s. &quot;OLGA&quot; to proceed in safety to Brest.    Mean-while dumping of the dangerous part of the cargo has been proceeding since 27th April and about 120 tons have already been so dumped to the Westward of May Island,    A French Destroyer will be sent as escort when the ship is ready to pail.&quot;ICITOBOI&quot;.&quot;&quot;CChe question of returning this despatch vessel to the Russians is still under consideration.General,- It is proposed that H.M, Ships &quot;HOOD&quot; and &quot;TIGRR&quot;with half flotilla ot destroyers will cruise jji the Baltic during June, visiting Kiogo Bay and Scandinavian Ports.   They are due to leave England about the end of May.   Rear-Admiral Sir Wo Cowan, KGB. will continue to act as/;S.N.O. Baltic, during the time that these ships are present in the Baltio5 and. ...     requests that fuel requirements /or this force will be dealt with separately from those of the/Baltic Force. Mr Young, formerly in Constantinople,Replaces Mr Gade as American Commissioner for the Baltic States.   S.S. &quot;DANIA&quot; is due at Chatham on 28th May with pettish troops from Viadi-vladivostock.     Gtters will be fitfced before the ship proceeds to the Baltic, and a guard will&apos; be placed on board to prevent the Letts leaving the ship while in port.esthonia. :;At a meeting held,at the Foreign Office on 19th May, the question was raised whether Esthonia should be invited to signify her adherence to the Arms [Traffic Convention. &quot;Do facto&quot; recognition of independence was considered suffi-cient to justify an invitation*being put forward.Latvia. Difficulties at the beginning of the week.wereexfeTTenced with regard to the peace negotiations at MoscoWj due largely, it is stated, to German influence.    Latvia has since declared that she will proceed seriously to make peace with Germany, and it is now reported that outstanding frontier points have been settled.    Military questions are being con-sidered and economic questions will be considered latesi.   The Lettish   Government state that the Bolsheviks are disposing of machinery evacuated from Riga in ways designed to make its return impossible.     France has recognised both Latvia and Lithuania fde facto-&apos; and hinted at 5De jure&apos; recognition.   The Lettish Minister for Foreign Affairs requests that if &apos;Be jure&apos; recognition is contemplated by the Allies, Great Britain should be the first to announce it.     Colonel Taileats strongly supports this request.Lithuania,The Chairman and some delegates of the Lithuanian peace Delegation have received instructions to return to Kovno to report.     Negotiations are at a standstill owing to boundary differences.     The Bolsheviks urge a
t iLithuanian offenaiveagainst Poland, but Lithuania replied that until,peace was signed and ratified, this proposal could not be considered, as circumstances might arise in which Lithuania would assist Poland,Rep atriat ion of British Nationals.The S.S. &quot;DONGOLA11 arrived at Southampton on 21st May with the last batch of British nationals from Russia^ including the Reverend       North CuB.Ee, British, Chaplain at Moscow. Thirteen British are still in prison, according to Bolshevik reports fcrr criminal offences against Soviet State.     Mr * North states that the charges are absurd.0Kara Sea Relief ExpeditionNorway has raised the question of insurance for the rSVIAT0G0R&quot; and has been informed that this is a question between Norway and the Soviet Government; the latter having guaranteed&apos; all expenses connected with the expedition.    Negotiations are now proceeding.     Meanwhile Christiania reports that on 10th May a telegram was received at Murmansk from the &quot;SOLOvUI BUDIMIROVl!i&apos;CHtt, stating that all w&amp;a well on board and that the weather was warm.Evacuation of tflensburg,The date of evacuation is still under consideration, the latest information stating that the/date will be about the middle&apos;of June, probableenty&apos;s Birthday.S.NcO. Baltic, has been informed that His Majesty1s Birthday is to be celebrated an June 3rd, ships being dressed overall and salutes fired,     If considered inadvisable in particular cases to carry out this order ships are to be dressed with masthead flags,Trade,&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;Preliminary negotiations with the Soviet Trade represent-atives in Ijondon have now commenced.   They have demanded:1.   The right to enter and leave England freely,2.   The right of postal, telegraphic and wireless communi-cation, if necessary in cypher, with Moscow, Copenhagen and with,other representatives in other places.3.   The right to send couriers to and from Russia,Copenhagen and wherever else their representatives      -may be,4.   The right to send their despatch bags under seal.The Russian Trade Committee.propose to approve all the above requests,     Krassin has been informed that if he comes to England he will be granted an interview with the Prime Minister, and an assurance regarding the discussion of general questions as to removing obstacles to trade.     Sir M. Pindlay, Christiania aske for Confirmation of the Press statement that Litvinov is proceeding to Norway, and states that the visit appears to coincide with a reported impending Labour crisis in Norway.Rus si an Znteina! conditions.The Finnish General Staff reports that a Russian Officer who crossed the frontier on 15th May, states that the Soviet of People:s Commissaries has been replaced by a Directorate corn-posed of Lenin, Trotsky and Bark (late Financial Minister under
Csar Regime), Finland.Eh 3 political situation is not yet really settled. It was expected that on the reassembling of the Diet on 24th May the Socialists would make a strong effort to overthrow the pro sent Government, but any attempt was likely to be frustrated owing to the Government1s&apos; decision to accept Cbibherin*s proposals to re-open peace negotiations     Mo Holsti, whowould play a loading part in any &quot;Left&quot; Government, prefers the present Government to remain in power until peace is concluded, as they will move slowly and with caution.    M.Holsti confirmed the conversation at Stockholm referred to in last week?s Appreciation, and states that Swede$promised their support in the Karelia and pechenga questions if the Finns accepted the Swedish proposals for the Aaland Islands settlement0     It is now understood that the Finns have addressed a formal refusal to the Swedish Minister at Helsingfcrs.     The Finnish prime Minister requests that the Allies should declare their die-&apos; interestodness in the Aaland/question,     The Finnish Govern-&apos; raent have addressed a sharp protest to Oblcherin regarding Bolshevik occupation of Eastern Karelia and demand restoration of the military status quo,     The Esthcnian Delegation are at Helsingfore to ask Finalnd to recognise Esthonia &quot;dejure&quot;. - &quot;. &apos;. Finland asks for advice from tho Allies.PoJ.and*The Poles are reported as consolidating their positions on the Dnieper around Kioff.     North of the Pinsk Marshes the Russians have started an offensive which has so far met with success,     The Poles, however, hope to recover the lost ground in the north within a short period sand then to initiate peace negotiations.Denmark.The Danish Government are negotiating for the purchase of HoMcS, &quot;OAEUATION11.   AConstruotcr is being sent to inspect the ship at Devonport.Sweden,* Or 1UMM1UMThe Press reports that the Swedish S0M. &quot;LAXM-&quot; sank at Karlekrona on 19 th May alongside ,the quay;   no one was on beard at the time and the cause of the accident is unknown.(KOTS:   The SSM. hLAXElT&quot; is not mentioned in CBnl543^l).)BLACK SJjA AKD CASPIAN.The Ukraine is asking whether R\.M* Government would con-side r the possibility of &quot;de facto3 recognition now that Petlurafs Government is established on Ukrainian soil.Crimea.&quot; &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; The military situation is satisfactory, and the internal situation improving steadily.A &quot;Red&quot; aerodrome has been located at Temriuk.   The Bolsheviks claim to have engaged Volunteer craft 10 versto West of Berdiansk and to have forced them to withdraw.General Milne has just visited the Crimea.   He states that General Wrangel has brought about en extraordinary change in his array.    Morale is now high, and administration (Supply, Army and Civil), is being properly handled.     Three good lines of defence have been prepared, and the Crimea should be very strong in another fortnight.   The general opinion there seems
&quot;Hi&quot;to &quot;be that Bolshevism is breaking up internally owing to local risings against its power.     General Milne states that Wrangel!s Army, no longer called the Volunteer Army* seems to merit our support. -&quot;; &apos;Bat urn,Fighting has ceased, near Kobuletti, between the Georgians and Adjarians.   The former have withdrawn across the Cholckh   river.   British troops follorad their withdrawal.The Georgiansc who had adopted an uhcompromising attitude, threatening  severance of relations with the British over the Batum province question, are now anxious to re-open railway communication with Batum.     Ihe G,OtfC, before giving per-mission, is awaiting a promise of better behaviour, their recent action having shown a tendency distinctly hostile towards the wishes of the Entente.Ihe Adjarians are -willing to recognise any mandate for Batum except Georgian, and may turn to Turks for assistance.A battalion of French Algerian Tirailleurs left Constan-tinople for Batum on the 17th May.The despatch of an Italian battalion to Batum has been suspended.     The British Ambassador at Rome has been instructed to inform the Italian Government that HeHo Government are at a loss to explain this change of attitude, and that it is confidently hoped that the battalion will be despatched forth&quot; with in accordance with S. Nittfo definite undertaking,Italian Jo roes at Cons tant incplo.The Italian Government has agreed to the Italian forces at Constantinople being placed under General Milne-s orders until the signature of the Turkish peace Treaty on the 4th June, but request that a distinct zone on the Asiatic side may be allocated to them.Armistice Negotiations,Lord Curzon on 17th May, in reply to Chicheiyin-s telegram of 7th May, expresses satisfaction that the Soviet Government agree to opening of negotiations on a basis of general amnesty. Endeavours are being made for immediate commencement. Consequently High Commissioner, Constantinople, has been informed and asked to suggest a place fos? the negotiations and to inform General Wrangel that he must nou expect any change in our policy as the result of the polish offensive,A British Military representative and a Political officer will assist,   Mr picton Bagge has been selected as the political Officer and is expected to leave England during the next few days.     High Commissioner reports that the special, delegation from General Wrangel, headed by M. Struve, has arrived at Constantinople, but Lord Curzon considers that there is no need for this delegation to come to London,     Chicherin, en 21st May, answering Lord Curzon*s telegram of 17th; stated that the Russian Government would- consider in most friendly spirit any proposals put forward by the British representatives during the impending armistice negotiations.Azerbaijan. , The new Azerbaijan Government have-approached the Dutoil Consul, at Baku to enter into commercial relations with Holland.     The Dutch Government has been requested to take any action possible for the release of British nationals at Baku, It is reported that differences have occurred between Russian Soviet troops and Azerbaijans and that the former are disarming the Tartars, causing considerable ill-feeling.The Admiralty have addressed a Memorandum to the Foreign
Office pointing out the extreme urgency of talcing definite steps to secure the release of British nationals and Naval Mission at Baku.Georgia,Reports are still &quot;being received that peace has been concluded between Soviet Russia and Georgia- and actions of Georgians in Batoum Province justifies serious misgivings as to their future intentions,     High Commissioner states that we may find ourselves at any moment in a state of war with them. Foreign Office has wired, for information of General Milne, that a conflict with the Georgians would be highly inadvisable and should if possible be avoided.     Fighting is taking place between the Georgians and Azerbaijans at poili, the latter strongly assisted by Russian Soviet troops-Enzeli,Bolsheviks on 18th May, with numerically superior forces attacked Kaaian and Enzeli,     A motor-boat flying the Persian flag and white flag attempted to parley, but was fired on and forced to return, to port,   Later parley was effected, and, under terms arranged, British withdrew to Resht. Bolsheviks removed the shipping in the port and state that now that they have obtained control of the ex-Volunteer Fleet, they will evacuate Persian territory; this has not yet been carried out,Siberia.*&quot;*&quot; Railway communication between Vladivostock andManchuria was re-opened on 12th May,   The Japanese state that they will not support individual Russians against the will of the people, and this evidently means that Japan will support project cf a &quot;buffer state&quot; east of Lake Baikal.     Reliable reports state that the Bolsheviks regard the proposal in a favourable light and have ordered that no attempt is to be made to displace the frontiers in Trans-Bakalia.   The Japanese landed on 15th May an advance guard of 2 infantry companies at Castries Bay, 125 miles south of Nicosk.   A Bolshevik force, wearing Japanese uniforms believed to belong to Japanese soldiers wounded at Nicosk on 12th March, was easily repulsed. The Czech evacuation is continuing.    part will be evacuated via Canada and thence in Atlantic steamers.yUHKSY.General Appreciation.The provinces have ceased to regard the authority of the Central Government and all telegraphic communication between them and Constantinople is cut.The regular troops in the interior are all, so far as is known, committed to the National movement.     The Nationalist leaders control the situation %n Anatolia and probably inTb t r*i*sThffi Government can rely on no regular troops anywhere out-side Constantinople.   The anti-Nationali3t movement in the region between panderma and Balikesser^ under the leadership cf Anzavur, has collapsed, and the Nationalists have assembled such forces against him as to make it doubtful if any recovery is possible,   \This set-back deprives the Government of any hope of securing Bruasa, or the Anatolian Bailway beyond Ismid, and diminishes the probability of their being able to utilise the germs of other anti**Nationali3t movements in the Yalova and Ismid districts.The possibility of fostering cnti-Nationalist movements in the more remote districts, e,g. Konia, on the north coast of Asia Minor and on the Kurdish frontier, is very remote,
The 12th. and 9th Turkish divisions from Erzerum have concentrated at Olti and Sarikamish.   The 11th Division from Van has concentrated at Bcyasid and pushed forward to lakichevan via Bayazid and Baku.     Turkish troops are guarding the Persian Azerbaijan frontier.Soviet Russia is in pursuit of *** (a)&apos; An improvement of ins internal situation and, as thisturns on transport, (bj   Oil.(c)   The creation of difficulties for Great Britain through the medium of the Mohammedans, Territorial expansion is probably not an object,, but the expansion of Soviet theories is.In connection with (a) mu3t be remembered Defective morale of Soviet armies. Difficulties of communication and supply. Strain of the polish offensive. All of which are arguments against a big military effort.As regards (c); the obvious policy is to prevent Allied promises of assistance to Armenia from -materialising, and this can be most easily achieved by inducing the Turks to attack.The Armenian Army is at present 25,000 strong, with 15r000 rifles, and can mobilise up to 40,000.     The personnel is neither good or well organised, Hostile forces are, roughly:On the North and East:   Bolshevist 38,000Aze r&apos;b ai j an 22^ 00000,000On the West: Bolshevist 30,000Tu rk s, re gulars        5,000 !!   irregulars      XSJL0009T7000On the South: Turks, regulars       3 .,500&quot;   irregulars        ^jOOO106,500Bolshevist troops are probably being withdrawn to meet the Polish offensive.Courses open to Soviet Russias-(a) Direct attack on Armenia.    Calls for most troops, but is the best way to back up the Nationalists and to threaten.Great Britain in Persia and Mesopotamia,(b) Encourage the Nationalists to attack Armenia.   Sameobject as (a).    Calls for fewer troops but is less certain,   weuld enable Lenin to keep up his fiction of not being at war with us.(c) Rely on internal  causes bringing Armenia into the Sovietorbit,The internal condition of Soviet Russia is such that it is difficult to believe an active offensive in the Caucasus will be attempted.   Aggressive action by Turkey, with Soviet support and encouragement is more indicated.Resistance on the part of Armenia becomes almost hopeless if Soviet Russia, or its Allies, gain control of Datum, Batum is essential to Armenian independence.Lenin is probably relying on internal, rather than external pressure to accomplish his ends.In advancing to occupy the 3 Trans-frontier Sanjaks the Turks are evidently actuated by:-
(1)   Land hunger:(2)   Pears of a3olshorU8t-Getirsian--agi^ement, following onnews of a treaty between these Governments. (3)   Endeavour to forestall the creation of an independent Armenian State by taking action befjofte Armenia can mobilise or be given munitions. They are enlisting town and tribal aid by distributions of arms, thus forming a local militia to watch Armenian prepara-tions.Religious enmity is being played upon and is fanned by the natural reluctance of the Kurdish tribes to disgorge former Christian property.At the back of Mustapha Kemal&apos;s mind is, no doubt, the possibility of a combination with the Azerbaijan Tartars and even with the Bolshevists, working through Enver, Nuri and iChalil, though this latter contingency is doubtful.MED ITSRRANJBAN.. A French report dated May 10th reveals a very serious state&apos;of affairs&quot; in Syria,     At that date the town of Alexandretta was practically cut off; the French garrison at Antioch was unable to leave the town; at Tripoli the situation was critical: brigands were menacing the whole region of Tyre and Sidon ana Christians there had been murdered.Lord Allenby after a conversation with the French Liaison Officer on May 21st confirms the critical nature of the situation.     He states that the French are seriously contemplate-ting the evacuation of Cilicia and Syria.Reinforcements, i&amp;cluding mountain batteries and field artillery are being sent from Constantinople to Cilicia.Northern Syria and Cilicia.On May 10th it was reported that railway communication was cut between Adana and Mersina.     Also that the effort by Turkish Nationalists to surround Adana, Tarsus and Mersina had commenced.Aintab.-   On May 2nd after violent artillery and machine gun&apos; preparation the Turks captured the French advance posts.     The Turks attacked the Armenian town the next day employing flame throwers and incendiary shells.     Later the garrison was attacked by a force of 5,000 Turks with 6 guns.   Fighting continued, from 60 to 70 French wounded were being evacuated daily by train from Aleppo to Beirut.About May 9th a French relieving force of 3,500 men en route for Aintab met with strong resistance 8 or 10 miles from Aintab and were believed to be returning toPKillis strongly pressed by their opponents.     It is said that the Nationalists were helped by having guns of longer range than the French. The situation both at Killis and Aintab is extremely critical. A French detachment has started for the relief of Bazanti, where the garrison has long been besieged.     The French post at Karab, on the railway east of Arapunar, was captured on April 25th.     The survivors are prisoners at Urfa.Fiume.There has been a defection of certain of D^nnunzio^ troops at Fiume.     Considerable numbers of carabinieri and men of two or three line regiments insisted on returning tat Italian territory.     After negotiations, D^nnunzio consented, but on their actual departure a scuffle occurred between them and the Arditi.     A bomb was thrown by the latter at the commanding officer of the departing troops, but missed him, killing   a civilian standing in. the crowd.
I T A I: yeVice-Admiral V0Gagni has been appointed C-in-C of the newly constituted Maditerranean Fleet.It is reported that Italy h.a3 concluded an agreement with Soviet Russia providing for the exchange of prisoners of WasThe nCorriere della Serafi of 13th May announces that the &quot;Carracciolo&quot; has been launched at Ca3t&amp;llamare without incident, and Has subsequently towed to Spesia.This ship is one of 4 super-Dreadnoughtn laid down in 19140 Construction of 3 has been abandoned and the &quot;Carracciolo&quot; will be completed as a merchant ship.     She will be fitted out so that she can be used as an armed transport if necessary and will retain her under water anti*-torpedo protection.     Her speed will be about 12/14 knots.The Royal Decree providing for the scrapping of battleships light cruisers, scouts and destroyers laid down in 1903, or before, affects some 150,000 tons and so may be expected to affect materially the Italian market in regard to obsolete British ships for disposal.GlffiCE.The Treasury has sanctioned the gift of a further 25 aeroplanes to Greece, bringing the total presented to 50.Vice-Admiral W.A.H0Kelly, RoHoH., arrived at Smyrna on 20th April for a stay of several days.     One of the objects of his visit was to persuade General Paraskevcpoulos to do away with one division of troops and to accept Naval aircraft in lieu, thus enabling the money saved to be expended on the Navy. General Paraskevopaulos subsequently left for Athens, presumably in tMs same connectionsinformation received from Asia Minor shows that the Italians are becoming more and more anti-British and anti-Greek in their sentiments and actions.     The Turks in Sckia have been told that all Allied troops have been ordered to quit Turkey by order of the peace Conference.    Meantime the attitude cf the Italian Military authorities towards the British Liaison Officer is beconing covertly offensive though outwardly of the friendliest description0Italy has recognised our protectorate over Igypt in a Note which commences^   &quot;As HeB*M&apos;s Government id giving the Egyptian nation an ever wider share in the government cf their own country15 - As the words make the recognition dependent upon our internal policy in Egypt the Note is considered unsatis-factory and representations are being made to Rome accordinglyftMEXICO.HoM6S, ^CAJJBEIAN55 returned to Vera Cruz from Puerto Mexico on the JrtOthMay.HcM.3. S-CALLJQP18 remains at Kingston^ Jamaica,MISCELLANEOUS HOMES CTl^I,T;IGMai. -Dockerg^ 3trikeTees,jdc.   Dockers on tho  ees have decided to resume work, and to leave the points in dispute to the negotiating Committee for adjustment.
4W  -i.   xm QEvil.   The Trawler ^fETP^OH&apos;5 reports having seen the tracer r/f/7iLARIA&quot; blow up Girdle -fishing at 0830 on the 15th May in 55*19 Ho, 4,20. E.   She vessel sank immediately with all hands.Qrlms^y, Bage*   preparations are &quot;being made for closing the H&amp;Til Base .at G-rimsby at an early date.     The disposal of the Humber Loom Defence Vessels is under consideration,^ainiM        2JP^H3! ^^C^be ..^?.?1^ Owing to theatTItude &quot;adopted &quot;lay Wo&quot; Itbme&quot;&apos; Of Fib e&quot;,7&quot;lt&apos;&apos; Has been decided to close down this Industrial Training Ship, which has a record of 44 years work and has trained some thousands of boys for the ITavy and Mercantile Marine.     This Ship was originally the frigate &quot;WINCHESTER&apos;5 and was for come time Flagship on the China Station ana at the Cape.Accident^in^H      . Jl&amp;GB HpY,lt      During a steam trial off the rsieToT^fgK^&quot;eir&apos;^e^ror&quot;:Cn&quot;sFant, a &quot;back flash&quot; causing a fire with explosions in the foremost boiler compartment, occurred Five stokers were severely injured, and Commissioned Engineer Harry Smith and Chief Engine Room Artificer Alfred Eraser are specially mentioned for gallant conduct in rescuing these men, whose lives were in great danger.H.M,S-   CKATHM&quot;.    Qn completion of her rofit, abou-c the end of &quot;June, wlTl be transferred to the New Zealand Navy.Sinn FeJjv^Ealds on^QQasi^ard Stations; eto.,     The Coastguard StlHHTand Boal^ox ^$radiP^t^t^Ball^cr3neen, Co, Cork, were raided on the 12th May.   Some equipment was stolen from the former, and the latter was dismantled.     The CoG. Station at Ballinayall, Smerwick Bay, was attacked by 20 to SO well drilled; atomed and masked Sinn joiners on the night of 13th to 14th May,   The attack was repulsed by pistol fire.The Admiralty huts at  ingaskiddy recreation grounds (Queenstown) wore set on fire at. 0330, 23rd May.   One hut completely burnt, canteen and pavilion, partly burned,Brandon Coastguard Station was also raided and burnt d\iring the night of the 23rd May.B*J2J eya?Q2B^2I^g b e &apos;     rj-1lie triennial conference of the Dock, itfHarFJ Riverside and General Workers1 Union was held at Plymouth during the past week,     Motions protesting against the export of arms to polacid, and in favour of &quot;self determination for Ireland&apos;&apos; and &quot;hands off Russia&quot; wore carried unanimouslyo     The membership of the Union is nearly 6,500,000.The federation of Engineering and Shipbuilding ffrades ,als^..held SEelr conferen ce at &quot;Plymouth on the &quot;^Otfi*ltna&quot;&quot;tflsti. May.   It is . understood that the question of temporary suspension of demarcation rules to enable merchant shipbuilding in the Bock-yard to be economically carried out, was discussed, and that the -general feeling was not unfavourable,     The meeting wae.pr*v*,tovgeneral Situation in Ireland.     Outrages of every description continue to&quot;&quot;Be carried out with impunity.     The attitude cf the civil population towards the Military continues to be almost tolerant.     Towards the RrIeC0 it is, if possible, more hostile,,ADMIRALTY, S.^/.27th May 1920. 1Ifflllllllfllillll^^...............................................mm......i.i.......i ___,________....

</content>
</cab>
