<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/106/0 images: 322-322</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-%ilf      Secret, 138-1\ 1 273      JMibm Viceroy, Army Department, to Secretary of State for India,____27tk May 1920.WaU(Received 28th.) --^716.  No. 193.Part I. (1) Afridi. Nadir Khan has invited Ghulam llaidar of Chora to be chief Malik of Afridi jirga ; he intends summoning to Jalalabad, lie also suggested Amir might re-build Chora fort in return for proprietary rights.(2) Waziristan. Haji Abdur Razak apparently discredited by Mahsuds. On his arrival in their country Mahsuds refused him permission to remain, refused to sell him grain and looted some of his kit. Small ration convoys continue to arrive at Wana from Afghanistan. Ali Abbas, head of Red Crescent Mission, has returned to Kabul.(3) Amir has issued official instructions regarding Indians emigrating to Afghanistan on account of Khilafat question. They are to have equal rights with Afghans, and those accepting Afghan nationality will receive various concessions of laud and revenue.(4) Recruiting of now battalions continue in Kabul, about 3,000 recruits having been enlisted. Present output of Kabul arsenal reported as less than half maximum output.(5) Representative of Amir of Bokhara reported arrived Kabul 9th May. (6) Kandahar.   Afghan officials still preparing people for possibility of Jehad. Defensive preparations in progress round Spin Baldak.   Khairo Jan summoned to Kandahar from Baldak by Governor.(7) Several reports received that Afghan camel owners in Siestan and Persia have1 been ordered to return with camels to Afghanistan.(8) Afghan representatives from Herat have left for Kushk to discuss Jamshedi question with Russian official from Tashkend. Excitement in Herat subsiding owing to news of departure of delegates to India.Part II. (9) Convoy moving between Harnai and Loralai on 25th fired on by marauders.   Our casualties one killed, one wounded. Paras. (2) and (9) only to be given to Press,

</content>
</cab>
