<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/106/0 images: 343-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. v       o .:.THE CABINET.&apos;f 380  &apos; %J       4 &apos;-;        THE SITUATION IN TURKEY.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.I circulate herewith for the informatioD of my colleagues a telegram from the General Officer Commanding, Constantinople, to the War Office, on the present situation in Turkey.W. S. C.The War Office,Ut June, 1920.From General Officer Commanding, Constantinople, to War Office.Handed in 29th May, 1920, 1420. (No. G.C. 723, cipher.) (Received 30th, 0900.)28th. Your No. 84974,* M.O. 1, 28th May. I did not see High Commissioner, No. 624, 25th May, until he had sent it, nor was I consulted. In order to counteract any false impression I then sent you my telegram No. I. 8676, 25th May, which explains the situation east of Ismid, where, owing to incapacity, the Government forces have been unable to make any headway against the Nationalists who represent the (?) intensity and energy of the Turkish nation.Civil war now exists in Turkey in Asia. Whether Government signs Peace Treaty or not is immaterial; they are powerless to enforce it.They hold sway in the area between Ismid and Chataldja, thanks only to allied battalions, but outside of this area they are powerless.We are thus getting involved in their civil war.I do not consider that any advance in force will be made against us, but guerilla warfare will in all likelihood be commenced in the Ismid Peninsula in order to compel us to retire on Constantinople.To protect (?) neighbourhood adequately I must hold the line Ismid Shile. I intend to resist any aggression in the Ismid Peninsula. In order to enable me to do this and to guard the Dardanelles, I hope that it will be possible now to send me a cavalry regiment.No other policy is possible, for if the Nationalists are allowed to approach any nearer there will be trouble in Constantinople. From the Italians and French I can expect no assistance ; the former are frankly favourable (?) to the Nationalists and the latter are bent on discrediting British policy.&apos; It should be noted that while British officers are prisoners of war in Anatolia, there is a French Mission at Broussa.To employ Greek troops at Ismid would be to put a match to the fire.Anti-British propaganda is being actively carried on by our Allies who are endeavouring to make us solely responsible for the present situation.With the help of the Batoum General Headquarters and a cavalry regiment to assist in the defence of Ismid and the Dardanelles I shall be quite happy, but I look upon the Italians who are to arrive shortly as a weakness and not as a strength.As yet Nationalists are more of an armed mob than an Army, but once they are in touch with Bolshevist forces in the Caucasus a change may take place.At the same time it is my duty to warn you that the published details of the Peace Treaty have consolidated public opinion in Turkey, and that full measures will be taken by the inhabitants to resist Greek aggression and to prevent the present Ministry, who are regarded as traitors, from securing their position by force of arms.* Telegram No. 84974, 28th May, reads as follows: &quot; Reference High Commissioners No. 624, of 2oth May, to Foreign Office regarding military situation in Anatolia, please telegraph your views and any comments you may wish to make with regard to above telegram.&quot;(B20/261!)   ldU   6/20  H&amp;S   827HWJ

</content>
</cab>
