<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/106/0 images: 391-396</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property of ^uoSSCKET,    For the information of Members of the Board.iY APPRECIATION CP MA.OTR8 OP NAVAL INTEREST.   No. 7(5,^ A   For the vrcek ended 29th May 1020.CM 3 8 5-   )JItl^ALL^^^ BALTIC,H.M. Ships &quot;Hood&quot; and 5*Tiger&quot; sailed on 29th May for a cruise in Scandinavian water3,Plenaburg.   A Prench detachment from Flensburg proceeded to Copen-Hagen ori 26th May&quot; to be entertained by the Danish Government.     At the request of the French Civil and Military authorities, the British Vice-Admiral visited Copenhagen in H.M.S. &quot;Carysfort&quot; in order to be present at the review held on tho 29th,Information has now been received that the date for withdrawal of the Allied Porce from Plensburg has been fixed for 15th June. but that it is not intended that this date should be made public as yet.     The British Porce will pay a two-day visit to Copenhagen before returning to li^/land,3.S. &quot;QI.GA&quot;.    It is expected that the s.s. &quot;Olga&quot; will be ready &quot;for sei aSout 10th June.     The French Government have ty&amp;en requested to send the destroyer detailed for escort to Risyth. to arrive not later than 7th June, so that ample time will be avail-able for re-fuelling, etc,&quot;Kitoboi&quot;.     The Admiralty., after considering 1, Sablin&apos;3 - yreply, &quot;have replied that the loan deed executed between Rear-Admiral Sir Walter Cowan, K.C.B., and Captain Knupffer, Russian Navy, attached to General Yudenitah&apos;s Berth West Army, is considered to be a perfectly legal document and above question, yet, in order to deal sympathetically with the request that the vessel be allowed to remain in Russian hands, the Admiralty have agreed to turn the vessel over to tho Russian authorities now in possession, provided that no further claim is made on H.M* Government.     Failing this, immediate acquiescence to British demands must be given.Latvia.   w/T reports that in view of negotiations concluded be-tweefci Lettish and German representatives, Germany is ready to assist Latvia in the reconstruction of her railway system by handing over railway material.     The resumption of diplomatic relations between the&quot; two countries is impending.     The s.s. &quot;Dania&quot; is now expected at Chatham on 1st June with 500 Lettish troops, 121 Lettish women and children, and 40 British refugees f rom VI adiv o s to ck *Lithuania.     It was reported on 2ord May that, although part of uhe&apos; lIthii ani an delegation are returning to Kovno , the Bolsheviks are showing a more conciliatory spirit with regard to Lithuanian territorial demands.     Colonel Tallents ha3 been asked to report whether there is any possibility of Lithuania joining the Bolsheviks against Poland,Denmark.     The Danish Naval Attache proceeded to Devonport on ^6ph May to inspect H.M.S. &quot;Carnation11.   Mr Grant Watson on the 29th reported that the Danish Ministry of Marine had informed him that Denmark is purchasing a sloop, name unknown, instead of IMS &quot;Carnation&quot;.     Commander H.R,H. prince Axel of Denmark will arrive at Harwich on 2nd June, accompanied by six others, to take over the ship.Pintend.     Germany by W/T denies the delivery of German arms to Pinjaland,     Chicherin, replying to the Finnish protest concerning
2-Eastern Karelia, denies that the status quo has been changed and hopes that the Finnish Government will disregard the dangerous rsmours spread by ill-wishers with the object of preventing the conclusion of peace.     The Finnish Government has wired to Moscow proposing that negotiations for peace be opened at Dorpat on 10th June.     Foreign Office wired to H.M. Minister at Stockholm advising the Swedish Government to refer the Aaland Islands question to the League of Nations, and asks whether this advice would be acceptable at the present moment.Red Fleet.     The Minister of Foreign Affairs, Finland, informed Mr Kidston, 29th May, that a telegram had been received a week ago from the Soviet Government announcing their intention of sending out warships from Kronstadt for hydrographical and pilot-age purposes and giving particulars of flags they would fly.   It is reported that Naval Headquarters at Kronstadt demanded from the Supreme Soviet for Defence that Kronstadt should be prepared for defence and specialists supplied for laying mines in the Gulf of Finland.     The demand was refused for the following reastas;-1.     The laying of mines in the Gulf of - -    - Finland would -contradict peace policy of the Bolsheviks.2,     They are unable to supply specialists, and also vessels for this work are in a very bad condition.3.     This project would entail large expenses and no monoy is available.The Bolsheviks arc reported to be reconstructing defences against Finland, probably due to the Polish offensive and lack of knowledge as to agreement existing between Poland and Finland.Trade.   M.Krassin arrived at Newcastle on 27th May.   H.M. Government have conceded to the Russian delegation the right of communicating in cypher and immunity of persons and baggage; that of sending bags under seal is under consideration.    A Cabinet meeting was held on Friday, 28th May, to decide on the guarantees and concessions necessary from the Bolsheviks before negotiations could commence, the release of British nationals and especially the Naval Mission at Baku being ;one of the most important.     America has decided not to permit expert, of goods from United States of America3 either directly orthroiigh the intermediary of European Countries, when the final destination is Soviet Russia,Kara Sea Relief Expedition,     Chicherin has wired the Minister ofForeTgn Affairs of Norway that Gukovsky, Soviet Representa-tive at Reval, has been instructed to consult with the Central-banken of Norway for the transfer of two million crowns as a credit for the insurance of the Icebreaker &quot;Sviatogor&quot;.Norway lias wired to Moscow stating that if any change at Petchonga in favour of Finland was being considered by Soviet Russia, Norwegian claims 3hbuld also be considered.     She had always been on friendly terms with Russia, but would not relish Finland obtaining control of this district.    Finland has addressed a Note to Norway pointing out that the realisation of Finnish aspirations in Petchenga would not exclude friendly discussions leading to an agreement between Finland and Norway. Norway has protested against the annoyance being caused at Murmansk to the Norwegian Consul, M. Finstad, and the nationalisation of Norwegian property.     The Press states that M. Finstad attempted to evade customs dues by smuggling goods into Murmansk and, on account of this, the Soviet attitude would be explained,     Norway is apprehensive of extensive Finnish migration into district South of Varanger Fjord and especially the town of Kirkenes.     The Norwegian population is being gradually replaced by a Finnish colony and Press agitates,
in view of the annexations].ist policy of the Finns in this district and of the incompatibility of the Norwegian and Finnish population, that immediate steps should bo*taken for the removal of so serious a menace.Poland,   From reports received it would appear that the poles have checked the Bolshevik advance.     It is stated that the poles when they have re-established the military situation on the North ern frontj which they expect to do in about a week, will intimate their readiness to resume peace discussions,     The original terms, will probably be modified.     The poles state that more method is apparent&quot; in the direction of Bolshevik attack., which tends to confirm reports that Brussilov is directing operations,BLACK SBA AND ppiTSPJVa^AN.Crimea,   Bolshevik aeroplanes carried out bombing attacks near KertcH&apos; on the 13th May,   An attack on the Chongar Front was repulsed on the 24th May. - ^    -It was reported on the 26th May that Bolshevik air raids were continuing daily.H.M. Ships &quot;Concord&quot; and &quot;Seraph&quot; are in the Theodosia area, and &quot;Benbow&quot; and &quot;Sikh&quot; at Sevastopol.Co in c. Mediterranean, has been asked to report whether the British Naval Mission to General frangel should be maintained at its present strength, or whether a reduction can now be made, It has been pointed out that the opportunity may be favourable for recognising this Mission as separate from the British Mi1i t a ry Mission.C* in Co has further been asked to report whether coal and oil from Admiralty sources are still being issued to General Y?rangel&apos;s Force or other authority in the Crimea, and if so, the average quantity per wreck.     Also whether provisions are being issued, or have been issued, during the last four weeks,Caucasus.     The 9th Bed Army, with a strength of 3 battalions with four 6-inch batteries, has been identified in the area Adler-Sochi-Tuapse.     One Georgimbattalion is at Gagri.     Batum is quiet.     Two bombs have been found near the kerosene storage tanks.H.M. Ships &quot;Resolution&quot;,,&quot;Royal Sovereign&quot;, &quot;Caradoc&quot; and &quot;Swallow&quot; are at Batum, and &quot;Marlborough&quot; and &quot;Torch&quot; at Ga&amp;ri.Enzeli.     others  is no further information from Enzoli.    The Military detachment which recently evacuated Enz&amp;li has been ordered to withdraw from Resht to Kasvin.The Russian internees   fr;om the Caspian Volunteer Fleet will, unless orders to the contrary are sent, be evacuated to Mesopotamia.     The Soviet has sent a congratulatory message to the Bolshevik Caspian Fleet on the capture of Enzeli and the ships of the Volunteer Fleet,Baku.      No information has been received concerning the officers indmen detained by the Bolsheviks at Baku, since the .      18th May, when it was reported that all foreigners at Baku nad been released with the exception of the British who wore being made to work in the Docks.Azerbaijan.     Commander Luke reports that Russian Bolsheviks are in soio control of Azerbaijan.   The Tartar population an$ Army are sullen but powerless to assist themselves.     Of troops acting against Georgia   only 300 are not Russian.     Eught thousand tons of oil are being sent daily from Baku to Astrakhan and Krasnovodsk, also silk, wool and cotton, and none of these commodities are being paid for.
GEORGIA.     Commander Luke reports that Gegfcgia still assorts her determination to fight Bolshevism and requests assistance in the form of munitions,     Foreign Office stated that it was hoped to despatch a consignment of arms ofi 29th May, but it was not stated whether for Georgia and Armenia or for Armenia alone0Commander Luke requests whether Georgian Government should bo informed.     About 12,000 - 15,000 Russian Bolshevik troops arc attacking Georgia at Poili despite nominal peace with.-the Soviet.     On 19th May it was reported that a six-day armistice had been arranged;, but that fighting was resumed on 23rd May. It is most essential that a definite promise of support should be forthcoming if Georgia is to continue the straggle.ITALY.The post of Inspector General of the Navy hasbeen abolished and Admiral di Revel is therefore placed on the unemployed list. A full Admiral cannot be retired;   he will therefore remain nominally on the active service list.21122?.*- ,Tho Adriatic negotiations with Jugo-Slavia will not be resumed&apos;until the new Government has received a vote of confidence in the Chamber.Press reports indicate a hardening of public opinion in favour.of abandoning these negotiations and applying the Treaty of London.Batum,     As no Italian battalion.has been sent to Batum and as the French are only sending an Algerian battalion, General Milne has boen asked to report if the position there is unsound, and has been authorised to withdraw forthwith if he considers this necessary.The Italian Government has boen informed that H.Jt. Government are at a loss to explain the failure to fulfil a definite undertaking to send an Italian battalion to Batum and confidently hope that it will bo despatched forthwith.The Italian Government contend that there has been no breach of any undertaking and no change in their attitude, as the arrr-mgement was that Italian troops should not be used to defend BatuEs against Bolshevist attacks but only to maintain order and to prevent the Georgians from taking possession.   They admit; however, that the Bolshevists at Baku do not regard the Italians there as their enemies.TURKEY.A report (considered reliable) announces that the Turks are orJgmising a comitadji movement in Thrace, to commence with the arrival of the Greek troops of occupation.   The Bulgarian Government is giving assistance, individual Bulgarians are joining in and there arc indications of French connivance.The Turkish plan is to burn Adrianople and to px-oduce a state of chaos which will compel the Allies to intervene and Continue the administration of Thrace.The Grand Vizier has informed the High Commissioner that the whole country regards the poace Treaty as excessively severe, especially those clauses which deprive Turkey of Smyrna, Thrace, and the Dardanelles region.     To sign the Treaty as it stands will, he says, place tho Government and&apos; the Sultan in an extraordinarily difficult position.Constantinople Smyrna and Thrace wore reported quiet on the 26th instant.
*M 0N a t ionaliat Movement ,     The Grand Vizier i-s complaining of the difficulties&quot; he encounters in organising a regular force for the repression of the Nationalist movement, and is endeavouring to obtain permission from the Supreme Council to equip and utilise a force of 10,000 men.     He i3 satisfied that he could suppress the movement in throe weeks with such a force, and points out that it is considerably less than tho 50,000 men -which the Peace Tioaty will allow Turkey to maintain.A previous telegram from General Milne stated that the Grand Vizier askw to be allowed io a?qu;Lp up to the number authorised in the peace Treaty, viz, 15,000 regulars and 55, 000 gendarmes,On the 24th May the Nationalists commenced an apparently successful attack on Adabazar and Sabanja and moved eastwards, Adabazar and Arif ie were captured.The Ottoman Government has requested through the Allied High. Commissioners an ex tendon of tirne^ until the 11th July, for consideration of the Treaty,     The High Commissioners consider this request reasonable and recommend it being granted.GKEIEiCE.Cartain George Panas has been appointed Naval Attache in London and has taken up his duties,.SYRIA.General Nouri Said reached Beyrout, on his Return from Europe, on May 22nd and left for Damascus on May 24th.     He is reported to have given out that the independence of Syria is assured.It has been decided not to pay any further instalments of Peisal&apos;8 subsidy at present,   He has been informed that H.M. Government still regard him as their friend, but that tho attitude of what are presumed to be irresponsible Arabs makes the payment of the subsidy at present obviously impossible.A French report dated May 17th states that more than 70 Christians, including womon and * children, have been massacred by sections of the Metwali tribe in the village of Ain Ibl,According to the press General Go^r anal has stated that a normal situation has been re-established,Prom native reports it appears that an action took place at Tibnin, to the North of Ain Ibl,&apos; on May 22nd, in which the Metwali tribe retired.   The French column reached Bint urn Jubinl, close to Ain Ibl, and bombarded and burnt it.     The surrounding villages have been abandoned, and some hundreds erf tho inhabitants have entered the British zone.On May 25th a village in the British zone was bombed by the Prench who afterwards occupied the village.     The attention^ of Prench Headquarters has been drawn to the matter.Northern Syria and, Cilicia.     On May 21st a Prench relief column left Killis for Aintab, where they found the Turks in position with about 20 gun3.   After sharp fighting on May 24th the Prench garrison was relieved.     Tho Turks are reported to havo suffered heavily, their casualties amounting to 1,200, including a considerable number of prisoners.The Prench forces in Syria and Cilicia are now equal to four Divisions.MEXICO.H.M.S. &quot;Cambrian&quot; arrived at Tampico on the 25th May.
jaS01lT,L.Aj.iffiUS HOME INTELLIGENCE.Transfer of pioat-Ing Dock.     No.l Floating Dock sailed from Invefgofaoh&quot; atTSTv/o oh May 27 th in tow of tugs, bound for ports-mouth,     This deck was transferred from Portsmouth to Invergordon during the war.Merchant Shinbiulding in Dockyard.     The ballot of Devonport sHipwrFghts &quot;oh the&quot; Aurniralty proposal to waive certain trade demarcation rules in order to facilitate the economical construe-tion of merchant vessels in the Dockyard, resulted in tho rejoc-tion of the proposal by 1087 votes to 294,     At Portsmouth the ballot was in favour of the proposal.     Local opinion generally condemns the Shipwrights policy as suicidal.Threatened flying of Sinn^Fein Plag at Admiraltyt pierfQueenstown,&quot;&quot;On the 21?tli May xE&quot;e&quot;&quot;CorT harbomr Board&apos; passed a resolution that in future the flag of the Irish Republic should be flown at Admiralty Pier, Queenstown, and all buildings under the control, of the Board,SinnPein dostruotjon o^JP^^L^Q^.^ Stations.     Pour Stations have been attacked and destroyed during the. week *   Two of the Stations iwrsro unoccupied and at tho ethers no resistance was offered and there were no casualtiesA regular campaign against Coastguard Stations appears to have boon started to prevent their eventual occupation&quot;by the Military0     SCO Marines are being sent for their protection,jvov,&apos; Admiral Suporintendont.   Rear-Admiral Clinton Baker, OB. CBE, Hoisted&apos;his* plagf as -Admiral Superintendent of Chatham Dockyard, in succession to Roar-Admiral Sir W,E.Gcodenoughj JCCB, MO, on tho 26th May,Refusal to handle Munitions for Military Forces in &apos;Ireland.     On We ^oK^ay^lE^&apos;^&apos;^&apos;.Rc^consHerod&apos; the position arising-out of the refusal of the Dublin railwayman to handle munitions arriving for the Military Forfc&amp;s in Ireland.     The executive confirmed their previous decision to submit the question to a meeting of tho Triple Alliance which is being arranged forthwith.General Situation in Ireland.   The general situation has certainly not improved during the&quot;past week.   Officers patrols and the property -vision of Military escorts for police patrols have, however, effected an improvement in tho morale of the R.I.C., and in two cases attacks on police barracks have been prevented by the timely arrival cf troops.The holding of SoP- Courts of -Justice, in substitution for the &quot;Kin.gJs Courts1&apos;, and the policing of districts by the I.R.A. are now being carried on openly and reported in tho press.   At Ballinasloe on tho 27th instant, a Sinn Pein Court was held in the Town Hall, presided over by a Barrister on the High Court, and some   3 to 10 solicitors of the Irish Circuit took part in the cases.Annual^Conference of the^Hational Federation of Discharged SaTlorand So^Sr&quot;&quot; At Wfs 6&apos;orlerenco&quot; at LiverpooI Tresolu-to^r^haT^the Federation should henceforward work with the Labour Party was negatived.Admiralty8 S.V. 2nd June 1920.

</content>
</cab>
