<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/106/0 images: 483-499</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Dr-jr^ont h -&apos;&quot;se Property of w&apos;U V   v    V1-&apos; &quot;j ;y3 Government.5g n p-3B0RETReport Ho, 57DIRECTORATE OF INTELLIGENCE(Rome Office)UQqMallei3rd June, 19SOREPORT OH REVOLUTIONARY organisation,    IN THE UNITED KINGDOM ............-------oOo-.....-.....(Circulated by the Rome Secretary)THE &quot;HANDS OFF RUSSIA&quot; MOVEMENT...................... PAGETHB RAILWAYMEN.......................................THB HOUSING QUESTION .................................THE CO-OPERATIVE.....................................LABOUR PARTY ORGANISATION ............................DIVISION AMONG THE MINERS............................FEELING AMONG EX-SERVICE MEN .........................EDUCATIONAL SCHEMES AMONG THE DURHAM MINERS..........SCOTTISH LABOUR COLLEGE..............................THE COMMUNIST PARTY ..................................AGITATORS PROM THE COLONIES..........................BRITISH SUPPORT FOR DANISH STRIKERS ..................THE BRITISH SOCIALIST PARTY..........................THE RETURNED RUSSIAN PRISONERS .......................HAROLD BURGESS.......................................CONVICTIONS ..........................................SEIZURE OP ARMS.......................................SINN FEIN IN GREAT BRITAIN ...........................IRELAND ..............................................1 8 3 4 5 6 6 7 7 7 8 9 9 10 11 11 13 12 13SUMMARYOn the whole, the past week has been uneventful. The extremist section has been concentrating on the Polish offensive, the question of handling munitions for Ireland and the negotiations on the claims of the railwaymen and tramway workers for increased wages.The Workers&apos; Socialist Federation has been organising demonstrations as near to the Polish Legation in Grosvenor Square as the police would permit.   The audience has not exceeded 1,500, consisting of people from the East End who always attend extremist meetings.,      The Executive of the National Union of Railwayman is trying to pass on to the Triple Alliance the responsibility for deciding whether munitions for Ireland should be handled by railwayman. The Triple Alliance is equally disinclined to commit itself to a ^definite policy and requests, that a special meeting of the Trade Union Congress be summoned.There are indications that sections of the railwaymen will stand firm for a considerable increase of wages.Some details are given of a Guild scheme among the London building operatives, and of educational schemes for Labour.The conviction of Harold Burgess for attempting to corruptthe/
Ill- 2 -the Irish Guards appears to have met with publio approval, for the demonstrations&quot; in his favour have fallen singularly flat.i. seizure of conoealod arms was made in an unoccupied room in the East 12nd*&apos;Miss Sylvia Panl^urst and mr Theodore Rothstein have been in touch with the Russian Trading Derogation.   A caution has been conveyed to Mr, Erassin. who spates that it is extremely difficult to exclude suoh visitors, but that as far as he knows even Nogin will dooline oo have any doalings with them in Contravention of the Bigned agreement. 4
THE &quot;BANDS Off RUSSIA&quot; movement the little band of extremists in London have been holding demonstrations in Grosvenor Square against the Polish offensive.   The worst part of these demonstrations is that the speakers are able to point out to the 3ast 2nd Jews, who form the greater part of their audience, the difference between the conditions in which they live and-those in the West Snd.   On May 29th some 1,500 persons collected and attempted to reach the Polish Legation but were stopped by the police.   The speakers-who belonged to the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation made violent speeches and Lieut. Colonel Maione, M.P, is reported by police witnesses to have actually suggested the burning down of the Polish Legation.   On the other hand, the speakers were heckled by members of the crowd.On May 30th Miss Sylvia Pankhurst tried to lead 100 demonstrators from Trafalgar Square to the Polish Legation but was stopped by the police.   A monster demonstration is planned for about six weeks hence, and in the meantime meetings are to be held in Grosvenor Square every Wednesday and Saturday.The &quot;Hands off Russia&quot; Committee is trying to raise funds for a manifesto calling a general strike of one day to enforce peace with Russia.   This does not suit the extremists who think that the strike should be continued until peace is made.The provincial Labour Parties and Trades Councils are giving lip service to the Soviet cause, and at Liverpool a twenty-four hours&apos; strike is advocated.The ISnglish Labour Delegation to Russia is reported to have exercised mischievous influence on Norwegian socialists while in Christiania,   The following account of their utterances, in public, on May Day and in private has been received:-&quot;Robert/
- 2 -&quot;Robert Williams boasted - in camera - of his power of sabotage and of disorganising traffic.   He professed himself as a Bolshevist.   He did his best to persuade his hearers that the mass of British intellectuals are &quot;Clartists1 and as revolutionary as the bulk of British labour.&quot;&quot;Mrs. Snowden boasted of secret influence exerted upon the Cabinet and posed as &apos;in the know1 with regard to British high politics.&quot;&quot;All the delegates promised active support of Soviet Russia by sabotage, direct action or otherwise. Further, to slop supplies sent by Groat Britain or her Allies to enemies of Soviet Russia. It ic said that they will give this promise to Lenin on behalf of their organisations.&quot;The &quot;Isvestia&quot; of May 28th reports that Tanner and Beech spoke at a &quot;banquet&quot;, presumably in Moscow; the former stated that on his return he would &quot;raise a storm of protest against the lies, and slanders spread in Sngland regarding Soviet Russia.&quot;   Beech affirmed that the time for speech was past; now was the time for action.THE RAILWAYHBNThe &quot;Work to Rule&quot; strike has come to an ignominious end in London.   On May 30th a special meeting of the District Council of the National Union of Railwayman was held to consider future action.   The Chairman stated the Council had exhausted its financial resources and still owed the Committee one week&apos;s wages and all expenses. Re recommended immediate cessation of the &quot;strike&quot;. Paddington (No. Z) reported that the men were restive as they were losing 3s. to 5s. per day.   Smithfield said they had been &quot;sold&quot;.   Farringdon reported that a &quot;rot&quot; had set in and that the men were all working &quot;bonus&quot;. Homsey stated that only one man had worked to rule for one day and then reverted to the usual system.Bine Elms, on the other hand, reported that there would be difficulty in inducing the men to go back to normal conditions.   They would never revert to tonnage and/
- 3 ***and would do their best to make others follow their example.It was proposed by Paddington, seconded by Smithfield and carried by 46 to 16 votes that the &quot;Workto Eule Strike&quot; be called off as from Sunday midnight,sMay 30th.It was agreed by 65 votes to 2 to invite branches to make a levy of Id. per member to relieve the bankruptcy of the London District Council.   The two delegates who voted against the motion considered  d. sufficient,THE HOU3IHG QUESTIONAll my correspondents lay stress on the discontent caused by the lack of housing accommodation which is second only in importance to the cost of living.   There is to be a conference of Labour, Socialist and Co-operative Societies in Lancashire and Cheshire on the 5th dune.In some districts the shortage of bricklayers is handicapping work; in Kidderminster, for instance, my correspondent states that only two bricklayers have been working on forty houses.At Harrington a number of new municipal houses : has been ooinpTeted but cannot be occupied as the rent has not been fixed.   The Corporation considers 8s. per week, exclusive of rates, sufficient, whereas the Ministry of Health is said to desire that 13s. 6d. be charged.   Over a thousand applications have been made, but only a few of the wrkers would pay the higher rent.Inspired by the example of Manchester, Guildsmen in London have issued a prospectus to all branches of the Building Trades Operatives in the London area.Workers/
- 4 -Workers, technicians and administrators have been asked to volunteer for Guild service.   The scheme is not quite identical with that of the Manchester operatives, for the London Guild scheme is registered under the Industrial and Provident Societies Acts and not as a limited company. The Guild in London will work for every type of building owner, whether public or private, at a rate which will secure to every Guildsman continuous Guild pay.   The Guildsmen will lie on the strength for life arid will draw pay in sickness, bad weather and unemployment.   The minimum pay will be the full standard rate, but it is hoped to save .   money by scientific organisation.   Workers may send delegate to the Committee, and the surplus earnings will not be distributed as dividends but will be used for buying equipment and for eliminating hired capital.   The Guild will give no financial guarantee for the performance of contracts for it considers that its pledge is the best guarantee that can be devised.   A loan is being raised for preliminary expenses, to be repaid as soon as the Guild acquires surplus earnings.   This interesting experiment will be watched.THE CO-0?ERATIVa MOVEMENT,At the Bristol Conference last week the leaders of the Co-operative movement contrived to avoid the directiissue of federation with the Labour Party and the Trade      j Union Congress.   The President ruled the resolution advocating the alliance out of order, as the plans had not been discussed by the district conferences in accordance with the decision of the Carlisle Congress last year.It is possible that the President&apos;s ruling was based on the belief that the proposed alliance would not have met with the approval of a large number of, co-operators. In any case, the yearrs delay entailed by his rulingwill/
4 *J rj o- 5 -will disappoint the officials of the Labour Party and the Trade Union Congress, more especially those who are working for a &quot;General Staff&quot;.   The best brains of the Labour movement have realised that industrial power is largely destructive and can succeed only if backed by Co-operative food and money.LABOUR PARTY ORGAN ISAT ion the efforts of the Labour Party to strengthen its hold on the constituencies, to which I referred in my -last report, is again in evidence.   On May 29th a conference of Labour representatives on the City, Borough, Urban and County Councils of the Worth Eastern Federation of Labour Parties was held at Newcastle.   Housing problems formed the chief subject of discussion but the object of the conference was well put by the Chairman, Councillor David Adams, who said that it was proposed to initiate District conferences to deal with Municipal questions.   In view of the remarkable ascendancy of Labour in the political world, it was essential that Labour should have-a constructive policy municipally and he trusted that this meeting would be the precursor of many important District conferences.   He regarded the rise to prominence of the Labour Party in the country as very remarkable, especially in view of the hostility, veiled as it was, of a certain section of the press.   Preparation of policy and personnel was essential to success, and they looked forward to the time when they could not only head the local elections, but would dominate the Imperial Chamber as well,DIVISIOH/
- 6 -DIVISION jM THE MINERSIt has become-evident for some time -that-the -Soxrth, Wales Miners&apos; Federation&quot;might.secede from the Federation of Great Britain.   The immediate trouble is the proposal to raise the weekly contribution.   The voting on this question in the Pontypridd district resulted in a majority against contributing the increased amount - Is. weekly - and a special conference is to be held at Cardiff on June 5th to consider the matter. Should the defection take place it will make a serious breach in the ranks of the miners, for the South Wales Federation has a membership of 310,000,   Apart from the Yorkshire Miners&apos; Association, which is still suffering from the sectional strike last year, no group can compare with Wales in point of numbers and funds,FEELING AMONG SZ-SERVICE LOTThe two extreme societies, the National and Inter-national Unions, are opposing recruiting for the Territorials.   Behind this movement is the Herald League and the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation,   in anti-recruiting propaganda is working in the London, Plymouth, Portsmouth and Southend areas.At a meeting of the National.Union at Cardiff on May  9th resolutions were passed against obeying calls for mobilisation in connection with Poland, rejoicing in the failure in recruiting Territorials, calling upon the Government to withdraw armedjfdrees from Ireland and condemning the employment of black troops on the Rhine.Ex-Service men in Bristol are still restive. According to the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; they wish to send a       ^ deputation to the Prime Minister and say that if he will not receive them they will march to London and &quot;paradebefore/
- 7 -9 rj a&quot;before Buckingham Palace and appeal to see His Majesty&quot;.   They want the Government to furnish at least  1,000,000 for relief work.The Midland Branches of the National Federation have raised nearly  2,000 and distributed  2,601 in prizes by a sweepstake.*EDUCATIONAL SCHEMES iUOTO THE DUKE AM MINERS .On May 29th, 873 delegates met at the Miners&apos; Hall, Durham, to discuss education, and it&apos;was resolved to allocate  670 for the maintenance of three students in Ruskin College;  42 for eight scholarships in Secondary Schools, and  259 for classes on such subjects as citizenship, club life, co-operation, economics, history, internationalism, literature, music, nature studies, trade unionism and horticulture.A resolution was also-adopted unanimously for the restoration of pre-war conditions in clubs and institutes.SCOTTISH LABOUR COLLEGEThe College in Glasgow has 854 students and 30 classes; district classes in other areas number 51 with 2,000 students.   At the first -Annual Conference held on May 29th it was stated that the College had received  2,000, of which it expended from  1,600 to  1,800 a year.   The teaching is, of course,- revolutionary.THE COMMUNIST PARTY :The extremists have not given up all hope of forming a Communist Party.   A National Convention is to be held ir London at the beginning of August, and the Workers1 Socialist Federation has distributed a voting paper among its/
8 -its members on the question of accepting the Third International and the Dictatorship of the Proletariat. AGITATORS FROM THE COLONIES JI()Following in the steps of George Hardy, who came to this country to enlist the sympathy of British labour for members of the Industrial Workers of the World imprisoned in America, four agitators from the Colonies ar* now working in Great Britain on behalf of extremists imprisoned in Canada and Australia.   These men are John C Kavanagh, Sidney Gage, Tom Barker and Alexander Ross or Itosenthal.   The first named arrived in this country from  Canada on February 16th, 1920, and was. shortly followed by Gage.   The two men are agitating for the release of the men imprisoned in Canada as a result of the Winnipeg strike last year.   They declare at Labour meetings that the trial of these men was a &quot;farce&quot; and that they hope that British Labour will secure their release.   They also interview many provincial Trades Union officials, but my correspondent says that in Yorkshire, which was visited last week, they merely elicited expressions of sympathy.Tom Barker, whose mission has hitherto been equally fruitless, has confined his attention chiefly to London, where he is working on behalf of Labour men imprisoned in Australia.   He is a British subject who emigrated to New Zealand in 1911 or 1918, where he became secretary-treasure of the Industrial Y/orkers of the World.   He was deported from Australia to Chili in 1918 after having been convicted for various breaches of the law.   He arrived at Newcastle on May 3rd, 1920, and came to London, where he has address&apos; meetings at the International Socialist Club.   He has      J( apparently made thia club the headquarters of what he calli the &quot;Australian Workers&apos; Defence Committee&quot;.   Barker has issued]
issued a leaflet entitled &quot;To British Workers - An appeal from Australia&quot; in which are given the names and sentences of the men for whom he is appealing. He has acknowledged in the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; the receipt of  2. 0. 10.Ross, who was also deported from Australia tg Chili during the war, is working with Barker and the two men apparently constitute the Defence Committee.Members of the Industrial Workers of the World in London regard Barker and Ross with suspicion, as they are acting independently of the London organisation, and allege that they are merely trying to make a living out of their agitation on behalf of the imprisoned Australians.BRITISH SUPPORT gOR DANISH STRIKERSIt is reported that at the Conference of Scandinavian Seamen at Copenhagen, llr. iluogee (probably G. (I. HoEee. Secretary of Amalgamated Association of Hull Seamen and Lcrine Firemen) promised an immediate British contribution .  of  5,000 to the Danish strike fund.THE BRITISH SOCIALIST PARTY ,This Party, which is in close touch with Soviet Rubsia, intends to bring pressure to bear upon tho forthcoming Conference of the Labour Party, in favour of direct aotion in support of Russia.   Two members of the delegation to Russia, Ben Turner and Tom Shaw, will return in time to lay an early report before the Conference and the British Socialist Party will probably have received messages from Robert Williams by that time.A special Committee of tho National Guilds League, including Norman Kwer and William Mellor, has approached the British Socialist Party for particulars of tho Sovietsystem/ \
- 10 -system.   The British Socialist Party will probably propose that the National Guilds League shall take part in the formation of the Communist Party.The British Socialist Part? is reported to be negotiating for a printing press, end have been given to understand that the expense, which will amount to about  2,000, will be met.   The circulation ot &quot;The Call*l is reported to be increasing, end the paper has for five weeks received a subsidy of  25 per week.   In ardor that this amount shall not show on the balanoe sheet, Inkpin is purchasing paper privately.   The &quot;Call&quot; account is still in debt.The organisers of the hankey: and Ifile Convention have appealed to the British Socialist Party for funds as they are threatened with legal proceedings.   Inkpin replied that Hiss 3ylvia Pankhurst had received money for the convention and that as she had evidently not handed it over, cbe must have retained it.THE RETURNED RUSSIAN prisoners in view of the certainty that the British Labour Delegation will return from liosoow with Bolshevik propaganda, it sefems very desirable that the returned British prisoners should make themselves heard.   One of the prisoners, to. Robert Wale, has already engaged in open-air speaking., and at Woolwich an interrupter told him that Woolwich had a Soviet and arms, which they would bo prepared to use if necessary.   ^ale appealed.to the crowd to make this man repeat the assertions end said, &quot;I have personal experience of Communism under arms; are you people down here going to let this man start these Russian tricks?M   The crowd        i shouted, &quot;No, we don&apos;t want him, chuck him out!&quot;Hi HOLD/&apos;
- 11 -HAROLD BUR03SSThe Workers Socialist Federation has organised &quot;demonstrations&apos;&apos; to protest against the imprisonment of Harold Burgess.   The first was held outside Pentonvillo on Hay 27th and was attended by seven members of the Federation and about 50 local residents who resented the appearance of the extremists and heckled them severely. When Miss 0&apos;Callaghan called for volunteers to march round.the prison, she was accompanied by a crowd of ohildren who laughed and booed,Mrs. Melvina Walker met with a similar reception at V/illesden on the following day.   She attempted to defend Burgess and was met with cries of &quot;What about the bribery&quot;.   Mrs. Walker replied that &quot;there was no harm in buying soldiers a drop of beer&quot; end that as she had a long way to go, home, she would not answer any a ore questions that night.OOHVICTIOflSOn May 24th Mord Wilgus, a Russian, naturalised American, was arrested in Hyde Bark for insulting behaviour which incensed his audience.   It was then ascertained that he had landed in the United Kingdom without the permission of the Immigration Officer. On June 1st he was fined 403. or one month for insulting behaviour, sentenced to six weeks&apos; hard labour for breach of the Aliens Act and recommended for expulsion. ,   Wilgus has been in cloftio touch with Sylvia Pankhurst ,;ar;d has contributed to the &quot;Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot;.itertrand di Colonna, a British subject of Italian birth who claims the title of &quot;Count&quot;, is a young Herald League speaker who has twice been convicted of theft. He was arrested for assaulting the police after a meetingat/
at Marble Arch on May 26th and was sentenced to six weeks1 imprisonment at Maryborough Street Police Station on May 29th.   Colonna told a friend that as Mhe was destitute he was looking forward to a few weeks&apos; holiday in prison and added:   &quot;A nice little sum will be collected for me by the old women of both sexes in the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation&quot;.SEIZURE OP ARMSOn the 1st June, 21 automatic pistols and 50 cartridges, a printing press, type and about a ton of revolutionary literature were found secreted in an unoccupied room at 73, Jubilee Street, E.   Enquiries as to the destination of the arms are proceeding.   They appear to have been purchased some time ago by a Russian who has now returned to Russia and who is still paying the rent of the room.SUN PBIN IN GREAT BRITAINThe possibility of inducing English workers to refuse to handle munitions for Ireland has been uppermost in Sinn Pein circles during the week.   The leaders are appealing to the Irish workers to use their influence in the Trades Unions&apos;,&apos; and the greatest possible pressure will undoubtedly be brought to bear.   Prom the resolutions passed by the Executive of the National Union of Railway-men it is difficult to deduce the final attitude of that Union; the executive must, however, be in something of a dilemma, for, on the cne hand, there are numerous resolutions pledging the branches to support the Irish     j&apos; and, on the other hand, there is the apathy and in many cases the dislike of the Irish.- &apos;   &apos; The/
M-) r, o1&amp;6 Annua2  ene.ru3 -Me-erUng^ of the^Gaelic League- of linden was held In St, Br4,oVs XrmtdJtrrrba on May 29th, The membership now totals 1100 as against 466 in 1919, but is considered xmsatisfactory as it only represents a small percentage of the London IriBh.The finances of the League appear to be comparatively soundj subscriptions for the year 1919 amounted to  183. 4. 0., donations to  3. E. 0, and collections at St. Bride!s to.  S3. 14.        The Annual festival realised 317. 16. Zi   Thf excess ,of income over expenditure forvthe year was  237. 15. 7., but it has not yet been decided whether this money shall be forwarded to Dublin.   Theleague has also a &quot;Language Fund&quot; which realised by meansof collections and entertainments  110. 16. 9-i, and had*a balance from the previous year of  38. 3.       from this money the sum of  133. 0. 0. was sent to Dublin.The Irish Self-Determination League has held the usual meetings in London and has formed a new branch in SouthwardMy Glasgow correspondent states that the riot on May 29th, when six-policomen- were injured and twenty-one people arrested, arose from a brawl among drunken Sinn ffoiners.  He adds that smaller disturbances occur praotioally every Saturday night owing to Irishmen fight-ing amongst themselves.The SxeoutCfe of the Lanarkshire Miners Union is asking the sanction of its branches for a 84 hours&apos; strike as &quot;a protest against the treatment of the Irish people by the Government.&quot; IRELANDThe condition of the country remained unchanged during the past week.   Up to 29th instant the number 0$ outrages reported was as followsSinn/
- 14 --   Sinn Fein outrages. 131Agrarian &quot; 39Other serious   &quot;. ,    ...    25The latter figure does not include a large numberof ordinary cases-of outrage such as housebreaking,larceniee,  etc., nor does- it include 25 cases ofattempted destruction of vacated Ko$al Irish ConstabularBarracks by Sinn Feiners.rfThe Sinn Fein Executive are doing all they can to ^ further the ddea that they are the only body that can Tim. the Country.   With this end in view a considerable number of Sinn Fein Courts are being held in* different parts of the Country.   The procedure of these Courts is advertised in the ultra radical newspapers -in England and in those with Sinn Fein sympathies over here.   In pursuance of the same policy a -certain number of cases are reported ct the irish Volunteers attempting to do Polioe duty. .. * t.;Information has hie en received to the effect that all policemen who assisted in the,arrest of rebels deported to England will be &quot;tried&quot; by rebel Court Martial on the return of the prisoners who have now been released on Hunger Strike.Efforts are still being made to break down the discipline and morale of the Royal Irish Cons^abrjpfery,The &quot;Watehword of Labour&quot; and &quot;Old Ireland!&apos; appear^ this week as usual.   The former-is concerned with the &quot; Knockloag &quot;Soviet Creameries&quot; where the workers took over1 the creameries during a labour dispute-, but relinquished the task after five days.   An agreement wa come to between the workers and the management.-3,-;&apos; At Kingstown and Worth Wall, Dublin, dockers and^ railwaymen refused to handle munitions sent from Bngltxi1 - to/
- IS -3also ^to the troops in Ireland, and/at Queenstown whe:re a   I,    j)regiment which arrived on the 29th had to land its ownstores.The Dublin Metropolitan Police area has been quiet during the week.   Whether this quietness is the result of a well arranged system of patrolling by Police and Military, or is merely the forerunner of Sinn Pein operations, as in the past, .remained*s to be Been.*The dockers still refuse to handle munitions at Dublin and Kingstown.   Beneficial results are being obtained from enforcement of the Curfew Order.

</content>
</cab>
