<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/55/0 images: 10-12</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINETThe attached paper (C. (52) 30 2,Japan and the General Agreement on tariffs and Trade) will be considered at tomorrow^ meeting of the Cabinetunder Item 2.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1.17TH SEPTEMBER, 1952.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT)SECRETfC.(52) 302 COPY NO. 0Y17TH SEPTEMBER,  1952CABINETJAPAN AND THE GENERAL AGREEMENT on tariffs AND trade memorandum by the Minister of StateWhile the course of action proposed by the President of the Boardof Trade in his memorandum ( C. (52) 301) will be less harmful than if wewere to vote against Japanese admission to the General Agreement on tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.), there is no doubt that it will be interpreted, in view of our past attitude, by Japan, U.S.A. and othercountries as evidence of our continued distrust of Japan and of our desire to delay her accession to G.A.T.T. and if possible, to prevent it.It will accordingly amount to a severe blow to the standing of post-warJapan, will cause resentment in U.S.A. and will increase the temptation to Japan to resort to her pre-war &quot;unfair&quot; trade practices which are more to the disadvantage of the United Kingdom than to that of any other country.2. The negative policy represented by abstention is, in the view ofthe Foreign Office, open to the following objections(a) It will not delay or prevent the accession of japan and will be seen in Japan as a fruit-less gesture, which would accentuate ourweakness in their eyes.(b) It will not assist British industries to compete with Japan nor serve any useful economicpurpose.(c) It will cause resentment in Japan and may therefore endanger negotiations with japan in which the United Kingdom has more to lose or gain than the Japanese, particularly those dealing with the status of BritishCommonwealth Forces in Korea and withsterling area payments.(d) It will tend to increase antagonism and conflict between Japan on the one hand and the Common-wealth on the other.    Cn the commercial sidethis will make Japan redouble her efforts toundercut and oust British exports in important and valuable markets over which Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment have no direct control and whenthey consequently cannot ensure that measures are taken to protect British industry.-1-
S.E.Foreign Office, S. W. 1.17TH SEPTEMBER, 1952.(e) Politically it will be a blow to those Japanesewho favour cooperation with the West, but agift to communist propaganda in Japan.    Itwill add to the temptation to which Japan issubjected of playing the free world offagainst the communist world and will contribute to the very real danger of japan&apos;s moving away from the West towardscommunism.    Strategically this is dangerous.(f) It will run counter to United States policy ofbuilding Japan up economically and politically as the main anti&quot;communistbulwark in the Far East and so tend toincrease the divergences between UnitedKingdom and United States policy in that area.3. The Japanese language, way of life and standards of conduct areutterly different from Western ways.     There is therefore always aninherent tendency for Japan to play a lone hand.     Japan&apos;s increasingpopulation (large in relation to her area) and the commercial threatwhich she presents to other countries combine to turn her isolationisttendencies into competitive and antagonistic ones.    It is this which is so dangerous for the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth.    If Japancan be brought into international organisations and can play an equalpart with other Western countries in international life, these tendenciesmay be counteracted.    Her accession to G.A.T.T. would be particularly desirable as it contains a number of useful safeguards against the sort oftrade malpractices which caused such bitterness between Japan and theUnited Kingdom before the war.    This is a further reason for avoidingan attitude of opposition or hostility barely disguised as neutrality (whichwould be the effect of abstention) towards Japan&apos;s application to accede to G.A.T.T., all the more so as neither opposition nor abstention will be effective in preventing or delaying Japanese accession.    We have also torecognise that Japanese competition with British industries is largely in colonial and Commonwealth markets over which Her Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave no direct control and where British industries can consequently onlybe protected if the governments concerned are willing to increase margins of preference and thereby raise the prices charged to their consumers.4. The Foreign Office therefore consider that, as an alternative tothe line proposed by the President of the Board of Trade, it would bemore compatible with our interests for instructions along the following lines to be issued to the United Kingdom delegation at Geneva:-(i)    to work and vote for a resolution which would welcome the Japanese application to accede  to G.A.T.T. anddeclare Japan eligible in principle to become a contracting party after she has carried out tariff negotiations;(ii)    to explain that the United Kingdom is reconsideringits attitude towards G.A.T.T.,  and give notice that,pending this reconsideration, Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment would be unable to undertake tariff negotiationswith new applicants and might be forced to invoke article XXXV if new applicants acceded to G.A.T.T.This would safeguard us as regards retaining our freedom of action to protect United Kingdomindustries against Japanese competition.

</content>
</cab>
