<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/55/0 images: 110-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
noC. (52) 33213th OCTOBER, 1952.cabinet situation IN KENYAMemorandum by theSecretary of State for the colonies attach copies of two telegrams which I have just received from the Governor.   He proposes to declare a state ofEmergency and detain those who are regarded as the realleaders of Mau Mau.   I propose to approve the action which herecommends, but before doing so I should like to have theconcurrence of my colleagues.The Governor expects that the arrests will lead to someviolence and I think it important to give him the military support which he and the General Officer Commanding think necessary.   I accordingly seek approval for the despatch of aBritish battalion from the Middle East to Nairobi,O.L.Colonial Office, S.W.I.13th OCTOBER, 1952.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of........................... jTOP SECRET Copy No.....
INWARD TELEGRAM.TO THE SECRETARY OF STATE  FOR THE COLONIES.IllFROM KENYA    (Sir E: Baring)CYPHER (O.T.P.) D.  10th October, 1952.R.  10th.       &quot; &quot;  .    07.50 hrs.I^EDIATgTOP secret no.  616.Following information gained dtxring a short tour ofthe most troubled areas of Kilcuyuland, both reserves and farms,and recent sharp increase of tempo of crime, I have regretfullycome to the following conclusions:1. Quite apart from their political views, most KenyaAfrican union leaders, including Kenyatta, are planners of theMau Mau movement, an organised conspiracy exists and Mau Maucrimes committed are either the result of direct instigationby Kenya African union leaders at Nairobi- or arising indirectlyfrom the initiative of local Africans and inflamed against,loyal Africans and Europeans by speeches and messages fromthese leaders.2. The main reasons for holding this view are:(i) there has been a regular pattern of events at mostplaces in the trouble areas (e.g. the-Fort Hall and Nyerireserves and Timau and Thompson&apos;s Falls farms).    First,speeches by Kenyatta and other Kenya African union leaders,next a shuttle service of emissaries from Nairobi and localmen returning there for instructions: then widespread Mau Mauoath taking; finally murder, assault, boycott.    All this has happened in areas which, before the speeches mentioned, were quite quiet (e.g. Thompson&apos;s Falls-farms) or were areas ofmild oath taking ceremonies (e.g.  in Fort Hall attendances at these ceremonies arose from an average of about - twenty to several thousands after the speeches).(ii) when he chooses, Kenyatta has induced Kikuyu to obeyhim.    He practically stopped the drinking of European beer byAfricans in Nairobi.    Yet his denunciation of Mau Mau crimeshas been ine3?fective and has often, I am told by. Kikuyus, been accompanied by sayings and gestures making clear to hisaudience that he did not mean what he said..(iii) Kikuyu chiefs and headmen, African administrative officers, Kikuyu teachers, both European and Kikuyu missiiyn-aries of the three denominations predominant (i.e. Catholic,Church of Scotland and American Independent Mission) inKikuyuland, as well as European Government officers andfarmers, unanimously and with emphasis told me that:(a) the&apos; Kenya African union leaders, and particularlyKenyatta, were at the back of the Mau Mau movement and violentcrime and(b) without their removal, no other measures would succeed in checking the increasing rate of deterioration of the position.
(iv) Kenyutta lias allowed his name to be inserted blasphe-mouslsr in hymns and prayers as part of strongly anti-Christianmovement which, has gone a long way in some areas to empty themission schools in favour of the Kikuyu Independent schools and churches in favour of the Mau Mau religion.3- I conclude, therefore, that we must remove Kenyattaand several of his henchmen during the nest few weeks. If wedo not(i) the chiefs, headmen, Government servants.and mission-: aries among the Kikuyu who still support us will cease their support and may well &quot;be killed;(ii) the trouble will spread to-&apos;other tribes who are morewar-like than the Kikuyu and who provide men for Kenya Police..Already attempts are being made to infiltrate into NyanzaProvince and Wakamba area.(iii) there will be reprisals by Europeans.    Attacks havebeen first on loyal Africans, headmen and informers, twentysixof them have been murdered, next on European property, and finally on leading Africans and on Europeans.    During the last few days the killing of Chief Waruhiu (perhaps one of the threeleading Africans in Kenya) and two murderous attacks onEuropeans have produced a temper bound to lead to reprisals andthen almost to civil war, unless leaders of the Mau Mau move-ment are removed during the next few weeks.. h); If we do remove, them, I believe indoctrination oftribes other than the Kikuyu will cease and, even among theKikuyu, there are -(a) sufficient centres of&apos;resistance and(b) so many followers of Mau Mau who have joinedfrom fear alone, that position can be regained.5.       I am .informed by all my advisers that the arrest ofKenyatta may well be followed by much violence.    Greatestdanger at the moment is that this may lead to Europeanreprisals.    &quot;Following&apos;Timau outrage, attacks on Europeans andWaruhiu murder? situation has so much worsened since the visit of Whyatt and Davies that, if we proceeded against Kenyattaunder new Special District Ordinance, the violence I anticipatewould develop during the fourteen days1  grace.    If, alterna-tively, we could obtain sufficient evidence to use the deportation-tion (immigrant British Subjects) Ordinance the same violencewould develop during the judicial.enquiry at Nairobi.    our information is that this vi0lence would start from the momenthands&apos; are laid on Kenyatta, there would be reprisals, loss of life, and it would then become necessary to declare a stateof emergency.6.       The most likely way of avoiding bloodshed would be .to declare an emergency and then immediately remove Kenyattaand his followers by executive action under the emergency regulations.    I would propose to proceed under the emergency powers.Order-in-Council 1939 rather than under the LocalEmergency Powers Ordinance 19^4-8; Rogers&apos;  secret -letter of
1/3TOP SECRETisfejfZZZlZl- INWARD TELEGRAM.* HI TO THE SECRETARY  OF STATE  FOR THE COLONIES.15th June 19^0 and your secret circular despatch of18th I^ebruary 1950 refer.7-        If this operation was staged for about 23rd Octoberwe would have time to build up adequate police and militaryforces..    I believe the risk of trouble is very great and weshould be too strong rather than too weak.    For this reason Ihave asked the local military authorities to communicate withG.O.G. -in-C. Middle Last Land Forces about sending to NairobiBritish battalion allocated for this purpose and I trust youwill agree.3.       We would be most grateful for loan of a special branch police officer to remain here for about a year tooverhaul our security machine.    This is a vital and urgent need-9.       I much regret having to recommend such strong actionso soon.    I have very much-in mind, need for a positive as wellas a negative policy.    Members of the Government have already agreed to work towards abolishing the rules by which africans in senior posts draw (? omission; fifths of the European pay and arrangements are being made for promotion of certainAfricans from grade 0 to grade B.    More money is being allo-cated to African, housing and education.    With one farmers&apos;meeting I have frankly discussed&apos;-a &quot;minimum agricultural wage.Letter follows.,-Dis t r ibut i on:Secretary of StateSir Ti LloydP.8.  to Parliamentary U/SSir 0.&quot; JeffriesSir EL PoyntonMr, K.H.  DaviesMr, T.K. ParsonsMr. Gorell barnes mr. P. rogers mr. EL P. Hall
INWARD TELEGRAM.TO  THE  SECRETARY  OF STATE  FOR THE COLONIES.FROM KENYA    (Sir E. Baring)CYPHER (O.T.P.) D.  13th October,  1952..R.  13th       &quot; H       08.45 hrs.. I Mail]DIATE&apos; TOP SECRET AND PERSONALNo. 620.  :Prom Baring for Lloyd. -Begins. ,Your telegram Ho. 651.1 am most grateful for your-telegram and realise that decision of this importance requires most carefulconsideration.    Unfortunately the situation here continuesto deteriorate, and since my telegram No. 616 was sent therehas teen another serious attack cn two elderly Europeans inthe Kiambu area, where farms and the Kikuyu Reserve areintermingled.2.       Emergency Regulations will-give power to detainwhere the Governor is satisfied that it is necessary toexercise control over any person for the purpose of main-taining public order.    In addition, they will confer powerto prohibit the carrying of weapons of offence such as&quot;pangas&quot; in disturbed areas, and the power to maintain food supplies and essential services if, as my Advisers consideralmost certain, such supplies:and services are disrupted bygeneral strike or disturbed by conditions following upon the detention of Kenyatta&apos;&apos; and his henchmen.3.        I entirely appreciate the political desirability ofbeing ready on or about 23rd October.    Planning is almost complete, and, provided suitable arrangements concerningBritish battalion are made, we think we can keep to approxi-mately this date.    I &quot;believe that Penher Brockway may be theguest of Chief Koinange at his home in Kiambu.    You should know that the Criminal Investigation Department are strongly of the opinion that ex-Chief Koinange and his two sons areimplicated in the murder of vvaruhui.    Investigations arestill proceeding.h&apos;       In my view,  and in that of my.Advisers, presence ofa British battalion &quot;before (repeat &quot;before) Kenyatta and his main followers arc detained under the Emergency regulations may well be the decisive factor in preventing outbursts .*fviolence by Kikuyu, followed probably by reprisals byEuropeans with resulting bloodshed.    G.O.C.  and I both believe the situation might then become so serious that it would benecessary to call on the Middle East for more than one battalion.    Moreover, apart from preventive effect, conditionsin Kenya, with its scattered European population, will makenecessary so great a dispersal of military and police forces that without British battalion a very weak reserve (of only two companies) would be left.    For these reasons andespecially for the psychological and preventive effect, Iwould be most grateful for help in obtaining battalion.\ h - . - I iia
5.       Timing presents a difficulty.    On our present infor-mation from M.E.L.P.,  eight full days will be required fromreceipt of order  until concentration at Nairobi, since aire-craft are only available to lift half a battalion in one, operation.    For fly-in to: be completed by 23rd or 2q.th, itwould therefore be necessary for Her Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;decision to be communicated to me and to M.E.L.F.  on the 11+thor 15th.    If this is not possible, I am afraid we will haveto postpone detentions to Monday 27th October since, if detention-tions take-place during the week-end when the town Kikuyu arenot at work, trouble is far more likely.6.       I will certainly bear in mind your point concerningExecutive Council meetings.7-       Presume you have by now received my letter of9th October amplifying my telegram No.  616.Distribution&quot;: -H. k53Secretary of StateSir T. LloydP.S.  to Parliamentary U/SSir C. JeffriesSir H. EoyntonMr. K.H. DaviesMr. T..R, ParsonsMr. Gorell barnes mr. P. rogers mr. H.P. Hall- Mr. Trafford SmithWar Office. (D. M.O.) - Gen. McLeodDisturbances Distribution sent.

</content>
</cab>
