<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/55/0 images: 136-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I &apos; 1%(TI-IfeDOCUJMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT)secret.(52) 343 COPY NO.20TH OCTOBER, 1952CABINETHORTICULTURAL TARIFFSAPPLICATION FOR INCREASES BY THE national farmers&apos; UNIONSMemorandum by the President of the Board of trade as my colleagues are aware, I have under examination applicationsby the National Farmers&apos; Unions (N.F.U.) for increased import duties onhorticultural products.   The group of officials appointed to advise the Boardof Trade on the domestic merits of tariff applications have now reported onthe main part of the case;  and their recommendations have been approved inprinciple by the Economic Policy Committee, subject to one or two points of detail which have now been settled with the Ministers concerned.   these recommendations involve straight increases in duty in a number of cases andin certain other cases changes in the form of duty which will effectivelyresult in increases.   The items affected are listed in Annex A.2. There is, however, a major obstacle in the way of implementingmost of these proposals, namely, the conflict between our Ottawa commitments and commitments we have undertaken in the General Agreement on tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.).   This arises, of course, from the fact that in order tocomply with the G.A.T.T. &quot;no-new-preference&quot; rule we must match any increase in the rate of duty applying to foreign goods by such duties on commonwealth and Colonial goods as will leave the margins of preferenceunchanged: yet, as a result of our Ottawa free-entry undertakings to theCommonwealth we are prohibited by law from imposing duties on the majorityof goods imported from other parts of the Commonwealth; and even if we hadpowers we could only impose such duties by consent.3. The whole question of the G.A.T.T. preference rules will of course be among the subjects to be discussed at the Commonwealth Prime Ministers1Conference, and it is impossible to say at this stage what the final outcome willbe.   Meanwhile we cannot avoid making some statement on the N. F. U. case.The pressure for such a statement continues to grow.   What we have now todecide, therefore, is how we should deal with the case, pending the outcome ofthe Conference and any discussions with other countries which may result from it.4. My own view, which is shared by my colleagues in the economic policy Committee, is that the right course is to explain the difficulty franklyto the N. F. U, and to assure them of our intention to implement decisions ontheir application as soon as freedom to do so can be secured; and subsequently to make a statement to this effect in the House of Commons.   The economic policy Committee felt that any such statement should stress the governments intention to find a means of implementing decisions on tariff applicationsbut should not, in advance of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers 1Conference, commit the Government to taking any particular course ofaction to obtain the necessary freedom.   I ha/ve set out in Annex B a form of words which might serve as the basis for the explanation to the N. F, U. and fora statement in the House.
-   5, Action on these lines will inevitably expose us to many difficulties.IpThe N. F. U. will feel that they might have been warned earlier of the majorobstacle in the way of implementing decisions on their case.   (The reason for not warning them earlier is that it has not been thought desirable to exposeour dilemma until there was a concrete case for increasing duties).Industry generally is also likely to express alarm when they grasp the fullsignificance of the &quot;no-new-preference&quot; rule in relation to the United Kingdomtariff.   There will, no doubt, be renewed pressure for the denunciation of theG.A.T.T.;  and the admission that we cannot for the present provide increasedtariff protection is likely to intensify the pressure for protection by import licensing restrictions - a development which I should deplore.6. Nevertheless, I frankly do not see any alternative to the course ofaction proposed in paragraph 4,   The N, F, U, are aware that the examinationof the main part of their case is complete and we cannot, therefore, assertthat we are still considering it^   Equally, there is no way of implementing our decisions which would not expose us to even greater difficulties.   There arestrong political objections to taking powers to enable duties to be imposed on commonwealth goods; and, even if this were not so, such an arrangement would not provide a complete solution to our present problem since we shouldbe unlikely to get Commonwealth consent in all cases.   We clearly cannot floutour G.A.T.T. obligations.   Equally it would be a mistake to prejudice futurenegotiations on the &quot;no-new-preference&quot; rule by trying to get a waiver fromthe G.A.T.T. Contracting Parties to enable us to deal with the N, F, U, case,I do not think, therefore, there is any escape from the conclusion that thecourse proposed, though objectionable, is less objectionable than any other alternative,7, There is one further point to which I should draw my colleagues&apos;attention.   On nine of the items on which increased duties are recommended weare free, in the main, owing to the way in which the &quot;no-new-preference&quot; ruleoperates, to bring the higher rates of duty into operation without imposingduties on Commonwealth products.   The items affected are shown by asteriskin Annex A.   On these the Economic Policy Committee agreed that thequestion whether or not we should take action to alter the rates should bediscussed with the N, F, U. and decided in the light of their reactions.   If inthe event it is decided to take action in these particular cases it would bedesirable to lay the Order effecting the changes of duty, together with a white paper explaining the reasons for these changes, at the same time as thegeneral statement is made in the House.8, Discussions with the N, F. U. and with such organisations as theFederation of British Industries (to whom I should think it desirable to giveadvance warning of this problem) are bound to take a little time and I should not expect to be ready to make a statement in the House until about mid-November:if an Order had to be made in respect of those items where we axe free totake action this might delay things for a day or two.   This means that thestatement will be made shortly before the Prime Ministers&apos; Conference starts.9, I seek authority to proceed on the basis outlined in paragraph 4,namely(i) to explain our dilemma to the N, F, U, and other leading trade organisations on the lines indicated in Annex B;(ii) to make a statement in the House broadly on the lines set out in annex B when these discussions have been completed,P.T.Board of Trade, S,W,10,20TH OCTOBER, 1952,
RECOMMENDED INCREASESFresh fruit:CherriesCurrantsGooseberriesjs   Grapes (hothouse)Plumss   Raspberries and Loganberriesr   StrawberriesFresh vegetables:*   Asparaguss   Broccoli and CauliflowersCarrotsCucumbers (other than gherkins)Green BeansGreen Peas (a) Unshelled(b) Shelled36    (a)    Lettuce and Endiveh   (b)    Chicory (Salad)x   MushroomsTomatoesTurnipsDry Bulb Onions and Shallots&amp; Preserved fruit - unsweetened (including fruit pulps)Dried peas, whole,  other than peasof the varieties commonly known asmaple peas, dun peas and.yellow and white peas.-Vegetables preserved in salt or brine:-Cauliflowers in brineChicoryRaw or kiln driedRoasted or ground.
ANNEX draft statement with your permission, Mr. Speaker, and that of theHouse I propose to make a statement about the United Kingdomprotective tariff and in particular about import duties onhorticultural products.As the House will be aware, the National Farmers&apos; Unionssubmitted a comprehensive application for the revision ofthe tariff on horticultural products, and this was accepted for examination by the previous Government.    The examinationof the main part of the application, relating to certain freshand preserved fruit and vegetables, has now been concluded.All interested parties have been given full opportunity tomake known to my Department their views upon the application,and full aocount has been taken of the representationsreceived.Her -Majesty&apos;s Government have been impressed by thestrength of the evidence in favour of the revision of some ofthese duties and they have decided, therefore, that in those cases the existing import duties should be increased./&quot;&quot;Subject to certain exceptions which I shall mentionpresently.,/ it is however impossible to give effect to these decisions at the present time.   The reason for this difficulty is the conflict between our Ottawa commitments, and our commitments under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.This arises from the fact that, owing to the rule in theGeneral Agreement which prohibits new or increased preferences,we are obliged to match any increase in the rate of duty onforeign goods by such duties on Commonwealth (includingColonial) goods as will leave the margin of preferenceunchanged.    But we are unable to comply with this obligationsince our Ottawa commitments, and our legislation fulfillingthose commitments, require us to accord free entry into thiscountry for the majority of Commonwealth products.This problem does not apply, of course, solely to the horticultural tariff.    It applies to virtually the whole ofour protective tariff and means that we oannot increase duties on foreign goods even in those cases where we have not under-taken specific commitments to other countries on particularrates of duty.    It is perhaps unnecessary for me to emphasise the gravity of this situation.    In effect it means thatagreements have been entered into which virtually freeze thewhole of the United Kingdom tariff.    I doubt if any majortrading nation has ever been placed in such a situation.We do not intend to let the matter rest here.   As hasbeen made clear on a number of occasions Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment regard the tariff as the proper method of providingprotection and it is a basio assumption of our policy that where a clear case for protection has been established itshould be provided by means of the tariff.    There can be noquestion but that we must recover the right of the UnitedKingdom to increase rates of duties in the tariff save to theextent that such duties are limited by specific international commitments given in respect pf particular goods or classes
litOof goods in return for what must have appeared at the time as valuable consideration.    This particular effect of theno-new-preference rule has not &quot;been noticeable until nowsince it has been, and remains, our policy not to increaseprotective tariffs unless the need is established beyond doubt, and there has hitherto been no case of proved needsince the war.    But we have now a proved case to increasecertain protective duties.    In such circumstances I can assure the House that Her Majesty^ Government are determined to secure a solution to this problem, and to give effect totheir decisions on the horticultural tariff as soon as theyare free to do so.   This problem is clearly closely linked with our whole Commonwealth commercial policy and we intend to discuss it at the forthcoming meeting of commonwealth prime Ministers./&quot;in the particular case of the horticultural tariff,there are nine items on which we are free under the G.A. T.T.to raise the rates of duty to some extent in certain periods.I will not trouble the House at this stage with details ofthese cases.    I have recommended that these revised rates should be put into effect immediately.    The Chancellor of theExchequer has accepted this recommendation and an Order giving effect to these decisions has been laid before the house to-day.    The House may wish to know that a White Paper hasalso been published to-day and is available in the Vote Officegiving further information about these cases.As the House will be aware, arrangements were made some time ago for the seasonal withdrawal of certain open general Licences for fruit and vegetables as a specialmeasure, pending decisions on the tariff application.    such these arrangements as have remained in force up to thepresent will come to an end in the periods in respect ofwhich the tariff has been adjusted;    and in these casesimport licensing arrangements will in future be determinedsolely by balance of payments considerations.^

</content>
</cab>
