<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/55/0 images: 143-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Trfrl DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)**&apos; mm Km m mm mhm m m as a mt mm mm mm n a m m mm m m -a m an mm m m m m n mm mm mm mm ma m mm as as m w bm      m cm bb bb m u ^confidential.(52) 345 COPY NO,   b C17TH OCTOBER, 1952.CABINETJUDGES&apos; salaries memorandum by the Lord chancellor welcome the statement by the Chancellor of the Exchequer(C, (52) 334) that he does not question the special position of the Judgesor their need to maintain some state and dignity.    I do not think that thefact that a certain allowance is paid to Judges on circuit to meet thealtogether exceptional expenditure which they then incur affects thequestion,,-&apos;2, I agree that under the existing law no adequate provision can bemade.    There must be legislation which recognises the special position,3, If so, how is it to be recognised?    The alternatives are:-(1)   An increase of gross salary.(2)   A tax-free allowance on top of the presentgross salary;  or(3)    A provision that a part of the present grosssalary shall be tax-free.4, The Chancellor of the Exchequer advocates the first course.    the objection to this course is that the amount of increase of gross salary isdisproportionate to the benefit received.    As he points out, under presenttaxation an increase of  2,000 gross is required to provide even a net increase of  450.   I do not think that this is an adequate net increase:a larger one produces a greater disproportion.5, The objection to the other courses is stressed by the Chancellorof the Exchequer.    I agree with him and have always recognised that either of them involves discrimination in favour of the Judges and that&quot;it would mean that their income would be treated in a quite differentway from that of all the rest of the community&quot;.    Where I venture todisagree with him is in his contention that if there is discrimination andif &quot;we break the principle that all without any exception are subject to thegeneral law we have started on a very dangerous slope&quot;.    It is just becausethe Judges have a &quot;special position in the community&quot; that I urge andwelcome discrimination.    It is no recognition of their special positionin the community to give them a gross salary which is equalled orsurpassed by that of scores of men in industry and commerce.    Eut it isa proper and striking recognition if they are given a tax-free allowancewhich is given to no one else.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer fears the slippery slope and byway of example indicates the direction from which danger may come.    he suggests first that discrimination between them and the lower judiciary andother   semi-judicial officers might soon become a bone of contention,,    I, onthe other hand, am confident that these persons would never on their ownbehalf claim the same privileges as Judges of the High Court, and I am sure that if they did they would not receive the support of the present or any otherLord Chancellor.    He next refers to &quot;other public figures of high statusincluding ministers themselves&quot;.    I prefer to say nothing about n ministers andfor the rest I do not know what public figures are intended.    Is there any public figure who would pass the vital test that Parliament would think fit to discriminate in his favour?    I know of none.    Of course if the Judgesthemselves do not pass that test there is an end of the matter.Finally, the Chancellor of the Exchequer refers to overtime pay of miners and other key workers.    This is surely not a valid comparison.I will not repeat the arguments which perhaps at too great length I urgedin my first memorandum.6, I ask my colleagues to reject the slippery slope argument and todetermine that the simple and commonsense way of providing for personsholding a special position in the community is to give them what other personsdo not get.    I see no difficulty or danger in providing either a tax-free allowanceon top of their salary of at least  750 per annum or for a sufficient part of theirsalary being free of tax to reach the same net result.    As I said before,legislation would be necessary and I hope that it may be introduced.SIMONDSLord Chancellor&apos;s Office,   S. W. 1.17TH OCTOBER, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
