<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/49/12 images: 102-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1945.SECRET.       - Copy No.W.M. (45)lUtfii Conclusions.WAR CABINET 12 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet War room on Monday, 29th January, 1945, at 5-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.F., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information. -The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of State (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint    Parliamentary    Secretary,Treasury (Items 5 arid 6).Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary   of   State   for . ForeignAffairs Utems 1-4).Air Marshal Sir Douglas C. S. Evill,Vice-Chief of the Air Staff (Item 1).The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The   Right   Hon.   Sir   archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Major   the   Right Hon.   G.   LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Fuel and power (Items 5 and 6).The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(Items 5 and 6).The   Right  Hon.  Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint     Parliamentary    Secretary,Treasury (Items 5 and 6).Vice-Admiral Sir E. Neville Syfret,Vice-Chief of Naval Staff (Item 1).Lieut.-General Sir Archibald E. Nye,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff (Item 1).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General L. C. Hollis.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[29426-1]
WAR CABINET 12 (45),Contents.minute no.                                      Subject. Page.1      Naval, Military and Air Operations................      71Air Operations:Mediterranean.Naval Operations:East Indies?Pacific.Military Operations :Russia.Burma.Pacific.2      Attacks by Rockets and Flying Bombs     ........      ....      728      Foreign Affairs...........................      72Poland.4      Message Circulated to the Troops in Greece      ........      725      General Election       ........   .....      ........      ....      73Release of Candidates and Agents.6      Coal      ....................      ....      ....      ....      74Distribution in the. London Are&apos;a.
Naval, Militaryand AllOperations.(previous reference:W.M.(45)7thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Mediterranean.naval operations.Bast Indies.Pacific.MilitaryOperations.Russia.Burma.Pacific.1. ThcVicerChiefs of Staff reported the principal events ofthe previous week.Bomber Command had flown 1,500 sorties and had attackedCologne marshalling yards, Duisburg, Gelsenkirchen and Stuttgart.Mosquitoes had attacked Berlin on the previous night.United States bombers had flown 1,400 sorties for the loss of29 aircraft and had attacked communications and fuel targets.The Allied Expeditionary Air Force had flown 11,000 sorties.They claimed to have destroyed 4,300 motor vehieles, 99 locomotives,1,400 road and rail cars and 200 tanks and fighting vehicles.Sixty-four enemy aircraft (including 15 on the ground) had been destroyed as against Allied losses of 13 bombers and 66 fighters and fighter-bombers.Bad weather had again interfered with, air operations. 6,300sorties had been flown and 970 tons of bombs dropped. Allied losses had been 76 aircraft.Shipping losses from enemy action for the week amounted to3,964 tons. The total shipping losses from enemy action for january so far amounted to 67,181 tons.U-boat activity continued in the Irish Sea. One U-boat hadbeen sunk and one possibly sunk.On the morning of the 28th January H.M.S- Diadem and h.M.S. Mauritius intercepted and engaged a force of three enemy destroyers north-west of Bergen. The enemy retired at high speedbut several hits were observed on each destroyer.On the 24th January carr,ier-borne aircraft had successfully attacked oil refineries at Palembang in Sumatra. Thirteen enemy aircraft had been shot down in combat and 34 were claimed to havebeen destroyed on the ground.Formosa had been under almost continuous attack during theweek by shore-based and carrier-borne aircraft. considerable damage had been caused and a large number of enemy aircraft destroyed or damaged.On the Western front a French attack west of Mulhouse and north of Colmar had made little progress. On the 25th january the enemy had made a strong attack north of Strasbourg, but a vigorous counter-attack by the Americans had resulted in theoriginal line being restored. On the previous day United states forces had attacked north-east of St. Vith, meeting stubbornresistance.In the north the Russians were reported to be within 4 miles of Konigsberg. The thrust north of Warsaw had now reached theBaltic and Russian forces&apos;were within 30 miles of Danzig. It was estimated that 15 German divisions were hemmed in between Danzigand Konigsberg. The Russian attack west of Warsaw had reachedthe old German-Polish frontier. Enemy forces in Toruh and Posenwere still holding out. North and south of Breslau the Oder hadbeen reached. The average Russian advance since the commence-ment of the offensive was 16 miles a day.The Russian claims for German casualties were 86,000 prisoners and 300,000 killed.Our forces on Ramree Island had advanced some 25 miles. Onthe 26th January the Royal Marines had also landed on ChedubaIsland. In the Akyab area Myohaung had been captured and the advance continued for some 25 miles. In Central Burma our forces had advanced east and south-east of Gangaw. Monywa had alsobeen captured. In North Burma our forces were within 18 miles of Mong Mit.Substantial gains had been made by American forces in the island of Luzon and patrols were now within 40 miles of Manila.The War Cabinet-Took note of these statements.[29426-1]
Attacks by 2.   The Home Secretary and Minister of Home SecurityRockets and informed the War Cabinet that during the previous week there hadFlying Bombs, been 52 incidents from long-range rockets: 33 in London, 15 in(Previous Essex, 2 in Kent,, 1 in Hertfordshire and 1 in the sea off Claeton.Reference: This represented a slight increase in activity compared with theW.M.(45)7th week before.Conclusions, No flying-bomb incidents had been reported.Minute 2.) The casualties for the week had been 123 killed and 448seriously injured.The Prime Minister suggested that there would be advantage in including in the periodic report to the War Cabinet figures ofslightly injured and missing. Their propaganda value in the UnitedStates was great.        . .The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security undertook to make the necessary arrangements.The War Cabinet-Took note of the statement by the Home Secretary and minister of Home Security.Foreign Affairs.Poland.(previous reference:W.M.(45)7thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Minister of State informed the War Cabinet that the czechoslovak Government were now likely, as a result of represen-tations from the Soviet Government, to recognise the LublinCommittee the following day as the Government of Poland.A discussion followed, a record of which is contained in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet-Took note of the Minister of State&apos;s statement.Circulated tothe Troops in greece.(previous reference:W.M.(45)lstConclusions&apos;,Minute 8.)   -4. At their meeting on the 2nd January, 1945, the WarCabinet had set up a Committee consisting of the Minister ofLabour and National Service (Chairman), the Minister of Produc-tion and the Minister of Aircraft Production, to establish the factsabout the source of the Reuter message, dated the 13th December,1944, containing an article about Greece by Mr. A. J. Cummings,and to report on the circumstances in which, and the approvalsubject to which, the message was transmitted to Athens and theredistributed to the troops.The War Cabinet now had before them a report by theCommittee (W.P. (45) 63). The Committee reported that the source of the message in question was Reuter&apos;s Overseas Serviceand that it had not been transmitted in Reuter&apos;s special service of news for the troops. It had been picked up by the Anglo-GreekInformation Service and included in their Basic News File, whichwas ordinarily distributed to all main departments of Headquarters.Responsibility for its appearance in the News File rested with theAnglo-Greek Information Service, subject to their control byGeneral Scobie. . Responsibility for, the circulation of particular items in the News File to the troops rested with the senior officers,who in the discretion given them decided to circulate the article.The article had come to General Scobie&apos;s notice, but he had decided on consideration that, since censorship of an item of this type was bound to be noticed, its suppression might, through repercussionsat home, do more harm than its publication to the troops.The Committee recommended that in future the decision asto the circulation or distribution of such material in areas wheredifficult political problems were likely to arise should rest with theproperly constituted Committee under the Commander-in-Chief,e.g., in Athens the Press and Information Committee, and not withsenior officers in the field.
GeneralEjection.Release ofCandidatesand Agents.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 164thConclusions,Minutes 5and 6.)The Minister of Labour and National Service said that theCommittee&apos;s report established the facts. The War Office had notbeen responsible for the issue of this message, and the committee felt strongly that a responsible body should be set up which should recommend whether a particular item should be made available tothe troops or not, and that this responsibility should not be left onthe Commander-in-Chief or on Commanding Officers, who had other and quite different duties. Arrangements of this nature might wellbe of material importance as we advanced into the Continent.After a brief discussion, the War Cabinet -Approved the proposals in paragraph 8 (g) of the reportof the Committee, as set out at &quot; X &quot; above, and invited theSecretary of State for War to arrange for the issue of thenecessary instructions.5. At their meeting on the 11th December the War cabinet had invited the Minister of Labour and National Service to submitrevised proposals on the matters dealt with in the Annex toW.P. (44) 645.The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Labour and National Service (W.P. (45) 65) submittingrevised proposals, which had been worked out in consultation withthe Service Ministers, the Chief Whip and representatives of thefour main Party organisations.It was proposed that, subject to overriding military considera-tions, potential candidates serving in the Forces should be grantedfacilities to enable them to appear before selection committees andthat adopted candidates should be temporarily released in adequatetime before the Election. There should be early release from theForces, the Civil Defence Services and industry of recognised agentsor organisers and of key staff of headquarters and regional offices of political parties. Persons who had been part-time or honoraryagents should be released from the Forces or the Civil defence services if they were required as full-time agents. Persons whohad not been agents before should not, however, be released from theForces or Civil Defence Services, and former constituency agentsnow wanted for headquarters and regional offices should not be eligible for release unless they were posted at home and could easily be spared.&apos; These restrictions should not necessarily apply to therelease from industry of persons who were required for full-timeemployment.In dealing with applications for the grant of facilities to candidates and for the release of agents, organisers and officials,the Ministry of Labour would, so far as the four main political parties were concerned, be assisted by a small committee consistingof representatives of the four main Party organisations. The samerules would apply in the case of the small Parties and of independent candidates, but the Ministry of Labour would have todecide these cases without the assistance of the proposed committee.If the proposals set out in the Annex to WP. (45) 65 were approved, the Minister of Labour and National Service would announce them at an early date in the House of Commons.  -The following points arose in discussion : (a) The Minister of Labour and National Service confirmed that the intention of the suggestion which he had made inparagraph 3 of WP. (45) 65 was that when the proposals had been announced it would be open to the Parties to send in applicationsfor releases and that, as soon as any particular application had beenapproved by the proposed machinery, the release should be granted.(b) In reply to a suggestion that adopted candidates should beallowed to claim their release from the Forces at any time from now onwards, the Secretary of State for Air said that difficulties would arise if adopted candidates occupying key positions in the RoyalAir Force had to be released a long time in advance of the General
Election and before the end of the war in Europe. He thought that adopted candidates should be enabled to claim their release fromthe date of the announcement of the Dissolution of Parliament.The general view of the War Cabinet was that, while a finaldecision as to the date on which adopted candidates should be released might be deferred for a few weeks, it was desirable thatcandidates should, subject to overriding military considerations, be released in good time.(c) The First Lord of the Admiralty pointed out that certainclasses of industrial Civil Servants were not required to resign eventhough they had stood as candidates at an election. If-the conditionsin paragraph 12 of the Annex to W.P. (45) 65 were applied to these classes there would be complaints.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that the classesreferred to were not at present covered by the Servants of the Crown(Parliamentary Candidates) Order, 1927, and that their positionwould not be altered. This should be made clear in the proposed announcement.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed to resume consideration in two or three weeks&apos; timeof the question of the date at which adopted candidatesshould be released. .(2) Subject to (1). approved the proposals set out in the annex to W.P. (45) 65.Coal. 6.   The Prime Minister said that all possible steps should beDistribution taken to assist the Minister of Fuel and Power in dealing with thein the London problem of coal distribution in the London area, particularly byArea. the loan of labour and transport from the Services.   The Secretaryof State for War and the Secretary of State for Air were alreadyproviding help, and the General Officer Commanding, Anti-aircraft command, had informed him that men from the Anti-aircraft command could be made available, should they be required. Theproblem must be tackled vigorously, and, if it were necessary tomake any statement in Parliament on the subject, the statement should bring out the positive action which the Government were taking.His attention had been drawn to a newsreel in which the handling of the coal distribution problem appeared to be unfairlycriticised; and he would be glad if the Minister of information would look into this matter.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed that all possible steps should be taken to assist theMinister of Fuel and Power in dealing with the problemof coal distribution in the London area.(2) Took note that the Minister of Information would enquire into the circumstances in which the newsreel referredto by the Prime Minister had been produced.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,2$th January, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
