<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/49/0 images: 53-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentoPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1952TOP secret copy No.C. (52) 819th January, 1952CABINETTHE ECONOMIC situation memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer at their meeting on 17th January (C.C. (52) 4th Conclusions, Minute 3), theCabinet decided to examine on Tuesday, 22nd January, the economic and financial measures which I would recommend to them. These are contained in this and in another paper which I am circulating to my colleagues. I put these proposalsforward on my own responsibility, but most of them owe their origin to and havealready been approved by the Sub-Committee on the Economic Situation.2. Since the Sub-Committee&apos;s first report was submitted it has become increasingly clear that we are facing a balance of payments crisis of major dimen-sions. The rate of loss of gold and dollars is continuing and it now seems certainthat, even taking into account the aid which we have been promised from theUnited States, the reserves will have fallen to  500 million by the end of June that is, the level at which they stood at the time of devaluation in September .1949.It is quite clear that only the most powerful and convincing action can prevent a major calamity for sterling.3. Discussions have been proceeding between the Commonwealth finance ministers in order to get effective and co-ordinated action throughout the whole ofthe sterling area to stop the rot. I am circulating a further paper on this.4. This paper deals with internal action in the field of investment, consump-tion and Government expenditure. This action is all of decisive importance fordealing with the balance of payments crisis. This is for two reasons:  (i) The balance of payments crisis is at bottom due to our failure and thefailure of the other sterling area countries to develop earning powerto the extent required to pay for the imports we need. The increase ofour earning power is fundamental and this requires that our exports should be competitive and our industry flexible. Over a wide range of our exports we are becoming uncompetitive and we canbuild our exports only if our industry has the load for home demandtaken off it and is placed in a position in which is must compete forexport business in order to survive. This state of affairs can be createdonly by resolute action to reduce the internal load upon our economy.(ii) There is a general feeling abroad that the United Kingdom economy is&quot; soft.&quot; There will be no return of confidence in sterling until it isshown beyond any doubt that there is a major change in the direction ofour economy and that we are hardening ourselves to deal with ourcrisis.5. To expand our earning power to the necessary extent, and in quickenough time, is a formidable task. Our exports to North America, and indeedto the whole of the world outside the sterling Commonwealth, fall a long wayshort of our needs; and we are tending to lose ground in the markets which are open to competition.
26. Furthermore, the make-up of our export trade, and the opportunities for .expansion of sales in the different parts of it, adds particular problems to theftask. Broadly speaking, one-fifth of our exports consist of industrial materials,including semi-manufactures (such items as iron and steel, coal, cement, chemicals,non-ferrous metals); three-fifths of miscellaneous consumer goods (notably textiles,motor cars, bicycles, leather and rubber manufactures); and one-fifth of capital goods properly so called. It will clearly be difficult for us in the present circum-stances of stringency to expand the first class at all substantially: the bulk of the items in the second class have now to face a buyers&apos; market almost everywhere:the third group represents the only one for which a large unsatisfied demandstill exists in export markets. It follows that if the total increase needed had to be concentrated in that particular sector an expansion of as much as 25 per cent,would be necessary. That is, of course, an over-simplication: some expansion in exports in the first two classes will undoubtedly prove possible, though this may involve some difficult decisions of policy in certain fields (e.g., in respect of suchmaterials as coal, cement, &amp;c). In general, however, it is clear that a substantialexpansion in exports can only be achieved in engineering goods, particularly inthe sector of capital goods with all that that implies in terms of steel availabilityand the concentration of our engineering resources on the export field.7. Paragraphs 8-13 below set out the proposals in brief, and the Annexes tothis paper give them in more detail. They should be read against the background of the rearmament programme. My colleagues are aware of the latest position on this from the memoranda which have been circulated and which were approvedby the Cabinet on 14th January (C. (52) 4 and 5 and C.C. (52) 3rd Conclusions,Minute 2). The measures taken to spread the programme over a longer period will be one of the factors helping our recovery.8. The most urgent and the most important of the problems facing us is thatof coal. We must rapidly increase our production for many reasons: it is needed to provide an adequate basis for our own industry; it is needed as a direct export;and in the eyes both of America and Europe the solution of this problem is a touch-stone of our ability to handle our own affairs.9. The most promising source of increased exports is in the engineering and metal-using industries. The additional steel we now hope to get from the UnitedStates will permit of an expansion of output in the later part of this year. but even after some slowing down of the defence programme these industries will haveto bear this year an increased load of defence production, so that, but for this,additional steel, exports from these industries would have fallen. The extra steelwill enable this fall in exports to be off-set and produce some net increase in thecurrent year. It will, moreover, provide a firm base for a much higher volume of exports next year. Quicker results cannot be expected because the bulk of theAmerican steel will not arrive until the second half of this year and capital goodstake a long time to make. We must make reductions in investment in plant and machinery (see Annex I) and in durable consumer goods (see Annex II) to set freeresources for export.10. The reduction in industrial building (of which further mention is madein Annex I) will reduce the demand for building steel, and for machinery whichwould have been needed if the programme had been maintained. It will also enabledefence works, and the provision of new houses, to be increased within the presentsize of the building industry. Proposals for settling the outstanding points arenow being put to the Economic Policy Committee.11. The President of the Board of Trade proposes certain restrictions onhire-purchase, of which an account is given in Annex III. This will have the effectof reducing home demand for certain types of product. The details of his proposals are about to be considered by the Economic Policy Committee.12. In Part I of the Confidential Annex* will be found details of the reform of purchase tax and Utility which we recommended in our earlier Report (para-graphs 23 and 24 of C. (51) 48).13. The remaining measures are reductions in Government expenditure,which can only be achieved at the cost of considerable sacrifice, Our proposals are contained in Annex IV.  Their purpose is to reduce the demand made by the* The circulation of the Confidential Annex has been restricted.
Government itself on our resources, and thus contribute towards the general free-(y of our economy from the excess of demand, which is drawing in too manyimports and holding back goods we ought to be exporting.14. In paragraph 39 of C. (51) 48 the Sub-Committee refer to a possible white paper on the wage-price problem which the Minister of Labour and National Ser-vice and I are preparing. We will consult our colleagues as to the general lines which it would take. Meanwhile I would ask my colleagues&apos; agreement to myreferring to it during the Debate as something which will shortly be issued.15. All these measures, in addition to those taken already by import cuts andby our new monetary policy, and those to be announced in the Budget, form partof a general policy. They will not be fully effective except in combination, andthey must therefore be considered as. a whole. We cannot force other countries&quot;to buy our goods, nor can we force our own manufacturers through detailed controlsto export them. But by reducing home demand by the Government, the investor,and the consumer, we can create the climate which is necessary if our exports areto be expanded. Our exporters will still have to make use of the resources we shall make available to them but unless the resources are made available, their taskwill be impossible. If they cannot carry it out, we shall have to reduce our imports to match our income, with disastrous results to production, employment and food supplies.R. A. B.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1.\9th January, 1952.
ANNEX ITHE INVESTMENT programme a. Building Work. The recommendations of the Investment programmes committee for 1952, after taking into account the increase in the housing pro-gramme approved by Ministers, would give a programme of new building workfor civil purposes about 5 - 5 per cent, less than was done in 1950. If defence new building work is taken into account, the programme will be 3 per cent, more thanin 1950, and 7 per cent, more than in 1951. This programme of new building work is, however, about  45 million more than could be achieved with the steel suppliesunder the current level of steel allocation, unless, the requirements of building steelhave been much overstated. The building programme, therefore, allows room forthe transfer of resources from steel using building work to types of work which useless steel. There is a number of claims for increases on the civil programmes onwhich decisions have yet to be taken. Effect will be given to the decisions throughthe control of building licences.B. Plant and Machinery. The objective set was to reduce investment in plant,machinery and vehicles, in 1952 by  100 million below the level achieved in 1950.Compared with that year there is, however, a net increase in the investment in plant and machinery in the fuel and power group of programmes, and also for defence purposes. With the exception of a saving on shipbuilding, due to reduced suppliesof steel, no other large savings can be made in the controlled sectors. The Invest-ment Programmes Committee, therefore, proposed that the reduction should besought in the following fields: -   milHonat end 1951 pricesPublic    service    and   commercial    goodsvehiclesPassenger cars............Agricultural machinery.........Manufacturing industry        ......Miscellaneous plant and machinery ...		1952 as a		percentage1950	1952	of 1950132	75	57128	59	4654	37	68310	271	8770	61	87694	503	73461	462	10018	105	5831,173	1,070	91Sub-totalOther civil programmes       .........Plant and machinery for defence purposes ...Total:The entire reduction has, therefore, to be found from the five items in the upperpart of the table, on which substantial reductions have to be made. These will not come about unless the necessary measures are taken. No single measure has beenfound which will achieve these reductions. An elaborate system of direct physicalcontrol is not practicable. A combination of measures is, therefore, the only course.The following could be used for this purpose:  (a) Discussion and agreement with industry to raise the level of exports by voluntary action reinforced by a declared intention to discriminate inthe distribution of scarce materials in favour of firms with a risingexport performance. This would be the intensification of a well known and well understood procedure.(b) Limitation of supplies to the home market by statutory orders in exceptional cases.(c) Tightening up of credit policy.- Of these, (c) is already in operation; it is suggested that1 (b) should be appliedto parts of the capital goods field to reinforce the measures under (a), (a) willhave to be restated in vigorous form, and applied sternly through the steel alloca-tions. The proposals do, however, involve the possibility of a reduction in thetotal output of cars and commercial vehicles, because it is probable that exports ofthese cannot be much increased.One further expedient is discussed in Part II of the Confidential Annex.** The circulation of the Confidential Annex has been restricted.
ANNEX IIDURABLE CONSUMER GOODSThe Cabinet approved on 21st December a recomendation put forward inour first report (paragraph 27 of C (51) 48) that the level of production of consumer goods for the home market by the metal-using industries should be cut by  60million a year at 1950 prices.2. The stringency in steel supplies has meant that allocations to industriesproducing metal consumer goods have had to be put at a very low level for thefirst quarter of 1952. It is calculated that, on the basis of such a level of steelallocations, the production of these industries for the home market will be reducedby an amount in excess of the  60 million figure postulated by the Cabinet something like  80 million a year at 1951 prices or, say,  72 million at 1950 prices.And it appears most unlikely that, even taking into account the increase in steelsupplies which we may now expect from the United States, it will be possible,given the scale of other urgent demands for additional steel, to increase the alloca-tion of steel to these particular industries to a point which would mean a reductionin production for the home market of less than the  60 million target.3. We shall rely on voluntary arrangements with industry to devote to exportsan adequate proportion of their output. This is likely to succeed, but if it failsexceptionally, we may have to impose statutory limitations on supplies for thehome market.ANNEX IIIHIRE PURCHASE1. As part of the policy of agreed restrictions of credit the Capital IssuesCommittee are withholding permission for the raising of money for hire purchasebusiness, and the clearing banks are restricting and will restrict further the financewhich they make available for that purpose. These limitations of credit do not,however, affect those suppliers who are able to finance hire purchase operationsout of their own resources.2. Hire purchase transactions in certain goods are already regulated by aBoard of Trade Order. But this Order applies only to price-controlled goods (andnot, therefore, to goods like radio and television sets) and is not intended to restrict the volume of hire purchase business. Inasmuch as a range of metal-using consumer goods can be obtained in hire purchase, often on very easy terms, it is recommendedthat, as a complement to the other measures which are being taken to make creditrestriction more effective and to divert resources from home consumption and investment, restrictions should be placed by means of a Board of TradeOrder on hire purchase transactions in respect of goods such as motor vehicles,bicycles, radio and television sets, electrically operated domestic appliances andapparatus (e.g., vacuum cleaners, polishers, immersion heaters, refrigerators)and office furniture. For all these goods fairly stringent terms, namely a minimuminitial deposit of 33^ per cent, of the cash price and a maximum repayment periodof eighteen months will be prescribed; at present most transactions take place on terms of a deposit of 20-30 per cent, and a repayment period of eighteen months to three years.3. It is not proposed that any additional restrictions should be placed onthe hire purchase of goods like domestic furniture, cookers and perambulators.4. This proposal will not involve legislation; the necessary restriction can be imposed by Order. This would be published On the day following any statement in the House and in order to avoid forestalling it would come into force at once.
ANNEX IVCIVIL expenditure the general policy which the Cabinet approved (C.C. (51) 19th Conclusions,Minute 3) is that purely civil expenditure should be reduced substantially below thefigure for 1951-52. This, would still leave the total of Civil Estimates (which contain a good many defence and semi-defence items) well above last year&apos;s figure and would contribute nothing to meet the inevitable increase in Service Estimates.On the other hand, costs will be higher next year than this by about 10 per cent.;expenditure over the range of civilian expenditure has been increasing over recentyears by something approaching  100 million a year, in spite of strong efforts to check it; it is therefore not a negligible achievement to keep it steady.2. The figures in the table at the end of this paragraph show how far we aretowards attaining this result. The first two columns correspond to those in para-graph 34 of the Sub-Committee&apos;s Report (C.C. (51) 48), subject to some adjustmentswhich have been made to give a truer picture. The first column shows the revised estimates for 1951-52. The second column shows what expenditure would be inthis field, if there had been no change in policy (except so far, of course, asDepartments had already taken account of projected economies in their first sub-missions to the Treasury of next year&apos;s estimates). The third column shows, notthe final figures these cannot be given at a moment when the scrutiny of estimates in the Treasury is in full swing , but the latest estimate available. The figures forthe National Health Service and education take account of the important proposals made below on those services. The remaining figures take account of as muchpruning of the estimates as the Treasury has already done, but it must be realised that allowance has had to be made not only for decreases but for some importantincreases: for example, the increase by about  15 million of Civil Service pay dueto the recent agreement between the Treasury and the Staff Side. The economiessecured are therefore appreciably greater than the net difference of figures would suggest.Table( millions)	1951-52	1952-53		Revised	Before	Latest	Estimates	Cuts	StateNational Health Service  ......	398	415	389Education   ...      .........	228	251	235Other Social Services	418	437	437All Social Services.........	1,044	1,103	1,061Food subsidies      .........	410	410	410Other services	460	454	449Total Social and Administrative ...	1,914	1,967	1,9203. These results cannot be obtained without important measures affecting thesocial services for which we wish to ask our colleagues&apos; specific approval. Forthe rest it is sufficient to draw their attention to the work which has been done,both by Departmental Ministers (who have made great efforts on their own account to secure economy) and by the Treasury. Examples are the Estimates of theMinistry of Works which show a decrease in every Vote compared to last year;a saving of  1 - 2 million on Information Services as a result of an enquiry conducted by the Lord Privy Seal; and a decrease in the numbers of the Civil Service of about10,000, which should be accomplished during the next six months, to be followedby a further decrease of 10,000 to 15,000 over the following six months, if thenecessary restrictions of services can be accepted.4. The important measures which I propose concern the National health service and education.
^111   5.   The following additional charges in the National Health Service are pro-posed (aiming at the savings shown in a full year&apos;s operations:(a) A charge of Is. for each prescription form      ......- (b) Charge for certain hospital appliances.........(c) A charge under the General Dental Service of  1 (or thefull cost if less) for all treatment other than dentures(for which a charge is already made), except that nocharge would be made to children and expectant ornursing mothers ...      ...      ...      ...    -n...(d) Increased charges for &quot; amenity &quot; beds in hospital(e) A new power to local health authorities to charge for theuse of day nurseries having regard to the means of the parents   .........    &quot;......      ......Total of increased charges.........A further reduction in the cost of the service, not by way of economy or increase of income fromcharges, but by increase of general revenue, can besecured by an increase of 2d. per insured person inthe contribution towards the cost of the national health Service made by the National Insurance Fund,to be met by an increase of 2d. in the employee^ shareof the stamp     ............total. Legislation will be required for all these proposals, except for the charge on prescriptions for non-hospital patients and the increased charges for amenitybeds. As my colleagues know, the proposal is that a Bill should be introducedimmediately after the announcement and passed as quickly as possible in orderboth to secure the most revenue from the charges and to reduce the amount of forestalling. By this means we should not be far short of obtaining a full year&apos;revenue in 1952-53 from all the charges; but only two-thirds of a year&apos;s revenue from the increased contribution from the National Insurance Fund, since it takeslonger to make the new stamps available and the danger of forestalling is not present.7. Special arrangements will be necessary to provide for refund or exemption of the charges payable by the recipients of National Assistance, War Pensioners and(in the case of the Dental Service) by children and expectant or nursing mothers.Suitable arrangements are being worked out.8.   As regards education, we propose the following economies:  England and Wales  million(a) 5 per cent, reduction in estimated L.E.A. expenditure (MainGrant services)       ..................       8-5(b) Reduction in the administrative costs of the School MealsService .....................       0-5(c) Reassessment of the provision for the payment of balances of grant to L.E.A.&apos;s for the current and earlier years       ...       3-0(d) Reassessment of the estimated liability for teachers&apos; pensionpayments      .....................       0-8(e) Reduction in direct grants and other charges in the Ministry&apos;s-   Estimates      ......       .....      .........       2-0Total (England and Wales)    ......      ...      14-scotland(/) Goschen proportion of above......      .........       2-212,000,000500,0007,000.000250,000500,00020,250,0009,000,00029,250,000Total (England, Wales and Scotland)17-0
9. The most important item here is the 5 per cent, reduction in estimate. /expenditure by the Local Education Authorities. The Minister sent out a circularsome time ago asking them to frame their estimates accordingly and she hopes toget good results from it. The reduction in the cost of the School Meals Service willbe obtained by economies in administration. The Minister hopes to increase this figure later in the year. In view of this we decided against an increase in thecharge for School Meals, although the price of food alone has gone up by aboutId. per meal since the Labour Government increased the charge, and overheadshave also gone up by about Id. a meal. If the Minister finds it impossible to reduceoverheads any further, or if the price of food goes up again, we recommend that thepossibility of increasing the charge should be reconsidered. Items (c) to (e) are tech-nical adjustments or the accumulation of various minor savings. Under the&quot; Goschen &quot; formula Scottish expense on Education is, by Statute, a regular pro-portion of English expenditure.10. We have considered whether to legislate to increase the rate of contribu-tion for teachers&apos; superannuation, since the Scheme is now in deficit. We think thepresent moment (when a further claim by the teachers is before the Burnham Com-mittee) to be inopportune for taking this action, but the Ministers concerned will raise the matter again later in the year. Meanwhile we can take credit for no savingunder this head.11. I should mention an important saving by the Minister of Education whichdoes not appear on the face of the Budget. She proposes to cut her investment programme over the next seven years by about  90 million. She will do thismainly by using secondary schools for a larger number of children and by increasingthe age at which children transfer from primary to secondary schools. TheSecretary of State for Scotland proposes to take corresponding, though notidentical, measures.  7 - 5 million of the saving for the two countries will accrue in1952-53. As school building is met by advances from the Local Loans Fund, whichare over a long period of years repaid with the help of Exchequer grant over theperiod of the repayment, this saving appears &quot; below the line &quot; and not in Estimates:but it is none the less welcome for that.
Th CONFIDENTIAL ANNEXPart IPURCHASE TAX AND UTILITYAt present almost all Utility goods are free of Purchase tax. This means thatthere is little manufacture of goods immediately above top Utility in untaxed value,resulting in a gap in production (the &quot; blind spot&quot;) and harm to exports. It alsomeans discrimination against imported goods of Utility type, which pay fullPurchase tax, and we have been strongly attacked for this at meetings of G.A.T.T.2. The Douglas Committee was set up last summer to examine these problems and it has now reported recommending a D Scheme. This Scheme would replace the automatic exemption from Purchase tax of Utility goods by a tax-free deduction(D) to be made from the wholesale value of all goods, Utility or not, in thoseclasses but only in those classes where Utility schemes exist (i.e., textiles, clothing,footwear and furniture). Tax at existing standard rates would be charged on that part of the wholesale value which exceeds D. There would be different D&apos;s for different types of article such as shirts, suits, vests, &amp;c. Legislation would be neces-sary on Finance Bill lines.3. This scheme would solve the import problem, as imported goods wouldhave equal benefit from the tax-free deduction; and it would remove the &quot;blindspot &quot; by providing a gently graduated rate of tax in place of the present jump fromtax-free top Utility to fully-taxed non-Utility.   I therefore recommend its adoption.4. Although the normal place for such legislation would be the Budget and finance Bill, there are compelling reasons for dealing with it earlier. A major factor in the present textile recession is uncertainty about possible Purchase-taxchanges. Removal of the blind spot is the only immediate help we can give totextile exports and we should give it at once. It is now generally assumed that theDouglas. Report has been received, and intelligent guesses have appeared in thepress as to its contents; pressure to publish it as soon as the House reassembles willbe very great. Publication must be quickly followed by action, otherwise therewould be serious dislocation in industry. I therefore recommend publication of theReport on about the 2nd February, the necessary Ways and Means Resolution inthe House of Commons about ten days later, the scheme to come into effect a fewdays after that, and the Bill to be introduced and passed into law before Easter.5.   A few special points about the D Scheme need mentioning (i) D&apos;s will be so fixed as broadly to maintain existing revenue.  This will be substantially achieved if D is set, in each group, in such a way that50 per cent, of the transactions in that group are tax free.(ii) Although more expensive Utility goods will bear some small tax, theeffect on the cost of living will probably be negligible since the purchases of working-class families are almost wholly in the lower Utility gradeswhich will remain tax free.(iii) The future of Utility itself is being separately considered by the Presidentof the Board of Trade. If, as seems by no means improbable, Utilityas we know it disappears, the D principle must still, for revenue reasons,be confined strictly to the field where Utility previously existed.(iv) Standard rates of Purchase-tax will remain the same as at present forthe purposes of the D Scheme, although the introduction of the scheme would not prevent their being altered, or the whole Purchase-tax systembeing revised and broadened, for other reasons, in the future.(v) For special reasons the Scheme will not initially be applied to furniture.But powers will be taken to extend it to furniture after discussion withthe furniture trade.(vi) In grouping articles for separate D&apos;s, we must try and avoid, except inthe case of wool, having different sets of groups for articles made ofcloth of different fibres. But linen is a special case, since, if groupedwith cotton articles, all linen articles would be taxed, and NorthernIreland has a special interest in this. The question is being discussed with the Government of Northern Ireland.
Part II OFISCAL MEASURES TO CONTROL INVESTMENT IN PLANT ANDMACHINERYVarious ways of restricting investment in plant and machinery by fiscal meanshave been considered. The only one which is practicable and not open toinsuperable objections would be the suspension of the Income Tax DepreciationAllowances on new purchases of plant and machinery for, say, the next threeyears, on lines recently followed by the Canadian Government. Although, by itself, this would have only a modest effect, it would be a clear earnest of theGovernments intentions, and, in conjunction with the other measures proposed,we think it would be of real value in present circumstances.2. The suspension of the allowances would have to be operated on a non-discriminatory basis, both on administrative grounds the Inland Revenue havenot the staff to operate a discriminatory scheme-and because once discriminationwere admitted in one case, it would lead to pressure for discrimination elsewhere,and the effect of the measure would largely be lost.3. Obviously the suspension of the allowances would be criticised by industry on various grounds, e.g., that it was imposing an additional burden on the defence effort, on export industries, on shipping, oil and other British enterprises operatingoverseas, and that it was a breach of the accepted principle that industry should only be taxed on its true profits, computed after allowance of the full costs incurred in earning the profits, including depreciation costs. This principle was recentlyreaffirmed by the Tucker Committee.4.   The proposal could be announced in February to operate from 6th Aprilnext, the same date as applies for the suspension of the initial allowance.

</content>
</cab>
