<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/49/0 images: 111-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1952CONFIDENTIALCopy No.C. (52) 231th February, 1952CABINETPOLITICAL SITUATION IN THE GERMAN FEDERAL republic memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs my colleagues may like to have the following brief review of certain long-terminternal trends in Germany, of which account must be taken in entering into theproposed new contractual relationship with Germany.After the Federal elections of 1949 the Christian Democrats and the social democrats each held about one-third of the seats in the Lower House. hopes that they might form a stable coalition proved vain, largely owing to the clash ofpersonalities between Adenauer and Schumacher. The parties forming the Govern-ment (the Christian Democrats in association with two moderate Right-wing parties,the Free Democratic Party and German Party) hold just over half the seats.Since the Christian Democratic Party is itself a heterogeneous grouping,Dr. Adenauer&apos;s internal policy has necessarily been one of compromise. Con-cessions to the views of his Right-wing coalition partners have partially alienatedthe Left wing of his own party, which would prefer compromise with the social democrats. The instability of the Government has been increased by the losses of the Christian Democrats in the Land (Provincial) elections since 1949 and bythe emergence of the Refugee Party, of the semi-Nazi Socialist Reich Party andof the League of German Soldiers.The Refugee Party has won marked successes in those States with numerousrefugees. It is a pressure group representing the dispossessed, especially those fromthe eastern territories, and a focus for unhealthy nationalist and irredentist tenden-cies. The political moderation it has so far shown might cease if economic improve-ment were checked.The Socialist Reich Party gained over 350,000 votes in the Lower SaxonyLand elections in May 1951, becoming a possible focus for the disunited extremeRight-wing splinter parties. By playing down its extremism the party hasstrengthened its position. Although the Federal Government has petitioned theConstitutional Court to ban it (and also the small Communist Party), somerespectable parties, including Dr. Adenauer&apos;s coalition partners, are tending insome districts to regard it as a possible ally.The League of German Soldiers, a roof organisation for various ex-soldiers&apos;associations, was created in November 1951; it is at the moment dominated bya group of extreme Right-wing nationalists. The moderate Right-wing parties hope to have a moderating influence on the League, but it is equally likely that theinfluence of the League will work in favour of the extremists in these parties.The tendency of Dr. Adenauer&apos;s coalition partners to be pulled graduallyfurther towards the Right, subjects the Government to increasing strain.Dr. Adenauer&apos;s unique influence has so far held it together, but as the next Federalelections in July 1953 approach, the chances of reconstituting the present coalitiondiminish and the risk of its replacement by a less acceptable Government increases.Analyses of recent Land elections suggest that, if present trends are maintained,the Christian Democrats would be able to form an effective majority government after the next Federal elections only by extending the present coalition to includeeither some near-Nazi groups or the Refugee Party or both. The Social Democratswould not at present seem able to form a Government even with the Refugee Party,41829
but, if present trends were intensified, might be able to do so in 1953.  Aftes^.autumn 1953 we may. therefore be faced either with a Government including t!v J,extreme Right or with a Social Democratic Party Government. There is fortunatelylittle prospect of the Communists strengthening their weak position.The situation is thus not without its dangers, more especially as there are no obvious leaders in sight capable of taking over from either Adenauer or Schumacher,whose personalities now dominate German politics. We are no longer in a positionto influence events by direct intervention. But there are important factors whichshould mitigate the dangers.The present danger signs are for the most part restricted to a few mainly agri-cultural areas. The presence of large numbers of allied troops is a stabilisinginfluence. The economy is still expanding and would be further stimulated by adecision to allow some defence production. The integration of Germany into theWestern community, if successfully carried forward, should strengthen the respon-sible and moderate elements. The trade unions have shown themselves a stableelement and have remained independent of the Social Democratic Party. Alliededucational activities if maintained on an adequate scale can still have a healthyeffect. Above all the continued division of Germany and the presence of soviet troops on the Elbe should make for restraint and common sense.A. E.Foreign Office, SWA,1th February, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
