<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/49/0 images: 145-148</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  February 1952SECRETC. (52) 33Uth February, 1952CABINETTHE FINANCIAL SITUATION OF THE STERLING area memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer circulate for the information of my colleagues a telegram which I have sentto Commonwealth Finance Ministers in order to keep them informed of currentdevelopments. I propose to send them a telegram each month and I shall circulatethese to the Cabinet. I draw special attention to paragraphs 11 and 12.R. A. B.Treasury Chamber, S.W. I,Uth February, 1952.Message from the Chancellor of the Exchequer to Commonwealth FinanceMinisters1. When we met in London recently we were able to exchange information ina most helpful way about the balance of payments position of the sterling area asa whole and of individual sterling area countries. In the present critical phase Ithink it would be a good thing if I were to follow this up by sending you a periodicalreport giving the most up-to-date information about the course of events, in par-ticular about the movement of the gold and dollar deficit and of the central reserves.At the same time I shall also try to say how I view our prospects in the fairly nearfuture. We shall in this way maintain close and continuous contact and I hope thatyou for your part will be able to let me have your views both on the progress ofyour own affairs and on the general problem that confronts us all.2. . The present message is therefore the first of these reports and refers mainly to developments during January.3. In January the gold and dollar deficit amounted to $297 million. this compares with $372 million in December (or $196 million excluding $176 millionservice on the North American loans), $240 million in November and $320 million inOctober, which was, of course, a month of exceptional pressure.4. Receipts from E.R.P. are now negligible. This means that the reservesfell in January by the full extent of the deficit and finished up on 31st January at$2,038 million compared with $2,335 million on 31st December, 1951, and $3,269million on 31st October.5. This is a very disappointing result. Although we must be prepared to face a heavy drain for some time the actual loss in January was larger than we had expected. So soon after the event it is impossible to say whether the excess is dueto further loss of confidence in sterling, or is merely an accidental matter resultingfrom fortuitous variations in the timing of earnings or expenditure, or is the result41843Copy No. 6 1
^Our position in EoF.U, in January was alsoclisappoiintingo    The net deficit amounted to 54 million compared with , 53 million inDecember,  61+ million in November and  Qkmillion in October,,   The provisional estimate is that the January deficit willbe met by credit from S.P0Ue to us amountingto  20,5 million, and a gold payment by usto E0P0TJ. of  33o5 million or $Sk million.^
of more substantial causes. There is nothing in developments since the beginning fof February to give any further guide to the correct explanation, though in due course more details will become available.6. A As you probably know during January v/e paid  26-8 million or$75 million to E.P.U in settlement of our December deficit; the  33-5 million for January to be paid this month therefore brings the two months&apos; total to 60 - 3 million or $169 million.7. With the January E.P.U. deficit we move from the fourth tranche where60 per cent, has to be settled in gold into the fifth or last tranche where 80 percent, is settled in gold.8. In the first few days of February our position in E.P.U. has changedsuddenly from a heavy deficit to a small surplus. This is mainly a result of extremeweakness of the French franc which has encouraged a flow of funds to othercountries including the United Kingdom. It is too soon to say how far or forhow long this movement is likely to continue. As you know measures have been announced by the French Government for deliberalising their imports from other.E.E.C. countries and this is bound to have some effect on us, though this maynot be very great. Moreover in so far as the present movement is semi-speculativein origin it is essentially short-term and reversible and any gain that we make nowmay well be counterbalanced by losses later on. Nevertheless unless the reversaltakes place soon and is sharp we can expect our E.P.U. position in February to-be substantially better than in January, and we can certainly look for a much lowergold loss for the month of February than we have recently experienced. On theother hand any significant reversal of the speculative element in our current surpluswith France would lead to a rapid increase in the deficit towards the end of themonth or in March. As an offset to this our position with the other O.E.E.C.countries, though still heavily in deficit, appears to be improving. We can take some comfort from the fact that the drastic measures of economy which havealready been made in imports from O.E.E.C. countries are beginning to show their effect. The position is still very obscure, however, and some time must elapse before we can be sure of the underlying trend of events.9. Latest information about the course of the United Kingdom&apos;s sterlingliabilities to other countries shows a continuation of the very sharp decline, par-ticularly in liabilities to other sterling area countries, which has been a markedfeature of the past six months. This decline has particularly affected IndependentSterling Area countries, and is, of course, a reflection of a substantial overallbalance of payments deficit for the group as a whole. On the other hand sterlingliabilities to the Colonies show comparatively little change, which suggests that,the Colonies as a whole are still in a position of balance or even in surplus. this situation, of course, will not come as a surprise in view of the analysis and theestimates for 1952 with which we were confronted during the course of our recent meeting in London.10. The general picture for the sterling area as a whole in January is thusone of.continued acute unbalance vis-a-vis the non-sterling area. Reserves havefallen even faster than in December, if the special dollar loan transactions aredisregarded; the E.P.U. deficit was at approximately the same rate as in Decemberbut its cost in gold was greater; the rest of the sterling area, particularly the Inde-pendent Sterling Area, is still in heavy deficit and using, up external assets at asubstantial rate.11. Nor, in looking ahead over the next month or two, can one expect muchrelief, apart from the E.P.U. possibilities, already mentioned. There have beentwo unsatisfactory developments recently in our relations with the United states which will reduce considerably the flow of dollars that we hoped to receive duringthe next few months. We had counted on getting a further $40 million this quarterunder the so-called Katz-Gaitskell agreement following the $40 million paid to uslast quarter. We have now been informed by the United States that only a further$10 million in all can be made available up to the end of the present fiscal year, i.e.,30th June, 1952, , In addition, great technical difficulties have been encountered in arranging for the receipt of the $300 million which was recently allocated to us underthe Mutual Security. Act for the fiscal year 1951-52. This makes it extremely unlikely that we shall receive more than a small amount, say of the order of $25million, in the present quarter, and possibly not more than $125 million before the
\/l of the present United States fiscal year i.e., 30th June, .1952. We have noreason to believe that the remaining portion of the $300 million will not be carried over into the next fiscal year, but we have never before during the E.R.P. era had such a large carry-over of funds, and the position is clearly hazardous.12. To sum up, therefore, we can only look for comparatively little realreinforcement to the reserves from United States aid of one kind or another duringthe next few months. We can certainly expect that our recent tin and rubber dealswith the United States will make some contribution. But this is likely to be only of the order of $20 million during the first quarter of the year.13. Although it is clearly dangerous in present highly unsettled conditions to venture any guess even about the near future, I think we should do well to recon-cile ourselves to a gold and dollar deficit during the present quarter of the year ofthe order of $750 million, and a roughly similar loss of reserves. It may be rather less if the E.P.U. position in February, for the special reasons given in paragraph 8,turns out very favourably. But this seems at the present moment to be the mostreasonable estimate that can be made.14. A loss of the order of $750 million would bring the reserves down from$2,335 million at the end of December and $2,038 million at the end of january to under $1,600 million at the end of March. Even if the rate of drain is slackeningoff considerably by that time we must contemplate a reduction well below $1,600million after the 31st March.15. I have set out the latest position and the immediate prospects as I seethem with candour and without any attempt to conceal their gravity. Nor have Ithe slightest desire to exaggerate our difficulties. But if we are to meet the situation the utmost frankness on all sides is necessary and the clearest possible appreciation of the magnitude of the task which lies before us. The facts as I have presented themunderline the imperative need for immediate action designed to relieve the situation at the earliest possible moment. I am convinced that you realise to the full this need and that your actions and those of your Government will be dictated entirely by it.

</content>
</cab>
