<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/49/0 images: 149-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  February 1952CONFIDENTIAL Copy No. g \C. (52) 34Uth February, 1952CABINETTHE IMPERIAL CROWNNote by the Prime minister circulate to my colleagues the following short note on the expression&quot; Imperial Crown&quot; which was used in Accession Proclamations until her present Majesty&apos;s.w. s. c.10, Downing Street, S.W. 1,Uth February, 1952.During the Middle Ages the Sovereign was referred to in a number of ways, e.g., Our Sovereign Lord the King, The King&apos;s Highness, The King&apos;sGrace, but never as Majesty, an expression which came into use in the SixteenthCentury.Henry VIII is said to be the first King who used the expression Imperialin statutes. For example:  The Act forbidding Appeals to Rome 1532-3 starts:&quot; Where by divers sundry old authentic histories and chronicles it ismanifestly declared and expressed that this realm of England is an empireand so hath been accepted in the world . . . .&quot;
Again, the Statute of Wales 1535-6 starts:&quot;Albeit the dominion principality and county of Wales justly andrighteously is and ever hath been incorporated annexed united and sub-ject to and under the imperial crown of this realm &quot;,And the Act of 1543-4 ratifying the King&apos;s title as King of Ireland declaresthe King&apos;s title to be:&quot; Henry VIII, by the Grace of God King of England, France andIreland, defender of the faith and of the Church of England and also ofIreland, in earth the supreme head &quot;and provides&quot; the said style shall be from henceforth .... united and annexedfor ever to the imperial crown of His Highness realm of England.&quot;The sixteenth century saw the rapid development of nationalism amongthe countries of Western Europe and the emphasis on the imperial nature ofthe Crown was one aspect of that development. Ireland was created a king-dom and in consequence Henry VIII was king of more than one kingdom quite apart from the traditional claim to be King of France. He asserted that hissovereignty was of an imperial nature to show his independence of the HolyRoman Empire and of the Papacy. His ambition to be as good as his fellowswas marked by his eagerness to have a special title from the Pope like his fellow monarchs of France and Spain.The use of the expression &quot; Imperial Crown of this realm &quot; in the AccessionProclamation certainly dates from the reign of Edward VI, the earliest proclamation-mation of which there is a complete text.

</content>
</cab>
