<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/49/0 images: 168-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(52) 39 COPY NO. fe^15TH FEBRUARY, 1952CABINETREFORM OF THE NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY organisation memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs my colleagues may like to know that the North Atlantic Council,during its meeting at Lisbon, will discuss a scheme for the reform of theNorth Atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.).2*    Agreed proposals the Council will presumably endorse the following proposals, onwhich the Council Deputies are all agreed:-(a) The North Atlantic Council will be in permanent session (likethe Security Council).    Whenever necessary, and in any eventthree times a year, the Council will meet at Ministerial level.At other meetings Governments will be represented byPermanent Representatives of sufficient standing to act ontheir behalf.(b) The Council Deputies, Financial and Economic Board and defence Production Board will be abolished and their functionsvested in the Council, which will set up such committees as itthinks necessary.(c) The Military Committee and the Standing Group will remain,as organs subordinate to the Council.(d) The Headquarters of the Organisation and all its civilianagencies will be located in one place, where the ministerialmeetings will normally be held.    The Military Committeeand the Standing Group will remain in Washington.(e) A Secretary-General will be appointed to direct the inter-national staff, which should be unified and strong in qualitythough not in numbers.3.    Points still in disputeThere are two main questions on which the Deputies could not agree and which must be decided at Lisbon: the location of the Head-quarters and the respective functions of the Chairman of the permanent representatives and the Secretary-General,(a) LocationThe choice lies between London (where the Council Deputies arenow established) and Paris.    The Americans believe that the effective-ness of N.A.T.O. depends on its being close to European problems and
other international organisations situated in Paris.    Other memberssupport the move to Paris on grounds of administrative convenience.To my mind, London is the natural Atlantic capital and. it is only here that N.A.T.O. can develop on right lines.    This view is now shared by several other members, but probably not by a majority.(b)  Functions of the Secretary-General and the Chairman ofthe Permanent RepresentativesWe propose that the Chairman of the Permanent representatives should be elected from among their number to preside over their       -meetings; the mainspring of the Organisation should be the Secretary-General, who would co-ordinate the work of the Organisation and follow up the decisions of the Council.    The United States propose that these latter functions should belong to the Chairman of the permanent representatives, who should not be a member of a national delegation and who would have direct access to Governments.    The solution tothis problem probably lies in finding the right man.    If he is of ministerial standing, we could agree that he should be both Secretary-General and Chairman of the Permanent Representatives.4. I shall continue to make strenuous efforts to obtain agreement on the headquarters remaining in London, and, if I am successful, Ishall be prepared to agree to the appointment of a Secretary-Generalfrom a country other than the United Kingdom.    A Canadian would be best of all.A.E.Foreign Office, S.W.1,15TH FEBRUARY, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
