<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/248/0 images: 52-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OE HIS BRITANNICMAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).copy NO.      5^ SECRET CP.  73(34).CABINET. INDIA.Appreciation of the Political Situation in India, dated 12th March, 1934, issued on the authority of the Secretary of State for India.Circulated for the information the Cabinet by the Secretary of State for Indi
Confidential Appreciation of the Political Situation in India dated 12th March, 1934, issued on the authority of the Secretary of _____State jfov JEndia.The lull in political activity which has been so marked a feature of recent months still continues.Jawahar Lai Nehru&apos;s arrest and trial for deliveringthree highly seditious and inciting speeches arousedlittle attention in Calcutta,  and his conviction wasreceived almost with indifference even in his ownProvince.      His semi-coimnunist preaching, though it wasproving attractive to the irresponsible, had alreadyseriously alarmed those with any stake in the countryand,  in addition to the removal from the scene of thechief opponents of the withdrawal of civil disobedience,was probably not regretted by the growing circle of congress workers who recognise failure of the movement and wish to substitute some more practical programme.Opinion differs as to what the programme should be.Some leaders,  in particular Mr.  Satyamurti of Madras andMr, Jamnadas Mehta and Mr. Kelkar, the founders of the democratic Swaraj Party in Bombay,  are pushing the policy.of council entry which was adopted by the late Mr.  CP.Das and Pandit Moti Lai Nehru in 1924, but whether theywill succeed in securing substantial support for thispolicy is uncertain,  for,  apart from the opposition ofthe militant left wing,  others may regard it as destroying the unity of Congress and may also be influenced by thewell known views oi Mr.  Ganahi on this point.      A meetingwill probably be held shortly in Delhi to discuss thisquestion.     Meanwhile, Mr. Nariman in Bombay has not given up hope of persuading Congress, as a whole, formally toabandon civil disobedience and thus secure freedom to function again as a constitutional party.
2.Relief work in the earthquake stricken areas of Bihar is giving Congress an opportunity, of which they are taking full advantage, to strengthen their position in Bihar itself and of restoring their prestige generally throughout India.      Congress papers continue to publish long and,  in,many cases, exaggerated accounts of the distress,  in particular, regarding the amount of damage to fields, the prospect of famine and the prevalence of epidemics partly, no doubt, with a view to increase subscriptions to their relief funds, which already amount to over Rs.18 lakhs, partly with the object of damaging the credit of the Government by showing they are minimising the situation, and that their relief measures are inadequate.      The proposals of the Government of India for giving financial aid tc the province, though criticised in Congress circles, have been well received by the Assembly,  and the Viceroy&apos;s Fund rises steadily from day to day,  and is now-over Rs.30 lakhs.      His Excellency the Viceroy&apos;s recent visit to Bihar has also been very favourably received. In the province itself Rajendra Prasap, the Congress leader is working, harmoniously with the Government and refuses to be led by the smaller men into an attempt to embarrass the local officials.      Mr.  Gandhi is reported to be visiting the area shortly and it remains to be seen whether his visit will further strengthen Congress position.In regard to the terrorist movement, there are encouraging signs.      The further legislation introduced by the Government of Bengal has just boen passed by a
very substantial majority in the Bengal Council;    in the Chittagong district, police, with the aid of troops, have arrested 13 members of the chief revolutionary party,  seised 3 revolvers and 8 daggers and recovered valuable ornaments believed to be the proceeds of dacoitiesj    convictions have also been secured in the trials instituted after the murder of Mr, Burgc and after the attack on a railway station in North Bengal referred to in the appreciation dated 22nd November,  1933.      The pressure on terrorists in bengal is, however, having the effect of driving them into the adjacent province of Assam and,  in particular,  into these parts which are geographically and ethnologically part of Bengal,  and it has become necessary for the Government of Assam to undertake legislation to prevent the movement spreading in Assam and fo facilitate co-operation with the Bengal police.

</content>
</cab>
