<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/248/0 images: 258-262</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ittOHET, copy NO.     3 ,p786C34). CABINET.WATERLOO BRIDGE,Memorandum by the Minister of Transport..It is necessary for me again to bring to the notice of the Cabinet the position of Waterloo Bridge.Tenders have been invited and are due to be received next month for reconditioning the existing bridge and for corbelling out the parapets so as t;* provide for four lines of traffic according to a design which has received the approval of the Royal Fine Arts Commission.I received on Monday a visit from Mr. Herbert Morrison accompanied by Mr. G.R. Strauss, the Chairman Designate of the new Highways Committee with which the Improvements Committee is being merged.     Mr. Morrison reminded me that the London County Council had never itself regarded the proposal to spend a substantial sum of money on preserving the existing bridge as one which was justified on the merits of the case, and that the new Council would have to review the matter.     Mr. Morrison further said that he had no doubt that the new Council would take the same view as the old Council and desire to demolish the existing bridge and replace it by a modern bridge adapted for six lines of traffic.     He urged me to give him Informally some indication of the probable attitude of the Government in the event of the Council inserting in their annual Money Bill provision for oapital expenditure upon this subject.I replied that he could not reasonably expect me to give him any such indication in a matter of such importance which had given rise to so much recent controversy, and that I should not even be in a position to ap-proach my colleagues until I knew clearly what proposals the London County Council itself would wish to make, if indeed they wished to depart from existing
arrangements at all.     Mr. Morrison explained that the new Highways Committee had not yet met and he was therefore only in a position to say that their general intention would he to adopt the design made by Sir Giles Scott when the previous Councils with the support of the Government, was intending to reconstruct the bridge, and that he knew of no reason to depart from the estimate of cost of about SI,300,000 which had been put forward by the Council in previous discussions.     I told him definitely that, so long as the opinion of the House of Commons remained recorded as adverse to the destruction of the existing bridge and its replacement by one of different design, it would he out of the question, and indeed unconstitutional, for the Government -to make or promise to make a grant from the Road Fund, but that I should he prepared to consult my colleagues as to the attitude they would adopt towards any revised proposals which the Council may wish to submit to Parliament as soon as I was given sufficiently definite information as to the cost of those proposals and the design to he adopted, and also an assurance that they have the Council&apos;s support.      This was the procedure adopted by my predecessor towards the then Chairman of the Improvements Committee and I was sure the Cabinet would think it inadvisable to depart in any way from that precedent,I understand that it is necessary for the Council to determine what provision, if any, to insert in their annual Money Bill by the end of next week, end I have, therefore, warned Mr. Morrison that I cannot sey whether I shall in fact be able to give him any indication of the Government&apos;s attitude before he is ooliged to submit the matter formally to the Council.
The three main considerations appear to me to he asfollowss-1.      Upon the traffic and other merits of the case there is no ground for departing from the view expressed on behalf of the Government by my predecessor in favour of a new bridge.      Indeed, the obstruction to navigation which any attempt to recondition the existing bridge is likely to cause may be more serious and form the subject of stronger objections by the shipping and allied interests than was previously expected.     V/e cannot, therefore, I think, seek to deter the Council from submitting renewed proposals for replacing the bridge if they so desire, and we must fall back upon the policy described in the conclusions of the Cabinet Committee which sat on the evening of the 51st May, 1932, and which interpreted the decision of the Government as communicated to the London County Council (see letter of 20th January, 1932, annexed) as a declaration of non-intervention rather than a positive statement of policy.2. long as the vote of the House of Commons remainsunaltered it is out of the question for the Government to depart from its decision not to make a grant to a project of which Parliament has disapproved.3.      In view of the past history of the matter, the Government would not be justified in taking any steps to persuade Parliament to alter its mind.I recommend that I should be authorised, on behalf of the Government, to inform Mr. Morrison that while, of course,  it is open to the Council to take any action which, in the exercise of their discretion as the responsible highway and improvement authority, they may think necessary or advisable, the Government
22nd March, 1934.would not bo able to make a grant to any scheme which runs contrary to the expressed opinion of Parliament, and would not be prepared itself to take any steps with a view to urging Parliament to alter that opinion.(sgd.)    O.F.G.S.
COPY.CQKPIDEFTIAL. 20th January, 1932.Dear Sir Percy,In view of the terms of the report with which you furnished me on Monday last,  stating the reasons why the London County Council do not regard the scheme known as the Temple Bridge as a feasible one, I confirm the intimation whicl I gave you on Thursday,  the 14th instant, as to the Governments attitude in the matter of Waterloo Bridge.This, you will remember, was to the effect that if in the exercise of their discretion as the responsible highway and improvement authority, the London County Council decide that the only satisfactory course is to build a new bridge to take six lines of traffic, the Government will not feel justified in intervening.     Any grant from the Road Fund to such a scheme would have to be limited to 60 per cent., the normal rate of grant to reconstruction of a Class Ibridge, and would be subject to an assurance that the Council would appoint in connection with the scheme an-architect of high standing-and repute.Yours sincerely,(Sgd.)    P.J. Pybus.Sir Percy Simmons, K.C.V.O., County Hall,

</content>
</cab>
