<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/248/0 images: 304-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    208THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET , &apos;C.P.92 (34). CABINET. Copy No.-      * *-COTTON    TRADE    WAGES.LORD    WEIR&apos;S    MEMORANDUM.Note by the Minister of Labour.1.      I have found Lord Weir&apos;s observations, C.P087 (34) 9 particularly Interesting in that they indicate that lie has apprached the matter with the same general views on the desirability of preserving our voluntary collective system as those held by myself and by the Cotton Weaving employers and operatives.    As he says, however, he is not well informed as to the detailed conditions and organisation of the industry and the suggestion made in his final paragraph indicates the further disadvantage of not knowing  the action &quot;which has been already taken.2.      Lord Weir suggests that,  if the three independent commissioners are appointed now to hear objections to the agree-mehis,  and if they do their job well,  loyalty will be secured without the necessity of any statute.    I took action of this kind in another and more acceptable way early last year9 with the full co-operation of the employers and operatives, by making a detailed investigation in certain districts of the operation of the agreements.    At the end a confidential report was made to both sides which fully indicated the difficulties arising from the agreements.    Since then the main object in the minds of all concerned has been to get negotiations begun for a comprehensive agreement but this has been impossible because there was no assurance that, if concessions were made by either side and agreement reached,  the agreement would be generally observed. Every day of delay in taking action to give this assurance brings further disintegration.    Lord Weir&apos;s proposal would,  therefore, be regarded only as another attempt to avoid taking the only) 1.
action which appears to all those who have studied the circumstances closely to he likely to maintain the voluntary system and to avoid the taking of more drastic statutory action. Having regard to the amount of inquiry and critical comment which has already been made there might be a feeling of exasperation at least as great as would be caused hy inaction, 5.      I should hesitate,  in any case,  to create a precedent for appointing a Board compulsorily to examine the working of voluntary agreements and I should expect such a proposal to be strenuously resisted.    I should also lay myself open to inconvenient requests in any quarter in which a particular agreement was disliked and where one party could not itself secure a change in the conditions.    It would clearly be an attempt to impose by an external authority new conditions and, however unbiassed the report, it is unlikely that the parties would accept them without controversy.    My own proposals, on the other hand, are calculated to give the maximum incentive to the parties themselves to examine their agreements and to make the necessary adjustments,4.      Lord Weir appears to be under the impression that it is proposed to give the effect of law to existing agreements.    This is not the case.    If it were, his observations would he apposite. The proposal is to give both sides the assurance that,  if suit-able conditions are agreed,  they will be observed and that the present waste of the resources of the industry in purely selfish cutting of wages and margins will be stopped.    Without that assurance the unions will not enter into negotiations and the employers will be unable to hold their organisation together. Wages are already in many cases below a reasonable level and the process of undercutting can continue until social unrest makes outside interference necessary in most difficult circumstances. The usual remedy for breach of agreements in a voluntary system is expulsion of members from their organisation.    The limit of this action has been reached by the unions and, on the employers&apos;
side,  they have hesitated, in the face of the magnitude of the action required,  to weaken the membership of their organisations further and so to make voluntary collective agreements impossible,, The crisis will come by the termination of agreements and a policy of &quot;sauve qui peut&quot;.    Lord Weir obviously has no realisation of the situation with which the organisations are faced and which they have described to me.5.      Lord Weir&apos;s questions in paragraph I of his memorandum are pertinent.    The reply to the first is that disloyalty is definitely causing harm to the industry and that a continuance of the present individual competition in wage-cutting will produce worse and not better ultimate results.    It is organisation and co-operation, not disorganisation,  that the industry requires for the improvement of the competitive position.    With regard to the second question,  the transgression is not confined to either the home or the export section.    The fact that it is taking place in the home section, which is comparatively prosperous,  to an extent that is reducing margins to an unremunerative level without any increase in business is a sufficient commentary on the position. Given order,  there is room for considerable economies in production costs in the export section;    and it is recognised by those who most desire this legislation that it is chiefly by such economies that the industry can hope to meet its competitors in the kinds of cloth,  the trade in which is not finally lost. 6.      With regard to J and K of Lord Weir&apos;s memorandum,  it is seriously believed that,  seeing that &quot;universal loyalty&quot; to voluntary wages agreements does not exist, temporary assurance of that loyalty is in the line of progress.    Three years of accumulated difficulties have produced the demand for legislation as the alternative to despair.    Under the new conciliation machinery set up in 1932, reasonable agreements can be expected but inability to get negotiations started holds up all action, although
both sides are fully ready to utilise the new machinery.    I believe that the legislation suggested would bring this machinery into action.7.      My reply, therefore,   to Lord Weir&apos;s observations is that I am entirely in agreement with him in his desire to preserve our voluntary collective system.    I can conceive of no greater blow to that system than its breakdown in an industry so important as Cotton.    But,  in the present circumstances of the Weaving section, we are faced with a situation in which the parties,  left to their own resources,  are unable to avoid a breakdown from which recovery would be difficult if not impossible.    The Bill provides a means by which confidence in the making of voluntary agreements can be restored.(Intld, ) H.B.23rd March,  1934*

</content>
</cab>
