<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/60 images: 573-582</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CM (71)60th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 30 November, 1971,at 11.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,mp, Secretary of State for the home department \    &apos;  ,       ,The Right Hon.&apos;William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hori: Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State^ for; Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and Science .The Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for; the Environ-ment the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicob,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Davies, m p,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry and President of the Boardof trade the following were also present:Mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, chief secretary, Treasury [The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . N. F. cairncross mr. B. G. tucker mr. K. T. barnett mr. J. AnsonTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1973Copy No.
contents item     ; Subject page 1     Top Salaries Review Body       ...............     3&apos;      Report on the Pay of Ministers and Members of Parliament.2 . Cotton Textile Imports   ..................     8
Top salaries review BodyReport on the pay of     ... &apos;Ministers and members ofParliament(&quot;1.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum of the lord president of the Council (CP (71) 141) on the Report of the top salaries Review Body about the pay of Ministers of the Crown and: Members of Parliament.The Lord President said that a small Ministerial group under his chairmanship had considered the Report of the Top salaries review Body (TSRB). While he had made clear in announcing the reference of Ministers&apos; and Members&apos; pay to the TSRB on  December last that the final decision on their recommendations would rest with the Government, it had nevertheless been theGovermenfs declared intention to implement the recommendationsunless there were clear and compelling reasons for not doing so.The TSRB had referred to this intention in paragraph 121 of theirReport and had said that they regarded this as placing on them anadded responsibility to keep their recommendations for increases and improvements to the absolute minimum which they considered.; to be necessary. In their view it was of the highest importance thattheir recommendations, as they affected both salaries and allowances,should:now be implemented as a whole and in full. Against this background the view of the Ministerial group was that theGovernment should accept all the recommendations in the B.eport,subject only to reservations relating to (i) the proposal to establishtwo funds to which individual Members could apply for assistanceto meet their costs of travel within the United Kingdom and overseastb; inform themselves of subjects of relevance to their work; (ii) thepropbsal that provincial Members should be eligible to draw asubsistence allowance, based on Civil Service rates, to meet theadditional costs of staying away from their homes when engaged on parliamentary duties; and (iii) the proposed salary for theGovernment Whips in the House of Commons.: hum m\ i;j :; The TSRB considered that members remuneration should nowbe assessed on the basis of two principles, namely that membership of the House of Commons was a full-time commitment and that, ingeneral, Members should not in future be expected to meetreasonable expenses out of their salary. The Ministerial group hadnoted that the survey carried out by the TSRB had shown that theaverage number of hours spent each week by all Members on parliamentary work was 63. The TSRB had also pointed out thatthe more expense a Member at present incurred in carrying out hisjob (however reasonable), the less were his disposable earnings: andthis might mean that the more work he did in visiting his constituencyand dealing with his constituents&apos; problems, the less money was left in his pocket. The Ministerial group considered that the twoprinciples which had been put forward by the TSRB should beaccepted. ; &quot;,&apos; The proposal to establish two funds from which members could seek assistance towards the cost of their &quot; self-information &quot;travel in the United Kingdom and overseas could give rise to
! difficulties of administration. The selection of Members to receivepayments from the funds would be invidious. Moreover, the payments would generally be taxable as part of a Member&apos;s emoluments,subject to a deduction for any admissible expenses; and the questionof the types of travel expenses which would be admissible fordeduction could give rise to dispute. It was therefore desirable that,while accepting the recommendation in principle, the Government: should say that further consideration would be needed in consultationwith the Parties in the House and that the administration of the funds and the tax treatment of payments made from them should bej    studied in detail.The new subsistence allowance for provincial Members also raised problems of administration and personal taxation. Subjectto appropriate conditions and safeguards, the allowance could beaccepted by the Inland Revenue as being non-taxable; but excess^Expenditure would not be allowed as a tax deduction unless it was incurred for reasons outside the Member&apos;s control and was notreimbursed. It would be necessary to establish where a Member ofParliament had his real home and to decide whether the allowance would be paid in respect of the number of days necessarily spentaway from home on Parliamentary duties or would relate to thewhole period of the Parliamentary Session, a point which was not entirely clear in the TSRB&apos;s Report. The introduction of thesubsistence allowance might therefore have an adverse effect on; those Members who had substantial private means and were atpresent able to claim the extra costs of living away from home inLondon against their Parliamentary salaries for tax purposes. Itwas therefore desirable that the Government should indicate that further consideration would be given to the implementation of thisrecommendation in consultation with the House Authorities and the inland Revenue.&apos; On the question of the payment of Government Whips in the ,House of Commons the general view of the Ministerial group was jthat the TSRB had failed to recognise the very long hours worked pby the Commons Whips as compared with those in the Lords. %&apos; Lord Boyle, to whom he had mentioned the point in confidence Ii had said that he would accept a Government decision to increase ,I the salary for Commons Whips to the same level as that for the lords Whips., The major question on Ministers&apos; pay was whether the increases should be staged in the case of Cabinet Ministers. The general conclusion of the Ministerial group was that this would yield littlepresentational advantage. Nevertheless, the Cabinet, who were finally responsible for the decision on the Report, might take theview that in the case of their own pay some staging, as had beenagreed voluntarily in the past by some senior public servants, mightbe desirable.Subject to a decision on this issue, the increases in salaries and allowances for Members of Parliament and the increasedParliamentary salary for Ministers should be brought into effect from 1 January next.   These increases could be dealt with by
appropriate Resolutions. If necessary, the proposed subsistence allowance could be dealt with in a subsequent Resolution after thepractical details of the scheme had been considered. The salaries of Ministers, and in most cases, other paid office holders wouldrequire legislation; and the operative date should therefore be 1April, 1972, in all cases. The pensions proposals, which were acceptable in substance, had to be worked out in more detail before they could be incorporated in legislation; and it would be necessaryto introduce a separate Pensions Bill subsequently. It would be convenient ,to include in the legislation on Ministerial salaries alimited number of changes in the provisions affecting Ministerialappointments.The present intention was that the Report of the SelectCommittee on the Civil List should be published on Monday, 6December; and it was for consideration whether the TSRB report and the Government&apos;s statement about it should be published before or after the Civil List Report.In discussion it was urged that it was essential that theGovernment should adhere to their declared intention to implementproposals made by the TSRB unless there were overriding reasonsagainst doing so. Their position would be greatly weakened ifchanges were made to the individual recommendations, no matterhow justifiable the particular modifications might be shown to be.The recommendations would not be popular in the country and theGovernment would be gravely embarrassed if, in addition todefending their acceptance of the Report in principle, they had tojustify making changes to it in particular respects. It would be particularly objectionable to increase a salary above the levelproposed by the TSRB, as was suggested in the case of the CommonsWhips, since to do so would run counter to the Governments generalpolicy on,incomes. If the Government themselves changed any1 recommendations, they would find it more difficult to resist pressuresfor- other changes in the proposals.! : Much the same general argument applied also to the suggestionthat the increases in the pay of Cabinet Ministers should be staged.This would be represented as an empty gesture; and it would be unlikely to. mitigate the inevitable criticisms of the increases or toreduce; the possible repercussions on the Governments incomes policy. Moreover, the effect would be to keep the issue alive; andit would become a continuing source of embarrassment throughoutthe staging period when other pay increases were being considered.Any political or presentational advantage would be small; and itwould therefore be wiser to implement the increases in a singleoperation. On the other hand, the increases for Cabinet ministers were so substantial that the Government might not be ablesuccessfully to defend them without making a voluntary renunciation of some sort. The pay of Cabinet Ministers was last raised seven years earlier ;i: and over that period the increase, if the largerParliamentary salary now proposed was also included, would be64 per cent, which was substantially in excess of any level of increase which the Government would now generally accept astolerable under their incomes policy.  It was true that, on the last
occasion, as the TSRB had pointed out in their Report, the increases recommended for Ministers had been halved because theGovernment of the day considered that it would not be appropriate in the prevailing economic circumstances to increase ministerial salaries to the full extent recommended. But Ministers in theCabinet would be particularly vulnerable to the charge that theywere according themselves more favourable treatment than they wereprepared to give others under their incomes policy. Moreover, therewas some feeling among the Governmenfs supporters that theGovernment should show a readiness to make some sacrifice; andthe voluntary renunciation which had been made by senior public. servants a year ago had in fact been helpful in tempering the generalopposition to the Governmenfs endeavours to reduce the rate of pay increases in other fields.V: ;. In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) It would be necessary for further consideration to be givennot only to the reservations proposed by the Lord President inrelation to the travel funds and the provincial Members&apos; subsistence allowance but also to the treatment for tax purposes of payments from the proposed travel funds and of the element to be included inthe increased secretarial allowance in respect of the employment ofa research assistant.(b) It would be invidious if Peers were not eligible to receiveassistance from the travel funds.; (c) The proposal that Members should continue to draw their salaries throughout the period of a Dissolution might be criticisedbh the ground that they might then be at an advantage in relationto other candidates; and it would be regrettable if pressure thendeveloped for all candidates to be paid from public funds during aGeneral Election. On the other hand many candidates would undoubtedly continue to be paid by their employers throughout the campaign.(d) Consideration should be given to announcing an increasein the Peers&apos; expenses allowance in the Governmenfs statement onthe TSRB Review. On the other hand the balance of advantageirnight lie in confining the statement to the matters covered by theTJSRB and dealing separately with any adjustment of the allowances of Peers.(e) On balance it seemed preferable that the Report on theCivil List should be published slightly before the TSRB Review.If so, the respective dates of publication might be Thursday, 2December, and Monday, 6 December.v The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the Report of the TSRB should be acceptedsubject to further consideration of the points which had been raised in relation to the two travel funds, the provincial Members&apos;subsistence allowance and the allowance for the employment of research assistant. The Cabinet also agreed that it would be unwise to amend any of the recommendations of the TSRB, particularly ifthe effect of the change was to improve those recommendations, as
had been suggested in respect of the Commons Whips. The cabinet approved the arrangements proposed by the Lord President for the implementation of the recommendations, including the proposal to defer the provisions relating to pensions to a subsequent Bill. Subjectto the views of the Chancellor of the Exchequer (who was absent onan official visit to Rome), the Cabinet agreed that the TSRB report should be published on Monday, 6 December, and that a statement should be made on behalf of the Government at that time. Onthis basis, the Cabinet could, if necessary, defer until their meetinglater in the week a final decision on the question whether the increasesm the salaries of Cabinet Ministers should be staged; but the general view of the Cabinet appeared to be that the attractions of such acourse were outweighed by the disadvantages. The question of apossible increase in the expenses allowance for Peers should be,^considered; separately.The Cabinet-.....,   (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summingrip of their discussion.(2) Invited the Lord President &apos; .... (i) subject to the views of the Chancellor of theExchequer, to make arrangements accordingly forthe publication of the Top Salaries Review BodyReport on Monday, 6 December;(ii) to consult the office holders concerned, including the speaker, before the Report was published;(iii) to arrange for a Government statement to be4 &apos; prepared, taking account of the points made inthe Prime Ministers summing up;(iv) to arrange, after the publication of the Report, forthe necessary consultations to take place on the outstanding points relating to the travel funds,; the provincial Members&apos;subsistence allowance andthe allowance for the employment of a research-u&quot; ; &apos;;!       assistant;- I        (v) subject to the outcome of the consultations under (iv)I above to arrange for the introduction of thenecessary Resolutions and legislation to give effectto the recommendations of the Top Salaries,; Review Body and to the proposed changesaffecting Ministerial appointments in accordancewith the timetable which he had indicated.(3) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to bring forward separatelyproposals for increases in the expenses allowance paidto Peers.
CONFIDENTIALCotton ; i 1.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the SecretaryTextile.      : of State for Trade and Industry (CP (71) 142) on imports of cotton imports        textiles.;   The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that inI I       October, 1970, the present Government had endorsed the policy adopted by the previous Administration whereby the cotton textile industry would be afforded only tariff protection from 1972 onwards.An undertaking had been given that when the new tariff was applied. we would not retain a general system of quantitative restrictions andwould only reintroduce them if total imports of cotton textiles rose., and caused disruption.  When we entered the European economic community (e.c.) in 1973, however, we should be adapting to aj    regime which included quantitative restrictions, with the result that imports, which were already likely to increase early in the NewYear, would inevitably rise further as suppliers tried to forestall the* !!i1 ! i; ^quantitative restrictions which would be imposed in 1973 and thus&apos;lYf &apos; !&apos;&apos;    p to increase the base from which the new quotas would be calculated.1       ! ^Employment in the Lancashire textile industry had recently fallen;- $M; H?ahd the restrictions imposed by the United States on imports of:i inon-cotton textiles would increase the pressure on our market still- &quot;further.   If quantitative restrictions were not retained at this.., juncture, the disruption of efficient Lancashire production would j/undermine our intention to create an economic textile industry. he proposed, therefore, that quantitative restrictions on cotton textiles should be retained and that this decision should be announced in ;;the Debate which had been arranged for 1 December on the affirmative Resolution approving the new tariff for 1972. It wouldbe necessary to give prior warning to the developing Commonwealthsuppliers, who could be expected to protest strongly, although in&apos;; practice traditional suppliers like India and Hong Kong might wellbenefit by being protected by the restrictions on more competitive, ,&apos; i \] suppliers in Korea and Taiwan.   In presenting the proposal hewould not put the blame exclusively on the e.c. developments oroh unemployment but would indicate that the new factors incbmbination would pose an intolerable threat to the industry whichcould not have been foreseen when the original decision was made.&apos; and that in these circumstances we could not sustain a more liberali i cotton textile policy than other industrialised countries. Nevertheless,; , , :j;.ivyelshould still be taking a far higher proportion of low-cost textile^i    imports than any other major industrial country.&quot;-&quot; &apos;] .; The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that we hadimgiven categorical assurances to India and Hong Kong that wej:;: : ;l;jf I L ^bidd not have both tariffs and quantitative restrictions in 1972. The,v;.... ij -advice of our High Commissioners in those countries and of thejjj-j ^Governor of Hong Kong was that a reversal of the decision toj&apos; abandon quantitative restrictions would be regarded as a high---handed and unfriendly act and that the reaction of the countries/concerned would be explosive.   We would have no satisfactory:&apos; defence against such accusations of breach of faith.  Moreover, if]; we were to go back on our undertakings on textiles, this could castl
doubt oh the guarantees which we had given during the course of the e.c. negotiations to other Commonwealth countries, such as new Zealand and the sugar producers; and this could affect thepassage of our e.c. legislation through Parliament. To explainproperly to the Commonwealth countries the reasons for our action would require at least a week; and to try to do it in a single day would provoke the most vigorous protests.In discussion is was argued that unemployment in the North-West was already serious and that, if quantitative restrictions werenot maintained on cotton textiles, the problem would be aggravatednot only during the coming winter but also thereafter, since a high level of imports in 1972 would tend to be perpetuated in later years.In the last; 50 years we had ceased to be a net exporter of textiles and had become a large net importer; and restrictions were necessaryto allow the necessary adaptation of the industry. On the otherHand, ffie^assurances which we had given to the Commonwealth werespecific and binding; and, if circumstances had now changed, ourproper course would be to explain to our Commonwealth partnerswhy we felt unable to fulfil our undertaking. If we merelyannounced a reversal of policy without any prior consultation withthem,&apos; this could have serious effects on the credibility of the assurances which we had given during the e.c. negotiations. InOrder to postpone the Debate on the Order relating to the tariff,it would be necessary for the Order to be relaid; but this could bejustified on the grounds that it had become inconvenient in terms ofthe management of current Parliamentary business to debate it onthe following day. There was a risk, however, that, if suppliers ofcotton textiles realised that we might be contemplating maintainingquantitative restrictions in 1972, they might enter into contracts with british importers before the proposal was formally announced andthen claim that the quantitative restrictions should not apply to such contracts.In further discussion it was suggested that other courses thanthe imposition of quantitative restrictions might be explored in orderto limit imports; or that quantitative restrictions might be retainedbut that the introduction of the tariff might be postponed to1 January, 1973. But there seemed to be no alternative machinery which could readily be used in this case, while abandonment of thetariff proposal at this stage would be attacked by the British textile industry ^; removing the basis on which they had planned their future pricing policy.Sir TheSSPrime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thiswas a problem which admitted no satisfactory solution. The Cabinetaccepted that the present situation in the textile industry required themaintenance of restrictions on imports of cotton textiles; and they recognised -the risk of forestalling if a decision to this effect was notannounced on 1 December when the tariff Order was due to be debated. 6n the other hand, to announce a reversal of policy withso little opportunity for prior discussion with the commonwealth countries concerned would involve unacceptable risks in terms ofour relations with our Commonwealth partners, especially in the context of the e.c. negotiations. The tariff Order should therefore
be relaid and the Debate should be postponed for a week, in orderto give time for a full explanation to Commonwealth Governmentsof the reasons which had led us to conclude that quantitative restrictions on cotton textiles should be retained. Our case, whichwould have to be very carefully presented, should be based primarily on the effect of imports of cotton textiles on employment in the textile industry rather than on the obligations which we had accepted in the eec from 1973 onwards.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister, and invited the Secretaryof State for Trade and Industry, in consultation with theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary, to proceed accordingly.Cabinet Office,30 November, 1971.

</content>
</cab>
