<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/11/0 images: 115-117</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;JAB. - CAEIMET . G.T. 521proposal for the Despatch of American Troops to the Eastern-Pront . (Memorandum &quot;by Gcunt Eorodyski)Although there nay he grounds for irmajdiato optimism with regard to the pros; ect of .,i.ussia continuing to wage vex effectively, the Western -Powers cannot afford to count absolutely on her being able to continue to the end.    The Anarchist elements may not succeed in getting the upper hand, but the conflict between them end the i-rovisicnal Government must have an increasingly disruptive effect on the military organisation, must permanently undermine discipline,  and must in any case prevent the combined national effort necessary for even successful, defensive warfare.     At the worst the conflict might sharpen into civil vrex which would open the door at once to German invasion..The &quot;western &apos;Powers would be wiser not to count on any sustained effort by Russia,  if left to her own re-souro.es-,  beyond the next few months and should seriously consider now whether it is not possible to devise a scheme for propping her up &quot;when under the stress of internal dis-integret ion she begins to totter.The disastrous results of Russia going out of the war - whether formally or through colla/pse does not. matter -do not need to be laboured.     The Western armies night have driven the enemy back on to his own coil, but they would be unable to impose the terns necessary to bring about the huropean reconstruction to which they are committed either on paper or otherwise..     In particular Poland would remain a pledge in Gem an hands., and the elimination of the ..ussian, armies in the East would put off indefintely all chance of extracting from her grasp both Poland., hitherto hussian,  and Posen,. the detachment of which is essential, not merely to the new Polish State, but to all the Allies, and which she will never relinquish except under military pressure on both her frontiers.     Prussia would therefore be left still doni-nant in Central Europe, and fully capable of speedy recuperation.There would appear to be one obvious way cf meeting a situation created by the Russian effort slackening to a dangerous degree and that would be by directing America1s immediate attention to that problem.     America, has a direct interest in that the war on the Eastern front is carried to a successful conclusion, in that she has definitely declared for a united Poland and nust recognise that that can only be attained by force applied at the right spot.     In keeping her to this programme, the Allies have the surest guarantee that she will stick to then to the end,  as Germany will surrender Posen only when she is conpletely crushed and has no outlet for escape.     Moreover, America has of course a sentimental interest in first    going to the support cf the Eew i&apos;JiSBia, and her democratic emotions which have been excited in the last few weeks should lead her to wish for an immediate demonstration of solidarity.The dispatch cf 510,000 American troops to hois si a within the next six months nay be fraught with many technical
2difficulties,, and it would certainly involve the temporary control of the Siberian railway by Americ an railway experts. But it would have this practical advantage over&quot;their des--patch to France,, that they would not have tc be accompanied by food supplies&apos; and would&apos;not be exposed to the dangers of the Atlantic voyage..Politically- it could hot fail to be of the utmost-importance and there can be little    doubt that,  as militant socialism is not a-serious force in the united States, the -American- army would act as a strong counter-irritant in . ussia and help to direct tho democratic tendencies in   oiosia into the right channels.This-scheme which could begin to become operative quite soon, would not in any way prejudice the larger intention cf sending a force on a big scale to Prance.,-    The latter ooulcl net in any case arrive till it had been thoroughly organised and trained, whereas.considerably less training would be required for the smaller- force destined immediately for Aussia.. Acreo^er, it is entirely to t he - inter est of the French to see ahy measures taken to lessen the immediate danger involved.in a Aussian cell apse,  and they could hardly   ail to welcome a scheme for - stiffening the Aussian resistance and especially designed for bringing about.the complete defeat of Germany, which &quot;is as necessary to-their aspirations as to those of the other Alii es.April, 1917.
difficulties-,, and it would certainly involve the temporary control of the Siberian railway by American railway experts. Aut &quot;it would have t hie practical advantage&apos; over &quot;tho ir des-patch to France,, that they would not have to be accompanied by food supplies&apos; and&apos;&quot;would&apos;&quot;not be exposed to the dangers of the Atlantic voyage..Politically it could not foil to&apos;be of the utmost importance and there can be little   doubt that,  as militant socialism is not a - serious force in the united States, the American army would aot as a strong counter-irritant in .ussicv and help to direct tho democratic tendencies in   ussia into the right channels.This scheme which could begin to become operative quite soon, would net in any way prejudice the larger intention cf sending a force on a big scale to Prance..-    The latter could net in any case arrive till it had been thoroughly organised and trained, whereas.considerably less training would be .required for the smaller-force destined immediately for Aussia..: Moreover, it is entirely to the-interest of tAe French to see any measures taken to lessen the&apos; immediate danger involved.in a Pussi an cell apse,  and they could hardly   ail to welcome a scheme f cr - stiff ening the Axis si an resistance and especially designed for bringing about. the complete defeat of Germany, which &quot;is as necessary to-their aspirations as to those of the other Aliies.April, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
