<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/11/0 images: 193-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
p a Q R R S -G.T.-539HH CABINET17Report of a Meeting held at &quot;MO, Downing Street, S.W. on Tuesday, April 24th, 1917, at 3.15 p.m.PRESENTThe Prime   Minister (in the Chair)lord PirrieSir Edward Carson,Dr. AddisonSir J.P0MaclayAdmiral Sir&quot;J:R0&quot;Jellicoe,Rear-Admiral F.C,T*TudorSir Eustace Tennyson-d^yncourt.Lieut-Colonel Sir*M;P,A.Hankey - SecretaryFleet Paymaster P0H,Row, R.N.   - Assistant SecretaryCaptain Clemont Jones - Assistant Secretary.The Meeting was convened to consider the question of &quot;Building an unsinkable Mamuth Wheat Ship (War Cabinet 117, Minute 16, and War Cabinet 125, Minutes 11 and 12 (h)).   -The Third Sea Lord explained, by means of a large scale plan, the construction of the proposed ship.She would be able to make 10 round voyages to North America per year and have carrying capacity of 40,000 tons.     She would hare two sets of engines, one forward and one aft, and have two screws protected by fins so that they would be practically in^-yulherable.LORD PIRRIE said that his firm (Messrs. Earland &amp; Wolff, Belfast) could build such a vessel in 14 months provided that they could get the steel.     They were well equipped to do the work because(a) They had no shortage of labour at Belfast.(b) They had less trouble with the men than elsewhere.(c) They had the keel&quot;already laid down, but unfinished, of a big merchant ship, 800 feet long, which could be completed as a Mart-moth Iheat ship.The SHIPPING CONTROLLER urged that while this One Mammoth ship was building he 6ouldy with the same amount of Steel, build eight standard vessels, some of which would be ready in 4-fr months.It was pointed out, however, that all the eight standard ships Eight be sunk whereas tho mammoth ship, even if torpedoed, would only be damaged.The 2BBE3 MINISTER said that if only four of these Mammoth ship? were now in existence, the danger of the wheat situation would be greatly reduced..It was decided :.-1. That the FIRST  2RLD should ascertain what naval&quot;slips were available for building a Mammoth Ship, e*g. the slip at present occupied by E.M.S.. &quot;HOWE&quot;, and report to
nthe War Cabinet.2. The MINISTER 02 MUNITIONS should notify the - War Cabinet, by. Thursday nest how much more steel he could supply for shipbuilding.LORD PIRRIE raised two further points..    He asked--to be allowed&apos; to finish six ships, launched but uncompleted;.-rupon which work had been stopped owing to the fact that Certificates for. proceeding had been withheld by tho Board of Trade *     These 6 vessels would be converted into cargo&apos;carriers and would give a total carrying capacity of 00,000 tons.He also asked for an extension of his works at Belfast in order to enable him to take on extra work of building standard ships or a Mammoth Ship if required.It was decided(a) That the Board of Trade should issue Certificates for the completion of tho six vessels above referredto.(b) That the.Ministry of  Munitions should grant facilities for&apos;the extension of works desired by Messrs .Harland &amp; Wolff. ..2, Whitehall Gardens, S.Tf. 24th April,1917.   1

</content>
</cab>
