<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/20/28 images: 310-329</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTSECRET. Copy No.W.P. (41) 305(Also C.O.S. (41) 754)December 25, 1941TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 121)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 December 18th, to0700 December 25th,1941[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]
naval SITUATION.General Review.1.   H.M.S. Neptune has been mined and sunk off Tripoli, and H.M.Submarine Perseus has been lost in the Eastern Mediterranean.Three, possibly four, German U-boats have been sunk.Shipping losses have been considerably heavier than of late; largely due to enemy mines off the East Coast.Home Waters and North Atlantic.2. On the 19th, H.M. Destroyer Stanley, escorting a homeward-bound convoy from Gibraltar, was sunk by a U-boat which was subsequently destroyer!by H.M. Sloop Stork. Later in the day, aircraft from H.M.S. Audacity (auxiliaryaircraft carrier) shot down two Eocke Wulf aircraft and damaged anotherwhich were in the vicinity of the convoy. On the 21st, H.M.S. Audacity was torpedoed and sunk 500 miles west of Capt Finisterre.During the night 22nd/23rd, H.M. Destroyer Tetcott (new &quot; Hunt &quot; class)and H.M. Corvette Heartsease were damaged in collision off the west coast ofScotland.The sixteenth Canadian troop convoy has arrived in Home Waters and h.M. Aircraft Carriers Illustrious and Formidable have also arrived, after under-going repairs in America.Our aircraft have damaged 39,000 tons of enemy shipping. Details are given under &quot;Air Situation.&quot;As an example of the escort work done by H.M. ships in the North Sea, thefollowing details of the service of H.M.S. Valorous, of the Rosyth Force, aretypical: Except for a short spell in the Western Approaches, she has beenstationed on the East Coast for the whole period of the war, and has spent592 days at sea in this area and has covered over 93 000 miles. She has escorted159 convoys, and has been in action with enemy aircraft on 69 occasions andwith E-boats twice. She has destroyed three enemy aircraft and probably a fourth. H.M.S. Valorous is a destroyer of the last war and was completed in 1917.Mediterranean.3. During the night of the 18th/19th, H.M. Cruisers Neptune, Aurora andPenelope and H.M. Destroyer Kandahar, while attempting to intercept an enemyconvoy, were mined 20 miles north of Tripoli. Penelope was only slightly damaged, and Aurora was able to return to Malta under her own steam, butNeptune capsized after striking a number of mines. An Italian report statesthat a few survivors have been picked up. H.M. Destroyer Jaguar rescued eightofficers and 166 ratings of Kandahar, which was subsequently sunk.H.M. Submarine Perseus is overdue from patrol and must be considered lost.On the 13th, H.M. Submarine Upright, in the Gulf of Taranto, attackedtwo large north-bound merchant ships escorted by one destroyer, and claimedthree hits on the leading merchant ship and one on the other. Later on the same day H.M. Submarine Utmost obtained one hit on two merchant ships escorted by two destroyers in the same locality On the 11th, H.M. Submarine Truanttorpedoed and probably sank a.large tanker entering Suda Bay (Crete).A belated report states that H.M. Submarine Thrasher torpedoed a 5,000-ton merchant ship, which was last seen on fire with a heavy list, to the eastward ofBrindisi on the 25th November.&quot; Hunt &quot; class destroyers and anti-submarine craft have escorted convoyswhich now run regularly to Tobruk, and a night patrol has been maintained oftBardia and Sollum by Greek destroyers.Our aircraft have sunk or damaged 16,000 tons of enemy shipping. details are given under &quot; Air Situation.&quot;During the week upward of 36.000 tons of French shipping passed gibraltar eastbound and 14,000 tons westbound.
Far Bast.Hong Kong.4. Motor torpedo boats attacked enemy craft crossing from Kowloon Bayto the island of Hong Kong on the 20th, sinking four landing craft with troops on board. Two M.T.Bs. were sunk and one damaged. H.M. Gunboat Tern, anauxiliary patrol vessel, the Oiler Ebonol and Boom Defence Vessel Barlight,which were unable to steam, have been scuttled.H.M. Gunboat Cicala was sunk by dive-bombing on the 21st, and H.M.Destroyer Thracian, which had been damaged, was beached and dismantled.Singapore.5. The Netherlands Submarine 0. 1G, which was returning from successfuloperations off the Northern Malayan coast, entered a British minefield and wasblown up.   There is one survivor.Anti-Submarine Operations.6. The escort of a homeward-bound convoy from Gibraltar obtained afurther success on the 19th (two or possibly three U-boats having already been sunk by them, as reported in last week&apos;s Resume), when H.M. Sloop Storkrammed and sank a U-boat after she had been forced to surface from depthcharge attack. On the 21st an aircraft flown from the auxiliary aircraft carrierwith the convoy sighted a U-boat transferring men from another which had beenholed in the side. Another U-boat was sunk by a naval aircraft off Cape Spartel;one officer survivor was picked up by a corvette.During the night of 18th/19th H.M. Destroyer Jervis sank a U-boat offAlexandria, and on the same night another was damaged or sunk by H.M.Trawler Kingston Cyanite in the same vicinity. A number of other attackswithout definite result were made by surface vessels and aircraft, chiefly in the gibraltar area.Enemy Intelligence.Main Units.7. There is no change in the position of the main units in the WesternBaltic. At Brest Gneisenau left dry dock on the 23rd, and Prinz Eugen hasreturned to dry dock from the fuelling station.Italy.8. Four or five ships of about 5,000 tons are known to have got across from italy to Libya in the past week. One of these was damaged by aircraft but was subsequently towed in.Japan.9. On the 21st December one cruiser and three destroyers with 12 transportswere employed in the Japanese landing at Davao, Philippine Islands. Theforces employed in the main landings in the Lingayen Gulf on the 22nd are said to have been 70 to 90 transports supported by one heavy cruiser, eight destroyers and an aircraft carrier.The forces blockading Hong Kong on the 20th consisted of two cruisers,two destroyers and two torpedo boats.On the occasion of the Japanese landing on Wake Island on the23rd December, two destroyers ran aground.It is assumed that the Japanese have been in occupation of Guam since the20th December.U-boats.10.   A group of U-boats has been operating on the convoy route northwardsfrom Gibraltar in co-operation with Focke Wulf aircraft, and it is possible that[23278] e
other U-boats may be moving towards the Western Atlantic. During the latter part of the period there has been no indication of any U-boats operating in the atlantic south of 300 north. There is evidence from prisoners that one ormore German U-boats refuelled from merchant ships lying in Vigo about themiddle of this month.A considerable number of German U-boats are now operating in theMediterranean, of which four or five were operating near Alexandria during theearly part of the week.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.11. During the week a British and Norwegian ship in a homeward-bound convoy were sunk by U-boats west of Cape St. Vincent and Cape Finisterrerespectively. Another Nonvegian ship was torpedoed in the Gibraltar area. two ships were torpedoed and sunk in the Eastern Mediterranean and several ships have been attacked by Japanese U-boats off the Eastern Pacific coast. On theBritish East Coast six ships have been mined, of which three were sunk and two were beached. A laden British tanker was bombed and abandoned off the Welshcoast, and a Russian ship was sunk by Japanese aircraft in the China Sea.Protection of Seaborne Trade.12. During the week ending the 24th December, 949 ships, including251 Allied and 33 neutral, were convoyed. One armed merchant cruiser, oneocean boarding vessel, four anti-aircraft ships, 84 destroyers (including 27 UnitedStates destroyers) and 79 sloops, corvettes and minesweepers were employed on escort duties.Imports into the United Kingdom during the week ending the 20th Decembertotalled 890,000 tons, compared with 1,043,000 tons during the previous seven days and an average for the past ten weeks of 942,000 tons. Oil imports were290,807 tons.During the month of November imports other than those in tankers were asfollows: Ministry of Food 954,400 tons, Ministry of Supply 1,099,500 tons,Board of Trade 86,500 tons, Eire 72.500.   Total 2,212,900 tons.&apos;British Minelaying.13. During the week mines were laid by surface craft off the Flemish coast,off the Butt of Lewis and in the Bay of Biscay area. Minelaying by aircraft hascontinued both in the Bay of Biscay area and off the German North Sea coast.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.Home Waters.14. Considerable minelaying activity has been shown by the enemy duringthe past week, both E-boats and aircraft having been employed. Aircraft have laid mines off the East Coast between Flamborough Head, the Tyne and the thames Estuary, off Milford Haven and in Liverpool Bay. E-boats which wereactive between Yarmouth and Cromer on the night.of the 19th/20th Decemberwere believed to be minelaying.Eighteen magnetic and 13 acoustic mines have been detonated during theweek, 17 of which were detonated in the Humber and its approaches. The minetotals, including those detonated in Foreign Waters, are 1,638 magnetic,1,207 acoustic and 1,063 contact mines.M mediterranean.During the week ending the 14th December, four minelaying raids weresuspected off Tobruk, and three minelaying raids took place the following week.Seven magnetic mines and five acoustic have been detonated.vichy Merchant Shipping.15. There have been several reports to show that Vichy is arming certainmerchant ships to act as escorts for convoys, and thus relieve the French Navyof this work.
The United States authorities do not intend at present to interfere with vichy ships operating between the Antilles and the United States, South Americaor North Africa.There are four Vichy passenger ships, totalling some 34,000 tons, immobilisedin Buenos Aires. One of these, the A urigny (9,589 tons), is reported to havecaught fire.The Vichy authorities have been warned that, in consequence of the situationin the Far East, ships encountered by British or Allied navies in the Gulf of siam and the China Sea may be sunk unless they can prove that they are sailingwith the special permission of the Allied authorities.MILITARY SITUATION.(An outline map showing Axis operations against Russia is included in this resume as an inset.)Russo-German Campaign.Leningrad Sector,16. The Russians have resumed operations east of Leningrad and southof Tikhvin.Central Sector.17. North of Moscow the Russians have retaken Kalinin and Klin. TheGerman withdrawal in the latter sector was under heavy pressure, and severecasualties were suffered. West of Moscow the Russians have made a further advance to the areas of Volokolamsk and Rusa. The Germans, whose firstwithdrawal in this sector was to conform with a rearward movement further north, are now being pressed hard. South of Moscow the Russians have continued their advance south-west of Aleksin and south-east of Tula. In the latter area the Germans suffered heavy casualties. Strong Russian pressure continues in thearea between Yefremov and Tim.Ukraine.18. The Russians are also attacking in the Donets Basin, but the results arenot yet known. There is no change in the position on the River Mius or atTaganrog.Crimea.19. Sevastopol is holding firm against an attack by six divisions, mostlyRoumanian. It is probable that, unless this attack achieves early success, theenemy forces in the Crimea will go into winter quarters. There is no change,at Kerch.Conclusions.20. There has been no slackening in the Russian counter-offensive, whichextends along nearly the whole of the Central sector from Kalinin to Tim.Pressure is also being applied in the Leningrad area and in the Donets Basin.The initiative remains with the Russians and there seems no immediate prospectof the Germans stabilising their front.Libya.21.   Last week&apos;s Resume covered the period up to the 17th December, onwhich day the Axis forces withdrew from the Gazala position.   General Ritchie&apos;s immediate object was then to prevent the enemy from forming a fresh front onthe line Mekili-Derna.   This object was achieved with conspicuous success.[23278] b 2
22. The remnants of the two German armoured divisions had slipped awaybefore the withdrawal of the main body of four Italian divisions, and had succeeded in making their way to the Derna area under cover of darkness. Ofthe main body, two motorised divisions were directed on Mekili and two infantry divisions took the road north to Derna. Before this withdrawal, General Ritchiehad despatched mobile columns of artillery and lorried infantry, withdetachments of armoured cars, to forestall the enemy on the Derna-Mekili line and harass his retreating forces. The operations of these columns, combined with the relentless pursuit by 4th Indian Division and almost continuousattacks by the R.A.F., effectively prevented General Rommel from collecting hisdisorganised force and forming a new line. Some attempt was made to holdMekili and Derna, but immediate steps were taken to outflank both positions andthey were evacuated on the morning of the 19th December.23. The conduct of these operations was in the hands of Lieutenant-general a. R. Godwin-Austen, commanding 13th Corps; the Headquarters of30th Armoured Corps, which had played the major part earlier in the campaign,had taken over command of the forces investing Bardia and protecting 8th Army&apos;sL. of C. Area. The pursuit continued westward along the desert route fromMekili and along the roads from Derna to Benghazi. The enemy&apos;s columnswere subjected to unremitting air attack and became greatly disorganised. Bythe morning of the 21st December patrols of the 4th Indian Division had reachedCyrene and Apollonia and were advancing on Barce.24. Meanwhile, a small force supported by some American tanks and artillery was moving South-West to join a detachment of the force which, sincethe 24th November, had been in occupation of Jalo. These combined forces were directed on Magrun, 16 miles south of Ghemines, where a large number of enemy aircraft were concentrated to cover the withdrawal. At the same time a mixed column, which included some tanks, was moving along the desert road fromMekili, directed on Benina.25. By the 22nd December there were indications that the enemy wasattempting to hold a position east of Benghazi with his Italian formations,presumably with the object of covering the evacuation of stores and material from the Benghazi area. There were also indications that the bulk of whatremained of the German Afrika Corps was in the Antelat-Jedabya area, and it seemed likely that General Rommel was trying to form a front, for the timebeing at least, about Jedabya.26. This attempt was, however, short lived. A raiding party destroyed 37enemy aircraft at Jedabj^a on the night of the 21st/22nd December, and on the22nd other troops occupied Antelat and sent detachments on to Beda Fomm, some17 miles further to the West. These penetrations probably caused the enemy todecide on further withdrawal and though he attacked strongly on the following day in the Antelat area, using 35 tanks and 150 M.T. vehicles, general auchinleck thought that it was only a delaying action to cover withdrawal fromBenghazi.27. By the evening of the 23rd December the 4th Indian Division had occupied Barce and was moving on towards Benghazi. Columns of the7th Armoured Division Support Group occupied Benina and regime on the afternoon of the 23rd December and the Royal Dragoons occupied Benghazi on the morning of the 24th December. It would seem that our operations around Soluk,together with the occupation of Benghazi, have separated the German andItalian forces and that little fight is left in the latter. Further South, on the evening of the 23rd December, the bulk of the German force, estimated as 40-50tanks, 800 vehicles, 16 guns and about 25 A.T. guns had withdrawn some 24 miles south-west from Antelat, where they had been in action that afternoon.28. The German remnant will almost certainly try to get away, but its dailylosses in transport vehicles have been heavy, and it may be possible to bring itto battle, in spite of our own tremendous maintenance problems.
The Far East.Malay a.29. In the North-East there has been little activity, apart from patrolencounters. On the 21st December the 8th Indian Infantry Brigade was with-drawn to a new area in Pahang about 60 miles north-east of Kuala Lumpur,leaving at Babong, about 90 miles to the North, a rearguard with an armouredtrain, whose task is to withdraw down the railway, demolishing it as they go.The Japanese have now advanced down the East coast as far as Dungun(120 miles south of Kota Bharu) without opposition.30. Pressure by the enemy advancing down the West coast, which had beenheavy, has ceased in the last two days. Withdrawal by stages of the 11th indian division has been carried out, and they are now reorganised in the Ipoh area east of the Perak River.31. Penang was successfully evacuated on the 18th December, air raidcasualties have totalled 600 killed and 1,000 wounded.32. The estimated Japanese strength in this area remains at four divisions and one Tank Regiment.Sarawak.33. All denial schemes, including the destruction of Kuching aerodrome,have been completed.Hong Kong.34. The Japanese have succeeded in making further landings, and theWestern half of the island is in their hands, with our troops holding threeisolated areas in the South, Central and North-West districts.On three occasions we have taken offensive action, but, although the first had some success, the last two failed owing to the exhaustion of our troops. Weshelled and destroyed one of the two oil installations on the mainland, but theother cannot be bombarded on account of its proximity to a civil hospital.Bombardment by dive-bombing, mortars and artillery has been carried outpersistently by the enemy and the situation must be regarded as having reached a critical stage. One of our main ammunition and supply depots has beensurrounded. Our troops are very tired and the water and transport situation isgrave. One report on the 23rd December stated that little more than one day&apos;supply of water was available. Health and conduct of civilians is good, butcasualties have been roughly 4,000, of whom 1,000 have been killed.Philippine Islands.35. Japanese landings in force and with tanks have been repeated in the philippines. It is estimated that the Japanese are employing up to five divisions in these operations.Western Pacific.36.   In Portuguese Timor Australian troops now occupy the airfield of Dilli.The Japanese are reported to have withdrawn from Taraua in the NorthGilbert Islands.Persia.37. There has been some fighting between the Kurds and Persian troopsnorth of Sinneh. The situation is still obscure, but it appears that the Kurdshave been forced to retire North.   Our troops took no part in these operations.Intelligence.Germany.38. As has been announced, Field-Marshal von Brauchitsch has been retiredand succeeded as Commander-in-Chief of the German Army by Hitler himself.Hitler has been, since February 1938, Supreme Commander of the German Armed
Forces, and has exercised control of the armed forces through the followingmachinery : &apos;(a) A Supreme Combined Defence Staff under Field-Marshal Keitel, and(b) Separate Commanders-in-Chief for the Army, Navy and Air Force.Although the Supreme Combined Defence Staff has always been in a positionto issue orders to the Commander-in-Chief of the Army, the latter had a direct responsibility to Hitler, and naturally the views of the General Staff carried verygreat weight. The principal result of the change in effect is to make KeitelCommander-in-Chief under Hitler an analogy is the position of the eldervon Moltke under Kaiser Wilhelm I in 1870. It is impossible at this stage todecide why the change has been made or to assess its possible consequences.Coming as it does, however, on the heels of the reverses which have been sustained in Russia and in Libya, it is bound to prove a shock to the German public andfrom our point of view it certainly seems a hopeful sign.France and Spain.39. A large number of rumours are in circulation regarding the entry ofGerman forces into Spain, but these may be attributed to the German war ofnerves. There is no confirmation of any large-scale movement of German troops from Russia to France. On the other hand, there are indications that one low-category division may be in process of transfer to the Eastern front fromthe West.Balkans.40. The German rumour campaign is as active in Turkey as it is in theIberian Peninsula. This must also be an example of the war of nerves. Therehave been several reports of German preparations for future military action basedon Bulgaria.Italy.41. Press reports stating that martial law has been declared in a numberof areas in Southern Italy are probably due to the fact that these areas have beendeclaimed war zones, a term which corresponds to our defence areas. the identification in recent months of a large number of coast defence battalions andso-called &quot;anti-parachute&quot; detachments also appears to indicate increasingnervousness about the possibility of invasion. These units are home defence troops of secondary value.Bulgaria.42. It is reported that a proportion of the men of various annual classeswho were released in the autumn are now being recalled to the colours. There is,however, no sign of a general mobilisation. There have been no fresh troop movements towards the Turkish frontier, and the 4-5 divisions stationed in this area are stated to be kept at a distance of 20 kilom. from the actual frontier.Far East.43. Reliable reports indicate that a further mobilisation has been inprogress in Japan since the 15th December and it seems probable that as a resulta further ten divisions will be ready for service within two months. this increase will raise the total strength of the Japanese army to its estimated ceiling of 72 divisions.Japanese resources can support in addition 20 independent brigades, 18 tankregiments, 15 depot divisions and the necessary proportion of Corps and Armytroops.44. The course of operations during the past week shows clearly the determination of the enemy to secure a speedy conquest of Singapore and the philippines. There are also indications of preparations for an attack on burma and of operations to the South and South-East from bases in the Caroline andMarshall Islands.It is estimated that they have approximately one division concentrated inthe Marshall Islands at Jaluit.   It is possible therefore that the Japanese intend
to move against Fiji or to carry out a further penetration of the Gilbert islands and possibly the Phoenix group, m order to interrupt communications betweenAustralia, New Zealand and America.Netherlands East Indies.45 It has been reported that an army under General Yamashita has beenformed for operations against the N.E.I. There is no indication yet as to itslocation, but it is possible the enemy intends to concentrate it in Formosa andHainan.AIR SITUATION.General Review.46. Bad weather again considerably restricted bombing operations against targets in Germany and occupied territory. One daylight and two night attacks were made on enemy warships in Brest.In Libya our bombers and fighters continued to harass retreating enemycolumns, and made many successful attacks on enemy landing grounds.In Malaya the enemy&apos;s main effort has been directed against the Kedah front.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.47. Bomber Command despatched 72 sorties. Fighter Command flew247 sorties against shipping and over occupied territory. Attacks on shippingare reported under &quot; Coastal Operations.&quot;48. On the 18th December, heavy bombers, escorted by long-range fighters,dropped 135 tons of HE. bombs, including five of 4,000 lb. and 18 of 2,000 lb.,on naval targets at Brest. The weather was good and visibility excellent. the attack was pressed home- in spite of opposition from enemy fighters and very heavy A.A. fire. Photographs taken during the attack show that at leastfour sticks of bombs straddled the dry docks in which the battle cruisers werelying. It is thought that altogether 13 bombs burst in the vicinity of the drydocks, but no direct hits were observed. During this operation our aircraft destroyed in combat ten enemy aircraft, probably destroyed three and damagedsix.  We lost five bombers and one fisrhter.49. On three days of the week a total of 21 Hampdens were despatched toattack targets in North-West Germany and aerodromes in Holland, but they were obliged to abandon their tasks owing to insufficient cloud cover.Night.50. Owing to bad weather, bombing operations were carried out on fournights only. One hundred and eighty-five sorties were flown as compared with548 in the previous week. Nearly 200 tons of H.E. bombs and 15,000 incendiaries were released. The principal objectives were the enemy warships at Brest, thenaval base at Wilhelmshaven, the industrial area of Cologne, and the docks atOstend and Dunkirk.51. Following the daylight attack referred to in paragraph 48, the warships at Brest were attacked on two nights by a total of 58 aircraft, whichreleased 90 tons of H.E. bombs and nearly 5,000 incendiaries. Results were generally unobserved owing to cloud on the first night and a smoke screen on thesecond, but bursts were seen in the dock area and some fires were started.52. Cologne was attacked by 60 aircraft, which dropped 60 tons of H.E.bombs and over 6,000 incendiaries. Thick cloud was encountered, but some bursts were seen in the town.53. Over 20 tons were dropped on Wilhelmshaven. Drifting cloud madepm-pointing difficult, but bomb flashes and the glow of fires were seen in the target area.I . 54. Attacks on a lighter scale were made on the docks at Ostend andDunkirk, and on the Donges oik refinery, near St. Nazaire.
United Kingdom.55.   Fighter Command flew 1,176 sorties by day and 229 sorties by night.56. Enemy activity was on a somewhat larger scale than in recent weeks,particularly at night. Offensive operations were principally directed against shipping, though a few bombs were dropped in coastal areas.Coastal Operations.57. Coastal Command flew 177 patrols (265 sorties) and provided 35 convoy escorts (58 additional sorties). Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Commandtotalled 312 (749 sorties).58. On the morning of the 23rd, a tanker of about 12,000 tons steeringwestward was attacked by a Sunderland with depth charges 180 miles north-west of Cape Finisterre. The tanker altered course to the eastward and reducedspeed to eight knots, leaving a large oil track. On the following morning, shewas again sighted (about 10 miles east of Cape Ortegal) and appeared to bedown by the stern. She was attacked with depth charges and anti-submarinebombs by a Sunderland, and later a Beaufort hit her amidships with a torpedo.Two hours afterwards she appeared to be beached close to the Spanish coast.59. Hudsons and Beauforts made several attacks on enemy shipping, withthe following results : Description.	Estimated Tonnage.	Locality.	Results.Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Tanker Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Coastal Vessel Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ...	3,000 2,500 6,000 8,000 3,000 3,000 200 1,500 3,500	Off Standlandet...... Off Stavanger Off Aalesund Off Den Helder...... Off Den Helder...... Off Den Helder...... Off Den Helder...... Off Hardanger Fjord Off Lister Light......	One hit. One hit near funnel. At least one hit. ^ All were hit  by   cannon &apos;    and machine-gun fire. Bombed and machine gun-ned. Attacked with torpedo and machine gun fire.   Eesults unobserved owing to bad visibility.In addition, Spitfires attacked a convoy of four ships off the Dutch Coast,and one vessel and one flak ship are claimed as damaged.Mediterranean.Cyrenaica.60. Enemy landing grounds and retreating transport columns were theprincpal targets of our air forces during the week. On the 18th and 19th,Blenheims, Bostons, Hurricane bombers and Tomahawks attacked enemytransport, estimated at 2,000 vehicles, withdrawing westward from Mekili.Beaufighters attacked dense traffic between Barce and Benghazi, and long-rangeHurricanes inflicted heavy casualties on lorry-borne troops in the El Agheilaarea.   Binina and Marawa aerodromes were bombed.61. On the 20th, adverse weather and the enemy&apos;s withdrawal beyond the range of fighter escorts considerably restricted, bombing attacks on M.T. a formation of 12 Blenheims with fighter escort was intercepted near Barce by15 Me. 109s, which forced them to jettison their bombs, and shot down fourBlenheims and five Tomahawks; three Me. 109s were destroyed, and probably a fourth.62. Subsequent day bombing was directed against enemy aerodromes,although fighters continued their successful attacks on transport south
4 P&apos; fi55Benghazi. Following a heavy night attack by 24 Wellingtons on the landingaround at Magrun, 48 miles south of Benghazi, day bombers, on the 22nd,destroyed at least six aircraft, including Ju. 52 transports, and damaged many others; Tomahawks attacked aircraft which were taking off and landing and destroyed nine and damaged seven, without loss. On the following day theydestroyed a further eight on the ground. At Nofilia, further west, Beaufightersdestroyed two aircraft on the ground and damaged many others, besides inflictingcasualties on ground personnel.63. Forty-two Wellingtons operated against Benghazi on the night of the18th/19th: five dropped bombs in the harbour area as a diversion from others,which were engaged in minelaying. Berca aerodrome and M.T. concentrationswere also attacked. On the following night ten Wellingtons started many firesamong dispersed aircraft on Binina aerodrome.64. Enemy bombers were not much in evidence during the week, although they made a heavy attack on Tobruk on the night of the 19th/20th, causing little damage.  One of our forward landing grounds was unsuccessfully attacked.65. At five of the enemy landing-grounds occupied or raided by our ground forces a total of 174 enemy aircraft were captured or destroyed. In addition,100 damaged aircraft were found at Binina, some&apos;of which were probably relicsof our previous advance.Tri/politania.66. Blenheims from Malta made a successful daylight attack on Zuara,where goods sheds were hit and trucks destroyed. A large schooner in the harbour was attacked later in the week, and probably hit, by three Blenheims,one of which crashed after striking the mast. On the 22nd eleven Blenheimsbombed westbound M.T. carrying troops and stores between Sirte and Misurata.At least 12 vehicles were destroyed, and bombs also fell in a closely-packedM.T. park and on two A.A. positions.67. Tripoli (L) was the principal target for our night bombers, and wasraided on five nights of the week. Two of the attacks were on Castel Benitoaerodrome, where hangars and administrative buildings were hit and at leastseven aircraft were destroyed. On the night of the 23rd/24th four aircraftmaintained a 10-hour nuisance raid over the town. On the following night nineWellingtons attacked the Spanish quay, scoring many hits and causing fires anda large explosion. Naval aircraft also took part in these attacks and laid minesoutside the harbour.68. M.T. parks and air personnel barracks at Misurata were bombed byseven Wellingtons; many bombs, including three of 4,000 lbs., fell in the target area, and on an ordnance depot and buildings, where four fires broke out.69.   On the night of the 18th/19th naval torpedo bombers scored hits on two8,000-ton merchant ships north of Horns (L).-Malta.70. Wellingtons and Blenheims flew many sweeps in search of enemy shipping and in co-operation with our naval forces. Weather conditions wereoften bad and no successful attacks were made.71. Enemy activity against the Island was on an increased scale, both by day and by night. The Grand Harbour was twice attacked in daylight by fourou. 88s, escorted by about 20 fighters, and a merchant ship was hit. Otherdaylight attacks caused slight damage to barracks and civilian property. Fiveenemy aircraft were destroyed, one at least by A.A. fire; we lost five Hurricanes.72.   Attacks were also made nightly by up to 12 aircraft.   The most serious damage was done at Luqa Aerodrome, where a Wellington was destroyed andothers damaged,  while  four  craters  in  the  main   runway  grounded14 Wellingtons which were waiting to take off.   It is probable that sea mines were dropped on one or two nights.[23278] &quot; c -
The Far Bast.Thailand.73. On the 21st, our fighters destroyed seven enemy bombers on the aerodrome at Prachuab Kirikhund, 150 miles south of Bangkok, and machine-gunned the aerodrome at Huahin, 100 miles south of Bangkok.Burma.74. On the 23rd, enemy aircraft bombed Rangoon for the first time, startingseveral fires in the town.  Ten enemy aircraft are believed to have been shot down.Malay States.75. Our aircraft continued their daily reconnaissances of the coastal andbattle areas, and provided escorts for naval units.76. On the 23rd. our aircraft attacked Sungei Patani Aerodrome, butresults were unobserved owing to poor visibility.77. During the week, enemy aircraft made several raids on Ipoh. A petroldump and an ammunition dump were destroyed, and the aerodrome was slightly damaged. Kuala Lumpur Aerodrome was attacked on the 21st by 13 enemy bombers escorted by ten fighters, and on the 22nd by 18 aircraft, but only slight damage was caused to the aerodrome. Two enemy&apos;&apos; aircraft were destroyed, andone was probably destroyed.   We lost four fighters, but three pilots are safe.Borneo.78. Our aircraft and those of the Netherlands East Indies carried outreconnaissances of the north and west coasts of Borneo and of the islands offthe coasts.79. On the 18th, six Glenn Martins attacked Japanese naval forces offMiri, scoring a hit and a near miss on a cruiser, and two near misses on a largetransport vessel, thought to be an aircraft (or seaplane) carrier. A Glenn Martinand an enemy aircraft were shot down. On the 24th five Blenheims bombed anenemy force off Kuching, in Sarawak. One direct hit was obtained on the sternof a transport vessel.80. On the 19th the enemy continuously bombed Pontianak on the westcoast of Borneo. The town was considerably damaged. On the same day15 aircraft bombed Kuching Aerodrome, where a petrol store was set on fire.Singkawang Aerodrome was heavily attacked on the 23rd. The aerodrome was rendered unserviceable, but no aircraft were destroyed.Hong Kong.81. Throughout the 18th, the Island was subjected to heavy bombing.Government buildings, army barracks, telephone communications and oil installations were seriously damaged.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.82. A few bombs were dropped on two days and five nights of the week in coastal districts of North-East, East and South-East England, with a fewincidents in South-West England and the West Coast of Wales.Some damage was done to property but no important incident has beenreported.Casualties.83. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600, the 24thDecember, are one killed and six seriously injured.
APPENDICES I, II and III, will be published monthly,and APPENDIX IV fortnightly.APPENDIX V.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.23rd December. Motor Fishing Vessel Margaret Hamilton was sunk in collision in Greenwich Harbour.ISth December-25th December. At Hong Kong. M[L No. 80 burnt out andSkid-towing vessel Indira sunk.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 7 killed, 9 missing, 3 wounded.Ratings : 23 killed, 36 missing. 2 wounded.&apos; 23278]d
Operational Aircraft Battle Casualties.(These figures are based on the best information available at the time of goingto press.) . . , , &apos;\0700 hours, Thursday, 18th December, 1941, to 0700 hours, Thursday,25th December, 1941.Metropolitan Area.British. In the Air. On the (jrouud.Bombers...       ...      ...      ...      ...       ... 9Fighters................. 2Coastal   ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 3Army Co-OperationTotal.........       ... 14ProbablyGerman. Destroyed.        Destroyed. Damaged.Bombers.........       ... 7 ... 7Fighters     ........... 10 4 4MiscellaneousTotal      ...       ... 17 4 11No account is taken of aircraft destroyed on the ground.Middle East.0700 hours, Tuesday, 16th December, 1941, to 0700 hours, Tuesday,23rd December, 1941.British. In the Air.   . On the Ground.Bombers...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ... 10 2 &apos;,Fighters...       ...      ...      ...      ...       ... 24CoastalTotal......       ...       ... 34ProbablyGerman. Destroyed. Destroyed. Damaged.Bombers  ...       ...    &apos; ...       ... 5 1 fighters............        11 2 6MiscellaneousTotal     ......        16 3 11Of the above totals 2 Bombers, 1 Fighter and 4 unknown type aircraft were destroyed and 2 Bombers damaged by A.A. fire.probably Italian. Destroyed. Destroyed^ Damaged.Bombers  ...Hghlers   ......      .... 2 3 5Miscellaneous     ...       ...       ... ... ... 1Total    ...... 2 3 6 in addition to the above 1 unidentified German or Italian aircraft casualty was reported from the Middle East.
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week from Air Reconnaissance and Intelligence Services : Germany.Berlin. In the raid of 7th/8th November one side of the large store&quot; Kaufhaus des Westens,&quot; situate in the Tauentzien Strasse (akin to&quot; Selfridges &quot;), and the Reuter building were severely damaged.Occupied France.Brest. In recent night attacks no bombs have fallen on the town and the damage has been confined to the dock area. On the night of 11th/12th Decemberone bomb fell about 15 metres from the end of one of the dxy docks.Photographs taken during the daylight attack on the 18th December showthat at least four sticks of bombs straddled the dry docks in which the scharnhorst and the Gneisenau were lying. It is thought that altogether13 bombs burst in the immediate vicinity of the dry docks, but no direct hits were observed.Italy.Naples. In raids in November the Town Hall and Exchange were hit andafter the raid on the 27th/28th rail services to Rome were once more affected.Trains were routed from the Mergellina Station and were upwards of 15 hourslate arriving in Rome.A photographic reconnaissance of Naples reveals that since the11th November the following major damage has been inflicted : (i) A direct hit has been registered on the largest building of a big factorynorth-west of the railway sheds,(ii) A large area, of the roof has been removed from a big building in thesouth-west corner of the Olificio Figure Depot.(iii) Extensive damage to a group of small warehouses near the railway station.(iv) Further damage to the royal arsenal, particularly to three large buildings, one of which has been gutted.   Half the arsenal has been completely destroyed,(v) Further severe damage to the torpedo factory, including the demolition of some factory buildings adjoining this factory,(vi) To the east of the Alfa Romeo Works a long building and two small buildings have been gutted, and the south-east corner of the AlfaRomeo Works themselves has been damaged and has the roof missing.(vii) At the A.G.I.P. oil storage depot one tank has been gutted and threedamaged.(viii) Buildings to the south-east of the gas works in the west of the town havebeen destroyed, including a large block which has been gutted by fire,although the gas works themselves are still operating,(ix) The roofing of some large buildings in the southern part of the I.M.A.M.Airframe Works has been shattered, probably by blast,(x) A large hole is visible in the roof of the main railway station and halfa mile to the north of the station two blocks of warehouses and a smallfactory have been destroyed or seriously damaged.Sea Mining.A vessel employed on mine destruction damaged itself on entering the port of Bordeaux on the 5th December and has had to be dry-docked.






</content>
</cab>
