<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/8/16 images: 158-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DCCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT ANIttG-MAJESTY * S GOVERNMENTKj? R E g.(^1(41)16.jfiroh, 1941Copy No.FOOD SITUATION OF THE UNITED kingdom monthly REPORT. JQR JANUARY 1941I. ARRIVALS &amp; SKTBviENTS&apos; LAGGING BEHIND IROGRAMMB(i) Arrivals (as recorded in the Trade Accounts andexoluding itemsnot in the&quot; import programme) in thefour months Sep. -Bee. 1940 give a monthly average of13)5 less than l/l2th of the revised import programme.(ii) January arrivals (as estimated by the Ministry ofFood and excluding items: not in the import programme); were only ................ v.&quot;-................ vv.-......This is the Icwest monthly figure since the beginningof the war-and represents only 66$ of l/l2th of the revised import programme.(iii) Estimated arrivals ini February and March are 12$below the revised import programmes for these months.(i) Allocations of shipping for*February were........Actual shipments are estimated at...............giving a deficiency of 12$.(ii) Provisional allocations of shipping for MarchShipments are unlikely to exceed................(i) The maximum quantity of meat will be shipped from south America, involving a transfer of refrigeratedtonnage from Australian and New Zealand routes.But the effect of the shorter haul &quot;will be fcoincrease 2nd year of war imported supplies, by only(ii) Tonnage has been diverted from steel to wheat for february.,and March loadings.     No cereals are to be imported from countries other than North-Americaunless of a type which North America cannot supply.*000 tons1115851113910001516130030tfGS&apos;II. LOSSES DUE TO ENEMY ACTION-- u(i) Fifteen ships.carrying food and &quot;feed were lost inJanuary.     The quantity lost....................was the lowest monthly figure since May 1940.(ii); Sinkings during the five months Sep. ,4D-/jaiim &apos; 41 haveamounted to.7$ of total arrivals.Damage during January was small.     Animal-feedprocessing plant in Bristol was the only importantitem.67
III.    COMMODITY SUPPLY POSITIONENERGY POODSWheat &apos;stpcksLcontinue to fail;    sales of whole rice are being(&quot;carbohydrates)   reduced until the end of April;    sugar stocks are at a seasonalhigh level;    potatoes are in ample supply.Wheat &amp; Flour; (i) The fall in -wheat stocks is expected to continue&quot;&apos;..&apos;     during February, but it is hoped that shipments from Canada for arrival in April will check the______decline.   Reserve stocks at the end of April are&quot;forecast at&quot; 1208&quot; weeks&apos; supply (making no allowance for air-raid damage).     Future shipmsr.are being planned to increase the reserve stocksv. . to fifteen weeks&apos; supply by the&apos; end of June.,(ii) To increase flour stocks millers have been&apos;&quot;&apos; instructed to work to maximum capacity.An increase in the demand for oatmeal has result from &quot;the., publicity campaign and the subsidisedLow arrivals are forecast for February/April.Sales of whole rice will be reduced so that stocwill last till the end of April.,    Substantialarrivals are,expected in May0(i) A gradual decline in stock?; is inevitable duringthe remaining months of the S-esond year of warbecause of the seasonal nature of home productiand imports. - &apos; :(ii) The&quot;1940/41 home production seasonvas completed in January. . Total output, at 480, thousand tons(refined &quot;value) was slightly less-than the1939/40&quot; output but 5L70 greater than the averagethe&quot; five years 1934/35 - 1938/390________ .&apos;   -   The December census of stocks, revealed a smallersurplus over estimated .human requirements thanbeen anticipated and the programme for thedisposal of surplus potatoes has been curtailedStocks of oilseeds are falling but human consumption may not beaffected;     the butter ration is being increased^ giving thepossibility of -building.up stocks of margarine-,.Oilseeds &amp; (i) Imports during January, were low;    stocks of softOatmeal:Rice:Sugar;Potatoes:ENERGY FOODS(fats)Vegetable Oils;oils did not show the expected improvement and oil stocks declined more than had been foreseen(li) The outlook for soft oils is reasonably good inspite of heavy sinkings in the early part ofFebruary:   the hard oil position is weak.(iii) Oilseeds and oils for edible purposes and for essential industrial uses are given priority in&apos; the import_programm.ec . . -----Margarine; A small increase in..stocks took place in january the increase in the butter ration should make possible, an expansion of stocks^Butter; (i) Heavy arrivals in the early part of February an....large: stocks afloat have madq-possible an incre-&apos; :.. incthe domestic ration from 2 ozs^ to 4 ozs. Pehead per week, as from 10th-.March.(ii) Any delays in loading butter in New Zealand will result in embarassingly large stocks in thatcountry.
Apart from &quot;bacorij the supply position of animal protein   foods is very weak0Supplies of meat will not he sufficient to maintain a l/2d, ration duringPerpr-iaryApril,   For bacohy the. immediate (but not the more distant) outlookis favourable0 -.Meat:(i)   Severe weather which delayed transport reduoed supplies in some areas belou requirements under the 1 /2d0 ration^ssues. of.:-?orned beef as a supplement to butchers&apos;butmeatwersmaBacon:Fish :Cheese:(i)(ii)   Imports and-supplies of - home-killed meat for February/Aprilare      present forecast at&apos; only slightly belay the estimated requirements at the present very lew level of consumption,,but these forecasts, may nob be realized^(iii)   Additional supplies. of - frozen meat from South Americaduring May/August ?/ill be offset by smaller home^killed.    suppliesdue^j^ou-the. asute shortage of feeding stuffs0(i)   Despite, the acute -shortage of feed concentrates, home production has not yet shown the expected increase.   In...   .      fact home.-production-is. espteoted to decline in the first half of March,;;-;&apos; - -. -:;-&apos;. -(ii)   AfterrAprilr.;,a:-severe decline-.ih home production is fore-seen and it may not be possible to maintain the presentation during the summer months(i)   Supplies of fresh and frozen were at a seasonal low level in January and a slight improvement is expectedup to the end of May0  - British landings are approximately25/o of pre-war quantities 0(ii)   Stocks of canned salmon are smaller than at any period since the outbreak of war;   releases for civilian:.&apos;.&apos;.      consumption are being continued at a reduced rate,.Civilian consumption in January was slightly less than5C a of pre-war quantities^     There is little&apos;prospect ofany increase: in the distribution to piviiians during thenext three months0Home production is shov/ing a seasonal increase but output is less than last year and total supplies,, includingimported ^eggsj; continue. to:;be very short0Milk and home grown vegetables .are.;,still unrestricted&apos;;&apos; but all the otherprotective foods are in very shor,t;,supply^-If oranges from Spain do notarrive very little fresh fruit will be available in February/ApriloFresh Milk:   (i)   Owingto, the acute shortage of feed concentrates, theprospects of maintaining&apos; an adequate supply of freshmilk after the spring flush are disquieting^,(ii)   Sales of milk for liquid consumption during &quot;&quot;January were: - - - the highest ever recorded .jf.$c -&quot;any month,       - -(iii)   Quantities of milk distributed under the National MxLk   *Scheme have increased steadily in recent months and inJanuary (together with school milk) amounted to li^^o of&apos;&quot;&apos;   tcial liquid sales. -&apos;-.(iy). r An April/September 191.1 programme&quot; for the utilisation of&apos; &apos;&quot;;    &apos;&apos; &apos;        &apos; milk for manufacture lias been drawn up0     Cheese andcondensed whole milk are scheduled to receive 8&apos;Qjo of theestimated total quantity of manufacturing milk in GreatBritain^It is unlikely that distribution (now only 25/S and20/o of ncjrmal for the three types) of condensed milk for domestic consumption,will be increased during thenext few monthsu -%CondensedLlk
Fresh Fruit: Supplies of fresh fruit during Fobruxry/April will consist almostentirely of limited quantities of home grown apples and some!    oranges which nay arrive from Spain.     The purchase of thelatter is still the subject of negotiations, ^CannedFruitThe reduction in consumption has become more marked.Dried Fruit: Larger quantities of currents and sultanas should be availablefor distribution in the early spring.OTHERCOHODITIESANIMALfeeds&quot;Fresh There are ample supplies of carrots, turnips, swedes and vegetables;   cabbages available at reasonable priceso     Emergency stocksof carrots are being accumulated in seven large towns.Tea: Stooks were stationary during January, but with delayedimports arriving during the next two months, stooks should show a marked improvenerit by April,,S tar ch; Supplies for human consumption and manufacture will have tobe further restricted,,(i)   The feeding stuffs situation is already&quot;1 very serious and it will bevery aaute in the summer when the&apos; stook carrying capacity ofpastures declines,(ii) It will certainly be necessary substantially to devalue the Aprilcerdal coupon and probably necessary to devalue the April proteincoupon.(iii)   The low level of spring and summer rations envisaged in the existing scheme cannot be maintained unless priority imports of feed concen-trates are substantially increased (at the expense of imports ofnon food and feed items&quot;) above the level provided in the current import programme.IV, DISTRIBUTIONTRANSPORT &amp;    (i) Some improvement has taken place in rail tranoport.WAREHOUSINGtimesJ damaged by being conveyed in open trucks^Foods are, at(ii) More v/arehouses are being requisitioned and some new buildingserected to store in the interior of the country approximately300 thousand tons of food at present in port areas.     Approximately500 thousand tons of Government owned stocks have already been storedin requisitioned warehouses,   :RETAIL FOOD   The retail food price index fell by one point in both December and January?In January the change was due to lower egg prices, the effect of which wasonly partially off-set by increases in fish arid potato prices.PRICESRATIONEDFOODS:There were ho rationing changes during January,    The amount of butterwhich can be taken up under the combined butter/nargarine ration (6 ozs*)will be increased from 2 02s, to A ozs9 per head per week as from 10thMarch,,UNRATIONED A Departmental Committee is drawing up proposals for the better distribution PJ22hL cf non-rationed foods such as cheese, eggs, sausages, jam and marmalade.Approximately 75,,000 meals a day are now being served in all communityll?5SSSf.        feeding centres^     Schemes for centres in 30 towns have been approved,,&apos;      w^linistry of Food,Neville House,Page Street, S.W.1.3rd March. 19414.
no.	Commodity.	1939	1940		1941	1941			Weekly -fcotal consumption	No.of weeks&quot; supply; basis February 1941 consumption.				End  End Aug. Dec.	End    End  End  End    End    End Mar. June Sept. Oct.   Nov.   Dec.		End Jan.	End Feb.(b)	End March (b)	End kpril (b)	1934/35. Feb.1941 to       fore-1938/39   cast average													End Jan. 1941	End April 1941(b)	No.1	Wheat &amp; flour (as wheat)(c)					sand Tons 1622(1615)	1591(1570)	1601(1562)	114.8(d) 125.0(d)			1		1356   858	1445 1982	2142   2068   1938   1867	1731					15.8	12.8(12.5)	2 3 4	Barley(inc.farm &amp; brewers&apos;stocks Maize Oilcake	1085   671 207   103 185    80	356   267 92   185 57   153	1244   1056    907    746 292    284    248    265 215    208    187    152	555 187 129	440 (439) 161 (160) 135 (128)	310 (308) 150 (146) 135 (125)	233 (229) 57   (49) 89   (73)	32,3       31.0 63.1       26.5 32.1       27.0	17.9 7.0 4.8	7.5 (7.4) 2.2 (1.8) 3.3 (2.7)	2 3 45 6 7 8 9	Oilseeds Vegetable oils Whale oil Margarine Lard and compound lard	224   180 69    40 293   227 4 not a^ 2 not ai	173   272 50     79 216   328 available 6 -available 12	299    221    169    189 83      92      83      90 289    275    263    251&apos; 14      18      24      22 21      15      12      11	146 84 237 25 9	136 (133) 82   (81) 227 (227) 21   (21) 12   (12)	153 (144) 85   (85) 215 (215) 25   (25) 14   (14)	116   (99) 87   (84) 200 (200) 32   (32) 17   (17)	30.0       29.0 11.8        15.0 2.8         2.5 3,6         8.0 3.9         3,4	5,0 5,6 94,8 5.1 2.7	4.0 (3.4) 5.8 (5.6) 80.0 (80.0) 4.0 (4.0) 5.0 (5.0)	5 6 7 8 910 11 12	Meat (e)(f) Corned Beef Bacon &amp; ham(h)(i)	64   118 26    36 7    27	164  156 37    43 32    26	159    161      94     64 87      96      99    103 16      12      20      22	41 101 22	56 (b) 97   (97) 3\   30)	65 (b) 105 (105) 35   (34)	50 (b) 121 (121) 37   (36)	42.9       30.3 1.0         (g) 10.4         7.5	3.2 (g) 2.9	3.9 (b) (g) (g) 4.9 (4.8)	10 11 1213	Canned salmon	24    42	41    33	23      22      19      20	18	19   (19)	18   (18)	18   (18)	1,1         0.8	24,0	24.0 (24.0)	1314	Sugar (as refined)	287   362	290   374	274    416    532     629	658	659 (655)	637 (625)	584 (562)	48.4(3)   27.1(3)	24.3	21.6 (20.8)	1415	Rice	60 not available50		42      37      38      37	36	29   (29)	23   (23)	20   (19)	2,2          3,0	12.0	6.7 (6.3)	1516 17 18	Butter Chee se(inc.farm and wholesale) Condensed Milk	24    26 23    21 not avaiJ	67    51 21    19 .able    31	.   22      18      12      25 36      31      21      14 59      57      48      44	26 17 38	35   (35) . 18   (18) 32   (32)	39   (38) 22   (22) 29   (29)	37   (35) 22   (21) 32   (32)	9,5         3,3 3.7         2,5 5.2(3)     2.4(,1)	7.9 6,8 15,8	11.2 (10.6) 8.8 (8.4) 13.3 (13.3)	16 17 1819	Eggs in shell	13      2	0      8	4       2        1       1	0	0	0&apos;	2     (2)	8,1         4.6	0	0.4 (0.4)	1920	Potatoes(e)(k)	0 1789	640     30 3172   2854   2484   2120		1654	1310(1310)	967 (967)	589 (589)	73,0(1)   82,0(1)	20.2	7,2 (7.2)	2021	Dried Fruit	35    57	-57    23	19      15        9      13	22	22   (22)	-  21   (20)	20   (18)	3,3         2.6	6.7	6.1 (5.5)	2122	Tea	71    77	65    36	40      44      54      53	55	75   (73)	87   (87)	88   (87)	4,4(.j)     3.5(3)	15.7	25.0 (25.0)	22(a) include quantities undischarged from ships, in warehouses, cold stores, emergency depots,mills,refineries &amp; factories;(b)see footnote(b)inTable IIj(c) reserve stocks only i.e.stocks in mills and warehouses, less millers working stocks of 113,000 tons of flour;(d) wheat consumed asflour only;(e) Great Britain only;(f) stocks and number of weeks&apos; supply refer to imported only;(g) stocks reserved for Services and emergencies;(h) up to end. August 1940, Great Britain only; from September onwards, United Kingdom;(i) excluding baconer carcases in cold stores;(3) includingexports; (k)o*farm stocks of  main crop available for human consumption; (l) human consumption only. (V;

No.	&apos;     commodity	Imports (a)	home production	total consumption	total stocks (b)				(c)				No.		Jan.   Feb. Mar.   Apl. 5        4 &apos;    4        5 wks.   wks. wks.   wks.	Jan.   Feb.   mar.     Apl. 5        4        4         5 wks.   wks.   wks.    wks.	jan.   feb.    mar. Apl. 5        4        4      5 wks.   wks.   wks. wks.	end jan.	end Feb.		end march.			end April.		1	Wheat &amp; Flour (as wheat)												1		429    336   414     600	125(d) 100(d) 80(d)   50(d)	698     550     530   645	2405	2191(2184)		2075(2054)			2030(1991)		2 3 4	Barley (incl.farm &amp; brewers1 stocks) Maize Oilcake	20        9      8       3 77      80   103      45 34      46    42        9	177(d)   41(d) 81(d)   39(d) 0         0       0         0 68        66      70        83	210     124     138     80&apos; 154     106     114   138 125     108     110   138	555 187 129	440 ( 439) 161 (160) 133 1128)		310 150 135 (	[308) ;i46 125	I	233 (229) 57   (49) 89   (73)		2 3 45 6 7 8 9	Oilseeds Vegetable Oils Whale Oil Margarine Lard &amp; compound lard	81     108   136     108 17        8    13      17 0        0      0        0 0        0      0        0 0       0      0        0	0 0 0 0 54       50 &apos;   50        60 0 0 0 0 41        29      29        36 16        16      16        20	124    117     121   145 77      60      60    75 14      10      12     15 39      32      25     29 18      14      14    17	146 84 237(e) 27 11	136 (133) 82   (81) 227 (227) 24   (24) 13   (13)		153 (144 85   (83] 215 (215; 28   (28; 16   (16&quot;		1	116   (99) 87   (84) 200 (200) 35   (35) 19   (19)		5 6 7 8 910 11 12	Meat (f)(g) Corned Beef Bacon &amp; ham	49      64     63      72 6        2     14      23 21      20     15      19	84        70      67        69 0         0        0          0 20        18      19        21	153     119     123   154 8       6       6      7 37      30      30     38	41 101 33	56 (b) 97   (97) 41   (40)		63 (b) 105 (105) 45   (44)			50 (b) 121 (121) 47   (46)		10 11 1213	Canned Salmon	14      2        3	0          0        0          0	3       3        3      3	18	19	(19)	18	(18)		18   (18)		1314	Sugar (as refined) (h)	113     112     89      90	52          0        0          0	129*   108     111   133	720	721	[717)	699 (687)			646 (624)		1415	lice	13        5      6      11	0          0        0          0	14      12      12     14	43	36	(36)	30	(30)		27	[26)	1516 17 18	Butter Cheese Condensed Milk(h)	17      23     25      25 14      11    14        9 2        2      2        3	0.1      0.1    0.2      0.5 , 0         0       0         3 12        5         8	17      13      20     27 11      10      10     12 10      10      10       8	28 17 39	38 18 33	(37) (18) (33)	44 22 30	(43) 22 (30)		42 22 33	[40) ,21) [33)	16 17 1819	Eggs in shell	9        3      3        5	13        15      21       20	23      18      24    23	1	1		1			3     (3)		1920	Potatoes (f)	10      50     50       62	483 (i) 344(i)345(i) 383 (i)	496(j) 394(j)393(j)445(,	3)3724	1380(1380)		1037(1037)			654 (654)		2021	Dried Fruit	17      10     S       9	0         0        0         0	8      10      10     10	22	22	(22)	21	(20)		20   (18)		2122	Tea (h)	22      33     28      18	0         0       0         0	20      14      14    18	68	87	(87)	101 (100)			101 (100)		22 i(a) a deductxon of 8/0 from expected arrivals of each commodity has been made to cover possible sinkings; (b) excepting neat (the stocks ofwhich will be maintained at a minimum figure by varying the ration) the forecasts not in brackets reflect the allowance made forsinkings; those in brackets reflect, in addition, an allowance made for possible air raid damage to stocks equivalent to the averageloss sustained by individual commodities during the months Sept/Tan; (c) excluding any quantities held by retailers- (d)movements offfarms *nd quantities utilised.by growers&apos;for feed and seed; (e) hardened oil, 4 thousand tons only; (f)Great Britain only; (?) stocks ofimpor-^i only;(hjconsumption includes exportsmovement of main crop off farms; (j)including ware quality potatoes fe^o stock or

Food DivisionENGLAND AND WALESNorthernNorth-EasternNorth-western north MidlandMidlandEasternEastern IILondon (M.-P.A.)South-EasternSouthernSouth-West emNorth wales south WalesSCOTLANDSouth-EastWestEastNorth-EastNorthNORTHERN IRELANDEstimatedCivilianBuyingPopulationat 28.12.40UNITED KINGDOM-TOTAL(&apos;000)2,5313,8636,4543,1403,9201,4621,1936,5761,6992,6063,2395952,0327392,7426554611831,283Stocks of CommoditiesWheat42.5102.8365.656.214.426.719.199.77.816.5155.957.252,798.13.8&quot;  00.161.145,373    h.160.2FlourMeat( imported)19,243.4101.129.947.720.714,567.710.426.546,08.619,513.545.96.65.71.112,6540,6Canned I Bacon CannedCornedBeefandHamSalmonSugar(as re-fined)iRice1.61.3. 8.50.71.20.60.511,51,01,63.01,01.45.90.20o30.240.5Thousand    tons.410,117.018.611.52.74.06.53.75.72.72.24.90.54.11.20.40.20.1103o50.61.14.60.20.90.20.34.50.20.21.7* * *0.80.10.6ft o *0.10.51.11.45.81.50.90.60.31.90.51.31.0* * *0.60.50.90.30.216.155.997.5il49.860.691.728.267.52.612.323.82.59.62.632.911.01.40.32.316.618.8668.6(c)1.56.98.30.80.63.90.113.70.10.20.80,10.32.12.50.10.2Oft ft0.4Butter(cheese1.11,84.51:43.10.80.76.10.41.21.71.60.41.80.10.1nol.jar-garine42.6   27.8  I 17,20,30.83*00,62.50.20.16.40.20.31.30.30.20.80.10,1o ft fta a a1.31.95.21.51.70,51.24.50.61.22.00.11.50.62.10.30.20.10.5Cook-ingFats27,00,60.71.70,50,40.30,31.10.20,40.4* 4 *0.20,10.29 ft ft0.1Con-den sedlilk2.15.45.74-45.00,31.11.80,13.64.00,21.30.32.30.30.30.10.1Jam &amp;liarma-ladeTea38,4      21a8(a) The differences between the totals shown in this Table and those in Table II represent stocks in transit and farm stocks,for which regional details are not available.(b) Excluding animal lard.(c) Excluding stocks held by food manufacturers.Indicates quantity less than 50 tons.0.31.06.00.30.52.10.25.60,21.20,8* * *0,10.32.90,2),11.02.822.41.12.20.2 i0.1 !31.7 !0.3 I1.41.40,10.70.63.10.10.1O 4&apos; ft0,369.6j

Pood Division	Estimated Civilian Buying Population at 28.12.40	Stocks of Commodities                                                                                           \																Wheat	Flour	Meat      ! Canned i Bacon (imported) I Corned !  and &apos; Beef  !   Ham i			Canned Salmon	Sugar (as re-fined)	Rice	Butter I	Cheese	Lar-garine	Cook-ing Fats (b.)	Con-densed Lilk	Jam &amp; ilarma-lade	Tea iENGLAND AND WALES Northern North-Eastem North-Western North Midland Midland Eastern Eastern II London (M.P.A.) South-Eastern Southern South-Western North Wales South Wales SCOTLAND South-East West East North-East North NORTHERN IRELAND	(&apos;000) 2,531 3,863 6,454 3,140 3,920 1,462 1,193 6,576 1,699 2,606 3,239 595 2,032 739 2,742 655 461 183 1,283																	42.5 102.8 365.6 36.2 14.4 26.7 19.1 99.7 7.8 16.5 155.9 57.2 52.7 98.1 3.8 0.1 61.1 --	19.2 43.4 101.1 29.9 47.7 20.7 14.5 67.7 10.4 26.5 46,0 8.6 19.5 13.5 45*9 6.6 5.7 1.1 12,6 1	1.6 1.3 . 8.5 0.7 1.2 0.6 0.5 11.5 1.0 1.6 3.0 * * * 1.0 1.4 5.9 0.2 0.3 0.2	7.4 10.1 17.0 18.6 11.5 2.7 4.0 6.5 3.7 5.7 2.7 2.2 4.9 0.5 4.1 1.2 0.4 0.2 0.1	0.6 1.1 4.6 0.2 0.9 0.2 0.3 4.5 0.2 0.2 1.7 * * * 0.8 0.1 i 0.6 doc 0.1 0.5	1.1 1.4 5.8 1.5 0.9 0.6 0.3 1.9 0.5 1.3 1.0 * * * 0.6 0.5 0.9 0.3 0.2 0 * ft O 9 9	16.1 55.9 97.5 149.8 60.6 91.7 28.2 67.5 2.6 12.3 23.8 2.5 9.6 2.6 32.9 11.0 1.4 0.3 2.3	1.5 6.9 8.3 0.8 0.6 3.9 0.1 13.7 0.1 0.2 0.8 0.1 0.3 2,1 2.5 0.1 0.2 0 * * 0.4	1.1 1.8 4.5 1;4 3.1 0.8 0.7 6.1 0.4 1.2 1.7 1.6 0.4 1.8 0.1 0.1 1=0	0,3 0.8 3,0 0,6 2.5 0.2 0.1 6.4 0.2 0.3 1.3 * * * 0,3 0.2 0.8 0.1 0.1 Q 9 * o 9 a	1.3 1.9 5.2 1.5 1.7 0,5 1.2 4.5 0.6 1.2 2.0 0.1 1.5 0.6 2.1 0.3 0.2 0,1 0.5	0o6 0.7 1o7 0.5 0.4 0.3 0,3 1.1 0,2 0.4 0.4 * 9-9 0.2 0.1 0.2 9 9 9 0.1 C 9 9 9 9 9	2.1 5.4 5.7 4.4 5.0 0,3 1.1 108 0,1 3.6 4.0 0.2 1.3 0.3 2.3 0.3 0.3 0.1 0.1	0.3 1.0 6.0 0.3 0.5 2.1 0.2 5.6 0.2 1,2 0,8 * * * 0.1 0,3 2.9 0.2 0 u * b 9 9 0,1	1,0 2.8 ! 22.4 I 1.1 2.2 0.2 i o.i ! 31.7! 0.3 ! 1.4 ! 1.4 0.1 0.7 0.6 3d 0.1 0.1 9 9 9 0.3UNITED KINGDOM-TOTAL --,-r-	i 45,373    M,160.2 I i , . .    -i_. i ,1 -  _		5*5-0.6 j   40.5 i I		103=5	16.6	18.8 i	668.6 (c)	42c 6	27.8	17,2	27,0	7.2	. 38,4	2108	69.6 -(a) The differences between the totals shorn in this Table and those in Table II represent stocks in transit and farm stocks,for which regional details are not available.(b) Excluding animal lard.(c) Excluding stocks held by food manufacturers.Indicates quantity less than 50 tons.J

TABLE IV.LOSSES OF FOODS JJSTO FEEDS AT SEASEPTEMBER, 1940 - JANUARY, 1941(as reported up to 14th February,194l)1--Commodity               j  September		October	November	1  December     jJanuary	l^lVheat I, piour t, Kisc. Cereals H. Rice B, pulse	36,375 170 1,173 45	46,183 1,796 74	12,758 2,139 482	34,572 1,907 117	28,2b6 mm 1,000 200bl Maize/Maize Heal I, Cereal   Offals S, Feeding Seeds I, Rice Bran k. Oilcake I, Locust Beans E, Miscellaneous Feeds	642 2,500 1,000 ms	6,210 3,569 589 mm &quot;l47	28,354 63 3,113	1,340 4,563	13,867 1,285 1,400 2,207 1,117ft. Oilseeds V, Vegetable Oils K, Lard R, Other Animal Fats	6,172 573	&quot;l63	2,702 16 391	4,850 1,270 10 1,294	3,750 1,0401. Sugar 1. Starch (a) ft, Glucose	17,619 85	8,696	15,457 619 52	3,272 166	2,769 2,412Ki Meat 1. Rabbits, etc. it, Canned Meat 1. Bacon 1. Fish w. Canned Salmon i. Other Canned Fish	1,340 2,508 379	7,128 278 799 1,602 534	11,107 160 147 1,645 99	7,106 1 1,383 1,566 1,506 800	3,508 -49 131 -12. Butter p. Cheese ft.. Processed Milk p Eggs in Shell 1. Eggs not in Shell	955 113	1,510 1,156 905 165	5,779 4,081 386 922 40	4,252 2,786 855 25	55 719f Dried Fruit 19. Nuts  &apos; p. Oranges p. Other Citrus Fruit p. Bananas 6. Other Fresh Fruit 17. Canned Fruit	m mm	975 3,000 2,874	22 14 71 4,500 34 27	136	am mV- Tea 12. Cocoa J5. Wines &amp; Spirits BP *    Ml                  T r\v* Xmi -	600 4 -	100	2,196 650	2,142	3,203		81	&quot;       171	39	-_J 10 1TOTAL	72,304	88,534  !    98,197 1		75,958	67,008(a) Including Edible Tapioca, Sago and Arrowroot.					

Chart I  Sheet /.TOTAL STOCKS. IMPORTS &amp; CONSUMPTIONOF FOODS &amp; FEEDS

82Chart I Sheef 2.TOTAL STOCKS , IMPORTS &amp; CONSUMPTIONOF FOODS &amp; FEEDS1939 1940 194-1Sep. - Jan._       Apr. July Oct. Jan. Apr. Julyt      i     i      i      i      i      i      i     i     i   1 i .......a11&quot; t      i      i     i      i     i     i    tt--*rVEGETABLE OILS

Chart I - Sheet 5.TOTAL STOCKS, IMPORTS &amp; CONSUMPTIONOF FOODS   &amp;   FEEDS1939Sep.1940Jan. Apr. July     i     i    j     i     i     i1    iOct. jan.&quot;t..............%&apos; 111 **r.....t*&quot;SUGAR ( as refined)-500meatccb.&apos;) Consumption: Imported 8. home produced..-      &apos; Stocks f       Only200J100 JBACON 8* HAM (g.b.)L 30Apr. JulyTonsu70oSOOLSQOL400jl 300IL 200.100. 200IOO

84Chart 1 - Sheet 4.TOTAL STOCKS, IMPORTS &amp; CONSUMPTIONOF   FOODS  &amp;  FEEDS

Chart 2ARRIVALS , SINKINGS AND AIR-RAID damage to FOODS  AND ANIMAL FEEDSIT2,000.pre-*or importsi5,;i6 eootonsiyupcrpnj gramme2e,ci?,oootons*n.&apos;n&apos;my averts: t&amp;fiooo tens.Arrivals Sinkings j Air-raid damageJulyApr.        Julycootons2,5002.000Pre-war Imparts23,006,oootons .monthly avcrfeaci,?1t,000 tons.i,sodRevised programmefi, o% modifiedi5,4ZOtq00tonsmonthly avrfacic1,285,000 tonj&apos;.1.1,000Source:- Board of Trade Import Statistics when available(Sept. 193? -fjomfuo); other data Ministry of Food ,Statistics and Intelligence Division,


</content>
</cab>
