<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/9/3 images: 26-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  September 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)241st Conclusions.Copy No,&apos;. KEPT   UNDER  LOCK AND  KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 241 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, September 4, 1940, at 11 a.m.Present:The Eight Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Eight Hon. Viscount Halifax,The Eight Hon. C. E. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Eight Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.secretary affairs.of   State   for   foreign the Eight Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Aircraft Production.The following were also present:The Eight Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Eight Hon. L. C. M. S. Amery,M.P., Secretary of State for Indiaand Burma (Items 1-5).The Eight Hon. E. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries(Item 6).Sir Horace Seymour, Assistant Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 1-4).The Eight Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 1-4).The Eight Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War(Items 6-8).Mr. Ealph Assheton, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofLabour (Item 6).Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff (Item 5).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.[21730]
WAR CABINET 241 (40).Contents.minute no. Subject.1      French ColoniesMartinique.2      Aircraft Production ...Aircraft for the Middle East.3      Aircraft Production ...Situation at Castle Bromwich.4      The Far East.........The Burma Boad.The position in Indo-China.5      IndiaManufacture of aircraft.6      Harvest Work ...Employment of troops.Hop-picking.7      The Colonies    .........War effort.8      The Balkans    .........The Hungarian-Roumanian settlementParliament.Page..........      19..........      19..........      19..........      2021.      .........      22..........      22..........      23statement to he made in
Aircraft 2.   The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet that theProduction. Air Ministry had temporarily stopped the export of HurricanesAircraft for the overseas.   It was hoped that this measure would not be in forceMiddle East. for long.(Previous The Minister for Aircraft Production asked whether he couldBeference: now be given authority not to fit further Hurricanes with specialW.M. (40) 240th Middle East equipment.Conclusions, The Prime Minister thought that this measure would beinu e   &apos; premature.   The position was constantly under review.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Aircraft 3.   The Minister of Aircraft Production reported that on production. Saturday, the 31st August, 700 men had left Castle BromwichSituation at factory at lunch time without authorisation, and a further 700 atCastle 5 p.m.; 3,500 men had remained at work over the week-end, butBromwich. there was a marked disinclination on the part of the men to continue at work after an air raid warning had been sounded. production had already fallen off and prompt action was necessary if thesituation was not to deteriorate further. He would like to see thesounding of the sirens discontinued.In discussion, the following points were made :  (1) It was generally agreed that the operation of the air raid warning system ought to be modified. The existing system had been framed to meet the contingency of air raids which would create very great destruction, andwas not suitable for the sort of conditions now being experienced.The Prime Minister referred to the suggestionsoutlined at the Cabinet two days earlier for modifying&apos;the warning system in regard to which discussions were proceeding.(2) For a year it had been impressed on workers that it was their duty to take cover when the sirens sounded. the habit had become ingrained, and a new outlook waswanted.(3) The Government had ample legal powers to compel men toremain at work. But it would be a grave decision toapply compulsion to skilled workers in the aircraft industry.(4) A more suitable method would be the withdrawal of protec-tion from service with the forces. But, beforeconsideration was given to this or any other method, afull report should be obtained as to the local conditionsin this factory, and the Minister of Labour should be consulted.[21730] b 2(previous reference:W.M. (40) 239thConclusions,Minute 4.)French Colonies. 1. The attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to a report(Previous that Martinique was moving in an anti-Vichy direction, and thatBeference:        &amp; plebiscite was likely to be held in the island.W.M. (40) 239th        The War Cabinet-Conclusions,Minute 10.) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider whether United. . States influence could be brought to bear against the Vichyai lmque. elements at Martinique and to instruct Lord Lothian totake any steps in his power.
(5) It would be difficult to keep secret any measures foundnecessary to induce munition workers to continue atwork; and there was a risk of affording encouragement to the enemy. The first step might well be that the men should be addressed by some national figure, who could bring them to a better realisation of the position.The War Cabinet Invited the Lord Privy Seal to investigate these matters,in consultation with the other Ministers concerned, in the      qcourse of the day, and to report to a Meeting of the WarCabinet to be held at 9-30 p.m. that evening.The Far East.The BurmaBoad.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 239thConclusions,Minute 9.)The position in indo-China.4. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (40) 348) about the burma Road Agreement. that was to happen after ^ the17th October, when His Majesty&apos;s Government could either continueor discontinue the present partial closure of this route ?The Foreign Secretary said, that the factor most likely to influence the Far Eastern situation in our favour before the17th October would be the successful termination of the Battle of britain. In the meantime we ought so to handle the situation asto leave ourselves free to reopen the road, if we should decide todo so. To this end we should decline to allow the Japanese toextend the scope of the existing agreement, and should emphasiseits temporary nature, and the fact that it involved the fulfilment of an obligation on the part of Japan.In discussion the following points were made : (1) The Burma Road situation had been overtaken by the Indo-China situation, on which the facts were far from clear.The Japanese Foreign Office had denied a report thatthey had presented an ultimatum on the 1st September,demanding the right to send their troops through Indo-China.(2) If Japan attempted a military occupation of Indo-China,this brought Burma under air threat from japanese forces.(3) Could the United States be persuaded to take any action ?A great moral effect would be produced on the Japaneseif President Roosevelt were to send one AmericanCruiser Squadron to Singapore, on a ceremonial visit.(4) Would aggression against Indo-China make Japan strongeror weaker in the military and economic spheres ? If theFrench Government of Indo-China and the local population put up a good resistance, the Japanese might become considerably involved, and pro tanto discouragedfrom further adventure. A Report was required on thispoint from the Chiefs of Staff.(5) The Foreign Secretary said that he had instructed his department to consider, in consultation with the otherDepartments concerned, whether we could offer any economic inducements to Japan which would prove soattractive as to keep her on the paths of virtue.(6) The Prime Minister said that, if the present air battle wentin our favour, it would greatly increase our prestige.But it would not materially affect the military position vis-a-vis Japan. A war with Japan would funda-mentally affect our strategy in the Middle East. Theright course was to go some way in offering inducements
India. 5.   The War Cabinet had before them Memoranda by theManufacture of Secretary of State for India and the Minister without Portfolioaircraft. (W.P. (G.) (40) 219 and 231) in regard to a scheme for the manu-facture of aircraft in India.The following points were made in discussion : (1) The Secretary of State for India said that the scheme wouldmake no immediate demands for aero-engines. SixtyFighter engines would be required, beginning next april, and 60 Bomber engines beginning towards the endof 1941. If need be, these dates could be postponed. Itwas, however, important that authority should be givenwhich would enable orders to be placed and the schemeto go forward.(2) On a long term view it would be strategically advantageous to have a factory in India for the manufacture of air-craft. The scheme was also valuable as extending theexisting facilities for the repair of aircraft in India.(3) The scheme was strongly urged by the Viceroy.(4) The Minister of Aircraft Production said that the outputof completed aircraft was conditioned by the enginesavailable. We had contracted for every available enginewhich could be obtained in America. If the schemewent through it would mean that engines would not beavailable for a number of air frames which had been ordered, and which would be wasted.(5) Demands for aero-engines were being made by all theDominions. He would be greatly handicapped in refusing these demands if the present scheme was approved.(6) The Vice-Chief of the Air Staff said that on a long term basis the scheme had attractions, but on a short termview seemed unlikely to be worth while.(7) The Prime Minister said that Germany was no doubtplanning to organise aircraft production in all theenslaved countries of Europe. We must be prepared tomeet aircraft production on a European scale. We couldonly do this if we used the most efficient centres ofproduction and we must not dissipate our resources.(8) While the present air battle continued, we must direct all our energies to making ourselves as strong as possible;but if matters developed favourably for us, it might bepossible to reconsider long term projects of this nature.to Japan, and possibly also to go some way in usingthreats, but not to commit ourselves irrevocably toforcible action.The War Cabinet-(a) Invited the Foreign Secretary to sound the United StatesGovernment about the possibility of their sending a cruiser Squadron to Singapore, on a ceremonial visit.(b) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to report to what extent an% extension of the Far Eastern hostilities to Indo-Chinawould be likely to cause military or economic embarrass-ment to Japan, on the assumption that effectiveresistance was offered by the Government and populationof Indo-China, aided perhaps by the Chinese.
The War Cabinet (i) Withheld approval from the scheme proposed by theSecretary of State for India in his Memorandum of the21st August (W.P. (G.) (40) 219).(ii) Agreed that further consideration might be given to thisscheme in, say, two months&apos; time.Harvest Work. 6.   The War Cabinet had before them two Memoranda by theEmployment of Secretary of State for War (W.P. (G.) (40) 323 and H.P.C. (40) 276)troops. about employing troops in harvesting.Should the troops so employed be paid extra? The Secretaryof State for War said that, while troops who had volunteered forharvesting last year had been paid a shilling a day extra, it was not thought suitable that the men would this year be detailed forharvesting should be paid.The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Labour, said that from the Ministry of Labour&apos;s point of view it would be desirablethat they should receive some extra pay.The general view of the Cabinet was that they should not bepaid, but should be given free beer by the farmers. The Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries explained that arrangements would be-made for the cost of the beer to be deducted by the farmers from thesum paid by them to the Army authorities in respect of the men&apos;s.labour.Hop-picking. The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries explained that atthe moment it was only proposed to use soldiers for hop-picking.It might be necessary to use them later for the potato and sugar-beetcrop. 20,000 hop-pickers were required at once. It seemed unlikelythat the full requirements could be met by the employment ofsoldiers. Many of the hop-fields were in prohibited area, and the regional Commissioner had not allowed hop-pickers from london to take their children with them. As a result, many had returned to&apos;London. The War Cabinet thought that, in the circumstances, theban on children accompanying hop-pickers should be removed.The War Cabinet: (1) Approved the policy of employing troops on harvest work.Soldiers detailed for this work should receive their armypay without addition, but arrangements should be madefor them to get free beer.(2) Invited the Home Secretary to instruct the regional commissioner for South-East England that children should be allowed to accompany hop-pickers.The Colonies. 7.   The Lord Privy Seal said  that Lord Winterton hadWar effort. proposed that there should be a Debate in the House of commons on the extent of the war effort of the Colonies. The view of theColonial Secretary, with which he agreed, was that such a Debateat the present time would be undesirable and would raise awkwardissues, including questions affecting Palestine.The Prim,e Minister agreed with this view. If a debate wereinsisted on, however, he favoured a statement in general terms thatthe war effort of the Colonies greatly exceeded the effort which theyhad made in the late war.
O       The Balkans. 8.   The Foreign Secretary read to the War Cabinet an extractThe Hungarian- from the draft of a statement which he proposed to make in theRoumanian House of Lords on the 5th September in regard to the recentSettlement: territorial changes in Roumania. The draft statement was to theStatement to be effect that His Majesty&apos;s Government favoured modifications of themade in status quo, provided always that such modifications were just and parliament. equitable in themselves, and were reached by means of free and peaceful negotiation and agreement between the interested parties and not by methods of aggression or compulsion. It followed thatthey were unable to accept the settlement of the Hungarian-Roumanian dispute over Transylvania which had recently been announced. It was not their intention to recognise during the warterritorial changes which had evidently not been freely agreed between all the parties concerned, but it was their hope that at theend of the war there might be a general settlement on lines so just and equitable that it would be assured of durability, and they wouldbe prepared to use all their influence to this end.The War Cabinet approved a statement on these lines.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,September 4, 1940.The War Cabinet agreed: That it was undesirable to have a debate in Parliament atthe present time on the Colonies war effort, and that theLord Privy Seal should therefore ask that the debate should be postponed.




</content>
</cab>
