<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/157/22 images: 277-280</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYlS government cp(71) 72 COPY NO 6121 June 1971CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE; VOLUNTARY SOCIAL service memorandum by the Lord Privy seal. In our Election Manifesto we said:  &quot;We recognise the important contribution to social welfare that volunteers and voluntary organisationsare already making, and we believe that there is scope for considerable expansion and development.    We are convinced that many of the social problems that now scar society can only be solved through a genuinepartnership of effort between statutory and voluntary organisations -between the professional and the volunteer.    We will give active support,both financially and legislatively, so that new opportunities may be created in co-operation with the local authorities for all those - and in particular the young people and the retired people - who want to do voluntary social work&quot;.   At the request of the Social Services Committee, I have been considering, with a group of Ministers from the Departments concernedhow we can pursue these ideas and implement our pledge.    At its last meeting the Social Services Committee agreed that the Government should give positive encouragement to voluntary social service, and suggested that means to this end should be considered in the context of the public expenditure Survey Review.2. There can be no doubt of the growing need for the voluntaryorganisation and for the volunteer in our society,    On the one hand,there are the limitations on public authorities&apos; insights, experiencesand freedom of action, and the constraints on public service manpower;on the other, the stimulus and pioneering that one can get from voluntary bodies, and the gaps waiting to be filled by them and by volunteers, forexample in identifying and helping to meet the needs of the young, the sick,the elderly and the handicapped, in helping prisoners and in the probationand after-care service, in community relations and in the preservation and improvement of the environment.    I am confident that an increasedresponse could be evoked to this need,3.        It is not possible precisely to define or to give a figure of presenttotal public expenditure on voluntary social service.    It is, however,possible to identify direct Government subventions, largely in the formof direct grants to national voluntary bodies.    Last year these were
estimated at some  2, 6 million (excluding expenditure of about  ljj million on Youth Service capital programmes the future financing of which is nowbeing discussed with the interests concerned).    But to give a completepicture it would be necessary to take into account the sizeable expenditurealso incurred through local authorities and the National Health Service forwhich separate figures are not available (included in this would be the ^ million spent in 1970-71 under the Urban Programme).    On present plans the direct grants will have increased by about  1 million by 1975-76,While this may be enough to defend us from the charge of broken promisesI do not believe that it would represent a positive enough commitment on thepart of the Government for us to claim either that we have fully redeemedour Manifesto promise or that we have risen to the need and opportunity thatconfront uo in this field.4, This is by no means wholly a matter of moneys it is just as much,if not more, one of organisation and ideas and I have felt that a discussiondocument examining our attitude and relationship towards the voluntary bodies, drav/ing attention to the unfilled needs for voluntary social service,and setting out some of the main issues in this field would serve a valuablepurpose of focusing public discussion.    But the touchstone by which oursincerity and commitment will be judged is cash, and I therefore suggest to my colleagues that they should be prepared to earmark a modestadditional sum (say  4 million) to be spent by Government within the quinquennium of the current Public Expenditure Review on proposals to advance the aims of voluntary social service.    After a modest startnext year this might lead by 1975-76 to an annual addition to Governmentspending on voluntary social service of about  1-jj million over that already planned.5. If this proposal is accepted, the detailed allocation of the expendi-ture to objectives and Departmental Votes, and by years, could be worked out later,    I would like to concentrate on proposals which would stimulaterecruitment and efficient deployment of volunteers as well as the general development of activity by voluntary organisations and which would provideresources at both the material and organisational level to enable the fullestand most effective contribution to be made to meeting social needs.    Iwould hope, too, that - given the necessary co-operation by localauthorities - part of any extra money made available could be channelledselectively to the voluntary sector through the machinery of the urban programme.6, Some further injection of public funds is needed to prime the pumpof voluntary enterprise but a healthy voluntary movement needs to haveresources of its own.    We should therefore aim to mobilise further privatesupport.    The Manifesto also committed us &quot;to encourage the flow ofprivate funds to charities, including voluntary social service, sport andthe arts&quot;.    The Chancellor is, I know, aware of the studies in this matter which we commissioned when in Opposition.    I quite understand that he hasnot been able to deal with it in this year&apos;s Budget, more especially in view
of the far-reaching proposals which this contained.    I imagine, however,that some legislative provision will be essential on this subject when the tax restructuring is undertaken: otherwise it seems clear that theposition of charities will be worsened.    I hope that when this time comes the Chancellor will have in mind our Manifesto commitmentand will be able actually to effect some improvements in the taxarrangements in the charitable field.J civil  Service Department SW121 June 1971


</content>
</cab>
