<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/39/2 images: 18-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)MOST secret copy NO.  *M,l4gJ.,,96TH CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE confidential Annex(9th July,   1943 - 11,45 a.m. )MAN-POWER(previous references:W. M. (42) 167thConclus ions,Minute 1; andW. M. (43) 90thConclusions,Minute 2).AircraftProductionThe War Cabinet had before, them the followingMemorandaBy the Prime Minister and Minister of Defence(W.P.   (43) 295 and 296 )by the Lord President of the CouncilCWi.P.   (43) 271).By the First Lord of the Admiralty(W.P.   (43) 221).By the Secretary of State for War(W.P.   (43) 272).By the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of Statefor Air(W. P.   (43)  273).By the Minister of Production(W.P.   (43) 260).THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the WarCabinet should hove a preliminary discussion of thewhole situation, but should not reach final Conclusionsat that Meeting.It was clear that our resources in man-powerwere now strained to the utmost and would not enable us to meet all our needs.      Decisions must thereforebe taken as to the proportions in which the variousdemands sboiild be cut.The Prime Minister said that he had reviewed the provisional allocation made by the Lord President,and had somewhat shifted the emphasis in favour of theAir.      Earlier in the year the Minister of aircraft production had reduced the production programme tofigures which he thought could be attained, but even this reduced programme would not be achieved unless the flow of labour into M.A.P. was increased.THE MINISTER OF LABOUR AND NATIONAL SERW^Jk^^said that a net increase of. 175,000 for M. A, P.Jtu V^v /the nine months    April-December    involved a net f^e^ Qof 155,000 in the months August-December,  i. e, , atrate of 31,000 a month,    &quot;//hen wastage was taken intoaccount, this would mean a gross intake of 80,000 amo nth.

The Minister said that this meant giving something in the nature of an overriding priority to the Ministryof aircraft Production.      It would involve the following measures:-(a) The intake of tradesmen into the Navy, Armyand 3. A. Fc   would have to he cut down tonegligible figures.(b) The requirements of R.E.M.E,  for technical officers would have to be very substantially reduced0(c) The demand of the Fleet Air Arm for aero-engine and air-frame fitters would haveto be cancelled.(d) It might also be impossible to withdrawcertificated engineers of the Merchant Navy .at -present employed in munitions (mainly in aircraft production)  and required to manthe- ships assigned to this country from america,(e) There would have to be either heavier cutsthan those proposed in the Ministry of Supply,or an arrangement whereby those cuts were soplanned that the labour could be absorbed&quot;into M.A.P.(f) The intake into the Women&apos;s Services wouldhave to be reduced to the minimum,,(g) The 9,000 R. A. P.  mechanics now due forrecall to the R. A. P.  would have&apos; to beretained in aircraft production.(h) The R.A.P.   deferred service men would haveto be directed into aircraft production untilcalled up for the R. A. P.THE PRIME MINISTER,   commenting on (d),   said thatit was impossible to contemplate any measures which meant that we should be unable to man the ships built in the United States and assigned to this country.Commenting on (k),  THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIRSo     : said that he could not accept any interference with thet*  -fcfcy? ja^-gTfiBr  of men selected for service in air crews.THE MINISTER OF PRODUCTION said that the numbers to be released from the Ministry of Supply and thenumbers required in aircraft production for the restof the year very nearly balanced.    In practice,  however,he thought that it would be impossible for the Ministry ,of Supply to achieve the full cut proposed by the end ofthe year without great prejudice to the Army munitions programme.      Furthermore,  only a proportion of the labourreleased from Ministry of Supply work was actuallyabsorbed in aircraft production,   and there must be sometime-lag before the cuts in the Ministry of Supply hadthe effect of building up the aircraft production ab our-force,

The Minister also attached great importance to.  the statement in paragraph 9 of the Prime Minister&apos;s Note(W.P.(43) 295),  that the intake into the Services forthe rest of the year should he at a uniform rate.      the strain on industry would he materially.increased if theUl Services  took a disproportionate share of their allocationin the early part of the period.ho hoped that the - Minister of Labour and national Service ould cancel&quot;the arrangement wherebywomen.&apos; -who   pted f r the Women&apos;s Services could not bedirects    t , employment in industry.      The Minister addedthat he thought that, owing to the increase in UnitedStates production,  it should be considerably easier forus to get equipment from the United States in 1944.      this factor would tend to relieve our difficulties.inistry of THE MINISTER OP SUPPLY said that his Departmentupply had been reduced by 70,000 in five months, and&quot;that afurther reduction of 52,,. 000 would be -made before the end.of September,  thus completing the cut of 120,000 whichhad been imposed at the last general review.    While hecould not resist the further cut piro;posed, he did notbelieve that the total reduction of 215,000 could beeffected by the end of the calendar year without creating a degree of confusion which would gravely hamper productionand cause public misgiving.      He hoped that the decision&apos; might be -that the reduction should be accelerated as faras possible,  and he thought that  the total reduction now suggested could be achieved by about April,  1944.Complaint was already being made that in some cases wherethe Ministry of Supply had closed factories, the labourdisplaced had not found alternative employment.      Whilehis Department had effected reductions amounting to42,000 in the last three months,  the labour force on aircraft production had increased by only 16,000 in thatperiod.avy THE FIRST LORD OP THE ADMIRALTY said that he wasgravely perturbed at the allocation proposed for theRoyal Navy. &apos;   Paragraph 2(c) of the Prime Minister&apos;sMemorandum W. P.(43; 295 assumed that there was scope for reductions by further economies, but in fact theseeconomies had already been taken into account in estimating the Navy&apos;s man-power requirements.      Thus,   escort carrierswere now being manned by paying off armed merchant cruisers.      A decision had already been reached to payoff three &quot;R&quot; Class battleships and four cruisers.      but these measures would not enable the remaining requirementsof the Navy and of Combined Operations to be met.Unlike tee other two Service Departments theAdmiralty had spread their intake evenly over the whole year and it looked as though they were now to suffer fromfollowing this course.      Not only was the increasedrequirement of 43,000 to be refused, but it was also&quot;proposed to reduce their previous allocation by 14,000.TILS PRIME MINISTER enquired whether the admiralty could not effect a greater degree of interchangeabilitybetween the personnel required to man the Fleet and landing-craft.      He also referred to the further easementswhich, they might hope to achieve by future developments in the Mediterranean situation.

THE FIRST SEA LORD said that there was no meansof making the personnel of the Royal Navy and of landing-craft interchangeable until either -(!,&apos;  Germany was defeated;    or(2) A stage was reached at which we should know that we should not have to carryout any further landing operationsexcept, in the Par East,He emphasised the need for training landing crews, and added that what was now under consideration was therequirements for 1943,  in regard to which interchange of personnel was not feasible.      After 1943 the position could be further reviewed.THE FIRST LORD summed up the position as follows.The total Naval deficiency on the allocation proposed would he 57,000.      Of this number,  approximately&apos;31,500belonged to the Navy proper.      This was equivalent tothe personnel required to man 47 cruisers, or 135destroyers,  or ISO corvettes.      The remaining 25,250would represent a deficiency in landing craft personnelwhich would have the effect of reducing by one-third thetotal lifting capacity for Operation OVERLORD.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that he would,of course,   do his best with the allocation proposed, butgreat economies had already been effected in the personnel of non-fighting units.      The fact that the Army contained406,000 men who were not graded A.1.  made it difficultto secure further economies on these lines.      He thoughtthat the allocation -proposed would mean disbanding one division before very long, and probably another in the spring,      But no Division would be &quot;cannibalised&quot; withoutthe specific approval of the Prime Minister.The Secretary of State referred to the PrimeMinister&apos;s request that an increase of 72 men should bemade in the rifle strength of each battalion.      Anincrease of 36 per battalion &quot;was now being made, but he did not think that the fall increase asked for by thePrime Minister could be achieved.      THE PRIME MINISTERindicated that he would be satisfied with the stepproposed.THE SECRETARY OF STATS FOR WAR thought that theMinister of Labour&apos;s statement that there would be a negligible supply of tradesmen for the Army might have serious consequences.      He hoped that the supply wouldnot be allowed to dry up completely.      He would be glad to discuss with the Minister of Labour whether thelatter&apos;s Department could help him in training existingArmy personnel to become tradesmen.The Secretary of State for War said that theallocation proposed meant that the Army&apos;s intake for therest of the&quot;year would be only about 25,000.      He hopedthat the largest possible proportion of these would bemen of high medical category.

THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said that emphasishad been laid on building up the labour force of theMinistry of Aircraft Production.      If the M.A.P.&apos;programme was achieved,  the Royal Air Force- would be 20%larger next year than it was now.      But under theallocation proposed,  after allowance had been made forwastage,  the Royal Air Force would be only 7,000 larger than it was today.      Consideration had been given to the ways in which the situation could be met.      He thoughtthat a solution would have to be found on the lines ofreinforcing those areas in which the greatest effort was required,  - nd making reductions in those which were forthe time being of lesser strategic importance,  the changes being made according to the strategical importanceof-different theatres from time to time.      The AirMinistry would do their best to work on the allocationproposed.THE PAYMASTER-GENERAL pointed out that theexpansion of the Services generally had proceeded more rapidly than had been contemplated at the end of 1942.While in general agreement with the allocationsproposed.: be would have preferred to have seen thebalance between supply and demand closed without a deficit.      This would have resulted in somewhat smallerallocations being made, but the Services and Departmentsconcerned would have been able to place greater relianceupon allocations made on this basis.Discussion then turned on the Building Programme.THE MINISTER OF PRODUCTION referred to the variousprojects for which the United States were now pressing for additional labour.      He said that the exact amount oflabour involved was now being examined,  and that no precise figures could be given;    but it looked as thoughit would be necessary to maintain the labour force now employed on the Government Building Programme until theend of December if all the essential works were to becarried out to time.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR urged that theMinister of Production&apos;s allocation of building labour(W.P. (43) 260) should now be confirmed.      He thoughtthat the prime need at the moment was an early decision.The War Office saw their way,- without any additional labour, but by deferring other work, to build three off the additional depots or dispersal points required bythe Americans,,  and probably the fourth could be managedalso.It was asked whether the position could not be-met by bringing over additional U. S.  ConstructionCompanies at an earlier date.      The view was expressed that the United States authorities doubted whether theycould, send over in the near future as many ConstructionCompanies as they had originally undertaken to make available.      The view was also expressed that the U. S.demand was unreasonable and that we were under no obligation to comply with it.

THE PRIMS MINISTER said that he thought we should at all events avoid taking away men from the aerodromeswhich we &quot;re now being constructed for the United states forces in East Anglia.      To do so would clearly have an unfortunate effect.      He suggested that the ministers concerned - the Minister of Production, the Minister ofLabour and National Service,  the Secretary of State forAir and the Minister of Works - should have an early meeting on the matter, with a view to determining theamount of labour  r/hich must be made available in orderto meet essential. U. S.  requirements,  and how this additional labour could bost be found.The Prime Minister hoped that a final settlement could be reached on this matter,  and on man-powerallocations generally, at a Meeting to be held early inthe following week.Offices of the War Cabinet,3.W. 1.




</content>
</cab>
