<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/157/0 images: 166-174</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   . &apos;   92SECRET.BRITISH EMPIRE REPORT.No. 58.   7th December 192J.Contents.Great Britain.Remedial Measures for Unemployment.Colonies, Protectorates, &amp;c.Aden. Air Force.Iraq. Relations with Turkey.laiia.The Frontier Situation.   Mission to Kabul.The Dominions.The Aland Islands.Australia. Migration.   Message for the President of the United States.   Meat. Imports and Exports&apos;.New Zealand. Delay in discharging Produce in London.South Africa. Commissioner&quot; of Commerce for Europe.   The Strike in the-Crown Mines.    South African Politics.    Transvaal  Education Officials. Defences.   General Smuts.on Unemployment.Newfoundland. Naval Reductions.
GEEAT BRITAIN.Remedial Measures for Unemployment. The following is taken from the report of the Ministry of Labour on unemployment for the week ending 18th November :-During the autumn session, &quot;1921, the following measures were submitted to Parliament and approved : (1) Amendments to Exports Credits Scheme. (a) Government guarantee to be increased from 85 per cent, of the cost to 100 per cent, with recourse against the exporter for 57  per cent.(6) Maximum guarantee for each firm to be fixed by a special advisory Committee.(c) Extension of scheme to all countries, including the British Empire.(d) Extension of period of credit in certain cases to 1927.(2) Government Guarantee of Payment of Interest and Principal of Loans raised by Dominions, Colonies, foreign Governments, public authorities, &amp;c, where such loans are to be applied towards the carrying out of any capital undertaking or in the purchase of articles to be manufactured in the United Kingdom required for the purposes of any such undertaking, the British Governments liability under: this scheme not to exceed 25,000,0002. It is to be a condition of the guarantee that the application of the loan is calculated to promote employment in the United Kingdom.(3) A Sum of 5i- Millions for General Unemployment- Relief.-Subject to Treasury approval, the money will be used in connection wiih schemes for providing employment on land improvement and drainage (650,0002.), forestry (250,0002.), light railways, and also by way of loans to boards of guardians or parish councils in necessitous areas who are unable to meet claims for relief.(4) &quot; The Unemployed Workers&apos; Dependants&apos; Fund,&quot; to be established by legislation for a period of six months for the purpose of making grants towards the maintenance of the wives and dependent children of unemployed workers in receipt of unemployment benefit. The grants will be at the weekly rate of 5s. for the wife and Is. for each child. The necessary money will be obtained by means of further contributions paid by those now contributing to the unemployment fund (both employers and workmen) together-:, with a grant from the State. The total amount available will be approximately 64; millions.(5) Overseas Settlement.-A. further 330,0002. was voted to assist ex-service men desiring to emigrate&apos;to the Dominions.(6) Acceleration of Government Contracts. The position with regard to Govern-ment contracts is being examined to see whether, in any cases, a reasonable anticipation of requirements can be made with advantage from the point of view of increasing employment.(7) Ministry of Transport. A further sum (2,000,0002.) will be available from the road fund for expenditure on roads to relieve unemployment in necessitous areas.(8) Office of Works. A sum of 50,0002. has been voted for unemployment relief works in the royal parks.For the above schemes (apart from the assistance to local authorities -with regard to loan charges, the export credits scheme and the Governments liability under the guarantee of loans for capital undertakings) the Government has undertaken to find 12,000,0002., the greater portion within the current financial jeav.COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, &amp;c.ADEN.Air Force.-The following telegram [No. 72] was sent by the Resident on 25th November :-The Royal Air Force flight at Aden has had an excellent political effect. The relief of the recent border situation was without doubt largely due to the presence of
aeroplanes. I consider an air force is indispensable in the absence of a strong land force if we are to uphold our proper position. The continuance and extension of their nights will restore and increase our prestige and our influence over our own tribes,, and proportionately with the Imam.IRAQ.Relations with Turkey. On 2.1st November the High. Commissioner telegraphed [No. 700] as follows, in summarizing the further evidence of Iraq being a Turkish objective :  (1) There are persistent aiid definite signs of Turkish activity in intelligence and propaganda within and on the borders of Iraq which appear to include the encourage-ment of the antiSunni prejudice of the Shiahs and the anti-Arab prejudices of the Kurds. With these ends in view attention is being devoted to the jealous element among the priesthood of the holy cities and to the pro-Turkish parties in Mosul, Suloimaniyah and Baghdad&apos;. One oE the most dangerous manifestations of these activities is the attempt to arouse discontent in the Arab army through the former Turkish officers. The Angora Government definitely allotted to Shirkk Ahmed Seuussi the task of conducting anti-British propaganda in Iraq and Ajaimi; he is still retained in Turkish pay and is the chief medium for passing on Nthacbs agents, and is in communication with Senussi. To secure co-operation in the tribal forces on the northern border for future offensive enterprise is without doubt one of the chief purposes of this propaganda.&quot;,(2) In Russian expert opinion a provision for the supply of arms by France for Turkish aggression on Iraq was included in the Bouillon agreement. Whether such a provision exists or not, there is significance in the fact that as regards Turkish objectives the Russian mission at any rate holds the same view as we in Iraq do.(3) A recent report of a reliable agent asserts that, in conversation during September, Kiazim Karabekir emphasized that the claims of the Angora Government to the mutessarilig of Dair-az-Zor and the vilayet of Mosul were intrinsic items of national policy which they would not abandon. The continuance of the Turkish control of northern Kurdistan he regarded as essentially contingent upon,, the possession of Mosul and both Mosul and Dair-az-Zor as necessary economically. .,, :&apos;;(4) This agent also heard the general staff officers of Kiazim Karabekir&apos;s headquarters discuss a plan of offensive against Iraq as a definite project on the conclusion of an offensive and defensive alliance between the Turks and the Bolsheviks, to effect which endeavours are being made. It is alleged that this plan contemplates a demonstration via Jezireh and a serious attack via Itowanduz.(5) Considerable point is given to the preceding paragraph being the actual preliminary step before the fall of winter by the establishment of a permanent Turkish outpost at Rowanduz by troops from Van under orders from the eastern army headquarters. The recently reported minor enterprises at Batas and Rania, supported by troops of this outpost, were, there seems little doubt, intended to test the powers of Feisal and the British on land and in air, and to gauge the possibilities of tribal assistance on the Rowanduz line.(5) Comment.Briefly, then, viewing it from the Turkish standpoint, the situation, seems to be that they are confronted with the following alternatives in order of preference: (1) To make peace with Europe excluding Britain; in which case an attack on Iraq will be made by their western troops, whose route.from Sivas to Mardin is not closed in winter. (2). To make peace with Europe, Great Britain&apos;? interest in Iraq being safe-guarded.   The danger to Iraq will in that case be lifted. (3) hailing the above, to go back to the Bolsheviks and conclude an offensive and defensive alliance, in which case the attack on Iraq will be made by the troops of the eastern army. (C) The news that there is a prospect of peace is most welcome in view of the foregoing, but nevertheless I feel it incumbent on me to urge most strongly that while nothing should be done that might militate against the success of the negotiations you indicate, equally no action should be taken, or neglected or reasonable precaution, omitted merely on the assumption that the negotiations will be successful.   While I agree that it is.not the time to give the Kurds any encouragement, 1 trust they may
be kept in play and instructions accordingly issued to those oi&apos; His majesty&apos;s repre-&apos; -sentatives abroad who maybe concerned.   We shall want every possible assistance should the present negotiations also with Turkey break  down.   Meanwhile Khalil is leaving Iraq and Rafat is returning to Constantinople.On 25th &quot;November Sir Percy Cox sent the following telegram in continuation of the above: It is reported by the inspector-general of levies that-during the last live days there has been a.marked endeavour on the part of ex-officers and men of the Turkish army other than Iraqis to get enlisted in the levies. Of such ex-officers speaking Turkish only but styling themselves&quot; Kurds, 1(1 have applied for commissions, and 20 out of: 26 men have applied for enlistment. In the same connexion it should be noted that the loss of 63 rifles in the first battalion of levies, of which 19 have been recovered, is attributed to an ex-Turkish officer and a Turkish chaoush who had managed&quot; to get enrolled. In future, special care will be taken to see that applicants of this category are rejected. .INDIA.The Frontier Situation [B.E.R. LVII, p. 3j. On 23rd November the Viceroy telegraphed [2086] that beyond occasional sniping and minor incidents, nothing of importance had occurred in Waziristan. At the same time he announced the receipt of the report of a raid having occurred in Baluchistan on 22nd November. Full details of this raid and of the light which ensued were received by the Viceroy on 26th November and communicated by him. These have appeared in the public press.Mission to Kabul [B.E.R., Ivii, p. 3j. The Viceroy transmitted [2586 S. and 2593 S.1 on 17th and 18th November messages from Sir Henry Dobbs reporting various amendments, agreed upon between the Amir and himself, to the treaty presented at the meeting of 19th September [B.E.R., liii, p. 4]. Among other matters Sir Henry reported that he had made it clear that the cession of Torkham was conditional on the evacuation of Arnawai.The Secretary of State telegraphed [5925] on I8lh November his pleasure at the reports received showing the satisfactory course of the negotiations. He approved the general principles of procedure indicated by Sir Henry Dobbs, and&quot; agreed with the Viceroy that at that stage the details must be left to Sir Henrys discretion.In a telegram transmitted [2603 S.] by the Viceroy on 18th November, Sir Henry reported, an appeal from the Amir for some immediate and tangible gift which he could show to his people and would enable him to silence those who were opposed to his policy of returning to friendship with Great Britain. He mentioned 10 lakhs of rupees to begin with, or consideration of the offer of motor lorries and cars, tents and telegraph material referred to in the Mussborie aide-memoire. Sir Henry strongly recommended the exercise of a little generosity on these lines if the treaty were signed.   The Ariceroy supported Sir Heury&apos;s recommendation.Telegraphing [5930] on 19th November the Secretary of State agreed to the course proposed by Sir Henry Dobbs.Further telegrams from Sir Henry, reporting the text of the draft he had sent to the Afghan Foreign Office, with his comments thereon, were transmitted [2606 S., 2608 8., 2615 S. and 2620 S.] by the Viceroy on the 19th, 20th and 21st November.On 20th, 21st and 22ud November telegrams were exchanged between the Viceroy and the Secretary of State regarding a draft communique submitted, by the former which he proposed to publish in the event of the conclusion of the neighbourly treaty.The Viceroy forwarded [2625 S.] on 21st November a message from Sir Henry Dobbs advocating the exchange of Ministers as early as possible after the signature of the treaty; and suggesting the prompt exchange by telegram as to the acceptability of the respective nominees of the British and Afghan Governments.   The Viceroy
endorsed Sir Henry V recommendations and suggested that a message from His Majesty the King should be in readiness for onward transmission. ;A reply to this was sent [5981] by the Secretary of State on 23rd November, conveying a message from His Majesty expressing pleasure at the restoration of friendly relations and hopes for their continuance.On 21st November Sir Henry Dobbs reported [2631 S.] that the signature of the treaty was to take place on the following day. On 23rd November the Viceroy telegraphed [2642] a message from Sir Henry saying that the treaty had been signed at a full-dress meeting at the Dilkusha Palace on the afternoon of the 22nd. The mission was to leave Kabul on 26th November.On 23rd November the Secretary of State telegraphed [5995] to the Viceroy a friendly message from Lord Curzon to be conveyed by Sir Henry Dobbs to the Afghan Foreign Minister. The telegram also announced the selection of Mr. Pears as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of the Amir, and hoped that this appointment would be agreeable to His Majesty.The Viceroy transmitted [2657 S.] on 24th November a telegram from Sir Henry Dobbs reporting that the Amir had repudiated the conversation with him of 13th November, in which a distinct understanding had been come to that Arnavvai was to be ceded to Chitral and that we should give up Torkham in return.In continuation of this telegram transmitted [2660] on 25th November, Sir Henry attributed the AmiPs manoeuvre to the fact that he had incurred reproaches iu certain quarters by not obtaining a subsidy or tribal concessions in the treaty, and this was his method of saving his face. In expressing his disappointment Sir Henry discussed the advisability of postponing the attempt to find a solution of the difficulty until after the exchange of Ministers, rather than wreck a treaty which was otherwise advantageous.A further telegram from Sir Henry Dobbs transmitted [2661 S.] on the same date reported that the Amir had informed him that the appointment of Mr. Pears would not be acceptable to him, not on account of his personal qualities, of which he had high reports, but because in the minds of himself, his Ministers and his people, Mr. Pears&apos; name was mixed up with the diplomatic rebuffs that Wali Khan had met with in London. The Amir had requested that some other name might be suggested, and vehemently stated that he would not accept a representative of Indian nationality. . ,. ...On 27th November the Viceroy telegraphed [2687 S.] that he had sent the information, with full details, of the Waziri raid down the Bashore Valley, an outrage which local Afghan officials had failed to prevent. Sir Henry had been requested to make the strongest representations to the Afghan Government, and to demand immediate apologies and reparations.Telegrams from Sir Henry Dobbs forwarded [2704 S.] and [2706 S.] on 29th and 30th November, reported interviews with tho Foreign Minister and the Amir, both of whom expressed their horror and regret at die Waziri outrage. The Amir, who had undergone an operation on his throat the day before, discussed the raid and the Arnawai question. Eventually in a graceful and dignified fashion he gave up Arnawai, and then aud there gave orders for the withdrawal of all Afghan soldiers from Arnawai, and for its immediate restoration to Chitral.THE DOMINIONS.The Aland Islands. On 5th December the Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed as follows to the Governors-General of Canada, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa : Following on the decision of the Council of the League of Nations on the 24th June a convention was drawn up and signed at Geneva on 20th October by the representatives of.the Governments concerned as to neutralization of the Aland Islands.36-1 B
The convention sets out fully the limits of the zone of the islands, and defines the territorial waters as extending for three marine miles from the low water&apos;mark-. Finland engages not to fortify the. islands or to set tip or maintain any base for warlike operations.. Provisions are inserted limiting the number and the size of the warships of Finland and other Powers which may anchor in the islands in time of peace. Liberty of passage for warships through territorial waters is permitted in accordance with international custom. In time of war the zone Is to be treated as neutral, power being reserved to Finland&apos;, however, to lay mines in order to protect its neutrality in case of war&apos;affecting the Baltic.The contracting parties undertake (1) to invite&apos; the Council of the League of Nations to decide the measures to be takenywhere necessarydn1. order to&apos; enforce- the execution of the convention ; (2) to join in measures necessary to give effect to the councils decision, Finland being empowered to act in the?meantime if the neutrality of the zone is threatened.The text of the convention was sent to your Prime Minister on 22hd November and a copy follows by mail. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thinks it most desirable that His Majesty&apos;s ratification of the convention should be deposited&apos; as soon as possible.  Bo-f-ouivMinisteinsj-agree^ttfieiTatifiGaliiimJ?ACSTRALIA. .Migration. On 24&apos;t&apos;h November the following telegram from the Governor-General, transmitting a message from his. Prime Minister, was received&apos;at&apos;the-Colonial Office;-The Commonwealth Government, as you no doubt know, has,, by arrangement with the States, taken over the control of migration from Britain&apos;and elsewhere, and lias created an organization to secure and&apos; transport a sufficient number of immigrants of the right kind.The Commonwealth&apos;Government, recently agreed1 with&apos;the State Premiers that it v/as prepared, subject to-a loan -of money being obtained, to finance the development of such lands as the States:-were prepared to make available dor immigrants.This involves the inauguration of a great developmental policy for the building of railways, roads, water conservation or irrigation, and the clearing of forests or bush. Immigrants coming out under this scheme would be guaranteed employment in constructing such railways, clearing forests&apos;and scrub, making roads, &amp;c.,.and then given the opportunity of selecting land upon which they could settle with, their families.  &apos; / \Leagues called the New Settlers&apos; Leagues have been formed in Australia to help the immigrant, and by aid and kind advice make-him feel he is-among friends and nota stranger in a strange land.Each State has undertaken to submit definite proposals setting out the number of families that can be absorbed, area of land, works necessary to make it available for settlers, &amp;c. ....We can deal with a-very-large-number if we can get the-money to enable us&apos;,to deal with this great question in :&amp; business-like way--guaranteeing the ; migrant employment and land to settle on. We took 100,000 a year in 191,3 and 1914. We can do this; and more, easily enough, but-only if we can get money to enable the ncwc(mier to be a producer of additional wealth.To do this he must be settlednot in overcrowded-cities, but on the land ; and unless we have money to develop the Crown lands-which cost us nothing for resumption-he cannot get land to settle on at prices which will enable us to deal with large numbers.Now this is the point I wash to emphasize. Britain wants to find employment for its overcrowded population.   We want-people to develop our great estates.The remedy for each of these troubles suggests itself. The unemployment problem in Britain cannot be solved by doles or by any multiplication of such a policy. The position is grave and needs; a Temedy that goes to the root of the trouble. We have not-enough people;; you havetoo many. This- interests.-you-as much as us.We want. immigrants-;- it1 is.immaterial whether you want to lose /population or not. I tdsf inevitable, asthe. --world is-, to-day and as things -are in-Britain, that-yon -must -reduce your population.   Itris. sound policy&apos; -to- send-them from; one apart of the Empire
-where they are not wanted.to another where they are. But it requires money-a good deal of money. You cannot establish a sound comprehensive policy of iiuniigratibn for one or two years. It will take time to prepare and to grow. As the shortest time, in which this is possible, I have taken a five years&apos; period. I estimate that it will take 50,000,OOOL it we are to do anything on. a scale that will help you and us. But this can be spread over the five years. Ten millions will be wanted next year; In view of all the circumstances the Commonwealth Government asks the British Government to consider this phase of migration as an urgent question with a view to co-operating with the Commonwealth to the extent of paying one-half of the interest on the loan used for developing lands for immigrants;Message for the President of the United States. On 30th November the Governor-General transmitted a message from his Prime Minister asking that the following motion agreed toby the Senate of the Commonwealth Parliament should becommuni-cated to the President of the United States of America :-That this Senate tenders its deepest congratulations to the President of the American Republic, Mr. Harding, and the nations associated with him for the mighty work sought to be accomplished in bringing to an end the reign of destructive strife amongst men and leading them to believe that peace and goodwill have still a meaning for them, and trusts most earnestly that the good work so auspiciously begun will be steadfastly pursued until the temple of Janus is permanently closed for troubled mankind.Meat [B.E.R., Ivii, p. 10].-On 30th November the Secretary of State for the. Colonies telegraphed to the Governor-General as follows in reply to his telegram of 12th November: The Board of Trade now have disposed of all Government stocks at a considerable loss, although the purchases are not yet all cleared. The Board of Trade explain that one of the chief reasons for the recent glut was the coal strike in the summer. This caused steamers to be held up, with the result that too many arrived here simultaneously. The result was that importers and buyers had to make quick sales at lower prices. No preference has been given to Argentine meat. The Board of Trade hope that as the best period of. the year for the sale of imported meat in the United Kingdom is now approaching sales will be effected more readily; but they emphasize that the working costs will need to be stringently reduced overseas, as they anticipate that the movement of prices will continue to be downwards, and likely to settle at 5 per cent, or 10 per cent, above pre-war prices. With regard to the proposal for a subsidy His Majesty&apos;s Government appreciate fully the advantage to everybody of the arrangements under which meat supplies from Australia and New Zealand were secured during the war at a reasonable price, but regret that the present financial stringency and serious unemployment here renders help in the direction suggested quite impossible. &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government understand that the Commonwealth and New Zealand Governments and shippers are negotiatiug or about to negotiate with the steamship companies with a view to the reduction of freight, and hope that the negotiations will prove fruitful.Imports and Exports. The following statement was issued . by the official Secretary of the Commonwealth in London on 1st December : I have to advise you that the values of the goods imported to and exported from Australia during the month of October 1921 were as follows : Imports. Exports..  &apos;     &apos;6,906,985 Australian produce -   9,1.60,280Other produce        -     45S,602Total     -  9,618,882NEW ZEALAND.Delay in discharging Produce in London. The Governor-General telegraphed as follows to the Secretary of State for the Colonies on 6th December: My Ministers are most seriously concerned over the extraordinary delays which are occurring in the discharge at the port of London of steamers carrying New Zealand35-1 O
produce. Cases in point are the steamer Somerset, which recently occupied two months in discharging, and the Athenic, which arrived in London on 4th November and is still delayed in discharge; vessels which have arrived subsequently are also undergoing delay. One reason given for these delays is that the cold storage accommodation in London is congested with meat and other refrigerated produce and consequently is unable to accommodate the newly-arrived produce. My Government realize that this constitutes a very serious difficulty,&apos; which-: probably could not be overcome unless at considerable expense. But they yet feel that, having regard to the extremely serious financial position of New Zealand producers at the present time, it is urgently necessary to do all that is possible in every direction to relieve the position, seeing that not only New Zealand shippers on consignment, includ-iug a very large proportion of the dairy producers, are handicapped by being unable to realize on their shipments, but the extra cost involved to the shipping companies must naturally have a detrimental effect upon the coming negotiations for reduced freight rates. The gravity of the position is now accentuated by the collapse of the butter market in England, and my Government would be glad if His Majesty&apos;s Government would take all steps possible to enquire into the whole position as now existing at the port of London with a view to bringing about the improvements which are possible under the, circumstances. It is realized that the mere discharge from ship to cool store may not relieve the market conditions, but it will at least reduce other disabilities and provide a measure of relief from a state of affairs which, if not remedied, will have grave and far-reaching effects on the financial position of New Zealand,, whose prosperity is entirely bound up in the welfare of its producers.SOUTH AFRICA. The following paragraphs were telegraphed by ReuteFs agents :  Commissioner of Commerce for Europe. Mr. Karl Spilhaus, of Capetown, hasbeen appointed Union Commissioner for Commerce on the continent of Europe.[Capetown, 23rd November.] .&apos; The Strike in the Grown Mines. (1) Representatives of the Mines Department and the executive of the South African Industrial Federation are endeavouring to negotiate a settlement of the dispute in.the Crown mines.. It is stated that the rank and. file of the mine workers do not want to strike. The Chamber of Alines has issued, a statement pointing out that.it has; frequently laid down the principle for which it is now contending;, which it regards as &quot; absolutely vital to the discipline and efficiency of any kind of business, and that it is impossible that the Chamber can give way on this point.&quot;   [Johannesburg, 25th November.](2) The executive of the Mineworkers&apos; Union have agreed, to accept the suggestions by the Minister of Mines regarding the settlement of the Crown mines dispute subject to the stipulations that there shall be no victimization or loss of service. The matter now rests with the Chamber of Mines. [Johannesburg, 28th November.](3) The strike at the Crown mines has been settled. [Johannesburg, 2nd December.]South African Politics. Speaking at the South African party congress here to-day, General Smuts foreshadowed a Nationalist-Labour combination, lie declared that a meeting bad recently taken place in Bloemfontein, which he believed would have the most far-reaching effect on politics L South Africa. There, continued the Premier, they found at a meeting of the National Union of Railway and Harbour Services General Hertzog and Mr. Boydell on the same platform. There they embraced each other, there a new compact was signed. The position of the Nationalist party had become impossible. They might deny it, but he asked the thousands of patriotic nationalists to keep a watchful eye upon their leaders and see whither they were leading them.   [Pretoria, 29th November.]Transtaal Education Officials. A.committee of the Transvaal Executive has rescinded by 3 votes to 2 the resolution passed on 3rd November for the compulsory retirement of Dr. Adamson, the Transvaal Director of Education, and other officials at the end of 1922.   [Pretoria, 22nd November.]Defences. The Governor-General was present at a brilliant banquet last, night given by General Smuts, the Prime Minister, in houour of General Molyneux-Carter
on the occasion of his handing over officially the direction of military defence to the Union authorities.General Smuts, in proposing the health of Prince Arthur of Comiaught, declared that he was the most popular governor they had had in South Africa.Prince Arthur, in responding to the toast, said, he contemplated with regret the severance of the long and varied association of the British army with South Africa, which was, however, an inevitable incident of the UnioiPs history. The Prince declared that the delegation of the defence of one of our most important naval bases was further evidence of the mutual confidence between South Africa and the Empire which had been developed since the Union.General Smuts, in proposing the health of General Garter, expressed regret at his departure, lie went on to outline the history of the British army in South Africa, and said-the country was not only united under a strong Government, but the dominant white races were united in an everlasting and indissoluble pact of peace and friendship, and there was no more work for the British army.The equal status of South Africa was not only recognized in the British league of nations, but also internationally in the world-wide League, and the final step had been taken without reserve or misgiving and with perfect goodwill on both sides, aud a complete trust in the good faith of each other.General Smuts paid a tribute to the Imperial Governments generous gift of war material, lands and buildings, and laid emphasis upon the fact that while the army was passing away and the Union was maintaining Simons Town from the laud side, the navy would remain their bulwark on the oceans, and in security they could proceed with the task of African development.General Carter made a brief reply in which he declared that they could leave with absolute confidence.General Smuts on Unemployment. Speaking to-day at the congress of Free State ministerialists, General Smuts described last years amalgamation of the South African and Unionist parties as the corner stone on which a united South Africa had been built. The reconstituted Cabinet was the most harmonious one in which he had ever participated. The recent dismissal, of British educationists in the Transvaal was a lightning flash showing what would happen if the nationalists came into power.He dwelt on the measures the Government were taking to assist farmers to tide over the present depression, which included the obtaining of a reduction in maize freights and the appointment of Mr. Karl Spilhaus as South African Trade Commissioner for northern and western Europe with&apos; headquarters at Rotterdam. He referred to Mr. Spilhaus as being a man of outstanding ability, of whom he had the highest expectations. In conclusion he said he feared unemployment would grow still worse, but the public should not become panicky and employers should carry their share of the burden.NEWFOUNDLAND.Naoal Reductions.- The Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed to the Governor of Newfoundland on 5th November, as follows : &quot; As the Newfoundland Royal Naval Reserve, as formerly constituted, has now no men serving, and no training is being carried out on board H.M.S. Briton; aud in view of the difficulty and expense of maintaining the vessel, the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty propose to withdraw the crew and dispose of the ship.&quot;In reply to the foregoing the Governor sent the following telegram on 6th December : &quot; My Ministers urgently request the Admiralty to issue instructions at once for the training of 100 men for the Royal Naval Reserve. My Ministers are tackling in every direction the question of unemployment, which is serious, and such a decision will be of great value to them. It must be remembered that the Government of Newfoundland provides 3,&apos;000l. for this service. Meanwhile my Ministers undertake that no additional charge shall be thrown upon Imperial funds in respect of berths for H.M.S. Briton. They further undertake to find half the cost of dredging the berth in the point, of the Admiralty premises, if His Majesty&apos;s Government will bear the balance of the expenditure ; the work to be taken in hand as soon as possible.

</content>
</cab>
