<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/157/0 images: 223-230</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.SECRET.BRITISH EMPIRE REPORT.No. 65.   14th March 1922.Contents.Colonies, Protectorates, &amp;c.Cyprus. Action by a Greek Warship.Egypt.-New Ministry.Iraq. Draft Treaty with King Eeisal.India. . -The Viceroy&apos;s Fortnightly Report.The Dominions.Signature of League of Nations Protocols.Australia.-Air Communications.   Naval Prize.   Canned Fruits.   Food Prices. Trade.
COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, &amp;c.CYPRUS.Action by a Greek Warship. The following telegram was sent to the Secretary of State for the Colonies by the High Commissioner on 9th March : A Greek warship named Ierax anchored on the afternoon of 9th March off Cape Andreas, where, despite the customs officers protests, an officer and a man forced a landing. The customs officer-at Cape Andreas told the Greek officer that, in view of instructions which he had received, they could not be permitted to land there, hut if they required anything must proceed to Pamagusta, the nearest port, 50 miles distant. The Greek officer replied that he insisted upon landing. He landed and proceeded to the monastery, where he had a hurried inter view in secret with the abbot and subsequently departed. Against this violation of the law and territory of Cyprus by an armed ship of war, I must protest in the strongest manner of which I am capable; and I urge that immediate steps be taken to secure from the Greek Government the fullest satisfaction for this occurrence.EGYPT.New Ministry. The following telegram [No. 93] was sent by Lord Allenby on 28th February :-I saw the Sultan at 3 p.m. and communicated to him the declaration of His Majesty&apos;s Government, lie expressed satisfaction and said that he would summon Sarwat Pasha to form a Ministry.Sarwat Pasha called on me at 7 pan. and told me he had accepted office and that he would give me the list of his Ministry to-morrow after approval by the Sultan.I had a most cordial reception to-day in Alexandria and Cairo from, all classes and nationalities.On 1st March Lord Allenby reported [No. 91] that the following would constitute the new Ministry :  -;Abdel Khalek Sarwat Pasha - Prime Minister, Minister of Interior,and Minister for Foreign Affairs.Ismail Sidky Pasha -         - - Finance.Ibrahim Fa thy Pasha - - War.Gaafar Wali Pasha   -         - - Wakfs.Mustafa Maher Pasha - - Education.Mustafa Fa thy Pasha - - Justice.Mohammed Shukry Pasha   - - Agriculture.Hussein Wnssef Pasha        - - Public Works.Wassef Semeika Bey- - - Communications.On the same day he further reported [No. 97] that Sarwat Pasha having brought the members of his Ministry and introduced them, he found them all confident and ready to co-operate with him, Lord Allenby.IRAQ.Draft Treaty with King Feisal [B.E.R., lxiv, p. 4].-The following telegram [No. 163] was sent by the High Commissioner to the Secretary of State for the Colonies on 27th February : -As I have already informed you, both King Feisal and the Naqib, especially the latter, pressed with great insistence for the definite abrogation of the mandate. I have discussed the subject fully with them and, both verbally and in writing, have explained to them the position of His Majesty&apos;s Government and your own point of view, as set forth in your telegrams and letters. In an attempt to circumvent the sentimental difficulty I have also suggested alternative draft treaties, but they maintain their previous attitude unchanged in spite of all my efforts.
I have now received from King Feisal a long letter setting forth his final views. Be starts with his conversations with you in London and covers all the ground. This letter and our discussions come to this^ King Feisal. and the Naqib are definitely of the opinion that neither on the line, indicated by your modifications nor, by the ^alternative which you propose is it possible for them to proceed with the treaty. It is clear, they contend, that in either case it is still intended to maintain the mandatory relation. They are unwilling to accept this in principle, and it makes no difference whether it is expressed explicitly or in. a camouflaged form.Their view may be expressed in this way: &quot;Our desire for Great Britain is sincere, our need for friendship and assistance is clamorous. We want no one but -Great Britain, but we want her not as a mandatory but as an ally and a friend. His Majesty King George, in the telegram, with which he honoured me on the day of my accession, seems to have contemplated this, At the time when the idea and conditions of the &apos; mandatory &apos; were formulated by the Entente Powers they may have been reasonable and possible. Since then, however, much has happened and  to mention only one change-there has been an enormous increase in the strength of nationalist sentiment throughout Islam. Consequently, intelligent opinion in this country can no longer willingly tolerate the mandatory relation, especially now that the public have seen in what manner a parallel mandate has been interpreted or misinterpreted by the French, for whose presence in Syria, with its effect on the Arab cause, Great Britain is morally responsible. If you will give us a frank and free treaty, and complete independence, you will find that everything you need for ,the preservation of your own position and tiie interests and welfare of foreigners is yours; if, on the other hand, you insist on the proposal to &quot;mandate &apos; us, 1 and the Naqib cannot accept the odium and responsibility of being associated with such, a .policy. and you will need an army strong enough to impose your will upon am unwilling people. If, in. her own, interests or because of her undertakings towards -other Powers, Great Britain feels obliged to insist dn pressing upon Iraq a treaty on the line indicated by the Secretary of State&apos;s modifications, His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos; may prefer (since I and the Naqib cannot accept the task) to ask the National Assembly, when it is convened, to consider the treaty. We could not oppose such a -decision, but the only result, of such a course would be, in our opinion, to let loose a storm of controversy upon the country, and we cannot say what the result of the reference or of the consequent delay would be.&quot;In answer to above J have used the arguments with which you furnished me in your communications, and in addition I have argued somewhat as follows: If Great Britain and Iraq only were concerned, I am convinced that His Majesty&apos;s Government would, if only for her own convenience, respond to Iraq&apos;s aspirations towards freedom to the utmost in spite of the proverbial danger of patching old garments with new cloth, provided that they were left in a position of sufficient influence to safeguard their own reasonable interests and ensure the proper treatment of foreigners. In point of fact, however, the abrogation of the mandate may well be politically impossible for Ureat Britain vis-d-vis her allies and the League of Nations too, since other mandatories and the interests of those (one group) may be affected by any action taken in regard to Iraq. In reply to this they express their firm conviction that Great Britain can get rid of the mandate if she washes. This is in spite of the views, policy, and arguments of His Majesty&apos;s Government which I have not failed to place clearly before them.My own comment is as follows : Our attitude appears to me to be weak in. this, that the promises on which it is based, however sound at one time, are sound no longer, and I think we need to reconsider the situation with all (one group) on the basis of actualities.At the time when the mandate relationship was devised it seemed reasonable and. -even, benevolent in idea, name, and form. Since then, however, the situation has changed greatly. On the one hand we find ourselves in a state.of increasingly severe financial stress ; on the other hand a strong wave of nationalism is passing over the East. Although, owing to the absolute necessity of reducing our expenditure and withdrawing our troops, we are no longer in a position either to fulfil our obligations under the mandate in the direction of defence or to enforce it if the people of Iraq are unwilling, we still seem to cling to the idea that we are performing a duty to humanity by maintaining the mandatory relation. A considerable proportion of the people of Iraq are no doubt inarticulate. As for the rest, the moderate and pro-British party will find it very difficult to run counter to the expressed opinion of the Naqib, and if we asked them to do so we should be putting their loyalty to us to too
great a strain, while it may be taken for granted that a small bat potent element of the intelligentsia will support, and out-vie the attitude of King Feisal. When it; became known that not only King Feisal but our staunch supporter the Naqib had been unable to come to an understanding with His Majesty&apos;s Government, the-alternative of leaving the treaty for the consideration of the National Assembly would, I am convinced, offer no likelihood of a different result. We.should have very strong-public feeling against us by the time the Assembly met and the decision of the Assembly would, I think, be a foregone conclusion. Moreover, work generally will be paralyzed until the treaty is concluded, or at all events until terms are agreed upon between the King and ourselves, and the question of the British personnel, which hinges upon the treaty, and the organic law will be hung up. It seems to me, therefore, that before wo go further His Majesty&apos;s Government must review the situation seriously and come to a final decision on this fundamental question of policy. Regard being had to our admitted inability and disinclination to force any solution on Iraq, and with the fresh experience of Ireland and Egypt before us, it seems to me that we must consider whether we are or are not in a position to go to our Allies and the League of Nations and say in effect: &quot;In practice we have fulfilled our mandatory duties to Iraq for three years. The-form of mandate as first contemplated is now out of date and has moreover been interpreted by France as circumstances seemed to her to demand. The League of Nations is still ineffective and meanwhile the internal situation in Iraq has been developing quickly and satisfactorily and we cannot stop this process. - Our sole object is to do our duty by the people of Iraq while maintaining sufficient influence to ensure that legitimate British interests and the welfare of foreigners in the country are safeguarded. We have never had any other designs in Iraq. We consider that both from our own point of view and that of the people of Iraq this end can best be achieved if our future relations are formulated in a treaty of alliance (one group) as between two independent States. The terms which have been agreed upon between the two-parties are now communicated (one group).&quot; My object- in expressing myself so fully on such a point (and I do so with great diffidence) is in order that you may know in what direction I am thinking. It is my personal conviction that it is only in this direction that we can expect to find success. Considering the impossibility of adopting any costly policy in Iraq it seems, in view of the attitude of the British taxpayer, more prudent to secure the goodwill of the Iraqis by giving them what they want, the onus of failure thus remaining on them, than to adopt any policy Avhich would probably have the contrary effect.INDIA.The Viceroy&apos;s Fortnightly Report. The following telegram was sent on 28th February : Madras. Political interest centres in Guntur, but the collection of revenue is now proceeding briskly. It is not clear yet whether Gandhi&apos;s suspension of civil disobedience will have any effect, though it will probably be quoted as an authority for the payment of taxes if the movement breaks down. The district committee decided that payment should begin, but that the district should prepare for civil disobedience by strengthening the volunteer organization. Certain parts of the district will not accept this decision, and there are therefore no grounds for the relaxation of the special measures taken to reinforce the police and facilitate the collection of revenue. The arrack sales throughout the presidency have been successful.Section 2. In a few places there was excitement. In Madura, a European executive engineer and his wife were held up by crowds parading the streets, and had an uncomfortable experience until the police saw them safely through the crowd. An ordinance withdrawing martial law in Malabar, and providing for the period subsequent to the withdrawal of martial law and pending the restoration of normal -conditions, has been promulgated.Section 3. Bengal. The general attitude is one of expectancy. The postpone-ment of civil disobedience has not been welcomed by the non-co-operation leaders in.
general, and a split in the congress is freely spoken of, while the attitude of the caliphate party is still uncertain. It is too early to gauge precisely the-effect in the. more troublesome districts. There is a doubt as to whether the advice of the provincial congress committee will carry much weight,- and the possibility of control being assumed by members of the old revolutionary party. In Calcutta, the attempt to defy the authority of the police continues, but with less regularity and persistence. The general situation in Mofussil has undergone no change. The campaign against the rural police and a widespread contempt for authority is shown mainly in the boycott and general harrassment of Government servants, especially police officers on tour. This form of campaign is developing steadily in Tabna, Noakhali, parts of Chittagong and Tipperah, and seriously handicapping the investigation and punish-ment of ordinary crime. An increasing tendency for a &quot;no rent &quot; campaign has been reported from several districts. In general, the more violent elements are working up for a trial of strength, and it was expected that Bardoli would give an opportunity. Every effort has been made to organize demonstrations on the con-viction of Kalam Azad and C. R. Das. On the other hand, the more sober portion of the community is getting steadily more alarmed. The Citizens Protection League has received considerable support, and the Indian Association has issued a manifesto. The present disposition is one of apprehension (one corrupt group)ed with relief at the temporary stoppage of operations. There is a fairly considerable feeling that the postponement of civil disobedience is only a political move, and intended to lull the country to a false security, and some fear that the Government may be deceived thereby.Punjab. In the central and eastern divisions there has been very great political activity, and the campaign directed against the Government is increasing in intensity and scope. Civil disobedience-is principally confined to demonstrations by volunteers, who, specially in the sikh districts, have extended activities to the rural areas. There has been a certain amount of picketting of liquor and cloth shops. In some cases the police were able to check the nuisance, but in others the tendency of the volunteers was to get out of hand. . The activities of the provincial congress and the caliphate leaders have been largely inspired from the outside, but the sikh agitation is developing on lines of its own. The sikh political leaders are engaged in preaching unity amongst hinclns, sikhs and mohamedans, with the avowed object of winning Home Rule at an early date. The speeches do not indicate present support of extreme measures. The number of akalis is gradually increasing, the movement becoming more dangerous and openly hostile to Government. On several occasions there have been public demonstrations in military formation with drawn kirpans. In some cases subordinate officials are boycotted or humiliated for having given information or otherwise assisted in the prosecution of political cases. In Hoshiapur, speeches have been made by the sikhs threatening to take forcible possession of police stations, and directly inciting the public to defy the law. The campaign against government servants continues. Soldiers returning from leave have complained that the akali threatened them with molestation of their women if they did not leave the military service. The efforts made to bring about a strike on the North-Western Railway, before His Royal Highness&apos;s visit, have not materialized as yet. The encouraging features are the comparative quietness of the two western divisions, excellent crop prospects, the continued demand for currency notes, indications from a few quarters of a revulsion of feeling against violence and intimidation and the absence of signs of difficulty in recruiting. The conditions in the central and eastern divisions, however, are worse. The akali movement is a political one, aiming at the subversion of the present Government, with a claim for the succession for sikhs ; the possibility of military action in the sikh districts has been considered. But a meeting of officers recently held did not disclose any general conviction that the time for it has arrived. Steps are being taken by the Government to impress officers of the importance of the steady enforcement of law, and it is not impossible that dangers may be tided over until the harvest operations begin. The Punjab situation was discussed in Council on the 20th, Maclagan being present. He stated that orders had been issued for disarming to bo carried out, first on an experimental scale by the police, of Jathas marching about the country. It is not proposed at present, however, to prohibit the carrying of kirpans. It was hoped that the disarming of bands would be successfully carried out and no serious outbreaks occur before the harvest operations began. He could not forecast the course of events after the harvest was got in. Last year, contrary to expectation, there was some cessation of activity, and this experience might be repeated this year. In the event of untoward developments 38-8 rs
and troops being required, lie did not think that more than two companies would be needed in any one district. The armed police in various parts are being largely increased. The aim of the Punjab Government bad been to keep the religious side of the agitation separate from the political, and to a large extent it had been successful in this. The akali movement as a whole had developed on lines of its own and independently of the general non-co-operation movement.United Provinces.-Bareilly is quiet but sullen. In Gorakpur, the Chauri Ghaura-neighbourhood, is largely deserted, but the outlying than as are suffering fromnervousness. The police have been strengthened, and a detachment of Punjabis sent from Lucknow. In many districts high tension is reported and the activities of the non-co-operators are extending, e.g., Shalijahanpur, Budau-n, Pilibhit, Etah, Fyzabad, Bahraioh. Sultanpur, Bara Banki, Allahabad, Sitapur, Kheri, Hardoi, and even Banda. The situation is rapidly deteriorating and getting more out of control. The local Government has no doubt that the deterioration will spread and have alarming developments unless action is taken to stop the agitation at its source. The United Provinces situation was also discussed in the Council on the 20th; Sir Harcourt Butler said that the police were apprehensive and, in general, showed signs of being disheartened. Steps were being-taken, to enrol additional police armed with modern rifles and intended for the use of the armed police more largely in dealing with mobs. The element in the United Provinces which believed that the British iiaj was weakening was gaining in strength. The subversive propaganda amongst the masses had had the result that the disorderly elements were now only imperfectly, if at ail, under the control of the leaders of the non-co-operation, movement. The mohamedan population of numerous small towns -which had been subjected for many years to economic pressure, was very hostile and controlled by fanatical maul vis,Bihar and Orissa. The strike on tho East Indian Railway has necessitated the imposition of strike schemes. At Jamalpur the situation, at one time was very serious, but tlie local officers have the situation in hand, and do not anticipate trouble unless there are political developments, elsewhere. The reports from the district officers and commissioners unite in describing the general political situation as quiet on the surface, with a good deal of underground agitation. There has been some recrudescence of picketting. The police force is being increased ; some districts, hitherto comparatively free from trouble, now report agitation, e.g., the Palamow andSantal pargannas. It is reported that the (? incessant) (inception of) active agitation in Tirhoot may provoke troubles, which the leaders themselves would gladly prevent. The Government can expect very little support from the moderates, beyond abstention from criticism, or from voting against the Government.North-West Frontier Province. The political situation is satisfactory.Section 4. Delhi. The outstanding event is His Royal Highness the Prince of Wales s visit, which has been completely successful. The rural population and the people of the city came in thousands ; on the processional route the greatest enthusiasm prevailed, there was no disturbance or unpleasant demonstration.Burma. The political calm continues. There has been little political oratory in the country, except from the monks. The Rangoon Times gave currency to a rumour that Gandhi had been arrested, which led to partial hartal in Rangoon, but the pews, although apparently generally believed, excited little interest. There has been considerable improvement in the spirit of the local sikhs; and the reception committee of the All-Burma Khalsa Diwan, held recently at Pegu, was completely captured by the moderates.Section 5. Central Provinces. There has been no increase in political activity ; the excise sales are passing off quite successfully; picketting of the liquor shops has been extended, but is not generally effective. In some cases consumers are beginning to show active resentment against interference with their habits. The enrolment of volunteers continues ; the non-co-operation party is capturing a number of seats iu the municipal elections. Berar is more peaceful than it has been for some time past, and the attitude of the villagers leaves little to be desired. There is a strong move-ment towards removing the: boycott of the Legislative Councils. In the Chattisgargh divison the situation is more disquieting.Assam-In the Surma Valley many meetings had been held and numbers of volunteers enlisted. The volunteers have been active, their efforts being directed to contaminate the garden labour force by enlisting coolies as volunteers. The Governor has decided that a more active policy is required in this valley, and instructions have
been issued accordingly. , The civil police and the Assam Rifles are being increased in consequence. More or less decided improvement is reported from most districts of the Surma Valley; except Lakhimpur, where the non-co-operation &apos; movement is spreading. In Sibsagar, there is a tendency to convert religious into political meetings. Interference with the hats is diminishing. The collection of land revenue is backward, but the firm measures are succeeding. Attempts fo boycott Government -servants appear to have ceased. There have been minor strikes in tea gardens. In the Assam Valley the main danger is that the non-co-operation movement may widely infect the tea garden coolies. It is impossible to estimate the direct effect of the postponement of civil disobedience on Assam. The movement passed into the hands of the numerous local leaders, to such an extent that it is doubtful whether the congress declaration will restrain it for so long as the enlistment of volunteers .goes on.Section 6. General.--In the Assembly, ,on the 23rd, the Home member, in answer to a question, made the following statement : The Government have seen and -considered the resolutions referred to, i.e., the Bardoli resolutions. They can discover in them, no indication of any fundamental change in the attitude and policy of the non-co-operation party. Whilst civil disobedience is to be postponed for the present, there was no suggestion that it should be definitely abandoned as an item in the programme. On &quot;the contrary, the clear intention of the resolution was that the&apos; step :should be merely suspended until the ground had been adequately prepared for inauguration on. a large scale. Though volunteer processions were temporarily to cease, the enrolment of volunteers was to continue, and to be speeded up. Seditious propaganda, which has been carried on throughout the country since the inception of the movement, was in no way to be abated, and the continuance of attempts to (? seduce) Government servants was specially provided for. The resolution thus points merely to a temporary change in tactics, and not to any reversal or radical alteration of aims, which are directed, as before, to the subversion and paralysis of the lawfully con-.-stituted Government of the country. The Government of India desire to make it clear that, unless and until there is a complete cessation of the illegal activities of the non-co-operation movement, there will be no change in their attitude in regard thereto. These activities have already produced a serious situation, which may at any moment -eventuate in bloodshed and disorder. The All-India congress committee met at Delhi on the 25th, and resolved, after long deliberation, that individual civil dis--obedience, whether of a defensive or an aggressive character, may be commenced in respect of particular places or particular laws, at the instance of, and upon permission being granted by, the respective provincial committees ; provided that such civil disobedience shall not be permitted unless all the conditions laid clown by the congress, or. the All-India congress committee, or the working committee, are strictly fulfilled. The Bardoli resolutions are unacceptable to the younger men, to the more -extreme elements in the Punjab, United. Provinces and Bengal, and to mohamedans. The view put forward by Pandit Malaviya is merely to confirm the Bardoli resolution, -and the idea Of the abandonment of civil disobedience, non-co-operation, had no support in any quarter of the committee. Gandhi moved the resolution, which was carried, but it probably does&apos; not strictly reflect his personal views, and was drafted to meet the general opinion prevalent among the congress leaders. There is danger that the control of provincial, organizations over local agitators and disorderly elements may become half-hearted and ineffective.THE DOMINIONS.&apos; Signature of League of Nations Protocols. On 8th March the following telegram was sent by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Governors-General of Canada. Australia, New Zealand and South Africa with reference to his despatch dated 31st December 1921 :-It was decided that the Protocols embodying the amendments to the Covenant, League of Nations, except those relating to Article 16, should be signed by the British representative on the Council at the first opportunity, probably at the next meeting of the Council, and. proposed that the Protocols so signed should be ratified by His Majesty in clue course.   Do your Ministers concur in the ratification, of these
Protocols ? If so it would be convenient if tbey could arrange for tlie prior signature--. of the Protocols in question at Geneva at a convenient opportunity.AUSTRALIA.Air Communications [B.E.R., lix, p. 6].-With reference to previous telegraphic communications the Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed to the Governor-General of Australia on Sth March as follows : His Majesty&apos;s Government have given very careful consideration to the proposal of the Commonwealth Government regarding the Imperial Airship Service. In view of the financial difficulties of the present time, and the inability of the Governments-of New Zealand, and the Union of South Africa, as well as of the Government of India, to participate, they have witli much regret come to the conclusion that they are no longer justified in maintaining the airships and the airship establishments as proposed by yon. The Air Council accordingly have found it necessary to proceed with the arrangements for handing over to the Disposal Commission the airships and: airship establishments and material.Naval Prize [B.E.R., xlvii, p. 10]. Referring to the Secretary of State&apos;s telegram: of 30th June 1921, the Governor-General telegraphed on 13th March as follows :-The Government of the Commonwealth of Australia is desirous of accepting the-alternative that His Majesty&apos;s Government waive, in favour of the Dominion Govern-ments concerned, their rights iu the condemned prizes not adjudged to the Prize Fund, which are. condemned within the Dominions. The Commonwealth will agree-to the conditions as set out under this alternative in your telegram of 30th June. They would be glad of advice, as soon as practicable, as to whether this alternative is adopted.Canned Fruits. The High Commissioner for Australia has been officially advised that the Australian pack of this season&apos;s canned fruits is turning out splendidly. A mild summer has been most favourable both for the gradual maturity of the fruit and for its delivery to the canneries, and it is confidently announced that a high quality Australian fruit, well graded and well got up, will be placed upon the London market this year.! Food Prices - On 28th February the following was issued from the offices of the High Commissioner; There has been a sharp decline in the cost of living in Australia and things look as though they would soon be at the normal again or very near it. The latest advices received by the High Commissioner, Sir Joseph Cook, are to the effect that on 22nd January the then current prices in the Commonwealth for food and groceries represented an increase of 41&apos; 8 per cent, only on their pre-war cost in July 1914. The highest point reached during the war was about 100 per cent, above pre-war-level. According to these figures, GO per cent, of the inflation has gone a very satisfactory state of affairs, and an indication of the way in which Australia is getting over her war troubles.Trade. On 1st March the acting official secretary of the High Commissioner issued the following statement in regard to the trade of Australia during the month of January 1922 :- ^Imports - -        - -    8,644,9S5Exports        ------  10,486,557Of the exports, Australian produce amounted to&apos; 10,190,156Z.

</content>
</cab>
