<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/157/0 images: 319-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.SECRET.BRITISH EMPIRE REPORT.No. 79.  27th September 1922.Contents.Great Britain.Unemployment Situation.Colonies, Protectorates, &amp;c.Kenya Colony. The Indian Problem.   Indian National Congress.   The Turkish Victories.Rhodesia. The Referendum.Palestine. Monthly Administrative Report.Iraq. The Near East Situation.India.The Fortnightly Report.    Moslem Resolution.    Moslem Deputation to the Viceroy.The Dominions.New Zealand.-&quot; C &quot; Mandates.South Africa.-Gold Output.   The Near East.
GREAT BRITAIN.Unemployment Situation. The following summary of the situation is taken from the special report on unemployment for the period 1st to 15th September, issued by the Ministry of Labour: In the coal-mining industry noticeable improvement is reported from all districts. The position in the iron and steel industry in the North-Eastern Division shows signs of improvement; in fact, slight improvement is reported from almost all other districts. Shipbuilding and repairing remains depressed generally, but an encouraging sign is a report that some orders for new constructional work are in hand in the North-Eastern Division.   The engineering industry is still very quiet generally.The woollen and worsted industry in the North-Eastern Division continues active. The cottou industry is very unsettled, although the fine-spinning section is still fully employed. The lace industry in the Midlands shows slight revival. In Scotland the overseas trade in hosiery and lace is well maintained, and the cotton aud textile trades are in good condition. The linen and jute trades are still depressed. The building industry is generally quiet, and the improvement previously reported in the South-Western Division has not been maintained. Employers in the South-Eastern Division, however, consider the prospects for the coming winter to be brighter than last year. A temporary revival of the glass bottle industry has occurred in the North-Eastern D^dsion, but in the South-Eastern Division the glass trade is further depressed.   -Discharges are taking place from Government establishments under the arrange-meuts for the cessation of short-time working.COLONIES, PROTECTORATES, &amp;c.KENYA COLONY.The following reports were telegraphed from Nairobi by Reuters agent The Indian Problem. A meeting of the Executive Council was held here yesterday, presided over by the Governor, Sir Robert Coryndon, at which, it is understood that the final terms of the settlement of the Indian question were discussed. It is believed that these terms include inter alia a common franchise, subject tp an education test, the greater part of the highlands to be reserved for Europeans, but there will be one Indian district, and the immigration of Indians to be very considerably restricted.   [10th September.]Indian National Congress. An Indian national congress, which was opened by the Governor of the East African Protectorate, Sir Robert Coryndon, was held here during the week-end. Numerous resolutions were passed, demanding equality of status. One speaker demanded : &quot; Either equality in the Empire or no Empire at all.&quot;A resolution was moved by the Zanzibar delegates and passed by the congress to the effect that the post of High Commissioner of Zanzibar should be withdrawn, as it-had not justified its retention in past years.It is understood that the Zanzibar Chamber of Commerce and the Sultan are in favour of this step, as the British resident is capable of carrying out all duties and of dealing direct with the Colonial Office.Another resolution passed by the congress stated that if municipal right was not granted to India within a certain period, they would refuse to pay rates. [18th September.]The Turkish Victories.-A. mass meeting of Moslems held here yesterday, composed of Indians, Arabs, Somalis, and Africans, passed a resolution expressing gratitude for the success of the Turks, and offered prayers for the restoration of the Caliphate. The meeting called attention to the British Governments pledge of neutrality, and expressed in very strong terms its resentment at intervention by Christian Powers.   [18th September.]
RHODESIA.Telegraphing from Salisbury, Reuters agent sent the following report:  The Referendum [B.E.R., lxxviii, p. 5]. Tbe political situation is developing rapidly. While the movement in favour of incorporation in the Union of South Africa is much in evidence, the cause of Responsible Government appears to have won most support from the general public, and on present indications there appears little doubt but that the referendum will result in a large majority in favour of Responsible Government.Note. A referendum will be taken in Southern Rhodesia on 27th October to decide whether the territory shall become a self-governing colony or a province of the Union of South Africa.PALESTINE.Monthly Administrative Report [B.E.R., LXXVII, p. 3]. The following information is taken from the administrative report for the month of August 1922 : -Agricultural Service. Threshing of winter crops is not yet completed in several districts. Summer crops have matured early as a result of a high range of temperature, and sesame, durra and peas are already being harvested in the plains. The general condition of these crops is excellent, and yields are expected to be above the average.   The vintage is practically finished.Satisfactory yields and prices have been noted in the northern districts, and there is a general and insistent demand for seed and technical assistance. The importance of this development is accentuated by a further slump in the values of all other staples. The grain market is absolutely stagnant, and prices are nominal. Foreign produce of all classes iss being imported into Palestine despite the protection of an 11 per cent, customs duty, while an attempt to collect arrears of taxation in Transjordania has led to heavy movements of grain and livestock across the -Jordan.With last seasoiPs vintage still unsold, the larger wine-cellars are devoting their attention to the preparation of other products, Thus at Zichron and Rishon the grape juice is being boiled to a syrup, which is being exported to England, The &quot; Victoria Wine Company &quot; in that country intend to attempt the local manufacture&apos; of wine from this substance. Efforts to find new openings for Palestinian wines in India, Japan and America have proved abortive, while an unfavourable exchange&apos; still closes the French and Italian markets. Similarly, prices realized for table grapes in Egypt have barely covered freight and charges.Veterinary Service. Livestock maintains condition satisfactorily, despite heat and lack of grazing.   Prices both of working and slaughter cattle have responded to- continued heavy importations, and meat values have slumped with the influx of livestock from Transjordania. Animals to the number of 29,020 were imported during the month, exclusive of some 22,000 camels brought across the Jordan at Semakh by the Roalla tribe. Livestock to the number of 8,200 head returned to Syria and Trans-jordania after grazing in Palestine.Forest Service. The propagation of nursery stock is proceeding rapidly at all centres in the hope that loan funds may be forthcoming this season for a scheme of commercial afforestation. Agricultural assistants have rendered valuable help since associated with forest-rangers in the work of conservation, and exhibit great interest in this additional duty. All felling has been prohibited until further notice in the Ramallah area, and additional permits wall be issued for the Nablus district only in very exceptional circumstances. With a growing recognition of the requirements of the &quot;Woods and Forests Ordinance,&quot; the number of forest offences continues to&apos; decrease, and the re-growth of dak-coppice in many districts is evidence of the value- of control.Antiquities. At Beisan, Dr. Fisher has resumed work on the acropolis, and is now preparing to remove a Byzantine level 2 metres thick in order to lay bare the earlier Roman works below.Commerce and Industry. Brisk building operations continue at Haifa, Jaffa and Jerusalem.The transit trade at Haifa showed an increase on the month of June. Further information as to the causes for the steady decline in this trade prior to the month of
July now indicates that it has been due to a decline in trade at Damascus rather than, to any diversion of transit trade from Haifa to Beyrout.A branch of (he Imperial Ottoman Bank is to be opened at Nablus on 1st Sep-tember 1922.A Belgian shipping society has inaugurated a monthly shipping service to Haifa,, which it is hoped will stimulate the export of wines and cereals to Belgium.Immigration and Travel. 8,9-57 travellers entered Palestine during the month of July, and 2,786 left, including 48 discharged Egyptian labourers, 186 emigrants (jews 39, christians 87, moslems 60), and 112 immigrants (jews 89, christians 13, moslems 10) who had decided not to remain.Three hundred and forty-nine immigrants, of whom 336 were jews, entered Palestine during the month ; of these 176 came from Poland.Twenty-two immigrants who failed to comply wdth the Palestine Immigration Regulations were refused admission.Labour. Unemployment, showed a further diminution during the month, and there are probably at present not more tban 500 or 600 unemployed men in Palestine. To a considerable extent this is due to the building activity in the towns. With the-end of the vintage more men will become available for employment, but these should be absorbed by the new undertakings thatare about to be commenced.IRAQ.The Near East Situation. On 18th September the High Commissioner sent the-following report to the Secretary of State for the Colonies :-Feisal and I naturally spoke of the stirring news from Smyrna and Constantinople-at the interview to which my immediately preceding telegram refers. According to-public opinion, Mustapha Kemal would move against Iraq at once if the Dardanelles question led to a state of war between Great Britain and Turkey. Feisal begged to-be kept in our confidence as regards the possibility of the Turks undertaking a move--meat against Iraq, and any other developments of the situation. Feisal said that, in such a contingency as a Turkish advance on Iraq, Great Britain must inform the-Government of Iraq in what way the latter could best co-operate in resistance to the-Turks. All available men of Iraq local forces should, in his opinion, be concentrated, in Mosul.INDIA.The Fortniglillij lie-port. The following is an official report from India on events-of the fortnight ended 13th September : Madr.;s. There has not been a great deal of political activity during the fortnight.   The visit of the Civil Disobedience Committee to Telegu districts does not seem to have produced a lasting effect.   The author of a communist pamphlet, a dangerous anarchist named Nilakanta Aykari, has been arrested.   He attempted to shoot a constable who was taking him to the police station, and will be tried for attempted murder, as well as under sections 153a and .1 24-a.   He has given certain information against important members of the extremist party in Madras, and the--case may well prove to be sensational.   The situation as regards the outbreak in Gudiam Hills (Vizagapatam Agency) is still extremely obscure, and the cause and object of the outbreak is not clear.   The immediate object of the gang seems to have been the release of one Virayya Dora, concerned in a similar outbreak in 1916, and detained as a State prisoner, who was under trial for escape from custody.   The police reserves have not yet established control, but should be able to deal with the-situation without further assistance.   It is not thought that the outbreak has any-political significance.Bombay. Nothing of importance to report.Bengal. The general situation has undergone very little change during the-fortnight. Spasmodic picketing is reported from a few districts; picketing has ceased in Calcutta. Leading non-co-operators are interested in trying to ascertain the views of C. It. Das on the present situation and future policy.   He gives guarded
replies now, and will state his reasoned opinion at the All-India Congress Committee meeting in the middle of September. He is reported to advocate entry into tbe Councils, with a view to opposing all Government measures. No change in tbe situation is likely until after the meeting of the All-India Congress Committee.United Provinces. No marked change. Efforts to keep agitation alive con-tinue, especially in Benares, Etavva and Jhansi. Two divisions report more than the usual friction between the hindus and mohamedaus in connexion with the Muharram festival.   Crime is normal or below normal.Punjab. Gandhi Day was ignored save for a few meetings, and the lull in Congress and caliphate agitation continues. On 22nd August, the declaration of Congress of Caliphate and National Volunteers as unlawful associations was cancelled in all districts except Lahore, Amritsar, Rawal Pindi and Ambala. Liquor shops in Rawal Pinch are no longer being picketed. As to the Muharram riot at Multan, the latest correspondence shows that the situation has improved, though there is still acute tension. The leaders are working to restore confidence. Deaths so far verified number 4 ; the cases of grievous hurt are not likely to exceed 100, but accurate figures at present are impossible to obtain.Bihar and Orissa. The general political situation remains much the same. The small excitement caused by the visit of the Civil Disobedience Committee has spent itself. The Committee had a good reception at Patna. The proceedings were secret, but it is believed that the majority of witnesses considered Bihar unfit for mass civil disobedience. Opinions were divided with regard to the boycott of Councils and Government institutions, but a strong body of opinion was in favour of entering the Councils and allowing legal practitioners, who could not support themselves, to resume practice. There was a general admission that the present constructive programme did not appeal to the masses aud that more attractive features must be found. Evidence taken by the Caliphate Euquiry Committee seems to have shown a contrary tendency, the most important witnesses urging mass civil disobedience and the wholesale boycott of foreign goods. The difference of tone between hindu and mohamedan witnesses indicates, in the opinion of the Commissioner of Patna, a split between the Caliphate and Hindu Congress parties.Central Provinces. Some revival of political agitation during the fortnight is shown. The non-co-operation party is attempting to rouse enthusiasm by demon-strations welcoming the leaders released from jails. The most objectionable speakers have been prosecuted under section 109. The enrolment of Congress members is not large, funds are low and some national schools have collapsed. The straggle between the followers of Gandhi and Tilak continues. There are signs of some small revival of the volunteer movement.Institutions for training volunteers have been started at Raipur. The renewal of picketing of liquor shops in Seoui failed, owing to the strong attitude of consumers. It is reported that attempts are being made at Bilaspur by an Indian Labour Union to create unrest among the Indian employees of the Bengal-Nagpur Railway.Assam. The visit of the Civil Disobedience Committee has had little effect. The fortnight was without incident.Noam-West Frontier Province. There has been no political agitation.Delhi.--Some revival of interest in politics is shown. On the whole the fortnight w as uneventful.General. Pandit Motilal announces that the meeting of the All-India Congress Committee will be held at Calcutta on 10th November to consider the report of the Civil Disobedience Enquiry Committee. Mr. lvale&apos;s resolution condemning the Prime MinisteFs speech on the Civil.Service was rejected on 7th September by the Council of State without being pressed to a division. The Assembly yesterday, by 48 votes to 34, adopted the following resolution :-&quot; This Assembly views with grave concern the pronouncement of the Prime Minister, and considers that the tenor of the whole speech and the sentiments therein are in conflict with the declarations of His Majesty and Plis responsible Ministers, and &apos;: -that it is calculated to create serious apprehensions in the minds of the Assembly and people of this country, both in the matter of attaining swaraja and of the Indianization of the services.&quot;44-4 B
GOfficials, members and non-official Europeans urged that, not only had assurances been given by His Excellency the Viceroy, on the authority of the Prime Minister, tbat nothing in the Prime Minister&apos;? speech was intended to conflict with previous declarations as regards the policy of His Majesty&apos;b Government, but that the refusal to accept these assurances would produce an unfavourable impression on the British Parliament and people, whose goodwill was essential to any further development of the reforms.The balance of argument, it would probably be generally agreed, was decidedly on the Government side, but the majority of the non-official members were determined to give expression to their resentment. A notable feature, however, was the number of members who were either absent or abstained from voting, and it is significant that the votes of the mohamedan elected members were almost exactly divided. AVe do not think that the passing of this resolution need be taken very seriously, though it undoubtedly gave expression to feelings which at the moment are fairly widely felt in India. It. illustrates, however, the difficulties inherent in a constitution under which the executive Government are in a large permanent minority in the Legislature.Modem Resolution. The Viceroy telegraphed the following report on 15th September: A meeting of the Moslem members of the Indian Legislature passed the following resolution and transmitted it to mo :  . &quot; This meeting, representing 70 millions of His Majesty&apos;s Indian Moslem subjects, is sincerely convinced that the conclusion of an honourable peace, whereby Turkish Empire will retain Asia Minor and Thrace, including Adrianople, with guarantees for the protection oE minorities, whereby International control over Constantinople and the Straits should be removed, with guarantees for the freedom of the latter, aud whereby the religious position of the Sultan as Caliph &quot;of Islam should be duly recognized, is essential to the restoration of peace in the Near and Middle East, and to mutual co-operation and goodwill in it.&quot;Moslem Deputation to the Viceroy. The following telegram to the Secretary of State for India was sent by the Viceroy on 21st September : -I received a deputation of Moslem Members of the Indian Legislature yesterday, and, in accordance with my promise to them, 1 forward their views to you for the information of the Cabinet.2. I was impressed with the moderation and restraint With which they placed their points before me. They urged that Moslem opinion in India was deeply stirred by recent Turkish victories. Present moment, in their opinion, was favourable for termination of long hostilities. While admitting grave wrong done by Turkey in siding with our enemies in late war in spite of historical obligations to us, they earnestly expressed deep present sympathy of Indian Moslems, on religious grounds, with Turkey, and desire that Turkey should not be deprived of the fruits of victory over Greeks; that peace should be concluded, ensuring conditions essential to Turkey&apos;s position, at an early date ; and that Great Britain and the Empire, with its large Moslem population, should once more&apos; join in friendly relations with greatest Mohamedan Power. Essential conditions of peace for Turkey, in their view, were restoration to Turks of Ottoman Thrace, including Adrianople, Constantinople and Asia Minor, with Smyrna,.after settlement of measures for protection of minorities. As regards the Straits, they appreciated the difficulties of the situation, and desired the Straits to be restored to Turkey on furnishing guarantees. I pointed out that, in February last, they would have been content with the neutrality of the Straits in the control of a number of nations, together with Turkey, if carried out in a manner to safeguard Constantinople itself against sudden attack by an enemy. It was unthinkable to them that sacred relics of Prophet most revered by Moslems should be at the mercy of an attack on Constantinople, owing to restrictions on Turkish defence in the Straits. My impression is that it is to the latter point they attach most importance. A plan of control of the freedom of the Straits by a European Commission, with Turkey holding a prominent place on it, would, I think, satisfy them, unless Turkey itself raised strong objection. They made request that Indian Moslems should be associated in discussions regarding peace.3. They did not wish, at this moment, to press their views on the control of Holy Places outside Turkey proper, or on Arab settlements, wdiich they admit can be. dealt with separately, and at a later date.
4. A motion.to adjourn the House to consider the Near East situation, and urge&apos; &quot;that Indian troops be not employed in any dispute in territories of the former Turkish Empire, had been, dropped in the morning, in view of. my consent to receive this deputation.5. It must be remembered that this was not a public deputation, and that the Press did not attend, and considerable restraint and calmness were displayed. But public meetings are taking place throughout India, and more jubilation and excitement consequent upon the Moslem victories are noticeable, and more extravagant demands are advanced, and, in some places, bitter attacks are made upon Britain as the outstanding Power, operating to check the legitimate effect of Turkish triumphs, whilst the Extremist (? Hindu) Press points to France and Italy as the more moderating influences in favour of Turkish claims.THE DOMINIONS.NEW ZEALAND.&quot;0&quot; Mandates [B.E.R., lxxviii, p. I].-The Secretary of State for the Colonies telegraphed to the Governor-General of New Zealand on 16th September as follows :   . Further consideration of the question raised by the Government of the United States of America as to Article 3, 1899 Treaty, was postponed on account of the -attitude of the United States on the general question of &quot; C &quot; Mandates, but as the Government of the United States have been pressing for a reply on the treaty point, Plis Majesty&apos;s Government would be glad to be able to deal with the matter at an early date.The general representations of the United States as to their treatment in &quot;C&quot; Mandate territories, as to which see my telegram of 30th August [B.E.R., lxxviii, p. 3], -cannot be answered pending, the result of consultation, with all the Dominions concerned. But the United States&apos; claim under the 1899 Treaty, although mentioned in the general representations, is a special and separate matter primarily affecting New Zealand, and the reply can be settled independently of the general discussion. The Law Officers of the Crown here have been consulted on the questions (1) whether Article 3 of the treaty should be regarded as still in force as between Great Britain .and the United States; (2) if so, whether the establishment by New Zealand of preferential tariff for western Samoa, from the benefits of which the United States are excluded, is in accordance with Article 3; (3) whether Article 3, if still in force, debars the United States Government from any system of preference for United States shipping trading with Tutuila., The Law Officers have advised that Article 3 of the treaty is still in force, and accordingly that any tariff discrimination as between British and United States goods in western Samoa seems precluded, but that the treaty equally precludes preference for United States shipping trading with Tutuila. In view of the Law Officers&apos; advice the best course appears to be to inform the Government of the United States that the Government of New Zealand are prepared to extend any preferential tariff in western Samoa to United States goods under the 1899 Treaty, but that in the opinion of the New Zealand Government and His Majesty&apos;s Government the treaty equally prevents any system of preference for United&quot; States vessels in Tutuila, and especially precludes the United States Government from confining trade between the United States aud Tutuila to United States vessels, and that the proposed extension of preferential tariff to western Samoa is conditional on the acceptance of this view by the United States Government. Please telegraph whether your Ministers concur.SOUTH AFRICA.Gold Output. Referring to a message of 30th July 1919 on the disposal of the :South African gold output, the Governor-General of South Africa sent the following telegram to the Secretary of State for the colonies on 16th September :--My Ministers point out that with the expiration of the Public Welfare and Moratorium Act of 1914 as subsequently amended on 1st July last, the export of gold .from the Union has been freed from Government control.   In these circumstances
the Union of South Africa is no longer directly concerned with any arrangements-which the gold producers may make with the Bank of England or any other purchaser for the disposal of their product.&apos; As the existing arrangements were approved by both His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Union of South Africa, my Ministers ask me to advise you of the change of circumstances rendering the approval of the Union of Eouth Africa to any such arrangements unnecessary. They add that the Union gold producers have been advised accordingly, aud express the view that the interests of&quot; the producers and of the Union would best be served if the marketing of the gold output were free from all restriction as to the destination and conditions of sale.The following information was transmitted by ReuteFs agent: Tlie Near East,. Commenting in a leading article ou the British Governments, appeal to the Dominions in regard to the Near East, the Cape Times declares that none of the Dominions, remote though each may feel from the present conflict, can affect indifference to a thing which is vital to the economic restoration of the world,, but for the moment there is no special urgent question of the Union of South Africa sending a contingent to the Dardanelles.The journal continues: &quot;We take it that what the Prime Minister of Great Britain wants to show the world is that the Dominions stand solidly and unitedly at the back of the Imperial Government and in this there should be no difficulty. The Dominions as signatories of the unratified Treaty of Sevres have a definite obligation in the matter. The South African Government ought therefore to announce in the-clearest possible terms that the British Government will have the unswerving moral support of the Union in its determination to resist any violation of the demilitarized neutral zone, and, if necessary, and if Parliament authorizes it, material support also.&apos;&apos;The newspaper concludes: &quot;If the Union Government added to its message to-the Imperial Government the devout wish that&apos;the whole problem of the Near East should be referred for honest settlement to the League of Nations instead of to a-conference dominated by intriguing European Powers whose hands are tied by all sorts of secret understandings, it would express the opinion generally entertained in South Africa.   [Capetown, 17th September.]

</content>
</cab>
