<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/184/0 images: 218-231</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1927.SECRET.Copy No.     30CP. 19 (27).CABINET.REPORT BY THE SELECT COMMITTEE OF THE HOUSE OF lords on IRISH LAND  PURCHASE.IN May, 1925, I circulated to the Cabinet a memorandum (OP. 274 (25)) on &quot;The position of Loyalists in the Irish Free State.&quot; In the first part of that memorandum I dealt with the question of Land Purchase; and after referring to the conclusion reached by the previous Conservative Government in July, 1923, that &quot;Lord Birkenheachs pledge was sufficiently fulfilled by the Land. Bill (now the Land Act of 1923) now before the Free State Parliament,&quot; I stated that &quot;taking into consideration all the circumstances and comparing the position of the landowners with that of other classes who have suffered by the change of Government in Ireland, I am bound to say that I do not think the landowners have been badly treated by the Free State Government.&quot;This memorandum was considered by the Cabinet on the 26th June, 1925 (Cabinet 31 (25), Conclusion 3). The Cabinet approved certain recommendations which I had made regarding the reconstitution and terms of reference of the Irish Grants Committee. No reference appears in the Cabinet minutes to the question of Land Purchase, but I assume that my colleagues agreed with my view and reaffirmed the conclusion of their predecessors in 1923, to which I have already referred.On the 3rd February, 1926, a debate took place in the House of Lords on a motion by Lord Oranmore and Browne &quot;that a Select Committee be appointed to examine the pledges given between 1920 and 1923 by Ministers of the Crown in regard to the completion of Irish Land Purchase, and to report whether these pledges have been fulfilled.&quot; The motion was opposed by the Government, and I would refer my colleagues to the Debate, and particularly to the speeches of Lord Clarendon and the Lord Chancellor.   Nevertheless, the motion was carried by 35 votes to 33.A Select Committee, consisting of Lord Chelmsford (Chairman), Lord Halsbury,. Lord Lamington, Lord Redesdale, Lord Askwith, Lord Forres and Lord Darling was in due course appointed and has now issued its Report, a copy of which I annex.* Lord Chelmsford wrote to Lord Salisbury asking whether His Majesty&apos;s Government desired through any of its members to offer evidence to the Committee, but the Cabinet decided on the 30th June, 1926 (Cabinet 43 (26), Conclusion 11), &quot;that the Lord Privy Seal should reply to Lord Chelmsford that the Government did not desire to offer any evidence before the Irish Land Purchase Committee, which was appointed contrary to their wishes.&quot;It will be seen that the Committee found (paragraph 33) that &quot;in so far as the Free State is concerned, the pledges have not been fulfilled, to the extent that the provisions of the Free State Land Act differ from and fall short of the provisions of the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925.&quot; Lord Oranmore and Browne came to see me on the 2nd December and asked whether the Government proposed to take any action on the Report. In reply I promised to bring- the Report to the notice of my colleagues and to inform him of our decision in due course.(Pledges by Ministers of the Crown.)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.* Annex I.[156671b
I have carefully examined the Select Committee&apos;s Report, and I do not feel that it adds anything to the considerations which I put before my colleagues in May, 1925, nor to those on which the previous decision of the Cabinet in 1923 was based. I annex to this memorandum a note on the Report* which, I venture to thinks, shows that the members of the Committee were not well acquainted with the question which they were called upon to examine and that their examination was of a superficial character. Should the Report be discussed in Parliament, I do not anticipate that it would be difficult to show that the question at issue is not affected one way or the other by the deliberations of the Select Committee.As to the merits of the question itself, I pointed out in my memorandum of May, 1925, that the claim of the landowners (a claim which is restated and reaffirmed by the Select Committee) is for the difference, amounting to approximately  6,000,000, between the purchase price which they would have received had the terms of the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925, been applied to the Irish Free State and that which they will receive under the Free State Act of 1923, and that this claim was, in my opinion, inadmissible, whether it was for  6,000,000 in cash or for  6,000,000 in stock. I adhere to that opinion. I went on to say, however, that it remained to be considered whether there was any concession substantially less than their full claim which we could and ought to grant, and that this could not, in my opinion, be considered without, at the same time, considering the position of the many others who have suffered owing to the change of Government in Ireland.The position of these others has now been considered and dealt with by the appointment of the new Irish Grants Committee. The terms of reference to that Committee direct that it shall &quot;consider claims from British subjects now and formerly residing or carrying on business in the area of the Irish Free State who, on account of their support of His Majesty&apos;s Government prior to the 11th July, 1921, sustained hardships and loss by personal injuries or by the malicious destruction of or injuries to their property .... or who have otherwise suffered special hardships and loss on account of such support as aforesaid, and to advise His Majesty&apos;s Government in each case, taking into account the degree of hardships suffered by the claimant, whether .... any further ex gratia grant should in reason and fairness be made to the claimant by His Majesty&apos;s Government, and if so what should be the amount of such grant.&quot; These terms clearly exclude the consideration of any claims based solely on loss occasioned by the operation of the Free State Land Act, inasmuch as such loss cannot be regarded as having been suffered &quot;on account of such support as aforesaid,&quot; and I understand that the Committee have in fact rejected any claims of this nature which have come before them.If we are to do anything for the landowners whom Lord Oranmoreand Browne represents (and I am not convinced that there is any obligation upon us, moral or other, to do anything) our assistance can only, in my opinion, take one of two forms. We can either (a) decide to make a grant to each landowner affected by the Act of a certain proportion of his loss (which, in the case of lands subject to judicial rents, is measurable with some approach to accuracy, although difficulties may arise in the case of untenamted lands), or (b) we can. extend the terms of reference of the Irish Grants Committee so as to enable them to make recommendations, adapted to the circumstances of each case, as to the grant, if any, which is to be made to each of the persons affected.As to (a) there seem to me to be the strongest possible objections to the adoption of this course. An announcement that we are going to give a stated proportion of the amount claimed would inevitably carry with it an implicit admission of liability for the whole, and our failure to pay the whole could only be justified on the ground of poverty. I am not prepared to make, or to imply, any such admission, which incidentally would convict the Lord Chancellor and Lord Clarendon of insincerity and evasion in their speeches in the debate of the 3rd February. Furthermore it is undoubted that the landowners have suffered less by the operation of the Land Act, 1923, than have other property owmers by the operation of the Damage to Property (Compensation) Act, 1923. As some alleviation for the loss suffered by the latter class&apos;, as well as for the loss suffered by very many others unaffected by that Act, the Cabinet decided (meeting of the 28th July, 1926, conclusion 8) to assign a sum not exceeding  400,000: and it seems to me that, quite apart from questions of financial stringency, we could not in fairness assign a larger sum to the landowners. To undertake, however, to nay to the landowners, say, 1/15 of their claim would, in addition to the strong objection in principle to which Tkhave already referred, be regarded as merely derisory.   So far from satisfying* Annex II.
Lord Oranmore and Browne and his friends, it would, I feel sure, encourage them to claim, and strengthen their claim for, a far larger concession.As regards the alternative course (&amp;), namely, the extension of the terms of reference of the Irish Grants Committee so as to empower the Committee to recom-mend grants in respect solely of loss occasioned bythe operation of the Land Act, 1923, it is to be observed that under their present terms of reference the Committee, in advising His Majesty&apos;s Government, are to take into account the degree of hardship suffered by the claimant. If, therefore, the Committee were empowered to deal with claims arising under the Land Act, they would presumably recommend grants only in cases in which they were satisfied that the reduction in the claimant&apos;s income attributable to the operation of the Act occasioned actual hardship; and it would further be open to the Government to place a limit (as they have done in respect of the claims already referred to the Committee) on the amount which they are prepared to spend in meeting any such recommendations.The adoption of this course would not be open to the objections to which I have already referred, and, after careful consideration, I recommend it to my colleagues. It would, I think, have to be clearly understood that the Committee, in acting under any such extension of their terms of reference (which would have to be carefully drafted in consultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer), would have to confine themselves to cases in which the claimant was, by reason of the operation of the Act, reduced from a position of comparative comfort to one of poverty. Taking into consideration the fact that in very many cases the Northern Ireland Land Act of 1925, if it had been applied to the Free State, would have given the landowner a larger and certainly a more secure income than he was in fact previously receiving, and that the difference between the income which would have been produced by the Northern Ireland Act, and the income produced by the Free State Act, is on an average 14 per cent., it is clear that the number of cases in which hardship in this sense is occasioned by the Act of 1923 will be small, and the sums involved not very considerable. But if any such cases exist, it is, I think, right that they should be dealt with on the same lines as the claims already referred to the Irish Grants Committee.If this recommendation is approved, it remains to consider what limit should be placed on the amount of money which we are prepared to assign for this purpose. In my opinion, it is unlikely that the recommendations of the Committee, within the restricted limits which I have suggested, will exceed  50,000 in all, and I recommend that that sum should be fixed as the limit beyond which His Majesty&apos;s Government would not be prepared to go in meeting the Committee&apos;s recommendations in respect of this class of case. I understand unofficially that the Committee, on the material at present before them, anticipate that their recommendations under their present terms of reference will be less by an appreciable amount than the  400,000 which the Government is prepared to expend; and it may well be therefore that if the recommendations which I now make are adopted, our total expenditure will still be within  400,000. I recommend, however, that the  400,000 already assigned, and the  50,000 which I now suggest should be assigned, should be kept separate, i.e., that if the recommendations of the Committee under their present terms of reference amount to less than  400,000, the  50,000 available to meet their recommendations under the new terms should not be regarded as being pro tanto increased, and conversely that if the recommendations under the new terms amount to less than  50,000, the  400,000 available to meet recommendations under the old terms should not be increased.To sum up, I recommend (a.) That the terms of reference of the Irish Grants Committee shall be extended (subject to the concurrence of the Chancellor of the Exchequer in the drafting of the new terms) so as to cover hardship and loss occasioned by the operation of the Irish Free State Land Act, 1923.(&amp;.) That the sum to be expended in meeting any recommendations of theCommittee under any such extension shall not exceed  50,000, and thatthis sum of  50,000 shall be kept separate from the sum of  400,000assigned to meet the recommendations of the Committee under theirexisting terms of reference.5 L. S. A.Dominions Office, January 21, 1927.[15667JB 2
ANNEX I.REPORTBY THESELECT COMMITTEEOF THE HOUSE OF LORDSonIrish Land Purchase (Pledges by Ministers of the Crown).Ordered to be Printed, 19th July, 1926.PRINTED &amp; PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE. ,e purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the JoUowJiw ^dresses Adastral House. Kingsway, London. WC1.8; 28 Abmgdon Street, London, S.W.1, York Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew&apos;s Orescent, Cardiff, .... 19(1   na^fcra Ctwiof   Edinburgh:or 120, George Street, Edinburgh; or through any Bookseller.1926Price 2d. net.

and report, on 1st November, 1917.   The Sub-Committee made App. IX. an unanimous report to the Convention.9. On 25th February, 1918, Mr. Lloyd George, then Prime Minister, wrote to Sir Horace Plunkett, Chairman of the Con-vention, and his letter contains the following reference to Land Purchase :-&quot; Finally the Government have noted the very important Report which has been prepared on the subject of Land Purchase and on which an unanimous conclusion has been reached by the Committee of the Convention set up to consider this subject. It this Report commends itself to the Convention, the Government would be prepared to intro-duce in Parliament as part of the plan of settlement (and simultaneously with the Bill amending the Government of Ireland Act, 1914) a measure for the purpose of inviting Parliament to give effect to the recommendations of the Convention on the subject of Land Purchase.&quot;The Convention accepted the Report of the Sub-Committee unanimously.10. The Committee pass on now to declarations they do not for the moment call them &quot; pledges &quot; by Ministers of the Crown.On 29 March, 1920, Mr.  Macpherson, then Secretary for Hansard Ireland, said : &quot; The Government, recognising as it does that it is (3- 0^9 h under au obligation to introduce a Land Purchase Scheme, has p 935  &apos; decided to accept this scheme of the Convention as its basis and will introduce a Bill upon the lines of that scheme immediately.&quot;On 13 May, 1920, Mr. Bonar Law, then Lord Privy Seal, said Hansard that the Government adhered to their determination to complete f^j 0*29^&apos; Land Purchase. p q^O. &apos;On 19 May, 1920, Lord Birkenhead, then Lord Chancellor, Hansard said : &quot; The Government recognising, as I have already said, yjj ^o^&apos; that it is under an obligation to bring before Parliament pro- p- 421.&apos; posals for a land settlement, as nearly concurrently as may be with its Home Rule proposals, has decided to adopt the Con-vention scheme as a basis, and to introduce a Land Purchase Bill for the purpose.&quot;11. On November 11, 1920, a Bill was presented to the House of Commons &quot; to amend the Law relating to the occupation and ownership of Land in Ireland,&quot; but did not proceed further.12. On March 9, 1921, in answer to a question from Lord Hansard Oranmore and Browne, the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lan- y^j^^&apos; caster (the Earl of Crawford) said: &quot;The Government quite p. 452.&apos; appreciates the obligation to which Lord Oranmore and Browne has referred, and it is the intention of the Government to intro-duce the Bill again   .   .   .   substantially on the lines of that which was introduced last year.&quot;
Hansard (H. of Ji.), Vol. 45, p. 1069.p. 1072.Hansard (H. of L.), Vol. 49, p. 414.Oranmore, Qu. 109.Qu. 112.Hansard (H. of L.), Vol. 63, p. 68.Hansard (H. of L.), Vol. 54, p. 1240.Hansard (II. of 0.), Vol. 129, p. 620.Hansard (H. of L.), Vol. 45, p. 1072.13. On July 13, 1921, Lord Birkenhead said : &quot; It is true as everyone knows that the Government was deeply pledged ami is of course deeply pledged on this question. Bat it is also clear that any undertaking of that kind must be construed in relation to the circumstances as they existed then and as they were anticipated by most people at that time.&quot;In the same speech Lord Birkenhead stated that &quot; . . . this is one of the questions which must be dealt with, and dealt with upon the lines which the Government have already indicated.&quot;14. On March 9, 1922, in answer to a question from Lord Oranmore and Browne &quot; whether the Imperial Government repudiate any responsibility for the promises which have been made to this Parliament to settle the Irish Land question in Southern Ireland as well as in Northern Ireland, and which have been stated by several Ministers to be an obligation of honour and a necessary part of a plan of Irish settlement Lord Peel, then Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, said : &quot;I do not understand that the Imperial Parliament denies any of its obligations or any of its undertakings.&quot;15. In March, 1922, as well as on several subsequent occasions, a deputation from the Irish Landowners&apos; Convention waited on several Cabinet Ministers, and while it may not be permissible to allude in any detail to what occurred, it appears &quot; there was no attempt made to suggest that the pledges given would not be fully carried out.&quot;No refutation was made of statements such as that by Lord Carson in the House of Lords on the 3rd February, 1926, when, in referring to the same deputation he said that three Ministers &quot; . . . stated fully and absolutely that the pledges given by the Government regarding land purchase must be carried out, and they affirmed their intention of fulfilling them.&quot;16. On 23rd July, 1923. Lord Birkenhead, no longer a member of the Government, said : &quot; We were pledged to dispose of the question of Land Purchase.&quot;17. The Committee have now given a recital of the various declarations of Ministers in the years 1920 and 1923 on the subject of Irish Land Purchase. It will be noticed that they are very distinct promises to introduce a Land Purchase Bill upon the lines of the Convention indeed, on occasion Ministers went further. As has already been stated in para-graphs 10 and 13, Mr. Bonar Law in 1920 re-affirmed that the Government adhered to their determination to complete Land Purchase, and Lord Birkenhead in 1921 said : &quot; . . . question must be dealt with, and dealt with upon the lines which the Government have already indicated.&quot; When he was no longer in office he alluded to the matter in the manner
referred to in paragraph 16: &quot;We were pledged to dispose of the question of Land Purchase.&quot;18. The Committee are satisfied that pledges were given by Ministers of the Crown necessarily subject to the concurrence of Parliament, that they would complete Irish Land Purchase upon the lines of the Convention Scheme, and they are fortified in this conclusion by the facts : (1) that in 1920 an Irish Land Purchase Bill was intro-duced into the House of Commons, and(2) that in 1925 a Land Purchase Act was passed by Oranrnore. Parliament for Northern Ireland; and that both the Bill and Qu. 113. the Act were drawn substantially on the lines of the pro-posals agreed to by the Convention.19. As has been stated in paragraph 4 above, the Committee have not had the advantage of being helped by any evidence from members of His Majesty&apos;s G-overnment. They have been forced, therefore, to rely on the speeches of Ministers as reported in the Parliamentary Debates for the presentation of arguments per contra.20. The first trace of these is to be found in the speech of Hansard Lord Birkenhead on 13th July, 1921: &quot;But it is also clear ^j0^10&apos; that any undertaking of that kind must be construed in relation     jQgg&apos; to the circumstances as they existed then and as they were anticipated by most people at that time.&quot;   Again &quot; .   .   .   and p. 1070. he (Lord Oranmore and Browne&apos;) would not seek to impale me on the dilemma of logic or morality in order to show that as circumstances have so vitally changed, any Government could, as a matter of honourable obligation, be held either to the letter or the spirit of what was said in circumstances so different.&quot;21. The ambit of this inquiry is strictly limited by the terms of reference. It is to examine the pledges given by Ministers and to report whether these pledges have been fulfilled.The Committee have now examined those pledges in the light of the evidence available to them, and, in the absence of evidence from the Government which might explain the circumstances in which they were made, they can only construe the statements above set out in their plain and literal meaning.22. Again, the following contention has been put forward Hansardby Lord Birkenhead when out of office in 1923, but adopted (H. of L.)by Lord Clarendon, who spoke for the Government in 1926 :  Vol. 63,p. 58.&quot;,But the Bill of 1920, which the noble Earl appears to Hansardthink possesses some verbal sanctity, was a Bill which (H. of L.),depended upon the hypothesis that agreement was reached Vo]2fo&apos;by the Convention.   No such agreement ever was reached. p&apos; It depended in the second place and was stated to depend in the second place upon the agreement of the landlord and the tenant.    And no one can claim that anybody was verbally
Hans ird (H. of L. Vol. 40, p. 421.Midleton, Qu. 104.Hansard (H. of L.), Vol. 63 p. 86.- bound until the conditions precedent, soon to prove them-selves impossible of verbal repetition or attainment, were satisfied, the first condition being that there was agreement at the Convention, the second condition being that there was agreement between landlord and tenant.&quot;23. The Committee find it difficult to understand this presenta-tion of the facts. In so far as the land purchase question was concerned, agreement was reached by the Convention as shown in paragraph 9 of this Report; indeed, Lord Birkenhead himself, in an earlier speech on 17th May, 1920, alluded to the preparation of the Irish Land Purchase Scheme as the most noteworthy practical achievement of the Convention, and that it was a tribute to the efforts of the Sub-Committee that their report was accepted by the Convention unanimously.As far as the second point is concerned, Lord. Midleton said, &quot; With regard to agreement between landlord and tenant there is no question Lord Oranmore and Browne, who was on the Committee, will correct me if I am wrong that the Bill of the Convention was to be a compulsory one, and therefore it is not a question of agreement &quot;Finally, the Committee fail to understand how a Bill which was introduced in the autumn of 1920 could &quot; depend upon the hypothesis that agreement was reached by the Con-vention &quot; which had in fact come to an end in 1918. The fact that the Bill was introduced by the Government clearly shows that they were satisfied on these two points, and that the condi-tions mentioned had been fulfilled.24. Lastly, it was urged by Lord Cave, the Lord Chancellor, on 3rd February, 1926, in the debate which resulted in the Committee being appointed, as follows : &apos;&apos; Surely no one says that the bringing in of a Bill consti-tutes a pledge or that if a Bill is introduced and not carried the public fund must make good to those, who would have benefited by the Bill, all that has been lost by its rejection. No one contends that the Bill of 1920 was anything in the nature of a pledge, otherwise the difficulty of proposing measures to Parliament would be greater than it is.&quot;25. The Committee have shown in the preceding pages of the Report the declarations of Ministers of the Crown, which are described, and therefore presumably defined, by Ministers themselves as pledges, and they have felt bound to accept the Ministerial definition.They have alluded, in paragraph 18, to the Bill of 1920 not as a pledge, but as evidence of the nature of the pledge.It is not their function to say &quot; that the public funds must make good, etc.&quot; It is their duty &quot; to examine the pledges given between 1920 and 1923 by Ministers of the Crown in regard to the completion of Land Purchase,&quot; which they have now
done,  &quot; and to report whether these pledges have been ful-filled,&quot; a duty which they will now proceed to discharge.26. Fortunately the task of the Committee has been greatly simplified in this matter by the evidence given by the repre-sentatiyes of the Irish Landowners&apos; Convention.Broadly speaking, it may be said that the representatives accept the provisions of the Bill of 1920 and of the Northern Oranmore, Ireland Land Act, 1925, as fulfilling the pledges of Ministers of Q&quot; m the Crown ; and they point to the omission of the bonus provision in the Irish Free State Act, 1923, as the main respect in which that Act has failed to fulfil the pledges of Ministers, though they also indicate other respects in which the Irish Free State Act is less favourable.   (Vide Table of Figures, p. 12, Evidence.)It is clear that the witnesses relied, as the chief ground of their complaint, on the absence of the bonus in the provisions of the Free State Act.27. The Committee have noted that in the debate of February (jj af3rd, 1926, in the House of Lords, Ministers pleaded, in respect Vol.63,of this matter of fulfilment, in part that the pledges had been P- 55-fulfilled; that a result was obtained by the Act of 1923 closely p. 59. comparable to the proposals which were contained in the 1920Bill; that His Majesty&apos;s Government did not regard this Act p- 60.as a wholly unsatisfactory fulfilment o^ the pledge given by their p. 61.predecessors in 1921; and that in the matter of arrears but for p. 88. the provisions in the Act of 1923 the landowners, if the Bill of 1920 had been passed, would have recovered only a very smallportion of the arrears which were due to them.   Further, that the p. 88. present Government did for the first time promise and give a British guarantee for the stock to be issued.28. The Committee have gathered together the observations of the Government on the charge of non-fulfilment of the pledges given in respect of Land Purchase, and they have duly weighed them in view of the respect which should attach to utterances of the Government, but they are unable to accept the matter recited as fulfilment of the pledges categorically given.29. A pledge was given to complete Irish Land Purchase upon the lines of the Convention scheme. So far as Northern Ireland is concerned the witnesses who appeared before this Committee were satisfied that the pledge was fulfilled when the Government introduced and passed through Parliament the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925.So far as the Free State is concerned the witnesses contended that the pledge has been unfulfilled to the extent that the provisions of the Irish Free State Act, 1923, depart from those in the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925, which is generally accepted as fulfilling the pledge.
Hansard (H. of L.) Vol.63,    &apos; P. 89.MidJeton(v20) ^   ^&quot;-406 760 h.s, 0,7!30. The question was raised in the course of this inquiry as to how far the bonus contemplated under the Convention scheme constituted a liability on the Bi-itish Exchequer, for it is to be observed that Lord Cave said, on 3rd February, 1926, &quot; I do not think that anywhere in the whole of history can you find a promise to put a charge of  6,000,000, or indeed, any charge at all upon British funds.&quot;31. To ascertain the exact position it is necessary to look back to the Convention which forms the basis of all the pledges given. At page 102 of the Report the following passage appears : &quot; The bonus was always regarded as &apos; a free gift to Ireland,&apos; that is. it was to be paid, not by. the taxpayers of Great Britain or of Ireland, but of the United Kingdom as a whole.&quot; ueton, Lord Midleton puts the matter clearly in his evidence &quot; thatQu. 10-2.       aj.  ]le jjjjjg wben the bonus under the Wyndham Act was being paid, the revenues of Ireland did not suffice for her expenditure, and therefore, in point of fact, tho whole of the bonus was paid by the population of England, Scotland and Wales.   It would only be a repetition of the same.&quot;32. If this be so, it would appear that the bonus contemplated in the Convention scheme did anticipate a. liability on the funds of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and formed part of the pledge given by^Ministers of the Crown.33. To sum up : The Committee have examined the declara-tions made by Ministers of the Crown in regard to the com-pletion of Irish Land Purchase and they accept the Ministerial definition of those declarations as pledges.The nature of the pledges given may be found crystallized in statutory form in the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925.In so far as Northern Ireland is concerned, the pledges have been substantially&apos; fulfilled by the passing into law of that Act.In.so far as the Free State is concerned, the pledges have not been fulfilled, to the extent that the provisions of the Free State Land Act differ from and fall short of the provisions of the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925.
ANNEX II.Note on the Report of the Select Committee of the House of Lords on Irish Land Purchase (Pledges of Ministers of &quot;the Crown).Paras. 1-8.No observations.Para. 9.In connection with what follows it is important to observe that Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s undertaking was to the effect that the Government would introduce a Bill to give effect to the Convention scheme &quot; as part of the plan of settlement and simultaneously with the Bill amending the Government of Ireland Act, 1914.&quot; Similarly, on the 13th July, 1921, Lord Birkenhead said (see paragraph 13 of the Report) that it was clear &quot; that any undertaking of that kind must be construed in relation to the circumstances as they existed then and as they were anticipated by most people at that time &quot; i.e., the Bill of 1920 (which embodied the Convention scheme) was part of and was dependent upon the scheme for the government of Ireland embodied in the Government of Ireland Act 1920, a scheme which never came into operation, so far as the Irish Free State was concerned, and which was finally killed by the Articles of Agreement of the 6th December, 1921. There was never any pledge that land purchase would be completed on the lines suggested by the Convention and embodied in the Bill of 1920 irrespective of whatever other arrangements might be made for the future government of Ireland.Paras. 10-12.No observations.Para. 13.See on paragraph 9 above.Paras. 14-17.No observations. %Para. 18.As regards the statement that &quot; the Committee are satisfied that pledges were given by Ministers of the Crown .... that they would complete Irish Land Purchase upon the lines of the Convention Scheme,&quot; see on paragraph 9 above.Paras. 19-21.No observations.Paras. 22-23.Lord Birkenhead made two statements both of which are traversed by the Committee: (a.) Lord Birkenhead said (paragraph 22 of Report) that &quot; the Bill of 1920 .... depended upon the hypothesis that agreement was reached by the Convention. No such agreement ever was reached.&quot; The Committee say that agreement was reached by the Convention.It is quite true that agreement was reached by the Convention on the question of land purchase; but it must be perfectly obvious to anyone reading Lord Birkenhead&apos;s speech that he was referring not to agree-ment upon one (and a comparatively minor one) of the many subjects dealt with by the Convention, but to agreement upon the whole question of the government of Ireland. On that question agreement was not reached by the Convention.(&amp;.) Lord Birkenhead said (paragraph 22 of Report) that the Bill &quot; depended in the second place and was stated to depend in the second place upon the agreement of the landlord and the tenant&apos;&apos;; and to this the Committee reply that the Bill of the Convention was to be a compulsory one and therefore there was no question of agreement. Here again it must be perfectly obvious to anyone reading Lord Birkenhead&apos;s speech
that he was not referring to agreement between each individual landlord and each individual tenant but to a general agreement between the landlords as a whole and the tenants as a whole. The Bill of T920 was a compulsory Bill; but it was based, and was known to be based, on such a general agreement, but for which it would never have been introduced. The Northern Ireland Bill (now the Act of 1925) which is also com-pulsory was based on a similar agreement; and it is relevant to note that such general agreement was secured in 1925 by means of a further concession to the tenant made at the expense partly of the landowners and partly of the Northern Irish taxpayer. But after 1920 no such agreement existed or could have been reached in the area which is now the Irish Free State.The Committee add that they fail to understand how a Bill which was introduced in 1920 could &quot; depend upon the hypothesis that agreement was reached by the Convention, which had, in fact, come to an end in 1918.&quot; It is submitted that what Lord Birkenhead meant is abundantly clear. The Convention was established for the purpose of endeavouring to secure an agreed scheme for the government of Ireland. It failed to agree upon any scheme, but it did reach agreement upon one fragment of such a scheme, namely, land purchase. Thereupon the British Government devised its own scheme for the government of Ireland - namely, the scheme embodied in the Government of Ireland Act, 1920 -and as part of that scheme it adopted the land purchase arrangements upon which the Convention had agreed, and embodied them in the Bill of 1920. Had the Government of Ireland Act ever come into operation in the area which is now the Irish Free State, there can be no doubt that the Land Purchase Bill would eventually have been passed and also brought into operation. But when the scheme embodied in the Government of Ireland Act broke down, any hope of bringing into operation the fragment of that scheme embodied in the Land Purchase Bill broke down also.Paras. 24 and 25. -   No observations.Para. 26.It is not the case that the Free State Act of 1923 contains no bonus provision. On the contrary, Section 25 of the Act provides that &quot; the price of each holding shall be a capital sum, hereinafter called c the standard price &apos; . . . . together with a contribution by the State to the price calculated at 10 per cent, on, and added to, the standard price.&quot; Possibly the fact that this is called a contribution by the State instead of a bonus (as in the Northern Ireland Act) has misled the Committee.In addition the Act (Section 5) establishes a Costs Fund, payable by the State, amounting to 2 per cent, on the total purchase money, for the purpose of recouping vendors in whole or in part for the costs of sale.Paras. 27 and 28. No observations.Para. 29.As regards the statement that a pledge was given to complete Irish Land Purchase upon the lines of the Convention Scheme, see on paragraph 9 above.As regards the statement that &quot;so far as Northern Ireland is concerned . . . . the pledge was fulfilled when the Government introduced and passed through Parliament the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925,&quot; it is to be observed that in the case of Northern Ireland the two conditions laid down by Lord Birkenhead (see on paragraph 23 above) were fulfilled. The Government of Ireland Act, 1920, did come into operation, and is to-day in operation in Northern Ireland, and there was in 1925, and is to-day, agreement between the landlords as a whole and the tenants as a whole on the terms of the Bill.Paras. 30-32.In the Debate of the 3rd February, 1926, Lord Clarendon said &quot;The Bill of 1920, had it been carried through as part of an agreed Irish settlement, would not have involved the payment of one single penny of English money.&quot;    The
Lord Chancellor, in the same Debate, said &quot; It was never intended to put the charge upon British funds. That was not the proposal of 1920 &quot;; and again (as quoted by the Committee) &quot; I do not think that anywhere in the whole of history can you find a promise to put a charge of  6,000,000, or indeed anv charge at all upon Britishfunds.&quot;These are very precise statements by Ministers of the Crown on a point of first-rate importance.   They are, however, denied by the Committee.The facts are perfectly clear. The Government of Ireland Bill was introduced into Parliament on the 25th February, 1920. The Bill provided (see Sections 23 and 24 of the Act) that the greater portion of the Irish taxes (including income-tax and super-tax and customs and excise duties) should continue to be collected by the British Government, and that the proceeds thereof should be paid over to the Irish exchequers after deducting the cost of reserved services. Land purchase is a reserved service (see Section 9 (3) of the Act). The Irish Land Bill of 1920 was introduced into Parliament on the 11th November, 1920, by which time the Government of Ireland Bill had passed through the Report stage and was awaiting Third Reading. It was beyond doubt therefore from the very first that the whole cost of the scheme of land purchase embodied in that Bill would fall exclusively upon the Irish Exchequer. Similarly, the whole cost of land purchase in Northern Ireland under the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925, falls on the Northern Irish Exchequer.It is specifically stated in the Report (paragraph 26) that the representatives of the landowners &quot;accept the provisions of the Bill of 1920 and of the Northern Ireland Land Act, 1925, as fulfilling the pledges of Ministers of the Crown &quot;; and it says little for the sense of responsibility of the Committee that they should on so important a point have failed to make themselves acquainted with those provisions.O

</content>
</cab>
