<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/184/0 images: 280-306</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:-HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.f SECRET. COPY NO .JO.P. 27  (27)CABINET.&apos;30TRADE RELATIONS V/ITH RUSSIA.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.I attach a detailed note on our trade with Russia.   From this it appears that Russia sells more than she buys in this country, and that our re-exports to Russia largely exceed our exports to Russia of United Kingdom goods.   A large proportion of our exports of manufactures are being paid for by instalments, some of these transactions involving as much as 2 years credit.If there is a breach of relations the Russian Government (a,) would probably stop purchasing in this country, and (b) might default on Instalment payments for work already in hand in this country for Russia, though this would have a re-aotion on the credit of the Russian Government which they appear to be very anxious to build up and maintain.Nothing could be done to prevent the Russians from ceasing to buy here, and we should therefore lose a certainIamount of trade.    The only weapon we could turn against the Russian Government if they default in payments on their contracts would be to prohibit the Importation of Russian goods.       The United Kingdom is far the best market there is at the present time for Russian produce and they might be deprived of this market.    But we should injure our own trade very seriously by such an embargo.    Imports from Russia consist   almost entirely of food and raw materials.    Some, e.g. Bristles (one kind) and Platinum are essential, as Russia Is the sole source of supply.    The prohibition of others might raise prices and cause an outcry.    A cumbrous
licensing system would have to be set up for special cases and for existing contracts.    Moreover, we should have to institute a system of certificates of origin for similar imports from neighbouring countries.    This would be an impediment to trade with those countries.The only article we could prohibit with comparative ease would be oil.Prohibition would of course require legislation.    In view of all the difficulties I think the weapon of embargo must be ruled out.(Intld.) P.O.-L.Board of Trade,88th January, 1927.
The first Table in Appendix B showB, from the United Kingdom Trade Returns, the total value of the trade between the UnitedKingdom on the one hand and Russia and the Sucoession States on the*other hand in the years 1912, 1913 and 1921-1926.     Table II in   the same Appendix shows from 1923 the principal goods and groups Of goods v:htch:-fora the bulk of. this trade.It will be seen that exports to the Soviet Union of goods of United Kingdom origin or manufacture have been as follows:-1921.. 1922.. 1923.. 1924.. 1925.. 1926. .. .  2,181,007 . .  3,640,624 ..  2,491.650 ..  3,860,385 ..  6,239,717..  5,861,000 (provisional)Total.. 24,275,000In 1913 exports to Russia of goods of United Kingdom origin and manufacture amounted to  18,103,000.(Note:    In comparing the volume of trade done during the pre-war period with that of the post-revolutionary period, it must be remem-bered that pre-war statistics of trade with Russia related to trade with an area which, in addition to the territory we now oall the Soviet Union, included a number of countries which are now Indepen-dent, viz., Finland, Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania and part of Poland. Also it must be remembered that the level of prices is now sub-stantially higher.)Re-exports from the United Kingdom to Russia of goods of foreign or colonial origin during the same period were:-1921  .....	.  1,210,2831922  .....	.      970,4031923  .....	.  1,989,4761924  .....	.  7,212,1441935  .....	. 13,017,2121926  .....	.  8,566,000 (provisional)Total re-exports	 32,965,000The corresponding figure   for the year 1913 was  9.591,000. Imports Into the United Kingdom of goods from the Soviet Union were1921 . 1922 . 1923 . 1924 . 1925 . 1926 . Total  2,694,674 ..   8,102,829 ..   9,266,100 ..  19,773,842 ..  25,322,033..  23,950,000 (provisional)  89,110,000The corresponding figure in 1913 was  40,S71j000*
*3-1Some outstanding features of our imports from Russia are indicated by the figures belowImports into the United Kingdom from Russia in 1925.1 Commodity.          i	(A) Imports from Russia.	IB) Total Imports.	(A) % of (B) . .    .	 	 		8,535,670	570,105,184	1.5Raw Materials .........	&apos; 11,894,999	424,783,148	2.8Manufactured Article s(i)i u	4,891,364	319 , 631,089	&apos;    1.5Detail of above (Principal Commodities)Foodstuffs.--Butter........Eggs (in shell) S almon, c anne d Barley ........Raw Materials.Manganese Ore ... Bristles (il)  ... Timber     (iii) Flax and Flax Tow Sunflower seedLinseed.........Oil-seed cake ... Fursklns, undressedManufactured Articles.Platinum.......... .Petroleum, refined, including Petrol .Petrol, included in above............2,448,095 1,277,555 1,304,385 1,490,46353,204,417 4.616,584,898 I 7.73,892,833 j .33.58,532,885 i 17.5244,419 771,2555,755,759 483,314 539,975 522,488 533, 6232,644,8461,231,043 1,737,655 46,496,039 4,173,395 559,634 7,268,461 4,428,623 9,100,79319.9 44.4 12.4 11.6 96.5 7.2 12.0 29.11,688,625 2,302,716 l;249,4341,951,233 j 86.5 30,647,921 I 7.5 16,826,010   :      7.notes: -(i) (ii)Includes platinum and refined Petroleum.About half from Russia - the rest comes mainly from China, but Is probably a different description of bristles.The timber coming from Russia consists mainly of soft wood.    Our total imports of soft woods are approximately to the value of  26,200,000 of which some  4,900,000 worth is from Russia.
91^t-j JL oIt will be apparent from a perusal of the first figures given abcve that exports of goods of United Kingdom produce, and manufacture do not exhibit any steady increase, but fluctuate in value during the period under review from about 2 millions sterling in 1921 to about 6 millions sterling in 1925 and 1926, and that even if we take into consideration the discrepancy between the area represented by the old Russian Empire and present-day Soviet Russia, the present export trade in United Kingdom goods still falls considerably short of the pre-war trade.In 1926 our exports of goods of United Kingdom produce or manufacture represented 0.90f of our total exports, and our re-exports to Russia represented 6 .S2f. of our total re-exports.The figures relating to re-exports reveal that re-exports (consisting principally of raw cotton, rubber, tea and hides) of goods of foreign and colonial origin showed a remarkable increase up to the end of 1925 though the 1926 figure is almost back to the 1924 level.   Taking Into consideration the increase in values which has occurred since the pre-war period and the change in territory, re-exports to Russia during 1925 compare very well with those of the pre-war period, but the 1926 figures are substantially below the level of pre-war years.The figures of imports show a rapid increase of Russian imports into the United Kingdom up to 1925 followed by a slight set-back in 1926, and reveal the extent to which the Russians have taken advantage of facilities afforded them for the sale of Russian goods on the British market . The figures naturally fall short of those of the pre-war period because the Succession Statos are excluded, but the extent of the fall
compared with the pre-war period is very much less than in the case of British exports     The total balance of Russian imports over United Kingdom exports and re-exports during t,he whole period shows an excess of imports into the United Kingdom as f ollows :-1921-26. 1924-26.   viz. Imports into UnitedKingdom from Russia....     89,110,000 69,046,000Exports and Re-exports from U.K. to Russia....     57,240,000 44.756,000Balance  ...    51,870,000 24,290,000It should be borne in mind that these values represent for imports c.i.f. values and for exports f.o.b. values and that the cost of freight and insurance on all the goods passing between Russia and the United Kingdom may probably amount to or even exceed half the balance shown.The following official Soviet Statistics of purchasesand sales in the United Kingdom by Soviet trading organshave been put forward:-U.S.S.R. sales U .S .S .R. purchaseson British market. on British market.    1921....... 1,866,375 7,281,2581922....... 5,933,283 9,432,9361923 ........      10,458,066 4,658,5921924........      19,443,669 14,800,9561925........      26,907,678 51.170,995 64,609,071  67,344,737No 1926 figures have yet been Issued.It will be noticed that whereas the Russian figures of sales in the United Kingdom approximate fairly closely to the British Customs statistics of Imports into the
United Kingdom from Russia, the Russian figures of Soviet purchases are greatly in excess of those furnished by the British Customs relative to exports to the Soviet Union.Several explanations have been given for this, the principal one being that given by the Russian themselves namely, that considerable quantities of foreign and colonial goods  (flour, rubber, tea, wool) although purchased in London are shipped direct from the country of origin (Canada, India, Australia) and do not therefore appear in the Board of Trade returns of re-exports from the United Kingdom.   It Is also probable that Insurance, freight and other expenses are included in the purchase price, and as stated earlier these items would probably amount to some-thing of the order of  15,000,000 during the six years. Purchases also are probably included of goods such as machinery, the delivery of which is to be spread over several years.Table III in Appendix B shoes, according to the Russian Trade Returns, the distribution by countries of Russia^ trade in 1913, In the years October 1923 to September    1924, and October   1924, to September   19 25, and in the six months ended March, 1926,These figures show clearly that the biggest customer of the Soviet Union is easily Great Britain with Germany second.   The principal sellers to Russia are Germany,Great Britain and the United States of America in the order r. named,  according to the latest figures  available.   Germany appears to be outstripping her rivals and the United States of America to have been displaced from the predominant position occupied by her in 1925 .An important fact which arises from an examination of these returns is the amount of trade done by the Russians with the British Empire.
Empire. Thus imports from:-Australia during the year ending 50th September/1925, wore 29.37 -million roubles or nearly 3 millions sterling.   Most of this was wool,Canada during the same periods amounted to 2.39 million roubles or about  200,000,India amounted to 8 million roubles or about  800,000, of which tea accounted for 5.2 million roubles.It will thus be seen that there is a considerable amount of Empire trade with the Soviet Union. There appears to have been a tendency lately in the Russian returns to attribute imports of certain commodities to oountries of origin rather than countries of consignment.   For example some of the Indian tea asoribed to India was probably imported from the United Kingdom.The Russian export plan for the last eaonomic year (ending September 30th, 1926) was not realised and the generous over-issue of import licences for Russian purchases abroad during the early part of the year resulted in there being another although smaller adverse balance of trade (88 million roubles).    The previous year&apos;s adverse balance was 150 million roubles).The maintenance of a favourable trade balance is considered by the Soviet authorities to be a matter of vital importanoe and the severe import licensing restrictions Imposed by the State Monopoly of trade operate largely to that end.In the absence of a large reserve of foreign currenoytherefore it would seem likely that no purchase of foreigngoods by Russia can be expected on any large scale untilexports are developed sufficiently to permit of there being no possibility of an adverse balance. Foreign trade is ofcourse a state monopoly and its volume is fixed by the Stateaocording to plan import licences being allowed over a givenperiod only in accordance with the quotas fixed.-8-
On the other hand Soviet industry is operating very close to capacity and cannot develop further without fresh plant.    Partial replacements take place from time to time but although there is little hope for many years of the financial recovery necessary for purchases to be made on the scale demanded by the present situation,  limited     ; purohasos are bound to continue.     Accumulation of money and individual tastes are growing and the demand for manufactured goods for personal consumption is greatly in excess of the home production. Taking into consideration, however, the great importance (a) of ruthlessly reducing imports of unnecessary goods to prevent another adverse trade balance,   (b) of developing the industry of the country, there will be a tendency in favour of importing technical good3 rather than those required for personal consumption, the idea being to produce sufficient manufactured goods to satisfy the internal demand and obtain a surplus of export of agricultural produce which the peasant is reluctant to part.with otherwise.No estimate of the amount of Russian purchases which are likely to be made abroad in the forthcoming year can however be given, but in view of the position as described above, those are hardly likely to bo in excess of those mado in the preceding year.There is no doubt that, apart from the credit risk Involved, British exports to the Soviet Union, although only a fraction of pre-war exports, are a source of considerable profit to certain British manufacturers at present.  Credit normally plays a very large part in contracts placed in this country and few orders can be obtained by British firms unless they are prepared to grant a large amount of credit.The growth of confidence of British firms in Soviet purchasing organs is shown by tho fact that whereas for a long time after its establishment In 1921, Arcos Limited was unable to purchase except on oash terms, 22)* (according to-&apos;&quot;-vWTOW^ltra       ^ ......... .......... ^      - .    ....... -r?,7^
91 0the Russians) of orders placed in the United Kingdom by arcos in 1924-25 were on credit terms and during the three quarters of 1925-26, 74fe were placed on a credit basis.It is also claimed that whoroas in 192-3-25 cash advances on orders placed equalled Ufa of their value, advances on orders placed were reduced to 5$ in 1925-26, and that at present orders are placed without any cash advance.No case is known of any Soviet trading organ repudiating a contraot   or failing to meet a bill when due and British firms with whom the Department has come in contaot who have accepted contracts on credit terms have expressed themselves as satisfied at the readiness of the Soviet organisations to meet their acceptances.So far as the official attitude of Great Britain towards the Soviet Union is conoerned, there are two factors which affect trade between the two countries, one of which is largely dependent on the other. These are (a) the obscurity of the present political relations and (b) the absence of oredit facilities from British official or private banking sources. As regards (a) the impression which the Department of Overseas Trade has formed from the enquiries received from British firms during periods of political tension between the two countries in the past few years is that considerable nervousness and uncertainty has resulted from the obscure political situation, or from speeches and press reports. Several definite orders have probably been either refused outright or negotiations have been so protracted, pending an improvement in the situation, that they have been placed in other countries.Pear that a breach of relations between the t-ro countries is not impossible has done much to oreatc  a feeling of insecurity amongst British firms contemplating acceptance of an order for Russia, especially as fairly long oredit is usually involved.
It is thus obvious that such a breach might come at a very inopportune moment for a firnmdio had shipped goods to Russia an   had accepted bills which were not due till a later date.As regards  (b) the absence of Government Credit Facilities (Export Credit Facilities and Trade Facilities Act) has formed the burden of complaint of several groups of manufacturers since the resumption of trade with Russia in 1921.For instance only last month the Department of Overseas Trade was approached by a firm of manufacturers of rolling mill plants who were likely to participate in an order from Russia, with a request for assistance to enable them to compete with the very favourable credit terms which the Germans were able to offer under the recent 300 million mark credit recently voted by the Reichstag.The attitude of the banks in the United Kingdom has also been consistent throughout and large credits except for short periods and then on good security have not been advanced to British firms for the purpose of carrying out Russian contracts.Certain firms or groups of firms have managed to finance large orders without recourso to the banks, as for instance&quot;&apos; the order placed in 1925 with British manufacturers of textile machinery for plant to the value of over one million sterling (this order has now probably increased to over two millions).Generally speaking therefore trade operations of any magnitude have at present to be financed by firms from their own resources, the acceptances being carried by them till their maturity.    In this connection it should be mentioned that the insuring or discounting of bills i3 a matter of great difficulty and where there is no recourse to tho exporter, the rates charged are as high as 20 or even 25j  per annum.      This practice is not, however, by any means
general.      There is not much credit insurance done on Russian account, and the few concerns which undertake the business are only able to carry a limited amount on their-books.Many British traders appear to bo keenly interested in Russian trade and the prospects of doing business.   As an instance of this, the Department of Overseas Trade recently accorded a wide- distribution to information relative to certain forthcoming changes in the Russian purchasing system which had been reported by the British Mission In Moscow. Over two hundred replies were received from British manufacturers of varied classes of goods, all expressing great interest in the information imparted to them and in the subject of Russian trade generally.There are of course instances where firms steadfastly refuse to consider the question of trade with   Russia at all, but these are the exception and are mostly confined to those firms vdio formerly did business with Russia and having had their property or goods confiscated are naturally antagonistic to the present regime or its trading organs.To sum up, the attitude of the British manufacturer or exporter appears to be one of business before sentiment or even matters of principle.Notable exceptions are of course bodies such as the London Chamber of Commerce and the Association of British Creditors of Russia who have complained bitterly of the facilities enjoyed by the Russians for the sale of confiscated goods in the United Kingdom (e.g. oil, timber), and have frequently urged, the   Foreign Office to break off relations.
A study of the statistics in Table III in Appendix B will show that German expordvs to Russia during 1926 were increasing much more rapidly than British exports.    The United States of America on the other hand fell from her position of principal exporter to the Soviet Union to third place.The progress made by Germany is no doubt largely due to the introduction early last year of a special export Credits Scheme for Russia, under which the German Reich and German States undertook to guarantee between them 60 per cent, of the risk incurred by German firms exporting goods to the Soviet Union.    The total amount of the credit involved was 300 million marics of which about one half had been utilised up to the end of 1926.This advantage has probably enabled Germany to secure orders which might otherwise have passed to this country. There is no doubt that, in view of these facilities, there has of late been a marked tendency on the part of the Soviet Government towards increased purchases in Germany, principally for financial reasons.   Political motives also play a large part in the destination of Soviet contracts,   as for instance the temporary cessation of the activities of all Russian purchasing organisations in Germany in 1924 when feeling between the two Governments became tense over the question of the extra-territoriallty of the Soviet Delegation In Berlin.The trade boycott of Switzerland owing to the murder of Vorovsky also provides a striking instance of the powerful economic weapon which the monopoly of foreign trade has placed in the hands of the Soviet Government, and the extent to which that Government will use It if inspired by political motives.
9 9 9&amp;j fjWhatever therefore the immediate effect of the denunciation of the Trade Agreement., the Soviet Government would he almost certain to  retaliate with some similar action as reg;ard3 their purchasing activities in this country even if this was against their own economic interests.Germany would probably stand to benefit most from this situation, especially in view of her encouraging attitude on the matter of credits.With regard to British interests or commitments which might be prejudiced through any breach of relations between the two countries, there are first, the outstanding contracts placed with British firms by Soviet purchasing organisations to be taken into account.The Russian Government might regard a diplomatic rupture as an excuse for repudiating such contracts and imagine that in the circumstances this default would be without prejudice to the reputation as prompt payers which Soviet purchasing organisations have managed gradually to acquire in this country.      It must be remembered that as most of these contracts are placed on credit, theirirepudiation would be to the detriment of the British manufac-iturer and to the corresponding advantage of the SovietIGovernment.    The Trade Agreement does indeed provide for1time to wind up existing contracts but contains no under-1taking by the Soviet Government to fulfil obligations contracted.IUnfortunately it is impossible to give a detailed list of these contracts,  of which there must be a considerable and gradually increasing number, or even to state with certainty the actual amount involved In any particular con-        1 tract.   British firms rarely trouble the Department of Overseas    1 Trade unless in difficulty and could not reasonably be expected to reveal the intimate details of orders received from Sovietsources unless specially requested to do so.-14-
The following^contracts may &quot;be taken as being among the most Important:-(i) A large pr&amp;er for textile machinery was placed at the end of 1925 with Lancashire manufacturers. The amount originally involved was in the neighbourhood of one million sterling, but it is believed that this amount has since been considerably Increased. Twenty-four months1 credit was involved and although the original contract is in process of running out further options have been taken up by the firms concerned- &apos;&quot;(ii) Contracts covering the delivery of about 4,000 tons of rubber over a long period have been concluded.    Prices were, it is stated, fixed when they were at the top of the market and It is claimed that repudiation of the bargain by the Russians would deprive Mincing Lane brokers of a large anticipated profit.(iii) British electrical firms such as Metropolitan Vickers and the British Thomson Houston are known to be in the act of fulfilling contracts in connection with the erection of electrical power stations at Sterovka (in the Donetz Region), Nizni-Novgorod, Volkhov and elsewhere.    It is believed that long credit Is involved.    These firms send out a few skilled engineers and foremen to supervise the erection of the plant.(iv) Messrs. Vickers have been recently engaged on the manufacture of oil-cracking plant for refining purposes.(v) Messrs. Babcock and Vvileox appear to be doinga more or less continuous business in boiler plant with the Loviet Union.    It is believed that they hold certain stocks in Russia..
The second type of contract which would be affected is that involving the purchase by British firms of Russian produce &quot;(timber, flax, platinum, dairy produce).    Soviet organs concerned usually stipulate for and obtain considerable advances prior to the shipment of the goods from Russia.   Hence the British firm would be in a somewhat unenviable position, if the Soviet organisations were able to plead &quot;force majeure1 as an excuse for non-delivery of goods against which advances had already been made. The following are typical of this class of contracts:-(l) Union Cold Storage Company who finance shipments of   dairy produce from the Soviet Union;(ii) Co-operative Wholesale Society and others who finance grain exports to the United Kingdom;(iii) Johnson Matthey and Company who have a contract for the supply of platinum to the value of  800,000 over a 6 months period.    This is a renewable agree-ment and its financing would probably involve partial advances from the British firm.    It is estimated that nearly 90/o of the world supply comes from the Urals; the only other sources of supply are Colombia and South Africa.    It is, however, probable in the event of a breach that Russia will continue to export this valuable commodity to other countries from whence we can Import it(iv) Messrs. Churchill &amp; Son, who finance considerable shipments of timber from the White Sea,The third class of  contract in which British interests are Involved covers industrial and other concessions secured by   British firms in the Soviet Union.    There are only four concessions of importance, all of which are mining concessions.
(i) Lena Goldfields concession.    This is an important goldmining concession in which large capital is involved. Although it is doubtful to what extent British capital participates, the Company is registered as a British concern and the concession is usually termed a British one;  (Recent press reports state that this concern is meeting with labour difficulties).(il) Harriman ^anaganese Concession in the Caucasus. This is undoubtedly an American concession, the capital being $20,000,000, of which it is stated that British interests participate to the extent of about 12f .    The concessionaires are however endeavouring to obtain a revision of the terms of the concession which have proved too onerous.(iii) The Ayan Corporations concession for gold mining in Eastern Siberia.    This appears to be on the point of cancellation-tion if the British firm can persuade the Soviet Government to agree, no gold having been discovered by them.(iv) Tetiukhe Mining Corporation.    This is a recent concession for prospecting and mining metals but the concessionaires do not appear as yet to have become very deeply involved.In this group might be included Consignment stock&apos; agreements concluded between British firms and Soviet organisations.    In this connection the Russian press reports that the Commissariat for Trade has confirmed an agreement concluded between a Russian Trust and Messrs. Van Moppes &amp; Sons, the well-known, dealers in industrial diamonds, whereby the latter undertake to keep in Moscow on consignment a stock of diamonds valued at 300,000 roubles  ( 30,000).
Supposing that His Majesty&apos;s Government terminate the Anglo-Russian Trade Agreement immediately instead of giving the six months notice provided for in Article XIII (which it can do if the situation demands) a reasonable period must be allowed for winding up any transactions entered into. The effect of the withdrawal of the Soviet Charge d&apos;Affaires and his staff at Chesham House would not however necessarily terminate the trading activities of commercial concerns such as Arcos Limited, Centrosoyuz etc.    These are British companies, with Russian capital, it is true, but, nevertheless, companies which under our somewhat elastic Company Law enjoy the same privileges as any other British concern.In the United States of America, Soviet American trade relations appear to be in no way affected by the absence of official recognition or of a trade delegation in America. All v business is done through commercial bodies analogous to Arcos and Centrosoyuz in this country.It has already been remarked, however, that political motives are an important factor in influencing the direction of Soviet contracts placed abroad and a commercial boycott of British goods would probably be the Soviet Government&apos;s retort to any political gesture of His Majesty&apos;s Government.In the event of a rupture it is presumed that the Home Office would be much more severe in regard to the entry of Russians into the United Kingdom, and any drastic restriction on the present comparative free ingress of Russians purporting to do business here will react on the present volume of trade and might lead eventually to the liquidation of bodies like Arcos and Centrosoyuz.    It is assumed that the judgment of the Court of Appeal which permits the Soviet Government freely to dispose of Russian goods (whether confiscated or not) on tho British market would not be affected.
09 iyIt is almost impossible to say whether it would pay the Soviet Government to cancel any contracts which have been entered into or not, and it is anticipated that Russia will be guided by expediency if they think it safe to retaliate in this way.    For instance, there Is hardly any doubt that they would still wish to take delivery of the textile machinery which has been ordered as nearly every mill in Russia is equipped with British machinery with which the mill hands are thoroughly familiar.The same can probably be said of the Vlckers contract as there is strong desire to pursue Lenin&apos;s ideal of electrifying the whole oountry.It is assumed that it would be both undesirable and impracticable to break off diplomatic relations and leave the Trade Agreement of 1921 in force.    It will, however, be convenient for the Cabinet to have a note on the scope and effect of this agreement and this is contained in Appendix A.
9 f) o 6 &amp; appendix A.The Trade Agreement (dated March 16th, 1921), between Great Britain and the Soviet Republic is terminable at any-time on six months1 notice, but in the event of Infringement by either party of any of its provisions the other party is immediately to be freed from the obligations of the Agreement. In this event it is provided that before taking any action inconsistent with the Agreement the aggrieved party shall give the other party a reasonable opportunity of furnishing an explanation or remedying the default.    In either of these events all necessary facilities have to be accorded for the winding-up of transactions already entered into under the Agreement and for the withdrawal of the nationals of the other party and their movable property;    no specific limit of time is mentioned in this connection.The main provisions of the Agreement, as regards British trade with Russia, are that no form of blockade shall be maintained against this country and no discrimination shall be exercised against trade between the United Kingdom and Russia, in any commodities which can be legally exported or imported, as compared with any other foreign country;    that British ships and cargo shall receive in Russian ports the treatment usually accorded by the established practice of commercial nations to foreign-merchant ships;    that facilities shall be given to an agreed number of British nationals to enter Russia and carry on trade there;    and that postal and telegraphic correspondence shall be renewed in accordance with the rules and regulations in existence up to 1914.The most important of these provisions is the undertaking to give to this country most&apos;-favoured-nation treatment in matters of trade.   While, hovjever, the accord of equal treatment is of
9 c* 0&amp; :&apos;j yimportance it has to be borne In mind that the system under which trade is conducted In Russia would render it easy for the Soviet Government if they so desired to discriminate against this country without any clear infringement of the provisions of the Agreement.   At the same time an entire refusal by the Soviet trading organisations to buy from or sell to this country might be argued to be a form of blockade and/or discrimination against trade between the United Kingdom and -Russia as compared with that between Russia and other foreign countries.The provision relating to ships again could be rendered nugatory by the insertion In contracts made by the Soviet trading organisations of a requirement that goods bought and sold by them should not be carried in British ships.    This though in conflict with the spirit of the Agreement would not apparently conflict with its actual terms.The requirement that British subjects shall be permitted to sojourn and carry on trade in Russia is mainly of importance in connection with the obtaining and carrying out of contracts with the Soviet trading organisations.    It does not appear1, on the wording of the Agreement,  to apply to the admission of British subjects in connection with the working of concessions granted to British interests.The provision relating to postal and telegraphic correspondence Is only of importance in so far as there Is trade to be carried on between this country and Russia and as operations are proceeding under concessions controlled from this country.Generally,  it may be said that the existence of the Agreement would be of little value to British trade if the   -Soviet Government wished to place hindrances in its way,By a further provision the Soviet Government undertook to make no claim (pending the conclusion of the general treaty to which the present Agreement was to be a preliminary) to dispose
in any way of the funds or other property of the late Russian Governments in the United Kingdom.    The lapse of this undertaking would, open the way for the Soviet Government to take proceedings in the British Courts for the recovery in particular of the Baring funds.At the time of the signature of the Trade Agreement a deelaration of recognition of claims was signed on behalf of H.M, Government and the Soviet Government, In which among other things the latter declared that it recognised in principle that it was liable to pay compensation to private persons who had supplied goods or services to Russia for which they had not been paid.    This declaration is of course in the nature of things not subject to withdrawal and In any case it has probably lost most of its importance.It is to be remembered that the Trade Agreement applies to the Irish Free State which was part of the United Kingdom when it was concluded and that it has also been extended by an Exchange of Notes in 1922 to the Dominion of Canada.    The termination of the Agreement by H.M. Government would presumably operate in the absence of a special arrangement with the Soviet Government in respect of its application to the Irish Free State and Canada.
9 Q -?APPENDIX B. TABLE I.Trade of the United Kingdom with Russia and its Succession States.Country.!    1912. I 1913.   j   1920.1921.!    1922,1923. !  1924. j  1925-1926.(A) Imports consigned from -1,000 j 1,000Russia I (former)&apos; Russia    ) I (U.S.S.R.)) Finland. ) Estonia. ) j Latvia.. ) Lithuania) Poland    )I (in- )l 1 eluding));j Dantzic))l1,000 40,271; 33,52340,539Not separately recorded. Included for the most part with Russia above.1,0001,000  1,000  1,000  1,000 i     i1,000  See new classification below.(2,695 8,103 9,566&apos;19,774 25,322 23,950 (7,721 jl0,434  113,205 13, 804 J13, 214 J13, 285Russia ;j( former) ; Russia    ) (U.S.S.R ) ) Finland. ) Estonia. ) Latvia.. ) I Lithuania) -Poland    ) 1 (in-      ) \ eluding) i Dantzic) )Russia (former). Russia ) (U.S.S.R. ) ) Finland. ) I Estonia. ) jlatvia( 730 (1,618 3441, 136 3,005 1, 1161,828 5, 660 8172,462 ! 1,813 i 2,235 6,375 j 5,279 j 5,604 1 735 &apos;     475 !     635(1,840 I 2,863  I   5, 3621  8, 320 j 5,165 18,525(B) Exports of United Kingdom Produce and Manufacture ___consigned to -___r____13,738 j 18, 103 111, 992See new classification below.Not separately recorded. Included for the most part with Russia above.!(1(2,181 3,641 i(l,932 ! 2,761 1(3,890 ! 1,030 l( 521 i 1, 118 i( 53 i 116 !( Ij( !(3,002 ! 2,435   ;   2,722J  3,500 ! 3,712 ; 2,4712,4921 3,860 I 6,240 j 5,8613,911! 4,558 i 3,999 j 2,772921; 628 \      604 j     552l,502j 2,207 i 1,632    1,155- 217&apos; 315 j      297 i     151(C) Exports of Imported ivierchandise consigned to -8,003 i   9, 591 j 4, 84li)flithuania jPolandf (in- ) eluding) Dantzic))Not separately recorded. Included for the most part with Russia above.KU, 210 K    970 379 425 see new classification below.970 707 356 282 2i ( iK j((1,867 j     6371.989 922 451 367 27,212 0.3,017 1,019 i      699 286 !      306222 16973 I 1,507181228888, 566 767 85 126. 9912S0JJ2:-. Prior to 1st April,  1923,   the particulars relate to the trade of the British Isles with the countries specified.    Since 1st. April,  1923,  they relate to the trade of Great Britain, and Northern Ireland only with the same c-^uutrias,
TABLE IIStatement showing the value of the Principal Articles imported into and Exported and Re-exported from the United Kingdom consigned from or to Russia in each of the years 1923-1926.(a) Imports consigned from Russia.Article.Declared Value.1923.1   1924.Th. .i  Th. .Butter ^................. *............&apos; ladders, Casings, &amp; Sausage Skins ...&apos;tg rs in shell........................Salmon, canned..................-----&quot;Oil Seed Cake ..  ...................rheat ...   . .    . .    ....................Barley........... ...............jMaize....................-......&quot;Fur skins, undressed (other thanRabbit and Seal).................Manganese Ore........................R*x or Linseed ......................(Sunflower seed  .....  .................:Soya Beans........................Flax, raw and dressed ................Flax, tow or cod ilia ,..............:,Pood and Timbers -Hewn, soft.......................Sawn, soft........................Pit props......................Sleepers.........................fool, raw, sheep^s and lambs &apos;.......Bristles............................iPlatiaum, refined and not refined petroleum, refined: -Lamp oil..........................Motor spirit.....................Lubricating Oil.................,Skins and Furs, unenumerated, dressed,not leather......................fll other articles..........  . . ....Total Imports consigned from Russia,238 7 174 864 10 79 174 8447 211 31730 260 88123 3,465 197 172186 153115 216 86354 8789,2662,338 i 122 ! 479 !1,239 56 395 490 8621,982 249 82 381270238246 4,887 465 365 52 548 808205 800 251532 1.4321926,2,448 139)1,278)1,304), 533 )i 802 )i1,490)1 206 )l )i2,643)! 244)&apos; 522 ! 540 I407 I 76 !379 j4,553 333 367 338 771)1,689) )295 ) 1,249) 175 *1926Th. . 1,92419,774198) 2,34325,322(a)576 (a)130 26197 3,224 (a) (a) 14(a)17,85923,950(a) Particulars not yet available:    Included with Other Articles
9  &apos;j 1      cjTABLE II (Continued ).Statement showing the Value of the Principal Articles Imported into and Exported and Re-exported from the United Kingdom, consigned from and to Russia during each of the years 1923-1926 (continued;.(h ) Exports of United Kingdom Goods.ArticleDeclared Value.1923. Th. .Herrings..................*.......***** ;&quot;heat meal and flour...................\Goal *.................................. i^ool, raw, sheep*s and lambs&apos;..........!Iron and steel and manufactures thereof: :Iron and steel wire, other than for      \ fencing and Insulated electric ...... other manufactures of Iron and steel . ! Lead and manufactures thereof .......... jTin, bars, Ingots, blocks and slabs .... jCutlery, Hardware Implements and Instruments: &apos; jFiles and rasps......................jSaws, Including saw &quot;blades........... other implements and tools (ex, ;machine tools and tool handles of j wood) .............................&apos;Scientific instruments and appliances (except electrical) ......jElectrical goods and apparatus ......... jMachinery !Prime movers (not electrical).........&apos;Textile............................ !Other................................ ;Machinery belting- IOf leather...........................other................................Cotton Yarns...........................jCotton piece goods.....................!&quot;col tops............................;&apos;,:?woollen and worsted yarns :-woollen and worsted..................IAlpaca and mohair . ,..................!Jute sacks and bags, empty, new ........ iChemicals, Drugs, Dyes and Colours .....IVehicles :Pail Locomotives and parts thereof ... IAeroplanes and parts thereof ......... JMotor cars and parts thereof ..  ...... iAll other Articles...................ITotal exports of United Kingdom i&quot;merchandise consigned to Russia......,1924.Th. .1925. Th. &quot;.&apos;1926Th. .9   l	729 2   !	154   j	10...		722	(a)695   j	48  !	59	11-     !	9 i	.191   i	(a)3 132211 1379 49 2038 657 139 I65 !1386 j83 i19 j421 i26 573656 489218 53486 50 13 2 3111238 34 190168 19 95822   J	45	114	(a)35  j	168	319   i	(a)38  j	139	34   :	12175  !	35	59   i	14104 ) 140) ) )81) )75 ) 9154(a)(a)56323. 11,221    1716 l I;25 ) 9) 63? ) 611) 205 ) )294 ) 102 )144 ) )-   )95 ) 241) 635(a)(a)4,5372,492      3,860 j   6,240   ;5,861(at Particulars are not yet available:    included with &quot;Other Articles&quot;.
TABLE II (Continued ).Statement showing the Value of the Principal Articles Imported iflto and&apos;Exported and Re-exported from the United Kingdom Consigned from and to Russia In each of the years 1923-1926.    (Continued).(c ) Exports of Imported Merchandise (Re-exports).Declared Value.Article.1923.1924.1925. I   1926Tea.............................*...&quot;Tieat ..............      ..............Flee, cleaned .4.....................&apos;rrheat meal and flour................Cotton raw (except linters ).........&quot;wool, raw, sheop^s and Iambs    .......Hides, wet.................- .. -.....Rubber, crude ........*..............Gums and Resins.....................Chemicals, Drugs and Dyes...........Cotton yarns and manufactures  .......Leather undressed and dressed .......Machinery...........................Lead, pig and sheet.........----...Tin;   Blocks,  ingots, bars and slabs.Zinc and Zinc manufactures ..........All other articles ..................Total exports of imported merchandise consigned to Russia1019731624 10 3750 123 91 40 173Th-  * 37614,149508 722 120 45 1415 53 237 251 80 5241,989  I   7,212Th. .	Th. .1,011 i	240260 !	184);	(a)191 )j	5,264 ,	3,274319 i	6801,346  1	6761,506  !	2,576175 )i	179 ): 195 )l115)1     (a) 208 )i 37l)j 465 )j 254)!974 j1,12013,0178,566(a) Particulars not yet Other Articles.available:    included with
TABLE III - RUSSIA - TRADE BY COUNTRIES.luntry whence iported or to Ihich Exported.ermany.......fjnited Kingdomkited States.ejtherlands. ..fustria..........)luhgary.....zecho-Slovakiaoiand......inland.....ranee.... rgentina.gypt.....weden...,ltlon* *&apos;* lustra lia.anada. . . , Smia;ither Countries.Total. . . .fermany.,.........Ilted Kingdom. . . .Wiei. States.....Jtherlands. ......is&amp;ria...........liigary...........see no-Slovakia...(land............n&amp;and...........ance............ligium...........p?ark...........ply.............tonia...........jityia............f&amp;ey............her Countries. .. (11913.1923-4.1924-5.1925-6 fOct.125-Mar.&apos;26)(a) ImportsAmount(1913Values)Thous. Rbls.652,209 173,012 79,093 21,389 35,698(a)	a.50,959	3.756,990 (b)	4. 1	-5, 939	0.416,926	1. 214,222	1-0366	0.0(b)	-34,550	2. 5232,681	17.01, 374,034	1O0.OPropnof Total47.5 12. 6 5.8 1.6 2. 6Amount(1913Values])Thous. Rbls.44,970 48,796 49,941 1,372 2,448 02,650 2,836 6,897 2,297 1,312 158 12,257 67 2,032 2 9822,400200,533Propn :j Amount of   j (Current Total. Values)22.4 24.4 24 9 0.7 1.2 0.0 1.3 1.4 3.4 1.1 0.7 0. 1 6.1 0.0 1.0 0.011.3100.0Thous. Rbls.101, 107, 188, 33, 10,21, 10, 18,9, 10, 22, 15,1, 29,2, 8, 59.602 806 252 878 512 610 800 267 605 079 621 961 465 919 871 394 110 559633,311Propn^of Total.116.1 17.0 29.7 5.4 1.7 0.1 3.4 1.6 2.9 1.4 1.7 3.6 2.4 0.3 4.7 0.4 1.3 6. 3100.0Amount(CurrentValues).Thous. Rbls.94,545 70,975 61,255 5,244 11,92114,693 5,798 9,97310,212 3,55117,535 9,511 1,34411,256 415 6,99541.662Propn:of Total.376,88525.1 18.8 16.3 1.4 3.23.9 1.5 2. 6 2.7 0.9 4.7 2.5 0.4 3.0 0.1 1.9 11.0300.0(b) Exports.5Thous. Rbls.453,584 267,80114,155 177,41265,297Total.(a)	-55,284	3,6100,879	6.664,663	4.336,425	2.473,761 (a)	4.9	-(a)	-35,783	2.4175.091	11.529.8 17.60.9 11.74.3I Thous. Rbls.66. 80,6, 21,2,9, 14,9, 10, 15, 14, 37, 24,.25*402 368 010 543 883189 919 417 609 484 772 264 791 312 025 70119.5 23.7 1.8 6.3 0.30.0 0.8 2.8 4.3 2.8 3.2 4.5 4.4 11.0 7. 1 7.5Thous. Rbls.87, 185, 21, 20, 2,3, 2, 22, V 19, ! 13, i 15, 13, 62, 9, S7A005 ! 442 ! 169 &apos; 514 975 42 377 i 762 507 i 133 i S71 ! 697 j 433 967 744 666 140Thous. Rbls.1,520, 135100.0 339,689100.017. 1 36.7 4.2 4.0 0.6 0.0 I 0.1 0.7 0.5 4.4 3.8 2.7 3.0 2.7 12. 3 1.9 5.354,145 i 17.6 98,220 31.9507,844 H0O.O13,224 10,147 2,340**   i306i 1,627 2,737i 21, 1361 10,344: 5,623i 15,852j 13,769 32,947 8,052 17,745308,2144.3 3.3 0.80. 1 0. 5 0. 9 6. 9 3.3 1.8 5. 1 4.5 10.7 2.6 5.7100.0(a) Formed part of Russia in 1913,(b) Not separately recorded.

</content>
</cab>
