<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/184/0 images: 426-429</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I^TTTg^POCPMEMT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNTC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)SECRET. COPY NO. .. ---1 C A B I MB T. :C.P. 39(27).EDUCATIONAL    POLICY. MBMORAMDUM BY TEE PRESIDENT OF THg BOARD OF EDUCATION.1.      I should like the Cabinet to consider&quot; educational policy in connection with the Report of the Barstow Committee on Block Grants.2,      Two years ago I invited Local Education Authorities to define their educational policy by submitting to me programmes covering the period 1927-30.     These programmes are now before me and it is necessary to come to some decision as to the way in which they should be treated.3.     The Board of Education might,  of course,  carry on as in the past- authorising new work where it thinks fit and regulating the rate of progress as best it can in the-light of its general knowledge of government policy,.     This procedure, however, tends to commit the Exchequer in advance to financial liabilities for which the Government secures no political credit and the system of three-year programmes was designed to supply the Exchequer with a better knowledge of its probable commitments and the Government with, a definite educational policy for which it can claim credit.4.      The actual work for which the programmes provide,  in school building, provision of higher education, and the like, is,  on the whole,  reasonable,  though there is, of course, a great deal to be criticised in detail.     On the
other hand, their estimates, both of cost and. of teaching staff, are so exaggerated that it is impossible to accept them as the stand,5. 1 propose, therefore, to define the Government&apos;s attitude towards Local Authorities&apos; programmes in the following terms  :-&quot;The Board have considered the programmes submitted by Local Education Authorities for the yoars  1927-30. It is clear that Authorities have found it difficult to forecast at all closely the ultimate financial effect of their programmes,   and they will not expect that the Board should commit themselves at this stage to the full amount of the programme estimates. The programmes themselves have, however, for the most part been evidently drawn up with great care,  and, taken together,   they appear to constitute a sound and  practical plan of educational development.      The Board propose, therefore, to accept these programmes a3 the general basis of educational policy during the next three years whilst continuing to discuss with each Authority the details of its particular programme Curing the &quot;programme period&quot; 1927-30,  grant will continue to be paid on the percentage basis,&quot;6.      Such a statement xvill leave the Board free to refuse sanction to particular proposals which they consider unnecessary or extravagant and to regulate from year, to year the number of elementary school teachers whose salaries they will be prepared to recognise for grant. It will also leave the Cabinet free to check development at any time if the state of the national finances requires it, but it will provide the Government with a definite
educational prograiiuiie extending over the next election, I propose, further,  to announce,  in agreement with the Treasury,  certain &quot;rations&quot; on expendjture in various branches of the education service *7.     This policy will not,  I anticipate,  involve any net increase in Exchequer expenditure before the year 1939-30. The board s Estimates for 1927-28, as they have been submitted to the Treasury,  show no increase on the Estimates for the year now expiring, the automatic increase foreseen last year as the result of the retardation of certain grant payments having been balanced by economies in other directions.     Any increase in grant in the year 1923-29 will,  in all probability, be more than balanced by the contributions receivable from Local Authorities in that year for the first time towards teachersr pensions,&apos;    The ultimate cost to the Exchequer of fully carrying- out all reasonable proposals in the programmes may be in the neighbourhood of  2-g- Millions, a figure which might be reached in the year 1931-32, but I do not propose that the Government should bs publicly committed to this,  or any-other figure.      Nor.,  of course,   should any Local Authority-be regarded as committed to its programme if it wishes to modify or abandon it.      Subject to the Beard&apos;s statutory duty of maintaining the efficiency of the education service all work dene under the programmes will be undertaken on the initiative and at the discretion of tho Local authorities thornselves.      Generally speaking,  Authorities who wish to carry out the whole of their programmes will be amply covered by the proposals of the Barstow Committee, but any
Authority not so covered will be free to adjust its programme accordingly and no Authority will be obliged against its will to mortgage its block grant in advance.All V .--   c2/2/27.Board of Education, S.7i.l* February 2nd, 1927.

</content>
</cab>
