<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/66/25 images: 336-353</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO(79) 25thnclu sionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 13 DECEMBER 1979at 10.15 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MPPrime Ministere Rt Hon William Whitelaw MPcretary of State for the Home Departmente Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MPancellor of the Exchequere Rt Hon Francis Pym MPcretary of State for Defencee Rt Hon Sir Ian Gilmour MPrd Privy Seale Rt Hon Michael Heseltine MPcretary of State for the Environmente Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MPcretary of State for Walese Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MPcretary of State for Social Servicese Rt Hon John Nott MPcretary of State for Tradee Rt Hon Mark Carlisle QC MPcretary of State for Education and ScienceThe Rt Hon Lord Hail shamLord ChancellorThe Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph MPSecretary of State for IndustryThe Rt Hon James Prior MPSecretary of State for EmploymentThe Rt Hon Peter Walker MPMinister of Agriculture, Fisheriesand FoodThe Rt Hon George Younger MPSecretary of State for ScotlandThe Rt Hon Humphrey Atkins MPSecretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Norman St John-Stevas MPChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterThe Rt Hon David Howell MPSecretary of State for EnergyThe Rt Hon John Biffen MPChief Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Angus Maude MPPaymaster GeneralSECRET309
SECRETTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTRtHon Norman Fowler MP The Rt Hon Michael Jopling MPrter of Transport Parliamentary Secretary, TreasuryMr Paul Channon MPMinister of State, Civil Service Department(Items 6 and 7)SECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMr M D M Franklin (Items 3 and 4)Mr     Le Cheminant (Items 5-7)Mr P J Harrop (Items 1 and 2)Mr R L Wade-Gery (Items 3 and 4)Mr P Mountfield (Items 6 and 7)Mr W N Hyde (Items 1 and 2)Mr G D Miles (Item 5)C ONTENTSSubject PagePARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSBusiness in the House of Commons 1Local Government, Planning and Land Bill 1Parliamentary Building 3BRITISH LEYLAND 3FOREIGN AFFAIRSIran 4Rhode sia 4Defence 4COMMUNITY AFFAIRS 6AIRPORT DEVELOPMENT POLICY 6THE ECONOMIC OUTLOOK AND PUBLIC EXPENDITURE 9PAY AND PRICE PROVISIONS FOR THE 1980-81 CASH LIMITS 10SECRET310
CONFIDENTIALLIAMENTARYAIRSliness in the! of Commons1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.    It was pointedout that, if the Motions to approve the Rate Support Grant r(Increase) Orders were not passed before the recess, it was likelythat some local authorities would have to borrow at the highprevailing rates of interest in order to meet their commitmentsin the present financial year.    These Orders, unlike the Orderssetting the Rate Support Grant for the next financial year, couldbe taken after 10. 00 pm.    They did not have to be approved by theHouse of Lords and should be debated in the House of Commons thefollowing week, probably on Thursday, 20 December.The Cabinet -1.Took note.Ill Government,tig and LandInousirence:24thIllusions,lite 2THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said thatfurther concern had been expressed about the Local Government,Planning and Land Bill.    The Chairman of the Conservative Partyand representatives of the local authority associations hadexpressed opposition to the provisions in the Bill for transferringplanning powers from County to District Councils, for a new formof Rate Support Grant and for a new system of control for localauthority capital expenditure.    In view of the length of the Bill,there was also concern about the timetable for its passage throughParliament.    He was prepared to shorten the Bill by droppingsome 60 clauses.    There could, however,  be no question of amajor alteration of policy on block grant or capital controls. Hebelieved that many local authorities would welcome the proposalto change from a project-based to a ceiling-based control ofcapital expenditure.    It was not clear on the face of the Bill,however, how its provisions would achieve that result. Thatwould depend on how the provisions would be operated;  and hehad not yet had an opportunity to explain this to local authorities.Once he had agreed with the Chancellor of the Exchequer howthese controls were to operate in practice, he proposed to meetand explain to the Tory group leaders of local authorities that,despite the imposition of overall ceilings for capital expenditure,authorities would benefit greatly from the relaxation of the presentdetailed controls.    He would, however, need the firm backing ofhis colleagues for the essential provisions of the Bill.In discussion, it was argued that problems of Parliamentaryhandling would arise both from the length and complexity of theBill and from the number of controversial issues that had to bedebated.    There was strong opposition in Parliament and amongConservative local authorities to some of its financial provisions,CONFIDENTIAL311
CONFIDENTIALand the County Councils objected to the proposed changes in thedistribution of planning powers.    If the financial provisions wereto remain at the core of the Bill, as many clauses as possibleshould be deferred to a later session;  otherwise the whole of theGovernments legislative programme would be put at risk. Infurther discussion there was strong support for the early implementa-tion of the main elements of the Bill to establish effective controlover public expenditure by local authorities.    The provisionsrelating to the efficiency of local authorities, the greater accounta-bility of direct labour organisations and the repeal of theCommunity Land Act would command support among Governmentbackbenchers.    The consequential re-enactment of the powers ofthe Land Authority for Wales, though lengthy, should not occupymuch Parliamentary time.    If, in the event, there had to be aguillotine, it seemed unnecessary to contemplate dropping majorprovisions of the Bill.    Detailed amendments to meet legitimatepoints raised by local authorities could be made in Committee.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theabolition of detailed controls and the sorting out of planningfunctions would enable staff to be saved in both central and localgovernment.    The Cabinet had reaffirmed the need to introducethe new form of Rate Support Grant and a new system of capitalcontrols in order to prevent future over-spending by localauthorities.    The Secretary of State for the Environment shoulddiscuss the operation of the new controls with representatives oflocal authorities, stressing the benefits of the new procedures,but also offering to consider any alternative suggestions they mighthave for achieving the Governments objectives.    The presentationof the provisions in the Bill for the control of capital expenditureshould be revised.    The Cabinet had noted the offer of theSecretary of State for the Environment to omit 60 clauses from theBill.    He should consider whether any further reductions could bemade in the else of the Bill without jeopardising essential provisions.He should report on all these matters, as early as possible in theNew Year, to a small group of Ministers to be set up under thechairmanship of the Home Secretary.    The Bill, as shortened andamended, should be introduced into the House of Commons, as soonas possible after the recess.    Every effort should be made tosecure the passage of the Bill this session:  an extended sessionmight well become necessary for both Houses.The Cabinet -2. Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.s2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL3. Invited the Secretary of State for theEnvironment to agree the detailed working of thecontrols over local authority capital expenditurewith the Chancellor of the Exchequer;  to discusswith and explain the proposals to the group leadersof local authorities;  and to seek an amendedpresentation of the relevant provisions in the Bill.4. Invited the Secretary of State for theEnvironment to consider whether the Bill could befurther shortened by dropping provisions which werenot essential.5.      Invited the Secretary of State for theEnvironment to report on the progress he had madeand conclusions reached to an ad hoc group to be setup under the chairmanship of the Home Secretary.liamentarydingTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthere was no question of the Government going ahead with thebuilding of new offices for Members of Parliament at a time whenpublic expenditure on important social services had to be reduced.She would be prepared to answer a Parliamentary Question to thaljeffect.The Cabinet -6. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.nsHfLANDiousfrence:J?9) 23rd(elusions,pte 42. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that theChairman of British Leyland had been due to visit Japan beforeChristmas to sign the contract with Honda for the joint productionof a new model at Cowley.    It would be impossible for theGovernment to reach a decision on the British Leyland plan andrequest for additional Government funding before then.Sir Michael Edwardes intended, therefore, to postpone his visit.It was hoped that Honda would be prepared to postpone a decisionon the deal;  if, however, Honda decided in the circumstances notto proceed with the joint venture, rather than to wait for apostponed visit, British Leyland might feel obliged to withdrawtheir plan for reconsideration.The CabinetTook note.CONFIDENTIALQ1 Q
SECRETnsice:24thsions,33. THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that during his visit on10 December the United States Secretary of State, Mr Vance, had in thecontext of the American hostages in Tehran asked the Government totake action to freeze Iranian assets in London.    The Government wasanxious to support the United States Government if it could;  but it hadnot been possible to agree to this proposal because it was not clear thatthe Government had the necessary legal powers and because any suchaction could do lasting damage to London&apos;s role as a financial centreand to the oil-producing countries&apos; confidence in the internationalmonetary system.    The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary was inBrussels and in touch with Mr Vance and the French and German ForeignMinisters.    The Americans were likely to pursue their case before theInternational Court of Justice and with the United Nations SecurityCouncil.    Her Majenty&apos;s Ambassador and other diplomaticrepresentatives in Tehran were advising against resort to more drasticaction at present.    But it would not be easy to satisfy American publicopinion.    Given Iranian disregard for international law, the possibilityof Britain and other European countries withdrawing their Ambassadorsfrom Tehran might have to be considered but did not on balance seemdesirable at present.ice:24thsions,3THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that British sanctions against Rhodesiahad now been lifted, with little adverse reaction so far.    New Zealandhad followed suit, and the Federal Republic of Germany was thought tobe about to do so.    It waa also hoped that the United States Governmentwould lift sanctions in the near future, in spite of the initially unhelpfulattitude of their representative at the United Nations.    Meanwhile atLancaster House the Salisbury delegation appeared willing to accept boththe latest British proposals on the ceasefire arrangements and the FinalAct of the Conference.    The intentions of the Patriotic Front delegationremained uncertain, but there was a reasonable prospect that they toowould accept.The Cabinet -1.Took note.17thsions,2THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that the Foreign andCommonwealth Secretary and he were on balance well satisfied with thedecisions on long-range theatre nuclear forces taken at the MinisterialMeeting of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation in Brussels on12 December.    As well as settling the arms control proposals to be putforward (including the American offer to withdraw 1, 000 nuclear war-heads from Europe), the Alliance had agreed to the deployment in Europe4SECRET314
SECRETof all the 572 new American missiles envisaged.    Reservations byBelgium and the Netherlands had proved less serious than at one timeseemed likely.    The Belgian Government had agreed to accept theirshare of the missiles, subject only to reconsideration after six months,in the light of the progress of arms control negotiations;  and the DutchGovernment had accepted the proposals as a whole, but had postponed adecision on taking a share of the missiles in Holland until the end of 1981.Even the latter date was at least a year earlier than the proposeddeployment could in practice begin.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, when she and the Foreign andCommonwealth Secretary visited the United States on 17-18 December,she would have a preliminary discussion with President Carter on thereplacement of the British strategic nuclear deterrent force, for whichon economic grounds alone American assistance would be necessary.The President was unlikely to want to take firm decisions on the matterat this stage, and it might be several months before agreement wasreached.The Cabinet -2.Took note.5SECRET
fCONFIDENTIAL[QNITY 4. THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that discussions between theS budget Ministers of the European Economic Community and theEuropean Parliament had so far failed to reach agreement, and it couldwell be that the European Parliament would vote to reject the draftdices Community budget for 1980,    It was arguable that this would create a)24th situation in which we could hope to change the budget to our advantage,sions, and there had been indications that the Germans saw a connection withs 4 and 5        the problem of our net contribution.    On the other hand, the confusioncreated by Parliaments failure to vote the budget might detractattention from our immediate problem.    On balance, failure to decideon the 1980 budget would probably not be helpful to us.In a brief discussion it was stressed that the Government should seekwherever possible to avoid getting into the position which it had founditself on this issue, of being unable to support Conservative Members ofthe European Parliament who were trying to be helpful to Britishinterests.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that,at the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) on 10-11 December, the Frenchrepresentatives had sought to block the proposals for a devaluation ofthe Green Pound and the Italian Green Lira, in order to extractconcessions on wine and sheepmeat.    After long and difficultnegotiations, including a powerful and effective intervention by hisMinister of State (Mr Buchanan-Smith), agreement had been reached ona package of structural measures in the wine sector which involved lessCommunity expenditure than the Commission^ proposals.    The UnitedKingdom representatives and the Commission had refused to agree to aFrench plea that further legal proceedings on sheepmeat should beabandoned.    The French had finally agreed to lift their reserve on theGreen currencies devaluations.The Cabinet -Took note.rtLOPMENT5. The Cabinet considered a letter dated 10 December from thePrivate Secretary to the Secretary of State for Trade to the PrivateSecretary to the Prime Minister, and a note prepared by the Secretaryof State for Trade for the Ministerial Committee on Economic Strategy(E(79) 69), both about airport development policy.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TRADE said that the previousGovernment had set up two Committees, an Advisory Committee onAirports Policy and a Study Group on South-East Airports, to consider6CONFIDENTIAL316
CONFIDENTIALthe longer-term options for handling growth of air traffic in the South-East.    These Committees, which included membership of all the majorinterests concerned, including the local authorities, had now reported tohim, and he proposed that the reports should be published.    It wasdesirable that the Government should put an end to the uncertaintysurrounding airport policy, and he proposed therefore to make astatement on the day of publication of the reports announcing theGovernments conclusions.    The issues had been examined in theMinisterial Committee on Economic Strategy, and a number ofpreliminary decisions had been reached, subject to endorsement byCabinet, both on substance and presentation.    These were that thereshould be no major new airport for London on the lines envisaged by theRoskill Commission;  that the fullest use of regional airports should beencouraged;  that additional airport capacity should be provided as thetraffic developed, at the existing airports of Heathrow, Gatwick andStansted;  that there should be a fourth, but not a fifth, terminal atHeathrow;  that there should be no second runway at Gatwick;  that theBritish Airports Authority (BAA) should be invited to bring forwardproposals for a new terminal at Stansted, so as to make maximum useof the existing runway facilities;  and that outline planning consent shouldalso be sought for the development of a second runway at that site. Anactual need for a second runway at Stansted would not emerge, if itemerged at all, before the 1990s, but the grant of outline planningpermission would enable any property owners in the affected area (about2, 000 acres) who wished to dispose of their properties to do so to theBAA at unblighted values.    He proposed that the announcement should bemade early next week, and that he should hold out the prospect of aParliamentary debate on the policy early in the New Year.In discussion the following main points were made -a. In handling the planning aspects of developments like thatenvisaged for Stansted it was desirable that there should beopportunities both for public and for Parliamentary debate.There were a number of ways in which both objectives could beachieved.    All involved a public inquiry, but there was no needyet for the Government to decide on the most appropriateParliamentary arrangements.    A decision here could be deferreduntil after the proposed debate and public reaction to theannouncement as a whole.b. It would be important to avoid compromising the quasi-judicial function of the Secretary of State for the Environment inrespect of planning applications.    The proposed statement wouldneed to be worded with this in mind.7CONFIDENTIAL317
CONFIDENTIALc. It would be important for the statement to go as far aspossible in relieving the anxieties of those who were opposed tothe development of a new airport at Maplin or at inland &quot;greenfield&quot; sites.d. An enlarged traffic flow to Stansted would requireimprovements in access both by rail and by road, including theroad links between central London and the Mil.    The provision ofthese links, with due regard to the interests and feeling of thosethrough whose communities the new links would pass, would bevery important to public attitudes to the proposals for developingStansted.    These would require additional public money, but theextra sums needed to provide for improved surface links wouldbe lower in the case of Stansted than in any of the sites canvassedfor &quot;green field&quot; development.    The provision of a new rail linkfrom Stansted to the Liverpool Street to Cambridge line wouldrequire the passage through Parliament of a Private Bill.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the Cabinetwere agreed that the provision of a new major airport for London shouldbe ruled out, as should the possibility of a second runway at Gatwick,and a fifth terminal at Heathrow.    The Government were prepared forthe BAA to bring forward detailed proposals for further development atStansted, including a new terminal and other facilities to increase theuse made of the existing runway, together with outline proposals for thepossible longer-term development of a second runway.    These proposalswould then be examined by an appropriate planning procedure, beforeany final decision was taken.    Early next week the Secretary of State forTrade should make an announcement along the lines he had indicated,taking into account the points made in discussion, and should publish thereports of the study groups at the same time.    He should consultcolleagues as appropriate about the precise terms of the statement.The Cabinet were also agreed that he should offer the prospect of aParliamentary debate early in the New Year, and that decisions aboutthe planning procedures for dealing with this case should be deferreduntil the debate had taken place.    The Cabinet thus endorsed all therecommendations contained in paragraph 16 of E(79) 69, except that thedecision on the planning procedures should be held over for the timebeing. *The Cabinet -1.       Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.8CONFIDENTIAL318
CONFIDENTIAL2.       Invited the Secretary of State for Trade, afterconsultation with the Secretary of State for theEnvironment, to make a Parliamentary statement onthe lines indicated in the Prime Minister&apos;s summingup, and to arrange for the publication of the reportsof the Advisory Committee on Airports Policy andthe Study Group on South-East Airports at the sametime.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum (C(79) 61) by theOMIC Chancellor of the Exchequer, reporting his present view of the economicOOK outlook and making recommendations for further reductions in publicUBLIC expenditure.NDITUREThe Cabinet1 s discussion is separately recorded.ousence: The Cabinet -)21stusions, 1.       Agreed upon the necessity to make the further4 reductions in the total of public expenditurerecommended by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.2. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theChief Secretary, Treasury, to discuss with theDepartmental Ministers concerned programmereductions to achieve the agreed reductions in thetotals.3. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer tocirculate a further memorandum on the economicbackground and on monetary policy.4. Agreed to resume their discussion before theend of January.CONFIDENTIAL319
CONFIDENTIAL(IiND 7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer (C(79) 60) proposing the pay and price adjustments to be usedISIONS in setting cash limits for central Government expenditure in 1980-81 toIHE correspond with the Cabinet1 s earlier decisions on the volume of1 expenditure.S THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that Ministers hadalready agreed to the cash limits and external financing limits for localous authorities and nationalised industries.    The next step was to set cashince: limits for the remainder of central Government expenditure, including]) 19th the National Health Service (NHS) and the defence budget, but excludingusions, the pay of the Civil Service, for which separate provision would be made5 later.    He proposed a single combined figuie of 14 per cent for expectedpay and price movements, year upon year.    This figure was in line withthe forecast published under the provisions of the Industry Act.    If in theevent the outturn was higher, the volume of expenditure would have to beadjusted so as to stay within the cash limits.    The figures should not beset so low as to risk the breakdown of the cash limits system. Herecognised that these proposals could be thought to involve a measure ofautomatic indexation, of a kind which Cabinet regarded as undesirable;but this was inevitable, in a system where expenditure decisions weretaken in volume terms and had to be translated into cash figures. Hehoped it would be possible to use much smaller adjustment factors inlater years.In discussion the following points were made -a. There was a risk that any built-in inflation factor would bemisunderstood, and if separately published, might be construedas a pay norm.    It was another example of the automaticadjustment for movements in the Retail Price Index which lay atthe root of the public expenditure problem.    Against this it wasargued that Ministers had already agreed their approach to thevolume of public expenditure-    It would be wrong, and in a sensesurreptitious, to seek to impose  a further volume reduction byway of cash limits.    A single provision for pay and pricemovements combined could be presented as covering a widerange of individual changes.    There was, however, no way ofavoiding publication of individual cash limit figures.b. It was suggested that it would be preferable to adopt afigure of 13 per cent, to correspond with the figure used forRate Support Grant expenditure.    Against this it was arguedthat the difference was justified because local authorities hadalternative methods of financing not available to centralGovernment, and in particular to the NHS.10CONFIDENTIAL320
CONFIDENTIALc. Special provision would be made for those groups for whomthe Standing Commission on Comparability had yet to report.The exact amount to be allowed for this purpose, eg foruniver sity teacher s, should be considered further.d. The measures suggested would present problems for theMinistry of Defence, where the Government was bound not only byits own Manifesto but by international commitments on defenceexpenditure.    A particular problem might arise on the pay of theArmed Forces, since the Government was committed toimplementing the recommendations of the Armed Forces PayReview Body (AFPRB) in April, and these might well indicate ahigher figure.    It was argued that, if significant cuts were to besought from the defence budget, such cuts should be discussed onmerits, not imposed as a by-product of cash limits.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet approved the proposal made by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,and generally endorsed the adjustment factors set out in Annex A to hispaper.    The precise allowance to be made for individual groups shouldbe discussed further with the Ministers concerned.    The Cabinetrecognised that the pay of the Armed Forces might present specialproblems, given the Governments commitment to implement the findingsof the AFPRB:  one possibility might be a separate limit for ArmedForces pay, as for Civil Service pay.    The Cabinet would be content,accordingly, for the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary ofState for Defence to seek to reach agreement on any special treatmentwhich might be necessary in this case.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.2. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer todiscuss with the Secretary of State for Education andScience and the Secretary of State for Social Servicesthe cash limits to be adopted for the pay of thosegroups for whom there were outstanding comparabilityawards.3. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer toconsider with the Secretary of State for Defence, inthe light of the points made in discussion, theapplication of the Cabinet&apos;s decisions in the area ofthe defence budget, having regard in particular to theGovernment&apos;s commitment on Armed Forces pay.11CONFIDENTIAL321
CONFIDENTIAL4. Subject to the outcome of these discussions,approved the proposals for cash limits for 1980-81set out in Annex A to C(79) 60.Cabinet Office13 December 197912CONFIDENTIAL
SECRET(DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAjESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NOCABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEXCC(79) 25th Conclusions, Minute 6Thursday 13 December 1979 at 10.15 amThe Cabinet considered a memorandum (C(79) 61) by the Chancellor ofOMIC the Exchequer, reporting his present view of the economic outlook and0OK recommending further reductions of  1, 000 million in publicPUBLIC expenditure in 1980-81 and of  2,000 million in each of the subsequentNDITURE years.ous THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that Cabinet hadence: accepted, in its discussion of the November economic measures, the)21st possibility that further cuts in public expenditure might be necessary,iisions, beyond those already agreed.    The present economic strategy, based4 on tight control of the growth of money supply, was the only one opento the Government.    To achieve it without intolerably high interestrates or increases in taxation - which would themselves be inconsistentwith the strategy - required further reductions in public expenditure.Since the Budget in June there had been a number of adversedevelopments.    Oil prices had increased faster than expected.    So hadpay settlements, though recently there had been some more favourableindications.    The problem of our contributions to the European budgethad not yet been satisfactorily resolved.    The Cabinet&apos;s earlierdecisions on reductions in public expenditure had not been as far-reaching as he had hoped or recommended.    Without further cuts, itwould be necessary to increase taxes in the 1980 Budget if continuedhigh, and perhaps even higher, interest rates were to be avoided.Most outside commentators had recognised the need for furtherreductions in expenditure, going beyond the published figures for1980-81, and pressure for such cuts was mounting.    He believed thatit was necessary to reduce expenditure in 1980-81 by a further 1,000 million, and to reduce the plans for later years by 2, 000 million in each year.    Without early decisions of this kind,the Cabinet could easily be forced into a series of improvisedemergency economic measures.    Such decisions would entail thepostponement of publication of the White Paper on Public Expenditurefrom 1981-82 to 1983-84.1SECRET323
SECRETIn discussion the following main points were made -a. The published figures for public expenditure in 1980-81 hadbeen regarded as disappointing, and this was one of the factorswhich had made necessary an increase in interest rates. Indeed,had the Cabinet accepted the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;searlier advice on expenditure cuts the 17 per cent MinimumLending Rate and the 15 per cent mortgage rate might have beenavoided.b. If anything, the Chancellor of the Exchequers forecastswere over-optimistic.    The prospects for world trade weredeteriorating.    Oil prices were likely to rise sharply again inthe near future.    The expenditure plans made no provision for anumber of possible additional burdens, including measures tooffset the rundown of the steel industry, and the needs of BritishLeyland.c. Too much reliance should not be placed upon forecasts ofthe Public Sector Borrowing Requirement (PSBR).    In arecession the money supply and demand for credit would tend tocome down, and a temporary increase in Government borrowingmight be the appropriate response.    Against this it was arguedthat allowing the PSBR to rise was the correct response to arecession only if the PSBR was at a low level to begin with. ThePSBR in the United Kingdom was too high in relation to the grossdomestic product, and it could not be allowed to rise furtherwithout unacceptable risks to confidence.d. The main dynamic factor in the growth of public expenditurewas the way in which so many programmes increased directly orindirectly in proportion to movements in the Retail Price Index(RPI).    The RPI would rise in any case next year, for reasonsquite outside this country&apos;s control, as world oil pricesincreased.    The United Kingdom economy could not be insulatedfrom these movements.    This meant that it was now desirableto look again at all index-linked expenditures, including socialsecurity benefits and public sector pensions - though in thelatter case action might more fruitfully be concentrated onensuring that an adequate contribution was made by employeesto the cost of their pension rather than by seeking to removeindex-linking as such.    It was essential that public sector paynegotiators should realise that pay could not automatically beincreased to compensate for movements in the RPI.e. Other elements in public expenditure would also need to becurtailed.    There would be much to be said for seeking toachieve the necessary savings by means of a relatively small2SECRET324
SECRETnumber of large reductions, concentrating on major decisions,however painful these might be.    Difficult decisions would inparticular be needed in social security and in other socialservices, and on public sector rents.    But no area could bewholly exempt:  other Departments would have to meet theirshare, although inevitably the major burden would have to fall onsome of the largest spenders.f. It was undesirable that the incidence of further cuts shouldfall, as it had tended to do in the past, on capital expenditure,and there was probably little scope for further reductionsfollowing the cuts made in previous years.    The prime targetshould therefore be current rather than capital spending.g. It was suggested that the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;sstrategy was seen by many as relying too much on influencing theprice of money and not sufficiently on controls of the quantities ofcredit.    It might well be that an explosion of financial technologyhad made quantity controls ineffective, but it would helpMinisters in the public exposition of the Governments case ifthey could be given a fuller account than was at present availableof the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s monetary strategy and ofthe instruments by which it was being pursued, to enable them toanswer public criticism of this kind.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed to aim at reductions of public expenditure of 1, 000 million in 1980-81 and of  2, 000 million in each of the threesubsequent years.    It would be less difficult to make these decisionsnow than to take further offsetting action later.    Ministers shouldthemselves review their own programmes, to see where reductionscould be made.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer and the ChiefSecretary, Treasury, should discuss proposals for reductions withDepartmental Ministers.    If necessary, a small group of Ministerscould be established to consider any points which could not be resolvedin bilateral discussion.    The results should be reported to Cabinetbefore the end of January.    Meanwhile, publication of the second PublicExpenditure White Paper, covering the years 1981-82 to 1983-84, shouldbe postponed, and an announcement about this should be madeimmediately before or just after Christmas.    The Chancellor of theExchequer would circulate a further paper to the Cabinet on theeconomic background to the public expenditure problem, and on thetechniques of monetary control available to him for controlling thegrowth of the money supply.3SECRET
SECRETThe Cabinet -1. Agreed upon the necessity to reduce publicexpenditure by  1, 000 million in 1980-81 and by 2, 000 million in each of the subsequent years.2. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theChief Secretary, Treasury, to discuss with theDepartmental Ministers concerned programmereductions to achieve the agreed reductions in thetotals.3. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer tocirculate a further memorandum on the economicbackground and on monetary policy.4. Agreed to resume their discussion before theend of January.Cabinet Office14 December 1979SECRET326

</content>
</cab>
