<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/4/4 images: 72-85</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER  LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document. &quot;SECRET. Copy No.W. P. -(39)154.WAR   CABINET.AIR OPERATIONS AND INTELLIGENCE.Fourteenth Weekly Report &quot;by the Secretary of State for Air(Previous Report Paper W.Pe  (39) 14:6)The accompanying report on Air Operations and intelligence for the week ending Midnight, 10th December,is submitted to the War Cabinet.(Sgd.)    KINGSLEY WOOD.Richmond Terrace, SoW.l,11th December, 1939,

WEEKLY REPORT  (MO.  14) OF AIR operations and INTELLIGENCE FOR THE WEEK ENDING MIDNIGHT.     4 01QTH DECEMBER.   1959,ROYAL AIR FORCE OPERATIONS.Bomber Command,1. Operations against the German Fleet.      Two squadronscontinued to be held in readiness during the first days of theweek at advanced bases in Scotland from which they could operate against the tfDeutschland;i,  if located,.      The search for the&quot;Deutschland,: proved unsuccessful, however,  and the squadrons havenow returned to their bases.2, Night Reconnaissance and Leaflet Dropping,,      On the night of 5/6th December, 360,000 leaflets were dropped over Bremen and hamburg by two Whitley aircraft:    one of them experiencedconsiderable anti-aircraft fire on the return journey, but no enemy aircraft were seen.Fighter Command,3. Enemy aircraft.      German air activity during the past week has taken place mainly at night in the area from Norfolk tothe Downs, although enemy aircraft have also been detected offthe Scottish and North Riding coasts, and over the Home Counties.On three occasions enemy aircraft penetrated inland.      On the night of 5/6th December, one aircraft flew across the Midlands toSheffield, passing out to sea again over Lincolnshire, and on thefollowing day an enemy track was plotted, down the Channel andinland by way of Portsmouth, Horsham, Brentwood and Chelmsford.The third flight over England took place by day on December 10thwhen a single aircraft, flying very1 high, passed over Lincolnshireand East Anglia.4. Fighter patrols have been hampered by poor visibilityand low clouds, Interceptions, however, were made on December7th off the Scottish coast,.      At 11 aom,  on this day a Spitfire/attacked

attacked two Heinkel 111&apos;s flying just above the water off NorthBerwick.      Later,  seven Heinkel 111*8 flying down the coast frompeterhead were intercepted by one flight of No,72 Squadron, andsubsequently by a section of No.603 Squadron.      The German,aircraft dived almost to sea level,  and after an engagement,disappeared eastwards.      Later in the day, a German S.O.S. washeard giving a position thirty miles north-east of Fifeness, anda reconnaissance was made of the area but without finding tracesof the aircraft.      Pour Spitfires were hit during the engagement,but they all returned safely.5.      Because of German air activity over the fishing fleet in the North Sea,  &quot;sweeps&quot; are being undertaken by Blenheimfighters, &quot;when weather conditions permit, over the area occupiedby the fishing fleet.6. Defence against Mine-dropping:.      Arrangements for defence against mine-laying aircraft are progressing in the East Coastestuaries.      Three paddle boats have been fitted with search-lights and light anti-aircraft guns for operations in the thames estuary, and a few balloons are now flying from vessels oradjacent land sites in the estuaries of the Thames, Humber, Teesand Tyne^and also off Harwich.      Progress in extending thesearchlight zone in the Thames estuary has been delayed owing todifficulty in obtaining suitable vessels on which to mountsearchlights for experimental purposes.      As a special measurecertain areas in estuaries, and in the vicinity of defended ports,are being treated as &quot;inner artillery zones&quot; between sunset andsunrise:    in these zones anti-aircraft guns open fire on everyaircraft observed, unless recognised as friendly, and the zoneswill not be entered by our fighters except when in hot pursuit.7.      The dispositions of certain fighter squadrons have been altered with the object of strengthening the fighter defenceposition in Scotland and. the North of England.i /Coastal

Coastal Command.8.      Routine and anti-submarine patrols, searches, andconvoy escorts have continued, v/ith some interference from the weather.    Five submarines were sighted, and attacks were made on four of them:    it is believed that as l result of one of these attacks the U-boat was destroyed,    Four enemy aircraft were alsoseen during the week and two of them were engaged without definiteresults, although it is estimated that a Dornier 18 was badly damaged and may not have been able to reach its base.    The Dornierwas six times attacked by a Hudson aircraft, and fuel oil was seenstreaming from both sponsons of the enemy aircraft before it madeits escape.9. Air escort was provided for twenty-eight convoys,involving the use of one hundred and twenty-three aircraft.Advanced Air Strikin^ fore,  .10.      Fighter Squadrons.      Unfavourable weather has restrictedair activity?    eighteen patrols,  involving a total of 75 aircraft^were despatched during the week, v/ithout encountering an enemy aircraft.Royal Air Force Component of the British Expeditionary Force.11.      Bomber Squadrons.      No reconnaissances of enemy territoryhave been possible owing to adverse weather conditions..12.      Fighter Squadrons.      No engagements with enemy aircraft have been reported..Overseas Commands.13.,      Anti-submai&apos;ine patrols and convoy escorts have bee lcarried out by aircraft from the Mediterranean Command.-    Theoperations by the Aden Command referred to in Weekly Reports Nos. 11and 12 were brought to a successful conclusion on the 6th Decemberby the complete submission of all sections of the tribe concerned,the surrender of hostages, and the payment of the fines demanded.The murderers of the crew of the Blenheim aircraft which made aforced landing on the first day of the operations are still at largehut steps have been taken for their apprehension./INTELLIGENCE

INTELLIGENCE,German Air Force Activity.14.        Bombers. No offensive action has &quot;been undertaken by german bombers during the week.    The Heinkel lll&apos;s interceptedoff the east coast of Scotland on December, 7th (see paragraph 4)are believed to have come from a bomber unit normally locatednear Hamburg.15. Some bomber units have been identified as having movedwestwards, but it is probable that these moves took place before december 3rd.16.        Fighters,        There has been no appreciable change inthe estimated distribute:.cn of  the German fighter force.17,       Reconnaissance-       A new reconnaissance unit has beenformed, a proportion of whose flying personnel belonged to theLufthansa (Civil) Fleet.18,        Apart from one flight over the French coast betweenDunkirk and Boulogne, German reconnaissance operations have been limited to the country south of Thionville and Rheims.    OnDecember 7th fifteen enemy aircraft were seen over Chalons-sur-Marne, Rheims,  St. Menehould and Verdun,  and reconnaissances were also reported north of Verdun,  in the area between Chaumont andBar-le-Duc,  south of Nancy,  and over Strasbourg:    on the following day four flights were made over south-east France.19. An unidentified aircraft, flying at great height, isreported to have dropped a parachutist north of Soissons onDecember 10th, but no confirmation of the report has beenobtained.20. Coastal Squadrons. Two new coastal squadrons have,been identified.    The first few months of the war have put astrain on German coastal units and the formation of new units is alogical expansion.    The great amount of coastal-type training being undertaken by coastal schools in the Baltic is additionalevidence that there is need for more trained personnel in this branch of the German Air Force,

21.      The activity cf coastal units over the North Sea hascontinued during the past week and single coastal aircraft havebeen identified off the East Coast.French Air Force Activity.22.      Reconnaissance activity by the French Air Force was again restricted during the week by unfavourable weather conditions.K.W.




</content>
</cab>
