<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/44/16 images: 120-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTTS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (44)445th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 145 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime ministers room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, 2nd November, 1944, at 6 p.m.PresentThe Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome security.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for xAir.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,.M.P., Minister of Plealth (Items 1-3).The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport.Major the Right Hon. G. LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Fuel and power.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 4-6).The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Lord Portal, Ministerof Works.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 4-6).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.&apos;Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. W. S. Murrie.[28717]
WAR CABINET 145 (44).Contents.minute no. Subject. Page.1      Munitions Production....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     189Discharge from Employment on Aircraft Production.2      Prisoners of War       ....      ....      ....      ........      ....     189Employment of Italian Prisoners.3      Government Building Programme ....      ....      ....      ....     189Proposed Labour Allocations, October/December 1944.4      Man-power      ....      ....      ....      ....      ........      ....     190Eeallocation between Civilian Employments during the Transi-tional Period.5      Economic Controls in the Transition Period      ....      ....     1916      Civil Service    ........      ....................    193Recruitment during the Reconstruction Period./
munitions production.DischargesfromEmploymenton aircraft production.(previous reference erence:&quot;W.M. (44) 138thConclusions,Minute 2.)1. The War Cabinet were informed that, consequent upon thedecisions reached on the 17th October as to the aircraft production programme, some men had been discharged from aircraft factories in London. Their proper course was, of course, to apply to theLabour Exchange when they would be transferred to other posts.As, however, they had been receiving very high wages on piece-ratework, the alternative employment was not very attractive. One ortwo demonstrations had resulted.The Prime Minister said that steps should be taken at once to put the matter in its true light.After a short discussion the War Cabinet Invited the Minister of Labour and National Service toarrange to answer a private notice Question on thefollowing day in order to make the position clear.The Minister of Information was also invited to giveappropriate guidance to the press.Prisonersof War.Employmentof italian prisoners.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 129thConclusions,Minute 5.)2. The Minister of Labour and National Service drew attention to the persistent criticism in some newspapers of theemployment of Italian prisoners. It was important to make thebest use of the labour of prisoners of war. Any decisions as towhether prisoners of Avar could appropriately be employed on certain types of work should be made by the War Cabinet rather than by individual Departments.The Minister of Information promised to help with the press;but asked that a general statement as to the employment of prisonersof war should be issued under the authority of the War Cabinet.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he was proposing to circulate a paper on the subject to the War Cabinetshortly.The War Cabinet Took note of these statements.GovernmentBuildingProgramme.ProposedLabourAllocations,October /December,1944.(previous references:W.M. (44) 126thConclusions,Minute 4; andW.M.(44)99thConclusions,Minute 9.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Production (W.P. (44) 596) setting out the Labourallocations proposed for the period October-December 1944.The Minister of Production said that the situation was verytight. Departments were down to the bone and the Ministry ofSupply, in particular, were below the safety level. If the WarCabinet would agree that the amount of building labour employedon the repair of damaged houses in the London area should not beincreased beyond its present figure of 117,000 (and he believed thatthis limitation would be acceptable to those responsible) that would leave him a very small margin with which he could deal Avith casesof extreme urgency.Points in discussion : (a) The Secretary of State for Air asked for help Avith therepairs of runways of a group of bomber airfields in the Midlands.This Avas of urgent operational importance. The question Avas&quot;raised whether the best use was being made of all available suitablelabour. In this connection, the Secretary of State undertook tosubmit to the Prime Minister particulars showing the strength ofthe RA.F. Regiment at its maximum strength and to-day, head-quarters staffs and officers of various ranks being shown separately.(b) The Secretary of State for Air said that more labour was needed for the aerodrome under construction at Heath Row if itwas to be in running order by the early summer. He required150 men for runways and 600 for essential buildings. The Ministerof Labour and National Service suggested that no less satisfactory[28717]b 2
results would be secured by the postponement of any increase in thelabour force until the spring when the weather would enable good progress to be made.(c) The Minister of Production said that he would considerso far as possible requests such as those put foward by the Secretaryof State for Air, but his margin would be extremely narrow.The War Cabinet (1) Agreed that the total of building labour employed on repair of damaged houses in the London area should not beincreased beyond its present figure of 117,000.(2) Subject to this understanding, approved the proposals ofthe Minister of Production as set out in W.P. (44) 596,and authorised him to deal with cases of extreme urgencyat his discretion, from the small available margin.Man-Power.ReallocationbetweenCivilianEmploymentsduring theTransitionalPeriod.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 125thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. At their meeting on the 22nd September the War cabinet had approved a draft White Paper on the Reallocation of Man-power as a basis for discussion with the Joint consultative committee, and the Minister of Labour and National Service had undertaken to consider certain points raised in discussion in theWar Cabinet, and to submit a revised draft after the discussionwith the Consultative Committee had taken place.The War Cabinet now had before them :--(a) A Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and NationalService (W.P. (44) 563) to which was appended a revised draft ofthe White Paper embodying amendments made in the light of theprevious discussion in the War Cabinet and of discussion with theJoint Consultative Committee.(b) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air (W.P.(44) 605).Points in discussion:  (i) The Minister of Labour and National Service drew attention to the modification made to paragraph 19 of the revised draft White Paper in order to ensure that experienced workersreturned to their former industries at the earliest possible momentso as to get factories ready for peace-time production.(ii) The Minister of Labour and National Service said that hehad originally proposed to give their discharge to women over 45and men over 60. The women&apos;s organisations had been opposedto any such differentiation between men and women. They were reluctant to see a statement in a State document which might be interpreted as meaning that women were too old at 45. To meet this, he now proposed to substitute 60 as the age at which women should be discharged without the authority of a National ServiceOfficer. At the same time, women over 45 who wished to be discharged, and who could be spared, would be released throughthe formal act of the National Service Officer.(iii) The Chancellor of the Exchequer was uneasy at thesuggestion that 45 should be chosen as the age for the discharge ofwomen who did not wish to serve on and who could be spared, since this might react on non-industrial women in clerical employment,In order to.avoid sudden losses of trained staff by public depart-ments, he would much have preferred 50.The Secretary of State for Air said that women in the services would be held until 50, while under the proposals in the white paper civilian women, working in the same office, would be eligiblefor release at 45. The Minister of Labour and National Serviceagreed, in the light of the discussion, to substitute 50 for 45 inhis proposed amendments to paragraphs 16 (2) and 29 of the draft white Paper.(iv) The Secretary of State for Air suggested that para-graphs 18 to 20 of the revised White Paper might be construed as
EconomicControlsin theTransitionPeriod.(previous reference:W.M (44) 125thConclusions,Minute 2.)5. At their meeting on the 22nd September the War cabinet had invited the Minister of Reconstruction, after consultation withthe other Ministers concerned, to submit to them proposals aboutthe continuance of economic controls in the transition period, inorder that a Government announcement on this subject might bemade simultaneously with the publication of the White Paper onthe Reallocation of Man-Power between Civilian Employments.The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Reconstruction (W.P. (44) 604), to which was appendeda draft statement prepared by the Reconstruction Committee&apos;s Sub-Committee on Industrial Problems. The Ministers concernedrecommended that the proposed statement should be made in replyto a Parliamentary Question and should precede the publication ofthe White Paper on the Reallocation of Man-Power betweenCivilian Employments.Discussion centred mainly on paragraphs 5 and 6 of the .draft statement. It was urged, on the one hand, that these paragraphswere open to criticism on the ground that they suggested that itwas the intention of the Government to maintain the controls foran indefinite period in the future. In fact, there were alreadysome industries in which the removal of the controls would bejustified, since there were already surpluses of their products. Itwould be preferable not to make any statement on the subject of controls unless more definite promises of their removal could begiven and unless the Government could state that immediate action was being taken to remove some of them.On the other hand, some Ministers felt difficulty in acceptingparagraph 6 of the draft statement, since it implied that so soonas there was a balance of supply and demand in any field thecontrol would be relinquished. In their view, there might be other considerations which would justify the continuance of the controlapplying only to young men who were redundant in their presentemployment. He suggested that a footnote might be added to makethe position clear. The Minister of Labour and National Serviceundertook to consider the point.(v) The First Lord of the Admiralty suggested the amendmentof the last two lines of paragraph 17 of the draft White Paper to read &quot; unless in such cases there are strong production reasons tothe contrary.&quot;   This was agreed.(vi) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that a very heavy burden seemed likely to fall on the staff of the labour exchanges inconnection with these individual reallocations. The Minister ofLabour and National Service said that, while the strain was heavy,he thought it could be borne.(vii) The Minister of Fuel and Power asked whether thescheme of balloting for service in the mines would come to an endwith the end of the war in Europe and whether such action wouldbe taken administratively or by a formal announcement. TheMinister of Labour and National Service said that he did not feelthat public opinion or Parliament would favour the continuanceof the ballot system of recruitment for the mines once the war withGermany was over, though he anticipated full support for thecontinued calling up of men for service with the Armed forces, inorder to release men discharged from the forces. He would prefer to postpone any decision as to the method by which the scheme should come to an end until nearer the time. Men who had alreadybeen directed to the pits by ballot would be released on the same basis as those who had been serving in the Forces.The War Cabinet-Approved the draft White Paper appended to W.P. (44)583 subject to the amendments at &quot;X&quot; and &quot; Y &quot;; and agreed to its presentation to Parliament at an early date.
even after this situation had been reached. Moreover, the sameMinisters could not accept the proposition, which seemed implicit in paragraph 6, that the ultimate aim was a return to the pre-warcondition of laissez-faire. It was also urged that a White paper should be produced (i) recording the work of the war-time economic controls, and (ii) stating the Government view about such controlsduring the transition period.The following other points were made in discussion :  (i) The process of reconversion from wartime to peacetimeindustry involved the transfer of workers from highly paid work on munitions to less well paid civilian jobs. It would be impossible touse the labour controls for this purpose unless the workers could be assured that the economic controls were being continued in order tosecure to them a fair share of the necessities of life and of anyimprovements in the standard of domestic comfort which it mightbe possible to make. The question whether a particular control could be removed did not depend entirely on whether there was a surplus Of the products of the industry concerned. The unloading ofsurpluses on the market would lead to confusion; employers and workers alike were concerned to see the maintenance of economic controls for as long as necessary to secure an orderly change-over from wartime to peacetime production and stability in the yearimmediately after the war. The type of control appropriate in caseswhere there was a surplus was, of course, different from that suitablewhere the difficulty arose from a shortage of supplies.(ii) It was suggested that the words &apos;&apos; where necessary &apos;&apos; or&quot; so long as they are required &quot; should be inserted in the first sentence of paragraph 5 of the draft statement. If this were done,paragraph 6 might be omitted.(iii) It was suggested that the continuance of the wartimeeconomic controls during the Transition Period ought not to beregarded as in any sense a step towards the nationalisation ofindustry. The controls had been imposed for the purposes of the warand, if we were to avoid industrial depression on the scale of thatwhich followed the last war, the controls would continue to berequired to meet the difficult conditions during the transition from war to peace, whether that transition was to a more socialised state or to the system of private enterprise which prevailed before the war.Summing up the discussion the Prime Minister said that thestatement should be confined strictly to the intentions of the Govern-ment for the period up to the end of the Japanese war, during whichthere was no doubt that the controls would have to remain. If thestatement were so restricted, it would be in line with the proposals in the White Paper on the Reallocation of Man-Power betweenCivilian Employments.A statement of the length of that appended to W.P. (44) 604was liable to misunderstanding and it would be better to make a shorter statement on the lines proposed in the course of the debate onthe reallocation of man-power. The statement would make it clearthat there would be some relaxation of the economic controls, but thatthe process would be carried out in an orderly fashion and byorganised steps, and that in every case the governing consideration would be the public interest.The War Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Labour and National Service andthe Minister of Supply to prepare and submit to the WarCabinet a statement on the lines indicated at &quot; Z &quot; above,which the Minister of Labour and National Service might make in the course of the forthcoming debate on thereallocation of man-power.
CivilService.Recruitmentduring theRecon-structionPeriod.(previous reference:W.M,(44)20thConclusions,Minute 7.)6. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (44) 598) about recruitment tothe Civil Service during the reconstruction period.To the memorandum was attached &apos;(a) a Whitley Council report, which it was proposed to publishas a White Paper;(&amp;) a proposed preface to the above report, to be included in theWhite Paper;(c) a draft Parliamentary Question and Answer announcing theWhite Paper.The Chancellor of the Exchequer^ memorandum explained thatit was proposed that recruitment to the established Civil service should be resumed as soon as possible after the end of the german war, and that substantial proportions of the vacancies should be reserved for ex-Service candidates, subject to the attainment ofthe appropriate qualifying standard in the ReconstructionExamination.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said,that, from the point ofview of public presentation, the crux of the problem lay in the handling of the ex-Service question. The complete reservation to ex-Service candidates of appointments to the clerical and other classes after the last war had had a serious effect on efficiency.Moreover, such a. reservation would be unfair to the rest of thecommunity, who had clone their duty in other forms of nationalservice during the war.In discussion, very general agreement was expressed with theproposals in the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s memorandum. Butit was suggested that it was of the utmost importance that the scheme should be so presented as to make clear to Parliament and the public the extent of the treatment proposed for ex-Service candidates.This was all the more important since in certain quarters demands were likely to be voiced for complete ex-Service reservation of appointment to certain classes.After further discussion, the War Cabinet *(1) Approved in principle the proposals in the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer &apos;s memorandum and the Whitley council report appended thereto.(2) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer proposed toreceive a deputation of Members of Parliament in thenear future on the recruitment to the Civil service during the Reconstruction Period.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to give furtherconsideration to the question of how the measure of ex-Service reservation proposed would best be presented,and to report again to the War Cabinet after he hadreceived the deputation.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1;2nd November, 1944.*




</content>
</cab>
