<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 33-34</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIE. BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET.CP.106(30) .COPY NO3S.CABINETTHE ECONOMIC CONSEQUENCES OF DISARMENT.     copy of a letter from the Secretary to the JointDisarmament Committee, oF*&quot;&quot;the Parliamentary Labour Partythe General Gouge ll&quot;c7f the Trades Union Congress and theExecutive Committee of the National Labour Party, to the present ime - M in&quot;i s t e r.Reference EPH/NVj/469         Re search JTThe Trades Union Congress General Council,   Transport House (South Block),          Sm i t h Square,              London, S . W . 1.            17th March, 1930.Dear Sir,          Acting upon your suggestion, my Committee has hada preliminary discussion of the proposals outlined in itsMemorandum with the Rt.Hon. A.V. Alexander, M.P., First Lordof the Admiralty, and other members of the Government.       Mr.GovernmentAlexander indicated the tenour of the Report ofCommittee set up to examine the Memorandum, butmade it clear thatupon these mattersno Cabinet decisions had yet been made          The Committee has since discussed the matters arising out of this interview and I have to Inform you ofthe grave dissatisfaction expressed by the Committee at theReport of the Government Committee as outlined byMr. A.V. Alexander.          I have again to emphasise the very strong opinionof the Disarmament Committee that Trade Facilities, undersuitable safeguards, are essential to the Shipbuilding and engineering industries .          Regarding the administration of Export credit facilities, it is gathered from Ministerial statements inthe Commons that the Government is strongly influenced bythe advice of the Advisory Committee.  It would&apos; appear,however, that the present Committee is prejudiced against
Russian trade since it refuses to advise credits forlonger periods than twelve months for this trade whilegranting them up to five years for other trades.  It isthe opinion of my;Committee that the present Advisory    ,   committee I urgently needs reconstruction and that provision should be made for the representation ofindustrial interests upon it.          My Committee is still very anxious to meetyourself at the earliest opportunity, but realises the abnormal demand upon your time at present.  I am, there-fore, authorised to inform you that if it is not possiblefor you to meet the Committee in the near future, theywould be glad if you could arrange for them to meet theMinisters concerned in the proposals that have beensubmitted.  We assume that other Departments have theMemorandum under consideration in addition to the admiralty and the Board of Trade.                 Yours, etc.,  (Signed)  E.P. HARRIES *SECRETARY, DISARMAMENT COMMITTEE.

</content>
</cab>
