<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 94-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BBiTANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.                    Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1930.SECRET.                                                    Copy No.   36CP. 108  (30).                                CABINET.PALESTINE:  HIGH  COMMISSIONERS  VIEWS  ON  POLICY.         MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY  OF  STATE FOR THE COLONIES.    I CIRCULATE for the information of  my colleagues a despatch from Sir JohnChancellor on the  situation  in Palestine.   The despatch was  written before the findings of  the  Shaw Commission were known.   I am circulating a  separate memorandum dealing with the Commission^ Report and the situation arising outof it.P.Colonial Office, March 27, 1930.    The Right Honourable Lord Passfield, P.C.,        His Majesty&apos;.s Principal Secretary            of State for the Colonies.(Confidential.)My Lord,                                                   January 17, 1930.    I HAVE the honour to submit for your Lordship &apos;s consideration my views asto the causes which led to the recent outbreaks in Palestine, and my recommendations as to the measures necessary to prevent their recurrence.    2.  The principal immediate cause of the disturbances was undoubtedly thedispute between Jews and Moslems concerning their rights and claims at the Westernor Wailing Wall.    The Western Wall dispute was,  however, only a secondary issue,  and, until ithas been considered in relation to the  situation as a whole, its importance as a causeof the bitter hostility of the Arabs towards the Jews which the recent outbreaks haverevealed, may be over-estimated.    3.  In order to explain the situation in Palestine it is necessary to examine theWestern or Wailing Wall question in  detail, and the history of the relations betweenthe Arabs and the Jews and the Mandatory since 1915.    The dispute concerning the rights and claims at the Wailing Wall  is dealt within detail in the enclosed Memorandum^ and I shall in this despatch  refer only tosome of its more important points.    The main features of the relations of  the Arabs, the Jews and the Mandatoryin Palestine during the last ten years are described in the following paragraphs.    4.  The first event of importance  in the relations between His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment  and  the Arab  peoples generally,  was the  correspondence in 1915 betweenSheriff Hussein of Mecca and Sir Henry McMahon,  His  Majesty&apos;s High Com-missioner for Egypt.   That correspondence, known  as the  McMahon letters, hasnot been published in whole.    That part of the  correspondence which has been made  public  makes it known that His Majesty&apos;s Government promised Sheriff Hussein of Mecca  that they would recognise and support the independence of the Arab peoples then under Ottomanrule, subject to the exclusion of certain geographical areas, on condition that theyrevolted against the Turks.    It will be seen from letters Nos. 5, 6 and 8  in  Command Paper  1700, 1922, thatthe excluded areas were not definitely  described.                                 *  Enclosure I.      [20835]                                                        B
    When the Arab leaders of Palestine became aware of the correspondence they believed  that in  the  context  the  intention of His  Majesty.&apos;s Government was to exclude from the  pledge only that part of Syria in regard to which the interests ofFrance had long been recognised.    In  the light  of subsequent events (particularly the  Balfour Declaration) theArabs now believe that His Majesty&apos;s Government illegitimately made use of thatindefiniteness of description to evade the fulfilment of pledges previously made tothem, and to impose upon Palestine the  mandatory system of government, togetherwith its essential feature, the policy of establishing a Jewish National Home in theircountry.    5.  The  next event of importance was the Balfour  Declaration of  November1917.  In that Declaration His Majesty&apos;s Government stated that &quot; they were infavour of the establishment in Palestine of a national home for  the Jewish people,it being clearly understood that nothing should be done which might prejudice thecivil and  religious rights  of  existing non-Jewish  communities in Palestine, or therights and political status enjoyed by Jews in any other country.&quot;    By Christmas 1917 the southern half of Palestine was in British occupation,and&apos; the inhabitants  speedily  learned  the  character of  that Declaration.   they received it with incredulity.    6.  In 1918 the commander-in-Chief of the Allied Forces in Palestine and Syriaissued what is known as the Anglo-French Declaration.  That Declaration reads asfollows :          &quot; Le but qu&apos;envisagent la France et la Grande-Bretagne en poursuivant en    Orient la guerre dechainee par 1&apos;ambition allemande, c&apos;est raflranchissement    complet  et  definitif  des  peuples  si  longtemps opprimes  par les  Turcs et    1&apos;etablissement de  Gouvernements et administrations nationaux puisant leur    autorite  dans 1&apos;initiative et le  libre choix des  populations indigenes.    Pour    donner suite  a ces intentions la France et la Grande-Bretagne sont d&apos;accord    pour  encourager  et aider a 1&apos;etablissement en Syrie  et Mesopotamie, actuelle-    ment liberees par  les Allies, et dans  les territoires dont  its poursuivent la -   liberation et pour&apos;reconnaitre ceux-ci aussitot  qu&apos;ils seront effectivement etablis.    Loin  de vouloir imposer  aux populations  de ces regions telles ou telles institu-    tions, elles n&apos;ont d&apos;autre souci que d&apos;assurer, par leur appui et par une assistance  .  efficace, le fonctionnement normal des Gouvernements et administrations qu&apos;elles    se seront librement donnees,  assurer une justice  impartiale et egale  pour tous,    faciliter le developpement economique du pays en suscitant et en encourageant    les  initiatives locales, favoriser la  diffusion  de 1&apos;instruction,  mettre fin aux    divisions trop longtemps exploiters par la politique turque tel est le role que    les  deux  Gouvernements  allies  revendiquent  dans  les  territoires liberees.    7 Novembre 1918.&quot;    While the Commander-in-Chiefs Declaration, which was given wide publicity,made no specific mention of Palestine, it is a fact that the northern half of palestine was at that time included in the Vilayet of Beirut; and  the Arabs of Palestinebelieved either that Palestine was included in the scope of the declaration or, if that were not  so, that the  reason  for its exclusion was to be found  in  the  balfour declaration.    7.  In 1919  the  Principal  Allied  and  the  Associated Powers adopted theCovenant of the League of Nations, Article XXII of which definitely assigned thestatus-of tutelage to certain territories detached from the enemy on the conclusion ofpeace.    It was stated in that Article  that &quot;certain communities  formerly belonging tothe Turkish  Empire  have reached  a  stage of  development where their existenceas independent nations can be provisionally recognised subject to the rendering of administrative  advice and assistance by a Mandatory until such time as they are able to stand alone.&quot;    &quot; The wishes of these communities must be a principalconsideration in the selection of the Mandatory.&quot;    8.  The  announcement  of the application  to their country of the  mandatorysystem was received by the Arabs of Palestine with consternation.    In  1919 the Allies contemplated&apos; sending  an Inter-Allied commission, in  whichthe United States was to  participate,  to the Middle  East in order to ascertain thewishes of the peoples in so far as the selection of the Mandatories was concerned!
                                      S    No Inter-Allied Commission  was set up.  The President of the  United States,however, sent a Commission appointed by himself, the members of which travelledthrough Palestine and Syria and took evidence from individuals in  various places.    Their report was not made public by the Government of the United States.    It is claimed by the  Arabs that the Allies  did not attempt to ascertain thewishes of the communities formerly belonging to  the Turkish Empire as laid downin Article XXII of the Covenant, and that, therefore, the wishes of those peopleswere not a principal consideration in  the selection of the Mandatory.    9.  In 1918 a Zionist commission with  liaison with the Commander-in-Chiefwas established in Palestine, and its presence was a source of irritation to the Arabinhabitants of the country.    10.  In 1920  the country became  disturbed:  Arab national  sentiment wasaroused by the establishment of King Feisul in  Damascus  and at the pilgrimageseason a serious anti-Jewish outbreak occurred in Jerusalem.    After these riots a Military Commission of  Inquiry under the Presidency of major-General P. C. Pelinwas appointed in Palestine to investigate the disturbances.    That Commission submitted a Report  to the Commander-in-Chief,  but theReport was never made public.    11.  During the  period  1918-1920 Arab incredulity Avith  regard to  balfour declaration  was changed  into hostility; and, Avhatever may have been the causes of the Arab riots in Jerusalem in March 1920,  those riots  gave expression to theArab  feelings of hatred for the Zionist policy.    In April 1920, shortly after the outbreak of the riots in Jerusalem, the principal allied Powers represented at San Remo  conferred the Mandate for Palestine on great  Britain, and  at the  same  time  endorsed the policy of Great  Britain  as expressed in the Balfour Declaration.    12.  In July, 1920, His  Majesty&apos;s Government appointed Sir Herbert Samuelto be  High Commissioner  for Palestine, and he initiated the Civil Administrationof the country.    It should  be observed that the Treaty  of Sevres contained a renunciation ofPalestine by Turkey; but that Treaty  was never ratified by Turkey.    13.  Between the  beginning  of  1915 and July  1920 therefore the principal features of the history of Palestine were :       (i)  In 1915 a pledge was  given  by His Majesty&apos;s Government  to support the          independence of the Arab peoples, the terms of which were not free  from          ambiguity.  (See paragraph 4 above.)              (Palestine  was not then occupied by the Allies and  was still  part          of  the  Turkish  Empire,  the northern part of Palestine  being  then          included in the Vilayet of Beirut and Jerusalem being a separate sanjak.)    (ii)  On the 2nd November, 1917, the Balfour  Declaration was made, giving the          Jews a special status in Palestine.  (See paragraph 5 above.)              (Palestine  was not then occupied by  the Allies and  was still  part          of the Turkish Empire.)    (iii)  In  November 1918 the Anglo-French Declaration was made  encouraging          the aspirations of the Arab peoples for &quot; national governments&quot; in Syria          and Mesopotamia.  (See paragraph 6  above.)              (Palestine  was then occupied by the  Allies, but was not detached          from the Turkish Empire.)    (iv) In 1919 the Covenant of the  League of Nations was signed. Article XXII          of which gave a certain status to communities formerly of  the Turkish          Empire.  (See paragraph 7 above.)              (Palestine  wasthen occupied by the  Allies, but was not detached          from the Turkish Empire.)    (v) In April 1920 the Balfour Declaration was endorsed by the  Allied Powers          at San Remo and  the Mandate for Palestine was conferred upon Great          Britain under Article XXII of the Covenant.              (Palestine  was then occupied by the  Allies,  but was not detached          from the Turkish  Empire.)
     14.   In the year 1920 nominated representatives of the people were introduced into an Advisory Council, whom the High Commissioner was bound to consult before exercising his legislative powers.     An important step towards ensuring Moslem control over purely Islamic affairs was taken  in 1921, when a  Supreme  Moslem  Shari&apos;a  Council, elected  by adult Moslems,  was constituted for the control and management of the Moslem Aicqaf (Pious Foundations) and the affairs of.the Shari&apos;a (Religious Law).     Daring the same period the Zionist Organisation (i.e., the Palestine Agency of the  Zionist Organisation in  London) pursued  a vigorous policy that led to the immigration on a considerable scale of Jews from Eastern Europe.     15.   In the spring of 1921. anti-Jewish disturbances  again  broke out at Jaffa, where  the  immigrants are  usually  disembarked, and  attacks  were made  on neighbouring  Jewish  Colonies.   A  Commission of  Inquiry   was  appointed  by Sir Herbert Samuel to inquire into and report upon the disturbances.     The Report of that Commission was published in  Command Paper 1540, 1921.     16.   In October  1921  the Council of the League of Nations authorised  His Majesty&apos;s Government  to administer Palestine in the  spirit of  the  draft mandate which by  then had been public for some months.  Before the Mandate  could enter into force it was necessary that its terms should be approved by the Council of the League of Nations.  In virtue, however, of the  authority given  by  the Council of the  League of Nations to His Majesty&apos;s  Government, Palestine was, from that date, administered in the  spirit of the draft mandate.     17.   In July. 1922 the terms of the  Palestine Mandate were formally approved by the Council of the League of  Nations.  The mandate came  into full effect in September 1923,  following a notification to that effect addressed to His Majesty\s Government by the Secretary-General of the League of Nations.     In July 1923 the Treaty of Lausanne was signed, and ratified in August 1924.     By that Treaty Turkey  effectively renounced Palestine.     18.   In October 192]  the Moslem Christian Association, founded in 1918, sent a delegation to London, which entered into discussion with the  Secretary of State (Mr.  Winston  Churchill) as  regards the  draft Order-in-Council  that had  been prepared  with the  object of giving a constitution to  Palestine.  The  purport of those discussions is given in  Command Paper 1700 of 1922.     The Arab Delegation adopted an attitude of uncompromising hostility to any constitution under  which the development of a Jewish  National Home; howeverconceived, would be possible.     These  discussions  led  to  the  definition  of  the policy  of  His  Majesty&apos;s Government in  Palestine.   (See  &quot; Statement  of  British  Policy   in  Palestine.&quot;Enclosure in No. 5 of Command Paper 1700 of 1922.)  This definition of policy was formally accepted by the Zionist Organisation; but it was not accepted by the Arabs because it would have implied acceptance of. the policy of the Jewish National Home.     19.   The Palestine Order-in-Council of the 10th August, 1922, which provided for the establishment  of  an elected Legislative  Council, came  into effect  on the 1st September, 1922.     Elections for the Legislative Council were held in the first half of  1923.  the majority  of the Arab population abstained from the polls and so confirmed the attitude of  uncompromising hostility to the constitution that had  been taken by the Moslem-Christian Delegation in London.  (See Command Paper  1889, 1923.)     20.   In May 1925  the Palestine (Amendment) Order-in-Council was made, by which the elections were declared null and void, and legislative power was vested in the  High Commissioner,  who was empowered  to promulgate ordinances afterconsultation with an Advisory Council.     The  Palestine  Government attempted  to reconstitute  the  Advisory Council,consisting of official and nominated unofficial members, of the same  composition asthe rejected Legislative Council. These attempts were unsuccessful, inasmuch as the unofficial members, while, at  first, accepting the invitations sent to them, were, in theend, prevailed upon by public opinion not to sit in the Council.     The Advisory Council has since then consisted solely of official  members.     21.   A further attempt  to overcome  Arab  opposition to  the  policy  of  His Majesty&apos;s Government  was.made in 1923, when the  offer to recognise an Arab Agency, similar to the Jewish Agency, was made.
    That offer was rejected;  the Arabs argued that they required no agency torepresent them in their own country, and that their acceptance would have impliedrecognition of the Jewish Agency.  (See Command Paper  1889, 1923.)    Since then no further attempts have been made by His Majesty&apos;s Governmentto invite the Arabs to co-operate in the government of the country.    22.   In 1926, however, certain Arab notables expressed a desire to enter intoformal discussions with the Palestine Government as to the possibility of finding abasis for the establishment of representative government; and certain proposals were submitted by them to Lord Plumer.  In view of the fact that he was then about toset up elected municipal councils, Lord Plumer decided that no further steps towardsestablishing representative government should  be taken until experience had been gained of the manner in which municipal electors exercised  their  responsibilities andin which elected councillors performed their duties in local administration.    23.   Shortly after my arrival in Palestine at the end of  1928, the Arab Executivesubmitted to  me a request that some form of representative  Government should beestablished in Palestine.  I informed the Executive that I  would consider their request.    Confidential conversations on the subject were conducted with certain of  theArab political leaders by  the Chief Secretary during May 1929, which  resulted inthe Arab leaders agreeing to co-operate in the  working of a nominated  LegislativeCouncil with an unofficial majority and with the powers intended to be given to theabortive Legislative Council of 1922.    Proposals for the establishment of such a Legislative Council were submitted tothe Secretary of State for the Colonies in my Secret Despatch of the 12th  June, 1929!    In that despatch  I expressed the opinion that it would  be difficult to resist much longer the demand for the conversion of the present Advisory Council into some formof Legislative  body  with a view to associating  the people  of  Palestine  with  theadministration of the country, especially in view of  the fact that the demands of theArab community for representative institutions had become more insistent since theestablishment of representative Government in the politically less-advanced territory of Trans-Jordan.    These proposals were still under consideration at the  time  of  the outbreaks inAugust.    24.  It will have been seen from the preceding paragraphs  that  the  formalefforts made to secure the co-operation of the people of Palestine in the governmentof the country have been rejected by the Arabs on the ground that they were designedto give effect to a policy to which they were bitterly opposed.    The present position is       (i) that the Arabs have not accepted the Palestine  Mandate, on  the  ground          that it gives direct government to the mandatory  and thus goes  beyond          the  terms of Article XXII  of the Covenant  as applied &apos;&apos; to  certain          communities formerly belonging to the Turkish Empire &apos;&apos;;     (ii) that, the Arabs believe that direct government was introduced  by  the          Mandatory Power because without it the policy of the Balfour Declara-          tion could not be fulfilled;    (iii) that the Arabs have not accepted the Balfour Declaration or the definition          of British Policy in Palestine stated in Command Paper 1700, 1922;     (iv) that the Arabs have objected  to Articles 4, 6 and  11 of the Mandate on the          grounds  that  their  provisions do,  in  operation,  lead  to preferential          treatment for  the Jews in regard to the establishment and development          of the Jewish National Home, and  do  therefore, &quot;prejudice the civil          rights &quot; of the existing inhabitants.  And thence they consider that these          Articles are in conflict with the second half of  the Balfour Declaration.    25.  Despite the failure to gain Arab co-operation in the government of  thecountry, the Administration set up by the Mandatory has in some measure succeeded in promoting the development of the material resources of Palestine to the well-being of the population as  a whole.   The Government has given the  country a railway system,  good roads, agricultural and veterinary services, an efficient public  health.service, modern postal and telephone facilities, and opportunities for employment on public works.  A system  of public education, in which instruction is given  in thevernacular tongue, has been created.   Local  government, elective in character,  hasbeen developed.                                                              -
     The British officials generally have established relations of mutual confidencewith the inhabitants of the country with whom they work.     But the Central Government has had few opportunities of establishing contact with the leaders of Arab  opinion.  This lack of contact has been productive  ofmisgiving in regard to legislation. Any acts of the Government which appeared tobe ambiguous or partisan in spirit became at once the cause of suspicion and distrust.That distrust could only be dissipated through intimate contact between Arabs andthe Government; such contact could not  be made unless the Arabs had participationthrough some representative means in the acts done or contemplated by the centralauthority.     26.  The Arab peoples have never forgotten their pride of race and empire, andthe sentiment of Arab  nationalism, which was growing before the &quot;War, was greatlystimulated by the propaganda of the Allies during the War.   Since the War thatmovement has continued to gather momentum.     During the last seven  years the  Arabs have witnessed the development of Iraqunder the principles of Article  XXII of the Covenant of the League of Nations,and they have  seen that, within a  measurable time, Iraq may achieve complete independence.  They have also seen the  establishment of representative governmentin Trans-Jordan.     The Arabs of  Palestine  remember  that the Arab populations of Iraq, Trans-Jordan and Syria were formerly parts of the Turkish Empire like themselves; andthey also remember that in Command Paper 1700 of 1922 it was stated that it was because His Majesty&apos;s  Government were bound by a pledge given before the date atwhich the Covenant of the League of Nations was signed that they were not treated in the same way as &quot; their neighbours in Iraq and Syria.&quot;    27.  During the years 1923-29 the  Arabs of Palestine have seen the movement for the establishment of the Jewish National Home in Palestine develop.    The progress of the works under the monopoly.granted to Mr. Rutenberg  for developing hydro-electric power  from the Jordan was evidence that an  important part of the natural resources of  the  country had been granted  to Jewish interests,although many of the Arabs have recognised the value to the country as a whole ofthe objects  to be achieved by the  concession.    They have seen the grant of a concession for the development of  the mineral resources of the Dead Sea to Mr. Novemeysky, a Jew, and Major Tulloch, a british officer, and  they fear that the  development of a potentially valuable natural resourceOf the country has passed into Jewish control without consideration  of  Arab&quot;interests.    Furthermore, Arabs have seen from the Press that Jewish bodies  have  madeinsistent demands upon the Government, laying stress on the obligations imposedupon the Mandatory by the Palestine Mandate in regard to the establishment of theJewish National Home.    Facts such as these have had the effect of making Arabs fear that the economicand  political control of Palestine will  pass into  Jewish hands.  They fear thatJewish domination in Palestine is possible, even although the Jews in Palestine maynot be in a majority.    28.  The mass immigration of Jews during the years 1924, 1925 and 1926  ledto grievous unemployment in Palestine.   . But  since, throughout the period 1926-28,  the revenue  has been directly  or indirectly increased as a result of  the  influx of Jewish capital and  by Jewishimmigation  and enterprise, it was possible for the Government to make financial provision for  relief  measures on a considerable scale by anticipating the normalprogramme of Extraordinary Public  Works.    In the case of many of these relief measures, the Arabs saw only that publicworks were being executed  solely by Jewish labour although paid for from Govern-ment funds; but they failed to realise that Jewish capital spent in the country hadsubstantially augmented the revenue, and had helped to make such works possible without increasing the burden upon the taxpayer.    The immigration of Jews from  Eastern Europe has made the Arabs acutelyconscious of the presence among them of an alien population, which is, nevertheless,in Palestine not on sufferance but as of right; and  the Jewish  authorities and  theJewish press publicly make demands for Jewish immigration on a large scale andfor grants of State lands for  settlement  by Jewish immigrants.
     The Jewish Press has not been backward in criticising adversely the Adminis- tration, complaining of its inertia in regard to matters in which Jews consider that they have a right to expect active support.     These social and political factors have-kept alive the hostility of  the Arabs to Zionist Jews.    29.  Suspicion and distrust of  the policy of the Government have been, and continue to be, the distinguishing features of the Arab political movement, and, as a consequence of Zionism, latent hostility has been the distinguishing feature of the relations between Arabs and Jews.     The apparent growth of  mutual toleration during the years 1923 to 1928 was , not real.     30.  That there had been no manifestations of that latent hostility in recent years may  be attributed in a large measure to the severe  economic depression from which the Jewish National Home movement in Palestine suffered during the years following upon the mass immigration  of 1924-1926.    During the year  1927 and  the  first  part of 1928  Jewish immigration was suspended, and many Jewish  immigrants left the country permanently.    The Arabs saw that the economic depression which followed the  Jewish mass immigration in the years 1924-1926  had checked  the  progress of Zionism  in Palestine.  They were also aware that the flow of Jewish capital into the country for Jewish enterprises was abating.    They therefore believed that the Zionist movement was  waning and that they had no longer reason to fear  Jewish domination.. They believed that Zionism had ceased to be a danger.    31.  During the year 1928, however, the movement for broadening the basis of the Jewish Agency by  admitting to it non-Zionist Jews, including American Jews who contribute the greater part of the funds for the establishment of the Jewish National Home, revived the fears of the Arabs.    The proceedings of the Jewish World Congress at Zurich in July 1929,  when the agreement between the Zionist and non-Zionist  Jews was ratified, served  to confirm those fears.    The speeches made by some of the  Jewish  leaders at Zurich,  the  Resolutions adopted at the Zionist  Congress, and the combination of virtually the  whole of  the Jews of the world, with their large financial resources, to  further the movement  for the establishment of the Jewish National Home in Palestine caused the Arabs to realise that Zionism still threatened their interests, as they saw them, and that to continue their apparent acquiescence  in the Zionist policy would endanger  the fulfilment of Arab national aspirations.    32.  In its religious aspect, the Wailing Wall dispute aroused  the excitement of the Moslems; but, because their antagonists were Jews,  the  dispute became a political issue, on which Moslem Arabs were able to enlist the  sympathy and support of the Christian Arabs.    After the incidents at the Wailing  Wall on the  15th and 16th August,  1929, rumours of the designs of the  Jews on the Wailing Wall and the Haram-el-Sherif spread through the country.  These rumours were &quot;readily believed by the credulous among the  Moslem Arabs, who were thereby roused to a  state of religious frenzy,which culminated in acts of violence.    Viewed in its relation to  these circumstances, the dispute about rights at the Wailing Wall became much more than a question of the rival claims of two religiouscommunities.    33.  The details of the Wailing Wall dispute are given  in Enclosure I to this despatch, but the main facts may be summarised as follows :      (i) The whole property  is Moslem pious  foundation (Waqf).     (ii) The Moslems  have the rights  of ownership, and claim tnat  these rights           are limited only by a servitude of a public right of access to the Wall.    (iii) The Jews  claim the&apos;right to conduct public worship at  the  Wall.    (iv) The Jews have, since the British Occupation, sought from time to time           to insist upon  the congregational character of  their  practices at the           Wall.     (v) The, Moslems have  continuously  protested  against all  practices which           they regarded as Jewish innovations.
                                      s    (vi)  The acts of the Government in  checking  Jewish innovations have been           deemed by Jews to be deliberate humiliations to Jewish prestige, as well           as improper denials of their rights.    (vii)  In 1925 the Zionist Organisation and the National Council of the Jewish           Community in  Palestine submitted memoranda requesting that their           rights at the Wall should be safeguarded.   These  memoranda were           regarded by the Arabs with suspicion.   The Local Jewish Press openly           demanded theexpropriation of the property in the interests of  Jews.   (viii)  Command Paper No. 3229 of 1928  informed both Jews and Arabs that           &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government  regard it  as their duty, and it  is their           intention,  to  maintain  the established  Jewish right to access to  the           pavement in front of the Wall for the purposes of their devotions, and           also their right to bring to the Wall those appurtenances that they were           allowed to take to the Wall under the Turkish regime.&quot;     (ix)  In regard to appurtenances, the Moslems interpret &quot; were allowed to take &quot;           to mean &quot; were  officially authorised to take.&quot;     (x)  The Jews interpret &quot;were allowed  to take&quot; to mean &quot;actually took,&quot; or           &apos;&quot;&apos; were not prevented from taking.&quot;     (xi)   In  1926 the Moslems made Structural alterations in the area adjacent to           the Wailing Wall.    (xii)  In the  light of  advice received from His Majesty&apos;s  Government,  the           Palestine Government decided that they could not order the Moslems to           discontinue the new constructions on Moslem property near the Wall, on           condition that the worship of Jews was  not interfered with.   (xiii)  In not forbidding these new constructions, Government were believed by           the Jews to be partisan in favour of the Arabs.   (xiv)  In Arab opinion,  the situation  was aggravated by the delay in putting           into effect the principles of Command Paper  3229, 1928.    34.  An  important factor in the Wailing Wall  dispute  was the position inwhich the Government was placed.    In virtue of the provisions of Article 14 of the Mandate, the Government do not possess the power to determine legal rights at the Wall.   The only powers possessed by the Government in that ai^ea are those  inherent in  all Governments in virtue oftheir obligation to maintain public order.    If Government did nothing  in regard to the Wall, both Arabs  and Jews  hadground for complaint.    If Government did  anything at all,  they laid themselves open to charges ofpartisanship, and their acts in regulating practices  at  the Wall,  except  for  thepurpose of maintaining public order, had, and have, no legal  sanction.    35.  The conclusions appear to be that     (1) The Arab hostility to Zionism has existed since 1918.    (2) The immediate causes of the disturbances in August 1929 are to be found           in            (a) the Balfour Declaration;           (b) the growth of Arab nationalism;           (c) an interpretation by the Arabs of the  McMahon pledge of 1915 which                 is not admitted by His Majesty&apos;s Government;           (d) an interpretation by the Arabs of the  Anglo-French Declaration of                  1918 which was not intended by His Majesty&apos;s Government;           (e) the belief of the Arabs that the Mandate for Palestine is inconsistent                 with Article XXII of the Covenant of the League of Nations;           (/) the belief of the Arabs that Articles 4, 6 and 11 of the Mandate have                  been so  designed as to enable the Mandatory to  justify acts which,                  if it had not been  for those Articles, would be in conflict with the                  second half of the Balfour Declaration.     (3) The hostility of the Arabs to Zionism found opportunity for expression in           the  Wailing  Wall  dispute,  primarily religious in character, in which           Arab and Jew regarded the Government as the partisan of the other.     36.   I now turn to the consideration of the measures to be  taken to prevent are currence of the recent disturbances.
    37,   It has been explained in the earlier paragraphs of this despatch that the belief is general among the Arabs of Palestine that the promises  of  freedom and self-government, which they maintain were made to them by Great  Britain and theAllies, have been broken in order that the movement for the establishment  of theJewish National Home in Palestine might be promoted.    The distrust that has been engendered by  that belief has now become general.It has embittered our relations with the Arabs in our Mandated  territories, and hasgained for the people  of Palestine the sympathies  of  the Arabs  in neighbouringterritories in their efforts to obtain self-government.    The  feeling of antagonism towards the policy  of  Great  Britain in Palestinehas now become so deep and so general that it is almost certain  that any repetition of the outbreaks  in Palestine would be actively supported by incursions of Arabsfrom the neighbouring territories.    38.   Although owing to the policy pursued in  Palestine during the past tenyears doubts, which are freely expressed, have been raised in the  minds of the Arabsas to our good faith, they still have a profound belief in British fairness and Britishjustice, provided that the true facts become known to the British people.    The  refusal of the Arabs to co-operate with the Government has, in a large measure, been the cause of our failure to fulfil the promises of representative govern-ment which were made to them, but, as the Arabs saw the situation, co-operation onthe terms offered to them implied acquiescence in a policy to which they were bitterlyopposed.   Be that as it may, that failure has lowered British prestige in all arab countries.    The doubts which are widely felt as to the completeness of the answers of theBritish Government to the Arab charges of bad faith have weakened the moral basis on which the Government of Palestine must stand if  it is to act with conviction andfirmness.    The consciousness that the moral basis on which it stands is unsuitable, and theknowledge that it would be  exposed to attack  by either Jews  or  Arabs for everyimportant administrative act, have  tended  to  make the Government  of Palestine,in its desire to be credited with an attitude of impartiality, deal with questions which arise not solely upon their merits  but not uninfluenced by the consideration that any concession made to one side should be balanced by a concession to the other.    39.  As a consequence of the recent outbreaks, a wave of  Pan-Arab nationalistsentiment has swept  over Palestine and the neighbouring Arab  countries, and it is certain that the political situation will never again be as it was, &quot;or appeared to be,before last August.    40.  Since the recent outbreaks occurred, members of His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave, on several occasions, made public statements to the effect that  the policy of the balfour Declaration will be adhered to.    Any proposals for the measures  to  be taken to prevent  a repetition  of theoutbreaks must therefore be based upon the assumption that the Balfour Declarationwill continue to be the basis of British policy in Palestine.    On that assumption  I am of opinion that, as regards future policy in Palestine,there are now two courses open, either      (1) to withdraw from the Jews the specially privileged position  (as compared          with the Arab inhabitants of the country) which has been given to  them          under the Mandate, but which is not justified by the terms of the Balfour          Declaration, and to grant the people of Palestine  a measure of  self-          government, or    (2)  to continue the present policy unchanged and to enforce the provisions of the          Mandate  by  maintaining  in Palestine military  forces  of  sufficient          strength to keep order and to protect the Jews from  attack by the Arabs          in Palestine supported by their sympathisers in the adjacent territories.    41.  I  reject the second  alternative,  because  it  is altogether repugnant to modern sentiment, and because it would provide no permanent solution of the present difficulties in Palestine and no palliative apart from repression by force of arms, fora situation which has become dangerous, and, if allowed to continue, will become a menace to the Empire  in its relations  not only  to  the  territories adjacent to palestine, but also to the whole Moslem world.    It is only by taking measures on the  lines suggested in the first alternative, byshowing the Arabs that Great Britain is no less mindful of her obligations to  them than of her obligations  to  the Jews,  and that she is equally  solicitous for  their
interests and welfare, that true peace can be restored in Palestine and the sympathy and co-operation of the Arab population secured.    Taking long views as to the future welfare of Palestine, that policy would be no less to the interest of the Jewish inhabitants of the country than to the interest of theArabs.  Many of the wiser Jews have already  expressed the view that  the national home in Palestine cannot be permanently established under the  protection of theBritish bayonets.    This view is widely held by the supporters of the spiritual ideal of Zionism, andby the inhabitants of the  Jewish Colonies who live alongside the Arabs, and do not desire that special privileges should be conferred upon them;  in this they differ from many of the Zionist Jews  who do not live and do not intend to live in Palestine.    42.  It is necessary to study the question whether it is possible to satisfy such ofthe demands of the Arabs as  may properly be complied with, while ensuring that theJews  shall not be deprived of facilities for establishing a national home in Palestine.    43.  The Treaty of Versailles  was signed by the Allied and Associated Powerson the 28th June, 1919.  In Section XXII of the Covenant of the League of Nations,which formed Part I of the Treaty, it is stated that     &quot; certain communities formerly belonging  to the Turkish Empire have reached    a state of development  where their existence  as independent nations can be    provisionally recognised, subject to the rendering of administrative advice and    assistance by a Mandatory until such time as they are able to stand alone.  The    wishes of these communities must be a principal consideration in  the selection    of the Mandatory.&quot;    Among the  communities referred to in  that  Section,  Palestine  was  clearlyincluded.    Article XXII of the Covenant of the League of Nations may be regarded asthe organic  constitutional document laying down on the authority  of the victoriousAllies the principles  governing the status of Palestine.  It  embodies the principlethat the rights of sovereignty snarl be exercised not in the interests of the conquerors,but in the interests of the people of the conquered territories.    Further, it is stated in  the preamble to  the Mandate  for Palestine that thePrincipal Allied  Powers agreed  that the Mandatory should be responsible for putting into effect the declaration originally made  on the 2nd November, 1917, bythe Government of His  Britannic Majesty, and adopted by the  said Powers, infavour  of the establishment in Palestine of a national home for the Jewish people,it being clearly  understood that nothing should be done which might prejudice thecivil and religious rights of existing non-Jewish communities in Palestine.    Paragraph  8 of Article  XXII of the Covenant also provides that the degree of authority, control or  administration to be exercised by the Mandatory shall, if not previously agreed upon by the Members of the League,  be explicitly defined  in eachcase by  the Council of the League of Nations.    In  accordance with that provision, the  task of drawing up  the Mandate wasdelegated by the Allies to the Council of the League of Nations.    44.  In discharging  the responsibility  for defining the degree of authority,control  or administration to be exercisecf by the  Mandatory, the  powers of theCouncil of  the  League of Nations were, therefore, limited by the provisions ofArticle  XXII  of  the  Covenant  and  by  the policy affirmed  in the  balfour declaration. And it may be contended that if  and in so far as the provisions of theMandate are inconsistent with or contrary to the provisions of Article XXII of theCovenant or the Balfour Declaration, they are ultra  vires, and, therefore, invalid.    45.  This view is confirmed by the statements contained in a pamphlet entitled&quot; The Mandate System,&quot;  issued by the Secretariat of the League of Nations in 1927.In  that pamphlet it is shown that the original intention  of the authors&apos; of theCovenant was that the  terms of all the Mandates should be embodied  in the peace treaty, and it is stated that     &quot; the Mandates contain a series of provisions  reaffirming with greater detail    and precision the principles laid down in  the Covenant.&quot;    In  that pamphlet it  is further stated that the &quot;A&quot; Mandate  &quot;is applied tocertain communities formerly belonging to the Turkish Empire (Mesopotamia, Syriaand Palestine) which have  reached  a stage of development where their existenoeas independent nations can be provisionally  recognised, subject to the  rendering of
 administrative advice and assistance by a Mandatory  until they are able to stand alone.  At present  they  are  allowed a certain measure of self-government, while at the same time obliged to accept the &apos; assistance&apos; given to them by the Mandatory, in the selection of which the wishes of the people must be the principal consideration.&quot;     46.   The Mandate for Palestine, having been approved by the  Council of the League of Nations, holds a  position as an authoritative  constitutional document governing the status of Palestine.  Article 27 of the  Mandate  provides that the consent of th** League of Nations is required for any modification of its terms.     If, however, it can be shown that that Mandate contains provisions which are inconsistent  with Article XXII of the Covenant or the  Balfour Declaration  and contrary  to the general interests of the people of Palestine it  would, I  submit, be proper for His Majesty&apos;s Government to lay before the  League of Nations proposals for  amending the Mandate with the object of removing  from it those provisions.     47.   The Balfour Declaration lays down two principles,  viz. :       (1) That the Powers favour the establishment in Palestine of a national home           for the Jewish people.     (2) That nothing should be done in  promoting the establishment of that national           home which might prejudice the  civil and religious rights  of existing-           non-Jewish communities in Palestine.     In the Balfour  Declaration there is no  suggestion that the Jews  should be accorded  a special or favoured position in Palestine  as compared with the Arab inhabitants of the country, or that the claims of Palestinians to enjoy self-government (subject to the rendering of administrative advice and assistance by a  Mandatory as foreshadowed in  Article XXII of the Covenant) should be curtailed  in order to facilitate the establishment in Palestine of a National Home for the Jewish people.     48.   The undertaking given in the  Balfour Declaration to favour the establish- ment of  a national home for  Jews in Palestine would  therefore be given effect to by according to the  Jews opportunities of entering  Palestine and settling there up to the economic capacity of the country  to absorb new arrivals.     49.   When the  Mandate  for Palestine was drawn up,  however, several  of its- provisions were so drafted as in appearance  to confer  special  privileges upon the Jews,  so that the first part of the Balfour Declaration  regarding the establishment of the Jewish National Home has tended to become the primary and overriding consideration of the Mandatory Power,  while the  second  part the safeguarding of the civil  and religious rights of the other inhabitants of  Palestine appears to have been  relegated to a second place.     If the interests of the population  of Palestine as a  whole are to prevail the Mandate  should not  lay special emphasis on measures concerned with the establish- ment of the Jewish National Home, and it should not contain provisions which have the appearance of granting preferential treatment  to the&apos;Jews  over the  Arabs.     50.   As stated above, it  does not appear that  the Balfour Declaration  taken by itself is inconsistent with Article XXII of the Covenant.  And it may reasonably be maintained that there is no  inherent inconsistency between the policy of favouring the establishment of  a national home ft  ? the Jews in Palestine and the granting of a  measure of self-government to the inhabitants of Palestine  in accordance with the promises made to the  Arab peoples  as a whole by Great Britain and the Allied Powers, and  as provided in Article XXII of the Covenant.     But by certain provisions of the Mandate the position has been fundamentally&quot; changed.    51.  The first sentence of Article  2 of  the Mandate lays  down  that  &quot;the Mandatory  shall be  responsible for placing the  country  under  such political, administrative and economic conditions as will  secure the establishment of the Jewish national home, as laid down in the preamble, and the development of  self-governing- institutions.&quot;    Owing to the rejection by the Arabs of the offers made to  them of  a share in the Government of the  country, the effect of  that provision has been to place the Jews in a  favoured position; for the fact that  complete control over the administra- tion has during the last nine years remained in the hands of the High Commissionerhas enabled the Jews to  make more rapid progress with the movement for the
 establishment of the national home than they would have been able to achieve under any form of representative Government.     In spite of  their constant criticism of the  Palestine Government, the Zionist Organisation are well aware of the advantages the Jews enjoy under existing condi- tions, and the Zionist leaders have not concealed  and do not conceal their opposition to the grant of any measure of self-government to the people of Palestine either now or for many years to come.  Some of them even go so far as to claim that that provision of Article 2 of the Mandate constitutes a bar to  compliance with the demand of the Arabs for  any measure of self-government.     In view of the provisions of Article XXII of the Covenant and of the promises made to the Arabs on several occasions that claim  is inadmissible.     In these circumstances I submit that that  part of Article 2 of the Mandate which  requires  the  Mandatory  to  place the  country  under  such political, administrative and  economic  conditions  as  will ensure the  establishment of the Jewish national  home should  be rescinded as being inconsistent with Article XXII of the Covenant  and  prejudicial to the rights of the people of Palestine.     52.  Article 4 of the Mandate provides for the establishment of a Jewish Agency as a public body for the purpose of advising and co-operating with the administration of Palestine on such economic, social and other matters as may affect the establishment of the Jewish national home and the interests of the  Jewish population in Palestine.     The privileged position so accorded to the Jewish Agency is embarrassing to the Government of Palestine, since it excites the suspicion and resentment of the Arabs. In  actual  practice  the special privileges  accorded  to  the Jewish Agency,  as represented by the Palestine Zionist  Executive in Palestine, are not of great value or importance.   The Palestine Zionist Executive enjoy the  right of access to the Government with a view to advising and co-operating in Jewish affairs, and that right cannot&apos;t be withdrawn;  but similar privileges  are accorded to representatives of responsible Arab bodies who may seek them,  although the Mandate is silent on the subject.     It is stated in the White Paper (Cd.  1700) that  the Palestine Zionist Executive does not possess  any  share in the general  administration of the country, nor in practice does it do so; but owing to  the privileged position assigned  to the Jewish Agency under the Mandate,  the Palestine Zionist Executive are inclined to claim that representations which they may  make to the Government should receive special consideration  and to   feel   aggrieved  when  their   requests are  not granted.I accordingly submit  that Article 4 of the Mandate should  be cancelled.     53.  The  first part of  Article 6  of  the Mandate  provides  that  jewish immigration shall be facilitated, subject to the conditions that the rights and positionof other sections of the population are not prejudiced.  That provision is not unfair;but the provision in the  concluding sentence for the close settlement of Jews on theland, including State lands  and waste lands not required for public purposes, is regarded by the  Arabs as unjust  and as placing the Jews in  a privileged positionover the other  inhabitants of Palestine.     Owing to improved hygienic conditions, the annual natural increase of the Arab population is now considerable.  It amounts to from 15,000 to 20,000 per annum, andthe rate of increase  is  growing.   In certain districts the Arab population  is inconsequence already becoming congested; and the Arabs claim that the satisfaction of the needs of the Arab inhabitants of the country for land to live upon shouldhave priority over the claims of the  inhabitants  of other countries who may desire to immigrate into Palestine.     This claim is just;  and the grant to  Jews  of prior claims to  State lands doesnot expressly or  implicitly form part of the Balfour Declaration.     It  is therefore for consideration whether the concluding  sentence of Article 6 of the Mandate should not be omitted.     I revert to the land question in  paragraph  65 of this Despatch.     54.  Another provision  of the Mandate which the Arabs regard as unjust to them is the second part of Article 11, which provides that the administration may arrange with the Jewish Agency for  the construction and operation of public works services and utilities and for the development of the natural resources of the country, in so far as these matters are not directly undertaken by the  administration.     There is no good reason why provision should be  made to give the Jewish Agency special  privileges over other  private bodies  in  the grant of concessions for such
 enterprises; ancl.it  would be well if  the  second  paragraph  of  Article 11 of  the Mandate could be omitted.    55.  I understand that His Majesty&apos;s Government have given an undertaking that the Report of the Commission of Inquiry will be laid  before the Mandates Commission.   I suggest that that occasion would afford  a convenient opportunity for submitting to the Council of the League of Nations proposals for amending  the Mandate in the sense suggested above.    56.  I now  turn  to the  consideration of the question of what measure of seif-government would satisfy the denmncls of the Arab population, and  whether such demands can be granted  consistently with the discharge of the obligations assumed by His Majesty&apos;s Government under the Mandate.    The most recent statement in regard to Bri tish policy in Palestine is that made by His Majesty&apos;s Government in  1922  (Command Paper No. 1700 of 1922, No.  5). The main features of the policy stated in that Paper were summarised in a telegram dated the 29th June, 1922, addressed to the Officer Administering the Government of Palestine by  the Secretary of State for the Colonies, in the  following terms :     (1)  His Majesty&apos;s Government  re-affirm  the  Declaration of November 1917,           which is not susceptible of change.    (2)  A Jewish National Home will be founded in Palestine.  The Jewish People           will be in Palestine as of right and not on sufferance.  But His Majesty           Government have no such aim in view as that Palestine should become as           Jewish as England is English.    (3)  Nor  do  His   Majesty&apos;s  Government   contemplate  disappearance  or           subordination of Arab population, language or culture.    (4)  The Status of  all citizens of Palestine will be Palestinian.  No section of           population will have any other status in the eyes of the law.    (5)  His Majesty&apos;s Government intend to foster the establishment of full measure           of self-government in  Palestine, and  as  the next  step a  Legislative           Council with a majority of elected members will be set up immediately.    (6)  Special position of Zionist Executive does not entitle it to share in  any           degree in government of country.    (7)  Immigration will  not exceed the economic capacity of country at the time           to absorb new arrivals.    (8)  A Committee of elected members of Legislative Council will confer  with  the           administration upon matters relating to the regulation of immigration.           Any difference  of opinion will be referred to His Majesty&apos;s Government.    (9)  Any religious community or considerable section of the population claiming           that the terms  of the Mandate are  not being fulfilled will have  right of           appeal to the League of Nations.    The Executive of the Zionist Organisation formally assured  His  Majesty&apos;s Government that the activities of  the Zionist  Organisation would be conducted in conformity with  the policy stated in the White Paper.  But, in spite  of that assurance, many Zionists do not conceal the  fact that their policy is not only to create a Jewish National Home  in Palestine,  but also to convert Palestine into a JewishNational State.    By  the Arabs that statement  of policy was never accepted.    During the last seven years the policy of the Government of Palestine has been guided by the principles laid down in that  White Paper, and it has been taken as abasis for the proposals which I submit in this  despatch.    57.   I  have discussed the situation confidentially with the Arab leaders whohave recently sought interviews with me.    I have impressed upon them that it was/vain to ask His Majesty&apos;s  Governmentto abandon the policy  of  the Balfour  Declaration.  Not only had several  of HisMajesty&apos;s Ministers recently made public statements to the effect that they intendedto adhere to that policy,  but  those  statements had  been reinforced  by  similarannouncements made during the last session of  the Council of the League of nations at Geneva.    Declaration of policy so formally and so unanimously  made could  not  berescinded.    The manner in which the policy of the Balfour Declaration was given  effect towas, however, another matter which might  be open to discussion and argument.
     58.   I have pointed out to the Arab leaders the extreme folly of their actionin  refusing  to  co-operate with the Government  in the working of the electedLegislative Council which was offered  to them under the Order in Council of the10th August, 1922, and the unfortunate consequences to themselves of their refusal to accept the  policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government stated in the White Paper of 1922.The consequence of those refusals has  been not to bring the  Arabs any nearer the fulfilment of  their aspirations, but to leave them in a state of isolation and impotencein that during the last seven years they have had little opportunity for pressing theirviews in regard to draft legislation on the Government or of influencing the decisions and acts of the Government in matters affecting the special  interests of the arab population.     I urged  them not to repeat that folly at the present time,  and to remember that,if, as was probable, His Majesty&apos;s Government should not be able now to grant them so complete a measure of self-government as they hoped ultimately to attain, theirsuccessful conduct of affairs under such representative institutions as His Majesty&apos;sGovernment  felt justified in granting them would furnish the strongest argument in favour of an advance in the future stage along the road towards  the fulfilment oftheir aspirations.     The justice of that argument was acknowledged, and the leaders admitted thatthey had acted foolishly in refusing  to co-operate with  the Government.  Theyexplained that the Arab politicians were divided into two parties, the policy of oneof which was &quot; all or nothing,&quot; while the policy of the other was  &quot; take what you can get and ask for more.&quot;  The former party had up to now been  in  a majority.     59.  In  setting up representative institutions in Palestine, two  considerations should, I suggest, be borne in mind.  These are :      (1) That the time has not yet come for establishing any system of democratic          parliamentary government in Palestine; and     (2) That the Legislative  Council should  include official  and elected members,          and that provision should be made to enable the elected  members to  have          some share in the responsibility for the executive and administrative acts          of the Government as well as for legislation.     60.  As  regards (1), it was pointed out by the Permanent Mandates Commissionin September 1928, in reply to a petition from the Arab Congress,  that the institu-tion of any system of democratic parliamentary Government is not compatible  withthe obligations devolving on the Mandatory Power under the Mandate.  And it isclear that considerable powers must be reserved to the High Commissioner, as repre-sentative of the  Mandatory Power, in order to enable His Majesty&apos;s Government todischarge their obligations under the  Mandate without hindrance  by the  locallegislature.     61.  As  regards  (2), I  do not propose in this despatch to submit proposals for a constitution for Palestine, but I would observe that, owing to the recent rise of Arabnationalism,  it  is highly improbable  that  the grant of  a  nominated  LegislativeCouncil with an unofficial majority, as suggested in my Secret  Despatch of the12th June, 1929, would now satisfy the Arab population, even if their leaders couldbe induced to accept it.     The partially elected  Legislative Council, which was provided  for under thePalestine  Legislative Council Election  Order-in-Council of the 10th August, 1922,might, however,  be taken as a basis for discussion in framing a new constitution forPalestine.     62.   In  paragraph 59 above I have expressed the opinion that it is highly desirable that provision should be made for the elected members to have some share in the responsibility for the  administrative acts of the Government.  The intro-duction of this provision is of importance, in order that the elected  members maynot be tempted  to waste their energies on the sterile task of pouring a stream ofcarping criticisms on every act of the Government.     63.   It is possible that the new Constitution, which has recently been offered tothe  people of  Ceylon,  and the  method devised  therein  for  enabling  the elected members of the  Assembly to take a share in the executive work of Government bymeans  of  committees associated with each department  of the administration, mayafford  a helpful guide to the framers of a constitution for Palestine.   Apart  fromtheir value as an instrument of government, such Committees would be beneficial in
this respect, that they would serve to promote the establishment of closer personalrelations between the Arab and Jewish members of the Legislative Council.    In order to prevent the possibility of a deadlock, it will be necessary to provide that  the High Commissioner  in  Council  shall  be empowered  to  pass  necessary measures when the Legislative Council is not  in session, and that His Majesty inCouncil or the High Commissioner-in-Council should be empowered to pass essentiallegislation, such as the Appropriation Bill, if the Legislative Council fails to pass it.    It would also be desirable to make use of  the  provisions of the second part ofSection IV of the Royal Instructions, to summon more or less regularly extraordinarymembers of the Executive Council.   These Extraordinary members might be invitedto attend to deal with all matters that  come before the Executive Council exceptreserved subjects, such as defence, public security and  foreign relations.    64.   I have already expressed the opinion that a necessary preliminary to there-establishment of good relations  between the  Arabs and the Jews is a final settle-ment of the Wailing Wall dispute.  It  is an  issue which introduces the  religiouselement, and so long as it remains  unsettled, there will always be ready to  the hand of the ill-disposed a formidable weapon, to which  recourse will be had in times of racial tension.    It only requires the dissemination of false reports of encroachments by  the Jewsat the Wall or of concessions granted to them by Government in  that locality, torouse the ignorant section of the Moslem population  to a state of frenzy,  in whichthey become hardly responsible for  their actions.   I am aware that the  questionof the appointment of a special Commission under Article 14 of the Mandate is now before the Council of the League of Nations, and I  desire to reaffirm the view whichI have already expressed that, in the interests of peace and good order in Palestine,the need for the appointment of an authoritative body to study, define and determine the rights and claims  of the Moslems and Jews  relating to the Wailing Wall is urgent.    65.   I now turn to the question of the acquisition of agricultural land by Jewsfrom Arab owners, and its effect on the existing Arab agricultural population.    66.   In order to understand this question, it is  necessary to refer to  the  landlegislation, beginning with the Land Transfer Ordinance, 1920.    Section 6 of that Ordinance contained a provision designed to secure two objects,namely     (a)  the prevention of speculation in land, and    (6)  the retention, on the occasion of a sale of agricultural land, by the tenants          in  occupation of sufficient land  in the  district or  elsewhere for the          maintenance of themselves and their families.       -             ,                 .    ,       .     .                         j    67.   At the third  meeting of  the Advisory Council, held on the 7th December,1920, one of the unofficial members asked what measures were being taken to safe-guard the rights of cultivators, as he understood that, in several villages, cultivatorshad been expelled from their holdings.    In reply to that inquiry, the High Commissioner called attention to that partof Section 6 of the Land Transfer Ordinance, 1920, which provided that the Govern-ment should withhold its consent to the transfer, unless it was  satisfied that, in thecase of agricultural land, either the person transferring the property, if he were inpossession, Or  the tenant in occupation,  if the property were leased,&quot; would retainsufficient land in the district or elsewhere for  the maintenance of  himself and his family.    The High Commissioner also quoted the following extract from the instructionsto the  Land  Commission,  with the object of showing the precautions  taken  by government to prevent expulsion of cultivators :          &quot; The Government of Palestine,  while desirous to promote in every possible    way the closer settlement  of the country, is at the same time anxious that the    interests of the present tenants and occupants  of land, whether  Government    property or private property, should be properly protected.  It will be necessary,    on the one hand, to take steps to prevent the eviction of tenants by the  landlords    on a sale of  the land, and, on  the other,  to secure -for those who have  exercised    customary rights of cultivation and grazing, without full legal title, a  sufficient    area for  the maintenance of their families.  ...&quot;
    68.  The instructions referred to in the preceding paragraph purported to makea  distinction between  &quot; tenants&quot;  and  &quot; persons exercising customary  rights of cultivation and grazing without full legal title.&quot;    The former class of persons would  presumably comprise persons who were inoccupation of land as lessees and were, therefore, undoubtedly liable to eviction;the instructions contemplated that  such  persons should be afforded protection onlyon the occasion of a sale, and, although the  instructions stated that, on the occasion of a sale, the eviction of such persons was to  be prevented, it is apparent, fromSection 6 of the Land Transfer Ordinance,  1920, that what was meant was that, ifevicted, they were to be provided with land in  the district or elsewhere.  The lawcould,  however,  always be evaded by a landlord  evicting his tenants before applyingfor the consent of Government to the sale.    With  regard to the  latter class  of  persons,  namely,  &quot; persons  exercisingcustomary rights of cultivation and  grazing  without full legal title,&quot; the instructionscontemplated that such  persons should, at all times,  be secured in the occupation of sufficient land for the maintenance of themselves and their  families.   Section 6 ofthe Land Transfer Ordinance, 1920, could, however, only protect such persons onthe occasion of sale, and  would protect them  then  only if the  law were strictlyenforced and if&apos; the phrase  &quot; tenant In occupation &quot;  were construed to include&quot; persons exercising customary rights &quot; and if the phrase &quot; property which is leased  &quot;were construed to include the land which they occupied.    69.  In  practice, however,  Section  6 of  the Land  Transfer  Ordinance, 1920(amendment  Ordinance  (No. 2), 1921), did not, save  possibly in  one individual case,secure, either for &quot; tenants in occupation &quot; or  for  persons  &quot; exercising  customaryrights,&quot; sufficient land for the maintenance of their  families, since the Governmentallowed such persons to contract out of the law and to accept  monetary compensation in lieu of their statutory right to land.    70.  Section 6 of the Land Transfer Ordinance,  1920 (as amended by the LandTransfer (Amendment)  Ordinance (No. 2), 1921), was repealed by the Protection ofCultivators Ordinance,  1929,  which was promulgated on the 1st August,  1929.    That Ordinance was passed as a result of the acceptance by the  Government ofthe  recommendations contained in  the  report of a   Committee  appointed  byLord Plumer to consider the question of legislation for the protection of tenants fromeviction.  That Report was  forwarded to your predecessor under  cover of LordPlumer&apos;s despatch No. 1022 of the 6th July, 1927.    One of the recommendations made in that  Report was  that  the section  of theLand  Transfer Ordinance referred to should be repealed; and  among the reasons give  by the Committee for that recommendation were      (a) that the law could be evaded by the  purchaser refusing to  purchase the           land, except with vacant  possession, and so compelling the  vendor  to           remove all tenants from the land before the sale took place;     (b) that to require a landlord, who wished to  sell  a block of his property,  to           procure land in a different area for tenants  whom he proposed to evict           was an extraordinary impediment on the landlords right  to dispose  of           his land  and was calculated  to  prove  a  great obstacle  to the close           settlement of land; and     (c) that tenants who are removed from one area can usually find for themselves           other land to  cultivate  in a  different area without  great  difficulty, and           that they are  better able than their former  landlord to obtain the land           they want, and that the payment of money is, therefore, likely to be  of           greater assistance than the provision of a piece of land.     With regard to (a), there was foundation  for the recommendation,  since there were  four  cases during  the period  1924-27  in which the purchaser  made  it a condition that the land should be delivered to  him  with .vacant possession.     With regard to (c), the succeeding  paragraphs of this despatch show that it is incorrect to state, in general terms, that persons evicted can obtain land elsewhere, if by that  is meant cultivable  land in  Palestine, since this statement  involves  an unfounded assumption that  there is a surplus of  agricultural  land in Palestine. Furthermore, under the Protection of Cultivators Ordinance, 1929, a tenant receives only compensation for disturbance and improvements, which is insufficient to enable him  to purchase land elsewhere.    Consequently,  even when  he can obtain land elsewhere,  he can only afford to hold it as a  tenant, liable to eviction,  unless  he
possesses or commands, apart from the compensation he has received, sufficient funds to enable him to purchase.    71.  The  present position  is,  therefore, that  the  Protection  of CultivatorsOrdinance, 1929, affords  the  only statutory protection to cultivators;  and  theprotection is of the same character as that provided by  the Agricultural HoldingsActs in the United Kingdom.    If, therefore, a landlord wishes to sell,  with vacant possession, he must  firstgive his tenants one year&apos;s notice as prescribed by the Ordinance;  and tenants,  whoare widely defined by Section 2  of the Ordinance, are entitled to  compensation fordisturbance  and  improvements  but  have no  statutory right to land  elsewheresufficient for the maintenance of themselves and their families.    72.  During the last ten years the purchase of agricultural land by Jews fromArab owners has proceeded on a considerable  scale.   The times at which these landswere acquired deserve a short examination :     (a) In the years J921  and 1924-25 the Jews acquired  236,000 dunams  almost          exclusively from individual absentee landlords.    (b) Since  1921  the Jews have  been gradually acquiring  undivided shares in          village lands, the vendors being either  effendis  and fellaheen  or solely          fellaheen.   The area  so  acquired  would,  on  partition, amount  to          116,000 dunams.    (c) In the year  1929  the  Jews  acquired  the Wadi Hawareth  lands  in  the          circumstances set out in paragraph 80 of this despatch.   This was the          first large acquisition since 1925.    As regards  (b), the  fellaheen  vendors  were  in many cases  indebted  tomoneylenders for money borrowed at  usurious rates of interest.   When pressed bytheir creditors they  sold their share in the village lands, frequently at high prices, inorder that they might be able to discharge their liabilities.   Until partition takes place the Arab cultivators are usually allowed to remain  on the land  as tenants.   Insome of the cases, where shares of village lands have been  acquired by Jews, partitionhas already taken place, as a result of which the Arab cultivators either have  beencompensated and evicted, or have moved on to the area remaining in Arab ownership.    In all cases the policy  of the Jewish purchaser is to obtain a partition as  soonas he is in a position to do so, and, so long as the law remains as at present, it is  onlya matter  of time  for the  whole of the Arab inhabitants of such  villages to bedispossessed of their land.    73.  Since 1920 the Jews have acquired approximately 373,000 standard clunamsof agricultural land.  (A standard dunam is equal  to  1,000 square metres, or 0247of an acre.)  And they now own about 900,000 dunams, the greater part of which island of the best quality.    The Jewish  population how engaged  in  agriculture  numbers  about  35,000persons.    The average holding  per  Jewish  family is, at present, 130  dunams;  but theJoint Palestine Survey  Commission, which visited  Palestine in 1927, advised  thatthe area was insufficient and must be increased to 160-320 clunams.    It is to be observed that all  land acquired by the Jewish National Fund is  held as the  inalienable property of the Jewish nation, to be leased, but not sold, to thosewho occupy it.    74.  The  experts, who reported  to the Joint  Palestine  Survey Commission,pointed out  that all the Jewish colonies  in the hills  are financial failures.  Theyadvised, that, for the present, no more Jewish colonies should be founded in the hills,but that colonisation should be limited to the valleys and the  plains, and  they recommended that no expenditure for  founding new colonies should  be made untilthe development of  existing colonies has been completed, or the money needed fortheir full  development has  been  provided.    In particular,  they laid stress on the  importance  of  the coastal plain fromHaifa  to  Gaza as a citrus-producing  area;  and during recent years the markedtendency of Jewish effort in rural areas has been to develop this form of horticulture.    It is an  enterprise which involves considerable capital expenditure.   Thepreparation of land for citrus cultivation alone costs  50-75  a dunam, and seven years must elapse before a grove  produces an economic return.
    No one among the Arabs, except a few owners of large  estates, possesses orcommands sufficient capital to embark on the enterprise of transforming their laudinto citrus-producing land.    75.  The situation as regards  agricultural land  in  Palestine is,  briefly,  asfollows :     The total area of Palestine is about 26,000,000 dunams.  It is estimated that, ofthat area, 11,000,000 dunams are cultivable (excluding the Beersheba district, whichis occupied by Bedawin).    Of the cultivable land, 10,100,000 dunams  (or 12,100,000 dunams including theBeersheba district) is in the occupation of  Arabs and other non-Jews.    The latter area includes 700,000 dunams of cultivable State domain, all of whichis occupied.    The area of cultivable land now  in Jewish ownership is 900,000 dunams.    According to the Land Registers, since 1920 up to the present time, the Jewshave acquired 373,000 dunams of rural  land; while the area of rural land in Arabownership has decreased by 357,000 dunams, although the number of the  indigenouspopulation, apart from Jews, has, during that period, increased by  78,000 the rateof natural increase being about 23 per thousand per annum.    76.  It is estimated that, excluding the population of the Beersheba district,which  numbers aboutT04,000, the Arab rural population of Palestine is 460,000.    Assuming an average  of  five  persons per  family, there are approximately92,000 Arab  families engaged in agriculture.    The cultivable land in occupation of  the  indigenous population is  10,100,000dunams; an average holding of 110 dunams is  thus available for each  Arab family.    It is estimated that the area of land required to support the average Arab familyis from 90 to 150 dunams, according to the  quality of the land.    It would appear, therefore, that the agricultural land in the occupation of the indigenous population cannot, under existing conditions and methods of cultivation,support a greater population than that now occupying it, unless and until agricultural education and capital expenditure have borne  fruit.  A change from extensive  tointensive methods of cultivation must take a considerable time, so  far as education is concerned, and  can be effected only if a large  amount  of capital,  which is not now available, is  made available and is wisely expended.    77.  The position in regard to cultivable land may, therefore, be summarised inthe following- terms :     (a) All cultivable State domain is occupied.    (b) Government owns waste land,  such  as the coastal sand dunes, the desert           area south-east of Beersheba and the  mountainous region between  the           Jerusalem-Hebron  road  and   the  Dead Sea.   These areas are  not           cultivable.     (c) Government owns large areas of land in the hilly parts of the country, which           are fit only for afforestation.    id) The cultivable land in the occupation of the indigenous population is fully           occupied and cannot support a larger population under  existing methods           of cultivation..    (e) Any change from extensive to intensive methods  of cultivation must take           time and money, and is unlikely to proceed at a more rapid rate than that           required to permit of the absorption on the  land of the annual natural           increase of the Arab population.    (/) If more land now in the occupation of the indigenous population is sold           for the purpose of Jewish settlement, either the existing cultivators will           be dispossessed of their land and will  cease to be cultivators,  or their           holdings must be reduced below what is now  regarded as the average area           sufficient to support an  Arab agricultural family.     78.   The land policy of the Zionist Organisation is indicated  by the following- resolutions passed at the 16th Zionist Congress, held at Zurich in  July and  August 1929 :-         &quot; 7.  The most important task of the Jewish National Fund  in the immediate     future is the creation of land reserves  in all parts of the country;  in particular,     the Congress  is of opinion that it is  necessary to create, as soon  as possible, a     land  reserve of irrigable lands  in  accordance   with   a  definite plan   for     colonization  policy.         &quot; 8. The Congress accordingly recommends  that a systematic plan for  the     acquisition of land be worked out at once by the proper authorities.....&quot;
As regards colonization, the Congress declared :         &quot; that it is to be the basic policy of the Jewish Agency for all time to do    everything  to  assure  development  and  extension  of  Jewish  agricultural    colonization in Palestine in  accordance with the principles laid clown by the    Congress for co-operation in the Jewish Agency on as large a scale as possible.&quot;    79.   Having regard to these  resolutions and this declaration of policy, and tothe  facts set out in the preceding paragraphs, it is clear that a situation has now arisen in which the interests of the indigenous population and the  interests of theJews as regards agricultural land are in direct conflict; for further purchases ofagricultural land by the  Jews can be made only by dispossessing Arab cultivatorsof the land they are occupying and so creating a class of landless peasantry.    80.   Already a difficult situation has arisen in the case of the Wadi Nawarethlands.    These lands were recently purchased by the Jewish  National Fund at  a publicauction ordered by the Court in satisfaction of a judgment debt.   The lands have long been occupied for cultivation and grazing by Arabs, who number about 1,200persons and own 2,000-3,000 head of stock.    An order for their eviction was recently made;  but I have caused the Police tobe instructed not to execute the order at present, since no land has, as yet, been foundto which the persons to be evicted and their stock can be transferred, and I cannot,in any circumstances, allow them  and their stock to be placed upon the public roads and there set at liberty to wander where they will.    81.   I am also informed that, during the last few weeks, two contracts havebeen signed, and a third contract is in the process of negotiation, for the purchaseof three areas of land, amounting to 30,000 dunams, which are all occupied by Arabcultivators.    82.  In considering the problem thus created, it is necessary to  bear in mind -    (a) the second half of the Balfour Declaration, which provides that nothing shall           be done in establishing a national home for the Jewish people which may           prejudice  the civil  rights  of  existing  non-Jewish communities  in           Palestine;    (b)  Article 6 of the Mandate which, while imposing on the Administration the           obligation of encouraging close settlement by Jews on the land, provides           that the rights and position of other sections of the population shall not           be prejudiced; and    (c) Article 11 of the Mandate which provides (among  other things) that the           Administration shall  introduce a land system appropriate  to the needs           of the country.    These  provisions make it impossible for the Government to adopt the  attitude that the indigenous population itself can solve the problem by not selling its land,and I am of opinion that, by reason of these provisions, the Government are undera positive obligation to protect  the interests of the indigenous population.    83.  With regard to the solution of the problem, two measures appear to benecessary      (i) That immigration of Jewish agricultural colonists must be  restricted.    (ii) That  legislative measures must be taken  to ensure  that  the indigenous           agricultural population is not dispossessed of its land.    84.  As to the legislative measures referred to in the preceding paragraph, they need only relate to the indigenous agricultural population, which  is not Jewish,since the Jews are protected by their own organisations and, to a large extent, by therules of the Jewish National Fund, which provide that all land acquired by the Fundshall be held as the inalienable property of  the Jewish nation to be leased, but notto be sold, to those who occupy it.    For the reasons given in  paragraph 70 (a)  legislation based on the principleembodied in the Land Transfer Ordinances  (1920-1921) would be ineffective, sincesuch legislation can be and has been evaded.    I am therefore of the opinion that the only effective legislative measure whichcan be taken is to provide that the transfer of Arab agricultural land, except betweenArabs, and the creation of rights  over such land, except in favour of Arabs, should,for  the present, be allowed only with the consent of the High Commissioner.  Such
a measure may appear to be unduly drastic, but the principle is the same, Mutatis Mutandis, as is contained in Article 6 of the Mandate for Tanganyika; and  it will do no more than afford to the Arab peasants a measure of protection similar to that now enjoyed by the Jews in respect of the land owned by the Jewish National Fund.     I propose, therefore, to submit to  Your Lordship a Bill to give effect to that principle.     85.   It is possible that such an Ordinance may be challenged in the  Courts onthe ground that it is in conflict with the terms of the Mandate.     Although I am advised that such an argument is not likely to succeed, I thinkit is  desirable that the Mandate should be so amended as to sanction the principleof the Bill.     The necessities of the moment are, however, so urgent that I do  not propose to-await the  amendment  of the  Mandate before submitting  the  proposed  draftOrdinance.     86.   In Command Paper  1700 of 1922,  His Majesty&apos;s Government gave theArabs an assurance that immigration would not exceed the economic capacity of thecountry at the time to absorb new-comers.     During the years  1924-26 that undertaking was, as subsequent  events proved,too liberally interpreted.  Mass immigration of Jews was permitted, which resultedin severe economic  depression and unemployment on a large scale.     Immigration was consequently temporarily suspended and was resumed onlyin the latter half of the year 1928.     87.   The information given  in the preceding paragraphs in regard to the landmakes it clear that  the demands of the Jews for immigration on a large  scale for thedevelopment of new colonies cannot be  complied with without infringing that partof the Balfour Declaration which limits the pursuit of the  policy  of the JewishNational Home by the stipulation that nothing shall be done to prejudice  the rightsof the existing non-Jewish communities in Palestine.     As explained above, the conclusion seems inevitable that, unless and until more intensive methods of cultivation are generally adopted in Palestine, no  further landcan  be made available  for settlement by Jews and  that,  for  the  present,  the immigration of  Jewish agricultural colonists  must be  restricted to  the number required to develop and cultivate the land now in Jewish ownership.     88.   In rega,rd to immigration of Jews of the working classes for  employmentin industries or on  manual labour other than agriculture, there is great difficulty in determining with any degree of accuracy the  economic  capacity of the country to absorb settlers.     It is  comparatively easy to ascertain approximately the number of newcomerswho can be absorbed in industries of a more or less permanent character.  difficulties arise, however,  in  considering  the capacity  of absorption  of industries  whichfluctuate.     The building trade, for instance, during the years 1924-26 was active,  and manyJews were permitted to enter the country because there was urgent demand for the class of artisan  required by that industry.   After a time,  however,  the  supply of buildings began  to exceed the demand; building construction slackened,  and a largenumber of men were thrown out  of employment.  Some of these men  were absorbed into other industries; but many, after a painful experience of poverty and suffering,left the country.     89.   In  order  to  avoid a repetition of  these experiences,  it is  necessary toexercise caution in  determining periodically the number of immigration permits tobe issued.     The existing inhabitants of the country must be assured that their rights shallnot be prejudiced by excessive immigration;  and, at the same time, the Jewish people in Palestine and elsewhere must be satisfied that the rights of Jews to enter Palestine.subject to the economic capacity of the country to absorb them, are being maintained.     90.   The interests of Arabs and Jews  in regard to  Jewish immigration are soconflicting that it would be inexpedient to place the final decision in regard to thenumber of immigration certificates to be issued at any time within the  powers of  alegislature, composed mainly of representatives of the people of Palestine.     Under Article 34 of the Palestine Order-in-Council of  August 1922,  it was provided  that the High Commissioner should confer upon all matters relating tothe regulation of immigration with a Committee consisting of one-half of  the official
members of the Legislative Council, and that provision should be made by Order-in-Council for investing that Committee with the necessary powers.    It was also provided that in the event of any difference of opinion between theHigh Commissioner and the Committee, the High Commissioner should make a full report on the subject to a Secretary of State, whose decision thereon would be final.In the absence of a Legislative Council the matter  has, up to now, been  left in thehands of the High Commissioner.    91.   The consideration  of  immigration questions by  a committee  is  highly desirable, because that procedure permits of an open discussion of the question andof all the economic factors affecting a decision.   That  the recommendations of theCommittee should be followed by a decision by the  High Commissioner, with the rightof appeal to the Secretary of State, if one or other of the  two parties should feelaggrieved at the decision, is in the circumstances necessary.  The Arabs are, however,unlikely to welcome such an arrangement; for they  regard the immigration of Jewsinto Palestine as of right as constituting a grave  menace to their interests; whilethe Jews will equally resent the adoption of a procedure which may have the effectof imposing increased restrictions upon Jewish immigration.    92.   In connection Avith the question of the organisation of the public security forces, I enclose a Memorandum setting forth the decisions that have been taken byHis Majesty&apos;s Government  since  1925 in  regard to the  establishments of thepublic security  forces in Palestine and Transjordan,  and  describing the  defence arrangements generally (Enclosure II).    93.   At the  beginning of August 1929, the distribution of the air and militaryforces in Palestine and Transjordan Avas as follows :     (a) Amman           Command H.Q., Palestine and Transjordan.          H.Q.  and 2 Sections No. 2 Armoured Car Company.          No. 14 (Bomber) Squadron.    (b) Ma&apos;am           1 Section No. 2 Armoured Car Company.          1 Company (Mounted) Trans-Jordan Frontier Force.    (c) Kerka           FI.Q.  and Training Depot, Trans-Jordan Frontier Force.          2 Mounted Companies Trans-Jordan Frontier Force.          1 Camel Company, Trans-Jordan Frontier Force    (d) Ramieh           Base Details of No. 2 Armoured Car Company.    (e) Sarafand           Palestine General Hospital.          No. 1 Wireless Company, Royal Corps of Signals.    The total  personnel  of the  Royal Air  Force and Armoured  Car Company  inPalestine and Trans-jordan numbered 29 officers and 354 other ranks.    The  establishment of the  Trans-Jordan Frontier Force included  23 british officers and Warrant Officers, and 653 local officers and other ranks and 50 reservists.    No. 2 Wireless Company consisted of  5 officers  and 64 other ranks.   Of thelatter only 12 men could immediately be made available for combatant duty.    The Palestine Police consisted of the  British Section, with an establishmentof 5 British officers and 170 other ranks, and  the  Palestinian  Section, Avith an establishment of 42 British  officers, 73 Palestinian officers and 1,261 Palestinianother ranks.    The Arab legion  (Transjordan Police)  consisted of  a  British  officer, 33  local officers and 786 other ranks.    94.   Apart from locally recruited forces and the personnel of the Air Force and armoured Car Sections Avho are confined to their technical duties, there were thusavailable to deal with outbreaks in the  towns and populous centres on the  23rdAugust, 1929,  only 47  British officers and Avarrant officers and 182  British other ranks.
    95.  Recent events have shown that the optimistic views held as to the improve-ment of the relations between the Arabs and the Jews were ill-founded, and that thepublic security forces maintained  in Palestine were  insufficient to prevent orsuppress outbreaks of violence in time of tension between the  two sections of thepopulation.  It also became apparent that the Palestinian members of the police force cannot be relied upon to do their duty in situations in  which they  are calledupon to act against members of their own race and religion.    There is the  further consideration that the recent manifestations of  the latenthatred felt by the Arabs for the Zionist Jews have been followed by a wave of Arab-nationalist sentiment which has  spread over Palestine and the neighbouring arab countries and has engendered among the Arabs a feeling of distrust of the MandatoryPower. Any  recrudescence of the outbreaks in Palestine is  therefore likely to be supported by incursions of Arabs from the neighbouring countries.    96.  In determining  the  future establishment  and composition of the public security forces in Palestine, these considerations must be taken into account, and itmust be remembered that even if, as the result of the Report  of the Commission of inquiry, it should be decided  to make substantial changes  in the political status ofPalestine in order to meet the demands of the Arabs for a share in the Governmentof the country, a considerable time must elapse before the acute tension that nowexists between the Arab and Jewish sections of the  population will be relaxed.    In these circumstances, I am of opinion that  the establishment of the public security forces in Palestine and  Trans-Jordan  should be increased, and  that these forces should include a substantial proportion of British personnel, on whom alonethe Government can place implicit reliance in times of inter-racial disturbances.    97.  In other despatches  I have submitted  to Your  Lordship proposals for theincrease of the Trans-Jordan Frontier  Force  and for the reorganisation of thePalestine  Police,  which include recommendations for an increase  of the establish-ment of the British Section of the Force.  On the assumption that the Police force has been reorganised and that the proposed increase of  the Trans-Jordan frontier force has been effected, I submit  the following observations as regards the imperial forces required to support the police and other  local forces in time of emergency.    The experiences of the recent outbreaks have made it clear that life and property in Palestine cannot be effectively protected by the local forces supported  by the air arm alone, even in the case of  internal disorders.    Aeroplanes and armoured cars are able effectively to deal with Raids  by Beduinin the open and sparsely  populated  regions of Eastern  Trans-Jordan.  But theycannot adequately provide  for the defence of Palestine.  They are  unable to under -take many of the military operations that are necessary  for the  defence and for themaintenance of order in a country such as Palestine, which contains large  towns andpopulous districts often enclosed and wooded and of  which a large area consists of mountainous and broken country.  They are unable to break up riotous  assembliesin towns with narrow and  tortuous streets inhabited by a mixed population  or  toprotect agricultural colonies from attack by day or by  night.  They are unable tosurround and search villages or to round up roving bands of marauders.  They cannoteffectively make reconnaissances  in broken or  wooded country.  To carry out  allthese operations  effectively there is no substitute  for  infantry, preferably mademobile by being provided with adequate motor transport.    Further, owing to the nature of the soil and the absence of properly constructedaerodromes, aircraft  in Palestine are practically immobile during and after heavyrains.  Finally, in Palestine punitive action from the air is, as a rule, to be deprecatedby dictates of humanity and policy alike.  For the indiscriminate destruction of life and property which  are almost  inseparable from  air action under the  conditions prevailing in Palestine make it  desirable to avoid having recourse to such actionexcept as a last resort.    98.  In this  connection I  would observe that the views expressed by Sir HerbertSamuel in paras. 1-4 of his Secret Despatch of the  19th April,  1925, on the schemefor the defence of Palestine show so just  an appreciation of the situation as it thenwas and are so applicable to  the conditions of to-day that I  venture here  to quotethem :           &quot; The scheme for  the defence of Palestine which has  now been submitted    has the great advantage  that it draws a clear line  between the military forces     and the police, and gives to  the Air Officer Commanding and  to the  Inspector-     General of Police full control  of their  several units.  But I  am bound to say
     that it involves considerable risks.   The British Gendarmerie will disappear,     200 of its men  being embodied in the Police.  The cavalry regiment  is  to     be removed in the year after next.  The security of the country will then depend     entirely upon two flights of aeroplanes,  four armoured cars, and a battalion  of     900 Palestinians.         &quot;2.  If we could be certain that the condition of the country would remain     as it is now, and as it has been during the last two years, such a force would,  in     my opinion, be sufficient.   But we cannot be certain.  We must envisage as a     possibility a change in the political situation, which might result in a recurrence     of the conditions  of the spring of 1921.  If at that date there had not been a     considerable body of troops in the country,  the serious riots which broke out  in     Jaffa and the districts would almost certainly have spread to other towns .and     other districts.  If in the future there were simultaneous disturbances in several     places, lasting (as in  May  1921)  for several days, and  if the unrest here was     accompanied  (as in April 1920) by raids on a considerable scale from Trans-     Jordan, I do  not think that the forces proposed Avould be able to cope with the     situation.         &quot;3. There is also to be considered the  psychological effect of the removal     from the  country  of all white units of infantry, cavalry or gendarmerie.  The     more extreme  elements among the Arabs might thereby be encouraged to insist     upon a change in the present policy of opposition limited to constitutional lines,     in which they now concur with reluctance.  It would certainly make the Jewish     population apprehensive,  and might lead to a renewal of  the secret importation     of arms and the  formation of secret defence forces, which occurred after the     serious  loss of life and property suffered  through the Arab attacks in  1920     and 1921.         &quot; 4. It must  be  remembered that  aeroplanes  are not by themselves  an     effective weapon with  which to meet conditions such as  I have described in a     small country like Palestine.  Armoured cars  also, while of the greatest value     in the open or in main streets, are,  of course, of little use in places like the     Old City  of Jerusalem and the  Arab quarters of Jaffa, the places where  in     fact the previous riots took  place.  Nor would  a British cavalry regiment, even     if retained,  be the best kind of force for Palestine, although its presence would     in itself have  a certain moral effect.&quot;     99.  In addition to maintaining  the present  establishment of the  Air Forceand  Armoured  Cars   now in Palestine  and Trans-Jordan, I  consider that thepermanent Garrison of Palestine should include not less than two battalions  ofBritish infantry with the  necessary ancillary  services.     100.  When the permanent garrison has been so strengthened I  recommendthat the defence of Palestine should cease to be a responsibility of the Air ministry and  should be  transferred to the charge of the War Office.     During the recent  disturbances by far the greater  part of the work of restoringorder fell upon the military forces, and it is logical that the ultimate responsibilityfor the defence of  the country should rest with the  Department mainly concerned.     If responsibility for the defence of Palestine is transferred to the War office i recommend  that, for defence  purposes, Palestine should be made part  of theEgyptian Military Command.     That arrangement would be not only economically  and  administratively con-venient,  but  it  would also be  strategically  advantageous,   for it would greatlyfacilitate the reinforcement of the troops in Palestine in time of need.     101.  I am aware that  objections have been raised to  the stationing of battalions of British  Infantry   in  Palestine  on  account of  the expense;  but  in  viewof the international obligations undertaken by His Majesty&apos;s Government under theMandate and of the world-wide criticisms to which the  Mandatory Power and theGovernment of Palestine have been exposed by the recent outbreaks, I regard  it as essential that no avoidable  risk should be  incurred  of a repetition of the disorders;and  I  submit  that financial considerations should not be allowed to  stand in theway  of the discharge by the Mandatory Power of its primary  duty of providing theGovernment of Palestine with sufficient force to enable it to insure the maintenanceof order and the safety of life and property.     102.  There is another consideration that cannot be altogether ignored in fixing the establishment of the public security forces in Palestine and  Trans-Jordan; thatis the interests of  the Mandatory for  Syria.
    In spite of the sympathy and assistance that the French Authorities in Syriahave extended to the Government of Palestine during the recent outbreaks, theyhave criticised adversely  the arrangements made for the  defence of this  country.And I understand, from information that has reached us that, if the British Forcesin Palestine are reduced to such a point as in  their opinion to  endanger the peace of&quot;Syria, the French Government will probably make representations to His Majesty&apos;sGovernment on the subject.    In this connection I may mention that when  a battalion was withdrawn from palestine at the  end of October the General  Officer Commanding the DamascusDistrict made protests on  the subject to the British Liaison Officer in Syria,  when was informed  of these protests  I authorised  the British  Liaison  Officer, inaccordance with the authority which you gave  me in your telegram No. 237  of the21st October,  to assure the French Authorities that m  case of need the  garrison of Palestine would be reinforced at short notice by a battalion from Malta,                           SUMMARY OF CONCLUSIONS.    103.  The  following  are  the  main  conclusions  which  I  submit  forconsideration :     (1) That the Balfour Declaration should be reaffirmed, and that it should be           given effect to in the spirit of the statement of British Policy contained           in Command Paper 1700 of 1922.  (Paragraphs 40-48.)    (2) That the Mandatory should submit to the League of Nations proposals for           the amendment of Articles 2, 4, 6 and  11 of  the Mandate with a view           to removing from  them those provisions which give  or  appear to  give           the Jews a privileged position in Palestine over the indigenous popula-           tion.   (Paragraphs 49-55.)    (3) That,  subject to  the  reservations  of such  powers as may be necessary to           enable His Majesty&apos;s Government to discharge their obligations under           the Mandate,  the  people of Palestine should  be granted a measure of           representative government, which should provide that the representatives           of  the people shall  have some share  in  the responsibility for the           administrative and executive acts of the  Government  as well as for           legislation.  (Paragraphs 59-63.)    (4) That a  special commission  should be appointed under  Article  14 of the           Mandate to study,  define  and determine  the rights and claims of the Jews           and Moslems relating to the Wailing Wall.   (Paragraph  64.)    (5) That  all  the  cultivable land  in Palestine  is  now occupied.  (Para-           graphs 72-77.)    (6) That no cultivable land now in possession of the indigenous population can           be  sold to Jews  without creating a  class of landless Arab cultivators.           (Paragraphs 78-81.)    (7) That legislative measures should be taken (a) to ensure that the indigenous           agricultural population shall not be  dispossessed of its land, and (b) to           prevent the creation of a class of landless peasantry.  (Paragraphs 82-85.)    (8) That the immigration of Jewish agricultural colonists should be restricted           to the number required to develop and cultivate the land now in Jewish           ownership.  (Paragraphs 86-87.)    (9) That the permanent  garrison of Palestine should include two  battalions           of British Infantry with the necessary ancillary services.  (Paragraph 99.)   (10) That responsibility for public security  in  Palestine should be transferred           from the Air Ministry to the War Office. (Paragraph 100.)   (11) That for defence purposes Palestine should be made part of the Egyptian           Military  Command.   (Paragraph 100.)                                            I  have, &amp;c.                                   (Signed)       J.  R. CHANCELLOR,                                            High Commissioner for Palestine.
Enclosure I to Confidential Despatch to Secretary of State, dated January 17, 1930.                      Memorandum on the  Wailing Wall.    THE Western  or Wailing  Wall,  in Hebrew  Kotel-Maaravi, and  in  ArabicEl-Burak, is to the Jews the holiest place in their religion.  It is believed to be thelast remnant of the  Temple remaining  above the ground, and it is taught that fromthese stones the Spirit of God has never departed.  The Jews claim that they haveprayed before the Wall from time immemorial, and certainly there is a  continuoustradition of Jewish worship at the Wall since the  middle ages.    2.   The Wailing Wall is also an exterior boundary wall of the Naram Al Sharif,one of the most sacred places of Islam, and, as such,  it is the property of the MoslemCommunity.  Tradition also states that here was the tethering place of &apos;&apos; al Buraqwhich bore the Prophet on his miraculous ascension.    3.   There is a narrow  pavement  in  front of the Wall (29-45 metres long by4-20 metres broad), where Jewish worshippers stand to pray, and where on Sabbathsand on the principal holy-days  (Passover, New Year, Day of  Atonement and the anniversary of the  Destruction  of the Temple) they  congregate  in large numbers.This pavement lies within the boundary of the Moslem Naqf of Abu Midian, a piousfoundation. The beneficiaries of the foundation are Moroccans  who have lived inthis neighbourhood since the fifteenth century.    4.   Although the pavement in front of the  Wall is contiguous to the wall of theHaram-el-Sharif, and although  it was the tethering-spot  of &quot; Al-Buraq,&quot; there  isno record of its having been held by the Moslems in any special veneration.    5.   The legal position  is the  same  now  as it was  before  the  War.   It  isunderstood by Government to be as follows : the Wailing Wall and the pavement arethe absolute property of the Moslems,  who permit access  to the Wall to the public generally; and, in addition, &quot;the Jewish community have established an undoubtedright of  access  to the pavement for the purposes of  their devotions.&quot;    6.   Only on  very rare occasions before the conquest of Palestine by the allied forces had there been any  interference on the part of the Moslems with Jewishobservances at the Wall, and in general the relations between the worshippers andtheir Moslem neighbours were cordial.   Soon after  the  occupation, however, theJewish  authorities  made certain demarches  with the object of transforming aprivilege on sufferance into a right founded on actual ownership of this area.  Tothat end Dr. Weizman made tentative inquiries of  the Military Government in the spring of 1918 as to the possibility of  purchasing the whole of the Waqf propertynear the Wall.    The Military Governor of Jerusalem (Sir  Ronald Storrs)  sounded the  Moslemcommunity informally and indirectly;  but,  following the  agitation due  to the factthat it became known that  pecuniary offers were being made privately to certainMoslems with regard to the purchase of this area, he reported that &quot; it would be forthe moment a grave error of policv for the Military Government to raise the question at all.&quot;    The  Foreign Office, which  was then   the  responsible  Department,  were communicated with,  and they instructed &quot;that for the time  being no further action should be taken in  the matter by the  Government.    7.   From that day to this it has not been  possible  for  the Jews to acquire, byagreement with the Moslems, any part of the  land adjacent to the Wailing Wall.As the result, their  rights and exercise of worship have  been  definitely limited bythe legal fact of the ownership of the Wall and its precincts by Moslems.    8.  In the absence of a settlement of  the dispute by agreement between theparties, the Government have endeavoured, in  view of  Article 13 of the Mandate,which imposes upon the Mandatory responsibility for preserving existing rights  inconnexion  with the  Hoty Places,  to preserve  the status  quo,  as in other cases  in dispute between  different religious communities or sects.    9.  But the preservation of the status quo has presented difficulties.  It embracesnot only the question of the ownership of the property, but also  the question of whatappurtenances the Jews may bring to the Wall for  the purposes of their devotions.
 The view  held  by the Mandatory Government  in this matter  is  set  out  in  a memorandum by the Secretary of State, entitled :  &quot; the Western or Wailing Wall in Jerusalem,&quot; which describes certain incidents  which occurred at the Wailing Wall on the Day of Atonement, 1928  (the 24th September).  The most  important point  is contained in the following quotation :          &quot;His  Majesty&apos;&quot;s . Government  regard it as their  duty,  and  it  is their     intention, to maintain the established Jewish right of  access  to the pavement in     front  of  the Wall for the purposes of their devotions, and  also their  right to     bring  to the Wall the appurtenances that they were allowed to take to the&quot; Wall     under the Turkish regime.   It would be inconsistent with their duty under the     Mandate were they to endeavour to compel the Moslem owners  of the pavement     to accord any further privileges or rights to the Jewish community.&quot;     10.  On  the  Day  of Atonement, 1928, there was an incident  regarding the removal of a portable screen erected to separate  the male and the female worshippers. This, however, was not the first occasion on which this question of the appurtenances arose.     Before the Occupation, indeed, in 1919, a Decree of the Administrative Council of Jerusalem  had forbidden the bringing of chairs, benches, screens and the like. Similar incidents  also occurred  in April 1922 and on  the Day of Atonement  again in 1923.   These two incidents related to the bringing of benches to  the Wall.     It may seem a matter of reason and humanity that aged worshippers should lie permitted to have seating accommodation, especially on the Day of Atonement, when they fast for twenty-four hours, but the other point of view is stated by Sir Ronald Storrs in a memorandum written in 1925 :           &quot; The Moslem objection to the introduction of benches (which I have con-     sistently endeavoured to overcome on grounds of reason and humanity)  is based     partly upon the fact that the pavement in front of the  Wall is actually  the only     approach to one or more of the Moghrabi houses, and that  it is in  danger of     being  blocked if benches or anything of a permanent nature were  allowed to     obstruct the fairway; but still more upon the theory,  unfortunately  verified by     universal experience in Jerusalem, that  any concession  or abrogation from     existing rights tends to become the thin end of a wedge before which  rights are     apt to disintegrate. Chairs, they state, would become wooden benches, wooden     benches stone benches, stone bencbes fixed stone benches, with the corollary that     covering  from above against sun and rain and  from the side  against cold  is     equally a matter of humanity; so  that the  Waqf would  one  day find houses     belonging to others erected against.their wishes upon their own property.  I     would add that such exaggerated suspicions have been for centuries at  the root     of most of the constantly recurring trouble between the various Christian rites     at the Holy Sepulchre, where, after all, the conflict is between adherents of one     faith and uncomplicated by  the hopes and apprehensions aroused by the Balfour     Declaration.&quot;     In a word,  the Moslems were, and are, afraid  that the first steps were  being taken for the conversion of the area into a Synagogue.     11.  In transmitting this memorandum to  the Secretary  of State, Lord Plumer expressed  his sympathy with the Jewish  worshippers, but said that it would be extremely unwise  to attempt to make any  alteration in the regulations which now obtain except  by mutual agreement, and that he proposed a little  later on, when the excitement had somewhat subsided, to endeavour to come to some arrangement which might mitigate the discomfort of the worshippers without infringing the legal rights of the owners of  the  ground.   The Government  admitted, however, that  small portable camp-stools and cushions might be brought for the convenience  of aged or infirm worshippers.     12.  No other special incidents regarding the Wailing  Wall occurred during Lord Plumer&apos;s  regime except  that the Moslem authorities continued  to submit protests regarding the placing of any form of  seat on the  pavement.     13.  The length  to which some Jews were prepared to  go for  the purpose of-securing what they considered  to be proper conditions for  free and undisturbed worship at the Wailing Wall is illustrated  by an article in &quot; Hahed &quot; (Jerusalem) which  appeared at the beginning of  September 1928,   i.e.,  before the  Day of Atonement (the 24th September). The article, under the title of &quot;On the Pilgrimage Celebrations,&quot; praises  the work of the Yeshurun Congregation in Jerusalem in
2797reviving the old institution of pilgrimage on the three pilgrim festivals of Passover,Pentecost  and Tabernacles,  and says, &apos;&apos; with the increase in recent years of theJewish population in Palestine and of the Jewish tourists who visit the Holy Land,the congestion at the Wailing  Wall has become more serious, and especially duringthe festivals, when it becomes dangerous, and is becoming more dangerous every year.This year, on the day of Pentecost the morning prayer was interrupted several timesowing to the congestion.  It reaches its climax during the pilgrimages, which  havebeen renewed this year and which will develop  even more in the future.   Of thethousands of pilgrims  who made the pilgrimage, a few  hundred only managed to push their way into the enclosure before the Wailing Wall, while the rest, in serriedmasses, were forced to wait for  many hours in the  narrow lanes until they might cometo the Wailing Wall itself for a few minutes. It is, no  doubt, possible to  improvematters by posting ushers, but a, thorough solution can only be found by enlarging theenclosure adjacent to the Wall/&apos;    14.   The article then proceeds to say that the enlargement of the enclosure bythe demolition of the dilapidated houses encumbering it would not be offensive to the religious feelings of any community; the Jews would pay the  full price of the land and houses; if the  Arab leaders had any sense of justice  they would have raised noobjections to this scheme; it is the duty of the Government to intervene and expeditea settlement; just as the Government expropriated land for work of  a public nature,such as the construction and widening of roads, so ought they  to do for the  mostHoly sanctuary of the Jewish people, which cannot be regarded as of less significance.    15.   The article concludes by urging the Palestine Zionist Executive and theChief Rabbinate and the Vaad  Leumi (the General Council of the Jewish community of Palestine) to take the initiative and enter into negotiations  with the palestine government, the Mandatory Government  and the League of Nations with a view tosolving this problem.  The  Jewish National Fund should undertake the task of raising the necessary funds  to redeem the enclosure and  to enlarge it.  &quot; If Israelknows that this holy place is redeemable,  the whole people will hasten to redeem it;and if success attends our efforts, it will serve as a sign of  the beginning of theredemption of Israel.&quot;    16.   The importance of this article lies in the fact that it was published beforethe incident which occurred  at the Wailing Wall in September 1928, and before the religious question was openly confounded with political and racial questions.    17.   The Jews had tried to purchase the necessary land from the Moslems andhad failed.  The Jewish press  seized upon the unfortunate incidents of the Day ofAtonement to force the issue to the front.  One section demanded that Governmentshould  discharge  its responsibility by expropriating  on behalf of the Jews theprecincts of the Wailing Wall in order that Jews  should worship there in futureunhampered by any restrictions    18.   Many protests from  Jewish bodies  and individuals were  received by theGovernment and the League of Nations.   The  following is a  quotation  from theMinutes  of a meeting of  the  Permanent  Mandates  Commission  held  on the8th November, 1928 :         :&apos; Mr. Orts pointed out that telegrams and letters had  been received  from    Jewish organisations  all over the world.   This seemed  to indicate concerted    action  taken on a given word of command rather than a spontaneous  outburst    of  indignation.        &quot;The Chairman (the Marquis  Theodoli) thought that, if this  were the    case, the responsible body  was the Zionist Organisation.  The protests received    by the Commission from various parts of the world had been worded in similar    terms, if not identically.  This would lead one to suppose that the protest had    been organised.&quot; .    19.  The effect of  this  Jewish propaganda in Palestine and  abroad and  itsrepercussions amongst  the Arabs was to obscure the purely religious aspect of theWailing Wall and to  rouse again the political and racial antagonism of arabs and Jews which had been suppressed or at least masked  for nearly six years,  now,however, with a dangerous religious  colouring.    About this time a society was formed among  the Sheikhs of the  Mosque entitled&quot;the Society for the Protection of Al-Aqsa.&quot;
    20.  The Moslems feared that the political influence of the Jews in London andat Geneva and elsewhere might lead to a decision to expropriate the land near theWailing Wall.  They suspected the Expropriation Ordinance of being an enginefor the alienation of Moslem Waqf property in general and the Waqf property near the Wailing Wall in particular;  the more  ignorant and fanatical Moslems furtherbelieved stories that the Harem area and the Mosque of Al Aksa were in danger.    21.  Shortly after the incident at the Wailing Wall on the  Day of  Atonement,1928,  the Palestine Zionist Executive represented  to Government that the SupremeMoslem Council, in order&apos; to excite Moslem fanaticism were deliberately spreadingrumours that the whole of the Harem area was in danger from Jewish encroachment.Government made  enquiries,  but could  find  no  definite evidence to  support thesuggestion.    22.  Public security  became  threatened  by  the  spread of  these  exaggeratedrumours amongst  a fanatical population.    On the 10th October,  1928, the Officer Administering the Government suggested to the representatives of the Palestine Zionist Executive the issue of a communiqueby the Jewish authorities, making it clear that the Jews had no desire to acquire the site of the Harem.    The representative of the Palestine Zionist Executive replied that he  mustdecline the suggestion of publishing such a communique, which  would only provokefurther discussions about  a matter that was already beyond discussion.    23.  A month later, however, the Executive of the Zionist Organisation issued from  London the following statement for publication in Palestine and abroad :         &quot;In view of the fact that the Jewish aspirations  to secure the conditions    necessary for free and undisturbed worship  at the Kotel-Maaravi, known as    the Wailing Wall, have been misrepresented as involving designs  to encroach    upon the Harem area, the Zionist Organisation desires to reaffirm  its repeated    declarations  unreservedly recognising the inviolability of  the Moslem  Holy    Places.&quot;    24.  It may  be noted that Government were made aware that the publicationof &amp; communique by the Jews  disclaiming any aspirations towards the Harem  itselfmight be embarrassing since such a statement would not be accepted by  all Jews.    25.  In the intervening month the  feelings  of Moslems in Palestine and the neighbouring countries had been roused to a  dangerous pitch.   Any effect that the.published statements of the Palestine Zionist Executive and the Vaad Leumi might possibly have  had in allaying Moslem feeling, was afterwards negatived when thepetitions submitted  to the League of Nations by those two bodies were published.Notwithstanding the fact that the two petitioners disavowed any intention to askfor appropriation, the two petitions are capable of that interpretation.    26.  The preceding paragraphs give some idea of the state of popular feeling in Palestine from the Day of Atonement (the 24th September), 1928, until the termsof the White  Paper  (Cmd. 3229  of November 1928).  which defined the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government on the Wailing Wall became known.  It was published in the Official  Gazette of the Palestine Government  on the 11th December.  this paper gave satisfaction  to the Moslems who were immediately appeased :  their confidence in the British Government in the matter of the Wailing Wall was restored;for the time being the danger to  public security passed.  : . 27.  The Jews on the other  hand were far from satisfied.  They did not want the status quo, in that thereby the state of  sufferance which  had  prevailed under theprevious regime  was  perpetuated.  Statements  were openly made by  responsibleleaders that under the terms  of the Mandate the status quo did not suffice.   Suchsentiments were expressed at  the  Zionist Congress held at  Zurich in July of 1928.These claims of the Jews together with their other political demands were reproduced in the Arabic Press.    28.  The White Paper had one fundamental difficulty which nevertheless inthe nature of things could not have been  avoided. The status quo was defined ingeneral terms as being &quot;that the Jewish  community have  a right of  access to thepavement for the purposes of their devotions, but may bring to  the Wall only thoseappurtenances of worship which  were allowed under the Turkish regime.&quot;
    29.  This very general definition gave rise to certain  questions which had to be answered before complete practical effect  could  be given to  the  White Paper. The question was what was the  meaning  of  &quot;allowed&quot;;  whether  it meant only such practices as were officially admitted by the Ottoman Government, or  whether it meant in addition such practices as were tolerated by the guardian of  the Waqf or tolerated by him in virtue of private arrangements made between him  and the Jews.    The Moslem authorities have consistently maintained that the Jews merely have the same right of access to, and station at the Wall  as any  other persons.   They do not even admit that they have  the right of access for the purposes of prayer, and consider, further,  that the phrase  &quot; and  the like&quot;  in  the 1912 decision of the Administrative Council precluded any form of seating or appurtenances whatsoever.    The Jews, on their side, interpret the  word &quot; allowed  &quot; in the wider  sense as being what was actually  done  under the Turkish regime.   It is certain that the Ottoman Government from time  to time expressly forbade  the bringing of certain appurtenances, in particular, benches and a screen, to the Wall.  There is evidence, however, of a relaxation of these orders  at different times, and  conditions at the Wall appear to have depended largely on the state of relations between the JeAvs and their neighbours.    30.  The Moslem authorities, interpreting the status quo in  the  narrowest sense, asked  that the terms of the White  Paper should be enforced, and  became suspicious that the delay was due to Jewish pressure on the Home Government to modify its provisions.  His Majesty&apos;s  Government,  on the other hand, were unwilling that the status quo should be defined in Avriting until it became clear that there was no possibility of arriving at a  settlement by agreement between the parties.  The result was that the Jews continued to bring various  appurtenances to  the Wall and the Moslems planned structural alterations in the buildings  in the neighbourhood of the Wall, whilst each party complained to  the Government of the infringement of the status quo by the other.    In  consequence  there was a state of tension at the Wailing Wall all through the spring and  summer  of 1929.    31.   Soon after the 24th  September,  1928, the  Moslem  authorities  resumed work on a building erected above the  northern end of the Wall, overlooking a small garden belonging to the Moroccans,  and immediately  adjoining the  Wailing Wall proper.  They also began to convert  certain houses adjacent to the southern end of the Wall into a Zawieh, a meeting place of  some religious significance. A Muezzin began to call to prayer from a roof adjacent to the pavement.  At a later date they began to reconstruct a wall adjoining the Bab-el-Mogharbeh entrance to the Mosque which overlooked the Wailing Wall from the  south end,  and at the same time they opened a new door in this Avail to give access to the ZaAvieh.    32.   The Jewish  authorities complained  to the Government  that these works were infringements of the status quo in that worship at the Wall Avas disturbed. Government  thereupon  sought  the   advice  of  His  Majesty&apos;s  Government  in November 1928, in order to ascertain their legal position in this matter.  The matter was referred to the Eaw Officers of  the Crown, and their opinion Avas received  on the 16th May, 1929.    33.   Basing themselves thereon,  Government addressed  a  letter,  dated  the 11th June,  to  the  Supreme Moslem Council on the  particular subject   of  the houses adjacent to the southern end of the Wall into a ZaAvieh, since, on the personalrepresentation of the  High Commissioner,  the President of the  Supreme  Moslem Council had given  an  undertaking  at  an  intervieAV  in May not to  proceedwith the  contemplated structural alterations pending the receipt of the  advice  ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government as to whether certain acts, or certain kinds of acts, Avouldor would not constitute an interference with existing rights.    34.   The letter read :-        &quot; In the LaAv  Officers&apos; opinion,  the JeAvs  are entitled  to  conduct their    Avorship Avithout any greater disturbance than has occurred in the past, or may    be inevitable by reason of changes in the habits of the population of Jerusalem    or otherwise.  If the erection of the proposed  Zawieh results in the observance    of Moslem rites in the presence of jewish Avorshippers, or in an incursion  by    Moslems into the place Avhere the JCAVS pray during  the customary times  of    Jewish Avorship so as to cause genuine annoyance  or disturbance, this would  be    regarded as an interference with existing rights.   -  , .
         &quot; In  accordance with  these rulings  His  Excellency  approves of  the    suspended work being resumed on conditions that the wall leading up to the    Bab-el-Mogharbeh of the Harem area is built up  to its former height, and that    no  annoyance  or  disturbance  is  caused to Jewish  worshippers  during  the    customary times of their prayer.&quot;    35.  A letter was then addressed, on the 13th June,  to the Palestine ZionistExecutive  informing them, among other things, of  the  substance  of. the  letter addressed  to  the Supreme Moslem  Council.   This letter, being in  reply to  a confidential communication, was also sent under confidential cover.    36.  On the 4th July, the Palestine Zionist Executive replied, expressing regret at the piece-meal treatment of the question of the Wailing Wall, and pointing outthat the condition that  no annoyance or disturbance should be caused to Jewishworshippers during the customary times  of their prayer was being infringed;  andthat, therefore, existing rights were being interfered with.   They drew attention tothe following matters :       (i) The practice  introduced during the preceding months  of the Muezzin           calling from the immediate neighbourhood of the Wall during the hours           of  worship  caused annoyance and disturbance,  and would appear to be           calculated to do so, since the practice was an innovation introduced after           the incident on the Day of Atonement, 1928.    (ii) During the proceeding few weeks the Moslems had been  gathering in the           garden on the left of the Wailing Wall area, and at other places adjacent           thereto, during the hours of Avorship, and had been deliberately creating           annoyance and disturbance by shouting  and beating drums.    37.  This form of disturbance,  which, from reports received, the Governmentbelieved to be a deliberate provocation, reached its climax on Friday evening, the5th July, Avhen the Acting Deputy District Commissioner visited the Wall  and&quot; heard a din of drumming and singing Avhich can only be described as deafening,&apos;&apos;shortly  before the  President  of  the Supreme Moslem  Council had  given anundertaking to the Officer Administering the Government  that the noise Avould notbe continued.  The noise was, therefore, stopped by the  Sheikh of the Moghrabis onthe instructions of the Acting Deputy  District Commissioner, pending confirmation by the President  in accordance with his undertaking.   This was duly  given, but theimpression remained that this incident Avas a calculated move to bring pressure tobear on the Government to enforce the recommendations of the White Paper,  andas a response to the Jewish propaganda regarding the Wailing Wall.    38.  Shortly after this date (the 16th July), the principal officers of the PalestineZionist Executive and of the Vaad Leumi left Palestine  to attend  the  SixteenthZionist Congress at Zurich, which opened on Sunday, the 28th July, and lasted untilSunday, the 11th August.    39.  About the middle of July, the Supreme Moslem Council  resumed work onthe Zawieh and the wall of the Bab-el-Mogharbeh, in accordance with the permissiongranted by Government in the letter of the 11th June.    On account of its being marked &quot; confidential,&quot; the letter of the 13th June fromthe Government had not been communicated to the other jewish public bodies by thePalestine Zionist Executive.    The Jews, unaware of the fact that  the Moslems were  acting  with the permission of Government,  saw with consternation the  work proceeding at thesouthern end of the Wailing Wall.  The  perturbation among the Jews of Jerusalemswiftly spread throughout Palestine  and was  communicated to  London and theworld, and especially to the Congress then sitting at  Zurich.    40.  The Acting  Deputy District Commissioner,  Jerusalem,  anticipated theaction of the Central Government by informing Chief Rabbi  Kook, Avho had requested that the work should be promptly  stopped, in  a letter dated  the 21st July of the facts which had  been given confidentially  to the Palestine Zionist  Executive  on the13th June.  The  substance of that letter  was published  in the &quot; Palestine Bulletin &quot;and &quot; Doar Hayom&quot;  on the 22nd July.  Unfortunately, in the Acting DeputyDistrict Commissioners letter, the phrase &apos;&apos; Customary hours of Jewish Avorship &quot;was mistranslated  into Hebrew as &quot; fixed hours of Jewish worship.&quot;  The natureof the error was, however, immediately explained.
    41.   The fears of the Jews as to the effects of the Governments decisions wereenhanced by the manner in which these decisions had become known.  The Press tookon a very bitter tone,  accusing the Government of treachery and secret plotting to deprive the Jews of their rights at their Holiest place.    On the 24th July they represented to Government as follows :       (i)  There were no &quot;fixed times&quot;  of prayer for Jews at the  Wailing Wall,          whatever might be intended by the phrase &quot; customary times.&quot;     (ii)  They  understood that  the  Zawieh  would be used for worship; Moslem          worship and Jewish worship would, therefore, conflict, since &quot; customary          times &quot; in the Jewish sense means &quot; any times.&quot;    (iii)  The opening in the wall of the Mugharbeh lane turned a cut de  sac into a          thoroughfare and thereby increased, indefinitely and permanently, the          danger of a collision.    42.   Prom that moment, the tension became  more and more acute.  A JewishOrganisation for the defence of the Wall was created, of which Professor Klausner,the noted scholar and writer  of world-wide reputation, was the founder and head.    The tone of the Press, both Jewish and Arab, became more and more violent.    43.   Meanwhile,  at Zurich, after years of patient labour, Dr. Weizman  had succeeded in broadening,the basis of the Jewish Agency.  Up to that time the zionist organisation had  been  the  Jewish  Agency.   Henceforward,  the Jewish Agencywould consist of Zionists and  non-Zionists in  equal  proportions united on the platform of the upbuilding of Palestine.    In the atmosphere of this great  political achievement, the Congress dealt withthe question  of the Wailing Wall,, among other  things.  One of the  sessions was suspended as a sign of mourning when the delegates heard the news about the Zawiehand the opening in the southern wall.    A special aeroplane, carrying  Lieutenant-Colonel Kisch,  a  member of thePalestine  Zionist Executive,  and Mr.  David Yellin,  of the  Vaad  Leumi,  was despatched to London, so that the Secretary of State might be interviewed about thismatter.    44.   In the report of the meetings  of the Congress, the following statement isattributed to Mr. Sacher, of the Palestine Zionist Executive :           &apos;&quot; In reference to the Wailing Wall, the  Executive have submitted that the    whole question is governed by the Mandate, and that the  doctrine of  the status    quo,hitherto adopted by the  Government as a  basis of policy is not warranted by    the Mandate,  and that  our rights  under the Mandate are more complete and    more extensive  than those embraced within the status quo.&quot;    45.   The proceedings of the Congress were reported  and  commented on in theArabic and Jewish Press in Palestine, and all these events were followed very closelyby  the Moslem authorities.    The effect of  these reports on  the  minds  and  feelings  of  the  Arabs  wasdisturbing;  for they felt that their suspicions as to why  the White Paper had notbeen implemented and the status quo  defined  were confirmed.  They believed that the explanation  was  that the  Jews had  not  accepted  the decision  of the  BritishGovernment  contained in the White Paper,  and that their  hid den  but powerfulinfluence was preventing any action  from being taken until that decision could be reversed  to meet their wishes.    46.   The occurrences at the Wailing Wall on the days immediately  preceding the outbreak in August last  need not be recounted here.    The present  situation is that the  High Commissioner has made provisionalregulations governing the observances of the Jews and the conduct of the Moslemsat  the  Wall  in  the  interests of public order.    These regulations  were issuedimmediately before  the Jewish New Year (the 4th  October, 1929) accompanied by thefollowing communique&quot; :          &quot; In the interests of good order and decorum the High Commissioner has    issued certain instructions to the officers of the Government concerned in regard    to the use of the Wailing or Western Wall.
         &quot;In accordance  with  these  rulings  His  Excellency  approves  of  the     suspended work being resumed on conditions that the wall  leading up to the     Bab-el - A log ha rbeh of the Harem area is built up to, its former height; and that     ho annoyance  or disturbance is  caused to Jewish worshippers  during the  &quot;..  -customary times of their prayer.&quot;     35.  A letter was then addressed, on the 13th  June,  to the Palestine  ZionistExecutive  informing them,  among other  things, of  the  substance  of. the letter addressed  to -the Supreme  Moslem - Council.   This letter, being in  reply  to  a confidential communication, was also sent under confidential cover.     36.  On the 4th July, the Palestine Zionist Executive replied, expressing regret at the piece-meal treatment of  the question of the Wailing Wall, and pointing outthat the condition  that  no annoyance or disturbance should be  caused to  Jewishworshippers  during  the customary times of their prayer was being infringed;  andthat, therefore, existing rights  were being interfered with.   They drew attention tothe following matters :-                                       -     (i) The practice introduced during  the preceding months of  the Muezzin           calling from the immediate neighbourhood of the Wall during the hours           of worship caused annoyance and  disturbance,  and would appear to be           calculated to do so, since the practice was  an innovation introduced after          the incident on  the Day of Atonement, 1928.     (ii) During the  proceeding few weeks the Moslems had been gathering in the          garden on the left of the Wailing Wall area, and at other places adjacent           thereto, during the hours of worship, and had been deliberately creating          annoyance and  disturbance  by shouting and beating drums.     37.  This form  of disturbance,  which, from  reports received, the Governmentbelieved to be a deliberate provocation, reached its climax on  Friday evening, the5th July,  when the  Acting Deputy District  Commissioner visited the Wall and&quot;heard a din of drumming and singing which can only  be described as deafening,&apos;,&apos;shortly before the  President  of  the  Supreme  Moslem  Council  had given anundertaking to the Officer  Administering the Government that the noise would notbe continued.  The noise was, therefore, stopped by the Sheikh of the  Moghrabis onthe instructions of the Acting Deputy District Commissioner, pending confirmation by the  President in accordance with  his undertaking.  This was duly given,  but theimpression remained that this incident was a calculated move to  bring  pressure tobear on the  Government  to enforce the recommendations of the White  Paper, andas a response to the Jewish propaganda regarding the Wailing Wall.    38.  Shortly after this date (the 16th July), the principal officers of the PalestineZionist Executive and of the Vaad Leumi left  Palestine  to attend  the SixteenthZionist Congress at Zurich, which opened on Sunday, the 28th July,  and lasted untilSunday, the 11th August.    39.  About the middle of July,  the Supreme  Moslem Council resumed work onthe Zawieh and the wall of the Bab-el-Mogharbeh, in accordance with the permissiongranted by Government in the letter  of the 11th June.    On account of its being marked &quot; confidential,&quot; the letter of the 13th June fromthe Government had not been communicated to the other Jewish public bodies by thePalestine Zionist Executive.    The  Jews,  unaware of the  fact  that  the  Moslems were  acting with  the permission of Government, saw with consternation the work proceeding  at  thesouthern end of the Wailing Wall.  The perturbation among the Jews of Jerusalemswiftly spread throughout Palestine and  was communicated  to London and  theworld,  and especially to the Congress then sitting at Zurich.    40.  The  Acting Deputy District  Commissioner,  Jerusalem, anticipated  theaction of the Central Government by informing Chief Rabbi Kook, who had requested that the work should be promptly stopped, in a letter dated the 21st July of the facts which  had been  given  confidentially, to the  Palestine  Zionist Executive  on  the13th June.  The substance of that letter was published in the &quot; Palestine Bulletin &quot;and  &quot; Doar  Hayom&quot; on  the .22nd July.  Unfortunately,  in  the Acting  DeputyDistrict Commissioners letter,  the phrase   Customary hours of  Jewish worship &quot;was  mistranslated into Hebrew as &quot; fixed hours of Jewish worship.&quot;   The  natureof the error was, however,-&apos;immediately explained.
    41.  The fears of the Jews as to the effects: of the Governments decisions wereenhanced by the manner in which these decisions had become known.  The Press tookon a very bitter tone, accusing the Government of treachery and secret plotting to deprive the Jews of their rights at their Holiest place.   : On the 24th July they represented to Government as follows :-      (i) There were no &quot;fixed times&quot; of prayer for Jews  at the Wailing Wall,          whatever might be intended by the phrase &quot;customary times.&quot;     (ii) They  understood that  the  Zawieh would  be used for  worship; Moslem          worship and Jewish worship would, therefore, conflict, since &quot; customary-          times &quot; in the jewish sense means &quot; any times.&quot;    (iii) The opening in the wall of  the Mugharbeh  lane turned a cul de sac into a          thoroughfare and thereby increased, indefinitely and permanently, the          danger of a collision.    42.  Prom  that moment, the tension became more and  more  acute.  A JewishOrganisation for the defence! of the Wall was created, of which Professor Klausner,the noted scholar and writer of world-wide reputation, was the founder and head.    The tone of the Press, both Jewish and Arab, became more and more violent.    43.  Meanwhile, at Zurich, after years of  patient labour,  Dr. Weizman  had succeeded in broadening the basis of the Jewish Agency:  Up to that time the zionist organisation had been the Jewish  Agency.  Henceforward, the jewish Agencywould  consist of  Zionists and nomZionists in equal proportions united  on the platform of the upbuilding of Palestine.    In the atmosphere of this great  political achievement, the Congress dealt withthe question  of  the Wailing Wall,, among other things.  One of the sessions  was suspended as a sign of mourning Avhen the delegates heard the news about the Zawiehand the opening in the southern wall.    A  special  aeroplane,  carrying  Lieutenant-Colonel  Kisch,  a member of thePalestine  Zionist  Executive,  and Mr. David  Yellin,  of the Vaad Leumi,  was despatched to London, so that the Secretary of State might be interviewed about thismatter.    44.  In the report of the meetings of the Congress,  the following statement isattributed to Mr. Sacher, of the Palestine Zionist Executive  :         &quot; In reference to the Wailing Wall, the Executive have submitted that the    whole question is governed by the Mandate, and that the doctrine of the status    quo. hitherto adopted by the Government as a basis of policy is not warranted by V  the Mandate,  and that our  rights under the Mandate  are more  complete  and    more extensive than those embraced within the status quo.&quot;    45.  The proceedings of the Congress were  reported and commented on in theArabic and jewish Press in Palestine, and all these events were followed very closelyby the Moslem  authorities.    The effect  of these reports  on  the. minds  and feelings  of the Arabs  wasdisturbing;  for they felt that their suspicions as to  why the White Paper had notbeen implemented and the status quo  defined Avere confirmed.   They believed that the explanation  was that the Jews had not  accepted  the  decision  of  the BritishGovernment contained in the White Paper, and  that their hidden but  powerfulinfluence was preventing any action  from being taken until that decision could be reversed to meet their wishes.    46.  The occurrences at the Wailing Wall on the days  immediately preceding the outbreak in August last need not be recounted here.    The present situation is  that the High Commissioner  has  made provisionalregulations governing the observances of the JeAvs and the conduct of the Moslemsat the Wall in the  interests of public order.   These  regulations were  issuedimmediately before the Jewish New Year (the 4th October, 1929) accompanied by thefollowing communique:         &quot; In the interests of good order and decorum the High Commissioner  has    issued certain instructions to the officers of the Government concerned in regard    to the use of the Wailing or Western Wall.
         &quot; These instructions are of a temporary and provisional character.  They    clo not purport to define the existing rights of either Moslems or Jews, nor do    they prejudice the rights  and claims of Jews or Moslems.  These instructions    will remain in force only pending the determination of existing rights by an    authoritative body which  His Excellency has requested the Secretary of State    to cause to be constituted for the purpose.&quot;    It was thus made plain that the Regulations were provisional and would not prejudice the authoritative definition of rights.    They have, nevertheless, been received with a storm of protest from both sides     Enclosure II to Confidential Despatch to the Secretary of State dated                               January 17, 1930.Memorandum enumerating the Decisions taken in regard to the Establishments of    the Police and Defence Forces in Palestine and  Trans-J or dan since  1925 and    on the Defence Arrangements generally.    ON the 16th April, 1925, a conference Avas held in Jerusalem, at Avhich werepresent Mr. Amery, Secretary of State for the Colonies, Sir Samuel Hoare,  Secretaryof State for Air, and Sir Herbert Samuel, High Commissioner for Palestine.    This  Conference decided that  the  reorganisation of public  security  forces inPalestine  and Trans-J ordan should be undertaken in accordance with the  following principles :       (i)  A complete  separation between the police forces  and the local military           forces;     (ii)  Palestine and Trans-Jordan to be more self-dependent  in regard to local           defence;    (iii)  A reduction to be made in the amount of the Grant-in-Aid hitherto made           by the British Treasury  on this  account.    2.  At the date of this  Conference the Civil Forces of Palestine and Trans-Jordan were  as follows :     (a)  The Palestine Police Force;    (b)  The Palestine Gendarmerie;    (c) The British Gendarmerie;    \d)  The Arab Legion.    (a)  The  establishment of the Police was 73 officers and  966 other ranks, thelatter being all Palestinians.  They were distributed throughout Palestine on normalPolice duty, i.e., the prevention, detection and prosecution of crime.    (b)  The  strength  of the  Palestine Gendarmerie, a semi-military force,  was approximately 500.  They were distributed as follows:              Headquarters       ...       ...       ...    Sarafand.1112111trooptrooptrooptroopstrooptrooptroopJ ericho.Tulkarem.Metullah.Beersheba.Roshpina.Beisan,Samakh.-    One troop  consisted  of  1  British officer,  1 British  Warrant Officer  and approximately 50 other ranks.    The duty of the Palestine Gendarmerie was mainly frontier  control and theprevention of armed raids into Palestine.  They also assisted the police in dealingwith gangs of highway robbers and carried out police duties in specified areas    (c)  The  strength of the British Gendarmerie Avas approximately 450   Thevwere distributed as follows :-Headquarters and 2 Companies1 Company   ,     ....i Company         ...       ...1 Company         ...       ...1 Officer and 17 Other RanksSarafand.Nazareth.Jerusalem.Nablus.Haifa.
     One Company consisted of 4 Officers and approximately 80 Other Ranks.  From 1922-1924 the British Gendarmerie comprised a Mounted  Company as well.     The Force was trained on a semi-military basis and acted as an armed reserve to the Police,  and  co-operated in the extirpation of brigands.   They carried out motor car patrols on the main roads; they were  employed on escort  duties  and guards.   In  certain  emergencies detachments  were  temporarily  stationed  in Trans-Jordan.     (d) The. Arab  Legion, stationed  in  Trans-Jordan, had an establishment of 1,033 of all ranks and the Police and Prisons Staff of 72.     By the end of 1925 the numbers had been increased to 1,253 and 219 respectively, principally on account of the  taking over of  the Ma&apos;an Vilayet by the Trans-Jordan Government.     3.  Besides the Civil Forces described above, the following military forces were stationed in Palestine and Trans-Jordan ;          1 Regiment of Cavalry,         1 Squadron of aeroplanes,         1 Company of Armoured  Cars (R.A.F.),         1 Wireless Company (R.C. of Signals),           Palestine General Hospital,together with ancillary services.    4.  No written record of the Jerusalem Conference of the 16th April, 1925,appears to exist, but the general lines of the scheme of  reorganisation approved were stated  in  a   letter  from  the Air  Ministry to the  Colonial Office,  dated  the19th May, 1925, and were communicated to the High  Commissioner of Palestine in colonial Office despatch, Secret, the 16th July, 1925 (11/705/S/26), as  follows :-    (a) The British Gendarmerie to be reduced to 200 and  to be absorbed in  the          Police Force under the Acting Inspector-General of  Police;    (b) The total strength of the Police to be raised to  1,500;    (c) The Palestine Gendarmerie to become the Local Military Force at a strength          of  500 in  the  first  instance,  to  be  taken  over  by the Air  Officer          Commanding;    (d) The Cavalry Regiment to be withdrawn;    (e) Remaining units to remain unchanged.    5.  Sir Herbert Samuel thought that the scheme proposed at the Conference ofthe 16th April&apos;, 1925, involved considerable risks to the safety of the  country, and ina Secret despatch to the Secretary of State, dated the 19th April,  1925, he expressed his views on the situation.    In that despatch Sir Herbert  Samuel  dwelt especially on  the limitations ofair-craft and armoured cars  in a country such as Palestine,  and suggested that asmall British Military Force, preferably two companies of Infantry,  should again be  stationed in Palestine on the withdrawal of the cavalry regiment.    That suggestion, however, was  definitely rejected by the Air Ministry  in their letter of the 19th May, 1926, enclosed with Mr. Amery&apos;s Secret despatch of  the16th July, 1925.    6.  In his telegram No.  198 of  the  3rd July, 1925,  the  Secretary of Stateinformed  the  Palestine Government that  no official decision regarding the exactmeasures  to be adopted in  connexion  with the  reorganisation of the  PalestineGendarmerie would be reached until  Lord Plumer  had examined  the question  on.the spot.    Sir Herbert Samuel left Palestine  on the 30th June,  1925,  and Lord  Plumerarrived on the 25th August, 1925.    7.  After  studying  the  problem  Lord Plumer  made his proposals  in  hisConfidential despatches of the 30th October, 1925, and the 4th February, 1926.    He proposed the  disbandment  of the British Gendarmerie  and the PalestineGendarmerie, and the reconstitution of the Arab Legion as the Trans-Jordan police force.  He  also recommended the raising  of an  Imperial mounted  regiment, to be recruited locally,  as a military force to be paid for by His Majesty&apos;s Government.This force was raised, and was called the Trans-Jordan Frontier Force.
Under Lord Plumer&apos;s organisation the local forces therefore consisted of-    (a) Palestine Police.    (b) Trans-Jordan Frontier Force.    (c) Trans-Jordan Police (afterwards renamed the Arab Legion).8.   The details of Lord Plumer&apos;s proposals, as set out, were (a)  Palestine Police to be reinforced by 5 officers and 212 other ranks from the       British Gendarmerie and by 237 mounted policemen from the Palestine       Gendarmerie;  and by a Training School.(b)  Trans-Jordan Frontier Force to be recruited from the Palestine Gendarmerie       and the Arab  Legion and to consist of  the following:  :A mman-  Headquarters   ...       ...       ...      ...     36  2 Companies Mounted Rifles      ...      ...    306  2 Troops Hotchkiss Guns ...       ...      ...     75Ma&apos;an   1 Camel  Company        ...       ...            153Sarafand   1 Company Mounted Rifles       ...      ....    153Total     ...      ...       ...     723     (c) Trans-Jordan Police (afterwards renamed the Arab Legion) to be gradually           reduced, by the completion of contracts and recruitment to the Trans-           Jordan Frontier Force, from,  its existing establishment of 1,400  to  a           force  of 650,  not  costing more than   70,000.   The Trans-Jordan           Authorities, however, doubted the expediency of reducing the Civil Police           below 930 at an approximate cost of  90,000 a year.     9.  In his Confidential despatch of  the 30th October, 1925, Lord Plumer also expressed the opinion  that the then existing establishment of Royal Air Force inPalestine and Trans-Jordan was inadequate and should be increased by two flights.     The Air Ministry  objected to this on financial, strategic and political grounds(vide  Secret  telegram  from  Sir  Hugh Trenchard to  Lord  Plumer  of  the20th November, 1925.   &apos;&apos; The financial question  at  home is at  present  supreme.&quot;Vide also Colonial Office Despatch, Confidential A. of the 14th January, 1926).     In view of these representations Lord Plumer waived his request for an increaseof the Air Force on the understanding that  the flight of Bristol Fighters then inPalestine should be replaced by D.H.Q.A.S.     10.  Lord Plnmers proposals for the reorganisation of Public Security forcesin Palestine as set out above were generally approved by the Secretary of State inhis telegram No. 9 of the 18th January, 1926.     Correspondence followed mainly on the question as to whether the  Imperialor the Palestine  Government should bear the cost of the Trans-Jordan frontier force  and the  grant-in-aid to Trans-Jordan;  and also  on questions  of detailregarding the organisation.     11.&apos;  In February 1926, the Cavalry Regiment (IX Lancers) left Palestine withthe concurrence of Lord Plumer.  In the course  of 1926 the British Gendarmeriewere disbanded, the Trans-Jordan Frontier  Force was created  and the PalestinePolice were strengthened.     12.  The distribution of the reorganised military forces proposed by  the air officer Commanding and concurred in by Lord Plumer (Confidential despatch of the5th February, 1926) was :      . .   Amman-             1 Company  Mounted Rifles (T.J.F.F.).  - -         2 Sections Machine Guns (T.J.F.F.).  V:      Ma&apos;an-   ,      &apos;-:      &quot; .              ,                    ^   -: &apos;  ;   .  -     1 Company  Cavalry  (T.J.F.F.).         &apos;         Sarafand--                     -,&quot;&apos;.&quot;.&apos;      .       ;.      * .....             Headquatrers (T.J.F.F.).. &quot;  &quot; ,                       &apos;  .  - .             2 Companies Mounted  Rifles (T.J.F.F.).  .  -   &apos;   .    -,.       \ .  ,
        A mman             2  Flights Aeroplanes (R.A.F.).            1  Section Armoured Cars (R.A.F.).        Ramlen                                        .   -&apos;            1  Flight Aeroplanes (R.A.F.).            2  Sections Armoured Cars (R.A.F.).        Sarafand                 -                                    -            Command Headquarters (E.A.F:).            Depot for Transport, Repair and Supplies (R.A.F.).            Hospital (R.A.F.)    Before the end of 1926, however, Lord Plumer ordered that the whole of the trans-Jordan Frontier Force should be stationed in Trans-Jordan.    The final distribution of the Trans-Jordan Frontier Force was :-        Zerqa: Headquarters and 3 Companies.        Ma&apos;an: 1 Company.    13.   At the end of  1926, after the reorganisation, the  establishment  of theForces was :          (a)  Palestine Police                British officers  ...       ...      ...       ...       50               British other ranks      ...      ...       ...      200               Palestinian officers      ...      ...       ...       75               Palestinian other ranks  ...      ...       ...    1,300        (b)  Trans-Jordan Frontier Forces-                British officers and warrant officers        ...       31               Native officers  and other ranks   ...       ...      756        (c)  Arab Legion                British officers and warrant officers       ...        4               Native officers  and other ranks   ...       ...      833        (d)  Royal Air Force                1  Squadron  of aeroplanes.               1  Company of Armoured  Cars.                 Palestine General Hospital and ancillary services.        (e)  Royal Corps of Signals-               1  Wireless  Company.    14.   The strength of  the  Palestine Police has remained  fairly constant.  Thetotal establishment of Palestine Other Ranks remained from the end of 1917 to the23rd August, 1929, at about 1,300;  in addition, the establishment of British other ranks was 170 on the 23rd August.    The total number of British Officers remained 50,  of whom 3 were attached tothe British Section and 5 to the. Prison Service.    In 1928 the cost of the Palestine Police was  P. 363,656, all of which was borneby Palestine funds.    15.   There have been three successive annual reductions of the Trans-JordanFrontier Force  by 50 troopers, so that  the establishment of the Force was reduced from 750 at the end of 1926 to  a little over 600 on the 23rd August, 1929.    It was Lord Plumer&apos;s intention that the  Force should be reduced progressivelyat the rate of  50  per annum until a strength of 500 was reached.   This was to  beeffected  by not  replacing casualties amongst the troopers.  No reduction was to bemade in the number of officers and non-commissioned officers except as regards British^Warrant Officers, who should fall out as their contracts expired.    Lord  Plumer intended that the cadres of officers and non-commissioned officers should continue in existence in order that the Force might quickly be expanded to1,000 men should the necessity arise.   With this  object in view,  pari pussu withthe reduction, a Reserve was to be formed. The strength of this Reserve was fixed at first  at 150, and in July 1929 50 men were enrolled.   In 1928 the cost of the trans-Jordan  Frontier Force  was  P. 151,909,  of which  one-sixth was  borne  byBritish  funds.  Palestine  contributed  P. 31,000 to  the cost  of the military forcesof the Mandatory in Palestine and Trans-Jordan.       -            -
    16.  The strength of the Arab Legion has remained the same;  the Gendarmeriesection has been reduced by 20, and the Police and Prisons staff strengthened.    In 1928 the cost of the Arab Legion, which was entirely borne by Trans-Jordan,was  P. 98,662.    17.  The establishment of the Royal Air Force remained unchanged up to the23rd August, 1929.    18.  The defence arrangements generally were as follows :       (i) The Commandant of Police.worked out the numbers and provenance of          police reinforcements in certain  defined emergencies, and local Defence          Schemes were drawn up for the more important  centres in  conjunction          with the Officer Commanding the Royal Air Force.t     (ii) The Officer Commanding Trans-Jordan Frontier Force worked out similar          schemes for that Force.    (iii) As  there were no troops in Palestine, Lord  Plumer  inquired of the Air          Ministry whence he would be  able to obtain reinforcements in case of          emergency.  The reply was that, in case of emergency, the Cabinet would          decide that point,  but that, probably, reinforcements would come from&quot;         Egypt in the first place.    19.  It will thus be seen that the outstanding difference between the organisationand disposition of  the  public security  forces before and  after the reorganisationdecided upon by the Colonial Office and the Air Ministry in 1925 were as follows :     20.  At  the beginning of August 1925 there was considerable semi-military support for the Police by  the  presence of detachments  (each  composed of 4 Officersand 80 men) of British Gendarmerie at the principal strategic centres of Palestine;and by the presence of detachments (each composed of 1  British  Officer,  1 BritishWarrant Officer and 50 Palestinians) of the Palestine Gendarmerie at the principalstrategic points on the frontier between Palestine and Trans-Jordan.    The responsibilities of the Palestine Police were also diminished by the fact thatthe Palestine Gendarmerie did all the Police work in the frontier zone.    21.  At the beginning of August 1929, on the other hand, there was no support for the Police in Palestine in  the shape of organised&apos;military or semi-military land forces.  The police numbered about 1,300, as against 1,000 in  1928, but they were allengaged at  the same  time,  so  that  no reserve  of  force  was  available.   It was,therefore, impossible  to send  reinforcements to places where disturbances arose or were threatened.    22.  The only  semi-military units  actually present and  available in Palestinewhich could act as a reserve in support of the Palestinian Section of the Police werethe British Section of the Palestine Police, the effective strength of which, in August1929, was only  140, and  the  Special Constables,  numbering about 170, who werespecially enlisted after the disturbazices had broken out.o

</content>
</cab>
