<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 246-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   [This Document is the Property of His  Britannic  Majesty&apos;s Government.]                      Printed for the Cabinet.  April 1930.SECRET.   CP. 118 (80).                                  CABINET.                         The Nepal-Tibet Dispute.      MEMORANDUM  BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE  FOR  INDIA.   This dispute (arising out  of an  incident  in  the course of  which the NepaleseLegation at  Lhasa was violated by the Tibetans) has now been  peacefully  settled.The Government of India have throughout taken  the most energetic action to secure this result, and have been laced with great  difficulties due to the reluctance of theDalai  Lama  to send the  apology which the Government of Nepal had the right&apos;to expect.  Ultimately, on 6th March, the Dalai  Lama sent an adequate apology based ona formula suggested to him by the Government of India through Laden La, an officerof Tibetan race in their  service whom  they  sent to Lhasa to  facilitate  mediation.I circulate two telegrams from the  Government of India, one dated 22nd March,stating that the Tibetan communication  has been accepted by Nepal, and a further telegram of  26th  March  repeating an exchange  of  friendly messages  between theNepalese Prime Minister (Maharaja Sir Bhim  Shumshere Jung) and the Dalai Lama.These messages seem to leave no  room for  doubt  that the incident may now beregarded as closed.   This result is due in the first place  to the manner in which the Government ofIndia  nsed their good  offices  with both parties.   The difficulties  of their task andtheir strenuous and persistent  efforts to overcome them are clearly shown in theirvoluminous correspondence with Nepal and Tibet of which  I have received copies by every  mail.   I have sent a telegram to the  Government  of  India expressing the appreciation of His Majesty&apos;s Government and  congratulating them on the successful outcome of their efforts.   In the second place the avoidance of  war is due to thepatience exhibited  by the new Prime Minister  of Nepal.   I attach copy of  a telegram sent to him by the Government of India on  29th  January, communicating a message of appreciation of his attitude from the Viceroy.   It was suggested to the Government of India in a telegram  of 18th February thatif the dispute were peaceably settled  no time should be lost in supplying to theNepalese Government such of the  munitions for which they  had indented  as areavailable in India.   (It will be remembered that the supply  had been deferred whilethe dispute remained unsettled.)  It  was thought that the prompt supply of thesemunitions  after settlement  of the  dispute would  reassure  the  Nepalese  of  our determination  not  to fail in our Treaty obligations, as Nepal expects us to construethem in the light of past practice, and might also give evidence of  our moral  supportof the new Prime Minister.  In view of past experience of the fratricidal bloodshedusually attending a succession  in Nepal, it is surprising how easily Sir Bhim  appearsto have established himself, but there are several  factors  which  might tend  to make his position  unstable,  lie is  new to his office, he succeeds a man of outstandingpersonality and ability  (the well-known Sir Chandra Shumshere Jung),  and his attitude of forbearance during the  dispute  may  not have increased  his  popularitywith certain elements among his people.                                                                       W. B.    5th April  .1930.Telegram from Viceroy, Foreign  and. Political Department, to Secretary of State for                         India, dated 22nd. March 1930.   Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Peking.   911  S.   Our telegram of the 15th  instant, No.  832  S.  Nepal-Tibet.   BritishEnvoy, Nepal,  telegraphs 20th March :    &quot; Communication has been received from  the Tibetan  Government and acceptedby Nepal.&quot;     4435    75 4.30J
Telegram from  Viceroy, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary  of State  for     India, repeating telegrams from, British Envoy, Nepal, and Political Officer, Sikkim,     dated 26th March, 1930.    Addressed to Secretary of State for India and repeated to Peking.    952 S.   Our tele gram of  the 21st instant, No. 911  S.   Nepal-Tibet.  following telegrams are repeated for information :     (1) British Envoy, NepaTs telegram of 22nd March, No. 141 C.    &quot;Maharaja has telegraphed in most friendly terms to Dalai Lama and to TibetanGovernment accepting apology, and has instructed Nepalese  representative, Lhasa, to resume his functions  and also visit Dalai Lama, and to express  to  him  Maharaja&apos;sgratification.at settlement of the dispute.&quot;    (2) Political  Officer, Sikkim&apos;s  telegram of 24th March, No. 1 (1) P. 30.    &quot; Dalai Lama  has  telegraphed to Maharaja of Nepal, 24th March, acknowledginglatter&apos;s telegram.   He  expresses gratification  at its  receipt and  states  that he has&apos; now ordered Tibetan officials to act in all matters in  keeping with old friendship.&apos; &quot;Telegram from  Viceroy, Foreign and  Political Department, to Secretary of State for     India, repeating telegram to British Envoy, Nepal, dated  2Qth January 1930.    Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Peking.   Nepal-Tibet.  Following-telegram sent to British Envoy, Nepal :-    &quot; Please convey  following  message from  His Excellency the  Viceroy to  PrimeMinister  : &apos; I should like to  assure  Your Highness  with what satisfaction I havelearnt  from  my Envoy that   in  face  of  alarming  reports you have consented  to defer measures, the effects of which could not, in my judgment, have been  other thandetrimental to prospects of peaceful settlement which my Government  is anxiouslylabouring to secure.  By continuing  to  display patience  and forbearance,  Nepal  willwin approbation of my Government  and His Majesty&apos;s  Government  and throughoutthe civilised world, and her military position  will surely  not be  imperilled.   your highness is no doubt aware that an emissary from my Government is now  on his wayto Lhasa, and I hope  that nothing  will  be  done in  the  meantime  which couldprejudice the chances of his mission.&apos; &quot;

</content>
</cab>
