<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 346-354</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
24THIS DOCUMENT IS THE FHOPEHTY OF HIS BBIT&amp;MM1G m.?ESTY&apos;S GOYESNMENCONFIDENTIAL.          proposed anglo-EGYPTIAN  TREATY(27985)
PROPOSED  ANGLO-EGYPTIAN  TREATY.Articles agreed with, the Egyptian Delegation.         -           &apos;L   THE military occupation of Egypt by theforces of His Britannic Majesty is terminated.                     2.   An alliance is established between the highcontracting parties with a view to consolidatingtheir  friendship, their cordial  understanding and their good relations.   As Egypt intends to apply for membership of: the League  of  Nations,  His  BritannicMajesty  recognises  her  right as a  sovereignindependent State to become  a member of theLeague on complying with the provisions of theCovenant of the League.Each of the high contracting parties under-Treaty Proposals of 1929.Lines on which agreement in principle has been reached.          or appears likely to be reached.   THE military  occupation  of Egypt by theforces of His Britannic Majesty is terminated.   An alliance is established between the HighContracting Parties  in  consecration of  theirfriendship,  their  cordial  understanding  andtheir good relations.                     3.   Egypt, being anxious to become a member ofof the League  of Nations, will present  in  theconditions  prescribed by  article  1 of   theCovenant a request for admission to the League,which  His  Britannic Majesty undertakes tosupport.Each of the High Contracting Parties under-&apos; takes  not to adopt  in foreign  countries an ; takes not to adopt in foreign countries&apos; an atti-&apos;attitude-which is inconsistent with the alliance, i tude which is inconsistent with the alliance or
or to  conclude political treaties  inconsistent with the provisions of the present treaty.CDW        .  &apos;&apos;     &apos;    &apos;    5.              &apos;&apos;    1 Should a dispute with a  third  State  arise  which; in the terms of article 12 of the Covenant  of the League of Nations, is likely to lead to a  rupture  with that State, the high  contracting  parties will consult  each other with a ,view to  the settlement of  the  said dispute by peaceful  means, in accordance with the provisions of the  Covenant, and of any other international obliga-  tions which may be applicable to the case.   His Britannic Majesty recognises that theresponsibility for  the  lives and property  of foreigners in  Egypt devolves exclusively uponthe Egyptian  Government, who will ensure the fulfilment of their obligations in this respect.                      7/   Should, notwithstanding the provisions ofarticle 5 above,  either of the high contractingparties become engaged in war, the other highcontracting party will, subject always to theprovisions of article 14 below, immediately cometo-his aid in  the capacity of an ally.  -Hiswill create  difficulties  for the  other  Partythereto.  In pursuance of this undertaking theywill not oppose each other&apos;s policy in foreign-countries, nor conclude with a third Power any agreement of a political character which mightbe prejudical to the interests of the other Party.                      4.   Should any dispute with a third State pro-duce  a situation  which  involves a  risk  of a rupture with that State, the High ContractingParties will concert together with a view to thesettlement of the said dispute by peaceful means in  accordance  with  the  provisions  of  theCovenant of the League of Nations and of anyother international obligations which  may be applicable to the case.                      6.   His  Britannic Majesty  recognises that theresponsibility for the  lives  and property  of foreigners in Egypt devolves henceforth upon theEgyptian Government.   His Majesty  the king of Egypt  will  ensure  the  fulfilment  of hisobligations in this respect.                      7.   Should,  notwithstanding the provisions  ofparagraph 4 above, either of the High Contract-ing Parties, become engaged in war, the other high Contracting Party will, subject always tothe provisions of paragraph 14 below, immedi-ately come to his aid in the capacity of an ally.
Articles agreed with the Egyptian Delegation.Treaty Proposals of 1929.Egyptian Majesty&apos;s aid, in the event of war, orimminent  menace  of  war,  will  consist  infurnishing  to  His  Britannic   Majesty,   on egyptian  territory,  in accordance  with  theEgyptian system of administration and legisla-tion,  all the  facilities and assistance  in  his power,  including  the use of  his  ports, aero-dromes  and means of communication.   It will accordingly be for the Egyptian Government totake  all  the administrative  and legislativemeasures necessary to render these facilities and assistance  effective.       BRITISH DRAFT OF ARTICLE 9.   In  view of the fact that the Suez Canal,while being an integral  part of Egypt,  is  auniversal  means of communication  as  also anessential means of communication between thedifferent  parts of  the  British  Empire,  HisMajesty the King of Egypt, until such time as[the high  contracting parties agree that] theIn particular, His Majesty the King of Egyptwill, in the  event of  war  or  menace  of  war,furnish to His Britannic Majesty on egytian territory all the facilities and  assistance in mispower,  including the  use of  his  ports,  aero-dromes and means of communication.                      8.   In  view of the desirability of identity intraining and methods between the Egyptian andBritish armies, His Majesty the King of Egyptundertakes that, should he deem it necessary tohave recourse to foreign military instructors,these  shall  be chosen  from  amongst  Britishsubjects.                      9.   In  order to facilitate and secure to HisBritannic Majesty the protection of  the  suez canal  as an essential  means of communication between  the different parts  of the BritishEmpire,  His   Majesty  the  King  of  Egyptauthorises His Britannic Majesty to  maintainupon  Egyptian territory  in  localities to  beLines on which agreement in principle has been reached          or appears likely to be reached.  :    -.   The Egyptians have accepted the principleof this Article, but wish it to be expressed in theArmv Note rather than in the Treaty.   The Egyptians insist on the omission of thewords in square brackets.  This involves a vitalpoint of principle.   The British delegation are prepared to omit the words underlined provided that it is foundthat there is sufficient suitable hard ground, west of the  Canal at Ismailia and to the north and
Egyptian forces are in a position to ensure bytheir  own  resources  the  liberty  and  entiresecurity of navigation of the Canal, authorisesHis Britannic Majesty to station in the neigh-bourhood  of Ismailia and in an area north of suez, such forces as His Britannic Majesty con-siders necessary to ensure in co-operation withthe Egyptian forces the defence of the Canal;for the same purpose the Eoyal Air Force depotwill be transferred from Abukir to Port Fuad.The British forces will enjoy facilities for com-munications and will have access to the desertareas on either side of the Canal for purposes oftraining and manoeuvre. The presence of these forces  shall not constitute in  any manner an occupation and will in no way prejudice the sovereign  rights of Egypt.agreed upon, to the east of longitude  32c  E.,] west of Ismailia as far as Mahsama (10 milessuch forces as His Britannic Majesty considers : from Ismailia) to accommodate 8,000 men withnecessary for this  purpose.   The  presence  of  adequate training grounds.these forces shall not constitute in  any  manner jan occupation and will in no way prejudice  the sovereign rights of Egypt.                     10.   In view of  the friendship, between the twocountries and of the alliance contemplated in thepresent  proposals,  the Egyptian government when engaging the services of foreign officialswill     rule engage British subjects.                     11.   His Britannic Majesty recognises  that the jcapitulatory regime now existing in Egypt is no jlonger, in accordance with the spirit of the times and with the present state of Egypt.   His Britannic Majesty accordingly undertakes to use all his influence with the Powerspossessing  capitulatory  rights  in  Egypt toobtain,- in conditions which will safeguard the   The Egyptians refuse to accept this articleor to admit the principle which it embodies.   The Egyptians wish to  change the second paragraph,  but admit  that the form of thearticle will depend  on the agreement  to bereached in regard to the lines in which the reform of the Capitulations is to be effected.  They have promised but hot produced a note explainingtheir point of view.
Articles agreed with the &quot;Egyptian DelegationLines on which agreement in principle has been reached          or appears likely to be reached.                     13.   While reserving liberty to conclude new con-ventiqns in future modifying the conventions of1899,^the High Contracting Parties agree that without  prejudice  to  Egypfs   rights  andmaterial  interests the status of the Sudan shallbe&apos;, that  resulting from the  said conventions.Accordingly, the Governor-General shall  con-tihue to exercise on the joint behalf of the HighContracting Parties the powers conferred upon him by the  said conventions.legitimate interests of foreigners, the transfer tothe Mixed  Tribunals of the jurisdiction of theexisting Consular Courts, and the application of egyptian legislation to foreigners.                     12.    In view of the friendship between the HighContracting Parties and of the alliance contem-plated in the present proposals,  His BritannicMajesty will be represented at the Court of HisMajesty the King of Egypt by ah Ambassador.duly  accredited, and His Majesty the King ofEgypt wil reserve the highest diplomatic rank athis Court to the representative of His BritannicMajesty.    His Majesty the King of Egypt will be repre-sented at the Court of St. James&apos;s by an Ambassador.                     13.   While reserving liberty to conclude new con-ventions in future modifying the conventions of1899, the  High Contracting Parties agree thatthe status of the Sudan shall be that  resultingfrom the said conventions.    Accordingly,  theGovernor-General shall continue to exercise  onthe joint behalf of the High Contracting parties the powers - conferred upon him  by  the  saidconventions.   The Egyptians  accept the principle of our ambassador  enjoying special  precedence,  butwish the principle embodied in  an exchange of notes.   Though  the Egyptians have  accepted  thedraft in Column I, it is accompanied by a pro-posed  note  on  the Sudan which contains  anumber  of  passages  regarded  as  definitelyinacceptable.  This proposed note in rough draft is printed as an Annex hereto.
14.14.   Nothing in the present proposals is intendedtp or shall  in any way prejudice the rights and obligations which devolve, or may devolve, uponeither of the High Contracting Parties underthe Covenant of the League of Nations or theTreaty for the Renunciation of War signed at paris&apos;on the 27th August, 1928.                     15.   The High Contracting  Parties  agree  thatany difference on the  subject of the applicationor the interpretation of the provisions of thepresent proposals  which they are  unable tosettle  by  direct  negotiation  shall  be  dealtwith in accordance with the provisions of theCovenant of the League of Nations.                     16.   At any time after the expiration of a periodof twenty-five years from the coming into forceof the Treaty, the High Contracting  parties will, at the request of either of them, enter into negotiations  with a  view, to  such revision byagreement  between them of  its terms as may be appropriate in the circumstances as they  thenexist.   In  case of  disagreement  the differencewill be submitted to the League of Nations.    Nevertheless, at any time  after the expira-tion of a period of ten  years from the cominginto  force of  the  Treaty and  at  intervalsthereafter  of  not  less than ten years,  negotia-tions  may  be  entered into with the consent ofboth the High Contracting Parties with a  viewto such revision as aforesaid.   Nothing in the present proposals is intendedto or shall  in any way prejudice the rights and obligations which devolve, or may devolve, uponeither of the High Contracting Parties under theCovenant of the League of Nations or the Treaty -for the Renunciation of War signed at Paris onthe 27th August, 1928.                      15.   The High Contracting  Parties  agree  thatany difference on the  subject of the applicationor the interpretation of the provisions of thepresent proposals which they are unable to settleby  direct  negotiation shall be dealt with  inaccordance with the provisions of  the covenant of the League of Nations.                     16.   At any time after  the expiration of a periodof twenty-five years from the coming into forceof a treaty based on  the above proposals  such modification  of its terms as may  be deemedappropriate in the circumstances  as they  thenexist may  be  made by agreement between theHigh Contracting Parties.
                                  ANNEX.   Rough draft of the Sudan note communicated by the Egyptian  Delegation                               April 15, 1930.    By application of Article 13,.it is understood that Egypt&apos;s right of sovereignty over the Sudan remains  intact and that administration of the  Sudan  will beexercised by the High Contracting Parties in a joint and effective manner.    Accordingly, an Egyptian Deputy Governor will be appointed, as also Egyptianofficials, to co-operate with the British officials in the administration of the Sudan.Egyptian troops will return to the Sudan after the ratification of the Treaty.  Theremust be no restrictions upon Egyptians as to emigration, property and commerce.Foreign Office, April 15, 1930.
Counter-draft of Sudan Note as considered, without final recommendation, by-         British Delegation, not submitted to Egyptian Delegation.     IT  is desirable  to place on  record  our common  understanding  as to theinterpretation and application of Article 13 of the Treaty signed to-day.  We haveagreed that in recognition of the share of Egypt in the working and development ofthe system of administration and legislation for the Sudan created by the agreementof 1899,  and without prejudice to the conjoint sovereignty of the High ContractingParties over the territory the Governor-General, in whom the supreme military and civil command in the Sudan is vested, shall be recommended in the exercise of thesaid Powers to select and  appoint a certain number of  Egyptians possessing thenecessary qualifications to fill suitable vacancies in administrative posts in the Sudanas and when they occur.  We have also agreed that there shall be no discrimination in the Sudan between  British subjects  and  Egyptian  nationals in  matters ofcommerce and emigration or the possession of property.    It has further been  agreed that if  the Treaty is worked  in the same friendlyspirit in  which it has been  negotiated His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government will beprepared to examine sympathetically a proposal for  the return to the Sudan of an egyptian battalion with the withdrawal of the British forces from Cairo.[20935A]

</content>
</cab>
