<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 443-455</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Hi(PHIS DOCUMENT IS. THE PEQPBBJY Off HIS ERITAIIUIO MAJESTY1S QOvERMMMT.&apos;&quot;&quot;lI6&quot;COPY NO.37CAB I.QJ.League cf Nations Preliminary Conference with a view           to Concerted Economic Action.     Memorandum by the. President of the Board,of Trade.     1. I would refer to the memorandum which I submittedto my colleagues before the opening of this Conference(CP. 43(30) of the 8th February).     2, The Conference opened at Geneva on the 17thFebruary, and terminated on the 24th March:  the following is a summary account of its proceedings and its results forthe information of my colleagues.     3. The League1s invitation to all States to berepresented at the Conference was accepted by thirty of them,twenty-six of these being European (i.e. all the european countries except Albania and the Soviet Union):  of overseas countries, four participated actively, viz:  Japan, Peru,Colombia and Turkey.    Brazil, China, Cuba, the DominicanRepublic, Mexico, Persia and the United States sentobservers.   Of the twenty-six European countries,  it isnoteworthy that fifteen, including Belgium, France, Germanyand Italy, sent their Ministers of Commerce or othercompetent Ministers:   this is an unprecedented development in League Economic Conferences.     4. The Conference opened with four days&apos;  general discussion in which the representatives of all the  principalcountries took part.    The views expressed were,  withthe exception of those of the Italian representative,generally favourable to the proposals outlined for  the con-si deration of tli e  Conference- viz: a tariff truce to serve as a preliminary tc a programme  of multilateral negotiations for the-1-
reduction of obstacles tQ trade and especially  of excessivetariffs,   The Italian Minister of Corporations,  however,took  the line that the method of bi-lateral negotiations -in tariff matters had proved of value in the past, andthat to superimpose upon it a system of multilateralconventions would be liable to lead to complications and difficulties:  moreover, he argued that such multi-lateralnegotiations would be difficult in themselves owing tothe disparate situations of the various countries whichwould need to be taken into account *   Unfortunately theFrench Government fell on the second day of the Conference,and as a result of the twelve days1 political crisiswhich followed, the French delegation were unable during that time to take up any definite standpoint,     5, In these circumstances, the Conference divideditself at the end of the first week into two Commissions,of which the first was to consider the Truce, and thesecond the programme of further negotiations.   The firstCommission took as the basis of its work the draftConvention prepared by the Economic Committee, theprovisions of which were summarised  in my previous memorandum.   The work of the Commissions proceededwithout interruption till the 27th February, by  which time reports covering a  considerable part of the groundhad been produced.     6. On the  27th February, however, immediately aftertho reconstitution of the  second Tardisu Cabinet, theFrench delegation  stated that the French Government could.not accept the Truce proposals.   As it appeared evidentthat it would bo unprofitable  for the Conference  tocontinue considering the original Truce proposals, certain
fresh suggestions were taken as a basis for furtherconsiderations   Under these new proposals the  participantcountries were to be divided Into two groupsj   on the onehand those who do not normally consolidate their duties(a category which in practice coincides closely with thegroup of European countries who do not possess  comprehensivetariffs of a protective character),, and the tariff countries on the other,   The former would undertake obligationsolosely resembling those of the original Truce  proposal:while the second class would undertake not to increase,during the period of the Truce, those duties which were,at the critical date, consolidated in their commercial treaties, and as regards non-consolidated duties, would undertake to give previous notice and the opportunity forany State which might consider itself to be adversely affected to make representations in regard to any proposed increase, subject to the right of denunciation by anycountries who were not satisfied by the action taken ontheir representations,     7. This was the  situation on the 7th i&amp;rch, whenM, Flandin, who had by then been re-appointed Minister ofCommerce in the new Tardieu Cabinet, returned to Q-eneva.Before making any public pronouncement, he placed himself in communication with the British delegation,,   11* Plandinwas in general agreement with the new proposals but  statedthat his Government could not go so far as to undertake not to modify at all duties already consolidated In  anycommercial treaty with another High Contracting party,when it could be done by agreement with the other party tothe treaty.   They would be willing, however, to enter intoa commitment  not to denounce their commercial treatiesduring the period of  the Truce;  to give 20 days&apos; notice ofany proposed  increases of tariffs and  concede to any Partywho regarded  himself as being  Injuriously affected by  such increases, the right to ask for the immediate opening
                                                     -     32?Of negotiations with a view to restoring the  equilibrium thusdisturbed.   Should these negotiations not lead to  a  result  within two months, the complainant Party should be entitled  to denounce the Convention.     8. The new proposals already under discussion fixed theoriginal period of validity of the Truce for one year only,  withthe option of extensions, and to this Ivl. Flandin agreed.  He  didnot, however, at this stage think it possible to dispense  with thescheduling of exceptions in favour of particular countries,  towhich  I had previously drawn attention as a possible  source  of danger in tho original Truce proposals.   His preoccupation inthis direction was to cover the  so-called French 1 padlock law&apos;,which makes possible the immediate imposition by administrative action, subject to subsequent legislative sanction and without previous notice, of increased duties upon a number of the items of agricultural produce  which principally interest France,    Inthe public speech which  he delivered  on  the following day in thoPlenary Conference, iVI, Flandin avoided making  any definitesuggestions, and in the  main confined himself  to generalobsex^ations on tho problem, the tenor  of which was to minimizethe importance of  tariffs  as a factor in Europe&apos;s economic difficulties,     9, Both before this date and after-  ii, Flandin&apos;a speech theBritish delegation laid  especial emphasis  on the tariff issue.They pointed out that  most questions  affecting matters  otherthan tariffs could be, and indeed were  already being, dealt withby  the Eoonomic Organisation  of  the League to  a  large  extentwithout the necessity for a Tariff Truco or for  any  specialmandate from the Governments, and that  negotiations  for reducingtrade  barriers, of which the  chief were  tariffs, constituted  the cardinal  reason for  the  calling  of  the Conference.   They thoreforomaintained that the  subject of tariffs  should  bo given  specialprominence in  the  programme.   Effect was  eventually given  tothis contention,-   The  Italians  in particular  had desired thatno  special prominence  should bo  given to the question of Tariffs,
    10. Having regard to the critical sta^s which the work ofthe conference had reached, I thought it veil to return atthis juncture to ueneva, and in a speech in the Plenaryconference on March 14th I emphasized the minimum requirements which \re must insist on;  viz: that as regards the Truce,while vie were disappointed that it had not been found possibleto accent a binding and comprehensive engagement such as had originally been proposed, we- could accept the new Proposals-jrovided that they did not undergo any further weakening.  I also pressed that the exceptions which were to be put up forthe approval of the Conference should be kept within the narrowest possible limits, if any were to be retained.  FinallyI insisted on the extreme importance of opening the actualnegotiations for tariff reduction at the earliest possible moment, as being the ultimate raison d&apos;etre of the jonferenoe.I closed with a warning that any failure of the conference could not but give a strong renewed impetus to protectionismin all countries.     The  principal instruments under theConference&apos;s consideration, i.e., the modified Truce and the^rograrrme of further negotiations, were ultimately adoptedsubstantially in the form which they had reached at thisstage.    11.  Difficulties were encountered as soon as the lists of exceptions were put up by individual countries for theapproval of the Conference.   The French themselves desired tomake an exception for their &quot;padlock law&apos; relating to duties on agricultural produce, v/hich has already been mentioned.Others shoved a dis position to follow their exar-principle, with theresult that the agricultural countries of central and eastern europe would evidently have refused to adhere to theConvention, and it became olear that in other respects alsothere was little hope of limiting the exceptions to what was really necessary.   In these circumstances it was decided to
drop the method of scheduling exceptions, and insteadcertain provisos ware introduced into the operative clauses of the Convention, by which the undertakings given by the&quot;tariff5 countries in regard to previous notice of increases and negotiations relative thereto are not to apply in caseswhere the countries concerned are prevented from givingsuch notice or entertaining such negotiations by provisionsof particular laws or by circumstances of urgency.     12* Eventually the Conference concluded its work onthe 24th March with the signature of our documents, (l) aCommercial Convention; (2) an explanatory Protocol attachedto the Convention; (3) a Protocol regarding a programme of future negotiations;  and (4) a Final Act.   Of these,Nose (l) and (2), which forma single instrument, are subject to ratification; (3) and (4) ar? not.   Document (3)becomes operative on signature only, since it merelyinvolves acceptance ox a programme of negotiations and procedure to give effect bo it..   (4), the Final Act, containonly recommendations by the Conference, and has no bindingforce.     13.  The Commercial Convention and its explanatoryProtocol provide generally that existing Commercial treaties and Agreements in existence between any two High ContractingParties on March 24th, 1930, shall not be denounced beforethe 1st April, 1931, though the possibility of agreedmodifications being made in existing Treaties by means of bilateral negotiations between the signatory States is not excluded.   A result of this is to ensure that the period ofconsolidation of the duties governed by such Treaties and agreements is extended to the same extent and under the same conditions as the Treaties or Agreements in which they areembodied.
     14,   As regards Customs duties generally, a distinction Is made between the States which make a practice of consolidating rates of duty in their commercial treaties and those which do not normally do so.   As regardsthe former class, which includes the majority of continental countries, it is provided that, if they are obliged to make increases of duty as compared with theposition on March 24th* 1930, they will, wherever they arenot prevented from, doing so by the provisions oi tueir laws or by circumstances of urgency, give to the other Partiesto the Convention twenty days&apos; previous notice.of such increases, and will also, ii any State party to theConvention considers taat its interests are likely oo be seriously affected, enter upon friendly negotiations withsuch State in order to restore the equilibrium so disturbed.An aggrieved Party may denounce the Convention unlessnegotiations lead to a result within two months.     15,  The second class, i.e. those States which donot make a practice of consolidating duties in their commercial treaties, (Great Britain, Denmark, the Netherlands;Norway and Portugal are so enumerated) undertake not toincrease their protective duties or impose new protective duties as compared with the position on March 24th, 1930during the period of the Convention:  thay may, however,Increase their fiscal duties (i.e. duties not having as taeirobject the protection of national production against foreigncompetition) or impose new fiscal duties, without previousnotice and without the liaoility of being called on oonegotiate.   States parties x,o t^e Convention who considerthat their int rests hav-:- been Injured by such increasesmay, however, denounce the Convention.
     16.  As already mentioned, the Convention terminates on1st April, 1931, unless extended.   It may be prolongedthereafter by successive periods of six months if no Stateparty to it announces its intention of withdrawing.   If any state makes use of Its right to withdraw, any otner Party tothe Convention may require all the Parties to be consultedfor the purpose of taking a decision regarding the Convention.If necessary, a further Conference may then be summoned to reconsider the whole situation as regards the Convention..     17.  The Protocol regarding a programme of futurenegotiations is the second of the instruments contemplated by the Tenth Assembly1s Resolution.   It makes provisionfor the initiation of negotiations between the signatoryStates (after the necessary preparatory work), with a viewto facilitating economic relations and reducing hindrancesto trade.   Among ohe means of achieving this aim, special attention is drawn to those in the sphere of Customs andnotably those which have the effect of reducing duties.The negotiations are also to deal with the questions of theadoption of a uniform Customs nomenclature, simplificationof Customs formalities, indirect protectionism, exportbounties and subsidies, veterinary regulations, etc.   Theimportance of opening negotiations before the expiration ofthe Commercial Convention (i.e. before 1st April, 1931) isEtressed, since that Convention, it is pointed out, is designed as a preliminary step int-extended to ensure thatthe future negotiations shall be held under favourable conditions and in an atmosphere of tranquillity.     18.   The Final Act contains certain recommendations by the Conference, notably that the Economic organisation
 of  the  league  of nations  should  investigate the means of establishing co-operation in  the matter of trade relations between Europe and  the  overseas  countries, considering that overseas  countries  should be  associated with the proposed future  negotiations to  the greatest possible extent.     19,  The instruments  drawn up by the conference remain open for  signature  till the 15th April, 1930.  The convention must, be ratified before 1st November, 1930, and a meeting                                               - of the Contracting  Parties is to be called between 1st and     N 15th November, which shall fix the conditions of its coming into force, that is the number of ratifications required and, if necessary, the list of  States whose accession is considered l\                                                               I indispensable.  It may of  course be that at the meeting in November  the Convention will  be blocked by the Insistence by some countries on conditions  that are not and are not likely to be fulfilled,  as the Convention is concluded in the first instance for the period from April 1st 1930, tu April 1st 1931, the observance of its  undertakings even before ratificationwill evidently be necessary to enable a country to ratify,     20.  At the final Plenary meeting of the Conference, the various instruments were  signed by the following States:-                                                                I          (1)  The Commercial Convention and its explanatory Protocol by eleven States, viz - Germany,  Austria, Belgium,Great Britain,  Estonia, Finland, France, Italy, Luxemburg, the Netherlands and&apos; Switzerland;          (2)  The Protocol regarding the  programmed of future  \negotiations by fifteen States ive. those  who signed theConvention, with the addition of Greece, Latvia, Lithuania and Portugal;  and
         (3)  The Final Act &quot;by seventeen States, viz  -  those who  signed the Protocol mentioned in (2)  plus Denmark and Sweden .      In  addition,  the following  countries also signed by April 15th (the closing date for signatures):-         (l)  The Commercial Convention:  Denmark, Greece, Latvia,  Norway,  Poland,  Roumania,  Sweden,  makirg a  total  of 18 signatures  to this instrument (including all the &apos;non- conventionalising&apos; countries referred  to  in Article 4 except Portugal):         (2)  the Protocol of  Further Negotiations:  Czecho- slovakia, Denmark, Hungary,  Norway, Poland, Roumania,  Sweden, Yugoslavia,  making a  total of 23 signatures:      &apos;   ^^&quot;js-i^fc- TP ft ni HI Act by States who have not signed the Convai tion may  accede to it  after  it has  been brought  into force; the Convention also contains the usual form of Colonial Clause,  under which States who so desire  may make the Convention applicable to  any of  their Colonies, etc., or thereafter v/ithdraw its  application to any of them, at any time during  its  currency.     21.   While  the instruments  drawn up by the Conference lack to  some extent the binding  and precise character of  the original proposals, in my opinion they were fully worth adopting with a  view  to making an attempt  to mitigate the obstacles to our export presented by trade barriers in Europe. In some respects the  greater elasticity in  the arrangements concluded is an  improvement,  and if it should lead to eventualfailure  the blame cannot  be  laid at our door.  Moreover it is certain  that insistence  on the original ideas would have  lead to the breakdown of the Conference,  and the probable result would have been  the postponement of any attempt to  give effect                               -10-
 to  the recommendations of  the v/orld Economic Conference regarding Tariffs to  some  indefinite future, and a strong revulsion towards protection in the European countries generally, v/hich would have defeated the very object that the Conference set itself out  to attain.     22.  Mention should here &quot;be made of the manner in which various points of detail to which I referred in my previous memorandum have been dealt with.  The Key Industry Duties were explained in a statement by the British Delegation which was circulated to the Conference:   in this it was explained that in our view, no contravention of the provisions of theConvention was involved, and to this no objection was made.     23.  No provision ve.s made for the permissible substitu- tion of import duties for prohibitions and we did not raise the question.  Consequently if it should be necessary to continue the protection of the manufacture of dyes after theDyes tuffs Prohibition Act runs out early next year, the Act would have to be temporarily extended during the period of the Truce.     24.  The provision for arbitral jurisdiction in regard to disputes arising out of the Convention has been dropped, asbeing out of place in an agreement of this characters&apos;  each state is left to judge whether the action of other par-ties in any given case would justify it in denouncing theConvention.     25. The definition of fiscal duties mentioned in my previous memorandum met with numerous objections when it was discussed;  indeed,  in the tariffs of Continental countries any distinction between fiscal and protective duties is as a rule difficult to draw, since practically all their dutiespartake of both of these characters.   Consequently the
Convention merely provides that a wide interpretation shallnot he placed upon the term &quot;fiscal&quot;, and that in particularfiscal duties are not to he understood to include those whichhave as their object the protection cf national productionagainst foreign competition.     26. The original provision for conditional ratificationhas been dropped, but it will be seen that Germany, Prance andItaly are among the States who have signed the Convention.The Parliamentary arrangements in various countries made itimpossible for ratifications to be required before thebeginning of November, and in these circumstances it wasdecided that a Conference of the States who have ratifiedshould be summoned early in November, after the final date forratifications, in order to take a decision as to the putting into force of the Convention.   In the meantime it willcontinue to operate even as something more than a moral obligation, since evidently any States who in the meantimetook action clearly contrary to its provisions could not claim the right to ratify.     27. Finally, I may refer to the announcement made by the hungarian delegation, before the conclusion of the Conference,that It was unable to sign the Convention, in view of the factthat considerable comment has been made on this declaration inthe press.     The reasons which led the Hungarian representative totake up this attitude were (at any rate ostensibly, and Ithink actually) of a quite special order;-  they may besummarized as follows.-     Hungary is a pre-dominant supplier of agricultural produce to her neighbours, Austria and Czechoslovakia.-  . Lastyear&apos;s superabundant harvest, which was practically universalthroughout europe, led to a collapse in the price of cereals,and the consequent importation of low-priced cereals intoAustria and Czechoslovakia caused the Governments of those
                                                   -     336                                                   A&amp;tcountries to desire to raise their duties on this produce.They were&apos;, however, prevented from doing so owing to thefact that these duties were &quot;conventionalized&quot; In theirtreaties with Hungary,   They therefore desire to modifythese treaties, and wish to retain for this purpose the&quot;leverage&quot; which the power of denunciation would confer on them:  they would, however, he deprived, of this power by the prolongation of the Treaties in question under Article I.The situation was not explained to the Conference till a verylate stage in the proceedings, but what seemed at the time asatisfactory solution was found, in making a specialexception in favour of Austria and Czechoslovakia in respectof these Treaties.   The Hungarian delegate took part in the conversations which resulted in this arrangement, which willbe found in Section C of the Protocol ad Article I of theConvention, and provisionally he raised no objection, as it seemed the best that could be done;  but it appears that hisGovernment were not satisfied, and he accordingly declared inthe First Commission, two days before the close of theConference, that the modification respecting these particulartreaties had deprived the Convention of all its value so faras his country was concerned, and that accordingly Hungarycould not sign or ratify it*   It would not have beenadvisable for the Conference simply to ignore the requestof Austria or Czechoslovakia, since the result would no  doubt have been a refusal on the part of these countries to sign the Convention;  and, in view of the tendency of certain countries to make their attitude dependent on that cfneighbouring States, the consequence might have been fatal tothe Convention.   In these circumstances the Conference hadno alternative but to attempt to localize the trouble in theway it did.                                    \7.G.Beard of Trade,     22nd A-april, 1930.

</content>
</cab>
