<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 458-463</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE, PROPERTY OF KIS 3R IT AMI 10 MAJESTY1 S GOVSiiMMEflT ).  SECRET.  CLP. 132(50).                           CABINET.                          LIQXFQR SMUGGLCTG.             ffote byi the. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.                    I circulate to my colleagues a memorandum          dealing with the desire of the United States Consul at          Edinburgh to be informed by the Collector of Customs at          Leith when shipments of liquor are made from that port          to Amsterdam, Antwerp, Copenhagen and Hamburg, which have          been in the past, and doubtless still are used, as          bases for the illicit liquor trade.                          (Intld.)  A. H.COFf 15o.foreign Office, S^if. 1.,          April 28th, 1930.
                  M E M 0 B A N, 1) U. M.                   Liquor Smuggling.          In the suomer of 1926 there were held in london aseries of informal conferences between British and United states officials, the object of which was to ascertain to what extent itwould be possible for His Majesty1 s Government, without seeking the amendment of existing legislation, to co-operate with theGovernment of the United States in combating liquor smugglingfrom the sea, with particular reference to the participation ofBritish ships in the Illicit liquor trade.    These conferencesresulted in a joint report embodying a number of suggestions which were subsequently adopted - for administrative co-operation on the part of the appropriate British authorities in this country;and in the West Indies, and these suggestions were carried intoeffect in due course and have worked satisfactorily enough duringthe last four years.    The only one of the eight &quot;suggestions11contained in the joint report with which we are immediately concerned Is Ho. 3, providing f^r a special liaison in Londonbetween the Registrar-General of Shipping and Seamen and other british government offices on tho one hand and the United StatesConsul-General on the other.    The wording of suggestion Bo. 3was as followss-          ,TThe United States Consul-General in London should     keep in touch with the Registrar-General of Shipping     and Seamen and other British Government officers, so     that he may obtain on request on the usual termsi-          (a)  Information as to whether a vessel flying               the British flag has been given a provision-               al or permanent British Register.          (b)  Information as to whether the name of a               vessel flying the British flag has been               changed lawfully.
          (c)  Information as to the names and addresses of               the registered owner or owners and mortgagees               of a vessel under the British flag, and^  if a               company or corporation, the registered office               of that company or corporation, as well as               any information that can be given as to the               shareholders.          (d)  Tho Mercantile Havy last and monthly supplements.          fe)  Certified copies of registers and of all               doovunents relating thereto.          (f)  Any information that can be given, by reference               to lloyd publications or otherwise, as to the               movements of suspect vessels or cargoes&quot;.          On February 26th last the United States Embassy drew the attention of the Foreign Office semi-officially to a report which they had received from the American Consul at Edinburghwhich emphasised that whiskey was constantly being removed frombonded warehouses at that port for shipment to continental portswhere it was &quot;concentrated for despatch to ports on the westernside of the Atlantic from whioh it is smuggled into the UnitedStates&quot;.    The Consul suggested that in those circumstances, ifhe could be informed by the local Collector of Customs of the shipment to Amsterdam, Antwerp, Copenhagen and Hamburg of &quot;sizablecargoes or whiskey&quot; he could then pass this information on to hiscolleagues at the four continental ports in question, and they in turn would presumably watch for the departure of liquor-ladenvessels clearing for destinations on  the pacific coast of Mexicoand Central America which are used as advance bases for supplyingsmuggling vessels hovering off the coasts of California and Oregon          After this proposal had been carefully considered it was submitted officially to the Board of  Customs and Excise on April3rd, with a recommendation that it should be granted.  In supportof this recommendation it was suggested to the Board of Customsthat His Majestyrs Government were already committed by their acceptance of the suggestions contained in the joint reportresulting from the informal conferences of 1926 to providingthrough the  special liaison between the United States Consul-
General in London and the competent British authorities any information that could be given by reference to lloyd publica-tions or otherwise as to the moveiae&amp;ts of suspect vessels orcargoes.   The point was also made that while it  could not be suggested that all liquor exported from Leith to Amsterdam, Antwerp,Copenhagen and Hamburg was destined for Illegal importation intothe United States, it was none the less a fact that the ports inquestion had been in the past and doubtless still were used asbases of supply for smuggling vessels.          The opinion was also expressed that by granting thefacilities now sought by the American Consul at Leith His Majesty^Government would strengthen their position vis-a-vis the Govern-ment of the United States in resisting any attempt on the partof the latter to seek such assistance in their fight againstliquor smuggling as would call for fresh legislation irj. thiscountry.          It will be recalled in this connection that during thePrime ministers conversations with the President of the United &apos;States in Washington in October last, Mr. Hoover expressed a wish that His Majestyrs Government would take steps to prohibit theexport of liquor from the United Kingdom to any destination whereIts importation was forbidden.     In practice no liquor is evercleared direct from a UiiitSu Kingdom port to a port In the UnitedStates, and In the circumstances the action desired by Mr,, Hoover,which would call for the amendment of existing law, would have as its object the remedying of a non-existent ovil.          The fact remains, however, that the Canadian Governmenthave lately introduced legislation to the above effect to dealprimarily with the unsatisfactory and unique situation which has long existed on the Great Lakes where vessels ha-ve cleared at frequent intervals from Canadian ports to such destinations asDetroit.   The action of the Dominion Government in finally
acquiescing after months if not years of delay in the representa-tions made by the United States Government against theseconditions may well Induce the latter to press their demandsagainst this country.,    In this connection it is pertinentto observe that one of the results of the measures about to been forced by the Canadian authorities may well be to stimulate the already extensive export of liquor from Canada to suchdestinations as St. Pierre et Miguelon, the Bermudas and british west Indies and ports in Mexico and Central America  and therebycause a revival on liquor smuggling from the sea, which, duringthe last three years, has fallen off very considerablye          Furthermore, if the new Canadian legislation proveseffective in stemming the illicit importation of liquor on theGreat Lakes, &quot;bootleggers&quot; In the United States may be expectedto look elsewhere for their supplies and this in turn may leadto an increase in the direct shipment of liquor from Europeancontinental ports.   As unhappily, the majority of shipsparticipating in this trade fly the British flag, any develcp-ments cf the nature outlined above may be expected to lead tofurther pressure from the United States Government for extendedassistance on the part of His Majesty1s Government.  The lattermight find themselves at a disadvantage In dealing with such representations were they to have to admit that they had latelyfound it impossible to agree to a measure of co-operation longsince admitted in principle.          On April 11th, the Board of Customs and Excise agreedthat the facilities sought by the United States Consul at Leithshould be granted, and in doing so outlined In detail theprocedure to be adopted, adding that they attached considerable importance to the principle that confidential Information of
this nature should be  furnished only to career membersof tho American Consular Service and not communicated to temporary or tmsalariod employees-     There Is no reasonto suppose that this condition will not be entirelyagreeable to the United States Embassy.                  (Sgdo)  G- H. (THOMPSON,April 15th, 1930.

</content>
</cab>
