<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 596-600</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.as DOCUMENT ISIt is requested that special care may be taken to     ensure the secrecy of this document.?VERW?fFNT ).0 A B I N E T145(30)OH EMPLOYMENT POLICY (1950) COMHt TTEEMemorandum by the First Commissioner of WorksMosley memorandum I do not desire to enter into any lengthy counterargument with my oolleagues of the Cabinet sub-committee Inconnection with their report on the Mosley memorandum, andthe proposals set forth by sir Oswald Mosley,, Mr*  Tom  Johnstonand myself on Retirement Pensions.  It  iss however, necessaryfor me, as a member of the Cabinet, that I should, on  my ownbehalf and without any consultation with others, put on recordas briefly as I am able^ my dissent from some of the conclusionsarrived at.Rat1onalIsat iontion.o  The Labour movement, however, has  claimed  that  theworkers must not, and when we are In power,  shall  not  be calledupon to bear the cost of these changes  in the  form of  misery,privation and want caused by Inevitable unemployment,  and  ourdemand, voiced by all our leaders in written and  spoken wordsfor nearly 40 years, has been that when work was  not availablefor willing workers, the State and Local  Authorities must provide work or adequate maintenance for  these unemployed persons, their wives and dependants*  The late JosephChamberlain, as far back as 7885, laid  this  down  as the policywhich Governments should adopt so far as  work  was concernedP andour Labour movement added adenuate maintenance apart from  the poor Law, as the only alternative, when - neither privateNobody outside Bedlam opposes  the policy  of rationalisation-enterprise-
 enterprise  nor.the  State  or Municipality  could provide work,        Today  in office  we are  faced with  a  desperate  situation which the report of our colleagues assumes  will only  be  settled by vigorous and  persistent reorganisation -ea^-^e^Hrg-fer^hutlett?;  and to this  end supports the Lord Privy  Seal in  his efforts  to  advise and persuade 3?anious industries to adopt this course.        On  the  question of work the Cabinet has, on the  advice of the Minister  of Agriculture, rejected any idea of land cultivation and development as  a means of  providing work in this  country. Migration to  the Dominions, and Colonies we  are told.is not  practical politics -  an elaborate scheme for land settlement In Western Australia,,  put  forward  by an important official of the Ministry of Labour sent out specially to report on the  subject by the late Government, is  treated  with humorous indifference as  a matter not worth a moment&apos;s consideration.  The conclusion of the whole matter is that the workers who pinned their faith  to us and  our declarations in &quot;Labour  and  the  Nation&quot;, in our Election Manifesto, and  the broadcast appeals of our leaders, are now to be told  we  have no                                            an extension of immediate measures  for  dealing with the evil other than^those  and  various  proposals  for the development  of private enterprise on adopted by  our  predecessors^     I a^ not  unmindful  of  the fact                                  /what is  termed a long view basis * that  nearly 100 million pounds worth of^work is under considerations R^irgment  Pensions                    &apos;        Before the General Election and during  the  election, no&apos; subject was more widely discussed than the  raising of the  school age and  retirement  pensions for aged  workers.  Our leaders and.  our party conference  recognised  the difficulty  of providing  immediate work for  the unemployed  which would arise  if we  came into  power, and declared  in clear and  unmistakeable language  that  our policy would be  to keep  young people out of the  labour market until they reached 15  years  of age, and later on  to  raise  the  age  to  16, This proposal is  in process of being carried out.    On  the  question of retirement pensions  we were just  as explicit -  the  aged were  to  be  given  a                                                           chance
enterprise nor the State or Municipality could, provide work.       Today in office we are faced with a desperate situationwhich the report of our colleagues assumes will, only be settled, byvigorous and persistent reorganisation ^^4-^4.^Lrlbutloiif and tothis end supports the Lord Privy Seal in his efforts to advise andpersuade Fanious industries to adopt this course.        On the ciuestioh of work the Cabinet has, on the advice ofthe Minister of Agriculture, rejected any idea of land cultivationand development as a means of providing work in this country.Migration to the Dominions, and Colonies we are told,is not practical politics - an elaborate scheme for land, settlement in Western Australia., put forward by an.important official of the Ministry ofLabour sent out specially to report on the subject by the late government, is treated with humorous indifference as a matter not worth a moment&apos;s consideration.  The conclusion of the whole matter is that the workers who pinned, their faith to us and our declarationsin &quot;Labour and the Nation&quot;, in our Election Manifesto, and  the broadcast appeals of our leaders, are now to be told we have no                                            an extension of immediate measures for dealing with the evil other than^those and various proposals for the development of private enterprise onadopted by our predecessors/      I an not unmindful of the fact                                  /what is termed a long view basis.that nearly 100 million pounds worth of^work is under consideration.Re^tiremerxt pensions                     &apos;       Before the General Election and during the election, nosubject was more widely discussed than the raising of the school age and retirement pensions for aged, workers.  Our leaders and.  our party conference recognised  the difficulty of providing immediate workfor the unemployed which would arise if we came into power, and declared  in clear and  unmistakeable language that our policy wouldbe to keep young people out of the labour market until they reached16 years  of age, and later  on  to raise the age  to 16.  This proposals is in process of being carried out.   On  the question of  retirement pensions  we were  just  as  explicit - the aged were to be given a                                                          chance
chance of retiring and thus making room for the able-bodied.       My object in calling attention to these facts is to remind the Cabinet that if there is anything stupid or uneconomic in theproposal to substituteable bodied workers for aged workers,  thanthose responsible for the party?s policy must accept to the full responsibility for this stupidity.  My colleagues, who, with me,signed the report on pensions; never claimed that we were findingnew. work for anybody - what we did claim was that a policy suchas we recommended would leave vacancies for able-bodied people to fill, and thus, in so far as vacancies were created, would reducethe number of able-bodied persons receiving money for nothing.       The chancellor and his committee recommend the Cabinet toIssue a considered repudiation of the Retirement Pensions policy.If this is intended to refer to the emergency scheme, [ respectfullysubmit that our full scheme must be published at the same time.  .If the suggestion Is that we should reject the policy as laid down at the 1928 conference, and embodied in &quot;Labour and the Nation&quot;                                             -and later in our Election Manifesto, I suggest that no decision of                     -the Cabinet oan bind the party, whose policy is laid down only bythe annual conference.  The Cabinet, of course, decides in what manner and at what time it will introduce reforms, but it has no power, and would not desire.,  1 should imagine, to have power  todetermine the propaganda of the Party,,  It is necessary for us  all to keep this in mind because  our people am  still teol^voVffi in  thec4i&amp;^^^**e  that most of us so enthusiastically preached  in  our propaganda days, that it is much better to provide  education  forthe young and  comfortable  leisure  for the  aged, than to pay able-bodied people  to live in idlenessB  Mr,-, Banfield  in my hearingdevoted  some time  at one of his meetings to  advocacy of  this,  policy        I  therefore earnestly  hope  the  Cabinet  will  not hastilyaccept  the  sweeping  condemnation  of  the Mosley memorandum?  or the                                                        propos !,l
proposal to reject the policy of Retirement Pensions0  1 amwriting before the event so I am not swayed by Fulham one way orthe other.  I desire to say that the Liberal Party lost its holdand was driven from the counsels of the nation because it failedto live up to its declared -policy and. programmes.  Our Party, and certainly not Mosley, . Johnston or myself, do not cry for the moonnor expect our whole policy to be carried through in a year or eventwenty years, but it is the apparently contemptuous rejection of policies adopted by the Party, and on which we obtained votes,which I object to, and the fact that a policy of loan raising andspending up to, I think, 200 million pounds, advocated by LordPassfield in the House of Commons, is now spoken of in terms of something like ridicule.   It makes me ask myself whether, if theCabinet does anything at all, we should not tell the nationwithout reservation that the statements in &quot;Labour and the nation&quot;and in our Election Manifesto concerning unemployment, were ill-thought out and not worth the paper they were written on.HoMo Office of Works   6th May, 1930,

</content>
</cab>
