<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/211/0 images: 633-652</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE, PROPERTY OF 13,XS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S                                                   ISecret CP.HuK^O). 0 A B 1 N E T&quot;           Copy No                 CHARING  CROSS ... SCHEME...          Memorandum by the Minister of Transport *         I wish to refer to my Memorandum C.P.if2(30) ofuth February, 1930* in which the Cabinet were informed in general terms of the character of the scheme for a new bridge atCharing Cross finally adopted by the London County Council with my approval and. of the opposition on the part of the RoyalInstitute of British Architects and other similar bodieso         The Bill promoted by the Council to give effect to thisscheme received Second Reading in the House of Commons on the1$!th February with the substantial majority of 2^0 to 62 and was committed to a Select Committee.         The Committee after hearing evidence made a statement onthe 10th April to the effect that they recognised the need forsuch a bridge and were prepared to approve generally the schemefor the bridge itself and the lay-out on the north side of theRiver Thames.   As regards the south side of the River however,they stated that they saw objection to the proposal that the newCharing Cross Station should be on the river front, and theyadjourned until 6th May with a request that the Promoters wouldin the interval reconsider this &quot;oart of the scheme.         During the Easter Recess the County Council have gone into the matter very thoroughly with the Southern RailwayCompany and my Department,  with a result that we have become morefirmly convinced than ever that the only really practical schemeis the one in the Bill.    This conclusion axid the grounds on
was presented to the Committee by the Promotors this morning.The essential decisions are contained in the last two paragraphs on pages 10 and 11.         After considering this statement the Committee thismorning again affirmed their objection to the proposal containedin the Bill that the new station should be placed on the riverfront, and suggested that the Promotors might withdraw the Billwith a view to its re submission to Parliament in an altered&apos; form.so as to provide a site for the station set back from the river.         The Promotors, to my mind quite rightly, refused toaccept this suggestion and the Committee thereupon rejected theBill.         It is clear that if the Committee&apos;s decision is to beaccepted there is no prospect of securing the nationalimprovement represented by a new bridge at Charing Cross and theconstruction of an embankment on the Lambeth siceo         In this event it- is probable that the Council willrevert to the proposal which they put forward before theappointment of the Royal Commission, to pull down &quot;waterloo bridge and to construct an entirely new bridge to take six linesof traffic.   In such circumstances, I should not feel justifiedin objecting to their taking this actionc         In view of the very definite opinions on this important matter expressed both by the present Government and by the late government, I think it highly desirable that no decision shouldbe arrived at by the Council until the present position has beenfully discussed between their representatives, and myself.   Thequestion has already been raised whether in view of the national importance of the  scheme it would be a proper course for a motion to be moved in the House on behalf of the Council for the
Bill to be recommitted either to a new Committee or to theCommittee who rejected it to-day.   This would admittedly be an exceptional procedure, but the circumstances are themselvesexceptional.         A decision upon this point must obviously come from theCounty Council as the Promotors, but before meeting the leadersof the Council to discuss the next step and in view of the factthat the Committee were definitely informed that I concurred inthe Council&apos;s views, I feel that if this question of recommittalis raised and the Council are in favour of it, I should be in aposition to know whether on such a motion I could, on behalf ofthe Government, support it.         I feel that the London County Council cannot possiblyleave the matter where it has been left by the decision of aCommittee consisting of four members, and that they are entitledin the unusual position that has arisen to obtain furtherguidance from the house of Commons as a whole as to the actionwhich they should take with regard to the Charing Cross schemeitself and Y/aterloo Bridge.         I see no other means of bringing the matter again before the House this Session than by a motion for recommittal,and I seek the authority of the Cabinet to inform the council that should they decide upon this course they will receive thesupport of the Government.                                       (Intld.)     H.M.
LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL  (CHARING              CROSS  BRIDGE) BILL.    Wlien the  Committee  adjourned  on 10th  April  last,  theyintimated to the London County Council, who are the Promoters ofthis Bill, their desire that during the period of the adjournment a thorough investigation should he made into the possibility of findingsome site for the new station on the Lambeth side of the river, otherthan the Lion Brewery site, which is the site proposed in the schemeof the Bill.    Accordingly the London County Council, in co-operation withthe Southern and Underground Railway Companies, undertook a renewed examination of the numerous alternative proposals whichhad been  suggested or indicated from time to time and  instituteda detailed comparison of them with the scheme of the Bill.  Amongthe proposals so examined and to which special attention has beengiven was a plan and perspective of a scheme for placing the stationon the Waterloo Junction site submitted  to the promoters by theLambeth Borough Council on 16th April, 1930.    It now becomes the duty of the Council to communicate to theCommittee the  results  of the investigation, and,  as the  matter isone of vital public importance, the Council  desire to avail themselves of the precision of a printed statement.ALTERNATIVE SITES TO LION BREWERY SITE.    This  examination  included  the  five possible  alternative sitesindicated by the Committee.  These alternatives are called SchemesC. 1, C. 2, C. 3, C.  4 and C. 5,  and may be summarised  as followswith reference to the site proposed for the station : Scheme. C. 1.                Proposed Site for Station.South-east  of  Waterloo  Station  between West-  minster   Bridge   Road,  Oakley   Street  and  Waterloo Road.C. 2.Divided Station-One-half north-west of Waterloo  Station between  Westminster  Bridge  Road, York  Road  and  Waterloo Road.One-half  south-east of Waterloo  Station between  Westminster Bridge Road, Oakley  Street and  Waterloo Road.350.  T.R. 48-3.  6-5-30.  J.T.S.
       Scheme:                 Proposed site for Station.         C.  3.  Divided  Station                  One-half north-west  of Waterloo  Station between                   Belvedere Road, York Road and Cornwall Road.                  One-half south-east  of Waterloo  Station between                    Oakley Street and Windmill Street.         C.  4.    North-west  of Waterloo Station between  York                    Road, Belvedere Road and Cornwall Road.         C.  5.     The same site as C. 4 but with rails at higher level.     Further consideration has also been given to three other possibleschemes for placing the new station  on the Waterloo Junction site,which had previously been examined  by the Council  and rejectedin favour of the scheme of the Bill.  These three other schemes are called Schemes J. 1, J. 2 and J. 3.   In addition there is the scheme submitted by the  Lambeth Borough Council, which relates to theWaterloo Junction site.COMPARISON OF THE ALTERNATIVE SCHEMES.    Comparing  the  alternatives  suggested  by  the  Committee,namely, Schemes C. 1,  C.  2, C. 3, C.  4 and C. 5,  the Council are definitely of opinion that Scheme C. 1  is the best of the five.  Thereasons for this opinion are indicated in Appendix I.    Comparing the  scheme submitted by the Lambeth  borough council and the other schemes (J. 1, J. 2 and J. 3) that had previously been  examined by the Promoters providing for the erection of thenew station at or adjacent to the Waterloo Junction site, the council have  come to the conclusion  that of  these four schemes, scheme. 1 is open to least objection.  The reasons for this conclusion are indicated in Appendix II.    Scheme J. 1 shows a new station at Waterloo Junction site moreor less balancing the existing Waterloo Station about Waterloo Road.    The Council  then compared Scheme  C. 1 with  Scheme  J.  1,and have carefully examined  their  respective advantages  and dis-advantages ; the results of this comparison may be summarised asfollows:     SCHEME C. 1  COMPARED WITH SCHEME J.  1.       (a) Advantages of Scheme C. 1  as compared with Scheme J. 1.           (1) Railway viaduct swung further back from river front.
      (b) Disadvantages of Scheme C. 1 as compared with Scheme J. 1.          (1)  The new station would be further from Charing Cross,              and passengers desiring  to  proceed on foot to  the              Strand  would have further  to walk.          (2)  Passengers proceeding between the  new station and              the  Underground  Railway  Stations  at Waterloo              Would have to Walk a further 350 yards.          (3)  Interchange  facilities for passengers  between the new              station  and the present Southern Railway Waterloo              Station would be much inferior.          (4)  Position of new station front would  cause road traffic              proceeding to and  from that station  to  use West-              minster Bridge.                The road traffic on Westminster Bridge Road and              Westminster Bridge would be increased as it would              not be practicable to divert the omnibuses to the new              Charing Cross road  bridge for the purpose of serving              the new station, and taxicab and other traffic Would              also chiefly use  the  Westminster  Bridge approach              to the new  station  as it would be more direct.  The              new station fronting Westminster Bridge Road would              therefore  attract traffic  to thoroughfares already              overcrowded instead of on  to the  new road bridge              and to  the new carriageways  provided  for in the              scheme of the Bill.           (5)  Access to Southern  Railway Waterloo Station would              be greatly inferior.      Conclusion.          Scheme C. 1 is definitely inferior to Scheme J.  1.COMPARISON OF  BEST ALTERNATIVE  SCHEME, VIZ. J. 1,  WITH  THE  SCHEME OF  THE  BILL.    Having  reached the  conclusion that of all the alternativesScheme J. 1 is the one that is least open to  objection, it remained to compare that scheme with the scheme of the Bill.    In  making  this comparison,  the Council were  bound, in thepublic interest,  to have  regard to certain fundamental  require-ments, namely :     (a)  that the new station should be conveniently placed in relation        to  the  existing  Southern  Railway and  Underground&apos;        Railway stations at Waterloo ;
    (b) that adequate and reasonable facilities for passengers arriving          at  the new  station to continue their journey either by          underground train or by omnibus should be available ;    (c) that  the distance to be covered by passengers desiring to          walk to the Strand should be reduced to a minimum ;    (d) that the construction of the  new station should involve the          minimum  disturbance to the passenger train services of          the Southern Railway ;    (e) that the new Charing Cross  road bridge should afford the        maximum amount of relief to Waterloo and Westminster        Bridges ;    (/) that easy and unimpeded access by road should be afforded        to the Southern Railway Waterloo Station and the new        station ;    (g) that the lines of traffic using Waterloo Bridge, Westminster        Bridge and the new Charing Cross road bridge, respectively,        should not  converge until the maximum  opportunity for        dispersal was afforded;    (h) that  the number  of new and valuable properties  to  be          demolished should  be reduced to a minimum :    (j) that  the number  of persons  of the working class to be dis-          placed and re-housed should be kept as low as practicable ;    (k) that the scheme to be adopted should provide not only an        opportunity for, but a stimulus to the proper development of          the Lambeth side  of the River ; and    (I) that the cost of the scheme should be kept as low as possible          and be commensurate with the traffic advantages to be          secured.    From a careful analysis of Scheme J.  1 and of the scheme of theBill in the light of the foregoing requirements, the following pointsemerge :     (a) Communication  with  the  Southern  Railway  Waterloo        Station. With regard to the Southern Railway Waterloo        Station, the scheme of the Bill provides for direct access to        that station for  passengers from the new station by means        of a short footbridge over York Road.  Similar  means of        access could only be provided from a new station as proposed        by Scheme J. 1 at Waterloo Junction by means of crossing        over two station approach roads  or by means of a long and        inconvenient subway.
(&amp;)  (i.) Underground  Railway  facilities. The  Underground    Railway stations are immediately below the area between    Waterloo Station and  York  Road and from  the  point    of view of interchange of passengers between the new    station  and the Underground Railway stations, the ideal    position  for the new station  should be such as to  bring    the centre of the platforms of  the new  station immediately    over the Underground  Railway  stations.   This object is    attained by the scheme of the  Bill to a substantially greater    degree than by Scheme J. 1.(ii.) Passengers interchanging  between the  new station and    the Underground Railway stations would, under scheme    J. 1,  have to walk approximately 490 yards from a new    station  as proposed by Scheme J. 1 at Waterloo Junction,    i.e.,  approximately 300 yards further than  ha  the case    of the scheme of the Bill.(iii) Omnibus  facilities. Passengers  desiring   to  travel  by    omnibus to or from the new station, would have to walk    190 yards further under Scheme J. 1 as compared with the    scheme  of  the Bill where  a walk of only a few yards is    involved.  In addition,  omnibuses crossing the river  to    and from the new station  would  have to travel 630  yards    further under Scheme J. 1,  involving a fresh fare stage.      The arrangements under the scheme of  the Bill for the    interchange of passengers between the  new station and the    Underground  Railway  stations and the proposed omnibus    station  have  been Worked out in  collaboration with  the    Underground  Railway and Omnibus Companies, and would    provide means whereby passengers emerging from the new    station to a common concourse would have immediate access    to tube or omnibus services without crossing the highway.(c) Pedestrians crossing the River to or from the new station    would have to walk 500 yards further under Scheme J. 1    than under the scheme of the Bill.(d)  The scheme of the Bill can be carried out without any inter-    ruption to the train services of the Southern Railway.   In    the case of Scheme J. 1, certain of the train services to and    from  Charing Cross would require to  be suspended for a    considerable time.(e) Under Scheme J.  1, the road  approaches  from  the new    Charing Cross road bridge  to the new station as compared
 with those of the scheme of the Bill would be both indirect and inconvenient, and, in view  of the  connection which York Road Would afford  to  a new  station as  proposed by  Scheme J. 1 at Waterloo  Junction, a large volume of traffic  to  and from  such  a new  station would use West- minster Bridge in preference to the new Charing Cross  road bridge and thus defeat one  of the main objects of the scheme.Road traffic under the scheme  of the Bill would have more efficient access both to the  new station and the  Southern Railway Waterloo station  than would be  the  case under Scheme J. 1.Under Scheme  J.  1, the road traffic from Waterloo Bridge and the new  Charing  Cross  road bridge would  converge at the junction of York Road and Waterloo Road, and, in consequence,   Waterloo  Road immediately  beyond  that point  would require  to  carry  the traffic coming  from and proceeding to  both bridges.   The scheme  of the Bill would on the other hand enable the traffic from the new Charing Cross road bridge to proceed without interruption until  it reached  the New Cut Circus which would afford immediate access to a number of import- ant  radial roads affording the maximum means of dispersal to the  traffic.Scheme J. 1 would  involve the  demolition  of important properties, including  St. John&apos;s Church, Waterloo  Hospital, the  London Telephone  Service Offices, and  the  premises recently erected by Messrs. W. H. Smith &amp; Sons in Stamford Street, none of which would be affected by the scheme of the Bill.The  number of persons of the  working class who would be displaced under Scheme J. 1 would be greater than under the scheme of the Bill by over 1,400 persons.The  scheme of  the Bill provides for the construction of an embankment on the Lambeth side of the River as a necessary element of the new Charing Cioss  road bridge.  Provision is also made for  ensuring that the architectural treatment
        of the new station, hotel or other buildings proposed to be&apos;        erected on the River front shall be worthy of the site.           Under Scheme J. 1, the embankment could not be included        as an integral part of the scheme.  The embankment must        therefore be left to be dealt with under any town-planning        or  other  development  scheme which  may be  evolved at        some future date.           If the site proposed for the station under Scheme J. 1        were  adopted,  its  environment  would inevitably  be        unfavourable to the  erection of  a  large  modern hotel or        important office buildings.    (I) Scheme J. 1 would involve an increase of  over two million        pounds in the net  cost of property and works as compared        with the amount required in the case of the scheme of the        Bill.POSSIBLE  MODIFICATIONS   OP  THE-  SCHEME  OF  THE BILL.    The Council have also addressed themselves to seeing whether any modifications  could be made in the scheme of the Bill to meetcertain objections indicated by the Committee.    In this the Council and the Southern Railway Company have -operated and, as a result of the joint examination of the whole matter,  the  Council  are   in  a  position  to  make the  following suggestions :     (1) It  would be practicable for the turntable and the coaling        stage to be moved to a position further east so that  they        would not be visible  from the approach road to the new        Charing Cross road bridge.    (2) The Southern Railway Company  are willing to be placed        under the same restrictions at the new station in respect of        goods traffic  as those which now obtain  at their existing        Charing Cross Station.    (3) The Southern Railway Company have agreed that, not only        the frontage to the River, but any other portions of the        buildings  and  works  which are adjacent  to  the  new        southern  approach road  should  conform  to  the general        architectural scheme.   The Company would be prepared to        enclose the station as far as practicable with other buildings        to improve the amenities of the immediate neighbourhood.
     (4) The removal of the turntable and the coaling stage, and the         consequent alterations  in  the  lay-out  of the  sidings,         would make it possible to reduce the covered-in portion of         Waterloo Road from 420 feet, as originally provided for in         the official scheme, to 323 feet, made up of about 170 feet         of railway bridge and 153 feet of road bridge.  These two         bridges would thus be separated by a clear space of about         47 feet.     (5) While it has not been found possible to reduce the length of         the covered-in portion of York Road, arrangements could be         made to improve the lighting and ventilation of the covered         portion by means of (a) prismatic pavement lights set into         the  railway platforms  over the  line  of the road, and         (b) louvre  ventilators in the platform walls.    THE GENERAL  CONCLUSIONS  OF  THE  COUNCIL.    As the result of the further investigations which the Council havemade in response to the intimation of  the  Committee,  there  arecertain general observations  which the  Council desire to  submit tothe Committee.    The Council  have submitted to Parliament a scheme for a newCharing  Cross road bridge expressly as a means of adding  to and improving the general road transport facilities of London, as recom-mended  by the Royal Commission, and of providing much  neededrelief to Westminster Bridge and of affording a solution of the vexedproblem  of Waterloo Bridge.    This is  the primary aim and the fundamental object  of  thescheme of the Bill and constitutes the only justification for the Councilembarking upon  the scheme and imposing upon the ratepayers ofthe administrative County of London the heavy expense entailed incarrying  it out.   Apart from the merits of the scheme of the Bill on traffic grounds, the Council at the same time admit and fully recognise the force of the declaration by  the present  Government  and their predecessors that the construction of a  new road bridge at CharingCross,  in the light  of the conclusions reached as the result of theexhaustive consideration  of the matter by the Royal Commission,must be  regarded also as the fulfilment of a national necessity.     The carrying out of this national scheme, it has to be borne inmind, is  only practicable on the assumption that the present Charing
     (4) The removal of the turntable and the coaling stage, and the         consequent alterations  in  the lay-out  of  the  sidings,         would make it possible to reduce the covered-in portion of&quot;         Waterloo Road from 420 feet, as originally provided for in         the official scheme, to 323 feet, made  up of about 170 feet         of railway bridge and 153 feet  of road bridge.  These two         bridges would thus be separated by a clear space of about         47 feet.     (5) While it has not been found possible to reduce the length of         the covered-in portion of York Road, arrangements could be         made to improve the lighting and ventilation of the covered         portion by means of (a) prismatic pavement lights set into         the  railway platforms  over the  line  of the  road, and         (6) louvre  ventilators in the platform walls.    THE GENERAL  CONCLUSIONS  OF THE  COUNCIL.     As the result of the further investigations which the Council havemade in response to the intimation of  the Committee, there  arecertain general observations  which the Council desire to submit tothe Committee.     The Council  have submitted to Parliament a scheme for a newCharing  Cross road bridge expressly as  a means of adding to and improving the general road transport facilities of London, as recom-mended  by the Royal Commission, and of providing  much neededrelief to Westminster Bridge and of affording a solution of the vexedproblem  of Waterloo Bridge.     This is the primary aim and the  fundamental object of  thescheme of the Bill and constitutes the only justification for the Councilembarking upon  the scheme and imposing  upon the ratepayers ofthe administrative County of London the heavy expense entailed incarrying  it out.   Apart from the merits  of the scheme of the Bill on traffic grounds, the Council at the same time admit and fully recognise the force of the declaration by  the present  Government and their predecessors that the construction of a new  road bridge at CharingCross,  in the light  of the conclusions reached as the result of theexhaustive consideration of the matter  by the Royal Commission,must be  regarded also as the fulfilment of a national necessity.     The carrying out of this national scheme, it has to be borne inmind, is  only practicable on the assumption that the present Charing
Cross Station of the Southern Railway is to he removed to the Lam-beth side of the river.  The retention of the present Charing Crossrailway bridge and the addition of a new bridge at Charing Crossfor road traffic is open to the most serious objections on engineering,architectural, navigation and other grounds.    Accepting therefore as an essential part of the scheme the removalof the station to the south side, it is  inevitable that the further thenew station is placed back from the river the greater will bethe distancewhich passengers will have to walk from the new station to the Strandor vice versa, and the less convenient and, indeed, practicable Will bethe interchange for  passengers between the new  station and the underground  Railway stations,  assuming  in  each  case  that  a practicable site for a railway station  can be secured, that is  to say,a site on which the new station can be built without  appreciabledisturbance to the working of the present  Charing Cross  station and its railway approaches.    As the Council interpret the intimation which the committee made on 10th April, the Committee are of opinion that the portion ofLambeth adjoining the river, if left open to fortuitous influences andnot used to form the site of a new railway station and other buildings,Would develop on natural economic  lines, and in so doing attain a standard of architectural treatment that would transcend anythingpossible under the scheme of the Bill, and that the probabilities of thateventuality justify the economic disadvantages of placing the stationaway from the river front.    The  Council  have re-examined  most carefully  the questionwhether there is  any evidence on which they  Would  be justifiedin taking  the responsibility for  proceeding  upon  the probability that the values and standard  of development on the Lambeth sideof the river would in any reasonable period of time after the openingof the new Charing Cross road bridge become the values and standardof development on the Strand side.    The result of the further examination of this aspect of the matter has re-affirmed  the evidence which  the Council placed before theCommittee that just as experience has shown that the constructionof none of the existing bridges has hitherto resulted in establishingon the south side anything like the values and standard of develop-ment on the  north side, so the construction of a new road bridge atCharing Cross is not likely, of itself, to create in Lambeth values and a standard of development even remotely approaching those existingon the Charing Cross  side of the river.
     Were the station to be set back to a site away from the riverbank, the  necessity would not arise for constructing as part of aCharing Cross road bridge scheme  the embankment and riversidegardens that form part of the scheme of the Bill.  If an embankmentdid not form part of a road scheme no grant could be made from theRoad Fund to assist its construction, and without such a grant theCouncil would not be in a position to incur within any reasonablespace of time the expense  of embanking the river.  It seems to theCouncil certain that  under this state of things the Lambeth river-side Would  remain, except so  far as a clearance Was necessary toprovide for the site of the new bridge, in its present condition.     On the other hand, if the scheme of the Bill is carried through,the riverside at this part of Lambeth would be embanked, and suitablyproportioned station  buildings  would be erected of a character and design in keeping with the importance of a site on the river frontoverlooking an attractive embankment.     Although the placing  of the station some distance  back fromthe river front would result in eliminating certain heads of expendi-ture involved in the scheme of the Bill, the carrying out of any schemefor the erection of the new station on the Waterloo Junction site wouldbe more costly than the scheme of the Bill.   For example, in the caseof Scheme J. 1,  which  does not provide for the embanking of theriver, it is estimated that there  would be an increased net expenditureof over  2,000,000.     Before adopting  the scheme of  the Bill the numerous  schemes which had  been  suggested  in recent years for  a road bridge in theneighbourhood  of Charing Cross  were examined and investigated by the Council.   Apart from these a great number of plans dealingwith different proposals and with various modifications of particularproposals were prepared and examined from every angle before theconclusion was reached that the scheme of the Bill was incomparablythe best of all the schemes that  had come under review from the stand-point of cost,  street traffic,  railway  passengers,  convenience  ofomnibus and railway interchange facilities and the practicabilit y ofdignified  architectural  treatment.   In  reaching  this  conclusion the Council were confirmed by the unanimous opinion of all the expertadvisers who have been assisting them and whom they regard as out-standing authorities  in their respective professions.   In deference,however, to the  wishes of the  Committee, the  Council have, as hasbeen stated, once more reconsidered all the practicable alternative schemes that have been suggested and have also explored the whole
problem afresh in order to see whether some new or modified scheme could be devised which  accorded more nearly with the conditionsindicated  by the  Committee.  This further examination has morethan ever convinced the Council that the scheme of the Bill is theonly one that meets satisfactorily what they regard as the fundamentalrequirements of the case.  In the discharge of their duty, as they see it, to London, they cannot assume any responsibility for carrying out a scheme for a new road bridge at Charing Cross which involves the setting  back of the proposed new station from the river front at a heavy  sacrifice measured in time,  convenience and money  to the travelling public  and involving further considerable expenditure,and at the same time leaves the portion of Lambeth  adjoining theriver to develop under whatever spasmodic influences chance  and time and other uncoordinated effort might call into action.    The Council, as has been stated, are firmly of opinion that theprovision of a new road bridge at Charing Cross is definitely dependentupon the removal of  the present Charing Cross Railway Station tothe south  side  of the  river.   Accepting that as a  fundamentalcondition  the Council are  convinced, for the reasons that  havebeen given in the  foregoing part of  this  statement, that there is noother practicable site  for the new station than the  Lion Brewery sitewhich has been  adopted in  the  scheme of the Bill.  This being the considered conclusion of the  Council,  in  which  the Minister ofTransport concurs, the Council think that they would  be wantingin candour to the Committee if they failed to convey to the Committeein respectful but definite terms that, should the scheme of the Billbe not accepted, there is no alternative  scheme which the council could accept the responsibility  of submitting to  Parliament.   TheCouncil therefore  feel it their duty to state that, if the scheme ofthe Bill is rejected, they see no prospect of securing the nationalimprovement represented by a new road bridge at  Charing Cross.
LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL (CHARING              CROSS BRIDGE)  BILL.                       APPENDIX  I.  COMPARISON OF THE SCHEMES SUGGESTED BY THE COMMITTEE.SCHEME C. 1.                              N    This is considered the best of those suggested by the Committeeand Committee Schemes C. 2, C. 3, C. 4 and C. 5 are each in turncompared  with it.SCHEME C. 2 COMPARED WITH C. 1.    (a)  Advantages of Scheme C. 2.        (1)  Suburban passengers brought nearer to north side  of            the river.        (2) Suburban passengers brought nearer  to Underground            Railway gathering point.        (3) Total length  of covered main roads less.        (4) Slightly better interchange between the two main line            passenger stations.    (b)  Disadvantages of Scheme C. 2.        (1) Split station  less efficient.        (2) Impossible  to  maintain  railway  traffic to  existing            CharingrCross station during construction of new works.        (3) Suburban station rail level 10 feet higher than Waterloo            Station and Main Line Station level 4  feet higher than            Waterloo Station.        (4) Vehicular access to Waterloo Station at platform level            partly cut off.        (5) In and out new station traffic would have to use the same            roads.        (6) Existing railway viaduct doubled. Conclusion. The  disadvantages,  particularly (1),  (2)  and  (6),        are so  great  as  to  outweigh the  advantages  and render        the scheme inferior to C. 1.
SCHEME C.  3 COMPARED WITH C. 1.     (a) Advantages of Scheme C.  3:         (1)  Suburban passengers brought  nearer  to  north side of             river.         (2)  Suburban passengers brought  nearer  to  Underground             Railway gathering point.         (3)  Less  tendency for station  traffic to  use Westminster             Bridge Road.     (b) Disadvantages of Scheme C. 3.         (1)  Split  station less efficient.         (2)  Impossible to maintain railway traffic to existing Charing             Cross station during construction of new  Works.         (3)  Gradients of l-in-26 down  from new  road bridge  and             l-in-27 down from Waterloo Bridge-.         (4)  Free-flow traffic facilities inferior.         (5)  Length  of covered main  roads greater.         (6)  Existing railway viaduct  doubled.         (7)  Suburban station rail level 14 feet higher than Waterloo             Station.     Conclusion. The disadvantages, particularly (1), (2), (3) and (6),         outweigh  the advantages and  render  the scheme inferior         to C. 1.SCHEME  C. 4 COMPARED WITH C.  1.     (a) Advantages of Scheme C. 4.         (1) Passengers brought nearer to north side  of river.         (2) Passengers brought  nearer to  Underground  Railway             gathering point.    (b) Disadvantages of Scheme  C.  4.         (1) Impossible to maintain railway traffic to existing Charing             Cross station  during a very long period of construction             of the new station.         (2) Bad southern  approach to new road bridge.         (3) One additional circus.         (4) Number and length of covered main  roads greater.         (5) New station  rail level  16 feet higher than Waterloo             Station.    Conclusion. Disadvantage No. 1 alone renders   this scheme        impracticable.
                               14 vSCHEME C. 5  COMPARED WITH 0.1.          &apos; :Vl  (a) Advantages of Scheme  C.  5.  \,:        (1) Passengers brought nearer to the north side of the river.       ; (2) Passengers brought nearer to the Underground Railway             gathering point.    (6) Disadvantages  of Scheme C.  5.        (1) Impossible to maintain railway traffic to existing Charing             Cross Station during a very long period of construction             of the new station. ;       (2) Gradient of Lin-25 down from new road bridge on south             side.                .        (3) Length  of covered main road much  greater.        (4) New  station rail  level   18  feet  higher than Waterloo             Station. ,    Conclusion. Disadvantage  No.   1   renders,   this   scheme        impracticable.
LONDON  COUNTY COUNCIL (CHARING             CROSS  BRIDGE)  BILL.COMPARISON OF SCHEMES FOR NEW STATION AT WATERLOO JUNCTION.SCHEME J.  1.    This is the best  of the four Waterloo Junction Site Schemescompared herein, and the  Lambeth Borough Council Scheme andSchemes J.  2 and J. 3 are compared with it.LAMBETH BOROUGH COUNCIL SCHEME COMPARED WITH SCHEME J. 1.    (a) Advantages of Lambeth Borough Council Scheme.        (1) Length  of new railway site inadequate.        (2) Width of Waterloo Road insufficient.        (3) Free flow of  new bridge traffic prevented by cutting            across York  Road traffic.        (4) New Cut Circus inefficient for traffic working.    Conclusion. General  inadequate  traffic facilities render  this        scheme inferior to Scheme J. 1.SCHEME J. 2 COMPARED WITH J. 1.    (a) Advantages of Scheme J. 2.        (1) Maintenance of railway traffic to existing Charing Cross            Station during construction of new station slightly            easier.    (b) Disadvantages of Scheme J. 2.        (1) In general, station passengers to the north side of the            river and to the Underground Railway gathering point            have 20 yards further to go.        (2) Possibilities of architectural treatment of north side            of New Cut Circus inferior.APPENDIX II.    (1) No &quot;kink&quot; at  South Bridge Head.    (2) St. John&apos;s Church retained.(b) Disadvantages of Lambeth Borough Council Scheme.Conclusion. This scheme is similar to J. 1, but inferior in detail.
SCHEME J. 3 COMPARED WITH J.  1.    (a) Advantages of Scheme J. 3.        (1) Passengers brought 100  yards nearer to north side of            river.        (2) Passengers brought  70 yards  nearer to Underground            Railway  gathering point.        (3) Omnibus  concourse better situated.        (4) Maintenance of railway traffic to existing Charing Cross            Station during construction of new station is  easier.    (b) Disadvantages  of Scheme  J. 3.        (1) Road access  to new station inferior.        (2) Road access  to Waterloo Station inferior.        (3) Interchange between the  new station and the Southern            Railway  Waterloo Station less easy.        (4) Length of railway viaduct slightly  greater.        (5) New  open space smaller.        (6) Architectural layout  inferior.    Conclusion. The  slight  traffic advantages  are more than  out-        weighed by the architectural disadvantages and hence this        scheme is inferior to Scheme J. 1.

</content>
</cab>
