<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/19/43 images: 474-478</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT  232Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1941.SECRET. Copy No.  43W.M. (41)107th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 107 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S. W. 1, on Thursday, October 30, 1941, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anberson,   The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,M.P., Lord President of the Council.      Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,Minister without Portfolio. M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Earle Page,Special Envoy from the Governmentof the Commonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma(Item 5).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secre-tary of State for the Colonies.Captain the Right Hon. H. D.Margesson, M.P., Secretary of Statefor War.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,.M.P., Minister of Information.[23090]
The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Air Chief Marshal Sir Wilfred Freeman, Vice-Chief of the AirStaff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.WAR CABINET 107 (41).Contents.minute no.                                    Subject. page 1      Sir Earle Page............................    1192      Naval, Military and Air Operations................    119Air Operations.Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations:U.S.S.R.3      Yugoslavia      ............................     1194      Blockade ............................    119Vichy France and Vichy French Territories.5      Burma  ................................     120Constitutional Questions.
Sir Earle Page.1. On behalf of the War Cabinet, the Prime Minister extendeda warm welcome to Sir Earle Page.The War Cabinet-Invited Sir Earle Page to make a statement at their meeting on Thursday, the 6th November.In the meantime, Sir Earle Page would have consultations with the Secretaries of State for Foreign Affairs and forDominion Affairs, and with the Service Ministers.Waval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 106thConclusions,Minute 4.)Air Operations.naval operations.Shipping Losses.MilitaryOperations.U.S.S.R.2. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following informationamplification of Cabinet War Room Records Nos. 786-788 : Summary of aircraft losses since the 23rd October : Home Theatre Enemy 13 destroyed.3 probable.5 damaged.mOur Own 11 Fighters.3 Bombers.Our losses in heavy bombers had lately much decreased.On the night of the 28th /29th October Hudsons had carried out an attack on merchant vessels off Aalesund. It was believed that wehad destroyed two merchant vessels and had hit two others.During the previous three days three vessels totalling about12,000 tons had been sunk by enemy action. The latest report fromthe homeward-bound Gibraltar convoy was that-we had lost fourvessels out of seventeen.Only slight changes had occurred since the 27th October. TheRussians were counter-attacking on the Leningrad sector and atKalinin. A new German armoured thrust had reached the vicinity of Tula, about 100 miles south of Moscow. Both on the Moscow andthe Ukraine fronts the weather was causing difficulties to the enemy.At Rostov the Russian resistance was stubborn. The Germansappeared to have reached the mainland of the Crimea.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Yugoslavia.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 105thConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the rebellion in Yugoslavia appeared to be on a considerable scale. Hethought that it might be necessary to bring before the DefenceCommittee the question of co-ordination of communications withthe patriot forces, since the present position in this respect was not satisfactory.Blockade.Vichy Franceand VichyFrenchTerritories.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 83rdConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The War Cabinet were given certain information, whichis recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.
Burma.     . 5.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theConstitutional Secretary of State for Burma (W.P. (G) (41) 122) relating to theQuestions. constitutional future of Burma. In this Memorandum the Secretary(Previous of State asked for authority to discuss with the Prime Minister ofReference: Burma the proposal that he should be sent a letter (draft attachedW.M. (41) 7lst to W.P. (G) (41) 122) giving a general and non-committal assuranceConclusions, regarding the future constitutional position of Burma.Minute a) The War Cabinet authorised the Secretary of State for burma (1) To see U Saw and discuss with him the last two para-graphs of the draft letter appended to W.P. (G)(41) 122.(2) To despatch the letter to U Saw without further reference to the War Cabinet, provided (a) that no alterations of substance were made; &apos;(6) that it was understood that U Saw would receive the letter without making a rejoinderto it.Great George Street, S. W. 1,October 30, 1941.


</content>
</cab>
