<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 119-120</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1921.SECRET... rC.l\ 8112 CABINET.I circulate to my colleagues a copy of a Despatch addressed to rue by the Government ol: India, dated 21st *\i&amp;f, and of my -Despatch in reply of the 30th June, in regard to the recognition of the grant of fiscal autonomy to the Government of India subject to the provisions of the Government of India Act.An extract from the Report of the Joint Select Committee on the Government of India Bill, 1910, is appended.4th July 192.1. E. S. M.3To the Rigid Honourable Edwin Montagu, His Majesty1 &amp; Secretary ofState for India.Simla, 21st April 1921..Fiscal Autonomy.Sir,We have the honour to report for your information that a Resolution was passed in the Council of State on the 23rd February last in the following terms: &quot;This Council recommends to the Governor-General in Council that His Majesty&apos;s Government be addressed through the Secretary of State with a prayer that the Government of India be granted full fiscal autonomy subject to the provisions of the Government of India Act.&quot;2. The last ten words of this Resolution were substituted on the motion of our late colleague Sir George Barnes for the words &quot;under the direction of the Indian Legislature&quot; which appeared in the Resolution as moved by the Honourable Mr. Lalubhai Samaldas. We were unable to accept the Resolution in its original form as it proposed that in fiscal matters the Government of India should be subject only to the control of the Indian Legislature. We regarded this proposal as being incon-sistent with the provisions of the Government of India Act. The Resolution as amended indicates the agreement of the Council of State with-the views expressed on the subject of fiscal antonomy by the Joint Select Committee in its remarks on clause 33 of the Government of India Bill. The Joint Committee pointed out that fiscal autonomy could not be guaranteed to India by statute without limiting the ultimate power of Parliament to control the administration of India and without limiting the power of veto which vests in the Crown. It took the view- that fiscal autonomy could be assured to India only by the acknowledgment of a convention, and it expressed the opinion that, in order that a convention of this kind might grow up, the Secretary of State should, as far as possible, avoid interference when the Govern-ment of India and the Legislature were in agreement, and that his intervention, when it did take place, should be limited to safeguarding the international obligations of the Empire or any fiscal arrangements within the Empire to which His Majesty&apos;s -Government was a party.3. We request that the Resolution may be laid before His Majesty&apos;s Government.We have the honour to be, &apos; Sir,Your most obedient, humble Servants,(Signed)     Reading.W. H. Vincent. W. M. Hat ley. T. H. Holland. Ji N. Sailma.4298     100     7.21
To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India, in Council.Revenue, India Office,No. 70. 30th June 1921.Resolution of the Council of Stale regarding Fiscal Autonomy.My Lord, - - i&apos; ;I have received and noted on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government the Despatch of Your Excellency&apos;s Government, No. 16 (Department of Commerce), dated 21st April .1921, which communicated the Resolution passed in the Council of State.on 23rd February 19^1, recommending that His Majesty&apos;s Government should be addressed with a prayer that the Government of India be granted full fiscal autonomy subject to the provisions of the Government of India Act.2. In this connection I would refer to my reply to the deputation from the Manchester Chamber of Commerce,,received at the India Office on 10th March 1921, forwarded with my Despatch No. 44 (Revenue), dated the 21st April 1921, from which it will appear that I have, on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, accepted the principle recommended by the Joint Committee in their report on clause 33 of the Government of India Bill.1 I have the honour to be,My Lord,v Your Lordship&apos;s most obedient humble Servant,(Signed)     Edwin S. Montagu.Extract from, the Report of the Joint Select Committee on the Government ofIndia Bill, 1919.Clause 33. The Committee have given most careful consideration to the relations of the Secretary of State with the Government of India, and through it with the provincial Governments. In the relations of the Secretary of State with the Governor-General in Council, the Committee are not of opinion that any statutory change can be made so long as the Governor-General remains responsible to Parliament, but in practice the conventions which now govern these relations may&apos;wisefy be modified to meet fresh circumstances caused by the creation of a Legislative Assembly with a large elected majority. In the exercise of his responsibility to Parliament, which he cannot delegate to anyone else, the Secretary of State may reasonably consider that only in exceptional circumstances should he be called upon to intervene in matters of purely Indian interest where the Government and the Legislature oi: India are in agreement,.This examination of the general proposition leads inevitably to the consideration of one special case of non-intervention. Nothing is more likely to endanger the good relations between India and Great Britain than a belief that India&apos;s fiscal policy,is dictated from Whitehall in the interests of the trade of Great Britain. That such a belief exists at the moment there can be no doubt. That there ought to be no room for it in the future is equally clear. Iudia&apos;s position in the Imperial Conference opened the door to negotiation between India and the rest of the Empire, but negotiation without power to legislate is likely to remain inafTective. A satis-factory solution of the question can only be guaranteed by the grant of liberty to the Government of India to devise those tariff arrangements which seem best fitted to India&apos;s needs as an integral portion of the British Empire. It cannot be guaranteed by statute without limiting the ultimate power of Parliament to control the administration of India, and without limiting the power of veto which rests in the Crown ; and neither of these limitations finds a place in any of the Statutes in the British Empire. It can only therefore be assured by an acknowledgment of a convention. Whatever be the right fiscal policy for India, for the needs of her consumers as well as. for her manufacturers, it is quite clear that she should have the [same liberty to consider her interests as Great Britain, Australia, New Zealand, Canada and South Africa. In the opinion of the Committee, therefore, the Secretary of State should as far as possible avoid interference on this subject when the Government of India and its Legislature are in agreement, and they think that his intervention, when it does take place, should be limited to safeguarding the inter-national obligations of the Empire or any fiscal arrangements within the Empire to to which His Majesty&apos;s Government is a party.

</content>
</cab>
