<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 410-419</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS BOCTJMEHT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT AM IC MAJESTY!S GOVERN tCEHTt^1 (bmi imi 4^ 4m(^ **a **tfc fefct        *4m **** **nw *wiv ***** ta* **** ***** **&quot;**t ****** ****** ***** *-4 1*** ***** i*i** **m** ***i*t  **v* ******* *n** *w** *-*l* *ti**oi %** *t*&quot; **&apos;w v*** ***** v4f *v** ttw mm mm a..,. mb  *ft  *tf ** iw*0OKB&apos;IDENTIAL C A B IJJ T0.P.3126. COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRSSUPREME COURT OFFICERS (RETIREMENT, PENSIONS, &amp;C.) BILL.The accompanying Draft Bill Is circulated at the request of the Lord Chancellor for consideration by the Committee of Home Affairs.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W, July 12th, 1921.
Supreme Court Officers (Retirement, Pensions, &amp;e.) I MILARRANGEMENT OE CLAUSES.Clause.1.   Compulsory retirement of certain officers of the Supreme Court.2.   Pensions of certain officers of the Supreme Court.3.   Payment of pensions, &amp;c.4.  Registrars and clerks to registrars in Chancery Division.5.  Amendments of 42 &amp; 43 Viet. c. 78. 6.   Short title. Schedules.72-3
[11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.1  Supreme Court Officers (Retirement,  1tensions, SfG.)DRAFTof aBILLto-Lake further provision with respect to the a.d. 1921. appointment, conditions of service and Pensions of certain Officers of the Supreme Court in England, and to authorise the abolition of certain offices therein, and for purposes con-nected therewith.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : 1. A person holding any of the offices in the compulsory Supreme Court in England specified in the First Schedule retirement to this Act shall vacate his office at the end of the 0Lcertill!!11t j   -i c . oi-i!    officer sol the completed year or service m the course 01 which he supreme 10 attains the age of seventy-two years: court.Provided that where the Lord Chancellor considers it desirable in the public interest to retain any such person in the public service after he attains the age of seventy-two years, he may, with the approval of the Treasury, 15 authorise his continuance in the service up to such later age (not exceeding seventy-five years) as he thinks fit.2. (1) The provisions of the Superannuation Acts, pensions 1834 to 1914, shall, in their application to persons holding of certain any of the offices specified in Part I. of the First ^cgus^me 20 Schedule to this Act, have effect subject to the following court!11&quot;6&apos;1&apos;6 modifications: (a) The following provision shall be substituted for section ten of the Superannuation Act, 1859, -72-3 A 2
Supreme Court Officers (Retirement, [11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.]Pensions, &amp;c.)(which prohibits the grant of a superannua-tion allowance to a person under the age of sixty years except upon evidence of infirmity) &quot;It shall not he lawful to grant any 5 superannuation allowance under the pro-visions of this Act to any person who is under the age of seventy-two years, unless upon a medical certificate to the satisfaction of the Treasury [Lord Chancellor] that he 10 is incapable from infirmity of mind or body of discharging the duties of his office and that the infirmity is likely to be permanent, or unless he has served fifteen years in one or more of the offices specified in Part I. of 15 the Schedule to this Act and has attained the age of sixty years:(b) On the retirement of a person from any of the offices aforesaid there may be granted to him a superannuation  allowance calculated  in 20 accordance with the provisions of the Second Schedule to this Act instead of a superannua-tion allowance calculated in accordance with the provisions of the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1914; and no such person shall, be 25 entitled to have granted to him any other&quot; allowance or benefit whatsoever under those Acts except a gratuity in case of short service or  an allowance or compensation on the abolition of his office: 30Provided that (i) the foregoing provisions of this section shall not apply to  any person who was first appointed to one of the offices aforesaid before the first day of January, nineteen hundred 35 and twenty, or who, having been so appointed after that date, was at the time of his appoint-ment whether he was appointed before or after the passing of this Act, a civil servant within the meaning of the Superannuation 40 Act, 1887, unless he gives notice in such form and within such period -as may be prescribed by the Lord Chancellor, of his -desire to accept those provisions in lieu of
[11 &amp;12 GrEO. 5.]   Supreme Court Officers (Retirement,  3Pensions, Sfc.).the general provisions of the Superannuation A.D. 1921. Acts, 1831 to 1914 :(ii) any person who holds any of the offices afore-said at the commencement of this Act, and who 5 has the option of accepting or not accepting the foregoing provisions of this Act may, if he was appointed to any such office as aforesaid after the passing of the Superannuation Act, 1909, or if he has first adopted the provisions10 of that Act, accept the provisions of thissection with the substitution for the allow-ances under the Second Schedule to this Act of the allowances and other benefits set out in the Third Schedule to this Act, and this15 section shall in any such case apply accord-ingly.(2) Section twenty of the Supreme Court of Judi- 47 &amp; 48 Viet, cature (Officers) Act, 1879, and section twenty of the c-61-Supreme Court of Judicature Act, 1884, shall not apply20 in the case of appointments to offices to which this section applies, but before any person is appointed to any such office the person making the appointment shall take steps to satisfy himself that the state of health of the person proposed to   be appointed is25 satisfactory.(3) For the purpose of computing any allowance or benefit under the Second Schedule or Third. Schedule of this Act, no account shall be taken of any years of service in any office other than an office specified in Part I. of 30 the First Schedule to this Act.3. All allowances payable and all other payments Payment of to be made by virtue of this Act shall be paid out of pensions, &amp;c money provided by Parliament.4.- (1) The registrars and clerks to registrars of the Registrars 35 Chancery Division of the High Court shall be appointed aatl.clerks t( by the Lord Chancellor, and their number shall be such ye^trars111 vJilcillCCVVas the Lord Chancellor, with the approval of the Treasury, Division, may fix.(2) The registrars shall be appointed from among 40 the persons who at the time of the appointment are clerks to registrars, and a person shall not be qualified to be appointed as clerk to the registrars unless he is a solicitor of the Supreme Court of not less than two years standing.72 A3
4   Supreme Court Officers (Retirement,   [11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.jPensions, Sfo)A.d. 1921. (3) The Lord Chancellor shall appoint one of the registrars to he Chief Registrar, and the Chief Registrar shall exercise as respects (tlie other registrars and the clerks to registrars such duties and functions as the Lord Chancellor may from time to time assign to him.      5(4) The chief registrar, registrars, and clerks to registrars shall retire from office at such age as the Lord Chancellor, with the consent of the Treasury, may fix.(5) Any person who at the time of the passing of 10 this Act is exercising functions as a registrar or clerk to the registrars of the Chancery Division, shall he deemed to have been duly appointed in accordance with the provisions of this section to the office of registrar. or clerk, as the case may be, but any such person shall be 15 entitled to reckon as service for the purpose of the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1914, the service during any period before the passing of this Act during which he exercised such functions.5 Viet. c. 5.        (6) The Court of Chancery Act, 1841, is hereby 20 repealed with the exception of sections four and seventeen thereof.Amendments 5. (l) The Lord Chancellor may (with the approval of 42 &amp; 13 of the Lord Chief Justice of England, the Master of the Viet. c. 78. Rolls, and the President of the Probate, Divorce and 25 Admiralty Division of the High Court, as respects offices to which they have respectively a power of. appointment) abolish any office in the Supreme Court which appears to him to be unnecessary.(2) Section seventeen of the Supreme Court of 30 Judicature (Officers) Act, 1879 (which gives power to the Lord Chancellor to add years to the service of the holders of certain offices) and sections twenty-three, twenty-four, and tAventy-five of that Act (which relate to the rights, status and privileges of officers of the 35 Supreme Court) shall cease to have effect:Provided that nothing in this provision shall affect the rights of any person who before the passing of this Act has been appointed to any office in respect of which an order has been issued by the Treasury under the said 40 section seventeen.Short title. 6. This Act may be cited as the Supreme CourtOfficers (Retirement, Pensions, &amp;c.) Act, 1921.
[11 &amp; 12 G-eo. 5.]  Supreme Court Officers (Retirement,   5Pensions, 8rc.)SCHEDULES. a.d. 1921.EIRST SCHEDULE. Sections!and 2.Part I.Offices to which Sections One and Two5 apply.Permanent Secretary to the Lord Chancellor. Master of the Supreme Court, King&apos;s Bench Division. Assistant Master of the Supreme Court, King&apos;s Bench Division.10       Master of the Supreme Court, Chancery Division. vMaster of the Supreme Court, Taxing Office.Master in Lunacy.Legal Visitor in Lunacy.Official Referee to the Supreme Court. 15       Official Solicitor to the Supreme Court.Registrar, High Court in Bankruptcy.Taxing Master, High Court in Bankruptcy.Registrar, Probate, Divorce, and Admiralty Division.Part II.20  .   Offices to which Section One only applies.Registrar, Chancery Division. Medical Visitor in Lunacy.SECOND  SCHEDULE. Section 2.Scale of Allowances.25 1. An annual allowance not exceeding ten-sixtieths of the last annual salary may be granted after the completion of a period of service of five years.2. Where the period of service completed exceeds five years, there may be granted an annual allowance not exceeding 30 ten-sixtieths of the last annual salary with an addition of one-fortieth of such annual salary for each completed year&apos;s service in excess of five.3. The maximum allowance shall be two-thirds of the last annual salary.
6 Supreme Court Officers [Retirement,   [11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.jPensions, Sec).a. i). 1921.THIRD SCHEDULE.Section 2.Allowances, &amp;c. in the Case oe Officers to whom the Superannuation Act, 1909, applies.1. The scale of allowances set out in the Second Schedule to. this Act shall apply to officers who aclopt the provisions of 5 this Schedule, with the substitution for the amounts set out in the Second Schedule to this Act of those amounts reduced by one quarter.2. The Treasury may on the recommendation of the Lord Chancellor grant, by way of additional allowance to any such 10 officer who retires after having served for not less than five years, in addition to any allowance which may be granted to him under paragraph 1 of this Schedule, a lump sum equal, where the officer has served for five completed years, to ten-thirtieths of such annual salary, and where the officer has 15 served for more than five completed years, to ten-thirtieths of such annual salary, with an addition of one-twentieth of such annual salary for each completed years service in excess of five, so, however, that the additional allowance shall in no case exceed one and a half times the amount of such annual salary :   20Provided that (a) in the case of any officer appointed before the passing of the Superannuation Act, 1909, the amount of the additional allowance shall be in-creased by one-half per cent, in respect of each 25 completed year which he had serveel at the dateof the passing of that Act; and(b) if any officer retires after attaining the age of sixty-five years there shall be deducted from the amount of the additional allowance which would otherwise 30 be payable to him one-twentieth of that amount for every completed year&apos;s service subsequent to attaining that age.3. Where any such officer who was appointed to his office after the passing of the Superannuation Act, 1909, dies after- 35 serving five years or upwards and while still employed in his office, the Treasury may, on the recommendation of the Lord Chancellor, grant to his legal personal representatives a gratuity equal to the annual salary of his office, or equal to the additional allowance calculated in the manner provided by the last 40 preceding paragraph, whichever is the greater:Provided that the amount of the gratuity which may be so granted shall be reduced by one twentieth for every completed year&apos;s service subseqnent to attaining the age of sixty-five years. 45
[11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.]  Supreme Court Officers (Retirement, 7Pensions, 8fc).4. Where any such officer dies after having become entitled A.1). 1921. to an allowance, and the sums &apos; actually received by him up&apos; to   the time of his death on account of his allowance together with the sum received by him by way of additional allow-.5 ance are less than the amount of the annual salary of his office, the Treasury, on the recommendation of the Lord Chancellor, may grant to his legal personal representatives a gratuity equal to the difference.
Supreme Court Officers (Retirement, Pensions, &amp;e.).DRAFTOP ABILLTo make further provision with respect to the appointment, conditions of service and Pensions of certain Officers of the Supreme Court in England, and to authorise the abolition -tion of certain offices therein, and for purposes connected therewith.LTV.   (2.)Uth July 1921.72-3

</content>
</cab>
