<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 489-512</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOC THE NT IS THE PROPERTY OP H^g BRITANNIC majesty&apos;s government. )SECRET.-, C.P, 5,136,.0 A-B I -N El. DEC.u,R:\TT^)N OF THE TERMINATION OF THE WAR, memorandum by the Treasury..(Prepared in eccordance with Home Affairs Committee93, Conclusion 3(4).
The Treasury asked for the observations of the following Departments on the proposed Order in Council fixing the termination of the war for August 4th.1 The Departments under (a) have replied that,they ha\-e no observations.    Departments under (b) have made observations lendix A  which are annexed.(a)      Admiralty, Air Ministry, Colonial Offioe, Foreign Office, Ministry of Pensions, Inland Revenue, Post Office, Office of Works, Scottish Offioe, Irish Office, and Ministry of Labour.(b)       Home Office, Board of Trade,(including Shipping and Food) War Office, Disposal Commission, Ministry of Transport Liquor Control Board, and Customs, appendix B There are also appended copies of the originalletters from the London Stock Exchange and the London Clearing Banks.The Treasury strongly advocate the passing of the proposed Order in Council.     Firstly on the ground that the general Government policy is one of decontrol; secondly on the ground that it was never contemplated when the financial arrangements mentioned by the Banks and the Stock Exchange were made that the war period would last for over 2 years, after the Armistice, and that the result is becoming daily more and more indefensible; and thirdly on the ground that very considerable economies will result, for instance in connection with Pensions (see CP,3032).With regard to the Departmental observations nine Office The Treasury would not object to postponing the date of the termination to the 1st September (or even, 1st October) in order to allow regulations to be made under the Dangerous Drugs Act 1920.TheT&amp;HfviBIATIOfl OP TIB/.. WAR.
The Workmen&apos;a Compensation (War Additions) Acts, can &quot;be continued in the Ilxnirinf? Laws Continuance Bill.The Police Regulations referred to would be revivedIin an emergency under the Emergency Powers Act 1020but their continuance apart from such emergency would depend upon the passing of further   legislation to dealwith public order.    It is understood that a Billfor this purpose is under the consideration of theCabinet,   In any case the matter seems to be one to bedealt with by permanent   legislation rather than bycontinuance of the present war powers.Board of Trade.       The Board of Trade have no objectionto the proposed Order in Council though they point outthat arrangements will have to be made to deal with therights to oetroleum on the Duke of Devonshirelsland at Hardstoft, on which a legal action is in progress.The Board do not anticipate any serious difficultyin dealing with this matter.Ministry of Transport.   Certain negotiations with theRailway Companies will have to be completed but the Ministrydo not appear to anticipate any particular difficulty.War Office and the Disposal Commission.     Both these Departmentspoint out that steps to deal with property occupied under theDefence ef the Realm Act (which is to be surrendered 3 monthsafter the termination of the war unless other arrangements are made by Depts) will have to be expedited.   It would aonear   however that their difficulty would be met by slightly postponing the date of termination.The War Office also raise the Question of compensation for service in Ireland.   The Treasury have Already agreed that this matter can be dealt with independently Of the cessation of the r*ar Pensions ict.LIquor
Liquor Control Board.If tho Liquor Bill now &quot;before the Cabinet is not passed this session it will be necessary to pass (as there Is power to do) an Order in Counoil continuing the Liquor Control Board for a period not exceeding 12 months * Customs^war powers mentioned^ The more important powers have already been continued.There is no objection to the lapse of the
copy,HOME&apos; OFFICE,wmmzi,A590,314/5530th June, 1931.SirIn reply to your letter of the  7th instant J(Po33 l) respecting the question of declaring at an early date the termination of the war under the Termination of the Present War (Definition) Act, 1918, I am directed &quot;by the Secretary of State to say that the only serious point so far as the Home Offioe is no one concerned is that from the termination of the war the following Defenoe of the Realm Regulations will]cease to have effect -9-A.   Power to prohibit holding of meetings or process-42.     Prohibition against causing mutiny, sedition or disaffection *51.    Power to search premises.53..    Power of question.55.     Power of arrest.During such an emergency as is contemplated by the Emergency Powers Aot, 19E0, these provisions oan be temporarily revived and put in f aroe: but* apart from any such emergenoy, Regulations 42, 51, 53 and 55 Lave been, and continue to be, essential to the efficiency of the action taken by the Police to deal with. Sinn Feiners in England and with bolshevist troubles and revolutionary activities, and it is very desirable that before they are allowed to lapse the legislation which the Government contemplates for the better preservation of publio order should be passed. If that, legislate on is passed, the Home Office could offer noions.s Seoretary.,objeotionTREASURY.
objection to fixing the end of the war at the date suggested, and it would he of advantage to act under new powers rather than under powers given during the war and generally regarded as more or less moribund.I am,Sir,Ynur obedient Servant,(Sgd*)   EDWARD lEROUPt
Sir,With further reference to your letter of the  7th instant (F.33S1) respecting the question of declaring at an early date the termination of the war under the Termination of the Present War (Definition) Act, 1918, I am directed &quot;by the Secretary of State to say that he desires to-supple ment his previous letter of todayTs date on two points.If the termination of the war is fixed for the 4th August it will he necessary to continue the Workmenls Compensation (War Addition) Act, 1917, as amended &quot;by the Workmen^ Compensation (War Addition) Act, 1919.   This could he done in the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill if thero is no objection on grounds of policy.If the termination of the war is fixed for the 4th August there will he an interval of four weeks in which the traffic in dangerous drugs will he uncontrolled as the Regulations under the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1920, do not come into force until September 1st.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Sgd.) EDWARD TROUP. ecret&amp;ry,ASURY.HOME OFFICE, WHITEHALL.30th June, 1921.0,314/55.
Sir,In reply to your letter (li1.3321) of 27th June respecting the proposal to declare the War ended on the 4th August next, I am directed by the Board of Trade to stato that they do not desire to offer any objection to this proposal.Action will, of course, have to be taken in certain matters by this Department in connection with the termination of the War, but no real difficulty is anticip-ated in any case other than that of the oil well at Hards toft, with regard to which a Memorandum is enclosed,I am to ask you to be good enough to take this letter as applying also to the communication which you addressed to the Secretary of the Ministry of Shipping&apos;, That Ministry lias been terminated, and such of its powers and duties as still remain have been transferred to the Board of Trade.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant, (SD) H.A. PAYffiil.The Secretary, Treasury, S.W.1,BOAR]) 01? TFtADEGreat George Street,mmit S.V/.L.5th July 1921.
PROPOSED TERMINATION OF THE WAR. Petroleum in Great Britain.1.   Messrs. S. Pearson &amp; Son, under authorization of the Board of Trade, and using public funds, have been obtaining, under Defence of the Realm Regulation 2&amp;AA, petroleum on the Duke of Devonshire1s land at Hardstoft, Derby;   the Board of Trade have sold about 500 tons, 300 tons more is in store, and production is continuing at the rate of one to three tons daily.2.   The Board will have no further statutory powers when the Regulation comes to an end at the termination of the war, which it is proposed to fix for August 4th. After that they and Messrs. Pearson will be in the position of trespassers, and be liable to have legal proceedings taken against them.   The most complete solution of this difficulty would no doubt be the passing of such legislation as would regularise their position, but it is not expected that any such legislation could be passed in sufficient time.   Indeed, the Cabinet, last Spring, had a Petroleum Bill before them for vesting in the Crown all rights in Petroleum existing in the United Kingdom in the natural state, but they decided on March 7th - Cabinet 11 (21) -that the Bill should not then be introduced and that a certain legal action which had already been begun by the Duke, should take its course.     (See CP.2482).3.   This action, which is still pending against Sir John Cadman of the Petroleum Department and Messrs. Pearson, seeks for the recovery of the value of the oil already sold, for a declaration by the Court that the property in the oil is vested in the Duke as owner of the land, and for damages for trespass.   The Board of Trade defence is (at least inpart
part) that they acted under the Regulation and further, that the Indemnity Act is a bar to the proceedings.4.     The question as to what course should be taken after the date of the legal termination of the v/ar, in view of the position indicated in paragraph 2 above, - whether for instance an attempt should be made to arrive at a friendly arrangement with the IDuke of Devonshire - Is under consideration.Board of Trade.5th July, 1921.
r    297Copy,I.S.C.MffJm SHffEIP. Roferenoe B* 877.With reference to your 3?,2321 of the 27th ultimo relative to the date to he declared for the termination of the war, I attach copy of a reply sent me by the Ministry of Transport with their observations on the proposal to declare the war ended on the 4th August next.(Sgd) S. Hardman Lever.6th July 1921.6, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.
0 opy.Treasury Officer.With reference to the official letter from the Treasury of the 37th ultimo in regard to the date of the termination of the War, we have no comments to make upon the draft Order in Council, except that it does considerably increase the urgency of a settlement as to the future of the surplus works on and adjoining railway property.   A letter has however been despatched to the Standing Committee of General Managers, pointing out the probability of an early termination of the War by Order in Council, and putting forward to them proposals as a basis for discussion with a view to broad principles being agreed without delay upon which the Railway Companies would be prepared to negotiate for the acquisition of the works in question.A copy of the letter is attached.(Sgd) R.FRANC IS OTNElIu5th July. 1921.
WAR OPHGB,LONDON, S.W.Sth July, 1921.121/9849. (0.2.)Urgent.Sir,In reply to your letter P.3321 of 27th Juno, on the subject of a proposal to fix the 4th August next as the date of the official termination of the war under the Termination of the Present War (])efinition) Act 1918, I am commanded by the Army Council to make the following observations for the information of the Jkrcs Commissioners of His Majesty1 s Treasury.,The official termination of the war mainly concerns the War Department in connection with its effect on the Department1s rights over lands and buildings occupied for war purposes.As from the date fixed for the termination of the warthe right to remain in occupation of such lands and buildingswill be governed by the Defenoe of the Realm (Acquisition ofLand) Act 1916.    Under that Aot, as Their lordships are aware, there are certain classes of property e.g, landbelonging to railway and dock companies, local authorities,etc., of which there is no power to remain in occupation for more than three months after the war unless the consent ofthe &quot;appropriate&quot; Government Department iB obtained to a longer occupation.    There are a very large number of cases to which this provision applies e,g. railway sidings to factories, sites of storage sheds in docks, etc, etc.,   TheDepartment has been endeavouring for a long time past to obtainThe Secretary, listsTHSASUEY.
lists of the so properties but the lists are still by nomeans complete or up-to date.   It is obvious thatthese oases will entail considerable correspondence with the various appropriate Government &quot;Departments who will themselves, no doubt, wish to obtain the views of theauthorities who own the properties oonoerned.From this point of view It would be very desirable(1)   that this &quot;Department should have longer notice of the official termination of the war than that allowed by the Chancellor of the Exchequers proposals.(2)   that the date fixed for the termination of the war should not fall in the usual leave season, when the staffs of all Government offices are much depleted.It would be more convenient, therefore, that the date should be fixed at a time when the departmental machinery is in full working order, e,g. about the end of September.It must also be borne in mind that by the combined effect of the Defence of the Realm (Acquisition of Land) Acts 1916 and 1920 property occupied under the Defence of the Realm Act can only be transferred to a Government Department, other than the Admiralty, War Department and Air Ministry, before the termination of the War.   This, hov/ver, is a point which does not specially affect the War Department.With regard to pensions, I am to point out that the Cabinet has not yet deralt with the Report of the Committee on Post War Disability rates, which takes effect
30 days after the legal termination of the warfi A question raised by this Department as regards the effect of the cessation of the war rates for disability and death if hostilities are still continuing in Ireland at the date of termination is already under the notice of the Cabinet in this connection.*I am,*Sir,Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) H.J.CKE&amp;DY.
COPY iDISPOSAL AND L1Q,UTMTI0I COMMISblON.Surplus Government Property, SeeiGen/2564 (A4) Disposal Board,Caxtbn House (West Block), Tothill Street, London, S.W.I. 9th July, 1921,Sir,I am directed by the Disposal and Liquidation Oom-raission to acknowledge the receipt of Treasury letter of the 27th ultimo, Ho. .3321, with enclosures, regarding the declaration of the official date of the termination of the war.The only respect in which the functions of this Department will be materially affected is as regards works erected during the war on land the property of Railway Companies and other Public Authorities.     Their Lordships will remember that, to secure adequate time for the disposal of these works, the D.O.R.(Acquisition of Land) Act 1916, was   .amended by the D.O.R. (Acquisition of Land) Act, 1920, by which power is given to the appropriate Government Department to approve extended tenure of land for the purpose of facilitating disposals.The Commission assume that Their Lordships willgive the necessary directions to the Departments concerned to secure that the provisions of the Act 1920, are appliedso as to safeguard Government interests.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant.,The Secretary, (Sgd. )   D. FJYLAUTreasury.-Li..- .
tExtract from a Note from the Secretary of the Liquor Control Board *Mr. Eisner, the Chairman of the Home Affairs Committee, is aware that unless before the end of the war statutory provision had been made by Parliament both fa) in substitution for the existing Orders of the Central Control Board and also (b) in relation to the ownership and continuance of the Board1 s Direct Control Undertakings (Carlisle, etc), an Order in Council would have to have been made under the power given by Section 1 (I) of the Defence of the Realm (Amendment) (No.3) Act, 1915.   UnLess this were done, (a) the country would automatically lapse at the end of the war into pure pre-war conditions in regard to the hours of sale of intoxicating liquor and to the other conditions of sale which are regulated by the board Orders, and (b) there would be no person or body with any powers to manage or dispose of the property in the Board1s Direct Control Areas.If, however, a Liquor Bill were passed so as to come into operation before the end of the war, the necessary provision could be made in such a Bill, and no Order in Council would be necessary.
Copy.CUSTOMHOUSE, LOHDON, El 3.3. 60371/1921. nth July, 1921Sir,With reference to Treasury Letter lo. F. 3321 ofthe 27th ultimo, transmitting a copy of a Draft Order inCouncil declaring the termination of the War under theTermination of the Present Tar (Definition) Act, 1918,I am directed by the Board of Customs and Excise to state,for the information of the Lords Commissioners of H.M.Treasury, that, so far as this. Department is concerned, theproposed Proclamation will have the following effect.2. The operation of the undermentioned Acts, which areonly in force during a War in which Hi3 Majesty is engaged,will be suspended, viz:-(a) The Customs (Exportation Prohibition) Act, 1914, which extends the power to prohibit export under section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879 to goods of every description, and(b ) The Customs (Exportation Restriction) Act, 1914, which extends in a similar manner the provisions of the Exportation of Arms Act,1900.3. The proposed Proclamation will also have the effect of bringing to an end the Defence of the Realm Regulations and any Acts which remain in force during the present war only.   These Acts include the Customs (War Powers) Act, 1915, the Customs (War Powers) (lo.2.) Act, 1915, the Customs (Export Restriction) Act, 1915, the Customs (War Powers) Act, 1916 and the Output of Beer (Restriction) Act, 1916*4. The only Customs provisions in the War time Acts which it has been necessary to make permanent are -(a) those contained in Sections 1, 2 and 3 of theOust Mr
Customs (War Powers) Act, 1915, which extendCustoms control over the shipment of stores and the cirriap-o of goods and clearance ofshins coaotwlso, andfh) those contained in Section 4 of the Customs(War Po.vers) Act, 1916, which make it an offence to.attempt to ship p.:oods requiring pro-entry and clearance..The continuance of these provisions will hesecured on the passing of the finance Bill for the current year (see clause 11 as regards (a) and clause 13 asregards fb) ).5. The provisions of the Output of Beer (Restriction) Act, 1916, have ceased to be enforced, so far as they effect this Department, under the authority of Treasury letter 35134/19 of 30th August 1919-.6. So far as my Commissioners are aware, the only existing absolute import prohibition under the Defence of the Realm Regulations is the prohibition of the importation of Carrier and Homing Pigeons, and this prohibition will presumably lapse under the proposed Order in Council.   This is a matter primarily for the Admiralty to consider.7. Export Prohibitions are now confined mainly to the following four classes of goods:-(a) Gold and silver, fb) Fertilisers.(c) Dangerous drugs.(d) Arms and ammunition.The continuance of these prohibitions is secured by thefa) Gold and silver Export Control Act, 1920.(b) Fertilisers (Temporary Control of Export)Act&apos;, 1920.
The Secretary to the Treasury, Treasury Chambers.(o) Dangerous Drugs act, 1920.(a) Order in Council of 24th March, 1921, made under s.8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act,1879, prohibiting the export of Arms and ammunition.8. No provision ,has been made for continuing afterthe legal termination of the war the existing prohibitionson the export of &quot;Nicotine and its pounds&quot; and &quot;Whiskey&quot;,which depend  on special war legislation, and theseprohibitions will presumably lapse.   The department concerned with these prohibitions is the Imports and exports Licensing Section of the Board of Trade.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Sd)
COMMITTEE BOOM copy*. THE STOCK EXCHANGE,LONDON, E.C.23rd May 1921.The Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Home K.C. Chancellor of the Exchequer.Sir,The long delay in the issue of the Order in Council announcing the Official, termination of the Present War is causing considerable anxiety to the Committee of The Stock Exchange.When the Emergency Rules were passed in accordance with the Treasury Scheme of the 31st October 1914 for providing Government assistance in dealing with account to account loans on the Stock Exchange and the Temporary Regulations for the Re-opening of the Stock Exchange were made in December of that year, it was not anticipated that the War would last as long as it did or that so long a period would elapse between the termination of hostilities and the ratification of the Peace Treaties.It will be remembered that the Scheme provided for the holding up of the completion of certain loans and transactions until twelve months after the conclusion of peace or after the expiry of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act 1914 whichever should happen first.It must also be remembered that the arrangements made in the autumn of 1914 did not contemplate the entry of Turkey into the War and that the principal obstacle at the present time to the issue of the Order in Council seems to be the difficulty in getting Peace signed with a Power not in the mind either of the Government or the Committee at the time the arrangements were made.The Committee are very anxious that all outstandingStock
Stock Exchange obligations should be completed at the earliest possible date and it seems to them that there is at the present time no reason politics! or financial which should prevent the realisation of thitf desire.They therefore ask the Government to earnestly oonsider whether some special step should not be taken to at once fix a date on which the twelve months laid down in the Scheme should commence and it appears to the Committee that the proviso in Clause 1(1) of the Termination of the Present War (Definition) Act 1916 should enable the Government to do so.In the event of the Government deciding to accede to their request the Committee suggest that the 4th August 1921 the seventh anniversary of the Declaration of War with Germany, would be a suitable date, provided, of oourse, that the order in Council has not previously been made.I am Sir,Yours truly, (SD) EDWARD SATTSETBWAITE. Secretary..Manchester Stook Exchange have strongly supported these re commendat ions.
COPY THE BATORS CLEAR 111G HOUSE,Lombard 3treet, London E.C. 2nd June 1921*Dea r M r. Cha no e 11 o r,At a meeting of the Committee of the London Clearing Bankers this day it was unanimously resolved that the Chancellor of the Exchequer should be informed that the Bankers have read the letter addressed to the Chancellor by the Stock Exchange on the 23rd May, asking that the 4th August 1921 should be made the official date at which the War should end, if no Order in Council be previously made.     The Bankers understand that very special legislation will be required for this and they urge that the Government should put the matter in hand at once, since the delay in arriving at the termination of the War is causing serious inconvenience to the business community of the country.Yours sincerely,(SD)     R.   HOLLAND MARTIN. Hon. Secretary.Both the Bank of England and the Clearing Bankers have, made further urgent representations orally in the same sense.Sir Robert Horne, C.B.E., K.C., M.P.The Chancellor of the Exchequer, The Treasury,Whitehall, S.W.
, C A B I g E T       ,BRITISH NAVAL POLICY. Memo, by the First Lord of^ the Admiralty(CtPi 3137),The attention of Ministers is drawn to the specially SECRET nature y of this paper.2,, Whitehall Gardens., 16th July 1921.

</content>
</cab>
