<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 584-589</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This DocHfwent Is tho Property of......... * i     wmtjKM] mi mAMHisSECRET!?,To be destroyed when replaced by a subsequent number.SE0R3T   ADMIRALTY ffMKLY   INTELLIGENCE . SU1MEIY.No. 28.   16th July, 1921.Issued by the Naval Intelligence Division, Naval Staff, Admiralty, for the information of Recipients only.DISTRIBUTION, Sent Toy All British Route to :-rd of Admiralty.................f.Sec.,Naval Sec.,P.A.S.F. ,P.A.S..v Captain........................Cabinet......................... ,Navy Board, Melbourne..........,Naval Board, New Zealand ......actor, Navy Service, Ottawa ......N.A.C..........................QopjjBS,. Copies,.*&quot;l0 Admiralty naval staff i-4 I.D.................   18O.D*4...............Jd of Naval Section, Paris al Representative,League of Nations .. * Imanders-in-Chief :-The Nore .......* % * * *Portsmouth ..........Plymouth............Scotland............v7. Approaches .......Atlantic Fleet ......North America &amp; Mediterranean .......China.......&apos;........East Indies .........Africa..............1*0., Reserve Fleet ......1st Battle Squadroni.Vi *r1.1st Battle Squadron 4th Battle Squadron .......Battle Cruiser squadron ... 1st Light Cruiser Squadron 2nd Light Cruiser Squadron 3rd Light Cruiser SquadronYangtse ...................(D)&quot;.......................* . *o . ** a *40 2 2 1 1 11 1 1 1 1 2 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1P.D.......T.D. ..............Intelligence Officers:-S.I.0&apos;8&quot;-Mediterranean ........China...............East Indies .......**.S. America..........N. America ...........D.I.0?s -Portsmouth..........Chatham.............Devonport ...........Rosyth..............Liverpool..............Queenstown.............Gibraltar...............Malta............S.....Colombo................Singapore...........*Shanghai ...........* * * *Wellington .....*Cape Town ..............Bermuda................Ascension ..............Liaison 1.0., Melbourne ..Liaison 1.0., Ottawa &apos;.....N.L.O., Hong Kong........N.V.C., Monte Video ......N.V.C., Callao ....2 11 1 1 1 11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 II 1 1 1 total (Distribution by Copying Branch;TOTAL (I.D.Distribution)      50
To be destroyed when replaced by a subsequent number.REGRET   ADMIRALTY&quot;Jill mi J     ill III II      I tmft K*ta^l *i*W*/wv^l-^w**WWEEKLY   INTELLIGENCE   mmiSZ.(flMoS.)No. 28.   For the week ending 16th Jjflylg&amp;La PART   1*   NAVAL   BTTELLIGMOE.ii i. mm  we.*m mi iji.....f *r iI-ti w-----&quot;*&apos; -i-&quot; &apos;*--* f -jt***.**t-r iit^^jPROGRAMMED   OF , H. Jfe SHIPS.H.M.S. &quot;CCMTS&quot;, &quot;CAROLINE&quot;, C-in-C, East Indies, v/lll arrive Mauritius 19th July and remain about a fortnight, calling at Chagos Islands on return.H.M.S. &quot;RALEIGH&quot; - Oamnrissions as soon after 19th July as possible and proceeds to Bermuda without delay.H.M.S. &quot;DANAE, &quot;tfESSEX&quot; and WINDSOR8 - Leave Copenhagen 18th July, Danzig 19-23 July, Memel 24-20 July, Libau 2o-27 July. Riga 2&amp;-30 July, Revel 31st July - 2nd Aug., Helsingfors 2-5 Aug., Stockholm 6-9 Aug., Copenhagen 11-13 Aug., returning to England via Kiel Canal.H.M.S. &quot;DILIGENCE&quot; - To relieve Blenheim in Mediterranean as depot ship, 7th Destroyer Flotilla.RUSSIA,The three Norwegian sealers, captured about two months ago in the flhite Sea and taken to Arkangel, have been heavily fined.   Each sealer has to pay 10,000 gold roubles together with confiscation of the vessel1 s catch.   The Norwegian Minister of Foreign Affairs has sent a strong protest to Moscow requesting a reconsideration of the case.A dredger has been sent to tfindau and it is expected that in about two months time *7indau harbour will have its pre-war depth of water.A Russian delegation inspected the icebreakers &quot;SVXATOGOR&quot; and &quot;ALEXANDER&quot; on July 14th at Roayth.   They propose to take over the &quot;SVIATOOOR&quot; as soon as possible and &quot;ALEXANDER&quot; later.According to latest reports ex-Rear-Admiral Nernitz, .affairs ormer O-icr-0 0, Black Sea Fleet, succeeds Captain Behrens as head of the Soviet Naval Administration at Maeoow, tho-latter having been appointed as Soviet representative on the International Mine Clearance Committee.    Sailor Ziif O^off) is now Baltic Fleet Commissar.   Ex-Lieutenant Viktorov commands the Baltic Fleet, ex-Commander Petrov commands the Baltic Torpedo Flotillas and ex-Oommander Baron Maidel commands the Baltic trawlers and minesweepers.   Ex-Captain Panzerjanski commands the Black sea Fleet.
General Press reports $tate that conditions for ships entering Petrograd and tot discharging cargoes are favourable, but that apart front this^ conditions are very bad.   Pood is very aaarde arid very bad,   crater is infected with typhus. Ships should provide themselves before arrival with food stores to cover their stay in port.The Greek Master and crew of the Greek steamer &quot;POLYXENI&quot; under British charter have been arrested at Sevastopol on the plea that Greece had declared war on Soviet Russia.Swedish Press July 2nd announoes the launch of a new submarine &quot;ILLERN8.   A seoond submarine &quot;UTTSRN&quot; will probably be launched in August.A flotilla of German Minesweepers has obtained permission to visit Paresund during July and August.UNITED STATES.The U,S. Battle Ship &quot;MASSACHUSETTS1 was laid down on 4th April 1921,   She is the last Battleship of the 1916 Programme.
PART II. MESOPOTAMIA iInterest in Turkish affairs and propaganda is dying out and leading Sheiks- of North Shammar, who have for some time past been on intimate relations with &quot;the Turks, are making overtures to come in.LITHUANIA.The Lithuanian Cabinet has definitely decided against the acceptance of the Geneva resolutiongof 28th June, and Seim endorsed the Cabinet action on July 9th.   The League of Nations has been informed that the Lithuanuan represantatives would be unable to attend at Brussels on July 15th and a considered reply to resolutions has been promised as soon as possible.RUSSIA.Siberia. It is now reported that General Notchaiev has been unable to advanoe owing to sujjerior strength of the Bolshevik forces.   Semenov intends to prooeed to Mongolia, although Baron Ungern is now unwilling to co-operate..The Bolsheviks appear to be adopting a waiting policy with regard to events in the Near East.  By establishing large foroes on the Turkish frontier - particularly in the vicinity of Batum - they can exercise strong moral pressure on the Nationalists and Persians and at the same time maintain a menace to British interests.NQRffAY.Strong Bolshevik propaganda is reported in the North of Norway.   It wotfld appear that headquarters will be at Tromso under a Russian Captain Botohovski.GERMANY.The situation in Upper Si&amp;Qsia in becoming strained largely on account of the delay in arriving at a definite decision as to the frontier.General Hoeff er has been superseded by General von Leokny who enjoyed a very bad reputation when he was in command of German troops in Poland in 1919.The Commission have asked for further re-informeigents.
The Austrian request to be allowed to manufacture civil aircraft has been refused pending a settlement by the Supreme Council as to the control of civil aircraft in ex-enemy countries oh the withdrawal of aeronautical Commissions of Control.DANUBE,The Conference in Paris has now drawn up a Convention regarding the Administration of the Danube, the signature of which is fixed for the 21st July.   The Italian representative has throughout taken up an uncompromising attitude over the imposition of dues and taxation questions, with the object apparently of promoting Italian economic interests in the Adriatic.AE3OTIA.In a report dated July 11th the Armenian Archbishop of Tabriz states that the Zahgezur Ar&amp;ox&amp;5&amp;$ have been completely overcome by a determined Bolshevik attack from all sides.SERBIA.tfith referenoe to rumours of Jugo-Slav troop movements in Albania the Ju&amp;o-Slav Government state that their troops *have not advanoed but have in plaoes withdrawn to better defensive positions as an attack by the Albanians is expeoted. The Jugo-Slav Government oannot endure these perpetually rocurring attacks and orders have been sent that if the Albanians do attack they are to be punished in an exemplary manner.TCfRKgy.The situation at Constantinople is much improved, the dangerous elements being 7/ell under control and the $riutfLsh administration much respeoted.General Harington does not consider the door closed as regards a meeting with M* Kemal and y/ill not be surprisedfurther developments.   As regards an attack on Constantinople t!he General feels that the city &quot;and the Dardanelles must be the main objective of the Kemal is ts, who, if the Greek offensive fails, will not be slow to turn their attentions that way and will be urged on in doing so by Moscow.Kemal1st forces ih the Ismid area are estimated at 7,500, but there may be forces in reserve raising this total to 13,000.   Identifications in this area are difficult and unsatisfactory, and the Kemalists have a complete system of centre espionage.The Greek offensive which commenced 10th July is proceeding according to plan.AUSTRIA,
Brusa Front.    Aghachhlssar has &quot;been reached and the lineYenisher-Hassan passed.Ushak Front.    The line YennJkeui-Vaku reached.Greek Cavalry were operating west of Sandikli on 11th.General Papoulos reports that the Greek advance towards Eskishehir and Kutahia continues with insignificant losses and meets with little opposition.   Greeks also report the occupation of Afivp. Karahissar.N.I.D. Note.        .T.I.S. No. 27, page 4, &quot;Greece&quot;,   For Smyrnaread Salonica.CHINA.Early in June, first Ichang arid then tfuchang, which is opposite Hankow were burnt and looted by Chinese soldiery. At the former place foreign property and interests suffered considerable damage.   The British Minister in Peking considers it quite probable that further outbreaks of a similar nature may occur, and therefore an increased amount of police work may be required of the Naval Forces in the Yangtze.

</content>
</cab>
