<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 697-700</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-   41911-: &quot;DOQULPKT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMEM T)CABINS!?3RET r\ &apos;3l53Q.O.VER39jM0SNT BUSINESSMemorandum by the Ohief Whip1 circulate herewith, for the Information of the Members of tho Cabinet, the following statement with regard to the business of the House to be completed before Prorogation, and I attach two statements - (A) suggested business of the House for the next few weeks (B) a list of Bills now on the Order Paper, or of which I have had notice of presentation, showing the various stages of these Bills,The main reason which prevents tho House rising is the necessity for the passing into law the Railways Bill, and, under no circumstances would it be possible for the House to rise before the 19th August if the Railways and the Safeguarding of Industries Bills are to be passed, even if other legislation were delayed until an Autumn Session.Prom Statement (A) it will be seen that up to the 11th August, there is no time available for any Bills other than Supply, the Rail-ways Bill and the Safeguarding of Industries Bill, except after 11 p9m. It is evident that the Opposition intend to obstruct, as far as they possibly can, any business taken after 11 pm,, and,  pom Information which I have, this intention to obstruct is animated by the desire to kill the Safeguarding of Industries Bill.It will be seen further from statement (A) that If we proceed with the Railways Bill, and leave the Safeguarding of Industries Bill until the former Bill has reached the House of Lords, the Railways Bill can be sent to the Lords on the night of the 9th August; on the other hand, we cculd complete the remaining three allotted days of the Safeguarding of Industries Bill
as soon as possible and the Railways Bill would then reach the house of lor els on the evening of the 11th August.Taking into consideration that there would he only t^o days difference, I would submit that the Safeguarding of Industries Bill should be completed first as I consider this would remove a good deal of the opposition when it was found that the Government intended that this Bill should  becoma law.:1th regard to statement (B) I hope it will be possible for instructions to be given that several of these Bills need not be proceeded with, hut, while the Railways Bill is being considered by the House of Lords, it will be possible to pass the necessary remainder of these measures which it has not been possible to deal with after 11 o&apos;clock on preceding days.If tho Hallways Bill reaches the House of lords on the 11th August, the Safeguarding of Industries Bill having been token first, there is reasonable hope that it will be possible to Prorogue Parliament by the 86th of that month, but it might be necessary to sit for a week after that date.(Signed)     E3SLIB rjILSON.12, Downing Street, S.&quot;.r, July 22nd. 1921.
W!421&quot; A &quot;SUGGESTED BUSINESS IN THE HOUSE.Com production Acts (Repeal) Bill;   Report and3rd Reading.Supply:   (19th allotted day) Treasury vote.Railways Bill;;   1st allotted day of Report stage.Supply: (20th allotted day) Scottish estimates, or Corn Production Acts (Repeal) Bill; 3rd Reading.Finance Bill;   3rd Reading.Railways Bill; 2nd allotted day of Report stage, or Safeguarding of Industries Bill;   1st allotted dayof Report stage.Railways Bill; 3rd allotted day of Report stage, or Safeguarding of Industries Bill;   2nd allotted dayof Report stage.Supply;   Committee stage - Guillotine. Extra SupplySupply:   Report stage   - Guillotine.   Extra Supply (labour vote.) day*Safeguardiar ^ industries Bill;   3rd Reading.Railways Bill;   2nd or 4th allotted day of Report stageRailways Bill;   3rd or 5th allotted day of report stage and 3rd Reading.Safeguarding of Industries Bill; 1st and 2nd allotted days of Report stage, or remaining two allotted days of the Railways Bill.day.Safeguarding of Industries Bill;   3rd Reading, or other Bills..
BILLS WHICH MUST BECOME! LAV/ BEIGES PROROGATION.20.Title of Bill,Admiralty tensions* * 6Consolidated Fund (2 days) ,oo Criminal Lav.&apos; Amendment (Hi/,.,Criminal Law Proceduro (Scotland) (EC.L*)5*   Education (Consolidation)(EL) cExpiring Lews (Continuance).^ Government of Burma (EL)m a 4J    0 * irish Railways (Settlement of Claims)Juries (BmergencytProvisione) (Renewal/ (ED). ovt10,   Licensing (No03)Law of Property (HL)Land Settlement AmendmentPolice Pensionse . o4*00*0Salmon &amp; Freshwater Fisheries (Noc2)15.   Territorial Army &amp; Militia^ Telegraph (Money)Trusts (Scotland) (HL), War Pensionso e *)oeoWater Undertakings (Modifioa^ tion of charges)c0 0.Supreme Court-Of f ioers1(Retirement, Pensionsf etc) BillaProgress.To he introduced. (Financial Resolut-ionjpassed)To be introduced. Standing Committee, 15/7/21,End Reading.2nd Reading,To he introduceda2nd Reading?To he introduced, (Financial Resolution required2nd Readingo 2nd Readings 2nd Readings 2nd Reading o Lords Amendments.2nd Reading.Standing Committee. 20/7/21,To he introduced.(Financial Resolution passed).2nd BeadingoReport and 3rd Reading..Report and 3rd ReadingoTo he introduced...Exchequer and Audit Bill.To he introduced.

</content>
</cab>
