<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 784-788</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.To bs destroyed when replaced by a subsequent number.SECRET   ADMIRALTYWEEKLY   INTSLLIgMCE   SOMMMff.(W.I.S.)No. 29.   23rd July 1921.Issued by the Naval Intelligence Division, Naval Staff, Admiralty, for the information of Recipients only.DISTRIBUTION, Sent by all British. Route to :-Board of Admiralty.................Dep*3eo. yNaval Sec ,P.A.S.F. .P.A.S..Duty Captain .....................*.rue Cabinet........................Sec. ,Ns,vy Board, Melbourne.......**Sec, feral Board, New Zealand .....Director, Navy Service, Ottawa .....P.A.N.A.0........................Head of Naval Section, Paris .......Naval Representative,League of Nations .........Conmanders-in-chief the Nore.................*Portsmouth...............*Plymouth ..................Scotland..................W. Approaches.......Atlantic Fleet............North America &amp; W.I. Mediterranean ......China o. rt..........East Indies Africa V.A.C., Reserve Fleet V^AcC, 1st Battle Squadron R.A*R. A., R&amp;A. , R^A*,1st Battle Squadron4th Battle Squadron..........Battle Cruiser Squexlron......lat Light Cruiser Squadron ... R.A., 2nd Li$it Cruitnr Squadron ... R.A., 3rd Li $it Cruiser Squadron ...R.A., Yangtss **....*..............R.A., (D)..........................TOTAL (Distribution by Copying Branch).Copies. Copies.10 Admiralty Naval Staff4 I.D................. 181 O.D. ................ 340 P.D. ................ 22 T.D................. 12 Intelligence Officers1 S.I.O&apos;s-1     Mediterranean.......... 11     China.................. 1East Indies ............ 11     S. Amerioa............. 1IT. America............. 11 D.IoO&apos;s -1 Portsmouth .............. 11 Ch&amp;tfoam ................ 11 Devonport .............. it1 RcVjjoh ................. 12      Hull................... 11     Liverpool.............. 11     Queenstown............. 1 -1 Gibraltar .............. 11      Mil&amp;a.................. 11     Colombo................ 11     Sii^pore.............. 11     $lan^hai..............* 11     Wellington............. 11     Cape Town.............. 11     Bermuda        ........... 11     Ascension.............. 11 Liaison I.O., Melbourne . 11 Liaison 1.0,., Ottawa .... 11    NoL.O., Hong Kong....... 11    N.V.C., Monte Video ..... 1N.V.O., Gallao...... 185TOTAL (I.D. Distribution)50
SECRET!, 1.To &quot;be destroyed when replaced &quot;by a subsequent number.SSOHgT   ADMIRAUTYtoely intellig^joe swmz.No. 29,......For the week ending 23rd July 1921,PART   I.   NAVAL   INTELLIGENCE. GREAT   BRITAIN. Movements of HoM. Ships.19th July. H.M.S. &quot;Thunderer1 arrived Bergen from scapa Flow.20th July. H.M.S. &quot;Dauntless1 and &quot;Velox&quot; arrived Havre from Oowes.22nd July. H.M.S. &quot;Monafch&quot; left Portsmouth for Gibraltar and Malta.23rd July. H.2 .S. &quot;Calcutta&quot; left Portsmouth forBermuda.PROGRAMMES.H.ILS. ^Thunderer* (revised) visits Vik, Hardanger .&quot; Fiord 25-511 iriilyi&apos; j5EH35I53La 1-5 August, Portsmouth 8th August.HOLS, o^onaroh&quot; left Portsmouth 22nd July Gibraltar 26-27 Ju:iy/lalTa&apos;T0uTTuly-6 Aug., Gibraltar 9-10 August, Devonport 14th Aug., Portsmouth 15th August.H*M0S. 8Raleighf/will not sail until further orders.EJioSo &quot;Bfrribow^ Leaves Constantinople 6th August for Malta Co reTit.AUSTRIA r1!he first merchant ship flying the Austrian ensign since the war left Wolgast early in July for Mediterranean ports.ITALY.2 Oil Tankers are being built for the Italian Navy at Messrs. Caamdro of Flume.   These vessels will-^eaoh have a carrying capacity of 1,800 tons and will be named &quot;Istria&quot; and nDalmaz&quot;iai&apos;&apos;.An oil tanker with anti-submarine protection is being built at the Cantiert di Riva Trigoso and will be called the &quot;Brennero&quot;.
ROMANIA.The Naval Base of Constanza is to he transferred to Sulina.   At present two lighters have heen fitted out as engineering and repair workshops.   A tank is being built outside the town of Sulina for the storage of petrol.   It is understood that an aerodrome is also to be built on the beach near Sulina.   500 naval recruits have been brou$vt to the nei^ibourhood of Sulina for training purposes.DANUBE.The Danube Flotilla left Belgrade on the morning of 21st July.   Their reception has been marked by the greatest cordiality.UNITED STATES.U.S.S. &quot;Utah1 arrived at Lisbon from U.S.A. on 18th July.   She will prooeed thence to Cherbourg where Vice-Admiral Niblack will transfer to her froiaU.S.S. &quot;Pittsburgh&quot;, - the &quot;Utah&quot; becoming flagship of U.S. Naval Forces in European Waters.Subsequently U.S.S. &quot;Utah&quot; will attend Oowes Regatta flying Vice-Admiral Nlblaok s flag.
* 3 t*PART   II. GENERAL   INTST-LIGMOS.PERSIA.Sayed ed Dowleh!s foroes have lately succeeded in driving &quot;back the Persian  Cossacks and capturing the Salamvar Pass, some 30 miles to the eastward of Kasvin, thereby threatening the Kasvin-Teheran Road and the Cogsack line of communication.The situation- has been further complicated by the arrival at Resht of 500 Soviet Government troops, who are demanding that ICuchik Khan should hand over all arms and anrainition received from the Russians since 1917.   Kuohik Khan has sent a representative to Tehran, with a proposal to the Persian Government that they should, for the moment, set aside their, mutual differences and take combined action with a view to driving out the Russians.HJSSIA.Confirmatory reports of the failure of the harvest in South Eastern Russia have been received.HDNQARg.The Conference of Ambassadors have decided to bring the Treaty of Trianon into force on 26th July.ALBANIA.Somewhat serious fighting has occurred during the past few days in Mirditia and Rtheila, the Chiefs having risen against the Government.The Greek   blister for Foreign Affairs has received a telegram from the leader of the l&amp;rdites declaring their (Mirdites) constitution an independent Republic, separate from the rest of Albania, and asking for Greek recognitionsJUGO SLAVIA.Monsieur Drashkovitch, ex Minister of the Interior, was shot at Delnice in Croatia on 21st July.   The assassin is said to be a Bosnian Mussulman of 18 years of age.ARMENIA.Attacks on Zangorzur by large Russian forces, and[ repression at Erivan continue.TURKEY&quot; *General Harington reports that all the best Turks have become Kemalists, and that he has had to disband his squadron of Turkish cavalry as it was discovered that Turkish Officers were plotting to shoot the British Officers.
The first phase of the Greek offensive appears to he complete with the capture of Kutaya on 17th July, and of EsfcLshehr on 20th July, and the army is being rested and stores sent forward.It is understood that the Greeks will re-oooupy Ismid in the near future, probably with a view to using the railway.

</content>
</cab>
