<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 958-960</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Hag PQOUment &amp;g tfhe Property of His Britannia Majesty&quot; 8 Goverroriftnt..!IRELANDT MILITARY LAW, COMMITTEE.SBEffiI*The reference to this Committee is,-wTo examine with special reference to recent events in Ireland the steps to be taken to establish firmly the position of the Mill-tary Oovernor under martial law, se that his proceedings shall be recognised as final and unaffected by the proceedings in a court of law&quot;.We think it proper in the first place to point out that all these objects, were, until recent events, quite fully secured.   The law was and is clear that in an area where martial law applies the writ of habeas corpus does not run. With tile exception of the Master of the Rolls in Ireland, every Judge in that country has repelled such an attempt. This Judge, however, has recently directed the issue of a rule nisi for such a writ and ordered the rule to be made returnable before himself for the purpose of being made absolute.   On the return day the same Judge sj&amp;sl directed writs of attachment to issue against the Commander-in-Chief, the Military Governor, and other officers, adding a rh^orical allocution to the effect that if these orders were disobeyed the arm of the law would be shown to be paralysed.The Committee are of opinion that the principles involved were so important, and an indefinite addition to the number was of casea/so certain, that it would have been wise to challenge the issue there and then *** not, indeed, by way of-1-(mm     j*
appeal, for no appeal lies in such a case, hut by disregarding the order s6 made.This course, however, was not adopted.   On the contrary, the two persons detained in custody were ordered to be released, with the result that there was an acquiescence, at least apparent,, in the illegal assumption by the Judgo of the right to issue a writ of attachment under the circum-stances indicated.We are now as ted to advise how the authority of the mili-tary Courts may be most effectively asserted against the usurped jurisdiction of the Master of the Rolls in Ireland. 1ve have no difficulty In answering this question.   If and when applications are made in analogous cases, and similar orders are made, the routine may be expected to repeat itself. Under these circumstances in due course further writs of attachment will no doubt be issued.   These should be absolute-ly disregarded, and the instructions given by the Chief Secretary ^or Ireland and the Secretary of State for &apos;?/ar in the present case should be repeated and made applicable to the cases under consideration.We do not find ourselves able to suggest a distinction, based upon any intelligible principle, between the two casea in which release has taken place and the cases in which we nois* advise that, i** and when they arise, no release shall be directed.    But ^e are satisfied that the authority of martial law in Ireland cannot, with a reservation to be presently stated, be asserted in any other way.The reservation referred to is founded upon the idiosyn-crasies of the Irish Easter of the Rolls.   A Vacation Judge is now sitting in Ireland.   In the ordinary course such appli-cations as these would fall to be made before him.   The Master of the Rolls      who, like any other Judge, is technical-ly qualified to deal with such a matter   has in a very unusual way thrust himself forward in order to enforce a view
disavowed by every colleague he has on the Bench.   Those who know- the learned Judge better than we do way he able to advise the Cabinet whether there is any private method by which it n-ifrht be pointed out to the Master of the Rolls that the natural person to hear such natters in vacation is the Vacation Judge.   We fear4 however, that he may he too elated by the success of his latest effort willingly to give place to colleagues of whom he knows that they will declare the law correctly.Should the Cabinet think proper to accept the view express-ad upon tho general question by the Committee, they will no doubt consider what put)lie statement should be made to correct the impression, now naturally held generally except among, lawyers, that officers acting in martial law areas are amen-able to writs such as were issued in this case.   A detailed recommendation upon this point hardly falls within the terms o^ the r*f*r*ncfc to this Committee,* * * *(Intd)     BtWhitehall Gardens, S.$;l, August 1, 1981.

</content>
</cab>
