<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 969-970</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property oi His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovemmentT^-----glSECRET. &quot;CP. 3188.THE CABINET.SURPLUS STORES.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.The existing procedure in respect of stores declared surplus by the Army is, generally speaking, that the War Department is responsible for all duties connected with the storage, custody and physical handling of such stores, except those in dep6ts containing only surplus stores which are transferred en bloc to the Disposal and Liquidation Commission (see Cabinet Decision 4 (20)5 dated 14th January, 1920). There continue to exist in army dep6ts large quantities of stores declared to the Disposal and Liquidation Commission as surplus, but not yet cleared, for which the War Department are under the existing arrangement compelled to bear all charges in respect of storage, movement and handling.The Disposal and Liquidation Commission finds itself compelled to effect sales under conditions known as &quot; free on rail,&quot; &quot; free on board &quot; and &quot; free alongside ship.&quot; These conditions, over which the Army has no control, have to be fulfilled ,by the personnel at army depots, in addition to their normal duties, and entail much clerical work, much packing and hand labour, the cost of which falls on Army Votes. Again, purchasers of these surplus stores frequently subsell to others, and these latter in turn subsell, with the result that the Army has continually to place &quot; free on rail&quot; small packets of these stores for despatch to large and small dealers. Further, the purchasers of these surplus stores are unable in many cases to sell them again rapidly, with the result that military depots become, to all intents and purposes, civilian warehouses. The Army, even now, are holding in their depots stores declared surplus in March, 1919.Although everything is done by the Disposal and Liquidation Commission to enforce rapid clearance, yet in the majority of cases existing conditions of trade prevent the enforcement of the penalty clause which exists in every agreement.It is fully realized that the Disposal and Liquidation Commission is doing everything in its power to effect clearances, and has throughout co-operated with and assisted the Army in every possible way, and that the Commission itself is faced with circumstances over which it has no control, such as the present state of the purchasing market and the fact that it is difficult to forecast with accuracy the &quot; throws up &quot; of stores either in respect of quantity or time, since this depends on settlements of policy, Army establishments, &amp;c. It is also realized that to separate these stores physically on each occasion would necessitate the retention of clerks and labour out of all proportion to the monetary value of the stores, and might involve double moves, which would entail increased costs to the State.At the same time, the charges entailed in connection with the handling and custody of these stores, in which the Army has now no interest, should no longer be shown in the Estimates as part of the cost of the Army.Attention must be drawn to the fact that the reduced establishments of necessity now maintained at army depots are physically unable to cope with the additional work thrown on them, without their military duties suffering. Moreover, the drastic cuts in Army expenditure, which are now regarded as imperative, necessitate the removal from Army Votes of all expenditure incurred on behalf of other Government Departments, expenditure which, it should be added, the Secretary of State for War is not in a position to defend in reply to criticism, inasmuch as the Army Council have no control over it.Excluding stations overseas, it is estimated that the monthly cost to Army Votes of duties connected with surplus stores may at the present time be taken at 16,000/.It is therefore submitted in the first place that Cabinet Decision 4 (20)5of 14th January, 1.920, referred to in paragraph 1 above, should be rescinded forthwith, the War Office at the same time undertaking to give all possible assistance to the Disposal and Liquidation Commission for the remainder of the present financial year.
In future financial years, all charges of every description connected with stores declared surplus should be debited against the Disposal and Liquidation Commission after a period of 14 days from the date of despatch of the official &quot; throw-up &quot; notification by the War Office.The amount of such charges, ascertained by some not too elaborate method to be agreed between the War Office and the Commission, should be refunded by the latter to the former. This would be in harmony with the normal commercial practice of treating expenses of realization as a deduction from the amounts realized.In the second place, since by the end of October declarations of war surpluses of any appreciable size will have been completed, it is submitted that the time has arrived when a reversion to peace time procedure in regard to the disposal of surplus stores is advisable and desirable.It is, therefore, suggested that after the close of the present financial year all stores which have not then been actually declared surplus should be dealt with by the Army in accordance with normal peace time procedure, any minor modifications or adjustments rendered necessary by this ruling to be dealt with as a matter of routine between the Departments of State concerned.L. W.-E.The Wae Office,2nd August, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
