<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 972-978</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document ia the property of His Britannic MajestyJsGovernment). ^CAB I jj E T . Copy No .COMMITTEE OF TOE AFFAIRS. ISLE OF MAN (CUSTOMS) BILL,I circulate herewith as a measure of extreme urgency, the draft of the Isle of ran (Customs) Bill for the information of the Home Affairs Committee.     It is necessary to pass the Bill this Session, and it should be introduced as early as possible.(Initialled)   E,H,Y.SB 0 RET . CP.3190TREASURY,. S,,W3rd August, 192
DRAPTOF ABILLtoAmend the law with respect to Customs in the a.d. 1921.Isle of Man. &quot;7&quot;BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords . Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows :-1. (1) The additional duties of Customs on tobacco Duties on removed or imported into the Isle of Man, imposed by the tobacco. Isle of Man (Customs) Act, 1918, shall continue to be 8&amp;9Geo.5. charged, levied and paid as from the first day of August, c- 41-10 nineteen hundred and twenty-one, until the first day of August, nineteen hundred and twenty-two.(2) As from the thirty-first day of May, nineteen hundred&apos; and twenty-one, the additional duty of Customs on cigars removed or imported into the Isle of Man, 15 imposed by subsection (2) of section two of the Isle of 10 &amp; n Geo. Man (Customs) Act, 1920, shall cease to be chargeable.    5-c- 60-2. The additional duties of Customs on ale or beer Duties on removed or imported into the Isle of Man, imposed by the ale or beer. Isle of Man (Customs) Act, 1919, shall continue to be 9 &amp;lOGeo.5. 20 charged, levied and paid as from the first day of August, c- ^-nineteen hundred and twenty-one, until the first day of August, nineteen hundred and twenty-two.3. In addition to the duties of Customs payable on Duties ou spirits removed or imported into the Isle of Man there sPmts-148-3 A
2 Isle of Mem (Customs).   [11 &amp;. 12 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1921. shall, as from the thirty-first day of May, nineteen hundred and twenty one, until the first day of August, nineteen hundred and twenty-two, be.charged, levied, and paid on spirits shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners of Customs and Excise to have been 5 consigned from and grown, produced, or manufactured in the British Empire, as defined in section eight of the 9&amp;lOGeo.5. Einance Act, 1919, and on other spirits respectively, such c,32?        additional duties of Customs as shall he sufficient tomake, when added to the existing duties, duties at the 10 rates set out in the Schedule to this Act.Duties on 4.-(l) On and from the thirty-first day of May,cocoa.        nineteen hundred and twenty-one, until the first day of August, nineteen hundred and twenty-two, there shall be charged, levied and paid on cocoa removed or imported 15 into the Isle of Man, shown to the satisfaction of the 9&amp;lOGeo.5. Commissioners of Customs and Excise to have been con-c 32. signed from and grown, produced or manufactured in theBritish Empire, as defined by section eight of the Einance Act, 1919, and on other cocoa so removed or imported 20 respectively the following duties of Customs Eate of Dutyconsigned consignedfrom and grown from and in the British       grown^       25Empire.      &apos; elsewhere.  s.  d.        s.   d. Cocoa    -     -      -  the cwt.   1 15  0     2  2  0 Husks and shells     - &apos; 5   0 6   0Cocoa butter -  the lb. 31 4i  30(2) The duties of Customs imposed by this section are duties of Customs within the meaning of section seven l Edw. 7.    of the Einance Act, 1901, and the Customs (Tariff) Act, 1876, shall apply to the Isle of Man so far as necessary to give effect to that section. 35c 739 &amp;&apos;40Vict. c. 35.^import 5.-(l) On and from the thirty-first day of May, nineteen hundred and twenty-one, until the first day of August, nineteen hundred and twenty-two, there shall be charged, levied and paid on any of the following articles removed or imported into the Isle of Man which have 40
been manufactured outside Great Britain or Ireland the i following duties of Customs Clocks, watches and the com-lponent parts of clocks and 5 watches.Musical instruments, includinggramophones,   pianolas  andother similar instruments (ex-An amount equal to thirty-three and    one-thirdcept   pianos,   harmoniums, y ,   ea     . &apos; j    . &apos;     per cent, oi thevalue of the article.10 American organs and  pipeorgans).Accessories and component parts of musical instruments and records and other means of 15 reproducing music.(2) The value of any article for the purposes of this section shall he taken to be the price which an importer would give for the article if the article were delivered freight and insurance paid in bond at the port of impor-20 tation in Great Britain or Ireland, or in the case of importation into the Isle of Man direct from outside Great Britain or Ireland, at the port of importation into the Isle of Man. Duty shall be paid at that value as fixed by the Commissioners of Customs and Excise.25 (3) Any dispute arising as to the proper rate of duty payable under this section shall, so far as the question of value is concerned, be referred to a referee appointed by the Lieutenant-Governor of the Isle of Man, and the decision of the referee shall he final and conclusive.30 If the decision of the referee involves any variation in the amount of duty payable, duty shall he paid or repaid, as the case may he, so as to correspond with that decision.(4) Where it is proved to the satisfaction of the 35 Commissioners of Customs and Excise that any article is of a kind mainly used as an accessory or component part which is liable to duty under this section but is imported for use for some other purpose, or has been or is being exclusively used for some other purpose, the Commis-40 sioners shall, subject to such conditions (if any) as they think fit, allow the article to be imported free of duty or repay any duty paid on importation as the case requires.148 A 2
Isle of Man (Customs).  [11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.]a.d. 1921. (5) The Lieutenant-Governor of the Isle of Man may by order exempt any articles mentioned in the order which are liable to duty under this section from that duty if he is satisfied that, having regard to the small value of the article, it is inexpedient that the duty 5 should be charged.Short title.        6. This Act may be cited as the Isle of Man (Customs) Act, 1921.
SCHEDULE.A.D. 1921.Duties on Spirits.	Rate of Duty	Nature of Spirits.	consigned from or produced in the British Empire, i	consigned from or produced elsewhere.10 Brandy, Geneva and other foreign spiritsthe gallonRuin,   including   shrub   of   the   British Possessions -      -      -      -   the gallon British and  Irish   spirits,  not otherwise 15     exempted from the payment of dutythe gallonLiqueurs, cordials and mixed or sweetened spirits -      - -      -   the gallonAll ,such spirits to be computed at hydro-20 nfeter proof, provided that where a person importing liqueurs, cordials or mixed or sweetened spirits in bottle has entered same in such manner as to indicate that the strength is not to be tested, duty shall 25     be levied and paid at the rate of the gallonPerfumed spiritsthe gallon    s.	d.	 	S.	d3  7	6	CO	10	03  7	6	CO	10	03   7  63   7   6,3 19 5 4   6  63 10 0 3 10   04 2 9 4 10   6
Isle of Man (Customs).DRAFTOP AB   I   L   IiTo amend the law with respect to Customs in the Isle of Man.CXXI.   (3.)3rd August 1921.148-3

</content>
</cab>
