<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/126/0 images: 980-985</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HS TDCUMEOT 13 THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC majesty&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET CP. 5192.The Cabinet may be interested to see a copy of the following confidential letter recently written by Lenin to a friend in Switzerland.    There sedma no reason to doubt its authenticity.  As a revelation it is of great interest and importance.August 2nd, 1921. C. bf K.MOSCOW,10th June, 1921.&quot;You ask me, dear friend, why the tone of my letters - or rather ny chats with you - have ceased to be as optimistic asthey used to be.  Indeed, I think that if we met, you would beastonished still more at the change which, has taken place in me,and which is involuntarily reflected in     letters, imagine aman who, in the course of three years, from day to day, fromhour to hour, goes on doing one and the same sort of work wlth-out having a single moment to himbelf ,aM no possibility of breaking away from the great burdien of toil which swallows upall his time, energy and strength.&quot;More and more, I recall the happy days in Zurich,when weused to converse for hours on the approaching upheaval and ofthe inevitable realisation of our theories a$d of the inevitablephases which would mark the sociological changes in the classrelationships and social forms of contemporary Europe.You exas-perated me more than once by the cold criticism of your practicalmind - a criticism which seemed to me quite divorced from the realities to which I, and those who thought with me,had devote^ all their abilities,and which,it seemed to me,we had suc-ceeded in learning how to study.&quot;You
&quot;You practical men only think ol what grips you in the present and on that you spend your labour. You see in life the one path which, according to you,a realist who wants to create in life ought to tread.&quot;You understand every task only from a narrow egotistical point of view, in so far as brings you directly this or that advantage, this or that profit.    Without ever dipping deep down into the reality of your surroundings, without interesting yourself in that which is not directly of use to you, with your egotistical morality you thick it right to live for yourself, to conquer for yourself and to throw to the weaker only the crumbs you do not need, without thirking whether they are sufficient or not.    If you remember -to judge by your letters, you have not forgotten - our talks in Zurich. Library, and later in Geneva when, foaming at the mouth, you proved to me how Utopian were ray thoughts, how incompatible they were with the contemporary outlook of European society, in Which the highest form of Capitalism and egotistic philosophy had finally crystalised,  then I will tell you of one little fact which then escaped my observation,   but which deeply interests me now as affording an indirect proof of the accuracy of my deductions in my arguments with you and so emphasises, once again, the superiority of our theories over your practical observations.&quot;Three years unceasing study of the phases of the revolution in Russia have taught me to seek and find in everything, not the genius of clans constructive Bess, not collective instinct, driving the members of a class to work in the right direction, but - above all other forces - the strength of individual personality, whosefreewill
m 3 mfreewill is exalted above class, grips this class and dictates to it what are the most useful and essential methods to adopt at the present moment of the class struggle.  We have all made a mistake in attributing such vast importance to the class, looking upon it as if it were an intellectual organism, capable of giving a direct and spontaneous manifestation of its will. Class is nothing more than an organism absolutely de-prived of intellect, freewill and self-possession, and is animated only by the class instinct of self-preservation, which never dictates any more useful line of action than what the immediate present demands. 1 The act of a class, as such, is always deprived of reason for it never takes thought of what the further course of the struggle is likely to be.  The life of a class -it is like a vast mollusc, which resists and struggles with the same energy, whether it be against an enemy upon which its existence depends or against the most paltry foe.   The strength of the free intellect alone can further the course of the struggle and sum up the whole situation pro and con.ttBoth I and my colleagues and you practical men alike have overlooked this greatest factor in social life, and if we paid any attention to it it was only in so far to refer to it as a form of our conclusions on the nature of class.&quot;Those endless perspective^ for observation which the Russian revolution opens have made it possible for me more than once to convince myself of the falsity of our promises, and approaching the question from yourpoint
point of view, I canndt but,,admit that you were more right than I.&quot;Now, of myself/ I am tired.  I feel this more aftd more every day, and involuntarily long t6 relax over my books and verify by objective observation the conclusions to which I have given my whole life.  W nerves are not what they were. More and more I begin to fret at the triviality of those around me, their suburban attitude of mind, which destroys the organism of the party. To run the State as it is being run now with us is down-right impossible.  Our young bureaucracy has embraced all the shortcomings of their fore-runners and in their naivete have deepened still further the rift which existed before between the rulers and the ruled.&quot;We have lost out in our wager on the collective instinct which was to have supported the members of the party.  Our hopes on the same collective instinct and class consciousness on the part of the workers and peasants have also been a fiasco.&quot;I remenfcer now your parting words when I left for Russia in 1917.   You told me that I ought never to forget that I had completely forgotten how to understand the psychology of the Russian workmen and peasants after years of exilehad torn me away from the possibility of observation of Russian society on the spot, and that I ougit to be careful.  Power - success - lashed U3 all on.  I myself was carried away by the possibility of verifying my theories in practice, deeply believing in the staunchness and vitality of my party. Throwing to the crowd the broad perspectives of the coming socialreforms,
m    5   mreforms,   I tried &quot;bo awaken in the intelligent proletariat of the workers and peasants the self action which would cause the orders of the Centre to be carried out, thus forming the foundations of a Socialist State in the future, to serve as a model to the peoples of the world.   I tell you I have hesitated for three years in coming to realise that we were wrong, that I had chosen wrong measures, hut now, in weighing up the sum of our activity, I must admit that I was wrong, that I over-estimated the forces and strength of the party, and I over-estimated the Eussian workmen and peasants.&quot;I tell you , in short, that both the Russian work-man and Russian peasant have betrayed their interests, have betrayed the party absolutely and unconsciously in virtue of their flabbiness and heavy psycho logy, which overcame the revolutionary spirit and sapped the develop-raent of the revolutionary psychology half-way.  The naivete, the childish culture, the childish cruelty, the complete lack of understanding, the inability to understand the necessity of working, slowness in re-acting to new ideas - that is the log which we have shown ourselves unable to move, notwithstanding all these really heroic efforts which the party has made during these years.   If we hold together, we do so only by the efforts of the party which is waging all its lilting force only in order to retain power and so -if only a little - prolonging the possibility of building up a new social outlook, and thus preparing the way for the further development and extension of the social revolution.   But I feel that the strength of the party isdaily
daily becoming more and more exhausted, and that the beeds of internal dissfesion and petty ambition of liodivi4ualfei who place private interests above conmon interests ire beginning to eat the party away. Thisj    &apos;,! &quot;struggle meets us in all manner of Ways.  Long ago I sal the inevitability of compromise, the inevitability of concessiohs from our fcide, which tpuld pour new strength infcb the party, to strengthen - if ohly a litile - the worn-out band of really devoted tfarty workers. Without this, thare was no possibility of us i inot j)nly retaining power, but even of continuing to exist.  Revolutionary militarism, which our &quot;Napoleons&quot; are but for, will, in my opinion, be broken, and will be the last effort of our party, which will perish in ex-hausting the whole of its human reserve.   I wrote to ICrassin about the necessity of entering privately into pourparlers with the Socialist groups abroad as to the possibility of some sort of compromise.  I turn to you with the same request as an old friend, and besides, an absolutely non-party man. It will be easier for you to get into contact with the exiles, and easier for you to come to some sort of understanding with their leaders.&quot;I do not conceal that I would like to have some news of you as soon as possible, as time will not wait, and it is better to come to an understanding now than in six months when it may be too late.&quot;I shall look for letters from you in the immediate future.   I find it a rest reading them, remembering you and our Zurich talks.&quot;I greet you with all my heart.&quot;Yours,&quot;V. ULYANDV&quot;.

</content>
</cab>
