<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/51/0 images: 110-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential.(52) 113 CABINET OFFICE copy no.RECORD COPY5TH april, 1952cabinetFARM prices memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and fisheries the Cabinet are aware of the negotiations we have been conducting withthe National Farmers1 Unions (N. F. Us.) on farm prices.   i have been acting inthe closest association with the other Agricultural Ministers, keeping the lord president, the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister of Food fully informed.2. Our objective has been to provide a firm basis for a great effort on thepart of farmers to increase the home production of food, particularly meat.Some addition to farmers1 resources will be needed, but within the scope of thecurrent Investment Programme we think that by way of increased efficiency,especially in the management of grassland, farmers should be able to expandnet production over the next four years by about 15 per cent.   This will requirein the later years of the period more fertilisers, particularly nitrogen, andsome more machinery than current investment allows for 1952.   But broadly onthe current allocation of national resources this objective appears to us and to the farmers&apos; leaders a reasonable one.   It includes a reasonable hope that home production of meat could be built up by 1956  to an annual rate some 250,000 tons(mainly pigmeat) above the present with further substantial increases to follow(mainly beef and mutton).   Alternatively the programme would soften the impact on home food production of a failure to maintain imports of feedingstuffs.3. Achievement of these objectives will depend mainly on increasing efficiency and we have been studying what can be done immediately to strengthen the effectiveness in practice of the powers we possess by statute.   We should require as an essential feature of a satisfactory settlement on prices a publicassociation of the N. F. Us. with a continued and intensified campaign by county committees and Agricultural departments  officials to eliminate really badfarmers and stimulate the middle range to greater productivity.4. On the financial aspect we have established in the course of negotiations that recoupment to the farmers partly by way of increased prices and partly byway of subsidies to a total amount of something over  40 millions should maintaintotal net incomes at about  296 millions (the 1951/52 figure) on the assumptionthat the volume of production, degree of efficiency and the general level of costs remain as at present.   The N. F. Us. have not disputed this but have urgedthat with costs rising as they have done the farmer, particularly the small farmer, has found it increasingly difficult to finance his operations and thatthis is a major cause of the trend to less intensive production which we are agreed is setting in.   The question is how much we ought to add to the  45 millions which was the original maximum agreed between Ministers.5. A strong part of the farmers1 case has been that the rise in costs overthe past year has caused a slackening in productive effort because of the increasein working capital required.   This will also particularly affect the small man inrespect of feeding stuffs.   We propose, therefore, that a large part of the
appropriate recoupment should be by way of subsidies in place of adjustments to prices.   This could be done by -(i)  authorising the Minister of Food to carry up to 31st March, 1953, thecost of maintaining basic prices of feedingstuffs under his direct control at their present level plus  3 a ton;(ii)   continuing at appropriate rates the fertiliser and ploughing subsidiesrecently introduced;(iii)   introducing a calf subsidy and a special subsidy scheme to help thesmall farmer particularly affected by the feeding stuff price increase.Legislation will be required;  and(iv)   continuing contributions to the cost of liming agricultural land and of farm drainage and water supply schemes and the marginal productionscheme.   We are preparing the necessary statutory instruments.6, In accordance with the Cabinet Conclusions of 3rd April (C.C. (52) 36thConclusions, Vlihute 5) I saw the President of the English National Farmers&apos;Union that afternoon and told him that the Government would be prepared to make an addition to annual farm incomes of  52^ millions gross on the clear under-standing that the leaders of the three Farmers&apos; Unions would pledge their full support and co-operation in a production and efficiency df ive designed to attainthe objectives we have in mind.   I made it clear also that within a total of 52^ millions gross there would have to be definite limitations on the amountof recoupment provided for milk and eggs.   I left it that no definite decisionhad been taken about feeding stuff   prices.7. The President is under instructions from the N. F. U. Council to referback to the Council before agreeing to a final settlement.   He has summoned a council for Tuesday, 8th April.   Meanwhile he has, in consultation withrepresentatives of the other Unions, put to me proposals which in effect wouldinvolve an addition of some  4 millions to the figure decided upon by the Cabinet.He further stipulates that the break-down of the agreed global figure should be onthe basis of a negotiated schedule.   I am afraid that even if we were to concede the global total there would still be great difficulty - to put it no higher - in reaching agreement on the prices for milk and eggs.8. The President has also asked:(a) that the announcement of the settlement should contain an undertaking that consultations between the Government and the industry will be initiated forthwith to prepare a long-term policy as expeditiouslyas possible:  there is no difficulty about this; and(b) that decisions in a sense desired by the N. F. Us. should be reached on anumber of supplementary points.9. The main issue is, however, summed up in the two requests reported inparagraph 7 and in view of the fact that the farmers1 attitude will be determined atthe N. F. U. Council meeting on Tuesday next I feel that my colleagues will wishto be informed immediately of the position.T. L.D.Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, S.W.1.,5TH APRIL, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
