<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/51/0 images: 136-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is the property of her britannic ma jest y&apos;s government)secret r......cabinet OFFICfc copy no.     h Uc-(52) m                  RECORD COPY It        : \9th april, 1952.cabinetLICENSING OF ROAD PASSENGER VEHICLESMemorandum by the Lord President of the Council.As promised in my memorandum of 8th April (C. (52) 110), the Committeeon Road and Rail Transport have now considered, as requested by the Cabinet(C.C.(52) 36th Conclusions, Minute l(3)&apos;and 38th Conclusions, Minute 1) thequestion of road  passenger transport, including the possibility of standstillarrangements.2.       The Road Traffic Act, 19-30 is the main pillar on which the structure of passenger transport rests.   Though this Act was passed by a Labour Government,it had been planned and drafted, almost exactly as it was enacted, under thepreceding Conservative administration.   If it were knocked away the unregulatedcompetition which would certainly follow would create worse conditions thanthose for which the Act was by common consent a necessary remedy.3.        Although this Act was designed in part to regulate road competition withrail an equally important objective was the regulation of competition between road operators themselves.   Many of these operators are private firms whobuilt up their businesses between the two wars, mostly from very smallbeginnings.   The Act is as much and as necessary a protection to them as itis to the railways.4.       The free-for-all which would follow any suspension of the licensing system could not be defended.   Newcomers would try to establish themselves on the best paying routes, existing operators in defence would try to crowdthem off, and the bus-travelling public would find themselves withoutservices on the less remunerative routes.   The backbone of the herring wouldbe overcrowded, and the small bones empty.5.        Possibilities for consideration are:-(i)    a standstill of some kind;(ii)  a modification of the principles which at present govern the issueof new licences.6.        A standstill would have to take the form of -(a) freezing the position at a particular date;  or(b) cillowing no appeals against the grant of licences;  or(c) allowing the Minister to suspend his decision on appeals at his discretion.
137Of these, (a) would prevent the adjustment of services to current publicneeds and must be ruled out on that account.   Course (b) would remove thepower of the Minister to revoke a licence which has been granted although he could grant a licence which has been refused.   The grant of licences wouldbe entirely at the discretion cf the licensing authorities and the uniformity of administration which the appeal machinery secures would be lost.   Existingoperators would lose the legitimate protection which they have under the1930 Act against the incursion of new operators.7.        As for the possibility referred to at 5(ii) above - modifying theprinciples which at present govern the issue of new licences - the difficulty is to determine an appropriate dividing line.   The existing balance between road and rail has been struck in the course of twenty years1 experiencewithout serious public complaint until the last week or so.   If we are toattempt a new balance, full and impartial investigation will be n&apos;eeded.   this could not be completed during the current Session.   The Government couldannounce its intention of undertaking such an investigation at once, the reportto be submitted within twelve months.   We are unanimously agreed thatthis is the right solution.8.        It would be possible, but we think inadvisable, to couple this with legislation, on the lines indicated at 6(c) above, to permit the Ministerto suspend decisions on appeals at his discretion pending the submission and consideration of the report by the investigating body.   Such a Bill would be short and should not form part of the main Transport (Amendment) Bill.   Itwould be highly contentious and would be open to the criticism that it neithermaintained the existing balance between road and rail which has been evolvedin the light of experience under successive Governments, nor effected a newbalance resulting from a review of the facts.   It would be most unpalatable tomany of our own supporters.    Moreover, suspensions of decisions on appealswould leave both holders of licences and objectors in a state of suspense andwould lead to many applications for new licences by those who would hope&apos;that the findings of the investigating body might favour them.9.       If this expedient were adopted, we should be faced not only withcomplaints from the travelling public who might be deprived of services onwhich they had relied, but also with opposition from private road operators,who are among our strongest supporters, and who established a highlyefficient organisation which was of great assistance to us at the last election.For these reasons, and those given in paragraph 8 above, we do not recommendenabling the Minister to suspend decisions on appeals.10.      In short, our unanimous recommendation is that there should be an impartial enquiry into the working of the Act of 1930 and that there should beno form of standstill.W.Privy Council Office, S.W.1.9th APRIL,, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
