<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/51/0 images: 215-217</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2 ifinCABINET OFFlCtconfidential 0 n       n ^ .,,- RECORD COPY copy no.C.(52) 1422nd may, 1952.cabinetMALAYA-&quot;DAILY WORKER&quot; PHOTOGRAPHSOF A ROYAL MARINE HOLDINGTHE SEVERED HEAD OF A BANDITMemorandum by the First Lord of the admiralty the incident that gave rise to these photographs occurred in April, 1951,when a jungle J^atrol was ambushed at short range while returning from a four-day operation.   In the first burst of fire the Lieutenant in charge was fatallywounded and the Corporal second in command killed outright.   The Patrolreturned the fire and beat off the attack.   In the engagement two members ofthe Patrol were wounded and one bandit was killed.   After the bandits had with-drawn an Ibam tracker, who had run away during the engagement, returnedand decapitated the dead bandit.   The Patrol had no camera.   Great importance is attached to identification of bandits.   Normally this would have been doneby photographing the bandit on the spot before burial or by bringing in the body.The members of the Patrol had difficulty in bringing back their own wounded and brought back the head of the corpse as the only method of identificationopen to them in accordance with Police requirements in the area,2. When those members of the Patrol concerned in the incidentreturned to their camp some of them posed for the photographs that have been published.   This was a reprehensible act but the Patrol had lost an officer for whom the whole Troop had the greatest regard and respect and a Corporal who was probably the most popular man in the Unit.   It was without a leader.   the photographs were taken before an Officer arrived and sent the head off in a sackto Police Headquarters.   An immediate follow-up Patrol was taken out whichkilled another bandit.   This body and the remains of the first bandit were decentlyburied.   This account is based on questions put to the Brigadier of the CommandoBrigade, the Colonel of No. 40 Commando, the photographer and the Marine inthe photograph (both of whom have been identified).3. CONCLUSION   Considerable interest has been aroused.   There areto be two Parliamentary Questions on Wednesday, one from Harold Davies(Socialist) asking about the restraints placed on head hunters employed in malaya and one from Crosthwaite-Eyre (Conservative) asking for a statement onthe recent engagement in which the Royal Marines have been concerned in malaya:  this is a friendly Question from an ex-Royal Marine officer in orderthat he may ask a Supplementary Question about this episode.4. I suggest that a statement should be made to the Press datingthe photographs (1951), explaining the circumstances and condemning suchphotography as a reprehensible act.5. The Commandos are leaving Malaya and while there they have beenunder Army operational control.   It is not, therefore, for me to decide whether decapitation of corpses for identification purposes is necessary.   My
opinion is that it should not be allowed even though identification may be lostas a result.   Nor, in my opinion, should photographing of corpses of banditsbe allowed except officially for identification purposes.6. Criticism in the Press or in the House may be reduced if weare prepared to deal with these points.7. RE C OMME NDAT IONS(1)   That a statement should be issued by the Admiralty(see Annex).(2)   That decapitation of corpses in Malaya should beexplicitly forbidden.(3)   That photographing of corpses of bandits should beallowed only for official purposes.J.P.L.T.Admiralty, S.W.I.2nd MAY, 1952.
The attention of the Board of Admiralty has been drawn tophotographs that have been published in which members of the armed forces and of the Malayan Police are shown holding the severed headof a bandit.2. When the first photograph was printed it appeared at first sight that it was a composite picture but immediate enquiries wereinstituted to establish whether the photograph was genuine and if so the circumstances in which decapitation occurred and the photographwas taken .   Normally dead bandits are identified by photographing on the spot before burial or by bringing in the body.3. A Royal Marine who featured in one of the photographs inquestion has been identified and interviewed.   The person who took the photographs has also been identified and interviewed.   Both confirm thatthe photograph   is genuine.4. The Admiralty understands that the incident which gave riseto these photographs occurred in April, 1951, when the officer and corporalof a jungle Patrol were killed by bandits and two other members of the Patrolwere badly wounded.   The remaining members of the Patrol had the greatest difficulty in bringing back their wounded and were thus unable to bring back the body of the dead bandit for identification as was customary.   Asit was essential to identify the bandit who had been shot dead they producedthe head from the corpse as the only method of identification open to them,in accordance with the Police requirements in the area.5; When those members of the Patrol concerned in the incidentreturned to their camp some of them did indulge in the reprehensibleact of posing with the head when it was being photographed.DRAFT STATEMENT BY THE ADMIRALTY

</content>
</cab>
