<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/51/0 images: 240-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1952CABINET OFFICE C(W No^^RECORD COPYCABINETECONOMIC AID TO YUGOSLAVIA IN 1952-53Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs at their meeting on 1st April the Cabinet considered a memorandum whichI circulated outlining the instructions which I proposed to give to the representativeof Her Majesty&apos;s Government at the discussions in Washington with representativesof the United States and French Governments regarding the scale of economic assistance to be given to Yugoslavia in 1952-53 (C.C. (52) 35th Conclusions,Minute 6).2.   The Cabinet (i) Authorised the United Kingdom Delegation to offer a United kingdom contribution to tripartite aid of  4 million or, if necessary, tA\ million.(ii) Agreed that, if assistance were given in 1952-53, the Yugoslavs shouldbe pressed to facilitate the delivery of goods, e.g., maize, which we wishto obtain from them.Negotiations in Washington3. Agreement has now been reached in Washington, subject to Ministerialapproval, that aid to Yugoslavia should continue on a. tripartite basis. The UnitedKingdom is to contribute, in new money,  4J million, which is the amountauthorised by the Cabinet. In addition, out of the 1951-52 grant, an amount of 2 million, which has not yet been made available to the Yugoslav government but to which Her Majesty&apos;s Government are committed under the Anglo-French-American agreement of June 1951, is to be deferred until 1952-53, making a total united Kingdom contribution in 1952-53 of  6^ million. Copies of the Reportof the Washington Conference and of a draft Aide-Memoire for presentation tothe Yugoslav Government, setting out the conditions on which future aid will begranted, are attached.The Report of the Conference4. Paragraph 1 of the Report states &quot; This Report has been prepared on theassumption that it is of great political and military importance to the UnitedKingdom, France, the United States, and the Western world generally to maintainthe advantages which the existence of an independent Yugoslavia outside the Sovietorbit confers upon the West, to avoid the consequence which a collapse of Yugo-slav resistance to the U.S.S.R. would entail, and to move Yugoslavia further inthe direction of the West.&quot; An examination of Yugoslavia^ balance of payments position showed that for the year 1952-53 i Yugoslavia will require externalassistance of about  35 million.5.   The Report recommends (i) that the three participating Governments should make available in theform of grants the following amounts:  United States Government: $78 million ( 28 million).United Kingdom Government:    4^ million.French Government: Frs. 2,940 million ( 3 million).(ii) That these grants should be used to finance Yugoslav imports and for technical assistance.42246SECRETC. (52) 1458th May, 1952
(iii) That each of the participating Governments should be free to determine,in consultation with the other two Governments, the purposes for which its own grant is to be applied.6. The Report also examines the problem of Yugoslav investment, concludesthat the annual rate of investment expenditure should be reduced and sets upcertain criteria to be applied to future investment.  It recommends:  (i) That the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development shouldbe considered the source of loans for Yugoslavia.(ii) That each of the participating Governments should make available to theInternational Bank an amount for this purpose, provisionally fixed at:  United States dollars: 5*-6 million.Sterling equivalent to : $5-6 million (up to a maximum of  2-06 million).French francs equivalent to: $10-12 million.(iii) That the Yugoslav Government should be requested to seek the advice of the three participating Governments before contracting any creditsoutside the International Bank and that failure to follow such adviceshould entitle any of the three Governments to cease its grants.7. As regards Yugoslavia^ external debts, the Report concludes that thepresent debt burden of Yugoslavia exceeds the capacity of the Yugoslav economy and that unless moratoria on debt payments are obtained much of the presentgrants will be used merely to cover Yugoslav debt payments.8.   The Report recommends that the three participating countries (i) Should either postpone or regard as being covered by their grants Yugoslavdebts to themselves for the period 1st July, 1952, to 31st December, 1953.(ii) Consider sponsoring a conference of Yugoslav creditors to study thepossibilities of lessening Yugoslavia^ debt burden.(iii) In the meantime should work to secure moratoria on Yugoslav debtpayments.9. Furthermore, the Report makes clear that the three participating Govern -ments expect Yugoslavia (i) To try to satisfy the reasonable demands of the three Governments for materials and products of value to them.(ii) To take advantage of facilities for technical assistance; and(iii) To supply the fullest information about the Yugoslav economy.Aide-Memoir e10.   The purpose of the Aide-Memoire is to indicate (i) The decisions of the three participating Governments concerning future economic aid to Yugoslavia.(ii) The measures which the three participating Governments consider the yugoslav Government should take to become independent ofextraordinary foreign aid.(iii) That the provision of aid is dependent upon the Yugoslav Government^acceptance of the terms of the Aide-Memoire.(iv) That the amount of assistance for 1952-53 should be made known in thelight of the Yugoslav Governments reply.(v) That assistance, if any, after 1952-53 will be progressively reduced.11.&apos; The Aide-Memoire may well be unpalatable to the Yugoslavs. Severeas it is, however, it does ho more than diagnose some of the major faults of Yugo-slavia&apos;s present economic policy and prescribe remedies which will have to be taken if the Yugoslav Government are to achieve their declared object of becomingindependent of Western aid.Recommendation12. I recommend that we should approve both the report, and the draftAide-Memoire to the Yugoslav Government, and that I should be authorised to seek Parliamentary sanction for the United Kingdom contribution.Foreign Office, S.W.J,8th May, 1952.
REPORTIntroduction1. This Report has been prepared on the assumption that it is of great political and military importance to the United States, the United Kingdom,France and the Western world generally to maintain the advantages which theexistence of an independent Yugoslavia outside the Soviet orbit confers upon theWest, to avoid the consequences which a collapse of Yugoslav resistance to theU.S.S.R. would entail, and to move Yugoslavia further in the direction of the West.2. An estimate of Yugoslavia^ balance of payments in the year 1st July, 1952,to 30th June, 1953, has been prepared and is given in Appendix&apos;C. This estimateshows that, after allowance has been made for all financial facilities at present in prospect, the maintenance of a volume of imports only slightly above that of 1949will necessitate, further assistance of about  35 million and the taking of steps todeal with problems relating to Yugoslavia^ investment and external debts.3. The attainment of the objectives set out in paragraph 1 is therefore stillthreatened by the economic situation of Yugoslavia, and the Governments of theUnited States, United Kingdom and France (in this report called &quot; the participating governments &quot;) should agree that they will continue to give economic assistance to yugoslavia in the period ending 30th June, 1953, and will continue to co-operate and consult together in the provision of such assistance.Responsibility of the Yugoslav government. The Yugoslav Government should make every effort to achieve theeconomic viability of Yugoslavia, and consequently its independence of foreigneconomic assistance, at the earliest possible date. As, however, part of Yugoslavia^resources are devoted to its defence plans, the economic cost and duration of whichare not fully known, the participating Governments, are not in a position to deter-mine at the present time a target date for the achievement of viability. progress towards viability will, nevertheless, depend principally upon the policies and actions of the Yugoslav Government, which should be informed on this subject in the terms set out in the draft aide-memoire attached as Appendix A.Proposals Concerning the Provision of Grants5. The participating Governments should accept responsibility towards one another for providing the Yugoslav Government with the following grants in theyear 1st Jifly, 1952, to 30th June, 1953:  The United States Government $78 million.*The United Kingdom Government  4J- million sterling.The French Government 2,940 million francs.6. Each of the participating Governments should apply its grant to financingYugoslav imports and technical assistance, for the purpose of contributing to the attainment of the common objectives set out in paragraph 1.7. Each of the participating Governments should, however, after consultationwith the other two Governments, be free to determine to which purposes its owngrant is to be applied, and the times at which, and the manner in which, it will beapplied. Each Government should also be free to determine, in agreement withthe Yugoslav Government, the projects to which the counterpart funds resultingfrom its own grant may be applied, but should consult with the other two Govern-ments concerning the general purposes for which such funds are to be applied.* The United States Delegation reserves to its Government the right to provide part of thestated amount by way of loans instead of grants, should that Government so decide in the lightof United States law. If this right is to be exercised, the United States Government should so inform the other two Governments in good time, and should indicate the proportion of thesaid amount which is to be provided by way of loans, whereupon the other two governments should be entitled to provide loans instead of grants in the same proportion.42246-1
Proposals Concerning Yugoslav Investment8. An examination of investment in Yugoslavia has shown that the annual rate of investment expenditure constitutes too heavy a drain on the resources available, and should be reduced. It has also shown the need for the yugoslav government to arrange its investment projects in order of priority, and to directits efforts towards the completion of those of first priority. The data provided bythe Yugoslav Government do not include sufficiently firm figures (quite apart fromthe technical examination which will be necessary) to enable decisions to be reachednow by the participating Governments about which groups of industries or whichprojects are most likely to yield the maximum benefit to the Yugoslav economy.An examination of the Yugoslav &quot; key project &quot; programme and supporting datahas, however, shown that in deciding which groups of industries or projects are tobe financed the following factors should be borne in mind:  (a) The direct improvement in the balance of payments;(b) The direct or indirect effect on Yugoslavia^ resources as a whole;(c) The necessity of substantially reducing the burden which the Yugoslav&quot; key project &quot; programme would place on Yugoslavia^ resources, bothof materials and of technical skill;(d) The extent to which for any group of industries or any project there is theessential related investment, e.g., iron ore, coke and power for the ironand steel industry;(e) The extent to which a project has already been financed;(f) The ability of the industry or project to compete effectively in world trade;(g) The length of time required for completion.9. Assistance should be given to Yugoslavia to carry out investment selectedin accordance with the criteria set out in paragraph 8. Such investment would increase its productivity and help to reduce its balance of payment deficit. TheInternational Bank for Reconstruction and Development (I.B.R.D.) should be con-sidered the source of loans for investment for Yugoslavia. In view of these considerations the participating Governments should support the granting, as soonas possible, of a second I.B.R.D. loan to Yugoslavia of an amount approximately equal to the amount of the loan of  10 million approved by the I.B.R.D. on11th October, 1951. In view of the special circumstances of grant aid to Yugoslaviaby the participating Governments and the close interdependence of investment and such aid in achieving the general objectives of the participating governments and the I.B.R.D. in Yugoslavia, there should be close consultation, particularly in belgrade, between the I.B.R.D. and the participating Governments on the projects to be financed and the conditions of such a loan.10. Each of the participating Governments should, subject to such consulta-tion, accept responsibility* towards the other two Governments for assuring the availability to the I.B.R.D. of an appropriate amount, t on request by the I.B.R.D.,of that country&apos;s currency for a second I.B.R.D. loan to Yugoslavia.X &quot;11. Such amounts of the currency of each of the three countries as are used by the I.B.R.D. for a second I.B.R.D. loan shall be considered as reducing protanto the amount of that country&apos;s obligation arising from paragraph 13 of theLondon Report? to increase its assistance to Yugoslavia instead of postponing debtpayments due from Yugoslavia in the period 1st January, 1951, to 30th June, 1952.* The United Kingdom and French Delegations reserve to their Governments the right toinform the I.B.R.D. of the conditions on which they will allow their respective currencies to beused for financing specific projects.t According to information made available by members of the staff of the I.B.R.D. duringthe course of the Conference, the present view of the I.B.R.D. staff on the appropriate amountis as follows:  United States dollars: $5 to $6 million.Sterling: equivalent to $5 to S6 million. ,French francs: equivalent to $10 to $12 million.% The United Kingdom and French Delegations indicate that the maximum amounts which their Governments would be prepared to permit to be used by the I.B.R.D. for a second loan to yugoslavia are  2- 06 million and francs 4,200 million respectively.g The Report signed in London on 13th June, 1951, by the heads of delegations representingthe United States, United Kingdom and French Governments at a conference on the Yugoslaveconomic situation.
Proposals concerning Yugoslav External Debts12. The present position of each of Yugoslavia^ external debts is shown indetail in Appendices D and E. These indicate that on 1st January, 1952, Yugo-slavia&apos;s total outstanding debt (as there defined) amounted to  78 million, and anadditional  36 million^ was still undisbursed. At the same date Yugoslavia^ swingceilings on trade agreements amounted to  20 million,, of which  .14 million hadbeen utilised. The estimated service falling due in the next few years (exclusive ofrepayments of &quot; swings &quot;) is as follows :  	Principal	Interest	Total	 	million	1952	......      18	2	201953	17	2	191954	......      17	3	201955	......      14	4	181956	......       8	2	101957	......       6	2	81958	......       9	2	11In the years 1959 to .1971 the anual amounts are substantially less, ranging from 4 million to  1 million. From a comparison of these figures with the estimate inAppendix C of Yugoslav foreign exchange earnings from exports and services in 1951-52 and 1952-53, which are of the order of  93 million, it is apparent that unless moratoria on debt payments are obtained, a considerable part of the aidproposed in paragraph 5 will be covering payments of debt, and that the debtburden as at present constituted exceeds the capacity of the Yugoslav economy.13. The participating Governments should agree that such of Yugoslavia^debt payments owed to their respective countries as fall due in the period 1st July,1952, to 31st December, 1953, and as are set forth in Appendix B, will be postponedor dealt with so as to eliminate effective payment thereof by Yugoslavia. Debtpayments to the United States, United Kingdom and France not included inAppendix B should be considered by the participating Governments as dealt withthrough their respective grants to Yugoslavia.14. The participating Governments should confirm their continuing intentionto work actively for a revision of Yugoslavia^ debt repayment schedules. For thispurpose, they should agree to consider the sponsoring of a conference of Yugoslavia^creditors to study possible action for amelioration of Yugoslavia^ debt burden,either through funding on a long-term basis or through other measures, and to take such action as may then appear appropriate.15. In the meantime the participating Governments should, by more activelysupporting Yugoslav efforts, or by assuming the initiative where desirable (a) workfor moratoria on debt payments falling due to countries other than the UnitedStates, the United Kingdom and France in 1952 and 1953 and (b) urge such countries to consider amelioration of Yugoslavia^ debt burden after 1953. Inthis latter connection the participating Governments should, after consultation withthe Yugoslav Government, inform the other creditor countries that the participating governments are considering sponsoring a conference of Yugslavia&apos;s creditors forthe purpose stated in paragraph 14.16. The participating Governments should by means of paragraph 3 (c) ofthe draft aide-memoire contained in Appendix A request an assurance from the yugoslav Government that it will seek the advice of the participating governments in good time before contracting any new credits (to be understood as includingloans, lines of credit, bank acceptance facilities and overdrafts) with the exceptionof credits extended by the I.B.R.D. and credits for the sole purpose of refinancingexisting credits. &apos;   &apos;17. The participating Governments should consult together on the problems arising from any credit, as defined in paragraph 16, which the Yugoslav Govern-ment proposes to seek abroad. The participating Governments should endeavourto reach agreement on the advice to be given to the Yugoslav Government and* Being the total of the columns headed &quot;Amount Drawn&quot; in Appendix D for the periodssubsequent to 1st January, 1952.
in the event of such agreement should give their advice jointly. Failing such agree-ment each Government should separately inform the Yugoslav Government ofits views. If the Yugoslav Government fails to seek the advice of the participating governments in accordance with paragraph 16, each of the participating Govern-ments shall be entitled, after consultation with the other two Governments, to cease the issue of its grant assistance referred to in paragraph 5 to the extent it considers necessary to protect its financial interests. If the Yugoslav Governmentproceeds, contrary to the advice of any one Government, to contract the credit,that Government shall similarly be entitled, after consultation with the other twoGovernments, to cease the issue of its grant assistance to the extent it considers necessary to protect its financial interests.Procedure in Belgrade18. The participating Governments should instruct their Economic missions in Belgrade that, in carrying out the recommendations of this Report if approved,they should exchange information and should consult together to the end that theassistance given in the form of grants or otherwise by the participating governments will be such as most effectively to promote their objectives as stated in this Report.In particular, the Missions should continue to review developments in the Yugoslaveconomy, with special reference to their impact on the need for foreign assistance.Communication to the Yugoslav Government19. If the participating Governments accept the recommendations of thisReport, they should instruct their diplomatic representatives in Belgrade to present to the Yugoslav Government an aide-memoire in the terms set out in Appendix A,which should be construed as an integral part of the recommendations of thisReport.London Report20. The agreement between the participating Governments which resulted from the adoption by them of recommendations contained in the London report should terminate on 30th June, 1952, except as provided in paragraph 13 of thepresent Report.
Draft Aide-memoire to be presented to the Yugoslav GovernmentThe Yugoslav Government will recall that the plan of assistance to Yugoslaviawhich was proposed by the Governments of the United States, United Kingdomand France on 12th July, 1951, and accepted by the Yugoslav Government on17th July, 1951, will come to an end on 1st July, 1952. The Governments ofthe United States, United Kingdom and France have recently completed a reviewof the operation of that plan, and of the present condition and future prospects ofthe Yugoslav economy. They desire to make known to the Yugoslav Governmentthe results of their review, and the action which in consequence they propose totake in the period 1st July, 1952, to 30th June, 1953.2. The three Governments reaffirm the second paragraph of their aide-memoire of 12th July, 1951. As the three Governments stated therein, theyconsider it essential to be satisfied that the Yugoslav Government is determined to balance its payments, and is taking measures calculated to bring this about inthe shortest possible time. The three Governments are seriously concerned that adequate measures towards this objective have not yet been taken. The three Govern-ments therefore call upon the Yugoslav Government to give its urgent and seriousattention to this most important matter and to acquaint the three Governmentsat an early date of the steps it is taking in this direction.3. The attainment of viability will depend upon the policies of the yugoslav government, and the three Governments invite the attention of the yugoslav government to the following matters:  (a) Investment. Although the  Yugoslav  Government  has  modified  itsinvestment programme during the last two years, the three Governmentsconsider that the annual rate of expenditure on this programme stillconstitutes too heavy a drain on the resources available to the Yugoslaveconomy. Accordingly, the three Governments urge the yugoslav government to reduce the annual rate of investment.Moreover, it is essential that the Yugoslav Government use anyfinance available for investment in such a way as to maximize itsability to pay for current imports. To accomplish this, the yugoslav government will need to direct its efforts toward the completion ofthose projects which have the highest priority. It is the opinion of thethree Governments that in assigning priorities to individual projects and industries, the following factors should be taken into account:(a) the direct improvement in the balance of payments; (b) the extentto which for any group of industries or any project there is the essentialrelated investment; (c) the extent to which a project has already beenfinanced; (d) the ability of the industry or project to compete effectively in world trade; (e) the length of time required for completion.(b) Agriculture. The three Governments wish to impress on the yugoslav government their belief that among the most important steps which need to be taken towards viability is the adoption and determinedpursuit of policies designed to encourage agricultural production and increase the agricultural output of the country, at least to the general level reached before the war. The great majority of the people of yugoslavia lives by agriculture, and a prosperous agriculture is essential for a strong Yugoslavia.(c) External Debts. The three Governments are considering the sponsoringof a conference of Yugoslavia^ creditors to study possible action foramelioration of Yugoslavia^ debt burden, either through funding ona long-term basis or through other measures, and to take such action as may then appear appropriate. The three Governments trust thatthey may rely on the full co-operation of the Yugoslav Government insuch a conference if convened.The three Governments consider that in the meantime the yugoslav government should continue to work for moratbria on debt paymentsfalling due in 1952 and 1953 to countries other than the United States,United Kingdom and France, and should urge these other countries to consider amelioration of Yugoslavia^ debt burden after .1953. Thethree Governments will actively support the efforts of the yugoslav government.42246-2
The three Governments take this opportunty of reaffirming t\ pthey consider the International Bank for Reconstruction and Develop-ment as the source of loans for investment for Yugoslavia. The three governments request an assurance that the Yugoslav Government will seek the advice of the three Governments in good time before contractingfrom any source other than the International Bank any new credits(to be understood as including loans, lines of credit, bank acceptancefacilities and overdrafts) with the exception of credits which are forthe sole purpose of refinancing existing credits.4. The three Governments note that the Yugoslav Government has not found it possible to supply all of the three Governments with desired quantities of materials and products of value to them. They trust that the Yugoslav Government will useits best endeavour to satisfy the reasonable needs of the three Governments inthis field.5. The three Governments believe that Yugoslavia would greatly benefit bythe provision of technical assistance, through arrangements for sending foreigntechnicians to Yugoslavia and for training Yugoslav technicians, both of the higherand lower grades, abroad. The three Governments trust that the Yugoslav Govern-ment will take advantage of such facilities as the three Governments are able tomake available.6. The three Governments continue to be concerned to receive from the yugoslav Government the fullest possible information on the state and prospects of the Yugoslav economy, and the fullest possible assistance in enabling the three governments to interpret and assess this information. The Yugoslav Governmentis already aware of the principal fields in which the three Governments are interested, and details of the information required will be communicated to the yugoslav Government from time to time as in the past.7. In accordance with the belief of the three Governments that the yugoslav government can make more rapid progress towards attaining economic viability,and consequently independence of foreign economic assistance, at the earliestpossible date, the Yugoslav Government can expect that economic assistance forthe period 1st July, 1952, to 30th June, 1953, will be less than the assistance whichit is receiving between 1st July, 1951, and 30th June, 1952. Assistance, if any,after 30th June, 1953, which of necessity would depend upon future considerationby the three Governments, will be progressively reduced.8. The three Governments request that the Yugoslav Government reply tothis aide-memoire indicating whether its terms are acceptable to them. In the lightof the reply of the Yugoslav Government, the United States Government will, indue course (dependent upon the provision of funds by appropriate legislation),inform the Yugoslav Government of the amount of the assistance which it isprepared to furnish to Yugoslavia in the period 1st July, 1952, to 30th June, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
