<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/8/27 images: 300-311</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. * ^It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document,f P,(40)197. . , COPY NO,.    ^FjgrO73.(40,)445 j o^flft JUNE.  1940.WAR CABINET0STRATEGIC IMPORTANCE OF THE CHANNEL ISLANDS.Report/by the Chiefs of Staff,,,committee.We have examined the strategic importance of theChannel islands in the light of the present situation.Strategic posit j on of the &quot;Islands o2. There are four main islands located as followsDistance from the French Coast 10 - 30 milesDistance from Portland. 60 - 90 milesDistance from Dieppe 130 - 160 milesImportance of Jshe islands 03. There are cable-landing points on Tooth Guernsey andJersey and a repeater station at st  Helier, while in certainplaces on both islands the cable runs along the shore.   Thiscable is at present of great importance as it is the onlytelephone cable link to france the cable lands in france at pirou (immediately east of Jersey) and then runs viaRennes to Paris0    Instructions have already been sent to theDistrict commanders to provide for its protection againstsabotage in the Islands04.      &apos; There are aerodromes on both jersey and GuernseyIslands.    The former is used by the Admiralty for training and the latter accommodates the NOo 1 School of general reconnaissance of the Royal Air Force.    In addition there are many sheltered bays with sandy beaches suitable for the landing of troop-carrying planes.   The harbours of the Islandswill give complete shelter only to light craft.5. possession of the Islands would give Germany air, andpossibly IvLToBop bases which might be used for the developmentof an attack on our lines of communication and bases in France,the Western Approaches and our southern coastline, or on 3ire*-The establishment of any. such bases would, however, necessitate

the provision of strong defences against attach by sea or air and to establish these a seaborne expedition would berequired.      Moreover, the enemy&apos;s line of communicationwould be extremely hazardous.6. If the Germans advance further west and a battledevelops for possession of the Cherbourg peninsula,  the aerodromes in the Islands might be of operational value tous;   but their value to the enemy would hardly-be sufficientto justify him in the effort nee dad to capture and use thempurely for the purposes of this battle.      Similarly, the harbours,  though, in these circumstances, they might be used by our small craft, would not be of sufficient value to theenemy for hini to attempt&apos;to capture them.      Should the enemyoccupy the Cherbourg peninsula, the Channel Islands cableroute would cease to be of value,,7. Should the Germans succeed in occupying the wholenorth coast of France, the,Channel Islands could evidentlynot be held by us for long;   but under these conditions theywould no longer to  of value to the enemy who would have manybetter mainland harbours and aerodromes available.     On theother hand, it is inconceivable that the Germans wouldoccupy the adjacent mainland and leave the Islands untouched.Sgale ,of Attach8* If the enemy should decide on the occupation of the islands, he could in existing circumstances land an over-whelming force in troop-carrying aircraft, and there is littlewe could do to interfere with his initial action.      He might also be able to transport troops in fast motor boats.      once in occupation, however, the difficulties of maintenance,,though not insuperable, would make his position precarious.It is doubtful therefore if Germany would think it worthwhile to attempt the occupation of the Islands.9. Germany might well attempt a raid, however, with the objects of:-(a) destroying the cable to France;(b) striking a blow at.our prestige by the temporaryoccupation of British territory.Military Forces in the Islands10.        On the outbreak of war the Militia were embodied bothin Jersey and Guersney (the smaller Islands of Alderney,Sark and Herm are dependencies of Guernsey)..      The GuernseyMilitia was disbanded in January, 1940, and the presentforces in the Islands are as follows;--

Guernsey and Alderney District.The 341st M.G. Training Centre (1500 men) is located in Alderney.       This force, combined with the R.A.F.personnel at the training school in Guernsey, is adequate for the protection of the1 cable and thedefence of the Islands against minor raids.Jersey- District.The only defence in this Island consist of some 150men of the Jersey Militia, who have a proportion ofLev/is guns and some 250 rifles.       There is also a party of 50 naval ratings at the Fleet Air Armaerodrome.       These latter are only partially trained and may he removed.     A local Defence Force againstparachutists is being formed some 500 strong, butrifles will not be available locally for more than half this number.There are   also small detachments of Royal Engineers inGuernsey and Jersey, and one Army Technical School, forboys in Jersejr.11.    There are no coast defences or A.A. guns in the islands and no considered appreciation for defence is believed to exist.12,   Acts are about to be passed which will render all maleinhabitants liable for military service;    those of suitableage and fit for service overseas, in the rank of UnitedKingdom military forces,  and older men and those unfit for service abroad in units for local defence.Course of action open to us.13..   It appears that the following courses of action are open to us:-(a) To provide the full scale of defence requiredto prevent the capture of the Islands.With the forces at present at our disposal thisis clearly out of the question.(b) Tonrovide fcross from the United Kingdom toto secure the Islands against minor raidsj   butin no circumstances to involve ourselves; In aooKKiitmont to reinforce the garrison:    we should,therofore, bo prepared to evacuate them ultimately,(c) To limit the defence of the islands to localresources.    Existing resources are not atpresent sufficient to defend the island againstminor raids.    This course would not ensurethe safety of the cable and would not afford a reasonable measure of protection to thelocal inhabitants.

(d) To demilitarize the Islands.    This might have unfortunate repercussions on the French.   we might be accused of exposing the FrenchNorthern flank to a further scale of attack from bases in these Islands.    This would nolonger apply if the German advance reached aposition on the mainland adjacent to theIslandso14,        In addition, the evacuation of the&apos;civil population of approximately 100,000 must be considered.The objections to this are:-(a) The shipping problem would be considerableparticularly in the face of probable air attack against which we could not afford toprovide fighter x^rotection.(b-): We have already too many useless mouths in theUnited Kingdom^ &apos;(c) The inhabitants may.very well be unwilling to evacuate.In spite of these objections, we consider that it is our duty to give a reasonable opportunity of voluntaryevacuation to those who wish to leave the Islands.    This shouldhe done at once sinqe we cannot contemplate the evacuation oflarge numbers of civilians iV^er heavy air attack.-Summary.IB.        To sum up:-(a) The Channel Islands are not of majorstrategic     importance either to ourselves orto the enemy,(b$ They are of minor strategic importance for thefollowing reasons:-(i) The only telephone cable to France runsvia the islands.(il); We might require the aerodromes if theGerman^advance penetrates further west.(iii) Germany might make use of the Islands forair and M.T.iB. bases.Noteo These reasons would cease to obtain whenthe enemy advance reaches the adjacentFrench Coast.

(a)(e)On strategical grounds measures to ensurethe security of the Islands against allpossible scales of attack would not hejustified at the expense of our commitmentselsewheretJ     It is, however, desirablethat we should secure the cable as long aspossible.The Islands areestablishmentsano longer safe for trainingWe are under an obligation to providefor the reasonable security of the Islandsagainst raids and we feel it is our duty to make available facilities for voluntaryevacuation of at least some of thepopulation,,Action tobe taken016c       Accordingly we are arranging:-(a) To despatch immediately two battalions, oneto Guernsey and one to Jersey,(b) That after the establishment of (a) above,he should immediately withdraw all training establishments,That preparations should be made inconjunction with the Ministry of Home security and the Governors of the Islands, for thedestruction of all facilities which mightbe of value to the enemy (e.g. aerodromes and oil scc-cks), and for the ultimatewithdrawal of the garrison if necessary.17.       We recommend that immediate consideration shouldbe given by the Ministry of Home Security and otherdepartments concerned to the desirability of offeringfacilities now for the evacuation of all women andchildren on a voluntary and free basis,      If evacuationon these lines is decided upon, it should be made clearthat persons not availing themselves of this offer willnot be evacuated at a later date,(Signed) C.L.N. NEWALL.&quot;        DUDLEY POUND.&quot;       R,H, HAINING.V.C.I.G.S.Cabinet War Room.




</content>
</cab>
