<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/198/23 images: 289-300</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 113COPY no. 7 December 1977CABINETINQUIRY INTO THE CROWN AGENTSMemorandum by the Lord chancellor. The note by officials attached at Annex sets out in paragraph 8 thequestions which Ministers must now consider in the light of the decision ofthe House of Commons on 5 December 1977.    This was, in effect, to reject the Governments proposals to set up an inquiry which would sit in privatebut would publish its report, its terms of reference limited to assessing theculpability of individuals in the Crown Agents, the Ministry of overseas development, the Treasury, the Bank of England and the Exchequer andAudit Department.    That rejection by the House of Commons followed asimilar reaction by the whole of the Press to the announcement of theGovernment&apos;s decision.2. The reasons put forward for the rejection are set out in paragraph 2of the Annex.    The major factor was the fear that a private inquiry would bea &quot;cover-up&quot; which would protect those who should not be protected.3. In this situation, nothing less than a public inquiry would, I believe,now satisfy Parliamentary and public opinion.    Paragraph 5 of the Annexidentifies three possible forms of public inquiry - a non-statutory Inquiry, a1921 Act Tribunal and a Select Committee of the House of Commons.4. While a non-statutory Inquiry would get round any difficulty created bythe language of the 1921 Act which requires the matter being enquired into tobe &quot;a definite matter of urgent public importance&quot;, and might (although I think this is doubtful) make it easier to build upon the Fay Report and its supportingevidence, I think the absence of compulsory powers would be a serious defect.Although in practice it may be true that even then the necessary evidencewould be forthcoming, nevertheless a non-statutory Inquiry would, I believe,not inspire the same public confidence in the Tribunal&apos;s ability to get at thefull truth.    I think therefore that the only real choice now is between a tribunal and a Select Committee.5. As to the ground to be covered by the Inquiry, the possibilities are set out in paragraph 8(b) of the Annex.    That set out in paragraph 8(b)(ii),i. e. &quot;all individuals whose part in the Crown Agents affair may be thought to beblameworthy&quot;, would cover not only the individuals concerned in the CrownAgents, the Ministry of Overseas Development, the Treasury, the Bank ofEngland and the Exchequer and Audit Department, but also the responsible ministers and the businessmen and solicitors involved in the relevant CrownAgents &quot;own account&quot; transactions.    It would therefore be appreciably wider than the original terms of reference proposed by the Government.1
6. I do not think the scope should be narrower than this.    The difficult question is whether the failure of organisations as well as cf individuals shouldbe expressly included.    As organisations act through the individuals who runthem, investigation of the failures of those individuals would enable theenquiring body, if so minded, to comment on failures attributable to organisa-tional defects.    In these circumstances I do not think it would be necessary toinclude a specific reference to the failure of organisations in the terms of.reference, particularly when to do so could involve the risk of a very wide-spread inquiry covering again the whole ground of the Fay Report.7. As to item 8(b)(iv) of the Annex, the investigation of the conduct of theindividual businessmen and solicitors involved would enable the enquiring body to examine and report upon the relevant business and commercial practices inso far as they contributed to that conduct.    A wide ranging investigation ofcommercial morality generally would not be appropriate for this kind of inquiry.8. The merits and demerits of proceeding by way of a Tribunal under the1921 Act or a Select Committee are conveniently set out in paragraphs 6 and 7of the Annex.    An additional difficulty attaching to a Select Committee is thatit would cease to operate at the end of the Parliamentary session unlessre-activated in the succeeding session.    Dissolution cf Parliament before thecompletion cf the Select Committee&apos;s work could give rise to awkwardconsequences.9. It is also to be borne in mind that any form of public inquiry into theconduct of individuals would almost inevitably preclude the institution of anycriminal proceedings against them and could well involve the abandonment ofany pending prosecution.    Civil proceedings too might be prejudiced and could hardly be continued while the public inquiry was taking place.10.       Of the two options, I think a Tribunal of Inquiry would be a better meansof satisfying public anxiety and public opinion, and of ensuring that those concerned are seen to be given fair treatment, even though this would inevitably take longer and be far more costly than a Select Committee.11.       At this stage it may be sufficient to announce the Governments intention that there should be a public inquiry and that its form and precise scope will be announced shortly.    This would give the Government more time to consider bothits terms of reference and, if it is to be a Tribunal, its composition, or, if it isto be a Select Committee, to enter into consultation with the other Parties in theHouse of Commons.    &quot;Whichever procedure is decided upon, there would have tobe a Parliamentary debate on a Resolution - in both Houses in the case of a tribunal of Inquiry, or in the House of Commons in the case of a SelectCommittee.E-lord Chancellor&apos;s office December 19772
CROWN AGENTS - COMMITTEE OE INQUIRYNOTE BY officials the Minister of State for Overseas Development announced on 1 December theGovernment&apos;s decision that following the Fay Report there should he a subsidiary inquiry under Sir Carl Aarvold with the following terms ofreference -&quot;In the light of the report of the Fay Committee, to assess thenature and gravity of any neglect or breach of duty by individualswhich may have occurred in the Crown Agents, the Ministry of overseas Development, the Treasury, the Bank of England and theExchequer and Audit Department.&quot;This inquiry would have sat in private but its report would have been published.     It would have had a clear and narrow objective - to help themanagement of the organisations concerned decide on any disciplinary actionwhich was needed against individuals who were blameworthy for neglect orbreach of duty.2.     In the House of Commons debate on 5 December (Hansard, Col. 1026-1096)and in press and public comment it has been strongly argued that the termsof reference are too narrow and that the inquiry should be in public.There are five strands in the criticisms -(l)   The inquiry should be in public in order to demonstrate that people in public positions are held to account for their misdeeds inthe same way as private citizens;(2)    the inquiry should be in public to give Ministers and officials who were criticised in the Fay Report a public opportunity to justifythemselves;(3)   a statutory inquiry is needed to compel evidence because some people (in fact three, of whom two were subject to criminal proceedings)refused to give it to the Fay Committee;1
(4)    the inquiry needs to cover not just the behaviour of individualsbut also the behaviour of the organisations concerned;(5)    the inquiry should deal with standards of commercial moralityexposed by the Fay Report.(A summary of the main points made in the Debate is at Appendix A.)The Questions for Consideration3.     The Government does not formally need to take any action following itsdefeat on a motion to adjourn the House.     There are indeed arguments for continuing with the private inquiry as originally conceived.     It would bethe quickest and cheapest way of establishing the culpability of individuals in the public service without pillorying in public individuals who were subsequently held to be relatively free of blame.     It would keep to a minimumany duplication with the work of the Fay Committee and any diversion of effort from current work by the organisations concerned.     Moreover if any public inquiry is set up it will in practice be necessary to abandon the criminal proceedings against Mr Sidney Finley (because the proceedings ofthe inquiry could prejudice his trial).     This course would not however meetthe strong views which have been expressed both in Parliament and more widelyand Ministers may feel that some form of public inquiry is now inevitable.In that event the main questions for consideration are -a. What should be the scope of such a public inquiry?b. What form should it take?The Scope of a Public Inquiryk.   There are four main possibilities -a.   A public inquiry with the same terms of reference as were proposed for the Aarvold inquiryThis would not meet the pressure from G-overnment supporters for a widerinquiry although it would meet the desire of the Opposition thatMr Richard Wood should have an opportunity to defend his actions in public.     In practice such an inquiry might well be driven wider thanits terms of reference and a more effective inquiry might result if2
this were accepted from the start.     It might well he thoughtinequitable that the public servants involved in the Crown Agents affairshould be subjected to a public inquiry while those outside the publicservice who contributed to that affair were not formally subject to it.On the other hand it can be argued that there are clear standards of duty owed by public servants and that no corresponding obligationsbind the other individuals involved.     If they acted illegally the remedy lies in criminal proceedings.     If not there is no reason why they should be subject to a public inquiry the proceedings of whichcould in practice leave a stain on their reputations even if they werecleared by the eventual report.b. A public inquiry covering the conduct of individuals both inside and outside tho public services involved in the Crown Agents affairThis would go a long way to meet the criticisms both in Parliament andin the press.     The inquiry would still be kept within bounds.     Onthe other hand such an inquiry could leave unfinished business if itexposed weaknesses in organisations without including recommendations to deal -with them.c. A public inquiry dealing both with the conduct of individuals andthe working of the organisations involved (Crown Agents, ODM, Treasury.Bank of England and Exchequer and Audit Department)This course -would meet the widely-held view that weaknesses inorganisations were as important as the failings of individuals incontributing to the difficulties of the Crown Agents and could providethe basis for effective remedies.    An inquiry of this sort would however be more appropriately undertaken by a Royal Commission than by a judicial or semi-judicial body.     It would be prolonged and couldseriously divert the organisations concerned from their ongoing business and obviously duplicate the work of the Fay Committee.     It could affectpublic confidence in Government as a whole as well as in the other institutions concerned.     In any case an inquiry worth its salt lookinginto the conduct of individuals would be likely in practice to exposeany weaknesses in organisations which came to its attention.3
d.   A public inquiry ranging into the general issues of commercialmorality raised in the House of Commons debate.There was some demand for such an inquiry.     It would however rangeso widely as to be of doubtful utility.     It would overlay the work ofthe Wilson Committee on Financial Institutions.Form of a Public Inquiry5.     It would be possible to have a non-statutory public inquiry.     Thiswould not be able to require the attendance of witnesses, a point to whichmuch attention was directed in the House.     This attention was somewhatmisplaced.     Fay managed well without powers but was of course sitting in private.     Only three people refused to give evidence, two of them in anycase subject to criminal proceedings.     It would be most unlikely that thequestion of powers would arise with any still serving in the public sectoras to disclosure of papers in that sector.     If however a power to compelwitnesses is felt to be essential in the case of an inquiry to be held in public the choice lies between -a. an inquiry under the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act 1921;its establishment would require affirmative resolutions in bothHouses of Parliament;b. an investigation by a Select Committee of the House of Commons.6.   An inquiry under the 1921 Act would be the normal procedure for dealingwith this sort of case.     It would ensure a judicial hearing for those whowere subject to criticism.     The tribunal would have statutory powers to compel witnesses to attend and give evidence.     On the other hand such an inquiry would be slow-moving (probably taking at least a year) and expensive(the costs could amount to about  1 million).     The proceedings of thetribunal could attract maximum publicity while it was sitting.   There couldbe a problem of forming terms of reference which met the requirement of the1921 Act that a tribunal is to inquire into &quot;a definite matter   ... ofurgent public importance&quot;.
7.     A Select Committee of the House of Commons could inquire into the waythe House itself handled the Crown Agents affair.     It can be held that a situation which has been provoked by an unprecedented surge of back benchopinion requires   action by Parliament itself.     A Select Committee wouldin practice be able to compel evidence.     Failure to submit it would be a breach of privilege.     The problem is essentially bipartisan:    the events inquestion took place under administrations of both Parties.     On the otherhand since the Select Committee on the Marconi scandal in 1912 select committees have been generally thought to be an unsatisfactory way ofinvestigating allegations of public misconduct.     The Report of the RoyalCommission on Tribunals of Inquiry under Lord Justice Salmon in 1966commented -&quot;The Marconi scandal for this purpose sounded the death knell of this form of investigation, and because it was wholly discredited, theAct of 1921 was passed.     To go back to it would, in our view, be aretrograde step.     We of course recognise that there are many purposes for which Select Parliamentary Committees are most useful and indeedindispensable - but the investigation of allegations of publicmisconduct is not one of them.     Such matters should be entirelyremoved from political influences.&quot; (Cmnd. 3121 para. 35)In addition a Select Committee would also be costly as those involved would no doubt expect to be provided with legal representation.     And there could be some awkwardness if a Select Committee had not completed its work during the life of the present Parliament.Questions for Decision8.     The questions which Ministers will wish to consider are -a. Should the inquiry be held in public or private (paragraph 3);If the inquiry is to be held in public -b. Should it cover -i.   the conduct of individuals in the Crown Agents, the ODM, theTreasury, the Bank of England and the Exchequer and Audit Department;5
ii. all individuals whose part in the Crown Agents affairmay be thought to be blameworthy;iii. failure of organisations as well as of individuals;iv. the wider question of commercial morality raised by theCrown Agents affair?    (paragraph I+)Should it be conducted in -i. a non-statutory public inquiry;ii. a tribunal under the 1921 Act;iii. a Select Committee of the House of Commons (paragraphs 5-7).6
APPENDIX a debate ON THE ADJOURNMENT - HOUSE OP COMMONSMONDAY, 5 DECEMBER 1977 (OFFICIAL REPORT COLS 1026-1096)The main criticisms made on the debate on 5 December were as follows -The business practices of the CityCriticism of such practices as letters of comfort or window-dressing (iegiving false information to shareholders).   &quot;This happens in the City allthe time.&quot;   -   Mr John Mendelssohn.The Bank of EnglandCriticism of the Bank for turning a blind eye to what was going on at theCrown Agents for so long, to which was coupled criticism of the auditorsand solicitors involved.- Mr John MendelssohnMr CunninghamMr SkinnerThe need to tighten tho regulations and rules under which auditors preparebalance sheets -- Mr Peter BrookeThe Civil service the Service was criticised especially for its mode of recruitment, its lackof business expertise and, in the case of the Treasury, for its pre-occupationwith relatively minor matters concerned with the Crown Agents when it failedto notice massive losses resulting from speculative dealings.- Mr Michael EnglishMr George CunninghamMr Dennis Skinner7
Tho Director of Public ProsecutionsCriticism of his jrlcwness of action in this case.- Mr Dennis SkinnerThe Excessive Independence of the Controller and Auditor General- Mr Michael EnglishSuppression and cover upCriticism of attempts made to dissuade the present Minister of overseas development from pursuing her attempts to bring the affairs of the CrownAgents into the open.   Reference to &quot;a closing of ranks&quot;.- Sir Harold WilsonThe House of CommonsFailure to organise itself so that Select Committees could pursueinvestigations of the kind that could have revealed at an earlier stage the situation of the Crown Agents.- Mr George CunninghamFailure of the House to exercise proper control- Sir Harold WilsonFailure of the House to react to warnings from the Press about thedifficulties of the constitutional relationship, the speculative work ofthe Crown Agents and the possible financial dangers for the Government.- Mr George CunninghamThe Select Committee on Overseas DevelopmentLack of urgency to start investigation of the affairs of the Crown agents and lack of tenacity in terminating their inquiries prematurely.- Mr Cunningham8
II.   Proposals for an open inquiry came from Mr Mendelssohn who opened the debate and most of those who followed,   The main points in favour of this course ofaction were -The need to avoid a whitewash and to counter &quot;great distrust about Whitehalland about Parliament&quot;.- Mr Richard LuceThe need for judicial procedures to give adequate protection to witnesses.The form of inquiry should be such as to compel witnesses to give evidence;reference to the Salmon Report on Tribunals of Inquiry in support of the1921 Act procedure.- Sir Michael HaversRequest for a special inquiry in respect of the Crown Agents AustralianInvestment.- Mr Prank Tomney7 December 19779


</content>
</cab>
