<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/30/14 images: 142-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT&quot;secretn^tpber 26th,  1942To be kept under lock and keyWAR    cabinet copy No. 2 6Increase in Corvette ConstructionMemorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.Requirements of ocean escort vessels.The Naval Staff have estimated that the adequate defence ofshipping in areas of British strategic responsibility requires themaintenance of a force of 1050 ocean escort vessels comprising destroyers,sloops, corvettes and a &quot;proportion of the large minesweepers.Present Strength and New Construction.2.      There are now available 445 such vessels and it is estimatedthat on the present scale of production the following numbers of escort vessels will be completed for British and Dominion Navies.In the U.K.In canadian  AustraliaLast Quarter194216NilNil19435039111944424023.      The decrease in UoK.  production in 1944 is due to the big shipsbuilding in the dockyards displacing sloops and to the destroyer yardsturning over to destroyers proper instead of building Hunts and Sloops,thus standardising types of construction to particular yards.      Newdestroyers joining the main forces are expected to release older ships for allocation exclusively to convoy duty as follows;-Nil94. In addition we can count on our large minesweepers assistingin convoy duty to an extent equivalent to a reinforcement of;-4 20The total British reinforcements will therefore be;20 129151086.      The assignment of American built vessels has not been carriedbeyond the allocation to the Royal Navy of 6 Destroyer Escorts to becompleted in the period up to March 1943.    It is a matter-of great difficult.y to forecast &quot;further assignments but it is not expected that totalswill exceed;- 1943 1944 ore19436080cast of Losses through enemy action.&apos;   7.     Having considered the experience of the war to. date, theincrease in number of U-Boats and the additional number of escort vesselsoperating, the Naval Staff estimate that the losses by enemy action of0cean escort vessels will be;-Last Quarter19421943401944458, Of the 445 vessels now in service about one hundred are theyia destroyers of the last war including the ex-American Town class,

2 -n(j it cannot be expected that more than half of these 25-year old shipsfill be fit for further use after two more winters.      In fact, ships ofthe type have already worn out and have been withdrawn from service.jn spite of the urgent need for keeping ships in service it is apparent that we must be prepared to withdraw some of these old vessels fromoperational work and it is estimated that this will be at a rate of:-Last quarter1942 1943 1944Nil 20 30^vailabilityo90      On the assumption that American assignments reach expectations,and allowing for losses and obsolescence,  the present scale of productionfill provide the following total numbers of ocean escort vessels at thedate shewn:-December December December1942 1943 1944456 585 .   69810.      The shortage in our requirements in ocean escort vessels will therefore amount to 465 at the end of 1943 and 352 at the end of 1944*.11.      To assist in meeting this shortage the Admiralty have examined the possibilities of speeding up and increasing corvette construetionQAs a result, it is proposed to utilise the structural engineering capacityof the country to make a large amount of pre-fabricated parts now made inthe shipyards, thus freeing skilled shipyard labour to build the ships andassemble the pre-fabricated portions.      At first the parts will be limitedto weights of about 5 tons on account of the limited capacity of thelifting appliances and transport immediately available, but by improvingthese facilities it is hoped to increase both the dimensions and weightsof the pre-f abricated parts.12.    By adopting this method it is hoped to obtain by the end of 1944delivery of 145 Twin Screw and 70 Single Screw Corvettes including vesselsstill under construction from earlier programmes.      This will involve theconstruction of 83 Twin Screw and 45 Single Screw vessels -(the latter ofa somewhat improved design) beyond the numbers already approved and it isintended to make provision as necessary in the 1943 and 1944 new construction Programmes.      Orders for some of the ships must, however, beplaced forthwith to enable materials to be collected and the vessels laiddown as soon as slips become available in 1943,13.      To carry this large expansion of output through it is essential(a) to standardise the design of equipment of these vessels in every respect including details of equipment;(b) to improve facilities in the Shipyards and Structural Engineeringwo rks;(,c) to provide steel as follows, for the Structural Engineering firms;i1943 1944Smarter_1st     2nd     3rd      4th_1st     2nd     3rd     4thTons 8000    16000 16000 16000 16000 16000    16000 16000(d) to obtain the necessary steel forging. capacity;&apos;e) to provide additional labour, as follows, at the earliest possible moment: -(i)    In the Shipyards:-19 per week to the North Bast Coast and the East coast of Scotland.14 per week to the Clyde,

- 371to a total estimated labour requirement of about 1000, a proportionl^f which should be skilled if possible.(ii)    In the Shipyards and their electrical sub contractors:-400 electricians, the majority of whom may be trainees.14c      When methods similar to those now proposed for corvetteconstruction &quot;*ere adopted for merchant ships and landing craft there[fas a certain ^ffhount of opposition from the Trades Unions.      If therefore[the present proposals are sanctioned, it is suggested that approval shouldJso be given to the principle that all possible steps should be taken to forestall difficulties with the Trades Unions over this extension of pre-fabrication to warship construction, which will require that shipyardiorkers should assemble constructional engineers&apos; work and constructionalengineers do what might technically be termed shipyard workers1  jobs.15.     As at present planned, this programme will not affect anymerchant shipbuilding slips, but it will affect engineering works at its inception and this may react on the construction of merchant shipengines until these works can expand to cope with both requirement.This is expected to result in the loss of up to 100,000 tons of merchantshipping during the expansion period.      This loss is part of thatcontemplated in D. C.(S) (42) 88, paragraph 37 (d).16.      The success of this plan is dependent on the ability to put it into operation at once, and for this reason Cabinet approval for theAdmiralty to employ the necessary capacity in the ConstructionalEngineering Trade, to obtain the necessary expansion in labour and plantin this trade, to obtain the necessary additional labour and plaht inthe Yards and to be allotted the necessary steel and steel forgingcapacity is asked for as a matter of urgency.17.      A financial statement is attached.     No estimate can be madeat present of the capital cost of the plant extensions necessary to meet this programme., but this matter will be the subject of consultationwith the Treasury if the present proposals are approved.Admiralty, S.W. 1.

S5CRETFINANCIAL STAT3.ENTIncreased construction of Twin Screw and Single Screw CorvetteScEstimate of Expenditure by Financial Years,,1942 194-3 1944- 1945 Total83 Twin Screw Corvettes 1.,750,000 10,000,000 11,000,000 75,000 22,825,000j Single Screw Corvettes 500,000      3,000,000     3,650,000     50,000      7,200,000Total2,250,000    13,000,000   14,650,000   125,000    30,025,000The above figures are only to be regarded as approximationsgiving an indication on broad lines of the order of expenditurelikely to be incurred, apart from plant, extensions.(




</content>
</cab>
