<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 16-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i r.iilS DOCUMENT IS THE ^RO^TY J)F^ HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S 0OVERTOBNT)I   R E T.tP5202(24)CABIN E&apos; T      NAVAL  ESTABLISHMENTS.WORKMEN UNDER NOTICE OP DISCHARGE.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty on         the Question of their retention.      The men entered for the winter months,  as explained in my statement on the Navy Estimates,  and now under notice of dis-charge, are distributed as follows   Districts,    ArmamentWoolwich&apos;,,Chatham -  SheernessPortsmouth.Devonport ,Rosyth   ,.Portland&quot;DepoTs&quot;  100  320  350   81   30 Torpedo and mining&quot;&quot;De^*oTs, 5402736WorksDepts t183173170 20 60Total.  100  508  563  278   86 &apos;  60&apos;***** mm MI M 1595&apos;      If these men are retained, they could with advantage beemployed as shewn belowAT ARMAMENT DEPOTS.      Bringing reserves of the following stores into a service-able condition - Guns, Ammunition,  Small Arms, Machine Guns,  etc,AT TORPEDO AND MINING DEPOTS.      Bringing reserves of the following stores into serviceablecondition - Torpedoes, Mines, Depth Charges and Paravanes etc.AT THE DOCKYARDS (Works Dept.)      On repairs and maintenance of buildings, the provision forwhich has for several years been strictly limited, so that thereare many arrears to be overtaken in order to bring the buildingsinto a satisfactory condition.      If those men are retained for the whole year,  an additional sum of  130,000 will be required on Vote-9, and an additional sumof  120,000 on Vote 10.  If &quot;wastage&quot; of labour staff during  the .year is not made good, it would be  safe to reduce this sum by,  say 10,000, making a total additional  expenditure of  240,000.
        Provision of this  240,000 was not  included in the  Estimates, because of the necessity for keeping them to  the  minimum  amount possible, but although the work in  question  can be postponed if the financial  situation makes  this Imperative,  It  is work which  would be  of the greatest  use  and would  save heavier expenditure at some later date        It  lias already been agreed between  the Chancellor of the  Exchequer and  the First Lord that  if progress on contract ship-  building  and contract work generally during 1924-25 should  exceed the Chancellor&apos;s anticipations, based on previous  year&apos;s experience,; - thereby causing naval  expenditure to  exceed the provision actually made in the Estimates - a  Supplementary  Estimate within a certain figure will be  forthcoming.  The Admiralty suggest that  if it is desired  to avoid  the discharge of these men, the sum necessary for  their retention should be added to the amount which the  Chancellor has  thus agreed to cover, in the event of need  arising,  by  a  Supplementary Estimate.                                     G4 MAR  1924

</content>
</cab>
