<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 21-23</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE  PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT.                         CABINET.               MEMORANDUM  BY THE MINISTER  OF LABOUR.             *^  &apos;      THE TRADES  UNIOE  CONGRESS GENERAL  COUNCIL  AND LEGISLATION.&amp;CRET.     1.  I h&amp;ve rooontly  had. oorrespondonoe  with Mr.  Fred Bromley,TOT(84).   Secrotary  of the Trades Union Congress General  Council, as a       result of  which  a point has  emerged  on which I  should like the       dooleion of tho  Cabinet.          2.  As &amp; matter of oourtesy and in order to obtain tho best       advice available, I  have  sent to  the General Council (and to       the National confederation of Employers1  Organisations) memoranda       describing tho proposals  to  be  contained  in two Bills which I  am       about  to introduoo - the  Unetnploymont Insurance Bill providing       for an extended  Insurance Scheme, and the Hours of Employment       Bill dealing with the  Washington  Hours Convention.   I have       asked  the  General Council  (and  the Confederation)  to let me have       any observations which thoy  may have to offer upon those pro-       poeale, and I  have stated my willingness  to see the representa-       tivee  of the Council (and of the  Confederation) upon any of the       pointy if thoy  so desire.          3.  Mr.  Bramloy has  written to  me  to  say that it is tho       polioy of  the  General  Oounoil to  desire to see  tho drafts of the       Bills  which it is proposed  to introduoe.    Ho alleges that a       refusal to submit the Bills  to  the Council would be a departure       from previous  practice.   So far  as  Ministry of Labour Bills       are concerned., he quotes  in  support  of his argument the case       of two Bills that were doalt with by the  Minister of Labour in       1919 - the Hours of Employment  Bill  of  that year and the       Industrial Courts Bill.    The former Bill, however, was ^he       result of  the  work of a Joint Committee  appointed by the       National Industrial Conference  and specifically asked by the       Government of  the day to  advise upon the  form of legislation.                             -1-
It is true that the then Minister of Labour in effect adopted the proposals of the Joint Committee and introduced a bill which they had assisted  in preparing, but the decisions of theMinister and of the Government  were taken upon the proposals ofthe Joint Committee - it was  not  the case that the JointCommittee were asked to  examine a Bill containing proposalsinitiated by the Government.  Aa  regards the Industrial CourtsBill, I understand  that  there were in that Bill certain clausesdealing with the question of  the  extension of agreements andthe imposition of penalties for breach of agreement; the objectof the discussion in 1919 upon  these clauses was to ascertain whether it was practicable to reach agreement between theTrade Union movement on  the one hand and the Employers&apos;Confederation on the other hand,  on a matter upon which neitherthe Minister of Labour nor the  Government had themselves taken adecision,     In the case of the  Trade Boards Bill of last Session,the Minister of Labour declined to discuss the Bill withinterested parties  until it had first been presented toParliament.   4. I have informed Mr,Braraley of the difficulties that I see in acceding tc the  request of the General Council,  It is not asif the proposals in these two Bills were proposals upon which Iam endeavouring to  secure agreement between organisations ofemployers and employed,  nor are they proposals to carry outagreements reached by these organisations or by any Committeerepresenting them;   the  proposals are based upon operativedecisions of the Government.    It seems to me, and I have so informed Mr.Bramley, that Parliament is the body to which theGovernment must submit its proposals,  I have said that I am prepared to go. to any reasonable length by way of memoranda andverbal discussions-., etc. to ensure that the proposals are
                                                            (.J 1explained fully toConfederation) , but it seems to me that it would be-wrong to take the line that-any. body other than Parliament has any right to claim consultation upon the precise terms ofprojected legislation.  It is obviously convenient to discussin detail with parties interested particular clauses whichmay affect them;  it is a common device to consultinterested parties upon particular clauses as a means of facilitating the ultimate progress of a Bill.   5,  Because  of the constitutional issue involved, I shouldhesitate to accede to the request which the General council have made to me, at any rate without first obtaining theviews of my colleagues and a docision by the Cabinet,                                   (Initld,) T.S.Ministry of Labour,24th March. 1924.

</content>
</cab>
