<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 822-823</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY QP HIS ERITANNIO MA.JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.        In accordance with tho Cabinet instruction (Item 11cf Cabinet 18 (24)  ) that the Chancellor of the Exchequerand the Minister of Transport should examine the question ofthe method by which tho proposed new jrogpomme can best be financed, we have examined estimates prepared by the Ministryshowing (a) the income of the Rind during the seven years ending 1930/1931 (b) the probable minimum demands against theFund for the maintenance, reconstruction and improvement of.Roads and Bridges during these years and (o) the probable rateof disbursement from the Fund, including disbursements undea?the proposed programme of  13:1 millions,       These estimates assume that the gross reoelpts fromthe Motor Taxes will rise to  17,600,000 In 1926/27 and willthereafter remain constant at that figure, and that theminimum demands against the Fund for maintenance reconstruction and other purposes will rise to  15,000,000 in 1928/29 and thereafter remain at that figure.   Upon those assumptionsit appears that the fund could add a new programme of  13 millions to its existing liabilities in respect of schemes to be undertaken now in relief of unemployment, and would still be able to meet its payments as they fall due,  out ofits accumulated and accruing revenues.       The estimates put before us are necessarilyapproximate and on the side of gross reoelpts are probablycautious.   On the other hand the amounts provided for maintenance and improvement are admittedly minima,  and may prove to be insufficient.,P.268(24).C A B I NET,ROAD  FUND  FINANCE.Joint Memoranda by the Minister of Transport and tho Financial Secretary to the Troa3ury*
       Miile, therefore, we are able to report that Inour opinion the Road Fund oan finance Its share (estimatedat  10,400,000) of a further programme of  13^ millions(to be devoted to works to be put in hand earlier  than would otherwise be done with a view to affording employment)by anticipating Its future revenues up to 31st March,  1931and without recourse to borrowing, we do not consider  thatths future revenues of the Fund 3hould at present  beanticipated for such works to any greater extent than  thlaprogramme entails.       The Treasury guarantee of financial &quot;cover&quot;  givento. the Fund in connexion with previous programmes  shouldbe extended to include this programme if authorised.                      (Initialled)  H. G.                                    W. 0.

</content>
</cab>
