<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 866-867</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OB&apos; HIS BRITANNIC MJF.SXY&apos;S government,iSsffiRET.                    CABINET,P,P. 274   (24),                                                  V:f                      Airship  Development.           Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air,1,        If, as I hope, my colleagues approve the report of theAirship Development Committee (C,P.267(24)) recently circulatedby the Secretary of State for the Colonies, I desire to suggestthat, before it is finally adopted, four small amendments shouldbe embodied.   These amendments are set forth on the attachedsheet.          Only the first is of any substance.   Furtherconsideration and discussion of the original proposal that theBurney interests should retain and operate the airship to be constructed by them have shewn that It would present considerable financial and administrative complications.   It is thereforenow proposed that this ship shall be constructed for, and, on completion, handed over to the Air Ministry, who will give theBurney interests an option to purchase it at a greatly reducedfigure, if they require it for the purpose of operating an approved commercial airship service,2,        I further desire to draw the attention of my colleagues to the urgent need for euthority to be given to the Air ministry to put in hand the research work etc,, at Cardington. which mustprecede the construction of a 5,000,000 cubic feet airship,in accordance with paragraph 2 (i) of the Committee&apos;s report.          My colleagues will, I think, agree that it is ofimportance that we should be able to inform Parliament withoutfurther delay that we are taking active steps to proceed withthe development of airships;  and I would emphasise that, unless8 start is made forthwith, progress at a later stage may be setback several months owing to our being unable to take advantageof the right season for tha first experimental flight to India,3.        As regards the second ship which is to be builtsimultaneously by the Burney interests, the Committee (of whichI am Chairman) appointed to conduct provisional negotiationshas already met Commander Burney and plr.oed the propositionbefore him in broad outline,   So far as it is possible to judgefrom the tenor of this meeting, I am hopeful that it may bepossible to reach a satisfactory agreement,4,        The initiation of the preliminary work by the AirMinistrv at Cardington should not, however, for the reasons have given in paragraph 2, be delayed until a contract withCommander Burney has been definitely negotiated, and I therefore ask the authority of the Cabinet to proceed with this workforthwith.                                              T&apos;secretary OF STATE FOR AIR.
   PROPOSED AMEHDMBKTS TO REPORT OF CABINET COMMITTEE           ON AIRSHIP DEVELOPMENT (0 .P.267/24).1*      Paragraph 2 sub-paragraph (ii) lost three lines.           Delete the words &quot;to be retained&quot; to  &quot;as required&quot;inclusive..           This omission is suggested because further consideration and discussion of the original proposal thet the Burney  interestsshould retain and operate tha airship to be constructed  by them have shewn that it would present considerable financial  andadministrative complications...2.      Paragraph 3.           Amend to read as follows:-           &quot;The terms of the Burney contract to  be settled by aCommittee, of representatives of the Treasury (Sir G. Barstow) andAir Ministry (Sir S, Dannreuther) with the Secretary of  State forAir in the Chair, in consultation with Commander Burney&quot;.           The reason for this amendment is that it is perhaps  not altogether appropriate that Commander Burney should be a member ofa Government Committee which is to settle the terms of a contract to  be made with l^im.3.          Pa paragraph 5 sub-paragraph ph (a).           In the last line of this sub-paragraph put a  semicolonafter the words &quot;Post office&quot; and add the words  &quot;also of shippinginterests&quot;.4,          Paragraph 6 third, line.           For the words &quot;research work at Cardington&quot; substitute&quot;research work etc. at Cardington as in paragraph 2 (i)&quot;.                                                I!

</content>
</cab>
