<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 885-910</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                       ^_ (I          L,     *J                                                                U .1 this DOCUMENT  IS  THE HiOPEilTY OP HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT,CABINET.PRESENT  DISPARITIES  IN  WAGES.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.3*fcORETE7OT9(24)     I circulate for the information of ray colleagues theaccompanying Memorandum with regard to the present dis-parities in wages in different industries.   This subject Isattracting a considerable measure of public attention, and demands are being mads for a general enquiry by the Govern-ment into the whole question.   Further, some of the more marked anomalies which exist as between the retes of wages of different classes of workers have contributed towardsrecent industrial  unrest.     It will be seen from the Memorandum that the increases in wages between 1914 and 1920, and the reductions between1921-and 1924, varied widely in different cases,, accordingtc the varying conditions in different industries.  At theend  of 1920, when the rise in wages had reached approxi-mately its highest point, the increase over pro-war weeklywage rates for full-time ranged from less than 130 per cent,in some industries to between 200 and 300 per cent, in others, the average increase being about 170 to 180 per cent.as compared with an average increase of about 165 per cent.in cost of living.   At the end of torch, 1924, the increases over pre-war rates of wages variecjbetween extremesof less than 20 per oent. and over 150 per cent, the generalaverage being about 70 per cent., as compared with an average increase of 73 per cent, in cost of living.  Under theInfluence of these variations, the weekly full-time wages ofunskilled labourers in the large industrial towns, whioh                                                     /were
were mostly about 20s. to 25s. a week before the war, nowrange from less than 40B, in same industries up to over 55B.In others.   For skilled men in the larger towns, whoseweekly time rates mostly fell between 34a, and 42a, a week in 1914, there is now a range from less than 50s, up toover 75 a , Consequently, some classes of skilled mechanics(e,g., in the shipbuilding industry) are paid less thanunskilled or only partially skilled men in other industries,and much less than other classes of skilled men whose ratesof pay before the war approximated to their own rates.  Forexample, shipwrights were paid.roughly the same rates, in 1914,aa wiremen employed by electrical contractors, and rather morethan hand compositors on book and jobbing printing, whereas the electrical wiremen in the large towns now receive nearly29s, a week more, and the compositors nearly 28s. a week more,on average, than the shipwrights.     In the public discussion that has recently been arousedspecial attention is being focussed on the differences betweenthe relative wage-levels in certain industries and services not directly exposed to foreign competition and in certain industries which are largely dependent cn exports, or largelyexposed to foreign competition.   The Memorandum shows thatin the &quot;sheltered&quot;&quot; industries and services the increases over pre-war rates of wages are greater, on the whole, than in the&quot;exposed&quot; industries.  There are some notable exceptions,however, which suggest that caution is necessary in drawinggeneral inferences from this fact, and detailed considerationof the individual circumstancos of different industrios leads to the conclusion that a variety of special factors, other thanforeign competition, have had an important bearlngton the changes in the relative wage levels in different industries,                                                    /Among
                                                                6&apos;&apos;0     Among these  factors  may  be  mentioned  the  varying effects  on the     prosperity of different  industries  of abnormal expansion  during     the war  and  subsequent dislocation  resulting from shrinkage     of war requirements,  of  increases  in  prices  of imported raw     material and other  costs of production, and  of trade     organisation.    The  differences  in  the strength of Trade  Union     organisation have also had  a considerable Influence in some     cases.                               (Intd)  T. S.Ministry of Labour,     1st May, 1924.
    MEMOKAHDUM BY QEg MINISTRY Off LABOUR OH THE ERBSSBHT                     DISPARITIES IB WAGES.      As  a result of tha disputes whioh have arisen recentlyout of demands lor improved conditions cf pay in many industriesa considerable amount of attention Is being directed to thedisparities whioh at present exist betwoes the wagos of work-people in different industries and to the marked changes whiohhave taken plaoe in tha relative well-being of different classesof workpeople  as oompared with normal conditions before the war.      The Committee on Pay, eto.t of State Servants, appointed in 1923 under  the Chairmanship of Sir Alan Anderson, devoted aconsiderable part of their enquiries to this subject and reportedthat &quot;The difference between tha profits and wages in world -&quot;trade and tha profits and wages in sheltered employment, is to&quot;our mind, ths clue through what otherwise seems a tangle of&quot;anomalies and injustice.   The results of world trade jump up&quot;and down, while sheltered trade follows with an increasing lag&quot;as the 3helter becomes more oomplete&quot;.  In a speech in thaHouse  of  Commons on 10th Maroh, Mr.......Baldwin dealt with the same question  at considerable length.  &quot;I believe&quot;, he said, &quot;thatone of tha most fruitful sources of trouble in the industrial&quot;world, not one that is on tfte surface, but below, is this&quot;disparity of  wages whioh exists throughout the oountry........&quot;The most striking foature of the wagos position to-day, as&quot;compared with before the war, ic the way in which what I may&quot;call  the sheltered trades - that is the trades whioh are&quot;naturally protected - have improved their position at ths cost&quot;of the trades which are subject to foreign competition&quot;.  In a letter to the &quot;Times&quot; on 29th Maroh, Mr, O.N. Barnes said &quot;I am&quot;?lad  to  note  that at last, the disparitj/ in wage rates as&quot;between  skilled and unskilled labour is attracting widespread                                                 /attention
"attention......  Present conditions at Southampton show how "things are going.....  Here in London engineers  are working "side by side with unskilled labourers who are paid nearly "twice as high wages. The dustman is paid higher, the busman "is, by comparison, an aristocrat". There have been further discussions, in the press and elsewhere, in which Mr. Hitchens, Mr.  Pybus, Lord Weir, and Mr. L.S. Amery, among others, have taken part. In the case of the Southampton Shipyard Strike, the Central Strike Committee issued a statement contrasting the weekly full-time wages at Southampton of

Semi-skilled Shipyard Workers (38s. 0?)

and  Skilled Shipyard Mechanics (47s.6d)

with those of Dockers (60s.6d)

Builders&apos; Labourers (46s.9d)

Electricity Works Labourers (51s.Od)

Refuse Collectors (47s.3d)

Road Sweepers (47s.3d)

Policemen (70s.0d)

Tram Drivers (58s.1Od)

and Tram Conductors (55s.0d)

There have also been two recent questions in Parliament by Mr. Grahame White on 2nd April and General Cockerill on 7th April) drawing attention to the subject and asking the Prime Minister to institute an enquiry;  in reply the Minister of Labour referred to certain information already published in the "Ministry of Labour Gazette" and stated that he was considering whether additional information could readily be made available. 

In this Memorandum some indication is given of the dis-parities in wages in the principal industries, so far as this can be done from such information as is at present available in the Ministry of Labour, with particular reference to the position of the "sheltered" trades as compared with those trades which are largely dependent on exports or exposed to foreign competition.


                 Pre-war1  and Present Wages.      Before  the  war  the  weekly  time rates of wages of adultworkmen ranged generally within relatively narrow limits.Unskilled labourers  in the  large industrial towns mostlyreceived about 20a.  to  5s. a week, and  skilled time-workers from  about 34s.  to 42s.  a week;  partially skilled menreceived intermediate  amounts.   There were certain exceptionst&apos;g&quot;.  builders&apos; labourers&apos; rates  in the large towns averagedabout 273. a week in summer, though less in winter, and manyrailway porters were rated at less than  20s a week:  but thebulk  of the rates of adult men  on time-work in the chief industrial areas fell within the limits  stated.   The earnings of skilled piece-workers w-ere generally somewhat higher thanthose of corresponding classes  of skilled time-workers, butthe proportion of men  earning more than  4Ss.  a week was verysmall.    Wages in agriculture were lower than in urbanindustry,  the average  earnings  of ordinary agricultural labourers  in England and scales  being about 18s, a week.     It tho present time, rates of wages are  much more widelydispersed.  In agriculture, the lowest paid of the largeindustries, the average rate of wage in England and v/ales isonly about 283.  a week, and in many distriots it Is as lowas 25a.    Labourers in the shipbuilding industry,  and steel-v?ork.3 labourers in many of the principal distriots,  receiveless than  40a. a woek.  On the other hand,  labourers,  in manyindustries and services reoeive over 50s. a week,  and insome cases their rates exceed 55a,    Among skilled men the&quot;spread&quot;  of wage rates is even greater,  the weekly time ratesranging  from about 45s. to 50s.  in the shipbuilding  industryup to over 70s.  in the larger  towns,  in  the printing,  book-binding:, building,  furniture,  and some other  trades.    Beforethe war, skilled artisans In the large towns  obtained wagessubstantially higher  than those  of any class  of unskilled men,                                                /whereas
whereas the present wage r&amp;tes of considerable numbers of skilled men in the shipbuilding industry are lower than thoseof unskilled labour era in many other industries in the samedistricts, and the rates of skilled engineers are less thanthoae of some of the higher paid classes of unskilled-or only partially skilled workmen.     Marked departures, of this kind, from what was regardedbefore the war, as the normal relationship of wage rates,began in the early years of the war, when the urgent demandfor men in the principal war munitions industries resultedin the grant of increases in wages, in those industries, muchgreater than those granted in ether industries.   She varia-tions in the extent to which different industries have been affected by the depression of the past four years have resulted in similar inequalities in the downward movementof wages, and in some oases the relative positions of differentclasses of workers have, in the process, been  reversed.  Forexample, workpeople in the iron mines, and in the iron andsteel works, whose wages are among those most severely affected by the present depression, were  among the classes        vof workers who received the greatest increases in wages between1914 and 19 20.      The Variation^ in the Increases pyer^ Pre-war Wages.     In Appendix able I details are given of the increasesover pre-war rates of wages, in a number of the principal industries, at the end of 1920 (when wages generally hadreadied their maximum) and at 1st April, 1924.   Vihereaa theaverage increase over pre-war rates of wages for a fullordinary week, in the industries and services for whichparticulars are available,  is estimated at about 70 per cent.                                                         /et                                                                jSsfeiBtaiiiia^                     .... V &apos;......-*&quot;..,&apos; ,&apos; m^MBMJKIWlT1 111  &quot;&quot; &apos; &apos;. &quot;&quot;BBSS
at the beginning of April, 1924, it will be seen thatthe Individual inoreasea range in different casesfrom as little as 18 per cent, up to over 150 per cent.The average increase in cost of living over the pre-war level at the same date was about 73 per cent,  Itwill also be seen from the Table that disparitiesbetween the amounts of increase in different tradeswere quite as marked at the end of December, 1920,when wages were approximately at their highest point,as  they are at present.   The individual percentageof increase over pre-war rates, at that date,  rangedfrom lesB than 130 per cent, in some cases up to between 200 and 300 per cent, in others,  the generalaverage being about 170 to 180 per cent.   The increasein cost of living at that time averaged about  165 percent.     In the following Table the trades for which figures are given in Appendix I are grouped so as to distinguishthose in which the increases at the end of 1920  andat the beginning of April, IS24,  were (1)  substantially above ttfe genersl average increase for all trades  (2)not markedly different from the general average, and(3) substantially below the general  average.
      End&quot; of December-,  1920,Average  Increase - 170, to 180%(Cost of Living   165% above      pre-war)0            1st April, ICTJi.Average Increase - about 70$(Cost of Living -&quot;lb% above pre-   -_     war ).(1)  Increases substantially above the general average.Over 190  per  cent  Increase.  -   Pig Iron Manufacture   Iron Mining   Railway Service - lower         paid  grades.   ^obacco (vvomen)   Building Labourers   Iron and Steel  Puddling,       Rolling, etc.   Chemical Works  Labourers   Engineering - Labourers   Shipbuilding -  Labourers   Wool Textile   Textile Bleaching, Dyeing,     etc.  (Men in  Lancashire,     Cheshire  and  Scotland )   Silk (Women at  Leek     and  Winders,  Doublers,     etc.  at Macclesfield ).   Dyeing and- Cleaning  -     Labourers .   Police Constables   Gas Works  Labourers,Over 100 per cent Increase,  -  Railway Service - lower paid              grades,  Tobacco  Brewing Labourers (Burton)  Printing and Bookbinding .  Boot and Shoe Manufacture  Baking  Road Transport (one-horse         drivers ).  Police Constables  Dyeing and Cleaning  - Labourers  Textile Bleaching, Dyeing, etc;    (men in Lancashire, Cheshire    and Scotland ),  Silk Workers (Women  - Leek),  Electricity Supply - Labourers,80 to 100 per cent. Increase. -  Tramways  Local Authorities&apos; Non-Trading    Services - Labourers,  Building Labourers .  Chemical Works -  Process    Labourers  Electrical Installation  Railway Service (Engine Drivers,           etc , )  Silk leaving (Men -  Leek)  Dock Labour  Wool Textile  Furniture  Gas Works Labourers  Textile Bleaching, Dyeing, etc.    (women in Lancashire. Cheshire    &amp; Scotland and  Time-workers in    Yorkshire ).  Basket Making (Lancashire)  Saddlery &amp; Harness (Midlands)   (2 ) Increases not markedly different from the  averageo 190 per cent. Increase.-j 60 to 80 per cent. Increase.  -Coal Mining                 jLooal Authority Non-Trading I  Services - LabourersAgricultureTinplateSteel Smelting - Skilled Men!Brewing Labourers (Burton)  jPrinting and BookbindingBakingTobacco (Men)Building (Skilled Men)Engineering LabourersSeamenShipbuilding LabourersCottonCarpet Manufacture (Time-Workers)Textile Bleaching, Dyeing,  etc. (Piece-Workers in  Yorkshire ),Silk leaving (Macolesfield )
    End of December, 1920,  .Average Increase a 170 to 180?(Cost of Living a 165,? above          pre-war)._          1st  April,  1924.lAverage  Increase  - about 70?. (Cost of Living s 73% above&apos;I__pre-war)o(2) Increases not markedly different from the  average.  (Contdc )ii0-\o 190 per cent. Increase,-   Seamen   Electrical Installation     Cotton   Deck Labour   Road Transport (one-horse     drivers ).   Textile Bleaching, Dyeing,     etc. (//omen in Lancashire,     Cheshire and Scotland and     Time-workers in Yorkshire),   Basket Making (Lancashire)   Electricity Supply Labourers   Furniture 60  to  80  per  cent.  Increase.-.  Hosiery Manufacture  Gold  and Silver  (London)!  Bespoke Tailoring (London -     West-End)  Hand-Sewn Book Making  (London-     West -End )(3 5  Inoreases substantially below the  average.Below 160 per cent. Increase,-   Building - Skilled Men   Carpet Manufacture   Boot and Shoe Manufacture   Tramways   Railway Service (Engine     Drivers, etc, )   Hosiery   Engineering - Skilled Men   Shipbuilding - Skilled Men   Pottery   Textile Bleaching, Dyeing,     etc, (Piece-Workers in     Yorkshire),   Silk leavers (Men-- Leek)   Lace (Nottingham)   Pelt Hat Making   Basket Making (London)   Saddlery and Harness (Midlands   Gold and Silver (London)   Silk Weaving (Macclesfie Id)   Bespoke Tailoring (London -     West-End )   Hand-Sewn Boot Making (London     West-End ),! Below  60  per  cent..  Increase , -j   Coal Miningj   Agriculture!   Pottery   Carpet  Manufacture  (Piece -     Workers)   Pig  Iron Manuf 80 ture   Iron and Steel  Manufacture   Tinplate Manufacture   Engineering - Skilled Men   Shipbuilding -  Skilled Men   Lace Manufacture  (Nottingham)   Pelt Hat Making   Basket  Making (London)   Iron Mining
     Of the industries in which the increase  in pre-war wageshow lies substantially below the general average  for alltrades, the pig iron, iron and steel, and iron mining industries had increases substantially above the average at  the end of1920, and ooal mining, agriculture, and. tinplate  manufacturehad increases, at that date, well up to or slightly abovethe general average,  Even before the war, the wagefluctuations in the mining, pig iron, and iron and steel industries were considerably greater than in other industries,     Present Time-^ork Rates of Wages of Skilled  Men and          Unskilled Labourers in Different Industries,     In Appendix Table II comparative figures are given ofthe present-weekly time rates of wages of (a) representativeclasses of skilled men and (b) unskilled labourers, in various industries.  As rates of wages vary, within each  Industry,  indifferent districts, the district rates In 10 of the largesttowns have been averaged s, for the purpose of this Table,  inorder to facilitate comparison.     The following examples taken from that Table, with figuresadded for July, 1914, and December, 1920,  illustrate the widevariations which have arisen between the wage rates of  different-classes of men who received roughly similar amounts of  weekly               vwages before the war:-E  The information available as to the numbers of men receivingdifferent rates in each town is insufficient to enable true&apos; weighted&quot; averages to be computed, and as the figures relate onlyto 10 of the large towns they cannot, of course, be used as showing the absolute level of wages in the country as a whole;  butthey are sufficiently comparable for the particular purpose forwhich they are used In this Memorandum,  The towns included areLondon, Glasgow, Liverpool. Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol,Sheffield, Leeds, Hull and Newcastle.
ft 0 $Industry and occupation.Average&apos; Weekly Time Rates ofA&apos;ages jn the larger towns atJuly,1914,December,  1920,April,1924,Skilled  Men:Shipbuilding    ii                 Shipwrights                 Ship Joiners  Engineering - Fitters and  &apos;                    Turners  Building    - Bricklayers  Printing - Jobbing Composit-                         ors.  Electrical Installation&apos;-                 8iremenLabourers:414038413639IIron and Steel Manufacture  I 23Shipbuilding                I 23Engineering                 j 23Building                    ! 27 &quot;dT.  6,.  7,.  7..  4..  9,4  9 0.  4,.  8,,10,,10.  s.  d ] 91.  5.102.  5. 89.  1.102.  8. 95.  8,106.11.73.  2,71.  4,70.  0,90.  8. s;  d,48,  9.51.  2,56,  8.72.  3.76,  7.77.  7,37, 1.38,10,40, 4.54. 6,     These  examples  are sufficient to indicate  the markeddisparities which at present exist in many cases  as comparedwith pre-war conditions.   The average for shipwrights,  forexample,  which was 41s,6d. before  the war, is now 48s. 9d.,whereas  that for electrical contractors&apos;  wiremen, -which was39s.9d.  in  1914, is  now&apos;77s.7a.  An examination of the  more detailed  figures given in Appendix II will show that some  ofthe  highest paid classes  of labourers are receiving as  much as,or more  than,  highly skilled classes of artisans  in engineeringshops and shipbuilding yards.     &quot;Sheltered&quot; Trades compared with Trades  dependent     on  Exports or exposed to Foreign Competition.     It  has already been remarked  that considerable attention is being directed to the  differences in relative  wage  levels in &quot;sheltered&quot; trades and in trades exposed to  foreigncompetition or dependent  on exports for their prosperity,  andin some  quarters it  is contended that the conditions of theexport trade,  coupled with foreign competition, are responsiblefor  the  disparities  which have arisen,                                                   /In
     In Appendix Table I details are given, so far as availableto the Ministry of Labour, of the percentage increases over pre-war rates of wages for a full ordinary week, at the endof 1920 and at the beginning of April, 1924, in aconsiderable number of industries, classified in 3 groups, viz.,(a) industries largely dependent on exports or largelyaffected by foreign competition (b) industries partlydependent on exports or partly affected by foreigncompetition and (c ) Industries not directly dependent on exports and not directly affected by foreign competition.This classification presents difficulties in certain casessince there is not, in practice, any clear line of demarcation between the different groups and certain industries might be classed in either of two groups,according to the view taken by the observer.  In the main,however, the classification may be regarded as sufficientlysound for purposes of broad comparison.     In the following Tsble the particulars given inAppendix I have been condensed, by arranging those industries,for which particulars of increases over pre-war wages areavailable, in groups so a3 to show the extent to which shelterfrom foreign competition was accompanied at 1st April, 1924,by a relatively high increase over pre-war rates of wages./Table
[sheltered&quot;  and^ &quot;Exposed&apos;&apos; &apos;InduBtries grouped according  to  theLant of Increase over Pre-V/ar Weekly Wage Rates at  1st April,  1924Sposed&quot;  Industries,Partly &quot;Exposed&quot; Industries&quot;Sheltered&quot; IndustriesCases of Increases in Wages  substantially above the Average.Sial ManufacturetextileBoot and ShoeBleaching, Dyeing,  &amp;c,Silk (Leek)Dock LabourFurnitureBasket Manufacture  (Lancashire)Saddlery and Harness                                                  Railway  Service                                                  Tobacco                                                  Brewing  (labourers)                                                  Printing and Book-                                                    binding                                                  Police                                                  Dyeing and  Cleaning                                                  Electricity Supply                                                  Tramways                                                   Local Authorities                                                    Non-Trading Services                                                    (Labourers).                                                  Building                                                  Electrical  Installa-                                                    tion,                                                  Gas Works                                                  Road Transport                                                  Baking.Cases of Increases&apos; in Wages  not  markedly different from the Average.iering  (Labourers)IngJilding (La boure r s) Manufacture -workers)lifacclesf ield)HosieryGold, Silver and  Electro PlateBespoke Tailoring  (London)Bespoke Bootmaking  (London)Cases of Increases in &quot;/ages  substantially below the AverageIture anuf act lire8-Workers)&apos;6n Manufacture . e Manufactureertng (SkilledKen)ilding (SkilledHen)anufactureat MakingCoal MiningPotteryIron MiningBasket Making  (London)     It will be seen from this  Table  that  in the  &quot;sheltered&quot;industries the increases over pre-war rates  of wages havebeen greater, on the whole, than  in the  industries which are most dependent on exports or largely  affected  by  foreign/competition,
competition, although in some of the &quot;largely exposed^9industries and in a considerable proportion of the&quot;partly exposed&quot; industries increases in wagesequivalent to, or greater than, the average for all industries have been obtained,  A calculation made from the further details given in Appendix I showsthat, in December, 1930, when the average increase over pre-war rates of wages was about 170 to 180 percent, the average increase in the &quot;sheltered&quot; trades and services was not appreciably greater than in tradesmost dependent on exports or most exposed to foreigncompetition.   In each group the average increase atthat date, among the trades included in Appendix I, appearsto have been about 170 per cent.   In April, 1924, however,the highest wage rates and the greatest percentages of increase over pre-war rates are to be found amongindustries which are neither dependent on exports nordirectly affected by foreign competitionj   the lowestwage rates and the smallest increases over pre-war rates,also, were in certain industries largely dependent on exports or affected by foreign competition.   The average increase, at 1st April,  1924,  in the &quot;sheltered&quot;, industries and services included In Appendix Table I was roughly100 per cent, over pre-war rates compared with little more-than 60 per cent. in.the industries which are to any considerable extent dependent on exports or affected by foreign competition.     The foregoing Table shows exceptional cases,however,which suggest that caution is necessary in drawinggeneral inferences from the data given.     For example, the increases in wages in the textilebleaching, dyeing and finishing industry are above thegeneral average for all trades, although a considerable                                            /part
part of the work of this industry is on goods forexport;  they are greater than those in the cottonmanufacturing industry, which is working on the sameproducts.   Again, the increases in wages In the Fooltextile industry are above the average, though this industry is to a considerable extent engaged in &quot;world trade&quot;, and are higher than in some Industries which are certainly not engaged in &quot;world trade&quot;.  In the coalmining industry, which is only partially dependent on world trade, (and in which the total exports in 1923 were greater than in 1913 and considerably greater than in 1911or 1912) the increases in wages are less than in various industries which are either more dependent on exports ormore affected by imports.   An examination of the Tablesin the Appendix will furnish other examples of wagedisparities not wholly explained by the conditions of export trade or by foreign competition, and considerationof the circumstances of individual industries appears to lead to the conclusion that in many cases special factorshave contributed to the discrepancies in wage rates.     For example, in the railway sorvice, and in someother industries in which pre-war rates of wages were relatively l*ow, the Increasing strength of the workmen&apos;organisations would probably have led in any case to increases in wages proportionately greater than in many other trades in which a higher level of wages had been attained before 1914.   In the mining industry and theiron and steel industries, in which prices have alwaystended to fluctuate more than the average, the longestablished practice of relating wages more closely anddirectly to selling prices than in other industries                                           &apos;.j                                            /would
would have continued to result in high wage lcvel3in time of prosperity and low wagos in time of depression.   The abnormal expansion of tho iron andsteol industry during the war is also a factor witha considerable bearing on the present conditions inthe industry.   The cotton industry has been affectedmuch more by the rise in the cost of raw cotton,resulting in  inability of customers - especiallyin the East - to buy its products, than by foreigncompetition.   The shipbuilding industry has been affected by the rise in the cost of raw materials, bythe large numbers of ships available after the war,and by the general diminution of demand for new ships.In the tinplate industry, in which wage rates are relatively low, the volume of exports is considerably greater than before the war.     It may also be noted as a point of some importance that in the public discussion, which has been proceeding,attention has been given almost wholly to the questionof nominal wage.rates, with little reference to tho statsof employment and the actual  earnings in the different industries,   In some of the &quot;exposed&quot; trades,includingengineering and shipbuilding, iron and steel manufacture,and the cotton industry, the state of employment iscertainly bad, and actual earnings, as well as nominalrates of wages, are relatively low.   On the other hand,in certain &quot;exposed&quot; trades in which nominal rates ofwages are relatively low, -e0g.., tinplate and steel sheetmanufacture, coal mining, and carpet manufacture,employment is good, and actual earnings are not so much                                           /below
below the general average for all industries as arethe nominal rates of wages.   Conversely, in some&quot;sheltered&quot; occupations in which wage rates are relatively high (e,g,,builders&apos;  labourers) the proportions unemployed are high, with the resultthat the average earnings of the whole group of work people are not so favourable as would appearfrom consideration of the nominal rates of wages alone.     While, therefore, the condition of foreign trademay explain some of the anomalies which are at presentapparent in the wage-levels of different industries,it would appear that many of the changes which havooccurred are the outcome of the operation of specialfactors, unconnected with exports or foreign competition,varying in their nature in the case-of different industries, and that the disparities which are atpresent apparent are not likely wholly to disappear(though some of them would no doubt be mpdified) evenif there should be a substantial revival of prosperityin the export trades.
APPENDIX - TABLE I.ftPPROXIliATE  INCREASE IN WAGES AT  1st APRIL,  1924,  AND AT 3lst DECEMBER, 1920,1                      OVER THE  LEVEL OF  AUGUST,  1914.[industry  andbupation.j Rates of  Wages for aI full week (unless otherwise specified).I Percentage  increase in Wages for a full week (unless  otherwise specified).r--.........1------t j 4th Aug. I  3lst Decj   1st  Apl,1914.1920.1934.31st Dec.1920.1st Apl,1984,Trades largely  dependent on JExports orj&quot;largely  affected by ForeignOompetition.       jItton Manufacture.lG6neraT&quot;Tnor eas ein list pricesSodlfled  to  allowlor the effect  ofSeductions inlour a of  labour).jlk manufacture. Less&quot;) Beavers  (Men)I/omen.laoclesfield - Power Loom I Weavers. thrown Silk (Winders, poublers etc.pa Manufacture.lottlngTiam.iplato^ Manufacture.: Wiles &amp; Mon.jlneerAverage  6T reccg-    time  rates1 18  large towns).matters &amp; Turners.ohmoulders.ltternmakers.ibourers.jrop Manuf aoture,  s. 58. 41.142. 22.  &apos;cHpaflson of^er-&apos;  iritag6 additions  1 oasis rates,  lowing for in-  sasee in such-&quot;la rates.)  &quot;isveland.  Il!mberland,   Wales &amp; Morit d.11. 8. 1.10.s.  d.89.92.93.70.2.3.5.8.B .d.56.  5-59.  1.60. 10.40.  3.160150220   102180 to 220 70 to 75/150 to 231 901157085 to 10550 /4812912112220945424576525 to 300500 to 350   124 *59 to 10655 to 73   25kis applies to higher paid men only.   For lower paid men the increase as greater.Edition list prices were  revised in some oases./iron
Rates of Wages for apull Week (unless otherwise specified).percentage increase in wages for a full week(unless otherwisespecified). .4th Aug.1914.3lat Deo.1920.lBt Apl.1924.Slat Dec.1920. .&quot;1&quot;let Apl.fj^r*j1924.   Vo v and Steel Smelting,ing  Hiaparlson of per-.tago additionsbasis ratos).f England (irondling and iron steel rolling).Iand3   do.tland (irondling andling).Ifalos &amp; Mon.m and steelling.)tland (steelling).ious distriotsieel smolting). Textile industry.uersj. increases,lading increasesnted in oompen-ten for reduood a of labour). ame workers.Piece workers.ical Manufacture,ocghTsad mThTZ rates.) Labourers.  (Proqess) bourara,llljleaching^B.L?rTntIh^&apos; and            : &amp;-of-living bonus in the oase of ahire, increases aais rates). ,ashire, Cheshire b(&quot;tland - lien, &quot;omen. hiro- 8 workers T s.  d.23.  0.35.  0. s.  d. 74. 5.107. 0.s.  d.47. 0.69. 0.is,  aPpiTes to hlgner  paid men only,  Po&apos;r lower paid  men the Increase&quot;a greater,th9 case of higher paid workers the incroases were not so great.  241  284  242  124 *  207159 to 206   216  /181 to  190/224207240 to  270approx,)160 to  200(approx.)   185   143  51  63  55  25  3727 to 5590 /80 y104 97(90 to 150( (approx,))85 to 100)(100 approx.9573     andloooupation.
Rates  of  Wages for apull Weok (unless otherwise specified,percentage InareaaoIn wages for  a  fullweek (unless  otherswise specified).4th Aug.1914,31st Deo.1920.1st Apl,1924.31st Dec.1920.1st Apl,1924.J-pet Manufacture.ijoit^oF-living&quot;Tohus,) Midlands  -  Time  workers.  piece &quot; It^Hat Making. jntch,  Hyde  and&quot; [strict - lime Workers. Sieoe  &quot;ipbuilding^jveTagTToT recog-Ised time rates  13 principalgntres).shipwrights,Kip Joiners.   .giatersELvetters.labourers.    Seaman. ireiaen, [culture. fdinafy  L&quot;ab our er s England  and Kaleo).160165 9510060555055 o.41.40.40.37.22. d. 4. 0. 4 9.10.  Per Month.100 ^to 110/jrf110/-to ISO//13s.to 21s, s. 91.101. 90. 87. 70.d.3.0.0.2.4.Per iionth.29o/- /300/- /46s.to 52s.s.4R.50.47.45.38.5.7,6.Per Month180/- /190/- $25s.to 35s.  1P4 /121152123131204176 /161 /1826lp196 P71 /65 /58 /Trades partly  dependent on Exports and partly affected by Foreign                        Competition,^^ManufactureNral increasesJlist prioes).LleiT Manufacture.  H-oF-LivlngI onus).[Midlands.Lining,erage earnings  manshiftked).rthumberland.      East Mid.noa.N.staffs.  Cheshire.Walea &amp; Mem. &quot;tland. 1 districts.pershTft..  &quot;37&apos;.   2..   3..   8.0.9.9.perShift.d.IB. 2.18. 2.IP, 3.17. 0.19. 8.19. 4,18-. 6.persh&quot;ff&apos;t.a. &quot;H.10, 7.10. 4.10. 7. B. 9. 9.11,10. 7.10. 1,180 //125EggsETft.19419217518419018718650 ft67pershift.71675944465758 fddition list prioes were  revised in some oases.Bh rates.Pwod Is provided in addition,   andI Occupation,
bdus try- anafjecupation.Hates  of Wages  for a         ^percentage  IncreasePull Week                     jin wages  for a full(unless otherwise            :week  (unless other-f?!2&apos;^2*L--_______     .  i*ise  specified)4th Aug.!  31st  Dao.:  1st Apliilst  De^7&quot;?lsFIpl&quot;&quot;1914     I  1980      ,  1924.   !1920       11924.h shoe Manufac tur 9ijflclial minimumbe rates  for  manu-Icturing prooesses),;[Hen -  heel-build-- i  ing  and stook  and  Shoe rooms    -  other de-  par tmentsIfomens. d.127.  0.s. d.S.  d .65. 0.   i 57.  0.127j111                  130. 0.                  !17s. &amp;                  I 18s.labour.to recognised)    &apos;per day. prinoipal ports)  ;General oar gofror22rs.pure  Manufactureforage of  recog-ped rates  in 17pge towns).Cabinet makersUpholsterers.French polishers;  4s,61.ito 6s.8d.68. 0.   i 60.  0.        141        10040. 0.   ; 36.  0.    122 to 135;i00 to 112per day, j par  day.                   I                   1169 (based\bb  (based15s.to   ! 10s.to  Ion average ion  average17a.61.  I 12s.61.  tof daily   iof  daily! rates).[per wk.I  s. d.I[39. 9.;38. 9.i 37. 1.per wk.  I per wk.   s.  1.&apos;102.  2.j102.  0.!102,  0 s. 1.73. 9.73. 6.73. 5.It vaklng. London Lancashirepry &amp;- HarnessTJJIT Midlands. Mining. Cleveland Cumberland157163175     97i170 to 180150     200&apos;200 to 300rates)85909845 to 5090 to 100100     4336 to 63
 Industry   and occupation.Rates of Wages for  aPull Week(unless otherwisespecified).4&quot;th Aug 1914.&quot;   Percentage IncreaseI&apos;  in wages for a fulll   week (unless other-j   wise specified)Slst Bee.) 1st &quot;Apr. &quot;1   Sis Fife c . I    TsTTpTT  1920.  !  1924.         1920.      .1924.   Ill, Trades not directly (dependent on Exports&apos;and not directly                affected  by IPorelgn Competition . i           :Building.lAvorage of reoog-nised time ratesin 40 large towns).  Bricklayers  Maeons  Carpenters and    Joiners  Plumbers  Plasterers  Painters  LabourersElectrical Installa-s. d.40 . 7I 39. 7tion. (Average of39 .1139. 840. 036 . 327. 0s.  d.100 .10101.  0100.  8102.  6100 .  8 99 .10 87.  8d.i 70 .  9-s171.  0*170 .  8&quot;,70 .  8*:711700&apos;-0*53. 2-::- reoognised time rates in 12 large towns).  Wiremen           iSold j  Si Ivor andITlled^ TrauTes. Percentage inoreaae ! for piece-workers.  !  London                 &quot;   iRailway Service . 0   &apos;14915513215815117622574SO777878939739. 4  j  104. 9   175. 616792l  Engine  drivers  Guards             !                    I  Ticket  Collectors I                    i  Goods Porters  i   \                    i  Passenger Porters &apos;.    (Olasa 2)       . \                 -  . I- SPl-Tr1 an s p o r t,.      ; (Average  of rocog-   ! nised rates in 12 towns)  One horse dri-      vers.39 a . to46 B .422s .to31s .23s . &amp;27 s.-19s ,to23s .18s ,toSOs . 88s .to106 s .4 72s. to. 82s .6d. 70s ,6d. to 78s. 66 s . toi 72s .6d. 65s,to 69s.  &quot;i72s.to;90s .4I50 s .to165s .54s,  CC58 s.47 s. to51s .46 s.  &amp;48 s.143126 to 1306085 to  95 166  to  &quot;27  piO  to 127           &apos; iI           &quot;ij178  to  220  I 115  to 135!S15  to  247  I 122  to 147i   m : b; ?  i: &apos;^  ,!245  to  272  j 140  to .15525s .7d.;  68s.5d,  i52s.4d.167104-------------.------1--------------.....?-----------a-----------j.------.....Por the purpose of this comparison  tho hours.of  labour at 1st April, 1924,  are takon as 44 per week.    It is  probable,  however, that in some districts the hours of labour in tho  summer poriod of 1924 will be 46i- and tho average hours for  tho year  will  therefore be slightly in excess of 44.The rates quoted for 1914 are the  approximate average rates of tho various grades, except for engine  drivers,  in wlfioh case tho figures represent the usual- range of wages? those  for 1920 and 1.924 are thei agreed, standard rates.Mileage payments&quot;wore made in addition to drivers of long-distance trains.
Rates of Wages forPull Seek(unless otherwisespecified)4th&quot;Iu &quot; &quot; 31st&quot;5eo&quot;1914     : 19201st simple.1924peroentage  increasein wages for a  fullweek (unless other-wi3e^s;pecif iedj31st :Deo&quot;&quot;&apos;&quot;lst&quot;.i.pir1920      ! 1924tayg. erage of recog-ised rates in 53wne) Drivers Conductors erage of recog- g$d rates in  6jvras) Hand Compositors on book or job- ting work Bookbinders and maohino rulersig.ferage of recog-LECCL rates in 13irge towns) Pore bands Table handsHon-on-Tront)Labourersoo.Kenafomenig and DryLabourersto TailoringEctonist snd)Class  1  Shops  II   3Made Bootmelon - West  End)arting  rates  ofy.  excludingobationexs&apos; rates)Constablesper wk.  ; per wk. s. d.   .  s. d.30. 6.26. 7.35, 8.33.11.! 37. 6,i 29. 9.23. 0.  21s.toj  30s.73. 3.68, 7.93, 5.93. 4.88. 2.00. 7.j 65. 0.75s.6d.to 84a.per wk, s. d.58. 5.53. 4,72. 9.73. 4.70. 4.62. 6.I56. 0,!  72s.140157 92101162176107117135170183 , 87110143    170       170!(aporox) i  (apprcx)    230       230i(approx) I  (approx)230100100100140SO8565180 to   260140 to 240  and occupation,
                    Ratos of Wages for a         Percentage Increase Industry           Full Week (unless other-     in wages&apos;for a full   and              wise specified).             week  (unless other-Occupation.                 ^____^__^   wise  specified) .                    4th&apos; AUGT. 31 st &quot;Deo. ist&quot;Apl.  31st  Dec&apos; 1st Apl.                     1914.    1930.     1924.     1920.      1924.tag Industry.           per week,  per week.  per woek.&quot;&quot;[Average  of &quot;rates in 44  large  towns).     a.d.     s.d.    s, d. Labourers              35.  8.    75.  0.   50. 9.     192       98leetricity Supply.(Average of rates in 57 large towns) . Labourers             26 . 5.    75.  5.    53. 6.      185       103goal AuthorityNon-Trading Sorvices) .Average of rates in36 large towns),                                  i Labourers             26.10,    75. 6.   52.  1.      181        94
AITEwDDTABLE II,AVERAGES .0F THE&apos; RECOGNISED TIKE RATES OF WAGES 0? VARIOUS  OCCUPATIONS IN TEH                   LARGE TOOTS AT APRIL, 1924.Skilled Men.AverageII eeklyFull-timeRates ofWages.Unskilled Labourers,!  Averagei  Weeklyj  Full-time  Rates of!  fapes. -ay Service - Engine Drivers rical Installation - Wiremen ting. - Compositors (Jobbing) binding - Bookbinders, &amp;c. jig, lio,,Engineering - Pipe tars            ,.,       .,t iture Manufacture - Cabinet Itors             ...       . wlsterers       ...       . onoh Polishers   ,..       , ling - Plasterers          ,    - Plumbers  ,,,       ,    - Masons    ...       ,    - Bricklayers         ,    - Carpenters and       Joiners  ...       , rioity Supply - Mechanical matters            ,,,       , iing - Painters  ...       , tricity Supply - Fitters and reirien            ,.,       ,  - Fore Hands  ,.,       , airing - Machinists       . wing - Coopers            , Silver and Allied Trades Hied Men        ,,,       , Milling - 1st Roller-men  . els Building - Bodymakers, ealyrrights       ...       , ; and Dry Cleaning - led Dyers      .,.       . Malting - Maohinemen      . engineering - Ircnmoulders     . and Shoe Manufacture - illod Men        ...       . tar Tanning - Skilled Ken Repairing - Ship Joiners  , fay Service - Guards eering - Fitters andfners            ...       ... Repairing - Shipwrights   ,.,building   - Ship Joiners  ,.,          - Shipwrights!  72s, toI  90s,*;  77s. 7d,!  76s. 7d,i  76s. 6d,j  74s. Bd,;  73s.lOd,I  73s.lOd.;  73s,lOd,I  72s. 3d,;  72s. 3d,j  72s, 3d,I  72s, 3d,I  72B, Id,]-  72s, Od,!  71s, 6d,i  70s.l0d,!  69s.lOd,!  69B. 4d.j  69s, Od,i  68s. 7d.i  68s, Od.,!  67s. 7d.  66s. Od.  66s. 3d.  60s. 2d.  60s, Od.  53s. to  65s.  57s.lOd.  50B. to  65s,  56s, 8d.  56s. 2d,  51s. 2d,  48e. 9d.r..............------ Took Labour      ...Jl  Civil  Engineeringjj Brewing;l Printing         ,..j! Tramways (Car Cleaners) ...*..Si Building         ....., Local Authority (Non-Tfading)   Service        ,.,     ... Electricity Supply       c Wool Textile  jj  .,,     ... Textile Bleaching,       ...   Dyeing, ete.   ...     ... Soap and Candle Making   ... Flour Milling    ,,,     ... Railway Service (Permanent  . Way Labourers) ...     ... Mill Saring      ...... Gas Works        ...     ... Dyeing, and Dry Cleaning  ... Railway Service (Goods   Porters)       ...     ,., Gold Silver and Allied*  Trades                 ... Electric Cable Making    ... Paint, Colour and   Varnish        ...     .., Leather Tanning  ...     ...;! Railway Service (Passen-&apos;;,   ger  Porters  Class  2).jj Chemical          t-i Paper  Making     .;i Vehicle Building ,jj Pottery jtf        ,ii Ship Repairingjj Engineeringij Shipbuilding     ,jj Iron and  Steel Manu-i!   facture,  $     .........i *. 61s,  Id, 68s,  3d, 58s,  Od, 57B,  7d./ 54s.  2d, to 58c.  4d, 54s,  6d, 64s,  5d, 53a,  5d, SHs,  3d, 62s.  2d. 52s.  Odi 52s.  Od. 51s.  8d. 61s.  8d, 51s.  2d, 51s.  0d; 50s.  6d, 49s.  5d, 45s.  and 60s,  5-fd, 43s.  Od, 42s. to 54a.  Od, 47s.  Od, 47s. Od., 4Ss.  9d. 43s. 4d. 42s,  6d. 42s. 5d.40s, 4d.38s.lOd.37s. Id, Mileage payments are made in addition to  drivers  of long distance trains. The rate quoted in this case is that agreed upon  for the principal centres of the  industry,&apos;-verage of the recognised rates in 5 of  the principal districts.This rate applies to general assistants  employed mainly as machine feeders.  In some oases lower rates are paid to warehouse porters,  etc.     1:KOTEj-  The ten lores towns  noludod era London, Glasgow, Liverpool,  Manchester,        Birmlngh*m8 Bristol, Sheffield, Le^sds, Hull and Newcastle,

</content>
</cab>
