<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 1049-1070</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINET.RET.&quot;g&amp;S (24j.        Nationalisation of. Mines ang Minerals Bill.&apos;if               -  Note by the President of the Board of Trade,              I circulate to my colleagues a memorandum by the         Secretary for Mines on the attitude to be adopted by the         Government towards the above Bill, which will come up for         Second Reading on Friday, 16th May.              It should, perhaps, be made clear that, If the         Bill receives a Second Reading (which seems unlikely)         no undertaking can he given that time can he found this .         Session for subsequent stages,                                               S .W.         poard of Trade,              -7/5/24.5 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMEMT.
                                                  -   &apos;        I                                                       7! j   i                                                              i         Nationalisation  of Mines and Minerals Bill.                                                              ! I               Memorandum by Secretary for Mines.     The Bill  introduced  by Mr., George Hall under this                                                              rtitle, which will come up for  Sesond Reading on the 16thMay, does not  differ materially from the Bill put beforethe Sankey Commission by  the Miners1 Federations  Subject tothe approval of the Cabinet, I propose to take the following  Iline in announcing the Government&apos;s attitude towards it.     I suggest that I should accept unreservedly the principleof the nationalisation of mines and minerals, should avoid committing the Government to accepting in detail the mannerin which this Bill proposes to carry that polioy into effect,and should point out that political exigencies make itimpossible for the Government to undertake the task of               mlegislating on this subject at the present time*     In these  circumstances it does not seem necessary toexamine the provisions of the Bill too closely,:  Criticism(apart from criticism of  the principle of nationalisation)is likely to centre mainly round two pointsc  On one ofthese I propose to range  myself with the criticsj  on theother to say nothing.    v    The first  is that, although the Bill proposes  that theGovernment should pay compensation to the colliery ownerswhose collieries they acquire, it does not provide for theGovernment&apos;s paying a penny to the royalty owners  whose coalthey acquire,  I suggest  that I should say that the Governmenthave under consideration  the question of introducing a Billto acquire the property in coal royalties for the  State;  butthat, if they do so, it will not be, as this Bill  is,  ona purely confiscatory basis,  I would also emphasise&apos; thevalue of nationalisation  of royalties as a 3tep towards                             -1-
nationalisation of mineB, and the importance of proceeding by stages in making changes of this magnitude,     The second main criticism that is likely to bemade is that the Bill provides for too little control by Parliament and too much control by &quot;the associationknown as the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain&quot;, who,to the exclusion of all other associations of mine-workers and without any guarantee of the Maintenance of their representative character, are to nominate half theMining Council, and, at the same time, to preserve their full Trade,Union rights vis a vis that council  But Ithink it neither necessary nor politic that I should say anything about the criticisms that will no doubt hefreely made on this point.  It will be sufficient if,while accepting the principle of the Bill, I carefullyrefrain from committing the Government to approval ofits details.     As the Eill is a Private Members Bill, there cannotof course, in the circumstances, be any question of putting the Whips on in the Division.,                                (Sgd0) E. Shinwell.
Nationalisation  of Mines  and            Minerals  Bill.ARRANGEMENT OP CLAUSES.Clauso.1,  Establishment of Mining Council.2.  Minister of Mines and Parliamentary Secretary.3.  Officers, &amp;c.I.  Constitution of Mining Council.5.  Transference  of mines and minerals to  Mining      Council.6.  Purchase of mines.7.  Mines Commissioners.8.  Valuation of mines.9.  Ascertainment of purchase price.10.  Issue of State mines stock.11.  Powers of Mining Council.12.  District mining  councils and pit councils.13.  Fuel consumers&apos; council and advisory conference.14.  Payment of Mining Council&quot;&apos;and district  mining       committees  and pit councils.15.  Accounts.16.  Transference of  existing assets and liabilities.17.  Payments out of moneys provided by Parliament.18.  Payment out of consolidated fund.19.  Regulations.20.  Statutory regulations to apply to the Crown.21.  Duty of mining  council to supply fuel.22.  Partial repeal of Mining Industry Act,  1920.23.  Title and commencement.   SCHEDULES.   V
                         A               BILL                        to nationalise the Mines  and  Minerals   of  Great  A.D. 1924.  Britain, and to provide for the national winning,     -   distribution, and sale of coal and other minerals,  and for other purposes connected therewith.     7 HEREAS it is  expedient that mines and minerals        should be taken into the possession of the State :      Be  it  therefore enacted  by the  King&apos;s  most  Excellent  Majesty,  by  and  with  the  advice  and 5 consent  of  the Lords  Spiritual  and Temporal,  and  Commons, in this present Parliament &quot;assembled, and by  the authority of the same, as follows :       1. (1) For  the  purpose of winning,  distributing, Establish-  selling and searching for coal and other minerals, there meat of10 shall be established by His Majesty by warrant under the Mining  sign manual, a Mining Council, consisting of a President Council.  and twenty members, ten of whom shall be  appointed  by His Majesty and ten  by the association known as&quot;the  Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain.15     (2) It shall be lawful for His Majesty, from time to  time,  to appoint any  member of the Privy Council to be  President of the Mining  Council, under the  name of the.  Minister of Mines, to hold office.during His Majesty&apos;s  pleasure.             *20     (3) The members of the Mining Council, other  than  the President, shall be appointed for five years, but shall  be  eligible  for  re-appointment;  Provided  that His
           2            Nationalisation of Mines and  [14 GEO. 5.]                                 Minerals. AD. 1924.  Majesty or the association known as the Miners&apos; Federa-           tion  of Great Britain respectively shall  have power to           remove any person appointed by them and appoint some           other person in his place.  On a casual vacancy occurring           by reason of the death  or resignation of  any such 5           members  or   otherwise,  His Majesty orthe Miners&apos;           Federation of Great Britain, as  the  case may be, shall  &apos;           appoint some other person to fill the vacancy, who shall           continue in office until the  member in whose place  lie           was appointed should have retired, and shall then  retire. 10           The  members of  the  Mining Council shall devote  the           whole of their time to the business of the Mining Council.               2. (1) The Minister of  Mines and one of the secre-           taries of the Mining Council  (to  be known as the Parlia-           mentary Secretary, and to be appointed by  His Majesty) 15           and the members of the Mining Council  shall at the same           time be capable of being elected to and of sitting in the           Commons  House of Parliament.                         j               (2) The  Minister  of Mines  shall take  the oath of           allegiance  and official  oath,  and shall be deemed to be 20j           included  in  the  First Part of the. Schedule to  the           Promissory Oaths Act, 1868.               (3) There shall be paid out of  money provided by           Parliament to  the Minister of Mines a salary at the rate           of two thousand pounds a year, and to the Parliamentary 25           Secretary a salary at the rate of one thousand five hundred           pounds a year.               (4) The  Minister  of Mines  and  the Parliamentary           Secretary shall be  responsible to Parliament for the acts           of the Mining Council.                                30Officers, &amp;o.      3. (1) The Mining Council  shall appoint a secretary           (to be known as  the permanent  secretary),  and such           assistant  secretaries and officers and  servants as the           Mining Council may,&apos;with the sanction of the Treasury,  j           determine.                                           35               (2) Subject to the provisions of subsection (2) of section           eleven of this Act, there shall be paid  out of money provided  j           by Parliament to the permanent secretary, assistant secretaries           and other officers and servants such salaries, or  remuneration. :           &apos;as the Treasury shall from time to time determine.        D)               (3) There shall be transferred and attached to the  .           Alining Council such of the persons employed under any           Government  department or local authority in or  about  .           the  execution of the  powers and duties  transferred  by  ,Minister of mines andParliamen-tary Secre-tary.
     or in pursuance of tins Act to the Mining  Council  as  A.D.1924.     the Mining Council and the Government department  or     local authority may, with  the sanction of the Treasury,     determine..g   5    (4) Notwithstanding anything in any Act, order  or  :   regulation,  any society of  workers, all or some of whose     members are wholly or partly employed in or about mines,     or in any  other manner  employed  by the Minister  of     Mines, or  the  Mning Council,  or by a  district miningIQ 10 council or pit council, or otherwise under this Act,  may     be registered or  constitute themselves  to  be a trade     union, and may do anything individually or in combina-     tion which the members  of a trade, union or a trade     union may lawfully do: Provided further that notwitb-   15 standing any Act, order,  or regulation to the contrary,15   it shall  be lawful for any person employed under this  1   Act to participate in any  civil or political action in like  I 1  manner,  as if such person were not employed by His     Majesty, or by any authority on his behalf :   20     Provided, further, that no such&quot;person  shall suffer2&quot;   dismissal or any deprivation of any kind as a consequence     of any political or industrial action, not directly forbidden     by the terms of his employment, or as a consequence of     participation in a strike or trade dispute.25 25     4. (1) The Mining Council shall be a  corporation  Constitu-     to be known by the name of the Mining Council  and by  tionof     that  name  shall  have  perpetual succession, and  may  \   acquire  and hold land without licence in mortmain.        &apos;01&quot;1U &apos;  I       (2)  The Mning Council shall have  an official seal,30 30 which shall be officially and publicly noticed, and such     seal shall be authenticated by the Mining Council or a     secretary  or one  of  the  assistant secretaries, or  some     person authorised to act oi^ their behalf.         (3)  The Mining Council may sue and be sued without35 35 further description under that title.         (4)  Every document  purporting  to  be an order,  \   licence,  or other instrument issued by the Mining  Council     and to be sealed with their seal, authenticated in manner     provided by this Act, or to be signed by a secretary  or by40 40 one of the assistant secretaries, or any person authorised     to act, shall be received in evidence and be deemed  to be  \   such order, licence, or other instrument without further  I   proof unless the contrary is shown. ,         [13]                  A 3
              &quot;(5) Any  person having  authority in that  behalf,           either  general or special, under the  seal of  the  Mining           Council may, on behalf of the Mining Council, give any           notice or make any claim,  demand,  entry,  or distress,           which the Mining  Council in its corporate capacity  or 5           otherwise might give or make,  and  every such  notice,           claim, demand, entry, and distress shall be deemed  to           have been given and made by the Mining Council,               (6) Every deed, instrument, bill, cheque, receipt  or           other document, made or executed for the purpose of the 10           Mining Council by, to, or with the Mining Council, or any           officer of the Mining Council, shall be exempt from any           stamp duty imposed by any Act, past or future, except           where that duty is declared by the document, or by some           memorandum  endorsed thereon, to be payable by some 15           person other than the Mining Council, and except so far           as any future Act specifically charges the duty.Transfer-        5. (1)  On and after  the appointed  day, save  asence of      in subsection (3) of this section provided, mines andminerals to      (a) every  colliery  and  mine (including all  mines, 20Mining              quarries and open workings of ironstone, shale,Council.             fireclay and limestone,  and  every  other mine                   regulated under the Metalliferous Mines Regula-                   tion Acts,  1872  and 1875,  but not including                   mines, quarries or open workings of minerals 25                   specified  in the  First  Schedule to this Act),                   whether  in actual work,  or discontinued,  or                   exhausted,  or abandoned, and every shaft, pit,                   borehole, level,  or inclined  plane,  whether  in                   course of being made or driven for commencing 30                   or opening any such colliery or mine, or other-                   wise,  and  all associated properties  (including                   vessels, lighters, railway rolling  stock, and  all                   works, including works for the manufacture of                   byeproducts,  in  the opinion  of  the  Mining 35                   Council reasonably ancillary and belonging  to                   any  mine undertaking  or connected with any                   colliery or  mine, and every house belonging  to                   the owners of any such colliery or mine,  which,                   in the opinion of the Mining Council, is usually 40                   occupied by workmen employed at such colliery                   or mine) (all of which are  herein included  in                   the expression &quot; mine &quot;); andA.D. 1924!
8730(6) all coal, anthracite, lignite, ironstone,  shale,  A.D. 1924.    fireclay, limestone,  or other mineral, excepting         the minerals specified in the First  Schedule to    this  Act, whether  at present being worked or    not  worked,  or connected or  not connected    with  any  mine beneath  the  surface of  the    ground (all of which are herein included in the    expression &quot; minerals &quot;); and(c) all rights and easements  arising out  of or neces-    sary to the working of any  mine or  the winning    of any mineral,  including all mineral wayleaves,    whether air-leaves  or water-leaves,  or rights to    use a shaft, or ventilation or drainage, or other    royalties,  lordships, or  rights  in   connection    therewith,  whether  above or below the ground    (all of which are herein included in the expressionJshall be transferred to, vested in and held by the MiningICouncil in  their corporate  capacity in  perpetuity, andIsliall for all purposes be deemed to be royal mines, and that minerals and rights thereof respectivelyiI   (2)  The Acts contained in  the Second  Schedule  toI this Act are hereby repealed.I   (3)  Provided that the  Mining Council may at anyItime before the appointed day give notice in writing toIthe owner of, or person interested in, any mine or mineralslor rights,  disclaiming,  during  the period of  such dis-jclaimer, all or part  of  the property in such mine  or[minerals or rights to the extent specified in the notice, and thereafter such mine or minerals  or rights shall, until such time as the Mining Council shall  otherwise determine, to the  extent  specified in such notice, not  vest  in the Mining  Council as  provided  by subsection  (1) of this section: Provided that in such case it shall not be lawful for any person other than the Mining Council, without the permission of the Mining Council, to work or use such mine or minerals in any way: Provided further that on the termination of such disclaimer by the Mining Council, such mine  or  minerals or rights shall, to the  extent  of such notice, as from such date as the notice  may pre- scribe,  vest in the  Mining Council as if  such  notice  of (iisclanner had not been  given.              .rights &quot;);[13]A 4
          6             Nationalisation of Mines and.  [14 GEO,  5.]                                 Minerals. A.TX 1924.      (4) In the event of the Mining Council disclaiming all         or part of any property as in subsection (3) of this section          provided, and in the event of the Mining Council witholding          permission from any person otherwise entitled to work such          mine or minerals, to work or use such mine or minerals,          the  Mining Council may refer the question of compensation          of such person to  the Mines  Commissioners and, on their          recommendation, may.pay an annual grant to such person          for  such  times  and of such amounts as may seem to  the          Mining Council expedient, the cost of which grant shall be          charged on the Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom.Purchase        6. The Mining Council  shall  purchase the  mines ofoi mines.   Great Britain in them vested by this  Act (other than          those which are the property of the Crown at  the time          of the passing of this Act or which have been disclaimed          in whole  or in part in accordance with subsection (3) of          section five of this Act)  at the price and in the manner          provided by this Act: Provided always  that the value of          any rights as defined by paragraph (c) of subsection (1)          of section five of this  Act shall not be taken into account          in.  computing  such  price,  for  which  no compensation          shall be paid.Mines Com-      7 -(1) For the  purpose of assessing  the  purchasemissioners.  price  of  mines it shall  be lawful for His Majesty, by          warrants under the sign manual,  to appoint ten  Com-          missioners, to  be styled the Mines Purchase  Commis-          sioners (herein called &quot; the  Commissioners &quot;),  of whom          one, appointed by His Majesty, shall be chairman.               (2)  Three of the  said Commissioners shall be nominate-          ated by the association known as  the Miners&apos; Federation          of  Great  Britain, and three by the association known          as the Mining Association of Great  Britain.               (3)  At  the expiration of twelve months from  the          passing  of this Act,  in  the  event of a majority of  the          Commissioners failing to  agree as to the purchase price          of  a particular mine or of  its  associated properties, it          shall  be lawful for the chairman himself to fix the pur-          chase price of such mine,  which  price shall then he          deemed to be the. price fixed by the Commissioners, but,          save as herein expressly provided, the finding of a majority          of  the Commissioners voting on  any question or as to          the purchase price of rnines  shall be final and conclusive           and binding on all parties.
       (4)  It shall be lawful for His Majesty to remove any  A.D. 1924.   Commissioner for inability or misbehaviour.   Every order         of removal shall state the reasons for which it is made,   and no such order shall come into operation until it has 5 lain before the Houses  of Parliament for not less than   thirty days while Parliament is sitting.       (5)  The  Commissioners  may appoint and  employ   such assessors, accountants, surveyors, valuers,  clerks,   messengers, and other persons required for the due per- 10 formance of their duties as  the Treasury on the recom-   mendation of the Commissioners may sanction.       (6)  There shall be paid to the Commissioners  and to   each  of the  persons appointed  or  employed  under this   section  such salary or remuneration as the  Treasury may ]5 sanction ;  and all such salaries and remuneration and the   expenses of the Commission incurred in the execution of   their  duties, to such amount  as may be  sanctioned by the   Treasury, shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parlia-   ment.   . .                                  : 20     8. (1) The Commissioners shall, as soon as may be  Valuation   after the passing of this Act, cause a valuation to be  of mines.   made of all mines other than those disclaimed, whether   or not developed or working or abandoned or exhausted, in   Great Britain, showing what on the fourth day of August,. 25 nineteen hundred and fourteen, and what at the date of the   passing of this Act was respectively the total ascertained   value of each mine and  its associated properties, and the   rights,  as defined by paragraph (c)  of subsection (1)  of   section five  of this  Act, therein, and the total ascer- 30 tained value  of such mine and its  associated properties   respectively exclusive of such rights; and the owner  of   every mine and any person receiving any rents, interest,   or profit from any mine  or possessed of any rights therein   or connected  therewith, on  being required by notice by35 the Commissioners, shall furnish to  the Commissioners a   return containing such particulars as the Commissioners   may require as to his property, rent, interest, profits, or   rights in such mine.       (2) The Commissioners may likewise cause any mine40 to be inspected, require the production of  documents,   or do any other thing which rfltay,  in their  opinion, be   necessary to fix the purchase  price of the  mine or its   associated properties.
 A. D. 1024.      (3) The Commissioners in making  such valuation        shall have  regard to returns  made under any statute          imposing  duties or taxes or other obligations in respect          of mines, or minerals or rights, and to any information          given  before or  to any  Commission  or Government 5          department, including the  Coal  Industry Commission          constituted under the Coal Industry Commission  Act,          1919.Ascertain-       9. (1) The purchase  price of  mines, exclusive ofment of    associated properties (other than mines in the possession 10purchase   0  tne Qj.own a^ the time of the passing of this Act, shall          be computed subject to the provisions of subsections (2)          and  (3) of this section by ascertaining the average annual          number of tons of minerals actually raised during the five          years preceding the fourth day of August, nineteen hundred 15          and  fourteen:               Provided that, as regards coal mines, in no case shall          the  maximum purchase price, exclusive of  associated          properties, be taken to be more than the following :                                                       s.   d.     20               When 100,000  tons or less have been                raised  per annum   on  the  average                during such  five preceding  years,  a                capital sum equal to one such year&apos;s                output at......12  .0     25                                                    per ton.               When  more  than  100,000  tons have                been raised per annum on the average                during such  five preceding  years,  a                capital sum equal to one such year&apos;s            30                output at  -     -     -    -    -    -  10  0                                                     per ton,               (2) The Commissioners in arriving at such compu-          tation shall also have regard to the  actual gross and net          profits which have been made in the mine during such 35          years or thereafter and to  the  amounts which may have         . been set aside  from  time to  time for  depreciation,          renewals,  or development,  and to the probable  duration          of the life of the mine, and to the nature and condition          of such mine, and to the state of repairs  thereof, and to 40          the assets and. liabilities of any  mine undertaking existing          at the time of  purchase which are  transferable  to  the          Mining Council under section sixteen of this Act.
  [14 GEO. 5.]  Nationalisation of Mines arid              9                        Minerals.      (3) Provided further that where a coal mine, in the  A.D. 1924.  opinion  of the Commissioners, has  not been fully de-        developed, the  amount which would  be raised under full  development without any increase of capital expenditure  shall be taken as the average annual number of tons raised,  and the maximum purchase price in such case shall be  taken to be a capital sum equal to the product of such  number  of tons and twelve shillings or ten shillings per  ton  respectively,  for  the  purpose  of ascertaining the  maximum  value  per ton  under subsection (1) of this  section.                  -     -      10. (1) The purchase price of any mine and such  Issue of  of Us associated  properties as have been purchased, as  State mines  ascertained under  the provisions of this  Act,  shall be paid  stooli- 5 by the Mining Council  in mines  purchase stock to the  persons who, in the opinion of the Mining Council, have  established  their  title to such stock:  Provided that an  appeal shall lie to  the High  Court, under Rules to be framed  by the High Court, from the decision of the Mining Council  as to the title of any such persons, but for no other purpose.      (2) For the purpose of paying such purchase price the  Treasury shall,  on the request of the Mining Council, by  warrant  addressed to the  Bank  of  England,  direct  the  creation of a new capital stock (to be called  &quot; Guaranteed!5 State Mines Stock &quot;), and  in  this Act referred to as &quot; the  stock,&quot; yielding interest at the  rate on the nominal amount  of capital  equal to that payable at the date on which this  Act received Royal Assent  on  what,  in  the opinion of the  Treasury,  is  the nearest   equivalent  Government Loan10 Stock. -      (3) Interest shall be payable by equal  half-yearly  or  quarterly dividends at such times in each year as may  be  fixed by the warrant first creating the stock.      (4) The stock shall  be redeemed  at the rate of one15 hundred pounds sterling for every one hundred  pounds  of  stock at such times and by  such drawings as  the Treasury,  on the recommendations of the  Mining Council, may think  fit.      (5) The stock may be issued at such times and in such  amounts and subject to such conditions as the Treasury may  direct, and may be issued  as  bearer  bonds  with quarterly  or half-yearly interest coupons  attached.      (6)  The stock shall  be  transferable  in the books of the  Bank of England in like manner as other stock is transferable45 under the National Debt Act, 1870.
10[14 GEO. 5.] AJD.1924.      11.-(1) Subject to. the provisions of this Act, it          shall bo lawful for the Mining Council to open and workPowers of   mjnes an(j search for,  dig, bore, win and  deal  withCouncil      minerals and  generally to  carry on  the  industry of           mining,  distributing,  vending,  and exporting, together 5           with all other  industries  carried  on  in  connection           therewith:  Provided  that it shall not be lawful for the           Mining Council to lease or sell any mine or minerals or           rights to any person,  association, or corporation.               (2)  The Mining  Council&apos;may, from  time to time, 10           in such manner and on such terms as-they think fit                (a)  subject to the general  consent  of  the Treasury,                   appoint or continue in employment  or dismiss                   managers, engineers, agents, clerks, workmen,                   servants and other persons;  and              15               (b)  construct,  erect or purchase, lease, or otherwise                   acquire buuclings,  plant, machinery,  railways,           ;-.       tramways, hulks,  ships and other  fixed  or                   moveable appliances  or works of any descrip-                   tion, and sell or otherwise dispose of the  same 20                   when no longer required; and               (c)  sell, supply,   and deliver fuel, coal and other                   products, the result of mining operations, either                   within or without Great Britain; and               (d)  enter  into and enforce contracts and engage-21                   ments; and             -  (e)  generally  do  anything that  the owner of  a                   mine.might  lawfully do in the working of tho                   mine, or that is authorised by regulations under                   or by this or any other Act; and              3               (/).  employ local  authorities for any  purpose they                   may think necessary to  carry out their duties                   under this Act, on such terms as may be mutually                   agreed; and               (g)  regulate  the  export of fuel  and the supply  of 3                   coal for  the  bunkering of vessels; and regulate                   the price  of  fuel to be charged for coal sold for                   consumption,  at   the  pithead   or  otherwise,                   within or without Great Britain; and               (A)  give such directions as  to wages or salaries to be                   paid to workers in of  about coal mines as may                   be expedient to carry out the provisions of this                   or any other Act:               (3)  In addition  to the powers  conferred  on the           Mining  Council by  the last preceding  subsection, the ii
 Mining Council may, in such  manner as they think fit, .AJD. 1924. work any railway, tramway, hulk, ship or other appliance       for the purpose of winning, supplying and delivering coal or other products.g    (4) The Mming Council may compulsorily  purchase land or  acquire  such  rights over  land  as  they may require for the purpose of this Act, and shall have, with regard  to the&quot; compulsory purchase  of&apos; land,  all the powers of purchasers acting under the Land Clauses Act,0 1845,  and the Land  Clauses Consolidation (Scotland) Aot, 1845, or any other Act giving power to acquire land compulsorily  for  public  purposes,   which  may hereafter be enacted.       -     (5) With respect to any such purchase of land under the Land Clauses Acts or the Acquisition of  Land (Assess- ment of Compensation) Act,  1919, in Great Britain the following provisions shall have effect (that is to say):      (a) The Land Clauses Acts shall  be  incorporated         with this Act, except the provisions relating to0      &apos;  access to the  special Act,  and in construing         those Acts for the purposes  of this section &quot;the         special Act &quot;  shall be  construed  to mean this         Act, and &quot; the promoters of the undertaking &quot;         shall be construed to mean  the Mining Council,5        and &quot; land &quot;  shall be  construed  to have the         meaning given to it by this  Act.     (&amp;) The bond required by section eighty-five of the         Lands Clauses  Consolidation  Act, 1845, and         by  section  eighty-four of  the Lands ClausesI)        Consolidation (Scotland) Act, &quot;1845,  shall  be         under the seal of the Mining Council, and shall         be sufficient without  sureties.     12. (1) The Mning Council shall, for the purpose District of the carrying  on  and  development  of the mining mining5 industry,  divide Great  Britain  into districts, and shall councils in each district constitute a district milling council of  jjFj* ten members,  half of which shall be  appointed by the counci - Miners&apos;Federation of Great Britain.     (2) The Mining Council may delegate to any district0 mining council or pit council,  such of their powers under this Act  as  may conveniently be exercised locally, and the district  mining council shall upon such delegation have and  exercise withiniheir district all the powers and duties  of  the  Mining  Council as may be  delegated to5 them.
A.D. 1924.Fuel eon-sumers&apos;council andadvisoryconference.Payment ofMiningCouncil anddistrictmining com-mittees andpit councils.Accounts.    (3) A&apos; district  mining council shall, subject to theapproval of the Mining Council, have power within their area to appoint pit councils for each mine  or  group of mines, composed of ten members, half of which shallbe members of the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain,and nominated by  the workers of the mine  or groups of mines aforesaid, and the .district mining  council maydelegate to such pit council such of their  powers con-cerning the immediate working or management of aparticular mine or group of mines as the district miningcouncil may,  subject to  the  approval  of  the  MiningCouncil, think fit.    (4) The members of  the district mining councilsshall be appointed for three years, but shall be eligible forre-appointment, and the  members of  the  pit councilsshall  be appointed for  one year, but shall be  eligiblefor re-appointment.    13. (1)  For the  purpose of advising  the MiningCouncil it shall be lawful for His Majesty to appointpersons to represent the interests of  consumers, to be known as the fuel consumers&apos; council.    (2) The Mining Council shall have power to convokeat such time  as they think fit, and under  such regula-tions   and conditions as  they may prescribe, advisoryconferences of representatives of district mining councils,and the district mining councils shall  have  power  inlike manner to  convoke  advisory  conferences  of  pitcouncils within their area.    (3) The expenses of  the fuel  consumers&apos; council,national and district  mining conferences shall, subject 3(to the approval of the Treasury, be paid by the MiningCouncil.     14. There  shall he paid  to each of the members ofthe  Mining  Council,  other  than  the  President,  suchsalary  as  the  Treasury  may  determine,  and to  themembers of the district mining councils, and  to the pitcouncils, such  salaries and emoluments as  the  MiningCouncil, with the consent of the Treasury, may determine.     15.-(1) The  Mining Council  shall cause full andfaithful accounts to be kept of all moneys received and 4expended under this Act,  and of all assets and liabilitiesand of all profits and losses, and shall annually lay suchaccounts before Parliament.     (2) The  Mining  Council  shall  annually  cause  a balance sheet of accounts  to be made, including a capital 4
13734   account  and a  profit and  loss account for each mine A.D. 1924.   worked under this Act.       (3) Such  balance sheet and  statement shall  be  so   prepared as to show fully and  faithfully the financial 5 position  of each such mine  and the financial result of  its   operations for the year.       (4) All moneys raised  under the  authority of this   Act shall, as and when raised,  and  all other moneys   received  hereunder shall, as and when received, be paid10 into  a separate account called  &quot; the National  Mines   Account.&quot;       (5) All moneys  withdrawn from  the National  Mines   Account  constituted under  this Act  shall be withdrawn   only by  the order of the Mining Council or such other15 person as the  Mning Council may  from time to time   appoint.       (6) All moneys in the National Mines  Account,  or   payable  into that account  by any person whomsoever,   and also all moneys  owing by any person under this Act,20 are hereby declared to be the property of the Crown, and   recoverable accordingly as from debtors to the Crown.       16.-(1) There shall be transferred  to the Mining   Council all the existing assets and nubilities of mine under-   takings and associated properties, as and when they are25 transferred to  and vested in the Mining Council, other   than liabifities for rights, including royalty rents,  way-   leave rents, or any  other underground rents or charges,   payable  or due at the time of the passing of this Act to   any person, all of which shall cease to be payable on and30 after the appointed day.       (2)  On the passing  of this Act, there shall be ascer-   tained by the  Commissioners the amount of all moneys   due to or from all mine undertakings,  and the findings   of the Commissioners as to the amount of such moneys35 shall be  binding and conclusive on all parties.       (3) The net amount of all moneys due to any mine   undertaking, after all debts due  from any such under-   taking have beenv deducted, including moneys reserved   on account of depreciation or for other purposes and40 fixed mining assets, as  ascertained under subsection  (2)   of this section, shall be  paid by  the Mining Council  to   the  persons to  whom in  the opinion  of the Commis-   sioners such debts are due,  and  shall be  deemed  to  beTransfer-once ofexistingassets and liabilities.
14[14 GEO.  5.]A.D. 1924.  expenses incurred  under this Act: * Provided that  an   -     appeal shall  he to  the High  Courty  under rules to be          framed by the High Court, from the decision of the Com-          missioners as to the title of any such person, but for no          other purpose.   &apos;    &quot;   \     -  &apos;Paymentsout of moneys pro-vided byParliament.Paymentout of Con-solidatedFund.Regula-tions.     17. (1) All sums expended or payable under this Actin.carrying out the provisions of this Act for expenses, or forsalaries or wages payable under this Act, or in theconstruc-tion, erection or acquisition of buildings, plant,  machinery,railways,  tramways, hulks,  ships, or other -appliances or 1Cworks, or otherwise, shall  be  payable out of the moneys provided by Parliament.     (2) Provided that moneys received under  this Act inrespect of the sale or export or supply of coal or otherminerals (including the moneys received from the Govern- 15ment  departments) may  be  directly  expended  in ortowards carrying out the purposes of this Act.     18. After full provision has  been made for all  out-goings, losses, and habihties  for  the  year  (includinginterest  on  securities  created and issued in  respect of 20moneys raised as aforesaid, and on moneys paid  out ofthe  Consolidated Fund),  the net  surplus  profits thenremaining shall be applied in establishing a  sinking fund and, subject thereto, in establishing a depreciation fund,in respect of capital expended.                           -3     19. (1) The  Mining  Council  may from time totime make such regulations as they think necessary forany of the following purposes:-     (a) The management of  mines under this Act;     (b) The functions, duties, and powers of the district         mining councils, pit councils, and other bodies or         persons acting in the management and working         of mines or distribution and sale of fuel under         this Act;     (c) The form  of  the  accounts  to be kept and the 35         balance sheets to be prepared in respect of mines         under this Act;     (d) The mode to which the smking funds and other         funds connected with mines under this Act shall         be  held and  administered;                    40     (e) Generally  any other purpose  for which, in the       &quot; opinion of the Mining Council,  regulations are         contemplated or required..   v
   [14 GEO. 5.]  Nationalisation of Mines and            15                         Minerals.                                        7 1 ^       (2) The  Mining Council,  before  making  or  altering A.D.1924.   any regulations or conditions of employment, mcluding   wages, as affect any persons engaged in the management   of the mining industry or workmen engaged in the mining 5 industry,  shall consult  with the  association known  as   the Miners&apos;  Federation of  Great  Britain,  and, in the   event of such  representatives and the Mining  Council   failing to agree, the matter in dispute may  be  referred   to arbitration on such terms as may be mutually  agreed.10    (3)  Provided that  nothing in  this section  shall  be   deemed to interfere  with the right  of  any employed   person,  subject to  his contractual obligations, to dispose   of his labour  as he  wills.      20. (1) Every mine worked under this Act  shall  be Statutory15 managed and worked subject to the provisions of the regulations   Metalliferous  Mines Regulations  Acts, 1872  and  1875, ^Orown0   the Coal Mines Regulation Act, 1908, the Coal Mines   Acts, 1911  and 1919, and any other  Act regulating the   hours, wages,  or  conditions  of  labour  (including the   appointment  and functions of  check weighers) in  mines.      (2)  There shall be transferred to and be  vested in the   Mining Council  all the powers and duties of  the Board of   Trade and the Mines Department  and of  any  other   Government  department  imposed  upon  them  by the25  Metalliferous  Mines Regulations  Acts, 1872  and &quot;l875,   the Coal Mines Regulation Act, 1908, the Coal Mines   Acts,  1911  and 1919, or any other  Act  regulating  or   affecting mines  or the hours or  conditions of labour  therein.SO     (3)  This  section shall  apply to  the Crown, and  in all  Acts in which mines are owned or worked  by the Crown,  the Crown  shall, for the purpose of the Acts mentioned  in this  section be  deemed for all purposes  to  be the  owner.15     21. (1)  It shall be the duty of the Mining Council Duty of  to ensure that there is a sufficient supply of fuel (which Mining  expression herein includes coal, coke, briquettes or other Counoil to  solid fuel) at reasonable  prices  throughout Great Britain, supp y  ue &apos;  and for  this  purpose  it shall  be lawful for the  Mining  Council,  or for any local authority  or Government depart-  ment acting on their behalf, to establish stores and depots  and to employ  vehicles and to use all other necessary  means for the selling of fuel and  to sell fuel within the      [13]                  B
&apos;A;D. 1924.  area of  every  local authority,  and,  further,  for  this        purpose  it shall be  the  duty of the railway companies          or authorities of Great Britain to provide such facilities          for the conveyance  of fuel as the Mining Council may          deem necessary to enable them  to carry out the duties 5          imposed upon them  by this section  at rates not greater          than such  railway companies or authorities are at  any          time entitled to charge for the conveyance of fuel.              (2) Where the Mining Council delegates to any local          authority all or any  of their powers under this section, it 101          shall be lawful for such local authority to exercise all or          any of the  powers of the Mining  Council  so delegated to          them.              (3) All moneys had  and received or  expended by a          local authority under this section shall be deemed to be 15 (          had and received  or  expended on behalf of the Mining          Council.Partialrepeal ofMiningIndustryAct, 1920.Title andoommenoe-ment.    22. The power of regulating the export and price ofcoal contained in section three of the  Mining industry act, 1920, shall not be limited to the period of one year 201after the thirty-first day of August, nineteen hundred andtwenty,  and all the powers hereby  conferred upon theBoard of Trade shall be  deemed to be confirmed uponthe Mining Council, and  the  powers of  the Board  ofTrade under sections eighteen to twenty-three of that Act 2ajare hereby transferred to and vested in the Mining Council,and save as herein  provided, the Mining Industry Act,1920, is hereby repealed  to the  extent  shown  in theSecond Schedule hereof.    23. This Act may be cited as the Nationalisation of 31)1Mines and  Minerals Act,  1924, and this  Act and theMetalliferous Mines Regulations Acts,  1872 and 1875,and the Coal Mines Regulation Acts,  1887  and 1908, andthe Coal Mines Acts, 1911 and 1919, may be cited together as the Mines Acts, 1872-1924, and shall come into opera- 35jtion  on the first day of the second year, which shall hethe appointed clay, after the passing of this Act, and, save in the case of  disclaimer, all valuations,  purchase, andtransference of mines and  minerals to the Mining Council,and  all other arrangements for the carrying  out  of this 40JAct shall be concluded on or before  the first day of thethird year after the  coming into operation  of this Act.
[14 GBO. 5.]  Nationalisation of Mines and             17        &quot;r        ..........                        Minerals.                                                rin n                 SCHEDULES.                    A.D. 1924.FIRST  SCHEDULE.Minerals excluded from this Aot :-Sandstone.Granite.Cherts.Slate.Chalk.Flints.Building clay.Gravel and  sand.Igneous rocks.SECOND  SCHEDULE.ENACTMENTS REPEALED.Session and Chapter.Title or Short Title.Extent of Repeal.1 William  and  Mary, oh. 30.5 William  and  Mary, oh. 6.55 George III.,  oh. 134.  1 James I.  of5  Scotland, oh.   12.  12 James VI. of   Scotland, ch.   31.  10 &amp; 11  Geo. 5.   c. 50.An Aot to repeal the statute made  in the fifth year of King Henry  IV. against multiplying gold and  silver.An  Aot to  prevent disputes and  controversies concerning Royal  Mines.An  Aot for altering the rate  at  whioh the Crown may exeroise  its right  of pre-emption of Ore  in whioh there is lead.Mines of  Gold and Silver pertains  to the King.Anent the Tenth Part of MynisMining Industry Aot, 1920 -The whole Aot,The whole Aot.The whole Aot.The whole Act.The whole Aot.In  Part  - one, sections  one and two.In section three the    words &quot;During   a &quot;  period  of &quot;  one   year
-S-3 ffs  S ?^. 3,2 P  CII HCO   &quot; &amp;T) 4-J TJ&amp; 3  13   a a                      A            B    I    L    L To nationalise the mines and minerals    of Great Britain, and to provide for    the national winning,  distribution,    and sale of coal and other minerals,    and  for  other purposes connected    therewith.        Presented by Mr. George Hall,                 supported byMr. Tom  Smith, Mr.  John, Mr. William. Jenkins,       Mr. David  Grenfell, Mr. Smillie,    Mr. Barker, and  Mr. Charles Edwards.Ordered, by The House&apos;of Commons, to be Printed,            .-  18 January 1924.                 LONDON:PUBLISHED BT HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE.            To be purchased directly from    HJSI. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses:   Imperial House, Kingswaj&apos;, London, W.C. 2; 28, Abingdon     Street, London, S.W. 1; York Street, Manchester:J, St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff; or 120, George Street, Edinburgh ;              or through any Bookseller.      Printed by ETRE and SPOTTISWOODE, LTD.,            East Harding Street, E.O. i.      Printers to the Kjng*a roost Excellent Majesty.               [Price  6oZ. Net.][Bill 13]

</content>
</cab>
