<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/166/0 images: 1122-1133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IIS JXCPXBUT  IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAMIC MAJESTY13  GOVSRH^OT)l?ID?4TIAL. p,  291jjj24&apos;h*****G A B I II E TEX&quot;RANKER OFFICERS,REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE  ON THE  CLAIMS OF PROFESSIONAL EX-RANKER OFFICERS.&quot;    The accompanying advance  copy of the  above report is circulated to the Cabinet:  by direction of the PrimeMinister.  .                           (Sd).  M.P.A. BANKEY,                            Secretary to  the Cabinet,fnitehall Gardens, S.W.1,      May 8th, 1924,
1     EX-RANKER  OFFICERS.Report of  the Committee on the Claims  of      Professional Ex-Ranker Officers.Presented to Parliament byCommand of His Majesty.                      LONDON:   PRINTED &amp; PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE.To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the lollowmgaddressee: Imperial House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 28, Abingdon Street, London, S.:W.l;       York Street, Manchester;  1, St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;               or 120, George Street,  Edinburgh;                 or through any Bookseller.                        1924                      Price 3d. net.                   *&apos;Cmd.  .
EX-RANKER OFFICERS COMMITTEE.REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON THE CLAIMS OF   PROFESSIONAL EX-RANKER  OFFICERS.Terms of Reference :   &quot;To consider the claims of Army  pensioners for increase ofpension in  respect of service during  the war with  particular reference to the claims put forward  by professional ex-rankerofficers, having regard to the general conditions of service in theArmy during the War and to report.&quot;  Tile following information is  appended as to the cost of the--Committee :-   ;  :Constitution of the Committee : The Bight Hon. GEORGE N. BARNES (Chairman).,The Hon. Sir WILLIAM FINLAY, K.B.E., K.C.Sir FELIX POLE.Mr. T. JONES (Secretary).a-.    (li Travelling Expenses- ;q :.  (3) Cost of Printing the Report   s. d.6 12 47 10 0Total14 2  4
REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON THE CLAIMS OF    PROFESSIONAL EX-RANKER OFFICERS.To the Pvt. Hon. J. RAMSAY MAODONALD, M.P.,SIB-, -                       \                  -;:   1  1. We  have interpreted our terms of reference as  limited tothe claims which have been recently put forward by professionalex-ranker officers and as not extending to a general enquiry intoincrease of pension  in respect  of  war service.   This construc-tion is, in our view, in accordance with your statement in theHouse of  Commons.   Any wider interpretation would  have made it impossible for us to report within the short time promised by you to Parliament.  2. The  claimants are all of them Army Pensioners who receivedtemporary commissions during the war.  The majority of them were pensioners who early in the  war rejoined for service  and received commissions but  some were serving  at the outbreak ofwar and took their discharge during its course on being  offered thecommission.  3. The claim put  forward is in substance that the  claimants,though in fact only  given  temporary commissions, ought &quot;to betreated under the terms of Article 572A of the  1914 Pay Warranton the same footing as if they.had been given permanent  com-missions.   This Article gave gratuities  and retired  pay under special  conditions to  regular soldiers  promoted to  permanent commisions.  4. It is essential in order  to appreciate what  is the presentposition of the claimants and what is claimed  by  them to under-stand the general nature of the Army Pension scheme applying to and accepted by them prior to this appeal.  5. Officers after a  certain  number of years service retire onretired  pay.   Men  after  a certain number of  years retire  on pension.  Articles in the  Pay Warrant provide  for the case ofsuch officers and men being re-employed during- a time  of national emergency. They are entitled to draw their retired pay or pensionduring the period of this further service and also to receive the payappropriate to the rank in which^ they are serving but they are not entitled to any further or increased retired  pay or pension inrespect of the period  of further service,   4760Q                                             A 2
  *. (Articles 495 and 496 lay down the conditions governing re-employment,and emoluments..  The following is an extracts from Article 496 :       &quot;In thecase of retired officers, these rates shall be additional to any    retired pay of which they may be in receipt, or irrespective of any gratuity   -they may have received on retirement.&quot;).  f (Under Articles 1162 to 1166. the pensioner could be granted a disabilitypension should he become disabled in consequence of his service in the war,)  6. The following extracts are from the relevant Articles of tliJJPay Warrant of 1913 :-     Re-employment of Retired Officers.       516.  Officers who, having retired pay or gratuity, are re-    . employed under  the conditions of Article 495 or 496,* shall     not be entitled to any increase of such retired pay or gratuity     in respect of the period of re-employment.    &apos; Re-enlisted Pensioners.       1158. A  pensioner re-enlisted during a. time  of  national     emergency  may  draw  his pension in  addition  to  his pay     during the  period of his service, but he  shall not  receive any     addition to his pension in respect  of  such service unless lie     becomes  entitled to a  higher rate under the provisions of     Articles 1162 to 1166. t   7. This is a  system  under  which the  retired pay or  pensionbeing  regarded as paid in  respect  ol:  a  past service is  paid inaddition to the pay appropriate to  the further service.   It is atthe time advantageous  to the  officers and men concerned but itcarries with it this result that the retired pay or pension whichcontinues through the  further service  continues after  it  and isof  course  the retired pay  or   pension  measured by the  originalservice.  A different system prevailed, as we were informed, duringthe South African war but this system which had been the subjectof  much criticism was altered as the  result  of the  report of aCommittee presided  over by Lord Derby  when Financial Secre-tary to the War Office.   8. The present system  has, like any  system of the  sort, its advantages and disadvantages, but it is a coherent and intelligible system and we  see no reason to doubt that it was generally under- stood.   Two illustrations  will make the  working of the system quite  clear. ,A retired Captain taken into employment  for the war who rose to the  rank of Major-General  would receive the pay of  Major-General  and  in   addition   the retired  pay  of  a Captain.  At  the  end of his  period of  service his  pay  of Major-General would,  of course,  cease, aaid he would  then only receive  his retired pay as Captain.  A retired Corporal  re-enlist- ing for the war and  rising to the rank of Sergeant-Majoi- would. receive  the.pay of ;Sergeant-Ma.jor,  and in addition his Corporal&apos;s pension.  At the end of his period of service his pay as Sergeant- Major would, of course, cease, and he would then only receive his Corpora-Vs pension.
  9.  The present claimants were, as to the great majority of them, men  who had, prior to the war, retired  on pension and who re- enlisted  soon after the outbreak of war.   If they had  remained below commissioned rank, they would, even though rising above the rank from which they had been pensioned, have been exactly in the position illustrated above.   But at some  stage of the war they were offered and accepted temporary commissions.  We may say in passing  that we accept the view  put  forward on  their behalf, that morally and practically they had in most cases little choice but to accept.  10.  It is clear that all the claimants applied for and obtained temporary commissions or territorial  commissions which are for the present purpose in  the same category as temporary commis- sions   and do not  require  separate  treatment.  A temporary commission does not,  apart  from  disability, carry  any right to pension or retired pay.   Officers holding these commissions drew their pay as officers.  If they were entitled to pensions  they  also drew  those pensions.  On retirement they drew a gratuity equal to four months&apos;  pay for their first year of service and two months&apos; pay for each subsequent year or part of a year.   Temporary corn-missions were, of course, very  familiar during the war, because they were given in great numbers to civilians who had  joined up for the duration of  the war.  It was pointed out to us that many men  took temporary commissions  because they  were induced to do so by their superior officers and that in the hour of the country&apos;sneed few  troubled over  much to examine the full financial impli-: cations of their re-engagement.  There is no doubt truth in these contentions but the fact remains that as temporary officers the men  in  question did  draw pension  and pay  concurrently  and could not have imagined that  their war service  would  count to augment their pension after the war was over.  11.  In  regard  to pre-war pensioners  (eighty per  cent.),  a decision- favourable to  the claimants would be contrary to  the&apos; Warrant of 1914.   This, as we have seen, provided  for payment of pension in addition  to pay right through any further service they might render, but as a set-off it excluded consideration ofany increase of pension.   These conditions were duly fulfilled. Pensions  were  paid throughout the  war  service and,  in 1919, they were re-assessed upon fa much more generous scale. -  12.  It has been put  to us that Article 1158 of the Warrant of 1914 did not contemplate promotion front the ranks to a coimnis-sion and does not provide for it.   The terms of the Article appearto us to be general and unqualified.  If it is said that on promoting- tion to.a  commission these terms might have been  modified we agree, and there is an obvious example of this.  Any non-commis-sioned officer with enough  service for soldiers pension,  who  waspromoted  to  a permanent commission would not draw  his -non-commissioned officer&apos;8  pension, but would, on  the^ptlier hand,become entitled  to  the retiring  pension of an officer/counting his service: in the ranks as half-service under  the usual conditions.
The general pro-visions of  Article 1158  would,  in  his case, be ^superseded by the terms upon which the commission was granted in the case, however, of a  temporary commission there was no provision for pension ; the commission lasted only for the duration of the war and the recipient of it continued to draw his soldier&apos;pension.  In truth,  the answer to the argument we are consider-big may be put in an  alternative form.  If the case is regardedas  falling  under Article  1158  (and  this is  in our  opinion  the correct view) then the terms of that Article are directly againstthe claim.   If the case is regarded as falling outside that Articleby reason of the grant of&apos;  the temporary commission then  theterms upon  which such  a-  commission was  granted  show thatthere could be no claim to a pension.  Article 516 deals with anofficer re-employed as an officer.  Article 1158 with a pensionerre-enlisted as a  soldier.  Assuming that the actual transfer fromone  class to the other is not specifically provided for on whatground can it be claimed that the act of transfer creates a rightto pension ?  The grant  of a pension  requires a positive enaet-ment.  It  does not  automatically arise  unless  the  contrary isstated.  19. The  case  of  the  serving  soldier  who  was discharged  to pension in  order to receive a temporary commission is somewhat different from that of the pre-war pensioner,   The former was inthe army at the outbreak of war and there was no break of civil life.  Being a serving soldier he was eligible for permanent corn-missioned rank under the terms of Army Regulations which barredpre-war pensioners.  But his status was decided at the  time of hispromotion, and we  see  no reason why it should be altered.  the guiding idea- of the War Office seems to have been a desire to limitpermanent commissions as much as possible,  so  as to be left atthe end of the war with  the  minimum excess over  Army  peacerequirements. In giving effect to this idea it must he assumed that regard was  had generally to age,  fitness,  and  branch ofservice, and to the stipulations of Army Orders in regard to someor all of these points.  14. It is significant that the claim now made is one made inthe light of  events which  happened long after  the Armistice, andafter gratuities had been paid  to, and  apparently accepted by, theofficers in final settlement. The Ranker Officers&apos;  Association, theforeninner of the present  organisation,: was not formed untilNovember,  1919.   There was some  difficulty about the  officialrecognition of this body by the War Office because serving soldierswere eligible for membership  and the first formal presentation ofgrievances to.the War Office is dated 6th October, 1920.  In this appeal complaint is made of the unfairness of re-assessing pensionson pre-war service only and it is pointed out that the Royal MarinePensioners  commissioned  during  the  war   were   drawing  aminimum  pension   of  43250.  15. The decision  to  grant  these favourable terms  to a small body of  Royal Marines was taken in the summer of 1919.   Weare satisfied  that but for  this decision and also the prior offer to
serving soldiers  in. May, .1918, which  is dealt, with below,, little or nothing. would  have been heard of  the claim which.has beenthe subject of the present enquiry.  It is only right tq point,outthat the appellants  who appear  before us  did not ask  for-the marine terms ( 250 per annum) but for the terms given in. theArmy to.permanent  regular officers.  We shall return later.to (hecase of the Marines  and the terms of the offer of May,,. 1918, but would  only say here  that in our judgment.they,did  not,constitute a sufficient reason for re-opening the question of the status or re-tired pay of the ex-ranker officers.  These had accepted the.tem-porary commission with the pay and prospects attached tq.it,.and,although it is no doubt true; that  some-accepted  at  the time as amatter of duty without regard to conditions, these conditions musthave been fully  known  to all long before October,  1920.  In airycase the appellants  were  in  exactly  the  same  position as the civilian and the territorial officer in this respect, and were paidexactly the same gratuity. 16. As regards the suggestion of any breach of the conditions we need say  little more, for  this was not the basis of the case which was made before us. Objection was taken and we thinkrightly to the use of the word contract in this connection. Theconditions as  to pay and  pensions  do not  constitute a  contractupon which any officer or  soldier could under any  circumstancessue.  But it is nevertheless essential that these conditions shouldbe strictly observed  on  the part of the Crow,n. We think it rightto say distinctly that in our opinion  there is ho ground for sayhigthat  the  conditions upon  which the claimants accepted  com-missions have not heen strictly and  exactly  complied with. 17. We  proceed to  offer some observations on  the plea, thatMarine Officers were  admittedly  given  better terms than! tem-porary Army Officers.  It is said to be anomalous  that there shouldbe such a disparity  between the  treatment  of: the  officers of the-two Services.  In regard to this we have to point out that.thewhole treatment of  men and women for war services was honey-combed with anomaly.  The  greatest of all the anomalies was between those who  served in the trenches for Is.  a day in 1914and those who came in later to positions.of comparative comfort and who were paid  half-a-dozen  times as,much.  Large numbersof the first were, killed, and many, left, dependants but .meagrp.lyprovided for.  The  majority of the  second came.home .and were paid substantial gratuities.  There were scores of other anomalies.In  view of  these  considerations we,do not  think thai what,was done for a relatively  small number  of Marine Officers by theAdmiralty affords a justification for adding to  the anomalies ofthe  Army..  In the  event of the contrary view, being taken&apos; therewould be, for instance, the  added anomaly of the officer promoted.to commissioned rank ii^the last few  months of the war retiringwith a life pension or its equivalent, contrasted with a TerritorialOfficer of many years&apos; experience who had served throughout,thewar and who is outside the present claim.      i:j
  18. A further point  upon which reliance was placed was theissue of the Royal Wan-ant of 3rd May,  1918.  This Warrant had its origin in  the emergency which arose out of the great german attack of March, 1918, and its effect was,  put concisely, to offertemporary commissions to men serving on ordinary peace attesta-tions upon  the terms as to  pay and pensions applicable to permanent commissions.   It did not apply to pre-war pensionerswho had rejoined for the duration of the  war and were not servingon ordinary peace attestations  in the Regular Army.  19. Permanent  commissions had  throughout  the war beengranted to regular soldiers serving on ordinary peace attestations.One reason for the offer of these terms  to such soldiers was that by  accepting the commission  they gave up  the  years they had served in the ranks counting towards their pensions.  20. The offer contained in the May Warrant was made at sucha late&apos; period of the war that except for six who were promoted inthe  field all  those affected were in training  with  Officer CadetBattalions when the Armistice came and had not qualified for  ncommission.  We are  not  concerned in  defending  the offer, butonly in pointing out how restricted was its operation. -  21.  It was explained to us that in drafting the Warrant of 3rdMay,  1918, an  unfortunate mistake  was made.   The intention was  to restrict the terms offered to  combatant  officers.  the warrant mentioned the combatant corps  in  which commissionswere offered, but did not specify combatant commissions.  Somesix months  ago claims to bring Quartermasters-who do not holdcombatant  commissions under the Warrant  were  advanced.Legal advice was taken by the War Office, and the legal opinion was, to the  effect that by reason of the omission  of the  word &quot; combatant &quot;  .in the Warrant the claim of  the Quartermastersappointed after the  date of the Warrant to the combatant corpsspecified in ,the Warrant, could  not be resisted.   Accordingly,their claim  was allowed.   Considerable  stress was  laid upon thismatter by some of  the present claimants, but we think it has little direct bearing upon the problem before us.   22. In coming to our decision we have sought to exclude the consequences which would follow from the grant to the claimantsof the status and retired pay of officers.  But  the danger  of introducing into any coherent  code of regulations a modification operating retrospectively and intended to meet a grievance of one particular class, without regard to the  claims of other classes,  is perfectly obvious.  The recognition of the claim of the ex-ranker carries with it recognition of the right of the pensioned soldier  or officer promoted  to higher rank.  There is the  Private  made Sergeant and Captain promoted to Colonel or General.   They are at present paid pensions appropriate to Private or Captain as the case-may be, and are not included in the present claim.  But they would, in equity, have an equal right to pension  on  the higher scale in each case.   And the &quot;matter  does  not stop there, forapart from cases which might be regarded as consequential, it has
to be remembered that if, on grounds of special merit or hard-ship, express  conditions are to be  set aside, in  favour of one particular class, then it would  be  by no means easy to refuse ahearing to any other class, who, admitting that their conditionsas to pay and pension had been fulfilled, might plead that specialmerit or  hardship made it proper  that the  conditions should be modified  in then- favour.  23. Complaint was made to us; of the comparative treatment of army Pensioners according as  they were given temporary corn-missions  in the Naval Division  (Royal Marines) or in the Armyand  conversely of Marines who received  temporary  commissionsin the Army.   We are satisfied that the equitable course is that adopted,  viz.,  to treat each class for pension purposes under theconditions of the original  service.  24. Some of the appellants have suffered by virtue of having to relinquish status as well  as emoluments to  which, as  officers,(hey had become accustomed, and which carried with it,certainlights in civil  life.  This phase  of the matter was put to us, withsome feeling  by one of the  witnesses.  We do not  belittle it.And many of  them feel keenly  the fact that, after rendering dis-distinguished sendee in the  War, their pension, even re-assessed,is so incommensurate with that service.   One officer, who had risen to high  rank, finds his  pension increased by 8M to a totalof 3*. lid-, per day.   Some have  had  much difficulty in  findingwork.  We can only  express our regret and say that exactly thesame lot  has befallen many of the  officers who had been civiliansor who had been  Territorial officers.   These  have experiencedhardship  and  deprivation just as severe and have made no claimto higher status or retired pay.  25. A further contention which was urged upon us by a numberof witnesses was that the  service of the ex-ranker was of  greatervalue than that of the civilian soldier and that for this reason he ought to be regarded in  a  different light.   It is  said that theve-engaged professional soldiers trained the new. men of the Armydrawn from  civil life, ami while  the witnesses were careful todisclaim  any reflection on the spirit or service&apos;of the latter&apos;, theyyet claimed that the  professional experience of the re-engagedsoldier calls for special recognition.  This  plea,: assuming thegreater value of services,  applies with most:force.to the earlierpromotions, and could be  urged with equal force, on, behalf of theTerritorial officer.                        ,    ,,.vw.;,  26. It  is difficult, indeed  impossible, to compare the Value&apos;&apos;ofthe services and the  hardships  of the claimants with&apos;those ofother classes who, whether  officers or  men,  served in the great war-strong cases we doubt not could be made1 out ombehalf ofother classes.   It is enough  for our present purpose1 to say thatwhile fully appreciating the value of the services/of- the -claimantsand  the  hardships  suffered by  them, we. are- clearly-of-opinionthat those services  and hardships  were not  of&apos; -sucli a character
 as.to justify the step, only in our view to be justified by circum- &apos; stances of an  extraordinary and abnormal character, of revising at this date the conditions on which they served!    27.  A suggestion was made to us  to the effect  that the claimants might be given an  extra pension of  &amp; in respect of each year or part  of a year that an Army pensioner or serving soldier had served in commissioned rank.  But it was made clear to;iis that this special addition to pension would not satisfy men whose  demand is to be given the status and the retired pay of officers.  Nor  do we ourselves  see  how, if the  principle under- lying  the  demand  is admitted  it  is  possible  to  confine the addition to the pension to any fractional part of the whole.   28. At a late stage of the hearing the  claimants advanced the argument that they were  legally entitled to be treated as regular officers for retired pay on the ground that they  had served as officers hi  the&apos;embodied  Special Reserve or  Territorial Force, and that under the Pay Warrant such service counts for officers1 retired pay.  The claimants have overlooked  the fact  that this is the. case only when an officer who has given this service snbse- quently obtains a permanent  commission in the regular army. The Committee is satisfied that this claim is not well-founded.1:129.; There:is one-group of soldiers, who fall  outside the class whose  claims were  specially before  us, whose lot made a strong appeal  to us.  There were a certain number of serving soldiers who took their discharge-during the war  and received temporary corn- missions without enough  service on discharge to  qualify for a soldier&apos;s pension. -They were of two classes :  (a)  Those who by adding. commission sendee to  rank  service made 21 years and were given pensions at the end of  the war; -and  (b) those who although they added commission service to rank service could not make 21 years.  Class (a)  have no ground for complaint, but we think that something should be done for class (b), and we propose that the  very small  number of cases which will  arise should be dealt with on  the  lines indicated in paragraph 32.   30. Our conclusion is that the claim put forward on  behalf oj the Ranker .JSxfOfficers has not been made out.   31: We have more than once referred above to the cases of hardship: which still prevail among men who have held  His Majesty&apos;s Commission and who rendered distinguished service to their country&apos;in the Great War.    We recommend thai  His Majesty&apos;s Government should make renewed appeal to employers of labour, to give the  tnost Sympathetic consideration to the claims of all these ex-officers for suitable employment.   -32. We recommend that soldiers who, having already completed a  12 yearsengagement as soldiers,  were  discharged during the -war on being granted, a temporary commission without sufficient service  [in, theaanksio qualify for a soldier&apos;s  pension,  and had not.,;on[being-demobilized, sufficient combined service to qualify :foj^a\soldier\s. pension, should be allowed to submit their claims
Jo the War Office with a view to their being awarded a soldier&apos;pension from, the date of their ceasing to draw pay as officers, reactions much of their combined service as will not exceed a total of 18years service, notwithstanding that it falls short of the minimum period normally necessary for pension, viz. : 21 years.  33. We desire to acknowledge the assistance which  we havederived  from  those  ex-officers  who  gave evidence before us.Captain  Bone  presented the  case of  those whom he representedwith much ability and with a courteous moderation which addedto the effect  of his advocacy.  Mr. R.  J. Paterson, G.B., of theWar Office was charged with the ungrateful but absolutely essen-tial  task  of subjecting to critical examination the various claimsput  forward.  We received great assistance from his exact know-ledge of the Regulations and his rapid apprehension of the variedcircumstances of the different cases.   We desire to acknowledgewith grateful thanks the devotion and ability of our Secretary,Mr. Thomas Jones.                       We are, Sir,                         Your obedient Servants,                     (Sgd.)   GEORGE N. BABNES (Chairman).                              WILLIAM FINLAY.                             &apos; FELIX J. C.  POLE.(Sgd.)    T.  JONES (Secretary).  2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.        1st  May, 1924.(47MD) \Vt.2875-G 103 2500 5/24 H. St  G. IS

</content>
</cab>
