<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/61/25 images: 254-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1945. &apos;SECRET.W.P. (45) 70.30th January, 1945.WAR CABINET.AMERICAN SALESMANSHIP.Memorandum by the Minister for Civil aviation think my colleagues will be interested to see the attached letter, whichhas been sent from the United States Embassy in London to Jersey Airways,one of the air lines owned by.the Railway Companies. A similar letter wasreceived by B.O.A.C. It will be seen that the United States Mission for economic affairs, working in the United States Embassy, and writing as from the Embassy,is soliciting orders from British airline operators for surplus American aircraft.The operators are invited to do business on &quot; satisfactory prices and terms.&quot;Some indication of how satisfactory to operators are the prices which the americans are ready to accept, may be found in an offer which, I understand,was recently made to the Egyptians to sell them three D.C.&apos;s in good condition for a total price of  40,000, including spares and shipping.2. Not only are the British air lines solicited to buy American aircraft;but in replying to the offer they are invited to answer an ingenious questionnaire,which would give to United States airline operators exactly the information asregards present capacity and future plans of British air lines, which a competitorwould like to have.3. It is interesting to note that this intrusion is made at a time, when we are prevented by the restrictions the Americans insist on under the presentLease-Lend position from selling, even to our own Dominions, surplus british aircraft.S   .Ariel House, W.C. 2,-30th January, 1945.Copy of a Letter dated 15th January, 1945, from the Mission for economic affairs, Embassy of the United States of America, 1, GrosvenorSquare, W.1, to Jersey Airways Ltd., Paddington Station.Gentlemen,This Mission has been advised by the Foreign Economic Administration,Washington, D.C., that a limited number of Douglas DC-3 and Lockheed Lodestartransport aircraft are now available for sale. All planes will be allocated inthe United States by a Government Committee, after careful consideration ofeach application. In view of the limited supply of aircraft, no assurance can begiven that all requests will be acceded to.If you desire to purchase some of these aircraft you should make application,over the signature of an authorised official, to Mr. W. W. Brinckerhoff, Chief,Air Transport Division, Surplus Property Branch, Foreign Economic Adminis-tration, Washington, 25, D.C. The information in your application should beas full and complete as possible. A copy of the application should be sent tothe Mission for Economic Affairs, Embassy of the United States, 1, GrosvenorSquare, W.l.Applications should include the following data : (1) The name, address, ownership, business and nationality of the applicant:(2) A statement of the number and types of aircraft presently in use :[29139]Copy No.
(3) The specific types and quantities of aircraft and spare parts desiredwith full particulars as to the preferred type of engines and similartechnical details, and a listing of alternate second and third choices :.(4) A description of the routes presently served :(5) A full statement ^of the use for which the equipment is intended, as for instance, additional routes and territories which are to be served;whether the aircraft are required for cargo only or for passenger service, &amp;c. :(6) A detailed statement of urgency of need :(7) A description of operating and maintenance facilities:The maximum price for the Douglas DC-3 will be $100,000, less reduction forreasonable conversion costs and actual condition, as the terms of sale will beon a basis of condition, and locations of the aircraft. The maximum price forthe Lockheed Lodestars is $68,000, less the same allowance.All aircraft are believed to be in reasonably good condition and it shouldbe pointed out that application does not constitute a firm order, but is subjectto negotiation of satisfactory prices and terms.Sincerely yours,RUTLEDGE BERMINGHAM, Jr.



</content>
</cab>
