<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/12 images: 136-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT68TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.REGRETCOPY NO.     MWAR CABINET.Weekly Resume (No.21) of the Naval,Military and Air Situation (12&quot;n&quot;oon,18th January, 1940,  to 12 noon,25th January, 1940.)(Previous Paper No.W. P. (40) 22.)Report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee.The accompanying joint Naval,  Military and AirForce Resume of the situations from 12 noon on18th January, 1940 to 12 noon on 25th January, 1940 is circulated in accordance with the recommendation contained in Taper No.W.P.(G)(39)3 and approved by theCabinet on 7th September, 1939.   (W.M.(39)7th Conclusions,Minute 17* )&apos; (Signed)EDMUND IRONSIDER.E.C.   PEIRSE.(For C. A,S. )T.S.V.   PHILLIPS.(For O.N. S. )Cabinet War Room,27th January, 1940,

-  TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WEEKLY RESUME(No. 21)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR SITUATION12 noon January 18th, to12 noon January 25th,1940Cabinet War Boom,January 26, 194020698SECRET Copy-No.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENT
NAVAL SITUATION.Home Waters.The Northern Patrol has been maintained at full strength, supported by a force of heavy ships which have also provided cover for the convoys to and from norway.Two further sweeps carried out by our light forces off the Dutch coast have resulted in 2 Norwegian, 2 Dutch and 2 Swedish ships being sent into the Downsfor examination.On the 19th January, while returning from the first of these sweeps,H.M.S. Grenville (flotilla leader) struck a mine and sank 23 miles east of theKentish Knock Light Vessel. The destroyers in company picked up the survivors,but 75 men lost their lives. Grenville was blown in two by the force of the explosion, which occurred at the junction of the engine room and her after boilerroom. All the personnel in these two compartments must have been killed. Thebow of the ship floated for some time, with the stem pointing upward and thebridge submerged, but it is not thought that any of the crew were trapped insideas the coxswain, who was the last man to leave the mess decks, reported that theywere clear of men. The afterpart of the ship sank in a few minutes, going down with no list by the forward end. In this short time the First Lieutenant and apetty officer were able to make their way aft and to set the depth charges to&quot; safe.&quot; This prompt action probably saved many lives, since otherwise manyof the men in the water would almost certainly have been killed by the explosion of the depth charges when the stern sank.2. As a result of a report that two German cruisers had arrived at Borkumfor an operation on the following day, a force of cruisers and destroyers wasordered to make a sweep in the North Sea on the 21st January, and foursubmarines were sent to patrol off the Texel. No enemy surface ships were sightedand the whole force was withdrawn on the 22nd.3. During the night of the 20th-21st January, H.M.S. Exmouth (flotillaleader) disappeared whilst escorting s.s. Cyprian Prince with a cargo of importantnaval stores from Aberdeen to Kirkwall. Nothing more was heard of Exmouthuntil the Cyprian Prince arrived at Kirkwall on the evening of the 21st, and reported that she had heard two explosions, at 4-44 a.m. that day, which shesurmised at the time to be depth charges dropped by H.M.S. Exmouth. shortly afterwards she passed through some light wreckage but, failing to appreciate theactual situation, proceeded on her course. Subsequently, patrol vessels were sent out to investigate and found one lifebuoy marked &quot; H.M.S. Exmouth &quot; with somefloating debris. The ship is presumed to have sunk with all hands (15 officersand 173 ratings). It cannot yet be definitely stated whether she was torpedoedor mined.4. H.M. Submarine Tribune, while patrolling off the Skaw (northern pointof Denmark), reported that torpedoes were unsuccessfully fired at her by a U-boaton the 13th January. On the 17th January she fired eight torpedoes at astationary U-boat in the same locality; there were some indications that theU-boat was hit by one torpedo, but when Tribune surfaced some hours later no signs of wreckage were found. So the attack cannot be regarded as definitelysuccessful.5. H.M. Trawler Valdora is overdue, and is presumed to have been sunkwith the loss of 1 officer and 9 ratings. It is possible that she was attacked by enemy aircraft on the 12th January.H.M.S. Salopian (armed merchant cruiser) was slightly damaged in collisionwith a Finnish ship on the 20th January. On the same day H.M.S. Keppel, whohad collided with the French destroyer Jaguar, arrived safely at Gibraltar for temporary repairs, before proceeding to Malta to refit.A minelaying operation off the East Coast was carried out successfully onthe 24th January by H.M.S. Princess Victoria.Foreign Waters.6. H.M.S. Exeter and H.M.S. Ajax, both of which were damaged in the battle off the River Plate, are returning home for repairs; the former is beingescorted across the South Atlantic by two cruisers.
The Japanese s.s. A sama Maru was intercepted by a British cruiser 35 milesoil&apos; Cape Nogima (Japan) on the 21st January, and 21 officers and techniciansbelonging to the German merchant service were taken prisoner. This action hasbeen resented in Japan and has produced a strong protest from the JapaneseGovernment.A report, received on the 25th January, of an aircraft sighted by a merchant ship 360 miles east of Bahia (Brazil) gives rise to the possibility that there maybe an enemy raider operating in these waters. I;Protection of Seaborne Trade.7. 516 ships, including 21 Allied and 65 neutral, have been convoyed duringthe week. Included in this number are six ocean convoys, two from Gibraltar,two from Halifax (Nova Scotia), and two from Sierra Leone, comprisingaltogether over 100 ships, which have arrived safely at United Kingdom ports.Only one ship in convoy, the British s.s. Cairnross, was lost. She was sunk by.a mine on leaving Liverpool outward bound.Two Norwegian convoys, one outward and one homeward, have arrived with-out incident, the latter consisting of 37 neutral and 2 British ships. 40 destroyers and 14 escort vessels have been employed in escort duties in addition to 1 battle-ship, 1 cruiser and 6 armed merchant cruisers for ocean escorts. Since thebeginning of the war over 7,000 ships have been convoyed, of which 14 British and1 neutral have been sunk by mine or torpedo, giving a percentage of 0-2, or 1 inevery 500 ships.A secret circular issued by the Norwegian insurance companies expressestheir intention to reduce substantially the premium paid on voyages to the UnitedKingdom and France, provided a written declaration from the Master shows thatthe ship proceeded in convoy.Anti-Submarine Operations.8. There has been an increase in L-Boat activity during the past week.U-boats have been reported off the coast of Portugal, in the Western Approaches,in the Bristol Channel, off the North Coast of Scotland and the Moray Firth; itis estimated that eight U-boats were operating.Following the loss of H.M.S. Exmouth and two merchant ships in the vicinity of the Moray Firth on the morning of the 21st, intensive searches have beencarried out in that area which have culminated in an attack on a possibleIJ-Boat off Montrose. The Armed Trawler Northern Duke, which was escortingthe Swedish s.s. Pajala to Kirkwall for contraband inspection when the latter was sunk by torpedo, opened fire on the U-Boat and claims to have obtained adirect hit.9. H.M.S. Veteran delivered a series of attacks on a presumed U-Boatcontact on the 19th, 15 miles south of the Owers Light Vessel, and reported thatafter the third attack an additional dull explosion was heard but contact was thenlost. After sighting a periscope off Caldy Island (South Wales) on the22nd instant, IT.M.S. Vanquisher delivered an attack on an asdic contact withpromising results.  Sixteen attacks in all have been carried out during the week.A. new destroyer striking force will shortly be formed in the western approaches, it will consist of 6 destroyers of the &quot; H &quot; class which were building in this country for the Brazilian Government. They are being specially equipped for anti-submarine operations and will carry a large depth-charge armament.German Attacks on Seaborne Trade.10. Excluding the British merchant ship of unknown name which was reported sunk by torpedo on the 17th January, all the 8 ships attacked by U-Boatsthis week have been neutrals, 3 Norwegian, 3 Danish, 1 Greek and 1 Swede.5 British ships have been mined, of Avhich 4 were sunk, and 5 neutrals have been mined and sunk. Tonnage statistics are shown in Appendix I. The actual losses in the week were above the average for the present war, being 17 ships and55,496 tons. Since the beginning of the war 20 Norwegian merchant ships(68,652 tons) and 24 Swedish (48,218 tons) have been sunk.[20898] B 2
11 The damage to the Danish tanker Danmark (10,500 tons), inflicted onthe 12th January, while she was at anchor in Inganess Bay near Kirkwall, has since been proved to have been caused by a torpedo, divers having recovered partsof an enemy torpedo in the position where the ship was lying when the explosionoccurred.  This position was exposed to attack from the -sea.12. The British s.s. Baron Ruthven, bound from Narvik to the Tees, reportedbeing bombed and gunned by enemy aircraft off Lerwick (Shetlands) on the 24th.A trawler was also attacked&apos; at the same time, but no damage was sustained. Thedrifter Triple Alliance and the steam trawler Newhaven are both overdue andpresumed lost. The three neutral ships Mercator, Lars Magnus Trozelli andSvarton, previously reported as mined, are now regarded as having been sunk by U-Boat action. This has necessitated a slight adjustment in the recordedstatistics to date.German Minelaying.13. On the 19th January two German mines were blown up by magneticsweeps in Liverpool Bay close to the position in which s.s. Cairnross was sunk.On the 20th a German moored mine was cut about a mile west of the LongsandHead Buoy in the Thames Estuary, where six casualties had occurred in Novemberwhich had been put down to magnetic mines. This is the first evidence of anymoored mines in this area. On the same day s.s. Protesilaus was mined in the approaches to Swansea Bay, and the motor vessel Caroni River off Falmouth.In consequence the latter port was temporarily closed to shipping.14. It is considered probable that H.M.S. Exmouth and the two merchant ships sunk on the 21st January off the Moray Firth were torpedoed, but minesmay have been responsible. A mine was swept up in the War channel offNewbiggin (15 miles north of the Tyne) on the same day that the british.s. Ferryhill was mined and sunk in this vicinity. The channel north of the tyne is at present closed, pending mine-sweeping operations.On the 22nd January three unexplained explosions occurred 4 miles east ofGirdleness.15. Enemy aircraft have not been much in evidence during the week, andhave only once been suspected of dropping parachute mines, on the afternoon of the 23rd January close to Margate. No enemy fast surface vessels have beenreported or located by D.F. The master of the Finnish s.s. Onto informed theB-amsgate Control Officer that he had heard that few German magnetic mines were laid by aircraft, and it was a public secret that Dutch Scoots were being usedextensively for the purpose.British Mine Sweeping.16. Bad weather has retarded mine sweeping generally, and experimental work has been limited in consequence.Special apparatus has been designed to recover a sinker of one of the Germanmoored mines in order that the time-release gear can be examined. Five million yards of electric cable are on order for the purpose of demagnetisation of ships.It is hoped to complete the order within eleven weeks.British Contraband Control.17. During the week ending the 20th January, 3,080 tons of cargo wereseized in prize. The main items were 592 tons of ores and metals, 216 tons of oils and fats, 286 tons of oil seeds, 323 tons of feeding stuffs and 441 tons ofcotton and 532 tons of fibre.On the 23rd January there were 35 neutral ships in the three contraband control Bases in the United Kingdom, of which 25 had been there for 5 days or less. This total included 19 Dutch, 4 Norwegian, 3 Belgian, 3 Finnish,2 Swedish, 2 Danish, 1 Greek and 1 United States ships.18. During the week ending the 25th January the Contraband committee considered the cargoes of 80 ships which had arrived since the 13th January and33 outstanding cargoes from the previous week. In 52 cases entire cargoes were released either on first consideration or after enquiries.
In 25 cases out of 38 of ships, in which advance copies of their manifests of cargoes were available before their arrival, immediate release by the Committeewas possible subject merely to the formal checking of the original manifests ontheir arrival.The second batch of Newfoundland Volunteers arrived in Great Britain onthe 24th January. These men are fishermen with exceptional skill in the handling of boats in rough weather and they are to be used for the boarding ofmerchant ships for Contraband Control purposes.German Merchant Shipping.19. Within the last week there has been activity among German merchant ships at Seville. Cargo from Spanish ships is reported as having shifted to german ships and the German merchant ship Hunsdeck is reported to bepreparing for sea after loading with almonds and orange pulp.The A ugust Thyssen (2,343, tons), without a pilot, struck a Swedish mine onthe 18th January when passing Understen Light. She was engaged in theSweden-Rotterdam ore trade. The crew were rescued by a Swedish patrol vessel.The North German Lloyd Augsburg (6,512 tons) has been transferred from theGerman to the Dutch flag. The transfer has been recognised by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment since the sale was effected before the war, although the vessel hasbeen lying in Dairen under charter to a German firm. The Time Asmussen,6,795 tons, lying at Puerto, Mexico, is reported to have been transferred to the mexican flag and renamed Ceroasul.20. At the beginning of the war at least 350 German ships were shut up in neutral ports, a figure which represented about a quarter of the total availableGerman merchant shipping tonnage. 21 German merchant ships repre-senting a tonnage of 89,163 have been captured by the Allied fleets;23 representing a tonnage of 139,236 have scuttled themselves; and some40 German ships have managed to return to their home ports. The total german merchant shipping at the beginning of the war was 4,492,708 tons. german merchant shipping captured or scuttled 224,606 ^8 = 5 per cent. german merchant shipping in neutral ports 1,204,000 = 29 per cent.21. No German ship has entered Antwerp since the 1st January, and between the 1st and 17th January only five ships entered Rotterdam. They werethe Tlior (2,526 tons), Schleswig Holstein (2,369 tons) and August Thyssen(2,342 tons), each of which brought 2,000-3,000 tons of iron ore and left withcoal, and the Castor (519 tons) and the Mercur (758 tons), with general cargoes.Ice is proving a source of trouble to German shipping. The A jaw (2,297tons) reported herself stuck in the ice off the Aaland Islands on the 21st, and onthe same day the^Travenmunde (1,756 tons) stated that there were ten german ships stuck in the&quot; ice on the west coast of the Gulf of Bothnia. The Ostpreussen(3,030 tons) was reported aground on the Dicksand to the north-east of the mouth of the Elbe.MILITARY SITUATION.Western Front.22. Intense cold has limited operations on the Western Front to patrolling.The 50th Division has begun disembarkation in France.Germany.23. The severe weather has led to the diversion of locomotives to freightservice, particularly for the haulage of coal. In consequence, a number of passenger services have had to be cancelled. Many of these services are, however,reported to be excursion trains for winter sports traffic. If this is so, it would clearly be unwise to assume that the German railway system is overloaded.24. The recent formation of a Propaganda Ersatzkompanie (P.K.), orschool where writers, journalists, cameramen and artists are given a course oftraining before being sent to formations in the field, is reported. The task ofthese men will be to give the troops a vivid and convincing picture of theFatherland&apos;s struggle for freedom.
%Bohemia and Moravia.25. Comprehensive registration of horses and horse-drawn and motor vehicles is reported to be taking place throughout Bohemia and Moravia.Returns are to be completed by the 10th February. Motor vehicles commandeeredby the Germans last autumn are now being returned to their owners^ mostly in adilapidated condition, and only motor vehicles in good condition are being listed in the new registration.Slovakia.26. It appears that considerable work is being carried out on road and rail communications in Slovakia. Until recently it was necessary to enter Hungarianterritory at Kassa (Kosice) in order to travel from Western to Eastern Slovakia.This has now been avoided by the completion of the line between Presov andVranov. The widening and repair of roads has apparently been restricted, sofar, to those leading into Hungary.Poland.27. Interest has been focussed on the reported move of German troops intothe Western Ukraine. Accurate information of what has taken place is notavailable, but it has been established that German engineer and railway troops are in Sniatyn on the Roumanian frontier, and that many German uniformsare to be seen in Lemberg. Fairly reliable reports indicate that the whole of thePolish oil-field districts of Drohobycz and Stanislawow, which lie in Sovietoccupied Poland, are now under German control, as is also the railway fromLemberg to the Roumanian frontier. These districts are said to be only lightlyheld, though there are German S.S. formations in other parts of Soviet territorysuperintending the repatriation of German nationals. It is thought that theGerman intention behind these moves is to ensure the protection of the railway bywhich Rumanian petrol reaches the Reich, and perhaps also to exploit theGalician oil-field. In any case, the presence of troops in the area will be areminder that the military might of Germany is always at hand and may serve to ease German trade relations with the Balkan States.Rumours of the imminent cession of the Western Ukraine to Germany are probably unfounded, as the Soviet Government could hardly abandon so soon the&apos;&apos; blood brothers &apos;&apos; whom they saved in September and who have now been formally incorporated in the Soviet Union. Even the more modest arrangementmooted above suggests that Russia must have stood in considerable need ofGerman good offices. Otherwise, she would hardly have allowed the Germanssuch excellent opportunity for getting in touch with the Ukrainian population,since she must suspect that the latter&apos;s Ukrainian schemes are only shelved andnot abandoned.The output of the Drohobycz and Stanislawow oil-fields, when in Polishbands, was about 375,000 tons a year, but it is believed that, given time, this could be considerably increased.Russia.28. Conditions in Russia seem to be slowly deteriorating, and the foodshortages in Moscow and Leningrad are said to be serious. There appears to be some uneasiness in the country, but no sign of serious trouble. Some Armyformations have undoubtedly been shaken by the Finnish successes, but little news of these events has been allowed to reach the civilian population, and there is no sign that a general drop in morale has set in. It must be noted, however, that the morale of the Army is not high, and the attitude of the mass of the soldiery is oneof fatalistic apathy.Middle East.British Reinforcements.29. The second echelon of the 1st Cavalry Division, comprising the5th Cavalry Brigade and attached troops, left England between the 8th and19th January, and are due at Haifa on the 29th.
Iran.30. At the outbreak of war the Iranian Army was organised in ninedivisions and five independent, composite brigades. It now appears that three off these brigades are in process of expansion to divisions. Reservists and newconscripts are being called up progressively for this purpose and to increase thestrengths of existing divisions. This process is due to be completed by March1940. The general indication is a strengthening of the Caspian defences andof the troops facing the Soviet frontier, but a reinforcement at Kermanshah alsoindicates a watchful interest on the main route leading to Iraq.India.31. Except for Waziristan, the situation on the frontier is satisfactory.In Waziristan gangs of hostile tribesmen have increased and action againstcommunications has been more frequent. A number of bridges have been destroyed, notably on the Sarorogha-Razmak Road, which is consequentlyimpassable. In the Ahmedzai Salient (N.E. of Bannu) road-protection troopssuffered twenty casualties and lost ten rifles on the 8th December. The Salientis under air proscription, but this seems to cause little inconvenience to gangswhich constitute a constant threat to the important rail-head of Bannu.Alhough these adverse happenings have been partially offset by the successfulefforts for the release of the kidnapped Major Duggal, there seems little likelihood-hood of a decrease in our present military commitments in Waziristan.Recruiting in India is proceeding satisfactorily, in spite of anti-recruiting and anti-war propaganda in some districts notably the United Provinces.Far East.Operations.32. Reports have been received that the Japanese in the Canton area mayextend their operations up the West River. Although these reports cannot be entirely discounted, there is insufficient evidence as yet to show that the Japanesecontemplate any further large-scale operations in South China. They are stillapparently hoping to reach a successful conclusion of the China incident by political means.The Haiphong-Yunnan railway is expected to be re-opened to passenger traffic about the 25th January and to freight about the 6th February, providedno further damage is caused by bombing. The railway, however, is very vulnerableat many points and the defence measures now being taken are stated to be inadequate owing to the shortage of anti-aircraft guns.Chinese Communications.33. As the Chinese are reported to be much concerned over the cutting ofthe Indb-China railway, the following note on Chinese communications with the outside world may be of interest.Since the establishment of an effective Japanese blockade of all the principalChinese ports, the latter have been forced to rely on four lines of communication,of which the Haiphong-Yunnan railway has been one of the most important. Thethree others have been the Nanning Road (since cut), the Burma Road, and theoverland route from Russia. The tonnage supplied by the Russian route is not known, but the Haiphong-Yunnan railway has been carrying quantities in theneighbourhood of 7,000 tons monthly, and the Nanning Road about 5,000 tons monthly. The first consignment of arms along the Burma Road was made onthe 19th February, 1939, and up to the end of October 1939, 16,900 tons hadbeen transported by this route. The road has stood up to traffic and weather conditions better than was expected, although during the rainy season, from june to October, there was a very considerable reduction in the tonnage trans-ported. The largest quantity carried was 4,960 tons during May, but this figure-had dropped to 339 tons in September and was only 635 tons in October. Earlyin October last it was estimated that, including local manufacture and such material as was brought in from Russia, the Chinese Army was better equippedthan it was in October 1938.
AIR. SITUATION.Royal Air Force Operations.Bomber Command.Night Reconnaissances.34. Two Wellington and three Hampden aircraft reconnoitred areas of north-West Germany on the night of the 18th January and dropped leafletsover Hamburg, Bremen, Brunswick and Hanover. The pilots reported thatblack-out conditions varied, and whereas Hanover was well darkened, Bruns-Avick showed a few lights and Brunsbuttel and Cuxhaven were normally lit.Two Wellingtons repeated this operation over the same area the following night,when some slight sea,rchiight activity and anti-aircraft fire were encountered.A.nti-minelaying patrols over German seaplane bases.35. The offensive patrols over Borkum and Sylt were rendered almostunnecessary by conditions which in themselves made it exceptionally difficult for enemy seaplanes to operate. One Whitley aircraft was, however, despatched on anti-minelaying patrol on the night of the 18th, but returned owing to the extremely unfavourable weather conditions. On the following night the patrolwas sent out again, routed via the Dutch Frisian Islands (outside territorial waters) and with the additional role of searching for two enemy cruisers reportedto be operating from Borkum. Weather conditions were again unfavourableand no enemy craft were sighted, although one aircraft remained over the objectivefor an hour and a quarter, in clouds all the time.Fighter Command.36. There was little enemy air activity off the East Coast during the weekand, of the 217 fighter patrols despatched, a large proportion were for convoy,leave boat and trawler protection. On the 19th January a Heinkel 111 flewsome six miles inland near Peterhead. On its return flight it was interceptedand engaged by three Spitfires at 20,000 feet, some 20 miles off Aberdeen, withoutdecisive result, although it appeared to be damaged. The enemy took no evasiveaction and little return fire was encountered by our aircraft. The attention ofour pilots was drawn to the Heinkel by a trail of white smoke, which was veryconspicuous at a distance but somewhat handicapped the attack at close quarters.A similar trail was seen by fighters on patrol on the 18th January, but no aircraft was sighted.Coastal Command.37. There has been a marked revival of U-Boat activity during the week and.in consequence, an increased number of search and reconnaissance flights havebeen undertaken. Three suspected U-Boats have been sighted and one was attacked. On the 21st January a Lerwick aircraft sighted a U-Boat 60 miles north of Cape Wrath lying almost in the track of a cruiser, which it evidentlyintended to attack. The U-Boat dived at once and one bomb was dropped nearits track. The position was marked and the cruiser warned.A search was made on the 20th January over an area between Horns Reefand Lodbierg to report on possible enemy salvage operations in connection withthe three missing British submarines. While engaged on this task, a Hudsonaircraft sighted four enemy patrol vessels 15 miles west of Horns Reef. Thevessels challenged, and the pilot of our aircraft descended to 50 feet to investigate.After satisfying himself that they were armed, he climbed to take up a position for attack and was immediately engaged by accurate fire with incendiary andyellow tracer shells. Four 250-lb. bombs were dropped about 20 yards fromthe rearmost vessel, but it was impossible to state whether any damage wasinflicted. On the 21st January there were further patrols in connection with areport that the German cruisers Leipzig and Nuremberg had arrived at Borkumfor an operation in the North Sea.Escorts have been provided for 54 convoys, and routine flights have continued in weather conditions which increased the strain on the flying crews.
Operations in France.R.A.F. Component.   British Expeditionary Force.38. Fog and snow have made reconnaissance almost impossible, and therehas been no activity apart from the usual fighter patrols, but enemy flying hasbeen restricted as much as our own and no interceptions were made.French Air Force.Activity was slight during the week, except on the 19th, when there werefive photographic reconnaissances over the German lines and two night flights,which included the dropping of leaflets on Nuremberg. French fighter aircraftmade 120 sorties, and one enemy fighter was shot down on the 19th.German Air Activity.39. German air activity over the North Sea has been below normal duringthe week, very probably because of the bad weather. Some sign of impendingactivity appeared on the 18th, when the number of wireless beacons in service was suddenly doubled, but no major operation ensued.Three enemy aircraft were identified during the week; one of these was intercepted off Aberdeen, as reported earlier in this resume. The other twoappeared over the Shetlands on the 24th and dropped four bombs on waste landnear Lerwick. Four bombs were also aimed at the merchant vessel Baron Ruthven.but no damage was done. Three Gladiator fighters and one London flying boatwere sent to investigate, but the enemy escaped in the clouds. The bombs droppedwere of the armour piercing type. Single-engined, low-wing Arado seaplaneshave been seen on German cruisers and capital ships, and there was an aircraft of this type on the Graf Spee.Foreign Air Intelligence.40. American specialists employed largely in the Soviet oil industry andto a lesser degree in the aircraft industry are being recalled from the U.S.S.R.on instructions from the U.S.A. Government. Although the President of theU.S.A. is stated to have left the matter to the conscience and discretion of theindividual companies, there are indications that all American specialists mayleave the Soviet Union in the near future. The specialists are confident that the oil refinery plants will very shortly be ruined when handed over solely to Sovietengineers. It is, of course, possible that, when the Americans leave, their placeswill be taken by German specialists. Unfamiliarity with the plant, however,combined with the obstinacy and conceit of the Soviet technicians should militateagainst the success of the Germans.If this is so, the existing Soviet productive capacity for high-grade petrolwill be seriously over-strained.RUSSO-FINNISH HOSTILITIES.41. No naval operations are reported this week. Ice conditions areunchanged.42. The Russians are attempting to maintain some 15 to 16 divisions on thefront north of Lake Ladoga, which is served only by the Murmansk railway,single track for the greater part of its length. Their forces on this front musthave depended largely on stocks built up before the concentration of the armies,and, as protracted Finnish resistance Avas probably not foreseen, there is some reason to believe that these stocks may be nearly exhausted. It is, therefore, quite possible that major offensives in the central and northern sectors will be deferred until the summer, when the opening of the White Sea ports will reduce Russianmaintenance difficulties. Such a postponement is the more likely if the Finnscan, in the meantime, interfere effectively with the Murmansk railway.[20698] c
The general position remains fairly satisfactory from the Finnish point ofview, though the strain of meeting sustained Soviet land attacks, combined with air bombardment of the civil population, must be beginning to tell. The need forprompt deliveries of war material, and especially of aircraft, is acute.43. The outstanding news of the week has been the failure of the freshRussian attacks on the Karelian Isthmus; the retreat of the Russian forces operating west of Salla; and the activity of the Russian Air Force, both againsttroops in the line and against objectives in the interior.  -The Soviet attacks on the Karelian Isthmus were renewed in great force onthe 20th January, after a lull of nearly two weeks. The feature of these attackswas the extensive use of aircraft; aircraft machine-gunned the western sector of the Finnish lines where minor attacks were made, and bombers and fightersco-operated in the main attack on the eastern sector, where the artillery bombard-ment was heavy and a large number of tanks were used. These attacks failed to penetrate the Finnish defences, but further attacks in force are expected soon, asthe Russians are believed to have accumulated large stocks of munitions.North of Lake Ladoga Russian attacks in the direction of Loimola havemade very little progress, but there are indications that two divisions, which were pratically surrounded, near Kitela, may have succeeded in extricating themselves.Further north nothing of importance has taken place except in the Sallasector where Russian troops, which had penetrated nearly to Kemijarvi, were forced to retreat. These columns are now reported to be holding a position about18 miles west of Salla, but to be in difficulties owing to interruption of their com-munications. The Russian retreat seems to have been carried out in much betterorder than were the retreats from Tolvajarvi and Suomussalmi earlier in the war.The threat to the Finnish waist-line has. therefore, for the present, been countered,though it will doubtless be renewed.44.   Russian air attacks on Finnish towns have continued, and therewas an attack on coastal batteries by 300 aircraft on the 21st.   An attemptto land Soviet troops by parachute behind the Finnish lines was frustrated by the finns.Finnish aircraft have been engaged in offensive operations against Sovietair bases, so far as their limited resources have permitted. They succeeded indestroying five Soviet aircraft in one raid, and a Finnish communique claims thedestruction of eleven Soviet bombers and one observation balloon in anotherattack.45. Of the 36 Swedish aircraft which are to accompany the Swedishvolunteer force, 12 have arrived in Finland. Six of these assisted in recent opera-tions round Salla, where they shot down three (or possibly four) Russian aircraft and heavily bombed Russian lines of communications. One Swedish aircraft was lost and two others made forced landings.46. The British Government have agreed to release 12 Hurricane fighters,17 Lysander (army co-operation) and 12 Blenheim aircraft for Finland, inaddition to the 12 Blenheims, 28 Gauntlet fighters and 30 Gladiators already approved.47. The Finnish Government ordered 54, Brewster F.2A fighter aircraft from the United States of America, and the American Government has agreed to release 40 of these aircraft for export to Finland. The first six were due to leaveon the 29th December and the remainder were promised for shipment thisJanuary. The French Government are also supplying certain air material to the finns, including 30 fighter aircraft and 12 dive bombers.
APPENDIX I.Ships Mined.Date.	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	In Convoy or not.	Position.	Fate of Crew.	Remarks.Jan. 17  ... Jan. 17  ... Jan. 18  ... Jan. 18 ... Jan. 20  ... Jan. 21   ... Jan. 21   ... Jan. 23   ... Jan. 23 ... Jan. 23  ...	Cairnross (5,494 tons) Asteria ... (3,313 tons) Flandria (1,157 tons) Foxen   ... (1,304 tons) Caroni River   . . (7,807 tons) Protesilaus (9,577 tons) Fernjhill (1,086 tons) Baltanglia (1,500 tons) Pluto    ...... (1,598 tons) Onto (1,333 tons)	British Greek Swedish Swedish   ... British British British British Norwegian Finnish	Coal and general Coal In ballast In ballast Coal Wood pulp and general In ballast	Liverpool ... Hull -Antwerp   ... Falmouth ... Liverpool ... Blyth Bergen Bergen	St.   John&apos;s, N.B. Marseilles... Gothenburg Aruba Barry Docks Tyne Type&apos;    .... Tees	In convoys OB 74, Not...... Not...      ... Not... Had left convoy, OBG 75 Not... 1 Not ,    ... \ (previously j in UN 8) Not...	4 miles west of Bar light vessel, Liver-pool Off Haisborough Off  Ymuiden,  Hol-land 70   miles   east   of Orkneys Off Ealmouth Off Swansea... 2 miles S.E. of Blyth (not   in   searched channel) 6 miles S.E. of Earn Islands 27 miles to N.E. of Yarmouth	Whole crew landed by H.M.S. Mackay 11 survivors landed... 13 missing 4 survivors picked up from raft by Nor-wegian S.S. Balzac 17 missing 1 survivor All saved 14 wounded ... 2 survivors  ... 14 missing All  saved by  local fishing boats All saved     ......	Sunk. Sunk. Sunk. Sunk.    &apos; Sunk. Beached. Sunk. Mined within 4 minutes of each other, and sunk. Sunk.Total tonnage lost by mines during the week      ......      ...   24,592 tons.Total British tonnage lost by mines during the week...      ... - 15,887 tons.-v3
Ships attacked by Submarines.Date.	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	Nature of Attack.	In Convoy or not.	Position.	Fate of Crew.	Remarks.Jan.  12 Jan.  17 *Jan. 17 Jan.  18 Jan.  18 Jan.  21 Jan. 21 Jan. 22 Jan.  23	Danmark (10,500 tons) Enid    ...... (1,140 tons) Unknown Pajala  ... (6,873 tons) Canadian Reefer (1,831 tons) Miranda (1,328 tons) Tekla   ...... (1,469 tons) Ekatontarchus Drakoulis (5,329 tons) Sydvold... (2,434 tons)	Danish Norwegian British Swedish   ... Danish Norwegian Danish Greek Norwegian	Oil Pulp    ... Coal Grain	Trondheim Buenos Aires Gibraltar ... Blyth Firth of Forth Rosario Tyne	Dublin    ... Gothenburg Denmark ... Denmark ... Tyne Christian-sand	Torpedoed... Set on fire by gunfire Torpedoed... Torpedoed... Torpedoed... Torpedoed... Torpedoed... Torpedoed... Probably torpedoed	Not... Not....... Not...... Not...... Not... Not...... Not...... Not...... Not...	At   anchor   in Inganess   Bay (Kirkwall) 6 miles north of Muckle Flugga, Shetlands Near above posi-tion 40 miles north of Cape Wrath 25  miles   from cape finisterre 30 miles north of Kinnaird Head 25 miles S.E. of Wick 120 miles S.W. of Oporto Off coast of Scot-land	All saved All saved Unknown Crew rescued by Trawler North-em Duke Whole crew res-rescued by Trawler Jose Ignacio 3 survivors picked up. 9 survivors pick-ed up by Nor-wegian S.S. Iris 8 missing 6 killed...... 23 survivors : 19 survivors 5 missing	Back broken.   Total loss. Derelict, eventually sunk by -H.M.S. Firedrake. S.S.  Enid reports seeing ship of about 5,000 tons, presumed British, torpedo-doed and sunk.   She was proceeding to the rescue of survivors, when she was herself attacked. Sunk while under escort of Armed Boarding Trawler Northern     Duke,    who    tsO carried out an attack on the submarine. Sunk. Sunk. Sunk. Sunk.Total tonnage lost bjp-U-Boat action during the week     ...      ...      30,904 tons.* This ship may be S.S. Polzella (4,751 tons) which left Narvik for Methil and Tees on January 13.
BRITISH SHIPPING losses due TO ENEMY&quot; ACTION

SHIPPING LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTIONBRITISH ALLIED AND NEUTRAL

Mercantile Losses, British, Allied and Neutral, to noon, Wednesday,January 24, 1940.British. No. Tonnage.By Submarine       ........      .... 67 272,893Mine      ................ 41 144,483Raider   ................ 10 55,133Aircraft................ 14 7,772Cause unknown, presumed sunk.... 3 691135 480,972Allied.By Submarine       ....      ........        8 49,516Mine      ................        3 6,06511 55,581Neutral.BySutTria:.  ::::  ...  :::: it i8$SRaider   ................ 1 ^JJJgAircraft................ 1 757Mine or torpedo     ............ 1 i tnlCause unknown, presumed sunk .... 1,304105 307,998Summarised, the Totals are : By Submarine        ............ 117 455,041Mine      ....      ............ 103 319,501Raider   ................ 11 57,051Aircraft................ 15 8,529Mine or torpedo     ............ 1 2,434Cause unknown, presumed sunk.... 4 1,995251 844,551
Losses and Gains of British Mercantile Tonnage of vessels of 500 gross tonsand oirer.From September 3, 1939, to January 21, 1940.Gains.New vessels enemy vessels capturedTransfer from other flags other gainsNo.519520Tankers.Tonnage.42,0006,00067,0009,000Other Vessels.124,000No.381872689Tonnage.209,00077,00019,00053,000358,000Total Gains: 109 vessels of 482,000 tons.Losses.By enemy action other total lossesTankers.No. Tonnage.12 92,0002 14,00014Other Vessels.No. Tonnage.9222106,000 114Total Losses : 128 vessels of 568,000 gross tons.398,00064,000462,000Yessels under construction in United Kingdom on January 21, 1940.tankers other vessels no.13127140Gross Tons.105,000730,000835,000The average weekly increment of British ships and Tonnage over 20 weeks was about 5&apos;4 ships and 24,000 gross tons, compared with an average weeklyloss due to enemy action for the same period of 5&quot;2 ships and 23,600 gross tons.APPENDIX IY.Additions to His Majesty&apos;s Fleet during the week.1 Submarine.1 Destroyer.11 Mines weeping Vessels.4 Anti-Submarine Vessels.



</content>
</cab>
