<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/80/0 images: 39-40</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
V,-4&apos;HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OE HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. March 1956SECRETCopy No. 49CP. (56) 612nd March, 1956CABINETCOAL DISTRIBUTION COSTSMemorandum by the Minister of Fuel and power in E.P. (56) 19 I put to the Economic Policy Committee the proposal that Ishould set up an independent inquiry, &quot; To ascertain what are the various items which make up the difference between the prices received by producers of coal,coke and manufactured fuels in Great Britain [Northern Ireland] and those paidby inland consumers [in Northern Ireland]; to investigate the merchants&apos; distributioncosts and profit margins in respect of these supplies and to make recommendations.&quot;My proposal arose from a request to my predecessor by the Trades UnionCongress (T.U.C.). They originally suggested that the inquiry should also cover the &quot; structure &quot; of the trade, but before consulting the Committee I had had an informal talk, without commitment, with Sir Vincent Tewson, the General Secretaryof the T.U.C., and found that rather narrower terms of reference drafted as above would satisfy him.2. The Economic Policy Committee accepted my proposal in principle(E.P. (56) 5th Meeting, Item 5). Of the advantages to be gained by an inquiry I need perhaps only repeat here that, an independent assessment might prove to bea valuable preparatory move towards the decontrol of household coal and might help to educate public opinion on the hard facts of a difficult problem.3. The Committee asked me, however, to look at the possibility of a one-mancommittee since, notwithstanding the limited terms of reference, the inquiry mightstray into examination of the structure of the trade and the presence of a TradeUnionist might increase the risk of recommendations embarrassing to theGovernment.4. The risk that embarrassing recommendations may be made is inherent inany inquiry which is truly independent, but in this case I do not think we shouldbe unduly apprehensive, if only because any proposal to nationalise distribution would almost certainly be opposed by the co-operative societies.5. Further, the inclusion of the T.U.C. in the inquiry would have somepositive advantages:  id) Their interest is legitimate and without their participation it would bedifficult to convince the miners that their ideas of excessive distributioncharges were ill-founded. Moreover the dirty and arduous nature ofcoal distribution has given rise to labour shortages in some areas andthe distributors are sure to emphasise the need to pay adequate wagesand provide welfare facilities. Thus by taking part in this inquiry aT.U.C. representative would have brought home to him the conflictinginterests that have to be reconciled.(b) The acceptance of the T.U.C.&apos;s idea of an inquiry, coupled with an invitation to participate, would be regarded by them as a gesture offrankness and goodwill, whereas a one-man inquiry might well havethe appearance of a &quot; whitewashing &quot; operation and a rebuff to theT.U.C.49659
6. After reconsideration therefore I still think that a committee of five members, one being a trade unionist, would be best. If all the members are carefully selected I do not think that there will be much danger of undesirableconsequences.7. The Minister of Commerce in Northern Ireland is under strong pressure to institute a similar inquiry and I have agreed with him that if an inquiry is set uphere the same members could be appointed by him to perform a similar task there.With some difficulty the Northern Ireland Government have persuaded their back-benchers to postpone a further motion on this subject until 13th March. It wouldbe of some help therefore to the Northern Ireland Government if a decision couldbe reached and announced before then.A. J.Ministry of Fuel and Power, S.W. 1,1st March, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
