<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/80/0 images: 134-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
- &apos; ft 90(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;SGOVERNMENT)confidential.P.(56) 685th March, 1956SECURITY CONFERENCE OF PRIVY COUNCILLORSNote by the Secretary of the CabinetThe Ministerial Committee which have been consideringthe Report of the Conference of Privy Councillors on Securityrecommended that a White Paper should be presented toParliament summarising the main conclusions of the Conference.By the direction of the Prime Minister, I circulate forconsideration by the Cabinet a draft of this White Paper.(Signed)  NORMAN brook cabinet Office, S. W. 1.5th March,  1956.COPY NO.CABINET
CONFIDENTIAL proof of the Conference ofPrivy Councillors on SecurityPresented to Parliament byby Command of Her majesty march 1956LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office net cmd.
1. On 23rd November, 1955, the Prime Minister informed the Houseof Commons that a Conference of Privy Councillors had been set up with thefollowing terms of reference :-&quot; To examine the security procedures now applied in the public services and to consider whether any further precautions are called forand should be taken.&quot;The Conference consisted of the following Privy Councillors: My^noblc.....Friend&quot;fhe Lord President of the Council;My nohlfin^and-lffarn^d FripnH&quot;^&quot; Lord Chancellor; ^   .       .My &quot;right hon&quot;.&quot;&apos;aii^--grflaitt&apos;&quot;r^eiml&apos;^he hfes*e Secretary^) S*wC lCJfei*The nobte-a,nd learned Earl; Lord Jowitt; J JThe right hon. GsatlaraaB-tbe. Member for Lewisham, South (Mr. H.        *Morrison);The right hon. Gentleman tha. Member for Vauxhall (Mr. G. R.Strauss);The Permanent Secretary to Her Majesty&apos;s Treasury.2.   The Conference have presented their Report and their recommenda-tions have been considered by Her Majesty&apos;s Government.3. The Prime Minister stated on 29th November last that if there weresteps which could be made public as a result of the Conference, there would,of course, be a report to Parliament. The Report of the Conference includes a close examination of the security procedures in the public services, andit would not be in the public interest to publish the full text of the Reportor to make known all its reconphdations. But in compliance with theundertaking given by the Prime Minister, this White Paper gives the substance of the Report in so far as it can properly be made public, including a numberof specific recommendations.4. The report starts by an analysis of the general nature of the securityrisks with which this country is faced to-day. The Conference point outthat, whereas once the main risk to be guarded against was espionage by foreign Powers carried out by professional agents, to-day the chief risksare presented by Communists and by other persons who for one reason or another are open to exploitation by Communist Powers. The Communistfaith overrides a man&apos;s normal loyalties to his country and induces the belief that it is justifiable to hand over secret information to the CommunistParty or to the Communist foreign Power. This risk from Communistsis not, however, confined to party members, either open or underground, butextends to sympathisers with Communism.5. At one time the Fascist ideology also presented considerable securityrisks. Although to-day the chief risk is that presented by Communism,the security arrangements instituted in 1948 were directed, and will continueto be directed, against Communism and Fascism alike, In this paper for convenience and brevity the term &quot; Communism&quot; is used to coverCommunism and Fascism alike.
v^4.&apos; One of the chief problems of security to-day is thus to identify the members of the British Communist Party, to be informed of its activities and to identify that wider body of those who are both sympathetic toCommunism; or susceptible to Communist pressure and present a danger to security. Thereafter steps must be taken to see that secret information is not handled by anyone who, for ideological or other motives, maybetray it.7. Her Majesty&apos;s Government agree with this broad analysis and willcontinue to base their policy on preventing persons of this nature from having access to secret information.8. Against the background of this general analysis, of which only avery brief outline has been given, the Conference address themselves to an examination of the Governments security arrangements. Their mainconclusion is that there is nothing organically wrong or unsound about those arrangements. They make, however, certain recommendations, the purpose ofwhich is to strengthen the system in some respects. Her Majesty&apos;s government propose to give effect to all the recommendations which the Conferencehave made.9. The Report of the Conference deals with the public services generally.But it is implicit in the Report that the Conference recognise that in certain areas of the public service notably in the Foreign Service, the Defencefield and the Atomic Energy Organisation the need for stringent security precautions is greater than elsewhere. Her Majesty&apos;s Government accept this view.10. Some of the recommendations of the Conference deal with what may be called the relation between security risks and defects of character and conduct. The Conference recognise that to-day great importance mustbe paid to character defects as factors tending to make a man unreliableor expose him to blackmail, or influence by foreign agents. There is a dutyon Departments to inform themselves of serious failings such as drunkenness,addiction to drugs, homosexuality or any loose living that may seriously affect a man&apos;s reliability.11. There is a natural reluctance to make adverse reports on colleagues and nothing could be worse than to . encourage tale-bearing or maliciousgossip. Nevertheless, it is important to impress not only on Heads of departments but on supervisory officers generally that it is their duty toknow their staff and that they must not fail to report anything which affectssecurity. This covers both evidence which suggests Communist associationsor sympathies, and also serious defects or failings which might jeopardise the security of the section of the public- service in their charge. TheGovernment accept this recommendation, although they recognise that themeasures necessary to give effect to it will require very careful consideration.12. While confining themselves to the security aspect of these defectsof character and conduct, the Conference also record the view that in individual cases or in certain sections of the public service, a serious characterdefect may appropriately be the determining factor in a decision to dismissa particular individual or to transfer him to other work.13. The Conference also recommend that it should be recognised thatthe fact that a public servant is a Communist not only bars his employment on secret duties, but may also therefore have an unfavourable effect onhis prospects of promotion.49666
14.   The Conference also make a series of recommendations which Mnon the risk presented by those in regard to whom there is no evidence that: they are themselves members of the Communist Party, but evidence existsof Communist sympathies or of close association with members of theCommunist Party.15. The Conference recommend that in deciding these difficult andofter borderline cases, the balance must be tilted in favour of offering greaterprotection to the security of the State rather than in the direction of safe-guarding, the rights of the individual. For example, they recommend thatan individual who is living with a wife or husband who is a Communistor a Communist sympathiser may, for that reason alone, have to be moved from secret work, and that the same principle should be applied in other cases of a like nature.16. The Conference recognise that some of the measures which theState is driven to take to protect its security are in some respects aliento our traditional practices. Thus, in order not to imperil sources ofinformation, decisions about the reliability of individuals have sometimesto be taken without giving full details of the evidence against them. Again,it is sometimes necessary to refuse to employ a man on secret duties, or inthose cases where no alternative work can be found for him in the publicservice, to refuse to employ him at all, because after the fullest investigationdoubts about his reliability remain, even although nothing may have beenproved against him on standards which would be accepted in a Court ofLaw- The Conference agree regretfully that these counter-measures, although they are distasteful in some respects, are essential if the security of the state is to be ensured. But they recognise that it is also important to convincepublic opinion that the measures taken and the procedures in force willnot be exercised unreasonably. For this reason the Conference approve the Tribunal (commonly known as the Three Advisers) set up in 1948to hear appeals from civil servants threatened with transfer from secretduties or dismissal from the Service on securijy grounds. This machinery should continue; and the person whose continued employment in Govern-rnerit Service is called in question on account of Communist association orsympathies will be able to have his case considered by it. The Conferencealso recommend that the terms of the reference of the Three Advisers shouldbe amended so as to enable them to conduct a rather wider enquiry.17. The measures necessary to carry out these recommendations will involve alterations in existing procedures. These alterations will be notified to the staff associations concerned and an opportunity given for representationjp be made before the alterations are promulgated in full. This paper istherefore confined to giving the broad details of the decisions reached on those recommendations which can be properly made public.18. Two other matters should be mentioned. The first is that theConference considered whether additional statutory powers should be sought to enable the Government to detain suspects or prevent them from leaving the country.19. The Conference point out that, while an individual can be arrestedon suspicion that he is about to attempt to convey secret information to aforeign Power, he must be brought before the courts on a charge withoutdelay. The time required to collect evidence upon which a charge can bebased is often long, and the Conference dismiss any suggestion that power should be sought to detain persons for an unlimited period without preferringcharges against them, on the grounds that this would run counter to thiscountry&apos;s traditional principles of individual freedom, and would be most unlikely to be approved by Parliament in time of peace.   They also come
I He conclusion that legislation which would permit arrest and detention,without a charge being preferred, for a short specified period, say, fourteen days, would not be much help. The Conference also consider that thewithdrawal of a passport could not be relied upon to prevent a UnitedKingdom citizen in connivance with a foreign Power from leaving the country.20. For these reasons the Conference recommend that no additional powers should be sought to detain suspects or prevent them leaving thecountry.21. The second matter is that the Conference reviewed the existingprocedures for the security of secret Government contracts involving personsoutside Government employment. The Conference have considered whetherpersons subject to these procedures should be given the same right as isenjoyed by persons in the public service of having their case considered bythe Three Advisers. The Conference recognise that this is a difficult matter,but are in favour, if suitable arrangements can be made, of access being given to the same tribunal in certain types of cases. They recommend,however, that in the first instance this matter should be discussed with theNational Joint Advisory Council. Arrangements for such discussion totake place are being made.49666  Wt. K        /56   F.o.r.
Printed and published by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery OfficeTo be purchased from york House, Kingsway, London w.c.2423 Oxford Street, London w.lP.O. Box 569, London s.e.113a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2109 St. Mary Street, Cardiff39 King Street, Manchester tower Lane, Bristol 12 Edmund Street, Birmingham 380 Chichester Street, belfast or through any booksellerPrice   d. net printed in Great Britain

</content>
</cab>
