<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/80/0 images: 141-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY CF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S-GOVERNMENT)SECRETCCP. (56) 696th March, 1956CABINETC OST OF MEAT INSPECTIONMemorandum by the Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food have considered this question of meat inspection costs in thelight of the Chancellor of the Exchequers memorandum, Q, P.. (56:) 50.Throughout the long series of discussions on this matter it has beenclearly recognised that Exchequer assistance would raise difficulties atthe present time.    In recommending very strongly, and after the most careful consideration, that Exchequer assistance should nevertheless begiven to those authorities on whom an unreasonable burden falls, the HomeAffairs Committee were, I think, moved by the consideration that thealternative course would involve much greater difficulties for the Govern-ment.2. There is general agreement that financial help should be givenin suitable cases.    Various ways of doing this have been examined, and itis clear that the only practicable alternative to an Exchequer grant is toimpose a charge for inspection on the owner of the meat.    I would like mycolleagues to consider some of the difficulties to which this alternative -would give rise.(a) The first is that ever since the passage of the first Saleof Food and Drugs Act in 1075 it has been an acceptedprinciple that public health services should be paid forout of public funds.    There has been no departure fromthis principle in the 80 years since then.     The firstbreach would be bound to attract criticism from many quarters.(b) There would be extremely hostile criticism from the meattrade organisations, who would argue that there can beno justification for singling out one of the food tradesfrom all the others and imposing on it an obligation topay for a public health service v/hich in the case ofall other commodities is paid for out of public funds.The force of their opposition on grounds of principle would not be diminished even if in practice they couldrecover the charge from either the producer or theconsumer.     The National Farmers1 Union are alsostrongly opposed to a levy on the trade.    All the associations of food processors and manufacturers arelikely to object strongly because they will regard thedecision as the thin end of the wedge and likely to bea precursor of similar impositions upon other foodtrades and industries.COPY NO, L O
(c) The professional organisations most closely concernedwith meat inspection, representing medical officers ofhealth and sanitary inspectors, object to a levy on thegrounds that meat inspection is a public health serviceand should be paid for out of public funds.(d) I understand that the Secretary of State for Scotlandregards a levy on the trade as objectionable in principleandj even if it were to be adopted for England and Wales,he would prefer not to accept it in Scotland,    Althoughthe problem is relatively less acute in Scotland and thecost of meat inspection could, to that extent, more readily continue to be borne on the rates without a grant,the most would likely be made of any difference in thetwo countries.(e) The regulations authorising local authorities to impose alevy on the trade would have to be submitted to the(statutory) Food Hygiene Advisory Council, which is responsible to the Minister of Health and to myself.I think the Council would in any case be concerned aboutthe effect on public health policy of a charge for meatinspection.    Moreover, two of its members are associatedwith organisations opposed to a levy.    I would thereforeexpect the Council to recommend against a levy, which wouldbe extremely embarrassing to the Minister of Health aswell as to me.(f)    The Opposition would seize the opportunity of impugningthe sincerity of the Government&apos;s clean food policy on theground that we are not prepared to make even a smallcontribution to the cost of an important public health service which is recognised to be in need of improvement.     As theproposal for a levy would have to be laid in Parliament, theOpposition would have ample opportunity to deploy all thearguments there are against the Government.3. The likelihood of criticism, however strong, should not of coursedeter us from imposing a charge on the trade if we feel it is justified;but I can see no adequate defence in this case to the kind of criticism towhich we shall be exposed.     The argument put forward by the Inter -departmental Committee on Slaughterhouses, and endorsed by the Chancellorof the Exchequer, would provoke the objection I have indicated in (b) above.It would be argued that there is no difference in this respect between meatinspection and the many other forms of inspection to which food manufacturers and traders are subject.4. By contrast, there is likely to be no opposition either inParliament or outside to the solution which the Home Affairs Committeehave so strongly recommended.   Moreover, there are special circumstances which will make an Exchequer grant in this instance less embarrassing tothe Treasury than the Chancellor apprehends.    It would not be a new departure,  since central government grants to local authorities for meatinspection were given during the 15 years of controls     I think that the grant to port health authorities does afford an analogy.     These services, which include meat inspection, are performed for the \\hole country and so benefitwider areas than the authority&apos;s own district.    The meat inspection grantthat I propose wouldnot apply to all authorities with slaughterhouses but would only go to those faced with disproportionate expenditure because they
provide substantial inspection of meat going to areas outside their owndistricts.    If the principle is that local rates bear the cost of local publichealth services, it is reasonable to make some grant where the expenditusubstantially benefits wider areas.5, If a further safeguard is needed, I am prepared to accept thatit should be made clear to local authorities that the grant for meatinspection should be on a provisional basis and subject to review after,say, two or three years, in the light of any reorganisation there may beof the structure and finance of local government.6. For the reasons set out above I invite my colleagues to agreethat assistance to local authorities should be given by means of an exchequer grant, on the basis I have indicated.     The Minister of Healthhas asked me to add that he is in full agreement with my views and conclusions as set out in this paper.B.H.A.Ministry of Agriculture, fisheries and Foods S.W.I.,6th March,  1956.

</content>
</cab>
