<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/80/0 images: 176-190</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0 If 3i/HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCONFIDENTIALjit-CP, (56) 77 COPY NO,       I13th March, 1956.CABINETTHE IMPLICATIONS OF FULL EMPLOYMENTMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer on 22nd February the Cabinet took note of a decision by theEconomic Policy Committee that the draft of the White Paper on the implications of Full Employment should be brought up to date and thatthis revised version should be submitted to the Cabinet with a view toits early publication.    (C.Ma (56) &apos;6th Conclusions, Minute 3).2. Since then I have been considering the text in the light bothof suggestions made about the earlier draft circulated -with CP, (55) 123and also of figures now available in respect of 1955.     The attachedrevise takes full account of both;   there are no major revisions of substance to which I wish to draw the attention of my colleagues, except the two additions to paragraphs 25 and 26, which I felt needed strength-ening by repeating the thought in Part V of the White Paper in Part VI,in order to bring the two together.     Textual changes required by theuse of more up-to-date figures did not involve any change in the argument30 There remains the question of timing.     The White paper should clearly not clash with Easter or the Budget,  so that the practicalchoices are round about 22nd/23rd March or after the end of April.4. Ideally it would be best for it to appear in a lull betweenrounds of wage increases,  so as to give it the best chance of being accepted as an objective statement.     This in itself would suggest thebeginning of May.     But this might be too late to influence the formulation of policy by the Unions preparing for their Whitsun conferences.     Thereare also the current talks between Ministers and the two sides of industry on balance, I am in favour of getting the White Paper out as soon aspossible - before Easter, and well before the Budget,,HDM3
E&apos;I-113 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCONFIDENTIALCP. (56) 7713th March, 1956.THE IMPLICATIONS OF FULL EMPLOYMENTMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer on 22nd February the Cabinet took note of a decision by theEconomic Policy Committee that the draft of the White Paper on the implications of Full Employment should be brought up to date and thatthis revised version should be submitted to the Cabinet with a view toits early publication.     (C,M8 (56) 16th Conclusions, Minute 3).2, Since then I have been considering the text inthe light bothof suggestions made about the earlier draft circulated with C,P,(55) 123and also of figures now available in respect of 1955.     The attachedrevise takes full account of both;  there are no major revisions of substance to which I wish to draw the attention of my colleagues, except the two additions to paragraphs 25 and 26, which I felt needed strength-ening by repeating the thought in Part V of the White Paper in Part VI,in order to bring the two together.     Textual changes required by theuse of more up-to-date figures.did not involve any change in the argument30 There remains the question of timing.     The White paper should clearly not clash with Easter or the Budget, so that the practicalchoices are round about 22nd/23rd March or after the end of April.4. Ideally it would be best for it to appear in a lull betweenrounds of wage increases, so as to give it the best chance of being accepted as an objective statement.     This in itself would suggest thebeginning of May.    But this might be too late to influence the formulation of policy by the Unions preparing for their Whitsun conferences.     Thereare also the current talks between Ministers and the two sides of industry on balance, I am in favour of getting the White Paper out as soon aspossible - before Easter, and well before the Budget.COPY NO.   v3CABINETH8M.
i^RAFT CONFIDENTIALRevise 13.3.56THE IMPLICATIONS of full EMPLOYMENTPresented by the to parliament by Command of Her Majesty1956
THE IMPLICATIONS OF FULL employment. introduction. The White Paper on Employment Policy (Cmd. 6527), issued by the coalition Government in May 1944, set out the policies to be pursued afterthe war to maintain a high and stable level of employment and to combinethis with a rising standard of living. These policies have been applied with considerable success. Full employment has, in fact, been maintained in mostparts of the country over practically the whole of the past ten years, andwe are to-day consuming more as a nation than we have ever done before.But full emploment has brought with it one problem to which we have notyet found a satisfactory solution: yet, unless we do find the solution, itwill be more difficult to achieve a further advance in living standards, and full employment itself may be threatened. The problem is that of continuallyrising prices. It affects everyone, and everyone must contribute if it is tobe solved. The purpose of this White Paper is first to focus attention on it, analysing its causes and explaining its dangers, and then to suggest what will have to be done by the Government and people of this country ifreasonable price stability is in future to be maintained. fII. Full Employment since 19452. In the years immediately before the war the average rate ofunemployment in the United Kingdom was over 10 per cent. Since the war ithas never (except for a few weeks in 1947) exceeded 3 per cent. For mostof the period 1945-55 it has been under 2 per cent.; and it is now about1 per cent. These figures are for the country as a whole. Unemploymentin Northern Ireland and some other areas has remained appreciably abovethe national average, but has been much lower than before the war.3. The maintenance of full employment has been accompanied by a rapid increase in production. Since 1946 the national output of goods and services has risen by 30 per cent.; industrial production alone has risen by56 per cent. But only part of this increase has been available for improvingliving standards, because there were other, more urgent, claims on our resources to be met. We have had to devote our efforts to making good the physical damage and destruction of the war, to overtaking the arrears of capital investment, and to restoring our overseas earnings, which hadbeen seriously run down during the war. Moreover, we need much largerexports than before the war, partly because import prices have risenmore than export prices, and partly because we have lost a large proportionof our pre-war income from overseas investments. These difficulties hadbeen only partially overcome when, in 1950, the outbreak of war in korea and the growing international tension compelled us to undertake a substantialprogramme of rearmament. In the past two or three years, however, theindividual consumer has become the main direct beneficiary of the increasein production.4. If we take full advantage of the opportunities open to us, thereis every prospect that we shall be able to secure a further big improvementin our living standards in the years ahead. We are on the eve of greattechnical advances in the application of nuclear energy and electronics to industrial processes. Under the stimulus of full employment new attitudesto production are developing on both sides of industry and increasingattention is being paid to raising standards of technical training and education. The possibilities of economic progress and the importanceof productivity command a greater understanding and a wider degree of acceptance than they did ten years ago. As new techniques of production are developed, more efficient methods of work are introduced, and the
benefits of rising investment are felt, we can look forward with confidence to a- continuing expansion of out capacity to produce; and this risingproductive capacity will provide the means for a further progressive improve-ment of our standard of living. It is right that we should look forward tothis possibility: the ultimate objective of economic expansion is to satisfy the natural desire of mankind to enjoy a fuller life, in terms of security and happiness, leisure, and the fulfilment of personal hopes and ambitions.But a sustained growth of the economy is no less essential to enable us todischarge our duties as a major political and industrial Power, to sustain our commitments in many parts of the world, and to contribute to economic development overseas.5. The future growth of production in this country must, of course, beaffected by what happens in other parts of the world. A nation which, isas dependent as the United Kingdom on overseas trade could not hope tomaintain the full momentum of economic expansion in the face of a severeor prolonged recession in the rest of the world. But all member countries of the United Nations are committed, under the United Nations Charter,to mantain full employment; and in the past decade the majority of theindustrial countries have succeeded in doing so. A growing recognition ofthe truth that prosperity is indivisible has found practical expression in the readiness of countries to co-operate in policies designed to ensure a high and expanding volume of world trade, and these policies have proved remarkablveffective, as is shown by the fact that, apart from a minor set-back in 1952,the volume of world trade has been rising steadily, year by year, ever since theend of the war.6. But whatever other countries do, the rate of progress which we shallachieve, and the increase in living standards which we shall attain, will depend mainly on our own enterprise and our own efforts. It is not sufficientthat we should have the capacity simply to produce more. We must be ableto produce and sell abroad enough exports to pay for essential imports offood and industrial materials and at the same time to meet the cost of our overseas capital commitments and to build up the reserves. This meansproducing the kind of goods our overseas customers want, at prices they are willing to pay. In the increasingly competitive conditions which have developed in world markets in the last few years, continually rising costs and prices in this country must inevitably weaken the whole basis of our exporttrade; and if we do not export enough, we shall be unable either to support a steady expansion of production at home or to maintain full employment.Quite apart therefore from the serious economic and social strains theycreate, rising prices endanger the full realisation of the possibilities of economic progress, and it must be one of our major objectives to maintain in future amuch greater degree of price stability than has been achieved in the past ten years.... III. Prices Since 1945 ..: 7. The White Paper of 1944 stated that &quot; It must be regarded as the dutyof both sides of industry to consider together all possible means of preventinga rise in the costs of production or distribution and so avoiding the rise inprices which is the initial step in the inflationary process.&quot; This need for joint action was again stressed in White Papers in January 1947 (Cmd. 7081) andin February 1948 (Cmd. 7321). Yet in fact between 1946 and 1955 the pricesof the final output of goods and services of all kinds increased by over50 per cent.* Apart from the relatively minor effects of changes in subsidies and indirect taxation, which are dealt with in paragraph 10. these prices are* A definition of this price index, and index numbers showing changes in costs and prices between 1946 and 1955, are given in the Appendix.3 .49677 c*
determined partly by the prices of our imports and partly by our own costs of production. These costs of production are themselves determined by the incomes of those who produce the goods&quot; and services at each stage of the productive : process in&quot; other words, by wages and salaries and profits.Increases in incomes need not necessarily lead to rises in costs and prices,but they do so when they rise proportionately, more than production, soputting up costs per unit of output.8. The level of incomes depends on the balance of supply and demandthroughout the economic system as a whole. If demand is significantly inexcess of the supplies available to meet it, the pressure of demand will itselfcontribute to forcing up prices. Prices can also be forced up by pressure for higher incomes even when the level of demand is not excessive. But,generally speaking, the higher the level of demand in relation to supply, theeasier it becomes to obtain larger money incomes and to pass on anyresultant increases in costs in the form of higher prices.9.   The history of prices since the war falls broadly into five phases : (i) The immediate legacy of the war was an accumulation of demand,combined with. a shortage of goods due to the dislocation of pro-duction. World prices therefore rose sharply, and from 1946 to 1948the average prices of our imports increased by 25 per cent. this increase would, if it had been the only factor at work, have raised theaverage level of our final prices by about 5 per cent. But it was accompanied by an excess of demand inside this country and by wide-spread pressure for higher incomes; and because this increase in incomes outstripped the growth of output, costs of production rose,the rise being reflected in ah increase not of 5 per cent, but of 15 percent., in the average level of prices.(ii) During 1948 and 1949 incomes did not increase much faster thanoutput, and costs of production were therefore more stable. Sinceat the same time world supplies were becoming more plentiful, import prices also were rising/less fast. As a result, our own final prices roseappreciably less steeply (by 3 per cent, between the two calendaryears 1948 and 1949),(iii) This period of comparative stability was ended by the act of devaluation of sterling in September .1949, which followed the weakening of the sterling area&apos;s balance of payments in that year.One of the ultimate causes of that devaluation was the earlier post-war rise in prices; and one of the consequences was a marked risein import prices, measured in sterling. Then, in 1950, the KoreanWar provoked a fresh outburst of world demand, particularly for primary products; and import prices rose sharply. This resulted ina rise in retail prices in this country, which itself initiated a demandfor compensating increases in incomes. These increased incomesadded substantially to costs, because at that time it was provingdifficult to increase output: shortage of steel retarded production in1951, and the lower levels of home and overseas demand for textiles,clothing and other consumer goods, which were in. part a reaction from the conditions created by the Korean War, led to an actual fallin industrial output in 1952. In the event, our final prices rose by23 per cent, between 1949 and 1952.(iv) The reduction in the food subsidies and changes in indirect taxesin 1952 had two effects. They added a little to prices in the latter part of that year and in the early months of 1953. They also willhave helped to reduce the pressure of demand. After 1952 thegrowth of production was resumed.  These last two factors together
resulted in a second period of comparative stability. Home costsrose by about 4 per cent, between 1952 and 1954, that is by aboutthe same as in the previous period of comparative stability from1948 to 1950. Moreover, the effect on final prices was furthermitigated by the fall in import prices which occurred during 1952and 1953. As a result, final prices rose by less than 2 per cent,between 1952 and 1954.(v) Towards the middle of 1954 import prices began to rise again andthe upward trend of home costs accelerated as the tendency forincomes to rise faster than output Was accentuated. The combinedresult has been the renewed upward pressure on costs and prices which continued throughout 1955. This is reflected in a further increase in final prices of 4 per cent, between 1954 and 1955.10. This brief summary of the course of our final prices in the past ten years has inevitably compressed into a few paragraphs a highly complexprocess.   But there are certain features which stand out: (a) Since 1946 the prices of the final output of goods and services ofall kinds have risen by about 50 per cent. Of this increase about one-seventh is attributable to the net effect of changes in subsidies and indirect taxes. The rest has been determined by movements in import prices and in our own costs of production.(b) Since 1946 the prices of our imports of goods and services have risen by about 70 per cent., partly as a result of the devaluation of sterling in 1949. In the same period money incomes per unit of output haveincreased by about 45 per cent. But for the economy as a whole ourown costs of production, as measured by money incomes per unit of output, are between four and five times as important as import prices in terms of their effect on final prices. Thus, although the risein import prices has been greater than the rise in our own costs ofproduction, it is the latter which have been responsible for by far thegreater part of the increase in our final prices.(c) Although import prices have risen substantially since 1946, the upward trend has not been continuous. Whenever they have risen theyhave not only added directly to our price level, but also initiateddemands for higher incomes, the result of which has been greatly to magnify the immediate impact on the price level of the rise in import prices themselves. This process, which has proved irreversible,has established, from time to time, a new and permanently higher level of prices in this country. That level has never fallen whenimport prices have fallen, because the gain from lower import prices has been more than offset by the rising trend of incomes and costsat home.11. Much of the rise in prices in the United Kingdom since the war hasbeen due to the quite abnormal world conditions which were associated first with recovery from the war and subsequently with events in Korea; and ourown experience has been shared in varying degrees by rnost other industrial countries. But even apart from these abnormal factors there has been in thiscountry-to a greater extent than in many other countries a continuingtendency for prices to rise as incomes increase faster than output. Thesetendencies have been manifest even when more normal conditions of peace-time full employment have prevailed. This is what gives ground for concern.For if these tendencies persist, and incomes go on rising faster than outputover the economy as a whole, full employment will continue to be associatedwith rising prices and with all the consequent economic and; social strainswhich are discussed in Section V.
IV. Changes in the Distribution of Income\2. Thus, of the factors which determine the level of final prices themost important is our own costs of production, that is, our own incomes and productivity. It is not possible to analyse the extent to which changes indifferent categories of income have contributed to the increases in costs ofproduction, and so to the rise in prices discussed above. But the relativemovements of these categories of income over a period of years are ofobvious relevance and public interest. They are shown in Table 1.&apos; &apos; &apos;     .i &quot; .      - Table 1 -&apos;Changes in Incomes before Tax	  million	Index (1938 = 100)	Shares in total domestic incomes^) (Per cent.)Wages and salaries 1938       ...... 1948       ......... 1955       .........	2,830 6,140 10,075	100 217 356	58 58 60Income from self-employment(2) 1938       ......... 1948       ...      ...... 1955	647 1,328 1,755	100 205 271	13 13 10Gross trading profits of companies and public enterprises(3) 1938       ......... 1948       ...... 1955.......	764 2,018 3,335	100 264 437	16 1Q 20of which: Gross trading profits of companies(3) 1938       ......... 1948       ......      ... 1955       .........	690 1,790 2,910	...(*)	14 17 17Gross trading profits of public enterprises(3) 1938       .......... 1948       ......... 1955	74 228 425		2 2 3O Before providing for depreciation and stock appreciation. Only the main categories of domestic income are shown. Rent, the pay of the Forces, and employers&apos; contribu-tions to the National Insurance Fund and superannuation schemes are not included.The percentages in the right-hand column do not therefore add to 100.(?) Incomes of farmers, professional persons and other sole traders and partnerships beforeproviding for depreciation and stock appreciation.(3) Before providing for depreciation and stock appreciation.&apos;-&quot;(*) Indices are not given as the coverage of each of the two series is affected by successiveacts of nationalisation and denationalisation. The combined series for companies and public enterprises is comparable throughout.Source: 1938 and 1948 National Income and Expenditure, 1955, Tables 1 and 2. 1955 preliminary estimates.
V ..-(3. This table shows that four-fifths of the incomes earned in thiscountry consist of wages and salaries and the gross trading profits of companies and public enterprises; that the total of wages and salaries is about three times as great as the total of gross trading profits; that the latter showed a considerably greater proportionate rise than the former between 1938 and1948; and that both types of income have risen at a more or less equal rate-by about 65 per cent.-in the period between 1948 and 1955.14. The distribution of gross profits as between dividends, taxes and reserves is a separate question. Table 2 provides estimates of the allocation of the total income of companies from their trading and other activities inthe years 1938, 1948 and 1955.Table 2The Appropriation of Company Income^1)  million1938    1948    1955Per cent, of total19381948    1955Dividends on preference andordinary shares(2)Other interest payments, &amp;c.(3) ...United Kingdom taxes onincome(4)Saving before providing for depreciation and stock apprecia-tion(5) ...        .........Total income of companies (6)481160952995122067438958153859551,56547159292293138221026421,0352,3563,720100100100(9 The coverage of this table is affected by successive acts of nationalisation anddenationalisation.   It relates to companies in private ownership at each date.(z) Dividends paid by one company to another are excluded.(3) Debenture interest, co-operative society dividends and interest, interest on building society shares and deposits, other interest paid by banks, &amp;c, and taxes and remittancespaid abroad.(4) Includes additions to tax reserves.(s) Includes additions to dividend reserves.(6) Gross trading profits of companies operating in the United Kingdom as in Table 1,plus trading profits earned abroad and non-trading income.Source: 1938 and \94S-National Income and Expenditure, 1955, Table 29. 1955-preliminary estimates.15. This table shows that in 1938 dividends in the sense in which theyare normally understood, i.e., dividends on the preference and ordinary shares of companies absorbed nearly one half of the total income of companies;taxes took 9 per cent.; and reserves, together with depreciation, less than 30 percent. The balance of about 15 per cent, consisted of a variety of other types of interest payments, together with payment of taxes abroad. In both1948 and 1955 dividends took a little over 20 per cent, of total companyincome; taxes accounted for between one-quarter and one-third; about 40 percent, was set aside to provide for depreciation and stock appreciation charges or put to reserve; and the balance of some 10 per cent, was absorbed by theother items.
16. Dividend payments by companies now constitute about 5 per cefthe total of incomes analysed in Table 1, and their relevance to the movementof prices lies much less in their direct effect on the level of incomes than inthe pressure which they are liable to generate for what are felt to becorresponding adjustments of Wages and salaries. Table 3 compares themovement of dividends over the period 1938-1948-1955 with the movementof wages and salaries. The figures for wages and salaries are the same asthose in Table 1 and cover all incomes of this kind, in whatever industry of occupation they are earned. Corresponding changes for dividend paymentscannot, however, be calculated directly from Table 2 because the coverageof the figures in that table is affected by successive acts of nationalisation anddenationalisation. To ensure the same coverage throughout, the estimatesused in Table 3 are those of dividends paid on ordinary and preference sharesby companies which were not nationalised at any time during the period1938 to 1955.Table changes in Wages and Salaries and Dividends^)iiiili		Wages an	d Salaries	Divid	3nds(x)		  million	Index 1938=100	  million	Index 1938 = 1001938    ..: 1948   ... 1955   ...		2,830 6,140 10,075	100 217 356	426 470 800	100 110 188(x) Dividends paid on preference and ordinary shares by companies which were notnationalised at any time during the period 1938 to 1955. Dividends paid by one company to another are excluded.Source: 1938 and 1948-National Income and Expenditure, 1955, Tables 2 and 30. 1955 preliminary estimates.17. These estimates, which take no account of direct taxation, show that between 1938 and 1948, while prices of consumers&apos; goods and services*roughly doubled, wages and salaries rather more than doubled, and dividendsof non-nationalised companies rose by about one-tenth. Over the period1948 to 1955, while consumer prices rose by about one-quarter, wages and salaries increased by a little under two-thirds and dividends by a little over two-thirds, dividends having in the last few years moved rather faster thanwages and salaries. Taking the period 1938 1955 as a whole, wages and salaries have increased by very much more than dividends; and the real valueof wages and salaries has increased by two-fifths over this period, while thatof dividends has decreased by one-quarter.* The price index used for these calculations covers prices; of consumers&apos; goods and services of all kinds (Item 5 in the Appendix).
V. Price Stability and Economic progress18. Earlier sections of. this paper have referred to the possibility of future economic expansion, and have discussed the forces which have madefor rising prices since 1.945. Unless the upward, pressure of rising money incomes on prices is moderated, the economy is likely, to be, exposed to.serious and increasing strains. These strains, if not relieved, will prevent us from realising the full potentialities of economic growth and may, lead to unemployment by making it more difficult to pay for our imports.19. Our overseas earnings must be increased if we are to pay for theimports needed to sustain an expanding economy, to provide for overseas investment and to build up our reserves. The necessary expansion of exports will depend for its realisation on two factors first, a continuinggrowth of production and trade throughout the world; second, our ownability to secure a sufficient share of this growing trade. The governments policies are directed, in co-operation; with the Governments of many othercountries, to securing the maximum expansion of trade and to creatingconditions in which this trade can flow freely. But no efforts of government alone can ensure that this country reaps the fullest advantage from theexpansion of world trade.20. An adequate volume of exports will depend above all upon the competitive strength of our goods in overseas markets. That strength isitself the outcome of many factors the quality of the product, promptnessof delivery, effective salesmanship, good after-sales service, and so forth.But the basic factor is price. Unless our prices are fully competitive, our exports will be inadequate for our vital national needs, our currency willnot retain its value in world markets, and unemployment will result fromshortage of imported raw materials.21. Competition in overseas markets is keen;, and this country no longerenjoys the pre-eminent position which it held during the last century. To-day we have to match ourselves against formidable rivals, not only in foreing markets, but in the Commonwealth as well. The dislocation caused by thewar left the United States of America the only important source of supply for many goods; and the United States&apos; share of world trade in manufactures*has risen from about 20 per cent, in 1937 to more than 25 per cent, to-day.As against Western Germany we enjoyed a considerable advantage in theyears immediately after the war; even as late as 1950, her share of worldexports was little more than 7 per cent. To-day it is more than doublethat figure. In the same five years the total volume of world trade inmanufactures has risen by over 40 per cent; but our own share has fallen from over 25 per cent, to about 20 per cent.22. A country&apos;s share of world trade is affected by many factors apartfrom its competitive power, and too much weight should not be attached tothe precise percentage at any single point in time. But a continuingdownward trend in the share must inevitably be a cause of concern if itreflects the fact that exports are not increasing sufficiently to meet a growing import bill and to finance other external commitments. Such a situation must be corrected.23. A weakening of the balance of payments is the most obvious and immediate consequence of a disproportionate rise in costs and prices.   But* Strictly, the exports of manufactures of 11 main exporting countries, i,e. (in order ofimportance in 1955) the United States, United Kingdom, Western Germany, France, Canada/Belgium-Luxembourg, Japan, Netherlands, Switzerland, Italy and Sweden.
such a rise, if it persists,,has other, and no less serious, effects at home. Tillfuture growth of the economy will depend upon a sustained expansion of investment; andthe rate of investment which we can afford will dependon our willingness to save. The full effect of continually rising prices onsavings is unpredictable; but it is clear that they can progressively undermine the whole relationship between borrower and lender and thus the acceptedstructures of savings. That structure rests, to a considerable extent, on the willingness; of the lender to hold, for long periods, titles to fixed sums-inthe form of Savings Certificates, Government securities, insurance policies,debenture stock, and so forth. This willingness itself derives from a basicconfidence that money will broadly retain its value. In so far as rising prices impair this confidence and thereby reduce people&apos;s willingness to save,the financing of investment becomes more difficult and more expensive,industrial development is retarded, and the pressure on prices is accentuated.This is particularly serious, because the necessary expansion of production,with a labour force that is not likely to expand much further, will depend ona sustained expansion of investment. A high rate of investment cannot beachieved if too much of our wealth is devoted to consumption, and attempts to maintain both simultaneously at levels we cannot afford only result in further inflation-: 24. But the effects of a rising price level have a much more direct andmore immediately personal impact. Continually rising prices are an obvioussocial evil. For many people this evil is obscured by the fact that they eitherare, or believe themselves to be. able to secure increases in their incomes to offset the rise in prices; and although their pressure for higher incomes itselfadds to the pressure on prices and they do not in fact gain very much fromthe rise in incomes, at least they do not lose very much from the rise inprices. Even so, the spiral of rising incomes and prices is a cause ofconsiderable personal anxiety and of an acute sense of social unfairness. Thedifficulties and hardships inherent in such a situation bear most heavily on those dependent on fixed incomes, who. are in continual danger of having their standard of living progressively reduced. The longer this processcontinues, the more arbitrary its effects appear, and the more sharply the sense of injustice is felt.VI.-The Conditions of Price Stability25. The Government is pledged to foster conditions in which the nationcan, if it so wills, realise its full potentialities for growth in terms of productionarid living standards. But the Government must no less seek to ensure thatthe pressure Of domestic demand does not reach a level at which it threatensprice stability and endangers the balance of payments. To maintain full employment without inflation necessarily involves continual adjustments. at times the pressure of demand will grow too strong and will need curbing;at other times this pressure will be weak, and the economy will need a stimulus. It is the Government^ job to keep the pressure right, and adjustsmerits will have to be made from time to time in fiscal, monetary and socialpolicies in order to achieve this result. But the ultimate aim will alwaysremain essentially the same the encouragement, by all the means which theGovernment commands, of the general climate most favourable to themaximum development of a balanced economy. This demands continuingattention to the problems discussed in Section V; as a nation whose lastingprosperity depends on a high level of overseas trade, we simply cannot afford to allow excessive demand at home to undermine our competitivenessin world markets or to take too much of the output that we need to sellabroad to secure our essential imports.   We must guard against the sense
V.^Alse internal prosperity that can be given by continually rising money incomes unaccompanied by the necessary levels or output and exports, whichcannot last and must ultimately endanger our long-term prosperity, andwith it the whole ideal of full employment as a feature of our national economy. &apos;26. In order to maintain full employment the Government must ensurethat the level of demand for goods and services is high and rises steadily asproductive capacity grows. This means a strong demand for labour, andgood opportunities to sell goods and services profitably. In these conditions it is open to employees to insist on large wage increases, and it is often possiblefor employers to grant them and - pass on the cost to the consumer, somaintaining their profit margins. This is the dilemma which confronts thecountry. If the prosperous economic conditions necessary to maintain full employment are exploited by trade unions and business men, price stability and full employment become incompatible. The solution lies in self-restraint in making wage: claims and fixing profit margins and prices, so that totalmoney - income rises no faster than total output. In the absence of suchself-restraint, it may seem that the country can make a choice albeit apainful one between full employment and continually rising prices, or price stability secured with some danger to the level of employment that might otherwise have been achieved. But soon looms up the grim danger that thefirst of these apparent alternatives will turn out to have been no alternativeat all, because we may fail to secure sufficient imports to maintain full employment and our present standard of living.27. How fast output rises depends on our success in raising produc-tivlty. The achievement of a sustained increase in productivity calls forcontributions from both management and labour. Management must striveto ensure the maximum expansion of output by progressive investment in themost efficient capital assets, by the introduction of the most modern industrialtechniques and by the elimination of all restrictive practices which inhibit theeconomic growth of production. The contribution of labour lies in co-operating to the full in the adoption of new methods of working and insetting aside all practices which, however much they may have been justifiedin the past as means of safeguarding status, conditions of work, or the securityof employment itself, are not appropriate in conditions of full employment.28. The healthy functioning of the economy and the progressive growth of its output depend also on co-operation within industry in maintainingan efficient and enlightened system of industrial relations. The relationship between management and workers which this implies is a vital but intangiblefactor which only they can create by common effort. It demands a fulland frank exchange of opinion and information at all levels between representatives who have confidence in each other&apos;s competence and integrity.If this confidence is achieved and maintained, the gain, in terms both of physical output and of human relations, can be incalculable. If not, the resulting discontent and friction will impede production and hamper exports,thereby discrediting British industry abroad as well as at home.29. Efficient methods of work and sound industrial relations should result in a sustained growth of productivity, yielding economic production and competitive prices. How well off we are as a nation depends not on thesum total of the money incomes we earn, but on the sum total of the goods and services we produce; and. as individuals it is what we can buy with ourpay rather than the pay itself which determines our standard of living. price reductions can therefore contribute to raising our standard of living just as49677D*
much as increases in money incomes, and so far as practicable it is thrC^price reductions that we should aim to enjoy the benefits of higher productivity. If we all press constantly for more money, regardless of how much we produce to spend it on, prices are bound to go on rising. But ifwe concentrate On increasing productivity, and on keeping costs down, price stability can; be achieved along with full employment and a rising standardof living. !&quot;30. From the point of view of industry and trade this means that firms should try, wherever possible, to pass on gains from higher productivity inlower prices and to expand their profits not by the maintenance of highprofit margins, but by the expansion of turnover. This will be easier to achieve in some sectors of the economy than in others, since the scope for increasing productivity,&apos;will vary not because of better or harder work, but because of differences in the amount of capital employed, varying rates of technical progress, changes in the pattern of demand, greater opportunities forsecuring economies from increased output and so forth. If general price stability is to be maintained, it is essential that there should be a positivereduction of prices in those sectors in which productivity tends to risemore rapidly than the average. Enterprises which can achieve an increaseof output and sales by a reduction of costs, including profit margins, will be making a real contribution to the maintenance of price stability and to thewhole process of balanced economic growth.31. The counterpart of realism in relation to prices is realism in relationto personal incomes. The Government of this country does not attempt totell the people what income each one of them ought to be receiving at any given moment. Wages are fixed by free negotiation between employersand workpeople, within a system of collective bargaining which has been built up over a long period of years. By equally well established practice,the level of dividend declared by a company is a matter for recommendation by the directors and confirmation by the shareholders. - But the satisfactoryoperation of this whole system depends upon everyone involved being fully aware of the issues at stake, and upon their acceptance of the full dutiesof citizenship which this realisation places upon them. If they always placesectional interests before the nation&apos;s welfare, economic stability will been dangered and the possibilities of future expansion impaired, possibly tothe extent of jeopardising those very sectional interests which they seek toprotect.32. We all want full employment and we all want stable prices. Butwe have not yet succeeded in combining the two. The experience of thepast ten years has shown that the fuller employment is the more liableprices are to rise; but the Government does not believe that there is anyinevitable conflict between the two objectives. We can achieve them both ifcertain conditions are fulfilled; and it has been the aim of this White paper to state what these conditions are, in the belief that a greater awareness ofthe nature of the problem will contribute to finding a solution for it.
APPENDIXIndices of Prices and Costs since 1946 (1948 ^ 100) (x)j	1946	1947	1948	1949	1950	1951	1952	1953	1954	1955	Percentage increase between 1946 and 19551. Prices of imports of goods and services	81	93	100	102	118	149	143	132	132:	136	68 ,/2. Home costs per unit of output(2)	90	94	100	103	104	111	122	125	127	131	&apos; 46 v3. Price index of final output(3)......	87	94	100	103	107	119	126	127	128	133	:     534. Prices of exports of goods and services	84	92	100	103	110	130	138	130	128	130	LIi55 US5. Consumer price indexC)	87 s	93	: 100	102	106	114	121	. 123	125	131	50 &apos; ;6. Interim index of retail prices(5)		93(&quot;)	100	103	106	116	126	130	132	138	(]) Except for Item 6, the series in this table for 1946 to 1954 are currently weighted price indices derived from National Income and Expenditure,1955, by comparing current price estimates with similar estimates at 1948 prices.  The figures for 1955 are preliminary estimates. ;(2) This index is obtained by dividing estimates of total domestic income (i.e., wages, salaries, gross profits and other trading income, after providingfor stock appreciation) by estimates of the gross domestic product at 1948 factor cost.(3) This index relates to the prices of all goods and services produced for consumption investment and exports.       , . ,y.     ;;:(4) This index relates to the prices of all goods and services bought by personal consumers. i5(s) This index relates to the prices, of those goods and services bought by working-class families.  It differs from the consumer price index in various ways-for instance, by giving a greater weight to food prices (which have risen more than the average) and less weight to rent and rates (which;have risen less than the average).  There is no retail price figure for 1946 comparable to that for the later years. - i(6) Figure for June 1947.

</content>
</cab>
