<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/80/0 images: 272-277</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1956SECRET Copy N0.3 ()CP. (56) 8523rd March, 1956CABINETSINGAPOREMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesIntroductionI am to begin constitutional talks in London on 23rd April with Mr. Marshall,the Chief Minister, and an all-Party delegation from Singapore.2. The talks are in fulfilment of the undertaking given to Marshall last Augustthat we would consider the situation in the light of a year&apos;s working of theconstitution. The events leading up to this undertaking were recorded in theappendix to CP. (55) 162, and in greater detail in CA. (55) 3 which was latercirculated to the Colonial Policy Committee.3. Marshall visited London last December to discuss the agenda for theconstitutional talks and to press for certain interim concessions. At Appendix Ais the statement issued at the end of his visit, which sets out what was agreed.4. I now seek my colleagues approval for the general line to be taken at the talks next month.The Background5. The talks will begin in a highly charged atmosphere of emotional demands for &quot; independence &quot; from rival politicians of limited political experience andvarying allegiances. Some analysis of the political situation in Singapore istherefore essential to a proper perspective of the problems.6. Singapore, with its 80 per cent. Chinese population, is as politicallyconscious and self-conscious as any part of Asia. The politicians representing itsmillion and a quarter people look round at India, Burma, Indonesia andIndo-China and (disregarding the unsophisticated Borneo territories) see singapore as the last remaining stronghold of &quot; Colonialism &quot; in the new Asia, now thatMalaya itself has the promise of full self-government. All political parties arecaught up in the fioodtide of Asian nationalism and anti-colonialism. Nopolitician can command a following without &quot; Merdeka &quot; &quot; freedom &quot; as hiswatchword, or defeat his rivals save by outbidding them in promises and protests.The moderates as always are small in numbers and ineffective in impact.7. This much is common form in the mid-20th Century and part of an inevitable historical process. In Singapore it is made doubly difficult to handle bythe precarious balance of political parties and by the levantine approach and almostpsychopathic personality of the Chief Minister. The elections a year ago underthe present constitution, instead of producing the reasonably responsible Chinesemiddle-class Government for which the constitution has been designed, threw up an assortment of political parties, all &quot; anti-colonial,&quot; all in varying degrees Leftwing, and a surprised and unprepared Marshall found himself head of a mildlySocialist &quot; Labour Front &quot; Government supported by a bare majority of the elected members of the Assembly (13 out of 25). Since then two defections have reduced his support to a minority of the elected members, with the presence of 349737 b
official and 2 of the nominated members giving the Government no more thanequality of numbers with the Opposition in the Legislative Assembly. OfMarshall^ 16 supporters, 13 are Ministers. The Opposition is led by a brilliantWesternised Chinese, Lee Kuan Yew, of Extreme Left-wing sympathies, thoughprofessed anti-Communist. He took a double first at Cambridge. He is not a,fluent speaker in Chinese which limits his appeal to the masses. Behind him is-the more sinister figure of Lim Chin Siong, a shrewd and tough young Chinesewho speaks, little English and is undoubtedly a Communist sympathiser. both these men will be members of the delegation next month: and they and their followers are reputed to be leaving Marshall in power until after the April talks in the hope that he will there obtain greater concessions than they could themselves.They would then contrive to remove Marshall and inherit the concessions. an analysis of the political parties and the composition of the Legislative assembly is at Appendix B.The Central, Issue8. We are unlikely to have in advance of the talks any more preciseindications of what the delegation will demand than the present generalities issuingfrom Singapore about their desire for &quot; independence &quot; or &quot; dominion status.&quot;Marshall was recently in Switzerland for his health and asked for a private talk with me in London. I avoided this, on the grounds of my preoccupation with andimminent visit to Cyprus, since it was clear that had I given him any indication of what Her Majesty&apos;s Government might agree to in the April talks (which was what he was after, and which I was not in any case prepared to give without consulting my colleagues) he would have used the intervening period to build upsuch pressures and develop such arguments as he could against anything I said which did not suit him. He took offence at not being seen, and.is apparentlytaking the line that since I will not be open with him, neither he nor the delegationwill disclose their position on any subjects in advance of the discussions.9. &quot; Independence &quot; for Singapore is a delusion. A trading centre and port,however important, at the mercy of world economics, with a large population andno natural resources, could have no viable place as a full member of theCommonwealth or as a State on its own. marshals own idea of &quot; dominion status,&quot; which he calls the &quot; positive approach &quot; and which was suggested to himby Nehru, is that Singapore should be given full self-government within theCommonwealth in April 1957 and at the same time should hand back to her majesty&apos;s Government, of her own freewill, responsibility for external affairs and defence. Marshall would thereafter expect Singapore to have the status and treatment of other Commonwealth countries, though he also wanted Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment to have the right to resume control if the Communists came into power.This is other considerations apart a logical absurdity and would I am quite sure be unacceptable to other members of the Commonwealth.10. I do not believe we could accept any proposals of this kind, howeverframed or disguised, which limited our direct responsibility solely to external affairs and defence (and Marshall has throughout said he does not wish to interfere withthe base) because they Would leave responsibility for internal security entirely in local hands. I am satisfied that, whatever temporary peace might be bought byhanding over control of the police, we ought not do so at the present stage. Thereasons speak for themselves. The subversive threat is serious and we must beable to ensure that firm action is taken when necessary, and this depends in thelast resort on British troops since there are no local forces: marshals precariousGovernment could at any time be succeeded by a violently Left-wing combination:there would be a general exodus from the police if we handed it over and itsmorale and effectiveness would be gravely affected: if we later were forced to resume control our police force would by then be emasculated and the remnantsof doubtful loyalty: and the maintenance of law and order is vital to the securityof,the base itself, so that a continuing authority in internal security matters isessential to our defence interests.11.   It must be recognised that the Conference could break down over a refusal to concede independence or &quot; dominion status.&quot;  If it did, Marshall would almost certainly resign, and we should be faced with the prospect of an alternativeGovernment in Singapore which might rapidly prove unacceptable to Her, Majesty&apos;s Government.   There might then be no choice but to suspend the
constitution and to replace it by what Marshall has already fatalistically prophesied, would be&quot; rule by British bayonets.&quot; Such action would be bound to be met withwidespread disturbances in the Colony which would concern our friends, and fromwhich our enemies would profit to the full. It might also disturb the present cordialunderstanding with the Federation of Malaya. But it is a course which-even ifwe were not drawn into it by a failure at the Conference -may always be forced upon us in the unstable political circumstances of the Colony, and for which wemust be prepared.12. It is therefore important to ensure that if this drastic and unwelcomestep had to be taken our case before the world is as solidly based as possible, andour goodwill is established beyond doubt. And to do this we must in my viewshow that we have gone as far as our vital strategic and economic interests permittowards meeting the desire of the people of Singapore to manage their own affairs.Further steps to this end are necessary because:  (i) Singapore, though enjoying high comparative standards of culture and education, now lags far behind the interim constitutional arrangements in. Malaya, even without Malaya&apos;s promise of full self-government within the Commonwealth at an early date.(ii) The present constitution is patently capable of useful revision.   TheLegislative Assembly is too small-it leaves the present Governmentwith three backbenchers. And while the constitution gives thesubstance of government into local hands it retains officials on theCouncil of Ministers whose ability to participate in the exercise of power is extremely limited, but whose presence is seen as evidence of a desire to perpetuate in some degree the &quot; Colonial&quot; form ofGovernment.13. In all these matters we must take account of our own view of whereSingapore&apos;s future lies. It seems clear to me that, sooner or later, Singapore mustreunite with the Federation of Malaya unless we are prepared to see it become anindependent Chinese outpost at the strategic heart of South-East Asia.It has long been our policy that Singapore and Malaya should be reunited, butthat this should come about by agreement between themselves and not underpressure from Her Majesty&apos;s Government. This policy would have its dangers ifit were implemented too quickly, but the Chief Ministers of the two territories(after a refusal by Tunku Abdul Rahman to consider asking the constitutional commission for Malaya to make provision for it) have recently agreed that itshould not be further considered until after the next stage in the Federation hasbeen completed.Proposals14. I therefore propose that 1 should endeavour to prevent the Conferencebreaking down over the issue of &quot; independence &quot; by trying to negotiate with the delegation the fullest measure of self-government consistent with reserving to theGovernor control over external affairs, defence, and internal security. This wouldinvolve:(i) An enlarged Assembly of, say, 50 members.(ii) An all-elected Council of Ministers, the 3 officials (Chief Secretary,Financial Secretary and Attorney General) being withdrawn from theLegislative Assembly.   This would in turn mean:(a) A reconsideration of the position of the Chief Secretary, who might possibly become Deputy Governor.(b) The substitution of a Minister of Finance for the FinancialSecretary.(c) The retention of the Attorney General as an official outsidepolitical control (though Marshall is known to wish to make this a political appointment) with full responsibility for the initiation, &amp;c, of prosecutions.(hi) The creation of some special machinery for handling the reservedsubjects: I have in mind that the control of these subjects should be reserved to the Governor in his discretion, but that he would have asmall Committee of Ministers to assist him in discharging his49737 B 2
responsibilities.    Legislation would normally  be  enacted  by  theLegislative Assembly and introduced by the Chief Minister, but theGovernor would have the power to promulgate laws affecting thesereserved subjects in his own discretion, subject to reference back tothe Secretary of State in case of local disagreement,(iv) I also propose that I should endorse our previous statements of policy,that reunion with Malaya represents the logical and most satisfactory. future for Singapore, and I would hope that, the possibility of:    Singapore finding her fullest self-government as part of a largerFederation of Malaya might help to deflect the delegation from theirillusory demands for immediate independence.   A watertight defence agreement with the Federation (on which local negotiations are dueto start shortly) would provide a basis for securing our defence requirements in Singapore in the event of reunion.15.   There are three other matters I must mention.(i) I would propose that any arrangements reached at the Conference sffouidbe dependent on our securing a proper and equitable scheme ofcompensation for the members of Her Majesty&apos;s Overseas CivilService serving in Singapore, and on their being fairly treated in theprocess of Malayanisation. A recent report by a local committee onthis subject is a vindictive and short-sighted document.(ii) I would like to do something to meet the intense desire of Marshall andothers to get rid of the word &quot; Colony.&quot; It would help materially andmight be indispensable towards agreement if we could do so. I wouldlike to explore with my colleagues most concerned the possibility of singapore being designated the &quot; State of Singapore,&quot; without thisimplying any general policy towards the smaller territories. This name(and it need have no special significance other than a local pertinence)would be in harmony with the possible later conjunction of singapore and the existing States of the Federation of Malaya: and thiscircumstance might itself justify the new title.(iii) Mr. marshals proposals for a Singapore citizenship have been by agree-ment postponed for consideration at the Conference. He is anxiousto secure the allegiance to Singapore of the 200,000 local Chinese whowere not born there, and who are technically aliens, and who claim that naturalisation involves too many difficulties of expense and &quot; face &quot;for them to apply for it. Mr. Marshall wanted to create a localcitizenship by local legislation but (apart from not obtaining the supportof his Malay colleagues) he is unwilling to accept the fact that thiswould not give those concerned any nationality other than the Chinesenationality they already have and would consequently not secure either the travel documents or the protection of Her Majesty&apos;s posts abroadwhich the Chinese seek. This problem is under discussion between my Department, the Foreign Office and the Home Office. I do notthink my other colleagues need be troubled with it unless these discussions show this to be necessary. It may also be held in suspenseif it is agreed at the talks that any agreement should look towards a later link-up with Malaya, since premature legislation aboutcitizenship in Singapore in advance of a solution of the same problem in Malaya might prejudice successful reunion of the two territories.16. I am sorry that, in the circumstances explained earlier in this paper,it is not possible to submit proposals in any more detail for the approval of theCabinet. I believe, however, that the proposals I have made in this paper coverwhat will be the principal issues in the forthcoming talks, and I invite my colleagues to approve them.A. L.-B.Colonial Office, S.W.1,22nd March, 1956.
APPENDIX a press STATEMENTTalks between the Secretary of State for the Colonies and Singapore MinistersMr. David Marshall, the Chief Minister of Singapore, accompanied byMr. Lim Yew Hock, the Minister for Labour and Welfare, and Inche AbdulHamid bin Haji Jumat, the Minister for Local Government, Lands and Housing,has been having talks during the past week with the Secretary of State for theColonies, Mr. Alan Lennox-Boyd, and officials of the Colonial Office. The talkswere cordial and constructive.As has been previously announced, the primary purpose of the talks was toarrange the agenda for discussions in the spring of next year when Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment have invited a delegation from Singapore to come to the UnitedKingdom to review the situation in the light of a year&apos;s working of the present constitution.It has been provisionally agreed that the Constitutional Conference should begin in London on the 23rd April, 1956. It is expected to last about two to threeweeks.It has also been agreed that the agenda for the talks in April should be:  id) A definition of internal self-government;(b) A date for the introduction of internal self-government;id) The structure of the Legislative Assembly;id) The future of the Public Service;ie) External relations and external defence;(/) Any other business.The main purpose of the talks having been completed successfully, and agreement having been reached on the matters which it had been proposed todiscuss, Mr. Marshall also raised several other questions.Mr. Marshall said that there was a desire in Singapore that its major languagesshould be recognised in the Legislative Assembly. The Secretary of State saidthat he saw practical disadvantages in such a step, but that he would recommend amendment of the constitution to enable the Assembly to introducemulti-lingualism if it so wished.Mr. Marshall also discussed the possibility of introducing a Singaporecitizenship for which the large number of adult aliens, principally Chinese,domiciled in Singapore would be eligible. The Secretary of State said that he had considerable sympathy with the desire of the domiciled alien population to acquirecitizenship rights but he thought that the matter ought to be examined in Aprilin the context of the wider constitutional issues by which it might be affected.In response to a request from the delegation it was agreed that the control oflocal National Service men should in future be a matter for the Council ofMinisters.Mr. Marshall then raised the question of the right of access of the Civil service staff Association to the Chief Minister. He agreed with the Secretary of State thatthe Civil Service should be kept divorced from politics and that there could be noquestion of the Chief Minister concerning himself with personal issues of any kind such as individual promotions or appointments. It was, however, agreed that civil Service Staff Associations should have the right to approach the chief minister through the Chief Secretary on matters affecting general conditions ofservice and public policy relating to the Public Service.Mr. Marshall stated that he found the pressure of business upon him as chief minister at this formative stage such that he was unable to devote sufficientattention to his responsibilities as Minister of Commerce and Industry and he proposed that the Chief Minister be relieved of a Ministerial portfolio and that oneof the Assistant Ministers be promoted to be Minister of Commerce and Industry.It was agreed that for this purpose the number of appointed Ministers should beincreased from six to seven.
APPENDIX BComposition of the Legislative Assembly, SingaporeSpeaker :GovernmentOpposition3 Ex-officio.8 Labour Front.3 Alliance.2 Nominated.6322Peoples Action Party.Liberal Socialists.Independents.Nominated.Ex-Labour Front.1616Notes(1) The Labour Front is led by Mr. Marshall, the Chief Minister. It has littleparty organisation or cohesion apart from Mr. marshals leadership.(2) The Alliance (UMNO/MRCA). Led by Enche Abdul Hamid but followsthe line of Tunku Abdul Rahman, the Chief Minister and Leader of the alliance in the Federation of Malaya.(3) The two nominated members on the Government side were nominated bythe Governor on the suggestion of the Chief Minister. One is the deputy Speaker.(4) Peoples Action Party. Left, with a Communistic wing. Led by Lee KuanYew.(5) Liberal Socialists. A new party resulting from the union of the progressive and Democratic Parties. These were middle-classconservative. The new party lacks unified leadership and has no firmpolicy.   It has so far tried to gain support by outbidding the Left wing.

</content>
</cab>
