<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/30 images: 506-511</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
P^Hnrument is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovernmentPrinted for the Cabinet, January, 1940SECRETW.P. (R.) (40) 30Copy No. &quot;2-to BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet war OFFICE PROGRESS REPORT (DECEMBER, 1939)(Previous Paper No. W.P. (R.) (39) 122)MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WARI. Formations and PersonnelGeneral.(a) The total number of British Troops under arms (excluding native troops:id Indian Army) is as follows : 	November	December	IncreaseE) Great Britain and N. Ireland   ...       ......... pi) British Expeditionary Force pi) Garrisons and Defended Ports ...      ...      ...... p) India and Burma... Total.....................	777,000 188,000 60,000 37,000	838,000 200,000 61,000 38,000	61,000* 12,000 1,000 1,000	1,062,000	i,I35.ooo	75,000* Includes Canadian contingent (b) The following gives the detail of item (i) : 			 	November	December	Increase or decreasejb.G.B. hj^t Defence ... bpe Defence Bns. kjmng Units......      &quot;&apos;        &quot;&apos; W&amp;M^r- esfablishments and Field Force Formations ... hf^11 Contingent................ m To:al hi 777&quot;&quot;&quot;------	133.000 12,500 21,500 193,000 417,000	148,500 13,300 30,600 222,500 407,800 15,000	4- i5,5oo 4- 800 4- 9,100 4- 29,500 - 9,200t 4- 15,000	777,000	838,000	4- 61,000stry,- . J un-   ^UUIU-UUL   Ul   LUG    JL ll.KJi.LL     VJr. it immature, posted to A.D.G.B. and Coast Defence.
2. During December (i)   25,900 men  enlisted  voluntarily, making a total   of   119,500 s;n3rd September, 1939. &apos;&apos;    &quot; l.e.(2) Army Class intake amounted to 29,200, bringing the total to 160 orsince the inception of compulsory service.3. Over 8,000 candidates for commissions have been posted to Officer CadetTraining Units.4. British Expeditionary Force.A large number of units totalling 24,000 men were despatched to France asreinforcements for the B.E.F. Against this the numbers despatched home fromthe B.E.F. on account of sickness, immaturity, release from labour duty, courses and the like, amounted to a few thousands.5. Garrisons and Defended Ports Abroad.(a) The present strength of army personnel is: 	November			December			British	Native	Total	British	Native	TotalDefended Ports Middle East   ......... West Africa   ... East Africa Other Garrisons Totals ...	20,soo 35.400 ioo 3.500	23,200 13,600 13,000 20,900 1,500	44,000 49,000 13,000 21,000 5,ooo	20,800 37,400 100 2,700	20,800 14.500 13,000 25,000 1,700	41,600 51.900 13.000 25,100 4,400	59,800	72,200	132,000	61,000	75,000	136,000Note. -India and Burma excluded.(b) The first Flight of the Cavalry Division is en route to Palestine. Thbalance is due to sail during January, 1940.6. Troops in the United Kingdom other than A.D.G.B.(1) The 55th Division moved from Western Command to Charnwood Forest.(2) The 160th Infantry Brigade (less the 2nd Battalion, The MonmouthshirRegiment) moved from Western Command to Northern Ireland, and relievedregular  Infantry Battalions, which in their turn joined the 49th, 44th an1st Armoured Divisions respectively in England.aiII. Equipment7. Hutted Hospitals for the B.E.F.Orders have been placed for the balance of requirements.   It has beearranged that one 1,200-bed and one 600-bed hospital will be delivered eveweek, beginning in March, 1940.   The total requirements to be supplied17,200 beds, i.e. 10 weeks&apos; deliveries.8. Nissen Huts.Despatches of Nissen Huts to France were made at the rate of 400 a week.9. Aerodromes for the B.E.F.Orders to the value of approximately  350,000 have been placed for e caXconcrete mixers, narrow gauge permanent way, etc., for aerodromes in riaI
io   Liquid Fuels and Lubricants,-0win hand    ...      -      ......itimated for completion Dy......-    ...itimatc of completion&apos;date in last report ...Percentage of Authorised Reserves nowin the United KingdomPetrolLightDiesoleumLubricants65 per cent.30th June,194030th April,I940100 per cent.31st December,193923 - 6 per cent.29th February,194031st January,1940   ,The limiting factors are once more the completion of tankage and thevailability of tanker tonnage.1. A. A. Guns for A.D.G.B.Number on the strength of A.D.G.B.3-inch3* 7-inch4-5-inchLight A.A. Guns 2-pdrs.(Single and Twin)th November, 1939...St December, 1939......Net receipts during month   ,3613603433672421424026Si1642312. AA. Equipment for the B.E.F.3-in.3.7-in.; during December, 1939actually with B.E.F. on 28th December,:I939............    - ... &apos;ptabhshment...................  ._______Surplus or deficiency ...      ...12048A- 722472192-120LightA.A. guns40148252-104Searchlights120192288- 96III. StoresAmmunition. , ,The tonnage to be shipped in January will practically complete the 2nd andline equipment and the Base Reserve and Transit Stock for thesistand2ndntingents, including the T.A. increment. One or two items ^^^^February, by the end of which 2&quot; mortar ammunition should alone be outndingIV. Supplies to Dominions and Alliesembef S^FlJKA gives a Hst of items of equipment  despatched  duringuei to Allied and other countries.(4429)
V. Transportation15. The following table shows the numbers of personnel and the quantitiescertain equipment and stores shipped to France during December.	, Personnel Nos.	M.T. Vehicles Nos.	Ammunition D.W. Tons	Petrol D.W. Tons	General Stores D-W. TonsNovember (for  com-parison). December	17,000 26,000*	1,700 1,600*	7.5O0 2,600	29,800 5.400	57,ooo 3Q.0O0During the month the following numbers of personnel were shipped from theB.E.F. to the U.K. :-Leave   ...      ...      ...      ...      ....     ...   25,590*:Other reasons ...       ...      ...      ....      ...     5,340*16. During December the following personnel, equipment and stores wereshipped to ports, etc., abroad, other than for the B.E.F.	Personnel Nos.	M.T. Vehicles Nos.	Tanks Nos.	Guns Nos.	-Stores of all sons measures. TonsDecember...	1.450	502	5	32	16,17017. Railway Material for France.(a) Rolling Stock. Orders for the 10,000 covered goods wagons referred to last month have now been placed, and will be delivered from March, 1940, a300 to 400 a week.(b) Ambulance Trains. Orders have now been placed to bring the total up tthirteen.   The 5th and 6th trains should be ready during January.18. Development at Home.(a) A provisional design for train ferries has been agreed by all concernedNegotiations are in progress with the Southern Railway for the installation ofTerminal at Southampton, and with the French for one at Havre.(b) Development schemes fcr the ports of Poole, Newhaven and Littlehamptoare well in hand.   Other schemes are under investigation.* Includes R.A.F.O.F.G.S.The War Office,20^ fanuary, 1940.
APPENDIX AWAR OFFICE PROGRESS REPORT (DECEMBER, 1939)Equipment dispatched from Army stocks to allied and other countries during december, 193912 3&apos;7-inch A.A. Equipments mobile.S 3-7-inch A.A. Equipments static.12 Holdfasts for static A.A. Equipments.20,000 Rounds 3-7-inch A.A. Ammunition.5 Heightfinders.5 Predictors.12 Scammell Tractors.5 Light Tanks.20,000 Rounds 18-pounder shell, H.E.200 Anti-Tank Rifles.10,000 Rounds -55-inch S.A.A. for Anti-Tank Rifles.ilattd60,000 Respirators, G.S.60,000 2-oz. outfits Anti-Gas Ointment.10,000 Anti-Tank Mines, Mark III.100 Anti-Tank Rifles.40,000 Rounds -55-inch S.A.A.100 Vickers Machine Guns.1,000,000 Rounds S.A.A.200 Verey Pistols.20,000 Cartridges, Signal.50,000 Hand Grenades.25 4-5-inch Howitzers.20,000 Rounds Ammunition 4 - 5-inch Howitzers.The following were also prepared for shipment early in January 5,000 Tents.100,000 Greatcoats.100,000 Mess Tins and covers.100,000 Uniforms.1,000 Tons Biscuit.300,000 Blankets300,000 Groundsheets.50,000 Pairs Gumboots.20,000,000 Sandbags (diverted from our orders from India).4 Bren Light Machine Guns.150 Steel Helmets.50 Anti-Tank Rifles.10,000 Rounds -55-inch S.A.A.1 B.E.S.A. Machine Gun.itieium 4 3-7-inch A.A. Guns.10,000 Pairs Gumboots.60   1/40  W.O.P.  4429


</content>
</cab>
