<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 24-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS D0CUK3KT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)THE FOLLOWING- ;7BRE ALSO PRESENT: -Sir W.A. Robinaon, K.C.B.,O^B.B.First Secretary, Ministry of Health.Mr. E.R. Forber, C.B.3., Ministryof Health.FINAL COPY. CONCLUSIONS of a Conference of ,-* Ministers held in the Beard RobinTreasury, on Tuesday 12th July,19SI, at 12 Noon.&apos;P RE S E N T:The Right Hon.. Sir Robert Home,G.B.E. ,X.C ,M.F.&apos;, Chancellor ofthe Exchequer, (in the Chair).&apos;The Right Hon. Sir A. Mond, Bart.&apos;,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right &quot;Eon. H.A.L.Fisher,&apos;M.P.,President of the Board of Education.The Right Hon. 3f;&apos;J.&apos; Mao name ra,&apos; M.P. ,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon..&apos; C. Addison, M..P.The. Right Hon. R. Munro, K.C.&apos;,M.P.,&apos;Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon.   .CA. McCuxdy, IC.C,M.P-.Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury.Ms?. T. Jones.....................&apos;. ......... .Priaoipal Assistant Seoreta:Mr. T. St. Quintin Hill..................... Principal.
ioElTOE OF TIE;     (1)     She Chancellor eiatseL that he had received aJCiir-TARY FORiCTLABI1. strong protest from the Secretary for Scotland against thj. holding of a Conference of Ministers on the subject of housing at a time when he was engaged in the House ofCommons in connection with the Railway Bill and thereforeunable to attend.The Chancellor of the Exchequer added that he had. arranged that the statement which had been prepared bythe Minister Of Health for. announcement in the House ofCommons would be shewn to the Secretary for scotland in draft.if)?0SED STATE- (2) The Conference met in accordance with Cabinet 58 (21mi BY THESINISTER OF Conclusion 14, and had before them a draft which hadDSAiTB.been prepared by the-Minister of Health on the statement which he proposed to make in the House of Commons (SeeAppendix),     The Conference agreed to the following; -(1) To approve the first paragraph of theDraft without alteration;(2) To insext the words &quot;for the time being at any rate&quot; after the first sentence inthe second paragraph.(3) To leave for further consideration thequestion whether the time for completion ofwork by local Authorities should be extendedbeyond July 1922, as suggested in paragraphS of the Draft;  -   -(4) To approve July 1st as the date by whichhouses will have to be begun in order toqualify7 for the subsidy, and to alter the wording of the draft to the following:-&quot;and additional houses will be subsidised only if begun before 1st July&quot;,(5) To approve the insertion of the following words     in line 3- of paragraph 5 of theDraft after the word &quot;year&quot;;- &quot;includingthe absorption of considerable &quot;numbers ofox-service men&quot;.(6 ) To
f6) To insert the word &quot;contemplated&quot;after the phrase, &quot;larger clearanceschemes&quot; in line 4 of paragraph of the Draft,(3)   During the consideration of the Draft Statement bythe Minister of Health the change of policy decided on by the Government was the subject of discussion.    It was &apos;pointed out that the present Conference had been convenednot to consider questions of policy which had alreadybeen settled by previous minutes of the Cabinet tar.fi the.Finance Committee, but to decide the exact form of thegeneral statement to be made by the Minister df Health..At the same time the Minister tJibhout portfolio state-d.that he still desired to challenge the decision of the for the reasons set out inFinance Committee/ his Memorandum of July 4th(CP .3108) Considerahhdiscussion ensued as to the wisdom of the policy laiddown by the Finance&apos; Committee.    It was urged in supportof reconsideration of thajb policy that by the cancellation of contracts and by the abrupt termination of building,the Government would in effect be dishonouring its obligations.     It was true that the statement preparedby the Minister of Health expressly said that all expenditure in connection with Housing Schemes which hadbeen incurred by Local Authorities with the^ approvalof the Ministry of Health would rank for financialassistance under the present scheme (which limited the liability of local Authorities to the produce ofa Ido rate&quot;), but if this meant that the Governmentwould suspend all building operations at once and soleave derelict     sites on which houses were not actually being erseted but which had been preparedby the laying of roads-and sewers, etc? the result woiaJLd
&quot;be an actual -Jiltougir-pexhs^ acrb&apos;-s^.t^c^ixy^aJ^. - Jb:ffe&amp;oluof faith.      It should not be forgotten that since .theArmistice the Government had exercised, continualpressure on local Authorities to support new schemes and float loans and generally concentrate their energieson large housebuilding operations,by Er, AddisonIt was urged/that it would be wrong now:for theGovernment1 to suspend immediately all builddng operationsexcept-those for which it had incurred,a local obligationby reason of the approval, of contracts.    The right policy was not to suspend the building operations permanently,but to delay those operations and spread them over a longer period of time, say three or four years,,    This latter.policy would&quot; not have any different result from thatadvocated by -the Minister of Health, at least during the,next year,  since the whole building trade would bo fully occupied in completing schemes for which the Government,accepted responsibility.     The result of.publicly with-drawing Government support to Housing Schemes in contemplation would be a complete cessation of housebuilding in this country since contractors could notbuild to let at an economic rent.     Moreover, there wouldbe no confidence in any future pledge &amp;iven by theGovernment if it were at any time decided to rene\^ theGovernment&apos;s support to house building.     Politically,moreover, an abrupt suspension of Government support to house building would be disastrous.It was pointed out,  on the other side, that theFinance Committee had decided and the Cabinet had approved the decision, that Government support should not begiven to&apos;the building of more than 1^6,000 houses,..Latitude was allowed, however,  in cases where there wasa scheme which was not so far completed, but which could.be rounded off-, and the Minister of Health had discretion(subject to the general limit of ITS 000 houses) to allow the
the erection of houses in particular places where-such houses were necessary for the completion of ascheme.   The estimated margin for this purpose was about12,000houses.    Reference was made to the difficulty ofJ3i . . other&apos; than approved tendersfinding a universal test/by which it could be decided whether the Government wore committed to the erection ofhouses ,ta any particular place and it was urged that under the proposal to spread out building operations forthree or four years the Government liability would beunascertainable and in any case very much greater than thatcontemplated by the Cabinet.     The Government would finditself in the morass of continuing corarai allotments,.The Conferenoe agreed:(1) That the concluding sentence of thesecond paragraph of the Draft statement should be &quot;altered to read as follows;-&quot;it is o^course oisvious that all ex-penditure in connection with theHousing Scheme which has alreadybeen incurred by local authorities with the approval of the Minister ofHealth will rank, etc.&quot;(2) That at the end of paragraph 2. of the Draft ,statement the following sentence should beinserted:-&quot;except with the prior consent of theMinister of Health no further assistance will be given by the State in respectof any houses for which        contractshavo not been made.&quot;(3).    That tine LUuxuxar wit no at portfolio should,(   ]      in consultation with the Officials ox the- Ministry of Health prepare a memorandum for consideration by the Conference at aMoating to be held at 10.30 a,ra, in *hQTreasury Board Room on Wednesday   July 13th,19 1     This Memorandum to ahow thealternative form of statement to the Houseof Commons pr^cssad by Dr. Addison.
HOUSINGSUBSIDYSLUMAREAS(4)     The Conference were informed that this subsidyhad been in some measure misused for the erection of dwellings other than -working class dwellings and thatsome reference might well be made to the fact in the minister of Health&apos;s statement.It was pointed out, however, that no greatabuse could exist because of the restriction of thecubic capacity of the houses to a maximum of 1,400 ft.The Conference agreed -What the Minister of Health should notin his statement refer to the allegedmisuse of the subsidy to private builders.(5) The Conference were informed that the annual contribution of  BOO,000 was necessary in view ofthe length of time which must elapse between the floating of loans by Local Authorities to improveslum areas and the actual execution of work on thoseafceas.     Unless the Government made a contributionto the interest on the loans, Local Authorities wouldbe unwilling to operate.-The Conference agreed - and the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer concurred -That the Treasury should provide a.maximumannual contribution of  200,000 towardsthe deficiency of capital charges on slumareas during the currency of loans raised on approved schemes.OuJHClUBING   (6) The Conference agreed -PARAGRAPHOP That the&apos; announcement by the MinisterANNOUNCEMENT of Health should conclude with a brief/statement of what had actually been.effected under the housing schemes.since the Armistice,METHOD OP     (7)    It was stated that the announcement of the changeANNOUNCEMENTin housing policy would be made in answer to a question in the House of Commons.    The announcement had therefore been drafted in a concise form.     If however the adjournmont was moved, as was quite likely, it would bo necese-arto be prepared with a more elaborate exposition of  he&apos;&quot;v:&apos;,:&apos;:v&apos;::&apos;.:: &apos;-fGovernments policy . \sWhitehall Gardens, S.W,July 12th 1921 i
APPENDIX.In view of the very grave .financial&apos;. clifficultiesconfronting the nation and the Government at present andin the next financial year owing to the unparallelledand world-wide depression in trade and the unfortunateindustrial troubles which have, so seriously affectedboth expenditure and revenue, the Government after themost careful consideration have come to the decision,        ,with great regret, that the Housing programme must be subjected to a general review.The Government, therefore, finds itself compelled tocome to the decision of limiting the present expenditureon housing schemes.    With this object it has been decided-to limit the number of houses to be constructed by localauthorities and publio utility societies under the present scheme to 176000.  &apos; This is the number of houses for whichtenders have been approved,      It is, of course,  obviousthat all expenditure in connection with, the housingschemes which has been incurred by local authorities with the approval of the Ministry of Health will rank for financial assistance under the present scheme, which limits the liability of local authorities to the produce of a penny rate.In cases where work undertaken by local authorities with the.approval of the Ministry of Health cannot for reasons outside the control of the authorities be completed by July 1922, the time for completion will be extended bythe Ministry as may be necessary.As regards the scheme of Subsidy to private builders,the powers taken under the recent Act will be exercised tothe extent of making payment in full for houses completed&apos;, within.... .o.
3 ftwithin the four months after the expiration of theprevious Act., i.e., by April SSrd last, and additionalhouses will be subsidised if begun before the 1stJuly.     There will be oases in which commitments havebeen entered into, although the construction has not actually been begun, in anticipation of the continuanceof the Subsidy.     In order to meet these cases discretionwill be vested in.the Ministry of Health, to allowSubsidy to be paid and if building is started within one month of the present date,- where commitments havebeen entered into before the present announcement of theGovernment policy.There is sufficient building in hand, and in prospect to occupy the building industry for at least ayear and during that time it is the intention of theGovernment to re-examine the whole sitriation and to review the policy so as to bring it into closer relationto the financial capacity of the country.The Government recognise the urgent necessity ofmaking what improvements are possible under fresentfinancial circumstances in slum areas.    While iijmaynot be possible to carry out larger clearance schemes the Government are of opinion that much pan be doneby measures of improvement ovement and amelioration.    In -*?rder.to assist local authorities in such work they are preparedto provide an annual contribution not exceeding 200., 000 towards the deficiency of capital charges -on slum areas.    This contribution will continue&apos; forthe whole term of the loans to be raised by localauthorities to defray the necessary expenditure.    Bymeans of this contribution it is estimated, that about 4,000,000 could be expended in the improvement,vofsuch areas..

</content>
</cab>
