<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 95-100</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS .POCUJCEM IS THE PROPERTY OP HISBRIBUffllO MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).rEC RET,FINAL COPY NO,CONCLUSIONS of a Conference Of Ministershalo, ut 10, Dawning Street, S.W.1., on Thursday,24th November, 1921, at 5 p.m*PRESENT s -THE PRIME MINISTER(IN THE CHAIR),The.Right Han. A, Chamberlain,M.P*, Lord Privy-Seal,[The Right Hon. W.S. Churchill.LP*, Secretary of State for colonies.Ilhe Right-Hon. Sir L, Worthlngton-JBvans, Bart^^ M.P., Secretary .lof State for War.The most Hon. The Marquess Curzsnof Kedlestcn^ K.G., G.C.S.I.,G.C.I,E., Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. E,S. Montagu, M,P,,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. S, Baldwin, M.P.,President-of the Board of Trade.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT;Vlce-A.admiral Sir Henry F. Oliver,K.C.B., K.C.M.G.) M.V.O.,Acting First Sea Lord.(for part of Conclusion 1 only).Thomas Jones.... t........... *Michel S.H. Wilson,, C.B., C.M.G..Acting Secretary, Cabinet.
WASHINGTON CONFERENCE.

(1) With reference to Cabinet 88(21) Conclusion 5, and Appendix I, the Conference had before them the following papers:-

Telegram from Mr. Balfour, Washington, No. 28 of November 17th, 1921.

10th Minutes of Standing Sub-Committee of Committee of Imperial Defence, dated October 14th, 1921.

Wei-hai-Wei. Proposed surrender of.

It was explained that the matter had been put down for discussion in consequence of the receipt from Mr. Balfour of the telegram dated November 17th, 1921, and in view of the fact that the Geddes Committee were taking special interest in the possibility of cutting down expenditure by reducing the strengths of British naval and military garrisons oversea.

During the discussion which ensued it was suggested that if any naval or military forces were maintained at Wei-hai-Wei it was not for the protection of that place, but as a matter of convenience, and that in view of the situation in North China it was essential to keep a certain number of troops in that part of the world apart altogether from the fact that in the future Wei-hai-Wei might be developed as a useful naval base. At the same time it was pointed out that under existing conditions Wei-hai-Wei had no strategical importance.

The conditions under which Wei-hai-Wei had been originally leased to Great Britain were explained to the Conference, and it was pointed out that it would be no breach of faith if Great Britain still retained Wei-hai-Wei as Japan had simply replaced Russia in Port Arthur.

Attention was called to the fact that in the past Great Britain had surrendered territory which was greatly regretted afterwards, viz: Holigoland, Corfu and Java, and it was suggested that in no circumstances should His Majesty&apos;s Government agree to give up any territory   
territory without knowing what they were going to get in return and what the other Powers represented atWashington were ready to do.     Emphasis was laid on theinexpediency of making any concessions to China so longas the country was in its existing chaotic position,and it was pointed out that in any case if any concessionswere made it should be as part of a general bargain, andthat in her present position it would be ridiculous to hand over anything to her as a gift.It was explained to the Conference that Mr. Balfourhad also raised the question of releasing China from herobligation to pay to Great Britain her share of the&quot;B&amp;xer indemnity&quot; which amounted to some  10,000,000.During the discussion which ensued it was argued that there was no reason for Great Britain giving up 10,000,000 to which she was justly entitled.     As inthe case of Wei-hai-Wei, it was contended that any concessions in connection with the indemnity should alsoonly be made as part of an all round bargain and with a stable Chinese Governments     It was further contended that His Majesty1s Government should only agree to remittheir share of the Indemnity on three conditions; firstly,that there should be an all round remission;    secondly,that any remission at all should be dependent on theestablishment of a united and stable Government inChina; and thirdly, that if and when the British shareof the indemnity was remitted part of the money shouldbe spent on the education of Chinese on British lines,Regarding the whole question of concession to Chinait
It was suggested that Instructions should he sent   toMr0 Balfour saying that the British Delegation worenot; on their own, to raise the question of makingconcessions; that before any such concessionswere made it was essential to know what the otherPwoers proposed to doj   and further that while heshould be quite ready to discuss such questions no    :arrangement should be come to except on the condition that any concessions which were made should be made toa recuperated and reconstituted OhinaeIt was agreedThat the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should send atelegram to Mr0 Balfour on thelines of the discussion which hadtaken place,WASHINGTON       (2) In the course of the preceding discussionCONFERENCE.Naval Policy,reference was made to the Views in regard to naval policy and particularly to submarines which werebeing expressed at Washington,The Conference agreedThat a further meeting of theCommittee of Imperial defence should be suramonod to review the positionoDRAFTS (3) The Secretary of State for War raised theFORINDIA, question of the despatch of drafts to India,     he explained to the Conference that In addition to somedrafts the men composing which were serving in Ireland,two Battalions were due to leave for India on the 1stand 3rd of December next.     It was necessary for theWar Office to get an early decision as to whether these battalions were to be sent or not, as otherwise -It would upset the whole of the War Office arrangementsfor the reliefs to be carried out during the ensuing
trooping season and would cost a lot of money.It was pointed out how inexpedient it would be under existing conditions to take away troops from ireland as drafts for India, and at the same time itwas explained to the Conference that tho two Battalionswhich it was proposed to send abroad were not atpresent in Ireland, and that their despatch would notin any way affect the strength of the Irish garrisonexcept in so far as these formations were potentialreserves for the reinforcement of that garrison.It was agreed -That the two regiments should be despatched as arranged, on the 1stand 3rd December next, but thatthe drafts should be held up pend-ing the Secretary of State for Indiacommunicating with the Viceroy onthe subject;PR003DDES IN     (4)        The Prime Minister , aalled the attention of theCOMMUNICATINGWITH THE BRITISH Conference to a t&amp;lear&amp;m whioh had been sent direct fromDELEGATION ATWASHINGTON.       the Board of Trade tc Sir Hubert Llewellyn Smith atifWashington, and to a letter from the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to the Aoting Secretary, Cabinetin connection therewith.It was pointed out how undasirsble it was for any single department to eommaiiioate direct with theirrepresentatives at 7?ashinjgton, and especially on matters which were under consideration by Cabinet Committees orthe ComaittQQ of Imperial Defence, and emphasis was laid on the importance of all massages sent to Mr.Balfour, or sent by Mr. Balfoar to His Majesty&apos;s Governmentpassing through either the Foreign Office or the cabinet secretariat, who should&quot; be held responsible for seeing that they t*;are properly dealt with.
It was agreed -(a)    That the Acting Seoro-tary to theCabiiaet ah**ald arrange with theSeorotary of State for ForeignAffairs as to whether the Foi-oignOffice or the Cabinet Secretariatshould be the responsible Department.fb)   That the necessary instructions should be issued to the British4Delegation at Washington and to the      ;Depar-smsn ts in  onion to ensnre that vin future all metssages to and from war?hiugton are sent through theah&amp;siie*i agrood upon.THrOD 0F-^PEXSCB^i5)     The Saor^tarr of State for India road a03? TCAEBS TOINDIA. telagrani.from-theMJowrnor of Bombay describing the remarkable reoeptioA aooordo^^n^JEadla to the Prince of wales, the parsonaX-&amp;*lumph of His Royal Hlghnosa andpopular m^alfeatatlons of loyalty-ascending allexpeotatlone.The Confereaoe heard the news with profoundgratification aad asked the Secretary ofState to arrangedfrnrHdi^publJLo^^     of the telegram.t2, Whitehall Gardens, SaW.24th Noisfember, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
