<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 129-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-pOXnjMEia^lS^^^ OF--flXS*-BHTTAinmr^ GOVERNMENT).,C R E T*                            /      I A? /L    f*r,------ As&amp;U     /IQt /31PIKAI, copy  NO___.CONCLUSIONS of a Conferenceof Ministers lielct in the Board Room, Treasury,on Thursday, 22nd De-ceriberf. 1921, at 3.-0 poiricPRE SEN T:-The Right Hen., A, Chamberlain.Mo P.,, Lord ^rivy Seal,(In the Chair)aThe Right&apos;Horn Sir Robert Home,Go B-,E.i , Ko C, ,MoP. , Chancellor ofthe Exchequer,The Right hon  Sir Alfred Mond,Bart^,M,P.&apos;j Minister of Heal thoThe Right&apos;Hon-. ToJ0 Macnamara.Mo P., Minister of Labour,.The Right Hon- R&amp; Munro. K.C.M.P., Secretary for Scotland.-/THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO present mr, CF,, Rey, Secretary., LordSt, Davids1 Committee...homas Jones t^................. . Acting Secretary, Cabinet,ftnbroke Wicks11111 m 11 * t. * i i a 111111 1111 1111 11 [i i t Principal j Cabinet(
^LOYMSKT        1.      With re ea*ei*oa-&apos;to -Gavblne-t^S (21) Conclusion 4,UA.NOLSL the coduct?efreiKKK had he-fore them a .Meaoranfeun by theSlMOIttMinister of Health (0,P. 3574) upon the financial commitments of the Government in respect of schemes approved by the Unemployment Grafts Committee foroapital expenditure to be incurred by Local Author it ie-for works put in hand by them in order to provide employment.     It appeared -that when tho scheme for assisting Local Authorities was first set up, it was arranged at a meeting of thus Cabinet Commit toe onUnemployment fC.,U* 28* Conclusion 5 (3)a thatschemes should not be authorised exceeding a totaloapital expenditure of  10 millions without consultation between tins Minister of Health, end the Chancellor of theExchequer.,     Owing to an unexpected increase in theapplication from local        authorities the  10 millionlimit would shortly be reached, and at a meetingof the Cabinet Committee; on ,Unemployment (C*U. 45,Conclusion 1), on December 13th, it had been made clear that the Chancellor of the Exchequer was notprepared to sanction an increase of the limit which hadbeen provisionally laid down,     The matter had therefore been referred to the Cabinot, who had directed that the list of schemes before the Unemployment GrantsCommittee should he revised, with a view to eliminatingthose which were not of a strictly utilitariannature, and that the list, as revised, should be remitted for consideration to the present conference,.On a review of the applications already received bythe Unemployment Grants Committee, it appeared that only a very small proportion      were for works suchas Parks and Recreation grounds, and that the remaindercould not he classed as luxury expenditure*1 2 3
The Conference) wore informed by the Secretaryof the Unemployment Grants Committee that up to dateschemes had been   sanctioned by his Committee to thevalue of  9-jg- millions;     that the total eost ofschorr.es which had not yet been examined amountedto rather under  5g millions, and that it might beanticipated that of those roughly one-sixth would be rejected,  judging by the experience of the pastadministration of the scheme.     There would, therefore,,probably be an excess of some  4 millions over the 10 millions limit, if the adminstraticn of theGommittoe proceeded without interruption.   Moreover,aB sdheraes were ocming in at &amp;ho rate of some 50 a day,and would continue to do sc during tho next few days,i% was probable that schemes amounting to a further one million pounds would bo recaivod before the end of theyear.     It would,  therefore, bo unsafe to assume hyJanuary 1st that the total number of applicationswould be less than  16 millions, making an excess of 6 millions, of which  5 millions might be expected torank for grant, the remainder being rejected.The Committee were informed that ho indicationhad been given tc Local -Authorities that there was a financial limit to the capital oost of these schemes;that Local Authorities had been pressed to send insohomos, which wore now ocming in quickly, and thatthere would be a groat cutcry and strong politicalfeeling if Local Authorities were now informed thattho Government were unable to find any j?further money for financing schemes which they themselves had askedLocal Authorities to prepare.     It was made plain that
 the omission to inform Local Authorities of the financial limit which had provisionally been fixed arose from the fact that at the inception of the scheme it was thought that Local Authorities would not be anxious to come forward. The flood of applications received, had recently developed to an extent which had not been contemplated.

The Chairman suggested that the Departments concerned should take note for future guidance that, when a limit was provisionally fixed for any expenditure of this character, these concerned with the administration of the scheme must take care in carrying out the scheme, that there was no risk of that limit boxing exceeded, unless and until a definite decision to exceed it had been taken. 

It was explained to the Conference that the standard of unemployment which the Minister of Labour had laid down for the qualification of particular districts to have their schemes approved, was 6% of workmen unemployed, with a minimum of 300 persons. It was suggested that the limit thus fixed was much too low, and that having regard to the extraordinary effort which the Government had been obliged to make to deal with the emergency, the limit of severity should be comparable with the distress which had induced the Government to set up so expensive a scheme.

It was suggested that the limit should be raised to 10%, but the Minister of Labour was unable to agree to this without consulting his advisers. It was pointed out that in as much as the circular from the Minister of Health to Local


Authorities had beem issued&quot; in September, with an instruction that in order to qualify for grants,wCrk on sli&amp;$Bee must eonmsaoa before January 1st,Xtooal Authorities who had not submitted their schemesfor approval before Christmas, could hardly oomplainthe Government had broken faith, If sanction were refused.After seme discussion the Committee agreed.-That tho limit of the total oapitaloost of sahemes presented by localAuthorities, asd approved by theUnemployment Grants Committee, shsuldhe increased from  10 millions to 13 millions, en the understandingthat the Minister of Health, the minister of labour, and the Secretaryfor scotland, in consultation with theSecretary of the Unemployment GrantsScmmittee, should arrange to imposesuch tests, either in regard to the severity of unemployment in a particulardistrictj the date by which schemesmust be submitted, or tha date before which work, must ccmnenoo     as would ensure that tha total value of sohemesapproved wnuld fall within the limit of  13 milliens.S.        The Committee had under Consideration aQuestion which had been raised at a meeting of theUnemployment Committee (0oU. 44th Conclusions,Minute 5), relating to the propecsl by tho MinisterOf Health to permit Looal Authorities to developat the charge of the Exchequer account in connectionwith housing, building sites already purchased whichwere beyond what was actually required for buildingunder the curtailed housing programme.It was suggested that this should be dene inlocalities in which there was serious unemployment which would otherwise^bo provided for, subjeot to
 there being a reasonable prospect of the land being required at an early date for the natural development of the district. Local Authorities could at present undertake the work themselves, with the assitance of the 65% grant of loan charges from the Unemployment Grants Committee for half the loan period, but were not prepared to take the risk involved by this in the present uncertain position of the housing problem.

It was stated by the Minister of Health that the proposal would involve an addition to the Government burden on housing account of about £50,000 a year.

In the opinion of the Treasury this figure would be £80,000 for an indefinite number of years. In the view of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, housing expenditure was already proving a very heavy burden on the State, and to add so large a sum would be a serious matter at the moment, when the Government were trying to cut down expenditure in every direction.

It was stated that the Ministry of Health were of opinion that Local Authorities should be able to sell sites thus developed before very long, having regard to the fact that the price of building was coming down, and that there was no reason why a large part of the money should not be recovered. £1,000,000 had heen suggested as the total capital expenditure involved, but probably one-half of that sum would meet the needs of the case. It would be in one respect better that the money should be spent as part of the housing scheme, rather than that the development of building sites should be assisted
by the Unemployment Grants Committeo.     Whore a housingsohome was involved, the officials of the Ministryof Health would examine the sites with tho greatest care, and only sanction those which woro reallysuitable for development,     This the unemployment grants Committee had not the staff to aocl&apos;ho Minister of Health suggested that the scheme could be worked In consultation with the unemployment grants Committee, and that the amount of money at thedisposal of that Committee could be pro tanto reducedto compensate fer any additional expenditure under thehousing schemeoTho Committee agreed:To approve the proposal that localAuthorities should &quot;be permitted todevelop, at the charge of theExchequer account in connection with housing, building sites already purchased,,beyond what is actually required for building under tho curtailed housing programme, provided that it could bearranged that any sums charged to theExchequer should be taken pro tantoin reduction of the commitmatsof the Unemployment Grants Committee,ABILITYiSIOSS &amp;LAWIEFb   .3.       The Conference had before thorn a recommendationof the Home Affairs Committee to the Cabinet (how,C,100th Conclusions).&quot;   that the Minister of Health be authorised&quot;to inform Boards of Guardians that the&quot;Government propose to introduce legislation&quot;which they would endeavour to make retrospective,&quot;permitting Boards of Guardians, in assessing&apos;&quot;the claims of applicants for out-door relief,&quot;to ignore a part of disability pensions, but&quot;that they could not guarantee that the exclusion&quot;of a higher amount than a flat rate of 10s, a&quot;week would be authorised by such legislation,&quot;
The Mini s-ter of Health-explained that it was   thepractice of many Guardians to deduct the whole or partof a disability pension in   computing the income of an applicant for cut-door relief, and this, under the lawas it stood at present, they were not entitled to do.As in London out-door relief was now a charge upon theCommon Poor Fund, it would shortly bo necessary for himto inform tho Boards of Guardians that they wero not entl-tlod to make 1his deduction, arid the question fordeeislon &apos;was whether, following the ree^msBondjations ofthe Home Affairs Committee,he should inform Boards of guardians that they might continue to deduct disabilitypension, and that, if legal difficulties arose, theGovernment would pass legislation to indemnify then andto alter the law.The Secretary for Scotland stated that, apart fromthe merits of the question, he must press that so far asScotland w**s   concerned, no directions to Guardiansshould be given in advance of legislation.     Considerabletrouble had already arisen in Scotland from thodecision of the Government to authorise payment of out-door rollof to able-bodied persons contrary to thastrict lettor of the law, and the adtion which had beentaken of curing the legal difficulty by subsequentlegislation had created a very difficult preoodentwhich must on no aacount be repeated.
The Conference wore j^cnerally topresseu with the difficulty of taking thy action suggested bytho Minister of Health in .advancc of legislation;.while they appreciated the political difficultieswhich would ariae, they felt that tho Minister ofHealth must Insist on the observance of the law.Jajpllament had already strongly resisted the payment ofmoney in advance of Parliamentary sanction;   thiswould Involve eatpon&amp;ituro, not merely in advanceof Parliamentary sanction but in defiance of the law.It was pointed out that, while the Ministeriif Health must direct Guardians that such illegalpayments oeuld not beujaade a charge upon theMetropoli tan Common JPfwsr Fund, the Guar guardians oo ul d,if they chose, continue to bear the cost of the deduction out of their own rates, and tho Ministerof Health would incur no responsibility in tho&apos; natter .The Conference agreed:(1)   that a final decision in thematter should be postponed, ontho understanding that if theposition became really acute,legislation oould bo passed,although no action must be takenin anticipation of such legislation.(Z)   that the Minister of health should inform Boards of Guardians. that the Elusion of tho wholeor part of a disability pensionin computing the Income of an applicant for outdoor &quot;relief wasillegal and that any sums illegallyexpended in censequenoe could notbe made a charge upon theMetropolitan Common Poor Fund.8.Wkitshall Gardens, S.\7.82nd December, 19 21.

</content>
</cab>
