<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 188-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His BritannicMajestyfs Government)/pEORET mil MINUSES of a Conversation held, at10, Downing Street, 3.17./l, on Monday,19th June, 1922 at 12 Ho on.OOPTPRESEHS:-The Prime Minister:She Rt.Hon.A. Chamberlain, M.P.,lord Privy Seal:The Rt.Hon.Earl of Balfour, Z.G., CM,,Acting Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs:The Ht,Hon.Sir Robert Home, G.B.E., E.C., M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer:Sir Maurice Halikey, G.C.B.,Secretary.
(1) THE PRIME MINISTER reminded hiecolleagues that 11. Poincare   had accepted an invitation to lunch with him:.that day to meetthe Members of the British Cabinet.     Up to thepresent time nothing had been decided as to whether there were to be any Official conversations afterthe luncheon.     M. &quot;Poincare^s attitude as revealedin a private and personal telegram from lord hardinge to Lord Balfour appeared to be thathe was willing to enter into conversations ifthe initiative came from the British side;   hewas somewhat reluctant to take the initiativehimself.After full discussion, it was agreed(a) That either the Prime Minister orthe Acting Secretary of State for foreign Affairs.should take a convenient opportunity to say toM,Poincare that as he was herein London on a purely unofficialvisit, the Prime Minister and the acting Secretary of State for foreign Affairs would be glad totake the opportunity to have con-Versations with him on any subjectif he desired;(b) That if M. poincare asked whatsubjects the British Governmentwould &quot;like to discuss, the reply should be limited to Tangiers, theHear East, and perhaps The Hague;fo) That the British Government shouldnot ask for discussions on Repara-tionSj but if M. poincare wishedto raise the question, they should%e willing to^enter into conver-sations on the subject;(d) That the Prime Minister and the acting Secretary of State for foreign Affairs&apos;should represent theBritish Government and in the eventof Reparations being raised, thev   Chancellor of the Exchequer should attend if his Parliamentary dutiespermitted.     If he could not be present, Sir Basil Blackett of the&apos;: Treasury should be summoned forany discussions on Reparations.
POSSIBLE CONVERSATIONS WITH M. POINCARE.

(1) THE PRIME MINISTER reminded his colleagues that M. Poincaré had accepted an invitation to lunch with him that day to meet the Members of the British Cabinet. Up to the present time nothing had been decided as to whether there were to be any official conversations after the luncheon. M. Poincaré&apos;s attitude as revealed in a private and personal telegram from Lord Hardings to Lord Balfour appeared to be that he was willing to enter conversations if the initiative came from the British side: he was somewhat reluctant to take the initiative himself.

 After full discussion, it was agreed:-

(a) That either the Prime Minister or the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should take a convenient opportunity to say to M. Poincaré that as the was here in London on a purely unofficial visit, the Prime Minister and the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs would be glad to take the opportunity to have conversations with him on any subject if he desired;

(b) That if M. Poincaré asked what subjects the British Government would like to discuss, the reply should be limited to Tangiers, the Near East, and perhaps The Hague;

(c) That the British Government should not ask for discussions on Reparations, but if M. Poincaré wished to raise the question, they should be willing to enter into conversations on the subject:

(d) That the Prime Minister and the Acting Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should represent the British Government and in the event of Reparations being raised, the Chancellor of the Exchequer should attend if his Parliamentary duties permitted. If he could not be present, Sir Basil Blackett of the Treasury should be summoned for any discussions on Reparations.

    
Age DEBITS IN (2) Some disci? a si on took place in regard(0 HOUSE 01?10RP3 03 GEN 01.      to the forthcoming debate in the House of Lords on tuesday,  June 27th,  on the Genoa Conference,when it is understood that Lord Grey will make animportant speech on Anglo-Prench relations.       Baringthis discussion the PRIME MINISTER instructedMr.Shakespeare,  one of his Private Secretaries, toobtain for Lord. Balf our, the following material:-(a) Mr, As^uith&apos;s letter to the&quot;ManchesterGuardian&quot; denying that the IndependentLiberal Party had not expressed a view on the proposed Pact of Guarantee to france ;(b) The leading article in the &quot;ManchesterGuardian&quot; which had called, forth this letter;(c) An interview which Mr.Aso.uith had sub-secuently given to the &quot;EestminsterGazette&quot;;(d) Mr. Asauithfs speech at Blackpool advocatingthe remission of the German debt and the revision of the Treaty of Versailles;(e) Lord Grey-1 s speeches,and any articles intho Independent Liberal Press commenting on these speeches;In connection with any questions    that mightbe raised in tho House of Lords in regard to the GenoaConference, Lord Balfoar was advised to read thePrime &quot;Minister1^ speech in the House of Commons onMay 25th, 1922, and more particularly the Parliamentary&quot;White. Paper containing the Cannes Resolution -Cd, 1621.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W./I20th June, 1922

</content>
</cab>
