<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 192-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property, of His britannic  j. est yI &amp; Gov.government.ent.)gJLP. R E ? -NOTE OP A CONVERSATION HELD AT 3.0, downing street,  S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY, JUNE SI, 1922,at 11-15 a.m.PRESENT&quot;.-The Right Hon. D. Lloyd George, O.M.M.P.,Prime Minister.The Right Hon. The Earl of Balfour, K.G.,O.M.,Acting Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P., lord privy Seal.The Right Hon. The.Lord d*Abernon^ G.C.M.G.,British Ambassador in BerliniSir Maurice Hankey, G.0.3. (Secretary -tonthe Cabinet).Sir Edward Grigg, K.C.V.0,,C .M.G.HUME (i) The Prime Minister instructed Sir Maurice Hankey toSTSR&apos;SriNG WITH arrange that Lord d^bernon should bo furnished with a oopy0INCARE\of his notes of the meeting with M. Poincare&apos; on Monday,June 19th. (r.CvP.-349-C)(Sir Maurice Hankey sent a copy to thePoreign Office for this purpose thesame day.)
US SI OK OF (2)  On the tpieetaon of &quot;tho - -entry ^&quot;Vrorr^^r&apos;^^^^ &apos;:$Vr TOK IB AGUE      he aqua of Nations, - the following two arguments were/NATIONS. &apos;mentioned as additional to the argument commonly used:-Pirst, if Germany was not brought into the Leaguenow, it would strengthen the hands of those people inGermany who desired a German-Russian Alliance.   It was true that such&apos; an alliance would, not&apos;, at the present time,put those two countries in a position to make war.    later on, however, they would recover their Strength and might become a danger.The second argument was relatively local to theLeague in character,  aid related to South America.    TheArgentine &quot;had to some extent separated herself from theLeague, not formally hut practically, insomuch as sheabstained from attending the meetings.    This was not dueto any desire on her part to follow the&apos;lead of the UnitedStates of America, hut had more to do with the idiosyn-cracles of the present President.   The President-Electwas understood to he in favour of the League,    (in thisconnection a proposal was made in regard to the President-Elect, which is recorded in a separate Conclusion.)Mr Edwards, who usually represented Chile at the League ofNations, was reported to hold the view that South Americagenerally wished Germany to he admitted to the League.The same was true of all tha States which had been neutralin the late War.Against this it, was pointed out that Germany was unwilling to come into the League unless Prance agreed,and unless she was assured of British support to her elec-tion to the Council of the League.   At the present time,however, it was pointed out, we always appeared to he onthe verge of difficulties with Germany.    It was understoodthat Germany would be able to pay her next reparationsinstalment punctually, hut that she would not he able to pa;
the instalment after that.   This would at once create difficulties.   If the Reparation Commission reported thatGermany was in default, there would &quot;be a demand, from france to put pressure on Germany.   Juridically it might be truethat Germany could be a member of the League, and even ofthe Council, while the Allies were putting pressure upon her, but the positionwotild.be one of embarrassment.Supposing it were decided that it was desirable for the British Government to support the entry of Germanyto the League, what, it was ashed, would the next step bo?Would it be to approach France, point out to her the desir-ability of separating Germany from Russia, and. also thatGermany would not come into the League if Franco -was strongly opposed?   Some people, it was stated, consideredthat France would not object to. Germany being brought intothe League if she were not elected a member of the Council.It was doubtful, however, if Germany would accept this position.Certain objections were pointed out to the coursesuggested..   If M. Poincare were asked the question directif he woul&amp; support the admission of Germany to tho League,It would be very difficult for him to agree, owing to thepolitical pressure to which he was exposed.In this connection, those present were reminded ofthe difficulty which had been encountered in securing the admission of Germany to the various Commissions at the GenoaConference.(Mr Chamberlain entered at this point, andthe Prime Minister explained to him thepoint which had been reached in the Con-versation.)It was recalled, however, that at Genoa the French hadreceived no support on this point even from nations whichusually, stood b y her, like the Belgians and the czecho-Slovaks,
The suggestion was made that the right course wouldhe to let the French know generally that we considered thetime had come to. admit Germany to the League, without pro-vokihg a discussion with the French Government on theShbject.   We should then he in a position to support aGerman application to enter the league.It was pointed out that no-one was likely to opposeactively the entry of Germany to the League at the AssemblyLord d&apos;Ahernon was then asked what was likely tohe the attitude of the Germans if he were to tell theGerman Government that he had discussed the matter with british Ministers and that they were favourable to the entry of Germany to the League?It was pointed out that the Germans would probablyreply by. asking what view the French Government took.&quot;Lord d&apos;Abernon might then reply that they would probablybe admitted to tha Assembly, but that as regards election to the Gouncil he could not say definitely, thotigh hethought that the majority of the Assembly would electGermany to be one of the xaon-parmanent members of theCouncil.LORD D&apos;ABKRNOII said it was Impossible to express a definite view, hut on the whole he was inclined to think the Germans, in those circumstances, would make an appli-cation.   Dr WIrth was already Inclined, to join the League,but Dr Hathenau was at first likely to be less favourable.He might change his view, however, if he were given argu-m^nts which he could use to. the Reichstag.   Moreover, the with M, Poincarofact that the conversations/in London had not resulted &quot;insalutaryany decision to apply pressure to Germany might hay? a /effect.    He asked if the United States of America were likelyto advise- the German Government not to enter the League?There was general agreement that this was improbable
It waa agreed to make the following rocommendationsto the Cabinet:-(a) That it was desirable that Germany shouldbo admitted as a Member of the Assembly andof the&apos;Council&apos; of the League of Nations:(b) That a direct proposal on these lines to theFrertch Government was bound to lead to a refusal:(c) That the most hopeful plan appeared to be to let the French Government know that we were generally in favour of the admission ofGermany to the League, without entering into discussions with them- on the subject:(d) That the Acting Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should discuss with the British Ambas-ambassador in Parisr now on a visit to this country,the best manner of approaching the French Gov-ernment on the subject:(e) That the Acting Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should authorise the British ambassador in Berlin to encourage the German Goviornment toapply for membership of the League of Nationsbefore the next meeting of the Assembly, and tolot tho German Government know that the repre-sentatives of the British Government on theLeague would support the admission of Germanyto membership of the Council.
flPOSED VISIT.      (g) In the course of the preceding discussion, THETHE PRESIDENT-.;0T OP THE     ACTING SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS said that0JTINE RE-iLlO.the President-Elect of the Argentine Republic was propos-ing to visit this country, and a suggestion had been made,which he favoured., that, in view of the importance of theposition he was shortly -to occupy, he should be given acordial reception by the British Government.   Before ap-proaching His Majesty the King on the subject he had wished to know the Prime Minister1 s view. .THE PRIME MINISTER, after alluding to the importanceof good relations with the Argentine Republic from a financial and commercial point of view, said he was entire-ly in favour of the proposal of the Acting Secretary ofState for Foreign Affaire.
3 UNITEDiVTES OP0RIOA ANDA LEAGUE.(4) Arising out of the discussion on the subject ofGermany and the League of Nations, consideration was givento the position of the United states of America in regardto the League of Nations.The suggestion was made that it would be worth while to sound the American Secretary of State as to whether, ifArticle 10 of the Covenant were amended, it would have anyInfluence on the attitude of the United States towards theLeague.It was generally agreed that this was somewhat deli-cate ground, particularly In&apos;view of the approaching Con-gressional Elections in the United States of America.Having &quot;regard, however,  to the fact that the DemocraticParty were definitely in favour of the admission of theUnited States of America to the League and were expectedto make some considerable gains at the Congressional Elec-tions, it was possible that the Party now in office mightthethink it worth while politically to obtain,/alterations inthe Covenant which they had always contended that instrumentought to contain.Allusion was made to the fact that the amendment ofArticle 10 had been proposed by Lord Balfour&apos;s Committeeof the League of Nations in the previous year, but that thematter had been postponed for various reasons. 7^tMIt was stated that some of the small States were rather favourable to Article 10 in its present form.Mention was made of private and confidential inforxaa-tion which had been received.to the effect that the UnitedStates Government might consider co-operation with theLeague on its juridical side only.The Acting Secretary of State for foreign affairs undertook to.discuss the matter with Mr Taft, who Is now on a visit tothis country. *
IMPERIAL (5) Attention was called to a personal telegram received-TINGS, 1921.- by the Prime Minister from the Prime Minister of Canada,posed Pub- _ - .cation of     asking if the British Government could agree to the pub-oranda.lication of certain Secret Memoranda prepared for theImperial Meetings in 1921, referring to subjects which included ReparationsEgypt, Petroleum, Mesopotamia, and palestine.   Most of these Memoranda had been prepared forthe Imperial Meetings On the understanding that theypartook of the nature of Imperial Cabinets rather thanImperial Conferences, and contained much secret matter.It was recognised that this was a matter whichcould not be decided in tho absence of the Secretary ofState for the Colonies, but,subject to his concurrence,there was general agreement that publication should notbe agreed to.The drafts of two telegrams from the Prime Ministerto the Prime Minister of Canada wars read, and the longerversion was approved, subject to certain small amendments,and subject also to the concurrence of the Secretary ofState for the Colonies, whom Sir Edward Grigg undertook to consult.&apos; lj?bit shall-- Gardens, S .W. 1,June 21, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
