<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 362-364</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COPY.MINUTES of a Commit too hold at the&apos; ColonialOffice on Tuesday., 26th September-,,-1922, at&apos; 6 p-.nuPRESENT.: ...The Right Horio 1.3. Churchill, MeP&amp;,Secretary of State for the Colonies.(In the Chair),THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT2.General the Earl of Cavan? K.P.,G0C cMcGo ,&apos;&quot; GoO cVcO., KoCBof Chiefof the Imperial General Staff.Lt-e-General Sir Travers Ea Clarke,KoOoBs, KcCoMcGoj QuartermasterGeneral to the Forces c-Lt*-General Sir Philip W0 Chetwode, Bartv,KoCoBof KcC.MoGor d.s.c.Ot, Adjufeant-General to the ForcestSir Edward Grigs, K-.C-.V. 0,, C.M.G.ptenant-Colonel Sir MoPoA. Hankey,. G.C*B.,*....c.Secretary, Cabinet,utenant-Colonel CJiiUG. Walker, DfiSff0e,oi eAssistant Secretary, CsIvD.
*j 5 4.JD.     1.      The Adjutant-General drew attention to thesituation which would arise in Ireland if it were necessaryto mobilise one or two divisions.      If one division weremobilised only 26 battalions would remain. In Ireland (i,e,4 short of allotment), if two divisions were mobilisedonly 20 battalions would be left In Ireland (i te. tenshort of allotment).     Accordingly, if the Irish garrison weremade up to strength, only two line battalions and four Guardswould be left in England.      If two divisions were mobilisedit would be necessary to withdraw the troops from&apos; eitherDublin or Ulster, for unless battalions were withdrawn from ireland both battalions of certain regiments would be abroad and these regiments would have no reserves to draw on,   Therewere, however, 8 battalions on the Rhine which might possibly be used if the French would agree.      He also pointed out thatin the event cf mobilisation a large portion of the mechanical transport both personnel and vehicles in Ireland must perforcebe drawn upon.Mr. Churchill said he did not wish to evacuateDublin on political grounds.     At present the ProvisionalGovernment were getting in such a strong position that he did not think it could become necessary to use Britishtroops in support or them, but If the British troops fromDublin were&apos; withdrawn he was afraid that it would givemuch encouragment to Valera and others to redouble their efforts against the Provisional Government,.      The Forcesin Ulster could in no case be weakened.      He considered,however,  that this matter raised a broad question of policywhich would require careful consideration.     He suggestedthat in the event of mobilisation it would be necessaryto call.for volunteers and also to make use of theterritorial force.      The whole question should be adjourned for. further consideration.-1-&quot; / SH3RGAT
GAT8.-        Mr. Churchill informed the Committee that he wasdespatching a telegram to Sir Percy Cos: saying that the demolition of the. Shergat railway must he suspended untilthe present crisis was, over.ait eh all Gardens y S.W

</content>
</cab>
