<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/39/0 images: 365-372</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
L D0CTH3HT IS THE PROPERTY OP . HIS miVWIQ MAJESTY13 GO vERMGjRT)&quot; ^______      ,,   ,............. - - - &apos; .  ;.....-ii ______.        ..   Uim^M of a Committee of Ministers ^*held in Mr Churchill&apos;s Room, Colonial Office, SaW**.on v/e&amp;nesday, September 27th. 1922, at 3 p,m0FR3SBNT-The Rt. Hon. A. Chamberlainj M.P., ,   3 .Lord Privy Seal. (in the Chair)Most Hon. The Mar quo as Gurzon ofjleston, K.G.. G.C.S.I., G.C*IoS,,,Icrotary of State for poreign Affairs,It, Hon. Sir L. WortMngton-Evans,L, G.3.E., M.P., Seoretary ofate for War.The Rt., Hon, Wh-Sc Oinirshili, M*PSeoratary of stata for thoGolanies,The Rt, Hon. the Lord, &quot;eo of Fareham, G*B*JB** RsOA P-j 3Pirst Lord of the admiral ty^The following were also present^:-iral of the Pleet Earl Beatty,.B., O.M., G.C.Y.O., P.S.09*rat Sea Lord and Chief of thePal Staff.Chief Marshal Sir Hugh II.pshard, Part., E*C.B., D.3o0.,hi of tho Air Staff.General tha Earl of Cavanj, K*P.,G9CcM.G.j GoCoYaOs? EhCoBssChief ef the Imperial GeneralStaff.Air Commodoro J,M. Steel;  C?B. *C*H*G. * Director of operations and Intelligence, Air Ministry,Jol. Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.3.......,............ 0* Secretary, Cabinet,wi. Sir John Chancellor, R.C.U.G., P.S.O.,Principal Assistant Secretary, 0*1*1).
DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY 0;? HIS 3BIT.AHIII0 MAJ33TYr3 GOVERNMENT)mi.........    ....   MINUTES of a Committee of ministers hold in Mr Churchill&apos;1 s Room, Colonial Office, SoW?*.on Wednesday, September 27th. 1922, at 3 p.m.oPRESENT,The Rt. Hon. A* Chamberlain, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.(in the Chair)lost Hon. The Marquess Gurzon ofis ton, K.G.* G.G.S.I., G.C*IoS,s,drotary of State for poreign Affairs.It. Hon, Sir L. Worthington-Evans,ll, G.3.E., M.P., Seoretary ofaife for war.The Rt., Hon* w.*Sc Ghurcshili, M*PoSeoretary of state for theColonies.The Rt, Hon. the Lord Leo ofPareham3 G* Bo E* * KoCb Be sPirs t Lord of the Afimi ral ty.1The following were alsoJ-presentIfral of the Pleet Earl Beatty,%t CM., G.C.V.O., D.S.08*rat Sea Lord and Chief of them Staff.Chief Marshal Sir Hugh M.shara, Bart., .E.C.B., P.3.O.,of the Air Staff.General the Earl of Cavan? K*P.,GsCcM.Gt,      0*7*0., E.CoB*.Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.Air CommocLoro J,M. Steel; C*Bo,C^II.G.5 Director of operations and Intelligence, Air Ministry,U* Sir 11.P.A. Hankiey, G.C.3....................o,Secretary, Cabinet.- Sir John Chancellor, E.C.U.G., D.S.O.,Principal Assistant Seoretary, de-D.
MR. CHAMBERLAIN stated that the meeting had toensummoned in order to endesvour to elucidate certain navaland military aspects of the situation before having afull meeting of Ministers at 7 p.m.MR. CHURCHILL read Telegram No. 466 from the HighCommissioner, find SIR LAMING 7J0RTHINGT0N EVANS read aTelegram No. 2479 from General Harington In which it Isreported that he is now in touch with Kemal Pasha.MR. CHURCHILL asked the C.I.G.S. what his views were as to the  situation which Would arise if hostilities be-gan, in particular how long our troops could hold Chanakbefore the arrival of reinforcements.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF read telegrams nos. 2468 and 2469 which ho had received from general harington.     He was of opinion that the position which washold at Chanak with a perimeter of four miles would not give sufficient room for the landing and depIo?/m.eni of alarge force there.      He was also doubtful if the trans-ports could reach Chanak if hostilities had begun.     Assoon as mobilisation was ordered, he was certain thatEternal would at once attack the Chanak position.      He didnot bcliovo that he could turn our forces out of Chanakwhich could hold their   own without reinforcements for three or four weeks, but there was nothing to prevent &amp;eirialfrom bringing up guns to positions on the shore of theDardanelles from which they could fire up and down theNarrows.     That fire would prevent transports from
disembarking troops in the Dardanelles. The reinforcements would, therefore have to be landed on the North Side of the Gallipoli Peninsula and move across to Chanak. This would entail a very difficult operation and heavy losses would probably be incurred in transferring troops across the Dardanelles. An alternative plan was to divert the two divisions of reinforcements and land them at some place which must be kept secret as a counter offensive. He understood that it would be difficult for His Majesty&apos;s Government to order the evacuation of the Chanak position, but it was for consideration whether a force of one battalion would not be as effective as the force that we now have in Chanak. If, as appeared, probable, Kemal was unable to prevent his irregular troops from harassing our troops in Chanak, he could not prevent them from lining the shores of the Dardanelles with guns. It must be realised, that if we do withdraw from Constantinople and Chanak that we have, not sufficient forces to enable us to go book there. If it is considered probable that Kemal would loyally observe an undertaking for the Withdrawal of British and Turkish troops alike from the neutral zone, such an agreement would be to our advantage. If it were decided to evacuate Chanak now we might claim that our action was a "beau geste", and explain that our object was to avoid, the risk of a collision In view of the fact that Kemal cannot control his irregular troops in that locality.

MR. CHAMBERLAIN observed that the proposals for withdrawal were based on Barrow military considerations, to the exclusion Of all others, and no-was or the opinion that we could not now withdraw from chanak with credit to ourselves in order to avoid Komal&apos;s irregulars. He would regard such a withdrawal as an humiliation to the British Empire.


- v.-r.;:.-:MR . GHURCRILL^ot^Tnrrod in.. Mr-. -chamberlain s view,and added that, if it were possible to ensure the immunityof the Neutral Zone by withdrawing from Chanak, we should accept such an arrangement at once, but he considered itto the last degree improbable that Kemal would consent to sacrifice the advantages he now had of access to theshores of the Dardanelles without firing a shot.LORE CURZON remarked that in Paris last week M.Poincare had urged that we should consent to withdraw from Chanak and had expressed an opinion that Kemal would come to an agreement on the subject.     The situation had changed einco then.In reply to enquiries from Mr. Churchill as to themilitary position at Chanak, the CHIEF OP THB IMPERIALGENERAL STAFF stated that, if fighting occurred at Chanakwithin the next 48 hours, Kemal would probably be able tobring artillery against the position In about four days1time.     There were now 3,500 British troops at Chanak.Reinforcements   &quot;fire due to arrive as follows:-S Pack Batteries from Egypt due on the 28th.6&quot; Howitzer Battery from Gibraltar duo on the 30th.1,000 Marines and a Signal Detachment due on the30th.1 Battalion is due to arrive on the 3rd October.3 Battalions left    on the 27th and aro due on 7thOctober.The Turks are reported to have 7 Infantry and 4 cavalry divisions in that locality, a force of 23,000 rifles andsabres.MR. CHURCHILL expressed the opinion that   general harington&apos;s last telegram was different in tone from his previous/
Previous ones. Up to now, he had been confident that he could maitain himself at Chanak for four weeks without difficulty.

THE CHEIF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF explained thath there was no change in General Harington&apos;s view in regard to that matter, but he asked to be assured as to the reinforcements that would be sent if hostilities broke out.

THE FIRST SEA LORD stated that the facts put forward by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff would add to the difficulties of the Navy. He was of opinion that immediate withdrawal should be avoided if possible, as it would involve considerable less of prestige. He considered that the Navy could assist in the debarkation of reinforcements at Chanak with the support of howitzers mounted on the Gallipoli Peninsula. He thought that the guns that might be mounted on the shores near Chanak as suggested by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff could be controlled by the fire of the Navy and the howitzers on the Gallipoli. Peninsula. If Chanak fell, the Navy could keep open the passage of the Straits for warships. There need be no anxiety as to the withdrawal of the military forces from Constantinople and Chanak. He had instructed the Naval Commander-in-Chief to take all measures necessary to ensure that safe withdrawal in case of need and he had no doubt carried out his instructions. His observations did not qualify in any way the Chief of the Imperail General Staff&apos;s view as to the difficulties of deploying a large force in the small position at Chanak where they would be landed on a beach overlooked by hills commanding the position.

MR. CHURCHILL remarked that it clearly emerged that the forces at Chanak could hold out until reinforcements arrived, and that the Navy could ensure the withdrawal of
of troeos now there or that reinforcements can reach them if necessary, but the difficulties of the Operation are greatly increased by the new considerations which hadbeen put forward.     It was desirable not to exaggerate thepower, of Kernel1 s artilleryIt was true that he had some&quot; and 6M field guns, but his supply of ammunition was probably lilt?!ted and the difficulty of transporting the .ammunition across broken country to the shores of theDardanelles must be very greats     If necessary, reinforce-ments cduld be landed at Bulair, marched along theGallipoki Peninsula to opposite chanak and ferried acrossto Ghaiiak.     There should be therefore no difficultyin getting reinforcements toOhsajfJc if it is desirable todo so .     Ke enquired if it is certain that General Haringtoncould not hold the two high hills commanding theGhariak position.     He suggested that if General Haringtonknew, that reinforcements would be sent to him that he might be prepared to do so.     He suggested that -that&apos;(Question should be put. to General Harington and that heshould be told that he might move troops from Constantinopleto Chanak for that purpose if he thought it necessary.He enquired if it would bo more humiliating for vis to evacuate Ghanak now or to repulse the Turkish attack and if need be withdraw   pending the arrival of reinforcements.He enquired., assuming a serious collision takes place on 1stOctober., and orders were given to mobilise, what intervalwould elapse before the reinforcements began to arrive.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF read extracts fromappreciation of the situation prepared by the GeneralStaff on the assumption that our troops in the Chanakposition are attacked on the 30th September and that the
the attack was repulsed and that, orders for mobilisationwere given on the 2nd October. He explained that rein-forcements would arrive as follows :-By the 7th October, 5 more Battalions,By the 15th October, 2 Pack Batteries and one Batteryof 6&quot; Howitzers.After that there would he a gap until the 23rd October whenthe mobilised troops would begin to arrive.     The whole of the infantry of the 1st Division would have arrived by the SOthOctober and the whole Division by the 3rd November.     the infantry of the 2nd Division would have arrived by the 3rdNovember and the complete Division by the 7th November.      Itwas proposed to expand the position at Chanak as reinforcementsarrived.MR. CHAMBERLAIN requested that the Naval, Militaryand Air Chiefs would consider the Naval, Military and Airaspects of the situation as now discloser] in readiness fora meeting of the Cabinet at 7 p.m. and present, If possible, an agreed appreciation.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff was authorisedto consult General Harington as to whether It would not bepossible to hold the two high hills commanding the position at Chanak.fhitehsll Gardens, S.W..,!27th September, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
