<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/126/0 images: 131-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property ofher britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1966C (66) 116 Copy No.    6 719th July, 1966CABINETTHE FUTURE OF CONCORDMemorandum by the Minister of aviation on 30th June, the Cabinet invited me to circulate a further report on the commercial prospects for the Concord with particular regard to the effect of the sonic bang.2. The Attorney-GeneraFs advice (a copy of the Attorney-GeneraFs minute to the Prime Minister is at Appendix A) is to fhegeneral effect that the problems relating to sonic bang do not providegrounds which would justify our unilateral withdrawal from the project.3. My predecessor reaffirmed in the House on 20th July, 1965(a copy of his statement is at Appendix B), our intention of ourproceeding with Concord and the joint communique issued afterthe recent visit of the French Prime Minister stated &quot;... theyconfirmed their intention of proceeding with this [Concord], while maintaining constant scrutiny of the financial aspects&quot;. this statement will be interpreted as an indication of our determination to proceed with the project and the French will be quick to exposeany reservations in our position. The French will ask whether we accept, as they have already, the report of the Committee of Officials(Annex B to C (66) 88) recommending the continuation of theprogramme.4. So far about  45 million has been irrevocably committed tothe development of the Concord. Just to continue&apos;, the existing contracts which cover the construction of two prototypes will resultin a commitment of about  60 million by the end of the year. the continuation of the programme however also implies entering intonew contractual commitments for the construction of twopre-production aircraft and two airframes for test purposes, and for materials for series production. By the end of the year these further commitments will have taken the total up to  65-70 million.Financially the commitment will build up steadily, but politically avery critical point has been reached as the report of the Committee7058A
of Officials explained. Once we have indicated that we are preparedto continue with the project despite its increased development costs and the need for the Government to underwrite the production, itwill be even more difficult to discuss withdrawal.5. The fuller note on commercial prospects which was requestedis at Appendix C. It is based on extensive work carried out byBritish and French officials and is the most authoritative advice wecan obtain. Inevitably it makes a number of assumptions on suchmatters as rates of traffic growth, the fare structure which airlineswill agree to adopt, the relative attractions to passengers of different kinds of travel and the extent of sonic bang restrictions by governments around the world. Some of these assumptions maybe proved wrong but we cannot know for a number of years.Equally we cannot know for certain until the prototypes fly in 1968whether or not Concord will be a technical success.6. A note on the effect of the sonic bang is at Appendix Dbut the short point is that no testing in this country will enable usto forecast directly or accurately the restrictions which otherGovernments may place on operations by supersonic transport aircraft (SSTs).7. No new factors are likely to emerge until we have committed most of our money. I believe therefore that there ^areonly two alternatives:either (a) we accept the Committee of Officials report andannounce our firm intention to proceed with the projectthereby committing ourselves to the increaseddevelopment costs and the need to underwrite production,or (b) we seek to withdraw unilaterally.For the reasons explained in my earlier paper (C (66) 88) I considerthat (a) is the only practical course.F. M.Ministry of Aviation, S.W.1,18th July, 1966.
Appendix a prime Minister1. On 30th July the Cabinet invited the Minister of Aviationto consult me on the question, inter alia, whether technical consideration (and particularly the sonic bang) constituted a technical drawback which would legally justify our withdrawal fromthe Concord project. I have now considered this problem, inconsultation with officials of the Foreign Office and the Ministry of aviation; you may find it helpful to know my conclusions before the visit of M. Pompidou. I understand that the Minister is preparing a report on the broader question of the commercial prospects for the concord in relation to technical considerations and rising costs ofdevelopment.2. I am informed that the extent to which the operations ofcivil supersonic transport aircraft (SSTs) would be restricted by governments so as to limit the disturbance from the sonic bangs,which these aircraft must inevitably produce while they flysupersonically, has been a major cause of concern since they were first mooted. This applies as much to the proposed American SST(and to the one the Russians are known to be developing) as toConcord. The problem is thus not peculiar to Concord, and it hasnot hitherto deterred any of the four countries which are capableof doing so from embarking on the development of SSTs. Thesonic bang question will thus require our attention whether or not we continue with Concord, as we shall in any event have to determineour policy about allowing SSTs to fly over this country, and to haveregard to the restrictions which other Governments may place onsupersonic flight over their territory. On the other hand, Iunderstand that SSTs operating into or out of the United kingdom are not likely to cause sonic bangs even if we place no restrictions on them at all, because the aircraft will not achieve supersonic speedwithin 100 miles or so of take-off or landing, at which stage theywould generally be over the sea.3. There have, I am told, already been extensive, butinconclusive, tests in the United States, and more limited ones in theUnited Kingdom and France, to determine the effects of sonic bangs,and public reaction thereto. I am also told that it can be expectedthat further tests in this country would add to our knowledge and enable us to speak with more direct authority in these matters, butthey would not remove the uncertainty about the attitude which other Governments may eventually take toward the restriction of regular supersonic operations by airlines over their territories.4.  The conclusions which I draw from these considerations are:(a) the development of Concord has not in itself created any new technical problem in relation to sonic bangs;(b) even if we were to withdraw from the Concord project wewould still have to face the problems arising fromsupersonic flights by the aircraft developed by othercountries and which BOAC or BEA might have to acquireto stay in the business with competitors who may flythem; andSECRET7058 A 2
(c) the most that can, I think, be said about the sonic bangproblem in relation to our liability under the agreement is that the impact of sonic bangs on the commercialviability, and therefore the saleability, of Concordremains uncertain. It cannot be said that this uncertaintygives us a let-out at this stage. Nor do I think that wewould be able to contend successfully before theInternational Court that the problems relating to sonicbangs were not in the contemplation of the parties whenthe agreement was entered into, and that their emergencenow constitutes such a fundamental change of circumstances as would entitle us to withdraw unilaterallyfrom our commitments under the agreement.5. Despite these conclusions you may wish to note that in thecourse of the preliminary discussions between British and french officials which took place in London on 2nd October, 1961,M. Moussa, the Directeur des Transports Aeriens, is reported- tohave said &quot; the expectation would be that the aircraft would becompleted, but if some technical snag, like the sonic boom, provedinsuperable, then the [French] Government would cut its losses andabandon the project&quot;. This is an extract from a Unilateral british note which has not been agreed by the French, and therefore its value as evidence is limited. No provision was made for the contingency referred to by M. Moussa in the treaty that was signeda year later and there is no record that the British delegates referredto it at all. Moreover, it is clear that the sonic bang has not as yetproved an insuperable snag, and there is no evidence that it is likelyto do so.6. I am sending copies of this minute to the Lord Chancellor,the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Foreign Secretary, the Secretaryof State for Defence and the Minister of Aviation.F E J6th July, 1966.Appendix statement BY THE MINISTER OF AVIATION IN THEHOUSE ON 20th JANUARY, 1965&quot; We have now completed the review of the Concord projectwhich we set in hand in October and we have exchanged views withthe French Government.We had, and we still retain, some doubts about the financial andeconomic aspects of the project. We have, however, been much impressed by the confidence of our French partners and my right on. Friend the Prime Minister has informed the French PrimeMinister that we stand by the treaty obligations into which the lastGovernment decided to enter.During the coming months we shall be discussing with our partners the detailed programme of development and production.Now that the uncertainty over the future of this project has been removed I am sure that all those concerned with it on both sides of the Channel will press forward with a real sense of purpose. Inthis, they will have the full backing of Her Majesty&apos;s Government.&quot;
secret&apos;     132Appendix CCOMMERCIAL PROSPECTS FOR CONCORD1. The basic facts regarding the costs of devlopment were givenin paragraphs 5 and 6 of my previous paper (C (66) 88). The estimate for the United Kingdom share of development costs now stands at 225 million or  250 million when contingencies of  25 million havebeen added. This includes  40 million for development beyondcertification of airworthiness. The amount of technical progressachieved to date is one reason for our having confidence in ourpresent estimates. This confidence is further supported by specialinvestigations by British and French officials into the cost-controlmethods of the main contractors.2. It has long been recognised that the money spent ondeveloping the Concord will not be fully recovered from sales. at best one-third of our outlay may be recovered. (This assumes at least150 aircraft are sold plus spares to an equivalent value, and that themarket will bear development levies ranging from 4 to 10 per cent.)But I believe that we can develop and produce a technicallysatisfactory aircraft at a time and at a production cost which will result in its being sold in considerable numbers to the world&apos;s airlines,with consequential benefits to our balance of payments. Thecommercial prospects of the aircraft have to be considered in relationto our technical ability to carry through the planned programme,the operating economics that Concord is likely to be able to offer,and the competition from other types of aircraft to which it will be exposed.Prospects of the technical programme being achieved3. My previous paper (C (66) 88) and the report from theAnglo-French Committee of Officials recorded the British and french officials&apos; view that the planned performance will be achieved and thatthere is a good prospect of first deliveries to airlines before the endof 1971, as planned. This view follows 10 years of continuous workin the United Kingdom, of which the last 3\ have been in association with the French. The preparatory technical work, leading byprogressive refinement to the present design, has thus been on alarger scale than usual. Agreement with the French firms and officials is complete on all important technical features. eighteen months&apos; manufacturing work on the prototypes has enabled the basicproduction methods to be established. In all areas there is now anunusually good understanding of the total work involved in developing and producing the aircraft. Leading American (e.g.-,Pan Am and United) and other airlines are known to regard the concord as a practical technical and engineering proposition and tohave confidence in its manufacturers and in their ability to maintainthe time-schedule.Operating economics4. C (66) 88 stated that the total operating cost of the Concordper seat/mile on the North Atlantic will be about 25 per cent greaterthan the cost of the most economic present-day aircraft and that the7058
projected large subsonic aircraft (the so-called &quot;jumbo jets&quot;) will increase this difference to 30-35 per cent. This is based on estimatesby the Anglo-French Official Committee.5. Airlines however are concerned not just with the operatingcost per seat/mile, but also with the proportion of seats they can expect to fill. Concord should have an advantage in this respect,especially in its earlier years when it will have the supersonic fieldto itself. Experience has shown that reductions in journey time are important to many passengers, especially over long distances.Concord will make a quite dramatic advance in this respect, bringingNew York within some 3 hours and Sydney within 15 hours flyingtime of London. (At present the journeys take nearly 2\ times aslong.) The first aircraft to provide such service will undoubtedly be popular and operate with a high average complement of passengers. Its profitability to airlines can hardly be doubted inthis initial phase and even in later years when passenger loadingsmay fall to a more normal level, profitable operation can still beexpected.6. A fare differential will, however, be needed, not only toensure the profitable operation of the Concord but also to protectsubsonic aircraft against the Concord.Competition from other aircraft7. On the long-distance routes for which it is designed,Concord will have to face competition from subsonic jets and,eventually, rival American and Russian supersonic transport aircraft(SSTs).8. The general belief is that in the 1970s there will be a demandfor both subsonic jets and SSTs and that long-haul carriers will needsome of each in their fleets in order to meet passenger demands.9. Among SSTs the only potential competitors are a russian aircraft, the Tu-144, which is very similar in conception to Concordand which may be expected to be available in roughly the sametimescale, and the American design (by either Boeing or Lockheed)which will not be available until at least two years and possibly three or four years later. Russian competition can be discounted-our real competitors are the Americans.10. The United States Government intends to spend the rest ofthis year in evaluating the rival designs of Boeing and Lockheed fora Mach 3 aircraft, and to decide at the beginning of 1967 which ofthem to proceed with. The United States SSTs weight is nowapproaching twice that of the Concord and its first cost and itsproductivity will be so large that these factors must form a severerestriction on the market for it. Thus the American aircraft will be largely restricted to routes such as the North Atlantic with very heavy traffic. It is likely that by such time as the American SST isin service the Concord, with its smaller capacity, will be used onless dense routes. To a large extent therefore, the United StatesSST and the Concord should be regarded not as competitors but ascomplementary aircraft.SECRET
The market11. The general agreement on both sides of the Atlantic is thatthere should by 1980 be a market for some 300-400 supersonic transport aircraft and that, if all goes well, the Concord should, in theopinion of British and French officials, capture 150 or more of this market. This is supported by independent United States assessments.On the assumption that traffic will continue to increase between1975-80 at the same rate as up to 1975 (instead of the more modestincreases actually assumed the Concord market up to 1980 would increase from 150 to 225 aircraft.12. &quot; Partial&quot; sonic bang restrictions have been assumed inthese calculations. Even assuming the most extreme restriction i.e., a complete ban on supersonic flying over populated areas thiswould still leave half the long-distance market open to supersonicaircraft, i.e., at least 200 aircraft of Concord type by 1980, and onthe same assumption as in the earlier paper, the Concord&apos;s sharewould be about 100 aircraft. The reason for this is that on manyroutes, e.g., the bulk of boac&apos;s, such a ban would have less effectthan might be expected. The extra distance flown to avoid such areas, or alternatively subsonic flying over them, is quite small.13. The following airlines have already taken out options forthe following numbers of aircraft:With the addition of 16 aircraft reserved for BO AC and Air France,this makes a total of 60. Negotiations are far advanced for 2 more for Eastern Airlines, and 3 for Braniff. Almost every one of theUnited States airlines for whose route network Concord would be suitable has already signed up, or is about to do so. The number ofoptions, both actual and projected, more than 18 months before thefirst prototype is due to fly, support the view that it! should be possibleto sell 150 eventually.Conclusion14. We are unlikely to get much return on our development expenditure, but Concord is likely to have sufficient appeal to enable us to sell around 150, with spares to an equivalent value. Our shareof these sales could improve our balance of payments by a total of around  1,000 million over the decade 1970-80.Pan AmericanTWA .....American Airlines ..Qantas       .....Continental AirlinesJapan AirlinesSabena       .....Air IndiaMiddle East AirlinesEastern AirlinesUnited Airlines86643322226
Appendix DSONIC BANGSCause and nature of sonic bang1. Sonic bang has no connection with the familiar noise fromjet aircraft: this derives from the engines and is a nuisance only in and around airports. With sonic bang the reverse applies. when an SST is within about 100 miles of take-off or landing its speedwill be too low to cause a bang (and thus SSTs using British airportsneed cause no bangs over the United Kingdom). But as soon as theaircraft achieves supersonic speed it produces a bang and continuesto do so for as long as it is flying supersonically. The bang thussweeps across the countryside over which the aircraft is flying. It is most intense immediately below the aircrafts flight path, but occurswith diminishing intensity for several miles on either side of it. the size and height at which the aircraft is intended to operate are theonly design features which can have any significant effect on the intensity of the bang: altering its shape, or designing it for a lowerspeed (so long as it is still supersonic) can have no significant effect.Peculiarities in atmospheric conditions or in the lie of the land orin the disposition of buildings can greatly affect the intensity of thebang otherwise to be expected, and this is one of the main reasonsfor anxiety.Effects of sonic bang and results of earlier tests2. The effects of sonic bang are known from theoretical studies,the incidental experience gained from flying military aircraftsupersonically, and from tests directed specifically to the problem.We know that intensities far greater than those expected from normaloperations by SSTs have to be reached before damage to buildingsdefinitely attributable to sonic bangs occurs, although bangs of lesserintensity could occasionally, for example, result in falls of looseplaster and broken windows. The main reason for anxiety aboutsonic bangs is that &quot;people will find them disturbing and annoying.3. Only the Americans have so far conducted large-scaleexperiments aimed at a direct assessment of public tolerance ofbangs. Their report on these tests, carried out over Oklahoma Cityin 1964, which they have been unable to summarise, says:&quot; There will be many conclusions and judgments on thebasis of this total Oklahoma City record, and there may be room for technical controversy in some areas.&quot;Both supporters and opponents of the SST programme have foundammunition in the Report in support of their case. The americans are about to start a further series of tests. They have mildlyreproached us (and the French) for having done so little beyondtheoretical studies. Despite the public reaction to the tests, the americans intend to go on with their SST project and for the first time to vote federal funds for a civil aircraft.
4. The French have produced a survey of public reactions tosonic bangs of which the populations of eastern and south-westernFrance have had considerable experience as a result of military flying in recent years. Like the American report, this leaves muchscope for controversy. In Britain, the only sonic bangs heard inrecent years have been from occasional flights by military aircraftunder development; and these give rise to a fair volume of complaint.Service aircraft are required to do their supersonic flying over thesea. Our own efforts in the field of sonic bang research have been confined to theoretical studies and a few brief, simple andinconclusive tests (e.g., the one-day test (Operation Westminster) atPeterborough in April 1965).The need for regulation5. Undoubtedly the annoyance which would be caused byunrestricted operation of SSTs in regular airline service would be so great that Governments will be obliged to restrict their operation.Tolerance of bangs is dependent on frequency as well as intensity.Most experts consider that the level at which people would findfrequent bangs intolerable probably lies between 1 and 2\ poundsper square foot. Both Concord and the American SST are expectedto produce bangs within this range while cruising at supersonicspeed. No one knows whether people&apos;s tolerance would increase or decrease with increasing experience of bangs. Even if there were no Concord, it would still be necessary to decide our attitude tooverflights of United Kingdom territory by foreign SSTs and to restrictions by foreign Governments on overflights of their territory by SSTs operated by British airlines.Possible further tests6. It would be possible to use RAF aircraft to produce a fewunannounced sonic bangs over populated areas. If the bangs werelight, it might be possible to demonstrate that they were notnoticeable against the background of ordinary urban noise in large cities. If heavy bangs were deliberately made over small towns amost adverse public reaction could readily be evoked which couldbe used to support an argument that regular supersonic operationover populated areas would be intolerable. But none of this wouldbe at all scientific, convincing, or conclusive. The thorough testswhich my colleagues asked me to consider would have to be carefullyplanned and prepared (especially from the public relations and social survey aspects). They would have to extend over several months(at least six months, to be of any real value) and they would take further time to evaluate. Even if we were prepared to proceed tosuch tests without legislation (and I am very doubtful whether, inthe light of the Attorney-GeneraFs advice to which I refer below,we should risk doing this) and even if we regarded the tests as a first claim on the resources of RAF Fighter Command (whoseLightnings are the only aircraft capable of producing the bangs wewould need), we could not hope to have the results before the summer of 1967 at the earliest. Such tests, therefore, cannot help us to decide whether or not to continue with Concord for the next year or so.
7. Thorough tests would involve a series of flights by RAFLightnings over populated areas (which we should have to select inadvance), starting with one light bang a day and building upgradually, over six months, to about eight bangs a day of about the intensity to be expected from Concord. There is no doubt that the tests would be unpopular with a large number of people and that alarge number of damage claims would be made. These would be investigated and wherever there was a reasonable supposition thatsonic bang had been the cause of damage the Claims commission would make ex gratia payments in the usual way. I am advised bythe Attorney-General that there is some risk of an aggrieved personbringing an action against the Crown for damages or for an injunctionto stop the tests. While he does not consider that this risk in itselfnecessitates legislation, it would, in his view, be undesirable for theCrown to initiate tests on a large scale which would inevitably causedamage to property and be a nuisance in law. For this reason he suggests that legislation would be desirable. A preliminary estimateof the costs of the social survey and other scientific research thatwould be required and of the settlement of claims arising from the test is  70,000. To these might be added the costs of the use ofRAF aircraft, for which the charge by the Ministry of Defence tothe Ministry of Aviation might be about  50,000.8. We could hope to gain from the tests a better unstanding of the intensity and frequency of sonic bangs which people mighttolerate and of the possibility of their becoming acclimatised tothem. We should have demonstrated that we are prepared to investigate the problem in practical terms and would have a betterbasis on which to discuss with other Governments the regulation ofSST operations. For these reasons I think the tests would be worth while, and if my colleagues agree, I shall submit more detailed proposals. I should in this context consider the possibility of carryingout joint tests with the French, or of pressing them to carry out theirown tests in parallel.9. Meanwhile, however, I must emphasise that there is nothingwe can do in this field in the short term which will help us materiallyin deciding whether or not to continue with Concord. I am. doubtfulwhether, even if we do carry out tests such as I have indicated,we shall at the end be in a much better position to decide, since notests in this country will enable us to forecast directly or accuratelythe restrictions which other Governments may place on operations by SSTs.SECRET


</content>
</cab>
