<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/25/0 images: 8-8</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.(65) 14 4 March 1965 10 a.m.

1. Parliament (oral).

Absent.

2. Oversea Affairs (oral).

Absent.

3. National Army Museum C.(65) 36.

Absent.

4. Soundproofing of private houses near London Airport. C.(65) 38.

[Enter M. Avn.

Absent for beginning.

M.P. Large increase in freight services coming. Therefore must meet problem – somehow, but not this way? Function of travel from airports to city centres. ?Also compel L.A.‟s to build only soundproofed houses.

M.H.L.G. Noise protection required near some factories: therefore can‟t be restricted to this case. Military airports: overhead motorways also a good case. Therefore go ahead – on basis that maker of noise pays.

S/S. D. I agree: but L. Airport so much worse than others that can restrict initially to this case.

H.S. Will measures be effective?

M. Avn Reasonably so.

M.T. Watch overhead motorways. Repercussions inevitable.

Ch. Exch. ?Therefore wider survey of implications. And essential to make producers of noise pay.

M. Avn 40% a realistic figure. Since service of loan will be met by Authority, from its revenue, cost will be met by noise makers.

F. S/S. Can‟t hold it at 4½ mile limit. And motorways services, therefore consider in greater detail before committing ourselves.

P.M. Can‟t defer much longer: and marginal cases will always arise. If act now, can use A. Authy Bill. But ? power to make loans to householders without ready cash.

M.H.L.G. £100 not the limit: if we concede s‟proofing in principle, improvements will add to cost.

P.M. Agree in principle: must be self-financing: tax on night noise: Exch. must provide initial loan: repercussions must be resisted on grounds of difference

(legal &amp; otherwise) between airport and other noises. Treat this case as an experiment. Inter-govtl. considn to go on meanwhile.

5. Deduction of union subscriptions from wages. C.(65) 35.

P.M. Shd. first discuss among “political” Ministers.

F. S/S. I agree.

P.M. Consider without Secretariat.

6. Farm Price Review (oral).

M.A.F.F. If we appear reasonable, no major row. Therefore go to +£10m. or £11m.

Ch. Duchy. Quite small price changes affect pattern of prodn: watch milk and eggs. But +£10-11m., tho‟ worth conceding to safeguard posn of Ag. Ministers in future review of ag. Indy, must be sticking point.

S/S. S. I agree. Even at +£10-11m., farmers will be dissatisfied: but our posn will be defensible.

Ch. Exch. Not a good bargain. £21m. is margin between +£10-11m. and minimum permissible settlement.

Can we assume at least acquiescence at +£10-11m?

And are we conceding another £3m. on middle band for pigs?

M.A.F.F. It will be offset. Can‟t guarantee acquiescence: but moderate farmers want to be reasonable and major row avoidable.

P.M. Agree.

5. Deduction of union subscriptions from wages. C.(65) 35.

(Resumed with Secretariat!)

Ch. Exch. As in memm. Now requested by Staff Side as a whole. Practice of deducn of subscripn of this kind now more widespread. Therefore concede here, on basis of charge to cover cost. Only issue is political levy. If Staff Side are content, we won‟t object. And principle will be contracting in, not out.

Note U.P.W. &amp; P.O.E.U. Even if practice spreads to industrial unions, same principles will protect us.

P.M.G. I support this: U.P.W. feel strongly about it – and they and P.O.E.U. are unions mainly concerned. Practice is already adopted by natd inds: and G.P.O. is very close to these.

On levy, six choices will be open to individual: and if unions concerned don‟t fear impact on members, nor need we. Staff Side not affd to T.U.C.

Ch. Duchy. I don‟t like this: pressure comes entirely from U.P.W. and shd. be resisted if civil servants not to become entangled with politics. Consider further.

M. Lab. Practice (wh. I dislike) is growing. Safeguards now proposed – voluntary basis etc. – are adequate. Can‟t exclude U.P.W., merely because civil servants; and rejection will increase pressure for „closed shop‟.

S/S. W. I too support. If we reject, Govt. as employer will be rejecting what other employers concede: and it is a request from all unions concerned via Staff Side.

S/S. S. On balance I too support. A minor complicn in Scotland‟s hospitals.

P.M. Agree any statement on this with Tsy: no individual treatment.

F. S/S. I dislike the practice. But on merits:-

a) political levy will appear objectionable: we shall be charged with using Govtl machinery for Labour Party‟s benefits.

b) we shall also be accused of using political affiln to affect promotion prospects of individual civil servants.

c) we shall face „closed shop‟ issue, on grounds that this is first step in promoting c.s. in public service.

d) we shall be asked about breakaway unions: and, if they are not included, c.s. charge will be reinforced.

In short, bad ground for a political row. Let us take more time to consider.

Ch. Exch. I don‟t dissent; but not all unions are L. Party‟s unions. Some are not affd either to T.U.C. or to L. Party.

L.P. I support F. S/S. It will be represented as political coercion.

M.P. Unless deduction is flat sum, no means of detecting whether pol. Levy is included or not.

Ch. Exch. Most C.S. deductions are flat sums.

M. Lab. Closed shop argument rebutted it we reject claim for it in G.P.O. unions – as we must.

P.M.G. I agree. And no charge of coercion will stand if range of 6 choices is open.

P.M. Take more time: resume in “political” group. Might be wise to remit to

R. Cmn.

</content>
</cab>
