<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/25/0 images: 15-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (65) 21 1 April 1965 10 p.m.

1. T.S.R.2 or F-111A. C.(65) 57 contd and C.(65) 58.

Ch. Exch. Cancelln of TSR2 wd. be major point in convincing opinion we were in earnest about redeployment.

H.S. If cancel TSR2, can any other aircraft (apart from TFX) fulfil role which we regard as indispensable?

F. S/S. TSR2 began 8 years ago after Bucc. had been adopted as naval aircraft. If Bucc. had started as R.A.F., there wd. have been no T.S.R.2. Role cd. be discharged by Bucc. wh. is used by S.A.A.F. as land based. Its ferry range is only 500 miles less than TSR2: and at operational (subsonic) level, its capability is as good as TSR2 or TFX.

Therefore we shd. not continue wasteful expre. on TSR2, and try for 100% perfection when 95% perfection (Bucc. II Star) is within our reach. No need to replace with TFX – at cost of £500m. in $, since only 10 wd. be useless &amp; we shd. have to buy more, for which there is no case. Therefore examine Phantom/Kestrel mix and Buccaneer: and discuss with C. of S. other than C.A.S.

This wd. help R &amp; D &amp; design teams – whereas TFX wd. not. Ordinary labour force – say 20,000 – shd. be easily absorbed and are badly needed, particularly if Weybridge, not Preston.

Therefore concede option on TFX, provided other options are open &amp; examined and we cancel TSR2 now.

S/S. D. See C(65) 58: firm assurance from McNamara that offer of price is open without any commitment except that initial order must be by 1.1.‟66.

P.B.T. Difficult to judge F. S/S.‟s new proposal at short notice.

On redeployment, easy to exaggerate export potential of released resources. Since Jan., $ cost has risen from $400m to $500m. If so, better to spend extra £250-300m. on completing TSR2.

On option, if 10 TFX‟s useless, option is really a commitment to buy more: and then we are dept on U.S., even more than already in respect of Polaris.

Even if order is reduced $ liability still heavy: dependence on U.S. remains; and export potential of B.A.C. gravely damaged in face of growing U.S. competn. If we don‟t want any TFX‟s, that is a new sitn wh. needs more examn.

? Better to buy smaller number of TSR2‟s – even at higher unit cost – if we want some aircraft of this type.

M. Techy I support P.B.T.

S/S. D. Bucc. II Star no more real than TSR2: and range, bomb load and carrier capacity not adequate.

P.M. Reject –

i) carry on full blast with TSR2.

ii) cancel TSR2 &amp; replace with firm order for TFX.

There remain:

iii) cancel TSR2 and make no replacement.

iv) .. .. .. take TFX option without commitment.

v) continue .. until defence review completed.

S/S. D. ? And (vi) continue TSR2 and take option. I have strained McNamara‟s patience. If we let option go for now, we may have to pay more later.

M.H.L.G. If review is in summer, negligible amount at stake meanwhile. And does Budget impact matter? But depce on U.S. does: and don‟t hurry this until whole review picture before us. F. S/S‟s proposal wd. land us with TFX.

S/S. ES. I favour (iii). Cannot afford to continue TSR2: must release resources: and don‟t then waste them in paying for TFX for wh. there may be no military need.

M. Avn If option really open, leave it open until other options explored.

S/S. D. I cdn‟t justify cancelln of TSR2 unless I cd. say what aircraft will replace it, if replacement found to be necessy.

If option disallowed, go on with TSR2.

Ch. Exch. I wd. go for iv), believing we shall never take up option.

M. Techy But don‟t risk charge that we have transferred aircraft industry and large part of electronics industry to U.S. Therefore I side with P.B.T. and S/S. E/S.

Ch. Exch. But go in with French!

M.A.F.F. I favour (v) – like M.H.L.G.

M.P. I favour (iii): but investigate F. S/S.‟s proposal on Buccaneer: postpone decision however, until industrial implicns of cancellation clear.

L. Ch. I favour (iv).

S/S. E/S. So, on reconsidn, do I.

M.O.D. So do I. But we must cancel TSR2: postponement wd. be politically disastrous.

Ch. Duchy. To cancel TSR2 and go American is technological defeat. Therefore I favour (v).

Col. Sec. I favour (i).

S/S. W. So do I.

L.P. If Bucc. II Star is out [S/S. D. confirmed], substn of TFX for TSR2 is too damaging politically. Therefore I vote for (v).

H.S. I for (iv).

M.T. Option wd. be surrender to U.S. And irresponsible to cancel TSR2 before review. Therefore I vote (v).

C.S. I vote for (iv) – and hope for Buccaneer in interim.

L.P.S. I for (iii).

S/S. S. I for (v).

M. Lab. Can‟t risk political damage of postponement again. Therefore I vote for (iv).

F.S. I also for (iv). It is our insolvency wh. inhibits our foreign policy.

M. Avn Nature of option keeps changing: is it really open-ended? Otherwise cancellation of TSR2 v. dangerous.

S/S. D. No commitment to buy TFX: only stipn is that, if we take it up, we must place first order by 1.1.66. Price firm for 110-70: below 70 R &amp; D waiver for negotn.

M. Avn Then I vote for (iv).

M. Techy If an option, it will be exercised. Therefore I favour (v).

M.H.L.G. I agree – entirely.

Ch. Whip I too favour (v).

F. S/S. I favour (iv).

Col. Sec. I favour (v).

L.P.S. I favour (iv) – with reservn we shall never take up option.

S/S. W. I too favour (iv).

P.M. Small majority in favour of (iv). I will accept this decision: but it can be v. badly misrepresented as surrender to U.S. Presentn therefore v. important. My redraft of first para. of Annex to C(65) 58: accept second para: omit third para. (tho‟ complete these arrangements without publication in either country until we find it convenient). Announce in Budget: with full

M. Def. statement that evening, with script. If any change in wholly non-committal nature of option, Cab. must reconsider.

2. E.L.D.O. C.(65) 54. [Enter Ch. Secy

P.M. As in memm. Watch impact on France – particularly if TSR2 decision looks like another Nasser – and on our techl image.

Ch. Exch. In light of decision on TSR2, must temper wind a bit, without committing ourselves too far – e.g. let it run on till end of year.

Ch. Secy I agree – but reconsider before reach E.L.D.O. B, in light of costs of B.

M. Avn An untenable position. Can‟t avoid decision on going ahead (or not) with E.L.D.O. B. in principle. Otherwise we shall be isolated. But I will try to

bring our share of expre. down to 25% or 30% at max: and try to keep at Woomera.

Ch. Exch. In principle – but not in cash or commitments!

P.M. M. Avn probably right: but I will do my best with de G. to protect Ch. Exch. &amp; to offset against Str./Trainer aircraft.

S/S. E.S. No economic case for continuing: no real scientific interest: no evidence that techl co-opn with Europe improves relations – rather the reverse.

P.M. Paris tel.: French may be more flexible!

M. Avn This may make it more difficult for us!

P.M. Agree v. low economic priority. But may have to go on for political reasons. I will explore with de G.

F.S. Must avoid odium of appearing to kill project.

</content>
</cab>
