<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/25/0 images: 18-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (65) 24 8 April 1965, 10.30 a.m.

1. Parliament (oral).

L.P. As in Statement. Intrusion of V. of Censure will require H/C. to reassemble on Monday 26 April, instead of Tuesday 27 April.

Discussion of Vote of Censure: decided not to amend but simply to vote down.

2. Oversea Affairs (oral).

(a) Viet-Nam.

M/S. F.O. L.B.J.‟s statement more hopeful. In line with our own initiative. We had advance notice last night. P.M. will welcome in Statement this afternoon. Can we get response? N. V-N. have rejected P.G.-W.‟s visit: keep that secret for moment. Peking still silent. But even if they reject, still let trip proceed. [Exit L.P.S.

(b) Berlin. [Enter Dy S/S.D.

M/S. F.O. New harassing of access: &amp; Soviet jets buzzing Bundestag meeting in Berlin. (The first since 1958.)

Don‟t take too seriously: inevitable Soviet reaction wh. shd. end when B‟stag meetings end on 11 April. Must make formal protest: but try to keep temperature down. Shows we were right to oppose meeting in Berlin: and Germans recognise this.

3. Military Aid to India and Pakistan. C.(65) 60.

C.S. As in memm. If some aid given, must time it with our eye on our oversea creditors. Proposals are more modest than originally, and cd. be authorised with min. of publicity.

Ch. Exch. Military aid only began after Chinese aid – but growing rapidly. Five years ago total was £5m: now £29m. And watch dangers of competitors bidding by I. &amp; P. Total bill, including further demands, cd. be v. large. Therefore take stock before committed too far. And prefer ec. aid, if possible.

M.H.L.G. Shd. be clearly without prejudice to defence review.

S/S. ES. Aircraft maybe: but why submarine (for P. as well)?

And expansion of Govt. expre. overseas contrary to Ch. Exch.‟s attempts to save on oversea investt.

P.B.T. But must maintain some degree of military aid. Otherwise v. damaging to our political relations with India.

M.O.D. But mustn‟t jeopardise ec. aid. Russian ec. aid to I. already higher than ours.

D.S/S.D. Proposals are minimum qua defence needs of I. If we don‟t give it, I. will go elsewhere. And our ec. aid will free resources with which they can, if we won‟t help them.

L.P. And ec. advantages to us in building two subs. in U.K.

S/S. W. Will defence aid compel us to reduce ec. aid?

Ch. Exch. Probably not: but U.S. shd. carry more of the defence aid.

M/S. F.O. But that wd. reduce our standing with U.S. Whatever we do, we must concert it with U.S. in light of our joint E. of S. policy.

P.B.T. And don‟t sacrifice good will (= markets) wh. we have gained by prompt response to original I. appeal for help.

M.A.F.F. I entirely agree.

F. S/S. ? Concede 4 aircraft.

Ch. Exch. That commits us to other 26.

C.S. But other 26 are no use to us. And I. will turn elsewhere.

If we don‟t give military aid, ec. aid won‟t be necessary. We shall break away from I. Navy: links will be broken: and we shall lose all our influence with I. Then no need for ec. aid.

At least try to concert policy with U.S. before final decision.

F. S/S. Ec. case for building subs. here – in vacant berth of 5th Polaris.

L.P. If we refuse I. may go Communist.

D.S/S.D. And watch risks of Soviet penetration of I. Navy.

M.H.L.G. But that means committing ourselves to policy of competitive bidding in arms E. of S.

Ch. Exch. I agree: concert with U.S. – who may have spare subs.

F.S/S. No: don‟t shift any more defence orders to U.S. Concede 4 aircraft – and subs?

L. Ch. No: all the Hunters, but no subs. No harm in one Russian sub.

M.H.L.G. Sub., won‟t protect I. against China!

D.S/S.D. But it trains escort vessels.

M/S. F.O. And, if we reject it, we are out of I. Navy: and we cdn‟t do this without consultn with U.S. – who might then withdraw from our other I. Ocean sharing proposals.

L.P. But if I. turns to S.U., they will lose U.S. aid. They won‟t risk that.

M.T. Must concede 30 Hunters: but not subs. Must therefore discuss these with U.S., before decision.

S/S. S. I agree: subs are merely prestige projects wh. we can‟t afford to finance.

H.S. And what is our total commitment on defence aid likely to be?

C.S. We have rubbed in our limitations, to all our clients!

F. S/S. Either refuse or concede 30 aircraft: and subs in balk until discussns with U.S. Cab. approve latter. [Exit M/S. F.O: D.S/S.D.

[Enter A.G: Parly Sec. M/L.

4. Iron and Steel Nationalisation. C.(65) 59.

M.P. As in memm. On para. 15(c), I will do my best with T.U.C., to satisfy them. But watch leak. On hybridity, Speaker is formally reserving his position: but all indications are that no real risk.

Discussion of draft W.P.

a) Para. 2: second sentence – delete in order to avoid risk of defeat, wh.

wd. be defeat on Bill, &amp; compel us to go to country on steel. Therefore delete and amend to read “legislative proposals”.

b) Section III: P.M. queried necessity – but, if so, omit para. 14.

Agreed: to change title and reorder as proposed by M.H.L.G. Omit

Para. 14: quantify sums in paras 11 &amp; 12. Delete para. 10 and first sentence of para. 11.

c) Para. 15(c). ? Strengthen refces. to surplus manpower: or too

dangerous at outset? Leave alone – except for expansion of refces. to pace of future techl devt in this industry.

d) Para. 15(d). Rewrite to make more positive.

e) Para. 18. Does this presentn increase risk of hybridity? Better to state

principle – e.g. tonnage outputs etc. – wh. produces these names rather than other way round. Also deal separately with R.T.B. – already publicly owned.

f) Para. 21. Clarify which is subsidiary of which – add “respectively”.

g) Para. 24. This shd. be layman‟s version, with technical appx. Or

confine to v. general statement, leaving details for Bill? Latter wd. expose us to v. damaging attack – expropriation etc. Therefore include.

h) Paras. 25-26. Is retrospection too long? Wd. date of publicn of W.P.

be wise?

Reconsider: if no large scale disposals etc. – substitute date of W.P. M.P. to consider.

No: risk too great. Stand as is. Possible compromise or right to take to courts any option conditional on W.P.

i) Para. 44: last sentence. ? Omit &amp; say it in a speech. Gives more room

for manoeuvre. Omit.

j) Para. 46. Omit last two sentences.

Timing of publicn. Committed not to publish before Easter: and give time for stock markets &amp; intl markets to settle down after Budget. Therefore defer until after Easter &amp; then reconsider in light of I.M.F. drawing etc. Therefore take 30 April as target – but let Cab. reconsider nearer time. Debate in first half of May. Introduce Bill in June; guillotine &amp; send upstairs. Lords will be squeezed – but so what?

</content>
</cab>
