<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/25/0 images: 24-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (65) 30 13 May 1965, 10.30 a.m.

1. Parliament (oral). [Enter Ch. Whip.

L.P. As in Statement.

2. Legislative Programme (oral). [Enter M.L.N.R.

P.M. ? Bring forward Land, Steel and Housing Finance in order to have them all before public opinion in case of early election.

? Or bring forward Land &amp; Steel, make some progress and decide whether to have extended session; or abandon &amp; reintroduce them (with housing finance?); or decide election necessary in autumn if mortality so dictates!

L.P. August sitting impracticable. But can‟t accuse Oppn of deliberate obstruction so far.

Session could be ended in July (or with small overlap) on basis of legn now introduced. Steel cd. be introduced in June: Land not till July. Tactical advantages in taking them together.

Adjourn for one week at Whitsum: and at end of July until mid Oct. – for summer. Then take Steel &amp; Land (and housing finance) forthwith: take cttee. stages upstairs.

Could introduce Land &amp; Steel before end of July – with open admission they are to be introduced for informn only.

Cab. cd. also decide, if they wished, to prorogue in Sept. and go to the country.

P.M. Not necy to decide – or make open admission – now. Cd. introduce, with apparent intention of enacting this Session; and leave till Sept. to decide whether to take this course or to abandon and reintroduce. Decision wd. have to be taken in Sept. in any case, for electoral reasons.

Ch. Exch. Must try to include Leasehold Reform somehow.

M.L.N.R. Not easy to accelerate Land: but publish as soon as possible, with minimum of interval after the White Paper.

M.H.L.G. 3 large policy issues on L. reform; but v. difficult and wiser to continue to promise to deal with it than to tackle prematurely!

L. Ch. And don‟t forget Parliamentary Commissioner!

Ch. Duchy. And two Social Security Bills!

P.B.T. And Companies Bill – including political contributions.

L.P. Not more than 14 days desirable between introdn of Steel &amp; 2 R.

M.H.L.G. Then more sensible to decide now whether to have extended session or not and time Steel accordingly.

M.A.F.F. I agree. And all argts. favour ending Session in July.

P.M. If so, must say when Bill is introduced?

Ch. Exch. No: can‟t introduce in July and say not proceeding this Session.

P.M. I accept. Announcement about end of Session shd. be made in Sept. – and not decided till then.

F. S/S. But at least take 2 R. of Land Bill in July – which keeps all options open, leaves everybody guessing &amp; puts Land slightly ahead of Steel.

Ch. Duchy. But don‟t fox our own supporters too much. 2R. of Land Bill will be taken by them as meaning Session goes on. Must therefore be reasonably frank.

P.M. Maybe: but balance of advantage lies in introducing Steel &amp; Land – and others (incl. Housing Finance) if possible – in July, leaving till then to decide what shd. then be said about their timetable and also whether Land shd. be only W.P. or a Bill.

F.L. Cttee. shd. now plan on assumpn that Land &amp; Steel will probably be first orders in autumn. [Exit M.L.N.R.

3. Oversea Affairs (oral).

a) N.A.T.O. Council.

F.S. Reasonably amicable. Even Fr. did not press U.S. to abandon V.Nam; but great emphasis on need for U.S. to negotiate and to keep allies informed.

b) Dominican Republic.

F.S. No real Govt. yet: and no qun of recognition. Both factions have armed support: and various armed splinter groups. U.S. forces of 40,000 remain: but O.A.S. force to take over and to try to evolve acceptable Govt.

In S. Council, U.S. force wd. have been accepted if only moderate. Its build up more open to criticism: but difficult not to support Uruguayan resn, tho‟ U.S. dislike. Must judge according to support wh. it commands – avoiding split with U.S. if possible.

P.M. We have made our anxiety clear to U.S. Must try to moderate U. resn and then vote for it, even if U.S. abstain.

M.H.L.G. Did we back U.S. (at outset) prematurely, thus putting ourselves in embarrassment of saying now what we ought to have said at the beginning. Always clear that U.S. intervenn was not merely for saving of life: and this has worried those elements of Party who accommodated V.Nam policy with difficulty.

F.S. We only supported attempt to save lives (incl. Br. lives); and our posn is reserved on anything more. But can‟t let D. lapse into chaos; must recognise U.S. help unavoidable for reconstitution of D; and must reaffirm principles of U.N. Charter. Difficult to steer course through these.

P.M. Agree: intervenn may be violation of Charter and Caradon will make this clear.

M.H.L.G. Now: but why not at the outset, since it was clear then that this was military intervenn.

F.S. This may have been its purpose: but must consider effects also – can‟t condemn U.S. action but expect our nationals to be protected.

M.O.D. To vote for resn on wh. U.S. may abstain cd. do nothing but good.

F.S. Maybe: but it happens v. rarely and is inconsistent with our declared policy of Atlantic Alliance etc. Therefore I am warning Cab. in time that this sitn may arise.

P.M. And we will maintain pressure on U.S. to consult us properly in cases of this kind. We will rub it into Rusk.

F. S/S. I endorse all that we have done from outset. May have to vote differently from U.S., but recognise a bad thing and a v. grave decision.

[Exit M.H.L.G.

4. Commercial Policy: Imports of Cotton Textiles after the end

of 1965. C.(65) 71.

P.B.T. As in memm – imports to increase by 1½% p.a., as best compromise between interests of oversea suppliers and domestic producers.

On method, global quota (perhaps with country quotas) the best – to last for 5 years. Tariff on C‟w. imports (for first time) untimely before C‟w. P.Ms. Meeting and impracticable at any reasonable level.

Col. Sec. Why not a Cotton Commission?

P.B.T. C. Board must in any case be reconstituted in next 12 months.

F. S/S. Quota (global) for 3-5 years certainly right. But concept of Cmn ought to be kept open, not dismissed.

M.O.D. How will global quotas be allocated? Cd. not this be function of Commission?

P.B.T. Global wd. be partly unallocated (for competn) and partly allocated (for sake of India).

M.O.D. Unallocated part will be unacceptable to Lancs., and, in so far as it depresses prices, to underdevd countries also. Both want stability and end of uncertainty. Countervailing levy better, with Cmn wh. cd. manage market; and margin cd. be used for addl aid to underdevd countries.

P.M. We proposed Cmn because we opposed quotas and tariff on C‟w. imports. But Consve Govt. endorsed quotas – wh. alters posn. Better to keep Cmn in reserve, since it is fear of this wh. will make foreign suppliers accept voluntary quotas. Therefore negotiate quotas on this basis and then consider whether we want c‟vailing levy or Cotton Cmn or what.

P.B.T. I agree. Must avoid both price disruption and rigid country quotas. Some element of competn will be good for Lancs.

P.M. Agree: must allow time for I.C.I./Courtaulds venture to mature.

C.S. Agree: tariff v. unwise at this moment and quotas much better.

P.M. And must press E.E.C. to take more imports.

P.B.T. Implicit that any increase in domestic prodn must be exported, unless it can compete with quota imports, wh. won‟t then fill quota. It is here that I.C.I./C. venture may be helpful.

Ch. Duchy. We neglect domestic industry: cf. agriculture. I speak for Todmorden!

It is not our duty to help low cost producers abroad, especially since surcharge is not permanent. P.B.T. must be tough in negotiating quotas if viable dom. indy is to survive.

Col. Sec. Make sure threat of Cmn is clear in our presentation.

Ch. Exch. Leave as is for 12 months?

P.B.T. Existing agts. expire at end of this year: pointless to extend for only 12 months.

F. S/S. Only 7% of labour in cotton belt works on cotton.

P.M. Approve – try for 5 years.

[Exit F.S.

5. Links between E.F.T.A. and E.E.C. (C.(65) 73; and 51 and 52).

P.M. Genesis of Vienna meeting. Base initiative on new institutions; review substantive proposals without committing ourselves; watch U.S. anxieties about extension of commercial discrimn against U.S. exports and disruption of K. Round by premature launching of initiatives wh. shd. follow K.R. and not exaggerate scope for mere bridge-building.

Metric system a possy and say so at Vienna. Dec. coinage more slowly. Must strengthen E.F.T.A., while avoiding excessive rigidifying until future of relationship with E.E.C. more clear; and must prevent its disintegration.

Col. Sec. Any scope for joint E.E.C./E.F.T.A. initiative to help devg countries?

P.M. Might be – to supplement O.E.C.D. and U.N. agencies.

Ch. Exch. Watch monetary co-opn v. carefully – dangerous for next few years. And don‟t offer any further redn of surcharge yet.

P.M. Agree on mony policy, particly capital movements. On surcharge, stick to declared policy.

M.A.F.F. E.F.T.A. Sect will try to give agricl (and fisheries) content to discussns. That means more access to our market. Be careful!

M. Techy Scope for techl collabn not yet clear: but if to go ahead must take indy etc into consultn.

C.S. Prior consultn must include Eire. [Exit M. Lab.

M.P. Little scope for real progress while de G. is with us.

P.M. Not sure: he likes E.F.T.A. more than E.E.C.!

M.P. If so, use orgns such as I. and Steel Community.

P.B.T. Circulate statements on metric system. If so, must consult B.S.I. and inform F.B.I. (who favour in principle).

M. Techy My Advisory Council will be considering this, qua standards, next week. There is a lot of oppn – unless we clear the way first – qua stocks of non-metric components.

This is a major step: watch it!

C.S. I agree: must watch trade with U.S. &amp; C‟w. who do not use metric standards.

P.M. P.B.T. to consult other Depts. on wording of Statements and on timetable of consultns with other countries. [Exit P.B.T.

6. Trade Disputes Bill: Retrospection. C.(65) 72. [Enter A.G.

A.G. As in memm – concession on Report. Advisable to avoid major row on issue of principle.

P.M. M. Lab. endorses.

L. Ch. So do I.

M. Techy ? Consult T.U.C.

A.G. But they might reject it!

M. Techy At least inform them.

P.M. I agree: I will ask M. Lab. to do so – or F. S/S.

</content>
</cab>
