<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/25/0 images: 48-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (65) 58 9 November 1965 1 p.m. H/C.

Rhodesia (oral).

P.M. Beadle arrived: brief discussn shows u.d.i. imminent, perhaps to-night. Rh. Cab. divided: S. still trying to launch R.C. Sticking point is our willingness to commend to Parlt whatever action wd. follow unanimous report. No risk of un. report. Even so – if no secret understanding, wh. is unacceptable – wd. be an issue of confidence. Also wd. commit Parlt in some sense: and if e.g. a Sharpeville in interim wd. alter sitn. But, if we refuse, may be a u.d.i.

Even so, Rh. technique is blackmail. Although domestic Oppn hope to divide U.K. on this issue, especially on sanctions and on colour question – tho‟ Heath‟s statement reserved rights of Parlt – public opinion supports us and rejects S.‟s illegal and presumptuous attitude.

Pending further discussn with B., merely say this afternoon what I said in my message – including offer of discussn in Malta.

S. might accept un report – but at risk of resigning. Therefore must put posn in terms of Govt.‟s willingness to accept – provided we don‟t commit ourselves.

S/S. D Risk of u.d.i. v. grave. ?Better to concede undertaking to commend if Rh. Govt. will do same. ?At least ask them.

M.O.D. But, if so, we shall have abandoned all but the 5th principle.

A.G. That sitn won‟t arise: there can‟t be a unanimous report.

C.S. But, if we concede this, we will ask for more.

L. Ch. Must make clear we haven‟t asked B. to come, and that he comes with S.‟s good wishes.

Avoid anything wh. wd. provoke u.d.i. to-day. Ask S. for written undertaking that, if we concede this point, S. won‟t raise any more points. If he gives this undertaking, we shd. put it to H/C. – Govt can‟t give this commitment alone.

P.M. Won‟t close any doors this afternoon: no major statement pending further talks with B. Reply, via B., must be in writing: and Cab. must approve it.

F. S/S. If real risk of u.d.i. to-day, Cab. shd. meet again for final thoughts.

P.M. Yes: but keep door open to-day, particularly as regards Malta.

</content>
</cab>
