<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/26 images: 458-469</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,    THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO EE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.MOST SECRET. COPY NO.     AW..M.  (40) 57th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 5.Confidential Annex.(9 th February,   1940,)ASSISTANCE THE PRIME MINISTER referred to the conclusion to FINLAND.reached by the War Cabinet at thci? meeting on 7th(previous reference:      February, that Brigadier Ling should convey to MarshalW.M. (40)35thConclusions,   Mannerheim an indication of our intentions in regardMinute l),to assistance to Finland.    He enquired when BrigadierLing would be starting.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said thatBrigadier Ling would not be leaving until Sunday.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that, if our intentions and plans were disclosed to Marshal Mannerheim,there was a grave risk that they might be communicated,first to the Finnish Government, and then possibly to norway and Sweden.   The Germans were evidently suspicious of our intentions, and were closely watching events,,   Theywere putting out threats as to the action which they wouldtake if we sent troops to or established air bases in Sweden,If they got to know of our plans, they might forestallus in Sweden.    It might be worth while reconsideringthe proposal to send Brigadier Ling to Finland,In discussion the following arguments, wereadvanced:-(a)   If no communication were made to the finns to indicate that we would behelping them before the critical momentarrived, there was a danger that they

might lose heart, arid suffer defeatbefore we were ready.    Marshal Mannerheimwould he greatly encouraged if he knew that he had only to hold out for acertain length of time before considerable assistance would arrive,(b)     It was possible that even if the Finnsdid not crack, if they did not know our intentions, they might consent to negotiations, or to mediation by Germany.Against this, however, the foreign secretary drew attention to TelegramNo. 75 from Finland, in which thePrime Minister of Finland was reported as having said that no suggestion ofmediation had been received, and that,if it were, it would not willingly belistened to, since peace offered byGermany would put the Finns under an obligation to Germany.    The Finnish minister for Foreign Affairs had under-taken to keep the French and ourselvesinformed if any proposals were madeDOn the other hand,(a)   Present information tended to show thatthe Finnish military 2?ceibtanc*ei wouldnot crack, especially as there werereports that the Swedes might send further assistance in the shape of volunteers,

(a-)   A communication to Marshal   Mannerheira ofour intentions might prejudice secrecy. Inthis connection, it was pointed out thatsecrecy would in any case he very hard tomaintain, as could he judged from a report received by the Secretary of State for war that M. Eeynaud and M, Leger had told thev/hole Allied plan to a British Memberof Parliament (not a member of the&amp;ove?mesit) who had passed throughPariso(c)     If Marshal Mannerheim knew of our intentions, there was a risk that, if. the finns  were hard pressed, he might make a premature...appeals   The Germans had their troops ready, and might well attack Swedenbefore we could intervene.It was suggested as an alternative thatBrigadier Ling might go to Finland, and afford moral support to Marshal Mannerheim as a friend, and talk tohim in terms of volunteers.   He could explain to theMarshal how difficult it was to get the Swedes to allowsubstantial numbers to pass through their territory,and might urge him to bring all possible pressure to bearon the Swedes,    At the same time, he could act as a link with Finland, and furnish accurate reports of thehappenings there,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that hewould like to give the matter further consideration,and hear the views of Brigadier Ling himself before adecision was taken.-

mTHE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO thought therewas one Important aspect of our plans for interventionwhich had not been fully examined.     This was theprogramme for subsequent reinforcement after the first three divisions had been landed in Scandinavia.   when we informed Norway and Sweden of our proposed plan, itwas almost certain that they would ask what furtherforces we were prepared to send.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY assumed thatwe would move any reinforcements as necessary to counter the strength of the forces employed by Germany.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF saidthat General Gamelin had remarked to him, in c on versa-tion, that if there was no attack on the Western Frontby April, the Allies must look for other theatres of operation.     General Gamelin clearly envisaged thepossibility of taking divisions away from France incertain circumstances.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY thought thatthe moral   to be drawn was the urgency of pressing on with our preparations as fast as possible, and he askedwhether the War Cabinet could be provided with a time-table.     It would be of special interest to see how soonthe leading elements of our forces would be ready tomove.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFFemphasised the dangers of a gap between the movement ofthe first units and the next supporting body.THE CHIEF OF NAVAL STAFF informed the WarCabinet that the Chiefs of Staff had arranged to meeton Thursday eaoh week, to review the progress of the detailed plans and preparations.     He suggested that a

report should he made each week to the War Cabinet.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO thought thatthe Norwegians would be very anxious about the safety of Oslo, as a result of German threats to bomb their capital the moment the Allies attempted to set foot in norway.     He suggested that the possibility of ourtaking steps to increase the security of Oslo might be examined.THE PRIME MINISTER agreedo(i)   Agreed that it was undesirable thatBrigadier Ling should be authorisedto convey an indication of HisMajesty&apos;s Government&apos;s intentions toField-Marshal Mannerheim;   and in thesecircumstances invited the Secretaryof State for War to reconsider whetherBrigadier Ling should return to finland forthwith as arranged.    (Thissupersedes Conclusion (iii) toW.M. (40) 35th Conclusions, Minute 1,Confidential Annex.)(ii)   Requested the Chiefs of Staff -(a) To report each week,on Friday,the progress made in the preparations for the Scandinavianexpedition.(b) To examine whether there were any steps which could be taken toprovide protection to Oslo against air attack.-Richmond Terrace, S.W.1*




</content>
</cab>
