<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/83/0 images: 417-433</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
london^DQCUMENT IB THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).few 0 RET.COPY NO.cabinet  85 (36).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street, S.W.I.,  on WEDNESDAY, 1st APRIL, 1936,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1&apos;    FOREIGN AFFAIRS    -    (if required).2.    GERMANY AND THE LOCARNO TREATY    -    (if required).(Reference Cabinet 24 (36) Conclusion l).3.    THE ITALO-AbYSSINIAN DISPUTE    -    (if required).(Reference Cabinet 24 (36) Conclusion 2).4*    ANGLO-EGYPTIAN TREATY NEGOTIATIONS    -    (if required)(Reference Cabinet 24 (36) Conclusion 3).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.      CP.  98 (36).5.    MALTA:    PROPOSED LEGISLATION.(Reference Cabinet 51 (55) Conclusion 4 (c)).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for theColonies.CP.  91 (36)    -    to be circulated.6.    PALESTINE:    ESTABLISHMENT OF A LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL -(If required).(Reference Cabinet 24 (36) Conclusion 8).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for theColonies.CP. 87 (36)    -   already circulated.H Memoranda by the Secretary of State for theColonies.        CP.  95 (36) and CP. 99 (36).
7.    REMOVAL OF PARTS OF THE ROYAL ORDNANCE FACTORIES.(Reference Cabinet 41 (35) Conclusion 4).Note by the Secretary, covering Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for War, together withReport of an Inter-Departmental Committee andextract from the draft Minutes of the 275thMeeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence.CP. 93 (36)    -    to be circulated.8.    EMPLOYMENT OF UNTRUSTWORTHY PERSONS IN THL defence departments.(Reference Cabinet 24 (36) Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.CP. 82 (36)    -   already circulated.Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence.CP. 94 (36)    -    to be circulated.9.    PRIVATE MEMBERS&apos;  BILLS.For Friday, 3rd April.1. Betting (No.  1) Bill;    Second Reading.(Mr. R.J. Russell (L.N.)).(Reference Cabinet 24 (36) Conclusion 12).Memorandum by the Home Secretary.CP. 90 (36)    -   to be circulated.2. Representation of the People Bill;    SecondReading.    (Mr. Short (La.)).3. Local Authorities (Enabling) Bill;    SecondReading.      (Mr.  Thorne (La.)).(Signed)    M.P.A, HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.,27th March, 1936.
ll^jDOCUMSNT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).Ijr R E T.. COPY NO.C A B I N E T    85 (56),.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., onWednesday, 1st APRIL, 1936, at 11.0 a,m.PRESENT;The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).fe Right Hon.J.Ramsay MacDonald,M.P. 9Lord President of the Councilsfe Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.h Right Hon.Anthony Eden, M.C.,M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.ie Right Hon.A.Duff Cooper, D.S.O., M.P.,Secretary of State for War.Me Right Hon.jj The Viscount Swinton, G.B.S. ,M.C,Secretary of State for Air.fie Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,C.M.G.,  M.P.,Secretary of Statefor Scotland.fe Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.lie Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, CB .E. ,K.C .,M.P., Minister for Co-Ordinationof Defence.fe Right H0n.Oliver Stanley, M.C..M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.fie Right Hon.pErnest Brown, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, CCS. I. ,K.C.V.0.,O.B.E., K.C., M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G.,G.C.S.I.,  G.C.I.-jo,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,G.CS.I.,G.C.I.E., Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.J.H.Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies..The. Right Hon.The Viscount Monsell,G.B.E.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.F.*Minister of Health.The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works.
CONSCRIPTION. 1.    The Prime Minister drew the attention ofthe Cabinet to the following question to be asked. r.P--2.o(V^s!        in the House of Commons the same afternoon:-To ask the Prime Minister if he can givea guarantee that a conscription measure will not be introduced so long as peaceprevails.To this he proposed to answer:-Yes, Sir, so far as the present Governmentis concerned.The Cabinet agreed.
GERMANY ANDTHE locarno treaty..(previous reference:Cabinet 24 (36)Conclusion l).F.R.2.     The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs reported that he and the Lord Privy Seal had seen Herr von Ribbentrop that morning and hadreceived from him a document headed &quot;The Peace plan of the German Cabinet&quot;.       He gave the Cabinet aresume&apos; of the principal proposals.After a short discussion, the cabinet agreed:(a) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should arrange for the immediateduplication and circulation of theGerman Memorandum.(b) That the Cabinet should meet the same afternoon at 4.0 p.m.  in the PrimeMinister&apos;s room at the House ofCommons.(c) That as the document was to be publishedthe same evening, the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs should, if theGermans had no objection, communicateit to the French and Belgian governments the same afternoon.(d) That immediately after the/meeting ofthe Cabinet the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should see represen-tatives of the Press and give themsome guidance.
f CERMANY ANDI ipHB LOCARNOI TREATY.1 StaffI conversations.I The proposed Letter to the&apos; prench and belgian Govern-ments.(previous reference:Cabinet 24 (36)Conclusion l).p. K3.    The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairsconsulted the Cabinet as to what he was to say to the French Ambassador in reply to the FrenchGovernment&apos;s request for (i) Staff conversations,as provided in Section III of the White Paper(cmd.. 5134), and (ii) the dispatch of the letterto the French and Belgian Governments provided foron page 7 of the same White Paper. He consideredthat our position would not in any way be worsened,and from several points of view would be strengthened,by the dispatch of the letter and by acceding to therequest for Staff conversations, provided they were limited as had been proposed.In the course of the discussion, theMinister for Defence Co-Ordination reported thatthe Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee were anxious tohave precise instructions on the subject of the conversations before they took place.      They pointedout, as they had done before he himself had joined the Cabinet, that so long as our Mediterraneancommitments were maintained, our position in northern europe was a very weak one, even to the point ofour being dependent on the French Navy for theprotection of our coasts.      He understood that they intended to point out that the French themselvesmight be in  a  better state, but there was a risk that we might find.ourselves involved in a war inwhich we had to make demands on the French for ourprotection.      If the Mediterranean position had been cleared up the position would be better, but ifconversations took place in the present conditionthey would be very difficult.      Those were some of
the reasons why the Chiefs of Staff wanted veryprecise instructions.After discussion the Cabinet agreed:(a) That with a view to a decision inregard to the letter, the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs should, beforethe meeting of the Cabinet arranged forthat afternoon, circulate the revisedtext of the proposed letter.(b) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should be authorised to inform theFrench Ambassador that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment agreed to military conversa-tions on the understanding that theywere confined to the terms set out inSection III of the White Paper (Cmd.5134/36), and provided they.complied with thefollowing statement set forth in his speech in the House of Commons, onThursday, 26th March, viz:It is understood that this contactdoes not imply any political under-taking or any obligation as regardsdefence organisation between thetwo parties.(c) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should try to arrange for the conversations to take place in London.(d) That the Committee of Imperial defence should meet on Thursday, 2nd April, at11.0 a.m. to discuss the arrangementsfor the military conversations and theinstructions to the British Delegates.
fi the italo-i abyssinian[dispute.I The use of&quot;poison gas.I( previous Reference:1 Cabinet 24 (36)Conclusion 2).4.    The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,apart from mentioning that M. Madariaga,  theChairman of the Committee of Thirteen, was in touchY/ith the Italian Government on the question oftheir use of poison gas, said he had no question to raise.5 -
fb-EC-YPTIANloTlATIOWS.fitaryIvisions,previous reference sqtbinet 6 ( 36^ ,Inclusion 6.)I5. The Cabinet had. before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (C.P. 98 (36))covering a further exchange of telegrams with theHigh Commissioner in Egypt.      At the Meeting referredto in the margin the Cabinet had approved negotiationswith Egypt on the basis of what were known as stages&quot;A&quot;, &quot;B&quot; and &quot;C&quot;.      Stage &quot;Cu was a minimum, about which the Cabinet were not enthusiastic, and was notto be mentioned without prior reference in good timeto His Majesty&apos;s Government.      The Secretary of Statenow asked for a decision whether, in case the high commissioners further efforts were unsuccessful, he(the Secretary of State) could be authorised,  at themoment which he considered opportune, to instruct sir Miles Lampson to foreshadow stage siC&quot;,  includingthe evacuation by British troops of Abbassia and Helmiain favour of Helouan,  or some equally central locality,as a means of securing Egyptian consent to the continuedposting of British troops at Alexandria or in theneighbourhood of that city.After a short discussion the Cabinet agreed:-That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should be given discretion at such time as he might think opportune (but notduring the present week) to instruct SirMiles Lampson to pass to stage &quot;C&quot;, andthat he need not bring this question beforethe Cabinet again unless some new factorshould arise.
6.    The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (CP. 91.(36)),JfposedIffislation. recommending the introduction of a short Bill to restore to the Crown the full power to legislate forfevious Malta by prerogative legislation!    this would makeIference %cabinet 51 (55^,      possible the issue of Letters Patent repealing the(Inclusion 4(c)).present Constitution and setting up &quot;Crown Colony&quot;r.  .1%(2i0/3    Government.      The preparation of such a Bill had been authorised in the previous July, but it had afterwardsbeen decided to hold it over, in view of the alteredsituation in the Mediterranean.      The present position was that, while the restoration of self-government in malta remained impossible, it was undesirable thatprovisional government should continue.      early legislation was now additionally important,  as Lord1Strickland had been granted leave to appeal to the privy Council in a case which impugned the validity of the existing form of government.After discussion the Cabinet agreed:That the Secretary of State for the colonies should be authorised to arrange for theearly introduction in the House of Lords ofa short Bill to restore to the Crown fullpower to legislate for Malta by prerogativelegislation.
a oRablishment of legislative*Jncil.I-eviousIference %,&apos;. unet 24 (36),Inclusion 8.)7.   The Cabinet had before them the following papers %-A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (CP. 37 (36)), inwhich they were invited to give a finalendorsement to the proposal to establish   -a Legislative Council in Palestine.Consideration of this item had been adjourned pending the receipt of theHigh Commissioners observations onthe position resulting from the Houseof Commons debate on March 24th.Memoranda by the Secretary of State forthe Colonies (CP. 95 (36) and CP. 99 (36)),covering an exchange of telegrams with theHigh Commissioner, from which a new proposalemerged, namely, that an Arab deputati on wtshould be given an opportunity of puttingtheir case to the Secretary of State inLondon.The Secretary of State for the Colonies paid a tribute to the very helpful attitude of the HighCommissioner.      He read further telegrams which hehad interchanged with the High Commissioner.      he himself had ashed whether the proposed Arab deputation,who in any event could not receive full satisfaction of their wishes, would not perhaps go back to Palestinemore dissatisfied than ever and make the work of anyeventual Commission more difficult.      The high commissioners reply, which he had only received thesame morning, was in the negative.      He thought thatthe mere fact of their reception in London would givegreat satisfaction to the Arabs as placing them onthe same footing as the Jews who had already beenreceived here. The Secretary of State for theColonies gave the Cabinet a full appreciation of thesituation and made the proposals which appear inConclusion (a).The Secretary of State for India warned theCabinet of the repercussions of British policy in
Palestine on other parts of the Moslem world and more particularly on India.      It was important to remove any impression that British policy inPalestine was run by the Jews. He, therefore,supported the Secretary of State for the Colonies.After discussion, in which the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs, the Secretary of Statefor Air and others took part, the Cabinet agreed:-(a) To approve the proposal of the Secretaryof State for the Colonies that theHigh Commissioner^ advice should beaccepted and an Arab deputation shouldbe given an opportunity of coming toLondon to state their case to theSecretary of State.        If a possibility should arise of bringing together theArab deputation and the representativesof the Zionists,  the Secretary of state should avail himself of it.      Failingy      . that, after the return of the Arab(fyafiwqn i     Jt deputation, a smalV Commit too should beappointed^to proceed to Palestine and advise/on the proposal to establish a legislative Council in Palestine, but asto the time when it should be broughtinto existence.(b) That the Secretary of State for theColonies should be authorised in reply to questions to be asked in Parliament next week to state that the establishment of a legislative Council would be delayedpending the visit of an Arab deputation to London.(c) That the Secretary of State for theColonies should consider the desirabilityof seeing privately those supporters of the Government who were critical ofthe present proposals and laying thewhole situation before them in a way that could not be done publiclya  For example,he should emphasise the extent to whichwe were pledged in the matter (includingthe High Commissioners pledge to localleaders in 1925) and the danger that, if wewent back on our pledges, Arab riots, aswe were warned by the High Commissioner,would arise and would probably stop thedevelopment of Zionism for years.
IfOVAL OPfETS OP THEfyAI ORDNANCEICTORIES.previous reference ;fabinet 41 (35) slonclusion 4.)8.      The Cabinet had before them a Note by theSecretary (CP. 93 (36)),  circulated by directionof the Prime Minister, covering a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for War (C.I.D. Paper No.223-A),to which was attached the Report of an Inter-Departmental Committee on the removal of parts ofthe Royal Ordnance Factories^    together with an extract from the draft Minutes of the 275th Meetingof the Committee of Imperial Defence, in which thefollowing recommendation was made;-That approval should be given to therecommendations contained in paragraph 12(i)and 12(v) of the report of the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Removal of parts of the Royal Ordnance Factories whichare as followss-u12(i) On the basis of the assumptionsstated in paragraph 1, we recommendthat a part of the filling factory shouldbe established elsewhere than at Chorley,and that it should be established onthe site of 900 acres at Eridgend withinthe South Wales Special Area, described,at (i)  of paragraph No. 3, as a suitablesite.12(v) If it  should hereafter be decidedto remove the Cordite factory at Waltham,we recommend, as suitable, on the assumptions stated in paragraph 7, the site at Bishopton situated in theScottish Special Area and lying to theWest of the Railway from Georgetown toBishopton,  10 to 12 miles North-west of Glasgow.      In this connection we draw attention to what we have stated asregards housing, etc.,  in paragraph 10.&quot;In the course of discussion it was urgedthat whenever a statement had to be made of thoGovernments intentions most careful consideration should be given both to workers who would Iftse theirjobs and to those who would be moved to other places.In regard to the latter, it should be made quite clear,
In a sympathetic manner, that their case would he most carefully considered, fromlhe point of view both of housing and of the arrangements for the removal oftheir families and themselves. The government must show itself to be a good employer.The subject was found to involve large questionsof principle which were likely to arise in other caseswhere the removal of industries of various kinds was contemplated, and to affect several departments of theGovernment.The Cabinet agreed:(a) To approve the recommendations ofthe Committee of imperial defence as set forth above.(b) That the means of mitigating thesocial consequences of theremoval in the Woolwich area,  asdealt with in the report of sir arthur Robinson&apos;s Committee,should be the subject of further investigation in relation to other problems of the same kind that were liable to arise.(c) That the latter aspect of thequestion should be reserved forconsideration at the next weekly meeting of the Cabinet, by which time the Prime Minister, afterconsultation with some of hiscolleagues, hoped to be in aposition to make a proposal as to how the question should be handled(e.g. by a Cabinet Committee,? an.Inter-Departmental Committee, or both).(d) That in the meantime no decision should be announced In regard tothe Government&apos;s intentions.
iOYMSNT OFIjstforthyIns inDEFENCEStments,lyiousFerence;binet 24 (36) ,conclusion 4.)9.       The Cabinet had again under consideration a most secret Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty(CP. 82 (36))  recommending the adoption of new rules for the elimination of disaffected civilian employeesfrom the service of the Defence Departments.      Thisquestion had arisen in connection with recent casesof sabotage in the dockyards.      The Cabinet had alsobefore them a Memorandum by the Minister forCo-ordination of Defence (CP. 94 (36))  in which someapprehension was expressed regarding the effect onthe great majority, consisting of perfectly reliablemen, if an established man received notice of immediatedischarge, without any reason &quot;feeing assigned.      Onlyexperience could show whether careful administrationof the new rules would be accepted without complaintby the Trade Unions and the dockyard men themselves.After the Minister for Defence Co-ordinationhad expressed his views the Minister of Labour said he had discussed the matter with his advisers on industrial relations. They thought that the FirstLord of the Admiralty was right as to the desire of trades unionists working in the dock-yard, to have thematter cleared up, but they considered that nevertheless the trades unions would be bound to adopt officiallyan attitude of criticism. His advisers attached importance to there being a legal member of theproposed committee to sift evidence.The Minister for Defenoe Co-Ordinationsuggested that the sifting of evidence could be done by(fu Liu hu^-fotweaU (j tUthe Judge Advocate-General/efr^^Befenoe^-Bepartmeafc-who could see the evidence, but need not necessarily- 12 -
tie a member of the proposed Committee.In order to meet,  in some degree,the difficulties that were foreseen in carrying out the proposals of theService Ministers,  a suggestion was made that the proposed committee should, before dismissing a man, see him If he asked for an interview..The Cabinet agreed.(a) To approve the adoption of the newrules proposed in CP. 82 (36) forthe elimination of disaffectedcivilian employees from the serviceof the Defence&apos; Departments&apos;..(b) That the Service Ministers should consider the adoption of thefollowing proposals:(ii) that the Committee should see a man who, before beingdismissed, asked for an interview, but should not be bound to give him thereasons for dismissal or theevidence against him:(iii) that they should examinethe corresponding arrange-rnents made in connectionwith the internment of aliens, etc.  during the War,1(i) the examination of theI       evidence by the Judge,      Advocate-G-eneral^of the-
Ring (no. i)jiviousference sItnet 24 (36),conclusion   12,10.     The Cabinet had before them the Betting (No. 1)Bill, to be introduced by a Private Member on Friday,April 3rd, the object of which was to prohibitoff-the-course betting en the pool or pari-mutuelprinciple5    together with a Joint Memorandum by theHome Secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland(CP. 90 (36)).      The Cabinet were reminded that theGovernment Bill of 1934 had contained similarprovisions, based on the recommendations of the RoyalCommission on Betting and Lotteries, but that these provisions had excited much opposition, and &quot;had been withdrawn.      The present Bill, therefore, was certain to be controversial.      After examining other possible courses, the Memorandum came to the conclusion thatthe Government should accept no responsibility forthe Bill, which should be left to a free vote of theHouse of Commons.After a short discussion the Cabinet agreed:To approve the proposal of theHome Secretary as set forth in cp. 90 (36), and summarised above.&apos;3, Whitehall Gardens, S,W.l.,1st April, 1936*

</content>
</cab>
